Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is ע״ג, Ayin Gimmel,
מנחות Menachos 73. We pick up with the new פרק Perek at
the bottom of ע״ב עמוד ב׳ Ayin Bet Amud Bet and we're
in the middle of describing the different ways in which מנחות Menachos
were prepared, which have oil, which have קמיצה Kmitzah and so on.
So ואלו מנחות נקמצות ושיריהן לכהנים: Ve-elu menachos nikmatzos u-shiyureihen la-kohanim: the
following מנחות Menachos you do קמיצה Kmitzah on and the remainder is
eaten by the כהנים, Kohanim, which is of course a standard
מנחה. Mincha. מנחת הסולת והמחבת והמרחשת והחלות והרקיקין: Minchas hasoles ve-hamachavas ve-hamarcheshes
ve-hachalos ve-harekikhin: so all the מנחות Menachos mentioned there in the beginning
of ויקרא; Vayikra; flour, frying pan, more of a saucepan, loaves, wafers,
which are the two variations of the מאפה תנור. Ma-afeh tanur. מנחת
עובדי כוכבים Minchas ovdei kokhavim if it's brought by non-Jews. מנחת נשים
Minchas nashim brought by women, not clear why you would think that
would be different, not made a different category in the תורה. Torah.
מנחת העומר מנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות: Minchas ha-omer, minchas chotei, u-minchas kena'os:
last three are all out of barley. The מנחה Mincha of the
עומר, Omer, and which we've been discussing, the מנחה Mincha of the
חוטא Chotei in the case of a קרבן עולה ויורד, Korban oleh
ve-yored, the end of פרשת ויקרא, Parshas Vayikra, and a מנחת קנאות
Minchas kena'os of the case of סוטה, Sotah, and those are the
ones that don't have oil and frankincense on them, the last two.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says: מנחת
חוטא של כהנים נקמצת והקומץ קרב לעצמו והשיריים קרבים לעצמן. Minchas chotei
shel kohanim nikmetzes ve-hakomets karev le-atsmo ve-hashiyurayim krevim le-atsman.
So one of the מנחות Menachos not mentioned in the first list
was a מנחת כהן Minchas kohen because a מנחת כהן Minchas kohen
is completely burned. And if it's completely burned, why do you need
a
קמיצה? Kmitzah? The קמיצה Kmitzah is what goes on the fire and
the remainder is eaten. So the assumption is no קמיצה, Kmitzah, you
just put it all on the fire. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says no, you actually would do a קמיצה Kmitzah on a מנחת
כהן Minchas kohen and you would offer up the קמיצה Kmitzah separately.
There would be a meaning, a separate sort of ritual and significance
to offering up the
קמיצה, Kmitzah, and then the remainder of the מנחה Mincha would also
then be put on the fire. So I think this is an
interesting conceptual debate going on here. I think according to the חכמים,
Chachamim, fundamentally since it's all burned by a כהן, Kohen, it's like
it's all the קמיצה, Kmitzah, it's all fundamentally the offering to God.
Whereas within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon you could conceptually understand it: no,
even by מנחת כהן, Minchas kohen, the קמיצה Kmitzah is fundamentally what
is offered to God. Then you have the next question: okay, well
the remainder should be eaten by the כהנים. Kohanim. But because the
כהן Kohen is the person himself who is מקריב, Makriv, then it
can't be eaten by the כהן. Kohen. It's supposed to be eaten
by somebody other than the owner. So I mean it could be
a different כהן, Kohen, but conceptually, some a different category than the
owner, and therefore it's eaten by the fire. But the fire eating
it is separate than it being offered on the fire. I think
that is sort of what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon might be getting
at. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב
פפא כל היכא דתנן עשר תנן. Amar Rav Papa: Kol heikha de-tenan
eser tenan. Now the גמרא Gemara says this a lot of times.
רב פפא Rav Papa says: wherever the משנה Mishna lists מנחות, Menachos,
it lists ten. מאי קא משמע לן? Mai kamashma lan? What is
this coming to teach us? לאפוקי רבי שמעון דאמר מחצה חלות ומחצה
רקיקין יביא קא משמע לן דלא: Le-apukei Rabbi Shimon de-amar mechtza chalos
mechtza rekikhin yavi, kamashma lan de-lo: to exclude the position of רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says that a מנחה מאפה תנור Mincha ma-afeh
tanur is not only that it could be ten חלות Chalos or
ten רקיקין, Rekikhin, it could also be five and five. So רב
פפא Rav Papa is telling us that the משנה Mishna rejects that.
Now how is the משנה Mishna rejecting it and what does he
mean by ten? So you'll remember that רש״י Rashi gives two explanations.
One is: there are ten מנחות Menachos that are listed in these
lists. Okay, let's talk about them: סולת מחבת מרחשת חלות רקיקין, Solet,
machavas, marcheshes, chalos, rekikhin, that's five; עובדי כוכבים נשים עומר חוטא קנאות,
Ovdei kokhavim, nashim, omer, chotei, kena'os, that's another five. That's ten. So
he's saying there are only ten מנחות Menachos and according to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon you would have an eleventh. What would the eleventh
be? Something that is half רקיקין Rekikhin and half חלות. Chalos. So
because it says ten, it's implicitly refuting or rejecting רבי שמעון's Rabbi
Shimon position. The other way of saying it is that he's just
making a claim that all of these get ten full loaves for
each category, and for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon the case of חלות
Chalos and רקיקין Rekikhin would get five loaves of each. The first
read is probably a better one. ושיריהן לכהנים: Ve-shiyureihen la-kohanim: and the
remainder of these ones that you do the קמיצה Kmitzah are eaten
by the
כהנים. Kohanim. מנלן? Menalan? Where do you learn this from? So the
גמרא Gemara says: where do you learn it from?
דכתיבא כתיבא, De-chtiva chtiva, the ones that say it explicitly, take a
קמיצה, Kmitzah, burn the קמיצה, Kmitzah, the remainder is eaten, say it
explicitly; ודלא כתיבא כתיבא בי, U-delo chtiva chtiva bi, and the ones
that are not written explicitly, you still have a general פסוק Pasuk
that's written in צו: Tzav: וזאת תהיה תורת המנחה, Ve-zos tihye toras
hamincha, this will be the law of the מנחה. Mincha. So תורה
Torah means it's like a category, it applies to all the
מנחות. Menachos. הקרב אותה בני אהרן, Hakrev osah bnei Aharon, the children
of Aaron should offer it up. And then it says: והנותרת ממנה
יאכלו אהרן ובניו: Ve-hanoseres mimena yokhlu Aharon u-vanav: what remains is eaten
by Aaron and his children. So very clear that the rule of
כהנים Kohanim is when there's a קמיצה, Kmitzah, what remains is eaten
by the כהנים. Kohanim. Aaron and the children. So the question might
be, okay, is it explicit that you do קמיצה kemitza for everything?
So let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, so you know רש"י Rashi here lists, you know,
the various מנחות menachos why it says קמיצה kemitza and we can
sort of assume
קמיצה kemitza is said by all the מנחות menachos and therefore if
there's a קמיצה kemitza implicitly the remainder is eaten by, you know,
by the כהנים Kohanim or not implicitly, explicitly from וזאת תורת המנחה.
V'zos toras haminchah. By the way, I should note something, on all
these דפים dappim here and, you know, a little bit of the
few פרקים prakim moving forward, you'll see that it also says רש"י
כתב יד. Rashi Kesav Yad. Because the publisher, you know, we don't
always fully appreciate, how did we get this תוספות Tosafos on the
side, this רש"י Rashi on the side? The publisher had to decide,
there were different types, there were different תוספות Tosafists from the different
schools. He had to decide which school of the תוספות Tosafists you're
going to use, which manuscript you're going to use. So the person,
you know, when they came to putting the גמרא, Gemara, by the
time they came to this version of the גמרא, Gemara, they had
found a different manuscript of רש"י Rashi that claimed that the רש"י
Rashi that we have in the slightly larger font, which had been
there originally, is not the original רש"י Rashi and the one in
the manuscript is the original רש"י. Rashi. It seems to be that
that is the case because when תוספות Tosafos cites רש"י, Rashi, it
parallels what's in the smaller רש"י Rashi where it says רש"י כתב
יד Rashi Kesav Yad and not what's in the bigger רש"י Rashi
that was originally, you know, the only רש"י Rashi that was on
the page. Anyway, okay, so רש"י Rashi points out, you know, that
there are, it says it by the קמיצה kemitza and therefore once
it says קמיצה kemitza based on this פסוק pasuk you can assume
the הנצום, hanatzum, the שיריים shirayim are eaten by the כהנים. Kohanim.
So the גמרא Gemara says no here's our question. The גמרא Gemara
says like this, בהא לא קמיבעיא לן, Behai lo kamibaya lan, we're
not asking about what happens by a מנחה minchah that is coming
from, from flour, you know, from wheat flour, because that's the standard
וזאת תורת המנחה, V'zos toras haminchah, the standard מנחות menachos listed in
ויקרא Vayikra and צו Tzav are ones out of wheat flour. כי
קמיבעיא לן דשעורים, Ki kamibaya lan d'seorim, our question is the ones
that come out of barley, how do you know those are also
included in וזאת תורת המנחה? V'zos toras haminchah? So now, now by
the way, תוספות Tosafos points out, sometimes we assume וזאת תורת המנחה
V'zos toras haminchah includes all מנחות menachos we don't care wheat or
barley. But here maybe we think specifically it might be limited to
wheat, not only because those are the standard מנחות menachos we're talking
about, but because wheat is normally, you know, wheat flour is normally
eaten by people whereas barley flour was standard only fed to animals.
So maybe we should not assume that the idea that the remainder
is eaten by the כהנים Kohanim applies to the מנחות menachos of
barley. So the גמרא Gemara says כי דשעורים נמי מנא ידעינן דשייריא
לכהנים, Ki d'seorim nami m'na yad'inan d'shayeraya l'kohanim, also
so what says the גמרא, Gemara, you know, even so, from the
very fact that you're doing קמיצה, kemitza, even if you don't want
to read it into the פסוק, pasuk, from the very fact that
you do קמיצה kemitza by a מנחה minchah of barley, obviously you're
doing קמיצה kemitza so that the, you know, it's assigning a different
role to the קמיצה kemitza which is burned and implicitly there's something
else happening with the remainder, the remainder is eaten. So it's implicit
from the fact of קמיצה. kemitza. גמרא Gemara says no, not necessarily,
אליבא דרבנן לא קמיבעיא לן, Aliba d'Rabbanan lo kamibaya lan,
according to the רבנן Rabbanan that say by מנחת כהן, minchas kohen,
the fact that you do קמיצה, kemitza, you know, excuse me, by
מנחת כהן, minchas kohen, you know, you can never have it that
you do קמיצה kemitza and burn the remainder, and therefore for מנחת
כהן minchas kohen they burn the whole thing, they would never split,
they would never sort of, you know, say that. For them clearly
if there's קמיצה, kemitza, you're going to eat the remainder and that's
why by מנחת כהן minchas kohen where it's not eaten there's no
קמיצה. kemitza. כי קמיבעיא לן אליבא דרבי שמעון, Ki kamibaya lan aliba
d'Rabbi Shimon, but our question is according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
דאמר איכא מנחה דמקמצה ולא מתאכלה, d'amar ika minchah d'mikamtza v'lo misachla,
he says you can have a case of קמיצה kemitza where the
remainder isn't eaten, מנחת כהנים. minchas kohanim. So the very fact that
the תורה Torah writes קמיצה kemitza doesn't by itself prove that the
remainder is eaten and maybe the by barley the remainder wouldn't be
eaten, maybe it wouldn't be included in וזאת תורת המנחה. V'zos toras
haminchah. דתנן רבי שמעון אומר מנחת חוטא של כהנים נקמצת והקומץ קרב
בעצמו והשיריים קרבים בעצמם. D'tenan Rabbi Shimon omer minchas chotei shel kohanim
nikmetzes v'hakometz karev b'atzmo v'hashirayim krevim b'atzmam.
So he says by מנחת כהן minchas kohen you can have not
eat the remainder, the remainder could also be burned and you could
do a קמיצה kemitza by מנחת כהן. minchas kohen. So מנלן, m'nalan,
so where do we know it from? אמר חזקיה דאמר קרא, Amar
Chizkiyah d'amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן וחרבה,
V'chol minchah belulah vashamen vacharevah,
any מנחה minchah that is mixed with, you know, oil or that
is dry, לכל בני אהרן תהיה איש כדאחיו, l'chol b'nei Aharon tihyeh
ish k'achiv, it should be for all בני אהרן, b'nei Aharon, it
should be equally eaten by all of them. This is an interesting
פסוק pasuk in צו Tzav where it seems to indicate a different
type of division based on which type of מנחה minchah it is.
The פסוק pasuk there says as follows,
it says...
actually, no, excuse me,
this is actually a פסוק, pasuk, yes, excuse me, it is in
צו, Tzav, it's just a little later, it's in זיין, Zayin, it
says like this, it says וכל מנחה אשר תאפה v'chol minchah asher
teafeh Any מנחה mincha that's in an oven or in a frying
pan, you know, saucepan, לכהן המקריב אותה לו תהיה lakohen hamakriv otah
lo tihiyeh
goes to the כהן kohen who offers it. וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן
וחרבה לכל בני אהרן תהיה איש כאחיו. Vechol mincha belulah vashemen vacharevah
lechol benei Aharon tihiyeh ish ke'achiv. And however anything that is just
mixed with oil, meaning not baked, you know, but similarly like a
סולת, soles, or it is dry, no oil, that gets equally divided.
So it sounds from here that based on the מנחה mincha it
either goes specifically to the כהן kohen who offers it or it
gets equally divided. However חז"ל Chazal understand that
all מנחות menachos are equally divided by the כהנים. kohanim. That's actually
going to be a major part of today's דף. daf. And what
do you do with the fact that it says לכהן המקריב אותה?
lakohen hamakriv otah? So רש"י Rashi says, יכול לו לבדו תלמוד לומר
לכל בני אהרן. yachol lo levado talmud lomar lechol benei Aharon. So
he says no, the next פסוק passuk tells you it's equally divided.
So what does it say המקריב אותה? hamakriv otah? It says לבית
אב של אותו יום שמקריבין אותה. leveis av shel oso yom shemakrivin
otah. It means that it is for the entire like, you know,
waitresses who share their tips, you know, pool it and share it.
So it means it's for the people that are working that day
but not specifically for the כהן kohen that is doing it. רמב"ם,
Rambam, you know, has an interesting interpretation to try to explain why
it separates them if fundamentally the הלכה halacha is they're all equally
divided. We'll get to that a little later in today's דף. daf.
But anyway,
so from that פסוק, passuk, וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן וחרבה לכל בני
אהרן תהיה, vechol mincha belulah vashemen vacharevah lechol benei Aharon tihiyeh, אם
אינו עניין לבלולה של חטים, im eino inyan lebelulah shel chitim,
so the fact that it is saying that it is divided, so
here we're not emphasizing equally divided or who gets it, but the
fundamental fact that that פסוק passuk says לכל בני אהרן lechol benei
Aharon means that they're going to consume it. So that פסוק passuk
teaches us that it gets consumed. So you don't need it to
tell you that for case of בלולה של חטים, belulah shel chitim,
a case of because two types: one mixed with oil and one
dry. So you don't need it to tell you that a מנחה
mincha of flour of wheat flour mixed with oil is eaten by
בני אהרן. benei Aharon. That's explicit in the פסוקים pesukim like we've
been saying. So therefore what is it when it's saying that it's
eaten by בני אהרן, benei Aharon, בלולה בשמן? belulah vashemen? תנהו עניין
לבלולה של שעורים. tenahu inyan lebelulah shel se'orim.
It's coming to tell you that the ones mixed with oil of
barley, which is the עומר. Omer. Okay? ואם אינו עניין לחרבה של
חטים, Ve'im eino inyan lecharevah shel chitim, if it's not coming for
the case of a dry מנחה mincha out of flour, תנהו עניין
לחרבה של שעורים, tenahu inyan lecharevah shel se'orim, apply it to case
of a dry מנחה mincha excuse me out of wheat flour, teach
it to case of a dry מנחה mincha out of barley flour
which is the מנחה mincha of the סוטה. Sotah.
Okay so the dry one
out of wheat would be the מנחת חוטא minchas chotei of a
what do you call it, of an עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, but
the מנחה mincha of the סוטה Sotah would be out of barley
flour. So that's where we're going to learn it from. תנהו עניין
לחרבה של שעורים. tenahu inyan lecharevah shel se'orim.
Okay so basically what it's saying is we don't know that the
remainder is eaten, it's not explicit that the remainder of a מנחה
mincha of שעורים se'orim is eaten by the כהנים, kohanim, and we
learn it from the פסוק passuk that says you know וכל מנחה
בלולה בשמן וחרבה לכל בני אהרן תהיה vechol mincha belulah vashemen vacharevah
lechol benei Aharon tihiyeh that the ones with oil and the dry
ones are eaten by בני אהרן benei Aharon and that's to tell
you that the two מנחות menachos of שעורים, se'orim, one mixed with
oil which is for the עומר Omer and one a dry one
which is for the סוטה, Sotah, those also go to בני אהרן
benei Aharon and that's what that פסוק passuk is telling you because
there's no need to tell it in a case of where it's
mixed with the wheat flour because that's already explicit in the פסוקים.
pesukim. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says והאי להכי הוא דאתא?
vehai lehachi hu de'asa? Is that really what it's coming to tell
me? המיבעי ליה לכדתניא. Hamiba'ei lei lichdesanya. No, we need that פסוק
passuk of לכל בני אהרן תהיה איש כאחיו lechol benei Aharon tihiyeh
ish ke'achiv not to tell me that the remainder of a מנחה
mincha of certain types of מנחה mincha are eaten by כהנים. kohanim.
It's telling you much more explicitly what the פסוקים pesukim is telling
you which is: how do who has a right to it? Okay?
מנין, minayin, and here's what the ברייתא braita teaches and this is
a whole ברייתא braita about how do they divide the different קרבנות
korbanos in the מקדש Mikdash that the כהנים kohanim had a right
to. So מנין שאין חולקין מנחות כנגד זבחים, minal she'ein cholkin menachos
keneged zevachim,
how do you know that at the end of the day you
don't say, "Okay, we have all these מנחות menachos that are to
be eaten by the כהנים, kohanim, all these חטאות chata'os you know
and other meat that's to be eaten by the כהנים, kohanim, and
let's just who like who are the vegetarians? Okay I'm kidding, but
like you're like: who wants the מנחה? mincha? You guys can get
this much מנחה, mincha, you can take that much meat." How do
you know you can't divide it up and have some somebody and
have some כהן kohen get the מנחות menachos and a different כהן
kohen you know get the meat? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: וכל מנחה
אשר תאפה בתנור לכל בני אהרן תהיה איש כאחיו, vechol mincha asher
te'afeh batanur lechol benei Aharon tihiyeh ish ke'achiv, you know it should
be you know the anyone that's in a oven it should be
for all בני אהרן, benei Aharon, they should divide it equally. So
that is telling you that you know
so first of all it's just worth noting that the פסוק passuk
there the גמרא Gemara jumped over the פסוק passuk that said לכהן
המקריב אותה lakohen hamakriv otah and goes to the next פסוק passuk
which says לכל בני אהרן תהיה איש כאחיו l'chol Bnei Aharon tihiyeh
ish k'achiv like I said, חז"ל Chazal read the equal division to
be going on all of the מנחות menachot that are mentioned in
that פסוק. Pasuk. Okay, so the fact that it says that it
is equally divided is coming to tell
you that מנחות menachot are divided with מנחות, menachot, they're not divided
that some people get מנחות menachot and some people get the meat.
יכול לא יחלוקו מנחות כנגד זבחים שלא קמו תחתיהם בדלות.
yachol lo yachloku menachot keneged
zvachim shelo kamu tachteihem bidalut.
Perhaps, okay, one, you don't do one person gets animal like the
meat of a cow or the sheep and somebody else gets a
מנחה mincha because those are never seen as a substitute for one
another.
What, if somebody's bringing a חטאת עולה ויורד, chatat oleh v'yored, a
certain type of חטאת chatat that depends on your financial ability, so
if you don't have money for a sheep or for a sheep,
you go ahead and you bring a bird. And if you don't
have money for a bird, you bring a מנחה. mincha. So a
bird is a substitute for a sheep, but a מנחה mincha is
never substitute for a sheep. So that would explain
why you can't divide birds against sheep, I mean, מנחות menachot against
sheep. אבל יחלוקו מנחות כנגד עופות, aval yachloku menachot keneged ofot, but
maybe, okay, but maybe if like there are certain bird sacrifices to
be eaten by the כהנים Kohanim and certain מנחות, menachot, maybe there
we can read them as rough equivalents
and you can divide them. Some get the birds and some get
the מנחות. menachot. שהרי קמו תחתיהם בדלות, sheharei kamu tachteihem bidalut, because
that is a substitute. תלמוד לומר וכל נעשה במרחשת. Talmud lomar v'chol
na'aseh b'marcheshet. No, because it doesn't just say וכל מנחה אשר תאפה
בתנור, v'chol mincha asher te'afeh batanur, missed, it also mentions and everything
made in a frying pan. So that is or a saucepan, excuse
me. So that is coming, the fact that it's listing different type
of
מנחות, menachot, each separate item is coming to tell you and insist
that the divisions have to be of the same genre. They can't
be of significantly different genres,
מנחות menachot and sheep or cows, they can't even be of somewhat
similar genres, מנחות menachot and birds. Each additional word that is saying
that it's equally divided is insisting
on division within each category and not across categories.
Okay. יכול לא יחלוקו מנחות כנגד עופות שהללו מיני דמים
והללו מיני קמחים. yachol lo yachloku menachot keneged ofot she'hallalu minei damim
v'hallalu minei kmachim. Perhaps fine, you can't divide divvy out מנחות menachot
against birds because one is flour and the other is blood, meaning
one's meat and one's flour. However, יחלוקו עופות כנגד זבחים שהללו והללו
מיני דמים, yachloku ofot keneged zvachim she'hallalu v'hallalu minei damim,
but maybe you can divide it up that some people get the
bird meat and some people get the sheep and the cow meat
because those are both like real blood and like real meat. תלמוד
לומר ועל מחבת. Talmud lomar v'al machavat. Again, now, and on
a מחבת machavat again mentioning another type of a מנחה, mincha, obviously
now we're applying it to things that are not about מנחה mincha
at all. But again, each word is seen as insisting that every
single category has to be divided
within its own category
and not across categories. לכל בני אהרן תהיה. l'chol Bnei Aharon tihiyeh.
יכול לא יחלוקו עופות כנגד זבחים שהללו עשייתן ביד והללו עשייתן בכלי.
yachol lo yachloku ofot keneged zvachim she'hallalu asiyatan b'yad v'hallalu asiyatan bikli.
Okay, fine, you won't divide some people get birds and some people
get sheep because one you with a כלי kli with the knife
and one you with your hand, the fingernail. אבל יחלוקו מנחות כנגד
מנחות שהללו והללו עשייתן ביד. aval yachloku menachot keneged menachot she'hallalu v'hallalu
asiyatan b'yad.
Yeah, but maybe when fine, let's talk about within the genre of
מנחות. menachot. So maybe some people can get a מנחה, mincha, one
כהנים, Kohanim,
I'll say I'll take the one that's the wafer, and no, I
want the one that's the baked in the oven, and I want
the one that's the frying pan, right? Maybe you can divide them
that way. תלמוד לומר וכל מנחה בלולה בשמן לכל בני אהרן תהיה.
Talmud lomar v'chol mincha blulah bashamen l'chol Bnei Aharon tihiyeh.
No, again, another part of the
פסוק, Pasuk, anyone mixed with oil. So that's insisting that you can't
even divide them even within מנחות menachot against different categories of מנחות.
menachot. יכול לא יחלוקו מחבת כנגד מרחשת ומרחשת כנגד מחבת שזו מעשה
קשין
וזו מעשה רכין. yachol lo yachloku machavat keneged marcheshet u'marcheshet keneged machavat
she'zu ma'aseh kashin v'zu ma'aseh rachin. Fine, fine, you can't divide a
frying pan against a saucepan,
one comes out, one is very hard, fried, fried and hard, the
other is sort of more soft and oily. אבל יחלוקו מחבת כנגד
מחבת ומרחשת כנגד מרחשת. aval yachloku machavat keneged machavat u'marcheshet keneged marcheshet.
And that's where I thought we were going, right? Okay, but maybe
if you have a hundred מנחות menachot of מחבת machavat that were
brought today,
you can each and you have a hundred כהנים, Kohanim, each כהן
Kohen gets a different מנחה. mincha. That makes sense, it's all within
the same category. תלמוד לומר וחרבה. Talmud lomar v'charavah.
No, yet again, another word in that פסוק, Pasuk, וחרבה v'charavah
is to insist that each thing gets divided separately to the point
that it means every single sacrifice gets divided separately, not just. just
within a genre of sacrifices. לכל בני אהרן תהיה. Lechol bnei aharon
tihyeh. Okay,
so if you think about it, that means, oh my God, can
you imagine the end of the day in the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, how difficult that would be? You have hundreds of sacrifices being
brought of all different types, and what do you have to basically
do is you have to basically take with each single sacrifice, break
it up into however many pieces of different כהנים Kohanim that you
have, and do that again and again and again with every single
sacrifice, even if you have a hundred ones of חרבה chareva or
a hundred ones of מחבת. machavat. It's really pretty mind-boggling and hard
to imagine. You know, תוספות Tosfos suggests that the point here of
לא יחלוקו lo yachloku is not to say don't divvy it up
across categories but, you know, only each individual one has to be
divvied up, but to rather say nothing should be divvied. It's never
about,
sort
of, you know, a-apportioning it out. It's that it's just for everybody
to eat. Come and get it, take what you want, for everybody
to eat, and there's no real divvying up of it at all.
תוספות Tosfos goes back and forth between whether that's the way to
read the גמרא Gemara or the way we've been reading it, which
is, no, at the end result, every single sacrifice has to be
divided up, which is just enormous to think about that amount of
effort. Okay, now it continues. יכול לא יחלוקו בקדשי קדשים אבל יחלוקו
בקדשים קלים. Yachol lo yachloku bekodshei kodashim aval yachloku bekodshim kalim. All
these types of things we've been talking about are קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodashim, you know, things that are, can only be eaten in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. But maybe the portion that כהנים Kohanim get
that they can eat in all of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, like the, like
the the the breast and the thigh of the of the שלמים,
shlamim, maybe that can be divided up, maybe that's seen more like
their own personal property and, you know, maybe easier to make a
logic that that could be divided up divided up.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse says, איש כאחיו ואם על תודה.
Ish ke'achiv ve'im al todah. It ends, ואיש אל אחיו, ve'ish el
achiv, you know, יהיה לכל בני אהרן תהיה איש כאחיו. yihyeh lechol
bnei aharon tihyeh ish ke'achiv. And then the next words are ואם
על תודה, ve'im al todah, that even when it comes to a
תודה todah and a שלמים, shlamim, those have to be divided up
equally, presumably each individual sacrifice has to be divided up.
Okay. כשם שאין חולקין בקדשי קדשים, כך אין חולקין בקדשים קלים. Keshem
she'ein cholkin bekodshei kodashim, kach ein cholkin bekodshim kalim. The same way
you don't do it by קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, you don't divide
up by קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, you don't divide one קרבן korban
against another, each קרבן korban individually has to be divided up. One
last point that this ברייתא braisah says: איש. Ish. Why does it
say איש, ish, you know, איש כאחיו? ish ke'achiv? To tell you,
איש חולק ואפילו בעל מום ואין קטן חולק ואפילו תם. Ish cholek
va'afilu ba'al mum ve'ein katan cholek va'afilu tam.
An adult כהן Cohen gets it even if he's a בעל מום,
ba'al mum, you know, the תורה Torah actually says that a בעל
מום ba'al mum gets a portion in the קרבנות, korbanos,
but a כהן Cohen who is a minor does not get it
even if he is unblemished. Okay, so that's interesting. It's only, this
is the job for the adults, or this is the right of
the adults. All right, anyway, that is a very long ברייתא, braisah,
but what we see from that ברייתא braisah is the פסוק pasuk
that וכל מנחה אשר תאפה בתנור וכל מנחה בלועה שמן וחרבה לכל
בני אהרן תהיה איש כאחיו vechol mincha asher te'afeh batanur vechol mincha
belua shemen vachareva lechol bnei aharon tihyeh ish ke'achiv is not coming
to teach you that the מנחות minchos of שעורים, se'orim, if they
are, you know, the מנחת העומר minchas ha'omer or the מנחת קנאות,
minchas kena'os, that the that the כהנים Kohanim have a right to
eat it. That's not what it's telling you at all. All these
פסוקים psukim are coming to tell you how do you divide up
the sacrifices.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
ההוא מ-כל נפקא. Hahu mikol nafka. No, no, we're learning that from
where it says, you know, וכל מנחה אשר תאפה בתנור וכל מנחה
בלועה שמן. vechol mincha asher te'afeh batanur vechol mincha belua shemen. So
the כל kol is coming to teach you this idea that, you
know, about the basic rules about divvying up and so on. But
what we, you know, but our לימוד limud was בלועה שמן וחרבה
belua shemen vachareva to teach the basic פשט pshat of the פסוק
pasuk to teach you that they have a right to it. Okay,
so so that's how we're saying it. You can learn both out.
They have a right to the מנחת שעורים minchas se'orim and stuff
are divided up equally because the וכל vechol is an additional לימוד.
limud. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא אפיקתיה לרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה.
Veha apiktei le'Rabbi Yosi berabi Yehuda. Don't, wait. We used the וכל
vechol to teach you another הלכה halacha from רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yosi berabi Yehuda, which we discussed in an earlier פרק. perek.
אלא הוא מ-ו-כל. Ela hu mivachol. Fine, the extra ו. vav. וכל,
Vechol, מנחה אשר תאפה, mincha asher te'afeh, so that extra ו vav
is teaching you this הלכה. halacha. Which הלכה halacha are we learning
from the ו, vav, which from the כל, kol, and which from
the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is not exactly clear, but
somehow those three things tell us this teaching of רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yosi berabi Yehuda from a previous פרק, perek, teach us
the equal division amongst כהנים, Kohanim, and you divide each individual sacrifice,
and tell us that the כהנים Kohanim have a right to the
מנחה Mincha of the עומר Omer and מנחת קנאות, minchas kena'os, even
though they are of barley, the remainder is eaten by the כהנים.
Kohanim.
Okay, רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, for that was a very long explanation
of where you know they have a right to these ones of.
barley. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina has an easier explanation. אתיא
מדתני לוי, Asya midetani Levi, we learn it out from what לוי
Levi teaches. דתני לוי, Detani Levi, because לוי Levi teaches, לכל קרבנם
לכל מנחתם לכל חטאתם ולכל אשמם. Lechol korbanam lechol minchasam lechol chatasam
ulechol ashamam. Okay, so this is a פסוק pasuk in במדבר Bamidbar
after the whole thing with קרח Korach where the תורה Torah reaffirms
the rights of the כהנים Kohanim to the various קרבנות. korbanos. And
then after it lists them very like individually,
it says sort of at the end there—here, let me read it—excuse
me, at the beginning, it lists them individually, but at the beginning
it frames it with a very broad opening statement. ויקרא י"ח... Vayikra
18... excuse me, במדבר
י"ח, Bamidbar 18, את
משמרת תרומתי לכל קדשי בני ישראל לך נתתים למשחה ולבניך לחק עולם.
Et mishmeret terumotai lechol kodshei Bnei Yisrael lecha netatim lemashcha ulvanecha lechok
olam. זה יהיה לך מקדש הקדשים מן האש, Zeh yihyeh lecha mikodesh
hakodoshim min ha'esh, this is what you get from the Holy of
Holies, כל קרבנם לכל מנחתם לכל חטאתם ולכל אשמם—all kol korbanam lechol
minchasam lechol chatasam ulechol ashamam their קרבנות, korbanos, all their מנחות, menachos,
all their sin offerings,
all their
אשמם, asham, another type of sin offering—אשר ישיבו לי קדש קדשים לך
הוא ולבניך, asher yashivu li kodesh kodoshim lecha hu ulvanecha, which they
will return to me,
God. It is Holy of Holies, you get it. They're bringing it
to me but I God am giving it to you. That's basically
the idea of משולחן גבוה קא זכו. Mishulchan Gavoah ka zachu.
So from that we're going to learn, because it mentions מנחות, minchos,
that that's going to include the מנחה mincha of שעורים se'orim that
the כהנים Kohanim eat the remainder. Okay,
ולכל אשמם כל קרבנם. ulechol ashamam kol korbanam. So now what are
each of these words coming to teach? Because after this the פסוקים
psukim go individually and tell you all the things כהנים Kohanim get.
So what do you learn from this broad general statement?
כל קרבנם, Kol korbanam, לרבות לוג שמן של מצורע. lerabbos Log shemen
shel Metzora. That's the לוג log of oil that the מצורע Metzora
brings in the purification process. It doesn't tell you what you do
with it after you use some of the drops ritually. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Salka deitach amina, I might have thought מן האש—it min ha'esh
says מקדש הקדשים מן האש, mikodesh hakodoshim min ha'esh, from the fire—so
maybe you only get the rights to things that have some aspect
brought on the מזבח. mizbeach. כתב רחמנא קמשמע לן, Kasav Rachmana kamashma
lan, so it's telling you כל קרבנם, kol korbanam, even something like
the oil of the מצורע Metzora you get, you the כהנים. Kohanim.
לכל מנחתם, Lechol minchasam, all the מנחות, menachos, לרבות מנחת עומר ומנחת
קנאות. lerabbos minchas Omer uminchas Knaos. Ah, beautiful, exactly what we're talking
about, the מנחת עומר minchas Omer and the מנחת קנאות minchas Knaos
of the סוטה, Sotah, which are both brought from barley. סלקא דעתך
אמינא, Salka deitach amina, I would have thought ואכלו אתם אשר כפר
בהם אמר רחמנא, v'achlu otam asher kupar bahem amar Rachmana, not so
much a wheat versus barley distinction, but the fact that the תורה
Torah speaks when it emphasizes the fact that the כהנים Kohanim eat
the remainder of certain sacrifices, it is in the context of the
owners getting atonement. So maybe it's only with קרבנות korbanos that there's
a sense of
כפרה. kapara. והאי, Ve'hai, these
קרבנות, korbanos, להתיר קאתיה—one l'hatir ka'asya of it, the עומר, Omer, is
not coming for any atonement, it's coming to make the new grain
permissible. ואידך, Ve'idach, and the other one for the סוטה, Sotah, נמי
לברר קאתיה—it's nami levarer ka'asya not coming because she has definitely sinned
and it is for atonement, it is coming as a test to
determine whether she sinned or not. So maybe these would be things
that the כהנים Kohanim would not eat. קמשמע לן, Kamashma lan, מנחתם
minchasam tells you they even get these, but very nicely these two
are also exactly out of barley. So if you were to have
thought that a כהן Kohein wouldn't get the barley ones, again as
תוספות Tosafos says maybe because they're not really made for human consumption,
לכל מנחתם lechol minchasam is telling you they get that as well,
a much cleaner דרשה drasha than the previous one. Okay, now we're
going to finish the דרשות. drashos. לכל חטאתם, Lechol chatasam, all their
sin offerings, לרבות חטאת העוף. lerabbos chatas haof. This includes even a
bird חטאת. chatas. What do they do with the meat after the
blood is put on the מזבח? mizbeach? The כהנים Kohanim eat it.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina, I would have thought to say
נבלה היא. neveila hi. Since it's shechted from the back with the
finger of the כהן, Kohein, it's not a kosher שחיטה, shechita, it's
a נבלה, neveila, כהנים Kohanim shouldn't eat it. That's a very good
הוה אמינא, hava amina, קמשמע לן kamashma lan they do. לכל אשמם,
Lechol ashamam, all of their אשם asham sacrifices, לרבות אשם נזיר ואשם
מצורע, lerabbos asham Nazir v'asham Metzora, to tell you that the אשם
asham of a נזיר Nazir and an אשם asham of a מצורע—it
Metzora doesn't say who eats it—the כהנים Kohanim eat it. So the
גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אשם מצורע בהדיא כתיב ביה. asham Metzora
behedya ketiv bei. It does say who eats the אשם asham of
a מצורע: Metzora: כי כחטאת האשם הוא לכהן, ki chachatas ha'asham hu
lakohein, this אשם asham is like a חטאת chatas for the כהן,
Kohein, the כהן Kohein eats it. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא,
ela, fine, this is what the ברייתא braisa means: לרבות אשם נזיר
כאשם מצורע. lerabbos asham Nazir k'asham Metzora. The אשם asham of a
מצורע Metzora we know
is eaten, that's explicit. The אשם asham of a נזיר Nazir is
also eaten by the כהן Kohein based on לכל אשמם. lechol ashamam.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina, I would have thought to say
להכשיר קאתיה. l'hachshir ka'asya. The אשם asham of a נזיר Nazir is
coming
because of a נזיר Nazir who became טמא, tamei, so it's to
begin the נזירות nezirus again as
opposed to like we said by the עומר Omer whatever it's not.
The same type of a קרבן korban and the כהנים kohanim might
not eat it. קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that they do. אשר ישיבו
Asher yashivu that they will return, which is a funny פסוק, pasuk,
it just said that they will give. What's return to me? זה
גזל הגר. Ze gezel hager. If you steal from a, if somebody
swears to a גר, ger, you know, that he stole, I mean
that he stole and he denies stealing money and he's lying, then
he has a מצוה, mitzvah, you know, I mean he swears to
anybody, you know, and he's lying, he has a מצוה mitzvah to
give it back and add a fifth and bring a special קרבן.
korban. But an אשם, asham, but if the person is a גר
ger and dies and doesn't have any heir, what do you do
with the money? The כהן kohen gets that money. Okay, so that's
אשר ישיבו Asher yashivu because that's what you do with a גזילה,
gezeilah, והשיב את
הגזילה. veheishiv et hagezeilah. לך הוא ולבניך, Lecha hu ulvanecha, it is
to you and to your sons. שלך הוא ולבניך, Shelcha hu ulvanecha,
it is considered to be fully yours, אפילו לקדש בו את אשה.
afilu lekadesh bo et isha. So this is a topic for מסכת
קידושין, Masechet Kiddushin, but normally you might think that קדשי קדשים kodesh
kodashim as we've been discussing is sort of משולחן גבוה זכו, mishulchan
gavoah zachu, it's not really considered their property, they're eating off of
God's table. So even when a כהן kohen gets his piece of
קדשי קדשים kodesh kodashim to eat it, you know, we just discussed
before the idea of divvying it up and is it really yours,
so maybe, okay, you're given it to eat, but you're eating, when
I invite you to my table and I put some food in
front of me, you can't say, thanks for the food, put it
in your pocket and walk out the door, right? You're not, I'm
not giving it to you, I'm allowing you to eat from my
food. But שלך הוא ולבניך Shelcha hu ulvanecha tells you no, you
do have a degree of ownership and if you use it to
do קידושי אשה kiddushei isha it actually works, which is a whole
discussion in קידושין. Kiddushin. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, said אמר
רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, top of עג עמוד ב. Ayin Gimmel
Amud Bet. Now we're on
a,
so that's it, that's how we learn out this issue that it
applies even to מנחת חוטא, minchat chotei, in short, the פסוקים psukim
say by almost all of these that you do קמיצה, kemitzah, if
you do קמיצה, kemitzah, it's implicit you eat it. The פסוקים psukim
also in general say that you eat it, so it's תורת המנחה,
torat hamincha, that the remainder is eaten. But I might have thought
that the ones out of barley are different and we learn from,
you know, either the פסוקים psukim about לכל בני אהרן תהיה lechol
bnei Aharon tihyeh or better the פסוקים psukim here in קרח Korach
that they are all eaten by the כהנים. kohanim. Now we're going
to go on to a topic which seems unrelated and it's a
nice new topic, the only, but we're quoting it because it's going
to reference our משנה mishna in the discussion. So let's take a
look. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, said אמר רב הונא,
Amar Rav Huna, שלמי עובדי כוכבים עולות. shlamei ovdei kochavim olot. If
a non-Jew, we know that non-Jews can bring sacrifices, we learn it
from איש איש, ish ish, any man,
you know,
אשר יקריב להשם. asher yakriv l'Hashem. So let me read the actual
פסוק. pasuk.
This is ויקרא כב: Vayikra Kaf Bet: וידבר השם אל משה לאמר
דבר אל אהרן ואל בניו ואל כל בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם. Vayedaber
Hashem el Moshe lemor, daber el Aharon ve'el banav ve'el kol bnei
Yisrael ve'amarta aleihem. Interesting, he speaks to Aaron and all בני ישראל.
bnei Yisrael. איש איש מבית ישראל, Ish ish mibeit Yisrael, if any
man from the house of Israel, ומן הגר בישראל, umin hager beYisrael,
or from the sojourner in Israel, אשר יקריב קרבנו לכל נדריהם ולכל
נדבתם אשר יקריבו להשם לעולה. asher yakriv korbano lechol nidreihem ulechol nidvotam
asher yakrivu l'Hashem le'olah. That they will bring it for all of
their, you know, free-will offerings and all their dedications as an עולה.
olah. And then it says what you go ahead and have to
do with it and it can't have a blemish and then it
says what happens if it's a
שלמים, shlamim, etc. So what's fascinating is even though it emphasizes בני
ישראל bnei Yisrael twice and then it says גר, ger, חז"ל chazal
read איש איש, ish ish, any man even includes a non-Jew. And
you know, there are definitely פסוקים psukim about non-Jews bringing sacrifices, you
know, and that they know and recognize God and certainly Messianic פסוקים
psukim and so on, but it's still quite in נ"ך, Nach, but
it's quite fascinating that they read a פסוק pasuk that heavily emphasizes
Jew to say איש איש ish ish including non-Jews. And says here,
you know, this statement of אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna is
that since it says לעולה, le'olah, what it is telling you is
when it's איש איש, ish ish, when it's a non-Jew, even if
he dedicates it as a שלמים, shlamim, it only, a non-Jew can
only give an עולה. olah. He cannot give anything other than an
עולה. olah.
איבעית אימא קרא ואיבעית אימא סברא. Iba'it eima kra ve'iba'it eima sevara.
If you want I will tell you that it's a פסוק, pasuk,
if you want I will just tell you it's logical. איבעית אימא
סברא, Iba'it eima sevara, if you want I will tell you that
it's a סברא. sevara. עובדי כוכבים לביהו לשמים. Ovdei kochavim libehu lashamayim.
That's a very interesting phrase. A non-Jew thinks about God, his heart
is to heaven. But what it means is is that, you know,
thinks about when you dedicate something to God, that means you give
it fully over to God. This concept of a שלמים shlamim that
I'm eating, you know, from God's table, in God's presence, I mean
if I gave it as a god, the God, why should I
still be eating from it? So that's fascinating that that's sort of
attributed to a non-Jewish mentality, you know, if anything somebody might think
that eating, you know, in the context of a sacrifice might sound
even a little pagan maybe
דוקא davka with a non-Jewish idea. But anyway,
that is one explanation that they think it has to be fully
to God. So even when they say שלמים, shlamim, they're just assuming
it's all to God. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, if you want, קרא
kra it's a פסוק pasuk because we learn... out non-Jews from איש
איש, ish ish, and I already sort of,
you know, ruined the surprise. The end of the פסוק pasuk is
אשר יקריבו להשם לעולה, asher yakrivu l'Hashem l'olah, that they offer to
God as an עולה. olah. So later פסוקים pesukim talk about שלמים,
shelamim, but this is read as, if a non-Jew is offering it,
it is going to be an עולה. olah. כל דמקרבי עולה להוי,
kol demikrevi olah lehavei,
whatever they offer is going to be treated as an עולה. olah.
All right. So that's the statement. Now we're going to challenge it.
מתיב רב חמא בר גוריא. metiv Rav Chama bar Guria. So רב
חמא בר גוריא Rav Chama bar Guria challenges. One wonders if גוריא
Guria means גר, ger, and whether he was, sort of had a
personal stake in this. Anyway, exactly a stake, but anyway, he challenged
it the following way: עובד כוכבים שהתנדב להביא שלמים, oved kokhavim shehitnadev
lehavi shelamim,
if a non-Jew takes a vow to give a שלמים, shelamim, so
this is a תוספתא, Tosefta, נתנם לישראל ישראל אוכלם, netanam l'Yisrael Yisrael
okhlam,
if he gives it to a ישראל, Yisrael, the ישראל Yisrael eats
it; נתנם לכהן כהן אוכלם, netanam l'kohen kohen okhlam, to a כהן,
kohen, a כהן kohen eats it. So it's a very hard-to-parse teaching.
What does it mean he gives them to an Israelite? What it
seems to be saying is he can bring a שלמים shelamim but
he can't eat it. Okay, we'll take his sacrifice, but to have
a non-Jew eating from a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, that's not acceptable. So you choose. You can give it to
a ישראל Yisrael and then it'll be treated as a ישראל. Yisrael.
You give it to a כהן, kohen, maybe then it'll be treated
as the portion of a כהן. kohen. That seems to be what
the ברייתא braita is saying.
But anyway, it seems like he can bring a שלמים. shelamim. So
אמר רבא הכי קאמר, amar Rava hachi ka'amar, no no, here's what
the ברייתא braita means: על מנת שיתכפרו בהן ישראל ישראל אוכלם, al
menat sheyitkapru bahen Yisrael Yisrael okhlam, על מנת שיתכפרו בהן כהן כהן
אוכלם. al menat sheyitkapru bahen kohen kohen okhlam. He can dedicate something
as a שלמים shelamim of a ישראל. Yisrael. If a ישראל Yisrael
has, took a vow to give a שלמים, shelamim, a non-Jew can
say, let me dedicate my animal, my cow, this cow will be
ראובן's Reuven שלמים, shelamim, or let me dedicate it to this כהן,
kohen, it'll be this כהן's kohen שלמים. shelamim. So even though he
owns the cow, it is the sacrifice of the person on whose
sake it was dedicated and sanctified and therefore, and then you follow
accordingly, but not that the שלמים shelamim can actually be his שלמים.
shelamim. It could start as his cow, but it's not his שלמים.
shelamim.
Okay. מתיב רב שיזבי. metiv Rav Shizbi. So רב שיזבי Rav Shizbi
challenged, and this is why we're discussing it here. אלו מנחות נקמצות
ושיריהן לכהנים. elu menachot nikmatzot v'shiyreihen l'kohanim. Our משנה, mishnah, the following
מנחות menachot you take a קמיצה kmitzah and the remainder is eaten
by the כהנים. kohanim. מנחת עובדי כוכבים, minchat ovdei kokhavim, and it
says non-Jew. So you see a non-Jew can bring a מנחה. mincha.
And רב הונא Rav Huna is saying a non-Jew can only bring
an עולה. olah. So it doesn't have the challenge like a שלמים
shelamim that the owners would eat it, because here the כהן kohen
eats it. So you might have made a חילוק, chiluk, you know,
you said he could bring an עולה olah or a מנחה, mincha,
but he can't bring anything that the owners would eat. But that
is not what רב הונא Rav Huna said, so this is a
challenge to רב הונא's Rav Huna statement.
So אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא רבי יוסי הגלילי והא
רבי עקיבא. ha Rabbi Yossi HaGlili veha Rabbi Akiva. Really what רב
הונא Rav Huna said was is a debate of תנאים. tannaim. It's
a debate of רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili and רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, and our משנה mishnah is taking the side, as we'll
see, of רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili, that it's not limited
to an עולה, olah, but what רב הונא Rav Huna was saying,
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position, that it is limited to an עולה.
olah. דתניא, detanya, we learned in the ברייתא: braita: איש, ish, this
is the exact פסוק pasuk I was
quoting, איש איש מבית ישראל מן הגר בישראל אשר יקריב קרבנו לכל
נדריהם ולכל נדבותם אשר יקריבו להשם לעולה.
ish ish mibeit Yisrael min hager b'Yisrael asher
yakriv korbano l'chol nidreihem ul'chol nidvotam asher yakrivu l'Hashem l'olah. So איש,
ish, מה תלמוד לומר איש איש, mah talmud lomar ish ish, what
does it say, "any man"? לרבות עובדי כוכבים שנודרים נדרים ונדבות כישראל.
lerabot ovdei kokhavim shenodrim nedarim unedavot k'Yisrael. So that's basically what we've
been working off of from the beginning, that איש איש ish ish
is even a non-Jew can make a vow and an offering and
sanctify it and it be offered in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
אשר יקריבו להשם לעולה. asher yakrivu l'Hashem l'olah. So now jumping to
the end of the פסוק, pasuk, "as an עולה." olah. אין לי
אלא עולה, ein li ela olah, I might think it's limited to
עולה, olah, which is רב הונא's Rav Huna position, and as we'll
see, רבי עקיבא's. Rabbi Akiva שלמים מניין, shelamim minayin, how do you
know it includes a שלמים? shelamim? תלמוד לומר נדריהם, talmud lomar nidreihem,
their נדר. neder. Now a נדר neder can be an עולה, olah,
but it's an extra word to teach you anything they make a
נדר neder for, even a שלמים. shelamim.
תודה מניין, todah minayin, how do you know even a category of
a תודה, todah, you know, which is really a type of a
שלמים? shelamim? תלמוד לומר נדבותם, talmud lomar nidvotam, another extra word to
tell you even yet another category of קרבנות. korbanot. מניין לרבות העופות
והיין והלבונה והעצים? minayin lerabot ha'ofot vehayayin vehalevona veha'etzim? How do I
know anything that you can, that a Jew can, you know, dedicate
and be offered up on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, including bird sacrifices, wine,
frankincense, wood? All these types of things are things that can be
dedicated and offered up on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. תלמוד לומר נדריהם לכל
נדריהם נדבותם לכל נדבותם. talmud lomar nidreihem l'chol nidreihem nidvotam l'chol nidvotam.
The לכל l'chol and the use of נדרים, nedarim, נדבות, nedavot, לכל
l'chol is coming to tell you anything, anything that can be sanctified
and offered, a non-Jew can do. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר עולה?
im ken mah talmud lomar olah? So why does the end of
the פסוק pasuk emphasize עולה? olah? עולה
פרט לנזירות, olah perat l'nezirut, דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי, divrei Rabbi Yossi
HaGlili, to exclude the עולה olah of a נזיר, nazir, that he
can't do since He can't be a נזיר, nazir, he can't bring
the עולה olah of a נזיר. nazir. Fine, so that's the only
thing רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi Haglili excludes. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rebbe
Akiva omer, however רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva says, אשר יקריבו לה' לעולה,
asher yakrivu la-Shem l'olah, אין לי אלא עולה בלבד. ein li ela
olah bilvad. I look at the end of the פסוק. pasuk. Only
an עולה olah a non-Jew can bring. So now okay so that's
it so it's a debate of it's not clear what he does
with those all those extra words, but it's a debate of רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi Haglili and רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. Our משנה
mishnah that has a non-Jew bringing a מנחה minchah is רבי יוסי
הגלילי, Rebbe Yosi Haglili, but רב הונא'ס Rav Huna's statement was a
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva statement. And now the גמרא'ס Gemara's just going
to wrap this up.
והאי פרט לנזירות מהכא נפקא, ve-hai perat lenezirut me-hacha nafka, do we
learn that a non-Jew can't bring a קרבן korban from נזיר nazir
from here? והא מהתם נפקא, ve-ha me-hatam nafka, we learn it from
the פסוק pasuk by a נזיר. nazir. דבר אל בני ישראל ואמרת
אליהם איש כי יפלי לנדור נדר נזיר להזיר. dabber el benei Yisrael
ve-amarta alehem ish ki yafli lindor neder nazir lehazzir. Speak to the
children of Israel. בני ישראל נודרים ואין עובדי כוכבים נודרים. benei Yisrael
nodrim ve-ein ovdei kochavim nodrim. בני ישראל benei Yisrael can be a
נזיר nazir and not non-Jews. So גמרא Gemara says no, אי מהתם
הוה אמינא קרבן הוא דלא ליתי אבל נזירות חלה עליה קמשמע לן.
ei me-hatam hava amina korban hu dela liti aval nezirut chala alei
kamashma lan. If it was from there I would have said fine
maybe you know they can't bring the קרבן korban of a נזיר
nazir but maybe they would become a נזיר? nazir? So that's why
it teaches you know that they can't become a נזיר. nazir. Now
it sounds a little like it's saying our פסוק pasuk is teaching
that they can't become a נזיר, nazir, but actually it makes more
sense to say the opposite. Our פסוק pasuk is teaching that they
don't bring a קרבן korban of a נזיר nazir and the פסוק
pasuk by נזירות nezirut itself is teaching that they can't become a
נזיר. nazir. What the גמרא Gemara doesn't exactly answer is why still
why do you need both? Just tell me they can't become a
נזיר nazir and then obviously they can't bring a קרבן korban of
a נזיר. nazir. Okay but anyway, כמאן
אזלא הא דתנן, ke-man azla ha de-tenan, who is it going like
that which we taught, meaning this debate of what a non-Jew can
dedicate? אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rebbe Shimon, said רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon,
שבעה דברים התקינו בית דין. shiv'ah devarim hitkinu beit din. בית דין
beit din established seven things, וזה אחד מהם ve-zeh echad me-hem and
the following is one of them. עובדי כוכבים ששלחו עולתם ממדינת הים,
ovdei kochavim she-shalechu olatam mi-medinat ha-yam, if a non-Jew sent an עולה
olah to be brought from overseas, ושלחו עמה נסכיה, ve-shilechu imah nesacheiha,
and he sent with it the you know the נסכים, nesachim, the
wine and the flour and the oil that's brought with an עולה.
olah. קרבים משלו kerevim mishelo then you offer that up as well.
ואם לאו ve-im lav and if he didn't send this accompanying נסכים,
nesachim, קרבים משל ציבור kerevim mishel tzibbur we use communal funds. So
his חידוש chiddush was that we use communal funds if he didn't
send it. But implicitly it's saying that he can send an עולה
olah with the נסכים. nesachim. So לימא רבי יוסי הגלילי ולא רבי
עקיבא, leima Rebbe Yosi Haglili ve-lo Rebbe Akiva, let's say it's רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi Haglili and not רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, because
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva maybe would not let him bring the נסכים
nesachim that would accompany an עולה? olah? So the גמרא Gemara gives
the obvious answer. No, אפילו תימא רבי עקיבא, afilu teima Rebbe Akiva,
could even be רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. עולה וכל חברתה. olah ve-chol
chavratah. עולה olah and its friends, עולה olah and its retinue I
would say. So yes you bring an עולה olah and then you
bring the wine and the flour and oil that come with an
עולה. olah. He wouldn't bring wine and flour and oil by itself.
Fine, מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן, man tana le-ha de-tanu rabbanan, who
is the תנא tanna of which that which we
taught? אזרח. ezrach. Okay אזרח מביא נסכים, ezrach mevi nesachim, this is
by a פסוק pasuk that speaks about the bringing of the נסכים.
nesachim. I only know that a citizen brings to the נסכים nesachim
and only a citizen, only a ישראל Yisrael brings the נסכים, nesachim,
ואין עובדי כוכבים מביא נסכים. ve-ein ovdei kochavim mevi nesachim. Okay but
not a non-Jew. יכול לא תהא עולתו טעונה נסכים, yachol lo tehei
olato te'unah nesachim, maybe I would go so far to say that
even if he brings an עולה olah it cannot come with the
נסכים nesachim that accompany the עולה? olah? תלמוד לומר ככה. talmud lomar
kachah. It
this is how it has to be. So it has to be
this way when he brings an עולה olah he brings it with
the נסכים, nesachim, but he can't dedicate נסכים nesachim independently. מני, mani,
who is this going like? לא רבי יוסי הגלילי ולא רבי עקיבא.
lo Rebbe Yosi Haglili ve-lo Rebbe Akiva. It wouldn't seem to work
according to either of them, which is not so clear why not.
אי רבי יוסי הגלילי, ei Rebbe Yosi Haglili, if it's רבי יוסי
הגלילי, Rebbe Yosi Haglili, הא אמר אפילו יין נמי, ha amar afilu
yayin nami, then he says he can bring נסכים nesachim by itself.
And this ברייתא braita says he can't. אי רבי עקיבא, ei Rebbe
Akiva, if it's רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, הא אמר עולה ומידי אחריני
לא. ha amar olah u-midi achrinei lo. He said just an עולה
olah and now we're still working with before the answer we gave
before and we think just an עולה olah and not even the
stuff that accompanies it. So גמרא Gemara says אי בעית אימא רבי
יוסי הגלילי ואי בעית אימא רבי עקיבא. ei ba'it eima Rebbe Yosi
Haglili ve-ei ba'it eima Rebbe Akiva. It could go according to either.
אי בעית אימא רבי יוסי הגלילי, ei ba'it eima Rebbe Yosi Haglili,
סמי מכאן יין. sami mikan yayin. It could be רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rebbe Yosi Haglili but let's take off of the list יין. yayin.
When we have a list that רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi says הגלילי
Haglili says he could bring anything, anything except wine. Now wine would
be a bizarre thing to exclude, but maybe that's what we're learning
from the word from here אזרח. ezrach. The word אזרח ezrach would
say even for רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Yosi Haglili a non-Jew could
bring anything except wine. Again somewhat bizarre and רבי יוסי הגלילי'ס Rebbe
Yosi Haglili's original statement did say wine. So the better answer is
the other point. ואי בעית אימא, ve-ei ba'it eima, if you want
I can tell you, רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva is רבי עקיבא. Rebbe
Akiva. עולה וכל חברתה, olah ve-chol chavratah, like we said before, עולה
olah and its retinue. So yes according to רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
a non-Jew brings an עולה olah with the נסכים, nesachim, but any
קרבן korban other than an עולה olah and נסכים nesachim by themselves
cannot be brought by the non-Jew. Okay we will end here.