Video. Okay, so today's דף Daf is פ"ב עמוד א'. Phei Bet
Amud Aleph. We pick up in the middle of פ"ב עמוד ב',
Phei Bet Amud Bet, ובתרביצא. U-ve-tarbitza. It is about 20 lines from
the bottom, beginning of a line, ובתרביצא. U-ve-tarbitza. Two lines above the
א aleph in parenthesis. So what we had just seen was a
whole debate between ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and, who was it, ר'
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer about how we know that a פסח Pesach can
only come from non-sanctified funds, from
non-מעשר שני ma'aser sheini funds, where ר' אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, I'm trying
to remember,
yes, ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer learns it out from the פסח מצרים
Pesach Mitzrayim and ר' עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you cannot learn out
מעשה אפשר ma'aseh efshar from מעשה שאי
אפשר. ma'aseh she-ee efshar. And then we had a whole back and
forth about that and about how ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer learned it
out from a היקש, hekesh, from an explicit פסוק pasuk that linked
the two. And the גמרא Gemara has a famous line: אין משיבין
על ההיקש. Ein meshivin al ha-hekesh. Once you have an explicit פסוק,
pasuk, then the questions are no longer even valid. And now the
גמרא Gemara just wraps this up. ובתרביצא אמרי. U-ve-tarbitza amre. Now, ובתרביצא
tarbitza is an interesting word. רש"י Rashi says it means like a
gathering of students, like in the ישיבה, yeshiva, like הרבצת תורה. harbatzat
Torah. So there they ask the following question about learning it out
from פסח Pesach and applying it to other קרבנות, korbanot, this principle.
They said: וכי דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש Ve-chi davar ha-lamed
be-hekesh chozer u-melamed be-hekesh? One minute, we learned פסח דורות Pesach Dorot
from פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim. Then we're going to take the
פסח Pesach of future generations and apply from that to all other
קרבנות korbanot that it can't come from מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money.
So now we have this problem which we're familiar with in קדשים:
Kodshim: can something that you learned out from one link then you
know, from A, you learn out A applies to B, can you
then take B and apply it to C? חוזר ומלמד בהיקש Chozer
u-melamed be-hekesh? Are you allowed to do that? So the גמרא Gemara
says: בכללה איתמר. Be-khulala it-mar. No, it was said
as a general group, meaning when פסח... Pesach... כולה חדא מילתא היא.
kula chada milta hi. The פסח, Pesach, whatever כולה חדא מילתא היא,
kula chada milta hi, all קרבן פסח korban Pesachs are one thing.
So when you learn out פסח דורות Pesach Dorot from פסח מצרים,
Pesach Mitzrayim, that's not really, even though you needed a היקש hekesh
because it was דורות Dorot from שעה, Sha'ah, from a general law
to something that applied only once in history, nevertheless when you learn
it out, it's not considered to be like you learned A from
B. It's considered to be one category. And therefore you're learning all
פסח Pesach this applies and therefore from פסח Pesach you apply to
other קרבנות, korbanot, so that's considered not like daisy-chaining it twice. Okay,
now ר' עקיבא: Rabbi Akiva: בפסח אין דנו אלא מן החולין מנין.
be-Pesach ein danu ela min hachulin minayin. Now again, ר' עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva doesn't debate the ruling. The ruling is that פסח Pesach can
only come from non-מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money and from this we
treat all other קרבנות. korbanot. But he just says that you can't
learn it out from פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim. So where does he
know this principle that
פסח Pesach can only come from non-מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money or
that generally קרבנות korbanot only come from non-מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money?
Where does he know this principle? נפקא ליה מהא דאמר שמואל משום
ר' אלעזר. Nafka lei me-ha d'amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Elazar. The statement
of שמואל Shmuel in the name of ר' אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Interesting
here because it's ר' אלעזר Rabbi Elazar as well, and we'll actually
see part of this statement also makes an assumption like ר' אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. Anyway, there's going to be a general פסוק pasuk which
is going to teach us a lot of laws of קרבנות, korbanot,
and from all of the laws of קרבנות korbanot we're going to
learn from this פסוק, pasuk, one of them will teach us what
we need to know: that קרבן korban can only come from non-מעשר
שני ma'aser sheini money, even if you can't learn it out from
קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. What is this פסוק? pasuk? זאת התורה לעולה
ולמנחה. Zot ha-Torah la-olah ve-la-minchah.
This is a פסוק pasuk that appears in צו Tzav after it
lists all the various קרבנות: korbanot: 'This is the law for the
עולה, olah, the מנחה, minchah, ולחטאת, ve-la-chatat, ולאשם, ולמלואים, ul'asham u'l'miluim
and the consecration sacrifice, ולזבח השלמים.' u-le-zeivach ha-shelamim.
And the שלמים shelamim sacrifice. So it links all of them, one
law for all of them. So what we're going to do is
take a feature that we know by each one of these that
we don't know by the others and we're going to say that
this applies to all קרבנות. korbanot. So this פסוק pasuk actually is
one in which we learn... thank you... a lot of laws of
קרבנות. korbanot. Actually, quite interestingly, that exact same דרשה drasha of this
פסוק, pasuk, a nice sort of like summing up general פסוק, pasuk,
which is what it's doing here, comes towards the end of the
מסכת, masekhet, and it actually came almost exactly at this location towards
the end of זבחים. Zevachim. So you know, after you go through
everything, you have a זאת התורה, Zot ha-Torah, you have something that
sort of sums it all up and teaches you a lot of
laws that are shared by all of them. So what we're about
to read now is almost word for word in זבחים. Zevachim. So
let's take a look.
זאת התורה לעולה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמלואים ולזבח השלמים. Zot ha-Torah la-olah
ve-la-minchah ve-la-chatat ve-la-asham ve-la-miluim u-le-zeivach ha-shelamim. עולה. Olah. So first of all,
let's start with עולה. olah. מה עולה טעונה כלי, Ma olah te'unah
keli, the same way by an עולה olah you need to use
a vessel, אף כל טעון כלי, af kol ta'un keli, every קרבן
korban you need a vessel. So מהי? mahi? What type of a
vessel are we talking about? אילימא מזרק, Ileima mizrak, if you're talking
about the bowl for catching the blood, how do we know you
had this by an עולה? olah? Because after הר סיני Har Sinai
it says that they slaughtered sacrifices: ויזבחו עולות, va-yizbechu olot, what is
it, וזבחים שלמים לה' פרים. va-zevachim shelamim l'Adonai parim. So they brought
עולות olot and שלמים shelamim and it says that they took the
blood: וישם באגנות, va-yasem ba-aganot, and they put it in bowls. Right?
Remember משה Moshe sprinkles the blood on the מזבח mizbe'ach and he
sprinkles it on the people. So there they... blood, how do we
know you had this by an עולה? Olah? Because after הר סיני
Har Sinai it says that they slaughtered sacrifices, ויזבחו עלות, va-yizbehu olot,
what is it, וזבחים שלמים להשם פרים, u-zvachim shlamim l'Hashem parim, so
they brought עלות Olot and שלמים, Shlamim, and it says that they
took the blood וישם באגנות, va-yasem ba-aganot, and they put it in
bowls, right? Remember משה Moshe sprinkles the blood on the מזבח Mizbe'ach
and he sprinkles it on the people? So there you see you
caught the blood in a bowl, in a vessel, and that's what
we learn out from an עולה. Olah. So the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, גבי זבחי שלמי צבור נמי כתיב, gabei zivchei shalmei tzibbur
nami ketiv, but that's not just written by the עולה, Olah, it's
also written by שלמים, Shlamim, by communal שלמים, Shlamim, because the פסוק
Pasuk says וישם באגנות, va-yasem ba-aganot, he put it in the vessels.
Now who cares that it's also written by שלמים? Shlamim? Because the
assumption here is that we are finding something that only is written
by one of the, by you know, by each thing that's listed
in this פסוק. Pasuk. We are finding a law that's written by
just that one thing and then because the פסוק Pasuk links them,
we're applying it to everything. So it's, you know, doesn't have to
be a problem that it's written by more than one, but we're
assuming that we're going to look for something that only exists by
one of them. So the idea that that it requires a bowl
to catch, that's not unique to an עולה. Olah. So that's not
what we're focusing on. אלא, Ella, what vessel are we focusing on
that is unique by an עולה? Olah? סכין, Sakin, that you need
a knife. Okay, that's a knife now for שחיטה. Shechitah. So the
גמרא Gemara says ועולה גופא מנלן, v'olah gufah minalan, how do you
know the עולה Olah itself required a knife, a vessel? דכתיב, de-chtiv,
it says, prepare yourself, וישלח אברהם את ידו ויקח את המאכלת לשחוט
את בנו. va-yishlach Avraham et yado va-yikach et ha-machelet lishchot et bno.
So אברהם Avraham sent forth his hand and he took the knife,
you know, actually I forget, I think one of the מפרשי המקרא
Mefarshei Ha-Mikra contemporary ones, not traditional ones, points out that the word
מאכלת, Machelet, which is basically like, you know, like a meat eater,
like it's a very graphic term, you know, for a knife. It's
something that like, you know, that that cuts into meat. Anyway, this
is like the only place where the תורה Torah uses that word
to refer to a knife, which is actually also interesting because when
יצחק Yitzchak says to אברהם, Avraham, he says, you know, הנה האש
והעצים ואיה השה לעלה, hinei ha-esh v'ha-etzim v'ayeh ha-seh l'olah, he doesn't
mention the knife, right? That's the thing that he's like avoiding. So
anyway, but it's a very graphic term for a knife. Anyway, so
you see that אברהם Avraham used a knife. Now והתם עולה הוא,
v'hatam olah hu, and there we know that יצחק Yitzchak was considered
an עולה. Olah. דכתיב, de-chtiv, because it says by the ram afterwards,
ויעלהו לעולה תחת בנו, va-ya'alehu l'olah tachat bno, that he raised it
up as an עולה Olah in exchange for his son. So his
son was being treated like an עולה Olah and he had a
knife. So it's a pretty funny that that is, or a little
bit more than funny, I think anyway, a little disturbing that that
is the source of, you know, because the whole idea of course
being that it's not supposed to be about human sacrifice, we would
like to think not only is it not about human sacrifices, but
we're not supposed to think that the animal sacrifices are some type
of a substitute of human sacrifices. We would think we'd like to
think it's a complete rejection while it's true by אברהם Avraham it
says, you know, תחת בנו, tachat bno, עולה תחת בנו, olah tachat
bno, I it's funny that that becomes then a model for animal
sacrifices afterwards.
So I don't have anything to say about that other than just
noting it. Yes.
So why are we referring to specifically to עולה? Olah? Obviously every
kind of animal sacrifice would require a knife.
Ah, but it doesn't say it by others. So what your question
is what was the other option? How else would you שחט? shechet?
So
you could have שחט shecheted it with something that wasn't a vessel.
And the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara in חולין Chulin when it
talks about general laws of שחיטה Shechitah wants to know does the
knife have to be something that is, you know, movable? Can it
be, what can it be, let's say I have a sharp edge
on a wall? Can I somehow, of course then you'd have to
move the animal rather than moving the knife. But anyway, the גמרא
Gemara wants to know can it be מחובר לקרקע? mechubar l'karka? And
it says, I'm not exactly sure how you would manage that by
moving the thing. Let's say it was a swaying tree, okay, I
sharpened an edge of a tree and I moved the tree. That
would be an example. So it says no, you can't. We know
it has to be detached. And we learn again from אברהם, Avraham,
the idea that that the knife was detached. So we learn that
the knife has to be detached. The question is what is our
גמרא Gemara teaching more than the issue of detached when it says
כלי? kli? That's true by general by שחיטה. Shechitah. So תוספות Tosafos
assumes that we're taking the idea that it has to be a
כלי שרת. kli sharet. If you remember when we learned זבחים Zevachim
I pointed out that there's a מחלוקת ראשונים machloket Rishonim actually whether
you need a כלי שרת kli sharet by שחיטה, Shechitah, whether it
has to be a sanctified vessel or not. If it is telling
כלי שרת, kli sharet, it's funny how we learn that out by
אברהם. Avraham. Where do you see it was a כלי שרת? kli
sharet? I mean it was a vessel, who tells you it was
a כלי שרת? kli sharet? So תוספות Tosafos tries to figure out
somehow from an extra word that we're learning it out, but it's
not clear. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say כלי שרת, kli sharet, it
just says כלי. kli. So it could be that this גמרא Gemara
is saying nothing more than the גמרא Gemara in חולין, Chulin, that
it has to be something separate, maybe something fashioned as a knife.
You know, the question is what about if you let's say picked
up a sharp rock and you used your sharp rock? Would that
be considered good? So that might be something, it might satisfy the
non-קרבן korban requirement of detached, but it wouldn't satisfy the קרבן korban
requirement of כלי. kli. כלי kli might mean that it has to
be fashioned specifically to function as the knife. So there really are
like three levels if you think about it. There's one that it
has to be detached, which is what the גמרא Gemara in חולין
Chulin says by normal שחיטה. Shechitah. There's another that it has to
be a vessel as opposed to let's say a sharp rock. And
there's a third that it has to be a כלי שרת. kli
sharet. כלי שרת kli sharet is actually debated in terms of שחיטה
Shechitah of קרבן. korban. Yes.
The action doesn't appear with the איל? ayal? It does.
Oh you mean why did we have to go via via יצחק,
Yitzchak, why didn't we just quote... yeah, I just think it says
ויעלהו, va-ya'alehu, it doesn't mention the use of the knife.
So they are viewing
יצחק Yitzchak as a potential
real potential sacrifice and right.
יצחק Yitzchak was being treated as a type of a sacrifice and
as an עולה. olah. And for that, and because he was being
treated as a sacrifice, Avraham insisted to have this סכין. sakin. So
from there we can see. Yes, it would have been much better.
It's very disturbing to learn out laws of sacrifices from יצחק. Yitzchak.
We would like to sort of try to bracket that and certainly
not with the even in the context of animal sacrifices, not think
that somehow it's in some parallel to, you know, to that type
of...
Well, I think you're in a way forced to say it is
a parallel, that just like here, the איל ayil תחת בנו tachat
bno is telling you very clearly, you are sacrificing an animal instead
of a human. Right. I know.
I'm just saying, you know,
you don't like it, but it's very clear.
I understand, you're right. These are one some of the things that
we would like to bracket and the גמרא Gemara is sort of
forcing us to pay attention to it, right. Although I wish I,
you know, had something more to say about it than that it's
disturbing. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, so that's one we
learn from an עולה. olah.
והתם עולה, v'hatam olah, oh, I just did that. Okay, מנחה. minchah.
Now after that
pretty, you know, disturbing whatever
discussion, now we go on, we just totally switch, keep on moving,
מנחה. minchah. So it says לעולה ולמנחה. l'olah v'laminchah. So what are
we going to learn out from מנחה? minchah? מה מנחה אינה נאכלת
אלא לזכרי
כהונה. mah minchah einah ne'echelet ela l'zichrei kehunah. A מנחה's minchah only
eaten by male כהנים. kohanim. It says that explicitly.
Well, it does, no, that it says explicitly. That it says explicitly
in the תורה. Torah. אף כל אינו נאכל אלא לזכרי כהונה. af
kol eino ne'echal ela l'zichrei kehunah. So anything that's eaten by כהנים,
kohanim, now that doesn't mean anything that's eaten because the שלמים shlamim
is eaten and it's eaten by whoever brings it and anybody they
want to give it to, man or woman or whatever. So that's
not limited to כהנים, kohanim, it's not limited to males, but anything
that goes to the כהנים kohanim of the קרבנות korbanot is limited
to the male כהנים kohanim as opposed to for example תרומה, terumah,
right, תרומה terumah you give to the כהנים, kohanim, it's not a
קרבן korban and the כהנים kohanim can feed it to their whole
family, to the women, to the children and so on. But here,
the קרבנות korbanot that go to the כהנים kohanim is only the
male כהנים. kohanim. How do you know that? It says first of
all the... well, we learn it from מנחה, minchah, but the גמרא
Gemara says but where do we... where do we not know that?
מאי? mai? So
what is this applying to? אי חטאת ואשם ei chatat v'asham if
you're telling me the law of a חטאת chatat and an אשם,
asham, בהדיא כתיב, behedya ktiv, it's written explicitly in the פסוקים psukim
says that this goes to the כהנים. kohanim. אלא, ela, אם זבחי
שלמי ציבור, im zivchei shalmei tzibur,
if it is from the communal שלמים, shlamim, it's so funny that
this is a category in itself that only has, you know, one
thing in the category, which is basically the כבשי עצרת, kivsei atzeret,
the lambs of שבועות. Shavuot. Well, I mean, actually did also have
the lambs, the שלמים shlamim that were brought during the מילואים, milu'im,
but that... those no longer apply. So anyway, if it is the
communal שלמים, shlamim, which normally a שלמים shlamim goes to the owner
and here because of communal שלמים shlamim it goes to כהנים, kohanim,
מריבוייא דקרא אתיא, me'ribuyah d'kra atya, we get it from an extra
word in the פסוק. pasuk. We don't need to learn it from
that. Why, what's the extra word? So here it says in במדבר
Bamidbar at the end of פרשת קרח Parshat Korach when, you know,
because the כהונה kehunah was challenged, the תורה Torah reiterates to the
כהנים kohanim all of the things that they are entitled to and
that is their portion in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So it
says and after listing a whole list of things, of חטאת chatat
and an אשם asham and so on, that this is what you
get from the... from the fires in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
it says the following: בקודש הקודשים תאכלנו, bekodesh hakodashim tochelenu, in the
holy of holies you shall eat it, כל זכר יאכל אותו, kol
zachar yochal oto, all male, not say כהנים, kohanim, but anyway, but
that's implicit. All male כהנים kohanim will eat it. So why... and
then we say, לימד על זבחי שלמי ציבור, limed al zivchei shalmei
tzibur, that's an extra פסוק pasuk because it... whatever it... because it
didn't have to say
יאכל אותו. yochal oto. It could have just said בקודש הקודשים תאכלנו
כל זכר. bekodesh hakodashim tochelenu kol zachar. It already said eat it,
so why does it add the words יאכל אותו? yochal oto? So
לימד על זבחי שלמי ציבור, limed al zivchei shalmei tzibur, even things
not mentioned in this פסוק, pasuk, even not the חטאת chatat and
the אשם asham and the מנחה, minchah, even the communal שלמים shlamim
שאינו נאכל אלא לזכרי כהונה she'eino ne'echal ela l'zichrei kehunah is only
eaten by the male כהנים. kohanim. So the law we know, but
we know it from this פסוק pasuk in קרח. Korach. We don't
have to learn it from the מנחה. minchah. So the גמרא Gemara
says תנאי היא, tannai hi, you're right, it's a debate of תנאים,
tannaim, how to... where to learn it from. איכא דמייתי לה מהכא,
ika d'maiti lah mehacha, some learn it from the פסוק pasuk of
מנחה, minchah, ואיכא דמייתי לה מהכא, v'ika d'maiti lah mehacha, and some
learn it from there or here from the פסוק pasuk by קרח.
Korach. But okay, that's a debate where you learn it from, but
this תנא tanna learns it from מנחה. minchah. So now what have
we learned? עולה olah we learned a knife, מנחה minchah we learned
that anything the כהנים kohanim get is limited to the male כהנים,
kohanim, which the only thing it needs to teach me about is
the שלמי ציבור, shalmei tzibur, and now we go on. לעולה ולמנחה,
l'olah v'laminchah, what's next? ולחטאת. v'l'chatat.
So חטאת, chatat, what do we learn from the word
חטאת? chatat? מה חטאת מקדש בבלוע אף כל מקדש בבלוע. mah chatat
mekadesh b'valua af kol mekadesh b'valua. The same way a חטאת chatat
sanctifies by absorption, other things sanctify by absorption. What does this mean?
The תורה Torah says in צו, Tzav, it says כל אשר יגע
בבשרה יקדש. kol asher yiga b'visarah yikdash. Anything that touches the meat
of a חטאת chatat becomes holy. From here the גמרא Gemara learns
that if a
חטאת... chatat... The phrase itself like something was absorbed in the חטאת,
chatas, but the bigger חידוש chidush is that some of the חטאת
chatas or חטאת chatas juice gets absorbed into another קרבן, korban, so
that status transfers to the other קרבן. korban. Basically, it's a principle
that we have in כשרות kashrus of, you know, like mixtures, that
it's not בטל, batel, you have some of the חטאת chatas mixed
up into something else, so you have to treat it like the
similar stringency of the חטאת. chatas. It's actually more stringent than normal
laws of mixtures because basically when we get to חולין Chullin we'll
discuss it, but even if under normal principles of mixtures like if
it was non-כשר kosher and כשר, kosher, we would say it would
be בטל, batel, by the חטאת chatas the תורה Torah is telling
you it's not בטל. batel. So therefore what is this? This is
based on a פסוק pasuk in the תורה. Torah. It says כל
אשר יגע בבשרה יקדש, Kol asher yiga bivsarah yikdash, anything that touches
the flesh of the חטאת chatas becomes holy, and from there the
גמרא Gemara says יקדש להיות כמוה. Yikdash lihyos kamoha. It's holy like
the original חטאת. chatas. If the חטאת chatas was כשר, kasher, then
it's let's say it was a two-day sacrifice, it touched the חטאת
chatas which is a one-day sacrifice, you can only eat this second
thing for one day, it's limited the same way a חטאת chatas
is limited, ואם פסול, ve'im pasul, and if the חטאת chatas happened
to have been invalid and touched another sacrifice, תפסל, tipasel, then it
also becomes פסול pasul because basically it becomes a mixture and you
have to treat it like the more stringent one. So that is
the concept of מקדש בבלוע. mikadesh bevalua. It sanctifies through being absorbed.
So that's not limited to a חטאת. chatas. אף כל מקדש בבלוע.
Af kol mikadesh bevalua. If any קרבן korban gets absorbed into something
else, a קרבן korban or a non-קרבן, korban, whatever gets absorbed into,
you have to, you know, attend to this other to to its
status that is now mixed up with this other קרבן korban and
that status now applies to this other קרבן korban or to this
other thing. Okay, so this again, you know, you might ask why
is this a special קרבן korban principle? This is a general principle
of mixtures, that if something isn't בטל, batel, then you give it
the more stringent status. But it is special because as we'll see
in חולין, Chullin, it would be true even if under normal circumstances
it would be בטל, batel, by קרבנות korbanos it is not. Okay,
so that's what we learn by חטאת. chatas.
אשם, Asham, so it says זאת התורה לעלה Zos hatorah la'olah which
we learn a כלי, kli, a שחיטה shechitah knife, ולמנחה velaminchah we
learn that male כהנים, kohanim, ולחטאת velachatas we learn that if it
touches something and the juices get mixed up then that it transfers
its status, ולאשם. ve-la-asham, So now what are we going to learn
from the word אשם? asham? מה אשם אין שפיר ושליא קדוש בו,
Mah asham ein shapir veshilya kadosh bo, the same way an אשם,
asham, its placenta and embryo don't have any sanctity, אף כל אין
שפיר ושליא קדוש בו, af kol ein shapir veshilya kadosh bo, similarly
by any animal the embryo and placenta don't have any sanctity. Now
how do we know that an אשם asham the embryo and the
placenta don't have any sanctity? Because an אשם asham has to be
male. So
since there is no embryo and placenta, obviously it can't be holy.
So therefore even if you have a female sacrifice that has an
embryo and a placenta, it is not holy. Okay, which means what?
Which means you שחט shacht your, you know, your חטאת chatas and
you find this embryo or placenta in it, so you do not
have to offer it up on the מזבח. mizbeach. One thing רש"י
Rashi says in זבחים Zevachim is let's say you find it, well
not for the placenta but for the embryo, would you have to
take the kidneys and the fat out of whatever, I don't know
if it has fat at that stage, anyway, out of the embryo
and put it on the מזבח mizbeach because you're supposed to put,
you know, the kidneys and the fat on the מזבח? mizbeach? No,
that because now that's not saying it doesn't have sanctity so much,
that's more saying like because it's not, you know, the kidneys, it's
the kidneys of the mother, not the kidneys of the thing in
the mother. But nevertheless it could be even saying even more than
that, there's absolutely no sanctity, that you don't have to, you know,
not only does it not go on the מזבח, mizbeach, but you
don't have to treat it like meat of the קרבן korban and
it has none of the restrictions of
the
קרבן. korban. So that seems to be the point here that it
has no, that it does not have any sanctity. Now the problem
is is that of course how do you learn it out from
an אשם asham that doesn't even have these? So the גמרא Gemara
is about to say it. Let's take a look.
Where were we?
קסבר, Kasavar, so this is opinion number one, ולדות קדשים בהוייתן הן
קדושין, velados kodashim behavayasan hen kedoshin, the children of sacrifices are become
קדוש kadosh when they are become, בהוייה, behavayah, meaning when they're born.
But when they still, when they just exist as an embryo in
their mother's womb, they do not have קדושה, kedushah, they will be
קדוש, kadosh, that's a principle we learned, you know, yesterday about the
תודה, todah, that a child of the תודה todah has קדושת תודה,
kedushas todah, but that only is when the child is born. It
does not exist when it's in the womb, then it doesn't have
the קדושה. kedushah. And number two, ודנין אפשר משאי אפשר. vedanin efshar
mish'ee efshar. You can learn the possible from the not possible. So
although the אשם asham can't have an embryo and a placenta, nevertheless
you can apply for the fact that ah there's no sanctity of
an embryo placenta, so we'll apply that even when they can exist,
an embryo placenta, even to a female קרבן. korban. Now what is
a little ironic here is that we are quoting all of this
to to explain where רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva gets his principle about,
you know, about that a פסח Pesach can only come from non-sanctified
funds, because he doesn't get it from where רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
gets it from, because he doesn't. rejects the idea of דנים אפשר
משאי אפשר. danim efshar mishe'ee efshar. Okay, so why are here we're
saying that this whole ברייתא braita assumes that? But remember also this
ברייתא braita was אמר שמואל אמר רבי אליעזר. Amar Shmuel Amar Rebbe
Eliezer. This ברייתא braita actually is exactly from the school of רבי
אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer that says דנים אפשר משאי אפשר. danim efshar mishe'ee
efshar. So the point is until now though we have not yet
introduced רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. This is all like preface. This is
רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, שמואל Shmuel in the name of רבי אליעזר.
Rebbe Eliezer. It assumes דנים אפשר משאי אפשר. danim efshar mishe'ee efshar.
It learns something out from a male אשם asham to tell you
something about a female חטאת chatat in terms of the embryo; it
doesn't bother by אפשר efshar and אי אפשר. ee efshar. Eventually we're
going to get to רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, but we're not there
yet. This is still within the idea of רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
and דנים אפשר משאי אפשר. danim efshar mishe'ee efshar. Okay, so now
we have the אשם, asham, the מלואים. miluim. Now it says מלואים.
miluim. מה מלואים מותריהן, Ma miluim mosreihen, not motreihen, mosreihen, their extra
בשריפה bi'sreifa ואין בעלי חיים מותריהן. ve'ein ba'alei chayim mosreihen. If you
have something left over from a מלואים, miluim, meaning נותר. notar. The
תורה Torah says explicitly to the כהן Kohen to אהרן Aharon and
his children when they do the מלואים, miluim, if anything is left
over burn it in the fire. Now what's actually interesting is, you
know, I don't know why, maybe because I learned, you know, גמרא
Gemara at an early age, גמרא Gemara in פסחים Pesachim that speaks
about how you always burn נותר. notar. I assumed that it's in
all the פסוקים psukim that you burn נותר. notar. But actually it's
not by every case of נותר. notar. It says sometimes that you,
you know, the תורה Torah says that you burn the נותר notar
in fire, but it doesn't always. It always says you can't leave
it over, you can't eat it after you leave it over, but
it doesn't always say you burn it in fire. One place it
does say that is by the מלואים. miluim. So the same way
by the מלואים miluim it says מותריהן בשריפה mosreihen bi'sreifa that what
is left over meat you burn, so we're going to say that
by all sacrifices any נותר notar is burnt. And the other thing
though we do know by מלואים miluim is ואין בעלי חיים מותריהן.
ve'ein ba'alei chayim mosreihen. If there is live animals בשריפה bi'sreifa and
if an animal is alive hasn't been, you know, slaughtered, then even
if it's considered somehow left over and not used, you don't burn
it. Now of course you don't really, you never even had that
case. This is another case of like אי אפשר. ee efshar. רש״י
Rashi says שלא מצינו שריפה במלואים אלא בבשר לאחר שחיטה. shelo matzinu
sreifa bi'miluim ela bi'vasar le'achar shechita. The תורה Torah never relates to
that case. So this is another case of like
it just wasn't there. But the תורה Torah speaks about burning the
leftover meat and it doesn't talk about burning anything that's not meat,
that's not dead meat. So from there we'd learn that leftover meat,
נותר notar meat is burnt, but that you would not apply this
to an animal that was still alive. So how does this apply?
Let's take a look at the next line.
So...
oh no, we didn't even say אף כל. af kol. So similarly
מותריהן בשריפה, mosreihen bi'sreifa, any time you have נותר notar meat
you burn it. ואין בעלי חיים מותריהן בשריפה. ve'ein ba'alei chayim mosreihen
bi'sreifa. But not if you have leftover animals. Now what's the idea
of leftover animal being a נותר? notar? Well again this gets back
to what we taught before by the תודה. todah. Remember the case
of the תודה todah is you had a תודה, todah, I mean
it could be by any sacrifice, you had a תודה todah that
got lost, you designate another animal for it to replace it, then
you find your original one. Then you're going to bring one, well
what's the other one? The other one is like leftover. Right? It's
in a way it's נותר. notar. It was supposed to be brought,
it isn't, it's leftover. But the point is, okay, but the idea
of like, oh it's leftover and it was a day since the
first one's been brought, we're not going to start calling it נותר
notar and burning it. We're going to do something with it, we'll
figure it out, you'll bring it, you won't bring the bread, whatever
you're going to do, you don't apply the concept of נותר notar
to a live animal. Okay, so that's one of the other things
we learn out from מלואים. miluim. That when you do say נותר
notar you burn it, but you only apply it to meat, not
to a live animal. Okay so now what do we have?
לעולה שחיטה le'olah shechita ולמנחה מה
כהנים ul'mincha ma kohanim ולחטאת... מה אמרנו בחטאת? אה,
מקדשת בבלוע, mekadeshet bi'vlua, sanctifies if it gets, you know, some juice
transfer. לעולה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם le'olah u'l'mincha u'l'chatat u'l'asham
no embryo placenta being קדוש. kadosh. ולאשם vela'asham. ולמלואים ve-la-miluim,
the מלואים miluim is נותר, notar, you burn the נותר notar meat,
but it only applies to meat, and the last one of the
פסוק pasuk is ולזבח השלמים. ul'zevech ha'shlamim. שלמים, shlamim, אה, שלמים, shlamim,
מה שלמים מפגלים ומתפגלים, ma shlamim mifaglim u'mitfaglim, ah, our good friend
פיגול. pigul. The same way שלמים, shlamim, right, the תורה's Torah case
of פיגול pigul is totally by שלמים. shlamim. That is the case
that the תורה Torah writes פיגול pigul and that is the paradigm
of פיגול. pigul. So the same way by שלמים shlamim it creates
פיגול pigul and becomes פיגול. pigul. אף כל מפגלים ומתפגלים. af kol
mifaglim u'mitfaglim.
So this by everything that creates פיגול pigul in others also becomes
פיגול. pigul. What does this mean? רש״י Rashi says one thing which
is not פשט. pshat. רש״י Rashi says it means like
if I have a thought about פיגול pigul about the animal I
also make the attendant wine פיגול pigul and נסכים nesachim פיגול. pigul.
That's not really פשט. pshat. What תוספות Tosafot says is much more,
you know, focused on basic principles of פיגול pigul that the גמרא
Gemara says, which is, remember for example we've taught that
if a כהן's Kohen מנחה mincha you can't have פיגול pigul with.
Why can't you have פיגול pigul with a כהן's Kohen מנחה? mincha?
Because there's not a part that you offer that is מתיר matir
the rest. You burn the whole thing. To create פיגול, piggul, you
have to let there be זורק הדם, zorek hadam, which is מתיר
matir the בשר, basar, or you burn the אימורים, emurim, again, which
is like מתיר matir מתיר matir the rest. You do it to
one thing and there's some leftover which this is sort of affecting
the status of. So that's פיגול. piggul. So that is what the
גמרא Gemara here means מפגלין, mifaglin, it is מפגל mifagel something else.
You sprinkle the blood and it's מפגל mifagel the בשר. basar. If
you have a פיגול piggul thought while you are sprinkling the blood,
it is מפגל mifagel the בשר, basar, okay, and therefore מתפגלים, mitpaglim,
then it itself also becomes פיגול. piggul. But again, it's only because
there are two parts: something you're doing the act to, and therefore
the פיגול piggul is applying to something else, as opposed to, again,
a מנחת כהן, minchat kohen, the whole thing is burnt. Since the
whole thing is burnt, you can't have פיגול. piggul. That's the way
תוספות Tosafot explains the מפגלין ומתפגלים. mifaglin umitpaglim. It is מפגל mifagel
others and therefore becomes פיגול piggul itself. Okay, במתניתא תנא, bematnita tana,
that is one thing we learn out from all of those. That
was a nice little חזרה chazarah on laws of קרבנות. korbanot. Okay,
במתניתא תנא, bematnita tana, now we have a ברייתא. braita. That was
in the name of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Now we're going to
introduce רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, which is why we quoted this to
begin with. במתניתא תנא, bematnita tana, in a ברייתא, braita, we taught
משמיה דרבי עקיבא, mishmeih deRabbi Akiva, in the name of רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, the
following: זאת התורה, zot hatorah, etc. etc., the whole פסוק. pasuk. So
now we're going to go through. So for whatever reason we skipped
עולה, olah, maybe עולה olah we learn out the same knife thing,
so it spared us going through that again. Like יצחק, Yitzchak, it
spared us the knife. Okay, so now we go straight to the
מנחה. minchah. So מנחה, minchah, מה מנחה מקדשת בבלוע. mah minchah mikadeshet
bivalua. So rather than this idea that it sanctifies through transfer and
being absorbed, the תורה Torah says that both by חטאת chatat and
by מנחה, minchah, כל אשר יגע, kol asher yiga, but what's the
פסוק, pasuk, let's see,
by מנחה, minchah, רש"י Rashi quotes it,
כל אשר יגע בהם יקדש. kol asher yiga bahem yikdash. Okay, very
similar פסוק pasuk to the חטאת. chatat. So as opposed to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who learned it out from a חטאת, chatat, we're
learning it out from a מנחה. minchah. מה מנחה מקדשת בבלוע, mah
minchah mikadeshet bivalua, sanctifies through being absorbed, אף כל מקדשת בבלוע. af
kol mikadeshet bivalua. Other things also sanctify if they get absorbed into
something else, they transfer their status.
ואיצטריך למכתב בחטאת ואיצטריך למכתב במנחה. veitztarich lemichtav bachatat veitztarich lemichtav beminchah.
Now this is obviously the גמרא Gemara inserting it because רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva never said that it was written, this is what we
learn out from a חטאת. chatat. Oh, well actually, forget it, meaning
it probably is referring to the fact, why did the תורה Torah
have to write it by both? Meaning yes, here we're using this
פסוק pasuk to apply to all קרבנות. korbanot. But why did the
תורה Torah have to write it both by חטאת chatat and by
מנחה? minchah? Why couldn't the תורה Torah have just written it by
one? So here's why the תורה Torah had to write it both
by חטאת chatat and by מנחה. minchah. דאי כתב רחמנא במנחה, dei
katav rachamana beminchah, had it just been by מנחה, minchah, משום דרכיכא
בלעה, mishum derachicha balah, because it's soft, it
absorbs. אבל חטאת, aval chatat, אימא לא, eima lo, I would think
maybe it doesn't absorb so much. ואי כתב רחמנא בחטאת, vei katav
rachamana bachatat, had it written by a חטאת, chatat, משום דבשר אגב
דשמין קדיר, mishum debasar agav deshamein kadir, because meat, because it's fatty,
it sort of
penetrates. אבל מנחה, aval minchah, אימא לא, eima lo, I would think
not. צריכא, tzricha, need it written by both. Now I have to
tell you that, okay, by the case of the meat it says
penetrating, which is the classic idea of the תורה Torah about what
the point, that if it transfers, it transfers its קדושה kedushah to
something else by some of its juices getting absorbed in the other
thing. But by the מנחה, minchah, I don't understand. If a מנחה
minchah is soft, it absorbs, presumably that means it's absorbing other things,
not that it's getting absorbed into something else, right? If you put
a מנחה minchah on a חטאת, chatat, it'll slide off, right? The
מנחה's minchah quality is more to absorb from other things, but that's
less of a חידוש. chiddush. The חידוש chiddush is that if you
put something into a מנחה, minchah, it gets a status of a
מנחה minchah is much less of a חידוש chiddush than saying that
if a מנחה, minchah, a little of a מנחה minchah goes into
something else, that its status now applies to the other thing. So
the idea that the גמרא Gemara says because it's soft it absorbs,
I'm not sure,
maybe that's what it's saying. If it had just said מנחה, minchah,
I would have thought that only when it absorbs something else. But
then the answer is then don't say מנחה, minchah, say חטאת, chatat,
and then I'll obviously apply it to a מנחה. minchah. So it's
not clear to me what
this is mean, because it's soft it absorbs, since the point is
that we're talking about this transferring into something else, going into the
other thing, not taking from something else. Alright, so anyway, that's what
we learned from a מנחה. minchah. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns
that from a מנחה, minchah, not the idea about מאכלי כהנים, ma'achlei
kohanim, which is and now we'll go, which is not a problem
because if you remember, מאכלי כהנים, ma'achlei kohanim, we had another פסוק
pasuk for שלמי ציבור shalmei tzibbur from קרח. Korach. So that's what
he does for מנחה. minchah. Now we go on,
okay, אבל מנחה אימא לא צריכא. aval minchah eima lo tzricha. חטאת,
chatat, so what does he learn from חטאת? chatat? מחטאת אינה באה
אלא מן החולין. machatat einah ba'ah ela min hachulin. This is why
we brought this whole thing in. This is now רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, and now he's learning out the principle that it has to
come from non-מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, not from פסח, pesach, which he
doesn't learn
out, that's אפשר משאי אפשר. efshar mishei'efshar. He learns it out from
the חטאת chatat word of this פסוק. pasuk. דמי חטאת demei chatat
only comes from non-sanctified funds, from non-מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. וביום u'vayom
and only comes in the daytime, ובידו הימנית u'veyado hayemanit and requires
the hand, the right hand of the כהן, Kohen, אף כל af
kol so all other קרבנות korbanot אינה באה אלא מן החולין eina
ba'a ela min hachulin only from non-מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, וביום u'vayom
and in the daytime, ובידו הימנית u'veyado hayemanit and with the כהן
Kohen's right hand. Now we're going to say how we know this
by a
חטאת. Chatas. חטאת גופה מנלן Chatas gufah minalan where do you know
it by a חטאת? Chatas? Now we're finally getting to why we
quoted all of this. How do you know that קרבנות korbanot only
come from obligatory קרבנות, korbanot, excuse me, only come from non-מעשר שני?
Maaser Sheni? So אמר רבי חסדא אמר קרא amar Rebbe Chisda amar
kra because the פסוק pasuk
says והקריב אהרן את פר החטאת אשר לו, vehikriv Aharon et par
hachatat asher lo, right by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, אהרן Aharon shall
bring the חטאת Chatas that is his,
לו משלו, lo mishelo, it's his meaning it comes from his own
personal funds, ולא משל מעשר velo mishel maaser and not from any
other funds even not from מעשר Maaser funds. So from the לו
lo we say it has to come from his personal funds and
there we learn out that a חטאת Chatas comes, an obligatory קרבן
korban comes from, from non-מעשר Maaser and that is true now by
all קרבנות. korbanot. And that is the purpose of quoting all of
this. But now we're going to finish, וביום, u'vayom, how do you
know that a חטאת Chatas only comes in the day? Because it
says on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it says כי ביום הזה יכפר
עליכם. ki vayom hazeh yechaper aleichem. The גמרא Gemara doesn't say it,
but anyway that would be how we know a חטאת Chatas comes
in the day. So the גמרא Gemara says we don't need to
learn that from a
חטאת, Chatas, מביום צותו נפקא, mivayom tzavoto nafka, we learn it from
a פסוק pasuk that says these are the קרבנות korbanot on the
day that God had commanded and from that פסוק pasuk on the
day that God had commanded we learn that all קרבנות korbanot have
to be brought only in the day. So the גמרא Gemara says
you're right, כדי נסבה, kidi nasba, it was taken for nothing, it
was just thrown in. Okay, כדי kidi means like nothing. So it
was taken for no real purpose. It was just thrown in. The
real thing we learn out is that it has to come from
חולין. chulin. Okay, so now the other thing though that it said
we learned out from חטאת Chatas was ובידו הימנית, u'veyado hayemanit, that
the כהן Kohen has to use his right hand when doing the
עבודה. avodah. So the גמרא Gemara says מדרבה בר בר חנה נפקא,
miderabba bar bar Channah nafka, we learn it from רבה בר בר
חנה Rabba Bar Bar Channah that this is a general rule by
קרבנות. korbanot. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר ריש לקיש da'amar Rabba
Bar Bar Channah amar Reish Lakish כל מקום שנאמר אצבע וכהונה kol
makom shene'emar etzba u'kehuna
wherever it says finger and כהן, Kohen, אינו אלא ימין, eino ela
yamin, it's only right, and you know we had whole גמרות Gemaras
on whether that is both or one of those. But anyway we
don't learn it from this פסוק, pasuk, we learn it from a
more general principle that when the תורה Torah speaks about a כהן
Kohen and their finger that it's talking about the right hand. So
the גמרא Gemara says all right you're right, כדי נסבה, kidi nasba,
that also was just thrown in. Okay, so what we're really learning
from the חטאת, Chatas, those things we know but we're not really
learning, we know them elsewhere, what we're really learning from a חטאת
Chatas is what we came here to talk about, which is that
an obligatory קרבן korban can only come from חולין. chulin. Now we're
not done though with רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, we have מנחה Mincha
which he learns out again this idea that it transfers through being
absorbed. We learn חטאת, Chatas, we learn what we came to learn
which was that only from non-sanctified funds for an obligatory קרבן. korban.
And now we're finishing the פסוק, pasuk, אשם. Asham. What do we
learn from an אשם? Asham? מה אשם עצמותיו מותרין, mah Asham atzmotav
mutarin, the same way by an אשם Asham you can use its
bones are permissible, אף כל עצמותיו מותרין, af kol atzmotav mutarin, everything
else its bones are permissible. What does this mean? It means you
know the same way you give the כהן Kohen the meat, but
you know you also get leather. Leather is nice, expensive, make shoes
out of it, make handbags, whatever. Anyway, so the other thing that
they get out of the animal is how about the bones? So
do the bones, are they limited by the same status as the
meat let's say that they have to, you know, use them within
the day? No. I mean they're permanent, it's sort of like the
leather, they can take the bones home, they have no קדושה kedusha
like the leather, and they can use it for whatever they want,
they can make, you know, bone-handled knives out of them or whatever
they want to make. Now how do we know this? To soup?
Well soup is less of a חידוש chiddush because then in the
end you're eating it, but the ones that you can even make
it as a knife or whatever, okay, without and you don't have
to treat it as any קדושה kedusha like the leather. Now how
do we know this is true? Well we know it's true by
the אשם, Asham, I mean really not specifically by the אשם, Asham,
but any קרבן korban they eat because there it speaks about them
eating the meat. So again we sort of implicitly understand that anything
not meat does not have this status. So if that's true why
do we have to apply it to another קרבן? korban? This should
just be true in general. Ah, there's one קרבן korban that it's
not about the meat. There's one קרבן korban that is fully burnt,
the עולה. olah. So I might think the עולה, olah, there everything
is supposed to be burnt and even the bones are supposed to
be burnt, but believe it or not we learn from here that
no, bones are always excluded and that you can even use the
take the bones of the עולה olah and use them for your
own, you know, personal use, they are not something that has to
go on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So that we're learning out here from
אשם. Asham. All right so that's אשם. Asham.
And now רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, so now we're done. Okay we
didn't bother with the end of the פסוק, pasuk, right? We also
had ולמלואים ולזבח השלמים, ulamilu'im ulezavach hashelamim, but we quoted enough for
our interests. Okay so now we see that רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
learns it out from חטאת, Chatas, רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer learns it
out from פסח, Pesach, we learn out that a קרבן korban has
to come, an obligatory קרבן korban from non-מעשר Maaser funds. So now
the
גמרא Gemara says רבי עקיבא האי וזבחת פסח, Rebbe Akiva hai u'zavachta
Pesach, so רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva what does he do with the
פסוק pasuk that it says וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך צאן ובקר? u'zavachta
Pesach l'Hashem elokecha tzon u'vakar? Remember from בקר vakar we learned out
according to רבי אליעזר... Rebbe Eliezer... to apply it to all other
קרבנות. korbanos. Because בקר, bakar, you don't bring a פסח Pesach from
בקר, bakar, from cattle. So from רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that was
to teach you that you apply the principles of פסח Pesach to
other קרבנות. korbanos. What do you do with that according to רבי
עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? מיבעי ליה לכדרב נחמן mibayei lei le-khide-Rav Nachman to
teach you the teaching of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. דאמר רב נחמן
אמר רבה בר אבוה de-amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha מניין
למותר פסח שקרב שלמים? minayin le-motar pesach she-karev shelamim? How do you
know if anything is left over from a פסח Pesach that you
bring it as a שלמים? shelamim? What is מותר פסח? motar pesach?
מותר פסח motar pesach is, for example, I lost my פסח, Pesach,
that's always the classic example of מותר, motar, we had this before,
leftover. Lost my פסח, Pesach, I designated a substitute, then I found
my original. So what am I one of them I'm going to
bring, what am I going to do with the other? It becomes
a שלמים. shelamim. Which is again not a big חידוש chiddush because
it's really true even about the קרבן פסח korban pesach itself. Once
it's no longer פסח Pesach or even before it's פסח, Pesach, we've
taught that the קרבן פסח korban pesach is brought as a שלמים.
shelamim. Okay, so how do you know that the מותר פסח motar
pesach comes as a שלמים? shelamim? שנאמר וזבחת פסח לה' אלוקיך צאן
ובקר. she-ne'emar vezavachta pesach lashem elokecha tzon u-vakar. Sheep and cattle. והלא
אין פסח בא אלא מן הכבשים ומן העזים. ve-halo ein pesach ba
ela min ha-kevasim u-min ha-izim. It only comes from sheep and from
goats. So what does it mean cattle?
אלא מותר פסח, ela motar pesach, if you have a leftover פסח,
Pesach,
יהא לדבר הבא מן הצאן ומן הבקר. yehei le-davar ha-ba min ha-tzon
u-min ha-bakar. You can use it for the type of a קרבן
korban that would could come from sheep and cattle. What type of
קרבן korban can come from sheep and cattle? Basically a שלמים. shelamim.
Now that's not the only one, I mean an עולה olah can
come from sheep and cattle, but okay, it's the one that we
know we want to get to, so it's the one that's most
like a פסח Pesach that's eaten by the owners. So actually what
it's saying here is וזבחת פסח לה' אלוקיך צאן ובקר. vezavachta pesach
lashem elokecha tzon u-vakar. This is like a קרבן korban of צאן
ובקר, tzon u-vakar, this is like a שלמים. shelamim. So because it's
somewhat like a שלמים, shelamim, it becomes a שלמים shelamim if you
can't bring it as a פסח. Pesach. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara obviously this פסוק pasuk of צאן ובקר tzon u-vakar by פסח
Pesach is very difficult for חז"ל, Chazal, I mean it doesn't fit,
so it's one of the more difficult פסוקים. pesukim. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
והא מהכא נפקא? ve-ha me-hacha nafka? Do we really learn that from
here? מדאבוה דשמואל נפקא, mi-de-avuha de-Shmuel nafka, we learn it from the
teaching of the father of שמואל. Shmuel. דכתיב אם מן הצאן קרבנו
לזבח שלמים. de-chtiv im min ha-tzon korbano le-zevach shelamim. So this is
the פסוק pasuk by שלמים shelamim itself. If your שלמים shelamim comes
from the
cattle. ואמר אבוה דשמואל, ve-amar avuha de-Shmuel, so why do you need
the פסוק pasuk אם מן הצאן קרבנו? im min ha-tzon korbano? Why
didn't you just say אם מן הכבשים? im min ha-kevasim? It has
this whole introductory phrase אם מן הצאן, im min ha-tzon, if it's
from the cattle,
if it's from the sheep, from the flock. So what's that introductory
phrase saying? So says the father of שמואל, Shmuel, דבר הבא מן
הצאן, davar ha-ba min ha-tzon, things that come only from sheep. What's
something that comes only from sheep? פסח. Pesach. Or from flock. יהא
לזבח שלמים. yehei le-zevach shelamim. If you can't use it for the
פסח, Pesach, then it becomes a שלמים. shelamim. So and the גמרא
Gemara says not only that, we have a third פסוק pasuk that
teaches me that a פסח Pesach becomes a
שלמים. shelamim. והא מהכא נפקא? ve-ha me-hacha nafka? Do we learn it
from over here? מהתם נפקא, me-hatam nafka, we learn it from over
there. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Beraisa, כשב. keshev. So
this is again by a שלמים. shelamim. אם מן הצאן קרבנו אם
כשב הוא מקריב. im min ha-tzon korbano im keshev hu makriv. If
he's bringing a כשב. keshev. לרבות את הפסח לאליה. le-rabos es ha-pesach
le-alyah. To come to tell you that even the פסח, Pesach, meaning
it פסח Pesach has a similar status to a שלמים. shelamim. What
do you do by a שלמים? shelamim? If it's a sheep you
burn the fat tail. So therefore what do you do with the
fat tail by a פסח? Pesach? You also burn it. Okay, we
learn it from this word כשב, keshev, the sheep, that it says
by the שלמים, shelamim, which we assume to be extra. כשהוא אומר
אם כשב, ke-she-hu omer im keshev, if it's a sheep, להביא פסח
שעברה שנתו, le-havi pesach she-avrah shenaso, to tell you that not only
are we talking about a פסח Pesach that you burn the fat
tail, but we're talking about things that used to be a פסח
Pesach have a הלכה halacha of a שלמים. shelamim. So for example,
the פסח Pesach its year is over, it's more than one year
old, the פסח Pesach has to be within one
year. ושלמים הבאים מחמת פסח, u-shelamim ha-ba'im machmas pesach, and שלמים shelamim
that come because of the פסח. Pesach. לכל מצוות שלמים, le-khol mitzvos
shelamim, that they're treated as, I'll discuss that category in a minute,
they're treated as a full שלמים. shelamim. What does it mean? שטעונים
סמיכה, she-te'unim semichah, you do with them everything you'd do with a
שלמים. shelamim. You do סמיכה, semichah, ונסכים, u-nesachim, and the wine. Again,
you don't do this by a פסח, Pesach, but you do this
by when the פסח Pesach transforms into a שלמים. shelamim. ותנופת חזה
ושוק, u-tenufas chaze ve-shok, you wave the חזה chaze and the שוק.
shok. That's what you do with a פסח Pesach when it becomes
a
שלמים. shelamim. כשהוא אומר, ke-she-hu omer, and then the פסוק pasuk says,
ואם עז, ve-im ez, but if you're bringing a goat for your
שלמים, shelamim, הפסיק העניין, hifsik ha-inyan, that interrupts it. ללמד על העז,
le-lammed al ha-ez, that if you're bringing a goat שאינה טעונה אליה.
she-einah te'unah alyah. You don't apply what the תורה Torah said before
by the sheep, you don't give a fat tail of the goat.
It's always quite fascinating that the גמרא Gemara have to learn out
that you don't give a fat tail of a goat. Goats don't
have fat tails. You ever see a goat? Has a tiny little
tail. You ever see a sheep? A little, right anyway, sheep has
this big fat tail. Anyway, for some reason the גמרא Gemara has
to learn that out not just that it doesn't have it. Right,
that's again an אפשר efshar and an אי אפשר ee-efshar case. Anyway,
okay, but what do we learn from this? We have three פסוקים
pesukim by פסח. Pesach. One we learn out from צאן ובקר tzon
u-vakar to tell me a פסח Pesach is like a שלמים. shelamim.
One from אם מן הצאן, im min ha-tzon, which is by the
שלמים shelamim to include a פסח. Pesach. And one is אם כבש
הוא מקריב *im keves hu makriv*. So כבש *keves* also to tell
me a פסח Pesach *Pesach* is like a שלמים *shelamim*. Why do
I need all three פסוקים *pesukim*? Now, before we answer that, to
just repeat what we said, which type of a פסח *Pesach* is
like a שלמים *shelamim* or what are we saying? First of all
we're saying when it's a שלמים *shelamim*, you do all the laws
of a שלמים *shelamim*. The חזה והשוק *chazeh v'hashok* and the waving
and the סמיכה *smicha*, that's not by a פסח *Pesach*. You do
do those all those things, but that's by a שלמים *shelamim*, that's
when it transforms. What else we also saying is what types of
things become a שלמים *shelamim*? So we've mentioned a few. We've mentioned
מותר פסח *mutar Pesach*, which means that I lost my פסח *Pesach*
and I created a substitute one. We've mentioned עברה שנתו *avrah shnato*,
its year has passed, so it's no longer can be used. We
also mentioned a third thing, which is a debate of רש"י Rashi
תוספות Tosafot *Rashi Tosafot* what it means, which is שלמים הבאים מחמת
הפסח *shelamim habaim machmat haPesach*, שלמים *shelamim* that are coming because of
the פסח *Pesach*. What does this mean? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
what it means is that the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says you would
bring שלמים *shelamim* on the 14th of ניסן *Nissan*, which is called
we call חגיגת ארבעה עשר *chagigat arba'ah asar*, the חגיגה *chagiga* of
the 14th, in order so that when you ate the קרבן korban
פסח *korban Pesach*, you were full. You know, you're supposed to eat
the קרבן פסח *korban Pesach* as like a dessert, as the last
thing, not when you're ravenous. So you would bring other קרבנות korbanot,
*korbanot* to fill you up. That's what רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* is saying
is שלמים הבאים מחמת הפסח *shelamim habaim machmat haPesach*, which has an
interesting point, because as a שלמים *shelamim* it really should be eaten
for two days. But here, if that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying, it's saying that when it's coming with the פסח *Pesach*,
it has some of the status like the קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*
itself and is limited to a day. That's the way רש"י *Rashi*
reads this. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* reads it to be referring to something
else. But anyway, let's just keep on going now to see what
we do with all three פסוקים *pesukim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: תלתא קראי כתיבי *tlata kra'i ktivi*. So you're right,
there are three פסוקים *pesukim*. חד לעבר זמנו ועברה שנתו *chad l'avar
zmano v'avrah shnato*, one to tell you that it becomes a שלמים
*shelamim* when its time is up, it's more than a year old
and, I'm sorry, עבר זמנו *avar zmano*, it's no longer פסח *Pesach*,
פסח *Pesach* has passed, and עברה שנתו *avrah shnato*, its year is
up, it's more than a year old, so sort of completely is
not usable, right? א' *alef*, it's already פסח *Pesach* has already come
and gone, and ב' *bet*, it's too old, it's more than a
year old. וחד לעבר זמנו ולא עברה שנתו *v'chad l'avar zmano v'lo
avrah shnato*, one is when its time is passed, פסח *Pesach* has
come and gone, but it is still a year old. So in
theory it could have been a פסח *Pesach* right now because it's
within a year old, but the only problem is that פסח *Pesach*
is either too far in the past or too distant in the
future. וחד דלא עבר זמנו ולא עברה שנתו *v'chad d'lo avar zmano
v'lo avrah shnato*, it's a year old, it's not yet a year
old, so it's the right age, and פסח *Pesach* hasn't come by
yet, it's פורים *Purim*. It's not פסח *Pesach*. Okay, so it's still,
it's gonna, when פסח *Pesach* comes, it'll be able to be used
as a פסח *Pesach*, but right now it's פורים *Purim* and it's
not פסח *Pesach*. וצריכי *v'tzrichi*, and you need all three cases. דאי
אשמעינן עבר זמנו ועברה שנתו *d'ei ashmi'inan avar zmano v'avrah shnato*, if
you had just said when it's over a year old and פסח
*Pesach* is in the past, that then it no longer a פסח
*Pesach*, it becomes a שלמים *shelamim*, משום דאדחיי ליה לגמרי *mishum d'idchei
lei legamrei*, it's been totally rejected from a פסח *Pesach*. So now
all that's left is for it to be a שלמים *shelamim*. אבל
עבר זמנו ולא עברה שנתו *aval avar zmano v'lo avrah shnato*, if
however פסח *Pesach* is in the past, but it's still within its
year, so at least in theory it could be a פסח *Pesach*,
it's the right age, דחזי לפסח שני *d'chazi l'Pesach sheni*, and not
only that, if it's not yet אייר *Iyar*, right? The 15th of
אייר *Iyar* or the 14th of אייר *Iyar*, maybe you can even
bring it for the פסח *Pesach* that's coming up, for פסח שני
*Pesach sheni*. So it really is in theory usable for a קרבן
פסח *korban Pesach*. So אימא לא *eima lo*, maybe it doesn't become
a שלמים *shelamim* if I shechted it then. דאי אשמעינן עבר זמנו
ולא עברה שנתו *d'ei ashmi'inan avar zmano v'lo avrah shnato*, and if
it had just said that, דאדחיי ליה מפסח ראשון *d'idchei lei m'Pesach
rishon*, at least there it's been rejected or it's been you know
passed by for the first פסח *Pesach*. אבל לא עבר זמנו ולא
עברה שנתו *aval lo avar zmano v'lo avrah shnato*, if it's the
right age and it's not even yet פסח *Pesach*, it's פורים *Purim*,
דאפילו לפסח ראשון נמי חזי *d'afilu l'Pesach rishon nami chazi*, that maybe
I'll be able I can use it for פסח *Pesach* when it
comes by, so I might think that if I shechted it now
as a קרבן *korban*, maybe it's considered a פסח *Pesach* because I
will be able to use it as a פסח *Pesach* in a
month. תמא אימא לא *tema eima lo*, maybe there it doesn't become
a שלמים *shelamim*. צריכא *tzricha*, it tells me that in all those
cases, even something that could be used as a פסח *Pesach* in
a few days or few weeks from now, if you're bringing it
and it's not פסח *Pesach*, it has a status of a שלמים
*shelamim*, not of a פסח *Pesach*. Okay, so that was a very
long thing, but basically very big גמרא Gemara *Gemara* we just did
over the last two days, which all it boils down to is
two things. Number one is the principle that an obligatory קרבן *korban*
cannot come from מעשר ma'aser, שני *ma'aser sheni* money. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* learns it from פסח ראשון *Pesach rishon*, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
*Rabbi Akiva* learns it from a חטאת *chatat*. And then the question
is well what do you do with this difficult פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
by פסח *Pesach*, וזבחת הפסח לה' אלוהיך צאן ובקר *v'zavachta haPesach l'Hashem
Elokecha tzon u'vakar*. So there רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says no, it's
telling you that to apply this principle of פסח *Pesach* to all
sacrifices. צאן ובקר *tzon u'vakar* means all sacrifices. Okay. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* says no, what it's telling you is if something
was a פסח *Pesach* but now is leftover or was brought or
it's not the right time or it's too old or whatever it
is, it becomes like a type of a sacrifice at צאן ובקר
*tzon u'vakar*, it becomes a שלמים *shelamim*. That's what you do, that's
what he does with the פסוק *pasuk*. So it ended with talking
about what
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* does. Now, we move on to another פרק
perek? which gets us moving away from תודה, Toda, gets us focused
back on מנחות, Menachot, and once again is a nice little thing
in terms of trying to systematize and organize the entire information. So
let's take a look. כל קרבנות הציבור, Kol korbanot hatzibur, all communal
sacrifices. Now, this does not really mean all communal sacrifices, it really
means all communal מנחות, minchot, okay, cause that's the context of קרבן
now, not talking about animal sacrifices. I'll talk about, I'll mention animal
in a minute. Anyway, וזה היחיד, veze hayachid, whether they are communal
or individual, all קרבנות, korbanot. really all מנחות, minchot, באים מן הארץ
ומחוצה לארץ. ba'im min ha'aretz u'michutza la'aretz. You can take it from
grain that grew in Israel and out of Israel. מן החדש ומן
הישן, Min hachadash u'min hayashan, old grain or new grain, grain that
just grew recently, grain that's been stored up. You can bring these
מנחות minchot from any type of grain, חוץ מן העומר ושתי הלחם,
chutz min ha'omer u'shtei halechem, with the exception of the עומר Omer
and the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem what was brought on פסח and
שבועות. Shavuot.
Why? שאינם באים אלא מן החדש, she'einam ba'im ela min hachadash, they
come from the new grain. Their whole point is that the עומר
Omer is the new barley and that the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
is the new wheat, so they have to come from the stuff
that was just harvested, not old stuff, and ומן הארץ, u'min ha'aretz,
and they're the first harvest of the land of Israel, so they
have to come from grain that grew in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
So these are the only two. The flour, the grain from other
מנחות minchot can come from wherever, you know, any land, any time
they were harvested. But these, the whole point is that they are
the first barley and grain harvest, wheat harvest of the land of
Israel, it has to be new grain that grew in Israel. וכולם
אינם באים אלא מן המובחר, V'chulam einam ba'im ela min hamuvchar, and
whatever you use, you have to use choice grain, choice flour. ואיזהו
מובחר שלהם, V'eizehu muvchar shelahem, what would be the sort of choicest
type of flour to get in Israel?
מכניס וזתחא, Machnis v'Zatcha,
so these two places, grain that grew in these two places called
מכניס Machnis and זתחא, Zatcha, never heard of them before, but apparently
whatever, you know, the מפרשים meforshim say they're places in Israel.
Isn't it ממי מכניס? Mei Kanis?
ממי מכניס Mei Kanis maybe,
the מ mem maybe means from?
I'm not sure.
The ערוך Aruch has the גרסה girsa of מחמס וזנוחא. Machmas v'Zanocha.
Some have the גרסה girsa מחמס. Machmas. Oh, actually if you look,
it says on the bottom, some משניות mishnayot it
says ממכמס ומזוניחא. mi'Michmas u'mizunicha. So it has the מ mem in
front of both, so that would mean the מ mem is a
from, right. But others assume that the מ mem is actually the
name of the place itself. Anyway, these two places, אלפא לסולת. Alfa
l'solet. It's cute. They are the grade A for flour, אלפא. Alfa.
You know, they're אלפא סולת, Alfa solet, alpha male, they're אלפא סולת.
Alfa solet. Okay.
The Greeks come in again?
Yeah, exactly.
So, so those are the choicest flour. So you're supposed to bring,
you know, although you can bring from anywhere if it's not the
עומר Omer and the מנחה mincha and from any type of grain,
you're supposed to bring choice grain. Here's where you can get some
choice flour from, these places. שנייה להם, Shniya lahem, grade B flour
or right under them, A-minus flour, עפוריים בבקעה, Aforayim babika, this place
called עפוריים Aforayim in the valley. Okay. כל הארצות היו כשרות, Kol
ha'aratzot hayu ksheirot, really you could bring from anywhere, אלא מכאן היו
מביאים, ela mikan hayu mevi'im, this is where they would bring from
because, because these would be the best. Now, it sounds like that,
you know,
it could be that this last whole discussion, וכולם אינם באים, v'chulam
einam ba'im, it's a little bit unclear because, you know, a minute
ago it said that you could bring from anywhere outside of Israel
or whatever. So when it says מכאן היו מביאים, mikan hayu mevi'im,
is this talking about for all מנחות minchot or is this talking
about just for the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם? Shtei HaLechem?
That, you know, for the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם, Shtei
HaLechem, they would דוקא davka bring from these two places. Not exactly
clear. רש"י says it's the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם. Shtei
HaLechem. רש"י says, if you look at רש"י, says כל ארצות של
ארץ ישראל כשרות. kol artzot shel Eretz Yisrael ksheirot. So that is,
so now he's really, so if he's limiting himself to Israel, he's
referring to the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, because
we just taught
that only the עומר Omer and שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem have to
come from Israel grain. Okay. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara מתניתין דלא כי האי תנא, Matnitin d'lo k'hai tanna, our משנה
mishna is not like the following תנא, tanna, דתניא, d'tanya, we taught
in a ברייתא, braita, עומר הבא מן הישן כשר. omer haba min
hayashan kasher. Very bizarre. If you bring the עומר Omer from last
year's grain, the whole idea is supposed to be מנחה חדשה, mincha
chadasha, ראשית קצירכם. reishit ktzirchem. If you bring it from last year's
grain, you know, it's כשר. kasher. So that's clearly not our משנה.
mishna. Our משנה mishna says it has to be new grain. שתי
הלחם הבאה מן הישן כשירה, Shtei halechem haba'ah min hayashan ksheira, and
if you bring שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem from last year's grain, it's
כשרה. ksheira. אלא שחיסר מצוה, Ela shechisar mitzvah, you're missing a מצוה.
mitzvah. No kidding. עומר דכתיב תקריב את מנחת ביכוריך, Omer dechtiv takriv
et minchat bikurecha, because now how do we know that? Because it
says by the עומר, Omer, you shall bring. There's an extra verb
of תקריב. takriv. So תקריב takriv means you can bring from anything,
אפילו מן העלייה, afilu min ha'aliya, even from the attic, meaning even
from stored grain, the extra verb תקריב. takriv. ושתי הלחם. v'shtei halechem.
שתי הלחם דכתיב ממושבותיכם תביאו Shtei halechem dechativ mimoshevoteichem tavi'u from your
from your inhabitants dwelling places you shall bring, ולא מחוצה לארץ velo
michutz la'aretz it can't be from out of Israel and that's ממושבותיכם
mimoshevoteichem is excluding that. But when it says ממושבותיכם mimoshevoteichem from wherever
you are, from wherever you dwell, ואפילו מן העליה vafilu min ha'aliyah
even from the attic, somehow we learned that out from ממושבותיכם. mimoshevoteichem.
So on the one hand it excludes חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but
it's according to this ברייתא braita coming to include even old grain.
So the גמרא Gemara says הא אפיקתיה, ha apiktei, what do you
mean you already used the פסוק to tell me not חוצה לארץ?
chutz la'aretz? How can you use it to tell me that you
can use old grain? So אמר קרא תביאו, amar kra tavi'u, you're
right, we're not learning it out from ממושבותיכם, mimoshevoteichem, we're learning it
out from the verb תביאו, tavi'u, you shall bring, means bring from
anywhere, ואפילו מן העליה, vafilu min ha'aliyah, okay, even from even from
the attic. So now we learn out according to this ברייתא braita
you can bring the עומר שתי הלחם omer shtei halechem from old
grain, pretty amazing. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי בעי ליה, vami
bayei lei, one minute, don't we need the תביאו tavi'u to tell
me what we learned in last פרק? שכל שאתה מביא ממקום אחר
הרי הוא כזה, shekol she'atah mevi mimakom acher harei hu kazeh, when
you bring
other
things they are like the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. What did we
learn from that? The same way the שתי הלחם shtei halechem was
an עישרון issaron per חלה, chalah, right remember, that that bag of
flour, five pound bag of flour for every חלה, chalah, we learned
it out to tell me by the מנחה mincha of a תודה
todah that every every חלה, chalah, every every loaf of חמץ chametz
is an עישרון. issaron. So that's what we learn out from the
תביאו tavi'u to tell you the amount of flour you use for
תודה todah bread, not not to tell you this. So the גמרא
says no, אם כן לכתוב קרא תבי, im ken lichtov kra tavi,
then it could have just said bring. מאי תביאו, mai tavi'u, which
is more inclusive somehow? שמע מינה תרתי shma mina tarti to tell
you both. So now we've got this crazy ברייתא braita that says
against our משנה mishna that you can bring the עומר שתי הלחם
omer shtei halechem from last year's grain. So now the גמרא gets
upset, or not gets upset but gets sort of like, you know,
fights back. The גמרא says והכתיב ראשית, ve'haktiv reshit, it says it
has to be the first of your
cutting! ומצוה, umitzvah, that's ideally first מצוה mitzvah should be that way.
הא כתיב חדשה, ha kativ chadashah, it has to be a מנחה
חדשה! mincha chadashah! So the גמרא says האי מיבעי ליה לכדתניא. hai
mibayei lei lichd'tanya. רבי נתן ורבי עקיבא אמרו שתי הלחם הבאות מן
הישן כשרות. Rabbi Natan veRabbi Akiva amru shtei halechem haba'ot min hayashan
kesherot. רבי עקיבא it's not just a ברייתא, braita, it's רבי עקיבא
and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan say that if you bring the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem from old grain it's still כשר. kosher. ומני מקיים
חדשה, umani mekayem chadashah, so what does it mean it has to
be new? שתהא חדשה לכל המנחות, sheteheh chadashah lechol haminachot, that it
has to be the first of all other מנחות minachot meaning ironically,
not ironically until now, but that you cannot bring any מנחה mincha
from the new grain until you bring the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem.
Okay, so that's what it means חדשה, chadashah, that before this no
other מנחה mincha can be brought from the new grain. Of course
the irony is that this isn't from the new grain according to
them, but even though it isn't from the new grain once you
bring it now you are allowed to bring other מנחות minachot from
the new grain. Okay, so that's where we will end here by
this amazing idea that the עומר שתי הלחם omer shtei halechem can
come from the new grain. I did want to add one point
which is that although it says כל הקרבנות kol hakorbanot I said
what it really means is all מנחות minachot because that's clearly the
context, but תוספות Tosafot does make an interesting question about what is
the story about where you can bring your animals from. Is there
limits about bringing your animals from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, חוצה לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, old animals, new animals because you know there is a
sense of old and new animals because you would take מעשר בהמה
ma'aser behemah every year. So you know, is there any sense of
that? So if you just look very quickly at תוספות Tosafot
he says כל הקרבנות, kol hakorbanot, תוספות Tosafot says ונראה דשייך נמי
בזבחים, venira d'shayach nami bizvachim, it turns out it applies even to
animal sacrifices. ונתחייב במעשר venitchayev bema'aser in theory you could do it,
but if you look in the middle of תוספות where it says
כל הקרבנות kol hakorbanot he says ובתוספתא תניא, uvetosefta tanya, the תוספתא's
Tosefta explicit that this is that the מנחה's mincha contrasted to the
animal קרבנות. korbanot כל קרבנות הציבור והיחיד באין מארץ ומחוצה לארץ אפילו
מבין עובדי כוכבים, kol korbanot hatzibbur vehayachid ba'in me'eretz umichutz la'aretz afilu
miben ovdei kochavim, you can bring all animal קרבנות korbanot from Israel
from out of Israel from Jews from non-Jews we know, and then
it says except for you know the בכור bechor and מעשר בהמה
ma'aser behemah actually those two do come only from animals that are
born in Israel. Okay, and then it says and then it goes
on to speak about the מנחות. minachot. So anyway just so you
should be aware that תוספות makes the point we are talking about
מנחות, minachot, general rule is that by animal קרבנות there are no
limitations with the interesting exception of בכור bechor and מעשר, firstborn animals
and מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, there there might be some exceptions. Anyway
we'll learn much more about בכור bechor when we reach מסכת בכורות.
Masechet Bechorot.