Okay today's דף *daf* is כ"ה *Kaf Hey*, בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*
25, and we are on דף כ"ה *daf Kaf Hey* right after
the משנה Mishnah *mishna* about six lines down from the top of
the דף *daf*, and our learning should be in the זכות *zechut*
of the protection of our חיילים *chayalim* and חיילות *chayalot* and the
continued return of the hostages and their safety and security. Okay, so
we pick up with the debate of רבי טרפון Rebbe Tarfon *Rabbi
Tarfon* and the חכמים *Chachamim*. רבי טרפון Rebbe Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon* said
that when an ox gores in the רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak, *reshut
hanizak*, in the property of the person who is damaged, that the
payment is full, not half, even though it's the first time, and
he does this from a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer* from
שן *shen* and רגל *regel*. That in רשות הרבים reshus ha-rabim *reshut
harabim*, שן *shen* and רגל *regel* are exempt, and that they're liable
in רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak. *reshut hanizak* the full amount. And so
therefore קרן keren, *keren*, which is half damages in רשות הרבים *reshut
harabim*, קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* should be רשות הניזק reshus
ha-nizak *reshut hanizak* the full amount. To which the rabbis say דיו
dayo, לבוא מן הדין להיות כנדון *dayo l'avo min hadin lihyot k'nidon*.
It is sufficient for that which you are learning out that it
starts, that it doesn't exceed that which you derived it from. So
since you derived it from קרן *keren* in רשות הרבים *reshut harabim*
which is half, yes we concede that in רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak.
*reshut hanizak* it's certainly a weightier situation, but the most you can
get to is that you can get to half. And therefore it,
you do not get to full, even though רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak
*reshut hanizak* is weightier. And then in the משנה *mishna*, רבי טרפון
Rebbe Tarfon, *Rabbi Tarfon* sort of switches and says no, no, let's
not focus on קרן *keren* in this case, קרן *keren* in that
case, that would be, so then you couldn't get beyond half, let's
focus on רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* versus רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak *reshut
hanizak*. רשות הרבים *reshut harabim* is a place where sometimes you pay
zero in שן *shen* and רגל *regel* and sometimes you pay half
by קרן *keren*. So therefore, and רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak. *reshut hanizak*
is a place where you pay full by שן *shen* and רגל
*regel*, so you should certainly be paying full by קרן *keren*, which
is a weightier case. You should certainly be paying it because רשות
הניזק reshus ha-nizak, *reshut hanizak* is a place that you pay full.
So therefore the comparison is רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak. *reshut hanizak* by
שן *shen* and רגל *regel* which is full to רשות הניזק reshus
ha-nizak *reshut hanizak* by קרן *keren* which should be full, so you
shouldn't be limited by דיו dayo. *dayo*. But they basically respond back
and say no, at the end of the day it really is
still קרן *keren* to קרן *keren* and it really should be limited
by דיו dayo, *dayo*. That's the debate in the משנה *mishna*.
Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, rather than sort of take his second
tack, which is, it seems to be a stronger position, which seems
to be like let's just focus on רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak *reshut
hanizak* as a place where you pay full by שן *shen* and
רגל *regel*, you should pay full by קרן *keren*, they say no,
he really is learning קרן *keren* from קרן *keren* but he does
not hold of דיו dayo *dayo*, or he doesn't hold of דיו
dayo. *dayo* all the time. And let's take a look at that
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: ורבי טרפון לית ליה דיו dayo, *v'Rabbi Tarfon leise lei dayo*?
Does רבי טרפון Rebbe Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon* not hold of דיו dayo
*dayo*? Because he only switched tacks in the משנה *mishna* when the
חכמים *Chachamim* pushed back and said דיו dayo *dayo*. But it sounds
like he himself wasn't bothered by דיו dayo *dayo*. It sounds like
he himself would say קרן *keren* which is half in רשות הרבים
*reshut harabim* should certainly be full in רשות הניזק reshus ha-nizak *reshut
hanizak*. Okay, that's a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* that doesn't
have דיו dayo *dayo*. But then what's the limit? You know, shouldn't
you be limited by דיו dayo, *dayo*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says והא דיו dayo? דאורייתא הוא *v'ha dayo de-oraita hu*? And דיו
dayo *dayo* is a דאורייתא *de-oraita* principle. You know, besides that it's
a דאורייתא *de-oraita* principle, the question also is that if you don't
say דיו dayo, *dayo* you don't know how far you can go.
קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* allows you to say it should
be at least as good. It wouldn't tell you that it should
be better. If it's better, how much better? Where do we see
דיו dayo. *dayo* is a דאורייתא *de-oraita* principle? דתניא d’tanya: *detanya*, we
taught in a ברייתא braisa *braita*: דין דיו dayo, *din dayo*. This
is in the list of the י"ג מדות *Yud Gimmel Middot*, the
thirteen hermeneutic principles that the תורה Torah. *Torah* is, you know, that
הלכה halacha *halacha* is derived from based on פסוקים *psukim* in the
תורה Torah *Torah*. And one is a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal
vachomer*. כיצד *keitzad*, how does קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer* work?
says the ברייתא *braita*. So this is sourced in a פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* in the תורה Torah *Torah*. ויאמר ה' אל משה Moshe, *Vayomer
Hashem el Moshe*, ה' *Hashem* said to משה Moshe *Moshe* when מרים
Miriam *Miriam* got צרעת *tzara'at* and she was outside of the camp.
And ה' *Hashem* said to משה Moshe *Moshe* ואביה ירק ירק בפניה
הלא תכלם שבעת ימים *v'aviha yarok yarak b'faneha halo ticalem shivat yamim*.
If her father were to spit in her face, would she not
be embarrassed for seven days? So therefore the end of the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* is תסגר מחוץ למחנה שבעת ימים *tisager michutz lamachaneh shivat
yamim*. Let her be closed up outside of the camp for seven
days. And she was, and therefore she was kept separate and outside
of the camp for seven days. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says that's if her father would spit, but here God has basically
shown her displeasure. So קל וחומר kal vachomer לשכינה ארבעה עשר *kal
vachomer l'Shchina arba-asar*. The קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* should tell
you when it's God who's doing it, it should be 14. אלא
*ela*, but rather you can't go beyond where you started. אלא דיו
dayo. לבוא מן הדין להיות כנדון *ela dayo l'avo min hadin lihyot
k'nidon*. It's enough that it goes from that that which we're learning
out from, you know, to be from the place that we're up,
the case we're applying to, suffices that it goes is no more
than the place we're deriving from. So since the case of the
father was seven days, even though this is a case of God,
the קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer* will just get you seven
days. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so you see this
principle of דיו dayo, *dayo* is based on a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*.
Because she wasn't closed up more than seven days, she was only
closed out of the camp for seven days. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says no. כי לית ליה דיו ki leis leh dayo, *ki
leise lei dayo*, when does רבי טרפון Rebbe Tarfon *Rabbi Tarfon* not
hold of דיו dayo *dayo*, היכא *heicha* היכא דמיפרך קל וחומר. heicha
de-mifrach kal vachomer. If that would mean that you would that the
alternative is giving up on the entire קל וחומר. kal vachomer היכא
דלא מיפרך קל וחומר, heicha de-lo mifrach kal vachomer, if the קל
וחומר kal vachomer produces results even after applying
דיו, dayo. איתא דיו isay dayo he would hold דיו. dayo, So
what does that mean? It means in the case of מרים Miriam
and most קל וחומרים, kal vachomers, you're deriving from A to B.
You don't know the story about B. קל וחומר kal vachomer lets
you get to B. So even when you apply דיו, dayo you
still have said what we know about A applies to B. Really
B should be even more, but דיו dayo at least tells us
what we knew about A. There he would hold of דיו. dayo
What would be the story when God, you know, spits in the
face of מרים Miriam figuratively? We don't know, but we know by
her father it's seven. So we know by God it's seven and
even though דיו, dayo even though we would want to go more,
דיו dayo limits us to seven, but at least we have the
קל וחומר kal vachomer bore fruit. In our case of the שור
shor that gores in רשות הניזק, we know that a שור shor
that gores is half. We know it's half in רשות הניזק. There
would never be a reason to think רשות הניזק would be different.
We didn't know רשות הרבים more than רשות הניזק. We knew every
place is half. So the קל וחומר kal vachomer which tells us
רשות הניזק should be more, if you apply דיו dayo it's nothing
more than we knew to begin with. We always knew that a
שור shor that an ox that gored is half everywhere. So therefore
there דיו dayo undermines the קל וחומר. kal vachomer The קל וחומר
kal vachomer lets us go to the next stage. Now what is
the next stage? How do you know how far to go? So
there you might look for other cues. So there, you know, it's
not like you can say whatever you want. So by the שכינה
Shechina for example, תוספות Tosafot says one logic is is that based
on a גמרא Gemara that says that, you know, the father contributes
five things, the mother contributes five things, so the שכינה Shechina contributes
ten. So it's not just we're gonna double. There's a logic to
say that. But דיו dayo. might hold us back. In רשות הניזק
we see that שן ורגל shen ve-regel pay full amount. Okay, so
therefore if we already knew it and then you can add to
that the basic הלכה halakha, about that place, and קל וחומר kal
vachomer. tells us but the place should be weightier or that thing
should be weightier, then רבי טרפון R’ Tarfon, says I'm not going
to go by דיו, dayo I'll use other cues to tell me
how far to take it. And that will let me say that
it will be full nezek in רשות הניזק. Okay, so let's read
that again. כי לית ליה דיו, dayo when does רבי טרפון R’
Tarfon hold that I'm not going to be restrained by דיו? dayo.
היכא דמיפרך קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If that would undermine the קל
וחומר. kal vachomer Like רשות הניזק, I started off knowing it half
damages. I'm not going to use דיו dayo, which will basically tell
me I can't do anything. היכא דלא מיפרך קל וחומר, heicha de-lo
mifrach kal vachomer, but if the קל וחומר kal v’chomer allows me
to learn something even with the constraints of דיו, dayo. איתא דיו
isay dayo he would hold of דיו. dayo, התם שבעה דשכינה לא
כתיבא. hasam shiva de-shechina lo ksiva. So the idea that God, if
God were
to reject somebody or show displeasure, it would be seven days, we
never had a reason to say that. אתא קל וחומר, ata kal
vachomer, you use the קל וחומר kal v’chomer from the father. אייתי
ארבעסר, ayty arbasar, that would logically lead you to say fourteen. אתא
דיו, ata dayo, comes דיו, dayo? אפיק שבעה ואוקי שבעה. apik shiva
ve-okiah shiva. It removes the additional seven but it leaves you on
the base seven. So the קל וחומר kal v’chomer allowed you to
say seven, which is basically the point of the תורה. Torah The
תורה Torah says if the father would do it it's seven, so
certainly it should be at least seven here. But you wouldn't have
started understanding the idea of seven. So the קל וחומר kal v’chomer
produced the idea of seven, so you go with the constraints of
דיו. dayo Okay, אבל הכא חצי נזק כתיב. aval hacha chatzi nezek
ksiv. Here the תורה Torah says that an ox that gores is
half damages. There'd be no reason to think there's any distinction of
where it gores, so of course it applies even in רשות הניזק.
ואתא קל וחומר ואייתי חצי נזק אחרינא. ve-ata kal vachomer ve-ayty chatzi
nezek achrina. And the קל וחומר kal v’chomer tells you ah, רשות
הניזק is even more, it's even going to be full because רשות
הניזק is weightier and we can look at שן ורגל shen ve-regel
and we can assume that it's going to be full. ונעשה נזק
שלם. ve-nasa nezek shalem. And it turns to full nezek. אי דרשת
דיו, ei darashta dayo, if you were to now insist on your
דיו, dayo איפרח ליה קל וחומר. ivrach leh kal vachomer. Your קל
וחומר kal v’chomer would be completely destroyed, you'd be back to half
which you knew to begin with. So basically the principle is רבי
טרפון, R’ Tarfon not the nice twist רבי טרפון R’ Tarfon did
in the משנה to focus on רשות הניזק and to say he's
deriving it from שן ורגל, shen ve-regel, forget that. He is deriving
it from קרן, but רבי טרפון R’ Tarfon does not hold of
דיו dayo if the קל וחומר kal v’chomer otherwise would not produce
any fruit. And as I said, presumably you have to use know
if you're going to go beyond the base case, look at other
evidence how far you can then take it. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara says ורבנן שבעה דשכינה כתיבא. ve-rabanan shiva de-shechina ksiva. But
the רבנן Rabbis would disagree. They would say that we already knew
seven by God. How do we know seven by God? Because the
end of the פסוק pasuk says תסגר שבעת ימים, tisager shivas yamim,
let her be sealed up for seven days. Now it's funny, that
obviously as we're going to see in a minute, that's what you
get from the קל וחומר. kal v’chomer: But the רבנן Rabbis are
saying no, the פסוק pasuk, starts by saying, you know, we know
that if the father disgraces her it's seven and you know that
if God were to do it it would also be seven and
it's a קל וחומר. kal v’chomer, But you would have known God
to begin with and you still, nevertheless, the קל וחומר kal vachomer.
is limited by the principle of
דיו. dayo רבנן, Rabanan, the
rabbis would say back,
כתיב קרא אחרינא, kativ kra achrina, it says another פסוק, pasuk ותסגר
מרים, v'tisager Miriam, and she was sealed up for seven days. So
since it says twice, therefore by God seven and מרים Miriam, was
sealed by seven, it’s coming to tell you I always knew the
idea that God seven, and even though a קל וחומר kal vachomer
would have pushed me more, I’m limited by דיו, dayo? even though
I started by knowing God seven.
רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon. what would רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon. say back?
He would say, ההוא דאפילו בעלמא דרשינן דיו. hahu d’afilu b’alma darshinan
dayo. No, it does say it again, but that’s to tell you
that you would, that the reason it repeats it is to tell
you that this principle of דיו dayo applies not only here, but
you would always say דיו dayo if you actually the קל וחומר
kal vachomer bears fruit. Why would I think here it would be
different? ולא תאמר הכא משום כבודו של משה, אבל בעלמא לא, קא
משמע לן. v’lo tomar hacha mishum kvodo shel Moshe, aval b’alma lo,
kamashma lan. Don't say that normally you don't say דיו dayo at
all, but
because God cares for משה, Moshe. משה Moshe, prays for מרים, Miriam
God is going to say here I’m not going to go fourteen,
here we’re going to apply דיו and only say seven, because of
you משה I care for you so we’re going to limit מרים
to the case of had it been like her father. So the
second, so therefore it says again, no, seven days, it’s repeating seven
days to tell you this principle of דיו is a general principle,
it’s not God was applying it because God cared more for משה.
Okay, so bottom line is רבי טרפון says, that was a little
bit weird because clearly that’s a case where you did not have
it already written that it was seven. So רבי טרפון says yes
I concede to דיו and I concede to דיו in all cases,
not just by משה, but that is when the קל וחומר kal
vachomer bears fruit. If the קל וחומר kal vachomer would not bear
fruit like in our case, I started by knowing that הלכה, halakha
the קל וחומר kal vachomer allows me to go beyond the הלכה
halakha I knew from the beginning and I’m not constrained by
דיו. Alright, so that’s the discussion of רבי טרפון not holding by
דיו if the קל וחומר kal vachomer. otherwise would not bear fruit.
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask whether this is true
in all cases. אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar lei Rav Pappa
l’Abaye, רב פפא Rav Pappa said to אביי, Abaye, והאי תנא דלא
דריש דיו ואף על גב דלא מפרך קל וחומר, v’hai tanna d’lo
darish dayo, v’af al gav d’lo mifrach kal v’chomer, I'll show you
a תנא tanna that is not constrained by דיו even if the
קל וחומר kal vachomer. is not undermined, even though it could bear
fruit, he’s still not constrained by דיו. Where do you see this?
דתניא: d’tanya: קרי בזב מנין? keri b’zav minayin? How do you know
that if a זב zav sees קרי, keri, sees שכבת זרע, shichvat
zera, sees semen, that that semen is טמא? tamei? Okay, now the
normal הלכה halacha is that if a normal person, a normal man,
has a seminal emission, that semen is considered an אב הטומאה. av
hatumah. If a somebody who is a זב, zav, somebody who has
had emissions for like three times and they’re of a certain quality,
they come from the penis but they’re not semen, that person is
considered a זב zav and he’s a very, he’s an אב הטומאה
av hatumah and it goes for seven days and it’s very weighty
and so on, and the תורה Torah says that if he spits,
his spit is also considered to be an אב הטומאה. av hatumah.
Okay, so different liquids, fluids that come from him are also an
אב הטומאה, av hatumah, but the תורה Torah specifically speaks about spit,
וכי ירוק הזב על הטהור. v’chi yarok hazav al hatahor. So how
do you know that the semen of a
זב zav is also an אב הטומאה? av hatumah? That is the
question here. Now remember and again, the semen of a טהור tahor
person, of somebody who’s just a normal person, is an אב הטומאה.
av hatumah. So it says like this, דתניא: detanya, קרי בזב מנין?
keri b’zav minayin? How do you know the קרי keri of a
זב zav is טמא? tamei? ודינו, v’dino, it’s a קל וחומר: kal
vachomer. מה טהור בטהור טמא בטמא. ma tahor b’tahor, tamei b’tamei. So
what is the story with spit, טהור, tahor, that in a case
of a person who is טהור tahor it is טמא tamei by
a man that, by somebody that is טמא? tamei? So you have
spit, spit is normally טהור tahor when it comes out of a
normal person,
of a טהור tahor person, but when it comes out of a
טמא tamei person, out of a זב, zav, his spit is טמא.
tamei. Okay, so מה טהור בטהור, ma tahor b’tahor, what is something
case of something that is טהור tahor when it comes from a
טהור tahor person is טמא בטמא, tamei b’tamei, is טמא tamei the
spit is טמא tamei when it comes out of a זב? zav?
טמא בטהור, tamei b’tahor, the thing that is טמא tamei when it
comes from a טהור tahor person, semen, אינו דין שיהא טמא בטמא?
eino din shehei tamei b’tamei? Certainly we will טמא tamei when it
comes from a זב? zav? Alright, now that's fine, that’s a קל
וחומר, kal vachomer. so fine, שכבת זרע shichvat zera is טמא tamei
by a
זב. zav. But now we’re going to go beyond the original case.
וקמייתי לה בין למגע בין
למשא. v’kameisi la bein l’maga bein l’massa. But that's But the purpose
of that הלכה halacha. is to tell you that the semen of
a זב zav is טמא tamei not only when you touch it
but even when you carry it. So here's the הלכה. The semen
when it comes from a normal man
is
טמא tamei only by touching, not by carrying. The spit of a
זב, zav, the what's called מעיינות ma'ayanos of the זב, zav, the
fluids of a זב, zav, but the Torah only speaks about the
spit, is טמא tamei even if you carry it. It's a weightier
טומאה. tumah. We want to know that the semen
of
a זב zav is טמא tamei even, is טמא tamei the weightier
one, when you carry it. So we do it by a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer If semen is טמא tamei by a normal person,
certainly it's טמא tamei by a זב. zav. Okay, that's all very
nice, but if you apply דיו, you don't get to the idea
that even when you carry it. You just get based on the
original case when you touch it. So that's a case of a
קל וחומר kal vachomer and we're not saying דיו. And the גמרא
Gemara is saying the קל וחומר kal vachomer would bear fruit even
with דיו, because it would tell you it's טמא tamei by a
זב, zav, it's טמא tamei by touch. Okay, so ואמאי נימא הני
קל וחומר למגע? ve'amai neima hanei kal vachomer lemaga? Why are you
allowed to use your קל וחומר kal vachomer and now speak about
the semen of a זב zav even when you carry it, which
goes beyond the original case without דיו? Why don't we say that
the קל וחומר kal vachomer, even with דיו will bear fruit? The
קל וחומר kal vachomer works to tell you למגע, lemaga, that your,
that the, that the semen of a זב zav is טמא tamei
by touch, והני דיו לאפוקי משא. vahanai dayo leafukei massa. And דיו
will tell you, but not carrying. Okay, sorry, you can't go beyond
the original case. Now you're probably realizing that there's an obvious answer
here. This is just like the goring of the half-damages. Why should
I ever have thought that the case of semen would be distinguished
between a normal person and a זב? zav? If it's טמא tamei
by a normal person, it's טמא tamei by a זב. zav. I
already start by knowing normal טומאה tumah of semen. So that's what
the גמרא gemara says. The same way I always start by knowing
half-damages of an ox regardless of where it happened. That I knew
before the, before the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. וכי תימא, vechi teima,
now the גמרא gemara, says, so the גמרא Gemara addresses that. You'll
say למגע לא איצטריך קל וחומר. lemaga lo itztrich kal vachomer. No,
for touching I didn't need a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer, דלא גרע מגברא טהור. dilah gara migavra tahor. You
know, it's not worse than a person who is טהור. tahor. You
don't need a קל וחומר. kal vachomer The Torah says when semen
comes from a man, it's טמא tamei by touch, and that's no
distinction by a טהור tahor person or by a זב. zav. Okay,
איצטריך. itztrich. No, you still, still needed a קל וחומר. kal vachomer,
Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitchach amina, I would have thought to
say,
מקרה לילה כתיב מי שקריו גורם לו, mikreh laylah ksiv mi shekeiryo
gorem lo, יצא זה שאין קריו גורם לו. yatza zeh she'ein keiryo
gorem lo. When the Torah talks about a person who is טמא
tamei because of seminal emission, it says he is not טהור, tahor,
שלא יהא טהור, shelo yihey tahor, because of this, because of this
event of the evening. So it says somebody
whose seminal emission causes him to be טמא. tamei. It wouldn't have
applied to a זב, zav, who was טמא tamei already. So the
Torah's case of semen was only a טהור tahor person. I needed
a, because this semen caused him to become טמא. tamei. I needed
a קל וחומר kal vachomer. to apply it to a זב zav
and it should be limited to the original case of מגע. maga.
אלא יצא זה שאין קריו גורם לו, ela yatza zeh she'ein keiryo
gorem lo, which excludes the case of a זב zav that his
semen doesn't cause him to be טמא, tamei, אלא דבר אחר גורם
לו, ela davar acher gorem lo, his זב zav causes him to
be טמא. tamei. קא
משמע לן. kamashma lan. So the קל וחומר kal vachomer teaches you
it applies to a זב, zav, but that it doesn't let you
go beyond your original case. So the גמרא Gemara says, מדי ולא
דבר אחר כתיב? midei velo davar acher ksiv? What are you talking
about? The גמרא Gemara says. It doesn't say only the semen caused
him to be טמא tamei and nothing else. It says the semen
caused him to become טמא, tamei, something else could also be caused
to become טמא. tamei. So therefore the original פסוק pasuk by a
בעל קרי ba'al keri includes a טהור tahor person and a זב.
zav. So I already knew that the קרי keri of a זב
zav was טמא tamei like a קרי keri of a normal person.
I already knew it was טמא tamei by touch. The קל וחומר
kal vachomer tells me that it should go up one stage and
it should be like the spit. Okay, and should be even by
carrying. So that's a case exactly fits, fits the idea of
רבי טרפון. You knew קרי keri was טמא tamei by all people,
a normal person and a זב, zav, but for זב zav of
course even spit is טמא tamei and spit is טמא tamei like
by carrying. קל וחומר kal vachomer the קרי keri should be טמא
tamei by carrying, and don't say דיו because דיו would completely undermine
the קל וחומר, kal vachomer it wouldn't bear fruit, and the קל
וחומר kal vachomer lets me see that it's like another comparable case,
lets me see that it's like the spit and that it is
טמא tamei even by carrying. So that works very nicely with רבי
טרפון. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומאן תנא
דשמעת ליה דאמר שכבת זרע של זב מטמא במשא? u'man tanna de'shamiesh
leidei dam shichvas zera shel zav metamei bemassa?
So the גמרא says okay, so who is this תנא tanna therefore
that holds like this תנא tanna that we just cited, that says
that the spit... ומאן תנא tana דשמיע ליה דאמר שכבת זרע shichvat
zera, של זב zav מטמא metamei במשא *u-man tana dishame lei d'amar
shichvat zera shel zav metamei be-massa*? who is the one that holds
that? לא רבי אליעזר ולא רבי יהושע *lo Rabbi Eliezer ve-lo Rabbi
Yehoshua*. It's neither רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* nor רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*.
Now, דתנן *de-tenan*, we taught in the משנה *Mishna*: שכבת זרע shichvat
zera של זב zav מטמא במגע ואינו מטמא במשא *shichvat zera shel
zav metamei be-maga ve-eino metamei be-massa*, דברי רבי אליעזר *divrei Rabbi Eliezer*.
So רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* actually completely rejects that the semen of
a זב zav. *zav* is worse than the semen of a normal
male, and says it's only טמא tamei *tamei* by touch and not
by carrying, certainly not like the תנא *tanna* we just quoted. רבי
יהושע אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua omer*, רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says, אף מטמא
במשא *af metamei be-massa*, no, it is even טמא tamei *tamei* through
carrying. But why? לפי שאי אפשר בלא צחצוחי זיבה *lefi she-i efshar
belo tsichtsuchei ziva*, it's impossible that it does not have some little
drops of זיבה *ziva*. זיבה *Ziva* is the fluid, the fluid that
makes this person a זב zav *zav*, that came from his penis
three times. So that's got to be a little bit of it
mixed up in the semen. And therefore that, the זיבה *ziva* itself
is מטמא במשא *metamei be-massa*, so clearly it's present, so therefore the
semen is also מטמא במשא *metamei be-massa* because of the presence of
the זיבה *ziva*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, עד כאן לא קאמר
רבי יהושע התם אלא לפי שאי אפשר בלא צחצוחי זיבה *ad kan
lo ka-amar Rabbi Yehoshua hatam ela lefi she-i efshar belo tsichtsuchei ziva*.
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* says it's only מטמא במשא *metamei be-massa* because
it's impossible that there's not a little bit of זיבה *ziva* mixed
into it. הא לאו הכי *ha lav hachi*, לא *lo*. He doesn't
say the semen itself is מטמא במשא *metamei be-massa*. So neither of
the opinions in the משנה *Mishna* hold like this ברייתא *braita* that
uses a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal va-chomer* to say intrinsically the
semen of a זב zav *zav* would be like the spit, okay,
and the semen of a זב zav *zav* therefore is intrinsically מטמא
במשא *metamei be-massa*. אלא האי תנא הוא *ela hai tana hu*, it's
the following תנא *tanna*. דתנן *de-tenan*, we taught in a משנה *Mishna*:
למעלה מהן זובו של זב zav *lema'la mehen zovo shel zav*. The
משנה *Mishna* here says, this is in כלים *Kelim* where it lists
different degrees of טומאה tumah *tumah*, and it says, one level above
the thing we just mentioned is the fluid of a זב zav
*zav*, ורוקו *ve-roko*, and his spit, ושכבת זרעו *ve-shichvat zaro*, and his
semen, ומימי רגליו *u-meimei raglav*, and his urine. Okay,
so you'll notice all of these things are fluids that come from
the זב zav *zav*. Okay? ודם הנדה *ve-dam ha-nidda*, and also the
blood of a נדה *nidda*. So fluids that come from people that
are טמא tamei *tamei* because of fluids that emitted from their body,
בין במגע בין במשא *bein be-maga bein be-massa*, whether touching or by
carrying. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, ודילמא הכא נמי לפי שאי אפשר
בלא צחצוחי זיבה *ve-dilma hacha nami lefi she-i efshar belo tsichtsuchei ziva*?
How do you know semen there is intrinsically because it's a fluid
and because it's semen? Maybe it's also because there's drops of זיבה
*ziva* mixed into it? Of course then you would ask, well why
urine? Right? The point of this משנה *Mishna* seems to be any
fluids. And the גמרא *Gemara* basically says that. אם כן ליתנייה גבי
זובו *im ken litneiyei gabei zovo*. Then it should have said the
זיבה *ziva* of a זב zav *zav* and his semen, if semen
was because of the זיבה *ziva*. מה ישנא דקתנייה גבי רוקו *ma
yishena de-katneiyei gabei roko*? Why did it insert spit? And remember spit
is the case in the תורה Torah... *Torah* where it's a fluid
that
actually there's normally an innocuous fluid that nevertheless is מטמא במשא *metamei
be-massa*. אלא משום דאתי מרוקו *ela mishum de-ati me-roko*. It's you're learning
it out from the spit, and you're saying that really spit and
other types of fluids as well, including semen etc. So, somebody else
could have come along and said spit represents all fluids maybe without
a קל וחומר kal vachomer? *kal va-chomer*, I mean maybe it would
have been questioned how do you know that? טומאה tumah וטהרה *tumah
ve-tahara* is relatively arbitrary and so on. So therefore the גמרא *Gemara*
is saying in the end this is exactly the קל וחומר kal
vachomer דרשה *kal va-chomer drasha* from spit to say that if semen
is normally טמא tamei *tamei* it'll certainly be טמא tamei, *tamei* by
a זב zav *zav* where even spit is טמא tamei *tamei*. And
therefore the קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal va-chomer* allows you to say
and therefore like the spit and it should be full, and full,
it should be even by carrying and you do not apply דיו
*dayo* because דיו *dayo* would then have undermined the קל וחומר kal
vachomer, *kal va-chomer*. Okay.
So that's that. So now we've actually proven a nice example of
something that works like רבי טרפון *Rabbi Tarfon*, okay, and where we
see that otherwise the קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal va-chomer* would be
undermined. אמר ליה amar lei רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא *amar lei Rav
Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina*. So רב אחא מדפתי *Rav Acha mi-Difti* said to
רבינא ravina *Ravina*: והאי תנא לא דריש דיו ואף על גב דלא
מיפרך קל וחומר kal vachomer. *ve-hai tana lo darish dayo ve-af al
gav de-la mifrach kal va-chomer*? Let's try again. I'll show you a
תנא *tanna* that does not hold of דיו *dayo* even though the
קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal va-chomer* would otherwise bear fruit. Where do
you see this? דתניא *de-tanya*, another case of טומאה tumah, וטהרה *tumah
ve-tahara*. מפץ mapatz במת bemais מנין minayin? *mapats be-met minayin*? How do
you know that a מפץ mapatz *mapats*, which is like a wicker
mat, how do you know that's טמא tamei. *tamei* if it touches
a dead body? Because a מפץ mapatz *mapats* is not the normal
types of things that are טמא tamei. *tamei*. It's not a כלי
עץ *kli etz*, it's not a metal vessel, it is not a,
I mean it might, even if you consider the wicker a type
of a wood, it's not מקבל *mekabel*, it doesn't have a בית
קיבול *beit kibul*, it doesn't have a receptacle, it's flat. It's not
food, okay? It's not a garment. But we do know it's טמא
tamei. *tamei* in one case. We know it's טמא tamei *tamei* by
a זב zav *zav*, because a זב zav *zav* and a זבה
*zava* and a נדה *nidda*, things that they sit on, משכב mishkav.
ומרכב *mishkav ve-merkav*, כל המשכב אשר ישכב עליו *kol ha-mishkav asher yishkav
alav*, those things actually are טמא tamei *tamei*. and this is made
for sitting. So how do you know something that is a משכב
mishkav, by a זב zav made for sitting, what would become טמא
tamei through contact by a dead body? Not so obvious, maybe it's
a unique status by a זב zav, because it's a category of
משכב. mishkav Is that okay? דתניא, מפץ mapatz, במת bemais, מנין? How
do you know that a mat becomes טמא tamei if it touches
a dead body? ודין הוא, vedin hu, it's a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer, ומה umah פחים קטנים pachim ketannim שטהורים shetehorim בזב bezav מטמאי
metamtei במת, bemais. tight little little pottery vessels are טהור
tahor by a זב. zav Why? Because a little pottery vessel, meaning
it has a very tiny little hole, it
cannot become טמא tamei by touching or by moving. Why? Because a
pottery vessel can only become טמא tamei if something touches it from
the inside. So if it's a tiny little hole, think of like
a perfume vial like you see sometimes in the like the museums
or whatever, these ancient little pottery perfume vials,
so therefore there's no way you can get your finger in, the
זב zav, can get his finger in. And since he can't get
any part of his skin in, there's no way he can touch
it on the inside. And now how about what if he moves
it? If a זב zav moves something he makes it טמא, tamei,
but the idea that when you move something you make it טמא
tamei is only based on the idea that it's like you touched
it, so you have to be able to touch it in a
way that will make it טמא. tamei? Okay, so this type of
little pottery vessel there's no way a זב zav, can make it
טמא. tamei?
And nevertheless, מטמאי metamtei במת. bemais? By a dead body it's טמא.
tamei Why? Because because a dead body causes טומאה tumah not just
by touch, but by being under the same roof. Okay, and therefore
and if you want to conceptualize it as if the טומאה tumah?
fills the room and goes into that hole, you know this sort
of you know type of abstract metaphysical טומאה, tumah, but whatever, you
don't need the physical actual skin of the flesh of the מת
mais to touch it. So therefore,
so these little vessels are a זב zav cannot make them טמא
tamei but a מת mais can. מפץ mapatz שמטמא shemetamei בזב, bezav,
a mat that is טמא tamei by a זב zav because of
משכב, mishkav אינו דין eino din שיתטמא sheyitamei במת? Would it certainly
not become טמא tamei through the being under the roof or through
touching with a dead body? Now of course, you know you could
say this is sometimes the problem with a קל וחומר, kal vachomer.
maybe each thing has its own characteristics. The small little vessels work
by a מת mais because a מת mais is about אהל ohel
and being under the same roof, and a מפץ mapatz works by
a זב zav because a זב is about what do you call
it, is about משכב and about sitting on things. But nevertheless, the
קל וחומר kal vachomer says we have we know that a מת
mais is weightier
and
it can communicate to these vessels, so therefore it should certainly be
able to communicate to the to this type of a mat. Okay,
now fine, so that's a normal קל וחומר, kal va'chomer but how
do you know you're not going to say דיו? So the גמרא
says, ומייתינן umaysinan לה בין לטומאת ערב bein letumas erev בין לטומאת
שבעה. bein letumas shiva.
But it is applied in that ברייתא to say that when a
מת mais touches a mat, a מפץ, mapatz it makes it טמא
tamei for seven days like if a מת mais touches anything it
makes it טמא tamei for seven days, even though the source of
this which is a זב is that it actually only makes it
טמא tamei. for one day, not for seven days. So therefore you
have exceeded your קל וחומר. kal va'chomer Okay, you needed the קל
וחומר kal va'chomer to tell you it makes a mat טמא, tamei,
and you could apply דיו and limit it to one day and
you still would have gained something from your קל וחומר without bringing
it to the full status of something touched by a מת mais
which is seven days. ואמאי ve'amai says the גמרא, אימא eima אהני
קל וחומר ahanei kal vachomer לטומאת ערב, letumas erev, the
קל וחומר will help you tell you that if a מת mais
touches a mat it's טמא tamei till the evening like was the
original case by if a זב sits on it, ואהני דיו va'ahanei
dayo לאפוקי טומאת שבעה, le'appuki tumas shiva, and דיו will help you
and דיו will limit it and say but not the whole seven
days. And that's a really good case because we didn't know the
case of a מפץ mapatz by a dead body. אמר
ליה so רבינא said back to him, כבר רמיה kevar ramya ניהלי
nihali רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak לאביי, le'Abaye, רב
נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman Bar Yitzchak
already asked this question to אביי, Abaye, ואמר ליה אביי va'amar lei
Abaye and אביי Abaye gave an answer. What was אביי'ס Abaye's answer?
תנא ממפץ בשרץ מייתי לה. mimapatz besheretz mayisi lah.
You're right, we don't start by a מת. mais. We start by
the idea of a שרץ. sheretz. How do you know a שרץ
sheretz like a dead creepy-crawly that also is an אב הטומאה av
hatumah and causes טומאה tumah like you know like a זב causes
טומאה? tuma So how do you know a שרץ sheretz that touches
a מפץ mapatz, will make the מפץ mapatz טמא? tamei. And then
we're going to apply the קל וחומר simply. Anything a שרץ sheretz
normally touches is one day, anything a זב normally touches is one
day, and we're going to apply the קל וחומר and say we
go מפץ mapatz from a זב, we bring it into the world
of contact טומאה, tuma. not just a זב that's the world of
משכב ומושב, umoshav, into the world of contact טומאה tumah of a
שרץ, sheretz, and we're going to say one day. Okay, and we'll
get to מת mais in a minute. והכי קאמר vehachi ka'amar and
here's what it says, מפץ בשרץ מנין? mapatz besheretz minayin? How do
you know that if a שרץ sheretz touches a מפץ, mapatz how
do you know that is how do you know that's טמא? tamei
ודין הוא vedin hu it's a קל וחומר. Now what's the קל
וחומר? ומה umah פחים קטנים pachim ketannim שטהורים shetehorim בזב bezav טמאים
tmeiyim בשרץ. besheretz. Little,
little vessels, pottery vessels are טהורים tehorim by a זב, but they're
טמא tamei with a שרץ. sheretz. Why are they טמא tamei, with
a שרץ? sheretz? Because a שרץ sheretz doesn't have to stick its
finger in, a שרץ sheretz has much smaller body parts, and the
principle is that a שרץ sheretz is מטמא even בכעדשה, be'kadasha, even
like the tiniest little bit of a שרץ sheretz like the size
of a bean. So therefore, a שרץ sheretz can get into a
tiny little vessel. Okay. So therefore these tiny little vessels are טהור
tehor by זב and טמא tamei, by שרץ. sheretz. מפץ שטמא בזב,
Mapatz she'tamei be'zav, a מפץ mapatz which is טמא tamei, by a
זב, אינו דין שיטמא בשרץ, eino din she'yei tamei be'sheretz, certainly it'll
be טמא tamei by a שרץ. sheretz. So that's how we bring
this idea of a mat, of a מפץ mapatz into contact טומאה
tumah, because of a שרץ sheretz and the קל וחומר is that
there are things that a שרץ sheretz can make טמא tamei that
a זב cannot, like these little types of perfume vials. So the
גמרא says, אלא מפץ במת מנא לן? ela mapatz be-meis minayin? Okay.
Now how do you go from that to apply to learning out
a מפץ mapatz by a case of a מת meis to say
the full seven days? נאמר, Ne'emar, now that we got it into
שרץ, sheretz, now we can do it. נאמר בגד ועור בשרץ, Ne'emar
beged v'or be'sheretz, it says by a שרץ sheretz if it touches,
you know, a garment or something or leather, something made of leather,
it makes it טמא. tamei ונאמר בבגד ועור במת, Ve'ne'emar be'beged v'or
be'meis, and it says it by a מת. meis. So now we're
going to do it based on a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. מה
בגד ועור האמור בשרץ מפץ טמא בו, Ma beged v'or ha'amur be'sheretz
mapatz tamei bo, the same way you got the idea of, now
that we got the idea of מפץ mapatz into שרץ, sheretz, we're
going to say, ah, so now שרץ sheretz makes a mat טמא,
tamei. the קל וחומר will say that it's also true by מת.
meis. אף בגד ועור האמור במת מפץ טמא בו. Af beged v'or
ha'amur be'meis mapatz tamei bo.
Now, you're going to say, how again, just because it's a קל
וחומר, just because it's a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, how do you
know that it goes beyond one day? The whole problem was we
know we can make a מפץ טמא tamei by a מת. meis.
How do you get it to be the full seven days of
a מת? meis? We'll see that in a minute. But first we
have to make the following point. מופנה, Mufna, now this קל וחומר
actually is open, meaning the words that are used to link בגד
beged and עור or are extra, they're not necessary. They're free to
use for the קל וחומר. And that's important because when words are
needed for their own sake in the פסוק, pasuk it's a much
weaker קל וחומר and any type of challenge it's vulnerable to. When
the words are extra, they're there specifically for the קל וחומר, then
it's impervious to challenges. So מופנה, mufna, the words are extra. דאי
לא מופנה, De'ee lo mufna, if it weren't extra, איכא למפרך, ika
le'mifrach, you can challenge it. מה לשרץ שכן מטמא בכעדשה, Mah lesheretz
she'ken metamei be'kadasha,
because a שרץ sheretz is weightier than a מת meis in a
certain way, that even like the size of a bean causes טומאה.
tumah, תאמר במת שאינו מטמא בכעדשה, Tomeir be-meis she'eino metamei be'kadasha, by
a מת, meis, you know, it's not a bean, אלא בכזית, ela
be'kzayis, it needs something the size of an olive. So therefore you
have to say that these words of בגד ועור beged v'or are
extra to make it an ironclad קל וחומר. Now the גמרא says
לאפנויי מופנה. le'afnuyei mufna. How is it extra? מכדי, Michti, שרץ איתקש
לשכבת זרע, דכתיב Sheretz itkesh le'shichvat zera de'chsiv, או איש אשר תצא
ממנו o ish she'tetzei mimenu, שכבת זרע. shichvat zera
Okay. The פסוק pasuk that talks about if you touch, it says
a person who touches a שרץ sheretz or a man from whom
semen, you know, emits from. So in that פסוק pasuk. they're linked
together. וסמיך ליה או איש אשר יגע בכל שרץ, Ve'samich lei o
ish asher yiga be'chol sheretz, וכתיב בשכבת זרע וכל בגד וכל עור
אשר יהיה עליו שכבת זרע. ve'chsiv be'shichvat zera ve'chol beged ve'chol or
asher yihyeh alav shichvat zera. Okay.
So therefore when the תורה Torah talks about שכבת זרע, shichvat zera,
it says any garment or whatever or leather that there is semen
on it, and then you know juxtaposed to it, it says that
if a person touches a שרץ. sheretz.
Hold on a second, I'm sorry, I misread that, let's do that
again. Okay. שרץ איתקש לשכבת זרע sheretz itkesh le'shichvat zera, דכתיב,
so שרץ sheretz is connected to שכבת זרע shichvat zera... because it
says או איש אשר תצא ממנו, o ish asher taitzei mimenu it
speaks about semen and then it says וסמיך ליה או איש אשר
יגע בכל שרץ, ve'samich lei o ish asher yiga be'chol sheretz,
and immediately juxtaposed to the semen case it talks about touching a
שרץ. sheretz. So there the two are already linked. וכתיב בשכבת זרע
Ve'chsiv be'shichvat zera and you know by שכבת זרע shichvat zera, it
already says בגד ועור, beged v'or, וכל בגד וכל עור אשר יהיה
עליו שכבת זרע. ve'chol beged ve'chol or asher yihyeh alav shichvat zera.
So therefore the תורה already juxtaposed and linked שכבת זרע, shichvat zera.
the semen, to the case of the שרץ. sheretz. And we already
know by the semen that if it touches בגד beged or עור
or it's טמא. tamei So it didn't have to say בגד ועור
beged v'or by
שרץ. sheretz. You would have known it just from the fact that
the תורה linked it to the case of the semen. So שכבת
זרע... shichvat zera so בגד ועור דכתב רחמנא בשרץ למה לי? beged
v'or de'kasav rachmana be'sheretz lama li?
Since it says בגד ועור beged v'or by semen, why does it
say it again by שרץ sheretz if the two are linked? שמע
מינה לאפנויי, Shma mina le'afnuyei, it's to make it extra. And therefore
since it's extra, that makes an ironclad קל וחומר between שרץ sheretz
and מת. meis. And if מפץ is טמא tamei, with שרץ, sheretz,
מפץ is טמא tamei, by מת. meis. So the גמרא says ואכתי
מופנה מצד אחד הוא. ve'akati mufna mitzad echad hu.
But okay, that's one half of it is extra. The words of
בגד ועור beged v'or are extra by שרץ. sheretz. But the words
of בגד ועור beged v'or we have yet to say are extra
by מת. meis. So how ironclad is a גזירה שוה... gezeirah shavah...
גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah when only one side of it is extra?
So הני למאן דאמר מופנה מצד אחד למידין ומשיבין. hani leman de'amar
mufneh mitzad echad lemedin u'meshivin.
That's good if you say that a גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah where
one set of the words is extra, you can learn your גזרה
שוה gezeirah shavah and אין משיבין ein meshivin and you do not
accept critiques. You know, you don't have, it doesn't allow for responses.
It's invulnerable. That's good. So now you have, you know, בגד beged
and עור or extra on one side. אלא למאן דאמר
למידין ומשיבין, ella leman de'amar lemedin u'meshivin,
but the one who says that even when one side of words
are extra by a גזרה שוה, gezeirah shavah, you can critique it.
And in order to make it ironclad, you need to have both
sets of words extra.
So מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? What can you say? This
one is, this one can be critiqued because שרץ sheretz is weightier
in the sense of at least that it causes טומאה tumah. even
בכעדשה, be'ke'adashah, even the size of a lentil piece. So the גמרא
says דמת נמי אפנויי מופנה. demet nami afnuyei mufneh.
You know what? The words בגד beged and עור or are also
extra by the case of the of the מת, meis, of the
corpse. מכדי מת איתקש לשכבת זרע. michdi meis itkash le'shichvat zera. מת
meis is also connected to the case of semen. דכתיב והנוגע בכל
טמא נפש. de'chtiv ve'hanogei be'chol tmei nefesh. Somebody that touches somebody who
has become impure due to a corpse. או איש אשר תצא ממנו
or a man from whom זרע zera comes out. Same פסוק pasuk
we were talking about before. וכתיב ביה בשכבת זרע וכל בגד וכל
עור אשר יהיה עליו שכבת זרע. ve'chtiv bei be'shichvat zera ve'chol beged
ve'chol or asher yihiyeh alav shichvat zera. So again, same point. שכבת
זרע, shichvat zera it says בגד beged and עור. or. And both
שרץ sheretz and מת meis in the same פסוק pasuk are all
connected to שכבת זרע. So therefore, בגד ועור דכתב רחמנא במת למה
לי? beged ve'or de'chtav rachmana be'meis lama li?
So why do you need בגד beged and עור or by the
case of the corpse? שמע מינה לאפנויי והוי מופנה משני צדדים. shma
mina le'afnuyei ve'havai mufneh mi'shnei tzaddim.
It comes to show you that it's extra and it's extra on
both ends. Okay, so let's take a pause and remind ourselves where
we are. Okay? From the case of זב that makes a מפה
mapah טמא, tamei, we made a קל וחומר to מת meis that
a מפה mapah should be טמא, tamei but we said that would
limit you to one day. So fine, so we made a קל
וחומר to שרץ sheretz and said that's טמא, tamei, that's one day.
Now you know that a מפה mapah is טמא tamei by a
שרץ. sheretz. The קל וחומר is the small little vials that a
זב can't get his finger in, but a שרץ sheretz can go
in and מת meis can go in by being under the same
roof. Okay, so now you know a שרץ sheretz that touches a
מפה mapah is טמא tamei one day. You also know that the
words, we also are going to now have that the words of
בגד beged and עור or are extra both by a שרץ sheretz
and by a מת. meis. Why? Because it says that a שכבת
זרע is טמא tamei by בגד beged and עור, or, by clothing
and leather, and שכבת זרע and מת meis and שרץ sheretz are
all in the same פסוק. posuk So therefore we know that שרץ
sheretz and מת, meis, בגד beged and עור or are טמא. Why
did the תורה... so the fact that the תורה still said בגד
beged and עור or by שרץ sheretz and בגד beged and עור
or by מת, meis, those words are extra. They allow us to
make an ironclad גזרה שוה. gezeirah shavah. The words are totally there
just for the linkage. And therefore, since there is, a מפה mapah
is טמא by a שרץ, sheretz, a מפה mapah is טמא by
a מת, meis, even though there would be a way you might
want to challenge that גזרה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Okay, so now how
we're going to get to seven? That's what we're going to do
now. הניחא למאן דאמר דון מינה ואוקי באתרה. hani'ach leman de'amar don
minah ve'okei be'atrah.
The idea you can get to seven now works if you say
learn from it and apply it in its appropriate context. So learn
from שרץ sheretz that a מפה mapah is טמא, make a גזרה
שוה gezeirah shavah with these words that make ironclad גזרה שוה, gezeirah
shavah, בגד beged and עור, or, make a גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah
and now apply it to a case of a מת. meis. And
a מת meis making something טמא, we know the general rule is
when a מת meis makes something טמא, it makes it טמא for
seven days. So the גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah said דון מינה, don
minah, we apply the principle of a מפה mapah and we learn
from שרץ, sheretz, ואוקי באתרה, ve'okei be'atrah,
and you put it in the context of a מת. meis. And
when a מת meis makes something טמא, it makes it טמא for
seven days. And that's how we get seven days. אלא למאן דאמר
דון מינה ומינה מאי איכא למימר? ella leman de'amar don minah u'minah
mai ika lemeimar?
But according to the one who says learn from it and take
along its context, what can you say? It's almost like right now
sometimes you have when you do cut and paste in Windows, do
you carry over the original formatting or do you apply the formatting
of the place you're pasting it into? It's actually a perfect analogy.
Okay, so if you say you're carrying over the original formatting, דון
מינה ומינה, don minah u'minah, so then we're limited to the case
of only one day טומאה, not seven day טומאה, because yes you
learn it from שרץ, sheretz, but שרץ sheretz is only one day
טומאה.
So אמר רבא אמר קרא, amar Rava amar kra, the פסוק says...
we'll have a פסוק that tells you that no, that it is
seven days. וכבסתם בגדיכם ביום השביעי. ve'chibastem bigdeichem ba'yom ha'shvi'i. You shall
cleanse your garments on the seventh day. כל טומאה שאתם מטמאים במת
לא יפחתו משבעה. kol tumah she'atem mitamim be'meis lo yifchatu mi'shiva.
Anything that's טמא by a מת meis is going to be ביום
השביעי, ba'yom ha'shvi'i, is going to be seven days. So even though
the originally we used the original context and maybe would have only
said one day. By the case of the מת, meis, this extra
פסוק of וכיבסתם בגדיכם vechibastem bigdeichem tells you that anything that's טמא
by the case of a מת meis is seven days and that
upgrades this from the one day to the seven. Okay, we will
stop here.