Okay, today's דף daf is ס"ח samech chet בבא קמא Bava Kamma
68 and we pick up on ס"ז עמוד ב' samech zayin amud
bais five lines from the bottom and we are going back to
the משנה mishna that began the seventh פרק. perek. אינו גונב אחר
גנב ואינו משלם תשלומי כפל, eino gonev achar gonev v'eino meshalem tashlumei
kefel, so the משנה mishna says that if somebody steals from a
גנב ganav the second גנב ganav does not pay כפל kefel because
he did not the first גנב ganav didn't own it and similarly
if he slaughters the animal he doesn't pay four or five to
the first גנב ganav because the first גנב ganav did not own
it. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so says רב, Rav, לא שנו אלא
לפני יאוש, lo shanu ela lifnei ye'ush, the exemption of the second
גנב ganav is only if this happened before יאוש, ye'ush, אבל לאחר
יאוש קנאו גנב ראשון, aval l'achar ye'ush kano ganav rishon,
but if there was יאוש, ye'ush, the first גנב ganav now owns
it, this is going back to the position that יאוש לחודיה קני,
ye'ush lechudei kanei, יאוש ye'ush alone is enough to transfer ownership, וגנב
שני משלם תשלומי כפל לגנב ראשון v'ganav sheni meshalem tashlumei kefel l'ganav
rishon and the second גנב ganav would pay double to the גנב
ראשון, ganav rishon, the גנב ראשון ganav rishon becomes the owner. Okay,
so we've seen this position before. אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet,
said רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, אמינא כנם בשכבי רבא אמרה להא שמעתא,
amina konam b'shachvei Rava amra l'ha shma'ata, I said that רבא Rava
must have been dozing off when he said this teaching, דתניא, d'tanya,
because we taught in a ברייתא beraisa not that way. אמר רבי
עקיבא מפני מה אמרה תורה טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה, Amar
Rabbi Akiva mipnei mah amra Torah tovach u'machar meshalem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamisha,
why did the תורה Torah say that when you slaughter or sell
a sheep or cow you pay four or five? מפני שנשתרש בחטא,
mipnei shenishtares b'cheit,
because that puts further roots into the sin. You did sin number
one by stealing it and now by slaughtering it or selling it
you've deepened the sin. Now, אימת, eimas, when do we consider it
to be deepening the sin? אילימא לפני יאוש, iyleima lifnei ye'ush, top
of ס"ח עמוד א', samech chet amud aleph, מי איכא נשתרש? mi
ika nishtares?
You didn't deepen the sin. I mean, the גנב ראשון ganav rishon
now handed it over to some second person, but it didn't get
any further away from the owner, it's still, you know, it's still
out of the possession of the owner, the sin didn't deepen in
any way, it wasn't taken even more from the owner, it was
just transferred to another person. אלא לאחר יאוש, ela l'achar ye'ush,
it must be after יאוש ye'ush that after יאוש, ye'ush, then יאוש
ye'ush alone you don't own it, but now the גנב ganav sells
it to somebody else and now it transfers... it goes away from
being outside of the owner's control to actually leaving the owner's ownership
by being a יאוש ושינוי רשות. ye'ush v'shinui reshus. So you've even
furthered and laid
even deeper roots to your sin. ואי סלקא דעתך יאוש לחודיה קני,
v'ei salka da'atach ye'ush lechudei kanei, if יאוש ye'ush alone was enough
to transfer ownership to the first גנב, ganav, אמאי
משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה? amay meshalem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamisha? שלו טבח ושלו
מכר, shelo tovach v'shelo mocher,
then when you got around to selling it after יאוש ye'ush you
would be selling something that was already yours. Okay, and clearly you
can't be חייב chayav once it's already yours.
So therefore you see he says that it must be יאוש ye'ush
is not קונה. koneh. Since the obligation of מכר mocher is by
making the sin go deeper, meaning so transferring ownership away through your
מכירה, mechira, it has to be מכירה mechira after יאוש ye'ush and
it has to be that at that stage you don't already own
it. So that's why יאוש ye'ush is not enough to be קונה,
koneh, number one it proves that, and number two it shows that
the paying of the four and five for selling occurs only after
יאוש. ye'ush. אמרי, amri, no, you could respond back and say כדאמר
רבא, k'd'amar Rava, like רבא Rava said, מפני ששנה בחטא. mipnei sheshana
b'cheit.
רבא Rava says that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is not saying נשתרש,
nishtares, it goes deeper, you set roots, but you repeated the sin.
Okay, so you did it again, even though it didn't do it
in any deeper way. So once you took it away from the
owner and here again you're showing that you, you know, are taking
property away from the owner by going ahead and selling it and
you're demonstrating the sense that you own it and you can do
with it what you want, you're disregarding the owner's ownership, but you
did not deepen it in any way, you did not now remove
it from the owner's ownership, you just essentially repeated your first act,
took it out of the owner's control and demonstrated as if you
own it. Okay, so therefore you do not need נשתרש בחטא nishtares
b'cheit and therefore the obligation would be before יאוש. ye'ush. So according
to this now, there's a debate, there's a debate whether יאוש ye'ush
is קונה koneh and linked to that debate is when are you
obligated for מכירה. mechira. If you say יאוש ye'ush is קונה, koneh,
then you can only be obligated for מכירה mechira before יאוש ye'ush
or else you're selling your own object, that's the position of רב,
Rav, and therefore even though you did not make the sin go
any deeper, you know, but you repeated your sin not only through
stealing it but through selling it. The other opinion is יאוש ye'ush
is not קונה koneh and you're only obligated after יאוש ye'ush because
then you've made the sin go deeper, you've taken it away from
the ownership of the original owner. Okay,
תא שמע, tashma, now we're going to try to bring other evidence
for and against this position.
וטבחו ומכרו, u'tevacho u'mecharo, this is a ברייתא, beraisa, you slaughter it
or you sell it, מה טביחה שאינה חוזרת אף מכירה שאינה חוזרת,
mah tevicha she'eina chozeres af mechira she'eina chozeres, the same way slaughtering
you cannot restore to its original status, it has to be a
sale that does not go back to its original status. אימת, eimas,
now when are we talking? אילימא לפני יאוש. iyleima lifnei ye'ush. אימת,
Eimas, now when are we talking? אילימא לפני יאוש למה אינה חוזרת?
Ilima lifnei ye'ush lama eino chozeres? If you sold it before יאוש,
ye'ush, why does it not go back? You just give it back
to the owner. Now somebody else is holding onto it. Now not
the גנב ganav ראובן, Reuven, but the purchaser שמעון, Shimon, but fine,
give it back to the owner. How does אינה חוזרת eino chozeres
similar to slaughtering? אלא לאחר יאוש, Ella le'acher ye'ush, it must be
after יאוש ye'ush and therefore it's not it doesn't go back. Why
does it not go back? Because now שמעון Shimon legally owns it.
So ראובן, Reuven, you know the person who was stolen from will
get his money back, but the thing is not restored to its
original status under ראובן's Reuven's under the original owner's control. The same
way when you slaughter it, it does not go back to its
original status.
So אלא לאחר יאוש. Ella le'acher ye'ush. אי סלקא דעתך קניא, Ei
salka da'atach kanyia, now if יאוש ye'ush you own it, ראובן Reuven
the גנב ganav owns it, אמאי משלם ארבעה וחמישה שלוטבח ושלו מוכר?
Amai meshallem arba'ah vachamisha shelo tovach veshelo mocher? So why is he
paying four and five? He's selling something that's his own. So the
idea of אינה חוזרת eino chozeres suggests makes it sound like the
sale has to be a permanent sale. That could only be possible
after יאוש ye'ush and you could only be חייב chayav under that
case with a יאוש ye'ush plus שינוי רשות, shinnui reshus, but you
don't yet own it at the stage of יאוש. ye'ush. That shows
that יאוש ye'ush is not קונה koneh and against the and again
the obligation for מכירה mechira is after יאוש. ye'ush. So the גמרא
Gemara says
כדאמר רב נחמן, kedamar Rav Nachman, no, we can explain that exception
of אינה חוזרת eino chozeres like רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. What does
רב נחמן Rav Nachman explain that that means? פרט לשהקנה לשלושים יום.
Prat shehikna leshloshim yom. הכי נמי פרט לשהקנה לשלושים יום. Hacha nami
prat shehikna leshloshim yom. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says that that does
not mean that the object does not return to the owner. It
means it's telling you about the intention of how the מכירה mechira
was framed. Something that is framed as a permanent sale, ראובן Reuven
the גנב ganav sells it to שמעון Shimon the buyer and says
I'm selling this to you permanently, that's the type of מכירה mechira
the תורה Torah obligated you for. If ראובן Reuven says to שמעון
Shimon I'm selling you this for thirty days, since it's not framed
as a permanent sale, you're not חייב chayav four and five. But
it is true that even when you are חייב, chayav, when you've
framed it as a permanent sale, it would only be taking place
before יאוש ye'ush according to רב, Rav, because רב Rav says you're
only obligated before יאוש. ye'ush. And therefore it is true that it
would go back to the person it was stolen from, but when
we say it has to be אינה חוזרת, eino chozeres, it means
it has to be framed in an אינה חוזרת eino chozeres type
of a way. Okay, so fine. מיתיבי, Mesivai, we'll try again. Here's
another ברייתא. braisa. גנב ובא אחר וגנבו. Ganav uva acher ugnavo. So
ראובן Reuven stole it and then שמעון Shimon came and stole it
from ראובן. Reuven. הראשון משלם תשלומי כפל והשני אינו משלם אלא קרן
בלבד. Harishon meshallem tashlumei kefel vehasheni eino meshallem ella keren bilvad. So
ראובן Reuven pays כפל kefel to the original owners and שמעון Shimon
only pays קרן keren to, you know, let's assume ראובן. Reuven. Okay,
but he does not pay the original owners because he did not
steal it from the original owners, he stole it from ראובן, Reuven,
and he doesn't pay
ראובן Reuven isn't really the owner. Okay, now אלא קרן בלבד. ella
keren bilvad. גנב ומכר ובא אחר וגנבו. Ganav umechoro uva acher ugnavo.
Now let's say the, you know, let's say ראובן
Reuven stole it and he sold it to שמעון Shimon and then
somebody came and stole it from שמעון. Shimon. הראשון משלם תשלומי ארבעה
וחמישה והשני אינו משלם תשלומי כפל. Harishon meshallem tashlumei arba'ah vachamisha vehasheni
eino meshallem tashlumei kefel. Let me say that again. Okay, let's do
that again. גנב ומכר ובא אחר וגנבו. Ganav umechoro uva acher ugnavo.
So ראובן Reuven stole it and sold it to שמעון. Shimon. And
then came לוי Levi and stole it from שמעון. Shimon. Okay, not
sure I said that the right way the first time. הראשון משלם
תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. Harishon meshallem tashlumei arba'ah vachamisha. So ראובן Reuven pays
four and five. He stole it and he was stole it and
sold it. והשני Vehasheni and לוי Levi who stole it from שמעון
Shimon משלם תשלומי כפל. meshallem tashlumei kefel. He will pay I'm sorry
did I skip a line? I skipped a line. I'm sorry, let
me do that... גנב ומכר ובא אחר וגנבו הראשון משלם תשלומי ארבעה
וחמישה והשני משלם תשלומי כפל. Ganav umechoro uva acher ugnavo harishon meshallem
tashlumei arba'ah vachamisha vehasheni meshallem tashlumei kefel. Now I got it right.
Okay, and לוי Levi pays כפל kefel to שמעון Shimon because he
stole it from שמעון. Shimon. Fine, and שמעון Shimon now owns it
after ראובן Reuven sold it to him. גנב וטבח. Ganav vetavach. Now
ראובן Reuven stole it and slaughtered it. ובא אחר וגנבו. Uva acher
ugnavo. And now let's say let's call him again לוי. Levi. לוי
Levi comes and steals it from ראובן. Reuven. הראשון משלם תשלומי ארבעה
וחמישה. Harishon meshallem tashlumei arba'ah vachamisha. So ראובן Reuven pays four and
five. והשני אינו משלם תשלומי כפל
אלא קרן בלבד. Vehasheni eino meshallem tashlumei kefel ella keren bilvad. But
לוי Levi doesn't pay ראובן Reuven כפל, kefel, he only pays ראובן
Reuven קרן. keren. Now that's a little something to understand, right? Because
if ראובן Reuven slaughtered it, ראובן Reuven now owns it. So לוי
Levi if he steals it from ראובן Reuven should be paying ראובן
Reuven כפל. kefel. So we'll have to figure that out. So we'll
get back to that. קתני מיהת מציעתא. Katni meihas metzi'asa. We teach
nevertheless the middle. When the גמרא Gemara says מיהת mihas it means
we realize there's a problem with another part of this ברייתא, braisa,
but we're going to hold off on that. Let's focus on the
middle section of the ברייתא. braisa. Okay, what do we teach in
the middle section? גנב ומכר. Ganav umechoro. ואחר כך גנבו. v'acharkach ganavo.
So ראובן Reuven stole it, sold it to שמעון, Shimon, and then
לוי Levi came and stole it from שמעון. Shimon. הראשון משלם תשלומי
ארבעה וחמישה. Harishon meshalem tashlumei arba vechamisha. So ראובן Reuven pays four
and five, he stole it and sold it. והשני, v'hashani, לוי, Levi,
who stole it from שמעון, Shimon, משלם תשלומי כפל. meshalem tashlumei kefel.
He pays כפל kefel to שמעון. Shimon. Okay? לוי. Levi. לוי Levi
pays כפל kefel to שמעון. Shimon. So אימת, aimas, now, when is
he paying, why is לוי Levi paying כפל kefel to שמעון? Shimon?
שמעון Shimon is the guy who bought it from ראובן. Reuven.
אילימא לפני יאוש, ileima lifnei yeiush, if there was no יאוש, yeiush,
שמעון אמאי משלם תשלומי כפל? Shimon amai meshalem tashlumei kefel? So שינוי
רשות בלא יאוש מי איכא מן דאמר דקני? shinui reshus blo yeiush
mi ika man d'amar dekani? So why is לוי Levi paying כפל
kefel to שמעון? Shimon? ראובן Reuven sold it to שמעון Shimon without
any יאוש, yeiush, שמעון Shimon doesn't own it. So if לוי Levi
steals it from שמעון, Shimon, then he's not stealing it from somebody
who owns it. Why is he paying שמעון Shimon כפל? kefel? It's
שינוי רשות shinui reshus without יאוש. yeiush. אלא פשיטא לאחר יאוש. ela
pishita l'achar yeiush. It must be ראובן Reuven stole it, there was
יאוש, yeiush, sold it to שמעון, Shimon, שמעון Shimon now owns it.
לוי Levi steals from שמעון, Shimon, לוי's Levi going to pay שמעון
Shimon כפל. kefel. So you see that there was יאוש yeiush and
שינוי רשות, shinui reshus, but יאוש yeiush isn't קונה koneh by itself.
ואי סלקא דעתך יאוש קונה, v'isalka dach yeiush koneh, because if יאוש
yeiush were קונה koneh by itself,
אמאי משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה? amai meshalem tashlumei arba vechamisha? דידיה הוא
דזבין, didei hu d'zavin,
he's selling something that's already his own. So if לוי Levi is
paying כפל kefel to שמעון, Shimon, there must have been יאוש yeiush
and שינוי רשות. shinui reshus. And you see if there's יאוש, yeiush,
יאוש yeiush was not enough to make ראובן Reuven owner of it,
because then ראובן Reuven would be off the hook for selling it
to שמעון. Shimon.
וסו דתני רישא. visu d'tani reisha. So that's proof number one that
you do that יאוש yeiush is not קונה. koneh. Number two:
the first case. גנב, ganav, that ראובן Reuven stole. ובא אחר וגנבו.
uvachar v'ganavo. And לוי Levi came, we'll have לוי Levi be the
consistent second גנב. ganav. לוי Levi came and stole it from ראובן.
Reuven.
ראשון משלם תשלומי כפל ושני אינו משלם אלא קרן. rishon meshalem tashlumei
kefel v'shani eino meshalem ela keren. So you know, ראובן Reuven pays
כפל, kefel, he was the גנב. ganav. לוי, Levi, who stole it
from ראובן, Reuven, only pays קרן, keren, because ראובן Reuven doesn't yet
own it. מכדי לאחר יאוש קאמינא. michdi l'achar yeiush kamina. Now, we
just said in order to explain the sale case that we're dealing
with יאוש yeiush and שינוי רשות. shinui reshus. If there's יאוש, yeiush,
then if ראובן Reuven stole it and there's יאוש, yeiush, why isn't
לוי, Levi, who steals from ראובן, Reuven, paying ראובן Reuven כפל? kefel?
ואי סלקא דעתך יאוש קונה, v'isalka dach yeiush koneh, ושני אמאי אינו
משלם אלא קרן? v'shani amai eino meshalem ela keren? Why is לוי
Levi not pay, only paying קרן keren to ראובן? Reuven? אלא שמע
מינה יאוש לא קני. ela shema mina yeiush lo konei. You see
that יאוש yeiush is not קני. konei. וקשיא לרבא. vekashya l'Rava. It's
difficult to רבא. Rava. Okay. So in short, the case is that
the only way the middle case makes sense, where somebody who steals
from the purchaser is going to pay him כפל, kefel, is if
there's יאוש yeiush and שינוי רשות. shinui reshus. And if there's יאוש
yeiush and שינוי רשות shinui reshus and you're still the first גנב
ganav is חייב chayav for selling it, you see that יאוש yeiush
is not קונה. koneh. Okay, so that seems to be a good
question. אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא. Rava. ותסבירא, v'tisbira, does that
make sense? הא
מתרצתא? ha metaratzat? Do you think now the ברייתא braita makes sense
according to the way you're reading it? אלא דתני סיפא, ela d'tani
seifa, the last part of the ברייתא braita clearly doesn't make sense.
That was the part you were trying to bracket. But he says
you can't bracket it, you have to have a consistent explanation of
the whole ברייתא. braita. Let's look at the last section of the
ברייתא. braita. גנב וטבח ובא אחר וגנבו. ganav v'tavach uvachar v'ganavo. So
you
know ראובן Reuven came and slaughtered it and then came לוי Levi
and stole it from ראובן. Reuven.
ראשון משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. rishon meshalem tashlumei arba vechamisha. So ראובן
Reuven pays four and five. ושני, v'shani, and לוי Levi who stole
it from ראובן Reuven after it's been slaughtered, אינו משלם אלא קרן.
eino meshalem ela keren. Only pays קרן. keren. Now why is that?
ומי איכא מן דאמר שינוי מעשה לא קני? umi ika man d'amar
shinui ma'aseh lo kani? Why is לוי Levi not paying כפל kefel
to ראובן? Reuven? If ראובן Reuven slaughtered it, it's a שינוי מעשה,
shinui ma'aseh, ראובן Reuven totally owns now the dead carcass. And now
לוי Levi should be paying כפל kefel to ראובן. Reuven. So there's
something not making sense with this ברייתא. braita. We gotta fix, figure
out the end before you can start asking questions. אלא לעולם כולו
לפני יאוש. ela l'olam kulo lifnei yeiush. Here's the, here's what you
have to understand about the ברייתא. braita. It's all לפני יאוש. lifnei
yeiush. And how do you deal with the problem about the end?
Why isn't ראובן Reuven קונה koneh it with after slaughtering it? ואיפוך
סיפא למציעתא ומציעתא לסיפא. v'eipoich seifa l'mitziata u'mitziata l'seifa. It must be
there's an error in the ברייתא braita and which case you pay
כפל kefel and which case you don't must have been got flipped.
Okay? And here's how it has to read. ואימא הכי, v'eima hachi,
here's how you have to read it. גנב ומכר ובא אחר וגנבו,
ganav u'machar uvachar v'ganavo, ראשון משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה, rishon meshalem tashlumei
arba vechamisha, ושני אינו משלם אלא קרן. v'shani eino meshalem ela keren.
In the case where it was sold to another party and then
somebody stole it, לוי Levi stole it from שמעון. Shimon. We're talking
לפני יאוש. lifnei yeiush. So that's the case where you're only paying
קרן. keren. No כפל. kefel. שמעון Shimon doesn't own it yet. Okay?
דשינוי רשות בלא יאוש לא קני, de'shinui reshus blo yeiush lo kani,
it's not קני. konei. So what we saw at the end case
of slaughtering was you only pay קרן keren and not כפל. kefel.
No, no, no. That's the middle case. The selling case is when
you only pay קרן keren and not כפל kefel because there was
no יאוש yeiush and therefore שמעון Shimon doesn't own it. Okay? גנב
וטבח ובא אחר וגנבו. ganav v'tavach uvachar v'ganavo. Now, if however ראובן
Reuven slaughtered it and then it was stolen, ראשון משלם תשלומי ארבעה
וחמישה. rishon meshalem tashlumei arba vechamisha. ראובן Reuven pays four and
five. and five, and the guy who stole it after it's been
slaughtered pays double, דקניא בשינוי מעשה, d'kanya b'shinuy ma'aseh, you're קונה koneh
with a שינוי מעשה, shinuy ma'aseh, but this is not our version
of the ברייתא. braita. The last case why you're not paying כפל
kefel after slaughtering is a real קשיא. kashya. So a not-bad explanation
is that the פסוקים psukim got mixed up between the second and
third case. So the third case where you slaughtered it, you own
it, and the guy who steals it pays כפל, kefel, and the
second case, it was sold but it was before יאוש, ye'ush, so
the guy who steals it does not pay כפל kefel because the
second guy, the guy who bought it, does not own it. Okay,
so there you go. So that neutralizes that ברייתא. braita. רב פפא
אמר לעולם לא תפיך. Rav Pappa amar le'olam lo tipoch. רב פפא
Rav Pappa says no, I would rather, I'm going to try to
explain this ברייתא braita without reversing the order. סיפא בית שמאי
היא דאמר שינוי במקומו עומד. Seifa Beit Shammai hi d'amar shinuy bimkomo
omed. And the last thing you were so bothered, oh you slaughtered
it, why don't you own it? That's בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. בית
שמאי Beit Shammai says even with a שינוי shinuy you don't own
it. So yes, the last case is you slaughtered it, he still
doesn't own it. The guy who stole it from ראובן Reuven after
ראובן Reuven slaughtered it only pays ראובן Reuven קרן keren not כפל.
kefel. And now we're back to the middle case though that after
having sold it, the other guy does own it. And that would
seem to indicate יאוש ye'ush plus שינוי רשות, shinuy reshus, not יאוש
ye'ush alone. Okay, let's take a look. אי הכי קשיא רישא מציעתא
לרב? Ei hachi kashya reisha mziata l'Rav? So now do we תאקע
taki have a contradiction to רב? Rav? Because it sounds like we're
talking about יאוש ye'ush and שינוי רשות, shinuy reshus, and that's why
the second guy owns it. And according to רב, Rav, if there's
יאוש, ye'ush, then the first guy should have already owned it and
not be חייב chayav for selling it.
אמר רב זביד לעולם כולהו לפני יאוש והכא במאי עסקינן שניתיאשו הבעלים
בלוקח ולא נתייאשו בגנב. Amar Rav Zvid le'olam kulhu lifnei ye'ush v'hacha
b'mai askinan she'nityashu hab'alim b'loke'ach v'lo nityashu b'gannav. Okay, so he says
look, there is יאוש, ye'ush, but when did the יאוש ye'ush come?
In the hands of the גנב, gannav, there was no יאוש. ye'ush.
And that's why when you stole it from the גנב, gannav, the
גנב gannav didn't own it. You don't pay the גנב gannav כפל.
kefel. And that's why when the גנב gannav sold it to שמעון,
Shimon, the גנב gannav is חייב chayav because
he was selling something that he didn't yet own. Ah, how does
שמעון Shimon own it so that therefore לוי Levi now has to
pay שמעון Shimon כפל? kefel? Now, after it got into שמעון'ס Shimon's
possession, now there's יאוש. ye'ush. And that's why שמעון Shimon owns it
and that's why לוי Levi pays שמעון Shimon כפל. kefel. So the
case is all of the stuff in the hands of the גנב
gannav was without יאוש ye'ush and that's why you don't pay the
גנב gannav כפל kefel and that's why the גנב gannav is חייב
chayav for selling it because it's not yet his. And the reason
you pay כפל kefel when you steal it from the purchaser is
because the יאוש ye'ush happened after the guy purchased it. And this
is according to רב Rav that says יאוש ye'ush alone is קונה.
koneh. Okay. והכא במאי עסקינן שניתיאשו הבעלים בלוקח, V'hacha b'mai askinan she'nityashu
hab'alim b'loke'ach, they had יאוש ye'ush once it was in the hand
of the purchaser ולא נתייאשו בגנב, v'lo nityashu b'gannav, but not in
the hand of the גנב. gannav. דהוי ליה יאוש ושינוי
רשות, D'hava lei ye'ush v'shinuy reshus,
if you have that גירסא, girsa, meaning in the hands of the
purchaser it's
יאוש ye'ush and שינוי רשות. shinuy reshus. ולא תימא משום דבעינן יאוש
ושינוי רשות. V'lo teima mishum d'ba'inan ye'ush v'shinuy reshus. Now, the reality
is that
if you wanted to get a case where the second גנב gannav
pays כפל, kefel, why did you have to have the second גנב
gannav paying כפל kefel when there was יאוש ye'ush in the hands
of the purchaser? Right? There's יאוש ye'ush and it switched possession. Why
not just have the יאוש ye'ush having taken place in the hands
of the גנב? gannav? And then the second גנב gannav would pay
כפל kefel to the first גנב? gannav? So he says you're right.
יאוש ye'ush by itself is really enough. And if we wanted to
get the second גנב gannav paying כפל, kefel, we could have had
it while it was still in the hands of the first גנב.
gannav. אלא אפילו ביאוש לחודיה נמי קני גבי גנב. Ella afilu b'ye'ush
l'chudei nami kani gabei gannav. יאוש ye'ush alone the גנב gannav would
have owned it. אלא, Ella, so why did the ברייתא braita have
the scenario where the second guy pay כפל kefel only after it
was in the hands of the purchaser and that יאוש ye'ush only
occurred in the hands of the purchaser? דלא משכחת דמשלם תרוייהו גנב
ראשון וגנב שני אלא בהכי. D'lo meshkachat d'mishalem tarvaihu gannav rishon v'gannav
sheini ella b'hachi. You can't get both a four and a five
plus a כפל kefel except in that scenario. Okay? If you had
the יאוש ye'ush in the hands of the גנב, gannav, then the
second גנב gannav who stole from him would pay כפל, kefel, but
the first גנב gannav would never pay four or five because he
already owned it after יאוש. ye'ush. So if you want to get
a scenario where the first גנב gannav pays four or five and
the second גנב gannav gets to pay double, you have the first
גנב gannav sold it before יאוש, ye'ush, so he's חייב chayav four
and five, he doesn't own it yet. And then there was יאוש,
ye'ush, and then the second גנב gannav stole it from the purchaser,
and the second גנב gannav is paying כפל. kefel. So that's why
we gave that scenario, but really יאוש ye'ush alone is קונה. koneh.
Okay. So short point being that for רב, Rav, the only חיוב
chiyuv is before יאוש ye'ush because otherwise you already own it. And
for רב פפא, Rav Pappa, no, the חיוב chiyuv is דווקא davka
it would seem after יאוש ye'ush because יאוש ye'ush is not קונה,
koneh, you're still able to be חייב chayav after יאוש, ye'ush, and
maybe you're only דווקא davka חייב chayav after יאוש ye'ush because then
it's נשרש בחטא. nishrash b'cheit. Then it really transfers ownership. Okay, now
we're going to see there's a logical third position that has yet
to be said and now we're going to say it. Let's take
a look at the two dots.
איתמר: Itmar: המוכר לפני יאוש, hamocher lifnei yeush, somebody sold before יאוש.
yeush. רב נחמן אמר חייב, Rav Nachman amar chayav, Rav Nachman says
you're חייב. chayav. Okay, רב ששת אמר פטור, Rav Sheshet amar patur,
Rav Sheshet says you're פטור. patur. רב נחמן אמר חייב, Rav Nachman
amar chayav, Rav Nachman says you're פטור—you're patur חייב—why? chayav ומכרו אמר
רחמנא ואזבין, u-mcharo amar Rachmana ve-azvin, it says sell it; it doesn't
say that it has to actually transfer ownership. You just did an
act of sale. לא שנא לפני יאוש ולא שנא לאחר יאוש, lo
shena lifnei yeush ve-lo shena le-achar yeush, it doesn't matter before or
after יאוש. yeush. Okay, now that's the missing position: it doesn't matter
before or after. He holds יאוש yeush is not קונה, koneh, so
you're חייב chayav after יאוש; yeush; that's יאוש ושינוי רשות. yeush ve-shinui
reshus. But he's also saying that I'm willing to say you're חייב
chayav before יאוש yeush because you don't need נשתרש בחטא. nishtaresh be-cheit.
It's enough to do an act of selling even if it doesn't
transfer ownership.
That's רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. לא שנא לפני ולא שנא לאחר יאוש.
lo shena lifnei ve-lo shena le-achar yeush. רב ששת אמר פטור, Rav
Sheshet amar patur, you're exempt if it's before יאוש. yeush. חיובא לאחר
יאוש הוא, chiyuva le-achar yeush hu, it's only after דאהני מעשיו, de-ahani
maasav, that that's when your act helped that it actually transfers ownership,
יאוש ושינוי רשות. yeush ve-shinui reshus. אבל לפני יאוש דלא אהני מעשיו,
aval lifnei yeush de-lo ahani maasav, before יאוש yeush that it didn't,
לא מיחייב, lo michayav, you're not obligated. דומיא דטביחה בעינן דאהני מעשיו,
dumya de-teviachah bainan de-ahani maasav, like slaughtering, it has to actually make
a real, actually effect a real change. It now your actions did
something, it now is owned by another person, like the point of
נשתרש בחטא. nishtaresh be-cheit. Okay, so there are three debates. If יאוש
yeush is קונה, koneh, then it's only possible to be חייב chayav
before יאוש, yeush, otherwise you're selling to something that's already yours. And
then clearly your חיוב chiyuv is even just for it's even though
your act didn't really have any halachic meaning, nevertheless you're still חייב.
chayav. It's שינוי בחטא, shinui be-cheit, not נשתרש בחטא. nishtaresh be-cheit. That
you have to say only before יאוש yeush if יאוש yeush is
קונה. koneh. If יאוש yeush is not קונה, koneh, you have the
debate of רב נחמן Rav Nachman and רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. רב
נחמן Rav Nachman says you're חייב chayav both ways, both before and
after יאוש, yeush, right, it doesn't matter whether your acts make a
difference or don't make a difference and you're חייב chayav before even
though it doesn't make a difference, and you're חייב chayav after it
did make a difference and יאוש yeush isn't קונה, koneh, you didn't
already own it. And רב נחמן Rav Nachman says you're only חייב
chayav after יאוש yeush when your act actually has a permanent difference.
Those are all three possibilities. Okay,
so now we're going to be revisiting some of the issues
before except focusing more on the nature of the חיוב chiyuv of
מכירה. mechira. Does it have to be אהני מעשיו ahani maasav or
like נשתרש בחטא, nishtaresh be-cheit, another way of saying it? Okay, so
let's take a look.
אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, and now we're about eight lines,
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven lines from the bottom. אמר
רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, מנא אמינא לה, mena amina lah, where
do I get this idea? דתניא: De-tanya: תניא בברייתא, tanya be-beraita, אמר
רבי עקיבא מפני מה אמרה תורה טבח ומכר משלם ארבעה וחמשה מפני
שנשתרש בחטא, Amar Rabbi Akiva mipnei mah amrah Torah tavach u-machar meshallem
arba'ah va-chamishah mipnei she-nishtaresh be-cheit, exactly like we said before, Rabbi Akiva
says because you set roots into the sin. So you see, אילימא,
eillima, when is it? אילימא לפני יאוש, eillima lifnei yeush, if it's
before יאוש, yeush, מי איכא נשתרש, mi ika nishtaresh, you didn't make
roots, somebody else is holding onto it, but you didn't make the
sort of
further the the way in which this is being taken away from
the owner. מי איכא נשתרש, mi ika nishtaresh, אלא לאו לאחר יאוש,
ela lav le-achar yeush, it must be לאחר יאוש. le-achar yeush.
So that's the point we made before. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מפני
ששנה בחטא, mipnei she-shanah be-cheit, you can say it doesn't mean נשתרש,
nishtaresh, that you set roots, you went deeper, it just means you
repeated it. You did another act of showing your taking it and
your control of it even though it didn't really take it any
further away from the owner. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear.
וטבחו ומכרו מה טביחה שאינה חוזרת אף מכירה שאינה חוזרת. u-tevacho u-mcharo
mah teviachah she-einah chozeres af mechira she-einah chozeres. We had all this
above. Okay, the same way slaughtering it cannot be restored, selling cannot
be restored. אימת, Eimat, when is this talking? אילימא לפני יאוש, eillima
lifnei yeush, if it's before יאוש, yeush, אמאי אינה חוזרת, amai einah
chozeres, what do you mean it can't be restored? Just give it
back to the owner. אלא לאחר יאוש, ela le-achar yeush, it must
be only after יאוש. yeush. ושמע מינה חיובא לאחר יאוש הוא, u-shma
minah chiyuva le-achar yeush hu, so you see it only after יאוש,
yeush, only when it's in a place of נשתרש בחטא, nishtaresh be-cheit,
only it's in a position of שאינה חוזרת, she-einah chozeres, it can't
be restored to the way it was because now it's owned by
the purchaser. תרגמה רב נחמן, Targemah Rav Nachman, no, Rav Nachman explained
it. פרט לשכרו לשלושים יום, perat le-scharo le-shloshim yom, no,
it does not really mean that you need to really make it
change its status and take it away from the owner, but the
framework under which it's sold has to be it's sold as if
it was a permanent sale even though it won't actually take effect.
That has to be the intent, not something that's only being sold
for a temporary purpose. Okay, last line of ס"ח. samech chet. ואף
רבי אליעזר סבר חיובא לאחר יאוש הוא, ve-af Rabbi Eliezer savar chiyuva
le-achar yeush hu, even Rabbi Eliezer holds the obligation is only after
יאוש. yeush. דאמר רבי אלעזר, de-amar Rabbi Elazar, top of ס"ח עמוד
ב. samech chet amud bet. תדע שסתם גניבה יאוש בעלים הוא, teda
she-stam gneiva yeush be-alim hu, you should know that a normal case
of גניבה gneiva we should assume יאוש yeush is present. שהרי אמרה
תורה טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמשה. she-harei amrah Torah tavach u-machar
meshallem tashlumei arba'ah va-chamishah. The Torah says when you slaughter and sell
you pay four and five,
and obviously that's a case of גניבה, gneiva, that's a case of
כפל. kefel. Okay, and that's a debate whether we assume that there's
we assume that one of them גניבה gneiva or. גזילה, Gzeila, you
know, has סתם יאוש, Stam Ye'ush, and it's a debate which one.
The argument for גניבה Gneiva is since you don't know who the
גנב Ganev is, so therefore you never hope of getting it back,
but גזילה Gzeila you know who it is so you hope to
get it back so we don't assume יאוש, Ye'ush, and the reverse
argument is גזלן, Gazlan, the guy had the חוצפה Chutzpah to, you
know, confront you face to face and take it away, you figure
you'll never be able to bring him to court. גנב Ganev you
figure he's a coward, you know once you get the police and
you figure out who did it you'll be able to bring him
to court. Okay, so he is saying רב אליעזר Rav Eliezer says
סתם גניבה Stam Gneiva is יאוש בעלים, Ye'ush Bialim, you give it
up hope right away. And the proof is that you're חייב Chayav
for selling it. Okay, and therefore since you're חייב Chayav for selling
it, he's going to assume that it's only when the sale is
permanent, meaning when there is יאוש, Ye'ush, and therefore how why does
the Torah assume there's יאוש? Ye'ush? It must be that it assumes
with every גנב Ganev there's יאוש. Ye'ush. ודילמא לא יאוש? Udilma lo
ye'ush?
Maybe why are you חייב Chayav when you sold it? Maybe there
was no יאוש? Ye'ush? So, and again, we're presuming that you're only
חייב Chayav if it was יאוש ושינוי רשות. Ye'ush v'Shinuy Reshus. אלא
לאו משום דאמרינן סתם גניבה יאוש בעלים הוא. Ela lav mishum d'amrinan
stam gneiva ye'ush bialim hu.
Since obviously you're only חייב Chayav when you sell it with יאוש,
Ye'ush, and the Torah says you're חייב, Chayav, must be that we're
assuming that with every גניבה Gneiva comes יאוש. Ye'ush. So now the
גמרא Gemara says ודילמא אף על גב דלא יאוש אמר? Udilma af
al gav d'lo ye'ush amar?
How do you know? Maybe the Torah says you're חייב Chayav even
without יאוש? Ye'ush? אמרי לא סלקא דעתך, Amri lo salka daitach, that
doesn't make sense. דומיא דטביחה מה טביחה דאהני מעשיו אף מכירה דאהני
מעשיו. Dumya d'tvicha ma tvicha d'ahani ma'asav af mechira d'ahani ma'asav.
The same way, now a lot of this is the גמרא Gemara
expository, you know,
exposition on רב אליעזר. Rav Eliezer. רב אליעזר Rav Eliezer didn't say
all this, you can tell by the Aramaic and so on. But
this is the hidden assumptions behind רב אליעזר. Rav Eliezer. Okay, so
רב אליעזר Rav Eliezer is assuming that it has to be just
like slaughtering. And the same way slaughtering, it had an effect, a
real permanent effect, you know, selling also did. So רב אליעזר Rav
Eliezer is assuming that the sale has to be like the slaughtering
and it has to be permanent and there has to be יאוש.
Ye'ush. And therefore he's able to prove that סתם גניבה Stam Gneiva
is יאוש בעלים. Ye'ush Bialim. So you see the assumption he's working
with is that the חיוב Chiyuv for מכירה Mechira is only with
יאוש. Ye'ush. Okay. אף מכירה דאהני מעשיו ואי לפני יאוש מאי אהנו?
Af mechira d'ahani ma'asav v'ee lifnei ye'ush mai ahano?
And if it's before יאוש, Ye'ush, then how did his act help?
So that proves that he's assuming
that the חיוב Chiyuv is only with יאוש. Ye'ush. Now the גמרא
Gemara is asking, even though, okay, you've proved that's his assumption, let's
try to understand his argument. ודילמא דשמעינן דיאוש? Udilma d'shaminan d'ye'ush?
How do you know, רב אליעזר, Rav Eliezer, that the Torah is
talking that a סתם Stam case is יאוש? Ye'ush? Maybe the Torah
is talking in a case where you know there was יאוש? Ye'ush?
Why should we assume that it's always assumed to be present? אמרי
לא סלקא דעתך, Amri lo salka daitach, that doesn't make sense. דומיא
דטביחה מה טביחה לאלתר אף מכירה לאלתר. Dumya d'tvicha ma tvicha l'alter
af mechira l'alter. No,
because the Torah says וטבחו או מכרו, Utvacho o mecharo, it sounds
like without any other criteria being met. The same way you're חייב
Chayav if you slaughtered it immediately, you're also חייב Chayav if you
sell it immediately. And the only way that makes sense is if
we assume there's יאוש Ye'ush present. סתם גניבה יאוש בעלים. Stam Gneiva
Ye'ush Bialim. And of course what all this demonstrates is that רב
אליעזר Rav Eliezer just takes for granted that the חיוב Chiyuv for
מכירה Mechira is only with יאוש. Ye'ush. Now תוספות Tosafot of course
said it can't literally mean לאלתר l'alter because there's a whole question
in בבא מציעא Bava Metzia about whether, you know, about יאוש שלא
מדעת. Ye'ush shelo m'da'at. The, you know, like he doesn't, if he
doesn't even know it's stolen, then he doesn't yet have יאוש. Ye'ush.
Do we say that once he, when he knows he's stolen, he'll
have יאוש, Ye'ush, it's like he'll have יאוש? Ye'ush? And we basically
פוסקין Poskin יאוש שלא מדעת לא הוי יאוש. Ye'ush shelo m'da'at lo
havai ye'ush. No, that you can't say if you were to know
about it he would have יאוש, Ye'ush, he has יאוש Ye'ush now.
He has to actually have יאוש. Ye'ush. So therefore it can't literally
mean immediately, but within a short period of time, תוספות Tosafot says
by the time we assume the גנב Ganev will get it to
his house and be ready to slaughter it, you know, we can
also assume in that period of time the original owner will be
aware that it happened. So it doesn't literally mean immediately but almost
immediately as soon as the owner is aware it's happened, you're חייב
Chayav and that's only because סתם יאוש. Stam Ye'ush. And, okay, another
way of saying this, the Torah does not demand that another criteria
be satisfied, that there be only once יאוש Ye'ush takes place and
that could be because we assume that יאוש Ye'ush will always be
present. Okay.
Okay, fine. So now we have, so now we have the positions
that it seems like the strongest way to read all the sources
is יאוש Ye'ush isn't קונה Koneh and you're only חייב Chayav with,
after יאוש, Ye'ush, יאוש ושינוי רשות. Ye'ush v'Shinuy Reshus. That's a case
of אהנו מעשיו, Ahano ma'asav, נשתרש בחטא, Nishtaraish b'cheit, you know, it's
אינה חוזרת Eina chozeret and all of that. But we do know
that the other possibilities exist, that you're חייב Chayav both before and
after יאוש Ye'ush or only before יאוש. Ye'ush. Okay. אמר ליה רב
יוחנן Amar lei Rav Yochanan and so fine, גניבה בנפש תוכיח. Gneiva
b'nefesh tochi'ach.
Now רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan pushes back on the idea that you're
only חייב Chayav after יאוש. Ye'ush. How about a case of kidnapping?
שאין יאוש בעלים She'ain ye'ush bialim that there's no יאוש בעלים Ye'ush
Bialim by a case of kidnapping? You're your own בעלים. Bialim. And
if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says very pointedly, especially
thinking about now what's going on in, you know, Gaza and the
hostages, רש"י Rashi says גניבת
נפש הגונב נפש ומכרו אין כאן יאוש שאין אדם מתייאש על עצמו.
Gneivat nefesh hagonav nefesh umacharo ain kan ye'ush she'ain adam mityai'esh al
atzmo. That a person... never gives up hope, you know, for their
own for the fact that they will be redeemed
and taken back from the captive. Okay. So גונב נפש דכתיב דאין
יאוש בה, gonev nefesh dechtiv de'ein yeush bah, there's no יאוש, yeush,
וחייב. vechayav. So the same way there it's a case of
גונב איש ומכרו, gonev ish umacharo, and it's without יאוש, yeush, the
חיוב chiyuv for here should also be even before יאוש. yeush. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says, מכלל דסבר רב יוחנן לפני יאוש
חייב. michlal desavar Rav Yochanan lifnei yeush chayav. Now from there it's
clear that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan holds—I mean that's obviously his point—you're
חייב chayav before יאוש. yeush. Now that's before יאוש. yeush. ואחר יאוש
מאי? ve'achar yeush mai? What would be the story after יאוש, yeush,
right? Now, meaning that's the question about whether we say that יאוש
כדי קונה. yeush kidei koneh. So
because obviously after יאוש yeush it's always more of a reason to
be חייב chayav unless you think that יאוש קנה. yeush kanah. רב
יוחנן אמר חייב וריש לקיש אמר פטור. Rav Yochanan amar chayav veResh
Lakish amar patur. רב יוחנן אמר חייב חיובא בין לפני יאוש בין
לאחר יאוש. Rav Yochanan amar chayav chiyuva bein lifnei yeush bein le-achar
yeush. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says you're חייב chayav both before and
after, so meaning יאוש yeush isn't קונה. koneh. So once יאוש yeush
isn't קונה, koneh, if you're חייב chayav before, you're certainly חייב chayav
after. After, you're נשתרש בחטא nishtaresh b'cheit and so on. וריש לקיש
אמר פטור. veResh Lakish amar patur. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says you're
exempt. חיובא לפני יאוש אבל לאחר יאוש קנה שלו הוא טובח שלו
הוא מוכר. chiyuva lifnei yeush aval le-achar yeush kanah shelo hu tovei-ach
shelo hu mocher. But after יאוש, yeush, קנה, kanah, and you're selling
your own thing. So again, same types of debates just different ways.
If יאוש yeush is קונה koneh by itself, you can only be
חייב chayav by מכירה mechira and טביחה tevichah before יאוש. yeush. If
יאוש yeush isn't קונה, koneh, then you have both options and then—and
if יאוש yeush isn't קונה koneh and you're חייב chayav before יאוש,
yeush, then you're certainly חייב chayav after יאוש yeush because that's even
נשתרש בחטא. nishtaresh b'cheit. Okay. איתיביה רב יוחנן לריש לקיש. eiseivei Rav
Yochanan l'Resh Lakish. So now the question—רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan is going
to challenge ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish's position that יאוש yeush is קונה.
koneh. גנב והקדיש ואחר כך טבח. ganav vehikdish ve-achar kach tavach. So
somebody stole it and sanctified it and then he slaughtered it. משלם
תשלומי כפל ואינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. meshalem tashlumei khefel ve'eino meshalem
tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah. He pays double but not four and five. Why
not? Because presumably once he was מקדיש makdish it, you know, then
it's no longer his, it's הקדש hekdesh and you're not חייב chayav
by גניבה geneiva four and five when you take something that's הקדש
hekdesh because it's רעהו. re'eihu. רעהו ולא הקדש. re'eihu v'lo hekdesh.
אימת? eimas? Now what's the case? אילימא לפני יאוש, eileima lifnei yeush,
if he sanctified it, the גנב, ganav, before יאוש—מי קדוש? kadosh. Can
the גנב ganav sanctify? איש כי יקדיש את ביתו קודש אמר רחמנא
מה ביתו שלו אף כל שלו. ish ki yakdish es beiso kodesh
amar rachmana mah beiso shelo af kol shelo. That you can only
sanctify something that's already yours. אלא פשיטא לאחר יאוש. ela peshita le-achar
yeush. But it must be after יאוש. yeush Alright, or else you
can't be מקדיש makdish something that the owners haven't been מייאש miya-eish
on it. וטעמא דהקדיש הוא דאינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. v'ta'ama dehikdish
hu de'eino meshalem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah.
Now the reason is once you sanctified it, יאוש yeush. plus הקדש,
hekdesh, יאוש yeush and שינוי רשות shinui reshous or שינוי השם, shinui
hashem, now it actually becomes קדוש. דכי קטבח דהקדש קטבח. dechi katavach
de-hekdesh katavach.
Now that you're slaughtering it, you're slaughtering something that's הקדש. hekdesh. אבל
לא הקדיש טבח משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. aval lo hikdish tavach meshalem
tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah.
If you slaughtered it, you would pay four and five. Okay, now
because it sounds like only because you were מקדיש. makdish. ואי סלקא
דעתך יאוש קנה—now ve'i salka da'atach yeush kanah רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
says to ריש לקיש—if Resh Lakish you think יאוש yeush is קונה,
koneh, אמאי משלם שלו הוא טובח שלו הוא מוכר? amai meshalem shelo
hu tovei-ach shelo hu mocher? Why are you paying? So רב יוחנן
Rav Yochanan says what's the case that you were מקדיש? makdish? You
can't be מקדיש makdish it before יאוש yeush because it wouldn't have
done anything. So the גנב ganav must have been מקדיש makdish it
after יאוש. yeush If יאוש yeush. is קונה koneh then you'd be—even
without the הקדש hekdesh you'd
be פטור patur because it's now it's yours. So it must be
יאוש yeush happened but wasn't קונה, koneh, and יאוש yeush plus שינוי
רשות shinui reshous or שינוי השם, shinui hashem, that allows you to
be מקדיש. makdish. So it's a little bit different, you know, when
רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says how could you be מקדיש makdish מה
ביתו שלו אף כל שלו? ma beiso shelo af kol shelo? You
really can be מקדיש makdish before it's yours because the יאוש yeush
plus the שינוי רשות shinui reshous and the שינוי השם shinui hashem
of הקדש hekdesh is what allows you to be מקדיש. makdish. But
without יאוש yeush you can't do anything. So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
says this scenario that you were able to be מקדיש makdish but
you needed to be מקדיש makdish for it to—for you to get
exempt could only be with יאוש yeush and you see that יאוש
yeush alone is not קונה. koneh. Okay so that seems like another
excellent proof. So let's see what he says. אמר ליה, amar leih,
he says back to him, הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהקדישו בעלים ביד
גנב. hacha bemai askinan k'gon shehikdishu be'alim beyad ganav.
No when it says it was מקדיש, makdish, it doesn't mean that
the גנב ganav was מקדיש. makdish. It means that the owners were
מקדיש. makdish. It was before יאוש yeush and the owners were מקדיש.
makdish. And since the owners were מקדיש, makdish, now when the גנב
ganav comes to slaughter it, he is now slaughtering something of הקדש
hekdesh and therefore he does not pay four and five. So the
גמרא Gemara says ומי קדוש? u-mi kadosh? One minute, can the owners
be מקדיש makdish once it's not under their control? והאמר רב יוחנן—now
veha-amar Rav Yochanan רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says, okay this is ריש
לקיש, Resh Lakish, but רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan says—גזל ולא נתייאשו הבעלים
שניהם אינם יכולים להקדיש. gezel v'lo nityashu habe'alim shneihem ainam yecholim le-hakdish.
If something is stolen and the owners haven't had יאוש yeush yet,
neither can be sanctified. זה לפי שאינו שלו, zeh lefi she'eino shelo,
the גנב ganav can't sanctify because it's not his, with יאוש yeush
he has— With ייאוש yei'ush he has enough control that his ייאוש
yei'ush plus הקדש hekdesh makes, does work like we said before, but
without ייאוש yei'ush the גנב ganav or גזלן gazlan can't do anything.
וזה V'zeh the original owner, even though it's before ייאוש, yei'ush, לפי
שאינו ברשותו, l'fi she'eino birshuto, even though they've had no ייאוש yei'ush
and even though it's theirs, they're not in control of it, so
they can't be מקדיש makdish it. So how could רייש לקיש Reish
Lakish say the scenario is the original owners were מקדיש makdish it?
Since when can owners be מקדיש makdish it once it's out of
their control? So אמרי, amri, you could say, yeah, you know what,
he argues with that point with רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמרי, amri,
הוא דאמר כצנועין, hu d'amar k'tznuin, and he'd say like the צנועין,
tznuin, like the frum, you know, צנוע's tznu like the modest people,
the people that were very concerned about
מצוות mitzvos and
עבירות, aveiros, that תנן: t'nan: הצנועין מניחין את המעות. hatznuin manichin es
hamaos. If you had, you know, like a orchard that was כרם
רבעי, kerem revai, and you were afraid—now fourth year, it can only
be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim or has to be redeemed to be
eaten out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and you were afraid that passersby would
come and eat from the fruit and they'd actually be גזלנים gazlanim
because they wouldn't ask permission, but that's what happens; people pass by
and they pluck apples, and you don't want anybody to sin on
account of you even though they're stealing your fruit. So what would
they do, these צנועין? tznuin? They'd set aside some money ואומרין: v'omrin:
כל הנלקט מזה יהא מחולל על המעות האלו. kol hanilkat mizeh yehei
mechulal al hamaos ha'elu. If anybody passes by and picks an apple
off my tree—okay, well let's say, I don't know, a date or
a fig, make it something—anyway then, then as—then that the קדושה kedusha
of כרם רבעי kerem revai will be transferred on this money, and
therefore you will save them from actually eating כרם רבעי kerem revai
outside or נטע רבעי neta revai outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, or grapes
if it was כרם רבעי. kerem revai. Fine. Outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
So you see even after it is not in your
control—it's גזל, gezel, it's the people plucked your grapes—you can still do
this פדיון, pidyon, and therefore since you can still do this פדיון,
pidyon, presumably you can still be מקדיש makdish it. Now there's a
big תוספות Tosafot who points out that there's a big logical difference.
You know, being פודה podeh something is you're,
you know, there's a lot of evidence that you could be פודה
podeh something that isn't yours; it's already in the hands of הקדש,
hekdesh, you're being פודה podeh it from הקדש, hekdesh, it's no longer
in the hands of the original owner. Besides which, you know, when
you're being מקדיש makdish something, you're taking something that belongs to somebody
and giving it to הקדש. hekdesh. When you're being פודה podeh it,
it's something that already הקדש hekdesh sort of has control over and
you have a right to come ahead and transfer, you know, the
קדושה kedusha away; it's not really something that the owner has a
right that they can stand in your way to prevent. Even if
the owner could, says תוספות, Tosafot, here you're doing like you're זוכין
לאדם שלא בפניו, zochin l'adam shelo b'fanav, you're helping these גזלנים gazlanim
by being פודה podeh it. So obviously you should be able to
be פודה; podeh; that's much better than being מקדיש makdish something that
somebody stole and is no longer, you know, under your control and
that you're going ahead and being מקדיש makdish it. Anyway, that's what
the גמרא Gemara says, that רייש לקיש Reish Lakish would say that
the original owners were מקדיש makdish and רייש לקיש Reish Lakish somehow
by comparison to this case of פודה, podeh, רייש לקיש Reish Lakish
would argue that the original owners could be מקדיש makdish it. And
that's the scenario, not that the גנב ganav was מקדיש makdish it.
So says גמרא, Gemara,
okay, והא אמרי: v'ha amri: חזרה קרן לבעלים? chazra keren l'balim? I
don't understand, says the גמרא. Gemara. Why
is the גנב ganav חייב כפל, chayav kefel right, if the owners
were מקדיש makdish it? They've reasserted their control; it's like they've taken
it out of the hands of the גנב ganav and given it
to הקדש. hekdesh. And now when they bring the גנב ganav to
the בית דין, beis din,
you know, the גנב ganav can say, "I don't have to pay
כפל; kefel, כפל kefel; is only when I'm still holding on to
it by the time we come to בית דין. beis din. If
I've returned it to you before בית דין, beis din, I don't
have to pay כפל." kefel And here you basically took it back
from me before we got to בית דין, beis din, so why
am I paying כפל? kefel. So the גמרא Gemara says, כעמד בדין.
k'amad b'din. Ah,
the case was: the owners schlepped the גנב ganav into בית דין,
beis din, they—the בית דין beis din said, "You're חייב chayav to
pay כפל," kefel? and then the owners were מקדיש makdish it. And
now the גנב ganav slaughters it. And because the owners were מקדיש
makdish it, he's not חייב chayav four and five for slaughtering it,
but because there was a בית דין beis din before—before they were
מקדיש, makdish, he is חייב chayav כפל. kefel,
So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי? heichi dami? What's the case?
אי דאמרי: i d'amri: צא תן לו, tzei ten lo, if the
בית דין beis din said, "Go pay," they actually, you know, gave
out the order that he now has to pay the owners and
pay them כפל, kefel. מאי איריא mai irya הקדיש? hikdish? אפילו לא
הקדיש נמי לא מחייב. afillu lo hikdish nami lo mechayev.
Even so if that's true, then, right, you have to get him
to pay כפל, kefel, so there was a case of בית דין,
beis din, they said, "Go pay," and now we're going to say
the owners were מקדיש makdish it and that gets the גנב ganav
off for slaughtering it. But the גמרא Gemara says, but even if
the owners weren't מקדיש makdish it, once they said you have to
go pay, that that is a complete break, you know, from... We're
no longer in the middle of the process of his גניבה geneiva
and so on. So the גמרא Gemara says דאמר רבא, d'amar Rava,
צא תן לו, tzei ten lo, טבח ומכר פטור, tavach u'machar patur,
that
if there was a court case and the בית דין Beis Din
said go pay back the animal you stole and then the גנב
ganav before he got around to paying it back slaughtered it he
would be
exempt why מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? כיוון דפסקי למילתא keivan d'paski l'milsa
וטבח ומכר, v'tavach u'machar, since the matter was like broken you know
like cut off right the whole previous process stealing and being found
and בית דין Beis Din or whatever now we're done with it
so even though the animal hasn't been returned once there was a
פסק psak of בית דין Beis Din if you were to slaughter
it this would be a totally new thing you know it's like
he went into their house now and slaughtered their animal it's not
a continuation of the
גניבה geneiva כיוון דפסקי למילתא keivan d'paski l'milsa since it interrupted the
matter וטבח ומכר v'tavach u'machar and then he slaughtered it הוי ליה
גזלן havei lei gazlan now he's taking an animal new it's a
new act it's not גניבה geneiva it's their cow that he's supposed
to pay back and he's slaughtering it in their presence okay וגזלן
אינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה v'gazlan eino meshalem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah he
wouldn't pay four and five so if בית דין Beis Din said
צא תן לו tzei ten lo and that's why he's paying כפל
kefel, then you wouldn't need הקדש hekdesh for him to get off
four and five so now the end of this teaching of רבא
Rava top of ס"ט עמוד א' samach tes amud aleph חייב אתה
ליתן לו chayav atah litten lo however if בית דין Beis Din
said you're obligated to pay but they didn't yet set the sheriff
after him they didn't yet say go pay so you're obligated you
know it's sort of it's before it's translated into acting on it
like הלכה halacha and not yet למעשה l'ma'aseh so in that case
טבח ומכר משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה tavach u'machar meshalem tashlumei arba'ah v'chamishah
in that case after they said חייב chayav if he would slaughter
it since we're still in the middle of it we haven't yet
issued the actual you know command that he does do the paying
then it's still a continuation of the original גניבה geneiva and if
he slaughtered it he would still pay four and
five מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? כיוון דלא פסקי למילתא keivan d'lo paski
l'milsa since the matter has not been totally you know cut off
אכתי גנב הוא achti ganav hu he's still in the original category
of גנב ganav and now slaughtering it would pay four and five
so the גמרא Gemara says לא צריכא lo tzericha so you're right
the only case we're talking about is דאמרי ליה חייב אתה ליתן
לו d'amri lei chayav atah litten lo so that's how ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish would explain the case of הקדש hekdesh what's the case
of הקדש hekdesh רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says the case of הקדש
hekdesh and then the גנב ganav gets off proves that there is
יאוש yeush and then הקדש hekdesh and יאוש yeiush itself is not
קונה koneh and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no the case is
before יאוש yeiush and the case is that
he came to a בית דין Beis Din and the בית דין
Beis Din said חייב ליתן לו chayav litten lo and that's why
he's going to pay כפל kefel then the owners were מקדיש makdish
it it's like they took it back but it's okay he's already
חייב chayav כפל kefel they were מקדיש makdish it and now he
slaughtered it and because they were מקדיש makdish it he's exempt for
four and five had they not been מקדיש makdish and בית דין
Beis Din had just said חייב ליתן לו chayav litten lo he
would still be paying כפל kefel but you would still be in
the middle of being a גנב ganav and the slaughtering it would
make him obligated in four and five and that's how ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish explains that case that ברייתא beraisa okay we will stop
here.