Today's דף *daf* is י"ט *yud tes*, 19. We pick up second
line from the top. Also, 30th day of the עומר *Omer*. Public
service announcement, there's some good apps out there for your phones to
remind you every day what ספירה *sefirah* you're in. Just saying, since
I've had the app, I haven't miscounted. Okay, second line from the
top, י"ט ע"ב *yud tes amud beis*. שבת Shabbat ויום טוב *Shabbos
v'Yom Tov* was a problem. תנו רבנן tanu rabbanan, *Tanu Rabbanan*. כלי
kli שנטמא בערב יום טוב Yom Tov, אין מטבילין אותו בין השמשות
bein hashmashot *keli shenitma b'erev Yom Tov ein matbilin oso bein hashmashos*.
So we've been talking about the fact that you can't do טבילת
כלים kelim *tevilas keilim* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* and יום טוב Yom
Tov, *Yom Tov*, and all these like technical differences or between whether
it was or not so technical, whether it became טמא tamei *tamay*
on יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* or before יום טוב Yom
Tov. *Yom Tov*, whether you're doing it to focus on the water,
which is allowed, or the כלי kli. *keli*, which is not allowed.
Now we deal with the question about ספק *safek*. So it became
טמא tamei *tamay* on ערב יום טוב Erev Yom Tov *erev Yom
Tov*. You can't do it בין השמשות bein hashmashot *bein hashmashos* because
it might already be יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, and then
you can't do it. It's an איסור דרבנן Derabbanan *issur d'Rabbanan*. So
אין מטבילין אותו בין השמשות *ein matbilin oso bein hashmashos*. רבי שמעון
שזורי Rabbi Shimon Shezuri אומר, אף בחול אין מטבילין אותו מפני שצריך
הערב שמש herev shemesh. *Rabbi Shimon Shezuri omer, af bechol ein matbilin
oso mipnei shetzarich ha'erev shemesh*. Even on a weekday we wouldn't let
somebody do it בין השמשות *bein hashmashos* because it needs nightfall to
be טהור tahor *tahor*, right? The same way a person who goes
to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah*, he's only fully טהור tahor. *tahor* at
nightfall. So if you put a כלי *keli* in the מקוה mikvah
*mikvah*, it's only fully טהור Tahor *tahor* when it hits when it
becomes nightfall. By the way, I should mention that's not relevant for
us for like when a woman who is a נידה *niddah* goes
to the מקוה mikvah? *mikvah* because this residual טומאה *tumah* only has
relevance for like, you know, for like eating תרומה terumah *terumah* and
קדשים kodshim
*kodshim*. Nevertheless, it needs הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh*. So what's the problem?
So the problem is that if this guy does it right before
nightfall, he's going to right at בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*, so רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says it sounds like he's ready to eat why is
he doing it at this time? Obviously, because he wants to use
it tonight. So he's going to use it tonight, it's obviously he's
not going to have הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh* because he only dunked
it in the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*, it might
already be night. So therefore we shouldn't let a person use the
מקוה mikvah *mikvah* when it's already בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*. According to
that logic also, we shouldn't let them use the מקוה mikvah. *mikvah*
at night because it shows that they want to use it tonight.
But though obviously you can understand that בין השמשות *bein hashmashos* is
particularly problematic. If they use it at night, they realize it doesn't
have הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh*. If they're using it בין השמשות *bein
hashmashos*, they persuade themselves that they got it in while it was
still daytime and then it became night. Or maybe they'll say well
maybe it's ספק הערב שמש *safek ha'erev shemesh*. So doing it בין
השמשות *bein hashmashos*, you will allow you to fall into this trap
of not waiting till it's fully nightfall before or until the next
night in order to use it. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon שזורי
*Rabbi Shimon Shezuri* doesn't want to allow a person to use it.
Again, it's quite interesting because who are the people that need to
wait the הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh* as I said, only if you're
eating תרומה *terumah* or קדשים *kodshim*. How many, you know, of those
are really not going to like know the הלכה halakhah *halacha*? But
as I said, maybe it's not not knowing the הלכה halakhah *halacha*,
maybe it's persuading yourself that you got it in before it became
nightfall and therefore you got הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh* when you really
did not. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this,
ומה תנא קמא לא בעי הערב שמש *u'ma Tana Kamma lo ba'ei
ha'erev shemesh*? So the תנא קמא *Tana Kamma* doesn't require it? Meaning
question mark, exclamation point? How does he address this concern about doing
it during the weekday at בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*? So אמר רבא
*amar Rava*, אשכחינהו לרבנן דבי רב *ashkachinhu l'Rabbanan d'bei Rav*, I found
the Rabbis, meaning the rabbinic students in the in the, you know,
in the ישיבה *yeshiva*, דייתבי וקאמרי *d'yasvi v'ka'amri*, and they were sitting
and saying, אמרי *amri*, we can say, במחשבתו ניכרת מתוך mitoch. מעשיו
קמיפלגי *b'machshavto nikares mitoch ma'asav kamiflegi*. So the debate is how much
can you see a person's intentions through his actions? Meaning how much
by the way is he acting does that indicate that he enough
knows what's going on and therefore we don't have to have this
concern? והיכי דמי *v'heichi dami*, what's the case? כגון דנקיט מנא בידיה
*kegon d'nakit mana b'yadeih*, you see him taking a vessel in his
hands, ורהיט ואזיל בין השמשות לאטבולי *v'rahit v'azil bein hashmashos l'atbolei*,
and he's running and it's about it's already בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*
and he's running to get to the מקוה mikvah. *mikvah*. So you
see though that he's running, he clearly understands that there's some urgency.
So מר סבר האי דקרהיט ואזיל מידע ידע דבעי הערב שמש *mar
savar hai d'karahit v'azil mada yada d'ba'ei ha'erev shemesh*. So the approach
that says we let him do it בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*, so
again, this is during the week, we let him do it, this
says look, the fact that he's running shows that he understands that
he's got to get there before nightfall if he wants the nightfall
to count as הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh*. So from his actions it's
clear he knows what the הלכה halakhah *halacha* is, so we don't
have to tell him he can't do it בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*.
Now, of course, if he knows he needs הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh*
and he gets there and it's already בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*, why
is he doing it? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says no, he gets
there, he realizes he missed the time but then he's already at
the מקוה mikvah, *mikvah* with his כלי *keli*, so he's going to
use it. But the fact that he was running to get to
the מקוה Mikvah *mikvah* right before sunset shows he understands the importance
of sunset and we don't have to make a גזירה gezeirah? *gezeirah*.
ומר סבר umar savar מחמת מלאכה Melacha הוא דקרהיט *u'mar savar machmas
melacha hu d'karahit*.
Nah, people run because, you know, they have a job to do,
they have work, they they can't waste time. It doesn't prove that
he understands the importance of sunset. Okay? So that's the question, do
we really have to make a גזירה gezeirah, *gezeirah* if somebody's doing
it בין השמשות *bein hashmashos*? And they said the question is, you
know, most of the time you'll see somebody running to get there
בין השמשות *bein hashmashos* or whatever, it's clear
he knows what
the הלכה halakhah, *halacha* is. No, that we can sort of interpret
a person's intentions through his actions. Everybody agrees that that's that we
don't debate that. כי פליגי, ki peligi, what would be the debate?
I mean that we could assume we know, we can see his
intentions and that he's aware that it needs nightfall. כי פליגי, what
would be the debate be? In the case of איטמי בפחות מכעדשה,
itmei b'pachot mi'k'adasha, and not a case guy running. Somebody became, something
became טמא Tamei with less than an עדשה, adasha, less than like
a bean size, a lentil size of a like a dead bug,
a dead rodent. ואתא לקמיה דרבנן לשיולי בפחות מכעדשה איטמי אי לא,
v'ata l'kamei d'rabbanan lish-ulei b'pachot mi'k'adasha itmei i lo,
and he went to the rabbis to ask, does this become טמא
Tamei if it touched something, a rodent smaller than the size of
a כעדשה? k'adasha? Now the answer is no, it didn't, but he
had another כלי that he had to בטבילה, bitvila, but he came
to ask about this כלי. So מר סבר מי דהאי לא גמיר,
mar savar mi d'hai lo gamir, look, the guy's such an עם
הארץ, am ha-aretz, he doesn't know this הלכה halakhah of פחות מכעדשה.
pachot mi'k'adasha. So הערב שמש נמי לא גמיר. herev shemesh nami lo
gamir. So he also wouldn't know the הלכה halakhah that you needed
nightfall. So this type of a guy we're not going to allow
to you know to use the מקוה בין השמשות because clearly he
doesn't know laws of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. ומר סבר and the
other one holds, no, הא הוא דלא גמיר, ha hu d'lo gamir,
that הלכה halakhah of the minimum size, that he doesn't know because
Rashi says that's not written anywhere in the Torah. האי הערב שמש
גמיר, hai herev shemesh gamir, but the fact that you need nightfall
to make it fully טהור that he could know, that's a more
common הלכה, halakhah that's written in the Torah and so on. I
have to say this whole thing is very bizarre because it's like
it's talking about a highly specific case. Like are we talking about
making a גזירה? Are we talking about giving advice to somebody? And
if he's right there and asking you about פחות מכעדשה, pachot mi'k'adasha,
so tell him, by the way, don't use the מקוה tonight because
it's going to require הערב שמש. So what does it mean? It
means it's not this case, it's another case? So we're going to
like, I mean, it's crazy. What are we talking about, identifying individuals
based on their knowledge and ignorance and then telling them whether they
can use the מקוה? It's like we have a policy whether you
can use the מקוה once it's already sunset. You have to ask,
answer a quiz, and if you do well on the quiz, we,
I don't really understand like what are we talking about, a גזירה,
an attitude? Maybe we're talking about a general attitude, but I don't
know. All right, I should, I will say something else which is
the phrase מחשבתו ניכרת מתוך מעשיו machshavto nikeret mi-toch ma'asav is interesting
because it's also used in very different contexts. Like a question about
a minor, and can you assume a minor has דעת da'at in
הלכה halakha or doesn't have דעת? da'at? You know, or has כוונה,
kavanah, doesn't, and how much that you can sort of judge a
person's intentions. You know, here it's basically judging your intentions. We understand
you're a בר דעת, bar da'at, but we want to assess, get
to what you're thinking. But there's another question about just using it
to assess how much intelligence you know a minor does have, if
you see them acting in an intelligent way and in a way
that's thoughtful and planned and so on, whether that then becomes relevant
for הלכתי halakhic purposes as well. Good.
Except for that we're saying that you're the person that doesn't know
the הלכה halacha? well enough, so we'll make up a new הלכה
halacha. for you.
Right exactly, to make sure there's something else they don't know, exactly.
Right, that's a good point too. How will they ever know the
הלכה halacha you're not supposed to do it בין השמשות unless we
have a, unless we're in control of the מקוואות mikvaot and we,
and we turn them away. All right, נמטבלין מגב לגב. nimtabelin mi-gav
l'gav. Now there's, the last line of the משנה mishnah was very,
was very vague. It said you can be טובל tovel although you
can't be טובל tovel on שבת and יום טוב, Yom Tov you
can be טובל tovel from back to back and from חבורה chaburah
to חבורה, chaburah, from group to group. What does that mean? So
תנו רבנן, our rabbis taught, this is a תוספתא. Tosefta. כיצד מגב
לגב? keitzad mi-gav l'gav? What does it mean from back to back?
הרוצה לעשות גתו על גב, harotzeh la'asot gitto al gav,
now our גירסא girsa is כדו, kaddo, which is your, a pitcher,
but probably the better גירסא girsa is בדו, baddo, בית הבד. bet
habad. So אגת, agat, right, and a בית הבד bet habad is
the cases
of, אגת agat is like where you press olives, and a בית
הבד bet habad is where you press grapes. So the point is
that you were מטהר metaher your כלים Keilim because you were going
to make olive oil, and you wanted to use them for your
olive press, and
and you wanted it to be pure, you wanted it to sell
it to כהנים kohanim or whatever. And then you decided I'm going
to use these vessels not in my olive press, I'm going to
use them in my wine press. Okay, now of course the point
is who cares? Like just, they're טהור. It's not like you're going
from תרומה to קדשים with different levels of קדושה kedushah of טהרה.
taharah. So the point is you're right, you don't really need to
take them to the מקוה again, but you for some reason, like
every time you get ready to use your wine press, you take
all the vessels to the מקוה. And every time you get ready
to use your olive press, you take all your vessels to the
מקוה. So you took all your olive press vessels to the מקוה,
now you want to reuse it for your wine press, so those,
so you want to re-be טובל tovel them. So you want to
do that on יום טוב, Yom Tov. געזונטהייט, gesunteheit, it doesn't even
need, you don't need to do it, so you want to do
it, be my guest. Okay?
וכדו u-khaddo or your vessel or should be ובדו על גב גתו
עושה. u-vaddo al gav gitto oseh. You can do it because you
really don't need it to do it at all anyway. So you
want to do it? געזונטערהייט! Gezunterheit! כיצד מחבורה לחבורה? Keitzad Mechabura Lechabura?
What does it mean from one group to the next? היה אוכל
בחבורה זו ורוצה לאכול בחבורה
אחרת. Hayah Ochel Bachabura Zo V'rotzeh Le'echol Bachabura Acheret. You were eating
with one group and you wanted to go eat with another group.
Now the whole use of the phrase חבורה Chabura Rashi says specifically
is על פסחך, Al Peschecha, okay?
And now once you started eating with one group you're actually not
allowed to take a פסח Pesach מחבורה לחבורה. Michabura Lechabura. So היה
אוכל Hayah Ochel must mean you intended to eat with one group.
And then you changed your mind and you wanted to eat with
another group. הרשות בידו. Ha-reshut biyado. So you want to now be
say oh I have to טובל Tovel my כלים Keilim to be
to be together with this group. Somehow you had that in your
head that you have to טובל Tovel your כלים Keilim new whenever
you're joining a group. So maybe again that was your practice. Whenever
you're about to join a פסח Pesach group you bring your כלים
to the מקוה because you want it all to be טהור for
the פסח. Pesach. So now you switched groups. This was before the
שחיטה. Shechita. Now you switched groups so you had to want to
bring them again. So that type of a thing you can go
ahead well I don't know because it's on יום טוב Yom Tov,
or maybe it's שבת before יום טוב. Yom Tov, But anyway okay,
so that type of thing you're allowed to do. Now I have
to tell you, on the one hand okay this is obvious, it's
not a הלכתית טבילה. Halachic Tevilah. But given all of the concerns
that were raised, maybe you'll come to carry it, maybe it'll look
like you're מתקן. Metaken. Every single one of those concerns is just
as relevant in this case although you're doing it for a נארש
Narish purpose, right? So it again gets to the point that the
גמרא Gemara raised before that the concerns are just as relevant but
somehow in some formalistic way this isn't a הלכתית טבילה. Halachic Tevilah.
And since it isn't a הלכתית טבילה Halachic Tevilah it's going to
be allowed. The same way there's no obvious difference whether it became
טמא ערב יום טוב Yom Tov? or on יום טוב, Yom Tov.
or whether it became טמא with an אב הטומאה Av HaTumah or
a שני לטומאה. Sheni LeTumah. And somehow still we allow some and
we don't allow others. So it's very hard to understand given the
nature of whatever the concerns were why we make these distinctions, but
again since technically this is not really a טבילה Tevilah that does
anything we allow it. Okay, so that was an interesting little digression
about טבילה. Tevilah. Now we get back to what I would say
is some more
direct יום טוב Yom Tov? issues and at the biblical level as
well. And here's a very famous debate around יום טוב. Yom Tov.
בית שמאי אומרים, Beit Shammai Omrim, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says,
מביאים שלמים ואין סומכין עליהם. Mevi'im Shelamim Ve'ein Somchin Aleihem. You can
bring שלמים Shelamim on יום טוב, Yom Tov. free will offerings, right?
Which you eat the meat because then you're going to eat the
meat so that's a צורך יום טוב. Tzorech Yom Tov. But you
cannot do סמיכה Semicha on them. סמיכה Semicha is putting your hands
on the קרבנות. Korbanot. And the problem with that is is that
you're resting your weight on the קרבן Korban on the animal. It's
like using an animal on יום טוב, Yom Tov, a rabbinic concern.
אבל לא עולות. Aval Lo Olot. You cannot bring a burnt offering
because you don't get any food benefit from it. ובית הלל אומרים
U-veit Hillel Omrim מביאים שלמים
ועולות. Mevi'im Shelamim Ve'olot. You can bring שלמים Shelamim which בית שמאי
Beit Shammai didn't disagree but you can also bring עולות Olot even
though you won't eat from them. וסומכין עליהם. Ve-somchin Aleihem. And you
can do סמיכה Semicha on them. You can rest your weight on
them. So at this level the debate is number one can you
bring an עולה Olah even though you won't be able to eat
from it? Is bringing a קרבן Korban a legitimate use to do
מלאכה Melacha on יום טוב? Yom Tov? And number two can you
do סמיכה? Semicha? Can you rest your weight on it? Is that
a concern or not? Now people might be familiar that this is
like one of the earliest debates, or maybe the earliest debate in
recorded debate in rabbinic history, right? And in the חגיגה Chagigah there's
a whole list of the נשיא Nasi and בית אב Beit Av
going back hundreds of years that were always debating this issue of
do you do סמיכה Semicha on שלמים Shelamim when you bring them
on יום טוב. Yom Tov So I really just have to comment
and say I don't know why of all things this was the
one thing that was debated. First of all it's a rabbinic point.
It's not, you know, the question of סמיכה. Semicha. The עולה Olah
might be biblical. Is that a מלאכה Melacha or not bringing an
עולה Olah on יום טוב? Yom Tov But the סמיכה Semicha is
a rabbinic point. And I don't know why of all things that's
the one that was debated. And it's also worth noting, since I
mentioned this earlier but I'll mention it again, how much all of
מסכת ביצה, Masechet Beitzah, almost all of מסכת ביצה Masechet Beitzah are
debates of בית הלל ובית שמאי. Beit Hillel Ve-veit Shammai. Right? If
you think about it, almost every single משנה Mishnah was a debate
of בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit Hillel Ve-veit Shammai, whether it's דאורייתא
De'oraita about carrying, bringing קרבנות, Korbanot, whether it's דרבנן about the egg
and about the עירוב תבשילין. Eruv Tavshilin. Pretty much every single thing
we've seen is a משנה בית הלל ובית שמאי. Mishnah Beit Hillel
Ve-veit Shammai. It's very, very rare that you have that, and this
is almost the entire מסכת. Masechet. So I don't know why it
is, but it seems that there's a lot of early material around
issues of יום טוב. Yom Tov. So I just note that without
really having a good explanation.
You're going to the obvious point that סמיכה Semicha is not מעכב.
Me'akev. סמיכה Semicha is not מעכב, Me'akev,
that's true.
Oh, yes, and that's why בית שמאי Beit Shammai says it's possible
to bring without doing סמיכה. Semicha. That is correct. Okay, so let's
say try to get try to refine exactly what this debate is.
אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, says עולא, Ulla, מחלוקת בשלמי חגיגה לסמוך ועולת
ראייה להקריב. Machloket Beshalmei Chagigah Lismoch Ve-olat Re'iyah Lehakriv. Which type of
שלמים Shelamim and which type of עולות Olot are we talking about?
So עולא Ulla says they're debating when בית הלל Beit Hillel says
you can bring שלמים Shelamim and בית שמאי... Beit Shammai... בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai both say you can bring
שלמים, Shelamim, they're talking about שלמי חגיגה. Shalmei Chagigah. Right? It says
every time the תורה Torah says you should make it like חג
להשם, Chag L'Hashem, right? חג המצות, Chag HaMatzot, חג הסוכות. Chag HaSukkot.
שלמי Shalmei because of the rejoicing of the חג, chag, and that's
an obligation to bring on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And if you
don't bring it on יום טוב, Yom Tov then you can bring
it on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So when is it that בית
שמאי Beis Shammai will concede that you can bring a שלמים shelomim
on יום טוב? Yom Tov, That's only for שלמי חגיגה. Shalmei Chagiga.
I should point out that there's one יום טוב Yom Tov. that
you have to bring it on יום טוב Yom Tov and you
can't bring it on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, which is שבועות. Shavuos.
שבועות. Shavuos. So if חג chag means שלמי חגיגה, Shalmei Chagiga, right,
everybody has to agree that you can bring שלמי חגיגה Shalmei Chagiga
on יום טוב. Yom Tov And that has two things: Number one
is it's a חיוב chiyuv of the day, and number two is
that it's that you eat שלמים, shelomim, so it's certainly something that
can be done on יום טוב. Yom Tov? Okay, although again, it
could be בדיעבד bediavad be done on חול המועד Chol HaMoed on
פסח Pesach and סוכות. Sukkos. So שלמי חגיגה Shalmei Chagiga is the
one that they both agree can be brought. And לסמוך, lismokh, the
debate is whether you can do סמיכה. semikhah. Now how about the
issue about what עולה olah does בית הלל Beis Hillel say you
can bring? Similarly, ועולת ראייה ליקרב. ve-olat re'iyah likarev. The debate about
the עולה olah is the עולת ראייה. olat re'iyah. When it says
יראה כל זכורך yeira'eh kol zekhurkha all your males should appear before
God, we are talking about a עולת ראייה, olat re'iyah, about an
עולה olah that is brought that is brought to show like to
bring your presence, ולא יראו פני ריקם, v-lo yeira'u fanai reikam, you
shall not see my face empty-handed, it's through the bringing of an
עולה. olah. Okay, so that again is an obligation of the חג
chag and that's where בית הלל Beis Hillel says you can bring
it and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says you cannot. Now I actually
a little bit misstated or before because what do you do on
if that what I said before was correct that you have to
bring it on שבועות Shavuos only on יום טוב Yom Tov itself,
then according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai how are you ever יוצא
yotzei ראייה re'iyah on יום טוב, Yom Tov on שבועות? Shavuos? Right?
You have to come שלוש רגלים, shalosh regalim, ולא יראו פני ריקם,
lo yeira'u fanai reikam, so you have to bring an עולה olah
and he doesn't let you bring an עולת ראייה olat re'iyah on
יום טוב. Yom Tov So the הלכה halacha is that the same
way on פסח Pesach and סוכות Sukkos you have days after the
first day יום טוב Yom Tov, to make it up if you
miss your שלמי חגיגה, Shalmei Chagiga, the חז"ל Chazal learned that the
same is true by שבועות. Shavuos. So according to בית שמאי Beis
Shammai you would never actually do your obligation of עולת ראייה Olat
Re'iyah on שבועות Shavuos itself. You would only do it in the
days after שבועות Shavuos that we learn out from the extra days
of פסח Pesach
and סוכות. Sukkos. Okay, so
there is opportunities for makeup even for a שבועות. Shavuos. So what
we think is the whole possibility of bringing קרבנות korbanot is the
קרבנות korbanot of the חג. chag. שלמי חגיגה Shalmei Chagiga everybody agrees
you can bring because it has the חיוב chiyuv of the חג
chag and you can eat from it. The whole debate is doing
סמיכה semikhah and עולת ראייה Olat Re'iyah where you're not eating from
it, that's the debate of בית הלל, Beis Hillel, בית שמאי: Beis
Shammai: do you bring it on the יום טוב Yom Tov, or
do you bring it on the days following יום טוב? Yom Tov
Now what's that debate about? דבית שמאי סברי De-Beis Shammai savrei וחגותם
אותו חג להשם, vachagosem oso chag Lashem, you should make it into
a festival for God. חגיגה אין, Chagigah in, so it's for חג,
chag, that what you have to do. עולת ראייה לא. Olat Re'iyah
lo. So the פשט P'shat understands that the double language of וחגותם
אותו חג vachagosem oso chag means on the חג chag itself, on
the יום טוב Yom Tov itself is when you bring the חגיגה
Chagiga but the עולה olah isn't mentioned, you don't bring the עולה.
olah. ובית הלל סברי U'Beis Hillel savrei and בית הלל Beis Hillel
holds להשם, Lashem, no, it says חג להשם. chag Lashem. כל דלהשם,
Kol de-Lashem, anything that is for להשם, Lashem, any קרבן, korban, or
not any קרבן, korban, but any any קרבן korban of of the
חג chag that is for להשם Lashem can be brought. אבל נדרים
ונדבות דברי הכל אין קרבים ביום טוב. Aval nedarim u-nedavot divrei hakol
ein krevim be-Yom Tov. But when it comes to free-will offerings that's
not related to the חג, chag, everybody would say you don't bring
it. Now I want to just remind you about putting this on
a larger context. You remember before we had a whole debate about
carrying on יום טוב Yom Tov. between בית הלל Beis Hillel and
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, right? So and the one way the גמרא
Gemara read it which seemed to be the way the גמרא Gemara
was going is do we say מתוך שהותרה לצורך הותרה נמי שלא
לצורך mitoch she-hutrah le-tzorech hutrah nami she-lo le-tzorech and the application was
if you bring an עולת נדבה olat nedavah on יום טוב Yom
Tov, are you do you get מלקות malkus or not? What says
you get מלקות malkus for בית שמאי Beis Shammai but not for
בית הלל. Beis Hillel. So although here the גמרא Gemara is saying
that even בית הלל Beis Hillel agrees you don't bring an עולת
נדבה, olat nedavah, it might be that בדיעבד bediavad if you did
bring it you would not have violated. Okay, so בית הלל's Beis
Hillel more lenient approach is consistent with an earlier גמרא Gemara idea
that בית הלל Beis Hillel holds of מתוך. mitoch And once you
can do שחיטה shechitah for food purposes, you can do it even
for עולה, olah, even for קרבנות, korbanot, and maybe even if you
did an עולת נדבה olat nedavah you wouldn't get מלקות. malkus. Whereas
בית שמאי Beis Shammai basically does not hold of מתוך mitoch, and
he only allows it for food and he only allows if you're
going to do it in the context of a קרבן, korban, he
only allows it if it is a שלמי חגיגה. Shalmei Chagiga. Let
me say one other word about that: why should בית שמאי Beis
Shammai not want you to bring any שלמים, shelomim, even a שלמי
נדבה? Shalmei Nedavah? I mean you're going to eat from it so
why is it different than just שחט shechting in my backyard? What,
I'm not going to eat from the entrails and the fat? I
wouldn't eat from the entrails and the fat anyway, so why can't
I just bring a שלמי נדבה? Shalmei Nedavah? Why only שלמי חגיגה?
Shalmei Chagiga? And the So I can't just bring a cow? I
can only שחט shecht a chicken? We had שחט-ing shecht cows before.
So it means that the difference is that that's only eating from
a שלמים shelamim is seen as the eating is seen as a
secondary intent. The primary purpose of a שלמים shelamim is still bringing
it as a קרבן, korban, or at least it's not the primary,
maybe it's some joint or it's eating it in the context of
a קרבן, korban, it's not just eating it because to fill my
stomach. Now again, that's quite funny because you would think if there's
any sense of joining the idea of שמחה simcha and אך אשר
יאכל לכל נפש ach asher ye'achel lechol nefesh on יום טוב, Yom
Tov bring the שלמי חגיגה shelami chagigah would be the best way
to eat meat on יום טוב, Yom Tov, right? So it is,
we should note that it is a little bit ironic that בית
שמאי Beis Shammai even if they don't hold of מתוך, mitoch according
to this, don't want you to bring a שלמים. shelamim. According to
this, even בית הלל Beis Hillel wouldn't want you to bring a
שלמים shelamim if it wasn't שלמי שמחה, shalmei simcha, if it was
just סתם stam a שלמים. shelamim. But again, again that's because presumably
a שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha is when you get those two coming
together. It's a שלמים, shelamim, but it's in the context of שמחת
החג simchat hachag and that brings it all together. But if it's
not a שלמי—well shalmei we'll get to שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha later,
we're talking here about שלמי חגיגה. shelami chagigah. So anyway, I'm digressing
too much. Let's get back. So it says right here, he says
that they debate the קרבנות korbanos of the חג, chag, but if
it's simple נדרים ונדבות, nedarim unedavos, דברי הכל divrei hakol אין קרבין
ביום טוב. ein krevin beYom Tov. Everybody would say you don't bring
it on יום טוב Yom Tov. because that is, even though you'll
eat some of the meat, that's not related to the חג chag
and as I said before, even if בית הלל Beis Hillel holds
of מתוך mitoch, and בדיעבד bedi'eved it might be okay, but certainly
לכתחילה lechatchila those you do not bring on יום טוב Yom Tov.
even though you'll eat from the meat because fundamentally it's about bringing
a קרבן. korban. וכן אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, V'chen amar Rav
Adda bar Ahava, נדרים ונדבות אין קרבין ביום טוב. nedarim unedavos ein
krevin beYom Tov. Free will sacrifice—nobody says you can bring on the
יום טוב. Yom Tov The whole issue here is the עולה olah
and the שלמים shelamim that is related specifically to the חג. chag.
מיתיבי Meisivei says, asks you on this. אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר,
Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על
עולה שאינה של יום טוב lo necheleku Beis Shammai uBeis Hillel al
olah she'eina shel Yom Tov שאינה קריבה ביום טוב. she'eina kreiva beYom
Tov. So nobody disagreed that if the עולה olah was not an
obligation of יום טוב, Yom Tov it wasn't an עולת ראיה olat
re'iyah that you do not bring it. That has nothing—it's, A, not
related to יום טוב Yom Tov. and B, you don't eat from
it. So everybody agrees an unrelated עולה olah you do not bring.
Okay, so far it's what we've been saying. על שלמים שהן של
יום טוב שקריבין ביום טוב. al shelamim shehein shel Yom Tov shekreivin
beYom Tov. But here he says different than we said before. If
it's a שלמים shelamim that is of יום טוב, Yom Tov, meaning
a שלמי חגיגה, shalmei chagigah, it also by the way would include
a שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha which we'll see about, even בית שמאי
Beis Shammai would agree, everybody agrees you do bring it on יום
טוב. Yom Tov על מה נחלקו, al mah necheleku, what did they
debate? על עולה שהיא של יום טוב ושלמים שאינם של יום טוב,
al olah shehi shel Yom Tov ushelamim she'einam shel Yom Tov, if
the עולה olah was a יום טוב עולה, Yom Tov olah, which
is עולת ראיה, olat re'iyah, and שלמים shelamim which is not related
to יום טוב. Yom Tov שבית שמאי אומרים לא יביא ובית הלל
אומרים יביא. sheBeis Shammai omrim lo yavi uBeis Hillel omrim yavi. בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says you can't bring and בית הלל Beis Hillel
says you can bring. So in which way is this different than
what we said before? How it's different is that this has בית
הלל Beis Hillel saying you can even bring שלמים שאינם של יום
טוב. shelamim she'einam shel Yom Tov. And he said before that even
בית הלל Beis Hillel would agree that if it's not יום טוב
Yom Tov related you cannot bring. And we're not even getting to
that yet. That also seems subtly to be part of the difference
as well that he says there was no debate of a שלמים
shelamim that was של יום טוב, shel Yom Tov, which might mean
that they would also agree you could do סמיכה. semicha. But we're
not focusing right now on סמיכה, semicha, we're just focusing on the
bringing of it. If you have the shift, like the tannaitic material
has been re-emphasized. Right. Well, we'll get back to the סמיכה semicha
later, but we first want to figure out the basic parameters. So
the first approach of עולא Ulla was they're only discussing the קרבנות
korbanos of the חג. chag. So even when they discuss whether or
not you do סמיכה semicha on a שלמים shelamim etc., they're only
the קרבנות korbanos of the חג chag and if it's not of
the חג, chag, even בית הלל Beis Hillel would say you cannot
bring it. And this approach says no, that actually they're also—that's true
about the עולה, olah, nobody would think you could bring an עולה
olah that's not of the חג, chag, but when it comes to
שלמים, shelamim, like I was saying before, why should שלמים shelamim be
a problem? So that also is part of the debate. בית הלל
Beis Hillel says it's fine to bring a שלמים shelamim even if
it's not a שלמים shelamim of the חג. chag. So how do
you deal with that? So the גמרא Gemara says תרגימא ואימא הכי.
targima v'eima hachi. All right, reinterpret it. It's not just going to
be reinterpreting, we're going to change the text. אמר רבי שמעון בן
אלעזר לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על עולה ושלמים שאינם של
יום טוב שאין קרבין ביום טוב. Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar lo
necheleku Beis Shammai uBeis Hillel al olah ushelamim she'einam shel Yom Tov
she'ein kreivin beYom Tov. So we're going to switch the text and
we're going to have him say what עולא Ulla said. If it's
not a יום טוב קרבן, Yom Tov korban, even a שלמים, shelamim,
everybody agrees it cannot be brought. ועל שלמים שהן של יום טוב
שקרבין ביום טוב. ve'al shelamim shehein shel Yom Tov shekreivin beYom Tov.
And everybody agrees that if it is two things that are good,
it's שלמים shelamim and it's related to the חג, chag, that it
can be brought. על מה נחלקו על עולה שהיא של יום טוב.
al mah necheleku al olah shehi shel Yom Tov. The only thing
they debated about bringing, as opposed to סמיכה, semicha, was the עולה
olah that was a יום טוב עולה. Yom Tov olah. שבית שמאי
אומרים לא יביא ובית הלל אומרים יביא. sheBeis Shammai omrim lo yavi
uBeis Hillel omrim yavi. So basically what we did is we cut
and pasted in order to get it to be the same as
עולא. Ulla. But the simple sense of that ברייתא braita has that
בית הלל Beis Hillel would allow you to bring even a שלמים
שאינם של יום טוב shelamim she'einam shel Yom Tov for the reason
I said before that at least for שלמים shelamim you're eating the
meat. So that right now is the question: when בית הלל Beis
Hillel lets you bring a—nobody thinks that בית הלל Beis Hillel lets
you bring an עולה olah that's not related because you're not eating
the meat and it's not related. The question is would בית הלל
Beis Hillel let you bring a שלמים? shelamim? רב יוסף אמר *Rav
Yosef amar*, now רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*'s response to this ברייתא braita
*braita* that contradicted עולא Ulla *Ulla* was, תנאי tnai, שקלת מעלמא *Tannai
shakalat me'alma*? What, you're just grabbing תנאים *tannaim* out of the air?
Meaning, okay, you found a תנא *tanna* that disagreed with עולא Ulla
*Ulla*, it's not like there are no other תנאים *tannaim* in the
world. So תנאי tnai *tannai*, it's a debate of תנאים *tannaim*. דתניא
*Detanya*, we learn in a ברייתא Braita. *braita*, שלמים Shelomim הבאים מחמת
יום טוב Yom Tov. ביום טוב *Shlamim ha-ba'im machmat Yom Tov be-Yom
Tov*. שלמים Shelomim *Shlamim* that come for the sake of יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, שלמי חגיגה Shelomei Chagiga *shalmei chagiga* or שלמי
שמחה Shelomei Simcha, *shalmei simcha*, as we'll see, that are brought on
יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*. בית שמאי Beit Shammai אומרים סומך
עליהם מערב יום טוב Yom Tov. ושוחטן ביום טוב *Beit Shammai omrim
somech aleihem me-erev Yom Tov ve-shochtan be-Yom Tov*. Do the סמיכה semichah.
*smicha* on ערב יום טוב Yom Tov *erev Yom Tov*, because you
can't do it on יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. ושוחטן ביום
טוב *Ve-shochtan be-Yom Tov*, but those you can bring on יום טוב
Yom Tov *Yom Tov*. ובית הלל אומרים סומך עליהם ביום טוב ושוחטן
ביום טוב *U-Beit Hillel omrim somech aleihem be-Yom Tov ve-shochtan be-Yom Tov*.
No, you can even do the סמיכה *smicha*. So meaning what they're
debating is a יום טוב Yom Tov שלמים Shelomim, *Yom Tov shlamim*.
Like everybody agrees that you can bring it, the question is, can
you do סמיכה *smicha*? אבל *Aval*, says the ברייתא Braita *braita*, נדרים
ונדבות *nedarim u-nedavot*, freewill sacrifices that are not related to יום טוב
Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, דברי הכל אין קרבין ביום טוב *divrei ha-kol
ein krevin be-Yom Tov*. Everybody would agree they could not be brought.
Okay? And that supports עולא *Ulla*'s contention. So here we have the
issue. עולה Olah *Olah* that is not related to יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*, everybody agrees you cannot bring. That's no question. Okay?
אבל *Aval*, again I reminded you that we said earlier that according
to בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel*, if you did bring an
עולה Olah *olah*, it could be that you don't get מלקות *malkut*
because of מתוך *mitoch*. But certainly everybody agrees לכתחילה *lechatchila* if an
עולה olah *olah* is not related to יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom
Tov* you don't bring it. Everybody also agrees that the debate of
בית הלל ובית שמאי Beis Hillel uBeis Shammai *Beit Hillel ve-Beit Shammai*
about an עולה *olah* is about the עולת ראיה *olat re'iya*, the
עולה *olah* that you have to bring. That בית הלל Beit Hillel
*Beit Hillel* would say the fact that you have to bring it
allows it to be brought, חג chag להשם *chag l-Hashem*, and בית
שמאי *Beit Shammai* says no, bring it tomorrow. Okay, that's the debate
that we all agree on relating to עולה *olah*, the עולה *olah*
of עולת ראיה *olat re'iya*. The question is, what's the issue of
the שלמים Shelomim, *shlamim* that they both are conceding can be brought?
Is it only שלמי חגיגה Shelomei Chagiga. *shalmei chagiga* and every other
שלמים Shelomim *shlamim* that's not יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* related
everybody agrees cannot be brought, or does בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit
Hillel* go so far to allow you to bring even שלמים Shelomim,
*shlamim* that is not related to יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*
because in the end of the day you're going to be eating
the food? Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this:
והני תנאי tnai כי הני תנאי *Ve-hani Tannai ki-hani Tannai*. These תנאים
*tannaim* that are debating the question of bringing a שלמים Shelomim *shlamim*
that is not a יום טוב Yom Tov. שלמים Shlamim, *Yom Tov
shlamim* but bringing it on יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* is
like the following debate of תנאים *tannaim*. דתניא *Detanya*, we learn in
a ברייתא Braita? *braita*, אין מביאין תודה בחג המצות מפני חמץ שבה
Ein mevi'in Toda b'Chag HaMatzot mipnei chametz she'ba. *Ein mevi'in toda be-Chag
ha-Matzot mipnei chametz she-bah*. Okay, that's pretty obvious. You don't bring a
תודה Toda, *toda*, which is a type of a שלמים Shlamim, *shlamim*
but it's only eaten for one day and it comes with loaves
of מצה *matzah* and חמץ chametz. *chametz*, and it's specifically for the
sake of thanksgiving. You don't bring it on פסח Pesach *Pesach* because
you can't bring the חמץ chametz *chametz* that's part of that קרבן
korban, *korban*. ולא בעצרת מפני שהוא יום טוב Velo Be'atzeret mipnei shehu
Yom Tov, *Ve-lo be-Atzeret mipnei she-hu Yom Tov*. But guess what? You
also can't bring it on שבועות Shavuot, *Shavuot* because there's no חול
המועד Chol HaMoed. *chol ha-mo'ed* on שבועות Shavuos *Shavuot* and you can't
bring it on יום טוב Yom Tov? *Yom Tov*, which reflects the
fact that a שלמים Shlamim *shlamim* that is not מחמת יום טוב
Yom Tov, *machmat Yom Tov*, that is not connected directly to יום
טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, cannot be brought on יום טוב Yom
Tov *Yom Tov*, right? Because there's no way to bring a תודה
Toda, *toda* on שבועות Shavuos *Shavuot*. So, אבל מביא אדם תודתו בחג
הסוכות Aval meivi adam todato beChag HaSukkot, *Aval mevi adam todato be-Chag
ha-Sukkot*. If you have a תודה Toda, *toda* you need to bring,
bring it on סוכות Sukkot *Sukkot*. Okay. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר
*Rabbi Shimon omer*, that's the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says, הרי הוא אומר *harei hu omer*, the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* says, בחג המצות ובחג השבועות ובחג הסוכות beChag HaMatzot ubeChag
HaShavuot ubeChag HaSukkot. *be-Chag ha-Matzot u-be-Chag ha-Shavu'ot u-be-Chag ha-Sukkot*. So it connects
all of these three קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. Okay, all three חגים *chaggim*,
right? ולא יראה פני ריקם *Ve-lo ye-ra'eh panai reikam*. כל שבא בחג
המצות בא בחג השבועות ובחג הסוכות *Kol she-ba be-Chag ha-Matzot ba be-Chag
ha-Shavu'ot u-be-Chag ha-Sukkot*. Anything that can be brought on פסח Pesach *Pesach*
can be brought on שבועות Shavuot, *Shavuot* and סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkot*. וכל
שלא בא בחג המצות *Ve-chol she-lo ba be-Chag ha-Matzot*—and if it can't
be brought on פסח Pesach, *Pesach*—אינו בא בחג השבועות ובחג הסוכות *eino
ba be-Chag ha-Shavu'ot u-be-Chag ha-Sukkot*, cannot be brought on שבועות Shavuos, *Shavuot*
and סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkot*, which sounds like he's saying—the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
going to try to understand what he means—but it sounds like he's
saying since you can't bring a תודה Toda *toda* on פסח Pesach?
*Pesach*, you can't bring it on סוכות Sukkot, *Sukkot* either. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say, 'What? You can't bring a קרבן korban,
*korban* on חול המועד סוכות Chol HaMoed Sukkot, *chol ha-mo'ed Sukkot*? Like,
why not?' But that's what it sounds like he's saying. By the
way, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* switches the גרסא *girsa*, and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot*
says it really should read: כל שבא בחג המצות ובחג השבועות Kol
sheba beChag HaMatzot ubeChag HaShavuot, בא בחג הסוכות ba beChag HaSukkot, *Kol
she-ba be-Chag ha-Matzot u-be-Chag ha-Shavu'ot ba be-Chag ha-Sukkot*. וכל שאינו בא בחג
המצות ובחג השבועות *Ve-chol she-eino ba be-Chag ha-Matzot u-be-Chag ha-Shavu'ot*, if you
can't bring it on פסח Pesach. *Pesach* and on שבועות Shavuot *Shavuot*,
you also can't bring it on סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkot*. Okay, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* will try to figure out what that means. We'll put
that aside for a moment. Yes? Is this the only קרבן korban.
*korban* that has חמץ chametz, *chametz* besides this? Yes, תודה Toda *toda*.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. So now, okay, so but we still so far
do not seem to have debated the fact that you cannot bring
a תודה Toda, *toda* on שבועות Shavuos, *Shavuot* because it is a
שלמים shelamim *shlamim* not related to the חג chag. *chag*. רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון אומר *Rabbi Elazar be-Rabbi Shimon omer*: מביא אדם תודתו בחג
הסוכות Mevi adam todato b'chag ha'sukkot ויוצא בו ידי חובתו משום שמחה
Simcha ואין יוצא yotze בו משום חגיגה chagiga, *mevi adam todato be-Chag
ha-Sukkot ve-yotzei bo yedei chovato mishum simcha ve-ein yotzei bo mishum chagiga*.
Now this also does not seem to be any issue that was
debated before. He's just pointing out that if you brought your תודה
Toda *toda* on סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkot*, which is when everybody says you
can bring it, you fulfill your obligation of שמחה Simcha *simcha* but
not of חגיגה chagiga *chagiga*. What does that mean? It means the
following. And I was maybe throwing it in before a little bit
too soon. There are two types of שלמים shelamim *shlamim* that are
related to יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. One is a שלמי
חגיגה Shelomei Chagiga, *shalmei chagiga*... A שלמי חגיגה shalmei chagigah, is based
on the פסוק pasuk of וחגתם אתו חג, V'chagotem oto chag, what
it means to do a חג chag. is to bring the שלמים
shelamim that represent the חג. The other is a שלמי שמחה, Shelomei
Simcha. which is a קיום kiyum of the פסוק Pasuk of ושמחת
אתה וביתך, V'samachta ata u'veitecha, like שמחת יום טוב. Simchat Yom Tov.
Now, the fact that it's a קיום kiyum of שמחה Simcha has
mostly to do with the fact that you're going to eat the
meat. Meaning, let's say you brought a שלמים shelamim and you didn't
eat the meat, are you really יוצא or not? Or let's say
somebody invited you to eat from their שלמי שמחה. Shelomei Simcha There,
it's much more about eating the meat than about bringing the קרבן,
korban, but specifically the meat of a קרבן, korban. not just סתם
stam meat, but the meat in the context of God and the
meat in the context of a קרבן. korban That's what a שלמי
שמחה Shelomei Simcha, is, and that's the idea of when we learn
in סוכות Sukkot, that the מצוה mitzvah of שמחה Simcha applies throughout
the רגל regel and so on, specifically it's in the context of
שלמי שמחה, Shelomei Simcha, which is why חז"ל Chazal say that nowadays
that we don't have קרבנות, Korbanot? how do you translate what that
שמחה Simcha means? So it says men is for with wine, women
is with clothes, kids are with nuts. That famous גמרא Gemara about
that, by the way, which is, the רמב"ם'ס Rambam's גירסא girsa says
nowadays it's with meat and wine, but that's not our גירסא girsa
in the גמרא. Gemara Our גירסא girsa in the גמרא Gemara is
just nowadays it's with wine, which leads to the whole question of
whether people feel you have to have פליישיגס fleishigs on יום טוב
Yom Tov. or not. Okay, but that's the idea of שלמי שמחה,
Shelomei Simcha which is yes, it's bringing a שלמים, shelamim but it's
much more focusing on the eating of the meat than on the
bringing of it, which leads to this question of, can you fulfill
your obligation of שלמי שמחה Shelomei Simcha, by a standing obligation you
had already? You had obligated yourself, you took some trip, it was
a dangerous journey, you made a נדר, neder, you took some obligation
to bring a קרבן תודה, Korban Toda,
and you set aside and you sanctified an animal for your קרבן
תודה. Korban Toda. Now, you waited until the רגל regel to bring
it, because that's when you're going up to ירושלים Yerushalayim anyway. Can
you use this קרבן תודה, Korban Toda, which is a type of
a שלמים, shelamim and bring it and say, "Ah, I'll get two
for the price of one, I'll bring my תודה, Toda I'll eat
the meat, it'll count as a שלמי שמחה," Shelomei Simcha, or "I'll
bring it and it'll count as a שלמי חגיגה"? shalmei chagigah, And
the answer is, you can get two for the price of one
for שלמי שמחה, Shelomei Simcha, but not for שלמי חגיגה. shalmei chagigah
Why? Because by שלמי שמחה, Shelomei Simcha? as we said, it's not
so much about bringing the קרבן, korban it's more about eating meat
that was brought as a קרבן. korban So therefore, it's not like
there's no problem. I fulfill my obligation of a תודה, Toda. and
then I use the meat and I'm doing also my obligation of
שמחה Simcha on the רגל. regel. Whereas by שלמי חגיגה, shalmei chagigah.
it's an obligation to bring a קרבן חגיגה, Korban Chagiga, and you
cannot fulfill one obligation with another obligation. If you're going to, if
you have a standing obligation, you can only fill it from something
that is not already pre-assigned to satisfy a pre-existing obligation. So that's
what he says. מביא אדם תודתו בחג הסוכות ויוצא בה חובתו משום
שמחה. v'yotzei bah chovato mishum simcha. When you eat from your תודה,
Toda, that counts as your מצוה mitzvah of שמחה on יום טוב.
Yom Tov It's שמחה from the קרבן korban that was a שלמים
shelamim that was brought on יום טוב, Yom Tov. and there the
obligation was more the eating and not the bringing. ואין יוצאין בה
משום חגיגה, V'ein yotzin bah mishum chagiga, but you don't fulfill your
obligation for חגיגה, chagiga because you can't use one obligation to satisfy
another obligation.
Okay, and the פסח Pesach which is like a שלמים, shelamim right?
What about שלמי שמחה? shalmei simchah Because the eating is...
Yeah, except that the פסח Pesach was brought on, was שחט shachted
on ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. And actually, you have to actually bring
the קרבן Korban. on יום טוב itself, although you're right, it's a
little bit funny based on the way I framed it why that's
true, but you do have to bring the קרבן Korban, on יום
טוב itself. It has to be somehow, it's not just eating meat,
it's meat that connects to a קרבן korban. that connects to the
חג. But it's true, but it's a good point, but yes, if
you שחט shachted it ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, it won't work. Okay,
yes, and חגיגה chagiga on פסח, Pesach,
isn't the eating important because you're supposed to be full before you
eat the פסח?
Pesach Yes,
so that's another function that is served by the חגיגה chagiga. that
comes with the פסח. Pesach? That is true. The חגיגה chagiga that
comes with the פסח Pesach? is brought on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach,
so it's a different type of a חגיגה. chagigah It's not this
חגיגה chagigah which is brought on יום טוב itself. Okay. Alright, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this,
where are we?
Okay, so now that doesn't seem relevant to our question either. The
only thing that seems relevant to our issue was can you bring
the תודה toda on שבועות, Shavuot which everybody seems to agree that
you cannot, which seems to agree that you don't bring שלמים shelamim
that are not related to the רגל regel on the רגל. regel.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with it, how it tries
to say that this ties into our debate. אמר מר, Amar mar,
so that's a way of saying let's go back and unpack the
ברייתא Braita that we just quoted. אין מביאין תודה toda בחג המצות
מפני חמץ Chametz, שבה.
You don't bring it on חג המצות Chag HaMatzot because of the
חמץ. פשיטא, Pshita, of course not! אמר רב אדא בריה דרב יצחק
ואמרי לה רב שמואל בר אבא הכא בארבעה עשר עסקינן. Amar Rav
Adda brei d'Rav Yitzchak v'amrei lah Rav Shmuel bar Abba hacha b'arba'ah
asar askinan.
We're talking about not even bringing it on the fourteenth, that you
can't bring it. Why not? You can eat the חמץ at least
to the beginning of the day. קסבר אין מביאין קדשים לבית הפסול.
Kasavar ein mevi'im kodashim l'veit ha'pasul. You do not bring sacrifices to
become invalid. You don't bring sacrifices in a context where it'll more
make them susceptible or increase the likelihood that they'll be invalid. If
you bring a תודה toda the beginning of the morning of the
fourteenth, you have very little time to eat all the חמץ, and
you're running the risk that not the meat will become פסול, pasul,
but at least the loaves of bread which are also part of
the sacrifice. sacrifices will become invalid, will have to be נותר Notar
and have to be burned because you'll stop being able to eat
them as soon as midday hits, which is by the way the
reason we don't say מזמור לתודה Mizmor Letoda on ערב פסח, Erev
Pesach, and why we don't say it on פסח Pesach, because of
the חמץ, so you don't even say it on ערב פסח. Erev
Pesach. Okay, the... so that's number one. When it says not on
פסח, Pesach it means even ערב פסח. Erev Pesach. ולא בעצרת מפני
שהוא יום טוב, and you can't bring it on עצרת Atzeret on
שבועות Shavuot, because it's יום טוב. So that clearly ties into our
discussion. קסבר נדרים ונדבות אין קרבין ביום טוב, Kasavar nedarim unedavot ein
krevin beYom Tov, that
that makes it clear that a שלמים, even a שלמים, if it's
not related to the יום טוב, if it's something else like a
תודה, toda cannot be brought on יום טוב, which is like עולא
wanted to say that both בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel ve-Beit
Shammai, agree that you do not bring unrelated שלמים on יום טוב.
אבל מביא אדם תודתו בחג הסוכות, but you can bring it on
סוכות. Sukkot, אימת? Eimas? When does this mean? אילימא ביום טוב עצמו,
Ilima beYom Tov atzmo, if you mean יום טוב itself, והאמרת ולא
בעצרת מפני שהוא יום טוב? veha'amart velo be'Atzeret mipnei shehu Yom Tov?
So this is pretty straightforward. You already said we can't bring it
on שבועות Shavuot. because it's
יום טוב. אלא בחולו של מועד. Ela beCholo Shel Moed. Fine. So
far, very straightforward. Now let's get to the more slightly more complicated
parts of that ברייתא. braita רבי שמעון אומר הרי הוא אומר, Rabbi
Shimon omer hareihu omer, the פסוק says בחג המצות ובחג השבועות ובחג
הסוכות. כל שבא בחג המצות ובחג השבועות, kol sheba beChag HaMatzot ubeChag
HaShavuot, I'll read this תוספות's Tosafot גרסה Girsa which works better, כל
שבא בחג המצות ובחג השבועות, if you can bring it on those
two ימים טובים, Yamim Tovim, בא בחג הסוכות, you can bring it
on סוכות. Sukkot. וכל שלא בא בחג המצות ובחג השבועות, Vechol shelo
ba beChag HaMatzot ubeChag HaShavuot, אינו
בא בחג
הסוכות. eino ba beChag HaSukkot. Okay?
And if you can't bring it on פסח Pesach, and שבועות, Shavuot,
you can't bring it
on
סוכות, Sukkot, even on חול המועד סוכות, Chol HaMoed Sukkot which is
crazy. So מתיב לה רב זירא, Masif lah Rav Zeira, רב זירא
Rav Zeira asked on this: השתא שלוסי מסלטינן? Hashta shulusei mesaltinan? I
don't get it says רב זירא. Rav Zeira. We can gather wood
from the forest to make a fire on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed,
You can do things which really are, you know, מלאכה related as
long as they are somehow, you know, within the confines, within the
parameters of חול המועד, Chol HaMoed. but you have a lot a
lot of latitude in what you can do on חול המועד. Chol
HaMoed, ונדרים ונדבות מיבעיא? Venedarim unedavot mibaya? And you're telling me that
you can't bring certain types of קרבנות? Korbanot I mean, what a
better time to bring קרבנות korbanot than on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed
right? So you're really telling me you can't bring a תודה toda,
on חול המועד סוכות Chol HaMoed Sukkot, just because you can't bring
it on
פסח? Pesach So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says you're right.
That's not what he was talking about. I mean, it sounded like
that, but that's not what he was talking about. בהקרבה כולי עלמא
לא פליגי דשרי. Behakrava kulei alma lo pligi desharei.
Bring your תודה toda, on חול המועד Chol HaMoed סוכות, Sukkot nobody
debates that. That's not what he was talking about. כי פליגי למיקם
עליה בבל תאחר. Ki pligi lemakam aleih beval te'acher.
And what אביי Abaye says here is, and רש"י says he's not
just making like an אוקימתא Ukimta for this one line, he's really
telling you what the whole point of this whole ברייתא was. Like
ask yourself, what was the point of this ברייתא? What was its
basic focus? And אביי Abaye says the basic focus was the question
of בל תאחר. Bal Te'acher. Right, the תורה Torah says כי תדור
נדר לה' אלוהיך לא תאחר
לשלמו. Ki tidor neder l'Hashem Elokecha lo te'acher leshalmo. You cannot postpone
satisfying your obligations to God, which means if you... if you made
a נדר Neder bringing a קרבן. And the question is חז"ל Chazal
understand that that's related to the idea of the רגלים Regalim because
if on the רגלים Regalim when you come to the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, which is your greatest opportunity to satisfy your obligations. And
the assumption generally is, although we'll see in a minute not everybody
agrees, that you have a cycle of the רגלים Regalim to bring
it. The question is when do you start counting the cycle? Is
it שלא כסדרן shelo kesidran or only כסדרן? kesidran? Is it once
there've been three רגלים Regalim and you did not bring your קרבן,
you are over on בל תאחר, Bal Te'acher, or only once you've
gone through the cycle in the norm if starting from the beginning,
starting from פסח? Pesach And that's what is being debated here. You...
it's a scenario where he says the whole ברייתא is talking about
the בל תאחר Bal Te'acher question. And it's talking about a scenario
that you made a נדר Neder to bring a תודה. toda, And
the question is Joe, move your foot here, you're on the wire
here, thank you. You made a נדר Neder to bring a תודה,
and the question is when... when is your opportunity to bring it
so you don't transgress בל תאחר? Bal Te'acher? So the first opinion
said, gotta bring it on סוכות. Sukkot, You can't bring it on
פסח, Pesach you can't bring it on שבועות, you gotta bring it
on סוכות. Sukkot And the implication being if you didn't bring it
on the first סוכות, Sukkot, you're over on בל תאחר, Bal Te'acher,
right? If you... if you went through פסח and שבועות and now
it's סוכות, Sukkot, this is your one and final opportunity to bring
it without being over on בל תאחר. Bal Te'acher. Now, it's in
that context, what does רבי שמעון שזורי say? So let's take a...
רבי שמעון says. What does רבי שמעון say? So it says
תנא קמא סבר שלוש רגלים אמר רחמנא אפילו שלא כסדרן, Tanna Kamma
savar shalosh regalim amar Rachmana afilu shelo kesidran, that you have three
רגלים Regalim to bring it and without that you're over. So... so
you won't be able to bring it on פסח, you won't be
able to bring it on שבועות, you better bring it on... you
better bring it on סוכות. Sukkot And if you don't bring it
on סוכות, Sukkot you blew it and it doesn't matter what order.
סוכות Sukkot. is the one רגל Regel you have a chance. Now
of course what you could do is when you go up for
שבועות you could bring it after שבועות, when you go up for
פסח you could bring it a day earlier or a day later
or something like that. But that's the context. the one רגל *Regal*
to bring it is פסח *Pesach*, is סוכות Sukkot *Sukkos*. Right. אפילו
שלא כסדרן *Afilu shelo
kesidran*. Right. So רב שמעון סבר *Rav Shimon savar*, now רב שמעון
*Rav Shimon* holds כסדרן אין שלא כסדרן לא *kesidran in shelo kesidran
lo*, only כסדרן *kesidran*. And how does he read it? He reads
it the following: He says, if you didn't bring it כל שלא
בא בחג המצות ובחג השבועות *kol shelo ba beChag HaMatzos uBechag HaShavuos*,
if you didn't bring it on פסח *Pesach* and on שבועות *Shavuos*,
then you better bring it, then you know then אינו בא *eino
ba*, you know well how do you read the אינו בא *eino
ba*?
You'll be over, I guess you'd read it if you do not
bring it on then סוכות Sukkot *Sukkos*. But if you but right
but if you did meaning but if but meaning it had to
have been that order is the way he reads it. It's still
a little hard to fit into the words.
But it's determined as as the first bar? Yeah. So if you
don't bring it on סוכות Sukkot *Sukkos* well you're not going to
be able to bring it on פסח *Pesach* or שבועות *Shavuos* you
know that already. Right. So it was your only chance. You have
to bring it on מועד *Moed*.
Right,
but that would be, that would be the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*
who says that you can only bring it on סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkos*
and if you don't bring it on סוכות Sukkot, *Sukkos* you're going
to wind up basically being over. That's essentially how we're reading the
תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma*. Whereas we're reading רב שמעון *Rav Shimon* who
says no, only if it first didn't bring it on פסח *Pesach*,
only if you went in the order. You first didn't bring it
on פסח *Pesach* and then you didn't bring it on שבועות *Shavuos*.
Let me just see how רש"י *Rashi* reads the exact words. Hold
on one minute. כל שבא בחג המצות *Kol sheba beChag HaMatzos*. Okay,
רש"י *Rashi* reads it, oh רש"י *Rashi* reads כל שבא בחג המצות
*kol sheba beChag HaMatzos*, meaning anything that was you were already obligated
to bring it. Oh that's the way he reads it. If you
were כל שבא בחג המצות ובחג השבועות *kol sheba beChag HaMatzos uBechag
HaShavuos*, if you were obligated to bring it already by פסח *Pesach*
and you had the opportunity to bring it by פסח *Pesach* and
the opportunity to bring it on שבועות *Shavuos*, then you better bring
it on סוכות Sukkot, *Sukkos*. Okay, because then it's the right order.
But if you didn't have the opportunity to bring it on פסח
*Pesach* and שבועות *Shavuos*, you didn't yet have your obligation then, then
אינו בא *eino ba*, you don't have to bring it this סוכות
Sukkot. *Sukkos* because you'll have another סוכות Sukkot *Sukkos* to bring it
and you'll be able to bring it later. Okay, still a very
funny way of articulating it, but that's the point. The first one
says you better bring it on סוכות Sukkot *Sukkos*, the order doesn't
matter, and the רב שמעון *Rav Shimon* says only if you had
the opportunity, only if the process started on פסח *Pesach* is your
last chance סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkos*. But otherwise you'll have another chance. כסדרן
אין שלא כסדרן לא *Kesidran in shelo kesidran lo*. רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אומר *Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon omer*. Now how about רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon*? That's a different point. מביא אדם
תודתו בחג הסוכות *Mevi adam todaso beChag HaSukkos*. You can bring your
תודה *toda* on סוכות Sukkot. *Sukkos*. Okay, now let's take a look.
And but still his focus of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar
beRabbi Shimon* was primarily whether you fulfill your obligation in terms of
whether you can use your תודה *toda* to satisfy other obligations. But
we're also going to read it in the context of this debate.
So let's take a look. He says if you want to address
בל תאחר bal te'acher. *bal se'acher*, you better bring your תודה *toda*
on סוכות Sukkot *Sukkos*. אימת *Eimas*? Now when is he talking about?
אילימא בחולו של מועד *Ilima bechollo shel moed*. If he says you
better bring your תודה *toda* on חולו של מועד סוכות Sukkot *chollo
shel moed Sukkos*, היינו תנא קמא *hainu Tanna Kamma*. So that's the
תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* who says you better bring it on, hey,
you can't bring it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* on שבועות *Shavuos*
etc., you only can bring it on חולו של מועד *chollo shel
moed*, you better bring it on חולו של מועד סוכות Sukkot. *chollo
shel moed Sukkos* and order doesn't matter. אלא ביום טוב *Ella beYom
Tov*. It must be if he's going out of his way and
saying bring it on סוכות Sukkot *Sukkos*, the only way he'd be
different than the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* is to tell you you
can even bring it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* דקסבר נדרים ונדבות
קרבים ביום טוב *dekasavar nedarim unedavos kreivin beYom Tov*. And he holds
that you can that you can even bring not related שלמים *shelamim*
on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Now if that's true that he holds
that you can bring it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, again it
seems a little forced because it seems like his only point there
was to discuss using a תודה *toda* to satisfy other obligations. But
because he repeated this line, you bring your תודה *toda* on סוכות
Sukkot *Sukkos*, and we want to make that line different, we're going
to say he means you can even bring it on יום טוב
*Yom Tov* of סוכות *Sukkos*. But if that's true, ומה שנא חג
הסוכות דנקט *umashna Chag HaSukkos denakat*? Then why mention סוכות *Sukkos*? You
could even bring it on שבועות *Shavuos*, right? Because you can bring
it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi
Elazar beRabbi Shimon*. So so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון לטעמיה *Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon leta'amei*. He's going according to
another position because remember we said the whole theme here was the
בל תאחר bal te'acher. *bal se'acher* theme. דתניא *Detanya* we taught in
a ברייתא *braisa*, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר *Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon
omer*, לא יאמר *lo yomar*. Don't say, it didn't have to say
חג הסוכות *Chag HaSukkos*. It could have just said בחג המצות ובחג
השבועות *beChag HaMatzos uBechag HaShavuos*, שבו כתוב ומדבר *shebo kasuv umedaber* because
the the list of the three רגלים regalim *Regalim* come in the
תורה Torah. *Torah* at the end of mentioning all three and at
the end of describing סוכות *Sukkos*. So why didn't it have to
repeat סוכות *Sukkos*? It could have just said חג המצות וחג השבועות
*Chag HaMatzos veChag HaShavuos*. A pretty funny question. So למה נאמר *lama
ne'emar*? Why did it repeat ובחג הסוכות *uBechag HaSukkos*? לומר שזה אחרון
*Lomar shezeh acharon*. To tell you that that's the last one, meaning
this is רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*'s position that you need כסדרן *kesidran*,
that you only are עובר over, *over* on בל תאחר bal te'acher
*bal se'acher* when חג הסוכות *Chag HaSukkos* comes at the end, when
you've been through all three starting with פסח *Pesach* and ending with
סוכות *Sukkos*. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר *Rabbi Elazar beRabbi Shimon omer*,
no, even more than that. לומר שזה גורם *Lomar shezeh gorem*. The
only one that matters is סוכות *Sukkos*. You don't need the order
and not only do you not need the order but you can
start in the middle. He says once סוכות *Sukkos* is the only
חג *Chag* where you have to bring where you have to bring
your קרבנות korbanot *korbanos* and if you don't you're עובר *over* on
בל תאחר bal te'acher. *bal se'acher*. So if you made a נדר
neder. *neder*... A day before סוכות and you passed over סוכות, you're
over on בל תאחר. If you
made it—סוכות's the deadline, right, regardless of when you made your נדר.
neder You made it a day after סוכות, you got a year
to bring it. You made it a day before סוכות, you got
סוכות to bring it. It ends by סוכות to tell you all
קרבנות korbanot. have to be brought by סוכות. Pretty fascinating. Maybe it's
evoking back that idea that סוכות also, you know, there are two
calendars in the תורה. Torah There's the one that starts with החודש
הזה לכם Hachodesh hazeh lachem where פסח is the beginning and the
רגלים always have פסח at the beginning, but then there's also one
which is that סוכות is תקופת השנה tekufat hashanah or בצאת השנה,
betzeit hashanah, right, it's the end of the year, right, and the
whole ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah association. So he says סוכות is always
the deadline for קרבנות korbanot: and that's why the תורה Torah repeated
סוכות. Now, how is this relevant to us? Because it's reading his
statement that he is saying you've got to bring it on סוכות,
so A, to make him different than the earlier opinions that said
you can also bring it on חול המועד סוכות, we have him
saying יום טוב of סוכות. But if it's יום טוב of סוכות
then you could also bring it on שבועות. No, because remember אביי
Abaye said the whole context here was בל תאחר. So what he's
saying is, sure, if you want to bring it on שבועות, גוזונט
א-הייט, gezunt aheit, but you have to bring it when סוכות comes
along, you have to bring it on סוכות. That is the deadline
date and there you can bring it even on the יום טוב
of סוכות. So what we have done is we've made this basically
about בל תאחר and we sort of have forced into רבי אלעזר
בן שמעון Rabbi Eleazar ben Shimon when he's saying סוכות to have
him say יום טוב of סוכות to be this earlier debate about
whether you can bring שלמים on יום טוב, whether שלמים that are
not related to the יום טוב can be brought on יום טוב.
But what the גמרא is primarily focused on in this context is
the issue of בל תאחר. So let's just repeat what we've got.
עולה cannot be brought
by בית הלל—בית שמאי בית הלל Beit Hillel debate bringing an עולה
on יום טוב. The גמרא claims and has not yet questioned the
idea that everybody agrees that at most an עולת ראייה, olat re'iyah,
but an עולה that's a נדר and נדבה nedavah not related to
יום טוב, everybody, even בית הלל would agree could not be brought.
Again, maybe you're—you're not עובר, maybe we say מתוך, but everybody would
agree cannot be brought. The big debate is the שלמים that they're
debating about סמיכה. But what type of שלמים are they assuming can
be brought on יום טוב? So certainly שלמים that are related to
the יום טוב, שלמי חגיגה, shalmei chagigah presumably שלמי שמחה shalmei simchah.
as well. The question is שלמים that are not related to the
יום טוב, can those be brought? So according to one version that's
part of the debate of בית הלל ובית שמאי, and according to
the other version, עולא's version, no, that even בית הלל would also
agree since it's not related to the יום טוב even though you're
going to eat from it cannot be brought. So that's the key
question—שלמים that are not related to the יום טוב. And now we've
said that's the debate going on in this ברייתא which discusses bringing
a תודה on חול המועד סוכות. That seems to be the idea.
Agree with that idea, you do not bring שלמים on יום טוב.
And then the last position of רבי שמעון that says bring it
on סוכות—רבי אלעזר בן שמעון—that we say means even on יום טוב
of סוכות that you can bring שלמים on יום טוב. Okay.
Everybody brings three קרבנות.
korbanot In general you bring three קרבנות: עולת ראייה, olat re'iyah, שלמי
חגיגה, chagigah. and שלמי שמחה. shalmei simchah, Correct. Okay. Now the last
point of רבי אלעזר בן שמעון: Rabbi Eleazar ben Shimon היוצא בו
משום שמחה ואינו יוצא בו משום חגיגה. hayotzei bo mishum simchah ve-eino
yotzei bo mishum chagigah. So פשיטא, pshita, it's obvious you can't use
your תודה to satisfy your חגיגה obligation. דבר שבחובה הוא, davar she-be-chovah
hu, וכל דבר שבחובה אינו בא אלא מן החולין. ve-chol davar she-be-chovah
eino ba ela min ha-chulin. Your שלמי חגיגה is an obligation, and
obligatory things can only be satisfied by things that are not already
sanctified. Again, the—I think the bigger חידוש chiddush is that you can
use it for your שלמי שמחה, but the גמרא says it's not
a חידוש chiddush at all that you can't use your תודה for
your שלמי חגיגה. No, לא צריכא, lo tzericha, no, צריכא דאף על
גב דפריש. tzericha de-af al gav de-parish. No, it's coming to tell
you you can't use your תודה for your שלמי חגיגה even if
you explicitly said that's what you wanted to do. What's the example?
כי דבעי מיניה רבי שמעון בן לקיש מרבי יוחנן ki de-ba'ei minei
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish me-Rabbi Yochanan האומר, ha-omer, somebody says, הרי עלי
תודה ואצא בה
ידי חגיגה. Harei alai toda ve-etze bah yedei chagigah. I will—here's this
תודה, I
accept
the obligation of a תודה, but I'm going to use it to
satisfy my חגיגה obligation. So maybe since you stipulated at the time
you took the vow you should be able to get two for
the price of one. Or somebody says, הריני נזיר ואגלח דמי מעשר
שני, Hareini nazir ve-agaleach demi ma'aser sheni, I'm going to be a
נזיר, nazir, but when I have to bring the קרבנות of the
נזיר, nazir, I'll use my מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. So you
stipulated at the time you took the vow that you're going to
do it with—using some other obligation to satisfy that קרבן. מהו, mahu,
what's the הלכה? אמר ליה, amar leih, he said back to him,
נדר ואינו יוצא, neder ve-eino yotzei, נזיר ואינו מגלח. nazir ve-eino megaleach.
The vow takes effect and you're obligated in the תודה, but you
can't use it for your חגיגה. And you're a נזיר, nazir, but
you can't use your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni money. Now, why not?
You might have said it's like a מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה.
matneh al mah she-katuv ba-Torah. You're trying to stipulate against the way
the whole, you know, the whole
תורה sort of sets up the system. But then you should say,
you know—so that's one way of formulating it, where we say the
תנאי, we reject the תנאי and the basic act is binding because
the תנאי was against—was contradicting הלכה. The way רש"י says it... is
as soon as you say the words הריני נזיר hareni nazir or
you say the words הרי עלי תודה harei alai toda that kicks
in. Those words already become effective. And then when you want to
say על מנת al menat that's already not even not relevant already.
Your obligation kicked in and your על מנת al menat doesn't do
anything. If that's true, then it's about the order. And then we're
going to the order if you reverse the order it might be
different. And that's what we're about to see in the next story.
Let's take a look. ההוא גברא דאמר להו hahu gavra de-amar lehu
a certain man said to people. Now אמר להו amar lehu the
context is he's on his deathbed and he's saying to all the
people that are around him and this has the הלכה of מתנת
שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera where the גמרא said a deathbed gift
sort of like a will is binding and it takes effect immediately
when the person says it so that it doesn't like in order
so to not to do upset the person who's who's there you
know with his illness and on the and about to die so
they gave it the power of being immediately binding. So he said
to the people around him הבו ליה ארבע מאה זוזי לפלוני havu
lei arba me'ah zuzie le-ploni give 400 zuz to a certain person
ולינסוב ברתי ve-linsov barti and let him marry my daughter. So אמר
רב פפא amar Rav Pappa so says Rav Pappa ארבע מאה שקיל
arba me'ah shakil the 400 zuz he can take וברתי u-barti the
daughter אי בעי נסיב ואי בעי לא נסיב ei ba'ei nasiv ve-ei
ba'ei lo nasiv if he wants he can marry her if he
wants he doesn't have to marry her because it's two separate statements
or because first he said the 400 zuz and then he only
said the daughter afterwards and as soon as he said the 400
zuz that became binding. So the גמרא says אבל אי אמר לינסב
והבו
ליה aval ei amar linsav ve-havu lei but if he said let
him marry my daughter and then give him 400 zuz אי נסיב
שקיל ואי לא נסיב לא שקיל ei nasiv shakil ve-ei lo nasiv
lo shakil if he takes it he if he marries her he
gets the money if he doesn't marry her doesn't get the money
because there the second statement that the 400 zuz was only said
after the precondition of let him marry my daughter was already said
so it's only said in that context. Okay and we'll just read
one more line about this יתיב מרימר וקאמר להאי שמעתא משמיה דנפשיה
yativ Mareimar ve-ka-amar le-hai shema'ta mi-shamei de-nafshei so Mareimar was telling over
this discussion in his own name about the fact that you know
if you say the other statement הריני נזיר hareni nazir or הרי
עלי תודה harei alai toda first it's binding regardless of the condition.
ואמר ליה רבינא למרימר ve-amar lei Ravina le-Mareimar and Ravina said to
Mareimar אתון הכי מתניתו לה atun hachi matnitu lah you teach it
like as a סתם stam teaching like anonymous. אנן anan we כדבעי
מיניה ריש לקיש מרבי יוחנן מתנינן לה ke-di-ba'ei minei Reish Lakish me-Rabbi
Yochanan matninan lah we have this as a tradition that Rabbi Yochanan
asked Reish Lakish that's how the גמרא introduced it. So תוספות Tosafot
makes the obvious connection and תוספות Tosafot says therefore somebody said על
מנת שאצא בו ידי חגיגה הרי עלי תודה al menat she-etzei bo
yedei chagigah harei alai toda that actually that would work. That actually
the stipulation could work as long as it's preceded. So for תוספות
right and you know it's not now there's a difference that case
is against a halachic requirement the second case is not. So this
is an interesting issue is the problem with like מתנה על מה
שכתוב בתורה matneh al mah she-katuv ba-Torah or is the problem just
the order in which you said it. תוספות suggested if you reverse
the order it actually could work based on this based on this
second story and this really ties into a הלכה in הלכות תנאים
Hilchot Tna'im where you need to have תנאי קודם למעשה. tenai kodem
le-ma'aseh. You first stipulate the condition then you stipulate the act to
make it clear that the act is only being done in the
context of the preceding condition. Okay.