בוקר טוב, Boker tov, we pick up today on דף מ"ט, daf
mem tes, and we are continuing the discussion about the text of
benching. So we discussed yesterday the various components about ברכת הארץ, Birchas
Ha'aretz, which is not enough to mention the land, but you have
to mention the good land, the wide, the prosperous, and then mention
the context in which we have the land, the ברית, bris, תורה,
Torah, and the גמרא Gemara even continued to turn ברית bris into
a discussion about ברית מילה bris milah which is interesting how that
is exactly connected to the land. Anyway,
then the גמרא Gemara says like this,
פליגי בה אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי ורבנן. pligi ba Abba Yosi ben
Dostai v'Rabbanan. So the line starts with the word רבנן, Rabbanan, it's
about ten lines down on מ"ט עמוד א'. mem tes amud aleph.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, maybe twelve lines
down on מ"ט עמוד א' mem tes amud aleph starts with the
word ורבנן. v'Rabbanan. So there's a debate of אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי
Abba Yosi ben Dostai and the Rabbis.
חד אמר הטוב והמטיב, chad omar HaTov veHaMeitiv, so now we're putting
aside ברכת הארץ Birchas Ha'aretz for a minute and going to הטוב
והמטיב. HaTov veHaMeitiv. צריכה מלכות
וחד אמר אינה צריכה מלכות. tzricha Malchus v'chad omar einah tzricha Malchus.
Do you have to say, like, מלכות Malchus here is not מלכות
בית דוד Malchus Beis David which we mentioned before by בונה ירושלים,
Boneh Yerushalayim, but here מלכות Malchus is God, מלך העולם, Melech Ha'olam,
so do you have to say ברוך אתה ה' הטוב והמטיב Baruch
Atah Hashem HaTov veHaMeitiv or do you have to say ברוך אתה
ה' אלוהינו מלך העולם הטוב והמטיב? Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam
HaTov veHaMeitiv? Okay, and by the way, the ברכה bracha as we
said before originally was just הטוב והמטיב. HaTov veHaMeitiv. We have a
whole paragraph that's an expanded version of which we'll see somewhat of
that in the גמרא. Gemara. But anyway, do you have to say
אלוהינו מלך העולם? Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam? So one says yes and one
says no. מאן דאמר צריכה מלכות, man de'amar tzricha Malchus, you have
to say מלך העולם, Melech Ha'olam,
קסבר דרבנן, kasavar d'Rabbanan, it's Rabbinic and therefore why do you need
מלך העולם? Melech Ha'olam? Because therefore it stands by itself, it's not
as we've seen before considered סמוך לחברתה. samuch l'chavertah. It was pasted
on, stapled on at the end after the ברכת המזון Birchas HaMazon
had already been established with the core three ברכות. brachos. So it's
a ברכה bracha that stands by itself. You say אלוהינו מלך העולם,
Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam, you always say that by ברכות brachos that stand
by themselves.
ומאן דאמר אינה צריכה מלכות, uman de'amar einah tzricha Malchus, if it
doesn't, קסבר דאורייתא, kasavar d'Oraisa, Biblical and therefore again the significance of
not being Biblical or Rabbinic per se, but whether that means it
was originally part of the original benching. So if you think about
for example the ברכות brachos we make in שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei,
right, ברוך אתה ה' רופא חולי עמו ישראל, Baruch Atah Hashem Rofei
Cholei Amo Yisrael, ברוך אתה ה' גואל ישראל, Baruch Atah Hashem Go'el
Yisrael, there's no מלכות. Malchus. We don't say אלוהינו מלך העולם Elokeinu
Melech Ha'olam because it all ultimately links back to the first ברכה
bracha which had מלכות Malchus in it. So once you open with
a ברכה bracha with מלך העולם, Melech Ha'olam, all the next ברכות
brachos which are סמוך לחברתה samuch l'chavertah
can just say ברוך אתה ה'. Baruch Atah Hashem. So if it
is connected to the early ברכות, brachos, so benching opens with
אלוהינו מלך העולם, Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam, right, that's how benching opens, so
then it's all connected to that, it does not need מלכות. Malchus.
That's a consistent literary
principle.
Sure there are exceptions, but yes,
that is
the
standard literary principle is if it's a סמוך לחברתה samuch l'chavertah it
will not be with שם ומלכות. shem u'malchus.
Right exactly, it does not need. Now there are exceptions always of
course, but let me just check שבע
ברכות
sheva
brachos
like a string.
Well שבע ברכות sheva brachos has a whole question about סמוך לחברתה.
samuch l'chavertah. Here you give me the סידור siddur there like the,
what do you call, like ברכת התורה, Birchas HaTorah, right, which is
also an interesting example of what's considered סמוך לחברתה samuch l'chavertah or
not.
But it's still a working principle.
As a working principle, yes, that is correct. So ברכת התורה Birchas
HaTorah starts with אלוהינו מלך העולם Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam and then the
end of the paragraph is המלמד תורה לעמו ישראל. HaMelamed Torah l'Amo
Yisrael. And then the next ברכה bracha which starts with a ברוך,
Baruch, so it's not being treated as סמוך לחברתה, samuch l'chavertah, is
אלוהינו מלך העולם אשר בחר בנו Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam asher bachar banu
and it ends with ברוך אתה ה' נותן התורה.
Baruch Atah Hashem
Nosein HaTorah. So right, exactly. So generally סמוך לחברתה, samuch l'chavertah, right,
is
not, does not require אלוהינו מלך העולם Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam exactly and
therefore if it's דאורייתא d'Oraisa considered סמוך samuch and does not, if
it's דרבנן d'Rabbanan it stands by itself.
Essentially maybe in a way because the שם ומלכות shem u'malchus is
implied by its connection.
Yes, yes,
and so it's not לבטלה. l'vatalah.
That is exactly it. That is exactly it. Since the theme of
מלכות Malchus is mentioned in the opening ברכה bracha and this is
all connected to the opening ברכה, bracha, it would not need it.
If it stands by itself then it does need it. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues, תנו רבנן, Tanna Rabbanan, מה הוא חותם בבנין
ירושלים, mah hu chosem b'vinyan Yerushalayim, what's the חתימת הברכה, chasimas habracha,
the end of the ברכה bracha by בונה ירושלים? Boneh Yerushalayim? You
open with רחם, Racheim, how do you end it? רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה אומר מושיע ישראל, Rebbi Yosi b'Rebbi Yehuda omar Moshia Yisrael, savior
of Israel. Now remember we said yesterday there's an opinion cited that
מושיע ישראל, Moshia Yisrael, הרי זה בור harey zeh bur was an
ignoramus. But of course nobody's going to bother to say that if
you say this you're an ignoramus unless some people are saying it.
So look at this, here we have that actually there's a תנא,
Tanna, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yosi b'Rebbi Yehuda that says that
you actually end with מושיע ישראל. Moshia Yisrael. So the גמרא Gemara
says, מושיע ישראל אין בנין ירושלים לא, Moshia Yisrael in binyan Yerushalayim
lo, you only מושיע ישראל, Moshia Yisrael, you don't say בנין ירושלים?
binyan Yerushalayim? אלא אימא אף מושיע ישראל, Ella eima af Moshia Yisrael,
even מושיע ישראל, Moshia Yisrael, which either means you actually say both
or it means that you can say either.
That's the way רש"י Rashi reads that. If you want to you
could say, you could certainly say both. If you want to, you
could say מושיע ישראל. Moshi'a Yisrael. You could read it that it
means you say both: מושיע ישראל ובונה ירושלים. Moshi'a Yisrael u'voneh Yerushalayim.
But clearly this goes back to the גמרא's Gemara's bias in favor
of the explicitly בונה ירושלים, Boneh Yerushalayim, but as we saw yesterday,
there are the opinions that emphasize the redemption of Israel as perhaps,
at least what I'm speculating is maybe having to do with a
post-חורבן Churban reality, that the first step of בונה ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim
is מושיע ישראל, Moshi'a Yisrael, and certainly from a גלות's Galut's perspective,
that might even be of a heightened concern.
You have that same language in the ברכה bracha after מגילת אסתר,
Megilat Esther, after the reading, הא-ל
המושיע, Ha'el HaMoshia,
and that's a
diaspora-oriented.
That's a good point too. And in שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei also,
what are the ברכות brachot in שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei ברכות brachot are,
what do we have? We have בונה ירושלים, Boneh Yerushalayim, and then
afterwards we have מצמיח קרן ישועה. Matzmiach Keren Yeshuah. Okay,
but that's דוד, David, that's צמח דוד עבדך. Tzemach David Avdecha. So
it speaks about מלכות דוד, Malchut David, but the פסוק, pasuk, the
ברכה bracha is, I'm sorry, we have earlier, we have מקבץ נדחי
ישראל, Mekabetz Nidchei Yisrael, then we have בונה ירושלים, Boneh Yerushalayim, and
then מצמיח קרן ישועה, Matzmiach Keren Yeshuah, which clearly refers to בית
דוד. Beit David. So obviously these are connected themes. So let's take
a look now how the גמרא Gemara continues this.
רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna איקלע לבי ריש גלותא.
ikla l'vei Reish Galuta. רבה בר רב הונא Rabbah bar Rav Huna
came to the house of the
ריש גלותא. Reish Galuta. פתח בחדא וסיים בתרתי. Petach b'chada v'sayeim b'tarti.
He opened with one, with רחם ה' א-להינו, Racheim Hashem Elokeinu, let's
say, על ירושלים עירך, al Yerushalayim irecha, and he ended by saying
two things, by saying presumably מושיע ישראל ובונה ירושלים. Moshi'a Yisrael u'voneh
Yerushalayim. So אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, דבורתא למיחתם בתרתי? Devurta
l'meichtam b'tarti? It's a big deal to end with two
things? So I'm going to mention both themes in the חתימה. chatimah.
You think that's such a big thing? והתניא רבי אומר אין חותמין
בשתים. Vehatanya Rabbi omer ein chotmin b'shtayim. This is that theme we
mentioned earlier, a point we mentioned earlier about things like about על
הארץ ועל הפירות, al ha'aretz v'al hapeirot, you're not supposed to have
two themes in the ברכה, bracha, only one theme at least in
the חתימה. chatimah. Okay, so now let's take a look. By the
way, when we do the בניין binyan of בונה ירושלים, Boneh Yerushalayim,
when we do that ברכה, bracha, we actually start with two themes
but we end with one. How does that ברכה bracha begin? That
ברכה bracha begins with
וצמח דוד עבדך u'tzemach David Avdecha מצמיח? matzmiach? Let's take a look.
No, no, no, that's in שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. I meant in
benching. רחם ה' א-להינו על ישראל עמך ועל ירושלים עירך. Racheim Hashem
Elokeinu al Yisrael amecha v'al Yerushalayim irecha. So that's על ישראל עמך
al Yisrael amecha is מושיע ישראל Moshi'a Yisrael theme we've been mentioning,
and then על ירושלים al Yerushalayim is the, the text itself has
both themes, but the ending is בונה ירושלים, Boneh Yerushalayim, only ending
with the בונה ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim theme. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara is saying here, you should only end with one theme.
הוה תני, Hava tani, let's look at that statement. רבי אומר אין
חותמין בשתים. Rabbi omer ein chotmin b'shtayim. You don't end a חתימה
chatimah with two themes.
איתיביה לוי לרבי. Eitiveih Levi l'Rabbi. לוי Levi asked רבי, Rabbi, על
הארץ ועל המזון? al ha'aretz v'al hamazon? What do you
mean, על הארץ ועל המזון? al ha'aretz v'al hamazon? No, ארץ דמפקא
מזון. Aretz d'mapka mazon. That's connected, the land that brings forth the
food. It's not two separate, although the wording is two separate things,
for the land and for the food, it's for the land that
brings forth the food. על הארץ ועל הפירות?
al ha'aretz
v'al hapeirot?
Same point. ארץ דמפקא פירות. Aretz d'mapka peirot. The land that brings
forth the fruit. מקדש ישראל והזמנים? Mekadesh Yisrael v'hazmanim?
ישראל דקדשינהו לזמנים. Yisrael d'kadshinhu l'zmanim. You sanctify Israel which then, and
Israel sanctifies the times by making the calendar, ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
מקדש ישראל וראשי חדשים? Mekadesh Yisrael v'roshei chodashim? Same
point. ישראל דקדשינהו לראשי חדשים. Yisrael d'kadshinhu l'roshei chodashim. So ultimately they're
basically one theme, they're connected.
What about מושיע ישראל ובונה ירושלים?
Moshi'a Yisrael u'voneh Yerushalayim? You could say that מושיע ישראל Moshi'a Yisrael
that thereby through ישועה yeshuah comes בניין ירושלים, binyan Yerushalayim, but you
could have tried to say that. Although there, notice until right now,
it's ascribing only one act to God. Meaning God is the one
that makes the land, God is the one that's מקדש ישראל, mekadesh
Yisrael, although actually the language we say is we ascribe both to
God, God sanctifies Israel and sanctifies the זמנים, zmanim, but in the
end the way the גמרא's Gemara's dealing with it to say it's
one theme is basically saying one thing is God. God sanctifies Israel,
Israel therefore then does acts. So here you don't really have the
same option as easily available by מושיע ישראל ובונה ירושלים, Moshi'a Yisrael
u'voneh Yerushalayim, because you're ascribing therefore two actions to God.
Long time to get to
שבת.
Shabbat. Let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. How about
מקדש השבת וישראל והזמנים? Mekadesh haShabbat v'Yisrael v'hazmanim? What about when we
have שבת Shabbat at a יום טוב? Yom Tov? Can't get out
of that one. So the גמרא Gemara says, חוץ מזו. chutz mizo.
Besides that. ומאי שנא? U'mai shna? Why is that different? How do
you get out of it? So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא חדא
היא התם תרתי. Hacha chada hi hatam tarti. Here it's one, there
it's two. What does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says what it
actually means is that
that... If you look at רש"י, Rashi, he says הכא חדא, hacha
chada, אין כאן אלא ברכה המקדש, ein kan ella bracha hamekadesh, שברוך
אתה השם המקדש השבת והזמנים. she-baruch ata Hashem hamekadesh ha-shabbat ve-hazmanim. That
basically, yes, God is doing two things, but it's basically the same.
God is sanctifying. So God sanctifies שבת, Shabbat, God sanctifies ישראל, Israel,
God sanctifies the מועדים moadim or ישראל Israel sanctifies מועדים. moadim. It's
all God has sanctified it. One verb, although applied to, if you
would, different things. Whereas here it's two different things. One is saving
ישראל, Israel, redemption, and the other is building ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It still
counts as more of two than the other, then the example of
שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov. So the גמרא Gemara says
והתם תרתי כל חדא וחדא באפי נפשה. ve-hatam tarti kol chada ve-chada
be-apei nafsha. And each one is different. First there's מושיע ישראל moshia
Yisrael and then there's בונה ירושלים, boneh Yerushalayim, and that's considered to
be distinct and should not be combined. So the גמרא Gemara says
וטעמא מאי חתמין בשתים? ve-taama mai chasmin bi-shtayim? So why shouldn't you
therefore do two? לפי שאין עושין מצות חבילות חבילות. lefi she-ein osin
mitzvos chavilos chavilos. You don't make מצות, mitzvos, you don't bundle them
up. Each one should get its own sort of focus. So the
מצוה mitzvah is an idea the גמרא Gemara has exactly about like
how do you, how do you, like can you do multiple מצות
mitzvos at the same time? What constitutes multiple מצות mitzvos at the
same time? Anyway, each one deserves its own focus. You should not
bundle it all up. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי הוי עלה?
mai havei alah? So what was the upshot of all of this?
What do we make in the end for בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim
for ירושלים? Yerushalayim? So אמר רב ששת amar Rav Sheshes פתח ברחם
על עמך ישראל. patach be-racheim al amcha Yisrael. You open with רחם
על עמך ישראל, racheim al amcha Yisrael, which is what we have.
You can open with the theme of ישראל. Israel. חותם, choteim, so
I'm sorry, if you open with the theme of ישראל, Israel, חותם
במושיע ישראל. choteim be-moshia Yisrael. Then you end with מושיע ישראל. moshia
Yisrael. Again, this was a נוסח nusach that was not going away
so quickly. פתח ברחם על ירושלים, patach be-racheim al Yerushalayim, if you
opened with רחם על ירושלים, racheim al Yerushalayim, so חותם בבונה ירושלים.
choteim be-boneh Yerushalayim.
You do the חתימה, chatimah, so the חתימה chatimah should be exactly
comparable to the opening, the way you opened the theme. Which is
interesting again, because here the גמרא Gemara is considering the possibility that
both the theme you open with and close with is not about
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It's only about the גאולה. geulah. Not to bundle ירושלים
Yerushalayim and the גאולה, geulah, it's only about the גאולה. geulah. So
how does that exactly connect to the theme of the ארץ? eretz?
It's presumably okay, restoring us to the land, but again in the
context that the גמרא Gemara wants to learn out that it's based
on the פסוק pasuk of הארץ הטובה הזאת, ha-aretz hatovah hazot, על
הארץ הטובה, al ha-aretz hatovah, that what makes land good is not
only the material benefit but the presence of the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. So that at least you would think ירושלים Yerushalayim is central,
that that's part of the emphasizing what is good about the land.
It's not just a prayer to be restored to the land. But
here it allows for that possibility that you open with מושיע ישראל
moshia Yisrael and you end with מושיע ישראל. moshia Yisrael. That was
one opinion. ורב נחמן אמר, ve-Rav Nachman amar, and רב נחמן Rav
Nachman says first wide line, אפילו פתח ברחם על ישראל, afilu patach
be-racheim al Yisrael,
even if you're going to open with mentioning ישראל Israel first, which
is what we did, חותם בבונה ירושלים. choteim be-boneh Yerushalayim. You have
to end with בונה ירושלים, boneh Yerushalayim, which is exactly our נוסח.
nusach. That is the חתימה, chatimah, משום שנאמר mishum shene'emar בונה ירושלים
השם נדחי ישראל יכנס. boneh Yerushalayim Hashem nidchei Yisrael yekaneis. God builds
ירושלים Yerushalayim and gathers in the dispersed of ישראל. Israel. So a
process, although here it's mentioned in the reverse order, but it's understood
that God builds ירושלים Yerushalayim having gathered in the dispersed of ישראל.
Israel. So therefore you begin with God being מושיע ישראל, moshia Yisrael,
but it leads to the culmination is בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim and
that is considered to be מעין החתימה me-ein ha-chatimah within the theme.
The חתימה, chatimah, excuse me, is מעין הפתיחה me-ein ha-ptichah is similar
to the way in which it was opened.
Okay, so actually, yes, the actual פתיחה ptichah is more than double,
it's quadruple, right?
מושיע עמך ישראל,
moshia
amcha Yisrael, רחם על
ציון. racheim al Tzion.
Right, mention all those things. Right, right. I mean in general the
point the גמרא Gemara more emphasizes is that the חתימה chatimah should
follow the last theme mentioned before the ברכה. bracha. Because very often
ברכות brachot have multiple themes and then you want the last line
to lead into the חתימה. chatimah. Here it's talking about also even
connecting to the very opening. But it is true we have multiple
themes. Now רש"י Rashi actually says the more literal in terms of
the פסוק. pasuk. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, he says רב
נחמן אמר בונה ירושלים תשועת ישראל היא דכתיב בונה ירושלים השם ואז
נדחי ישראל יכנס. Rav Nachman amar boneh Yerushalayim tishu'at Yisrael hi de-chsiv
boneh Yerushalayim Hashem ve-az nidchei Yisrael yekaneis. That actually first there's going
to be a restoration of ירושלים Yerushalayim and then that will lead
to the ingathering of the exiles. So that actually that the בונה
ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim is not that it's the culmination of תשועת ישראל,
tishu'at Yisrael, but you can open with תשועת ישראל tishu'at Yisrael and
end with בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim because בונה ירושלים boneh Yerushalayim is
the beginning of the process of תשועת ישראל. tishu'at Yisrael. So it's
interesting in terms of our sort of eschatological vision there.
Okay, and one other double חתימה. chatimah.
Wait, let me just read the line because the line of the
גמרא Gemara which I forgot to read was אימתי בונה ירושלים השם,
eimatai boneh Yerushalayim Hashem, when does God build ירושלים? Yerushalayim? בזמן שנדחי
ישראל יכנס bizman she-nidchei Yisrael yekaneis when he gathers in the dispersed
of ישראל. Israel. So again I think פשט pshat of the גמרא
Gemara and the reason the גמרא Gemara had to interpret the פסוק
pasuk is because it says בונה ירושלים Bonei Yerushalayim, *bonei Yerushalayim* occurs
after נדחי ישראל Yisrael יכנס *nidchei Yisrael yicanes*, that it's the culmination.
רש״י *Rashi* is somehow reading it that following בונה ירושלים Bonei Yerushalayim,
*bonei Yerushalayim* is נדחי ישראל Yisrael יכנס *nidchei Yisrael yicanes*, which I
don't think is an easy reading of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Yes. So on תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* we use a double חתימה
chasima, *chatimah*, right?
מנחם ציון ובונה ירושלים Yerushalayim *Menachem Tziyon u-vonei Yerushalayim*.
And it's funny because we insert a new paragraph, נחם *nachem*, which
starts with נחם *nachem*, but we
still start the paragraph, if I remember right, with לירושלים *L'Yerushalayim*. Exactly.
So yeah, that's a good question. How is it? You mean how's
that נחותמי בשתים *nechotmei bishtayim*? Right. Yeah, you could say well מנחם
ציון *Menachem Tziyon* is right, and you say similar type of an
answer that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying here, you know, that
the means of מנחם ציון *Menachem Tziyon* is through the בונה ירושלים
Bonei Yerushalayim. *bonei Yerushalayim*. But yes, the general question about how much
the חתימה chatimah. *chatimah* has to parallel the opening line, here in
the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying it doesn't have to
be the exact same theme. It has to be seen as a
continuation of the theme and so on. But more of the greater
emphasis tends to be also on the line right before the חתימה
chatimah. *chatimah*, which is not what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is
emphasizing so much. In the בענטשן benching? *bensching*, the line before the
חתימה Chatimah *chatimah* is... well, it doesn't actually mention ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*
right before. It says כי מלאת ידך המלאה הפתוחה הקדושה והרחבה שלא
נבוש ולא נכלם לעולם ועד *ki malei yadcha ha-mela'ah ha-petuchah ha-kedoshah ve-ha-rechavah
shelo nevosh ve-lo nicalem le-olam va-ed*. No, I'm sorry, but it does.
ובנה ירושלים Yerushalayim עיר הקדש במהרה בימינו *u-venei Yerushalayim ir ha-kodesh bimherah
ve-yameinu*. Right. ברוך אתה Baruch Atah ה׳ בונה ירושלים Bonei Yerushalayim? *Baruch
Atah Hashem bonei Yerushalayim*. And which is why all the insertions come
before ובנה ירושלים Yerushalayim. *u-venei Yerushalayim*, like the יעלה
ויבא *ya'aleh v'yavo* or רצה Retzei *retzei*, because you always want to
end with that line that is the segue into the ברכה bracha.
*bracha*. But here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is even talking about the
beginning, but as you see it seems to be a little looser
its connection to the beginning. You know, the connectedness of people and
the building of
Jerusalem to ברכת המזון
Bircas Hamazon *Birkat Hamazon*, which is about planting and food, right, I
wish it would say this explicitly.
I don't like to argue from silence, but biblically the theology is
clear. Jewish people are always described as seed. They're planted in the
earth. That's interesting. And the ground is the
fertile place for the Jewish people to grow. זרע ישראל Yisrael. *zera
Yisrael*. That's interesting. And it's also מצמיח ישועה *matzmiach yeshuah*, which is
exactly the
verb of to sprout forth a redemption that's embedded in the Bible
explicitly. It's just not being brought out here, but it does seem
like the חכמים *Chachamim* might be building on that. Right. That is
a very nice idea, although you would have wondered like for those
that had the גירסא *girsa* who had the חתימה chatimah. מושיע ישראל
Yisrael. *chatimah moshia Yisrael*, why not have it according to you the
way we
have it in the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei. *Shemoneh Esrei*, which is
מצמיח ישועה *matzmiach yeshuah*, which actually is a biblical phrase, right, and
would exactly build into that metaphor. So it's a nice idea. I'm
just not so sure how much it's here. Just as a footnote,
only because you mentioned it, it's מצמיח קרן
ישועה *matzmiach keren yeshuah*, right, which actually conflates two concepts. One is
the evolutionary idea, right, מצמיח *matzmiach*, and the other is the great
man of history idea where the קרן *keren* would be announced and
everything changes automatically. Right.
And מצמיח קרן ישועה *matzmiach keren yeshuah* is
about מלכות בית דוד Malchus Beis Dovid, *malchut beit David* in the
שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei*, exactly. But we do have מצמיח
ישועה *matzmiach yeshuah* elsewhere which it's just about ישועה *yeshuah* and not
about דוד *David*, right? I'm trying to remember where. Right. Where? Let's
say it again. In the end of מכלכל חיים *Mechalkel chayim*? Right.
מכלכל חיים בחסד מחיה מתים מצמיח ישועה *mechalkel chayim be-chesed mechayeh meitim
matzmiach yeshuah*. Right. Exactly. So alright, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
continues. Okay. Third line, wide line. אמר ליה amar lei, רב זירא
Rav Zeira לרב חסדא *Amar lei Rav Zeira le-Rav Chisda*. So רב
זירא Rav Zeira *Rav Zeira* said to רב חסדא Rav Chisda *Rav
Chisda*. ניתי מר Mar וניתני *Neisi mar ve-nisni*. The master should come
and teach us some משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, teach us some of the
Tannaitic sources that you have memorized. אמר ליה Amar lei, *Amar lei*.
So he said to him. ברכת מזונא לא גמרינא ותנויי מתנינא *Birchat
mezona lo gamrina ve-nisnui masnina*? I don't even know benching, you want
me to teach you משניות *Mishnayos*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said.
אמר ליה mאי האי *Amar lei mai hai*? What's going on here
that you say you don't know benching? אמר ליה דאכלתי בי ריש
גלותא *Amar lei de-achalti bei Reish Galuta*. Because I'll tell you what
happened. I was visiting the house of the ריש גלותא *Reish Galuta*.
He's coming up a lot in these stories. וברכי ברכת מזונא *U-varchi
birchat mezona*, and I made ברכת המזון Bircas Hamazon *Birkat Hamazon*. וזקפי
רב ששת Rav Sheshet לקיליה עלי כחיויא *Ve-zakfei Rav Sheshet le-kaleih alai
ke-chivya*. And רב ששת Rav Sheshet *Rav Sheshet* sort of like stuck
out, raised up his throat against me like a snake, like the
way like a serpent, you know, rises up ready to strike. That's
how he, you know, when I made the benching. ואמאי *Ve-amai*? Why
was he so angry with me? דלא אמרי לא ברית bris ולא
תורה Torah *De-la amri lo berit ve-lo Torah*. Until now we've been
saying you have to say ברית bris *Berit*, you have to say
תורה Torah *Torah*, where all these things are part of ברכת הארץ
*Birkat Ha'Aretz*. We even said according to one opinion if you didn't
say it you're not יוצא yotzei *yotzei*. And he said I didn't
say it. ולא מלכות malchus *Ve-lo malchut*. I didn't say מלכות malchus
*malchut*. Now not the מלכות Malchus *malchut* we've been talking about before,
immediately before, about the הטוב והמטיב Hatov Vehametiv *Ha-tov ve-ha-meitiv*, which is
מלך העולם Melech Ha'olam, *melech ha-olam*, but the מלכות Malchus, *malchut* we
mentioned earlier yesterday which is מלכות בית דוד Malchus Beis Dovid *malchut
beit David*. Mentioning that in בונה ירושלים Bonei Yerushalayim. *bonei Yerushalayim*. I
did not mention those themes, although now we've been saying you have
to mention all those themes. ואמאי לא אמרת *Ve-amai lo amarta*? Why
did you not say it? כדרב חננאל אמר רב Rav *Ke-de-Rav Chananel
amar Rav*. Because I was only like רב Rav. חננאל *Rav Chananel*
in the name of רב Rav *Rav*. I had a reason not
to say it. דאמר רב Rav. חננאל אמר רב Rav... *De-amar Rav
Chananel amar Rav*. לא אמר ברית bris תורה ומלכות Torah u'malchus יצא
*Lo amar berit Torah u-malchut yatza*. If you didn't say ברית bris
*Berit*, תורה *Torah*, or מלכות Malchus, *malchut*, you are יוצא yotzei *yotzei*,
as opposed to opinions before that said you're not יוצא yotzei, *yotzei*.
ברית לפי שאינה *Berit le-fi she-einah* לפי שאינם לא בנשים ולא בעבדים
l'fi she'einam lo b'nashim v'lo b'avadim and women ברית does not apply
to women they're not in ברית מילה bris milah I mean in
the ברית but not in ברית מילה bris milah תורה ומלכות and
תורה and מלכות Malchus. לפי שאינם לא בנשים ולא בעבדים doesn't apply
to women and slaves who are not obligated in תלמוד תורה Talmud
Torah at least to the classic formulation and kingship is applies you
know applies to מלך melech I mean you know the גמרא'ס Gemara's
clear that about slaves about this or even but there's a famous
רמב"ם Rambam that says מלך ולא מלכה melech v'lo malka but here
the גמרא Gemara sort of is implicitly saying kingship is a kind
applies by men not women and not slaves so therefore you know
I presumably and what he's presumably saying is that I intentionally you
could read this as therefore it's not מעכב me'akev since it is
not a since it's not universal and therefore that you can't argue
say that that text is required because it's not because it doesn't
apply to some people who are obligated in בנטשינג bentching it can't
be a required part of the text. But רש"י Rashi even goes
further and says that's why he didn't say it so as not
to exclude I think רש"י Rashi says this שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says שטיינזלץ
Steinsaltz says it okay no so רש"י Rashi doesn't say it but
one of the ראשונים Rishonim does say it I think the רשב"א
Rashba says it one of the ראשונים Rishonim definitely says does say
that specifically it's not just it's not just I פסק'ן pasken that
way but specifically I didn't say it because I did not want
to say a text that did not work for all people. So
he says no just okay בדיעבד b'diavad I'm not because it still
works because it's not meaning it's not intentionally he adopted it because
it was universal. He פסק'ן'ד paskened it wasn't מעכב me'akev because it
wasn't universal but it's not like he made a point of adopting
a universal although even according to that explanation you have to ask
so okay but even if it's not מעכב me'akev why not say
the other text. So it does seem and that I believe is
the רשב"א Rashba says explicitly he wanted to say a text that
was a universal text and it wasn't מעכב me'akev and that's what
he said. So according to him one minute let's see what the
answer is ואת שבקת כל הני v'at shavkat kol hanei so the
response back was so ואת שבקת כל הני v'at shavkat kol hanei
so רב זירא Rav Zeira said back to רב חסדא Rav Chisda?
but you and you abandoned כל הני kol hanei תנאי ואמוראי Tannai
v'Amorai all the תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים Amoraim we've been talking until
now who said
you have to say this text ופשקת כרב v'pashkat k'Rav and you
wanted to follow רב Rav.
so that's why רב ששת Rav Sheshet got mad at you because
you know you
adopted a
minority opinion here that says that these were not necessary. You said
רב ששת Rav Sheshet right with about רב חסדא? Rav Chisda רב
זירא Rav Zeira was explaining was saying to רב Rav, ששת he
was astounded that רב Rav. ששת adopted this position abandoned all the
other positions that said it was required and רב זירא Rav Zeira
sorry רב זירא Rav Zeira. was astounded that רב Rav, חסדא abandoned
all those positions in order to to go like רב. Rav But
according to this women really shouldn't say על בריתך שחתמת בבשרינו al
brisecha shechasamta b'vshareinu that's right but we found that in the I
think it's in the הגר"א'ס Gra's some manuscripts don't and I checked
it out once I saw this in the seminar manuscripts it just
says על בריתך al brisecha doesn't say שחתמת בבשרינו shechasamta b'vshareinu so
women are included in the general covenant with God על בריתך al
brisecha could mean right exactly but our בנטשינג bentching says על בריתך
שחתמת בבשרינו al brisecha shechasamta b'vshareinu right so we of our בנטשער
bentcher we left that right so that is a good question the
גמרא Gemara although it did not start with ברית מילה bris milah
it started with ברית in general when it shifted to י"ג בריתות
yud gimmel brisos at the top of this דף daf that refers
to the ברית מילה bris milah that always is what the גמרא
Gemara I mean that's what the גמרא Gemara refers to and the
fact that it says אינם בנשים einam b'nashim seems also to say
that at least it understood that that's what's referred to but it
doesn't necessarily mean that the text said that explicitly right so exactly
what the text was as we've been seeing until now the גמרא
Gemara. has you know discussions about the themes but is not so
explicit about the exact text so that is interesting that there were
versions that did not have שחתמת בבשרינו shechasamta b'vshareinu I think I
remember hearing that maybe by reading רב ברנשטיין. Rav Bernstein. Okay yes
but the גרים Gerim don't have a חלק chelek so תוספות Tosafot
discusses that earlier look the whole discussion earlier whether women are חייב
chayav in ברכת המזון birkat hamazon. the גמרא Gemara never said clearly
why they shouldn't be and רש"י Rashi earlier refers to this גמרא
Gemara, about whether their exclusion from ברית מילה bris milah or not
getting a חלק בארץ chelek b'aretz is a reason to say they're
פטור דאורייתא patur d'Oraisa although I will say two things first of
all there's a question about what text you say and then there's
a question when the גמרא Gemara says like you're לא יצא lo
yatza does it mean you're לא יצא דאורייתא lo yatza d'Oraisa does
it literally mean you know sometimes the גמרא Gemara. says לא יצא
lo yatza as a what do you call it as a you
know rhetorically and even if it means it literally it could mean
it דרבנן d'Rabbanan not biblically where you see the idea that you
need to say ברית and you know and what do you call
it and תורה as part of ארץ aretz and מלכות Malchus as
part of ירושלים Yerushalayim, as a דאורייתא d'Oraisa you could certainly be
this גמרא'ס Gemara's א דרבנן a d'Rabbanan but anyway this does become
part of an earlier discussion in ראשונים Rishonim we had about a
month ago about the question of whether women have the same level
of חיוב chiyuv in ברכת המזון birkat hamazon where the גמרא Gemara
never spelled out why not but it raised that possibility same thing
for גרים Gerim yeah תוספות Tosafot raises that too. So we've been
talking about מלכות Malchus before; now we're saying that it does need
מלכות, Malchus and consistent with—this is not מלכות malchut בית דוד, it's
מלכות השם, Malchus Hashem, מלך העולם, Melech Ha'olam. consistent with the idea
that הטוב והמטיב Hatov Vehametiv. is an independent ברכה. bracha It's not
סמוכה לחברתה, semucha l'chaverta, and therefore you say מלך העולם. Melech Ha'olam,
The גמרא Gemara says: מאי קא משמע לן? Mai kamashma lan? What
does this teach us? כל ברכה שאין בה מלכות לא שמה ברכה?
Kol bracha she'ein bah Malchus lo shema bracha? That any ברכה bracha.
without מלכות, מלכות השם, Malchus Hashem, מלך העולם, Melech Ha'olam. is not
a ברכה. bracha, והא אמר רבי יוחנן חדא זימנא? Ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan
chada zimna? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said it one time? So we
already know that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's position. We quoted that by,
you know, a month ago in the גמרא. Gemara You need מלכות.
So אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, לומר שצריכה שתי מלכויות. loma
shetzricha shtei malchuyos. You need to say מלכות twice. חדא דידי וחדא
דבונה ירושלים. Chada didei vechada d'Vanei Yerushalayim. Since you don't say מלכות
by בונה ירושלים, Bonei Yerushalayim you say ברוך אתה השם בונה ירושלים
Baruch Atah Hashem Bonei Yerushalayim or ברחמיו בונה ירושלים, be'rachamav Bonei Yerushalayim,
you don't say מלך העולם. Melech Ha'olam So therefore you're going to
double it up and say מלך Melech twice in, in הטוב והמטיב.
Hatov Vehametiv. It's sort of like, you know, the second day gets
two כי טוב, ki tov, I mean, you know, Tuesday gets two
כי טוב ki tov because there isn't a כי טוב ki tov
on, on Monday. So there wasn't מלך העולם Melech Ha'olam in בונה
ירושלים, Bonei Yerushalayim. you too—you have two מלך Melechs in, in הטוב
והמטיב. Hatov Vehametiv, And just to remind you the text of הטוב
והמטיב, Ha-tov ve-ha-metiv it starts with מלך העולם Melech Ha'olam? and then
it says: רוענו רועה ישראל המלך הטוב והמטיב לכל. Ro'enu Ro'eh Yisrael
Hamelech Hatov Vehametiv lakol. So we have another מלך Melech in there.
So that's also for בונה ירושלים. Bonei Yerushalayim So he says wait
a minute. אי הכי ניבעי תלתא? I hachi niba'ei tlosa? So we
should have three? חדא דידי וחדא דבונה ירושלים וחדא דברכת הארץ. Chada
didei vechada d'Bonei Yerushalayim vechada d'Birkas Ha'aretz. We don't have it for,
you know, we don't also have it, you know, על הארץ. al
ha'aretz. אלא ברכת—I mean, על הארץ ועל המזון Al Ha'aretz Ve'al Hamazon.
we don't say it. אלא ברכת הארץ מאי טעמא לא? Ella Birkas
Ha'aretz mai ta'ama lo? Why don't we say it? Why do we
just say על—why do we say על הארץ ועל המזון without מלך
העולם? Melech Ha'olam. משום דהויא לה ברכה סמוכה לחברתה, Mishum d'havya leh
bracha semucha l'chaverta, because it's juxtaposed to the first ברכה, bracha. which
starts with מלך העולם. Melech Ha'olam So בונה ירושלים נמי לא ליבעי?
Bonei Yerushalayim nami lo liba'ei? So it's also not needed for בונה
ירושלים? Bonei Yerushalayim.
דהויא לה ברכה סמוכה לחברתה. D'havya leh bracha semucha l'chaverta.
So there's no need like, oh, we have to pay back because
we didn't do it on an earlier ברכה. bracha Earlier ברכה bracha?
didn't require it. So גמרא Gemara says: No. הוא הדין דאפילו בונה
ירושלים נמי לא בעי. Hu hadin d'afilu Bonei Yerushalayim nami lo ba'ei.
Fine, you're right. You didn't need it in בונה ירושלים. Bonei Yerushalayim
So why do you say מלך Melech twice in this ברכה? bracha,
אלא אידי דאמר מלכות בית דוד, Ella eidi d'amar Malchus Beis Dovid,
because since we mentioned מלכות בית דוד in the בונה ירושלים Bonei
Yerushalayim. ברכה, bracha. לאו אורח ארעא לא לומר מלכות שמים. lav orach
ara lo lomar Malchus Shamayim. So it's not like from ברכות brachos
perspective, you didn't have to say מלך העולם Melech Ha'olam, at the
end of בונה ירושלים. Bonei Yerushalayim. But since in בונה ירושלים Boneh
Yerushalayim, you mentioned מלכות דוד, Malchus David, that sort of demanded a
mentioning of God's מלכות to—you know, what? For theological reasons, exactly, exactly.
So therefore, that's why it was sort of waiting to be said
in בונה ירושלים. Bonei Yerushalayim, And since it wasn't said, we re—we
double it up in the next ברכה. bracha, רב פפא אמר הכי
קאמר. Rav Papa amar hachi q'amar. רב פפא Rav Papa says: No,
this is what he says. צריכה שתי מלכויות לבר מדידי. Tzricha shtei
malchuyos l'var mididei. In addition to the מלך Melech for itself, מלך
Melech? העולם, you have two מלכויות malchuses in, in this ברכה, bracha,
one presumably for בונה ירושלים Boneh Yerushalayim and one for על הארץ
ועל המזון. So where is it? We say המלך הטוב והמטיב לכל,
Hamelech Hatov Vehametiv lakol, and then we say, wait, where do we
say the other מלך? Oh, אל אבינו מלכנו. El Avinu Malkenu. So
we say אל אבינו מלכנו El Avinu Malkenu and then we say
המלך הטוב והמטיב לכל. Hamelech Hatov Vehametiv lakol. So that actually we
do pay back the two earlier ברכות. brachos. Again, why we should
be paying them back, it's not really clear. But it's a nice
way of tying it all together. That's true. יתיב רב זירא אחרי
דרב גדל. Yasiv Rav Zeira acharei d'Rav Giddel. So רב זירא Rav
Zeira was sitting behind רב גדל. Rav Giddel. ויתיב רב גדל קמי
דרב הונא. V'yasiv Rav Giddel kamei d'Rav Huna. רב גדל Rav Giddel
was sitting in front of רב הונא. Rav Huna. So it was
רב הונא, Rav Huna, רב גדל, Rav Giddel, and רב זירא. Rav
Zeira, יתיב וקאמר. V'yasiv v'ka'amar. Now רב גדל Rav Giddel was saying
to—talk—and he didn't mention של שבת, shel Shabbos, אומר ברוך שנתן שבתות
למנוחה לעמו ישראל באהבה לאות ולברית, omer Baruch shenatan shabbasos limnucha l'amo
Yisrael b'ahava l'os u'lebrit, ברוך מקדש השבת. Baruch Mekadesh HaShabbat. So this
actually is how we פסקן, pasken, that in—now we're moving from the
text of the benching to insertions in the benching. So it's taken
for granted, like we said before, that you mention שבת Shabbos in
בונה ירושלים. Boneh Yerushalayim, What happens if you forgot to say it?
So you make the following ברכה, bracha and this is actually printed
in the—some סידורים, siddurim, in some benchers: ברוך אתה השם אלוקינו מלך
העולם אשר נתן שבתות למנוחה לעמו ישראל באהבה—so Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu
Melech Ha'olam asher natan shabbasos limnucha l'amo Yisrael b'ahava you mention—start with
אלוקינו מלך העולם, Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam, and then you end with לאות
ולברית, l'os u'lebrit, and then you end with ברוך אתה השם מקדש
השבת. Baruch Atah Hashem Mekadesh HaShabbat. Again, because it's a חתימה, chatimah.
it does not get the full אלוקינו מלך העולם. Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam.
So that's what he said, he—except he did not have the אלוקינו
מלך העולם Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam and so on, but ברוך אתה השם
מקדש השבת. Baruch Atah Hashem Mekadesh HaShabbat. So that's what you do,
you make actually an independent ברכה bracha if you missed inserting it
into בונה ירושלים. Boneh Yerushalayim, אמר ליה מאן אמרה? Amar lei: Man
amra? So he said to him, so—so רב זירא Rav Zeira said
to רב גדל, Rav Giddel, who said this? So he said, רב
Rav said. Okay. הדין יתיב וקאמר. Hadin yasiv v'ka'amar. Then, you know,
sort of like רב גדל Rav Giddel was apparently like the, you
know, the inter—the intermediary, he was telling over to רב זירא, Rav
Zeira he wasn't hearing directly what רב הונא Rav Huna was saying.
So he was doing the חזרה שיעור chazara shiur as it were.
So he told רב זירא Rav Zeira this פסק, psak, רב זירא
Rav Zeira, said: Who said it in the name of? He said
in the name of רב. Rav. Then רב... Rav He went and
said the next thing. וקאמר, Ve-kamar, so he טעה ולא הזכיר של
יום טוב, ta'ah ve-lo hizkir shel Yom Tov, if you forgot יום
טוב Yom Tov in בונה ירושלים, Yerushalayim, אומר: omer: ברוך שנתן ימים
טובים לעמו ישראל, Baruch she-natan yamim tovim le-amo Yisrael, ברוך אתה ה'
אלוקינו מלך העולם שנתן ימים טובים לעמו ישראל לשמחה ולזכרון ברוך אתה
ה' מקדש ישראל והזמנים. Baruch atah Adonai Eloheinu melech ha-olam she-natan yamim
tovim le-amo Yisrael le-simcha u-le-zikaron baruch atah Adonai mekadesh Yisrael ve-hazmanim. So
אמר ליה, said back to him, בשמא דמאן אמרה, bi-shma de-man amrah,
who is that in the name of? רב. Rav, Okay, same idea.
Then he said, הדר יתיב וקאמר. Hadar yasiv ve-kamar. Now, by the
way, the idea of let me just so here, yeah, so our
גרסא, girsa, this גרסא girsa is, is what is it? לשמחה ולזכרון.
le-simcha u-le-zikaron. זכרון Zikaron is interesting. I mean, we do say אלוקינו
ואלוקי אבותינו יעלה ויבוא Eloheinu ve-Elohei avoteinu ya'aleh ve-yavo on, on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, which is: our remembrance should go up. So there's
a sense of זכרון, zikaron, but actually if you look at the
נוסח nusach we have here for when we mention it, first of
all, we have it mentioned as a specific ברכה bracha: on יום
טוב: Yom Tov: ברוך אתה ה' אלוקינו מלך העולם אשר נתן ימים
טובים לעמו ישראל לששון ולשמחה. Baruch atah Adonai Eloheinu melech ha-olam asher
natan yamim tovim le-amo Yisrael le-sason u-le-simcha. We don't mention זכרון, zikaron,
ששון ושמחה, sason ve-simcha, את יום חג המצות חג השבועות הזה ברוך
אתה ה' מקדש ישראל והזמנים. et yom chag ha-matzot chag ha-shavuot ha-zeh
baruch atah Adonai mekadesh Yisrael ve-hazmanim. So slightly different than the נוסח
nusach of the גמרא, Gemara both mentioning specifically the יום טוב Yom
Tov and not mentioning זכרון, zikaron, mentioning ששון ושמחה. sason ve-simcha. Okay.
הדר יתיב וקאמר, Hadar yasiv ve-kamar, then he was saying again: טעה
ולא הזכיר של ראש חודש, ta'ah ve-lo hizkir shel Rosh Chodesh, if
you forgot ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, אומר: omer: ברוך שנתן ראשי חדשים
לעמו ישראל לזכרון. Baruch she-natan rashei chodashim le-amo Yisrael le-zikaron. Now there,
you know, it's לזכרון, le-zikaron, there's not a שמחה simcha theme, but
it's לזכרון. le-zikaron. ולא ידענא, Ve-lo yadana, and now I don't know:
אי אמר בה שמחה אי לא אמר בה שמחה. i amar bah
simcha i lo amar bah simcha. So now רב זירא Rav Zeira
is saying, this is what I heard from רב גידל, Rav Giddel,
and this one I don't know, as opposed to the other ones,
whether number one you mentioned the theme of שמחה, simcha, right? We
saw here mentioned זכרון, zikaron, not שמחה. simcha. If you don't, אי
חתים בה אי לא חתים בה. i chasim bah i lo chasim
bah. Maybe there's no חתימה. chatimah, It's such a short ברכה: bracha
שנתן ראשי חדשים לעמו ישראל לזכרון. she-natan rashei chodashim le-amo Yisrael le-zikaron.
Maybe it does not deserve a חתימה. חתימה is only once the
ברכה bracha. gets to be a certain size, you have to wrap
it up with an end ברכה. bracha If it's short like על
העץ, al ha-etz, you know, you know, על פרי העץ, al pri
ha-etz, I should say בורא פרי האדמה, borei pri ha-adamah, it does
not get a חתימה. Like בורא נפשות. Borei Nefashot. Or בורא נפשות.
Borei Nefashot. So I don't know if this is big enough to
get, I don't know whether, you know, whether he said you do
שמחה, simcha, whether he said you do a חתימה. Okay. אי דידיה
אי דרב, i dideih i de-Rav, I don't know if he said
in his own name, if he said in the name of his
רבי, Rebbi, of רב, Rav, because the other stuff was in the
name of רב. So I don't know exactly. Now the ברכה bracha,
we have for this is: ברוך אתה ה' אלוקינו מלך העולם אשר
נתן ראשי חדשים לעמו ישראל לזכרון. Baruch atah Adonai Eloheinu melech ha-olam
asher natan rashei chodashim le-amo Yisrael le-zikaron. No חתימה, no שמחה. simcha.
So actually no more than was actually said. He didn't know if
there was more to it, we do happen to do exactly what
was said. זכרנו לטובה היום. Zochreinu le-tovah ha-yom. I understand. Okay, yes.
Why is it that if we say it, if we remember when
we say רצה Retzei there's no special שם ומלכות? shem u-malchut? Right.
Yet when we forget all of a sudden there's a whole... Well,
there's no שם ומלכות shem u-malchut in רצה Retzei because it's part
of the... oh, you mean why the מלכות of the supposed ברכה,
bracha, meaning because in רצה Retzei it's considered סמוך לחברתה samuch le-chavertah
and it gets the and therefore it piggybacks on the שם ומלכות
shem u-malchut from the beginning of the בענטשינג. bentching. When it's not
inserted in רצה Retzei. and it stands by itself, then it's not
סמוך לחברתה. samuch le-chavertah. Meaning the way you're saying it right now,
it's סמוך, samuch, but it wasn't נתקן סמוך. nitkan samuch. סמוך לחברתה
Samuch le-chavertah has to do with how it was originally established. The
same way the הטוב והמטיב Hatov Vehameitiv. now is סמוך לחברתה samuch
le-chavertah because it's put as the fourth ברכה, bracha, but as we've
been seeing, it doesn't have the הלכה halacha of סמוך לחברתה samuch
le-chavertah because it was originally independent. So the basic rule of סמוך
לחברתה samuch le-chavertah has much more to do with how it was
originally established and not if in this circumstance it happens to be
juxtaposed. רב משה Rav Moshe actually uses this on one important question
about שבע ברכות. Sheva Brachot. When you're giving שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot
to the honors under the חופה, chuppah, there's some people that say
you cannot divide them between different people because a number of the
שבע ברכות Sheva Brachot don't open with a ברוך baruch. אתה because
they're סמוך לחברתה. samuch le-chavertah. And they say in order for it
to count as סמוך לחברתה, samuch le-chavertah, you have to say both.
Or maybe even more, they say, maybe or maybe they're a little
bit more lenient, you have to have heard the previous one and
be יוצא שומע כעונה, yotzei shome'a k-oneh, so it counts as סמוך
לחברתה samuch le-chavertah for you, else you're not saying it סמוך לחברתה.
samuch le-chavertah. And רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein says no, he
says סמוך לחברתה samuch le-chavertah is how it was originally established. And
since it's not how it's being said right now in this instance.
Okay, and that can work in both directions. So here, just to
say if someone took too long to get up, I don't know
what they would say, but they certainly לכתחילה le-chatchilah they're saying
it shouldn't be the same it needs to be the same person.
Anyway, מר says like this: Okay. גידל בר מניומי הוי קאי קמיה
דרב נחמן. Giddel bar Minyumi havah kai k-mei de-Rav Nachman. So גידל
בר מניומי Giddel bar Minyumi was in front of רב נחמן. Rav
Nachman. טעה רב נחמן. Ta'ah Rav Nachman.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman forgot,
he
forgot to say יעלה ויבוא ya'aleh ve-yavo or he forgot to say
רצה. Retzei, והדר לרישא, Ve-hadar le-reisha, he went all the way to
the beginning of the בענטשינג. bentching. אמר ליה מאי טעמא עביד מר
הכי, Amar lei mai ta'ama avid mar hachi, why do you do
this? Go all the way to the beginning of the בענטשינג? bentching?
אמר ליה דאמר שילא אמר רב, de-amar Sheila amar Rav, טעה חוזר
לראש, ta'ah chozer le-rosh, because it was said in the name of
רב, the same רב who a minute ago it was said in
his name you say a special ברכה, bracha said if you forgot
the insertions, you have to go back to the beginning of בענטשינג.
bentching. So the גמרא Gemara. says והא רב הונא אמר רב טעה
אומר
ברוך שנתן,
v'ha Rav Huna amar Rav
ta'ah omer
baruch shenatan, but didn't רב הונא Rav Huna say in the name
of רב טעה אומר ברוך שנתן ta'ah omer baruch shenatan that you
say this special ברכה bracha?
for ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you're not חוזר לראש? chozer l'rosh? So
by the way, notice here it says אמר רב הונא אמר רב,
Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav, right? In the original story רב גידל
Rav Giddel was saying it to רב הונא, Rav Huna, to רב
זירא, and when רב זירא said, "Who is it in the name
of?" he said רב. So that sort of wasn't originally said אמר
רב הונא אמר רב. Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav. רב גידל Rav
Giddel was saying over what he heard from רב הונא Rav Huna
and then he clarified that it was in the name of רב
and now in the recap it's just become a nice distilled אמר
רב הונא אמר רב. Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav. By the way,
when are you supposed to say ברוך שנתן? Baruch Shenatan? As soon
as you remember or at the end of the entire בענטשן? benching
We're about to find out. So let's take a look. So he
said, "Ah, don't we, doesn't he say you can say this special
ברכה?" bracha, אמר ליה, איתמר לה, itmar lah, אמר מניומי בר חליפא
אמר רב. amar Minyumi bar Chalifa amar Rav. Now another teaching in
the name of רב, לא שנו אלא שלא פתח בהטוב והמטיב. lo
shanu ela shelo patach b'Hatov Vehameitiv. It's only if you didn't begin
the next ברכה, bracha, you didn't start הטוב והמטיב. Hatov Vehameitiv אבל
פתח בהטוב והמטיב, aval patach b'Hatov Vehameitiv, if you began the next
ברכה, bracha חוזר לראש, chozer l'rosh, then you messed up the בענטשן
benching because this thing has to occur if not in רצה, Retzei
at least before the end of בענטשן benching, or before הטוב והמטיב
Hatov Vehameitiv which is clearly now the fourth ברכה bracha and you're
moving on. And therefore if it did not, if you had basically
started הטוב והמטיב Hatov Vehameitiv, which is clearly after the core בענטשן,
benching then you messed up the בענטשן benching and you have to
go back to the beginning. You can't just go back, you don't
just go back to the ברכה bracha you messed up. As we
know, there are times where things are seen as a unit and
you go back all the way to the beginning when you make,
when you mess something up in the first three ברכות brachot of
שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. You don't just go back to, let's say
the ברכה bracha, you, let's say you forgot משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
Mashiv HaRuach U'morid HaGeshem or something, or you said it when you
shouldn't say, you don't just go back to that ברכה, bracha you
go back to the very beginning. So here too, once you're considered
to have been finished because you start הטוב והמטיב, Hatov Vehameitiv, then
you have to go back all the way and do the בענטשן
benching again. If you haven't finished yet, you can add it sort
of before, you can add it at the very end. Now by
the way, if it actually is happening, if it actually is happening
and you're saying ברוך אתה השם, אלקינו מלך העולם, Baruch Atah Hashem
Elokeinu Melech Haolam, and you're about to start the הטוב והמטיב, Hatov
Vehameitiv and then you realize, oh my gosh, I forgot to say
רצה or whatever, then you can end the אלקינו מלך העולם Elokeinu
Melech HaOlam, with the אשר נתן. Asher Natan. So in that, because
starting הטוב והמטיב Hatov Vehameitiv really means to get so far to
say האל אבינו. Ha'el Avinu. Okay? And once you say that, then
you've already considered to have moved on and you have to repeat.
Yes. But I don't understand why the order is so important. We
saw once before if you forgot to דאווענען daven מנחה, Mincha, you
have two מנחה'ס, Minchas, one after the other. Right. Right. But that's
just you forgot the whole prayer. Here, they didn't have printed בענטשערס,
benchers, everybody had to בענטש. bench. Right. So well, that's why they
had the זימון. zimun. So one mistake, why, why not add it
out of order? What's the big deal if you say it in,
well, again, it raises an interesting question, which is, had they, was
it the out of order? Was it that going back to the
emphasis that בענטשן benching? is over, הטוב והמטיב Hatov Vehameitiv. is really
considered a ברכה bracha, after בענטשן? benching. It's really not considered integral
to the בענטשן. benching, You know, let's say you miss something in
an earlier ברכה, bracha could you say it in a later? No,
we don't really have a test because the only thing we say
in an earlier ברכה bracha, is the על הנסים, Al HaNissim, and
על הנסים Al HaNissim if you miss you don't have to go
back for. So even if you forgot the על הנסים Al HaNissim
the whole בענטשן, benching. you don't have to repeat. But I don't
know if the point here is you can't go out of order
or the point is that you missed it in the third and
final ברכה, bracha. so now you would, you're actually actually have completely
like there's no, you can't say it in הטוב והמטיב. Hatov Vehameitiv,
You're already done. You left the ballpark. Exactly. You're already done. You're
no longer in the core בענטשן. benching I think that could be
a part of it. So you're saying that whole בענטשן benching that
you just did is no good rabbinically. Completely. Look, I understand we've
had these discussions before, which is, you know, you said it with
כוונא, kavanah, you're thanking... same thing, same thing with... One mistake. I
understand. So this is not a question whether biblically you're יוצא or
not. Biblically there's no need to mention that it was שבת Shabbos
or any of those types of things, right? Biblically, even if we
say that all these things about, you know, ארץ Eretz and ירושלים
Yerushalayim are themes in the Torah, the exact נוסח התפילה nusach hatfillah
is clearly rabbinic. And in addition to the requirement to mention all
of the special days is clearly rabbinic. So yes, the bit to
repeat it is a rabbinic requirement. You know, as far as the
Torah is concerned, a lot of times you're יוצא as far as
the Torah is concerned, but most of our ritual life is a
lot the rabbinic structures that have been created, not the Torah. So
that's correct. Yes. So what would we be thinking then if you
just said, forgetting starting הטוב והמטיב, hatov vehametiv, you just said ברוך
אתה השם, Baruch Atah Hashem, then you didn't say בונה ירושלים, Yerushalayim?
you just ended in אלקינו מלך העולם Elokeinu Melech HaOlam or didn't
say what you'd do? Yeah, so that idea of saying למדני חוקיך
Lamdeni Chukecha if you said ברוך אתה השם Baruch Atah Hashem, in
order to not make you have finished, that comes up in the
אחרונים, Acharonim, that's not in the גמרא. Gemara So what was גמרא
Gemara thinking then? Let's say you said ברוך אתה השם, Baruch Atah
Hashem you didn't say yet... According to רב, you would finish בונה
ירושלים Yerushalayim. and then say this special ברכה. bracha? This idea, this
trick of saying למדני חוקיך lamdeni chukecha whatever and then continuing is
discussed, is discussed in the אחרונים acharonim in the ביאורי הלכה beurei
halacha as they said, it's so פתח patach הטוב והמטיב, hatov vehametiv.
what's difference does it פתח, patach, it's you already said בונה ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, right? It's the same thing. Yeah, fine. Okay, I just need
clarification: what are we saying? At what point, when do we חוזר
לראש chozer lerosh and when do we say that extra ברכה? bracha
Say this extra ברכה bracha. before you started saying... if once you
say ברוך אתה השם אלקינו מלך העולם הא-ל הטוב והמטיב לכל, Baruch
Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Haolam ha'Eil hatov vehametiv lakol, then you've already
begun הטוב והמטיב. hatov vehametiv. You blew it. חוזר לראש; chozer lerosh;
do the whole בענטשינג bencing again. Any moment before that you say
the ברכה. bracha If you said ברוך אתה השם Baruch Atah Hashem,
אלקינו מלך העולם, Elokeinu Melech HaOlam then end with this; I mean
אשר נתן שבתות למנוחה. asher natan shabatot limnucha. If you just said
בונה ירושלים, Yerushalayim, say this. Okay? It's a real problem, by the
way, that a lot of בענטשערס benchers don't have this ברכה bracha
in it because it is not uncommon... some do. It is not
uncommon. When my wife and I were picking out our wedding בענטשערס,
benchers, one of the requirements was that it had to have these
ברכות brachot in it because you know it's not uncommon that people
forget it. And who remembers this נוסח הברכה? nusach habracha? You have
to go search around for a סידור siddur to find the ברכה
bracha. and it's so insulting to your guests. What, it's insulting to
your guests? Right. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay. אמר
רבי אידי בר אבין אמר רב עמרם אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל
הא ולא הזכיר של ראש חודש בתפילה מחזירין אותו. amar Rabi Idi
bar Avin amar Rav Amram amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel ha velo
hizkir shel Rosh Chodesh bitfilah machzirin oto. Now that we're mentioning things
you have to go back for, so if you didn't mention ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh in the דאווענינג, davening, you also go back. בברכת
המזון אין מחזירין אותו. bevirkat hamazon ein machzirin oto. We spoke about
going back for not mentioning things in בענטשינג; bencing; doesn't apply to
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It only for ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh דאווענינג,
davening, yes, but not ברכת המזון. birkat hamazon, אמר ליה רב אבין
לרב עמרם; amar leih Rav Avin le-Rav Amram; so רב אבין Rav
Avin said to רב עמרם, Rav Amram, מאי שנא תפילה מאי שנא
ברכת המזון? maishana tefillah maishana birkat hamazon? What's the difference between שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei? and ברכת המזון birkat hamazon when it comes to
ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, when do you go back and when you
don't? אמר ליה אף לדידי קשיא לי. amar leih af lediidi kashya
li. You know what, I didn't know either. I had the same
קשיא. kashya. וכי שאלתיה לרב נחמן; vechi sheiltih le-Rav Nachman; so I
asked רב נחמן Rav Nachman because this was said in... רב עמרם
Rav Amram said it in the name of רב נחמן Rav Nachman
who said it in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. ואמר לי מיניה
דמר שמואל; veamar li minei demar Shmuel; and he told me from
the name of שמואל, Shmuel, who was the originator of this teaching,
לא מיניה דמר שמואל לא שמיע לי; lo minei demar Shmuel lo
shmia li; from שמואל Shmuel I did not hear the explanation of
this. שמואל Shmuel gave the teaching, I did not hear the reason
for the distinction. אלא נחזי אנן; ela nechzei anan; let's figure it
out for ourselves. תפילה דחובה היא; tefillah dechova hi; תפילה tefillah is
an obligation. You have to דאווען. daven. מחזירין אותו. machzirin oto. So
if this for ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh this is the נוסח התפילה,
nusach hatefillah, you didn't do the נוסח התפילה nusach hatefillah for today,
this is what the text is, so you didn't do it, so
you have to go back. ברכת מזונא דאי בעי אכיל אי בעי
לא אכיל. birkat mezona de'ibayei achil ibayei lo achil. When it comes
to ברכת המזון, birkat hamazon nobody's demanding that you eat today. You
have to do ברכת המזון Birkas HaMazon when you eat, but there
was no obligation to make sure you did ברכת המזון Birkas HaMazon,
today. So therefore, אין מחזירין אותו; ein machzirin oto; do not make
him go back. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה, ela me'ata,
if that's true, שבתות וימים טובים דלא סגי דלא אכיל הכי נמי
דטען? shabbatot veyamim tovim delo sagi delo achil hachi nami deto'ein? So
when you say on שבתות Shabbatot and ימים טובים Yamim Tovim where
you have to have a סעודה, seudah, if you made a mistake
you have to go back? What's the answer? It's pretty clear as
we said before about going back. So he's going back for let's
say שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov. אמר ליה אין, amar
leih in, yes, דאמר שילה אמר רב חוזר לראש. d'amar Shila amar
Rav chozer lerosh. Because we said earlier there are times where if
you forget you have to go to the beginning, so that would
exactly be those days where you actually have a חיוב chiyuv to
have a סעודה. seudah. So גמרא Gemara. says ואמר רב הונא אמר
רב טעה אמר ברוך שנתן. ve'amar Rav Huna amar Rav ta'ah omer
Baruch shenatan. Wait a minute, we had another version that you don't
have to go back, it's just enough to say the special ברכה.
bracha גמרא Gemara says לא שנו אלא, lo shanu ela, we just
got through saying לא שנו אלא, lo shanu ela, שלא פתח בהטוב
והמטיב אבל פתח בהטוב והמטיב חוזר לראש. shelo patach be'hatov ve'hametiv aval
פתח בהטוב והמטיב חוזר לראש patach be'hatov ve'hametiv chozer lerosh. This ברכה
bracha doesn't always work. It only works before you... if you haven't
gone on to the הטוב והמטיב. hatov vehametiv, Once you've gone on
to הטוב והמטיב, it's too late. So yes, there are times where
mentioning שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov is מעכב, me'akev, and
that's when there's a חיוב סעודה. chiyuv seudah. And that, by the
way, is why על הנסים Al Hanisim is not מעכב, me'akev, because
על הנסים Al Hanisim on פורים Purim and on חנוכה, Chanukah, there's
not a חיוב. chiyuv. On פורים Purim there is a משתה, mishteh,
whatever, but you nevertheless it's not like you know, it's not first
of all there's a question about, you know, is טאקע taka סעודה
seudah with bread, is it more of a חיוב chiyuv of משתה?
mishteh? Anyway, and there also, you know, so number one there's the
question about whether there's a חיוב סעודה. chiyuv seudah. Number two, what
it doesn't get you is, it's interesting הלכה halacha that by ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh you don't go back for מעריב, Maariv, even in
שמונה עשרה. Okay? And that's for other reasons because they're only מקדש
החודש. mekadesh hachodesh. You know, at night they wouldn't know it was
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. The active קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh happened the
next day. But the basic הלכה halacha is when there's a חיוב
סעודה, chiyuv seudah, then since you have to have a meal, then
the בענטשינג bencing of this meal reflects the nature of the day.
Since the day demands a meal, if you don't have to then
you do not have to, then you don't have to. You should
say it, but if you miss it you don't go back. A
wedding, is there a חיוב סעודה chiyuv seudah if you're a guest
at a wedding? Yeah, but the but yeah, but first I mean,
well that's a yeah, but but again... but there's no need to
mention—I mean, what are we talking about, like דוי הסיר? D'Vay Haseir?
Meaning there's no—they didn't—they weren't מחייב... m'chayeiv... ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Yeah,
but then it's not the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh that is מחייב
m'chayeiv the סעודה. seudah. So it's when the time is מחייב m'chayeiv
a סעודה, seudah, the בענטשן benching. is a תפילה tefillah always reflects
the nature of the time that you're in, whatever, you know, כל
יום תן לנו מברכותיו, kol yom ten lanu mivirkosav, so ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh, חנוכה, Chanukah, פורים, Purim, whatever, it's always reflected in the
ברכת המזון Birkas HaMazon. in the בענטשן. And if that time demands
a סעודה, seudah, then it is integral to the ברכת המזון, Birkas
HaMazon and if you don't do it, you go back. If it
does not demand a סעודה, seudah, then it's incidental, seen as, and
therefore you do not go back. That's my understanding it. Because I
mean, because even in ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh you're going to have
a special מוסף, Musaf, so why does it mean you should go
back in שחרית? Shacharis? Right. So the point is that it's not
after be that the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is מחייב. m'chayeiv. It's
true, it's מחויב m'chuyav for today, but even if it's not מחויב
m'chuyav by virtue of it being ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So let's
get to the question which you asked, which is let's say it's
שבת ראש חודש. Shabbos Rosh Chodesh. So you're חייב chayav because it's
שבת, Shabbos, you also go back if you forgot ראש חודש? Rosh
Chodesh? And actual actually the answer is no. Which is interesting because
then why is it different than the שמונה עשרה? So that's a
good question. But that's the הלכה. halacha. Okay. So צריך עיון. tzarich
iyun. So anyway, now let's go further in the גמרא. Gemara עד
כמה מזמנין? ad kama mezamnin? So that's a very, you know, interesting
גמרא Gemara. we just had about yesterday and today about all the
textual issues. Now we get up to how many people, how little
can you eat and still make a זימון, zimmun, which is also
the question of still do ברכת המזון. Birkas Hamazon. So there was
a debate. One said כזית kezayis and one said כביצה. kebeitzah. So
the גמרא Gemara says: למימרא דרבי מאיר חשיב ליה כזית. l'meimra de-Rabbi
Meir chashiv lei kezayis. Rabbi Meir says a כזית kezayis is what's
significant and that's enough for ברכת המזון Birkas Hamazon and to lead
the זימון. zimmun. ורבי יהודה כביצה. v'Rabbi Yehuda kebeitzah. And Rabbi Yehuda
says a כביצה. kebeitzah. ואיפכא שמעינן להו, v'ifcha shmanan lehu, but we
heard that they had opposite positions. דתנן וכן מי שיצא מירושלים ונזכר
שהיה בידו בשר קדש. d'tnan v'chen mi she-yatza mi-Yerushalayim v'nizkar she-hayah b'yado
basar kodesh. So this is a משנה Mishnah. in פסחים Pesachim that
talks about, first it talks about if you're on a trip and
you remember that you forgot to do ביעור חמץ. biur chametz. How
do you do ביעור חמץ biur chametz when you're still on your
trip? When do you have to go back and do ביעור? biur?
When do you have to just be מבטל mevatel the חמץ? chametz?
And then it said by analogy if somebody is leaving ירושלים and
they just brought a קרבן. korban. And then as they're leaving, you
know, as they're a few miles out, they open up their their
lunch and they realize that they had packed a קרבן korban sandwich.
They had forgotten and they took this קרבן korban meat outside of
ירושלים. So now that it's taken outside of ירושלים, it's פסול, pazul,
it's יוצא, it's outside of ירושלים, it has to be burned. But
normally it's burned in ירושלים when you have something that's פסול ביוצא.
pazul b'yotzei. When do you have to go back to ירושלים? When
can you burn it where you are? So it says אם עבר
צופים, im avar Tzofim, if you passed צופים Tzofim which is הר
הצופים, Har Hatzofim, exactly, Mount Scopus, which is where you can see
ירושלים. So if you can no longer sort of see ירושלים, שורפו
במקומו, sorfo bimkomo, you burn it wherever you are. ואם לאו, v'im
lav, and if you are still within from הר הצופים Har Hatzofim
and towards ירושלים, so you can so you're still in the vicinity,
then חוזר ושורפו לפני הבירה, chozer v'sorfo lifnei ha-birah, then you have
to burn it in the presence of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
in a special place because it's like you haven't left the vicinity,
then you have to turn around and go back. Isn't it חוזר
ושורפו? chozer v'sorfo? I don't know. מבית המערכה mi-Beis HaMa'arachah from the
word, from the, you know, that was used for the, for the
fire. Now, עד כמה הן חוזרין? ad kama hen chozrin? How much
meat you have to go back for? When we're telling you to
go back that, you know, how much is significant that you'd have
to make this trip back. So רבי מאיר אומר זה וזה כביצה.
Rabbi Meir omer zeh v'zeh kebeitzah. ורבי יהודה אומר זה וזה כזית.
v'Rabbi Yehuda omer zeh v'zeh kezayis. That it is whether we're talking
about the meat or whether we're talking about חמץ. chametz. חמץ chametz
was another case about coming back and doing ביעור חמץ. biur chametz.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says a כביצה kebeitzah is what is
significant to go back for, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says a
כזית. kezayis. So that's exact opposite of what we have in our
משנה. Mishna. Exactly, then you just... What's the difference?
How many ounces?
How many ounces? I mean, a כזית kezayis is
we normally say is about three and a half fluid ounces. A
כביצה kebeitzah is what's the ratio of כביצה kebeitzah to כזית? kezayis?
I think it's a question of whether it's a three or a
four ratio? No, my memory, a two or three ratio. I think
it's a question of whether כביצה kebeitzah to כזית kezayis is a
two or three ratio. So it's about, you know, somewhere so a
כזית kezayis is about three and a half ounces and a כביצה
kebeitzah could be up to ten ounces, six to ten ounces. Okay,
so what do you do
if it's less than that?
Less than that you burn it where you are or if it's
חמץ chametz you do ביטול bittul where you are. Right, it's not
significant enough to go back for. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda so
it's the reverse position because here רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says כביצה
kebeitzah and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says כזית. kezayis. So אמר רבי
יוחנן מוחלפת השיטה. Amar Rabbi Yochanan mukhlefet ha-shitah. Fine, it got reversed,
just switch the names. Okay, that's an answer. That happens. אביי אמר
לעולם לא תיפוך. Abaye amar le'olam lo teipoch. You don't have to
switch the names to make it work. הכא בקראי פליגי. hacha b'krai
pligi. Here by benching they're arguing on what the פסוק pasuk means.
רבי מאיר סבר ואכלת זו אכילה. Rabbi Meir savar v'achalta zo achilah.
You should eat, that's eating. ושבעת זו שתיה. v'savata zo shtiyah. Interesting.
It's drinking. Doesn't mean fill yourself up. It means like a satisfying
eating, one that's accompanied with drink. ואכילה בכזית v'achilah bi-chezayis and a
כזית kezayis is considered an act of eating. רבי יהודה סבר ואכלת.
Rabbi Yehuda savar v'achalta. ואכלת ושבעת, v'achalta v'savata, you should eat and
be satisfied, אכילה שיש בה שביעה. achila she'yesh ba svia.
Now, an eating that leads to being satisfied. ואיזו, v'eizo, what is
this? זו כביצה. zu k'beitzah. That is a כביצה, k'beitzah, an egg
of food. Now before we get to how the other case about
the meat and the קדשים, kodshim, until now we've been assuming that
biblically based on other גמרות Gemaros that biblically until you fill yourself
up it's not דאורייתא d'oraisa and כזית k'zayis and כביצה k'beitzah is
a rabbinic amount. The way the גמרא's framing it here, it sounds
not that way. It sounds that there's possibilities that even as little
as a כזית k'zayis or כביצה k'beitzah could be a biblical amount
for ברכת המזון. Birkas Hamazon. Number one, how do you explain it?
Number one, one approach de-emphasizes ושבעת. v'savata. It's really about ואכלת, v'achalta,
when you do something considered eating, that obligates ברכת המזון Birkas Hamazon,
even if it doesn't fill you, you ate. That's enough כזית, k'zayis,
okay, which is not only but that's how we're reading it as
even as a דאורייתא. d'oraisa. The other position, although he reads satisfying,
doesn't say in this instance it has to have filled you up.
It's saying a type of eating that has the potential to be
filling. You know, so if you eat a certain amount that was
that could be filling, even if it didn't fill you up right
now, that also demands a ברכת המזון. Birkas Hamazon So if you
take this גמרא literally, it really is saying that you could have
a biblical obligation even less than being filled, even as little as
a כביצה k'beitzah or כזית, k'zayis, and possibly the כזית k'zayis approach
is that it's more about eating than it is about being satisfied,
which is a sort of different approach that we have been saying.
So that's what this debate is. Let's finish the גמרא. Okay. Now
how about the issue about the meat? והתם בבשרא פליגי, v'hasam b'visra
pligi, that's not a פסוק, pasuk, it's just a סברא. svara. רבי
מאיר סבר חזרתו כטומאתו, Rabbi Meir savar chazarato k'tumaso, when you return,
the amount that's significant for returning for meat is the amount that's
significant for
טומאה. tumah. מה טומאתו בכביצה, mah tumaso b'khabeitzah, טומאה's tumah with a
כביצה, k'beitzah, אף חזרתו בכביצה, aph chazarato b'khabeitzah, you go back for
כביצה. k'beitzah. Now in some הלכות halachos even a small amount is
מטמא, metamei, but there's some aspects in which you need an egg
size for טומאה. tumah. So that as since this is about becoming
פסול, pasul, you know, invalid in meat, so similar ideas, the meat
becoming טמא tamei and this is the significant size when we're dealing
with issues about קדשים kodshim that become פסול. pasul. That's what he
says. רבי יהודה סבר, Rabbi Yehuda savar, no, חזרתו כאיסורו, chazarato k'issuro,
it's based on what the forbidden aspect of it, מה איסורו בכזית,
mah issuro b'khazayis, the same way you're not allowed to eat a
כזית k'zayis of קדשים kodshim that is
פסול, pasul, אף חזרתו בכזית, aph chazarato b'khazayis, so returning you return
for a כזית. k'zayis. Now it doesn't mention חמץ, chametz, but we're
also returning for חמץ. chametz. So it could be that, you know,
somehow I don't know for whatever reason חמץ chametz followed the קדשים,
kodshim, but that could also be why he had the second opinion
says you go by כזית, k'zayis, maybe he starts with the חמץ
chametz as the paradigm. So by חמץ chametz כזית k'zayis is more
dominant as a, you know, that's the איסור כרת issur kares and
that's the focus and why are you doing ביעור חמץ. biur chametz.
So you shouldn't come you know to own it, to eat it
and so on. So there you focus on the כזית k'zayis and
then he applies that to קרבנות. korbonos. So it might be one
picks one model and one picks the other and they apply it
to the other of these two of the קדשים kodshim and the
קרבנות. korbonos. Two questions.
But if it's based on an איסור, issur, which is the second
position, then it'd be even אסור במשהו, osur b'mashahu, right? So shouldn't
you go back for משהו? mashahu?
Yeah, but whatever. It's אסור במשהו osur b'mashahu in terms of like
what you get מלקות malkus for and so on, that's a different
issue. I mean חצי שיעור דאורייתא, chatzi shiur d'oraisa, you know, so
whatever.
The other question is that according to the first position, you're saying
that it's both debating the biblical obligation, one is saying, I understand
the second position that says כביצה k'beitzah is a שיעור shiur to
be משביע masbia you, but what about the first position, when it
says it's a כזית k'zayis but accompanied by drinking. So would you
say if he ate כזית k'zayis but didn't drink.
I don't know. I don't know. Anyway, can we get down to
the question or
no? No. Okay, let's do the next משנה. Mishna All right, so
a lot of fascinating stuff there, moving, notice by the way, we
also transitioned from זימון zimun to ברכת המזון, Birkas Hamazon. right? Both
the text of ברכת המזון and this last discussion, although in the
משנה Mishna it's about זימון, zimun, seems very much in the גמרא
about what is the obligation for ברכת המזון. So let's take a
look at that. כיצד מזמנין. Keitzad mezamnin. Now back to זימון. zimun.
What is the text of the זימון? zimun? So בשלושה אומר נברך.
b'shlosha omer nevarech. With three you say
נברך שאכלנו משלו. nevarech she'achlanu mishelo. בשלושה והוא אומר ברכו, b'shlosha v'hu
omer barchu, you bless, because three is enough to bless, so I
can, so if I have to be one of the three I
say נברך. nevarech. But if you three could do it all by
yourself, right? There's a זימון zimun without me, I can call on
you ברכו, barchu, I don't have to include myself in that group.
So he says רבותי ברכו? rabosai barchu?
Yeah, let's see what the גמרא says. Yes. So בעשרה אומר נברך
אלוהינו. b'asara omer nevarech Lokeinu. With ten you say אלוהינו. Lokeinu. בעשרה
והוא אומר ברכו, b'asara v'hu omer barchu, same idea if it's ten
plus you instead of נברך nevarech becomes ברכו. barchu. אחד עשרה ואחד
עשרה ריבו. Echad asara v'echad asara ribo.
Now the same text is whether it's ten or whether it's a
hundred thousand, ten ten-thousands, ten myriads. במאה הוא אומר, b'meiah hu omer,
then the משנה mishna. after saying it's the exact same text, now
gives you different text. So we'll see about this in the גמרא.
במאה הוא אומר b'meiah hu omer with a hundred you say not
just אלוהינו Lokeinu but נברך ה׳ אלוהינו. nevarech Hashem Lokeinu. במאה והוא
אומר ברכו. b'meiah v'hu omer barchu. Okay again the נברך nevarech and
the ברכו barchu if you're one extra. But anyway the point is
things when you hit a hundred according to this you add השם,
Hashem, השם אלקינו. Hashem Elokeinu. ובאלף הוא אומר U've'elef hu omer if
you hit a thousand you say נברך להשם אלקינו אלקי ישראל. N'varech
l'Hashem Elokeinu Elokei Yisrael. Okay, the אלף הוא אומר elef hu omer
ברכו. barchu. So you add God of ישראל again more they're there
the more the sense of the presence of the שכינה Shechinah of
God's presence or the more the presence of ישראל seen as representative
of ישראל. Okay, בריבוא birivo with ten thousand אומר omer נברך להשם
אלקינו אלקי ישראל אלקי צבאות יושב הכרובים. N'varech l'Hashem Elokeinu Elokei Yisrael
Elokei Tzevaot Yoshev HaKeruvim. So God of hosts who dwells on the
cherubs so who sits upon the cherubs. So when would you have
I don't know when you would have this maybe they had I
was going to say at the סיום הש"ס Siyum HaShas they could
have done this.
How many people have to have
eaten?
Maybe maybe only 7,000 right because it's a
רובא דמינכר ruba d'minkar or something. Good question. I have no idea.
על המזון Al Hamazon by the way though we had יושב הכרובים
Yoshev HaKeruvim early in the מסכתא masechta if you remember it says
you know when who was it כהן גדול Cohen Gadol when he
was came in he says to בפנים ולפנים bifnai v'lifnai and it
says וראיתי
השם צבאות יושב הכרובים v'raiti Hashem Tzevaot Yoshev HaKeruvim and he said
ברכני בני ברכני barchini b'ni barchini right.
That was בפנים ולפנים bifnai v'lifnai I know I know I don't
know. Okay I don't know. Anyway על המזון al hamazon okay now
this
is already let
us bless God על המזון שאכלנו. Al Hamazon she'achalnu. So here finally
it actually adds the end of that not just God's name but
actually adds על המזון al hamazon for the for the for the
sustenance which we ate. בריבוא והוא Birivo vehu if there's ten thousand
and one אומר omer ברכו. barchu. כעין שמברך כך עונים אחריו. Ke'ein
shemevarech kach onim acharav.
Same way you say נברך אלקינו n'varech eloheinu so you say ברוך
אלקינו. baruch eloheinu. If you say נברך השם אלקינו n'varech Hashem eloheinu
you say ברוך השם אלקינו. baruch Hashem eloheinu. So whatever text I
say you say back to me except I say נברך n'varech and
you say ברוך. ברוך השם אלקינו אלקי ישראל אלקי צבאות יושב הכרובים
על המזון שאכלנו משלו. Baruch Hashem eloheinu elokei Yisrael elokei tzevaot yoshev
hakeruvim al hamazon she'achalnu mishelo. So it uses the full text if
that's your case ten thousand then you respond back the exact same
one. Now רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili אומר omer לפי רוב
הקהל הן מברכים lefi rov hakahal hen mivarchim based on the numbers
that's the ברכה שנאמר במקהלות ברכו אלקים ממקור ישראל shene'emar bemakhelot barchu
elohim mimikor Yisrael with the sort of congregation praise God from the
source the wellspring of ישראל. אמר רבי עקיבא Amar Rabbi Akiva אמר
רבי עקיבא amar Rabbi Akiva מה מצינו בבית כנסת אחד מרובין ואחד
מועטין mah matzinu beveit kneset echad merubin ve'echad muatin he says no
it's just like in שול shul in the שול shul it doesn't
matter if you have 10 it doesn't matter if you have 10,000
אומר omer ברכו את השם barchu et Hashem the same ברכו את
השם. barchu et Hashem. So what the גמרא says is this debate
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael is exactly
the debate earlier in the משנה. mishna All of the text of
the משנה mishna that gave all those different texts for a hundred
a thousand ten thousand was all רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael who says
it reflects the number. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says it's just
like in שול shul it's the same if you have 10 or
if you have 10,000 that was the line earlier in the משנה
mishna that says it doesn't matter how many you have. So the
two versions in the משנה mishna. were really a conflation of a
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position and a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael position.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the numbers don't matter once you hit
10 and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says it always varies based on
the numbers.
Then רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael I'm sorry רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili right. So רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGlili says it goes by the numbers and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says once you hit 10 it doesn't matter. Then רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Ishmael אומר omer as a footnote רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says since
we're talking about שול shul I should mention it's not ברכו את
השם barchu et Hashem it's ברכו את השם המבורך barchu et Hashem
hamivorach which is the נוסח nusach that we say in שול shul
when we say ברכו barchu and that wraps up this משנה.