Today's דף daf is
צדי ו Tzaddi Vav 96 and today's דף daf is צדי ו
Tzaddi Vav 96 and we pick up at the bottom of צדי
ה עמוד ב Tzaddi Hey Amud Bet and what we're dealing with
is the debate in the משנה Mishnah if somebody finds תפילין Tefillin
on the street and there's a way how to have, and there's
no עירוב, Eruv, there's no walls, how do you get them into
the house? And or not in the house, well yeah in the
house, and you wear them. So can you wear one pair at
a time or two pairs at a time? That was debated. What's
the debate? So the גמרא Gemara has been saying that the debate
is a couple of possibilities: number one, whether שבת Shabbos is a
זמן תפילין, zman Tefillin, a time when you wear תפילין. Tefillin. Ironically,
if it is a time when you wear תפילין, Tefillin, you're limited
to one because then you look at it through the lens of
the מצוה. mitzvah. If it's not a time, then in theory you
could wear two because it's not looked at from the מצוה mitzvah
perspective, it's looked at as just a type of a garment, and
interesting choice of garments, but a garment nonetheless and therefore you can
wear two. More than two not, because more than two תפילין, Tefillin,
there's only place to put on two תפילין Tefillin in the place
תפילין Tefillin go and if you were wearing it somewhere else, it
would be like wearing a tie
around your leg. So therefore it's not even considered wearing it as
a garment. Now the other reason, if it's not זמן תפילין, zman
Tefillin, it's more able to wear two is not just which lens
you look it through, but, and this is going to be the
focus of the גמרא, Gemara, the fact that it's not an issue
of בל תוסיף, Bal Tosif, of adding to the מצוה. mitzvah. Adding
to the מצוה mitzvah is much more when it's the time of
the מצוה mitzvah and you change its
parameters, so like you take two לולבים lulavim at one time on
סוכות, Succos, but if I were to take a לולב lulav right
now, it would be very hard to see that as בל תוסיף;
Bal Tosif; it would be stupid but it wouldn't be בל תוסיף
Bal Tosif because you wouldn't have the core מצוה mitzvah to begin
with in order to expand. So if שבת Shabbos is not the
time of תפילין, Tefillin, it's harder to be over on בל תוסיף,
Bal Tosif, you don't look at it as basing yourself on the
מצוה mitzvah as much and therefore two pairs is not a problem.
But if you are over on בל תוסיף, Bal Tosif, like if
שבת Shabbos were the time of תפילין, Tefillin, not only would it
be a בל תוסיף Bal Tosif problem, but presumably it would be
a שבת Shabbos problem as well because then the extra pair would
be very clearly labeled as superfluous. So that is one approach as
to whether שבת Shabbos is the זמן תפילין zman Tefillin or not.
And now we pick up two lines from the bottom, ואיבעיא אימא.
ve'iba'ya eima.
I have a very quick question.
I'd really rather not. Let's look two lines on the bottom, ואיבעיא
אימא, ve'iba'ya eima, you can ask it in a minute or two.
ואיבעיא אימא, ve'iba'ya eima, to two lines on the bottom of צדי
ה עמוד ב, Tzaddi Hey Amud Bet, דכולי עלמא שבת זמן תפילין
הוא, dekhulei alma Shabbos zman Tefillin hu, everybody agrees שבת Shabbos is
the time of תפילין. Tefillin. Okay, so how do you get around
this issue about two, why is that acceptable, what about the whole
בל תוסיף Bal Tosif issue that comes up? והכא במצוות צריכות כוונה
קמיפלגי, vehakha bemitzvos tzrichos kavanah kamiflgi, here the debate is whether you
need כוונה kavanah in order to be יוצא yotzeh a מצוה. mitzvah.
תנא קמא סבר לאתצואי בעי כוונה, Tanna Kamma savar le'atztu'ei ba'ei kavanah,
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds in order to be יוצא מצוה
yotzei mitzvah you need כוונה kavanah and you don't have כוונה kavanah
here. ורבן גמליאל סבר לא בעי כוונה, veRabban Gamliel savar lo ba'ei
kavanah, and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds you don't need כוונה. kavanah.
Now how is that relevant to one or two? So רש"י Rashi
basically says the assumption at this stage is that what is required
to be fulfilled, the מצוה, mitzvah is what is also required to
transgress בל תוסיף. Bal Tosif. If you don't need כוונה kavanah to
fulfill the מצוה, mitzvah, we define it as a מצוה mitzvah, without
כוונה, kavanah, then that same way it applies to תפילין Tefillin number
one, it applies to תפילין Tefillin number two. So if you're wearing
two pairs, then we say you're expanding the מצוה. mitzvah But if
מצוות צריכות כוונה, mitzvos tzrichos kavanah, therefore it's not defined as a
מצוה mitzvah. without your intention, it also wouldn't be בל תוסיף Bal
Tosif without your intention. And since you're wearing two pairs not for
the purpose of a מצוה, mitzvah don't tell me I'm expanding the
מצוה. mitzvah, I'm not wearing it for the purpose of the מצוה,
mitzvah. I'm just wearing it to get it into the house. So
therefore it is not בל תוסיף. Bal Tosif. So what presumably define
what you need to fulfill the מצוה mitzvah, defines what's part of
the מצוה mitzvah act, and therefore if כוונה kavanah is needed, it's
less you would not be over on בל תוסיף. Bal Tosif.
So if I take my second אתרוג esrog and just because I
like the smell of it, am I over on בל תוסיף?
Bal Tosif? According to this, that is correct. And now the גמרא
Gemara is more explicit top of צדי ו עמוד א Tzaddi Vav
Amud Aleph about about the exact בל תוסיף Bal Tosif aspect. ואיבעיא
אימא, ve'iba'ya eima, if you want you could say, דכולי עלמא לצאת
לא בעי כוונה, dekhulei alma latzet lo ba'ei kavanah, everybody agrees that
fulfilling the מצוה mitzvah when you're actually doing the right thing at
the right time, you don't need כוונה kavanah to be יוצא. yotzeh
That by itself almost defines itself as the מצוה mitzvah act. But
maybe you need more to be over on בל תוסיף Bal Tosif
because there you're doing something wrong and to incorporate this additional thing
into the מצוה, mitzvah that's not naturally defined as the מצוה, mitzvah,
that needs your specific intention to incorporate it into the מצוה. mitzvah,
והכא לעבור משום בל תוסיף קמיפלגי, vehakha la'avor mishum Bal Tosif kamiflgi,
to be over משום mishum בל תוסיף. Bal Tosif. דתנא קמא סבר
לעבור משום בל תוסיף לא בעי כוונה, deTanna Kamma savar la'avor mishum
Bal Tosif lo ba'ei kavanah, that once you're doing the מצוה mitzvah.
and you're doing that without כוונה, kavanah, you know you're יוצא yotzeh.
it without כוונה, kavanah, so if you have other components to the
מצוה mitzvah like an extra pair of תפילין Tefillin or you're taking
an extra לולב lulav in your hand and you weren't doing it
for the sake of the מצוה, mitzvah you were doing it to
see how it feels, doesn't matter, you're doing the מצוה, mitzvah, you're
doing it with an extra component, that's בל תוסיף Bal Tosif and
therefore wearing two תפילין Tefillin would be בל תוסיף Bal Tosif and
would be that problem and presumably also a שבת Shabbos problem. ורבן
גמליאל סבר לעבור משום בל תוסיף בעי כוונה.
veRabban Gamliel
savar la'avor mishum Bal Tosif ba'ei kavanah. No, the same way by
taking the לולב, lulav, we'll do that example, you're not יוצא, yotzeh
excuse me, I said that wrong, even though for taking the original
לולב lulav You're יוצא yotzeh, without כוונה, kavana, that's 'cause it's the
מצוה. mitzvah, But if you have another לולב lulav in your hand,
that doesn't become part of the מצוה mitzvah. unless you want it
to be part of the מצוה. mitzvah And here too, if you're
wearing two תפילין, tefillin, so if you were just wearing one תפילין
tefillin you'd be יוצא yotzei without any כוונה, kavana, but then when
you put on your second one and you're doing it in order
to bring it indoors, the fact that you happen to be wearing
two תפילין tefillin is not בל תוסיף, bal tosif, it doesn't become
incorporated into the מצוה mitzvah. act unless you have that intention. And
since you are not being over on בל תוסיף, bal tosif, presumably
it's not a שבת Shabbos problem either, because presumably then it could
be considered just as a type of another type of a garment
that you are wearing. And it's not considered inappropriate because in theory
it's possible to wear two תפילין tefillin as long as you don't
have intent for the second one to be part of the מצוה.
mitzvah Okay, so the basic point here is is that how could
you wear two תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbos or any time by
not being over on בל תוסיף? bal tosif? How could you not
be over on בל תוסיף? bal tosif? Either 'cause שבת Shabbos is
not the time of the מצוה mitzvah. or it is the time
of the מצוה mitzvah but you don't have intent and generally מצוות
mitzvos require intent, or even if generally מצוות mitzvos don't require intent
to incorporate another object into the מצוה mitzvah act, that does require
intent and therefore you would not be over בל תוסיף bal tosif
and could wear two pairs of תפילין. tefillin. Yes.
Does the גמרא Gemara use that different answer we started the day
with on the דף daf of yesterday?
Yesterday it was about whether שבת Shabbos was זמן תפילין. zman tefillin.
Today, previous to this we had about כוונה.
kavana. That was about generally whether מצוות mitzvos need כוונה. kavana. Here
we're making a sharper point that even if מצוות mitzvos don't need
כוונה, kavana, so when I take the לולב lulav and I'm just
taking it to see what you know to look to I don't
know I'm lifting up the אתרוג esrog to smell it and I'm
not thinking about the מצוה, mitzvah I would still be יוצא yotzei
because I happen to be picking up an אתרוג esrog on סוכות.
Sukkos. Okay, so even if מצוות mitzvos don't need כוונה kavana but
if I do the same with a second אתרוג esrog at the
same time, that would not be part of the מצוה mitzvah, act.
In order to incorporate something external, that requires an active כוונה kavana
even if the base מצוה mitzvah does not really require it.
And what did we say? Although the משנה mishna is different from
when he found the תפילין, tefillin, it has to be during the
day, right? Because it was at night, everyone, so
right, presumably it's during the day and I mean in a way
it indicated that because it spoke about if you can't wear them
then you cover it and you wait until nightfall. So it was
presumably the day anyway, and we'll get to the nightfall issue in
a minute. Okay, yes.
My understanding is that you don't wear תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbat
because they don't want you to carry.
No, you don't wear תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbat because שבת Shabbat
itself is an אות. os. Right. And we're about to, we're going
to get to that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So that's a very nice different ways of explaining the debate, all
boiling down to is it a בל תוסיף bal tosif issue or
not? Okay. ואי בעית אימא, Vi-ee ba'is-ei-ma, and
if you want
you could say, five lines from the top, אי דסבירא לן ee
de-sevi-ra lan דשבת זמן תפילין, de-Shabbos zman tefillin, were we to hold
שבת Shabbos was the זמן תפילין, zman tefillin, דכולי עלמא de-khulei alma
לא לעבור בעא כוונה ולא לצאת בעא כוונה, lo la'avor ba'ei kavana
velo litzos bei kavana, that actually you'd be יוצא yotzei מצוה mitzvah
without כוונה kavana in their right time and you'd be over on
בל תוסיף bal tosif without כוונה. kavana. So it would be a
real problem because there would be no way of getting out of
it being בל תוסיף. bal tosif. So if שבת Shabbos was the
זמן תפילין zman tefillin and you wore two pairs, whatever your כוונה
kavana would be, it'd be a problem. So what's the issue? והכא,
Ve-hakha, here's the issue, בלעבור שלא בזמנו קמיפלגי. be-la'avor she-lo bi-zmano ka
mipalgi. But before we assumed that if שבת Shabbos was not זמן
תפילין zman tefillin you're totally safe. Okay, because you don't look at
it through the מצוה mitzvah lens and anyway because it's not בל
תוסיף bal tosif because I said it's like taking a לולב lulav
today or you know and
therefore it would completely not be a בל תוסיף bal tosif problem.
גמרא Gemara says maybe not, maybe this is the debate. Can you
be over on בל תוסיף bal tosif שלא בזמנו? she-lo bi-zmano? To
wearing two pairs of תפילין tefillin on שבת, Shabbos, which is not
the time, is it possible to be over on בל תוסיף, bal
tosif, it's like if I took a לולב, lulav, you know, on
ל"ג בעומר, Lag B'Omer, is that בל תוסיף? bal tosif? Okay, is
it possible שלא בזמנו? she-lo bi-zmano? Okay, והכא בלעבור שלא בזמנו קמיפלגי.
ve-hakha be-la'avor she-lo bi-zmano ka mipalgi. תנא קמא Tana kamma סבר, savar,
the תנא קמא Tana kamma who said only one pair on שבת,
Shabbos, לא בעא כוונה, lo ba'ei kavana, you don't need כוונה kavana
and you'll be over on בל תוסיף bal tosif even if שבת
Shabbos is not the time of תפילין. tefillin. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
סבר savar לעבור שלא בזמנו בעא כוונה, la'avor she-lo bi-zmano ba'ei kavana,
you need כוונה kavana and therefore you can wear two pairs, געזונטהייט.
gezunteheit.
What about the one or two?
Ah, excellent. So Michael is of course already two steps ahead. אי
הכי Ee hakhi says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's the issue, ורבי
מאיר זוגא חדא נמי לא, ve-Rabbi Meir zuga chada nami lo, so
we're associating the תנא קמא Tana kamma with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
but okay, according to the תנא קמא Tana kamma you shouldn't be
able to wear one pair of תפילין tefillin on שבת. Shabbos. Right?
If to transgress בל תוסיף bal tosif שלא בזמנו she-lo bi-zmano you
could do without כוונה, kavana, so then how would they allow you
to do even one pair of תפילין tefillin on שבת? Shabbos? ועוד,
Ve-od, and in addition,
הישן בשמיני בסוכה ילקה, ha-yashen bi-shmini be-sukka yelakeh, we we say, I
mean we would say we eat on שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres in
a סוכה, sukka, we won't talk here about different מנהגים minhagim but
according to the גמרא Gemara you're supposed to eat on שמיני עצרת
Shemini Atzeres in a you know on a סוכה, sukka, thank you.
The גמרא Gemara refers to it as sleeping because again we won't
talk about that we have plenty to talk about when we get
to מסכת סוכה, masechet sukka, but thank you though but but according
to the גמרא Gemara obviously you don't only eat in a סוכה
sukka but you sleep in a סוכה. sukka. So it says if
we sleep in a סוכה sukka on שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres, that's
שלא בזמנו she-lo bi-zmano because biblically the מצות סוכה mitzvat sukka ended
on the seventh day of סוכות, Sukkos, we could say ah well
I'm not having כוונה kavana to be מוסיף, mosif, I'm only doing
it because of ספיקא דיומא, sefeika de-yoma, I'm only doing it because
חז"ל Chazal told me to do it. What do I know? Okay,
if בל תוסיף bal tosif שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano doesn't need כוונה,
kavanah, you should be עובר over in בל תוסיף. bal tosif. So
clearly says the גמרא, Gemara,
שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, you cannot be עובר over on without כוונה.
kavanah. Okay, and if I took a לולב lulav today, or I
put on תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbos even if it wasn't the
right time, or I sat in the סוכה sukkah on שמיני עצרת,
Shemini Atzeret, if I'm not doing it with the intention to add,
I am certainly not עובר. over. And I should say one interesting
question. Let's say, however, I had the כוונה kavanah to be מוסיף.
mosif. So if I sat in the סוכה sukkah on שמיני עצרת
Shemini Atzeret because I said, I am doing this not just because
of ספקא דיומא, safeika deyoma, because I want the biblical מצוה mitzvah
סוכה sukkah to be eight days, that would be בל תוסיף. bal
tosif. Okay, or let's say I wore תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbos
and I'm saying, I am doing this because I believe that the
מצוה mitzvah of תפילין tefillin applies seven days a week and I
want this to be part of the מצוה mitzvah of תפילין, tefillin,
not because I was, then I would be עובר over בל תוסיף.
bal tosif. How about if I took a לולב lulav today with
כוונה, kavanah, I want לולב lulav to be a מצוה mitzvah to
do on, I don't know, the second day of תמוז, Tammuz, or
whatever today is, the third day of תמוז. Tammuz. So would that
be בל תוסיף? bal tosif? So that maybe not, because there it
is completely separate from, even chronologically separate from the original מצוה. mitzvah.
Even if you're שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, if you're the next day,
what you've done is you've expanded סוכה sukkah from a seven-day מצוה
mitzvah to an eight-day מצוה, mitzvah, or לולב lulav from a seven-day
מצוה mitzvah to an eight, or תפילין tefillin from a six-day מצוה
mitzvah to a seven. So you've worked with the base מצוה mitzvah
and you've expanded it. By taking לולב lulav today, I haven't expanded
the biblical מצוה mitzvah of לולב, lulav, I've made up a brand
new ritual on the third day of תמוז. Tammuz. So it could
be that that even with כוונה kavanah could be I'm not עובר
over when it's in no way juxtaposed to the original מצוה. mitzvah.
But if I do it every
day until then, then I would be
עובר.
over.
But בל תוסיף bal tosif wouldn't apply to creating a new מצוה?
mitzvah?
It might not, because according to חז״ל, Chazal, בל תוסיף bal tosif
they define it in very narrow terms of expanding a מצוה mitzvah
from its base. Okay, now here's an interesting question. What if rather
than doing it as the second or third day of תמוז, Tammuz,
whatever day it is. Anyway, third day of תמוז. Tammuz. Oh sorry,
fourth. Okay, so today's so today's fourth day of תמוז. Tammuz. Fine.
What if, what if I took the לולב lulav on פסח, Pesach,
on ליל סדר, Leil Seder, and I said, would that be בל
תוסיף? bal tosif? Maybe it wouldn't be בל תוסיף bal tosif of
adding to the לולב lulav מצוה, mitzvah, but maybe it would be
בל תוסיף bal tosif in adding to the פסח Pesach מצות, mitzvos,
you know? But anyway, for חז״ל Chazal needed for בל תוסיף bal
tosif a base of the original מצוה. mitzvah. Anyway, but what it's
saying here is שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano without כוונה, kavanah, there's no
way you
could be עובר. over. Then even one pair of תפילין tefillin wouldn't
be acceptable, then you couldn't sit in a סוכה sukkah on שמיני
עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. So that clearly would not be an issue.
So if you sit... how can you put on two pair of
תפילין tefillin at one time?
Why not? Because you're adding to the מצוה? mitzvah?
But how you can put...
there's not enough room? So that's what the גמרא Gemara said yesterday,
that we're talking about small תפילין, tefillin, and if they're small enough,
both will fit in the in the right space. Our תפילין tefillin
today are very big. Okay, they used to have, I don't know
if you've ever seen, did you ever see the תפילין tefillin that
they found in מצדה, Masada, in the, you know,
they're tiny, right? The תפילין tefillin that they used to have are
very, very small, so those would be able to fit.
Yeah, so the question is like let's say, you know, you're taking
your לולב lulav and you said, you know what? I want grapes
to be part of my מצות לולב. mitzvas lulav. So does that,
is that בל תוסיף bal tosif because you're adding on to things
that are in the לולב? lulav? Or it's not because you're just
making up a whole new species?
No, no, it is true, those are questions and we can talk
about them more when we learn the סוגיא, sugya, but in that
would be more possible, especially if you're doing it at the time
of the מצוה. mitzvah. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues like
this.
Okay. אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא. Ela mehvarta keshaninan mei'ikara. It's better like
we said originally that if you're already שבת Shabbos is לאו זמן
תפילין, lav zman tefillin, then you're totally safe and all the debates
are whether שבת Shabbos is זמן תפילין zman tefillin or not, or
if שבת Shabbos is זמן תפילין, zman tefillin, what you need to
be עובר over on בל תוסיף. bal tosif. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, now that we've introduced this question whether שבת
Shabbos is זמן תפילין zman tefillin or not, let's talk about it.
ומאן שמעת ליה, U'man shamat lei, and who have you heard that
says, ומאן שמעת ליה שבת זמן תפילין? u'man shamat lei Shabbos zman
tefillin? רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So now we're going to try to
find the תנא tanna that holds that שבת Shabbos is the time
of תפילין. tefillin. So is who says that? So we're first suggesting
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita:
ושמרת את החקה הזאת למועדה מימים ימימה. V'shmarta es hachuka hazos l'moada
miyamim yamima. So this is at the end of one of the
פרשיות parshiyos in the תפילין, tefillin, and it says not the two
פרשיות parshiyos of שמע, Shema,
but the פרשה parsha at the end of בא. Bo. And it
says there that you should observe this ordinance, you know, for all
days. Now the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is talking
about, talking about the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, but because it's one
of the פרשיות parshiyos of תפילין, tefillin, one דרשה drasha is to
see that as referring to the actual the מצוה mitzvah of תפילין
tefillin because that is one of the places the four פרשיות parshiyos
of תפילין tefillin are the four times פרשיות parshiyos in the תורה
Torah where it says that you should be for a sign on
your hand and for זכרון zikaron or for טוטפות totafos between your
eyes. So those are two of those פרשיות parshiyos are at the
end of at the end of בא Bo and it says, you
know, you'll come to this land which God has given
you, שבעת ימים תאכל מצות, shivas yamim tochal matzos, etc, לא יראה
לך חמץ, lo yeira'eh l'cha chametz, והגדת לבנך ביום ההוא לאמר בעבור
זה עשה ה׳ לי בצאתי ממצרים, v'higadta l'vincha bayom hahu leimor ba'avur
zeh asah Hashem li b'tzeisi mimitzrayim, והיה לך לאות על ידך ולזכרון
בין עיניך למען תהיה תורת ה׳ בפיך, v'hayah l'cha l'os al yadecha
u'l'zikaron bein einecha l'maan tihyeh toras Hashem b'ficha, כי ביד חזקה. ki
b'yad chazakah. So is that פשט pshat of course is this thing
to keep is the חג chag of חג המצות chag hamatzot or
the קרבן פסח korban pesach but one reading is it's what we
said just a second ago לאות על ידך ולזכרון בין עיניך. l'ot
al yadcha ul'zikaron bein eineicha. So let's take a look what the
גמרא Gemara says. דתניא ושמרת את החוקה הזאת למועדה מימים ימימה d'tanya
v'shamarta et hachukah hazot l'mo'adah miyamim yamimah ימים ולא לילות. yamim v'lo
leilot. You only do so it assumes we're doing it during the
day. Then we're talking about תפילין tefillin and therefore it says day
and not night, so night is not a time of תפילין. tefillin.
מימים miyamim from the day the from you know from all days
מימים ימימה miyamim yamimah you know from here to till forever, but
it's reading it מימים miyamim some of the days ולא כל ימים
v'lo kol yamim פרט לשבתות וימים טובים prat l'shabatot v'yamim tovim to
exclude שבת Shabbat and יום טוב Yom Tov דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי.
divrei Rabbi Yosei haGlili. Now how do you get to שבת Shabbat
and יום טוב? Yom Tov? תוספות Tosafot says this ultimately is informed
by a דרשה drasha we're going to say later about the idea
of תפילין tefillin being an אות ot and שבת Shabbat being an
אות. ot. But right now we're anchoring it in the פסוק pasuk
that says some of the days and assuming it's talking about תפילין.
tefillin. That's רבי יוסי הגלילי's Rabbi Yosei haGlili position. רבי עקיבא אומר:
Rabbi Akiva omer: No, that's not what the פסוק pasuk is talking
about. לא נאמר חוקה lo ne'emar chukah this idea that it's an
an edict that like has boundaries and limited you know and זו
אלא
לענין פסח בלבד. zo ela l'inyan Pesach bilvad. It's only talking about
bringing the קרבן פסח korban pesach from year to year. So it's
not talking about תפילין. tefillin. So according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
we're assuming if this פסוק pasuk of מימים ימימה miyamim yamimah is
not talking about תפילין tefillin we don't have a basis to exclude
שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov. Maybe we don't have a
basis to exclude nighttime either. Okay, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who
doesn't learn this פסוק pasuk about תפילין, tefillin, he would presumably say
שבת Shabbat is included. Now we're not done. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. ואלא הא דתנן ve'ela ha d'tenan that which we
taught in the משנה: Mishnah: הפסח והמילה מצות עשה. haPesach v'haMilah mitzvot
aseh. The פסח Pesach and מילה Milah are positive מצוה mitzvah and
not a negative one, because this is a משנה Mishnah that says
that there are only two types of things that you get כרת
karet for that you don't have to bring a חטאת chatat if
you didn't do them, or if you whatever transgressed, and those are
פסח Pesach and מילה. Milah. Because those are the only two things
that there are a מצות עשה mitzvot aseh that the lack of
performance doesn't you know get you כרת. karet. As opposed to everything
else where it's a a prohibition and the transgression gets you כרת.
karet. So the only time like חילול שבת chilul Shabbat so the
only time you bring a חטאת chatat is about an active transgressing
a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh that gets כרת, karet, not about the
lack of performance of פסח Pesach and מילה. Milah. But what it
says is therefore that פסח Pesach is only a מצות עשה. mitzvot
aseh. There's no לא תעשה lo ta'aseh of don't not bring the
קרבן פסח. korban pesach. And therefore okay so therefore לימא דלא כرבי
עקיבא. leima d'lo k'Rabbi Akiva. Let's say it's not רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. דאי רבי עקיבא de'ei Rabbi Akiva הא מילה
דכל זכר שלא ימול וסר לו וניחא סיפא.
ha
milah
d'chol zachar shelo yimol v'sar lo v'nicha seifa. What do you do
with that? דאמר וערל זכר אשר לא ימול בשר ערלתו ונכרתה. de'amar
v'arel zachar asher lo yimol b'sar orlato v'nichretah. What do you do
with that?
It does say you shall not, that's descriptive, who has not had
the ברית מילה. brit milah. Okay, so now but since רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says that you should observe this edict מימים ימימה miyamim
yamimah refers to the פסח, Pesach, and we know the phrase ושמרת
v'shamarta normally means heed it do not transgress. So presumably according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva you would have a negative prohibition relating to
the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. לימא דלא כרבי עקיבא? leima d'lo k'Rabbi
Akiva? Would we say that's not רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? דאי רבי
עקיבא de'ei Rabbi Akiva since it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva כיון דמוקמי
לה בפסח keivan d'mokeimi lah b'Pesach since he says that you should
observe this edict means the פסח Pesach לאו נמי איכא. lav nami
ika. So there's a negative prohibition relating to the קרבן פסח. korban
pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says no. כדרבי אבין אמר רבי אילעא.
k'Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila'i. There's an answer to that. Like רבי
אבין אמר רבי אילעא. Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila'i. דאמר רבי אבין
אמר רבי אילעא d'amar Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Ila'i כל מקום שנאמר
השמר פן ואל. kol makom she'ne'emar hashamer pen v'al. Anytime the תורה
Torah says guard yourself lest and you shall not אינו אלא בלא
תעשה. eino ela b'lo ta'aseh. That means it is a negative prohibition,
it is prohibiting something. אפילו afilu but I'm sorry that's part of
the question. So since it says השמר hashamer it should be a
negative prohibition, and therefore according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva פסח Pesach
should be a negative prohibition. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אפילו
תימא רבי עקיבא. afilu teima Rabbi Akiva. It even works according to
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. השמר דלאו לאו השמר דעשה עשה. hashamer d'lav
lav hashamer d'aseh aseh. It all depends on context. If you say
guard yourself lest you do A B and C, lest you you
know eat חמץ chametz בפסח be'Pesach then it is telling you you
shall not. But if it's saying guard yourself to bring the קרבן
פסח korban pesach then it is telling you you shall. Okay, so
the words השמר hashamer guard yourself in the context of not to
do something means it's a negative prohibition. Guard yourself to do something
is a positive. So that just deals with the side issue but
now we're back to our point that if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says that פסוק pasuk is talking about the קרבן פסח korban pesach
it is not talking about תפילין tefillin and תפילין tefillin would apply
even in night. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. וסבר רבי
עקיבא שבת זמן תפילין היא? v'savar Rabbi Akiva Shabbat zman tefillin hi?
Do you really believe that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds שבת Shabbat
is a time as תפילין? tefillin? והתניא v'hatanya we taught in the
ברייתא braita רבי עקיבא אומר: Rabbi Akiva omer: יכול יניח אדם תפילין
בשבתות ובימים טובים? yachol yaniach adam tefillin b'shabatot u'v'yamim tovim? Perhaps a
person should put on תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbat and יום טוב?
Yom Tov? תלמוד לומר והיה לך לאות על ידך. talmud lomar v'hayah
l'cha l'ot al yadcha. They should be a sign on your hand.
מי שצריכין אות mi she'tzrichin ot those who need a sign. יצאו
אלו שהן גופן אות yatz'u elu she'hen gufan ot to exclude these
days that they themselves are a sign and therefore you do not
put on תפילין tefillin not only do you not need to but
presumably you're not allowed to. I don't I'm not exactly sure, maybe
it's a type of בל תוסיף. bal tosif. Maybe the idea that
you put on תפילין tefillin as a sign on שבת Shabbat undermines
the אות ot of שבת. Shabbat. It's as if the אות ot
of שבת Shabbat were not sufficient. So it's seen as an actual
prohibition to wear תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbat because שבת Shabbat itself
is a not it's not only a מצוה mitzvah the actual day
itself the actual full day of שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* is itself an
אות os. *os*. So you see רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
hold that שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* is not זמן תפילין zman tefillin. *zman
tefillin*. Now I want to pause here for a moment and make
two side comments. First of all, there's a love—I think a nice
רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, if you look at the רש"י Rashi *Rashi* of
מי שצריכין אות os *mi shetzrichin os*, it explains before the lines
get wide. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, ימים שישראל צריכין להעמיד אות os
על עצמם להכיר שהם מחזיקים בתורתו של הקדוש ברוך הוא *Yamim sheYisrael
tzrichin le'amid os al atzmam lehakir shehem machazikim b'Toraso shel haKadosh Baruch
Hu*. I just like that phrasing. The sign is not like where
God's chosen people or whatever, the sign of wearing תפילין tefillin. *tefillin*
is a sign to show that we embrace God's מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos*.
There's something nice and active about that, that directly you're, you know,
you're doing this act of wearing and that is an act that
shows how you sort of embrace God's מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos* and it's
על ידך *al yadecha* like very much on your body.
Okay, so I just like that phrasing about the idea of what
the אות os *os* of תפילין tefillin *tefillin*. And יום טוב Yom
Tov,
*Yom Tov*? Well, יום טוב Yom Tov.
*Yom Tov* presumably, it's a good
question how you get יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, because אותי
ביני וביניכם *osi beini uveineichem* is much more about שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*.
It's a very good question. The very idea of of a day
is והיו לאותות ולמועדים *v'hayu l'osos ul'moadim*. Right. But that's a nice
idea. אותות שבת Shabbos *osos Shabbos*. Well, that's about the actual luminaries
are והיו לאותות *v'hayu l'osos*, I don't know that that is directly
about the special days are called an אות *os*. Yeah, but I
think it's a good question, and with the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s easy
assumption that the אות *os* aspect extends—I mean certainly all of these
things are זכר ליציאת מצרים
*zeicher l'yetzias Mitzrayim*, you know, and they're וזכרת כי עבד היית בארץ
מצרים *v'zacharta ki eved hayisa b'eretz
Mitzrayim*, you know, you know, you sit in a סוכה sukkah, *Sukkah*
למען תזכרו *l'ma'an tizkru*, you know, כי בסוכות הושבתי *ki va'sukos hoshavti*,
but is the actual word of רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says because רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* doesn't refer explicitly to the פסוק pasuk
*posuk* that שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* is an אות *os*. Right. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* though does. The רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* of מחזיקים *machazikim* is about
the תפילין tefillin *tefillin*. Then רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, יצאו שבתות וימים
טובים שהן עצמן אות בין הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל דכתיב כי אות
היא ביני וביניכם *yatz'u Shabbosos v'yamim tovim shehen atzman os bein haKadosh
Baruch Hu l'Yisrael deksiv ki os hi beini uveineichem*. Right. Right. Yeah,
it's a good question. But that actually I have to think about,
you know, I'm sure somebody addresses that directly. I actually was just
leapfrog over that and I wanted to mention the big מחלוקת ראשונים
Rishonim *machlokes Rishonim* about חול המועד Chol Hamoed, *Chol HaMoed*. Okay, because
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is never clear about it. Now maybe you'd
say פשט pshat *pshat* of the word יום טוב *Yom Tov* means
only יום טוב *Yom Tov*, right, but it's a little ambiguous and
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* never clearly addresses it. It's a huge מחלוקת
*machlokes* in the time of the ראשונים *Rishonim* and this became a
major area where קבלה *Kabbalah* played a big role in that whole
debate about חול המועד Chol Hamoed. *Chol HaMoed*. And so I just
wanted to quickly just, you know, mention it. If you look at
the תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos*, ימים *Yamim*, the top תוספות Tosfos, *Tosafos* on
the page, פרט לשבתות ויום טוב *perat l'Shabbosos v'Yom Tov*, תוספות Tosfos
*Tosafos* says, נראה דדרשה דלאות על ידך דבסמוך דסמוך ולכאורה אין להניח
תפילין tefillin, בחול המועד שאין צריך אות *Nireh de'drasha d'le'os al yadecha
d'bisamuch d'samuch v'lichura ein l'haniach tefillin b'Chol HaMoed she'ein tzarich os*. How
do we know you don't need an אות *os* on חול המועד
*Chol HaMoed*? דאסור במלאכה *d'assur b'melacha*, okay, דבדבר שאינו אבד *d'bidvar she'eino
aved*. So first of all you can't do certain מלאכה *melacha* on
חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*, so that makes חול המועד *Chol HaMoed* a
distinct day presumably reminds you that's a day is related to יום
טוב *Yom Tov*. So that's enough of an active symbol of the
special nature of the day. ועוד חייב chayav בסוכה בחג ובפסח אסור
באכילת חמץ *V'od chayiv b'Sukkah b'Chag u'v'Pesach assur b'achilas chametz*. And there
are rituals, not just not doing מלאכה *melacha*, right. And סוכה sukkah,
*Sukkah* is an active ritual of sitting in the חג *Chag* and
sitting in the סוכה *Sukkah*. You notice he didn't say לולב lulav,
*Lulav* because לולב lulav *Lulav* is דרבנן *drabanan* on the other days.
And in and פסח *Pesach* not eating חמץ *chametz*. So there's active,
you know, special rituals that remind you that it's a special day.
What about שבועות *Shavuos*? But so if I bring a... what about
שבועות *Shavuos*? ציצית tzitzis *Tzitzis*? No, no, no. It's a trick question.
No חול המועד *Chol HaMoed* on שבועות *Shavuos*. Okay, anyway, so that's
what תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says. It would seem logical that this day
is a special day and that should be suffice for the אות
*os*, but then he quotes ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* that that he says it's
a clear פשט *pshat* of the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* is you don't wear
it on—is you do wear it on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*. And
then if you look at the bottom line at the bottom of
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos*, he says... he's talking about because the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*
is talking about can you write תפילין tefillin *tefillin* on חול המועד
*Chol HaMoed*? And it sounds like you can write it לצורך המועד
*letzorech
ha'moed* if you're going to wear them
on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*. So if you look like at the
last four lines of תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos*, he says, אבל לצורך המועד
יכול לכתוב אף לאחרים וכן עמא דבר *aval letzorech ha'moed yachol lichtov
af l'acherim v'chein ama davar*. And that is the common practice, he
actually says, to wear תפילין tefillin *tefillin* on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*.
And other people bring another ראיה *raya*. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* himself
says, look, I would think logically you shouldn't, but there's a common
practice to do it. So it's very interesting whether חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed* is included or not. Like I said, it became—קבלה *Kabbalah* became
a big issue about the זהר *Zohar*'s position in it. And, you
know, what a lot of people wear—my, you know, I started one
way
because my father had a חסידיש *Chassidish* background and then I sort
of switched or whatever. And then my current מנהג
*minhag* is, what I do is I wear it without a ברכה
beracha? *bracha*, but half the time I, you know, I just go
into autopilot. I'm putting it on, I made the ברכה beracha *bracha*,
though darn, I'm not supposed to be making... anyway, but so the
wearing it on and think all the time to not for the
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*. Right, right, right. So wearing it without a ברכה
beracha *bracha* is an interesting compromise because it, a, it sort of
says you're play—you'll play it safe, you'll be יוצא *yotzei*, you know,
you'll do it if it's a מצוה mitzvah? *mitzvah*, but you don't
want to make a ברכה beracha לבטלה *bracha l'vatala*, which is sort
of why I do it. It also somewhat gets to the whole
בל תוסיף ba'al tosif, *bal tosif* type of a question as well,
you know, if you think you're not supposed to do it on
חול המועד *Chol HaMoed* and then you're doing it לצורך המצוה *letzorech
hamitzvah*. So it's a very interesting—the debates around around חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed*. I knew somebody who used to go into work on חול
המועד *Chol HaMoed*... and he wouldn't wear תפילין, tefillin and then when
he stopped going into work on חול המועד, then he started wearing
תפילין. tefillin, So at least he was consistent about how much the
special nature he gave חול המועד. Okay, let's get to קרבן Korban
that day, is that like somehow also from שבות shvus for עשיית
מלאכה? assiyat melacha? So is that enough of a sign? No, no,
no. So it's a good question why the גמרא Gemara extends it
and it's not any special day, right? It's not like ערב פסח
Erev Pesach which is אסור בעשיית מלאכה assur b'assiyat melacha from חצות.
chatzot. It's but right, it's a day that that is associated with
the קדושה kedusha of the day but how the גמרא Gemara extends
it beyond שבת Shabbos. is the point you made before, is a
good question. Okay, let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara אלא, Ela,
so we don't know, so so far רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
you don't wear תפילין tefillin. on שבת. Shabbos So we still want
to know who says you do wear תפילין tefillin on שבת. Shabbos
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא האי תנא הוא, ela hai tanna
hu, the following תנא, tanna, דתניא. detanya. הניעור בלילה, Haneior balayla, if
you're awake at night, רצה חולץ רצה מניח. ratza choletz ratza maniach.
If you're and you happen to be wearing תפילין, tefillin. so you
take it off if you want, but you could also put on
תפילין tefillin. if you want. דברי רבי נתן. divrei Rabbi Natan. That's
the words of רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, which means that לילה זמן
תפילין. layla zman tefillin. There's a major debate. Everybody agrees that in
principle that the practice is you don't wear תפילין tefillin. at night.
The question is why not? Is it because biblically it's only מימים
ימימה, miyamim yamima, a daytime מצוה mitzvah and not a nighttime מצוה?
mitzvah. Or is it no, biblically it could apply at night but
we're afraid you'll fall asleep, nod off and fall asleep, and that
you'll יפיח? yepiach? So this position says that if you and a
big difference would be, you might be, some would say if you
have it already wearing you don't have to take it off, but
you can't לכתחילה lechatchila put it on. Okay, but so but those
that basically allow you to לכתחילה lechatchila put it on clearly hold
that לילה זמן תפילין. layla zman tefillin. ואם תאמר פסח v'im tomar
Pesach or whatever. Anyway, and the concern of passing gas, רש"י Rashi
says that's why it specifically says ניעור, neior, like you're wide awake,
you can't fall asleep, so we're not afraid you're going to pass
gas. Whatever it is, if you're putting it on it's clear that
לילה זמן תפילין. layla zman tefillin. Okay, that's what one, that's what
רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says. רבי יונתן הקיטוני אומר, Rabbi Yonatan Hakitoni
omer, אין מניחין תפילין בלילה. ein manichin tefillin balayla. No, you cannot
put it on actively at night. Maybe you don't have to take
it off. So anyway you see that there's an opinion that says
לילה layla is זמן תפילין. zman tefillin. So the גמרא Gemara says
that means that you reject the
פסוק pasuk of מימים ימימה miyamim yamima
to apply the תפילין tefillin. and you have no limits. So מדלילה
לתנא קמא זמן תפילין, mi'd'layla l'tanna kamma zman tefillin, since for תנא
קמא tanna kamma he holds night is the time of תפילין, tefillin.
שבת נמי זמן תפילין, Shabbos nami zman tefillin, so presumably the פסוק
pasuk doesn't apply and therefore שבת Shabbos also is a time of
תפילין. tefillin. גמרא Gemara says no, who says that they go as
a package deal? דילמא סבירא ליה לילה זמן תפילין הוא שבת לאו
זמן תפילין הוא. dilma sevira leh layla zman tefillin hu Shabbos lav
zman tefillin hu. No, maybe לילה layla is the time and not
שבת. Shabbos How you know that? Because it's exactly what רבי עקיבא
said. דשמעינן ליה לרבי עקיבא דאמר לילה זמן תפילין, d'shaman leh l'Rabbi
Akiva d'amar layla zman tefillin, implicitly רבי עקיבא said לילה layla is
the time of תפילין tefillin because he rejected the פסוק pasuk of
מימים ימימה miyamim yamima to apply the תפילין. tefillin. He said that's
applying to the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. And nevertheless he said, and
he said שבת לאו זמן תפילין הוא, Shabbos lav zman tefillin hu,
but nevertheless he says not שבת. Shabbos, שבת Shabbos is an אות.
So לילה layla is a more arbitrary exclusion. You might exclude לילה,
layla, you might not. But שבת Shabbos maybe everybody excludes it because
of the idea that שבת Shabbos is itself an אות and you
undermine that אות or you can you know you sort of conflict
with that אות when you're putting on תפילין. tefillin So we still
don't know who is the one that says that שבת Shabbos is
the time of תפילין. tefillin So now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. אלא האי תנא הוא. ela hai tanna hu. It maybe
it's the following תנא tanna or it is the following תנא tanna
who says that שבת, Shabbat it's a proof to you that שבת
Shabbat holds the position that שבת Shabbat is the time of תפילין.
tefillin. דתניא, detanya, we talked in a ברייתא, braita, מיכל בת כושי.
Michal bas Kushi. That's an interesting name. Yeah, מיכל Michal the daughter
of the כושי, Kushi, right? Like we just had משה Moshe taking
the אשה כושית. isha Kushis. היתה מנחת תפילין haysa menachas tefillin were
putting on תפילין. tefillin So who is this מיכל בת כושי Michal
bas Kushi first of all? So תוספות Tosfos says, or רש"י Rashi
says, excuse me, that it's actually the daughter of שאול, Shaul, because
we know שאול Shaul had a daughter named of מיכל, Michal, and
there's a פסוק pasuk that uses the phrase כושי Cushi to refer
to שאול. Shaul. So why חז"ל Chazal felt you know that here
they wanted to
refer to her that way I don't know, but okay, so מיכל
Michal used to wear תפילין. tefillin. היתה מנחת תפילין haysa menachas tefillin
ולא מיחו
בה חכמים
v'lo
michu
bah chachamim and the rabbis did not object. ואשתו של יונה היתה
עולה לרגל v'ishto shel Yona haysa ola l'regel and יונה Yona's wife
used to make עליה לרגל aliya l'regel ולא מיחו בה חכמים. v'lo
michu bah chachamim. יונה Yona the prophet, yep, and the rabbis did
not object. So, מדלא מיחו בה חכמים, mi'd'lo michu bah chachamim, since
they didn't object, presumably she was doing the מצוה mitzvah. she was
commanded. אלמא קסברי מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא היא. alma kasavri mitzvas asei
shehazman grama hi. They must have understood that תפילין tefillin was not
a time-bound מצוה. mitzvah So therefore, and if it's not time-bound that
means it has to apply both on שבת Shabbat and and what's
the other time that we were excluded, possibly night? Okay, so therefore
if women are obligated that means you must don't have either time-bounded
nature of it, not שבת Shabbat and not לילה. layla. Now of
course the problem is is that if it really weren't time-bound it
wouldn't just be לא מיחו בה חכמים, lo michu bah chachamim, it
would actually be ברצון חכמים b'ratzon chachamim and actually every woman should
be putting on תפילין. tefillin So it actually makes you wonder like
is the גמרא Gemara. imagining a possibility that women are obligated but
somehow they're you know sort of socially discouraged from doing it? You
know, cause what does it mean לא מיחו בה lo michu bah
at the same time contemplating that they really are fully obligated in
תפילין tefillin? and it's not an option, if you're obligated you have
to do it. So it's quite interesting that גמרא Gemara thinks that
that can reconcile with the phrase. Did it occur to anyone that
maybe she's the the princess, the queen? Yes. That's why they didn't,
oh, haha. Yes, good interesting point too. Okay. ודלמא סברה לה, ve-dilma
savra lah, okay, ודלמא סברה לה כרבי יוסי. ve-dilma savra lah ke-Rabbi
Yose. No, maybe the reason of לא מיחו lo mihu and this
obviously works better with the phrase לא מיחו lo mihu is not
because it's not time-bound, it is time-bound and שבת Shabbat is לאו
זמן תפילין. lav zman tefillin. So why did they not object? Because
just because they're exempt doesn't mean you have to object, doesn't mean
it's a problem. Maybe you hold like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that
says that even מצות mitzvot that women are exempt from they can
do. דלמא דאמר נשים סומכות רשות, dilma de-amar nashim somchot reshut, women
have the right
to do סמיכה smicha on קרבנות. korbanot. They're not obligated but they
are allowed to and we'll
quote that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in a minute.
Okay, דאילו תימא הכי de-ilu teima hachi and I'll prove to you
that we're not assuming they're obligated in this little phrase, in this
little story. Why? Because if you don't say that you want to
assert that they're obligated, אשתו של יונה היתה עולה לרגל ולא מיחו
בה חכמים ishto shel Yona hayta ola la-regel ve-lo mihu bah chachamim
because we also have Jonah's wife would be עליה לרגל. aliya la-regel.
So one minute, מכדי למאן דאמר רגל לאו מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא
הוא? michdi le-man de-amar regel lav mitzvat asei she-ha-zman grama hu? רגל
Regel is clearly a time-bound מצוה. mitzvah So no one would ever
suggest that עליה לרגל aliya la-regel would apply to women especially because
it says יראה כל זכורך. yera'eh kol zechurcha. So anyway, so clearly,
clearly the גמרא Gemara says we're not talking that they're obligated, we're
talking that they're exempt and that they were allowed to do it.
And if that's true by the case of עליה לרגל, aliya la-regel,
it's true about the case of תפילין tefillin and therefore women are
exempt from תפילין. tefillin It is time-bound, שבת Shabbat, is לאו זמן
תפילין lav zman tefillin and it's only that the חכמים chachamim did
not object even though they were exempt. And then we're going to
talk about that about the idea of being exempt and doing it
and whether that leads to objection or not. You wanted to say
something Joe? Yeah, well just in agreement because I mean the fact
that somebody goes to ירושלים Yerushalayim on a רגל... regel... right, does
not mean that she would go to ירושלים Yerushalayim and she brought
a קרבן עולה... korban olah... right, I can imagine a lot of
people bringing their wives... right, right, so although if you read the
story by what's her name, by חנה, Chana, you know, clearly they're
all there but the husband is off in the בית המקדש Beit
Ha-Mikdash doing his you know his stuff. So anyway okay, back to
the גמרא. Gemara So clearly it means that they're exempt but they
did it anyway and חז"ל Chazal would not object. So the גמרא
Gemara says we're trying to prove whether שבת Shabbat is זמן תפילין.
zman tefillin. So if a woman were חייב chayav. in תפילין tefillin.
clearly שבת Shabbat would be זמן תפילין. zman tefillin But it's saying
that you cannot prove from this story that a woman is חייב.
chayav The פשט of the story is that she was exempt because
it is time-bound but still nevertheless they didn't object. And now we're
going to look at that issue. First we're going to get to
the answer of שבת Shabbat being exempt and we'll circle back to
this issue about women being exempt and objecting or not. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אלא קסבר רשות, ela kasavar reshut, by
עליה לרגל aliya la-regel it was a רשות, reshut, הכא נמי רשות,
hacha nami reshut, so it's a רשות reshut so it is time-bound,
you're still stuck, you can't find anybody that says שבת shabbos is
the time of תפילין. tefillin. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא האי
תנא היא, ela hai tanna hi, the following תנא tanna is he,
דתניא, de-tanya, המוצא תפילין מכניסן זוג זוג, ha-motzei tefillin machnisan zug zug,
אחד איש ואחד אשה, echad ish ve-echad isha, אחד חדשות
ואחד ישנות.
echad chadashot
ve-echad yeshanot.
So it's not
what we have in our משנה, mishna, you could wear the תפילין
tefillin. in one pair at a time whether man or woman, whether
old or new. So the new he's not afraid that it's like
an amulet but more significantly he allows a woman to do it.
Now if he allows a woman to do it, you could say
well maybe she's not obligated and it's just like a piece of
clothing. But if you'll remember when we learned שבת, shabbos clothing that
is normally worn by women, worn by men or vice versa is
considered a burden, not clothing. It has to be considered a within
the normal bounds of this gender to be wearing this object of
clothing. So if a woman could wear תפילין tfillin it shows that
she's obligated. If so, שבת shabbos is זמן תפילין zman tefillin and
she's doing the מצוה Mitzvah or it's not זמן תפילין zman tefillin
and it's normal for her. But one minute, if it's not זמן
תפילין zman tefillin why would it ever be normal for a woman
to wear תפילין? tfillin. And again even if maybe it's sometimes a
woman would do it, it certainly wasn't the norm. So if we're
assuming that a woman could wear תפילין tfillin when she finds it
on the street, it means that it's normal for women to wear
תפילין tfillin which means it's שבת Shabbat, is זמן תפילין zman tefillin
and women are obligated. According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, it could
be that רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, no one listened to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would פסקן pasken women should
be wearing תפילין. tfillin רבי יהודה אוסר בחדשות ומתיר בישנות. Rabbi Yehuda
oser be-chadashot u-matir be-yeshanot. And even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only disagrees
in terms of don't do the new ones, those might be קמיעות.
kmei'ot. עד כאן לא פליגי אלא
בחדשות וישנות.
ad kan lo pligi
ela be-chadashot ve-yeshanot.
They're only arguing about new versus old, אבל באשה לא פליגי. aval
be-isha lo pligi. So by woman they don't disagree and therefore presumably
they feel that it's
normal for a woman to wear תפילין. tefillin It must be that
שבת Shabbos, is זמן תפילין zman tfillin and therefore women are obligated.
שמע מינה מצות עשה שלא הזמן גרמא היא וכל מצות עשה שאינה
הזמן גרמא נשים חייבות. shma mina mitzvat asei she-lo ha-zman grama hi
ve-chol mitzvat asei she-einah ha-zman grama nashim chayavot. So you see that
it is not time-bound because it's okay for women to be wearing
תפילין. tefillin So the גמרא Gemara now says no, again back to
what we said before, you don't have
to be obligated for it to be an acceptable practice.
But the גמרא Gemara is saying is that, okay, but the גמרא
Gemara is saying, you know, all of those things, there were ranges
of what's considered normal, but maybe the גמרא Gemara at least is
saying you can't prove that women are obligated. It might be that
it's considered normal within the normal enough range, at least theoretically normal,
that it would be allowed for her to do. Would it be
different if the kid found it, who aren't... well, I don't know,
that's interesting. Maybe. Anyway, let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka datchach. That doesn't make sense
to think that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
are saying a woman could wear it because she's exempt but it's
acceptable. Why can't that be a reasonable position? Because דלא רבי מאיר
סבר ליה כרבי יוסי ולא רבי יהודה סבר ליה כרבי יוסי. d'lo
Rabbi Meir savar lei k'Rabbi Yosi v'lo Rabbi Yehuda savar lei k'Rabbi
Yosi. We know that neither רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir nor רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda agree with רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, and they actually are
of the position that if a woman is exempt, she's also prohibited
to do that מצווה mitzvah act. Where do you see them saying
that? לא רבי מאיר סבר ליה כרבי יוסי. lo Rabbi Meir savar
lei k'Rabbi Yosi. And now we're going to finally get to the
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir doesn't hold like רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. דתנן, detnan, we taught in a משנה, Mishnah, אין
מעכבין את התינוקות מלתקוע. ein m'akvin es hatinokos mil'itkoa. You don't prevent
the kids from blowing a שופר shofar on ראש השנה Rosh Hashana
because it's חינוך chinuch for them, assuming of course תינוקות tinokos means
male, boy kids. הא נשים, ha nashim, but women presumably מעכבין, m'akvin,
you would let them blow a שופר. shofar. Okay? So why did
it mention everybody that's exempt is allowed to do it? Why does
it only mention the kids? Presumably women you would prevent. And why
would that be? So you see this משנה Mishnah holds, and a
סתם משנה וסתם מתניתין רבי מאיר, stam Mishnah v'stam masnisin Rabbi Meir,
a סתם משנה stam Mishnah is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So this
משנה Mishnah presumably holds that something that women are exempt from they're
not allowed to do. Now of course you'll say one minute, first
of all, how good of a דיוק diyuk is that? Maybe it
speaks about kids because maybe kids it sounds like they're playing around.
Number two is there is a special problem on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashana because if it weren't for the מצווה mitzvah of תקיעת שופר
t'kias shofar you wouldn't be allowed to blow a שופר, shofar, right?
Maybe it's a special problem, it's not a general idea that you
can't do a מצווה mitzvah you're exempt from. Okay, so I'll get
back to that, I'll note that for now and I'll get back
to that. But that's proof number one that according to this משנה
Mishnah women can't do something they're exempt from and presumably that's רבי
מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's position. ולא רבי יהודה סבר ליה כרבי יוסי, v'lo
Rabbi Yehuda savar lei k'Rabbi Yosi, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't
hold like רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. And now we're finally going to
see the רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. דתניא, detanya, we taught in the
ברייתא, Braisa, דבר אל בני ישראל, daber el b'nei yisrael, speak to
the children of Israel, this is at the beginning about bringing a
קרבן korban and then it says וסמך ידו v'samach yado and you
should put your hands on the head of the קרבן. korban. So
it makes a דרשה drasha which the גמרא Gemara, sometimes makes sometimes
doesn't make whether בני ישראל b'nei yisrael is assumed to be male
or not. So here it assumes that it is. בני ישראל סומכין
ואין בנות ישראל סומכות. b'nei yisrael somchin v'ein b'nos yisrael somchos. Okay?
So that's not debated that דרשה drasha that women are exempt from
doing סמיכה smicha on קרבנות korbanos putting their hands on קרבנות. korbanos.
רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים נשים סומכות רשות. Rabbi Yosi v'Rabbi Shimon
omrim nashim somchos reshus. But רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon say they're still allowed to do it. Which presumably means
that the תנא קמא tanna kamma who did not make that qualification
presumably held that women are not only exempt but not allowed. Okay,
now how do you know that's רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Because that
דרשה drasha is a דרשה drasha on a פסוק in ויקרא. Vayikra.
And the Tannaitic דרשות drashos of ויקרא Vayikra are all collected in
a book called the ספרא Sifra and the סתם ספרא stam Sifra
was edited or is seen to come from the school of רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. סתם ספרא מני stam Sifra mani and an unattributed
ספרא, Sifra, who is it going like? רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. It's
going like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So with this the גמרא Gemara
concludes, with this the גמרא Gemara says look, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir from these various proofs of saying women
don't do סמיכה smicha or women don't do תקיעת שופר t'kias shofar
on their own on ראש השנה Rosh Hashana hold that a מצווה
mitzvah that a woman is exempt from she's actually not allowed to
do. And therefore and therefore when, if they would still say, given
they say that, and the two of them still say that a
woman finds תפילין tefillin? on the street on שבת Shabbos. can wear
it, right? How can you say that if normally you say a
woman's not allowed and why isn't it carrying? Why isn't it seen
as completely extraneous? It must be that both רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda hold that שבת is זמן תפילין zman
tfillin. and that women are חייב chayav in תפילין. tefillin And that...
okay, so, or I should have said the opposite. Women are חייב
chayav in תפילין tefillin which therefore implies שבת is זמן תפילין. tefillin
Now that's pretty amazing, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, I mean that's probably half of the all-star team. So if
we would follow them, women would be חייב chayav. in תפילין tefillin
but we would also wear תפילין tefillin on. שבת, you know, we
don't wear תפילין tefillin on שבת, so it leads to the idea
that women are exempt. But now what we have to deal with
is two very important issues that arises from this גמרא, Gemara which
is this debate that which is not necessarily tied to the previous
debate. Women doing מצוות mitzvos that they're exempt from is it seen
as something that is, you know, objectionable or is it seen as
permitted? You know, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose נשים סומכות רשות, Nashim somchos
reshus, מיכל בת שאול. Michah bas Shaul. But then the גמרא Gemara
asks רבי מאיר... Rabbi Meir... anyway the גמרא Gemara about רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda about not doing סמיכה, smicha,
not doing it. So what is the logic to say that you
should object? So here it's a very important debate of רש"י and
תוספות, Tosfos which translates into a number of ראשונים and translates in
ways into practical הלכה. halacha. If you look at רש"י, רש"י says
הנשים מעכבים. hanashim me'akvim. It's like five lines from the top of
the narrow lines. אף על גב דלאו חילול יום טוב הוא, Af
al gav d'lav chilul Yom Tov hu, כדתני דבי שמואל, kedesanya bei
Shmuel, יצאת תקיעת שופר ורדיית הפת, yatzas kiyas shofar u'diyat ha-pasal, היא
חכמה ואינה מלאכה. hi chochma v'einah melacha. Even though it's not really
a violation of יום טוב, מיהו נראות כמוסיפות. mihu niros k'mosifos. So
according to רש"י, the problem of women doing a מצווה mitzvah that
they are exempt from is it's not technically בל תוסיף, ba'al tosif,
okay, because I mean heck, if they're exempt from it, they don't
have a base מצווה mitzvah to begin with. But it's a type
of a בל תוסיף, having somebody that's not supposed to be doing
it do it looks like you're expanding the parameters of the מצווה
mitzvah and therefore it's seen as intrinsically problematic. תוספות Tosafot does not...
if according to רש"י that would then be true about everything. Women
shouldn't sit in a סוכה, women shouldn't make a point of going
to hear תקיעת שופר. tekias shofar. Anything a woman is exempt from
she should not just, you know, it would be general, נראות כמוסיפות,
niros k'mosifos, a woman shouldn't do. Okay. תוספות Tosafot and almost all
the ראשוני אשכנז Rishonei Ashkenaz that follow רש"י say no, no, no,
it's not a huge global problem. The problem here was was that
if you are exempt, you know, that there are other problems that
exist in all of these cases that only normally we would assume
would be okay and overridden if you're חייב. chayav. But if you're
exempt, those problems pop up. Each one of these has local problems.
What are they? Well, the easiest one to start with is תקיעת
שופר. tekias shofar. What would be the problem? If there was no
מצווה, mitzvah, you're playing a musical instrument on יום טוב. So therefore
the position, and this is just רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is the position that would
allow it. But even the more stringent position is only because once
you're exempt then you've got a problem about playing a musical instrument
on יום טוב not in a situation of being חייב. chayav, How
about the קרבנות? korbanot? How about putting your hands on the קרבן?
korban? Well right, that looks like שבות, shevus, בקדשים. b'kodshim. Okay, קרבן
korban is קדשים kodshim and when you put your hands you put
your weight on it, so you're supporting your weight on the קרבן.
korban. So if it's not actually a מצווה, mitzvah, not that it's
actually a biblical prohibition, but it's very close to and it looks
like and it's at least a rabbinic problem of like you know,
using as it were קדשים kodshim because you're supporting your weight. So
therefore if you're not obligated, says רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, we can't let you do it. Okay, how about
the תפילין tefillin issue? Okay, so that's very nice, those are the
two cases of תקיעת שופר tekias shofar and the thing. What about
the תפילין? tefillin So here תוספות Tosafot says what? You might carry
it on שבת. No, we're talking about during the week. But anyway
here תוספות Tosafot says that we are talking about that the problem
is the גוף נקי guf naki issue. Now as you might be
aware, גוף נקי guf naki gets quoted a lot specifically in the
women context, but תוספות Tosafot is saying this as a general point
and to explain the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. That for all of us, you know, it's תפילין
tefillin is very challenging in terms of preventing yourself from passing gas,
which is why as I've mentioned you see this played out that
the fact that in the גמרא Gemara they would wear תפילין tefillin
the whole day. We only wear תפילין tefillin just for the time
of דאוונען. davening. Not only that, as opposed to other things where
חינוך chinuch starts many years before בר מצווה, Bar Mitzvah, we start
תפילין Tefillin, for some, like some only start like a month before,
three months before, because it's seen as a very challenging מצווה mitzvah
and you want to sort of, you know, therefore you have to
be care because of this issue of not passing gas. So therefore
if that would...
so if you're חייב, chayav! you're חייב! chayav, But if you're not
חייב, then you know, we have to say don't do it because
of the concerns. So what תוספות Tosafot does, and but I want
to reiterate, this is all according to the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position, not רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. So
there are two implications of תוספות's approach. Implication number one is מצוות
Mitzvos which have nothing problematic about them, there's absolutely no problem, everybody
would agree that women could do it. So sitting in a סוכה,
okay, hearing the תקיעת שופר, tekias shofar, taking a לולב, lulav right?
None of those things, although again somebody really want to make a
problem they would call a לולב lulav מוקצה, muktza, but it's hard
to call a לולב lulav? מוקצה muktza on סוכות. Succos. So anyway,
okay, so... none of those would be a problem. Putting on ציצית
tzitzit for example, right? So none of those would be a problem.
The problem only is in the area in specific מצוות Mitzvos, where
they have problematic aspects to them if you're not obligated. So nowadays,
putting doing סמיכה smicha on קרבנות korbanos is a moot point. Okay.
Blowing שופר shofar is not as moot, you know, but again normally
women are going to hear men blow. It would be an interesting...
Okay because as you'll as I assume know you know within the
question about women a woman who wants to opt to wear תפילין
Tefillin, so whether a woman again this is a whole bigger conversation
I'm not going to I just want to give you the ראשי
פרקים Roshei Perakim here right but women wearing for example ציצית tzitzit
is completely not problematic you know הלכתית halachically and nevertheless you know
there's opposition to it so some wanted to so some people create
new problems מחזי כיוהרא Mechzei Ke-yuhara da da da but the I
would want to point out that one problem I think that particularly
applies to a problem I don't mean a הלכתי halachic problem but
a reason that people feel you know find it objectionable and want
to find problems is because both ציצית Tzitzis. and תפילין tefillin are
garments are things you put on your body and garments are probably
some of the most gendered things that are part you know that
in the world you know so for a lot of people to
see a woman wearing a טלית tallit or a woman wearing תפילין
tefillin? it feels like oh my god you know she's dressing as
a man or something like that and that's why you'll find people
to try to give articulation to that to say it's a problem
of בגד איש Beged Ish and they then want to make it
a הלכתי halachic issue okay but that's you know again I'm not
giving you the whole תורה Torah on this it's very weak as
a הלכתי halachic argument the גמרא Gemara never raises that in all
its discussion of טלית tallit and תפילין tefillin? whatever never raises that
it's very weak as a הלכתי halachic argument but I think that's
where it's coming from is the gendered nature of clothing. By תפילין
tefillin, the other thing that gets raised is the גוף נקי Guf
Naki issue but I want to point out that that question about
do we concern ourselves with גוף נקי Guf Naki if you are
not obligated you know or do we say that your ability to
do the מצוה Mitzvah. even if you're not obligated overrides those concerns
that is really that's essentially debated here in the גמרא Gemara רבי
מאיר Reb Meir and רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda are more you know
more concerned and say if you're not obligated don't do it and
רבי יוסי Reb Yosi is not concerned okay so that is so
in terms of framing the debate about when there are problematic aspects
and even then it's debated רבי מאיר Reb Meir רבי יהודה Reb
Yehuda and רבי יוסי. Reb Yosi. I do want to add though
that the תפילין tefillin. גוף נקי Guf Naki issue although תוספות makes
it not gender-based is you know only based on the idea well
if women are exempt then according to רבי מאיר Reb Meir and
רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda then they have to contend more with the
גוף נקי Guf Naki which we also contend with but we're only
allowed to you know overcome because we're obligated but I do want
to admit that according to the אשכנזים Ashkenazim you know particularly in
a number of places in the רמ"א Rama not necessarily in תוספות
but anyway in the you know the idea of women and גוף
נקי Guf Naki went beyond the normal issue of passing gas went
to issues of of you know menstruation and and you know ideas
of keeping women away from שול shul and דאוון daven and other
types of things when they were menstruating and seeing that as a
very much of a whole problem of women and the concern of
menstruation and its connection with you know with holy things and this
was what what's that to do with ברכות berachot and whatever anyway
it didn't get that far but I mean some it did but
anyway in the רמ"א Rama it got to the issue of שול
shul not going to the שול shul so anyway that becomes an
expanded aspect of the גוף נקי. Guf Naki. So that's some of
the issues that are around the תפילין tefillin but again according to
a narrow you know just what we have in the גמרא Gemara
it really just boils down to a debate within תוספות's approach of
רבי מאיר Reb Meir רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda that say you have
to if you're not obligated those become issues and רבי יוסי Reb
Yosi says even if you're not obligated. Now one last point what
does according to רבי יוסי Reb Yosi that a woman is allowed
to do it what about making a ברכה? beracha So if you
look at the first line of תוספות דילמא סבר לה כרבי יוסי
דאמר נשים סומכות רשות dilma savar leh ke-Rebbi Yosi de-amar nashim somchot
reshut at the bottom of צ"ו Tzadi Vav תוספות says מכאן אמר
רבינו תם דמותר לנשים לברך על כל מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה אף
על גב דפטורות כמה דהכי שעושה מסתמא כמברכת. mikan amar Rabbeinu Tam
de-mutar le-nashim le-varech al kol mitzvat aseh she-hazman gerama af al gav
de-peturot kama de-hachi she-osa mi-stama ka-mevarechet. Okay well she was doing it
presumably she was also making a ברכה beracha and then תוספות goes
into a whole discussion whether women can make the ברכה Bracha because
the problem is can they say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו? asher kiddishanu
bemitzvotav vetzivanu? If they're not מצווה metzuvet to do it. Now אשכנזי
Ashkenazi practice is that women make the ברכה Bracha ספרדי Sephardi practice
is that women do not and I should point out that if
you combine number one a general sort of you know sort of
a reluctance or you know with of רבי מאיר Reb Meir and
רבי יהודה
Reb Yehuda about you know women doing things because there might be
problematic things and you combine it with an idea that even if
a
woman does it she doesn't make a ברכה Bracha it leads to
an overall culture of not being invested in women doing you know
non-time-bound מצווה. mitzvah. I still remember when I was once at a
at the house of some ספרדים Sephardim for a סוכות Sukkos and
you know I took I it was
סוכות Sukkos and so I took לולב lulav? in the morning and
the and you know the בעלת הבית Baalat Ha-Bayit was there you
know the woman of the house and I said to her so
do
you want you know do you want to take לולב? She said
no why would I want to take לולב? So it was like
completely had zero register of any sense of any value.
If you're not making a ברכה obviously. of the act and the
fact that there's a value, so it's a significant issue.
Now, how do Ashkenazim understand why we say וציוונו? Vetzivanu? So there
basically are two answers. One answer is that the word וציוונו Vetzivanu
is meant as part of a collective. So we כל ישראל Klal
Yisrael וציוונו, Vetzivanu, maybe not me personally, but we וציוונו. Vetzivanu. The
other explanation, which is even more powerful and speaks to the value
of women doing this מצוה Mitzvah and maybe gets to also the
idea of why it overrides these other types of concerns, is that
no, women are obligated as well. They're just given an exemption. But
being obligated and then saying but you're exempt is different than saying
you were never obligated to begin with. Because if you're obligated and
you're exempt and then you opt to not take the exemption, then
you are back into the category of obligated. And not to the
same level because you could always opt to exempt. But it allows
you to say וציוונו Vetzivanu and that also might explain why it
gives much more weight to the fact that you're doing a מעשה
מצוה. Maaseh Mitzvah. And therefore when a woman wants to, according to
that she could do it and not have to concern herself with
גוף נקי Guf Naki or משתמש בקודשים Mishtamesh Bekodashim or these other
issues, because then she actually is doing, you know, something that has
very serious, you know, very much a מצוה. Mitzvah Okay, so those
are some of the issues. You've been having your hand up for
a long time. Yeah, and I've got three things. One is we
normally, there's a normal rule we hold by רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
in dispute with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda or רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Right, so it's debated how we פסקן Pasken here. The רמב"ם Rambam
by the קרבן פלי Korban Play position פסקן Paskens נשים סומכות, Nashim
Somchos, that it's not רשות. Reshus. Okay, yeah, okay. רמב"ם Rambam also
פסקן Paskens women don't make a ברכה for מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא.
Mitzvas Aseh Shehazman Grama. So anyway, but yes. Second is regarding the
issue of בגד איש, Beged Ish, so a woman could wear a
pink or a lavender טלית Tallis and nobody should object to that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so that's what some people do. They say, you
know, you don't have that option by תפילין, tefillin. but some people,
but you know, some would say if you think that it's too
masculine, fine, wear a feminine type of a טלית. Tallis. And regarding
the ברכה on מצוות that aren't really מצוות, we say ברכות Brachos
every ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh on הלל. Hallel. Yes, so they would.
I mean, so you know, so that's exactly right and ספרדים Sefardim
don't say a ברכה on a half הלל. Hallel. It's a consistent
debate. Okay, so now let's move on. So that was quite fascinating.
Now we have three minutes to start a new topic, but we
need to get a little further in the דף. Daf. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Elazar. Now
we're going to turn to the issue about whether we are, I
hope you're not leaving out of objection, רבקה. Rivka. All right. Now
we're going to turn to the issue about נוי תפילין Noy Tefillin
and are we
going to how concerned are we that something that looks like a
מצוה object might not really be a מצוה object? And remember for
רש"י the idea of נוי Noy is it didn't have the knots
on it so therefore it's not as evident that it was real
תפילין, although it's black and square and all of that. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי אלעזר. Amar Rabbi Elazar.
המוצא תכלת בשוק, Hamotzi Techeiles Bashuk, you find a blue threads in
the marketplace, you know, on the floor. לשונות פסולות, Leshonos Pesulos, if
they're simple threads,
they're or how do they translate, like a fabric is פסול, Pasul,
חוטים כשרים, Chutim Kesherim, if they're twisted as
threads, they're כשר. Kasher. Okay. לשונות? Leshonos? Fabric or what? Strips, right.
Okay, they haven't been twisted into threads. כשר Kasher for what? For
ציצית. Tzitzis, Okay. But the issue is that ציצית, Tzitzis? if they're
blue, they have to be dyed לשמה. Lishma. So you don't you
don't know if these are the right object or not. You know
what they look like, but you don't know if they were done
properly. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי שנא לשונות? Mai
Shna Leshonos? Why why are the simple strips or pieces of fabric,
why are those not good? Why can't you twist them and make
them into strings? דאמר אדעתא דגלימא צבעינהו, De'amar Ada'ata Deglima Tzavinhu, because
maybe you did it to make a nice blue cloak. You know,
you weren't doing and it wasn't...
right, it wasn't dyed לשמה.
Lishma. So חוטים נמי נימא אדעתא דגלימא צבעינהו? Chutim Nami Naima Ada'ata
Deglima Tzavinhu? So strings also, maybe you you know, you made the
strings for the sake of, you know, for sewing it, maybe it
was a blue thread, and you know, and maybe you made a
blue thread to sew for a blue garment. So who says you're
doing it for ציצית? Tzitzis. So the גמרא Gemara says בשזורין. Bishzurim.
No, it's שזורין Shzurim is not just as a thread, it's more
like a twisted string, like we have our ציצית. Tzitzis? So twisted
strings, what are you doing with twisted strings if not for ציצית?
Tzitzis You wanted tassels. So the גמרא says: שזורין נמי נימא אדעתא
דסיפסא דגלימא עבדינהו, Shzurim Nami Naima Ada'ata Desipsa Deglima Avdinhu, maybe you
made a twisted string to be like a, you know, on the
edge of the garment. What's that called when you have something like
these things on the edge? Trim or something, right. So maybe you
made it for trim? So the גמרא says
במפסקי. Bimfaksikin. No, because they're cut into perfect ציצית Tzitzis. sized strings.
Okay. So the גמרא says: דכולי האי ודאי לא טרחי אינשי. Dechulei
Hai Vadai Lo Tarchai Inshi. To that extent, people are not going
to dye it and make it a string and cut it the
right size unless clearly they were doing it for the sake of
ציצית. And as I was saying, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, וכי אדם
טורח לעשות קמיע? vechi adam tore'ach la'asot keme'a? If that's a sufficient
evidence that that's done properly, how about when you find a brand
new תפילין box? I mean, give me a break, of course it
was made לשם תפילין leshem tefillin if you want to go by
percentages. וכי אדם טורח לעשות קמיע כמין תפילין? vechi adam tore'ach la'asot
keme'a kemin tefillin? Is somebody going to make a קמיע keme'a to
look just like תפילין? תנן, Tnan, במה דברים אמורים בישנות, אבל בחדשות
פטור. beme de'amru biyishanot aval bechadashot patur. So therefore why can you
not take the brand new ones? Let's use just the way they
look as enough of evidence. So אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira,
so said רב זירא Rav Zeira לאבא בריה, le'Ava brei, to his
son אבא, Ava, פוק תני להו, Puk tani lehu, go out, this
was being discussed in the בית מדרש. Beit Medrash. He says go
out and tell to them המוצא תכלת בשוק, hamotze tchelet bashuk, לשונו
פסולים, leshono pesulim, חוטים מופסקים כשרים. chutim mufsakim kisherim. It says explicitly
in the ברייתא braita cut strings are כשר, kasher, לפי שאין אדם
טורח, lefi she'ein adam tore'ach, exactly for this reason, nobody would
bother. So just tell them you got a ברייתא braita that says
nobody would bother, don't try to challenge that ברייתא. braita. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said back, ומשום דתני לה אבא
בריה דרב זירא, umishum detani lei Ava brei deRav Zeira, so just
because אבא Ava רב זירא's Rav Zeira's son teaches this ברייתא, braita,
כייפינן ליה, kifinan lei, what, we should give him an award? That
was my idiomatic translation. It basically means should we put a ring
on him? So who cares? Wonderful, you got a ברייתא braita but
I still got my problem. Why do you have to worry about
brand new תפילין? Brand new תפילין, nobody would make it to look
that way unless it was real תפילין. ותנן, Vetnan, במה דברים אמורים
בישנות beme de'amru biyishanot, אבל בחדשות פטור. aval bechadashot patur. So what's
the issue? So that is a cliffhanger, I will leave you until
tomorrow to find out why it is that you have to be
concerned about brand new looking תפילין that they could be anything other
than תפילין. Okay.