בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
Today's דף daf is דף daf ט, tet, nine, and it's the
ninth day in the עומר. Omer. That's going to continue to be
true for the next five days or so, correspondence.
But and that's true, ninth day will only be till tonight. Anyway
we pick up at the top of ט עמוד א. tet amud
aleph. What we're going through are the cases, the conditions under which
you bring a פר העלם דבר של ציבור par he'elam davar shel
tzibbur and in parallel the כהן גדול kohen gadol brings his פר.
par. Some basic issues, they both need a פסק הלכה, psak halacha,
they both only חייב chayav with a הוראה hora'ah that's about a
קיום מקצת וביטול מקצת. kiyum miktzat u'bittul miktzat. It's only about something
that is otherwise you would bring a קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, not
something that you would bring an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, that's sort
of what we focused on yesterday. Also קרבן חטאת korban chatat requires
just in general a קרבן חטאת korban chatat requires something that there's
a חיוב כרת chiyuv kares for, which is a whole sort of
whole things we did here by the דרשות drashot that also an
אשם תלוי asham talui is only something that's linked to a קרבן
חטאת, korban chatat, not to a קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh v'yored.
Fine. And then the last thing we did was that what's the
story within the עולה ויורד oleh v'yored discussion, okay, that's not going
to be a case of like a כהן גדול kohen gadol bringing,
you know, his special קרבן korban is not going to be based
on an עולה ויורד. oleh v'yored. Again those sort of special קרבנות
korbanot like the בית דין beis din or whatever is only based
on a קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. But there is going to be
an interesting question about whether he individually brings an עולה ויורד, oleh
v'yored, or a נשיא, nasi, does he in the, you know, he's
got a special קרבן korban but it's not about a פסק, psak,
it's just about a normal type of an action.
But and but does he bring an עולה ויורד? oleh v'yored? Or
are their קרבנות korbanot completely limited to those, you know, their special
ones which themselves are linked to a קרבן חטאת korban chatat as
we've discussed. So the end of the משנה mishna yesterday did not
discuss the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, the end of the משנה mishna
yesterday though did discuss the נשיא. nasi. And according to רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, the נשיא nasi would generally bring a קרבן עולה ויורד
korban oleh v'yored when, I mean, if it's a type of a
חטאת chatat he brings his special one, but otherwise he'd bring an
עולה ויורד oleh v'yored with the exception of the עולה ויורד oleh
v'yored based on being sworn to give testimony because that's not relevant
for a king. And רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says, one
minute, okay fine, one minute, oh, and רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGlili says that
a נשיא nasi doesn't do an עולה ויורד oleh v'yored at all.
Okay, so the question is why not according to רבי יוסי הגלילי?
Rabbi Yose HaGlili? One explanation given in the גמרא Gemara is that
because he doesn't have the קרבן korban relating to being sworn to
give testimony, if one of the aspects don't apply, none of them
apply. And the other answer given in the גמרא Gemara is because
עולה ויורד oleh v'yored is only for people who are in a
position in society where they could be rich and they could be
poor, which is really anybody, except a כהן גדול kohen gadol and
a king, because those are people that because of their status we
ensure that they always have wealth. It's interesting that רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose HaGlili did not say the reason that the נשיא nasi
only has his special קרבן, korban, that he only has his קרבן
korban of the שעיר se'ir and he only has or the כהן
גדול kohen gadol only has his special קרבן korban of the פר
par and therefore they don't have another קרבן. korban. That's not the
reason they say, in theory they could be in the category of
עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, but because a נשיא nasi and then he
also actually throws in a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, that wasn't discussed
in the משנה, mishna, because a נשיא nasi and a כהן גדול
kohen gadol never can get poor, that's why they're excluded from עולה
ויורד, oleh v'yored, okay? So right now you have רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva that says he doesn't discuss כהן גדול, kohen gadol, but at
least by the נשיא nasi fundamentally he's in the category. The only
thing he's excluded from is the oath relating to giving testimony,
whereas רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili excludes both a כהן גדול
kohen gadol and a נשיא nasi from an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored,
but not because again of that they're limited to their other קרבנות,
korbanot, but because they cannot be poor and therefore they're not in
that category. Okay, so those are the opinions we saw now we're
going to continue with this about to what degree does עולה ויורד
oleh v'yored apply to a כהן גדול kohen gadol and a נשיא.
nasi. But the בית דין הגדול beis din hagadol only would bring
its קרבן korban and something linked to a חטאת. chatat. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues like this. בעי מיני. Ba'ei minei. We're
about ten lines from the top on ט עמוד א, tet amud
aleph, line starts the word מיני. minei. בעי מיני רבינא מרב נחמן
בר יצחק. Ba'ei minei Ravina me'Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. רבינא Ravina asked
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, נשיא שנצטרע מהו? nasi
shenitztara mahu? So let's say this נשיא, nasi, which according to you've
just said, you know, would not bring an עולה ויורד oleh v'yored
because he's never in a position where he could become poor, what
happens if he got צרעת? tzara'at? And the presumption is that if
a king has צרעת tzara'at he can't serve as a king. Okay,
so
מדחא דחי או מיפטר פטר? midcha dachi o miptar patar? Is he
completely pushed like you know now the question is pushed out of
what? Pushed out of the category of... of you can say pushed
out of the category of being a king and therefore חייב chayiv
in a קורבן. korban. רש"י Rashi reads it the other way: is
his status of a king does that completely push away the category
of קורבן, korban, and therefore even if he's not functioning as a
king, somehow he's still a king, but not acting king or something,
or maybe because once in his life he was king or something,
somehow that completely pushes away the sense of the relevance of this
קורבן korban to him? Or do we say that no, that it
just exempted him for the time being, it was when he was
a king it exempted him from a קורבן, korban, now that he's
not serving as a king, it's no longer this exemption is no
longer relevant and it's not a complete categorical exclusion, and therefore he
goes back to being obligated in a קורבן. korban. ומפטר פטיר, umiftar
patir, okay, it's very...
That's kind of ironic ומפטר פטיר umiftar patir means then he would
bring it; it sounds like he wouldn't bring it.
Yeah, because he was ומפטר פטיר umiftar patir when he was king,
but he wasn't completely it didn't completely exclude him from the category.
It was an exemption for the time. אמר ליה, amar lei, so
it was a very cryptic question, what does מדחא דחי midcha dachi
mean, what does ומפטר פטיר umiftar patir mean? The answer is also
very cryptic. אמר ליה amar lei he said back to him דילך
או דגנזא. dilach o deganza. Is it from yours or is it
from the treasure house? It's like what? So the way רש"י Rashi
reads this, the question was, where do you expect the money for
this קורבן korban to come? Are you going to pay for the
קורבן, korban, or is it going to come from the king's treasure
house? Since were he to sin it would come from his treasure
house, assuming that his treasure house is his personal wealth and not
the country's wealth, okay, so therefore bottom line what he's saying is
at the end of the day, since the king is still wealthy
even though he has צרעת, tzara'at, since he's still wealthy and the
whole reason of excluded from the קורבן korban is somebody who doesn't
become poor, so therefore he remains exempt because he's still wealthy. Now,
that's the way רש"י Rashi reads it. The הרא"ש ha-Rosh has a
great question. The הרא"ש ha-Rosh says, I don't understand, says the הרא"ש.
ha-Rosh. It's very nice that he's wealthy, there's a lot of people
who are wealthy and still bring a קורבן עולה ויורד. korban olah
veyored. If Bill Gates, it doesn't say Bill Gates here, it does
say it just says Bezos, but anyway,
if Bill Gates or what's his name Jeff Bezos would have sinned
they'd bring an עולה ויורד olah veyored even though they have billions
of dollars,
okay, who knows, people become poor, they have the possibility in theory
of losing their wealth. The only reason a כהן גדול kohen gadol
and a king don't bring it is because a כהן גדול kohen
gadol we will always contribute to make sure that he has money
if he loses his wealth, and a king, which was never said
explicitly in the גמרא Gemara but
the גמרא Gemara quoted a פסוק, pasuk, but anyway, the הרא"ש ha-Rosh
says, the king can always levy taxes and take from other people
and become wealthy if he gets poor, which of course is very
interesting, that he's allowed to make taxes to enrich himself and not
just for the sake of the government, but anyway, but the הרא"ש
ha-Rosh says, so I don't get it, if he's no longer king,
what does that mean that he's still wealthy, that's not a reason
to be פטור patur from a קורבן, korban, once you've lost your
power as king, okay, so the הרא"ש ha-Rosh actually suggests an opposite
reading of the גמרא. Gemara. He basically says that the reading of
the גמרא Gemara was basically
that he says if he has to take money for the קורבן,
korban, does he have the right anymore to stick his hand into
your pocket? דילך. dilach. Now that he's no longer acting king, he
no longer has the right to stick his hand into your pocket.
או דגנזא o deganza it's going to have to come from his
own storehouse. And since it's from his own treasure house and since
it's going to come from his own treasure house, he's now back
to being a private individual because he doesn't have the right to
stick his hand into your pocket, so actually he does have to
bring the קורבן. korban. So the הרא"ש ha-Rosh has a possibility of
reading the גמרא Gemara in the exact opposite. In the end he
concedes that he likes רש"י Rashi's reading better. But it is a
good question, pointing out that just because he's wealthy doesn't mean that
he's exempt from the קורבן. korban. He was just suspended.
Yeah, so that's the sense, that he's only suspended, and when he
gets better he's going to now be back, which is the way
the גמרא Gemara phrase it as מדחא דחי midcha dachi or ומפטר
פטיר, umiftar patir, how do you view this interim stage? The answer
of whether he's taking your money or his own seems a little
bit not framed in terms of the question, seems like a different
way of approaching it.
Is he still ruling? Who's ruling?
No, a regent, somebody is ruling in his stead. Okay, תניא tanya
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר, omer, משיח mashiach פטור patur מכולן. mikulan.
Okay, so now we get to the question of as I said,
that's the story about the king, what's the story about the כהן
גדול? kohen gadol? Because you could say a king whose קורבן korban
looks like anybody else's קורבן korban because it's normally just for the
action, so he would bring a normal שעיר sa'ir for when he
does a normal sin and he would in principle be relevant to
the category of עולה ויורד olah veyored based on the earlier discussion,
but a כהן גדול kohen gadol who's much more categorically different, he's
more like the בית דין, Beit Din, it's only based on a
פסק, psak, you could say the same way בית דין Beit Din's
קורבן korban is limited to a חטאת, chatat, his קורבן korban is
limited to a חטאת. chatat. Does a כהן גדול kohen gadol ever
bring maybe he's completely excluded from עולה ויורד, olah veyored, not just
because of this issue of wealth. Fundamentally his קורבן korban is limited
to the type of corban like a בית דין, Beis Din, a
קרבן korban linked to a חטאת. chatas. So that's the question, what's
the story of a כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? So רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says he's exempt. Okay, now let's see why. אמר רבא מאי
טעמא דרבי עקיבא? Amar Rava mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Akiva? What's the reasoning?
אמר קרא Amar Kra the verse says זה קרבן אהרן ובניו. Zeh
korban Aharon u-vanav. This, the קרבן korban that they would bring every
day, the מנחה mincha that they would bring every day, half in
the morning and half in the evening, is the קרבן korban of
a for the כהן, Kohen, a regular חביתי כהן Chavitay Kohen or
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, חביתי כהן גדול. Chavitay Kohen Gadol. זו בחובה,
Zu ba-achovah, this one comes as a regular obligation, ואין אחרת בחובה.
v'ein acheres ba-achovah. So this is the only regular מנחה mincha obligation,
only מנחה mincha obligation of a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. A כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol has no other מנחה mincha obligation. And so what
does that have to do with anything? Well, an עולה ויורד, ole
v'yored, if you don't have money, you bring the lowest level is
a מנחה. mincha. So this is a similar to the previous argument.
The previous argument was he's wealthy, therefore it's not, he doesn't go
up and down the scale. This is an argument is, the bottom
of the scale is never relevant to him because the תורה Torah
is saying a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can never be obligated, you
know, like in a מנחה. mincha. Okay, so therefore since the bottom
of the scale isn't relevant to him, the whole scale isn't relevant
to him. So again, this is not an exclusion of a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol because somehow categorically he's like the בית דין Beis
Din and he's only in that world of פסק psak and חטאת
chatas and not an עולה ויורד. ole v'yored. No, in principle he
is an עולה ויורד. ole v'yored. So whereas רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yosi Ha-Gelili or רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya excluded him based on the
fact that he doesn't get poor, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva excludes him
because on the fact that he is fundamentally excluded from the bottom
of the scale from being a מנחה. mincha. Okay, זאת Zos at
least that's way רבא Rava reads רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. זו בחובה
לו ואין אחרת בחובה לו. Zu ba-achovah lo v'ein acheres ba-achovah lo.
ואימא V'aima why don't I say כי ממעיט רחמנא מדלי דלות ומאי
ניהו עשירית האיפה? ki mi-ma'it Rachmana mi-dal-dalus u-mai nihu asiri ha-eifa? Maybe
I'll just say that he's just excluded from the bottom of the
scale, he's just excluded from being the מנחה. mincha. Okay, אבל עניות
ועשירות לא ממעיט, aval aniyus v'ashirus lo mi'it, but if he's, but
if he's middle level or he's wealthy, you know, then he's not
excluded and he could bring the bird or the major animal. לא
ממעיט רחמנא. Lo mi'it Rachmana. לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salika daitach, that
doesn't make sense, דכתיב
וכפר עליו הכהן על חטאתו אשר חטא מאחת מאלה, de-chtiv v'chiper alav
ha-kohen al chataso asher chata mei-achas mei-eleh, this is by the case
of עולה ויורד, ole v'yored, the כהן Kohen will atone for him
for the sin that he sinned on one of these. מאחת מאלה,
Mei-achas mei-eleh, המתכפר באחת, ha-miskaper b'achas, one who sinned on who can
atone with one of these קרבנות, korbanos, with any, with you know,
with any one of these three options about the מנחה, mincha, the
bird or the or the larger animal, מתכפר בכולן, miskaper b'chulan, then
the other options are available to him. ושאין מתכפר באחת, V'she-ein miskaper
b'achas, if one of the options is not available to you, כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol and the מנחה mincha isn't available to you, so
אין מתכפר בכולן, ein miskaper b'chulan, the other ones are also not,
do not atone for you. Okay, so it's a similar argument to
the one we made before. Somehow you're excluded from one, you're excluded
from all of them, and that's why a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
is excluded from these. אלא מעתה Ela mei-ata says the גמרא Gemara
דכתיב והיה כי יאשם לאחת מאלה, de-chtiv v'haya ki yesham l'achas mei-eleh,
that's talking about which קרבן korban you bring, המתכפר, ha-miskaper, right, if
you are, if this קרבן korban works for you, if if any
one קרבן korban works for you they all work for you, if
one of the קרבנות korbanos don't work none of them work. So
that's not talking about the קרבן, korban, let's talk about the sin.
Okay, it says והיה כי יאשם לאחת מאלה v'haya ki yesham l'achas
mei-eleh if he sins about one of these three things: about the
oath to testify, about טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumas mikdash v'kodashav, or or
about just swearing falsely. Okay, so why don't we say the same
thing? That this this קרבן korban only applies to you if you
could do any, if you could be bringing for any one of
these sins. הכי נמי דכל המתחייב באחת מתחייב בכולן, Hachi nami de-kol
ha-mischayav b'achas mischayav b'chulan, let's just say only if you could bring
any one of these, do any be obligated for any one of
these things can you be obligated for the other. ושאין מתחייב באחת
V'she-ein mischayav b'achas if there's a sin here that you can't be
obligated for, אין מתחייב בכולן, ein mischayav b'chulan, you can't be obligated
for the others. And that would actually be the position of רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi Ha-Gelili by the נשיא. Nasi. Since the נשיא
Nasi can't be sworn to testify, he's excluded from everything. So if
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying since the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
can't bring the מנחה mincha he's excluded from everything, why doesn't he
agree to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi Ha-Gelili and say since the
נשיא Nasi can't be sworn to testify he also can't bring anything?
אלמה תנן Alama tnan
so why did our משנה Mishnah teach?
רבי עקיבא אומר נשיא חייב חוץ משמיעת קול Rabbi Akiva omer nasi
chayav chutz mi-shmias kol that a נשיא Nasi is obligated except for
the oath to testify. So one exclusion should lead to the other
exclusions. If it's true about a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol which by
the קרבן, korban, it should be true about the נשיא Nasi by
the sin. So it's a very good question. אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו
Abaye v'Rava d'amri duvaih אביי Abaye and רבא Rava they both come
and explain: מאחת משמע ליה, Mei-achas mashma lei, from one of these
suggests that he has to be able to bring any one of
the קרבנות. korbanos. לאחת L'achas he sinned about one of these things
לא משמע ליה lo mashma lei it doesn't suggest to him that
he has to be able to sin for any one of them.
So it's not exactly clear what the מ mem versus the ל
lamed matters and the גמרא's Gemara going to say: ומאי שנא מאחת
דמשמע ליה דכתיבי U-mai shana mei-achas d'mashma lei de-kasvei and why does
מאחת mei-achas suggest that only if he's obligated in all of them,
if he can bring any of the קרבנות, korbanos, you know, does
he bring them? Why? It's not because of the מ mem versus
the ל. lamed. It's where it's written. Okay, whether it's מאחת mei-achas
or לאחת. l'achas. It might just mean any one. It would not
suggest that only if you're obligated, that you have to be able
to bring one of them to bring all, any of them. Okay,
and that's why when it comes to the sin, even though he
can't bring the קרבן korban for the oath of testifying, he can
bring the others. The word מאחת, me'achas, לאחת l'achas by itself does
not mean all of them have to be available to you. But
it does mean it when it comes to the מנחה, mincha, not
because of the מ mem versus the ל, lamed, but because of
where it appears in the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, ומאי שנא מאחת דמשמע
ליה, u'mai shna me'achas d'mashma lei, דכתב רחמנא לבסוף, d'kasiv Rachmana l'besof,
because that word, if he sins from one of these, it's written
at the very end after it gets to the case of the
מנחה, mincha, after it mentions the other קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, גבי עשירית
האיפה, gabei asiris ha'eifa, למימרא דכל דמיחייב בעשירית האיפה מיחייב בכולן, l'meimra
de'chol d'mechayev b'asiris ha'eifa mechayev b'chulan, to tell you only if you
can bring the מנחה, mincha, then can you be obligated in the
other ones. דאי סלקא דעתך מיחייב באחת אף על פי שאין מיחייב
בכולן, de'is salka daich mechayev b'achas af al pi she'eino mechayev b'chulan,
if it means as long as you're obligated in any one of
them, even if you're not obligated in the others, then that's okay,
so נכתביה להאי מאחת מאליה בדלות אי נמי בעשירות, nidkev l'hai me'achas
me'eila b'dalus i nami b'ashirus, why did it write it in the
case of the מנחה, mincha, why didn't it write it in the
other ones? So the only reason it must have written it in
the case of the מנחה mincha was because there's a person, i.e.
a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, who never would bring a מנחה. mincha.
And therefore it's writing it in the case of the מנחה mincha
to signal to you that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is exempt.
So bottom line the word מאחת me'achas or לאחת l'achas does not
by itself suggest that you have to all of these things have
to be possible for you. And that's why a king brings the
other עולה ויורד ole v'yored even though the oath of swearing is
not relevant to him. But when it comes to this case, since
it could have written the word מאחת me'achas in the other by
by the other קרבן, korban, and it wrote it by the מנחה,
mincha, we're going to say the only reason to write it by
the מנחה mincha is to exclude a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and
to say a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who can't bring a מנחה
mincha is excluded from this whole category of קרבנות. korbanot. That's the
way we're reading it. Okay, so what we bottom line have is
the following.
Fundamentally it's very funny, I could have said fundamentally a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is excluded from עולה ויורד ole v'yored because he's just
like the בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol and he's only limited
to things which you bring a normal חטאת. chatas. The גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that. The גמרא Gemara says that a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol and a נשיא Nasi fundamentally are in begin in the פרשה
parsha of עולה ויורד. ole v'yored. And now we have to decide
if we're going to take them out. Do we take a נשיא
Nasi out? Well we certainly take him out of the thing about
testifying. Do we take him out of the rest? So רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says we take him out of the rest.
Either since he can't testify since he's not in one of them
he's not in any, or what the גמרא Gemara winds up saying
is since he doesn't get poor he's not in any. So that's
the נשיא. Nasi. כהן גדול Kohen Gadol fundamentally is in the category.
Do we take him out? So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says we
do take him out, he can't get poor, same reason.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva also says we take the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol out for a different reason, I mean it's very similar but
it's a little different.
Since the תורה Torah excludes him from the קרבן korban of the
מנחה, mincha, therefore he's excluded from them all. So by the end
of the day for one reason or another even though in principle
they started in, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is out, a נשיא Nasi
is out according to רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva there's some cases a נשיא Nasi would still
bring. Let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishnah. Yeah.
I'm sorry, so but it says by the עולה ויורד ole v'yored
it says both לאחת l'achas and מאחת. me'achas.
Right, right. Right, so the גמרא Gemara is saying we're not really
being מדייק medayek the מ mem versus the ל, lamed, it's just
where the word is situated.
But it's but it's which which word? לאחת? l'achas?
One of them is about the sin and one of them is
about the קרבן.
korban. It says both in the very very beginning and at the
very very end.
Right, but but where it uses the word מאחת me'achas by it's
speaking about the type of קרבן korban brought, it only said it
by the מנחה mincha and it didn't say it by...
Well it says it after it's finished not like right next to
the מנחה.
mincha. Right, so the I understand, look, there's a you're right, meaning
the reason the גמרא Gemara waited to the end, the גמרא Gemara
the תורה Torah waited to the end is because after it lists
all of them it says any one, that what it would have
made sense earlier. I understand. All right, I don't know how to
explain that. All right, let's take a look at the next משנה.
mishnah. כל מצות שבתורה שחייבין על זדונן כרת ועל שגגתן חטאת, kol
mitzvos she'baTorah she'chayavin al zedonan kares ve'al shigegan chatas, so now this
is going to be now that we've sort of dealt with the
sort of this is a little bit of a recap, any type
of a normal sin that you a that you would get כרת
kares for and you would also if you did it unintentionally you'd
get a חטאת. chatas. היחיד מביא כשבה, ha'yachid meivi kesva, so we're
talking about a standard fixed חטאת. chatas. היחיד מביא כשבה ושעירה, ha'yachid
meivi kesva ve'se'ira, now we're talking about what types of animals. So
the standard חטאת chatas of a יחיד yachid is a is a
female sheep or goat. הנשיא שעיר, ha'Nasi se'ir, the one of a
נשיא, Nasi, the conditions of him bringing are the exact same, right,
it's a שגגת מעשה, shiggas ma'aseh, but the actual קרבן korban is
different, it's a he-goat, okay, שעיר. se'ir. ומשיח ובית דין מביאים פר.
u'mashiach u'Beis Din meivi'im par. And the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and
the בית דין, Beis Din, that's when they do a הוראה, hora'ah,
before we discussed the conditions, their conditions of bringing are different, when
they do a הוראה hora'ah then they bring also the type of
קרבן korban they bring is different, it's not a goat, it's not
a sheep, it's a whatever, it's a male ox. Okay, that's by
a normal חטאת. chatas. ובעבודה זרה, u've'avoda zara, then let's say it's
a sin that you would get כרת kares for relating to עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. היחיד והנשיא והמשיח מביאים שעירה. ha'yachid ve'haNasi ve'haMashiach meivi'im
se'ira. Okay, so there... Every all of the individuals are the same,
even the כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen gadol* and the נשיא nasi
*Nasi*, and they all bring a she-goat. All right, ובית דין *Ubais
din*, and when בית דין beis din *Bais din* does it based
on a פסק psak *P'sak*, that's פר par? ושעיר *Par v'se'ir*. That
actually is two, an ox and a male goat. פר par לעולה
ושעיר לחטאת *Par l'oloh v'se'ir l'chatas*. Okay, a פר par? *Par* is
actu- the ox here is actually an עולה *Olloh*, and the שעיר
sa'ir. *Se'ir* that's the sin offering. אשם תלוי asham taluy. *Asham taluy*,
what is an אשם תלוי asham taluy. *Asham taluy*? When it's based
on that you don't know if you did something that otherwise you'd
bring a fixed חטאת chatas. *Chatas* for. Okay, היחיד והנשיא חייבים *Hayachid
v'hanasi chayavim*. So first of all, before we get to the animal,
the נשיא nasi *Nasi* and the היחיד *Hayachid* and the נשיא nasi
*Nasi* are חייב chayav. *Chayav* because they're individuals. Only an individual brings
an אשם תלוי asham taluy *Asham taluy*. It says נפש *Nefesh*. ומשיח
ובית דין פטורים *Umashiach u'bais din peturin*. בית דין beis din *Bais
din* is פטור patur. *Patur*. Why is the משיח mashiach, *Mashiach* פטור
*Patur*? כהן גדול kohen gadol. *Kohen gadol*, he's also a נפש *Nefesh*.
The reason he's פטור *Patur* is because we learn out על שגגתו
אשר שגג *Al shegogaso asher shagag* that a you only bring an
אשם תלוי asham taluy. *Asham taluy* by somebody whose sin is based
on just acting, whereas a כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen gadol* whose
sin is also based on הוראה hora’ah *Hora'ah* doesn't bring an אשם
תלוי asham taluy *Asham taluy*. So that's why a כהן גדול kohen
gadol *Kohen gadol*'s excluded from אשם תלוי asham taluy *Asham taluy*. I
know some of this is review, mostly this is coming to focus
on which what the animal is, but it's also a bit of
review. Okay, it doesn't say what the actual animal is for the
אשם תלוי asham taluy *Asham taluy*. אשם asham ודאי *Asham vadai*, how
about a case where you bring an אשם asham *Asham* for, you
know, there are like five specific cases that you bring an אשם
*Asham* for, four I think, one of the אשם *Ashams* is an
אשם תלוי asham talui. *Asham taluy*, the other four אשם ודאי *Asham
vadais*. Anyway, that you bring an אשם ודאי *Asham vadai* for, okay,
which is special types of sins. So what's the story there? היחיד
והנשיא והמשיח חייבים *Hayachid v'hanasi v'hamashiach chayavim*. So that's just the sin
of an individual. So all of these individuals are חייב chayav *Chayav*,
okay, and ובית דין פטורים *Ubais din peturin* and בית דין beis
din *Bais din* is exempt. Okay, very good. Because בית דין beis
din, *Bais din* only brings based on a חטאת chatas, *Chatas*. אשם
*Asham*... where we just did... Okay, שמיעת הקול וביטוי שפתים וטומאת מקדש
mikdash, וקדשיו *Sh'mias hakol v'vituos sefasayim v'tum'as mikdash v'kodashav*. So here's what
we were just talking about, עולה ויורד oleh veyored *Oleh v'yored*. בית
דין beis din פטורים *Bais din peturin*, בית דין beis din *Bais
din* is exempt, בית דין beis din *Bais din* is only something
fixed that's based on a חטאת chatas. *Chatas*. והיחיד והנשיא והמשיח חייבים
*V'hayachid v'hanasi v'hamashiach chayavim*. In principle, the כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen
gadol* and the and the נשיא nasi *Nasi* are חייב *Chayav*. Now
we just got through saying reasons they'd be excluded, the נשיא nasi
*Nasi* at least for the oath of testifying and maybe for everything,
the משיח *Mashiach*, כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen gadol* also maybe fully
excluded because he doesn't get poor, because he doesn't bring a מנחה
mincha, *Mincha*. Okay, but anyway this משנה mishna *Mishnah* starts by saying
that at least in principle they're חייב *Chayav*. Okay, אלא שאין כהן
גדול kohen gadol. משיח חייב על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodashav,
*Ella she'ain kohen gadol mashiach chayav al tum'as mikdash v'kodashav*. And now
we have another way of excluding a כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen
gadol*. As opposed to what we said before to totally exclude him
because he doesn't get poor or he doesn't bring a מנחה mincha
*Mincha*, here we're going to exclude him parallel to the way we
for just one thing. So parallel to the way we excluded the
king for the testifying oath, the one of the sins that a
כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen gadol* is not going to bring a
קרבן korban *Korban* for is טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash, *Tum'as mikdash*. Of
course you would think it's the one he דוקא *Davka* more than
anything should bring a קרבן korban *Korban* for. No, he wouldn't because
that's what the ציץ tzitz *Tzitz* is for, isn't it? Right. So
you could say since he's sort of like there all the time
and the ציץ *Tzitz* is there to be מכפר mechaper *Mechaper* for
it, maybe he's got a little bit more of latitude about it.
Right. So anyway we'll see why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it
in a minute. Okay, but this is diff- this is different than
we said before, here it's saying in principle that he actually is
חייב *Chayav* for the others, but he's excluded from one of them.
דברי רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon? *Divrei Rabbi Shimon*, that's what רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* says. ומה הן מביאין *U'mah hein mevi'in*? קרבן עולה ויורד
korban oleh veyored, *Korban oleh v'yored*. Now when they do those things,
what do they bring? Okay, the כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen gadol*
and the נשיא nasi *Nasi*, assuming that they do bring for some
of those sins, so a normal קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh veyored
*Korban oleh v'yored*, whether it's, you know, based on their wealth and
it's a sliding scale etc. רבי אליעזר אומר הנשיא מביא שעיר Rabbi
Eliezer omer hanasi meivi sa'ir. *Rabbi Eliezer omer hanasi mevi se'ir*. When
a נשיא nasi *Nasi* brings for the קרבן korban עולה ויורד oleh
veyored? *Korban oleh v'yored*, the type of קרבן korban, *Korban* he's going
to bring is the קרבן korban *Korban* he would bring for a
חטאת chatas. *Chatas*, a שעיר sa'ir, *Se'ir*. He doesn't bring based on
the sliding scale, so it's a bizarre hybrid. Yes he's in the
category of עולה ויורד oleh veyored, *Oleh v'yored*, but when he's obligated,
he brings his normal קרבן korban, *Korban*. So this is disagreeing with
those other opinions you had before? Right, I mean he's not disagreeing
that he's חייב *Chayav*, but he's talking about then once he's חייב
*Chayav*, the type of קרבן korban *Korban* he's going to bring. It's
not- he's not disagreeing, that wasn't discussed until now, but implicit in
the other positions is that yes, you're right, because the whole fact
that we say could he bring בדלי דלות *B'dalei dalos*? So right,
yes, the other positions were assuming that obviously if you're going to
be חייב *Chayav* an עולה ויורד oleh veyored, *Oleh v'yored* it's going
to be the normal- the normal קרבן korban *Korban*. Okay, let's take
a look. תניא *Tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braisa *Braisa*, רבי
שמעון היה נותן כלל היה נותן בהם סימנים *Rabbi Shimon hayah nosein
klal hayah nosein bahem simanim*. דשח- Okay, היה נותן כלל *Hayah nosein
klal*, כל שהיחיד באשם תלוי *Kol she'hayachid b'asham taluy*. This was the
general rule, as long if a case where an individual would bring
an אשם תלוי asham talui. *Asham taluy*, הנשיא hanasi כיוצא בו *Hanasi
k'yotze bo*. So in a case of a normal חטאת chatas, *Chatas*
that you don't know if you did it, you bring an אשם
תלוי *Asham taluy*, so a נשיא nasi *Nasi* is just like an
individual for an אשם תלוי *Asham taluy*. ומשיח ובית דין פטורים *Umashiach
u'bais din peturin*. משיח *Mashiach* and בית דין *Bais din* they're on
the other side because an אשם תלוי *Asham taluy* is only for
things that's based just for action. וכל שהוא באשם ודאי *V'chol she'hu
b'asham vadai*, anytime that you're talking about a case of an אשם
ודאי *Asham vadai* for a normal person, נשיא nasi משיח כיוצא בהם
*Nasi mashiach k'yotze bahem*. So then they're just like any other individual.
Okay, ובית דין פטורים *Ubais din peturin*. שמיעת הקול וביטוי שפתים וטומאת
מקדש וקדשיו *Sh'mias hakol v'vituos sefasayim v'tum'as mikdash v'kodashav*. How about the
things that you would bring for an עולה ויורד oleh veyored *Oleh
v'yored*? בית דין פטורים *Bais din peturin*, בית דין *Bais din*'s exempt,
they're linked to a חטאת chatas, *Chatas*. נשיא nasi ומשיח חייבים *Nasi
u'mashiach chayavim*. And a נשיא nasi *Nasi* and a משיח *Mashiach* at
least in principle are חייב *Chayav*, till we start getting to pick
away at it. אלא שאין הנשיא חייב בשמיעת הקול. The only a
נשיא nasi is exempt from the oath about testifying. ולא משיח בטומאת
מקדש וקדשיו. Velo mashiach betumat mikdash vekodashav. And the כהן גדול kohen
gadol for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumat mikdash vekodashav. not like some positions
we saw earlier that would totally exclude a נשיא nasi or totally
exclude a כהן גדול. kohen gadol כל שהוא בעולה ויורד, Kol shehu
be’oleh veyored, נשיא כיוצא בו, nasi kayotze vo, משיח ובית דין פטורין.
mashiach uveit din peturin. Now if you’re dealing with an עולה ויורד
oleh veyored. which hey, weren’t we just dealing with an עולה ויורד?
oleh veyored So this line is going to seem to contradict the
previous one. If you’re dealing with an עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, so
a נשיא nasi? is in the category of an עולה ויורד, oleh
veyored but a כהן גדול kohen gadol and a בית דין are
not in the category. So that’s bizarre. One point you say a
כהן גדול kohen gadol is in the category of עולה ויורד oleh
veyored. except for טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash. and now you say he’s
fundamentally not in the category of עולה ויורד. oleh veyored, So make
up your mind. So that’s what the גמרא Gemara says. הגופא קשיא,
Hagufa kashya, you’re contradicting yourself. אמרת שמשיח חייב בטומאת מקדש וקדשיו. Amarta
shemashiach chayav betumat mikdash vekodashav. First you were saying a כהן גדול
kohen gadol is in the category of עולה ויורד oleh veyored. with
the exception of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash? מטומאת מקדש וקדשיו הוא דפטור
אבל בשמיעת הקול ובביטוי שפתיים חייב. Mitumat mikdash vekodashav hu depatur aval
bishmiat hakol uvitui sfatayim chayav. But by the other two he’s חייב.
אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at the next line of the ברייתא
brayta you just said. כל שהוא בעולה ויורד, Kol shehu be’oleh veyored,
anybody who is in the עולה ויורד, oleh veyored. נשיא כיוצא בו,
nasi kayotze vo, so a נשיא nasi, is in the עולה ויורד
oleh veyored. category. משיח ובית דין פטורין, Mashiach uveit din peturin, but
a משיח, a כהן גדול kohen gadol is fundamentally excluded. So both
of those are legitimate options, but you can’t say them both; they
contradict one another. So קתני משיח ובית דין פטורין. Katani mashiach uveit
din peturin. מה בית דין פטורין מכולהו, Ma beis din peturin mikulhu,
the same way בית דין means they’re fundamentally completely excluded. אף משיח
פטור מכולהו, Af mashiach patur mikulhu, same as a כהן גדול. kohen
gadol So what’s the story? Is a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, completely
out of the category or just out of it for טומאת מקדש?
tumat mikdash. קשיא אהדדי, Kashya ahadadi, top of דף י׳ עמוד ב׳.
daf yud amud beis. Doesn’t this contradict itself? So אמר רב הונא
בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua, לא קשיא, lo
kashya, it’s not difficult. כאן בדלות כאן בדלי דלות. Kan bidalus kan
bidlei dalus. It’s a difference between whether we’re dealing with the lowest
level, the מנחה, mincha or we’re dealing with the middle level, the
bird. Okay, so what he basically is going to say is, I’ll
say it first and then I’ll read it inside, like the first
line, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol fundamentally is in the category with
the exception of טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash? What about the line when
we said a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is fundamentally excluded? It means
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was excluded from bringing a קרבן מנחה.
korban mincha. A כהן גדול Kohen Gadol's would never bring the מנחה
mincha of an עולה ויורד. oleh veyored, Okay, which is funny, like
when would he ever be that poor? But were he that poor,
he would never bring a מנחה mincha. and he would be פטור.
Okay, so that’s all we meant when we excluded him. Okay, so
רב שמעון סבירא ליה כרבי עקיבא בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא. Rav Shimon
sevira lei k’Rabbi Akiva bechada ufalig alei bechada. He holds like רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in one way and he disagrees in another. סבירא
ליה כרבי עקיבא בדלי דלות דפטור. Sevira lei k’Rabbi Akiva bidlei dalus
depatur. He agrees that the פסוק pasuk זה קרבן אהרן ובניו zeh
korban Aharon uvanav says that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol will never
bring a מנחה mincha as an obligation other than his daily מנחה.
mincha, So therefore a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol when it says he’s
excluded from עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, it means he’s excluded from the
מנחה mincha, of עולה ויורד. oleh veyored, Okay, ופליג עליה בדלות. ufalig
alei bidalus. But he disagrees. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says once he’s
excluded from the מנחה, mincha he’s completely excluded. ורב שמעון v’Rav Shimon
says no, he’s excluded from the מנחה, mincha. but he’s obligated in
the other parts of an עולה ויורד. oleh veyored, Okay, that’s a
little difficult read, I mean to say that when we were saying
we’re excluding him, we mean he doesn’t bring the מנחה mincha. part.
Anyway, bottom line though, what this seeming contradiction is reflecting is these
two different approaches. Right? Do you say fundamentally a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol is in the category, but there’s some cases he’s excluded, like
the case of טומאת מקדש? tumat mikdash Or do you say he’s
like בית דין הגדול? Beis Din Hagadol? That since his פסק psak,
is based on like הוראה hora'ah etc., you know maybe that fundamentally,
I mean the גמרא Gemara hasn’t said that idea, the גמרא Gemara
has given different reasons: he never gets poor, you know, he doesn’t
bring a מנחה. mincha. But anyway, for one reason or another that
he’s fundamentally excluded from עולה ויורד. oleh veyored So those two approaches
are said side by side and the גמרא Gemara resolves it in
this way, that he’s excluded just from the מנחה. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara, continues. Now we get to the idea why the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is in
the category, why he doesn’t bring for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tumat mikdash
vekodashav. אלא שאין כהן גדול חייב. Ella she’ein kohen gadol chayav.
He’s not חייב for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tumas mikdash v'kodashav אמר חזקיה
מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון? Amar Chizkiyah mai ta’ama d’Rabbi Shimon? What’s this
reasoning of רבי שמעון? דכתיב ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מתוך הקהל. Dechtiv venichresa
hanefesh hahi mitoch hakahal. That soul should be cut off from the
congregation. Okay, the soul that sins with טומאת מקדש tumas mikdash. is
טמא. tamei. Okay, and enters in, you know, and I think this
is את מקדש ה׳ טמא. es mikdash Hashem tamei. Thank you. Okay,
so somebody who’s טמא tamei and enters in, he’s cut off. So
he’s talking about מי שקרבנו שווה לקהל. mi shekorbano shaveh lakahal. So
who is? So only somebody that’s מתוך הקהל, mitoch hakahal, somebody whose
קרבן korban about טומאה tumah is the same as the קרבן korban
as the rest of the community. יצא זה שאין קרבנו שווה לקהל.
Yatza zeh she’ein korbano shaveh lakahal. A כהן גדול’s Kohen Gadol קרבן
korban, when it comes to טומאה, tumah, I’m sort of jumping a
little ahead in the גמרא, Gemara is not the same as the
rest of the community because if you think about it, on יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, right? The fundamental thing the פסוקים psukim we all...
Always talk about the קרבנות korbanot of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the
ox and the goat, you know, as like it's about atoning for
the sins. But actually, the goat that atones for the sins is
the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir La'Azazel. The actual thing that it emphasizes in
terms of the ox and the goat in the תורה Torah is
וכיפר על הקודש מטומאות בני ישראל. Vekiper Al Hakodesh Mitum'ot Bnei Yisrael.
Okay, and there you have a separate קרבן, korban the כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol actually all of the כהנים, Kohanim, which is what we'll
ask in a minute, קרבן korban is distinct from that from the
community, which means that the תורה Torah is saying, and this makes
a lot of sense, sort of like what we said before, which
is, is that the טומאה tumah of כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. and
of the כהנים, Kohanim, because they are all the time, is put
in a different category than that is the community, their issues with
טומאת מקדש. tumas mikdash, So therefore, the תורה Torah says that this
thing of מתוך הקהל mitoch hakahal is saying, now of course this
is talking about כרת kares and we're talking about a קרבן, korban
but nevertheless, it's sort of saying that only if you're part of
the larger community does the קרבן korban of the larger community apply
to you. And therefore the קרבן korban עולה ויורד, oleh veyored the
same way on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, their קרבן korban of טומאה
tumah doesn't apply to you, so the קרבן korban עולה ויורד oleh
veyored, also doesn't apply to you. It's a nice סברא. svara. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara, says אם כן im ken now, but the
גמרא, Gemara I jumped ahead, and I said it's about a קרבן
korban of טומאה. tumah. For now the גמרא Gemara thinks we're just
talking about a קרבן korban in general. So a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol has a special קרבן, korban he has an ox for a
normal sin. So if that's all you need to have a special
קרבן korban to be excluded from טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash? אם כן
נשיא נמי אין קרבנו שוה לקהל. im ken nasi nami ein korbano
shaveh lakahal. So a כהן גדול kohen gadol also, so a נשיא
nasi also doesn't bring the same קרבן korban? as the rest of
the community, right? He's got his special קרבן korban of the goat.
So why doesn't that also say, oh, so you're not part of
the community by טומאת מקדש? tumas mikdash So the גמרא Gemara says:
שוה בכפרה דיום הכיפורים. shaveh bakaparah deYom Hakippurim. So that's really the
punchline. It's not about your general קרבן korban, of
a sin, is it the same or different from the community? It's
about יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. On יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, his טומאה tumah is the
same as the טומאה tumah of the community, whereas the כהן גדול
kohen gadol טומאה tumah and the טומאה tumah of the כהנים Kohanim
is in a separate category. Why do we focus on just one
day out of the year as opposed to all the rest? Well,
that's, that's significant. I mean, יום כיפור Yom Kippur is the heightened
day where it's all about cleansing the מקדש, and it signifies the
idea that we look at כהנים Kohanim in their relationship to טומאת
מקדש tumas mikdash, in a different category than we look at ישראל.
Yisrael. I think it's a nice point. The only point is that
then the גמרא Gemara: says the logical conclusion is it should apply
to all כהנים. Kohanim. Right. אם כן, im ken, yeah, the fact
that the כהן kohen brings all these thousands of קרבנות korbanot for
others, that doesn't give them any credit. Right. Well, maybe it does.
Maybe that's like what we were saying, the ציץ is there for,
you know, to be מכפר for טומאת מקדש, tumas mikdash so maybe
it is, like maybe that's why we're giving him a little license.
אם כן, im ken, says the גמרא: Gemara כהנים נמי לא שוי
לקהל בכפרה דיום הכיפורים. Kohanim nami lo shavei lakahal bakaparah deYom Hakippurim.
Okay, so כהנים Kohanim also shouldn't bring a קרבן korban. for טומאת
מקדש tumas mikdash. because they have a different קרבן korban, on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. כהנים שוי לקהל בשאר מצות דשתא כולה. Kohanim shavei
lakahal beshar mitzvot deshana kula. All right, but for other sins, like
let's say a בית דין פוסק'נס paskens and people follow בית דין,
right, including כהנים, Kohanim, they'll be part of the community in other
ways. So maybe you're right that when it comes to טומאה tumah
you're a separate group, but since in other ways you're part of
the community, we're not going to fully separate you out. But a
כהן גדול kohen gadol is always separate. He's separate by טומאה tumah
and he's separate by normal sins. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, it says משיח נמי השוה בשאר מצות דשתא. mashiach nami hashava
beshar mitzvot deshana. But remember we taught that if the בית דין
פוסק'ד, paskened, you know, maybe the כהן גדול kohen gadol brings his
own קרבן korban as an individual, but if the בית דין פוסק
pasken and the community listen to the בית דין and the כהן
גדול kohen gadol also does a similar act, he is part of
the community there. He's not seen as separate. So if the idea
is that he's separate for טומאה, tumah, that's true about the rest
of the כהנים. Kohanim. If the idea is that the rest of
the כהנים Kohanim are part of the community when it's a communal
sin, a כהן גדול kohen gadol is also part of the community
when it's a communal sin. So we still don't understand why a
כהן גדול kohen gadol is a separate קרבן korban for טומאת מקדש.
tumas mikdash. Okay, אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, so rather רבא
Rava says: אימא הכי, eima hachi, מי שחטאתו שוה ליחידים ומאי ניהו
קהל. mi shechataso shava leyachidim umai nihu kahal. No, the explanation of
the פסוק pasuk is that only somebody whose sin is like a
normal sin of a normal private individual. A normal private individual's sin
is based on just שגגת מעשה, shiggas ma'aseh, just on action. A
כהן גדול kohen gadol whose sin is also based on פסק, psak,
they're not seen when it comes to sin as the same as
the rest of the community. So it says: ונכרתה מתוך הקהל, venichresa
mitoch hakahal, you have to be a normal member of a community.
A normal member of a community, it's right, like that we pointed
out that's bizarre about a כהן גדול. kohen gadol, A כהן גדול
kohen gadol normally is not seen as a פוסק paskening body, but
when it comes even to his private sin, he's not just like
any normal individual. He did a private sin, he accidentally ate חמץ
פסח, chametz pesach, no, if you're not somehow also doing some official
capacity of פוסק paskening and then acting on your own פסק, psak.
you don't bring for your own private sin. It's almost like saying,
I mean, maybe one way as you know, for if you were
here the last two days you, I mean, you heard me struggle
with this idea. Why does the כהן גדול kohen gadol need to
פסקן? pasken? Why is that relevant? פסקנינג paskening for himself? But maybe
part of the point like we learn, when it says in אמור,
Emor, right? ומן המקדש לא יצא, U'min hamikdash lo yeitzei, that he
doesn't even and it's actually coming up in שמיני, Shemini, the whole
question about אהרן Aharon is told ignore the fact that your sons
died, and the כהן גדול kohen gadol with his relatives die, he
doesn't leave the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So כהן גדול kohen gadol?
is like somebody that's not allowed a private life whose entire identity
is as a public individual. I think that's part of the message
of the תורה Torah that he doesn't even go to mourn for
when his father or mother dies, right? So somebody who's always a
public individual, you don't get to bring a קרבן korban for your
private sin. Yes, you sinned, whatever, but that would be in your
capacity as a private individual. You never get to be a private
individual. You're always a public individual. So only if you פסקנד, paskened,
even though you're פסקנינג paskening for yourself, but then to some degree
your private sin is also somehow reflective of a public type of
a role. Because one of the roles, I know, yeah, I don't
really get it. Okay but anyway, but the king, but at least
by the כהן kohen you do have this emphasis, right? He doesn't
get to mourn and so on. So since one of the roles
of a כהן kohen is פסק להורות את בני ישראל, psak l'horos
es Bnei Yisrael, somehow that's I think the sense. Okay, that he
only he never gets to be seen as a private individual. So
if that's true, that's sort of what the גמרא Gemara is saying
here, מתוך הקהל. mitoch hakahal. Only somebody who is like any normal
member of the society, which surprisingly as Michael pointed out even includes
a king, gets a private life, is seen as a normal individual,
when they're normal sin, they bring for טומאת מקדש. tumas mikdash But
you who's always a public individual, and you're never like a normal
person, you don't bring. Now, why this plays out by טומאת מקדש
tumas mikdash? and not by other things, I don't have the slightest
idea. Why of all things should it play out by טומאת מקדש?
tumas mikdash If anything, טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash is specifically in his
public capacity. So I really don't understand it. Yes, but when you
were going through this in the last couple days, I kept thinking
of this משנה mishna in יומא Yoma where the כהן גדול kohen
gadol is taught all the הלכות halachos by the sages and it's
very clear that the כהן גדול kohen gadol is not in charge
and doesn't have the right to, well, that's true too. That's a
question about authority and certainly in the eyes of חז"ל, Chazal, it's
very questionable if this was ever historically accurate, but in the eyes
of חז"ל, Chazal, the idea that a rabbinic authority was over the
כהונה kehunah authority. But that's different. This is חז"ל Chazal too. Yeah,
I understand. But that's different. That's a question about power and authority.
This is a question about what public versus private role. Okay. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר הנשיא מביא שעיר. meivi sa'ir. הנשיא מביא שעיר.
sa'ir. Even when the נשיא nasi is going to bring for an
עולה ויורד, oleh veyored it's not going to be the standard קרבן
korban of עולה ויורד, olah veyored it's going to be a שעיר.
sa'ir. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן לא אמר רבי אליעזר אלא בטומאת מקדש
וקדשיו הואיל ונאמר כרת בו כבקבוע. Amar Rabbi Yochanan lo amar Rabbi
Eliezer ela b'tumas mikdash v'kodashav ho'il v'ne'emar kares bo k'be'kavua. So רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only said it by טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumas mikdash
v'kodashav because yes on the one hand it's an עולה ויורד, olah
veyored so it should go by the sliding scale. On the other
hand, of the three of not testifying and swearing falsely, טומאת מקדש
וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodashav is the only thing that has the normal
conditions of a normal קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. It's something that when
you do it willfully, you get כרת. kares. So if the תורה
Torah had not put it in the עולה ויורד, olah veyored it
would have been a normal חטאת. chatas. And therefore, since this would
have been a normal חטאת, chatas he says that when the נשיא
nasi brings it, he brings his normal קרבן korban, of a שעיר,
sa'ir which is bizarre because individuals don't bring their normal קרבנות, korbanos,
they're in the sliding scale. Actually wait, let me just double check
that. What is the קרבן? korban Is it the same כשבה kesbah
or שעירה? se'irah? What's at the top of the scale? I forget.
No, והביא את אשמו חטאת אשר חטא נקבה מן הצאן כשבה או
שעירת עזים לחטאת. v'heivi es ashamo chatas asher chata nekeivah min hatzon
kesbah o se'iras izim l'chatas. Yes, so that makes sense. So the
top of the scale is the normal קרבן korban. that you would
bring for a חטאת. chatas. It's a כשבה kesbah or שעירה. se'irah.
Okay, so now it makes sense. He's saying, look, when you're at
the top of the this type of a thing is had it
not been put in the עולה ויורד olah veyored. would have been
a חטאת. chatas Even in the עולה ויורד olah veyored category, the
top of the scale is a normal חטאת, chatas a כשבה kesbah
or שעירה. se'irah. So therefore, the נשיא nasi is going to bring
a שעיר. se'ir. Okay now, okay, so let's take a look. He
will bring what he would normally bring for his sin. Wait, a
male one, the שעיר. se'ir. A male, right, because that would be
true by a normal חטאת, chatas a normal person would bring a
כשבה kesbah or שעירה. se'irah. Okay. אמר Amar okay, הואיל ונאמר כרת
בו כבקבוע. ho'il v'ne'emar kares bo k'be'kavua. אמר רב פפא הכא נמי
מסתברא. Amar Rav Papa hacha nami mistabra. That also makes sense. דאי
סלקא דעתך רבי אליעזר אכולהון קאמר. D'ei salka dach'tach Rabbi Eliezer akulhon
ka'amar. If he's saying that the נשיא nasi would bring a goat
for all of the sins of עולה ויורד, olah veyored מכדי שעיר
נשיא ופר משיח במקום יחיד דחטאת קאי. michdi sa'ir nasi v'par mashiach
bimkom yachid d'chatas ka'i. So the שעיר se'ir, of the נשיא nasi
and the פר משיח par mashiach are what they normally bring when
a normal person brings a normal חטאת. chatas So if you're going
to say that let's replace the נשיא nasi when it's a נשיא
nasi who does an עולה ויורד olah veyored he should bring. his
שעיר. se'ir Why don't you say that when the כהן גדול kohen
gadol gets an עולה ויורד olah veyored, he should bring a פר?
par That makes sense by parallel: if a נשיא's nasi going to
bring his standard קרבן, korban the כהן גדול kohen gadol should bring
his standard קרבן. korban. Okay, so נסטינני nistinani משיח מביא פר בשמיעת
קול וביטוי שפתים. mashiach meivi par bishmiat kol ubituy sefatayim. So why
did he only say his הלכה halacha by the נשיא? nasi Why
didn't he say the exact same thing, let a כהן גדול kohen
gadol bring a פר par when he's in the עולה ויורד olah
veyored, category? אלא מדלא קתני משיח, ela mide lo katani mashiach, since
he didn't say that, שמע מינה, shma mina, טומאת מקדש וקדשיו קאי.
tumat mikdash vekodashav ka'i. So that shows you that even when he
said it about a נשיא, nasi he only said it by טומאת
מקדש tumat mikdash. because that would be a כרת, kares, that would
be a normal type of a חטאת chatas, under other circumstances. And
that's why he couldn't say the same thing by a כהן גדול,
kohen gadol because דמשיח פטור, de'mashiach patar, because a כהן גדול kohen
gadol doesn't bring for טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash, Okay. So he asks
a very logical question. I get רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer whole סברא
svara here that when somebody's doing an עולה ויורד olah veyored they
bring their special קרבן, korban, so the נשיא nasi is going to
bring a שעיר. se'ir But why not say a כהן גדול kohen
gadol brings a פר? par. So the only logic is because he
was only talking about טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodashav where a
כהן גדול's kohen gadol excluded. Okay, and even when he says the
נשיא nasi brings his שעיר, se'ir it's only the one that is
about something that corresponds to כרת, kares, okay, that a normal חטאת.
chatas שמע מינה טומאת מקדש וקדשיו קאי דמשיח פטור. shma mina tumat
mikdash vekodashav ka'i de'mashiach patar. That's a nice דיוק. diyuk. אמרי ליה
רב הונא בריה דרב נתן לרב פפא, amre leh Rav Huna brei
de'Rav Natan le'Rav Papa, ממי, mi'mai, who says that that's the right
read? דילמא dilma רבי אליעזר אכולם קאי. Rabbi Eliezer akulam ka'i. Maybe
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that a נשיא nasi brings a שעיר
se'ir. for all three of the sins of עולה ויורד. oleh ve-yored,
So then why didn't he say the same about a כהן גדול?
Kohen Gadol ובמשיח סבר לה כרבי עקיבא דאמר משיח פטור מכולם. u've'mashiach
savar lei ke'Rabbi Akiva de'amar mashiach patar mi'kulam. Maybe he didn't say
it because maybe he holds that a כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol categorically
excluded from עולה ויורד and not for your reasoning. אמר ליה, amar
lei, רבי עקיבא מי פטר ליה מפר ולא מידי? Rabbi Akiva mi'patar
lei mi'par ve'lo midis? So now the גמרא Gemara. drops a little
bit of a bomb and it says, until now we used to
say that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva totally excluded a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol? from עולה ויורד because he can't bring, you know, the מנחה.
Now we're saying just because he excluded him from the specific קרבנות
korbanot that the תורה Torah indicates for an עולה ויורד doesn't mean
that he excluded a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. completely. Maybe רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva would say that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would bring
a פר par? for an עולה ויורד, which is a very bizarre
idea because a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, usually only brings a פר
par, when there's an idea of a פסק. psak. But here there's
no idea of a פסק. psak, Okay. So we're putting out there
as a hypothetical possibility that even for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not fully excluded and could bring a
פר. par, So then we say, which is bizarre, but okay. But
then we say, so why did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only speak
about the נשיא nasi, bringing a שעיר se'ir, and not a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol, bringing a פר? par? So it must be that
he holds even when a נשיא nasi brings a שעיר se'ir it's
only for טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash. only for something that you would
normally, if it had not been an עולה ויורד, would have brought
a חטאת chatas for. And that's why he didn't give the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol. example because a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol doesn't bring
for טומאת מקדש. tumat mikdash Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan
מודה רבי אליעזר שאין מביא אשם. modeh Rabbi Eliezer she'ein meivi asham.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. would agree that the נשיא nasi would not
bring an אשם for, you know, when he brings an אשם he
does not bring let me just check רש"י Rashi here, one minute,
oh right, an אשם תלוי. One minute. Ah right, even though he
is treating the sin of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodashav like
a normal type of a חטאת chatas, because it basically has a
חיוב כרת, chiyuv kares, and therefore it allows him to say that
when a נשיא Nasi does the sin of טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash
he's going to bring his normal קרבן korban, of a שעיר. sa'ir.
Okay, that טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash we're going to look at as
a type of a normal חטאת at least for that הלכה. halacha.
We're not going to look at it as a normal חטאת that
if there's a ספק safek you say you bring an אשם תלוי.
אשם תלוי is still only going to be for a חטאת קבועה.
chatas kavua. So even though, yes, it's true that טומאת מקדש tumat
mikdash had it not been עולה ויורד would have been a normal
חטאת, and that allows him to say that a נשיא Nasi brings
a שעיר, sa'ir it's not going to, we're not going to treat
it as a normal חטאת to the point that says you'll even
bring an אשם תלוי. Okay. מודה רבי אליעזר שאין מביא אשם. modeh
Rabbi Eliezer she'ein meivi asham. תני תנא קמיה דרב ששת tanei tana
kamei de'Rav Sheshet אשם תלוי בא על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. asham taluy
ba al tumat mikdash vekodashav. Now as opposed to what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan just said, a תנא tana actually had a ברייתא braisa
that says that you would bring an אשם תלוי if you had
a ספק safek whether you did the sin of being מטמא metameh
the בית המקדש. beit hamikdash. אמר ליה דאמר לך מני רבי אליעזר
היא, amar lei de'amar lach mani Rabbi Eliezer hi, so רב ששת
Rav Sheshet said back, "Oh, that makes sense that there would be
an אשם תלוי for טומאת מקדש tumat mikdash, according to רבי אליעזר."
Rabbi Eliezer דאמר חובה נאמר בו כרת כבקבואה מעשה נשיא שעיר עליה.
de'amar hova neemar bo kares k'bekavua ma'asei nasi se'ir aleha. Since רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that the נשיא Nasi. brings a שעיר sa'ir
because he treats טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tum'as mikdash ve-kodashav as a type
of a regular קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, so according to that, it
would logically follow that you could bring an אשם תלוי on טומאת
מקדש, tumat mikdash we would treat טומאת מקדש as a type of
a regular קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. Okay, so... But that's against what
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. ואמר רבי יוחנן מודה רבי אליעזר שאין
מביא אשם תלוי. ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan modeh Rabbi Eliezer she-ein mevi asham
talui. But wait a minute, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wouldn't go that far. He's only saying exchange of
the כשבה, kisba, you know, exchange the שעירה se'irah and the כשבה
kisba for the נשיא's Nasi שעיר. sa'ir You know, that's what he's
saying, like which animal you bring, but he's not fundamentally treating it
as a חטאת and he's not saying that you bring an אשם
תלוי. קשיא. Kasha. That's difficult. That's nice that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said it, but here we have a ברייתא braisa, and at least
according to this ברייתא, it believes that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, really
treated טומאת מקדש וקדשיו as a type of a normal חטאת, both
to say that a נשיא Nasi, brings a שעיר se'ir, and to
say that you have an אשם תלוי. So that's an interesting idea.
Okay, and again the other interesting thing that we just mentioned in
passing, which was wild, which was even though we thought that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was completely excluding a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. from
עולה ויורד, we have the possibility that he would actually bring a
פר, par which is really wild, how you make that hybrid type
of a thing and there's no פסק, pasken you normally need a
הוראה hora'ah, and so on. Okay, הדרן עלך הכהן המשיח. hadran alach
hakohen hamashiach. Let's now we have eight more minutes, so let's get
to the let's finish let's begin the next פרק. perek. כהן משיח
שחטא ואחר כך עבר ממשיחותו. Kohen mashiach she-chata ve-acharchach avar mi-meshichuso. Okay,
he sinned as a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. and then he got
deposed. All right. So now does he bring a קרבן korban, now
as a normal כהן kohen based on the type of קרבן korban,
he would have brought as a כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol He sinned
as a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, Okay, so but he's just not
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. now. One minute. וכן נשיא שחטא ואחר
כך עבר מגדולתו, ve-chen nasi she-chata ve-acharchach avar mi-gedulaso, or a נשיא
Nasi that sinned as a נשיא Nasi and then he was obligated
a שעיר se'ir, but now he got deposed and he's no longer
a king. Does he bring a שעיר for the sin that he
did as a king? Okay, כהן משיח מביא פר ונשיא מביא שעיר.
Kohen mashiach mevi par ve-nasi mevi se'ir. Yes, you bring the קרבן
korban. for based on the conditions when you did the sin, even
though those are not your current conditions. We're going to find out
that there's going to be a position, I think of רבי אליעזר,
that's going to say that actually you need both. If you didn't,
you need to become aware of your sin, you know, when you
were a king, when you were a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol and
only then when you sinned and became aware and the same status.
But that's not what our משנה mishna says. Our משנה mishna. says
that as long as the sin was when you were at that
status, that's the way you bring your קרבן, korban. even if you're
not in that status right now. Now, משיח שעבר, mashiach she-avar, okay,
now, okay, משיח שעבר ממשיחותו. mashiach she-avar mi-meshichuso. Now let's say you
have a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, who's no longer a כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol okay, but as Charlie was indicating before, you don't really
fully stop being a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol Okay, so we'll see
about that. Right. So we'll see about that. So that plays out
a little bit at the end of this משנה. mishna So you're
no longer a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, ואחר כך חטא, ve-acharchach chata,
and then you sinned. So you sinned only when you were a
past כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol Okay, when you did the sin you
were no longer a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol וכן הנשיא שעבר מגדולתו
ואחר כך חטא, ve-chen hanasi she-avar mi-gedulaso ve-acharchach chata, or let's say
you used to be a king and now you're not a king
and now you sinned. So you would think you totally go by
your current status, right? Because you didn't do the the sin you
did, you know, that other status you had was only in the
past. So it says, כהן משיח מביא פר והנשיא כהדיוט. Kohen mashiach
mevi par ve-hanasi ke-hedyot. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, still brings it
as if he were still a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol even though
he's no longer כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol Okay, and this probably has
a lot to do with the fact that even when a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol stops being an acting כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol he
doesn't fully lose the status. Amen. But the thing is, there are
sins that can only be committed by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and the king. Right. And that once he's no longer the king
he can't, okay, but we're not that but fine, but we're not
talking about that. Okay, we're talking it doesn't matter what the sin
is. Okay, a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who is a past כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol even if he sins after he's been deposed, he
still retains his status of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. for the
point in the sense that the קרבן korban, he's going to bring
is still the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol קרבן. korban By the way,
which would presumably mean that he also has to, I mean it's
not explicit, but it would presumably mean he also has to פסק
psak and act on it. Right. So he's still that that his
קרבן still reflects his old status of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol:
whereas a נשיא Nasi, who no longer is a נשיא, for him,
you know, now that he sinned after he got deposed as king,
he's just like any commoner and he brings a normal קרבן. Okay,
so the obviously the funny case here is the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol who was deposed, that his status still keeps with him. So
let's just see a little bit about that in the גמרא. Gemara
First גמרא Gemara just points out that the משנה mishna? is a
little bit, you know, a little redundant. השתא יש לומר עבר ממשיחותו
ואחר כך חטא מביא פר. Hashata yesh lomar avar mi-meshichuso ve-acharchach chata
mevi par. So if you say that once you said that even
after he's stopped being a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol he sins, he
still brings the פר, par. so why did you need the first
line in the משנה? חטא ואחר כך עבר ממשיחותו צריכא למימר? chata
ve-acharchach avar mi-meshichuso tzricha le-meimar? So why did you have to say
the first line? Why did you have to say that if he
sinned as a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. and now he's no longer
he still brings the פר? par Of course! He's going to bring
a פר even if his sin happened after he was deposed. So
the גמרא Gemara says you're right, but it's stylistic. משום דקתני גבי
נשיא דכי עבר מנשיאותו ואחר כך חטא כהדיוט. mishum de-katani gabei nasi
de-ki avar mi-nesiuso ve-acharchach chata ke-hedyot. Since by the נשיא there's a
contrast, that when he sinned as a נשיא and now he's not...
That if he sinned as a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. and now
he's no longer, he still brings the פר. Of course! He's going
to bring the פר even if his sin happened after he was
deposed. So the גמרא says you're right, but it's stylistic. משום דקתני
גבי נשיא דכי עבר מנשיאותיה ואחר חטא כהדיוט mishum d'katni gabi Nasi
d'ki avar minesi'usa ve'achar chata kehedyot since by the נשיא there's a
contrast that when he sinned as a נשיא and now he's not,
he brings the שעיר, but if he's not and then he sinned,
then he's like a normal person. So מאי הכי, maisy, הכי תני
גבי משיח חטא ואחר כך עבר hachi tani gabei Mashiach chata ve'achar
kach avar מביא פר. meivi par. Fine, it's stylistic, right? It obviously
makes for better structure. So yes, once you say the second ruling
by כהן גדול Kohen Gadol the first is superfluous but you want
to sort of point out the difference between that and a נשיא.
A נשיא when he sinned as a נשיא, it's a שעיר, when
he sinned after he was deposed, it's like a normal person, a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol whether if he sinned as a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol. or sinned after he was deposed, he always brings as
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, So now, מנא הני מילי? minani mili?
So where's this idea from that you would say a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol doesn't lose his status? So, דתנו רבנן, d'tano rabbanan, והקריב
על חטאתו. ve'hikriv al chataso. This is by the כהן גדול: Kohen
Gadol, he shall bring on his sin. מלמד שמביא חטאתו משעבר. melamed
shemeivi chataso mishe'avar. So because it's על חטאתו, al chataso, it's somehow
it's past-oriented on the sin that he has done, it shows you
that even if it's something of the past. Now the funny thing
is from the פסוק pasuk the sin is of the past, but
somehow we're reading it like even if his status his sin as
a כהן גדול—no Kohen Gadol, but he didn't sin as a כהן
גדול—even Kohen Gadol though somehow his כהונה kehuna status is a past
thing, he's still going to bring as a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Like I really don't get how he gets it from the פסוק.
pasuk. Somehow the past language allows us to tell us that even
though he himself is no longer a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol שיכול
ולא דינו, sheyachol velo dino, I could make a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. ומה נשיא שמביא בשגגת מעשה, umah Nasi shemeivi bishigas ma'aseh, נשיא
who has a lower threshold of bringing a קרבן, simply an action,
אין מביא חטאתו משעבר, ein meivi chataso mishe'avar, he doesn't bring his
sin offering as a נשיא after he's been deposed even though you
know it's not such special conditions under which he brings, but nevertheless
once he's not a נשיא, his status, you know, his status changes.
משיח שאין מביא בשגגת מעשה אלא עם דבר עם שגגת מעשה, Mashiach
she'ein meivi bishigas ma'aseh ella im davar im shigas ma'aseh, כהן גדול
that has a high criteria to bring a קרבן, not only an
action, a פסק psak and an action, לא כל שכן lo kol
shekein certainly I should think that when he's no longer an acting
כהן גדול that those special you know that it you don't bring
the same קרבן, it's a very special קרבן, it's a very limited
type of a קרבן. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar והקריב על חטאתו, ve'hikriv
al chataso, מלמד שמביא על חטאתו משעבר, melamed shemeivi al chataso mishe'avar,
he brings on it even after, even על חטאתו al chataso even
his sin I guess now even if he's no longer a כהן
גדול. I really still don't get how they get it from the
פסוק. pasuk. But it doesn't emphasize that he remains the status of
a כהן גדול, which there are some ways where he never fully
loses the status and it could have said that. It makes it
more a detail in the הלכות halachos of a כהן גדול's קרבן.
Once כהן גדול, not once כהן גדול, once a כהן גדול you
know once he had one category of קרבן, that's the category of
קרבן that will remain. And presumably it means that he also needs
a הוראה, even though he's no longer a כהן גדול. He only
brings under the same conditions as a כהן גדול with this type
of פסק and action. Okay, we will continue tomorrow.