Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is דף ח, Daf
Chet, we pick up with the משנה, mishna, also the אסיסי דייומא.
asisei d'yoma. We're in the second פרק, perek, we're dealing with not
only the קרבן korban of the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol
when the people follow, but also the קרבן korban of the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, which has this strange idea that it's parallel. He
has to פסקן pasken for himself and follow his own פסק, psak,
and otherwise if he does a normal sin בשוגג, b'shogeg, he doesn't
bring the קרבן, korban, very strange idea. Anyway, and we're dealing with
various parallels, also in the case though by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
where there it's a she-goat, right, a normal individual, and there there's
a debate of the רבי Rebbe and the חכמים. Chachamim. רבי Rebbe
says there he's fully like a normal individual and doesn't need that
special פסק psak for himself, but the חכמים Chachamim say even there
he needs the special פסק psak for himself. So now we continue
with the משנה mishna on ח עמוד א. Chet Amud Aleph. אין
בית דין חייב עד שיורו בדבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת. Ein Beis
Din chayav ad she-yiru b'davar she-zidono kares v'shigigato chatas. When does the
בית דין Beis Din bring their special קרבן, korban, the פר, par,
when they give a wrong פסק psak and people follow it? It's
only a type of a sin that if you were to do
it intentionally you'd get כרת, kares, and if a normal person would
do it unintentionally without this special circumstances that we're talking about, they
would bring a normal חטאת, chatas, a normal sin offering.
So their קרבן korban is for a sin that would otherwise have
a normal חטאת chatas brought for it. וכן המשיח. v'chen hamashiach. And
similarly by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, he only brings his special
קרבן korban when it's a type of sin that a normal person
would bring a חטאת. chatas. Okay? If it's a type of a
thing that a normal person would bring, let's say, an אשם ודאי
asham vaday or an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, those are cases where
he might bring like a normal person. But when does he have
this special criteria that it's only based on his own פסק psak
and this special קרבן korban of a פר, par, of an ox,
that's only by something that a normal person would bring a חטאת
chatas for. ולא בעבודה זרה עד שיורו בדבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת.
v'lo b'avodah zarah ad she-yiru b'davar she-zidono kares v'shigigato chatas. Similarly, if
בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol rules by עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
they're only going to do for a type of a sin of
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and they bring both
a פר לעולה ושעיר לחטאת par l'olah v'sayir l'chatas because most of
the ציבור tzibbur follow. That's only by a type of a sin
of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that you normally you'd get כרת kares
for if you did it willfully and a חטאת chatas unintentionally. As
opposed to a type of a sin of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
like, you know, showing, רש״י Rashi says, hugging or kissing an עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, which is a type of an עבודה avodah but
not really the normal עבודה avodah for that עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
Some act that shows like love and fealty but it's not an
actual act of worship for that עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. That would
be a simple לאו, lav, it would not be something that you
would bring a sin offering. So in that case, if בית דין
Beis Din ruled on that
and the people followed them, they would not bring their special קרבן
korban because it's not a type of a sin that a normal
person brings a חטאת. chatas. And the same would be true about
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. There's no sin offering, you know, there's
no special, whatever, by as we just said the other day, his
anyway offering by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is a שעיר, sayir, but
it would only be by the normal type of a thing that
you would normally bring a חטאת chatas for. Okay, מנלן? menalan? Where
do you know that the special קרבן korban of the בית דין
Beis Din is only by something that normally you would bring a
חטאת chatas for?
דתניא תנו רבנן, detanya tanu rabanan, רבי אומר, Rebbe omer, נאמר כאן
עליה, ne'emar kan aleha, ונודעה החטאת אשר חטאו עליה, v'nodah hachatas asher
chatu aleha, they the בית דין Beis Din or it's known the
sin that they sinned about it, that's by the case of the
בית דין. Beis Din. ונאמר להלן עליה, v'ne'emar lehalan aleha, and it
says by לגלות ערותה עליה, l'galos ervata aleha, it's being by the
עריות, arayos, it says the word
עליה. aleha. Okay, מה להלן דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת, mah lehalan
davar she-zidono kares v'shigigato chatas,
the same way there it's something that if you do it willfully
you get כרת kares and if you do it unintentionally you get
חטאת. chatas. How you know that if you do it unintentionally you
get חטאת chatas is not clear, because there by the case of
the עריות arayos the emphasis is on getting כרת kares when you
do it willfully. But okay, אף כאן דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת.
af kan davar she-zidono kares v'shigigato chatas.
Even the case of the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol and
their פסק psak is by something that normally you would get כרת
kares or bring a חטאת chatas for. אשכחן ציבור, ashkan tzibbur, fine,
that's true about the בית דין הגדול. Beis Din Hagadol. משיח מנלן?
mashiach menalan?
How do you know a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol also for his
own special קרבן korban it's only a type of a thing that
you would normally get כרת kares for?
So, like we said before, the thing we're going to use to
constantly connect the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to the case of the
בית דין, Beis Din, it says that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
sins לאשמת העם, l'ashmas ha'am, to the iniquity of the people. הרי
משיח כציבור, harei mashiach k'tzibbur, he, his sin is like the sin
of the congregation. So the same way the congregation's sin is only
by something that you would normally bring a חטאת chatas and get
כרת, kares, same about his. Okay, נשיא. nasi.
Now how about נשיא? nasi? How do you know about the, we
haven't actually directly explored this, but now we're constantly bringing it in
because those three are sort of written in the same area there
at the end of פרשת ויקרא: Parshas Vayikra: the כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, the בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, and the נשיא, nasi,
the מלך melech or the political head. So how do you know
him too, that his special קרבן korban that's mentioned there is also
by a normal sin that a normal person would bring a חטאת
chatas for? So, נשיא יליף מצוות מצוות. nasi yalif mitzvos mitzvos. כתיב
גבי נשיא ועשה אחת מכל מצוות השם, kasiv gabi nasi v'asah achas
mikol mitzvos Hashem,
it says by the נשיא nasi he does one of the מצוות
mitzvos that he's not supposed to do. וכתיב בציבור ועשו אחת מכל
מצוות. u'chsiv b'tzibbur v'asu achas mikol mitzvos. מה ma ציבור tzibbur דבר
davar שזדונו shezedono כרת kares ושגגתו חטאת, ushgegoso chatas? same as what
we proved from the עליה aleha link, that the קרבן korban of
the בית דין Beis Din is only by something that normally you
would get כרת kares for, and otherwise or bring a חטאת chatas,
under normal situations, אף נשיא דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת, af nasi
davar shezedono kares ushgegoso chatas, similarly by the נשיא. nasi. יחיד, yachid,
now how do you know about the individual? Now here it's because
the thing is, like in the end of ויקרא, Vayikra, there's really
three פרשיות, parshiyos, right? It speaks about like at the end of
ויקרא, Vayikra, you know, it says,
it's actually quite interesting, just might as well just put it up,
right? At the end of פרשת ויקרא Parshas Vayikra towards the end,
whatever, פרק ד', Perek Daled, you know, it basically starts by saying,
okay, פרק ד' פסוק א' Perek Daled Pasuk Aleph is נפש כי
תחטא בשגגה מכל מצוות השם, nefesh ki techeta bishgaga mikol mitzvos Hashem,
okay, it starts by saying נפש כי תחטא בשגגה מכל מצוות השם,
nefesh ki techeta bishgaga mikol mitzvos Hashem, okay, אשר לא תעשינה ועשה
מאחת מהן, asher lo teaseina veasa meachas meihen, okay, אשר לא תעשינה.
asher lo teaseina.
So that's about תחטא בשגגה. techeta bishgaga. So this is opening the
category of חטאת. chatas That's פסוק א' pasuk aleph in פרק ד',
Perek Daled, okay,
and then what you have is, you have the following, אם הכהן
המשיח. im hakohen hamashiyach.
The first one it talks about is פסוק ב', pasuk beis, אם,
im, well, I don't know, it should be, okay, אם הכהן המשיח,
im hakohen hamashiyach, and then it has the whole case of the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, okay, that's פסוק ב' pasuk beis through י"ב.
yud beis.
Then it says ואם
כל עדת ישראל ישגו ונעלם
דבר, veim
kol adas Yisrael yishgu venaalam
davar, okay,
ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו ונעלם דבר.
veim kol adas Yisrael yishgu venaalam
davar. So that's the case of, that's, this is כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, this is
בית דין הגדול, Beis Din Hagadol, okay,
and that's this from י"ג yud gimmel to כ"א. chaf aleph. Then
it is
אשר נשיא יחטא, asher nasi yecheta, okay, and that is the case
of the נשיא nasi or the מלך. melech. And then finally, that's
כ"ב chaf beis
through כ"ו. chaf vav. And then finally it's
ואם נפש אחת תחטא, veim nefesh achas techeta, ואם נפש אחת תחטא,
veim nefesh achas
techeta, which is the case about a simple יחיד, yachid, just an
individual, okay, and that's like כ"ז chaf zayin to like ל"ה lamed
hey to the end of פרק ד'. Perek Daled. Okay, so all
of פרק ד' Perek Daled is the sins of a חטאת, chatas.
the last one finally being the simple חטאת chatas, of an individual.
So what we have done is we have said because of this
פסוק pasuk by the עריות arayos where it says לגלות ערותה עליה,
legalos ervasa aleha,
לגלות ערותה עליה, legalos ervasa aleha, and that's the עריות arayos and
that's about כרת, kares, okay, we say ah, כרת, kares, well, this
says עליה, aleha, so the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol is
that, and then we sort of link it to the כהן משיח
Kohen Mashiyach and we link it to the נשיא nasi and then
finally we say, because remember the requirement is that it's only a
קרבן, korban, they only bring the קרבן korban if in a normal
circumstances you would get כרת kares and an individual would bring a
normal חטאת. chatas But we don't even know yet that the individual
would bring a normal חטאת, chatas. it's only because now we're also
linking it to the last section here which is the sin of
an individual that brings a קרבן חטאת korban chatas that we say
that a normal sin that you get כרת kares for is a
type of a sin that a normal individual brings a חטאת. chatas,
And now we're saying all of these are also only bringing their
special קרבנות korbanos if it's that sin that you get כרת kares
and the normal individual brings a חטאת chatas. for. All right, so
that's what it says. It says, אף נשיא דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו
חטאת. af nasi davar shezedono kares ushgegoso chatas. יחיד, yachid, so חטאת
יחיד, chatas yachid,
so how do you know that the חטאת chatas of an individual
is something you only you get כרת kares for, is only something
that you get כרת kares for? אמר קרא amar kra ואם נפש
veim nefesh וי"ו תחתם מעליון, vav tachtam mealayon, it says ואם נפש
veim nefesh and the וי"ו vav lets us link it to the
stuff on top. So the stuff on top we learned is only
stuff for כרת, kares, so even a normal חטאת chatas is only
a case of כרת. kares. Okay, ולא בעבודת כוכבים? velo baavodas kochavim?
Similarly by the special קרבן korban of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, it
has to be a type of a sin of עבודה זרה avoda
zara that you would normally bring a חטאת chatas for and that
you would normally get כרת kares for. בעבודת כוכבים מנלן, baavodas kochavim
minalan, and where do you know this idea by עבודה זרה? avoda
zara? דתנו רבנן, detanu rabanan, לפי שיצאת עבודת כוכבים לדון בעצמה, lefi
sheyatzas avodas kochavim ladun beatzma, since
עבודה זרה avoda zara it has a separate פרשה, parsha, you bring
a, you know, for בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol you get
a פר ושעיר, par veseir, you don't just get the normal
פר. par. So יכול יהא חייב אף על דבר שאין זדונו כרת
yachol yehei chayav af al davar sheein zedono kares ושגגתו ushgegoso חטאת?
chatas נאמר כאן מעיני ונאמר להלן מעיני. neemar kan meeinei veneemar lehalan
meeinei.
No,
because you have the מעיני meeinei here it says ונעלם דבר מעיני
הקהל, venaalam davar meeinei hakahal,
okay,
and And you have by the עבודה זרה, avoda zara, the case
of עבודה זרה avoda zara of the ציבור, tzibur, it says ונעלם
דבר, v'ne'elam davar, ואם, v'im,
what is it, מעיני מעיני העדה נעשתה לשגגה. me'einei me'einei ha'eida ne'esta
lishgagah. לשגגה. Lishgagah.
That's the פסוקים pesukim by עבודה זרה avoda zara and the case
of, of a case of ציבור, tzibur, okay, which is another case
of בית דין'ס Beis Din's עבודה זרה. avoda zara. That's a case
where you bring a פר לעולה par l'olah and a שעיר לחטאת.
se'ir l'chatas. So how do you know this case, this special קרבן
korban of בית דין הגדול Beis Din haGadol by עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, how do you know that's also כרת? kareit? Because we link
the מעיני מעיני, me'einei me'einei, and
that allows us to link it to the case of the בית
דין הגדול, Beis Din haGadol, the בית דין הגדול'ס Beis Din haGadol's
normal קרבן, korban, which is by כרת, kareit, so this too, by
עבודה זרה avoda zara is also by כרת. kareit. Okay.
נאמר כאן מעיני
ונאמר להלן מעיני מה להלן דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת אף כאן
דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת.
Ne'emar kan
me'einei v'ne'emar lehallan me'einei.
Mah lehallan davar she'zono kareit v'shigagato chatas, af kan davar she'zono kareit
v'shigagato chatas. אשכחן ציבור. Ashken tzibur. Now, that's you know that the
קרבן ציבור korban tzibur of עבודה זרה avoda zara is only if
it's something that you would get כרת kareit for. יחיד נשיא משיח
מנלן? Yachid nasi mashiach minalan? How do you know, there's another paragraph
by the case of the, you know, another פרשה parsha where it
speaks about the individual who brings a קרבן korban by עבודה זרה
avoda zara that brings a שעיר, se'ir,
that brings a goat, okay, which is so and there we said
that there the נשיא nasi that there it's true the same is
true by the king and true by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
they bring a goat, okay? So what's that paragraph? There the Torah
says, and there we've got all the stuff up on the board,
which we couldn't do over Yom Tov. So,
there it says, וכי תשגו ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה, v'chi
tishgu v'lo ta'asu es kol hamitzvos ha'eileh,
okay, so this will be עבודה זרה avoda zara on the bottom
here. So this is וכי תשגו. v'chi tishgu. This is במדבר ט"ו,
Bamidbar tes-vav, במדבר ט"ו. Bamidbar tes-vav. ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה.
V'lo ta'asu es kol hamitzvos ha'eileh.
So כל מצות kol mitzvos means עבודה זרה, avoda zara, something that
represents all the מצות, mitzvos, okay, אשר דבר ה' asher dibber Hashem
blah blah blah. Okay.
Oh, I'm sorry, that's actually this פרשה. parsha. That's the ואם מעיני
העדה. v'im me'einei ha'eida. Whoops. Okay. וכי תשגו ולא תעשו את כל
המצות האלה. V'chi tishgu v'lo ta'asu es kol hamitzvos ha'eileh.
So that's the case of עבודה זרה avoda zara for everybody. Now
where do you get the עבודה זרה avoda zara for the individual?
That's afterwards. ואם נפש אחת תחטא בשגגה. V'im nefesh achas techeta bishgagah.
So this is כל המצות האלה kol hamitzvos ha'eileh is עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. Okay. So the first is מעיני העדה, me'einei ha'eida, so
that's the עבודה זרה avoda zara of the ציבור. tzibur. And then
it continues and says, ואם נפש אחת תחטא בשגגה, v'im nefesh achas
techeta bishgagah,
okay.
And then it says, ta-da-da-da, what does he bring? He brings והקריב
עז בת שנתה, v'hikriv
ez bas shenatah, והקריב
עז בת שנתה. v'hikriv ez bas shenatah.
So that is a שעיר. se'ir. Okay. So that's עבודה זרה avoda
zara of the יחיד. yachid. Okay. And we say this case of
the שעיר, se'ir, okay, this includes the case of the יחיד yachid
includes כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and the נשיא. nasi. So, how do
we know that the עבודה זרה avoda zara of ציבור tzibur is
only עבודה זרה avoda zara when it's כרת? kareit? מעיני מעיני me'einei
me'einei links. How do we know the עבודה זרה avoda zara of
the יחיד yachid including כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and the נשיא, nasi,
which is its own special קרבן, korban, the שעיר, se'ir, how do
we know that that's also only by כרת? kareit? So that's the
גמרא'ס Gemara's question. Okay. So, יחיד נשיא משיח מנלן? Yachid nasi mashiach
minalan? אמר קרא ואם נפש אחת. Amar kra v'im nefesh achas. אחד
יחיד, Echad yachid, so the אחת, achas, whether it's a יחיד yachid
ואחד נשיא ואחד משיח כולן בכלל נפש אחת הן. v'echad nasi v'echad
mashiach, kulan bichlal nefesh achas hen. So נפש אחת nefesh achas includes
all these three. And how do we know to limit it to
the case of כרת? kareit? So וילמד תחתון מן העליון, v'yelamed tachton
min ha'elyon,
so ואם נפש אחת v'im nefesh achas links to the top thing
right above it. So therefore the same way this is כרת kareit
only, this is also only an עבודה זרה avoda zara of כרת.
kareit. Now הניחא למאן דמפיק ליה לעליה לגזירה שוה. hani'cha l'man d'mappik
lei l'aleha l'gezeirah shavah. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, this works
if the word עליה aleha here lets us learn כרת kareit that
עליה aleha because of it says עליה aleha here and עליה aleha
is כרת kareit by the עריות, arayos, and that's how we learn
כרת kareit and that we apply it all the way here, מעיני
me'einei lets us apply כרת kareit here, then we jump it here,
and כרת kareit spreads throughout all of this. And that's how we
know it's all about כרת. kareit. כי דאמרינן. kiddamrin. אלא לרבנן דמפיק
ליה לעליה לעריות וצרות, Ella l'rabbanan d'mappik lei l'aleha l'arayos v'tzaros, and
צרות, tzaros, but,
but for the רבנן Rabbanan who use עליה aleha in the פרשה
parsha of עריות arayos for telling you some other הלכה, halacha, הלכה
halacha about עריות arayos and צרות tzaros and יבום, yibum, and we're
not going to get into it, but if you need עליה aleha
to tell you something... else. So דבשלמא דתנו כשיעור חטאת מנלהו? De-bishlama
de-tanu k'shiur chatas menalhu? How do you learn all these things only
apply by a case of כרת? Kares? נפקא להו מדתני ליה רבי
יהושע בן לוי לבריה, Nafaka lehu midatni lei Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi
livrei, from Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi taught to his son. Because it
says תורה אחת יהיה לכם לעשה בשגגה. Torah achas yihiyeh lachem la'oseh
bishgagah.
Okay, that is the end right here of this פרשה parsha in
במדבר ט"ו, Bamidbar Tes Vav, which is this case of עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. That's the context we were just dealing with, right? So
it says right there at the end, let me just turn back
to it. It says,
what was it? 15:29? Thank you. Right after the פסוק pasuk we
just quoted, וכיפר הכהן על הנפש השגגת בחטאה בשגגה לפני ה' לכפר
עליו ונסלח לו האזרח בבני ישראל ולגר הגר בתוכם תורה אחת יהיה
לכם לעשה בשגגה. V'chiper hakohen al hanefesh hashogeges b'chetah bishgagah lifnei Hashem
l'chaper alav v'nislach lo ha'ezrach bivnei Yisrael v'lager hagar besocham torah achas
yihiyeh lachem la'oseh bishgagah. Okay, what was that? תורה אחת יהיה לכם
לעשה בשגגה,
Torah achas yihiyeh lachem
la'oseh bishgagah, right. So right after here at the end of all
this עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it says תורה אחת יהיה לכם לעשה
בשגגה. Torah achas yihiyeh lachem la'oseh bishgagah. So now where do you
see כרת? Kares? So what we're going to do is we'll get
כרת Kares here then we're going to be able to apply it
back up. But where are we going to get כרת Kares here?
So he says, okay, והנפש אשר תעשה ביד רמה את ה' הוא
מגדף. V'hanefesh asher ta'aseh b'yad ramah es Hashem hu megadef.
So when it says והנפש אשר תעשה ביד רמה, V'hanefesh asher ta'aseh
b'yad ramah, so that is that's an act of עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah actually it sounds more like an act of מגדף megadef but
it's a מחלוקת, machlokes, okay, somebody who does willfully ביד רמה b'yad
ramah את ה' הוא מגדף es Hashem hu megadef and what's the
end of it? The end of it is ונכרתה הנפש. v'nichresah hanefesh.
Okay, ונכרתה הנפש. v'nichresah hanefesh.
Okay,
so here you have כרת. Kares. Okay, so one way is you
get כרת Kares from עריות, Arayos, you get it here and then
it travels all the way down to all the various links. The
other is you get כרת Kares in this category of עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah and it's going to basically travel all the way up,
okay? So once we get כרת Kares in it we're able to
propagate it. All
right. So it says like this, it says הוקשה כל התורה כולה
לעבודת כוכבים מה עבודת כוכבים שחייבים על זדונה כרת ושגגתה חטאת אף
כאן שחייבים על זדונה כרת ושגגתה חטאת. Huksha kol hatorah kullah l'avodas
kochavim mah avodas kochavim shechayavim al zedonah kares ushgagatah chatas af kan
shechayavim al zedonah kares ushgagatah chatas.
So the same way this is about a case of כרת Kares
and therefore, right, it says תורה אחת יהיה, Torah achas yihiyeh, so
the תורה אחת Torah achas is even better, right, because the תורה
אחת Torah achas lets us even say this is a general principle
that you bring a חטאת chatas for something you get כרת. Kares.
It's true about עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and it's true in general.
All right, and that tells us here it's a חטאת chatas that
probably tells us this case of הדיוט, hedyot, נשיא, nasi, ומשוח, umashiach,
normal חטאת chatas is going to be when it's something that you
get כרת Kares for. Okay, שחייבים על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת.
shechayavim al zedono kares v'al shgagato chatas. אשכחן יחיד נשיא ומשוח בין
בעבודת כוכבים בין בשאר מצות. Ashkechan yachid nasi umashiach bein b'avodas kochavim
bein b'sha'ar mitzvos.
Fine. So you gave us the idea that individuals it's about something
that you get כרת Kares for, okay? So this idea applied here
to to to to it says תורה אחת Torah achas so it
applies to the individual sin of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it applies
to individual sins by other things you would get כרת, Kares, but
that's all by נפש אחת, nefesh achas, that's all by individuals. Where
are you going to get the idea that the ציבור's tzibur קרבן
korban is also only by something of כרת? Kares? ציבור מנלן יליף
עליון מתחתון. Tzibur menalan yalif elyon mitachton. So once you get it
in that פרשה, parsha, right, you can learn ציבור tzibur from the
other cases. All right. ורבי, V'Rabbi, great. So one way or another
we get כרת Kares into the mix and then we propagate it
throughout. ורבי הא דרבי יהושע בן לוי מאי עביד ליה? V'Rabbi ha
d'Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi mai avid leh? What does רבי Rabbi do
with the רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, what does
he do with the תורה אחת? Torah achas? What does he learn
from it? If he doesn't need him to tell you this principle
of
כרת. Kares. So מפיק ליה לכי דתניא, mapik leh l'chi d'tanya, like
we taught in a ברייתא. braisa. לפי שמצינו שחילק הכתוב בין רבים
ליחידים. Lefi shematzinu shechilak haksav bein rabim l'yechidim. Now we know when
it comes to עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah there's a difference between a
group of people who do עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and individuals. We
do not mean by the group all of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael.
We mean a city. When a city worships עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
they're different than when individuals do it, but when they do it
willfully. רבים בסייף, Rabim besayif, when a city does it they get
killed by the sword, executed, וממונם אבד umamonam avad and you destroy
their wealth, their property. יחידים, Yechidim, if an individual worships עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, בסקילה, beskilah, so it's stoning, וממונם פלט umamonam palat and
their money gets saved. So therefore, the same way there's a difference
when they do willfully, a city versus an individual, so
יכול yachol I might think, נחלקו בקרבנותיהם, nechelku b'korbanoseihem, if they do
it unintentionally maybe there's different קרבנות. korbanos. We have a קרבן korban
for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah for an individual, we have it for
a ציבור, tzibur, maybe we should have a separate קרבן korban for
a city the same way a city when it does it willfully
brings has a separate punishment. תלמוד לומר תורה אחת יהיה לכם. Talmud
lomar Torah achas yihiyeh lachem. So the תורה אחת Torah achas which
is here specifically in the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah area is to
tell you that no, that when you're dealing with individuals they all
have the same קרבן, korban, it doesn't matter one individual or a
thousand individuals. Anything short of the entire ציבור tzibur they're all going
to have the same קרבן. korban. Okay, fine. מתקיף לה רב חלקיא
מהגרוניא. Matkif lah Rav Hilkiya me-Hagronya. So רב חלקיא מהגרוניא Rav Hilkiya
me-Hagronya asked, טעמא דלא חילק הכתוב, Ta'ama d'lo chilak haksav, the reason
I know that a city when they do עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
brings the same קרבן korban is because the פסוק pasuk says תורה
אחת. Torah achas. That. הא חילק, Ha chilek, if it had not
said תורה אחת, Torah Achas, הוה אמינא נחלוק, Hava amina nachlok, I
would have said they'll bring a special קרבן. Korban. So מאי נייתי,
Mai neisi, what would have been left for them to bring that
would not have been like any of the other קרבנות Korbanot that
we already have, right? What's really left? נייתי פר, Neisi par, let's
say they would say that when a city does it they bring
an ox, ציבור בשאר מצוות הוא דמייתי, Tzibbur b'shear mitzvos hu d'maisi,
that's not unique, that's brought by the by כל ישראל Klal Yisrael
when they do a normal sin. נייתי פר לעולה ושעיר לחטאת, Neisi
par l'ola v'sair l'chatas, bring an ox for an עולה ola and
a שעיר sair for a חטאת chatas offering, ציבור בעבודת כוכבים הוא
דמייתי, Tzibbur b'avodas kochavim hu d'maisi, that wouldn't be unique, that would
be by a ציבור Tzibbur when it worships עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
נייתי שעיר, Neisi sair, bring a male goat, נשיא בשאר מצוות הוא
דמייתי, Nasi b'shear mitzvos hu d'maisi, that's what a נשיא Nasi brings
when he does other מצוות Mitzvos בשוגג. b'shogeg. נייתי שעירה, Neisi seira,
how about a she-goat, she-goat יחיד נמי היינו קרבנו, Yachid nami hainu
korbano, that's the that is the קרבן korban of an individual for
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. So what's left? We have a male goat,
a female goat, we have an ox, and that's basically it and
we have a goat for for חטאת chatas and an ox for
an עולה. ola. So what sort of is left for a special
קרבן korban for for עבודה זרה Avoda Zara of a of a
city that you thought we would have had a הוה אמינא, Hava
amina, which is funny, you haven't really exhausted all the possibilities, you
have a כשבה, kesba, you have a עז, ez, I mean I
don't know anyway. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says אלמה לא, Alma lo,
why not? איצטריך סלקא דעתך אמינא, Itzrich salka dachak amina, ציבור מייתי
פר לעולה ושעיר לחטאת, Tzibbur maisi par l'ola v'sair l'chatas, here's one
example, the ציבור Tzibbur brings an ox for an עולה ola and
a שעיר sair for a חטאת chatas by עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
So this, which is not a ציבור Tzibbur but not a יחיד,
Yachid, it's a it's a city, הני נייתי איפכא, hani neisi ipcha,
maybe reverse it, פר לחטאת ושעיר לעולה. par l'chatas v'sair l'ola. Okay,
אי נמי Ei nami or וצריך ואין לו תקנה, v'tzrich v'ein lo
takana, or okay, we wouldn't have known which קרבן, Korban, we would
have said they have to bring a קרבן, Korban, we wouldn't have
known which, but that wouldn't mean that we can't say that that
would have been our conclusion. So קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan,
fine, it teaches us the idea of תורה אחת Torah Achas that
even if a city does it, they're just like a lot of
individuals. Fine. Anyway, we got the idea here that one way or
another, either from עבודה זרה Avoda Zara or from עריות, Arayot, we
bring כרת Karet in and we say all these things only apply
by כרת. Karet.
Now, okay, דכולי עלמא מיהת, d'chulei alma mihat, everybody nonetheless, כי כתיבי
הני קראי בעבודת כוכבים הוא דכתיבי, ki ksivi hani krai b'avodas kochavim
hu d'ksivi, these verses here, which are the special קרבנות, Korbanot, פר
לעולה שעיר לחטאת, par l'ola sair l'chatas, שעיר sair for an individual,
the תורה אחת, Torah Achas, all of this is by עבודה זרה.
Avoda Zara. So so מאי משמע, mai mashma, where do you see
it talking about עבודה זרה? Avoda Zara? אמר רבא ואיתימא רבי יהושע
בן לוי ואמרי לה כדי, Amar Rava v'isima Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
v'amri lei k'di, אמרי קרא, amri kra, the verse says וכי תשגו
ולא תעשו את כל המצוות האלה, V'chi sishgu v'lo sa'asu es kol
hamitzvos ha'eileh, that's why we'll drop את כל המצוות האלה, es kol
hamitzvos ha'eileh, I forgot a ה. hey.
המצוות האלה. HaMitzvos ha'eileh. Okay, איזו היא מצוה שהיא שקולה ככל המצוות,
Eizu hi
mitzvah shehi shekula k'chol hamitzvos, what is the מצוה mitzvah that is
equivalent to all the מצוות? mitzvos? הוי אומר זו עבודת כוכבים, Hevei
omer zu avodas kochavim, that's עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. דבי רבי תנא,
D'bei Rabbi tana, אמר קרא, Amar kra, דבי רבי D'bei Rabbi has
another basis for saying it. The verse says אמר קרא אשר דבר
ה' אל משה, Amar kra asher diber Hashem el Moshe, all the
מצוות mitzvos that God spoke to משה, Moshe, וכתיב אשר צוה ה'
אליכם ביד משה, v'ksiv asher tziva Hashem aleichem b'yad Moshe, God commanded
you. So which are the מצוות, mitzvos, איזו היא מצוה שהיא בדיבורו
של הקדוש ברוך הוא וציוה על ידי משה, Eizu hi mitzvah shehi
b'diburo shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu v'tziva al yedei Moshe, which is the
מצוה mitzvah that God directly commanded us and משה Moshe also commanded
us? הוי אומר זו עבודת כוכבים Hevei omer zu avodas kochavim because
the only two we heard directly from God were אנכי Anochi and
לא יהיה
לך,
Lo yihiyeh lacha,
so that's both אשר צוה ה' אליכם, asher tziva Hashem aleichem, God
commanded us, and and אשר דבר ה' אל משה asher diber Hashem
el Moshe and you know, so both God commanded us directly and
we heard it through משה, Moshe, that's only עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara.
דתני דבי רבי ישמעאל אנכי ולא יהיה לך מפי הגבורה שמענום, D'tani
d'bei Rabbi Yishmael Anochi v'Lo yihiyeh lacha mipi HaGevura shemanum, we heard
those direct from God. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא, D'bei Rabbi Yishmael tana,
here's a third way we know this is talking about עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara because it says that God commanded us מן היום אשר
צוה ה' והלאה לדורותיכם, min hayom asher tziva Hashem v'hala l'doroseichem, that
God has commanded from the day God commanded you and forward for
all generations. איזו היא מצוה שהיא נאמרה בתחילה, Eizu hi mitzvah shehi
neemra b'tchila, which is the very first מצוה mitzvah we heard that
afterwards followed all the other מצוות? mitzvos? הוי אומר זו עבודת כוכבים,
Hevei omer zu avodas kochavim, it was about not worshipping idols, the
second, you know, מצוה mitzvah of on הר סיני. Har Sinai. והשתא,
V'hashta, the גמרא Gemara says wait a minute, no, that's not a
good לימוד limmud because even though that was the first of the
Ten Commandments, it wasn't the first מצוה mitzvah we got. והאמר מר
עשר מצוות נצטוו ישראל במרה, V'ha'amar mar eser mitzvos nitzavu Yisrael b'Marah,
we actually got ten מצוות mitzvos in מרה Marah before we got
to הר סיני. Har Sinai. אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא, Ella mechvarta k'dashninan
mei'ikara, the better explanation is the other two explanations, either because it
says את כל המצוות האלה, es kol hamitzvos ha'eileh, that means עבודה
זרה, Avoda Zara, or because it says אשר צוה ה' asher tziva
Hashem and אשר דבר ה', asher diber Hashem, which means the which
means which means
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. So this is עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, these
are the special קרבנות Korbanot for עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, this are
the special all the קרבנות Korbanot for normal things that are not
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara and we bring כרת Karet into one of
them and then we propagate it throughout the list. Okay, so that's
the idea that you know all of these things are only by
כרת. Karet. אין חייבין על עשה ולא תעשה שבמקדש. Ein chayavin al
asei v'lo sa'asei sheb'mikdash. Now, the same way you only these things
only apply when it is a thing that you get כרת, Karet,
remember we also said
for example by the בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol or the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol only a thing that under normal circumstances you
would bring a חטאת. chatas. There are some things you get כרת
Karet for that you don't bring a חטאת, chatas, or to say
it another way, there are also some things you bring a חטאת
chatas but it's not a חטאת קבועה, chatas kevuah, it's not a
fixed חטאת, chatas, it's an an עולה ויורד, Oleh VeYored, a variable
cost חטאת. Chatas. Okay, some of those are actually פרק ה ויקרא.
Perek He Vayikra. Somebody takes type of an oath and denies they
owe something or, you know, case of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. Tumas Mikdash
VeKodshav. They're טמא Tamei and they enter into the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Those are things that they bring a חטאת, Chatas, but based
on their wealth, what type of חטאת Chatas they bring changes based
on their ability to afford it. That's an עולה ויורד. Oleh VeYored.
That also is not if there was a ruling of בית דין
Beis Din on that, they would not bring their special קרבן. Korban.
If there was a case of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, he
would not bring his special קרבן. Korban. It's interesting, would a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol bring an עולה ויורד? Oleh VeYored? Okay, because when,
you know, he doesn't bring his special קרבן, Korban, but and the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol never brings a normal חטאת. Chatas. For a
thing that any individual brings a חטאת, Chatas, if he just sinned,
he would not bring it. He would have to both פסקן Pasken
and sin. But something like this that's a separate קרבן, Korban, an
עולה ויורד, Oleh VeYored, we'll have to see about whether a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol brings it. Okay, but the first point is, is
that it's not the special קרבן Korban when it's a case of
an עולה ויורד. Oleh VeYored. Okay, which is the case of מקדש
וקדשיו. Mikdash VeKodshav. Somebody enters into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, eats
a קרבן Korban when they are טמא, Tamei, the קרבן Korban that
they bring for that sin is חטאת Chatas which is an עולה
ויורד, Oleh VeYored, a variable sin חטאת. Chatas. Okay. אין חייבין על
עשה ולא תעשה שבמקדש. Ein chayavin al asei velo sa'asei shebemikdash. You
are not חייב Chayav בית דין Beis Din for ruling about a
מצות עשה Mitzvas Asei or a לא תעשה Lo Sa'asei of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay. מצות עשה Mitzvas Asei would be sending
out of the camp all the people that are טמא. Tamei. A
מצות לא תעשה Mitzvas Lo Sa'asei is not entering in when you
are טמא. Tamei. ואין מביאין אשם תלוי על עשה ולא תעשה שבמקדש.
Ve'ein mevin asham taluy al asei velo sa'asei shebemikdash. Or an individual
who doesn't know if they ate a קרבן Korban when they were
טמא Tamei would not bring an אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. An אשם
תלוי Asham Taluy is only brought for something that otherwise would be
a חטאת קבועה, Chatas Kavua, a fixed value חטאת. Chatas. Something that
would be an עולה ויורד, Oleh VeYored, a variable cost חטאת, Chatas,
that would not bring an אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. Okay, so the
new הלכה Halacha is, in addition to כרת, Kares, all these הלכות
Halachos apply only by a חטאת קבועה. Chatas Kavua. And otherwise you
would not bring these special קרבנות Korbanos and you would not bring
an אשם תלוי Asham Taluy if there was a doubt. Okay, אבל
חייבין על עשה ולא תעשה שבנדה. Aval chayavin al asei velo sa'asei
shebeniddah. But the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol would bring if
they פסקןed Pasken incorrectly about a positive or a negative command about
נדה. Niddah. Okay. What would that be? Let's say the positive would
be that husband and wife have to separate when it's close to
the period time of her period, because she might see her get
her period. And a negative would obviously be don't have intercourse when
the woman is a נדה. Niddah. Okay, so if they ruled incorrectly
about that. Now the funny thing is, if they ruled incorrectly about
the positive, you don't bring a קרבן Korban for transgressing the positive.
But I guess in the case where the transgressing of the positive
led to the transgressing of the negative, because they were having sex
right before she got her period then they were having sex while
she got her period too, because in the middle of their sex
she became a נדה. Niddah. Anyway, that type of a thing, that's
just an example of a type of case which is כרת, Kares,
which is a חטאת, Chatas, and that is the case that a
בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol does bring its
קרבן. Korban. Okay. אבל חייבין על עשה ולא תעשה שבנדה ומביאין אשם
תלוי על עשה ולא תעשה שבנדה. Aval chayavin al asei velo sa'asei
shebeniddah, umevi'in asham taluy al asei velo sa'asei shebeniddah. And if there's
a question about how they פסקןed Pasken about that about that excuse
me about whether if somebody did that doubtfully sinned about about a
case of נדה, Niddah, again as an individual he would bring an
אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. So these are just concrete examples. נדה's Niddah
a concrete example of a חטאת קבועה, Chatas Kavua, a normal חטאת,
Chatas, where the הלכה Halacha about if it was a בית דין
Beis Din ruling they'd bring their קרבן, Korban, you'd have an אשם
תלוי Asham Taluy if you had a doubt. And the טומאת מקדש
וקדשיו Tumas Mikdash VeKodshav is an example of an עולה ויורד Oleh
VeYored where these קרבנות Korbanos would not apply.
איזהו מצות עשה ולא תעשה שבנדה? Eizehu mitzvas asei velo sa'asei shebeniddah?
What is the positive מצוה Mitzvah of נדה? Niddah? פרוש מן הנדה,
Perosh min haniddah, separate from a נדה Niddah when she or even
when a woman's about to get her period. ומצות לא תעשה אל
תבוא אל הנדה, Umitzvas lo sa'asei el tavo el haniddah, do not
have intercourse with a נדה. Niddah. Funny, neither of them does it
actually quote a פסוק. Pasuk. Okay, conceptually that's the מצוה Mitzvah but
you would have expected it to quote a פסוק. Pasuk. Also very
strange that it why of all things does it quote נדה Niddah
and so on? Maybe because you have both an עשה Asei and
a לא תעשה Lo Sa'asei that and the even the עשה Asei
is linked to doing the actual עבירה. Aveyrah. The other thing it
might do is it might be suggesting the way in which נדה
Niddah is similar to טומאה. Tumah. You know, and there's a whole
discussions about that, about sort of seeing נדה Niddah and the way
is it דיני עריות Dinei Arayos or is it דיני טומאה? Dinei
Tumah? But anyway, that's for conversation for another time. Okay, מנני מילי,
Minani milei, where do we get this idea? דציבור לא מחייבי קרבן
בעלמא ויחיד אשם תלוי, De-tzibbur lo mechayvei korban be'alma veyachid asham taluy,
that a ציבור Tzibbur doesn't bring its special קרבן Korban and an
individual doesn't bring his אשם תלוי, Asham Taluy, לא מחייבי קרבן בעלמא
נמי לא, lo mechayvei korban be'alma nami lo, doesn't bring it on
something that is a עולה ויורד, Oleh VeYored, only brings it on
a fixed חטאת. Chatas. אמר רבי יצבר אבדימי Amar Rabbi Itzbar Avdimi
נאמר ואשם בחטאת, ne'emar ve'ashem bechatas, it says by a normal case
of a חטאת, Chatas, והוא לא ידע ואשם, vehu lo yada ve'ashem,
actually excuse me, והוא לא ידע ואשם vehu lo yada ve'ashem is
by עולה ויורד. Oleh VeYored. It says by אשם, Asham, what's the
פסוק Pasuk where he quotes
it? ואם נפש תחטא ועשתה אחת מכל מצות ה' אשר לא תעשינה
ואשם. Ve'im nefesh techeta ve'asata achas mikol mitzvos Hashem asher lo te'asenah
ve'ashem. So it says
ואם נפש תחטא אשר
לא תעשינה ואשם.
Ve'im nefesh techeta,
asher lo te'asenah ve'ashem. Okay so it says ואשם ve'ashem here.
I need a different color, but okay, anyway, it says ואשם v'ashem
by a normal חטאת. chatat. Okay, ובאשם
תלוי, u've'asham talui, ובאשם
תלוי. u've'asham talui. And by אשם תלוי asham talui it says, what
does it say by אשם תלוי? asham talui? It says ונפש כי
תחטא ועשתה אחת מכל מצות ה' אשר לא תעשינה ולא ידע ואשם.
V'nefesh ki techeta v'astah achat mikol mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asenah v'lo
yada v'ashem.
Okay, so by אשם תלוי, asham talui, we need a different color,
but anyway, over here by אשם תלוי asham talui it says אשר
לא תעשינה ולא ידע ואשם.
asher lo te'asenah v'lo yada
v'ashem. Okay, so that's אשם תלוי. asham talui.
Okay, so we've got it here, ואשם. v'ashem. Here, I'll ignore this
so we can focus on the ones we're focusing on. Okay.
So, we've got the ואשם v'ashem here by the case of a
normal חטאת יחיד. chatat yachid. We have the ואשם v'ashem here that
we have by אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay, so that's how we
know only an אשם תלוי asham talui is only by the case
of a normal חטאת. chatat. And now we have to also
link it to the קרבן korban of the בית דין. Beis Din.
Okay. נאמר ואשם בחטאת ובאשם תלוי ונאמר ואשמו
בציבור. Ne'emar v'ashem b'chatat u've'asham talui
v'ne'emar v'ashemu b'tzibur.
And by the ציבור tzibur it says, it says,
what does it say, it says...
What? 4:13. 4:13.
I'm looking for רש"י Rashi so he would actually quote the words,
trying to get רש"י Rashi to do my work for me. Okay,
4:13 it says: ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל
ועשו אחת מכל מצות ה' אשר לא תעשינה ואשמו.
V'im kol adat Yisrael yishgu
v'ne'elam davar me'einei hakahal v'asu achat mikol mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asenah
v'ashemu. Okay, מעיני
הקהל, me'einei hakahal, it says it right here:
אשר לא תעשינה ואשמו.
asher lo te'asenah
v'ashemu.
Okay, so there you go. ואשם, v'ashem, ואשמו, v'ashemu,
and אשר לא תעשינה ולא ידע ואשם. asher lo te'asenah v'lo yada
v'ashem. So that's how we know that this is a חטאת, chatat,
so a קרבן korban of the בית דין Beis Din is a
חטאת chatat and the אשם תלוי, asham talui, all of these are
only when they are, they would otherwise bring a normal חטאת קבועה,
chatat kevuah, a normal fixed חטאת. chatat. Okay, so נאמר ואשם בחטאת
ובאשם תלוי ונאמר ואשמו בציבור. ne'emar v'ashem b'chatat u've'asham talui v'ne'emar v'ashemu
b'tzibur. מה ואשם ביחיד בחטאת קבועה, mah v'ashem b'yachid b'chatat kevuah, so
the same way the ואשם v'ashem here, this is your standard חטאת,
chatat, your fixed חטאת, chatat, אף ואשמו בציבור בחטאת קבועה, af v'ashemu
b'tzibur b'chatat kevuah,
same way by the ציבור tzibur it's by a fixed חטאת, chatat,
ומה ציבור בחטאת קבועה אף אשם תלוי נמי אין בא אלא על
ספק חטאת קבועה. u'mah tzibur b'chatat kevuah af asham talui nami ein
ba ela al sefek chatat kevuah. And similarly the ואשם v'ashem
of the אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay, אמרי, amri, what? ובאשם תלוי?
u've'asham talui?
The אשם תלוי
asham
talui is only brought if there's a doubt if you did a
sin that you would otherwise bring a fixed חטאת chatat for. But
if there's a doubt if you did a sin that you would
bring an עולה ויורד oleh v'yored for like a... like טומאת מקדש
וקדשיו, tumath mikdash v'kodashav, you wouldn't bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui.
That's well then not for the ציבור, tzibur, only for a יחיד.
yachid. Right, ציבור tzibur never brings an אשם תלוי. asham talui.
So do we have a גמרא Gemara yesterday or the day before
that said that the יחיד yachid doesn't bring אשם תלוי asham talui
about משיח? Moshiach? That's by משיח Moshiach it doesn't.
Okay. But here we're talking about יחיד יחיד, yachid yachid, normal יחיד,
yachid, not talking about...
Right, where does the משנה Mishna separate that?
משנה Mishna doesn't, רש"י Rashi actually, look at the first רש"י Rashi
on the משנה, Mishna, he actually makes that point. When רש"י Rashi
actually goes out of his way to say exactly like you, like
up until now we've all been talking about a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, so you would think we're talking about a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, רש"י Rashi says no, no, no, here we're just shifting...
This is just a rule...
Right,
since we're talking about, right, all the right criteria, right, exactly. But
yes, you're right, we're now completely shifting and talking about a normal...
like if you look at רש"י, ואין מביאין יחידים אשם תלוי על
אסי ולא תעשה. Rashi, v'ein mevi'in yechidim asham talui al aseh v'lo
ta'aseh. Okay, and then he goes on to say obviously we're not
talking about a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol exactly the point you made
because כהן גדול Kohen Gadol never brings an אשם תלוי. asham talui.
Okay, yeah. So he says, okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: אי
הכי, ee hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, קרבן עולה ויורד נמי, korban
oleh v'yored nami, why not it? It's all very nice that ואשם
v'ashem links all of these and you want to limit it to
a חטאת קבועה, chatat kevuah, but guess what, עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored,
which is exactly what you're excluding from this little, little club, also
says ואשם. v'ashem. Okay. הא כתיב, ha ksiv, it says: והיה כי
יאשם לאחת מאלה. v'hayah ki ye'asham l'achat me'eleh. If a person sins
of one of these things, one of the types of things about
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumath mikdash v'kodashav or שבועה, shvua, all the things
that you bring an עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, it actually says ואשם,
v'ashem, so how can you exclude עולה ויורד oleh v'yored from this
little club of yours? So the גמרא Gemara says:
דנים אשמו מאשם ואין דנים אשם מיאשם. danim ashemu me'asham v'ein danim
ashem me'ye'asham. Okay, so it says, alright, אשם asham and אשמו ashemu
are more alike; by עולה ויורד oleh v'yored it says יאשם. ye'asham.
It starts with like a prefix, you know, it has the י
yud in the beginning, so that actually it's not exactly like it.
So the גמרא Gemara says, give me a break. So the גמרא
Gemara says... מאי נפקא מינא *Mai nafka mina*? Really? That's enough of
a distinction? I mean, it even the links you're making are not
exact words; it's אשם *Asham*, אשמו *Ashamu*, and יאשם *Yasham* all sounds
close enough to me. והא תני דבי רבי ישמעאל השב הכהן ובא
הכהן *Veha tani d'vei rabi Yishmael hashav hakohen uva hakohen* by this
case of צרעת *Tzara'at*, it says the Kohen returns and the Kohen
comes and it's basically returning and coming are the same thing, and
even though it's not the same word, it's close enough to make
a גזירה שוה *Gezeirah Shavah*, because it's the same idea. זו היא
שיבה זו היא ביאה *Zu hi shiva zu hi via*. ואו ניליף
מן ואשם מטומאת מקדש וקדשיו *Ve'o neleif min ve'asham mitumat mikdash vekodashav*.
And I'll do you one better, by the case of טומאת מקדש
tumas mikdash, וקדשיו *Tumat Mikdash ve'Kodashav* exactly the case our משנה *Mishnah*'s
excluding, that case of עולה ויורד oleh veyored. *Oleh Veyored*, it says
the exact word ואשם *Veasham*. The same word you're focusing on to
create your little club, it says there too. Okay? Because it says
דכתיב והוא טמא ואשם *Dichtiv vehu tamei veasham*.
Okay? So you can't say אשם *Asham* excludes עולה ויורד oleh veyored?
*Oleh Veyored*, עולה ויורד oleh veyored *Oleh Veyored* has the exact word
ואשם *Veasham*. אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav Papa* says רב פפא *Rav
Papa*, דנין ואשם ומצוות השם Hashem מן ואשם ומצוות השם Hashem *Danin
ve'asham umitzvot Hashem min ve'asham umitzvot Hashem*. Ah, no, because here it
both says, it says מכל מצוות השם Hashem אשר לא תעשנה ואשמו
*Mikol mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asenu ve'ashamu*. It says ואם נפש אחת
תחטא בשגגה מעם הארץ *Veim nefesh achat techete bishgaga me'am ha'aretz* מעשות
אחת מכל מצוות השם Hashem אשר לא תעשנה ואשם *ma'asot achat mikol
mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asenu ve'asham*. So here you've got מצוות השם
*Mitzvot Hashem* and ואשמו *Veashamu* and okay, here you say ואם נפש
אחת תחטא בשגגה מעם הארץ *Veim nefesh achat techete bishgaga me'am ha'aretz*.
What's this one? ואם נפש אחת תחטא בשגגה מעם הארץ בעשותה אחת
ממצוות השם *Veim nefesh achat techete bishgaga me'am ha'aretz be'asota achat mimitzvot
Hashem*. Okay? So here also it says ממצוות השם *Mimitzvot Hashem*. So
we have a double link, מצוות השם *Mitzvot Hashem* and ואשמו *Veashamu*,
מצוות השם *Mitzvot Hashem* and ואשם *Veasham*. And that it doesn't have
by an אשם תלוי *Asham Talui*. So that's how we know that
it's that this is linked to a חטאת chatas, *Chatat*, a regular
חטאת chatas. *Chatat*, and not an אשם תלוי *Asham Talui* because they
have the two words מצוות השם *Mitzvot Hashem* and ואשם *Veasham*. That
makes that a special club. Okay? So it says מן ואשם ומצוות
השם *Min ve'asham umitzvot Hashem*. אמר ליה רב שימי בר אשי לרב
פפא *Amar lei Rav Shimi bar Ashi le-Rav Papa*, וניליף ואשם ונשיאת
עוון מן ואשם ונשיאת עוון *Veneleif veasham unesiat avon min veasham unesiat
avon*? One minute! But there's a double link by the עולה ויורד
oleh veyored, *Oleh Veyored*. By the עולה ויורד oleh veyored *Oleh Veyored*
it says ונשא עוونو *Venasa avono*. It says it uses the פסוק
pasuk? *Pasuk* of ואשם *Veasham* and ונשא עוونو *Venasa avono*. And here
too it uses the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* ואשם *Veasham* ונשא עוونو *Venasa
avono*. So why do you link ואשם *Veasham* and מצוות השם *Mitzvot
Hashem* to create your little your special club? Use ואשם *Veasham* and
ונשא עוونو *Venasa avono* and link it to an עולה ויורד oleh
veyored *Oleh Veyored*, not a fixed חטאת chatas. *Chatat*. So it says
אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק *Ela amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*
דנין ואשם מצוות השם אשר לא תעשנה מן ואשם מצוות השם אשר
לא תעשנה *danin veasham mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asenu min veasham mitzvot
Hashem asher lo te'asenu*. Okay? Here it actually says אשר לא תעשנה
*Asher lo te'asenu*. Okay, מעשות אחת מכל מצוות השם אשר לא תעשנה
ואשמו *Ma'asot achat mikol mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asenu ve'ashamu*. I mean
it really is much closer link; they're right in the same פרשה
*Parashah*. So it's using the same types of phrases. Okay? And it
says ואם נפש אחת תחטא ועשתה אחת מכל מצוות השם אשר לא
תעשנה *Veim nefesh achat techete ve'aseta achat mikol
mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asenu*. אשר לא *Asher lo* here, לא תעשנה
*Lo te'asenu*. Okay?
So you have מצוות השם אשר לא תעשנה ואשם *Mitzvot Hashem asher
lo te'asenu ve'asham*, מצוות השם לא תעשנה ואשם *Mitzvot Hashem lo te'asenu
ve'asham*. Okay? I mean they're ממש *Mamash* the exact same phrases because
they're in the same פרשה *Parashah*.
Do the links follow to אשם תלוי *Asham Talui*?
Ah, so that's the problem. Okay? Is that at the end of
the day it doesn't create a link to אשם תלוי *Asham Talui*.
So how do you know in the end to link אשם תלוי
*Asham Talui* to this rather than to link אשם תלוי *Asham Talui*
to the עולה ויורד oleh veyored *Oleh Veyored*? And רש"י *Rashi* doesn't
really spell that out; that's an excellent question. Okay? How this is
linked, how the special קרבן korban *Korban* of the ציבור *Tzibur* is
linked to a חטאת קבועה chatas kavua, *Chatat Kavuah* and not an
עולה ויורד oleh veyored *Oleh Veyored* is clear; these all these three
phrases only exist here. Okay? But it is less clear at the
end of the day how we link an אשם תלוי *Asham Talui*
only to this and not to the case of an עולה ויורד
*Oleh Veyored*. Okay? ואל יוכיח שמיעת קול וביטוי שפתים u'vitui sefasayim וטומאת
מקדש וקדשיו שלא נאמר ne'emar, בהן ואשם מצוות השם אשר לא תעשנה
*Veal yochiach shemiat kol uvitui sefatayim vetumat mikdash vekodashav shelo neemar bahen
veasham mitzvot Hashem asher lo teasena*. Okay, so we have a very
tight link here which is our primary focus is the קרבן korban
ציבור *Korban Tzibur*'s link to חטאת קבועה *Chatat Kavuah* and not עולה
ויורד *Oleh Veyored*. But yes, the question you ask is an excellent
one. How we know in the end that this is the אשם
תלוי *Asham Talui* is only linked to these cases and not linked
to the עולה ויורד *Oleh Veyored* is less clear. Alright. Alright, let's
go on to the next משנה *Mishnah*. אין חייבין על שמיעת קול
ועל ביטוי שפתים ועל טומאת מקדש וקדשיו *Ein chayavin al shemiat kol
ve'al bitui sefatayim ve'al tumat mikdash vekodashav*. These are the three things
of an עולה ויורד *Oleh Veyored*, so it's really repeating itself a
little bit. I mean, before it used one concrete example, here it's
using three concrete examples. Okay? So a case about somebody who hears
a שבועה *Shevuah*, okay, and basically takes an oath that they don't
know testimony or something of that sort. Okay? Or, okay,
or somebody that takes a שבועת שקר shvuas sheker? *Shevuat Sheker*, ביטוי
שפתים *Bitui Sefatayim*, or a case of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו *Tumat Mikdash
ve'Kodashav*. These are the three cases. of a עולה ויורד, of a
קרבן korban that goes up and down, okay, so if you don't
bring, so בית דין beis din is not חייב chayiv for that.
So that's just repeating what we said before. בית דין beis din
is only for a fixed חטאת, not for a variable חטאת. Now
though we're going to add another phrase. והנשיא
כיוצא בהם. vehanasi kiyosei bahem. A נשיא, nasi, a king, a political
head, he never brings for an עולה ויורד. He only brings for
a fixed חטאת. That's an interesting idea. Why not? Why wouldn't he
bring for an עולה ויורד? Okay, דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי, divrei Rabbi
Yose HaGlili, that's
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva
omer, הנשיא חייב בכולן חוץ משמיעת הקול. hanasi chayiv bekulan chutz mishmias
hakol. No, no, no. For the case about like the oath or
the case of the טומאת מקדש, the נשיא nasi would bring your
normal קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh veyored. Okay, his special קרבן korban.
is for a חטאת קבועה, his special קרבן korban. of a שעיר,
seir, okay, but or שעירה, seira, but this, I forget שעיר, seir,
anyway, but this would be but when he does an עולה ויורד
sin he'd bring an עולה ויורד, except for the case about being
taken being sworn to give testimony. That doesn't apply to a king
and there he would not bring a קרבן. korban. שהמלך לא דן
ולא דנין אותו לא מעיד ולא
מעידין אותו. shehamelech lo dan velo danin oso lo me'id velo me'idin
oso. He doesn't judge and he's not judged, he doesn't he doesn't
testify against him, you can't bring him to court to testify, okay,
like all these questions we have now, right, about bringing a sitting
president to court, etc. Okay, anyway, so this is the issues. So
anyway, so he says that aspect of עולה ויורד he doesn't bring.
But the other ones what?
What's the connection?
Because one of the עולה ויורד is שמע קול והוא עד או
ראה או ידע אם לא יגיד ונשא עוונו. shama kol ve'hu ed
o ra'ah o yada im lo yagid venasa avono. One of the
three is being sworn to testify. So being sworn to testify to
you know force somebody to testify through making them take an oath
isn't relevant to a king. So therefore he doesn't bring that, but
the other two he would bring.
וביטוי שפתים is just שבועת שקר?
shvuas sheker, Yeah, well, שבועת שקר, right, exactly. Okay, so אמר עולא,
Amar Ulla, okay, so we understand why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva excluded
him from that one. But why did רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGlili exclude him from the other two? Okay, so אמר עולא, Amar
Ulla, מאי טעמא דבי יוסי הגלילי, mai ta'ama d'bei Yose HaGlili, אמר
קרא, amar kra, והיה כי יאשם לאחת מאלה, vehaya ki ye'asham le'achas
me'eileh, because it lists all three by עולה ויורד and it says
if he sins on one of these three he'll bring this קרבן.
korban So רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says he has to
be somebody who could bring on any one of the
three. כל שמתחייב באחת מתחייב בכולן ושאינו מתחייב באחת אינו מתחייב בכולן.
kol shemis'chayev be'achas mis'chayev bekulan veshe'eino mis'chayev be'achas eino mis'chayev bekulan. If
you could be obligated in one you could be obligated in all,
but if there's one of these you can't be obligated in because
you're a king because you can't be sworn to testify in court,
so you're not חייב chayiv for any of these things to bring
a קרבן. korban So the גמרא Gemara says how do you get
that from the פסוק? pasuk ואימא, ve'eima, why not read the פסוק
מתחייב
באחת מהן אף על פי שאינו מתחייב בכולן, mis'chayev be'achas mehen af
al pi she'eino mis'chayev bekulan, I'll read the פסוק the exact opposite.
באחת מאלה, be'achas me'eileh, it's even if you're חייב chayiv for just
one of them you bring a קרבן even if you can't be
חייב chayiv for the rest. אלא טעמא דבי יוסי הגלילי מהכא, ela
ta'ama d'bei Yose HaGlili mehacha, fine, it's based on the following idea.
תניא הרי רבי מאיר אומר, tanya harei Rabbi Meir omer, נאמר, it
says אם לא תגיע ידו, im lo sagi'ah yado, right, if he
can't afford for you know for for for the expensive one then
he brings the you know די שה, dai seh, if he can't
afford a sheep he brings a bird, if he can't afford a
bird he brings a מנחה, mincha, ונאמר, vene'emar, לא תשיג ידו, lo
tasig yado, so this whole קרבן of עולה ויורד only applies to
somebody who might have might be wealthy and might be poor. מי
שבא לידי עניות ועשירות, mi sheba lidei aniyus ve'ashirus, so this whole
category only applies
to somebody who could be rich or poor. יצא נשיא ומשוח, yatza
nasi u'mashiach, a נשיא nasi and the כהן גדול kohen gadol are
always rich. Okay, שאין באין לידי עניות, she'ein ba'in lidei aniyus, they
never become poor. נשיא דכתיב, nasi dechsiv, ועשה אחת מכל מצות השם
אלהיו. va'asa achas mikol mitzvos Hashem elohav. He does one of the
מצות mitzvos of השם his God. What does it mean השם his
God? השם is only his God? השם isn't everybody's God? So it
says מי שאין על גביו אלא השם
אלהיו. mi she'ein al gabav ela Hashem elohav. So he has to
be in a position in society where nobody is greater than him.
And that doesn't just mean that nobody has more structural authority, you
know, political authority than him, but nobody even has more influence than
him, nobody is wealthier than him. He has to be the wealthiest
person. You know there were times that there were people who were
wealthier than kings, you know, like the Rothschilds lent to kings, sometimes
you know they had more money than kings. But anyway, okay, but
that's what we learn out, that a king has to actually be,
you know, has to always be wealthy. Okay, I know if literally
it means if there's like Bill Gates, how do you how do
you make that work? Like you got a Bill Gates, you got
billions of dollars, say, hey, you got to give half of it
to the king because you can't be wealthier than the king. I
don't know. But anyway, a king always has to be wealthy, okay.
ומשוח, umashiach, a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, דכתיב והכהן הגדול מאחיו, dechsiv
vehakohen hagadol me'achav, greater than his brethren. שהוא גדול מאחיו, she'hu gadol
me'achav, בנוי, be'noy,
he's handsomer, בכח, be'koach, he's stronger, ובחכמה, u'vechochma, wiser, ובעושר, u've'osher, and
in wealth. אחרים אומרים מנין שאם אין לו, acherim omrim minayin she'im
ein lo, now how do you know if he doesn't have he's
not wealthy but otherwise he would be fit to be a כהן
גדול? kohen gadol? גדלוהו משל אחיו, gadlohu mishel achav, so you have
to make him wealthier and get all the other כהנים kohanim to
chip in. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, והכהן הגדול מאחיו, vehakohen hagadol me'achav,
אשר יוצק על ראשו, asher yutzak al rosho,
greater from then but from his brothers. גדלוהו מאחיו, gadlohu me'achav, make
him greater from his brothers. Greater, you know, even from his brothers.
So actually they have to contribute to make him wealthy. So according
to that, the reason a נשיא *Nasi*, and now we're saying also
כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*, wouldn't be in the פרשה *Parsha* of עולה
ויורד *Olah Veyored* is עולה ויורד *Olah Veyored* only applies according to
רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yossi Hagalili* to people who could be poor.
And therefore it doesn't apply to a king and a כהן גדול
*Kohen Gadol*. But רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says no, it applies to
them as well. The only thing that wouldn't apply would be the
oath to testify because the oath to testify doesn't apply to a
king because a king can't be forced to testify.
Okay, and we will end with
this.