Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is זיין, zayin, or
page seven, and we pick up, we've started a new פרק perek
about the obligation of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and which is
parallel to that of a בית דין Beit Din in that it
requires a הוראה Hora'ah and a מעשה. Ma'aseh. He has to פסקן,
paskin, although this time he's פסקן-ing paskin for himself and then acting
on it. So a very strange sort of reality because he's not
really a body of פסק, psak, the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and
it's only specifically for himself, but that's what we learn out based
on the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, so we pick up at the very
bottom of ו׳ עמוד ב׳. vav amud bet. And the גמרא Gemara
says מזיד ועשה שוגג. mezid ve'asa shogeg. So we're actually going to
go right now to discuss what are the פסוקים pesukim we learn
this from? That if he has a פסק במזיד psak bemezid and
he does שוגג, shogeg, which really just means he does a sin
בשוגג beshogeg without a פסק, psak, then he does not bring a
קרבן. korban. He doesn't bring any קרבן. korban. It's not that he
has a special קרבן korban for פסק psak and another קרבן korban
for the normal act. No. The only קרבן korban that a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol brings is a פסק psak together with an action.
So מנלן מילי, minalan mili, says the גמרא, Gemara, last line of
ו׳ עמוד ב׳. vav amud bet. Where do we know this from,
that he doesn't just bring a normal חטאת chatat like everybody else?
דתנו רבנן: De-tanu rabbanan: לאשמת העם. le'ashmat ha'am. Because at the end
of פרשת ויקרא, Parshat Vayikra, it speaks about אם הכהן המשיח יחטא
לאשמת העם, im hakohen hamashiah yecheta le'ashmat ha'am, if the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol sins for the
guilt of the congregation. So what is the לאשמת העם, le'ashmat ha'am,
what's the meaning of that? הרי משיח כציבור. Harei mashiah ketzibur. It
is just like the communal sacrifice of the ציבור tsibur of which
we've been talking about until now, the case of the פר העלם
דבר. Par He'lem Davar. שיכול, She-yakhol, because I might have thought, and
now what we're going to do is saying how I might have
derived this without the words לאשמת העם, le'ashmat ha'am, but why in
the end I couldn't have derived it and why I needed the
words לאשמת העם le'ashmat ha'am to teach me to connect it to
פר העלם דבר Par He'lem Davar and teach me that it comes
with a
פסק. psak. ציבור מוצא מכלל יחיד ומשיח מוצא מכלל יחיד. Tsibur mutza
miklal yachid, umashiah mutza miklal yachid. The ציבור, tsibur, the פר העלם
דבר של ציבור Par He'lem Davar shel tsibur what we've been talking
about until now, is different from the sin of an individual. As
we know, ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל, vene'elam davar me'einei hakahal, that there
has to be a פסק, psak, there has to be an action
also. It's different that it starts with, I'm sorry, I jumped to
the criteria, but it starts with the fact that it's different, that
they bring a פר. par. And that's not the case of a
יחיד, yachid, a יחיד yachid brings a, you know, either a she-goat
or
a she-lamb. ומשיח מוצא מכלל יחיד, Umashiah mutza miklal yachid, and the
כהן משיח Kohen Mashiah also brings a different קרבן korban than the
יחיד, yachid, okay, because it says by him
that he brings
an ox, a פר, par, just like the
ציבור. tsibur. מה ציבור אין חייבין אלא על העלם דבר עם שגגת
מעשה, Ma tsibur ein chayavin ela al he'lem davar im shiggat ma'aseh,
so the same way the ציבור tsibur only brings with a פסק
psak followed by an act based on the פסק, psak,
אף משיח לא יהא חייב אלא על העלם דבר עם שגגת מעשה.
af mashiah lo yehei chayav ela al he'lem davar im shiggat ma'aseh.
So similarly by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So basically it says,
look, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings an ox, that's different from
a normal חטאת chatat of a יחיד. yachid. And the ציבור tsibur
brings an ox. So we should assume that they are in the
same category and the same way פר העלם דבר של ציבור, Par
He'lem Davar shel tsibur, we based on the פסוקים pesukim is a
פסק psak with an action, the פר par of the כהן משיח
Kohen Mashiah should also be a פסק psak with an action. That
seems like a reasonable comparison and maybe we won't need a special
פסוק pasuk to teach me this. But then it continues, או כלך
לדרך זו, o khalach laderekh zu, but you know what, you could
make a different argument. נשיא מוצא מכלל יחיד משיח מוצא מכלל יחיד.
Nasi mutza miklal yachid, mashiah mutza miklal yachid. There's also the case
of the נשיא, Nasi, אשר נשיא יחטא, Asher Nasi Yecheta, also at
the end of פרשת ויקרא. Parshat Vayikra. And the נשיא Nasi when
he sins, you know, he brings a שעיר, se'ir, a goat, a
male goat, not a female goat. So he's different from a normal
individual and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is different from a normal
individual who brings a she-goat or she-lamb,
ומשיח מוצא מכלל יחיד, umashiah mutza miklal yachid, and the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is also different, he brings an ox. מה נשיא מביא
בשגגת מעשה בלא העלם דבר, Ma nasi meivi beshiggat ma'aseh belo he'lem
davar, the same way we know that a נשיא Nasi brings just
by a normal שגגה, shgaga, there's no basis to say for the
case of the נשיא Nasi that it's anything other than a straight
שגגה, shgaga, בלא העלם דבר אף משיח מביא בשגגת מעשה בלא העלם
דבר. belo he'lem davar, af mashiah meivi beshiggat ma'aseh belo he'lem davar.
Okay, so maybe we should say the same by a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. So basically you have, you know, at the end of
פרשת ויקרא, Parshat Vayikra, you have the כהן משיח Kohen Mashiah has
a separate קרבן korban of a פר par and the נשיא Nasi
has a separate קרבן korban of a שעיר. se'ir. Okay, and we
know that the ציבור tsibur has their special קרבן korban of a
פר. par. So where are you going to put the כהן גדול?
Kohen Gadol? Are you going to put him with the ציבור, tsibur,
they're both distinct from the normal קרבן korban of a חטאת chatat
of a יחיד, yachid, and therefore you're going to decide that it
requires a פסק? psak? Or are you going to put him in
the same category as the נשיא Nasi and decide that it just
is a simple
שגגה? shgaga? So
נראה למי דומה, Nireh lemi domeh, which one is it more similar?
ציבור בפר ואין מביאים אשם תלוי ומשיח בפר ואין מביא אשם תלוי.
Tzibbur bepar ve-ein meviim asham talui umashiach bepar ve-ein mevi asham talui.
On the one hand, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol most logically belongs
together with the ציבור. Tzibbur. First of all, for the reason we
just said. Both of them, the קרבן Korban that the תורה Torah
assigns is a פר, par, is an ox. Okay? So that should
already argue that they go in the same category. Beyond which, they
also both of them only do not bring an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. An אשם תלוי, asham talui, which we've discussed, is if you
are not sure if you sinned and you bring an אשם, asham,
a קרבן Korban that will sort of be a stopgap until it
becomes clear whether or not you have sinned or not. Now how
do we know that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not, does
not bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? We'll find out later, and
it might be a little circular argument, but for now we'll just
accept that. Okay? So on the one hand I would have put
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol with the ציבור Tzibbur because they both
bring an ox and they both do not bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. That would have argued for that category. מה ציבור אינו
חייב אלא על העלם דבר עם שגגת מעשה אף משיח לא חייב
אלא על העלם דבר ושגגת מעשה. Mah tzibbur eino chayav ela al
helem davar im shiggas maaseh af mashiah lo chayav ela al helem
davar veshiggas maaseh. And once I put him together with the ציבור,
Tzibbur, I'll say that it requires both a פסק Psak and an
action the same way that's true about the ציבור. Tzibbur. That would
have been one way I could have gone, that type of categorizing.
או כלך לדרך זו, O klach lederech zo, or maybe go the
opposite direction.
נשיא מביא שעירה בעבודת כוכבים ומביא אשם ודאי ומשיח מביא שעירה בעבודת
כוכבים ומביא אשם ודאי. Nasi mevi seira ba'avodas kochavim umavi asham vaddai
umashiach mevi seira ba'avodas kochavim umavi asham vaddai.
Here's the ways that they are similar. Both a נשיא Nasi and
the כהן משיח, Kohen Mashiach, both bring a שעירה, seira, a female
goat for a sin of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. That's comes in
פרשת שלח לך Parshat Shelach Lecha where it says that if the
ציבור Tzibbur sins, the entire ציבור Tzibbur sins by עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, which we're going to read just like our פר העלם דבר
של ציבור par helem davar shel tzibbur with a פסק psak and
the entire ציבור tzibbur sins, so then it brings a, you know,
a פר לעולה ושעיר לחטאת. par le'olah veseir lachatas. But it says
if an individual sins for עבודה זרה, avoda zara, that's how חז"ל
Chazal understand the פסוקים, psukim, if an individual sins, it's a שעירה,
seira, it's a female goat. All right? So and
we understand that that category of if an individual includes all cases
of individuals, even the special individuals that we have at the end
of פרשת ויקרא, Parshat Vayikra, even the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, even
the king, when it comes to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, they're all
in the same category of the individual and they all bring a
female goat. Okay? So now we'll say, well wait one minute, let's
put כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in terms of his regular קרבן, Korban,
the ox, in the same category as the נשיא, Nasi, as the
king, because they both are the same, that they're in the same
category when it comes to עבודה זרה, avoda zara, that they both
bring a female goat and they're not in the category of the
ציבור. Tzibbur. That's one way they're similar. מביא שעירה בעבודת כוכבים ומביא
אשם ודאי. Mevi seira ba'avodas kochavim umavi asham vaddai. And they also
bring an אשם ודאי asham vaddai because an אשם ודאי, asham vaddai,
like it take, there's a case about when you steal and you
swear or מעילה, me'ilah, those are, those also we learn from the
פסוקים psukim are only based on actions, not on פסק, psak, and
also as רש"י Rashi points out, they're מזיד. mezid. So it obviously
can't be based on following a wrong פסק. psak. Okay? So both
of those, so it does not apply to the ציבור, tzibbur, but
it does apply again because it says נפש nefesh and it means
any individual. So on the one hand, we have that he's similar
to פר העלם דבר של ציבור par helem davar shel tzibbur because
it brings a, because they're both an ox and they don't bring
an אשם תלוי. asham talui. On the other hand, maybe we'll put
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol in the same category as a נשיא
Nasi because
because both of them bring a goat, a she-goat for עבודה זרה
avoda zara
and different from a ציבור, Tzibbur, and both of them bring an
אשם ודאי asham vaddai and
because again it says נפש, nefesh, any individual including these special individuals,
and different from a ציבור, Tzibbur, it's אשם ודאי asham vaddai does
not apply to a ציבור Tzibbur because it's talking about a case
of מזיד. mezid. So
which I could have gone either way. I wouldn't have known which
category to put it in. And I wouldn't have known whether it
requires a פסק psak like בית דין הגדול beis din hagadol or
just a שגגת מעשה shiggas maaseh
like the standard case of a יחיד yachid or of a נשיא.
nasi. So the גמרא gemara says מה נשיא, Mah Nasi, so I
might have argued because of these similarities to a נשיא, nasi, מה
נשיא מביא בשגגת מעשה אף משיח מביא בשגגת מעשה. Mah nasi mevi
beshiggas maaseh af mashiach mevi beshiggas maaseh. So maybe it's like a
נשיא nasi and therefore just the action is enough. So you could
have gone either way if you didn't have a special פסוק. pasuk.
Logically you could have fit it into either category. תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar, and that's why we need the פסוק pasuk to tell me
לאשמת העם. le'ashmat ha'am. That's why it says by the כהן גדול
kohen gadol if he sins לאשמת העם, le'ashmat ha'am, comparing it to
the sin of the
people. הריהו משיח כציבור, Hareihu mashiach ketzibbur, it's connecting him to the
קרבן korban that the ציבור tzibbur brings. מה ציבור אינו מביא אלא
על העלם דבר עם שגגת מעשה. Mah tzibbur eino mevi ela al
helem davar im shiggas maaseh. so the same way that ציבור tzibbur
only brings with a פסק psak and then an action, ואינו מביא
אלא על העלם דבר שגגת מעשה, ve'eino meivi ela al he'elam davar
shigegat ma'aseh, so אף משיח אינו מביא אלא על העלם דבר שגגת
מעשה. af mashiach eino meivi ela al he'elam davar shigegat ma'aseh. It’s
the same thing with כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, פסק psak followed by
an action. So then, okay, that’s very nice. So that’s the ברייתא
braita and that’s how we know where this principle that a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol comes for פסק paskening and then acting. Now the
גמרא Gemara is going to ask: אי מה ציבור הורו ועשו אחריהם
בהוראתן חייבין... ei ma tzibbur horu ve-asu achareihem be-hora'atan chayavin... oh wait,
excuse me, this seems like it’s still the ברייתא. braita.
Not clear. Anyway, why don’t I say מה ציבור הורו ועשו אחריהם
בהוראתן חייבין אף משיח כשהוורה ועשו אחריו בהוראתו יהיה חייב? ma tzibbur
horu ve-asu achareihem be-hora'atan chayavin af mashiach kshe-hora ve-asu acharav be-hora'ato yehei
chayav? If I really want to compare him to the ציבור, tzibbur,
so the ציבור tzibbur they פסק pasken and other people do the
sin. So maybe if we’re putting the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol into
the ציבור tzibbur category, we should say he
פסק, paskens, and he’s seen as a religious authority, he’s a כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, and other people follow him and that’s the circumstances
in which he brings the קרבן. korban. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so
it teaches, והקריב על חטאתו אשר חטא, ve-hikriv al chattato asher chata,
that he brings for his חטא chet that he has sinned. על
מה שחטא הוא מביא, al mah she-chata hu meivi, for the sin
he did, ואין מביא על מה שחטאו אחרים, ve-ein meivi al mah
she-chatau acherim, and not for what others did. So that’s, I'm sorry,
this seems to be the end of the ברייתא. braita. The word
אימא, eima, which is Aramaic whereas the rest of this whole ברייתא
braita was Hebrew. That was probably thrown in by the גמרא. Gemara.
But this is the end of the ברייתא. braita. Okay, so we
know that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is like the ציבור, tzibbur,
it needs פסק psak and following and then to be acted on.
But unlike the case of the ציבור, tzibbur, he is the one
who acts on it because it says על חטאתו אשר חטא, al
chattato asher chata, his sin, he acted on it, so he both
פסק pasked and acted on his own פסק. psak. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara asks one question on this ברייתא. braita. אמר מר משיח
בפר ואין מביא אשם תלוי. amar mar mashiach be-par ve-ein meivi asham
talui. So what, the reason we would have categorized the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol together with the ציבור tzibbur is number one, they both
bring an ox, a פר, par, that’s explicit. And also, neither of
them bring an אשם תלוי asham talui if there’s a... if it’s
uncertain if he sinned.
So the גמרא Gemara says: מנלן דאין מביא אשם תלוי? minalan de-ein
meivi asham talui? How do I know that a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol doesn't bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? Why shouldn't he? דכתיב
de-chtiv because the פסוק pasuk says: וכיפר עליו הכהן על שגגתו אשר
שגג. ve-chiper alav ha-kohen al shigegato asher shagag. It’s the פסוק pasuk
by אשם תלוי asham talui says, and the כהן kohen will atone
for him for his accidental act, for his sin that he has
done unintentionally. And from there we
learn: מי שחטאתו ושגגתו שוה, mi she-chattato ve-shigegato shaveh, it says השגגה
אשר שגג, ha-shigegah asher shagag, it repeats the word שגגה. shgagah. So
only somebody that the sin and the שגגה shgagah are basically the
entire thing. You had a mistake and you acted on it and
it was all one thing, the שגגה shgagah and the sin were
all one thing. That’s the type of a person that brings an
אשם תלוי, asham talui, which would exclude any case where it requires
a different thing like a הוראה hora'ah and not just the שגגה
אשר שגג. shigegah asher shagag. יצא משיח שאין שגגתו וחטאתו שוה, yatza
mashiach she-ein shigegato ve-chattato shaveh, which excludes the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
because it’s not just about the action, it’s also about the פסק.
psak. Obviously also includes
the בית דין. Beis Din.
So the גמרא Gemara says: But one minute, how do you know
that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol requires הוראה, hora'ah, requires a פסק,
psak, not just an action? דכתיב לאשמת העם הרי הוא משיח כציבור.
de-chtiv le-ashmat ha-am harei hu mashiach ke-tzibbur. Like we said, the לאשמת
העם, le-ashmat ha-am, that he’s like the ציבור tzibbur and he requires
a פסק. psak. So what have we said? How do you know
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does not bring an אשם תלוי? asham
talui? Because an אשם תלוי asham talui is only for people who
it’s all based on action. But for a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
it’s also based on פסק, psak, no אשם תלוי. asham talui. And
how do you know that it’s also based on פסק? psak? Because
it says לאשמת העם. le-ashmat ha-am. But the גמרא Gemara says that’s
circular. The whole thing we were trying to figure out, which category
do we put him in, in the category with ציבור tzibbur or
in the category with the נשיא, nasi, was saying if we didn't
know the פסוק pasuk of לאשמת העם le-ashmat ha-am and we didn't
yet know whether he required a פסק. psak. So how could we
say let's put him together with ציבור tzibbur because they both don't
bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? We don't have any basis to
say he doesn't bring an אשם תלוי asham talui until we have
figured out this question of whether he requires a פסק psak or
not. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, you're right. ולאשמת
העם עד כאן לא קאמר לה. ve-le-ashmat ha-am ad kan lo ka'amar
lah. And the לאשמת העם le-ashmat ha-am that teaches us that a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol needs a פסק, psak, we haven't figured that
out yet. We're trying to figure out, does a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol need הוראה hora'ah or not, which category do you put him
in? Eventually we'll get to לאשמת העם. le-ashmat ha-am. So before we
have figured it out and before we have לאשמת העם, le-ashmat ha-am,
how can you tell me he doesn't bring an אשם תלוי? asham
talui? So the גמרא Gemara says: You know what, you're right. אלא
אשם כדי נסבה. ela asham kedei nesavah. אשם asham was just thrown
in. It’s making a point that once we know the הלכה, halacha,
we know they're similar in that way, you should understand that. But
you're right, in this hypothetical, that would not have been the reason
to group him with the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, with the ציבור.
tzibbur. The only reason to group him with the ציבור tzibbur would
have been that they both bring a פר. par. But we... and
once now we learn that he is like the ציבור... tzibbur... It
requires הוראה horah and an action, we also know that he does
not bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy the same way the ציבור
tzibur does not bring it. Okay, very good.
Next משנה. mishnah. So that was the basic principle of a כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, פסק psak followed by an action. הורה בפני עצמו
ועשה בפני עצמו מתכפר לו בפני עצמו. horah bifnei atzmo ve'asah bifnei
atzmo mitkaper lo bifnei atzmo. If he rules for himself and acts
for himself then he brings his own קרבן, korban, which is obvious.
הורה
עם הציבור ועשה עם הציבור מתכפר לו עם הציבור. horah im hatzibur
ve'asah im hatzibur mitkaper lo im hatzibur. If he פסקס paskens with
the ציבור tzibur and acts with the ציבור, tzibur, then he's included
in their קרבן. korban. Now we'll see in the גמרא Gemara how
it describes בפני עצמו bifnei atzmo and עם הציבור. im hatzibur.
To me it would seem that the simple explanation is that like
on one he's just making his own חשבון, cheshbon, he's figuring out
are you allowed to eat חלב chelev or not or this חלב
chelev אסור assur or not, he פסקס paskens for himself and he
acts on his own. And whatever if the ציבור tzibur is doing
something and they're פסקנינג paskening wrong, maybe they're even פסקנינג paskening about
the same issue, they're doing it independent of him. He's operating independent
of them. Okay, that's then then they each bring separate. However, if
he פסקס paskens together, right, הורה עם הציבור, horah im hatzibur, he
was in the בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol or somehow or
he פסקד pasked with them or they were in conversation and it
was somehow happening together, and then they acted, then he's just part
of the עם am in that case, he's following the פסק psak
of the בית דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol and in that case
he would,
there would not be a special קרבן korban for him. That's how
I would have read it. We will see in the גמרא Gemara
that the גמרא Gemara is going to make a more radical read,
as it were,
that there'll be that ways in which he will bring that he'll
be part of the ציבור tzibur even when there was more independence
in his own פסק. psak. All right.
שאין בית דין חייבין עד שיורו לבטל מקצת ולקיים מקצת she'ein Beis
Din chayavin ad sheyoru levatel miktzas ulekayem miktzas because the question is
what's the ש shin because it doesn't really seem connected to the
previous part. The ראש Rosh says it really means a separate point.
You should know, a בית דין Beis Din is not חייב chayav
until they פסקן pasken to be מבטל mevatel some and to be
מקיים mekayem some, right? We've already taught this earlier, it was in
an earlier משנה, mishnah, only if they not if they uproot an
entire thing, but only if they פסקן pasken to do מבטל mevatel
some and מקיים mekayem some. וכן משיח, vechein mashiach, and the same
is true with the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, so not surprisingly since
a כהן גדול kohen gadol requires פסק, psak, it requires the same
type of פסק, psak, some of the מצוה mitzvah is kept and
some of it is said to not be applicable.
וכן משיח. vechein mashiach. ולא בעבודה זרה עד שיורו לבטל מקצת ולקיים
מקצת, velo be'avodah zarah ad sheyoru levatel miktzas ulekayem miktzas, and the
same by עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, even though there's a special קרבן
korban by עבודה זרה avodah zarah for the ציבור tzibur as we
said, a פר par for an עולה olah and a שעיר se'ir
for a חטאת, chatas, that nevertheless it's fundamentally also based on הוראה
hora'ah and action, and it requires the the criteria of that they
keep some of the הלכה halacha of the מצוה mitzvah and some
of it they negate. Okay, now what's interesting is it did not
say in the second part וכן במשיח. vechein bemashiach. So the question
is as that since the משיח mashiach is like the נשיא nasi
and is like the normal individual when it comes to עבודה זרה
avodah zarah and that they bring a שעירה, se'irah, female goat, and
they're all in
נפש nefesh in that category, and it's not his special קרבן korban
of a פר, par, what is the story about a נשיא'ס nasi's
bringing of the goat of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Does that is
that just by the action or does that also require a פסק?
psak? We will see at the end of today's דף daf that
that is a debate between רבי Rebbi and the חכמים, chachamim, but
it's interesting that the משנה mishnah here does not end with וכן
במשיח. vechein bemashiach. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
מנא הני מילי, mana hanei milei, where do you know this that
this idea that if he acts together with the ציבור, tzibur, the
כהן גדול, kohen gadol, it's the קרבן korban of the ציבור? tzibur?
דתנו רבנן, detanu rabanan, we taught: הורה עם הציבור ועשה עם הציבור,
horah im hatzibur ve'asah im hatzibur, if he פסקד pasked with the
ציבור tzibur and acted with the ציבור, tzibur, יכול
יביא פר לעצמו, yachol yavi par le'atzmo, maybe he should anyway just
still he's still in his box and he's going to bring his
own his own פר. par. ודין
הוא, vedin hu, and that would make sense.
נשיא, nasi, there's a lot of קול וחומר kal vachomer of מדרש
הלכה midrash halacha here.
נשיא מוצא מכלל יחיד ומשיח מוצא מכלל יחיד. nasi mutza miklal yachid
umashiach mutza miklal yachid. A נשיא nasi is different than the individual
and the משיח mashiach is different than the individual.
So in the sense that neither of them brings
the normal קרבן korban for a sin. The individual brings as we've
said, a כשבה kisbah or שעירה, se'irah, female goat or female sheep,
and the נשיא nasi brings a שעיר, se'ir, and the כהן גדול
kohen gadol brings an ox. So both the כהן גדול kohen gadol
and the נשיא nasi are not in the normal category of an
individual. Okay, so נשיא מוצא מכלל יחיד ומשיח מוצא מכלל יחיד. nasi
mutza miklal yachid umashiach mutza miklal yachid. מה נשיא חטא בפני עצמו
מביא בפני עצמו, mah nasi chata bifnei atzmo mevi bifnei atzmo, the
same way when a יחיד yachid brings, does his own sin, he
does because there's no idea of פסק psak by a נשיא. nasi.
He just sins, so he brings his קרבן, korban, that's true. חטאו
עם הציבור מתכפר לו עם הציבור, Chatau im hatzibur mitkaper lo im
hatzibur, but if he sinned with the ציבור, tzibur, right again, because
there's no הוראה hora'ah relevant to a נשיא, nasi, obviously if he's
following the פסק psak of the בית דין beis din and he
is, and he is sinning together with the ציבור, tzibur, he's in
the normal category of the ציבור tzibur and the קרבן korban of
the בית דין beis din works for him. Okay, חטאו עם הציבור
מתכפר לו עם הציבור. chatau im hatzibur mitkaper lo im hatzibur. So
therefore, so I would say אף משיח. af mashiach. So by the
נשיא nasi there's obviously he's part of the ציבור tzibur because there's
no idea of הוראה. hora'ah. So I will say the same thing,
אף משיח, af mashiach, חטא בפני עצמו מביא בפני עצמו. chata bifnei
atzmo mevi bifnei atzmo. If he sins by himself he brings by
himself, but חטאו עם הציבור מתכפר לו עם הציבור, chatau im hatzibur
mitkaper lo im hatzibur, but if he's sinning with the ציבור tzibur
it should be atoned for by the ציבור. tzibur. Okay, even though
הוראה hora'ah is relevant, but if he actually was, I'm going to
describe for now עם הציבור im hatzibur means exactly listening to בית
דין beis din and following בית דין, beis din, then he should
be part of their קרבן. korban. So the גמרא gemara says לא,
lo, not necessarily, or the ברייתא braisa says אם אמרת בנשיא שכן
מתכפר לו עם הציבור ביום הכפורים תאמר במשיח שאין מתכפר לו עם
הציבור ביום הכפורים. im amarta benasi shekein mitkaper lo im hatzibur beyom
hakippurim tomar bemashiach she'ein mitkaper lo im hatzibur beyom hakippurim. No, we
know that a נשיא nasi in other circumstances is part of the
ציבור tzibur on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, right, the case of the
שעיר, se'ir, you know, that's blood is sprinkled on the inside for
the entire ציבור, tzibur, so that's the entire ציבור, tzibur, it includes
the king. So therefore, it makes sense that in other places he
could be included in the atonement of the ציבור. tzibur.
But תאמר במשיח, tomar bemashiach, but when it comes to the כהן
גדול, kohein gadol, שאין מתכפר לו עם הציבור ביום הכפורים, she'ein mitkaper
lo im hatzibur beyom hakippurim, we never have any evidence that the
כהן גדול kohein gadol ever is part of a כפרה kappara
together with the ציבור. tzibur. I mean he's part of the קרבנות
ציבור, korbanos tzibur, the
תמיד, tamid, even the חטאת chatas that's brought on the מוספין, musafin,
but when a case that there's a real need for כפרה, kappara,
we never have him together with the rest of the ציבור tzibur
because on יום כפור Yom Kippur the פר par is for him
and for the כהנים. kohanim. So therefore, maybe even when he sins
with the ציבור, tzibur, it does he does not get, you know,
he is not included in the category and does not get the
the same קרבן. korban. So therefore, since I can't figure it out
just logically which box to put him in, I have to learn
it from a פסוק, pasuk, תלמוד לומר על חטאתו אשר חטא talmud
lomar al chataso asher chata for the sin that he has sinned.
Okay, when it's only his sin or when it's his sin uniquely
then he brings this קרבן, korban, the special קרבן korban for the
כהן גדול, kohein gadol, okay, but when it's not just his, when
he's part of the ציבור, tzibur, then not this he's not in
his box, he's in the ציבור tzibur box and it's the קרבן
korban for the ציבור. tzibur. הא כיצד, ha keitzad, חטא בפני עצמו
chata bifnei atzmo if he sins by himself, מביא בפני עצמו, mevi
bifnei atzmo, חטא עם הציבור chata im hatzibur if he sins with
the ציבור, tzibur, מתכפר לו עם הציבור mitkaper lo im hatzibur then
it works with the ציבור. tzibur. Okay, so that all makes sense,
what we have to figure out, I mean it makes sense the
פסוק, pasuk, logically it makes sense, what is the definition of עם
הציבור? im hatzibur? So this is where things get a little a
little like not so logical. Okay, היכא דמי? heicha dami? So now
the גמרא gemara is going to ask that.
What's the case about him doing it with the
ציבור? tzibur? אילימא דהוא מופלא והם אינם מופלאים, eiliima dahu mufla veheim
einam muflaim, if he is a מופלא, mufla, an expert, and they
are not מופלאים, muflaim, experts. Now what does this word מופלא mufla
mean? The גמרא, gemara, so רש"י, Rashi, you know, it's funny, sometimes
it just means somebody who is fit to be on the בית
דין, beis din, somebody who's ראוי להוראה, raui lehora'ah, what the גמרא
gemara said גמיר וסביר, gamir vesavir, that's the way the תוספות רא"ש
Tosafos Rosh reads it. רש"י Rashi reads it that it could be
referred to like somebody of an extra high level, you know, a
real expert. And we said before that you need not only to
have the בית דין הגדול, beis din hagadol, you need there to
be the מופלא שבבית דין mufla shebeveis din to be there as
well. All right, but רש"י's Rashi read doesn't really fit because as
we continue to read it, but let's take a look. If they
are, you know, if he is able to פסקן, pasken, we'll read
it like the רא"ש, Rosh, and they're not really at the level
of פסק. psak. Now like it's important, I'm going to read the
רא"ש Rosh inside just because it's such a funny idea that the
בית דין הגדול beis din hagadol is not מופלאים, muflaim, so if
you take a look at the רא"ש Rosh here, he says like
this: five lines from the bottom, היכא דמי דקאמר חטא בפני עצמו
מתכפר בפני עצמו. heicha dami deka'amar chata bifnei atzmo mitkaper bifnei atzmo.
דעל כרחך בדהוי
תרי הוראות כדפרישית. de'al korchacha badehavei terei hora'os kidephreishis. Now he says
like this,
well three lines from the bottom, excuse me, ומוקי לה רב פפא
בשוין שכולן מופלאים. umokei lah Rav Pappa beshavin shekullan muflaim. And he
says ולא ברירא ליה שפיר מאי הפירוש מופלא. velo berira leh shapir
mai haperush mufla. I don't really fully understand the meaning of the
word מופלא mufla in this context. דראוי להוראה היינו גמיר וסביר
כולי תלמודא, deraui lehora'ah hainu gamir vesavir kulei talmuda, that somebody fit
to פסקן pasken is normally what we would think מופלא mufla means
and that means that you know the entire ש"ס shas and you
are able to analyze it, כשמעון
בן עזאי, keShimon ben Azzai, וגמיר וסביר מה חסר ליה להיותו נקרא
מופלא? vegamir vesavir mah chasar leh lihyoso nikra mufla? So, you know,
when if מופלא mufla means an expert like רש"י Rashi said, what
bigger expertise do you need? You know, if you have the qualifications
to be on the בית דין הגדול, beis din hagadol, you know
all of ש"ס, shas, you know how to analyze, who's this מופלא
mufla that you might not be that's at a higher level? ואפשר
דמושיבין בסנהדרין אף על פי שאינו ראוי להוראה אם לא מ ve'efshar
demoshivin beSanhedrin af al pi she'eino raui lehora'ah im lo m משכחת
ראוי
להוראה. meshkachat ra'uy le'hora'ah. So this is a shocking statement, but in
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin of 71, we're told that all of the crazy
criteria you needed to be on this סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. The ראש Rosh
says, if you couldn't find people that really were ראוי להוראה, ra'uy
le'hora'ah, that really knew all of ש"ס Shas and had good analysis,
you would also put people that weren't yet מופלא mufla on it.
ואותן הראויים להוראה נקראין מופלאין, ואחריו מה שקורין ראוי
להוראה. Ve'otan hara'uyim le'hora'ah nikrain mufla'in, ve'acharyav mah shekorin ra'uy le'hora'ah. So
this is a fascinating read of the ראש Rosh that you could
imagine a בית דין Beit Din that does not have people, a
סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, that not everybody there is ראוי להוראה. ra'uy le'hora'ah. רש"י
Rashi says it means that you don't have somebody there who's a
super expert. So let's read that again. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's
the case? אילימא דהוא מופלא, Ilima dehu mufla, he is an expert
or he is ראוי להוראה, ra'uy le'hora'ah, והם אינם מופלאין, veheim einam
mufla'in, and they on their בית דין Beit Din have people that
are not ראוי להוראה ra'uy le'hora'ah like the ראש Rosh or like
רש"י Rashi would say, their בית דין Beit Din doesn't have a
super expert present. So in that case, פשיטא דמסתקבל בפני
עצמו, peshita demistakbel bifnei atzmo, obviously he's not going to be together
with them. הוראה דילהון לאו כלום
היא, Hora'ah dilehon lav klum hi, it's like they didn't פסקן, pasken,
and ובעי אתויי כספור סיירן וכל חד וחד. Uva'ei atuwei kesipur sayran
vechol chad vechad. So not only him, the entire כלל ישראל, Klal
Yisrael, it's not a case of the פסק psak of a בית
דין. Beit Din. Everybody brings as a יחיד yachid because if the
בית דין Beit Din had on it people that weren't fit for
הוראה hora'ah or it didn't have on it the super expert the
way רש"י Rashi reads it, then their פסק psak is not a
legitimate פסק. psak. So obviously we're not talking about that case. אלא
ואי דאינון
מופלאין, Ella ve'i de'inun mufla'in, let's say the בית דין, Beit Din,
the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, they're all ראוי להוראה ra'uy le'hora'ah and they have
their super expert on it and their פסק psak is going to
be a פסק. psak. Obviously that would be the case. והוא לאו
מופלא, Vehu lav mufla, but he is somebody that is not ראוי
להוראה. ra'uy le'hora'ah. So this is a good question. What scenario of
are we talking about that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol פסקנס? paskens?
Is he fit to be on the סנהדרין? Sanhedrin? Is he ראוי
להוראה? ra'uy le'hora'ah? So the גמרא Gemara says if he's not ראוי
להוראה, ra'uy le'hora'ah, אמידי מסתקבל בפני עצמו, הוראה דידיה לאו כלום
היא, amidi mistakbel bifnei atzmo, hora'ah dideyh lav klum hi, then he'll
never have, he won't bring his own קרבן korban because his own
פסק psak is not פסק. psak. So what we're finding out here,
which we never analyzed before, is that if a כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol needs to פסקן pasken and then follow his פסק, psak, the
scenario is not that he's an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, which sometimes
you had by the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and פסקנינג. paskening. His
פסק psak has to be real פסק. psak. He has to be
ראוי להוראה ra'uy le'hora'ah and פסקן, pasken, otherwise it doesn't count as
פסק. psak. So the גמרא Gemara
says when we're talking about בית דין, Beit Din, סנהדרין Sanhedrin פסקנינג
paskening and him פסקנינג, paskening, the only scenario is that the סנהדרין
Sanhedrin is all ראוי להוראה ra'uy le'hora'ah because that's the case where
it's the פר העלם דבר, par he'elam davar, and he's ראוי להוראה
ra'uy le'hora'ah which is the case where he would bring his קרבן
korban because that's a real פסק. psak.
So the answer's going to be obvious. So therefore, top of ז
עמוד ב. Zayin amud bet. אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, כגון שהיו
מופלאין
שניהם, kegon shehayu mufla'in sheneihem, that they both were expert. So now
you get it. They פסקן pasken and their פסק psak is a
good פסק. psak. He פסקנס paskens on his own, he follows his
פסק, psak, separate. However, if he פסקנס paskens with them,
then he doesn't bring his own קרבן, korban, it's part of the
קרבן korban of the ציבור. tzibbur. And now comes the question of
what does "with them" mean? So let's take a look. סבר למימר,
Savar lemeimar, חד בפני עצמו ועשה בפני
עצמו היכי דמי, chad bifnei atzmo ve'asah bifnei atzmo heichi dami, what's
the case that he did it independent of them? דיתבי בשני מקומות
וקא מורי בתרי
איסורי, Deyatvei bishnei mekomot veka morei bitrei issurei, that they're sitting in
two separate places and they're פסקנינג paskening two different issues. בית דין
Beit Din is פסקנינג paskening about חלב chelev and he's פסקנינג paskening
about דם. dam. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava
said, אטו שני מקומות
גרמי, atu shenei mekomot garmei, who cares about two places? That's not
what makes them separate. It's that they're not connected to one another.
Geography is irrelevant. אלא אפילו יתבי בחד
מקום, ella afilu yatvei bechad makom, even if they're sitting in the
same place, the עם הבית דין im haBeit Din does not mean
physically next to them. וכיון דקא מורי בתרי איסורי, חד בפני עצמו
הוא. vekeivan deka morei bitrei issurei, chad bifnei atzmo hu. If they're
פסקנינג paskening in two different things, one is פסקנינג paskening חלב chelev
and one is פסקנינג paskening דם, dam, then they're separate and they
bring their separate קרבנות. korbanot. That's obvious, two different איסורים, issurim, but
now is separate. The question is going to be what constitutes "together".
Let's take a look at the next piece of גמרא. Gemara. פשיטא
הוא בחלב והם בעבודה זרה, Pshita hu bechelev veheim be'avodah zarah, it's
obvious if he's פסקנינג paskening about חלב chelev and they're פסקנינג paskening
about עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, חטאת בפני עצמו
הוא, chatat bifnei atzmo hu,
that's him sitting by himself. Why? דחלוקין בטעמיה, Dachalukin betameih, first of
all, they're different reasons, meaning they're different עבירות, aveirot, that should be
enough. וחלוקין בקרבנות, Vechalukin bekorbanot,
and the קרבנות korbanot that each one would bring don't link. Why
is that? דהוא בפר, Dehu bepar, when he's פסקנינג paskening by a
normal sin of חלב, chelev, he's in the box of bringing a
פר, par, והם... veheim... and they're in פר ושעיר par ve'se'ir and
they bring a פר par for an עולה olah and a שעיר
se'ir for a חטאת chatas because of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So
obviously there is no way to see him as being together and
him getting the כפרה kapparah together with them. Okay? Because the types
of כפרות kapparahs that they're fit to get are fundamentally different and
the sins that they're doing that are different. Okay? והן בפר ושעיר
ve'hein be'par ve'se'ir דהכא מייתי הני שעיר והוא
לא מייתי. de'hacha mayisi hanei se'ir vehu lo mayisi. They bring, they
bring the goat for that's their חטאת chatas and he's not, he's
only bringing an ox. Okay, so clearly there they would not combine
and he could not get the כפרה kapparah together with the people.
וכל שכן הוא בעבודת כוכבים והן בחלב, ve'chol shekein hu be'avodas kochavim
ve'hein be'cheilev, certainly if he's פוסק'ן paskening relating to עבודה זרה avodah
zarah and they're פוסק'ן paskening relating to חלב. cheilev. דחלוקין בקרבנותיהם לגמרי
de'chalukin be'korbanoseihem legamrei that there the קרבנות korbanos are totally separate. Why?
דהוא שעירה ואינהו פר de'hu se'irah ve'inhu par because he brings a
goat and they bring an ox. At least in the other one,
you know, they were also bringing a פר. par. Maybe it was
a פר par for an עולה. olah. Okay, but in this scenario,
he's עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, he's a goat, and they're a normal
sin, they're a פר. par. There's nothing similar with their קרבנות. korbanos.
Fine. Anyway, they're different עבירות. aveiros. Why would I have put them
in the same category? Okay? אלא הוא בחלב המכסה את הקרב והן
בחלב שעל הדקין. ella hu be'cheilev hamichaseh es hakerev ve'hein be'cheilev she'al
hadakin. So now we're going to get to something that makes sense
to put them together. He's making a פסק psak about, you know,
the חלב cheilev that covers up the inner organs and they're relating
to the חלב cheilev that's on the, you know, that's on the
intestines. So we're not going to try to figure out exactly where
these different חלבs cheilevs are, but they're both פוסק'ן paskening about חלב
cheilev but about different parts of the חלב cheilev of the animal.
מהו? Mahu? Then what's that story? Would they be considered to be
פוסק'ן paskening together? מי אמרינן אף על גב דקרבנם שוה Mi amrinan
af al gav de'korbanam shaveh even though they both bring the same
קרבן, korban, you know, they both would bring a פר par because,
you know, because that's the standard קרבן korban for that for both
of the כהן גדול kohen gadol and for the ציבור. tzibur. כיון
דמתרי קראי קאתו keivan de'mitrei krai ka'asu but nevertheless it's their different
halachic arguments because one of the ones we learn out, you know,
it says the ו, vav, ואת החלב, ve'es hacheilev, comes to include
the חלב cheilev that is on like the intestine, על הדקין. al
hadakin. So, you know, since they're learned out from different פסוקים, pesukim,
even though they're both the same איסור issur of חלב, cheilev, so
clearly the arguments are going to be separate so they're not really
the same פסק. psak. Alright? I mean, I don't know, I could
have said even if they're exactly the same thing, they're both talking
about the חלב על הדקין, cheilev al hadakin, they're just arguments are,
you know, each one is making a completely separate argument. But anyway,
that's what the גמרא Gemara is talking about saying that they're slightly
different based on different פסוקים pesukim even though they're the same thing
and therefore they're a little bit different because their arguments are different.
מהו? Mahu? What do we say in that case? מי אמרינן, Mi
amrinan, do we say אף על גב דקרבנם שוה af al gav
de'korbanam shaveh even though it's the same קרבן, korban, they both would
bring a פר, par, כיון דמתרי קראי קאתו keivan de'mitrei krai ka'asu
since the two the איסור, issur, although it's also both חלב, cheilev,
but since the איסור issur are based on different פסוקים, pesukim, so
their sort of legal arguments are perforce going to be different. So,
הא פלגינהו בטעמייהו ha pelgina b'tama'iyu so they have different reasons and
therefore he can't be said to be following their פסק. psak. Okay?
Because the logical reasons are different. You know, his פסק psak and
their פסק psak have nothing to do with one another and his
actions have nothing to do with their פסק. psak. או דילמא, O
dilma, or do we say, שם חלב אחד הוא shem cheilev echad
hu at the end it's all חלב, cheilev, so he is considered
to follow their פסק. psak. And here's where it doesn't make sense
to me. If they're פוסק'ן paskening about חלב על הדקין cheilev al
hadakin and he's פוסק'ן paskening about חלב המכסה את הקרב cheilev hamichaseh
es hakerev and he goes ahead and he פוסק'ן paskens about חלב
המכסה את הקרב cheilev hamichaseh es hakerev and he eats the חלב
המכסה את הקרב, cheilev hamichaseh es hakerev, then who cares that the
בית דין beis din פוסק'ן paskened about the חלב על הדקין cheilev
al hadakin and the ציבור tzibur listened to them about the חלב
על הדקין? cheilev al hadakin?
Right? He didn't listen to the בית דין. beis din. He פוסק'ן
paskened about a different part of the חלב cheilev and he ate
a different part of the חלב cheilev that had nothing to do
with listening to בית דין. beis din. So it seems that the
גמרא Gemara is saying that even though in practice he was not
following their פסק, psak, okay, he was listening to his own פסק
psak because he was, you know, he was going to because it
was about a different part of the חלב, cheilev, had nothing to
do with what they פוסק'ן, paskened, since in the end right now,
you know, there was פסקים psakim around חלב cheilev and there were
sins around חלב, cheilev, he gets to piggyback on the ציבור. tzibur.
Alright? And be atoned for together with the ציבור. tzibur. I must
admit, I really do not understand that. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, and now the גמרא Gemara
is going to argue even more radical. אם תמצא לומר שם חלב
אחד הוא Im timtza lomar shem cheilev echad hu and if you
say that yes, in that case he would get atoned for with
the ציבור tzibur because it's all חלב, cheilev, הוא בחלב והן בדם
מהו? hu be'cheilev ve'hein be'dam mahu? Let's say he פוסק'ן paskened about
חלב cheilev and ate חלב cheilev and the ציבור tzibur פוסק'ן paskened
about דם, dam, the בית דין, beis din, and they ate דם.
dam. Okay? Now this is crazy. How could it be the same
קרבן? korban? מי אמרינן בטעמייהו הא פלגינהו Mi amrinan b'tama'iyu ha pelgina
and here
they're really, you know, different, you know, different פסוקים, pesukim, different איסורים,
issurim, או דילמא כיון דשוין בקרבנם. o dilma keivan de'shavin be'korbanam. בית
דין Beis Din brings a פר, par, he brings a פר par
and maybe he gets atoned with them? תיקו. Teiku. So the גמרא
Gemara says we don't know. So this is very, very, very strange
that the גמרא Gemara thinks that it possibly what the משנה Mishnah
means when he פסק paskens with them, acts with them, it's even
in two completely different איסורים. issurim. But the fact that I don't
know, they're happening roughly at the same time? I mean who does
it have to happen do they have to happen simultaneously? Can it
be sequentially? How do you exactly measure that? Okay, but somehow since
there's a פסק p'sak going on and an action going on and
it's both about פר, par, he gets to piggyback with their קרבן.
korban. Very strange idea. As I said I would have read the
משנה Mishnah very differently, that we are talking about that actually they
are פוסק paskening about the exact same thing. Anyway, that's how the
גמרא Gemara understands it. Okay. שאין בית דין חייבין עד שיורו לבטל
מקצת ולקיים מקצת. She'ein Beis Din chayavin ad sheyoru levatel miktzas ulekayem
miktzas. Now we're going on to a different point. בית דין Beis
Din is only חייב chayav if they keep some of the מצוה
mitzvah and negate some of it. מנא לן דעד שיורו לבטל מקצת
ולקיים מקצת? Mina lan de'ad sheyoru levatel miktzas ulekayem miktzas? How do
you know this? כדאמרינן בפרקין Kedamrinan beprakin like we said when this
first came up in the last פרק, perek, ונעלם דבר venelam davar
and a matter is hidden, דבר ולא כל הגוף davar velo kol
haguf a piece of it, not the entirety of it. וכן משיח
Vechen Mashiach and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol also, he has to
פסק pasken only to uproot part and to keep part.
מנאלן Minalan where do you know this from? דכתיב לאשמת העם הרי
משיח כציבור Dechsiv le'ashmas ha'am harei Mashiach ketzibur because we learn out
לאשמת העם le'ashmas ha'am makes an equation for whatever the case of
העלם דבר helem davar is, so it's the same type of פסק.
p'sak. ולא בעבודת כוכבים Velo ba'avodas kochavim and not by עבודה זרה
avodah zarah also unless there's a קיום מקצת kiyum miktzas and ביטול
מקצת, bittul miktzas, and עבודה זרה avodah zarah is a different פסוקים,
pesukim, the פסוקים pesukim in שלח לך. Shelach Lecha. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says מנאלן, minalan, where do you know that from that
it requires קיום מקצת kiyum miktzas and ביטול מקצת? bittul miktzas? דתנו
רבנן: Detanu rabanan: לפי שיצאת עבודת כוכבים לדון בעצמה, Lefi sheyatzas avodas
kochavim ladun be'atzmah, since עבודה זרה avodah zarah even in the case
of העלם דבר helem davar has a separate קרבן, korban, a פר
par for an עולה olah and a שעיר se'ir for a חטאת.
chatas. יכול יהא חייב על עקירת מצוה כולה? Yachol yehei chayav al
akiras mitzvah kulah? Maybe you would be, you know, the type of
הוראה hora'ah would be different, you'd be חייב chayav even if you
פסק paskened to completely uproot a מצוה. mitzvah. נאמר כאן מעיני ונאמר
להלן מעיני. Ne'emar kan me'einei vene'emar lehalan me'einei. So it says מעיני
me'einei by, you know, by the case פר העלם דבר, par helem
davar, and here in במדבר Bamidbar טו, tes-vav, it says וכי תשגו
ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה אשר דבר ה' אל משה vechi
sishgu velo sa'asu es kol hamitzvos ha'eleh asher diber Hashem el Moshe
you err and do not do all these מצות, mitzvot, and that's
how we know it means עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, something that's equal
to all the מצות. mitzvot. Okay, and then it says והיה אם
מעיני העדה נעשתה לשגגה, vehayah im me'einei ha'eidah ne'estah lishgagah, if it
is done hidden from the eyes of the ציבור. tzibur. So the
eyes of the ציבור, tzibur, those who have the vision, you know,
that's talking about the בית דין Beis Din and it's hidden from
them. So there we learn that it's talking about הוראה. hora'ah. And
because of the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah because it also said that
by פר העלם דבר, par helem davar, we learn it's the same
type of הוראה. hora'ah. נאמר כאן ונאמר להלן מעיני. מה
להלן מבית דין אף כאן מבית דין. Ne'emar kan vene'emar lehalan me'einei.
Mah lehalan mibeis din af kan mibeis din. So the מעיני me'einei
tells us we're talking about a בית דין. Beis Din. ומה להלן
דבר ולא כל הגוף אף כאן נמי דבר ולא כל הגוף. Umah
lehalan davar velo kol haguf af kan nami davar velo kol haguf.
In the same way again פר העלם דבר par helem davar is
a piece of it and not the whole
thing, here too it is a piece of it and not the
whole thing. Okay, so we make this whole big equation with כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol and פר העלם דבר. par helem davar. And again,
I guess because of the whole thing is learned out and equated,
it allows us to say that sometimes he gets an atonement with
the ציבור tzibur even in possibly cases where it's ממש mamash שני
חטאים. shenei chata'in. Okay. So now we move on to the next
point, next משנה. Mishnah.
אין חייבין אלא על העלם דבר עם שגגת המעשה. Ein chayavin ela
al helem davar im shiggas hama'aseh. So also something that we taught
that, well not only that we taught before, this is like the
basic principle, right?
That, you know, the בית דין הגדול Beis Din Hagadol is only
חייב chayav if they פסק pasken and then people act on it.
וכן המשיח, Vechen Hamashiach, and same by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
ולא בעבודת כוכבים אין
חייבין אלא על העלם דבר עם שגגת המעשה. Velo ba'avodas kochavim ein
chayavin ela al helem davar im shiggas hama'aseh. And similarly by עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, you have to have a פסק p'sak and you
have to act on it. And again, what's interestingly missing here is
it does not say וכן המשיח, vechen Hamashiach, similar to the previous
משנה, Mishnah, which leaves the question of when it comes to עבודה
זרה avodah zarah and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is like the
נשיא nasi and like the יחיד yachid that he brings a שעירה
se'irah because it's all included in the paragraph ואם נפש אחת. ve'im
nefesh achas. So is there still the idea of הוראה hora'ah for
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to be חייב chayav for עבודה זרה?
avodah zarah? So that is what the גמרא Gemara immediately turns to.
Let's take a look. מנא לן? Mina lan? Okay, and first let's
get to the basic principle of how do you know פסק p'sak
plus
action? דתנו רבנן: Detanu rabanan:
ישגו, Yishgu, so it says if the ציבור tzibur sinned. יכול יהו
חייבים על שגגת מעשה? Yachol yehu chayavim al shiggas ma'aseh? Maybe just
sinning by action makes them חייב? chayav? תלמוד לומר ישגו ונעלם דבר.
Talmud lomar yishgu venelam davar.
No, they sinned and the matter was hidden מעיני, me'einei, right? From
the eyes of the קהל. kahal. דבר, אין חייבין אלא על העלם
דבר עם שגגת המעשה. Davar, ein chayavin ela al helem davar im
shiggas hama'aseh. It both has to be hidden, so there has to
be a wrong הוראה hora'ah and an action. וכן המשיח, Vechen Hamashiach,
same by the משיח. Mashiach. מנא לן דכתיב לאשמת העם הרי משיח
כציבור. Minalan dechsiv le'ashmas ha'am harei Mashiach ketzibur. It says לאשמת העם,
le'ashmas ha'am, he's like the ציבור, tzibur, פסק p'sak and an action
and we said before it has to be. his action. Okay now,
ולא בעבודה זרה אלא על העלם דבר שגגת מעשה v'lo b'avodah zarah
ela al he'elam davar shigegat ma'aseh same by עבודה זרה avodah zarah
only if there's a פסק psak followed by an action for now.
מנלן? menalan? Now you know it, דתניא רבנן, d'tanya rabanan, לפי שיצאת
עבודה כוכבים לדון בעצמה. lefi she'yatzat avodah kochavim ladun b'atzmah. עבודה זרה
avodah zarah got its own paragraph, it's got its own treatment to
say that it's a פר לעולה ושעיר לחטאת par l'olah v'seir l'chatat
and not a normal פר לחטאת. par l'chatat. יכול יהיה חייב על
שגגת מעשה? yachol yiheyeh chayav al shigegat ma'aseh? Maybe for,
maybe עבודה זרה avodah zarah just the action is enough? We already
quoted this before. נאמר כאן מעיני ונאמר להלן מעיני. ne'emar kan me'einei
v'ne'emar lehalan me'einei. I know the מעיני מעיני me'einei me'einei links the
two. מה להלן? mah lehalan? We almost just said this. The same
way by the case of העלם דבר, he'elam davar, אין חייבין אלא
על העלם דבר שגגת מעשה. ein chayavin ela al he'elam davar shigegat
ma'aseh. You need a פסק psak and an action. אף כאן, af
kan, here too, even when it's talking again about a חטא chet
of the ציבור tzibur and it says מעיני me'einei by עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, even though it's a, it's a different קרבן, korban, אין
חייבין אלא על העלם דבר שגגת מעשה. ein chayavin ela al he'elam
davar shigegat ma'aseh. Okay, it's only with both, with the פסק psak
and the action. All right, so that's the idea about בית דין,
Beis Din, about a ציבור עבודה זרה, tzibur avodah zarah, you need
the פסק psak and the action. Now, the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ואילו, v'ilu,
finally it's pointing out what's missing from the משנה. Mishnah. ואילו משיח
בעבודה זרה לא קתני. v'ilu mashiach b'avodah zarah lo ktani. It doesn't
say when it's talking about עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, וכן המשיח. v'chein
hamashiach.
So it sounds like that by, when it comes to עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, it's not the idea for the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
it's not a פסק psak with an action. It sounds like it's
just the action. So the גמרא Gemara says, מתניתין מני רבי היא.
masnisin mani Rabbi hi. Who's our משנה? Mishnah? It's going like רבי.
Rabbi. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braita. משיח בעבודה זרה.
mashiach b'avodah zarah. So
what is the story about a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol when it
comes to עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Okay, where we learn from that
והנפש אחת v'hanefesh achas comes to tell us that he brings like
every other individual, he brings a שעירה. seirah. So רבי אומר בשגגת
מעשה. Rabbi omer b'shigegat ma'aseh. So if that's true, he's just like
every individual, for when it comes to עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, just
the action is enough to be חייב. chayav. וחכמים אומרים, v'chachamim omrim,
and the חכמים Chachamim say no, בהעלם דבר, b'he'elam davar, it's just
like the normal obligation. Yes, it is a שעירה, seirah, it's a
different animal, or whatever, male animal or a female animal, but well
it's, no, it's a different, it's not a פר, par, it's a
שעירה, seirah, okay, but so yes it's a different animal, but it
is the same type of circumstances of חיוב. chiyuv. When it comes
to the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, he requires פסק psak and action
by עבודה זרה avodah zarah as well. בהעלם דבר. b'he'elam davar. ושווין,
v'shavin, and they both, רבי Rabbi and the חכמים Chachamim agree, שבשעירה,
she'b'seirah, that he is in the paragraph והנפש אחת תחטא בשגגה v'hanefesh
achas techeta b'shigagah in שלח לך. Shlach Lecha. Okay, yes,
he's included in that and he brings a שעירה, seirah, he does
not bring a פר. par. Okay, that they agree on. ושוין שאין
מביא אשם תלוי. v'shavin she'ein mevi asham talui. And they also agree
that he doesn't bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. We'll get back
to that. Okay, so anyway, that's their debate. He's in the paragraph
of והנפש אחת, v'hanefesh achas, he brings a שעירה. seirah. It's different
from his normal קרבן korban of a פר. par. So רבי Rabbi
says okay, in this category, he's just like every other individual, just
שגגת מעשה. shigegat ma'aseh. And the חכמים Chachamim say no, he's fundamentally
still in the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol category and it requires a
הוראה hora'ah and an action. So that's why we're saying our משנה
Mishnah is רבי Rabbi because it doesn't say וכן המשיח. v'chein hamashiach.
So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא? v'tisbra? Does that make sense? That
the absence of saying וכן המשיח v'chein hamashiach really means it doesn't
apply to the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? ובזדונו כרת ובשגגתו חטאת מקתני?
u'vizdono kares u'v'shigagato chatas miktani?
So in the next משנה, Mishnah, if you take a look on
ח עמוד א, ches amud aleph, the next משנה Mishnah says אין
בית דין חייבין עד שיורו בדבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת. ein Beis
Din chayavin ad she'yoru b'davar she'zdono kares v'shigagato chatas. בית דין Beis
Din is only חייב chayav if it's the type of thing that
if you do it במזיד b'meizid you get כרת kares and if
you do it בשוגג b'shogeg you get a חטאת, chatas, וכן המשיח,
v'chein hamashiach, and same by the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the
weight of the sin has to be a type of a sin
that you would normally bring a חטאת chatas for. ולא בעבודה זרה
עד שיהיה בדבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת. v'lo b'avodah zarah ad she'yiheyeh
b'davar she'zdono kares v'shigagato chatas. And when it comes to עבודה זרה
avodah zarah as well, it has to be not a simple לאו
lav on עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but a weighty sin that you
would bring, get כרת kares or bring a חטאת. chatas. And it
doesn't say וכן המשיח. v'chein hamashiach. And the גמרא Gemara says it's
obvious and we're going to say it tomorrow that we know that
by כהן גדול Kohen Gadol obviously by עבודה זרה avodah zarah in
this category of עבודה זרה avodah zarah that you bring the שעירה,
seirah, it is only the type of thing that you normally bring
a חטאת chatas for. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says ותסברא בזדונו
כרת ובשגגתו חטאת? v'tisbra bizdono kares u'v'shigagato chatas?
That next משנה Mishnah that is saying that the קרבן korban for
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is only something that you would normally get
כרת במזיד kares b'meizid and חטאת בשוגג chatas b'shogeg for, מקתני? miktani?
Did it there say the same is true by כהן גדול? Kohen
Gadol? But we know the same is true by a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. אלא תני הכא והוא הדין להא. ela tani hacha v'hu
hadin l'ha. It says וכן המשיח v'chein hamashiach in the first half
of the משנה Mishnah and you, and it's true about the second
half. It didn't have to say it again. הכא נמי, hacha nami,
here too, תני הכא והוא הדין להא. tani hacha v'hu hadin l'ha.
It says it in the first half but it doesn't, not in
the second, but it is true about the second half as well.
Which is a little bizarre, I mean you must admit. I mean
I hear the argument that in the next משנה Mishnah it does
apply to a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but it is strange that
the structure of the משנה Mishnah leaves off וכן המשיח v'chein hamashiach
every single time it talks by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Maybe it
doesn't want to imagine
that
the כהן... Kohen... also do the פסק psak when it comes to
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but it's not clear whether our משנה Mishna
is רבי Rebbi that says שגגת מעשה shiggat maaseh is enough. It's
not clear from the silence which way our משנה Mishna is
פוסק. paskening. Okay, now מאי טעמא דרבי? mai taama d'Rebbi? What's the
reason of רבי? Rebbi? אמר קרא וכפר הכהן על הנפש השגגת, amar
kra v'chiper hakohen al hanefesh hashogeges, this is what it says there
in במדבר ט״ו Bamidbar Tes Vav by the case of עבודה זרה,
Avodah Zarah, the כהן kohen will atone for the sinning soul בחטאו
בשגגה b'cheto bishgaga when it sins with a שגגה. shgaga. הנפש, hanefesh,
the soul, זה משיח. ze mashiach. Okay, that's even including the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is even in that. I mean really from נפש
nefesh we just learned how it includes all individuals. הכא זה משיח,
hacha ze mashiach, השגגת hashogeges
that sins, okay זה נשיא, ze nasi, even the נשיא. nasi. So
even the special individuals are included in this category fine everybody agrees
to that. But how do you know that it's an action alone?
So בחטאו בשגגה, b'cheto bishgaga,
when the חטא sin is with שגגה, shgaga, רבי סבר חטא זה
בשגגה יהא. Rebbi savar chet ze bishgaga yehei. This חטא, sin, you're
only שגגה shgaga is the only thing that's מחייב m'chayev you. The
הוראה hora'ah is not relevant. The חטא chet here totally is defined
by the שגגה. shgaga. All right, and that applies to everybody who's
in this box and includes כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. רבנן סברי Rabbanan
savri and the rabbis would say, החכמים hachachamim say, מי שחטאו בשגגה,
mi she-cheto bishgaga, יצא משיח שאין חטאו בשגגה אלא בהעלם דבר. yatza
mashiach she-ein cheto bishgaga ella b'helem davar. And they would say no,
the idea that it says that the כהן kohen atones על הנפש
השגגת al hanefesh hashogeges that the שגגה shgaga alone of the action
is enough to bring a קרבן. korban. When does he bring it
for just a שגגת מעשה? shiggat maaseh? בחטאו בשגגה, b'cheto bishgaga, the
type of person who normally only brings for a שגגת מעשה. shiggat
maaseh. Okay, so it's saying the כהן kohen will bring for a
נפש השגגת nefesh hashogeges if you're the type of a person who
normally is judged by בחטאו בשגגה b'cheto bishgaga about your action. Okay,
but for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol the criteria would be different.
You would bring a שעירה s'irah yes, you're in this box bring
a שעירה, s'irah, but you need your normal requirements, you need to
be העלם דבר helem davar and a פסק psak as well. Okay,
יצא משיח שאין חטאו בשגגה אלא בהעלם דבר. yatza mashiach she-ein cheto
bishgaga ella b'helem davar. Okay, now ושווים שבשעירה כיחיד, v'shavim she-b'seirah k'yachid,
but again they both agree that he is in this category and
he does bring a שעירה. s'irah. מנלן? minalan? דאמר קרא ונפש אחת,
d'amar kra v'nefesh achat,
and if one soul, יחיד, yachid, so אחד יחיד ואחד נשיא ואחד
משיח. echad yachid v'echad nasi v'echad mashiach.
It doesn't matter how special you are, any individual whether you're a
king, whether you're a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, כולם בכלל נפש אחת
הן, kulam bichlal nefesh achat hein, they're all in the category of
נפש אחת. nefesh achat. So we know it's a שעירה s'irah and
then the question is are the criteria for being חייב chayav the
same or not. Let's just do a little on דף ח עמוד
ב, Daf Ches Amud Bet, משנה, Mishna, finish up this discussion. ושווים
שאין מביא אשם תלוי, v'shavim she-ein mevi asham talui, and
that they both agree that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does not
bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui, and we already saw some of
this before. מנלן? minalan? Where do you know this from? דכתיב וכפר
עליו הכהן על שגגתו אשר שגג. dichshiv v'chiper alav hakohen al shigagaso
asher shagag.
Okay, that's by an אשם תלוי, asham talui, on the שגגה shgaga
which he did and again that emphasizes the action. רבי סבר מי
שכל חטאו בשגגה, Rebbi savar mi she-kol cheto bishgaga, somebody whose all
sin is only בשגגה. bishgaga. Now the problem is going to be
like this. We already said that על שגגתו אשר שגג al shigagaso
asher shagag that an אשם תלוי asham talui is only for somebody
who his sins are you know that brings קרבנות korbanot for just
the actions, for just the שגגה shgaga and it doesn't apply to
somebody who also requires a פסק, psak, i.e. a כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. So that should be enough. That's certainly why according to the
חכמים chachamim we know there's no אשם תלוי asham talui because a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol always is not just שגגתו אשר שגג, shigagaso
asher shagag, he always requires a פסק. psak. The problem is as
well, the problem is for רבי Rebbi because רבי Rebbi says by
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that he actually just a שגגת מעשה shiggat
maaseh is enough even by a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So if
that's true maybe he has an אשם תלוי asham talui or at
least an אשם תלוי asham talui by עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So
let's see how רבי Rebbi is going to say that even though
by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah שגגה shgaga is enough he never brings
an אשם תלוי. asham talui. דכתיב וכפר עליו הכהן על שגגתו אשר
שגג. dichshiv v'chiper alav hakohen al shigagaso asher shagag. רבי סבר מי
שכל חטאו בשגגה, Rebbi savar mi she-kol cheto bishgaga,
only somebody who
all of his sins are determined based on שגגת מעשה. shiggat maaseh.
יצא זה yatza ze which excludes כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is out of the category of אשם תלוי. asham talui.
Why? שאין כל חטאו בשגגה אלא בהעלם דבר. she-ein kol cheto bishgaga
ella b'helem davar. Because
not all of his sins are fundamentally with a just an action,
every single one other than עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is also through
a העלם דבר. helem davar. Okay, so what רבי Rebbi says is
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol never brings an אשם תלוי asham talui
because even by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah because the אשם תלוי asham
talui is only for people that you know all the time it
only goes by their actions and a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol the
vast majority some of the time it only goes by his actions
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah but the vast majority of times it goes
also by פסק psak and therefore he's not in this category. So
the גמרא Gemara says מכדי כל כתיב? midi kol ksiv? It didn't
say כל, kol, it said אשר. asher. אשר שגג. asher shagag. How
do you learn from this that only somebody who always is based
on actions? So the גמרא Gemara says, אין, In, yes, דאם כן
יכתוב על שגגתו. d'im kein yichtov al shiggaso. If it just wanted
to say that this case, it's enough that it's based on actions,
it should have just said על שגגתו, al shiggaso, for your error.
למה לי אשר שגג, Lama li asher shagag, why does it emphasize
your error that you erred? הא קא משמע לן דעד דאיכא כל
חטאו בשגגה. Ha ka mashma lan d'ad d'ika kol cheto b'shigagah. It's
saying only for somebody who is always based on their actions, על
שגגתו אשר שגג, al shiggaso asher shagag, only that person gets an
אשם תלוי. asham taluy. Somebody like a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol that
most of the time or even some of the time it's based
on פסק, psak, does not get an אשם תלוי, asham taluy, even
by עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So we'll read the parentheses: יצא משיח
שאין כל חטאו בשגגה אלא בעבודת כוכבים. Yatza mashiach she'ein kol cheto
b'shigagah ela b'avodat kochavim. The only, it's not all of his sins
are בשגגה, b'shigagah, the only one that's just based on action is
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. ולא בשאר מצוות ולא בהעלם דבר עם שגגת
מעשה. V'lo b'shear mitzvot v'lo b'he'elem davar im shiggat maaseh. Okay. ורבנן
V'rabbanan and the Rabbis would say, מי שחטאתו בשגגה. mi shechataso b'shigagah.
The Rabbis it's easy because for them a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
always requires a פסק. psak. So when do you bring an אשם
תלוי? asham taluy? מי שחטאתו בשגגה, Mi shechataso b'shigagah, somebody whose sin
is based on action. יצא משיח שאין חטאו בשגגה לא בעבודת כוכבים
ולא בשאר מצוות. Yatza mashiach she'ein cheto b'shigagah lo b'avodat kochavim v'lo
b'shear mitzvot. But by a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol it never is
just based on action, whether עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, whether other things,
אלא בהעלם דבר עם שגגת מעשה, ela b'he'elem davar im shiggat maaseh,
you need both a פסק psak and an action. Okay, so we'll
end with that. So there is no אשם תלוי. asham taluy. It
is for a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, it is a שעירה seirah
for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and the debate of רבי Rebbi and
the חכמים Chachamim whether עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah it's just the action
or even by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah you need the פסק. psak.