Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. We are in the middle of הוריות.
Horayos. We'll be in it for one more week. It's the shortest
מסכת. Masechet. We are, today's דף Daf is דף ו, Daf Vav,
and we are picking up on ה עמוד ב, hey amud bet,
three lines from the bottom. We're in the middle of discussing who
brings the קרבן korban when you have a קרבן פר העלם דבר
של ציבור. korban par helem davar shel tzibur. Is it the בית
דין? Beis Din? Is it the קהל? Kahal? Is it the קהל
Kahal and בית דין? Beis Din? And as far as the קהל
Kahal is concerned, do you treat each שבט shevet separately or do
you look at them as one, as just as one unit of
all of עם ישראל? Am Yisrael? Okay, so תניא, Tanya, we're taught
a ברייתא, brayta, three lines from the bottom, ה עמוד ב. hey
amud bet. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, Rabbi Shimon says, 'מה
תלמוד לומר פר שני בן בקר תקח לחטאת?' Mah talmud lomar par
sheni ben bakar tikach lechatas? and a second פר par you shall
take for a חטאת. chatas. The first one was for an עולה.
Olah. This is talking about the קרבן korban in בהעלותך Behaalotecha that
was brought at the beginning,
when the לויים Leviim were being separated off to be dedicated to
the כהנים Kohanim to the service of the משכן. Mishkan. Okay, and
it says you bring two פרים, parim, one for a חטאת chatas
and one for an עולה. Olah. So why does it say the
second one, פר שני? par sheni? אם ללמד שהם שנים, Im lelamed
sheheim shenayim, if it's to teach that they're two, you know, that
there are two cows,
והלא כבר נאמר ועשית את האחד חטאת ואת האחד עולה, vahalo kvar
neemar veasita ha-echad chatas veh-echad olah, excuse me, bull. You shall make
one of them a חטאת chatas and one an עולה. Olah. We
know they're two. So why do you have to say פר שני?
par sheni? Why do you have to say the word second? אלא
יכול תאכל החטאת ללויים, Ela yachol teachel hachatas laleviim, perhaps this חטאת
chatas would be eaten. And you
know, while it says in for the לויים, Leviim, I don't believe
that the intent here is meaning that the לויים Leviim would eat
it, but it means that this חטאת chatas for the לויים Leviim
would be eaten, you know, is it a normal חטאת chatas that
is eaten? Which is, you know, eaten by the כהנים. Kohanim. תלמוד
לומר Talmud lomar פר שני, par sheni, שני לעולה. sheni laolah. And
it says the second ox, meaning it's, or it is second to
the עולה, Olah, it is like a pair with the עולה. Olah.
מה עולה לא נאכלת אף חטאת לא נאכלת. Mah olah lo ne-echelet
af chatas lo ne-echelet. The same way the עולה Olah is not
eaten, the חטאת chatas is not eaten. This is a special חטאת
chatas that would that the blood would not that that the meat
would not be eaten. כיוצא בו אמר רבי יוסי, Keyotzei bo, amar
Rabbi Yose, similarly
Rabbi Yose said, הבאים משבי הגולה, habaim mishevi hagolah, and this is
why we're quoting it, really we're not going to focus on the
לויים Leviim at all, but we're going to focus on this question
about חטאת chatas and an עולה Olah that are linked and the
חטאת chatas isn't eaten to get us to talk about our topic.
So, אמר רבי יוסי. amar Rabbi Yose. So we have a פסוק
pasuk in עזרא. Ezra. הבאים משבי הגולה הקריבו עלות לאלהי ישראל פרים
שנים עשר הכל עולה. Habaim mishevi hagolah hikrivu olot l'elohei Yisrael parim
shenem asar hakol olah.
So it said that those that came from returning from the exile
from בבל, Bavel, they brought these twelve oxen. And the actual, I'll
read you the whole פסוק, pasuk, this is in עזרא ח לה.
Ezra chet, lamed hey. הבאים מהשבי בני הגולה, Habaim mehshvi bnei hagolah,
those that returned from the exile, from the captivity, the those of
the captivity, הקריבו עלות לאלהי ישראל פרים שנים עשר על כל ישראל,
hikrivu olot l'elohei Yisrael parim shenem asar al kol Yisrael, twelve עלות
olot for all
on behalf of all of Israel, so on behalf of the twelve
tribes. Starting to sound a little more relevant to us. אילים תשעים
וששה כבשים שבעים ושבעה צפירי חטאת, Eilim tishim veshisha kvasim shivim veshiva
tzfirim chatas, וצפירי חטאת שנים עשר הכל עולה להשם. veshiva tzfiri chatas
shenem asar hakol olah l'Hashem.
So rams ninety-six, lambs seventy-seven,
and goats, חטאת chatas goats twelve, everything is an עולה olah for
השם. Hashem. So you have twelve cows and twelve goats and then
a whole lot of other קרבנות korbanos in the middle. Okay, but
then it ends by הכל עולה. hakol olah. So הכל עולה, hakol
olah, הכל עולה סלקא דעתך? hakol olah salka deitach? says the גמרא.
Gemara. It's not all an עולה, olah, you just said at least
that the goats there are are a חטאת. chatas.
הכל עולה סלקא דעתך, Hakol olah salka deitach, אפשר שחטאת עולה? efshar
shechatas olah?
Can you think a חטאת chatas is an עולה? olah? It said
that the twelve goats are a חטאת. chatas. אלא הכל כעולה, Ela
hakol keolah, everything is like an עולה. olah. מה עולה לא נאכלת
אף חטאת לא נאכלת. Mah olah lo ne-echelet af chatas lo ne-echelet.
The same way an עולה olah isn't eaten, the חטאת chatas isn't
eaten. This is a חטאת chatas that wasn't eaten. Okay, and what
חטאת chatas is this? דתניא, Detanya, we taught a ברייתא, brayta, רבי
יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, על עבודה כוכבים הביאום. al avodah kochavim
heviuhem. It was brought for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So the קרבן
korban that is brought for ציבור tzibur when it sins by עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, which we were talking about yesterday,
is as the Torah says in במדבר, Bamidbar, במדבר טו, Bamidbar tet
vav, it says that when you do when you have the whole
ציבור tzibur sinning by עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and we understand that's
also with a פסק psak of the בית דין הגדול, Beis Din
HaGadol, that they bring a פר par for a חטאת chatas and
a שעיר se'ir for a, excuse me, a פר par for an
עולה olah and a שעיר se'ir for a חטאת. chatas. Just like
here, you had twelve פרים parim for עלות olot and twelve שעירים
se'irim for חטאות. chataot. Okay, but what do you do with that
חטאת? chatas? Is it a normal חטאת? chatas?
Is the blood sprinkled on the outside מזבח? mizbeach? Is the meat
eaten? Or is the blood sprinkled on the inner מזבח mizbeach and
it is and and the meat is not eaten? So here we
are going to say that because it calls it הכל עולה, hakol
olah, and we're going to say that this these twelve חטאות, chataot,
these twelve פרים parim that were for עלות olot and the twelve
goats that were for חטאת chatas were for עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
Works very nicely, a פר par for עולה, olah, a goat for
חטאת, chatas, twelve, twelve tribes, etc. And it's comparing the חטאת chatas
to the עולה. olah. The עולה, olah, the חטאת chatas to the
עולה, olah, the same way the עולה olah isn't eaten, the חטאת
chatas isn't eaten. So it tells us that the חטאת chatas of
the קרבן korban for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. is not eaten. Okay,
so let's read that. דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא. baraita. רבי
יהודה אומר: Rabbi Yehuda omer: על עבודת כוכבים הביאו, al avodat kochavim
hevi'u, they brought them for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay, so
there, the twelve of the twelve is the קרבן korban for עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, a פר par for an עולה, olah, a שעיר
se'ir for a חטאת, chatas, and it is telling us that the
חטאת chatas is not eaten because the blood will be brought on
the inner מזבח, mizbe'ach, not on the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay. ואמר
רב יהודה. ve'amar Rav Yehuda.
Now we're going to focus on this. Does this work to be
a קרבן korban of עבודה זרה avoda zara for the entire ציבור?
tzibbur? ואמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: עבודת
כוכבים שעשו בימי צדקיהו. avodat kochavim she'asu bimei Tzidkiyahu.
This was for the עבודה זרה avoda zara that was done in
the time of צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu before they went into exile, and now
they are bringing the atonement now that they returned in the time
of the second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, seventy years later. So there
are going to be some questions here. Let's take a look. בשלמא
לרבי יהודה משכחת לה הני שתים עשרה חטאות כנגד שנים עשר שבטים
דעבדו שתים עשרה שעירים. bishlama leRabbi Yehuda meshkachat lah hanei shteim esrei
chata'ot kineged sheneim asar shevatim de'avdu shteim esrei se'irim.
So according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that you say that you
bring the number of sin offerings for פר העלם דבר של ציבור
par he'elem davar shel tzibbur and similar for the ציבור tzibbur that
does עבודה זרה, avoda zara, you bring according to each שבט shevet
by itself. So there would be twelve of these קרבנות korbanot by
עבודה זרה avoda zara for the twelve tribes if all twelve tribes
sinned with עבודה זרה, avoda zara, which they happened to have done.
So therefore it's going to be since each קרבן korban is a
פר par for an עולה olah and a שעיר se'ir for a
חטאת, chatas, there are twelve פר par for עולה olah and twelve
שעיר se'ir for חטאת. chatas. כנגד שנים עשר שבטים דעבדו שתים עשרה
שעירים kineged sheneim asar shevatim de'avdu shteim esrei se'irim that they bring
twelve goats for the חטאת chatas plus of course the פר par
for the עולה. olah. אינמי דחטו שבעה שבטים ואחרינא בגררא. inami dechatu
shiva shevatim ve'achrina bigrara. Or according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you
don't even really need all the tribes to sin. You just need
the majority and you're still going to be winding up bringing twelve.
Seven of the tribes sinned, ואחרינא בגררא, ve'achrina bigrara, and the rest
are dragged along as we taught in the משנה mishna yesterday. Okay,
so that's going to be how he's going to get his twelve.
That's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. For רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, as long
as the majority of the tribes sin, you're going to bring twelve.
You're going to bring twelve קרבנות, korbanot, which is twelve שעירים se'irim
and then twelve oxen for an עולה. olah. ולרבי שמעון נמי משכחת
לה כנגד אחד עשר שבטים דעבדו אחד עשר שעירים. uLeRabbi Shimon nami
meshkachat lah kineged achad asar shevatim de'avdu achad asar se'irim. For רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who has both the ציבור tzibbur bringing and the
שבטים shevatim bringing and the בית דין beis din bringing, you can
also get twelve. Eleven of the tribes sinned, דעבדו אחד עשר שעירים,
de'avdu achad asar se'irim, and again we're focusing specifically on the חטאת
chatas part here so we're talking just about the goat. So they
bring eleven goats for the eleven tribes, ואידך דבית דין, ve'idach deVeis
Din, plus one more for the בית דין. beis din. Okay, that
all works, that's twelve. אלא לרבי מאיר דאמר בית דין מייתו ולא
ציבור שתים עשרה היכי משכחת לה. ela leRabbi Meir de'amar Beis Din
maitu velo tzibbur shteim esrei heichi meshkachat lah. But according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir since it says the בית דין beis din brings
and not the ציבור, tzibbur, שתים עשרה היכי משכחת לה? shteim esrei
heichi meshkachat lah? How do you get to twelve? You're only going
to have one בית דין. beis din. How do you get twelve?
So the גמרא Gemara says: כגון דחטו והדר חטו והדר חטו. kegon
dechatu vehadar chatu vehadar chatu. That sounds like the whole story of
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael at the time of מלכים. Melachim. They sinned
and then they sinned and then they sinned. So again, if we're
now putting it in the framework of the הוראה hora'ah of the
בית דין, beis din, it's going to have to be בית דין
פסק Beis Din paskened and the ציבור tzibbur sinned and then they
realized and then they פסק paskened again and they sinned and they
realized, which is all very bizarre because since when was the sin
of עבודה זרה avoda zara that was happening in the time of
the first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash having to be based on a
פסק psak of a בית דין beis din and to really imagine
that they פסק paskened twelve times and forgot, and the גמרא Gemara
is eventually going to ask that. None of this was בשוגג, beshogeg,
all of this was במזיד. bemezid. Okay, but we'll take a look,
but this is where we're assuming right now. עד
שתים עשרה זימני,
ad shteim esrei
zimnei, it was twelve times that they sinned based on a פסק
psak and the בית דין פסק Beis Din paskened again and פסק
paskened again and פסק paskened again and remembered each time, עד שתים
עשרה זימני. ad shteim esrei zimnei. Okay. So now that's fine. That's
how you get the numbers. All right, but twelve certainly does work
the best according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But now the גמרא
Gemara is going to ask some more pressing questions. והמתו הנהו דחטו?
vehametu hanahu dechatu? The ones that did the sin died! That was
more than seventy years ago, so how are you bringing a קרבן
korban for them? Now רש"י Rashi says consistently through this discussion in
the גמרא Gemara what it's going to say they were dead. רש"י
Rashi says that the problem is it's a חטאת שמתו בעליה. chatas
shemetu ba'aleha. A חטאת chatas that was separated out by the owner
and the owner dies, you can't bring it as a קרבן. korban.
But that's not actually precise because nobody is saying that the דור
dor of צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu separated out the animals and then they died
and now you're bringing the same animals. The animals would have died
as well. Okay, what it's really saying that they're dead is you
can't bring a קרבן חטאת korban chatas on behalf of somebody that
is already dead. Now I could actually pause here and also note
that there's another problem as well because we were saying that it
was the sin
of the דור dor of צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, you were really left with
two and a half tribes, יהודה בנימין Yehuda Binyamin and לוי Levi
and the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay, all the other tribes were already exiled,
who knows how, a hundred years ago before that. So the whole
twelve doesn't work at all. The גמרא Gemara is completely glossing over
that fact. You could say you're bringing it for the עבודה זרה
avoda zara that those tribes did that were exiled by סנחריב, Sancherev,
but that's not what we've been saying. So anyway the גמרא Gemara
in the end is going to say this is all הוראת שעה.
hora'at sha'ah. So it really doesn't fit any simple category. It doesn't
fit the normal הלכה. halachah. It was a special decision at that
time, a divinely inspired decision to do it this way. It's representative
of the twelve tribes, but it is also worth noting that we're
only talking about two to three tribes, we're not talking about all
twelve. But that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Let's take a look. The
גמרא Gemara says,
where are we? והא מיתו להו הנך דחטאו ve-ha meitu lehu hane
d'chatu but the ones that sinned have already died. אמר רב פפא
Amar Rav Papa כי גמירי חטאת שמתו בעליה במיתה הני מילי
ביחיד. ki g'miri chatat she-meitu ba'aleha be-mitah hani mili be-yachid. So said
רב פפא Rav Papa and this is where רש''י Rashi is getting
it, but the ראש Rosh says it's לאו דווקא. lav davka. When
is the principle that if a חטאת chatat the owner dies you
don't bring the animal? That's when it's an
יחיד yachid individual, אבל לא בציבור aval lo be-tzibur but not by
a ציבור, tzibur, לפי שאין ציבור מתה lefi she-ein tzibur metah because
the ציבור tzibur doesn't die. Now again, רש''י Rashi reads this
as if you separated out the קרבן korban and then he says
he takes the punch out of the phrase אין ציבור מת, ein
tzibur meit, a ציבור tzibur doesn't die. רש''י Rashi says the הלכה
halachah that when the owner dies you can't bring the חטאת, chatat,
that only applies in the case of a יחיד, yachid, it doesn't
apply in the case of ציבור tzibur because the principle that the
חטאת chatat dies when the owner dies you can't bring the חטאת,
chatat, that principle doesn't apply to ציבור. tzibur. So according to רש''י
Rashi the whole thing אין ציבור מת, ein tzibur meit, a ציבור
tzibur doesn't die, according to רש''י Rashi that's really a very narrow
point that the הלכה halachah of חטאת שמתו בעליה chatat she-meitu ba'aleha
doesn't apply to the ציבור. tzibur. But again, we're not really dealing
with a חטאת שמתו בעליה. chatat she-meitu ba'aleha. It's not that the
animal that was separated
off at the time of צדקיהו, Tzidkiyahu, the owners died. No animal
was separated then. The animals are being designated now. So the ראש
Rosh says that, and he says then the question is how do
you bring a קרבן korban for somebody who isn't around? That's the
question, not that the owners died. There was no owners. But you're
bringing it for somebody who is now dead. And the answer is
that if you're bringing it on behalf of the ציבור, tzibur, you
don't look, the ציבור tzibur is you don't look at it as
the millions of specific individuals. It is the corporate entity of the
ציבור. tzibur. And then when people die and their children are alive,
this still is looked at as a continuity of the community. This
is still the same community, maybe the same community a generation later,
but conceptually it is the same community and you're bringing it on
behalf of the community and the community carries its history with it.
So that's a very powerful idea about the corporate nature of the
community and that continues even when all the people change over and
therefore you could bring a קרבן korban on their behalf. All right,
so that's a very powerful point but now let's see how the
גמרא Gemara discusses it. Let's take a look. מנא
ליה לרב פפא הא? Mena lei le-Rav Papa ha? Where does רב
פפא Rav Papa get this idea that a ציבור tzibur doesn't die?
אילימא ממאי דכתיב Ilima mi-mai de-chtiv תחת אבותיך יהיו בניך Tachat avotecha
yihyu vanecha that
your children rise up in the place of their fathers, of their
parents.
So every generation there's a sense of continuity. אי הכי אפילו ביחיד
נמי I hachi afilu be-yachid nami that would be true even about
an individual. Why can't the son bring a קרבן korban on behalf
of חטאת chatat on behalf of his dead father? We don't say
that, right?
We say אלא דוקיה דרב פפא משעיר דראש
חודש. Ella dukyei de-Rav Papa mi-se'ir de-Rosh Chodesh. He's figuring it out
from this שעיר דראש חודש. se'ir de-Rosh Chodesh. דאמר רחמנא De-amar Rachmana
מייתי מתרומת הלשכה. meiti mi-trumat ha-lishkah. You bring this שעיר דראש חודש,
se'ir de-Rosh Chodesh, that's a חטאת, chatat, and you're going to bring
it from the money that you collected at the beginning of the
year. והא מיתו להו מישראל והנך דפיישי היכי מייתו? ve-ha meitu lehu
mi-Yisrael ve-hanech d'pishi heichi meitu?
But one minute, between the time when you collected the money, in
the ניסן Nissan time till you're bringing ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh later
on in the year, some people have definitely died. So how can
you go ahead and bring this קרבן korban if some of the
owners have died? אלא שמע מינה חטאת שמתו בעליה בציבור קריבה. Ella
shema mina chatat she-meitu ba'aleha be-tzibur kreiva. So you see that even
if the owners die, you could still bring the קרבן. korban. So
now again this is the more narrow sense of that the, well
no, I shouldn't say that because the money was given by the
person before he died, but it is, it's somewhat more similar to
our case because when you actually separate out the קרבן, korban, one
of the people whose money you're using, so in a way for
whom the קרבן korban is being separated out for is already dead.
So it's a little similar to our case where the קרבן korban
is being separated out for somebody who's dead, although a little different
because that person already gave his money towards that. Either way the
גמרא Gemara says you see anyway we're more flexible when you're talking
about in the context of a ציבור, tzibur, even if some of
the members are dead.
Of course you could say that's a tiny number of it, a
small percentage.
Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Also you could say that since בית דין Beis Din has sort
of control over how the money is being designated, that it's their
sort of תנאי בית דין, t'nai Beis Din, they're implicitly saying the
money should be used for the people that are alive now. But
anyway, there's a lot of ways you could... How can you compare?
I'm sorry, I lost my point. וחטאת שמתו בעליה בציבור קריבה. V'chatas
shemeisu ba'aleha betzibur kreiva. So you see
that even when, yes, so you
see I did say that, so you see that even when the
owners have died, you can still bring it if it's a ציבור,
tzibur, if it's a חטאת Chatas of the ציבור. tzibur. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מי דמי, Mi dami, how can you compare it?
שעירי
ראשי חדשים, Se'irei Roshei Chodashim, by the goat of ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, maybe nobody died? Now, of course somebody has had to have
died in the last month, but you don't know who it died,
you don't know if you're using their money. There's a lot of
ambiguity here, you know. אבל הכא ודאי
מתו, Aval hacha vadai meisu, here they definitely died and so it's
obviously this is radically different than that case. אלא טעמא דרב פפא
מהכא, Ela ta'ama d'Rav Pappa meihacha, fine from here, דכתיב dechsiv by
the case of עגלה ערופה, Eglah Arufah, כפר לעמך ישראל אשר פדית
ה', Kaper l'amcha Yisrael asher padisa Hashem, atone for your people that
you have redeemed God. So what do you say? It says אשר
פדית, asher padisa, you redeemed, but it's talking about after they go
into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and many generations later. So ראויה כפרה
זו שתכפר על יוצאי מצרים, Re'uyah kapara zo shetchaper al yotzei Mitzrayim,
this כפרה kapara also works for those who left מצרים. Mitzrayim. Not
sure if we're trying to assign a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah type
of reality, excuse me, a עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah type of reality
to them, but whatever it is, somehow the כפרה kapara of the
עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah also works for those who came out of
מצרים. Mitzrayim. מדכתיב אשר פדית, Midechsiv asher padisa, so you see חטאת,
Chatas, of course it's funny, it's not exactly a חטאת, Chatas, it's
not a normal קרבן, korban, but whatever, you can bring a כפרה
kapara for people who are already dead. That's the basic point. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, מי דמי, Mi dami, how can that
be compared? התם כולהו איתינהו, Hasam kulhu isinhu,
everybody that you're bringing the atonement for is there. מיגו דמכפר אחיים
מכפר נמי אמיתים, Migo d'mechaper achayei mechaper nami amisim, since it's working
for the people that are alive, it also works for those that
are dead. אבל הכא מי הוו חיי, Aval hacha mi havu chayei,
but here they're not alive, they all died out. So now you
see the גמרא Gemara is shifting from the narrow point of חטאת
שמתו בעליה, Chatas shemeisu ba'aleha, you know,
it has to do with as I said with designating a קרבן
korban and then dying, and it's talking if you think about the
עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah case conceptually, no, it's about bringing כפרה kapara
on behalf of someone who is already dead. Okay, but the גמרא
Gemara says maybe it worked if you're primarily bringing it for them,
those who are alive, but here everybody who you're bringing it for
is dead. So how do you explain it? So Rav Pappa is
trying to say that it must be that the ציבור tzibur is
not dead. Okay, the ציבור tzibur lives on, but we have yet
to prove it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to say,
אבל הכא מי הוו חיי, Aval hacha mi havu chayei, so okay,
maybe it can work if some of the ציבור tzibur is alive.
We can maybe see it as a continuity and work for you
know the ציבור tzibur even those that have passed. But here none
of the ציבור tzibur is alive. So the גמרא Gemara says, אין
הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami, no, actually some of the ציבור tzibur
was alive and actually it's a מפורש פסוק, meforash pasuk, דכתיב, dechsiv,
ורבים מהכהנים והלוים וראשי האבות הזקנים. V'rabim meihakohanim v'haleviyim v'rashei ha'avos hazkeinim.
So here I'll read the whole פסוק. pasuk. This is talking about
when they returned, you know, and they started laying the foundation for
the rebuilding of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, and it says
like this at the end of עזרא ג', Ezra Gimmel, ורבים מהכהנים
והלוים וראשי האבות הזקנים אשר ראו את הבית הראשון ביסדו זה הבית
בעיניהם בוכים בקול גדול ורבים בתרועה בשמחה להרים קול. V'rabim meihakohanim v'haleviyim
v'rashei ha'avos hazkeinim asher ra'u es habayis harishon biyosdo zeh habayis be'eineihem
bochim b'kol gadol v'rabim bisruah b'simcha l'harim kol. The elder כהנים Kohanim
and לויים Levi'im and the tribes אשר ראו את הבית הראשון ביסדו,
asher ra'u es habayis harishon biyosdo, they saw the first בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash in its when it was founded, right, זה הבית, zeh
habayis, so בעיניהם, be'eineihem, when then they see this house, so
it probably means at the founding of this house, although the trop
is a little different, you know, this house, when they saw it
being founded, בוכים בקול גדול, bochim b'kol gadol, they were crying, ורבים
בתרועה בשמחה להרים קול, v'rabim bisruah b'simcha l'harim kol, but many others
were with a, you know, were rejoicing and blowing the שופרות. shofars.
The young ones who hadn't seen the first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
but the older ones who had seen it, they were crying because
this was nothing like the glory and you know and the reality
of the first בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So for them it was
tragic.
So anyway, you see that many of them were there, that there
were people that came from the time, you know, that were there
in the time of the first בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so
maybe that allows for the continuity similar to the way you had
something like that in the time of what do you call it
in for the עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah. So the גמרא Gemara says,
ודילמא מיעוטא הוו, V'dilma miuta havu,
okay,
but maybe they were a minority. Again, if you're using the עגלה
ערופה Eglah Arufah as your model, you have to it's talking about
when the majority of the people that you're bringing it for are
present. Right? Again, the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah was you're bringing it
for the people that are alive now and it's going to work
for an earlier iteration of the ציבור. tzibur. So here, you know,
you gotta bring it for the so it'll only make sense if
maybe if you could say the majority of the people here were
from the previous generation. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודילמא מיעוטא הוו
לאו רובא הוו? V'dilma miuta havu lav ruba havu? הכתיב, Hachsiv, no,
it
says actually they were the majority,
and the פסוק pasuk here I'll just read this next פסוק, pasuk,
ואין העם מכירים קול תרועת השמחה, V'ein ha'am makirim kol teruas hasimcha,
this is right after the פסוק pasuk I just read, and the
people could not recognize or hear, discern the voice of the of
the blasts of rejoicing לקול בכיהם, lekol bechiyam, for because it was
overwhelmed by the crying of the people, כי העם מריעים תרועה גדולה
והקול נשמע עד למרחוק. ki ha'am mari'im tru'ah gedolah vehakol nishma ad
lamerachok. Okay, so if the crying is overwhelming the sounds of the
שופר shofar blasts and rejoicing, then they must be more numerous. So
you see that the people who returned that the were the majority
of them were actually from the previous generation. Okay. ושבו... v'shavu... so
לקול בכיהם והקול נשמע עד למרחוק. lekol bechiyam vehakol nishma ad lamerachok.
Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara actually, you know, we have not really proven
רב פפא's Rav Pappa's powerful statement אין ציבור מת ein tzibur meys
in an absolute sense. That, you know, many generations later or whatever,
it's still considered the same ציבור tzibur and you could bring a
קרבן korban and atone, you know, it's a question about like nations,
right? You know, reparations in Germany and the Holocaust, like the later
it's not the same people, but can they atone for the for
you know for for them as an entity, as a nation, as
a community, as a ציבור, tzibur, you know, can you bring atonement
for previous generations because ultimately it's still in some way the same
entity. So that was רב פפא's Rav Pappa's point that אין ציבור
מת, ein tzibur meys, but the גמרא Gemara in the end sort
of had a narrower version of that, took out some of the
punch of that and basically spoke about a scenario in which the
majority of the same people are still here. Okay. By the way,
I should say it's not that the majority of the ציבור tzibur
that died is still here, because you know, the people that returned
from the in the time of עזרא Ezra were a very, very
small number. So it certainly was not the majority who went into
the גלות exile 70 years ago, but at least the majority of
the ציבור tzibur that is present right now is made up of
that previous generation. So the גמרא Gemara has accepted רב פפא's Rav
Pappa's statement in narrower parameters, but we'll be returning to it. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. והא מזידין הוו, veha
mezidin havo, but one minute, this doesn't make sense that this was
a קרבן korban of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It wasn't שוגג. shogeg.
They worshipped עבודה זרה במזיד. avodah zarah bemeizid. So the גמרא Gemara
finally says הוראת שעה הייתה. hora'as sha'ah haysah. Fine, it was all
a special edict for that time and it really is not fitting
in any normal parameters. הכי נמי מסתברא, hachi nami mistabra, that also
makes sense, דאי לא תימא הכי, de'i lo teima hachi, if you
don't say that, אילים תשעים וששה כבשים שבעים ושבעה, eilim tishim v'shisha
kvasim shivim v'shiva, there was like 96 rams and 77 lambs. כנגד
מי? k'neged mi? What was that about? אלא הוראת שעה הייתה. ella
hora'as sha'ah haysah. So the whole thing, so that clearly was a,
you know, a special ruling. הכי נמי הוראת שעה הייתה. hachi nami
hora'as sha'ah haysah. So even the 12 oxen and the 12 and
the 12 goats, even though that fits very nicely, we all know
they were עובדי עבודה זרה, ovdei avodah zarah, you know that there's
an איל ayil for an עולה olah and a goat for a
חטאת, chatas, you know there are 12 tribes, so it all fits
very nicely in that pattern, but still, it's not exactly הלכה. halacha.
That might be what it was symbolically about, but it's not exactly
הלכה halacha because they sinned and it was במזיד. bemeizid. And then
that could also, you know, free us from having to worry about
all the other things we tried to fit it into, how does
it work for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, how does it work for
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, they weren't alive, and so on. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, third
line down on wide lines on ו עמוד א. vov amud aleph.
מת אחד מן הציבור חייבין. meis echad min hatzibur chayavin. אחד מבית
דין פטורין. echad mibeis din pturin. If one of the ציבור tzibur
died before from the time they realized that they had, you know,
בית דין beis din realized that they had sinned and they were
חייב chayav in the קרבן, korban, then they're still obligated, you know,
to bring it, obviously, because they otherwise you would never wind up
bringing it. Somebody's always going to die, you know, in a whole
ציבור tzibur by the time it takes you to bring it to
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But if one of the בית דין
beis din died, you're exempt. So the גמרא Gemara says
מאן תנא, man tana, so who is the תנא tana that says
this, that if one of the בית דין beis din dies you're
exempt? So אמר רב חסדא אמר רבי זירא אמר רבי ירמיה אמר
רבי מאיר אמר רב רבי מאיר היא. amar Rav Chisda amar Rabbi
Zeira amar Rabbi Yirmeya amar Rabbi Meir amar Rav Rabbi Meir hi.
It's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir דאמר בית דין מייתין ולא ציבור. d'amar
beis din maytin v'lo tzibur. The obligation is on the בית דין.
beis din. הילכך מת אחד מן הציבור חייבין דהא קיימי כולהו בית
דין. hilkach meis echad min hatzibur chayavin deha kaymi kulhu beis din.
If one of the ציבור tzibur dies, they're not the בעלים be'alim
over it, so the whole בית דין beis din is around, so
you still bring it. Okay,
because בית דין beis din is the ones that are obligated and
it's their
קרבן. korban. מת אחד מבית דין פטורין דהוה ליה חטאת שמת אחד
מן השותפין ומשום הכי פטורין. meis echad mibeis din pturin d'hava leh
chatas shemeis echad min hashutfin umishum hachi pturin. It's one of the
owners of the חטאת chatas died and therefore they're exempt. Now רש"י
Rashi points out because then it becomes a חטאת שמתו בעליה, chatas
shemeyisu be'aleha, right? And that normal principle. So pause for a second
point out, first of all רש"י Rashi says there's really not an
idea of a שותפות shutfus by חטאת. chatas. You normally can't say
to your friend, hey, we both did this sin of a חלב,
chelev, let's bring a חטאת בשותפות. chatas b'shutfus. But there are a
few places where the תורה Torah speaks about a group that brings
a חטאת. chatas. One would be the בית דין, beis din, you
know, the other we're going to see is the חטאת chatas on
behalf of the כהנים Kohanim that is brought on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Okay, so that's sort of being termed here שותפות shutfus because
it doesn't want to use the term קהל. kahal. It's not the
entire community, it's on behalf of a group. Okay, so so the
גמרא Gemara says it works for רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. It's the
בית דין beis din that's חייב, chayav, so if one of them
dies, then it's a חטאת שמתו chatas shemeisu some of its owners
and you can't bring that as a קרבן. korban. Now, what would
be according to all the other opinions, you know, רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, רבי יהודה... Rabbi Yehuda... Yehuda, that the ציבור tzibur are the
ones who bring? Would they say if one of the ציבור tzibur
dies you can't bring it because it's מתו בעליה? mesu be'aleha? So
presumably the answer is absolutely not. It's what we said before, אין
ציבור מתה. ein tzibur mesa. Just because some of its members die,
especially if it's a minority of the members, but whatever, it's still
fundamentally the entire ציבור. tzibur. The ציבור tzibur is this corporate entity
unit. Okay. So that's a hanging question, but certainly if we say
that you're exempt when one of the בית דין beis din die,
that really works only for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who says that
בית דין beis din are the owners. מתקיף לה רב יוסף, maskif
lah Rav Yosef, so Rav Yosef challenged this, ונוקמה כרבי שמעון, venukmah
k'Rabbi Shimon, how about Rabbi Shimon? דאמר בית דין עם הציבור, d'amar
beis din im hatzibur, that says you both, the ציבור tzibur brings
their קרבן korban and בית דין beis din brings its קרבן. korban.
So how would it work? מת אחד מן הציבור חייבין שאין ציבור
מתה. mes echad min hatzibur chayavin she'ein tzibur mesa. So here we
have the answer to that. If one of the ציבור tzibur dies,
the ציבור tzibur still brings it because as רב פפא Rav Papa
said, as we've said, the ציבור tzibur always continues on. Different people,
but it continues on. So the ציבור's tzibur's קרבן korban will always
be brought. Doesn't matter if people of the ציבור tzibur die, it's
still the
ציבור. tzibur. שאין ציבור מתה. she'ein tzibur mesa. מת אחד מבית דין
פטורין כדאמרן, mes echad mibeis din pturin kedamaran, but when one of
the בית דין beis din die they're exempt, like we said. That
wasn't like a corporation. Another way to think about this is like
we have now, the legal entity of a corporation. The people who
are the shareholders or whatever, the corporation as an entity still exists.
The ציבור tzibur still exists. Okay, the problem is that הלכה halacha
doesn't recognize corporations. הלכה halacha can only recognize שותפות, shutfus, so real
partnership where each member matters and each member is seen as the
part owner. So that's actually the shift here that the גמרא's Gemara's
making. The קהל, Kahal, the entire ציבור, tzibur, that's like a corporation.
We can accept that that continues on, doesn't matter if people die.
But the בית דין, beis din, that's not an abstract entity of
a בית דין. beis din. That's specifically those individuals. They are the
בעלים be'alim of that קרבן. korban. And therefore, if one of them
dies, the קרבן korban cannot be brought. So it works just as
well for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon as רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. כדאמרן,
kedamaran,
like we said, דחטאת שותפין היא, d'chatas shutfim hi, because it's a
חטאת chatas of שותפין, shutfim, meaning not of ציבור, tzibur, of a
group of individuals but not of ציבור. tzibur. אמר ליה אביי, amar
lei Abaye, so Abaye said, שמעינן ליה לרבי שמעון דאמר חטאת שותפין
אינה מתה. shaminan lei l'Rabbi Shimon d'amar chatas shutfim einah mesa. No
no, it can't be Rabbi Shimon, because Rabbi Shimon says that even
when you're talking about a small group, this idea applies, not only
when you're talking about a whole ציבור, tzibur, that if one of
the members of that group dies, the חטאת chatas is still okay.
How do you know this? דתניא, d'tanya,
we taught a ברייתא. braisa. פר ושעיר של יום הכפורים שאבדו והפריש
אחרים תחתיהם. par v'sair shel Yom HaKippurim she'avdu v'hifrish acherim tachtechem. Okay,
so you lost the פר par and שעיר sair you would bring,
you would sprinkle the blood in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kedashim of
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. They got lost, one of them got lost,
both of them got lost, and you brought substitutes.
The פר par was brought on behalf of the כהנים. kohanim.
And then והפריש אחרים תחתיהם ימותו כולם. v'hifrish acherim tachtechem yamosu kulam.
And then you find the ones that you had lost. You have
to let them die. It's a חטאת chatas not here of מתו
בעליה, mesu be'aleha, but שנתכפרו בעליה באחר. sheniskapru be'aleha b'acher. The owners,
the כהנים, kohanim, עם ישראל, Am Yisrael, their atonement was now brought
through this, the substitutes that were designated. And therefore these חטאות chatas
which were designated, the atonement was already brought for that sin, נתכפרו
באחר, niskapru b'acher, and therefore you're going to have to let them
die.
That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים
ירעו. Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Shimon omrim yir'u. No, you let them graze.
Why? לפי שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. lefi she'ein chatas tzibur mesa. So
now again, this is a shifting between this broad principle that the
ציבור tzibur doesn't die, or specific הלכה halacha by חטאת. chatas. And
they say, when it's a חטאת ציבור, chatas tzibur, we don't let
it die. And therefore you let it graze until it gets a
blemish and then you redeem it and so on. So that's a
case where you can't use the thing itself because the atonement was
already achieved through another animal. But if once you don't have the
principle that a חטאת ציבור chatas tzibur dies, or the principle is
a חטאת ציבור chatas tzibur does not die, so then in our
case, since the other 70 members of the בית דין beis din
are still alive, just because one of them is dead, חטאת ציבור
chatas tzibur doesn't die. You don't let it die. That principle does
not apply with ציבור. tzibur. And they can go ahead and continue
to bring it even though one of their members has died. So
the גמרא Gemara says this idea, it's true, it's nice conceptually to
say if one of the ציבור tzibur dies, the ציבור tzibur still
exists, they bring their חטאת, chatas, but if one of the בית
דין beis din dies, then you don't have all of the owners
and they wouldn't bring their חטאת. chatas. That in theory could work
for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon just says
even if you have a group like here, like by יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, you had the כהנים, kohanim, and he still applied the
principle of חטאת ציבור. chatas tzibur. So similarly if you have this
group of the בית דין, beis din, presumably he would apply this
principle of חטאת ציבור chatas tzibur and say that you could still
go ahead and bring. So therefore the ברייתא braisa can only be
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר ליה רב יוסף, amar lei
Rav Yosef,
so Rav Yosef says, כהנים קאמרת, kohanim kaamart, one minute, you cannot
compare the fact that Rabbi Shimon applies the phrase... case ציבור tzibur
to the כהנים kohanim of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and to their
קרבן korban and their קרבן ציבור korban tzibur to the idea of
a בית דין. Beis Din. שאני כהנים דאיקרו קהל. Shani kohanim de'ikru
kahal. כהנים Kohanim themselves are a type of a קהל, kahal, a
type of a community, a recognized entity. דכתיב על הכהנים ועל כל
עם הקהל יכפר. Dechsiv al hakohanim ve'al kol am hakahal yichaper. On
the כהנים kohanim and all the people of the קהל. kahal. So
the fact that the קהל kahal and its parallel means that the
כהנים kohanim themselves are considered a קהל. kahal. Okay, so yes, it's
true that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says the חטאת chatas of a
ציבור tzibur is treated differently and that he applies that term to
the כהנים, kohanim, but that does not prove that he would apply
that term to the בית דין. Beis Din. Okay,
so therefore he might, you know, genuinely say that the בית דין,
Beis Din, if one of them dies, does not, cannot bring the
קרבן. korban. אלא מעתה Ela me'ata says the גמרא, Gemara, one minute,
if that's true, you're going to tell me that כהנים kohanim are
קהל kahal and he applies that term to כהנים, kohanim, so ניתו
פר בהוראה? neisu par behorah? Why did we only mention twelve tribes?
We should have mentioned thirteen tribes. Okay, we now have כהנים kohanim
are also a קהל. kahal. וכי תימא הכי נמי, Vechi seima hachi
nami, that's true, they would do that for רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon,
so טפי להו שבטים? tafi lehu shvatim? Then you'll have too many
tribes because רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon only mentioned twelve tribes. So it
cannot be that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon considers the כהנים kohanim like
a tribe by itself. אלא אמר רב אחא בריה דרבי יעקב, Ela
amar Rav Acha brei deRebbi Yaakov, top of ו' עמוד ב', vov
amud beis, בריה דרבי יעקב, brei deRebbi Yaakov, שבטו של לוי לא
איקרי קהל. Shivto shel Levi lo ikri kahal. Fine, you're right. לוי
Levi and similarly the כהנים kohanim are not a קהל. kahal. How
do we know that? דכתיב הנני מפרך והרביתיך ונתתיך לקהל עמים, Dechsiv
hinni mafrach vehirbisicha unesaticha lakahal amim, ונתתי את הארץ הזאת לזרעך אחריך
לאחוזת עולם. Venasati es ha'aretz hazos lezaracha acharecha la'achuzas olam. I will
give you to קהל עמים kahal amim and remember that's where we
learned that one שבט shevet is called a קהל kahal because that
is referring to בנימין. Binyamin. And the end of the פסוק posuk
says, and this land will be given as an inheritance. כל שיש
לו אחוזה איקרי קהל. Kol sheyesh lo achuza ikri kahal. Anybody that
has a portion of the land is recognized as a קהל, kahal,
is like a mini, you know, ציבור. tzibur. Sort of very much
like this whole thing like the United States, right? The individual states
and then the national government. So if you've got a piece of
the land, you're a קהל. kahal. If you have a state, you're
a קהל. kahal. כל שאין לו אחוזה לא איקרי קהל. Kol she'ein
lo achuza lo ikri kahal. And if you don't have an אחוזה,
achuza, you're not a קהל. kahal. So fine, you're right. The לויים
Levi'im are not a קהל, kahal, the כהנים kohanim are not a
קהל, kahal, and basically even without being called a קהל, kahal, רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon applies that idea of קרבן ציבור korban tzibur doesn't
die to כהנים kohanim even without trying to argue that they're a
type of a mini קהל. kahal. So similarly he would apply it
to the בית דין Beis Din as well. So fine. The fact
that רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says the כהנים kohanim that the קרבן
korban of כהנים kohanim is considered a חטאת ציבור, chatas tzibur, he
would also say that about the חטאת chatas of the בית דין
Beis Din and even if one of them died, you should still
be able to bring the קרבן. korban.
So if so, now the גמרא Gemara is going to work on
this question about are the לויים Levi'im really a tribe by themselves
or not? Because now we're arguing they're not, they're not called a
קהל. kahal. If so now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אם
כן חסרו להו י"ב שבטים? im kein chasru lehu yod bais shvatim?
So if the לויים Levi'im are not a tribe, you don't have
twelve tribes. Now we all know the answer to that, but before
the גמרא Gemara seems to have been thinking לויים Levi'im were a
tribe, but you were saying that the כהנים kohanim were also a
קהל, kahal, that would have gotten you thirteen. Now we're saying not
the לויים, Levi'im, not the כהנים, kohanim, so now the גמרא Gemara
says, okay, so now we're down to eleven. So we all know
the answer to that one. So אמר אביי אפרים ומנשה כראובן ושמעון
יהיו לי. Amar Abaye Efraim uMenashe keReuven veShimon yihyu li. יעקב Yaakov
says אפרים ומנשה Efraim uMenashe will be to me like ראובן ושמעון.
Reuven veShimon. They are the two tribes. And רמב"ן Ramban points out
that anywhere you look when the תורה Torah counts the tribes, you'll
have one of two things happening: either לוי Levi will be counted
or
אפרים ומנשה Efraim uMenashe will be counted and לוי Levi won't be
counted. The תורה Torah always gets to the number of twelve. In
some circumstances it recognizes לוי Levi as a separate tribe
and
counts אפרים ומנשה Efraim uMenashe as one, and in some circumstances it
doesn't and counts them as two, and you have to see each
circumstance why that makes sense, each case. Okay.
אמר רבא והכתיב בשם אחיהם יקראו בנחלתם. Amar Rava vehachsiv beshem acheihem
yikaru benachalasam. But one minute, that פסוק posuk says, what does it
mean that they're like ראובן ושמעון? Reuven veShimon? That they are called
with their brothers for the inheritance. לנחלה הוא דהוו כשבט ולא לדבר
אחר. Lenachaluh hu dehavu keshivet velo ledavar acher. Only for a portion
in the land, but for all other things ראובן ושמעון Reuven veShimon
are not two tribes. Which again goes against a lot of what
we know just reading חומש. Chumash. So the גמרא Gemara says ולא?
Velo? Are you telling me they're not called two tribes for any
other purpose other than a portion in the land? והא חלוקין בדגלים?
Veha chalukin bedegalim? But they have their own flags. You know, לוי's
Levi got an inner circle, you know, there in the you know
around the משכן, Mishkan, but the twelve tribes around the משכן Mishkan
are, you know, אפרים ומנשה Efraim uMenashe are two tribes. So the
גמרא Gemara says כנחלתן כך חנייתן. Kenachalasan kach chaniyasan. No, no, no,
we they established the encampment to correspond to the portion that they
would have you know that they would have in the land כדי
לחלוק כבוד לדגלים. Kedei lachlok kavod ledegalim.
In order to give honor to the flags. Not exactly sure what
that means, in order to give them respect and honor since. Getting
a portion in the land presumably means you therefore you deserve to
have recognition, so we're going to give you your own flag and
your own section here on the encampment. But that's essentially making them
a tribe. You know Rashi says it has to do with the
fact that the way they carried Yaakov's bier was the way he
arranged they were arranged around the המשכן, Mishkan, so maybe it means
giving honor for the way you know that אפרים ומנשה Efraim u'Menashe
carried his ארון, aron, you know, that's what's being done here. But
it's not exactly what the גמרא Gemara says. Once you're giving them
honor because they have a portion in the land and whatever and
making them one of the twelve tribes around the המשכן, Mishkan, you're
making them one of the twelve tribes.
So now the גמרא Gemara says וחלוקין בנשיאים, v'chalukin b'nesi'im, and look,
whenever you list נשיאים, nesi'im, you also get twelve and you also
get אפרים ומנשה Efraim u'Menashe separately. הוא לחלוק כבוד לנשיאים, Hu lachlok
kavod l'nesi'im,
that's to give honor to the נשיאים. nesi'im. It's a little circular.
What do you mean give honor to the נשיאים? nesi'im?
The other נשיאים nesi'im aren't being honored by the fact that you're
counting
אפרים ומנשה Efraim u'Menashe too. You're giving honor to אפרים ומנשה Efraim
u'Menashe that they should be counted among the נשיאים nesi'im and that
of course logically means because you're giving them all of the status
of a separate tribe. Anyway, דתניא, d'tanya, שלמה עשה שבעת ימי חנוכה,
Shlomo asa shivat yemei Chanukah, Shlomo made seven days of the establishment
of this is not the חנוכה Chanukah we have, this is you
know the חנוכה hachanukah of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ומה ראה
משה
לעשות
שנים עשר ימי חנוכה?
u'mah ra'ah
Moshe
la'asot shneim
asar yemei Chanukah? And so why didn't Moshe do twelve days of,
it's funny, you'd think you'd ask about Shlomo, but okay, why did
Moshe do twelve, you know, because he came later, but why did
Moshe do twelve days? כדי לחלוק כבוד לנשיאים, k'dei lachlok kavod l'nesi'im,
to give honor to the נשיאים nesi'im that each one should have
their own days. There were twelve days of the חנוכת המשכן. chanukas
haMishkan. Great, that's when you have the נשיאים nesi'im you give each
one a day for the חנוכת המשכן. chanukas haMishkan. It doesn't explain
why you separate off אפרים ומנשה Efraim u'Menashe as two נשיאים nesi'im
unless you are actually giving them status as a separate tribe. Anyway,
so that's basically the point. The גמרא Gemara sort of is a
little going back and forth with this issue about how do you
get twelve tribes, but as we you know the basic consensus conclusion
is that לוי Levi is not a tribe and אפרים ומנשה Efraim
u'Menashe are, although again sometimes תורה Torah does the numbering in different
ways. Anyway, all that was trying to figure out whether this idea
of חטאת ציבור chatas tzibur can apply not just to the entire
קהל, kahal, but can it even apply to a smaller group, can
it apply to the כהנים, Kohanim, can it apply to the בית
דין, Beis Din, you know are they also a type of a
corporate entity? And there might be a way to say the כהנים
Kohanim more than you know than the בית דין, Beis Din, but
we do have this idea of corporate entity and bringing a חטאת
chatas for a corporate entity has a different principle than for יחידים
yechidim and certainly in terms of the larger ציבור tzibur which has
been our focus, רב פפא's Rav Pappa teaching. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי הוי עלה? mai havei alah?
What was the upshot? Okay, in terms of this whole question about
you know רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and how he holds about the
חטאת chatas for the ציבור. tzibur. So let's take a look. מאי
הוי
עלה? mai havei alah?
I'm sorry, just lost my place.
תא שמע, ta shema, come in here, דתניא, d'tanya, רבי שמעון אומר,
Rabbi Shimon omer, חמש חטאות מתות. chamesh chata'os mesos. There are five
חטאות chata'os that die. That you know the principle is that five
types of different scenarios with a חטאת chatas you have to let
it die. ולד חטאת, vlad chatas, if a חטאת chatas was a
you know a female animal and it gave birth, then the child
has the status of a חטאת chatas but you can't bring it,
it's not designated for any particular חטא, cheit, so you have to
just put it in a pen
and
let it die. ותמורת חטאת, u'tmuras chatas, if you did a תמורה,
tmurah, you know this is in exchange of that, so the original
one keeps its קדושה kedushah but the other one also gets the
קדושה, kedushah,
and it's not designated for a particular חטא cheit so you have
to let it die. וחטאת שמתו בעליה, v'chatas she'mesu ba'aleha, if this
is what we've been talking about, if the owner died, so the
person who it's atoned for is meant to atone for is not
around, so you can't bring it on that person's behalf. וחטאת שנתכפרו
בעליה, v'chatas she'nitkapru ba'aleha, or like we were talking about in the
יום כיפור Yom Kippur scenario, if the owners, if another animal was
brought in its stead because it was lost for a period and
then it was found, okay but now the owners have already received
atonement, so it no longer can be brought on their behalf. וחטאת
שעברה שנתה, v'chatas she'avrah shnasah, if it's more than a year old
because it can only be brought when it is under a year.
Okay, by the way the mnemonic for that is ותמנה. v'timnah. ותמנה
היתה פילגש לאליפז בן עשו. V'Timnah hayetah pilegesh l'Elifaz ben Esav.
So ו vov is ולד, vlad, ת tav is תמורה, tmurah,
מ mem is מתו בעליה, mesu ba'aleha,
נ, nun, תמנה, timnah, is נתכפרו באחר, nitkapru b'acher, and then ה
hei is עברה שנתה, avrah shnasah, I guess it doesn't work but
at least sounds. Okay. וסימנא. v'simnah. Now we said like this: אי
אתה יכול לומר, i attah yachol lomar, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon continues,
ולד חטאת בציבור, vlad chatas b'tzibur, now ולד חטאת vlad chatas you'll
never get in a case of a ציבור tzibur why because שאין
ציבור מפרישים נקבה She'ein tzibbur mafrishim nekeiva because a ציבור, tzibbur,
because whenever the תורה Torah assigns a חטאת chatat for the ציבור,
tzibbur, it's always a, it's always a male. ואי אתה יכול לומר
תמורת חטאת בציבור Ve'ata yachol lomar tmurat chatat batzibbur and you won't
have the scenario of תמורה tmura by a ציבור's tzibbur חטאת, chatat,
שאין תמורה בציבור she'ein tmura batzibbur because תמורה tmura where the other
one becomes קדוש kadosh is only when a יחיד yachid does it.
If a ציבור, tzibbur, the גמרא, Gemara, the חז"ל Chazal understand that
the תורה's Torah category of תמורה tmura only applies to a יחיד.
yachid. If a ציבור tzibbur would try to do it, nothing would
happen. ואי אתה יכול לומר חטאת שמתו בעליה. Ve'ata yachol lomar chatat
shemetu ba'aleha. You can't have the case of מתו בעליה, metu ba'aleha,
why? בציבור, Batzibbur, שאין ציבור מתים. she'ein tzibbur metim. So you know,
we were ascribing this to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, but here it's
a ברייתא braita explicitly רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. A ציבור tzibbur doesn't
die, so you will never have the problem about ציבור מתה. tzibbur
meta. Okay. סיפא, Seifa, שנתכפרו בעליה ושעברה שנתה
לא שמענו. shenitkapru ba'aleha veshe'avrah shnatah lo shamanu. But now, so three
out of the five we know don't occur just במציאות bimtziut by
a ציבור. tzibbur. What about the other two? What about if it
was more than a year old or, they lost and they found
another one, like the יום כיפור Yom Kippur case, you know, and
then and then they lost, they brought another one, and then this
one was found. Will that apply to a ציבור? tzibbur? Will you
let it die or not let it die? The first three just
the whole realities don't occur. So the גמרא Gemara says לא שמענו.
lo shamanu. ימותו מן המפורש נלמד? Yamutu min hamforash nilmad? Maybe those
will follow the normal הלכה halacha by a חטאת chatat that you
can't use and you have to let it die. אמרת, Amarta, ימותו
מן המפורש נלמד. yamutu min hamforash nilmad. Let's learn what is, what
is, you know, not stated from what is explicit. מה מצינו בולד
חטאת ותמורת חטאת ושמתו בעליה ביחיד דברים אמורים. Ma matzinu bevlad chatat
utmurat chatat ushemetu ba'aleha beyachid devarim amurim.
The same way the first three clearly just by circumstance only apply
to cases of an individual
חטאת, chatat, ולא בציבור, velo batzibbur, and not communal, אף שנתכפרו בעליה
ושעברה שנתה ביחיד דברים אמורים ולא בציבור. af shenitkapru ba'aleha veshe'avrah shnatah
beyachid devarim amurim velo batzibbur. The same is true about the other
two, about over a year or נתכפרו בעליה. nitkapru ba'aleha. It would
only apply to a case of individual חטאת chatat and not a
case of a חטאת chatat of the ציבור. tzibbur. That has a
different הלכה. halacha. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara just ends and
asks the obvious question: וכי דנים אפשר משאי אפשר? Vechi danim efshar
meshei efshar? Wait a minute, you can't learn the other two from
the first three. It's not that the first three, the circumstances are
exist by a ציבור tzibbur and the הלכה halacha is it doesn't
die. The first three, they just don't occur in a ציבור. tzibbur.
So how can you learn from, so how can you infer from
that that the two cases which do occur in a ציבור, tzibbur,
the הלכה halacha of letting it die should not apply? So the
גמרא Gemara says רבי שמעון בחד מקום גמר. Rebbe Shimon bechad makom
gmar. In one place he does learn out. Now, that's the way
that sounds, it sounds like this is an exception, he does allow
you to learn it out in one place. But that's not the
way רש"י, Rashi, that's not very helpful, that's not the way רש"י
Rashi explains it. רש"י Rashi says that the principle of חטאות מתות
chatatot metot were all said like in the same place as one
group. Okay. We know that there are five חטאות מתות, chatatot metot,
actually four, one is a ספק, safek, but we didn't know which
one, so we say five. חמש חטאות מתות. Chamesh chatatot metot. Okay.
So רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon is saying, I know these are a
group, you know, if that, so therefore since the group does not
apply to a ציבור tzibbur because half of the circumstances don't apply,
the whole הלכה halacha doesn't apply. It only comes as a group
of five, and therefore it does not apply to a ציבור. tzibbur.
And you know, what this shows us is that when רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon said earlier by the case of, what do you call
it? By the case, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon holds of the principle
that חטאת מתה chatat meta does not apply to a ציבור. tzibbur.
So this shows us that when רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon said that
the reason by the פר ושעיר par vesa'ir of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur that if you found another one you don't let it die
is based on the principle that a חטאת ציבור chatat tzibbur does
not, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon is of the position that a חטאת
ציבור chatat tzibbur does not die. Now what does this tell us,
you know, because that was not already explicit? Because you know, already
explicit in the previous ברייתא, braita, it wasn't אביי Abaye who said
it was a חטאת ציבור. chatat tzibbur. When it was talking about
פר ושעיר par vesa'ir of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it said רבי
אלעזר ורבי שמעון אמרו ירעו לפי שאין חטאת ציבור מתה. Rebbe Elazar
veRebbe Shimon amru yiru lefi she'ein chatat tzibbur meta. So what have
we learned out here that we didn't already know, that רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon is of the position of אין חטאת ציבור מתה? ein
chatat tzibbur meta? So the תוספות הרא"ש Tosafot HaRosh explains, ah, we
do know something. We know that they all have to come as
a unit, and therefore in any case of חטאת chatat of שותפים,
shutafim, again, like more than one, of a group, כהנים, kohanim, בית
דין, Beit Din, etc., so one of those things, one or two
of those things won't apply. You don't have a תמורה tmura by
שותפים. shutafim. You only have it by an individual. Okay. So as
soon as you don't have one of them, you don't have all
of them. That's what we're learning out. So, so therefore what we
learn from this is that according to רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon, the
idea of חטאת ציבור chatat tzibbur doesn't die, א, Aleph, חטאת ציבור
chatat tzibbur doesn't die, and ב Beis he holds that that applies
even to something that is not כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, even to
something that's a group, not even כהנים, kohanim, even a בית דין,
Beit Din, because as long as one of the things don't apply,
like תמורת חטאת tmurat chatat by circumstance, then the whole category does
not apply. Okay. So that's just in terms of this הלכה halacha
of חטאת מתה. chatat meta. But what I think is really interesting
for us is that the גמרא Gemara in the end, you know,
you have an explicit statement by רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon here that,
you know, and the גמרא Gemara keeps on going back to that,
that the ציבור tzibbur doesn't die, it's considered a continuity of the
ציבור. tzibbur. You could bring a כפרה kaparah even in a later
generation, okay, and an interesting question about whether you apply that same
concept to the בית דין, beis din, you know, or not, at
least for the idea of חטאת מתה. chatas meisa. הדרן עלך פרק
ראשון. Hadran alach perek rishon. That is the end of the first
פרק, perek, which is about the בית דין הגדול. beis din hagadol.
Now we'll just read the משנה mishna to get into the beginning
of the next פרק perek which is about the כהן, kohein, because
the Torah also says אשר נשיא יחטא asher nasi yecheta and it
learns out from the פסוקים pesukim that when you are dealing with
the כהן גדול, kohein gadol, it's similar to the בית דין, beis
din, it has to come with a הוראה, hora'ah, but it's his
own הוראה hora'ah for his own action. So a כהן גדול kohein
gadol does not if he just normally does a שוגג, shogeig, he
doesn't bring a קרבן, korban, okay, if he makes a mistake. If
he פסק paskens wrongly he doesn't bring a קרבן, korban, only if
he פסק paskens wrongly about something and acts on it for himself.
He's both the בית דין beis din and the קהל, kahal, and
only when those two come together is he going to bring a
קרבן. korban. So let's just read the first section of this. הורו
כהן משיח לעצמו, Horu kohein mashiach l'atzmo, if he פסק paskens for
himself that let's say חלב cheilev is permissible, שוגג ועשה שוגג, shogeig
ve'asah shogeig, he made a mistake when he פסק paskened and then
he followed his פסק, psak, מביא פר, meivi par, then he will
bring the ox, that is what the Torah says that he brings
for his קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, but it is only when these
two come together. שוגג ועשה מזיד, Shogeig ve'asah meizid, if he פסק
paskened by mistake but then did the עבירה aveira במזיד, bemeizid, so
obviously he won't bring a קרבן korban because the עבירה aveira was
במזיד. bemeizid. מזיד ועשה שוגג, Meizid ve'asah shogeig, if he פסק paskened
willfully incorrectly, but then he accidentally did the sin, so it's hard
to exactly match that up, but he willfully פסק paskened that a
certain type of a דם dam was permissible and then he accidentally
ate that דם dam and didn't realize he was eating it. But
the point is you don't have both components, פטור, patur, you're exempt.
So even when he does an עבירה בשוגג, aveira beshogeig, he's exempt
if it didn't follow his own פסק, psak, his own פסק psak
about that issue. שהוראת כהן משיח לעצמו כהוראת בית דין וציבור. Shehoras
kohein mashiach l'atzmo kehoras beis din vetzibur. Him פסק paskening for himself
is like the בית דין beis din and the ציבור tzibur and
you need both the פסק psak and the action. So we'll just
see the first part of this in the גמרא. gemara. שוגג ועשה
שוגג מביא פר פשיטא. Shogeig ve'asah shogeig meivi par peshita.
If he פסק paskens שוגג shogeig and the act שוגג, shogeig, of
course he's going to bring it. Now of course that was just
a set up for contrast to later in the משנה, mishna, but
let's see what the גמרא gemara says. אמר אביי הכא במאי עסקינן,
Amar Abaye hacha bemai asikin, what are we talking about? דהורה ושכח
מאיזה טעם הורה. Dehoreh veshachach mizeh ta'am horeh. He פסק paskened that
דם dam was מותר muttar but he forgot why he פסק paskened
it, okay,
and then he went ahead and he ate some דם. dam. ובשעה
שטעה אמר הריני עושה על דעת הוראתו, Ubesha'ah sheta'ah amar hareini oseh
al da'as hora'aso, and when he was about to drink the דם,
dam, he said, you know, I remember I פסק paskened דם dam
was מותר, muttar, I don't remember why, but I remember I פסק
paskened it and I trust myself in how I פסק paskened last
week and he drinks the דם. dam. דמהו דתימא כיון דאילו מתידע
ליה שמא הדר ביה, Demahu deiseima keivan de'ilu mityada leh shema hadar
bei, maybe that's not considered following your פסק, psak, because maybe if
you had remembered the reason why you had פסק paskened דם dam
was מותר muttar you would realize you had made a mistake. So
you're not really fully following your פסק psak because you're not really
fully aware and remembering how and why you פסק. paskened. כמזיד דמי,
Kemeizid dami, so maybe you're like a מזיד, meizid, meaning maybe you're
acting on your own and not basing it on your פסק, psak,
ולא לחייב, velo l'chayiv, and you would not be חייב chayav in
a קרבן, korban, קא משמע לן kamashma lan that that is considered
to be following your own פסק. psak. Okay, we will end with
this for now.