Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"ד. lamed daled.
We start in the middle of ל"ג עמוד ב'. lamed gimmel amud
bet. אמר
רבי אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar, I'm sorry,
which is yes,
we start
with
ולהוי נמי שנייות, ulhavi nami sheniyot, it is line that starts with
the word שנייות sheniyot and it is about 20 lines before the
end of the דף. daf. So the גמרא Gemara is trying to
deal with the fact that the משנה Mishnah says that because if
blood doesn't come out of an animal, the meat is not susceptible
for טומאה, tumah,
and therefore even if your hands are טמא, tamei, the standard טומאה
tumah of hands which is a שני, sheni, the meat is okay.
The גמרא's Gemara question is, who cares if they are or are
not susceptible, the meat is חולין chullin and חולין chullin cannot become
anything more than a שני, sheni, even חולין chullin food. So the
גמרא Gemara has dealt with a couple of answers, the most recent
answer is it's a circumstance where your hands are ראשון rishon and
it's according to the approach that hands can become a ראשון rishon
under certain circumstances. They were put into the house that had צרעת.
tzaraat. And therefore the meat could become a שני. sheni. So now
the גמרא Gemara continues, ולהוי נמי שנייות, ulhavi nami sheniyot, even if
your hands were a שני, sheni, the גמרא Gemara says wait, we
have another answer, דאשמעינן ליה לרבי עקיבא דאמר שני עושה שלישי בחולין.
de'ashminan leh le'Rebbe Akiva de'amar sheni oseh shelishi bechullin.
רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva actually says that חולין chullin can become a
שלישי, shelishi, violating all of our standard assumptions that only תרומה terumah
and קדשים kodshim can be a שלישי. shelishi. Maybe it's רבי עקיבא
Rebbe Akiva who says חולין chullin can become a שלישי. shelishi. How
do you know this? דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה: Mishnah:
בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא, bo bayom darash Rebbe Akiva, on that
day רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva explicated. This was the day when רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה Rebbe Elazar ben Azariah became a נשיא. nasi.
And anytime the גמרא Gemara says בו ביום bo bayom it is
referring to that day. So on that day רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva
explicated the following teaching: בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא, bo bayom darash
Rebbe Akiva, וכל כלי חרס, vechol kli cheres,
the verse says any pottery vessel that a bug, you know, a
rodent falls into, the pottery vessel becomes טמא, tamei, and anything in
the pottery vessel becomes טמא, tamei, יטמא. yitma. Why? Because the rodent
makes the pottery vessel a ראשון, rishon, the rodent is an אב,
av, makes the pottery vessel a ראשון, rishon, and the pottery vessel
makes the food inside of it a שני. sheni. So that's what
we know that food can become a שני. sheni. Okay, so what
did רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva say?
וכל כלי חרס, vechol kli cheres, anything inside of it יטמא yitma
will become טמא, tamei, יטמא, yitma, so טמא לא נאמר, tamei lo
ne'emar, 'is tamei' the verse does not say, אלא יטמא, ela yitma,
shall become טמא. tamei. So now we're making the following דרשה: drasha:
לטמא אחרים, letamei acherim, it will make other things טמא. tamei. לימד
על כיכר שני שהוא עושה שלישי בחולין. Limed al kikar sheni shehu
oseh shelishi bechullin. So what's in the pottery vessel becomes טמא tamei
but יטמא yitma is future-oriented, so he is reading it that this
food will make other food טמא. tamei. So this food is a
שני sheni means it'll make other food טמא, tamei, so you see
that a שני sheni can make a שלישי. shelishi. So here's a
perfect solution. Why does our משנה Mishnah speak about the possibility of
the meat becoming טמא? tamei? Because it's רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva that
says that חולין chullin can become a שלישי. shelishi.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא הני מילי בטומאה דאורייתא. dilma
hani milei betumah de'oraita. Maybe when did רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva say
that? That was about biblical טומאה. tumah. That there it's true, biblical
טומאה tumah שני sheni can make a שלישי. shelishi. אבל בדרבנן לא
אמר. Aval bederabbanan lo amar. We never know that he said that
by the rabbinic טומאה tumah when rabbis said that your hands are
a שני, sheni, it's a purely rabbinic institution, we never said that
he gave it that weight that it could make something
a שלישי. shelishi. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, אבל
בדרבנן לא
אמר,
aval
bederabbanan lo amar, לא. lo. אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar
Rebbe Elazar amar Rebbe Oshaya, so now we're going to yet another
answer. So until now the answer has been that the hands were
a ראשון rishon a special case. Here's another answer, אמר רבי אלעזר
אמר רבי אושעיא, amar Rebbe Elazar amar Rebbe Oshaya, הכא
בחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש עסקינן. hacha bechullin shena'asu al taharat hakodesh
askinan. Here we are talking about that חולין chullin was done with
the, that the חולין chullin was treated as if it were sacrifices.
So we know that in the time of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and apparently even afterwards, there were people that ate all of
their food, even their non-sanctified food, as if it were תרומה terumah
just to be safe for circumstances in which they would be eating
תרומה. terumah. Or similarly, they ate all of their food as if
it were sacrifices. Now what would be the status of that food?
Would it have the same type of טומאה tumah as תרומה terumah
and sacrifices? That is debated. So this is the question. So the
answer is maybe our case is בחולין שנעשו על bechullin shena'asu al
We are dealing with חולין chulin that are made with the sanctity
of sacrifices, that's how they're treated. ודלא כרבי יהושע, udelo k'rabbi yehoshua,
not like Rabbi Yehoshua. Because now we're going to see a debate
when food is treated with the sanctity of sacrifices, does it have
the same type of טומאה tumah or not. It looks like they
are having some trouble over there. I don't know what exactly the
problem is. Seems like they got logged, I don't know. Anyway. Okay,
let's keep on going. Okay, so let's take a look.
Where are we?
Okay.
I'm sorry, just lost my place. All right, keep on going. So
על טהרת הקודש עסקינן, al taharat hakodesh askinan, ודלא כרבי יהושע, udelo
k'rabbi yehoshua, דתניא, detanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, האוכל, ha'ochel,
I'm sorry,
I'm just being distracted because it looks like they're having problems there.
Okay.
דתניא, detanya, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, האוכל אוכל ראשון, ha'ochel
ochel rishon, if somebody eats food that is a ראשון, rishon, ראשון,
rishon, the person himself becomes a ראשון. rishon. Normally if you touch
something that was טומאה, tumah, you would go down a level. So
if you touched ראשון, rishon, you would become a שני. sheni. But
if you ate the food that was a ראשון, rishon, you become
a ראשון. rishon. שני שני, sheni sheni, if you ate food that
was a שני, sheni, you become a שני. sheni. So here's the
perfect example of the principle you are what you eat. Okay? So
although normally if you touch it you go down a level, rabbinically
if you eat the food you become the same level of the
food itself. שלישי שלישי, shlishi shlishi, and if you eat food that's
a third level, you become a third level. Now, third level normally
is only by תרומה, terumah, but if you ate that food, you
become that level. For רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, Rabbi Yehoshua
says no, generally you go down a level. So let's take a
look.
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, האוכל אוכל ראשון ושני, ha'ochel ochel
rishon v'sheni, שני, sheni, you
become a שני. sheni. So you go down a level, you go
down to a שני. sheni. If it's a שני, sheni, you stay
at the level. שלישי, shlishi, if you ate food that's a שלישי,
shlishi, שני, sheni, then interestingly enough, you go up to a שני.
sheni. So basically, whatever type of food you eat, you become a
שני. sheni. We'll see why in a minute.
And now it is
saying לקודש ואין שני לתרומה. l'kodesh v'ein sheni l'terumah. Now that is
for if you were now to eat sacrifices, you would be considered
a שני. sheni. But if you're going to eat תרומה, terumah, then
you don't have any status of a שני. sheni. So it's all
very complicated. But for right now we're going to bracket some of
this question of going up a level, down a level, is it
for תרומה, terumah, is it for קודש, kodesh, and we're going to
focus on this last line. ובחולין שנעשו על טהרת תרומה. ub'chulin she'nasu
al taharat terumah. Now when is it that if you eat this
type of, you, if you ate a שלישי shlishi you became a
שלישי? shlishi? What type of food did you eat that was a
שלישי? shlishi? Normally the only food that can be a שלישי shlishi
is תרומה terumah or sacrifices. But comes רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and
says, no, even if you ate חולין chulin that was just treated
as with the purity of תרומה, terumah, it has the same type
of טומאה tumah as תרומה. terumah. So if you're treating your חולין
chulin as תרומה, terumah, it can become a שלישי. shlishi. Now the
גמרא Gemara makes the following inference. על טהרת תרומה אין על טהרת
הקודש לא, al taharat terumah in al taharat hakodesh lo, that only
when you're treating your food like תרומה terumah does it have the
status of תרומה. terumah. But if you're treating your, if you're treating
your food like קודש, kodesh, it does not have that status and
it cannot become טמא tamei in that way. Which seems a little
bizarre. If you're treating it more severely, why does it not become
טמא tamei in a similar way? So let's take a look. קסבר,
kasavar, he is of the opinion, חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש לית
בהו שלישי, chulin she'nasu al taharat hakodesh leis behu shlishi, that if
you treat your חולין chulin like, like sacrifices, it does not become
a שלישי. shlishi. Only if you treat it like תרומה. terumah. Now
what's the logic? On the one hand, you're treating it more severely,
so it should definitely have become טמא. tamei. On the other hand,
maybe it is a little bit crazy to be treating your normal
non-sanctified food like, like sacrifices. I mean, nobody would eat sacrifices unless
you were in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or at least ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. So maybe it is so crazy for a normal person to
treat their food like sacrifices, it has no הלכה halacha significance. You
want to treat your food like תרומה terumah because sometimes people eat
תרומה terumah at home, כהנים kohanim would always eat תרומה terumah at
home, and bread of תרומה terumah could get confused with other bread.
Fine. That makes a certain amount of sense and it would have
הלכה halacha significance. So if you treat your food like תרומה, terumah,
it'll get the holiness, the sanctity, not sanctity, the טהרה, tahara, it,
the טהרה tahara and טומאה tumah laws of תרומה. terumah. But like
sacrifices, that's so crazy it's irrelevant. Okay, so now what have we
said? We've said that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua here said that if
you treat your food like sacrifices, it does not have follow the
law of טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah sacrifices. Only if you treat your
food like תרומה. terumah. We are assuming that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
disagrees, that since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer didn't say anything, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer would say whether you treat it like תרומה, terumah, whether
you treat it like sacrifices, it can get those various levels of
טומאה. tumah. So now how have we tried to deal with the
משנה Mishna that says... that this meat can become טמא השלישי? tamei
hashlishi? We said you've treated your meat like sacrifices, and it can
become טמא tamei like sacrifices, it can become a שלישי, Shlishi, but
that's not like רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua only
allows it when you treat stuff like תרומה, Terumah, not like sacrifices.
So now the גמרא Gemara asks the obvious question. The גמרא Gemara
says וליוקמה, v'liokma, so if that's the issue, but if you treat
it like תרומה Terumah everybody agrees, so וליוקמה בחולין שנעשו על טהרת
תרומה, v'liokma b'chullin shenaasu al taharat Terumah, top of ל"ד עמוד א'.
lamed daled amud aleph. Let's say we're talking about a case where
your חולין chullin was treated like תרומה, Terumah, not like sacrifice. So
you treated your meat as if it were תרומה Terumah and everybody
agrees then that it can get the level of טומאה tumah of
תרומה, Terumah, רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, and it would go even like
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. So the גמרא Gemara says לא סלקא דעתך,
lo salka daatach, that does not make sense. דקתני בשר, d'katni basar,
because what's the case of our משנה? Mishnah? Our case is meat.
No, meat can never be תרומה. Terumah. So if you try to
treat your meat like it were תרומה, Terumah, that would be so
absurd that there would be no הלכה halakha significance. So if it's
possible that your meat, your non-sanctified meat is given some type of
טומאה tumah טהרה tahara laws as if it were something else, it
could only be if you're treating it like sacrifice. That is a
relevant thing to be treating your meat like, but not like תרומה.
Terumah. דקתני בשר, d'katni basar, ואי בתרומה, ve'ee bitrumah, if you were
treating your meat like תרומה, Terumah, בשר בתרומה מיכא? basar bitrumah meika?
Since when do you ever have meat that's תרומה? Terumah? So if
you were treating it like that it would be absurd and wouldn't
have a status. The only thing we could be saying is talking
that you're treating your meat like it's a sacrifice. So the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, אלא מאי דקדשים, ela mai d'kodshim, so what
do you want to say? You're treating it like it's a sacrifice?
So חיה בקדשים מיכא? chaya b'kodshim meika? Remember our משנה Mishnah also
mentions חיה chaya like a deer. Deer is never a sacrifice, so
that's also absurd. So the גמרא Gemara says you know what, there
are degrees of absurd. בשר בבשר מחלף, basar b'basar michelaf, meat with
meat you get confused. So it's meaningful enough to treat all meat
as if it were sacrificial meat. That would be a meaningful enough
thing for people to do and that it would therefore have הלכה
halakha implications and the meat would then be able to be susceptible
for the same degree of טומאה. tumah. But בשר בפירי לא מחלף,
basar b'peiri lo michelaf, nobody's going to get confused between תרומה Terumah
types of products like flour and bread and fruit with meat. So
it's absurd to treat your meat like תרומה Terumah and it has
no הלכה halakha significance. So now what have we said? The problem
is how can the משנה Mishnah sort of consider the possibility that
the meat can become טמא? tamei? Meat can't be a שלישי shlishi
if it's חולין, chullin, and the answer is you're treating your meat
like it's sacrifices, and because that's the only meaningful thing to treat
your meat like, not as תרומה, Terumah, and it's the opinion, not
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, that says if you treat חולין chullin like
sacrifice that has הלכה halakha significance and it could become טמא tamei
and it could become a שלישי. shlishi. Okay. So now let's see
where we go from this. Now we're going to focus on exactly
the question of
does רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua really exclude this case? So אמר עולא,
amar Ulla, so עולא Ulla says
חבריא אמרין, chavraya amrin, my colleagues say or the people in the
בית מדרש Beis Medrash say בחולין שנעשו על טהרת הקודש דלא כרבי
יהושע, b'chullin shenaasu al taharat hakodesh d'lo k'Rabbi Yehoshua, that the משנה
Mishnah is talking that you're treating your meat like sacrifice, that's how
it can become טמא, tamei, but it's not the position of רבי
יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua only says when you treat
it like תרומה, Terumah, not like sacrifice. That's too far-fetched. ואנא אמינא,
ve'ana amina, but עולא Ulla says but I personally say רבי יהושע
היא, Rabbi Yehoshua hee, that even רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would agree
that when you treat things like sacrifices they also follow those laws.
דלא מיבעיא קאמר, d'lo mibaiya ka'amar, and it goes without saying is
what רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is saying. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua talked
about the תרומה Terumah case, but it would be all the more
so true if you were treated it more weightily and you treated
it like sacrifice. לא מיבעיא חולין שנעשו על טהרת קודש דחמירי דאית
בהו שלישי, lo mibaiya chullin shenaasu al taharat kodesh d'chamiri d'it behu
shlishi, it goes without saying that if you are treating your חולין,
chullin, your non-sanctified food, like sacrifices, the most weighty thing, that then
they have the הלכה halakha status as sacrifices דאית בהו שלישי d'it
behu shlishi and then they have third level טומאה. tumah. אלא אפילו
חולין שנעשו על טהרת תרומה, ela afilu chullin shenaasu al taharat Terumah,
even if you only treated them like תרומה, Terumah, which is not
as weighty as sacrifices, נמי אית בהו שלישי, nami it behu shlishi,
they also follow the status of תרומה Terumah and can become a
שלישי. shlishi. So yes, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua talked about a case
of treating them like תרומה, Terumah, but what do you interpret? Do
you mean that if you treat them like sacrifices that's so far-fetched
it's absurd, it's nothing? Or do you say if you treat it
like sacrifices that's so much more weighty that certainly it has significance?
So now what have we done? We have come up with a
good explanation of the משנה. Mishnah. You're treating your meat like sacrifices
and therefore they can become a שלישי. shlishi. And now the only
question is who says when you treat חולין chullin like sacrifices it
follows those laws? One view was not רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, only
if you treat it like תרומה, Terumah, and the other is even
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would agree. And now we're going to exactly
explore that question about רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua position. So let's... So
let's take a look. מאן חבריא? Man chavraya? Who are the colleagues
that say that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua only says if you treat
it like תרומה? terumah? So
רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah Bar Bar Channah, it's רבה בר בר
חנה. Rabbah Bar Bar Channah. דאמר De'amar רבה בר בר חנה Rabbah
Bar Bar Channah אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, מה הדרו רבי
אליעזר ורבי יהושע להדדי? Ma hadru Rabbi Eliezer ve'Rabbi Yehoshua la'hadadi? What
did רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua say back
to one another in their debate? And now we have to get
into the heart of the debate about what happens when you eat
טמא tamei food, what does your status become? So what was their
back and forth? Because the משנה, Mishnah, the ברייתא Braitah or the
משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah just quoted their positions. It never quoted
the logic behind it. So here he's going to say what he
either imagines or has a tradition was that they exchanged with one
another in terms of what their reasons were. Let's take a look.
So אמר לו רבי אליעזר לרבי יהושע, Amar lo Rabbi Eliezer l'Rabbi
Yehoshua, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua.
Now remember רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position is: you are what you
eat. You eat a ראשון, rishon, you become a ראשון. rishon. You
eat a שני, sheni, you become a שני. sheni. So what's behind
that position? So here's what's behind it. מצינו אוכל חמור מן האוכל.
Matzinu okhel chamur min ha'okhel. We have found, now actually unfortunately the
word אוכל okhel in Hebrew can mean eater and it can mean
food, so in the next line actually it's going to be clearer,
it's going to use the word מאכל. ma'achal. I'm going to translate
one as מאכל ma'achal which means food. We have found that the
eater can have an even more strict status than the food that
he is eating. Where do you find that if you eat food,
your status can even be more severe? דאילו נבלת עוף טהור, De'ilu
nivlat of tahor, that very famous bizarre case of the carcass of
a dead kosher bird. What's the story of that? It does not
communicate טומאה tumah through touch. It only communicates טומאה tumah through eating.
So therefore what is the status? בחוץ לא מטמא, Bachutz lo metamei,
if it's outside of your body and you touch it, no טומאה.
tumah. ואילו אוכלה, Ve'ilu okhla, if you eat it, מטמא בגדים בבית
הבליעה, metamei begadim beiv beit habliyah, then you become a ראשון rishon
and it makes your clothes a ראשון, rishon, it makes you טמא,
tamei, everything on you as you swallow. So you see, the food
itself, touching the food does nothing. Eating it is more powerful. So
by loose analogy we will say that if you have food that's
a ראשון, rishon, so if you touch it, you become a שני.
sheni. Well not you, people don't become a שני, sheni, but whatever,
if something touches it, if food touches it, it becomes a שני.
sheni. If you eat it, it's even worse and you become a
ראשון. rishon. So that's his principle. Eating is worse than touching. Touching
goes down a level. Eating stays at the same level.
Okay, that's a nice little proof.
ואילו אוכלה מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה ואנו איך לא נעשה אוכל כמאכל?
Ve'ilu okhla metamei begadim beiv beit habliyah ve'anu eich lo na'aseh okhel
kemach'al? Therefore how should we not treat the eater like the food?
That at least you have the same level of טומאה tumah as
the food that you eat. So that's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position
and a very easy position to remember. Now רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
remember says that pretty much everybody becomes a שני. sheni. If you
eat ראשון rishon or שני sheni or שלישי, shlishi, you become a
שני. sheni. So let's take a look at that.
So רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, so what's first of all how does
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua reject this proof? So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
says, מנבלת עוף טהור לא גמרינן. Minivlat of tahor lo gamrinan. No,
you can't learn out from the carcass of a dead bird. דחידוש
הוא, De'chiddush hu, the whole thing is a crazy חידוש chiddush because
we never find that if you touch something טמא tamei you do
not become טמא. tamei. If you touch an אב הטומאה, av hatumah,
an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, source of טומאה, tumah, always communicates through
touch. And this bird does not communicate טומאה tumah through touch. So
therefore this bird is a completely bizarre exception and we cannot learn
any principle from it. So forget the bird. Okay, so דחידוש הוא.
de'chiddush hu. אלא, Ella, so therefore what principle is he going to
go by? מצינו שהמאכל חמור מן האוכל, Matzinu she'hamach'al chamur min ha'okhel,
the reverse. Food usually has greater טומאה tumah than the person who
eats it. דאילו מאכל כביצה, De'ilu ma'achal ke'beitzah, now how do you
know that? Food כביצה, ke'beitzah, food can only become טמא tamei if
it receives טומאה tumah if it is the size of an egg.
Okay, there's also a question about how big it needs to communicate
טומאה, tumah, but if it's the size of an egg it becomes
טמא tamei if it touches something טמא. tamei. ואוכל, Ve'okhel, an eater,
what how much food does he need to eat to become טמא?
tamei? עד דאכיל כחצי פרס. Ad de'achil kechatzi pras. Now eating food
that it makes you טמא tamei in a different way than if
you touch it, and there's ways you can eat without touching like
somebody sticks the food down your throat because the touching of the
throat of the inside of the body doesn't count as touching. So
the idea that eating is a way of becoming טמא tamei is
purely rabbinic. רש"י Rashi indicates that there's one approach that it's biblical,
but in general we assume it's purely rabbinic. Now one of the
things that the rabbis said is how much do you have to
eat that it's considered a real eating? So although we know normally
eating is like a כזית kezayit is a technical eating, but here
it's more closer to eating a meal. So a פרס, pras, a
half of a loaf of bread, is normally considered to be a
meal. כדי אכילת פרס, Kedei achilat pras, the time it takes to
eat half a loaf of bread. Here it's half of that, חצי
פרס. chatzi pras. חצי פרס Chatzi pras is basically שני ביצים, she'ne
beitzim, two eggs' worth, which is about ארבע כזיתים, arba k'zaytim, four
כזיתים. kzaytim. Okay, so that's how much food you need to eat
in order to become טמא. tamei. Twice. two כביצים. kabaytzim. So you
see eating, it requires bigger quantities than just the food itself, than
the food becoming טמא. tamei. So therefore, it's harder to become טמא
tamei through the process of eating. So that shows that, you know,
the food itself is stricter. Again, it's a very loose analogy because
in one case the food is receiving the טומאה, tumah, here you're
receiving the טומאה tumah anyway. That's his analogy. You see the food
is stricter. So therefore, ואנו איך נעשה אוכל כמאכל? ve'anu heich na'aseh
ochel k'ma'achal? How can we treat the eater like the food? The
food is stricter than the eater, and therefore, the eater has to
go down a level and cannot be the same level of the
food that he or she is eating. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, so
how would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer respond back to that? טומאה משיעורים
לא גמרינן. tumah m'shiurim lo gamrinan. No, you cannot learn טומאה tumah
from size. Quantities and size is not a direct index into how
strict or lenient something is. Each one has its logic. So for
example, the logic of eating is what's considered a meal or half
a meal. That's not necessarily the same logic of what's considered food,
but that is does not is not an index into which is
stricter and which is more lenient. ועוד, ve'od, and now we're going
to get to the heart of רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua's position, which
is a ראשון rishon and a שני, sheni, if you eat either,
makes you a שני. sheni. So like, make up your mind. Either
you go down a level or you don't go down a level.
So let's take a look. ועוד לדבריך, ve'od l'dvarecha, according to your
approach, says רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, שאתה
אומר ראשון שני יפה אמרת, she'ata omer rishon sheni yafeh amarta, that
you say if you eat a ראשון, rishon, you become a שני,
sheni, that makes sense. Personally, I feel you are what you eat.
You feel you go down a level. You eat a ראשון, rishon,
you become a שני, sheni, that I get. But here's my
question. שני למה שני שני למה? sheni lama sheni sheni lama? This
is a real tongue twister, this גמרא. gemara. Try to get somebody
to parse this גמרא gemara without context. Okay, so anyway, but if
you eat a שני, sheni, you become a שני, sheni, why is
that? Why aren't you going down a level? So אמר לו, amar
lo, no, מצינו שהשני עושה שני על ידי משקין. matzinu she'hasheni oseh
sheni al yedei mashkin. Sometimes a שני sheni can make some other
food a שני, sheni, how, through liquids? חז"ל Chazal generally, for whatever,
a lot of this I'm not going into all of the reasons,
but they basically gave liquids a powerful status that whatever טומאה tumah
touches a liquid, the liquid becomes a ראשון. rishon. Okay, so a
שני sheni or even a שלישי shlishi in some circumstances touches a
liquid, the liquid becomes a ראשון. rishon. So if you have a
food that's a שני sheni and this food now touches liquid, the
liquid is a ראשון. rishon. This liquid now touches food, so this
food now, food number two, the apple touches liquid, the liquid touches
an orange. So the liquid becomes a ראשון, rishon, the orange now
touching the ראשון rishon becomes a שני. sheni. So if your apple
touched your orange and there was a liquid on your orange, so
your apple, which is a שני, sheni, would have made your orange
a שני sheni via the liquid, which upgraded everything to a ראשון.
rishon. So therefore he's saying yes, normally you go down a level.
Basically, his principle is you treat eating food like touching food, you
go down a level, but sometimes when it comes to touching a
שני, sheni, things will stay at the שני sheni level. So since
sometimes touching a שני sheni will stay at a שני sheni level
if there's liquid present, so eating a שני, sheni, you stay at
a שני sheni level. So he's actually saying I'm very consistent. I
treat eating like touching. You eat a ראשון, rishon, you become a
שני, sheni, like if you touched it. You eat a שני, sheni,
you also become a שני sheni because sometimes touching a שני sheni
stays at a שני sheni level when there is liquid present. Okay.
ועוד, ve'od, now תוספות Tosafot takes out the words אמר לו, amar
lo, and he skips to the words just דתנן, d'tnan, one line
down. And we're going to read it like תוספות, Tosafot, which makes
it simpler. דתנן, d'tnan, and here's the evidence that water, liquid, has
that effect, because we taught in the משנה, mishnah, כל הפוסל בתרומה,
kol haposel b'trumah, anything that invalidates תרומה, trumah, meaning a שני, sheni,
which makes תרומה trumah into a
שלישי, shlishi, מטמא משקין, metamei mashkin, makes liquid טמא tamei להיות תחילה,
lihyot techila, to be a ראשון, rishon, תחילה techila of the first.
So there you see when a שני sheni touches liquid, it makes
it a ראשון. rishon. So if a שני sheni touches food that
has liquid on it, a שני sheni makes a שני. sheni. And
therefore when you eat it, you become a שני. sheni. Okay, fine.
חוץ מטבול יום, chutz mitvul yom, with the one exception of somebody
that's gone to the מקווה mikvah that day. If somebody became טמא,
tamei, I touched a carcass of an animal today, what do I
do? Anything that's not about טומאת מת tumat meit or things like
טומאה tumah coming from my body and so on, I go to
the מקווה mikvah and I'm טהור tahor that night. However, what happens
after I've gone to the מקווה mikvah before nightfall? I'm called a
טבול יום tvul yom and my status is a שני. sheni. Now
that status as a שני sheni is actually weaker than other שניים,
sheniyim, because it's a שני sheni that's basically the remnants of a
טומאה tumah and that's about to disappear at nightfall. So in that
case, that type of a very weak שני, sheni, it does not
have the impact on water, but any other שני sheni does have
the impact on liquid to make it into a ראשון. rishon. Okay,
fine. Now
that explains the positions of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua about why a
ראשון rishon and a שני sheni make you a שני. sheni. It's
like you touched it, and touching a ראשון, rishon, touching a שני,
sheni, in their cases where you become a שני, sheni, so you
become. ועוד, Ve'od, says רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, I have another question.
ועוד, Ve'od, שלישי שני למה? shlishi sheni lama? Why when you eat
a שלישי shlishi do you become a שני? sheni? If anything, when
you become- when you eat a שלישי shlishi you should be a
רביעי revi'i or you should be nothing because, you know, if you're
deal- you know, if you're not dealing with קדשים, kodashim, then you
can't go below a שלישי. shlishi. So how do you get up
to a שני? sheni? So אמר ליה, amar lei, אף אני לא
אמרתי אלא בתרומה. af ani lo amarti ela b'truma. No, remember he
said, what type of a שלישי shlishi are we talking about? Remember
we said- he said very clearly, we're not talking about תרומה, truma,
we're not talking about קדשים, kodashim, we're talking about חולין chulin that
you treated as if it were תרומה. truma. Okay, so you're treating
your חולין chulin as if it's תרומה truma and it became a
שלישי. shlishi. Now he said, what is the status of of things
for that are טמא tamei for תרומה truma or even טהור tahor
for תרומה truma from the perspective of קדשים? kodashim? So he says
the following. I'm talking about תרומה truma is a שלישי shlishi or
food treated like תרומה truma is a שלישי. shlishi. But there's a-
but here's the story with it. שטהרתה, shetahartah, even if something is
pure from the perspective of תרומה, truma, now the top of ה
עמוד ב, hei amud bet, שטהרתה תרומה היא אצל הקדש. shetahartah truma
hi etzel hakodesh. It's considered as if you're טמא tamei by הקדש.
hekdesh. Now what does that mean? We're going to see a little
bit later. You see, this is the problem of or the reality
about having all of these issues about, you know, not only do
you have
טהרה tahara by קדשים kodashim and טהרה tahara by תרומה, truma, but
people are even eating their חולין בטהרה chulin b'tahara and you have
all of these types of concerns, but it also certainly leads to
a hierarchy. It leads to I'm being very careful about this, I
can't trust you and you to touch my stuff. So therefore, if
I am treating my חולין בטהרה chulin b'tahara and you're an עם
הארץ am ha'aretz or you're somebody that's not careful, a non-חבר, chaver,
not careful about טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'tahara, get away from my food!
You're not careful about this stuff. And if you touch my food,
I have to assume you're טמא tamei and made my food טמא.
tamei. That's all what we assume. But guess what? Even me that
I am so פרום frum that I'm treating my food like it's-
like it's תרומה truma or even if I'm really dealing with תרומה,
truma, you who's eating sacrifices, you equally don't trust me. You say,
"Very nice that you're being so careful and you're treating your food
like it's תרומה truma or you're even eating תרומה truma and you're
being so careful, but you know what? I'm dealing with something even
holier, I'm dealing with sacrifices, and I can't trust that you're being
careful enough." So therefore if you were to touch my קדשים, kodashim,
my sacrifices, I'd have to consider you טמא tamei and have to
consider everything that I'm eating טמא. tamei. So really it's a lot
of people avoiding other people because of the concerns of טומאה וטהרה.
tumah v'tahara. By the way, this also gives you a little bit
insight into, you know, the whole sort of
significance of like eating groups that was going on in the period
of the בית שני, Bayit Sheni, the Second Temple, and you know,
and the stories in the Christian Testament about Jesus eating with all
these different types of people because there were all very clear delineations.
Look, you have it in the Torah as well, you know, the
Egyptians eating with the Hebrews, you know, who are you eating bread
with? There was all these delineations. So if I'm eating קדשים kodashim
and you're eating תרומה, truma, keep away from me! If you touch
my קדשים, kodashim, you'll make it טמא. tamei. So since that's true,
so therefore, says רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, since although your food is
a שלישי shlishi because it's תרומה truma or treated as תרומה, truma,
from the perspective of קדשים kodashim it's even more טמא. tamei. It's
even like a שני. sheni. So therefore from the perspective of קדשים
kodashim everything is worse, so if you eat this food that's a
שלישי, shlishi, we're going to treat it in the worst possible scenario
from the perspective of קדשים, kodashim, and if you ate a שני,
sheni, what did we just say? If you ate a שני sheni
you become a שני. sheni. So although you ate a שלישי, shlishi,
from the vantage point of קדשים kodashim you ate a שני sheni
and therefore you become a שני. sheni. And remember the end of
the line said that you become a שני sheni vis-a-vis touching sacrifices.
So therefore we're looking at it from the perspective of a person
who is eating sacrifices.
Okay, so now we have it. The משנה mishnah is talking about
you're treating your meat like it's קדשים kodashim or- and that is
treated as if it's קדשים. kodashim. We have the discussion about what
happens when you eat טמא tamei food. Are you what you eat
or you basically become a שני sheni
because you go down a level and whatever, become a שני? sheni?
And when you eat a שלישי shlishi of תרומה, truma, you become
a שני sheni from the perspective of people that eat קדשים kodashim
because you're really טמא tamei from the perspective of people eat קדשים
kodashim even if you're being really טהור tahor in your eating of
תרומה. truma. Now, to continue. אמר רבי זירא אמר רבי אסי אמר
רבי יוחנן אמר רבי ינאי, Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rabbi Assi amar
Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi Yannai, okay, so this long tradition, האוכל שלישי
של חולין שנעשו על טהרת הקדש, ha'ochal shlishi shel chulin shena'asu al
taharat hakodesh,
you ate this שלישי shlishi of חולין chulin that was made- treated
as sacrifices. Now, what is the significance? Number one, we're assuming that
when you treat חולין chulin like sacrifices, it's- it's meaningful, that was
debated before, and that it really does- can become טמא tamei like
sacrifices, so it's... Can become a שלישי. shlishi. So this food became
a שלישי, shlishi, you treated it like sacrifices, like we said the
case in our משנה, mishna, you treated your meat like sacrifices, it
became a שלישי, shlishi, now you ate it. Now, what's the story,
what do you become? נעשה גופו שני לקודש, Na’aseh gufo sheni lakodesh,
you become a שני. sheni. Now that's sort of like we said
before, if you eat a שלישי shlishi you become a שני, sheni,
but it's going further, because before we said why did you become
a שני? sheni? Because you were only being careful for תרומה terumah
and therefore it's you're not being totally careful. But here we're saying
even if you treated it like a sacrifice, you become a, you
become a שני. sheni. So we don't really have a clear explanation
why, but that is the הלכה halacha here, if you eat a
שלישי shlishi you always become a שני sheni vis-à-vis sacrifices. So let's
take a look. איתיבי רבי זירא לרבי אסי. Eiseivi Rebbe Zeira le-Rebbe
Assi. Rebbe Zeira asked Ab-Assi: שלישי שני לקודש ואין שני לתרומה. Shlishi
sheni lakodesh ve-ein sheni le-terumah. So this
is exactly the teaching of רבי יהושע. Rebbe Yehoshua. If you eat
a שלישי shlishi you become a שני sheni for the world of
sacrifices, not if you touch תרומה, terumah, but if you touch a
sacrifice now we'll treat you as a שני. sheni. Okay, this is
when you ate a שלישי. shlishi. What type of a שלישי shlishi
did you eat? בחולין שנעשו על טהרת תרומה. Be-chullin she-na'asu al taharas
terumah. If you ate חולין chullin that were treated as תרומה. terumah.
So על טהרת תרומה al taharas terumah in, על טהרת קודש al
taharas kodesh no. Only if you ate חולין chullin that was treated
as תרומה, terumah, not if you ate חולין chullin that was treated
as sacrifices. One reason as we said is that if you eat
חולין chullin that's treated as sacrifices, it's so absurd that it has
no הלכה halakhic significance. So how can you now say even when
you treat חולין chullin as sacrifices? So אמר ליה, amar lei, he
said back to him: לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka'amar. No, it
goes without saying. This is exactly what we debated before, whether to
read רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua's statement of treating your חולין chullin like
תרומה terumah as only תרומה terumah or even תרומה. terumah. He says,
I'm reading it as even תרומה. terumah. לא מיבעיא קאמר. Lo mibaya
ka'amar. So even if you treat it as תרומה terumah it can
become a שלישי, shlishi, but certainly if you treat it as sacrifices,
it can become a שלישי shlishi and it'll make you a שני.
sheni. So the גמרא Gemara says: והא אף אני לא אמרתי אלא
בתרומה קאמר. Ve-ha af ani lo amarti ela be-terumah ka'amar. But one
minute, had that in that whole back and forth of רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua that we just got through
saying, רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer explained his, רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua explained
his position and he said the reason eating a שלישי shlishi makes
you a שני sheni is because we're only talking about the תרומה
terumah level. And therefore from the sacrifice level it has to be
worse. So now you are really saying two things. First thing you're
saying is that חולין chullin treated as sacrifices can become טמא tamei
like sacrifices. Fine, I accept that. Let's say, let's say that even
though you're making this big jump and treating חולין chullin like sacrifices,
it's meaningful and it can become טמא. tamei. But the next point
is what happens if you eat this שלישי? shlishi? What do you
become? רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua said you become a שני sheni because
if you're eating stuff that was treated as תרומה, terumah, then
it's worse from the perspective of sacrifices. And he was very clear
that he only said his ruling if you're eating stuff that was
treated as תרומה. terumah. How can you now apply that ruling even
for stuff that was treated with the purity of sacrifices? There's no
logic why when you eat something that's a שלישי shlishi treated as
a sacrifice, should you become a שני. sheni. So let's see what
he answers. So he says: אמוראי נינהו ואליבא דרבי יוחנן. Amora’ei ninhu
ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yochanan. There's a debate according
to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Remember the other, this is in the
name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right? אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן. Amar Rebbe Assi amar Rebbe Yochanan. This is in the name
of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and the other statement about the back
and forth of רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua
was in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. He says, you
know what, you're right. There's a debate within רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
how to understand רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua's position or what רבי יהושע
Rebbe Yehoshua actually even said in response to רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer.
So in this second opinion, רבי יהושע Rebbe Yehoshua is saying not
only does stuff treated as sacrifices get that הלכה halakhic significance and
can become a שלישי, shlishi, but if you eat it you become
a שני, sheni, even though there's not really a good logic for
it and the logic is not being presented. Why if you eat
a שלישי shlishi do you become a שני sheni if it's treated
with the holiness of sacrifices and therefore it's completely pure, you know,
it's completely careful in terms of how you're treating it? Maybe the
answer is well you weren't completely careful, you let it become a
שלישי shlishi and therefore now we have to just start treating it
as worse. But anyway, that's what he said. So whenever you eat
a שלישי shlishi you become a שני sheni even in the case
of treating things as sacrifices. Good. Now the גמרא Gemara goes on.
אמר עולא האוכל שלישי של חולין שנעשו על טהרת תרומה. Amar Ulla:
Ha-ochel shlishi shel chullin she-na'asu al taharas terumah. Again, now we're going
back to the earlier case. You ate something that was a שלישי
shlishi that was treated like תרומה. terumah. So that was the case
where we all said that you become a שני sheni vis-à-vis sacrifices.
So now he's going to say, okay, but not only are you
a שני sheni vis-à-vis sacrifices, there's another implication as well. נפסל גופו
מלאכול בתרומה. Nifsal gufo mil-echol bi-terumah. You cannot eat תרומה, terumah, meaning
as far as touching תרומה terumah is concerned, eating a שלישי shlishi
did not affect your status. Maybe you're a שלישי, shlishi, at most
you're a שלישי, shlishi, but you can touch תרומה terumah if you're
a שלישי shlishi because תרומה terumah cannot become a רביעי. revi'i. But
if you are a שלישי, shlishi, you can't eat תרומה. truma. Here's
another הלכה, halacha, until now we've been saying if you eat something
you might become more טמא tamei than touching it, or not, that
was the debate, but now we're also saying that if you eat
something you're more I'm sorry if you're טמא, tamei, you're more restricted
in what you can eat than in what you can touch. So
if you are a שלישי, shlishi, which we are assuming happens if
you eat this stuff that is treated as תרומה truma and that
became a שלישי. shlishi. So you're a שלישי, shlishi, you can touch
תרומה truma but you cannot eat תרומה. truma. Since תרומה truma itself
can become a שלישי shlishi and you are a שלישי, shlishi, you're
considered off-limits for eating תרומה. truma. So you ate this stuff that
was a שלישי, shlishi, from the perspective of קדשים kodashim you're a
שני, sheni, don't touch or eat sacrifices, from the perspective of תרומה
truma you're a שלישי, shlishi, you can touch תרומה truma but don't
eat it. Alright, so מאי קא משמע לן, mai ka mashma lan,
so the גמרא Gemara thinks that this is all quite obvious. What
are you teaching me? תנינא, tanina, we taught in the משנה, Mishna,
שלישי shlishi if you eat שלישי, shlishi, שני לקודש, sheni lakodesh, then
you are שני sheni vis-a-vis sacrifices ואין שני לתרומה ve'ein sheni litruma
and you're not a שני sheni vis-a-vis תרומה. truma. And what is
the food that you ate that was a שלישי? shlishi? בחולין שנעשו
על טהרת תרומה, bechullin shenaasu al taharat truma, this חולין chullin that
was made with the holy with the purity of תרומה. truma. So
the גמרא Gemara says we can obviously infer the following from the
משנה, Mishna, שני הוא דלא הוי. sheni hu delo havi. So from
the perspective of תרומה truma you're not a שני, sheni, from the
perspective of sacrifices you are, but from the perspective of תרומה truma
you're not a שני. sheni. הא שלישי הוי, ha shlishi havi, implicitly
it's saying you are a שלישי. shlishi. You ate a שלישי, shlishi,
you are a שלישי, shlishi, which is not always what רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says, but that it's saying that's implicit here. And therefore,
of course we understand that if you're a שלישי, shlishi, you're not
allowed to eat תרומה. truma. So the גמרא Gemara says no, I
could not have necessarily inferred that. אי מההיא, ei mehahi, if it
was just from that, הוה אמינא hava amina I would have said
לא שני הוי ולא שלישי הוי, lo sheni havi velo shlishi havi,
you're not a שני sheni and you're not a שלישי. shlishi. You're
nothing, which is a reasonable thing, you ate a שלישי shlishi maybe
you can't be a רביעי revii from the world of תרומה truma
maybe you're nothing. ואיידי דאמר שני בקודש, ve'aidi de'amar sheni bakodesh, since
it says from the perspective of sacrifices you're a שני, sheni, אמר
נמי אין שני בתרומה amar nami ein sheni bitruma so it says
you're not a שני sheni for תרומה, truma, but it really means
you're nothing for תרומה. truma. That would have been a reasonable read
of that משנה, Mishna, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan and therefore
עולא Ulla teaches me otherwise. So עולא Ulla is now telling me
that according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, you eat this stuff that's
a שלישי, shlishi, it makes you into a what do you call
it? It makes you into a שני sheni for sacrifices because people
who eat sacrifices don't trust people who eat תרומה. truma. But for
תרומה truma it keeps it makes you the same level as שלישי,
shlishi, which is a little strange because רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua normally
says you don't you know the level doesn't stay the same. And
the other חידוש chiddush is once you're a שלישי shlishi although you
can touch תרומה truma you cannot eat תרומה. truma. Okay, so got
that clear. Now let's go on. So we have this debate of
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer to רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua about when you
eat something what level you become, and within רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
is you are what you eat, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is you
go down a level but not really it sort of always depends.
Okay, so now we're going to continue. Where are we? קא משמע
לן. ka mashma lan. איתיבי רב המנונא לעולא, eitivei Rav Hamnuna le'Ulla,
so Rav Hamnuna asked Ulla, הראשון שבחולין טמא ומטמא. harishon shebachullin tamei
umitamei. So something that is a ראשון rishon and we're talking חולין
chullin now, there's a huge תוספות Tosafot here, you can see, it's
going to be about explaining the last line and explaining the exact
case that we're talking about. Let us for simplicity make it easier
because although we started a little late we're going to finish on
time. So let us assume that we're talking here about and there's
a big רש"י Rashi too about figuring out what we're talking about.
Let's assume we're talking about חולין chullin that was treated as if
it were תרומה. truma. Okay? It's חולין chullin but it's as if
it were תרומה. truma. So if it's a ראשון, rishon, טמא, tamei,
it becomes טמא tamei ומטמא umitamei and it makes other things טמא,
tamei, it makes food that it touches into a שני. sheni. Fine.
והשני, vehasheni, if the food is a שני, sheni, פוסל, posel, it
makes other things invalid. What does that mean? A שני sheni touches
something else, it makes it into a שלישי. shlishi. Now this other
thing it's touching we're all talking within the same world of objects,
so things that are חולין chullin that are treated like תרומה. truma.
So let what happens if a שני sheni touches תרומה? truma? It
makes the תרומה truma שלישי, shlishi, it makes it פסול, pasul, invalid,
טמא, tamei, but it cannot make other things טמא. tamei. תרומה truma
cannot pass on from a שלישי shlishi to a רביעי. revii. It
stops at a שלישי. shlishi. So that's why it says פוסל, posel,
it invalidates the next object, ואינו מטמא, ve'eino mitamei, it does not
make it טמא tamei because טמא tamei suggests that that will be
able to pass it on. Okay, so basically we know this is
treated as תרומה. truma. A ראשון rishon makes a שני, sheni, a
שני sheni makes a שלישי shlishi and it stops there. והשלישי, vehashlishi,
now if you have שלישי, shlishi, if you actually do have this
חולין chullin that is being treated as תרומה truma and it is
a שלישי, shlishi, so we've already said it cannot make other things
טמא. tamei. Wait, but now we're going to say something else. נאכל
בנזיד הדמע. Ne'echal b'nezid hadema. You can eat it with a mixture,
like remember by יעקב Yaakov and עשו, Esav, נזיד העדשים, Nezid ha'adashim,
you can eat it with a mixture that is mixed up, things
that are mixed up together. What does it mean mixed up together?
That there's actually pieces of תרומה Trumah in it. So you have
your חולין, Chullin, you've got your meat and potatoes—well, not meat, whatever—you've
got your, you know, potatoes and flour and whatever, that's treated as
תרומה, Trumah, and it's a שלישי. Shlishi. Fine, it's a שלישי, Shlishi,
it doesn't pass on. And now you're going to add into your
stew some תרומה Trumah spices, a תרומה Trumah onion, and a תרומה
Trumah garlic. That's דמע, Dema, it's mixed up with real תרומה. Trumah.
Is it a problem? Doesn't seem to be a problem because the
שלישי Shlishi that is your חולין Chullin can't make your תרומה Trumah
anything because a שלישי Shlishi doesn't affect תרומה. Trumah. So it makes
sense, you can mix up your תרומה. Trumah. But he says, according
to you I've got a problem because what did עולא Ulla say
happens if you eat a שלישי? Shlishi? You become a שלישי, Shlishi,
and what happens if you become a שלישי? Shlishi? You can't eat
תרומה. Trumah. So what's going to happen now that you're going to
eat this stew? You're going to eat this stew, you're going to
eat the potatoes and the flour that's—that's חולין Chullin that's a שלישי,
Shlishi, you become a שלישי, Shlishi, then you're going to eat the
תרומה Trumah onion. Well, you can't eat the תרומה Trumah onion because
you're a שלישי. Shlishi. So obviously you're wrong. Either you don't become
a שלישי, Shlishi, or even if you are, you can still eat
the תרומה. Trumah. Although we assume not the latter, we assume if
you're a שלישי Shlishi you can't eat the תרומה, Trumah, but at
least you see you don't become a שלישי. Shlishi. אי אמרת, Ei
amarta, if you say נפסל גופו מלאכול בתרומה, Nifsul gufo mei'lechol b'Trumah,
that when you eat a שלישי Shlishi you become a שלישי Shlishi
and you can't eat תרומה, Trumah, מסקינן ליה מידי דפסל ליה לגופיה?
Maskinan lei midi d'pasul lei l'gufeih? Are we going to feed you
something that's going to make you a שלישי Shlishi and then you
won't be able to eat תרומה? Trumah? How is that possible? And
then you're about to eat the תרומה Trumah onion that's in the
stew. So obviously you're wrong, you don't become a שלישי. Shlishi. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him, no, here's the
answer. הנח לנזיד הדמע, Hanach l'nezid hadema, don't bother me with this
mixture, this stew mixture. Why? דלית כזית בכדי אכילת פרס. D'leit k'zayit
b'khdei achilat pras. Because I can say it's talking about a case—I
don't necessarily have to assume it's talking about a case, but I
can say it's talking about a case that the amount of תרומה
Trumah is so small that there is not a כזית K'zayit distributed
in the amount that's in a פרס Pras worth of food. A
פרס Pras is about eight or nine כזיתים, K'zeitim, so the ratio
of תרומה Trumah to the חולין, Chullin, the amount of onion תרומה
Trumah to the rest of the stew, is less than one to
nine. Therefore what? Therefore, even when I eat the stew and when
I become a שלישי Shlishi and I become טמא, Tamei, I'm never
going to eat a כזית K'zayit of the תרומה Trumah in the
space of time that would be combine it, right? If you eat
over a period of time, over a period of a פרס, Pras,
it's combined into one eating. I'm never going to eat it over—within
the period of a פרס Pras because it's such a little—a little
proportion. And therefore, although I am טמא, Tamei, I'm never going to
eat a כזית K'zayit of תרומה Trumah while I am טמא Tamei
in one time. Now, of course, if you—I were really טמא, Tamei,
like biblically, we wouldn't even want me to eat חצי שיעור Chatzi
shiur of תרומה, Trumah, right? There's a prohibition of חצי שיעור, Chatzi
shiur, of doing a prohibition—even of eating prohibition even less than the
full amount. But I am not really biblically טמא, Tamei, I'm only
rabbinically טמא. Tamei. And since I'm only rabbinically טמא, Tamei, I am
not concerned about the little pieces of תרומה Trumah because I'm never
going to eat a full כזית K'zayit at one time. So we
will end here in the middle of this discussion of if you
eat a שלישי, Shlishi, do you also become a שלישי Shlishi vis-a-vis
תרומה, Trumah, making it forbidden for you now to eat תרומה. Trumah.
Okay, to be continued tomorrow on שבת, Shabbos, שבת שלום Shabbat Shalom
to everybody.