Alright,
בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף היומי. daf hayomi. Today's דף daf
is כ"ג. chaf gimmel. We begin at the bottom of כ"ב עמוד
ב'. chaf beis amud beis. And we are continuing with the theme
here about חטאת chatas and אשם תלוי, asham taluy, about חטאת chatas
and אשם תלוי asham taluy and how many you bring and under
what circumstances. So, משנה, mishna, six lines from the bottom.
האשה שהביאה חטאת העוף. Ha'isha shehevia chatas ha'of. So, I should also
just remind you that yesterday we had two issues that came up,
one is do you bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy if there's
a doubt whether you did מעילה, me'ila, whereas otherwise you would bring
an אשם ודאי. asham vaday. And the other question is can you
bring an אשם בספק. asham besafek. Can you bring an אשם asham
without yet knowing, meaning not an אשם תלוי, asham taluy, but an
אשם ודאי, asham vaday, without yet being certain whether or not you're
obligated. Okay, that's just a little background. Let's take a look at
the משנה. mishna. האשה שהביאה חטאת העוף. Ha'isha shehevia chatas ha'of. A
woman brought a חטאת העוף. chatas ha'of. Now a woman meaning in
case of childbirth, where a woman has to bring an עולת העוף
olas ha'of and a חטאת העוף chatas ha'of to end her טומאה.
tuma. And let's say it's a case where she's uncertain whether the
child she gave birth to is considered what was considered to be
an actual הלכה halachic birth, whether it had been conceived for 40
days or other types of questions. So what does she do? She
brings כסף בטהר, kessef bitohar, she wants to go to the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so she brings her קרבן, korban, and she brings
it בספק. besafek. Now to bring an עולת העוף olas ha'of בספק
besafek is no big deal. You say either this is my עולת
חיוב olas chiyuv or if it's not then it's an עולת נדבה.
olas nedava. But a חטאת chatas you can't have a חטאת נדבה.
chatas nedava. So what do you do?
So there's a tradition that a woman can bring a חטאת מספק.
chatas misafek. Normally you don't bring a חטאת בהמה מספק, chatas behema
misafek, but here you can bring a חטאת העוף מספק chatas ha'of
misafek in order to become טהורה. tehora. But you don't eat it,
because if it was not an obligated חטאת, chatas, then it would
be נבילה neveila because you the way you שחט shecht it from
behind the neck. So let's take a look. So she brings her
חטאת העוף. chatas ha'of. אם עד שלא נמלק נודע לה שילדה ודאי.
Im ad shelo nimlok noda lah sheyalda vaday. So if before it
did the מליקה melika she becomes aware that she had something which
definitely constitutes
childbirth, then תעשה ודאי. ta'aseh vaday. Then you know it's just fine.
So now you שחט shecht it and you make it as a
חטאת ודאי chatas vaday and you eat it. שמין המין שהביאה על
הודע מביאה על לא הודע. Shemin hamin shehevia al hodam mevia al
lo hodam. Because for the same type of thing that she would
bring if she had a doubt, she brings if she doesn't have
a doubt, she brings if she does have a doubt. So she's
going to bring the same קרבן, korban, it's just that the first
הלכה halacha would be you bring it for a doubt and you
don't eat it. Now if you found out that you were definitely
obligated, then you could go ahead and eat it.
So why with the חטאת העוף chatas ha'of that you didn't eat?
Yeah, so you mean why isn't it a חולין בעזרה chulin ba'azara
problem like תוספות Tosafos asks? Either it seems like it really should
be חולין בעזרה, chulin ba'azara, but either we override that because of
this concern in order to make her טהור, tahor, there's no other
choice, or there just might have been a מסורה masora like הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe miSinai that she can do it. Okay. Now
the interesting question here is which the משנה mishna did not explore,
which it could have explored, is let's say she becomes aware after
שחט. shechts. Right? So it was שחט shechted on the assumption of
ספק, safek, and then she became aware ודאי. vaday. At the end
of the day, so what? It's a ודאי, vaday, she should why
not go ahead and eat it even if it was after it
was שחט. shechted. So that's curious and the משנה mishna does not
discuss that, I mean you would think that that should have been
a reasonable conclusion and the גמרא Gemara does not discuss it either.
We're not going to focus on this case, although it does leave
that issue, that example, you know, that particular circumstance unexplored, we're going
to now look at the other cases which are more our general
theme. Okay, so now it goes on and says like this. חתיכה
של חולין וחתיכה של קודש. Chaticha shel chulin vechaticha shel kodesh. Now
we're getting into your classic אשם תלוי asham taluy case. There's a
piece of איסור issur in front of there's a piece of two
pieces of meat in front of you, one was חולין, chulin, one
was הקדש. hekdesh. אכל אחת מהם ואין יודע איזו מהם אכל. Achal
achas meihem ve'ein yodea eizo meihem achal. You ate one and you
don't know which one you ate. And you're like a non-כהן? kohen?
Yeah, you're a non-כהן, kohen, exactly. So or even if you're a
כהן, kohen, it was before זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. So this is
a case of ספק מעילה. safek me'ila. You ate one of these
pieces, maybe it was קודש, kodesh, maybe not. If it was you
did מעילה, me'ila, ספק מעילה. safek me'ila. So this gets us back
to the debate of do you bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy
for ספק מעילה. safek me'ila. רבי עקיבא מחייב אשם תלוי. Rabbi Akiva
mechayev asham taluy. So that's what we just discussed the other day,
it's a ספק מעילה, safek me'ila, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you
bring an אשם תלוי. asham taluy. Now אכל את
השניה, achal es hashniya, let's say you went and you ate the
second one after eating the first one. So okay, it's obvious what
you did now, one of them you ate was קודש. kodesh. So
now you bring an אשם ודאי, asham vaday, everybody agrees on that.
מביא אשם ודאי. Mevi asham vaday. Everybody agrees you bring an אשם
ודאי. asham vaday. I should point out that there's still one ספק
safek here. The one ספק safek is you definitely did מעילה, me'ila,
but on which object did you do מעילה me'ila for? That is
not a sufficient ספק safek to be a problem. If you remember
we discussed like if you know you did a מלאכה melacha on
שבת Shabbos but you forget which אב מלאכה av melacha you did.
You're not sure whether you did זריעה zeria or חרישה. charisha. In
those types of cases you would not bring a חטאת chatas because
you're not sure which עבירה aveira you did. Here you know which
עבירה aveira you did, you know... did מעילה, me'ilah, you just don't
know which piece of meat you did it with and therefore that
is not a sufficient ספק safek and... What? That's an interesting question.
Right, you would probably have to be מחמיר machmir and pay back
the maximum of what it cost. Okay, but it doesn't affect the
קרבן. korban. As long as you know you did מעילה ודאי, me'ilah
vadai, you go ahead and you bring an אשם ודאי. asham vadai.
Now, אכל ראשונה ובא אחר ואכל שניה. achal rishonah u-va acher ve-achal
sheniyah. ראובן Reuven
ate the first one and then שמעון Shimon ate the second. So
each one is a ספק מעילה. safek me'ilah. Okay, so in that
case, זה מביא אשם תלוי וזה מביא אשם תלוי דברי רבי עקיבא.
zeh mevi asham talui ve-zeh mevi asham talui, divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva again says you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
for ספק מעילה. safek me'ilah. Each one brings an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. The other thing implicit in רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is you
don't need חתיכה משתי חתיכות, chatichah mi-shtei chatichot, because שמעון Shimon when
he ate it there was only one piece, there weren't two pieces.
Remember that debate go back to the beginning of the מסכת? masechet?
So therefore if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that שמעון Shimon also
is an אשם תלוי, asham talui, it shows that רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva thinks that you do not bring... that you can bring an
אשם תלוי asham talui even if when you did not have two
pieces in front of you, even when only one piece in front
of you. So that's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, they both bring because
you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui for ספק מעילה safek me'ilah
and even if the second guy only had one piece. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says forget אשם
תלוי, asham talui, I got a better solution to this case.
שניהם מביאים אשם אחד. sheneihem mevi'im asham echad. Have both of them
bring one אשם ודאי, asham vadai, an אשם מעילה, asham me'ilah, and
have them stipulate. ראובן Reuven says if I sinned then it's my
אשם ודאי, asham vadai, if I didn't sin then I'm מוחל mocheil
my part to שמעון. Shimon. And שמעון Shimon says the reverse. And
therefore it's brought and you don't know for who it's brought, which
brings an interesting question because you have to שחט, shecht, you know,
an אשם asham or חטאת, chatas, we'll talk in the גמרא, Gemara,
לשמו בעלים, lishmo ba'alim, but if you שחט shecht it סתם stam
that's also okay. Right, everybody remembers way back in the beginning of
זבחים, Zevachim, you need to be... חטאת chatas has to be done
לשמו בעלים, lishmo ba'alim, but if you do it סתם stam it
also works. And presumably they're saying it's possible to have a קרבן
חטאת korban chatas or... well here it's an אשם, asham, we'll soon
get to חטאת, chatas, that the owner is not specifically determined. It's
one of them but they stipulate and then it'll work and that
solves the problem. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosei omer, and now רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosei says no, I don't like that whole solution. אין
שנים מביאים אשם אחד. ein shenayim mevi'im asham echad. You cannot have
two people bringing one אשם asham or similarly one חטאת. chatas. Now
it doesn't mean that he rejects the idea of stipulation altogether. We
have a lot of stipulation by קרבנות. korbanot. You know, if I'm
חייב chayav in this עולת ודאי olat vadai it'll be an עולת
ודאי, olat vadai, if not let it be an עולת נדבה. olat
nedavah. Right, you have a lot of types of stipulations in cases
you're not sure where it's a possibility, but not for ownership of
an אשם asham or ownership of a חטאת. chatas. It could be
for two reasons. Number one, it could be a technical reason which
is like you have to sanctify it, it has to be yours
when you sanctify it. You know, here I'm sanctifying it, it was
half mine, so if it's not mine then what did I do?
Like my ownership... you know, the technical aspects might be a little
tricky, although presumably you can get over those. Those are obstacles you
can do, like you can do a קנין kinyan at the beginning
and who buys it, who owns it is stipulated and then who's
מקדיש makdish it also is dependent on who owns it. So there
are like technical problems if you can get the ownership in line.
It seems though it's not a technical concern, it seems that it's
a more fundamental principled issue. The same way for example we discussed
that a חטאת chatas has to be specific to a sin. If
you know you did חלב cheilev or נותר, notar, you can't have
a חטאת chatas for one or the other. It has to be
specifically identified for the sin. Okay, so here too it has to
be specifically identified for the owner. You have to have a חטאת
chatas that the owner is known and identified. It can't be a
חטאת chatas for ראובן Reuven or שמעון Shimon and we just don't
know which one. Okay, so he does not hold to this idea
of stipulating. In קרבנות korbanot maybe you can stipulate, but when it
comes to one person's קרבן korban and you don't know whose, then
he does not hold. Now again I should also point out there
are other examples of one person's קרבן korban you don't know whose,
but that's also different. Let's say for example we've got our, you
know, animals got mixed up and you don't know, one was mine,
one was שמעון's Shimon and they got mixed up and you don't
know whose is whose. Okay, so then the כהן kohen can bring
it for whomever it is. I don't know whose it is, but
whomever it is, that's whose קרבן korban I'm bringing. But again this
is different. This is a case from the beginning, the whole הקדשה
hakdashah is not clear, you know, was not defined as ראובן's Reuven
קרבן korban or שמעון's Shimon קרבן. korban. That for him might not
work, specifically not for a קרבן korban that's coming up for sin,
for an אשם asham or for a חטאת. chatas. Okay, so that's
what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says. Michael, you wanted to say something?
No, I was going to say because then you can just pull
it together, you know, even like, you know what I mean? It's
just like... so basically you're saying in... if you and I let's
say carry on...
we don't know if we carry on שבת, Shabbos, so we each
have to bring our own separate...
our own אשם תלוי, asham talui, yes. And we're going to get
to that case. So let's take a look.
Now, חתיכת חלב וחתיכת חולין. chatichat cheilev ve-chatichat chullin. That was a
special case of ספק מעילה safek me'ilah where only רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva was willing to say that you go ahead and bring an
אשם תלוי asham talui because it was ספק מעילה. safek me'ilah. Let's
talk about a normal case about a normal אשם תלוי. asham talui.
There's one piece in front... there's two pieces in front of you,
one is חלב cheilev and one is חולין, chullin, ואכל אחת מהן
ואינו יודע איזו מהן אכל, ve-achal achat me-hen ve-eino yode'a eizo me-hen
achal, you ate one you don't know which one, so that's a
classic example of אשם תלוי. asham talui. מביא אשם תלוי. mevi asham
talui. You bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. אשם את השניה, asham
et ha-sheniyah, now אכל את השניה, achal et ha-sheniyah, now you went
and ate the second one, so you definitely ate חלב. cheilev. מביא
חטאת. mevi chatas. You bring a חטאת. chatas. Even though you don't
know which piece was חלב, cheilev, you definitely ate חלב. cheilev. אכל
אחד את הראשונה ואכל אחד את השנייה. achal echad es harishona ve'achal
echad es hashniya. ראובן Reuven ate one, then שמעון Shimon ate the
second. So זה מביא אשם תלוי וזה מביא אשם תלוי. ze meivi
asham talui veze meivi asham talui. Each one brings an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. Now there's a question whether you have the דברי רבי
עקיבא divrei Rabbi Akiva here because on the one hand you don't
need רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva anymore because it's not about a ספק
מעילה. safek me'ilah. It's a normal case of an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. Maybe you ate חלב, cheilev, maybe you didn't. But there is
still a חידוש chiddush to this position. And the חידוש chiddush is
that שמעון Shimon did not have two pieces in front of him.
Right? ראובן Reuven ate the first piece, שמעון Shimon ate the second.
So this is also assuming forget ספק מעילה, safek me'ilah, this is
a classic case of אשם תלוי. asham talui. But nevertheless, if שמעון
Shimon is going to bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui, it means
you don't need one out of two pieces. One piece is sufficient.
Okay, so that might, that is not as we know from the
beginning of the מסכת masechet everybody's opinion. Okay, so it's either just
an anonymous תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who assumes you don't need two
pieces, or again it is specifically רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
The position of the second person doesn't bring, right? What? Yeah, the
position is the other person does not need, the second person does
not need to bring.
Right, because there were not two pieces. So this second person would
not bring according to that position. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer
again, so now it's really repeating the same thing. שניהם מביאים חטאת
אחת. shneihem meivi'im chatas achas. They can both stipulate and bring one
חטאת chatas as opposed to before one אשם, asham, he has one
חטאת. chatas. רבי יוסי אומר אין שניהם מביאים חטאת אחת. Rabbi Yossi
omer ein shneihem meivi'im chatas achas. I'm sorry, you can't do that.
If it's about sin, if it's about a חטאת chatas or an
אשם, asham, you cannot stipulate and do something like that. Now, חתיכת
חלב וחתיכת קודש. chatichas cheilev vechatichas kodesh. Let's say it is a
case of,
oh by the way, like I should say there's another example where
you could think about a ספק חטאת safek chatas of who the
owner is, which would go back to the beginning of the משנה,
mishnah, which might be different. Let's say for example two women had
births, had miscarriages,
and somehow their, you know, the embryos or whatever got mixed up
and then you looked at them and it was clear that one
of them had a birth that would have been חייב קרבן chayav
korban and the other had a birth that would not have been
חייב קרבן. chayav korban. Okay, so what do they do? So does
each one just go ahead and bring a חטאת העוף מספק? chatas
ha'of misafek? Or can they bring one קרבן korban and stipulate? Right?
You sort of see that that's a parallel case? Right? So would
that, would here the one that says you cannot stipulate and bring
one חטאת chatas or one אשם, asham, is it specifically because of
sin? What if it was a חטאת chatas that was about טהרה?
taharah? Could you stipulate there or not as well? So it's interesting
to try to understand what are the parameters of this position of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi that does not like the stipulating when it
comes to bringing one חטאת chatas or one אשם. asham. Yes?
I just thought of another possible concern. When you bring a חטאת
chatas you have to סמיכה smicha and do a וידוי. vidui. Right.
So if you don't know whether you sinned or not, how do
you do a וידוי? vidui?
That's interesting. Now normally סמיכה smicha is not מעכב, me'akeiv, but there's
a whole discussion in תוספות Tosafot about when you're not able to
do סמיכה, smicha, סמיכה מעכב smicha me'akeiv because there's a הלכה halacha
about טמאים tme'im being משלח meshalei'ach their קרבנות. korbanos.
So that is not, interestingly that's not raised in the גמרא Gemara
even in understanding רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi position. I have to go
back and check that תוספות Tosafot about the question about סמיכה smicha
being מעכב me'akeiv when you're not able to do סמיכה smicha because
there's a whole סוגיא sugya that טמאים tme'im are משלח meshalei'ach their
קרבנות korbanos even though they can't do סמיכה smicha because a שליח
shaliach can't do סמיכה smicha for you. And that's a case where
you're not even able to do סמיכה smicha because you're טמא. tamei.
So anyway, there's a long תוספות Tosafot עיין שם ayein sham on
that, but it's a good question. But the short answer is we're
assuming it's not מעכב. me'akeiv.
Okay, and when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says אין שניהם מביאים חטאת
אחת, ein shneihem meivi'im chatas achas, then what do they do?
They bring nothing? You're stuck. He might agree you bring an אשם
תלוי. asham talui. The גמרא Gemara will explore that. Okay, so now
we get to again, it's basically the same principle, just more interesting
cases. So let's keep on going.
Now, חתיכת חלב וחתיכת קודש. chatichas cheilev vechatichas kodesh. They're both איסור
issur in front of you. One is חלב cheilev which would lead
to a חטאת. chatas. The other is קודש kodesh which would be
מעילה me'ilah which would lead to an אשם. asham. Now we already
know by the way if it's חלב cheilev and נותר, nosar, right,
and you definitely sinned and you don't know which one, then we
know that that was an earlier discussion, you don't bring a חטאת
chatas for that, you still bring, right? So but now we're dealing
with a case that it's two different sins and two different קרבנות.
korbanos. Not just two different sins, but two different קרבנות. korbanos. חלב
cheilev which would lead to a חטאת chatas and קודש kodesh which
would lead to an אשם. asham. אכל אחת מהן ואינו יודע איזו
מהן אכל. achal achas meihen ve'eino yodeia eizo meihen achal. You ate
one and you don't know which one you ate. So either you're
חייב chayav in חטאת chatas or in אשם. asham. מביא אשם תלוי.
meivi asham talui. Now you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Why
do you bring an אשם תלוי? asham talui? So because minimally even
if, now here it's not דברי רבי עקיבא, divrei Rabbi Akiva, right?
Because even if you say you don't bring an אשם תלוי asham
talui for ספק מעילה, safek me'ilah, forget ספק מעילה. safek me'ilah. You
have ספק חטאת. safek chatas. You have ספק חלב. safek cheilev. So
that's enough to bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Of course, if
you'll remember, that's not so פשוט. pashut. There's an opinion earlier in
a משנה mishnah that said that you only bring an אשם תלוי
asham talui if you might have not have done איסור. issur. If
maybe you did איסור, issur, maybe you did היתר. heter. If ודאי
vadai did איסור issur and you don't know which איסור issur you
did, right, then you don't bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Here's
a case you ודאי vadai did איסור. issur. This משנה mishnah is
assuming again the same way the משנה mishnah assumed that you don't
need two חתיכות, chatichos, this משנה mishnah assumes you can bring an
אשם תלוי asham talui even if you ודאי vadai did איסור, issur,
you just don't know which one. So you bring an אשם תלוי
asham talui because you maybe did חלב cheilev even though you definitely
sinned. Okay, that's that case. אכל את השנייה. achal es hashniya. Now
you ate the second one. You bring both a חטאת ודאי chatas
vadai and an
אשם ודאי. asham vadai. אכל אחד הראשונה ואחר אכל את השנייה, achal
echad harishona ve'acher achal es hashniya,
ראובן Reuven ate one, שמעון Shimon ate the other. So ראובן Reuven
is ספק חלב ספק מעילה, safek chelev safek me'ilah, שמעון Shimon is
ספק חלב ספק מעילה. safek chelev safek me'ilah. זה מביא אשם תלוי
וזה מביא אשם תלוי. ze mevi asham talui veze mevi asham talui.
And again you don't need רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Forget even if
you don't bring an אשם תלוי asham talui for מעילה, me'ilah, each
both ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are a ספק אכל חלב, safek
achal chelev, are ספק כזית חלב safek kezayis chelev and they each
bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Again you don't need חתיכה משתי
חתיכות. chatica mishte chaticos. Again you'll bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
even if you definitely sinned, you just don't know which one. So
both ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon definitely sinned but they don't know
which, they both have a ספק safek that they ate חלב chelev
and therefore they both bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. And do nothing about the מעילה, me'ilah, right.
רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, רבי Rabbi now, רבי שמעון אומר,
Rabbi Shimon omer, שניהם מביאים חטאת ואשם. shneihem mevi'im chatas ve'asham. Just
bring the חטאת chatas between them they're obligated in a חטאת chatas
and אשם, asham, you just don't know which is which. Bring the
חטאת chatas and אשם asham and stipulate this is either my חטאת
chatas or your and your אשם asham or vice versa. רבי יוסי
אומר אין שניהם מביאים חטאת ואשם אחד. Rabbi Yosi omer ein shneihem
mevi'im chatas ve'asham echad. No, you can't do that, have two people
stipulate over the ownership of the קרבן. korban.
Now, and again we don't know what he says.
Correct. הגמרא hagmarah will tell us. חתיכת חלב וחתיכת חלב קודש. chaticas
chelev vechaticas chelev kodesh. Let's say there are two pieces of חלב
chelev in front of you, but one of them is חולין chullin
and one is קודש. kodesh. So if you ate the חלב chelev
that was קודש, kodesh, you did two sins, right? You did מעילה
me'ilah and you did חלב. chelev. Okay, so if you in that
case, so what happens? אכל אחת מהן ואין ידוע איזו מהן אכל.
achal achas mehen ve'ein yadua eizo mehen achal. You ate one,
you don't know which one you ate. So minimally what did you
do wrong? There's one thing you definitely did wrong. If you, right,
one is חלב חולין chelev chullin and one is חלב קודש. chelev
kodesh. So you're definitely חייב chayav in a חטאת. chatas. The question
is, are you also חייב chayav in מעילה? me'ilah? Did you eat
the one that was קודש kodesh or not? So what do you
do in that case? מביא חטאת. mevi chatas. You bring a חטאת.
chatas. Now, do you bring an אשם תלוי asham talui for ספק
מעילה? safek me'ilah? So that's the תנא tanna of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. רבי עקיבא אומר אף אשם תלוי. Rabbi Akiva omer af asham
talui. No, you'd also bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. You definitely
ate חלב, chelev, did you also do מעילה? me'ilah? Because we don't
know, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says אשם תלוי, asham talui, others disagree.
אכל את השנייה. achal es hashniya. You ate the second one. So
now we know what you did. You've done two חטאות, chataos, two
חלבs chelev and one מעילה. me'ilah.
In case of השגגה. hashgagah.
Yeah, but it's A, it's just interesting and B, there are here
and there there are some things that we wouldn't have assumed. מביא
שתי חטאות ואשם ודאי. mevi shtei chataos ve'asham vadai. In that case
you bring two חטאות chataos and one אשם. asham. אכל אחד את
הראשונה ואחר אכל את השנייה. achal echad es harishona ve'acher achal es
hashniya. ראובן Reuven ate one, שמעון Shimon ate the other.
So each one ודאי vadai ate חלב. chelev. Okay, the question is,
who ate
the, who also did מעילה? me'ilah? זה מביא חטאת וזה מביא חטאת.
ze mevi chatas veze mevi chatas. Each one brings a חטאת chatas
for their חלב. chelev. And the question is, who did מעילה? me'ilah?
Each one is a ספק. safek. So רבי עקיבא אומר זה וזה
מביאים אשם תלוי. Rabbi Akiva omer ze veze mevi'im asham talui. Each
one is a ספק מעילה, safek me'ilah, they bring an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. That's רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of אשם תלוי asham talui
for ספק מעילה. safek me'ilah. רבי שמעון אומר זה מביא חטאת וזה
מביא חטאת. Rabbi Shimon omer ze mevi chatas veze mevi chatas. They
each bring a חטאת, chatas, that we've agreed upon, each one individually.
And between them they're obligated in an אשם. asham. ושניהם מביאים אשם
אחד. ushneihem mevi'im asham echad. They bring one אשם asham and they
stipulate. רבי יוסי אומר אין שניהם מביאים אשם אחד. Rabbi Yosi omer
ein shneihem mevi'im asham echad. Sorry, you can't stipulate. Okay. So like
I said, it's a long משנה, Mishnah, but it's not too hard
once you get down the principle, it's a straight application. Yes, Charles.
Um, so according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, this, these past two
cases would seem to make it very clear that it really is
something fundamental because with these two קרבנות korbanos being brought and you
don't know who it is, you could by stipulation make sure the
right number of קרבנות korbanos be brought and you aren't bringing חולין
לעזרה chullin la'azarah and things like that.
But that's always the case. What do you mean? Here, in the
first case, one person was חייב chayav a חטאת, chatas, one person
was חייב chayav an אשם, asham, you just don't know who it
is. So what makes it better here that you say, you're חייב
chayav a חטאת, chatas, you're חייב chayav a חטאת chatas and one
of you is חייב chayav in an אשם? asham? Still you're stipulating
over the אשם. asham. It's not that
just because you also happen to be showing up to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash to bring your חטאת chatas doesn't change the question
about stipulating over the אשם, asham, right? Am I understanding you correctly?
It's not any more that you're certainly חייב chayav in the אשם
asham in this case than you were in the first case.
But you've got two people bringing two קרבנות, korbanos, it's different from
two people bringing one קרבן. korban.
Two people are bringing, each one is bringing a חטאת. chatas. And
what they're stipulating is on the third animal, which is the אשם.
asham.
I got it.
Okay, fine. Now the גמרא gmarah says like this, זה מביא וזה
מביא אשם אחד ורבי יוסי אומר אין שניהם מביאים אשם אחד. ze
mevi veze mevi asham echad veRabbi Yosi omer ein shneihem mevi'im asham
echad. חתיכת חלב וחתיכת חלב נותר. chaticas chelev vechaticas chelev nosar.
Now we're going to have three problems. One is חלב, chelev, חטאת,
chatas,
one is חלב נותר, chelev nosar, which means
חלב, chelev, מעילה me'ilah and נותר. nosar. So the נותר nosar actually
has two sins, right? It's two
חטאות, chataos, one for
חלב, chelev, one
for
נותר, nosar, plus מעילה. me'ilah. Okay anyway, doesn't say that, I don't
know why. Anyway, would he say that? Presumably he would. אכלת השנייה,
Achalas hashniyah, now you ate the second, so then it's also obvious.
Maybe ג חטאות, gimel chatasos, you bring three חטאות. chatasos. Now why
are you not also bringing an אשם asham for the מעילה? me'ilah?
Oh, I think we're assuming here, I'm sorry, we're assuming here that
there's no מעילה me'ilah for the נותר. notar. Right, I'm sorry, so
that also explains why we didn't say the other case. Right, right,
I'm sorry, so let me just double check רש״י. Rashi.
Yeah, I'm sorry, we are assuming that there is no מעילה me'ilah
for the נותר, notar, that since once it becomes נותר, notar, it
is no longer fit for being brought as a קרבן, korban, so
it's no longer in the category of קדשי השם, kodshei Hashem, so
there's not going to be מעילה me'ilah for the נותר. notar. So
that explains also why we didn't have רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's אשם
תלוי, asham talui, okay? So one of them is חלב, cheilev, one
חטאת. chatas. One is חלב cheilev and נותר, notar, which is two
חטאות. chatasos. מעילה Me'ilah is being bracketed because it's נותר, notar, there's
no מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, so therefore let's say that again. So let's
go back to that, let's just take that from the top.
חתיכה של חלב וחתיכה של חלב ונותר. Chatichah shel cheilev vechatichah shel
cheilev venotar. One is חלב, cheilev, one is חלב cheilev and נותר,
notar, so one is one חטאת, chatas, the other is two. No
מעילה me'ilah because it's נותר. notar. אכל אחד מהן ואין ידוע איזה
מהן אכל, Achal echad mehen ve'ein yadu'a eizeh mehen achal, מביא חטאת
ואשם תלוי. mevi chatas ve'asham talui. So you ate one, you definitely
ate חלב, cheilev, you might have also done נותר, notar, so it's
a חטאת chatas and an אשם תלוי. asham talui. אכל את השנייה,
Achal es hashniyah, you ate the second, מביא ג חטאות. mevi gimel
chatasos. Now you did three sins, חלב cheilev plus חלב cheilev נותר,
notar, so therefore three חטאות, chatasos, assuming that there was some ידיעה
yedi'ah between. אכל אחד את הראשונה ואחד את השנייה, Achal echad es
harishonah ve'echad es hashniyah, ראובן Reuven ate the first one, שמעון Shimon
came and ate the second one, זה מביא חטאת ואשם תלוי וזה
מביא חטאת ואשם תלוי. zeh mevi chatas ve'asham talui vezeh mevi chatas
ve'asham talui. Each one brings a חטאת chatas because each one definitely
ate חלב. cheilev. There's a ספק safek which one ate נותר, notar,
so because ראובן Reuven doesn't know if he ate נותר, notar, שמעון
Shimon doesn't know if he ate נותר, notar, they both bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. Again, assuming you do not need
חתיכה משתי חתיכות.
chatichah mishtei chatichos.
Right, right. Well, you'd need an assumption that you don't need חתיכה
משתי חתיכות, chatichah mishtei chatichos, which is the assumption of this משנה.
mishnah. רבי שמעון אומר זה מביא חטאת וזה מביא חטאת, Rabbi Shimon
omer zeh mevi chatas vezeh mevi chatas, שניהם מביאים חטאת אחת. sheneihem
mevi'im chatas achas. Again, like we said, each one brings a חטאת
chatas for their חלב. cheilev. In terms of the other sin of
נותר, notar, they bring one חטאת chatas and they stipulate.
I thought you said things don't matter if they're both אסור. assur.
What? I thought you said we don't need that if both things
are...
No,
that's another reason for it to be not an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. To be an אשם תלוי... asham talui... let me just finish
this point. רבי יוסי אומר כל חטאת שבאה על חטא אין שנים
מביאים אותה. Rabbi Yosi omer kol chatas sheba'ah al cheit ein shenayim
mevi'im osah. See, now that's where here he's most explicit at the
end. He doesn't just say you can't stipulate on a קרבן. korban.
If it's a חטאת chatas for sin, I gave you an example
of a חטאת chatas for a יולדת, yoledes, right, which would be
different. If it's a חטאת chatas for sin, you have to know
whose קרבן korban it is, you have to sanctify it for a
particular person. So here's the most articulate position of רבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yosi's position, here he's most articulate at the end. Now again, to
repeat, what is the חידוש chiddush of this משנה mishnah other than
the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva idea that you bring an אשם תלוי
asham talui for ספק מעילה? safek me'ilah? There are two other assumptions
of this משנה mishnah which we have learned earlier were definitely not
agreed upon. One is is that the second guy will bring a
חטאת... chatas... if he definitely sinned... the second guy, excuse me, will
bring an אשם תלוי, asham talui, in the ראובן ושמעון Reuven veShimon
cases, even though for the second guy it was only one piece
and not two pieces. Some people say you would never bring in
that case. The other חידוש chiddush is is that you bring an
אשם תלוי asham talui even when both of them... even when you
definitely sinned, you just don't know which sin you did. And we
had learned before that if you definitely sinned and you don't know
which sin you did, there was a... seemed to be the more
dominant opinion, here clearly not, that you would not bring an אשם
תלוי. asham talui. An אשם תלוי asham talui is only in a
case where you might have not sinned. If you definitely sinned and
you just don't know which one, you would not bring, and nevertheless
we say here that you would bring. Although I should say that
here in the past the case was you definitely did a sin
that חייב chayav you a חטאת, chatas, you just didn't know which
one. You either ate חלב cheilev or you ate נותר, notar, you
just don't know which one. Here where you're bringing an אשם תלוי
asham talui for a ודאי vadai sin, one sin would have been
מחייב mechayev you a חטאת, chatas, the other would have been מחייב
mechayev you an אשם. asham. You either did מעילה me'ilah or חלב,
cheilev, right, you don't know which one. So it's a little bit
different, right? There are three scenarios. One is I either did a
sin or I didn't, that's the clear case of אשם תלוי. asham
talui. The other extreme is I definitely did a sin that's מחייב
mechayev me a חטאת, chatas, I just don't know which one. Either
I ate חלב cheilev or I ate נותר. notar. Then that seemed
to be the more dominant position was you do not bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. Here it's I definitely did a sin, but
it's a sin that either was מחייב mechayev me חטאת chatas or
מחייב mechayev me an אשם. asham. I either ate חלב cheilev or
I did מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, so there's more of a two options
here than in an I definitely did a חטאת chatas sin. Okay,
anyway, and the assumption in this משנה, mishnah, which is undisputed, is
at least in that case you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui.
Okay, so that was a lot of fun.
Now what we've been saying before.
Before we never dealt with that specific case, but in general we've
been assuming you only bring an אשם תלוי asham talui when you
might have not sinned. Okay, now let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara because most of these cases are straight applications, but there
are some nuances. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, Amar lei Rava leRav Nachman,
רבי יוסי חטאת הוא דלא מייתו שנים. Rabbi Yosi chatas hu dela
mayisu shenayim. So
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says I'm sorry, you don't have that trick
of two people stipulating on one אשם Asham or two people stipulating
on a חטאת. Chatat. Okay fine, so you're not going to do
that trick of one חטאת. Chatat. What are you going to do?
Are they both going to bring an אשם תלוי? Asham Taluy?
It would seem like it presumably. So that's the תנא קמא. Tanna
Kamma. So we just said that that was the first position, the
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. They both bring
an אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. וכי תימא חתיכה משתי חתיכות איכא בינייהו,
Ve-chi teima chaticha mishtei chatichot ikka beinaihu, now maybe ah, no maybe
they don't both don't bring an אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. Maybe exactly
he disagrees with one of the assumptions that this משנה's Mishnah been
saying. Meaning the משנה Mishnah says right, if either ראובן Reuven or
שמעון Shimon ate חלב chelev and you don't know which one, each
one brings an אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. Now you could have argued
about that. You could have said שמעון Shimon doesn't, because שמעון Shimon
didn't eat from two pieces, right? So when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says you can't stipulate and both bring a חטאת, Chatat, it's not
clear what he would say you would do, right? So maybe you
would bring each one brings an אשם תלוי, Asham Taluy, but we
already said that. So maybe he would say that you that only
ראובן Reuven brings the אשם תלוי Asham Taluy because only ראובן Reuven
ate from two pieces. It's possible he doesn't tell you what you
would do. You can't say that, ותניא, ve-tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, Baraita, רבי יוסי אומר זה מביא אשם תלוי וזה מביא אשם
תלוי. Rabbi Yose omer zeh meivi Asham Taluy ve-zeh meivi Asham Taluy.
We have a ברייתא Baraita that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is explicit.
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says you can't stipulate, each one brings an
אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. So now the only question is רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose is saying exactly what the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said ראובן Reuven brings an אשם תלוי,
Asham Taluy, שמעון Shimon brings an אשם תלוי, Asham Taluy, and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose says to answer back רבי Rabbi who was it,
to answer back רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, no, you can't play this trick of each one
bring a חטאת, Chatat, I'm sorry, you each have to bring an
אשם תלוי. Asham Taluy. Well fine, that's exactly what the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma said. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה הא קמשמע
לן דמאן תנא קמא רבי יוסי, amar leh ha kamashma lan de-man
Tanna Kamma Rabbi Yose, fine. Okay. So first we said it sort
of anonymously and then when it came to having an explicit retort
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we named it, but the opinion other
than רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva only being introduced
to say the idea of אשם תלוי Asham Taluy for מעילה. Me'ilah.
Other than that, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is I mean רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva would agree, but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is the sort
of סתם stam of this משנה, Mishnah, which assumes you cannot stipulate
and bring one חטאת, Chatat, and that both ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon bring an אשם תלוי, Asham Taluy, you do not need חתיכה
משתי חתיכות. chaticha mishtei chatichot. Okay now we go on. חתיכת חלב
וחתיכת קודש חתיכת חלב וחתיכת חלב וקודש חתיכת חלב וחתיכת חלב, Chatichat
chelev ve-chatichat kodesh, chatichat chelev ve-chatichat chelev ve-kodesh, chatichat chelev ve-chatichat chelev,
no sir, so we have all these cases where one was חלב,
chelev, definitely you did חלב, chelev, one was חלב, chelev, the other
was חלב chelev plus, either חלב chelev plus מעילה, Me'ilah, חלב chelev
plus נותר notar and so on. Okay, or okay, so אמר ליה
רבא לרב נחמן, amar leh Rava le-Rav Nachman, וליתי נמי אשם ודאי
דנותר דקודש הוא, ve-leiti nami Asham Vadai de-notar de-kodesh hu, right. So
here, exactly the question we asked and we reversed ourselves in the
משנה, Mishnah, this is what רבא Rava asks רב נחמן. Rav Nachman.
In the case of נותר, notar, why do we only mention חטאת?
Chatat? What about the אשם Asham for מעילה? Me'ilah? When you ate
both pieces we said three חטאות, Chatatot, two חלבים chelevs and a
נותר, notar, what about the אשם ודאי Asham Vadai of מעילה? Me'ilah?
So, אמר ליה דליכא שוה פרוטה. amar leh de-leika shaveh perutah. There's
not a שוה פרוטה shaveh perutah of it. Okay. The נותר notar
is not worth a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. Now the assumption here
is again that not because since it's נותר notar you can't do
anything with it, it's therefore there's no מעילה, Me'ilah, because as רש"י
Rashi points out here, once it's put on the מזבח mizbe'ach it
can stay on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So therefore it's enough considered to
be of some value that it's not considered to be completely, you
know, worthless to קודש. kodesh. But the answer is okay, it's of
some value, but in the state right now you're not allowed to
put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach and it's a very little value
because mostly what you'll do with it is just burn it. So
therefore it's not worth a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. So it's not
categorically excluded. That's why we had to do the שוה פרוטה. shaveh
perutah. You understand if it's not categorically excluded, it could still be
of value to the הקדש hekdesh because if it were put on
the מזבח mizbe'ach you'd let it leave there. But because it is
a very little value it could be a case of not a
שוה פרוטה shaveh perutah and therefore there's no קרבן מעילה. korban Me'ilah.
By the way I should
say what if it's a
big piece then you would and we're going to get there. I
should say that this is important because we're about to get to
מעילה Me'ilah and the big question about מעילה Me'ilah is is it
a sin of eating or is it a sin of stealing or
somewhere in between or both? And one of the big differences what's
the שיעור, shiur, כזית kezayit or פרוטה. perutah. Okay here it's very
clear that we're talking about eating but we're identifying it as פרוטה
perutah as the definition of the שיעור. shiur. Okay so that's the
answer. Yeah because it's נותר notar it's not worth anything or it's
not worth much. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, והא מעיקרא
דאית ליה שוה פרוטה עסקינן, ve-ha me-ikkara de-it lei shaveh perutah askinan,
when we're talking about the earlier scenarios of something that was קודש
kodesh we were assuming it was worth a פרוטה, perutah, דתני אשם
ודאי. de-tani Asham Vadai. The earlier cases of חלב chelev versus חלב
chelev of הקדש hekdesh or חלב chelev or just הקדש, hekdesh, all
those earlier scenarios assumed that the piece was worth a פרוטה. perutah.
All of a sudden now we're assuming the piece isn't worth a
פרוטה? perutah? אמר ליה amar leh no, ההיא חתיכה דלא נותר היא
הוי שוה פרוטה. hahi chaticha de-lo notar hi, havi shaveh perutah.
When it's not נותר notar it's worth a פרוטה. perutah. When it's
נותר, notar, yes, the same size piece, if it's not נותר notar
then it's great, then you
it's definitely worth something, כהנים kohanim can eat it or you'd definitely
put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach it has definite value. As נותר
notar it has very minimal value and therefore the same size piece
is not worth a פרוטה. perutah. So the גמרא Gemara again thinks
that we're saying that categorically נותר nosar isn't worth a פרוטה. perutah.
And now I'm going to prove to you that's not true. והא
יש אוכל אכילה אחת V'ha yesh ochel achilah achat דתני בי נותר
d'tani bei nosar ותני מייתי ארבע חטאות ואשם אחד. v'tani meivi arba
chatatot v'asham echad. You might remember we had an earlier משנה Mishnah
that said you could have one piece of meat, that's what we
really got into the איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur
case. You have one piece of חלב chelev or whatever that you
bring four חטאות chatatot and one אשם. asham. And that piece was
חלב chelev and הקדש hekdesh and נותר nosar and all those things,
and one of the things that you were עובר over on was
מעילה, me'ilah, even though the piece was נותר, nosar, it was also
נותר. nosar. Okay, remember vaguely that משנה? Mishnah? Yes, you had one
piece that was חלב chelev and נותר nosar and הקדש hekdesh and
all those things and you could bring up to
four
חטאות chatatot and one אשם. asham. What?
It was הפנאה? hafna'ah?
Yeah, exactly, you remember even the details of אמימר'ס Amemar's discussion. So
the point is there you had a case of נותר nosar which
was מעילה. me'ilah. So you see נותר nosar isn't categorically excluded from
מעילה. me'ilah. So אמר ליה, amar leh, ההיא בגסה hahi begassah והא
v'ha or there's a question of the גרסא, girsa, but anyway והכא
בדקה. v'hacha bedakkah. So there's meaning there's a couple ways of reading
this, but the simplest way is a big piece versus a small
piece. It has very little value, right, but if it's a big
piece, you know, then it's although, you
know, נותר nosar is worth like pennies to the pound, okay, but
if it's a bigger piece, it's worth more. Now again, this whole
thing is pretty funny since the only value you get out of
נותר nosar is if it happens to be put on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, which you're not allowed to do. Okay, so how that would
compute into that ספק safek into a dollar value, but who knows?
I mean, everything I guess in the market has a value based
on possibilities and whatnot. So anyway, if it's a big piece, it's
worth a שוה פרוטה, shaveh perutah, a small piece would not be
worth a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah.
So if it was a big piece, you would אינמי inami bring
the third
קרבן?
korban? Yes. או איבעית אימא, O iba'it eima, ההיא בימות הגשמים hahi
bimot hageshamim הכא בימות החמה. hacha bimot hachammah. Is it wintertime or
summertime? If it's summertime, the stuff will spoil sooner. So again, if
it only has very doubtful value and very trivial value and it's
going to spoil, it's not worth a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. So
the upshot of all of this is נותר nosar is not categorically
excluded from מעילה. me'ilah. There is some potential value to it, but
in many there are definitely many cases that that value will not
be sufficient enough to lead to a קרבן מעילה. korban me'ilah. Okay,
now we go on to the other sort of חידוש chiddush of
our משנה. Mishnah. Notice we skip over the basic theme of the
משנה Mishnah because basically it's one principle that's just applied straight out,
there's not too much to say, and we focus on the more
interesting sort of characteristics. So one question was is there מעילה me'ilah
by נותר? nosar? And now the question is איסור חל על איסור.
issur chal al issur. How do you get multiple things for one
piece of meat? So let's take a look. We did, but now
we're looking at it in this
משנה. Mishnah. אמר ליה רבא
לרב נחמן, Amar leh Rava l'Rav Nachman, ומי אמר רבי שמעון איסור
חל על איסור? u'mi amar Rabbi Shimon issur chal al issur?
So of course remember here we have רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's position,
because one of the תנאי Tannai here is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
who said you can stipulate in both bring the same קרבן. korban.
So presumably he agrees that you have all of these transgressions. So
who's so remember one of the cases was you had something that
was both חלב chelev and מעילה me'ilah or חלב chelev and נותר.
nosar. So it starts its life with being חלב, chelev, right? The
animal is born, let's just get this clear, the animal is born,
it has חלב chelev in it. Okay, so it starts with חלב.
chelev. Then you sanctify it, then you're trying to add an איסור
issur of מעילה me'ilah or הקדש hekdesh on top of חלב. chelev.
Or then it becomes leftover, then you're trying to נותר nosar on
top of it. Okay, so the question is now normally would that
be an איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur problem? Well
again, remember, what are the two exceptions? Anybody? איסור כולל, issur kolel,
איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. Okay, what either if the new איסור issur
includes more objects, or if it includes which is איסור כולל, issur
kolel, or איסור מוסיף issur mosif if more people become forbidden. Now
let's think about what happens to this case. So it's חלב. chelev.
Then you sanctify it. Are more things forbidden as a result of
this sanctity than just the חלב? chelev? Are more come on, you
sanctify the animal, not just the חלב. chelev. So the whole animal
is sanctified. So that would be the right out would be an
איסור כולל. issur kolel. Okay, let's now go ahead and now it
becomes נותר. nosar. Are more things forbidden than just this חלב? chelev?
Yes, the other parts of the animal. So you basically have here
cases of איסור כולל issur kolel normally but not more than הקדש.
hekdesh.
Oh right, that's true, excuse me, not more than הקדש, hekdesh, I'm
sorry, but it becomes אסור
למזבח. assur l'mizbe'ach. Okay, so because it's אסור למזבח, assur l'mizbe'ach, that's
considered מוסיף mosif in the sense the people, not the people, but
you know, the the whatever I don't know what other word to
use, but anyway the audience it impacts, okay, is larger. Okay, so
right, thank you, that's an איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. Okay, so in
all these cases it should work because of איסור כולל issur kolel
or איסור מוסיף. issur mosif. So the question is going to be
but רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon seems to say you don't say איסור
חל על איסור issur chal al issur even in cases of כולל
kolel and מוסיף. mosif. So why does he agree in our משנה?
Mishnah? Okay, that's the key of the question. So let's take a
look. ומי אמר רבי שמעון איסור חל על איסור? U'mi amar Rabbi
Shimon issur chal al issur? Does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon really hold
of איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur even in cases
of כולל kolel ומוסיף? u'mosif? I'll say that he doesn't. דתניא, De'tanya,
we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer,
האוכל נבלה ביום הכפורים ha'ochel neveilah b'Yom HaKippurim
פטור. patur. It's פטור. patur. Now what happened? This animal is a
נבלה neveilah and then it became יום כפור. Yom Kippur. So is
that an איסור כולל issur kolel or מוסיף? mosif? Well, let's take
a look. Is it an איסור issur the
on יום כפור Yom Kippur the it's not not more people are
אסור Assur *assur*, everybody was אסור Assur *assur* on נבלה neveilah, *neveilah*
now everybody's אסור Assur *assur* also because of יום כיפור Yom Kippur.
*Yom Kippur*, but are more objects אסור *assur* because of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*?
Because of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* some people pay...
Well, every what? No, no, no, but every all Jews cannot eat
נבלה *neveilah*. Now all Jews cannot eat on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*.
Unless they have to.
Oh, but that's less people, not more people. Okay, fine. So not
more people are אסור *assur* in this because of יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*. Are more things אסור *assur* because of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*?
Yeah, of course, everything else in the world. Okay, so this is
clearly a case of of איסור issur כולל *issur kolel*. Okay, and
nevertheless רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says, I'm sorry, אין איסור
חל על איסור Ein Issur Chal Al Issur. *ein issur chal al
issur*. So you see רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* rejects אין
איסור חל על איסור Ein Issur Chal Al Issur *ein issur chal
al issur* even by איסור issur כולל *issur kolel*. Presumably he would
also reject it by by איסור מוסיף Issur Mosif, *issur mosif*, and
therefore we're saying how does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* agree
to the cases of something that's both חלב chelev. *cheilev* and מעילה
me'ilah, *me'ilah*, חלב chelev. *cheilev* and נותר nosar *nosar*? That's the question.
Isn't it just more more parts of the object? It's just more...
More objects in the world, correct. Exactly. Okay, so אמר רב ששת
בריה דרב אידי *amar Rav
Sheshet brei d'Rav Idi*, כגון דאכל כוליה בחלבא *k'gon d'achal
kulya b'cheilba*. Okay,
so we're going to get a special case which is not פשט
*pshat*. There are two איסורים issurim. *issurim* here. It's not just חלב
chelev. *cheilev*, there's a כזית *kezayit* of a kidney and a כזית
*kezayit* of חלב chelev, *cheilev* because there's fat on the kidneys and
you ate the whole piece. So therefore it's not just איסור חל
על איסור issur chal al issur. *issur chal al issur*, you ate
the fat is one איסור issur *issur* and the מעילה me'ilah, *me'ilah*
or the נותר Nosar *nosar* is the kidney that came with the
fat. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, וכוליה בחלבא *v'kulya b'cheilba* even
that case, נמי הכא אית ליה באיסור עולין *nami haka'i la b'issur
olin*?
When it goes from מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* to נותר Nosar *nosar*, right,
that should be an איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur.
*issur chal al issur* problem. Right, we just said, right, by מעילה
me'ilah *me'ilah* it's it's by once it's מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah* it's אסור
*assur* to everybody, but when it's נותר Nosar *nosar* it's also אסור
*assur* to the מזבח Mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*. So that's a case of of
an איסור issur מוסיף *issur mosif*. So how does this kidney become
נותר Nosar *nosar* if it already started with מעילה me'ilah, *me'ilah*? Okay,
so you sort of solved the problem of חלב chelev. *cheilev*, but
you still haven't solved the problem of of נותר Nosar *nosar* adding
on to the איסור issur *issur* of מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*, which by
the way should just be a general question, which is how could
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* ever have something חייב *chayav* for
נותר Nosar *nosar*? Right, something always starts
off... Right, because you could have the part that נותר Nosar *nosar*
is the part that is eaten by כהנים *kohanim* or the part
that's eaten by ישראל *Yisrael*. But the part that goes on the
מזבח Mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*, according to him, how does it ever become נותר
Nosar *nosar*? It's מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*, so נותר Nosar *nosar* shouldn't be
added to it. So באיסור עולין *b'issur olin*, it's something that has
to go on the מזבח Mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*. היכי אתי איסור issur נותר
Nosar חייל עליה *Heichi ati issur nosar chail alei*? How does איסור
issur נותר *issur nosar* come and take effect on it? וכי תימא
סבירא ליה לרבי שמעון דנותר איסור חמור issur chamur הוא וחייל איסור
issur, חל דעולין *V'chi teima sevara lei l'Rabbi Shimon d'nosar issur chamur
hu v'chal issur chal d'olin*? Maybe when it's also a weightier איסור
Issur. *issur*, right, that's the important thing that תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* always
insist, רש״י *Rashi* sometimes combines the two. The general idea of an
איסור Issur כולל או מוסיף *issur kolel o mosif* is not weightier,
it's larger scope, more objects, more people. Weightier normally is not a
sufficient reason to say איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur,
*issur chal al issur*, but it's a contributing factor. Okay, so here
he says, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* would normally say
you don't say איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur *issur
chal al issur* even though it's מוסיף *mosif* or כולל *kolel*, here
it is מוסיף *mosif*, but maybe if it's also weightier that would
tip the scales. Okay, and why is נותר *nosar* weightier than the
איסור Issur *issur* of הקדש *hekdesh*? So the the reason is it's
not really spelled out here, but one explanation is that the איסור
Issur הקדש *issur hekdesh* you only bring it's only
the איסור *issur* of מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* is only an איסור *issur*
of מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim. *mita b'yedei shamayim* which is
considered to be more קל *kal* than an איסור כרת issur kares.
*issur kareit*. Or it's only you bring איל או קרבן חטאת korban
chatas *ayil o korban chatat* which for for מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah* you
bring an אשם asham, *asham* for מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* which is seen
to be as not as weighty as a חטאת chatas *chatat*. So
for whatever reason we're assuming נותר *nosar* is weightier than מעילה me'ilah
*me'ilah*. So maybe the fact that it's איסור חמור issur chamur *issur
chamur* should tip the scales and should say that it should be
חל *chal*. והא נבלה דאיסור קל הוא *V'ha neveilah d'issur kal hu*,
because you can't say that איסור חמור Issur Chamur *issur chamur* tips
the scales, why not? והא דנבלה דאיסור קל הוא *V'ha d'neveilah d'issur
kal hu*, because נבלה *neveilah* is a lighter איסור *issur*, ויום הכיפורים
דאיסור חמור הוא *v'Yom haKippurim d'issur chamur hu*, יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*
is more weighty. Why is יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* more weighty than
נבלה *neveilah*? Because what's the punishment for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*? כרת
kares. *kareit*. That's more weighty than נבלה *neveilah*. And ולא אתי איסור
יום כיפור דחמור וחייל אאיסור נבלה דקל *v'lo kati issur Yom Kippur
d'chamur v'chail l'issur neveilah d'kal*. So the whole position of רבי שמעון
*Rabbi Shimon* not only rejects איסור כולל *issur kolel* איסור מוסיף *issur
mosif*, it even says that איסור חמור Issur Chamur. *issur chamur* does
not tip the scales. So אלא דהא היכי *ella deha heichi* do
you get חלב chelev. *cheilev* that's also מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah* that's also
נותר *nosar*? אלא בקדשים גלי רחמנא דאתי איסור חל על איסור issur
chal al issur. *Ella b'kodshim gali rachmana d'ati issur chal al issur*.
Ah, there's a special exception for רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* to the
principle of אין איסור חל על איסור Ein Issur Chal Al Issur.
*ein issur chal al issur* and that's when it comes to קדשים
kodashim *kodashim*. By קדשים kodashim *kodashim* we allow there to be an
איסור חל על איסור issur chal al issur. *issur chal al issur*.
At least so let's take a look. דתניא Detanya, *d'tanya*, we taught
in a ברייתא braisa, *braita*, אשר לה' *asher l'Hashem*. So this is
about an איסור *issur* that somebody who eats מזבח Mizbe'ach השלמים אשר
לה' בטומאתו עליו *mizevach hashelamim asher l'Hashem b'tumato alav*. Somebody that eats
from קדשים kodashim, *kodashim* when he is טמא tamei *tamei*, okay, and
that is so you know and that then that leads to whatever
an אשם asham עולה olah ויורד *asham oleh v'yored*. I'm sorry, a
חטאת Chatas, עולה ויורד *chatat oleh v'yored*. So אשר לה' *asher l'Hashem*
לרבות את *l'rabot et*... So there, so that case you even if
you eat the אימורים, imurim. the fats, the stuff that is an
איסור of מעילה, me'ilah and in addition to being an איסור of
מעילה, me'ilah you're now טמא tamei, and you eat it as well,
that you also are going to bring a קרבן korban not just
for מעילה me'ilah but also for טומאה. tumah. Okay, so that's a
case of איסור חל על איסור. issur chal al issur, The טומאה
tumah took a place on top of the איסור of מעילה me'ilah
by the אימורים. imurim The אימורים imurim קאי עלה באיסור kai ala
be'issur עולה וחלב, vechelev, ובחלב קאי
עלה באיסור כרת, uvechelev kai ala be'issur kares, ואתי איסור טומאה חל
עליה. ve'asi issur tumah chal aleha. So you already had by the
אימורים imurim? two איסורים. issurim What were the two איסורים Issurim. you
had by the אימורים? Number one, מעילה. me'ilah Number two, חלב. chelev
And comes along and now you're טמא, tamei and that fact that
you're טמא takes effect on top of מעילה, me'ilah on top of
חלב. chelev So you see that by קרבנות korbanos you can say
איסור חל
על איסור.
Issur Chal
Al
Issur, A little bit different because there your טומאה tumah is opposed
to something with the piece.
I know, but the same is true by יום כיפור. We are
assuming that by this איסור חל על איסור, although yes, you want
to make it about the חפצא cheftza not the גברא, gavra, about
the חפצא cheftza not the גברא, gavra, we don't always make that
distinction like the יום כיפור example. Okay. So there we say you
see that the תורה Torah says that even the איסור טומאה issur
tumah takes effect on top of the fats, the מעילה Me'ilah and
the חלב. chelev, So you see איסור חל על איסור by קרבנות.
korbanos. תדע שכן הוא, Teda sheken hu, know that this is true,
דהא רבי סבירא ליה איסור חל על איסור. deha Rebbi sevira lei
issur chal al issur. Rebbi in general holds איסור חל על איסור.
Okay. והני מילי איסור חמור על איסור קל. Vehani mili issur chamur
al issur kal. But even when Rebbi says that, it's only a
weightier איסור on a lighter one. תוספות Tosafot says it's not clear
where the גמרא Gemara knows that from, but okay, anyway, it's only
a weightier one on the lighter one even when he says איסור
חל על איסור. אבל איסור קל על איסור חמור לא. Aval issur
kal al issur chamur lo.
Normally Rebbi would say, we just know this, that even when you
say איסור חל על איסור, it's not when the second one is
lighter. Okay, not as severe, again, not bigger scope, smaller scope, but
lighter, less weighty. ובקדשים שמעינן ליה דאמר איסור קל על איסור חמור
נמי חייל. Uvekodashim sham'inan lei de'amar issur kal al issur chamur nami
chayil.
We know he holds a lighter one can take effect on a
weightier one. How do we know this? דאיסור מעילה איסור קל הוא.
De'issur me'ilah issur kal hu. Because מעילה Me'ilah is lighter than חלב,
chelev right? Everybody, we just got through saying, I mean everybody assumes
that you can have איסור מעילה issur me'ilah on חלב. chelev. Now,
or we're going to prove it, we're going to quote a פסוק
pasuk that we say explicitly Rebbi says it. Now we're going to
also assume that מעילה Me'ilah is lighter than חלב. Chelev Why? It
says דאיסור מעילה
קל הוא מיתה, ואיסור קדשים איסור חמור כרת. de'issur me'ilah kal hu
misa, ve'issur kodashim issur chamur kares. Okay, איסור מעילה issur me'ilah is
lighter, it's only מיתה, misa, it's only מיתה בידי שמים. misa bidei
shamayim Okay. Now איסור חמור Issur Chamur is איסור קדשים. issur kodashim.
Now that doesn't mean קדשים Kodshim because normally קדשים Kodshim, you would
think means מעילה. Me'ilah. It really means that the case here that
we're going to be dealing with is a case of the חלב
Chelev. of קדשים, Kodshim. that would be כרת. kares, Okay, so if
you have the חלב Chelev? of a קרבן, korban, that's כרת, kares.
and it's going to come along the איסור of מעילה Me'ilah. and
take effect on top of it. And we're assuming that מיתה, misa,
מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim is less severe than כרת. kares?
Why are we assuming מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim is less
severe than כרת? kares So some say because כרת kares means not
only that the person dies soon, but also that he goes childless,
which others say is not, that's כרת ערירי, kares ariri, not just
סתם כרת. stam kares. But some assume that מיתה misa is just
an early death and כרת kares is an early death plus going
childless. רש"י Rashi here says actually that it's because somehow since כרת
kares, leads to a קרבן חטאת korban chatas, and מיתה בידי שמים
misa bidei shamayim doesn't lead to a קרבן korban חטאת, chatat, somehow
that gives it greater weight.
First of all, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva disagrees. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
says מעילה Me'ilah leads to an אשם, Asham so why חטאת chatat
is weightier than an אשם Asham isn't clear. And just because you
have an opportunity for כפרה kaparah isn't clear why it's considered weightier.
But whatever the reason is, the גמרא Gemara understands that מיתה בידי
שמים misa bidei shamayim? is less severe than כרת, kares and therefore
if you're going to try to have an איסור מעילה issur me'ilah
take effect on top of חלב, Chelev you're going to try to
have a lighter prohibition take effect on top of a weightier one.
What's the difference between כרת and מיתה בידי שמים? Yeah. No, what's
the difference practically?
I told you, whether there's kids. Yeah. Okay. Others disagree on רש"י.
Rashi. Okay. ואתי איסור מיתה חל על איסור כרת. Ve'asi issur misa
chal al issur kares. And the איסור מיתה, issur misa, the איסור
of מעילה Me'ilah, can take effect on top of the איסור כרת.
דתניא, we learned in a ברייתא, Braita, רבי אומר כל חלב להשם,
Rebbi omer kol chelev LaShem, all חלב Chelev is to God. What's
the כל? kol? לרבות אימורי קדשים קלים למעילה. lerabbos imurei kodashim kalim
lime'ilah. That the fat, all things, even fat of a קרבן Korban.
which there generally is no מעילה Me'ilah, for, קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim,
because you can eat it, so there's generally no מעילה Me'ilah. for
that. In that type of a case, nevertheless, the fat is still
להשם LaShem and there still is מעילה Me'ilah, by the fat. Okay,
fine. But now you're telling me there's מעילה Me'ilah by fat, which
means even though the איסור קל issur kal of מעילה takes effect
on top of the איסור חמור of חלב. Chelev So ומעילה איסור
מיתה וקחייל על איסור חלב דאיסור כרת הוא. ume'ilah issur misa vekachayil
al issur chelev de'issur kares hu. שמע מינה ובקדשים גלי קרא. Shema
mina uvekodashim gali kra. So you see that by קרבנות korbanos it's
different. By קרבנות korbanos you can have a weightier איסור take effect
on top of a lighter איסור, and that explains why there can
be מעילה on the fat. That explains why there can be
נותר on the fat,
נ Okay. I'm just trying to think all the examples we gave
the second איסור was the קדשים Kodshim איסור. It was מעילה on
top of the fat or the נותר on top of the מעילה
or the נותר on the fat or the נותר on the מעילה
on the fat, right. So all of those are the second one,
which makes sense, that the חידוש Chiddush is that if the second
איסור is קדשים, Kodshim then it has the effect to take effect
on top of the earlier one even if normally you would say
אין איסור חל על איסור. Ein Issur Chal Al Issur. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara just wraps this up. ותניא, Ve-tanya, but it
teaches a ברייתא, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, אין פיגול בעולים
ואין נותר בעולים. Ein Pigul Be-Olim Ve-Ein Nosar Be-Olim. Explicitly,
he says you cannot be עובר Over on פיגול Pigul or נותר
by the parts that go on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach. right? You can
be עובר Over as we said, you can be עובר Over on
נותר let's say by the meat of the קדשים קלים, Kodshim Kalim,
but you can't be עובר Over on it by the stuff that
goes on the מזבח, that's already אסור as מעילה. You can't be
עובר Over on פיגול Pigul by the stuff that goes on the
מזבח, that's already אסור as מעילה. So it's very clear אין איסור
חל על איסור Ein Issur Chal Al Issur, even by קדשים. Kodshim
אלא תנאי היא. Ela Tannai Hi. Fine, it's a debate of תנאים
Tannaim whether there's this exception of קדשים Kodshim for אין איסור חל
על איסור. Ein Issur Chal Al Issur. ואליבא דרבי שמעון, Ve-aliba De-Rabbi
Shimon, according to רבי שמעון who normally says אין איסור חל על
איסור. Ein Issur Chal Al Issur. דאיכא דאמרי De-ika De-amri בקדשים איסור
חל על איסור, Be-Kodshim Issur Chal Al Issur, some say it does,
which is רבי שמעון of our משנה Mishnah that he agrees of
these multiple איסורים. If the second איסור is קדשים kodshim it can
take effect even if normally it wouldn't. ואיכא דמאן דאמר Ve-ika De-man-da-amar
and there's those that say בקדשים נמי אין איסור חל על איסור,
Be-Kodshim Nami Ein Issur Chal Al Issur, there's no exception by קדשים
and it can't. So according to positions of אין איסור חל על
איסור, Ein Issur Chal Al Issur, you wouldn't have נותר by חלב
Chelev or you wouldn't have נותר by the stuff that goes on
the מזבח or פיגול Pigul by the stuff that goes on the
מזבח. ולמאן דאמר, U-le-man De-amar, so now just to wrap up the
דרשות. Drashos. ולמאן דאמר בקדשים נמי אין איסור חל על איסור, U-le-man
De-amar Be-Kodshim Nami Ein Issur Chal Al Issur, if you say by
קדשים you don't say איסור חל על איסור, so
כל חלב לה' Kol Chelev L'Hashem מאי עביד ליה? Mai Avid Lei?
Which seems to say that there's an איסור מעילה Issur Me'ilah on
the חלב. How could there be an איסור מעילה Issur Me'ilah on
the חלב? אין איסור חל על איסור. Ein Issur Chal Al Issur
So מוקים ליה בולדי קדשים, Mokim Lei Be-valdei Kodshim,
it would be a special case of an animal that was born
to a קרבן. Korban A female you sanctified a, you know, a
female חטאת, chatas, it became pregnant, it gave birth, the animal becomes
קודש Kodesh the moment when it was birthed. דקסבר ולדי קדשים בהוייתן
הן קדושים. De-kasvar Valdei Kodshim Be-havayatan Hen Kedoshim. דתרווייהו בהדי הדדי קאתו.
De-tarvaihu Bahadi Hadadi Ka-atu.
When does the fetus become קדוש? Kadosh? The moment it's born. When
is there an איסור חלב? Issur Chelev? Presumably also the moment it's
born, although תוספות Tosafot discusses what if you stuck your hand into
the womb and took out חלב from the fetus or whatever, but
let's assume the איסור חלב Issur Chelev begins, that's not, the איסור
חלב Issur Chelev begins when it's born. So in that case, חלב
and מעילה come at the same moment. The moment that the child
is born, it's both אסור as חלב and מעילה, and not one
after the other, and in that case they can both take effect.
But in a normal scenario, once something is חלב it won't also
become נותר according to the position of אין איסור חל על איסור.
Ein Issur Chal Al Issur So what we've seen here is הדרן
עלך דם שחיטה. Hadran Alach Dam Shechitah. So what we've seen here
at the end is a position of רבי שמעון that says, we're
not done though, you can go if you want, but we're not
done. Okay, anyway, the position that number one, אין איסור חל על
איסור, Ein Issur Chal Al Issur, רבי שמעון holds אין איסור חל
על איסור even in cases where we would normally say it, איסור
חמור and איסור מוסיף, רבי שמעון rejects that even if it's an
איסור חמור. We've seen that the איסור חמור is a possibility of
tipping the scales, it's not a primary factor. We've seen, and then
we've seen the idea
that by קרבנות, Korbanot, even if for you'd normally hold אין איסור
חל על איסור for various reasons, you know, that nevertheless there's an
exception by קרבנות Korbanot that if the second איסור is קרבן korban
it can take effect. When it's simultaneously it's never a problem of
אין איסור חל על איסור, and we've also seen the interesting point
that נותר is not
categorically excluded from מעילה, it's just a question of its value, which
is a function of which is very little, but it still could
be נותר and מעילה. Okay, now we move on to the next
פרק, Perek, yeah?
Question? So with מעילה, do you actually have to get some benefit
out of it or is it just kind of like, you know?
Yes, no, there are two forms of מעילה and we'll discuss, one
is stealing and one is being, is benefit. We'll discuss it when
we get to the next מסכת. Masechet.
So now we move to all of those cases in the previous,
right, there was a hint to what this פרק Perek is going
to be in the previous משנה. Mishnah. Because the previous משנה Mishnah
spoke about a woman that brings a חטאת ספק Chatas Safek and
then she finds out that she definitely needed to bring it, right?
So now we're going to deal with that background scenario by an
אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. You bring an אשם תלוי Asham Talui and
then you find out you definitely did sin or you definitely didn't
sin. What is the status of the אשם תלוי? Asham Talui? If
the אשם Asham? is already brought, there's nothing to be done. But
let's say it hasn't been brought yet and now you know you
didn't sin or you know you did sin, the אשם asham. becomes
moot. So what's the status of the אשם? asham So let's take
a
look. המביא אשם תלוי, Ha-mevi Asham Talui, you bring an אשם תלוי,
Asham Talui, ונודע לו
שלא חטא, Ve-noda Lo She-lo Chata, and you
find out
that
you didn't
sin. אם עד שלא נשחט, Im Ad She-lo Nishchat, if you, if
before it was נשחט, Nishchat, then
okay, יצא וירעה בעדר, Yetzei Ve-yireh Ba-eder, דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi
Meir. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's not even קדוש. kadosh
No, they're not generic. We've talked about that before, although there is
an opinion that אשם asham, could be a little more generic, but
that's not the dominant one. Okay, so anyway, what's the reason? So
the reason the גמרא's gemara going to say is the גמרא's gemara
going to situate it in the person's דעת, da'at, but I would
also add that part of it has to do with the nature
of an אשם תלוי. asham talui. The גמרא's gemara going to say,
look, at the moment when you sanctified it, you knew you might
not have sinned, and nevertheless, you were sanctifying it because of the
possibility that you did sin. So you weren't sanctifying it because you
thought you had definitely sinned. You thought, you thought maybe you didn't,
maybe you did, and so you sanctified it because of the doubt.
The fact that now you find out you had never sinned doesn't
change the fact that at the moment you sanctified it, you were
in doubt. You knew you might not have sinned, but the very
fact that you were in doubt, you were sanctifying it because you
wanted it to be a קרבן korban. given that you were in
doubt, even knowing that the reality might be you wouldn't have sinned.
So therefore, the fact that it turns out that you didn't sin
doesn't change the fact that you had sanctified it because of your
doubt at the, your psychological status at the time and your doubt
at the time. Now the גמרא gemara adds to this the idea,
well, let's just leave it at that for now.
Okay, it doesn't change the fact that you can't bring it. That
you can't bring it,
right, exactly.
That's what changes, but not the circumstances of your הקדשה. hakdasha. At
the moment you sanctified it, you definitely weren't, had sinned or hadn't,
you just didn't know. Okay, so nothing really changed about that. רבי
אליעזר אומר יקרב, Rabbi Eliezer omer yikareiv, no, you can bring it,
שאם אינו בא על חטא זה הרי הוא בא על חטא אחר.
she'im eino ba al cheit zeh harei hu ba al cheit acheir.
That's spicy. You gotta love that idea. You know, you wonder where
Jewish guilt comes from, right? So if you remember, there was a
position that you could bring an אשם תלוי asham talui בכל יום
bechol yom because you've definitely must have done something. Anyway, so leave
this something else you need this for. Okay, you just don't know
about it. So that certainly doesn't require חתיכה משתי חתיכות. chaticha mishtei
chatichot. Now that might be the idea of אשם תלוי נדבה, asham
talui nedava, a non-obligatory one, right, generic possibility, but nevertheless he says
go ahead and bring it.
Now you just specified the sin for this one, right?
Anyway, correct, correct, and that is more of a generic idea. אם
משנשחט נודע לו, im mishenishchat noda lo, that's a good point too,
that even though this started with a specific identity. אם משנשחט נודע
לו, im mishenishchat noda lo,
now after you שחטed shacht it you found out, so what do
you do? So according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, turns out it
wasn't קודש. kodesh.
You found out that you didn't sin.
You didn't sin, or you did, but we're dealing with the scenario
that you didn't. The גמרא Gemara, will discuss both. Anyway, so ישפך
הדם והבשר יצא לבית השרפה. yishapeich hadam vehabasar yeitzei l'veit hasreifa. So
spill out the blood, burn the meat, because it's basically was חולין
chullin according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, now what would, now
would the חכמים Chachamim disagree? So
one minute, so
I think תוספות Tosafot discusses, yes, תוספות says that either it's going
according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, or he says even the חכמים
Chachamim would agree because
the חכמים, Chachamim, remember, said it had קדושה, kedusha, right? So they
would say, fine, it has קדושה, kedusha, so when it was שחטed,
shacht it had a status of an אשם תלוי. asham talui. Now
that you found out, you can't bring it. So what do you
do with an אשם תלוי asham talui that's שחטed shacht that can't
be brought? It's like קדשים שנפסלו, kodashim shenipsalu, so you have to
go ahead and burn it.
יצא לבית השרפה.
yeitzei
l'veit hasreifa.
But רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said you could still, you know, at
that point, and what רבי אלעזר? Rabbi Elazar? רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar,
yeah, would say it's not a problem. I mean, he says go
ahead and bring it. Okay, so that's if it was שחטed, shacht
then it's either חולין chullin or it's an אשם תלוי asham talui
that can't be brought and you have to go ahead and burn
it. Now נזרק הדם, nizrak hadam,
let's say you sprinkled the blood, what can you do? And then
you found out, can you eat the meat? So there יאכל, yei'acheil,
there actually even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can eat it
because at the moment it was brought, it was good. The fact
that now you find out that you're no longer obligated, whatever, it's
too late, it was brought as a כשר kasher קרבן. korban The
doubt was present at that moment. So therefore, go ahead and eat
the meat. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
says once that's true, אפילו הדם בכוס
יזרק והבשר יאכל. afilu hadam bekos yizarek vehabasar yei'acheil. Even if you
found out after the blood was in the vessel and has yet
to be thrown, throw the blood and go ahead and eat it.
Why? Because this is an opinion that כל העומד ליזרק כזרוק דמי.
kol ha'omeid lizarek kezaruak dami.
Once it's in the vessel and it's about to be thrown, it's
considered as if the קרבן korban was already brought and therefore it's
like if you found out afterwards. Now אשם ודאי אינו כן. asham
vadai eino kein. This idea of an אשם תלוי, asham talui, its
status might change if you find out, is not the same by
other things. For example, עד שלא נשחט יצא וירעה בעדר.
ad shelo nishchat
yeitzei veyeira'eh ba'eider. Let's say you were obligated in an אשם ודאי,
asham vadai, it would also be true about a חטאת, chatas, and
then you found out that you had made a mistake. You thought,
I thought I had ודאי vadai sinned and I sanctified this for
a חטאת chatas, or I sanctified this for an אשם, asham, and
then I found out I didn't sin. So fine, everybody agrees it
was הקדש בטעות hekdesh b'ta'ut because at that moment I thought it
was ודאי. vadai. I was mistaken as opposed to the doubt. It
was correct that you were in doubt, right? So that was that
your moment at thought at the time whether you had or hadn't
sinned was correct, your assumptions of the fact. Here, your assumptions of
the fact were totally wrong and therefore everybody agrees it has no
קדושה. kedusha. עד שלא נשחט יצא וירעה בעדר. ad shelo nishchat yeitzei
veyeira'eh ba'eider. משנשחט, mishenishchat, once it's שחטed shacht you found out you
didn't sin. הרי זה יקבר. harei ze yikaver. Bury it. Now the
question is why do we sometimes say ישרף yisareif and sometimes say
יקבר? yikaver? So basically the rule is like this: קדשים שנפסלו kodshim
she'nifselu
are ישרף. yisareif. חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah that are accidentally brought are
יקבר. yikaver. So why in the beginning of the Mishnah do we
say ישרף yisareif and here we say יקבר? yikaver? Well here it's
much more obvious that it was חולין. chullin. You sanctified it as
a חטאת, chatas it turned אשם, it turns out you didn't sin
at all. Okay, so there it's much more obvious that it's a
type of חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah and we say יקבר. yikaver. In
the earlier case, it was less obvious. It was an אשם תלוי
asham talui and there was a ספק safek and so even if
you do like Rabbi Meir's position, it's close enough to look like
קדשים that you just play it safe and do ישרף. yisareif. But
here it's clearly never קדוש and therefore it's יקבר. yikaver. נזרק הדם,
nizrak hadam, let's say you sprinkle the blood and then you found
out you weren't obligated a חטאת, הבשר יצא לבית השריפה. habasar yeitzei
l'veit hasreifah. I'm sorry. It's not like oh it was a good
קרבן korban. go ahead and eat it. It turns out it was
not a good קרבן. korban It was חולין chullin that was brought
as a קרבן because you were never obligated in a חטאת, so
it was a complete mistake. Okay,
so a חטאת or an אשם ודאי asham vadai are definitely different
than an אשם תלוי. asham talui.
Do you disagree?
Yeah, and Rabbi Eliezer would also agree to all of that because
he says you can only bring an אשם תלוי asham talui בכל
יום, bechol yom, you can't bring an אשם ודאי asham vadai בכל
יום. bechol yom. Okay, now, שור הנסקל shor haniskal is the same.
שור הנסקל shor haniskal if you found out later that you had
made a mistake also does not follow the rules of an אשם
תלוי. asham talui. עד שלא נסקל, ad shelo niska, what happens? That
basically you assumed this ox gored and then you found out that
the עדים edim were lying, okay, that it didn't gore. So עד
שלא נסקל, ad shelo niska, if you find out before it's been
stoned, יצא וירעה בעדר. yeitzei v'yireh ba'eder. Go ahead and put it
back in the flock. The whole גמר דין gmar din was a
mistake, right? It's like the governor calling up a second before the
execution, right? The whole גמר דין gmar din was a mistake, so
fine, it's not a שור
הנסקל. shor haniskal. משנסקל, misheniskal, after it was stoned you found out
it was a mistake, מותר בהנאה. mutar behana'ah. It still doesn't, it
no longer is a שור הנסקל, shor haniskal, it's a נבלה, but
you still not a שור הנסקל shor haniskal once you found out
the truth and you can derive benefit from it. עגלה ערופה egla
arufa is the same. עגלה ערופה egla arufa is also not like
the אשם תלוי. asham talui. What me, the עגלה ערופה egla arufa
now?
עגלה ערופה egla arufa is the one thing you would think would
be like an אשם תלוי asham talui because it's about a doubt
who the murderer is. So let's talk about what happens if you
find out who the murderer is in the middle of the process.
Okay, עד
שלא נערפה, ad shelo ne'erfah, if you found out who the murderer
was before you broke the neck, תצא ותרעה בעדר. teitzei v'teira'eh ba'eder.
Put it back in the flock. Now here that's just like an
אשם תלוי asham talui except here presumably even חכמים chachamim agree to
this. By the אשם תלוי asham talui they're saying that that was,
so we'll discuss why in the גמרא, Gemara. but why don't you
say well both of them were because of a ספק? safek? So
this too, now it could also be that עגלה ערופה egla arufa
maybe doesn't have קדושה, kedusha, so it doesn't get the status yet,
okay, but it is interesting why do the, this is the one
that is most similar to an אשם תלוי, asham talui, why is,
why
and this position so far is Rabbi Meir, why do the חכמים
chachamim here agree? So we'll talk about that. משנערפה, mishene'erfah, after the
neck is broken, תקבר במקומה. tikaver bimkomah. Then you bury it where
it was, meaning
where you broke the neck. שספק בא מתחילה, כפרה ספיקה והלכה לה.
she'safek ba mitechilah, kaperas sefeikah vehalchah lah. So just one minute, let
me just check what רש"י Rashi says here.
Right, so again this is actually like the אשם תלוי. asham talui.
If you went ahead and you broke its neck, it's like by
the אשם תלוי asham talui you were זורק הדם, zorek hadam, so
at the moment you broke its neck there was a doubt, so
therefore it gets the status of עגלה ערופה egla arufa because at
the moment you broke the neck the doubt was present and that's
what it says at the end. שספק בא מתחילה, she'safek ba mitechilah,
it was brought for a ספק, safek, כפרה ספיקה, kaperas sefeikah, so
it atoned for the ספק safek at the moment that the neck
was broken, והלכה לה vehalchah lah means and it did its job.
So therefore the fact that you found the guy afterwards doesn't change
its status as an עגלה ערופה egla arufa because at the moment
there was the ספק safek that it was being brought for. So
actually this whole thing seems to be exactly like an אשם תלוי.
asham talui. What do you mean it's not like an אשם תלוי?
asham talui? The only difference is that here the חכמים chachamim agree
to Rabbi Meir and the חכמים chachamim say that if you found
out before you would put it back in the flock. Why do
they agree to Rabbi Meir? Is it because עגלה ערופה egla arufa
is fundamentally a different type of a thing? Is it because somehow
the atoning for murder is different than, you know, the atonement of
a sin? Or maybe it's a more simple point that there's קדושה
kedusha in the first case and there's not קדושה kedusha in the
second? So we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's just
read one line
of
גמרא. במאי פליגי רבי מאיר, במאי פליגי? bemai paligi Rabbi Meir, bemai
paligi?
What's the debate of Rabbi Meir and the חכמים chachamim about if
it's found out whether it was a קדושה kedusha or not? Rabbi
Meir סבר כיון דלא צריך ליה לא מקדיש ליה. savar keivan delo
tzarich lei lo makdish lei. It turns out I didn't need it
so I didn't want to sanctify so it wasn't a good sanctity.
רבנן סברי מתוך לבו נוקפו, Rabbanan savri mitosh libo nokfo,
look, because your heart beats within you like, you know,
troubles you, because of it was because of your psychological doubt, so
גמר ומקדיש. gamar umakdish. So therefore you sanctified it even if it
turns out you didn't sin, you knew at the time you might
have sinned and you still sanctified it. תנא *Tana* now מתניתין *Matnitin*
our Mishnah said you found out you didn't sin and the ברייתא
*Braitah* we talk בין שנודע שלא חטא ובין שנודע שחטא *bein shenoda
shelo chata uvein shenoda shechata* פליגי רבי מאיר ורבנן *pligi Rabbi Meir
v'Rabbanan* פליגי *pligi*, right? They argue both ways. Either way you don't
need the אשם תלוי *asham talui*, whether you turned out you did
sin or you turned out you don't. Once you know ודאי *vadai*
what you did, you don't need the אשם תלוי *asham talui*. So
פליגי רבי מאיר ורבנן *pligi Rabbi Meir v'Rabbanan*. ובנודע שחטא *u'benoda shechata*,
I'm sorry, so they when in the case where it where you
know you sinned, why do they argue, why פליגי רבי מאיר ורבנן
*pligi Rabbi Meir v'Rabbanan*, why do they argue? להודיע כוחו דרבי מאיר
*l'hodia kocho d'Rabbi Meir* to tell you the strength of רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* דאף על גב דידע דחטא *d'af al gav d'yada d'chata*,
even though it turns out that you sinned, you did something worse
than that, you know, the worst possibility, nevertheless כיון דבעידנא דאפרשה לא
ידע *keivan d'be'idna d'afrasha lo yada* תצא ותרעה בעדר *tetzei v'tireh ba'eder*.
So you could say, oh, if I wind up I did sin
and I have to obligate it, then I would certainly have wanted
to brought this קרבן *korban*. No, at the end of the day,
whether you did sin or didn't, at the time you sanctified it,
right, you did not you would not have wanted to sanctify it
if you wouldn't have needed it. So there's two reasons why you
don't need it, because you sinned or because you didn't. Okay, so
ובנודע שלא חטא *u'benoda shelo chata*, when you know you didn't sin,
להודיע כוחו דרבנן *l'hodia kocho d'Rabbanan* to tell you the רבנן *Rabbanan*
that even though you're totally off the hook, דאף על גב דלא
חטא *d'af al gav d'lo chata*, כיון דבעידנא דאפרשה לא ידע *keivan
d'be'idna d'afrasha lo yada*, since at the time you didn't know what
the story was, ליבו נוקפו *libo nokfo*, therefore your heart sort of,
you know, pounds within you, disturbs you, הלכך גמר ומקדיש *hilkach gamar
u'makdish*, and
therefore you sanctify it even though even if it turns out in
the end that you had not actually sinned. Okay, so just to
continue to...