Right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, דף י"ז, Daf Yud Zayin, and we
finish up today with discussing גופין מחולקין על השבת Gufin Mechulakin Al
HaShabbos and then move on to a new פרק. Perek. So, we
pick up on דף י"ז עמוד ב' Daf Yud Zayin Amud Beis
and we are about, let's see where we are, we're about אביי's
Abaye statement. אמר ליה אביי, Amar Lei Abaye, the line starts with
the word ליה אביי, Lei Abaye, it's about ten lines before the
lines get wide. And basically, if you remember רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer had a discussion/debate in the משנה Mishnah
where about many, about תולדות, Toldos, are many תולדות Toldos one or
many for חטאת, Chatos, which really wasn't discussed, just raised. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says many, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the consensus is one.
But the thing we are focusing on is multiple שבתות. Shabbosos. Is
that the same מלאכה Melacha multiple שבתות, Shabbosos, is that גופין מחולקין
Gufin Mechulakin or not? רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says at the end,
seems to push that it's not גופין מחולקין, Gufin Mechulakin, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer said that it was. So anyway, רבא Rava just framed
the point that if it's about having forgotten שבת, Shabbos, then that's
a different issue. That's whether the days between are like a ידיעה
Yedi'ah or not, and that everybody would agree is considered a ידיעה
בינתיים. Yedi'ah Beintayim. The question was whether you knew it was שבת,
Shabbos, but you forgot about the מלאכות, Melachos, and whether שבת Shabbos
is גופין מחולקין, Gufin Mechulakin, that was the discussion, and at the
end רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it is גופין מחולקין Gufin Mechulakin
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says not. And now we continue with
the statement of אביי, Abaye, which has a slightly different version of
what they were discussing, but agrees in the end what their positions
are. So אמר ליה אביי, Amar Lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said back
to רבא, Rava, what did they then answer? This is the heat.
לעולם אימא לך, Le'olam Eima Lach, I would really have to tell
you, זדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות, Zadon Shabbos VeShiggas Melachos, פשיטא ליה לרבי
עקיבא דשבתות לאו כגופין דמיין. Peshita Lei LeRabbi Akiva DeShabbosos Lav KeGufin
Damyon. So actually, he's just saying that the discussion was different, but
the conclusion is the same. Really רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't even
bother talking to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer about the question about knowing
it was שבת Shabbos and forgetting the מלאכות, Melachos, and he took
it for granted that different שבתות, Shabbosos, the same מלאכה Melacha on
different שבתות Shabbosos is גופין מחולקין. Gufin Mechulakin. That he took for
granted, that he wasn't even discussing with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. That
is כגופין דמיין. KeGufin Damyon. שגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות, Shiggas Shabbos VeZadon
Melachos, היא דבעי מיניה. Hi DeBa'ei Minei. His question was when you
forgot it was שבת, Shabbos, and what happens, what happens then from
one שבת Shabbos to the next? ימים שבינתיים מי הוי ידיעה לחלק
או לא? Yamim SheBeintayim Mi Havei Yedi'ah LeChaleik O Lo? Are the
days in between like you remembered and does it make, does it
divide it? So that was the discussion. We took for granted different
שבתות Shabbosos were גופין מחולקין. Gufin Mechulakin. The question is if you
forgot it was שבת, Shabbos, are the days in between like you
remembered? ופשיט ליה דימים שבינתיים לחלק. U'Pashit Lei DeYamim SheBeintayim LeChaleik. And
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said to him, yes, those days in between
are like you remembered and do divide it. וקיבל מיניה, VeKibel Minei,
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva accepted it. So according to this version,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva actually accepted רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer response, that
because now the discussion was not about גופין מחולקין Gufin Mechulakin but
about whether the days in between divide. And there רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer said yes, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva accepted. ופשיט ליה ולד
מלאכות כמלאכות דמיין. U'Pashit Lei Velad Melachos KeMelachos Damyon.
Now regarding the other question, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said to him
that different תולדות Toldos count as if they're different אבות Avos and
count for different חטאות. Chata'os. ולא קיבל מיניה, VeLo Kibel Minei, and
that he did not accept. So according to this, really the only
question is what did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva take for granted, what
were they discussing? According to one version, he took for granted the
days in between divide, the discussion was whether גופין מחולקין, Gufin Mechulakin,
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wound up saying they're not גופין מחולקין.
Gufin Mechulakin. And according to the other version, it was the other
thing. They flipped. But either way, the conclusion is the same. And
it makes sense, right? The idea that if you forgot it was
שבת Shabbos and then six days passed, we consider it like you
remembered in between, that we're taking for granted that forgetting שבת Shabbos
and days pass, that is, that is ידיעה לחלק. Yedi'ah LeChaleik. The
only question is multiple things on multiple שבתות, Shabbosos, remembering it's שבת,
Shabbos, and there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that that is not,
that that is not גופין מחולקין. Gufin Mechulakin. Okay, so the same,
just for the reason we said before, that the only precedent of
גופין מחולקין Gufin Mechulakin was about עריות, Arayos, and there the people
were, you know, it was really different people involved and that made
it different. Okay, so according to both אביי Abaye and רבא Rava
that's the position for רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Different שבתות Shabbosos is
considered not גופין מחולקין, Gufin Mechulakin, the same thing repeated is one
חטאת, Chatos, and whereas forgetting שבת Shabbos and then it's a different
שבת, Shabbos, that's like you remembered and that's multiple חטאות. Chata'os. Now
we go on to רב חסדא Rav Chisda who has a different
opinion not only in what they were debating or discussing, but also
in what רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position was. רב חסדא אמר, Rav
Chisda Amar, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, now we are three lines
before the lines get wide, זדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות, Zadon Shabbos VeShiggas
Melachos, אפילו רבי עקיבא מודי דכגופין דמיין. Afillu Rabbi Akiva Modei DeKeGufin
Damyon.
No, if you remembered it was שבת Shabbos and you made mistakes
about the מלאכות, Melachos, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva actually says that different
שבתות Shabbosos are גופין מחולקין. Gufin Mechulakin. Okay, very different than what
we've said before, although that seemed to be the whole debate in
the משנה. Mishnah. We'll see later how he reads the משנה, Mishnah,
but he is actually saying no, the same way different women are
גופין מחולקין, Gufin Mechulakin, different שבתות Shabbosos are גופין מחולקין. Gufin Mechulakin.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva accepted that from the get-go. Okay, same מלאכה
Melacha on different שבתות, Shabbosos, different חטאות, Chata'os, גופין מחולקין. Gufin Mechulakin.
What do you do by the fact, by the way, that the
earlier משנה Mishnah that we quoted said that if you... forget the
מלאכות melachos and you do it on different שבתות, Shabbosos, חייב על
כל מלאכה ומלאכה? chayav al kol melacha u'melacha? So he would say
חייב על כל מלאכה ומלאכה chayav al kol melacha u'melacha for every
type of שבת. Shabbos. So if you forgot three מלאכות melachos and
you did it on this שבת Shabbos and next and the next
and the next, you would bring I don't know 12 or 15
חטאות chataos for however many different שבתות Shabbosos you repeated it for.
Okay, so that's what he says. He says...
Did everyone agree to that?
What do you mean everyone?
I mean רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer certainly, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva too,
right?
Yeah, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is always having multiple, you know, חטאות. chataos. Okay,
so רבי עקיבא... Rabbi Akiva... so רב חסדא Rav Chisda starts by
saying, no, you guys are wrong, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says different
שבתות Shabbosos are גופים מחולקים. gufim me'chulakim. וכי בעי מיניה ששת ימי
שבת זדון ומלאכות שבהן מיניה, ve'chi ba'ei minei shishat yemei Shabbos zadon
u'melachos she'ba'hen minei,
and the question was about remember... about forgetting it was שבת Shabbos
and... and then what... and
knowing that it's a forbidden מלאכה melacha but forgetting it's שבת. Shabbos.
הוא דבעי מיניה, hu de'ba'ei minei, דימים שבינתים הוי ידיעה לחלק, de'yamim
she'be'ntayim havi yedi'ah le'chalek, are the days in between from one שבת
Shabbos to the next like you remembered or not? ופשט ליה, u'pashat
lei, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer concluded, you know, responded to him,
ימים שבינתים הוי ידיעה לחלק, yamim she'be'ntayim havi yedi'ah le'chalek, it is
like it divided. וקיבל מיניה, ve'kibel minei, and you know what? In
the end of the day רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva accepted that answer.
So according to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, both רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer conclude with a maximum number of חטאות,
chataos, that both different שבתות Shabbosos are גופין דמיין, gufin damyan, same
מלאכה melacha on different שבתות Shabbosos is multiple חטאות, chataos, and also
forgetting שבת Shabbos and then days pass and it's the next שבת
Shabbos is like you remembered in between, ידיעה לחלק. yedi'ah le'chalek. So
both of those רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
agree in the end. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer responded to him about
בהמה, behema, עריות, arayot, and he thinks in the end that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva accepted רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer response. And in the
end both שבת Shabbos is גופים מחולקים gufim me'chulakim and the days
that pass is ידיעה לחלק. yedi'ah le'chalek. So do they debate about
anything? So... so ופשט ליה, u'pashat lei, yes, the one thing they
debate about is many תולדות toldot of the same אב. av. ופשט
ליה דולדי מלאכות כמלאכות דמיין, u'pashat lei de'vlad melachos ke'melachos damyan,
multiple תולדות toldot of one אב av count... רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says counts as multiple for multiple חטאות, chataos, ולא קיבל מיניה ve'lo
kibel minei and that's the one thing he did not accept. Okay,
so basically the way it boils down is like this: according to
everybody agrees for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer everything is multiple חטאות, chataot,
right? Whether it's remembering... it's like you remembered in between or שבת
Shabbos גופין. gufin. The question is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. According to
אביי ורבא, Abaye ve'Rava, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says different שבתות Shabbosos
is... is not גופים מחולקים, gufim me'chulakim, right? That's the whole debate.
You compare it to women, I think no, those are people, this
is objects, and therefore it's all like the same thing repeated, it's
not גופים מחולקים. gufim me'chulakim. The one thing that does divide is
if you forget it was שבת Shabbos and then the next שבת
Shabbos came, it's like you remembered in between, ידיעה לחלק. yedi'ah le'chalek.
That's אביי ורבא. Abaye ve'Rava. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says no, at
the end of the day רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says both things
divide. Both it's גופים מחולקים gufim me'chulakim and it's ידיעה לחלק. yedi'ah
le'chalek. But again, the... the emphasis is that he says even רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in the end agrees that multiple שבתות Shabbosos is
גופים מחולקים, gufim me'chulakim, אביי ורבא Abaye ve'Rava say that is not
true. Okay, so now what we're going to have to do at
one point is like this: we read the משנה, Mishna, I think
the simple sense of the משנה Mishna
is
like אביי ורבא, Abaye ve'Rava, they're debating גופים מחולקים, gufim me'chulakim, they're
comparing it to animals, to women, to this, to that, is it
גופים מחולקים gufim me'chulakim or not גופים מחולקים. gufim me'chulakim. According to
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, he says that they're discussing whether the time
that passes is ידיעה לחלק. yedi'ah le'chalek. So what does that have
to do with נידה? niddah? What does that have to do with
animals? You know, how's that related? According to him the question is
about whether the time that passes from one שבת Shabbos to another
makes it like you remembered in between. So we'll see in the
גמרא Gemara how later how רב חסדא Rav Chisda reads the משנה.
Mishna. But in the end אביי ורבא Abaye ve'Rava say the discussion
is whether it's גופים מחולקים gufim me'chulakim and in the end רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's not, and according to רב חסדא Rav
Chisda the discussion in the משנה Mishna is whether it's ידיעה לחלק
yedi'ah le'chalek and in the end רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva winds up
agreeing to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that it is ידיעה לחלק. yedi'ah
le'chalek. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Let's take a
look.
אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, so three lines down the wide
line, said רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, מנא אמינא לה, mina amina la,
where do I get this from? דתניא, de'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, Baraita, הכותב שתי אותיות בהעלם אחד חייב. ha'kotev shtei otiyot be'he'elem
echad chayav. Let's say you write two letters on שבת, Shabbos, one
state of forgetfulness, you're חייב, chayav, obviously. בבתי העלמות, be'vtei helamot, now,
you wrote one letter, then you remembered, whoops, it's שבת Shabbos or
whoops I'm not allowed to write, then you forgot again and you
wrote another letter. So this is the question about whether when you
remember in the middle of a מלאכה melacha does it divide the
מלאכה melacha or not? Right? We until now we've been talking about
remembering so that you bring two חטאות, chataos, that increases your obligation.
Will remembering in the middle also prevent you from being obligated? Could
it divide the מלאכה melacha in halves? So what's the הלכה? halacha?
רבן גמליאל מחייב, Rabban Gamliel mechayev, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says you're
חייב, chayav, וחכמים פוטרין. ve'chachamim potrin. The חכמים Chachamim say you're exempt.
So רבי אליעזר... Rabbi Eliezer... so חכמים Chachamim say reminding always divides
whether multiple קרבנות korbanot or to... or to exempt you. And רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says no, it only divides in order to increase
your קרבנות, korbanot, but it will not divide to get you off
the hook. Okay, so that's called... okay, so that's called
אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. ein yedi'ah le-chatzi shi'ur. He does admit that
if you write one letter on this שבת Shabbos and one letter
on the next שבת, Shabbos, you are exempt. Why? Because that's not
just about ידיעה. yediyah. What is it if you do it on
a different שבת? Shabbos? That is... what's the other thing other than
ידיעה yediyah from one שבת Shabbos to the next? גופין מחולקים. gufin
m'chulakim. That's considered fundamentally different acts. So that presumably is based on
the גופין מחולקים gufin m'chulakim principle.
דתניא אחריתי, De-tanya achrisi, we taught another ברייתא. Braisa.
הכותב שתי אותיות בשתי שבתות,
Ha-kosev shtei
osiyos
b'shtei Shabbasos, if
you wrote two letters on two שבתות, Shabbasos, אחת בשבת זו ואחת
בשבת זו, echad b'Shabbos zu v'echad b'Shabbos zu, רבן גמליאל מחייב. Rabban
Gamliel mechayev. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel actually says that if you write
it on different שבתות, Shabbasos, you're חייב, chayav, which basically means that
it's not even גופין מחולקים, gufin m'chulakim, okay? וחכמים פוטרין, V'chachamim potrin,
the חכמים Chachamim exempt. So
anyway we have a contradiction, would רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel obligate you
one letter on this שבת, Shabbos, one letter on the next. קסלקא
דעתך, Kasalka daitach, now we're going to assume דרבן גמליאל כרבי עקיבא
סבירא ליה, d'Rabban Gamliel k'Rabbi Akiva s'vira lei, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
holds like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay now, which now,
so through רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel we're going to try to figure
out the position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So here's what רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says.
בשלמא לדידי דאמינא זדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות ואליבא דרבי עקיבא אומר דשבת
גופין דמיין, Bishlama l'didi d'amina zadin Shabbos v'shigegas melachos v'aliba d'Rabbi Akiva
omer d'Shabbos gufin damyan, I say that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would
say that if you remembered it was שבת Shabbos and you just
forgot that this thing was prohibited, that שבת Shabbos has a status
of גופין מחולקים. gufin m'chulakim. According to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, שבת
Shabbos divides in two ways. Number one, if you remembered it was
שבת, Shabbos, שבת Shabbos is גופין מחולקים, gufin m'chulakim, and number two,
if you forgot it was שבת, Shabbos, then from one שבת Shabbos
to the next it's like you remembered. Okay now, assuming that, I
can explain the two positions of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. How? The
following way. הא דתניא פטור, Ha d'tanya patur, when רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel said one שבת Shabbos and the next שבת Shabbos you're פטור,
patur, בזדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות. b'zadin Shabbos v'shigegas melachos. That's when you
remembered it was שבת. Shabbos. So if you remembered it was שבת,
Shabbos, what do we say when you go from one שבת Shabbos
to the next? גופין מחולקים, gufin m'chulakim, according to his version of
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דשבת כגופין דמיין. D'Shabbos k'gufin damyan. It's considered
completely different things and therefore one letter from one שבת Shabbos does
not combine with one letter from the next. הא דתניא חייב, Ha
d'tanya chayav, top of י"ז עמוד א', yud-zayin amud aleph, how about
where do we say that according to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel you're
חייב chayav if you write one letter on one שבת, Shabbos, one
on the next? That's the case of בשגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות. b'shigegas
Shabbos v'zadin melachos. That's when you forgot it was שבת. Shabbos. So
what do we say when you forget it's שבת Shabbos and it's
one שבת Shabbos to the next? What do we say about the
days that passed? It's like you, right, if you forget it's שבת,
Shabbos, days that passed like you remembered. So that's the principle of
ידיעה. yediyah. Ah, but what's רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel position about when
you remember between one letter and the next? His position is that
it doesn't break it up, okay? דקסבר אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. D'kasavar
ein yediyah l'chatzi shiur. It does not break it up. So he
says like this: we have a contradiction of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
if you write one letter one שבת, Shabbos, one on the next.
I can work it out. I'm going to assume רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
So if you write one letter one שבת, Shabbos, one on the
next, and you knew it was שבת Shabbos both times, then we
have a principle of גופין מחולקים, gufin m'chulakim, then they don't divide.
If however you didn't know it was
שבת... Shabbos... they don't divide? They do divide, excuse me, they don't
combine. If you knew, if you forgot it was שבת Shabbos and
one letter on one and one on the next, in that case
even though it's like you remembered, that does not divide it for
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and in that case you're going to be
חייב. chayav. So I can work it all out, assuming רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says both גופין מחולקים gufin m'chulakim and ידיעה לחלק. yediyah l'challek. אלא
לרבא, Ella l'Rava, but according to רבא, Rava, it's also אביי Abaye
anyway, דאמר סבירא ליה לרבי עקיבא דשבת גוף אחד הן, d'amar s'vira
lei l'Rabbi Akiva d'Shabbos guf echad hein, that שבת Shabbos is considered
one unit, מרובה שבתות, meruba Shabbasos, multiple שבתות. Shabbasos. So how according
to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel are you ever going to get it
not to combine? Right? If you always say that all שבתות Shabbasos
count as one big thing, so then it should always combine according
to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So בשלמא הא דתניא חייב, bishlama ha
d'tanya chayav, the fact that you're חייב chayav from one שבת Shabbos
to the next I get, משתכח לה בין בזדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות,
mishtachach la bein b'zadin Shabbos v'shigegas melachos, whether you say you remembered
it was שבת, Shabbos, דשבת גוף אחד דמיין, d'Shabbos guf echad damyan,
the fact that it's one שבת Shabbos to the next doesn't divide
because it's all one גוף, guf, ובין בשגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות, u'vein
b'shigegas Shabbos v'zadin melachos, or if you forgot it was שבת, Shabbos,
then even though from one שבת Shabbos to the next it's like
you remembered, that's also not going to divide, דקסבר אין ידיעה לחצי
שיעור, D'kasavar ein yediyah l'chatzi shiur, that remembering for doing half a
מלאכה melacha doesn't divide. So I get why you're always חייב. chayav.
You're חייב chayav because even if it's like you remembered, that doesn't
divide, and because of גופין מחולקים, gufin m'chulakim, well we don't say
גופין מחולקים. gufin m'chulakim. So I get why according to רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel you're going to be חייב. chayav. What I don't get
is when you can be פטור patur according to רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. אלא הא דתניא פטור, Ella ha d'tanya patur, but that which
we say that you're פטור patur according to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
במאי מוקמת לה? b'mai mokmas la? How are you going to explain
why you're פטור? patur? לא בהא ולא בהא, Lo b'ha v'lo b'ha,
it doesn't work with one or the other. Okay, meaning, so what
we're saying now is like assuming
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva? fine. You worked out רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
as long as you hold גופין מחולקים, gufin mechulakim, fine. So who
says he has to be רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva. Let him go
like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. we all know
says גופין מחולקים. gufin mechulakim. דשבתות כגופין דמיין. de-shabbosot ke-gufin damyan. And
he says Shabbos is like גופין. gufin. So what we have רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel saying remembering doesn't divide two halves, but clearly what
would divide is גופין מחולקים. gufin mechulakim. And we have רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel saying in some cases they don't combine. So that obviously
means רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds of גופין מחולקים. gufin mechulakim. But
it doesn't prove רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva, Maybe it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer, גופין מחולקים. gufin mechulakim. Yes.
Weren't רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer a generation
before?
Yeah, but it just means he holds of that position. Okay, I
mean, right, he doesn't have to hold like a contemporary, he can
hold like an earlier position. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, one minute. והא מדקתני ומודה רבן גמליאל, Ve-ha mi-de-katani u-modeh Rabban
Gamliel, now this is going to get... והא מדקתני ומודה רבן גמליאל,
ve-ha mi-de-katani u-modeh Rabban Gamliel, מכלל דפליגי אחריני סיפא. mikhlal de-paligi achrini
sei. It says רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel agrees one Shabbos to the
next you're פטור. pattur. That sounds like there are other cases he
disagrees with. Now the גמרא Gemara makes a strange assumption because, right,
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel already said if you remember between two letters
you're going to be חייב. chayav. But he agrees that if it's
one Shabbos and the next you're going to be פטור. pattur. So
when it says he agrees one Shabbos to the next you're going
to be פטור, pattur, it says implicitly there's something he argues on.
It's clear what he argues on. He argues on when it's the
same Shabbos, remembering in between is not going to exempt you, you'll
be חייב. chayav. But the גמרא Gemara is going to assume when
he says he agrees at one Shabbos and the next you're פטור,
pattur, it's implicit that he argues on something. What he's arguing on
is
the patron of his opinion. Meaning, given that we're saying that רבן
גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel opinion about גופין מחולקים gufin mechulakim is either learned
from רבי... is either based on רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or based
on רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer we're going to assume that this statement
that, oh, I agree with you here but I disagree with you
somewhere else, is not disagreeing with the חכמים Chachamim about remembering between
letters. It's disagreeing with the opinion from which he sourced this idea
of גופין מחולקים. gufin mechulakim. So that's a pretty weird assumption, but
the גמרא Gemara assumes that. And now we're going to say that
if רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel is following רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, we
have to find a place where he disagrees with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer, Not disagrees about two letters and remembering in between, but disagrees
with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. That's going to be the question. והא
מדקתני ומודה רבן גמליאל, Ve-ha mi-de-katani u-modeh Rabban Gamliel, since it said
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel agrees from one Shabbos to the next you're
פטור pattur because of גופין מחולקים, gufin mechulakim, מכלל דפליגי אחריני סיפא.
mikhlal de-paligi achrini sei. It sounds like he argues on another opinion
of this like patron of his opinion. אי אמרת בשלמא כרבי עקיבא
סבירא ליה, Iy amrat bishlama ke-Rabbi Akiva sevira leh, so if he
is getting his opinion of גופין מחולקים gufin mechulakim from רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva היינו דפליגי בשגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות. haynu de-paligi be-shigegat Shabbos
ve-zedon melachos.
So then we can have a case where he disagrees with רבן
גמליאל... Rabban Gamliel with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. What is it? You
forget it's Shabbos and you remember the מלאכות. melachos. ד רבן גמליאל
סבר אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. De-Rabban Gamliel savar ein yedi'ah le-chatzi shi'ur.
Because what happens if you go from one Shabbos to the next?
But what happened was you forgot it was Shabbos. So what would
be the story there? What would רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, say? רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, would say it's like you remembered in between and
that makes it not combine. Okay, but רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel, would
say even if it's like you remembered in between, it doesn't prevent
it from combining because אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. ein yedi'ah l'chatzi shi'ur.
So that's where they would debate. They wouldn't only debate two letters
on the same Shabbos, they could even debate a case about one
letter on one and one on the next if the issue was
you forgot it was Shabbos. Because then remembering in between would not
matter for רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel. but it would matter for רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva Okay. ומודה רבן גמליאל, U-modeh Rabban Gamliel, so A,
they disagree when it's one Shabbos to the next and you forgot
it was Shabbos. It's like you remembered, that matters for רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva not for רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel ומודה רבן גמליאל בזדון
שבת ושגגת מלאכות, U-modeh Rabban Gamliel be-zedon Shabbos ve-shigegat melachos, but if
you remembered it was Shabbos, there he agrees שפטור, she-pattur, why? אמה
שבת כגופין דמיין. Ama Shabbos ke-gufin damyan. Because then it's גופין מחולקים.
gufin mechulakim. So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel clearly says Shabbos is כגופין
מחולקים, ke-gufin mechulakim, one Shabbos and the next if you remembered it
was Shabbos, you're פטור. pattur. Who is... where does he disagree with?
So if he's learning it from רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva he disagrees
when you forgot it was Shabbos. There everybody agrees it's like you
remembered, but for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it matters, for רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel it doesn't matter. That works. אלא אי אמרת רבן גמליאל
כרבי אליעזר סבירא ליה, Ella iy amrat Rabban Gamliel ke-Rabbi Eliezer sevira
leh, first wide line, if he's holding like רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer.
מכלל דפליגי, mikhlal de-paligi, there must be a case where he disagrees
with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer, מאי במאי? Mai be-mai? What? Now why
not say the same thing? It's when you... it's like you remembered
between the two שבתות, Shabbosos, so רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says that
doesn't help you, maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. would say it divides.
No, we know רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't say that. אי בשגגת
שבת וזדון מלאכות, Iy be-shigegat Shabbos ve-zedon melachos, if like we tried
to say before, you forgot it was Shabbos and therefore from one
Shabbos to the next it's like you remembered, and רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel. would say that wouldn't divide, and maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would say it would divide. No, we know that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer agrees to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel אפילו רבי אליעזר כרבן גמליאל
סבירא ליה. Afillu Rabbi Eliezer ke-Rabban Gamliel sevira leh. He holds like
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that remembering between two halves does not divide.
ואין ידיעה לחצי שיעור, Ve-ein yedi'ah le-chatzi shi'ur, that you... that knowing
after doing half does not divide.
Therefore you are חייב, chayav, right?
And therefore he's going to say you are חייב. chayav. So, right.
דתניא, De-tanya, how do we know that? הכותב שתי אותיות בשתי שבתות,
Ha-kotev shtei otiyot bi-shtei Shabbosos, exactly the same case, if you write
two letters on two different שבתות, Shabbosos, אחת
בשבת זו ואחת בשבת זו. ahat be-Shabbos zu ve-ahat be-Shabbos zu. one
on the next, רבי אליעזר מחייב. Rabbi Eliezer mechayev. So רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says you're חייב. chayav. Now it can't be that you
remembered it was שבת, Shabbos, then it was גופי מחולקין. gufei mecholakin.
So when is he saying you're חייב? chayav? It must be you
forgot it was שבת, Shabbos, it's like you remembered in between and
אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. ein yedi'ah l'chatzi shi'ur. So what you are
seeing is the following. Now both רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer are saying that שבת Shabbos is גופי מחולקין gufei
mecholakin and if you forgot it was שבת, Shabbos, it's like you
remembered in between. They both also say that if you remembered in
between, אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. ein yedi'ah l'chatzi shi'ur.
So assuming what it says רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel in this case
agrees that you're פטור patur when it's one שבת Shabbos to the
next saying גופי מחולקין. gufei mecholakin. So but where does he disagree
with רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer Assuming that his it's in reference to
רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer? In this case I agree with רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer. that you're פטור. patur. Where do you disagree? If it
was forgetting it was שבת Shabbos and remembering in between, the same
way you say you're חייב, chayav, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you're
חייב, chayav, you both agree אין ידיעה לחצי שיעור. So where would
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel disagree with רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer Okay, although
this is for some reason assuming that the one he's disagreeing with
had to be the patron of his position. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: אלא, Ella, rather, here's where they disagree. באחת
על האריג. be'achas al ha'arig. Let's say you have a case similar
to חצי שיעור, chatzi shi'ur, but it's not exactly the same. What
happens if you normally are חייב chayav only if you weave, you
know, two whatever, two weaves, two strings. Let's say however you had
something that was already being woven and there were already three strings
present and you just added a fourth when שבת Shabbos came. So
is that חייב? chayav? On the one hand you've done something significant
in the context that there were already three strings. On the other
hand you only did one string, not two. So you could go
either way. So maybe that's what they debate, that similar to the
idea of one letter on one שבת, Shabbos, one on the next,
you come into שבת Shabbos with something half done and you finish
it. Is that significant or not? So maybe that's where they debate.
Maybe that's where רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel would say that case I'm
going to say חייב chayav and here I'll say פטור, patur, two
different שבתות, shabbosos, but that there I'll say חייב chayav and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? will disagree with me and say פטור. patur. You
can't say that. Why? Because we know, the גמרא Gemara says, רבי
אליעזר מחייב. Rabbi Eliezer mechayev. We know that even רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer also says you're חייב chayav in that case. דתנן, Ditnan, רבי
אליעזר אומר האורג שלשה חוטין בתחילה, Rabbi Eliezer omer ha'oreg sheloshah chutin
bitchilah, if you do three strings at the outset, ואחד על האריג
חייב, ve'echad al ha'arig chayav, or if you add one string on
something that was already woven, you're חייב. chayav. So it can't be
that they're debating this which is somewhat analogous. That here רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel, says פטור, patur, but in another case he would say
חייב. chayav. He would disagree with רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer It can't
be this idea of adding the string because there also רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer. says חייב. chayav. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, no, מכלל
דפליג בחדא. michlal depalig bechada.
Here's where they disagree in the case of דתניא. detanya.
Here's the case they disagree in this ברייתא Braisa case. הוציא חצי
גרוגרת וחזר והוציא חצי גרוגרת בהעלם אחד חייב. hotzi chatzi gogeres vechazar
vehotzi chatzi gogeres be'helam echad chayav.
Similar, very similar type of case. When you carry on שבת, Shabbos,
you're only חייב chayav if you carry an amount equal to the
size of a גרוגרת, gogeres, of a pressed date. So now what
happens if you did half, okay, and then you did another half?
It's like writing one letter and then writing another letter. So if
it's all in one state of forgetfulness, you're חייב. chayav. בשתי העלמות
פטור. bishtei helamos patur. If you remember in between, you're exempt. This
is the idea of יש ידיעה לחצי שיעור. yesh yedi'ah l'chatzi shi'ur.
You remembered in between the two halves of the thing you carried.
רבי יוסי אומר בהעלם אחד ברשות אחת חייב. Rabbi Yosi omer be'helam
echad birshus achas chayav.
If it is one state of forgetfulness and you brought both halves
to the same place, you brought them both to the same street,
then you're חייב. chayav. בשתי רשויות פטור. bishtei reshuyos patur.
Let's say you brought a half to Broadway and the other half
to, I don't know, Columbus Avenue, assuming they're both רשות הרבים, reshus
harabbim, out of your house. So then you're פטור. patur. Those two
halves don't combine, they're in different places. Okay, that's a pretty reasonable
thing to say. Okay, now maybe if you did it intentionally it
would combine, but again for the sake of about whether you did
it unintentionally and do they combine for a חטאת, chatas, there he's
saying it does not combine. Okay, פטור. patur. רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel
now, so here you have an interesting debate which is, and it's
similar, right? Until now we're talking about do two halves combine. So
here you have a debate, do two halves combine when they are
into different רשויות. reshuyos. That the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says they
do and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says and who is it, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says they don't. So this maybe is the case
because there's no reason to say רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer have an opinion about this, but we're trying to
find something they could be disagreeing about. Something that is similar to
the two letters, that maybe that's an area they disagree with. Okay,
so that's what we're going to say. דתנא קמא deTanna Kamma רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says here by two שבתות, shabbosos, there I say
you're exempt. In other cases I say you're חייב. chayav. What would
that be? Two separate רשויות, reshuyos, each half of an amount. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer כרבי יוסי. keRabbi Yosi. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would say that no, even in that case you are exempt. Okay,
so that was a very long discussion, but basically the פשט pshat
is is that we're trying to find רבן גמליאל's position, one letter
one שבת, Shabbos, one on the other, sometimes they combine, sometimes they
don't, to prove the difference about גופי מחלקין gufei mechalekin that when
it's גופי מחלקין gufei mechalekin they don't combine, when it's like you
remembered in between they do combine and the question is does that
prove that that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position of גופי מחלקין gufei
mechalekin or is he only talking within רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer And
once we said that he was talking within רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer?
somehow we had to assume that it meant that he was debating
something else with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, and we found something analogous
to say they were debating, which was the case about two half
שיעורים shiurim into two different רשויות, reshuyot, one into one רשות היחיד,
reshus hayachid, the other into another.
So it was even more מחמיר machmir on רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
then?
Yes. Okay, so now we go on. That's the end. That was
all one long proof of trying to prove what רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says. Now we are thankfully going to end by bringing this
to our משנה mishna and trying to figure out what works out
in our משנה. mishna. Now again, remember our משנה, mishna, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer tried to prove it from נדה. nidah. And רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva, says, no, no, no, נדה nidah they're active participants, that's
different. Okay, then he tries to prove from a קטנה, ketanah, then
he tries to prove it from a בהמה. behemah. Now all of
those seem very much to be saying, do we consider different things
to be גופי מחלקין? gufei mechalekin? If we say it by נדה
nidah and this and this, then yes, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says those are things, those are people. Okay, so it seems to
be very much a גופי מחלקין gufei mechalekin debate. According to רב
חסדא, Rav Chisda, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva always accepted גופי מחלקין gufei
mechalekin by שבת. Shabbos. The question was, is one שבת Shabbos to
the next like remembering in between? Well, how's that relevant to the
whole discussion in the משנה mishna about נדה? nidah? What does that,
how does that all relevant? So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, תא
שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. אמר לו חייב על כל אחת
ואחת מקל וחומר. Amar lo chayav al kol achas ve'achas mikal vachomer.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said back to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you're
חייב chayav on every one, every different שבת Shabbos from a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה נדה שאין בה תוצאות הרבה, Umah nidah she'ein
bah totza'ot harbeh, נדה nidah doesn't have a lot of subcategories, a
lot of מלאכות, melachot, and nevertheless you're חייב chayav on each one,
how much more so שבת Shabbos that has all these categories and
all these subdivisions, you should be חייב chayav on each one. So
what's the, what are we learning out from נדה? nidah? So the
גמרא Gemara is honing in on the fact that it said נדה
nidah in the singular, not
נדות. nidot. So
בשלמא לרב חסדא דאמר שיגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות בעי מיניה, Bishlama leRav
Chisda de'amar shegagat Shabbos vezadon melachos ba'ei minei, according to רב חסדא
Rav Chisda that the discussion was forgetting שבת Shabbos and whether if
time passes it's like you remembered, ימים שבינתיים מי הוו ידיעה לחלק
או לא, yamim shebeintayim mi havu yedi'ah lechalek o lo, are the
days in between like you remembered or not? היינו דקאמר ליה ומה
נדה. Hainu deka'amar lei umah nidah. Therefore he spoke only about one
נדה. nidah. Now how is it still, how is it relevant? We'll
see in a minute, but for now we'll take that on trust,
but it can work with only one person. אלא לרבא דאמר זדון
שבת ושיגגת מלאכות הוא דבעי מיניה, Ela leRava de'amar zadon Shabbos veshegagat
melachos hu deba'ei minei, but according to רבא Rava the issue was
you knew it was שבת Shabbos and the question was are multiple
שבתות Shabbosos like גופי מחלקין gufei mechalekin and the whole question was
about גופי מחלקין, gufei mechalekin, so according to that, הוא דבעי מיניה
דשבתות כגופין דמיין או לא, hu deba'ei minei deshabbosos kegufin damyan o
lo, if whether it's multiple like multiple גופים gufim or
not, so תני נדות, tanni nidot, why does it say נדה? nidah?
It should say נדות. nidot. The comparison is multiple women who are
נדות nidot is multiple חטאות, chata'ot, so multiple שבתות Shabbosos should be
multiple חטאות. chata'ot. So say נדות nidot in the plural. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך רבא תני נדות. Amar lach Rava tanni
nidot. Fine, change the text, have it say נדות. nidot. Okay, I
actually agree with Michael, נדה nidah could mean the concept of נדה,
nidah, but anyway fine, if that's your problem say נדות, nidot, okay.
Now שמואל תני נדה. Shmuel tanni nidah. שמואל's Shmuel גרסא girsa was
נדה nidah and he learned like רב חסדא Rav Chisda that it
was not about multiple bodies, that wasn't the issue. רב אדא בר
אהבה תני נדה. Rav Adda bar Ahava tanni nidah. רב אדא בר
אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava teaches נדה. nidah. רב נתן בר אושעיא
אמר תני נדות. Rav Nasan bar Oshaya amar tanni nidot. He thought
נדות. nidot. So now the question about whether who you go like,
are we talking about bodies or are we talking about remembering, is
going to be a function of whether your גרסא girsa is נדה
nidah or נדות. nidot. Okay, now we are going to try to
explain if it, how, what is the whole comparison to נדה? nidah?
If it's about גופי מחלקין gufei mechalekin you say multiple women, multiple
חטאות, chata'ot, multiple שבתות, Shabbosos, multiple חטאות. chata'ot. But if it's about
remembering in between, like you remembered, how is it relevant to נדה?
nidah? So let's take a look. ולרב חסדא דאמר שיגגת שבת וזדון
מלאכות
הוא דבעי מיניה,
UleRav Chisda de'amar shegagat Shabbos
vezadon melachos hu deba'ei minei, he's asking about forgetting it was שבת
Shabbos and whether the days pass it's like you remembered, ימים שבינתיים
מי הוו ידיעה לחלק או לא, yamim shebeintayim mi havu yedi'ah lechalek
o lo, if that's the question, נדה מאי ימים שבינתיים הוו ידיעה
לחלק איכא, nidah mai yamim shebeintayim havu yedi'ah lechalek ika, what type
of comparison are you making to נדה? nidah? So now we're finally
getting to the question of if it's not about גופי מחלקין, gufei
mechalekin, if it's about the days in between like remembering, what's going
on in the משנה? mishna? What's the whole comparison to נדה? nidah?
So the גמרא Gemara is asking that. Let's see what the answer
is.
מי הוו ידיעה לחלק או לא איכא. Mi havu yedi'ah lechalek o
lo ika. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so says רבא, Rava, interesting,
although רבא Rava doesn't hold with רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, here he's
going to come to the defense of רב חסדא Rav Chisda and
here he's going to say how you could use נדה nidah as
a comparison to this idea of days in between. כגון שבא עליה,
Kegon sheba aleha, so a man forgot, the same way you could
forget it's שבת, Shabbos, he forgot that she was a נדה. nidah.
Okay, now by שבת Shabbos we say six days pass, you should
have remembered, it's like you remembered. What could happen by נדה nidah
that we say you should have remembered by this time, it's like
you remembered? Can you figure it out?
Do you have an exercise?
She had, and she went to the מקוה mikvah again, right. So
if she has gone to the, says... were so oblivious, we're going
to treat it as if you remembered. Okay, so they're actually not
a bad comparison. Okay, כגון שבא עליה, kegon sheba aleha, he actually
forgot she was a נדה, niddah, not forgetting it was forbidden, forgetting
she was a נדה, niddah, like he like the guy who forgot
it was שבת, Shabbos, וטבלה, vetavlah, then she went to the מקוה,
mikvah, וראתה, vera'asah, then she became a נדה niddah again, וחזר ובא
עליה, vechazar uva aleha, וטבלה, vetavlah, וחזר ובא עליה. vechazar uva aleha.
So you have the cases of not the six days passing, but
going to the מקוואות mikvaos in between. So, and he says דטבילות
הוין כימים שבינתיים, detvilos havin kiyamim shebeintayim, that the טבילות tvilos are
like days in between and it's like you remembered, we'll treat it
as if you remembered because you should have remembered and therefore we'll
divide it. So somehow רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer had a tradition about
this, right? The problem again with this read is we already know
from earlier משניות mishnayos that we have a tradition about multiple different
women is multiple חטאות. chataos. Here we're having to assert a new
point, that we're taking it for granted that going to the מקוה
mikvah in between is like you remembered, that was the tradition רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer had and then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was trying
to apply that to the case of from one שבת Shabbos to
the next. And in the end, according to this version, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva, winds up agreeing to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer You're right,
if from going to the מקוה mikvah divides, from one שבת Shabbos
to the next it also divides. Tradition vs innovation? No, in the
end not necessarily, in the end he just might have thought it
was a good comparison. Anyway, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear.
הבעל הקטנות יוכיח. haba al haktanos yochiach. So then the next proof
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says back
to him, oh, but in this case the woman is active and
in the other case it's not an object, it's more of an
object, etc. So he says fine, but how about a case where
it's a קטנה? ktana? בקטנות. bektanos.
Now here the before we emphasized the fact that נדה niddah was
the singular, now we're going to emphasize the fact that קטנות ktanos
is plural. Okay, so so יוכיח. yochiach. בשלמא לרבה היינו דקתני קטנות,
bishlama lerabbah hainu dekasni ktanos, multiple because it's אגופים. agufim. אלא לרב
חסדא מאי קטנות? ela lerav chisda mai ktanos? Why are you saying
קטנות? ktanot? קטנות דעלמא, ktanot dealma, it means you know, which you
could have said in the opposite, means you know קטנות ktanot as
a category. Obviously we're talking about one person, but we're talking about
when you're talking about young people, but in the end, you know,
it's talking about it doesn't mean we're talking here about multiple people.
Okay. Now, of course, what then becomes funny
is what then is the comparison, okay fine, what then is the
comparison to when he switches to the issue of בהמה. behemah. או
בהמה יוכיח. o behemah yochiach. So what's exactly the case about ימים
שבינתיים yamim shebeintayim by בהמה, behemah, right? That's bizarre too. So anyway,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
מתניתין דלא כהדין תנא. masnisin dela kehadein tanna. Let me just take
a look here at רש"י Rashi for just one minute.
Right, okay, so anyway let's take a look. מתניתין דלא כהדין תנא.
masnisin dela kehadein tanna. Our משנה mishnah that has the debate framed
around the question about what do you do about, you know, that
takes for granted נדה niddah and is trying to apply it to
שבת, Shabbos, is not like the following תנא. tanna. דתניא, detanya, we
have a ברייתא braisa that reframes the debate.
אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, לא נחלקו
רבי עקיבא ורבי אליעזר. lo nechelku Rabbi Akiva verabbi Eliezer. That wasn't
the question, it wasn't that we took נדה niddah for granted and
we tried to apply it to שבת. Shabbos. אלא על מה נחלקו.
ela al mah nechelku. Here's the question, it was the opposite. We
took שבת Shabbos for granted and we tried to apply it to
נדה. niddah. Okay, so he understood that the issue was the reverse.
הבא על אשתו נדה וחזר ובא על אשתו נדה בהעלם אחד מהו
חייב אחת על כולן או חייב על כל אחת ואחת. haba al
ishto niddah vechazar uva al ishto niddah be'elem echad mahu chayav achas
al kulan o chayav al kol achas veachas. So here it's not
even a גופים מוחלקים gufim mochalakim question. It's multiple person, the same
person multiple times. A man has sex with his wife multiple times
when she's a נדה. niddah. Now we've now taken for granted that
everybody would say one. He says that was actually the question, maybe
even there we say multiple. אמר ליה חייב על כל אחת ואחת.
amar leh chayav al kol achas veachas. And even there רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer said multiple.
Okay, מקל וחומר, mikal vachomer, learning it from שבת. Shabbos. Now we're
taking שבת Shabbos for granted. ומה שבת שאין בה אלא אזהרה אחת
שהוא מוזהר על שאר השבתות חייב על כל אחת ואחת. umah shabbos
she'ein bah ela azharah achas shehu muzhar al shear hashabasos chayav al
kol achas veachas. By שבת Shabbos for שבת Shabbos is only once,
you are forbidden, שבת Shabbos isn't forbidden to you. And nevertheless you're
חייב chayav every single one. Now of course by שבת Shabbos it's
not if you did זריעה זריעה זריעה zriah zriah zriah you're חייב
chayav every single one. It's if you did, this is רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer own idea, that if you did multiple תולדות toldos you're
חייב chayav for each one. If you did זריעה zriah and watering
and fertilizing and pruning. So he says by שבת Shabbos even if
you do multiple תולדות toldos of the same larger category you're חייב
chayav for each one. נדה שיש בה שתי אזהרות, niddah sheyesh bah
shtei azharos, נדה niddah that has two prohibitions. שהוא מוזהר על הנדה
והנדה מוזהרת עליו. shehu muzhar al haniddah vehaniddah muzheres alav. He's prohibited
on her, she's prohibited on him. אינו דין שיהיה חייב על כל
אחת ואחת. eino din sheyehei chayav al kol achas veachas. How much
more so should you be חייב chayav for every act of sex.
Of course it's different because there it's the same exactly the same,
it's not just like a subtle variation like you had by like
you had by different תולדות. toldos. And anyway we don't agree with
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's about different תולדות. toldos. So אמר לו, amar
lo, he said back to him, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva לא אם
אמרת בשבת שיש בה תולדות הרבה, lo im amarta beshabbos sheyesh bah
toldos harbeh, which is exactly now the response that שבת Shabbos has
many subcategories. By שבת Shabbos yes, if you did four types of
זריעה zriah you're חייב chayav because it has a concept of subcategories
and it has a concept of תולדות. toldos. So there you're חייב
chayav for each one לחטאות הרבה lechataos harbeh and that leads to
multiple sin offerings. תאמר בנדה שאין בה תולדות הרבה לחטאות הרבה. tomar
beniddah she'ein bah toldos harbeh lechataos harbeh. נדה niddah that has no
subcategories, it's not going to lead to multiple sin offerings if it's
the same person. אמרו לו, amru lo, so he said back to
him,
הבא על הקטנות יוכיח, haba al haktanos yochiach, שאין בהן תולדות. she'ein
bahen toldos. So
presumably he meant different קטנות, ketanos, different women, which is of course
bizarre. Then why did he have to switch to קטנות? ketanos? Just
talk about different women even if they're גדולות. gedolos. Anyway, אמרו לו,
amru lo, לא, lo, אם אמרת בקטנות שגופן מחולקין, im amarta b'ketanos
she'gufan mechulakin, that's because they're different people. We're talking about it's all
one person multiple times. אמר לו, amar lo, אבא על הבהמה יוכיח
aba al ha'behemah yochiach שאין גופה מחולק she'ein gufah mechulak וחייב על
כל אחת ואחת. v'chayav al kol achas v'achas. He says, how about
if you have sex with a בהמה behemah multiple times? Even if
it's one בהמה, behemah, it's multiple חטאות. chataos. Now how does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer know that? Who knows? He had some tradition about
בהמה. behemah. So אמר לו, amar lo, בהמה כנדה. behemah k'niddah. He
said fine, I don't think it's any different. So according to this,
they're debating the same act multiple times. And now we have a
really radical רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer That רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. would
say ממש, mamash, the person does the same thing multiple times, each
time you do it it's a different חטאת. chatas. You had never
heard that before. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said. Now תוספות
Tosafos by the way says, if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer knows thinks
it's true by בהמה, behemah, why does he have to learn from
בהמה behemah to נדה? niddah? I mean they're the, you know, of
course they should be the same הלכה. halacha. So תוספות Tosafos once
again this shows that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer just follows his tradition.
He had a tradition by בהמה, behemah, he didn't have a tradition
by נדה. niddah. So therefore he says to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva
he's not saying נדה niddah בהמה behemah by logic, he's saying it
by tradition. So he's saying oh, but by בהמה behemah I have
a tradition multiple times. If that's true it should be the same
by נדה. niddah. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. says I don't accept
your tradition. בהמה behemah should be only one. Okay, so at the
end of the day though,
the basic debate in the משנה Mishnah is, the easy way to
read the משנה Mishnah is this is about גופין מחולקין. gufin mechulakin.
That explains the discussion about is a נדה niddah a subject or
an object as opposed to שבת. Shabbos. How about קטנות, ketanos, how
about בהמות, behemos, גופין מחולקין gufin mechulakin or not. רב חסדא Rav
Chisda reads it it's a debate about whether it's ידיעה לחלק yediya
l'chalek and when the נדה niddah goes to the מקוה, mikvah, when
the woman who is a נדה niddah goes to the מקוה, mikvah,
is that a ידיעה לחלק yediya l'chalek or not. How that then
becomes relevant to the question of בהמה behemah is very strange. The
גמרא Gemara never explains that. How do we wind up פוסקנינג paskening
about this? So here, Micah usually asks
how we rule, because,
because there still is a difference there, you could still make the
difference about subject or object although it's not as relevant if it's
about ידיעה לחלק. yediya l'chalek. But you could still say if one
person knows it's like the other person knows, you could work that
in. Anyway, how do we rule? Micah usually asks how we rule,
but I got curious about this because, you know, so anyway, how
we rule means the רמב"ם. Rambam. So the רמב"ם Rambam actually says
interestingly, here he פוסקנס paskens like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, and which
basically means like we've been assuming רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer that he
says שבת Shabbos is כגופין מחולקין. k'gufin mechulakin. Not only so if
one שבת Shabbos to the next the same thing multiple חטאות. chataos.
Not only that, the other thing mentioned in the משנה Mishnah was
בהמה. behemah. So he actually, רמב"ם Rambam actually says that if a
man has sex with one בהמה behemah and then another בהמה behemah
in the same העלמה, he'elamah, that actually גופין מחולקין gufin mechulakin and
he says different חטאות. chataos. But what he says it's גוף אחד
guf echad is the earlier debate of רבי עקיבא with רבי יהושע.
Rabbi Yehoshua. If a man שחטס shachts one בהמה behemah outside of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then another בהמה, behemah, or eats
נותר nosar from one קרבן korban and then from another קרבן, korban,
that's all seen as the same עבירה aveirah multiple times and that's
only one חטאת. chatas. So the question of course is why different
בהמות behemos when it comes to נותר nosar and שחוטי חוץ shchutei
chutz is considered one sin multiple times, and when it comes to
עריות arayos it's considered multiple sins. And I think at the end
of the day the answer is similar to what רבי עקיבא was
saying in the משנה, Mishnah, that when you're talking about עריות arayos
and sex, even if it's with a בהמה, behemah, somehow there it's,
you know, it takes two to tango. And that works, meaning that
it's the other thing is not just an object. Somehow it's seen
as a different act based on who the participants are, even if
a participant is just a בהמה. behemah. But fundamentally that defines it
as a גופין מחולקין gufin mechulakin and a different act. When it's
really something about eating or שחטינג shachting or those types of things,
there the thing is completely an object and different objects just the
fact that they're, you know, they're completely immaterial. I'm just doing the
same thing multiple times. That's what I think, but it is interesting
the רמב"ם Rambam here rules שבת Shabbos and עריות arayos are גופין
מחולקין gufin mechulakin and everything else is גוף אחד. guf echad. What?
So that's how the רמב"ם Rambam פוסקנס paskens like רבי אליעזר?
Rabbi Eliezer, Or רב חסדא's Rav Chisda version of רבי עקיבא.
And what about like תולדות toledos and אבות? avos?
No, that everybody says multiple תולדות toledos of the same אב av
is only one. Okay, now הדרן עלך אמרו לו. hadran alach amru
lo. What? Everybody today. Everybody except רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer? Exactly. Okay,
הדרן עלך אמרו לו. hadran alach amru lo. So now that is
the end of the idea. These פרקים prakim are very sort of
nicely thematic. So that פרק perek was all about how many חטאות
chataos can you bring, when do you define it as multiple חטאות
chataos versus one if it's the same sin repeated in different contexts.
This next פרק perek is all about אשם תלוי. asham talui. If
you don't know whether you've sinned and you might have done something
that's obligated in a חטאת, chatas, then you have to bring an
אשם תלוי. asham talui. Okay, so that's the entire focus of this
פרק. perek. Let's take a look. ספק אכל חלב ספק לא אכל.
safek achal chelev safek lo achal. You don't know if you've eaten
חלב chelev or not. If you definitely ate חלב, chelev, you'd bring
a חטאת, chatas, but you don't know. ואפילו אכל, v'afilu achal, even
if you know you've eaten something, ספק יש בו כשיעור וספק אין
בו כשיעור. safek yesh bo k'shiur v'safek ein bo k'shiur. You don't
know if... whether it had a כזית kezayis or not. You know
you ate something, maybe you even know it was חלב, cheilev, but
what you don't know is: Did you actually, am I actually חייב
chayav in a קרבן korban because you don't know whether it had
a כזית. kezayis. Or here's another scenario. שומן וחלב לפניך. shuman v'cheilev
lefanecha. You have in front of you two pieces, two כזיתים. kezeisim.
One is a כזית kezayis of שומן shuman which is kosher fat,
and the other is a כזית kezayis of חלב. cheilev. And you
know and you and you maybe think they're both שומן, shuman, okay?
Or or you ate one thinking at least the one you were
eating was שומן. shuman. ואכל אחד מהם. v'achal echad meihem. And now,
if it turns out that you ate the one that was חלב,
cheilev, you'd bring a חטאת. chatas. But you don't know which one
you ate. Now somebody says, oh don't you realize one of those
was חלב? cheilev? What? What are you talking about? Okay, so you
don't know now whether you've eaten חלב cheilev or not.
So okay, all of these you understand are cases where had you
found out that you had sinned, you would bring a חטאת. chatas.
But now at the end of the day you still don't know.
You still don't know was there a כזית, kezayis, you still don't
know whether you ate חלב, cheilev, you still you still don't know
and therefore you bring an אשם תלוי. asham taloy. Now before we
go on I want to say an important point which is both
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos say all of these is cases where
you thought you were eating שומן, shuman, okay? You thought you were
you were doing was totally okay. Afterwards you found out as opposed
to the normal scenario after you found out you definitely sinned, here
afterwards you found out you might have sinned. But the case is
always you thought what you were doing was okay. רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafos both discuss what
if it's a case where you knew this piece of meat might
be חלב? cheilev? You knew there were two pieces in front of
you and one of them was חלב cheilev and you had no
concept which was which and you said I don't care, I'm going
to assume I'm going to eat one of them and I'll hope
that I'm doing the right thing, okay? And I'm going to assume
it's okay. Okay, so you actually knowingly did something that was ספק
איסור. sofek issur. That type of a case would not bring an
אשם תלוי asham taloy because that a classic חטאת chatas is when
you think you're doing היתר. heter. If you're doing something which you
know is a possible violation, first of all it gets to questions
whether ספק דאורייתא לחומרא מדאורייתא. sofek d'oraisa l'chumra mid'oraisa.
What does the תורה Torah tell you to do in a case
of ספק? sofek? Obviously, right, the תורה Torah can't tell you that
in a case of ספק sofek you're allowed to do it, then
you would never bring an אשם תלוי. asham taloy. So anyway that's
a whole conversation I'm not going to get into. But the point
is you knowingly violated the fact that you should not have if
it was possibly אסור assur you should not have gone ahead and
done it. And also number two is just the way we frame
when you bring the חטאת chatas is when you thought you were
doing total היתר. heter. If you were aware you were doing something
that might have been איסור, issur, then that would not bring a
חטאת chatas so similarly it would not bring an אשם תלוי, asham
taloy, nothing. So you have to live with the sin and do
תשובה teshuva on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
What? An impossible sin, right. Okay, so that's important though. All these
cases is you thought you were doing היתר, heter, you thought it
was totally okay and it turns out it might have been אסור.
assur. Now now we move back from עריות, arayos, these constantly moving
back, at least we had a nice break with שבת, Shabbos, but
tend to be moving back and forth between between food and sex.
So now we're going back to the case of
עריות. arayos. אשתו ואחותו עמו בבית. ishto v'achoso imo babayis. You have
your sister, somebody has his sister staying over in his house and
he's with his wife and he went into a bedroom and he
forgot which bedroom he went into, okay? שגג באחת מהן, shagag b'achas
meihen, and he didn't know באיזו מהן שגג. b'eizo meihen shagag.
So he made a he you know afterwards he he realized he
thought it was his wife but then somehow, yeah I know, exactly.
Somehow somebody said oh you you know somehow he realized afterwards maybe
he went into the wrong bedroom. Okay. שבת ויום חול. Shabbos v'yom
chol. Now here we're telling you things were not exactly objects but
we're back to שבת. Shabbos. Okay, it's between שבת Shabbos and a
week day, you just don't know which day of the week it
is or maybe it's בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, it's right between Friday
and שבת Shabbos or שבת Shabbos or שבת Shabbos and Sunday. ועשה
מלאכה באחת מהן, v'asa melacha b'achas meihen, and he didn't know באיזו
מהן עשה. b'eizo meihen asa. You don't know did I do מלאכה
melacha on שבת Shabbos and did I do it on Sunday? Okay,
now again in all these cases at the time you were doing
it you thought you were doing היתר. heter. Afterwards you found out
you might have done איסור. issur. In all these cases maybe אשם
תלוי, asham taloy, you bring an אשם תלוי. asham taloy. If you
would bring a חטאת chatas had it definitely been איסור, issur, you
bring an אשם תלוי. asham taloy. Here's the principle: כשם שאם אכל
חלב וחלב בהעלם אחת אינו חייב אלא אחת. kesheim she'im achal cheilev
v'cheilev b'he'elem achas eino chayav ela achas. Now how many אשם תלוים
asham taloys do you bring? So it would be a function of
how many חטאות chataos do you bring. If you had eaten חלב
cheilev twice in one state of forgetfulness you would bring only one
חטאת. chatas. כן על לא הודע שלהם, kein al lo hoda shelahem,
if you're if you're not aware, meaning it's not that you're not
aware, it's really you're aware that you might have sinned. הודע על
ספק, hoda al sofek, but it's called לא הודע. lo hoda. If
you're aware you might have sinned אינו מביא אלא אשם תלוי אחד.
eino meivi ela asham taloy echad. You only bring one. Since if
you would bring one חטאת chatas if you definitely sinned you bring
one אשם תלוי. asham taloy. That's if it's eating multiple times in
one state of forgetfulness. אם הייתה ידיעה בינתיים, im haysa yedi'ah beintayim,
now let's say you ate חלב, cheilev, you remembered and then you
ate again. כשם שהוא מביא חטאת על כל אחת ואחת, kesheim shehu
meivi chatas al kol achas v'achas, the same way if you had
definitely sinned you would bring multiple sin offerings, כך מביא אשם תלוי
על כל אחת ואחת. kach meivi asham taloy al kol achas v'achas.
You ate this piece, then you became aware oh my God that
might have been חלב, cheilev, I'm חייב chayav an אשם תלוי. asham
taloy. Then somehow you forgot again, you forgot again that these pieces
were problematic and you ate another piece. Okay, so the same way
had it definitely been חלב cheilev and you did it with remembering
in between it would be multiple חטאות, chataos, here where you doubt
fully sin, you bring multiple אשמות תלויות. ashamos teluyos. כשם שאכל חלב
דם ופיגול ונותר בהעלם אחד חייב על כל אחת ואחת, Keshem she'achal
chelev dam u'pigul v'nosar b'he'elam echad chayav al kol achas v'achas, let's
say it's multiple sins, פיגול דם חלב נותר, pigul dam chelev nosar,
all these different types of forbidden things and if you did them
all in one state of forgetfulness it's a קרבן korban for each
one. ככה לותה של אנו Kacha losah shel anu if it winds
up you did you might have done all of these things, maybe
אשם תלוי על כל אחת ואחת. asham talui al kol achas v'achas.
You bring an אשם תלוי asham talui for each one. So basically,
whatever would be the הלכה halacha for חטאת, chatas, if you're חייב
חטאת, chayav chatas, you're חייב אשם תלוי chayav asham talui when you
don't know. If you're חייב chayav multiple חטאות, chata'os, then you're חייב
chayav multiple אשמות
תלויות. ashamos teluyos. Now the גמרא Gemara right away and this actually
hopefully the rest of this דף daf will go quickly,
hones right in on the question of what's considered enough of a
doubt for אשם תלוי. asham talui. The משנה Mishnah first had a
generic statement: he might have eaten חלב. chelev. Then it gave you
something much more
concrete: חלב ושומן chelev v'shuman were in front of you and you
don't know which one you ate. Okay, now you can understand why
that case is much more of a basis to bring an אשם
תלוי. asham talui. There's a concrete possibility that you did a sin.
The other case is like, I don't know, maybe, maybe I did
something wrong. Who knows? I wasn't paying attention. It's way too abstract
and amorphous. Is that possible, the abstract possibility that somebody tells you,
hey, you know what? I think that piece you ate might have
been חלב. chelev. I mean, you know, it's just a possibility. Is
that enough to be a basis for an אשם תלוי? asham talui?
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Depends how you read
the first statement in the גמרא, Gemara, which is a generic statement,
which is you didn't know if it was חלב chelev or שומן.
shuman. So let's take a look. איתמר, Itmar, it was said. רב
אסי אמר חתיכה אחת שנינו. Rav Assi amar chaticha achas shaninu. The
first case in the משנה Mishnah is just one piece and you
just don't know. In the end, or at the time you thought
it was okay, in the end you don't know what its identity
was. Okay, just one piece. ספק דחלב ספק דשומן Safeik d'chelev safeik
d'shuman and that's enough to bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. חייא
בר רב אמר Chiya bar Rav amar no, חתיכה משתי חתיכות שנינו.
chaticha mishtei chatichos shaninu. Even the first case which was generic, it's
really the next case in the משנה Mishnah is explaining it and
it's only when there were two pieces in front of you and
one is definite איסור issur and one is definite היתר. heter. Then
we know that there was an איסור issur present and the only
question was did you eat it? You need that concrete possibility in
order to be enough of a basis for an אשם תלוי. asham
talui. Okay, so במאי קמיפלגי? b'mai kamiflagi? So first the גמרא, Gemara,
I've been explaining it conceptually, but first the גמרא Gemara is going
to explain it based on פסוקים. pesukim. What do they debate? רב
אסי סבר יש אם למסורת. Rav Assi savar yeish em l'masores. You
go by the way the פסוק pasuk is written. מצות כתיב. Mitzvos
kesiv. By the פסוק pasuk where it speaks about bringing an אשם
תלוי asham talui it says
ועשה אחת מכל מצות ה' אשר לא תעשינה ואשם. v'asah achas mikol
mitzvos Hashem asher lo se'aseinah v'ashem. He did any one of the
מצות. mitzvos. Okay, so where are we going to read one of
מצות mitzvos plural, meaning there were two things and you did one
of them? Okay, of course that's not a מצוה, mitzvah, that's חלב
chelev and an איסור, issur, but okay. We're going to read the
plural of מצות mitzvos meaning there were two objects and you ate
one of them. Okay, but that's if you read מצות, mitzvos, but
the way it's read is מצות. mitzvas. So since it's read מצות,
mitzvas, that means only one, even with one piece. וחייא בר רב
אמר יש אם למקרא. V'Chiya bar Rav amar yeish em l'mikra. No,
you follow how it's read. מצות קרינן. Mitzvos karinan. And since it's
plural, we say only one piece out of two pieces is enough
of a basis for an אשם תלוי. asham talui.
And on one piece you don't bring anything?
One piece you don't bring anything. איתיביה רב הונא לרב אסי. Eisivei
Rav Huna l'Rav Assi. Rav Huna asked Rav Assi. Or some say
חייא בר רב
לרב אסי Chiya bar Rav l'Rav Assi who said that it is
one piece. So here's our משנה. Mishnah. חלב ושומן לפניו ואכל אחת
מהן. Chelev v'shuman lefanav v'achal achas meihen. So it says so the
second case in the משנה Mishnah says there are two pieces in
front of
you. מאי לאו בסיפא שתי חתיכות? Mai lav b'seifa shtei chatichos? Since
the explicit case later in the משנה Mishnah is two
pieces, רישא נמי שתי חתיכות. reisha nami shtei chatichos. The first case
which was generic, you didn't know, is also talking about a similar
scenario of two pieces. אמר להו רב, Amar lehu Rav, so Rav
said back to the or whoever it was that asked this question,
anyway said back to those that asked this question, לא תצלו בתר
איפכא. lo sitzlu basar ipcha. Don't go looking for, don't go making
trouble, meaning תצלו בתר איפכא titzlu basar ipcha means go doing the
opposite. Don't ask questions, yeah, don't be contrary or something. Right, that's
maybe a good way of saying it. דאכלו לשנויי לכו. D'achlu l'shunayei
l'chu. First of all, I can answer you a very simple answer.
סיפא בשתי חתיכות רישא בחתיכה אחת. Seifa b'shtei chatichos reisha b'chaticha achas.
That might have been anyway what I would have thought, right? If
they're both שתי חתיכות, shtei chatichos, why do they repeat it? So
no, the fact that the second case is talking about two pieces
means the first case which says you don't know is a simple
case of one piece. Okay, so maybe it actually works very well.
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי יש לומר חתיכה אחת וחייב שתי חתיכות
צריכא למימר? ee hachi yeish lomar chaticha achas v'chayav shtei chatichos tzricha
l'meimar? No, if that's true, then once we said you bring an
אשם asham for just one piece, how much more so would you
bring it if there are two pieces? So why would you have
to say one and then say two? זו ואין צריך לומר זו.
Zu v'ein tzarich lomar zu. No, telling you this and it goes
even without saying that. And sometimes we do that. We start with
the bigger חידוש chiddush and then we say the lesser חידוש. chiddush.
Or also you could say by saying the end case of two
clarifies that the first case is even one. Okay, so that actually
works very well in the משנה Mishnah that we're talking about even
one piece. ולחייא בר רב דאמר מדסיפא בשתי חתיכות רישא נמי בשתי
חתיכות. U'l'Chiya bar Rav d'amar m'd'seifa b'shtei chatichos reisha nami b'shtei chatichos.
So according to Chiya bar Rav that says that since the second
case is two pieces, the first generic case in the משנה Mishnah
is also two pieces, משני תרתי למה
לי? mishni tartei lamah li? Why did it have to say twice?
If it said it once, why say it again? פירושא דמפרש. Peirusha
d'mifareish. No, the משנה Mishnah is explaining itself. ספק אכל חלב ספק
לא אכל מביא אשם תלוי. Safeik achal chelev safeik lo achal meivi
asham talui. If you don't know if you ate or not, you
bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. כיצד? Keitzad? What's... What what are
the specific examples of this? So כגון שהיה חלב ושומן לפניו, Kegon
she-hayah cheilev v'shuman lefanav, like you had two pieces and you didn't
know. So that's also a reasonable way of reading the משנה. Mishnah.
If you had a doubt, you bring an אשם תלוי. Asham Talui.
What would be a case of a doubt? You don't know if
you ate a כשיעור k'shiur or you had two pieces and you
don't know which one you ate, but only one piece, it's too
much of an abstract doubt and it's not or actually here they're
focusing on the פסוקים. psukim. So this is going to be a
major theme of this פרק, perek, what type of a doubt is
sufficient for bringing an אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. Is it just a
generic doubt, or is it that there was a חתיכה, chatichah, or
is it that there were two חתיכות, chatichot, one was definitely אסור,
assur, there was something concrete that you know you could have sinned,
and that's enough and that's what you need for an אשם תלוי.
Asham Talui. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue
with this debate, but different framing of what the issue is of
one piece and two pieces. Until now the issue has only been
a question of פסוקים. psukim. So let's keep on looking. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda now said in the name of רב, Rav, היו לפניו שתי
חתיכות אחת של שומן ואחת של חלב אכל אחת מהן ואינו יודע
איזה מהן אכל חייב. Hayu lefanav shtei chatichot achat shel shuman v'achat
shel cheilev achal achat mehen v'eino yodeia eizo mehen achal chayav. If
it's two pieces and you don't know which one, then you're חייב
chayav an אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. חתיכה אחת ספק של חלב ספק
של שומן ואינו יודע מה היא ואכלה פטור. Chatichah achat safek shel
cheilev safek shel shuman v'eino yodeia mah hi v'achalah patur. If it's
only one piece, ספק של חלב ספק של שומן safek shel cheilev
safek shel shuman and you don't know what it was, I mean
at the time you thought it was okay, now you don't know
what it was, ואכלה פטור, v'achalah patur, you're exempt. So that's a
long way of saying that one piece is not enough, you need
two חתיכות. chatichot. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מאי טעמא דרב, mai ta'ama
d'Rav, what's the reason of רב? Rav? So we're going to say
the same thing we said before. דאמר קרא אשר אחת מכל מצות
מצות ה' בשגגה, d'amar kra asher achat mikol mitzvot mitzvot Hashem bishgaga,
עד שישגוג בשתים. ad she-yishgog bishtayim.
Okay, so just מצות, mitzvot, you did the מצות mitzvot in error.
So you have to make a mistake about two pieces. Of course
those two pieces aren't מצות, mitzvot, they're one of them is an
עבירה, aveirah, but okay, you make a mistake about two people. מצות
mitzvot is in the plural. Otherwise it's מצות כתיב, mitzvot ktiv, but
it's written with מצות mitzvot singular, מצות קרינן, mitzvot karinan, no, but
we read it מצות, mitzvot, so same issue, do you read the
word מצות mitzvot as singular or plural, one piece or two pieces.
Okay, yes, question? No, not right now. איתיביה אביי, Eitivei Abaye, so
אביי Abaye asked on this. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now
we're going to bring in some other interesting cases about whether you
bring an אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. said כוי
koy or כוי, kvi, however you pronounce it, חייבין עליו אשם תלוי.
chayavin alav asham talui. Somebody ate the fat of a כוי. koy.
You might remember that this כוי koy or כוי, kvi, however you
pronounce it, is this animal, it might be a crossbreed, whatever it
is, it's a question whether it's a חיה chayah or בהמה. behemah.
Now, if it's a חלב cheilev of a חיה chayah is מותר.
mutar. The חלב cheilev of a בהמה behemah is אסור. assur. Okay,
so you ate this חלב. cheilev. So you don't know, did you
eat forbidden חלב cheilev or not forbidden חלב? cheilev? It depends whether
a כוי koy is a חיה chayah or בהמה. behemah. So he
says you're חייב chayav an אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. So now that's
not two חתיכות, chatichot, right? That's just a generic question. It's not
a question of a clear concrete אסור assur thing in front of
you. אמר לו, Amar lo, he said back, fine, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer is the other opinion. רבי אליעזר סבר יש אם למסורת, Rabbi
Eliezer savar yeish em l'masoret, you go by the way the פסוק
pasuk is written. And since it's written מצות, mitzvot, according to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you're right, you don't need two חתיכות, chatichot, but
according to me you do need two חתיכות, chatichot, but we'll have
to admit that according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you don't.
Yes, but for the meat, I'm sorry, מצות כתיב.
mitzvot ktiv. He goes by the way it's written and it's written
מצות. mitzvot. Yes, go ahead.
In case of the meat, there's someone who would have known which
meat was which, but for the case of כוי koy we truly
don't know.
Right. So we're going to get to that as well, whether it
has to be knowable.
But also if you have even multiple, let's say there are like
ten pieces, you know, do we say it's because it can go
fifty-fifty, do you say that or, you know, מצות, mitzvot, you're focusing
on two, does it mean two?
Well, so that might be a question about ביטול. bitul. You'd have
to construct a case where there wouldn't be ביטול bitul and then
also, okay, those are all good questions. I think that the answer
is no, that as long as there's no ביטול, bitul, it's enough
that there's one concrete thing here that is אסור. assur. But you
have to go, but you have to be able to bracket ביטול
bitul and bracket off אזלינן בתר רוב azlinan batar rov and bracket
all those things. Anyway, איתיביה, Eitivei, ספק בין תשעה לראשון או בין
שבעה לאחרון. safek bein tishah l'rishon o bein shivah l'acharon. A woman,
her husband dies, she does יבום yibum with the husband's brother, and
then she has a baby after seven months. And you don't know,
is it from the brother, the new husband, or is it from
the old one? And there's a big difference, because if it was
from the old one, then it turns out that she was not
childless and she was never חייב chayav in יבום yibum and that
she was אסור assur for her to marry this brother. So this
kid is a ספק ממזר safek mamzer number one, right? Because he
might be the product of an incestuous relationship. So what do we
say? יוציא, Yotzi, first of all the husband has to divorce her
because now there's a ספק safek whether he's חייב chayav or whether
it's whatever, you know, whether there's a מצות יבום. mitzvot yibum. והולד
כשר, V'havalad kasher, now the child is כשר kasher because
ממזר ודאי אמר רחמנא ולא ממזר ספק. mamzer vadai amar Rachmana v'lo
mamzer safek. So because he's a doubtful ממזר, mamzer, we actually rule
and assume that he's not a
ממזר. mamzer. וחייב באשם תלוי, V'chayav b'asham talui, but you have to
bring an אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, him and her, because they both
maybe did an עבירה. aveirah.
Because if there was a ספק ממזר safek mamzer because if there
was a מצות יבום mitzvot yibum he's not a ממזר, mamzer, if
there wasn't a מצות יבום mitzvot yibum then he's the child of
an incestuous relationship.
But he's but he was already born from the prior one.
We don't know. We don't know if he's the prior one.
If he was born from the prior one then he's a ספק
ממזר.
safek mamzer. No, no, if he was born from the first husband
he's okay. If oh, I see what your point is. Yeah, I'm
sorry, you're right. You're right. I'm sorry. Thank you. Thank you. Okay,
you're completely correct. It It's not because of ספק ממזר. safek mamzer.
Michael is correct, I misstated it. The reason is because of ממה
נפשך. mimenafshach. If the kid is born from the first husband, which
means that there's an איסור עריות, issur arayos, that there was no
מצות יבום, mitzvas yibum, but at least the kid is okay because
he was born from the first husband. And if the kid was
born from the second husband, then it means that there was a
מצות יבום mitzvas yibum and then the kid is also okay. You're
absolutely correct, correct, sorry. So, thank you for that. Okay, so good,
so the kid is okay, but you have to divorce because maybe
there's an איסור עריות issur arayos and bring an אשם תלוי asham
talui because maybe they did an איסור עריות issur arayos depending on
whether this kid was from the first husband or the second. So
וחייב אשם תלוי. vechayav asham talui. So the Gemara, so again you
see there's no חתיכה משתי חתיכות, chaticha mishtei chatichos, right? There's no
definite איסור עריות issur arayos here. There's a ספק. safek. One person,
is it איסור עריות issur arayos or not? So the Gemara says
כמאן רבי אליעזר היא. keman Rabbi Eliezer hi. Alright, that's also רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer Yes, I admit that there's a debate and those
that say you don't need שתי חתיכות, shtei chatichos, that's רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer. and that would be that case. Let's do one more
case. איתיבי. Eisivei. נמצא על שלו טמאים וחייבין בקרבן. Nimtza al shelo
tmeim vechayavin bekorban. על שלו. Al shelo. Now,
a man and woman have sex, husband and wife have sex, and
it turns out that she was found to be bleeding as soon
as right after they have sex. And the question is, was she
bleeding at the time of sex? Was she נדה niddah when they
had sex? So if he finds it על שלו, al shelo, meaning
on his genitals or on things he wiped himself away with, then
she was definitely a נדה. niddah. How did blood get on him
unless she was a נדה niddah when they were having sex? Okay,
then נמצא על שלו טמאים, nimtza al shelo tmeim, they're both טמאי
נדה tmei niddah וחייבין בקרבן, vechayavin bekorban, they definitely had sex when
she was a נדה. niddah. They didn't do it intentionally, so they
bring a חטאת. chatas. על שלה, Al shelah, if she finds it
על שלה, al shelah, on hers, on you know, on her body
or let's say on something she wiped herself with, so then we
don't know because maybe she bled after sex, not during sex, right?
So if it's אות יום, os yom, if it was immediately, like
a second after they
separate, טמאים וחייבין בקרבן. tmeim vechayavin bekorban. Then we assume that she
had been bleeding at the time of sex and they have to
bring a קרבן korban and they're טמא. tamei. נמצא על שלה לאחר
זמן, Nimtza al shelah le'achar zman, if however she wipes herself a
few minutes later and finds out that she's bleeding, then you don't
know whether she was bleeding when they had sex. So in that
case טמאים מספק, tmeim misafek, they're doubtful
טמא tamei ופטורין מן הקרבן, upeturin min hakorban, they're exempt from a
קרבן. korban. Okay, no חטאת. chatas. Now the question is, ותניא עלה,
vesanya alah, we have a ברייתא braisa on it that says חייב
באשם תלוי, chayav be'asham talui,
you bring an אשם תלוי. asham talui. So again, okay, we understand
that there's a very objective ספק safek here, but there's not חתיכה
משתי חתיכות. chaticha mishtei chatichos. There's not somebody who was definitely a
נדה, niddah, she's definitely a נדה niddah now, but there's not somebody
who was definitely a נדה niddah at the time of the sin,
at the time of the act. So again you see you don't
need a definite thing, a definite prohibited possibility at the time of
the act. The Gemara once again says כמאן רבי אליעזר היא, keman
Rabbi Eliezer hi, once again it is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer So
we now have a debate about which we're going to continue tomorrow
about one חתיכה chaticha or two חתיכות. chatichos. The one final point
I want to make though is in all the examples of one
חתיכה, chaticha, it did not just say oh, I don't know, maybe
I sinned, a very abstract thing. All the examples of one חתיכה,
chaticha, there was some very good reason to assume you might have
sinned. The woman was found to be bleeding right after sex. There's
a general question about a כוי. koy. What was the... oh, there
was a child and you don't know when the child was, you
know, when the child was conceived. All those cases, there's a very
concrete basis to say the person might have sinned. It's not just
an abstract, even within one חתיכה. chaticha. But nevertheless, the demand of
שתי חתיכות shtei chatichos means that you need that in front of
you, a definite problem in front of you at the time of
act. So even if there's a good reason to say you might
have sinned, that's not enough to bring an אשם תלוי asham talui
unless there was the definite prohibited thing at the time of the
action. That is the position of שתי חתיכות shtei chatichos and we
will continue with that tomorrow.