Okay, שנה טובה *Shana Tova*, today's דף *daf* is קידושין ל"ו *Kiddushin
Lamed-Vav*, 36. We pick up at the very bottom of ל"ה עמוד
ב' *Lamed-He Amud-Bet*, and we are dealing with the issue about the
scope of מצוות Mitzvot. *mitzvot* that apply to women and that apply
to men, and that all negative prohibitions apply equally to both, with
the exception of the shaving of the forelocks or the cutting of
the forelocks and the shaving of the beard and the מצוה Mitzva,
*mitzvah* of טומאה *tuma* for כוהנים *Kohanim*, and now we are also
dealing with the position of איסי Isi *Issi* that about the question
about this prohibition of making a bald spot in your head, which
according to one תנא *Tanna* also does not apply to women. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up here at the bottom of ל"ה
עמוד ב' *Lamed-He Amud-Bet* and it says the following: ואימא *ve'eima*, two
lines from the bottom, בנים ולא בנות Bnot, בין לקרחה בין לגדידה
*banim ve-lo banot bein le'korcha bein le'gedida*, and maybe if we're going
to read according to that תנא *Tanna* the exclusion of a bald
spot
for איסי Isi. *Issi*,
we're going to say that the בנים אתם לה' אלקיכם *Banim Atem
Lashem Elokeichem* that appears right before making a bald spot or a
laceration is בנים *banim* and not בנות *banot*, and it would apply
it only to the bald spot part of the פסוק Pasuk. *pasuk*.
ואימא בנים ולא בנות בין לקרחה בין לגדידה *ve'eima banim ve-lo banot
bein le'korcha bein le'gedida*, maybe it also applies to laceration? והכי כתיב
עם קדוש אתה לה' אלקיך בשריטה הוא דכתיב *ve'hachi ksiv Am Kadosh
atah Lashem Elokecha bisrita hu d'chsiv*, and the end of the verse
which איסי *Issi* learned to include women in the prohibition of laceration,
maybe that's not talking about גדידה Gididah *gedida* but it's talking about
שריטה *srita*. Now שריטה *srita* is also an איסור *issur* of a
laceration in the flesh, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says we and it's
not even in that פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* but רש"י *Rashi* says that
would have applied to let's say a laceration with the hand and
not with an actual implement, not with actually like a knife. So
maybe we should just say that women are excluded from both because
both are in the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*. קסבר איסי שריטה וגדידה אחת
היא *ksavar Issi srita u'gedida achas hi*, no he can't, because although
another פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* talks about a prohibition of שריטה *srita*,
that is not really any different than גדידה *gedida*, so therefore since
עם קדוש *Am Kadosh* is coming to include women, it's coming to
include them on גדידה *gedida*/שריטה *srita*, and women are excluded from the
prohibition of a bald spot by on their head. Okay, אביי Abaye
אמר *Abaye amar*, top of ל"ו עמוד א' *Lamed-Vav Amud-Alef*, אביי אמר
היינו טעמא דאיסי *Abaye amar hainu ta'ama d'Issi*, this is the reason
of איסי *Issi*, דגמר קרחה קרחה Karcha Karcha מבני אהרן *degamar korcha
korcha mi'Bnei Aharon*. He's learning it out from בני אהרן Bnei Aaron
*Bnei Aharon* because there's פסוקים *psukim* also by בני אהרן Bnei Aaron,
*Bnei Aharon* where it says לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם Lo yikrechu karcha
berosham, ופאת זקנם לא יגלהו *lo yikrechu korcha berosham u'peat zekanam lo
yegalechu*, we mentioned this before, right? So the same prohibition that applies
to ישראל Yisrael. *Israel* is said also by the בני אהרן Bnei
Aaron *Bnei Aharon*, and we normally don't learn that to be a
special prohibition on בני אהרן Bnei Aaron *Bnei Aharon* but we actually
link the two to give us some of the parameters of what
are those prohibitions of making bald spots and and so on and
shaving. So here he's going to say, well because it says בני
אהרן Bnei Aaron *Bnei Aharon* there, it's בנים *banim* and not בנות
*banot*, not limited to בני אהרן Bnei Aaron *Bnei Aharon* but it
is meant to exclude women. מבני אהרן מה להלן נשים פטורות אף
כאן נשים פטורות *mi'Bnei Aharon mah lahan nashim peturot af kan nashim
peturot*, the same way there it says בני אהרן Bnei Aaron *Bnei
Aharon* and it means only as it always does when בני אהרן
Bnei Aharon *Bnei Aharon*, only the male, אף כאן נשים פטורות *af
kan nashim peturot*, so women are excluded too from the prohibition of
a bald
spot. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says one minute, like before we
had the whole discussion of בני אהרן ולא בנות אהרן Bnei Aharon
velo bnot Aharon, *Bnei Aharon ve-lo bnot Aharon* by the issue about
the shaving and of the side-locks and of the
sideburns. But if איסי *Issi* is applying the בני אהרן ולא בנות
אהרן Bnei Aharon velo bnot Aharon, *Bnei Aharon ve-lo bnot Aharon* to
the issue of the bald spot, he doesn't need a גזירה שוה
Gezeirah Shavah, *gezeira shava* of קרחה קרחה karcha karcha *korcha korcha*, he
could just say if that's true by female כוהנים *Kohanim*, it should
be true by all females. ואי סבירא לן דהאי כתיב קרא בכולי
עניינא הוא דכתיב נישתכח קרא מיניה ותיתי בקל וחומר *v'ee s'vira lan
d'hai ksiv kra b'chulei inyana hu d'chsiv nishtakach kra minei v'sesei b'kal
vachomer*. Why doesn't it just silent? ותיתי בקל וחומר *v'sesei b'kal vachomer*,
ואנא אמינא *va'ana amina*, I would say מה כוהנים שריבה בהם הכתוב
מצוות Mitzvot יתירות בני אהרן ולא בנות אהרן Bnei Aharon velo bnot
Aharon, *mah Kohanim sheribba bahem hakatuv mitzvot yetirot Bnei Aharon ve-lo bnot
Aharon*, if when it comes to כוהנים *Kohanim*
that they have a lot of extra מצוות *mitzvot*, nevertheless this issue
of the bald spot is limited to the men and not to
the women, so if even women כוהנים *Kohanim* are excluded, בני אהרן
ולא בנות אהרן Bnei Aharon velo bnot Aharon, *Bnei Aharon ve-lo bnot
Aharon*, ישראל Yisrael? לא כל שכן *Israel
lo kol sheken*, certainly when it comes to non-כוהנים *Kohanim*, women should
be excluded. So basically, okay, I accept you're learning it from בני
אהרן ולא בנות אהרן Bnot Aaron *Bnei Aharon ve-lo bnot Aharon*, but
why did you need a גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah *gezeira shava*? So
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אילמלא גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah הוה
אמינה הפסיק העניין *ilmalei gezeira shava hava amina hifsik ha'inyan*. No, if
not for a גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah *gezeira shava* I would have
said that there's a interruption in the פסוקים *psukim* when it says
בני אהרן *Bnei Aharon* before it gets to this issue of גדידה
*gedida*. And therefore you would not have applied the limit of בני
אהרן ולא בנות אהרן Bnot Aaron. *Bnei Aharon ve-lo bnot Aharon* to
גדידה *gedida*. But once it's a גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah *gezeira shava*,
the גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah *gezeira shava* says you there's something to
learn from here. And if there's something to learn from well what
is there to learn from the איסור *issur* the prohibition of גדידה
*gedida* by בני אהרן *Bnei Aharon*? It must be what we're learning
is the limitation of—not גדידה *gedida*—קרחה Karcha. *korcha*. Excuse me, קרחה. Karcha.
Okay, but anyway both are in the same פסוק. But when it's
לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם, Lo yikrechu karcha berosham, excuse me, by בני
אהרן it's לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם, Lo yikrechu karcha berosham apologies, גדידה
is by ישראל. Yisrael, Okay. Anyway, so if when it gets to
לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם Lo yikrechu karcha berosham by בני אהרן, by
the case of the כהנים, Kohanim, there's an interruption between when it
first introduces בני אהרן and it gets to the prohibition of קרחה.
Karcha And therefore I can't, I would not normally have applied בני
אהרן and not בנות אהרן Bnot Aaron. to קרחה. Karcha But once
there's a גזירה שוה, Gezeirah Shavah and I say, well, why what's
the purpose of the גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah to apply קרחה Karcha,
from בני אהרן to ישראל? Yisrael. It must be to teach me
something. What else could it be teaching me? It must be to
teach me the limitation of men and not women. Okay. So therefore
because it's, there's an interruption, I would not naturally have applied the
limitation, but the גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah tells me there's gotta be
something to learn and therefore it's limited to בני אהרן and not
בנות אהרן. Okay. אי לאו גזירה שוה הוה אמינא הפסיק הענין. Ei
lav gezeirah shavah hava amina hifsik ha'inyan. השתא נמי נימא הפסיק הענין?
Hashta nami neima hifsik ha'inyan? So so what? So now that there
is a גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah we should say there's an interruption
and don't apply the limitation to women. Ah, what's the גזירה שוה
Gezeirah Shavah teaching me? דאי משום גזירה שוה מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, De'ei
mishum gezeirah shavah miba'ei lei lachad'tanya, we need it like we learned
in the ברייתא. Baraita. לא יקרחו, Lo yikrechu, יכול אפילו קרח ארבע
וחמש קרחות לא יהא חייב אלא אחת. yachol afilu karach arba ve'chamesh
karchot lo yehei chayav ela achat. Since it says לא יקרחו, Lo
yikrechu, I would have just, I would have thought that maybe, you
know, there's no, it doesn't count by the number of lacerations.
You lacerated, the number doesn't matter and it's all one prohibition. תלמוד
לומר
קרחה. Talmud lomar karcha. A laceration in the singular, לחייב על כל
אחת ואחת, lechayev al kol achat ve'achat, on each one. So לא
יקרחו קרחה Lo yikrechu karcha בראשם berosham by the כהנים Kohanim is
coming to teach me you're חייב chayav on each one. That's what
the גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah. is teaching me and that's going to
teach me that, excuse me, I did it wrong again. קרחה Karcha,
is the bald spot, not the laceration. I apologize. Anyway, okay, so
I would have thought that that even multiple bald spots would only
be one prohibition. So לא יקרחו קרחה is coming to tell me
that for every single bald spot, okay, לחייב על כל אחת ואחת.
lechayev al kol achat ve'achat. בראשם מה תלמוד לומר? Berosham mah talmud
lomar? Why does it say בראשם Berosham. by the כהנים? Kohanim? לפי
שנאמר לא תתגדדו ולא תשימו קרחה בין עיניכם
למת. Lefi shene'emar lo titgodedu velo tasimu karcha bein eineichem lamet. Here's
lacerations finally. Do not make a laceration and do not put a
bald spot between your eyes for a dead. That's by the ישראל,
Yisrael? that's not by כהנים Kohanim and again we're going to make
a גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah and equate them.
So I would have thought יכול לא יהא חייב אלא בין עיניו.
yachol lo yehei chayav ela bein einav. I would have thought that
it's only חייב chayav on a bald spot between the eyes. מנין
לרבות כל הראש? Minayin lerabot kol harosh? How do you know that
it's a prohibition of a bald spot on the whole head? תלמוד
לומר בראשם. Talmud lomar berosham. On their head. לחייב על כל הראש
כבין עיניו. Lechayev al kol harosh ke'vein einav. That that makes everything
is equal. The whole head equal to between the eyes. Okay. If
you make a bald spot over a dead. ואין לי אלא כהנים
שריבה בהן הכתוב מצות יתירות ישראל מנין? Ve'ein li ela kohanim sheribah
bahen hakatuv mitzvot yetirot Yisrael minayin? Now, that idea that it applies
to the whole head and that it applies for every single bald
spot, maybe that's only by the כהנים, Kohanim, right? That's how the
פסוק by the כהנים Kohanim is broader than the פסוק by ישראל.
Yisrael It says קרחה, any bald spot and it says בראשם. So
maybe it's only by כהנים Kohanim that there's a lot of מצוות.
ישראל מנין? Yisrael minayin? How do I know it applies to ישראל?
Yisrael נאמר כאן קרחה ונאמר להלן קרחה. Ne'emar kan karcha vene'emar le'halan
karcha. מה להלן חייב על כל קרחה וקרחה וחייב על הראש כבין
העיניים אף כאן חייב על כל קרחה וקרחה וחייב על כל הראש
כבין עיניו. Mah le'halan chayav al kol karcha ve'karcha ve'chayav al harosh
ke'vein ha'einayim af kan chayav al kol karcha ve'karcha ve'chayav al kol
harosh ke'vein einav.
That's what the גזירה שוה is doing for you to tell you
that also for ישראל Yisrael, it's true, you're חייב chayav on every
single bald spot and you're חייב chayav on the entire head. And
now we're going to though apply one limitation from ישראל Yisrael. that
applies also to כהנים. Kohanim. ומה להלן על מת? U'mah le'halan al
met? It says by ישראל, Yisrael it says לא תתגדדו ולא תשימו
קרחה בין עיניכם למת. lo titgodedu velo tasimu karcha bein eineichem lamet.
So the same way you're only חייב chayav on a bald spot
that's done over grieving over a dead person, אף כאן על מת,
af kan al met, here too for a dead. So we learned
a lot from the גזירה שוה of קרחה קרחה from כהנים Kohanim
to ישראל. Yisrael We learned that it's that both, that
just by כהנים Kohanim it's every bald spot and it's on the
whole head. By ישראל also it's any bald spot and it's on
the whole head and just by ישראל it's over a מת, met,
by כהנים Kohanim also it's over a מת. met. So the גזירה
שוה teaches us a lot and it is not a basis to
assume that we are that because there's a גזירה שוה we're forced
to say there's something else to learn out here and it's only
men and not women. So how do you אביי explain why we're
learning out men and not women? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
אם כן נכתוב קרא קרח. im ken nichtov kra kerach. Or קרח.
kerach. מאי קרחה? mai karcha? שמע מינה תרתי. shma mina tarti. The
extra ה hei of קרחה, it's funny because ה hei can often
be a feminine, but anyway it's telling me that there's like and
רש"י says because it says קרחה קרחה in both places and instead
of a קרח kerach or קרח kerach by both places, a קרח
kerach I guess it would have been. Anyway, that tells me there's
like a second גזירה שוה. And a second גזירה שוה is there's
even yet another thing to learn and that tells me to apply
the limitation of בני אהרן and not בנות אהרן. Okay, that's איסי's
opinion that the bald spot prohibition only applies to
men. רבא אמר היינו טעמא דאיסי. Rava amar hainu ta'ama de'Isi. רבא
Rava says here's the reason of איסי. דיליף בין עיניכם מתפילין. De'yalif
bein eineichem mitfillin. Ah. because it says בין עיניכם *bein eyneychem* by,
by the, by the ישראל *Yisrael*, we saw that, even though we
apply it to the whole head, but it says בין עיניכם *bein
eyneychem*, and it also says בין עיניכם *bein eyneychem* by תפילין *t'fillin*,
so מה להלן נשים פטורות אף כאן נשים פטורות *mah lehalan nashim
p'turot af kan nashim p'turot*. So we know תפילין *t'fillin* are women
are exempt from תפילין *t'fillin*, oh, so they're also exempt from the
bald spot prohibition. רבא מאי טעמא לא אמר כאביי *Rava mai taama
lo amar k'Abaye*? Why did he not say like אביי *Abaye*? קרח
קרחה לא משמע ליה *kerach karcha lo mashma lei*. He doesn't buy
that
the קרח *kerach* and it says קרחה *karcha*, that's like a second
גזירה שוה *Gezera Shava*. He's still stuck on the idea that like
בני אהרן *bnei aharon* and not בנות אהרן *bnot aharon* you would
not have said it because there's a distance from that, from those
words to when the פסוק *passuk* finally gets to talking about the
bald spot. ואביי מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבא *v'Abaye mai taama lo
amar k'Rava*? Why did אביי *Abaye* not like to say like רבא
*Rava*? אמר לך *amar lach*, he'll tell you, תפילין גופייהו מהכא גמיר
לה *t'fillin gufayhu meihacha gamir lah*. That because תפילין *t'fillin* we are
learning from the basic idea that תפילין *t'fillin* when it says בין
עיניים *bein eynayim* it doesn't apply to literally between the eyes, but
it applies to the head part where there's hair. And that's opposite
the space between the eyes. That you learn out from the link
to the what do you call it, to
קרחה *karcha*, to the bald spot between the eyes. מה להלן מקום
שעושים קרחה בגובה של ראש *mah lehalan makom she'osim karcha b'govah shel
rosh*. The same way when it says don't make a bald spot
between the eyes, it's obviously not talking about literally between the eyes.
It means where the hair grows on the top of your head,
you know, above your forehead. That's where it's talking about because that's
where you could make a bald spot. אף כאן מקום הנחה בגובה
הראש *af kan makom hanacha b'govah harosh*. Here too, it is talking
about תפילין *t'fillin*, that's where you put the תפילין *t'fillin*. And since
that's the purpose of the גזירה שוה *Gezera Shava*, to tell you,
you know, the specifics of what the word בין עיניי *bein eynai*
means, now why don't you make a גזירה שוה *Gezera Shava* and
learn both things? ראשונים *Rishonim* ask that but they say, you know,
it's not going to shift gears and go from a focusing on
the meaning of the word בין עיניי *bein eynai* to now teach
you some totally separate הלכה *halacha* that women are excluded. Okay. ובין
לאביי ובין לרבא האי בנים אתם מאי דרשי ביה *u'vein l'Abaye u'vein
l'Rava hai banim atem mai darshi beih*? Since אביי *Abaye* and רבא
*Rava* both say don't learn it out from, you know, from the
פסוק *passuk* of בנים אתם לה' אלוהיכם *banim atem l'Hashem Elokeichem*, they
learn it out from כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* or they learn it out
from
בין עיניים *bein eynayim*, from
תפילין *t'fillin*, so what are they do with the at the end
where it says not to make a bald spot or laceration have
to say, you know, actually what do they do with the beginning
of the פסוק *passuk* it says בנים *banim* since they're not learning
it about בנים *banim* and not בנות *banot*? האי בנים מאי דרשי
ביה? ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדתניא: בנים אתם לה' אלוהיכם, בזמן שאתם נוהגים
מנהג בנים אתם קרויים בנים. *Hai banim mai darshi beih? Hahu mibayei
leih l'khid'tanya: Banim atem l'Hashem Elokeichem, b'zman she'atem nohagim minhag banim atem
k'ruyim banim.* When you act like children, I guess you don't go
ahead and do these idolatrous rituals, then you are considered to be
children to God. Because you know making the lacerations and the bald
spot is most clearly simply understood, you know, could just be excessive
grief, but anyway, but also very much understood it could be in
the context of pagan rituals. Then you're called בנים *banim*. אין אתם
נוהגים מנהג בנים אין אתם קרויים בנים, דברי רבי יהודה. *Ein atem
nohagim minhag banim ein atem k'ruyim banim, divrei Rabbi Yehuda.* That's what
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says. Okay, that when you act like children
you're called children. רבי מאיר אומר בין כך ובין כך אתם קרויים
בנים. *Rabbi Meir omer bein kach u'vein kach atem k'ruyim banim.* רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* has a much more compassionate read, very appropriate for
this time of year. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says either way you're
called בנים *banim*. שנאמר בנים סכלים הם. *Shene'emar banim sechalim hem*. They
are foolish children. ואמר בנים לא אמון בם. *V'amar banim lo emun
bam*. Children without, they cannot be trust,
no trustworthiness. ואומר זרע מרעים בנים משחיתים. *V'omer zera m'rei'im banim mash'chitim*.
An evil seed, children that act corruptly, but they're still children. ואומר
בניי אתם. *V'omer banai atem*. You're my children. You might be bad,
but you're still my children, says God. ואומר והיה במקום אשר יאמר
להם לא עמי אתם יאמר להם בני אל חי. *V'omer v'haya bimkom
asher yeiamer lahem lo ami atem yeiamer lahem bnei kel chai*. Instead
of saying that you are my nation, he'll say לא עמי אתם
*lo ami atem*, instead of saying that you're not my nation, he'll
say to you you are the children of the living God. מאי
ואומר? *Mai v'omer*? What's the addition? Why always quoting extra פסוקים *pessukim*?
וכי תימא סכלי הוא דמיקרי. *V'chi teima sechalai hu d'mikrei*. Okay, foolish.
When you act foolishly we're still children, בנים *banim*. כי לית בהו
הימנותא לא מיקרי בנים? *Ki leit behu heimanuta lo mikrei banim*? But
when we act without trustworthiness we wouldn't be called children? תא שמע
ואומר בנים לא אמון בם. *Ta shma v'omer banim lo emun bam*.
וכי תימא וכי לית בהו הימנותא הוא דמיקרי בנים. *V'chi teima v'chi
leit behu heimanuta hu d'mikrei banim*. Fine, we're called children even when
we act without trustworthiness. But כי פלחו לעבודת כוכבים לא מיקרי בנים?
*Ki palchu l'avodat kochavim lo mikrei banim*? When we worship עבודה זרה
*avoda zara* God won't call us children? תא שמע ואומר זרע מרעים
בנים משחיתים. *Ta shma v'omer zera m'rei'im banim mash'chitim*. A children who
deal corruptly, and corruptly like כי שחת עמך *ki shichat amcha* is
עבודה זרה *avoda zara*. וכי תימא בנים משחיתים הוא דמיקרי. *V'chi teima
banim mash'chitim hu d'mikrei*. Fine, corrupt children. בנים מעלייא לא מיקרי? *Banim
me'alyah lo mikrei*? We'll never again be called, you know, you know,
worthy children? תא שמע ואומר ובמקום אשר יאמר להם לא עמי אתם
יאמר להם בני אל חי. *Ta shma v'omer uvimkom asher yeiamer lahem
lo ami atem yeiamer lahem bnei kel chai*. No, eventually we're always
God's children and eventually we will even be recognized as God's, you
know, you know, when we do תשובה *teshuva*, even all those other
modifiers will fall off and we'll just be, you know, God's children
without modifiers, you know, ideal children. Okay. Fine. So that is the
issue about women's exemption from מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא *mitzvot asseh shehazman
grama* and women's obligation in negative מצוות *mitzvot* with one or two
or three exceptions. Okay. Next משנה *mishnah*. הסמיכות והתנופות וההגשות. *Has'michot v'hat'nufot
v'hahagashot*. So
this is now acts, not of, particularly relating to קרבן Korban *korban*
that women are excluded. The first two relate to the owners. Doing
סמיכה Semicha *smicha* on a קרבן Korban *korban* is what an owner
does, and waving a קרבן Korban *korban*, okay, women are excluded. Excluded
from that, we're going to say this is only men. And now
we're going to the acts of the כהנים Kohanim and now it's
really just male כהנים Kohanim, are the only ones who the כהנים
Kohanim would do the service, not females born to כהנים, Kohanim. so
now women are going to be excluded from all these כהנים Kohanim
acts of service. Okay, הגשות, Hagashot, putting the מנחה Mincha against the
corner of the altar, and קמיצות, Kmitzot, taking the handbreath, and הקטרות,
Haktarot, burning it up on the altar, and מליקות, Melikot, doing you
know slaughtering the bird with the fingernail, and קבלות, Kabbalot, catching the
blood and conveying it as we'll see, and הזאות, Zaot, and sprinkling
the blood and throwing it on the altar, נוהגים באנשים ולא בנשים,
Noagim beanashim velo benashim, all that is men and not women, whether
the women are the, are the offerers in the first two cases
there by the סמיכה Semicha, and the תנופה Tnufa or whether talking,
I mean the one bringing the קרבן or whether we're talking about
the כהנים. חוץ ממנחת סוטה ונזירה שהן מניפות, Chutz miminchat Sota veNezira
shehen menifot,
the exception is the מנחה Mincha that is brought by a סוטה
Sota and a woman who is a נזירה, Nezira, okay, those are
two מנחות Minchot that are brought by women, the נזירה Nezira not
uniquely a woman, I mean נזיר, Nazir, but it's not a unique
sacrifice for her as a woman, and those they would do a
waving. Let's take a look at the גמרא. סמיכות דכתיב דבר אל
בני ישראל וסמך, Smichot dechtiv Daber el Bnei Yisrael vesamach, speak to
the children of Israel
and you should put your hand on, בני ישראל סומכים ואין בנות
ישראל סומכות, Bnei Yisrael somchim ve-ein bnot Yisrael somchot, only בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael and not בנות ישראל, Bnot Yisrael, there's actually a whole
debate whether it's רשות Rashut for בנות ישראל Bnot Yisrael to do
סמיכה, very important debate that has other implications about, you know, women's
participation in מצוות that they're excluded from. And it's interesting תוספות Tosafot
raises the whole issue here about מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמה, Mitzvot Aseh
shehazman grama, although we're not talking about doing these things like to
get like to get credit for doing a מצוה, we're talking about
it as what are the details in which a קרבן is brought.
You know רמב"ן Ramban also asks that what every time it says
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael we're going to exclude women? I mean בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael it says it all over the, all over the
place, but for whatever reason that's what חז"ל Chazal understand here that
it's בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and not בנות ישראל. Bnot Yisrael. תנופות,
Tnufot, the waving, דבר אל בני ישראל והניף, Daber el Bnei Yisrael
vehenif, similar, speak to the children, the sons of Israel and they
should wave, בני ישראל מניפים ואין בנות ישראל מניפות, Bnei Yisrael menifim
ve-ein bnot Yisrael menifot, only the sons, not the daughters. Okay,
הגשות, Hagashot, touching it to the altar, דכתיב וזאת תורת המנחה הקרב
אותה בני אהרן, dechtiv Vezot torat hamincha hakrev otah bnei Aharon, bring
it to the corner of the altar, the sons of Aaron, בני
אהרן ולא בנות אהרן, okay,
קמיצות, Kmitzot, the taking of the handbreath, דכתיב והביאה אל בני אהרן
וקמץ, dechtiv Veheviah el bnei Aharon vekamatz, the son of Aaron shall
take the קמיצה, Kmitza, בני אהרן ולא בנות אהרן, הקטרות, Haktarot, burning,
דכתיב והקטירו אותו בני אהרן, dechtiv Vehiktiro oto bnei Aharon, they shall
offer it up and it the, to burn on the altar, בני
אהרן ולא בנות אהרן, not the daughters, המליקות, Hamelikot, the cutting of
the neck of the bird, דכתיב ומלק והקטיר, dechtiv Umalach vehiktir, he
shall cut it and he shall offer burn it up on the
altar, והוקש מליקה להקטרה, vehukish melika lehaktara, so the same way the
הקטרה Haktara we just said was בני אהרן and not בנות, the
מליקה Melika also is, also says הכהן ומלק, HaKohen umalach, which is
interesting it's how the גמרא learns that that the כהן Kohen uses
his very fingernail, so interesting it doesn't learn it from that, but
anyway, okay, it's only the sons and not the daughters. הקבלות, Hakabalot,
catching the blood, דכתיב והקריבו בני אהרן, dechtiv Vehikrivu bnei Aharon, they
shall offer up the blood, ואמר מר והקריבו
זו קבלת הדם, veamar mar Vehikrivu zu kabbalat hadam, that's catching the
blood and it's also conveying it to the
altar, הזאות דהיכא, Hazayot deheicha, now could it say זריקה, Zrika, the
throwing of the blood, that's the normal way the blood is put
on the altar, הזאה Haza'ah is normally, not the word sprinkling is
not normally what you do with the blood except for certain cases,
so once we're going to say it applies to the sprinkling the
blood applies to the throwing as well, but it's interesting the גמרא
focuses on the word הזאה, Haza'ah, so הזאות דהיכא, Hazayot deheicha, אי
דפרה, ei de-Para, if it's the sprinkling of the ashes of the
פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, אלעזר כתיב ביה, Elazar ktiv bei, it says
אלעזר, Elazar, okay, so and even though we פוסקין pasken you don't
need a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but the fact that it starts
with a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and we have to include other
כהנים means obviously women are excluded, all right, so maybe it's too
obvious to have mentioned, אי דפנים, ei de-fnim, if it is you
know the sprinkling on the מזבח הזהב, Mizbe'ach Hazahav, הכהן המשיח כתיב
ביה, HaKohen haMashiach ktiv bei, it says the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol,
and again now on יום כיפור Yom Kippur that's limited to the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but anyway even if there's other sprinklings on
the inside that's also that isn't limited to a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, but since it starts with a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, obviously
women are excluded.
אלא הזאת דבין העוף, Ella haza'at de-vein ha-of, we're talking about the
normal way in which the blood of a bird is put on
the altar the תורה Torah uses the phrase that you should be
מזה, mazeh, sprinkle, rather than throw, there's not a lot of it.
Okay, דאתיא בקל וחומר מבן צאן, de-atya be-kal vachomer mi-ben tzon, and
here's why we're saying that that's not explicit and it's but we
learn it from a קל וחומר kal vachomer from a normal sheep
and that's how we're going to exclude also a normal sheep here,
the normal throwing of the blood, okay, מבן צאן. mi-ben tzon. ומה
בן צאן שלא קבע לו כהן לשחיטתו, Uma ben tzon shelo kiva
lo Kohen leshchitato, by a sheep it doesn't have to be a
כהן Kohen that is actually doing it as I mentioned before, well
no, the bird has to be actually with body of the כהן,
Kohen, but normal שחיטה shchita even of a קרבן can be done
by a non-כהן Kohen and can be done by a woman. So
if that's true about normally about an about like a sheep or
cow, קבע לו כהן להזאתו, kiva lo Kohen lahaza'ato, it still needs
a כהן Kohen to throw the blood because that's explicit in the
פסוק, and again בני אהרן ולא בנות אהרן, בן עוף שקבע לו
כהן למליקתו, ben of shekiva lo Kohen lemlichato, when it comes to
the actual you know slaughtering of the bird with the fingernail the
כהן Kohen You need a כהן *Kohen* to do it itself, even
the slaughtering of it. So אינו דין שקבע לו כהן להזתה *eino
din she-kava lo Kohen lehazzatah* so and that would also therefore limit
a כהן *Kohen* to the sprinkling of the blood of the bird.
Okay, now the exceptions חוץ ממנחת סוטה ונזירה *chutz mi-minchat Sotah ve-nezirah*.
Okay, אמר ליה רב אלעזר לרבי יאשיה דדריה *amar leh Rav Elazar
l-Rabbi Yoshiya d-darei*. Rav Elazar said to Rabbi Yoshiya of his generation.
There was an older Rabbi Yoshiya. אוטיב אקרעך *otive akreach*, don't sit
on your legs, don't sit down, עד דאמרת לי להא שמעתא *ad
d-amrat li l-ha shemata*, until you explain to me this discussion. מניין
למנחת סוטה שטעונה תנופה *minayin l-minchat Sotah she-te'unah tenufah*?
How do you know that a סוטה *Sotah* that you wave it
and the סוטה *Sotah* herself waves it? Okay, מנלן *menalan*? מנלן *menalan*,
where do you get it from? בגופיה כתיב *be-gufeih ketiv*. What do
you mean? It's in the פסוק *passuk*. והניף את המנחה *ve-henif et
ha-minchah*. No, אלא תנופה בבעלים מנלן *ela tenufah bi-be'alim menalan*?
Yes, I know that it says the כהן *Kohen* waves it, but
how do you know the owner and therefore the woman waves it
as well? Okay, אתיא יד יד משלמים *atya yad yad mi-shelamim*. You
learn it from שלמים *shelamim*. כתיב הכא ולקח הכהן מיד האשה *ketiv
hacha ve-lakach ha-kohen mi-yad ha-ishah*, the כהן *Kohen* should take from the
hand of the woman, the מנחת סוטה *minchat Sotah* after, excuse me,
the מנחת סוטה *minchat Sotah* after he should take it from the
hand of the woman and he should wave it. So it sounds
like that the כהן *Kohen* is waving it after he takes it
from the woman. וכתיב התם ידיו תביאנה *u-ketiv hatam yadav tevienah*.
His hands shall bring it. And by שלמים *shelamim* it says that
the owner waves it. מה כאן כהן אף להלן כהן *mah kan
Kohen af le-halan Kohen*. Now, we learn in both directions. By the
סוטה *Sotah* it's clear that the כהן *Kohen* waves it. It says
he takes it from the hand of the woman and he waves
it. So that teaches me by a שלמים *shelamim* not only the
owner waves it, but the owner and the but the כהן *Kohen*
waves it as well. And then in the reverse. מה להלן בעלים
אף כאן
בעלים *mah le-halan be'alim af kan be'alim*. And the same way by
שלמים *shelamim* it says that the owner waves it, אף כאן בעלים
*af kan be'alim* here too the owner waves it. So by שלמים
*shelamim* it says the owner waves it, by סוטה *Sotah* it says
the כהן *Kohen* waves it. The fact that both of them say
יד *yad*, the hand, we learn now that both by a שלמים
*shelamim* and by a סוטה *Sotah* both the כהן *Kohen* and the
owner wave it. And therefore by the סוטה *Sotah* the woman waves
it. הא כיצד *ha keitzad*? How do you make this work? כהן
מניח ידו תחת יד בעלים ומניף *Kohen meniach yado tachat yad be'alim
u-menif*. The כהן *Kohen* puts his hand under the hands of the
owner and they wave it. Okay, so now by the way Tosafot
says does it mean that the hands are touching one another and
then that he's not concerned about נגיעה *negiah* but he's concerned about
would that be a הפסק *hefsek* for holding onto the vessel itself?
Or does underneath mean that the owner holds it towards the lip
and the כהן *Kohen* holds it towards the base? Two ways of
understanding that. Okay, אשכחן סוטה *ashkechan Sotah*. That סוטה *Sotah*. נזירה מנלן
*nezirah menalan*? And how do you know about a נזירה *nezirah* that
the same is true that she waves it? אתיא כף כף מסוטה
*atya kaf kaf mi-Sotah*. Because it says כף *kaf*, the hand, and
makes a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. So there too the owner waves
it and she waves it. And we will end with this today.