So it's י"ד Yud-Daled and we pick up י"ג עמוד ב Yud-Gimmel
Amud Beis in the middle where we are from we have just
we're dealing with the fact that the משנה Mishnah the opening משנה
Mishnah אלו הן הלוקין Eilu Hein HaLokin lists a lot of sins
that you get כרת Kares for. And the משנה Mishnah says that
this is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's position and it quotes a ברייתא
Braisa three-way debate. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says that you get מלקות
Malkos you get lashes for any negative transgression even if eventually you're
going to even get executed by the court and certainly if you're
going to get כרת Kares which is a pretty harsh approach. And
the גמרא Gemara says it's based on the principle of that it's
all like one long drawn out death. Yes we would say that
you don't get pay a monetary fine and get lashes but lashes
leading up to a more severe bodily fine either by the court
or the heavenly court you would get. That's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
position we're not usually familiar with. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no
you don't get lashes when excuse me you do get lashes when
there's כרת. Kares. You don't get lashes when the court will execute
you because then you don't punish a person twice but כרת Kares
the person might not get they just have to do תשובה Tshuva
which is not what we're normally told the idea that the lashes
get you out of כרת. Kares. So now let's focus on the
position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So it's about 20 lines down
on י"ג עמוד ב Yud-Gimmel Amud Beis the line starts with the
word נמי דומיא דלאו דחסימה. Nami Dumya D'lav Dechasima. There's like an
asterisk one line above where it says דלאו דחסימה. D'lav Dechasima. So
there it says the following: ורבי עקיבא מאי טעמא V'Rabbi Akiva Mai
Ta'ama what's reason for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says that you
don't get court execution and lashes prior to the execution? כדי רשעתו.
Kedei Rishaso.
So that's right by where there's a little circle at the beginning
of the line. משום רשעה אחת אתה מחייבו ואי אתה מחייבו משום
שתי רשעויות. Mishum rishah achas atah mechayvo v'i atah mechayvo mishum shtei
rishayous. That because of for one wickedness and not two no double
jeopardy you only get punished once for the crime. ורבי ישמעאל V'Rabbi
Ishmael now רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael would say back we did that
already. Why were we rereading? הני מילי מיתה וממון או מלקות וממון.
Hanei milei misa u'mamon o malkos u'mamon. That's only if it's if
it's like a monetary fine together with execution or with lashes. אבל
מיתה מלקות Aval misa malkos but if
execution and lashes מיתה אריכתא היא misa arichta hi that's all one
long drawn out death pretty painful. Okay ולרבי עקיבא U'l'Rabbi Akiva now
what would רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say back? How does he distinguish
between getting מלקות malkos by case of כרת Kares and not getting
מלקות malkos by case of מיתת בית דין? misas beis din? He
would say the following: אי הכי חייבי כריתות נמי. I hachi chayvei
kerisos nami.
So if you're not going to get lashes with a court execution
don't get lashes with כרת. Kares. So מאי אמרת mai amart what
would you respond to this? What רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva himself says
שאם עשו תשובה She'im asu tshuva that oh they could do תשובה
tshuva and it won't be two punishments and therefore you're not necessarily
going to get כרת. Kares. So the גמרא Gemara says okay but
השתא מיהא לא עבדי Hashta miha lo avdi but at this point
the person has yet to do תשובה. tshuva. Now we don't know
for sure he'd yet to do תשובה tshuva so meaning reality is
that he already has a punishment of כרת. Kares. The fact that
in theory he could get rid of it doesn't mean that he
wasn't deserving of that punishment. So the גמרא's Gemara not happy that
that's a sufficient reason to get him out of the lashes. Okay
so how do you explain רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? So that's what
now we're going to focus on. How do you explain רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva since right now the person is deserving of כרת Kares
even if in theory he can get out of it? So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי אבהו בפירוש ריבתה תורה חייבי כריתות למלקות.
Amar Rabbi Abbahu b'feirush rivtah Torah chayvei kerisos l'malkos. No
you're right but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns it from a פסוק
pasuk that it's explicit that somebody who gets כרת Kares gets מלקות.
malkos. דגמר לעיני מלעיניך. Dgamar l'einei m'l'einecha. There's a גזירה שוה. gezeirah
shavah. It
by כרת Kares it says ונכרתו לעיני בני עמם V'nichresu l'einei bnei
amam they'll get כרת Kares in the face to the eyes of
their people. And by מלקות malkos it says ונקלה אחיך לעיניך. V'niklah
achicha l'einecha. The explicit verse of מלקות malkos says לעיניך. l'einecha. So
that's the basis of saying it and maybe it's somehow explained by
the fact that in theory you could do תשובה tshuva but fundamentally
it's based on a פסוק pasuk that shows you that כרת Kares
gets מלקות. malkos. Again not saying that מלקות malkos gets you out
of כרת. Kares. מתקיף לה רבי אבא בר ממל Matkif lah Rabbi
Abba bar Mammal so רבי אבא בר ממל Rabbi Abba bar Mammal
challenged that. אי הכי חייבי מיתות בית דין נמי. I hachi chayvei
misos beis din nami. Okay I can make a גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah and get to a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael conclusion and say
that somebody who gets executed by the court gets מלקות. malkos. נגמרם
מעיני מלעיניך. Nigmeram m'einei m'l'einecha. It's
by מיתת בית דין misas beis din it says אם מעיני העדה
נעשתה לשגגה. Im m'einei ha'eidah ne'estah lishgagah. Now interestingly that's when it's
done בשוגג b'shogeg not במזיד b'meizid but anyway that's by עבודה זרה
avodah zarah and it uses the word מעיני m'einei and it uses
the word לעיניך l'einecha by מלקות. malkos. So why not make the
same גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah and say you get מלקות malkos when
you get execution? So the גמרא Gemara says no דנין לעיני מלעיני
ואין דנין מעיני מלעיני. Danin l'einei m'l'einei v'ein danin m'einei m'l'einei. Right.
So לעיני L'einei and לעיניך l'einecha is a much closer link than
מעיני m'einei and לעיניך l'einecha the מ mem versus the ל. lamed.
Anyway yeah I don't know what to tell you. Okay ומאי נפקא
מינה U'mai nafka mina the גמרא Gemara says really? Does that make
a big difference? והא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Ve'ha tana d'vei Rabbi
Ishmael classic line the גמרא Gemara quotes just to show that we
can make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah even if it's not precise.
Because it says ושב הכהן ובא הכהן. V'shav hakohen u'va hakohen. The
כהן kohen will return and... The כהן kohen will return and the
כהן kohen will come. This is by a case of צרעת tzara'at
of the house. And returning and coming to the house either way
means he'll go to the house and we use the words even
though they're completely different words but because the sense is the same
that he'll come to the house to make a גזירה שוה gezera
shava in these הלכות halachot of צרעת. tzara'at. זו השיבה זו ביאה.
zo hshiva zo biah. So therefore it doesn't have to be precise.
ועוד לגמור מעיני מלעיניך. ve-od ligmar me-enei mi-l'enecha. Okay, so fine, but
have if it says מעיני me-enei where the
פסוק pasuk says, alright what does it say?
It says ונקלה אחיך לעיניך. ve-niklah achicha l'enecha.
Okay, by כרת kares it says אם ונכרתו לעיני
בני עמם. im v'nichretu l'enei bnei amam. So that's לעיני l'enei and
לעיניך, l'enecha, that's pretty close. Okay, and then here by מיתה misa
it says
אם מעיני העדה. im me-enei ha-eda. Now actually it's funny because it
says נסתרה שגגה nistara shgaga but okay but that's at least by
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay, so we're saying that מעיני me-enei and
לעיניך l'enecha is a big jump. All right fine because לעיני l'enei
לעיניך l'enecha is closer, you have to admit it's true, this has
a מ mem difference and there's a כ kaf difference. But the
גמרא Gemara says but מעיני me-enei and לעיני l'enei are pretty close,
that's just only a one letter difference. Okay, so why don't we
do this link and since from here you get מלקות malkus by
כרת kares and these two are linked, we should say you get
מלקות malkus by מיתה misa as well. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says so the גמרא Gemara is not impressed by saying a
גזירה שוה gezera shava answer. Says the גמרא Gemara דגמר מעיני מלעיניך.
degamar me-enei mi-l'enecha.
Okay, so that's a standing question. Why don't you get מיתה misa
and מלקות? malkus? So the גמרא Gemara says קיבלה מיניה רבי שמואל
בר יצחק kibla minei Rabbi Shmuel bar Yitzchak that Rabbi Shmuel bar
Yitzchak accepted this question or sort of received an answer and here's
the answer to that. כדי רשעתו משום רשעה אחת אתה מחייבו ואי
אתה מחייבו משום שתי רשעויות. k'dei rishato mi-shum rasha achas ata mechayvo
v'ee ata mechayvo mi-shum shtei rashaos. It goes back to what רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva himself said. No, it's no, no two punishments and
obviously you're not going to get מיתה misa and מלקות. malkus. So
how about, okay, but how about the fact that even by כרת
kares it's a punishment even if in theory you can get out
of it, right now it's a punishment? So no, here's the point.
ברישא דמסרה לבית דין הכתוב מדבר. be-reisha d'misra l'veis din hakatuv medaber.
It's כדי רשעתו במספר, k'dei rishato be-mispar, you the בית דין beis
din impose one punishment. So
rather than emphasizing the fact that כרת kares you could get out
of in theory because right now you haven't gotten out of it,
we're making a different point. It's a בית דין beis din point.
בית דין Beis din can't impose two punishments. So בית דין beis
din can't do מיתה misa and מלקות, malkus, that's two בית דין
beis din punishments. But God can impose כרת kares and בית דין
beis din can impose מלקות. malkus. Okay, so fine, don't say in
theory you can get out of it, you haven't gotten out of
it yet. But רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva point still is you can't
get two בית דין beis din punishments. To get מלקות malkus is
not a problem because the other punishment is a punishment from God.
And that pretty much fits in with רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva language.
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva language is that other punishment, כרת, kares, that
works on a different plane. God will forgive you for it if
you do תשובה, teshuva, that's between you and God. That's not our
concern. Okay, our concern is בית דין beis din down here and
therefore we're going to give you מלקות. malkus. Yes. Should it be
the same thing for something that's מיתה בידי שמים? misah bi-yedei shamayim?
Yeah, we don't make a difference about this about מלקות, malkus, it's
true the גמרא Gemara isn't exploring that but כרת kares and מיתה
בידי שמים misah bi-yedei shamayim get bundled together for these discussions. So
you would get מלקות malkus for that. Okay. Okay, so that's a
nice answer that's pretty close to the original version of what רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said. רבא אמר, Rava amar, first wide line of
יג עמוד א. yud gimel amud aleph. רבא Rava said עשו בה
לקלה כולה לא פליגי דאין לוקה ומת. asu ba l'kala kuli alma
lo pligi d'ein loka u-mes.
So רבא Rava now, now that we have a good explanation for
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and we could just go home, רבא Rava
though wants to tone down the position of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
because רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that you get lashes and מיתה.
misa. That's pretty harsh. So רבא Rava says that's not what רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael meant. Everybody would agree that you would not get
two punishments from a בית דין, beis din, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
would not say you get lashes and מיתה. misa. Okay, דאין לוקה
ומת. d'ein loka u-mes. כי פליגי, Ki pligi,
so what does רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael mean when he says that
you get lashes by something that you're חייב מיתה chayav misa for?
He means in a case where you're not going to impose the
מיתה misa punishment. Now what would be that case? Because if there
are witnesses and warning, you would impose the מיתה misa punishment. And
if there's no witnesses or no warning, you can't impose מלקות. malkus.
So which is the case that you wouldn't impose מיתה misa and
you would impose מלקות? malkus? So here's the case. So he says
כי פליגי דאתרו ביה למלקות, ki pligi d'atru bei l'malkus, that yes,
there were witnesses, but they gave him the wrong warning. They got
mistaken, they thought חילול שבת chilul shabbat was only lashes. Okay, they
didn't mention מיתה. misa. They had רחמנות rachmanus on the guy so
they didn't mention מיתה. misa. But they said if you do it
you'll get lashes. And he said אף על פי כן. af al
pi chein. So when רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says you get lashes,
he's not saying you get lashes together with the מיתה. misa. It
is a sin that you should be getting מיתה misa for, but
they gave you the wrong warning. Can we give you lashes for
that sin? Okay, that's the debate.
Even though this is a negative prohibition that is normally given to
forbid an act and to get for the sake of a court
execution, meaning even though the normal punishment of this act is a
court execution, nevertheless, if that was not the warning given, since at
the end of the day the guy's transgressed a negative prohibition and
any negative prohibition has within it the deserve the punishment of מלקות.
malkos. Okay, so if you're not going to get the punishment of
מיתה, misah, we can give you the punishment of מלקות. malkos. לוקין
עליו. lokin alov. For Rabbi
Akiva סבר לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין אין לוקין עליו. savar
lav shenitan l'azharas misas beis din ein lokin alov. No, so the
guy gets off scot-free? But this negative prohibition is only punishment assigned
to it is מיתת בית דין. misas beis din. So it's not
that everything has a default מלקות malkos to it. When there's a
weightier punishment there is not the lighter punishment. Okay, and it is
only מיתת בית דין. misas beis din. Does your חבר chaver make
a difference? Right, so that's an interesting question or even within the
חבר chaver question, the question is is if say they give you
wrong התראה hasra'ah does it reshape the nature of the act? Yeah,
so that's a discussion in the אחרונים. achronim. Okay, so now the
גמרא gemara says like this. Okay, for Rabbi Akiva, so that's now
the debate. The debate is not getting two, the debate is getting
one. Okay, but it's the lower one. For Rabbi Akiva אי הכי
חייבי כריתות נמי לאו שניתן לאזהרת כרית הוא. i hachi chayavei krisos
nami lav shenitan l'azharas kares hu. One minute says the גמרא, gemara,
but now for Rabbi Akiva's logic is, when the לאו lav is
assigned a weightier punishment, it can't be used to get lashes. So
then if you get כרת, kares, that's a weightier punishment. So why
do we say that the לאו lav is can be used to
give you כרת, kares, to give you lashes? אמר ליה רב מרדכי
לרב אשי הכי אמר אבימי מהגרוניא משמיה דרבא. amar lei Rav Mordechai
l'Rav Ashi hachi amar Avimi m'Hagronya mishmei d'Rava. Yes, what they say
in the name of רבא, Rava, חייבי כריתות לא צריכי התראה. chayavei
krisos lo tsrichi hasra'ah. No, they are the כרת. kares. For God
to give you כרת, kares, like the whole idea that you need
a negative prohibition in order to get a punishment, that's sort of
like a legal point, right? How down here in the court you
can't get punished unless there's a prohibition and the prohibition has to
match up with the punishment and so on. But as far as
God is concerned, God can give you כרת kares even without a
negative prohibition. Okay, now I'm sort of making it about God as
opposed to the court, but the גמרא gemara actually makes it just
even anyway based on the facts because there are cases where you
get כרת kares without a negative prohibition. What's the case you can
get כרת kares without a negative prohibition?
There's two cases you can get כרת kares for not doing an
עשה. aseh.
What are they? פסח וברית מילה. Pesach u'Bris Milah. So the גמרא
gemara says you don't need a negative prohibition for כרת. kares. So
the גמרא gemara says הרי פסח ומילה הנה שפיר השתא. harei Pesach
u'milah hineh shapir hashta. Okay,
so it works out perfectly. Rabbi Akiva says that, you know, a
לאו lav can only be used for one thing, so a לאו
lav for מיתה misah cannot be used for מלקות. malkos. You can't
get מלקות malkos for a sin that you would get מיתה misah
for. But כרת, kares, you don't need the לאו lav for כרת.
kares. If the תורה Torah says כרת, kares, you get כרת. kares.
The תורה Torah didn't even have to prohibit it. All the תורה
Torah has to say is you get כרת. kares. So when the
תורה Torah says don't do it, that לא תעשה lo sa'aseh is
matched to getting מלקות. malkos. And that's why you can get מלקות
malkos and get כרת. kares. Notice still again, it's not that the
מלקות malkos gets you out of כרת. kares. Okay, it's just you
can get מלקות malkos and the כרת, kares, they're working on different
planes. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says, one minute, ודילמא אזהרה לקרבן?
v'dilma azharah l'korban?
Maybe you need the לא תעשה lo sa'aseh not to get כרת.
kares. You're right, כרת kares you get by itself, you don't need
the לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. But maybe you need the לא תעשה
lo sa'aseh by all these כרת kares cases to bring a קרבן.
korban. Because every case you have כרת kares for, you bring a
קרבן korban for. And how do I know that that requires a
לא תעשה? lo sa'aseh? Because there are two כריתות krisos you don't
bring a קרבן korban for, and that's when there's no negative prohibition.
Not getting a ברית מילה bris milah and not bringing a קרבן
פסח, korban pesach, you don't bring a קרבן korban for. So that
shows you, what's the difference? It's כרת. kares. So it shows you
the קרבן korban is not because of the כרת. kares. The קרבן
korban is the combination of the כרת kares and the negative prohibition.
Okay, you got that? You need both combined. So since you need
both combined, maybe the negative prohibition can't get מלקות malkos for it.
You need it to be part of the קרבן korban package. So
the גמרא gemara says like
this: ודילמא אזהרה לקרבן דהא פסח ומילה דלית בהו אזהרה לא מייתי
קרבן. v'dilma azharah l'korban d'ha Pesach u'milah d'lais behu azharah lo maysei
korban. So you see קרבן korban is the combination of כרת kares
and a לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. So how can you use the
לא תעשה lo sa'aseh of a כרת kares to give מלקות? malkos?
You need it for part of the קרבן korban package. So the
גמרא gemara says no, התם לאו היינו טעמא. hasam lav hainu ta'ama.
The reason you don't bring a קרבן korban for פסח Pesach and
מילה milah is not because of a לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. You
don't need a לא תעשה lo sa'aseh to bring a קרבן. korban.
This is all very radical, right? You don't need a לא תעשה
lo sa'aseh to get כרת. kares. You don't need a לא תעשה
lo sa'aseh while we sort of knew but nonetheless what thought by
default was this. You don't even need a לא תעשה lo sa'aseh
to bring a קרבן. korban. You really bring a קרבן korban by
any כרת, kares, even in theory if there was no לא תעשה.
lo sa'aseh. So why do you not bring it by פסח Pesach
and מילה? milah? התם לאו היינו טעמא אלא משום דאיתקיש כל התורה
כולה לעבודה זרה. hasam lav hainu ta'ama ella mishum d'itkish kol haTorah
kullah l'avodah zarah.
Because we know you bring קרבנות korbanos because עבודה זרה avodah zarah
is a paradigm based on a certain פסוק pasuk of bringing a
קרבן. korban. So it has to be like עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
It's not because of the לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. מה עבודה זרה
שב ואל תעשה, mah avodah zarah shev v'al ta'aseh, the same way
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. עבודה זרה avodah zarah
if you're doing the right thing you're not doing anything. It's a
funny way of saying it, but meaning the transgression is an active
transgression, אף כל שב ואל תעשה, af kol shev v'al ta'aseh,
and therefore the only time you bring a קרבן korban is if
you should have been passive and you were active, meaning is when
only when you do an active transgression do you bring a קרבן.
korban. לאפוקי הני דקום ועשה l'afukei hani d'kum va'aseh to exclude פסח
pesach and מילה milah where you should have been active and your
sin was being passive. So what the גמרא gemara says is the
qualities of bringing a קרבן korban is כרת kares and an active
transgression. Okay, but you don't need the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. So
now what we're saying is for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva there's an
economy of the לא תעשהs. lo ta'aseh לא תעשה lo ta'aseh can
only use for one thing, so if a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh
is used to get say you get a death penalty, then you
can't get מלקות malkus even if they give you a different warning.
But if in case of כרת, kares, you don't use the לא
תעשה lo ta'aseh for כרת. kares. כרת kares can exist without a
לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, like פסח, pesach, you don't even need the
לא תעשה lo ta'aseh for a קרבן. korban. Any כרת kares that's
an active transgression you bring a קרבן. korban. So in that case
the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh is free to say that you get
מלקות. malkus. So the מלקות malkus is for the לא תעשה lo
ta'aseh and the כרת kares and the activity exists without the לא
תעשה lo ta'aseh and the קרבן korban exists without the לא תעשה.
lo ta'aseh. Okay, so that's a different read of the whole thing
and that's talking about how can you use the what are you
using the פסוק pasuk for? Can you use it for one thing
or two things? Now we go back to the more classically that
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is saying you get both and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva saying I can't give you you can't get two things.
Okay. רבינא אמר לעולם כדאמרינן. Ravina amar l'olam k'da'amarina.
Really top of י"ד עמוד ד'. yud daled amud daled. Really it's
like we were saying all along מעיקרא me'ikara originally, שחשיב גבי בית
דין שמו ליה מלקות. shechashiv gabei Beis Din shamu lei malkus.
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says I give you two punishments, מיתה מלקות,
misa malkus, pretty shocking, or מיתה כרת. misa kares. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says sorry, no two punishments, but כרת kares is not a
second punishment. Now why is it not a second punishment? So before
we said well because it's a it's a God punishment, not a
בית דין Beis Din one. But now we're going back to what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva really really said, which is that you could
get out of it. But the גמרא's gemara question is but how
does the fact that in theory you could get out of it
mean it's not a punishment? Right now you haven't gotten out of
it, right now you are deserving it. So let's take a look.
מאי אמרת הלוא עביד תשובה, mai amarta halo avid teshuvah, יופי, yofei,
okay, but maybe he but he hasn't done תשובה teshuvah yet. He
is deserving of it now, so how can we give him two
punishments? No, לא פסיקא מילתא לכרת, lo pesika milta l'kares, which is
clearly what it seems to be what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was
basically saying all along. Since you're not definitely going to get it,
it doesn't count as two punishments. Two punishments means when this is
a definite second one. Since the first one is something in theory
you could get out of, it's not like we're definitely giving you
two punishments. Okay, so that's just going back to the פשט pshat
of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. It's funny that it took him so
long to come along to that, but now what we have is
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says I don't have a problem giving the
guy מלקות malkus even though he gets כרת, kares, I because כרת
kares is not something בית דין Beis Din imposes, it's something God
imposes. Or even if I just look at it as a guy
is suffering twice, as long as it's not a definitely suffering twice,
he has the ability to get out of the כרת, kares, then
that's not my problem. Okay, so again with all these opinions, even
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says you get מלקות malkus for כרת
kares and not for מיתת בית דין, missas Beis Din, he's not
saying that it gets you out of כרת. kares. He's just saying
that it's not a problem of being punished twice. Now we finally
move on to רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says
you do not get מלקות malkus for כרת. kares. So again, I
know I keep on repeating it, but it's just because it was
going against everything that I was taught in the ישיבה. Yeshiva. Nobody
here is saying that the yet that the מלקות malkus gets you
out of כרת. kares. Right? רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says you get
two punishments, מלקות מיתה, malkus misa, מלקות כרת. malkus kares. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says for כרת kares you get two punishments, כרת kares
and not for מיתה, misa, because כרת kares in theory is only
from God or כרת kares you can get out of, but not
that the מלקות malkus gets you out of it. And רבי יצחק
Rabbi Yitzchak says if you're getting no, it's this is also considered
double jeopardy and you do by the way, I'm using misusing double
jeopardy, right? Double jeopardy means you can't be tried twice, isn't that
right? Okay, whatever. Anyway fine. Okay, you got my point though. Okay.
Anyway, רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says even this is two punishments and
if you're because something that you get כרת kares for you can't
get מלקות malkus for. רבי יצחק אומר חייבי כריתות בכלל היו. Rabbi
Yitzchak omer chayvei kerisos bichlal hayu. No, חייבי כריתות chayvei kerisos were
normally included, I'm reading this tosh line תוספות's Tosafot way, in all
negative prohibitions that you would be deserving of מלקות malkus for. So
in I would have started out assuming like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that you should get מלקות malkus for
חייבי כריתות. chayvei kerisos. So למה יצאת כרת באחותו? lama yatzas kares
bachoto? But why does the Torah explicitly mention by a man's sister
that it gets כרת kares since that was part of the general
כרת kares in the Torah in all the עריות? arayot? לדונו בכרת
ולא במלקות. ladunu b'kares v'lo b'malkus. He says you only כרת, kares,
not מלקות, malkus, so there's no מלקות malkus by the case of
by any case of a כרת. kares. Now what we're going to
do for the remainder of today's דף daf is to look at
all of to look at the times it says
כרת באחותו kares bachoto and all the extra things it says by
sister and understand what they're all coming to teach. Like how everybody
deals with the extra פסוקים. pesukim. So this is going to be
like a little complicated so maybe let me just write the פסוק
pasuk here on the board.
Here's what the פסוק pasuk says by אחותו. achoto. by the sister.
Right at the end of all the עריות arayos it says: כי
כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האל, ki kol asher ya'aseh mikol hatovos
ha'eil, oh that's ותטמא הארץ, vatitma ha'aretz, but anyway it says ונכרתו.
v'nichresu. Where's the end of the פסוק? pasuk? כי כל אשר
יעשה מכל התועבות האלה ונכרתו הנפשות העשות מקרב עמם. ki kol asher
ya'aseh mikol hatovos ha'eileh v'nichresu hanefashos ha'osos mikerev
amam.
That's at the end of אחרי מות. Acharei Mos. So even though
at the end of אחרי מות Acharei Mos it says one big
כרת, karet, okay, by the sister it says: ערות אחותך בת אביך
או בת אמך מולדת בית או מולדת חוץ... ervas achoscha bas avicha
o vas imecha moledes bayis o moledes chutz... wait one minute, no
I'm sorry, the אחותו achoso is by in קדושים. Kedoshim. Excuse me.
In the middle of קדושים, Kedoshim, it specifically mentions כרת karet by
the אחותו. achoso. It says: ואיש אשר יקח את אחותו בת אביו
או בת אמו וראה את ערותה והיא תראה את ערותו
חסד הוא ונכרתו לעיני בני עמם ערות אחותו גלה עונו ישא. v'ish
asher yikach es achoso bas aviv o vas imo v'ra'ah es ervasah
v'hi sir'eh es ervaso chesed hu v'nichresu l'einei v'nei amam ervas achoso
gilah avono yisa. That's a very long פסוק pasuk for אחותו, achoso,
okay? So what's that פסוק? pasuk? That is a פסוק pasuk in
כ' י"ז. Chaf Yud Zayin. It's where my... anyway. Okay, it says:
ואיש אשר יקח, v'ish asher yikach,
ואיש אשר יקח v'ish asher yikach
את אחותו, es achoso, בת... bas...
okay, then goes בת אביו או בת אמו, bas aviv o vas
imo, וראה את ערותה והיא תראה את ערותו, v'ra'ah es ervasah v'hi
sir'eh es ervaso, וראה את ערותה... v'ra'ah es ervasah... that's a very
long פסוק... pasuk... והיא תראה את ערותו. v'hi sir'eh es ervaso. Okay,
חסד
הוא, chesed hu,
חסד הוא. chesed hu.
Anyway then:
ונכרתו לעיני בני עמם. v'nichresu l'einei v'nei amam. Which it does not
say by the other... by the other things, but the other things
are just included in the general כרת, karet, okay? לעיני בני עמם,
l'einei v'nei amam, ערות אחותו גלה, ervas achoso gilah, ערות אחותו גלה,
ervas achoso gilah, where was it? עונו ישא. avono yisa. That's
a very long פסוק. pasuk. So anyway this whole extra כרת, karet,
ונכרתו, v'nichresu, right, in this whole פסוק pasuk in קדושים, Kedoshim,
is to tell you only כרת karet and not מלקות. malkos. So
now the גמרא Gemara says... but all the rest of them get
כרת karet because it says at the end of אחרי מות, Acharei
Mos, so it just says everybody gets כרת. karet. Yeah, but these
people, some of these are ערירי ariri maybe? Maybe you could say
that for ערירי ariri you don't get כרת. karet. I understand. כרת
karet and ערירי ariri is considered to be in addition to כרת.
karet. Anyway, כרת karet and ערירי. ariri. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this: So now that's what רבי יצחק Rebbi Yitzchak uses
it for. So now we have to say that רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva and רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, who say you do get מלקות
malkos for כרת, karet, so what do they do with this extra
ונכרתו? v'nichresu? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay, ורבנן,
v'rabbanan, so... well the רבנן rabbanan meaning רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל, Rebbi Yishmael, כרת באחותו למה לי? karet b'achoso lama li?
Why did the תורה Torah add כרת באחותו? karet b'achoso? לחלק, l'chaleik,
to tell you to distinct... distinguish, meaning to say that there's a
general principle if somebody does multiple sins in one state of forgetfulness,
you bring a קרבן korban for every distinct
sin. And every sin, meaning and we know that the sins you
bring קרבנות korbanos for are things you get כרת. karet. So the
reason it singles out כרת באחותו karet b'achoso is to tell you
don't think you're just going to bring one קרבן korban because you
did all these sins at once, you know, in one state of
forgetfulness. No, the actual source that you bring multiple קרבנות korbanos for
multiple sins done under one state of forgetfulness is the fact that
it singles this out. Since it mentions all the עריות, arayos, well
שבת Shabbos is a special thing because it's חילוק מלאכות, chiluk melachos,
so it's different. It's even within one sin each מלאכה melacha seen
is different, but that's different. But since all the עריות arayos is
one big כרת, karet, and this is singled out, is to tell
you even if you do a whole bunch of stuff, you get...
each one has to be treated separately, and each one is a
separate קרבן. korban. כגופות מוחלקות. k'gufos mocholakos. I know. So that's okay,
but this is where we learn that from. Then you have another
level of חידוש chiddush which is even when it's one person, one
body. We'll get to that. Okay? But first things first, like this
is the foundation.
Okay? So it's to teach you this principle. למה לי לחלק. lama
li l'chaleik. כדרבי יוחנן. k'deRebbi Yochanan. דאמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rebbi Yochanan,
שמהם כולם בהעלם אחד. shemahem kulam b'he'elam echad. Now this is going
on the משנה Mishnah in כריתות. Kerisus. Why does the משנה Mishnah
in כריתות Kerisus list the thirty-six עבירות aveiros that you get כריתות
kerisus for and it says these are thirty-six?
By highlighting the number, it's to tell you that this is the
maximum number of קרבנות korbanos you can bring. That even if you
do all of them in one state of forgetfulness, חייב על כל
אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achas v'achas, you're חייב chayav for everyone.
So now, okay, so that's now what you do with this פסוק
pasuk according to רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Rebbi Yishmael.
But רבי יצחק Rebbi Yitzchak who learns it for מלקות, malkos, where
does he learn this principle? רבי יצחק לחלק מנא ליה? Rebbi Yitzchak
l'chaleik m'na leh? Where does he learn this principle that each sin
is a different קרבן? korban? נפקא ליה מואל אשה בנדת טומאתה לא
תקרב לגלות ערותה. nafka leh m'v'el ishah b'nidas tumasah lo sikrav l'galos
ervasah. To a woman when she is a נידה. niddah. Why doesn't
it just say, you know,
ולנידה לא תקרב u'l'niddah lo sikrav when a woman is a נידה?
niddah? Why does it say a woman who is in her נידה?
niddah? It's actually interesting because it's only, so the emphasis of the
word אשה isha לחייב על כל אשה ואשה l'chayiv al kol isha
v'isha that every woman is a distinct, if you have multiple acts
of forbidden sexual acts, every woman is a distinct קרבן, korban, every
forbidden woman. That's where he learns it out from. Okay, so he
learns אחותו achoto to tell you no מלקות malkut and the פסוק
pasuk אשה isha to tell you each woman is a separate
קרבן. korban. ורבנן, v'rabanan, and the Rabbis, נמי תיפקו ליה מהכא, nami
teifku lei meihacha, why don't they learn it out from the word
אשה? isha? So the גמרא gemara says אין הכי נמי, ein hachi
nami, fine, let's say they learn it out from there. So now
we're back to the question, what do the Rabbis do with the
word כרת? karet? ואלא כרת דאחותו למה לי, v'ela karet d'achoto lama
li, what do they use it for? לחייב על אחותו ועל אחות
אביו ועל אחות אמו. l'chayiv al achoto v'al achot aviv v'al achot
imo. Let's say there are three separate sins that they're all sister
related. A woman who is a, now we first think this means
three women. A man sleeps in one state of forgetfulness with his
sister, his father's sister, his mother's sister, three קרבנות. korbanot. So the
גמרא gemara says, so you bring, so the חידוש chiddush is that
you bring three קרבנות, korbanot, each one is separate. גמרא gemara says
פשיטא! pishita! הרי גופין מוחלקין. harei gufin m'chulakin. Like Miles said, they're
different bodies, different people. We've already said it's a separate קרבן korban
for every separate sin. So how could you say, so now we're
saying נכרתו nichretu means, right, we already know separate קרבנות korbanot for
separate sins, but what they're saying to do נכרתו nichretu is if
it's three versions of a sister. But we think it means three
separate women. So the
גמרא gemara says, so that's what the גמרא gemara is going to
say. So the
גמרא gemara says, אלא לחייב על אחותו שהיא אחות אביו שהיא אחות
אמו. ela l'chayiv al achoto she'hi achot aviv she'hi achot imo. No,
no, a woman who is both his sister and his mother's sister
and his father's sister. Okay? והיכי משכחת לה? v'heichi mashkachat lah? How
do you get it? רשיע בר רשיע. rasha bar rasha. Okay, a
wicked person, the son of a wicked person. So basically, let's see
if I can get this right. Sounds like one of these Esav
kind of things. Yeah, רש״י Rashi describes it as basically,
okay,
here you have this man, okay, and he basically has sex with
his mother. And therefore from that comes this woman. So she is
both his sister and his daughter. Got that?
Then he goes ahead and has sex with her. And then this
woman is his daughter, wait, this woman is his daughter, am I
getting this right?
Daughter and his granddaughter.
Hold on a minute. No, but we have to get, the mother
has to have a second, hold on let me read רש״י, Rashi,
let me read רש״י, Rashi, let me see if I got this
right. Who's the grandfather? Hold on, hold on, hold on. Yeah exactly,
the הבא על אמו והוליד שתי בנות וחזר ובא על אחת מהן
והוליד בן ובא בן על אחות אמו. haba al imo v'holid shtei
banot v'chazar uva al achat meihen v'holid ben uva ben al achot
imo. So he had these two daughters, okay, and then, okay, and
then this was a son, okay, and then, where are we, ובא
בן על אחות אמו. uva ben al achot imo. So then he
goes, okay, so then he goes ahead and has sex with this
woman. So this woman
is his mother's sister, yeah, you with me? His father's sister, right,
because his father had sex with his mother and had both of
these girls. His mother's sister and his sister because they share the
same father. Okay, so there you go. Now we got it all
figured out. Anyway, so what we use נכרתו nichretu for, back to
this. What's נכרתו nichretu being used for? So
for רבי יצחק, Rebbe Yitzchak, you know he wants to say no
מלקות. malkut.
And for רבנן, rabanan, which is רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva etc., we're
going to use it to say, you know, whatever,
three, you know, for אחותו achoto etc. and אחות אמו achot imo
etc. if it's one person who's all three of them, it's still
separate קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay, that's what we're doing with that. Or also מלקות, malkut, right?
Because רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva holds,
yeah but we're not going to focus on that right now, now
we're focusing on קרבנות, korbanot, but yes. Okay, so that's what you
do with it. So now the גמרא gemara says like this: רבי
יצחק מנא ליה? Rebbe Yitzchak mna lei? So where does רבי יצחק
Rebbe Yitzchak know that הלכה, halacha, that this person who's three in
one, you get separate קרבנות? korbanot? Where does he know it from?
What? We assumed everyone agrees to it? So נפקא ליה מקל וחומר.
nafka lei mikol vachomer. He learns it from a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. דתניא, d'tanya, it was taught in a ברייתא: braita: אמר רבי
עקיבא, amar Rebbe Akiva, and here we're going to get the discussion
of exactly this הלכה. halacha. שאלתי את רבן גמליאל ואת רבי יהושע
sha'alti et Rabban Gamliel v'et Rebbe Yehoshua באיטליז, b'itliz, in the sort
of the, you know, the marketplace, but not the, whatever, selling meat,
the meat market של אמאום, shel Imaum, that was the name of
the place, שהלכו ליקח בהמה למשתה בנו של רבן גמליאל. shehalchu likach
behema l'mishteh bno shel Rabban Gamliel. You gotta love the color, like,
where? We were all going there to buy a nice little side
of beef for his son's wedding feast, okay? And you know, we
talk תורה. Torah. And we're walking. So here was a little הלכה
halacha תורה Torah he asked: הבא על אחותו היא אחות אביו היא
אחות אמו מהו? haba al achoto hi achot aviv hi achot imo
mahu? What would be the הלכה halacha there? How many קרבנות? korbanot?
אינו חייב על כולם אלא אחת, eino chayav al kulam ela achat,
you'd be bringing only one קרבן, korban, או חייב על כל אחת
ואחת? o chayav al kol achat v'achat? He'd be bringing three קרבנות
korbanot for the one act. אמרו לו: amru lo: זו לא שמענו.
zo lo shamanu. We don't have a tradition about this. אבל שמענו
aval shamanu we do have a tradition that הבא על חמש נשים
נדות בהעלם אחד haba al chamesh nashim niddot b'helem echad that a
man who has sex with five different women and they're all נדה
niddah in the same state of forgetfulness, שחייב על כל אחת ואחת.
shechayav al kol achat v'achat. He brings separate ones. Now, that is
also different than what we talked before. Before we talked about different
women, different עבירות, aveirot, and then there's two variations of that: same
woman, multiple, multiple עבירות aveirot that's this case of sister and whatever
and then there's different women, same עבירה, aveirah, which is five different
women that are נדה. niddah. So they thought, oh maybe we could
make an analogy: different women, same עבירה aveirah is multiple קרבנות, korbanot,
so one woman, multiple עבירות aveirot would also be multiple קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay. ודנו דברים מקל וחומר, v'danu dvorim m'kal vachomer, and
we'd like to make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה נדה ששם
אחד u'mah niddah she'shem echad that's all the same עבירה aveirah חייב
על כל אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achat v'achat, you bring different
קרבנות korbanot because it was different women, so כאן ששלשה שמות kan
she'shlosha shemot here it's three different statuses לא כל שכן, lo kol
sheken, how much more so should you bring three קרבנות? korbanot? So
that was their analogy. Of course, you could say it's not a
good קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Who says
that the maybe different bodies is more significant than different statuses? ואידך,
v'idach, the other one would answer back: קל וחומר פריכא הוא kal
vachomer pricha hu this קל וחומר kal vachomer can be challenged. מה
לנדה שכן גופין מוחלקין mah l'niddah sheken gufin mocholakin there are different
bodies in your case. ואינך נמי הבאתיך קל וחומר פריכא הוא. v'inach
nami havatich kal vachomer pricha hu. Fine. So you're right, so that
is that's not a good קל וחומר. kal vachomer. אלא נפקא ליה,
ela nafka leh, so now we're back. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva gets
from ונכרתו v'nichretu this three-in-one. Where does רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak get
the three-in-one from? Because he learns from this that you don't get
מלקות. malkus. נמי הוי קל וחומר פריכא הוא. nami havei kal vachomer
pricha hu. אלא נפקא ליה ela nafka leh he learns it מאחותו
דסיפא me'achoto d'seifa
because it says in the end אחותו achoto this is why I
wrote it out ערבת אחותו גילה. ervat achoto gilah. It could have
just said ערבתה גילה. ervatah gilah.
Why does it mention אחותו achoto again? Okay. So רבי יצחק Rabbi
Yitzchak gets this idea of multiple statuses of אחותו achoto each one
is different. That's where he gets it from. Alright, good. Now of
course the next question is going to be: what does רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva do with that אחותו? achoto? Okay. מאחותו דסיפא. me'achoto d'seifa.
ואידך, v'idach,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say back: אחותו דסיפא למה לי? achoto
d'seifa lama li? What does he do with that? לחייבו על אחותו
בת אביו ובת אמו לומר שאין עונשין מן הדין. l'chaivo al achoto
bat aviv u'vat imo l'omar she'ein onshin min hadin.
Okay, so here we have the same: when the תורה Torah says
a man should not sleep with his sister, it says don't sleep
the prohibition of sleeping with his sister is in אחרי מות Acharei
Mot and there it says the following, it says: ערבת בת אשת
ervat bat eshet no, excuse me, ערבת בת אביך או בת אמך
ervat bat avicha o vat imecha no, one minute thank you, ערבת
אחותך בת אביך או בת אמך מולדת בית או מולדת חוץ לא
תגלה ערבתן. ervat achotcha bat avicha o vat imecha moledet bayit o
moledet chutz lo tegaleh ervatan.
Don't sleep with your sister on your father's side or your mother's
side. Okay, but it doesn't mention your full sister. Now it's a
little funny. You would think that not only קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
it's better than a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, it is a קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, but you would actually think a full sister is
also a half-sister. But you know what I mean, it's also בת
אביו, bat aviv, but no. The גמרא Gemara says that's a separate
status. The תורה Torah says don't sleep with your half-sister, it never
says don't sleep with your full sister. But when it speaks about
the punishment of sleeping with your sister, right, in this case, איש
אשר יקח את אחותו בת אביו או בת אמו ish asher yikach
et achoto bat aviv o vat imo whatever, then it says ערבת
אחותו גילה. ervat achoto gilah. So here, right, it doesn't mention it
does mention half, but it also mentions full, okay? I mean, just
by simply saying אחותו achoto and אחותו achoto here, it includes even
full. So we have the punishment for full sister, but we don't
have the prohibition for a full sister. So what רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva so what, so what רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak says this אחותו
achoto teaches you all these multiple statuses, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says this אחותו achoto teaches you the prohibition for full sister. This
is the punishment for full sister, it teaches you the prohibition for
full sister. Okay. ואידך, v'idach, so that's what he says. אחותו דסיפא
למה לי? achoto d'seifa lama li? Okay, לחייבו על אחותו בת אביו
ובת אמו l'chaivo al achoto bat aviv u'vat imo לומר שאין עונשין
מן הדין. l'omar she'ein onshin min hadin.
Okay,
you don't get
oh wait, did I get this right or did I get it
reversed? One minute. No, I think I got it reversed. Hold on.
I'm sorry, I reversed it, I apologize everybody. The גמרא Gemara says
that because that this actually they are reading this, they are reading
this to be limited to half-sister because of this part. But in
the prohibition in אחרי מות Acharei Mot somehow because it says an
extra אחותך, achotcha, they're reading that to refer to full sister. I
don't exactly get the difference, but anyway, but that's what they say.
So the פסוק, pasuk, what's the פסוק pasuk say again? בת אחותך
בת אביך בת אמך Bat achotcha bat avicha bat imecha ובת אחותך
Uvat achotcha ובת אחותך, ubat achotcha, because I guess it starts with
אחותך. achotcha. But I mean, I know why that אחותך achotcha is
extra. So anyways, I'm sorry, so there it's ערוות, ervat, okay, there
it's ערוות אחותך ervat achotcha and then it's בת אביך, bat avicha,
I mean here it's also אחותך, achotcha, I don't get it, okay
whatever, או בת אמך. o bat imecha. So somehow we're assuming that
this means full sister, okay? So the prohibition is full sister, but
here when it speaks about getting כרת, karet, we're assuming only half
sister. So what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva do with this extra
אחותו? achoto?
He when he uses this extra אחותו achoto is he tells me
that the punishment is also for full sister.
I'm not exactly clear why the prohibition is clearer than the punishment.
But anyway, that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does. Let's read that
again: אחותו לסיפא למה לי לחייבו אחותו בת אביו ובת אמו. Achoto
leseifa lama li lechayvo achoto bat aviv uvat imo. To tell you
you get כרת karet for full sister, לומר שאין עונשין מן הדין,
lomar she-ein onshin min ha-din, that you don't get you wouldn't just
say it based on a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you need the
פסוק pasuk to tell you explicitly that you get the punishment for
the full sister as well. ואידך, Ve-idach, okay, so now רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva does for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva for ונכרתו ve-nichretu tells
me these double statuses, and for ואחותו ve-achoto רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
tells me that this is going to be full sister, okay? So
this is the double statuses and this is the full sister. That's
what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva does. Alright. Whereas רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak
says that the ונכרתו ve-nichretu is going to be רבי יצחק Rabbi
Yitzchak is going to tell me the ונכרתו ve-nichretu is going to
be the case of no מלקות malkos
and this is going to be the multiple statuses, multiple אחות. achot.
Okay, that's רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. Okay, so now we have a
problem though: where does רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak learn the idea that
you get punished for full sister? Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says,
well we already had multiple אחות. achot. So if multiple אחות achot
you know you get separate קרבנות. korbanot. Where do you get the
idea no but that's enough half sister versus full sister? How do
you know that full sister is the punishment? So the גמרא Gemara
says okay ואידך אי בעית אימא גמר עונש מאזהרה. ve-idach i bayit
eima gmar onesh me-hazhara. Okay, since here you're prohibited by full sister,
we'll learn from here to there and say you're punished for full
sister even without an extra word. ואי בעית אימא נפקא ליה מאחותו
דרישא. Ve-i bayit eima nafka lei me-achoto de-reisha. Oh, there's another אחותו
achoto that we forgot up here, okay? So this אחותו achoto now
רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak what does he do with that אחותו? achoto?
He basically tells you full sister, okay? So he's got full sister,
multiple, and no מלקות. malkos. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you do
get מלקות malkos so he has multiple and full sister. So now
we're going to have to figure out what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva do with that extra אחותו? achoto? Okay, ואידך, ve-idach, so now
what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva do with this extra אחותו? achoto?
ההוא
מיבעי ליה לחלק כרת למפטם ולסך Hahu mibaei lei le-challek karet le-miftem
u-le-sach to tell you a different הלכה halacha about since a major
thing we're doing here, right, is saying multiple קרבנות, korbanot, right? Particularly
this one, right, multiple statuses, multiple קרבנות, korbanot, לחלק le-challek etc. So
there's another interesting question: what do you do if the תורה Torah
tells you separate לאו תעשהs lo ta-aseh but one כרת? karet? So
meaning by תורה Torah when it says don't make the קטורת ketoret
like the like you know they would make in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and don't anoint the שמן המשחה shemen ha-mishcha from the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and then it says because anybody who makes
the קטורת ketoret or anoints the oil ונכרתו ve-nichretu
gets כרת. karet. So there's separate prohibitions but only one time it
said כרת karet in referring to both sins. Alright, so the question
is if you went ahead and did both sins בהעלם אחד be-he-elam
echad would you bring one קרבן korban because of one כרת? karet?
But maybe since the basis of קרבן korban is the time is
when you get כרת, karet, that's exactly the question. Well we had
it with עריות arayot already that it says ונכרתו ve-nichretu in אחרי
מות. Acharei Mot. You have all these different people and they only
get one כרת. karet. So why is that any different? Right, you
mean why doesn't the fact that it says כרת karet there so
רש"י Rashi sort of, so yeah, that's sort of what רש"י Rashi
then sort of worries about. I don't want to... it's a very
good question, okay? But at least, and that's why there's a big
תוספות, Tosafot, a big רש"י Rashi to figure out, but let's just
bracket it. Because what Michael is saying is that of by all
the cases of the of the עריות arayot
it doesn't say a separate כרת karet for each. It says like
a global כרת karet for all of them and we still learn
from אחותו achoto to divide it. So why don't we say the
same here? It's an excellent point but I'm just going to bracket
it. Okay, so the point is is that there you have two
לאוs lav and one כרת. karet. So what we're going to learn
from this extra אחותו achoto is even in a case where there
are two לאוs lav and one כרת karet you're going to get
separate קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, ההוא מיבעי ליה לחלק כרת למפטם ולסך Hahu
mibaei lei le-challek karet le-miftem u-le-sach to split up the כרת karet
and say that like one for each one, okay? So if you
look at רש"י Rashi Michael just to briefly answer your question, רש"י
Rashi is aware of this issue. So the רש"י Rashi two lines
from the
top says למפטם ולסך דהוו נמי שני לאווין. le-miftem u-le-sach de-havu nami
she-nei lavin. Notice the word
נמי, nami, okay, והוצרך לנו לחלק ביניהם כמו שהוצרך חילוק דעריות אין
הכי נמי ועניין להו. vehutzrach lanu lechalek beineihem kemoshe hutzrach chiluk de-arayot
ein hachi nami ve-inyan lehu. So basically to tell you that this
is not just by עריות, arayot, it is a general principle, okay?
So yes, but it's the same idea, okay? So this is to
tell you just like by עריות arayot you had one כרת, kares,
multiple לאוין, lavin, each one is separate קרבן. korban. Other places where
that idea similar, like מפתה ולסוך, mefateh ulesoach, you would have separate
קרבן. korban. Funny thing is, this is also in עריות. arayot. Right,
but the extra is by עריות arayot is to tell you one
thing. So that's רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. So now we've got everybody
using the פסוקים psukim but we're always one left over cause רבי
יצחק Rebbe Yitzchak uses one of these to tell you no מלקות.
malkus. So where does he get this idea of separating the for
מפתה ולסוך? mefateh ulesoach? ואידך, Ve-idach,
the other one say back, סבר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא דאמר
רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא כל מקום שאתה מוצא שני לאוין וכרת
אחד חלוקין הם לקרבן, savar Rebbe Eliezer amar Rebbe Oshaya d'amar Rebbe
Eliezer amar Rebbe Oshaya kol makom she-ata motze shnei lavin ve-kares echad
chalukin hein le-korban,
that really you don't need a special פסוק. pasuk. It's just a
logic that it goes by the לאוין, lavin, it doesn't go by
the כרת kares and that tells you just think you don't need
to learn it from a פסוק. pasuk. All right, that's easy enough.
So רבי יצחק Rebbe Yitzchak doesn't say, he says you need to
learn it from a פסוק. pasuk. Look, we should be able to
get to a period here somewhere, okay? You have to get to
one point where the other one learns it from somewhere else and
we're done. All right, so that's one answer, that he doesn't need
one learns it from a פסוק pasuk and the other one doesn't.
ואיבעית
אימא, Ve-ibayeit eima, maybe he doesn't hold like רבי אלעזר. Rebbe Eliezer.
So where does he learn that idea of separate קרבנות korbanot from
other places like מפתה ולסוך? mefateh ulesoach? ונפקא ליה מוואיש אשר ישכב
את אשה דוה, V'nafkalei mi-v'ish asher yishkav et isha dava,
if a man sleeps with a woman who is flowing, that's a
case of a נדה, niddah, okay?
And that פסוק, pasuk, what's extra in that פסוק? pasuk? Let me
remind myself what רש״י Rashi says is extra. You already have it
in מצורע Metzora and ותקרב, v'tikrav, right? Right. No, because one is
about the prohibition and one is about the punishment.
One minute. דכתיב, De-ketiv, it says an extra כרת. kares. Oh, I
guess it's similar to אחותו, achoto, okay? This is one of the
things like אחותו, achoto, the same way by אחותו achoto it says
כרת, kares, here it says in קדושים Kedoshim it says כרת kares
even though it was already part of a general rules of כרת.
kares. Okay, you're looking it up, ואיש אשר ישכב את אשה דוה
וגלה את ערותה את מקורה הערה והיא גלתה את
מקור דמיה ונכרתו שניהם. v'ish asher yishkav et isha dava v'gila et
ervatah et mekora he-erati v'hi gilta et mekor
dameha v'nichretu sheneihem.
Okay, so that's another time it says כרת kares extra. So it's
not about the words אשה דוה, isha dava, it's just an extra
כרת. kares. Okay, so he does it from the extra כרת kares
to tell you separate קרבנות korbanot by something like מפתה ולסוך. mefateh
ulesoach. All right. ואידך הוא מיבעי ליה לרבי יוחנן, Ve-idach hu miba'ei
lei le-Rabbi Yochanan, he needs it to tell you what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says. דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי מנין
לנדה עד שיצא מדוי דרך ערותה. D'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon
ben Yochai minayin le-niddah ad she-yeitzei midveih derech ervatah. How do you
know that a woman only becomes a נדה niddah when the blood
comes like you know through the genitals, to the nakedness, through the
vagina? Maybe it just says she bleeds, maybe if she has a
nosebleed. How do you know where the blood is coming from? שנאמר
ואיש אשר ישכב את אשה דוה וגלה את ערותה. She-ne'emar v'ish asher
yishkav et isha dava v'gila et ervatah. So connect the flow at
דוה dava's often read also as like illness, but here it's reading
it as flow with the nakedness, with her genitals. מלמד שאינה טמאה
עד שיצא מדוי דרך ערותה. Melamed she-eina t'meiah ad she-yeitzei midveih derech
ervatah. And the other response will say yeah, that's what I learn
from there but the extra כרת kares there is to teach you
this extra idea. So thankfully the גמרא Gemara stopped trying to figure
out how to deal with like one person has one extra פסוק,
pasuk, okay? Everybody learns it out from somewhere. When they say ערותה
ervatah does it mean one specific place? I mean there's lots of
places that are ערווה. ervah. No, ערווה ervah's considered to be the
vagina, that's where in the פסוק וגלה את ערותה pasuk v'gila et
ervatah anyway fine. All right, moving on. So now we're done. What's
fascinating is we have all three opinions: Do you get מלקות? malkus?
רבי ישמאל Rebbe Yishmael says I'll give you מלקות malkus with מיתה,
misa, מלקות malkus with כרת. kares. רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva says only
with כרת. kares. רבי יצחק Rebbe Yitzchak says I won't give you
מלקות malkus with any of those, okay? So רבי יצחק Rebbe Yitzchak
clearly argues against the משנה, Mishnah, but none of them say the
classic thing that we normally hear which is that the מלקות malkus
gets you out of the כרת. kares. All right. Now we finally
get to turn to the individual sins. Okay, so after all the
עריות, arayot, we get to some of these בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
things. וטמא שאכל את הקודש, Ve-tamei she-achal et ha-kodesh,
somebody who is טמא tamei that eats sacrifices. Okay,
בשלמא, b'lishlama, now that's also a כרת, kares, okay? Somebody who is
טמא tamei who goes into the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, somebody who's
טמא tamei eats a קרבן, korban, it's כרת kares but you get
מלקות malkus according to this משנה. Mishnah. בשלמא הבא למקדש טמא כתיב
עונשא וכתיב אזהרתה. B'lishlama ha-ba le-mikdash tamei ketiv onsha v'ketiv azharata.
If when it talks about being טמא tamei entering into the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it says the punishment and it says the prohibition.
עונשא דכתיב את משכן ה׳ טמא ונכרתה, Onsha de-ketiv et mishkan Hashem
timei v'nichreta,
okay, you know he defiled the sanctuary of God and he gets
כרת. kares. אזהרתה ולא יטמאו את מחניהם. Azharata v'lo yetame'u et machaneihem.
Good. אלא טמא שאכל את הקודש, Ela tamei she-achal et hakodesh, but
if a טמא tamei person eats
קרבנות, korbanos, בשלמא bishlama עונש כתיב, onash ktiv, הנפש אשר תאכל מבשר
זבח השלמים אשר להשם וטומאתו עליו ונכרתה. hanefesh asher tochal mi-besar zevach
hashlamim asher l'hashem v'tumato alav v'nichreta. That if you eat קרבנות korbanos
when you're טמא tamei you get כרת. kares. אלא אזהרה מנין? Ela
azhara minayin? Where's an אזהרה azhara from? Now of course רש"י Rashi
points out he needs an אזהרה azhara exactly because we don't want
to get you כרת, kares, we want to get you מלקות, malkos,
and for מלקות malkos you need a לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. But
it says already ונכרתה. v'nichreta. Yeah, but we don't want to just
get you כרת. kares. Our משנה mishna wants to get you מלקות.
malkos. For מלקות malkos you need a לא תעשה, lo sa'aseh, right?
So that's why we need to find, Michael's correct to remember that
what we said before is כרת kares doesn't need a לא תעשה,
lo sa'aseh, although that was only one opinion. But regardless, our interest
here is not כרת. kares. Our interest is מלקות malkos and for
מלקות malkos you need a לא תעשה. lo sa'aseh. Now רש"י Rashi
points out that there's actually a פסוק posuk that sounds pretty explicit
about this, which is ובקדשים לא יאכל עד אשר יטהר, u-vakodashim lo
yocheil ad asher yithar, which sounds pretty explicit: don't eat קרבנות korbanos
until you become טהור. tahor. But we're going to later say that
that applies to תרומה, terumah, not to קדשים. kodshim. So even though
it's a pretty explicit פסוק, posuk, that's not good enough for us.
So we want to know what's the פסוק posuk that says a
טמא tamei person can't eat קרבנות. korbanos.
So
where were we? תניא
זו, Tanya zu, so אזהרה מנין? azhara minayin? ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
אמר amar בכל קודש לא תיגע be-chol kodesh lo tiga by a
woman
who gave childbirth. בכל קודש לא תיגע ואל המקדש לא תבוא עד
מלאת ימי טהרה. be-chol kodesh lo tiga v'el hamikdash lo tavo ad
melos yemei tahora. Don't touch, which he understands to mean don't eat.
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan אמר amar תני בר דלא tani bar dala
אתיא טומאתו טומאתו. atya tumato tumato. Make a גזירה
שוה. gzeira shava. כתיב הכא וטומאתו עליו ונכרתה ktiv hacha v'tumato alav
v'nichreta by eating קרבנות. korbanos. It says וטומאתו עליו ונכרתה. v'tumato alav
v'nichreta. So that's eating קרבנות, korbanos, the punishment. וכתיב התם, u-ktiv hatam,
it says by going into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, טמא יהיה
עוד טומאתו בו. tamei yihye od tumato bo. מה להלן עונש ואזהרה,
ma lohalan onash v'azhara, so that's linking the eating קרבנות korbanos to
the going into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So the same way
by going into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash we know that that's
prohibited, אף כאן עונש ואזהרה. af kan onash v'azhara. So by eating
קרבנות korbanos we also know it's prohibited. Okay, so he has a
גזירה שוה, gzeira shava, just like going into the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash is prohibited, eating a קרבן korban is prohibited. All right, and
רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael learns it out from בכל קודש לא תיגע.
be-chol kodesh lo tiga. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish learns that from there.
בשלמא ריש לקיש דלא אמר כרבי יוחנן, Bishlama Resh Lakish d'lo amar
k'Rebbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish doesn't say like רבי יוחנן, Rebbi
Yochanan, גזירה שוה לא גמיר. gzeira shava lo gmir. He doesn't have
a גזירה שוה. gzeira shava. אלא רבי יוחנן מאי טעמא לא אמר
כריש לקיש? Ela Rebbi Yochanan mai ta'ama lo amar k'Resh Lakish? Why
does he not say from ריש לקיש? Resh Lakish? בכל קודש לא
תיגע be-chol kodesh lo tiga means don't eat a קרבן korban when
you're טמא. tamei. אמר לך, amar lach, ההוא אזהרה לתרומה. hahu azhara
l'terumah. That's not saying don't eat a קרבן, korban, that's saying don't
eat תרומה terumah when you're טמא. tamei. בכל קודש be-chol kodesh includes
even תרומה. terumah. וריש לקיש v'Resh Lakish
would say אזהרה לתרומה מנא ליה? azhara l'terumah mena lei? Where does
he know not to eat תרומה terumah when you're טמא? tamei? נפקא
ליה nafka lei מאיש איש מזרע אהרן והוא צרוע או זב בקדשים
לא יאכל. me-ish ish mi-zera Aharon v'hu tzarua o zav bakodashim lo
yocheil. Now that's the most explicit פסוק posuk not to eat a
קרבן korban when you're טמא, tamei, but he's going to say it
applies only to תרומה. terumah. And how does he say that applies
only to תרומה? terumah? I'll write this on the board in a
minute to help organize this information. איזהו דבר שהוא שוה בזרעו של
אהרן? eizehu davar she-hu shaveh be-zar'o shel Aharon? It says איש איש
מזרע אהרן. ish ish mi-zera Aharon. It doesn't just say the males.
So if it was talking about קרבנות, korbanos, it would have said
the males. But the seed of אהרן, Aharon, all of his kids,
what's the one thing that all of the אהרן Aharon descendants can
eat? הוי אומר זו תרומה. hevei omer zu terumah. So that prohibits
תרומה. terumah. So what are we saying now? I need a napkin
or something here. There are descendants of אהרן Aharon who can't eat
תרומה? terumah? Yes, fine, but חלה, challah, we're not dealing with that.
That was a good question. Never lend out your markers or erasers
to other teachers, you never get them back. Okay, so we have
בכל קודש לא תיגע be-chol kodesh lo tiga and then we have
איש איש מזרע אהרן, ish ish mi-zera Aharon, והוא צרוע או
זב
בקדשים לא יאכל. v'hu tzarua o zav bakodashim lo yocheil. Now this
would of course seem to be the פסוק posuk that we should
say that you're not allowed to eat קודש kodesh בטומאה. be-tumah. But
because it says מזרע אהרן, mi-zera Aharon, we basically say that this
is talking about תרומה. terumah. Okay,
so ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says that therefore, according to ריש לקיש,
Resh Lakish, this
פסוק posuk is
טמא שאכל תרומה. tamei she-achal terumah. Okay, and
בכל קודש לא תיגע, be-chol kodesh lo tiga, even though it says
לא תיגע, lo tiga, ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says that this is
about
טמא שאכל קודש. tamei she-achal kodesh. That's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
says. Got it? רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, I need a third color.
Anyway, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says בכל קודש לא תיגע be-chol kodesh
lo tiga is about תרומה. terumah. So what now, but he doesn't
argue on the זרע zera thing, מזרע אהרן, mi-zera Aharon, so he
has two פסוקים psukim about תרומה. terumah. So what's he going to
do? So let's take a look. Okay, so... האי למזו תרומה ואידך
חד לאכילה וחד לנגיעה. hai lemezo trumah veidach chad lachilah vechad lenegia.
Okay,
so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan says this is about טמא, tamei, this
is about רישא. reisha. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan says yes I agree
this is טמא שאכל תרומה. tamei sheachal trumah. I agree with you,
okay, they're both saying the same thing. Okay, and this is טמא
שנגע תרומה, tamei shenaga trumah. which is what it says. בכל קודש
לא תיגע, bechol kodesh lo tiga, okay.
So this is here in the פסוק pasuk doesn't have a ו
vov and it says תיגע. tiga. All right, Michael. Anyway, so this
is here about eating תרומה. trumah, Everybody agrees this is eating תרומה.
trumah. Get rid of it. Okay, so now we're going to focus
in on this debate. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish learns out eating קדשים
kodashim from a different פסוק pasuk and he says this is touching
תרומה. trumah. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't learn out eating קדשים kodashim
from a different פסוק, pasuk, so for ריש לקיש Reish Lakish this
is about eating קדשים. kodashim. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like
this.
ריש לקיש... Reish Lakish... okay. Now, ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, so now
the
גמרא Gemara says האי בכל קודש לא תיגע להכי הוא דאתא. hai
bechol kodesh lo tiga lehachi hu deata. So now we're going to
bracket this. We all know not to eat תרומה trumah. בטומאה betumah
from this פסוק. pasuk. And since they agree, we can take it
off, it's no longer relevant. Okay. So now the debate is, is
it about eating קדשים kodashim or about touching תרומה? trumah So does
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish disagree with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan that you
can't touch? Well that's what we're going to see. מאי לאו ריש
לקיש לית ליה... mai lav Reish Lakish leit lei... he doesn't have
an איסור issur for touching. Right,
that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Maybe ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish doesn't have an איסור issur of touching
תרומה. trumah? You would think that, but now we're about to see
that he actually does say that. So now we're going to have
a problem that he's going to learn both things from this פסוק.
pasuk. So let's take a look.
Okay. ריש לקיש האי בכל קודש לא תיגע להכי הוא דאתא? Reish
Lakish hai bechol kodesh lo tiga lehachi hu deata? Really is it
coming just to say not to eat קדשים? kodashim? הא מיבעי ליה
לטמא שנגע בקודש. ha mibaye lei letamei shenaga bekodesh. He learns it
not only touching תרומה trumah. but touching
קודש. kodesh. דאיתמר טמא שנגע בקודש. deitmar tamei shenaga bekodesh. ריש לקיש
אמר לוקה, Reish Lakish amar lokei, you get מלקות. malkut. ורבי יוחנן
אמר אינו לוקה. veRabbi Yohanan amar eino lokei. ריש לקיש אמר לוקה
בכל קודש לא תיגע. Reish Lakish amar lokei bechol kodesh lo tiga.
ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו לוקה התרא לתרומה הוא דאתא. veRabbi Yohanan amar
eino lokei hatra letrumah hu deata. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan is
consistent, this is about טמא שנגע tamei shenaga תרומה. trumah But ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says this is first טמא שאכל קודש tamei sheachal
kodesh and then he says it is טמא שנגע קודש. tamei shenaga
kodesh. So he's doing both things. Now I want to just pause
for a moment because תוספות Tosafot points out the irony that רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan says that there's a prohibition for touching תרומה trumah
when you're טמא tamei but not a prohibition for touching קדשים, kodashim,
right? קדשים kodashim which certainly should be weightier. Okay. So תוספות Tosafot
suggests that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan maybe means that this isn't a
prohibition for touching תרומה, trumah, it's telling you that if you touch
תרומה trumah you're מטמא metamei it, but it's not actually telling you
it's a prohibition. That's a problem that the גמרא Gemara doesn't explore.
We're really only looking at ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says, which does he say here? Is he saying don't eat
קודש kodesh or is he saying don't touch קודש? kodesh? Make up
your mind. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ריש לקיש אמר לוקה ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו לוקה ריש לקיש אמר
לוקה בכל קודש לא תיגע ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו לוקה התרא לתרומה
הוא דאתא. Reish Lakish amar lokei veRabbi Yohanan amar eino lokei Reish
Lakish amar lokei bechol kodesh lo tiga veRabbi Yohanan amar eino lokei
hatra letrumah hu deata. So the גמרא Gemara says yes, he learns
both.
מדיאפקיה רחמנא בלשון נגיעה. mideiafkeia rachmana bileshon negiah. So I know that's
saying don't touch because it says לא תיגע. lo tiga. That's טמא
שנגע קודש. tamei shenaga kodesh. How do I know it also means
don't eat for ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish? Okay, אחרא לאוכל achra leochel
because איתקש קודש למקדש. itkash kodesh lemikdash. Because the end of the
פסוק pasuk of בכל קודש לא תיגע bechol kodesh lo tiga ואל
המקדש לא תבוא. veel hamikdash lo tavo. So the same way going
into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash is כרת, karet, touching קודש kodesh
is not כרת. karet. Okay. Eating קודש kodesh בטומאה betumah is כרת.
karet. Okay. So I know it's טמא שנגע tamei shenaga because of
לא תיגע. lo tiga. I know it's eating, אכל קודש, achal kodesh,
because of the link to אל המקדש לא תבוא. el hamikdash lo
tavo. Okay, why? Because they're both כרת. karet. No, but how do
I know it's אכל? achal? Maybe it's just... that's the only other
thing because... what? I don't know, but whatever... I mean, what else
could it be? It's the only other thing you get כרת karet
for other than entering. Okay, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish actually says
yes, I learn both from this פסוק. pasuk. All right. So let's
keep on going. It could just be the way it sounds, just
don't go into the מקדש, mikdash, how did it have anything to
do with אכל? achal? No, the link. No, no, no. מקדש mikdash
is not... no, no. לא תיגע lo tiga is telling you two
things. לא תיגע lo tiga is telling you both don't eat and
don't touch. I know the touch because it's the פשט pshat of
the word, and I know the eat from the context. So the
word תיגע tiga has two meanings. Okay, the פשט pshat meaning and
the meaning from the context. That's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
saying. All right, let's just finish this up.
Okay. והשתא להכי הוא דאתא? vehashtah lehachi hu deata? One minute. But
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish uses it for yet another thing. הא מיבעי
ליה לטמא שאכל בשר קודש לפני זריקת דמים, ha mibaye lei letamei
sheachal basar kodesh lifnei zrikat damim, that you can't eat if you're
טמא tamei even before the blood has been sprinkled. דאיתמר deitmar it
was said, טמא שאכל בשר קודש לפני זריקת דמים. tamei sheachal basar
kodesh lifnei zrikat damim. ריש לקיש אמר לוקה. Reish Lakish amar lokei.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is a big one on getting מלקות. malkut.
ורבי יוחנן אמר אינו לוקה. veRabbi Yohanan amar eino lokei. ריש לקיש
אמר לוקה בכל קודש לא תיגע. Reish Lakish amar lokei bechol kodesh
lo tiga. So בכל קודש, bechol kodesh, we're going to learn out
from the word בכל bechol comes to include Don't even eat it
even before the blood has been sprinkled. ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* בכל
קודש לא תגע *bechol kodesh lo tiga*, לא שנא לפני זריקה ולא
שנא אחר זריקה *lo shena lifnei zrika velo shena achar zrika*. רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* אמר אינו לוקה *amar eino loke*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* לטעמיה *litaamei*, דאמר קרא *da'amar kra* טומאתו טומאתו *tumaso tumaso*. וכי
כתיב *vechi ksiv* טומאתו *tumaso* לאחר זריקה דכתיב *le'achar zrika dichtsiv*. Right,
remember, how did רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* learn that a טמא *tamei*
person should not eat a קרבן *korban*? Because of the גזירה שוה
*gezeira shava* of טומאתו עליו *tumaso alav* when it speaks about כרת
*kares*. When it speaks about כרת *kares*, כרת *kares* of eating a
קרבן *korban* בטומאה *betuma* is only after the meat is fit to
be eaten, after זריקת דמים *zrikas damim*. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
the only prohibition of a טמא *tamei* person eating a קרבן *korban*
is linked to the פסוק *pasuk* of getting כרת *kares* for being
טמא *tamei* for eating a קרבן *korban*. And that's only after זריקת
דמים *zrikas damim*. Because if the קרבן *korban* is not yet fit
to be brought to be eaten, it's not seen as as bad
of a sin. But ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish*, I know, but ריש
לקיש *Resh Lakish*, so that's why רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says you
don't get מלקות *malkos*. But ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* says you get
מלקות *malkos*. But he's already given you two מלקות *malkos* from this
פסוק *pasuk*. How does he get the third one? Where were we?
וכי כתיב טומאתו לאחר זריקה דכתיב *vechi ksiv tumaso le'achar zrika dichtsiv*.
ההיא מבכל נפקא *hahi m'bechol nafka*. Ah,
that's like I already told you, the word from בכל *bechol*. כל
*kol* is to tell you even before. So תגע *tiga* means two
things: it means don't touch if you're טמא *tamei*, and it means
don't eat if you're טמא *tamei*. We know the eat meaning from
the context, and the בכל *bechol* tells you don't even eat it
even if the meat is before זריקת דם *zrikas dam*. And we
just end with one תניא כוותיה *tanya kvasia*. תניא כוותיה *tanya kvasia*,
where were we? תניא כוותיה דריש לקיש *tanya kvasia deResh Lakish*: בכל
קודש לא תגע *bechol kodesh lo tiga* אזהרה לאוכל *azhara le'ochel*. אתה
אומר לאוכל או אינו אלא אזהרה לנוגע *ata omer le'ochel o eino
ela azhara lenogea*? תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar* בכל קודש לא תגע ואל
המקדש לא תבוא *bechol kodesh lo tiga ve'el hamikdash lo tavo*. מקיש
קודש למקדש *makish kodesh lemikdash*. מה מקדש דבר שיש בו נטילת נשמה
*ma mikdash davar sheyesh bo netilas neshama*, אף כל דבר שיש בו
נטילת נשמה *af kol davar sheyesh bo netilas neshama*. So it's some
type of a touching, quote unquote, that is a חיוב כרת *chiyuv
kares*. ואי בנגיעה מי איכא נטילת נשמה *ve'i bignia mi ika netilas
neshama*? אלא באכילה *ela ba'achila*. So for ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* this
לא תגע *lo tiga* has the פשט *pshat* meaning of touch and
the contextual meaning of eating קרבנות *korbanos* when you're טמא *tamei*, and
כל *kol* is even before זריקת דם *zrikas dam*. And that is
the end of our discussion of eating קרבנות *korbanos* when you are
טמא *tamei*. Excellent, we will pick up with this tomorrow. Just a
quick parallel: so it's not as serious a sin to טמא קדשים
*tamei kodashim* until the blood has been sprinkled?