Hi everybody, I hope you all had an enjoyable Thanksgiving.
Now you're going to have to do a תענית בהב Ta'anis Bahab
to recover. Okay.
We pick up today's דף, daf, it's מכות Makkos 19, יט. Yud
Tes. We pick up... where do we pick up?
Top of יט עמוד א, Yud Tes Amud Aleph, we're actually a
little bit ahead, right? Okay, so we are dealing with this question
about when do בכורים Bikurim become permissible to be eaten by a
כהן Kohen and the flip side of it as we pointed out,
right, like before... before that moment, if it's the moment of the
placing down or the declaration, then it's אסור assur to everybody, it's
sort of like a קרבן korban before the blood was sprinkled. That's
the lashes mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah, בכורים Bikurim before the declaration.
After the declaration a כהן Kohen can eat it and for a
non-כהן Kohen it's like eating תרומה Terumah and it's a problem of
זרות. zarus. So anyway, the question was when, and again so it's
been an ongoing question whether it's the declaration or the הנחה. hanachah.
And we said that... let's pick that up again.
Okay. So אמר רב יהודה בכורים, Amar Rav Yehudah Bikurim, top first
line of יט עמוד א, Yud Tes Amud Aleph, אימתי מחייבין עליהם,
Eimasai mechayvin aleihem, when is a non-כהן Kohen חייב chayav for eating
them as a זר zar and it's like a חייב מיתה בידי
שמים? chayav misa bidei shamayim? משיורו פני הבית. Mishe'yiru pnei habayis. So
not the placing down and not the declaration, but the actual bringing
into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And that was the third opinion
that we had before that reads the word הנחה hanachah to be
referring to waving, so it's not emphasizing הנחה, hanachah, so it's just
bringing into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. כמאן, Keman, who is this
going like? כי האי תנא, Ki hai tanna, like the following תנא,
Tanna, דתניא, detanya, as it was taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. רבי
אליעזר אומר בכורים מקצתם בחוץ ומקצתם בפנים, Rabbi Eliezer omer Bikurim miktzasam
bachutz umiktzasam bifnim,
if you have a basket let's say, half is inside the line
of the עזרה Azarah and half is outside, שבחוץ הרי הן כחולין
לכל דבריהם, shebachutz harei hen kechulin l'chol divreihem, outside is still like
חולין, chulin, which doesn't mean it's permissible to be eaten but again
would mean that it's not yet הקדש hekdesh and it's not an
issue of זרות. zarus. שבפנים הרי הן כהקדש לכל דבריהם. Shebifnim harei
hen k'hekdesh l'chol divreihem. And once it crossed the line then it's
fully sanctified and it's something that can only be eaten by the
כהן Kohen and has that קדושה kedusha status. But again, not to
suggest that beforehand it's okay to eat it but just it is
not the violation of זרות. zarus. One minute. אמר רב ששת, Amar
Rav Sheshes, said רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, בכורים הנחה מעכבת בהן. Bikurim
hanachah me'akeves bahen. So now that was the idea of יראו פני
הבית. ye'ira pnei habayis. But going back to an earlier position, no,
it's the placing down in front of the altar. הנחה מעכבת בהן
קריאה אין מעכבת בהן, Hanachah me'akeves bahen keriah ein me'akeves bahen, not
the declaration. Against our משנה, Mishnah, our משנה Mishnah says it is
the declaration.
כמאן, Keman, who is that going like? כי האי תנא, Ki hai
tanna, like the following תנא, Tanna, דתניא, detanya, as it was taught
in a ברייתא. Baraisa. רבי יוסי אומר שלשה דברים משום שלשה זקנים.
Rabbi Yose omer sheloshah devarim mishum sheloshah zekeinim. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
said three things in the name of three different elders. Okay, and
the first one is the one that's relevant to us, we're not
going to quote the other two. The first one he said in
the name of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. רבי ישמעאל אומר יכול יעלה
אדם מעשר שני בזמן הזה בירושלים ויאכלנו. Rabbi Ishmael omer yachol ya'aleh
adam Ma'aser Sheni bazman hazeh b'Yerushalayim v'yochlenu.
Now we are going to get into an interesting related topic, not
the same as when does the moment of it become permissible, but
look, מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni
is supposed to be eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. There are a few
things that are supposed to be eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. קדשים קלים,
Kodshim Kalim,
right, light sacrifices, including בכור, bechor, which is one we'll be highlighting.
בכורים Bikurim and מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. All of those have to
be done in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But there's a way in which מעשר
שני Ma'aser Sheni is different than the other two. Can you think
about it? In terms of nowadays. Why might I think בית המקדש...
Beis Hamikdash... Right, so
בכורים Bikurim and בכור bechor or קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim are things
that you have a ritual done in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
right? The קרבנות korbanos obviously the throwing of the blood, and the
בכורים Bikurim the waving, the placing down, לפני מזבח ה׳ אלקיך, lifnei
mizbach Hashem elokecha, in front of the מזבח. mizbeach. מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni it just says לפני ה׳ אלקיך תאכלנו, lifnei Hashem elokecha sochlenu,
right, eat it in the presence of God, eat it in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. So it's a reasonable suggestion: Hey, even without a בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, maybe when we separate off מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni we
should be able, rather than redeeming it and now eating it outside
the בית המקדש... Beis Hamikdash... maybe outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim, maybe we should
be able to and maybe obligated to go ahead and bring it
and eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Right nowadays what we do is
we just redeem it and we put aside the money, whatever, we
redeem it on a penny, you know, $1,000 on a penny and
we put aside the money, whatever, and we just don't use it.
But
because we're not able to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but maybe
we should be able to eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that's
the question. שלשה דברים משום שלשה זקנים. sheloshah devarim mishum sheloshah zekeinim.
רבי יוסי אומר שלשה דברים משום שלשה זקנים. Rabbi Yose omer sheloshah
devarim mishum sheloshah zekeinim. רבי ישמעאל אומר יכול יעלה אדם מעשר שני
בזמן הזה בירושלים ויאכלנו. Rabbi Ishmael omer yachol ya'aleh adam Ma'aser Sheni
bazman hazeh b'Yerushalayim v'yochlenu. Maybe a person can bring מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni at this time in ירושלים Yerushalayim and eat it there. דין
הוא. Din hu. Now I can make a דין, din, sometimes means
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, sometimes means a logical argument. I can make
a logical argument to say why you should not be able to.
Okay. What's the logical argument not to? בכור טעון הבאת מקום ומעשר
שני טעון הבאת מקום. Bechor teun havos makom u'Ma'aser Sheni teun havos
makom. בכור Bechor has to be brought to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, again I
don't know exactly why he's focusing on בכור bechor more than on
the other קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim but okay. בכור Bechor has to
be brought to ירושלים Yerushalayim and מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni has to
be brought to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. מה בכור
אינו אלא בפני הבית אף מעשר שני אינו אלא בפני הבית. Ma
bechor eino ela
bifnei habayis af Ma'aser Sheni eino ela bifnei habayis. Logically בכור Bechor
requires the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, מעשר שני Maaser Sheni does. So
that would be the argument to say not. But this is really
just a setup to point out the difference. Okay. No, מה לבכור
שכן טעון דם ואימורין לגבי מזבח. ma l'bechor shekein teun dam v'eimurim
legabei mizbeiach.
בכור Bechor of course you can't bring nowadays because you have to
throw the blood on the altar and burn the fat.
So therefore by מעשר שני Maaser Sheni you don't have to do
that. It's a reasonable argument that you should be able to eat
in ירושלים Yerushalayim nowadays. Okay, ביכורים יוכיחו. bikkurim yochichu.
So we'll use ביכורים Bikkurim to prove that it's not the throwing
of the blood on the altar that matters, and that even something
that you don't have to put blood on the altar you can't
eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That would be ביכורים. Bikkurim. Maybe it's because
בכור Bechor and ביכורים Bikkurim we specifically highlighted בכור. Bechor. Okay, מה
לביכורים, ma l'bikkurim, okay, okay, so ביכורים Bikkurim shows, something is taken
for granted now. How we take it for granted is a different
question, but it's taken for granted that you can't bring ביכורים Bikkurim
nowadays and eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So you see the problem
of eating in ירושלים Yerushalayim is not that it's a sacrifice because
even ביכורים Bikkurim which isn't a sacrifice you can't bring to ירושלים
Yerushalayim nowadays. But okay, it's not a sacrifice but there's still a
very concrete reason that makes it different from מעשר. Maaser. מה לביכורים
שכן טעונים הנחה. ma l'bikkurim shekein teunim hanacha.
ביכורים Bikkurim have to be put in front of the altar. So
both of those things we know why you don't bring them nowadays
to ירושלים Yerushalayim because they need an altar, they need a בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, it's a reasonable argument
to say you should be able to bring it and eat it
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So how do you know not? תלמוד לומר, Talmud
lomar, the verse teaches, ואכלת שם לפני ה' אלקיך מעשר דגנך תרשך
ויצהרך ובכרת בקרך וצאנך, V'achalta sham lifnei Hashem Elokecha maaser degancha tiroshcha
v'yitzharecha ubechoros bekarcha v'tzonecha, wonderful פסוק. pasuk. Okay,
and maybe that's why we mentioned בכור. Bechor. Since it says ובכרת
ubechoros and it says מעשר maaser and these are the two things
that are eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so the same way בכור Bechor
cannot be eaten nowadays for a specific reason there's no מזבח, mizbeiach,
even though that problem doesn't exist by מעשר, Maaser, the linking of
the two shows you can't eat מעשר Maaser in ירושלים Yerushalayim nowadays
either. Okay, מקיש מעשר לבכור. makish maaser l'bechor. So מה בכור אינו
אלא לפני הבית, ma bechor eino ela lifnei habayis, the same way
בכור Bechor is only in front of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
אף מעשר, af maaser, it
needs to be for מעשר Maaser that it needs to be a
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right?
There needs to be a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Right, it's linking
the two. מה בכור ma bechor the same way בכור Bechor אינו
אלא לפני הבית eino ela lifnei habayis requires there to be a
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, אף מעשר af maaser the linking of it
is telling you that if you want to eat מעשר Maaser in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which is what this whole פסוק pasuk is about, it's
about eating them in ירושלים Yerushalayim and it's putting them in the
same category. So this actually is a דרשה drasha that actually is
like close to the פשט pshat of the פסוקים, pasukim, right? It's
putting all these things in the same category. So the same way
ירושלים Yerushalayim for בכור Bechor means a ירושלים Yerushalayim that has a
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so the same is true for מעשר. Maaser.
אף מעשר אינו אלא לפני הבית. af maaser eino ela lifnei habayis.
So it requires a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so that's a
great דרשה, drasha, very interesting, that whole discussion and comparison, but but
the side point that we're bringing it in, we're going to go
back in a minute to look at it in greater depth, but
the reason we're bringing it in is because when it contrasts מעשר
Maaser to ביכורים Bikkurim and why ביכורים Bikkurim obviously needs a בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it describes the unique obligations of ביכורים Bikkurim as
הנחה, hanacha, it requires a placing down in front of an altar,
which shows that הנחה hanacha is the key thing that makes it
permissible and not something like קריאה. kriya. Okay, so that's the reason
we're bringing it in. Again we're going to go back to focus
on the main point of that ברייתא braisa in a minute. But
let's, or the משנה Mishna actually, well it's a ברייתא, braisa, a
תוספתא, Tosefta, anyway I think there's a question here if it's a
משנה Mishna or a ברייתא, braisa, maybe it's both. Anyway it says
like this, ואם איתא v'im isah if it's true that it's not
about the הנחה hanacha that's key by the ביכורים Bikkurim but it's
about the קריאה, kriya, לפרוך מה לביכורים שכן טעונים קריאה והנחה. lifroch
ma l'bikkurim shekein teunim kriya v'hanacha.
Why didn't it say, 'Oh no ביכורים Bikkurim obviously needs a בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash because it needs the placing and the declaration?' So
the fact that it didn't mention the declaration shows the declaration is
not key for making it permissible. That's the reason we brought that
in to show that it's all about the placing. So אמר רב
אשי Amar Rav Ashi says that's not really a proof. נהי דעכובא
ליכא nehi d'ikuva leka it's true that there's no, you know even
according to your logic that the קריאה kriya is not required to
make it permissible, right? That's your logic that look, it didn't mention
קריאה kriya because קריאה kriya isn't required to make it permissible. Fine,
but I could ask you even according to you, מצוה מי ליכא?
mitzva mi leka? There still is a מצוה mitzva to declare it,
to do the declaration. Nobody disagrees with that. So if we're mentioning
the distinct aspects of ביכורים Bikkurim that connect it to the altar,
you haven't answered your problem by saying, 'Oh look it's just about
הנחה.' hanacha. It's not just about הנחה. hanacha. הנחה hanacha might be
the absolute minimal requirement, but there is an element, everybody agrees there's
a מצוה mitzva of doing the קריאה kriya by the ביכורים. Bikkurim.
So if you wanted to point out what's distinct about ביכורים Bikkurim
why it's connected to an altar, you should have mentioned the קריאה
kriya regardless whether it's מעכב meakev or not מעכב, meakev, right? Whether
it's absolutely necessary or not, mention it as one of the things
that connects ביכורים Bikkurim to the altar, at least as a מצוה.
mitzva.
So why did we still have to deal with why it did
not mention the קריאה? Kriya? Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר רב אשי, Ela amar Rav
Ashi, if you want to know why it didn't mention the declaration,
it has nothing to do with whether it's absolute, it's required or
not required. Maybe it's not, but it should have mentioned it anyway.
Maybe it is required, but I'll still tell you why it didn't
mention it. Here's why it didn't mention it. כיון דאיכא ביכורי הגר,
Kiven de'ika bikkurei hager, דבעי למימר אשר נשבע השם לאבותינו לתת לנו,
deba'ei lemeimar asher nishba Hashem la'avoteinu latet lanu, since if a גר
ger would bring בכורים, bikkurim, he wouldn't be able to do the
קריאה, Kriya, because he couldn't say that God commanded our forefathers to
give us. By the way, that's a debate of the תנאים. tanna'im.
There's an interesting—I understand—there's a תנא tanna that says that no, once
he converts, not only does he adopt the religion, but he adopts
the history, and therefore he's able to say לאבותינו לתת לנו. la'avoteinu
latet lanu. Now, Michael points out, you know, a גר ger says
in שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei, אלוקינו ואלוקי אבותינו. Elokeinu ve'Elokei avoteinu.
That's a little different because here it specifically relates to the land,
right? And a גר ger doesn't get an—he could buy land, but
he doesn't get an inheritory portion in the land. Nevertheless, there is
an opinion in the משנה Mishna that says you say it. And
there's an interesting debate of the ראשונים, Rishonim, which way we פוסקן,
pasken, which is not relevant as much for בכורים, bikkurim, but it
is relevant for like the נוסח nusach that a גר ger says,
you know, in the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and in other תפילות.
tefillot. Like, one opinion says that he says
אלוקינו ואלוקי ישראל, Elokeinu ve'Elokei Yisrael, which is like so disturbing, right,
that like every single day in דאווננינג davening he has to acknowledge
his otherness, you know? So רמב"ם Rambam in a beautiful letter to
this גר, ger, עובדיה הגר, Ovadya HaGer, he talks about this debate
about בכורים bikkurim or whatever, and says we absolutely פוסקן pasken that
you say אלוקינו ואלוקי אבותינו Elokeinu ve'Elokei avoteinu and that, you know,
and he speaks about how, you know, you also have אברהם Avraham
as your father and once you've converted, you know, you are totally
part of us and with our history and so on. So it's
a really like important big philosophical question about how to understand like,
you know, a גר ger and what it means, right, like when
you just convert not just to a faith but to a nation
and a people and so on. But anyway, but for our point,
this is all being said as a side point, that's why when
it mentioned why בכורים bikkurim is connected to the altar, it didn't
mention קריאה, Kriya, because there are times you don't do קריאה. Kriya.
Now, it's funny it went to the גר ger case because yesterday
we had easier cases you don't do קריאה, Kriya, when it's brought
like after סוכות Sukkot or something. Okay, but regardless, okay, since there
are times you don't do קריאה, Kriya, it didn't want to mention
that as one of the unique things that connects it to the
altar. It mentioned something that everybody, you know, is always present by
בכורים bikkurim that connects it to the altar, which is the הנחה,
hanacha, the placing down. Hold on. ונהי, Venehi, so therefore, so ולא
מצי אמר, velo matzi amar, a גר ger can't say it. לא
פסיקא ליה. lo psika lei. Okay, so therefore it was not black
and white, it wasn't something that always applied. So you cannot prove
from the absence of mentioning קריאה Kriya in this context that קריאה
Kriya is not מעכב. me'akev. It could very well be that קריאה
Kriya is מעכב me'akev when it's done by a non-גר ger before
סוכות. Sukkot. Okay, but because there are times where קריאה Kriya isn't
relevant, it didn't mention it. It mentioned הנחה. hanacha. Okay, that's a
nice answer, but bottom line is, it still sounds like the only
thing it mentioned was הנחה hanacha is that הנחה hanacha is the
key, but he says it doesn't really prove it. It could just
be that הנחה hanacha is the absolute thing that always exists. So
that was in the context of our discussion of what makes בכורים
bikkurim permissible. Is it הנחה hanacha or the קריאה? Kriya? It sounds
from here that it's הנחה, hanacha, but the גמרא Gemara responded you
can't definitely prove that. Yes, Michael?
So the question is this. We know at somewhere along the way
that for the בכורים, bikkurim, you get מיתה בידי שמים, mita bidei
shamayim, you know, depending on how you use it. Right. But the
interesting thing is, correct me if I'm wrong, let's say you just
didn't take any בכורים bikkurim at all. Right.
If
it doesn't consider טבל tevel
if you took תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. No, בכורים bikkurim does not—בכורים
bikkurim does not make the rest טבל. tevel. Right. So that's interesting.
So suddenly by eating something—once you separate it, yeah, you know, like
at some point you're liable for מיתה בידי שמים, mita bidei shamayim,
but if you didn't separate it at all, you could have avoided
it.
Right. But that's—that is true, but you know—yeah, but
you
could sort of say, but—but you could have said like if I
מפריש mafrish a קרבן korban and I sanctify a קרבן korban and
then I eat from it or whatever, I also can do a
terrible sin. And if I didn't sanctify it to begin
with—but you have to מפריש mafrish a קרבן korban to begin with.
Right. I understand your difference. It is funny. בכורים bikkurim is funny
that there's a חיוב chiyuv to take it as opposed to
טבל tevel where you're—like,
I'm—it's more about a חיוב גברא, chiyuv gavra, it's not about the
status of the fruit. It's not like without having taken it, the
fruit has בכורים bikkurim mixed up in it. You're right. That is
a unique aspect of בכורים. bikkurim. Okay, so now we're going to
focus on—so that was the end of the discussion of is it
הנחה hanacha or the קריאה? Kriya? But now we get into this
really interesting question of: is the bringing the מעשר ma'aser to ירושלים
Yerushalayim connected to the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? And we said, you
know, based on this פסוק, pasuk, it connects it to בכור, bechor,
and we say, yes, you can't bring it without a בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash like בכור. bechor. But you could not have learned it
from בכור bechor and בכורים bikkurim alone because they are all connected
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash in a very concrete way that
מעשר ma'aser is not. So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, but
you can't learn it from בכור bechor by itself or בכורים bikkurim
by itself, but why can't you learn it from the common denominator
and still sort of made the argument without the פסוק? pasuk? So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So the
גמרא Gemara says ויהדר דינא ותיתי ממה הצד, V'yeihader dina v'teisi m'ma
hatzad, why not have the comparison go
back between back and forth between the two things you wanted to
learn from and still learn from the common denominator? Okay, yes, you
can't learn from בכור Bechor because it requires the blood thrown on
the מזבח. Mizbe'ach. You can't learn from ביכורים Bikkurim because it requires
הנחה לפני המזבח. hanacha lifnei hamizbe'ach. What?
Learn what again?
Learn that it requires the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. מעשר Ma'aser requires
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So you can't learn it from בכור
Bechor because בכור Bechor has to have the blood put on the
altar. You can't learn it from ביכורים Bikkurim because ביכורים Bikkurim needs
to be placed before the altar. Okay, but the common side between
the two of them is that they need ירושלים Yerushalayim and they
need a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, and so let's say the
same by מעשר. Ma'aser. All right, because again, if you look at
the common denominators, they're not exactly the same, בכור Bechor and ביכורים.
Bikkurim. But there's an obvious answer, there's enough that is similar to
them that makes them different from מעשר, Ma'aser, which is: they might
have different rituals done on the altar, but they both have rituals
connected to the altar. They're both very concretely connected to the altar,
which is what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, משום דאיכא למפרך: Mishum
d'ika l'mifrach: מה להצד השווה שבהן—fine, Mah l'hatzad hashaveh shebahen but even
if we looked at the two of those together, the common denominator
is שכן יש בהן צד מזבח. Shekein yeish bahen tzad mizbe'ach. They
have rituals that are very much connect them to the altar, okay?
And I might have thought that מעשר, Ma'aser, which is not connected
to the altar, could be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim even בזמן הזה.
Bazman hazeh. All right, so that's great. Now we're going to go
even a little further. ומאי קסבר, U'mai kasavar, now what do you
hold regarding the status of the קדושה Kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael or
ירושלים? Yerushalayim? אי קסבר Ei kasavar קדושה ראשונה Kedusha rishona קדשה לשעתה
וקדשה לעתיד לבוא—if Kiddsha l'sha'atah v'kiddsha l'asid lavo you think the original
קדושה Kedusha of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash at the time of
שלמה, Shlomo, whatever, יהושע, Yehoshua, that was in the time of the
first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, lasted after the destruction of the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so it lasts through the second and even after
the destruction of the second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So everything now
has full קדושה. Kedusha. So if everything now has full קדושה, Kedusha,
okay, so then I have a question for you. I guess I
get why you wanted to bring מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni into ירושלים
Yerushalayim because ירושלים Yerushalayim has full קדושה. Kedusha. But what makes it
obvious to you you can't even bring a בכור Bechor and eat
it in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Okay,
so אפילו בכור נמי, Afilu bechor nami, even בכור Bechor now, your
obvious answer is what the heck are you talking about? It might
have everything might have קדושה, Kedusha, but did you ever look around
and notice there's no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash there? So of course
you can't bring בכור Bechor nowadays. So interestingly, there is the הלכה
Halacha is in סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, רמב"ם Rambam פוסק, paskens, that if you
say קדשה לעתיד לבוא, Kiddsha l'asid lavo, that the קדושה Kedusha still
remains, then the הלכה Halacha is מקריבין אף על פי שאין בית.
Makrivin af al pi she'ein bayis. You don't really need the—did you
ever hear about how right around פסח Pesach time, there's always a
group wants to go up to the הר הבית Har Habayit and
bring קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? That is based on the principle that
you don't need a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, מקריבין אף על פי
שאין בית. Makrivin af al pi she'ein bayis. You would need to
build a מזבח Mizbe'ach on the grounds of the עזרה, Azarah, okay,
so it's not just they want to slaughter an animal, they'd want
to build a little mini מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Well, that's טומאה הותרה בציבור.
Tumah hutra b'tzibur. Okay, we can discuss that more when it gets
around to be פסח Pesach time. But you don't need an actual
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you just need to build a little מזבח
Mizbe'ach and you go ahead and you do it. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so okay, so why not so why should why are
we assuming you can't even bring בכור Bechor nowadays? Now, of course,
the point to be, okay, you would have to first build a
מזבח, Mizbe'ach, right? So the question might be: maybe in theory you
could bring בכור, Bechor, but without a מזבח Mizbe'ach you can't bring
it, but maybe we should be able to bring מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni without a מזבח. Mizbe'ach. That's okay, that's like a good way
of framing the question. But the גמרא's Gemara point at this stage
is: look, if everything has full קדושה, Kedusha, in theory you could
even bring בכור. Bechor. So why are you saying you don't bring
בכור Bechor nowadays? Okay, ואי קסבר, V'ei kasavar, and if you hold
קדושה ראשונה Kedusha rishona קדשה לשעתה ולא קדשה לעתיד לבוא, Kiddsha l'sha'atah
v'lo kiddsha l'asid lavo, it's not the sanctity doesn't remain till today,
it is funny I should point out that it mentions קדושה ראשונה,
Kedusha rishona, because it really could have just said in terms of
the second קדושה. Kedusha. The question is after the second destruction of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, does the קדושה Kedusha still remain? It's
really more dependent on whether the perseverance of the second קדושה.
Kedusha. But the גמרא Gemara assumes that if the first קדושה Kedusha
doesn't remain after the destruction of the first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
then the second one wouldn't remain after the destruction of the second
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And if the first one remains throughout, then
it still remains until now, right? It doesn't assume a possibility that
the first one doesn't remain and the second one does remain. People
sort of get that? Like, now רמב"ם Rambam actually does assume that
possibility, but we're going to bracket that. Logically, the גמרא Gemara assumes
if the קדושה Kedusha survives the destruction, then we still have the
first קדושה Kedusha left. And if it doesn't survive the destruction, then
we don't have the first one or the second one left. Okay,
so if we don't have the קדושה Kedusha anymore, says the גמרא,
Gemara, I get why you're assuming you don't bring בכור, Bechor, but
then מעשר, Ma'aser, what's your question by מעשר? Ma'aser? You don't even
have an obligation to bring מעשר, Ma'aser, right, if there's no קדושה
Kedusha left? All right, so the גמרא Gemara says now there's a
whole
question... different גרסה. Girsa. Okay. So תוספות'ס Tosafot's גרסה Girsa is
איכא סבר קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה לעתיד לבוא, Ika savar
Kedusha rishona kidsha l'sha'ata v'lo kidsha l'atid lavo, and if you hold
that the קדושה Kedusha nowadays does not remain, okay, אפילו בכור נמי.
Afilu Bechor nami. So תוספות Tosafot takes up the word תיבעי. Tiba'ei.
Okay. Even a בכור Bechor you shouldn't, actually hold on, let me
just check his גרסה Girsa one second. I think it's אפילו מעשר
נמי Afilu Ma'aser nami is his גרסה. Girsa. One minute.
Yeah, מעשר נמי. Ma'aser nami. Okay. So תוספות Tosafot says
is, right. So right, right. So תוספות Tosafot has like this, and
if the תוספות Tosafot גרסה Girsa is, our גרסה Girsa is אפילו
בכור נמי תיבעי, Afilu Bechor nami Tiba'ei, take out those words. תוספות'ס
Tosafot's גרסה Girsa is אפילו מעשר נמי. Afilu Ma'aser nami. Okay, which
means if the second if there's no קדושה Kedusha remaining today, okay,
then how do you think that you could eat it in ירושלים?
Yerushalayim? There's no what why you know you know you know where
does it even the same way it's obvious to you you don't
eat בכור Bechor in ירושלים Yerushalayim because there's no קדושה, Kedusha, so
of course you don't eat מעשר Ma'aser in ירושלים Yerushalayim because there's
no קדושה. Kedusha.
What about like these things of זכר למקדש? Zecher L'mikdash?
All right, so that's not our question. We want to know מעיקר
הדין. Me'ikar hadin. First of all, when זכר למקדש Zecher L'mikdash would
work because it was about, hold on a second. You mean because
you're thinking מעשר Ma'aser itself would only be דרבנן, D'rabbanan, right? Yeah.
Okay, hold on, I'm going to get to that, okay? So according
to תוספות Tosafot here's the question, okay? If here's your, okay, here.
Here's your הר הבית, Har Habayit, okay, here's your מקום המקדש, Makom
Hamikdash, okay? Now, the other thing we're not discussing here is, okay,
I don't know, here's ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I guess I'll make my walls
around ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Gets a little funny, הר הבית, Har Habayit, okay?
Anyway, here's ירושלים Yerushalayim
and here's ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay, now, the other thing you'd
have to know to appreciate the way תוספות Tosafot reads this גמרא
Gemara is
that there's a difference between the קדושה Kedusha of הר הבית Har
Habayit and ירושלים Yerushalayim and the קדושה Kedusha of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. Because if there was no קדושה Kedusha nowadays, if there is
no קידשה לעתיד לבוא, Kidsha l'atid lavo, then the question is not
just of course you can't eat מעשר Ma'aser in ירושלים Yerushalayim because
ירושלים Yerushalayim is not קדוש. Kadosh. The question should have been which
Michael's assuming is if there's no קדושה Kedusha nowadays, then what? Then
how are you dealing with מעשר Ma'aser to begin with? The מעשר
Ma'aser itself isn't right isn't obligated, right? You're with me, if there's
no קדושה. Kedusha. So תוספות Tosafot says is, there's a difference between,
רמב"ם Rambam says this as well, between the קדושה Kedusha of the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and the קדושה Kedusha of ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. When we're discussing now, is does the קדושה Kedusha still apply,
we want to know about the קדושה Kedusha of the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash and maybe ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That's the issue. The קדושה Kedusha
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael we're assuming that this applies, this is
still קדוש, Kadosh, okay? We're assuming that. So here's your grain, here's
your מעשר, Ma'aser, it's growing. This is real מעשר Ma'aser because the
קדושה Kedusha of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael still applies, okay? So this
is real מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni and has full קדושה. Kedusha. I
want to know, can I go ahead and bring it and eat
it in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? So what I'm really asking is, ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael has קדושה Kedusha nowadays according to from this approach, does
ירושלים Yerushalayim have קדושה? Kedusha? Now why would you think does if
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has קדושה, Kedusha, ירושלים Yerushalayim might not? It
doesn't it doesn't have less קדושה Kedusha than ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
but does it have the special קדושה Kedusha of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Why
might you think that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has קדושה Kedusha and
the grain is totally חייב Chayav in מעשר Ma'aser biblically speaking, it's
still right it has real full קדושה, Kedusha, but ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't
have the special קדושה Kedusha of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Why would you think?
Well because עיני ה' אלהיך בה מראשית השנה ועד אחרית שנה. Einei
Hashem Elokecha bah mereshit hashanah v'ad acharit shanah.
Okay, so
you're quoting why ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has קדושה. Kedusha. Why would
I think that there's a particular reason that ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't have
its unique קדושה? Kedusha? Just the destruction.
Because it
doesn't have a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, which raises, so that this
קדושה Kedusha is connected to a physical structure in the way that
ארץ ישראל's Eretz Yisrael קדושה, Kedusha, ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael promised to
אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov, Michael says עיני ה' אלוקיך בה,
Einei Hashem Elokecha bah, it's not necessarily connected to the physical structure
of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So conceptually, this is a very
nice conceptual position, right? ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael could retain its קדושה
Kedusha nowadays without a בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, but maybe the unique
קדושה Kedusha of ירושלים Yerushalayim which is connected might be connected to
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash might not have. But here's the question,
this is what this is such a beautiful גמרא. Gemara. The question
is, is that even if there's no קדושה Kedusha on הר הבית,
Har Habayit, it doesn't have the קדושת המקדש, Kedushat Hamikdash, which means
you can't bring קרבנות Korbanot nowadays, I could have a debate whether
ירושלים Yerushalayim has its special קדושה Kedusha or not. ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael has קדושה, Kedusha, מקום המקדש Makom Hamikdash where the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash used to be does not have the special קדושה Kedusha
of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash anymore because there's no physical structure
and the status of ירושלים Yerushalayim could be debated. Haha. Well debate
the status of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, East or West Jerusalem. Okay, why
could you- Yes
but how much is the קדושה Kedushah of ירושלים Yerushalayim
linked
to the בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, how much is it seen as
like a suburb of the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash or is it
seen as a sort of capital of ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Don't
want to talk about current contemporary politics. Anyway, so what is the
story? So this is like a great question. Now, when it comes
to eating בכור bechor or ביכורים, bikkurim, right? Should you be able
to do that in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? The obvious answer is no. Why?
Because בכור bechor and ביכורים bikkurim is connected to
the
בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash and a מזבח. mizbe'ach. So their eating in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, their being eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim is ירושלים Yerushalayim seen
as connected to the בית המקדש? Beis ha-Mikdash? You with me? So
if there’s no קדושה Kedushah here then obviously they shouldn't be eaten.
But here's the great question Rabbi Yishmael is asking: מעשר ma'aser starts
with the קדושה Kedushah of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because it’s grain
that grows in Israel. So since it starts and it doesn't get
brought to the altar, so since it starts with the קדושה Kedushah
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael when it's not connected to the altar,
maybe you should be able to eat it in ירושלים בזמן הזה?
Yerushalayim bizman hazeh?
Maybe the ירושלים Yerushalayim status for מעשר ma'aser is a different way
of looking at ירושלים Yerushalayim than you look at ירושלים Yerushalayim when
it comes to בכור bechor and ביכורים? bikkurim? Okay, what a great
question, right? His answer is it's all in the same פסוק, pasuk,
which might be saying we look at ירושלים Yerushalayim the same way
for מעשר: ma'aser: it is because it’s connected to the בית המקדש.
Beis ha-Mikdash. If by מעשר ma'aser it said לפני השם אלקיך, Lifnei
Hashem Elokecha, so part of what makes it לפני השם אלקיך, Lifnei
Hashem Elokecha, right, might be the fact that it is connected to
the בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash. But at least the question, right, is
maybe you could... I get you can't eat בכור bechor in ירושלים
Yerushalayim nowadays, there's no בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash. But maybe you should
be able to eat מעשר? ma'aser? Okay, that like is a really,
really good question. Okay, and that great assumes saying this has קדושה,
Kedushah, this קדושה Kedushah of מקדש Mikdash is connected to the structure.
What's the status of ירושלים Yerushalayim nowadays? All right, so the גמרא
Gemara says okay, let’s figure out how you hold about about the
קדושה. Kedushah. If you hold that this still has קדושה, Kedushah, right,
that’s what the גמרא Gemara said, then in theory you could bring
בכור bechor here. Okay, so then it, right, as long as you
made a מזבח. mizbe'ach. So then maybe it should be relatively obvious
that you could go ahead and bring מעשר ma'aser here, okay, because
the קדושה Kedushah still exists, you just need a מזבח, mizbe'ach, so
it all should be pretty obvious. If this doesn’t have the קדושה,
Kedushah, so at least in the הוה אמינא hava amina the גמרא
Gemara is saying, if it doesn’t have the קדושה, Kedushah, which we
just explained beautifully how the מעשר ma'aser could be looked at differently,
but the גמרא's Gemara first question is if this doesn't have the
קדושה, Kedushah, then obviously ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't have a קדושה. Kedushah. So
obviously you can’t eat מעשר ma'aser in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, why should
I think מעשר ma'aser should be different? If it has קדושה, Kedushah,
obviously you should be able to do both and if it doesn’t
have קדושה, Kedushah, obviously you should be able to do neither. That's
the גמרא's Gemara question. Without the way we conceptualized the distinction, the
גמרא Gemara is just saying it's either both or neither. What's the
answer? So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
So אפילו מעשר נמי Afilu ma'aser nami is the תוספות's Tosafot גירסא
girsa of the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, says Ravina, לעולם
קסבר, le'olam kasvar, really he holds, קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה
לעתיד לבוא. Kedushah rishonah kideshah lesha'atah velo kideshah le'asid lavo. That's the
תוספות's Tosafot גירסא. girsa. Let me just check that I've got תוספות's
Tosafot גירסא, girsa, make sure I got תוספות's Tosafot גירסא girsa right
here, one minute, one minute, לעולם קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד
לבוא. Le'olam kedushah rishonah kideshah lesha'atah vekideshah le'asid lavo. תוספות Tosafot switches
our גירסא girsa pretty drastically. Okay, I’m
going to go with תוספות Tosafot because I love the conceptual way
תוספות Tosafot reads the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says the
answer is לעולם קסבר קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא. le'olam kasvar kideshah
lesha'atah vekideshah le'asid lavo. Fine, it has the קדושה. Kedushah. Okay, והכא,
Ve-hacha, now even though, what does the manuscript say, do we have,
I did not check the manuscripts. It's a good question. Right, I
didn't check the manuscripts. Not all the manuscripts predate תוספות, Tosafot, but
you’re right, at least that would give us, some of them do
predate תוספות Tosafot and it would give us a good sense right
how much is תוספות Tosafot editing or not. לעולם קסבר קידשה לשעתה
וקידשה לעתיד לבוא, Le'olam kasvar kideshah lesha'atah vekideshah le'asid lavo, okay, and
but תוספות Tosafot is going to say like this and here’s the
difference, okay, והכא בבכור שנזרק דמו קודם חורבן הבית. ve-hacha bevichor shenizrak
damo kodem churban habayis. But the problem is, the only difference about
a בכור bechor is that fine it might be קידשה לעתיד לבוא,
kideshah le'asid lavo, but you need a מזבח. mizbe'ach. So תוספות Tosafot
says I will get you a בכור bechor that had a מזבח.
mizbe'ach. What בכור bechor had a מזבח? mizbe'ach? Here's the case: והכא
בבכור שנזרק דמו קודם חורבן הבית. ve-hacha bevichor shenizrak damo kodem churban
habayis. You brought a בכור bechor right there as the Romans were
at the gate, as the barbarians were at the gate, it doesn’t
matter, it's all hypothetical, okay,
and there you’re everybody
is there fighting the war and you’re waltzing into the בית המקדש
Beis ha-Mikdash bringing your בכור bechor right there while the while the...
fighting is going on in the street, שנזרק דמו קודם חורבן הבית,
Shenizrak damo kodem churban habayis, you brought it on the eighth of
Av or the ninth of Av before they got to the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. וחרב הבית V'charav habayis and then it was destroyed,
still בשרו קיים. Besaro kayam. And now while they're going ahead and
rampaging through the city, there's no longer מזבח mizbe'ach and you want
to know, so it was properly brought and you want to know
are you able to eat it without a מזבח? mizbe'ach? Okay, ומקשינן
Umakshinan now. The reason we describe this, it doesn't matter that it
never happens, happens, rather the question is it allows us to conceptually
isolate the eating from the bringing, okay, and to say like this,
to say we know that a בכור bechor can't be brought without
a מזבח. mizbe'ach. The question is can it be eaten without a
מזבח? mizbe'ach? Because and that makes it helps us sharpen the issue
by ביכורים bikurim and by מעשר, ma'aser, because מעשר ma'aser doesn't need
to be brought, it just needs to be eaten, right? There's no
bringing of it. So if so, so let's bracket the fact that
you need to bring, you need an altar to bring a בכור.
bechor. Let's say magically you didn't need that altar to bring the
בכור. bechor. What would be the case? You brought it and then
the altar was destroyed, okay, or fine, בזמן הזה, bizman hazeh, you
went up to הר הבית, Har Habayis, you built a little altar,
you brought your בכור bechor and then you destroyed your little altar,
okay? So it was brought. Can it be eaten without an altar?
That's the question, okay? And that helps us say because now don't
tell me, oh, מעשר ma'aser is obviously it's okay to eat because
you don't need an altar. I could get you a בכור bechor
that no longer needs an altar either, that it was already brought,
and I still want to know, is the presence of an altar
important for its eating? Okay. ומקשינן בשרו לדמו Umakshinan besaro ledamo and
we connect the flesh to the blood. מה דמו במזבח אף בשרו
במזבח, Ma damo bemizbe'ach af besaro bemizbe'ach, right? Because there's a פסוק
pasuk that says, Rashi quotes the פסוק. pasuk. What's the פסוק? pasuk?
It says את דמם תזרוק על המזבח ובשרם יהיה לך. Es damam
tizrok al hamizbe'ach uvasaram yihyeh lach. So it connects the blood to
the flesh. The same way the blood needs an altar to be
eaten, the flesh needs the presence of an altar to be eaten.
So yes, even if you brought a בכור, bechor, you can't eat
it without an altar, okay? So מה דמו במזבח אף בשרו במזבח.
Ma damo bemizbe'ach af besaro bemizbe'ach. So now what do we have?
We still have the קדושה kedusha of we have the קדושה kedusha
of the מקדש Mikdash and of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It's all קדוש, kadosh,
okay? But there's no physical altar. Now we know that a בכור
bechor can't be eaten without a physical altar. Even if it was
brought. It requires the physical altar to be eaten. And here's our
question: does מעשר שני, Ma'aser sheni, which never even needed an altar
to begin with, does it also need a physical... yes, it has
קדושה, kedusha, but there's no physical altar. Does מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
require a physical altar to be eaten? Okay, and that's the and
the answer to that question is yes. ומקיש מעשר לבכור, Umakish ma'aser
lebechor, מעשר ma'aser is connected to בכור. bechor. Okay, and that's our
answer that yes, even though this has קדושה, kedusha, a physical altar
is needed for בכור bechor and a physical altar is needed for
מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. Now I do want to tell you before
we wrap this up that I would have preferred the answer to
say that this doesn't have קדושה, kedusha, okay? It doesn't have קדושה.
kedusha. That's our version, right? Rather, to say it doesn't have קדושה
kedusha vis-a-vis קרבנות, korbanos, but we want to know if it has
קדושה kedusha vis-a-vis מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, right? That's like an even
more interesting... now we've said it has קדושה, kedusha, but there's a
technical requirement that for מעשר שני ma'aser sheni you need a מזבח,
mizbe'ach, which, you know, to me, it's a little more interesting to
say it doesn't have קדושה kedusha at all as far as קרבנות
korbanos are concerned because it's no longer like part of the there's
no longer קדושת בית המקדש, kedushas Beis Hamikdash, but I want to
know if it has special קדושה kedusha even not related to בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right? That would have been a different way to
have said it. Either way, the answer is that מעשר ma'aser is
like בכור. bechor. And the same way for בכור bechor you don't
eat it in ירושלים בזמן הזה, Yerushalayim bizman hazeh, for מעשר ma'aser
you don't either because they both need a physical מזבח. mizbe'ach. That's
the גמרא Gemara's answer, or you know, you could have said even
if they don't need a physical מזבח mizbe'ach or מעשר ma'aser might
not, it still needs a קדושה kedusha that's connected to the קדושה
kedusha of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so both מעשר ma'aser
and בכור bechor can't be eaten. Wait, I want to just finish
this. So yep, now the גמרא Gemara says like this, וכי דבר
הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? Vechi davar halamad behekesh chozer umelamed behekesh?
One minute. We only knew the flesh of a בכור bechor couldn't
be eaten because it's linked to the blood. But now you can't
sort of take that which is a derivative principle that you don't
eat the flesh and then apply it to yet another derived case.
Okay, something you learned out by a link, you can't go ahead
and learn, if you learned B from A, you can't now learn
the thing you know about B and apply it to C. Now
that's a principle by קרבנות. korbanos. It doesn't apply to non-קרבנות, korbanos,
which is what the גמרא Gemara's going to respond. The גמרא Gemara
says מעשר דגן חולין הוא. Ma'aser dagan chullin hu. No, מעשר ma'aser
of grain, yes, I mean it is holy, it's מעשר שני. ma'aser
sheni. but compare it to קרבנות, Korbanos, it's non-holy. It's not in
the category of קרבנות, Korbanos, okay. And therefore you can do a
double-derived לימוד Limud when you're not dealing in a world of קרבנות.
Korbanos. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר בתר למד אזלינן.
Ha nicha le-man de-amar batar lamed azlinan. That's good if you go
by the application. Since the final application is מעשר, Maaser, you're allowed
to do a double-derived לימוד. Limud. אלא למאן דאמר בתר מלמד אזלינן,
Ela le-man de-amar batar melamed azlinan, if you go by the origin,
the origin is the world of קרבנות, Korbanos, so you can't go
ahead and apply something two degrees derived. Okay, מאי איכא למימר, Mai
ika le-meimar, what can you say? So the גמרא Gemara says דם
ובשר חדא מילתא היא. Dam u-vasar chada milta hi. You're not really
learning the flesh from the blood. The flesh and the blood are
all seen as one point. The point of linking them is saying
that it's one הלכה. halacha. So it's fundamentally one הלכה, halacha, then
you're really just one link. You're linking here בכור bechor to מעשר.
maaser. And the same way בכור bechor needs a מזבח, mizbeach, מעשר
maaser needs a מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, yes, there might be קדושת ירושלים,
Kedushas Yerushalayim, there might be קדושת מקדש בזמן הזה. Kedushas Mikdash bi-zman
ha-zeh. In theory you could go up to הר הבית Har HaBayis
and build your own private מזבח mizbeach and bring a קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, okay? It all has קדושה, kedusha, but without the presence
of the מזבח, mizbeach, don't go ahead eating a בכור bechor and
don't go ahead and eating מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Yes. Is that
kind of the reason why we're not going to do a זכר
למקדש zecher le-mikdash and say, you know, still do it anyway even
though there's no... Well you can't do זכר למקדש zecher le-mikdash if
you feel that, if you believe that this has קדושה מן התורה,
kedusha min ha-Torah, then you can't do זכר למקדש zecher le-mikdash because
then you're actually you're not allowed to eat it without פדיון. pidyon.
You can only eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim when you're doing the
מצוה mitzvah of אכילת מעשר, achilas maaser, which you wouldn't be יוצא
yotzei nowadays. So you can't, so you couldn't. The way you could
have a זכר למקדש zecher le-mikdash is if you say that this
doesn't have, that קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushas Eretz Yisrael doesn't apply nowadays
and this doesn't have real קדושה מן התורה, kedusha min ha-Torah, okay?
So it only has קדושה דרבנן, kedusha de-Rabbanan, then you could ask
that question. And there's actually a גמרא Gemara about that, about how
they were מבטל mevatel it once ירושלים Yerushalayim was destroyed, like why
it was, whatever, there's a משנה Mishna in, there's a discussion in
ביצה Beitzah about how they stopped people bringing stuff to ירושלים Yerushalayim
because it was a little bit of an embarrassment. Okay, but if
it has קדושה מן התורה, kedusha min ha-Torah, that's the whole point,
then it's not like you don't have to eat in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
you're not allowed to eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. The קדושה kedusha demands
it be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim under certain circumstances. And we don't
have those circumstances. So therefore you can't eat. Well you have to
redeem it. That's what you do, you redeem it on a פרוטה
prutah or something like that. Okay. But so today, what do we
do today? We redeem it. It's actually something called a פרוטה חמורה
prutah chamurah because it has to be כסף צורה, kesef tzurah, it
has to be a certain... and then you throw it in the
sea... Well no, you keep it somewhere stored because then what you
do is you keep on because you have to every time you're
מעשר me'aser something you keep on going back and forth whatever. I
don't want to go into the details but yeah we redeem it
nowadays. Okay so now we turn to, that was really fun, I
liked it a lot. We now turn to, I don't know about
you guys but anyway. Now we turn to the second, a new
point in our משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna says that one of
the things you get lashes for is if you eat קדשים קלים
kodashim kalim or מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, we're still in the world
of מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, חוץ לירושלים. chutz l'Yerushalayim. Okay? But the
problem is that as we're going to see, that our משנה mishna
says קדשים קלים ומעשר שני חוץ לחומה. kodashim kalim u-Maaser Sheni chutz
l'chomah. That's one of the things you get lashes for. Now when
you're eating it out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right, what would be a
permissible way to eat מעשר שני Maaser Sheni out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
If you did what to it? We just discussed it, if you
redeemed it. So when it says the problem is you get lashes
for eating מעשר שני Maaser Sheni out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, what it
really means is eating it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim without having redeemed
it. But if you look at our first משנה mishna of the
פרק, perek, it says one of the things you get lashes for
is תרומה מעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו. terumah, Maaser Sheni ve-hekdesh she-lo
nifdu. מעשר שני Maaser Sheni that hasn't been redeemed. So the גמרא
Gemara says, that's the same thing! Eating מעשר שני Maaser Sheni that
hasn't been redeemed is the same עבירה aveirah as eating מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Because the problem of eating it
out of ירושלים Yerushalayim is you ate it without having redeemed it.
So why does one משנה mishna say you get lashes for eating
it if you didn't redeem it and one משנה mishna say you
get lashes for eating it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim if we're describing
the exact same scenario? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
תנינא חדא זימנא, Tanyina chada zimna, this second משנה mishna that says
the problem is eating it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim is repeating what
we already learned in a משנה: mishna: מעשר שני והקדש שלא נפדו,
Maaser Sheni ve-hekdesh she-lo nifdu, that hasn't been redeemed. So the problem
of not redeemed מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is that it's out of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So it's the exact same עבירה. aveirah. So why is
it mentioned twice in two different משניות? mishnayos? Okay. אמר רב יוסף
בר חנינא, Amar Rav Yosef bar Chanina, סיפא במעשר שני טהור וגברא
טהור. seifa be-Maaser Sheni tahor ve-gavra tahor. No, the problem in our
case of out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you're right, it's the problem of
not being redeemed when everything is טהור. tahor. You're טהור, tahor, it's
טהור, tahor, it's out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and the problem is it's
not redeemed out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Because out of ירושלים Yerushalayim implies
that had you only been in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you'd be able to
eat it. So that's a case where everybody is טהור tahor and
you're out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay רישא *reisha*, the first case which
has the problem is, emphasizes not the problem of out of ירושלים
Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*, but the problem that it's not redeemed, the רישא *reisha*
is the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni *Maaser Sheni* טמא tamei *tamei* and
גברא *gavra* טמא tamei *tamei*. Either you're טמא tamei. *tamei* or it's
טמא tamei *tamei*. Okay, it doesn't mean both, one or the other.
And there, the problem is not so much that it's out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, because even in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* you wouldn't be
able to eat it because you're טמא tamei *tamei*. The problem is
that it's not redeemed. Okay, so he's right that, yes, if it's
out of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, the problem is that it's not redeemed.
But by saying the problem is out of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, the
implication in our משנה mishna *mishna* is everything is טהור tahor *tahor*.
And the only problem is it's out of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. That's
one problem. In the רישא *reisha*, the problem in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*,
it has to be redeemed regardless. Either you or it is טמא
tamei *tamei*, okay, and therefore even in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* it's a
problem because you can't eat when you or it is טמא tamei.
*tamei*, you can't eat it even in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* until you
redeem it. Wait, so what's the law out of ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*?
You also can't eat it. Okay, there's no way it can be
eaten without being redeemed. Okay, so if you or it is טמא
tamei *tamei*, it's like the Yiddish proverb, right, which is what? That
if a poor person eats a chicken, either either either it or
the chicken is sick. So, anyway, either he or the chicken is
sick. Anyway, okay, so either you or it is טמא tamei, *tamei*.
Anyway, fine. So it says like this: ובאכלו בירושלים *u'be'achlo bi'Yerushalayim*. So
that's the problem. Okay, that if one of you is טמא tamei
*tamei*, even in ירושלים Yerushalayim? *Yerushalayim*, you get lashes for eating it
בטומאה betumah. *be'tumah*. So now this is a new idea, that you
get lashes for eating מעשר שני ma’aser sheni *Maaser Sheni* בטומאה betumah.
*be'tumah*. מנא ליה דמיחייב עליה משום טומאה tumah *minalei d'mechaiv alei mishum
tumah*? How do you know that you transgress and get lashes if
either you or it is טמא tamei, *tamei*? דתניא *dtanya*, we taught
in a ברייתא baraita *braita*: רבי שמעון אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer*: לא
ביערתי ממנו בטמא *lo biarti mimenu b'tamei*. This is the declaration you
make regarding מעשר ma'aser, *maaser*. I didn't eat from it when I
was טמא tamei, *tamei*, בטומאה betumah. *be'tumah* rather. בין שאני טמא והוא
טהור tahor *bein she'ani tamei v'hu tahor*, whether I was טמא *tamei*
and it was טהור tahor *tahor*, בין שאני טהור tahor, והוא טמא
*bein she'ani tahor v'hu tamei*, or I was טהור tahor. *tahor* and
it was טמא *tamei*. So, fine, from there we implicitly learn you're
not supposed to do it. But in order to get lashes, you
need a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that explicitly says "you shall not." והיכן
מוזהר על האכילה *v'heichan muzhar al ha'achila*? Where does it explicitly prohibit
you from doing it? So the גמרא Gemara... *Gemara* says: איני יודע
*eini yodeia*. This is the ברייתא *braita*, I don't know. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, so this is like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
quoting a ברייתא *braita*, the ספרי *Sifrei* actually, that's about to quote
a פסוק *pasuk* of which prohibits טומאה *tumah*. But the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* interjects before it gets to an answer. You know, you know,
don't you hate that? Like you're giving conversation, you're building up to
an answer and somebody says, "Wait, you can't!" You know, interjects in
the middle. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does. Okay, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so the ברייתא *braita*'s saying: how do I
know that, where does it explicitly say it's prohibited? So the גמרא
*Gemara* says, what do you mean where does it say? I'll give
you a פסוק *pasuk*. The גמרא *Gemara* says: טומאת הגוף בהדיא כתיב
*tumat haguf behadya ketiv*. What do you mean? It says it explicitly:
נפש אשר תגע בו וטמאה עד הערב ולא יאכל מן הקדשים *nefesh
asher tigah bo v'tamah ad ha'erev v'lo yochal min hakodashim*. Don't eat
from the holy things. And one of the things we learn from
holy things, it includes even מעשר שני ma’aser sheni *Maaser Sheni*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says, so fine. אלא טומאת עצמו מניין *ela tumat
atzmo minayin*? So the גמרא *Gemara* just clarifies. Yes, there's a clear
פסוק *pasuk* that says that when you're טמא *tamei*, you're not allowed
to eat from מעשר שני Maaser Sheni *Maaser Sheni*. But where do
you know when it's טמא *tamei*, that you're also not allowed to
eat from it even in ירושלים Yerushalayim? *Yerushalayim*? אלא טומאת עצמו מניין
*ela tumat atzmo minayin*? דכתיב *dechetiv*: לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך lo tuchal
le'echol bish'arecha *lo tuchal l'echol b'sharecha*. Man, the amount of things we
learn from this פסוק *pasuk* here. Okay, לא תוכל lo tuchal. לאכול
בשעריך bish'arecha *lo tuchal l'echol b'sharecha*, and what it says is, right:
מעשר ma'aser דגנך תירושך ויצהרך *maaser degancha tiroshcha v'yitzharecha*. Now, that tells
me don't eat it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. How do I
know it tells me don't eat it when it's טמא *tamei*? Because
it says בשעריך *b'sharecha*, in your gates, which means out of ירושלים
Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. ולהלן הוא אומר *u'l'halan hu omer*, and it says in
another place when it talks about a קרבן korban. *korban* that was
redeemed and that you're eating out of ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, once you've
redeemed it you can eat it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, it
says: בשעריך תאכלנו *b'sharecha tochelenu*, you can eat it in your gates,
in your cities out of ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*. הטמא והטהור יחדו *hatamei
v'hatahor yachdav*. The טמא *tamei* and the טהור tahor. *tahor* person can
eat it together. This is a קרבן *korban* that was redeemed that
had a מום *mum*. Okay, ותניא דבי רבי ישמעאל *v'tanya d'bei Rabbi
Ishmael*: אפילו טמא וטהור אוכלין בקערה אחת ואין חוששין *afilu tamei v'tahor
ochlin b'ke'arah achat v'ein chosheshin*. When it says a טמא *tamei* and
a טהור tahor, *tahor* person can eat it together, it means that,
you know, they can eat from one plate. Now, if a טמא
*tamei* person is eating from the same plate I'm eating from, he
is touching my the meat, my meat, the meat of this animal
that used to be a קרבן *korban* but now was now redeemed.
So if the תורה Torah *Torah* is telling you an animal that
was a קרבן *korban* that was once redeemed, a טמא *tamei* and
a טהור tahor. *tahor* person can eat it together, it's telling you
two things: you can eat this animal even if you're טמא *tamei*,
and you can eat this animal even if you're טהור tahor, *tahor*
and it and the meat became טמא *tamei* because you're eating it
together with the טמא *tamei* person. Okay, so that's what you can
do. Most people eat common together, they would. Fine. That's what you
can do by an animal that was a קרבן *korban* that was
redeemed and that animal is referred to and when it refers to
it, it says: בשעריך תאכלנו *b'sharecha tochelenu*. That's what eating in your
gates, eating in your cities suggests or implies the idea of eating
it בטומאה betumah. *be'tumah*. Okay, so that's the point. It's a nice
point, right? The תורה *Torah* sometimes when it says you can go
ahead and eat in your gates means however you want to eat
it, eat בטומאה betumah. *be'tumah*, be my guest. Okay? So right, okay.
That's by something that was redeemed. ואין חוששין and you don't have
to worry about it by that. וקאמר רחמנא veka'amar Rachmana היכי טמא
heichi tamei דשרי ליה כדבטהור deshari leh kedebetahor this fact that I
have permitted you in this case for a טהור tahor person to
eat the טמא meat of an animal that was redeemed, התם hasam
that's over there by the animal that was redeemed, but הכא hacha
by this case of מעשר ma'aser שני לא תאכל lo tachal you
can't eat it, לא תוכל. Okay, so לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך you
can't eat in your gates means not only can you not eat
this out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim but don't eat this stuff the way
you eat things that you eat in your gates. What's the way
you eat things in your gates? You eat it בטומאה. betumah This
stuff don't eat בטומאה. betumah So since the first thing mentioned here
is מעשר, ma'aser right, don't eat מעשר Maaser when you're טמא and
don't eat מעשר even if you're טהור if it's טמא. People get
that? That the בשעריך means don't eat it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim
and it means don't even eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim, in the
way you would eat it in your gates, don't eat it בטומאה.
betumah So from there we learn that you're prohibited to eat מעשר
even in ירושלים Yerushalayim בטומאה. betumah. But we also have other things
in there, a קרבן. Yeah, you're also prohibited to eat those בטומאה.
betumah Okay. So now we've got it. Our משנה mishna says what
it says out of the problem is out of ירושלים Yerushalayim, means
everybody is טהור and you get lashes because it's out of ירושלים
Yerushalayim and it hasn't been redeemed. And the earlier משנה mishna that
says the problem is that it's not redeemed means it's in ירושלים
Yerushalayim but he or it is טמא and therefore you're going to
get lashes because you ate it in ירושלים Yerushalayim בטומאה betumah without
it having been redeemed. Alright. So it says like this. Okay. ומנא
ליה דבר פדיה היא? uminalei debar pidyah hi? Now since the משנה
says that the problem was that it was בטומאה betumah and it
wasn't redeemed, it means that you're able to redeem it. How do
you know that in ירושלים Yerushalayim you can redeem it? Normally redeeming
it is something you do before you get to ירושלים. Yerushalayim How
do you know that because it's טמא you're able to redeem it
even in ירושלים? Yerushalayim, You have to, or the alternative would be
you bury it. דאמר רבי אלעזר de'amar Rabbi Elazar מנין למעשר שני
שנטמא שפודים אותו אפילו בירושלים? minayin lema'aser sheni shenitma shepodin oto afilu
biYerushalayim? How do you know if it became טמא you can redeem
it even in ירושלים? Yerushalayim, You're able to redeem it and then
you can go ahead and eat it. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar because
the verse says כי לא תוכל שאתו ki lo tuchal se'eto that
you redeem it because you could not carry it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim
So that means that you're physically distant. But he's going to do
a play on the word שאתו. se'eto. ואין שאת אלא אכילה ve'ein
se'et ela achilah שאתו se'eto does not mean carry, it means you're
not able to eat it because it's טמא. שנאמר shene'emar where does
שאת se'et mean eating it? וישא משאת מאת פניו. vayisa masa'ot me'et
panav. When יוסף Yosef gave the gift to his brothers, right, it
says that they... so now משאת masa'ot something carried and lifted because
it's like a gift, a presentation, but because there it was referring
to food, so he says, ah, you see the word לשאת laset
or שאתו se'eto means some type of a food portion. So because
you can't eat it, you're allowed to redeem it even if you're
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim Yes Michael, it is not פשט. pshat. Okay. אמר
רבי ביבי אמר רבי אסי Amar Rabbi Bibi Amar Rabbi Assi מנין
למעשר שני טהור שפודים אותו אפילו... minayin lema'aser sheni tahor shepodin oto
afilu... so now we know you can redeem it even בטומאה betumah
if it's טמא you can redeem it even in ירושלים. Yerushalayim Okay,
and that's one set of lashes that you didn't redeem it and
you eat it בטומאה. And the other is you ate it out
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim Now, that's eating out of ירושלים Yerushalayim, is the
classic example of redeeming it. So now that we said you can
redeem it in ירושלים Yerushalayim if it's טמא, we want to know
if you can redeem it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim, even like one
footstep out. How distant do you have to be in order to
redeem it? Okay. מנין למעשר שני טהור שפודים אותו אפילו בפסיעה אחת
חוץ לחומה? minayin lema'aser sheni tahor shepodin oto afilu bipsi'ah achat chutz
lachomah? Because you know it starts by saying כי ירחק ממך המקום
ki yirchak mimcha hamakom that you're very distant from ירושלים, Yerushalayim we're
going to allow you to redeem it. How do I know that
even if I was one footstep out of ירושלים Yerushalayim. I would
still be allowed to redeem it? אפילו פסיעה אחת. afilu psi'ah achat.
שנאמר shene'emar כי לא תוכל שאתו ki lo tuchal se'eto you can't
carry it. So meaning it's not just you can't travel with it,
you can't even lift it up. You can't even lift it, move
it one inch. Like just the fact that you have... that there's
any movement that has to be done to it to bring it
into ירושלים, Yerushalayim that's distant enough to allow you to redeem it.
Okay, now the obvious reason that the גמרא... I mean I know
the obvious, but one reason the גמרא is doing this is like
נתת דבריך לשיעורין. natata devarecha lish'iurin. Since the תורה doesn't describe how
distant you have to be, it's going to say well any out
of ירושלים Yerushalayim, counts as being distant. Okay, but it's basing it
on the fact that the פסוק says you can't even lift it,
as opposed to saying like you can't travel the distance, which would
suggest that there's a minimum amount of distance. Okay. So even one
foot... either in ירושלים Yerushalayim. בטומאה you redeem it, or out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim even one footstep you can redeem it. Okay. היי מבעי
ליה לרבי אלעזר. hai miba'ei leh leRabbi Elazar. One minute, you need
it for רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, the word שאתו se'eto to tell
you that you can't eat it and that it... I mean that
if it's בטומאה you can redeem it. No. If so let the
verse say כי לא תוכל לאוכלו, ki lo tuchal l’ochlo, be more
explicit, tell me you can't eat it. מאי שאתה? Mai se’eto? What
does it use the word שאתה se’eto which both suggests according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer eating it and the טומאה scenario, and suggests
moving it even a little bit out of ירושלים Yerushalayim to tell
you both. ואימא כולה הכי הוא דאתא, V'eima kulah hachi u-de’ata, maybe
it's all coming to tell you that if it's just out of
ירושלים even one footstep. No, אם כן לימא קרא לא תוכל לשאתו
im kein leima kra lo tuchal l’itlo because you can't move it.
מאי שאתה? Mai se’eto? So the fact that it uses the word
שאתה se’eto suggests two. שמע מינה תרתי, Shma mina tarti, it both
suggests it can't be eaten, it's בטומאה in ירושלים, and it suggests
that it has, it's not that it's a far distance to travel,
but even a little bit to be moved is a problem. Okay,
so you can redeem מעשר שני for one of two reasons: either
you're a little bit out of ירושלים, you know, it's even a
little movement is all that it's lacking to bring it into ירושלים
or it's in ירושלים and your, it's טמא and that also allows
you to redeem it. So you can redeem it in either scenario.
Okay, and the lashes so you get is when you eat it
out of ירושלים unredeemed or when you eat it בטומאה even in
ירושלים unredeemed. All right, so now the גמרא says like this. Theoretically
that applies today still. Yeah. יתיב רבי חנינא ורב הושעיא וקמיבעיא להו
אפסקי דירושלים מהו. Yativ Rabbi Chanina v’Rav Oshaia v’ka miba’ei lehu afpiskei
d’Yerushalayim mahu. So they were asking this question: let's say you're right
there at the gates, right? Which is exactly our question. One footstep
out, what's the story? So, פשיטא, peshita, פשיטא, peshita, פשיטא, peshita, so
it was obvious, הוא בחוץ ומשאו בפנים. hu bachutz u-masa’o bifnim. Now
not actually if you're fully outside the gates that we just discussed.
They want to ask about an interesting scenario. Okay, הוא בחוץ ומשאו
בפנים. hu bachutz u-masa’o bifnim. You're standing out of ירושלים, imagine it's
in your backpack because that's like the scenario. Okay, so if this
wall here were the gates of ירושלים and that way is ירושלים,
right? So if I'm standing here and I'm outside ירושלים but my
backpack is in, which has the מעשר שני in it, okay, in
that case you can no longer redeem it because the food itself
is in ירושלים. Okay, פשיטא peshita it's obvious, what? Well right. פשיטא
הוא בחוץ ומשאו בפנים קלטוהו מחיצות. Peshita hu bachutz u-masa’o bifnim kaltuhu
mechitzot. The walls absorbed it, right? It's an absorption city like עיר
מקלט Ir Miklat actually just occurs to me, similar to the earlier
discussion. It's been, the food has been taken in by the walls,
it's in the city and you can't redeem it anymore unless it's
טמא, but assuming it's not טמא, it can't be redeemed anymore. הוא
בפנים ומשאו בחוץ מהו? Hu bifnim u-masa’o bachutz mahu? But let's say
you're inside and your backpack is still out of the gates. Is
it too late to redeem it? Now if you happen to be
in ירושלים and your trip and your food is in תל אביב,
Tel Aviv, you can obviously redeem it because the food is out,
it's really about the food, everybody gets that, right? But if it's
on your backpack and you're inside, how much does the fact that
you're inside make it like the food is inside? Because the food
is on your backpack. Everybody sort of get the question? All right,
so תנא להו ההוא סבא, tana lehu hahu saba, so a certain
elder taught to them דבי רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, d’vei Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai, a ברייתא in the from the house of רבי שמעון
בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, כי ירחק ממך המקום, ki yirchak
mimcha hamakom, when it's distance from you, ממלואך, mimlu’acha, from your full.
So what does that exactly mean? It's a little vague, but basically
the way רש"י Rashi explains it, oh I wanted to say something
about רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot is that it means the entirety
of you. Now you're one big person, it's you and your backpack
because it's on your back, it's not your food is separate from
you. So since that entire unit is not outside of ירושלים, part
of that unit is in, you're in, even though your backpack is
out, but since part of the whole unit is in, you're already
in. Once you're a little bit in, you're fully in. So if
you're in, you're in with your backpack and you can't redeem it
anymore. So the basic answer is that's also too late to redeem
it. By the way, I want to pause, I know we're basically
over with time, but if you go up, I need to show
you five lines from the top in the narrow lines, okay, you
see in רש"י, Rashi, you see the parentheses it says רבינו? Rabbeinu?
From the top, five lines from the top, the narrow lines. Okay,
so the previous רש"י Rashi was talking about being טהור, okay, הרחץ
טהור דטבל על אוכל במעשר, harachatz tahor d’taval al ochal b’ma’aser, it
doesn't matter, he just said the word טהור. And in parentheses it
says רבינו, Rabbeinu, which is רש"י Rashi גופו טהור ויצאה נשמתו בטהרה,
gufo tahor v’yatza nishmato b’tahara, okay, which is by the way the
whole story about רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, if you remember the deathbed
scene of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, they said do you reverse yourself?
What's the story about the תנור של עכנאי? tanur shel achnai? He
said טהור. And that was the last word out of his mouth
and it says ויצאה נשמתו בטהרה. yatza nishmato b’tahara. So טהור, you
know, his soul departed when he said the word טהור. So טהור,
you know, the last line of this רש"י Rashi had the word
טהור and this commentary is saying that רש"י Rashi did not continue
his commentary. הרחץ טהור דטבל על אוכל במעשר, harachatz tahor d’taval al
ochal b’ma’aser, he died. Well right, he didn't die at that moment,
but he didn't continue, he died before he was able to complete
his commentary on מכות. Makkot. Now he also died in the middle
of בבא בתרא, Bava Batra, he died a few times. He was
working on doing a bunch of things at the same time. גופו
טהור ויצאה נשמתו בטהרה, gufo tahor v’yatza nishmato b’tahara, let’s say... goodbye.
no פירוש רש"י Peirush Rashi and he didn't explain any more of
מסכת מכות. Maseches Makkos. מכאן ואילך לשון תלמידו רבינו יהודה בר נתן.
Mikan va'eilach l'shon talmido Rabbeinu Yehuda Bar Nosson. Okay, so this is
his student's commentary from this point on, so actually it's no longer
רש"י. Rashi. It's actually the ריב"ן. Rivan. Anyway, let's just read one
more line of the גמרא. So the גמרא says even if you're
a little bit outside, even if roughly on the target, so even
if you're a little bit inside, part of you is inside and
the backpack is outside, you're still inside and you can't redeem it.
So בעי רב פפא, Ba'ei Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa
said, נקיט ליה בקניא מאי? Nakti leh b'kanya mai? Let's say it's
not a backpack. Let's say it's like those pictures of the hobo,
you know, you got the stick and you got the... so you
got a stick. So you're in ירושלים. You're not wearing it. You're
in ירושלים and you got the stick and at the end of
the stick is your מעשר bag. So, but you're in ירושלים and
it's out. What would the story be? So the גמרא says תיקו.
Teyku. Okay, so we end with one of the... with those great
רב פפא Rav Pappa questions that wants to figure out exactly where
to draw the line. We'll continue with this discussion tomorrow,
if you're part in or part out, at what moment מעשר שני
becomes no longer able to be redeemed.