Today's דף daf is ל. lamed. We have three days left. We
pick up at the bottom of כ"ט עמוד ב'. Kaf Tet Amud
Bet. A line starts with the word שחל להיות בשבת. Shechal Liyot
BeShabbat. It's about twelve lines from the bottom. It's about four lines
from below the line above רבינו חננאל. Rabbeinu Chananel. Starts with שחל
להיות בשבת. Shechal Liyot BeShabbat. ראש חודש טבת. Rosh Chodesh Tevet. ואמר
רב יצחק נפחא Ve'amar Rav Yitzchak Naphcha said רב יצחק נפחא, Rav
Yitzchak Naphcha, ראש חודש טבת שחל להיות בשבת. Rosh Chodesh Tevet shechal
liyot beShabbat. So we're dealing with times when you're going to need
multiple ספרי תורה. sifrei Torah. So you have ראש חודש טבת Rosh
Chodesh Tevet in which of course there's חנוכה Chanukah that happens on
שבת, Shabbat, one of the times that you get three ספרי תורה,
sifrei Torah, right? So what do you do? Also the longest בענטשינג
benching I believe. מביאים שלוש תורות וקוראים בהן אחד עניין של יום
וחד דראש חודש וחד דחנוכה. Mavi'im shalosh torot vekorin bahen echad inyan
shel yom vechad deRosh Chodesh vechad deChanukah.
Where are we?
Before or after that?
Two lines after that.
איתמר. Itmar. I'm sorry. Okay, איתמר, Itmar, ראש חודש טבת שחל להיות
בשבת. Rosh Chodesh Tevet shechal liyot beShabbat. I'm sorry. Okay fine. So
we were even further on. Six lines from the bottom. One, two,
three, four, five, six, seven lines from the bottom. Another ראש חודש
טבת שחל להיות בחול, Rosh Chodesh Tevet shechal liyot bechol, excuse me.
ראש חודש טבת שחל להיות בחול. Rosh Chodesh Tevet shechal liyot bechol.
Fine. Okay, so that was the שבת Shabbat case that we did
yesterday. ראש חודש טבת Rosh Chodesh Tevet falls out on a weekday.
אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, קורא תלתא בראש חודש וחד בחנוכה.
Kore telata beRosh Chodesh vechad beChanukah. So you have to do, you
have four עליות aliyot
and so how are you going to divide them? So you have
four because it's ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. You would have only three
because it's חנוכה. Chanukah. So he says you read three about ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh and one, the fourth עליה, aliya, is the חנוכה
Chanukah reading. ורב דימי מחיפה אמר קורא תלתא בחנוכה וחד בראש חודש.
VeRav Dimi miHaifa amar kore telata beChanukah vechad beRosh Chodesh.
Three of the חנוכה Chanukah reading, which is you know the נשיאים,
nesi'im, and one of the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh reading, which is
the מוסף של ראש חודש. musaf shel Rosh Chodesh. אמר רב מני,
Amar Rav Mani, said רב מני, Rav Mani, כוותיה דרב יצחק נפחא
מסתברא. Kevatei deRav Yitzchak Naphcha mistabra. Makes sense like רב יצחק נפחא
Rav Yitzchak Naphcha that most of it is the ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh reading. Why? דתדיר ושאינו תדיר תדיר קודם Detadir veshe'eino tadir tadir
kodem
because ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is more תדיר tadir and so therefore
you're going to, that's going to dominate and come first also. Although
come first doesn't necessarily mean you get three of it, but okay
it's going to come first and therefore it's going to be more.
אמר רב אבין, Amar Rav Avin, כוותיה דרב דימי מסתברא. Kevatei deRav
Dimi mistabra. No, like רב
דימי Rav Dimi makes sense. מי גרם לרביעי שיבוא? Mi garam lerevi'i
sheyavo? Why do you have a fourth עליה? aliya?
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It's only because of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
you have a fourth עליה. aliya. On a normal weekday חנוכה Chanukah
you have three עליות. aliyot. הלכך רביעי בראש חודש בעי מקרי. Hilkakh
revi'i beRosh Chodesh ba'ei mikri.
Therefore the fourth עליה aliya which is because of ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh should be the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh of the ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh topic. Should be the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh reading. מאי
הוי עלה? Mai hava alah? What was the conclusion? רב יוסף אמר
אין משגיחין בראש חודש. Rav Yosef amar ein mashgichin beRosh Chodesh.
You don't pay attention to ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, which doesn't mean
you don't pay attention at all but you don't give it significant
weight. The fundamental reading is חנוכה. Chanukah. ורבא אמר אין משגיחין בחנוכה.
VeRaba amar ein mashgichin beChanukah. You don't give weight to חנוכה. Chanukah.
The fundamental reading is ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. והלכתא, Vehilkhata, the הלכה
halakha is אין משגיחין בחנוכה וראש חודש עיקר. ein mashgichin beChanukah veRosh
Chodesh ikkar.
You don't pay attention to חנוכה Chanukah again, literally you don't do
it, but it does not have, you don't give it weight. You
fundamentally read ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, three עליות aliyot of ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh and the fourth עליה aliya of חנוכה. Chanukah. Fine. איתמר.
Itmar. חל להיות בואתה תצוה. Chal liyot beVe'ata Tetzaveh.
Now what happens if the פרשת שקלים parshat shekalim which is a
larger theme here falls out on the שבת Shabbat of ואתה תצוה?
Ve'ata Tetzaveh? The שבת Shabbat which precedes כי תשא. Ki Tissa. כי
תשא Ki Tissa is the פרשה parsha you read for פרשת שקלים,
parshat shekalim, the beginning of כי תשא. Ki Tissa. So אמר רב
יצחק נפחא, Amar Rav Yitzchak Naphcha, so רב יצחק נפחא Rav Yitzchak
Naphcha says great, קרי שיתא מואתה תצוה. Karei shisha meVe'ata Tetzaveh.
The first six עליות aliyot are the פרשה parsha ואתה תצוה Ve'ata
Tetzaveh עד כי תשא. ad Ki Tissa. Until כי תשא. Ki Tissa.
וחד מכי תשא עד ועשית. Vechad miKi Tissa ad ve'asita.
And the seventh עליה aliya you read the beginning of the next
פרשה, parsha, you read כי תשא Ki Tissa which is שקלים. shekalim.
It works out very nicely. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
אמרי Amri no, wait a minute, people will say אוקמי הוא דקא
מוקמי התם. Ukmi hu deka mokmi hatam.
It won't be top of ל עמוד א'. Lamed Amud Aleph. It
won't be clear that this is פרשת שקלים. parshat shekalim. People will
just think you know this בקרא bakara decided to go a little
bit further into next week's פרשה. parsha. They won't realize that this
specific reading is for פרשת שקלים. parshat shekalim. Okay, especially recognizing it
is interesting to note that they had the clear divisions that we
have, right? At least you know כי תשא, Ki Tissa, ואתה תצוה
Ve'ata Tetzaveh and so on. The גמרא, Gemara, you know we're going
to see of course I think the גמרא Gemara already yesterday right
dealt with the מנהג minhag of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael which divided
it over three years so obviously the divisions were going to be
very different. It should be noted that that's radically different than what
the non-Orthodox movements do nowadays which is they do the same פרשה,
parsha, you know, they follow the same what each year they sort
of finish the cycle except one year they read the first third
of each פרשה, parsha, the second the second third, and I've actually
heard from a lot of people that they don't actually keep to
that, like every single year they just read the first third or
something, but anyway but no here they really did divide it over
three years, so that would have led to a completely different division
of the פרשיות. parshiyot. But even so, you know, you're dealing at
a time where there was a certain amount of flux and
latitude. rather אביי Abaye said קרו שישה מואתה תצוה karu shisha mi-Ve'atah
Tetzaveh עד ועשית ad Ve'asita וחד
תני וקרי מכי תשא עד ועשית. ve-chad tani ve-kari mi-Ki Tisa ad
Ve'asita. You read six, and the guy who gets the sixth עליה
aliyah goes all the way, it's sort of like you do what
we do with מפטיר, maftir, but notice by the way, you know,
this gets into the whole issue whether מפטיר maftir is עולה מן
המנין oleh min ha-minyan or not עולה מן המנין oleh min ha-minyan
and all those types of things. The גמרא Gemara here is assuming
that the person who gets the קריאה kriah for, what do you
call it, for the special פרשיות parshiyot is not getting it for
מפטיר, maftir, he's getting it for שביעי. shvi'i. Right, that's the assumption.
And how we've evolved that it's the בעל מפטיר Ba'al Maftir gets
into the earlier discussions about whether the מפטיר maftir is עולה מן
המנין oleh min ha-minyan or not. But anyway, so אביי Abaye says
that what you do is the person who gets שישי shishi reads
through כי תשא, Ki Tisa, doesn't stop at the end of תצוה,
Tetzaveh, goes into
כי תשא Ki Tisa all the way till ועשית, Ve'asita, all the
way till the end of the reading for פרשת שקלים. Parshas Shekalim.
And the person who gets שביעי shvi'i doubles back and re-reads that
in order to be clear that it's a special reading for שקלים.
Shekalim. Okay. וחד תני וקרי מכי תשא עד ועשית. ve-chad tani ve-kari
mi-Ki Tisa ad Ve'asita. מיתיבי, Meisivi, says the גמרא, Gemara, ask you
on this: חל להיות בפרשה סמוכה לה בין מלפניה בין מלאחריה, chal
liyot be-parsha smucha lah bein milfaneha bein milachareha, if the, what do
you call it, if it occurred, the פרשת כי תשא Parshas Ki
Tisa fell out in the weekly reading either right before, which, you
know, if, excuse me, פרשת שקלים Parshas Shekalim fell out right before
or right after כי תשא, Ki Tisa, okay, so it fell out
on the שבת Shabbos immediately preceding or immediately following כי תשא, Ki
Tisa, קורין
אותה וכופלין אותה. korin osah ve-koflin osah. You read it and you
repeat it. Now, although this ברייתא braisa which the גמרא Gemara is
going to point out said before or after, let's imagine the case
of before. So the פרשה parsha fell out before כי תשא. Ki
Tisa. So what do you do? שקלים Shekalim falls out before כי
תשא. Ki Tisa. You read it and you repeat it. So that
sounds like אביי. Abaye.
All right, that's what we're going to get to. בשלמא לאביי ניחא,
Bishlama le-Abaye nicha, for אביי Abaye that's perfect. You read it for
שישי shishi and you repeat it for שביעי. shvi'i. אלא לרבי יצחק
נפחא קשיא. Ella le-Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha kashya. רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak
Nafcha doesn't make sense. You're not going to repeat it. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך רבי יצחק נפחא לאביי מי ניחא Amar
lach Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha le-Abaye mi nicha? Wait a minute, that ברייתא
braisa doesn't even work according to אביי Abaye the way you're reading
it. תימא לפניה. Teima lefaneha. You focused on the case of שקלים
Shekalim coming before כי תשא. Ki Tisa. So you had: okay, for
שישי shishi you read it and for שביעי shvi'i you repeat it.
אבל לאחריה מאי איכא למימר Aval leachareha mai ika lemeimar? The ברייתא
braisa said whether before or after. If שקלים Shekalim comes after כי
תשא, Ki Tisa, what does it mean? It doesn't mean that during
the פרשה parsha of that שבת Shabbos you're going to repeat the
שקלים Shekalim section. It came after כי תשא. Ki Tisa. There's no
issue. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מאי אית לך למימר Ella
mai is lach lemeimar? What does the ברייתא braisa have to mean?
It means what Michael said. כופלה בשבתות. koflah be-shabbasos. It means even
if שקלים Shekalim came right before or right after כי תשא, Ki
Tisa, you wind up reading that section from כי תשא Ki Tisa
two שבתות Shabboses in a row, בשבת שקלים be-Shabbos Shekalim and the
next שבת Shabbos of כי תשא Ki Tisa or the שבת Shabbos
of כי תשא Ki Tisa and the next שבת Shabbos of שקלים.
Shekalim. הכי נמי כופלה בשבתות. Hachi nami koflah be-shabbasos. Here too, you
repeat it the following or the preceding שבת. Shabbos. It has nothing
to do with when you're actually reading it that שבת Shabbos whether
you repeat the verses or not repeat the verses.
I know. Well, it's not a קשיא, kashya, but it's not relevant.
Okay. חל להיות בכי תשא גופה. Chal liyot be-Ki Tisa gufa. So
that's the debate for what happens if it falls out, if שקלים
Shekalim falls out before כי תשא, Ki Tisa, what do you do?
Do you re-read the section so as to give it, make it
clear that it's a special reading for שקלים? Shekalim? Let's say it
falls out on כי תשא. Ki Tisa. So now you're going to
read the first section of כי תשא Ki Tisa twice, once for
כהן Kohen and then again for שביעי shvi'i or for מפטיר. maftir.
So do you do that? So let's take a look. חל להיות
בכי תשא גופה. Chal liyot be-Ki Tisa gufa. אמר רבי יצחק נפחא,
Amar Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha, says רבי יצחק נפחא, Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha, who
remember רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha in the previous discussion did
not like repeating things, right? So he
said שביעי shvi'i before gets the second aliyah, he's not concerned that
people will think it's, won't realize it's distinct. He doesn't like repeating
things. So רבי יצחק נפחא Rabbi Yitzchak Nafcha here similarly says, קורא
שישה
מועשית עד ויקהל, korei shisha mi-Ve'asita ad Vayakhel, which is now even
more radical. He says you don't begin the פרשה parsha with כי
תשא. Ki Tisa. You jump over the שקלים Shekalim reading. You start
from ועשית. Ve'asita. You read to the end, till ויקהל. Vayakhel. וחד,
ve-chad, and then one עליה, aliyah, the presumably the seventh, קורא מכי
תשא עד ועשית, korei mi-Ki Tisa ad Ve'asita, goes back and reads
the שקלים Shekalim reading, which is very bizarre. So מתקיף לה אביי,
Maskif lah Abaye, says אביי, Abaye, השתא אמרי למפרע הוא דקרי. hashta
amri le-mafrea hu de-kari.
People will say you're reading backwards, out of order, and when one
of the earlier משניות Mishnayos right told us about how you don't
go out of order when you read the תורה. Torah. So אלא
אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says, קורא שישה עד
ויקהל. korei shisha ad Vayakhel. No, here you start from כי תשא,
Ki Tisa, you read six עליות aliyos till ויקהל. Vayakhel. וחד תני
וקרי מכי תשא עד ועשית. ve-chad tani ve-kari mi-Ki Tisa ad Ve'asita.
And the seventh עליה aliyah goes back to the beginning of כי
תשא Ki Tisa and reads the first section. section of it which
is פרשת שקלים. Parshat Shekalim. So this like clearly has to be
אביי, Abaye, you're not going to read out of order. The other
thing you could go either way. תניא כוותיה דאביי, Tanya Kevatei de-Abaye,
we taught like אביי. Abaye. חלה להיות בכי תשא עצמה, Chala Lihiyot
be-Ki Tisa Atzmah, if שקלים Shekalim falls out on כי תשא, Ki
Tisa, קורא אותה וכופלה. Koreh Otah ve-Koflah. You read it and you
repeat it, and here repeat it must mean you go back to
the first section and you re-read the first section.
Okay, but his pshat in השתא אמרי, Hashta Amrei, does he mean
that
people will perceive you're reading out of order because you're reading like
the פרשה Parshah which is not in its sequence?
Or people, right, that it
really is out of order.
Yeah, it's a good point, you're right. To say השתא אמרי Hashta
Amrei means oh people will perceive it as it's out of order.
But there, it really is out of order, you really skipped a
section. You know, it's nice that you went back to it not
because the order of reading the פרשה Parshah but in order to
do שקלים, Shekalim, but it doesn't matter, you skipped a section. Well
in the reading, you're reading the whole...
Right. I guess you could argue since there are some things that
are לא קוראים ולא מתרגמים. Lo Korim ve-Lo Metargemim.
Although no, the לא קוראים Lo Korim is nothing in the תורה,
Torah, the לא קוראים Lo Korim is only in נ"ך, Nach, right?
You could say well I'm not reading the תורה Torah out of
order, I skipped a section of the תורה, Torah, and then the
other thing I did wasn't the thing I skipped, it was actually
שקלים. Shekalim. So maybe that's a little bit the language of אמרי,
Amrei, but you're right. It was a very strange position there. Okay.
So now we get to, so that's about what happens about the
שקלים Shekalim in כי תשא Ki Tisa which can sometimes abut. But
now we're going to get to the whole issue of how to,
you know, arrange it in the calendar, the four special פרשיות Parshiyot
so that they fall out where they need to fall out. That
שקלים Shekalim falls out, you know, two weeks before פורים, Purim, that
זכור Zachor falls out before פורים, Purim, all these things, how to
happen based on which day of the week they fall out. So
let's take a look. חל להיות בתוך השבת, מקדימים לשבת שעברה. Chal
Lihiyot betoch ha-Shabbat, makdimim le-Shabbat she-avrah. So if
ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar falls during the week, you make
you have you read שקלים Shekalim the previous
שבת. Shabbat. איתמר. Itmar.
Let's sort of do a, of course now I can't find my
marker.
Oh, there's a marker. Okay.
So here we have, there's ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, okay,
there's one, okay, there's פורים Purim on the 14th, and here's the
15th, שושן פורים, Shushan Purim, okay, anyway, so that's פורים Purim and
this is שושן פורים, Shushan Purim, okay, fine. Okay. And then you've
got
what
do you have next? There's 29 days to אדר, Adar, right, and
then you've got this ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, and then
it's going to be פסח, Pesach, but okay. So what we need
to have is, we need to have פרשת החודש Parshat HaChodesh on
or before ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh,
right, we have to have פרשת החודש Parshat HaChodesh somewhere there. We
have to have, we have to have פרה Parah beforehand, okay. We
have to have זכור Zachor
let's say before פורים, Purim, maybe on, we'll see. And we have
to have שקלים, Shekalim, right, two weeks before, you know, before
because השולחנות היו יושבים, ha-shulchanot hayu yoshvim, so we have to have
שקלים, Shekalim, we have to have שקלים Shekalim on or before ראש
חודש אדר. Rosh Chodesh Adar. Okay. Yeah, or 30 days before ראש
חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. Okay, so that's basically how it happens.
So if שקלים Shekalim falls out, so if ראש חודש אדר Rosh
Chodesh Adar is on שבת, Shabbat, okay, and all these are being
read on שבת, Shabbat, so then you read it here. Okay. If
ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar is during the week, you have
to have it before because you have to give people enough time
to read, you have to give people enough time right to bring
their שקלים, Shekalim, so you can't do it later, you have to
do it earlier. Okay, so let's take a look. חל להיות בתוך
השבת, Chal Lihiyot betoch ha-Shabbat, so if ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh
Adar falls out during the week, מקדימים לשבת שעברה, makdimim le-Shabbat she-avrah,
you have
to have שקלים Shekalim in the previous week, the previous שבת. Shabbat.
איתמר. Itmar. ראש חודש אדר שחל להיות בערב שבת. Rosh Chodesh Adar
she-chal lihiyot be-Erev Shabbat. So let's say this was on Friday, okay.
So if this was on Friday, okay, do we have שקלים Shekalim
way back here, six days earlier, right?
Or do we have שקלים, Shekalim, do we just have it one
day later? But that cuts in one day to the two weeks
of bringing the שקלים. Shekalim.
Yeah, the question says, if it's בתוך השבת, betoch ha-Shabbat, right, בתוך
השבת. betoch ha-Shabbat.
All right, so let's take a look. So רב אמר מקדימין, Rav
amar makdimin, so רב Rav says yeah, like Michael, yep, says if
it's not on שבת, Shabbat, you do it the שבת Shabbat before.
ושמואל אמר מאחרין. ve-Shmuel amar me-acharin. No, you do it a day
later, you do it on the following שבת. Shabbat. רב אמר מקדימין
דאם כן בטלי להו ימי שולחנות, Rav amar makdimin de-im ken batli
lehu yemei shulchanot, because if you postpone it, you're not going to
have the full 14 days of bringing the שקלים, Shekalim, you know,
of getting ready to bring the שקלים Shekalim before the money changers
sit out there. ושמואל אמר מאחרין. ve-Shmuel amar me-acharin. No, you can
actually you are allowed to push this off one
day. אמר לך סוף סוף חמיסר במעלי שבתא מיקלי. Amar lach sof
sof chamisar be-ma'alei Shabta miklei. If the first is on Friday, then
the 15th is on Friday. So you want to get people two
weeks to get ready to bring their שקלים Shekalim before the money
changers sit out there. before the money changers went and opened up
shop, went and started being available to collect the שקלים. shekalim. But
if the fifteenth itself is gonna be a Friday, so then he
says ושולחנות לא נפקי עד חד בשבתא, v'shulchanos lo nafki ad chad
b'shabta,
they're not gonna start opening the whole business of the money changing
on a Friday. They're gonna wait till a Sunday. You don't want
to start doing that ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. So therefore in that
type of a month where the first is on a Friday, the
שולחנות shulchanos won't get open till the, you know, till the follow
till Sunday two weeks from then. So you have your two weeks.
So הלכך מאחרין, hilkach me'achirin, therefore you postpone it. Okay, now we're
gonna try to prove it one way or the other. תנן, Tnan,
we taught in our משנה: Mishnah: חל להיות בתוך השבת, chal lihiyos
b'soch ha'Shabbos, if it fell during שבת, Shabbos, מקדימין לשבת שעבר, makdimin
l'shabbos she'u'var, you make it,
you push it off to the earlier שבת, Shabbos, ומפסיקין לשבת אחרת,
u'maphikin l'shabbos acheres,
and you have a break for a שבת. Shabbos. מאי לאו אפילו
בערב שבת? Mai lav afilu b'erev Shabbos?
So look, like Rav said, it says if it falls during שבת,
Shabbos, you push it back in the middle of the week, you
push it off to the previous week. Doesn't that mean even if
it falls on a Friday? לא בתוך השבת דוקא. Lo b'soch ha'Shabbos
davka.
No, we mean like in the middle of the week. If it
falls at the edge of the week, if it falls on a
Friday, we're not gonna push it off six days earlier. Okay, תא
שמע, ta shema, let's try again. We have a ברייתא. Braisa. And
we're gonna quote sections of this ברייתא Braisa through the first part
of the דף, daf, and we're gonna quote the whole part of
it at the bottom of the עמוד. amud. תא שמע: Ta shema:
איזו היא שבת ראשונה, eizo hi Shabbos rishona, what is the first
שבת Shabbos of the four special שבתות? Shabbosos? כל שחל ראש חודש
אדר להיות בתוכה. kol she'chal Rosh Chodesh Adar lihiyos b'socha. Any שבת
Shabbos that has the, you know, any week that has ראש חודש
אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar fall during it. So, ואפילו בערב שבת. v'afilu
b'erev Shabbos. So any week, right, this week has ראש חודש אדר,
Rosh Chodesh Adar, here's the previous שבת. Shabbos. So in this week
here, right, ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar fell during this week
even though it fell ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, and that is the
first שבת. Shabbos. The first שבת Shabbos of שקלים shekalim would be
any, you know, any שבת Shabbos that the coming week has ראש
חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar in it, even ערב שבת. erev Shabbos.
So that seems to be, even if ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh
Adar falls on ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. So that seems to be
like Rav says, that you are מקדימין. makdimin. So איזו היא שבת
ראשונה eizo hi Shabbos rishona כל שחל ראש חודש אדר להיות בתוכה
kol she'chal Rosh Chodesh Adar lihiyos b'socha ואפילו בערב שבת. v'afilu b'erev
Shabbos. So מאי לאו אפילו בערב שבת דומיא דבתוכה? mai lav afilu
b'erev Shabbos dumya d'socha? When it says any week that has שבת,
Shabbos, that has ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar fall in it,
it's even ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, so ערב שבת erev Shabbos is
like in it. So
דומיא דבתוכה: dumya d'socha: מה בתוכה מקדימין, ma socha makdimin, the same
way when it says if it falls in the week, so it
means that and therefore we read
שקלים shekalim the previous שבת. Shabbos. So אף ערב שבת, af erev
Shabbos, so even when it falls on Friday, מקדימין, makdimin, we read
שבת, Shabbos, we read שקלים shekalim the previous שבת. Shabbos. So that
seems to be a good point. It says anything that ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh falls during this week, even if it falls on Friday.
So אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel, so Shmuel says בה. ba. No, it's
not בתוכה, b'socha, it's
בה. ba. וכן תנא דבי שמואל בה. V'chein tana d'vei Shmuel ba.
Now that explains it. What does that mean?
So that means he does not
read any
week, כל שבת שחל ראש חודש אדר להיות בתוכה, kol Shabbos she'chal
Rosh Chodesh Adar lihiyos b'socha, any week that has ראש חודש אדר
Rosh Chodesh Adar in it, this is the, you know, the beginning
שבת Shabbos is שקלים. shekalim. That's the simple way of reading it.
He reads it, we're not talking about a week, כל שבת שחל
ראש חודש אדר להיות kol Shabbos she'chal Rosh Chodesh Adar lihiyos not
בתוכה b'socha but בה. ba. Right, so שבת Shabbos can sometimes mean
week and it can sometimes mean שבת. Shabbos. So which is the
שבת Shabbos of שקלים? shekalim? כל שבת שחל ראש חודש אדר להיות
בה, kol Shabbos she'chal Rosh Chodesh Adar lihiyos ba, ראש חודש אדר
Rosh Chodesh Adar falls on שבת, Shabbos, that's considered the first פרשת
שקלים. Parshas Shekalim. Or ואפילו ערב שבת, v'afilu erev Shabbos, even if
ראש חודש שבת אדר Rosh Chodesh Shabbos Adar fell on ערב שבת,
erev Shabbos, that שבת Shabbos would be the שקלים. shekalim. Okay, so
he reads it very differently. שבת Shabbos doesn't mean the week, it
means if it fell on שבת Shabbos or even if it fell
ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, that שבת Shabbos is שקלים shekalim and has
it read according to him. And again the simple read of the
ברייתא Braisa is like Rav, that if it's, that any time it
falls during the week, שקלים shekalim starts on the שבת Shabbos that
preceded it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
כתנאי. ka-tanna'ei. This is based on the debate of תנאים. Tanna'im. מסרגין
לשבתות דברי רבי יהודה הנשיא. Mesargin l'Shabbosos divrei Rabbi Yehuda Hanasi. You
jump over שבתות, Shabbosos, so, you know, you take breaks in the
שבת Shabbos for, you know, to spread out the weeks, to spread
out the special שבתות Shabbosos according to רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda
Hanasi. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר אין מסרגין. Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
omer ein mesargin. You don't take breaks. Now what does that mean?
I mean it's often gonna work out you need to take a
break. So here's what it means. אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אימתי
אני אומר אין מסרגין? Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar eimatai ani omer
ein mesargin? When do I say you don't start, you know, take
breaks, you know, skip? בזמן שחל להיות בערב שבת. Bizman she'chal lihiyos
b'erev Shabbos. When it falls on ערב שבת. erev Shabbos. Right, so
basically here, this is gonna be Shmuel's
position. If it falls on ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, okay, so he's
saying I'm going to say in this case read שקלים shekalim here.
Now if we read שקלים shekalim here what day this שבת, Shabbat,
that's the second of אדר, Adar, right? The next שבת Shabbat is
the ninth, and the next שבת Shabbat is the sixteenth, okay? So
in this case, you don't have to skip. This שבת Shabbat is
שקלים, Shekalim, right? If you say if you say when it falls
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls on Friday you go one day later.
This is שקלים, Shekalim, this is זכור, Zachor, this is פרה, Parah,
right? Works out very nicely, right? And this is, right, and the
30th, and then and then the
23rd is החודש, Hachodesh, and then you have ראש חודש ניסן Rosh
Chodesh Nissan on the 30th, right? Yes? So you see you don't
have to skip. Now we're actually going to talk about that, maybe
you should have it on ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan itself.
Okay, but in this case, if you were able to to go
forward a day, you're not going to have to do any skipping.
What?
It's only if
it's on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat.
That's what he said. אימתי אני אומר אין מסרגין. Eimatai ani omeir
ein mesargin. When any other day, you'll have to skip. Right, because
there's going to be an extra exactly. This is the one time.
But you don't skip. You don't. In this case, okay? אימתי אני
אומר אין מסרגין בזמן שחל להיות ערב שבת, Eimatai ani omeir ein
mesargin bizman shechal lihyos Erev Shabbat, אבל בזמן שחל להיות בתוך השבת,
aval bizman shechal lihyos b'toch hashabbat, but if it's in the middle
of שבת, Shabbat, מקדימין וקורין משבת שעברה, makdimin v'korin mishabbat she'avra, אף
על פי שהוא שבט, af al pi shehu Shvat, and
then you have to read it the previous שבת, Shabbat, the previous
שבת, Shabbat, which is שבט, Shvat, and then you're going to have
to have a break of a week where you're not going to
have a special פרשה parsha so you could get זכור Zachor to
be right before פורים. Purim. All right, so that's the debate of
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. What happens when ראש חודש אדר Rosh
Chodesh Adar falls out on שבת? Shabbat? ובשנייה זכור. uv'shniya Zachor.
We're going to פסקן pasken in all of these like רב. Rav.
And don't worry Michael, because at the end of this there's a
big רש"י Rashi that's going to tell us how to always know
which weeks you which weeks you do and which weeks you skip.
Okay, ובשנייה זכור. uv'shniya Zachor. So that's debate number one, whether you
when it's on when ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar is ערב
שבת Erev Shabbat you do early or do you push it off
a day. Now, the second one is זכור Zachor when that's before
פורים. Purim. Sometimes there'll have to be a week break, but you'll
so you'll give it a week שבת Shabbos skip if you need
to and you get זכור Zachor right before פורים. Purim. איתמר. Itmar.
Now let's talk about another special case.
פורים שחל להיות בערב שבת. Purim shechal lihyos b'Erev Shabbat. פורים Purim
falls out on Friday. Okay, רב אמר, Rav amar, this will come
as no surprise, מקדימין. makdimin. You do it fine, you do it,
you know, you do it six days earlier. You gotta get זכור
Zachor before פורים, Purim, מקדימין פרשת זכור. makdimin Parshat Zachor. ושמואל אמר
מאחרין. v'Shmuel amar me'achrin. Again, שמואל'ס Shmuel's very consistent, he says no,
ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, it's already ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, yeah, just
do it the next day. Now that's a little surprising. רב אמר
מקדימין כי היכי דלא תקדם עשייה לזכירה. Rav amar makdimin ki heichi
d'lo tikdam asiya lizchira. You gotta do this before. You can't have
the fulfillment, the the, you know, the מחיית עמלק mechiyat Amalek that
is, you know, the story of פורים Purim before mentioning the idea
of remembering it. You're supposed to talk about remembering it and the
obligation and, you know, the sort of history that preceded it and
then the execution in the in the מגילה. Megillah. So so you
can't you have to have it earlier. ושמואל אמר מאחרין. v'Shmuel amar
me'achrin. No, you can push it off to the 15th. אמר לך
כיון דאיכא מוקפין דעבדי בחמישה עשר, Amar lach keivan d'ika mukafin d'avdi
b'chamishah asar, since there was a מוקפין mukafin that do פורים Purim
on the 15th and so עשייה וזכירה בהדי הדדי קא אתיא. asiya
v'zchira behadi hadadi ka'asya. Yeah, all right, but at least but we're
also to some degree connected. So therefore there's some aspect of it
happening at the same time. Okay, now that's again very strange, as
Michael said, but that's שמואל'ס Shmuel's again position. Okay, תנן. Tnan. Now
we're going to try to prove it. ובשנייה זכור. uv'shniya Zachor. So
it says in the second פרשה parsha you read זכור. Zachor. והא
כי מקלעי ריש ירחא בשבת, V'ha ki mikli reish yarcha b'shabbas, the
משנה'ס Mishnah's first scenario was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh fell out on
שבת. Shabbat. So מקלע פורים בערב שבת, mikla Purim b'Erev Shabbat, right,
do the math. If ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is שבת, Shabbat, so
the 15th is also שבת, Shabbat, which is פורים Purim is the
14th. Okay, which is exactly your scenario. So מקלע
פורים בערב שבת mikla Purim b'Erev Shabbat וקתני ובשנייה זכור, v'katani uv'shniya
Zachor, and the משנה Mishnah says if ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls
out on שבת Shabbat then the first one is שקלים, Shekalim, right?
So if ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls out on שבת, Shabbat,
there, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls out on שבת, Shabbat, first one
is שקלים. Shekalim. You skip, you know, the second one is זכור,
Zachor, right? And in this case, שבת Shabbat now becomes,
right, this is ערב שבת Erev Shabbat in this scenario, the 15th
is ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, so that's the case. It says if
the first one is שבת, Shabbat, if ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is
שבת, Shabbat, the next one is זכור. Zachor. That's exactly your scenario.
פורים Purim is ערב שבת Erev Shabbat and it says you have
it the previous שבת. Shabbat. A good proof again for רב. Rav.
So the גמרא Gemara says והא כי מקלעי ריש ירחא בשבת מקלע
פורים בערב שבת וקתני ובשנייה זכור. v'ha ki mikli reish yarcha b'shabbas
mikla Purim b'Erev Shabbat v'katani uv'shniya Zachor. אמר רב פפא מאי שנייה
שנייה להפסקה. Amar Rav Pappa mai shniya shniya lehafsaka. No, it's not
talking about when it says the second one is זכור, Zachor, it
doesn't mean it doesn't mean only when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls
out on שבת. Shabbat. It means like in all the scenarios when
you basically go ahead and you read, you know, you read שקלים,
Shekalim, well, on שבת Shabbat so you read it early, then when
it says you read before שבת Shabbat you're going to skip. Remember
when this came out earlier, right? You're gonna have to skip and
then the second one after you skipped will be זכור, Zachor, but
it's not talking about the scenario of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. In
the scenario of ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, you would not read שקלים.
Shekalim. Here you'd read it here. What it says second, it means
when the משנה Mishna refers to skipping a שבת, Shabbos, when you
have to skip a שבת, Shabbos, then you skip one שבת Shabbos
and the next שבת Shabbos will be זכור. Zachor. So we're not
talking about that
scenario. תא שמע, Ta Shma, איזו שבת שניה? eizu Shabbos shniya? The
same ברייתא braita like we had before, except now talking about the
second שבת. Shabbos. כל שחל פורים להיות בתוכה, Kol shechal Purim lihyos
besochah, any week that פורים Purim occurs in it, the שבת Shabbos
had זכור. Zachor. ואפילו בערב שבת, Va'afilu be'erev Shabbos, even if פורים
Purim fell on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. So this is just like
the ברייתא braita we had earlier. This is the second week, right?
Here's שבת. פורים Shabbos Purim, occurs during the שבת. Shabbat. You're going
to read זכור Zachor on that שבת, Shabbat. even if פורים Purim
came out on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. Again a proof like רב.
Rav. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי לאו ערב שבת כתוכה? mai
lav Erev Shabbos ketocha? This says that ערב שבת Erev Shabbos is
the same as פורים Purim falling out in the middle of the
week. מה תוכה מקדימין, ma socha makdimin, the same way it means
that when פורים Purim falls out in the middle of the week
you read it the previous שבת, Shabbat, אף ערב שבת מקדימין, af
Erev Shabbos makdimin, when it falls out on Friday you read it
the previous שבת. Shabbos, אמר שמואל בה. Amar Shmuel bah. So שמואל
Shmuel says no, it's not 'be' that when פורים Purim falls out
during the week, we're not talking about the week. Again we're talking
about שבת. Shabbos. Okay, which שבת Shabbat. is the one in which
you will read זכור? Zachor? Any שבת Shabbat in which פורים Purim
falls בה bah on it. So now שמואל Shmuel is going to
say, which should not be a surprise, since שמואל Shmuel will have
you say זכור Zachor even before פורים, Purim that if פורים Purim,
falls out on שבת, Shabbat you read זכור Zachor and even if
פורים Purim fell on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, right, you will read
זכור Zachor on that following שבת. Shabbat, So he does not read
שבת Shabbat. as the week, the week that פורים Purim falls you
read שבת, Shabbat you read זכור Zachor here? No. When פורים Purim
falls on שבת, Shabbat, you read זכור Zachor and even if פורים
Purim fell on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, you read זכור Zachor on
שבת. Shabbat, So again, rereading the ברייתא braita to be talking about
שבת Shabbat. and say בה bah and not talking about the week.
Okay, וכן תנא דבי שמואל בה. vechein tana dbei Shmuel bah. All
right, so again getting out of the ברייתא, braita, but the simple
ברייתא braita is again like רב. Rav. Now, חל להיות בשבת עצמה,
chal lihyos beShabbos atzmah, let's say פורים Purim falls out on שבת
Shabbat itself. So there's no חידוש chiddush there. I mean שמואל Shmuel
just read the ברייתא braita to say it. There's no חידוש chiddush
there that שמואל Shmuel is going to say then of course you
read זכור Zachor on שבת פורים, Shabbos Purim. because then, you know,
at least if you could read it the day after you could
read it on שבת פורים. Shabbos Purim. It doesn't have to דווקא
davka be before, it could even be on, could even be on
שושן פורים. Shushan Purim. So what, so that case? So clearly שמואל
Shmuel is going to say the same thing. What's רב Rav going
to say? So let's take a look. אמר רב הונא לדברי הכל
אין מקדימין. Amar Rav Huna ledivrei hakol ein makdimin. There רב Rav
would concede read זכור Zachor on שבת פורים. Shabbos Purim. 'Cause it's
the same day. It's not after, it's the same day. Read it
on שבת Shabbos פורים. Purim ורב נחמן אמר עדיין היא מחלוקת. VeRav
Nachman amar adayin hi machlokes. No, even there רב Rav would say
push it off a whole week early. Why? Because he wants זכור
Zachor not just to be not after, he wants it to be
before. So the גמרא Gemara says, איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it was
also taught, אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי אבא אמר רב,
amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Abba amar Rav, פורים שחל
להיות בשבת, Purim shechal lihyos beShabbos, if פורים Purim falls out on
שבת, Shabbat, מקדים וקורין בשבת שעברה זכור. makdim vekorin beShabbos she'avrah Zachor.
You read it, so here's the statement in the name of רב.
Rav. Even in that case, it's not enough that it's not later,
it has to be earlier, and you'll read, you'll read it in
the previous שבת. Shabbat. Okay. So by the way, though, this scenario
does not happen according to our calendar. Okay. The only time פורים
Purim can fall out on שבת Shabbat is if you're in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, okay, or if you're in a walled city, wherever that walled
city might be, מימות יהושע בן נון. mimot Yehoshua bin Nun. All
right. Now, ובשלישית פרה אדומה. Uvshlishis Parah Adumah. So on the third
one you read פרה. Parah. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, איזו היא שבת
שלישית? eizu hi Shabbos shlishis? So here again is the similar ברייתא
braita as we had before. What is considered the third special שבת?
Shabbos? כל שסמוכה לפורים מאחריה. Kol shesmucha lePurim me'achareiha. So the first
שבת Shabbos was anything that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls during the
week. The second שבת Shabbos was anything that פורים Purim falls during
the week. The third שבת Shabbos is in, is in reference to
the previous week. Any, any time when, any שבת Shabbos where פורים
Purim preceded it in the previous week. איתמר, Itmar, רב חמא בר
חנינא אמר, Rav Chama bar Chanina amar, שבת הסמוכה לראש חודש ניסן.
Shabbos hasmucha leRosh Chodesh Nissan. He says no, it's not the שבת
Shabbat right, you know, right after פורים, Purim, it's the שבת Shabbat
right before ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. Now that's funny because
you would think the שבת Shabbat right before ראש חודש ניסן Rosh
Chodesh Nissan is when you read החודש. Hachodesh. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ולא פליגי, velo pligi, and they don't debate. הא דאיקלע ראש
חודש ניסן בשבת הא דאיקלע באמצע שבת. Ha d'ikla Rosh Chodesh Nissan
beShabbos ha d'ikla be'emtza Shabbos. So if ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh
Nissan is on שבת, Shabbat, if this is שבת, Shabbat, okay, so
then right, if that's שבת, Shabbat, if ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh
Nissan is שבת, Shabbat, you're going to read החודש Hachodesh here, part,
you'll read החודש Hachodesh here. So in that case, that's 30, so
that case you go back seven and on whatever, on 23, is
when you will read, is when you will read פרה. Parah. Okay,
and then you go back seven. from there and you're going to
get sixteen where you do nothing, right? And then you're going to
have זכור Zachor. *Zakhor* back at what, at nine, and שקלים Shekalim.
*Shekalim* back at two. Okay, so that'll be, no, you'll have שקלים
Shekalim. *Shekalim* before then. You have to do it not back at
two. Oh, right, right, that gets back to the whole thing, right,
that's מחלוקת רב Rav, ושמואל *Machloket Rav u-Shmuel*, then you'll have שקלים
Shekalim *Shekalim* way back here, okay, in שבט *Shevat*. Okay, fine. All
right, so that's the one where you're going to have like a
lot of gaps, right? Because because you know you're going to have
שקלים Shekalim *Shekalim* have to be before ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh
Chodesh*, then nine, and then anyway then you'll have two שבתות Shabbatot?
*Shabbatos* that you skip. Okay, but this is because you can get
החודש Hachodesh. *Hachodesh* to be on ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan.
*Rosh Chodesh Nisan* itself, so then you do this the שבת Shabbat,
*Shabbat* before ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, but you'll notice that's
more that's not the שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* right after פורים Purim, *Purim*.
This was the שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* right after פורים Purim *Purim*. Okay,
so in this case because you can get פרשת החודש Hachodesh *Parashat
Hachodesh* on ניסן Nissan *Nisan*, you're going to have this you're going
to have פרה Parah *Parah*, you know, closer to here and you're
going to actually skip a week skip a שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* after
פורים Purim, *Purim*. But in all other scenarios you're going to do
it the שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* follow so all other scenarios let's take
the next you know the next case. So the next case would
be that this would be the twenty-ninth would be החודש Hachodesh, *Hachodesh*,
right? That would be the next you know that would be this
that would be the latest date you could read it is if
שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* was on was on ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh
Nissan. *Rosh Chodesh Nisan*. So if שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* is the day
before the twenty-ninth is החודש Hachodesh. *Hachodesh*, the twenty-second and is the
next שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, and then you have the fifteenth, right? So
in this case you read it you would then read it the
שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* before ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan *Rosh Chodesh
Nisan* because that would be the twenty-ninth, you'd read it the שבת
Shabbat *Shabbat* right after פורים Purim, *Purim*. Okay, but first we do
in you read פרשת החודש Hachodesh? *Parashat Hachodesh* in that case on
the twenty-ninth and פרשת פרה Parah. *Parashat Parah* would still be a
week would still be the week before. Oh yeah. Oh because you
have that's true actually in that case you actually do want it
closer. Okay. So anyway that's true actually. In that case you're skip
you are going to skip the fifteenth even putting aside the debate
of רב ושמואל *Rav u-Shmuel*, you're right that they're both going to
agree that you don't read פרה Parah *Parah* on עצמו של פורים
Purim, או שושן פורים Purim, *atzmo shel Purim o Shushan Purim*. So
that in that case פרה Parah *Parah* will be here. Okay, so
that's a little imprecise because that's not exactly the שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*
after פורים Purim, *Purim*, that's the שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* after פורים Purim,
*Purim* slash שושן פורים Purim, *Shushan Purim*. That's true. Michael's correct, you're
not going to read פרה Parah *Parah* during פורים Purim, *Purim* or
שושן פורים *Shushan Purim*. Okay, so basically you're always going to read
it after פורים *Purim* and שושן פורים *Shushan Purim*, the immediate שבת
Shabbat *Shabbat* after, with the one exception when ראש חודש ניסן Rosh
Chodesh Nissan, *Rosh Chodesh Nisan* is on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, then you're
going to have a another skip so you'll get it right next
to ראש חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nissan. *Rosh Chodesh Nisan*. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan* איזהי
שבת Shabbat שלישית *Eizehi Shabbat Shlishit* that we just read that. תנו
רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan* ברביעי החודש הזה לכם *Be-revi'i Hachodesh Hazeh Lachem* and
in the fourth one you read החודש *Hachodesh*. So תנו רבנן *Tanu
Rabbanan* ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar שחל להיות בשבת *Rosh Chodesh
Adar she-chal lihyot be-Shabbat* when ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar *Rosh
Chodesh Adar* falls out on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*, קורין כי תשא *korin
Ki Tisa* now so okay we've already discussed like the the division
of skipping over now we're just going to talk about the קריאת
התורה Kri'at HaTorah *kriat ha-Torah*. So you have ראש חודש אדר Rosh
Chodesh Adar *Rosh Chodesh Adar* on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. So that's the
case where it's going to be on that's going to be שקלים
Shekalim *Shekalim*. So קורין כי תשא *korin Ki Tisa* which is how
it'll fall out which is שקלים Shekalim *Shekalim*, excuse me, ומפטירים ביהוידע
*u-maftirin bi-Yehoyada* and the הפטרה haftarah, *haftarah* is יהוידע הכהן *Yehoyada Ha-Kohen*
which is also about the שקלים Shekalim *Shekalim*. ואיזו היא שבת Shabbos,
ראשונה *Ve-eizo hi Shabbat rishona* now this is the whole ברייתא Baraisa.
*braita* that we quoted selections of before. ואיזו היא שבת Shabbos ראשונה
*Ve-eizo hi Shabbat rishona* what is the first שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* of
these four פרשיות Parshiot. *parshiyot*, כל שחל ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh
Adar להיות בתוכה *kol she-chal Rosh Chodesh Adar lihyot be-tokhah* any שבת
Shabbat *Shabbat* that that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* falls on
it or during it ואפילו בערב שבת Shabbat *ve-afillu be-erev Shabbat* even
if ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar *Rosh Chodesh Adar* falls on
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat, *erev Shabbat*, the שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat* that precedes
or has ראש חודש אדר Rosh Chodesh Adar *Rosh Chodesh Adar* falling
on it is the פרשה parsha *parsha* of שקלים *Shekalim*. ובשניה *U-va-shniyah*
the second פרשה parsha. *parsha* is זכור Zachor, *Zakhor* ומפטירים פקדתי *u-maftirin
Pakadeti* right which is the whole story in שמואל *Shmuel* about עמלק
*Amalek*. ואיזו היא שבת Shabbat שניה *Ve-eizo hi Shabbat shniyah* which is
פרשת זכור Zachor *Parashat Zakhor*, כל שחל פורים להיות בתוכה *kol she-chal
Purim lihyot be-tokhah* any week that פורים *Purim* falls during it ואפילו
בערב שבת Shabbat, *ve-afillu be-erev Shabbat* even if פורים *Purim* falls on
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat, *erev Shabbat*, again we'll read it simply like
רב *Rav*. So any week that פורים *Purim* falls during you'll read
it on the preceding שבת Shabbat? *Shabbat* even if פורים *Purim* was
on Friday. ובשלישית *U-va-shlishit* פרה Parah אדומה *Parah Adumah* the third one
you read פרה Parah *Parah* ומפטירים וזרקתי עליכם *u-maftirin Ve-zarakti aleikhem* פרשה
parsha, *parsha* from יחזקאל *Yechezkel*. ואיזו היא שבת Shabbat. שלישית *Ve-eizo hi
Shabbat shlishit* which is פרשת פרה Parah, *Parashat Parah*, כל שסמוכה לפורים
le-Purim, מאחריה *kol she-smukha le-Purim me-achareiha* immediately following פורים *Purim*, although as
Michael correctly indicated following פורים *Purim* and שושן פורים *Shushan Purim* it
won't be on שושן פורים *Shushan Purim* either. Okay. וברביעית החודש *U-va-revi'it
Hachodesh* and in the fourth one you read החודש הזה *Hachodesh hazeh*
ומפטירים כה אמר ה' אלהים בראשון באחד לחודש b'echad lachodesh. *u-maftirin Ko
amar Hashem Elokim ba-rishon be-echad la-chodesh* another פרשה parsha, *parsha* from יחזקאל
*Yechezkel*. And look at this we're actually going to finish. ואיזו היא
שבת Shabbat רביעית *Ve-eizo hi Shabbat revi'it* which is the fourth שבת
Shabbat, *Shabbat*? כל שחל ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh ניסן להיות בתוכה *kol
she-chal Rosh Chodesh Nisan lihyot be-tokhah* any week that ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh ניסן *Rosh Chodesh Nisan* falls during it ואפילו בערב שבת Shabbat
*ve-afillu be-erev Shabbat* even if ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh ניסן *Rosh Chodesh
Nisan* falls on Friday you read it in the previous week and
again not dealing with the case of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh ניסן
*Rosh Chodesh Nisan* falling on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*, then actually you would
read it on ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh ניסן *Rosh Chodesh Nisan*. But
if it falls any day other than שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* you read
it in the previous one. So how do we make it all
work? We פוסק *pasken* like רב *Rav* in all the cases and
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* gives you a... Monday, Wednesday and Friday, that's when
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, אדר can be, it's ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
אדר can be on שבת, Shabbat. Monday, Wednesday and Friday, that's when
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh אדר will fall out, and based on when
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh אדר falls out, here will tell you the
days that you skip is זבדו, Zavadu, ברו, Baro, גד, Gad, והיה.
V'haya. Okay, which means what? If ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. אדר falls
out on שבת, okay, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, אדר falls out on
שבת. So if ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh אדר falls out on שבת,
what are your שבתות? Shabbatot Your שבתות Shabboses. are 1, 8, 15,
22, 29, right? That's your שבתות. Shabbatot. Okay. So, the first one
is going to be what? Right, שקלים. שקלים. Second one, זכור. Zachor
Okay. Then you skip 15. You skip the 15th, right, because again,
you don't have פרה Parah on the 14th or the 15th that
wasn't said earlier, but that's assumed. Then the 22nd is what? פרה.
And then חודש, Chodesh, and it's beautiful. Okay, so this basically is
a very simple scenario. It draws out as we said פרה after
פורים, but פורים being defined as 14th and 15th. Okay, that's that.
Let's say שבת is the 2nd. Okay, then the next שבת is
9, 16, 23, and then 30 is ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh ניסן.
Those are your שבתות. Shabbatot, Okay, so when are you going to
do it? So we're going to rule like רב, so you're not
going to read on, right, you're not going to read on the
2nd, you're going to read שקלים back here. Week before. Okay, so
you're going to skip the 2nd, you're going to skip the 2nd,
you're going to read on the 9th, which is going to be
זכור, Zachor then you're going to read what do you call... What?
You're doing nothing on the 16th, because you read זכור Zachor and
then you do פרה again before חודש. Chodesh. What am I doing
wrong? Wait a minute, wait a minute. No, I did it wrong.
If ראש חודש falls out on... If שבת falls out on... No,
ראש חודש falls out on a Monday. It's not when שבת falls
out, it's when ראש חודש falls out. I'm sorry. ראש חודש falls
out on a Monday. Okay, I got that right. ראש חודש falls
out on a Monday. If ראש חודש falls out on a Monday,
then שבת is what day? That's 1, then שבת is what day?
6. Okay, so 6 is שבת. I'm sorry, I was getting that
wrong. Wait, okay. So the first one was what happened again? ראש
חודש fell out on שבת. Okay, so that's why שבת was 1
and whatever. All right. ראש חודש falls out on a Monday, so
שבת is 6. Okay, so שבת is 6, and then 13, 20,
27. Okay, those are your שבתות, Shabbatot. right? So you're going to,
so in that case, שקלים is going to be back here, right?
Because שקלים has to precede, so you skip ו, Vav, you skip
6, right? And then you have זכור Zachor because precedes פורים, then
you have פרה and then you have החודש. Everything works out well,
right? זכור Zachor precedes פורים, that's the שבת after פורים, everything is
good. That's that. If it falls out on a Wednesday, if ראש
חודש, I did it again, if ראש חודש is on a Wednesday,
then שבת is what? Thursday, Friday, שבת, the 4th. So then שבת
is the 4th, so you have 4, 11, 18, 25, right? So
שקלים is back here, you skip the 4th, okay? זכור is before
פורים, פרה is after פורים, and החודש is before ראש חודש ניסן.
That's that. If it falls out on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, right,
ראש חודש falls out on ערב שבת, then that's the case where
שבת is the 2nd, right? ראש חודש falls out ערב שבת, שבת
is the 2nd, so שבת is 2, 9, 16, 23, and then
you have ראש חודש. So in that case, you have two skips.
שקלים is back here, you skip this one, right? Because you have
to get זכור before פורים, you have זכור before פורים, so you
skip ב, Bet, you also skip the 16th, right? Because you've got
to get, you want to get פרה to be close to החודש,
so you skip the 16th, you have פרה, and you have החודש.
And that was where we said that when ניסן was on ראש
חודש, when ראש חודש ניסן was on שבת, in that case פרה
is before ראש חודש ניסן, it's not after פורים, it's before ראש
חודש ניסן. Why can't ראש חודש fall on Thursday? That's just the
way the calendar's arranged. ראש חודש can only fall out on those
days. Okay? For החודש? What's that Sally? What's the point? You mean
רש״י Rashi is giving... yeah. Yes, thank you for noticing that. For
a lot of ראשונים, Rishonim, the not writing 15 as יוד ה
Yud Heh and the 16 as יוד ו, Yud Vav, they only
did that for the 15th because יוד ה Yud Heh is God's
name, יוד ו Yud Vav is not God's name. So actually in
a lot of ראשונים Rishonim they insist the 16th is written as
יוד ו, Yud Vav, not as טז. Tet Zayin. Did you think
it was 10 and 6? Right. Okay, now we know. Now remember
that and you'll always know when we do the various פרשיות. parshiot,
Okay, moving on. בחמישי חוזרין לכסדרן. Bachamishi chozrin le-ke-sidran. What? That was
a summary of that whole big רש״י. Rashi. Okay, בחמישי חוזרין לכסדרן.
Bachamishi chozrin le-ke-sidran. On the fifth שבת you get back to the
normal types of reading. To the normal reading. לסדר מאי? Le-seder mai?
What reading have you interrupted? רב אמי אמר Rav Ami amar לסדר
פרשיות, le-seder parshiot, you actually, this was quoted earlier in the גמרא
Gemara and you read this on שבת, probably came as a shock
to you, that according to some practices you actually did not read
the entire פרשת השבוע Parshat Hashavua on these special שבתות. You just
read the special reading. How you would divide it into seven עליות,
aliyot, I have no idea. Okay, but that's what he says. You
get back to the normal פרשה parsha וחוזר. ve-chozer. רבי ירמיה אמר
Rabbi Yirmeya amar לסדר הפטרות הוא חוזר. le-seder haftarot hu chozer. No,
no, no. As we've been discussing earlier, right, the assumption of the
בבלי Bavli is you keep the normal הפטרות, haftarot, the normal פרשיות,
parshiyos, you read this as the seventh עליה, aliya, we do it
as the מפטיר, maftir, and then what you've really been changing is
the הפטרות. haftarot. So that's what you resume. אמר אביי Amar Abaye
כוותיה דרב אמי מסתברא, ke-vatei de-Rav Ami mistabra, it makes sense like
רב אמי Rav Ami that you've actually interrupted the פרשה. parsha. תנן:
Tnan: לכל מפסיקין. le-chol mafsikin. You would interrupt your normal order for
any special day. לראשי חדשים, Le-Rashei Chodashim, לחנוכה, le-Chanukah, לפורים, לתעניות, le-Ta'aniyot,
ולמעמדות, u-le-Ma'amadot, ליום הכפורים. le-Yom HaKippurim. For any of these days you
interrupt your normal reading. So what does it mean? It must mean
your reading, not your הפטרה, haftarah, because בשלמא למאן דאמר bishlama le-man
de-amar לסדר פרשיות הוא חוזר, le-seder parshiot hu chozer, if you're saying
you've disrupted your normal reading of the תורה Torah and then you
resume your normal reading of the תורה, Torah, האי איכא פרשה בחול,
hai ikka parsha be-chol, that we'll understand. So, you know, when these
things happen because what two things of this list cannot be happening
on שבת? תעניות Ta'aniyot and מעמדות. Ma'amadot. The תעניות ta'aniyot were fast
days and the מעמדות, ma'amadot, the special readings of the מעמדות, ma'amadot,
were also only on the weekday, not on שבת. So we're talking
about things that happen during the week. So you're not interrupting a
הפטרה, haftarah, you're interrupting your normal תורה Torah reading. אלא למאן דאמר
Ella le-man de-amar לסדר הפטרות הוא חוזר, le-seder haftarot hu chozer, if
you think the משנה Mishnah means you've interrupted the הפטרות, haftarot, so
הפטרה בחול מי איכא? haftarah be-chol mi ikka? When it deals with
מעמדות ma'amadot and these things, it's not talking about interrupting a הפטרה,
haftarah. it's talking about interrupting a normal reading of the תורה. Torah.
So ואידך, ve-idach, what would the other one say back? הא כדאיתא
והא כדאיתא. ha ke-d-itah ve-ha ke-d-itah. All right, each one is in
its own context. When it's dealing with weekday readings, like and this
is what we do, right? If חנוכה Chanukah when it's on a
Monday you don't read the פרשה, parsha you read חנוכה. Chanukah. So
when it's talking about weekday readings, then you interrupt the actual reading
of the תורה. Torah. When it's talking about שבת readings, you don't
interrupt the פרשה, you only interrupt the הפטרה. Haftarah. Okay, but again
the simpler reading of the משנה Mishnah certainly is that you interrupt
the תורה Torah reading. Okay, הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא. ha ke-d-itah ve-ha
ke-d-itah. ובתעניות, U-be-Ta'aniyot, למה לי הפסקה? lama li hafsaka? Now the גמרא
Gemara says: wait a minute, I don't get it. According to the
idea of who is it? רבי ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmeya, that you're supposed
to try to preserve the normal reading as much as possible, that's
what he says on שבת, so why by תעניות ta'aniyot did we
override the תורה Torah reading? ליקרי בצפרא בענינא דיומא. likrei be-safra be-inyana
de-yoma. Why don't you preserve the regular reading if it falls on
a Monday or Thursday and do that in שחרית, Shacharit, read the
ענינא דיומא, inyana de-yoma, the normal thing that you would read that
day, ובמנחה בתעניתא, u-be-mincha be-ta'anita, read that the special תענית ta'anit reading?
So the same way you רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya says on a
שבת you preserve the normal שבת reading and you just do the
special one for the last עליה, aliya, by a תענית, ta'anit, why
not preserve the normal reading in the morning and do the special
תענית ta'anit reading in the afternoon? So the גמרא Gemara says: but
you don't say that. The fact that you don't say that מסייע
ליה לרב הונא. mesaye'a lei le-Rav Huna. It supports the statement of
רב הונא. Rav Huna. דאמר רב הונא, De-amar Rav Huna, רב הונא
Rav Huna says מצפרא כינופיא. mi-safra kinufya. In the morning you're gathering
people, meaning there's not time to do קריאת התורה Kri'at HaTorah. in
the morning and we only do because you're too busy as we're
going to see gathering everybody and sort of, you know, doing taking
stock of one's deeds and like doing a process of communal תשובה
teshuvah or self-assessment and that's the focus of the morning and therefore
there's not a time to do a קריאת התורה. Krias HaTorah, I
know. So the גמרא Gemara says היכי עבדין? heichi avdin? What do
we do? אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: מצפרא ועד פלגא דיומא, mi-safra le-palga
de-yoma, מעיינין במילי דמתא. me'aynin be-milei de-mata. We look into issues of
the city. What are things we're... doing as a community and a
city that need to be corrected. מפלגא דיומא לפניא, mipalga deyoma lepanya,
and from the midday until nightfall, רבעי דיומא קרא ומשכרי, rivei deyoma
kara u'maskiri, half the day, a quarter of the remaining half we
devote for reading the תורה Torah and doing the הפטרה. That's a
long קריאת התורה, Krias HaTorah but okay, you know, we do it,
you know, somehow that occurs during the second, that quarter of the
afternoon, that half of the afternoon. ולרביע דיומא, U'lerivya deyoma, the other
quarter of the day, the last half of the afternoon, בעי רחמי,
baei rachamei, we daven. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, as it says, ויקראו בספר תורת
השם אלוקיהם רבעית היום, Vayikreu besefer torat Hashem elokeihem rivit hayom, they
read in the תורה Torah for half the day, for a quarter
of the day, excuse me. ורביעית היום, U'revit hayom, and another quarter,
מתוודים ומשתחווים, mitvadim u'mishtachavim, they would, you know, they would confess and
bow down and they'd pray. ואיפוך אנא? Ve'ipuch ana? The גמרא Gemara
says reverse it. Not reverse those two, because that's based on the
פסוק, pasuk, but do all that in the morning and do the
sort of assessing of the issues of the city in the afternoon.
לא סלקא דעתך, Lo salka daitach, that doesn't make sense, דכתיב, de'chtiv,
ואלי יאספו כל חרד בדברי אלוקי ישראל על מעל הגולה. ve'eilai ye'asefu
kol chared bedivrei elokei Yisrael al maal hagolah. So this is exactly
what it's patterned after, all these פסוקים pesukim from עזרא נחמיה, Ezra
Nechemiah, to me gathered all those that would be trembling, fearful of
the word of God for the transgression of the exile, ואני יושב
משומם, v'ani yoshev meshomam, and I was sitting astounded, עד מנחת הערב,
ad minchat ha'erev, until the afternoon time. וכתיב, U'chtiv, וממנחת הערב קמתי
מתעניתי, u'miminchat ha'erev kamti mita'aniti, and from the מנחה Mincha time I
got up, and then you would go do the sort of the
praying and the reading and the various rituals. So the morning of
a תענית Taanis is really devoted not to the ritual aspect, but
to the whole part of the sort of taking stock and self-assessment.
So therefore, that's why there's no קריאת התורה keriat HaTorah in the
morning, and therefore we can't split the difference and have the regular
reading in the morning and the תענית Taanis reading in the afternoon.
We're too busy doing this other stuff in the morning, so all
the reading takes place in the afternoon. Yeah, what can I say.
All right, let's go on to now this next, the next משנה,
Mishnah, the last משנה Mishnah of מגילה. Megilla. Okay, so we dealt
with the special פרשיות, last משנה Mishnah is going to deal with
the special קריאות התורה keriot hatorah that you do on the מועדים.
moadim. Okay, so let's take a look. בפסח קורין בפרשת מועדות, B'pesach
korin b'parshat moadot, on פסח Pesach you read by the פרשת מועדות
parshat moadot in אמור, Emor, שור או כשב או עז כי יולד,
Shor o chesev o ez ki yivaled, של תורת כוהנים, shel Torat
Kohanim, in ויקרא, Vayikra, in פרשת אמור. parshat Emor. ובעצרת, U'va'atzeret, on
שבועות, Shavuot, שבעה שבועות, Shiva shavuot, which makes sense. בראש השנה, B'Rosh
Hashanah, on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, בחודש השביעי, bachodesh hashvi'i, right, the
special פרשה which is part of אמור, Emor, but it's the part
that refers to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, באחד לחודש. ביום הכיפורים, B'Yom
HaKippurim, אחרי מות. acharei mot. יום כיפור Yom Kippur we know we
read פרשת אחרי מות parshat Acharei Mot about the special עבודה. avodah.
ביום טוב הראשון של חג, B'yom tov harishon shel chag, on the
first day of סוכות, Succot, קורין בפרשת מועדות שבטורת כוהנים, korin b'parshat
moadot shebetorat kohanim, you read from שור או כשב או עז, Shor
o chesev o ez, right, the whole big section in אמור Emor
which has to do with all the קרבנות korbonot of the various
מועדים. moadim. ובשאר כל ימי החג, U'bishar kol yemei hachag, on the
other days, on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, because this doesn't have two
days of יום טוב, Yom Tov, on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, בקרבנות
החג, bekorbanot hachag, you read from the specific קרבנות korbonot of the
חג chag that appears not in אמור Emor actually, but in פינחס.
Pinchas. Now what's not mentioned in the משנה Mishnah is, it didn't
tell you what you do on חול המועד פסח. Chol HaMoed Pesach.
Right, so that's interesting. That's going to be elaborated in the ברייתא.
בחנוכה B'Chanukah you read בנשיאים, banesi'im, by the whole thing is in
במדבר, Bamidbar, in נשא, Nasso, of the נשיאים. nesi'im. בפורים, B'Purim, ויבא
עמלק. Vayavo Amalek. בראשי חודשים, B'Roshei Chodashim, ובראשי חדשיכם. U'vrashei chodsheichem. ובמעמדות,
U'vama'amadot, and when you did the מעמדות ma'amadot in the various towns,
you know, that would be divided, it corresponded to the כוהנים kohanim
that would go up to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So במעמדות
במעשה בראשית, b'ma'amadot b'ma'aseh bereishit, which is what we learned in תענית.
Taanis. ובתעניות, U'veta'aniyot, and in תענית, Taanis, ברכות וקללות, brachot u'klalot, you
would read the ברכות brachot and קללות. klalot. רש"י says it's of
בחוקותי. Bechukotai. To speak about, yeah, so that's interesting. We learned all
of מסכת תענית Masechet Taanis and we didn't learn that, and we
don't do that on תענית Taanis either. Why not? Right, it's a
good question. We'll see how the גמרא Gemara, says. Anyway, but that's
like to strike fear into the hearts of people, so about, you
know, you got to do תשובה, teshuvah, this is all the bad
stuff that's going to happen. Or maybe because you're already experiencing bad
things, those תעניות ta'aniyot that were—remember, the standard תעניות ta'aniyot of the
משנה Mishnah are not the תעניות ta'aniyot of like י"ז בתמוז, Shiva
Asar B'Tammuz, etc. They're the תעניות ta'aniyot because it's not raining and
bad things are happening and so on. So that's exactly, you know,
think like, hooked into that theme of the ברכות brachot and קללות.
klalot. אין מפסיקין בקללות, Ein mafsikin baklalot, you don't give two עליות
aliyot in the קללות. klalot. You have one עולה olah do the
whole thing. אלא אחד קורא את כולן. Ela echad korei et kulan.
Okay. בשני ובחמישי ובשבת במנחה, B'sheni u'vchamishi u'vshabbat bemincha, on Monday and
Thursday and שבת מנחה, Mincha, קורין כסדרן, korin kesidran, you read like
the, you know, normal פרשה. ואין עולין להם מן החשבון, Ve'ein olin
lahem min hacheshbon, but it doesn't count to you for the following
שבת. Oh, we already read those עליות, aliyot, we'll just start with
שני. Sheni. Okay. שנאמר, She'ne'emar, now this שנאמר she'ne'emar is not about
why you don't get credit, this שנאמר she'ne'emar is going back to
why we divide the פרשה as we did. וידבר משה את מועדי
השם אל בני ישראל. Vayidaber Moshe et moadei Hashem el b'nei Yisrael.
מצוותן שיהיו קורין כל אחד ואחד בזמנו. Mitzvatan sheyihyu korin kol echad
v'echad bizmano. Okay, so משה Moshe read to בני ישראל, B'nei Yisrael,
so... Spoke, so somehow it's not exactly clear how we get this
from this פסוק. pasuk. We'll see more in the גמרא, but the
idea of וידבר מועדי Vayidaber Moadei that you're supposed to be reading
about the מועדים moadim during the time of the מועדים, moadim, so
we have the קריאת התורה linked to the special period of the
day. Okay, we will end with this and we will pick up
next time.