Okay, so today's דף *daf* is ל"א *Lamed Aleph*, the penultimate דף
*daf* of מגילה *Megillah*. We are wrapping up issues relating to the
reading. So the מסכת *masechet* had been about the reading of the
מגילה *Megillah*, then we had issues of other aspects of שול *shul*,
part and then about the of the of the reading of the
תורה Torah. *Torah*, the reading of the הפטרה Haftorah *haftarah*, ברכת כהנים
Kohanim *Birchas Kohanim* etc. Then we dealt with whole sanctity of the
בית כנסת *Beit Knesset* itself. Now we're going back to the specifics
of which sections are read. And the very last משנה Mishna? *Mishnah*
deals with the various sections that are read on the on the
ימים טובים Yamim Tovim, *Yomim Tovim*.
And the משנה mishna *Mishnah* specifically mentioned only the תורה Torah *Torah*
readings, not the הפטרה Haftarah *haftarah* readings, and it also did not
really detail the תורה Torah *Torah* readings for פסח Pesach. *Pesach*. So
let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to start
with a ברייתא Braisa *braita* and then continuously interrupt the ברייתא Braisa
*braita* with Aramaic statements. And you'll know that the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*
is interrupting it not only because of the Aramaic statements but because
they're often introduced with the words of והאידנא *ve-ha'idna*,
nowadays, or you know nowadays our practice is different than the ברייתא
Braisa. *braita*, or nowadays now that we keep here in גולה *golah*
two days of יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, this is what
we do. And what's interesting is that it's going to show not
only changes because of one day יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*
and two day יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*, but a general
fluidity around the issue of what was actually established as the תורה
Torah *Torah* reading and the הפטרה Haftarah *haftarah* reading. And when we
get an opportunity, I mean some of this will be obvious to
you even as we read it, we will point out and then
we'll point out in תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafot* where he flags that even
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is not what we practice nowadays.
So there's this ongoing sort of fluidity about, you know, about what
exactly we do for the תורה Torah *Torah* and the הפטרה haftorah?
*haftarah* readings. So let's take a look as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* begins here on ל"א עמוד amud א'
*Lamed Aleph amud aleph* right after the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*, five lines
down. תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*, our Rabbis taught: בפסח קורא בפרשת מועדות
*be-Pesach korei be-parashat moadot*, on פסח Pesach *Pesach* you read in the
פרשה parsha *parsha* of מועדות *Moadot*, which is in אמור Emor, *Emor*.
Like I said, I advise people if you want to grab a
סידור siddur *siddur* because you can just take a look, this will
be, you'll sort of see this how this is all reflected. So
people here have the Koren סידור *siddur*,
turn to
page, let's see, ah here page 1123, right? No, I'm sorry, not
1123, that's first day פסח Pesach *Pesach*, we'll get back to that.
1126, reading for second day פסח Pesach *Pesach*, first day סוכות Sukkot,
*Succos*, second and second day in diaspora. So this is like a
standard reading for the beginning of the חג chag, *chag*, not the
first day of פסח Pesach *Pesach*, but first and second day of
סוכות Sukkot *Succos*, second day of פסח Pesach *Pesach*. We'll see why.
Anyway, and what is it? שור או כשב או עז כי יולד
shor o chesev o ez ki yivaled, *Shor o chesev o ez
ki yivaled* right from ויקרא *Vayikra*. Okay, and you've got some ארצות
*arzot*? That whole sort of paragraph in the beginning talks in general
about bringing an animal that's born to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beit HaMikdash*. And then by the by the next paragraph, דבר אל
בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם מועדי ה' אשר תקראו אותם מקראי קודש אלה
הם מועדי *Daber el benei Yisrael ve-amarta aleihem mo'adei Hashem asher tikre'u
otam mikra'ei kodesh eleh hem mo'adai*. שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* and then you
get on to פסח Pesach *Pesach* etc., etc. Now as we know,
there's also sections in פנחס Pinchas, *Pinchas* and other places that talks
about the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. In אמור Emor *Emor*, although it's about
the קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*, there's more also of a dimension of the
aspect of the חג Chag *chag* that is celebrated outside of the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*. It's not all about the קרבנות
korbanos *korbanot*. So for example, you have, you know, ובקוצרכם את קציר
ארצכם לא תכלה פאת שדך בקוצרך ולקט קצירך לא תלקט *u-ve-kutzrechem et
ketzir artzechem lo techaleh pe'at sadecha be-kutzrecha ve-leket ketzirecha lo telaket*
by the by שבועות Shavuot *Shavuot*, so also how you practice it
outside of the מקדש Mikdash *mikdash*. Then we have בחודש השביעי ba-chodesh
ha-shevi'i, זכרון תרועה *be-chodesh ha-shevi'i zichron teruah*, בעשור לחודש מקרא קודש ועניתם
את נפשותיכם *be-asor la-chodesh mikra kodesh ve-initem et nafshoteichem*, it starts with
ענוי *innuy*, it doesn't start with the קרבנות korbonos *korbanot*. So although
it's very heavy קרבנות korbonos *korbanot*, there's a dimension that's a little
bit broader and it's not surprising that חז"ל chazal *Chazal* have picked
that as like the core פרשה Parsha *parsha* to be read for
the מועדות *Moadot*. But we will find that then as you see,
it's not for שבועות Shavuos, *Shavuot*, at least in our practice it's
not for פסח Pesach *Pesach*. This ברייתא Braisa *braita* has it that
this is what you read for פסח Pesach *Pesach* as well, first
day of יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* on פסח Pesach *Pesach*,
this part this section of אמור Emor, *Emor*, yes.
What is read in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael* today when
they do only one day?
Well, I do, it's a good question. I think that based on
what the Koren סידור *siddur* is telling me, well let's take a
look, let's first see what we do and then we'll talk about
that. Okay, so the ברייתא Baraita *braita* says you read from אמור
*Emor*, from שור או כשב או עז Shor O Kesev O Ez,
*Shor o chesev o ez*.
ומפטירין בפסח בגלגל *u-maftirin be-Pesach be-Gilgal*, and the הפטרה haftarah? *haftarah* is
the פסח Pesach *Pesach* that they observed in גלגל *Gilgal* when they
first entered into ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael? *Eretz Yisrael* from יהושע Yehoshua
*Yehoshua*. That's the ברייתא Baraita, *braita*. Now again you'll see the shift
to Aramaic and the key word like והאידנא *ve-ha'idna*, nowadays, so this
is the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* interjecting. והאידנא *ve-ha'idna*, nowadays דאיכא תרי יומי
d'ika srei yomei, *de-ika terei yomei*, there are two days of פסח
Pesach *Pesach*, two days of יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov* in
חוצה לארץ *Chutz La'aretz*, יומא קמא בפסח גלגל *yoma kama be-Pesach Gilgal*,
the first day you read by the פסח Pesach *Pesach* of גלגל
*Gilgal* of יהושע Yehoshua, *Yehoshua*. That's the. הפטרה haftarah ולמחר בפסח יאשיהו,
U'lamachar b'Pesach Yoshiyahu, and then on the second day the הפטרה Haftarah.
is from יאשיהו Yoshiyahu where they had a
whole rejuvenation of the
observance in general and a major celebration of חג הפסח. Chag HaPesach.
So that's what we read for the second day פסח. Pesach Now
according to that though, we're still sticking to שור כשב או עז
Shor Chashev Ve'az on the first day and presumably the first two
days. That's not what we do, we'll get to that. Okay, but
that's the two הפטרות. Haftoros. And then the ברייתא Baraita continues. ושארי
ימות הפסח, U'she'ar yemot HaPesach, now what do you do on חול
המועד פסח Chol HaMoed Pesach which is not discussed in the משנה?
Mishna מלקט וקורא מעניינו של פסח, Melaket vekorei me'inyano shel Pesach, you
collect and gather different things relating to פסח Pesach because there's a
lot of פסח Pesach in the תורה. Torah Okay, so that's what
the ברייתא Baraita says. So that doesn't help us too much in
terms of specifics. So now again you have the Aramaic and the
גמרא Gemara commenting on the ברייתא. beraita מאי היא? Mai hi? So
what are the various readings of the פסח Pesach, that you do
on חול המועד? Chol HaMoed? So אמר רב פפא מ״אפ״ש סימן. Amar
Rav Pappa Ma'apash siman. Now what's מ״אפ״ש? Ma'apash? So if you look
at רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says משכו וקחו לכם צאן למשפחותיכם ושחטו
הפסח Mashchu u'kechu lachem tzon lemishpachoteichem veshachatu hapesach when משה Moshe commands
the פסח Pesach in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael? אם כסף תלוה את
עמי Im kesef talveh es ami which is in the middle of
משפטים Mishpatim which speaks about the רגלים Regalim in general and mentions
פסח Pesach among them. פסל לך, Psal lecha, right, שני לוחות אבנים
shenei luchot avanim which is the second לוחות Luchos which then repeats
some of the aspects of משפטים Mishpatim and again mentions the רגלים.
Regalim. So that's like a little short distilled version of it. And
then that's the פ Pei and the ש Shin is וידבר Vayedaber
which is in בהעלותך Beha'alotcha which is in במדבר Bamidbar which is
פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Okay, so that would be the ones that
they would do. Now that by the way does not, that is
only an answer for חוץ לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. Why? Because how many
days did he talk about? מ״אפ״ש Ma'apash is how many days? Four.
Right? How many days of חול המועד Chol HaMoed do you have
in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael, Five. Okay, but that's his answer. Who
knows what they would do in ארץ ישראל? They'd find a fifth.
Now יום טוב אחרון של פסח, Yom Tov acharon shel Pesach, now
that's not what we do by the way, let's finish the ברייתא
beraita, and then we're going to talk about what we do. יום
טוב אחרון של פסח Yom Tov acharon shel Pesach קורין ויהי בשלח,
korin Vayehi Beshalach, which is because the קריעת ים סוף Kriat Yam
Suf on the seventh day. According to חז״ל, Chazal, ומפטירים וידבר דוד,
u'maftirin Vayedaber David, right, בשירת דוד b'shirat David which parallels שירת הים
shirat hayam which because you do שירת הים shirat hayam you do
שירת דוד, shirat David, and
as רש״י Rashi points out there are elements of שירת דוד shirat
David which could be seen as evoking the idea of ים סוף
Yam Suf about ה׳ Hashem sending his anger towards his enemies. Okay,
so
that's seventh day.
ולמחר, U'lamachar, כל הבכור. Kol Habechor. Now this is interesting because this
ולמחר u'lamachar has to be talking about חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz and
it's still here in the Hebrew. So that's interesting. But anyway, so
the eighth day of פסח Pesach, you read כל הבכור, Kol Habechor,
which is also a common reading that we do on the חגים,
Chaggim, the reading from דברים. Devarim. And let me just point out
something about that, right? If you take a look here, where would
that appear?
Here, this is a common reading. The common reading we do the
first days of יום טוב Yom Tov. is שור כשב או עז
Shor Chashev Ve'az and the common reading that we do on the
last days of יום טוב is עשר תעשר Aser Te'aser or כל
הבכור, Kol Habechor, which is later than עשר תעשר Aser Te'aser in
the same section. It's in 11:43. Here it's in דברים. Devarim. Okay,
and if you take a look here, let's take a look at
that for a moment. People have that, right? So עשר תעשר, Aser
Te'aser, first do we have like general obligations of תרומות ומעשרות trumot
u'ma'asrot and so on. But of course all these tend to revolve
around the חגים Chaggim because the חגים Chaggim are the times of
the harvest, etc. And therefore particularly סוכות, Succos, and but other times
as well, and therefore, you know, שבועות Shavuos is the harvest, סוכות
Succos is the gathering in, and times that the תורה Torah. is
telling us about what to do with the תרומות ומעשרות, trumot u'ma'asrot,
the things that we leave to the poor when we're doing the
harvest. Okay, so you have the עשר תעשר, Aser Te'aser, you have
giving this is
the giving מעשר, ma'aser, and then you have another section of מעשר
מקצה שלוש שנים, ma'aser miktzei shalosh shanim, then you have מקצה שבע
שנים תעשה שמטה, miktzei sheva shanim ta'aseh shmita, so the whole מעשר
ma'aser and שמטה shmita and all these obligations to the poor. It's
very interesting that that is an opening to the section that we
read because again, as I said, so much of the period of
the חגים Chaggim in the תורה Torah is a time to be
concerned about the poor and about related to the harvest. כי יהיה
בך אביון מאחד אחיך באחד שעריך, Ki yihyeh becha evyon mei'achad acheicha
b'achad she'arecha, right? So you have somebody poor, you have to lend
them money. כי ימכר לך אחיך העברי, Ki yimacher lecha achicha ha'ivri,
sending out the slaves. All of these larger
agricultural societal responsibilities to the poor. That's where you start עשר תעשר.
Aser Te'aser. That's normally where you start on שבת Shabbos? when you
need a few extra עליות, aliyot, although that's huge. But anyway, then
כל הבכור Kol Habechor here on 11:44, if people are with me,
right? That starts getting us towards specifically קרבנות korbonos. of the חגים.
Chaggim. So again, you start with the, of a general bringing of
a קרבן korban and not having a מום, mum, etc. And then
שמור את חודש האביב ועשית פסח, Shemor es Chodesh Ha'aviv ve'asita Pesach,
וזבחת פסח, vezavachta Pesach, לא תאכל עליו חמץ. lo tochal alav chametz.
etc., etc. And again notice here, as opposed to פנחס, Pinchas but
similar to אמור, that even when discussing the חגים, Chaggim, it's a
much broader societal focus and not just a narrow מקדש Mikdash קרבן
מוסף Korban Mussaf type of a focus. Okay, so that's why the
שור כשב ועז, Shor Keshev Va'ez, these are the two sections אמור
and here from דברים Devarim from עשר תעשר, Aser Te'aser, which are
about the מועדים Moadim in greater length, all three of the מועדים,
Moadim, but are not in the very narrow מקדש Mikdash פנחס Pinchas
type of a focus, just a מוסף Mussaf focus. So the שור
כשב ועז Shor Keshev Va'ez tends to be first days and עשר
תעשר Aser Te'aser כל הבכור Kol Habechor tends to be the last
days. Okay, so that's what we have here. So back to the
גמרא. Gemara כל הבכור, Kol Habechor, so the last day of פסח
Pesach, we read כל הבכור, Kol Habechor, this would be in חוץ
לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. ומפטירים U'maftirim עוד היום בנוב לעמוד, Od Hayom BeNov
La'amod, this sort of Messianic vision, you know, because of פסח Pesach.
is גאולה Geulah and look forward to future גאולה Geulah as well.
Okay, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, so that's what the ברייתא beraita says
although interesting the last line seems to relate to חוץ לארץ. Chutz
La'aretz. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, האידנא Ha'idna nowadays נהג עלמא Nahag alma
למיקרי lemikrei משך תורא קדש בכספא פסל במדברא שלח בוכרא. Meshach Tora
Kadesh Bakaspa Psal Bemadbara Shelach Buchra. So this is a nice little
mnemonic. This covers all the eight days of פסח Pesach because one
extra for חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, and therefore what it is, and
this just shows you again the fluidity, it's not because of one
day to two days, this is just starting changing already from day
one. According to the ברייתא, braisa day one of פסח Pesach we
read, right, we
read what, שור כשב ועז. Shor Keshev Va'ez. But אביי Abaye says
no, you start the theme of פסח Pesach from the very beginning.
And here's what he says you read. Now the mnemonic is, here's
just first let's just tell you the way to remember the mnemonic
and then we'll talk about what each word signifies. Okay, so משך
תורא, Meshach Tora, draw for yourself an ox, of course the פסח
Pesach. is not an ox, but okay. Draw an ox, קדש בכספא,
Kadesh Bakaspa, sanctify it with money, and פסל במדברא, Psal Bemadbara, and
there was, that's a little harder, there's a פסל psal in the
מדברא midbara I guess, I don't know, and anyway שלח בוכרא Shelach
Buchra and send forth the firstborn. So פסל במדברא Psal Bemadbara could
be the עגל egel and then the, I don't know, and then
the וישלח את Vayishlach et what, פסל? Psal?
פסל, Psal, so it's the פסל psal of the פסל לוחות, Psal
Luchot, that's what it actually does mean in the פסוקים, pesukim, right.
I don't know, so that's part of the mnemonic, so because then
the שלח בוכרא, Shelach Buchra, the sending forth of the firstborn. Anyway,
so what does it refer to? So משך Meshach is משכו וקחו
לכם צאן למשפחותיכם ושחטו הפסח. Mashchu Ukchu Lachem Tzon Lemishpechoseichem Veshachatu HaPesach.
So the first day of פסח Pesach you read actually about the
command in מצרים Mitzrayim to bring the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, not
like the ברייתא Braisa had which you just read this sort of
more generic שור כשב ועז. Shor Keshev Va'ez. תורא Tora is שור
או כשב או עז, Shor o khesev o ez that's the שור
Shor one, okay. Then so we, so the first day though of
פסח we want to start with a specific פסח theme, not with
the generic שור כשב ועז, Shor Keshev Va'ez, okay. So that's, so
that's שור, Shor, that's the second one. קדש Kadesh is קדש לי
כל בכור, Kadesh Li Kol Bechor, which is also in מצרים Mitzrayim
and it gets to, you know, the firstborn and your son will
ask what's this and you tell him, you know, God took us
out of מצרים, Mitzrayim, etc. בכספא Bakaspa is אם כסף תלוה את
עמי, Im Kesef Talveh et Ami, that's from the middle of משפטים
Mishpatim and that's where the תורה Torah, just briefly dwells on the
שלוש רגלים Shalosh Regalim all together. Then you have פסל, Psal, פסל
לך שני לוחות אבנים כראשונים, Psal Lecha Shnei Luchos Avanim Karishonim, the
second לוחות, luchot, which also briefly has a section on the שלוש
רגלים. Shalosh Regalim. במדברא Bemadbara is במדבר סיני Bemidbar Sinai which is
in בהעלותך, Behaalotcha, which is פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. שלח Shelach is
ויהי בשלח פרעה את העם, Vayehi Beshalach Paro et Ha'am, so that's,
that's the first seventh day of פסח, right, where we do the
שירת הים. Shirat Hayam. And בוכרא, Buchra, that's כל הבכור Kol Habechor
like we said that you do כל הבכור Kol Habechor to the
end. So basically it switched a little bit of the middle days,
but it also more significantly switched the first day that you do
not start with the generic שור כשב, Shor Kesev, but you start
with the very specific משכו וקחו לכם צאן. Mashchu Ukchu Lachem Tzon.
Okay, and this is something we're going to see as well where
the ברייתא has a more sort of generic beginning of these ימים
טובים, the גמרא Gemara tends more to something very more specific about
the חג, Chag, yes.
Why is he saying this in Aramaic rather than Hebrew? For a
cite of biblical source you'd use Hebrew.
Oh, because it's a mnemonic. I mean, so it's like a way
of remembering, so you do it in the vernacular. Okay,
משך שור, Meshach Shor, I don't know, it just somehow wouldn't work.
Okay, anyway, okay, so that's, so that's what we do, so again
what we've covered is the הפטרות. Haftarot. We know what the הפטרות
Haftarot are, יהושע Yehoshua. and the פסח of יהושע, the פסח in
יאשיהו, Yoshiyahu, and then שירת דוד, Shirat David, and then עוד היום
בנוב לעמוד, Od Hayom BeNov La'amod, the future Messianic vision. What we've
not discussed here, we're going to discuss at the very bottom of
the עמוד is what do you do for the הפטרות Haftarot on
שבת? Shabbos, Okay, that we'll get to. Okay, and what we also
have is all the days mapped out, different sections relating to the
פסח, some very specific, some the שלוש רגלים, Shalosh Regalim, again starting
with the very specific one about משכו וקחו לכם צאן. Mashchu Ukchu
Lachem Tzon. משכו וקחו לכם Mishchu u-kechu lachem and also the points
that I'm telling you about that שור או כשב או עז shor
o chesev o ez tends to be at the beginning and כל
בכור Kol bechor tends to be at the end, and both of
those are sections in the תורה that deal with all the רגלים,
Regalim, but with more than just a very narrow מקדש focus. Okay,
now the
גמרא Gemara continues. בשבועות, Be-Shavuos, בעצרת, ba-Atzeret, on שבועות, Shavuos. שבע שבועות,
Shiva Shavuot, you read about the, you know, counting the seven weeks,
but again that's very much seven weeks and bringing a קרבן. korban.
ומפטירים u-maftirin
in חבקוק, Chabakuk, and the הפטורה Haftorah is חבקוק, Chabakuk, which is
a הפטורה Haftorah that, which is a, which has a vision that
sort of evokes or refers to the giving of the תורה at
הר סיני, Har Sinai, a type of a mystical vision. אחרים אומרים,
Acherim omrim, others say, בחודש השלישי. ba-chodesh ha-shlishi. No, you actually read
the story of מתן תורה Matan Torah at הר סיני, Har Sinai,
right? That's the one that not just the יום טוב שבע שבועות,
Shiva Shavuot, you focus on מתן תורה Matan Torah at הר סיני,
Har Sinai, which should be of course noted that for us that's
the focus of שבועות Shavuos, and the sort of historically significant aspect,
but it's never referred to that way in the תורה. ומפטירים במרכבה,
u-maftirin be-merkavah, and the הפטורה Haftorah is from מעשה מרכבה, Ma'aseh Merkavah,
right? Which in יחזקאל, Yecheskel, which was debated before if you actually
ever read from מעשה מרכבה, Ma'aseh Merkavah, but we do, and that's
about the, and that's, and that's again, the heavens open up and
there's this divine vision, which is important because the significance of מתן
תורה Matan Torah is not just the giving of the law, but
it is the direct encounter with God that occurred, you know, the
theophany of מתן תורה. Matan Torah. So therefore, that's the, that's the
reading of the מעשה מרכבה. Ma'aseh Merkavah. Okay, so according, so that's
the debate. So that's the debate when there's only one day of
שבועות. Shavuos, And now the גמרא Gemara interjects, והאידנא דאיכא תרי יומי,
ve-haidna de-ika terei yomei, and nowadays that there's two days of שבועות,
Shavuos, עבדינן כתרווייהו, avdinan ke-tarveihu,
we do like both of them, ואיפכא, ve-ifcha, and we reverse it.
We first start with the story of מתן תורה, Matan Torah, the
בחודש השלישי ba-chodesh ha-shlishi and the מרכבה, Merkavah, and then on the
second day, we read the more generic שבע שבועות. Shiva Shavuot. And
again, this is fitting in the pattern that I mentioned to you
before, that we like to start with more specific. שבע שבועות Shiva
Shavuot is also specific, but you know, it's not the narrative, it's
not the story. So we want to really start with the punch.
I actually had a great שאלה, shayla, which was somebody,
one of my students asked me a question, I'm blanking on the
specific, but basically he's a rabbi of a, you know, he was,
he was, he was being a rabbi for a small community on
שבועות, Shavuos and they would only, we were only going to get
a מנין minyan on the second day. So the question is, which
קריאת התורה krias ha-Torah does he read on the second day if
you only have a מנין? minyan? Right? So you go, well, second
day, you read שבע שבועות. Shiva Shavuot. On the other hand, you
know, who wants to read שבע שבועות? Shiva Shavuot? If you only
have one, you want to read, you know, מתן תורה Matan Torah
at הר סיני. Har Sinai. So quite interesting how to interpret sort
of parse this גמרא. Gemara Is it saying that they're, that they're
roughly equivalent? Are they saying that because you maybe אדרבה, aderaba, because
we reverse it in order to do
הר סיני Har Sinai first, that I mean, the בחודש השלישי ba-chodesh
ha-shlishi first, that shows that that's the more important one? You know,
or do you say that since that was a יש אומרים yesh
omrim in this ברייתא and the first opinion was שבע שבועות, Shiva
Shavuot, maybe שבע שבועות Shiva Shavuot is the more important one? So
it was a very interesting question. I told him to do, and
if you read the רמב"ם, Rambam, if I remember correctly, the רמב"ם
Rambam makes it sound like the more important one is the שבע
שבועות, Shiva Shavuot, which is interesting. But other, you know, but, but
other sources do not indicate that and again, the very fact that
the גמרא Gemara goes out of its way to reverse it and
do the בחודש השלישי ba-chodesh ha-shlishi first, so that's the one I
told him to do, but it was a fascinating question. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara continues. What, do you want to? No, you'd
have to bring out other ספרי תורה, Sifrei Torah, גוללה. golela. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues. ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, on ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, בחודש השביעי, ba-chodesh ha-shevi'i, again, according to the ברייתא,
the ברייתא notice you start with just the less, you know, it's
yes, it's specific, it's בחודש השביעי, ba-chodesh ha-shevi'i, it's the פרשה Parsha
in פנחס Pinchas, about the קרבנות, korbonos but it's nothing that really
speaks to the, you know, to the significant character of the day.
You read the section in פנחס, Pinchas again, I don't know how
you're supposed to get five עליות aliyos out of that, but okay,
maybe it means that it includes that. ומפטירים, u-maftirin, and the הפטורה
Haftorah is הבן יקיר לי אפרים, Ha-ben yakir li Ephraim, which is
זכור אזכרנו עוד zachor ezkrenu od because it's a day of God
remembering us. ויש אומרים, ve-yesh omrim, and some say, again, the ויש
אומרים ve-yesh omrim is the one that gets more to the character
of the day, וה' פקד את שרה, ve-Hashem pakad et Sarah, God
remembered Sarah, which occurred on according to, you know, various traditions, on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, and also because it's about God remembering us
and remembering us for good. ומפטירים בחנה, u-maftirin be-Chana, and the הפטורה
Haftorah is חנה, Chana, which is also a very similar story to
that of שרה. Sarah. והאידנא דאיכא תרי יומי, ve-haidna de-ika terei yomei,
and today that nowadays there are two days of ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, יומא קמא יש אומרים, yoma kama yesh omrim, again notice we
start with the second opinion first. The גמרא Gemara. tends in all
of these cases, פסח, שבועות, Shavuos ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, to prefer
the קריאה kriyah at least on the first day that gets more
to the character of the day, okay, as opposed to something that's
more generic. So we start with the וה' פקד את שרה ve-Hashem
pakad et Sarah and we do הפטורה Haftorah of חנה. Chana. Now
למחר, le-machar, the next day, we don't read בחודש השביעי, Bachodesh Hashvii,
which is also still pretty generic. We read והאלוקים ניסה. ve-ha-Elokim nisa.
of Avraham, right, we read the עקידה. Akeidah.
ומפטירים U'maftirin and the הפטרה Haftarah is הבן יקיר לי אפרים Haben
yakir li Efraim because the whole idea is the זכות zechus of
the עקידה Akeidah and the ram's horn, and all of that
obviously plays a very important symbolic role. So it's quite interesting that
when it comes to ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, we don't allow for
the generic פסוקים psukim even for the second day, right? We really,
I mean, I
assume it's the weight of the יום הדין, Yom Hadin, we want
the קריאה kria to really be about the character of the day.
Yes, we associate the עקידה Akeidah with ראש השנה Rosh Hashana so
strongly today, but it's clear that that was a later...
yeah, it's
true, it's a good question where are the first sources. I mean,
the
גמרא למה, Gemara lama,
the whole גמרא gemara about... I'd have to check where the first
sources that associate the איל Ayil and the ram's horn with the
עקידה. Akeidah. Here, anyway, to associate in terms of the קריאת התורה
Krias Hatorah is late. I don't think that necessarily means the whole
association is late, but it is a good question where did that
first occur.
Well, we have בחודש השביעי, isn't that
for the קרבן, korban, right? Right. Yeah, so Michael correctly says that
we do this as מפטיר, maftir, not as the main קריאה, kria,
that we do do that as מפטיר, maftir, that is correct. Okay.
It's interesting again that the גמרא gemara. is not identifying like a
separate מפטיר, maftir, right? According to the גמרא gemara it doesn't sound
like you have a separate מפטיר. maftir. Okay, from a different section.
Okay. Now, ביום הכיפורים קוראים אחרי מות, Beyom Hakippurim korin Acharei Mos,
which makes everybody happy because there you get both the עבודה avoda
and it's very specific and it's about the nature of the day.
ומפטיר כה אמר רם ונישא, U'maftir ko amar Ram V'nisa, so says
the one that's high and almighty, and the whole section there talks
about doing
תשובה. teshuva. And we actually do? Yeah, I believe so. You can
check, pretty sure. ובמנחה קוראים בעריות. U'vemincha korin b'arayos. In the מנחה
mincha you read the after the section of the אחרי מות Acharei
Mos of the עבודה, avoda, the עריות. arayos. ומפטירים ביונה, U'maftirin b'Yonah,
and the הפטרה is יונה, Yonah, which obviously has to do with
תשובה. teshuva. What's interesting is why we read the עריות. arayos. Some
people say you read it just because it's like finishing up what
we read in the morning. רש"י Rashi tries to give a more
specific reason, if you look at רש"י Rashi five lines before the
lines get wide: שמי שיש עבירה בידו יפרוש מהם לפי שהעריות עבירה
מצויה שנפשו של אדם מחמדם ויצרו תוקפו. Shemi sheyesh aveira beyado yifrosh
mehem lefi sheha'arayos aveira metzuya shenafsho shel adam mechamdam veyitzro tokfo.
It's a very widespread sin and therefore
that's what we want to read. It is sort of very much
מעניינו של יום. me'inyano shel yom. But one also wonders whether it's
connected to the fact that it's just a continuation of the morning
reading. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan.
I've heard another theory about that. Yes? With all those list of
עריות, arayos, there's got to be, if you think you're so awful,
it's יום כיפור Yom Kippur and you're hopeless, there's at least one
thing there that you must not have done.
Okay. Well, there you go. אמר רבי יוחנן כל מקום שאתה מוצא,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan kol makom she'ata motzei, and because we quoted רם
ונישא, Ram V'nisa, we're going to diverge, we're going to have a
little bit of a break to have a little agadic statement. כל
מקום שאתה מוצא גבורתו של הקדוש ברוך הוא, Kol makom she'ata motzei
gvuraso shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu, wherever you find God's power, אתה מוצא
ענוותנותו, ata motzei anvasnuso, you find His humility. Some people say this
מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos is part of ויתן לך. Veyiten Lecha. דבר
זה כתוב בתורה ושנוי בנביאים ומשולש בכתובים, Davar zeh kasuv baTorah v'shanui
baNevi'im u'meshulash baKesuvim, written in Torah, repeated in the נביאים, Nevi'im, and
said a third time in the כתובים. Kesuvim. כתוב בתורה כי השם
אלוקיכם הוא אלוקי האלוקים ואדוני האדונים האל הגדול הגיבור והנורא אשר לא
ישא פנים ולא יקח שוחד, Kasuv baTorah ki Hashem Elokeichem hu Elokei
ha'elokim va'adonei ha'adonim ha'Eil hagadol hagibor v'hanora asher lo yisa fanim v'lo
yikach shochad, right?
God is supreme, is almighty,
transcendent, He's above everything. He's greater and mightier than it all. וכתיב
בתריה עושה משפט יתום ואלמנה ואוהב גר לתת לו לחם ושמלה. U'chsiv
basrei oseih mishpat yasom v'almana v'oheiv geir lases lo lechem v'simla. And
with being all so elevated and mighty and powerful, God lowers Himself
to take care of the meek and the powerless and the orphan
and the widow, which is clearly the sense of that פסוק, pasuk,
right? And in general, it's important, I think there's a larger message
here that so many people, unfortunately, I mean look, this problem goes
all the way back to the נביאים ראשונים Nevi'im Rishonim and so
on, how people
associate religious behavior with a type of behavior that sets them apart
from
society and the type of basic sort of moral and ethical behavior,
caring for the poor and the marginalized and the weak or whatever,
that's not religious behavior, that's just I don't know, ethics, not really
important or something. That tends to be a mindset, right? That's what
ישעיהו Yeshayahu and all the נביאים Nevi'im were complaining about at how
do you sort of do all this bringing these קרבנות Korbanot. and
you're not basically doing basic issues of justice. And I really do
think that the sense of this פסוק pasuk is here God is
separate from everything, right? So that's the sort of separatism and whatever,
and nevertheless, the way that that
power and that what expresses itself is by is not by being
different but by taking care of those who need, of those who
need. גזונטהייט. Gesundheit.
So ושנוי בנביאים, v'shanui baNevi'im, it's repeated in the נביאים, Nevi'im, כה
אמר רם ונישא שוכן עד וקדוש שמו מרום וקדוש אשכון, Koh amar
Ram V'nisa shochein ad v'kadosh shemo marom v'kadosh eshkon,
something like that. So God dwells on the most high, He's holy,
He's elevated. וכתיב בתריה ואת דכא ושפל רוח, U'chsiv basrei v'es daka
u'shfal ruach, and for the lowly and those of meek spirit, להחיות
רוח שפלים ולהחיות לב נדכאים, lehachayos ruach shfalim u'lehachayos leiv nidka'im, to
give spirit to the to those that are lowly. משולש בכתובים, Mishulash
bakesuvim, three times in the כתובים, Kesuvim, דכתיב dechsiv סלו לרוכב בערבות
ביה שמו, solu larochev baaravos be-Yah shemo, right? Goes like the, you
know, in the chariots and the, God is elevated and high, וכתיב
בתריה uchsiv basrei אבי יתומים ודיין אלמנות. avi yesomim vedayan almonos. God
takes care of the orphans and of the widows. So again, that's
because it's from the, you know, the second one is כה אמר
השם רם ונשא koh amar Hashem ram venisa that we read on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But again, I think that the message is
not just a message of God, but the message about that the
way one demonstrates the greatest sense of sanctity is not by being
separate, but by translating into how we deal with one another and
particularly those that are most, you know, defenseless and marginalized. יום טוב
הראשון של חג, Yom tov harishon shel chag, back to קריאת התורה,
krias hatorah, first day of סוכות, Succos קוראים בפרשת מועדות שבטורת כהנים.
korim baparshes moados shebetoras kohanim. Back to the generic, right? In, now
this we do more by סוכות Succos. because סוכות Succos there are
fewer passages than there are by פסח. So there's a little bit
more of the generic reading. So we read the more generic here
of אמור, of שור או כשב shor o chesev. או עז כי
יולד, that's what we read the first day of סוכות. Succos ומפטירים
הנה יום בא להשם, umastirin hineh yom ba la-Hashem,
a day is coming to God right from זכריה Zechariah which talks
in the end about both a messianic vision but also about all
the nations will recognize God and observe חג הסוכות. Chag HaSuccos. ואידנא,
V-idna,
now the גמרא gemara interjects, nowadays דאיכא תרי יומי, two days of
יום טוב, למחר מקרא נמי אחרי קרינן, l-machar mikra nami achari karinan,
which just goes to show you how much fewer passages there are
for סוכות Succos. than for פסח because the second day of סוכות
Succos. you read the same as the first. And this is what
we do. We read שור או כשב או עז two days in
a row for סוכות. Succos, מאי מפטירים? mai maftirin? And what's the
הפטרה? ויקהלו אל המלך שלמה בחג. vayikhalu el hamelech Shlomo b'chag. So
they gathered to the king שלמה Shlomo and the dedication of the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. which occurred on סוכות. Succos
Okay. So then it says ושאר כל ימי החג, v-shaar kol yimei
hachag, and the other days of סוכות, Succos, קוראים בקרבנות החג. korim
bekorbonos hachag. Again, much less sort of interesting in terms of narrative.
We read the various קרבנות Korbanos that are brought on the different
days and also that works for סוכות Succos because there are different
קרבנות Korbanos, each day, so we read the different קרבנות. Korbanos. Okay.
יום טוב האחרון, Yom tov ha-acharon, and what do we read on
the last day? קוראים כל הבכור. korim kol habechor. Again, you see
the כל הבכור kol habechor from דברים Devarim is, tends to be
applied to the last days of יום טוב. Now, and the גמרא
gemara here even spells out מצוות וחוקים ובכור. mitzvos v'chukim u'bechor. So
what, I'm about to tell you. As it points out, you read
מצוות וחוקים ובכור. mitzvos v'chukim u'bechor. You read it from the, from
the beginning, you read it from, you know,
עשר תעשר aser t'aser and not from כל הבכור kol habechor because
you want to get in all of the various מצוות mitzvos and
the laws and then, of course, the part of כל הבכור. kol
habechor. Now why is this? You look at רש"י, Rashi, and this
is sort of part of the point I was telling you about
why we start a little bit earlier both in, you know, well
here in עשר תעשר aser t'aser and earlier in שור או כשב.
If you look at רש"י, Rashi, קוראים כל הבכור, korim kol habechor,
first wide line, אלא שמתחילין עשר תעשר ela shematchilin aser t'aser שיש
באותה פרשה מצוות וחוקים הרבה
הנהוגות בחג באותו זמן כי זמן אסיף. sheyesh b'osah parsha mitzvos v'chukim
harbe hanohegos bachag b'oso zman ki zman asif. They're needed to gather
food into their houses. So many laws apply during that time and
all of these agricultural gifts and the מעשר maaser and all these
things are so central in סוכות, Succos. right? Why the תורה constantly
emphasizes in סוכות Succos,
ושמחת אתה וביתך והלוי אשר בשעריך לא תעזבנו, v-samachta ata u-veisecha v'al
halevi asher bisharecha lo sa'azvenu, right? You have all this rejoicing and
all this grain and all this stuff. Share it, give תרומות ומעשרות,
trumos u'maasros, share it with those that are less fortunate. ועוד יש
באותה פרשה מעשר עני ומצוות מתן שתתן ופתוח תפתח והענק תעניק לעבד
עברי ושילוח חפשי והעבטנו, ve-od yesh b'osah parsha maaser ani u-mitzvas maton
shetiten u-posoach tiftach v'ha'anek ta'anik l'eved ivri v'shiluach hofshi v-ha-avtenu, all this
sense of the responsibility to those that are less fortunate which has
to be a major theme on the חגים chagim and in particular
around סוכות. Succos So if you look here at your Koren סידור
on 1143, you will see when do we read עשר תעשר? aser
t'aser? What does it say? Last day of פסח and שבועות and
שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres in diaspora, so it's the last days of
all the יום טוב. But as far as starting, do you start
by עשר תעשר, aser t'aser, do you start by כל הבכור? kol
habechor? It says, if the eighth day of פסח or the second
day of שבועות falls on שבת, Shabbos, start here. So meaning if
it's שבת, Shabbos. we
have, people may have a little bit more time, you know, seven
עליות aliyos not five עליות aliyos and not rushing home to cook,
so we start there. But otherwise we start with כל הבכור kol
habechor which is much closer to the actual קרבנות Korbanos of the
רגלים. regalim. If it falls on a weekday, start כל הבכור. kol
habechor. On שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres, start here regardless, right? So on
שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres, normally we only do the עשר תעשר aser
t'aser if it's שבת. Shabbos, We need more עליות, aliyos, people have
more time. But on last day of סוכות, Sukkot? well the second
last day, שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeres, we always start there because סוכות
Sukkot. is particularly the time where these מצוות mitzvos apply and where
we need to hear the message and that sense of responsibility. So
that's why the משנה here, the ברייתא here specifically, before it mentioned
כל הבכור kol habechor as well, but here specifically it says מצוות
וחוקים ובכור mitzvos v'chukim u'bechor to tell you you do it starting
from עשר תעשר. aser t'aser. You do the whole section on שמיני
עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. Okay. Back to the גמרא. gemara ומפטירים ויהי ככלות
שלמה. umastirin v'hi kechalos Shlomo. And then we get to another section
of the dedication. dedication of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. This section
is we really read all various sections of the שלמה's Shlomo dedication
of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, There are two big פרקים prakim
in מלכים, Melachim, but this section ויהי ככלות שלמה vayehi kichalot Shlomo
it's sort of towards the end and talks about he finished the
whole dedication and then it says וביום השמיני שלח את העם. uvayom
hashmini shilach et ha'am. On the eighth day he sent the people
home. So it's a question, does that mean the eighth day שמיני
עצרת, Shmini Atzeret, or was that the eighth day
after סוכות? Sukkot But nevertheless the mention of the eighth day connects
to שמיני עצרת. Shmini Atzeret. Okay, and that's all this happens on
סוכות. Succos, Okay. למחר, lemachar, and the reason why
we do for the first two days the same thing is you
say there's just not enough to go around?
I think so basically. למחר, lemachar, there's not just as many interesting
passages on סוכות Succos. as there are by פסח. למחר, lemachar, the
next day, קורין וזאת הברכה. korin vezot haberacha. So this is again
now although it's in Hebrew clearly we're talking here the in חוץ
לארץ. Chutz La'aretz. You read וזאת הברכה Vezot Haberacha ומפטירים ויעמוד שלמה
umaftirin vaya'amod Shlomo
and שלמה Shlomo stood and again from another passage from the תפילה
tefillah that he gave at the dedication of the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash, Now of course we all know that that's what we read
on שמחת תורה, Simchat Torah, right? So if you take a look
at תוספות, Tosafot he says
למחר קורין וזאת הברכה ומפטיר ויעמוד שלמה lemachar korin vezot haberacha umaftir
vaya'amod Shlomo ויש מקומות שנהגו להפטיר בויהי אחרי מות משה, veyesh mekomot
shenahagu lehaftir bevayehi acharei mot Moshe, which is what you do, right?
After the death of משה Moshe you continue it and it's a
reference to the death of משה Moshe and it's the beginning of
the time of יהושע. And it's the whole transition. He says ושיבוש
הוא. veshibush hu. That's a corruption. שהרי הש"ס אינו אומר כן. sheharei
hashas eino omer ken. ויש אומרים שרב האי גאון תיקן לומר ויהי
אחרי מות משה veyesh omrim sherav Hai Gaon tikein lomar vayehi acharei
mot Moshe אבל אינם יודעים הסברא מאי שינה סדר הש"ס ותקנה של
רב האי. aval einam yodim hasvara mai shina seder hashas vetakana shel
Rav Hai. But why is he changing what the גמרא gemara says?
So
of course it's quite interesting because we're going to see a later
תוספות Tosafot completely acknowledges that practices have changed and evolved from the
time of the גמרא. gemara And the גמרא Gemara itself recognizes that
there has been a change, right? It's not like the גמרא Gemara
is saying we were מתקן metakein it should be this instead of
that. האידנא נהוג. ha'idna nahog. Right, it's almost reflecting on a normal
natural evolution and change, not like some rabbis were מתקן. metakein. That
these things had a certain fluidity to them and the practices changed.
So the reality is is that in a number of places the
reading and particularly the הפטרות haftarot that we do differ from what
you find in the גמרא Gemara from מסכת סופרים Masechet Sofrim and
that these things and as we see in our גמרא Gemara and
it's funny that תוספות Tosafot here gets so upset because we'll see
a תוספות Tosafot in a few minutes that is not at all
upset that these things were evolving and were changing. So
and that's clearly indicated by the גמרא Gemara which the sort of
האידנא נהוג ha'idna nahog referring to what the practice has become.
Obviously we were saying like or the day before whatever we were
saying like you do six עליות aliyot and then the seventh or
we don't do any of that either. We do it as a
מפטיר, maftir, we do it as a מפטיר maftir instead of the
seventh עליה. aliyah. All that other stuff they were saying.
Right. So there's ways we but that's not so bad that you
could say the גמרא Gemara said it so we want to incorporate
it. It's very different when you completely switch it out for something
else. Okay so that's in שמחת תורה. Simchat Torah. אמר רב הונא
אמר רב שבת שחלה להיות בחולו של מועד. amar Rav Huna amar
Rav Shabbat shechala lihyot becholo shel mo'ed. So that we covered all
the מועד. mo'ed. Now we have to deal with שבת חול המועד.
Shabbat Chol Hamo'ed. So שבת שחלה להיות בחולו של מועד Shabbat shechala
lihyot becholo shel mo'ed בין בפסח בין בסוכות, bein bePesach bein beSukkot,
מקרא קרינא. mikra karina. What do we read? ראה אתה אומר אלי,
re'eh ata omer elai, right? החלק הזה hachelek hazeh ואתה דלה
הנחני ve'ata dalah hanchani and which is also about towards the second
לוחות luchot and again refers to the שלש רגלים shalosh regalim in
a pretty brief way. Okay. So we do that for both. אפורי,
aftorei, what of the הפטרה? בפסח העצמות היבשות, bePesach ha'atzamot hayaveshot, the
dry bones, because those were believed by חז"ל to be the people
that tried to leave מצרים Mitzrayim too early. Anyway, but it speaks
about
about revival of the dead in a sense that that sort of
גאולה geulah is symbolic about that whole again that whole sort of
messianic vision and those that are literally and figuratively dead coming to
life. ובסוכות ביום בוא גוג, u'beSukkot beyom bo Gog, which is again
the this גוג ומגוג Gog u'Magog type of a messianic vision. So
that's more about the war of course and the פסח theme is
more
about the redemption aspect of it. But both of those with a
with more of this sort of future messianic vision. בחנוכה בנשיאים beChanukah
be'nesiyim and that's what we do. בחנוכה בנשיאים. beChanukah be'nesiyim. On חנוכה
Chanukah we do the נשיאים nesiyim because they have it's חנוכת הבית
Chanukat Habayit and there's enough of them to cover the eight days
of חנוכה. Chanukah. ומפטירנא בנרות דזכריה u'maftirina benerot de'Zecharya
and the הפטרה is with the vision of the מנורה menorah in
זכריה. Zecharya. ואי מקלע שתי שבתות ve'ei mikla shetei shabbatot
and if there's two שבתות shabbatot in חנוכה, Chanukah, קמייתא בנרות דזכריה,
kameita benerot de'Zecharya, the first one in the מנורה menorah of זכריה,
Zecharya, בתרייתא batraita and the second one בנרות שלמה, benerot Shlomo, in
the vision in the מנורה menorah that שלמה Shlomo built. Do we
ever do that? I don't think so.
There's rarely you'll get two.
Yeah alright I just don't remember it in recent history. Okay. בפורים
ויבוא עמלק. bePurim vayavo Amalek. פורים Purim we read ויבוא עמלק vayavo
Amalek and now we stop mentioning הפטרות haftarot because it's no longer
a חג Chag, or שבת, Shabbos, so no more הפטרות. Haftarot. וראש
חודש Verosh Chodesh and ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, ראשי חדשיכם, Roshei Chodshachem,
the section in, right, the, you know, in פנחס about ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh, the straight קרבנות. Korbanos, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh שיחול להיות
בשבת, Sheyachol Lihyot BeShabbos, now if ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls out
on שבת, Shabbos, okay, מפטירים Maftirin
and—so it doesn't exactly tell you when you do the ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh reading of ראשי חדשיכם, Roshei Chodshachem, right? We do that
for מפטיר. Maftir. Interestingly it doesn't directly refer to that, it just
goes straight to the הפטרה. והיה מדי חודש בחודשו. Vehaya Midei Chodesh
Bechodsho. Okay, which is where—right, which is what we do. Right? השמים
כסאי, Hashamayim Kisi, which has—which has a פסוק Pasuk of every חודש
בחודשו. Chodesh Bechodsho. You know it should be mentioned that in the
נביאים, Neviim, the idea of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh as a חג,
Chag. we mentioned this last time when the גמרא Gemara said why
do you have four עליות Aliyot on ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh? And
one ברייתא said because it was a little bit of a איסור
מלאכה, Issur Melacha, which was very strange, you know we quoted the
מדרש Midrash about the women and so on. But anyway other ברייתא—the
other ברייתא gave a different reason for that. But ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh certainly in the time of the נביאים Neviim was a more
widely celebrated type of a—of a חג, you know, like you have,
you know, מדוע את הלכת אליו היום לא חודש ולא שבת, Madua
At Holeches Elav Hayom Lo Chodesh Velo Shabbos, חדשיכם ומועדיכם שנאה נפשי,
Chodsheichem Umoadeichem Sanea Nafshi, which we just had, right? So here והיה
מדי חודש בחודשו מדי שבת בשבתו. Vehaya Midei Chodesh Bechodsho Midei Shabbos
Beshabbato. The idea of חודש ושבת Chodesh VeShabbos קרוא מקרא, Karou Mikra,
you know,
the idea that חודש Chodesh was a regular time of a holiday
and celebration is clear in the נביאים, Neviim, although we really have
lost that in terms of our—you know, our practice. So anyway here
this idea מדי חודש בחודשו מדי שבת בשבתו Midei Chodesh Bechodsho Midei
Shabbos Beshabbato speaks—doesn't just mention חודש, Chodesh, but it speaks to the
weight of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh as a type of a חג.
יבא כל בשר להשתחוות לפני Yavo Chol Basar Lehishtachavot Lefanai is when
people gather, you know, together to pray—to worship God. Okay, so that's
what we read as the הפטרה on ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. באחד
בשבת Be'echad BeShabbos if ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh falls out on a
Sunday, נהגו מפטירים Nahagu Maftirin ויאמר לו יהונתן מחר חודש. Vayomer Lo
Yehonatan Machar Chodesh.
So we read the מחר חודש. Machar Chodesh. Doesn't say what you
do when it's a two-day ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, which there are
different practices, right? Some do just—just השמים כסאי, Hashamayim Kisi, some actually
read the one פסוק Pasuk of מחר חודש Machar Chodesh as well.
Yes.
And the reason why on שבת חול המועד Shabbos Chol HaMoed was
reading ראה אתה אומר אלי Re'eh Ata Omer Elai is because the
end of it is talking about the רגלים? Regalim? Correct.
And they just
want to start from earlier just to get more of a—I believe
so, yeah. Let's go back to the תוספות Tosafot about that the—the
common practice changing. It's kind of built into the גמרא Gemara? because
it's clear that there's—the גמרא Gemara? is—is—what's the word? You know,
there's a משנה statement and then the גמרא—right. Gemara And one of
the first ones is where אביי Abaye says והאידנא נהוג עלמא. Vahidna
Nahug Alma. So it's built right in.
Yeah, I was mentioning that. Yeah, exactly, I was mentioning that, that
the גמרא Gemara itself kind of paves
the way
for—I
know, I know, that's what I was saying, that the phrasing in
the גמרא Gemara is not just a different פסק, Psak, it's exactly
as you said, והאידנא נהוג עלמא. Vahidna Nahug Alma. Right,
A, nowadays, meaning things change, and B, נהוג עלמא, Nahug Alma, they're
changing not because of some edict, they're changing because the practices have
changed. So it is very strange and we're about to turn the
page and see another תוספות Tosafot that completely accepts it.
So it's not—I'm saying it's not strange at all because the גמרא
Gemara.
kind of—no, it's not strange that we've changed. It's strange that תוספות
Tosafot has a problem with it. That's what I'm saying. Why is
תוספות Tosafot all up in arms? Who allowed רבנו האי Rabbeinu Hai
to change what was in the גמרא? Gemara. No, the fact that
it's different isn't the problem, the problem is that תוספות Tosafot is
up in arms about it. All right, let's take a look. אמר
רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, says רב הונא, Rav Huna,
ראש חודש אב שחל להיות בשבת, Rosh Chodesh Av Shechal Lihyot BeShabbos,
if ראש חודש אב Rosh Chodesh Av falls out on שבת, Shabbos.
מפטירים חדשיכם ומועדיכם שנאה נפשי היו עלי לטרח. Maftirin Chodsheichem Umoadeichem Sanea
Nafshi Hayu Alai Latorach. Because
that's about ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, חדשיכם Chodsheichem and שנאה נפשי, Sanea
Nafshi, and it's about, you know, the castigating the people and the
impending doom. And therefore you would read that on שבת. Shabbos Of
course what פרשה parsha is that part of? It's part of חזון,
Chazon, right, חזון ישעיהו בן אמוץ. Chazon Yeshayahu Ben Amotz. We don't
read it on—exactly. So we'll look at that תוספות Tosfos. in a
minute, which recognizes that things do change. והיו עלי לטרח. Vehayu Alai
Latorach. מאי היו עלי לטרח? Mai Hayu Alai Latorach? Now a little
אגדתא. Agaddata. What does it mean that they were a burden to
me? אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא לא דיין לרשעים שהם חוטאים לפני אלא
שמטריחים אותי לידע איזה גזירה קשה אביא עליהם. Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu
Lo Dayan Lereshaim Shehem Chotim Lefanai Ela Shematrichim Osi Leida Eizeh Gezeira
Kasha Avi Aleihem. It's not enough that they sin before me, but
they make me have to now go off to all this effort
to figure out what's the proper punishment. Fascinating. Anyway, okay, so you've
given me all this צרות. Tzaros. בתשעה באב גופיה מאי מפטירים? BeTisha
B'Av Gufay Mai Maftirin? What do you say on תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av itself? Interestingly, completely skips over the שבת Shabbos preceding תשעה באב.
Tisha B'Av. Only has a special קריאה Kriya for שבת ראש חודש
Shabbos Rosh Chodesh as the day itself has weight because it's ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. There does not have—it does not have a specific—yes,
yes, yes. There does not have a specific
idea of the שבת Shabbos preceding תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. So מאי
מפטירים Mai Maftirin on תשעה באב? Tisha B'Av? אמר רב איכה היתה
לזונה, Amar Rav Eicha Haysa Lezona, which is also from ישעיהו, Yeshayahu,
from—from חזון. Chazon. So yeah, it's from the same section. מקרא מאי?
Mikra Mai? What—what do we read for the קריאה? Kriya?
תניא אם לא תשמעו לי Tanya Im Lo Tishme'u Li by the
ברכות וקללות Brachos U'klalos in—in בחוקותי, Bechukosai, because again we mentioned that
before, on תעניות Taaniyos you do ברכות וקללות, Brachos U'klalos, which is
not what we— The basically, look, this is the consequence of your
sins. ונתן בר יוסף אומר, V'Noson Bar Yosef Omer, עד אנה ינאצוני
העם הזה, Ad Ana Yin'atzuni Ha'Am Hazeh, because it's about the מרגלים,
Meraglim, because תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is the מרגלים. Meraglim. ויש אומרים
עד מתי לעדה הרעה הזאת, V'yesh Omrim Ad Masai La'eidah Ha'Ra'ah Hazos,
which is also the מרגלים. Meraglim. So that at least making it
a little more linking it in a particular narrative which we've seen
before, the desire to link it in a narrative. אמר אביי, Amar
Abaye, האידנא, Ha-idna, nowadays נהגו עלמא Nahagu Alma למיקרי Lemikri כי תוליד
בנים ובני בנים, Ki Tolid Banim Uvnei Vanim, right,
which is about when you're go, about punishment for sin but more
specifically about exile from the land, and it's certainly not as harsh
as the whole ברכות Brachos and קללות, Klalos, and that's the reading
we do. מפטרינן Maftirinan אסף אסיפם, Asof Asifeim, right, which is also
about a, you know, about sort of a very bleak vision of
what it looks like, you know, what the exile and the destruction
of the land will look like in the wake of the exile.
And that is our practice. But of course the interesting thing is
this does not have the three of פורעניות Pur'anyos and the seven
of נחמתא, Nechemta, and it doesn't have חזון Chazon and it doesn't
have נחמו. Nachamu. So take a look at תוספות. Tosfos ראש חודש
אב שחל להיות בשבת, Rosh Chodesh Av Shechal Lihyos B'Shabbos, ואין אנו
עושין כן. V'ein Anu Osin Kein. We don't do this. אלא מפטיר
בירמיה. Ela Maftir Bi'Yirmiyah.
The שבת Shabbos that sort of, you know, assuming that it's, that
it's
before the שבת Shabbos before תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, we do the,
we do from ירמיה Yirmiyah שמעו דבר ה׳. Shim'u D'var Hashem. ובשבת
שלפני
תשעה באב, U'v'shabbos Shelifnei Tisha B'Av, the one immediately preceding תשעה באב,
Tisha B'Av, חזון ישעיהו. Chazon Yeshayahu. והטעם, V'ha-taam, how do we explain
why we do different than the גמרא? Gemara לפי שאנו נוהגים על
פי הפסיקתא. Lefi She'anu Nohagim Al Pi HaPsikta. Now here maybe it's
okay to change from the גמרא Gemara because we've got another source,
the פסיקתא. Psikta. לומר דג׳ דפורעניות קודם תשעה באב, Lomar DeGimmel D'Pur'anyos
Kodem Tisha B'Av, to say the three of פורעניות. Pur'anyos. אלו הן:
Elu Hein: דברי ירמיהו, Divrei Yirmiyahu, שמעו דבר ה׳, Shim'u D'var Hashem,
וחזון ישעיהו. V'Chazon Yeshayahu. ובתר תשעה באב, U'basar Tisha B'Av,
and after תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, שבע דנחמתא, Sheva D'Nechemta, the seven
הפטרות Haftaros of נחמה. Nechamah. ותרתי דתיובתא, V'tartei D'Tiyufta, and the two
of תשובה. Teshuvah. So what are those? ואלו הן: V'elu Hein: נחמו
נחמו, Nachamu Nachamu, ותאמר ציון, Vatomer Tzion, עניה סערה, Aniyah So'arah, לבדה,
Levadah, meaning with whatever, אנכי אנכי, Anochi Anochi, רני עקרה, Rani Akarah,
קומי אורי כי בא אורך, Kumi Ori Ki Va Orech, שוש אשיש,
Sos Asis, and those are the seven of נחמה, Nechamah, and then
דרשו ה׳ בהמצאו Dirshu Hashem Behimatzo and שובה ישראל, Shuva Yisrael, which
is שבת שובה. Shabbos Shuva. Okay, and then he goes on and
then says הסדר זה מתחיל בפנחס, Haseder Zeh Matchil B'Pinchas, ta da
da, and he goes on like, and he goes on with the
details about how it works out when there's a שבת between יום
כיפור Yom Kippur and סוכות, etcetera. Now if you keep on looking,
he says the line starts לא ישתנה לעולם. Lo Yishtaneh L'Olam. It's,
I don't know where to tell you it is. About 20 lines
down in the line, המנהג לא ישתנה לעולם על פי הפסיקתא. HaMinhag
Lo Yishtaneh L'Olam Al Pi HaPsikta.
We do it based on the פסיקתא. Psikta. So maybe he's happier
with this change because at least it has a literary source as
opposed to the other one that does not. וכן פירש רבינו תם,
V'chein Peirush Rabbeinu Tam, ולא כדברי רבא החובל, V'lo K'divrei Rava HaChovel,
whoever that was, הופך ומבלבל Hofeich Umivabel לומר שובה קודם כיפור ושוש
אשיש, Lomar Shuva Kodem Kippur V'Sos Asis, etcetera, etcetera. Okay, and then
he goes on with various types, you know, with various related discussions.
But anyway, what's fascinating is,
oh, and I'll tell you one other change he has at the
end. He says like this: וכן פירש הרב אליעזר ממיץ, V'chein Peirush
HaRav Eliezer MiMetz, ולכן אנו מפטירים שמעו דבר ה׳. V'lachein Anu Maftirin
Shim'u D'var Hashem. וכן אנו נוהגים על פי מסכת סופרים V'chein Anu
Nohagim Al Pi Maseches Soferim שאנו קורין, She'anu Korin, the last two
lines here, ויחל בתעניות, Vayeichal B'taanios, ובמתניתין אמרינן U'v'Masnisin Amrinan שקורין ברכות
וקללות. Shekorin Brachos U'klalos.
Okay, there's another major change, right? What do we read on תענית?
Taanis? We read ויחל, Vayeichal, the משנה says ברכות וקללות. Brachos U'klalos.
So here תוספות Tosfos acknowledges some significant changes, but he's more at
peace with them because he has a literary source. מסכת סופרים, Maseches
Soferim, פסיקתא, Psikta, as opposed to just סתם Stam saying the practice
has evolved, which the גמרא Gemara accepts, but תוספות Tosfos at least
wants there to be some type of a literary source, you know,
that gives authority to that type of a change. Since anyway, but
the גמרא Gemara does not know about the three preceding תשעה באב,
Tisha B'Av, it does not know the שבע דנחמתא, Sheva D'Nechemta, but
that is our practice. Since we're talking about mnemonics, I'll just tell
you a mnemonic about the שבע דנחמתא, Sheva D'Nechemta, which is, which
is to remember, to remember what we do, right? So it's נחמו
נחמו עמי, Nachamu Nachamu Ami, right, so אמר אלהיכם. Amar Elokeichem. So
God is speaking to the נביאים Nevi'im and says, give them נחמה.
Nechamah. So the נביאים Nevi'im answer and they say, עניה סערה לא
נוחמה. Aniyah So'arah Lo Nuchamah. This, the כנסת ישראל Knesses Yisrael is
not refers to נחמה Nechamah because you're telling, because you're not doing
it yourself, you want us to be your messengers, they want to
hear it straight from you. So then the response is, what's the
response? אנכי אנכי הוא מנחמכם. Anochi Anochi Hu Menachemchem. Fine, I'll do
it myself. Oh, you'll do it yourself? Then רני עקרה, Rani Akarah,
now she's very happy, שוש אשיש בה׳, Sos Asis B'Hashem, קומי אורי
כי בא אורך, Kumi Ori Ki Va Orech, etcetera. All right, anyway,
so that is not in the גמרא. Again, what's interesting is תוספות
Tosfos is very bothered when there's a change without a written source.
He's happier when there's a change with a written source, but these
things are definitely not fixed and have undergone some change and fluidity.
The שבע דנחמתא Sheva D'Nechemta is from the פסיקתא Psikta also?
Yes, yes, I'd have to check the פסיקתא, Psikta, but that is
what he thinks. And then yeah, in the middle, תוספות Tosfos has
some very strange thing about how you might wind up saying שובה
Shuva after יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, between יום כיפור Yom Kippur and
סוכות. So some of the practice that תוספות Tosafos says there is
certainly different from our practices. Okay, let's get back to the גמרא.
Okay. Okay, back to then the next section will be go pretty
quickly. We've seen it before.
There's one point when I'm reading this, it's ספרדים Sephardim actually, from
what I understand, like before, especially before תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, like
I think at מנחה, Mincha, I think, I went to check a
מחזור, Machzor, we actually read the פרשה of
האזינו, Ha'azinu, האזינו השמים ואדברה. Hazinu Hashamayim va'adaber.
Oh, very nice. Okay. All right, so now, the מעמדות Ma'amados in
מעשה בראשית, Ma'aseh Breishis, the מעמדות Ma'amados that are done in, you
know, in these groups in the cities when on a different rotation
when the כהנים are on rotation in the בית המקדש, and they
gathered together and they fast and they read from מעשה בראשית, Ma'aseh
Breishis, you know, representing sort of the people's connection to the קרבנות
Korbanos that are being brought. This is every single week. So מנא
הני מילי, minani mili, where do they get this from that they
read from מעשה בראשית? Ma'aseh Breishis? אמר רב אמי, Amar Rav Ammi,
אלמלא מעמדות לא נתקיימו שמים וארץ. ilmalei Ma'amados lo niskaymu shamayim va'aretz.
If it weren't for the מעמדות, Ma'amados, the heavens and earth would
not continue, שנאמר, shene'emar, אם לא בריתי יומם ולילה חקות שמים וארץ
לא שמתי. im lo brisi yomam valailah chukos shamayim va'aretz lo samti.
If it were not for my covenant day and night, the laws
of heaven and earth I would not have placed. וכתיב, Vichtiv, okay,
so now what does בריתי brisi mean? Often the גמרא says that
בריתי brisi means תורה, but here it's understanding בריתי brisi meaning קרבנות,
Korbanos because they are representing the people's connection to the קרבנות. Korbanos,
So the קרבנות Korbanos, keep the heavens and earth, you know, in
their place and spinning on their axis, and therefore these people that
are connecting us to the קרבנות, Korbanos, they're reading מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh
Breishis because that is what is sustaining the acts of creation. וכתיב
ויאמר ה' אלהים במה אדע כי אירשנה, Vichtiv vayomer Hashem Elokim bamei
eda ki ireshena, אברהם Avraham says to God, what will I know
that I will inherit the land? אמר אברהם לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא,
Amar Avraham lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, רבונו של עולם, Ribbono Shel Olam,
Master of the universe, שמא חס ושלום ישראל חוטאי לפניך ואתה עושה
להם כדור המבול וכדור הפלגה, shema chas veshalom Yisrael chotei lefanecha ve'ata
ose lachem kedor hamabul vechedor haflagah, how do I know, I mean
אברהם Avraham wasn't of course doubting God's promise, he was doubting the
ability to remain worthy of God's promise. The children will sin, and
You'll punish them like the generation of the flood and of the
dispersion? אמר לו לאו, Amar lo lav, no I won't do it.
אמר לפניו רבונו של עולם במה אדע? Amar lefanav Ribbono Shel Olam
bamei eda? How will I know? Now again the גמרא is not
reading this as, you know, how I know you're telling me the
truth, but what is going to make sure that that's not going
to happen? Like what are they going to do to merit that?
אמר לו, Amar lo, so God said to him, קחה
לי עגלה משולשת, kcha li egla meshuleshet, the קרבנות Korbanos will do
it, the bringing of the קרבנות Korbanos, will keep them in my
favor. אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, אברהם Avraham said to God, רבונו של
עולם תינח בשעה שבית המקדש קיים בשעה שאין בית המקדש קיים מה
תהא עליהם? Ribbono Shel Olam teineh bish'at sheBeis HaMikdash kayam bish'at she'ein
Beis HaMikdash kayam mah te'ei aleihem? But what if there's no Temple?
אמר לו כבר תקנתי להם סדר קרבנות, Amar lo kvar tikanti lahem
seder korbanos, I've given them the order of the קרבנות, Korbanos. the
verses, כל זמן שקוראים בהם, kol zman shekoreim bahem, when they read
the קרבנות, Korbanos מעלה אני עליהם כאילו מקריבים לפני קרבן ומוחל אני
על כל עונותיהם, ma'aleh ani aleihem ke'ilu makrivim lifanai korban u'mochel ani
al kol avonoseihem, it's like they brought a קרבן Korban
and I forgive all of their sins. Now in a way it's
a little funny because this is being brought to support why we
read מעשה בראשית, Ma'aseh Breishis, but not why we read the קרבנות,
Korbanos. but think about it, when we're reading מעשה בראשית Ma'aseh Breishis
is בזמן שבית המקדש קיים, bizman sheBeis HaMikdash kayam, so the קרבנות
are keeping things going. When there's no, right, בית המקדש, what have
we just been hearing? What do we read on the מועדים? Moadim?
We read the קרבנות, so in a way it sort of ties
back into the earlier discussion of reading the קרבנות. But interesting the
פסוקים pesukim that talks about ארץ ישראל, במה אדע כי אירשנה, bamei
eda ki ireshena, the גמרא is much more generalizing it, what will
keep the people alive, what will keep sort of everything going, דור
המבול, dor hamabul, what happened in דור המבול? dor hamabul? It destroyed
the whole world. So the גמרא is making it a much more
cosmic type of an issue and that's sustained through the קרבנות or
the virtual קרבנות.
Yes, there was a very similar passage to this in תענית.
Ta'anis. Yes, that's what I said, we saw this when we dealt
with מעמדות.
Ma'amados. Are there any differences between this and this?
I think this one might be a little bit longer, I don't
know. בתעניות ברכות וקללות אין מפסיקין בקללות. Be-Tanios brachos u'klalos ein mafsikim
ba-klalos. On תעניות Tanios we read the ברכות brachos and קללות, klalos,
we've already heard on תוספות Tosafos that we actually read ויחל משה,
Vayechal Moshe, which is much nicer to read about a passage about
God forgiving our sins rather than one about the punishment of the
sins, and you do not interrupt the קללות, klalos, you do not
make an עליה aliyah and divide it into two. מנא הני מילי,
Minani mili, where do you know this from? אמר רבי חייא בר
גמדא אמר רבי אסי דאמר קרא, Amar Rabi Chiya bar Gamda amar
Rabi Assi de-amar kra, that you don't divide it. מוסר ה' בני
אל תמאס. Musar Hashem beni al tima'as. Do not despise my מוסר.
musar. So if you break it up, it's like it's maybe saying
like, oh, you know, you gotta end it in the middle. Of
course, often we think the opposite, you read it in one עליה
aliyah to get done with it so you don't have to stretch
it out. Okay. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish אמר amar לפי שאינו מן
הברכה על פורענות. lefi she-eino min habracha al puraniyos. You don't want
to make a ברכה, bracha, ברכת התורה, birchas haTorah, right, right before
and after the all this bad stuff, you don't want to say,
although כשם שמברכים על הטוב כך מברכים על הרע, ke-sheim she-mevarchim al
hatov kach mevarchim al hara, but okay, but you don't want to
make a ברכה bracha directly over it. Of course, by the way
this reflects the practice of when each עולה oleh was making the
ברכה bracha before and after, right? If you only made it at
the beginning and at the end, okay. So anyway, אלא היכי עביד,
ela heichi avid, what do you do? תנא, Tana, כשהוא מתחיל מתחיל
בפסוק שלפניהם. keshu-matchil matchil b-pasuk she-lifnehem. When you begin, you begin a
פסוק pasuk before. תוספות Tosfos points out not one פסוק pasuk before
because again you don't leave less than three פסוקים pesukim at the
end of a פרשה or whatever, anyway, you start a few
פסוקים pesukim before. וכשהוא מסיים מסיים בפסוק שלאחריהם. U-keshu-mesayem mesayem b-pasuk she-achareihem.
And when you finish, you go a פסוק, pasuk, you know, one
or two, you know, one פסוק pasuk or a few פסוקים pesukim
after, so the ברכות brachos are immediately juxtaposed, not to the קללה,
klala, but to the פסוקים pesukim that precede or follow. אמר אביי
לא שנו בקללות שבתורת כהנים *Amar Abaye lo shanu bekilelot shebeTorat Kohanim*
this idea that you don't interrupt is only the curses that are
in you know in ויקרא *Vayikra* אבל קללות שבמשנה
תורה *aval kelalot shebeMishneh Torah* the ones that are in משנה תורה
*Mishneh Torah* in כי תבוא *Ki Tavo* so פוסק *posek* that you
are allowed to interrupt. Those are not seen as harsh and therefore
you're allowed to interrupt. Why are they not as harsh? They are
longer, but מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama* הללו בלשון רבים אמורות *halalu belashon
rabbim amurot* and ומשה מפי הגבורה אמרן *u'Moshe mipi hagevura amran*. The
ones in ויקרא *Vayikra* are in the plural אם לא תשמעו לי
*im lo tishme'u li* ואם תלכו עמי בקרי *ve'im telchu imi bekari*.
So it suggests all the people are sinning and God is speaking.
God says I you know ואספתי ליסרה אתכם שבע על חטאתיכם *ve'asafti
leyasra etchem sheva al chatoteichem* I
God will punish you. So they're very harsh. It's all the people
and it's all God doing it. ומשה מפי הגבורה *u'Moshe mipi hagevura*.
Okay. ומשה מפי הגבורה *u'Moshe mipi hagevura*. אבל הללו בלשון יחיד *aval
halalu belashon yachid* those that are in כי תבוא *Ki Tavo* is
what's what's the פסוקים *psukim* in כי תבוא
*Ki Tavo*? It's בלשון יחיד
*belashon yachid*. Yeah. It says והיה אם לא תשמע *vehaya im lo
tishmah* not לא תשמעון *lo tishme'un* right? יככה השם בך *yakecha Hashem
becha* not בכם *bachem* בך בך בך יככה השם *yakecha Hashem* so
it's singular it doesn't suggest the whole people and ומשה מפי עצמו
אמרן *u'Moshe mipi atzmo amran*. He's talking in his own voice. He
now of course doesn't mean he made it up. If you look
at תוספות *Tosafot* two words תוספות *Tosafot* משה מפי עצמו *Moshe mipi
atzmo* I don't know if there's a shorter תוספות *Tosafot* on ש"ס
*Shas* וברוח הקודש *u'beruach hakodesh*. So we're not suggesting he's making it
up but he's talking in his own voice. God will do this.
Anyway it's less harsh for משה *Moshe* to say God will do
this than for God to say this is what I'm going to
do to you. So somehow because it's less harsh it's more acceptable
to break it up. לוי בר בוטי הוה קרי וקמגמגם קמיה דרב
הונא *Levi bar Buti hava kari u'kemagumgam kamei deRav Huna*. So לוי
בר בוטי *Levi bar Buti* was reading and he was like you
know קמגמגם *kemagumgam* he was hesitating he was reading it רש"י *Rashi*
says if you look at רש"י *Rashi* it's exactly the way we
read it רש"י *Rashi* says קמגמגם *kemagumgam* רש"י *Rashi* says קרא אותם
במרוצה ובקושי *kara otam bimrutza u'bekoshi* we tend to read it במרוצה
*bimrutza* very fast but like you know and he was having a
hard time getting it out. I don't know how you could do
both fast and have a hard time getting it out. Anyway but
okay clearly he was very discomforted by reading it דרב הונא *deRav
Huna* בארורות *ba'arurot* in the in the קללות *kelalot*. אמר לו *amar
lo* and רב הונא *Rav Huna* said to him אכסוף נפשך *achsof
nafshecha* like do what you want like you know don't bother you
know if you want to interrupt you don't want to be reading
this interrupt you know make a you know do do a do
break up the עליה *aliyah*. לא שנו אלא קללות שבתורת כהנים אבל
שבמשנה תורה פוסק *lo shanu ela kelalot shebeTorat Kohanim aval shebeMishneh Torah
posek*. This idea of not interrupting is only in תורת כהנים *Torat
Kohanim*. Here you can interrupt. Again not exactly clear how interrupting would
have solved his problem but okay. Anyway תניא *tanya*. We learned in
a ברייתא *braita*. Maybe he just needed a breather like it was
weighing very heavily on him. So you want to make a הפסק
*hefsek* do another עליה *aliyah* fine.
What?
He could have looked at the תוספות *Tosafot*.
Maybe that was the problem. I don't think that was the issue.
Although interestingly I'll read you a תוספות *Tosafot* we'll end with a
תוספות *Tosafot*. תניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר עזרא תיקן להם לישראל
שיהו קורין קללות שבתורת כהנים קודם עצרת ושבמשנה תורה קודם ראש השנה
*Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer Ezra tikan lahem leYisrael sheyehu korin
kelalot shebeTorat Kohanim kodem Atzeret u'shebeMishneh Torah kodem Rosh Hashanah*. That we
would get to and this roughly falls out. Yeah. We'd get to
the קללות *kelalot* the end of ויקרא *Vayikra* right around שבועות *Shavuot*
time.
Only in the one year cycle.
Right. Good point. And and the כי תבוא *Ki Tavo* before ראש
השנה *Rosh Hashanah* the קללות *kelalot* in כי תבוא *Ki Tavo*. מאי
טעמא *mai ta'ama* why? אמר אביי ואיתימא ריש לקיש *Amar Abaye ve'itayma
Resh Lakish* כדי שתכלה שנה וקללותיה *kedei shetichleh shana ve'kileloteiha* let all
the curses of the year be done with. Okay. So get done
with the קללות *kelalot* before you get to ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*.
Okay. That's the end of the year. Might as well mention it
now and wrap the you know and be done with it. Don't
mention it early. Mention it at the very end and then be
done with it. בשלמא שבמשנה תורה איכא כדי שתכלה שנה וקללותיה *Bishlama
shebeMishneh Torah ika kedei shetichleh shana ve'kileloteiha* because the year's about to
end. אלא שבתורת כהנים אטו עצרת ראש השנה היא *ela shebeTorat Kohanim
atu Atzeret Rosh Hashanah hi*? What do you mean by before שבועות
*Shavuot* end the year? Since when is עצרת *Atzeret* the beginning of
a year? In? Yes. עצרת נמי ראש השנה היא דתנן בעצרת על
פירות האילן *Atzeret nami Rosh Hashanah hi de'tnan ba'Atzeret al peirot ha'ilan*
that there's a judging of the fruit so end the previous year
of fruit beforehand mention the קללות *kelalot* and then start the new
year fresh. And by the way תוספות *Tosafot* points out we do
it so that these קללות *kelalot* are at least one שבת *Shabbos*
before the שבת *Shabbos* before ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* or before שבועות
*Shavuot* so that you actually you know enter into the new year
on a positive note. You don't juxtapose the קללות *kelalot* with the
new year. I'll end today by reading דב *Dov* you'll appreciate this.
Any בעל קורא ba'al koreh. *Baal Koreh* would appreciate this. So the
תוספות *Tosafot* at the end of קללות שבתורת כהנים *kelalot shebeTorat Kohanim*
he says
the very end ילמדנו *Yelamdenu* two lines from the bottom quoting another
sort of literary source about the קריאה *kriyah*. ילמדנו *Yelamdenu* two lines
from the bottom of the דף *daf* page in תוספות *Tosafot* on
פרשת יתרו *Parshat Yitro* אין אנו רשאי לקרוא בתורה עד שיחזור הפרשה
ג' פעמים *ein anu rashai likro baTorah ad she'yachzor haparsha gimel pe'amim*.
You're not allowed to be a בעל קורא *Baal Koreh* until you've
practiced it three times שנאמר אז ראה ויספרה הכינה וגם חקרה *shene'emar
Az ra'ah vayisperah hechinah vegam chakarah* so ויספרה הכינה וגם חקרה *vayisperah
hechinah vegam chakarah*. You have to prepare it three times, ואחרי כן
ויאמר לאדם. ואסור לסמוך על הבימה ve'assur lismoch al habimah דזמן נתינתה
מעומד. dezman netinasah me'umad. And you've got to be standing, can't be
leaning, et cetera, but I thought you'd find that interesting that תוספות
even says you have to practice three times before you can be
a בעל קורא. Right? Yeah. Exactly. Okay, see you tomorrow as we
wrap up מסכת מגילה. Masechet Megillah.
Going to have a סיום. siyum.
Bless you.