So, we pick up 22nd day of the עומר *Omer*, we pick
up on טז עמוד ב *Tetz Vav Amud Bet*, top of the
דף *daf*, middle of פרק *perek* of קדשי מזבח *Kodshei Mizbe'ach*. I
just want to repeat, because the rest of this פרק *perek* is
dealing with, not really מעילה *Me'ilah* issues, but issues of general combining,
so I just want to repeat just briefly the principle מעילה *Me'ilah*
issue that we taught at the beginning of the פרק *perek*. The
beginning of the פרק *perek* taught that you can combine מעילה *Me'ilah*
even from different קרבנות *korbanot* or even from half of a פרוטה
*prutah* of a קרבן *korban* and half of a פרוטה *prutah* from
something that belongs to the Temple treasury.
So, that is קדשי מזבח ובדק הבית מצטרפין זה עם זה mitztarpin
ze im ze. למעילה *Kodshei Mizbe'ach u-Bedek HaBayis mistarfin ze im ze
le-Me'ilah*. And that was very important because first of all, the whole
use of the פרוטה *prutah*, as I've mentioned, points us away from
a thinking of מעילה *Me'ilah* as אכילה achilah. *achilah*. It still could
be either a sense of either הנאה *hana'ah*, deriving benefit, or stealing.
But we would be more inclined, I would certainly be more inclined
to think that the stealing would be relevant primarily to בדק הבית
*Bedek HaBayis* and the inappropriate benefit, the הנאה *hana'ah*, would be appropriate
to קדשי מזבח *Kodshei Mizbe'ach* קרבנות *korbanot*, and maybe you can't combine
them. Maybe they're fundamentally different types of מעילה *Me'ilah*. The משנה mishna.
*mishnah* tells us that no, actually, it is one concept of מעילה
*Me'ilah* at least across those two different categories of קרבנות *korbanot* and
בדק הבית *Bedek HaBayis* and you can combine them. It doesn't tell
us what that primary category is, but it does tell us that
it's not limited or it's not specific to the type of קדושה
*kedusha*. And then we also had the opposition that was stated that
said the real פשט *pshat* of מעילה *Me'ilah*, whose position was that,
רבי ינאי *Rebbi Yanai*, was בדק הבית *Bedek HaBayis*, which certainly would
seem to emphasize at least that the paradigm, if it's בדק הבית
*Bedek HaBayis*, points more to this idea of גזילה *gezilah*. But again,
the key principle is that it is not linked, the type of
מעילה *Me'ilah* is not distinct for the type of קדושה *kedusha*, because
you can combine קרבנות *korbanot* and בדק הבית *Bedek HaBayis*. And we
still have this general tension or question what the primary concept of
מעילה *Me'ilah* is. Okay, and now with that, we continue to discussing
things that combine, and we had said in the משנה mishna *mishnah*
that all נבילות *neveilot* combine and all שרצים sheratzim. *sheratzim* combine. For
all נבילות *neveilot* combine, we had two possibilities. Either that means for
טומאה tumah. *tumah*, half of a כזית kezayit *kzayit* from one and
half of a כזית kezayit, *kzayit* of another. That it clearly means,
but maybe it even means for the איסור אכילה issur achila *issur
achilah*. And that led to the question of is a נבילה neveila
*neveilah*, a dead non-kosher animal, just let's say a dead חזיר *chazer*,
is it just חזיר *chazer* or is it also נבילה neveila *neveilah*?
Is there a concept of איסור חל על איסור issur chal al
issur. *issur chal al issur* play a role here? And if it's
also נבילה neveila? *neveilah*, then a half of a כזית kezayit *kzayit*
of pig and a half of a כזית kezayit? *kzayit* of a
dead cow would be מצטרף mitztaref *mitztaref* for the איסור issur *issur*
of נבילה neveila *neveilah*. So, there was a question whether the משנה
mishna, *mishnah* meant that or not. Minimally, it meant that it combines
for the issue of טומאה tumah *tumah*. And now we go on
to the second part of the משנה Mishnah. *mishnah*, which is that
a שרץ sharetz? *sheretz*, the טומאה tumah *tumah* of שרצים sheratzim *sheratzim*,
a half a שיעור shiur *shiur* and a half a שיעור shiur
*shiur* of different שרצים sheratzim, *sheratzim* combine. So, let's take a look.
Again, what does this mean? Combine for אכילה achilah, *achilah*? Combine for
טומאה tumah *tumah*? Let's take a look. So, top of טז עמוד
ב *Tetz Vav Amud Bet*, אמר רב Rav יהודה אמר רב Rav
*Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav*, אכילת שרצים achilat sheratzim לוקה עליו בכזית
be'kezayit, *achilat sheratzim lokeh alav be-kzayit*. If you eat שרצים sheratzim, *sheratzim*,
then you get lashes by eating כזית kezayit. *kzayit*. Okay, that doesn't
seem like a big חידוש *chiddush*. Normal things that are forbidden in
eating, the amount is a כזית kezayit *kzayit*.
So, even if you eat
a whole בריה *beryah* that's less than the כזית kezayit *kzayit*? Right,
there's a position about רבי אליעזר *Rebbi Eliezer* that you're לוקה *lokeh*
with a בריה *beryah*. Okay, but right, we are not dealing with
that. Correct.
The משנה Mishnah, *mishnah* says
שרצים sheratzim *sheratzim*, right, and here it says שקצים *shkatzim*. What does
it matter? Yeah, it seems to treat them interchangeably. You're right. I
mean, obviously they mean different things. שרץ sharetz, *sheretz* is crawl and
שקץ *sheketz* is more like an abominable thing. When the תורה *Torah*
speaks about the שרצים sheratzim *sheratzim* that cause טומאה tumah, *tumah*, זה
לכם הטמא בשרץ השרץ על הארץ *ze lachem hatamei basheretz hashoretz al
ha'aretz*, החלד והעכבר והצב למינהו *hacholed ve'achbar vetzev leminehu*, והאנקה והכח והלטאה
והחמט והתנשמת *veha'anaka vehako'ach vehaleta'ah vehachomet vehatinshemet*, אלה הטמאים לכם בכל השרץ
*ele hatme'im lachem bechol hasheretz*. But at the end it says שקץ
יהיו לכם *sheketz yihyu lachem*, right.
There isn't something called שקצים *shkatzim* in the תורה *Torah*, right, as
a collective.
But the משנה Mishnah?
*mishnah* does call them שקצים *shkatzim*, yeah. It's a good point. I
think for now we're assuming it's the same as שרצים shratzim *sheratzim*.
Okay, so anyway, so רב Rav *Rav* says here that it is
a כזית kazayis. *kzayit*. Michael correctly asked, isn't there sometimes a principle
about בריה *beryah*?
You know, but actually I might have answered you too quickly, because
there's a discussion about בריה *beryah*,
there's a discussion about בריה *beryah*, the מחלוקת machloket. *machlokes* about whether
by בריה *beryah* you're לוקה *lokeh* is when it doesn't have נשמה
*neshama*. No, no, no, no, no. Okay, I have to double check
about the מחלוקת machloket *machlokes* about the issue about בריה *beryah* by
מלקות malkus *malkus* whether it's דברי הכל *divrei hakol* or just a
דעת יחיד *da'as yachid*. If it is, I should double check, I
will double check that. If it is, then you could at least
say anyway we're talking about combining non-full שרצים shratzim *sheratzim*. Okay, so
bracketing the בריה *beryah* issue, Michael does raise the good point that
if you eat a whole... Michael does raise the good point that
if you eat a whole one, that could change the story. Okay,
but אכילת שרצים shratzim לוקה בפחות מכזית *achilas sheratzim loka b'fachos m'kezayis*.
But assuming either that's not the הלכה halacha *halacha* or assuming that
you're not dealing with a whole one, it's a כזית kazayis, *kezayis*.
Now, what's the reason? That should seem pretty straightforward. אכילה achilah כתיב
*achila kesiv*, it says אכילה achilah *achila*, don't eat. Okay. So, והתני
רב יוסף Rav Yosef בר חנינא קמיה דרבי יוחנן *vehasani Rav Yosef
bar Chanina kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan*, but one minute, didn't רב Rav יוסף
בר חנינא *Rav Yosef bar Chanina* teach in front of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* the following ברייתא *braisa*: והבדלתם בין הבהמה הטהורה
*vehivdaltem bein habehema hatehora*, right? We just read this a week ago,
the end of שמיני *Shemini*. You should distinguish between the טהור *tahor*
and the טמא tamei. *tamei*, the טהור *tahor* and the טמא tamei
*tamei* animal. There the word טהור *tahor* and טמא tamei. *tamei* primarily
mean kosher, non-kosher. ובין העוף הטמא לטהור *uvein haof hatamei latahor*, and
the kosher, non-kosher bird, right, because the תורה *Torah* never speaks about
about birds that are טמא tamei *tamei* in the sense of טומאה
tumah *tumah*, it speaks about them being kosher and non-kosher. Okay, and
ולא תשקצו את נפשותיכם בבהמה ובעוף *velo teshaketzu es nafshoseichem babehema uvaof*,
do not, what's the word, abominate your souls with the, with the
animals and the birds, וכל אשר תרמוש האדמה *vechol asher tirmos ha'adama*,
everything that crawls on the ground, אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא asher hivdalti
lachem le-tamei. *asher hivdalti lachem letamei*, that I separated out for you
to be טמא *tamei*. So פתח הכתוב באכילה *pasach hakatuv ba'achila*, it
starts with that type of טומאה tumah, *tumah* that means don't eat.
Now, how do you know it starts with that? So again I
would say because it speaks about עוף טמא וטהור *of tamei vesahor*,
בהמה טמאה behemah temeiah וטהורה *behema teme'ah utehora*, that the distinctions in
there פרשת שמיני *Parshas Shemini* between בהמה behemah, *behema* and עוף *of*
are about kosher, non-kosher, not about טומאה tumah? *tumah* and טהרה *tahara*
in the literal what we would call טומאה tumah. *tumah* and טהרה
*tahara*. רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* say that it's because of
ולא תשקצו את נפשותיכם *velo teshaketzu es nafshoseichem*, that נפשותיכם *nafshoseichem* meaning
like make your soul abominable which is a sense about like what
you ingest and eat and it's about sin and it's not about
טומאה tumah, *tumah*. Okay, so the first part of the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* is talking about טומאה tumah *tumah* in the sense of eating,
non-kosher. וסיים בטומאה *vesiyem b'tumah*, and it ends by טומאה tumah, *tumah*
by literal טומאה tumah, *tumah*. How do you know? Because somehow we're
saying אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא *asher hivdalti lachem letamei*, that extra פסוק
*pasuk* separated out for טמא *tamei*. תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says לטמא *letamei*
means that transmits טומאה tumah, *tumah*, or that you if eating it
you are מטמא *metamei* other people or other things, so, so therefore
that's referring to the more what we call metaphysical טומאה tumah. *tumah*.
Okay so it starts with טומאה tumah. *tumah* and it is true,
the תורה *Torah* in the end of שמיני *Shemini* uses טומאה tumah.
*tumah* interchangeably whether talking about kosher, non-kosher or whether it's talking about
what we would call טומאה tumah וטהרה *tumah vesahara*. So it says
this פסוק *pasuk* combines it all. What's the purpose of combining it
all? To tell you the following: מה טומאה tumah. בכעדשה אף אכילה
achilah, בכעדשה *ma tumah b'che'adasha af achila b'che'adasha*. To tell you that
the amount that creates טומאה tumah, *tumah* is the amount that creates,
that is forbidden to eat. Now, by animals and by like, you
know,
mammals and birds,
anyway, mammals and birds, it's a כזית kazayis *kezayis*. So it's irrelevant,
right? The כזית kazayis *kezayis* is the amount you can't eat, the
כזית kazayis. *kezayis* is the amount that causes טומאה tumah. *tumah*, it's
not a חידוש *chidush*. But it is a חידוש *chidush* by שרצים
shratzim, *sheratzim* because we say by a שרץ sharetz? *sheretz* the amount
is כעדשה ke'adasha. *k'adasha* like the size of a, of a bean,
of a... so that's very small. That causes טומאה tumah, *tumah*. And
he's saying because that amount causes טומאה tumah, *tumah*, here there's an
exception to the rule that you need a כזית kazayis, *kezayis* for
אכילה achilah, *achila*, and here the rule would be that you even
if you eat a כעדשה ke'adasha, *k'adasha*, it's true, you get lashes
for eating.
Okay, so how
do we know
from the, that
you get a כעדשה ke'adasha, *k'adasha*,
the amount for for טומאה tumah, *tumah*? Why, why was one כזית
kezayit, *kezayis* and one was עדשה *adasha*?
Well, we know the כעדשה ke'adasha. *k'adasha* because it says
there's a specific דרשה *drasha*. Well, besides just the general answer which
is it's all הלכה halacha למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*, I believe,
but if it's all הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai* then you
don't need a פסוק *pasuk* here that links the two because that
anyway is הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai*.
And
כזית kezayit *kezayis* is always assumed to be the amount that you
can't eat, right? So why is it כזית kezayit, *kezayis* for טומאה
tumah, *tumah* with in case of mammals and birds?
Yeah, so I was going to answer why it's כעדשה ke'adasha. *k'adasha*
by the others because it says, תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* brings a דרשה
*drasha*, it says מהם *meihem* and בהם *bahem*.
I don't know that somehow, somehow it understands that some of these,
that some of these rodents
begin with as the size of a lentil bean and somehow somehow
it says בהם *bahem*, them in their entirety, so the smallest size
of an entire one is a lentil bean and therefore that serves
as the paradigm.
So anyway there's that דרשה *drasha*. How do we know the other
stuff the טומאה tumah *tumah* is by a כזית *kezayis*?
I would have to check the תוספות *Tosafos* and I don't remember
what the דרשה *drasha* is.
Maybe it's like the eating but reversed, I don't know. I'd have
to check. טומאת מת *tumas meis* is a כזית *kezayis*. A lot
of those things, yeah, I don't know if we quote פסוקים *pesukim*,
a lot of the things I think just, just as a הלכה
למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai* assumption about the שיעורים *shiurim*.
Yeah, so anyway, there is a specific דרשה *drasha* by that this
is a כעדשה ke-adashah. *k'adasha* because of the assumption that at least
the smallest one of these when it begins its life starts with
the size of כעדשה ke-adashah *k'adasha*, these rodents. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says,
okay, so therefore we say that the same way מה טומאה tumah,
בכעדשה אף אכילה achilah. בכעדשה *ma tumah b'che'adasha af achila b'che'adasha*. So
now we say that it's a כעדשה ke-adashah. *k'adasha*, וקילסיה *vekilslei* רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*
praised him, Tzof, that's a great ברייתא *braisa*. And the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* here at least doesn't want to assume there's a debate of
רב Rav *Rav* and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. So how
does רב Rav *Rav* say... שרצים shratzim. goes by כזית and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that it goes by a כעדשה. ke-adashah Which
is it? So וקשיא לרב, v'kashya le'Rav, that's a contradiction to רב
Rav assuming that we're not going to be bothered by, assuming we
don't want to answer it's a מחלוקת. machloket גמרא Gemara says לא
קשיא. lo kashya. חד במיתתן וחד בחייהן. chad be'mitatan ve'chad be'chayeihen. It
depends if they're alive or dead. If they're dead, then they cause
טומאה. tumah These dead, like these are types of things which are
like a weasel, a type of a frog, a salamander, okay, these
are the things, there's eight of them the Torah says, the שמונה
שרצים. shmona sheratzim.
Yeah, it's not exactly צפרדע, tzfardaya, some frog-like thing, some amphibious type
of thing. Okay, you mean the שרץ? sharetz? The שרץ, sharetz. the
שמונה שרצים. shmona sheratzim. Okay, so these eight, these שמונה שרצים shmona
sheratzim that cause טומאה tumah
and even in the size of כעדשה, ke-adashah, but they cause טומאה
tumah when they're dead, במיתתן. be'mitatan. So if they're dead and they're
causing טומאה tumah, the size of כעדשה, ke-adashah therefore they combine, if
you eat them, you transgress when you eat the amount that causes
טומאה, tumah a כעדשה. ke-adashah. If they're alive and right now they're
not causing טומאה and you eat them alive, so since they're not
causing טומאה, it goes by the size of a כזית, so everybody
could be happy. רב Rav, says a כזית means they're alive.
So even if you eat them alive, it's a כזית?
What?
Is there אבר מן החי ever min hachai
by a שרץ? sharetz, Well, אבר מן החי ever min hachai if
you eat a whole אבר, ever, if it's בשר מן החי basar
min hachai is a כזית.
But the גמרא Gemara presumably רב Rav is talking about from the
איסור שרצים. issur sheratzim. I don't think there's אבר מן החי ever
min hachai by שרצים. shratzim, I think אבר מן החי ever min
hachai is only by animals to which there is a דין שחיטה.
din shchita.
No,
but you can't eat אבר מן החי ever min hachai from like
a camel? Is there a דין שחיטה?
din shchita? Well, that's a מחלוקת machloket if אבר מן החי ever
min hachai applies by טמאים, tme'im, but at least it's the type
of animals that there's שחיטה. shchita. There's no אבר מן החי ever
min hachai from birds, from fish. So I don't think there's אבר
מן החי ever min hachai here.
It's a good point, but I don't think it applies.
Is there נבילה neveila by a שרץ? So that would be probably
the question. See that's a good question. By the...
Why would it have נבילה neveila טומאה?
No, no, well first of all, there's the question before by, well,
is there an איסור issur. אכילה by נבילה? neveila So there's a
question before about איסור isur חל על איסור. But again, I think
the answer is the same as to Michael, which is that the
concept of נבילה neveila, and אבר מן החי ever min hachai is
only by types of animals to which like שחיטה shchita is relevant.
The Torah never speaks here, here's the evidence, the Torah never speaks
about, the only dead, these שמונה שרצים, shmona sheratzim, if they're dead
they're טמא. Other rodents that are dead, or you know, amphibians that
are dead don't cause טומאה. So there's clearly no נבילה neveila by
them. And that's why also there's clearly no אבר מן החי ever
min hachai by them. נבילה neveilah and אבר מן החי ever min
hachai is only by like birds and you know, mammals and so
on.
Okay, but those are good, yeah, very good questions.
If אבר מן החי ever min hachai doesn't apply to non-kosher animals,
that would be a leniency for non-Jews against Jews.
No, because אבר מן החי ever min hachai for non-Jews, however it
doesn't apply to Jews as well as אבר מן החי, ever min
hachai, it only applies as non-kosher animals. If somebody rips a limb
off of a pig, okay, so a non-Jew could be totally מותר
mutar and for a Jew it's, question is there אבר מן החי
ever min hachai by non-kosher animals, and for a Jew
it's pig, but it's not אבר מן החי. ever min hachai.
So a non-Jew can eat a limb from a living animal as
long as it's a non-kosher animal?
Well, that's a מחלוקת if אבר מן החי ever min hachai applies
to non-kosher animals.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara, just referred to it the other day, whether
אבר מן החי ever min hachai is נוהג בטמאים noheig be'tme'im or
not.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean there's definitely a link of אבר מן החי ever
min hachai to the idea of שחיטה, shchita, which is part of
the whole question of אבר מן החי ever min hachai by non-kosher.
Is that a leniency for non-Jews? Because if it doesn't apply, it
doesn't apply to Jews either, just the איסור of pig applies to
Jews. Okay, but those are definitely good questions. By שרצים shratzim, there
is no concept of נבילה neveilah. and you know because only the
שמונה שרצים shmona sheratzim are טמא dead, other rodents are not טמא.
There's no concept of שחיטה, shchita, right, and therefore there's no concept
of אבר מן החי. ever min hachai. But the only thing is
that there is this איסור שרצים. issur sheratzim.
But there would be a concept of בשר מן החי?
basar min hachai? No, no, if there's not a concept of שחיטה,
shchita, so they
all go together.
Yeah, yeah, if there's not a concept of נבילה, there's not a
concept of שחיטה, shchita, there's not a concept of אבר מן החי,
ever min hachai, okay, which is why there's not that concept by,
let's say fish.
Okay. So, and even if you let's say rip a limb off
of a lobster, there's not an אבר מן החי ever min hachai
idea there. So there's not an אבר מן החי, ever min hachai,
there's not a נבילה idea here. There is an idea of שרץ.
So he says when they're alive, then they're אסור assur as שרצים,
shratzim but it was very good to clarify that, not as אבר
מן החי. ever min hachai. And therefore שרצים, shratzim, but there's no
טומאה, so there it's a כזית like it normally is. If they're
dead, there's טומאה and there it's a כעדשה. ke'adashah. אמר ליה אביי,
amar lei Abaye, Abaye said back, והא רב אמתניתין קאי ומתניתין כל
השרצים קתני ve'ha Rav a'matnitin ka'i u'matnitin kol ha'sheratzim k'tanei אפילו במיתתן.
afilu be'mitatan. One minute, when רב Rav said אכילת שרצים shratzim. is
בכזית, he's going on our משנה. Mishnah And our משנה Mishnah says
all שרצים shratzim combine. And he understood that when רב Rav was
explaining our משנה, Mishnah what does it mean all שרצים shratzim combine?
It means they combine for a כזית for the איסור. אכילה. When
it comes for טומאה, they combine for כעדשה. ke'adashah But when it
comes for אכילה, they combine for a כזית. He understood that רב
Rav was going on the משנה. Mishnah. And our משנה, Mishnah, it
says שרצים shratzim. always combine, presumably it's regardless alive or dead, they
always combine. So you see you're not distinguishing between alive and dead.
Now how does he know that רב Rav. was going on the
משנה? Mishnah. Either number one he just assumed it, or if you
remember yesterday, we also had a statement of רב, Rav right? Yesterday
רב Rav said, אמר רב לא שנו אלא לענין טומאה אבל לענין
אכילה טהורים. amar Rav lo shanu ela le-inyan tumah aval le-inyan achilah
tehorim. רב Rav made another statement about are we talking about טומאה,
are we talking about אכילה by the first half of the משנה
Mishnah. about נבלה. neveilah. So we see רב Rav is commenting on
this משנה Mishnah about combining. He commented about the נבלה, neveilah, whether
it combines for טומאה, combines for eating. Here he's saying שרצים shratzim
combine for a כזית, so presumably he's explaining the משנה Mishnah that
speak about how do שרצים shratzim, combine and says when it comes
to eating, they combine for a כזית and presumably it's even dead.
So how can you say רב Rav is only talking about when
they're alive? Okay, so גמרא Gemara says, אמרי רב יוסף, amrei Rav
Yosef, so רב Rav יוסף said back to him, הא היא דיוקא
דילך. ha hi diyuka dilach. That's your way of interpreting רב. Rav
רב שמעתא בעלמא קאמר. Rav shema'ata be-alma ka-amar. I don't buy it.
I think רב Rav was just saying a statement independent of the
משנה. Mishnah. And since he was saying in the statement independent of
the משנה, Mishnah. I'll say he was only talking about live שרצים,
shratzim not dead שרצים. shratzim Some have the גרסא, girsa, if you
look at the side, some have the גרסא girsa not just that's
your דיוקא, diyuka, that's your interpretation, but הא היא דופקא דידך. ha
hi dufka didach. That's your way of slapping things together, like דבק,
devek, like glue. That's the way you juxtapose it. You say רב
Rav, is going on the משנה. Mishnah, I don't, I say רב
is talking about independent. So we actually have, and this is the
conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara is that that when it comes to
שרצים, shratzim if you're eating dead שרצים, shratzim you go by a
כעדשה ke'adashah. because that's the amount that causes טומאה. Yes.
Is this an example of רב being a תנא? Tanna?
No.
Why? No, it just means he wasn't commenting on the משנה. Mishnah
The משנה Mishnah, just says combine, right? Maybe the משנה mishna, is
talking about טומאה. It's just saying that רב's statement was not a
comment on the משנה. It's not contradicting the משנה. But when we
thought it was a comment on the משנה, that context made us
understand that he was talking about all שרצים shratzim. whether alive or
dead because the משנה is very categorical. Once we say he's not
commenting on the משנה, we're freer to say that רב's statement was
referring only to live שרצים, shratzim not to dead שרצים. shratzim, Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara is going to wrap this up.
מתיבי. meisvei. I'll ask you on this statement. Because רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan praised this, so now we're going to
go to this idea, now that we've somewhat resolved רב and רבי
יוחנן saying that there's a difference between alive or dead, we're going
to focus on this position itself that at least dead ones combine
for a
כעדשה. מתיבי. meisvei. איברים אין להם שיעור. eivarim ein lahem shiur.
There's no minimum size for a limb.
אפילו פחות מכזית נבלה פחות מכעדשה מן השרץ מטמא. afilu pachos mi-kazayis
neveilah pachos mi-ke-adashah min ha-sharetz metamei. So even if you have less
than a כזית of a נבלה neveilah or less than a כעדשה
of a שרץ, it causes טומאה. So a full limb of an
animal causes טומאה even if it's less than the minimum size. Okay,
that's טומאה. What do I care about that?
So now it goes on.
So we know that there's no אבר מן החי eiver min hachai
or בשר מן החי basar min hachai to have these שרצים shratzim
to begin with. But now we're saying in terms of טומאה, it's
the שיעור shiur is a כעדשה, but the limb is even smaller
than that then you're still... a limb of it. Correct. Exactly. Like
a leg of a millipede or something?
Exactly.
Exactly. Of course whether אבר eiver requires בשר וגידים ועצמות basar ve-gidim
va-atzamos because I think the leg of a millipede is primarily just
עצמות atzamos or something, but yes, whatever constitutes a limb, absolutely. Okay.
And this is not about אבר מן החי eiver min hachai because
it could come off even after it's dead, these are dead animals,
okay? So the limbs are important by themselves and therefore even less
than the minimum size cause טומאה. Fine. ואמר רבי יוחנן אין לוקין
עליהם אלא בכזית. ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan ein lokin aleihem ela be-kazayis. Although
they cause טומאה, you don't get מלקות malkus unless it's a כזית.
So here we're talking about dead שרצים and it sounds like that
you need a כזית, not like before you said רבי יוחנן said
you go by כעדשה when it comes to the איסור of eating.
So what's going on here? אמר
רבא במובדלים דיבר כתוב. amar Rava be-muvdalim diber kasuv. We're talking about
the מובדלים. muvdalim. What does that mean? So the end of the
פסוק says אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא. So what does that mean? So
let me just check before I tell you, just want to remind
myself how תוספות reads this exactly.
Oh, okay. So yeah, so תוספות reads it, I
mean it's a funny way to give this answer, but anyway תוספות
says like this that when רבי יוחנן said אין לוקין אלא בכזית,
ein lokin ela be-kazayis,
he's not talking about the שרצים. The שרצים you're right, רבי יוחנן
would say what he said before, that you get מלקות for a
כעדשה. Although a limb of a בהמה behemah. *behemah* causes טומאה *tumah*
by less than a כזית *kezayis*, when it comes that doesn't affect
the איסור אכילה *issur achilah*. And basically what רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan*
is saying and actually, you know, again, it's not so clear from
the words, but it's an important—but it makes sense in the larger
context. He's saying look, I compared the size of טומאה *tumah* to
the size of אכילה *achilah*. I said if you—because the איסור *issur*
of טומאה *tumah* for a שרץ *sheretz*—איסור טומאה *issur tumah* for a
שרץ *sheretz* is a כעדשה *k'adasha*, so the איסור אכילה *issur achilah*
is a כעדשה *k'adasha*. So you should say back to me, well
say the same about a בהמה *behemah*. But maybe that's a moot
point because a בהמה *behemah* both אכילה *achilah* and טומאה *tumah* is
a כזית *kezayis*. But it's not a moot point because there's a
case by בהמה *behemah* where the טומאה *tumah* is less than a
כזית *kezayis*. What's that case? A whole limb. So maybe we should
say that a whole limb of a בהמה *behemah* is also you
get מלקות *malkus* even if it's not a כזית *kezayis*. And therefore
comes along רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* to say אין לוקין אלא בכזית
*ein lokin ela bekezayis*. Not by the שרצים *sheratzim*. שרצים *sheratzim* yes,
a כעדשה *k'adasha*, I said that before. But by the בהמה *behemah*,
although I said that a limb is טומאה *tumah*, it's still not
going to be מלקות *malkus*. It's still not—it's still even when it
comes to eating a בהמה *behemah*, that's still going to be a
כזית *kezayis*. Why? So here it says במובדלים דיבר הכתוב *bimuvdalim diber
hakasuv*. And here is why בהמות behemot, *behemos* are different than שרצים
*sheratzim*. Because by שרצים *sheratzim*, the end of the פסוק *pasuk* says
אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא *asher hivdalti lachem l'tamei*. Some שרצים *sheratzim* are
טמא *tamei*, some שרצים *sheratzim* are not טמא *tamei*. Some dead שרצים
*sheratzim* are not. So within שרצים *sheratzim*, that's clearly what the end
of the פסוק *pasuk* is talking about. Some are טמא *tamei*, some
are not. So therefore when the תורה *Torah* links eating to טומאה
*tumah*, it's only talking about שרצים *sheratzim*. Okay, you get that? The
end of the פסוק *pasuk* אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא *asher hivdalti lachem
l'tamei*, only שרצים *sheratzim* have a difference that some of them cause
טומאה *tumah* and some don't. So the end of the פסוק *pasuk*
is talking about שרצים *sheratzim* and only שרצים *sheratzim* are linked eating
to טומאה *tumah*. But other things are not linked eating to טומאה
*tumah*. So when it comes to בהמה *behemah*, even if you have
a whole limb and it causes טומאה *tumah*, you will not get
מלקות *malkus*. Okay, so that's how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now answered
and now it makes a lot of sense why רב יוחנן *Rav
Yochanan* had to say this. במובדלים דיבר הכתוב *bimuvdalim diber hakasuv* because
the פסוק *pasuk* when it links טומאה *tumah* to אכילה *achilah* is
only by שרצים *sheratzim* where there's a distinction between types of שרצים
*sheratzim* and it is not by other things. So it is possible
by a בהמה *behemah* that you can get טומאה *tumah* by a
limb and not get מלקות *malkus*. מלקות *malkus* would always be by
כזית *kezayis*. Eating is not linked to טומאה *tumah* by a בהמה
*behemah*. אמר ליה אדא בר אהבה לרבא *amar leh Adda bar Ahava
le-Rava*. So אדא בר אהבה *Adda bar Ahava* said to רבא *Rava*.
אלא מעתה *ella me'atah*, if that's true, בהמה נמי לפלוג בין מובדלת
לשאינה מובדלת *behemah nami liflog bein muvdeles l'she'eina muvdeles*. So why not
by a בהמה *behemah* also distinguish between those that cause טומאה *tumah*
and those that don't cause טומאה *tumah*? Now again that doesn't exactly
or those that are distinguished and those that aren't distinguished. Now the
question does not make so much sense. Right? Yeah. So תוספות *Tosafos*
says—right. So what תוספות *Tosafos* basically says what that means is
one minute.
Yeah I mean it's a little again challenging how to read it
into the words. But the way תוספות *Tosafos* explains the question is—it
says like this. Look, I get the primary thing the פסוק *pasuk*
is talking about is שרצים *sheratzim*. And by שרצים *sheratzim* the תורה
*Torah* is making a link between
eating and טומאה *tumah*. But the same פסוק *pasuk*, it says בין
העוף הטמא לטהור *bein ha'of hatamei lat'hor*. You know, what's the whole
פסוק *pasuk*? והבדלתם בין הבהמה הטהורה לטמאה *ve'hivdaltem bein habehemah hatehorah lat'meiah*
ובין העוף הטמא לטהור *uvein ha'of hatamei lat'hor*. So even if the
end of the פסוק *pasuk* is talking about שרצים *sheratzim*, but the
whole פסוק *pasuk* is talking about everything. So let's link the הלכה
*halacha* of שרצים *sheratzim* that says that טומאה *tumah* and אכילה *achilah*
go together, let's link it to בהמה *behemah* as well. Okay, so
basically again what's going on is that רב יוחנן *Rav Yochanan* says
eating it comes to a כזית *kezayis*. Oh, didn't you say you
go by כעדשה *k'adasha*? So the answer is yes, when it comes
to שרצים *sheratzim*, that's called מובדלת *muvdeles* where the תורה *Torah* distinguishes.
Eating and טומאה *tumah* are linked, it's a כעדשה *k'adasha*. When it
comes to בהמה *behemah*, eating and טומאה *tumah* are not linked, so
you can have a whole limb and you still don't get מלקות
*malkus*, it goes by כזית *kezayis*. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying yeah, but the פסוק *pasuk* put בהמה *behemah* in the
same פסוק *pasuk* with שרצים *sheratzim*. So let's say the same way
by שרצים *sheratzim* that equation applies, it should apply to בהמה *behemah*
as well. Now how exactly to get that into these words בהמה
נמי לפלוג בין מובדלת לשאינה מובדלת *behemah nami liflog bein muvdeles l'she'eina
muvdeles* is not exactly clear. But presumably it means, you know, in
a case when it causes טומאה *tumah* and in a case when
it doesn't cause טומאה *tumah*. Anyway, why don't we apply whatever—it really
means let's apply the concept we find by שרצים *sheratzim* about at
least שרצים *sheratzim* that cause טומאה *tumah* that are מובדלת *muvdeles*. The
טומאה *tumah* and the eating is connected. Let's say the same by
the בהמה *behemah* since the פסוקים *pesukim* combine them all anyway. אמר
ליה *amar leh*, so he said back to him, כי קמקיש רחמנא
לבל תשקצו *ki kamakish rachmana l'val teshaktzu*. אבל לשיעורם לא *aval l'shiuram
lo*. No. The end of the פסוק *pasuk* says ולא תשקצו את
נפשתיכם *velo teshaktzu es nafshoseichem* בכל—what is it? What's the end of
the פסוק *pasuk*? One of the בעלי קורא *ba'alei koray* here. It's
right here. את נפשתיכם בבהמה ובעוף ובכל אשר תרמש האדמה אשר הבדלתי
לכם לטמא
*es nafshoseichem babehemah uva'of uv'chol asher tirmos ha'adamah asher hivdalti lachem l'tamei*.
So yes, it does link them all together. But it links to
tell you that there's a
לאו *lav* of
לבל תשקצו *l'val teshaktzu*. That is something that is distinct by שרצים
and doesn't apply. So what do we actually say? And the גמרא
seems to conclude that way. We have a very interesting הלכה at
the end. That by שרצים, when they are dead and it's the
eight שרצים that cause טומאה, those eight שרצים that cause טומאה, when
they're dead and cause טומאה, if you eat them, it goes by
כעדשה. Okay, and maybe presumably also if you eat a whole limb
of them, maybe it goes by a limb. That wasn't clear, but
that's quite possible if טומאה and אכילה are linked. But by other
שרצים which are אסור assur but don't cause טומאה, or by בהמות,
behemot right, which are not אשר הפרדתי לכם, asher hifdarti lachem, which
are not a distinction between... they're all בהמות are טמא that are
dead, all other things we do not link טומאה and eating and
all other things go by כזית, even if the טומאה is less
like the case of a טומאה of a limb.
Okay, I have a question
before, which was why
the כזית for בהמה, because
now we're saying,
right, although no, what you wanted to say is that they're all
linked and that it always goes by כזית, right? But the גמרא
is saying that they're not linked by בהמה.
No, I'm just formalizing that idea that they're not.
There's an assumption there that it was only by שרצים and not
by other things. Right, exactly. And now it's exactly saying that אשר
הפרדתי asher hifdarti means we're only talking about שרצים. Okay, so that
was the end about... about צירוף tzeruf for שרצים and again the
צירוף tzeruf works both for טומאה, different types of שרצים, and for
אכילה, but with this question about what is the שיעור shiur for
אכילה, does it go by כעדשה by at least these eight שרצים
that cause טומאה when they are dead, the שיעור would be less,
the שיעור would be כעדשה.
Just in my mind, because there's a מחלוקת of רב and לוי
Levi about the טהורים tehorim and טמאים temeim מצטרפין זה עם זה.
Did the גמרא resolve that?
No...
yeah, the גמרא it basically the question was just do we think
that a dead pig is also נבילה or not? And that would
be a question about whether מצטרף them and so on. Right, I'd
have to check how the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens about that. I
mean, just by going by the צית, Tzit, which isn't always the
best indicator here where the א alef is where the cross-references, it
looks like it's possible that the פסק psak is like רב, that
it does not combine for
אכילה. Right, I'm pretty sure that's the הלכה that a dead בהמה
טמאה behemah temeiah. does not have a status of נבילה. It only
has a status of בהמה טמאה. Okay, let's take a look now
at the next משנה, י"ז עמוד א, yud zayin amud aleph, top
of the page.