All
right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
Today's דף ח, Daf Chet, 15th day of the עומר, Omer, and
we start the second פרק. Perek. I was just mentioning why this
דף Daf is so small. תוספות Tosafot has all of the משניות
Mishnayot of the פרק Perek together, so he explains them all here
on the first דף, Daf, so it's going to be a short
דף. Daf. But the other thing I should mention is this discussion
why there's so many תוספות Tosafot in, and I said that תוספות
Tosafot is also doing the job half the time of being more
like a רש"י Rashi and explaining it. So I actually did some
investigation and it turns out that I was exactly wrong, I flipped,
because I had speculated that the רש"י Rashi in כריתות Keritot was
not רש"י, Rashi, and although there's a Zunz had made that claim,
it seems that nobody nowadays believes that, that they really do believe
the רש"י Rashi in כריתות Keritot is רש"י, Rashi, although that first
רש"י Rashi was a יוד, Yod, I don't know, maybe that was
a gloss. But anyway, there is not a question about that, but
in מעילה Me'ilah
there's a large scholarly opinion, you know, many many scholars have the
opinion that the רש"י Rashi in מעילה Me'ilah is not רש"י. Rashi.
And I don't think, unless I'm incorrect, that תוספות Tosafot in מעילה
Me'ilah ever quotes רש"י. Rashi. תוספות Tosafot in כריתות Keritot would often
say פירוש הקונטרס Perush HaKuntres or פירוש רש"י, Perush Rashi,
and I don't think he does it here in מעילה, Me'ilah, and
I think that could be an explanation why half of the time
תוספות Tosafot is doing the job of רש"י Rashi because maybe they
didn't really have a רש"י Rashi on this. So there are a
lot of scholars that believe that the רש"י Rashi on מעילה Me'ilah
is not רש"י. Rashi. Anyway,
now let's take a look now at this second פרק. Perek. We
have been... the first פרק Perek a lot discussed like פסולים, Psulim,
what type of פסולים Psulim prevent something status changing, but at the
end of מעילה, Me'ilah, but at the end of the פרק Perek
we got to the normal rule. That the normal rule is, is
that when there's זריקת הדם Zrikat HaDam by קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim
it gets it out of מעילה Me'ilah the meat, and by קדשים
קלים Kodshim Kalim it brings them more into מעילה. Me'ilah. And now
the rest of this is basically very sort of apodictic, very sort
of straight law about without special cases, when how when the status
of מעילה Me'ilah changes, when the status of a קרבן Korban changes
in a normal case. So let's take a look. So we start
for an interesting reason what תוספות Tosafot decides to explain why with
a not so much of a standard קרבן, Korban, a חטאת העוף.
Chatat Ha'Of. So, חטאת העוף מולקין בה. Chatat Ha'Of Molkin Bah.
So a normal bird חטאת, Chatat, there's מעילה, Me'ilah, all right, you
sanctify it, it's קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, there's מעילה Me'ilah משהוקדשה Mishehuktasha
from the moment you sanctified it. נמלקה הוכשרה להיפסל בטבול יום ובמחוסר
כיפורים.
Nimleka huchshara le'hipasel bi-tvul
yom u-michusarei kipurim.
Now it's קדשים, Kodshim, because of קדשים Kodshim they can be, קדשים
Kodshim can become טמא Tamei and more easily or in more cases
I should say than other things. The normal rule is the following,
I'll tell you this because it's going to be the focus of
the גמרא. Gemara. The normal rule is like this: something is a
source of טומאה, Tumah, dead carcass, a man who's a זב. Zav.
That's called an אב הטומאה. Av HaTumah. The exception is a מת
Meis which is אבי אבות הטומאה, Avi Avot HaTumah, like the granddaddy
of טומאות, Tumot, and that starts even at a higher level. But
a normal level is an אב Av source of טומאה. Tumah. Touches
a person or anything, that thing becomes a ראשון, Rishon, first degree
means first degree derivative. Anything can become a ראשון. Rishon. That person
touches something else, that becomes a שני. Sheni. What can become a
שני? Sheni? Basically just food. Okay,
people, objects cannot be a שני, Sheni, don't even give me a
שני Sheni as food. Now most things stop at שני, Sheni, even
if food touches other food or whatever won't go any lower. But
when you deal with תרומה, Terumah, now if things have a certain
level of קדושה Kedusha and the more קדוש Kadosh they are the
more they can become טמא Tamei even with very derivative טומאה. Tumah.
So תרומה Terumah can become a שלישי, Shlishi, so food touching תרומה
Terumah food makes it a שלישי. Shlishi. And תרומה Terumah cannot go
down further than that, but if תרומה Terumah touches קדשים Kodshim that
can become a רביעי, Revi'i, a fourth level of טומאה, Tumah, and
then it doesn't go any further than that. Another important term is
that when something becomes טמא Tamei but can't pass it on, it's
called נפסל. Nifsal. That's a technical term which means it is טמא
Tamei and therefore if it's תרומה Terumah you can't eat it, if
it's קדשים Kodshim you can't eat it, but if it's not a
strong enough טומאה Tumah that it can go any further then it's
called it's נפסל, Nifsal, it's invalidated, you don't use the word טמא.
Tamei. So if תרומה Terumah becomes a שלישי Shlishi you wouldn't say
it's טמא, Tamei, you'd say it's נפסל. Nifsal. If קדשים Kodshim become
a רביעי Revi'i you'd say it is נפסל. Nifsal. Now a person
that has gone to the מקוה Mikvah that day and is waiting
for nightfall to become טהור Tahor or waiting for the next morning
to bring a קרבן. Korban. So if you're waiting for the nightfall
you're called a טבול יום, Tvul Yom, you've been to the מקוה
Mikvah that day. Or waiting for the קרבן Korban the next morning
which is limited number of cases, זב Zav and a זבה, Zava,
יולדת, Yoledes, and המצורע, Ha-Metzora, you are called מחוסרי כיפורים, Michusarei Kipurim,
somebody we learned that, there was a whole פרק Perek about that
in כריתות, Keritot, lacking their atonement, not really the atonement, but lacking
the קרבן Korban that will purify them. Those people
can only make, so a טבול יום Tvul Yom can only make
תרומה Terumah טמא. Tamei. It's like a שני, Sheni, in קדשים, Kodshim,
תרומה Terumah and קדשים, Kodshim, it's only like a שני. Sheni. Okay
so now while this, so that's just an important category when it
says able to become פוסל Posel by טבול יום Tvul Yom מחוסרי
כיפורים Michusarei Kipurim means had this just been חולין Chullin and these
people touched it it wouldn't have had any effect because it's like
a שני Sheni or whatever it can only work on תרומה. Terumah.
Because it's קדשים, Kodshim, they become פסול, pasul, not טמא tamei but
פסול pasul and we'll get to that. Now, what, but of course
this animal was קדשים Kodshim before it was שחוט. shachut. After it
was שחוט, shachut, there was a lot. Okay as an alive thing,
not yet considered to be ראוי rauy to become and it's you
know the other cases in later משניות mishnayot we won't get the
alive, but it'll be like a מנחה mincha whatever, but a, until
it's dead, until it's food, until at some degree is ראוי rauy
to be brought, it does not yet have that status and therefore
if some טמא tamei touched it, it would not become טמא. tamei.
So if it's נמלקה, nimlekah, once the מליקה's melikah done and it
becomes now dead and and ראוי rauy to be eaten or ראוי
rauy to be put on the מזבח mizbeach and so on, then
it could become טמא tamei and הוכשרה, huchshara, the word of הכשר,
hechsher, right הכשר hechsher is a phrase we often use with when
water touches food, right it's actually in this parsha, וכי יותן מים
על זרע, vechi yutan mayim al zera, וכי יותן מים על זרע
vechi yutan mayim al zera or whatever the passuk is, anyway וכי
יותן מים על זרע, vechi yutan mayim al zera, ונפל מנבלתם עליו
טמא הוא לכם, venafal minivaltam alav tamei hu lachem, anyway, וכי יותן
מים על זרע vechi yutan mayim al zera
anyway, so that when water or liquids touch food, they become הוכשר,
huchshar, susceptible. So once this is שחוט shachut and it starts being
ראוי rauy to be eaten, ראוי rauy to be put on the
מזבח, mizbeach, no longer alive animal, it's הוכשר, huchshar, susceptible, ליפסל בטבול
יום ובמחוסר כפורים, lehipasel b'tvul yom uv'mechusar kippurim, to become טמא tamei
or פסול pasul if a טבול יום tvul yom or somebody who
is lacking a קרבן, korban, again for a טהרה taharah process touches
it. So that's stage one even before זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. Okay,
doesn't matter, now it's now it's a question of you're being susceptible
for טומאה, tumah, not susceptibility for for being ready to be eaten.
ולינה, v'linah, now it also could become פסול pasul in לינה. linah.
What that means is תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion and תוספות
Tosafot emphasize that means the לינה linah of הדם. hadam. Now you've
caught the blood and if you wait till the next morning you
won't be able to use the דם. dam. Now it could also
mean לינה של הבשר, linah shel habasar, but the problem is that
לינה של הבשר linah shel habasar normally only the clock only starts
after זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. Now really it's hard to think of
a נפקא מינה, nafka mina, because if you haven't done זריקת הדם,
zrikat hadam, you haven't
and then you've left the דם dam over, then you have לינת
הדם linat hadam and it's פסול, pasul, but the question is like
whether the meat would actually become if you if you ate the
meat would you be חייב כרת, chayav kares, would the meat be
considered
נותר, nosar, okay, as
opposed to just a regular איסור issur of eating something before the
דם dam is נזרק. nizrak.
Yes, but it's not an איסור issur of נותר. nosar. Okay, so
actually, so תוספות Tosafot emphasizes that this לינה linah is leaving the
blood over because leaving the meat over the clock really starts that
that status is only once the meat becomes fit for the מזבח
mizbeach and it's really only after זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam.
I think we even said that in the yeah, we actually said
that in the last משניות, mishnayot, לאחר זריקה, l'achar zrikah, right, it
says חייב עליו משום פיגול נותר וטמא. chayav alav mishum piggul nosar
v'tamei. Okay,
so the last משנה mishna says that you need זריקה, zrikah, you
need it to be fit for it to be eaten for the
meat or fit to be put on the מזבח mizbeach for the
meat to start to be considered if it's left over נותר nosar
and that you're חייב כרת chayav kares if you eat it. So
here where it says after שחוט shachut before הוזה, huzah, תוספות Tosafot
emphasize that the לינה linah means לינה של הדם. linah shel hadam.
Okay, הוזה דמה, huzah damah, now you sprinkle the blood. So after
שחיטה, shchita, now if you leave over the blood, you can't use
it, it can become טמא. tamei. If you sprinkle the blood, then
חייב עליו משום
פיגול נותר וטמא. chayav alav mishum piggul nosar v'tamei. Oh look, I'm
sorry, it says right here נותר, nosar, so it says לינה נותר,
linah nosar, it's a little bit, right, so it says the idea
נותר's nosar the idea of לינה, linah, you left it over it's
נותר. nosar. So here it says after זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, then
if you ate it חייב chayav for פיגול, piggul, the thought of
פיגול piggul could come earlier but it's only gets established as פיגול
piggul after זריקה zrikah and you're only if you eat it after
זריקה zrikah are you חייב chayav for post פיגול, piggul, are you
חייב כרת chayav kares or נותר nosar if the meat is left
over after זריקה zrikah are you חייב נותר chayav nosar or טמא
tamei if you're טמא tamei and you eat it, are you חייב
chayav for כרת kares if you ate it after the meat זריקת
הדם zrikat hadam the meat is fit to be eaten or the
אימורין imurin on the מזבח, mizbeach, but here okay here we're talking
about a חטאת העוף chatat ha-of so it's primarily about when the
stuff is fit to be eaten. ואין בו מעילה, v'ein bo me'ilah,
there's no מעילה, me'ilah, not at any part because under the regular
large animal there's אימורין imurin מעילה me'ilah by the אימורין, imurin, by
a bird there's no אימורין, imurin, you just a bird חטאת chatat
the כהנים kohanim eat all of it. So again what's the basic
principle? זריקת הדם zrikat hadam changes the status for מעילה me'ilah for
the stuff to then be eaten, by the bird that's all of
it. קבלת הדם kabalat hadam means that it's fit to become טמא
tamei and also לינה linah but again here לינה linah there's another
לינה linah coming up so תוספות Tosafot emphasize the לינה linah here
is for the blood, you can have לינה linah with the blood.
After זריקת הדם zrikat hadam and it's fit to be eaten or
we'll see in other cases fit to be put on the מזבח,
mizbeach, after זריקת הדם zrikat hadam then the status of פיגול נותר
וטמא piggul nosar v'tamei all apply and you're חייב כרת chayav kares
in those cases.
So we're going to ask a couple of Gemara questions, this isn't
anything new, I mean we've just
distilled it, we've had it before.
Not so clear, I mean the idea of נמלקה הוכשרה ליפסל. nimlekah
huchshrah lehipasel. Let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara does with
the הוכשרה. huchshrah. Okay, but the fact that we had it before
is not a question because it's not a chronology. These משניות mishnayot
if you ask me are probably very early משניות mishnayot and the
גמרא Gemara often has more obscure cases first and then only later
gets to some of the sort of fundamentals.
So but anyway you know let's see what they've each one. So
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. קתני הוכשרה ליפסל בטבול
יום ובמחוסר כיפורים ובלינה. Katani huchshra lipasol betvul yom umechusar kippurim uvelina.
So we learned that after the blood was caught, it's now fit
to become פסול pasul with a טבול יום tevul yom and מחוסר
כיפורים mechusar kippurim and there could be לינה lina again, I'll read
it Tosafot's way by the blood.
So ליפסל אין אבל לטמויי לא. Lipasol in aval letammuye lo. That's
the key phrase it tells you, yes it can become פסול pasul
but it cannot become טמא. tamei. So if this טבול יום tevul
yom who is a שני sheni touches it, it's פסול pasul which
means it can't be used, it's טמא tamei to the extent it
can't be used, but it's not טמא tamei meaning it can't pass
the טומאה tumah on. Now I was expecting when I was giving
my intro that you would ask me about that because I don't
get it, you said a טבול יום tevul yom was like a
שני. sheni. If he touches this קדשים, kodashim, he makes it a
שלישי. shelishi. I told you that קדשים kodashim can go up to
a רביעי. revi'i. So why are we calling it פסול? pasul? We
should call it טמא. tamei. It should be at the level of
שלישי, shelishi, right, and it should be able to pass it on
one more stage. So let's take a look, that's exactly what the
גמרא Gemara is pointing out and let's see where the גמרא Gemara
goes with this. So you're telling me at this stage it's פסול
pasul but it is not טמא. tamei.
מתניתין מני, Matnitin mani, who is our משנה mishna like? רבנן היא,
Rabbanan hi, the rabbis of the following
ברייתא, beraita, the תוספתא טהרות. Tosefta Taharot. דתניא אבא שאול אומר טבול
יום תחילה לקודש. Detanya Abba Shaul omer tevul yom techilla lekodesh. If
he touches קורבנות, korbanot, so he's considered like a ראשון. rishon. Okay,
even though normally a טבול יום tevul yom is like a שני
sheni whatever, if he touches קורבנות korbanot we're more מחמיר, machmir, we
treat him like a ראשון rishon and we say that the קורבן
korban is a שני. sheni. Again, if it's טמא tamei it means
it'll pass it on more times. Okay. רבי מאיר אומר מטמא את
הקודש ופוסל את התרומה. Rabbi Meir omer metamei et hakodesh uposel et
haterumah. No, when it comes to קודש kodesh he makes it טמא
tamei ופוסל את התרומה. uposel et haterumah. When he touches תרומה terumah
he makes it פסול. pasul. So what would mean פוסל את התרומה?
posel et haterumah? What level would תרומה terumah have? Remember, פסול pasul
means it can't go any further. So what would תרומה terumah be
if it's פסול? pasul? שלישי, shelishi, right? A תרומה terumah only goes
up to שלישי. shelishi. So פוסל את התרומה posel et haterumah it
ends there, end of the road for תרומה, terumah, it doesn't go
further than this, okay, that's פסול. pasul. So if he makes תרומה
terumah a שלישי shelishi and then he makes קדשים kodashim a שלישי,
shelishi, well by the case of קדשים kodashim you would call it
not פוסל posel but מטמא metamei because that can go one step
further to a רביעי. revi'i. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says he's
a שני sheni and therefore he makes קודש kodesh a שלישי, shelishi,
טמא. tamei. He makes תרומה terumah פסול. pasul. Okay so the חכמים
Chachamim say we treat him like a ראשון, rishon, that's, no,
the חכמים Chachamim is next thing. אבא שאול.
Abba Shaul. אבא שאול Abba Shaul said he's a ראשון, rishon, okay,
and he makes stuff into a שני. sheni. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says he's a שני, sheni, he makes it into a שלישי, shelishi,
a שלישי shelishi of תרומה terumah is called פסול pasul by קדשים
kodashim called
טמא. tamei. וחכמים אומרים כשם שהוא פוסל משקה תרומה ואוכלי תרומה, Vachachamim
omrim keshem shehu posel mashkeh terumah ve'ochlei terumah, the same way when
he touches food and drink of תרומה terumah it's פוסל, posel, he
makes it פסול pasul but not טמא tamei meaning it doesn't pass
it on, it's a שלישי. shelishi. כך הוא פוסל משקה קודש ואוכלי
קודש, Kach hu posel mashkeh kodesh ve'ochlei kodesh,
when it comes to food and drink of קורבנות korbanot he also
does not make it, he makes it פסול pasul but not טמא.
tamei. Again, טמא tamei yes meaning not a טומאה tumah that passes
on. Okay so that's a little funny then. What is he? If
he's a שני, sheni, right, then he should, I mean then he
should say like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. If he's a שלישי shelishi
he shouldn't have an effect on תרומה. terumah. So what they're saying
is, and the גמרא Gemara will say this, regardless of what you
call it. Call him a שני, sheni, fine. But nevertheless his טומאה
tumah is so residual that it can't go on two more stages.
It can only go on one more stage. The
טומאה tumah of this טבול יום, tevul yom, right, is such a
residual טומאה tumah that it will only go on to one object
and stop there. So hits תרומה terumah it's פוסל. posel. Hits קדשים
kodashim it's also פוסל posel but not מטמא, metamei, it can't go
after that קודש kodesh to affect another object. Okay so you have
a three-way debate of how to look at the טומאה tumah of
a טבול יום. tevul yom. Either he's a ראשון, rishon, makes everything
a שני, sheni, or at least he makes תרומה terumah and קודש
kodesh into a שני. sheni. Maybe he's not מטמא חולין. metamei chullin.
He's not a real ראשון. rishon. If he was a real ראשון
rishon he'd be מטמא חולין. metamei chullin. But at least when he
touches תרומה terumah and קדשים kodashim he's a ראשון, rishon, he makes
everything a שני. sheni. Or he's a שני, sheni, he makes it
into a שלישי, shelishi, a שלישי shelishi of תרומה terumah is called
פסול pasul by קודש kodesh called טמא. tamei. Or whatever he is,
we'll call him a שני, sheni, but because it's so residual he
only פוסל posel things, הוא פוסל ולא מטמא. hu posel velo metamei.
And presumably it's the same by מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kippurim, yes.
So therefore our משנה mishna says פוסל, posel, and that seems to
be, who's the only one that says he's פוסל posel by קדשים?
kodashim? It's the חכמים. Chachamim. So you see our משנה mishna is
the חכמים. Chachamim. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר
רבא לאבא שאול מה לעשות בקודש שוינו רבנן לטבול יום ראשון. Amar
Rava le'Abba Shaul mah la'asot bekodesh shavinu rabbanan litevul yom rishon.
You know what? Everybody agrees to our משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna
is talking דאורייתא. de'oraita. דאורייתא, De'oraita, now we know this guy's טמא
tamei because the תורה Torah says ובא השמש וטהר, uva hashemesh vetaher,
right, or by the eating of the קורבן korban ואחר יאכל מן
הקדשים, ve'achar yokhal min hakodashim,
like it's clear that you need the sun to set or to
bring a קורבן korban to be טהור. tahor. So there clearly is
an aspect, now part you could say part just means that I
personally can't eat קורבנות. korbanot. Maybe I can't, you know, affect something
else's status if I personally can't. But they're assuming that there actually
is a תורה Torah level of this and דאורייתא de'oraita in terms
of transferring and דאורייתא de'oraita everybody would agree that you פוסל posel
תרומה terumah and קודש. kodesh. That's the דאורייתא *De'oraita* level. That's our
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. When it says to פוסל *posel* תרומה *Terumah* קדשים
kodashim *Kodashim*, it means, or קדשים kodashim *Kodashim* excuse me, you know,
to תרומה *Terumah* פוסל קדשים kodshim *posel Kodashim*, it means דאורייתא *De'oraita*.
דאורייתא *De'oraita* it's פוסל *posel*, but it doesn't go beyond that. So
when we have this debate, is he a ראשון *rishon*, is he
a שני *sheni*, what do you do? That's all the דרבנן *derabbanan*
level. But דאורייתא *De'oraita* everybody agrees to our משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. Okay?
So let's read that again. אבא שאול מעלוהו בקדשים *Abba Shaul ma’alu’hu
be’kodashim*. It's a
stringency that the Rabbis made by קרבנות korbanot. *Korbanot*. שוויוהו רבנן לטבול
יום כראשון *Shavinuhu Rabbanan l'tevul yom kerishon*. They made him like a
ראשון *rishon*. ורבי מאיר כהשני *V'Rabbi Meir ke'hasheni*. And רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* they made him like a שני *sheni*. So the positions of
אבא שאול *Abba Shaul* and רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that he's a
ראשון *rishon* or a שני *sheni*, that's all rabbinic. But our משנה
mishna *Mishnah* that says he's פוסל *posel*, that's at a דאורייתא *De'oraita*
level, and that's what our משנה mishna *Mishnah* is talking about. Now
we have to explain conceptually what does it mean that he's פוסל
*posel*, meaning either right why how could it be that he doesn't
that, you know,
if he's a שני *sheni* he should פסול pasul *pasul* תרומה *Terumah*
and be מטמא *metamei* קדשים kodshim *Kodashim*. How can you say he's
פוסל פוסל *posel posel*? So here's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains:
שוויוהו רבנן
*Shavinuhu Rabbanan* according to the Rabbis of the ברייתא braita *Baraita* כיון
דטבל *kivan detaval* once he went to the מקוה *Mikvah* קלוש טומאה
tumah *kalush tumah* his טומאה *tumah* is very weak, very residual. פסול
pasul משוי טמא tamei, לא משוי *Pasul mashvei tamei lo mashvei*. He
can only invalidate things, he can't make it so טמא tamei. *tamei*
that it can pass it on. So normally what meaning he's saying
like it's a conceptually different framework, right? Normally what stops something from
going on is it's so derivative. And therefore, you know, there's a
difference between three degrees derivative, four degrees of derivative, תרומה *Terumah* and
קדשים kodshim. *Kodashim*. Here though it's not because it's derivative. Here it
just starts off being very residual. So because it's so because it's
not so derivative it can still go to תרומה *Terumah* but because
it's so residual it stops at the next level and it doesn't
go any further. Okay so basically what we're saying is טבול יום
*tevul yom* מדאורייתא *m'de'oraita* is פוסל *posel* פסול psul *pasul* תרומה *Terumah*
and קדשים *Kodashim*, makes them unusable, makes them טמא tamei *tamei* but
it doesn't go on. Why does it not go on? Because it's
so residual after he's gone to the מקוה *Mikvah* or or before
he's brought the קרבן korban *Korban* it's so residual it doesn't go
beyond. But what's not meaningful to call a שני *sheni* or שלישי
*shelishi* or whatever because it's the same effects on תרומה *Terumah* and
קדשים *Kodashim* and it's weak effect because it's so residual. At a
דרבנן *derabbanan* level there we have a debate: אבא שאול *Abba Shaul*
wants to call it a ראשון *rishon*, say it makes everything into
a שני *sheni*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* wants to call it a
שני *sheni*, say it makes קדשים *Kodashim* into a שלישי *shelishi*. But
at a דאורייתא *De'oraita* level it's just פוסל *posel* everything and that's
our משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*.
The only time that you really have שלישי *shelishi* and רביעי *revii*
is food case right not for items.
Yeah it's all food and even within food it's only by תרומה
*Terumah* and קדשים *Kodashim*. That's why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said: אוכל
ומשקה תרומה *Ochel u'mashkeh terumah*, אוכל ומשקה קדשים *Ochel u'mashkeh kodashim*. Okay
so that's the טומאה *tumah* aspect. Now we get to what we've
been focusing on. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* skips over the לינה linah
*linah* which as we pointed out is a little bit, you know,
curious because the נותר notar *notar* is really after זריקת הדם zerikat
ha-dam. *zrikat hadam*. And now it says after זריקת הדם zerikat ha-dam,
*zrikat hadam* that's when you are חייב chayav *chayav* for פגול piggul
*piggul* נותר notar, *notar* טמא tamei *tamei* and it changes the status
of מעילה me'ilah? *me’ilah*. Everything we've been circumventing until now. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* hones in on what what was bothering you yesterday. מעילה
me'ilah הוא דליכא אבל איסורא איכא *Me’ilah hu deleka aval issura ika*.
It says after זריקת הדם zrikas hadam, *zrikat hadam* there's no מעילה
me'ilah. *me’ilah* which implies that there is still some problem. Okay now
אמאי ואמאי *amai v'amai* why is there some problem? ממונא דכהני הוא
*Mamona dekahanei hu*. After you sprinkle the blood it's not like oh
okay there's no מעילה me'ilah *me’ilah*. It's still problematic though מעילה me'ilah
*me’ilah*. What do you mean? You're supposed to eat it after you
sprinkle the blood the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* eat it. Now
again it's funny because the obvious answer it could have given and
this is what Zach was sort of asking me about the other
day is it could have given the answer the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
first gave yesterday which is it says אין בו מעילה me'ilah. *ein
bo me'ilah* because it starts by saying חטאת העוף chattat ha'of מועלין
בה *chatat ha'of mo'elin bah*. So and you know the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* gave that answer but now it doesn't seem interested in that
answer. I think that תוספות *Tosafot* tries to address that but let
me see for a minute.
To me the simplest answer forget it man, it's still אסור assur
*assur* for everyone else to eat.
Yeah could be. But anyway it sounds like it's across the board
it's somewhat problematic. Anyway
no רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafot* don't address it here they
address it before.
Okay so anyway all right so for some reason it asks that
question: why does it say that there's no מעילה me'ilah *me’ilah*? It
sounds like there's some problem. Again even though interestingly the it's really
in contrast to the idea that before זריקת הדם zrikas hadam *zrikat
hadam* there is מעילה me'ilah *me’ilah*. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* answers. אמר רבי חנינא *Amar Rabbi Chanina* the same answer
he gave yesterday: ליוצא כרבי עקיבא היא דאמר זריקה zerika מועלת ליוצא
*Leyotzei keRabbi Akiva hi de'amar zrika mo’elet leyotzei*. Yeah there's a case
where there should be a change of status of the meat and
it could still be not מותר muttar, *mutar* to be eaten. That
was the case of יוצא yotzei? *yotzei*, it was taken out of
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*. And this is according to
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that זריקה zerika *zrikah* even for meat that
was יוצא yotzei. *yotzei*, זריקה zrika. *zrikah* takes it out of the
category of מעילה Meila. *me’ilah* but nevertheless it still remains אסור assur
*assur* to be eaten. דלאו בת אכילה היא *Delav bat achila hi*,
it still remains אסור *assur* to be eaten. Fine so same thing
we said yesterday. Again it's a little bit curious why... Now we
get on to a different point which which will turn back
to our
משנה mishnah
*Mishna*. אמר הונא אמר רב Rav *Amar Huna Amar Rav*. מיצוי mitzuy,
חטאת העוף chattat ha'of אינו מעכב meakev, *Mitzuy Chatas Ha'of eino me'akev*.
So this is going to be a general statement but it's relevant
to the משנה mishna *Mishna* it's going to be obvious. The Torah
says by an עולה olah. *ola*, what do you do by an
עולה olah... *ola*? עולת העוף olat ha'of. *olas ha'of*. After you do
the מליקה melikah, *mlika* you squeeze out, squeeze, you press the thing
the neck against the side of the מזבח mizbeach. *mizbeach* and you
squeeze out the blood. By a חטאת chattat. *chatas*, first it says
you squirt out the blood, okay, and then it says you squeeze
it afterwards. How do you treat the afterwards squeezing? Is that part
of the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam. *zrikas hadam* as it were? Or
is that sort of more like the שפיכת שיריים shirayim *shfichas shirayim*?
Okay,
by a normal קרבן korban *korban* you throw the blood and then
what's left you pour at the base. Here it says you, after
by a חטאת chattat *chatas* after you do the מליקה melika *mlika*,
the blood squirts out of the neck and then you squeeze the
neck against the wall and it runs out. Is that squeezing part
of the זריקה zrika *zrika* or is it what you do afterwards?
If you don't do it, have you done the קרבן korban *korban*
correctly? Are you יוצא yotzei, *yotzei* with the קרבן korban *korban*? Okay,
that's a pretty fundamental question and it's interesting it only starts getting
debated at the time of the אמוראים *Amoraim*. So אמר רב Rav
*Amar Rav*, so רב Rav *Rav* says מיצוי mitzuy. חטאת העוף chatat
ha'of מעכב meakev, *mitzuy chatas ha'of me'akev*.
If you don't squeeze it out after the squirting then it's prevented
from being good. It's not a good קרבן korban *korban*. Okay, I
skipped a line. I skipped a line. אמר הונא אמר רב *Amar
Huna Amar Rav* מיצוי mitzuy, חטאת העוף chatat ha'of אינו מעכב meakev.
*mitzuy chatas ha'of eino me'akev*. So רב הונא Rav Huna: *Rav Huna*
in the name of רב *Rav* said it's not מעכב meakev *me'akev*.
דתני רב הוזה דמה *d'tani Rav huzzah dama*. And this matches our
משנה mishna *Mishna*, because our משנה *Mishna* said by the bird after
the blood, right, it's all the status changes. There's no מעילה Meila.
*me'ilah*, people who are טמא tamei *tamei* starts being effective. So what
does our משנה *Mishna* say? After the blood was squirted, which means
that the squirting is the key moment, even if you didn't squeeze
out the blood afterwards, its status has changed. Okay, and therefore he
says if you didn't do the מיצוי mitzuy *mitzuy* it's still a
good קרבן korban *korban*. רב אדא בר אהבה אמר רב *Rav Adda
bar Ahava Amar Rav*.
רב אדא בר אהבה *Rav Adda bar Ahava* says in the name
of רב *Rav*. Doesn't he consider מיצוי mitzuy *mitzuy* still part of
the הזזה *hazzaza* of the הזזה *hazzaza*? In which case you haven't
finished anything? Maybe.
All right,
he's
assuming that the משנה *Mishna* would have used a different phrase. Anyway,
רב אדא בר אהבה *Rav Adda bar Ahava* says in the name
of רב *Rav* מיצוי mitzuy. חטאת העוף chatat ha'of, מעכב meakev *mitzuy
chatas ha'of me'akev*. It is מעכב me'akev. *me'akev*. Okay, that if you
don't do the מיצוי mitzuy *mitzuy* you haven't done the correct, all
the sufficient עבודה avodah *avoda* by the blood. So what does he
do with our משנה *Mishna*? Our משנה *Mishna* says the status changes
after הזיה haza'ah *hazzaya*. ותני רב מיצוי mitzuy, דמה *v'tani Rav mitzuy
dama*. He has a different גרסה *girsa* in our משנה *Mishna*. According
to that approach, what our משנה *Mishna* says after you do the
X with the blood the status changed, is his version says after
you do the מיצוי mitzuy הדם *mitzuy hadam*, after you squeeze out
the blood, and not after you squirt the blood. Okay, so now
we're going to try to so it's very much a שיטה *shita*
in our משנה *Mishna*, we're going to try to prove it. תא
שמע *Ta shema* come and hear. והנשאר בדם v'hanishar badam ימצה אל
יסוד המזבח yesod hamizbeach חטאת היא chattat hi, *v'hanish'ar badam yimatze el
yesod hamizbeach chatas hi*. So this is by the bird חטאת chattat
*chatas*. What's left after the blood after it squirts out, you should
squeeze out to the base of the מזבח mizbeach *mizbeach*, it is
a חטאת chatas *chatas*. Now again, I would have said the fact
that it's number one called נשאר nishar, *nish'ar*, the
remnant, and number two the fact that it goes to the base,
makes it sound like this is the not basic זריקת הדם zrikas
hadam, *zrikas hadam*. This is like what's left after the זריקה zrika
*zrika* that you pour it out, it's the שיריים shirayim *shirayim*, it's
the remnant, and you pour it out to the base. But the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* hones in on the phrase חטאת היא chatat hi.
*chatas hi*. That after doing this it says it is a חטאת
chatas, *chatas*, which means that once you've done this you've made it
into a חטאת chatas, *chatas*, and therefore this is מעכב me'akev *me'akev*.
That's how the גמרא *Gemara* reads it. בשלמא לרב אדא בר אהבה
היינו דכתיב והנשאר בדם ימצה חטאת chatas, היא *Bishlama l'Rav Adda bar
Ahava hainu d'chtiv v'hanish'ar badam yimatze chatas hi*. That's why it says
after you squeeze out the blood, then it's a חטאת *chatas* because
you need to do this to make it good. אלא לרב הונא
מאי והנשאר *Ella l'Rav Huna mai v'hanish'ar*. According to רב הונא *Rav
Huna* what does it mean והנשאר *v'hanish'ar*? Now again the real question
is why does it say חטאת היא *chatas hi* after saying והנשאר
*v'hanish'ar* which sounds like this is critical for giving it the status?
כדתני דבי רבי ישמעאל *K'detani d'bei Rabbi Yishmael*. Like we learned in
the school of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*. שאם נשאר *she'im nish'ar*. If
it remains.
It doesn't mean that you must make sure there's leftover and do
this. It means if there's leftover this is what you do. Okay.
ומאי חטאת היא *u'mai chatas hi*? What does it mean it's a
חטאת *chatas* which sounds like only after this is it a חטאת
*chatas*? רישא *reisha*. That's going to the beginning of the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*. The beginning of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* says, may I get
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in front of me?
Yeah, I can find it.
Where
is it? It's after it's in the קרבן korban עולה olah. ויורד
*korban oleh v'yored*.
It's ויקרא ה *Vayikra hei*. ומלק את ראשו ממול ערפו ולא יבדיל
והזה מדם החטאת על קיר
המזבח hamizbeach, והנשאר
בדם ימצה אל יסוד המזבח חטאת היא and then it ends with
הו. hu. Anyway, so חטאת היא *chatas hi* is going to the
beginning of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. The beginning of the פסוק *pasuk*
says והזה מדם החטאת על קיר המזבח *v'hizzah midam hachatat al kir
hamizbeach*. So yes it says it is a חטאת *chatas*, but it
doesn't mean that you have to do all of these to make
it a חטאת *chatas*. It means after you do the first thing,
after you do הזיה מדם *hazzaya midam* you've made it a חטאת
*chatas*. It's interesting actually here the text is חטאת היא *chatas hi*.
Anyway fine.
So
far. nobody's changing it to חטאת הוא. Anyway fine. Okay anyway, ולימא
חטאת היא ארישא. v'leima chattat hi areisha. So it doesn't mean only
after you do the מיצוי, mitzuy. it means after you do the
הזאה, hazah, then it's a חטאת. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא
לרב אשי. Amar leh Rav Acha berei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi. So we
don't know is what we're saying? It's a מחלוקת, machloket, you can't
prove the פסוק either way. Again, you'd ask me, the גמרא's emphasis
on חטאת היא, but
I would have said the emphasis is off מיצוי. mitzuy In fact,
the יסוד המזבח sounds more like it's not so מעכב, me'akev? but
anyway that's the debate. So now רב אחא Rav Acha says this
in the name of רבא? Rava?
Yes, מחלוקת machloket on מחלוקת, machloket, זה מה
שרב אמר. zeh mah sheRav amar.
We have all the time. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב
אשי: Amar leh Rav Acha berei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi: אלא מעתה גבי
מנחה דכתיב והנותרת Ela me'ata gabi mincha dechtiv vehanoteret
according to this idea that it's not really מעכב, me'akev? if there's
נותר notar and not you have to make sure there's leftover and
do this. So by מנחה mincha where it
says והנותרת מן המנחה יאכלו אהרן ובניו, v'hanoteret min hamincha yochlu Aharon
uvanav, should I read that הכי נמי דאם הותירה, hachi nami d'im
hotirah, if there's leftover? But you know what? If it spilled or
something happened, there's nothing left over, no big deal. If there's leftover.
Would we say that? הכי תימא הכי נמי, hachi teima hachi nami,
maybe that's true? Even if nothing was left over, as long as
you did burn the קומץ komets you would be יוצא? והתניא בברייתא
דף ס"ח עמוד ב': V'hatanya b'braita daf samach chet amud bet: מסולתה
ומשמנה על כל לבונתה, misoltah umishamanah al kol levonatah,
that you should offer up the קומץ komets which comes from the
flour and the oil together with all of the לבונה. levonah. And
what does that coming to tell you? פרט שחיסר סולתה, prat shechissar
soltah, if when you offered up the קומץ, komets, you didn't have
all of the remnant of the flour there, some of the מנחה
mincha had spilled, some of the נשאר, the נותרת noteret had spilled,
וחיסר שמנה, v'chissar shamanah, or some of the oil had spilled, or
וחיסר v'chissar even not of the thing you're offering, of what remains,
וחיסר לבונתה, v'chissar levonatah, or some of the לבונה, levonah, the frankincense,
that is what you're offering, had spilled, had got lost. All of
those would be no good. So you see, there must be נותר,
notar there must be the remainder of the מנחה, mincha, and we
don't read "if there is". So here too, we should read והנשאר
בדם only if there is what this leftover blood and you squeeze
it, only then are you יוצא. So the גמרא says: אמרי התם
כתיב והנותרת קרא יתירה. Amri hatam ktiv v'hanoteret kra yiteira.
No,
there it says והנותרת v'hanoteret twice. And since it says it twice
in the פסוק, it's coming to tell you, once it's a מצוה,
mitzvah, the second time it's מעכב. me'akev? Okay, whereas here, it only
says it once. And therefore if you don't have it, it's still
good. Of course it's a מצוה mitzvah to do it, but if
you don't have it, it's still good. This is the general principle
we apply by קדשים that you might remember of שנה עליו הכתוב
לעכב. shana alav hakatuv l'akev.
That normally when the תורה Torah speaks about מצוה, mitzvah, we assume
any time you say it, you mean it, if you don't do
it you're not יוצא, but by קדשים there are so many details
that a normal thing that's mentioned, our normal assumption is that if
you didn't do it, it's still good, unless the תורה Torah repeats
it. So by this idea that you have to have leftover מנחה
mincha repeats, this idea you have to have squeezed out the remainder
blood, it's not repeated, and therefore at least one position is that
בדיעבד bedi'avad it's still good. Yes.
Does the מיצוי, mitzuy, מיצוי mitzuy is that the head or with
the body?
The
no, the neck, it's the exposed part of the neck, again, it's
not the head. It's the body, but you take the exposed part
of the neck and you push it against the
המזבח, the wall of the מזבח. mizbeach.
No, but that's why I asked you, you have to push the
thing into the, he did.
He did. Alright. Well so okay but so we're saying מיצוי mitzuy
is מעכב me'akev. if there's blood. Yes. If there's no blood, you
don't have to do מיצוי. mitzuy Is that it? I mean, you
still have to do מיצוי mitzuy if, no.
Ah yes, a מצוה, mitzvah, but not that it's ever מעכב me'akev,
according to,
no, but if there is blood and you don't do מיצוי, mitzuy
then it is, right?
No. No. No.
So you can have blood leftover and you don't do מיצוי and
it's okay?
Yes. Sure, the same way you can have שירים shirayim leftover and
you don't do שפיכה ליסוד המזבח shpichah l'yesod hamizbeach and it's okay.
Alright. Alright, so it says okay okay. So the
גמרא
says like this: מתיב אבוה דשמואל לרב הונא. Metiv avuh d'Shmuel l'Rav
Huna. אבוה דשמואל Avuh d'Shmuel asked רב הונא: אחד חטאת העוף ואחד
עולת
העוף שמלקן ומיצה דמן חוץ לזמנו פסול ואין בו כרת חוץ למקומו
פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת.
Echad
chattat
ha'of v'echad olat ha'of shemalkan umitzah daman chutz lizmano pasul v'ein bo
kares chutz limkomo pigul v'chayavin alav kares.
So here we have a ברייתא braisa that talks about basically how
do you get פיגול pigul with bird קרבנות. korbanot So it says
whether you're dealing with חטאת העוף chatat ha'of or an עולת העוף.
olat ha'of Now remember, by עולת העוף olat ha'of, the תורה Torah
only speaks about מיצוי. It only says squeeze it out, it doesn't
speak about squirting. So it says whether you're dealing with חטאת העוף
chatat ha'of or an עולת העוף, olat ha'of. if you did מליקה,
melika meaning cut off the head and squeezed out their blood, if
you had it with a thought of חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, it's
invalid and there's no כרת, kares, that's not פיגול. pigul. חוץ לזמנו,
Chutz lizmano, if it's at the wrong time, then פיגול וחייבין עליו
כרת. pigul v'chayavin alav kares. It's פיגול. pigul. Fine, so all it's
basically saying is you can have פיגול pigul by a bird and
depending on if you're doing wrong time or wrong place. But what's
the moment? It says when you are basically cut off the head
and squeezed out the blood. It says squeezed out the blood, it's
talking about a חטאת and an עולה. olah. So it seems that
even by a חטאת the squeezing is necessary. If the squeezing was
not necessary it came afterwards. only seen as an after thing, it
would not be relevant for the thought of פיגול. pigul. So the
גמרא says קתני מיהת מיצוי דמה, katani meihat mitzuy damah,
so squeezing out, though squeezing out even by the חטאת is a
critical act. הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה. hu motivic lah vehu
mifarek lah. He asked but he gave an answer. להצטדן. le-itztadin. It's
only it's talking about different halves. What does that mean different halves?
It talked about two animals. It said חטאת העוף Chatas Ha'of. and
עולת העוף. olat ha'of שמליקה כאן ושמיצוי דמה מן. she-melika kan ve-she-mitzuy
damah man.
So it
means... להצטדן le-itztadin I think would be replaced by the English word
respectively. Okay, so you have a חטאת העוף Chatas Ha'of or an
עולת העוף olat ha'of. that you did מליקה melika. or that you
did מיצוי respectively. Then dot dot dot. Which means if you did
מליקה melika by the חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, you cut off the
head and squirted, although it is missing the word squirt, but that
wouldn't be accurate by the עולת העוף. olat ha'of... Or you had
an עולה... olah עולת העוף... olat ha'of. and you did מיצוי, that's
when the thought of פיגול pigul matters. But it doesn't mean that
we're talking about מיצוי by the חטאת, we're talking about מיצוי by
the עולה. olah, Okay. קתני
גופא. katani gufa. Now let's go back to the earlier statement. תנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל tana devei Rabbi Yishmael שנשאר בדם. she-nishar ba-dam. That
the requirement to do מיצוי is only if there's leftover blood and
even then it's not מעכב. me'akev. But so it's either way it's
not מעכב me'akev. and you only do it if you have leftover
blood. והא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל התם. ve-ha tana devei Rabbi Yishmael
hatam. שיריים מעכבין. shirayim me'akvin.
Don't we have a ברייתא in the name of Rabbi Yishmael that
says that the שיריים shirayim are מעכב? me'akev. And that's in the
גמרא in זבחים. Zevachim. And the גמרא in זבחים Zevachim now what
does that mean שיריים shirayim are מעכב? me'akev Does it mean by
a normal קרבן korban, the spilling out of the שיריים are מעכב?
me'akev So the גמרא there has a whole discussion. ואמר רב פפא
מיצוי חטאת העוף איכא בינייהו. ve-amar Rav Pappa mitzuy chatat ha'of ika
beinaihu. That the issue there being debated is whether the squeezing out
of the... the מיצוי of the bird חטאת, whether that's מעכב. me'akev,
A normal שיריים nobody would say is מעכב, me'akev. right? The normal
spilling out of the blood at the end on the base is
not מעכב. But there what Rabbi Yishmael means is that by a
bird קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, the squeezing out is מעכב. So here
he says it's not necessary and there he says it is מעכב.
So מעכב it prevents it from being good. Okay, which means it's
absolutely required. So תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי ישמעאל. trei tana'ei aliba de-Rabbi
Yishmael. Yep, fine, it's a מחלוקת תנאים machlokes tana'im according to Rabbi
Yishmael. Okay, so yeah, one version of Rabbi Yishmael says the same
way we had a debate what רב said, we have a debate
what Rabbi Yishmael said. So there's these interesting two versions at least
of רב whether the מיצוי of the חטאת העוף is מעכב and
there's two versions of Rabbi Yishmael whether it's מעכב, whether it prevents
it from being good. But again the תורה Torah says by the
חטאת העוף you squirted and then you squeeze it. So on one
hand the squeezing out is parallel to the spilling of the blood
by a normal קרבן korban, and we should say בדיעבד bedi'avad if
you don't do it it's okay. On the other hand it ends
by saying חטאת היא. So that leads at least some to say
that it is מעכב. All right, since we have I don't know
what we're going to do, I mean let's use some time let's
just read the next משנה at least get as you go to
the bottom of the דף. daf.
Move
a
bit so behind on themes. Yeah, okay, so let's take a look.
עולת העוף. olat ha'of. This is you who normally doesn't want to
see head. עולת העוף. olat ha'of, Ah, okay, fine. עולת העוף מולקין
בה. olat ha'of molkin bah. Now this next משנה basically goes through
all the קרבנות korbanos with the same structure. At what stage does
it become fit for becoming פסול psul by טמא, tamei by טבול
יום ומחוסר כיפורים? tevul yom u-mechusar kippurim? And at what stage does
it change its status for מעילה? Meila. What stage does it become
fit to become פיגול נותר וטמא? pigul notar ve-tamei? Okay, so let's
take a look. עולת העוף, olat ha'of a bird עולה. olah. מולקין
בה משיקדשו. molkin bah mishe-kideshu. מעילה Meila begins when it's sanctified. נמלקה,
nimleka, you did the
מליקה. הוכשרה ליפסל בטבול יום ובמחוסר כיפורים. huchshara lipasel be-tevul yom u-ve-mechusar
kippurim.
Then it becomes dead and now it becomes טמא. tamei? and it
also becomes fit for being put on the מזבח mizbeach. even though
the blood hasn't been thrown yet anyway, but the basic point is
it's no longer alive, it's become טמא tamei once the מליקה is
done even before זריקת
הדם. zrikas hadam. ולינה, u-linah, and also לינה linah applies against those
who said that means by the blood. מיצה דמה, mitza damah, once
you squeeze out the blood, there's no here about doing... doing the
הזיה squirting it because by the עולה olah, it's only the squeezing
out of the blood. Then חייבין עליו משום פיגול נותר וטמא. chayavin
alav mishum pigul notar ve-tamei. Then it is fit for being not
eaten, it's an עולה, olah fit for being put on the מזבח.
mizbeach. But once actually really is fit for being put, then the
statuses of פיגול נותר וטמא pigul notar ve-tamei apply to it.
Also, and פיגול pigul anyway you always need to do the last
עבודה avodah. before it can become פיגול. pigul. Anyway, all those things
begin once it really is... is כשר, kasher, once the blood was
on the wall of the מזבח. mizbeach ומולקין בה, u-molkin bah, now
there still is מעילה. Meila Why? Because even after זריקת הדם, zrikas
hadam. an עולת העוף olas ha-of, is off limits to everybody. Nobody
gets to benefit from an עולה. olah, So therefore מעילה Meila continues
straight. זריקה zrika. does not change the status of עולה, olah, whether
it's a bird עולה olah, or an animal עולה, olah, מעילה Meila
does, the זריקה does not change the status for מעילה. Meila So
מעילה Meila. continues עד שתצא לבית הדשן. ad she-tetzei le-veit ha-deshen.
Until it goes out to the burning place to the ashes place
outside of the camp. Why? Because there's a general principle which is
that מעילה Meila continues with something the same way for example things
that are אסור בהנאה, asur be-hana'ah, their status continues until it's נעשית
מצוותו. na'aseit mitzvato. If there's a מצוה mitzvah to burn it then
until you burn it. and you do what you're obligated, the מצווה's
mitzvah finished with it, their status continues. So that idea that we
say normally by איסור הנאה Isur Hana'ah is actually derived from this
principle by קודשים Kodshim and מעילה. Meila That something remains קודשי השם
Kodshei Hashem as long as its purpose is not yet completed. But
as long as every מצווה mitzvah that you needed to do with
this is done to it, once its מצוות mitzvos are all done,
then it is no longer considered קודשי השם Kodshei Hashem and then
there's no longer מעילה. Meila, So even after it's been burnt, the
מצוות mitzvos aren't done, because what, there's something you do with the
ashes. You take the ashes, you put them on the side of
the מזבח. mizbeach. That's תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen every day. You take
the ashes from the מזבח mizbeach. and you bring them outside of
the camp when you need to clean the מזבח. mizbeach. So those
types of, until that is done, it's still, the מצוות mitzvos of
it are not completed. But once that's done, then there's no longer
מעילה.
meilah And I also point out the אימורין eimurin side of the
מזבח. mizbeach.
Oh, by the, by the עוף, of, by the חטאת העוף.
So what's your point? That there shouldn't be מעילה meilah by the
אימורין? eimurin? But right, you don't mean אימורין, eimurin, but you mean
right, you mean
מוראה ונוצה. mora'ah venotzah. והשליך אותה מוראה ונוצה אצל המזבח קדמה אל
מקום הדשן. Vehishlich osah mora'ah venotzah etzel hamizbeach keidmah el mekom hadashen.
That's for the עולה, olah. right?
Yeah.
It's a good question whether there is מעילה meilah by that once
you throw it out at the side of the מזבח. mizbeach, My
guess would be no, but the משנה
doesn't mention. I'll look into that, that's an interesting question. Okay, anyway,
so part of this משנה what we're going to be talking about
is when מעילה meilah stops. Now, we didn't have to mention it
by חטאת העוף because as soon as the blood was נזרק, nizrak,
the meat became מותר, muttar. מעילה meilah stopped then. But here by
an עולה, olah, it's all going to be burnt, so the מעילה
meilah doesn't stop. But it does stop when נעשה מצוותו, na'aseh mitzvato,
which is that the ashes are taken outside the camp. Now, פרים
הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים, Parim Hanisrafim u'Se'irim Hanisrafim, how about when
you have cows and oxen that are burned, meaning those are special
cases that you bring the blood inside the, inside the,
inside the משכן Mishkan or inside the היכל Heichal
and you know, in the inner section and therefore you have to
burn them outside of the camp. So cases like that would certainly
be by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, would be a classic example of
that. There's also פר העלם דבר של ציבור. Par He'elam Davar Shel
Tzibbur. There's certain types of קרבנות korbanos. that you do that to.
So those types of things certainly are like עולה, olah right, which
is that nobody's going to ever benefit from them, so there's going
to remain מעילה. meilah So מועלין בהם משהוקדשו. mo'alin bahem mishehukdashu. מעילה
meilah. begins when you sanctify it. נשחטו, nishchetu, as soon as you
שחט shacht it, then it
becomes, then it becomes הוכשרו להיפסל בטבול יום ובמחוסר כיפורים ובלינה huchsharu
l'hippassel b'tvul yom u'v'mechussar kippurim u'v'linah by the blood. After שחיטה. shechitah.
הוזה דמן, huzah daman, once the blood is sprinkled, חייבים עליו משום
פיגול נותר וטמא. chayavim alav mishum piggul nossar v'tamei. You can be
חייב chayav for פיגול נותר וטמא piggul nossar v'tamei again. You can
get פיגול נותר וטמא piggul nossar v'tamei even by things that you're
אסור to eat. You can already, you can get פיגול נותר וטמא
piggul nossar v'tamei by the אימורין. eimurin. You can get פיגול נותר
וטמא piggul nossar v'tamei by the עולה. olah, You can get it
by the פרים הנשרפים. Parim Hanisrafim. You could anyway been אסור to
eat it. But you only get it once the קרבן korban is,
once there's זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam once the thing is ראוי ra'uy
either for eating or for the מזבח. mizbeach, Or here even after
the מזבח, mizbeach. but basically for
the קרבן korban is כשר. kasher. Okay, so all of these statuses
begin, even though they apply to things that can't be eaten, they
only begin after זריקת הדם zrikas hadam, and after the קרבן korban.
is כשר. kasher. Okay, so even something here that's not going to
be burnt on the מזבח, mizbeach. not going to be eaten, still
you only get פיגול נותר וטמא piggul nossar v'tamei after זריקת הדם.
zrikas hadam Now how long does מעילה meilah continue to apply? ומועלין
בהם בבית הדשן, U'mo'alin bahem b'veis hadashen, even in the place of
ashes. Because as opposed to an עולה, olah the מצווה mitzvah of
an עולה olah was it was burnt on the מזבח. mizbeach? The
מצווה mitzvah was done when you brought it out to the place
of the ashes. That was the last thing. This thing starts outside
of the camp and is burnt outside of the camp. So when
does its, it's already, it begins its life as it were, it
begins its process in the בית הדשן, beis hadashen, in the place
of ashes. So when is the מצווה mitzvah done? So it says
even when it's in the בית הדשן beis hadashen being burnt, there
still is מעילה, meilah its מצווה mitzvah isn't done. When is the
מצווה mitzvah done? עד שיתוך הבשר. Ad sheyituch habassar. The meat has
to basically dissolve. So meaning it has to turn into ashes. Okay,
so in a, so
in a way, "shouldn't
it say עד
שיעשה
אפר ad sheyei'aseh eifer then?" Yeah, maybe, I'm not, good question, is
יתוך הבשר yituch habassar a little bit earlier than actually becoming אפר.
eifer. The רש"י here says though, the פירוש רש"י Perush Rashi says
שנעשה אפר. sheni'aseh eifer. So I don't know why it uses the
phrase though. But anyway it's interesting, meaning on the one hand it's
an earlier stage than the עולה, olah because the עולה olah even
after it's ashes isn't done until it's taken out. Right here it
starts right here, it's done as soon as it's made into ashes.
On the other hand, here it already starts out and even though
it's outside, it's not yet מותר. You understand? So both things are
true by both of them. They're ashes and they're outside. Except the
עולה olah first became ashes and then was taken outside, then it's
done. This starts as outside. That's not done. It's only, now it's
outside combined... things turned into ashes. So in a way it's very
it's similar it's more or less the same for both of them:
ashes and they're in the בית המקדש. העולה מועלים בה, Ha-olah mohlim
bah, and that was עולת העוף, olas ha-of, it's a little funny
the way we're sort of circling around from the less common to
the more common. Anyway we start with חטאת העוף, עולת העוף, and
then these פרים הנשרפים. parim hanisrafim. Now we get to more normal
קרבנות. korbanos העולה
מועלים בה משהוקדשה, Ha-olah mohlim bah mishe-hukdesha, a normal עולה olah like
a sheep or cow, it's מעילה meilah from the moment it's sanctified.
נשחטה, Nishchata, once it's shechted, הוכשרה ליפסל בטבול יום ומחוסר כפורים ובלינה,
huchshara lipasel bitvul yom umchusar kippurim uvelinah, then it can become פסול
psul with a with a טבול יום
ומחוסר כפורים tvul yom umchusar kippurim and also by לינה linah by
the blood.
משיזרק דמה, Mishe-nizrak damah, after זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam now that it's
actually become a כשר קרבן, kasher korban, then these other statuses only
begin once it becomes a כשר קרבן. kasher korban. חייב עליה משום
פגול נותר וטמא. Hayav aleha mishum piggul notar vetamei. Then first of
all פגול piggul only takes effect. By פגול piggul, you require רצוי,
ritzuy, require זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam, נותר וטמא Notar vetamei again even
though even though it's an עולה olah, and you're not allowed to
eat it, nevertheless the meat is only considered to be נותר notar
or the the special כרת kares for eating נותר nosar? and the
special כרת kares for being טמא tamei, is only after the קרבן
korban. was made כשר, kasher, only after זריקת הדם. So that's been
consistent. Now ואין מועלים, ve-ein mohlim, there's no now by now you
should say מעילה meilah by an עולה olah. is continued even after
זריקת הדם because then you can never eat an עולה olah. so
it'll always go on the מזבח. mizbeach, So it should מעילה meilah
continue. But there's one thing that you are allowed to have from
an עולה, olah. which is the כהנים kohanim get the leather. Okay,
that doesn't get burned. So after זריקת הדם,
ואין מועלים בעורות. ein mohlim ba-oros. There's no מעילה meilah by the
leather. The כהנים kohanim. get the leather, there's no מעילה meilah by
the leather after זריקה. That is the one thing where the מעילה
meila status changes by an
עולה. olah אבל מועלים בבשר, Aval mohlim babasar, the מעילה meila continues
with the meat cause that even after זריקה there's no change for
the meat. עד שתצא לבית הדשן, Ad sheteitzei leveit hadeshen, same point.
It has to be burned, turn into ashes and brought outside and
only then is it done and there's no longer מעילה. meila So
that's an עולה. olah We're basically מעילה meila status doesn't change except
for the leather. חטאת ואשם וזבחי שלמי צבור, Chatas ve-asham vezivchei shalmei
tzibbur, how about all these other things which are קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim that is not that are not burned but are eaten? What
are those? A חטאת, a sin offering, an אשם, asham, we learned
about the pieces, other types of sin, זבחי שלמי צבור zivchei shalmei
tzibbur which is basically just on שבועות. Shavuos. But all these types
of things are, sorry, are קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and and
but they can be eaten unlike an עולה. olah, So there מועלים
בהם משהוקדשו, mohlim bahem mishe-hukdeshu, מעילה meila starts from the time they
were sanctified. נשחטו, Nishchetu, after שחיטה shechita again once it's no longer
alive, הוכשרו ליפסל בטבול יום ומחוסר כפורים ובלינה, huchsharu lipasel bitvul yom
umchusar kippurim uvelinah, they can become טמא tamei. and there could be
לינה linah by the blood. נזרק דמן Nizrak daman and after it
becomes a כשר קרבן, kasher korban, now חייב עליהן משום פגול נותר
וטמא, hayav aleihen mishum piggul notar vetamei, those three things: פגול, נותר
nosar and טמא tamei are now relevant concepts and you could be
you'd be חייב כרת chayav kares if you ate them with those
statuses.
ואין מועלים בבשר. ve-ein mohlim babasar. And also what's very relevant of
זריקת הדם here is there's no longer מעילה meila by the meat
because now the meat can be eaten by the
כהנים. kohanim. אבל מועלים באמוריהן. Aval mohlim be-imureihen.
What about the parts that
have to go on
the מזבח?
mizbeach. אבל מועלים באמוריהן, Aval mohlim be-imureihen, but the אמורין imurin which
go on the מזבח, mizbeach there remains מעילה me'ilah until that gets
burned and the ashes are taken out.
That's an intro. It's also like the other stuff.
Yeah, the fat and everything. ואמורין Ve-imurin is everything that goes on
the מזבח. mizbeach Okay, so till now it's pretty much what we
knew, that the שחיטה shechita changes the status for טומאה and the
זריקה changes the status for for the meat by קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodashim, not by the meat by עולה which is burned. And again
we've learned though by עולה the skin, the leather, there's no מעילה
me'ilah after זריקה. We've also learned the time when מעילה me'ilah. ends:
שתצא לבית הדשן. sheteitzei leveit hadeshen. Now we deal with things which
are not exactly
meat. שתי הלחם. Shtei halechem. Interesting, we're having so that's already the
second שבועות Shavuos reference. Okay, before we talked about זבחי שלמי צבור.
zivchei shalmei tzibbur. You have the two loaves of bread that come
with the the the שלמי צבור shalmei tzibbur by by שבועות. Shavuos.
מועלים בהם משהוקדשו. Mohlim bahem mishe-hukdeshu. From the time you sanctify the
dough, the flour, whatever, מעילה me'ilah? begins. Now, what would be the
parallel to when it could become טמא? tamei
So קרמו בתנור הוכשרו ליפסל בטבול יום ומחוסר כפורים. kermum batanur huchsharu
lipasel bitvul yom umchusar kippurim. And now by the way they take
out the word לינה linah because since of course לינה linah is
talking about the לינה linah of the blood, that's not really relevant
here. And the other point is, by the way, that the לינה
linah the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and we're back to see the
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim was many many days from the time it
was made to the time it was eaten. The שתי הלחם shtei
halechem was two to three days, the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim was
like was like you know nine days: it was made on ערב
שבת Erev Shabbos and you only eat it next שבת. Shabbos. So
there really is you know the concept of לינה lina. is pretty
foreign by these type of things. Now there is some interesting question,
which is so I made I made let's say the לחם הפנים,
lechem hapanim, I made it like ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and I
ate it you know on day nine. Like whatever the שבת Shabbos
later, it's the next שבת Shabbos over. Let's say I didn't eat
it that next שבת Shabbos over and I waited until Sunday or
Monday to eat it. Is maybe there is then a פסול pasul
a דין din of נותר? nosar Right? It's true that נותר nosar
doesn't begin because the time that it's fit to be eaten is
much later from the time that it sort of becomes a קרבן
korban or whatever the קדושה kedusha starts. But is there נותר nosar
after that time? That's an interesting point. But certainly the concept of
נותר nosar. doesn't begin after it becomes after it gets baked. Okay,
that it does not start with.
So משהוקדשו, mishehukdeshu, you mentioned that's when you מקדיש makdish the flour,
not when you necessarily מקדיש makdish it as לחם? lechem?
No, it doesn't really matter. Okay?
Because it's much later.
In other words, I understand but if you מקדיש makdish something, whenever
you מקדיש makdish it, מעילה me'ilah starts. So even with the flour?
Yes, sure, sure.
Okay, now,
okay but what is I should say interesting is that the idea
also here about the פסול about when it becomes fit for becoming
טמא tamei with the פסול טבול יום ומחוסר כפורים, tvul yom u’mechusar
kipurim, here
as opposed to what I was saying with the animals before, that
they were alive so they couldn't become טמא, tamei this is flour.
Flour and water, it's dough. Dough can become טמא. tamei We talk
about dough becoming טמא tamei all the time, right? And nevertheless, it's
not טמא as קדשים until actually it becomes like fit for what's
considered like קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. Until it’s קרמו פניה בתנור, karmu
paneha batanur, until it gets like a crust in the תנור, tanur,
we learned before that that's not considered לחם. lechem. So although it
has קדושה, kedusha, it would more be a type of a קדושת
דמים kedushas damim as opposed to a real קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf,
an intrinsic קדושה kedusha as the thing that is fit for being
the קרבן, korban. that is not until it gets the crust. And
therefore, even though it could not become טמא as the level to
which קדשים can become טמא until it reaches that stage of actually
getting a crust and being לחם lechem which is fit for being
the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. Okay, now, so that's that. Now the
לשחיטת הלחם את הזבח, lishchitas halechem es hazevach, once it's at that
stage also, now when you שחט shacht the קרבן, korban it can
that you can שחט shacht the קרבן korban now because the קרבן
korban has to be שחטed shacht with the bread and if the
bread isn't ready then its status doesn't change as part of the
קרבן. korban, So now that it's crust and it's fit to be
bread, now you can call bread, you can שחט shacht the קרבן.
korban, נזרק דמן של כבשים, nizrak daman shel kvasim, once the blood
of the lambs which are brought for with the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem on שבועות, Shavuos, the blood is thrown, then they become like
one with the קרבן and their status changes with the זריקת הדם
of the קרבן. So in that case, חייבין עליהם משום פיגול נותר
וטמא, chayavin aleihem mishum pigul nosar vetamei, you're חייב chayav פיגול נותר
וטמא pigul nosar vetamei if you have any of those by these.
So here we do have by the way נותר nosar is being
applied to the bread, presumably. Then if you did leave it over
the time it would be נותר. Okay? And if the קרבן is
פיגול, pigul, the bread is פיגול. pigul. If you're טמא and you
eat the bread, you're חייב for טמא that eats קדשים. All these
things only after the קרבן became כשר. kasher. ואין בהם מעילה. ve’ein
bahem meila. There's no מעילה me'ilah because the bread is eaten by
the כהנים. kohanim. So why is there there would never be מעילה
me'ilah. by the bread after the זריקת הדם, after it's fit to
be eaten by the כהנים. kohanim. Now לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, how
about the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim that you put on the table,
you bake ערב שבת, erev Shabbos, you put on the table, you
eat the following שבת? Shabbos? מועלין בהם משהוקדשו. moalin bahem mishehukdeshu. So
there is מעילה me'ilah. from the time that it's sanctified. קרמו בתנור,
karmu batanur, again once the crust it gets a crust, הוכשרו ליפסל
בטבול יום ובמחוסר כפורים, huchsharu l’hipasel b’tvul yom uv’mechusar kipurim, now here
there's no גירסא girsa of לינה. lina ולהסדר על גבי השלחן. u’lehaseder
al gabei hashulchan. Once it gets a crust, now now it's ready
to be put on the table the same way the other stuff
with the crust you were ready to שחט shacht the קרבן with
it by the שלמים, shlamim, here when it gets a crust it's
ready to be put on the table. קרבו הבזיכין, karvu habazichin, once
the now what you do is the following שבת Shabbos you offer
up these little little like spoons of incense and that makes the
bread fit to be eaten. So once those spoons of incense are
offered up, so the parallel here is to the שחיטה shchita by
the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, by the lambs that came with the
שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. Once they're now fit to be eaten, so
then חייבין עליהם משום פיגול נותר וטמא, chayavin aleihem mishum pigul nosar
vetamei, there's a חיוב chiyuv of פיגול נותר וטמא. pigul nosar vetamei.
Again נותר is mentioned here. ואין בו מעילה. ve’ein bo meila. And
there is no מעילה me'ilah of course because it's now supposed to
be eaten by the כהנים. kohanim, המנחות, hamenachos, how about a standard
מנחה mincha which is just the whole thing is the bread the
dough thing the מנחה? mincha? מועלין בהן משהוקדשו, moalin bahen mishehukdeshu, מעילה
me'ilah from the time it's sanctified. קדשו בכלי, kadeshu b’kli, now here
it's not about baking and crust and bread, here it's once it's
put into the כלי שרת. kli shares. הוכשרו ליפסל בטבול יום ובמחוסר
כפורים ובלינה. huchsharu l’hipasel b’tvul yom uv’mechusar kipurim uv’lina. That's when the
statuses start now that it becomes this idea I've been talking about.
it was really already קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, but it still needed
to be שחטed shecht at least to be dead, but here by
these things that are bread or whatever, קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf for
some of them comes when it's לחם, lechem, when it's crust, by
a מנחה mincha קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf is when it's put in
a כלי שרת. kli shares. So then it has those statuses ולינה
u-vlina and by לינה lina because now if you don't if you
don't bring the after you put in the כלי שרת kli shares
you have to bring it today, and if you don't bring it
today, the whole thing is פסול ולינה. u-vlina. Okay so here that
really the לינה clock starts. קרב הקומץ, karev hakometz, חייב עליו משום
פיגול נותר וטמא. chayav alav mishum pigul nosar v'tamei. Once you put
the קומץ kometz and you made it a כשר kasher קרבן, then
the status of פיגול נותר וטמא pigul nosar v'tamei apply, ואין מועלין
בשיריים. v'ein mo'alin b'shirayim. There's no מעילה meilah. by what's left because
what's left is eaten by the כהנים, kohanim אבל מועלין בקומץ aval
mo'alin b'kometz by the קומץ kometz which is burnt, there is מעילה
meilah עד שיצא לבית הדשן, ad she-yeitzei l'veis hadeshen, until you go
ahead and bring it out to the בית הדשן beis hadeshen like
we've seen, anything that's burnt on the מזבח mizbeach, until the ashes
are removed there is going to be מעילה. So wait, isn't the
בית הדשן beis hadeshen stated more by the actual animal קרבנות korbanos
because by the מנחה mincha you just put it on the top
of the מזבח mizbeach. and you're done? I mean, yeah, everything burns
and then but everything becomes ashes, everything has to be brought out.
Torah doesn't say you take out the ashes of the animals. No,
I know but but it mentions the ashes. זאת תורת העולה, zos
toras ha-olah, you know, you know. Yeah, but it only mentions it
by the עולה, doesn't mention it by other things. No, I know
but maybe I was taking it from a paradigm for like animal
קרבנות as opposed to apparently not. But actually let's take a look
at the first discussion with the גמרא which does get into this
interesting discussion about the ashes. Okay this would have been perfect a
week ago for צו, Tzav, but we just read it pretty recently.
איתמר. itmar. הנהנה מאפר תפוח, ha-neh-neh mei-eifer tapuach, תפוח, tapuach, תפוח tapuach
I guess anyway שעל גבי המזבח. she-al gabei ha-mizbeach. So like if
like you know they would have a big mound of ashes, right?
It's a very busy place, they're not going to clean it out
every day, they keep on collecting ashes, it's called the it's called
the תפוח tapuach like the dome, the dome of ashes. So when
you did the תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen every morning it was more
sort of ritual and symbolic. You took a you took a little
bit you put on the side of the מזבח, mizbeach you were
done. You take from the תפוח, tapuach, right? Put it on the
side. Yeah, so but only when you really need it every so
often would you do a real cleaning out of the ashes and
bring it outside. When it says בית הדשן, beis hadeshen, בית הדשן
beis hadeshen is when you do the whole cleaning and bring the
stuff outside of the מחנה. machaneh. Okay so what is the הלכה
halacha about the stuff, the ashes themselves? Is there still מעילה? Now
that seems to have been answered by our משנה. Our משנה seems
to say yes until you take it outside. But let's take a
look. So why would they use it, the כהנים kohanim, or and
so on, right? Grows crops? Right. Well they could have sold it
to farmers and maybe they did. כהנים, kohanim, I'm sure כהנים, although
you know they don't have land as an inheritance, I'm sure some
of them had wealth and they also had state ממון, mamon, right?
You want that. But you know you always could sell things, things
have a market value. Wait so with the ashes it's really helpful
fertilizer? Yeah. I mean that's assumed why you're asking because of fertilizer.
So meaning like every every several weeks they did a really big
cleaning. Right. Which means then you could have מעילה on the stuff
for several weeks. Exactly. Exactly. Okay, you could have מעילה on stuff
for years until you bring it to the קרבן, you know. Okay.
איתמר. itmar. הנהנה מאפר תפוח ha-neh-neh mei-eifer tapuach שעל גבי המזבח. she-al
gabei ha-mizbeach. So you you benefited from the ashes that were there
in the mound. רב אמר אין מועלין בו. Rav amar ein mo'alin
bo. No once it's ashes, no מעילה. רבי יוחנן אמר מועלין בו.
Rabbi Yochanan amar mo'alin bo. There is מעילה. So לפני תרומת הדשן,
lifnei trumas hadeshen, before you actually do the תרומת הדשן, trumas hadeshen,
the symbolic removal of ashes every morning, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דמועלין
בו. kulei alma lo pligi d'mo'alin bo. They all agree there's מעילה
because לא נעשית מצותו, lo na'asis mitzvaso, right? If these things are
still you know maybe maybe some of these ashes will still be
used for the תרומת הדשן. trumas hadeshen. And תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen
is done if you conceptually think that every morning it's done to
the ashes, so this thing from the time it was put until
the next morning of תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen hasn't had the מצוה
mitzvah of תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen done to it. So until that
ritual of תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen is done everybody agrees it's not
yet נעשית מצותו. na'asis mitzvaso. כי פליגי לאחר תרומת הדשן. ki pligi
l'achar trumas hadeshen. After the תרומת הדשן. trumas hadeshen. You brought it
yesterday, there was תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen this morning, is there is
there מעילה on the ashes after the תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen was
done the following morning? רב אמר אין מועלין בו. Rav amar ein
mo'alin bo. הרי נעשית מצותו. harei na'asis mitzvaso. תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen
is the last מצוה mitzvah done to it, the rest is just
you know janitorial, cleaning up the מזבח. mizbeach It's not a מצוה.
mitzvah. Okay so after תרומת הדשן trumas hadeshen the last מצוה mitzvah
was done. ורבי יוחנן אמר, v'Rabbi Yochanan amar, כיוון דכתיב וילבש הכהן
מדו בד ומכנסי בד ילבש על בשרו והרים את הדשן, keivan d'chsiv
v'lavash hakohen mido vad u-michnesei vad yilbash al b'saro v'herim es hadeshen,
כיוון דאיצטריך וגומר keivan d'itztrich v'gomar because the end of the פסוק
is ופשט את בגדיו ולבש בגדים אחרים והוציא את הדשן, u-fashat es
bgadav v'lavash bgadim acherim v'hotzi es hadeshen, he puts on other clothes.
Now the assumption is, what's other clothes? Other בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah
or your weekday clothes? So the assumption רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
saying which isn't exactly in the פסוק is that that's בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehunah. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying look, if you
need to wear בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah to clean off the מזבח
and take the ashes outside, it's still an עבודה. avodah. It's still
a מצוה. mitzvah. It's not just clean up. You know, I mean,
there would be clean up they wouldn't call an עבודה. avodah. Like
when you washed the floors you didn't call that an עבודה. avodah
Okay but here he says if בגדים אחרים bgadim acherim it means
They're different, but in some ways they're similar to the first ones.
They're still בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, just less expensive. So right, כיוון
דצריך בגדי כהונה בקדושתיה קיימי, keivan detzarich bigdei kehuna bikdushatiah kayei, it
still retains its קדושה kedushah because it's still an עבודה and it's
not yet the מצווה mitzvah isn't done until they're actually fully taken
outside. Now our משנה seems to be very clearly that position. So
תנן, tnan, our משנה says מועלין בהן עד שתוציא לבית הדשן. meilin
bahen ad shetotzi leveit hadeshen. קשיא לרוב, kashya lerav, that's a challenge
on רב because it's clear until the ashes are taken out, there's
מעילה. So אמר לך רב, amar lach rav, עד שתהא ראויה לבית
הדשן, ad shetehei reuia leveit hadeshen, which is where we'll end for
today, until the ashes are fit to be taken out, okay, sort
of like עד שתהא ראויה לזריקה. ad shetehei reuia lezrika. It doesn't
literally mean they're taken out, it means that they're at the state
that they're now able to be taken out because the תרומת הדשן
terumat hadeshen was done. So we will continue tomorrow with that question
about when מעילה stops and to what degree is it a מצווה
mitzvah to remove the ashes from the מזבח to the בית הדשן.
beit hadeshen.