Good morning. So
we continue מעילה, Meila, we're דף ג' daf gimmel today.
It's 11 תשרי Tishrei by the way. And מעילה Meila we started
yesterday, so thank you to דב וינשטיין Dov Weinstein for doing that,
but just a few words of introduction before we continue. As you
can see, the דף daf is a lot shorter, which means that
we won't have as many challenges getting through the דף daf today.
Has to do with the fact that there's a lot more תוספות
Tosfos here, and the סוגיות, sugyas, as you will find out, are
definitely a little bit more dense and challenging, although a lot of
these תוספות Tosfoses are more of a commentary תוספות Tosfos than a
critical analysis תוספות. Tosfos. It's a sort of a bit of a
mix.
Also, you know, the רש"י Rashi here is standard רש"י. Rashi. Is
this the תוספות?
Tosfos? The תוספות. Tosfos. It's תוספות שנץ. Tosfos Shantz.
רש"י Rashi is the standard רש"י. Rashi. I should say by the
way, I meant to say it when we were doing כריתות, Kerisos,
that although the first דף daf of רש"י Rashi seemed very unusual
and seemed to not be רש"י, Rashi, as you continued in the
מסכתא, masechta, it seemed to be very much standard רש"י, Rashi, and
the idea that the רש"י Rashi on כריתות Kerisos isn't real רש"י
Rashi is I think a not so accepted idea out there, but
it really did seem that that רש"י Rashi really was the real
רש"י Rashi except maybe the first דף. daf. But anyway, מעילה Meila
is certainly the case. The difference about מעילה Meila in terms of
the, if you will, the text of the basic מסכתא masechta is
that like a number of other מסכתות, masechtos, and I've mentioned this,
the language is not sort of the standard language we expect from
the בבלי Bavli in terms of some of the grammatical issues and
some of the sort of diction and so on, and there leads
to a whole discussion whether that means that it really was more
of an ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael מסכתא. masechta. Certainly the consensus nowadays
means that it was more, the editing, the final editing was done
in a different one of the בבל Bavel schools, whether it's
נהרדעא, Nehardea, סורא, Sura, פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, and so on. Anyway, you will
see something a little bit unusual in the language. In terms of
the basic makeup, in terms of the basic topic, the topic is
as clear, the איסור דאורייתא issur d'Oraisa of מעילה, Meila, which is
when somebody misuses הקדש hekdesh unintentionally בשוגג, b'shogeg, then they bring a
קרבן, korban, אשם מעילות, asham meilos, and they pay back the principal
with a חומש. chomesh. If with an extra fifth, which is really
a quarter. If they do it במזיד, b'meizid, then they don't bring
a קרבן, korban, and they don't do the fifth, and they just
pay it back. So it's actually interesting. Doing it בשוגג b'shogeg has
more consequences in terms of that, but that's part of the idea
of כפרה kappara and atonement, and that was sort of similar to
the discussion we had before in terms of כריתות, Kerisos, you know,
that there would actually, unless you're actually getting like physical lashes in
בית דין, beis din, there could sometimes be more consequences what you
need for כפרה kappara and atonement. So very often the term in
the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא, Gemara, whether in certain cases מעל
ma'al or לא מעל, lo ma'al, does not mean if you're לא
מעל lo ma'al it doesn't necessarily mean that what you did was
מותר. muttar. If you did it במזיד b'meizid we would say לא
מעל. lo ma'al. It doesn't, or doesn't mean that there aren't a
consequence. You have to pay back, but לא מעל lo ma'al means
you're not in the תורה'ס Torah's category of מעילה Meila in the
sense that you're חייב chayav an אשם מעילות asham meilos and you
pay back an extra fifth. So לא מעל lo ma'al has a
very narrow definition, and it's important to keep in mind about the
idea of the קרבן korban and the extra fifth. Similarly, as you
saw yesterday, there seems to be a concept of מעילה דרבנן. Meila
d'rabbanan. Now מעילה דרבנן Meila d'rabbanan doesn't just mean it's אסור. assur.
For example, you know, it could say לא נהנין ולא מועלין lo
nehenin v'lo ma'alin and so on, and you know, which sometimes it
says לא נהנין, lo nehenin, which is you're not supposed to derive
benefit. This is still somewhat קודש kodesh and or whatever דרבנן d'rabbanan
you're not supposed to derive benefit. But that's just an איסור דרבנן.
issur d'rabbanan. Say it's מעילה דרבנן Meila d'rabbanan is more expanding the
דאורייתא d'Oraisa category and giving it a lot more weight. And you
saw that yesterday that the cases that we basically technically it might
be out of מעילה דאורייתא, Meila d'Oraisa, but we'll still call it
מעילה דרבנן. Meila d'rabbanan. Since it's דרבנן, d'rabbanan, there's obviously not going
to be a קרבן, korban, there's not going to be a fifth.
That's what the גמרא Gemara said yesterday. But that is מעילה דרבנן,
Meila d'rabbanan, which is more weighty than just saying לא נהנין, lo
nehenin, it's אסור assur to get הנאה. hana'ah. Okay. So those are,
that's the basic concept of מעילה. Meila.
Conceptually, as I think I told you before and we're not going
to analyze this at length now, we will more in a later
פרק, perek, the question is to what degree does one conceptualize מעילה
Meila as a type of stealing from הקדש, hekdesh, or does one
conceptualize it as a type of deriving benefit from things that are
off limits, from things that don't belong to you, but it's not
so much stealing.
The שיעור shiur of מעילה Meila is a פרוטה, prutah, which certainly
monetizes it, is that a word? Monetize?
Which means it's not like איסור אכילה, issur achila, like of a
כזית. kezayis. But even if it's about, if it's determined by value,
is it that I've taken money away from הקדש, hekdesh, or is
it that I have taken something, benefited from something that I had
no rights to, that didn't belong to me? And there's an obvious
sort of middle case where, you know, where it's a neat test
case where you benefit but הקדש hekdesh doesn't lose out. You drink
from a כוס של הקדש, kos shel hekdesh, right? You benefit, hekdesh
doesn't lose out, and there is מעילה Meila in that case. Interesting
question becomes so are there maybe two types of מעילה? me'ilah? There's
another type of מעילה me'ilah where I take money that belonged to
הקדש Hekdesh and I hand it over to somebody. Okay, so I
actually didn't even benefit in a way because I gave it to
somebody else, maybe as a מתנה, matanah, but I certainly stole it.
Okay, so there might be two types of מעילה me'ilah and that's
another sort of interesting question of how do we conceptualize it? Interestingly,
the actual sort of clear discussions of what is the עבירה aveirah
of מעילה, me'ilah, what are the scenarios in which you're מועל, mo'al,
comes much much at the end of the מסכת. Masechet. And a
lot of the beginning of the מסכת Masechet really winds up being
more of a discussion of are things קדוש kadosh or not קדוש
kadosh and their level of קדושה, kedushah, which is like a prerequisite
for מעילה. me'ilah. As we've been discussing in the beginning of the
first משנה, Mishnah,
Shum Dov introduced to you, right? There's an idea of מקדשי השם,
mikodeshei Hashem, that it has to be something that is considered to
be like fully מקדשי השם, mikodeshei Hashem, a high level of קדושה.
kedushah. So for example, there is no מעילה me'ilah by the parts
of the קורבנות korbanot that could be eaten, by the meat of
the שלמים, Shelamim, by the meat of the חטאת Chatat and the
אשם Asham after it's שחט shachted and can be eaten by the
כוהנים. Kohanim. It's only something that is totally devoted להשם. la-Hashem. So
classic מעילה me'ilah is בדק הבית, Bedek ha-Bayis, you have no rights
to it, or by קורבנות korbanot the part that is going to
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Now what part is that? So if it
is שלמים, Shelamim, there's no מעילה me'ilah by שלמים Shelamim because fundamentally
שלמים Shelamim is קדשים קלים kodashim kalim and is like seen as
yours, like there's even an opinion of ממון בעלים, mamon be'alim, but
even if not ממון בעלים mamon be'alim certainly not fundamentally seen as
God's, okay, with the one exception of the אימורין, imurin, and even
the אימורין imurin they only have their designation after the שחיטה shechitah
and the זריקה zerikah and so on where now they are fit
to go on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So that's by שלמים. Shelamim. But
on the other extent is an עולה, Olah, at no stage does
anybody have any right to it except maybe the skin, okay, but
anyway and therefore the עולה Olah from the moment it's sanctified all
through the moment it's burnt and everything is all going to be
מעילה. me'ilah. Middle cases are like a חטאת Chatat and an אשם
Asham and so on where the כוהנים Kohanim eat the meat, and
there though again fundamentally קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, so fundamentally it starts
with the idea that it's fully God's as opposed to קדשים קלים.
kodashim kalim. Their eating of the meat is a היתר heter that
comes later. So after the זריקת הדם zerikat ha-dam then the meat
of the חטאת Chatat that is now מותר muttar to the כוהנים
Kohanim is now no longer מעילה. me'ilah. Everything else remains מעילה. me'ilah.
But there it's not like there until the זריקת הדם zerikat ha-dam
even the meat is אסור assur because conceptually that is all God
until the זריקה zerikah and then it becomes מותר לכהנים. muttar la-kohanim.
So that is some of the basic cases that מעילה me'ilah applies
to. But as we will see, a lot of the first פרקים
perakim of מעילה me'ilah are not the act of מעילה me'ilah but
defining the objects and in a way getting into a discussion about
what things have different types of קדושה. kedushah. So you'll have interesting
questions of you sanctify a tree and fruit grows from it, is
the fruit מעילה? me'ilah? Or you sanctify a well and rainwater gathers
in it, is there מעילה me'ilah on the rainwater? So when קדושה
kedushah is derivative or comes indirectly and those types of questions. So
be just anticipate and recognize the first two thirds of the מסכת
Masechet pretty much are more about the objects and about קדושה kedushah
and the act of מעילה me'ilah is sort of at the end.
So that's in terms of some general introductory things and then we'll
take a question or two and then start going on. Yes.
On מעילה דרבנן, me'ilah derabbanan,
the Rabbis said not to require the payment of the חומש. chomesh.
Correct, but they could have,
they could have,
and they didn't.
Yeah, they could have. I mean I think they wanted to make
it distinguish it from מעילה דאורייתא. me'ilah de'oraita. But okay, but again
to say that it's מעילה דרבנן me'ilah derabbanan a clear difference between
that and לא נהני lo nehani is when they say לא נהני
lo nehani that's more like איסור הנאה issur hana'ah and they never
say you had to pay back, okay, whereas by מעילה דרבנן me'ilah
derabbanan they said you had to pay back, so they clearly gave
it a different category. But you're right, they made certain distinctions in
order to I guess identify it as as distinct. Okay?
I thought something that רש"י Rashi said was linked to the איל
אשם ayil asham
of the חומש.
chomesh. Well, not really in the sense I mean the חומש chomesh
and the איל אשם ayil asham are both group with the דאורייתא,
de'oraita, but as we learned at the end of כריתות, Keritot, okay,
you add the fifth not to the cost of the איל אשם,
ayil asham, you add the fifth to the principal you're paying back.
So I'd have to check that רש"י Rashi again, but I don't
think he means literally it becomes part of the money of the
איל אשם, ayil asham, I think he just means that those go
together in what constitutes
דאורייתא
מעילה.
de'oraita
me'ilah.
אה ברישא דמסכתא מעילה מעילה דרבנן מאי הוי דרבנן דלית ביה קדושת
הגוף ומיירי
מעילה דרבנן משום קרן בלא חומש שמא ישכח ויקנה על מה שמשלם,
Ah be-reisha de-masechta Me'ilah me'ilah derabbanan mai havei
derabbanan de-leit beih kedushat ha-guf u-meiri me'ilah derabbanan mishum keren be-lo chomesh
she-ma yishkach ve-hikneh al mah she-meshallem, yeah, that's an interesting phrase ויקנה.
ve-hikneh. Let me see what the תוספות Tosafot says with that. אה
בהדי איל אשם, Ah bahadei ayil asham, so together with. But you're
right, either way it sort of emphasizes. Yeah, it's an interesting point
conceptually because certainly the גמרא Gemara we just learned a day or
two ago
in כריתות.
Keritot. So regarding let's say נדבת אשם, nidvas asham, so a non-כהן,
kohen, a זר, zar, eats the meat of an אשם asham after
the זריקה. zerikah. So we said there's no מעילה Meilah there, but
then there's still this concept of איש כי יאכל קדש. ish ki
yochal kodesh.
Yeah, yeah, right, right. Let me make that clear. You might get
out of מעילה, Meilah, but there could be a lot of other
איסורים. issurim. Like Michael says, a זר zar eating the meat that's
שייך shiyach to a כהן kohen is still an איסור issur of
זרות zarus and probably חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav misa biydei shamayim.
It's just not מעילה. Meilah. By the same way, there's as we
said, there could be an איסור הנאה דרבנן. issur hana'ah d'rabbanan. But
the difference of מעילה Meilah is that מעילה Meilah doesn't just mean
you transgressed, מעילה Meilah means you have to pay back the קרן
keren and a חומש chomesh and you bring an אשם מעילה. asham
meilah. But there could definitely be איסור זרות, issur zarus, absolutely. But
do I pay back
the תוספת tosefes or not?
No, no.
A זר zar who eats תרומה terumah pays back, but
if he eats the meat of an אשם asham then not.
Right, I mean if you stole from the כהן kohen maybe it's
a different story, but let's say he allowed you to, whatever, anyway
there would not be an idea of paying back. There's an איסור
זרות issur zarus but it's not paying back. And that's absolutely correct,
don't assume that saying no מעילה Meilah means it's מותר. muttar. A,
if you're מזיד, meizid, no מעילה Meilah in the sense that it
doesn't have those הלכות, halachos, it's certainly not מותר. muttar. And B,
right, there could be an איסור זרות. issur zarus. One last point
and then we, which is directly relevant to the גמרא Gemara we're
going to look and then we're going to go back, which is
there was an interesting discussion in כריתות. Krisos. Now normally the שיעור
מעילה shiur Meilah is a פרוטה, perutah, but the שיעור פרוטה shiur
perutah meaning did I benefit a פרוטה. perutah. Okay, if it's about
me being נהנה, nehenah, or if it's a type of מעילה Meilah
that's more about stealing, maybe it's the object I stole worth a
פרוטה. perutah. Now in theory it's possible to benefit a פרוטה perutah
without the object being worth a פרוטה perutah because if this stuff
is for example אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and it goes on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, it's an עולה, olah, it's whatever it might be, so
it doesn't have any market value, okay. And nevertheless if I eat
it I got הנאה hana'ah of a פרוטה perutah but it had
no market value but I actually got that benefit. So you would
think that certainly we would measure it and we do measure it
by did I benefit, not how much market value it has. Maybe
if it's in a שוה sheveh more like stealing and not benefiting
we would look more at market value. I just raise that because
you might remember a week or so ago in כריתות Krisos we
discussed the question about what is the market value, is the object
worth a פרוטה, perutah, and that really is at least for most
of our discussion not the focus. The focus is did I benefit
a פרוטה, perutah, טאקע take maybe is a focus of market value.
The reason it's directly relevant to what we're learning and now we're
going to turn back to the גמרא Gemara is because the גמרא
Gemara here is talking not only about a קרבן korban that I
don't have a benefit for but even a קרבן פסול, korban pasul,
right, that a קרבן korban that you shechted at night or you
did the זריקה zerikah in the wrong place or you did it
with a מחשבת פיגול. machsheves piggul. So A, it started off being
קודש kodesh and אסור, assur, B, now it's פסול pasul and therefore
it's going to have to be burnt. And nevertheless there's מעילה Meilah
by it because it's not a question of its value, there's a
question of did I benefit a פרוטה. perutah. And the only relevant
question therefore is, and this becomes again a central question in the
first four פרקים perakim or so of מעילה, Meilah, is can you
label the thing קדשי השם. kodshei Hashem. Okay, which is not the
same question of is it קדוש. kadosh. Of course it's קדוש, kadosh,
it remains קדוש, kadosh, what, we made it חולין? chullin? But if
it's not somehow designated for the מזבח, mizbeiach, if somehow something profoundly
wrong was done to it and it seems like now it has
to get destroyed and it's and so on, not just that it's
worthless, it loses the designation of קדשי השם kodshei Hashem for מעילה
Meilah purposes. So one example of that was Ulla's case of shechting
it what do you call it shechting it outside of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Was that it? Or was it, no, קדשים שמתו
בצידה kodshim shemeisu baziduh or let's say you shechted it fully outside
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not just בדרום, badarom, okay. Those types
of things, although it still has קדושה, kedusha, there's still an איסור
הנאה, issur hana'ah, okay, but that is no longer קדשי השם. kodshei
Hashem. That has been so misdirected and now it's הולך לאיבוד, holech
l'ibbud, it's not קדשי השם. kodshei Hashem. And therefore the question, the
first point the גמרא Gemara made yesterday is
that
when you do things wrong that are not that are still within
the ballpark, you know, it's called פסולו בקודש, psulo bakodesh, you shechted
it בדרום badarom or you you know and so on, but it's
still something a problem of how you did the עבודה avodah of
the קרבנות. korbanos. It is not like you shechted it outside, it's
not like it died, that type of פסולו בקודש, psulo bakodesh, you
did the rituals wrong, in that type of a way it's still
קדשי השם kodshei Hashem and there still is מעילה Meilah and that
is the first חידוש chiddush of our משנה Mishna that there still
is מעילה Meilah when it is those types of mistakes and not
more profound ones. And one of the ways to test does it
still have a concept of still a relevant קדושה kedusha is, and
the גמרא Gemara pointed this out yesterday, if עלו לא ירדו. alu
lo yardu. Once they're on the מזבח, mizbeiach, the הלכה halacha is
you don't take them off, then they're still in the ballpark. Okay,
it's still they're still פסול pasul and you're not allowed to, but
they're still in the ballpark if they're allowed to remain על המזבח.
al hamizbeiach. And the basic principle of everything in our משנה Mishna
is it's a פסולו בקודש psulo bakodesh אם עלו לא ירדו im
alu lo yardu and therefore it is still in the category of
קדשי השם. kodshei Hashem. Okay, one or two questions and then we
will actually start reading the גמרא, Gemara, yes.
I was thinking just the זה נבזה פסול zeh ne'evezeh pasul so
in relation to what you said does there does there have to
be
Sometimes it has to be a חסרון, chisaron, sometimes not and we'll
discuss that. But it can't be pure הנאה hana'ah without חסרון.
chisaron. Who determines what's the, I mean is it like a committee
and then they, how do you determine, I mean is it something
that...
well I mean there are these הלכות. halachos. If it's a practical
question and you did it and you need to ask a rabbi
or whatever, did I do מעילה meila or not, I mean you
would ask somebody. I mean it's like any question, who determines whether
you hit your spoon in your chicken pot and whether it's כשר
kosher or טרף treif or whether you waited twenty-four hours and is
it בן יומו ben yomo or whatever? So the person who has
the relevant issues asks the פסק. psak.
I don't know, but before those involved would it be like a
checkpoint did you do it right? Up to this point would people
be asked or...
I mean I'm sure you would investigate like you investigate all הלכה
halacha questions. I don't think there'd be an a priori test, yeah.
For example, where you drink from a metal כלי שרת. kli shares.
So I do that, I've gained a פרוטה pruta of benefit, of
הנאה, hana'ah, but I haven't caused any loss so I would not
need to pay anything but I should bring an אשם? asham?
No, no, no, you pay back right and that's exactly and again
we will talk much more about this in the future but and
that's why...
I pay the benefit?
Correct, it's the benefit, correct. It is important to realize that there
are, you know, it's easy to think, rather than try to conflate
it, it's easy to think that there are two categories. Stealing, where
I pay back what I stole, and there the object has to
be worth a פרוטה, pruta, or benefit that I wasn't entitled to
where I pay back what I benefited, even if הקדש hekdesh did
not lose out. Correct. Got it, okay. All right, so those are
the basic concepts and now we continue in the גמרא Gemara and
that's why yesterday's דף daf was a lot focusing on this idea
that yes, these problems about שחיטה בדרום shechta badarom etc. are obviously
it's פסול pasul but
still
עלו לא ירדו alu lo yerdu which is, and therefore we are
not, it
is still קדשי השם kodshei hashem and מעילה meila is still relevant.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes, wraps this up because רבא's
Rava position still was that if, that... right...
right... so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, איתיבי רב יוסף,
eiseivi Rav Yosef, we are on ג עמוד א, gimmel amud aleph,
about six, seven lines down. איתיבי רב יוסף לרבא. eiseivi Rav Yosef
le-Rava. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked רבא Rava who said עלו
לא ירדו alu lo yerdu if you שחט shachted it in the
wrong place. חדא מיגו חדא וחדא מיגו חדא. chada migu chada ve-chada
migu chada. One based on one and one based on one, which
means that we're going to string three משניות mishnayos together, learn something
from משנה mishna A which will clarify what משנה mishna B is
talking about and once we've clarified that we'll learn something from משנה
mishna B which will clarify what משנה mishna C is talking about
and then I'll be able to ask you a question from משנה
mishna C. Okay? So that's חדא מיגו חדא וחדא מיגו חדא. chada
migu chada ve-chada migu chada. I'll learn A, I'll learn B from
A, and C from B and then I'll be able to ask
you my question. Let's take a look at what this question is.
וכולן אין מטמאין בגדים בבית הבליעה. ve-chulan ein mitamin begadim beveit hablia.
So we have a משנה mishna that says that if you שחט
shacht the bird in the wrong place, whether it's an עולת העוף
olas ha-of or חטאת העוף, chatas ha-of, it's supposed to be above,
you did below, below you were supposed to be above, so if
you really did a, if you really did the מליקה melika of
the bird, what would the bird be if it weren't a קרבן?
korban? It would be a נבילה. neveila. And the הלכה halacha of
a bird that's a נבילה neveila is that if you eat it,
it makes you טמא tamei when you swallow. So say that it's
לא מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה, lo mitame begadim beveit hablia, it doesn't
make you and your clothes טמא tamei when you swallow it, is
a way of saying that it does not have a הלכה halacha
of נבילה. neveila. Okay? At least for certain purposes. Now you might
have thought that if I do a פסול מליקה, psul melika, I
do it in the wrong place, it is a נבילה, neveila, I
did a פסול מליקה. psul melika. They say no, again because of
פסולו בקודש, psulo bakodesh, it's really a פסול psul in the ritual,
it wasn't like you did it outside of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, it was a technical פסול psul of how you did the
ritual, that's called פסולו בקודש. psulo bakodesh. So therefore it does not
completely change its identity. We don't say it's like you strangled it.
Okay? You did a פסול מליקה, pasul melika, but nevertheless it's enough
in the ballpark, we're not going to consider it a נבילה. neveila.
Okay, so וכולן, ve-chulan, all of the birds that you did incorrectly,
אין מטמאין בגדים בבית הבליעה. ein mitamin begadim beveit hablia. They still
will not make you and your clothes טמא, tamei, they're not going
to be considered a נבילה neveila even though you did an incorrect
מליקה. melika. ומועלין
בהן, u-moalin bahen, and there's still an איסור מעילה. issur meila. Okay,
because again, it's פסולו בקודש, psulo bakodesh, right? Although it cannot be
brought as a קרבן korban now, there still is going to be
an איסור מעילה. issur meila. חוץ מחטאת העוף שעשאה למטה כמעשה חטאת
העוף לשם
חטאת. chutz me-chatas ha-of she-asa'ah lemata kema'aseh chatas ha-of leshem chatas. With
one exception of when you did everything right. You thought he did
everything wrong, but if you did a חטאת chatas below on the
bottom half of the מזבח mizbeach for the sake of a חטאת,
chatas, which is exactly what you're supposed to do, then what's the
הלכה halacha of חטאת העוף? chatas ha-of? What do you do after
you've brought a חטאת העוף? chatas ha-of? What do you do with
the meat? The כהנים Kohanim eat it.
You eat it, חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of.
So כהנים Kohanim eat it. So therefore the one case of a
bird that isn't מעילה meila is a חטאת העוף chatas ha-of done
correctly, because after it's done correctly, the meat can be... by כהנים
kohanim and therefore there's no מעילה me'ilah by the meat. Okay, what?
It has to be. So anyway, okay, but bracket that, forget that.
So that's actually...
Can a regular person eat it, it's not מעילה? me'ilah? No, that's
what we said. That's an איסור זרות, issur zarut, but it's not
an איסור מעילה. issur me'ilah. Okay, so therefore, okay, so bracket חטאת
העוף, chatat ha'of, that just means if it's done correctly then it's
היתר אכילה hetter achilah and it's not and it's not מעילה. me'ilah.
But the basic point is an עוף of done incorrectly still has
an איסור issur of מעילה me'ilah because it's פסולה בקודש psula bakodesh
because it's so that type of a problem is not enough to
take it out of מעילה, me'ilah, to take it out of קדשי
השם. kodshei Hashem. Now it says, וקתני עלוייה, v'katani iluyei, and we
have another משנה mishnah that sort of essentially references this: כל שפסולה
בקודש, kol shepsula bakodesh, any type of thing that's called פסולה בקודש,
psula bakodesh, which you know, is basically as I've been saying, it's
not something that preceded, it's not done out of the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, it's a technical problem of how you did some of
the rituals, you did them incorrectly, אינה מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה. eina
metamei begadim b'veit habliah. When you make that type of mistake by
a bird, we're not going to consider it a נבלה, neveilah, although
you did a מליקה, melikah, the fact is because it was you're
basically in the ballpark, it's not it's not going to be considered
a נבלה neveilah and won't cause טומאה בבית הבליעה. tumah b'veit habliah.
So what did we get from that משנה? mishnah? That's exactly what
we described in the previous משנה. mishnah. You slaughtered, you did the
מליקה melikah in the wrong place, it's not מטמא בבגדים. metamei b'vegadim.
What we got from it is the phrase of פסולה בקודש. psula
bakodesh. The first משנה mishnah did just describe what you did wrong—wrong
place. The second משנה mishnah conceptualizes it as פסולה בקודש. psula bakodesh.
So a type of a technical problem of where you did it
is considered פסולה בקודש psula bakodesh and therefore it is still going
to it's not going to be considered a נבלה neveilah and it's
still going to be in the category of
מעילה. me'ilah. Now we get to משנה mishnah number three:
וכל שלא היה פסולה בקודש, v'chol shelo hayah psula bakodesh, I'm sorry,
I didn't finish the, וכל שלא היה פסולה בקודש, v'chol shelo hayah
psula bakodesh, and if the פסול psul was not בקודש, bakodesh, again
meaning like as a technical ritual פסול psul of how you did
some of the עבודה, avodah, but you did it outside, you strangled
it, something of that nature, מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה, metamei begadim b'veit
habliah, that would be a נבלה. neveilah. Okay, so you see that
the concept is פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, it doesn't make it it
doesn't get it out of the מעילה me'ilah category. וקתני, v'katani, and
here we have משנה mishnah number three: כל שהיה פסולה בקודש אם
עלו לא ירדו. kol shehayah psula bakodesh im alu lo yerdu.
Anything that's in the category of פסולה בקודש psula bakodesh means that
once it goes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, it doesn't come down. So
now you string the three משניות mishnayot together, what do you have
as a conclusion? If it's פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, therefore there's still
מעילה. me'ilah. And if it's פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, it doesn't go
off the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Now what did רבא Rava say? רבא Rava
said when you slaughtered it in the wrong place, right,
it has to go down, right? If it has to go down,
that means that we're not calling it פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, right?
Because the principle is if it's פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, it doesn't
go down if it was put up. If we're not calling it
פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, then the משנה mishnah said when it's not
פסולה בקודש psula bakodesh essentially, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Okay, so therefore
how can רבא Rava say, all of this was a very nice
way of throwing through the משניות, mishnayot, the power of the sort
of argument that was made yesterday, which was: look, if you have
to take it off the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you're really saying it's out
of the ballpark of קדושה. kedushah. I mean again technically it has
קדושה, kedushah, but it's out of the ballpark of קדשי השם kodshei
Hashem and therefore how can you say there still is מעילה? me'ilah?
And here we've proven that. We've said if
it's called פסולה בקודש psula bakodesh
you leave it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. If it's not called פסולה
בקודש psula bakodesh you take it off. And that פסולה בקודש psula
bakodesh is also a function of whether there's מעילה me'ilah still or
not. So if רבא Rava says you take these things in our
משנה mishnah off the מזבח, mizbe'ach, then he's saying it's not פסולה
בקודש. psula bakodesh. If it's not פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, how can
you say that there's still going to be מעילה? me'ilah? So it
was a nice way of proving that if you take it down
from the מזבח, mizbe'ach, there is you cannot still say it's קדשי
השם kodshei Hashem and there's going to be מעילה. me'ilah. And the
גמרא Gemara takes this as an absolute proof. תיובתא דרבא תיובתא. tiyuvta
de'Rava tiyuvta. Understood and רבא Rava ends that discussion. You're right and
that actually is a very good now because we have a clear
idea of the concept of קדשי השם. kodshei Hashem. Meaning besides the
basic קרבן korban what constitutes קדשי השם kodshei Hashem is it's going
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, is that even if it's פסול, pasul, if
it's still enough in the category פסולה בקודש psula bakodesh that it
gets to stay up on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, then it's still קדשי
השם kodshei Hashem for מעילה. me'ilah. Once it doesn't it's not even
close enough for that and you'll even take it off the מזבח
mizbe'ach then already it's going to be what do you call it?
Then already it's going to be considered no longer קדשי השם. kodshei
Hashem. It still has קדושה, kedushah, but not קדשי השם kodshei Hashem
for the purpose of מעילה. me'ilah. Now the interesting point of course
here is that רבא Rava in order to counter that argument yesterday
said, Oh no, no, but מדרבנן mi'drabbanan it has it. But here
the point is that since the משנה mishnah is saying אין מעילה
ein me'ilah seems to be a categorical statement, which is there's no
מעילה me'ilah not דאורייתא de'oraita and not דרבנן drabbanan and therefore this
is the rule. If it's not פסולה בקודש, psula bakodesh, if you
take it which is indicated by you take it off the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, then no מעילה me'ilah neither דאורייתא de'oraita or דרבנן. drabbanan.
Is there no such thing as מעילה דרבנן me'ilah drabbanan or...?
No, no, there is מעילה דרבנן me'ilah drabbanan but not in this
case. Got it. Okay, and we will keep that. Okay. Now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: והא דפליגי ברבא ורב יוסף, v'ha d'peligi
b'Rava v'Rav Yosef, this debate of רבא Rava and רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, what's the case of שחטה בדרום, shachatah b'darom, do you have
to take it off the מזבח mizbeach or
not? קשיא ליה לרבי אלעזר. kashya lei l'Rabbi Elazar. רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar took for granted one of the sides. We're not sure which
one, but it's clear he took for granted one. Why? Because he's
going to have a question that assumes that this more basic issue
doesn't have to be addressed. Okay, let's take a look. דאמר רבי
אלעזר, d'amar Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says, עולת במת יחיד
שהכניסה לפנים. olas bamas yachid shehichnisah lifnim. You have an עולה olah
that you sanctified for your own private במת יחיד. bamah yachid. This
was at a time where there was still a central משכן, mishkan,
but there was not yet a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and therefore
you were allowed your במת יחיד. bamah yachid. This was when let's
say the משכן mishkan was in נוב וגבעון. Nob and Givon. You
were allowed it was שעת היתר במות. she'at heter bamos. You were
allowed your במת יחיד, bamah yachid, but there was also a central
place as well which you could bring which had many more laws.
When you brought on your במת יחיד bamah yachid you didn't need
a כהן, kohen, you didn't need כלי שרת, kley shares, you didn't
need to do it בצפון b'tzafon if it was an עולה. olah.
You had a lot of latitude. If you brought it in the
central place, A, you could bring certain more קרבנות, korbanos, you know,
חובות hovos and so on, and קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, and number
two, it had all of the requirements. So you sanctified your עולה
olah for your private במת יחיד, bamah yachid, which would have been
allowed then for you to do it any place you wanted, not
בצפון, b'tzafon, not whatever. And then what did you do? You said,
hey, look, I'm close enough to נוב Nob anyway. Let's go ahead
and bring it to נוב, Nob, might as well. And you brought
it to the central מזבח. mizbeach. שהכניסה לפנים. shehichnisah lifnim.
Now that you're bringing it to the central מזבח, mizbeach, you're going
to have to be מקריב makriv it by their rules. Even though
when you sanctified it, it was for your במת יחיד, bamah yachid,
which would have allowed you more latitude. But now that you're in
the central place, it has to follow more of the rules. So
the הלכה halacha is קלטוה מחיצות לכל דבר. kaltuha mechitzos l'kol davar.
The walls of the place of the of the נוב וגבעון Nob
and Givon of the central of the central מזבח, mizbeach, you know,
the the environs, that's collect that's sort of absorbs it.
Which means you're now in that space, you have to go by
that rule, and therefore the rules now apply. Okay, so the question
is let's say, however, although the rules apply, you violated the rules
and you went by the rules that you would have been had
been able to do out when you brought had you brought it
on your במת יחיד. bamah yachid. And that's רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar's
question. So בעי רבי אלעזר, ba'ei Rabbi Elazar, so רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar asks, עולת במות יחיד שהכניסוה שנפסלה עלו מהו שירדו. olas bamos
yachid shehichnisua she'nifselah alu mah she-yardu.
What happens if it was נפסלה, nifselah, okay, and again the real
question here as רש"י Rashi explains, it was not just סתם נפסלה.
stam nifselah. It was נפסלה nifselah in a way that wouldn't have
been a problem if it was my במת יחיד. bamah yachid. I
שחט shachted it in the south rather than in the north. Okay,
I took it out of the מקום המקדש. makom HaMikdash. If I'm
in a in במת יחיד bamah yachid there is no מקום המקדש.
makom HaMikdash. Okay, so I did some type of a פסול psul
which wouldn't have been a problem had it been the original, and
I now put it on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, does it get
to stay on the מזבח? mizbeach? Okay, so far that's an interesting
question. How much does it go by the original קדושה, kedusha, how
much does it go by where I brought it. But the fact
that we're asking that suggests that in a simple case where I
שחטה בדרום shachatah b'darom and put it on the מזבח, mizbeach, the
answer would be obvious. I want I'm asking a more interesting and
complex case about what if it was sanctified for a במת יחיד
bamah yachid which gives me more latitude, right? And then does it
get to stay on the מזבח? mizbeach? Which makes it sound like
it's obvious to me what the rule is in a more פרווה
parve vanilla case that you שחטה shachatah it in the wrong place
and put it on the מזבח. mizbeach. Yes.
Where was it established that the במת bamah in נוב וגבעון Nob
and Givon even had such a I don't recall.
The sense of מחיצות mechitzos and מקום. makom. It's the very very
end of זבחים. Zevachim. Like ממש mamash the last דף daf in
זבחים. Zevachim. Okay, so in about six and a half years when
we come back around. Okay,
so anyway, so so מדקמיבעיא ליה, mi'de'ka mibaya lei, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: מדקמיבעיא ליה mi'de'ka mibaya lei since he's asking
לחדא l'chada this question about what about the special case when it
was an עולה במת יחיד olah bamah yachid dot dot dot does
it go down, מכלל דאידך, michlal d'idach, sounds like the base case
of if it was שחטה בדרום shachatah b'darom and put on, פשיטא
ליה, pshita lei, אי כרבה אי כרב יוסף. i k'Rabbah i k'Rav
Yosef.
It's obvious to him what the הלכה halacha is, we don't know,
you could go either way. Now it wouldn't seem you could go
either way, it seemed like it should be that that's obvious and
it's no good and he wants to argue this might be better
because of the sanctity it gives you more latitude. The גמרא Gemara
will explain why in theory he could go either way. But but
the point is that it seems clear since he's asking such a
complicated question that he takes for granted what the standard case will
be. We don't know according to who and he's asking a complicated
question that's built on that. So
אי כרבה אי כרב יוסף. i k'Rabbah i k'Rav Yosef. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, חדא מיגו חדא קמיבעיא ליה, chada mi-go chada
ka mibaya lei, maybe he's asking maybe he doesn't know what the
answer is according to רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. But
you know, some people they're not happy asking straight questions. They have
to ask very convoluted questions. So he once said he's asking a
double question, he's saying first of all I want to know what
the הלכה halacha is in a base case of שחטה בדרום, shachatah
b'darom, עלו ירדו, alu yardu, and after I get that answer I
want to know what the הלכה halacha is in the special case
of במת יחיד. bamah yachid. So just because he asks the special
case doesn't mean he knows already the answer to the base case.
Okay, and now let's see how this could go either way. It
seems much more obvious one way, let's see how it could go
either way. So we'll start with the easier way. עד כאן לא
קאמר רבה התם אם על הירדן
אלא במחיצה
כתקנה פסלה Ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbah hatam im al hayarden ela
bimchitzah kitiknah paslah
שלא כתקנה לא פסלה. shelo kitiknah lo paslah. So meaning says like
this over there, it's like the language is a little funny, let
me see, אלא במחיצה כתקנה פסלה. ela bimchitzah kitiknah paslah. Why did
Rabbah say in the normal base case if you slaughtered in the
wrong place you have to take it down? Because everything was במחיצה
כתקנה. bimchitzah kitiknah. It was in the environment of the מקדש. Mikdash.
It was demanded to be בצפון. betzafon. You violated that, so now
it's really פסול, pasul, take it down. But you could say, but
you could say if it was שלא כתקנה, shelo kitiknah, if it
was not a normal case of the normal requirements, meaning it was
the type of thing that originally didn't require to be in מקום
המקדש, mekom haMikdash, was קדושה kedushah for a במה, bamah, maybe he
would say לא פסלה, lo paslah, it's not so bad. Right? That's
the easiest way to understand why the more complex case. Normally the
rule is you slaughter in the wrong place, take it down. Ah,
but if it was sanctified for a במת יחיד bamat yachid that
gave you a lot of latitude, and you just chose to bring
it here into the מקום המקדש, mekom haMikdash, maybe it's not so
bad and maybe you can keep it up. That's probably the easy
way to understand it. Now we'll see even according to רב יוסף
Rav Yosef why you could say that this case should be different.
או דלמא אפילו רב יוסף דאמר אם עלה לא ירד. O dilma
afilu Rav Yosef d'amar im alah lo yerad. Even Rav Yosef who
says in a standard case once it goes up it stays up
and doesn't come down, maybe this case is worse when you sanctify
it for a במת יחיד. bamat yachid. Why should it be worse?
Because we'll say the following. מחיצה כתקנה קלטה. Mechitzah kitiknah kaltah. Not
פסלה, paslah, but קלטה. kaltah. When everything was done in the מקום
המקדש mekom haMikdash and sanctified for the מקום המקדש, mekom haMikdash, then
we say that being in the מחיצות, mechitzot, if it were, being
in the environment, being in the, you know, in the, you know,
in the area of the מקדש, Mikdash, that sort of absorbed it.
That said you're one of us now and therefore if you go
on the מזבח mizbeach you get to stay on the מזבח mizbeach
because you've been done in the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, so that sort
of gave it the almost the right to stay on the מזבח
mizbeach because it was all done in the מקדש. Mikdash. However, I
would say שלא כתקנה, shelo kitiknah, if you did not start with
it being a מקדש קרבן, Mikdash korban, you started with it being
a במה קרבן, bamah korban, you started sanctifying for outside, then you
don't have any entitlement, any right, to stay on the מזבח mizbeach
because you fundamentally, you the קרבן, korban, did not fundamentally start as
a מקדש קרבן. Mikdash korban. And therefore you would, therefore שלא כתקנה
לא קלטה. shelo kitiknah lo kaltah. It would not absorb it. I
understand, so that's what it's saying. It's you could ask an interesting
question either way. You could say the פסול psul of דרום darom
is not so bad because it was a type of קרבן korban
that initially could have been done out of the מקדש Mikdash and
could have been done בדרום. badarom. On the other hand, the sense
that it gets, if it's in the מקדש Mikdash it stays in
the מקדש, Mikdash, and it, you know, and its being on the
מזבח mizbeach entitles it to stay on the מזבח mizbeach is less
true because it didn't start as a מקדש קרבן. Mikdash korban. So
that's the... so he says you could ask it either way. So
just because he's asking a more complex question, it's not clear how
he would decide between רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף Rav Yosef of
whether עלה לא ירד alah lo yerad or not.
It means it sounds like he's getting penalized by bringing it to
the מקדש. Mikdash. I mean, I would think that when someone's מקדיש
makdish even for a במה, bamah, he's not saying I'm not going
to bring it to the מקדש. Mikdash.
It's like, you know, I'm מקדיש makdish normally, I'm going to bring
it where I want. I understand. It's not about being penalized, it's
about identity. If it's identified as a מקדש קרבן, Mikdash korban, it
has... it more makes sense that once it's there you don't remove
it from that status. If fundamentally it's an outsider, then it's not
such a problem to remove it from there.
But if I'm מקדיש makdish it for either the במה bamah or
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I wouldn't stop the people who do
that at all. I would think it's like I'm מקדיש makdish it
סתם, stam, I'm going to bring it where I want.
Right, so that is an interesting question, which is to what degree
is there a specific sense of במת קדושה bamat kedushah or to
what degree, you know, and this makes it sound like there is,
because he's even asking. Let's say I'm מקדיש makdish סתם. stam. I
understand, so I don't know. That's a good
point. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תיקו. teiku. Okay, so we
don't know the answer to that. Okay, so now that is the
end of yesterday's סוגיא. sugya. That's the end of the debate of
רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף Rav Yosef whether עלה לא ירד. alah
lo yerad. And again just to remind us that this is important
for the general principle here for קדשי השם, kodshei Hashem, which is
the basic point of our first משנה, mishnah, even if it's פסול,
pasul, it's still קדשי השם. kodshei Hashem. But what type of פסול?
psul? Only a פסול psul that's called פסולו בקודש. psulo bakodesh. Not
something that completely is like you choke it or it dies or
it's outside of the מקדש. Mikdash. It's more of a technical problem
that the rituals weren't done correctly. And the test case is עלה
לא ירד. alah lo yerad. If it's allowed to stay on the
מזבח mizbeach once it was put there, that shows it's enough within
the category of קדשי השם kodshei Hashem because at least it could
stay on the מזבח mizbeach even though it shouldn't be there. And
therefore there will still be מעילה. meilah. So that is the basic
principle. פסולו בקודש psulo bakodesh stays on the מזבח mizbeach and there
is מעילה. meilah. Now, from now we move on to another statement.
And it's important at this stage to remind ourselves another thing that
was about the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah wasn't only saying it's
not like it was... It shouldn't be there and therefore there will
still be מעילה. me'ilah. So that is the basic principle: פסול בקודש
psul bakodesh stays on the מזבח mizbeach and there is מעילה. me'ilah.
Now, from now we move on to another statement. It's an important
and good point at this stage to remind ourselves another thing that
was about the משנה. mishna. The משנה mishna wasn't only saying it's
not like it was choked and died and is no longer קודשי
השם. kodshei Hashem. The משנה mishna was also saying another thing about
when things are done בפסול, b'psul, and that's the following: it said
that all קודשי קודשים kodshei kodashim if they were done even if
they were done even if they were done בפסול b'psul have מעילה,
me'ilah, which means the following: a normal קרבנות korbanot like a חטאת
chatas wouldn't always have מעילה. me'ilah. When would a חטאת chatas stop
having מעילה? me'ilah? What'd I tell you?
Bring out the blood,
after you sprinkle the blood, there stops being מעילה me'ilah on the
meat. But, you okay Rivka? Okay.
But if, but if it was done בפסול, b'psul, like wrong מקום,
makom, פיגול, pigul, etc., then you're never going to מתיר matir the
meat, right? So it's not like you sprinkled the blood and then
the meat became טמא tamei or נותר, notar, then there was a
moment the meat was מותר. muttar. But if it were done בפסול,
b'psul, like שחט shecht in the wrong place or פיגול pigul or
whatever, the meat is never מותר. muttar. And therefore, part of the
חידוש chiddush is not just that it doesn't become non-מעילה, me'ilah, part
of the חידוש chiddush is that it stays מעילה me'ilah forever, even
the meat is going to be מעילה me'ilah because once it was
done בפסול, b'psul, the meat was never made מותר muttar through the
זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. And that now is going to be our
focus about what types of cases might I say that even though
it's sort of the opposite, even though technically it wasn't מתיר matir
the meat, it was close enough and maybe actually there won't be
מעילה me'ilah by the meat. Okay, so again that our point of
the משנה mishna is it's close enough that it still is קודשי
השם kodshei Hashem and פסולה בקודש לא תרד. psulah bakodesh lo tared.
The bottom line, because it wasn't מתיר matir the meat, it retains
מעילה me'ilah on the meat. So let's take a look now at
the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב גידל
אמר רב, Amar Rav Gidel amar Rav, so רב גידל Rav Gidel
said in the name of רב, Rav, yes? Does that mean when
the כהנים kohanim eat that meat they're doing מעילה me'ilah then? Yeah,
as in yeah, absolutely. Okay. אמר רב גידל אמר רב: זריקת פיגול
אינה מוציאה מידי מעילה.
Amar Rav Gidel amar
Rav:
zrikas pigul eina motzi midei me'ilah. If you did זריקה zrika of
the דם dam with a מחשבת פיגול machsheves pigul to eat the
meat חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano or חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, it
is not considered a valid זריקה, zrika, which means what? אינה מוציאה
מידי מעילה בקודשי קודשים. Eina motzi midei me'ilah b'kodshei kodashim. If you
have a חטאת chatas or an אשם, asham, it doesn't say the
meat is no longer מעילה, me'ilah, right? Because even though it was
a זריקה, zrika, doesn't matter it was a זריקת פיגול, zrikas pigul,
and the meat still remains אסור, assur, it doesn't become מותר לכהנים,
muttar l'kohanim, so there's still מעילה me'ilah by the meat of קודשי
קודשים. kodshei kodashim. And also, there is one way in which the
זריקת הדם zrikas hadam turns something into מעילה. me'ilah. What is that
case? By קודשים קלים. kodshim kalim. After the זריקה, zrika, the אימורין
emurin do have מעילה. me'ilah. So it also doesn't work for that,
ואינו מביא לידי מעילה בקודשים קלים. veino mevi'ei lidei me'ilah b'kodshim kalim.
It doesn't make the אימורין emurin into מעילה. me'ilah. So all of
that seems pretty straightforward and basically seems to be the point of
our משנה. mishna. Our משנה mishna says that once it's done בפסול,
b'psul, then it's not, it doesn't change, it doesn't make, you can't
say the meat is no longer מעילה me'ilah because it was all
פסול. pasul. And he's also adding the idea that by קודשים קלים
kodshim kalim you can't say the אימורין emurin do have מעילה me'ilah
because it never had a kosher זריקה zrika to change the status.
So what's the חידוש chiddush here saying that it's essentially the משנה?
mishna? So תוספות Tosafos says the חידוש chiddush is the following: you
will remember that there, and actually did we say this yesterday? Yeah,
we did say it yesterday. That there's a principle by פיגול, pigul,
right? Remember when we were learning זבחים Zevachim we could never get
out of פיגול? pigul? Okay. Anyway, so there was a principle about
פיגול pigul that says something is not considered נטפל לפיגולו nitpal l'pigulo
עד שיהיה רצוי לפיגולו. ad she'yehei ratzuy l'pigulo. You have to do
all the other עבודות avodos correctly in order for it to have
a status of פיגול. pigul. You could do it with מחשבת פיגול,
machsheves pigul, but if you did the other עבודות avodos with another
פסול, psul, like חוץ, chutz, like you were thinking about, you know,
about instead of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano you're thinking about חוץ למקומו,
chutz limkomo, you were טמא tamei
or you didn't do the other עבודות, avodos, it would never become
פיגול. pigul. פיגול Pigul you have to finish it up correctly and
לא ירצה lo yeratzeh means that ultimately it has to have been
fit for being מרצה mirtzeh except for the פיגול pigul part. And
that's the concept that we call מרצה לפיגולו. mirtzeh l'pigulo. It's enough
of a ריצוי ritzuy to establish it as פיגול. pigul. So תוספות
Tosafos says that would have been the הוה אמינא hava amina here.
Our משנה mishna thought about a מחשבת פיגול machsheves pigul by שחיטה.
shechita. Fine, that clearly it's not going to be fine. But he
said let's say your מחשבת פיגול machsheves pigul was at זריקה. zrika.
Since it's the זריקה zrika itself which also is considered to be
מרצה לפיגולו, mirtzeh l'pigulo, it's considered to count enough to make it
a good פיגול, pigul, right? The זריקה. zrika. So therefore maybe it
also counts in all these הלכות halachos of מעילה. me'ilah. Right? Is
that clear? Meaning in a variation. So the general, not this. So
the general rule is is that when things are done בפסול, b'psul,
it doesn't change the status for מעילה. me'ilah. קודשי קודשים, Kodshei kodashim,
the meat of קודשי קודשים kodshei kodashim remain מעילה, me'ilah, the אימורין
emurin of קודשים קלים kodshim kalim don't become מעילה. me'ilah. The חידוש
chiddush of רב גידל אמר רב Rav Gidel amar Rav is that's
true even when the זריקה, zrika, even in the case of זריקת
פיגול. zrikas pigul. I might have thought that different because in זריקת
פיגול zrikas pigul is considered to be מרצה לפיגולו, mirtzeh l'pigulo, maybe
I'll consider that too to be as if it were a good
זריקה zrika for other הלכות, halachos, and the answer is no. So
that's the גמרא. Gemara. but at the end of the day, it's
just saying that it follows the rule of our משנה Mishnah *Mishna*.
Everything else must have been done right, that means up to that
point,
including the זריקה zrikah *zrika*.
Not that you finished and then you went back and you realized
one thing was wrong.
What do you mean?
Like if you had a מחשבת פיגול machshevet piggul. *machsheves pigul* during
שחיטה shechitah *shechita*.
Yes. Then you did the קבלה *kabala* and the הולכה *holacha* and
the זריקה zrikah *zrika* all correctly. Yes. And if you don't finish
it or if you stop, it's not פיגול piggul, *pigul*, or if
you finish it with another פסול pasul *psul* it's not פיגול Piggul
*pigul*.
So right at the מחשבת פיגול machshevet piggul, *machsheves pigul* during שחיטה
shechitah *shechita* you would stop.
Correct, exactly. Exactly. Right. In terms of the status of the meat
it wouldn't be פיגול piggul *pigul* exactly. So here the point is,
since we do have this concept of מרצה לפיגולו mirtzeh l'piggulo *meratzeh
la-pigulo*, as this way תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* explains it, maybe I would
say that that זריקה zrikah, *zrika* is considered meaningful for הלכות מעילה
meilah *hilchos me'ila*. And the answer is it is not. Okay, now
we're going to spend the rest of today and tomorrow focusing on
this statement. So let's take a look. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. אינו מוציא מידי מעילה meilah, בקדשי קדשים *Eino motzi midei me'ila
be-kodshei kodashim*, I would just say that. יתיב אביי וקאמר להא שמעתא
*Yasiv Abaye ve-ka-amar le-ha shema'ta*. So אביי *Abaye* was sitting over and
telling over this tradition in the name of רב גידל אמר רב
*Rav Gidal amar Rav*. איתיביה רב פפא לאביי *Eisivieh Rav Pappa le-Abaye*.
רב פפא *Rav Pappa* challenged אביי *Abaye* with the following statement. משנה
*Mishna*: השוחט את התודה בפנים ולחמה בחוץ *Ha-shochet es ha-toda bifnim ve-lachmah
bachutz*. So when you do the שחיטה shechitah. *shechita* of a תודה
toda *toda*, תודה *toda* comes with bread. So the bread is linked
to the תודה *toda* and we say with the שחיטה shechitah *shechita*
of the תודה *toda* that brings the bread to a status
of קדושת הגוף kdushas haguf, *kedushas ha-guf*. Until the תודה *toda* is
שחט shacht *shacht* the bread only has קדושת דמים *kedushas damim*. It's
owned by the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, but it only is considered
intrinsic קדושה kdusha *kedusha*, קדושת הגוף kdushas haguf, *kedushas ha-guf* when the
קרבן *korban* is שחט shacht *shacht*. So if the bread is in
the wrong place, it's outside of the מקדש *Mikdash*, it's therefore not
connected to the קרבן *korban* and the שחיטה shechitah. *shechita* of the
קרבן *korban* doesn't affect it. Okay, so if השוחט את התודה בפנים
ולחמה בחוץ לא קדש הלחם *ha-shochet es ha-toda bifnim ve-lachmah bachutz lo
kidesh ha-lachem*, the bread was outside of the מקדש *Mikdash*, לא קדש
הלחם *lo kidesh ha-lachem*, the bread does not become קדושת הגוף *kedushas
ha-guf*. שחטה עד שלא קרמו פניה בתנור *Shachatah ad shelo kermu paneha
ba-tanur*. The bread also has to be considered לחם lechem *lachem*. To
be considered לחם lechem *lachem* means that a crust forms in the
oven. So if the crust had not yet formed, it's not yet
לחם lechem, *lachem*. ואפילו קרמו כולן חוץ מאחת מהן *Ve-afilu kermu kulan
chutz me-achas meihen*, even if all except one, but you need all
the bread to be present and in that case it's not considered
all as present because one doesn't have a crust, לא קדש הלחם
*lo kidesh ha-lachem*. None of it becomes קודש *kodesh*. It's all or
nothing. Okay? So the שחיטה shechitah. *shechita* makes the bread קודש *kodesh*
when it is in the right place and it is bread. Now,
it goes up. So far not relevant for us. שחטה חוץ לזמנה
וחוץ למקומה *Shachatah chutz lizmano ve-chutz limkomo*. You שחט shacht *shacht* the
קרבן *korban* with a thought of פיגול piggul *pigul*. What does that
do to the קדושה kdusha *kedusha* of the bread? So the הלכה
halachah *halacha* is קדש הלחם *kidesh ha-lachem*. It still sanctifies the bread.
So again, here a שחיטת פיגול shechitat piggul *shechitas pigul* is considered
to be a significant שחיטה shechitah *shechita* for קדושה kdusha *kedusha* purposes,
and presumably if it's קדושה *kedusha* purposes, it would translate to מעילה
meilah, *me'ila* purposes. אלמא פיגול piggul מהני לדין מעילה meilah *Alma pigul
mahni ledin me'ila*. פיגול piggul *Pigul* can make it relevant for מעילה
meilah *me'ila*. Now, it's important to clarify a point that תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafos* says, which is that this is an argument by analogy. It's
not really, and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to actually
challenge the analogy later because he says the bread never becomes מעילה
meilah *me'ila*. Why does the bread never become מעילה meila. *me'ila*? Because
why is it never מעילה meila. *me'ila* by the bread? Any thoughts?
Just it's edible. The bread is like the meat of the תודה
*toda*, right? It's מותר באכילה *mutar ba-achila*, either to the בעלים *be'alim*
or some of the bread goes to the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*. The
bread is never קדשי השם *kodshei Hashem*. So the argument isn't that
the bread becomes מעילה meila *me'ila*. The argument is by analogy. שחיטת
פיגול shechitat piggul *Shechitas pigul* is still significant enough to raise קדושה
*kedusha*. So therefore why do we say that, you know, זריקת פיגול
zrikat piggul. *zrikas pigul* or other types of things, even if they're
פיגול piggul *pigul*, should still be able to make it, you know,
effect its מעילה meila? *me'ila* status, as if it were done correctly?
That's the question. So let's see what happens. אישתיק *Ishtik*. He was
silent. He didn't have an answer. דא טאקע א גוטע קשיא *De-ha
takeh a guteh kashya*. יתיב קמיה דרבי אבא *Yasiv kamei de-Rabbi Abba*.
So then he went to רבי אבא *Rabbi Abba* and sort of
asked him this issue. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, he said back to
אביי *Abaye*, אמר ליה רב אשי לרבא Amar lei Rav Ashi le-Rava.
*Amar lei Rav Ashi le-Rava*. Here's where רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav
Ashi* could say back to רבא *Rava*. Because why? I'm sorry, I
skipped a line. Right. אמר ליה בזריקה bizrikah. *Amar lei bi-zrika*. He
said, no, the difference is about זריקה zrikah. *zrika*. Now, what does
that mean? Again, I'm going to read this more like תוספות Tosafos
*Tosafos*. It's a complicated גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as you might not be
surprised with all this רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafos*. So I'm
going to read a little bit more like תוספות *Tosafos*. תוספות *Tosafos*
says what I told you before. He says שחיטה shechitah *shechita* is
different than זריקה zrikah *zrika*. Okay? Now, the because the focus we
were having was that זריקת פיגול zrikas pigul, *zrikas pigul*, you know,
and whether that has an impact. The problem is is that the
argument is the other way, is that the case is the other
way, right? In our משנה *Mishna*, our משנה *Mishna* was talking about
שחיטת פיגול shechitas pigul *shechitas pigul*. Right? Remember that? Our משנה *Mishna*
talked about שחיטת פיגול shechitas pigul *shechitas pigul* and our משנה *Mishna*
said it didn't have an impact for מעילה meila *me'ila*. תוספות *Tosafos*
says the only הוה אמינא *hava amina* was maybe זריקה Zrikah. *zrika*
would be better. Okay? So how does that, and the answer is
it isn't. זריקה zrikah. *zrika*'s just like שחיטה shechitah *shechita*, it doesn't
affect פיגול piggul *pigul*. So how do we answer the לחם lechem
*lachem* case? The לחם lechem *lachem* case said שחיטה shechitah. *shechita* worked,
right? שחיטה shechita *shechita* had an impact. And we're saying זריקה zrikah.
doesn't, but we're not just saying זריקה zrikah doesn't, we're saying even
זריקה zrikah. doesn't. We're saying nothing has an impact, so you still
have the question about if nothing changes for פיגול, piggul, that's what
our משנה says, why did שחיטה shechita here work to sanctify the
bread? So that is certainly a question and what רש"י Rashi says
and I'll try to again tell you this without overly complicating it,
I'm sure it was too late for that, but what רש"י Rashi
says is is that the and this is what becomes very complicated
for רש"י Rashi is he says the answer is like this. פיגול
piggul, only as we said becomes real פיגול piggul. when the עבודה
avodah is finished. Okay and therefore what רש"י is saying is you
know why קידוש הלחם kidush halechem because it's not yet really פיגול
Piggul yet. You שחט-ed it with מחשבת פיגול. machshevet piggul, תוספות also
might be thinking something like this. You שחט-ed it with מחשבת פיגול,
machshevet piggul but it's not yet full פיגול piggul until you finish
the עבודה. avodah. So therefore the לחם can be sanctified because that
happens at the moment of שחיטה shechita and at that stage the
פיגול piggul has not yet been vested as it were. So although
it was מחשבת פיגול, machshevet piggul, it wasn't full פיגול piggul until
the זריקה, zrikah. but the לחם gained its status at the time
of שחיטה. shechita And that's why it works. It worked because you
didn't have זריקה. zrikah. If you did go ahead with the זריקה
zerika then what? Whether it would retroactively change it is not clear,
but the point is maybe not. Maybe it worked at the time
and therefore that, it works because it happens at the moment of
שחיטה shechita and it's not full פיגול piggul yet. But I'm talking
about when it becomes full פיגול, piggul when you שחט-ed it with
מחשבת פיגול machshavas pigul, and you finished, or when you did זריקת
פיגול. piggul So therefore when you finish and it does become full
פיגול, piggul then it does not change the status from מעילה meila?
because here's the key point: when does מעילה, meila what moment of
time of the עבודה avodah of קרבנות korbanot does something's status change
for מעילה, right? What status changes? Either the meat of קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim becomes non-מעילה because it could be eaten by the כהנים
or the אימורים imurin become yes מעילה because it goes to the
מזבח. mizbeiach. At what moment is that? זריקה. zerika And that seems
to be the answer. He says לחם, that's a הלכה halacha of
שחיטה. shechita There the status could change because it's not yet full
פיגול. piggul פיגול piggul doesn't happen fully yet at שחיטה. shechita What
we're talking about, the critical moment of possibly changing the status is
זריקה. zerika. At that moment it is פיגול piggul and therefore the
status does not change. Okay? So that, I hope that's clear. By
by there שחיטה shechita. is the important status and therefore פיגול piggul
is not yet fully meaningful and therefore we can talk about maybe
a שחיטת פיגול shechitas pigul having some impact, but when we talk
about מעילה what we care about is זריקה. zerika And at the
זריקה zerika moment the פיגול piggul is fully in force and therefore
it will not have any impact. Okay so let's continue. All that
was in the word בזריקה. So, אמר ליה רב אשי לרבא. Amar
lei Rav Ashi le-Rava, So now now going to challenge this idea
about is something called פיגול piggul before it's finished? Is it called
פיגול piggul, because the answer was the שחיטה shechita, case of the
bread is better, it's not yet פיגול piggul really, it's only מחשבת
פיגול, piggul. it's not פיגול piggul until you're done. So is this
really true that something isn't and therefore we're able to change the
status and therefore the שחיטה shechita raised the status of the bread.
So is this really true that something isn't called פיגול piggul until
you're done? Let's take a look. Then it says like this, אמר
ליה רב אשי לרבא, והאמר עולא ve-ha-amar Ulla didn't עולא Ulla say
קומץ פיגול kometz piggul שהעלו לגבי מזבח she-he'elo legabei mizbeiach פקע פיגולו
ממנו. paka pigulo mimenu. Okay, that if you take a קומץ, kometz,
you did פיגול pigul on a מנחה minchah and then you took
the קומץ kometz from that מנחה, minchah, you thought to eat the
מנחה minchah חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano or חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and
then you took that קומץ kometz and you put it on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, so if it burns on the מזבח mizbeiach it's no
longer considered פיגול pigul which basically means לא תירד lo tayred and
it might even mean if it falls off you put it back
on, fine. We're not going to get into that idea about once
it's on the מזבח mizbeiach its פיגול pigul status changes. What we're
going to focus on is the following: וקמיצה היינו שחיטה. ve-kmitzah hainu
shechitah. If you did the קמיצה, kmitzah, right, that's like the שחיטה.
shechita, Now, okay fine, but then when you offered it that's like
the זריקה. zerika But no, the point is even before you offered
it how did we describe that thing in your hand? We called
it קומץ פיגול. kometz piggul. So you see you can call something
פיגול pigul even before the, now of course as תוספות says we
all admit that you're not חייב כרת chayav kares for eating it
until you do the זריקה. zrika Nobody is debating that idea that
the חיוב chiyuv of כרת kares for פיגול pigul. requires the זריקה.
zrika? Are you okay there? Yes. Okay. All right. Nobody is debating
that, that's a standard acceptance, right, you need הרצאה hartza'ah for פיגול,
pigul, you need to finish in order to be חייב כרת. chayav
kares. But his argument was we're not even going to label it
פיגול pigul until that moment and that's why שחיטת פיגול shechitas pigul
could work because we're not labeling it. But look, you labeled it!
You called it a קומץ פיגול! kometz piggul! Okay so וקמיצה היינו
שחיטה. ve-kmitzah hainu shechitah. What? אמרי Amrei אעסוקי דמסיק ליה פיגול. asokei
de-masik lei piggul. We're not being so technical, precise here. We called
it a קומץ פיגול kometz piggul we mean a קומץ kometz that
will become פיגול. pigul We don't exactly mean it's פיגול pigul yet.
But you're right, we're not going to label it פיגול pigul. at
this early stage. So the גמרא Gemara says והא קתני, ve-ha katani,
but we taught on that, now actually it's not קתני, katani, it's
really an אמורא-ic Amora statement. but it's interesting it says והקתני vehakatani
but anyway we taught on that statement דף י"ד עמוד א' daf
yud daled amud alef about the קומץ kometz אם אחרים מביא לידי
פגול הוא עצמו לא כל שכן? im acheirim mevi lidei piggul hu
atzmo lo kol shekein? If it causes other things to be פגול
piggul how much more so it itself which is a curious phrase
that the גמרא Gemara in זבחים Zevachim tries to figure out what
that means. But nevertheless the point is is that it's saying is
the act of קמיצה kemitzah when you're doing the קמיצה kemitzah you
define the שיריים shirayim as פגול piggul right and therefore it itself
should have the status. Again I'm not going to explain fully the
הלכתית halachic import of that and the גמרא Gemara in זבחים Zevachim
sort of turns it around but regardless the point is is that
it's saying it itself has the status of פגול. piggul. So again
it seems to be labeling it as פגול piggul from the moment
of קמיצה. kemitzah. So the גמרא says הא נמי איסורא דמטי ליה
לידי פגול. ha nami issura demati lei lidei piggul. Yeah don't drain
your cup about that. It doesn't mean precisely פגול. piggul. It means
it's something that's gonna become פגול piggul when you finish. So the
focus now here is again is something you're not חייב chayav in
פגול piggul for כרת kareis for eating it until it's done but
can we label it פגול? piggul? And the נפקא מינה nafka mina
is that this gave us the תירץ teretz for the bread that
when you do things at the moment of זריקה zrika and there's
a פגול piggul problem then it's already פגול piggul at the moment
of זריקה zrika and clearly it's not going to be meaningful to
change the status for it. Why is the שחיטה shechita meaningful for
the bread? Because that was there's a important moment with the שחיטה
shechita that's when the bread status changes and at that moment it
wasn't labeled פגול. piggul. So now that is our focus: are we
going to label something פגול piggul at an earlier stage at an
earlier stage? So now let's continue a little bit further. We have
a little short דף daf and it's good maybe we'll even get
ahead get our full דף daf ahead again. Anyway so not today.
So the גמרא says like this אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי. amar
lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi. So now רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי
והאמר אילפא מחלוקת בשתי עבודות. veha'amar Ilfa machlokes b'shtei avodos. There's a
whole debate in the we really can't get out of פגול piggul
there's a whole debate in זבחים Zevachim about right what happens if
I shechted it with a מחשבה חוץ לזמנו machshava chutz lizmano which
is פגול piggul and I was זורק הדם zorek hadam or מקבל
הדם mekabel hadam with a מחשבה של חוץ למקומו machshava shel chutz
limkomo wrong place which is פסול pasul but not פגול. piggul. Is
it considered to be a מרצה לפיגולו or not in the sense
of you know in the sense will the thing be פגול piggul
or because I also have a מחשבה machshava of חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo it stops it from being פגול piggul because there was another
פסול pasul. here. To be פגול piggul everything has to be done
correctly and there can't be another פסול. pasul What if the other
פסול pasul was a מחשבה פסול machshava pasul a חוץ למקומו פסול?
chutz limkomo pasul? So the גמרא says it like this if you
started with the חוץ למקומו פסול chutz limkomo pasul when you shechted
it with חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and when you were זורק zorek
it was חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano everybody agrees it's not פגול piggul
it was already פסול pasul before you got to the מחשבת פגול.
machsheves piggul. But if you started with a חוץ לזמנו פסול chutz
lizmano pasul when you shechted it and when you were זורק zorek
it was another problem חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo but again that was
just a מחשבה פסול machshava pasul then there's a debate whether that
will פסול pasul it prevent it from becoming פגול piggul or not.
Okay so on that אילפא Ilfa said the following מחלוקת בשתי עבודות
machlokes b'shtei avodos it's two עבודות. avodos. Now I gave you a
clearer case of שחיטה shechita, and זריקה. zrika, He's going to have
a less clear case but we'll still call it two עבודות avodos
כגון דאמר הריני שוחט סימן ראשון חוץ לזמנו סימן שני חוץ למקומו.
kegon de'amar hareni shocheit siman rishon chutz lizmano siman sheni chutz limkomo.
He calls both the two סימנים simanim of the שחיטה to be
two עבודות avodos because ישנה לשחיטה מתחילה ועד סוף yeshnah l'shechita mitechilah
v'ad sof we're not going to worry about that. But the point
is that you clearly had on one what we'll call distinct act
סימן siman one a פגול piggul thought and סימן siman two a
חוץ למקומו פסול. chutz limkomo pasul. And when חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo
comes after חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano there there is a debate about
whether it will say that it is no longer פגול piggul because
there's another פסול pasul here or not. That's the debate. אבל בעבודה
אחת aval b'avoda achas let's say when you were shechting one סימן
siman you had the thought of both חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano and
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo even it was the first half of the
סימן siman and the second half but if it was all during
the same עבודה avoda even if it was sequential דכולי עלמא עירוב
מחשבות הוא. de'kulei alma eiruv machshavos hu. Everybody would say if it
was all during the same עבודה avoda even if it was a
little bit before and after timeline clearly there's another פסול here and
this is not פגול. piggul. Okay fine so that's an interesting הלכה
about other פסולי מחשבה psulei machshava and does it stop it from
being פגול. piggul. Why is this relevant for us? It's only relevant
because we're talking about שחיטה not זריקה zrika and we're saying that
the question is does it become פגול piggul at the moment of
שחיטה or not based on עירוב מחשבות eiruv machshavos so again we
are prepared to label something פגול piggul before the זריקה zrika, is
done. So let's see what he says הכא נמי לכי זרק תיגלי
מילתא אי בעבודה אחת אי בשתי עבודות. hacha nami lechi zarak tigli
milsa ei b'avoda achas ei b'shtei avodos. He says don't drain your
cup about that. He maybe could have said we don't literally mean
פגול piggul we mean it'll become פגול piggul but essentially what he
says is yes what we mean is then when you finish and
do the זריקה zrika then based on what happened at the שחיטה
the עירוב מחשבות eiruv machshavos or not decide whether it's פיגול pigul?
or not. But of course, its status and identity of פיגול pigul
will come at the זריקה zrika based on what happened at the
time of the שחיטה. Now the reason it's important that he uses
the phrase פיגול מילתא, pigul milta, why doesn't he just say the
status will come at the moment of זריקה? zrika Because here's the
point. The whole question was, right, which came first? The מחשבת פיגול,
pigul. the מחשבת חוץ לזמנו? machshava chutz lizmano? If you say that
the status of פיגול pigul all comes later, okay, it comes after
the זריקה zrika moment, not retroactively, if it comes after the זריקה
moment, then we should be concerned about what מחשבה machshava you had
even after the שחיטה, right? Because the whole question was which bad
מחשבה machshava you had and which order it came in. Well, if
you're going to say that the whole label of פיגול pigul is
hailed off until זריקה, then it should be relevant what מחשבות machshavos
you're having at the moment of זריקה as well and we and
that wasn't part of the discussion. It should always be a case
of שתי עבודות. shtei avodos. So his answer do you get the
point? Is that pretty clear to people? And that's why this was
very relevant. It wasn't just we use the phrase פיגול. pigul. We're
saying order matters and when are you thinking and so on. So
and if we're focusing on שחיטה it means what happens afterwards isn't
relevant for its identity of פיגול, which means the label of פיגול
does not wait till זריקה, the label of פיגול comes already. And
his answer is okay, it doesn't you're right, it has to come
at the moment of שחיטה, but it'll come retroactively. It still requires
the זריקה to be done, okay, and then when it's done though
then the moment of label is not the זריקה moment then retroactively
the moment is the שחיטה moment. Okay, so now but that's a
big concession. Okay, because now we have to go back to the
bread case. How did I explain the bread case, why the שחיטה's
פיגול was able to elevate the bread? Because I said at that
moment it wasn't it wasn't labeled פיגול. But what if I just
conceded right now that when I finally get around to doing the
זריקה retroactively it will be labeled as פיגול? So that was Michael's
question. So fine, but when you get around to the זריקה retroactively
it was פיגול and then it's not מקדש הלחם. mekadeish halechem. So
we're back to square one. Now you basically have conceded that it
will eventually retroactively be labeled as פיגול. So let's just read that
question and answer. So he says like this: אי הכי גבי תודה
נמי עד דזריק, ee hachi gabi toda nami ad d'zarik, עד דזריק
ad d'zarik is a little bit of fame-fame. Like basically he says
so by תודה also once you're זורק zorek retroactively it was פיגול
and since retroactively it was פיגול how did how is it מקדש
הלחם? mekadeish halechem? Because in the end you are admitting it was
פיגול. So he says: מאי קדש ליפסל ובשריפה. mai kideish l'pasel u'bisreifa.
All right, and now is where it really says it was really
just a proof by analogy and now we're going to have to
say it wasn't a good analogy. Fine. So you know what? שחיטת
פיגול has the effect of sanctifying it to the degree that it's
קדושת הגוף, that it could become פסול בלינה, pasul b'lina, שחיטת פיגול
can do something. But that's not מעילה. That's not to the level
of having an impact for מעילה. For that it has to be
a completely valid עבודה. avoda. Okay, so the end of the response
to the לחם case is and remember תוספות pointed out from the
very beginning there is no מעילה by the לחם because it was
not it was always ראוי rauy for it to be eaten. So
the question was you're telling me זריקת פיגול, שחיטת פיגול doesn't effect
the status for מעילה? Here we see that שחיטת פיגול does effect
the קדושה of the bread. And the answer is fine, it affects
the קדושה of the bread as קדושת הגוף, but that doesn't but
for מעילה we need something different. We need it to be a
real שחיטה, real כשר זריקה kasher zrika because again what changes the
status for מעילה? What changes the status is it's now מותר לכהנים
muttar l'kohanim or it's now for the אימורים imurim fit for the
מזבח. mizbeiach. For that to work it has to be really כשר.
kasher. For to and therefore it is different than the case of
the bread which is just about קדושה but not about מעילה questions.
Continue.