שבוע טוב, Shavua Tov, good שבת, Shabbos, 13th day of the עומר.
Omer. Today's דף Daf is דף ו Daf Vav and we pick
up from the very beginning. The topic under discussion is we know
that once a קרבן korban is brought, its status for מעילה Me'ilah
can change. קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim are completely מעילה Me'ilah because they're
all קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, they're for God so to speak, but
after the דם dam is thrown on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, if it's
a חטאת chatas or an אשם, asham, then the meat becomes permissible
for the כהנים, Kohanim, so therefore the meat no longer has מעילה
Me'ilah that applies to it. מעילה Me'ilah still applies to the rest
of the קרבן, korban, so that's קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim after the
זריקה zrika the meat becomes permissible. The reverse is by קדשים קלים.
Kodshim Kalim. For there, it's fundamentally considered to be either even really
ממון בעלים mammon ba'alim but certainly not fully given over to God,
it's going to be eaten by the owners, and therefore only the
part that goes on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the אימורים, emurim, and only
after it's fit for going on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, only after זריקת
הדם, zrikas ha-dam, only then does מעילה Me'ilah apply to it. So
the act of זריקת הדם zrikas ha-dam for קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim
makes the meat no longer מעילה Me'ilah and for קדשים קלים Kodshim
Kalim makes the אימורים emurim fit for מעילה. Me'ilah. That's the basic
rule. What the גמרא Gemara has been looking at the last few
days is number one, let's say it's not a really כשר kasher
זריקה, zrika, but it's a quasi-כשר kasher זריקה, zrika, meaning a זריקת
פיגול zrikas pigul was one question. זריקת פיגול Zrikas pigul is כשר,
kasher, but in some ways it's considered as if the דם dam
was נזרק. nizrak. That seems to be rejected, although we'll revisit that,
that that would still be considered not a good זריקה zrika to
be meaningful. And the other issue that we've really been focusing on,
and that will be the focus at least for the first עמוד
amud of today's דף, daf, is the question about whether it's the
moment of זריקה zrika that is critical or is it a prior
moment when the דם dam was caught, קבלת הדם, kabbalas ha-dam, because
then it's fit for זריקה zrika and maybe that should affect the
change even though it hasn't really happened yet. And the גמרא Gemara
refers to in a slightly confusing way that the act of קבלה
kabbala means, it's referred to as היתר זריקה. heter zrika. Hold on,
let me just make sure I get the phrase
correct. היתר זריקה, Heter zrika, it's fit for זריקה, zrika, היתר זריקה
heter zrika is the act of קבלה. kabbala. And the fact that
it actually the זריקה zrika did take place was היתר אכילה, heter
achila, that it actually became permissible, so it's becoming permissible in fact
if we're talking about the meat of קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, or
just being fit for that, היתר זריקה. heter zrika. So we will,
that will be the focus today. Let's start at the beginning, top
of דף ו עמוד א. Daf Vav Amud Aleph. תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, יש נותר
שמועלין בו ויש נותר שאין מועלין בו. Yesh nosar she-mo'alin bo ve-yesh
nosar she-ein mo'alin bo. It's possible to do מעילה Me'ilah with נותר,
nosar, it's possible to not do מעילה Me'ilah with נותר. nosar. Again,
we're always assuming we're talking about קדשי קדשים. Kodshei Kodashim. So כיצד,
keitzad, how is that possible? So I'm going to read this what
I think is the פשט pshat way and then I'm going to
tell you the way רש"י Rashi reads it because, and he does
that because of the next segment of the גמרא. Gemara. So here's
I think what the פשט pshat way of reading this following statement
is: כיצד, keitzad, לן לפני זריקה, lan lifnei zrika, if the meat
slept overnight, became נותר nosar before the blood was thrown and then
you threw the blood. So when you finally got around to throwing
the blood, it was never, the meat was never מותר. mutar. Okay,
actually the blood also stayed overnight if the meat stayed overnight, so
anyway it wasn't a good זריקה zrika and anyway the meat was
never מותר. mutar. So that case, in that case, מועלין, mo'alin, there
would be מעילה Me'ilah because the meat never became מותר. mutar. לאחר
זריקה, Le-achar zrika, you threw the blood on the right time and
then the meat stayed overnight, right, so in that case, אין מועלין,
ein mo'alin, there is no מעילה Me'ilah because there was the moment
when the meat became מותר. mutar. Very straightforward, right? Okay fine. Did
the meat actually, was the meat actually מותר mutar at one point
or not? And now the גמרא Gemara goes on to say, קתני
מיהא, ktani mi-ha, so okay what do we see from this? That
מועלין בו, mo'alin bo, that it says that if it was, if
you did not do the זריקה, zrika, then you would be, right,
if you waited till, if the meat stayed overnight before you did
the זריקה, zrika, so then there's going to be מעילה. Me'ilah. So
one minute, but imagine the case, you caught the blood, then you
waited till the next day to do the זריקה, zrika, the meat
stayed overnight to do the זריקה. zrika. Okay, but you caught the
blood at the right time and it was ראוי לזרוק, rauy lizrok,
so why didn't that change the status?
לאו דהוי ראוי לזרוק, lav de-hovei rauy lizrok, isn't it not that
when you caught the blood at least there was the time that
you could have done the זריקה? zrika? ויזרק, Veyizareik, and you could
have thrown the blood and therefore okay you didn't get around to
it until tomorrow, but nevertheless
it was ראוי rauy for it. So you see שמע מינה היתר
אכילה שנינו, shma mina heter achila shaninu,
you really have to throw the blood in order to change the
status and it's when the meat actually becomes
מותר mutar באכילה. be-achila. לא, Lo, no, maybe that's not the case.
Maybe the case
is דקבליה סמוך לשקיעת החמה, de-kabla samuch lishkiyas ha-chama, דלא הוה שהות
לזרוק. de-la hava she-os lizrok. What's the case? Special case. You slaughtered
the animal one minute before 6:00 p.m., assuming sunset at 6, you
caught the blood and by the time the blood was caught, it
was 6:00 p.m.
and now you
can't
be זורק zorek the דם. dam. So there wasn't an opportunity.
Right, the רש"י Rashi pretty much says that's more or less what
it's saying. Although then, you know, why didn't it... so right, but
since it's since it's yeah, but either way. Either way, right. Since
it's saying that there was a לינה lina problem and that if
you did the קבלה kabbalah after שחיטה shechita the problem would have
preceded the לינה lina as it were, it would have been שחיטת
לילה. shechitas lila. So that's why we're drawing it this way. But
essentially what it's saying is, you know what, it's a special case.
Wait a minute. The reason that it was not מותר mutar is
not because you didn't זורק zorek the דם dam when it was
still kosher. The reason is because the דם dam was never fit
for זריקה. zrika. At the moment after the moment it was caught,
it was no longer fit for זריקה. zrika. That's why it never
became מותר. mutar. So now the גמרא's Gemara going to ask the
obvious question and tell Yosef this is your question. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this,
wait a minute, אבל הישנות מה? Aval hayeshnos mah? הכי נמי דאין
מועלין? Hachi nami d'ein mo'alin? So what? You mean to tell me
though that you forget לינה, lina, right? You mean to tell me
that you don't really need זריקה zrika to make the meat מותר.
mutar. As long as the blood was caught you know a minute
before you know five minutes before שקיעה shkiah you would have gotten
it out of לינה. lina. That's what you're trying to say. So
if that's true, מאי אריא דקתני לפני זריקה? mai irya d'katani lifnei
zrika? Why does it say, oh, it matters whether it happened whether
it slept over before זריקה zrika or after זריקה? zrika? Why is
that drawn as the dividing line? לתני קודם שקיעה ולאחר שקיעה. Lisni
kodem shkiah v'achar shkiah. Why not say that if you want to
distinguish between whether there's מעילה me'ilah or not מעילה, me'ilah, it's not
a question of did you do the זריקה zrika or not do
the זריקה? zrika? It's a question of whether you caught the blood
before you know before שקיעה shkiah or לאחר שקיעה. achar shkiah. So
here it actually says לאחר שקיעה. achar shkiah. But the point being
before שקיעה shkiah was time to throw it or without time to
throw it. לפני שקיעה Lifnei shkiah לאחר שקיעה achar shkiah makes the
difference when you caught the blood. Don't make the difference whether or
not you did זריקה, zrika, right? Very obvious point. So the גמרא
Gemara says you know what? הכי נמי קתני. Hachi nami katani. That's
really what it means.
קודם שראויה לזריקה ולאחר שראויה לזריקה. Kodem she-re'uyah l'zrika v'achar she-re'uyah l'zrika.
So when it says that to determine whether there's מעילה me'ilah here
or not is whether or not the blood was thrown, it doesn't
really mean whether or not the blood was thrown. What it really
means is whether or not the blood was ever fit to be
thrown. Okay, so when he says sometimes there's מעילה me'ilah by נותר
notar sometimes not. When is there not מעילה me'ilah by נותר? notar?
If there was לינה lina לפני זריקה, lifnei zrika, it really means
if there was לינה lina before there was a chance to זורק.
zorek. But if there was לינה lina לאחר זריקה, achar zrika, which
means if there was לינה lina after there was a chance to
do זריקה, zrika, if the blood was caught and there was a
chance to do זריקה zrika and then the problem occurred, then it
was long, then already since there was a chance it's okay. So
basically reinterpret the word זריקה zrika as opportunity to do זריקה zrika
and it's not a problem. But again the simple sense of this
ברייתא braisa says the key moment is the moment of זריקת הדם.
zrikas hadam. Charlie, yes.
This is a situation that would never happen because yeah, okay, the
last קרבן korban of the day is the תמיד tamid which is
עולה olah which is not going to be released from מעילה. me'ilah.
And the only day that's not the case is ערב פסח Erev
Pesach where the only thing they do afterwards would be קדשים קלים.
kodshim kalim.
All right, good point, but I will say בדיעבד, b'di'eved, בדיעבד, b'di'eved,
if you bring a קרבן korban after the תמיד tamid it's still
kosher. So even but okay. I thought you were just going to
say how you know which כהן kohen is going to be stupid
enough to do it one minute before שקיעה. shkiah.
But that's kind of related thing because if the כהנים kohanim have
their act together they're not going to get anywhere.
There was a
story where the תמיד tamid was no longer...
oh, בטל התמיד. butal hatamid. Ah, then
everything was done. No, no, I... anyway, okay, fine.
But but would
have been not להלכה. l'halachah.
They ran out of sheep they might have had goats for חטאת.
chatas.
We just asking on the פשט pshat that, you know, there were
three different opinions as to when when it is. Right. But you
know we probably are going to reject that opinion. We'll see. Not
so clear.
Okay. So all right. So that is the simple read of this
which is is that when he says why לפני שקיעה lifnei shkiah
why לאחר שקיעה, l'achar shkiah, it means when did the לינה lina
take place? Did you זורק zorek the דם dam and then the
problem was introduced or first was a problem and then you were
זורק zorek the דם. dam. But רש"י Rashi reads it differently. And
this is he's going to have to because of the next lines
so I want us to go back and look at that
from the top of the עמוד amud again and I'll tell you
the way רש"י Rashi reads it. תא שמע Ta shema רבי שמעון
אומר יש נותר שמועלין בו ויש נותר שאין מועלין בו כיצד? Rabbi
Shimon omer yesh notar she-mo'alin bo v'yesh notar she-ein mo'alin bo, keitzad?
לא. La. Period.
Let's say you have or whatever, כל. col. Let's say you have
blood that was לן. lan. You have blood that is נותר. notar.
Now, if you were נהנה neheneh from the meat לפני זריקה lifnei
zrika before you were זורק zorek the
דם dam then מועלין בו mo'alin bo because then obviously there's been
no זריקת הדם zrikas hadam so there's still מעילה. me'ilah. לאחר זריקה,
L'achar zrika, if you were נהנה neheneh from the meat after זריקה
zrika of דם dam that was נותר, notar, then in that case
אין מועלין בו. ein mo'alin bo. Okay, why? Because that's very bizarre
because the so he... okay. He reads it as, he reads this
as, even if you're זורק דם zorek dam that is לינה, lina,
it gets it out of מעילה. me'ila. And he says, you know,
because same we just discussed yesterday, that maybe פיגול, pigul,
so maybe you would say the same נותר notar once you had
זריקה zrika even afterwards it gets it out of נותר. notar. Now
that is a very difficult read of that, and also because not
only is the דם dam נותר, notar, but the meat is נותר.
notar. So why also would it get it out of פיגול pigul
even if, you know, so anyway, it's very complicated. I just wanted
to mention that because we're going to see the next quote of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that why that kind of read might be
necessary. Okay, but certainly the simple sense of what we just read
was, did the problem happen לפני זריקת הדם lifnei zrikat hadam or
לאחר זריקת הדם, le'achar zrikat hadam, which is exactly what the משנה
mishna was talking about. Let's go back, let's go back to where
we are in the גמרא, gemara, about ten lines down, beginning of
the line. תא שמע ta shma from in here.
רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: יש פיגול שמועלין בו, yesh pigul
shemo'alin bo, יש פיגול שאין מועלין בו. yesh pigul she'ein mo'alin bo.
There's a פיגול pigul that there could be מעילה, me'ila, and there's
a פיגול pigul that can't be מעילה. me'ila. Seems like we're going
in the same direction. כיצד, keitzad, what's the case? לפני זריקה lifnei
zrika מועלין. mo'alin. לאחר זריקה le'achar zrika אין מועלין. ein mo'alin. Now
to interpret this the way we would normally do it. When did
the problem of פיגול pigul arise? Did the problem of פיגול pigul
arise לפני זריקה? lifnei zrika? Then the זריקה zrika was never מתיר
matir it, so there's still מעילה. me'ila. Did the problem of פיגול
pigul arise לאחר זריקה? le'achar zrika? Then the זריקה zrika was מתיר
matir and therefore there won't be מעילה me'ila because the problem only
came after זריקה, zrika, right? Very straightforward. Did the problem come before
or did the problem come after? So Michael realizes what I think
was bothering רש״י, Rashi, which is you can't have פיגול pigul לאחר
זריקה. le'achar zrika. Okay, the פיגול pigul is at the עבודה: avodah:
שחיטה, schita, קבלה, kabala, הולכה, holacha, זריקה. zrika. So therefore you can't
read this like you would like to, 'oh, if the problem arose
after זריקה'. zrika Okay, so therefore now maybe we could say לאחר
le'achar is לאו דוקא, lav davka, it means פיגול בשעת זריקה. pigul
bishat zrika. That would be a way to get out of that,
okay? Because then you want to still understand, then the זריקה zrika
was never מתיר. matir. But that's why רש״י Rashi reads this line
the following is: you already had a מחשבת פיגול. machshevet pigul. Okay,
so if you weren't זורק zorek the דם, dam, then then then
you ate the meat, you were נהנה nehene before זריקת הדם, zrikat
hadam, there's still פיגול, pigul, no, there's still מעילה. me'ila. If you
were נהנה nehene after זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, גם gam of פיגול,
pigul, if you were נהנה nehene after זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, there's
no פיגול. pigul. And this argues on רב גידל אמר רב. Rav
Gidal amar Rav. This would say זריקת פיגול zrikat pigul counts as
a זריקה zrika to change the status. Okay, so that's the way
רש״י Rashi reads because there's a big problem, how do you have
פיגול pigul after זריקה? zrika?
So what does... don't read it this way... I don't know, I
haven't found anybody who doesn't read it that way. I would just
say the best you could do is say לאחר זריקה le'achar zrika
is לאו דוקא, lav davka, it means בשעת זריקה. bishat zrika. Okay,
but again, this really complicates things. It introduces רב גידל אמר רב
Rav Gidal amar Rav again. So our purpose is acknowledging רש״י's Rashi
read and what's pushing him that way. I will choose to read
this more of a פשט, pshat, which just means did the פיגול
pigul problem happen before, and rather say after זריקה zrika or during
זריקה. zrika. Okay, so let's just keep it at that level. It's
the same basic point of the גמרא gemara but it just makes
it, you know, the purposes for which the גמרא gemara is bringing
this, it makes it much more straightforward. So if the פיגול pigul
occurred לפני זריקה, lifnei zrika, then the זריקה zrika wasn't מתיר. matir.
And therefore it's מעילה. me'ila. If the פיגול pigul occurred during זריקה,
zrika, then the זריקה... zrika... if the פיגול pigul went before זריקה...
zrika... oh no, that still wouldn't work. It would still have to
argue on רב גידל אמר רב. Rav Gidal amar Rav. But anyway,
but at least it makes it a little better. If the פיגול
pigul occurred during זריקה, zrika,
then the זריקה... zrika... arguing on רב גידל אמר רב, Rav Gidal
amar Rav, saying זריקת פיגול zrikat pigul is as if it were,
then it's as if it מתירed matir and then it was okay.
So either way it argues on רב גידל אמר רב, Rav Gidal
amar Rav, but I'd rather have a discussion not when you ate
it, but when did the פיגול pigul occur. פיגול pigul occurs earlier,
it was never מתיר. matir. If it occurred after slash during, it
was מתיר.
matir. So... that's right, because רב Rav is a תנא tanna and
he...
because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is... right. So תוספות Tosafot asks that,
how would he deal with this שריפת פר? srifat par? Let's go
on.
Okay, yes, I had a question. Why is it... רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says the exact same thing except once it's נותר, notar, once
it's פיגול? pigul? Right, so why wouldn't he, why would he make
two separate statements with the exact same words? He could have said
יש פיגול ונותר שמועלין, yesh pigul venotar shemo'alin, right? So maybe he
only said one and they didn't know...
That could be. It also could be, right, I mean sometimes you
don't know, like in an... I mean sometimes again, you know, within
these oral traditions, what are sort of standard, you know... like sometimes...
this isn't really an answer, but you know, sometimes there's questions of...
like why they grouped certain things together and the order of things,
and sometimes it has to do with like the way things were
remembered in oral tradition, which I know isn't an answer, but, you
know, there is something I guess, you know, memorable of this idea.
יש נותר שמועלין בו, yesh notar shemo'alin bo, יש נותר שאין מועלין
בו. yesh notar she'ein mo'alin bo. יש פיגול שמועלין בו, yesh pigul
shemo'alin bo, יש פיגול שאין מועלין בו. yesh pigul she'ein mo'alin bo.
You know, once you start saying יש פיגול ונותר שמועלין בו, yesh
pigul venotar shemo'alin bo, יש פיגול ונותר שאין מועלין בו, yesh pigul
venotar she'ein mo'alin bo, it sort of makes the sentence complex. I
could imagine in an oral tradition actually there's something more, more sort
of digestible about this way. And that would be one answer. The
other answer I could expect also would be that, you know, the
situation of פיגול pigul is a very different one. It's not as
easily applicable as the נותר notar situation because you don't have פיגול
pigul occurring לאחר זריקה. le'achar zrika. so if you push them together,
you really can't push them together because there really is differences. I
mean, he's not unpacking the differences, but there really are. But you
could be right. It could be that one was the one that
was really said, the other was not. Actually, this is the first
sentence was quoted from a תוספתא. Tosefta. יש שונים Yesh Shonim in
the תוספתא. Tosefta. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon סתם. stam. But anyway, it
is that sentence. The other one is not in the תוספתא. Tosefta.
So you might be correct that the first was the original and
the second was some derivation. You could be correct about that. Okay,
so let's go back to that point then. תא שמע, Ta shma,
רבי שמעון אומר יש פיגול שמועלין בו ויש פיגול שאין מועלין בו.
Rabbi Shimon omer yesh pigul shemolin bo veyesh pigul she'ein molin bo.
כיצד? Keitzad? לפני זריקה, Lifnei zerika, if the פיגול pigul prompt preceded
זריקה, zerika, then מועלין בו, molin bo, the זריקה zerika was never
מתיר. matir. ולאחר זריקה, Ve'acharei zerika, if it was after, which we're
sort of modifying to say during זריקה zerika and assuming that זריקה's
zerika פיגול pigul is good, then אין מועלין, ein molin, then there's
not מעילה me'ilah because then it was considered as if it was
a good זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. קתני מיהא, Katani miha, nevertheless, however
you understand that statement, we say לפני זריקה מועלין בו, lifnei zerika
molin bo, that if the problem occurred before זריקה, zerika, there's מעילה,
me'ilah, okay, even though now, of course, if the problem occurred before
זריקה zerika there's מעילה, me'ilah, maybe there was already this means that
זריקה's zerika the critical moment, not קבלת הדם. kabbalat hadam. So one
time before זריקה zerika could be after קבלת הדם. kabbalat hadam. לאו
דהוה חזי למזרקיה דאי זריק, Lav dehavyei ra'ui limzorkei de'iy zareik, would
that include a case where you did the קבלה kabbalah well, there's
a chance to do זריקת הדם, zerikat hadam, and then you had
your פיגול pigul problem, and nevertheless we say it's no good? So
you see even with קבלת הדם, kabbalat hadam, the status hasn't changed;
the key moment is זריקה. zerika. Okay, דהוה חזי... dehavyei ra'ui... ושמע
מינה, veshma mina, וקתני מועלין בו. vekatani molin bo. דאי זריק, De'iy
zareik, you could have thrown the blood, and even so, וקתני מועלין
בו, vekatani molin bo, there's מעילה me'ilah even though so as long
as the פיגול pigul preceded the זריקה, zerika, there's going to be
מעילה me'ilah even though there was a good קבלת הדם. kabbalat hadam.
So you see what עיקר ikar is not the קבלה kabbalah but
the זריקה. zerika. ושמע מינה היתר אכילה שני ליה. Veshma mina heter
achilah shani leh. The key moment is the moment of זריקה, zerika,
of making it מותר. mutar. Now, of course I'm waiting for Michael
to ask, which is why this whole גמרא Gemara on the surface
is very easy but when you think about it it's very complicated
because the פיגול pigul came—what's the scenario? The פיגול pigul came after
the קבלה kabbalah before the זריקה. zerika. How did פיגול pigul come
after the קבלה kabbalah before the זריקה? zerika? You can only do
פיגול pigul at שחיטה, shechita, קבלה, kabbalah, הולכה, holacha, or זריקה. zerika.
Where did the פיגול pigul come after the קבלה kabbalah before the
זריקה? zerika? So I thought you'd answer: הולכה. holacha. Yeah, right. So
תוספות, Tosafot, one of the תוספות... Tosafot... Ah, but the problem. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says פיגול בשעת הולכה pigul besha'at holacha doesn't matter
because you could do without הולכה. holacha. So when exactly was this
moment that you did a good קבלת הדם kabbalat hadam and it
was after—and then you had a פיגול pigul thought after that before
זריקה? zerika? So תוספות Tosafot says: maybe at the end of קבלה.
kabbalah. Like, you know, as the blood is coming out, some first
and then by the end of קבלה kabbalah you would have had
that thought. But this is why the גמרא Gemara on the surface
is very simple, like רש"י Rashi actually just says, "Oh yeah, this
is just like the earlier גמרא Gemara about נותר." nosar. But it's
not because it's about פיגול, pigul, and פיגול pigul is very different,
פיגול pigul requires very particular moments. Anyway, so just to be aware
there are serious issues with this גמרא. Gemara. But the focus is
that the key line is the act of זריקה, zerika, and therefore
that's what makes the difference, before, after זריקה, zerika, even though there
was already a קבלה. kabbalah. So you see it's about זריקה, zerika,
it's not about קבלה, kabbalah, according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay,
according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So let's see what the גמרא's
Gemara answer is. לא, בלאו דלא חזי למזרקיה. Lo, belo shehera'ui limzorkei.
There wasn't time to do זריקה, zerika, meaning like, you know, a
second before שקיעת החמה, sheki'at hachamah, some type of a case where
it was never ראוי ra'ui for זריקה. zerika. So the גמרא Gemara
says: אבל שהיה ראוי למזרקיה מאי? Aval shehera'ui limzorkei mai? What would
you say if there was a chance to do זריקה? zerika? הכא
נמי דנפיק מידי מעילה? Hacha nami denafik midei me'ilah? You would say
that it's really the critical moment is the קבלה kabbalah as long
as there was an opportunity, and that's the critical moment and it's
no longer מעילה? me'ilah? מאי איריא דתני לאחר זריקה? Mai irya detani
acharei zerika? So then why did we emphasize זריקה? zerika? We should
have emphasized the real critical moment was קבלה. kabbalah. Okay, ליתני קודם
שקיעה אחר שקיעת החמה. lisnei kodem sheki'ah achar sheki'at hachamah. Why did
it say that the critical moment of when the פיגול pigul came
up, of when the פסול pasul came up, or according to רש"י
Rashi when it was eaten but I don't want to get into
that, when the פסול pasul came up was before after קבלת הדם,
kabbalat hadam, or a קבלה kabbalah that there was a chance to
do זריקה zerika or a קבלה kabbalah that there wasn't a chance
to do זריקה, zerika, if that's the key? הכא נמי קאמר, Hacha
nami kama, that's what it means. When it says before after זריקה,
zerika, what it doesn't mean is literal זריקה, zerika, it means קודם
שראוי לזריקה, kodem shehera'ui lezerika, לאחר שראוי לזריקה. achar shehera'ui lezerika. If
the פיגול pigul occurred, again I'm reading at the פשט pshat level
acknowledging the problem, if the פיגול pigul occurred before it was fit
for זריקה, zerika, which would be probably at the moment of שחיטה,
shechita, then okay, it was never ראוי. ra'ui. But if the פיגול
pigul occurred, you know, after it was fit for זריקה, zerika, after
you did a קבלה, kabbalah, even if you haven't done the זריקה,
zerika, then it was ראוי ra'ui and then— It will no longer
be מעילה meilah. *me'ilah* because then it was ראוי ra'ui. בשעת קבלה
kabalah. *ra'ui b'sha'at kabbalah*. So we don't mean before after זריקה zrika
*zrika*, we mean before after קבלה kabalah, *kabbalah*, זריקה zrika, *zrika* means
when it was fit for זריקה zrika *zrika*. Okay, and that's how
we now have explained both cases. I mean, the whole פיגול pigul
*piggul* case is very דחוק *dachuk*. Of course it's very דחוק *dachuk*.
The whole פיגול pigul, *piggul* case whatever, like I said, right, you
know, it's very hard to read the whole פיגול pigul, *piggul* case.
Anyway, we have two clear statements of רבי Rebbe שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
that the key moment is זריקה zrika, *zrika*. Was it before or
after זריקה zrika, *zrika*? And what we came out of it is
saying we don't mean זריקה zrika, *zrika*, we mean fit for זריקה
zrika *zrika*, we mean קבלה kabalah *kabbalah*. Okay, let's now wrap this
up. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: תא שמע הפיגול
בקדשי קדשים מועלין *ta shema ha-piggul b'kodshei kodashim mo'alin*. We had this
ברייתא *beraita* before. פיגול pigul. *piggul* by קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim *kodshei
kodashim* is מעילה meilah *me'ilah*. Now, it's so funny because on yesterday's
דף daf, *daf*, when we quoted it, we thought it meant פיגול
pigul, *piggul* at the time of שחיטה *shechita*. And the reason we
were emphasizing שחיטה *shechita* was to tell you that it had to—the
problem had to precede the קבלה kabalah *kabbalah*. And as we had
said yesterday, where do you get that from? It doesn't tell you
when the פיגול pigul, *piggul* occurred. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is going to assume the opposite. What is it going to assume?
The opposite. Okay, so מאי לאו דזרק *mai lav d'zarak*? Are we
not talking about the fact that the פיגול Pigul *piggul* occurred after
קבלה kabalah? *kabbalah*, even you know at the time of—at the time
of זריקה zrika *zrika*, or maybe—or maybe at the time of קבלה
kabalah *kabbalah*, but whatever, and ושמע מינה היתר פיגול pigul שניהם *u-shma
mina hetter piggul shneihem*... no, let's say it's the time of זריקה
zrika *zrika*, ושמע מינה היתר פיגול pigul שניהם *u-shma mina hetter piggul
shneihem*. If it says פיגול pigul *piggul* will always prevent it from,
you know, will always keep it as מעילה meilah *me'ilah*, will prevent
it from counting, presumably it means even פיגול pigul *piggul* at the
time of זריקה zrika, *zrika*. Even פיגול pigul *piggul* that occurred after
קבלה kabbalah *kabbalah*. So you see that it's about a good זריקה
zrika *zrika*, it's not about a good קבלה kabbalah. *kabbalah*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לאו דלא זרק *lav d'lo zarak*. No! So
I mean it's so funny, this is the classic example of reading
your assumptions into the text and then getting them back out of
the text because there's nothing there that says when we're talking. So
doesn't it mean we're talking even if the פיגול pigul *piggul* came
late, even after קבלה kabbalah. *kabbalah*? No, the פיגול pigul *piggul* came
earlier. The פיגול pigul *piggul* came before זריקה zrika *zrika* and therefore,
and that's why it's not good. But if the פיגול pigul *piggul*
came after קבלה kabbalah. *kabbalah*, you know, then it actually would be
good. וכי זרק מאי *ve-khi zarak mai*? If you want to—so what
are you going to say? If there actually was זריקה zrika *zrika*
and the פיגול pigul. *piggul* came בשעת זריקה zrika? *b'sha'at zrika*, then
it would be good because the whole issue, the key moment was
not the moment of זריקה zrika, *zrika* but the moment of קבלה
*kabbalah*. הכא נמי דלא מועלין בו mo'alin bo, *hakha nami d'lo mo'alin
bo*? You mean to tell me there's no מעילה meilah. *me'ilah*? If
that's true, מאי איריא דתני בקדשים קלים אין מועלין בו moalin bo
*mai irya d'tani b'kodashim kalim ein mo'alin bo*? Right, this was a
ברייתא *beraita* that basically said פיגול pigul. בקדשי קדשים מועלין בקדשים קלים
אינן מועלין *piggul b'kodshei kodashim mo'alin b'kodashim kalim einan mo'alin*, which really
what it means is that if you have פיגול pigul *piggul*, it
doesn't change the status, right? Because קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim *kodshei kodashim*
starts with מעילה meilah *me'ilah* and unless you have a good זריקה
zrika *zrika*, the status doesn't change. So if there's פיגול pigul *piggul*
on the problem, the status will remain מעילה meilah. *me'ilah*. קדשים קלים
kodshim kalim *kodashim kalim* starts with no מעילה meilah *me'ilah* and unless
you have a good זריקה zrika *zrika*, it also—the status won't change
and it won't become מעילה meilah. *me'ilah*. So if you have פיגול
pigul. בקדשים קלים *piggul b'kodashim kalim*, it will remain with no מעילה
meilah *me'ilah*. פיגול בקדשי קדשים *piggul b'kodshei kodashim*, it will remain with
מעילה meilah *me'ilah*. That's the point. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
saying like this: Look, the ברייתא *beraita* is looking to tell you
an example where there's no מעילה meilah *me'ilah*. So why did it
run to the example of קדשים קלים kodshim kalim, *kodashim kalim*, פיגול
בקדשים קלים *piggul b'kodashim kalim* no מעילה meilah, *me'ilah*? According to you,
there are cases in קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim *kodshei kodashim* where there's
also no מעילה meilah? *me'ilah* by פיגול *piggul*. What's the case? You
had the פיגול *piggul* thought after קבלה *kabbalah*, right? So if you're
saying that actually the key moment is קבלה *kabbalah*, why if we're
looking for a case where there's no מעילה meilah *me'ilah*, why did
we run to קדשים קלים kodshim kalim *kodashim kalim*? Just say if
you did the קבלה *kabbalah* correctly and then had the פיגול *piggul*,
there also wouldn't be מעילה meilah, *me'ilah*. Okay, so that's the question.
מאי איריא דתני בקדשים קלים אין מועלין בו *mai irya d'tani b'kodashim
kalim ein mo'alin bo*? Why did it have to go to the
קדשים קלים kodshim kalim *kodashim kalim* case to say there's no מעילה
meilah, *me'ilah*? ליתני כאן לפני זריקה zrika כאן לאחר זריקה zrika. *litni
kan lifnei zrika kan l'achar zrika*. Tell me even by קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim, *kodshei kodashim* there are two scenarios. There'll be a normal
case of no מעילה meilah *me'ilah*, which is you had your פיגול
*piggul* thought up through קבלה *kabbalah*. And then there are cases where
you do have מעילה meilah, *me'ilah* that you had your פיגול *piggul*
thought only at זריקה zrika *zrika* and that there... did I say...
did I do it wrong? That you normally have מעילה meilah *me'ilah*
if you had your פיגול *piggul* thought up through קבלה *kabbalah* and
there are cases where there won't be מעילה meilah *me'ilah* if you
had your פיגול *piggul* thought after קבלה *kabbalah* at the time of
זריקה zrika *zrika*. כאן לפני זריקה zrika כאן לאחר זריקה zrika *kan
lifnei zrika kan l'achar zrika*. No, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says:
You know what, it could have said that. That's true. But why
did it go to קדשים קלים kodshim kalim *kodashim kalim*? Because it
wanted to tell you another point. הא אתיא לאשמועינן *ha atya l'ashmi'inan*.
It's coming to tell me the following point. And this is a
very important line. Again, it's not exactly clear why it's saying this
here, but it's going to say it on the next עמוד *amud*
and it's a very important line. So הא אתיא לאשמועינן *ha atya
l'ashmi'inan*, it's coming to tell me: כל העשוי לידי מעילה meilah, זריקה
zrika. כתיקנה מביא לידי מעילה meilah *kol ha-asui lidei me'ilah zrika k'tiknah
mavia lidei me'ilah*. If it's about making something become in the category
of מעילה me'ilah *me'ilah*, then you need it to be a really
good זריקה zrika *zrika*. It has to be the זריקה zrika *zrika*
done correctly. כל האפוקי מידי מעילה me'ilah אפילו שלא כתיקנה נמי מפיק
מידי מעילה me'ilah, *kol ha-apokei mi-ydei me'ilah afilu she-lo k'tiknah nami mapik
mi-ydei me'ilah*. If it's to take out of the מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah*
category, even if the זריקה Zrika, *zrika* wasn't good, it also can
take it out of מעילה me'ilah. *me'ilah*. What does this mean? It
means that as we said, זריקה zrika *zrika* can change the status...
In two ways. זריקה zrika can make קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim. no
מעילה. me'ilah. זריקה zrika can make קדשים קלים kodshim kalim יש מעילה.
yesh meilah. Now we've been talking about questionable זריקות. zrikos. We've been
talking about a זריקת פיגול, zrikas pigul, for example. We've also been
talking about not exactly the זריקה, zrika let's say the key moment
was the קבלה. Do those things work or not work? That's our
general question, right? זריקה zrika we know works, but if it's a
זריקת פיגול, zrikas pigul, does it work? If it's a קבלה, does
it work? Those are our questions. So the גמרא Gemara says, you
know what? Maybe the answer is different whether you're going up or
down, meaning whether you're trying to make something change it into the
מעילה me'ilah category or take it out of the מעילה me'ilah category.
Okay, now that could go either way. You could say, well, we'll
just always be מחמיר, machmir, so if it's one of these questionable
things we'll say, okay, it's מעילה. Me'ila. You know, we'll always be
מחמיר machmir and assume it's מעילה Me'ila. rather than it has
to
be
really
clear to
make it not
מעילה. Me'ila. Or you
could say no, you could basically say that, you know, it's always
easier for something to lose
its
status.
You
know,
if מעילה Me'ila
means
קדשי השם, kodshei Hashem, right? It's a very tenuous status, it's a
very, you know, hard category to fit in and a
very
small category.
So
once there's a little bit of
a
question mark on that,
once it's a
little bit vaguer, it no
longer can be in that category of קדשי השם. kodshei Hashem. So
even
a
weaker זריקה, zrika like
זריקת פיגול zrikas pigul
or not a זריקה, zrika קבלה which is only ראוי לזריקה, ra'uy
l'zrika, that's enough
to make it no longer clearly קדשי השם, kodshei Hashem, no longer
fit for מעילה. Me'ila That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying here,
that the last line is כל אפוקי מידי מעילה, kol apukei midei
meilah, if you're taking it out of the מעילה Me'ila category, אפילו
שלא כתיקנה נמי מפקי מידי מעילה, afilu shelo ketiknah nami mafkei midei
meilah, even if it's not a perfect זריקה, zrika okay, if there's
some questions like we've been talking about, that could take it out
of the category. But to take the אימורים emurim of a קדשים
קלים, kodshim kalim which fundamentally is not קדשי השם, kodshei Hashem, and
to say now the אימורים emurim because they're going to the מזבח
mizbeiach are קדשי השם, kodshei Hashem, they're not going to be considered
that unless they're really going to the מזבח. mizbeiach. So there, so
to get it into the מעילה meilah category, that very small category,
it has to really be fit for being in that category. Okay,
so here the גמרא Gemara is saying the standards might be different
for whether we count it as a good זריקה zrika to change
the status, whether you're becoming in the מעילה meilah category or taking
it out. Now, we're going to say that again on the עמוד
ב amud beis except of course there we're going to reverse it,
but okay, anyway, but conceptually to distinguish between these two is a
key point. And how does that fit to what the גמרא Gemara
is just saying right now? Because what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is that, oh, so we were talking here and the whole thing
was emphasizing זריקה zrika and so on, and it says קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim is always a problem, then why does it run to
קדשים קלים kodshim kalim to say there's no מעילה, meilah. right? Why?
So the גמרא Gemara is basically saying, look, you're actually right that
we are talking in both cases about not about זריקה zrika per
se, about what I'm calling questionable זריקה, zrika about ראוי לזריקה. ra'uy
l'zrika. Okay, זריקה zrika: was לאו דווקא, lav davka, you know זריקה
zrika really meant ראוי לזריקה ra'uy l'zrika like everything we've been saying
up until now. Okay, so therefore, so but okay, so anyway, so
why does it say that קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim there's מעילה? meilah
It really means that there is מעילה meilah until it gets to
this questionable, let me just see if I get this exactly correct,
one minute. Yes, I'm not exactly so okay, no, I got the
point. So the real question of the גמרא Gemara was, let me
just rephrase, the question of the גמרא Gemara was if it's looking
for an example of no מעילה, meilah. then why didn't it give
you the then why didn't it say well it depends if the
פיגול problem happened before זריקה zrika or at זריקה? zrika If you're
saying the key moment is the קבלה and you're looking for an
opportunity to say there's no מעילה, meilah why didn't you say there's
no מעילה meilah if the problem happened after קבלה? That was the
question. Why did you run to the קדשים קלים kodshim kalim case?
And the answer is, you know why we ran to the קדשים
קלים kodshim kalim, case? Because we're interested, what you said is correct,
yeah, it is really about קבלה not about זריקה, zrika but we
wanted to talk about קדשים קלים kodashim kalim. and we wanted to
underscore the point that קדשים קלים kodashim kalim there is it's always
going to be no מעילה, meilah meaning if there's ever anything questionable,
it's always going to remain in the no מעילה meilah. category. To
get you into the מעילה meilah category, it has to be something
that is completely valid, no questions, and 100%. So if your question
was why did we run to קדשים קלים kodashim kalim. to say
no מעילה, meilah why didn't we give you a scenario by קדשי
קדשים, kodshei kodashim, of course we could have given you a scenario,
but we wanted to be talking about קדשים קלים kodashim kalim. and
we wanted to be emphasizing that if there is ever a problem,
even where in other cases it might be considered okay it's only
a זריקת פיגול, zrikas pigul, it's ראוי לזריקה, ra'uy l'zrika, that might
be enough to make a difference that's only in קדשי קדשים. kodshei
kodashim When you're dealing with קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim anything that's problematic
will not be able to become מעילה Meilah because to get into
that category it has to be 100%. To fall out of that
category, maybe even if it's even a little bit questionable. So in
the end, the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara now is what do
we פסקן pasken in the end? Number one, do we פסקן pasken
Micah was assuming we were going to פסקן pasken that it's all
about זריקה not קבלה because all the evidence seems to be זריקה
not קבלה. But the end of the גמרא Gemara. never rejected it
and seems to have answers and seems to be okay working through
the possibility that all the cases that say זריקה really mean ראוי
לזריקה ra'ui l'zrika and it really is about קבלה. That's not so
in the end that answer is not clear. What's also left to
answer in the end is we've had now two questions about what
I'd call questionable זריקה. We've had where it's not זריקה but ראוי
לזריקה, ra'ui l'zrika, is that enough? And we've had זריקת פיגול. zrikat
pigul. Okay. זריקת פיגול zrikat pigul we said was no good. ראוי
לזריקה ra'ui l'zrika maybe Micah wants to say I also want to
say maybe also should be no good, it needs real זריקה and
not זריקת פיגול. zrikat pigul. But now we say but maybe that
would only be that it needs it really good to go up.
Maybe at the last point the גמרא Gemara says to fall down
from grace as it were. It's so much easier to fall out
of grace than to get into grace. So to fall out of
מעילה Meilah category, maybe these things would be impactful enough. Maybe זריקת
פיגול, zrikat pigul, maybe ראוי לזריקה ra'ui l'zrika is enough to make
a רושם roshem versus not, right? So that gets back to do
we agree with רב גידל, Rev Giddel, do we not agree with
רב גידל? Rev Giddel? So now we have the important categories, right?
These questionable things: זריקת פיגול, zrikat pigul, ראוי לזריקה, ra'ui l'zrika, not
clear what our מסקנא maskana is and maybe we could split the
vote between what counts to get it into פיגול, which needs something
completely good, and what counts to make it not פיגול, which means
even something that is cause that is you know a little bit
good.
Yeah. So as opposed to saying that it depends whether it's bringing
it into מעילה Meilah versus out of מעילה, Meilah which is the
way the גמרא Gemara. just framed that, I would have thought it
would depend whether it's קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim versus קדשים קלים. kodashim
kalim קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim are always more מחמיר, machmir, I would
say it should be more likely to have מעילה.
So that's what we're going to say on the other side.
Okay. And קדשים קלים are more lenient. Fine.
So now let's read, now we turn the דף, daf. we are
on ו' עמוד ב'. vav amud bet. And now so that was
a sounding גמרא Gemara but again at the end, the ideas are
not so hard. At the end the ideas are: זריקה changes the
status. There are two moments of questionable זריקה we've been talking about,
זריקת פיגול, zrikat pigul, we also discussed זריקת טמא, zrikat tamei, that
those are things which are maybe not total פסולים psulim as other
things and also ראוי לזריקה, ra'ui l'zrika, the act of קבלה. And
we've ended by saying, you know what, it might make a difference
which direction you're going. Okay. That's like Rabbi Weiss loves telling the
חסידיש Chassidish story about the רבי that asks his you know the
חסיד, Chassid, he says: So you have two people on a ladder,
you know one is at you know it's fifty rungs, it's like
the ספירות Sefiros right? So one is on the fortieth rung of
the ladder, the other is on like the fifteenth rung of the
ladder. He says: Who's higher? And em say: the guy on the
fortieth. He says: No, depends which way you're going.
So here too, right? Depends which way you're going, that makes the
difference. All right, let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah.
בשר קדשי קדשים שיצא לפני זריקת דמים. Basar kodshei kodashim she'yatzah lifnei
zrikat damim. Now we're going to talk about what is the status
of a very particular פסול, psul, the פסול psul of יוצא. yotzei.
When something is taken out of the environs of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. It's קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim it can't be taken out
of the environs of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You did. So
let's take a look at what the question is. So you took
this, no, you took this meat of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim outside
לפני זריקת דמים. lifnei zrikat damim. רש"י Rashi says even that you
could have brought it even back afterwards. But once it was taken
out, it has the פסול. psul. רבי
אליעזר אומר מועלין בו. Rabbi Eliezer omer mo'alin bo. Even if you've
done the proper זריקה. So in this case, right, the rest of
the קרבן korban is okay. The זריקה was done correctly, maybe there
are אימורים emurim that go on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, maybe there's other
meat around, the rest of the קרבן korban is okay. And therefore
the meat of the rest of the קרבן, korban, if there's leftover
meat, doesn't have מעילה. But he says: This is already פסול. posul.
This never became ראוי לאכילה. ra'ui l'achilah. Right? Very clear. The meat
that was already פסול posul is never ראוי לאכילה. ra'ui l'achilah. So
מועלין בו, so it's not going to change its status, it's going
to remain not ראוי. Rauy. And therefore there's מעילה. Similarly, the זריקה
won't change the status of the
meat and because it doesn't change the status of the meat, therefore
ואין חייבין עליו משום פיגול נותר וטמא. v'ein chayavin alav mishum pigul
notar v'tamei. If you left over the meat till the next day
and you ate it, you're not חייב כרת chayav kares for נותר.
notar. If you had a מחשבת פיגול machsheves pigul by the קרבן
korban and you ate the meat, you're not חייב chayav for פיגול.
If you're a טמא tamei person who ate it, you don't get
כרת kares because this meat is already פסול. posul. Okay. Once this
meat is פסול, posul, in order to become חייב chayav for פיגול,
נותר notar and טמא, tamei, it's only on meat that otherwise would
have been כשר. kosher. This meat was already פסול, posul, these other
things do not apply.
If you eat it, you're punished for מעילה but not for the
other stuff.
And for eating פסולי מוקדשים psulei mukdashim and מעילה but not for
eating פיגול, נותר notar and טמא. tamei. Okay. רבי עקיבא אומר אין
מועלין בו. Rabbi Akiva omer ein mo'alin bo. No, actually although it's
פסול יוצא, psul yotzei, the דם dam changed the status. Now it
doesn't technically mean it's מותר muttar to eat this meat. It still
has a פסול יוצא, psul yotzei, but here's again this case of
like virtual. It's not so פסול, posul, it's as if it's ראוי
לאכילה. ra'ui l'achilah. And therefore there is מעילה. So here's another as
if, there is not, I'm sorry, אין מעילה, Ain Me'ila, excuse me,
it's as if it's ראוי לאכילה Rauy l'Achila and therefore there is
no מעילה. So here's another example of as if. We dealt with
זריקת פיגול, Zrikas Pigul, we dealt with ראוי לזריקה. Rauy l'Zrika. Here
we're not dealing, here we're dealing with the actual meat itself. Yes,
the meat is פסול, Posul, but it's still not such a פסול,
Psul, and therefore it's as if it's ראוי. Rauy, And because it's
as if it's ראוי, Rauy דחייבי על משום פיגול ונותר וטמא. d'Chayavei
al mishum Pigul v'Nosar v'Tamay. If it also became פיגול or נותר
Nosar or you were a טמא Tamay person and you ate, you're
חייב כרת. Chayav Kares. You're only חייב Chayav for eating something that
was otherwise כשר Kasher and although this has a פסול יוצא, Psul
Yotzei, but he's not so bothered with the פסול יוצא. Psul Yotzei.
Now so רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's is the curious position, why is
he not bothered with the פסול Psul and he's only saying it
by יוצא, Yotzei, he's not saying it by טמא Tamay or other
kinds of things? So let's take a look. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar
Rabbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going to try to
explain his position. הרי המפריש חטאתו ואבדה, Harei hamavrish chataso v'avda, you
set aside your חטאת Chatas and you lost it, so what do
you do? והביא אחרת תחתיה, v'Heivi acheres tachteha, you set aside another
חטאת. Chatas. ואחר כך נמצאת הראשונה, v'Achar kach nimtzeis harishona, and you
have the first one. והרי שתיהם עומדות, v'Harei shteihem omdot, you have
both חטאות Chatas's standing in front of you. Now obviously you can
only bring one and then the other one becomes like a חטאת
שכיפרו בעליה באחרת. Chatas shekipru ba'aleha b'acheres. Okay, now in certain circumstances,
normally you would say מיתה, Misa, there are some cases that if
they were both around and so on, maybe it could be that
the money goes to an עולה, Ola, but let's assume מיתה. Misa.
Okay. What did you do? לא
כשם שדמה פוטר את בשרה כך הוא פוטר את בשר חברתה. Lo
k'shem shedama poter es besara kach hu poter es besar chavertah. The
blood you sprinkle of one חטאת, Chatas, the same way it makes
the meat of that חטאת Chatas okay, it makes the meat of
the other חטאת Chatas okay. The what? The what?
So first of all, what's the case? So רש"י Rashi says the
case is you brought both חטאות Chatas's to the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you שחט'ד Shechted both, you caught the blood of both, so
even at this late moment you can still decide which one is
going to be your חטאת, Chatas, okay, 'cause there's nothing that pre-defines
one over the other. So you're going to be זורק Zoreik the
דם dam of one of them. Okay, and obviously that's now your
חטאת, Chatas, the meat is okay. Comes along רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
it's so funny when you bring a proof from a case that
is less clear than the one you're trying to prove, but anyway,
comes along רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and he says, "Oh, so it's
obvious that in that case because at that moment you could bring
either one, that we're sort of going to consider it to be
all one חטאת." Chatas. And therefore the זריקת הדם Zrikas haDam will
actually מתיר Matir the meat of the other one, which is okay,
that's a huge חידוש Chiddush right there.
Wait until זריקה, which is going to be your חטאת? Chatas? Yeah.
So you שחט Shechted both? I thought you said you also ideally
you שחט Shechted both לשם חטאת. l'shem Chatas.
But I thought you're not supposed to do that. Like if I'm
שחט'ing Shechting it for this person for this sin, then it can't
be שחט'ing Shechting the other one for this person for this sin.
I understand, so
I mean whatever, you're right, you were supposed to choose ahead of
time, but you didn't. Okay.
Both together or two separate?
Right, so that's an interesting question. Would the sequence matter? I'm just
checking רש"י, Rashi, hold on.
Yeah, רש"י Rashi does not say exactly that they were שחט'ד Shechted
at exactly the same moment, one minute.
I
was asking if the blood was mixed.
Yeah, no, no, רש"י Rashi just says since you had the choice
of which דם dam he זורק, Zoreik, he doesn't say that there
was a that it was at the same time, the blood was
not mixed. Okay. So I understand, Michael, if you don't say that
they were שחט'ד Shechted at the same time, shouldn't we say by
the time you got to the second one, it was already defined
that there was already another חטאת? Chatas? Yeah, I would agree that
it would be easier to say that the case is not practically
to have the case, but easier הלכתית Halachically to imagine that they
were ממש Mamash שחט'ד Shechted at the exact same time. Anyway, so
now the question is when it says also פוטר את בשרה פוטר
את בשר חברתה, Poter es besara poter es besar chavertah, it's important
to know that he doesn't take this idea עד הסוף. ad hasof.
He doesn't literally say it's one big double חטאת Chatas and you
can eat the meat. It doesn't say מתיר את בשרה, Matir es
besara, he says פוטר את בשרה. Poter es besara. So he says
what he means to say is, "I acknowledge that the one you
didn't do זריקת הדם Zrikas haDam is a חטאת שכיפרו בעליה באחרת
Chatas shekipru ba'aleha b'acheres and you can't eat the meat and so
on and so forth. But what I'm still saying is because at
that moment you could have been זורק Zoreik its דם dam and
because they were to some degree like one big זבח קרבן, Zevach
Korban, therefore at least the זריקת הדם Zrikas haDam should say that
the other meat is no longer ראוי rauy for מעילה." Okay, so
again it's like okay, that's an interesting position, I don't find that
any more persuasive than the case of יוצא. Yotzei. But anyway, that's
what he says. I'm taking that for granted that in this very
strange case, that although the meat is not כשר Kasher because the
other one was brought, conceptually it's seen as one thing and that's
enough to say the meat is no longer in a מעילה category.
If that's true, one minute, so I would say like this, אם
פטר דמה את בשר חברתה Im patar damah es besar chavertah מן
המעילה, min haMe'ila, if you can acknowledge that case that the blood
of one חטאת Chatas takes the meat of the other one out
of מעילה because conceptually they're one, דין הוא שיפטור את בשר עצמה,
Din hu sheyiftar es besar atzmah, how much more so should it
be able to make its take its own meat out of the
מעילה category if it's all based, you know, just because and just
because it has a פסול Psul of יוצא, Yotzei, why should that
be such a big deal? Now Jolly thinks that's pretty persuasive if
you bought the first one, but then what I would say is
then why is יוצא Yotzei special? If I buy that, that there
could be some problems and still because it's all one it's as
if it's changed, so why only יוצא, Yotzei, how about טמא? Tamay?
Right. So maybe you know, so to some degree he thinks well
יוצא yotzei is maybe a problem of like distance. If it's only
the problem of distance and then it's really conceptually all one maybe
somehow but you know you still have to answer that like a
why is it obvious the case of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and
b why do we then only apply it to the יוצא yotzei
scenario?
Well as you point out יוצא yotzei is actually different from the
other disqualifications.
In the way that it's lighter but here he's saying יוצא yotzei
is the lesser problem right.
But so but you but there are times when you bring a
קרבן korban בטומאה.
betumah. I understand but Rabbi Akiva is saying that יוצא yotzei it's
easy it's less of of an obstacle than טמא. tamei. You know
your argument is that טמא tamei sometimes is less of an obstacle.
I understand. Okay. Anyways that's his argument. Now that we say that
we're going to also apply this idea one minute to the flip
by קדשים קלים. And here is exactly where we get the comparison
of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim of which direction you're headed. אימורי קדשים
קלים שיצאו לפני זריקת הדם. eimurei kodashim kalim sheyatzeu lifnei zrikat hadam.
Let's say the same case but it was the אימורי eimurei of
שלמים shlamim and the אימורי eimurei of שלמים shlamim after זריקה will
be considered fit for מעילה because it's fit for the מזבח. mizbeach.
רבי אליעזר אומר אין מועלין בהן. Rabbi Eliezer omer ein moalin bahen.
Okay but they're פסול pasul now so the זריקה did nothing so
there's still no מעילה for them and because they're פסול pasul אין
חייבין עליהם משום פיגול נותר וטמא. ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul notar
vetamei. There's none of these פסולים psulim because it's not fit for
the מזבח. mizbeach. The first case obviously wasn't fit to eat and
here it's not fit for the מזבח. mizbeach. רבי עקיבא אומר לא.
Rabbi Akiva omer lo. זריקה for יוצא yotzei is effective. מועלין בו
and it makes it as if this is ראוי rauy for the
מזבח mizbeach and although it isn't it makes it as if and
therefore there is מעילה. And because it's as if it's ראוי rauy.
for the מזבח mizbeach חייבין עליו משום פיגול נותר וטמא. chayavin alav
mishum pigul notar vetamei. Again you have these חיובים chiyuvim because it's
as if it's ראוי. So the basic מחלוקת machloket boils down that
in the regarding the פסול psul of יוצא yotzei רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says it's like any other פסול psul and therefore זריקה is
not meaningful not effective and the status doesn't change and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says it's not like any other
פסול psul and the זריקה does change its status. It's as if
it's not פסול. pasul. It is פסול pasul of course but the
זריקה is effective to change the status. So the גמרא Gemara just
let's just finish the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara just tying
up on what we said on the עמוד א׳ amud aleph points
out that why you need to tell me both cases because of
this issue of which direction are you moving and maybe I would
have had a different standard based on which direction I'm moving. So
let's read that in the גמרא. Gemara והני תרתי למה לי ve-hani
tartei lama li why did I need two examples? The example of
קדשי קדשים or two cases and קדשים קלים. They're both saying the
same issue. They're debating whether the פסול psul of
יוצא yotzei gets in the way or not. So the גמרא Gemara
says צריכא tzricha you need them. דאי איתמר בקדשי קדשים de-ee itmar
be-kodshei kodashim had they the debate just by
קדשי קדשים הוי אמינא בהא קאמר רבי אליעזר מועלין בו. hava amina
be-ha ka-amar Rabbi Eliezer moalin bo. That's where רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says
the
פסול psul gets in the way and the זריקה wasn't effective. Why?
משום דזריקה דתקנה מפקא מידי מעילה שלא כתקנה לא מפקא מידי מעילה.
mishum de-zrika de-takna mapka midei meilah shelo ke-takna lo mapka midei meilah.
Because maybe to get it out of the category of מעילה it's
exact opposite of what we said before. I need it to be
a hundred percent. Okay this is not the logic like I said
sort of it's a tenuous category and it's easy to fall from
grace. This is the argument of חומרא chumra and קולא. kula. Okay.
If it starts off as קדשי קדשים and everything is אסור. asur.
If you want to get something מותר mutar it's better be a
clear status change or a clear game changer. So only if it
is a good זריקה a totally good זריקה will it get out.
If it's not good it won't get out and something that has
a פסול יוצא psul yotzei is not going to change its status.
Okay. אבל aval but I might have thought it might be different
when you're going in the opposite direction. לאתויי לידי מעילה le-atuyei lidei
meilah to make it to turn it into מעילה which is to
make it more אסור. asur. It's always easier to make something more
אסור asur than מותר. mutar. So there מודה לרבי עקיבא דאפילו שלא
כתקנה מייתי לידי מעילה modei le-Rabbi Akiva de-afilu shelo ke-takna meity lidei
meilah then I would agree to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Even though
you've got this problem of יוצא yotzei it doesn't have to be
a hundred percent to make it מעילה. Okay? It's sort of the
you know it's like the attitude it's always easy to be מחמיר.
machmir. So if it starts off מעילה if you want to make
it מותר mutar it's got to be a hundred percent. If it
starts off no מעילה and you want to make it מעילה then
I'll agree that even if it's got this little bit of a
problem of יוצא yotzei
it's enough to make it אסור. asur. Okay. And so therefore we
wanted to say that he says in both of the cases even
in the other case it does not make it אסור. asur. ואי
איתמר גבי קדשים קלים ve-ee itmar gabei kodashim kalim had they just
said the debate by קדשים קלים הוי אמינא hava amina I would
have said the same point except based on from רבי עקיבא's Rabbi
Akiva perspective. בהא קאמר רבי עקיבא מועלין בהן. be-ha ka-amar Rabbi Akiva
moalin bahen. Oh okay I understand by קדשים קלים why רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva would say that even though it's not a hundred percent
זריקה even though it's got this יוצא yotzei problem there's still מעילה.
Why? דאפילו זריקה שלא כתקנה מייתי לידי מעילה de-afilu zrika shelo ke-takna
meity lidei meilah because since all you're trying to do since all
you're trying to do is be מחמיר machmir and give it מעילה
even a not hundred percent זריקה does it even with the יוצא
yotzei problem. אבל קדשי קדשים aval kodshei kodashim but I would have
thought that when it comes to קדשי קדשים לאפוקי הוא le-afokei hu
that you're coming to be more lenient and you're coming to say
there's no מעילה and change its status that way I would have
said there שלא כתקנה לא מפקא מידי מעילה. shelo ke-takna lo mapka
midei meilah. There רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say there I'm not
going to say that with this יוצא yotzei problem it's going to
become
מותר. mutar. That is true. That's a good point. That then that
so Mike I actually I hadn't thought about that but Mike actually
raised an excellent point which is which is the גמרא you can't
say that it was just a question of being מחמיר machmir or
מיקל meikel and maybe you go different standards for different directions by
מעילה because they are also consistent about פיגול נותר notar and טמא
tamei and there it's and there in both cases it's מחמיר. machmir.
Yeah but okay but the point is like this: it doesn't matter.
It's still why the משנה Mishna had to tell it in both
cases because if the משנה Mishna had only told one I would
have thought that they would have switched their position by מעילה not
they would have totally switched their position but they would have at
least switched in the מעילה position. Okay but it's a very good
point. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan and therefore it teaches me
that. So again what is teased out here although the גמרא is
doing the צריכותא tzrichuta why did it need to tell me both
cases is that it's again revisiting this idea that זריקה is the
key moment that the status changed. But we've now been seeing three
categories of questionable
זריקה: זריקה of פיגול/טמא case, ראוי לזריקה raui l'zrika and now we
have זריקה with a פסול psul of יוצא, yotzei, some reason יוצא
yotzei is different. And in all these cases we're saying maybe it
makes a difference are you going up or going down but we
could say it both ways. To get מעילה that's a very special
category a very tenuous category. It needs to be 100% good to
get into that category but to fall out of that category is
very easy. Or the reverse. It's a חומרא. chumra. So therefore to
be מחמיר machmir on you we'll be more inclined to say these
questionable things make it אסור assur but we'd be less inclined to
say these questionable things make it מותר. mutar. There it would have
to be 100%. So very but we're very interesting we're dealing with
a series of questionable זריקות zrikot and the question is the standard
the same based on which direction you're going.
How does this fit in
with what we said on? We don't. The גמרא sometimes the גמרא
does that. I mean I think that's beautiful that the גמרא it's
a little funny that they're not all in the same place but
okay. And now let's just get to the bottom of the דף.
איתמר. itmar. אמר רבי יוחנן. amar Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said עד כאן אמר רבי עקיבא זריקה מועלת ליוצא. ad kan
amar Rabbi Akiva zrika mo'elet l'yotzei. When did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
say זריקה for a יוצא yotzei as if it were good? שיצא
מקצתו. she-yatza miktzato. Only if some of it has gone out and
some remained. Now you can understand actually better the comparison to the
חטאת chatat because by the חטאת chatat example the דם dam worked
for its meat, it works for the other meat. So here you
could say by יוצא yotzei they're saying some meat went out, some
meat remained, the דם dam worked for the meat that was here,
it's going to also work for the meat that went out.
Now I'm not talking about one piece of meat that's half in
and half out.
No no no. Some of the meat of the קרבן. korban. Okay
now again you still might ask why not say if it's טמא
tamei some got טמא tamei and some didn't. But anyway we'll worry
about that in a minute but for now he says if only
אבל יצא כולו, aval yatza kulo, if all the meat went out,
לא אמר רבי עקיבא, lo amar Rabbi Akiva, he would not say
it.
He'd agree to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that the זריקה doesn't do
any good. אמר ליה רב אסי לרבי יוחנן. amar lei Rav Assi
l'Rabbi Yochanan. So רב אסי Rav Assi said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, תרלדוני חבריי שבגולה, tirl'duni chavray she-ba-golah, okay so now רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and רב אסי Rav
Assi came from בבל Bavel so he said to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan my colleagues in exile have already taught me, see the first
line here and then we'll
continue tomorrow, מחשבין על האבוד ועל השרוף, m'chashvin al ha-avud v'al ha-saruf,
that if you thought when you were doing this is now we're
back to פיגול so you can never get out of it right
so you thought when you're doing פיגול thought right what's your פיגול
thought? Your פיגול thought is I'm going to eat this meat or
burn these אימורין imurin חוץ לזמנו. chutz l'zmano. You had that thought.
But at that time you were thinking about what wrong stuff you
were going to do with this meat or these אימורין imurin actually
the meat and the אימורין imurin had already been destroyed, they were
lost or they actually had burned. So you had this thought to
do something wrong about food about an object that wasn't there anymore.
And from my colleagues have taught me that guess what that actually
is a פיגול thought. Because when you have a פיגול thought it
doesn't just make that meat פיגול right? It makes the whole קרבן
korban פיגול. So if you have that wrong thought even if it's
not
doable because the object isn't there it's enough to make it פיגול.
Wait as long as something else is there? Meaning if I want...
No.
The אימורין imurin burnt and I'm having...
No there has to be other things for it to be relevant.
But none of the meat could be there but there's still פיגול
by the אימורין imurin or none of the אימורין imurin whatever. Because
פיגול applies to the whole
קרבן. korban. מחשבין על האבוד ועל השרוף. m'chashvin al ha-avud v'al ha-saruf.
והאבוד והשרוף לא הוו בעולם. v'ha-avud v'ha-saruf lo hayu ba-olam. But one
minute they don't exist at all. ואפילו הכי תני מחשבין. v'afilu hachi
tani m'chashvin. And nevertheless you can have you can be מחשב m'chashev
and turn it into פיגול. So what he's basically saying is now
we'll see that's not exactly a challenge on what we said before
who says these are the same type of a case. But he's
basically arguing that look you don't need for there to be still
a little bit of something there like you were trying to argue
for it to be meaningful. There could be cases where it's not
there at all and it's still going to be meaningful and he's
going to try to argue the same for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
but we will continue this tomorrow.