Shov שוב, Shov, today's daf דף Daf is daf daled דף ד,
Daf daled, today is the 12th of the Omer עומר, Omer, and
we pick up in the middle of daled amud alef ד עמוד
א. Daled amud alef. Leima mesayyeia lei
לימא מסייעא ליה, Leima mesayyeia lei, actually we're almost done with daled
amud alef ד עמוד א, Daled amud alef, four lines, five lines
from the bottom. So we are dealing with the position of Rav
Giddel amar Rav רב גידל אמר רב, Rav Giddel amar Rav, who
said that we had already taught in our mishna משנה, Mishna, that
when the avodas עבודות Avodas are done b'psul בפסול, B'psul, shechita שחיטה
Shechita is done with machshavas pigul מחשבת פיגול Machshavas pigul or done
in the wrong place and so on, that number one it remains
kodshei Hashem קדשי השם, Kodshei Hashem, the korban קרבן, Korban, because of
the principle of im lo alos tayreidu אם לא עלו לא ירדו,
Im lo alos tayreidu, and number two the meat of kodshei kodashim
קדשי קדשים Kodshei kodashim does not go out of being me'ila מעילה,
Me'ila, which it normally would be if the zerika זריקה Zerika had
been correct because then it would be mutar l'kohanim מותר לכהנים. Mutar
l'kohanim. But when it's done with a psul פסול, Psul, it never
becomes mutar l'kohanim מותר לכהנים Mutar l'kohanim and the meat remains me'ila
מעילה. Me'ila. Rav Giddel amar Rav רב גידל אמר רב Rav Giddel
amar Rav said that the same is true if the zerika זריקה
Zerika was done with machshavas pigul מחשבת פיגול, Machshavas pigul, it's not
considered a legitimate zerika זריקה Zerika and therefore the meat remains me'ila
מעילה. Me'ila. Or if it's
kodshim kalim קדשים קלים, Kodshim kalim, the
emurim אימורים Emurim do not become fit for me'ila מעילה Me'ila because
the zerika זריקה Zerika was no good. So why is that really?
I mean and then the Gemara גמרא Gemara goes at great lengths
to discuss it, why is it any different than the mishna משנה?
Mishna? So Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says, well it's different... I mean isn't
it obvious from the mishna משנה? Mishna? And Tosafot תוספות Tosafot says
no, not so obvious because since we know by zerika זריקה Zerika
there's a principle of mertzeh l'pigulo מרצה לפיגולו, Mertzeh l'pigulo, that you
have to be finished correctly and in a certain way it's considered
as if it was a legitimate korban קרבן Korban except for the
pigul פיגול, Pigul, but there's a sense of a theoretical legitimacy of
the korban קרבן, Korban, mertzeh l'pigulo מרצה לפיגולו. Mertzeh l'pigulo. So therefore
I might have thought that the zerika זריקה Zerika therefore is considered
a legitimate zerika זריקה Zerika for the laws of me'ila מעילה Me'ila
and he tells us no.
And so that's what we had said and we had questions about
it and in the end we admitted that a status of pigul
פיגול Pigul does exist even at earlier stages, it is called pigul
פיגול Pigul even before the zerika זריקה Zerika takes place. But nevertheless,
while we did say that a shechitas pigul שחיטת פיגול Shechitas pigul
can do something, can sanctify the bread of a toda תודה, Toda,
it still will not have the effect here of changing the status
of the korban קרבן Korban for me'ila מעילה, Me'ila, because that requires
a real zerika זריקה Zerika done b'hechsher בהכשר B'hechsher in order to
make number one the meat fit for kohanim כהנים, Kohanim, or by
kodshim kalim קדשים קלים Kodshim kalim the emurim אימורים Emurim fit for
the mizbe'ach מזבח, Mizbe'ach, and only when that's done properly will the
status of me'ila מעילה Me'ila change. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara
wraps this up at the bottom of daled amud alef ד עמוד
א, Daled amud alef, and it says the following: Leima mesayyeia lei
לימא מסייעא ליה, Leima mesayyeia lei, let me try to bring a
proof to you. Hapigul l'olam mo'ilin bo הפיגול לעולם מועלין בו. Hapigul
l'olam mo'ilin bo. It says a braisa ברייתא Braisa says you always
there's always me'ila מעילה Me'ila by pigul פיגול. Pigul. If you do
pigul פיגול, Pigul, it never changes from me'ila מעילה, Me'ila, which presumably
means that we're dealing with kodshei kodashim קדשי קדשים Kodshei kodashim and
you had a pigul פיגול Pigul thought and it's never going to
go out of me'ila מעילה Me'ila because the meat will never become
mutar מותר. Mutar. Okay, so that's straightforward and that seems to be
the point of Rav Giddel amar Rav רב גידל אמר רב, Rav
Giddel amar Rav, presumably pigul פיגול Pigul at any stage or pigul
פיגול Pigul at the zerika זריקה. Zerika. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara
says lav af al gav d'zarak dam לאו אף על גב דזרק
דם, Lav af al gav d'zarak dam, doesn't that mean even when
there's a zerikas hadam זריקת הדם? Zerikas hadam? And again we'll sort
of translate this explain this the way we've been saying, which means
even though the dam דם Dam was done b'pigul בפיגול, B'pigul, it's
nevertheless still is not considered a legitimate zerikas hadam זריקת הדם? Zerikas
hadam? Umesyyeia lei וּמסייעא ליה, Umesyyeia lei, and that actual dam דם
Dam was nizrak נזרק Nizrak altogether, we'll see why it says that,
and therefore to support Rav Giddel amar Rav רב גידל אמר רב.
Rav Giddel amar Rav. Gemara גמרא Gemara says lo, d'lo zarak dam
לא דלא זרק דם. Lo d'lo zarak dam. No, we're talking that
the blood wasn't nizrak נזרק, Nizrak, that the pigul פיגול Pigul was
at an earlier stage and there was no zerika hadam זריקת הדם.
Zerika hadam. Now so the Gemara גמרא Gemara says what's the olam
עולם Olam then? First of all what's the olam עולם? Olam? Second
of all it's like what's the chiddush חידוש? Chiddush? Then even without
pigul פיגול Pigul it doesn't change the status. No status will ever
change until there's zerika hadam זריקת הדם, Zerika hadam, whether it's kodshim
kalim קדשים קלים Kodshim kalim becoming mutar מותר, Mutar, kodshei kodashim קדשי
קדשים Kodshei kodashim the emurim אימורים Emurim becoming fit for the mizbe'ach
מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So that's what the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, what does
it have to do with pigul פיגול? Pigul? So the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says iy d'lo zarak dam mai l'meimra אי דלא זרק דם
מאי למימרא. Iy d'lo zarak dam mai l'meimra. If you didn't do
zerika hadam זריקת הדם, Zerika hadam, of course, why do I need
you to tell me, who needs to talk about pigul פיגול? Pigul?
If no zerika hadam זריקת הדם, Zerika hadam, nothing changes. Ella d'zarak
אלא דזרק, Ella d'zarak, fine fine, he threw the blood. V'chi tanyah
hi b'olah וכי תניא היא בעולה. V'chi tanyah hi b'olah. So what
does it mean that me'ila מעילה Me'ila doesn't change? It means by
an olah עולה. Olah. Now of course, that's obvious by an olah
עולה, Olah, there's no status change by an olah עולה, Olah, right?
Even after zerika hadam זריקת הדם, Zerika hadam, it is going to
be all for the mizbe'ach מזבח. Mizbe'ach. Before zerika hadam זריקת הדם
Zerika hadam it's all for the mizbe'ach מזבח, Mizbe'ach, after zerika hadam
זריקת הדם Zerika hadam it's all for the mizbe'ach מזבח. Mizbe'ach. So
an olah עולה Olah there's always me'ila מעילה. Me'ila. There's no... how
are you going to get
the or עור Or though?
Okay, but we're not talking about the or עור Or and let's
bracket the or עור. Or. So anyway but for the olah עולה
Olah there's no... there's me'ila מעילה Me'ila and therefore it has nothing
again to do with
pigul פיגול. Pigul. There's
never a change of me'ila מעילה Me'ila before after, there's never a
change of me'ila מעילה Me'ila with or without pigul פיגול. Pigul. Iy
b'olah peshita d'gavoa ihi kulla אי בעולה פשיטא דגבוה היא כולה. Iy
b'olah peshita d'gavoa ihi kulla. If it's for an olah עולה, Olah,
of course
there's always going to be me'ila מעילה. Me'ila. The entire thing goes
to God before and after zerika זריקה, Zerika, it has nothing to
do with machshavas pigul מחשבת פיגול. Machshavas pigul. This thing is
obviously a meaningless statement. And in addition דקתני סיפא Dekatani Seifa the
end of that ברייתא Braita says לן דמא Lan Dama
if the blood was לינה Linah meaning you left the blood overnight,
you didn't זורק Zorek it on the same day. אף על פי
שחזר וזרקה Af Al Pi Shechazar Vezarkah
even if you went ahead and did the זריקה Zrikah afterwards, מועלין
בה Mo'alin Bah there's still מעילה. Me'ilah. Now why is that? Obviously
because there was no כשרה זריקה, Kesheirah Zrikah, so you cannot מתיר
Matir the meat with אכילה. Achilah. Okay. Now why is that relevant?
It's relevant because it suggests that had you thrown the blood at
the right time it would have changed מעילה Me'ilah status. So we're
obviously not talking about an עולה, Olah, right? It says because the
blood was thrown a day later the מעילה Me'ilah status still applies.
So if you threw it in the right time it would have
changed. אי אמרת בחטאת Ei Amart Bechattas if we're talking about a
חטאת Chattas שפיר Shapir it makes sense. If you threw it at
the right time then the meat stops being מעילה. Me'ilah. If you
threw it a day late, you haven't done a good זריקה, Zrikah,
the meat doesn't stop being מעילה. Me'ilah. אלא אי אמרת בעולה Ela
Ei Amart Be'olah
if we're talking about an עולה Olah צריכא למימר? Treicha Lemeimar? Again,
why is this a חידוש? Chiddush? And why you know and not
only because before we already said why is it a חידוש, Chiddush,
but here's a little bit of a sharper question because it implies
that had you done the זריקה Zrikah at the right time it
would have been different and that's not true, it's always going to
be מעילה. Me'ilah. So סיפא ודאי מסייע ליה. Seifa Vadai Mesaya Lei.
Fine,
the end definitely is a proof. The end definitely makes it clear
that we're talking about a חטאת Chattas and that we're talking and
therefore so the גמרא Gemara says רישא מאי? Reisha Mai? הואיל ומסייע
ליה סיפא
מסייע ליה נמי רישא. Ho'il Umeshaya Lei Seifa Mesaya Lei Nami Reisha.
So the גמרא Gemara says shouldn't we say that since the end
is a support for you the beginning is also a support for
you which means since the end is talking about a חטאת Chattas
and the end says that when there's לינה Linah with the דם
Dam it doesn't change the status. Therefore we should assume that the
beginning is also talking about a חטאת Chattas and if there's by
analogy if there's פיגול Piggul by the זריקה Zrikah the same way
if the זריקה Zrikah was done with פסול דם, Pasul Dam, if
there's פיגול Piggul by the זריקה Zrikah it also doesn't change the
status and you've proven your point. That if there's פיגול Piggul by
the זריקה, Zrikah, okay so here we're talking about a חטאת Chattas
presumably and the status doesn't change because it does not מתיר Matir
the meat באכילה. Be'achilah. So the גמרא Gemara says again there's a
little question here about the גרסא Girsa but the גמרא Gemara says
like this,
one minute, let me just check right here one second.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא Lo actually I'm trying to
read the question here exactly what the גרסא Girsa is, let me
just decide in one second.
Yes so the side has the גרסא Girsa which reads a little
easier, not clear if it's the exact original גרסא. Girsa. Anyway it
says וסיפא מי מסייע ליה Veseifa Mi Mesaya Lei as opposed to
לאו ודאי מסייע ליה. Lav Vadai Mesaya Lei. But anyway if you
read it all the way it's saying no you know what סיפא
לאו ודאי מסייע ליה. Seifa Lav Vadai Mesaya Lei. We could read
it that way. The end that it's talking about a חטאת Chattas
and לינת הדם, Linat Hadam, that's not such an obvious proof that
you could make an analogy from the fact that if the לינה
Linah is פסול Pasul that it doesn't change the status, that פיגול
Piggul also doesn't change the status. Why? Isn't it a good analogy?
If the דם Dam is פסול Pasul and you're זורק Zorek it
בפיסול Bepisul it doesn't change the status, so if you're זורק Zorek
it with פיגול Piggul it doesn't change the status? So לאו, Lo,
not necessarily. Why not? מאי שנא הלינה דקעביד בידים? Mai Shna Halinah
Dekavid Bayadayim?
But anyway there it's because you're עביד בידים, Avid Bayadayim, לא מהני
זריקה Lo Mahni Zrikah therefore the זריקה Zrikah won't work לאפוקי מידי
מעילה Le'afokei Midei Me'ilah to change the מעילה Me'ilah status. מחשבה Machshava
לא קעביד בידים Lo Ka'avid Bayadayim when you have a thought of
פיגול, Piggul, you're not doing something actively, מהני ליה זריקה לאפוקי מידי
מעילה. Mahni Lei Zrikah Le'afokei Midei Me'ilah. Therefore maybe the זריקה Zrikah
will work. Now what does this mean? Actually it's quite interesting. If
you would have asked me which action is more active and which
one is more passive: letting the blood stay overnight and then throwing
it, or thinking about it to eat it at the wrong time
when you're throwing it? So you would have thought that neither of
them has a physical action. Thinking is at least doing something actively
rather than doing passively. So you would have thought that's the more
active. The גמרא Gemara says no, leaving over is somehow more active
because you're also
throwing it the next day.
But you're also throwing the דם Dam with מחשבת פיגול. Machshevet Piggul.
Okay maybe the throwing it at the wrong time is a doing
of something. Anyway right, but the גמרא Gemara says you know anyway
the way it seems to be saying is is that right is
that if you're supposed to do something with it and you're not
doing something with it you're in the world of action. So whether
you're doing it right or doing it wrong you're in the world
of action. And that's a little bit more seen as a active
type of a problem rather than if I'm just physically everything is
right and the thing that's going wrong is what's going on in
my head. Okay so anyway that's a little funny and it's also
a little funny that it says and therefore maybe it more changes
the status, it more has an implication for מעילה. Me'ilah. Now here
you can understand it a little bit because when the problem is
totally in my head maybe you could say that it is a
less sort of like concrete you know type of a פסול. Pasul.
So if you physically everything was done correctly, the only problem is
what I'm thinking. So therefore as opposed to when I do the
זריקת דם Zrikat Dam the wrong day there's an actual factual problem
that it's old blood and therefore. What it's saying is the following.
Remember, what are we trying to argue? We're trying to prove or
disprove that זריקת דם zrikas dam with a thought of פיגול pigul
maybe that should change the status. Why? I mean it's still פסול,
pasul, but as we said, well, yes, it's פסול, pasul, but a
מחשבת פיגול, machsheves pigul, you know, פיגול pigul in some ways has
this weird idea that it's as if it's מרצה, meratze, and so
here what we're saying is, you know why also maybe it works?
Because maybe it's not so much of an objective physical פסול. psul.
It's something going on in your head. And since in terms of
the physical world everything is going on correctly, maybe that's significant enough
that it's as if it was a good זריקה zrika to change
the status. Okay, so that's a nice way of explaining why I
might think that זריקת פיגול zrikas pigul might work, because at least
physically things are being done correctly. So here's what the גמרא Gemara
is saying. You know what?
This ברייתא braisa is clear that if you throw the blood a
day old, it does not affect the status for פיגול pigul because
you didn't do a good זריקת דם. zrikas dam. Isn't this a
good evidence that if you throw the blood with מחשבת פיגול, machsheves
pigul, it also doesn't change the status because you didn't do a
good זריקה? zrika? And the גמרא Gemara says, no. In the first
case you were physically doing something wrong, day old blood. Clearly it's
not good, clearly the status doesn't change. When you're physically doing everything
right and there's just a problem with the thought in your head,
so maybe in theory it's as if it were a good enough
זריקה zrika and maybe therefore it should change the status. So that's
what the גמרא Gemara is saying, that you can't argue by analogy
from the problem of old blood to the problem of a מחשבת
פיגול. machsheves pigul. The problem still is that while you can't argue
by analogy, the text of the ברייתא braisa still seems to be
evidence. Because since the end of the ברייתא braisa is talking about
a חטאת, chatas, the beginning of the ברייתא braisa is talking about
a חטאת, chatas, and the beginning of the ברייתא braisa said that
with a thought of פיגול pigul it doesn't change the status. So
the גמרא Gemara is sort of like bracketing that and the גמרא
Gemara is saying we might want to still insist the beginning of
the ברייתא braisa is an עולה, olah, okay, of course it's פשיטא,
pshita, it's not really telling you any חידוש, chiddush, and עולה olah
is always מעילה, meilah, fine, whatever. But anyway, the only explicit thing
we have is זריקה zrika of day old blood and that doesn't
prove the פיגול pigul question because there at least you're physically doing
something wrong as opposed to זריקת פיגול zrikas pigul you're not physically
doing something wrong. Okay, but the simple sense again is that the
ברייתא braisa is talking the entire thing about a חטאת chatas and
about פיגול pigul and it's a proof to רב גידל אמר רב.
Rav Gidal amar Rav. Now we're going to try one more time
with this.
Okay.
לימא מסייע ליה, leima mesayei lei, let's try to prove it from
here. הפיגול בקדשי קדשים מועלין בו, hapigul bekadshei kadoshim moalin bo, similar
type of statement. פיגול pigul by קדשי קדשים kadshei kadoshim there's מעילה,
meilah, which presumably means that although the meat of קדשי קדשים kadshei
kadoshim would change if you do the זריקה zrika correctly, if you
do it with פיגול, pigul, it's not going to change the status.
Seems again to be the statement of רב גידל אמר רב, Rav
Gidal amar Rav, although maybe it's שחיטה shchita not זריקה, zrika, but
whatever. Okay. לאו אף על גב דזרק, lav af al gav dezarak,
aren't we not talking about that there was זריקת דם zrikas dam
with again מחשבת פיגול? machsheves pigul? ומסייע ליה umesayei lei and that's
a support to רב גידל אמר רב. Rav Gidal amar Rav. לא
דלא זרק lo delo zarak he didn't do זריקת דם. zrikas dam.
Of course if you didn't do זריקת דם, zrikas dam, as we
said before, who cares about פיגול pigul thought? You didn't do זריקת
דם zrikas dam there's not going to be any status change. אבל
זרק מאי, aval zarak mai, what would happen if you did זריקת
דם? zrikas dam? הכי נמי דאין מועלין בו, hachi nami de'ein moalin
bo, you would say that actually there would be a status change
even with a thought of פיגול? pigul? אמאי קתני סיפא amai katani
seifa why did the end of the ברייתא braisa say בקדשים קלים
אין מועלין בו? bekadashim kalim ein moalin bo? So at קדשים קלים
kadashim kalim with the thought of פיגול pigul there's no מעילה. meilah.
Why is there no מעילה meilah by קדשים קלים kadashim kalim with
a thought of פיגול? pigul? Why not by the אימורין, imurin, same
point? A thought of פיגול, pigul, a זריקת פיגול zrikas pigul is
not a good זריקה zrika and doesn't change the status of the
אימורין. imurin. So if that's true that we're looking for opportunities to
say that there's no מעילה, meilah, why do we have to go
to קדשים קלים? kadashim kalim?
אמאי קתני סיפא בקדשים קלים אין מועלין בו? amai katani seifa bekadashim
kalim ein moalin bo? לפלוג ברישא וליתני, liplug breisha v'lisni, make a
distinction that sometimes even by קדשי קדשים kadshei kadoshim there's going to
be cases of no מעילה. meilah. וליתני, v'lisni, לפני זריקה מועלין בו,
lifnei zrika moalin bo, before זריקה zrika there's מעילה meilah because there's
no been זריקת דם. zrikas dam. לאחר זריקה אין מועלין בו, le'achar
zrika ein moalin bo, after זריקה zrika there's no מעילה. meilah. Why
no מעילה? meilah? Because there's זריקת דם zrikas dam and even with
פיגול pigul if it really disagreed with רב גידל אמר רב, Rav
Gidal amar Rav, even a זריקת דם zrikas dam with פיגול pigul
there should be no מעילה. meilah. So if you're looking for examples
of no מעילה, meilah, why didn't you say after זריקה zrika no
מעילה? meilah? Obviously after זריקה zrika there still is going to be
מעילה meilah because a זריקת פיגול zrikas pigul is not significant.
ההוא ודאי מסייע ליה. hahu vadai mesayei lei. So you're right, from
the end that it says that a זריקה zrika of פיגול pigul
doesn't work for קדשים קלים kadashim kalim is definitely a proof that
a זריקת פיגול zrikas pigul is not meaningful.
לימא הוא דמסייע ליה סיפא מסייע ליה רישא. leima hu demesayei lei
seifa mesayei lei reisha. So maybe we should say since the end
is a proof, it's a similar structure to before. Meaning there's two
questions here. Number one, the structure of the ברייתא. braisa. What's the
ברייתא braisa trying to talk about? And in both cases the end
of the ברייתא braisa is very clear. So there's two questions. A,
can we prove your case by analogy to the end of the
ברייתא, braisa, and number two is... Does the end of the ברייתא
braisa *beraita* prove what the beginning of the ברייתא braisa *beraita* is
talking about? So here we said that the end of the ברייתא
*beraita* makes it clear that זריקת פיגול piggul *zerikat pigul* by קדשי
קלים *kodshei kalim* doesn't change the status of the meat. So number
one, by analogy that would say that זריקת פיגול pigul *zerikat pigul*
by קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* also doesn't change the status of the
meat. By קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim* it doesn't make it fit for
פיגול pigul? *pigul*, by קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* it doesn't take it
out of the מעילה meilah. *me'ilah* category. That's one proof, the analogy
to the way פיגול piggul, *pigul* doesn't work by קדשי קלים *kodshei
kalim*. The other argument is since the סיפא *seifa* is talking about
this case, doesn't that prove that the רישא *reisha* is talking also
even after you've done the זריקה zrika *zerika* and even so the
status doesn't change? To which the גמרא gemara *gemara* says the second
point isn't a point. Why? I would say like this, סיפא *seifa*,
where
were we? מסייע ליה נמי רישא *mesayei lei nami reisha*. No, קדשי
קלים פסיקא ליה, הכא לא lo, פסיקא ליה *kodshei kalim pesika lei,
hacha lo pesika lei*. The reason we went to קדשי קלים *kodshei
kalim* to get an example where there's never going to be מעילה
meilah *me'ilah* is because that's categorical. If you're doing פיגול piggul, *pigul*
thought and you're dealing with קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim*, there's never מעילה
meilah *me'ilah*. There's not מעילה meilah. *me'ilah* before because it's קדשי קלים
*kodshei kalim*. There's not מעילה meilah *me'ilah* after because the זריקה zrika
*zerika* won't affect the status of אימורים *imurim* because it's פיגול piggul
*pigul*. So therefore if we're looking for an example of no מעילה
me'ilah. *me'ilah* with a פיגול piggul *pigul* thought, we're going to go
to קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim* because that is categorical, there'll never be
מעילה *me'ilah*. Okay, but I could argue that in theory there could
also be a case of no מעילה *me'ilah* by קדשי קדשים *kodshei
kodashim* that maybe after you do the זריקה zrika *zerika* by קדשי
קדשים *kodshei kodashim* maybe it does change the status of the meat
and maybe there would be an example of no מעילה *me'ilah*. So
why did I run to the example of קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim*
no מעילה *me'ilah*? Because by קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim* there's never מעילה
*me'ilah* from beginning to end with the פיגול piggul *pigul* thought. But
אין הכי נמי *in hachi nami*, in theory it's possible that in
the רישא *reisha* we're talking only before זריקה zrika? *zerika* and then
after זריקה zrika *zerika* the status would change.
Okay, so those are— and we say none of that though? What?
We say that we don't actually see that.
So these are very, very דחוק *dachuk* answers. Basically the point is
like this: these ברייתות *beraitot* are quite explicit that with a פיגול
piggul *pigul* thought the status doesn't change. Whether to raise קדשי קלים
*kodshei kalim* up or to bring קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* down, with
a פיגול piggul *pigul* thought the status doesn't change. And at the
end of the day, the point, the statement of רבי אלעזר אמר
רב *Rabbi Elazar amar Rav* is not such a חידוש *chiddush* because
our whole משנה mishnah *mishnah* says that when you do things בפסול
be-psul. *bepesul*, then the status doesn't change. You need a כשר kasher.
*kasher* זריקה zrika, *zerika* to either raise the level of the אימורים
*imurim* of קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim* or lower the level of the
meat by קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim*. So why is the גמרא gemara
*gemara* getting so worked up? Again, the גמרא gemara *gemara* somehow thinks
that פיגול piggul *pigul* with זריקה zrika *zerika* maybe is different. Since
זריקה zrika *zerika* for פיגול piggul *pigul* makes it as if it
was מרצה *meratzeh* for laws of פיגול piggul *pigul*, maybe that would
be impactful enough to even change the status for מעילה *me'ilah*. That's
the question: פיגול piggul *pigul* plus זריקה zrika *zerika*, maybe that is
considered to be meaningful for מעילה *me'ilah* and change the status. And
in the end, we pretty much admit that it is not. Certainly
what the ברייתא *beraita* is clear about is that it's not significant
enough to raise the level of the אימורים *imurim* of קדשי קלים
*kodshei kalim*. But certainly by analogy if we can't raise the קדשי
קלים *kodshei kalim*, it shouldn't also lower the status of the קדשי
קדשים *kodshei kodashim*. And that in the end is the conclusion, that
when things are done בפסול b'psul, *bepesul* and you don't have a
כשר kasher. *kasher* זריקה zrika *zerika*, even if the only problem is
פיגול piggul *pigul* and even if in some ways פיגול piggul *pigul*
and זריקה zrika *zerika* is as if it were a good זריקה
zrika, *zerika*, nevertheless that has no impact for מעילה *me'ilah* unless you
actually change the status of the meat. You make the meat fit
for the כהנים *kohanim*, or you actually make the אימורים *imurim* fit
for the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbeach*. Now that is a very nice segue
into the next discussion. Maybe we'll even get a whole דף daf,
*daf* ahead today. So let's take a look. Because the next discussion
is the next part of the משנה mishnah *mishnah*, which is exactly
this, that when the meat of
קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim* becomes מותר mutar לכהנים *mutar lakohanim*, then they
go out of— I think he says פיגול piggul *pigul*— goes out
of מעילה *me'ilah*. But only after the moment when it actually becomes
מותר mutar, לכהנים *mutar lakohanim*. So let's take a look. Now we're
quoting the next part of the משנה mishnah *mishnah*. At זריקה zrika,
*zerika*, but now the גמרא gemara *gemara* is actually going to question,
do you really need זריקה zrika *zerika*? The same way it questioned
before, is זריקת פיגול piggul *zerikat pigul* maybe it's כאילו *ke'ilu* a
זריקה zrika. *zerika*? Now we're going to actually question, maybe even a
stage a little bit before זריקה zrika. *zerika* could also work. Okay,
so all of these questions are going around this issue of when
does that status change?
The זריקה zerika. *zerika* in a classic case brings the meat of
קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* out of מעילה *me'ilah*, מותר mutar לכהנים *mutar
lakohanim*, and the אימורים *imurim* of קדשי קלים *kodshei kalim* into מעילה
*me'ilah*, fit for the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbeach*. So the first question was,
what about a quasi-זריקה zerika. *zerika*, זריקת פיגול piggul. *zerikat pigul*, which
is פסול pasul? *pasul* but it's as if it were a זריקה
zerika? *zerika*? Now we're going to ask, what about if it's not
exactly זריקה zerika, *zerika*? Okay,
so these are very conceptually linked issues. Let's read now from the
two dots here, of course the quote's from the משנה mishnah *mishnah*.
כלל אמר רבי יהושע *Klal amar Rabbi Yehoshua*. So Rabbi Yehoshua said
a general principle. כל שנעשה לו שעת היתר לכהנים אין מועלין בו
ein moalin bo. *Kol shena'asa lo sha'at heter lakohanim ein mo'alin bo*.
Any time there was actually the meat became מותר mutter לכהנים *mutar
lakohanim*, then there's no longer מעילה *me'ilah* about the meat of קדשי
קדשים *kodshei kodashim*. וכל שלא נעשה לו שעת היתר לכהנים מועלין בו
*Vekol shelo na'asa lo sha'at heter lakohanim mo'alin bo*. But if it
never became מותר *mutar*, then it retains its מעילה *me'ilah* status. איזהו
שהיתה לה שעת היתר לכהנים *Eizehu she'hayesa la she'at heter la'kohanim*? What's
an example of that? שלנה *She'lanah*, ושנטמאת *u'she'nitmeis*, ושיצאת *u'she'yatzas*.
Let's say you left the meat stay overnight, so it was originally
מותר *muttar*. Now it's just נותר *notar*, or it became טמא tamei.
*tamei* after you shechted it, but there was a moment that it
could have been eaten. Or it went out of the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash*, it's a פסול pasul יוצא *p'sul yotzei*. All of these
cases there was a moment the meat could have been eaten. So
therefore it stops being מעילה *me'ilah*. ואיזהו שלא היתה לה שעת היתר
לכהנים *Ve'eizu she'lo hayesa la she'at heter la'kohanim*? What's an example where
the meat never became מותר *muttar*? שנשחטה חוץ לזמנה וחוץ למקומה *She'nishcheta
chutz lizmanya ve'chutz limkomah*. You shechted it with מחשבה *machshavah* of פיגול
piggul *pigul*, either the wrong time or the wrong place, or similar
to פיגול piggul *pigul*. So therefore from the moment of שחיטה shechitah,
*shechitah* it wasn't fit. שקבלו פסולים psulim וזרקו ve-zarku את דמה *She'kiblu
p'sulim ve'zarku es dama*, or פסול pasul. *pasul* person caught the blood
or sprinkled the blood. So all these types of cases the meat
never became מותר *muttar*. So the simple way of reading this is,
is that if any פסול psul *psul* happened prior to the זריקה
zerika *zerikah*, it's no good. If the פסול pasul, *psul*—because then it
never became מותר *muttar*. If the פסול pasul, *psul* happened after the
זריקה zerika, *zerikah*, then there was a moment it was good. But
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is going to question whether we are talking
precisely about the moment of זריקה zerika. *zerikah* or not.
And no good equals מעילה *me'ilah*.
And if the זריקה zerika. *zerikah* was—if the meat was never good,
then it retains מעילה *me'ilah*. Okay, exactly. So, אמר ליה בר קפרא
לבר פדא *Amar lei Bar Kappara le'Bar Padda*. So בר *Bar*—or something—לבר
פדא *le'Bar Padda*. So בר קפרא *Bar Kappara* said to בר פדא
*Bar Padda*: בן אחותי *Ben achosi*, my nephew—he was his nephew—ראה מה
אני שואלך למחר בבית המדרש *Re'ei mah ani sho'alcha lemachar beveiseih medrash*.
He was sort of like prepping him, you know? He was saying:
Tomorrow we're going to go into the בית המדרש *Beis Hamedrash*, we're
learning מעילה *me'ilah*, be prepared to ask me the following question. You
know, feed me the good question. Oh, what a brilliant question! Or
maybe, maybe it was like, you know, the straight man in the
comedy act. Like he needed the question because he wanted to have
the discussion.
Anyway, it was just like: Make sure to ask me the good
question.
No, 'cause he's got—no, he's going to feed it to him right
now. Okay? Here's the question you should be asking me tomorrow in
the בית המדרש *Beis Hamedrash*. Okay? What's the question? היתר שחיטה shechitah
שנינו *Heter shechitah shaninu*? When we say the moment it becomes מותר
*muttar* changes its status, what precise moment is that? Is that that
the שחיטה shechitah *shechitah* was done correctly? Even if the פסול pasul,
*psul* came after the שחיטה shechitah, *shechitah*, once the שחיטה shechitah *shechitah*
was done correctly, that's close enough to changing the status and therefore
it's good, okay? או היתר זריקה שנינו zrika shaninu *O heter zerikah
shaninu*? Or are we talking about that מותר *muttar*—the היתר *heter* of
זריקה zerika, *zerikah*? Now the words שחיטה shechitah *shechitah* and זריקה zerika
*zerikah* mean something slightly different. היתר שחיטה shechita *Heter shechitah* means the
שחיטה *shechitah* was done correctly. היתר זריקה zerika *Heter zerikah* means it
was fit for being זרוק *zaruk*, which really means—for being—which really means
the קבלה kabalah *kabbalah* was done correctly. It's a little confusing. היתר
זריקה zerika *Heter zerikah* means it was at the status where it
could have been נזרק nizrak, *nizrak*. So the קבלה kabalah *kabbalah* was
done correctly. Maybe that's good enough. Maybe that's as if it was
נזרק nizrak. *nizrak*. Sometimes we have a principle of כל העומד לזרוק
כזרק דמי *kol ha'omed lizrok kezarak dami*. So maybe once it was
at a state where it could have been נזרק nizrak. *nizrak*, okay,
it's as if it was נזרק nizrak? *nizrak*. You don't actually need
it to be נזרק nizrak *nizrak*. או *O*, or third possibility, היתר
אכילה achilah שנינו *heter achilah shaninu*?
Only when it actually became in practice מותר באכילה *muttar ba'achilah*. So
what moment matters? שחיטה *Shechitah*, קבלה kabalah *kabbalah*, or זריקה zerika? *zerikah*?
Now, the simple reading of our משנה mishnah. *Mishnah* is of course
זריקה zerika *zerikah*, right? Because—but let's take a look at—so he fed
him this question. So it doesn't sort of happen next line, which
says: And then he asked him... we're not there yet. But that's
the סוגיא *sugya*. So they came the next day to the בית
המדרש *Beis Hamedrash*, he asked the question, and here was the conversation
they had. So חזקיה Chizkiyah. אמר *Chizkiyahu amar*, he said...
this is all in the בית המדרש *Beis Hamedrash*, presumably.
Presumably that's the end of where he fed him the line. Okay.
So now he never actually answered it then. Well, no, now he's
going to answer it. Okay? So now בר קפרא *Bar Kappara*, in
response—when this question was posed to him—laid out that there is a
debate about this. חזקיה אמר *Chizkiyahu amar*: היתר שחיטה שנינו *heter shechitah
shaninu*. It's a debate of חזקיה *Chizkiyahu* and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
חזקיה *Chizkiyahu* says we're talk—if—as long as the שחיטה *shechitah* was done
correctly, that changes the status. רבי יוחנן אמר היתר אכילה שנינו *Rabbi
Yochanan amar heter achilah shaninu*. No, it has to get to the
point where it's fit—actually fit to be eaten.
But no one says היתר זריקה zerika.
*heter zerikah*? Right. אמר רבי זירא *Amar Rabbi Zeira*... which—no, היתר שחיטה
*heter shechitah* meaning קבלה kabalah. *kabbalah*, don't get confused. היתר זריקה zerika,
*Heter zerikah* means fit for זריקה zerika *zerikah*, that the קבלה kabalah
*kabbalah* was done correctly. Okay, so אמר רבי זירא *amar Rabbi Zeira*:
לא דקא מתניתין דלא כחזקיה ודלא כרבי יוחנן *Lo daka matnisin delo
keChizkiyahu vedelo keRabbi Yochanan*. So now we're, by the way, on עמוד
א *Amud Aleph*. So, the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* is not—does not meet
precisely—meaning, if you're paying attention to the—to
the—if you do a precise and close reading of the משנה mishnah
*Mishnah*, it does not suggest either חזקיה *Chizkiyahu* or רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*, which is funny. I would have thought it suggests רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*. It sounds like the meat had to really be מותר
באכילה *muttar ba'achilah*. But let's see why he argues this. תנן tenan,
*Tnan*, let's see what our משנה mishnah *Mishnah* says. Here's the examples
where it says that it became—it has changed its status. שלנה *She'lanah*,
that it lay overnight, ושנטמאת *u'she'nitmeis* became טמא tamei. *tamei*, ושיצאת *u'she'yatzas*
and that it went out. Now what's the 'it' that lay overnight?
So he says: לאו דלן דם dam, *Lav delan dam*? So for
some reason he's assuming—of course, you know, this is like taking your
assumptions and reading them back into the text, okay? 'Cause we assumed
that the meat had to become מותר *muttar*, so we assumed that
what did it mean? It meant that after the meat was מותר
*muttar*, it stayed overnight, it became טמא tamei? *tamei*. But he's assuming
no, the meat doesn't have in practice to become מותר *muttar*. So
what stayed overnight? The blood. Okay? So he's reading it that you
caught the blood correctly and then the blood became טמא tamei *tamei*,
the blood went out of the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, the blood
stayed overnight, and therefore or it's going to still be have changed
the status. Why? Because the blood was caught correctly. So the היכי
קשיא is what is the thing that became פסול? pasul The meat?
And therefore the point is the meat has to actually have become
as long as the meat was מותר for a second? Or is
it the blood? And even if the meat never was מותר, as
long as the blood was fit for a second to be נזרק,
nizrak that's enough. דתני, De-tany, so he's reading it the blood and
the משנה mishna says אין מועלין בו. Once the blood, if the
blood became פסול pasul after it was caught, there's no longer מעילה.
ושמע מינה התר זריקה שנינו, u-shma mina heter zrika shaninu, you see
the key is that it was fit for זריקה zerika and even
if the problem came and it never actually the זריקה zerika, never
took place.
So says לא, no. Who says we're talking about the blood? לן
בשר, lan basar, the meat became you know slept over, the meat
became טמא. tamei So the meat it's all about the being fit
for being eaten and we're saying that the problem occurred to the
meat after the meat became fit for being eaten. So not that
it occurred to the blood.
That would only be if the זריקה zerika was done correctly.
Right. So basically it says look if a problem came later it's
not an issue like it became טמא. tamei Well what became טמא?
tamei Do you read it if the meat was first מותר and
then became טמא tamei, it stops מעילה or if the blood was
first caught and then became טמא tamei it stops מעילה even if
the blood hasn't been thrown and can't be thrown? So that's the
question. So he says, so he says no it's the meat and
therefore it's about actually eating it. אבל
דם נזרק, aval dam nizrak, but the blood was thrown correctly. משום
הכי תני אין מועלין בו. mishum hachi tani ein moalin bo. Therefore
there's no מעילה. Okay so that משנה mishna. was not so much
of a problem. It's much more of a problem according to the
idea that it's שחיטה, right? I mean I don't know how anybody
could say התר שחיטה. heter shechitah. The משנה mishna, says that says
either it means the meat became טמא tamei. or the blood became
טמא tamei but the שחיטה was done correctly. So the position of
שחיטה sort of gets falls by the wayside. I don't see how
it could at all be read in the משנה mishna and the
real question focus is on is it זריקה? zerika, Is it that
it has to be קבלה kabalah? has to be done correctly or
זריקה zerika has to be done correctly or framed by the גמרא
gemara that התר זריקה, heter zrika, fit for זריקה, zerika? or התר
אכילה, heter achilah, fit for being eaten? Those are the real two
positions that are in competition.
I don't know why they ask on חזקיה.
I don't know. So now the גמרא gemara says you already said
לא דייקא, lo daika, that was just a defense for the אכילה
position. So now the גמרא gemara says like this: תנן, let's go
back to our משנה. Mishnah באיזו שלא היתה לה שעת הכושר, Be-eizehu
she-lo haisah lah sha'as haksher, what's an example where it was never
fit? שנשחטה חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו, She-nishchata chutz lizmano ve-chutz limkomo, a
מחשבת פיגול machshevet pigul at the שחיטה, that doesn't prove anything. There
even the שחיטה was not done correctly. But now we get on:
וקבלו פסולים וזרקו את הדם. ve-kiblu psulim ve-zarku es hadam. It was
accepted the
פסולים psulim caught the blood and sprinkled the blood. Now how do
you read the וזרקו את הדם? ve-zarku es hadam? So there are
a couple ways of reading it. You could read פסולים psulim caught
it and in the same scenario they caught and threw the blood.
That's how the גמרא Gemara reads it. But I don't think I
would have read the משנה Mishnah, that way. I would have read
the משנה mishna two scenarios. Either פסולים psulim caught the blood or
פסולים psulim וזרקו the blood. An or not an and right? And
then again it proves that it's all about the זריקה zrika. because
even if everything was done correctly as long as the קבלה kabalah
was incorrect or even as long as just the זריקה zrika was
incorrect it's a problem. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't see and then
it would have been again a proof that it's about the זריקה
zrika. but the גמרא Gemara. doesn't read it that way. It reads
it as at least this position that says it's about the קבלה
kabalah reads the ו vav as one scenario. They caught and sprinkled
the blood.
Or else it would have said או זרקו. o zarku. I don't
know sometimes something's in the word.
Now
we say like this: So that's going to be his proof. So
he says like this: וקבלו פסולים וזרקו את הדם. ve-kiblu psulim ve-zarku
es hadam. היכי דמי? Heicha dami? So we're assuming one scenario. What's
the case? אילימא דזרקוה פסולים וקבלוה פסולים, Ilema de-zarkuha psulim ve-kibluha psulim,
that both פסולים psulim in this one scenario caught and sprinkled the
blood. למה לי הני תרתי? Lama li hanei tartei? Why would I
have to say both problems, you know? אלא לאו דקבלו פסולים וזרקו
כשרים, Ella lav de-kiblu psulim ve-zarku ksheirim, we're still assuming one scenario
but it says it says what's the phrase here? שקבלו פסולים וזרקו
את הדם. she-kiblu psulim ve-zarku es hadam. Didn't say who was זורק.
zorek. They. So it means פסולים psulim. caught the blood and then
the blood was נזרק. nizrak People threw זריקת הדם zrikas hadam not
the פסולים. psulim So he's reading the משנה mishna that way. The
only problem is therefore in the קבלה. kabalah. Okay and it's פסול.
pasul Now of course fine if the קבלה's kabalah. no good it's
no good. But the point is why did we hone in on
the קבלה? kabalah And the argument will be to suggest that if
the problem came a later than the קבלה kabalah. it would be
okay. אלא לאו דקבלו פסולים וזרקו כשרים? Ella lav de-kiblu psulim ve-zarku
ksheirim? ותני אין מועלין בו? Ve-tani ein moalin bo? And there's מעילה
because the קבלה kabalah. was בפסול. שמע
מינה התר זריקה שנינו. Shma mina heter zrika shaninu. So you see
the key is the again התר זריקה heter zrika means קבלה. kabalah
The key is the moment of קבלה. kabalah If there were פסולים
at the קבלה kabalah that's when it that's when it stops the
change but if the פסול psul came later like at the זריקה
zrika. then actually the status would have changed because it's all about
the קבלה. kabala, That's the argument. Again not the greatest proof because
it all depends on how you read that ו. vav. Let's see
how the גמרא Gemara answers it. The גמרא Gemara answers it in
a different way. מתקיף לה רב יוסף. Maskif lah Rav Yosef. רב
יוסף Rav Yosef asked on this. ואי סלקא דעתך איכא למיפלג הכי,
Ve-ee salka da'atach eicha lemiflag hachi,
if you think that you can make this type of a distinction,
what it really means is take this phrase of קבלו פסולים וזרקו
kiblu psulim ve-zarku and read it with that degree of precision to
hone in on
the קבלה. kabbala, I'm going to give you another place where we
use that phrase where we do not mean it precisely at all.
Let's take a look.
הדי תנן, Hadi tnan, that which we taught התם, hasam, over there
in זבחים, Zevachim,
another totally different הלכה. halacha. חטאת פסולה אין דמה טעון כיבוס. Chatas
pesulah ein damah taun kibus.
Okay, there's a הלכה halacha in the תורה Torah that says, מצוות
התורה mitzvas ha-Torah that says, by a חטאת, chatas, ואשר יזה מדמה
על הבגד אשר יזה עליה תכבס במקום קדוש.
va-asher yizeh mi-damah al ha-beged asher
yizeh aleha techabes be-makom kadosh. במקום טהור. be-makom tahor.
Michael? יכבס. yichabes. Anyway, anyway,
it says that if the blood of a חטאת chatas is sprinkled
on a בגד, beged, you have to be, there's a special ritual
of cleansing the garment. Now the הלכה halacha there is only a
חטאת כשרה. chatas kesherah. Only the blood of a חטאת כשרה, chatas
kesherah, not the blood of a חטאת פסולה chatas pesulah that sprinkles
on a garment, you don't have to do this special ritual of
cleansing it. Okay. Now what constitutes, at what moment is its status
determined as חטאת כשרה, chatas kesherah, חטאת פסולה? chatas pesulah? Similar type
of a question. So let's take a look. תנן התם, Tnan hasam,
we taught over there. חטאת פסולה, Chatas pesulah, if its חטאת chatas
is פסול, pasul אין דמה טעון כיבוס. ein damah taun kibus. Then
you do not have to cleanse the garment if it got sprinkled
onto some garment,
splattered, I should say. בין שהיתה לה שעת הכושר ונפסלה. Bein she-haysah
lah shas ha-kosher ve-nifselah. Now
this does not make the distinction our משנה made by מעילה. I
don't care when it became פסול, psul whether it at once was
fit and then became פסול, psul בין שלא היתה לו שעת הכושר
ונפסלה, bein she-lo haysah lo shas ha-kosher ve-nifselah,
whether it was never fit. So as opposed to where us it
matters if there was a moment when it was okay, there it
doesn't matter. All that matters is the here and now. If it's
פסול pasul now, whether it was fit once and became פסול pasul
or was never fit, it doesn't matter. If it's פסול pasul, now,
the blood does not affect the garment. Okay, בין שלא היתה לו
שעת הכושר ונפסלה. bein she-lo haysah lo shas ha-kosher ve-nifselah. Okay, either
way, the blood does not affect. איזו היא שהיתה לה שעת הכושר
ונפסלה? Eizo hi she-haysah lah shas ha-kosher ve-nifselah? So although we've just
said that this distinction doesn't matter, we're going to still describe the
two categories: what's a category of having been fit and a category
of not having been fit. So what's an example of having been
fit? שלנה ושנטמאת או שיצאה, She-lanah ve-shinitmes o she-yatza'ah,
exactly what we have in our משנה. It was שחט shachted correctly
and then it became טמא, taken out, slept over. Again, is the
it the blood or is it the meat? Maybe here the it
is the blood because the blood is here what's a little bit
more relevant. Okay. So anyway, what example is it was שחט shachted
correctly and then the פסול pasul occurred to and it became טמא
or whatever. איזו היא שלא היתה לה שעת הכושר? Eizo hi she-lo
haysah lah shas ha-kosher? What's an example where it never became fit?
שנשחטה חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו. She-nishchetah chutz lizmano ve-chutz limkomo.
It was שחט shachted with an intention of the wrong place, wrong
time, like a type of a פיגול thought. Clearly it was never
fit. From the moment of שחיטה it was never fit. וקיבלו פסולים
וזרקו את דמה, Ve-kiblu pesulim ve-zarku es damah, and that's what we're
honing in on and this last phrase of our משנה, which is,
or the blood was accepted, was caught by people that are פסול
psul or was נזרק. nizrak, Now what does that mean, the phrase
and it was נזרק? Again here, you can't say it matters whether
the פסול psul was done by קבלה kabbala? or זריקה zrika or
both or neither or whatever. Any פסול pasul we just said doesn't
matter when it occurs, right? It's the same הלכה. halacha. But here's
why the גמרא Gemara is going to make an issue about this
phrase in this case about the sprinkling, about the splatting of the
blood of the חטאת. chatas. Let's take a look. היכי דמי? Heichi
dami? What's the case? אילימא דקיבלו פסולים וזרקו פסולים, Ilima de-kiblu pesulim
ve-zarku pesulim,
so if you say like you were trying to be מדייק medayek
before, both things happened, a פסול pasul, person caught the blood and
sprinkled the blood, then that would suggest הוא דאין טעון כיבוס, hu
de-ein taun kibus,
that would suggest only that case because both problems were there then
you don't have to do כיבוס. kibus. הא קיבלו פסולים וזרקו כשרים
דמה טעון כיבוס. Ha kiblu pesulim ve-zarku kesherim damah taun kibus. So
first of all, now not only is it sort of patently obvious
that if even only a פסול pasul, at one stage, either the
קבלה kabbala or the זריקה, zrika it would not require כיבוס kibus
because we said we don't care when it became פסול, pasul, but
the גמרא Gemara goes even further. Not only that, even if כשרים
kesherim were מקבל mekabel and זורק zorek the דם, it's not required
כיבוס. kibus. Why not? Then everything, it's כשר. kasher Why would that
not be true? Because of another הלכה. halacha. Why? קרי כאן אשר
יזה מדמה Kari kan asher yizeh mi-damah ולא שכבר הוזה. ve-lo she-kevar
huzah. The תורה Torah says if its blood is splattered on a
garment, not after the blood has already been splattered in the right
place. That's the דרשה drasha of the גמרא. Gemara If the blood
was actually נזרק on the מזבח, any remainder blood, even not the
blood on the מזבח, any remainder blood will not have the potency
and the power to affect the garment. The idea that the blood
only affects the garment is only of a כשר חטאת kasher chatas
before זריקה, zrika okay, or at the moment of זריקה zrika. as
you're splatting it, some splatters on you. But before זריקה. zrika So
therefore it says look, that proves that the phrase of קיבלו פסולים
וזרקו את דמה kiblu pesulim ve-zarku es damah is a סתם stam
phrase and doesn't really mean it, because once you're talking about a
scenario of זרקו את דמה, zarku es damah, it's irrelevant whether it's
פסול pasul or כשר. kasher So what we did is we took
a סתם stam phrase, you know, קיבלו פסולים וזרקו את דמה, kiblu
pesulim ve-zarku es damah, and we plunked it in here. But we
weren't being precise. We really should have just said קיבלו פסולים, kiblu
pesulim, because once you're introducing זרקו, zarku, the whole issue of פסול
pasul, becomes irrelevant. So it's just a סתם stam phrase. If it's
a סתם stam phrase, don't get caught up over it in use
in our משנה and try to prove that it's קבלה kabbala, that's
significant and not זריקה. zrika Okay, it's a nice point, right? Don't
get caught up. you know, that don't get caught up over stock
phrases. Don't be so overly מדייק medayek like you always are, here
actually it's a little bit of a stock phrase. Okay.
I heard a little bit of, maybe the idea that the soul
came out when
it תמה tamah
and then the blood no longer has that potency.
Right, I agree, I do think it's the idea that once it
was מכפר. mechaper. I'm not sure if I would say the soul,
but I would sort of say the fact that it's fit for
being נזרק is what gives it this status. But yeah, but that's
true.
It says it says after it hits,
then any blood, even the blood on המזבח, haMizbe'ach, any left blood
does not... even blood that would have been fit for going on
המזבח, haMizbe'ach, once blood was put on המזבח, haMizbe'ach, it
says as the soul was taken out.
You you can frame it that way. Okay. Anyway. All right. Now
the גמרא Gemara says אלא לאו דווקא. ela lav davka. You see
that this phrase of they caught and threw the blood is not
precise, it's a stock phrase, because in this case of a חטאת
Chatat we're not talking about throwing the blood at all. That would
have changed the entire discussion. If we're talking about פסול pasul and
that that's the issue, then it's without throwing the blood. So it's
a stock phrase. הכי נמי לאו דווקא, hachi nami lav davka, here
too it's a stock phrase. Don't try to be מדייק, medayek, you
see it's about קבלה, kabbala it's not about זריקה. zrika, The whole
thing's a stock phrase. All right. אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi,
Rav Assi doesn't like that answer. אם כן למה לי למיתני תרתי?
Im ken lama li lemitni tarti? If that was true, why would
I use the same stock phrase in two places? Meaning, to say
a stock phrase means one place it made sense and then once
we used it one place in a meaningful way, then we sort
of just grabbed the phrase and, you know, used it other places
a little imprecisely. So he's saying, okay, if it's a stock phrase
over there by the חטאת Chatat and the blood, then in our
משנה it has to be precise. Because if it's a stock phrase
in both places, then when did I ever start using it? Okay,
which is a pretty good point. למה לי למיתני תרתי? Lama li
lemitni tarti? אלא לעולם במיעילה דווקא. Ela le'olam b'me'ila davka. It must
be in our משנה, it is precise, and once it's taught precisely
here, then we borrowed it and used it as a stock phrase
over by חטאת. Chatat. והא קא משמע לן איצטריכא ליה, V'ha ka
mashma lan itztaricha lei, but I still have an answer to you.
Okay, not... sorry, not a sub... so and I'm even going to
go further is what's sort of implied. Not only that, I'll even
say that over by the חטאת Chatat case, it's not a stock
phrase, that there's a reason we want to talk about זריקה. zrika.
Why do you want to talk about זריקה? zrika Once it's זריקה,
zrika the whole thing is a moot point anyway. Here's why we
want to be talking about זריקה zrika by the
חטאת. Chatat. והא קא משמע לן איצטריכא ליה V'ha ka mashma lan
itztaricha lei דפסול עושה שיריים, depasul oseh shirayim, that even if it's
done בפסול, it makes שיריים. shirayim. What does that mean? Well, the
גמרא Gemara will explain and then I'll explain. אף על גב דקיבל
פסול וזרק, Af al gav dekibal pasul vezarak,
even though a פסול pasul person catches the blood and does זריקה,
zrika and let's say with other blood, וקיבל כשר וזרק, vekibal kasher
vezarak, לאו כלום היא. lav klum hi. It's not... so
meaning, here's what happened. Catch the blood? Right, the blood is squirting
out of the animal, two people are here, one person is פסול,
pasul I don't know, he's a בעל מום ba'al mum or he's
טמא. The other person is a כשר כהן. kasher kohen. Okay, we're
both catching the blood. I go ahead and I'm the פסול, psul
I first beat the other guy with the good blood... with the
blood, I beat him to המזבח, haMizbe'ach, I do the זריקה. zrika,
Now he goes ahead and he does the זריקה. zrika So the
question is my זריקה, zrika. which is a זריקה zrika of a
פסול, is this considered a זריקה zrika or not? Right, it's sort
of like the question before, right? זריקה zrika of a פיגול is
it a זריקה? zrika Is the זריקה of a פסול a פיגול?
What's the נפקא מינה? nafka mina? זריקה. If it's not a זריקה,
then two things. First of all, you could even say that maybe
the כשר kasher guy can make it into a כשר קרבן. kasher
korban. Maybe this whole thing was nothing. Number two, for the הלכה
halacha of the splattering of the blood and laundering the clothes, we
said after זריקה took place, the law becomes irrelevant. Let's say it
was the זריקה of a פסול, and then from the blood that
the כשר kasher guy caught, that splattered on clothing. Is that considered
that it's already נזרק and that this now blood is irrelevant, or
no, that was meaningless what happened over there, it's still good blood
here, it's still not נזרק, and if it splatters on a garment
you would still have to launder it? And that's what it's telling
you, that even though it was a פסול guy that did the
זריקה,
that's enough of a זריקה to make the other blood considered שיריים,
shirayim, remainder blood, no longer usable blood. שיריים shirayim blood and you
pour it at the base of המזבח, haMizbe'ach, but it's no longer
usable blood. Which means number one, the guy who caught it, the
כשר כהן kasher kohen who caught it can't now throw the blood
and make it into a כשר קרבן. kasher korban. And not only
that, if it splatters on a garment, this blood, the garment would
not have to be כיבוס kibus even because my זריקה, even a
זריקה of פסול makes all the rest of the blood considered no
longer relevant.
Well, won't it be poured on המזבח? haMizbe'ach? Why doesn't it be
taken out and like
burnt or whatever it is? פסול blood? Yeah. No, that's the blood
that the כשר guy caught. That's שיריים. shirayim. So what do you
do with שירי הדם הנשפך על היסוד? shirei hadam hanishpach al hayesod?
But isn't שירי הדם shirei hadam of a כשר זריקה?
Meaning your... yeah, you're right. Okay, anyway. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay,
so let's read that again. והא V'ha והא קא משמע לן *Vehaka
mashma lan*, this is teaching me דפסול עושה שיריים *De pasul oseh
shirayim*, that even when a זריקה *Zrika* of a פסול *Pasul* guy
makes the other blood that the kosher guy caught into remnant and
it's not considered still usable blood. אע"ג דקיבל פסול וזרק *Af al
gav de kibal pasul vezarak*, even though the פסול *Pasul* guy caught
the blood and did זריקה *Zrika*, דקיבל כשר וזרק *De kibal kasher
vezarak*, and the kosher guy caught it and did the זריקה *Zrika*.
לאו כלום *Lav klum*, what the kosher guy did and his blood
is meaningless. It's not a good קרבן *Korban*. If it splattered on
a garment, it wouldn't טעון כיבוס *Teun kibus*. מאי טעמא *Mai taama*?
דשיריים נינהו *Deshirayim ninhu*. Once the פסול *Pasul* guy did it, even
though he was פסול *Pasul*, clearly true if he's kosher, but even
if he's פסול *Pasul*, the other blood is now considered שיריים *Shirayim*.
And now how does that read in the משנה *Mishna* by חטאת
*Chatas*? Because our point was why did it say קיבלו פסולים וזרקו
את דמה *Kiblu psulim vezarku et dama*? We wouldn't be talking about
זריקה *Zrika*. זריקה *Zrika* makes the whole thing irrelevant, right? That was
our question before. So זריקה *Zrika* is לאו דווקא *Lav davka*, because
once it's זריקה *Zrika*, the whole conversation is irrelevant. No! We actually
wanted to talk about that case. קיבלו פסולים וזרקו את דמה *Kiblu
psulim vezarku et dama*, and then the other blood that was caught
by a כשר *Kasher* splattered. Even that case, it would still also
not require כיבוס *Kibus*. Okay, so not the blood that you caught
and threw by the פסול *Pasul*, that obviously is irrelevant as being
נזרק *Nizrak* or done. But the point is even other blood at
that moment that was caught by a כשר *Kasher* also no longer
is טעון כיבוס *Teun kibus*. Okay, so he says don't tell me
it's a stock phrase. Two points. First of all, even if it's
a stock phrase, one place it has to really mean it. Okay,
so that's מילא *Meila*. Number two is that I actually think it
means it in both places. And even in the case of חטאת
*Chatas*, it wants to give me the scenario of זרקו פסולים *Zarku
psulim* to tell me that even if there's other blood and even
it was זרקו פסולים *Zarku psulim*, the other blood now has lost
its potency.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is reading קיבלו
וזרקו את דמה *Kiblu vezarku et dama* means that כשרים זורקים דם
פסולים היו מקבלים *Ksherim zorkim dam psulim hayu mekabelim* and to say
that the only important point is the moment of קבלה kabbala. *Kabala*.
Again, I think that's a very weak proof because you could very
easily read it קיבלו פסולים או זרקו פסולים אסתמא *Kiblu psulim o
zarku psulim astama*. But the גמרא *Gemara* is reading it as one
case and saying it's honing in on קבלה kabbala. *Kabala*, that's the
key moment. Okay, now that we've introduced this idea about whether פסול
עושה שיריים *Psul oseh shirayim*, we are now going to digress on
that point for a little bit. So let's take a look. ואיבעיא
ליה לריש לקיש מרבי יוחנן *Vebaia lei leReish Lakish meRabbi Yochanan*, but
this issue that you say is now פשט pshat *Pshat* in that
משנה *Mishna* over there by the blood of a חטאת *Chatas*, that's
a question that ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* asked רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* asked רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*: פסול מהו שיעשה
שיריים *Pasul mahu sheyaaseh shirayim*? If a פסול *Pasul* goes ahead and
does the עבודה *Avoda* and there's other blood, again, other blood not
on the floor because then there was no קבלה kabbala *Kabala*, other
blood that was caught by a כשר *Kasher* person, is it considered
שיריים *Shirayim* or not? He asked him this question. And what did
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* say? ואמר ליה *Veamar lei*, he said back
to him: אין לך דבר שיעשה שיריים *Ein lach davar sheyaaseh shirayim*
אלא חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו *Ela chutz lizmano vechutz limkomo* הואיל ומרצין
לפיגולן *Hoil umeratzin lepigulan*. So here we circle back. The only thing
that would make the other blood שיריים *Shirayim* is if it was
a פסול *Pasul* of פיגול *Pigul* or חוץ למקומו *Chutz limkomo* which
is like פיגול *Pigul*. Why? Because remember the irony of פיגול *Pigul*
is that פיגול *Pigul* only works if it was done correctly at
the end and if it was as if it was מרצה *Meratzeh*.
So since, and that's why we actually thought that זריקת פיגול *Zrikat
pigul* counted as זריקה *Zrika*, right? That was yesterday's דף daf *Daf*
and the beginning of today. So here רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is
using that idea. He says when will, if it's done בפיסול *Bepisul*,
sort of have an impact on the rest of the blood, like
זריקה *Zrika* took place and the rest of the blood is now
remnant? If it's a פסול *Pasul* of פיגול *Pigul*. Because by פיגול
*Pigul* we say that it's as if it was a good זריקה
*Zrika*. So for that, therefore, a זריקת פיגול *Zrikat pigul* to some
extent is a good זריקה *Zrika* and therefore the remnant of the
blood is, the rest of the blood is שיריים *Shirayim*. But any
other פסול *Pasul* is meaningless. It's completely like nothing was done and
therefore if you have leftover blood you can still use the other
blood; it's not שיריים *Shirayim*. Okay, so this is very much picking
up on the theme we did at the beginning of today and
the end of yesterday, which is זריקת פיגול *Zrikat pigul* might in
some ways be considered a זריקה *Zrika*. So even though we said
that's not true for מעילה *Meila*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying
it is true to affect the status of the rest of the
blood. But only that! Only זריקת פיגול *Zrikat pigul*! Anything else would
not affect the status of the rest of the blood and you
could use it. And that goes against what you just said. So
he says let's read that again: אין לך דבר *Ein lach davar*,
you have nothing, שיעשה שיריים *Sheyaaseh shirayim*,
which will be considered a meaningful זריקה *Zrika* to make the other
blood שיריים *Shirayim* אלא חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו *Ela chutz lizmano vechutz
limkomo*, only the פיגול *Pigul* type thoughts, הואיל ומרצין לפיגולן *Hoil umeratzin
lepigulan*, since they make it as if the קרבן *Korban* was accepted
for the purpose of פיגול *Pigul*. So it's as if it was
a good עבודה *Avoda*. For that, therefore, a זריקת פיגול *Zrikat pigul*
to some extent is a good זריקה *Zrika* and therefore the remnant
of the blood is, the rest of the blood is שיריים *Shirayim*.
But anything else is irrelevant and therefore the blood would not be
שיריים *Shirayim*. Okay, so that goes exactly against how you wanted to
read the משנה *Mishna* בחטאת *Bechatas*. You wanted to say that an
עבודה *Avoda* done בפיסול *Bepisul*, a זריקה *Zrika*... בר מפסול *bar mi-psul*,
אין פסול *ein psul* makes the blood into שיריים *shirayim*? So let's
see what the answer is. והא מאי לאו בר מפסול *Vehah mai
lav bar mi-psul* doesn't it mean that therefore if it was done
by a כהן *Kohen* who was פסול *pasul*, the rest of the
blood is not שיריים *shirayim*? או אפילו פסול *O afilu pasul*. Nay,
not only פיגול *pigul*, even if the כהן *Kohen* was פסול *pasul*,
the rest of the blood is שיריים *shirayim*. והא אין לך קתני
*V'ha ein lecha katani*. He said there is nothing that has that
impact except פיגול *pigul*, so how could you say that if a
פסול *pasul* כהן *Kohen* the זריקה *zrika* has this impact? הכי קאמר
*Hachi ka'amar*. He doesn't mean nothing, but he means in a certain
category. הכי קאמר *Hachi ka'amar*, אין לך דבר שאינו מרצה בציבור ועושה
שיריים אלא חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו *ein lecha davar she-eino mirtzeh b'tzibur
v'oseh shirayim ela chutz lizmano v'chutz limkomo*. There are most עבודות *avodos*,
they are never, most פסולים *psulim* are never overwritten. There's one פסול
*psul* that's overwritten. What's the פסול *psul* that could be overwritten בציבור
*b'tzibur*?
טומאה *tuma*.
So he says like this: so when we are saying nothing except
פיגול *pigul*, we don't mean nothing. We mean nothing of your standard
פסולים *psulim*. But when you're dealing with a פסול *psul* of טומאה
*tuma*, because sometimes טומאה *tuma* can be okay, טומאה דחויה או הותרה
בציבור *tuma dchuya o hutra b'tzibur*, so an עבודה *avodah* done בטומאה
*b'tuma* is still can be considered a quasi-עבודה *avodah*, can still have
some impact of being an עבודה *avodah*. So we said nothing other
than פיגול *pigul*, we mean nothing of the things that never are
overwritten בציבור *b'tzibur*. אין לך דבר שאינו מרצה בציבור ועושה שיריים אלא
חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו *Ein lecha davar she-eino mirtzeh b'tzibur v'oseh shirayim
ela chutz lizmano v'chutz limkomo*. You have no פסול *psul* that is
not of those that are never overwritten בציבור *b'tzibur* that will have
this impact except חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו *chutz lizmano v'chutz limkomo*. אבל
טמא *Aval tamei*, but if it's a פסול *psul* of טומאה *tuma*,
דאיתא בציבור *de-isa b'tzibur*, since there are times that that פסול *psul*
is overwritten like if the ציבור *tzibur* is טמא *tamei*, and therefore
there are times where קבלת טמא *kabalas tamei* is כשר *kasher* or
זריקת טמא *zrikas tamei* is כשר *kasher*, so the עבודה *avodah*, that
type of an עבודה *avodah* is not a meaningless עבודה *avodah*. So
therefore משוי שיריים *mishavei shirayim*. That can make the remnants of the
blood שיריים *shirayim*. שאר פסולים *She'ar psulim* דלא אתי בציבור *delo asi
b'tzibur*, other פסולים *psulim* that are not, don't exist בציבור *b'tzibur*, are
not allowed בציבור *b'tzibur*, לא משוי שיריים *lo mishavei shirayim*, would not
make it שיריים *shirayim*. So when the משנה *mishna* said in חטאת
*Chatas*, if a פסול *pasul* person caught and threw the blood, the
blood doesn't have the potency and we said it means the blood
the זכאי *zakai* caught, right, the second כהן *Kohen* caught, that that
made it into שיריים *shirayim*, when we said a פסול *pasul* guy
we didn't mean any פסול *pasul* guy. If he was פסול *pasul*
because he was a בעל מום *ba'al mum* or if he was
an אונן *onen* or whatever it was, then it would be meaningless,
his עבודה *avodah*, and the rest of the blood could be used
and it would have an effect for חטאת *Chatas*, for splatter on
a garment and all of that. When we said that the, this
act of זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam* was meaningful and made the rest
of the blood שיריים *shirayim*, even though it was, we meant a
very, only one type of פסול *psul*, a very specific פסול *psul*,
the guy was טמא *tamei*. Since when the guy was טמא *tamei*,
that would have been overwritten בציבור *b'tzibur*, therefore his זריקה *zrika*, his
קבלה kabbala *kabala*, his עבודה *avodah* were significant enough that it designated
the rest of the blood as שיריים *shirayim*. Why not say טמא
*tamei*? Why say פסול *pasul*? All right, the whole thing is a
דיוק diyuk *diyuk*. If all thing why does it talk about two
people caught the blood? All right, if פשט *pshat* is that it
is a stock phrase, but it's an ingenious reading of that משנה
*mishna*. But I want to just point out, draw out, sort of
the, there's
the importance of the parallels we're dealing with here. Like I said,
yesterday's דף *daf* and today's beginning of the דף *daf*, the question
was: okay, you need זריקה *zrika* to change the status. What if
it's like a quasi-זריקה *zrika*, if it's a זריקת פסול *zrikas pasul*
it's no good. But what if it's a פסול *psul* that it's
still, still considered somewhat of a זריקה *zrika*? What? A פיגול *pigul*.
Because there we still say it's as if it were מרצה *mirtzeh*.
So if it's not real, if it's not a real פסול *psul*,
okay, I mean it is a real פסול *psul*, but you know
what I'm saying, it's still in some ways could still be called
a זריקה *zrika*. So here we've revisited that. We've said some עבודות
*avodos* when they're פסול *pasul* they're completely irrelevant and some are maybe
as if they did take place. One example was פיגול *pigul*, that's
what we were talking about yesterday. Yesterday we said maybe it should
work for מעילה *me'ila*, we rejected that. But the focus was that
פיגול *pigul* because it's מרצה לפיגולו *mirtzeh l'pigulo* should be as if
it took place. And here we said רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said
actually that is true for the law of making the other blood
considered שיריים *shirayim*, although obviously the קרבן *korban* isn't כשר *kasher*, but
because the זריקה *zrika* is as if it took place the rest
of the blood is שיריים *shirayim* and can't be
used. And now we've added to that case of פיגול *pigul* as
if the עבודה *avodah* were good even though it wasn't good, the
case of טמא *tamei*. Because if the person is טמא *tamei*, that's
a type of a פסול *psul* that's overwritten בציבור *b'tzibur*. So even
though it's פסול *pasul*, there's some way in which we say it's
as if the עבודה *avodah* still took place regarding again this issue
of שיריים *shirayim*, not for מעילה *me'ila*, then there we needed to
really work. So now we have two things where the עבודה *avodah*
was not כשר *kasher* but there's still some power to it. פיגול
*pigul* because of the concept of מרצה לפיגולו *mirtzeh l'pigulo* and טומאה
*tuma* because of the concept of הותרה או דחויה בציבור *hutra o
dchuya b'tzibur*. Okay, so even though that was a little bit of
a digression, it really helped crystallize the... ideas that we're dealing with.
So now let's just read what we're going to keep on trying
to prove this question, we're going back now to the main point
about whether the important moment is קבלה or זריקה. Okay, so let's
take a look. תא שמע: tashma: הפיגול לעולם מועלין בו. happigul le'olam
mo'alin bo. פיגול, this is the ברייתא we quoted at the beginning
of today's דף, okay, a דף ago. הפיגול לעולם מועלין בו. happigul
le'olam mo'alin bo. So what does that mean? Meaning even if you
do the זריקה with פיגול, דלאו דלא זרק delav delo zarak ושמע
מינה הזריקה שנינו. ushma mina hazrika shaninu. So it's not exactly clear
what the דיוק diyuk is, but it's saying לעולם מועלין בו le'olam
mo'alin bo means that somehow even if you did פיגול at an
early stage, you did it at קבלה, you're stuck and therefore you'll
not change the status. But again, it's not at all clear to
me somehow it assumes that but we're not talking that they only
did the פיגול at זריקה. And isn't it clear from this that
the key stage is the קבלה? I have no idea what the
דיוק diyuk is and the answer is לאו זרקה. lav zarka. No,
you did do the זריקה. Now let me just read רש"י Rashi
to the מקום makom because if he explains this a little bit,
one
second.
Yeah,
I really don't know what the דיוק diyuk is. I mean I
don't know why the גמרא assumes that we're talking about that the
פיגול problem happened earlier at the שחיטה or at the קבלה and
tries to bring a proof from it and then it just says
the answer is no, actually we're talking about that the פיגול problem
happened later at the זריקה and therefore it's a problem. So I
don't exactly understand what the דיוק is. I mean I just reread
רש"י, Rashi, it's not any clearer to me but somehow we think
maybe it's the emphasis of the phrase לעולם. le'olam. But לעולם le'olam
means but again I don't understand, I really don't get it.
Okay, anyway why can't it be just from the phrase what's the
implication?
Meaning if you want to say זריקה שנינו it actually says that
if a פסול occurs later it's not a problem. So if you
want to say הפיגול לעולם מועלין בו, happigul le'olam mo'alin bo, right,
and you want to emphasize that it always sort of לעולם, le'olam,
excuse me, it always sort of creates a problem then that would
have more emphasized that even if there was פיגול later, even פיגול
at the time of זריקה there's still going to be an issue.
So again it's not clear to me how the גמרא infers from
the phrase לעולם מועלין בו, le'olam mo'alin bo, oh you see that
only if there's פיגול earlier is it a problem but if פיגול
was later like at the time of זריקה it's not a problem.
Anyway the answer is לאו זרקה, lav zarka, you did do זריקה.
זריקה was with פיגול and nevertheless because it was before because you
never had a good זריקה even if the problem wasn't at the
קבלה, the problem was later at the זריקה, even so it still
retains its status. ומאי לעולם? umai le'olam? So what's the meaning of
לעולם? le'olam? Now רש"י Rashi says here this question ומאי לעולם umai
le'olam is not based on whether we said קבלה or זריקה. You
could have asked that question regardless. What's the emphasis of the word
לעולם? le'olam? So the גמרא says הא קמשמע לן כרב גידל ha
kamashmalan k'Rav Giddal like Rav Giddal דאמר רב גידל אמר רב d'amar
Rav Giddal amar Rav זריקת פיגול אינה מוציאה מידי מעילה ואינה מביאה
לידי מעילה. zrikat piggul eina motzia midei me'ila v'eina mevia lidei me'ila.
The reason of לעולם le'olam is to underscore but of course that
then re-emphasizes the fact that we're talking about זריקה not קבלה. לעולם
le'olam emphasizes that even if the זריקה was only the only פיגול
was the זריקה's פיגול and as we just got through saying זריקה's
פיגול maybe counts as a quasi זריקה, no! פיגול will always be
a problem even if it's זריקה's פיגול. We're not going to say
it's as if it were a good זריקה. זריקה is always פיגול
is always going to be an issue and will not change the
status. Of course once you say that and the emphasis is זריקה's
פיגול if anything that should be underscoring the idea that the key
moment is זריקה not קבלה. So again how the גמרא thought that
that ברייתא was a proof to the idea of קבלה is not
clear to me. It's sort of like when the גמרא thought that
the idea when the משנה said if it became טמא obviously we're
talking about the blood. No it's only obviously we're talking about the
blood if you assume we're talking about the blood; it could be
talking about the meat. So anyway we're still in the middle of
this question of what is the key moment that changes the status.
I would say פשט of the משנה is זריקה when the meat
actually becomes מותר but the גמרא is seriously considering the possibility that
it's the moment before that, the moment of קבלה and we will
continue with this tomorrow.