Okay,
so we pick up 22nd day of the Omer, we pick up
on טז עמוד ב, Tes Zayin Amud Bet, top of the
דף, daf, middle of פרק של קדשי מזבח. Perek of Kodshei Mizbe'ach.
I just want to repeat because the rest of this פרק perek
is dealing with not really מעילה Me'ila issues, but issues of general
combining, so I just want to repeat just briefly the principle מעילה
Me'ila issue that we taught at the beginning of the פרק. perek.
The beginning of the פרק perek taught that you can combine מעילה
Me'ila even from different קרבנות korbanot or even from half of a
פרוטה prutah of a קרבן korban and half of a פרוטה prutah
from something that belongs to the Temple treasury.
So that is קדשי מזבח וקדשי בדק הבית מצטרפין זה עם זה
למעילה, Kodshei Mizbe'ach ve-Kodshei Bedek ha-Bayit mitztarfin zeh im zeh le-me'ila, and
that was very important because, first of all, the whole use of
the פרוטה, prutah, as I mentioned, points us away from a think
of מעילה Me'ila as אכילה. achila. It still could be either a
sense of either הנאה, hana'ah, deriving benefit, or stealing,
but we would be more inclined, I would certainly be more inclined
to think that the stealing would be relevant primarily to בדק הבית
Bedek ha-Bayit and the inappropriate benefit, the הנאה, hana'ah, would be appropriate
to קדשי מזבח Kodshei Mizbe'ach קרבנות, korbanot, and maybe you can't combine
them. Maybe they're fundamentally different types of מעילה. Me'ila. The משנה Mishna
tells us that no, actually, it is one concept of מעילה, Me'ila,
at least across those two different categories of קרבנות korbanot and בדק
הבית, Bedek ha-Bayit, and you can combine them. It doesn't tell us
what that primary category is, but it does tell us that it's
not limited or it's not specific to the type of קדושה. kedusha.
And then we also had the position that was stated that said
the real פשט p'shat of מעילה—whose Me'ila position was that? Rav Yannai—was
בדק הבית, Bedek ha-Bayit, which certainly seems to emphasize at least that
the paradigm, if it's בדק הבית, Bedek ha-Bayit, points more to this
idea of גזילה. gezeila. But again, the key principle is that it
is not linked—the type of מעילה Me'ila is not distinct for the
type of קדושה kedusha because you can combine קרבנות korbanot and בדק
הבית, Bedek ha-Bayit, and we still have this general tension or question
what the primary concept of מעילה Me'ila is. Okay, and now with
that, we continue to discussing things that combine, and we had said
in the משנה Mishna that all נבילות nevelos combine and all שרצים
sheratzim combine. For all נבילות nevelos combine, we had two possibilities. Either
that means for טומאה, tumah, half of a כזית kezayit from one
and half a כזית kezayit of another; that it clearly means, but
maybe it even means for the איסור אכילה. issur achila. And that
led to the question of is a נבילה, nevela, a dead non-kosher
animal, just, let's say a dead pig, is it just חזיר chazir
or is it also נבילה? nevela? Is there a concept, would איסור
חל על איסור issur chal al issur play a role here? And
if it's also נבילה, nevela, then a half of a כזית kezayit
of pig and a half of a כזית kezayit of a dead
cow would be מצטרף mitztaref for the איסור issur of נבילה. nevela.
So there was a question whether the משנה Mishna meant that or
not; minimally, it meant that it combines for the issue of טומאה.
tumah. And now we go on to the second part of the
משנה, Mishna, which is that a שרץ, sheretz, the טומאה tumah of
שרצים, sheratzim, a half a שיעור shiur and a half a שיעור
shiur of different שרצים sheratzim combine. So let's take a look again:
what does this mean? Combine for אכילה, achila, combine for טומאה? tumah?
Let's take a look. So top of
טז עמוד ב, Tes Zayin Amud Bet, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב:
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: אכילת שרצים לוקה עליו בכזית. Achilat sheratzim
lokeh alav be-kezayit. If you eat שרצים, sheratzim, then you get lashes
by eating כזית. kezayit. Okay, that doesn't seem like a big חידוש.
chiddush. Normal things that are forbidden in eating, the amount is a
כזית. kezayit.
Even if you eat a whole בריה beriya that's less than the
כזית? kezayit?
Right, there's a position about Rebbi Eliezer that by that you're לוקה
lokeh with a בריה. beriya. Okay, but right, we are not dealing
with that, correct.
The משנה Mishna says שקצים? shkatzim?
Right, and here it says שרצים. sheratzim. What's the matter? Yeah, it
seems to treat them interchangeably. You're right. I mean, obviously they mean
different things. שרץ sheretz is crawl and שקץ sheketz is more like
an abominable thing. When the תורה Torah speaks about the שרצים sheratzim
that causes טומאה: tumah: וזה לכם הטמא בשרץ השורץ על הארץ, Ve-zeh
lachem ha-tamei ba-sheretz ha-shoreitz al ha-aretz, followed by החולד והעכבר והצב למינהו,
ha-choled ve-ha-achbar ve-ha-tzav le-minehu, והכח והלטאה והחומט והתנשמת, ve-ha-ko'ach ve-ha-leta'ah ve-ha-chomet ve-ha-tinshemet,
אלה הטמאים לכם בכל השרץ. eileh ha-tmei'im lachem be-chol ha-sheretz. But at
the end it says שקץ יהיו לכם, sheketz yiheyu lachem, right.
There's nothing called שקצים shkatzim in the
תורה Torah as...
but the משנה Mishna does...
Right, the משנה Mishna
calls them שקצים, shkatzim, yeah. It's a good point. I think for
now we're assuming it's the same as שרצים. sheratzim. Okay, so anyway,
so רב Rav says here that it is a כזית. kezayit. Michael
correctly asked, isn't there sometimes a principle about
בריה? beriya? But actually I might have answered you too quickly because
there's a discussion about בריה, beriya,
there's a discussion about בריה, beriya, the מחלוקת machlokes about whether by
בריה beriya you're לוקה lokeh is when it doesn't have נשמה? neshama?
No, no, no, no, no. I have to double check about the
מחלוקת machlokes about the issue about בריה beriya by מלקות malkos whether
it's דכולי עלמא de-kulei alma or just a דעת יחיד. da'at yachid.
If if it is—I should double check, I will double check that—if
it is, then you could at least say anyway we're talking about
combining non-full שרצים. sheratzim. Okay, so bracketing the בריה beriya issue, Michael
does raise the good point that if you eat a
whole... But assuming either that's not the הלכה halacha or assuming that
you're not dealing with a whole one, it's a כזית. kezayis. Now,
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? That should seem pretty straightforward.
אכילה Achila כתיב, ksiv, it says אכילה, achila, don't eat. Okay, so
והתני רב יוסף ברבי חנינא קמיה דרבי יוחנן, v'hatany Rav Yosef b'Rebbi
Chanina kamei d'Rebbi Yochanan, but one minute, didn't רב יוסף ברבי חנינא
Rav Yosef b'Rebbi Chanina teach in front of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
the following ברייתא? braisa? והבדלתם בין הבהמה הטהורה, V'hivdaltem bein habehema hatehora,
right? We just read this a week ago. The end of שמיני.
Shemini. You should distinguish between the טהור tahor and the לטמאה, latmeia,
the טהור tahor and the טמא tamei animal. There the word טהור
tahor and טמא tamei primarily mean kosher, non-kosher. ובין העוף הטמא לטהור,
Uvein ha'of hatamei latahor,
and the kosher non-kosher bird, right? Because the תורה Torah never speaks
about birds that are טמא tamei in the sense of טומאה, tumah,
it speaks about them being kosher and not kosher. Okay, and ולא
תשקצו
את
נפשותיכם בבהמה ובעוף, velo tishaktzu es nafshoseichem babehema uva'of, do not abominate
your souls with the animals and the birds, ובכל אשר תרמש האדמה,
uv'chol asher tirmos ha'adama, everything that crawls on the ground, אשר הבדלתי
לכם לטמא, asher hivdalti lachem letamei, that I separated out for you
to be
טמא. tamei. So פתח הכתוב באכילה. pasach haksiv b'achila. It starts with
that type of טומאה tumah that means don't eat. Now, how do
you know it starts with that? So again I would say because
it speaks about עוף טמא וטהור, of tamei v'tahor, בהמה טמאה וטהורה,
behema tmeia uthora,
that the distinctions in there פרשת שמיני Parshas Shemini between בהמה behema
and עוף of are about kosher and not kosher, not about טומאה
וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, the literal what we would call טומאה וטהרה. tumah
v'taharah. רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos say that it's because of ולא
תשקצו את נפשותיכם, velo tishaktzu es nafshoseichem, that נפשותיכם, nafshoseichem,
meaning like make your soul abominable, which is a sense about like
what you ingest and eat and it's about sin and it's not
about טומאה. tumah. Okay, so the first part of the פסוק pasuk
is talking about טומאה tumah in the sense of eating, non-kosher, וסיים
בטומאה, v'siyem b'tumah, and it ends by טומאה tumah by literal טומאה.
tumah. How do you know? Because it says, because somehow we're saying
אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא, asher hivdalti lachem letamei, that extra פסוק pasuk
separated out for לטמא. letamei. תוספות Tosafos also says לטמא letamei means
that transmits טומאה, tumah, or that if eating it you are מטמא
metamei other people or other things. So therefore that's referring to the
more what we call metaphysical טומאה. tumah. Okay, so it starts with
טומאה tumah and it is true, the תורה Torah in the end
of שמיני Shemini uses טומאה tumah interchangeably whether talking about kosher non-kosher
or whether it's talking about what we would call טומאה וטהרה. tumah
v'taharah. So it says this פסוק pasuk combines it all. What's the
purpose of combining it all? To tell you the following: מה טומאה
בכעדשה אף אכילה בכעדשה, ma tumah b'chadasha af achila b'chadasha,
to tell you that the amount that creates טומאה tumah is the
amount that is forbidden to eat. Now by animals and by
mammals and
birds, mammals and birds it's a כזית. kezayis. So it's irrelevant, right?
The כזית kezayis is the amount you can't eat, the כזית kezayis
is the amount that causes טומאה, tumah, it's not a חידוש. chiddush.
But it is a חידוש chiddush by שרצים, shratzim, because we say
by a שרץ shretz the amount is a כעדשה k'adasha like the
size of a bean, so that's very small, that causes טומאה. tumah.
And he's saying because that amount causes טומאה, tumah, here there's an
exception to the rule that you need a כזית kezayis for אכילה,
achila, and here the rule would be that even if you eat
a כעדשה, k'adasha, it's true, you get lashes for eating.
Okay, so how
do we know from
the, the amount for the טומאה, tumah, why was it כזית kezayis
and one was כעדשה? k'adasha?
Well, we know the כעדשה k'adasha because it says
there's a specific דרשה, drasha, well besides just the general answer which
is it's all הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, I bet. But
if it's all הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai, then you don't
need a פסוק pasuk here that links the two because that's anyway
it's הלכה למשה
מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai.
כזית Kezayis is always assumed to be the amount that you can't
eat, right? So why is it כזית kezayis for טומאה tumah in
case of mammals and birds?
Yeah, so I was going to answer why it's כעדשה k'adasha by
the others because it says, תוספות Tosafos brings a דרשה drasha it
says מהם ובהם, mehem uvahem,
I don't know, that somehow, somehow it understands that some of these
rodents
begin with as the size of a lentil bean and somehow it
says בהם, bahem, them in their entirety, so the smallest size of
an entire one is a lentil bean and therefore that serves as
the paradigm.
Anyway, there's that דרשה. drasha. How do we know the other stuff
the טומאה tumah is by a כזית? kezayis?
I would have to check the דרשה drasha and I don't remember
what the דרשה drasha is.
Maybe if it's like eating it's reversed, I don't know, I'd have
to check. טומאת מת Tumas meis is a כזית, kezayis, yeah, a
lot of those things, yeah, I don't know if we quote פסוקים,
psukim, a lot of the things I think it's just a הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai assumption about the שיעורים. shiurim.
Yeah, so anyway, there is a specific דרשה drasha by that this
is a כעדשה k'adasha because of the assumption that at least the
smallest one of these when it begins its life starts with the
size of כעדשה, k'adasha, these rodents. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, so therefore we say that the same way מה טומאה בכעדשה
אף אכילה בכעדשה. ma tumah b'chadasha af achila b'chadasha. So now we
say that it's a
כעדשה, k'adasha, וקילסיה רבי יוחנן, v'kilsia Rebbi Yochanan, יוסף, Yosef, that's a
great ברייתא. braisa. And the גמרא Gemara here at least doesn't want
to assume there's a debate of רב Rav and רבי יוחנן. Rebbi
Yochanan. So how does רב Rav say? which is
it? So וקשיא לרב *Vekasha lerav*, that's a contradiction to רב Rav
*Rav* assuming that we're not going to be bothered or we're assuming
we don't want to answer it's a מחלוקת machlokes *machloket*. גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says לא קשיא *lo kashya*. כאן במיתתן כאן בחייהן *kan bemitatan
kan bechayeihen*. It depends if they're alive or dead. If they're dead,
then they cause טומאה tumah, *tumah*. These dead, like these are types
of things which are like a weasel, a type of a frog,
a salamander. Okay, these are the things, there're eight of them, the
תורה Torah *Torah* says they're...
Yeah, it's not exactly צפרדע *tzfardea*, some frog-like thing, some amphibious type
of thing. Okay, you mean the שרץ sheretz, *sheretz*. The שרצים shratzim
*sheratzim*. Okay, so these eight, these are eight שרצים shratzim *sheratzim* that
cause טומאה tumah, *tumah*
and even in the size of כעדשה k'adashah. *ke'adasha*, but they cause
טומאה tumah. *tumah* when they're dead, במותם *bemotam*. So, if they're dead
and they're causing טומאה tumah. *tumah* of the size of a כעדשה
k'adashah *ke'adasha*, therefore they combine, if you eat them, you transgress when
you eat the amount that causes טומאה tumah. *tumah*, a כעדשה k'adashah.
*ke'adasha*. If they're alive and right now they're not causing טומאה tumah
*tumah* and you eat them alive, so since they're not causing טומאה
tumah. *tumah*, it goes by the size of a כזית kezayis. *kezayit*,
so everybody could be happy. רב Rav *Rav* says a כזית kezayis,
*kezayit* means they're alive.
So everyone alive is a כזית kezayis, *kezayit*?
What?
Is there אבר מן החי ever min hachai *Ever Min HaChai* by
a שרץ sheretz. *sheretz*? Well, אבר מן החי ever min hachai, *Ever
Min HaChai* if you eat a whole אבר ever *ever*, if it's
בשר מן החי basar min hachai *Basar Min HaChai* it's a כזית
kezayis *kezayit*.
But the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* presumably רב Rav. *Rav* is talking about
from the איסור issur *issur* of שרצים shratzim *sheratzim*. I don't think
there's אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* by שרצים shratzim, *sheratzim*. I
think אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* is only by animals to
which there is a דין *din* of שחיטה *shechitah*.
Well,
can't you eat אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* from something like
a camel?
Is it a דין שחיטה *din shechitah*? Well, that's a מחלוקת *machloket*
if אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* applies by טמאים *tmeim*, but
at least it's the type of animals that there's שחיטה *shechitah*. There's
no אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* for birds, from fish. So
I don't think there's אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* here.
It's a good point, but I don't think so.
Is there נבילה neveilah *neveilah* by a שרץ sheretz, *sheretz*? So that
would be probably the question. See that's the question, that's a good
point, but by the, why would it
have נבילה neveilah *neveilah* טומאה tumah, *tumah*?
No, no, well first of all, there's the question before by well,
is there an איסור אכילה issur achilah. *issur achilah* by נבילה *neveilah*?
So there's a question before about איסור issur חל על איסור *issur
chal al issur*. But again, I think the answer is the same
as to Michael, which is that the concept of נבילה *neveilah* and
אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* is only by types of animals
to which like שחיטה *shechitah* is relevant. The תורה Torah *Torah* never
speaks here, here's the evidence, the תורה Torah *Torah* never speaks about
the only dead, these eight שרצים shratzim. *sheratzim*, if they're dead, they're
טמא tamei, *tamei*. Other rodents that are dead or you know amphibians
that are dead don't cause טומאה tumah. *tumah*. So there's clearly no
נבילה *neveilah* by them. And that's why also there's clearly no אבר
מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* by them. נבילה *neveilah* and אבר מן
החי *Ever Min HaChai* is only by like birds and you know
and mammals and so on.
Okay, but those were good, yeah, very good questions.
If אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* doesn't apply to non-kosher animals,
that would be a leniency for non-Jews against Jews.
No, because אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* doesn't apply to non-Jews
as well as אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai*, it only applies
as non-kosher animals. If somebody rips a limb off of a pig,
okay, so a non-Jew could be totally מותר *mutar*, and for a
Jew, it's, the question is there אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai*
by non-kosher animals, and for a Jew,
it's pig, but it's not אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai*.
So a non-Jew can eat a limb from a living animal as
long as it's a non-kosher animal?
Well, that's the מחלוקת *machloket* of אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai*
applies to non-kosher animals.
Yeah, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just referred to it the other day,
whether אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* is נוהג בטמא *noheig betamei*
or not.
Yeah, I mean there's definitely a link of אבר מן החי *Ever
Min HaChai* to the idea of שחיטה *shechitah*, which is part of
the whole question of אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai* by non-kosher.
Is that a leniency for non-Jews? Because if it doesn't apply, it
doesn't apply to Jews either, just the איסור *issur* of pig applies
to Jews. Okay, but those are definitely good questions. By שרצים shratzim,
*sheratzim* there is no concept of נבילה *neveilah*. And you know because
only the eight שרצים shratzim, *sheratzim* are טמא tamei, *tamei* dead. Other
rodents are not טמא tamei, *tamei*. There's no concept of שחיטה *shechitah*,
right? And therefore there's no concept of אבר מן החי *Ever Min
HaChai*. But the only thing is that there is this איסור *issur*
of שרצים shratzim, *sheratzim*.
But there would be a concept of בשר מן החי *Basar Min
HaChai*?
No, no. If there's not a concept of שחיטה *shechitah* so they
all go together.
Yeah, yeah, if there's not a concept of נבילה *neveilah*, there's not
a concept of שחיטה *shechitah*, there's not a concept of אבר מן
החי *Ever Min HaChai*, which is why there's not that concept by
let's say fish.
Okay. So even if you let's say take a rip a limb
off of a lobster or something, there's not an אבר מן החי
*Ever Min HaChai* idea there. So there's not אבר מן החי *Ever
Min HaChai*, there's not a נבילה *neveilah* idea here. There is an
idea of שרץ sheretz *sheretz*. So he says when they're alive, then
they're אסור assur *assur* as שרצים shratzim, *sheratzim*. But it was very
good to clarify that, not as אבר מן החי *Ever Min HaChai*.
And therefore שרצים shratzim. *sheratzim*, but there's no טומאה tumah, *tumah*. So
there it's a כזית kezayis. *kezayit*, like it normally is. If they're
dead, there's טומאה tumah. *tumah*, and there it's a כעדשה k'adashah *ke'adasha*.
אמר ליה amar lei, אביי *Amar lei Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* said back,
והא רב Rav אמתניתין קאי *Veha Rav amtnitin kai*. רב Rav *Rav*
is going on our משנה mishnah. *mishna*. ומתניתין כל השרצים קתני *Umatnitin
kol hasheratzim katani*, and our משנה mishnah *mishna* says all שרצים shratzim
*sheratzim* combine. אפילו במיתתן *Afilu bemitatan*, even in their death. One minute,
when רב Rav *Rav* said אכילת שרצים shratzim, *achilat sheratzim* is by
כזית kezayis, *kezayit*, he's going on our משנה mishnah? *mishna*, and our
משנה mishnah *mishna* says all שרצים shratzim. *sheratzim* combine, and he understood
that when רב Rav *Rav* was explaining our משנה mishnah *mishna*, what
does it mean all שרצים shratzim, *sheratzim* combine? It means they combine
for a כזית kzayis, *kezayit* for the איסור *issur*. When it comes
for טומאה, tumah they combine for כעדשה. k'adashah, But when it comes
for אכילה, achila, they combine for כזית. kzayis. He understood that רב
Rav. was going on the משנה. mishnah And our משנה mishnah. says
שרצים shratzim. always combine, presumably it's regardless alive or dead, they always
combine. So you see you're not distinguishing between alive or dead. Now
how does he know that רב Rav was going on the משנה?
mishnah, Either number one, he just assumed it. Or if you remember
yesterday, we also had a statement of רב. Rav Right, yesterday רב
Rav said, אמר רב לא שנו אלא לענין טומאה אבל לענין אכילת
טהורים. Amar Rav lo shanu ela l'inyan tumah aval l'inyan achilas tahorim.
רב Rav made another statement about are we talking about טומאה, tumah
are we talking about אכילה, achila, by the first half of the
משנה mishnah. about נבלה. neveilah. So we see רב Rav is commenting
on this משנה mishnah. about combining. He commented about the נבלה, neveilah,
whether it combines for טומאה, tumah combines for eating. Here he's saying
שרצים shratzim combine for a כזית, kzayis. so presumably he's explaining the
משנה mishnah that speaks about how do שרצים shratzim. combine. And it
says when it comes to eating, they combine for a כזית, kzayis.
and presumably it's even dead. So how can you say רב Rav
is only talking about when they're alive? Okay, so גמרא Gemara says,
אמלייה רב יוסף, Amlei Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said
back to him, ההיא דיוקא דלכו. Hahi diyuka dilachu. That's your way
of interpreting רב. Rav רב שמעתא בעלמא קאמר. Rav shmeisa b'alma qamar.
I don't buy it. I think רב Rav was just saying a
statement independent of the משנה. mishnah And since he was saying a
statement independent of the משנה, mishnah. I'll say he was only talking
about live שרצים, shratzim, not dead שרצים. shratzim Some have the גרסה,
girsa, if you look at the side, some have the גרסה girsa
not just that's your דיוק, diyuq, that's your interpretation, but ההיא דופקא
דידך. hahi dufka didach. That's your way of slapping things together, like
דבק, devek, like glue. That's the way you juxtapose it. You say
רב Rav is going on the משנה. mishnah. I don't, I say
רב is talking about independent. So we actually have, and this is
the conclusion of the גמרא, Gemara is that when it comes to
שרצים, shratzim if you're eating dead שרצים, shratzim you go by כעדשה
k'adashah because that's the amount that causes טומאה. tumah Yes?
Is this an example of רב being a תנא? tanna? Independent, commenting
on different sections? No.
Why? No, no, it just means he wasn't commenting on the משנה.
mishnah, The משנה mishnah just says they combine, right? Maybe the משנה's
mishnah, talking about טומאה. tumah It's just saying that רב's statement was
not a comment on the משנה. mishnah It's not contradicting the משנה.
But when we thought it was a comment on the משנה, that
context made us understand that he was talking about all שרצים, shratzim,
whether alive or dead, because the משנה's very categorical. Once we say
he's not commenting on the משנה, we're freer to say that רב's
statement was referring only to live שרצים, shratzim. not to dead שרצים.
shratzim Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is going to wrap this up.
מיתיבי. Meisvei. Last question on this statement. קלסיה רבי יוחנן. Kalsi Rabbi
Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan praised this, so now we're going to
go to this idea. Now that we've somewhat resolved רב and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying that there's a difference between alive or dead,
we're going to focus on this position itself, that at least dead
ones combine for
כעדשה. k'adashah. מיתיבי, Meisvei, אברים אין להם שיעור. evarim ein lahem shiur.
There's no minimum size for a limb.
אפילו פחות מכזית נבלה פחות מכעדשה מן השרץ מטמא. Afilu pachus m'kezayis
neveilah, pachus m'k'adashah min hasheretz metamei. So even if you have less
than a כזית kzayis. of a נבלה, neveilah, or less than a
כעדשה k'adasha of a שרץ, sheretz it causes טומאה. tumah, So a
full limb of an animal causes טומאה tumah, even if it's less
than the minimum שיעור. shiur. Okay, that's טומאה. tumah What do I
care about that?
So now it goes on,
so we know that there's no אבר מן החי or בשר מן
החי of these שרצים shratzim to begin with. But now we're saying
in terms of טומאה, tumah. it's the שיעור's shiur כעדשה, k'adasha, but
if the limb is even smaller than that, then you're מטמא metamei
for the limb of it. Correct. Exactly. So like a leg of
a millipede or something?
Exactly.
Of course, whether אבר requires בשר וגידים ועצמות, basar v'gidim v'atzamos, because
I think a leg of a millipede is primarily just עצמות atzamos
or something. But yes, whatever constitutes a limb, absolutely. Okay, so and
this is not about אבר מן החי, because it could come off
even as after it's dead, these are dead animals, okay? So the
limbs are important by themselves and therefore even less than the minimum
size cause טומאה. tumah. Fine. ואמר רבי יוחנן V'amar Rabbi Yochanan אין
לוקין עליהם אלא בכזית. ein lokin aleihem ela b'kezayis. Although they cause
טומאה, tumah, you don't get lashes unless it's a כזית. kzayis. So
here we're talking about dead שרצים, shratzim and it sounds like that
you need a כזית, kzayis. not like you go, and before you
said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that you go by כעדשה k'adasha.
when it comes to the איסור of eating. So what's going on
here? אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, במובדלים דיבר כתוב. b'muvdalim diber kasuv. We're talking about
the מובדלים. muvdalim. What does that mean? So the end of the
פסוק pasuk says, אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא. asher hivdalti lachem l'tamei. So
what does that mean? So let me just check before I tell
you, I just want to remind myself how תוספות Tosafos reads this
exactly.
Oh, okay. So yeah, so תוספות Tosafos reads it, I mean, it's
a funny way to say, give this answer, but anyway, תוספות Tosafos
says like this, that when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said אין לוקין
עליהם אלא בכזית, ein lokin aleihem ela b'kezayis, he's not talking about
the שרצים. shratzim The שרצים, shratzim you're right, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
would say what he said before, that you get מלקות malkus for
a כעדשה. k'adasha, Oh okay, so תוספות Tosfos reads it, I mean,
he reads it like this. He said that, which is a funny
way to give this answer, but anyway תוספות Tosfos says like this:
that when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אין לוקה אלא בכזית, ein
loka ella b'kzayis, he's not talking about the שרץ. sheretz. The שרץ,
you're right, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say what he said before,
that you get מלקות malkos for a כעדשה k'adasha? because that's the
עניין inyan of טומאה. tumah He's talking about the בהמה. behemah. Although
a limb of a בהמה behemah causes טומאה tumah by less than
a כזית, kzayis. when it comes that doesn't affect the איסור אכילה.
issur achilah And basically what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying and
actually, again, it's not so clear from the words, but it's an
important but it makes sense in the larger context. He's saying look,
I compared the size of טומאה tumah to the size of אכילה.
achilah. I said if you because the איסור of
טומאה tumah for a שרץ is a כעדשה, k'adasha. so the איסור
אכילה achilah is a כעדשה. k'adasha. So you should say back to
me, well say the same about a בהמה. behemah. But maybe that's
a moot point because a בהמה behemah both אכילה achilah and טומאה
tumah is a כזית. kzayis. But it's not a moot point because
there's a case by בהמה behemah where the טומאה tumah. is less
than a כזית. kezayis, What's that case? A whole limb. So maybe
we should say that a whole limb of a בהמה behemah is
also you get מלקות malkos even if it's not a כזית. kezayis
And therefore comes along רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to say אין לוקה
אלא בכזית. ein loka ella b'kzayis. Not by the שרצים. shratzim. שרצים
shratzim yes, a כעדשה, k'adasha I said that before. But by the
בהמה, behemah, although I said that a limb is טומאה, tumah it's
still not going to be מלקות. malkos. It's still not when it
comes to eating the בהמה, behemah, that's still going to be a
כזית. kezayis Why? So here it says במובדלים דיבר הכתוב. bimuvdalim diber
hakatuv. And here is why בהמות behemos are different than שרצים. shratzim,
Because by שרצים, shratzim the end of the פסוק pasuk says אשר
הבדלתי לכם לטמא. asher hivdalti lachem l'tamei. Some שרצים shratzim, are טמא,
tamei some שרצים shratzim. are not טמא, some dead שרצים shratzim are
not. So within שרצים, shratzim that's clearly what the end of the
פסוק pasuk is talking about. Some are טמא, some are not. So
therefore when the תורה links eating to טומאה, tumah it's only talking
about שרצים. shratzim Do you get that? The end of the פסוק
אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא, asher hivdalti lachem l'tamei, only שרצים sheratzim have
a difference that some of them cause טומאה tumah and some don't.
So the end of the פסוק pasuk is talking about שרצים sheratzim
and only שרצים sheratzim are linked eating to טומאה. tumah But other
things are not linked eating to טומאה. tumah. So when it comes
to בהמה, behemah, even if you have a whole limb and it
causes טומאה, tumah you will not get מלקות. malkos. מלקות malkos would
always be by כזית. kezayis Eating is not linked to טומאה tumah
by a בהמה. behemah. Okay, so that's how the גמרא Gemara now
answered and it now makes a lot of sense why רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan had to say this. במובדלים דיבר הכתוב bimuvdalim diber hakatuv
because the פסוק pasuk when it links טומאה tumah, to אכילה achilah
is only by שרצים sheratzim where there's a distinction between types of
שרצים sheratzim and it is not by other things. So it is
possible by a בהמה behemah that you can get טומאה tumah by
a limb and not get מלקות. malkos. מלקות malkos would always be
by כזית. Eating is not linked to טומאה tumah, by a בהמה.
behemah. אמר ליה אדא בר אהבה לרבא. amar lei Adda bar Ahava
l'Rava. So אדא בר אהבה Adda bar Ahava said to רבא, Rava,
אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if that's true, בהמה נמי ליפלוג בין מובדלת
לשאינה מובדלת. behemah nami liplug bein muvdeles l'she'eina muvdeles. So why not
by a בהמה behemah also distinguish between those that cause טומאה tumah
and those that don't? Now again, that doesn't exactly, or those that
are distinguished and those that aren't distinguished. Now the question does not
make so much sense. Right. Yeah, so תוספות Tosfos says right. So
what תוספות Tosfos basically says what that means
is, one
minute. It's exactly, it's a little again challenging how to read it
into the words, but the way תוספות Tosfos explains the question is
he says like this: Look, I get the primary thing the פסוק
pasuk is talking about is שרצים. And by שרצים the תורה is
making a link between
eating and טומאה. tumah, But at the same פסוק pasuk it says,
what's the whole פסוק? pasuk? והבדלתם בין הבהמה הטהורה לטמאה ובין העוף
הטמא לטהור. v'hivdaltem bein habehemah hatehorah l'tmeiah uvein ha'of hatamei latahor. So
even if the end of the פסוק pasuk is talking about שרצים,
but the whole פסוק pasuk is talking about everything. So let's link
the הלכה halacha of שרצים that says that טומאה tumah and אכילה
achila go together, let's link it to בהמה behemah as well. Okay,
so basically again what's going on is that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says in eating it comes to a כזית. Oh, didn't you say
you go by כעדשה? k'adasha. So the answer is yes. When it
comes to שרצים, that's called מובדלת muvdeles where the תורה distinguishes, eating
and טומאה tumah are linked, it's a כעדשה. When it comes to
בהמה, behemah, eating and טומאה tumah are not linked, so you can
have a whole limb and you still don't get מלקות, malkos, it
goes by כזית. And now the גמרא Gemara is saying yeah, but
the פסוק pasuk put בהמה behemah in the same פסוק pasuk with
שרצים. So let's say the same way by שרצים that equation applies,
it should apply to בהמה behemah as well. Now how exactly to
get that into these words, בהמה נמי ליפלוג בין מובדלת לשאינה מובדלת
behemah nami liplug bein muvdeles l'she'eina muvdeles is not exactly clear, but
presumably it means, you know, in a case when it causes טומאה
tumah and in a case when it doesn't cause טומאה. tumah Anyway
why don't we apply whatever, it really means let's apply the concept
we find by שרצים about that at least שרצים that cause טומאה
that are מובדלות, muvdelos, the טומאה and the eating is connected, let's
say this same by the בהמה. behemah. Since the פסוקים psukim combined
them all anyway. אמר ליה, so he said back to him, כי
קמקיש רחמנא לבל תשקצו. ki kamakish Rachmana l'bal teshaktzu. אבל לשיעורים לא.
aval l'shiurim lo. No, the end of the פסוק pasuk says ולא
תשקצו את נפשתיכם v'lo teshaktzu es nafshoseichem בכל מה? What's the end
of the פסוק? One of the בעלי קורא ba'alei kora here? It's
right here. ולא תשקצו את נפשתיכם בבהמה ובעוף ובכל אשר תרמש האדמה
אשר הבדלתי לכם לטמא. v'lo teshaktzu es nafshoseichem b'vhemah u've'of u'vechol asher
tirmos ha'adamah asher hivdalti lachem l'tamei. So yes, it does
link them all together, but it links to tell you that there's
a לאו lav of לא תשקצו. lo teshaktzu. בל תשקצו, bal teshaktzu,
which means that when you eat from all of these in addition
to all the other לאוין, lavin, you get the לאו lav of
בל תשקצו. bal teshaktzu. But they are not linked for this particular
הלכה halacha of אכילת טומאה. achilas tumah. That is something that is
distinct by שרצים and doesn't apply. So what do we actually say?
And the גמרא Gemara seems to conclude that way. We have a
very interesting הלכה halacha at the end that by שרצים when they
are dead and it's the שמונה שרצים shemonah sheratzim that cause טומאה,
those שמונה שרצים shemonah sheratzim that cause טומאה when they're dead and
cause טומאה, if you eat them it goes by כעדשה. Okay? And
maybe presumably also if you eat a whole limb of them, maybe
it goes by a limb. That wasn't clear, but that's quite possible
if טומאה and אכילה achila are linked. But by other שרצים which
are אסור but don't cause טומאה, or by בהמות, behemos, right, which
are not אשר הבדלתי לכם, asher hivdalti lachem, which are not a
distinction between they're all בהמות behemos are טמא that are dead, all
other things we do not link טומאה and eating and all other
things go by a כזית, even if the טומאה is less like
the case of a טומאה of a limb.
Okay, I had a question before which was why the why כזית
for בהמה behemah and I mean because
now we're saying
right
although no what you wanted to say is that they're all linked
and that it's always goes by a כזית right but the גמרא
is saying that they're not linked by בהמה. behemah.
No I was formalizing that idea that they're not there was an
assumption there that like
oh that it was only by שרץ and not by other things.
Right exactly and now it's exactly saying that אשר הבדלתי asher hivdalti
means we're only talking about שרץ. Okay so that was the end
about about צירוף tziruf for שרצים and again the צירוף tziruf works
both for טומאה different types of שרצים and and for אכילה achila
but with this different with this question about what is the שיעור
shiur for אכילה achila does it go by a כעדשה by at
least these שמונה שרצים shemonah sheratzim that cause טומאה when they are
dead the שיעור shiur would be less the שיעור shiur would be
a כעדשה.
Use my memory you know because there was a מחלוקת רב and
לוי Levi about the
טהור וטמא מצטרפין זה עם זה tahor vetamei mitztarfin zeh im zeh
did the גמרא resolve that? No.
Oh
yeah the גמרא it basically the question was just do we think
that a dead pig is also נבילה or not and that would
be the question about whether מצטרף mitztaref them together. Right. I have
to check how the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק paskens about that. I mean
just by going by the ציט tzit which isn't always the best
indicator indicator here where the א alef where the cross references it
looks like it's possible that the פסק psak is like רב that
it does not combine for אכילה but I'm pretty sure that that's
the הלכה halacha that
still a כזית but it's just בהמה טהורה. behemah tehorah.
Right I'm pretty sure that that's the הלכה halacha that בהמה behemah
a dead בהמה טמאה behemah temeiah does not have a status of
נבילה it only has a status of בהמה טמאה. behemah temeiah. Okay
let's take a look now at the next משנה י"ז עמוד א'
Yud Zayin amud aleph top of the דף. daf.