Okay boker
tov בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's daf דף daf is nun-tet נט,
nun-tet, Menachos מנחות Menachos 59, we pick up at the top of
nun-tet נט nun-tet at the mishnah משנה, mishnah,
for scheduling reasons we're going to just do the basically amud aleph
עמוד א amud aleph today till the mishnah משנה mishnah at the
top of nun-tet נט nun-tet amud beis עמוד ב amud beis and
then tomorrow we will catch up with, you know, cover the rest,
and the perek פרק perek is now in the middle of describing
the way the menachos מנחות menachos were made and the basic make,
you know, physical sort of aspects of the menachos מנחות, menachos, something
that we might have hoped would have been at the beginning of
the masechet מסכת masechet and the previous mishnah משנה mishnah told us
that all menachos מנחות menachos are kneaded with lukewarm water and you
have to be very careful they don't become chametz חמץ chametz and
the prohibition of letting a mincha מנחה mincha become chametz חמץ chametz
and that applies to all menachos מנחות. menachos. Our mishnah משנה mishnah
is now going to deal with aspects of the menachos מנחות menachos
that apply to some of which apply to some menachos מנחות menachos
and some to others. Okay, so let's take a look top of
nun-tet נט nun-tet amud aleph עמוד א. amud aleph. Yesh teunot shemen
u'levonah יש טעונות שמן ולבונה, yesh teunot shemen u'levonah, there are some
menachos מנחות menachos that require both oil, you've mixed the flour with
the oil and frankincense, you know, the handbreadth of the frankincense that
you put on top and then you offer it up on the
mizbeach מזבח. mizbeach. Shemen velo levonah שמן ולא לבונה, shemen velo levonah,
some have just the oil not the frankincense. You'll see if you
can figure out which is which before the mishnah משנה mishnah tells
you. Levonah velo shemen לבונה ולא שמן, levonah velo shemen, only frankincense
and not oil, that might seem very strange but think if you
can think what that might be. Lo levonah velo shemen לא לבונה
ולא שמן, lo levonah velo shemen,
neither oil nor frankincense, that is explicit in a pasuk פסוק. pasuk.
So here are the four categories. Ve'eilu ואלו ve'eilu and now it's
going to tell you which is which. Eilu teunot shemen levonah אלו
טעונות שמן ולבונה, eilu teunot shemen levonah, the following menachos מנחות menachos
require both oil and frankincense and these are all your standard menachos
מנחות. menachos. Okay, minchat hasolet ve'hamachavat ve'hamarcheshet ve'hachalot ve'harikikin מנחת הסולת והמחבת
והמרחשת והחלות והרקיקין. minchat hasolet ve'hamachavat ve'hamarcheshet ve'hachalot ve'harikikin. So all of
the standard mincha nedavah מנחה נדבה mincha nedava that are mentioned in
the beginning of Vayikra ויקרא Vayikra and, you know, whether it is
flour or just plain flour and oil or, you know, a frying
pan or a deep pan, wafers, loaves, all of those menachos מנחות.
menachos. Minchas kohanim מנחת כהנים, minchas kohanim, a mincha מנחה mincha of
a kohen כהן kohen which is also any of those but if
it's brought by a kohen כהן kohen the whole thing is offered
up on the mizbeach מזבח mizbeach but the basic physical constitution does
not change. Minchat kohen mashiach מנחת כהן משיח, minchat kohen mashiach, the
mincha מנחה mincha of a kohen כהן, kohen, the chavitin חביתין, chavitin,
half in the morning, half in the afternoon. Minchat ovdei kochavim u'minchat
nashim מנחת עובדי כוכבים ומנחת נשים, minchat ovdei kochavim u'minchat nashim, a
mincha מנחה mincha of a non-Jew, non-Jews can bring korbanot קרבנות, korbanot,
mincha מנחה mincha of a women, which is very bizarre that there'd
be any reason to think it would be any different, nothing in
the psukim פסוקים psukim indicate that there should be any difference between
a korban קרבן korban brought by man or women. The gemara גמרא
gemara it's true does say that women don't do semikhah סמיכה semikhah
on korbanot קרבנות, korbanot, they learn it from a pasuk פסוק pasuk
daber el benei yisrael דבר אל בני ישראל, daber el benei yisrael,
but nevertheless it'd be very strange that this is a separate category
that needs to somehow be explicitly included anyway. And minchas ha'omer מנחת
העומר, minchas ha'omer, the mincha מנחה mincha of the omer עומר omer
also has oil and frankincense.
Okay, but however,
minchas nesachim מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim teunah shemen ve'einah teunah levonah טעונה
שמן ואינה טעונה לבונה, teunah shemen ve'einah teunah levonah, the
mincha מנחה mincha that is brought with the wine and with the
korban קרבן, korban, you know, with an animal korban קרבן korban you
have to bring wine and you have to bring a mincha מנחה
mincha of flour and oil and that does not have levonah לבונה,
levonah, it's not really being offered on its own, the levonah לבונה
levonah is something, you know, you sort of take it and you
burn it on the altar as a type of a part of
the mincha מנחה mincha that gets offered but here it's really accompanying
the korban קרבן. korban. Anyway, we'll see from the gemara גמרא gemara
the psukim פסוקים psukim it learns it out from so there is
no levonah לבונה levonah but it is flour mixed with oil.
Lechem hapanim לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, now the lechem hapanim לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim which was on the shulchan שולחן, shulchan, so teunah levonah
ve'einah teunah shemen טעונה לבונה ואינה טעונה שמן. teunah levonah ve'einah teunah
shemen. That's really just flour and water but it does have the
levonah לבונה levonah which are in the two little, you know, spoons
that are on the shulchan שולחן shulchan and that's what's offered up
on the mizbeach מזבח mizbeach and then the lechem hapanim לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim is eaten by the kohanim כהנים kohanim and it is
basically just plain flour and water, no oil. Teunah levonah ve'einah teunah
shemen טעונה לבונה ואינה טעונה שמן. teunah levonah ve'einah teunah shemen. Shtei
halechem u'minchat chotei u'minchat kenaot ein teunah lo shemen velo levonah שתי
הלחם ומנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות אין טעונה לא שמן ולא לבונה. shtei
halechem u'minchat chotei u'minchat kenaot ein teunah lo shemen velo levonah. The
shtei halechem שתי הלחם shtei halechem for
Shavuos שבועות, Shavuos, so that's similar, it is basically flour and water,
similar to the lechem hapanim לחם הפנים lechem hapanim except that there's
no levonah לבונה, levonah, nothing gets offered up because, you know, that
is, I mean, the animals, the kivsei atzeres כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeres
get offered up but that is chametz חמץ chametz and therefore no
sort of thing that's connected to it directly like levonah לבונה levonah
gets offered up, so that is basically just flour and water and
that is chametz חמץ, chametz, so that's no shemen שמן shemen and
no levonah לבונה levonah and minchas chotei מנחת חוטא, minchas chotei, you
know, of the korban קרבן, korban, there's a korban oleh ve'yored קרבן
עולה ויורד korban oleh ve'yored at the end of parshas Vayikra פרשת
ויקרא, parshas Vayikra, some few types of sins based on your level
that you can afford, you bring, you know, either animal or bird
or a mincha מנחה mincha and if it's just a mincha מנחה
mincha and it's for a sin it's a... It's a type of
a חטאת chata'as for these small number of identified sins, then you
know there is no oil or or frankincense because it's for sins.
So therefore this thing that makes it beautiful, fragrant and nice, so
that is not a part of it. That's explicit in the פסוקים
pesukim and the מנחת קנאות Minchas Kenaos similarly for a woman who's
suspected of adultery: לא יתן עליה שמן ולא ישים עליה לבונה כי
מנחת קנאות היא מנחת זכרון מזכרת עון. lo yiten aleha shemen v'lo
yasim aleha levonah ki minchas kenaos hi minchas zikaron mazkeres avon.
Don't have any oil, don't have any frankincense. This is about jealousy,
about sin and so on. אין טעונה לא שמן ולא לבונה. Ain
teunah lo shemen v'lo levonah. So that has neither. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara is just going to learn out some of these
things which are not explicit in the פסוקים. pesukim. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: כל
היכא דתנן עשר תנן. Kol heicha d'tnan esser tnan. Whenever we have
this משנה Mishnah we're talking about ten. Now what does this mean?
רש"י Rashi has two explanations. So one explanation is that all of
the מנחות menachos that are mentioned in the משנה Mishnah you bring
ten חלות chalos when you bring them, that you bring them of
ten חלות. chalos. That's how you bring a מנחה mincha of each
of the מינים. minim.
And
okay fine, so what is that coming to to contrast against? So
let's see the next line in the גמרא. Gemara. עשר תנן Esser
tnan לאפוקי מדרבי שמעון. l'apukei mid'Rabbi Shimon.
This comes to sort of exclude the position of Rabbi Shimon דאמר
d'amar who says in a few pages in a משנה: Mishnah: מחצה
חלות ומחצה רקיקין יביא. mechtzah chalos u'mechtzah rekikin yavi. That when you
say that you're going to bring a מנחה מאפה תנור, Minchah Ma'afeh
Tanur, baked in an oven, so the Torah there says you know
if you say מנחת מאפה תנור, minchas ma'afeh tanur, it says חלות
מצות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן. chalos matzos belulos bashemen u'rekikei
matzos meshuchim bashemen.
It says it should be חלות chalos or it should be wafers.
So how do you read that? So Rabbi Shimon reads it that
you can bring all חלות, chalos, all ten could be חלות chalos
or all ten could be wafers or you could do half חלות
chalos and half wafers, any mix of those or at least maybe
an equal mix. החכמים Hachachamim disagree and they say no, the Torah
is giving you two options: when you say מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tanur,
it can either be all חלות chalos or it can be all
wafers. So comes along רב פפא Rav Papa and he says all
these, so the משנה Mishnah mentioned if you look, right, חלות ורקיקין,
chalos v'rekikin, those are the two types of מאפה תנור. Ma'afeh Tanur.
So he is saying when the משנה Mishnah talks about חלות ורקיקין,
chalos v'rekikin, I want you to know it's ten of each type.
If it's מחבת, Machavas, ten of
מחבת, Machavas, מרחשת, Marcheshes, ten of מרחשת, Marcheshes, חלות, chalos, ten of
those, רקיקין, rekikin, ten of those. Not like Rabbi Shimon who says
that you can have five חלות chalos and five רקיקין rekikin as
a type of מנחה מאפה תנור. Minchah Ma'afeh Tanur. Okay, so that's
what it's coming to reject. יביא קא משמע לן דלא כשיטתנא. Yavi
k'mashma lan d'lo kishituna. That's one way of reading it. The other
way is, this is very ingenious, if you count the מנחות menachos
mentioned in our משנה Mishnah there are ten of them, right? Let's
count. Of the ones that are both oil and לבונה. levonah. Okay
so let's count them. סולת Soles one, מחבת, Machavas, מרחשת, Marcheshes, חלות,
Chalos, רקיקין, Rekikin, that's five. כהנים Kohanim six, כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach
seven, מנחת עובדי כוכבים Minchas Oveidei Kochavim eight, מנחת נשים Minchas Nashim
nine and מנחת העומר Minchas HaOmer ten. So he says there are
ten listed in our משנה, Mishnah, not like Rabbi Shimon because Rabbi
Shimon would have an eleventh. What's the eleventh for Rabbi Shimon? Something
that is half חלות chalos and half רקיקין. rekikin. He thinks that
that is possible. Okay, so one way or another, basically saying our
משנה Mishnah is not Rabbi Shimon.
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ונתת עליה שמן ולא על לחם הפנים. V'nasata
aleha shemen v'lo al lechem hapanim. So that has neither. Okay.
So this is by a normal מנחה. mincha. It says ונתת עליה
שמן. v'nasata aleha shemen. So that's a פסוק pasuk actually by the
עומר. Omer. I'll read you the פסוקים. pesukim. It's ויקרא ב Vayikra
Beis starting at י"ד: yud-daled: ואם תקריב מנחת בכורים לה' אביב קלוי
באש גרש כרמל תקריב את מנחת בכוריך ונתת עליה שמן ושמת עליה
לבונה מנחה היא. v'im takriv minchas bikurim l'Hashem aviv kalui ba'eish geres
karmel takriv es minchas bikurecha v'nasata aleha shemen v'samta aleha levonah mincha
hi.
So by just saying oil and לבונה levonah it is a מנחה.
mincha. Certainly seems to be saying, hey, that's what you generally do
by a מנחה: mincha: oil and לבונה. levonah. So let's see what
we do with this. ונתת עליה שמן ולא על לחם הפנים שמן.
v'nasata aleha shemen v'lo al lechem hapanim shemen. So the עליה aleha
on it is coming to exclude the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Now
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim it never tells you one way or the
other, but that you should not assume, well it's a מנחה, mincha,
it's a מנחה, mincha, so it's all going to be the same.
No, עליה aleha only on this or on these types that are
being discussed right here. שיכול ולא דין הוא. Sheyachol v'lo din hu.
I could have thought make a קל וחומר kal vachomer or make
a logical argument to say that you do have oil in the
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Why? ומה מנחת נסכים שאינה טעונה לבונה טעונה
שמן. U'mah minchas nesachim she'eina teunah levonah teunah shemen. מנחת נסכים Minchas
nesachim you know does not have frankincense. How do we know that?
We'll learn that later, but now we're assuming that. But it does
have oil. The Torah is explicit: it's about flour and oil. It
tells you how much flour, how much oil for based on whether
it's a cow or sheep or you know or a goat or
a ram, excuse me. So therefore if the
if the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim doesn't have doesn't have לבונה levonah
and it nevertheless has oil, right? So עליה לבונה, aleha Levonah, so
לחם הפנים שטעון, Lechem Hapanim she-ta'un, לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim that is
even more strict, it's gonna have frankincense, אינו דין שטעון שמן? eino
din she-te'un shemen? How much more strict should it be on? I
mean that's if you assume that everything is linear, right? It's not
each thing is its own character. So here, we know that it
has something that the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim doesn't have, it has
לבונה, Levonah, so presumably that means it's more than the מנחת נסכים,
Minchat Nesachim, it should also have oil. You would think that that's
true about the לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar עליה.
aleha. עליה שמן ולא ללחם הפנים שמן. aleha shemen velo le-Lechem Hapanim
shemen. No,
so you shouldn't make that קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It comes to
tell you that only on this and not on something else where
it's not where it doesn't state state oil, not on the לחם
הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. The לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim does not get oil.
Okay, the next part of this פסוק: pasuk: ונתת עליה לבונה, venatata
aleha Levonah, place לבונה Levonah on it, frankincense. עליה לבונה ולא למנחת
נסכים לבונה. aleha Levonah velo le-Minchat Nesachim Levonah. And here's where we
learn out the other half of it. What we alluded mentioned before.
Only on this, the עומר Omer and these מנחות Menachot that are
mentioned here gets frankincense and not on something where it's not mentioned.
Don't come to try to argue that it should. What is that
thing where it doesn't say frankincense? By the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim.
It mentions flour and oil, never mentions frankincense. This is to tell
you uh-uh, frankincense is only by these מנחות, Menachot, not by those
that it has not been mentioned, not by the לחם הפנים. Lechem
Hapanim. So basically by the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim it doesn't excuse
me, not by the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. So מנחת נסכים Minchat
Nesachim doesn't mention frankincense, don't put it on. לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim
doesn't mention oil, don't put it on. שיכול ולא דין הוא? she-yachol
velo din hu? I might have made a קל וחומר kal vachomer
to say מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim get frankincense. Why? ומה לחם הפנים
שאינו טעון שמן טעון לבונה? u-mah Lechem Hapanim she-eino ta'un shemen ta'un
Levonah? We just basically learned from a פסוק pasuk that לחם
הפנים Lechem Hapanim does not get oil and nevertheless it gets frankincense.
So מנחת נסכים שטעונה שמן, Minchat Nesachim she-te'unah shemen, מנחת נסכים Minchat
Nesachim that is more than the לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim, we know
there's oil for the מנחת נסכים, Minchat Nesachim, אינו דין שטעונה לבונה?
eino din she-te'unah Levonah?
So again, if you assume it's linear, we already established that the
לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim is no oil but yes frankincense. So מנחת
נסכים Minchat Nesachim which is yes oil, so it's even weightier, so
maybe it should also be frankincense? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar עליה. aleha.
עליה לבונה ולא למנחת נסכים לבונה. aleha Levonah velo le-Minchat Nesachim Levonah.
No, עליה aleha is coming to say no, keep it here, keep
it where it's mentioned in these מנחות, Menachot, but in the מנחות
Menachot where it's not mentioned, you do not put לבונה. Levonah. Where
it's not mentioned שמן, shemen, you do not put שמן. shemen. So
no שמן shemen in the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim and no לבונה
Levonah with the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. Okay, עליה לבונה. aleha Levonah.
Where it's not mentioned oil or לבונה, Levonah, the שתי הלחם, Shtei
Halechem, don't put either of them. מנחה היא. Mincha hi.
But then the end of the פסוק pasuk says it is a
מנחה. Mincha. So that seems to underscore that oil and frankincense are
characteristic of a מנחה. Mincha. That seems to be a more inclusive
type of a word. לרבות מנחת שמיני ללבונה. lerabot Minchat Shemini le-Levonah.
To tell you that the מנחה Mincha that they brought on the
eighth day of the מילואים, Miluim, that does get the לבונה. Levonah.
Okay, היא. hi.
But היא hi is limiting, again another limiting word. להוציא שתי הלחם
שלא יתנו לו שמן ולא לבונה. lehotzi Shtei Halechem she-lo yitnu lo
shemen velo Levonah.
היא hi is coming to say another thing where it's not mentioned
oil or frankincense, the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. So again, if it's
not mentioned there oil or frankincense, היא hi says limit it to
what you've got here. Okay? Only these things where it's not mentioned
oil like לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim, don't put oil. Like עליה שמן.
aleha shemen. Where it's not mentioned לבונה Levonah like by מנחת נסכים,
Minchat Nesachim, don't put לבונה. Levonah. Okay, that's עליה לבונה. aleha Levonah.
Where it's not mentioned oil or לבונה, Levonah, the שתי הלחם, Shtei
Halechem, don't put either of them. היא. hi. All of these things
say don't put it where it's not said. All right? And the
only thing what we're expanding is the מנחה Mincha on the eighth
day of the מילואים Miluim which is a standard מנחה Mincha and
there it makes sense to include it in this group of standard
מנחות. Menachot. Okay. אמר מר. Amar mar.
Now we're going to go back and unpack this. עליה שמן ולא
ללחם הפנים שמן. aleha shemen velo le-Lechem Hapanim shemen. On it oil
and not on the לחם הפנים. Lechem Hapanim. אימא עליה שמן ולא
למנחת כהנים שמן? eima aleha shemen velo le-Minchat Kohanim shemen? What made
you, if we're going to exclude something, maybe we should also exclude
the מנחת כהנים? Minchat Kohanim? The תורה Torah tells you a מנחת
כהנים, Minchat Kohanim, you know, you burn,
but okay, once it's a different category, maybe it never explicitly says
oil, so maybe it also shouldn't get oil if it doesn't explicitly
say it. No, so we're going to say no. It makes sense,
the question is where does it make sense to category, what does
it make sense to put in this category of all these מנחות
Menachot that get oil and frankincense and what does it make sense
that the תורה Torah would be sort of saying is no, those
are different. So מסתברא מנחת כהנים הויא לריבויי. mistabra Minchat Kohanim havya
le-ribuy. It makes sense that מנחת כהנים Minchat Kohanim should be assumed
to be part of these standard מנחות menachot that get oil and
frankincense. Why? שכן sheken and now we're going to give a list
of similar characteristics. עישרון, issaron, okay, both of these, both a normal
מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen and all these מנחות menachot is
a עישרון issaron of סולת solet as opposed to the לחם הפנים,
Lechem HaPanim, which is bigger, which is a lot bigger. כלי, kli,
both of them use a כלי שרת, kli sharet, whereas the לחם
הפנים Lechem HaPanim gets sanctified either in the oven or on the
שולחן, shulchan, we discussed that before. Okay, so get similar to standard
מנחה mincha that way. חוץ, chutz, both of them can become no,
excuse me, both of them meaning the other מנחות menachot are done
outside, not חוץ chutz outside the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but outside
the
היכל, Heichal, right? The מנחת כהן minchat kohen and a standard מנחה
mincha are done in the עזרה azarah on the מזבח, mizbeach, but
the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim is done in the actual in the
actual היכל Heichal itself. Okay, so that's חוץ. chutz.
צורה, tzura, צורה tzura means like it loses its shape, that's a
word that the גמרא Gemara uses to mean that it becomes invalid
when it stays over the next night. So a normal מנחה mincha
becomes invalid by in the morning,
but the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim stays throughout the whole week.
הגשה, hagasha, normal מנחה mincha and a מנחת כהן minchat kohen you
touch the מנחה mincha to the to the מזבח, mizbeach, you do
not do that by the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, we'll learn that
later. ואישים, v'ishim, and both of those go on the מזבח. mizbeach.
A normal מנחה mincha קומץ komets goes and a מנחת כהן minchat
kohen the whole thing goes on the outer מזבח, mizbeach, whereas by
the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim only the לבונה levona goes on the
מזבח, mizbeach, but no part of the מנחה mincha itself. So bottom
line is a מנחת כהן minchat kohen is pretty much the same
as a normal מנחה mincha except that it all gets burnt. So
it makes sense to compare it to a normal מנחה mincha and
say it's in this general group. So the גמרא Gemara says back,
no אדרבה, aderaba, I'll argue the opposite. לחם הפנים הוה ליה לרבויי.
Lechem HaPanim hava lei leribuy. No, לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim actually should
be similar to this group in ways more than a מנחת כהן.
minchat kohen. Why? שכן ציבורא, sheken tzipura,
number one, a לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim is a קרבן ציבור korban
tzibur and a normal מנחה mincha can be a קרבן ציבור, korban
tzibur, but a מנחת כהן minchat kohen is only a קרבן יחיד.
korban yachid. חובה, chova, similarly, a מנחה mincha of לחם הפנים Lechem
HaPanim is an obligation, you have מנחות menachot that are obligatory, a
מנחת כהן minchat kohen is always free will. טמיא, tamya, and this
is like a little bit of a phrase: טמיא דאכל פיגולא בשבתא,
tamya d'achal pigula b'shabbata, a tamei person who ate pigul on Shabbos.
Okay, but what it means is that the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim
and a מנחה mincha that is a ציבור tzibur מנחה mincha would
be able to be eaten בטומאה b'tumah because טומאה הותרה בציבור, tumah
hutra b'tzibur, it's really a function of them being a ציבור tzibur
and obligatory, whereas that of a כהן kohen is always a יחיד
yachid and therefore would not override ציבור. tzibur.
Actually, I should say one step further, it's not just I'm trying
to say it's similar to these general category of מנחות menachot that
the תורה Torah is talking about in ויקרא, Vayikra, but the specific
פסוקים pesukim we're dealing with actually are the מנחת העומר, Minchat HaOmer,
and the מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer is a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur
not only is דוחה טומאה, docheh tumah, so I was talking more
generally about all מנחות, menachot, but specifically מנחת העומר, Minchat HaOmer, it's
very similar. It is an obligation, it is ציבור, tzibur, it is
דוחה טומאה. docheh tumah. דאכיל, d'achil, and the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim
and the standard מנחה mincha and the מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer is
eaten, whereas the כהן kohen is not eaten. פיגולא, pigula, by both
of these you can have פיגול pigul since there's a part that's
a מתיר matir by a normal מנחה mincha or by the עומר,
omer, the קומץ komets by a שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, it is
the לבונה. levona. If you had a thought of פיגול, pigul, you
turn the rest into פיגול. pigul. Whereas by a מנחת כהן minchat
kohen it's all burnt, there's no מתיר, matir, there's no way to
create פיגול. pigul. And בשבתא, b'shabbata, also that it overrides שבת, Shabbat,
מנחת העומר Minchat HaOmer and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem again because
they're obligatory קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so maybe דוקא davka we should say
שתי הלחם shtei halechem is similar particularly to the עומר, omer, which
is the פסוקים pesukim we're looking at. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, at the end of the day מסתברא נפש, mistavra nefesh, there's
one characteristic that is the trump card. And that is, when it
opens up it says נפש כי תקריב קרבן מנחה לה', nefesh ki
takriv korban mincha l'Hashem, if a soul, meaning it's an individual קרבן.
korban. And therefore, since a כהן kohen is the קרבן korban of
an individual and this category, yes it has a מנחת העומר Minchat
HaOmer but it's also שמן shemen and לבונה levona are all these
private individual קרבנות, korbanot, that is why it makes sense to say
מנחת כהן minchat kohen gets oil and לבונה levona and that the
לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim remains on the
outside. Okay. And רש"י Rashi just says also one thing more that
it again even these פסוקים pesukim not by the עומר, omer, we've
been focusing on the פסוקים pesukim by the עומר, omer, but the
פסוק pasuk that says נפש כי תקריב קרבן מנחה, nefesh ki takriv
korban mincha, I should read it, right? That's פרק ב' פסוק א':
Perek Bet Pasuk Aleph: ונפש כי תקריב קרבן מנחה לה' סולת יהיה
קרבנו ויצק עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה. V'nefesh ki takriv korban mincha
l'Hashem solet yihiyeh korbano v'yatzak aleha shemen v'natan aleha levona. Okay, so
It actually there also opening פסוק Pasuk of a מנחה Mincha is
שמן Shemen and לבונה Levonah and it says נפש, Nefesh, and it
makes sense that the כהן Kohen is included in נפש, Nefesh, a
personal קרבן. Korban. Fine. מנחה Mincha לרבות... Lerabot... we're continuing to
unpack. מנחה... Mincha...
I'm sorry, I skipped a line... לרבות נפש. Lerabot Nefesh. אמר מר,
Amar Mar, עליה לבונה Aleha Levonah ולא המנחת נסכים לבונה. V'lo HaMinchat
Nesachim Levonah.
Now we're going to look at the next part. So only these
מנחות Menachot get לבונה, Levonah, but not the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim.
אימא, Eima, עליה לבונה ולא המנחת כהנים לבונה, Aleha Levonah V'lo HaMinchat
Kohanim Levonah, same question. Maybe if we're going to be excluding something,
let's exclude כהן. Kohen. The מנחה Mincha of כהנים Kohanim once again
does not say oil and frankincense, so maybe it's that is what's
being excluded, that doesn't get frankincense. No, מסתבר מנחת כהנים הוה ליה
לרבויי. Mistabra Minchat Kohanim Hava Lei L'ribuyei. It makes sense that מנחת
כהנים Minchat Kohanim should be included with normal מנחות Menachot and with
this עומר. Omer. Why? Same reason. שכן עישרון, Sheken Isaron, it's an
עישרון Isaron of flour which is not the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim.
בלול, Balul, it says mixed with oil, the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim
says oil but doesn't say בלול. Balul. בלוג, B'log, it's only a
לוג Log of שמן, Shemen, the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim is multiple
לוגים. Logim. מוגש, Mugash, you do הגשה Hagasha by כהן Kohen and
a normal one but not by the מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. בגלל
עצמו, Biglal Atzmo, it's brought on its own accord as opposed to
the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim which is brought as an attendant to
the main
קרבן. Korban. So it has all those ways מנחת כהן Minchat Kohen
is like a normal קרבן Korban and therefore that should be on
the inside and מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim should be on the outside.
So גמרא Gemara says אדרבה, Adaraba, the opposite. מנחת נסכים הוה ליה
לרבויי, Minchat Nesachim Hava Lei L'ribuyei, שכן ציבורא, Sheken Tzipura, חובה, Chova,
ואתי בשבתא. V'ati B'shabta. So similar to what we said before, מנחת
נסכים Minchat Nesachim is can be brought by a
קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibur. A כהן Kohen never is in the context
of ציבור, Tzibur, and a normal מנחה Mincha can be in the
context of ציבור, Tzibur, an עומר Omer is that way. חובה, Chova,
an עומר Omer is an obligation, מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim are an
obligation. מנחת הכהן Minchat HaKohen is never an obligation. אתי, Ati, it's
brought בטומאה, B'tumah, the עומר Omer is brought בטומאה. B'tumah. If you
bring a קרבן Korban that's allowed to be brought בטומאה B'tumah you
can also bring the נסכים בטומאה. Nesachim B'tumah. But that's never would
be about a כהן Kohen because again it's always free will. בשבתא
B'shabta also, עומר Omer overrides שבת, Shabbat, מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim by
the קרבנות Korbanot that you bring on שבת Shabbat like the קרבן
תמיד Korban Tamid and the מוסף Musaf you bring מנחת נסכים, Minchat
Nesachim, never true by a מנחת כהן Minchat Kohen which you don't
bring on שבת. Shabbat. So again there's ways maybe to say that
מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim is on the inside and מנחת כהנים Minchat
Kohanim is on the outside. And the גמרא Gemara says the same
thing it said before. No, מסתבר נפש. Mistabra Nefesh. It makes sense
that since the opening פסוקים, Pesukim, and it's funny why we start
with the פסוקים Pesukim by עומר, Omer, but the opening פסוקים Pesukim
by מנחות Menachot say נפש כי תקריב Nefesh Ki Takriv and says
put on it oil, put on it לבונה, Levonah, so it makes
sense that anything that is a personal קרבן Korban like a which
would include a מנחת כהן Minchat Kohen gets שמן Shemen and לבונה.
Levonah. So the things that are being excluded where it didn't mention
שמן Shemen and לבונה Levonah are things that are not in that
category, things like שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim
and so
on. מנחה לרבות מנחת שמיני לבונה. Mincha L'rabot Minchat Shmini Levonah. So
what's the extra מנחה? Mincha? היא Hi to tell you even the
מנחה Mincha brought on the eighth day of the מילואים Miluim gets
the לבונה. Levonah. It didn't say it explicitly. ואימא להוציא, V'eima L'hotzi,
maybe it's coming to exclude? What makes you think that it's coming
to include? Maybe it's coming to exclude. האי מאי, Hai Mai, what
are you talking about? אי אמרת בשלמא לרבות שפיר. I Amrat Bishlama
L'rabot Shapir. If the מנחה Mincha is coming to include the קרבן
Korban of the eighth day, fine, you understand why you need a
פסוק. Pasuk. אלא אי אמרת להוציא למה לי שמי דורות לא ילפינן.
Ella I Amrat L'hotzi Lama Li Sh'mi Dorot Lo Yalfinan. But if
it's coming to exclude why would you need a פסוק? Pasuk? There's
a general principle that something that was only for that time is
not a all the time type of an obligation. You can't learn
out something that is very much for its very one day, one
particular time in history from general rules. So it does not say
by שמיני לבונה, Shmini Levonah, it just said by that it was
just oil. So if I had no פסוקים Pesukim I would say
it only I can only go by what it says. This is
a special קרבן Korban only once in history on this day, the
eighth day of מילואים. Miluim. I'm not going to try to apply
any other rules from it. So I wouldn't need a פסוק Pasuk
to tell me no לבונה. Levonah. Of course it gets no לבונה,
Levonah, you only go by what it says. You don't learn out
from anything else. So if there's going to be a פסוק Pasuk
of מנחה Mincha it's going to come to say yes לבונה, Levonah,
to include, and that's where what we're saying. היא להוציא שתי הלחם.
Hi L'hotzi Shtei HaLechem. And the last one היא Hi to exclude
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem where it mentions neither oil nor לבונה Levonah
that it gets neither of them,
שלא יתנו לא שמן ולא לבונה. Shelo Yitnu Lo Shemen V'lo Levonah.
ואימא להוציא, V'eima L'hotzi, why don't I say that the היא Hi
is coming to exclude מנחת כוהנים? Minchat Kohanim? That מנחת כוהנים Minchat
Kohanim are on the outs because they don't get מנחה Mincha and
לבונה. Levonah. Again it doesn't say by them... No, we know what
the answer's going to be, נפש, Nefesh, but let the גמרא Gemara
make its comparisons. מסתבר מנחת כהנים הוה ליה לרבויי. Mistabra Minchat Kohanim
Hava Lei L'ribuyei. No, it makes more sense that מנחת כהנים Minchat
Kohanim are like your standard מנחות Menachot and your מנחת העומר. Minchat
HaOmer. Why? And you know, and have more in comparison with it
than the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem do. שכן עישרון. sheken isaron. Again,
it's an עישרון, isaron, not the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. כלי, kli,
you use a כלי kli to make them, and you know, you
need them in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, and we're going to
learn that the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem is like the לחם הפנים
Lechem HaPanim that only gets sanctified in the תנור, tanur, you actually
it's פסול pasul if you do the kneading in a כלי שרת.
kli sharet. מצה. Matza. Okay, that's a very nice comparison. All מנחות
menachot are מצה matza except for the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, so
those are on the
outs. ועצם, Ve'etzem, and it is brought by itself, a מנחה, mincha,
a מנחת כהן, Minchat Kohen, as opposed to the שתי הלחם Shtei
HaLechem comes together with the כבשי עצרת. Kivsei Atzeret. הגשה, Hagasha, you
do the הגשה hagasha to the מזבח mizbeach which we're going to
learn you do not do by the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. ואישים,
Ve'ishim, and some of it goes on the fire, whether it is
the קומץ kometz or the whole מנחה mincha by a כהן kohen
as opposed to the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, nothing of it goes
on the fire. So therefore that makes sense that we're going to
put the מנחת כהן Minchat Kohen on the inside and the שתי
הלחם Shtei HaLechem on the outside. אדרבה Adaraba says the גמרא Gemara
the opposite. שתי הלחם הוי ליה לרבויי, Shtei HaLechem hava lei leribuyei,
I'll tell you why שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem should be on the
inside and get oil and לבונה. levona. שכן ציבור, sheken tzibur, it's
like the עומר Omer that it's a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. חובה,
Chova, again it's like the עומר Omer that it's obligatory. דדחי טומאה
ודחי שבתא de'dachi tumah ve'dachi shabta like we had before. Because it's
obligatory and it's a ציבור tzibur it is דוחה doche at the
טומאה tumah if it overrides טומאה, tumah, it is,
it is eaten, you eat the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, you eat
a normal מנחה, mincha, you do not eat the מנחה mincha of
a כהן. kohen. פיגול, Pigul, again the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem has
a מתיר, matir, you know, the מתיר matir is the, is the
what do you call it, is the כבשי עצרת, Kivsei Atzeret, all
other מנחות menachot have a מתיר matir which is the, the קומץ
kometz and therefore you can make them into פיגול. pigul. The מנחת
כהן Minchat Kohen you burn the whole thing, you can't make it
into פיגול pigul and so therefore, so therefore the מנחת כהן Minchat
Kohen is different, is on the outs, no פיגול pigul is not
possible. בשבתא, Be'shabta, again you bring it on שבת Shabbos because again
it's obligatory, it's ציבור. tzibur. מתיר, Matir, and both of them, yeah,
the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem really are similar
because the עומר Omer is מתיר matir the new grain in, you
know, in general for the lay person and the שתי הלחם Shtei
HaLechem is מתיר matir the new grain to be used in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. תנופה, Tnufa, and you both, you wave both
of them. You normally don't wave normal מנחות menachot but you wave
the עומר Omer and you wave the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. Not
normal מנחות menachot and not the מנחת כהן. Minchat Kohen. בארץ, Ba'aretz,
both of them have to only come from grain grown in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Again, these are the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and
the מנחת עומר Minchat Omer are really like parallel מנחות menachot except
one is, you know, for the barley and one is for the
wheat and one is to allow it outside the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and one is to allow it in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash but they're coming from the new grain from ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. בזמן, Bizman, and, you know, it comes at a very specific
time on פסח Pesach or on שבועות. Shavuos. חדש, Chadash, and they
both come from the new grain. והני נפישן ve'hani nefishen and these
are more, meaning okay, of all of the comparisons, שתי הלחם Shtei
HaLechem and עומר Omer are very, very similar. So maybe if the
עומר Omer gets oil and frankincense the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem should.
And so now that's the most convincing of all of the arguments.
But in the end the גמרא Gemara comes to the same conclusion:
מסתברא נפש. mistabra nefesh. At the end of the day, no. נפש,
Nefesh, any individual who brings a מנחה, mincha, oil and frankincense and
therefore if he is coming to exclude, it is excluding שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem since it doesn't say oil and frankincense, it does not
get it. At the end of the day, all these things that
don't get it, you know, מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesachim it doesn't say
frankincense, the, the לחם
הפנים Lechem HaPanim it doesn't say שמן shemen and, and שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem it doesn't say שמן shemen or frankincense, so these various
פסוקים psukim עליה עליה היא aleha aleha hi are just saying read
them, don't go beyond, you know, what it says in the פסוקים.
psukim. Only what it says, don't add these other things. The only
reason the גמרא Gemara asks by מנחת כהן Minchat Kohen is because
מנחת כהן Minchat Kohen also doesn't say oil and frankincense and in
the end that does get included because of נפש. nefesh. Okay, we
will end here.