Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is דף צא, Daf
Tzadi Aleph, מנחות Menachos 91. We pick up three lines from the
bottom on צא עמוד ב. Tzadi Amud Bais. We're in the middle
of a whole discussion of the נסכים nesachim of the wine and
the מנחה mincha of the oil and the flour that is brought
to accompany,
according to the פסוקים, psukim, it's in פרשת שלח, Parshas Shelach, נדר
neder או o נדבה, nedava, a free-will sacrifice. But actually, it plays
out that it's really an עולה Olah or a שלמים, Shelamim, the
types of sacrifices that are classically free-will, whether they're coming as free-will
or as an obligation, but not by a חטאת Chatas and an
אשם. Asham. And the last thing we discussed is that it's also
not by a bird sacrifice, and there's a debate where we know
that from. Okay, that רבי יאשיה
Rabbi
Yoshiya says that it comes from the word או, O, מן הבהמה,
min habiheima, excuse me, לעשות ריח ניחוח להשם מן הבקר או מן
הצאן, lasos reyach nichoach l'hashem min habakar o min hatzon, the extra
או O is somehow teaching you only cattle and sheep, but not
birds. That's what רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says. And רבי יונתן Rabbi
Yonasan says no, זבח zevach tells you only mammals and not birds.
And the או O is coming to tell me that when ויקרא
Vayikra opens up by saying אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן להשם מן
הבקר מן הבהמה ומן הצאן, adam ki yakriv mikem korban l'hashem min
habakar min habiheima u'min hatzon, that it doesn't mean that you have
to bring both. If the ו vav doesn't mean both, if you
say I'm going to bring an עולה, Olah, it doesn't mean you
have to bring both. The ו vav doesn't mean
both. The או O by the פרשה parsha of נסכים nesachim tells
me it could be cattle or a sheep. So now what the
גמרא Gemara is going to do, it's going to focus on that
issue. That רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan needed the או O to say
one or the other, and
רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya assumed it meant one or the other, and
he needed the או O to tell you to exclude birds. And
that actually is the reverse of the positions they normally take. Because
normally, you know, רבי נתן Rabbi Nosson is going to say that
a ו vav means or, that when the תורה Torah normally says,
you know, it's very it's not clear, you know, in Hebrew, sometimes
a ו vav can mean and, and sometimes a ו vav can
mean or, and it depends by context. And we're going to see
that רבי נתן's Rabbi Nosson's general position is that a ו vav
by default means or, unless the תורה Torah is very clear that
it means and. And רבי יאשיה's Rabbi Yoshiya's position is that a
ו vav by default means and. And the funny thing here is
that they're taking the reverse positions. So let's take a look at
that. רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonasan, רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonasan who says that
we needed the או O by נסכים nesachim to tell me that
an עולה Olah can be cattle or sheep, it doesn't have to
be both, למה לי קרא? lama li kra? Why do you need
a פסוק pasuk to tell me that it means or? The או
O explicit או O means or. הא אמר עד שיפרט לך הכתוב
יחדיו? Ha amar ad sheyiparet lecha hakasuv yachdav? His normal position is
until the תורה Torah says together, like לא תחרוש בשור ובחמור יחדיו,
lo sacharosh b'shor u'vachamor yachdav, together.
Unless it says יחדיו, yachdav, we're going to interpret a ו vav
to mean or. And if we're going to interpret a ו vav
to mean or, then in ויקרא Vayikra opens and says אדם כי
יקריב מכם קרבן להשם מן הבקר מן הבהמה ומן הצאן, adam ki
yakriv mikem korban l'hashem min habakar min habiheima u'min hatzon, it means
or from sheep. So since it means or, why was he the
one that said you need the extra או O to tell me
or? The whole פסוק pasuk that opens ויקרא Vayikra I would have
understood meant or according to him. That's what a ו vav by
default means. אצטריך, Itztrich, no, you need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka
dachach amina, I would have thought to say, top of צא עמוד
א, Tzadi Aleph Amud Aleph, הואיל וכתיב ומן הצאן, hove u'ksiv u'min
hatzon, כמאן דכתיב יחדיו דמי. k'man d'ksiv yachdav dami.
Since it has the extra ו, vav, it could have said אדם
כי יקריב מכם קרבן להשם מן הבהמה מן הבקר מן הבקר מן
הצאן. adam ki yakriv mikem korban l'hashem min habakar min habiheima min
habakar min hatzon.
It didn't need the extra ו. vav. I don't really understand that.
That wouldn't have been good grammar. But somehow that's what's being said
here. That extra ו vav is coming to actually mean and, not
or. It's as if it said יחדיו. yachdav. Fine. So somehow it
understands that that formulation in the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra would have
meant and, and that's why you needed the או O by the
נסכים nesachim to tell you it means or. Now we're going to
ask the same question in reverse to רבי יאשיה. Rabbi Yoshiya. ורבי
יאשיה דאמר אף על גב דלא כתיב יחדיו כמאן דכתיב יחדיו דמי.
U'Rebbi Yoshiya d'amar af al gav d'lo ksiv yachdav k'man d'ksiv yachdav
dami. Now רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya says that even when the תורה
Torah doesn't say יחדיו, yachdav, a normal ו vav is understood to
mean and. So for him a normal ו vav is understood to
mean and. How was he free to use the או O to
teach you something about birds? He should need it to teach you
that it doesn't have to be both cattle and sheep.
So לבעי קרא? libaei kra? Why doesn't he need a פסוק pasuk
to teach me that the ו vav in the beginning of ויקרא
Vayikra doesn't mean and, but means or? הא כתיב אם עולה קרבנו
מן הבקר, Ha ksiv im olah korbano min habakar, ואם מן הצאן
קרבנו. v'im min hatzon korbano.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, because if you keep on reading
after the opening פסוק, pasuk, מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן הצאן תקריבו
את קרבנכם, min habiheima min habakar u'min hatzon takrivu es korbanchem, then
the תורה Torah goes and spells out, if your עולה Olah comes
from a
בקר, bakar, אם עולה קרבנו מן הבקר, im olah korbano min habakar,
here's what you do. And it has a few פסוקים. psukim. And
then it says ואם מן הצאן קרבנו, v'im min hatzon korbano, and
if. It comes from the sheep, here's what you do. The reason
it separates it is because a sheep has the אליה, alya, the
fat tail. But he says obviously the ו vav in the opening
פסוק pasuk doesn't mean 'and' because then the Torah says, 'If it's
cattle, here's what you do. If it's sheep, here's what you do.'
Clearly it's one or the other. So since the ו vav there
doesn't mean 'and', I don't need the או o and the או
o I'm free to use to teach me not birds by the
נסכים. nesachim. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואידך, ve'idach, so that's a
really good point. So if that's true, why did Rabbi Yonasan need
the או o to tell you it means 'or'? It's clear. The
Torah says, 'If it's cattle, do this. If it's sheep, do that.'
איצטריך, itztrich, no, you still needed the open, you still need it
to separate those words in the opening פסוק. pasuk. Why? סלקא דעתך
אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would have thought to say הני מילי
במפרש. hani mili bemifareish.
If what the Torah is saying is it's giving you three options.
If you just say, 'I'm going to bring an עולה מן הבהמה',
olah min habiheima then it has to be מן הבקר ומן הצאן.
min habakar umin hatzon. It has to be both a cattle and
a sheep. And then it goes on to say, 'If you just
want to do cattle, you explicitly say, "I'm going to bring an
עולה olah from בקר," bakar, here's what you do.' ואם מן הצאן,
ve'im min hatzon, 'if you just want to do sheep and you
explicitly say I'm just doing sheep, here's what you do.' But I
still could have read the opening פסוק pasuk and the ו vav
to tell me that if you don't specify, it has to be
both. סלקא דעתך אמינא הני מילי במפרש, salka daitach amina hani mili
bemifareish, when does the Torah say 'if this, if that'? If you
explicitly say one or the other. אבל בסתם לייתיה מתרוייהו, aval bistsam
laysei mitruvayehu, but if you just said 'I'm going to bring a
בהמה, beheima, I'm going to bring an עולה', olah maybe you'd have
to bring both? קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, that's why he
needs it. Okay, so different ways to read those opening פסוקים. pesukim.
Do you need the או o to separate cattle and sheep as
different עולות olos or is the או o not needed for that
and free to teach you something about נסכים? nesachim? Now, the גמרא
Gemara continues: אמר מר, amar mar, תודה מנין? Toda minayin? Now, so
that was all a little bit of a digression back to the
discussion of when you bring נסכים. nesachim. So אמר מר, amar mar,
תודה מנין? Toda minayin? How do you know that you bring נסכים
nesachim even if it's a קרבן תודה? korban Toda? תלמוד לומר או
זבח. talmud lomar o zevach. He says עולה או זבח. olah o
zevach. So עולה olah is עולה, olah, זבח zevach is classically a
שלמים shelamim and the extra או o here is teaching you even
a תודה, Toda, which is a type of a שלמים. shelamim. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אטו תודה לאו זבח הוא? atu Toda lav
zevach hu? So why do you need the extra או?
זבח o zavach includes, should include שלמים shelamim and a תודה. Toda.
They were essentially a תודה Toda actually is like a subset of
a
שלמים. shelamim. איצטריך, itztrich, no, you need a special word to teach
you that נסכים nesachim come even with a תודה. Toda. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, I would have thought to say הואיל
ואיכא לחם בהדה לא תיבעי נסכים. ho'il ve'ika lechem bahada lo tibei
nesachim. This is actually a pretty good הוה אמינא. hava amina. The
Torah tells you by a תודה Toda you have to bring forty
loaves of bread. So it already tells you that there's something that
accompanies it. Conceptually the idea is you don't bring just the קרבן,
korban, just the meat, you bring it with accoutrements, but a תודה
Toda has its own accoutrements, maybe it doesn't get נסכים? nesachim? So
therefore the או o? teaches you it does.
ומאי שנא מאיל נזיר דאיכא בהדיה לחם ובעי נסכים? umai shna me'ayil
Nazir de'ika bahadei lechem uva'ei nesachim? So the גמרא Gemara says, 'Okay,
but
if that's true, we have why would I have thought that about
a תודה Toda if we have a case that proves that that
doesn't matter?' What's the case? The ram of a נזיר, Nazir, the
Torah's explicit that you bring bread with it, and we're going to
learn later, we haven't demonstrated it now, but we're going to learn
later that it also gets נסכים. nesachim. So that should prove to
me that even when bread comes with it, you still have נסכים,
nesachim, and I shouldn't need a special פסוק pasuk to teach me
that by תודה. Toda. So, no. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina,
that would not have necessarily proven it to me even if I
had known that thing by an איל של נזיר, ayil shel Nazir,
by the ram of the נזיר. Nazir. התם שני מינין, hasam shnei
minin,
that's only two types of bread that the Torah says to bring
with a נזיר. Nazir. הכא ארבעה מינין, hacha arba'ah minin, here we
know there are four different types of loaves that you bring. So
maybe again with all of this bread, forty loaves, four different types,
maybe no נסכים? nesachim? קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan,
that's why I needed the extra או o to tell me that
it applies even to a תודה. Toda. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: ולכתוב רחמנא לפלא נדר או בנדבה
ולא בעי עולה. velichtov rachmana lephale neder o bindava velo ba'ei olah.
So why do I need the Torah to specify עולה olah altogether?
Right? The פסוק pasuk opens that basically says if you're doing it
לפלא נדר או בנדבה, lephale neder o bindava, a נדר neder or
נדבה, nedava, which means a free-will sacrifice. So obviously that includes an
עולה. olah. That's a classic free-will sacrifice is an עולה. olah. So
what was the point the Torah had to add the word עולה?
olah? So let's take a look. ולכתוב רחמנא עולה, velichtov rachmana olah,
had it not specified עולה... olah... and just said when you bring
the נסכים, nesakhim, when it's נדר neder or נדבה, nidavah, הוה אמינא,
hava amina, I would have read the פסוקים pesukim this way. ועשיתם
אשה לה׳ כלל, Va'asitem isheh laHashem klal,
you bring a sacrifice, that's how the פסוק pasuk opens. לפלא נדר
או נדבה Lefala neder o nidavah for a נדר neder or נדבה
nidavah פרט. prat. Okay, and then לריח ניחוח, lere'ach nicho'ach, and but
the פסוק pasuk ends with לריח ניחוח lere'ach nicho'ach for a pleasing
odor. חזר וכלל, Chazar vekhlal, so I would have made a כלל
פרט וכלל. klal prat ukhlal. And what would I have inferred from
that? כלל פרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. Klal prat
ukhlal ee ata dan ela k'ein haprat. It would be similar to
the middle category of נדר neder and נדבה. nidavah. מה פרט מפורש
דבר שאינו בא על חטא, אף כל שאינו בא על חטא. Mah
prat meforash davar she'eino ba al chet, af kol she'eino ba al
chet. Okay, so that would have told me a נדר neder and
נדבה nidavah are not sin-related
and therefore it applies to all קרבנות korbanot that are not sin-related.
Okay, that's still getting us to what we know. עולה olah and
שלמים, shelamim, yes. חטאת chatat and אשם, asham, no. What's the problem?
Well, let's take a look. הוציא חטאת ואשם שהן באין על חטא.
Hotzi chatat ve'asham shehen ba'in al chet. Okay, but that would have
led me to exclude a חטאת chatat and an אשם, asham, which
are sin-related. But what would I have included? Anything not sin-related, which
would have meant אביא בכור מעשר ופסח שאין בהן חטא. Avi bekhor
ma'aser upesach she'ein bahen chet. I would have included בכור bekhor and
מעשר ma'aser and פסח. pesach. That's a logical thing to include. Okay,
it's even hard for us at this stage to understand exactly why
they're excluded. If you bring a normal עולה olah that's obligatory like
the תמיד, tamid, why shouldn't you bring it by בכור, מעשר, bechor,
maaser פסח? pesach? It has something to do with their distinct identity.
But okay, had it just, had it not said עולה olah and
just said נדר neder or נדבה, nidavah, I would have included even
בכור, bekhor, מעשר, ma'aser, and פסח pesach based on כלל פרט וכלל.
klal prat ukhlal. תלמוד לומר עולה. Talmud lomar olah. And
that's why it said עולה. olah. עולה Olah is to tell me
that something that is fundamentally, you know, comes as a free will.
That's true, there are עולות olot that come as obligatory, but an
עולה olah is a type of a קרבן korban that comes as
free will. בכור, bekhor, מעשר, ma'aser, and פסח pesach do not come
as free will. So it's an extra limiting word to make my,
you know, to make the scope not as wide. השתא דכתיב עולה
כלל פרט מאי מרבי? Hashta dekhtiv olah klal prat mai marbi? So
the גמרא Gemara says like, the תורה Torah says like this. Okay,
so now you have נדר, neder, נדבה, nidavah, and עולה olah and
those sort of play an expanding and a narrowing role and that
sort of gets you into like every case of like עולה olah
and שלמים shelamim and תודה. todah. So what are you doing with
your כלל פרט וכלל? klal prat ukhlal? What's that doing? How's that
expanding that category?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מה פרט מפורש שאינו מחוייב
ועומד, אף כל שאינו מחוייב ועומד. Mah prat meforash she'eino mechuyav ve'omed,
af kol she'eino mechuyav ve'omed. Here's what the כלל פרט klal prat
teaches you. It tells you anything that you don't all-, is not
already obligated. Okay, and therefore that would apply to other קרבנות korbanot
that you're not have a fundamental obligation for. Okay, but isn't that
what we've been saying like עולה olah and שלמים shelamim and תודה
todah yes, as opposed to חטאת, chatat, אשם, asham, בכור, Bekhor, מעשר,
ma'aser, פסח? pesach? What are you including? Here's what we're including. Okay,
we're including a derivative קדושה. kedushah. Let's take a look. להביא ולדות
קדשים ותמורתן ועולה הבאה מן המותרות. Lehavi veladot kodashim utmuratan ve'olah haba'ah
min hamotarot. A case of, you sanctified an animal and then it
gave birth, or you ex-, used tried to exchange one for another
and they're both קדוש, kadosh, okay, or you have extra
left over money from money given to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
you know, for the קרבנות korbanot and you bring an עולה olah
from that. In those cases it was not like proactively sanctifying an
animal, it was sort of derivative, and nevertheless they also get it
because they are also not obligatory. Okay, so, so נדר neder or
נדבה nidavah working together with עולה olah comes to teach you that
it's not just קרבנות korbanot that are not sin-related, it's also not
בכור, bekhor, מעשר, ma'aser, and
פסח pesach because those have are fundamental types of of קרבן korban
that are fundamentally about obligation. But the כלל פרט וכלל klal prat
ukhlal expands it to say even if it's not the initial thing
that was sanctified, even if it is some derivative thing like ולד
vlad or תמורה. tmurah. Okay, ואשם שניתק לרעיה, ve'asham sheinitak lere'iyah, or
another case is even something that started with a קדושה kedushah that
you would not bring a נסכים nesakhim for. You sanctified an אשם
asham and then, you know, you whatever got lost, you bought another
one, this one you had to let graze so it got a
מום mum and eventually this is going to be brought as an
עולה. olah. So there too it would actually get נסכים. nesakhim. Okay,
וכל הזבחים שנזבחו שלא לשמן, vechol hazvachim shenizbechu shelo lishman, a קרבן
korban that was שחט shechted not for the right sake of the
קרבן, korban, it's still כשר kasher but the owners don't fulfill their
obligation, so that also is a type of a derivative, it wasn't
sort of the קרבן korban that it was meant to be. Okay,
all those things you bring נסכים. nesakhim. Good. So now we've got
our category עולה, שלמים, תודה, olah, shlamim, todah, not. עולה, olah, שלמים,
shelamim, תודה, todah, not בכור, bekhor, מעשר, ma'aser, פסח. Pesach. עולה, Olah,
שלמים, Shelamim, תודה, Todah, yes, even if it's an obligation, and also
things that are like derivative קדושה kedusha that wind up being in
the עולה, Olah, שלמים, Shelamim, תודה Todah, category.
Okay, והשתא דאמרת, V'hashta d'amarta, או
לדרשה, o l'drasha, לפלא נדר או לנדבה, l'faleh neder o l'nedavah, למה
לי? lama lee? Now that we're using או o for a דרשה,
drasha, right, where it said like או זבח o zavach, and the
או o teaches you even a תודה, Todah even though it has
accompanying bread, okay, what do you do with the או o when
it says נדר או לנדבה, neder o l'nedavah, that extra או? o
לחלק, L'chaleik, to split, to divide them, like we were a little
bit like we were saying before.
לחלק. L'chaleik. איצטריך.
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Itzterich salka daatach amina, I would have thought, אי
דמייתי נדר ונדבה, ee d'maiti neder un'davah, this sort of gets us
back to the רבי נתן, Rabi Natan, רבי יאשיה, Rabi Yoshiya, had
it just said לפלא נדר
ונדבה, l'faleh neder un'davah, ולנדבה, ul'nedavah, not או לנדבה, o l'nedavah, I
would have said maybe you only bring נסכים nesachim if you're bringing
both a נדר neder and a נדבה nedavah together.
עד דמייתי נדר ונדבה לא ליבעי נסכים. Ad d'maiti neder un'davah lo
libaei nesachim. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, דאי אייתי נדר לחוד
ליבעי נסכים ואי אייתי נדבה לחוד ליבעי נסכים, d'ee aiti neder l'chud
libaei nesachim v'ee aiti nedavah l'chud libaei nesachim, even if you bring
just a נדר neder by itself, even if you bring just a
נדבה nedavah by itself, either one by itself. So the simple function
of the word או. o? So now the גמרא Gemara ties it
back to the רבי יאשיה Rabi Yoshiya and the רבי נתן. Rabi
Natan. הניחא לרבי יאשיה, Ha nicha l'Rabi Yoshiya, that's good for רבי
יאשיה Rabi Yoshiya that says that a ו vav normally means "and".
אלא לרבי יונתן למה לי? Ella l'Rabi Yonatan lama lee? For רבי
יונתן Rabi Yonatan that a ו vav normally means "or", so I
don't need the או o. to tell me "or", that's what the
ו vav could do. So what do I need the או o
for?
סלקא דעתך אמינא, Sal'ka dach'ta amina, אייתי נדר לחוד ליבעי נסכים, אייתי
נדבה לחוד ליבעי נסכים. aiti neder l'chud libaei nesachim, aiti nedavah l'chud
libaei nesachim. Maybe fine, without the או, o I would have said
by a נדר neder itself you bring נסכים, nesachim, נדבה nedavah itself
you bring a נסכים. nesachim. But, אייתי נדר ונדבה תסגי ליה בנסכים
דחד. aiti neder un'davah tisgi leih b'nesachim d'chad. The ו vav could
mean "or" and it could mean "and". I would have read the
פסוק pasuk without an explicit או, o, I would have read it,
if it just said לפלא נדר ולנדבה, l'faleh neder ul'nedavah, I would
have said if you bring just a נדר neder you bring נסכים,
nesachim, just a נדבה, nedavah, and I'll also read it as an
"and" as well. If you bring a נדר neder and a נדבה
nedavah you bring נסכים, nesachim, but maybe only one נסכים, nesachim, maybe
you group them together, because I could have read the ו vav
as an "and" as well. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. קא
משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. So therefore it's teaching me the או,
o, no, they're totally separate and if one per and if you
bring them together then you have to bring two, you still have
to bring one per. קא משמע לן. Ka mashma lan. Okay, now
או במועדיכם, o b'moadeichem, now again we're focusing on the אוs. o,
Okay. What does it have to tell me? או במועדיכם. O b'moadeichem.
במועדיכם B'moadeichem told me you're even going to bring an עולה Olah,
that's an obligation like you bring during the חג. chag. But what
does the או o teach me? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Sal'ka dach'ta amina,
הני מילי דקא מייתי עולה בנדר ושלמים בנדבה אי נמי איפכא. hani
mili d'ka maiti olah b'neder v'shelamim b'nedavah ee nami ipcha. Okay,
fine. When do you bring separate נסכים nesachim if you bring a
נדר neder and a נדבה? nedavah? If there's something else if it's
hard to categorize to put them in the same category. For example,
okay, you did, you know, you brought an עולה, olah they were
different types of קורבנות. korbanot. An עולה olah, was your נדר neder
and a שלמים Shelamim, was נדבה, nedavah, or the reverse. So that
doesn't let you make them a category. They're not the same thing,
they're fundamentally each one is its own thing. אבל היכא דקא מייתי
עולה ושלמים בנדר אי נמי עולה ושלמים בנדבה. Aval heicha d'ka maiti
olah v'shelamim b'neder ee nami olah v'shelamim b'nedavah. However,
if there were some type of a thing, it's like that game
Sets, you know, are they the same based on number, based on
color, based on shape? If there were something that let me categorize
them together, yes, it was an עולה olah and a שלמים, shelamim
but if they were both a נדר neder or they were both
a נדבה, nedavah, then I would have said שם נדר אחד ושם
נדבה אחת היא, shem neder echad v'shem nedavah achat hee, that the
fact that I have two נדרים nedarim here or two נדבות, nedavot,
that would have allowed me to group them together ותסגי ליה בנסכים
דחד v'tisgi leih b'nesachim d'chad
and then maybe again one set of נסכים nesachim would suffice because
I have a group here. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, או
במועדיכם. o b'moadeichem. The או o teaches me, again assuming that I
already know from a ו vav that ו vav means "or", so
the extra או o teaches me here everything is its separate thing,
you don't get to group them together even if there are some
ways you would want to group them together.
Okay, we're not done, still more אוs. o וכי תעשה בן בקר
עולה או זבח, V'chi taaseh ven bakar olah o zavach, למה לי?
lama lee? Why do you need the או זבח, o zavach עולה
או
זבח?
olah o
zavach? איצטריך, Itztirich. you need it. Again, we're still in the same
theme here of ways I would have wanted to group it together
and it's going to tell me you're not allowed to group it
together. Okay. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Sal'ka dach'ta amina,
I would have thought הני מילי היכא דקא מייתי עולה ושלמים בנדר
אי נמי עולה ושלמים בנדבה. hani mili heicha d'ka maiti olah v'shelamim
b'neder ee nami olah v'shelamim b'nedavah. Fine.
When can you not group them together even if they're both נדר,
neder, both נדבה? nedavah? If they're different, one is an עולה olah
and one is a שלמים. shelamim, או היכא דקמייתי שתי עולות חדא
בנדר וחדא בנדבה, O heicha dekamaisei shtei olot chada bineder vechada binedavah,
but
let's say the way they're groupable is not based on נדר neder
נדבה nedavah but on the more logical thing to group them, the
base of קרבן. korban. You have two עולות, olot, one's a נדר
neder one's a נדבה, nedavah, but they're both עולות. olot. אי נמי
שני שלמים Ee nami shenei shelamim or it's two שלמים, shelamim. אחד
בנדר ואחד בנדבה. echad bineder veechad binedavah. אימא שם שלמים אחת היא
שם עולה אחת היא. Eima shem shelamim achat hee shem olah achat
hee.
So if you have two עולות olot or two שלמים, shelamim, maybe
there you genuinely can group them together and והזקיקו לנסכים דחד vehizkiko
lenisachim dechad bring only one set of נסכים. nisachim. קמ"ל Kamashma lan
it teaches you לפלא נדר או lepale neder o קמ"ל. kamashma lan.
It teaches you not that way, okay. בן בקר או זבח Ben
bakar o zavach is teaching you, nope, each one separate, you're not
allowed to group. You can see the גמרא Gemara is staging itself,
right, it's doing this gradually to teach you why you need every
או. o The first one is telling me you don't get to
group them if they're the same based on נדר neder and נדבה.
nedavah. The second one is telling me you don't get to group
them even if they're two עולות, olot, two שלמים. shelamim, Now we're
going to have a third או o. and that's going to tell
me even if they're the same both in terms of the type
of קרבן korban and in terms of the נדר neder and נדבה.
nedavah. לפלא נדר או שלמים למה לי? Lepale neder o shelamim lama
lee? Why do you need the או o for the שלמים? shelamim.
איצטריך Itztirich, סלקא דעתך אמינא, Sal'ka dach'ta amina, I would have thought
הני מילי היכא דקמייתי שתי עולות חדא בנדר וחדא בנדבה. hani mili
heicha dekamaisei shtei olot chada bineder vechada binedavah. When can you not
group them if they're two עולות olot but they're still different, that
one is a נדר neder one is a נדבה. nedavah. אי נמי
שני שלמים חדא בנדר וחדא בנדבה Ee nami shenei shelamim chada bineder
vechada binedavah or they're the same that they're both שלמים shelamim? but
they're different that one is a נדר neder one is a נדבה.
nedavah. אבל היכא דקמייתי שתי עולות בנדר ושתי עולות בנדבה, Aval heicha
dekamaisei shtei olot bineder veshtei olot binedavah, אי נמי שני שלמים בנדר
ושני שלמים בנדבה, ee nami shenei shelamim bineder veshenei shelamim binedavah, שם
עולה אחד הוא ושם נדר אחד הוא shem olah echad hu veshem
neder echad hu והזקיקו לנסכים דחד vehizkiko lenisachim dechad קמ"ל. kamashma lan.
But I would have thought that if both of them were עולה
olah and they were both נדר neder or both were עולה olah
both נדבה nedavah or both שלמים shelamim both נדר neder or both
שלמים shelamim both נדבה. nedavah. If they were totally the same based
on the type of קרבן korban and the נדר neder נדבה, nedavah,
I would have thought under that circumstance that there ממש mamash you
can group them together and bring only one set of נסכים. nisachim.
So the extra או o tells me you can't. Okay, so that
was a whole big thing to tell me what do I need
all these אוs o for, assuming a ו vav anyway would have
meant or, and it's to tell me you don't get to group
them together, you always have to bring a separate נסכים nisachim for
each קרבן. korban. Fine.
So now we're not done. רבי אושיא, Rabbi Oshaiya, רבי אושיא Rabbi
Oshaiya who remember read the פסוק pasuk מן הבקר ומן הצאן. min
habakar umin hatzon. רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan said you needed the או
o to tell me that an עולה olah could be either בקר
bakar or צאן. tzon. But רבי אושיא Rabbi Oshaiya said no, no,
no, we already know it could be one or the other and
מן הבקר ומן הצאן min habakar umin hatzon comes to teach me
no birds. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is saying האי מן
הבקר ומן הצאן למה לי? hai min habakar umin hatzon lama lee?
Why do you need it? Now what do you mean why do
you need it? We said before he needed it to tell me
no birds. But the גמרא Gemara now understands that it could have
said מן הבקר ומן הצאן min habakar umin hatzon and that would
have told me no birds. And now we're focusing on the word
או. o So according to רבי אושיא, Rabbi Oshaiya, why do you
need the word או? o. What does the word או o? teach
you?
סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daatach amina, I would have thought הני מילי
בתרי מיני. hani mili bitrei minei. When is it that you can't
group them together even if they're both עולות olot and they're both,
you know, and they're both a נדר, neder, that's if maybe there's
still some point of difference, one is a cattle and one is
a sheep. אבל בחד מינא והזקיקו לנסכים דחד, Aval bechad mina vehizkiko
lenisachim dechad, but maybe if it is all cattle or all sheep,
maybe in that case one set of נסכים nisachim would be enough.
קמ"ל, Kamashma lan, so the final extra או o here is teaching
you no matter how many ways they're similar, each thing gets its
own נסכים. nisachim. Fine. Okay, ככה תעשה לאחד למה
לי? Kacha taaseh leechad lama lee? So at the end after the
תורה Torah introduces the bringing of the נסכים nisachim with the פסוקים
pesukim that we've been dealing with, עולה וזבח לפלא נדר או בנדבה
או במועדיכם לעשות ריח ניחוח לה' מן הבקר או מן הצאן. Olah
vezavach lepale neder o bindavah o bemoadeichem laasot reiach nichoach l'Adonai min
habakar o min hatzon. Those are the words we've been dealing with
which teach us the scope. And then it speaks about all the
specifics that you bring for the נסכים. nisachim. And then it wraps
it up and it says ככה יעשה לשור האחד או לאיל האחד
או לשה בכבשים או בעזים. Kacha yeaseh lashor haechad o laayil haechad
o laseh bakvasim o baizim. So we want to now understand what
that פסוק pasuk is coming to add that we haven't already said.
ככה תעשו לאחד למה לי? Kacha taasoo leechad lama lee? What is
that coming to teach me? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka daatach amina, I
would have thought הני מילי בזה אחר זה. hani mili bezeh achar
zeh. Maybe we're still not done with what we were saying, right.
Maybe when is it that you can't group them together and just
bring one if you bring them sequentially? אבל בבת אחת, Aval bevas
achat, if you bring them all at the same time, in that
case והזקיקו לנסכים דחד. vehizkiko lenisachim dechad. maybe finally in that case
you can just get away with one, קא משמע לן, ka mashma
lan, it's saying no, each one gets its own, end of story.
Okay, כך תעשו לאחד כמספרם, kach taasu leachad kemisparam,
that's actually the next פסוק. pasuk. כמספר אשר תעשו כך תעשו לאחד
כמספרם. kemispar asher taasu kach taasu leachad kemisparam. Now however, actually it's
pretty explicit what the פסוק pasuk is saying, however many you bring,
כך תעשו לאחד כמספרם. kach taasu leachad kemisparam. For each one they
get this, you do not get to group them together. All right,
that was the end of all of that דרשות drashot of those
פסוקים psukim to teach you each one gets it separately. Okay, אלא,
Ella, now we're moving on to the second part of the משנה.
mishna. אלא שחטאתו של מצורע ואשמו טעונים נסכים. Ella shechataso shel metzora
vashamo teunim nesachim. The one exception to this is the חטאת chatas
and the אשם asham of a מצורע. metzora. Even though those are
חטאת chatas and אשם, asham, there actually you do bring נסכים. nesachim.
So the גמרא gemara asks the obvious question: מנא הני מילי? Minani
milei? Where do you know this from? It's such an exception to
the rule. דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan, we
taught: שלשה עשרונים סלת מנחה. Sheloshah esronim soles mincha. So here's what
it says by the מצורע. metzora. So this is the beginning of
פרשת מצורע Parshat Metzora and it's on the eighth day of his
purification process. And it says like this, this is פרק יד פסוק
י perek yud dalet pasuk yud in
ויקרא: Vayikra: וביום השמיני יקח שני כבשים תמימים וכבשה אחת בת שנתה
תמימה.
Uvayom hashmini yikach shnei kevasim temimim vechivsa achas
bas shenata temima. Okay, so two male sheep and one ewe.
ושלשה עשרונים סלת מנחה בלולה בשמן ולוג אחד שמן. ushloshah esronim soles
mincha belula vashemen velog echad shamen. And then one of the אשמים
ashamim are, one of the sheep is an
אשם asham and then you use that one with the oil to
do this whole purification process. And then the other sheep, one is
an עולה olah and one is a חטאת. chatas. So that's what
you do with them. Those are the three different sheep, two male,
one female. But then it says, שלשה עשרונים סלת מנחה בלולה בשמן.
Sheloshah esronim soles mincha belula vashemen. Three עשרונים esronim of סלת soles
mixed with oil. So what is that? It calls it מנחה. mincha.
It says מנחה בלולה בשמן. mincha belula vashemen. So you could have
just thought it's the special מנחה mincha of three עשרונים esronim special
to the מצורע. metzora. Or you could say there are three sheep,
each sheep for a מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim gets an עשרון issaron
of flour. So maybe this is just saying these are the three
מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim that come with these animals, with the אשם,
asham, the חטאת, chatas, and the עולה. olah Not very clear in
the
פסוקים. psukim. When it actually talks about offering it up, it says
והעלה הכהן, Veheela hakohen, after it speaks about the whole אשם. asham.
It says ועשה הכהן את החטאת וכפר על המטהר מטומאתו ואחר ישחט
את העלה והעלה הכהן את העלה ואת המנחה המזבחה וכפר עליו הכהן
וטהר. veasah hakohen es hachatas vechiper al mitehar mitumato veachar yishchat es
haolah veheela hakohen es haolah vees hamincha hamizbeacha vechiper alav hakohen vetaher.
So you bring the אשם, asham, then you bring the חטאת, chatas,
and it says you bring the עולה olah. and the מנחה. mincha.
So I got to admit that פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim
is that this is not מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, right? It's not
like an עשרון issaron for the אשם, asham, an עשרון issaron for
the חטאת, chatas, an עשרון issaron for the עולה. olah It's like
after you bring the אשם, asham, the חטאת, chatas, and the עולה,
olah. you bring the מנחה. mincha. But that's not how the גמרא
gemara understands it. It understands that this is the מנחת נסכים minchas
nesachim of these קרבנות. korbanot. Okay, so let's take a look. מנא
הני מילי? Minani milei? דתנו רבנן: Detanu rabanan: שלשה עשרונים סלת מנחה.
Sheloshah esronim soles mincha. במנחה
באה עם הזבח הכתוב מדבר.
Bemincha ba'a
im hazevach hakatuv medaber. This is talking about the מנחת נסכים minchas
nesachim that comes with a normal קרבן, korban, except here it's also
coming with an אשם asham and a חטאת. chatas. אתה אומר במנחה
באה עם הזבח או אינו אלא במנחה באה בפני עצמה? Ata omer
bemincha ba'a im hazevach o eino ela bemincha ba'a bifnei atzma? You're
saying that it's the מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, or maybe it's talking
about it as a special obligation of a stand-alone מנחה? mincha?
כשהוא אומר, Keshehu omer, when it says והעלה הכהן את העלה ואאת
המנחה, veheela hakohen es haolah ve'et hamincha, הוי
אומר במנחה באה עם הזבח הכתוב מדבר. havei omer bemincha ba'a im
hazevach hakatuv medaber. When it says את העלה ואת המנחה, et haolah
ve'et hamincha, the way it sort of juxtaposes them and bundles it
together, clearly it's talking about a מנחה mincha that is coming together
with the עולה. olah, Now I might have said that if there
was only, if it was just that one עשרון, issaron, but that
מנחה mincha represents all three עשרונות, esronos, and that's only being bundled
together with the עולה, olah. not each one with its appropriate קרבן.
korban. But nevertheless the גמרא's gemara reading, עולה ואת המנחה olah ve'et
hamincha tells me it is the מנחה mincha that comes with the
קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay. ועדיין אני אומר, Veadayin ani omer, but I still would have
said, איני יודע אם
טעונה נסכים אם לאו. eini yodea im teuna nesachim im lav. That's
the מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, that's the מנחה mincha that comes with
the קרבן. korban. Where maybe I don't think since this is an
exception, certainly the אשם asham and the חטאת, chatas, where do I
know that you would also bring the wine that normally comes with
a קרבן? korban? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ויין לנסך רביעית ההין תעשה
על העלה או לזבח לכבש האחד. Veyayin lanesach reviis hahin taaseh al
haolah o lazavach lakeves haechad. Okay, so that's going back to the
פרשה parsha by נסכים nesachim where it says you speak about the
מנחה mincha you bring with the קרבן, korban, the wine you bring
with the קרבן, korban, and it
says ויין לנסך תעשה על העלה או לזבח לכבש האחד. veyayin lanesach
taaseh al haolah o lazavach lakeves haechad. עולה זו עולת מצורע. Olah
zo olas metzora. So the, this is seen as like an extra
פסוק, pasuk, okay, and and the extra words עולה olah, and זבח
zevach is telling me things that I would not have normally expected
there to be bringing the wine for. So the עולה olah is
the עולה olah of the מצורע. metzora. Now, I don't necessarily need
a פסוק pasuk for that so much, because that's just an עולה,
olah but okay, it's an obligatory עולה, olah, so maybe that's why
you need it. זבח זו חטאת מצורע. Zevach zu chatas metzora. זבח
zavach is the חטאת. chatas. Again, funny, the word זבח Zevach normally
doesn't apply to a חטאת. chatas. או לזבח זו אשם מצורע. O
lazavach zu asham metzora. Okay, so we're going to use that extra
פסוק pasuk to tell me מצורע. metzora. Now, nothing in the פסוק
pasuk that indicates that per se, but once we are asserting that
the קרבנות korbanot of the מצורע metzora get the מנחת נסכים, minchas
nesachim, we're going to read that they also get the נסכים nesachim
as well. ותיפוק ליה תרוייהו מזבח. Vesipuk lei tarvaihu mizevach.
Why not say that the word זבח zevach is... means חטאת chatas
and an אשם? asham? Both of them are slaughtered קרבנות. korbanot. And
if it's generic enough to not be limited to שלמים, shelamim why
shouldn't I just include both of them? Why did I need the
extra או? o דאמר מר, De'amar mar, top of צדי א עמוד
ב, tzadi aleph amud beis, חטאת ואשם מנין תלמוד לומר זבח. Chatas
ve'asham minayin talmud lomar zevach. Because
by the case of a נזיר, nazir, the תורה Torah tells me
that you take the hair of the נזיר nazir and you put
it under the pot in which is cooking the זבח השלמים. zevach
hashelamim.
And we teach there that it doesn't only have... it would only
apply to the שלמים, shelamim, it would also apply to the חטאת
chatas and the אשם asham of a נזיר. nazir. Don't get confused,
that's a נזיר, nazir, we're talking about מצורע. metzora. And we say
that the word זבח zavach there refers to the חטאת chatas and
the אשם asham as well. So why not say here as well
זבח zevach refers to both? Why did you need the extra או?
o? הני מילי היכא דתרוייהו כי הדדי נינהו. Hani mili heicha ditarvaihu
ki hadadi ninhu.
Fine, that's over there
by the נזיר, nazir, that they're both sort of doing the same
thing.
Because both of them
are basically restarting, that was when the נזיר nazir became טמא, tamei,
and they're both functioning to restart him as a נזיר בטהרה. nazir
betahara.
Excuse me, I got that wrong. Those are both coming when the
נזירות nezirot is ending, and both of those coming to sort of
end the נזירות nezirot and get him back into a non-נזיר nazir
state. Okay, so there the אשם asham and the חטאת chatas are
both coming to transition the נזיר nazir state. So the word זבח
zevach includes both. אבל היכא דאשם להכשיר, Aval heicha de'asham lehachshir, but
in our case of the מצורע, metzora, the אשם asham is clearly
part of the purification, because the תורה Torah says you take the
blood of the אשם asham and you take the oil and you
put it on his ear and you do this and so on.
So that's coming for a purification process. וחטאת לכפר, Vechatas lechaper, and
the חטאת chatas is completely separate, that's just a
כפרה. kapara. בעינן תרי קראי. Be'inan terei krei. All right, so once
more to repeat,
the מנחה mincha mentioned by the purification of the מצורע metzora is
understood to be the מנחת נסכים minchas nesachim that came with all
of the three קרבנות, korbanot, including the חטאת chatas and the אשם,
asham, based on a פסוק עולה או זבח pasuk olah o zavach
by the נסכים nesachim itself, the wine itself, we're also going to
include the חטאת chatas and the אשם asham by a מצורע metzora
to require the wine as well. And we need a separate או
o? זבח zevach to tell me, because each one does a separate
function. The אשם asham is used for purification and the חטאת chatas
is for כפרה, kapara, and it's telling me both of those get
the wine the same way both of them get the מנחה. mincha.
Okay. בעינן תרי קראי. Be'inan terei krei. זבח זו חטאת מצורע. Zevach
zu chatas metzora.
So now we're going to say, okay, how do we get that
out of the פסוק? pasuk זבח Zevach refers to the חטאת chatas
of the מצורע. metzora. ואימא זו חטאת ואשם דנזיר. Ve'eima zu chatas
ve'asham denazir. So why are you saying that the thing that requires
the wine is the חטאת chatas and the אשם asham of the
מצורע metzora based on the פסוק pasuk? עולה או זבח olah o
zavach by the wine? Why not say it's the חטאת chatas and
the אשם asham of the נזיר? nazir? Now, the obvious answer is
because we already know the מצורע metzora gets the מנחה mincha of
the נסכים, nesachim, so it would make sense to say they also
get the wine of their נסכים. nesachim. But let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. לא סלקא דעתך. Lo salka da'atach. That doesn't make
sense. דתניא. Detanya. ומנחתם ונסכיהם. Uminchasam veniskeihem. Their מנחה mincha and their
נסכים. nesachim.
So by the נזיר nazir where he actually is ending his נזירות,
nezirot, the פסוק pasuk says the following. It says, this is in
במדבר ו, Bamidbar vav, and it says like this: והקריב קרבנו להשם
כבש בן שנתו תמים אחד לעולה וכבשה אחת בת שנתה תמימה לחטאת
ואיל אחד תמים לשלמים.
Vehikriv korbano l’Hashem keves ben shenato tamim
echad l’olah vechivsa achas bas shenasa temima lechatas ve’ayil echad tamim leshelamim.
Okay,
so you bring an עולה olah, and a חטאת chatas and a
שלמים. shelamim, And then it says, וסל מצות סלת חלות בלולות בשמן
ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן ומנחתם ונסכיהם. vesal matzos soles chalos belulos bashemen
urkikei matzos meshuchim bashemen uminchasam veniskeihem. Their מנחה mincha and their נסכים.
nesachim. So
there are two things here that... normally would get מנחה Mincha and
נסכים, Nesachim, and that would be the שלמים shelamim. and the עולה.
olah So we're going to read it like this: דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in the ברייתא, Braita, ומנחתם ונסכיהם, U'minchatam v'niskihem, their מנחה Mincha
ונסכים Nesachim בעולתו ובשלמיו הכתוב מדבר. B'olato u'v'shlamav hakatuv m'daber.
It's the עולה Olah. and the שלמים Shelamim of the נזיר, Nazir,
those get as a normal עולה Olah and שלמים Shelamim would get
מנחה Mincha and נסכים. Nesachim. אתה אומר בעולה ובשלמים Ata omer b'olah
u'v'shlamim or maybe even by the חטאת? Chatat? One minute, a חטאת
Chatat is also mentioned in that פסוק. Pasuk. Maybe the חטאת Chatat
of a נזיר Nazir gets נסכים Nesachim as well? תלמוד לומר Talmud
lomar ואת האיל יעשה זבח שלמים V'et ha'ayil ya'aseh zevach shlamim the
Gemara's פסוק Pasuk as it continues says, you should a ram make
a זבח שלמים Zevach Shlamim ומנחתו ונסכו u'minchato v'nisko and its מנחה
Mincha and its נסך. Nesach.
איל בכלל היה. Ayil bichlal haya. We already included ומנחתם ונסכיהם. U'minchatam
v'niskihem. We knew that the שלמים Shelamim was going to get a
מנחה Mincha נסכים. Nesachim. ולמה יצא, V'lama yatza, so why when the
תורה Torah then mentions the שלמים Shelamim and the איל Ayil specifically,
does it again repeat עולה Olah and
שלמים? Shelamim Why does it again repeat מנחה Mincha and נסכים? Nesachim?
להקיש אליו, L'hakish elav, מה איל מיוחד הבא בנדר ונדבה אף כל
הבא בנדר ונדבה. mah ayil meyuchad haba b'neder u'nedavah af kol haba
b'neder u'nedavah. Okay, so to tell you no, we're only talking here
by the נזיר Nazir about those קרבנות Korbanot that normally come free-will.
An עולה Olah and שלמים Shelamim? yes, a חטאת Chatat no. Okay,
so what basically what have we said? The question is how do
we know that extra פסוק Pasuk about the wine by you know
that says עולה או זבח Olah o zevach is coming to teach
me to bring it by the מצורע Metzora קרבנות? Korbanot? Maybe it's
coming to teach me to bring it by the נזיר Nazir קרבנות,
Korbanot, the one, the חטאת Chatat of the נזיר? Nazir? And the
answer is no, we have a specific פסוק פסוקים Pasuk psukim by
the נזיר Nazir that tells me ומנחתם ונסכיהם U'minchatam v'niskihem and then
repeats it by the שלמים Shelamim ומנחתו ונסכו U'minchato v'nisko to tell
me by the נזיר Nazir it only goes by the classic עולה
Olah and שלמים Shelamim and not by the חטאת. Chatat. So if
I still have an extra פסוק Pasuk to teach me that a
חטאת Chatat is going to get נסכים, Nesachim, I'm going to apply
it to the חטאת Chatat of the מצורע. Metzora. Okay, very good.
So now it says like this: זו Zu
okay, עולה זו עולת מצורע. Olah zu olat Metzora. Okay, the עולה
Olah tells you that the עולה Olah of a מצורע Metzora gets
it as well. Now not so clear why you needed that, but
maybe because it's an obligatory עולה, Olah so that's what it's telling
you. ואימא זו עולת יולדת? V'eima zu olat yoledet? So maybe it
tells my- I should be talking me- telling me a יולדת Yoledet
needs the wine and not the מצורע? Metzora?
Now the reality is that an עולה Olah, of a יולדת Yoledet
does get it, cause the general rule is that all עולות Olot
get נסכים Nesachim whether they're ob- whether they're free-will or obligatory. But
what is making you read this עולה Olah here to be the
עולה Olah of the נזיר Nazir and to- excuse me- of the
מצורע Metzora and to tell me that type of obligatory עולה Olah
gets it? Maybe it should be telling me the עולה Olah of
a יולדת? Yoledet? So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says, עולת
יולדת מסיפא דקרא נפקא, Olat yoledet misayfa d'kra nafka, that you get
from the end of the פסוק. Pasuk. דתניא רבי נתן אומר,
Detanya Rabbi Natan
omer, לכבש זו עולת יולדת. L'cheves zu olat yoledet. Okay, cause then
it- it again says you know this is what you should do
לכבש האחד. L'cheves ha'echad. So לכבש L'cheves is to tell you the
עולה Olah of a יולדת. Yoledet. האחד, Ha'echad, זה אחד עשר של
מעשר שקרב שלמים zeh achad asar shel ma'aser shekarav shlamim and by
the way, here's another thing we're going to include, the eleventh of
a מעשר. Maaser, You are counting the animals of the newborn animals
and the tenth one is מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser behemah, and then accidentally
you said ten again by the eleventh. And the הלכה Halacha is
that that also gets קדוש Kadosh and that's brought as a שלמים.
Shelamim Okay, and that's a real חידוש Chidush that you're going to
bring the נסכים Nesachim with that. Why? שלא מצינו לה בכל התורה
שתהא טפל חמור מן העיקר. Shelo matzinu lah b'chol ha'torah she'tehe tafel
chamur min ha'ikar. Here's something derivative is more strict than the thing
itself. Why is that? The thing itself is the מעשר, Ma'aser. מעשר
Ma'aser, doesn't get נסכים. Nesachim. This thing that was an accidental מעשר
Ma'aser but now is brought as a שלמים Shelamim. does get נסכים.
Nesachim. I should tell you it's not the only thing, you know,
you have other cases before, you had an אשם Asham that became
an עולה Olah that would get the נסכים. Nesachim. You would have
a פסח שלא בזמנו Pesach shelo b'zimano that would be a שלמים
Shelamim that would get נסכים. Nesachim. But okay, that whole category of
things. All right, so that's what we do with the פסוק. Pasuk.
שלא מצינו בכל התורה שתהא טפל חמור מן העיקר. Shelo matzinu b'chol
ha'torah she'tehe tafel chamur min ha'ikar. Fine. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא
Rava says no, איזה דבר שצריך שלשה ריבויים הוי אומר זו מצורע.
Eizeh davar shetzarich shlosha ribuyim hevei omer zu metzora. רבא Rava says
the easiest answer. Okay, from this פסוק Pasuk right where it said
basically עולה או זבח, Olah o zevach, you are- three things, well
there's a מצורע Metzora that has three animals and that's already a
חידוש Chidush that all of them are getting נסכים Nesachim even though
there's an אשם Asham and a חטאת, Chatat, all of them are
getting מנחת נסכים. Minchat Nesachim. So this פסוק Pasuk that has three
things, עולה או זבח, Olah o zevach, it makes sense to apply
it to the מצורע Metzora and not to go look for other
things to apply it to. All right, so a lot, a lot
of פסוקים Psukim here, but basically to teach me that you get
it by a מצורע Metzora gets- gets the- when the תורה Torah
says שלשה עשרונים shlosha esronim by a מצורע, Metzora, it means for
each of the קרבנות, Korbanot, this is the מנחת נסכים, Minchat Nesachim,
and then that's even by the אשם asham and the חטאת chatas
and by this extra פסוק posuk we say and therefore also the
wine as well would apply. In the interim we understand that that's
not true by a נזיר, nazir, נזיר nazir goes by the normal
rules, only the עולה Olah and the שלמים, Shelamim and we also
find out that obligatory עולות, olos, like the עולת יולדת olas yoledes
and derivative things, even like a derivative of a מעשר, Ma'aser also
get נסכים. nesachim.
All right, לאיל למה לי? la'ayil lama li? Oy, we're still not
done. Okay, so we have the פסוק posuk says לאיל, la'ayil, what
is that teaching me? אמר רב ששת, לרבות אלו של אהרן amar
Rav Sheshes lerabos elu shel Aharon. to tell me even the ram
of
אהרן, Aharon, the ram that אהרן Aharon would bring on יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, his obligatory ram, that'll be איל אחד לעולה, ayil echad
l'olah,
again,
that's another case of an איל ayil that's obligatory, of an עולה
olah that's obligatory,
and somehow you would need this extra פסוק לאיל posuk la'ayil where
it says או לאיל תעשה מנחה. o la'ayil ta'aseh mincha.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, finally the גמרא Gemara says we
already know that basic idea. אמר רב ששת amar Rav Sheshes, לרבות
אלו של אהרן. lerabos elu shel Aharon So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלו של אהרן במועדיכם נפקא. elu shel Aharon b'moadeichem nafka. Not only
is it obligatory, it's an obligation for a specific מועד moed for
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so that's based on the פסוק במועדיכם. posuk
b'moadeichem.
So really why do we need an extra פסוק posuk to tell
it to me by אהרן? Aharon? No, סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach
amina, I would have thought הני מילי דציבור, hani milei d'tzibur, when
is a מועד moed obligatory קרבן korban get נסכים nesachim when it's
for communal. אבל דיחיד לא, aval d'yachid lo, maybe by a יחיד
yachid no, so it has to tell me yes, even a יחיד.
yachid. ומאי שנא? u'mai shna?
Now the גמרא Gemara is going to say but one minute, we
just got through talking about obligatory עולות olos that bring it even
if they're not יום טוב Yom Tov related. ומאי שנא
מעולת יולדת? u'mai shna m'olas yoledes? If an עולת יולדת olas yoledes
brings, that's obligatory, that's personal, so why should אהרן's Aharon עולה olah
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur be any different? סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka
da'atach amina, I would have thought הני מילי דבר שאין קבוע לו
זמן.
hani milei davar she'ein kavua lo
zman. Fine,
even though it's an עולת יולדת, olas yoledes, even though it's obligatory,
it's not fixed as a time. So there's something somewhat still similar
to the נדר neder or נדבה nedavah that could be brought at
any time. אבל דבר שקבוע לו זמן, aval davar she'kavua lo zman,
something that has a fixed time, so it's like an obligation, maybe
again and maybe that would not fall into either the category of
במועדיכם b'moadeichem or the category of עולת יולדת, olas yoledes, maybe that
wouldn't get נסכים? nesachim? אימא לא, קא משמע לן. eima lo, ka
mashma lan.
Fine. So now we're getting again, but the general principles are the
same, pretty much any עולה, olah שלמים, shlamim, תודה, Todah, even obligatory,
nothing חטאת chatas and אשם asham except the one case by the
טהרה tahara of a
מצורע metzora and not בכור, Bechor, מעשר maaser, and פסח, pesach, but
yes their derivatives which are treated more like שלמים. shlamim. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, או לאיל למה לי? o la'ayil lama li?
We're still not done. Okay, how about the fact it says או
לאיל תעשה מנחה, o la'ayil ta'aseh mincha, what does the extra או
o teach me? לרבות את הפלגס lerabos es ha-palgas to teach me
the case of a פלגס. palgas. פלגס palgas is a sheep that's
in its thirteenth month, it's not yet an איל ayil and it's
but no longer a צאן, tson, it's right in that middle, it's
a teenager. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says what's the case there? So you can bring that
as an עולה, olah, an עולה olah doesn't have to be a
certain age. But the point is the נסכים nesachim and the מנחה
mincha are different whether it's a כבש keves or an איל. ayil.
What do you bring for this thing that's right in the middle
of those two, that's this teenager? Do you bring it as a
כבש, keves, the amount of the מנחה mincha and נסכים nesachim or
as an איל? ayil? So it's coming to tell you, או לאיל,
o la'ayil, that even something that's not clearly an איל, ayil, even
something that's in the ambit of an איל, ayil, you bring like
an איל ayil and you're going to bring that level of a
מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, those quantities.
So the גמרא Gemara says, הניחא לרבי יוחנן דאמר בריה הוא. haniacha
l'Rabbi Yochanan d'amar birya hu. That's good for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that says that this פלגס palgas is like its own category, not
a כבש, keves, not an איל. ayil. דתנן, detnan, הכריבו מביא עליו
נסכי איל ואינו עולה לו מזבחו. hikrivo meivi alav nischei ayil v'eino
oleh lo mizivcho.
If you went ahead and you offered up this פלגס, palgas, what
do you do with it? מביא עליו נסכי איל ואינו
עולה לו מזבחו. meivi alav nischei ayil v'eino oleh lo mizivcho. You
bring the נסכים nesachim that go with an איל. ayil. So this
is a case where somebody made a vow to bring a כבש
keves or they made a vow to bring an איל ayil and
then what they wound up bringing was this פלגס, palgas, or however
you pronounce it. So what does
the משנה Mishna say if he goes ahead and he offers it
up? So fine, he's bringing this קרבן, korban, he brings the נסכים
nesachim like an איל, ayil, ואינו עולה לו מזבחו v'eino oleh lo
mizivcho but he doesn't get credit for his נדר neder
because he said a כבש keves and he's bringing a פלגס, palgas,
or he said an איל ayil and he's bringing a פלגס, palgas,
so it doesn't satisfy his נדר. neder. So he doesn't satisfy his
נדר, neder, but it's brought as a קרבן korban and you bring
the נסכים nesachim of an איל. ayil. ואמר רבי יוחנן *V'amar Rabbi
Yochanan*: או לאיל לרבות את
הפלגס *O l'ayil l'ravot et ha-palgas*. And רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says,
how do you know this? The word או לאיל *O l'ayil* comes
to tell you that it brings the נסכים nesachim *niscahim* that would
go with a פלגס *palgas*. אלא בבר פדא דאמר מאיס ומתני דספיקא
הוא *Ela b'Bar Parda d'amar maisu u'masni d'sfeka hu*, אצטריך קרא לרבויי
ספיקא *itstrach kra l'ribuyei sfeka*? But we have a different position. We
have the position of בר פדא *Bar Parda*. בר פדא *Bar Parda*
says the reason you bring the נסכים nesachim *niscahim* of an איל
*ayil* is not because of this extra word או לאיל *O l'ayil*.
The reason you bring the נסכים nesachim. *niscahim* of an איל *ayil*
is because you don't know if this פלגס *palgas* is a כבש
keves *keves* or an איל *ayil*. So what do you do? You
bring the נסכים nesachim *niscahim*, right, and you make a condition, a
stipulation and you say if this is an איל *ayil*, then the
full amount of these נסכים nesachim *niscahim*, you know, go for the
איל *ayil*, this פלגס *palgas*, if it's in the category of איל
*ayil*. If, however, it's in the category of כבש *keves*, then only
the proper amount is the כבש *keves* and the rest is a
נדבה *nedavah*, the rest of the מנחה *minchah* and of the wine
is a free will offering. So he says, so that's a debate
of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and בר פדא *Bar Parda*. What's that
a debate of? Whether this פלגס *palgas* is its own category. רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* doesn't say you stipulate, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says
it's its own category and the הלכה halacha. *halacha* of this category
is you bring the נסכים *niscahim* of the איל *ayil*. And that's
what או לאיל *O l'ayil* teaches you, that it's its own category
but you bring the נסכים *niscahim* of the איל *ayil*. But בר
פדא *Bar Parda* who says you stipulate, it's either a כבש *keves*
or an איל *ayil*, there is no third category. You just don't
know, so you have to bring the bigger נסכים *niscahim* and you
stipulate that it'll work out the right way. You know, it's the
full amount if it's the איל *ayil* and it's part if it's
the כבש *keves* and the rest is a נדבה *nedavah*. Okay, so
for בר פדא *Bar Parda*, you don't need the פסוק *pasuk*. It's
either one or the other and this is just how you solve
your lack of knowledge. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אלא בר פדא
דאמר מאיס ומתני דספיקא הוא *Ela Bar Parda d'amar maisu u'masni d'sfeka
hu*, it's a ספק *sfek*, אצטריך קרא לרבויי ספיקא *itstrach kra l'ribuyei
sfeka*? Do you need a
פסוק *pasuk* to include a case of a ספיקא *sfeka*? The או
*O* doesn't tell you that. This falls either into the כבש *keves*
or the איל *ayil* category, you don't know and you stipulate to
make it work. So גמרא *Gemara* says, ודאי לבר פדא קשיא *vaday
l'Bar Parda kashya*, fine, that extra או *O* is going to be
a problem for בר פדא *Bar Parda*. So we went through all
these פסוקים *psukim* that was a little tiring
but we figured out all of the different הלכות *halachot* and the
parameters of the scope of when do you bring נסכים *niscahim* or
not.
Alright, let's do a little bit more and then we'll wrap this
up for today. ככה יעשה לשור האחד או לאיל האחד או לשה
בכבשים או בעזים *Kachah yeaseh l'shor ha-echad o l'ayil ha-echad o l'seh
va-kvasim o va-izim*. That's like a wrap-up פסוק *pasuk* here by the
נסכים *niscahim* in the תורה *Torah*. This is what you do for
one ox or for one ram or for one sheep, whether it
be for one goat, a kid, whether it be a sheep or
a goat. לשור האחד מה תלמוד לומר *L'shor ha-echad mah talmud lomar*?
What's שור האחד *shor ha-echad* telling you? לפי שמצינו שחילק הכתוב בין
נסכי איל לנסכי כבש *L'fi she-matzinu she-chilek ha-katuv bein nishei ayil l'nishei
keves*. This actually is nice. You know, the תורה *Torah* makes a
distinction between the נסכים *niscahim* for a sheep and a ram, which
is really the same animal, it's just younger or older. יכול נחלק
בין נסכי פר לנסכי עגל *Yachol nechallek bein nishei par l'nishei egel*?
Maybe we should also make a distinction between whether it's a calf
or a cow. תלמוד לומר לשור האחד *Talmud lomar l'shor ha-echad*.
For an ox, it's all one, no distinctions for an ox. Yes,
there are distinctions for sheep and ram, no distinctions for ox. That's
a nice דרשה *drasha*. או לאיל מה תלמוד לומר *O l'ayil mah
talmud lomar*? What's that פסוק *pasuk* telling you? Or for a ram?
לפי שמצינו שחילק הכתוב בין נסכי בן שנה לנסכי בן שתים *L'fi
she-matzinu she-chilek ha-katuv bein nishei ben shanah l'nishei ben shtayim*. Because we
know in the case of sheep and ram, it makes a distinction
between a one-year-old which is a sheep and a two-year-old which is
a ram. יכול נחלק בין נסכי בן שתים לנסכי בן שלש *Yachol
nechallek bein nishei ben shtayim l'nishei ben shalosh*? Maybe we should then
also do more נסכים *niscahim* if it's a three-year-old sheep, if it's
an older ram. תלמוד לומר או לאיל האחד *Talmud lomar o l'ayil
ha-echad*. No, once it's a ram, it's all one, no distinctions, if
it's a two-year-old ram or three-year-old ram. או לשה בכבשים מה תלמוד
לומר *O l'seh va-kvasim mah talmud lomar*? What's that פסוק *pasuk* teaching
you about the sheep? לפי שמצינו שחילק הכתוב בין נסכי כבש לנסכי
איל *L'fi she-matzinu she-chilek ha-katuv bein nishei keves l'nishei ayil*. Because we
know it distinguishes between a ram and a sheep. Okay, but those
are both male. יכול נחלק בין נסכי כבשה לנסכי רחלה rechela? *Yachol
nechallek bein nishei kivsah l'nishei rachelah*? Okay, this is a good הוה
אמינא *hava amina*. So maybe it should make a similar distinction between
a one-year-old כבשה *kivsah*, female sheep, and two-year-old. So two-year-old isn't a
ram if it's female, but if a two-year-old male gets a different
level of נסכים *niscahim*, maybe a two-year-old female should also. תלמוד לומר
או לשה בכבשים *Talmud lomar o l'seh va-kvasim*. No, for the sheep,
בכבשים *va-kvasim*, it's all the same, no distinctions. או בעזים מה תלמוד
לומר *O va-izim mah talmud lomar*? What's it telling me finally this
last thing about goats? לפי שמצינו שחילק הכתוב בין נסכי כבש לנסכי
איל *L'fi she-matzinu she-chilek ha-katuv bein nishei keves l'nishei ayil*. Again, because
it makes a distinction between a sheep and a ram. יכול נחלק
בין נסכי גדי gedi. לנסכי שעיר *Yachol nechallek bein nishei g'di l'nishei
sa'ir*? Maybe it should make a distinction between. a baby goat and
a older goat, a one-year-old goat and a two-year-old goat, תלמוד לומר
או בעזים. No, goats are all the same. Okay, so the distinctions
are the distinctions stated. Don't make any analogies and make other distinctions
that weren't stated. Okay, let's just finish up to the משנה. Mishnah.
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, בדיק לן רבא, badik lan Rava,
רבא Rava tested us. נסכי רחלה בכמה? Niskei rechela bekama? How much,
what would be the נסכים for a רחלה? Okay, basically the question
before, right, would, what would be the wine that you would bring
for a older female sheep? Would it follow the rule of a
כבש and bring the smaller נסכים or would it follow the parallel
by the male and the ram and bring the greater ones? Exactly
what we were just saying, but he wanted to see if we
could come up with some evidence to this
הלכה. ופשטינא ליה ממתניתין Ufashtina leh mimatnitin and we sort of proved
it from the משנה. Mishnah. What does the משנה Mishnah say? גדי
משמש נסכי צאן של גדולים ושל קטנים של זכרים ושל נקבות חוץ
משל אילים, Gedi meshamesh niskei tzon shel gedolim veshel ketanim shel zecharim
veshel nekeivot chutz mishel eilim, that it, that there was a, a
like a receipt that you would get when you went to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you know, in order and you were going
to then go ahead and take that to the people that provided
the flour, the oil, and the wine, you know, when you paid
whatever, you know, and got this for your נסכים. And that it
basically said גדי. Okay, that was the receipt that you got. ומשמש
נסכי צאן Umeshamesh niskei tzon and that would, that would work to
get you the נסכים for, you know, sheep, של גדולים ושל קטנים
של זכרים ושל נקבות, shel gedolim veshel ketanim shel zecharim veshel nekeivot,
whether male or female, whether young or old, all of those types
of goats and sheep, young, old, male, female would all have the
same נסכים with the one exception חוץ משל אילים, chutz mishel eilim,
rams, male sheep, two years old, they would get a higher level.
But if it was female sheep two years old, same thing. Goats,
one year old, two year old, same thing. Everything, sheep, goats, male,
female, they all are the same with the one exception of male
sheep. So that shows that everything else was the same. Okay, perfect,
we will end here for today.