Dafa is נ''ח, Nun-Chet, we pick up in the middle of נ''ז
עמוד ב', Nun-Zayin Amud-Beis, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
It's about last two words on the line, it's about twenty lines
from the bottom, תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan with the asterisk. We just
had an extended discussion about whether the prohibition of not making חמץ
chametz applies to the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim and to the מנחת
נסכים. Minchas Nesachim. By the מנחת נסכים Minchas Nesachim the issue that
the גמרא Gemara was focused on was was there water in it?
Because you can't have a possibility of חמץ chametz without water, which
raised the question where was there water in all the other מנחות,
minachos, and the general assumption is well we're assuming there was. And
that's pretty much what the גמרא Gemara said by the מנחת נסכים
Minchas Nesachim as well.
The issue by the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim was another very important
question which we have not looked at yet, which is as was
raised the other day: well, if you made it חמץ, chametz, why
don't you just say okay, it's not the מנחה? mincha? And that
actually the גמרא Gemara says that's true, you can only transgress making
חמץ chametz once the flour, the water, the dough, the dough I
should say, has been designated and has קדושה kedusha of a מנחה,
mincha, קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, not just sanctified but intrinsic קדושה, kedusha,
and that normally happens when you put it in the various measuring
vessels or the kneading vessels and so on. But that led to
a discussion that not all those vessels were necessarily כלי שרת klei
shareis or were not necessarily קדוש kadosh and would not necessarily sanctify
the dough. And that was particularly an issue because of the question
about dry measures. That there's a debate whether the dry measures
were sanctified in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and therefore if something
did not have oil and just the flour and water you wouldn't
have a measure for water, there wasn't a specific amount, you'd only
use the dry measure for flour, so maybe it never became sanctified
until it was baked and by that time it's no longer חמץ.
chametz. So that was the issue of the לחם הפנים Lechem HaPanim
and again what it tells us other than the issue of whether
the dry measures were sanctified was the question about that you cannot
transgress the prohibition of חמץ chametz for מנחה mincha until the מנחה
mincha actually sanctified until designated as קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf as a
מנחה. mincha. Okay, now we pick up on a totally different tack,
so that was just to summarize yesterday because we ended pretty quickly,
so just wanted to make sure that was clear, but now we
pick up on a totally different tack, looking at the פסוק pasuk
about חמץ, chametz, but actually making a very different דרשה. drasha. So
let's take a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught.
Oh, we're mimic-ed the people who are not given in this room,
Bobby signs in.
She doesn't have a login. Bobby, you need a login.
To the other person who would say if you have a login,
I couldn't really?
Okay, to the other person who would say that the reason why
it would be a problem would be because I guess the dry
measures were sanctified, right? Yeah, that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara said,
correct.
Okay, so תנו רבנן, מנין למעלה מבשר חטאת Tanu Rabbanan: minayin l'maaleh
mibesar chatas, ומבשר אשם umibesar asham ומבשר קדשי קדשים, umibesar kodshei kodashim
how do you know, the basic rule here is anything that is
supposed to be eaten then instead of eating it you actually put
it on the מזבח mizbe'ach to burn? You offered it up on
the מזבח mizbe'ach to burn. And the relevance is because the תורה
Torah says don't put the שאור ודבש se'or u'dvash on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה', lo saktiru mimenu isheh laShem, and
now we're going to learn from that פסוק pasuk that there are
other things that you are prohibited to put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
And somewhat ironically, even things that are very much in the מקדש
mikdash itself, if these were the part that were supposed to be
eaten and instead of eating them you're burning them on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan, מנין למעלה
מבשר חטאת, chatas,
how do you know if you take some meat of a חטאת,
chatas ומבשר אשם asham, or some meat of an אשם, asham? ומבשר
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim, or the meat of any of the other
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim what קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim are there that
you would eat the meat that isn't a חטאת chatas and an
אשם? asham Anybody? Only one.
Well I mean you have like the stuff
on יום כיפור Yom Kippur that you're supposed to? No, the only
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim? that there is is עולה חטאת אשם, olah
chatas asham, עולה olah you're not eating the meat, so חטאת chatas
and אשם asham and זבחי שלמי ציבור zivchei shalmei tzibur דלחם בשתי
הלחם, d'lechem b'shnei halachem, בשר, basar, שוק וחזה בשבועות. shoke v'chazeh bashavuos.
Okay,
so we're very much always talking about שבועות Shavuos and we're leading
up to שבועות Shavuos here. So anyway, any of that meat, how
do you know, or ומקדשים קלים, umikodashim kalim,
of course all of the meat of the קדשים קלים kodashim kalim
which would normally be eaten, ממותר העומר, mimosar ha'omer,
what's left over of the עומר, omer, which an עומר omer was
a מנחה mincha you would do a handbreadth and the כהנים kohanim
would eat the rest, וממותר שתי הלחם, umimosar shnei halachem, what's left
over the שתי הלחם, shnei halachem, which is a funny phrase, you
would not be מקריב makriv any of the שתי הלחם shnei halachem
but it means you'd be זורק zorek the blood of the שני
כבשים shnei kevasim and you would eat the entire שתי הלחם. shnei
halachem. So here it really means the שתי הלחם. shnei halachem. ומלחם
הפנים, umilechem hapanim,
or of the לחם הפנים, Lechem HaPanim, right? Because that would eat
should have been eaten, ומשארי מנחות, umishe'ari menachos, or
really the remnant of any מנחה, mincha, so anything that you're supposed
to eat, how do you know if rather than eating it you
put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach שהוא בלא תעשה shehu belo sa'aseh
you've transgressed a negative prohibition? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches,
כי כל שאור וכל דבש, ki kol se'or vechol devash, any leaven
and any honey, לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה' lo saktiru mimenu isheh
laShem you shall not offer up from it a burnt offering to
God. So how does that tell you anything? Because we read it
the following: כל שהוא ממנו לאישים, kol shehu mimenu l'ishim, anything that
the key words here are ממנו אשה. mimenu isheh.
So although that's saying don't bring from this as a fire offering,
we're reading of it ממנו לאישים. mimenu l'ishim. Anything that from it
went to the fire, any קרבן korban that a part of the
קרבן korban was put on the fire, not this part, another part
was put on the קרבן korban שממנו לאשים, shemimenu l'ishim, הרי הוא
בבל תקטירו, harei hu b'val saktiru, הרי הוא בבל תקטירו. harei hu
b'val saktiru. Right.
That is included in לא תקטירו. lo saktiru. So you are not
able to offer up ממנו לאשה, mimenu l'ishah,
anything that from it went to the fire but this was not
supposed to be on the fire. This was supposed to be eaten.
It doesn't really fit in with... Of course it doesn't fit in,
but it's a דרשה. drasha. Okay, and what's interesting again is normally
the idea of don't put חמץ chametz or honey is the sense
that these things in terms of the physical object doesn't belong on
the מזבח. mizbeach. Right, חמץ chametz doesn't go on the מזבח. mizbeach.
Here we're sort of saying we're making a very different statement. Like
of course you could put מצה matzah on the מזבח mizbeach or
the מנחה mincha you already took a קומץ kometz of it and
you put it on the מזבח. mizbeach. It's the same physical object,
but it's just a point of like everything goes in its place.
You know, it might be true that the problem is not the
the nature of the physical object, but something that's supposed to be
eaten doesn't go on the מזבח. mizbeach. And something that goes on
the מזבח mizbeach doesn't get eaten. So they are so they are
using from this פסוק pasuk which speaks about what goes on the
מזבח mizbeach to extend beyond the wrong object and talk about the
physically it's the right object but it has a different designation. Okay.
Yes.
What's the penalty for a לא תעשה? lo saseh?
Well, it's lashes and so here...
Does this the כהנים? kohanim?
If the כהנים kohanim were to take from this מנחה mincha and
put it on the מזבח, mizbeach, they would have they transgressed. Correct.
Okay. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara is now going
to try to figure out the parameters of this.
So first it says for one minute, so שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים
shtei halechem v'lechem hapanim יש מהם לאשים? yesh mehem l'ishim? Is this
considered that the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and the לחם הפנים lechem
hapanim go to the fire? Because it's true there's something that put
on the fire. Let's let's ask ourselves all of the קרבנות, korbanot,
what goes on the fire? The קרבנות korbanot we understand the blood
goes on the מזבח, mizbeach, but what is ממנו לאשים? mimenu l'ishim?
The אימורין. imurin. Okay. מנחה mincha what goes on the fire is
a קומץ. kometz. How about the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, what goes
on the fire? Nothing of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem itself. The
אימורין imurin of the כבשים. kevasim. Not the blood of the כבשים,
kevasim, that's on the fire. The אימורין imurin of the כבשים. kevasim.
How about the לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, what goes on the fire?
The לבונה levonah from the like little like בזכי לבונה, bezichei levonah,
the little, you know, whatever dishes of לבונה levonah that are on
the שולחן. shulchan. Now those are not from the object itself. Right?
From the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, the the אימורין imurin of the
כבשים kevasim is not the שתי הלחם shtei halechem itself that goes
on the fire, it's part of the package. The same by the
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. The לבונה levonah is not part of the
לחם הפנים lechem hapanim itself. So the גמרא Gemara says is that
really considered from it on the fire? Okay. ושתי הלחם ולחם הפנים
v'shtei halechem v'lechem hapanim
יש מהם לאשים? yesh mehem l'ishim? Is that really saying that from
them goes on the fire, that from them they them goes on
the fire? והתניא, v'hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braisa. This is
in the middle of a discussion about what you have to do
הגשה hagasha for. Right? הגשה hagasha is every מנחה mincha you take
the מנחה mincha and you touch it on the מזבח mizbeach before
you then go ahead and offer it up. So which מנחות minchas
is that required for? So it says in the ברייתא, braisa, יצאו
שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים שאין מהם לאשים. yatzu shtei halechem v'lechem hapanim
she-ein mehem l'ishim. That you do not have to do הגשה hagasha
for the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and לחם הפנים lechem hapanim because
you don't take any of the מנחה mincha itself on the fire.
You only have to do הגשה hagasha for when you take from
the מנחה mincha and put it on the fire. So you see
it's not considered from it goes on the fire for that הלכה.
halacha. אמר רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, so Rav Sheshet says okay
different הלכות halachos have different parameters. אין מגופו לאשים. ein migufo l'ishim.
Okay. On the one hand you don't take from the thing itself,
right? The מנחה mincha itself doesn't go on the fire of the
שתי הלחם shtei halechem or the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. To that
is enough to exclude it from הגשה. hagasha. The requirements of הגשה,
hagasha, when do you have to do הגשה? hagasha? Touch it on
the to the corner of the מזבח mizbeach is only when the
thing itself is going on the מזבח, mizbeach, part of it. But
for the הלכה halacha of the prohibition to put the part that
should be eaten on the מזבח, mizbeach, that doesn't matter if the
thing itself went on or something connected with it went on. Okay?
This is a broader category. And of course you can understand conceptually
what that's about. The idea of הגשה hagasha is if you're about
to put from part of this on the מזבח, mizbeach, you some
way connect it to the מזבח mizbeach first. You know, there's some
conceptual logic there. Why would you touch something on the מזבח mizbeach
if it isn't even going on the מזבח? mizbeach? So you understand
why you wouldn't do that by the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. On the other hand, the logic here more
is the stuff that's supposed to be eaten, you're not supposed to
put on the fire. So obviously we're going to define that category
broader, and even if the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim do not themselves go on the מזבח, mizbeach, only the
blood of the of the כבשים, kevasim, I mean whatever the אימורין
imurin of the כבשים kevasim or the לבונה, levonah, it's enough that
says a portion went on the מזבח, mizbeach, this has to do
something else. This is supposed to be eaten and the prohibition applies.
So you understand logically why to define the parameters differently.
So הקטרת יום כיפור haktaras Yom Kippur was already included before like
in under חטאת chatas and אשם asham. or קדשי קדשים?
Yeah, what do you mean? All the קרבנות korbanos of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur are either חטאות chataos or אשמות?
ashamos? I thought they were talking about like you know regular חטאת
chatat and אשם.
asham No, no, no. Anything. Okay, איתמר. itmar. So now we're on
this tack, we'll be on this tack for a little while longer,
this new broader category of things that don't go on the מזבח.
mizbeach. So let's take a look. איתמר המעלה מכולם על גבי הכבש.
itmar hama'aleh mikulam al gabei hakevesh. Let's say you didn't put it
on the fire, you put it on the ramp. So רבי יוחנן
אמר חייב וריש לקיש אמר פטור. Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav v'Reish Lakish
amar patur. You're exempt. Now you might remember that we had discussions
before, right, in general about whether the ramp is considered to be,
you know, before it was actually... The question of once the מנחה
mincha gets on the ramp or gets on the top of the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, are you חייב chayav for letting it become חמץ chametz
there? So that was one thing in זבחים. Zevachim. Right, but in
general in זבחים Zevachim the question is always to what degree is
the ramp already considered the מזבח mizbe'ach itself. לא תקטיר ממנו אשה.
Lo taktiru mimenu isheh.
Now of course part of the challenge could be that if
לא תקטירו lo taktiru talks about
הקטרה, haktara, where you are doing הקטרה? haktara? But notice it says
המעלה מכולם על גבי הכבש, hamaleh mikulam al gabei hakeves, which does
not mean לא תקטירו lo taktiru does not mean that you happen
to lift it up on the ramp. It means you actually may
have made a little fire on the ramp and you burnt it,
you offered it on the ramp. So you are offering it as
an אשה, isheh, otherwise it is not לא תקטירו. lo taktiru. You
are offering it as an אשה. isheh. But you are doing it
on the ramp. You are not doing it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Does that count or not? So let's take a look.
רבי יוחנן אומר חייב Rabbi Yochanan omer chayav דתניא המזבח. d'tanya hamizbe'ach.
It says לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה' ועל המזבח לא יעלו לריח
ניחוח. lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem v'al hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach.
They shall not be offered up on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So that
sounds like the מזבח mizbe'ach proper, not the ramp. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says here we have a ברייתא: braita: המזבח. Hamizbe'ach. אין
לי אלא מזבח. ein li ela mizbe'ach. I only know the מזבח
mizbe'ach itself. כבש מניין? Keves minayin? How do I know the ramp?
תלמוד לומר ועל המזבח לא יעלו לרצון. Talmud lomar v'al hamizbe'ach lo
ya'alu l'ratzon. It is not לרצון, l'ratzon, it is לריח ניחוח, l'rei'ach
nicho'ach, isn't it? לרצון? L'ratzon? Maybe.
Excuse me. כי כל שאור וכל דבש לא תקטירו ממנו
אשה לה' קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם לה' ואל המזבח לא יעלו לריח
ניחוח. Ki kol se'or v'chol dvash lo
taktiru mimenu isheh
l'Hashem korban reishit takrivu otam l'Hashem v'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach.
Yeah,
quite bizarre. They normally collect it when... anyway. ואל המזבח לא יעלו.
V'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu. So it is ואל המזבח v'el hamizbe'ach towards
the מזבח mizbe'ach means not even the מזבח mizbe'ach itself.
So not only על המזבח, al hamizbe'ach, my little story here, to
be corrected,
לריח ניחוח. l'rei'ach nicho'ach. Fine, very good. I don't have it... okay.
Anyway, אל המזבח el hamizbe'ach even on the ramp. So you see
you are חייב chayav even on the ramp and therefore even if
it is not on the מזבח mizbe'ach itself. רבי אלעזר אומר פטור.
Rabbi Elazar omer patur. You are exempt. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דאמר
קרא. D'amar kra. The פסוק pasuk says שאור ודבש. se'or u'dvash. Talking
about, again, this is a paraphrase of the פסוק: pasuk: קרבן ראשית
תקריבו אותם. Korban reishit takrivu otam. אותם Otam is what Rabbi Elazar
says brings you the ramp as the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but anything else
no. What does the פסוק pasuk say? I will read you the
פסוק, pasuk, be a little clearer. It says כי כל שאור וכל
דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה לה' קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם לה'. Ki
kol se'or v'chol dvash lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem korban reishit takrivu
otam l'Hashem. You cannot bring them as a קרבן ראשית korban reishit
which
means ביכורים bikurim and שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, but of course ואל
המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. v'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu l'rei'ach nicho'ach. But
you are not going to put them on the מזבח mizbe'ach because
what do you do? You bring שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, that is
חמץ, chametz, but you do not put it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
You put the כבשים kvasim on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. You bring ביכורים,
bikurim, that is דבש dvash in the sense that you have dates
and you make date honey out of it, but that is also
אל המזבח לא יעלו. el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu. You do not put
the ביכורים bikurim on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. You give it to the כהן. kohen. So that is
פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk. But therefore what he is saying
is the words אל המזבח el hamizbe'ach towards the מזבח mizbe'ach which
includes even the ramp, not the מזבח mizbe'ach itself, is only referring
to the שאור ודבש. se'or u'dvash. Because it says קרבן ראשית תקריבו
אותם לה'. korban reishit takrivu otam l'Hashem. So what's it referring to?
The שאור ודבש se'or u'dvash can be brought as a קרבן ראשית
korban reishit and אל המזבח לא יעלו v'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu but
they can't be offered up. So שאור ודבש se'or u'dvash you transgress
even אל המזבח el hamizbe'ach on the ramp. The other things we
were talking about, this whole new category of ממנו לאישים mimenu l'ishim
and things that are normally supposed to be eaten, that is not
included in the idea of ramp. So for רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
what he has is he actually
has he wants to almost in a way maintain the conceptually distinct
category of שאור ודבש. se'or u'dvash. שאור ודבש Se'or u'dvash is more
problematic than something that just was fundamentally in terms of the objects
could go on the מזבח mizbe'ach but it happened to be it
was supposed to be eaten. So that is like of a lesser
degree of a problem. שאור ודבש Se'or u'dvash obviously the Torah is
very focused to keep it away. So therefore he says שאור ודבש
se'or u'dvash cannot even be on the ramp. These types of things
you do not transgress if they are on the ramp. Very nice
logic, but we do פוסק posek like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that
you transgress, פסקא? paska? No, that is the רמב"ם Rambam rule.
Anyway, so there we go, המעלה ממנו לאישים?
hamaleh mimenu l'ishim? Well, not a separate מצווה mitzvah because it is
learned out from the same פסוק, pasuk, but it is considered to
be a prohibition. I have to check the רמב"ם, Rambam, I don't
remember offhand. Okay, so therefore we have this new thing of things
that should go on, should be eaten, that go on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, and you cannot be מקטיר maktir them on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
And now we are learning that you might even not be allowed
to be מקטיר maktir them on the ramp, but certainly שאור ודבש
se'or u'dvash you cannot be מקטיר maktir not only on the מזבח
mizbe'ach but even on the ramp. Okay, so now top of נ"ח
ע"א. 58a. רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, האי אותם מאי עביד ליה? hai otam mai avid
lei? What does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan do with the verse of
אותם? otam? Because אותם otam the way רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar read
it is
they, שאור ודבש se'or u'dvash is a problem even on the ramp,
but the other things are not a problem on the ramp. So
what does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan do with the word
אותם? otam? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא Mibei lei l'chid'tanya what we taught in
a
ברייתא: braita: יכול יהא יחיד מתנדב ומביא כיוצא בהן נדבה. yachol yehei
yachid mitnadiv u'meivi k'yotzei bahen nedava. Am I allowed to bring a
שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, you know, not on שבועות? Shavuos? I'm just
going to give it, you know, be מקריב, makriv, I'll bring a
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem נדר? neder? What do you think that the
הוה אמינא hava amina is that I want to bring it as
a free will sacrifice and even take a קומץ komets and put
on the מזבח, mizbeiach, which is like, that's crazy, because that would
be burning חמץ chametz on the מזבח. mizbeiach. You could say that
it means maybe I want to be מקריב makriv שתי הלחם Shtei
HaLechem together with כבשים k'vasim and do that as a free will
sacrifice. But whatever, maybe I want to do this thing not as
part of my obligation of שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem but as a
free will sacrifice. And וקרי אני בה v'karei ani bah מוצא שפתיך
תשמור ועשית motza sefatecha tishmor v'asita and maybe they would say, okay,
you made a נדר, neder, you'll have to fulfill it and we'll
let you do that. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar קרבן ראשית, korban reishit,
yes Michael, and eight pages ago, you're right. Okay, yes, maybe it
was the גמרא Gemara בדף י' b'daf yud he
said it. Okay, twice. Okay, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so the פסוק
pasuk says קרבן ראשית תקריבו, korban reishit takrivu, you shall bring a
קרבן ראשית, korban reishit, you's plural, ציבור tzibur אמרתי לך ולא יחיד.
amarti l'cha v'lo yachid. The ציבור tzibur can bring the שתי הלחם,
Shtei HaLechem, right, not the individual. קרבן ראשית, korban reishit, as I
said before, includes both שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem because they are the
first of the new wheat on the, on the מזבח. mizbeiach. They
are considered a type of ביכורים bikurim and a ראשית reishit on
the מזבח. mizbeiach. Again, not that the bread goes on the מזבח,
mizbeiach, that's the whole point, it stays off. And ביכורים bikurim are
called ראשית reishit because basically the פסוק pasuk and they're also the
first of the new fruit. But anyway, here we're saying it about
the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. So you, the ציבור tzibur bring שתי
הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, not on a מזבח, mizbeiach, but you bring it,
not an individual. ולא יחיד. V'lo yachid. יכול לא יהא יחיד מביא
שאינו מביא חובתו כיוצא בה. Yachol lo yehei yachid meivi she'eino meivi
chovato k'yozei bah. Maybe an individual can't bring his own שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem קרבן korban because he never brings it as an obligatory
קרבן, korban, so he doesn't have the option of bringing it as
a free will קרבן. korban. אבל יהא ציבור מביא שמביא חובתו כיוצא
בה. Aval yehei tzibur meivi shemeivi chovato k'yozei bah. But maybe the
ציבור tzibur that on שבועות Shavuos brings the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
as an obligatory קרבן, korban, maybe on some other day they can
bring שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem as a free will קרבן, korban, right?
Maybe for them it's a meaningful קרבן korban and they could bring
it as free will. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar אותם, otam, and here's
what we do with the פסוק pasuk אותם. otam. קרבן ראשית תקריבו
אותם, Korban reishit takrivu otam, they shall be brought, that you can
only bring them. If you want to bring something with חמץ chametz
or with דבש, dvash, your only options are exactly what I've prescribed
for you, right? It's exactly the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem on שבועות
Shavuos and the ביכורים, bikurim, okay, those by the way, anyway as
I said, they don't go on the מזבח, mizbeiach, but that's your
option of bringing bread. You do not have some other option and
you cannot bring it as a נדבה. nedavah. Now let's not forget,
I should say parenthetically, you actually can bring something analogous to this
with bread which is a קרבן תודה, korban toda, which has with
it ten loaves of חמץ. chametz. Again, they don't go on the
מזבח. mizbeiach. So it's not like there's no other קרבן korban that
חמץ chametz is not a part of it, okay. But nevertheless, they
become another, become another here. Okay, there might be, there is a
small difference which is, or maybe not so small, רש"י Rashi points
this out later in today's דף, daf, that by the תודה toda
you can bring the bread at a later time, whereas by the
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem obviously it all, it's much more of a
package with the, with the קרבן. korban. But nevertheless, let's not confuse
what the גמרא Gemara is saying to mean that there's no other
קרבן korban that bread is part of the package. But what it
is saying by reading אותם otam is, when, if you're interested in
bringing קרבן ראשית, korban reishit, it only has to be אותם, otam,
it only has to be the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem that you've
been mandated, it cannot be a free will שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem.
Just to bit on that, what they're saying is, let's say I
want to do the קרבן korban on יום כיפור Yom Kippur as
a free will offering at some other point, that wouldn't be a
problem because that's not in the פסוק pasuk of אותם, otam, or
am I just completely not, misunderstood?
No, normally there are, why are you jumping back to יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? I don't understand.
No, I'm saying because what you're saying is only אותם otam is
a problem when you want to do this as a נדבה. nedavah.
Well, no, everything else, you mean like, let's say I wanted to
do and do with a special עבודה. avodah.
Yeah, right, that's what I'm saying.
No, the point here is, is that, is that, but
every other thing, אחת, achat, I already know for whatever, for whatever
reason, I mean you could say how do I know this? How
do I know I can't do a חטאת chatat, as a free
will? How do I know I can't do an אשם asham, as
a free will? But there are some things which we know the
nature of the קרבן korban is חובה. chovah. The interesting thing about
the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and if you want to say that
part of the question here is including the כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret
is that both of those things inherently, you know, can come as
נדבות. nedavot. You can have שלמים shlamim as a נדבה, nedavah, not
שלמי ציבור, shalmei tzibur, but שלמים shlamim as a נדבה. nedavah. You
can have a type of a מנחה mincha as a נדבה. nedavah.
You can even have a מנחה mincha that includes bread as a
נדבה, nedavah, like my תודה. toda. So these are things where there
was a הוה אמינא hava amina that maybe I can do this
package as a נדבה. nedavah. There are other things like, you know,
the יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, חטאת, chatas? אשם, whatever, that was not
even a הוה אמינא, hava amina, but maybe this package I can't?
This is no, you know, this is not an acceptable thing except
in the context of it being a חובה.
chovah. So because this is essentially a free will offering?
Well, it's a type of, it's the type of things or שלמים
shlamim and a מנחה mincha whatever that normally can come as free
will קרבנות.
korbanot. That's what has to be restricted. You just take for granted
that like all the other stuff, you don't even need that פסוק.
pasuk. Correct, correct.
Okay, so ומה יש לך להביא, u'mah yesh l'cha l'havi, so therefore
what can you bring if you want to bring a type of
a, you know, שאור se'or and דבש dvash at least in the
environs of the מזבח? mizbeiach? So what can bring שתי הלחם מן
השאור, shtei halechem min hase'or, the שתי הלחם shtei halechem comes from,
of course, the חמץ, chametz, and ובכורים מן הדבש, ubikurim min hadevash,
and ביכורים bikurim comes from honey because of the date. So קרבן
ראשית korban reishit תקריבו אותם. takrivu otam. דראשית dereishit is that both
of these are called ראשית reishit and ביכורים bikurim and so on.
They can be brought, of course, אל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח.
el hamizbeach lo ya'alu lere'ach nicho'ach. They don't get put on the
מזבח, mizbeach, but they are part of a קרבן korban that is
brought. Okay. ושתי הלחם לא יקריבו נדבה. ushtei halechem lo yakrivu nedava.
So that's what that teaches. Now the גמרא gemara says so now
by the way we have left the discussion of, we've used the
אותם otam as the transition as a way to pull us back
into discussing שאור se'or and דבש. devash. Okay, so we've left the
discussion, the fascinating new point that anything that should be eaten you
can't put on the מזבח mizbeach and you transgress כל שממנו לאישים
kol shemimenu le'ishim if it doesn't go on the מזבח mizbeach that's
offered up. And now we're back to discussing שאור se'or and דבש
devash don't go on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, and that you cannot
bring a free will שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. So let's take a
look. From what does ושתי הלחם לא יקריבו נדבה? ushtei halechem lo
yakrivu nedava? Are you telling me there's not an option to bring
a free will שתי הלחם? shtei halechem? והתניא, vehatanya, we
learned in the ברייתא: braita: אם נאמר כל שאור למה נאמר כל
דבש, אם נאמר כל דבש למה נאמר כל שאור? im ne'emar kol
se'or lamah ne'emar kol devash, im ne'emar kol devash lamah ne'emar kol
se'or? So the point here is not why do you need a
separate prohibition of honey and leaven, obviously those are different things. The
point here is the word כל. kol. We're going to learn from
the word כל, kol, any, that even not a full amount, even
not a full קומץ, kometz, maybe even not a full כזית, kezayit,
maybe even a משהו, mash'hu, כל kol is going to tell us
even a small amount of this you transgress. Okay, so the question
is why did it have to say both by the prohibition of
honey and the prohibition of חמץ, chametz, of שאור, se'or, that even
a small amount? Why can't it say by one? The word כל
kol is the focus here. Why can't I say by one and
infer the same is true by the other?
They would say כל שאור ודבש, kol se'or udevash, it should put
both of them together.
Maybe. Okay, that's a good point. You need it just to create,
just to separate the two. Okay, that's a good grammatical answer. That's
not the interest here. Okay, so why did it have to say
by both of them even a small amount? מפני שיש בשאור מה
שאין בדבש ויש בדבש מה שאין בשאור.
mipnei sheyesh
base'or
mah she'ein badevash veyesh badevash mah she'ein base'or.
Because there are different characters of honey and leaven that I might
have thought that just because you say a הלכה halacha by one,
it's not necessarily true by the other. There are different קולות kulot
and חומרות. chumrot. What are those? So let's take a look. ויש
בדבש מה שאין בשאור. veyesh badevash mah she'ein base'or.
שאור, se'or, here's the way they're different. שאור הותר מכללו במקדש. se'or
hutar miklalo bamiktash. There are sometimes that you can actually bring חמץ
chametz in the מקדש, miktash, which is surprising, shocking. We didn't think
so.
Okay. You're all חמץ chametz and all that.
Okay, well we'll talk about what does it mean? What does it
mean הותר במקדש? hutar bamiktash? דבש לא הותר מכללו במקדש. devash lo
hutar miklalo bamiktash. Honey never gets brought in the מקדש. miktash. So
therefore שאור se'or is more lenient in that way. So maybe if
the תורה torah is saying don't even bring a tiny bit, maybe
it's only by honey which is stricter, and it wouldn't have applied
to שאור se'or which is more lenient. Or you could say by
the תמרים, t'marim, so there is הותר מכללו. hutar miklalo.
Well we don't know what הותר מכללו hutar miklalo means yet. Let's
we're going to get back to that, so let's hold off. Okay.
Now here's the way in which it's the opposite, that honey is
more lenient. דבש הותר בשירי מנחה, devash hutar beshirei mincha, שאור לא
הותר בשירי מנחה. se'or lo hutar beshirei mincha. If you have your
remnant of the מנחה mincha that the כהנים kohanim eat, so if
they want to pour some honey on their מנחה mincha and eat
it, because honey is great, you're allowed to have the honey as
something that is eaten, you know, with the מנחה. mincha. But you
are not allowed to let the remnant of the מנחה mincha become
חמץ. chametz. Right? Remember it says
לא תאפה חמץ חלקם. lo te'afeh chametz chelkam. They can't even let
their portion, the remnant, become חמץ. chametz. So in that way honey
is more lenient because at least it can be part of the
מנחה mincha that they eat if they put it on afterwards. So
therefore each one has its leniency, so a stringency of even a
little bit we would not have been able to infer one to
the other. Not exactly. Okay, right. Because it's still not the מנחה
mincha is still not itself becoming דבש, devash, it's just an additive.
I understand. No, and also if I want to eat like חמץ
chametz with my
מנחה, mincha, I can do that as long as I don't bake
it חמץ. chametz. Right. You're right. It's like you can put honey
on it or right.
It is a bad parallel. You are correct. Anyway, okay. So therefore
הא מפני שיש בשאור מה שאין בדבש, ha mipnei sheyesh base'or mah
she'ein badevash, since there are things that are true about the חמץ
chametz which isn't true about the honey, ויש בדבש מה שאין בשאור,
veyesh badevash mah she'ein base'or, and things that are true about the
honey which isn't true about the חמץ, chametz, so did I skip
a line? מה שאין בשאור הוצרך לומר כל שאור והוצרך לומר כל
דבש.
mah she'ein
base'or
hutzrach lomar kol se'or vehutzrach lomar kol devash. It has to say
any even a smallest amount of חמץ chametz or we'll see how
much a smallest amount is, but even not a full amount, even
not a full שיעור shiur of honey you still transgress. So the
כל kol is telling you transgress even less than a full שיעור
shiur and it had to be said both by honey and חמץ
chametz because I could not have learned one from the other. Fine.
Now we want to go back, the reason we quoted this and
we will now in a minute focus on the implications of this
and really put our attention to this ברייתא, braita, but for now
the reason we quoted it is to tell me the idea that
this is thing called that it says that the חמץ, chametz, the
שאור se'or was הותר מכללו במקדש. hutar miklalo bamiktash. And we want
to figure out what that means. So let's take a look. So
it says like this: שאור דהותר מכללו. se'or dehutar miklalo. מקדש מאי
Mai? ניהו *mikdash mainihu*? What does it mean when it suggests that
the שאור seor *se'or* was allowed to be brought in the מקדש
*mikdash*? Where did we ever find that? לאו lav. שתי הלחם shtei
halechem דקרבה נדבה *lav shtei halechem dikarva nedava*, maybe this is saying
that you can bring a שתי הלחם shtei halechem *shtei halechem* as
a free will sacrifice and that we are allowing שאור seor. *se'or*
in the מקדש *mikdash*. Now that you know what does it mean?
If you're still not offering up anything on the מזבח Mizbeiach *mizbeach*,
you're not allowing it. So this is where רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
that we're actually thinking as a הוה אמינא hava amina. *hava amina*
that you can bring שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* as a נדבה *nedava*,
that you could not bringing it with the כבשים kevashim *kvasim*, you're
bringing just the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*, that you actually would take
a קומץ kometz, *kometz* and put it on the מזבח Mizbeiach *mizbeach*.
Is it ציבור *tzibbur* or is it נדבה *nedava*?
Is it ציבור *tzibbur*? יחיד *yachid*? It doesn't matter, somebody. So this
is a crazy הוה אמינא *hava amina*, right? You have all these
פסוקים *psukim* that are telling you you better not have any שאור
seor. *se'or* on the מזבח Mizbeiach. *mizbeach*, and if you're going to
bring שאור se’or, *se'or*, keep it off the מזבח Mizbeiach, *mizbeach*, right?
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has a הוה אמינא *hava amina* that
oh, if you give it as a נדבה *nedava* maybe you're able
to do it. And therefore הותר מכללו *hutar miklalo*, okay, so don't
you see you're allowed to do it. So לאו lav. שתי הלחם
דקרבה נדבה *lav shtei halechem dikarva nedava*? אמר רב עמרם לאו lav,
לקרבי מהם *amar Rav Amram lav likarvi mehem*, no, it doesn't mean
that they are actually brought on the מזבח Mizbeiach. *mizbeach*. What it
means as Michael said is that they're brought as a package, that's
what it means הותר מכללו *hutar miklalo*. How is הנהו *hano* הותר
מכללו *hutar miklalo* in the מקדש *mikdash*? That you bring the שתי
הלחם *shtei halechem* with the כבשים kevashim *kvasim* and you put the
כבשים kevashim *kvasim* on the מזבח Mizbeiach? *mizbeach*. Okay, so when it
says that there's a leniency by הנהו *hano*, that it is allowed
in the מקדש *mikdash*, it doesn't mean we put it on the
מזבח Mizbeiach. *mizbeach* and it doesn't just mean we let it in
the front door. What it means is we let part of the
package go on the מזבח Mizbeiach. *mizbeach*. Which part of the package?
The blood of the כבשים *kvasim*. Okay, so the כבשים *kvasim* goes
on the מזבח mizbeiach, *mizbeach*, that part of the package of the
שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*. Now to answer your question Michael because your
question was well what about the דבש devash *dvash*? Don't you bring
ביכורים Bikkurim, *bikurim* into the מקדש *mikdash*? The answer is yes, you
bring them into the מקדש *mikdash*, but no part of the ביכורים
Bikkurim, *bikurim* goes on the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbeach*, nothing connected to the
ביכורים Bikkurim *bikurim* goes on the מזבח mizbeiach? *mizbeach*. But now that's
exactly what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to ask. Let's take
a look. אי הכי *i hachi*, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, if
that's true, ביכורים Bikkurim. נמי *bikurim nami*, I'll show you that by
ביכורים Bikkurim *bikurim* as well some part of that package goes on
the מזבח mizbeiach. *mizbeach*. דתנן *detnan*, we taught in the משנה mishna.
*mishna*, הגוזלות על גבי הסלים *hagozalot al gabei hasalim*, when they would
bring their ביכורים Bikkurim. *bikurim* they would also bring with them some
turtle doves. Meaning what? Well, that's going to be the answer. So
you have those turtle doves there in your baskets and היו עולות
*hayu olot*, you would bring them as an עולה olah *olah* when
you brought your ביכורים Bikkurim, *bikurim*, והסלים *vehasalim*, and the baskets that
were filled with the fruit שבידם *shebeyadam* ניתנים לכהנים *nitanim lakohanim*, would
be given to the כהנים *kohanim*. So you see you would bring
a bird קרבן korban, *korban* with your ביכורים Bikkurim *bikurim*, something goes
on the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbeach*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
הנהו לעטר ביכורים Bikkurim, הוא דאתו *hano le'ater bikurim hu de'atu*, that's
just to לעטר *le'ater*, really means to crown, but maybe to beautify
the ביכורים *bikurim* and there's no הלכתי halachic *halachic* connection between the
birds and the ביכורים *bikurim*. The birds are not הלכתית *halachically* ביכורים
*bikurim*, you know, it's just a nice thing to bring with it.
It makes it look nicer. It gives you it makes it nice
to bring a קרבן korban *korban* when you're bringing the ביכורים *bikurim*,
but in no הלכתי *halachic* way are they part of the package
of ביכורים *bikurim* that are being brought on the מזבח mizbeiach, *mizbeach*.
So that's how we can say that שאור se’or. הותר מכללו *se'or
hutar miklalo*. And that is true, you know, that's in a way
פשט peshat *pshat* of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. The פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
says קרבן korban. ראשית תקריבו אתם ואל המזבח לא יעלו *korban reishit
takrivu otam v'el hamizbeach lo ya'alu*. Bring it as part of a
package, bring it with the שתי כבשים *shtei kvasim*, but don't put
it on the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbeach*. But to some degree it's הותר
מכללו *hutar miklalo*, at least you're letting it come as part of
a package. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, fine,
that is the end of that discussion about that the שתי הלחם
*shtei halechem* cannot come as a נדבה *nedava*. Of course the הוה
אמינא *hava amina* is totally crazy. Okay, but anyway, that's the end
of that discussion. שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* does not come as a
נדבה *nedava*. Now we are going back to the ממנו לאישים mimenu
l'ishim *mimenu l'ishim* discussion about things that should be eaten that get
put on the מזבח mizbe’ach *mizbeach*. בעי רמי בר חמא *ba'ei Rami
bar Chama*, so רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* asked מרב חסדא
*meRav Chisda*, from רב חסדא Rav Chisda *Rav Chisda*, המעלה מבשר חטאת
העוף Chatas HaOf אגבי המזבח מהו Mah hu? *hama'ale mibsar chatat ha'of
agabei hamizbeach mahu*? Do you really mean it when you say you
need ממנו לאישים mimenu l'ishim *mimenu l'ishim* or is it just the
principle of don't burn things you're supposed to eat? And here's a
good test case, חטאת העוף Chatas HaOf, *chatat ha'of*. What do you
do with a חטאת העוף Chatas HaOf. *chatat ha'of*? The כהנים *kohanim*
eat the חטאת העוף *chatat ha'of*, the blood goes on the מזבח
mizbe’ach, *mizbeach*, nothing gets burned. No part of the חטאת העוף *chatat
ha'of* gets burned. Every other thing something gets burned on the fire,
right? The קומץ kometz *kometz* gets burned on the fire for מנחה
mincha. *mincha*, the אימורים *emurim*, even by the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*,
the אימורים
*emurim* of the כבשים *kvasim* get burned, by לחם lechem?
הפנים *lechem hapanim*, the לבונה levonah *levona* gets burned. I'm going to
find you something that you
can eat that no part of it gets burned. What is it?
The חטאת העוף *chatat ha'of*. The blood goes on the מזבח mizbe’ach,
*mizbeach*,
no part gets burned
על המזבח *al hamizbeach*.
So is that a prohibition to burn that, to burn it? Do
you literally mean it's only a thing is prohibited is ממנו לאישים
mimenu l'ishim, *mimenu l'ishim* or what you're really trying to say is
that something you're supposed to eat you're not supposed to burn? Okay,
so that's what he's saying. Okay, so what do you do with
the head in a חטאת העוף *chatat ha'of*? I don't know, do
you maybe char it and eat it? Isn't this עולה *olah*? Okay,
so he says like this is only the עולה *olah* whose head
was... If it's an עולת העוף *olat ha'of*, the head you burn
everything, right? No no no, wait, so I'm not sure how much
you cut off. No, no, wait, so I'm not gonna play how
much you cut off or not cut off, we'll go there. Okay,
anyway, המעלה מבשר חטאת העוף על גבי מזבח, mizbeach. so let's say
you take the meat of the חטאת העוף and you put it
on the מזבח mizbeach. rather than eating it. מהו? What's the הלכה?
halachah? Have you transgressed? כל שממנו לאישים אמר רחמנא, Kol shemimenu l'ishim
amar Rachmana, you focused on a פסוק pasuk of a part of
it went on the fire and don't burn the rest of it.
והאי אינו ממנו לאישים, V'hai eino mimenu l'ishim, and this is not
burnt on the fire, no part of this goes on the fire
on the מזבח mizbeach, and therefore you don't transgress. או דילמא, O
dilma, or do maybe what you mean is really כל ששמו קרבן.
Kol sheshmo korban. Anything that's called a קרבן, korban, don't burn the
part you're supposed to eat, which really means it's not based on
the ממנו לאישים mimenu l'ishim? that פסוק pasuk even if that's where
we learn it from, it gets abstracted to a more general principle
of don't burn the parts of
the קרבן korban, you're supposed to eat. Okay? והאי נמי שמו קרבן,
V'hai nami shmo korban, and this is also called a קרבן. korban
So what do you say? ואמר ליה, V'amar lei, כל
ששמו קרבן והאי נמי שמו קרבן. Kol sheshmo korban v'hai nami shmo
korban. You're right. It's not really about whether you burned a part
on the מזבח. mizbeach, What it really is about is that don't,
if anything that's called a קרבן, korban even if nothing is burned
on the מזבח, anything that's called a קרבן, korban. don't burn, don't
be מקטיר maktir the part that you are supposed to eat. So
that makes a lot of sense. The
ממנו לאישים mimenu l'ishim was the hook in the פסוק pasuk but
there's not a particular logic why it should be limited to those
types of things. And what it's really saying is don't burn the
part of the קרבן korban. that you're supposed to be eating. Yes,
yes, this part, you know he's speaking of truly technically it's not
a קרבן korban, but people would associate... Oh, no, no, that's not
what we mean. כל ששמו Kol sheshmo does not mean what people
call. כל ששמו Kol sheshmo means the תורה Torah calls it a
קרבן. korban, It is a קרבן. korban. It just has a technical
thing that it's not, there's no part of it that's burned, no
part of it is burned. So the fact that no part of
it is burned, how, how critical is that? And the גמרא Gemara
says that really doesn't matter. What really matters is it's the קרבן,
korban? then the part, don't burn the part you're supposed to eat.
No, no, no, that's not what... No, שמו shmo does not mean
what people say. That means what its halachic category is. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara, says כתנאי. k'tannai. This is really a debate of
תנאים. tannaim. רבי אליעזר אומר כל שממנו לאישים, Rabbi Eliezer omer kol
shemimenu l'ishim, that we literally limit it to things that a part
of them were burned, that's where the prohibition applies, don't burn the
part you should eat. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, no, כל
ששמו קרבן. kol sheshmo korban. As long as it's called a קרבן,
korban. don't, then you should not be burning the part you're supposed
to be eating. מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? What's the difference? Obviously we
could have said a חטאת העוף, but we're looking for maybe there's
even yet another thing where this would play out. So אמר רב
חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, בשר חטאת העוף איכא בינייהו. b'sar Chatas HaOf
ika beinaihu. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says like it was רב
חסדא Rav Chisda before, right? Wasn't רב חסדא Rav Chisda. the one
that was asked before? Yeah, he asked רב חסדא. Rav Chisda So
רב חסדא Rav Chisda was already sort of asked this question, so
he had his answer in his pocket. בשר חטאת העוף איכא בינייהו.
B'sar Chatas HaOf ika beinaihu. The meat of the חטאת העוף. That's
the case where you don't burn any part of it, but it's
a קרבן. korban. And there would be the debate whether the prohibition
applies and we presumably רב חסדא and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva are
saying yes, the prohibition does apply, it does, and you're not allowed
to burn the part you're supposed to eat. רבא אמר, Rava amar,
לוג שמן של מצורע איכא בינייהו. log shemen shel metzora ika beinaihu.
The oil, the לוג log of the oil of a מצורע metzora
that the מצורע metzora brings with his קרבנות korbanos when he's ending
his period of צרעת. tzaraas. So that is a part that you
don't put any part of the לוג log on the מזבח. Okay,
so there's no ממנו לאישים, mimenu l'ishim and you're supposed to eat
the remnant of it. Are you prohibited from burning that שמן shemen
on the מזבח? Now how do you know it's called a קרבן?
korban Maybe that's not even called a קרבן. korban, So it says
no, דתני לוי, D'tani Levi, because לוי Levi taught it in another
context: כל קרבנם, Kol korbanam, all of their קרבנות, korbanos, לרבות לוג
שמן של מצורע, l'rabos log shemen shel metzora, that includes the לוג
log of oil of the מצורע. metzora. So you see in another
context it's called a קרבן. korban, So therefore that is the נפקא
מינה. nafkaminah. מאי? So on the end of the day, the question
is, you know, and obviously רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רב חסדא'ס
Rav Chisda's position makes more sense because conceptually this is something that
a part of the קרבן korban, that should be eaten, don't burn
on the מזבח. And if not really, why should it matter only
those things that a part was burnt? Although you could a little
bit understand it, that if part of it was burnt, then this
is even more being designated as the, as the part that you
don't burn. Right? If it's just naturally this is what you eat
but there's not like something else was burned, then maybe it's not,
you know, the lines aren't being drawn as starkly. But if you're
burning this part and you're not burning that part, then this is
almost very clearly labeled the part that's not burned and that's eaten.
So that's the emphasis of כל שממנו לאישים. kol shemimenu l'ishim. But
in the end we define a broader category of anything that's a
קרבן, don't burn the part that you eat. Two final points before
we move on. One is רש״י Rashi says, what do you mean
that the oil of the מצורע metzora is not ממנו לאישים? mi-meno
le-ishem. Why isn't it just as much as ממנו לאישים mi-meno le-ishem,
like the כבשים that come with the לחם? lechem Very good. Because
with the מצורע metzora you have a קרבן, the שלמים shelamim that
comes with the מצורע, metzora, you offer it up, you have the
לוג, log, so if the גמרא Gemara considered the כבשים that come
with the לחם as ממנו לאישים because part of the package, here
too part of the package goes on the מזבח. I might discuss
this later, right? So exactly. Oh Michael, so brilliant. So that's what
רש״י Rashi said. רש״י Rashi says no, it's different. The כבשים and
the שתי הלחם are much more of a package because you don't
bring them separately. The לוג שמן log shemen of the מצורע metzora
with the שלמים... shelamim... you are more able to bring separately and
therefore it would be considered not ממנו לאישים. So that's that point.
One final thing, one final point to point out what תוספות Tosafot
reminds us of is that although there's a prohibition of putting the
edible
parts on the מזבח, sometimes you have to. And you have that
whole debate about—you might remember before—debate of תנאים tannaim
of
what happens if the limbs of an עולה get mixed up with
the limbs of a חטאת? Do you leave it all at the
bottom of the מזבח and let it all become פסול, pasul, or
do you put it all up on the top of the מזבח?
And there's one opinion that you put it all up on the
top of the מזבח. What about the prohibition of not burning the
parts that you're eating? So he says, well, we're going to treat
that as firewood, right? We're not going to treat it as—we're not
saying I'm offering those parts up and putting them up, but not
as an offering. I'm putting them up as fuel and as firewood.
And that is a limit to this prohibition. There are times where
according to some where based on a debate of תנאים, tannaim, you
might actually have to put them up on the מזבח if things
get mixed up, but that will be allowed if you frame it
as firewood and not as an offering. Okay, so this is the
prohibition of כל שממנו לאישים kol she-mimmennu le-isheem and the question of
to what degree does that extend to—is that anything only when ממנו
לאישים, which as I said, more starkly labels the other part as
not going on the fire, or is it really any קרבן, the
part you eat you don't burn? And it seems like we adopt
the more broader definition. Now we turn to what we alluded to
before, the word כל. kol. כל שאור וכל דבש, kol seor ve-chol
devash, right? Getting us back to the prohibition of offering up חמץ
chametz on the מזבח, the כל kol is even including a smaller
amount, a small amount than a normal שיעור. shiur. So let's take
a look at what that comes to include. תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan:
שאור se’or? וכל ve-chol חמץ chametz בל תקטירו. bal taktiru. That's in
the prohibition of offering up. אין לי אלא כולו, ein li ella
kullo, I only know you can't bring it all up—all presumably means
the whole קומץ, kometz. right? You would normally offer up a קומץ
kometz, on the מזבח as the מנחה. mincha So I only know
maybe a full amount, presumably a קומץ. kometz ומקצתו מנין? u-miktzato minayin?
How do I know not even a full amount? תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar כל—even kol any amount, meaning even not a full amount, even
a little bit. עירובו מנין? eiruvo minayin? How do I know if
it's not coming by itself, if it's maybe you mix it up
with something else? You mixed it up with מצה, matzah, you mixed
it up with who knows what. So maybe it's not—maybe it's only
when the thing comes separate and not when it comes in some
type of a תערובת? taaroves? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar כי כל. ki
chol. It doesn't just say כל, kol, it says כי כל, ki
chol, which means even any, like even the—you know—even in any manifestation,
even a small amount, even in a תערובת, taaroves, you transgress either
way. Okay. מאי קאמר? mai ka-amar? What's it saying? Now, which means
how much is the שיעור shiur and what does it mean even
less than the שיעור? shiur? So אמר אביי amar Abaye הכי קאמר,
hachi ka-amar, this is what it means. שאור בל תקטירו, seor bal
taktiru, I know you can't offer up שאור. se’or, אין לי אלא
כזית, ein li ella ke-zayis, I would only think that I would—you
only transgress with a כזית. ke-zayis. חצי זית מנין? chatzi zayis minayin?
How do I know even half of a כזית? ke-zayis? תלמוד לומר
talmud lomar כל. kol. So that tells you even less than כזית.
ke-zayis. Now I will say that once it's less than a כזית,
ke-zayis, then it's infinitesimal. There is no הלכתי שיעור shiur of significance
sort of within this context, in another context yes, but in this
context less than a כזית. ke-zayis. So once he's saying it doesn't
have to be a whole כזית, ke-zayis, he's really saying it could
be the tiniest amount. That's what אביי Abaye says. עירובו מנין? eiruvo
minayin? Now how do I know even if it's some type of
a תערובת taaroves where it's not ניכר, nikkar, maybe that you would
get off? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar כי כל. ki chol. Okay. So
anyway for אביי, Abaye, the חידוש chiddush is even less than a
כזית, ke-zayis, which winds up meaning even the tiniest amount. Where do
you get עירוב eiruv from כי? ki? Because כי כל, ki chol,
I don't know, some of them understand כי ki as an intensifier,
okay, which means even the—you know—whatever form of it, it should not
be. Let's just understand it as an intensifier. Okay. רבא אמר, Rava
amar, רבא Rava says, הכי קאמר. hachi ka-amar. No, this is how
you read it. שאור בל תקטירו. seor bal taktiru. I know you
can't offer up שאור. se'or אין לי אלא קומץ. ein li ella
kometz. I wouldn't have started with a כזית ke-zayis as a הוה
אמינא. I would have started as a קומץ, kometz, a handbreadth. חצי
קומץ מנין? chatzi kometz minayin? How do I know even a half
of a handbreadth? Which might still be a כזית. ke-zayis. Okay, so
רבא, Rava, you still might have a bottom amount of a כזית.
ke-zayis. You don't need a full handbreadth, but you might still need
a כזית. ke-zayis. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar כל. kol. עירובו מנין? eiruvo
minayin? How do I know even with תערובת? taaroves? תלמוד לומר talmud
lomar כי כל. ki chol. Okay. So according to this, the—it seems
the debate of אביי ורבא Abaye ve-Rava is that אביי Abaye winds
up saying even less than a full כזית ke-zayis which means even
an infinitesimal amount and רבא Rava says even less than a קומץ
kometz? but presumably you have to be a כזית. ke-zayis. So if
you have a half a כזית, ke-zayis, I'm not—I'm not liable? If
you have a כזית, ke-zayis, right, I mean it might be חצי
שיעור chatzi shiur but you don't get מלקות, malkos, you don't get—okay.
So now, פשט of this debate is, you know, when the תורה
Torah speaks about doing הקטרה, haktarah, you know, how much is it
sort of—it sounds like they're debating what's my starting point? Is my
starting point to assume the תורה Torah means כזית ke-zayis which is
a normal amount that we normally think about, you know, eating and
so on, or is it that the תורה Torah is thinking about
or—או—קומץ, which is the normal amount that we think about not in
terms of eating, but in terms of הקטרה haktarah is normally a
קומץ? kometz. Okay, although we got to remind ourselves הקטרה haktarah is
not always a קומץ. kometz. הקטרת מנחה haktaras mincha is a קומץ.
kometz. הקטרה haktarah of let's say the לבונה levonah is not a—well,
actually that's not true, the לבונה levona is... by the לבונה of
a מנחה is a שהכל. she-hacol. It’s not a קומץ. kometz. So
not every הקטרה haktara is a קומץ. kometz. And you know תוספות
Tosafot discussed just two examples of where you have this contracted: פגול
Pigul and מעלה בחוץ. Ma’aleh Bechutz. By פגול, Pigul, everybody remember פגול?
Pigul? Can’t get away from פגול, Pigul, although the גמרא Gemara isn’t
doing it now, תוספות Tosafot is. If you have a מחשבה machshava
to be מקטיר maktir חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, you’re it’s פגול. Pigul.
How much are you thinking to be מקטיר? maktir? Anybody remember what
the שיעור shiur was? Michael, no? Trying to think. I mean, I
think if you have מחשבה machshava to eat חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano
it’s a כזית, kezayit, and even if you have מחשבה machshava to
be מקטיר maktir חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano it’s a כזית. kezayit. So
מחשבת פגול machshavat pigul is ככזית. kikezayit. Now that could be because
it’s linked to אכילה. achila. But when it comes to be מעלה
בחוץ, ma’aleh bechutz, the amount of being מעלה בחוץ ma’aleh bechutz you’re
חייב chayav for is a קומץ. kometz, So sometimes when we think
about הקטרה haktara we think about a קומץ, kometz? sometimes we think
about a כזית, kezayit, and it seems like that’s the debate of
אביי ורבא, Abaye ve-Rava, what’s our point of departure: to assume כזית
kezayit or to assume קומץ? kometz Nevertheless the גמרא Gemara frames it
differently. The גמרא Gemara says that even אביי Abaye who started with
כזית, kezayit, everybody really agrees that your point of departure is קומץ
kometz and not כזית. kezayit. Let’s take a look. Yeah, that could
be the same thing. I mean, because we had that before, like
when you do a קומץ kometz? you’re basically doing כזיתים. kezayitim. Well,
that’s what we’re going to see. Okay, but I’m just saying without
before you get to the גמרא, Gemara it sounds like they’re starting
about is my point of departure when I think about הקטרה, haktara,
a כזית kezayit or is it a קומץ? kometz That’s what it
sounds like. But the גמרא Gemara is going to say no. Let’s
take a look. Okay, במאי קמיפלגי, bemai kamipalgi, what are they debating
about? אביי סבר, Abaye savar, יש קומץ פחות משני זיתים, yesh kometz
pachot mishnei zeitim, a קומץ kometz. exists less than two זיתים, zeitim,
ויש הקטרה פחותה מכזית. veyesh haktara pechuta mikezayit. And therefore there’s הקטרה
haktara less than כזית. kezayit. What does that mean? It means אביי
Abaye also agrees that my point of departure is a קומץ. kometz.
So the תורה Torah says don’t be מקריב makriv שאור, se'or, that
means don’t be מקריב makriv a קומץ. kometz But a קומץ kometz.
for אביי Abaye could mean less than two כזיתים. kezayitim. Okay, so
don’t then it says don’t even be מקריב makriv less than a
קומץ. kometz Now, less, תוספות Tosafot says for whatever reason we’re assuming
doesn’t mean a little bit less, it means even half of a
שיעור. shiur. So if when the תורה Torah says don’t do it,
it means don’t do a קומץ kometz, which is one point eight
כזיתים kezayitim possibly, and then it says don’t even do half, so
it’s saying don’t even do less than a כזית, kezayit, because if
I divide one point eight by two I get point nine, I
get less than a full כזית. kezayit. So yes, I start with
a קומץ, kometz but I halved it. And if my קומץ kometz,
is less than two כזיתים kezayitim and I halved it, then I’m
left with less than a כזית. kezayit. That’s what, that’s what אביי
Abaye says. And therefore יש הקטרה פחותה מכזית. yesh haktara pechuta mikezayit.
The תורה Torah will say don’t be מקריב, makriv, and even less
than a כזית kezayit is considered a being מקטיר maktir the שאור.
se'or ורבא אמר, Ve-Rava amar, and רבא Rava says differently. אין קומץ
פחות משני זיתים. ein kometz pachot mishnei zeitim. It we also start
with a קומץ, kometz but he assumes a קומץ kometz, does not
exist, like, you know, any normal person decides that their hand breadth
is at least two כזיתים kezayitim big. And therefore when the תורה
Torah says even less than the full amount, even half of the
full amount, half of two point one is still going to be
one point zero five, is still going to be more than a
כזית. kezayit. Okay, therefore ואין הקטרה פחותה מכזית, ve-ein haktara pechuta mikezayit,
you cannot consider it, it would not be considered an act of
הקטרה haktara less than a כזית. kezayit. So both אביי ורבא Abaye
ve-Rava start with the assumption that the תורה Torah is talking about
a קומץ, but for some reason when the תורה Torah says that
word כל, kol, it means half of the normal size. So for
אביי Abaye that gets him under a כזית. kezayit. Once you’re under
a כזית kezayit there’s no minimum amount, even the tiniest amount. רבא,
Rava, half of the full size still keeps you over a כזית.
kezayit. So for רבא Rava the minimum amount is a כזית. kezayit.
Less than a כזית kezayit is not considered an act of הקטרה.
haktara. And this problem also then winds up playing out in other
areas: do we consider הקטרה haktara to require at least a כזית
kezayit or can we consider something an act of הקטרה haktara even
less than כזית? kezayit? Okay, so there’s the question about what is
the שיעור, shiur, does a שיעור shiur exist for being מקטיר maktir
שאור? se'or For אביי Abaye at the end of the day the
answer is no. For רבא Rava the answer is yes. Now in
our last two three lines which lead to these huge תוספותים, Tosafotim,
we’re going to talk about this issue about תערובת. ta’arovet. So let’s
take a look. איתמר, Itmar, it was said. המעלה שאור ודבש, hama’aleh
se’or u-devash, he put on the מזבח שאור, se'or right, חמץ, chametz,
and honey, אגבי מזבח. agabei mizbe’ach. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, לוקה
משום שאור ולוקה משום דבש. loke mishum se’or ve-loke mishum devash. So
you’ve transgressed for putting honey on the מזבח, you’ve transgressed for putting
חמץ chametz on the מזבח, assuming you have a שיעור shiur by
all of it. ולוקה משום עירובי שאור ומשום עירובי דבש. ve-loke mishum
eiruvei se’or u-mishum eiruvei devash. And you also get מלקות malkut because
you have mixtures of it. Now, what are we talking about? What’s
the מציאות metziut here that we’re talking about? So תוספות Tosafot at
one moment thinks that we’re talking about that everything is בתערובת. be-ta’arovet.
Everything is בתערובת. be-ta’arovet. So you get not only for תערובת ta’arovet
as well, it’s true it’s תערובת, ta’arovet, but you not only have
honey here, you not only have תערובת ta’arovet honey here, you also
have honey here. You not only have תערובת ta’arovet חמץ chametz here,
you have real חמץ chametz here. So תוספות Tosafot thinks that maybe
that’s what it means. But תוספות Tosafot one minute, that’s absurd, because
then any תערובת ta’arovet you would get two lashes, you never just
get a lash for תערובת ta’arovet because you have both תערובת ta’arovet
and the thing itself. And even if that were true... Let the
גמרא Gemara say that more simply. Let the גמרא Gemara say, you
know, המעלה מתערובת חמץ לוקה שתים, hamale m'ta'aroves chametz lokei shtayim, המעלה
מתערובת דבש לוקה שתים, hamale m'ta'aroves devash lokei shtayim, and it doesn't
say that. So תוספות Tosafos rejects that possibility. תוספות Tosafos assumes what
we mean is you have them separate and let's say, you know,
and let's say in the middle they're בתערובת, b'ta'aroves, okay? So you
have a lump of dough here, you have a whole thing of
honey here, you bring it together, here you have your separate dough,
here you have a separate honey, in the middle they're all בתערובת.
b'ta'aroves. That's the case, that's the physical case we're talking about. So
comes along רבא Rava and he says, okay, for the שאור se'or
you get מלקות, malkos, for the דבש devash, you get מלקות. malkos.
What do you have in the middle? You have תערובת ta'aroves here,
mixture of honey and שאור, se'or mixture of שאור se'or and honey.
And שאור se'or and honey, exactly. So for you get one set
of מלקות malkos for כל שאור kol se'or and one set of
מלקות malkos for כל דבש. kol devash. Okay? So one for שאור
se'or and one for דבש, devash and in the middle you have
both כל שאור kol se'or and כל דבש kol devash and you
have two more sets of מלקות, malkos, that's four. That's רבא. Rava.
What would be the motivation of someone to do? What did they
ever tell us about practical? Yeah, well that is... okay, so some
things what goes on, right, and then so the גמרא Gemara is
not, right, the גמרא Gemara is just interested in exploring, you know,
this theoretical. If you want to imagine why is this actually happening,
yes I think that that would be a good possibility. The רמב"ם
Rambam thinks actually, you know, posted about this on the blog about
what's the reason for the prohibition of חמץ. chametz. So some want
to say that חמץ chametz like represents, you know, decay and corruption
and it's like always symbolically bad, like and you know you hear
that type of stuff around פסח Pesach time that חמץ chametz is
in the definition of bad. But then הקרבת מנחה בשבועות hakravas mincha
b'Shavuos though, right? So I find that very difficult to think about
it in those terms and you know, חמץ chametz is acceptable for
eleven and a half months of the year and you know, bread
is supposed to be a positive symbol. Anyway, I'm much more attracted
to רמב"ם's Rambam's understanding that the prohibition of דבש devash and of
חמץ chametz relates to pagan fertility rituals. And that therefore and therefore
you might be motivated to do it and the תורה Torah says
keep it away and you understand why. And then why doing on
שבועות? Shavuos? First of all you understand by שבועות, Shavuos, ביכורים, that's
when that's exactly, that's exactly. The רמב"ם Rambam also some understand that
the prohibition of, I wrote about all this on the blog, read
my blog, the prohibition of בשר בחלב basar b'chalav is also linked
in the תורה Torah to ביכורים, right? ביכורים to ביכורים. ראשית ביכורי
אדמתך תביא בית ה' אלוהיך לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו. Reishis bikkurei
admascha tavi beis Hashem Elokecha, lo sevashel gdi b'chalev imo. Exactly. So
why? So the ספורנו Sforno says because people would be this is
the time of the year, the spring, the fertility, you know, the
produce of it, that people would do fertility rituals, okay? And therefore
that's the period of ביכורים and and you can understand that you
take the mother's milk, which is about, you know, giving birth and
nurturing, you know people only give milk if they've given birth, the
kid goat which was just a newly born thing, and you use
it in some type of fertility ritual and that's why the תורה
Torah juxtaposes the prohibition of בשר בחלב basar b'chalav with ביכורים. And
that's also why it juxtaposes it's the time of ביכורים, you don't
bring the ביכורים on the מזבח. You can give ביכורים, you don't
bring it on the מזבח. You don't bring חמץ chametz on the
מזבח, you could have it together with your שתי הלחם which is
also at the time of שבועות. Shavuos. So yes, maybe these things
are there as symbols but they certainly don't go on the מזבח,
let's not turn them into fertility. The analogy is fertility, we don't
want to turn them into pagan fertility. Exactly, basically. And you know
if again the point I made on the blog was there to
compromise, but בשר בחלב basar b'chalav is completely forbidden because בשר בחלב
basar b'chalav is not just the problem that it's evoking fertility but
you're actually reversing the point. You're taking things that are fertile and
you're sort of using them in a destructive way, you're using them
to turn them into meat, to not to represent the opposite of
life. Anyway, okay, that's so that's for the little השקפה hashkafa whatever,
דבר תורה, dvar Torah, השקפה hashkafa back to the גמרא here. So
if you wanted to say what maybe is going on in the
mind of רבא, Rava, right, maybe he's trying to do this as
a pagan ritual. Okay, but whatever is the motivation, you've got your
dough here, honey here, your mixture in the middle, so you get
one מלקות malkos for this, one מלקות malkos for that for each
one separate and two מלקות malkos from the middle because it's both
a honey mixture and a dough mixture. Fine, that's what רבא Rava
says, makes a lot of sense. Let's see what אביי Abaye says.
Okay, ומשום רב חסדא, umishum Rav Chisda, אביי Abaye says אין לוקין
עליו שבכללות. ein lokin alav shebiklalos. You don't get מלקות malkos for
a generic לאו. Now what does לאו שבכללות lav shebiklalos mean? There
has been so much literature on it which is also why there
are these huge תוספותים Tosafos-im and the גמרא doesn't always mean the
same thing by it. But basically it means that if the תורה
Torah is not saying something specific, it doesn't mean that it's not
prohibiting separate things. For example, רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos are very
quick to point out that when it says even if in one
פסוק pasuk it has two things, like כל שאור וכל דבש, kol
se'or v'kol devash, that's not a generic לאו. It's explicitly labeling the
things that are prohibited and those are separate prohibitions. Similarly, you know,
this week's פרשה, parsha, it says because who a כהן Kohen is
not allowed to marry. It says אלמנה וגרושה וחללה זונה את אלה
לא יקח. almanah u'grushah v'chalalah zonah es eileh lo yikach. No, that's
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol but anyway let's talk about that. So
all these things are listed. לאו שבכללות lav she'bichlalos is much more
a very general prohibition like when it says by חומר פסח chomer
pesach it says אל תאכלו ממנו נא ובשל מבושל במים, al tochlu
mimenu na u'bashel mevushal ba'mayim, so that's specific, half-cooked or cooked, it
says כי אם צלי אש. ki im tzli eish. So the גמרא
says כי אם צלי אש ki im tzli eish is another prohibition.
Don't eat from it anyway other than being צלי אש. tzli eish.
So even if it's not נא na or מבושל, mevushal, let's say
you did something else, you ate it raw, you transgress don't eat
from it כי אם צלי אש. ki im tzli eish. Don't eat
from it in any way that is not צלי אש. tzli eish.
That's very general, that can constitute a lot of different possibilities. Or
by a נזיר. Nazir. What's a נזיר Nazir not allowed to eat?
He says he can't eat מכל אשר יעשה mikol asher ye'aseh מחרצנים
ועד זג לא יאכל meichartzanim ve'ad zag lo yocheil says, but there's
one פסוק pasuk so it says so that מכל אשר יעשה mikol
asher ye'aseh which is very general can include a lot of different
types of phenomenon, that is a לאו שבכללות. lav she'bichlalos. So comes
along again, that's very general, there's a lot of problems with exactly
defining its parameters which is why you have these huge תוספות. Tosafos.
So comes along אביי Abaye and אביי Abaye says when it says
כל שאור כל דבש kol se'or kol devash which means תערובת, ta'aroves,
so that is a תערובת ta'aroves of what? Is it honey and
is it honey and meat? Is it honey and this? Is it
honey and fruit? Is it honey... there's a million types of תערובת
ta'aroves you could have and it's a very general category. You don't
get מלקות malkus for a general category. So yes you get for
the חמץ chametz by itself and for the דבש devash by itself,
but for the mixture it's too much of a general category, you
don't get מלקות. malkus. It's prohibited, but you don't get מלקות. malkus.
אביי Abaye says אין לוקין על לאו שבכללות. ein lokin al lav
she'bichlalos. Now the גמרא has two reads of אביי. Abaye. איכא דאמרי
חדא מיהא לקי, ika de'amri chada miha laki, איכא דאמרי חדא נמי
לא לקי, ika de'amri chada nami lo laki, דלא מיחד לאוי כלאו
דחסימה. d'lo meyached lavei k'lav d'chasimah. Some say at least you get
one lashes and some say you even don't get one lashes because
it's not specific or it's not sort of singles out like the
prohibition of חסימה. chasimah. Wait, here's two, one set, no, I'm going
to tell you two possibilities, wait a minute. So what's the prohibition
of חסימה? chasimah? לא תחסום שור בדישו, lo sachsom shor be'disho, do
not muzzle an ox, is juxtaposed to the Torah's description of giving
lashes. So from there the גמרא says that that is a paradigm
of the type of prohibition you need to give lashes for. And
therefore that prohibition is very specific. When it's not so specific, you
don't even give one set. Now, what does it mean you don't
get one set? תוספות Tosafos says very radically, broadly, that you don't
even get lashes for the שאור part or for the דבש devash
part by itself. He says since it's in a פסוק pasuk that
includes a lot of different sins, כי כל שאור וכל דבש לא
תקטירו ממנו, ki kol se'or ve'chol devash lo saktiru mimenu, include דבש
devash. and include שאור and include תערובת דבש, ta'aroves devash, include תערובת
שאור, ta'aroves se'or, there are so many things going on in that
פסוק that you don't get lashes for any of them. Now that
you get zero, so you get zero for the whole thing. That
even if you just did straight straight שאור according to this, you
would not get lashes. It's a לאו, but you don't get lashes
because it's in a פסוק that's got a lot of other stuff
going on. Now, you could say that, but then you got to
go look at a million examples which would seem to violate that,
which would seem like you do get lashes. Why? How about what
we just said by the כהן? kohen? אלמנה וגרושה חללה זונה almanah
u'grushah chalalah zonah also got a lot of stuff going on. That's
what רש"י says, that seems to be a little bit too extreme.
I think the easier way to read it is no, of course
you get for the שאור and the דבש. devash The question is
in the middle you've got this mixture. So maybe, remember רבא Rava
said you get two sets of lashes. What's אביי Abaye argue? Is
אביי Abaye saying zero for the middle or only one? That's the
simple way to read it. And then you can understand zero is
לאו מיהד לאוי כלאו דחסימה, lav miyached lavei k'lav d'chasimah, that by
חסימה chasimah לא תחסום lo sachsom it's a very specific act. Here
כל שאור כל דבש kol se'or kol devash are as I said
before somewhat generic categories, they're broad and inclusive categories. So you get
zero for the middle. Or you could say no, yes, if you
had just a תערובת ta'aroves of שאור you'd get lashes, just a
תערובת ta'aroves of דבש you'd get lashes. But when they come together
the fact that those aren't going to be a separate lashes for
תערובת שאור ta'aroves se'or and separate lashes for תערובת דבש, ta'aroves devash,
there's only going to be one set of lashes for any form
of תערובת. ta'aroves. So therefore the לאו שבכללות lav she'bichlalos means don't
go ahead and have multiple lashes for לאו שבכללות lav she'bichlalos whenever
something falls into the תערובת, ta'aroves, even if one is a תערובת
שאור ta'aroves se'or and one is תערובת דבש, ta'aroves devash, it's only
going to be one. That's the easier way to read אביי. Abaye.
So רבא Rava says two sets of lashes for the middle and
אביי Abaye says no, either zero because those categories are too generic
to begin with or at most one, because yes, the generic maybe
you still get lashes, but you're not going to get lashes because
it fell into that category in two different ways. And with this
we will end and we start a new משנה.