It's מנחות י"ח Menachot Yud Chet starting at the bottom of י"ז
עמוד ב' Yud Zayin Amud Bet
at a three lines from the bottom near the end of the
line לא. Lo. But I'll say one thing first of all because
it was an interesting debate Michael and I were having yesterday or
misunderstanding which finally became clear that Michael is understanding that the way
the לבונה Levona was brought is that it was put in the
כלי Kli with the קומץ Kometz and then it was all put
on the מזבח Mizbeach and I had been understanding from the last
like week and a half that you first do the קומץ Kometz
in the כלי Kli and then afterwards the לבונה Levona and the
גמרא Gemara even says that sometimes you can reverse the order and
throughout the entire גמרא Gemara it's been assuming with all the פיגול
Pigul discussion that the קומץ Kometz and לבונה Levona are done separately
and it even talks about doing one before the other and the
order doesn't matter and so on. So I did some חיפוש Chipush
and I found that Michael's assumption based on the book he had
read was actually that that book was adopting a statement of the
רמב"ם Rambam and the רמב"ם Rambam does say that you put it
in the כלי Kli and you put it all together based on
a line in a גמרא Gemara in סוטה. Sotah. However the גרי"ז
Griz and the קרן אורה Keren Orah and other אחרונים Achronim point
out first of all it's completely against רש"י Rashi why רש"י Rashi
in our גמרא Gemara throughout has been saying what I've been
saying but basically everything here based on our many דפים Dapim have
been assuming that they're separate and that they basically say that based
on סוגיות Sugyot the רמב"ם Rambam would have to agree that בדיעבד
Bedieved if you put it in a different כלי Kli and were
מקטיר Maktir that that would be fine and he can't understand all
of these סוגיות Sugyot without that but that fundamentally רמב"ם Rambam is
basing himself on one line in the גמרא Gemara in סוטה Sotah
which is against our סוגיה. Sugya. And the other difference interestingly is
that רש"י Rashi again states and again the simple sense of all
these גמרות Gemarot that there's no עבודה Avodah with the לבונה Levona
until you burn it maybe the discussion of gathering the לבונה Levona
off the מנחה Mincha but there's no putting it in a כלי,
Kli, there's no הילוך, Hilluch, the עבודה Avodah is the burning it
which is why we don't have the discussion of מפגל בחצי מתיר
Mafgil B'Chatzey Matir until the actual act of burning because until then
the לבונה Levona is not really doing anything. The רמב"ם Rambam that
understands that you have a נתינת כלי Nesinas Kli by the לבונה
Levona and a הילוך Hilluch by the לבונה Levona applies the idea
of חצי מתיר Chatzey Matir to the earlier stages of the לבונה
Levona as well which is again very much against the גמרא Gemara
as we said which at most considered it by the הילוך. Hilluch.
So it's a very interesting שיטת הרמב"ם Shitas HaRambam but I would
say very much against the גמרא Gemara we've been learning which explains
our debate but it also explains why you can't assume that the
power of pictures in a certain way you see the picture it
like burns in your memory that this is how it's done but
the pictures are reflecting certain positions which are not
necessarily yours
but how do you physically get it onto the מזבח? Mizbeach?
So according to רש"י Rashi you scoop it up in your
hand right and or whatever you do the קומץ Kometz then you
walk up to the מזבח Mizbeach and you burn.
But you're already holding so
you have to do it sequentially, exactly.
Wow you could be standing with the מנחה, Mincha, you could bring
the מנחה Mincha to the top of the מזבח Mizbeach and you
could do this and put it in the כלי Kli and then
do that and then do that but you're right I mean the
רמב"ם Rambam sort of simplifies the process.
But based on a גמרא Gemara in סוטה Sotah how does
רש"י, Rashi, I don't know, they say that maybe it's a מחלוקת
Machlokes of the סוגיות Sugyot and so on okay but the רמב"ם
Rambam totally goes by that whereas רש"י Rashi is adopting the dominant
but you know Rivka asks a good point if you've got to
do it separately either you have two כוהנים Kohanim involved or it
requires a little bit of juggling. True, okay.
So let's take a look
now we're on the ramp and we go back and up,
yeah you can, that's essentially what I'm saying, yeah, okay. So now
the גמרא Gemara on the bottom of
י"ז עמוד ב' Yud Zayin Amud Bet the
following: לא, Lo, דכולי עלמא Dechulei Alma כרת Karet לכם, Lakhem, no
no no,
nobody would say Rabbi Eliezer says כרת Karet that it's real פיגול
Pigul and all the attempt to read it in a פסוק Pasuk
is misguided, he's not basing himself on a פסוק, Pasuk, it's all
a purely rabbinic concern and that's why he consistently says
פסול, Pasul, alright? So what is the debate then that's going on
within Rabbi Eliezer? בהא ג' מחלוקות בדבר, Beha Gimmel Machlokot Badavar, the
three-way debate. תנא קמא סבר בהנך פליגי Tanna Kamma savar behanach pligi,
להניח דברי חכמים. L'haniach Divrei Chachamim.
So if you remember the ברייתא Braisa we were working off of
first quoted the debate of Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים Chachamim when
you were planning on eating the קומץ Kometz or burning the לבונה
Levona or the שיירים Shirayim and it didn't mention what the הלכה
Halakha would be if you were planning on leaving it over. Then
Rabbi Yehuda says oh if you leave it over it's פסול Pasul
and then... The third opinion, who was it? רב אלעזר Rav Elozar
says, no, this is the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
the חכמים Chachamim as well. So here's the three-way debate. The three-way
debate is what is the status of להניח? lehanniach? Okay. And let's
take a look. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma סבר בהנך פליגי, Savar behanach
pligi, they debate when you plan on doing אכילת אדם, achilas adam,
אכילת מזבח. achilas mizbeach. להניח, lehanniach, if you plan on leaving it
over, דברי הכל כשר. divrei hakol kasher. Everybody would say okay, right?
Even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that, I normally invalidate it
and now we're going to assume מדרבנן midrabanan if you switch אכילת
אדם achilas adam and אכילת מזבח, achilas mizbeach, that's because at least
you're having פיגול piggul types of thought. You're thinking about eating and
consuming and so on, thus you're switching the objects. But if you
just think about leaving it over, that's completely out of the פיגול
piggul category. Now again, it doesn't mean it's מותר muttar to leave
over. The surprising thing though is that פיגול piggul is not every
thought of something that's wrong to do. It's only the specific idea
of eating and being מקטיר maktir and being זורק הדם zorek hadam
and so on. So therefore, that's a logical position, that if דרבנן,
drabanan, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wouldn't be bothered by להניח, lehanniach, which
is a totally different category.
That's the first opinion. רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and then רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says, no, this is פסול. posul. סבר Savar בהנך פליגי,
Behanach Pligi yet they debate by אדם adam and מזבח. mizbeach. להניח
דברי הכל פסול, Lehanniach divrei hakol posul, opposite of what the Rabbis
say. Even the רבנן Rabbanan say that להניח lehanniach would be a
פסול דרבנן. psul drabanan. מאי טעמא, Mai taama, says the גמרא Gemara
jumps in and explains why it's worse. גזירה מקצת דמו אטו כל
דמו, Gezeira maktzas damo atu kol damo, וכל דמו פסולה דאורייתא. v'kol
damo psula d'oraisa. Because we're going to assert that even the רבנן
Rabbanan who say אדם adam and מזבח mizbeach is not a problem,
would say that if you're planning on leaving over all of the
blood, it is פסול דאורייתא. posul d'oraisa. Why? Because were you to
leave over all the blood, then what would that do? Then the
קרבן korban would not be כשר, kosher, would never have זריקת הדם
בזמנו, zerikas hadam bizmano, well not exactly also but anyway because you're
not leaving over the meat after it's הותר, huttar, but the דם
dam would never have been נזרק בזמנו nizrak bizmano and it would
be פסול. posul. And now we're going to find, and this was
actually discussed way back when in a משנה Mishna in זבחים, Zevachim,
you might remember roughly at the same state, I think at י"ז,
yud-zayin, about what if you had a דעת daas to... let me
just read you the משנה Mishna for one second. I think it's
י"ז, yud-zayin, hold on...
here it is, no not י"ז, yud-zayin, where is it? ל"ו lamed-vav
maybe? Hold on...
ל"ו, lamed-vav, I'm sorry, ל"ו. lamed-vav. Okay, so the משנה Mishna says
like
this. שחט על מנת להניח דמו או אימוריו למחר או להוציאן לחוץ
רבי יהודה פוסל וחכמים מכשירין. Shachas al m'nas lehanniach damo o imurav
l'machar o l'hotziyan lachutz, Rabbi Yehuda posel vechachamim machshirin. So you plan
on doing a thought that had you done it would invalidate, there
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says פסול posul even though it's not פיגול,
piggul, your thought is like you did it and it invalidated. So
what מר Mar is saying here is that
even those who argue on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and say that
a מחשבה machshava to leave over the blood does not פסול, posul,
does not... it's not a דאורייתא d'oraisa problem, would agree that the
thought to leave over all the blood, and were you to actually
do that the קרבן korban would never be הוקרב, hukrav, that would
פסול דאורייתא. posul d'oraisa. So since that would פסול דאורייתא, posul d'oraisa,
everybody would agree that it's פסול דרבנן posul drabanan if you plan
on leaving over some of the blood.
Okay, so
again, it's not exactly a clear proof, but this is what we're
saying, that להניח, lehanniach, if you assume כל דמו kol damo is
a פסול דאורייתא, psul d'oraisa, so להניח מקצת דמו lehanniach maktzas damo
says רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda everybody would agree would be פסול posul
at least דרבנן. drabanan. Okay, so that's the other side. And the
third side is,
ואתא רב אלעזר למימר, v'aso Rav Elazar l'meimar, and
רב אלעזר Rav Elozar is coming and saying אף בזו רבי אליעזר
פוסל וחכמים מכשירין. af b'zu Rabbi Eliezer posel v'chachamim machshirin. Okay, even
with this it's a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the
חכמים. Chachamim. רבי אליעזר... Rabbi Eliezer... So I've encountered this then, we're
saying two things: number one is the דם מזבח dam mizbeach split,
which for the גמרא Gemara made a pretty convincing argument you could
say is real פיגול. pigul. No, since רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says
פסול, possul, it's only דרבנן. derabbanan. Number two, what's the status of
להניח? lehaniach? Is להניח lehaniach better because it's a totally different type
of a thought, though it's not פיגול pigul at all, and nobody
would say it's even a דרבנן derabbanan problem? Is להניח lehaniach worse
based on the assumption that at least according to רבי יהודה, Rebbi
Yehuda, להניח כולו, lehaniach kulo, he thinks everybody should agree is פסול
דאורייתא? possul de'oraisa? Or is it within the same category that they
debate all things that are not פיגול דאורייתא, pigul de'oraisa, should we
make them פסול דרבנן? possul derabbanan? רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says yes
and the חכמים chachomim say no. Oh, okay. Yes.
I'm finding a hard time seeing, you know, if I plan to
let's say eat it another day, that's פיגול, pigul, but if I
plan to זורק zorek it another day or is להניח lehaniach just
to leave it over, not זורק zorek it or what? So להניח
lehaniach is to זורק zorek some and then leave the rest over?
That's really what להניח מקצת lehaniach miktas would be.
זורק zorek is to, well, you always in any קרבן korban leave
over some and you're going to and you're going to,
what do you call it, spill the rest. Oh, you mean how
could you have a thought of להניח מקצת lehaniach miktas if there's
always going to be מניח מקצת? maniach miktas? What type of a
thought is that according to רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? That's your question?
No, I'm trying to understand, like,
להניח, lehaniach, you plan on doing this זריקה zerika
on
time but then leaving some over, like, or or I'm just להניח
lehaniach it tomorrow and then do the זריקה? zerika? In which case...
No, no, no, no, so if להניח מקצת, lehaniach miktas, your question
is להניח כולו, lehaniach kulo, you understand I'm not going to do
anything. להניח מקצת, lehaniach miktas, why is that a meaningful thought? What
are you saying? I'm not going to be שופך השיריים? shofech hashirayim?
Who cares? No, so presumably what your thought is that you're planning
on being מניח maniach the stuff that you should be זורק. zorek.
Meaning not
do
the זריקה zerika at all?
Yeah, just I caught the blood in the כלי kli and I'm
not going to do anything with this.
That's להניח מקצת? lehaniach miktas? So then of course everyone would should
say if you don't really plan on doing the זריקה, zerika, then,
like, nothing gets off the ground. Yeah, if you don't do the
זריקה, zerika, since when do we say your thought
of of then then you're not going to do it? But then
we say that we treat every thought as if it was done?
That's רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda position, right? But the חכמים chachomim say
פיגול pigul is a very narrowly defined category of a thought of
חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. All right, so all right, Dad, do you
want to say something? Okay, so let's let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says וסבר רבי יהודה. vesavar Rebbi Yehuda. So
now we are continuing
יח עמוד א, yud ches amud aleph, one, two, three, six, seven
lines down, middle of the line. וסבר רבי יהודה להניח מדמה למחר
דברי הכל פסול. vesavar Rebbi Yehuda lehaniach midama lemachar divrei hakol possul.
Would רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda believe that when one plans להניח, lehaniach,
everybody agrees it's פסול, possul, meaning there's no debate of רבי אליעזר
Rebbi Eliezer and חכמים chachomim there? I mean, we know he would
say it's פסול, possul, but would he really say that it's not
debated? והתניא. vehatanya. We taught in a ברייתא braisa and now the
גמרא Gemara has a lovely little narrative. We're due for one. והתניא
אמר רבי. vehatanya amar Rebbi. רבי Rebbi says כשנחתי למצות מידותיו. keshenachati
limtzos midosav. Not למצוא. limtzo. למצות מידותיו. limtzos midosav.
So what does this mean?
רש״י Rashi says it's it's like to, if you look at
רש״י, Rashi, first narrow line, למצות מידותיו, limtzos midosav, לידע מיצוי תלמודו,
leida mitzui talmudo,
to know sort of the distillation or the essence of my learning,
ולשאול ספקותיו. ulishol sefeikosav. So
somehow מידותיו midosav means sort of the quality of my learning, and
למצות, limtzos, מיצוי, mitzui, to mean
like squeeze, right, like somehow the essence of my learning. So when
I came to clarify my learnings, so where did I go to
speak
to a greater rabbi who would help me
sort of, you know, get things very clear?
So what did he do? כשנחתי למצות מידותיו אצל רבי אלעזר בן
שמוע. keshenachati limtzos midosav etzel Rebbi Elazar ben Shammua. To רבי אלעזר
בן שמוע. Rebbi Elazar ben Shammua. ואמרי לה, veamri lah, and some
say למצות מידותיו של רבי אלעזר בן שמוע. limtzos midosav shel Rebbi
Elazar ben Shammua. I'm not trying to clarify my learning, I'm trying
to get the essence of his teaching. Okay, same point.
But the word doesn't mean teaching.
Well, we don't know about character, but you were applying it to
say like, you know, the essence of the quality of the teaching
or somehow, so you're right, it is funny that it is used
in this way. But anyway, he is saying, either I tried when
I was in a process of clarifying my own learning, or when
I went to learn, you know, the distillation, the essence of what
רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rebbi Elazar ben Shammua had to teach. What
did they translate it as? Well, let's see. To drain the measures
of רבי אלעזר בן שמוע. Rebbi Elazar ben Shammua.
To drain. Okay, drain. I like distillation better than drain.
It is, yeah, exactly, the distillation, the essence. Okay, anyway, okay, so
anyway, מצאתי יוסף הבבלי. matzasi Yosef Habavli.
I saw יוסף הבבלי. Yosef Habavli. And it's actually interesting, you know,
in the Tannaitic literature,
people are often explicitly labeled when they come from בבל. Bavel. Like
there's, you know, like when הלל Hillel comes from בבל, Bavel, it
says you know when they didn't know whether they can bring a
קרבן פסח korban pesach on שבת, Shabbos, it says אדם אחד עלה
מבבל והלל הבבלי שמו. adam echad ala mi'Bavel veHillel ha'Bavli shemo. So
clearly because the dominant rabbis of the תנאים Tannaim were in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so the Babylonians were labeled. Anyway, okay, מצאתי, matzasi,
I found יוסף הבבלי, Yosef Habavli, יושב לפניו yoshev lefanav was sitting
before him. in front of him, וחביב לו ביותר עד לאחת, vachaviv
lo beyoter ad leachat, and he was very dear to him. Now,
who is dear to whom? רש"י Rashi says two possibilities: either יוסף
Yosef was like a prize student of רב אלעזר בן שמוע, Rabbi
Eliezer ben Shamua, עד לאחת ad leachat like to an extreme or
singled out, or
יוסף Yosef or יוסף הבבלי Yosef haBavli was extremely dear to him
everything רב אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Eliezer ben Shamua was teaching. Now
the question of עד לאחת ad leachat might just mean like to
an extreme. If you look at תוספות Tosfos actually, עד אחת, ad
achat, he don't say לאחת, leachat, he says עד אחת. ad achat.
במגילת סתרים דרבינו נסים, BeMegillat Setarim deRabbeinu Nissim, that's fascinating, right? רבינו
נסים Rabbeinu Nissim wrote a little book of חידושים chiddushim on the
גמרא Gemara called מגילת סתרים, Megillat Setarim, like the hidden book, hidden
Megilla. Anyway, גרס עד לאחת פירושו עד מאד, gores ad leachat pirushu
ad meod, extremely.
כמא דמתרגמינן מאד לחודה, kema demetargaminan meod lechuda,
singularly or extremely. Okay, and then he has some other explanation. So,
he was dear to him, either the student to the rabbi or
the rabbi to the student, to an extremely dear or what רש"י
Rashi says is until they got or they had a great relationship
until they got to the following הלכה. Halacha. So, לאחת leachat means
one הלכה. Halacha. Let's see the following הלכה Halacha we're going to
say right now. אמר לו, amar lo, so יוסף הבבלי Yosef haBavli
said to
רב אלעזר בן שמוע: Rabbi Eliezer ben Shamua: רבי, השוחט את הזבח
להניח מדמו למחר מהו? Rebbi, hashochet et hazevach lehaniach midamo lemachar mahu?
If one slaughters a sacrifice and plans to leave over the blood
until tomorrow, what's the הלכה? Halacha? Which isn't our case of מנחות,
Menachos, it was the משנה, Mishnah, you know, way back when in
זבחים, Zvachim, interestingly though we did not get this discussion in זבחים.
Zvachim. If you look at the side on the right-hand margin, you
see where it comes from: תוספתא דזבחים פרק ב. Tosefta deZvachim perek
b. You see that in the right-hand margin, right of the רש"י?
Rashi? So obviously this is going on the משנה Mishnah back in
זבחים, Zvachim, but interestingly being quoted here.
So, he said to him: השוחט את הזבח להניח מדמו למחר מהו?
hashochet et hazevach lehaniach midamo lemachar mahu? What's the הלכה? Halacha? אמר
לו כשר, amar lo kasher, it's כשר. kasher. It's not פיגול pigul
and it's not even a דרבנן. derabbanan. ערבית אמר לו כשר. Arvit
amar lo kasher. And in the in the evening he said to
him כשר. kasher.
שחרית אמר לו
Shacharit
amar lo what?
No, no, no,
they were learning it in the evening. He said: what's the הלכה?
Halacha? He said כשר. kasher. Then he asked the next day: what's
the הלכה? Halacha? He said כשר. kasher. Okay.
שחרית אמר לו כשר. Shacharit amar lo kasher. Okay. צהריים אמר לו
כשר. Tzohorayim amar lo kasher. He obviously he kept on asking. Either
that as they were doing חזרה chazara till he memorized it, which
could be in an oral culture, but it seems like he kept
on asking. Okay. מנחה אמר לו כשר. Mincha amar lo kasher. אלא
שרבי אלעזר פוסל. ella sheRabbi Eliezer posel.
So finally by מנחה Mincha he said: alright, alright, it's true there's
an opinion of רב אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer that this is פוסל, posel,
but we're not talking about that. The הלכה Halacha is it's כשר.
kasher. But he finally sort of revealed this nuance by מנחה Mincha
time after a day.
אלא שרבי אלעזר פוסל. ella sheRabbi Eliezer posel. So what happened? צהבו
פניו של יוסף הבבלי. tzahavu panav shel Yosef haBavli. Oh, יוסף הבבלי's
Yosef haBavli face lit up that he heard the opinion of רב
אלעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So אמר לו, amar lo, so רב אלעזר בן
שמוע Rabbi Eliezer ben Shamua said to him: יוסף, כמדומני שלא כיוונו
שמועתינו עד עתה. Yosef, kimdumani shelo kivanu shemuateinu ad ata. It seems
to me like our learning has not been aligned until now. Which
basically means like I tell you a הלכה Halacha and you don't
accept what I say is הלכה, Halacha, you're interested in the דעת
יחיד da'at yachid or other possibilities out there. You know, here I
am, I'm trying to raise my star תלמיד, talmid, I want him
to come, I want him to like פסקן pasken הלכה Halacha and
know הלכה Halacha according to me, and he's not so sure that
what I'm saying should be הלכה. Halacha. So is that really true?
So he said: אמר לו רבי, הן, amar lo Rebbi, hein, yes,
yes, yes, of course I accept what you say is הלכה, Halacha,
not trying to פסקן pasken different than you. אלא שרבי יהודה פסול
שנה לי. ella sheRabbi Yehuda pasul shana li. רבי יהודה פסול שנה
לי. Rabbi Yehuda pasul shana li. When I learned from רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, he told me that it was פסול. pasul. Now I
don't פסקן pasken that for הלכה, Halacha, I go by you, you
say it's כשר. kasher. But I was trying to find the source
for רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda teaching. That was what I was interested
in. דחזרתי על כל תלמידיו ובקשתי מחברי ולא מצאתי. dechazarti al kol
talmidav uvikashti mechaveirai velo matzati. And
I consulted all of רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda students: is this true
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's פסול? pasul? And nobody could
corroborate it. And therefore what? And I was concerned, we'll see in
a minute, I was concerned maybe, or what רש"י Rashi says is
I was concerned maybe I had misremembered. I heard this thing from
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, none of his students corroborated it. I was
concerned maybe I had misremembered what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said. עכשיו
ששנית לי פסול, החזרת לי אבידתי. achshav sheshanita li pasul, hechazarta li
avedati. Now that you told me that רב אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
it's פסול, pasul,
you've returned to me my lost object. Now I know that it's
true what I remembered in the name of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is actually what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said, there is an opinion
out there. So don't be concerned that I'm trying to פסקן pasken
against you...
well we're going to see, רב אלעזר Rabbi Eliezer was like grand
Rebbi, we'll see, of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, okay? We'll see in
a minute.
So don't be concerned you were saying that I'm trying to, you
know, פסקן pasken against you or looking for opposing opinions, but I
was just trying to find, you know, this other things that I
heard. I was trying to corroborate that it was a legitimate opinion
out there. Okay, so what happened? זלגו עיניו דמעות של רבי אלעזר
בן שמוע. zalgu einav dimaot shel Rabbi Eliezer ben Shamua. רב אלעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer eyes like you know poured, gushed with tears. אמר, Amar,
he said, אשריכם תלמידי חכמים. Ashreichem talmidei chachamim.
Praised are you the students of the חכמים, Chachamim, and again here
תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim is meant in the narrowest sense, not the
way we use it, right? I'm the חכם, Chacham, רבי אלעזר בן
שמוע, Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua, and he was the תלמיד talmid of
the חכם, Chacham, okay, the student. Praised are the students of the
חכמים. Chachamim. דברי תורה חביבין עליכם ביותר, divrei Torah chavivin aleichem beyoter,
the words of Torah are so dear to you, are excessively dear
to you. קרא עליו המקרא הזה, kara alav hamikra hazeh, he said
on him the following פסוק: pasuk: מה אהבתי תורתך כל היום היא
שיחתי. mah ahavti Toratecha kol hayom hee sichati. How much I love
the Torah, every day, the whole day it is my speech, which
presumably means it's not just you want to know the
הלכה, halacha, you—every single thing is precious. You want to know all
the opinions, you want to make sure that what you remembered was
correct. So that, you know, that's what made him so joyous that
he was so concerned for the to
the what?
To
remember, to make sure
every opinion is recorded, right?
Okay.
הא מפני שרבי יהודה בנו של רבי אילעאי, Ha mipnei sheRabbi Yehuda
beno shel Rabbi Ilai, why was this true that you learned this
from רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was the
son of רבי אילעאי. Rabbi Ilai. רבי אילעאי תלמידו של רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Ilai talmido shel Rabbi Eliezer, and רבי אילעאי Rabbi Ilai was
a student of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. So therefore רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer's teaching פסוק pasuk got passed down to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and that's why what you heard from רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, yes,
is corroborated that this was an earlier teaching of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer.
I wonder why none of the students remembered it then. What? I
wonder why none of the students remembered it. Okay, anyway. לפיכך שנה
לך משנת רבי אליעזר. Lefichach shanah lecha mishnat Rabbi Eliezer. That's why
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda told you the position
of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which doesn't mean we פסקן pasken it.
Okay. Now, now the גמרא Gemara brought in this beautiful moving story.
It's so funny, you know, the גמרא Gemara brings in these like
really moving stories to get to like one little halachic point, right?
What?
The
why did it it must have occurred throughout ש"ס. Shas. Why did
they pick this story here? Yeah.
Well, we're going to see because it helps us resolve whether when
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says פסול, pasul, if he's saying everybody says
פסול, pasul, or רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying פסול. pasul. Okay?
So, but no, the but the you know, you definitely have אגדתות
aggadotas in the גמרא, Gemara, but sometimes you sort of see like
oh my god, there was like so much more to tell and
sometimes we only get exposed to it when it has a halachic
issue to address. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so now here's
the reason we brought in this whole wonderful story. The גמרא Gemara
says והאי סלקא דעתך דדברי הכל פסול אתניי, ve-hai salka daitach de-divrei
hakol pasul atnei, if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda when he says פסול
pasul by להניח lehaniach meant that everybody would agree it's פסול, pasul,
whether רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or the חכמים, Chachamim, in this case
if his claim was, in this case everybody would say it's פסול,
pasul, מר החזרת לי אבידתי, mar hichzarta li aveidati,
why did, you know, יוסף הבבלי Yosef HaBavli think that we had
now corroborated and restored the lost object, as it were? איהו פלוגתא
קאמר
ליה
ihu plugta ka-amar
leh because if he told him that it was a debate, meaning
what did רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua say? רבי
אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua said
כשר kasher ורבי
אליעזר פוסל.
ve-Rabbi Eliezer
posel. And now what did he hear from רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
According to the גמרא, Gemara, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda claims that everybody says it's פסול. pasul. So it
hasn't really been corroborated, right? רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben
Shamua says it's a debate of the חכמים Chachamim and רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, and he said I have a teaching from רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that it's פסול, pasul, but according to the גמרא's Gemara's
saying, but if that teaching was that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
claiming everybody says it's פסול, pasul, you're not really corroborating the teaching.
All right? Is that clear? Yes? All right. So the גמרא Gemara
concludes רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said everyone says it's פסול. pasul.
Right, meaning
meaning it would have corroborated if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said only
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's פסול, pasul, or my פסק pask
is it's פסול. pasul. But if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is claiming
everybody says it's פסול, pasul, it's not the same thing his רבי
rebbe is teaching him right now.
Right, it's teaching the opposite.
Right, his רבי rebbe is teaching it's a debate and that position
is a דעת יחיד. da'at yachid. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara said
איהו פלוגתא קאמר ליה, ihu plugta ka-amar leh, רבי יוסף Rabbi Yosef
and רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rabbi Elazar ben Shamua was telling him
it
was a מחלוקת, machlokes, not דברי הכל. divrei hakol. אלא מאי כשר
רבי
אליעזר פסול,
Ela mai kasher Rabbi Eliezer
pasul, so what do you want to claim? You want to claim
that when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's פסול, pasul, he means
it's a מחלוקת. machlokes. חכמים Chachamim say it's כשר kasher and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's
פסול.
pasul. פסול אתניי, Pasul atnei, but
when
יוסף הבבלי Yosef HaBavli heard it from רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, all
he says that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said was פסול. pasul. He
didn't say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda told me it was a מחלוקת,
machlokes, he said רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda told me it was פסול.
pasul. Now of course that could mean that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says that I, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, say it's פסול, pasul, but
I'm not saying everybody says it. But the גמרא Gemara feels that
since רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's quote was, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said
פסול, pasul, it sounds like everybody. Because the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי מאי הא מפני, ee hachi mai ha mipnei, what does it
mean?
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, but when the גמרא Gemara
says, you know, הא ha that because he's a student of רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, etc., הא מפני, ha mipnei,
so it's because he's a student of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that's
why he teaches you the position of רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. אנן
נמי פלוגתא קא מתנינן, anan nami plugta ka matninan,
so רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Meaning the גמרא Gemara is saying like
this: when
רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yose, when רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rebbe Elazar ben
Shamoah
said, oh, you know why you heard that from רבי יהודה? Rebbe
Yehuda? Because רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is following the tradition of רבי
אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. Now, that sounds like רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is
only presenting one side of the argument. It sounds like רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda is saying it's פסול. posul. You know why he said
פסול? posul? He's following his רבי'ס Rebbe's רבי. Rebbe. Okay, or his
father's רבי. Rebbe. But if רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is actually giving
him the accurate story, if רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is actually saying
it's a מחלוקת, machlokes, then it's not just that he's saying it
because he's following his רבי Rebbe you know his father's רבי. Rebbe.
Everybody agrees it's a מחלוקת. machlokes. So since it was framed that
the reason you heard this from רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda was he
was following רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer who was his father's רבי, Rebbe,
it sounds like רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is presenting it as though
this is the only opinion. It's פסול. posul. Okay? So now we
get to say that the simple sense of that story, right, on
the one hand we have basically an internal problem in the story,
which is not such a problem. It sounds like רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda transmitted it as if in an implicit way as if everybody
says it's
פסול posul and יוסי Yosef and רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rebbe Elazar
ben Shamoah said it's a מחלוקת. machlokes. So how do we say
החזרת לי אבדתי? hichtiri avedasi? Now the answer is simple. What he's
saying is רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda presented it as if it were
דברי הכל. divei hakol. What did he mean he claimed it was
דברי הכל? divei hakol? He didn't show you the alternate position because
he's following his tradition. But in reality it's a מחלוקת, machlokes, which
doesn't mean that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is explicitly claiming that it's
דברי הכל. divei hakol. Nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is bothered by this.
It seems that the fact that רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer presented it,
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda presented it the way he did, sounds like
he was claiming it was דברי הכל. divei hakol. So let's take
a look how the גמרא Gemara says this, והחזרת לי אבדתי. ve-hichtiri
avedasi. ולעולם דברי הכל פסול אתנייה. u-le'olam divei hakol posul asniye. So
really רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda did not say it's a מחלוקת. machlokes.
He said, now explicitly, I would have said implicitly, but he said
explicitly, everybody says it's פסול. posul. If that's true, מאי החזרת לי
אבדתי? mai hachzarta li avedasi? So why did he say you returned
me my אבדה aveda if what רבי אלעזר בן שמוע Rebbe Elazar
ben Shamoah is saying is a date, דהדר ליה משום פסלות דעלמא?
de-hadar leh mei-ha-shum paslus l'olam? Because at least he corroborated that there's
an opinion out there that says it's פסול. posul. Okay, so basically
this whole lovely story was brought to say when רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda says להניח lehaniach is פסול, posul, if he's saying that everybody
says it's פסול, posul, it's just רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. And since
we have this story where he says oh I heard that רבי
יהודה Rebbe Yehuda said רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says it's פסול, posul,
the גמרא Gemara says it makes it sound like רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda was claiming everybody says it's פסול. posul. Okay, and then he
said no, no, no, it's not true, it's not everybody, it's a
מחלוקת. machlokes. So anyway, the better way to resolve it I would
have thought would have been to say that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
was not in all these cases רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda isn't being
clear דברי הכל, divei hakol, just רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says פסול.
posul. So the whole point actually is that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
is not clarifying who the opinion is, he's presenting the opinion of
פסול posul because that is the position of רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer,
but he's not actually claiming that it's דברי הכל, divei hakol, he's
just כגוני אפיי. kakani appai. All right, either way the גמרא Gemara
concludes that רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is claiming that it was דברי
הכל, divei hakol, and we do have this lovely story here. But
what we do find out is it gets us back to the
idea that if פיגול pigul thought, would it apply to things that
are not specifically about פיגול, pigul, would it apply to להניח, lehaniach,
and that goes back to the debate we have way before in
זבחים Zvachim by the position of רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, which we
see goes back to רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer as well. Yep.
Did רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer live in the time of the המקדש?
Mikdash? He was old enough at the המקדש Mikdash at the time.
How old was he?
He was at the המקדש, Mikdash, so he may have been giving
an actual fact, not necessarily an opinion.
Like even in the time of the המקדש, Mikdash, you wonder how
often פיגול pigul came up.
Okay.
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda is quoting his father who was who's father?
Right, let's go back two generations.
So this is
אליעזר בן הורקנוס. Eliezer ben Hurkanos. תנא רבי אליעזר. Tan Rebbe Eliezer.
Yeah it was right around the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. Look what
it says about him.
רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, תנא בדור שני. Tanna ba-dor sheni. Oh he
was a student of רבי יוחנן בן זכאי. Rebbe Yochanan ben Zakkai.
So רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rebbe Yochanan ben Zakkai was at the
חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis. So he was, he might
have,
right.
That would lend.
So right,
it is getting closer to the actual event. So doing a פיגול
pigul ever happen enough to record these nuances? Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says נו משנה. nu masha. Okay, so that was a
debate of when do we say פסול דרבנן? posul de-rabbanan? Now, now
we actually guess what? You shift from פיגול pigul and we actually
talk about the requirement of making the מנחה. mincha. So again it
sort of follows the interesting pattern that we had by זבחים Zvachim
that first you talk about the invalidities and then you get to
the actual doing, except It's much quicker here; you notice we work
through the things a lot easier because we've already had them in
זבחים. Zvachim. So we talked about שלא לשמה, Shelo Lishma, we talked
about when פסולים psulim do the עבודה, avoda, we talked about wrong
מחשבה machshava and פיגול Pigul and now we actually talk about the
process, but even when we talk about the process, we talk about
what mistakes you could make and whether they're a problem or not
before we lay out the process. So let's look now at the
משנה. Mishna. לא יצק, Lo yatzak, you did not do the pouring
of oil. Basically, the way you would make the different מנחות Minchot
and we're going to get to each of them, but basically, the
way you would make it is let's say the simplest one, which
is a מנחה בלולה בשמן, Mincha belula b'shemen, which is not baked.
Okay, so you put oil at the bottom of the vessel, then
you put in flour, okay, mix it, and then you pour, do
יציקה, yetzika, you pour oil, more oil on top. In the end,
you have to use a לוג log of oil. Okay, so
לא יצק, Lo yatzak, if you did not do the pouring of
oil afterwards, but presumably you used your full לוג log because that
is מעכב. meakev. This is going to be a whole list of
things that are not
מעכב. meakev. The full עישרון isaron and the full לוג log of
oil is מעכב, meakev, but a lot of the ways in which
you exactly mix it is not, although the גמרא Gemara will modify
it. So לא יצק, Lo yatzak, you did not do the pouring
of the oil after the מנחה.
Mincha. And you did... so you put more than a לוג log
of oil, but a לוג log and a half or something.
Right, I mean, or somehow I don't know, right, you mixed it
up but without doing an official יציקה, yetzika, however the יציקה yetzika
gets done.
לא בלל, Lo balal, or you didn't mix it up. You have
the flour sitting on top of the oil, but you didn't actually
knead it into dough.
לא פתת, Lo pitet, or and/or you did not, it was one
of those מנחות Minchot that you bake. Now the מנחות Minchot that
you bake, the תורה Torah says פתות אותה פתים, patot otah pitim,
that you break it after you bake it. You bake it, then
you fold it over, break it into two, break it into four,
in order that you can take a קמיצה. kmitza. How do you
take a קמיצה kmitza of it when it's all one big wafer?
So let's say you did not break it into pieces. Now רש"י
Rashi clarifies, you had to break a little part so you could
do your קמיצה, kmitza, but you didn't break the whole thing into
pieces. Okay, לא פתת, Lo pitet, לא מלח, lo malach, you didn't
put salt on it. Right? The תורה Torah says על כל קרבנך
תקריב מלח. al kol korbancha takriv melach. Okay, בדיעבד, b'diavad,
this is not whether you were יוצא, yotze, whether you did your
חיוב. chiyuv. You have a מצוה mitzvah to put salt, but the
question is whether the קרבן, korban, the חפצא cheftza is כשר. kasher.
Okay, whether it invalidated it or not,
you did...
over on that לאו, lav, but was the קרבן כשר? korban kasher?
Okay. לא מלח, Lo malach, you did not put salt on it.
לא הניף, Lo henif, you did not wave it. Now only a
few קרבנות korbanot require, a few מנחות Minchot require הנפה. hanafa. מנחת
חוטא וקנאות, Minchat chotei v'kanaot, right, and the עומר, Omer, I believe...
also the עומר, Omer, let's see.
I thought also the עומר Omer you wave.
Anyway, okay, you did not wave it. Oh yeah, yeah, they say
it on the side of the רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi says מנחת
חוטא וקנאות Minchat chotei v'kanaot and then he adds in the עומר.
Omer. Okay, so anyway there are some קרבנות, korbanot, so those that
you wave, you did not wave it. That we already know from
animal sacrifices, that if you don't do תנופה tnufa it's
כשר. kasher. לא הגיש, Lo higish, you didn't catch it to the
קרן, keren, to the corner of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, the תורה
Torah says with the מנחה, Mincha, you shall bring it to the
מזבח, mizbe'ach, which we say means you touch it to the מזבח
mizbe'ach before you actually then bring the קומץ kometz and offer up.
You didn't do that. או שפתתן פתים מרובות, O she-pitetan pitim merubot,
or you did the פתיתה ptita but you did not do them,
but you did them as big pieces, not small. לא משחן, Lo
mashchan, or you did not do the משיחה, meshicha, which is the
putting
of oil... some of the things like the רקיקי מצות, rkikei matzot,
you have a משיחה, meshicha, like an anointing of oil, not like
a pouring but more like you would anoint a king, like you
make an 'X' or whatever it is, and you didn't do that
either. In all these cases, כשרה, ksheira, it's kosher. Okay, so all
of these, so many of the tiny little procedures, whether in the
physical construction of the מנחה, Mincha, which is surprising because we would
think the physical construction would define it as the right object. It's
one thing when you have the object and you don't do all
the ritual. Okay, even if you don't do the salt which is
a מצוה, mitzvah, or an עבירה aveira not to do the salt...
identified as זבח zevach too, yeah. That's one thing, but to have
the defined object we would think it necessary. This tells us בדיעבד
b'diavad it's not necessary to define it as the proper object. Okay,
there are other things that are. You need the full לוג שמן,
log shemen, you need the full עישרון, isaron, they both need to
be in the כלי, kli, etc. But these things are not. Now
the גמרא Gemara immediately limits this. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי לא יצק, Mai lo yatzak,
what does it mean you didn't do the יציקה? yetzika? אילימא לא
יצק כלל, Elima lo yatzak klal,
if it means you didn't do it at all, עכובא כתיב בה,
ikuva ktiv bah, the תורה Torah says that it's מעכב. meakev. Now
where does the תורה Torah say it's מעכב? meakev? And this gets
us back to our famous position that by a קרבן, korban, even
if the תורה Torah says you must do it, unless it says
it twice, או חוקה o chukka or it says the word like
היא hi or חוק, chok, unless it has some word to indicate
that it absolutely is מעכב, meakev, we assume all of these rituals
in the end do not prevent the קרבן korban from being כשר.
kasher. So why does the גמרא Gemara assume that it's מעכב meakev
by יציקה? yetzika? So if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, רש"י... Rashi... So it says יציקה yetzikah in
two separate מנחות. minchos.
Of course that's not very convincing, right? Because maybe he'll tell you
that through the each one you needed it. אי נמי ee nami
says רש"י, Rashi, דכתיב ויצקת עליה שמן מנחה היא. d'chsiv v'yatzakta aleha
shemen mincha hee. So the היא hee word. היא מנחה ולא שלא
יצק מנחה דהכל היא עיכובא. hee mincha v'lo shelo yatzak mincha dehakol
hee ikuva.
So the word היא. hee. It's interesting that the גמרא Gemara doesn't
even bother quoting a פסוק. pasuk. The גמרא Gemara takes it for
granted that it somehow is מעכב me'akeiv and says how could we
say you don't need to do יציקה? yetzikah? So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא ela what it must mean is לא יצק כהן אלא
זר. lo yatzak kohen ela zar.
That a non-כהן kohen did it because when how is the מנחה
mincha made? We say מקמיצה ואילך מצות כהונה. mikmitzah v'eilech mitzvas kehunah.
From קמיצה kmitzah onward is the מנחה כהונה mincha kehunah so the
קמיצה kmitzah is after the whole thing is made. So the whole
thing could be made by a non-כהן. kohen. So the יצקת yatzakta
here is not that there was no יציקה yetzikah at all. It
means that there wasn't a כהן. kohen.
Is the thing that it would be בדיעבד b'diavad or is it
a thing that the לכתחילה? l'chatchilah?
You're right. The implication of that would be that it's כשר kosher
בדיעבד b'diavad and we haven't said that at all that it's בדיעבד.
b'diavad. So that is a good question but it's certainly also taking
the whole thing out of the פשט. pshat. So the פשט pshat
is saying that if you didn't do it at all.
Are we going to revise that? What? Are we going to
revise? No actually אליבא דמאן. aliba d'man. Because you know because clearly
לא בלל lo balal was like אלא לאו דאמר ela lav d'amar
is what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask. So let's look
at the
next line of the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי ee hachi לא בלל נמי. lo balal nami.
So would you say the word לא בלל lo balal means the
same thing? לא בלל כהן אלא זר. lo balal kohen ela zar.
That it was a non-כהן kohen which is true if a non-כהן
kohen does it it's not a problem. But the point is the
הלכה halacha goes further than that. הא לא בלל קא פסלה. ha
lo balal ka pasla. The implication of that read would be that
if you didn't do בלילה belilah at all it would be פסול.
pasul. That only if a non-כהן kohen does it. But we know
that's not true. It says והתנן v'hasnan we taught שישים נבללים שישים
ואחד אין נבללים. shishim nivlalim shishim v'echad ein nivlalim.
So sixty עשרונות isronos of or of flour can be mixed together
with oil. Sixty-one cannot. Now what does this mean? And again remember
an עישרון isaron is we said about a two and a half
liters. Right? 43 and a... what? 43 and a third? 43 and
a fifth? Probably 43 and a third ביצים? beitzim? Two and a
half liters. So you think about a two liter thing of Pepsi
and then another half liter. So sixty of that would be 120
and then what? 30? About 150 liters. That's a huge amount of
flour. So if you made a took on yourself to bring a
מנחה mincha of sixty עשרונות, isronos, 150 liters, you would put in
its sixty לוג log of oil. Right? What do we say a
לוג log is? A לוג log is about one liter.
Right? One liter. And then that you could mix. It would be
pretty darn heavy.
I don't know how you'd manage it.
But if you said, if you said you were going to bring
a
sixty-one עישרון isaron מנחה, mincha, right, that you cannot bring. Why? Because
חז"ל Chazal understand that even if you have the same proportion, once
it gets that big, there's no way you can do a good
turning it into dough, a good בלילה. belilah.
Why doesn't it mean you bring it, you just bring them in
separate, would just say bring
them in two separate ones? What? No. So again, so if you
said, if you said sixty-one then you have then you would bring
it in two separate ones.
Up to, yeah I'm
sorry, but up to sixty you have to bring it in only
one כלי. kli. I don't care if you have such a big
כלי.
kli. Alright fine.
Either way so the גמרא Gemara says והוינן בה. v'haveinan bah. So
we asked on this, כי אין נבללים מאי הוי? kee ein nivlalim
mai havi? Who cares if it can't be mixed? דתנן לא בלל
כשירה. d'isnan lo balal ksheirah.
Even if you didn't do the mixing it's כשרה. ksheirah. So our
point about bringing this in is you see לא בלל lo balal
we're treating it literally. Doesn't mean if a non-כהן kohen did it.
It means even if you didn't do it at all it's כשרה.
ksheirah. So okay, bring it in all sixty-one together, what do I
care? You don't even need to do the בלילה. belilah.
You're saying therefore that the first explanation that it's a זר zar
also isn't untenable.
Because לא בלל lo balal we the later גמרא Gemara assumes that
לא בלל lo balal is literal and it asks this question. What
do I care if you can't mix it? You don't have to
mix it בדיעבד. b'diavad. So the גמרא Gemara says ואמר רב זירא.
v'amar Rav Zeira. So רב זירא Rav Zeira says no, it still
has to be all, it still matters if it's sixty or sixty-one.
כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת בו. kol harauy l'veilah ein veilah
me'akeves bo. Yeah.
וכל שאינו ראוי לבילה בילה מעכבת בו. v'chol she'eino rauy l'veilah veilah
me'akeves bo. רב זירא Rav Zeira says even though בדיעבד b'diavad you
don't have to mix it, okay, but it had to be mix-able.
So if you brought
sixty-one, you know, עשרונות isronos or sixty-one לוג log of oil in
one כלי, kli, that's not mix-able. So therefore it's פסול. pasul. You
have to bring it in two כלים. keilim. But up to... But
up until sixty is mixable and therefore even if you don't mix
it it's כשר. kasher. כל הראוי לבילה Kol haraui lebila if you
could mix it אין בילה מעכבת בו ein bila ma'akevet bo mixing
doesn't
prevent it from being valid. But if it's not fit for being
mixed then it's invalid so you don't have to do it but
it has to be mixable. Now I'm going to get back and
discuss this in a minute but for us the immediate relevance is
that it says if it's not mixed is taken literally even if
it's not mixed at all it's כשר. kasher. So why don't we
say the same about לא יצא? lo yatza? So the
גמרא Gemara says מי ניריא mi neerya what is that
relevant הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא ha ke-isa ve-ha ke-isa each phrase and
it means what is relevant for its context. לא יצא Lo yatza
means לא יצא כהן אלא זר lo yatza kohen ela zar לא
יצא lo yatza means that it was it was done but it
was done by a non-כהן. kohen. לא בלל Lo balal when it
says it wasn't mixed לא בלל כלל lo balal klal means it
wasn't mixed at all. Now that is not such a great answer
the question was much better since the simple פשט pshat meant it
wasn't done at all and clearly that's how we read the words
לא בלל lo balal even if you didn't mix it at all
לא יצא lo yatza should mean the same. But the גמרא Gemara
is coming with a position that יציקה yetzika is required and therefore
says that the משנה mishna means not a כהן kohen but a
זר zar because until the קמיצה kemitza it can be done by
a זר. zar. So again to understand the process the בלל balal
is you have your flour you have your oil you mix it
all together like you probably you make it into like a dough
type of a thing okay so that's the that's the בלילה blila
and then you take the extra oil I mean it's part of
the לוג log and you do a little יציקה yetzika you pour
on the top after you're done mixing it. So the בלילה blila
doesn't have to be done at all but the יציקה yetzika has
to be done they learn from a פסוק pasuk but it doesn't
have to be done by a כהן. kohen. Now I want to
talk for a minute about this principle
כל הראוי לבילה kol haraui lebila because you saw Michael Michael's eyes
lit up because anybody that's learned pretty much any מסכת masechet of
ש"ס Shas even if they've never learned מנחות Menachos knows this principle
of כל הראוי לבילה kol haraui lebila why I mean what difference
does it make you know why is this a big principle that
oh whether you have to actually mix it or have to be
fit for being mixed because the גמרא Gemara uses רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira in a range of different contexts to say sometimes the thing
doesn't actually have to be done it just has to be able
to be done. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says well who cares
if she can't do it doesn't רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira say whatever
the it is doesn't רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira say כל הראוי לבילה
אין בילה מעכבת בו? kol haraui lebila ein bila ma'akevet bo? So
the גמרא Gemara you know the question תוספות Tosafos asks is when
do you apply this principle like sometimes you really need the thing
to be done sometimes we're saying it's enough that it's fit to
be done how do we know the difference? And one of תוספות's
Tosafos's answers which he says right here is is that it really
depends on whether it is described as a character of the object
or whether it's focused on the action. When the תורה Torah speaks
about being בלילה blila it never says ובללת u'balalta you shall you
shall mix. What does the תורה Torah say? מנחה בלולה בשמן. mincha
belula bashamen. So בלולה belula describes the quality of the מנחה mincha
the character of the מנחה. mincha. So is this a מנחה בלולה?
mincha belula? So you could say well it's not actually בלולה belula
but it could be a בלולה belula potentially so that's enough to
just say that that's part of the character of of the מנחה.
mincha. But if the תורה Torah says you must do it then
how can you say you've done it if you haven't done it?
Okay so for example you know we do have principles like this
כל הראוי ל... kol haraui le... like you
know כל דבר העומד kol davar ha'omed which is you know דבר
העומד לקציצה davar ha'omed liketzitza
you know כל העומד לקציצה kol ha'omed liketzitza what's the phrase כל
העומד
ל...
kol
ha'omed li...
basically it's like plants ready to be harvested they're like they're already
harvested I'm forgetting me yeah כל
העומד לקצירה כקצור דמי
kol
ha'omed
liktzira kekatzur dami I think or right כל העומד לגיזה כגזוז דמי
kol ha'omed ligiza kigzuz dami right the things that once the sheep
is ready to be sheared it's like it's sheared the plant's ready
to be harvested it's like they're harvested. Because there you want to
describe what type of an object is this if you have standing
wheat that's ready to be harvested so I think about this as
attached to the ground or as not attached to the ground? So
you could say it's at that stage where that could be we
sort of look at it as if it's already so. So that's
similar to this idea of כל הראוי לבילה kol haraui lebila now
it doesn't work in every context but that is probably the best
understanding that when we're concerned about the character something we could say
if it's at the stage that if it's possible and so on
then you don't actually need the thing to be done for us
to see the the object that way as opposed to say when
you need the act done if it isn't done if you haven't
done the act you haven't done the act. Okay I mean it
would make מצוות mitzvos a lot easier כל הראוי להתפלל כאילו התפלל
kol haraui lehispalel k'ilu hispalel exactly you know so that's where acts
matter.
Okay
I mean
I think it's kind of interesting to say that because you know
I wouldn't say like you know he could be potentially an honest
guy he lies all the time but like you know so therefore
he's honest you know what I mean like kind of what we're
saying like you need to think if it's character there has to
be part of his success he's done it you know what I
mean.
I understand I mean the question still is that do we apply
are we very are we consistent about where we apply this? You
know the גמרא Gemara also applies it for example by
by טבילה tevila here's an example that
it says that it says that you don't need
you can't have a חציצה.
chatzitza. Let’s say like your orifices, like your mouth.
So you don’t have to open your mouth and get water in.
You just need to, but you can’t have a חציצה chatzitzah in
your mouth. It has to be ראוי לביאת מים, ra’ui l’biat mayim,
but it doesn’t actually require ביאת מים. biat mayim. Okay, so that’s
for example one case. Now that maybe doesn’t fit this pattern because
there you’re talking about an act of טבילה, tevilah, right? So what
is the sort of logic of this difference between ראוי ra’ui but
not actually doing it? So it is a question about how we
exactly determine the scope
of
this. Right.
So
somehow, but right, wouldn’t say that you know, if you only went
up to your neck, you could have gotten in.
Exactly. Exactly. Here’s a whole thing, whole body is immersed underwater, it’s
just this act of the water touching didn’t occur. That’s a harder
application of this idea. All right, but anyway this is the idea
that certainly occurs to us regarding יציקה yetzikah and here is its
natural location.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says: או שפתתה פתיתים מרובות כשר. O
shepitat petitim merubot kasher. If you broke it up into large pieces,
it’s כשר. kasher.
Does it mean too many?
Well,
that’s going to be the alternate explanation the גמרא Gemara would suggest.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says: השתא לא פתת כלל
שפירא. Hashta lo patat klal shapira. By the way, notice the גמרא
Gemara jumps down to the very end of the משנה. mishna. It
totally skipped over all the other cases, right? It had בלל, balal,
פתת, pitat, מלח, malach, הניף, henif, הגיש, higish, it
goes to the very last case because basically, okay, the other things,
there’s not a word that’s מעכב, me’akev, so we’ll accept it on
face value. You don’t do these things, it’s not מעכב. me’akev. The
תורה Torah never says it must, the only thing we had a
problem with was יצק, yatzak, and there we read it. So the
only thing after יצק yatzak that gets our interest is the פתיתים
מרובות. ptitim merubot. So let’s take a look. השתא לא פתת כלל
שפירא, Hashta lo patat klal shapira,
if you
didn’t do the פתיתה ptitah at all it’s כשר. kasher. רש"י Rashi
says you had to do a little bit to get the מנחה
mincha to get the קומץ, kometz,
but you didn’t do it on the whole thing. פתיתים מרובות מבעיא?
Ptitim merubot mibaia? Is there a question that if you made large
chunks that it would of course be כשר, kasher, you at least
started the process? So the גמרא Gemara says: No, מאי פתיתים מרובות?
mai ptim merubot? What does large ones mean? Doesn’t mean large, it
means what Mike heard.
שריבה בפתיתה בפתיתים, she-ribah
bi-ptitah bi-ptitim,
that you made too many pieces, you made it too small. Okay,
so you overdid פתיתה. ptitah. Now why would I think that that
would be invalid if not doing it at all? Because I would
think, you know, maybe I don’t do it at all, maybe that’s
sort of like כל הראוי, kol ha-ra’ui, I could do it into
פתיתים, ptitim, but once I make them too small, I, you know,
it’s the point of no return. I’m never going to get them
back to being the right size.
How big should they be? It doesn’t, it says פתות אותה לפתיתים
ואין פתיתה לפתיתים. patot otah l’ptitim v’ein ptitah l’ptitim.
So maybe the גמרא Gemara just sense a default to את, et,
or
I’d
take it one more time, את.
et. Okay, so let’s take a look. Okay, so
that’s a חידוש, chiddush, I might have thought that if you made
them too small that you actually did invalidate.
Treat it like מחשבת... machshevet...
Exactly. Now there is an opinion that you do that, there is
an opinion that you’re מחזיר לסולתה, makhzir l’soltan, that you keep on
you know breaking them up until you basically turn it back into
a flour like it gets discussed later I guess? Yeah, okay. Exactly.
I mean that’s the funny thing, that here we’re talking about things
you don’t do and it’s still כשר, kasher, and we haven’t even
told us that you do them yet, and we haven’t even described
how you do them. Okay, איבעית אימא, Iba’it eima, לעולם פתיתים מרובות,
le’olam ptitim merubot, it means large sizes ממש. mammash. ומהו דתימא, U’mahu
de’teima, nevertheless I would have thought התם הוא דאיכא תורת חלות עליהן,
Hasam hu de’ika torat chalot aleihen, if you didn’t do פתיתים ptitim
at all they’re still in a recognizable state, they’re חלות, chalos, and
the תורה Torah calls them you know חלות מצות בלולות בשמן, chalos
matzos blulos ba-shamen, so at least they’re in a state that the
תורה Torah recognizes for a מנחה. mincha. אבל הכא לית תורת חלות
איכא, Aval hacha lat torat chalot ika, when he makes them into
big pieces, on the one hand they’re no longer חלות, chalot, they’re
no longer whole, ולא תורת פתיתים איכא v’lo torat ptitim ika and
they’re not פתיתים, ptitim, they’re not small enough. So I might have
thought that it’s invalid. Either פתיתים ptitim or חלות, chalos, this middle
state maybe counts as nothing. קא משמע לן, Kamashmalan, but even that
doesn’t matter. Okay, because בדיעבד be-di-avad it’s not מעכב. me’akev. Now, לימא
מתניתין דלא כרבי שמעון. Leima matnitin d’lo k’Rabbi Shimon. Let’s say our
משנה mishna is not like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתניא, De-tanya, רבי
שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: כל כהן שאינו מודה בעבודה אין לו
חלק בכהונה. Kol kohen she-eino modeh ba-avoda, ein lo chelek ba-kehuna. Now
when we say our משנה mishna is not like רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, we’re jumping back to the earlier point about the יציקה. yetzikah.
We said לא יצק lo yetzak means that a זר zar could
do the יציקה, yetzikah, which again fits in our principle that only
מקמיצה ואילך mikmitsa va-eilach is it מצות כהונה. mitzvot kehuna. We’re going
to see that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon seems to say that a
כהן kohen needs to do the יציקה. yetzikah. Okay, because he says
any כהן kohen that does not agree to the עבודה, avoda, which
presumably means not just that like accepts upon himself being that he’s
prepared to do any of the עבודות, avodot, that could be one
thing that it means, but also presumably means like you
know he accepts the value of the עבודה. avoda. He doesn’t like
sort of disparage it. There’s גמרות Gemaras that talk about כהנים kohanim
that disparage certain parts of the עבודה avoda and it invalidates them
or raises questions about their legitimacy. So anyway. The way that מודה
בעבודה modeh b'avoda presumably means that he's prepared to do all of
the עבודות avodas and accept that this is a valuable עבודה. avoda.
אין לו חלק בכהונתו. Ein lo chelek b'khunaso. If you don't do
that, you have no portion in the כהונה, kehuna, which means you
don't get to do the
עבודה. avoda.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, המקריב וגו', hamakriv v'go, right.
Even the ones that you like to do, right. Okay, שנאמר המקריב
את דם השלמים ואת החלב מבני אהרן, Shene'emar hamakriv et dam hashlamim
v'et hachelev mibnei Aharon, the one who brings the דם השלמים dam
hashlamim and the חלב, chelev, לו תהיה שוק הימין למנה. lo tihiye
shok hayamin lemana. So notice the blood and the חלב, chelev, then
you get the שוק הימין. shok hayamin. So meaning you have to
basically be המקריב, hamakriv, somebody willing to do the עבודה, avoda, then
you get a portion. Okay now, so the גמרא Gemara says, so
מודה בעבודה, modeh b'avoda, if you do agree to the עבודה, avoda,
יש לו חלק בכהונה, yesh lo chelek bakehuna, שאינו מודה בעבודה, she'eino
modeh b'avoda, this is what he learns out, אין לו חלק בכהונה,
ein lo chelek bakehuna, you do not get a portion. ואין לי
אלא זו בלבד, V'ein li ela zo bilvad, maybe it's only this
thing about the שלמים. shlamim. מניין לרבות ט"ו עבודות, Minayin lerabbot tet-vav
avodot, how do I know to include all of the fifteen עבודות
avodot of the כהן? kohen? So let's see what they are. היציקות,
Hayetzikot,
notice the היציקה hayetzika is right there at the top, okay, והבלילות,
v'hablilot, the mixing of the oil and the flour, והפתיתות, v'haptitot, and
the breaking of it into the pieces. You hear here we don't
necessarily have to do the בלילות. blilot. We don't care if you
don't have to, we care if it requires a כהן. kohen. Meaning,
even if בדיעבד b'diavad it's not מעכב, me'akev, right, when you do
it, who does it? A כהן kohen or a זר? zar? So
he is saying that these things are done by
a כהן. kohen. So היציקה hayetzika he's saying is done by a
כהן, kohen, בלילה blila he's saying is done by a כהן. kohen.
This is against what we know. We think and we know that
היציקה hayetzika and בלילה, blila, right, are done by a זר zar
and פתיתה ptita as well, all these things. So he is not
saying that they're מעכב, me'akev, but at least he's saying it's done
by a כהן. kohen. That seems to go against what we explicitly
interpreted the משנה Mishna about the יציקה. yetzika. והמליחות, V'hamlichot, putting on
the salt, והתנופות, v'hatnufot, the waving, וההגשות, v'hahagashot, so those things are
done by כהנים, Kohanim, והקמיצות, v'hakmizot, taking the קמיצה, kmitza,
וההקטרות, v'hahaktarot, doing that burning, והמליקות, v'hamlikot, doing מליקה, mlika, והקבלות, v'hakabalot,
catching the blood, והזאות, v'haza'ot, and sprinkling the blood. We left out
הולכה holacha which we said sort of gets wrapped into קבלה. kabala.
רב שמעי Rav Shimi was the one who holds it's a זר,
zar, you're so smart, that's what תוספות Tosafot says too. Okay, והשקאת
סוטה, v'hashkat sota,
or making the סוטה sota drink her drink there, ועריפת עגלה, v'arifat
egla, breaking the neck of the עגלה, egla, which is עגלה ערופה,
egla arufa, thank you, right, עגלה agala is a wagon, which is
not done in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but it's still considered
an עבודה. avoda. Okay, these are talking about things that are not
necessarily limited to the מקדש Mikdash but are considered an עבודה. avoda.
So the טהרת מצורע, taharat metzora, right, purifying the מצורע, metzora, now
that's interesting.
I remember גמרות Gemaras in the, I mean that includes מראות נגעים,
marot nega'im, which is not necessarily
the טהרה, tahara, that's a כהן. kohen. Right, and that's my point,
it's not things that are limited to כהנים, Kohanim, things that are
considered an עבודה avoda of the כהן. kohen. Okay, ונשיאת
כפים בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ,
U'nesiat kapayim
bein mibifnim bein mibachutz, and doing the ברכת כהנים birchat Kohanim whether
in the מקדש Mikdash or out of the מקדש. Mikdash.
Because really we should be doing נשיאת כפים nesiat kapayim here too.
Right.
So anyway, so this is just a fascinating list because it says
things that are not limited to the מקדש Mikdash but are considered
עבודות. avodot. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says מניין, minayin, how do you
know that if a כהן kohen doesn't agree to this, he doesn't
have a חלק? chelek? תלמוד לומר מבני אהרן. Talmud lomar mibnei Aharon.
The פסוק pasuk said המקריב את דם השלמים ואת החלב מבני
אהרן. hamakriv et dam hashlamim v'et hachelev mibnei Aharon. עבודה המסורה לבני
אהרן, Avoda hamesura livnei Aharon, any of the עבודות avodot that are
given over to the כהנים, Kohanim, כל כהן שאינו מודה בה אין
לו חלק בכהונה. kol kohen she'eino modeh ba ein lo chelek bakehuna.
If you do not agree to it, you do not get a
portion in the כהונה. kehuna. So what do you see anyway? That
he assumes that יציקה yetzika requires a כהן, kohen, and we interpreted
our משנה Mishna to say יציקה yetzika does not require כהן. kohen.
אמר רב נחמן לא קשיא, Amar Rav Nachman lo kashya, it's not
difficult. כאן במנחת כהנים כאן במנחת ישראל. Kan b'minchat Kohanim kan b'minchat
Yisrael.
It's a difference about whose מנחה. mincha. Is it a מנחה mincha
of כהנים, Kohanim, which you burn the whole thing, or a מנחה
mincha of a non-כהן, kohen, a ישראל? Yisrael? מנחת ישראל דבת קמיצה
היא, Minchat Yisrael d'bat kmitza hi, a מנחה mincha of a ישראל
Yisrael that is going to have a קמיצה kmitza done because you
only burn the קמיצה. kmitza. We would say מקמיצה ואילך מצות כהונה.
mikmitza v'eilach mitzvat kehuna. That only from the קמיצה kmitza onward is
the כהנים's Kohanim work. לימד על יציקה ובלילה
שכשירה בזר, Limed al yetzika u'vlila shekshira b'zar, a non-כהן kohen to
do it. And presumably רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree to that.
So when does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say the יציקה yetzika and
the בלילה blila are required to be a כהן? kohen? מנחת כהנים
דלאו בת קמיצה היא, Minchat Kohanim d'lav bat kmitza hi, a מנחת
כהנים minchat Kohanim that doesn't have an act of קמיצה kmitza because
you burn the whole מנחה. mincha. מעיקרא בעי כהונה. Me'ikara bei kehuna.
From the very beginning of the process you need a כהן. kohen.
That's interesting. So you would say if you have an active קמיצה,
kmitza, until then a non-כהן kohen can do it, but a מנחה
mincha of the כהן kohen that doesn't have an active קמיצה, kmitza,
the whole from the beginning on has to be done by a
כהן. kohen.
I mean it makes sense, I mean are you going to have
a זר zar just doing someone else's מנחה?
mincha? Well, you could, in theory you could have a זר zar
do somebody else's קרבן. korban. Anyway, if a כהן kohen brings a
קרבן, korban, he could have a non-כהן kohen שחט shecht it. Anyway,
so that's a nice way to ליישב l'yashev and say רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would agree to that.
אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava answered that.
מכדי מנחת כהנים מהיכא איתרבי ליציקה? Michdi minchat Kohanim meheicha itrabbi l'yetzika?
One minute רבא. Rava. The תורה Torah never says you do יציקה
yetzika by מנחת כהנים. Minchas Kohanim. Where do we learn it out?
ממנחת ישראל. Miminchas Yisrael. We learn it out from a מנחה Mincha
of a ישראל. Yisrael. מה התם כשרה בזר אף הכא נמי כשרה
בזר. Mah hatam kesheira be-zar af hacha nami kesheira be-zar. Okay, so
it's the whole source of doing יציקה yetzika is from a מנחה
Mincha of a ישראל Yisrael and there a זר zar works, here
too a זר zar should work. איכא דאמרי, Ika de-amrei, some say,
a different version of this discussion, אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman,
לא קשיא, lo kashya, כאן בנקמצות, kan bi-nekmatsot, כאן בשאינן נקמצות. kan
beshe-ein nekmatsot. Similar to the same point. If you take a קומץ
kometz until the קומץ kometz it can be done by a non-כהן.
kohen. If you don't take a קומץ, kometz, everything requires a כהן.
kohen. The only difference is there's one other מנחה Mincha of the
מנחת כהנים Minchas Kohanim that you don't take a קומץ, kometz, which
is מנחת נסכים. Minchas Nesachim. מנחת נסכים Minchas Nesachim you burn the
whole thing. So any... but it's the same point. Anything that doesn't
have a קומץ, kometz, everything requires a כהן. kohen. אמר ליה רבא,
Amar lei Rava, רבא Rava said, דמכדי, de-mikhti, שאינן נקמצות she-ein nekmatsot
מהיכא איתרבי meheicha israbi ליציקה? liyetzika? How do we know things without
a קומץ, kometz, the תורה Torah never says you do יציקה, yetzika,
how do you know you do it? מנקמצות? Mi-nekmatsot? You learn it
out from those that have a קומץ. kometz. So כנקמצות, ki-nekmatsot, they
should follow the same rule. מה התם כשרה בזר אף הכא נמי
כשרה בזר. Mah hatam kesheira be-zar af hacha nami kesheira be-zar. The
same if that's כשר kosher with a זר, zar, this is כשר
kosher with a זר. zar. אלא מחוורתא מתניתין דלא כרבי שמעון. Ela
michvarta matnitin d'lo ke-Rabbi Shimon. It's better that our משנה Mishna is
not like רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, you're right. רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says the entire process requires a כהן kohen from the beginning and
we say only from קמיצה kemitza onwards. So now we are finding
out that the basic principle that only from קמיצה kemitza onward requires
a כהן kohen and earlier is a זר, zar, רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon disagrees and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says the whole process requires
a כהן. kohen. I just want to say over a beautiful ווארט
vort of רב Rav Soloveitchik about this idea of כל שאינו מודה
בעבודה. kokhol she-eino modeh ba-avoda. רב Rav
Soloveitchik says that this is like a difference between כהן kohen and
לוי. Levi. The תורה Torah says by לוי, Levi, לוי Levi is...
by לוי Levi actually לויים Leviim have a pointed job, like there
are the משוררים meshorerim and the משוררים, meshorerim, the singers, the gatekeepers,
and so on. כהנים Kohanim we find the opposite. כהנים Kohanim we
find that they have to be prepared to do any of the
עבודות. avodot. And he says that the difference is that כהנים Kohanim
are defined... לויים Leviim are defined by their תפקיד. tafkid. Your job
is to do X, you are a gatekeeper or you are a
singer, so you're sort of... whereas the כהן, kohen, like we sort
of, you know, just read now, the כהנים Kohanim were... went through
this whole process of inauguration and sanctification and they are more קדוש.
kadosh. They're not קדוש kadosh because of the job they do, they're
more this intrinsic sense of intrinsically
קדוש. kadosh. וקדשתו כי לחם אלהיך, Ve-kidashto ki lechem Elokecha, etc. So
קדוש kadosh means that their whole... they have to be totally given
over and they have to therefore be prepared to do everything. The
קדושה kedusha doesn't come from the act that they do, but from
the fact that they're totally given over to service in the מקדש.
Mikdash.