Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's daf דף daf is tzadi
beis צ"ב, tzadi beis, Menachos מנחות Menachos 92. We pick up at
the very top of tzadi beis צ"ב, tzadi beis, the mishna משנה,
mishna, three lines from the top.
Kol korbanos hatzibur ein bahem semicha כל קרבנות הציבור אין בהם סמיכה,
Kol korbanos hatzibur ein bahem semicha, all of the communal sacrifices you
do not do semicha סמיכה, semicha, the laying of the hands, chutz
mi-par he-elem davar shel tzibur ve-sa'ir hamishtaleach חוץ מפר העלם דבר של
ציבור ושעיר המשתלח, chutz mi-par he-elem davar shel tzibur ve-sa'ir hamishtaleach, with
the exception of the ox that comes for all of the mitzvos
מצוות, mitzvos, meaning when the Beis Din בית דין, Beis Din, the
topic of Masechet Horayos מסכת הוריות, Masechet Horayos, when Beis Din בית
דין Beis Din rules incorrectly and Klal Yisrael כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael
follows them, so they bring a special korban קרבן korban which is
a chatas חטאת, chatas, the par he-elem davar פר העלם דבר, par
he-elem davar, and obviously the goat that is sent off on Yom
Kippur יום כיפור Yom Kippur where the Torah תורה Torah is quite
explicit that Aharon אהרן Aharon places his hands on the goat.
Now, what is this mishna משנה mishna doing in Masechet Menachos מסכת
מנחות? Masechet Menachos? This is all about animal sacrifices. So it really
is just because the previous mishna משנה mishna was kol korbanos hatzibur
ve-yachid teunim nesachim כל קרבנות הציבור והיחיד טעונים נסכים. kol korbanos hatzibur
ve-yachid teunim nesachim. It was a discussion about which types of korbanot
קרבנות korbanot get the nesachim נסכים, nesachim, the wine and also the
mincha מנחה, mincha, the flour and the oil that comes with it,
and it divided between communal and individual. So here too, and before
that the previous mishna משנה mishna was kol midos she-bemikdash כל מדות
שבמקדש, kol midos she-bemikdash, which was about the various measuring vessels which
was also
done for multiple things but also for the flour and the oil
and the wine. So this is in the context of this kol
כל kol text and the most recent ones of the kols כל
kol were about everything, were about things that were directly related to
the menachos מנחות. menachos. Okay, but here we have this one that
is really related to the animal sacrifices and here there is, as
opposed to with what came to the minchas nesachim מנחת נסכים minchas
nesachim and the nesachim נסכים, nesachim, where the dividing line was between
the type of korban קרבן: korban: olah עולה, olah, shelamim שלמים, shelamim,
todah תודה todah on one side, chatas חטאת chatas and asham אשם
asham on the other. Here the dividing line is really between korban
tzibur קרבן ציבור korban tzibur and korban yachid קרבן יחיד. korban yachid.
So the communal sacrifices do not get semicha סמיכה semicha
with the exception of these two. Rabbi Shimon omer af se'ir avodat
kochavim רבי שמעון אומר אף שעיר עבודת כוכבים, Rabbi Shimon omer af
se'ir avodat kochavim, even the special goat for avodah zarah עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, which is also brought as a communal sacrifice when all
of Am Yisrael עם ישראל Am Yisrael sin relating specifically to avodah
zarah עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. That actually is here in Shelach שלח,
Shelach, interestingly right in the same area of where it speaks about
the nesachim נסכים, nesachim, and it says the following: Vekhi tishgu velo
taasou es kol hamitzvos ha-eileh asher diber Hashem el Moshe וכי תשגו
ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה אשר דבר ה' אל משה. Vekhi
tishgu velo taasou es kol hamitzvos ha-eileh asher diber Hashem el Moshe.
If you err and you do not do all these mitzvos מצוות,
mitzvos, which refer to all these mitzvos מצוות mitzvos the way Chazal
חז"ל Chazal understand it is the mitzvah מצוה mitzvah which is keneged
כנגד keneged all of the mitzvos מצוות, mitzvos, which is avodah zarah
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Es kol asher tziva Hashem aleichem be-yad Moshe
min hayom asher tziva Hashem va-haleah le-doroteichem את כל אשר צוה ה'
אליכם ביד משה מן היום אשר צוה ה' והלאה לדורותיכם. Es kol
asher tziva Hashem aleichem be-yad Moshe min hayom asher tziva Hashem va-haleah
le-doroteichem. Va-haya im mei-einei ha-eidah nista'ala lishgaga והיה אם מעיני העדה נעשתה
לשגגה, Va-haya im mei-einei ha-eidah nista'ala lishgaga, if it was hidden from
the eyes of the eidah עדה, eidah, the eyes of the community,
meaning understood to be Beis Din בית דין, Beis Din, and it
was because that they paskened פסקו paskened incorrectly. So it is a
type of a par he-elem davar פר העלם דבר, par he-elem davar,
but it is specifically about avodah zarah עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Va-asu
kol ha-eidah par ben bakar echad le-olah le-reiach nichoach l'Hashem u-minchato ve-nisko
ka-mishpat u-se'ir izim echad le-chatat ועשו כל העדה פר בן בקר אחד
לעולה לריח ניחוח לה' ומנחתו ונסכו כמשפט ושעיר עזים אחד לחטאת. Va-asu
kol ha-eidah par ben bakar echad le-olah le-reiach nichoach l'Hashem u-minchato ve-nisko
ka-mishpat u-se'ir izim echad le-chatat. So one ox and one goat for
a chatat חטאת. chatat. And then it says vekhipper hakohen וכפר הכהן
vekhipper hakohen etc. and no mention of semicha סמיכה. semicha. Now that
is compared to what do you call it the normal par he-elem
davar shel tzibur פר העלם דבר של ציבור par he-elem davar shel
tzibur which is at the end of Vayikra ויקרא, Vayikra, parshat Vayikra
פרשת ויקרא, parshat Vayikra, and there we read as follows: Ve-im kol
adat yisrael yishgu ve-ne’elam davar mei-einei hakkahal
ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל, Ve-im kol adat
yisrael yishgu ve-ne’elam davar mei-einei hakkahal, again ne'elam davar mei-einei hakkahal ונעלם
דבר מעיני הקהל, ne'elam davar mei-einei hakkahal, va-asu achas mi-kol mitzvos Hashem
ועשו אחת מכל מצות ה', va-asu achas mi-kol mitzvos Hashem, one of
all the mitzvos מצוות mitzvos as opposed to here where it says
es kol asher, here it is one of all the mitzvos מצוות.
mitzvos. Then it says yikrivu hakkahal par ben bakar le-chatas והקריבו הקהל
פר בן בקר לחטאת, yikrivu hakkahal par ben bakar le-chatas, the par
ben bakar פר בן בקר par ben bakar also, and there however
it says explicitly:
Ve-samchu ziknei ha-eidah es yedeihem al rosh ha-par lifnei Hashem ve-shachat es
ha-par lifnei Hashem וסמכו זקני העדה את ידיהם על ראש הפר לפני
ה' ושחט את הפר לפני ה'. Ve-samchu ziknei ha-eidah es yedeihem al
rosh ha-par lifnei Hashem ve-shachat es ha-par lifnei Hashem. Okay, so back
to our mishna משנה. mishna. Our mishna משנה mishna says the only
korban tzibur קרבן ציבור korban tzibur is par he-elem davar פר העלם
דבר par he-elem davar and se'ir hamishtaleach ושעיר המשתלח, se'ir hamishtaleach, those
are explicit in the psukim פסוקים. psukim. Rabbi Shimon adds the one
for avodah zarah עבודה זרה avodah zarah for the tzibur ציבור tzibur
which is very parallel to our case of the ox but it
doesn't mention semicha סמיכה semicha and he says that one also gets
semicha סמיכה. semicha. Kol korbanos hayachid teunim semicha chutz min habechor ve-hama’aser
ve-hapesach כל קרבנות היחיד טעונים סמיכה חוץ מן הבכור והמעשר והפסח. Kol
korbanos hayachid teunim semicha chutz min habechor ve-hama’aser ve-hapesach. All individual korbanot
קרבנות korbanot get semicha סמיכה semicha again with the exception of bechor
בכור, bechor, ma'aser מעשר, ma'aser, and pesach פסח. pesach. Okay, interesting again
that those are excluded. Here the issue is not obligation versus free
will, so again it's interesting that these are specifically excluded and it's
worth noting that by בכור, bechor, מעשר, maaser, and פסח, pesach, you
know, besides, you know, for example the Torah never exactly is explicit
about how, you know, what you do with the blood, חז"ל Chazal
have to learn out about the blood about those, that these are
the קרבנות korbanos that are least done as a type of לרצות,
leratzos,
you know, least coming as a way of connecting the individual to
God, finding favor to God, whether it's for a sin that to
atone for, whether it's as a type of a gift. Here, you
know, פסח pesach is fundamentally about the eating and about celebrating
the יציאת מצרים, Yetzias Mitzrayim, but that is fundamentally the גמרא Gemara
says it's really coming, you know, the הקרבה hakrava is a means
towards the experience of the eating of it, and בכור bechor and
מעשר maaser is much more a type of a gift to the
כהן kohen and the way it's given to the כהן kohen is
through this קרבן. korban. Okay, so it's interesting that that, you know,
could explain why it's fundamentally a categorical different whether it's in terms
of the נסכים, nesachim, you know, because how much you see that
as sort of directed towards God as a ritual type of a
thing, or here in terms of the סמיכה. smicha. Right? If סמיכה
smicha is really a sense of ownership and connection and is connecting
a way via the קרבן korban that the individual is like connecting
to God, that's not so relevant by בכור bechor and מעשר. maaser.
You might think it's relevant by פסח, pesach, but again a פסח
pesach is really much more about the eating than it is about
the הקרבה. hakrava. Okay, so and
so those are those. And now how about the last case here
is היורש סומך ומביא נסכים וממיר. hayoresh somech umevi nesachim umeimer. If
you are an heir, a parent died, a father died and you
inherited this cow, animal that was sanctified by the father, and then
you're bringing the father's sacrifice, so are you still considered to be
the owner of the sacrifice? Because if סמיכה smicha is about connecting
it to the owner, are you considered the owner? And this משנה
mishna says yes you are. You do סמיכה, smicha, you now have
inherited it so it is like it's yours. And you would also
bring נסכים, nesachim, that of course is almost obvious, that's not so
much of an emphasis of ownership. And you could do תמורה, temurah,
I mean you're not allowed to do תמורה temurah but it counts
as תמורה temurah which is also some if you try to exchange
it the other animal gets the קדושה kedusha as well. That is
also something that is fundamentally rooted in a sense of ownership. Okay,
so three different sort of interesting
sections: the exceptions of קרבן ציבור korban tzibur number one, number two
the exception, you know, קרבן ציבור korban tzibur does not but then
the exceptions to that rule, number two
קרבן יחיד korban yachid does but the exceptions to that rule, בכור,
bechor, מעשר, maaser, and פסח, pesach, and then finally this interesting issue
of יורש. yoresh. Okay, the גמרא Gemara for the most part is
going to follow focus on the debate about the קרבן ציבור, korban
tzibur, what are the exceptions to that rule? And by the way
you can understand to some degree why you don't have סמיכה smicha
by a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur because if the whole idea of
סמיכה smicha is to signify ownership, you know, then by a קרבן
ציבור korban tzibur like by definition it's all nobody
you're not going to have all of עם ישראל Am Yisrael do
it and it's going to have to be some representative body, and
what are you going to do, like every time that there's a
מוסף musaf or there's a תמיד של שחר tamid shel shachar בית
דין beis din is going to come and represent עם ישראל? Am
Yisrael? I mean maybe, you know, you had a whole idea of
מעמדות maamados in תענית Taanis where you have some sense of being
there to represent. But okay, there you sort of understand it is
more of collective עם ישראל, Am Yisrael, it is not a sense
of individual ownership. And the exceptions of פר העלם דבר של ציבור
par helam davar shel tzibur and maybe עבודה זרה avoda zara which
is a variation is like, well, there even though it's for the
ציבור tzibur it's also for the בית דין beis din and the
בית דין beis din is a much more, you know, סנהדרין, Sanhedrin,
small group of individuals and it's their קרבן korban so you could
idea of ownership is tighter there. And by the שעיר המשתלח seir
hamishtaleach that is really a completely different category. That's not about ownership.
There the Torah explicitly says that the כהן kohen says the וידוי
viduy and it says like he shall place, you know, the sins
על ראש השעיר החי. al rosh haseir hachai. So there the סמיכה
smicha is not as much and that doesn't go to God, it's
not about, you know, it gets sent off to the wilderness. That
is about the transferring of the sins. So it actually the exceptions
actually why you generally don't do it by ציבור tzibur makes sense
and the exceptions make sense as well. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: כל קרבנות הציבור אין בהם
סמיכה חוץ מפר הבא על כל המצוות ושעירי עבודה כוכבים דברי רבי
שמעון. Kol korbanos hatzibur ein bahem smicha chutz mipar haba al kol
hamitzvos ushirei avoda kochavim divrei Rabbi Shimon. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
has his position in the משנה mishna but he doesn't mention the
case by the שעיר המשתלח seir hamishtaleach which is explicit. He says
these are the two that are the exceptions that you do סמיכה.
smicha. The normal פר העלם דבר par helam davar and also the
special קרבן korban that is done with the שעיר seir of עבודה
זרה avoda zara when it's coming through the ruling of the בית
דין. beis din. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. אומר *Rabbi Yehuda Omer*: שעיר
se'ir. עבודת כוכבים אין in, בהם סמיכה smicha *Se'irei Avodas Kochavim ein
bahem smicha*. Nope, not the goats, that's not mentioned in the פסוקים
pesukim. *psukim*. So את מי אביא תחתיהם *es mi avi tachteihem*, so
who am I going to, what am I going to substitute? It's
a funny question, like somehow there's an assumption you need to have
two exceptions. So if I'm not going to have the goats, what
am I going to use as the substitute? The goat for עבודה
זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*? שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtalleach *Se'ir HaMishtale'ach*, I'll
use not the goat for עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah zarah*, but
the goat of יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* that is sent
off into the wilderness. Okay, so that's the ברייתא Baraita, *braita*. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, I mean, so two things come
from this ברייתא braita *braita* that weren't in the משנה *Mishna*. Number
one, that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* does not list the
שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtalleach. *Se'ir HaMishtale'ach*, which is funny, it's in the
פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. And number two, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi Yehuda*
senses that if he rejects the idea of the שעיר עבודה זרה
se'ir avoda zara *Se'ir Avodah Zarah*, somehow he needs a number two,
he needs to find a substitute for it. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* focuses first on the second thing. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says:
לא סגי דלא מייתי *lo sagi d'lo mayti*? What, it's not enough
if you don't have a substitute? Meaning where do you get this
idea that you need to come to a number of two, and
if you don't have the שעיר עבודה זרה se'ir avoda zara, *Se'ir
Avodah Zarah*, you're going to have... you need to find something to
take its place. אמר רבינא Ravina *Amar Ravina*: גמירי *g'miri*, there is
a tradition: שתי סמיכות semichos בציבור b'tzibur, *shtei smichos batzibbur*, that there
are two cases where the ציבור tzibbur *tzibbur* does סמיכה smicha *smicha*.
So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* had his two, so if
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* doesn't agree to the case of
the שעיר עבודה זרה se'ir avoda zara *Se'ir Avodah Zarah*, he has
to now find the second one. Okay, אמר ליה רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon, *Amar lei Rabbi Shimon*: so now we're going continuing in the
ברייתא braita, *braita*. Said רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* to רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*: והלא אין סמיכה semichah אלא בבעלים *Vahalo
ein smicha ella b'ba'alim*, וזה אהרן Aharon ובניו סומכים בו *v'zeh Aharon
u'banav somchim bo*. He says, ah, clearly the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtalleach.
*Se'ir HaMishtale'ach*, I'm not denying that אהרן Aharon *Aharon* does סמיכה semichah
*smicha* on it, but it's not the example of classic סמיכה semicha,
*smicha* which is סמיכה בבעלים smicha b'be'alim. *smicha b'ba'alim*. That's something else
like I was talking about, that's placing the sins on the head
of the שעיר se'ir *se'ir*, that's an act of placing of sins,
that's not the סמיכה semicha. *smicha* of ownership. How do I know
that? Because the סמיכה semicha *smicha*, as we know, is only the
owners. You can't have a שליח *shaliach* do your סמיכה semicha *smicha*,
the whole discussion in the משנה *Mishna*, who doesn't a יורש *yoresh*
count as it? It's all about ownership. And this שעיר Se'ir, *se'ir*
is part of the שעיר Se'ir *se'ir* for עם ישראל am Yisrael
*Am Yisrael*, right? It says: ומאת עדת בני ישראל יקח שני שעירי
עזים לחטאת ume'et adat Bnei Yisrael yikkach shenei se'irei izzim l'chatat. *ume'es
adas bnei Yisrael yikach shnei se'irei izim l'chatas*. Two שעירי *se'irim*, one
that goes, you know, sprinkled in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim, *Kodesh
Kodashim*, and one that's לעזאזל la'Azazel. *l'Azazel*, it's the שעיר Se'ir *se'ir*
of עם ישראל am Yisrael *Am Yisrael*. So it's not... the סמיכה
semicha *smicha* that אהרן Aharon *Aharon* does is not classic סמיכה semicha
*smicha*, it's not the סמיכה semicha *smicha* of owners. That's a very
good argument. Okay, אמר לו *amar lo*, so he said back to
him: אף זה אהרן Aharon ובניו מתכפרים בו *af zeh Aharon u'banav
miskaprim bo*. That
they're
also owners. The שעיר לעזאזל se'ir l'azazel *Se'ir l'Azazel* also the sins
of אהרן Aharon *Aharon* and the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* also get, you
know, of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* and all of
the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* also get atoned for with the שעיר המשתלח
se'ir hamishtalleach, *Se'ir HaMishtale'ach*. So they are, even though it's not all
the owners, he is representing עם ישראל am Yisrael, *Am Yisrael*. He's
not just there as a כהן Kohen *kohen*, he is part of
those that are being atoned for and he represents the community. He
is among those, among the owners.
Okay, so that's an interesting debate about how do we conceptualize the
שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtalleach, *Se'ir HaMishtale'ach* and do we see it as
a type of סמיכה בבעלים smicha b'be'alim. *smicha b'ba'alim*.
So אמר רבי Rebbi, ירמיה *Amar Rabbi Yirmiya*: ואזדו לטעמייהו *v'azdu l'ta'amayhu*.
This debate of רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* and רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* about how to think about the סמיכה semicha
*smicha* of אהרן Aharon *Aharon* by the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtalleach. *Se'ir
HaMishtale'ach*, they're going according to their positions that we know elsewhere. דתניא
*Detanya*, we taught in the ברייתא braita *braita*: וכפר על מקדש Mikdash.
הקדש *V'chiper al mikdash hakodesh*. This is by... this is by יום
כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, you know, where it speaks about the
כהן Kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol*, he does all the sprinklings with the
פר par *par* and then with the שעיר se'ir *se'ir* inside the
קודש Kodesh קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim* and then the היכל Heichal *Heichal*, you
know, and the מזבח *mizbe'ach* and the whole thing. So it and
it ends by saying: וכפר את מקדש Mikdash הקדש *v'chiper es mikdash
hakodesh*, so זה לפני ולפנים *zeh lifnai v'lifnim*, that's the sprinkling of
blood that he did on the inner sanctum. Okay, you know, in
front of the ארון *Aron*. ואת אהל מועד *V'es Ohel Moed*, זה
היכל *zeh Heichal*, and for the אהל מועד *Ohel Moed*, that's the
sprinkling in the היכל *Heichal*, what he does on the פרוכת *paroches*.
זה היכל *zeh Heichal*. מזבח *Mizbe'ach*, זה כמשמעו *zeh k'mashma'o*. וכפר את
מקדש Mikdash הקדש ואת אהל מועד ואת המזבח *V'chiper es mikdash hakodesh
v'es
Ohel Moed v'es hamizbe'ach*, so מזבח *mizbe'ach* כמשמעו *k'mashma'o*. That's what it
sounds like, that's the sprinkling on the מזבח הזהב *mizbe'ach hazahav*.
So those are all the sprinklings of the blood that cleanses the
מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash* from טומאה tumah *tumah*.
Then it says וכפר את מקדש Mikdash, הקדש ואת אהל מועד ואת
המזבח *v'chiper es mikdash hakodesh v'es ohel moed v'es hamizbe'ach* and then
you know and then the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* continues afterwards יכפר yechapper
*yechaper*. It says וכפר מקדש Mikdash הקדש ואת אהל מועד ואת המזבח
יכפר yechapper *v'chiper mikdash hakodesh v'es ohel moed v'es hamizbe'ach yechaper* ועל
הכהנים ועל כל עם הקהל יכפר v'al haKohanim v'al kol am haKahal
yechapper. *v'al hakohanim v'al kol am hakahal yechaper*. So what now is
the יכפר *yechaper*? אלו העזרות *Elu ha'azaros*. That is for, you know,
also the עזרה *azarah* even though there was no sprinkling on the
עזרה *azarah*, you know, the עזרת ישראל Yisrael, *Ezras Yisrael*, the עזרת
כהנים Kohanim *Ezras Kohanim*. even though that also is cleansed through this
עבודה of the דם. dam.
And then it goes on and says ועל הכהנים ועל כל עם
הקהל יכפר. ve'al hakohanim ve'al kol am hakahal yechaper. כהנים כמשמען. Kohanim
kemashma'an. The כהנים Kohanim is the כהנים. Kohanim, על כל עם הקהל
al kol am haKahal אלו ישראל. eilu Yisrael. יכפר אלו לוויים eilu
Levi'im because if you're mentioning כהן and ישראל, Yisrael, you could have
said לוויים Levi'im included in ישראל, Yisrael but we're going to say
the extra יכפר is explicitly including לוויים. Levi'im. הושוו כולם לכפרה אחת
שמתכפרים בשעיר המשתלח דברי רבי יהודה. hoshvu kulam l'chappara achat shemitkapprim b'se'ir
hamishtalleach divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So that is the key, the end of
the פסוק. pasuk The beginning of the פסוק pasuk is the blood
that is cleansing the מקדש. Mikdash, But the end that is saying
atoning for the people, what is atoning for the people? That is
the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtalleach. that atones for their sins. And they
are כהנים Kohanim. and ישראל Yisrael. and לוויים Levi'im are all in
the same category; the atonement for their sins comes through the שעיר
המשתלח. se'ir hamishtalleach, That's רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda So that makes sense
that if the כהנים Kohanim for him are included, אהרן Aharon סמיכה
semicha. is a סמיכה בבעלים. semicha b'ba'alim. He is one of the
people that is being atoned for for this שעיר המשתלח. Se'ir Hamishtaleach
He is representing all of עם ישראל Am Yisrael. and it is
a סמיכה בבעלים. semicha b'ba'alim That's רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon. says, כשם שדם שעיר הנעשה בפנים מכפר על ישראל על
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. keshem shedam se'ir hana'aseh bifnim mechapper al Yisrael al
tumat Mikdash v'kodashav. The blood of the goat that's done on the
inside, right? That's the two שעירים. se'irim. So the שעיר המשתלח, Se'ir
Hamishtaleach, the partner is the שעיר הנעשה בפנים se'ir hana'aseh bifnim when
you use the lots. So the blood of the goat done on
the inside, that is cleansing the מקדש Mikdash, and it is cleansing
the מקדש Mikdash and atoning for the sin that עם ישראל Am
Yisrael, did if they would have purified the מקדש. Mikdash, So by
parallel כך דם הפר מכפר על הכהנים על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. kach
dam hapar mechapper al haKohanim al tumat Mikdash v'kodashav. So the blood
of the ox, right, which is the one that אהרן Aharon, does
the סמיכה semicha, on the ox and he does the וידוי viduy
and notice by the way that פר par is not mentioned as
an exception of ציבור tzibbur, because that is very much the פר
par for the כהנים, Kohanim. right? He says there it says that
he's being מכפר mechapper for himself and for the כהנים. Kohanim? So
the blood of the goat that is done on the inside is
for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat Mikdash v'kodashav of ישראל. Yisrael The blood
of the פר par. that is done on the inside, that is
for אהרן Aharon and for his sons, that's not a ציבור, tzibbur
that's for the כהנים's Kohanim, טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. tumat Mikdash v'kodashav. So
that we know, that parallel exists.
So that's one parallel. The other parallel is כשם שווידוי של שעיר
המשתלח מכפר על ישראל בשאר עבירות כך וידוי של פר מכפר על
הכהנים בשאר עבירות. keshem sheviduy shel se'ir hamishtalleach mechapper al Yisrael b'sh'ar
aveirot kach viduy shel par mechapper al haKohanim b'sh'ar aveirot. So then
as far as all other sins, you have the וידוי viduy on
the שעיר המשתלח, Se'ir Hamishtaleach that is still for ישראל Yisrael not
כהנים. Kohanim. And where are you going to... what is going to
be the atonement for the sins of the כהנים? Kohanim That is
going to be the וידוי viduy that is done on the פר.
par Okay, not a separate קרבן, korban, not a שעיר המשתלח. Se'ir
Hamishtaleach, So you understand this as well, there's a certain logic here
because the תורה Torah explicitly says that אהרן Aharon, brings the פר
par. and it says ומאת עדת בני ישראל Yisrael יקח שני שעירי
עזים לחטאת. They bring two goats. So you could sort of see
it that those two goats are like one sacrifice for עם ישראל,
am Yisrael half done on the inside, half done on the outside,
לעזאזל. La'azazel, The half on the inside is for the מקדש, Mikdash
the half on the outside where it came with the וידוי viduy
is for שאר עבירות. sh'ar aveirot. For the כהנים, Kohanim they have
one; they have the פר. par The פר par is on the...
the blood is on the inside for מקדש Mikdash, and the וידוי,
viduy, which the תורה Torah is also explicit about, that's for שאר
עבירות. sh'ar aveirot. So there is... that works... there's a very nice
parallel there and the תורה Torah does say that אהרן Aharon, does
a וידוי viduy on the פר par and it says he does
a וידוי viduy on the שעיר. se'ir So a וידוי viduy on
the שעיר se'ir is for the sins of ישראל Yisrael and a
וידוי viduy on the פר par, is for the sins of the
כהנים. Kohanim Okay, so that is his position and the כהנים Kohanim,
do not have a portion in the atonement of the שעיר המשתלח.
Se'ir Hamishtaleach,
Now, you have to... there's something attractive about רבי יהודה's Rebi Yehuda
sort of egalitarianism, or equality of having like when it comes to
sins, we're all the same, we've all sinned, we're all in this,
we all get the same communal atonement of this שעיר המשתלח, Se'ir
Hamishtaleach right?
What sense does it make that we're separated when it comes, when
it comes to the טומאה tumah of the מקדש, Mikdash you could
say fine, the כהנים Kohanim work in the מקדש, Mikdash maybe their
sins are even more severe, they're more susceptible, so you understand a
separate קרבן. korban. But why for רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon, would they
be separate even for שאר עבירות? sh'ar aveirot? But maybe one way
you could understand this is, the concept of the תורה Torah is
that the reason the מקדש Mikdash, needs cleansing is not just for
the actual טומאה tumah, of the מקדש, Mikdash somebody entered in when
they are טמא. tamei. The reason the מקדש needs cleansing on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur. is a sense that when people sin in any
עבירה, averah, it's called that they are מטמא, mitamei, right? Like, you
know, whether it's מאכלות אסורות, ma'achalot assurot, whether it's עריות, arayot, it
speaks about לא תטמאו בהם, lo titam'u bahem, it causes טומאה, tumah,
a certain type of a metaphysical טומאה, tumah and that טומאה tumah
penetrates the מקדש, and then the מקדש needs to be cleansed because
God says, you know, ושכנתי בתוך בני ישראל. veshachanti betoch bnei Yisrael.
But how does God continue to dwell with us amidst our sins?
That's what it says at the end by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur.
it says השוכן אתם בתוך טמאתם, hashochen itam betoch tum'otam, right? That
God is going to manage to dwell even with our טומאה tumah
that we generate, but that is made possible through the regular cleansing
of the מקדש on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur, So if our sins
bring in טומאה tumah that penetrates the מקדש, it could be the
כהנים Kohanim that are much more central in the מקדש and maybe
more is expected of them, and so on. Maybe, you know, their
sins penetrate even, you know, even more than ours. So when it
comes time for a general atonement and a cleansing, the שעיר המשתלח
Se'ir Hamishtaleach. works for us, but maybe for the כהנים, Kohanim you
know, they need, you know, their atonement has to go even more,
penetrate even more inside in order for the atonement. One way of
thinking about it. Anyway, there is definitely a nice type of a
parallelism for רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon although it does mean that when
we think just about general sins, we are dividing the כהנים Kohanim
from the regular עם ישראל. Yisrael Okay. רבי שמעון, Rebbe Shimon
so anyway, so that's how. So for רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon אהרן's
Aharon וידוי, viduy, אהרן Aharon. is not part of the שעיר המשתלח,
Se'ir Hamishtaleach, so it is a וידוי viduy of the כהן but
is not a וידוי viduy of the בעלים, ba'alim, so he cannot
list the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach, as a example of a normal
סמיכה semicha. of בעלים ba'alim that is done by the ציבור tzibbur.
because that וידוי viduy and סמיכה semicha. have nothing to do with
ownership according to רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon, Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon הא ודאי הושוו? ha-vadai
hushvu?
So, that's all very nice רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that you made
this parallel and explained, you know, that the שעיר המשתלח, se'ir hamishtaleach
the וידוי viduy of the
שעיר המשתלח, se'ir hamishtaleach, the parallel for the כהנים Kohanim is the
וידוי viduy of the פר, par. but you have a problem that
the פסוק pasuk we just read says they all get atoned for
and it equates it: ועל הכהנים ועל כל עם הקהל יכפר. So
haven't they been equated in terms of the atonement that they get?
So the גמרא Gemara says,
אין, so הושוו, hushvu, yes, they are equated, דבני כפרה נינהו, dimnei
kaparah ninhu, everybody gets atoned for. מיהו, Mihu, כל חד וחד מכפר
בדנפשיה. kol chad vechad mechaper bidnafshei. Everybody gets their atonement in their
own way. So yes, everybody is atoned for, but in different ways.
The atonement of ישראל Yisrael comes through the שעיר, se'ir you know,
or half through the שעיר's se'ir blood and half through the שעיר
המשתלח se'ir hamishtalleach. and the וידוי viduy that's done with that. And
the atonement for the כהנים Kohanim comes through the blood of the
ox, that's for טומאת מקדש, tumat mikdash, and the וידוי viduy of
the and you know of the ox that is for שאר עבירות.
she'ar averot. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: לרבי
יהודה, L'Rebbe Yehuda, טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodshav ישראל Yisrael מתכפרי...
mechapperi...
Oh sorry, so what the גמרא Gemara is doing now actually is
it's pointing out that even according to לרבי יהודה, L'Rebbe Yehuda, even
though he says הושוו hushvu everybody gets the same atonement, it's not
exactly the same for everybody. There is a slightly different way in
which different groups get atoned for. Okay? So כל חד וחד מכפר
בדנפשיה, kol chad vechad mechaper bidnafshei, each one is atoned for in
the way that's appropriate. לרבי יהודה, L'Rebbe Yehuda, what does that mean?
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumat mikdash vekodshav, when it comes to the טומאה
of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, there they're going to be different.
ישראל מתכפרי בדם שעיר הנעשה בפנים וכהנים בפר של אהרן. Yisrael mechapperi
bidam se'ir hana'aseh bifnim vekohanim bepar shel Aharon. There ישראל gets it
with the blood with the שעיר se'ir that's done on the inside
and the כהנים kohanim. get it with the ox. There they're different.
When it comes to שאר עבירות, she'ar averot, בשאר עבירות beshe'ar averot
אלו ואלו מתכפרי בוידוי שעיר המשתלח. elu ve'elu mechapperi beviduy se'ir hamishtaleach.
But all other sins, there they ממש mamash are the same and
they totally are equal with the שעיר המשתלח. seir hamishtaleiach? But even
according to לרבי יהודה, L'Rebbe Yehuda, they're not equal in everything; in
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodshav they split, one gets the ox
and one gets the goat. לרבי שמעון, L'Rebbe Shimon, and for רבי
שמעון Rebi Shimon they split down the they split in all things.
בשאר עבירות נמי, beshe'ar averot nami, even when it comes to other
sins, כהנים בוידוי דפר מתכפרי, kohanim beviduy depar miskapperi, the כהנים kohanim.
still get it not through the שעיר se'ir המשתלח, but they get
it for the וידוי viduy of the פר. par כדתניא, Kidtanya, like
we taught in a ברייתא, braita אחד ישראל ואחד כהנים ואחד כהן
משיח. echad Yisrael ve'echad kohanim ve'echad kohen mashiach. So, as we teach
over in שבועות Shevuot exactly about this question about how the different
atonement for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash vekodshav work, it says the
following: אחד ישראל ואחד כהנים ואחד כהן משיח, echad Yisrael ve'echad kohanim
ve'echad kohen mashiach, whether it's ישראל or כהנים kohanim or even the
כהן גדול, you know, they all get atoned for טומאת מקדש וקדשיו.
tumat mikdash vekodshav. מה בין ישראל לכהנים ולכהן משיח? Mah bein Yisrael
le-kohanim u-le-kohen mashiach? What What difference is there between them? אלא שדם
הפר hapar. מכפר על הכהנים על טומאת מקדש וקדשיו Tum'at Mikdash v'Kodashav
דברי רבי יהודה divrei Rebi Yehuda. *Ella she'dam hapar mechaper al hakohanim
al tumas mikdash v'kadashov divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. So as far as רבי
יהודה Rebi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is concerned, the only difference is when
it comes to טומאת מקדש Tum'at Mikdash וקדשיו *Tumas Mikdash V'kadashov*. There
כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* get the ox, and ישראל *Yisrael* get the שעיר
se'ir *se'ir*. But when it comes to שאר עבירות shear aveiros *shear
aveiros*, they all get the שעיר se'ir המשתלח *se'ir hamishtale'ach*. זו דברי
רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda *Zu divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. ורבי שמעון אומר *V'Rabbi
Shimon omer*, but רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon, *Rabbi Shimon* says, nope, the
division continues. כשם *Keshem*, like we said before, שדם שעיר se'ir הנעשה
בפנים מכפר על ישראל כך דם הפר hapar. מכפר על הכהנים *shedam
se'ir hane'aseh bifnim mechaper al Yisrael kach dam hapar mechaper al hakohanim*,
the same way the blood of the goat is for ישראל *Yisrael*
טומאת מקדש *Tumas Mikdash*, the blood of the ox is for the
כהנים kohanim *Kohanim* טומאת מקדש *Tumas Mikdash*. כשם שוידויו של שעיר se'ir
המשתלח מכפר על ישראל כך וידויו של פר par מכפר על הכהנים
*Keshem she'viduyo shel se'ir hamishtale'ach mechaper al Yisrael kach viduyo shel par
mechaper al hakohanim*, same with the וידוי *vidui* of the פר Par
*par*, of the ox. Fine, just what we said before. Again, a
nice way to think about about רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*
is that the שעיר se'ir *se'ir*, you know, ומעדת בני ישראל יקח
שני שעירי עזים לחטאת *ume'adas bnei Yisrael yikach shnei se'irei izim l'chatat*,
that the two שעירים se'irim *se'irim* are basically like two halves of
one קרבן korban. *korban*. Half done בפנים *bifnim* and half done בחוץ
*bachutz*, but they are both for ישראל *Yisrael*. One gets the blood,
one gets the וידוי *vidui*. Whereas the פר Par. *par* is for
the כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*. It's all done בפנים *bifnim* and it both
gets the blood and the וידוי *vidui* on that one פר par
*par*. Okay, but now we know why רבי שמעון Rebi Shimon *Rabbi
Shimon* does not count the סמיכה semicha *smicha* of the שעיר se'ir
המשתלח *se'ir hamishtale'ach* because that is in no ways an owner doing
the סמיכה semicha *smicha* on it.
Okay, but what we don't know is why רבי יהודה Rebi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* does not have the case of the שעיר se'ir *se'ir*
for עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*. So let's take a look.
תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*, our rabbis taught: וסמכו זקני העדה את ידיהם
על ראש הפר hapar, *V'samchu ziknei ha'edah et yedeihem al rosh hapar*.
Okay, so here we are by the case of ויקרא *Vayikra* of
the normal פר העלם דבר של ציבור par he'elam davar shel tzibbur?
*par helam davar shel tzibur* where it's explicitly that you do סמיכה
semicha *smicha*. וסמכו זקני העדה את ידיהם על ראש הפר hapar *V'samchu
ziknei ha'edah et yedeihem al rosh hapar*. פר par טעון סמיכה semicha
ואין שעירי עבודה כוכבים טעונים סמיכה semicha דברי רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Par ta'un smicha v'ein se'irei avodat kochavim te'unim smicha divrei Rabbi Yehuda*.
So רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* presumably learns out from the הפר hapar?
*hapar*, the ox, that it's only the ox that gets סמיכה semicha
*smicha*, not when this פר העלם דבר של ציבור par hellem davar
shel tzibbur, *par helam davar shel tzibur* is also about עבודה זרה
avoda zara, *avodah zarah* and you add a goat. Even when you
add a goat, because it's about עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*,
only the ox gets סמיכה semicha *smicha*, not the goat. הפר hapar
*Hapar*. Okay, you could also just say, here it says סמיכה semicha
*smicha*, it doesn't say סמיכה semicha *smicha* over there. רבי שמעון אומר
Rebbi Shimon omer, *Rabbi Shimon omer*, no, פר par טעון סמיכה smicha?
בזקנים ואין שעירי עבודה כוכבים טעונים סמיכה smicha בזקנים אלא באהרן *par
ta'un smicha b'zkenim v'ein se'irei avodat kochavim te'unim smicha b'zkenim ella b'Aharon*.
So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* halfway concedes, maybe he has
to acknowledge the ה hey *hey* of הפר hapar *hapar* and it
doesn't say סמיכה smicha *smicha* explicitly by the case of עבודה זרה
avoda zara. *avodah zarah*, but what he says is there's a difference
who does the סמיכה smicha *smicha*. Here it is the elders that
do the סמיכה smicha *smicha*, in the case of the שעיר se'ir
עבודה זרה avoda zara *se'ir avodah zarah*, it is the כהנים kohanim
*Kohanim*. Now that's a little bizarre, right?
Because what exactly is the כהנים *Kohanim's* role? The elders at least
were involved, the בית דין Beis Din, *Beis Din*, the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*,
in the פסק *psak*, in the ruling that made everybody sin. If
you're already having them represent that, why you now have the כהנים
*Kohanim* represent the ציבור tzibbur? *tzibur* for the שעיר se'ir *se'ir*, for
the goat, for the עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah*? Not very
clear at all. Obviously they are included in those that get atoned
for,
but why we should divide it this way is not clear. ואין
שעירי עבודה כוכבים טעונים סמיכה smicha. בזקנים אלא באהרן *V'ein se'irei avodat
kochavim te'unim smicha b'zkenim ella b'Aharon*. But because he does have סמיכה
smicha? *smicha* by the זקנים zekeinim. *zkenim* for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon*, that is his second exception. So רבי יהודה'ס *Rabbi Yehuda's*
second exception is שעיר se'ir המשתלח *se'ir hamishtale'ach*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon* says, no, that's not בבעלים *be'be'alim*, and therefore his second
exception where there's סמיכה smicha, *smicha* by קרבן korban ציבור Tzibur *korban
tzibur* is the שעיר Se'ir *se'ir* of עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah
zarah*. ורמינהו *U'reminhu*, I'll challenge you, says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. החי
hachai. *Hachai*. החי hachai טעון סמיכה smicha, ואין שעירי עבודה כוכבים טעונים
סמיכה smicha דברי רבי יהודה *Hachai ta'un smicha v'ein se'irei avodat kochavim
te'unim smicha divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. So when it talks about the סמיכה
smicha. *smicha* that אהרן *Aharon* does on יום כיפור Yom Kippur? *Yom
Kippur*, it says that he shall do it על ראש השעיר al
rosh hase'ir, החי hachai *al rosh hase'ir hachai*. What's the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*? Let's take a look. וסמך אהרן את שתי ידיו על ראש
השעיר al rosh hase'ir, החי hachai והתוודה עליו את כל עוונות בני
ישראל ואת כל פשעיהם לכל חטאתם ונתן אותם על ראש השעיר hase'ir
ושילח ביד איש עיתי המדברה *V'samach Aharon et shtei yadav al rosh
hase'ir hachai vehitvada alav et kol avonot bnei Yisrael v'et kol pish'eihem
l'chol chatotam v'natan otam al rosh hase'ir v'shilach b'yad ish iti hamidbarah*.
Okay, so what does this ברייתא *braita* going to teach us? החי
hachai, *Hachai*. החי hachai טעון סמיכה smicha ואין שעירי עבודה כוכבים טעונים
סמיכה smicha. דברי רבי יהודה *Hachai ta'un smicha v'ein se'irei avodat kochavim
te'unim smicha divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. So here רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is
learning out to exclude the goat of עבודה זרה avoda zara? *avodah
zarah* not from הפר hapar, *hapar*,
not from the first case of סמיכה smicha, *smicha* by פר העלם
דבר par he'elam davar, *par helam davar*, but from the goat of
שעיר Se'ir המשתלח *se'ir hamishtale'ach*. So it's also על ראש השעיר hase'ir
החי *al rosh hase'ir hachai*. This one, this living one gets סמיכה
smicha. *smicha* and not the goat of עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah
zarah*. Okay, so this is similar because they're both goats. The ox
was similar that they're both about a פר העלם דבר par he'elam
davar, *par helam davar*, about a ruling of the בית דין Beis
Din *Beis Din*. Okay, but here he's learning out to exclude the
שעיר Se'ir *se'ir* of עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* from השעיר
HaSe'ir החי *hase'ir hachai*. ורבי שמעון אומר *V'Rabbi Shimon omer*: חי טעון
סמיכה Semicha, באהרן ואין שעירי עבודה כוכבים טעונים סמיכה Semicha, *Chai ta'un
smicha b'Aharon v'ein se'irei avodat kochavim te'unim smicha*. טעונים סמיכה Semicha, באהרן
אלא בזקנים. But he says, so here he concedes partly and he
says, yes, this is coming to tell you that the שעיר Se'ir
of עבודה זרה Avoda Zara of השעיר המשתלח hase'ir hamishtaleach is different
from the שעיר Se'ir of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara But now to
tell you that the שעיר Se'ir of עבודה זרה Avoda Zara? doesn't
get סמיכה, Semicha but it doesn't get the same type of סמיכה.
Semicha. The סמיכה Semicha by השעיר המשתלח hase'ir hamishtaleach is by אהרן,
and as we know for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that's not even
a סמיכה דבעלים, semicha d'ba'alim, but the סמיכה Semicha. of the שעיר
Se'ir of עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, that is with the בית דין,
okay, the זקנים. zekeinim. So now we've got, it's a little strange.
First of all, רבי יהודה is learning it out from two different
פסוקים. psukim. Fine, but at least it's not a contradiction. But רבי
שמעון, when he's responding to the פסוק pasuk by פר העלם דבר,
par he'elam davar he says it's different from פר העלם דבר, helam
davar, שעיר Se'ir עבודה זרה Avoda Zara that it's with כהנים. When
he's responding to the פסוק pasuk about שעיר Se'ir המשתלח, he says
it's different, the שעיר Se'ir of עבודה זרה Avoda Zara. is different
from שעיר Se'ir המשתלח that it's with the זקנים. zekeinim Which one
is it? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב ששת, amar Rav
Sheshes, so רב ששת Rav Sheshes said back, ותסברא דהא קמייתא מתרצתא
היא? v'tisbara deha kammaita metaretzta hi?
So רב ששת Rav Sheshes first he says before you even get
to the contradiction, you're assuming that the first ברייתא was like you
know was a reliable text. The first ברייתא, does it really make
sense that it's a reliable text, that it make even on its
own account does it make sense? Why not? הא אמר רבי שמעון
סמיכה בבעלים בעינא. ha amar Rebbi Shimon semicha b'ba'alim be'ina. רבי שמעון
says that סמיכה Semicha. is with the בעלים. ba'alim. And therefore according
to the first ברייתא he was saying the שעיר seir עבודה זרה,
the סמיכה Semicha, is with the כהנים. Now it's true the כהנים
are not totally excluded, they're part of עם ישראל, at least in
that case, okay, but still, since he has a strong emphasis of
the idea of בעלים, ba'alim, it's bizarre that he would say that
it's the כהנים that do it there and not the זקנים zekeinim.
who really represent the ציבור. So that original ברייתא that has him
saying that it was the כהנים by the שעיר seir עבודה זרה
is already suspect. אלא תריץ הכי, ella taretz hachi, here's how you
have to read it. הפר. פר טעון סמיכה ואין שעיר עבודת כוכבים
טעון סמיכה דברי רבי יהודה. par taun semicha v'ein se'ir avodas kochavim
taun semicha divrei Rebbi Yehuda. That's as we had it, right, that
the פר for העלם דבר, that gets סמיכה Semicha, and not שעירי
עבודה זרה. se'irei avoda zara. So he excludes שעירי עבודה זרה se'irei
avoda zara from הפר. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebi Shimon omer, and רבי
שמעון now is responding and he's not responding to הפר, he's ignoring
הפר and he's saying no, החי. חי טעון סמיכה באהרן ואין שעיר
עבודת כוכבים טעון סמיכה באהרן. chai taun semicha b'Aharon v'ein se'ir avodas
kochavim taun semicha b'Aharon. I have a different פסוק pasuk I work
off of. I work off of the פסוק pasuk by the שעיר
לעזאזל se'ir l'azazel and there it says החי and that's distinguishing that
goat from the goat of עבודה זרה. But to tell you that
the goat of עבודה זרה is with the זקנים. zekeinim. This is
with אהרן and it's not a סמיכה בבעלים. semicha b'ba'alim The goat
of עבודה זרה is a סמיכה בבעלים smicha b'bealim? and that's with
the זקנים. zekeinim. So from there I learn out that the goat
of עבודה זרה gets סמיכה Semicha and that it's with the זקנים.
zekeinim. והכי קאמר ליה רבי שמעון לרבי יהודה. v'hachi ka'amar leh Rebbi
Shimon l'Rebbi Yehuda. So here's how he's actually responding to רבי יהודה,
I mean because what's he doing with רבי יהודה's הפר? שעירי עבודת
כוכבים בעו סמיכה. se'irei avodas kochavim ba'u semicha. I say שעירי עבודה
זרה se'irei avoda zara require סמיכה. Semicha ואי שמיע לך דלא בעו
סמיכה,
v'ei shamia
lach d'la ba'u semicha, and if you have some tradition that they
don't have סמיכה, smicha, באהרן הוא דשמיע לך. b'Aharon hu d'shamia lach.
Then I want to tell you that I believe your tradition is
not that they never had סמיכה. smicha. The way I would make
sense of it consistent with my position is that it's teaching you
that they don't have the same type of סמיכה. smicha. It's telling
they don't have the סמיכה smicha of the goat of יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur? It's not a סמיכה smicha of אהרן, it's a סמיכה
smicha of זקנים. zekeinim, ומיעוטא הוא דשמיע לך ומיעוטא מהחי הוא. u'miyuta
hu d'shamia lach u'miyuta m'hachai hu. You were, you are teaching your
whole הלכה halacha from הפר to say that שעירי עבודה זרה se'irei
avoda zara doesn't get סמיכה smicha at all. I'm telling you, I
think that was a corrupt tradition and I think the פסוק pasuk
you have to anchor it in is החי and the teaching wasn't
that they don't get סמיכה smicha. at all, the teaching was that
they don't get the סמיכה smicha of אהרן, they get the סמיכה
smicha. of the זקנים, zekenim, they get סמיכה בבעלים and דווקא davka
it is a case of real סמיכה of the owners. ומיעוטא הוא
דשמיע לך ומיעוטא מהחי הוא. u'miyuta hu d'shamia lach u'miyuta m'hachai hu.
Fine, so that's a very nice way of fixing those two ברייתות.
braitos. רבי יהודה למה לי מתינהו מקרא, Rebbi Yehuda lama li matneih
hu mikra, ואמר רבינא גמירי שתי סמיכות בציבור? v'amar Ravina gemiri shtei
semichos b'tzibbur? So why does רבי יהודה need a פסוק pasuk to
tell me no סמיכה by שעירי עבודה זרה, se'irei avoda zara, whether
the פסוק pasuk is החי by contrasting it to the שעיר לעזאזל
Se'ir La'azazel or whether it's הפר contrasting it to the פר העלם
דבר של ציבור? par hellem davar shel tzibbur,
Doesn't, doesn't רבינא Ravina teach that there's a tradition that there's only
two סמיכות semichot that are done by the ציבור? So since he
already has פר העלם דבר and שעיר המשתלח, then why does he
need a פסוק Pasuk to exclude the שעיר of עבודה זרה? So
the גמרא Gemara says, גירסא בעלמא. girsa b'alma. Yeah, we know when
רבי, when רבינא Ravina said it's a tradition, he didn't really mean
it was a tradition, it was just a way of saying that
there's only two exceptions. But really, you know, they're learning it based
on the פסוקים. psukim It works out according to רבי יהודה there
are two exceptions this way, according to רבי שמעון there are two
exceptions in a different way, but it's not that they're starting fundamentally
with that tradition. Okay, that's reading גירסא בעלמא girsa be'alma saying that
what רבינא Ravina was saying wasn't really literal. You could say it
the other way, that רבי יהודה's דרשות drashot are not literal, that's
more of an אסמכתא, asmachta, okay, two different ways of רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosfos explaining that. Okay, so now, רבי שמעון, שעירי עבודת
כוכבים דבעי סמיכה מנלן? se'irei avodat kochavim deba'i smicha minalan? Now where
does רבי שמעון learn that שעירי עבודה זרה se'irei avoda zara need
סמיכה? Now you could say he learns it out from, you know,
החי, contrasting it to the שעיר of שעיר המשתלח. But, you know,
the גמרא Gemara feels like, well, that might say that they're different,
that one gets it with כהנים and one gets it with זקנים,
but you probably need some better source to first teach you the
idea that the שעירי עבודה זרה se'irei avoda zara get סמיכה all
together. So where does he learn that out from? So מנלן? minalan?
נפקא ליה מדתיניא: nafke lei mide'tanya: וסמך את ידו על ראש השעיר.
vesamach et yado al rosh hase'ir. He should do סמיכה on the
head of the goat. What is this about? So this is the
פרשה parsha right after פר העלם דבר של ציבור, par helam davar
shel tzibbur interestingly at the end of פרשת ויקרא. Parshat Vayikra. And
this is the case of אשר נשיא יחטא asher nasi yecheta ועשה
אחת מכל מצות ה' אלהיו אשר לא תעשינה בשגגה ואשם, veasa achat
mikol mitzvot Hashem Elokav asher lo teaseina bishgaga veashem, so for a
נשיא nasi who sins, he brings, like a king, he brings a,
what do you call it, a goat, not a normal type of
like a sheep or a female sheep or a female goat that
a normal ישראל would bring, but he brings a goat, a male
goat, וסמך ידו על ראש השעיר. vesamach yado al rosh hase'ir. Okay,
so what are we going to learn from that? וסמך ידו על
ראש השעיר. vesamach yado al rosh hase'ir. So לרבות שעיר נחשון לסמיכה,
lerabot se'ir Nachshon lesmicha, דברי רבי יהודה. So this comes to include
that there's another שעיר that you do סמיכה for, and what is
it? That would be the goat of נחשון Nachshon meaning the goats
that were brought, you know, when the נשיאים nesi'im brought their all
the various sacrifices for the חנוכת המשכן. chanukat hamishkan.
So in that case, you know, in that case that there would
be סמיכה on that קרבן. korban. To just to remind you what
that קרבן korban was, you know, this is what we read on
חנוכה, Chanukah, פר אחד בן בקר איל אחד כבש אחד בן שנתו
לעלה שעיר עזים אחד לחטאת. par echad ben bakar ayil echad keves
echad ben shenato leola se'ir izim echad lechatat. So there you would
have again a שעיר that would be a חטאת chatat just like
here the שעיר of the נשיא nasi that was brought on a
sin. So the שעירים that were brought, so there by the קרבנות
korbanot of the חנוכת המשכן, chanukat hamishkan, there would also be a
שעיר that was brought by the נשיאים, nesi'im, the שעיר לחטאת, se'ir
lechatat, and it's coming to tell you that that also gets סמיכה.
Now why do you need a פסוק pasuk to tell you it
gets סמיכה? The general rule is that, you know, every קרבן יחיד
korban yachid gets סמיכה, that was a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid, each
individual נשיא nasi brought their own קרבן. Okay, but that was הוראת
שעה, hora'at sha'ah, that was a special הוראת שעה, hora'at sha'ah, it
was a חטאת chatat that was not coming for any sin. And
therefore, you know, because that, you know, the עולה olah whatever, that's
a normal קרבן יחיד korban yachid that gets סמיכה, but the fact
that there the נשיאים nesi'im were able to donate a חטאת chatat
which you never have, that's an exception, so you need a special
פסוק pasuk to tell me even though that was an exception, you
do סמיכה as well. That's what רבי יהודה learns from it. I
have to say it's not clear to me what, where we are
learning that this is coming to include more. You know, normally before
we were saying like הפר, החי is coming to exclude. We want
to say here השעיר HaSe'ir is coming to exclude. So maybe it's
because it doesn't say וסמך ידו על ראשו, vesamach yado al rosho,
and it says על ראש השעיר, haseir so the שעיר is coming
to add an extra שעיר that gets סמיכה. But again, I don't
know why we're not focusing on the ה' to be more exclusive.
Anyway רבי יהודה learns from that that another נשיא nasi also does
סמיכה when the נשיאים nesi'im brought their free will חטאת chatat which
you never have, at the חנוכת המשכן, chanukat hamishkan, that also had
סמיכה. רבי שמעון אומר, no, it's not a case of a נשיא,
nasi, but לרבות שעירי עבודת כוכבים לסמיכה. lerabot se'irei avodat kochavim lesmicha.
Since it could've said על ראשו al rosho and it says על
ראש השעיר, that there's going to be another שעיר that gets סמיכה,
what is that? The שעיר of עבודה זרה. Okay, so he learns
out the שעיר of עבודה זרה from the extra word השעיר here.
שהיה רבי שמעון אומר shehaya Rebi Shimon omer because רבי שמעון used
to say, כל חטאת שנכנס דמה לפנים טעונה סמיכה. kol chatat shenichnas
damah lifnim te'una smicha. Okay, that any blood that the, you know,
when it went inside the קדש קדשים kodesh kodashim or inside the
קדש kodesh I should say, gets סמיכה. So what are the animals,
the קרבנות korbanot that the blood is brought on the inside? Well,
it's the פר העלם דבר של ציבור, par helam davar shel tzibbur
it's the פר and שעיר of יום כפור, Yom Kippur, okay, so
that
is, you know, that gets... Now
this is actually a little bit of a problem because this כלל
Klall is not totally true, because one of the things that don't
get סמיכה, nobody has said gets סמיכה, is the שעיר that is
brought on the inside, the שעיר of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur? right?
The שעיר לעזאזל Se'ir La'azazel gets סמיכה, and the question was do
you consider that a סמיכה of the ציבור or not. But the
שעיר that is brought together with the פר inside the קודש קדשים,
the blood, that does not get סמיכה. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to discuss why we didn't include it, but it's also just
bizarre here that he gives a law, a rule, and the rule
actually has exceptions. Okay, but anyway, but that's how he's saying you
should know that the שעיר of עבודה זרה gets סמיכה because the
blood goes inside, you know, the היכל for sprinkling inside the קודש
and therefore it's going to get סמיכה. So the גמרא says למה
לי למימרא שהיה? Lama li l'meimra shehaya?
So why did he have to say שהיה רבי שמעון אומר? shehaya
Rabbi Shimon Omer?
Why did he have to say oh here's the rule that the
blood goes on the inside? Like why did he need that? He
learned it from a פסוק that the שעיר for עבודה זרה gets
it because it says השעיר by the נשיא. Nasi. סימנא בעלמא. Simana
be'alma.
Okay, that's just a way to remember it, that's not the principle
that he's learning it from, but it's a way to remember which
animals get סמיכה. Of course the problem is, as I said, the
rule doesn't exactly hold and that's, you know, what the גמרא sort
of points out that there's something excluded from the rule. It doesn't
challenge this rule, again it's not a rule, it's just a memory
aid, but anyway, but it still says but why didn't we include
also, you know, use the דרשה Derasha for the שעיר of
יום כיפור? Yom Kippur, ואימא שעיר הנעשה בפנים? V'eima Se'ir hane'asa bifnim?
So why if he's going to learn out that a certain goat
gets סמיכה, why does he learn it for the goat for עבודה
זרה? Why doesn't he learn it from the goat of יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? You know, and that way it'll be very parallel to
the פר. Now one answer could be because the שעיר לעזאזל gets
סמיכה, so that's the סמיכה there, not the סמיכה for the goat
on the inside. But what anyway what's his basis for applying it
and to the goat of עבודה זרה, not the goat of יום
כיפור? So the גמרא says דומיא דשעיר נשיא דמכפר על עבירת מצוה
ידועה. Dumya d'Se'ir Nasi d'mechaper al aveirat mitzva yedu'a. No,
because we're learning it from a שעיר like the שעיר of the
נשיא. Nasi. So the שעיר of the נשיא Nasi was for a
particular עבירה, aveira, whatever that עבירה aveira was, okay, and the שעיר
for עבודה זרה is for the עבירה aveira of עבודה זרה. And
also because it's an עבירה aveira that you knew that you did
and therefore you're bringing this sin offering, okay, whereas the goat for
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו that was brought on יום כיפור, the way חז"ל
Chazal understand it, that was only for a type of a טומאת
מקדש that you were not yet aware had
occurred, and therefore that puts it in a different category. So the
גמרא says ולרבינא דאמר גמרא שתי סמיכות בציבור קרא למה לי? U'l'Ravina
d'amar gemara shtei semichot b'tzibur kra lama li? So back to that,
for רבינא who says that there's a tradition of two סמיכות בציבור,
once רבי שמעון and now we're treating this tradition as a serious
tradition, not as just like a like just a memory aid or
something. So once רבי שמעון did not include the שעיר for לעזאזל,
why does he need the פסוק by נשיא Nasi of השעיר to
include
a
שעיר טעון סמיכת חיים. taun smichas chayim.
Why the case of a שלמי יחיד, shalmei yachid, you don't wave
the animal when it's alive, but you and nevertheless you do סמיכה,
so therefore and I would have said so by זבחי שלמי ציבור
zivchei shalmei tzibbur where there's a תנופה tenufah that you do when
it's alive, so maybe קל וחומר kal vachomer you should do סמיכה.
So therefore אצטריך הלכתא. itrich hilchesa. So bottom line is the purpose
of the הלכה halacha is to not only give you a minimum
of two but a maximum of two. So if you had not
had the הלכה halacha sure you would have included שעירי עבודת זרה,
seirei avodas zarah, but you might have included, this is me just
throwing it in, also the שעיר של יום כיפור, seir shel yom
kippur, and you might have included זבחי שלמי ציבור zivchei shalmei tzibbur
by קל וחומר kal vachomer from normal שלמים shlamim to get סמיכה.
Okay, so two caps you at two.
ואי מהלכתא v'ee mehalechesa and if it had just been from the
הלכה halacha לא ידעינן היינו lo yadinan hainei I would not know
so I would know that you needed to another one in addition
to פר העלם דבר של ציבור but I would not have known
which one. Is it שעיר עבודת זרה? seir avodas zarah? Is it
שעיר של יום כיפור? seir shel yom kippur? Is it זבחי שלמי
ציבור? zivchei shalmei tzibbur? קא משמע לן דומיא דשעיר נשיא ka mashma
lan dumya d'seir nasi so since it's anchored in a פסוק by
the נשיא nasi it says וסמך ידו על ראש השעיר החטאת v'samach
yado al rosh haseir hachatas so the השעיר is telling me there's
another goat like this that there's going to be סמיכה so therefore
the only one that sort of likes this that is sin-based and
it's a specific sin is going to be the שעיר עבודת זרה
seir avodas zarah דמכפר על עבירות מצוות ידוע. dimchaper al aveiros mitzvos
yeduah. So that's how we know that for רבי שמעון you get
it for the שעיר של עבודת זרה seir shel avodas zarah and
not for the שעיר של יום כיפור seir shel yom kippur and
not for זבחי שלמי ציבור. zivchei shalmei tzibbur. So again what's interesting
here conceptually is how do you understand the סמיכה that אהרן does
on יום כיפור? Is that just the placing of sins and it's
not that he's the בעלים bealim or is it a type of
a סמיכה בבעלים? He's one of the people that he's representing identifying
the owners with the קרבן which is what normal סמיכה does.
That's one interesting conceptual debate how you could understand the סמיכה of
אהרן. What we also saw was an interesting debate whether the atonement
of the כהנים on שאר עבירות are they separated from that from
the rest of עם ישראל and their atonement comes from the פר
or do they get the atonement of the שעיר המשתלח? And then
you have this issue that for some reason for רבי יהודה I
mean it's based on פסוקים but even though the שעיר of עבודת
זרה avodas zarah is very similar it's part of a case of
פר העלם דבר של ציבור it's a פר plus a שעיר when
the בית דין rules incorrectly for some reason it does not get
סמיכה. Only the פר gets סמיכה whereas רבי שמעון says no that
actually that does get סמיכה. Okay we will end here for now.