Okay בוקר טוב boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is י״ז, yud-zayin,
מנחות Menachos 17. We pick up on ט״ז tet-zayin עמוד ב׳, amud
beis, about 12 lines from the bottom at the two dots, line
starts with הוליך, holich, we pick up at the two dots הקטיר
שומשום, hiktir shumshum, and we're in the middle of discussing the issues
relating to מפגלין בחצי מתיר, mefaglin b'chatzi matir, having a פיגול pigul
thought on something that is half of a two-part act. The קומץ
kometz of the מנחה minchah is half and the other half is
the קטורת, ketores, and you have a פיגול pigul thought on one
of those two, does it work? So that's the larger issue, that's
a debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and the רבנן. Rabbanan. Let's
see where the גמרא Gemara sort of turns this discussion. So הקטיר
שומשום לאכול שומשום עד דכלה קומץ כולו. hiktir shumshum le'echol shumshum ad
dekalah kometz kulo. So somebody is not just taking a קומץ kometz
of the מנחה minchah and putting it on the מזבח mizbe'ach and
planning on eating a כזית kezayis of the שיריים, shiyaryim, that would
be too easy, that would be standard פיגול. pigul. What they're doing
is they're taking the קומץ kometz of the מנחה minchah and then
they're taking one grain at a time, שומשום shumshum is the size
of a sesame seed, they're taking one grain at a time and
putting it on the מזבח mizbe'ach and saying I am planning on
eating a grain, let's say a gram, okay, we'll make it easy,
I take a gram and they put on the מזבח mizbe'ach and
they say I am planning on eating a gram of the שיריים
shiyaryim tomorrow. Then they take another gram from the קומץ kometz and
they put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach and they say I am
planning on eating an additional gram of the שיריים shiyaryim tomorrow until
they finally offer up all the קומץ, kometz, you know all those
little grams add up and they offer up all the קומץ, kometz,
and then they have now had thought about what is a כזית
kezayis or more of the שיריים, shiyaryim, okay, but not at one
time, each with every separate little gram of the הקטרה haktarah they
had a thought of a separate little gram of the שיריים. shiyaryim.
Does that create פיגול pigul or not? So let's take a look.
רב חסדא ורב המנונא ורב ששת, Rav Chisda veRav Hamnuna veRav Sheshes,
three-way debate between רב חסדא ורב המנונא ורב ששת. Rav Chisda veRav
Hamnuna veRav Sheshes. חד אמר, chad amar, one of them says פיגול,
pigul, so in that case the שיריים shiyaryim is פיגול. pigul. וחד
אמר פסול, vechad amar pasul, one says the שיריים shiyaryim is invalid
but it's not פיגול, pigul, you're not חייב כרת chayav kares for
eating it. וחד אמר כשר, vechad amar kasher, actually the whole שיריים
shiyaryim is כשר. kasher. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא, leima, let's
see if we can match this up with opinions that we're already
familiar with about מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mefaglin b'chatzi matir. לימא מן
דאמר פיגול כרבי מאיר. leima man d'amar pigul keRebbi Meir. The one
who says פיגול pigul is like רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, מפגלין בחצי
מתיר, mefaglin b'chatzi matir,
each little grain of the קומץ kometz was a חצי מתיר chatzi
matir and therefore that worked in order to create פיגול. pigul.
Okay, now actually if חצי מתיר chatzi matir alone should work, but
the חצי מתיר chatzi matir was only done on a tiny little
amount of the שיריים, shiyaryim, but each act is a חצי מתיר
chatzi matir and each act is meaningful and therefore all the little
bits of the שיריים shiyaryim that you had intention for all add
up because of מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mefaglin b'chatzi matir.
That's how that works according to רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. I should
say there's a lot of reasons you can question this and the
גמרא Gemara will exact, will question it in a minute. But I
should note it's not clear that this is a חצי מתיר, chatzi
matir, you know, it's here it's just quantitatively you need to do
a whole קומץ. kometz. It doesn't mean every little piece is considered
a חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. What did we have as a חצי
מתיר? chatzi matir? Things that are discrete: the קומץ kometz of the
מנחה, minchah, the קומץ kometz of the קטורת, ketores, you know each
of the separate lambs for the, you know, for the bread. Maybe
the קנה kaneh and the ושט, veshet, the trachea and the esophagus
of the animal. Each one of those are discrete acts and they're
two acts and combined they make the whole מתיר. matir. Here you're
talking about just quantitatively doing enough. That would be like saying if
I take one step, you know, for the הילוך, hiluch, is that
מפגלין בחצי מתיר? mefaglin b'chatzi matir?
But okay, that's usually not what we would say חצי מתיר chatzi
matir means, but that's how the גמרא Gemara is framing this. This
works according to רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, each little grain is a
חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, they all add up. Okay, מן דאמר פסול
כרבנן. man d'amar pasul keRabbanan. The one that says it's invalid would
be like the רבנן, Rabbanan, who say you don't, you're not מפגלין
בחצי מתיר, mefaglin b'chatzi matir,
but at the end, but they do say if you do the
act, at least דרבנן, deRabbanan, we'll say that the animal is the
קרבן korban is פסול, pasul, even though it's not פיגול. pigul. ומן
דאמר כשר כרבי, veman d'amar kasher keRebbi, the one that says it's
כשר, kasher, to רבי, keRebbi, it's like רבי, Rebbi, as you might
remember רבי Rebbi said earlier on דף י״ד daf yud-dalet that if
you שחט shacht one lamb to eat a half of a כזית
kezayis of bread of one of the חלות challos and the other
lamb to eat a half a כזית kezayis of the other חלה,
challa, that it's totally מותר, muttar, that it's not only a case
of a חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, but each thing is for a
separate half כזית kezayis and those two don't combine. So that actually
does seem to be maybe one of the things that's closest to
what we're talking about here, and רבי Rebbi says it's totally כשר.
kasher. So maybe it nicely lands, lines up that way. So the
גמרא Gemara says ממאי, mimai, who tells you that's the case?
דילמא, dilma, עד כאן לא קאמר רבי מאיר התם ad kan lo
ka'amar Rebbi Meir hatam Maybe I can make these things go according
to each of those opinions of the תנאים. Tannaim. When did רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir say מפגלין בחצי מתיר mifaglin b'chatzi matir and it's
פיגול, pigul, אלא דכי ela d'chi חשיב בשיעורא, chashiv b'shiyura, that when
you have the מחשבה machshava of the חצי מתיר chatzi matir of
the קומץ komatz or of the קטורת, ketoret, you're planning on eating
a full כזית kezayis of the שירים. shiyayrim. Okay, so the only
problem is the חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, but the thing you're intending
for is the full amount. אבל הכא דלא חשיב בשיעורא, aval hacha
d'lo chashiv b'shiyura, here each חצי מתיר chatzi matir was only on
a tiny little bit of the שירים, shiyayrim, so no particular act
was in itself meaningful. Okay, לא, lo, then maybe it wouldn't be
a problem at all or certainly wouldn't be פיגול. pigul. ועד כאן
לא קאמרי רבנן התם, ve'ad kan lo ka'amrei rabanan hatam, and when
did the Rabbis say אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר ein mifaglin b'chatzi matir
and you don't make it פיגול, pigul, maybe that's only over there
דלא חשיב ביה בכולי מתיר, d'lo chashiv beih b'chulei matir, that you
only had the מחשבה machshava in one of the מתירים, matirim, the
half, only in the קומץ, komatz, only in the קטורת. ketoret. In
that case, the thing by itself is not enough of a מחשבה
machshava to do
פיגול. pigul. אבל הכא דחשיב ביה בכולי מתיר, aval hacha d'chashiv beih
b'chulei matir, but here you had the מחשבה machshava on each little
grain of the קומץ. komatz. So in that case, that's not חצי
מתיר, chatzi matir, that's a full מתיר. matir. Okay, that's like having
the מחשבה machshava on the קומץ komatz and having the מחשבה machshava
on the קטורת. ketoret. You had the מחשבה machshava on this little
bit of the קטורת ketoret and this little bit and this little
bit. So the problem isn't חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, the problem is
that each separate act only related to a tiny bit of the
שירים. shiyayrim. So who knows if that is or isn't a problem,
but it ain't the problem of חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. Okay, so
for רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, could be that he's bothered with, he's
not bothered with חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, but he's bothered with the
fact that each מחשבה machshava was on less than a sufficient amount
of the שירים. shiyayrim. And the רבנן, Rabanan, חצי מתיר's chatzi matir
not an issue here because you do all of the מתיר matir
you have the מחשבה machshava for. ועד כאן לא קאמר רבי התם,
ve'ad kan lo ka'amar Rebbi hatam, now רבי Rebbi who's the most
relevant because he talks about half a כזית kezayis here and half
a כזית kezayis is כשר, kosher, so maybe he should definitely say
it's כשר kosher here. No, maybe he only says it over there
אלא דלא הדר מליא מאותה עבודה, ela d'lo hadar malya me'osah avodah,
that when you had the other half כזית, kezayis, it was on
a different עבודה. avodah. You שחט shachted one lamb for one half
כזית kezayis and another one was with the מחשבה machshava of another
half כזית, kezayis, and that was actually off two different חלות. challos.
אבל הכא דהדר מליא מאותה עבודה, aval hacha de'hadar malya me'osah avodah,
here,
the same עבודה avodah of the
הקטרת קומץ haktaras komatz is adding up all the little pieces of
the שירים, shiyayrim, in that case הכא נמי דפסול, hacha nami d'pasul,
maybe he would say it's פסול. pasul. Okay, because רבי Rebbi only
says when one lamb for a half כזית, kezayis, one lamb for
a half כזית, kezayis, those two חצי כזיתים chatzi zeisim don't combine.
But here, it was the whole קטורת. ketoret. Each little piece of
it was for only a little piece of the שירים, shiyayrim, but
it was one קטורת. ketoret. So maybe that all combines to be
one act of הקטרה haktara and all of the little מחשבות machshavos
that you had during that one act of הקטרה haktara all combine
to be one
כזית. kezayis. Also there it's the same מנחה mincha and in רבי's
Rebbi case there's actually two different breads, but that's a separate point.
Okay, so there's good reasons to say that none of this has
to go with רבי Rebbi or רבנן Rabanan or רבי מאיר, Rebbi
Meir, there's issues here that could make it be better for all
of them or worse for all of them. So the גמרא Gemara
says fine. אלא למאן דאמר פיגול דברי הכל, ela leman d'amar pigul
divrei hakol, למאן דאמר פסול דברי הכל, leman d'amar pasul divrei hakol,
למאן דאמר כשר דברי הכל. leman d'amar kasher divrei hakol.
This debate of אמוראים, Amoraim, is it פיגול, pigul, פסול, pasul, or
כשר, kasher, could go according to any position you take in the
רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, רבנן, Rabanan, and רבי Rebbi debate. Let's see
how that works out. למאן דאמר פיגול דברי הכל, leman d'amar pigul
divrei hakol,
I could say it's פיגול pigul according to all the opinions. קסבר
דרך אכילה בכך ודרך הקטרה בכך. kasavar derech achilah bekach v'derech haktarah
bekach.
Okay, so I'm going to start with דרך הקטרה derech haktara here.
דרך הקטרה בכך derech haktarah bekach is the first question before you
even get to פיגול. pigul. Do you consider when I do a
הקטרה haktara and a little bit each time, one tiny drop, one
tiny drop, one tiny drop, is that a valid הקטרה, haktara, even
if you had totally the right thoughts, that's what one of the
questions is going to be here. So the person that says פיגול
pigul first says, yes, that is a valid הקטרה. haktara. It's a
valid הקטרה, haktara, therefore we could be talking about a פיגול pigul
thought to invalidate the קרבן. korban. And the fact that each you're
thinking about I'm going to eat a tiny bit, eat a tiny
bit, eat a tiny bit, well if you eat tiny tiny bits
at a time, that's considered a normal אכילה. achilah. In הלכה halacha
we have the principle of תוך כדי אכילת פרס toch k'dei achilas
pras and so on, but thinking about planning on doing that type
of eating, a little bit, a little bit, a little bit, a
little bit, that is considered a normal
אכילה. achilah. basically say you did a legitimate הקטרה haktara for having
the intent to do an אכילה achila of a כזית kzayit at
the wrong time, that’s פיגול pigul because that thinking of a little
little little each time is a thinking of אכילה. achila. Now what
you also have to assert that the גמרא Gemara isn’t spelling out
is that because it’s all one act of הקטרה haktara all those
little thoughts combine within that one act. And in the totality during
that one act of הקטרה haktara you had a thought of an
אכילה achila of a כזית. kzayit. Okay, so that’s why it’s פיגול.
pigul.
ומאן דאמר פסול Uman de'amar pasul if you say it’s פסול, pasul,
דברי הכל divrei hakol that works according to all opinions, קסבר kasavar
דרך אכילה בכך derech achila bekach ואין דרך הקטרה בכך. ve'ein derech
haktara bekach.
Okay, so we’ll start with the ואין דרך הקטרה בכך, ve'ein derech
haktara bekach, that’s really the key. If doing it a little bit
at a time is not a valid הקטרה, haktara, forgetting your thoughts
of פיגול, pigul, then you didn’t, just didn’t do the הקטרה haktara
of this קרבן. korban. So if you didn’t do the הקטרה haktara
of the קרבן, korban, the קרבן korban is פסול, pasul, it can’t
become פיגול, pigul, because you never did the הקטרה haktara proper. Okay,
so it’s פסול pasul and that’s why there’s a question whether the
גרסא girsa is דרך אכילה בכך derech achila bekach or אין דרך
הקטרה בכך. ein derech haktara bekach. It really doesn’t matter. Once the
הקטרה haktara wasn’t valid, the קרבן korban is פסול pasul but not
פיגול. pigul. Okay, and והוי ליה כמנחה שלא הוקטרה v'havei lei k'mincha
shelo huktra and
so it’s a מנחה mincha that never had the הקטרה. haktara. ומאן
דאמר כשר Uman de'amar kasher
and if you say it’s כשר, kasher, דברי הכל divrei hakol that
could work according to all the
positions, רבי, Rabbi, חצי מתיר, chatzi matir, יש חצי מתיר, yesh chatzi
matir, no חצי מתיר chatzi matir going on here, you did the
whole thing, every little bit. Okay, but well then why will it
be כשר? kasher? קסבר kasavar דרך הקטרה בכך derech haktara bekach so
you first have to start with דרך הקטרה בכך. derech haktara bekach.
Doing the little bit at a time is a good הקטרה haktara
and therefore has the potential of being פיגול pigul and the potential
of being כשר. kasher. Okay, but it was a good הקטרה, haktara,
so why isn’t it then פיגול? pigul? ואין דרך אכילה בכך ve'ein
derech achila bekach
because thinking about eating a tiny bit, tiny bit, tiny bit, tiny
bit, that, if you were to do that, eat one little tiny
you know tiny gram then eat another little tiny gram, another, that
would not really be an אכילה. achila. Okay, it is a הקטרה,
haktara, it’s not an אכילה. achila. So you did a הקטרה haktara
which makes the קרבן korban כשר kasher and you had a thought
to do something which הלכתית hilchatit isn’t defined as an אכילה achila
or certainly not enough of an אכילה achila for this מחשבת פיגול.
machshevet pigul. And therefore since it wasn’t an אכילה, achila, a thought
of an אכילה, achila, it was not a מחשבת פיגול. machshevet pigul.
So the הקטרה haktara is good, the קרבן korban is good, it
was not a מחשבת פיגול. machshevet pigul. Okay, and the idea of
חצי מתיר chatzi matir isn’t relevant to this because in the end
you did, you had the מחשבה machshava for the entire מתיר. matir.
All right, that was very nice and elegant and seeing those different
ways of looking at it. אמרי חריפי Amrei charifei now top of
יז עמוד א. Yud Zayin Amud Aleph. אמרי חריפי דפומבדיתא, Amrei charifei
d'Pumbedita, the sharp ones of Pumbedita, which רש״י Rashi points out to
us in
סנהדרין Sanhedrin is עיפה ואבימי בני רחבא, Eifa v'Avimi bnei Rechava, the
sons of Rechava. Okay, so these sharp rabbis of Pumbedita said the
following. הקטרה מפגלת הקטרה. Haktara mefagelet haktara.
So if you have, are being מקטיר maktir the קומץ kometz with
the intent
to be מקטיר maktir the קטורת ketoret tomorrow, so that actually is,
creates פיגול. pigul. Okay, now there are two things going on here
that could make it not פיגול. pigul. One is אין מפגלין בחצי
מתיר. ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir. So the קומץ kometz is just a
חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. So the גמרא Gemara is going to address
that, let’s read that in the
גמרא. Gemara. דאפילו רבנן דאמרי אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, D'afilu rabbanan d'amri
ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir, even the rabbis that normally say you can’t
have פיגול pigul בחצי מתיר, b'chatzi matir, so if you have an
intent with the קומץ kometz to eat the שיריים shirayim tomorrow it
does not make it פיגול. pigul. הני מילי היכא דחשב ביה בשיריים
ולבונה במילתא קיימא.
hanei milei heicha d'chashav bei
b'shirayim v'levona bemilta kayma. That’s when your intent is with the שיריים
shirayim and the לבונה levona במילתא קיימא. bemilta kayma. That’s the other
מתיר matir is, you know, standing by itself and it’s not part
of your מחשבה. machshava. So then it’s like very, okay, you only
had a מחשבה machshava about half of the מתיר, matir, the לבונה
levona wasn’t part of that מחשבה, machshava, that’s not good enough, אין
מפגלין בחצי מתיר. ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir. That’s why normally a מחשבת
פיגול machshevet pigul does not work with the קומץ. kometz. Okay, אבל
הכא דחשב ביה בלבונה, Aval hacha d'chashav bei balevona,
but here your פיגול pigul thought, your object of the פיגול pigul
thought, the subject was the קומץ, kometz, the object was the לבונה,
levona, so you’re actually including the לבונה levona in your פיגול pigul
thought. True, as the object, not as the subject, but nevertheless, כמאן
דחשב ביה בכוליה מתיר דמי, k'man d'chashav bei bechulei matir dami, it’s
like you had a מחשבה machshava of the whole מתיר, matir, which
is a little funny because you would sort of say the מחשבה
machshava has to be on the entire act, but the point is
since your thoughts relate to the other half of the act, they
relate to the הקטרה haktara of the לבונה, levona, then it is
you had a פיגול pigul thought relating to the entire act of
הקטרה. haktara. And that’s considered כוליה מתיר, kulei matir, it’s still a
big, it’s still obviously a חידוש chidush because at the end of
the day, you know, you’re combining the subject of פיגול pigul with
the object
of
פיגול. pigul. But then... which is explained in the גמרא Gemara about
about... אין מתיר מפגל מתיר, ein matir mefagel matir, okay? So so
both the קומץ kometz and the קטורת ktoret are a מתיר, matir,
so you can't have a מתיר matir being מפגל mefagel a מתיר.
matir. That was רבי יוסי's Rebbe Yosi position, so it might be
that there's a way this works according to רבי יוסי Rebbe Yosi
again because these are two halves of a whole rather than in
the case in the earlier משנה mishna where they were different parts,
but maybe this just isn't going like רבי יוסי. Rebbe Yosi. All
right, our focus anyway is not that, our focus is מפגלין בחצי
מתיר. mefaglin b'chatzi matir. Okay, אמר רבא Amar Rava says רבא, Rava,
אף אנן נמי
תנינא. af anan nami tanina. We can also show that this is
indicated, you know, in in in a ברייתא. braita. Why, what does
the ברייתא braita say?
Excuse me, not a ברייתא, braita, it's the משנה. mishna. Okay, this
is actually indicated in our משנה. mishna. What does an earlier משנה
mishna say? זה הכלל, Ze ha-klal, this is the general rule. כל
הקומץ ונותן בכלי והמוליך והמקטיר, Kol ha-kometz v'noten b'kli v'ha-molich v'ha-maktir, anybody
that does the קמיצה, kmitza, does the נתינה בכלי, netina b'kli, conveys
it, is מקטיר maktir it, לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול להקטיר דבר שדרכו
להקטיר, le'echol davar she-darko le'echol lehaktir davar she-darko lehaktir, to eat something
that is normally eaten or to offer up something that is normally
offered up... להקטיר דבר שדרכו להקטיר, lehaktir davar she-darko lehaktir, whatever, להקטיר,
lehaktir, חוץ למקומו פסול
ואין בו כרת, chutz limkomo pasul v'ein bo kares, if the thought
is to do it in the wrong place, it's פסול pasul but
there's no כרת, kares, it's not
פיגול. pigul. חוץ לזמנו פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. chutz lizmano pigul v'chayavin
alav kares. Okay, so what does that show? Well, מאי לאו mai
lav says רבא, Rava, are we not talking הקטרה דומיא דהנך haktara
dumya d'hanach that with when the הקטרה, haktara, the thought you have
during the הקטרה haktara is like the thought you would have during
the קומץ kometz and the הולכה holacha and the נתינה בכלי. netina
b'kli. מה
הנך בין לאכול בין להקטיר, mah hanach bein le'echol bein lehaktir, so
since in those earlier stages, your thought can be whether to eat
the שיריים shirayim at the wrong time or to be מקטיר maktir
the קומץ kometz at the wrong time, right? Those are the two
types of thoughts of פיגול. pigul. So since those are true for
the first three עבודות, avodot, so אף הקטרה af haktara when you're
talking about making it פיגול pigul with the הקטרה, haktara, it should
be בין לאכול בין להקטיר. bein le'echol bein lehaktir. It should include
the case of whether to eat the מנחה mincha at the wrong
time, the שיריים, shirayim, or to be מקטיר maktir the other thing,
מקטיר maktir the קטורת ktoret at the wrong time. So you see
this משנה mishna basically allows for, you know, implies that הקטרה haktara
for this, you know, for the כוונה kavana of הקטרה haktara of
the other הקטרה haktara actually does make פיגול. pigul. Okay, now I
know it's דרבנן, d'rabannan, maybe it's רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, but whatever,
that is at least the the proof that that works to for
making פיגול. pigul. So the גמרא Gemara just answers very simply: לא,
lo, no, who says that they're the same? הנך, hanach, the earlier
stages, is בין לאכול בין להקטיר bein le'echol bein lehaktir before you
got to the הקטרה, haktara, the thoughts of פיגול pigul could be
whether to eat at the wrong time or to be מקטיר maktir
at the wrong time. הקטרה, haktara, but when you get to the
actual הקטרה, haktara, that would be לאכול, le'echol, your thought is to
eat at the wrong time, אין, in, yes. להקטיר, lehaktir, לא, lo,
but to be מקטיר maktir the קטורת, ktoret, the other half, that
wouldn't... maybe that wouldn't be פיגול pigul because אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר
ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir or because as I said another reason, you
know, אין מתיר מפגל מתיר. ein matir mefagel matir. So you can't
prove from there that that creates פיגול. pigul. Fine, that was the
first opinion. That was חריפי דפומבדיתא. charifei d'Pumbedita. Now we have another
opinion. יתיב רב מנשיה בר גדא קמיה דאביי. Yativ Rav Menashya bar
Gadda kamei d'Abaye. רב מנשיה בר גדא Rav Menashya bar Gadda was
sitting in front of אביי Abaye and יתיב וקאמר משמיה דרב חסדא
yativ v'ka'amar mishmei d'Rav Chisda and he now said the following in
the name of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, the exact
opposite: אין הקטרה מפגלת הקטרה. ein haktara mefagelet haktara.
The הקטרה haktara of the קומץ kometz cannot create a a פיגול
pigul if it's as intent to be מקטיר maktir the קטורת ktoret
at the wrong time. Okay, why? I keep saying קטורת, ktoret, but
I mean the לבונה, levona, excuse me. Okay, why? ואפילו רבי מאיר
דאמר מפגלין בחצי מתיר, v'afilu Rebbe Meir d'amar mefaglin b'chatzi matir, even
Rebbe Meir that says you can do פיגול pigul בחצי מתיר. b'chatzi
matir. So why can't the הקטרה haktara of the קומץ kometz have
worked if it's an intent to be מקטיר maktir the לבונה levona
at the wrong time? הני מילי היכא דחשב בשיריים דקומץ מתיר דידהו.
hani mili heicha
d'chashiv b'shirayim d'kometz matir d'idhu. That's if when you do the קומץ,
kometz, you have מחשבה machshava to eat the שיריים shirayim at the
wrong time, because the קומץ kometz relates to the שיריים. shirayim. The
קומץ kometz is a מתיר matir for the שיריים. shirayim. Okay, it's
half of a מתיר, matir, it's together with the לבונה, levona, but
it is a מתיר matir for the שיריים. shirayim. So your פיגול
pigul thought on the קומץ kometz is relevant to the
שיריים. shirayim. אבל הכא דקומץ לאו מתיר דלבונה הוא לא מצי מפגל
ביה. aval hacha d'kometz lav matir d'levona hu lo matzi mefagel bei.
But the קומץ kometz isn't a מתיר matir for the לבונה. levona.
Both the קומץ kometz and לבונה levona are מתירים matirim for the
שיריים. shirayim. You know, you could do the לבונה levona before you
do the קומץ. kometz. The קומץ kometz doesn't change the state of
the לבונה. levona. So therefore this is actually a a very compelling
idea. Okay, the קומץ kometz cannot be... have a מחשבה, machshava, פיגול
pigul thought relating to the לבונה levona because it operates, it's not
connected to the לבונה. levona. Both of those are doing half of
the work but they're not doing anything to one another. So your
thought of the, so your thought of the הקטרה haktara of the
קומץ kometz has no impact, you know, you know, it's disconnected, the
קומץ kometz is disconnected from the לבונה levona and therefore your thought
about doing that at the wrong time does not make the קרבן
korban פיגול. pigul. Very persuasive idea.
Okay. הכא קומץ לאו מצי לבונה הוא לא מצי מפגל ביה. hacha
kometz lav matzi levona hu lo matzi mefagel bei. Can't turn it
into פיגול. pigul. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, Abaye said
to רב מנשיה בר גדא, Rav Menashia bar Gada,
אני מרי, ani mari, let my master answer me. משמיה דרב? mishmeih
d'Rav? So
אמר ליה, amar lei, so
משמיה דרב? mishmeih d'Rav? So when you quoted רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya,
was רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya saying this in the name of רב?
Rav? So he said, אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to
him,
אין, in, yes. This statement of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya was in
the name of רב, Rav, correction, of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. So
this statement of רב חסדא Rav Chisda was in the name of
רב Rav and this idea that the קומץ kometz cannot be מפגל
mefagel the לבונה levona and vice versa because they don't relate to
one another. They both relate to the מנחה mincha but they don't
relate to one another. איתמר נמי, itmar nami, it was also taught,
אמר רב חסדא אמר רב, amar Rav Chisda amar Rav, so now
here explicitly the statement of רב חסדא Rav Chisda in the name
of רב, Rav, אין הקטרה מפגלת הקטרה. ein haktara mefagelet haktara. One
הקטרה haktara cannot be מפגל mefagel the הקטרה haktara for this very
elegant reason that they do not relate to one another.
Okay. אמר רב יעקב בר אידי משמיה דאביי, amar Rav Yaakov bar
Idi mishmeih d'Abaye, said Rav Yaakov bar Idi in the name of
Abaye, אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami tanina. So remember, this
was taught to Abaye in the name of רב חסדא Rav Chisda
in the name of רב Rav and now Abaye is going to
bring a support for it, okay, from a
משנה. mishna. שחט אחד מן הכבשים לאכול ממנו למחר. shachat echad min
hakevasim leechol mimenu lemachar. If you slaughtered one of the lambs of
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem to eat from the lamb itself tomorrow,
הוא פיגול וחברו כשר. hu pigul vechavero kasher. So that lamb is
פיגול pigul and the other lamb is
כשר. kasher. לאכול מחברו למחר, leechol mechavero lemachar, if you had intent
when you slaughtered lamb one to eat from lamb two tomorrow,
שניהם כשרים, shneihem kesherim, they're both כשר. kasher. מאי טעמא, mai taama,
what's the reason? לאו משום דכיון דלאו מתיר דידיה הוא לא מצי
מפגל ביה. lav mishum dekivan delav matir dideih hu lo matzi mefagel
bei. So he says that's exactly the logic we're saying here. Slaughtering
one lamb, even if the lambs are brought together, one lamb doesn't
have, they both are מתיר matir the bread, but they don't have
an impact. They're sort of like the two lambs are sort of
like the קומץ kometz and the לבונה, levona, right? They don't impact
one another. So since lamb one is not a מתיר matir for
lamb two, then a פיגול pigul thought when you're slaughtering lamb one
relating to lamb two is completely irrelevant and they're both כשר. kasher.
So that's exactly the same as the קומץ kometz and the לבונה
levona are equally מתיר matir the שיירים shirayim but they don't relate
to one another. So that seems to prove your point. So the
גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, not necessarily. התם הוא דלא איקבע בחד
מנא. hatam hu dela ikva bechad mana. There the two lambs aren't
brought together and made as one unit by being put in the
same vessel. אבל הכא דאיקבע בחד מנא, aval hacha deikva bechad mana,
here both, you know, the מנחה mincha and the לבונה levona are
all put in the same כלי. kli. So in that case כחד
דמו, kechad damu, they are, it's considered to be like one whole
unit. So yes, you can consider
that the קומץ kometz affects the לבונה levona and the לבונה levona
the קומץ kometz even though it's not מתיר matir it, it relates
to the whole קרבן korban and the whole קרבן korban includes all
those pieces. So maybe, you know,
it could be true but it's not a good proof from the
case of the lambs.
Okay. אמר רב המנונא, amar Rav Hamnuna, said Rav Hamnuna,
הא מילתא אוכלה לי רבי חנינא. ha milta ochla li Rabbi Chanina.
Rabbi Chanina sort of, you know, like spoon-fed me, made me swallow,
meaning he taught me this
הלכה. halacha. ותקנה לי כחולי תלמודא, vetakna li kechulei talmuda, and I
so love it, it carries the same weight for me like the
entire Talmud. Okay, what's this teaching? Let's take a look. הקטיר קומץ
להקטיר לבונה לאכול שיירים למחר פיגול. hiktir kometz lehaktir levona leechol shirayim
lemachar pigul. Somebody offered up the, excuse me, the קומץ kometz with
the intent
to
offer up the לבונה levona
and to eat the שיירים shirayim tomorrow. So it's basically
the intent is to do two things when you put on the,
up the קומץ. kometz. It is both to be offering up the
לבונה levona tomorrow and to eat the שיירים shirayim tomorrow. Okay, now
it doesn't have a ו vov לאכול שיירים leechol shirayim because the
גמרא Gemara is going to understand that the absence, because a ו
vov can sometimes be read as an 'or', not an 'and'. So
the absence of the ו vov means that you are bundling them
both together. You're offering up the קומץ kometz with the intent to
do two things tomorrow: offer the קטרת ketoret and eat the שיירים
shirayim tomorrow. and eat the שיריים *shirayim*. And in that case, it's
פיגול pigul *pigul*, פיגול pigul *pigul*. Okay, fine, that's interesting. But מאי
קמשמע לן *mai kamashmalan*? What's the חידוש chiddush, *chiddush* here? Like, and
why did you bundle these together? אי הקטרה haktara. מפגלה הקטרה haktara,
קמשמע לן *ei haktara mifagla haktara kamashmalan*, maybe what you really wanted
to tell us was the first part. If you offer up the
קומץ kometz *kometז* in order to offer up the לבונה levona *levona*
tomorrow, that that is פיגול pigul *pigul*. So that's the principle of
הקטרה haktara. מפגלה הקטרה haktara *haktara mifagla haktara*. That was what the
חריפי פומבדיתא *charifei pumbedisa* said, okay, that it sort of, you know,
it sort of like finesses the problem of חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*
because it includes the לבונה levona *levona* in the מחשבה machshava *machshava*.
Is that what you're trying to tell us? אי הקטרה haktara מפגלה
הקטרה haktara קמשמע לן *ei haktara mifagla haktara kamashmalan*, לימא *leima* then
just tell us that: הקטיר קומץ kometz להקטיר lehaktir לבונה levona *hiktir
kometz lehaktir levona*, להקטיר lehaktir לבונה *lehaktir levona*. So just tell us
that one case. Don't throw in the other half of it, the
other part about the שיריים *shirayim*. Just say you're מקטיר maktir. *maktir*
the קומץ kometz, *kometz* for to be מקטיר maktir *maktir* to the
לבונה *levona* tomorrow and that case is therefore פיגול pigul. *pigul*. מפגלה
הקטרה haktara, *mifagla haktara*, just say that. אי מפגלין בחצי מתיר mapaglin
b'chatzi matir, קמשמע לן *ei mifaglin bechatzi matir kamashmalan*, if you want
to tell us no, no, no, I'm going to tell us like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir* that even though you're just doing
the קומץ kometz *kometz*, that can do פיגול pigul *pigul*, מפגלין בחצי
מתיר *mifaglin bechatzi matir*. לימא הקטיר קומץ kometz לאכול שיריים למחר *leima
hiktir kometz leechol shirayim lemachar*. Just tell us the second half of
it, that if you do the קומץ kometz *kometz* for the שיריים
*shirayim* tomorrow it's פיגול pigul, *pigul* even though it's only a חצי
מתיר *chatzi matir*. Okay, so why did you bundle the two together?
Each one by itself is a חידוש chiddush *chiddush*: הקטרה haktara. מפגלה
הקטרה *haktara mifagla haktara* and מפגלין בחצי מתיר *mifaglin bechatzi matir*. But
why are you bundling it together? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
ואי תרוייהו קמשמע לן *ve'it ravaihu kamashmalan*, if you're trying to tell
us both חידושים *chiddushim*,
so לימא הקטיר קומץ kometz. להקטיר lehaktir לבונה ולאכול שיריים למחר *leima
hiktir kometz lehaktir levona v'leechol shirayim lemachar*. Use the ו *vav*. Say,
I'm going to tell you two חידושים *chiddushim*. If you offer up
the קומץ komets *kometz* to be מקטיר maktir *maktir* the לבונה *levona*
tomorrow it's פיגול pigul, *pigul* why, because הקטרה מפגלה הקטרה *haktara mifagla
haktara*. And if you do the קומץ *kometz* in order to eat
the שיריים *shirayim* tomorrow it's פיגול pigul, *pigul* why, because מפגלין בחצי
מתיר *mifaglin bechatzi matir*. So either one of those are פיגול pigul.
*pigul*. So fine, say either one are פיגול pigul *pigul*, but you
made it sound like דוקא *davka* when you have both מחשבות *machshavot*
combined. Why are you saying that? What are you trying to tell
us? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רב אדא בר אהבה
*amar Rav Adda bar Ahava*, לעולם קסבר אין הקטרה מפגלה הקטרה ואין
מפגלין בחצי מתיר *le'olam kasavar ein haktara mifagla haktara ve'ein mifaglin bechatzi
matir*. Actually, that's exactly the point. Each one of these by themselves
will not get the job done. To do the קומץ *kometz* for
the sake of הקטרה *haktara* of the לבונה *levona* won't work: אין
הקטרה מפגלה הקטרה *ein haktara mifagla haktara*. Okay, you know, why maybe
because אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר *ein mifaglin bechatzi matir*, maybe because they're
not related to one another like we discussed before, that by itself
won't work. Okay, אין הקטרה מפגלה הקטרה ואין מפגלין בחצי מתיר *ein
haktara mifagla haktara ve'ein mifaglin bechatzi matir*. Also, if you did the
קומץ *kometz* for the sake of the שיריים *shirayim*, that also won't
make פיגול pigul *pigul*. Why? אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר *ein mifaglin bechatzi
matir*. Each one by itself won't get the job done. ושני הכא
דפשטה ליה מחשבה machshava בכוליה מנחה Mincha, *ushani hacha depashta lei machshava
bekulei mincha*. Okay, but here when you combine them it works. When
you have a thought, if you had each one separately: הקטרה *haktara*
of the קומץ *kometz* for the לבונה *levona*, sorry, no פיגול pigul
*pigul*. הקטרה *haktara* of the קומץ *kometz* for the שיריים *shirayim*, sorry,
no פיגול pigul *pigul*. But if you have הקטרה *haktara* of the
קומץ *kometz* for the לבונה *levona* and the שיריים *shirayim*, then somehow
you take two things that don't work and you combine them together
and it does work. Why? Not really clear at all. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says because, you know, the מחשבה *machshava* spreads throughout. What
does that exactly mean? The best I can say what that means
is that you're transcending the problem of מפגלין בחצי מתיר *mifaglin bechatzi
matir*. That when you did the קומץ *kometz* for the שיריים *shirayim*,
that wasn't enough because it was a חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*. But
because you also intended, had the thought related also to the הקטרה
*haktara*, and you were planning on doing the הקטרה *haktara* of the
לבונה *levona* tomorrow, so then it's like you're thinking of both halves
of the מתיר *matir* are being pulled together. The act with the
קומץ *kometz* and the thought of the לבונה *levona*. That makes it
like a full מתיר *matir* and that has the power to make
the שיריים *shirayim* into פיגול pigul. *pigul*. Alright, so that was, that's
the חידוש chiddush. *chiddush*. You take these two halves that don't work
by themselves, you put them together and they work. תני תנא Tana
קמיה דרב יצחק בר אבא *tani tanna kamei deRav Yitzchak bar Abba*,
תנא תורה Torah לפני רב יצחק בר אבא *tana tora lifnei Rav
Yitzchak bar Abba*, הקטיר קומץ לאכול שיריים ודברי הכל פיגול pigul. *hiktir
kometz leechol shirayim vedivrei hakol pigul*. If you do the קומץ *kometz*
in order to eat the שיריים *shirayim*, everybody would agree it's פיגול
pigul. *pigul*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, what do you mean
everybody? הא מפליג פליגי *ha miflig palgi*, that's the debate of רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* whether מפגלין בחצי מתיר
*mifaglin bechatzi matir*. אלא אימא לדברי הכל פסול pasul, *ela eima ledivrei
hakol pasul*, everybody would agree that it's פסול pasul *pasul*. רבי מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* would say it's פיגול pigul. *pigul*, the חכמים Chachamim, *Chachamim*
would say דרבנן d'Rabbanan. *derabbanan* it's פסול pasul *pasul*, but at least
everybody would agree that the מנחה mincha, *mincha* is no good. The
debate is if it's פיגול pigul, *pigul*. whether it's פיגול pigul. or
not. So the גמרא Gemara says וליימא, v'leima, so okay I get
that you sort of changed now the text in order to make
it make sense. Instead of דברי הכל פיגול divrei hakol pigul you
said דברי הכל פסול. divrei hakol pasul. But why not rather than
change the word פיגול pigul? to פסול, pasul, if you want to
have the text make sense, change the word דברי הכל? divrei hakol?
וליימא הרי זה פיגול, v'leima harei zeh pigul, don't say דברי הכל
פיגול, divrei hakol pigul, keep the word פיגול pigul. and say this
is פיגול pigul. ורבי מאיר היא v'Rabbi Meir hi and say that
that's a teaching of like רבי מאיר. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, no, no. We can get how the text got corrupted one
way but not the other. תנא דברי הכל אתנויי פיגול, tana divrei
hakol asnoyei pigul, תנא דברי הכל אתנויי. tana divrei hakol asnoyei.
If the תנא taught him דברי הכל, פיגול divrei hakol pigul, בפסול
מחלף ליה.
So you know, to say he got the דברי הכל divrei hakol,
part of the teaching right, everybody says, what he confused was the
word, he was taught the word פסול pasul and he accidentally switched
it for פיגול. pigul? That we can understand. So we can say
even though he said דברי הכל פיגול, divrei hakol pigul. what he
really meant was דברי הכל פסול. divrei hakol pasul. פיגול pigul. and
פסול pasul sound alike. Okay? הרי זה בדברי הכל לא מחלף ליה.
harei zeh b'divrei hakol lo machlif lei.
But if he was originally taught הרי זה פיגול, harei zeh pigul,
he would not have gotten the words הרי זה harei zeh and
switched them into דברי הכל. divrei hakol Okay, so we can understand
that what he was originally taught was דברי הכל פסול divrei hakol
pasul and he misspoke or misremembered when he said דברי הכל divrei
hakol. פיגול. pigul, All right, so that is הדרן עלך הקומץ את
המנחה, hadran lach Ha-Kometz et ha-Mincha, that is the end of הקומץ
את המנחה, Ha-Kometz et ha-Mincha, which is mostly discussions about מפגלין בחצי
מתיר, fascinating different ways that those things can combine. New פרק. Perek.
הקומץ את המנחה. Ha-Kometz et ha-Mincha. We're still talking about מנחות. Minchos.
הקומץ את המנחה לאכול דבר שאין דרכו לאכול ולהקטיר דבר שאין דרכו
להקטיר כשר. Ha-Kometz et ha-Mincha le'echol davar she'ein darko le'echol u'lehaktir davar
she'ein darko lehaktir, kasher. Okay, so you know, if you offered up
the, took the קומץ and the intent was to eat something not
normally eaten, meaning, let's say to eat you did it with the
intent to eat the לבונה tomorrow, or to eat the קומץ tomorrow.
It doesn't mean it's not physically eaten, it could be the קומץ,
which is the same material as the מנחה, but the קומץ belongs
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So you did the קמיצה kmitza with the
intent to eat the קומץ tomorrow, that's, that's intending to eat something
that isn't normally as this קרבן korban operates eaten. Or you offered,
you know, you had an intent to be להקטיר lehaktir the something
that's not normally offered up tomorrow. You had an intent to be
להקטיר lehaktir the שייריים shirayim tomorrow. All right, so if you do
that, if your thought is, you know, not to eat the שייריים
shirayim tomorrow, but to be להקטיר lehaktir the שייריים shirayim tomorrow. Not
to be להקטיר lehaktir the קומץ tomorrow, but to be להקטיר the
שייריים shirayim tomorrow. So in that case it is כשר. kasher. It's
כשר kasher because that is not a מחשבת פיגול. machsheves pigul. מחשבת
פיגול machsheves pigul has to be to eat the thing that you
would eat at the right time at the wrong time, the thing
that you would be להקטיר at the right time to be להקטיר
at the wrong time, not to switch up the objects. רבי אליעזר
פוסל, Rabbi Eliezer poseil, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, that
actually is invalid. Okay now, לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול להקטיר דבר שדרכו
להקטיר פחות מכזית כשר. le'echol davar she'darko le'echol lehaktir davar she'darko lehaktir
pachot mi'kezayit, kasher.
If however you intended to do it less than a כזית, kezayit,
that would be כשר kasher and even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would
not invalidate.
לאכול כחצי זית ולהקטיר כחצי זית כשר שאין אכילה והקטרה מצטרפין, le'echol
ke'chatzi zayit u'lehaktir ke'chatzi zayit, kasher, she'ein achila v'haktara mitztarfin, that you
don't combine a thought of אכילה achila with a thought of הקטרה.
So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer only disagrees in the case of that
if it's a thought of a full כזית kezayit of הקטרה, that
will make פיגול, pigul well that will make it at least פסול,
pasul we'll see in the גמרא Gemara maybe even פיגול, pigul, even
if it is to do it with the שייריים. shirayim. If it
is a thought of a full כזית kezayit of אכילה, achila, that
will make it invalid, maybe even פיגול, pigul, even if it is
with the, you know, the לבונה or even if it is with
the קומץ. Okay, so he doesn't have that problem with דרכו לאכול
דרכו להקטיר, darko le'echol darko lehaktir, but he does demand a כזית
kezayit and he's in full agreement that less than a כזית kezayit
it would be כשר. kasher. So now the גמרא Gemara is going
to focus on the position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and whether
his saying that it's פסול pasul is Rabbinic, whether fundamentally he agrees
to the Rabbis but Rabbinically he's saying פסול pasul because it's too
close for comfort, or whether he even דאורייתא d'Oraisa thinks that this
is a problem and this maybe is פיגול. pigul, So let's take
a look. אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Assi amar
Rabbi Yochanan, said רבי אסי Rabbi Assi in the name of רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer? What's
the reason of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? אמר קרא amar kra because
the פסוק pasuk says ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו, v'im hayoakhol
ye'akhel mibesar zevach shelamav, if you will be eating from the flesh
of the שלמים, shelamim, you know, on the wrong day, לא ירצה,
lo yeratzeh, that's the פסוק pasuk we learn out most of the
laws of פיגול pigul from. And האכל יאכל, hayoakhol ye'akhel, if you
eat, we say it doesn't mean eat. means have intention to eat.
And because of the double language האכל יאכל He-achol ye-achel we mean
intention to eat or intention to be מקטיר. maktir So בשתי אכילות
הכתוב מדבר Bishtey achilot hakatuv medaber talking about two types of eating:
אכילת אדם ואכילת מזבח Achilat adam va-achilat mizbe'ach whether you're eating or
the altar's eating. לומר לך Lomar lach כשם שמחשבין באכילת אדם keshem
she-mechashvin be-achilat adam the same way פיגול pigul. works when you intend
to eat the meat at the wrong time, כך מחשבין באכילת מזבח
kach mechashvin be-achilat mizbe'ach
פיגול pigul also something also gets פיגול pigul. when you intend to
be feed it on the altar at the wrong time, to be
מקטיר it at the wrong time. וכשם U-keshem now everybody agrees to
that point. But now, now we're going to see רבי אליעזר Rebbe
Eliezer is going to use the equation or the double language to
take it one step further. וכשם שמחשבין מאכילת אדם לאכילת אדם ומאכילת
מזבח לאכילת מזבח U-keshem she-mechashvin me-achilat adam le-achilat adam u-me-achilat mizbe'ach le-achilat
mizbe'ach
and the same way the מחשבה works on something that you should
be eating, the שירים, shirayim, to be planning on eating it at
the wrong time, and something you should be offering, the קטורת, ketoret,
to be offering it at the wrong time, כך kach and here's
רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer חידוש, chiddush מחשבין מאכילת אדם למזבח. mechashvin me-achilat
adam le-mizbe'ach.
You can even have a מחשבה of taking the thing that's normally
eaten, the שירים, shirayim, and intend to offer it on the מזבח
mizbe'ach at the wrong time, that would also be פיגול. pigul. ומאכילת
מזבח U-me-achilat mizbe'ach something that's normally put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the
קטורת, ketoret, לאדם, le-adam, if you're intending now to eat it at
the wrong time, that also is פיגול. pigul. So that's the reason
of רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer because the way the פסוק pasuk uses
the double language it means they can sort of work across categories.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דאפקיה רחמנא להקטרה בלשון אכילה De-afkieh rachmana le-haktara
be-lashon achila since it's calling them both a type of אכילה, achila,
even the burning, it means they work at the categories work across
one another. So according to this רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer is saying
it's דאורייתא de-oraita and it's actual פיגול. pigul. Alright, so that's a
very strong read of רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. ורבנן Ve-rabanan what would
the rabbis say? הא דאפקיה רחמנא בלשון אכילה Ha de-afkieh rachmana be-lashon
achila the fact that the תורה uses the language of אכילה achila
top of יז עמוד ב yud zayin amud bet דלא שנא כי
מחשב בלשון אכילה מזבח דלא שנא כי מחשב בלשון הקטרה מזבח. de-lo
shna ki mechashev be-lashon achila mizbe'ach de-lo shna ki mechashev be-lashon haktara
mizbe'ach.
It's not coming to tell you that you can just combine the
categories, but the reason it uses אכילה achila to refer to offering
it up on the מזבח mizbe'ach is to tell you whether your
thought is I am going to feed this on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
whether your thought is I am going to offer this or burn
this on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, either way is a thought that makes
it פיגול. pigul, So the thought using the verb of eating makes
it פיגול, pigul but again not to tell you that they can
you can just combine the categories. אינמי I-nami or here's another reason
why it uses the לשון lashon of אכילה achila for הקטרה. מה
אכילה בכזית אף הקטרה בכזית Ma achila be-kzayit af haktara be-kzayit
to tell you that the that an intent of being מקטיר even
a כזית, kzayit, even not the full amount, can make it פיגול.
The same way the intent of eating is an intent of eating
a כזית kzayit at the wrong time, an intent of הקטרה is
offering a כזית kzayit at the wrong time. That's what you get
from the לשון אכילה, lashon achila, but you don't equate the two
אכילות achilot to one another. ולעולם אכילה דאורחיה משמע U-le-olam achila de-orcheih
mashma but the אכילה achila has to be the way it's normally
eaten. So the שירים shirayim eaten by a person and the קומץ
and the לבונה eaten as it were by the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer would say back to you אם
כן לכתוב רחמנא אם האכל יאכל im ken lichtov rachmana im he-achol
ye-achel
then just use the exact same words to if you know, אינמי
אם יאכל יאכל i-nami im ye-achel ye-achel
or say if it will be eaten. מאי האכל יאכל? Mai he-achol
ye-achel? Why does it change the language? שמע מינה תרתי Shma mina
tarti to tell you two things. Number one like you said that
the language of אכילה achila it you know works if that's your
thought and that אכילה achila and that the הקטרה is a כזית.
kzayit. But the changing of the language is to tell you there's
another חידוש of אכילה achila here that you can cross category. Now
I must say if anything the opposite would be logical because of
a different language you might say these are separate and distinct categories.
Had it said האכל האכל he-achol he-achol or יאכל יאכל ye-achel ye-achel
you would say it's teaching you that they're fundamentally all the same
category. But this is something that the גמרא does sometimes, it says
because it uses a slightly different language it's to tell you another
level of חידוש. And his other level of חידוש is you can
cross category. שמע מינה תרתי. Shma mina tarti.
Okay, so that's how we're reading רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer and that
makes it a דאורייתא. de-oraita. אמר ליה
רבי זירא לרב אסי. Amar leh Rebbe Zeira le-Rav Assi. רבי זירא
Rebbe Zeira said to רב אסי. Rav Assi. אי טעמא דרבי אליעזר
משום הכי הוא Ei ta'ama de-Rebbe Eliezer mishum hachi hu is that
the reason of רבי אליעזר? Rebbe Eliezer? כרת נמי ליחייב Karet nami
lichayev then should he get כרת karet if it's telling you it's
פיגול? וכי תימא הכי נמי Ve-ki teima hachi nami and maybe you'll
say yes that's right. I'm going to read רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
in the משנה Mishnah even though he uses the language of פסול
passul, and we've really been distinguishing פסול passul, from פיגול. I'm going
to read him here to mean פיגול. והא את דאמרת משמיה דרבי
יוחנן Ve-ha at de-amrat mishmeih de-Rebbe Yochanan but didn't you say in
the name of רבי יוחנן? Rebbe Yochanan? מודה רבי אליעזר שאינו בכרת
Modeh Rebbe Eliezer she-eino be-karet you explicitly taught that רבי אליעזר Rebbe
Eliezer says it's only פסול passul there's no כרת? karet? So how
are you now saying that he's basing himself on a פסוק pasuk
which would make it פיגול? אמר ליה Amar leh אמר ליה תנאי
היא אליבא דרבי אליעזר, amar lei tannai hi aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer, he
says, you know what, you're right. That statement of רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan that it's only פסול, passul that's one opinion of תנאים Tannaim
about what רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer's position is. This idea that I'm
putting forward about being based on the פסוק, pasuk, that's a different
position of תנאים Tannaim in understanding רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that would
say for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's actually פיגול. Where do you
see it's a debate of תנאים? Tannaim? איכא למאן דאמר פסול דאורייתא
ואיכא למאן דאמר פסול דרבנן. ika leman d'amar passul d'Oraisa v'ika leman
d'amar passul d'Rabbanan. There are some תנאים Tannaim that think for רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's דאורייתא d'Oraisa and it's פיגול, and some think
it's דרבנן. דתניא, D'tanya, we've learned in a ברייתא. braisa. השוחט את
הזבח, Hashocheit es hazevach, so this is now not about מנחה, this
is about—but it's all for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the same point,
it's all a פסוק pasuk from פיגול about, you know, switching categories.
So somebody שוחט shochets a קרבן, korban, an animal, לשתות מדמו למחר,
lishtos midamo l'machar, to drink from the blood tomorrow, so that's to
eat something that is normally put on the
מזבח. mizbeach. להקטיר מבשרו למחר, Lehaktir mibesaro l'machar, to offer burn the
flesh—let's say a שלמים—on shelamim the מזבח, mizbeach, so that's something that
is normally eaten to do an הקטרה with. So here again we're
crossing the categories. לאכול
מאימורין למחר, Leechol me'imurin l'machar, to eat from the אימורים, imurin, again,
something normally on the מזבח mizbeach to be eaten. כשר, Kasher, so
according to the חכמים Chachamim, it's כשר kasher like we saw in
our משנה. mishnah. רבי אליעזר פוסל, Rabbi Eliezer posel, and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer invalidates, just like our משנה. mishnah. However, להניח מדמו למחר,
lehaniach midamo l'machar, if your plan is not to do an act
of eating or an act of הקטרה, your plan is just to
let it be נותר, nosar, leave the blood over, not put it
on the מזבח, mizbeach, in that case, רבי יהודה פוסל, Rabbi Yehuda
posel, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's invalid. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar
Rabbi Elazar, and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says—different from רבי יהודה—אף בזו
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer פוסל וחכמים מכשירים. Even this is the debate
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים, Chachamim which is a
little funny and what was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda saying and whose
side was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda taking? So let's take a look—so
that's exactly what the גמרא asks. רבי יהודה אליבא דמאן? Rabbi Yehuda
aliba d'man? When רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that leaving it over
to the next day is the intent, makes it פסול, passul. according
to whom of the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. and the
חכמים, Chachamim which approach is he following? אילימא אליבא דרבנן, Ilima aliba
d'Rabbanan, if it's for the—according to the rabbis, that can't be. השתא
ומה התם דקמחשב בלשון אכילה מחשרי רבנן, Hashta u'mah hatam d'kamachsheiv belashon
achilah machshiri Rabbanan,
when you actually say I'm going to, you know, I'm going to
burn the—the you know—the meat on the מזבח, mizbeach, feed it to
the מזבח, mizbeach, or I'm going to eat the אימורים, imurin, so
you're actually all within this אכילה achilah category, you're just sort of
crossing one אכילה achilah to the other, but you're very close. And
if even in that case the rabbis say the קרבן korban is
כשר, kasher, not only not פיגול, they say it's totally כשר, kasher,
הכא לא כל שכן? hacha lo kol shekein? So when you're not
even in the category of פיגול, you're just saying I'm going to
leave the blood over to tomorrow, obviously the rabbis would say it's
כשר. kasher. Okay? So for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda to say it's
a פסול passul when you plan on this total not מחשבת פיגול—to
machsheves pigul leave it to tomorrow is fundamentally not פיגול, פיגול is
about eating or being
מקטיר—that can't be according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. אלא אליבא דרבי אליעזר.
Ella aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer. It must be according to רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that has this idea of some things
being פסול passul. even if they are a little off. So רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, would also
say that if it's not just crossing categories, but even if it's
just intent to leave it over to tomorrow, that's רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda saying it. ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar Rabbi Elazar, then comes רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, not רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer and says אף בזו
רבי אליעזר פוסל וחכמים מכשירים. af b'zo Rabbi Eliezer posel v'Chachamim machshirin.
This is also the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the
rabbis. So the גמרא says, so then how is that different from
what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda just said? רבי אלעזר היינו רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Elazar hainu Rabbi Yehuda? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda just said that
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar would say this is פסול. passul. So clearly
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar are debating like
how far רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, would go. אלא לאו כרת איכא
בינייהו. Ella lav kares ika beineiyhu. It must be the issue is
whether you get כרת kares or not.
דרבי יהודה סבר להניח פסולה בעלמא. D'Rabbi Yehuda savar lehaniach pesulah b'alma.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says when you plan to leave it over
for tomorrow, nobody would ever say that's פיגול. פיגול is all about
eating or הקטרה. So when he says that's פסול pasul according to
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer he means that it's just פסולה בעלמא. pesulah
b'alma. Okay? פסולה בעלמא. Pesulah b'alma. בהנך
כרת נמי איכא מחייב.
B'hanach kares
nami ika mechayeiv. You know, in the original debate of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן, Rabbanan, that was a debate of כרת
kares when you're switching categories,
that was a debate of כרת. kares. Here I'm saying it would
just be פסול. pasul All right? So he did not use the
language "this is the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the
רבנן" Rabbanan because it's different from the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and the רבנן. Rabbanan. According to him, the debate of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן Rabbanan is about כרת kares when
you're switching categories, and this case of להניח lehaniach is just פסול.
Okay? ואתא רבי אלעזר למימר, V'ata Rabbi Elazar l'meimar, and רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar says, no, it's the same debate. אידי ואידי פסול בלא
כרת. Idy v'idy passul belo kares. It's the same debate of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן. Rabbanan. Now if it's the same
debate, they can't be saying both are פיגול. להניח Lehaniach is never
פיגול. So if רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is saying it's the same
debate, he's saying the whole debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
the רבנן... Rabbanan... was always just about פסול and not about פיגול.
So that's actually a nice reading of this ברייתא, braita, right, that
you know you have רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. saying פסול in switching
categories. Then you have this case of להניח lehaniach where nobody would
ever say it's פיגול. So you know let's start with actually רבי
אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, oh, the same
debate there is the debate here. So clearly according to him, רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position is all just about a פסול דרבנן. psul
d'rabbanan. So it doesn't matter whether it's להניח lehaniach or whether it's
switching categories, it's all the same debate. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says, no, no, no, leave רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים's
debate where it is. That's a debate about פיגול, okay, and that's
about switching categories. This case of להניח, lehaniach, that's just a פסול
דרבנן, psul d'rabbanan, but that's not what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
the חכמים are debating. Okay, and therefore that shows therefore according to
this that there's a debate of תנאים Tannaim whether רבי אליעזר feels
when you switch the categories of אכילה והקטרה achila v'haktara whether that's
real פיגול or whether it's only a פסול דרבנן. psul d'rabbanan. So
we'll end here and we will see tomorrow that the גמרא feels
that that is not necessarily the way to read the ברייתא. braita.
Okay, very good.