Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ג מנחות Chaf
Gimmel Menachos 23, we pick up three lines from the top. איתמר,
Itmar, the context that we're dealing with is the משנה Mishnah that
talks about different מנחות Menachos getting mixed up with one another,
one that's sort of doughy as it gets mixed up with one
that's more battery and like a batter. And the position of the
חכמים Chachamim that עולים אין מבטלין זה את זה, olim ein mevatlin
zeh et zeh, things that go up on the מזבח, Mizbeach, there's
no ביטול bittel does not operate. And the position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that מין במינו לא בטיל, min b'mino lo batel, that
if it's the same type of thing then no ביטול bittel occurs.
That we were introduced to yesterday and is being brought to bear
on the issues of the משנה. Mishnah. So let's take a look
at where the גמרא Gemara goes with this. איתמר, Itmar, it was
taught, three lines from the top, כ"ג עמוד א', chaf gimmel amud
aleph, קומץ ממנחת חוטא ששמנו. komets mi-minchas choteh she-shimno.
So this actually is not back to the ביטול bittel yet, this
is more about mixing other things into it, and a little bit
of a bizarre case which you would not have expected from what
we've been talking about. You take the קומץ komets of a מנחה
mincha of like a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh ve-yored, you know
the case at the end of פרשת ויקרא, Parshat Vayikra, and you
add a little oil to it. Okay, ששמנו. she-shimno. So what are
you adding? Are you adding oil of חולין בעזרה? chulin ba-azarah? Then
it sort of be a problem of like חולין בעזרה. chulin ba-azarah.
You adding oil, you know, from something else, from some other קרבן,
korban, not exactly clear, but we'll get to that in a minute.
רבי יוחנן פסול, Rabbi Yochanan posul, פסול posul says it's פסול posul
over here. ריש לקיש אמר, Resh Lakish amar, הוא עצמו משכשכו בשירי
הלוג ומלאהו. hu atzmo meshachshacho bi-sheyarei ha-log u-malo'ehu. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says it's פסול. posul. This is supposed to be חרב, charev, it's
supposed to be without oil. You've added oil, you have made this
a different type of a מנחה, mincha, it's no longer חרב charev
and therefore it's not a legitimate קומץ. komets. And ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish says no, actually this is exactly how you're supposed to do.
You're supposed to take this... this קומץ komets and it's not appropriate
to put anything something on the מזבח Mizbeach without oil. I don't
know why not. And therefore you rub a little oil on it
from the remnant of the לוג. log. What does the remnant of
the לוג log mean? It means when you fill up a לוג
log of oil to put into a מנחה, mincha, not this מנחה,
mincha, a מנחה mincha that's a mixture of oil and flour.
You know you try to pour all the לוג log out but
there's a little residue that remains. So you take that residue- so
you take
this מנחה, mincha, this dry מנחה mincha without any oil, and you
sort of rub it on the כלי, kli, you know the measuring
vessel that you had this לוג log of oil in that has
this, you know, residue film on it and you get it a
little oily and you put it up on the מזבח. Mizbeach. So
first of all תוספות Tosafot says one minute if there's a little
residue left, then how was the מנחה mincha that you used this
oil for, the normal מנחה, mincha, how is it כשר? kosher? It
was חסר שמניו, chasar shemanav, didn't have all of the oil. So
תוספות Tosafot says לא ניתנה תורה למלאכי השרת, lo nitnah Torah l'malachei
ha-shareis, that's an important principle. Like okay, it's not possible to get
out the tiny little film of oil and that constitutes, it has
all the oil, even though it only has 99.9% of the oil.
That's a very important principle in הלכה, halacha, when do we consider
something to be like close enough because you it's impossible. Like for
example, a תפילין tefillin has to be square. How do you measure
it with a microscope? Like what how close of a measurement do
you do and are you required to do, because לא ניתנה תורה
למלאכי השרת, lo nitnah Torah l'malachei ha-shareis, you know it's has to
be some something that an operative principle of what constitutes all of
the oil. So that's one point. But the other point here is
that where's ריש לקיש Resh Lakish getting this idea? I mean that
it's supposed to have some oil to it, why would you want
to introduce anything external? And not only that this oil is, you
know, it's has it- maybe he feels it's קדוש kadosh and therefore
you want to get it up on the מזבח, Mizbeach, but it
doesn't belong on the מזבח. Mizbeach. You mixed it with a מנחה
mincha and you're only taking the קומץ komets of that מנחה, mincha,
you know to put on the מזבח. Mizbeach. So very strange that
we should be doing this. Anyway that's ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish position.
ומלאהו והכתיב, u-malo'ehu ve-ha-ksiv, so the גמרא Gemara says even a stronger
question than all the questions I'm asking. Doesn't the פסוק pasuk say
לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה, lo yasim aleha shemen
v'lo yiten aleha levonah, specifically by the מנחת חוטא minchas choteh which
does not have oil? You shall not put oil on it and
don't put on it like the frankincense. So isn't this a direct
violation of the פסוק? pasuk? So it says ההוא שלא יקבע לה
שמן כחברתה. hahu she-lo yikba la shemen k'chavertah. No, that means don't,
you know, mix it with oil like you do with a normal-
don't treat it like a normal מנחה mincha which is a mixture
of flour and oil, and
but that doesn't mean that you can't have like a little shmear
of oil on it. Pretty amazing given how absolute the פסוק pasuk
is that we're going to read it to just mean don't make
it as much of a mixture, you know, or mixture like other
מנחות. minachos. Okay. איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, eitvei Rabbi Yochanan le-Resh
Lakish, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan challenged ריש לקיש. Resh Lakish. חרב
שנתערב בבלול
יקריב, charev she-nitarev b'balul yakriv, רבי יהודה אומר לא יקריב. Rabbi Yehuda
omer lo yakriv. Okay, so here we... Okay so here we have
a ברייתא braita, *braisa* that says if you have a dry מנחה
Mincha, *mincha* that got mixed up with a מנחה Mincha *mincha* with
oil, so you can go ahead and offer it up. That's the
position of the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* that אין עולים olim מבטלין זה
את זה *ein olim mevatlin zeh es zeh*. And רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda. *Rebbe Yehuda* says you cannot offer it up. Because, you know,
he says, at least the way the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s been understanding
him, ביטול bittul *bittul* operates here. This is a type of maybe
מין בשאינו מינו *min b'sheino mino* and ביטול bittul. *bittul* operates and
therefore it's going to be like you won't have the right proportions
of the מנחה Mincha *mincha* here. Alright, so what does that mean?
So, מאי לאו lav. *mai lav*, hold on, מאי לאו *mai lav*,
are we not talking about קומץ Kometz, מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei דנתערב
בקומץ מנחת נדבה *komitz minchas chotei denisarrev bekomitz minchas nedavah*? You have
the קומץ Kometz, *komitz* of the מנחה Mincha *mincha* of a sinner,
you know, which is plain without oil, got mixed up with a
קומץ Kometz? *komitz* of a normal מנחה Mincha *mincha*, of a מנחה
Mincha *mincha* that's a free offering, and that,
and it's a problem according to the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim*. Okay, and
right because the חכמים Chachamim? *Chachamim* only say that you can offer
it up because אין עולים olim, מבטלין זה את זה *ein olim
mevatlin zeh es zeh*. So that's why it's okay to offer it
up. But fundamentally, the fact that oil is being mixed into this
dry מנחה Mincha *mincha* would be a problem were it not for
the principle of אין עולים olim, מבטלין זה את זה *ein olim
mevatlin zeh es zeh*. So therefore because of that principle we can
say any oil that is on the מנחת חוטא *minchas chotei* is
considered not part of the מנחת חוטא *minchas chotei*. It's considered part
of the מנחת נדבה *minchas nedavah* because אין עולים olim. מבטלין זה
את זה *ein olim mevatlin zeh es zeh* and you have an
actual מנחת נדבה *minchas nedavah* here that the oil came from. But
fundamentally, if you, you know, having oil on the מנחת חוטא *minchas
chotei* would be a problem if it was extraneous oil and didn't
belong to some other מנחה Mincha *mincha*, it would invalidate the מנחת
חוטא *minchas chotei*. Isn't that what it's saying? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, לא, מנחת פרים ואילים במנחת כבשים *lo, minchas parim v'eilim
b'minchas k'vasim*. No, what you're mixing up is, you know, two types
of מנחת נסכים *minchas nesachim*. Now מנחת נסכים *minchas nesachim* is always
the מנחה mincha. *mincha* that you would bring together with let's say
an עולה *olah* קרבן korban *korban*,
and it would be a mixture of, you know, flour and oil,
and you would also of course bring wine, the תורה Torah *Torah*
spells out what the various נסכים *nesachim* are that you bring with
the קרבנות *korbanos*. And here, what you bring if it is a
lamb, it says you bring a רביעית ההין *revi'is ha-hin*. So a
הין *hin* is twelve לוג *log*, so a רביעית ההין *revi'is ha-hin*
is three לוג *log*, and it says mixed up with one עשרון
*issaron* of flour. So that's a ratio of three to one, the
oil to the flour.
Whereas, three לוג *log* to one עשרון *issaron*. Okay,
but when you get to the cow and the rams, the ratio
is greater. Why? Because there it says that for a cow has
two עשרונות *isronos* of flour, and, excuse me, a ram has two
עשרונות *isronos* of flour, and it says that it is a שלישית
ההין *shlishis ha-hin*, which is four לוג *log* of שמן *shemen*, so
that's a four to two or two to one ratio. Similarly by
a cow, it is three עשרונות *isronos* of flour and a חצי
ההין *chatzi ha-hin*, which is six לוג *log* of שמן *shemen*, so
that's two to one. Okay, so the one for the lamb has
a greater amount of proportion of oil than the one for the
cow and for the ram. Alright, so that's dry
with oily. Now of course it's not really dry and that's a
very difficult read, but it's claiming that it means dry in comparison
to the one of the lamb that has even more oil. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, לא, מנחת פרים ואילים במנחת כבשים *lo,
minchas parim v'eilim b'minchas k'vasim*. והא *ve-ha*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, והא בהדיא קתני לה *ve-ha be-hedya katni lah*?
But one minute, it says explicitly your case and it says explicitly
the case of a קומץ Kometz, של מנחת חוטא *komitz shel minchas
chotei*. Because what does the ברייתא *braisa* say? מנחת פרים ואילים במנחת
כבשים *Minchas parim v'eilim b'minchas k'vasim*, case number one, those got mixed
up, different proportion of oil but everything has oil. Case number two,
חרב שנתערב בבלול יקריב *charev shenisarrev bevallul yakriv*, or a, you know,
the dry one got mixed up with one that had oil. Okay,
the חכמים *Chachamim* say you could be מקריב makriv *makriv* it because
אין עולים olim. מבטלין זה את זה *ein olim mevatlin zeh es
zeh*. ורבי יהודה אומר omer לא יקריב *v'Rebbe Yehuda omer lo yakriv*,
you can't be מקריב makriv *makriv*. So again, if we're talking about
the case of dry with oil, that's exactly your case ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*. And the only reason the חכמים *Chachamim* say
it's okay is because the oil gets attributed to the other מנחה
mincha *mincha*. But fundamentally, oil on the חרב *charev* is a problem.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, פירושי קמפרש
לה *peirushi kamfaresh lah*. No, no, even though it says dry and
with oil, really that's just explaining why there's a problem with the
מנחה mincha, *mincha* of the lambs getting mixed up with the מנחה
mincha. *mincha* of the rams and of the cows, because the מנחה
mincha. *mincha* of the lamb is oily compared to... drier מנחה minchah
of the cam of of the cows and of the rams. Okay,
very difficult read of that גמרא. gemara
But anyway, but if the גמרא gemara is able to say ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish, is able to say we're talking all about two
different types of מנחות Minchos with oil, then he's not dealing with
his case of the dry מנחה, minchah the מנחת חוטא which he
says it's okay to put a little oil on. Then he's dealing
with two different מנחות Minchos that have oil in them of different
proportions, and then it'll be a problem if ביטול bittul. is operative,
or you know, which is the debate of the חכמים and רבי
יהודה. reb yehudah Okay. So now the גמרא gemara says like
this. בעי רבא. Ba'ei Rava. So that was the debate of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish. again very shocking surprising
position of ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish? Now רבא Rava asked: קומץ שמיצה
שמנו על גבי עצים מהו? Kometz she-mitzah shamno agabi eitzim mahu? If
you took this קומץ, Kometz this, you know, flour and oil, and
you squeezed out some of the oil onto the wood, so what's
the story? חיבורי עולין כעולין דמו או לאו כעולין דמו? Chiburei olin
k'olin damu o lav k'olin damu? Is something connected to something that
goes up on the מזבח mizbe'ach like the thing that goes up
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, or is it not? Now what exactly is
the question, what's the problem? So there's three, רש"י Rashi has two
ways of reading it and תוספות Tosafos has a third way. רש"י's
Rashi way of reading it is the wood means the wood that
is on the top of the altar. So you squeeze out some
of the oil, it drips on it, and then you put the
what's left of the קומץ, Kometz most of it, but a little
less oil, you know, on the מזבח mizbe'ach on top of the
oil that you already put there. Is that considered like you were
מקריב makriv the קומץ? komitz. Because you have to be מקריב makriv
the whole קומץ, komitz, and here you actually first did oil and
then you did a קומץ komitz, that was missing some oil. So
or do we say since in the end you put it on
top of the oil that was sitting on the wood, that's considered
like it's all one unit? חיבורי עולין כעולין דמו. Chiburei olin k'olin
damu. It's a little funny and especially we'll see the case that
the גמרא gemara. compares it to that does not seem to fit
exactly this phrase of חיבורי עולין. Chiburei olin. So another reading that
רש"י Rashi has is that the wood is not the wood on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. You squeezed it out on some firewood and now
you have oil that's absorbed into that firewood. And the question is,
do you have to be מקריב makriv that wood on the מזבח?
mizbe'ach? And why so?
Because it has some of the oil. And what would the question
be? Is the oil which is connected to the thing that's on
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, what's the thing that's on the מזבח mizbe'ach that
goes on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? The flour. So the oil is חיבורי
אוכלין, chiburei ochlin, connected to, you know, to the flour. Is that
considered like the flour itself? If it's like the flour itself, it
has to be put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. If it's not like
the flour itself, then you can leave it absorbed in the wood.
Now that's very bizarre because why should we consider the flour to
be more of the מנחה minchah than the oil? I mean it
is true you are mixing
the oil with the flour, but isn't the מנחה minchah everything that's
mixed together? I mean this is a very interesting conceptual way to
think about it. That since the תורה Torah has a מנחה minchah
without oil, fundamentally a מנחה minchah, is flour. And oil is something
you add to the מנחה mincha the same way you add like
לבונה. levonah. Okay, maybe that's indicated in the פסוק pasuk by the
חרבה: chareivah: לא יתן עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה. lo yitein
aleha shemen v'lo yitein aleha levonah.
So you think of the oil as something added to the base
מנחה mincha, which is flour. So then the question is, does that
have the same obligation to be put on the מזבח mizbe'ach like
the flour itself? So you could actually if you say no, you
could actually be מקריב makriv a קומץ komitz that did not have
all the oil. חסר שמנו chisar shamno is a problem
but from when you create the מנחה mincha. itself. But here it's
suggesting that actually
maybe the oil some of the oil would not have to go
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Also pretty shocking. Okay, תוספות Tosafos has yet
a third possibility, we're going to leave it at these two of
רש"י. Rashi. So let's see what the גמרא gemara says. חיבורי עולין
כעולין דמו או לאו כעולין דמו. Chiburei olin k'olin damu o lav
k'olin damu. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי: Amar lei Ravina l'Rav Ashi:
So רבינא Ravina said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, לאו היינו דרבי
יוחנן וריש לקיש? lav hainu d'Rabbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish? Isn't this connected
to a different debate of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish דאתמר: d'itmar: It
was taught: המעלה אבר שאין בו כזית ועצם משלימו לכזית. Ha-ma'aleh eivar
she-ein bo k'zayis v'etzem mashlimo l'k'zayis. Somebody is ma'aleh something outside the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Are you חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ, shechutei
chutz, for העלאת חוץ? ha'alas chutz? For offering a קרבן korban. outside
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. You're only חייב chayav if you put
up a כזית k'zayis of a קרבן. So let's say it's three
quarters of a כזית k'zayis of meat and one quarter of a
כזית k'zayis of a little piece of bone that's in the meat.
Is that like you offered up a whole כזית k'zayis and now
you're
חייב? chayav? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says חייב, chayav, ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish אמר פטור amar patur you're exempt. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
אמר חייב: amar chayav: חיבורי עולין כעולין דמו, chiburei olin k'olin damu,
something attached to... to the meat is like the meat, even though
it's true that a bone, if it comes off of the מזבח,
mizbeach, you don't put it back up, it's not, there's not a
direct obligation to offer the bone. When it's attached to the meat,
it's like the meat and it's like you were מקריב makriv a
full כזית. kezayit. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish? אומר פטור, pattur, חיבורי עולין
לאו כעולין דמו. chiburei olin lav ke-olin damu. You're exempt just because
it's connected doesn't make it like the thing that goes up. So
this works much more better in the second version of רש״י, Rashi,
once you think of the oil as something added to the fundamental
מנחה. mincha So the question is, like the bone added to the
meat. So how much is the oil really something that is becomes
like the מנחה mincha and has to be offered up? So that's...
so the גמרא Gemara says isn't that this debate of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש? Reish Lakish So the גמרא Gemara says, no.
תיבעי לרבי יוחנן תיבעי לריש לקיש. tibbaei le-Rabbi Yochanan tibbaei le-Reish Lakish.
Our question about the case of the oil could be a question
whichever position you take in the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish debate. תיבעי לרבי יוחנן, tibbaei le-Rabbi Yochanan, you could ask
according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יוחנן
התם, ad kan lo ka-amar Rabbi Yochanan hatam, maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan only says his position about the bone with the meat adding
to a full כזית, kezayit, אלא בעצם דמינא דבשרא הוא, ela be-etzem
de-mina de-bisra hu, that's only the bone which is a natural part
of the meat. Okay? I mean, that's how the cow grows and
you're offering up the bone in its natural location, you know, it's
not like you took a separate bone and you stuck it in
the meat. This
is the natural formation. So that could be seen as one unit.
אבל האי, aval hai, and counts towards something offered up. אבל האי
דלאו מינא דקומץ הוא, aval hai de-lav mina de-komitz hu, but the
oil is not a natural part of the קומץ. komitz Now, of
course it is what the תורה tells you to take of the
קומץ, komitz but flour and oil don't somehow naturally grow together. This
is something added and mixed in, added from the outside. So maybe
even ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. what he says by the bone he
wouldn't say about the oil. או דילמא, o dilma, or you could,
I mean even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan even though he says it's
one with the bone, that was natural, but by the oil he
would consider that to be separate. או דילמא אפילו ריש לקיש, o
dilma afilu Reish Lakish, or you could on the other hand you
could ask even according to
ריש לקיש. לא קאמר אלא בעצם דבר מפרש הוא ואי פריש למזבח
לאדורי. lo ka-amar ela be-etzem de-bar mifrash hu ve-i parish la-mizbeach la-durei.
Maybe he only says it by the bone, because even the bone
is natural, why isn't it considered part of the meat to be
a כזית? kezayit? Because you don't have a direct חיוב chiyuv to
offer up the bone on the מזבח. mizbeach. And it's something that
can be separated out and if it flies off the מזבח, mizbeach,
you don't have to put it back up. Okay, we dealt with
that in זבחים. Zevachim. So therefore because fundamentally there's no direct מצוה
mitzvah to offer it, it's not one with the כזית kezayit of
meat even though they grew together naturally. אבל שמן דלאו בר מפרש
הוא, aval shemen de-lav bar mifrash hu, but oil that's not supposed
to be separated, you know, from the קומץ, komitz, and if it
is... so that's really meant to be together and the whole thing
is meant to be offered
up. או דילמא לא שני, o dilma lo shanei, do we say
it doesn't matter and the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, teiku, we'll leave
it as a question. So again what is really fascinating is the
idea that the oil seeing the oil as not intrinsic, it's sort
of like the לבונה, levonah, something put on the מנחה, mincha. and
the possibility that maybe when you take a whole קומץ komitz and
it's a full קומץ komitz, with the flour and the oil, maybe
you don't have to actually offer up all the oil because maybe
you're looking at the oil as something that was added. So that's
definitely not something I think we would have thought naturally. Okay, let's
take a look at the next משנה. mishna. שתי מנחות שלא נקמצו
ונתערבו זו בזו. shetei menachot she-lo nikmetzu ve-nitarvu zo be-zo. You have
two מנחות menachot that you have not taken the קומץ komitz out
of and they got mixed up, okay, and they could be the
exact same type of a מנחה. mincha, Now so what happened was,
imagine, imagine that you have, you know, think about like those Venn
diagrams where you have two circles and you have the overlap. So
that's what happened. You know, these מנחות menachot they... a part of
them overlapped
and got mixed up in the middle and all the oily flour
became like one homogeneous in the middle but there's the edges are
still distinct.
Okay so the משנה mishna says, or if the edges are distinct.
אם יכול לקמוץ מזו בפני עצמה ומזו בפני עצמה, im yakhol likmotz
mi-zo bifnei atzmah u-mi-zo bifnei atzmah, if you could take a קומץ,
komitz you know, you have an A circle and a B circle
and they've intersected with an AB section, but if in the A
part alone you can take a קומץ komitz, that is not mixed
and the B part alone you can take a קומץ, komitz
so כשרות, kesherot, then take that קומץ kometz and both מנחות menachot
are כשר kasher because you offered up the right קומץ kometz from
that מנחה. mincha ואם לאו, ve-im lav, but if you can't get
a full קומץ, kometz you know, from the A circle or from
the B circle when it's alone and you can only get it
when you include some of the AB overlap, then it's not going
to be, then it's going to be פסול pasul because then your
קומץ kometz is going to have for A is going to have
some of the flour and oil from B.
Okay, קומץ שנתערב במנחה שלא נקמצה. kometz shenitarav beminchah shelo nikmetzah. Now
let's say you have the you took, not the two מנחות minchos
got mixed up, you took a קומץ kometz from A and then
accidentally you put it down and it got mixed up with B,
which was the whole מנחה mincha that had not yet had the
קומץ kometz taken from it. So the קומץ kometz of A got
mixed up with B. לא יקטיר, lo yaktir, don't go ahead. Now
what you want to do is you have a מצוה mitzvah to
be מקריב the קומץ kometz from A, so just put this whole
mixture up on the מזבח mizbeiach and at least you'll be מקריב
the קומץ kometz from A. But the answer is no, don't do
that. Because B does not yet have the קומץ kometz taken and
therefore it does not it should not go on the מזבח. mizbeiach.
Only the קומץ kometz, goes on the מזבח. mizbeiach. לא יקטיר. lo
yaktir. ואם הקטיר, ve'im hiktir, but if you did put all of
this mixture up, the קומץ kometz of A plus B, זו שנקמצה
עולה לבעלים, zu shenikmetzah olah libaalim, so A, the one that the
קומץ kometz was taken out from, A actually counts because its קומץ
kometz was offered up. וזו שלא נקמצה vezu shelo nikmetzah לא עולה
לבעלים lo olah libaalim and B never had the קומץ, kometz because
B, there's no way to take the קומץ kometz from B because
now B is a mixture of B plus קומץ kometz A. So
since no קומץ kometz was taken, therefore the מנחה mincha, does not
count. נתערב קומצה בשיריה, nitarav kumtzah beshireha, let's say you take the
קומץ kometz of A and then accidentally you drop it back in
A. או בשיריה של חבירתה, o beshireha shel chaveirtah, or you took
a קומץ kometz from A and a קומץ kometz from B and
accidentally now you dropped A in the leftover part of the מנחה
mincha of B. Same הלכה, halachah, לא יקטיר, lo yaktir, don't offer
it up because then you're offering up קומץ kometz, plus the שיריים.
shirayim. And there's actually a
the way חז"ל chazal read a פסוק pasuk to not offer up
the
שיריים. shirayim. קומץ ממנו לאישים kometz mimenu leishim is what it said,
anything that from that a part of it was put on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, the stuff that remains cannot be offered up. So therefore
you can't offer the whole thing up, you'll be putting the שיריים
shirayim on the מזבח mizbeiach which is a לאו. But לא יקטיר,
lo yaktir, ואם הקטיר, ve'im hiktir, עולה לבעלים, olah libaalim, but if
you did offer it up then it does count, because now you
have A and the שיריים shirayim of A, but you did take
a legitimate קמיצה kmitzah and you offered up the קמיצה kmitzah on
the מזבח mizbeiach even though it was together with the שיריים, shirayim,
but that makes the מנחה כשר. kosher. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר רב חסדא, amar rav chisda, says
רב חסדא, rav chisda,
נבילה בטלה בשחוטה, neveilah betelah bishchutah, שאי אפשר לשחוטה שתעשה נבילה. she'ei
efshar lishchutah sheteiaseh neveilah. If you have three pieces of meat mixed
up, a
נבילה, neveilah, something not shechted properly, and two other steaks, let's say
a steak and two other steaks that were from an animal that
was shechted properly, and we're going to now do ביטול. bittul A
question of ביטול. bittul It's not going to be ביטול bittul in
order to eat it, it's going to be a question of ביטול
bittul if you touch it, do you become טמא. tamei. Okay? Or
if some תרומה terumah touches it or whatever. So if you have
the נבילה neveilah is the one object and the שחוטה shchutah are
the two, are the majority, so they're coming to negate the נבילה,
neveilah, then ביטול bittul does work. Why? Because the שחוטה shchutah cannot
become a נבילה. neveilah. Once something is a kosher piece of meat
it cannot become a נבילה. neveilah. Okay, we'll discuss in a minute
why that matters. שאי אפשר לשחוטה שתעשה נבילה. she'ei efshar lishchutah sheteiaseh
neveilah. ושחוטה אינה בטלה בנבילה. ushchutah einah betelah beneveilah. However, if
it was the reverse, if you have one kosher steak and two
that are נבילה, neveilah, those two נבילה neveilah do not do ביטול
bittul on the שחוטה shchutah to make it into a נבילה neveilah
as well, which is a funny idea that ביטול bittul could work
not just to remove a status but to add a status of
נבילה. neveilah. But okay, if you have the two that are נבילה
neveilah and the one that's a שחוטה, shchutah, in that case ביטול
bittul does not work. Why? שאפשר לנבילה שתעשה שחוטה. she'efshar leneveilah sheteiaseh
shchutah.
Because the נבילה neveilah could become שחוטה. shchutah. How could a piece
of נבילה neveilah become kosher or become not טמא? tamei? Why? דלכי
מסרחא, delichi masracha, because if it would become spoiled, פרחה טומאתה, parchah
tumatah, then once a נבילה neveilah is spoiled, it doesn't have a
status of a נבילה neveilah anymore and the טומאה tumah goes off.
So it could theoretically get a similar status to the שחוטה shchutah
of not being טמא. tamei. And therefore ביטול bitul. doesn't work. Now
what does this mean? So what they're working with, what the גמרא
Gemara is going to say is they're working with the position of
רבי יהודה reb yehudah that מין במינו לא בטל. min bemino lo
battel. Now
when רבי יהודה reb yehudah. says מין במינו לא בטל, min bemino
lo battel, we assume his definition of מין במינו min bemino is
that it's the same physical object, blood with blood, מנחה with מנחה,
that's what he's talking about. They are adding that you need it
to be מין במינו min bemino on another plane as well to
say ביטול bitul doesn't so they're narrowing רבי יהודה. reb yehudah When
would רבי יהודה reb yehudah say or he's narrowing, רב חסדא, rav
chisda, but then there's going to be רב הונא. rav huna. When
is רבי יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda מין במינו לא בטל? min bemino lo
battel? When it's both the Same physical object and they theoretically, they
could have the same halakhic status. Okay, what does that mean they
could have the same halakhic status? So for רב חסדא Rav Chisda
we're going to look at the thing that's doing the ביטול. bitul
So if the thing doing the ביטול bitul, is the kosher meat,
the kosher meat can never become a נבלה. neveila. So it can
never have the same status as a נבלה. neveila. So that's a
מין באינו מינו, min be-eino mino, great, ביטול bitul. occurs. But if
the thing that's doing the ביטול, bitul. the majority, is the נבלה,
neveila, since a נבלה neveila could lose its טומאה tumah by becoming
spoiled and therefore it could become like the kosher meat, that already
makes it that they're not just the same two pieces of meat,
they're also in some ways close to the same status. That's מין
במינו min be-mino and and that's the case that רבי יהודה Rebbe
Yehuda, would say there's no ביטול. bitul, When it's both the same
physically and somewhat the same in terms of status, and you ask
the question in terms of the thing that is the מבטל, mevatel,
doing the ביטול. bitul, רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, רב הונא Rav
Huna says the same in the reverse. Okay,
so רבי, Rabbi, I'm sorry not רב הונא, Rav Huna, רבי חנינא.
Rabbi Chanina. It's רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רבי חנינא. Rabbi Chanina.
רבי חנינא אמר, Rabbi Chanina amar, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina says, כל
שאפשר לו להיות כמהו אינו בטל. kol she-efshar lo liyot kamohu eino
batel. The same thing, if you could be like it, it's not
בטל, batel, but he is referring to the thing becoming בטל. batel.
So if the minority thing, the נבלה, neveila, could be if it's
two of the kosher against the one נבלה, neveila, since the נבלה
neveila could become not kosher, well could become not טרפה treif and
not טמא tamei by being spoiled, so therefore since it can become
like the things that are doing the ביטול, bitul. therefore it's מין
במינו min be-mino and it's not בטל. batel. וכל שאי אפשר לו
להיות כמהו, ve-kol she-ei efshar lo liyot kamohu, if it can't become
like the thing doing the ביטול, bitul. if the minority was the
שחוטה shechuta and the majority was the נבלה, neveila, since a שחוטה
shechuta cannot become a נבלה, neveila, in that case בטל, batel, it's
מין באינו מינו min be-eino mino and it's בטל. batel. Same idea,
except he says to measure whether they're considered to have the same
status or not, I look at the thing becoming בטל, batel, not
the thing doing the ביטול. bitul The בטל batel not the מבטל.
mevatel. Now why, other than narrowing רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda what is
the logic of saying that it's not enough that they be the
same physical object, but they actually have to have somewhat close to
the same status? Because as we discussed the other day, what's the
logic of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda מין במינו לא בטל? min be-mino
lo batel? The logic is that if everything is the same, then
you can't make it disappear. If you add meat to meat or
blood to blood or מנחה to מנחה, you can't say oh look,
the added thing disappeared, it was overwhelmed by the majority. What do
you mean? It's all blood, it's all מנחה. So how so so
it's still there, there's just more of it. So therefore there's no
ביטול. bitul, So this is what the ר"ן Ran says and the
ר"ן Ran says, so then he says, so what's the position of
the חכמים that ביטול bitul does occur in that case? He says
cause there still is difference to be erased. The difference to be
erased is not the physical object but the halakhic status. So if
you put a blood of קדשים, kodshim, blood of חולין chullin into
blood of קדשים kodshim into blood of חולין, chullin, so therefore it's
all blood but it's קדשים kodshim and חולין. chullin. So the חולין
chullin erase the קדשים. kodshim. The difference of status also can allow
for erasure. Alright, so what רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina are saying is they're basically saying רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
also is sensitive to that. So for רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda to
be מין במינו min be-mino and say no ביטול, bitul. they have
to be the same physically and close to the same in terms
of their halakhic status, and then there's almost no difference between them
and ביטול bitul does not occur. Okay, so that is a real
narrowing. So now let's see, now the גמרא's Gemara just going to
work to spell out what I just said. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, אליבא דמאן, aliba de-man, according to who are
they going to in the debate of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda, and
the חכמים? אי אליבא דרבנן, Ee aliba de-rabbanan, if it's the רבנן,
Rabbanan, אמר עולין ודלא מבטלי הדדי, amei olin u-de-lo mevatli hadadi, so
מין במינו בטל. min be-mino batel. It's clear from רב חסדא Rav
Chisda and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina that they're working within the principle
of מין במינו לא בטל. min be-mino lo batel. So that's not
the Rabbis, the Rabbis say it's עולין olin that aren't מבטל זה
את זה, mevatel zeh et zeh, but מין במינו min be-mino is
מבטל זה את זה. mevatel zeh et zeh. אבל אי אליבא דרבי
יהודה, Eval ee aliba de-Rebbe Yehuda, if it's going like רבי יהודה,
Rebbe Yehuda, which it sounds like, so the גמרא Gemara says ורבי
יהודה בתר חזותא אזיל והאי והאי מין במינו הוא. ve-Rebbe Yehuda batar
chazuta azil ve-hai ve-hai min be-mino hu. So as far as we
know, because before we now redefined רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda רבי יהודה's
Rebbe Yehuda definition of מין במינו min be-mino is the things look
the same. Are they fundamentally the same object? So steak and steak
is all looks the same, it's all the same object. We've never
heard that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda cares about the statuses being somewhat
the same. אלא אליבא דרבי חייא. Ella aliba de-Rabbi Chiya. Fine, what
they're discussing
the interpretation of a teaching of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. דתני רבי
חייא, De-tani Rabbi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught a ברייתא, נבלה
ושחוטה בטלה זו בזו. neveila ve-shechuta betela zo be-zo. נבלה Neveila and
שחוטה shechuta create ביטול. bitul So comes along רבי Rabbi רב חסדא
Rav Chisda and So comes along רב חסדא Rav Chisda and רבי
חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, a lot of ח Chet here, and they're saying
one says they only cause ביטול bitul this way, the other says
it only causes ביטול bitul in the other way. Okay fine, they're
arguing a text of רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, but we still have
to spell out how it works within the positions of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and רבנן. Rabbanan. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says.
רבי חייא אליבא דמאן? Rabbi Chiya aliba d'man? So who is this
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya going like? אי אליבא דרבנן הא עולין הוא
דלא מבטלי הדדי הא מין במין בטל. Ei aliba d'Rabbanan ha olin
hu d'lo mivtli hadadi ha min bemin batel. If it's according to
the רבנן, Rabbanan, the רבנן, Rabbanan, you know they still רב חסדא
Rav Chisda and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina are working within the idea
of מין במין, min bemin, and that's the model that they're using.
So that can't be according to the Rabbis. The Rabbis say עולין
olin are not מבטל mivatel one another, but מין במין min bemin
is. אלא דרבי יהודה? Ella d'Rabbi Yehuda?
So now we're back to where we were. Fine, they're working within
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of מין במין לא בטל. min bemin lo
batel. כל מין במין לרבי יהודה לא בטל. Kol min bemin l'Rabbi
Yehuda lo batel. So for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda he doesn't make
these distinctions. It's saying the same thing it said before in a
slightly different way. He doesn't seem to make these distinctions based on
status. For him it's meat and meat, and it's not בטל. batel.
Who cares about the status?
So the גמרא Gemara says no. לעולם. L'olam. So it's a long
way of saying what are you doing? We've never heard that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. cares about status to define מין במין. min bemin.
And now it's going to say yes, that is what they're claiming.
לעולם אליבא דרבי יהודה. L'olam aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda. They are going according
to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda וכי קאמר רבי יהודה מין במין לא
בטל, Vechi ka'amar Rabbi Yehuda min bemin lo batel, and when רבי
יהודה Rabi Yehuda. said מין במין לא בטל min bemin lo batel
and you thought for him it was all that meant was fundamentally
the same substance, הני מילי היכא דאפשר ליה למהוי כוותיה. hanei milei
heicha d'efshar lei l'meihavi k'vaseih. Their claiming that's only when the status
is also somewhat the same. When the status, when the different objects
one status could be like the other. אבל היכא דלא אפשר ליה
למהוי כוותיה, Aval heicha d'lo efshar lei l'meihavi k'vaseih, but if it's
not possible for their statuses to be similar, then בטל, batel, then
it's אינו מינו eino mino and ביטול bitul. works. ובהא קמיפלגי, Uvha
kamifligi, and this is what the basic debate of רב חסדא Rav
Chisda and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina are. רב חסדא סבר בתר מבטל
אזלינן ורבי חנינא סבר בתר בטל אזלינן. Rav Chisda savar batar mivatel
azlinan v'Rabbi Chanina savar batar batel azlinan. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
you ask can the מבטל, mivatel, the thing that's the majority, be
like the minority? And if so that's מין במין min bemin and
it's not בטל. batel. And
רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, excuse me, חנינא Chanina says can the בטל,
batel, the thing that's the minority, can that be like the majority?
And if so it's מין במין min bemin and not בטל. batel.
Okay, now we're going to try to see if we can prove
it one way or another from our משנה Mishnah about these מנחות
menachot mixing up.
תנן, Tnan, we turn the משנה. Mishnah. שתי מנחות שלא נקמצו ונתערבו
זו בזו. Shtei menachot shelo nikmetzu venisarvu zu b'zu.
So you have two מנחות menachot that were
not נקמצו nikmetzu and they got mixed up, you know A and
B and then the AB overlap. אם יכול לקמוץ מזו בפני עצמה
ומזו בפני עצמה כשרה. Im yakhol likmotz mizu bifnei atzmah umizu bifnei
atzmah k'shairah. If you can take from A alone and from B
alone then it's כשרה k'shairah even though there's an AB overlap. ואם
לאו פסולה. V'im lav pesulah. If not it's פסולה. pesulah. So now
the גמרא Gemara says let's figure this out. והכא כיון דקמיץ ליה
מחדא, Ve'hacha keivan d'kamitz lei mechada, as soon as you take the
קמיצה kmitzah from A, אידך הוי ליה שיריים. idach havei lei shiyarayim.
So now you're left the remnant of A that's by itself and
with the AB overlap is שיריים. shiyarayim. If it's שיריים, shiyarayim, it's
a different kind of thing than B which is considered the גמרא
Gemara uses the phrase טבל tevel meaning a מנחה that has not
had the קומץ kometz taken from it. Okay, הוי ליה שיריים. havei
lei shiyarayim. ולא קא מבטלי שיריים לטבלא. V'lo ka'mivtlei shiyarayim l'tevela. And
now the שיריים shiyarayim are not being מבטל, mivatel, it's clear from
the משנה Mishnah no ביטול bitul is taking place. The שיריים shiyarayim
are not being מבטל mivatel the טבל, tevel, you know, and you
can still go ahead and take the קומץ kometz from B. It's
no way is B disappearing because of the AB overlap. All right,
מאן היא? mani? Let's figure out who this is going like.
אי רבנן הא אמרי עולין הוא דלא מבטלי הדדי. Ei Rabbanan ha'amri
olin hu d'lo mivtli hadadi. So if it's so now why does
it only become a problem once it becomes שיריים? shiyarayim? Because when
it becomes שיריים, shiyarayim, why didn't the גמרא Gemara ask it when
it was just the whole setup scenario? Because when it becomes שיריים
shiyarayim it stops being עולין, olin, okay? When it, or
actually I'm not sure that's true I was going to say that
when it before it was שיריים shiyarayim they were both עולין olin
but actually that might not be true because they both have a
part that's עולין olin but you know but the whole things, the
whole A and B are not עולין. olin. But regardless, before it
became שיריים shiyarayim they were all fundamentally the same, so there was
you know no ביטול. bitul Okay? But אי... so אי רבנן ei
rabanan? הא אמרי עולין olin. הוא דלא מבטלי mivatli הדדי. hadadi, So
for the רבנן Rabbanan the only thing that's not מבטל mivatel one
another is עולין. olin הא
מין במין בטל. Ha min bemin batel. But in this case they're
not עולין olin, and it's שיריים shiyarayim which is clearly outside the
category of עולין, so ביטול bitul should be operative. So why doesn't
the שיריים shiyarayim do ביטול bitul on the AB overlap and make
the and make B a מנחה that's not complete? אלא פשיטא רבי
יהודה. Ella peshita Rabbi Yehuda. It must be the reason that once
A becomes שיריים shirayim *shirayim* it doesn't do ביטול bitul *bitul* on
B
is because it's going like רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda* about
מין במינו min b'mino, *min bemino*. אלא פשיטא רבי יהודה ela pshita
rabi yehuda, *ela peshita Rabbi Yehuda*. So בשלמא bishlama, למאן דאמר בתר
בטיל אזלינן *bishlama leman de'amar batar batil azlinan* if you go by
the thing becoming בטל batel. *batel*. What's the thing that's at risk
to become פסול *pasul*? It is B. So in this AB overlap,
if you go, so if we assess it by B, so בשלמא
למאן דאמר בתר בטיל אזלינן *bishlama leman de'amar batar batil azlinan* בטל
batel. הוה כמבטל *batel hava kimevatel*. So B could become like A.
The B part could become שיריים shirayim *shirayim*. דכי קמץ מאידך *dechi
kamatz me'idach* when you take the קמיצה kemitza *kemitza* from B, so
הוו להו שיריים shirayim, *havu lehu shirayim*, then the B in the
AB overlap would be שיריים shirayim? *shirayim*. So therefore it's מין במינו
min b'mino *min bemino* that they're both מנחה *mincha* and it's מין
במינו min b'mino. *min bemino* in the sense that the B part
could be like the A part. That's if you, and therefore no
ביטול bitul *bitul*, and that's why the B remains כשר *kasher*. That's
how it works if you go like רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* according to the opinion that you go by the בטל batel
*batel* by the thing that is becoming בטל batel, *batel*. כי הני
*ki
hanei* just like the rest, so they become שיריים shirayim *shirayim* just
like A. אלא למאן דאמר בתר מבטל אזלינן ela leman damar batar
mevatel azlinan *ela leman de'amar batar mevatel azlinan* if you go like
רב חסדא Rav Chisda, *Rav Chisda* that says you go by the
מבטל mivatel, *mevatel* which would be the A, that's the one that's
endangering the כשרות kashrus *kashrus* of B. שיריים shirayim הכא הוי טבלא
*shirayim hacha havei tavla*. The שיריים shirayim. *shirayim* A can never become
like retroactively like the טבל tevel *tevel* of B like an untaken
מנחה *mincha*. So therefore they remain מין באינו מינו min b'eino mino,
*min be'eino mino* because A now as שיריים shirayim *shirayim* is different
from B and ביטול bitul *bitul* should now take effect. לימא דלא
כרבי חייא lima d'lo k'rabi chiya? *leima d'lo keRabbi Chiyya*? So this
seems to be a proof against רבי חייא Rabi Chiya, *Rabbi Chiyya*
that you go by בטל batel *batel*, you don't go by
מבטל mivatel? *mevatel*. התם כרבי זירא *hatam keRabbi Zeira*. There it goes
like רבי זירא Rabi Zeira. *Rabbi Zeira*. By the case of a
מנחה *mincha* and קמיצה kemitza *kemitza* and שיריים shirayim *shirayim*, there's a
special principle operative that says that ביטול bitul *bitul* doesn't take effect.
And this would make it work even according to the רבנן rabanan,
*Rabbanan*. דאמר רבי זירא Rabi Zeira *d'amar Rabbi Zeira* because רבי זירא
Rabi Zeira *Rabbi Zeira* said נאמר הקטר בקומץ ונאמר הקטר בשיריים *ne'emar
haktara bekometz vene'emar haktara beshirayim*. It says הקטרה *haktara* by the קומץ
kometz, *kometz*. Obviously the פסוק *pasuk* is you're מקטיר *maktir* the קומץ
*kometz*. And by the שיריים *shirayim*, it says,
we learn a קומץ *kometz* of an איסור *issur* where it says
כי כל שאור וכל דבש לא תקטירו ממנו אשה להשם *ki chol
se'or vechol devash lo taktiru mimenu isheh l'Hashem*. And from that we
learn don't offer up something on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach* לא תקטירו
*lo taktiru* that a part of it already went up on the
מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach* that went to the אשה *isheh*. So don't put
the שיריים *shirayim* on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. So it's using the verb
תקטירו *taktiru*. So since the same verb is used for both, one
for a חיוב *chiyuv* and one for an איסור *issur*, they're telling
you they're basically in the same category and no ביטול bitul *bitul*
occurs between them. Okay. So let's see how we learn it out.
מה הקטרה האמורה בקומץ אין קומץ מבטל mevatel את חבירו *ma haktara
ha'amura bekometz ein kometz mevatel et chaveiro*. The same way one קומץ
*kometz* is not מבטל mevatel, *mevatel* another קומץ *kometz*. They're all the
same thing, מין במינו min b'mino לא בטל batel, *min bemino lo
batel* certainly according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda.
*Rabbi Yehuda*. But even according to the רבנן rabanan *Rabbanan*, if it's
all the same thing, no ביטול bitul. *bitul* is taking place. אף
הקטרה האמורה בשיריים אין שיריים מבטלין את הקומץ *af haktara ha'amura beshirayim
ein shirayim mevatelin et hakometz*. So even with the שיריים *shirayim* and
the קומץ *kometz* or the שיריים *shirayim* here and the טבל tevel,
*tevel*, we're actually saying no ביטול bitul *bitul* is going to occur.
Alright, so we have a special פסוק *pasuk*, we have a teaching
of רבי זירא Rabi Zeira, *Rabbi Zeira* that ביטול bitul. *bitul* does
not occur between the components of a מנחה *mincha*, and that's why
there's no problem question from the משנה mishna *Mishna*. So now we're
going to try again, but of course the same answer is going
to be available to us. תא שמע ta shma *ta shema*
come and hear from the next case of the מנחה *mincha*. הקומץ
שנתערב במנחה שלא נקמצה *hakometz shenitarev bemincha shelo nikmetza*. Okay, you took
from the קומץ *kometz* of A and then you accidentally dropped it
into B, which was a מנחה *mincha* that had not had the
קומץ *kometz* taken from it. לא יקטיר lo yaktir, *lo yaktir*, don't
offer it up because then you'll be offering B on the מזבח
*mizbe'ach*, and B is not fit for the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. ואם הקטיר
זו שנקמצה עלתה לבעלים וזו שלא נקמצה לא עלתה לבעלים *ve'im hiktir
zo shenikmetza alta leva'alim vezo shelo nikmetza lo alta leva'alim*. And if
you did, then A is כשר *kasher* because the קמיצה kemitza *kemitza*
was taken and the קמיצה kemitza *kemitza* was offered up, and B
is not כשר *kasher* because the whole B was burned but there
was no קמיצה kemitza *kemitza* taken. ולא... so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says so what happens? You have your A which is קמיצה
kemitza *kemitza* being mixed into B. Okay. So those are different things.
It's not like the initial AB mix where it's all the same,
all the same, there's no ביטול *bitul* taking place. Here they're literally
here they're different things, a קומץ *kometz* and טבל tevel *tevel*, B,
an un-kamtzed מנחה *mincha*. So why isn't ביטול *bitul* going to take
effect here? And why won't the קומץ *kometz* even though it's the
minority here? Well let's take a look. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ולא קא מבטל ליה טבלא לקומץ
*velo ka mevatel leih tavla lekometz* right? So B, right, B is
not going to be כשר *kasher* at all as we said. But
B is now endangering A because basically the משנה mishna, *Mishna* says
if you offer the whole thing up, which you're not supposed to
do, at least A had the קמיצה kemitza *kemitza* offered up and
it's כשר *kasher*. So B is endangering
the... status and it would not work, offering it up would not
work. So why does that not happen? Why is ביטול not happening?
מאני, Mani, who's this going like? אי רבנן הא אמרי עולים הם
דלא מבטלי הדדי. ei rabanan ha amri olim hem d'lo mivatli hadadi.
If it's the Rabbis, the Rabbis say only things that are עולים
are מבטלי הדדי, but this isn't עולים, you know, the קמיצה kemitza
is עולים, but B is not הופרש, hofresh, that's not
עולים. Okay, so and so they would say, so all you have
is מין במינו, min bemino and מין במינו min bemino is בטל.
batel, So according to the רבנן, rabanan, this can't work. The קומץ
should be בטל. batel. אלא פשיטא רבי יהודה, it must be it's
going like רבי יהודה. בשלמא, and that's why it's not בטל batel,
because it's all מין במינו. min bemino But now you're saying they
also have to have similar status, it's not enough that they're all
physically the same. So בשלמא למאן דאמר בתר מבטל אזלינן, bishlama l'man
d'amar batar mivatel azlinan, if you go like רבי חייא, Rabi Chiya.
you go by the מבטל, what's the מבטל? B that's endangering the
כשרות of the קמיצה kemitza of A. So מבטל הוי כבטל, mivatel
havei k'batel, B is like A, could be like A. Why? דכל
פורצא חזי למיקמץ, d'chol purtza chazi l'mikmatz, any part of B could
be the קומץ, so B is enough in the same status category
as A, and it's מין במינו and no ביטול occurs. So that
works according to
רבי חייא. Rabi Chiya, ומיקמץ מיניה והוי ליה מין במינו ומין במינו
לא בטל. v'mikmatz minei v'havei lei min b'mino u'min b'mino lo batel.
אלא למאן דאמר בתר בטל אזלינן, ela l'man d'amar batar batel azlinan,
but according to רבי חנינא Rabi Chanina that you go by the
thing becoming בטל, batel and the thing becoming בטל here is the
קמיצה kemitza, of
A, so קומץ מי קהוי טבלא? kometz mi ka'havei tavla? So if
you go by the בטל, the thing becoming בטל, that's the קמיצה
kemitza of A, so the קמיצה kemitza of A can never be
like B, an untaken מנחה. So
therefore it's מין באינו מינו, min b'eino mino since the קמיצה kemitza
can never be like B, and therefore it should be בטל. לימא
דלא כרבי חייא? So this would prove against רבי חייא, Rabi Chiya.
meaning against רבי חנינא Rabi Chanina's reading of רבי חייא.
So the גמרא says, why isn't it מין באינו מינו min b'eino
mino, since A cannot become like B? The גמרא says no, הא
נמי כדרבי זירא, ha nami k'derabi zeira, that's also רבי זירא. We've
already said when it comes to the קמיצה and the שיריים and
even the טבל tevel. of the מנחה, although רבי זירא didn't say
the טבל, no ביטול is going to operate.
Okay,
so now one more question.
תא שמע נתערב קומצה בשיריה או בשיריה של חברתה. ta shma nitariv
kumtza b'shireha o b'shireha shel chavertah. A gets mixed up, the קמיצה
of A gets mixed up with the remainder of A, alright, or
with the remainder of B, but we'll just say the remainder of
A. לא יקטיר, don't offer it up because you can't offer up
the שיריים on the מזבח. ואם
הקטיר עלו לבעלים, v'im hiktir alu l'balim, but if you did offer
it up, at least you put the קמיצה on the מזבח, so
the מנחה is כשרה. kesheira. So here, the שיריים, why isn't there
going to be the שיריים? Why won't they do ביטול now that
they're different, the שיריים and the קמיצה, ביטול could take place? Why
won't it do ביטול to A and prevent that קמיצה from being
valid and therefore prevent the מנחה from being valid? והכא דלא הוי
מבטל כבטל, v'hacha d'lo havei mivatel k'batel, for
here
the שיריים can't be like the קמיצה and the קמיצה can't be
like the שיריים. So whichever direction you go, it's מין באינו מינו,
min b'eino mino. whether you go like רבי חנינא, Rabi Chanina, whether
you go like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda okay,
in this scenario neither could be like the other's status. So why
shouldn't ביטול work? ולא קא מבטלי שיריים לקומץ, v'lo ka mivatlei shirayim
l'kometz, and ביטול doesn't work. Okay, why not? מאני, mani, אי רבנן?
rabanan. So it can't be רבנן because anyway forget רבנן, they're only
about עולים. And if it's רבי יהודה, still either read of רבי
חנינא Rabi Chanina or רב חסדא Rav Chisda. this should be מין
באינו מינו. min be'eino mino So what's the answer? So here, הא
נמי כדרבי זירא, ha nami k'derabi zeira, this is where רבי זירא
said it. Before we were referencing רבי זירא, but here's where he
originally said it. This part of the משנה mishna that doesn't work
either for רבי חנינא Rabi Chanina
or for רב חסדא. So
אמר רבי זירא נאמר הקטרה בקומץ ונאמר הקטרה בשיריים מה הקטרה האמורה
בקומץ אין קומץ מבטל את חבירו אף הקטרה האמורה בשיריים אין שיריים
מבטלים את הקומץ, amar rabi zeira neemar haktara b'kometz v'neemar haktara b'shirayim
mah haktara ha'amura b'kometz ein kometz mivatel et chavero af haktara ha'amura
b'shirayim ein shirayim mivatlim et hakometz, and it makes sense that he
says it here, for here that's exactly what we're talking about, the
שיריים of A and the קומץ of A. So that's why he's
referencing שיריים and קומץ and not the טבל and the קומץ, but
clearly the גמרא is using his principle to apply even to the
טבל. Okay, so we tried to challenge this idea of the statuses
have to be the same for רבי יהודה based on our משנה,
and we basically said our משנה is about a מנחה, מנחה has
a special הלכה. halacha. And maybe that's true even for the רבנן.
Okay, so גמרא has one last question. תא שמע come in here.
טיבלה בקצח tibla beketsakh if you spiced up your מצה, matza, this
is now a question of just מצה matza for the סדר seder
night, with cumin, בשומשמין beshumshamin or sesame, ובכל מיני ubekol minei any
types of spices, כשרה kshera it's kosher to use as מצה, matza,
מצה היא matza hi it's still called מצה, matza, אלא שנקראת מצה
מתובלת ela shenikret matza metubelat but it's called spiced מצה. matza. Okay,
how's this relevant? כסלקא דעתך דאפישי לה תבלין טפי ממצה. kasalka daitakh
de'afishei lei tavlin tefei mimatza. We're assuming that at least in some
section of this מצה, matza, the spices overwhelm, are more like a
greater volume or greater quantity than the מצה. matza. Now that's crazy,
who would ever have a מצה matza like that? But okay, that's
what we're going to assume. Okay? So now why aren't the spices
מבטל the מצה? matza? בשלמא למאן דאמר בתר בטל אזלינן bishlama leman
damar batar batel azlinan if you go by the thing being בטל,
so אזלינן בטל הוה כמבטל azlinan batel hava kimevatel the מצה matza
which is at risk to become בטל can be like the spices.
How? דלכי מאחשא הוי ליה כתבלין delakhi me'akhsha havei lei ketavlin when
it spoils, it's like spices. What it means it's like spices, it
means it's no longer usable for the מצוה mitzva of מצה. matza.
So the מצה matza could be like the status of the תבלין
tavlin and not be usable for מצה matza and therefore it's מין
במינו and no ביטול. Okay, אלא למאן דאמר בתר מבטל אזלינן but
if you go by the מבטל, the spices,
so תבלין מי קא הוי מצה tavlin mi ka havei matza spices
can never become kosher מצה. matza. So therefore why isn't it מין
באינו מינו min be'eino mino, and why doesn't ביטול occur? So the
גמרא gives the obvious answer. הכא במאי עסקינן hakha bemai askinan what
do we talk about? דלא אפיש ליה תבלין delo afish lei tavlin
it's not a majority spices. No kidding. דרובא מצה היא deruba matza
hi the majority is מצה matza and that's why there's no ביטול.
דיקא נמי deka nami and this is also implied by the close
reading of the words דקתני מצה היא אלא שנקראת מצה מתובלת dekatani
matza hi ela shenikret matza metubelat because it says it's kosher because
it's מצה matza but it's spiced מצה, matza, which means that it
fundamentally is מצה. matza. שמע מינה shma mina that is a good
proof. The funny thing about this is that this is מין באינו
מינו, it's מצה matza with spices. Until now we've been assuming that
their debate of רבי חזקיה Rabbi Chizkiya and רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina,
I mean the way the גמרא has been framing the debate, is
an extra requirement within רבי יהודה. It's not enough that it be
מין במינו of the object, it also has to be מין במינו
to some degree of the status. Here we tried to say just
go by the status and ignore the physical aspect of the thing.
But that is presumably not at all what they were talking about
and anyway the גמרא completely rejected this proof, so we don't really
have a resolution between רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina and רבי חזקיה. Rabbi
Chizkiya. It's also not clear if we really use their position to
limit רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's stance. Okay, we will end with here
now.