And so we start we pick up at the משנה יא Mishna
Yud Aleph on דף ט Daf Tes and with God's help we
will actually finish the פרק Perek today. Let's see. Okay, so now
this משנה Mishna like what we've seen in מנחות Menachot has really
been like
very parallel to the first פרק Perek or two פרקים Perakim of
זבחים. Zvachim. We've gone through the issue of שלא לשמה, Shelo Lishmah,
we've done the issue of פסולים Psulin and had a whole long
discussion about left hand and so on. And actually what we had,
which I don't believe we had in זבחים, Zvachim, was even a
physical description of how the קמיצה Kemitzah was done and some problems
about having too much or too little and so on. I did
want to mention by the way before we start the משנה Mishna
that I described that the קמיצה Kemitzah is done like this, like
with your palm faced down, I think that's פשט Pshat of the
גמרא. Gemara. Rashi and the Rambam sounds like that too. But anyway
Rashi understands that the קמיצה Kemitzah is done sideways and you go
like this. That's how you understood? That's how I thought yesterday. But
it's harder to get it up to the top unless you bury
your hand in the... I think this is easier. Anyway, that's one
issue. The other issue is that we mentioned yesterday if you have
too much of the לבונה Levonah it's פסול. Pasul.
The גמרא Gemara talked about having two קמצים Kematzim of לבונה. Levonah.
One read of Rashi which I did not mention yesterday was if
it was less than two units, it was like a half unit
extra, a half meaning קומץ Kolmetz extra that would not be too
much. Too much is only when you get to the point of
double. Although תוספות Tosafot and Rashi...
No, no, this is about the לבונה Levonah not about the קמיצה.
Kemitzah. All right, yeah, sorry. Anyway, just bracket that. It was we
had a complicated or not
גמרא Gemara about that they only said too little לבונה Levonah didn't
say too much. So the גמרא Gemara said we talked about you
have two units of
לבונה Levonah and when did you take the קמיצה Kemitzah and so
on. So I just wanted to mention that Rashi in one לשון,
Lashon, he has two approaches to the גמרא, Gemara, says that anything
less than double actually by the לבונה Levonah wouldn't be a problem.
And it's interesting because the תורה Torah never says what the שיעור
Shiur of the לבונה Levonah is, right? It's just the גמרא Gemara
learns it out so maybe it's a little more flexibility. Okay, so
now that we've done the פסולים, Psulin, the way it's done, שלא
לשמה, Shelo Lishmah, we get of course to our old friend פיגול,
Pigul, which is what this משנה. Mishna. So let's take a look.
Okay, six lines, seven lines up from the bottom.
הקומץ את המנחה, Hakometz et HaMincha, you do קמיצה, Kemitzah, לאכול שייריה
בחוץ. le'echol she'areha bachutz. You plan on eating the שיירים sheyrayim outside
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because a מנחה Mincha is קודשי קדשים
Kodshei Kodashim and it can only be eaten by כהנים Kohanim in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So that's a מחשבה machshava of חוץ
למקומו. chutz limkomo. A מחשבה machshava of חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo invalidates
the קרבן Korban and if you but it and you're over on
a לאו lav but it does not make it פיגול. Pigul. The
result of making it פיגול Pigul is again the one who thinks
the פיגול Pigul is only over on a לאו, lav, but if
you eat פיגול Pigul then it's כרת kareit similar to if you
eat נותר. notar. So the thought has the same effect of doing
it. And פיגול Pigul is a thought of the wrong זמן. zman.
So this is a thought of the wrong place. או כזית משייריה
בחוץ, O k'zayit mishe'areha bachutz, you don't even have to plan on
eating all the שיירים sheyrayim outside even a כזית k'zayit is enough.
או להקטיר קומצה בחוץ, O lehaktir kometzah bachutz, you take the קומץ
kometz but you plan on burning it in your private altar in
your backyard. או כזית קומצה בחוץ O k'zayit kometzah bachutz or even
a כזית k'zayit worth, enough to be considered an act of eating
or an act of
הקטרה. haktara. או להקטיר לבונתה בחוץ O lehaktir levonatah bachutz or you
plan on offering up the לבונה Levonah outside. Now, it does not
say the word כזית. k'zayit. Why not? Because they don't have a
כזית k'zayit of course? Well you have a קומץ kometz though of
the לבונה, Levonah, but as Michael correctly says according to everybody other
than רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir of the previous משנה, Mishna, of the
סתם stam previous משנה, Mishna, it's enough to be לבונה Levonah if
you do even one or two like rocks or whatever they're called.
Of course, קורט? kurt? Yes, so right well that's what the Hebrew.
It's actually funny though because the גמרא Gemara understood that the סתם
stam משנה Mishna before was assuming you needed at least a קומץ
kometz of all of the לבונה Levonah and here you have another
סתם stam משנה Mishna and there's no שיעור, shiur, so even the
smallest amount, which works with רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, but the סתם stam is shifting. Okay, but it does not
say the כזית k'zayit by the קטורת ketoret
לבונה levonah of the לבונה, levonah, excuse me. או להקטיר לבונתה למחר.
O lehaktir levonatah lemachar. So in those cases where your plan is
to do it לבונתה בחוץ, levonatah bachutz, outside, excuse me, פסול ואין
בו כרת. pasul ve'ein bo kareit. The קרבן Korban is פסול, pasul,
stay's lak כרת, kareit, it's not going to help you Jed because
there's no פיגול pigul afterwards. All right, anyway, sorry. So in all
those cases it's about the wrong place and therefore it's פסול pasul
but there is no כרת kareit because it's not פיגול. pigul. Now
if you did the exact same thing about the wrong time: פסול
ויש בו כרת. pasul veyesh bo kareit. לאכול שייריה למחר, Le'echol she'areha
lemachar, you plan on eating the remnants tomorrow, right? Because a מנחה
Mincha has to be eaten on that day, like קודשי קדשים. Kodshei
Kodashim. או כזית משייריה למחר, O k'zayit mishe'areha lemachar, or even a
כזית k'zayit the next day. להקטיר קומצה למחר, Lehaktir kometzah lemachar, you're
going to offer up a קומץ, kometz, the entire קומץ kometz tomorrow,
even in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. או כזית מקומצה למחר, O
k'zayit mikometzah lemachar, or even just one כזית k'zayit worth. או להקטיר
לבונתה למחר, O lehaktir levonatah lemachar, or you're going to offer up
the לבונה Levonah tomorrow. Again even the smallest amount.
פיגול, Pigul, this is פיגול pigul because it's all about the wrong
time, וחייבין עליו כרת, vechayavin alav kareit, anybody the thought. The thought
is not
מחייב mechayev כרת kareis. *mechayev kareis*, the thought is a לאו *lav*,
but eating it
is חייב hayav כרת kareis *chayav kareis* the same way eating נותר
nosar *nosar* is חייב chayav כרת kareis. *chayav kareis*. זה הכלל zeh
haklal. *Ze ha'klal*, this is the principle. And now this is all
about the act of קמיצה Kmitza *kmitza* you had that thought, but
the same way we learned by the animal קרבנות korbanot, *korbanos* that
you are you can make something פיגול Pigul *pigul* by any of
the four עבודות Avodot, *avodos* of the blood, not things that are
not related to make the קרבן korban, *korban* valid, but anything from
the שחיטה *shchita* onwards. Here too, it's anything from the קמיצה Kmitza.
*kmitza* until you actually offer up the
קומץ Kometz, *komets*. I didn't mean קטורת ketores *ktoret*, thank you. The
קומץ Kometz. *komets*, it's a combination of קומץ Kometz *komets* and לבונה
levona *levona*. I get to the קטורת ketores *ktoret*. Anyway, until you
offer up the קומץ Kometz *komets*
and the קרבן korban *korban* becomes valid. So let's take a look.
So we're going to list all the עבודות Avodot, *avodos*. But that's
interesting. Wait, you said until you offer up the what about the
לבונה levonah *levona*? We will discuss that. That's a מחלוקת *machlokes* here.
Yeah. What about like the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim. *lechem hapanim*? So
you have like a whole week to make it פיגול Pigul *pigul*?
No, it's only from the moment of קמיצה Kmitza. *kmitza*. The קמיצה
Kmitza *kmitza* of the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim. *lechem hapanim* is the
removing of the בזיכין *bazichin* from the table. Right, but it's baked
a week before. Yeah, and it's on the table for it's with
the בזיכין *bazichin*. Right, so you can have פיגול Pigul *pigul* all
whole week? No. No, it's only during the acts of the עבודה
*avoda*. From the the act right, it's if I said that I
probably I think I said it, you know, somewhat imprecisely before. Right,
it's not like a time span. It's all the עבודות Avodot *avodos*
during any of the עבודות Avodot, *avodos* that take place from the
עבודה *avoda* of קמיצה Kmitza *kmitza* to the עבודה *avoda* of הקטרה
haktarah, *haktara*. Okay, so therefore it's the what we're about to read.
All right, so therefore by the לחם lechem. הפנים *lechem hapanim* it's
only the עבודה *avoda* of removing it and then the other stages.
So what are those four עבודות Avodot, *avodos*? Let's take a look.
הקומץ *Ha'komets*, the act of קמיצה Kmitza *kmitza* which is parallel to
שחיטה *shchita*. או O נותן בכלי *O nosein bakeli*, or you put
it in the vessel, which parallels the קבלת הדם *kabalas hadam*. המוליך
*Hamolich*, you bring it to the מזבח *mizbeach* which parallels הולכה Holacha
*holacha*.
Yeah, Jeff, I'm sorry, there is no I didn't upload the PDF,
you'll get it tomorrow. Can you hear me? Jed, not Jeff, Yed.
Anyway, I don't know okay, או O *o*, back to this, sorry.
או O נותן בכלי המוליך המקטיר לאכול lechol דבר שדרכו לאכול *o
nosein bakeli hamolich hamaktir leechol davar shedarko leechol* or המקטיר *hamaktir*, you
burn it up. So in all these cases, לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול
ולהקטיר דבר שדרכו להקטיר lehaktir *leechol davar shedarko leechol u'lehaktir davar shedarko
lehaktir*, if you do this on something that is normally you plan
on eating what's normally eaten, meaning you're planning on eating the שירים
shirayim, *shirayim* the next day, not on eating the קומץ kometz. *komets*
the next day because the קומץ kometz. *komets* although it's made of
the same material, it physically can be eaten, halachically it's not supposed
to be eaten. So a thought to eat the קומץ komets. *komets*
the next day is irrelevant. That's לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול *leechol davar
shedarko leechol*. להקטיר דבר שדרכו להקטיר *lehaktir davar shedarko lehaktir* is you
plan on burning the קומץ komets. *komets* on the wrong day,
but that's something that normally burns. But if you plan on burning
the שירים shirayim *shirayim* the wrong day, that's an irrelevant thought. So
if you have the right thought for the right object, but for
the wrong time, דבר שדרכו להקטיר חוץ למקומו Chutz Limkomo. *davar shedarko
lehaktir chutz limkomo*, if it's about doing it in the wrong place,
פסול ואין בו כרת pasul ve'ein bo kareis. *pasul v'ein bo kareis*,
it's invalid there is no כרת *kareis*. חוץ לזמנו Chutz L'zmano *Chutz
l'zmano*, if it's a thought for doing it at the wrong time,
פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת piggul vechayavin alav kareis, *pigul v'chayavin alav kareis*,
you get כרת *kareis* if you eat it. And however, one other
criteria. ובלבד שיקריב המתיר כמצוותו *u'vilvad sheyakriv hamatir k'mitzvato*. The rest of
the process to make it permissible has to be done correctly. Meaning,
the general rule is you have to bring this קרבן korban *korban*
that it would've totally been a כשר kasher. *kosher* קרבן korban, *korban*
were it not for the פיגול Pigul *pigul* thought. And if any
of the things made it invalid otherwise,
let's say you never were מקטיר maktir, *maktir* the קומץ komets. *komets*,
or a זר *zar* did the הקטרה haktara *haktara* of the קומץ
komets? *komets*. You know, so it never would've been כשר *kosher* otherwise.
Or זבחים Zvachim *zvachim* case.
Right, exactly. Then it is not פיגול Pigul *pigul*. And the other
case, which is even more surprising, which the משנה Mishna. *mishna* says
explicitly is, even if the כהן *kohein* finished it all and did
it all and he was a כשר *kosher* כהן *kohein* and he
burned it, if he had another invalidating thought, since the פיגול Pigul
*pigul*, the חוץ לזמנו Chutz L'zmano *chutz l'zmano* thought is not sufficient
to invalidate it, therefore,
excuse me, it is sufficient, it's not necessary to invalidate it, it
would've been invalidated otherwise. So in that type of a case it
is not פיגול Pigul *pigul*. פיגול Pigul *pigul* has to be the
necessary thought to invalidate and without the פיגול Pigul *pigul* it would've
been כשר *kosher*. Okay, so let's take a look. כיצד *Keitzad*, what
is the example of not that the that it was not הקטיר
המתיר כמצוותו *hiktir hamatir k'mitzvato*? כיצד קרב המתיר כמצוותו *Keitzad karav hamatir
k'mitzvato*,
what is the example when it was done correctly? The thing that's
מתיר Mattir *matir* the קרבן korban *korban* that makes the קרבן korban?
*korban* permissible, meaning the קומץ komets. *komets* was brought up correctly. קמץ
בשתיקה *Kamat b'shtika*, you took the קמיצה Kmitza *kmitza* in silence. Again,
the word here שתיקה *shtika* in contrast to what you're thinking is
one of the indications that the when we talk about thinking we
mean articulated. Although look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, so he says שלא
חישב *shelo chishev*. I know, I know, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* already
earlier in the מסכת *maseches* has told us that anything about thought,
I don't know, it's a good point. Okay, קמץ בשתיקה *kamat b'shtika*,
so you did it in silence, meaning with no
problematic. thought, נתן בכלי והוליך והקטיר חוץ לזמנו. Natan B'kli V'holich V'hiktir
Chutz L'zmano, Now this ו Vav here means or. So okay, let's
say you did the קמיצה Kmitza okay, until now we've been focusing
that you had your wrong thoughts during the קמיצה. kmitzah So first
thing we want to do is tell you it's not all about
the קמיצה. kmitzah. קמיצה kmitzah was fine, but you did one of
the three other עבודות, avodos the placing in the כלי, Kli, the
הולכה Holacha or the burning of the קומץ, komets. חוץ לזמנו Chutz
L'zmano, with a thought of the wrong of the wrong time. Oh,
שקמץ חוץ לזמנו She-kamat Chutz L'zmano or the קמיצה kmitza thought was
done with the thought of the wrong time, the קמיצה kmitza act
was done with the thought of the wrong time. And נתן בכלי
והוליך והקטיר בשתיקה, Natan B'kli V'holich V'hiktir B'shtika, and then the remainder
of all the acts were done in silence. So obviously those are
simple cases, you had one חוץ לזמנו thought, one פיגול Pigul thought,
and everything else was done in silence or correctly. That's obviously going
to be okay. או O or שקמץ ונתן בכלי והוליך והקטיר חוץ
לזמנו, She-kamat V'natan B'kli V'holich V'hiktir Chutz L'zmano, you were thinking of
פיגול Pigul throughout every single of the four עבודות, זהו שקרב המתיר
כמצותו. Zehu She-karav Hamattir K'mitzvato. Then the מתיר Mattir, was offered up
correctly, meaning the חידוש Chidush of this, not much of a חידוש
Chidush but the חידוש Chidush of this is, we don't say that
since I had four פיגול Pigul thoughts, not any one of the
פיגול Pigul, thoughts itself was necessary, because it would have been פסול
Passul by the other פיגול Pigul. thought, but obviously that's not a
problem. What the point is, if you bracket the פיגול Pigul problem,
it would have been okay. So if you had one פיגול Pigul,
thought or you had consistent פיגול Pigul thought, you've made it פיגול
Pigul as long as you bring up the קומץ. komets, That's that
is קרב המתיר כמצותו. Karev Hamattir K'mitzvato. Now, what if you got
mixed up with this other wrong thoughts, like חוץ למקומו. Chutz Limkomo,
קמץ חוץ למקומו, Kamat Chutz Limkomo, I'm sorry, thank you, כיצד לא
קרב המתיר כמצותו? Keitzad Lo Karev Hamattir K'mitzvato? What would be an
example about not offering up the מתיר, Mattir the קומץ komets. correctly?
קמץ חוץ למקומו, Kamat Chutz Limkomo, when you did the קמיצה kemitza
you had a thought about the wrong place, another different type of
invalidating thought. And then נתן בכלי והוליך והקטיר חוץ לזמנו, Natan B'kli
V'holich V'hiktir Chutz L'zmano, you did all of the three or any
of the three remaining עבודות with a פיגול Pigul, thought. או O
or even if you started off with your פיגול piggul thought, שקמץ
חוץ לזמנו, She-kamat Chutz L'zmano, you did the קמיצה kemitza with the
wrong place thought, you started with your פיגול piggul thought, נתן בכלי
והוליך והקטיר חוץ למקומו, Natan B'kli V'holich V'hiktir Chutz Limkomo, and then
in any of the this could be read as any, any of
the remaining acts, you had a different invalidating thought, the wrong
place, או שקמץ ונתן בכלי והוליך והקטיר חוץ למקומו, She-kamat V'natan B'kli
V'holich V'hiktir Chutz Limkomo, or you had that thought throughout all four,
I don't know why you even have to say that, or maybe
terror- terrorism. Right, right. Anyway, in all those cases where you also
had a thought of חוץ למקומו, Chutz Limkomo. in any of those
cases, זהו שלא קרב המתיר כמצותו. Zehu She-lo Karev Hamattir K'mitzvato. That
is that the remnant was not done, the מתיר matir was not
done correctly, meaning there was another problem other than פיגול, piggul and
therefore it is invalid.
It is invalid but it is not פיגול. piggul פיגול piggul only
works if it is the only problem. Okay, so, let me just
check רש"י Rashi because I think he adds one thing here.
No. Okay, fine. All right. So that's so any other invalidating thing.
Now we're going to give one other thing to remind us of
the first
משנה. Mishna. One minute. Okay, זהו שלא קרב המתיר כמצותו. Zehu She-lo
Karev Hamattir K'mitzvato. לאכול כזית בחוץ כזית למחר. L'echol K'zayit Bachutz K'zayit
L'machar. Let's say you had, did I skip a line again? מנחת
חוטא. Minchat Chotei. Thank you, I knew I skipped a line. Right,
מנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות. Minchat Chotei U'minchat K'naot. That's where we're going
back to the first משנה. Mishna Here's another invalidating thought. Until now
we've been discussing two invalidating thoughts: חוץ לזמנו, which is פיגול, piggul
and חוץ למקומו. Chutz Limkomo, But the first משנה mishnah. told us
of another invalidating thought: שלא לשמה Shelo Lishma by a מנחת חוטא
ומנחת קנאות. Minchat Chotei U'minchat K'naot. So we don't want to forget
that, so we're going to use that as an example.
מנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות, Minchat Chotei U'minchat K'naot, if you have a
מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei or the מנחה Mincha of a סוטה, Sota,
שקמץ שלא לשמה She-kamat Shelo Lishma and you did it שלא לשמה
Shelo Lishma which is an invalidating thought, נתן בכלי והוליך והקטיר חוץ
לזמנו, even if you had another a פיגול piggul thought in the
remaining עבודות, או שקמץ חוץ לזמנו She-kamat Chutz L'zmano
or you started with a פיגול piggul thought, נתן בכלי והוליך והקטיר
שלא לשמה, Natan B'kli V'holich V'hiktir Shelo Lishma, but you had your
שלא לשמה Shelo Lishma invalidating thought in one of the other three
עבודות, או שקמץ ונתן בכלי והוליך והקטיר שלא לשמה, She-kamat V'natan B'kli
V'holich V'hiktir Shelo Lishma,
or you had it throughout all four, in any of those cases,
that's just like the other like the חוץ למקומו, זהו שלא קרב
המתיר כמצותו. Zehu She-lo Karav Hamattir K'mitzvato. That would be another example
of that the remainder was not done correctly, not the remainder, I
keep on saying that, that the קומץ komets, was not done correctly,
other than the פיגול, piggul. there was some other problem, and here
the problem was שלא לשמה. Shelo Lishma. Okay, so,
now we are going to talk about compound thoughts. I have a
question. Remember we had that opinion was, who was it, רבי שמעון
Rabi Shimon that says you don't הולכה holacha, doesn't even necessary. Right.
So would what why does why does he not repeat his position
here? That's a good question. I don't know.
It's a good question. Would would he repeat his position here? We
see him repeating this whole thing anyway. Right, right. Yeah, no, it's
it's a good question.
What was it anyway? I'm trying to look. I think it was
רבי שמעון, Rabi Shimon, right?
No, רבי אלעזר. Rabi Elazar. There was all these debates on י"ג
עמוד א' Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph in זבחים Zvachim, about הילוך. Hiluch.
רבי שמעון, Rabi Shimon, you're right, no I'm sorry, רבי שמעון Rabi
Shimon and רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar were different. Very good, Michael.
It depends if you had the thought when you were walking in
a straight line or not a straight line, I guess. Yes, it's
a very good point. You know, presumably to have their same positions,
it could be that the assumption is we don't פוסקין pasken like
them and therefore, you know, they were recorded there, you know, for
the sake of recording them, but since they're they're not פסק psak
we didn't bother repeating it here. But it is a question why
that was not repeated. Okay, so now let's finish the משנה. mishnah,
Okay, לאכול כזית בחוץ כזית למחר. lechol kezayis bachutz kezayis lemachar. Now
let's say you had a compound thought. You were planning during one
act. Before we were talking about two acts, one act you were
thinking of doing this thing wrong, the other act another thing wrong.
Let's say during one act you were thinking about two different parts
of two different כזיתים kezaysim of the מנחה. mincha. So during the
קמיצה kemitza, I was planning on eating one כזית kezayis tomorrow, לאכול
כחצי זית בחוץ כחצי זית למחר, lechol kichazayis bachutz kichazayis lemachar, one
כזית kezayis out of the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, one כזית kezayis
tomorrow. Or the reverse order. First I was thinking about כזית בחוץ
kezayis bachutz and then did I skip a line? I keep on
skipping. Okay, I'm sorry. לאכול—I'm going to start again. Yes. לאכול כזית
בחוץ כזית למחר. lechol kezayis bachutz kezayis lemachar. I planned on eating
one כזית kezayis outside, one כזית kezayis tomorrow. Or כזית למחר כזית
בחוץ kezayis lemachar kezayis bachutz in the reverse order. First I planned
on eating one כזית kezayis tomorrow, again the פיגול Piggul thought came
first, and then one כזית kezayis outside the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash.
So it's a compound thought. כחצי זית בחוץ כחצי זית למחר. kechatzayis
bachutz kechatzayis lemachar. That's more obvious. Half a כזית kezayis outside, half
a כזית kezayis tomorrow. That's more obvious not going to be a
problem because I don't even have a full פיגול piggul, thought, it's
not on a full כזית. kezayis. Or the reverse, כחצי זית למחר
כחצי זית בחוץ. kechatzayis lemachar kechatzayis bachutz. First I plan half a
זית zayis tomorrow, half a זית zayis outside. In all those cases
פסול ואין בו כרת. pasul ve'ein bo kareis. It's invalid and no
כרת. Now the second cases, half and half are obvious why not.
I don't have a full פיגול piggul thought on a כזית. kezayis.
But the first case is presumably rely on the principle of לא
קרב המתיר כמצותו, lo karaf hamattir kmitzaso, meaning even though it's not
like on separate acts and validated, the very same act, but at
the end of the day פיגול piggul. was not necessary to invalidate
this קרבן, korban you got another thought that invalidated it. אמר רבי
יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, זה הכלל. Zeh haklal, This is the principle.
And here Michael you should be an expert, here we do at
least have a, you know, one of these sort of more דעת
יחיד das yachid opinions at least by this part. So your question
is good. זה הכלל, this is the principle. אם מחשבת הזמן קדמה
למחשבת המקום. Im machshavas hazman kadma lemachshavas hamakom. This is not the
principle of the previous משנה, mishnah this is his principle, he disagrees
with the משנה mishnah we just said. אם מחשבת הזמן קדמה למחשבת
המקום, Im machshavas hazman kadma lemachshavas hamakom, it depends what invalidated it
first. If your פיגול piggul thought invalidated it first before your thought
of the of the wrong place,
פיגול וחייב עליו כרת. piggul vechayav alav kareis. It's defined as פיגול
piggul? and you get כרת if you were to eat it. אם
מחשבת המקום קדמה למחשבת הזמן, Im machshavas hamakom kadma lemachshavas hazman, if
your thought of the wrong place came first, so then it already
defined it as invalid before your פיגול piggul thought, פסול pasul, ואין
בו כרת. It's invalid and there is no כרת. But just so
you should have no questions about, you know, we don't want to
end with his opinion cause we don't rule like it, so וחכמים
אומרים vachachamim omrim not true, זה וזה פסול ואין בו כרת. zeh
vazeh pasul ve'ein bo kareis. Even if your פיגול piggul thought came
first, so maybe you would think that label sticks, no, it's got
another thing that invalidated it, then it's then it's not פיגול. piggul
פיגול piggul? is only if it could do it all by itself.
Okay, געזונטהייט gezuntheit again. Fascinating things by פיגול, piggul we have yet
to come up with a good philosophy theology about what it's all
about but פיגול piggul is one of those things that have these
very precise requirements in order for it to get this status of
פיגול. piggul
Okay and now interestingly the whole remainder of the גמרא Gemara pretty
much
ignores all until the next משנה mishna. ignores the central פיגול piggul
issue here and discusses on the theme of before of what happens
if the שיריים, shirayim, some of the שיריים shirayim got lost after
the קמיצה. kemitza Let's take a look. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. They
raised the following question. ודברי האומר שיריים שחסרו בין קמיצה להקטרה מקטיר
קומץ עליהן. Udivei ha'omer shirayim shechasru bein kmitzah lehaktarah maktir kometz aleihen.
According to the opinion which was רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that we
pretty clearly ruled like that says that if you lost the שיריים
shirayim or some of them, some of the שיריים shirayim got lost
between after the קמיצה kemitza. before the
הקטרה, haktara. you could still burn the קטרת. ktares. You could still
I said the קטרת ktares again because of the word of מקטיר,
maktir that's why I'm saying it. You could still be מקטיר maktir
the קומץ. komets, Okay remember that if there was no שיריים shirayim
left then it was like the debate about can you do זריקת
הדם zrikas hadam when there's no בשר basar and no חלב cheilev
left. But if there is some שיריים shirayim left רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says fine, then go ahead and still do the burning of
the קומץ. komets. It's just like if there's some בשר basar left.
Okay but he he added another point of qualification of course, וקיימא
לן vekayma lan but we also established earlier דאותן שיריים אסורים באכילה.
de'osin shirayim assurim beachilah. Unlike the case of a animal קרבן korban,
when you do זריקת הדם zrikas hadam and some of the meat
isn't there, where okay you eat the rest of the meat or
some of the חלב cheilev isn't there, you burn the rest of
the חלב. cheilev. Here if you don't have all the שיריים shirayim
there you can't eat it. Okay and that was based on a
פסוק. pasuk. So now we have the question. What would be, how
would this play into the issues of פיגול? piggul. מהו דתהני להו
הקטרה למיקבעינהו בפיגול. mahu detehani lehu haktara lemikve'inhu bepiggul.
So now I went ahead, I took my קומץ. komets Some of
the remainder got lost. Okay, now I'm going da-da-da-da-da-da and I burn
my קומץ. komets. And I'm allowed to burn my קומץ. komets? Is
that קומץ? komets, I keep on saying that קומץ. komets. Thank you,
because the word הקטרה haktara, is sticking in my head. Okay, so
I go ahead and I burn my קומץ. komets. Now, I'm allowed
to, right? There, even though some of the שיריים shirayim are lost,
I'm allowed to. And I'm having a פיגול piggul thought on the
שיריים? shirayim? Yeah, exactly. And I'm having a פיגול piggul thought on
the שיריים shirayim which you can't eat anyway? Exactly. And I'm having
a פיגול piggul thought on the שיריים shirayim which I'm אסור asur
to eat anyway. So is that כהרי המתר כמצותו? kaharei hamatir kemitzvato?
Well, yes, because I'm allowed to do that and I'm supposed to
do that. However, it's a מתיר matir which isn't really מתיר the
stuff to be eaten. So since the stuff can't be eaten anyway,
it's a little bit like that whole, you know, the gap in
the משנה. mishna The משנה Mishna, talks about what happens if it
becomes פסול, pasul. the entire קרבן korban becomes פסול. pasul? And if
I had, for example, a שלא לשמו shelo lishmo thought or some
of these other things, I'm not supposed to be מקריב makriv the
קומץ, komets. I'm not supposed to burn the קומץ. komets Here, I'm
allowed to burn the קומץ, komets, I'm supposed to burn the קומץ,
komets but I can't eat the remnant. Okay, does that get it
out of פיגול? pigul What? Because they're lost, you can't eat it.
Because no, some is lost, some remains. Right, so it's חסר, chaser,
meaning some is lacking but the rest is there. פיגול pigul. thought
on what's left? You have the פיגול pigul, thought on what's left,
exactly. But based on a פסוק, pasuk, you're not allowed to eat
what's left. But you are allowed to be מקריב makriv the הקטרה.
haktara. Now, the הקטרה, haktara I keep on doing, the קומץ. kometz,
Now, there would seem to be an obvious parallel to this. There
are times when I can be מקריב makriv the קומץ kometz. or
the דם dam and I can't eat what's left. Let's say it
became טמא, tamei, right? Let's say it went out of the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. But not the דם, dam, just the meat. Okay,
or just the remainder. I can't eat it. Is there going to
be פיגול pigul or not? So we are going to talk about
that. Part of the question can also be, not just is there
פיגול pigul when I can't eat the remainder, but part of the
question might be: how do I understand the idea of not eating
the rest? And this goes back to one of the general themes
we're always asking. Is it a problem about me personally, like a
מצוה mitzvah not to eat it, or is it that the rest
is considered פסול? pasul, Right? Normally, we think that what happens if
I can't eat it, somehow the object became invalid. It became טמא.
tamei. It went out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So if
the object, you know, in terms of the object itself can't be
eaten, it's harder to imagine why we would be discussing פיגול. pigul
You know, because I'm planning on eating something which fundamentally can't be
eaten. If, however, the object is not פסול, pasul. somehow there's some
restriction on me to eat it, but we're not saying that the
object became invalid in some way, maybe we can more say that
in principle, you know, I'm planning on eating something that as far
as the object's definition is not invalid even if in practice I
can't eat it. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with
it. Wait just one second. Cause you said this is only if
some of it was so if all of it was gone, then
even according to ר' יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan you'd just go home and
bring some more, right? If all no, that was when, that was
when it was lacking before you took the קומץ. kometz Oh. So
let's say, let's say it was all gone. Then what? After the
קומץ? kometz Yeah. Then according to the opinion that you can't be
זורק הדם zorek hadam when all the meat is gone, then you
can't be מקריב makriv the הקטרה. haktara The קומץ, kometz. yeah. No,
I mean, the קומץ. komets, Yeah.
Why today? I don't know. Must be a hangover from פורים Purim
or something. What? ונהפוך הוא. V'nahafoch hu. So anyway, so
according to the one that says that when you're זורק הדם, zorek
hadam, if all the meat is lost, you can't be זורק הדם
zorek hadam by a קרבן, korban all the meat and the חלב.
chelev. So then here, if all of the שיריים shirayim were lost,
you could not be מקריב makriv the קומץ. komets So then the
question wouldn't even get off the ground because you can't exactly. Exactly.
We want a case where you're מקריב makriv the קומץ. komets And
let's say you held like the opinion that you can be מקריב
makriv the קומץ komets, but there's no שיריים. shirayim. Also the question
wouldn't get off the ground because what are you planning on doing
with the שיריים? shirayim? Now, you could still have פיגול pigul because
you could plan on when I'm doing, let's say, the הולכה, I
could plan on doing the הקטרה haktara tomorrow. So you could have
פיגול pigul on the קומץ, komets but it's not an interesting question.
We want to have the question relating to the שיריים shirayim which
now can't be eaten. Okay? So therefore, so we want to say
that the שיריים shirayim are there, they are physically there, they're not
all there, they're not allowed to be eaten, can you have a
פיגול pigul thought on the שיריים? shirayim? Okay, so that's the question.
What do you do with the remainder? If you can't eat it,
you would burn it in the מקדש, Mikdash, yeah, like any פסולי
המקדש psulei hamikdash that you burn. In a pile on the side?
Yeah, exactly. And you burn it at a specific time?
No, but you might have to wait until it becomes, until the
next day, because it becomes obviously פסול. pasul. What's called, you know,
תעובר צורתן, te'aver tzuratan, especially something like this, which part of the
question we might be asking is whether they are
בחפצא becheftza פסול. pasul, תעובר צורתן te'aver tzuratan does it actually mean
that it like looks physically different, like starts to rot? No, it
just means you waited till the next day. Okay? All right. So
although the language suggests more. Okay, so let's take a look, you
know. Right. Okay, so let's take a look. So מהו דתהני להו
הקטרה, mahu detehani lehu haktara, can the offering up of the קומץ
komets have an effect on it, right? תהני tehani normally means help,
but here it means have an effect on it. למיקבעינהו בפיגול, lemikve'inhu
bepiggul, to make it... to people. So now if you eat it
you'll be חייב chayav for פיגול pigul if that was your thought
when you were burning the קומץ, komets ולאפקוניהו
מידי מעילה u'le'apkunhu midei me'ilah and to say there's no more מעילה.
me'ilah. What does that mean? Because any קרבן korban that's קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim means all given to God. So
you can transgress מעילה me'ilah when you benefit from it from the
moment it's sanctified. Until when? Until when, when would you no longer
get מעילה? me'ilah? As soon as it goes a little bit away
from being fully God's. As soon as it becomes מותר לכהנים mutar
l'kohanim or מותר לישראל mutar l'yisrael in a case where like a
שלמים shlamim is not because a שלמים shlamim you wouldn't get מעילה
me'ilah from the beginning. Okay. So normally after זריקת הדם zrikat hadam
of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim or הקטרת הקומץ, haktarat hakometz, the remainder
becomes מותר mutar for the כהנים. kohanim. So there's no more מעילה.
me'ilah. Here, you did the הקטרת הקומץ, haktarat hakometz, but it's not
exactly מותר mutar because you're not allowed to eat the remainder. So
but is it מותר mutar enough, meaning from the perspective of the
קדושה, kedusha, it's מותר, mutar, it's just this other problem. Is that
enough to get it out of the מעילה me'ilah category? So one
way of understanding this is a local question by מעילה, me'ilah, what
are its parameters? A local question by פיגול. pigul But because these
are two different areas of הלכה halacha and therefore logically they could
have had different parameters. You could have said, you know, yes to
one and no to the other, right? Because of, you know, do
you need the thing to be מותר באכילה? mutar ba'achila? And the
גמרא gemara is asking it together. It seems to me the question
is less about the parameters of those separate cases, but about the
nature of not being allowed to eat the שירים, shirayim right? Because
it's a bizarre הלכה. halacha. We've never had it before. You need
all of the שירים shirayim. present in order to be able to
eat any of them? Until now the הלכה's halacha always been some
meat becomes פסול, pasul. you eat the rest. Some meat is יוצא
yotzei is טמא, tamei, it doesn't affect the rest. So here we
might not be saying that the remainder of the מנחה mincha is
פסול. pasul. We might be saying that it's, you know, again, like
as an object it's totally כשר. Just there's some הלכה halacha that
I'm not allowed to eat some of the שירים if I'm not,
you know, able to eat all of them or something along those
lines. So it seems like we might be asking more of a
question of the nature of the prohibition or the status of not
being able to eat the remnant of the שירים. Remember for example
one of the דרשות drashos was
והנותרת מן המנחה, v'hanoteret min hamincha, ולא הנותרת מן הנותרת. v'lo hanoteret
min hanoteret. The leftovers, not the leftover of the leftover. But read
that way, it's just a restriction. The פסוק pasuk is והנותרת מן
המנחה יאכלו אהרן ובניו. v'hanoteret min hamincha yochlu aharon u'vanav. It's just
a restriction on under what circumstances are you allowed to eat it,
right? It's not somehow saying that it became פסול. pasul, So that's
how I would sort of understand the question. This thing which is
not פסול, pasul. you're just not allowed to eat it, maybe you
can still have פיגול, pigul, maybe you can still get out of
מעילה. me'ilah. Let's see what the answer is. What? I would think
the, you know, it has to be something that your פיגול pigul
would have an effect on. Right, but maybe it does have an
effect. It's again, you know, this is the halachic way of thinking
about it. Just because saying not eating it, you can say it's—are
you prohibited or is there something that changes the status of the
object? So פיגול pigul would still change the status of the object,
even though you'd already be prohibited or not allowed to eat it.
Okay, so let's read. I vote no. You vote no. Okay, good
to know. All right, so the גמרא gemara says like this. I
love the fact that whenever the גמרא gemara raises a question, you
like—you gotta say like, you know, your answer before you—you know, all
right. So anyway,
let's take a look. Where are we? Okay, אמר רב הונא אפילו
לרבי עקיבא דאמר זריקה מועלת ליוצא. amar rav huna afilu l'rabbi akiva
d'amar zrika mo'elet l'yotzei. So believe it or not, there's a parallel
debate by something by קרבנות, korbanos although something that's more clearly an
invalidity. Let's say the meat was taken out of the בית המקדש
beit hamikdash and now you were זורק את הדם. zorek et hadam.
So the meat is פסול. pasul, So can I have a פיגול
pigul? thought on the meat?
Same question. Will the meat no longer be מעילה? me'ilah? Okay, since
it was פסול, pasul it never became permitted to the כהנים. kohanim.
So רבי עקיבא rabbi akiva said yes, that even if the meat
is taken out of the בית המקדש, beit hamikdash, that's not enough
of a problem and you can still make it פיגול piggul, and
it will still stop being מעילה me'ilah in a—in a different case.
מועלת ליוצא, mo'elet l'yotzei, again, works—works to make a problem. הני מילי
יוצא דאיתא בעיניה ופסול מחמת דבר אחר. hanei milei yotzei d'ita b'einya
u'pasul machmat davar acher. That would be when it was—when it was
taken out where number one, it's all present and the problem is
some external thing, that it's not in the right place. So there
we could say it's not a hundred percent פסול—I pasul, mean, it's
פסול, pasul. but it's not somehow an intrinsic problem. And therefore it
can become פיגול piggul. and it can become, you know, out of
the מעילה me'ilah category. אבל חסרון דפסולה דגופיה הוא, aval hesron d'psula
d'gufeih hu, but when it's not—it's lacking, it's not—you don't have all
of the מנחה mincha there and the תורה torah is telling you
you need all of the מנחה mincha or the remnant of the
מנחה. mincha. דפסולה דגופיה הוא, d'psula d'gufeih hu, it's more of an
intrinsic problem. It's not like some of it—it was brought to a
wrong place. It's like it's not full. That's about its very identity,
okay, its very body. לא מהני ליה הקטרה, lo mahani lei haktara,
that's so invalid that הקטרה haktara would not be good. So here
we're suggesting that this is, you know, maybe even a worse invalidity
than things like יוצא yotzei or טמא. tamei. That was something external.
Here it's not even fully there. there. So if it's not even
fully there, that's even a worse invalidity and these things would not
help. It would not be affected by the זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam,
or, excuse me, by the bringing of the קומץ. komets That's one
approach. Or you could go to the opposite extreme.
So, whatever, find that was, that was what רב הונא Rav Huna
said, said that it would, that it would certainly be פסול. pasul,
אמר ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, רבא Rava said אדרבה, adra'ba, no,
I'll say the opposite way. You mean certainly wouldn't be not be
a problem for people, right? It would certainly be intrinsically פסול, pasul
thank you, certainly be intrinsically פסול pasul and therefore you could not
make it פיגול piggul, and it would not get out and the,
it would not, you know, the מעילה me'ila status would not change.
It's not enough, like, sort of, you know, theoretically and still in
the realm of קרבנות that what you do can affect its status.
So your פיגול piggul. is irrelevant because it's totally פסול pasul and
your bringing of the
קומץ—forgetting kometz a פיגול piggul, thought—does not get it out of מעילה
me'ila because, again, it's off of the, it's off the table. Is
it a valid קרבן? korban.
Well, the קומץ kometz. is valid, yes, but the שיריים shirayim are,
you know, are not affected. Okay, the שיריים shirayim are not affected.
They're totally פסול pasul, and they're not affected by what you do
with the קומץ. kometz? That's what רב הונא Rav Huna says. אמר
ליה רבא, amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said back to him,
אדרבה, adra'ba, I would say the opposite. אפילו רבי אליעזר דאמר אין
זריקה מועילה ליוצא, afilu Rabbi Eliezer de'amar ein zrika mo'ila leyotze, so
this is the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that when meat is taken
out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it does not, it's not
affected by the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Since it's invalidated, it's not
affected. So your זריקה zrika won't make it פיגול, piggul. your זריקה
zrika won't get it out of מעילה, me'ila, same idea, except he
takes the opposite position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. If it's יוצא,
yotze, it's פסול, pasul it's not affected. So even according to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says by יוצא yotze it's not affected,
הני מילי יוצא דליתא בפנים, hani milei yotze d'leissa bifnim, that's יוצא
yotze where it's not in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash itself, it's
like, you know, it's off of the reservation.
אבל חסרון דאיתא בפנים, aval chisaron de'issa bifnim, but something that's just
lacking that's in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash itself, in that type
of a case, because the rest of the שיריים shirayim are there.
The rest of the שיריים shirayim are there, exactly. Thank you, yes.
Meaning the שיריים shirayim we're asking about. We're not asking about what's
not here. We're asking about the שיריים shirayim that are here that
we want to know, are they פיגול piggul. or is there מעילה?
me'ila? So what is here is here. So in that case, מהני
ליה הקטרה, mahani lei haktara, that's case the הקטרה haktara would be
relevant and you would make it into פיגול piggul. and we'd get
it out of מעילה. me'ila. Now, of course, the other thing פסול
psul that we normally think about other than יוצא yotze is... Like
טמא. tamei. טמא. tamei. And why don't you give an example of
טמא? tamei? Because טמא tamei is בפנים. bifnim. So let's see what
their positions are by טמא. tamei. But טמא tamei is always a
wildcard because you have the ציץ tzitz being מרצה על טמא meratze
al tamei and טמא tamei being, you know, מותר בקרבן ציבור, muttar
b'korban tzibbur, so טמא tamei is not always a good model to
be using to try to figure out what the general rule is.
So here you have this question. So, you know, one way of
just framing it, like I said, is, all right, how bad of
an invalidity is it? Some פסולים psulim are considered really bad and
they're no longer—what happens with the זריקה zrika or the הקטרה haktara.
of the קמיצה kemitza is not relevant to them. Others are bad
and they invalidate, but it's still somewhat in the ballgame and therefore
the הקטרה haktara is relevant for it. But again, I would like
to conceptually frame it, not just really bad or not so bad,
but I would frame it as maybe it's not a פסול psul.
at all. Meaning the way I would like to see רבא's Rava
position is, you know, not being full is not a פסול. pasul.
Maybe it's you're not allowed to eat it if it's not all
there, but maybe, you know, conceptually it's not the same type of
invalidity as יוצא yotze or טמא. tamei. That's at least my way
of understanding רבא. Rava. But when we say not all there, we
really mean not all there. Not like, you know, let's say some
of it spilled and it got mixed up with like dirt or
something and, you know, and now you can't, like, you... That's a
good question. How much חסר chasar is חסר? chasar? Like if it
becomes inedible, is it חסר? chasar? Yeah, it's a good question. I'd
have to see if there's a discussion about that. I don't know
offhand. Okay, so let's see how the גמרא Gemara tries to prove
it.
Where are we? אמר רבא, amar Rava,
okay. אמר רבא מנא מנא לה? amar Rava mina mina la? Where
do I get this from, this position that there's no פיגול? pigul
Okay, it gets a little complicated here. דתנן, ditnan, we taught in
a משנה, Mishna. our משנה. Mishna הקומץ את המנחה לאכול שיריה בחוץ
או כזית משיריה בחוץ, hakometz es hamincha leachol shireha bachutz o kezayis
mishireha bachutz, somebody takes the קמיצה kemitza, in order to eat the
remnant outside or a כזית kezayis of the remnant outside and then
it says, you know, or to burn it, or to burn a
כזית kezayis of it, and then it says, you know, the same
thing for wrong place. Anyway, that's our משנה's Mishna. structure. Except when
it gets to the לבונה levonah? where even a small amount, it
always says the full amount or a כזית. kezayis. Okay, fine. ותני
רבי חייא, v'sani Rabbi Chiya, but רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught in
a ברייתא Baraisa that was exactly parallel to our משנה. Mishnah, He
basically taught the same thing, except he dropped out the words כזית.
kezayis. And here's what he taught: הקומץ את המנחה. hakometz es hamincha.
If one takes the מנחה, mincha, and it says, you know, you
want to eat the remnant and, you know, outside or the wrong
place, anyway, it never said you want to burn a כזית kezayis
or you want to eat a כזית. kezayis. It said the whole
thing without giving the example of כזית. kezayis. For any of them.
For any of them. ולא תני או כזית. v'lo tani o kezayis.
Now, מאי טעמא לא תני או כזית? mai ta'ma lo tani o
kezayis? Why didn't he... Now, you could say he didn't say it
because maybe he held that you're not חייב chayav until you plan
on eating all of it or burning all of it. Okay, but
that the גמרא Gemara at least will play with that possibility in
a minute, but for now we're not assuming that that's possible. So
why did he not say it? Must be here's why he did
not say it.
Okay, כגון—לא כגון kegon שחסרו שיריים shirayim, דקמו להו אכזיתא. So it's
a little confusing or a lot confusing here, but this is the
way תוספות Tosafos explains it. He says, כגון kegon he was concerned
that the phrase או כזית o kezayis could have suggested in your
mind that all that's left is a כזית. kezayis. Meaning, he says
you want to eat the remnant or a כזית. kezayis. Well, we
understand 'or a כזית' kezayis means a כזית kezayis of what's left.
But he was afraid that if we said או כזית, o kezayis,
you might think it even includes a case of when all that's
left is a כזית. kezayis. Meaning, not a כזית kezayis of what's
left, but that all that's left is a כזית. kezayis. The rest
got lost. Meaning, it's exactly רבא's Rava's case, this case of חסרו
שיריים. chasru shirayim. You took the קמיצה kmitzah, and now some got
lost and all you're left with is a כזית. kezayis. And he
did not want to teach that case. Okay, why did he not
want to teach that case? Now, again, you could have said that
if anything that's a proof according to the other opinion. He didn't
want to teach that case because maybe then it wouldn't be פיגול,
pigul right? But רבא Rava is saying it is פיגול. pigul So
how's רבא Rava going to use this as evidence for himself? Let's
take a look. וקמו להו אכזיתא. vekamu lehu achezyasa. וכיון דבמתן כלי
בהילוך ובהקטרה לא מתני ליה. vikeivan debematan kli behiluch uvehaktara lo masni
leh. So since he could
not—one minute—he couldn't teach it in the case of putting it in
the כלי, kli, הילוך, hiluch, and הקטרה. haktarah? Hope you saw that
for a second. I got to remind myself exactly what this point
is.
One minute.
Okay, so the way רש"י Rashi explains this, which does not sound
so—I mean not so clear in the words of the גמרא, Gemara,
but the way רש"י Rashi explains this is he could not have
taught if you're going to understand או כזית o kezayis to mean
all that's left is a כזית, kezayis, he couldn't have taught it
in the case of to be מקיטר maktir the קטורת—or ketores כזית
kezayis of the קטורת tomorrow. Why? Because—I keep on doing it, the
קומץ, kometz thank you. Never did it any day before. It's all
the word הקטרה haktarah, here. Anyway, so because being מקיטר maktir the
קומץ kometz? or כזית kezayis of the קומץ kometz tomorrow. Because a
כזית kezayis of the קומץ, kometz if it means that all that's
left is a כזית, kezayis, then this קרבן korban. is not going
to become פיגול, pigul right? Because you have to be able to
burn the entire קומץ kometz for it to be פיגול. pigul So
if the words או כזית o kezayis in רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiya's
mind means or suggests that all you're left with is a כזית,
kezayis, he's not able to talk about that because then you would
think that even if your קומץ kometz was only left with a
כזית kezayis that that would be פיגול, pigul but it's not true.
You need the whole קומץ kometz there. Let's say your whole קומץ
kometz was a כזית. kezayis. Well, okay, but that's not the normal
case. וכיון דבמתן כלי בהילוך ובהקטרה לא מתני או כזית. vikeivan debematan
kli behiluch uvehaktara lo masni o kezayis.
Since therefore the phrase of או כזית o kezayis would not work
by these other עבודות with what you're planning on burning the קמיצה
because you can't—if all you're left with is only a כזית kezayis
of the קמיצה, it's not going to become פיגול. pigul So therefore
you can't say או כזית o kezayis because you have to do
the whole thing. Because if any of the קמיצה is lacking, you
can't be burning the קמיצה. So
therefore
אשיריים בקמיצה—so ashirayim bekemitza או כזית אשיריים בקמיצה o kezayis ashirayim bekemitza
נמי לאכל שיריים לא תני ליה. nami leechol shirayim lo tani leh.
So therefore when it comes to when you take the קמיצה and
there is שיריים, shirayim right? So there you could say all there
is is a כזית kezayis left. Because then, okay, you go ahead
and you burn the rest even if there's only a כזית kezayis
left. But since I can't use the או כזית o kezayis when
I'm talking about the burning of the
קטורת—that I'm burning a כזית kezayis because that would mean there's only
a כזית kezayis left—I can't say the או כזית o kezayis when
I'm talking about eating the remnant
because I want to be consistent. Meaning, in practice I could. Okay,
if there's only a כזית kezayis of the remnant left, I could
say that I had that thought, it would be פיגול. pigul But
since I can't talk about it by the קמיצה, I can't talk
about it about the remnant. And this is a
proof. ותני סיפא, vesani seifa, and since it does say in all
these cases, פיגול pigul וחייבין עליו כרת, that it is פיגול. אלמא,
alma, we see, מהניא להו הקטרה, mahanya lehu haktara, that therefore the
burning helps. This is going to be one of the most convoluted
proofs. Again, I don't even—you know, this is why there's a big
רש"י and תוספות Tosafos trying to figure out what he even means.
First of all, the read of רש"י is difficult because it should
not be contrasting מתן כלי, הילוך, והקטרה. matan kli, hiluch, vehaktara. It
should be saying... And you can't say כזית kzayis *kazayit* by the
קמיצה *kmitza*, right, by the קומץ kometz *komets*, not the קמיצה *kmitza*,
the קומץ kometz. *komets*, right, you can't say I plan on being
מכתיר *maktir* a כזית kzayis *kazayit* of the קומץ kometz *komets* because
that would suggest there's only כזית kzayis. *kazayit* left, which would end
the process. So I can't say it by the שיירים *shirayim*. Number
one: according to רש"י *Rashi*, it shouldn't have thrown in the מתן
כלי *matan kli* and the הילול *hilul*. The point is I can't
say it by the קומץ kometz *komets*, so because I couldn't say
it by the קומץ kometz *komets*, even though halachically I could say
it by the שיירים *shirayim*, I want to be consistent. That's number
one. Number two is: what type of crazy proof is that? If
anything, you could say that's your סברא *sevara* that he couldn't say
it by the קומץ *komets*, so he can't say it by... so
he wants to be consistent, he can't say it by the שיירים
*shirayim*. You know, your בר פלוגתא *bar plugta*, whoever it is, רב
הונא *Rav Huna* will say, no, the reason he didn't say it
is because you couldn't say it by the קומץ *komets* and you
can't say it by the שיירים *shirayim*. Right? רב הונא *Rav Huna*
says if... if there's not the full amount left, פיגול *pigul* thought
doesn't help. So רבא Rava *Rava* is saying because I think that
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya *Rabbi Chiya* in principle would say it would
work by the שיירים *shirayim*, and he only didn't say it to
be consistent to the קומץ *komets* case, I can infer that he
basically פוסק *paskens* that it would make פיגול *pigul*. All right, how
do you know? Maybe he didn't say it by the שיירים *shirayim*
because in principle it doesn't work by the שיירים *shirayim*. Circular, right?
Yeah, it's a very difficult, which may probably means there's some other
explanation we're not getting. Okay, but this is at least how רש"י
*Rashi* reads it. So again, what's רבא Rava. *Rava*'s proof? His proof
is רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya *Rabbi Chiya* taught a ברייתא Braisa *braisa*
without the words כזית kzayis *kazayit*. He assumes that the reason רבי
חייא Rabbi Chiyya *Rabbi Chiya* taught it that way is כזית kzayis.
*kazayit* would have suggested that there's only a כזית kzayis. *kazayit* left.
And therefore רבא Rava *Rava* says that could not work in the
קמיצה *kmitza* case... in the קומץ *komets* case, and therefore by the
שיירים *shirayim*, although in principle it could work, he wanted to be
consistent. But yes, it's circular, as you're only saying in principle it
could work because you're reading yourself into that... into that silence. Okay,
so let's take a... let's keep on going. אמר ליה אביי *Amar
lei Abaye*. So אביי *Abaye* says, and אביי *Abaye*'s read is much
easier than רבא *Rava*'s anyway. לא *Lo*, no, that's not why he
did not say כזית kzayis. *kazayit*. Here's why he did not say
it: הא מני רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer היא *Ha mani Rabbi Eliezer
hi*. It's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer*. דתנן detnan, *Ditnan*: הקומץ
והלבונה והקטורת ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח ומנחת נסכים *Ha'komets v'halvona v'haktores
v'minchas kohanim v'minchas kohen mashiach v'minchas nesachim*. So all these things that
are about... about burning things on the מזבח *mizbeach*. The קמיצה *kmitza*,
the לבונה levonah *levona*, which you know, you take your קומץ *komets*
of the לבונה levonah *levona*,
or the burning of the הקטורת *haktores*. Here we finally have the
קטורת *ketores*. The burning of the קטורת *ketores* which you do on
the מזבח הזהב *mizbeach hazahav*. Or the מנחת כהנים *minchas kohanim*, which
is fully burnt. Or מנחת כהן משיח *minchas kohen mashiach*, which is
also fully burnt. Or מנחת נסכים *minchas nesachim*. All these things are
burnt, right? Those are the מנחות *minchos* that come with the קרבנות
*korbanos*. How much do you have to burn of them to be
חייב chayav. *chayav* for bringing them outside the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*?
We're not talking about a מחשבת חוץ *machshavas chutz*, we're talking about
actually העלאת חוץ *ha'alas chutz*. You're bringing them outside the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash*. So in all these cases, הקריב מאחת מהן כזית kzayis.
בחוץ bachutz. חייב chayav *hikriv me'achas mehen kazayit bachutz chayav*. Then it's
considered an act of הקטרה haktarah. *haktara* and you're חייב chayav *chayav*.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer פוטר עד שיקריב את כולו *Rabbi Eliezer poter
ad she'yakriv es kulo*. You have to do the whole unit. Whatever
the unit is in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, you have to
be מכתיר *maktir*, you have to burn the whole unit outside to
be חייב chayav *chayav*. So now we're going to say look, when
you have a מחשבה *machshava* of חוץ למקומו *chutz limkomo*, that's always
tied into what would it be if you really did it, right?
I mean, that's the whole idea. You have to have a מחשבה
*machshava* of a כזית kzayis *kazayit*, right? You're not actually doing an
act with a כזית kzayis *kazayit*, but you're planning on doing an
act with a כזית kzayis. *kazayit*. So you're always thinking about that
act that I'm thinking about. How problematic is it? And the reason
it's a כזית kzayis. *kazayit* is because it's not a real הקטרה
haktarah *haktara* if it's פחות מכזית *pachos mi'kazayit*. So now we're going
to say, you know, there's a way we can determine how... whether
that act is a really problematic act, the one you're thinking about.
Are you חייב *chayav* for doing it out of the המקדש *Mikdash*?
Okay, so let's look at the model. So the basic תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* holds once you do it with a כזית
kzayis, *kazayit*, that's a problem. And that's why when you have a
thought about doing it, if you're thinking about doing it with a
כזית kzayis *kazayit*, that's a problem. But רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi
Eliezer* says you're not חייב *chayav* outside the המקדש *Mikdash* unless you
do the whole amount. So logically, according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer,
*Rabbi Eliezer*, you're not חייב *chayav* for thinking חוץ למקומו *chutz limkomo*,
you don't invalidate the קרבן korban *korban* unless you're thinking about bringing
the whole קרבן korban *korban* outside the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay?
So and we're saying that if you don't have a whole thing
to bring then it wouldn't be a problem in this case over
here. Well, that's what we're saying. The reason רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
*Rabbi Chiya* did not say that the case of you're planning on
being מכתיר *maktir* a כזית kzayis, *kazayit* outside or the wrong time
is because he holds like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*. According
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, doing a הקטרה haktarah. *haktara*
with a כזית kzayis *kazayit* is not considered an act of הקטרה
haktarah, *haktara*. הקטרה haktarah, *Haktara* would only be the full amount, the
whole קמיצה *kmitza*. So that's why רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya *Rabbi Chiya*
did not say you're planning on being מכתיר *maktir* a כזית kzayis
*kazayit*, okay, because he's going like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
and you have to plan to be מכתיר *maktir* the whole amount.
And this is when what happens then... what? And now we're talking
about the שיירים *shirayim* in a minute. Right, that's what I'm saying.
No, but I'm saying the next step... Okay, here's... right, let's see
how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* deals with the next step. Okay. So
it says like this: וכיון דבאקטרת קמיצה לא מתני ליה כזית kzayis.
*V'kivan d'ba'aktaras kmitza lo masni lei kazayit*, and since he can't give
the example of כזית kzayis *kazayit* by burning the קמיצה *kmitza* because
that's only חייב *chayav* and it's only a bad thought if you're
planning on doing. So או כזית ok'zayis מקומצה בחוץ, that you're planning
on burning the כזית k'zayis of קומץ outside, בשיריים נמי לא מתני
או כזית. bishirayim nami lo matni ok'zayis. So therefore did not say
it by the שיריים shirayim, that you're planning on eating a כזית
k'zayis because let's talk now about the act of eating. Right? We're
defining the act. What is an act of הקטרה? haktarah So the
תנא tana קמא says an act of הקטרה, haktarah. whether it's שחוטי
חוץ shchutei chutz or your thought, is being מקטיר maktir a כזית.
k'zayis Or maybe even less like by the לבונה levonah where even
a tiny amount is significant. Okay, but if there's more of it,
like a larger amount, even a כזית k'zayis is an act of
הקטרה. haktarah, Comes along, you know, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no,
an act of הקטרה haktarah, is the full קרבן, the full thing
that you would normally burn. So maybe it's a קמיצה, maybe it's
larger, whatever the full thing you would normally burn, that's the act
of הקטרה. haktarah That's what he says for doing it out, and
that's what he says for your thought. That's why you can't say,
according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer. או להקטיר כזית. o lehaktir kzayis.
It's only a problem if you have a plan of להקטיר the
whole amount. Now, the other part is you're planning on eating something
at the wrong time or in the wrong place, right? You're planning
on eating the שיריים, shirayim not bringing the הקטרה, but eating the
שיריים shirayim wrong time or wrong place. So here what's the question
that we ask?
How much do you need to be considered what?
To be considered פסול. passul An act, no, but an act of
what? Of eating. An act of eating. So we know the answer
to that. How much do you need to be considered an act
of eating? כזית. k'zayis Everything is a כזית. k'zayis. And if I
were to eat something in the wrong place or the wrong time
or I were to eat נותר nosar. or whatever, it would always
be a כזית. So here you could say או לאכול קומץ משיריים
למחר o le’echol kometz mishirayim l’machar because here it would be the
שיעור shiur of a כזית. But since we're not going to say
כזית by the הקטרה, we're not going to say it by the
אכילה. achilah. So we're no longer talking that the שיריים shirayim. were
lost. We're totally rejecting רבא's crazy read of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya
that כזית means you're only left with a כזית. No, it means
you're planning on doing the act with just a כזית. But since
we don't say that שיעור shiur by הקטרה because according to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the act is the whole amount, even though clearly
that's the שיעור shiur for אכילה, achilah, everybody says you define eating
as a כזית, we're not going to say that language by the
אכילה achilah either. You had a question, דב? Dov? Oh, it seems
like it should be more, it could be more parallel. You could
take the position that ideally you're supposed to eat the whole thing.
That's why there's an idea of
נותר. nosar. Right? Eat the whole thing, so you have to burn
the rest. But really the eating of the קרבן means you should
eat the whole thing, just like הקטרה. But that's I guess that's
the מצות עשה mitzat aseh and but that's not well, I'd say
a couple things. Number one is that's not the act of eating,
that's that the קרבן should be eaten and it doesn't have to
be you eating it. If everybody eats less than a כזית and
you make sure none is left over, you've avoided נותר. So bringing
half the קרבן is not even it's not burning the קרבן. No,
no, no, I'm not saying that. I'm just saying that there's not
a מצוה mitzvah for you to eat the whole קרבן. There's a
מצוה mitzvah for the whole קרבן to be eaten. But you can
get a thousand people, each eat a half כזית, and the whole
קרבן will be eaten. That's point number one. Point number two is
is that we're talking here about an אסור assur eating, right? An
איסור הקטרה issur haktarah or planning on doing an איסור הקטרה. issur
haktarah. So if you ask, when have I done something wrong, when
have I transgressed, what type of an eating is a transgression, that
would be as soon as I eat a כזית of sorts. So
therefore the plan of eating a כזית would suffice. Okay? So that's
how he explains רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiya not using the phrase, which
makes a lot more sense than רבא. And that was because in
a different case? What? Because רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya holds like רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that הקטרה, you're not חייב for a כזית. So
he can't say או כזית ok'zayis by the הקטרה, so he can't
say או כזית o k'zayis. by the שיריים. shirayim Okay? So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי רבי אליעזר, ei
Rabbi Eliezer, היי להקטיר קומץ hai lehaktir kometz if it's רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer one minute, we've got another problem. You should not be
חייב when you just have a plan to burn the קומץ. להקטיר
קומץ ולבונה מיבעי ליה. lehaktir kometz ulevonah mibei leih. This is what
I thought you were going to ask me, Michael. How come it
becomes פיגול when you just have a plan with the קומץ? Whatever
happened to the לבונה? levonah, It's not a כשר קרבן kasher korban
until you burn both. So maybe your פיגול thought is not meaningful
until you think about both. So we're going to see that there
actually is a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says that. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says you don't make something פיגול unless you have a
plan to both do the קומץ and the לבונה levonah to burn
them, okay? How do we know that? You don't think לבונה's levonah.
included in this קומץ? What? I mean No, the קומץ is separate.
No, I know, but then you have to bring לבונה levonah. too.
It's one they're just in one vessel. Well, no, we're going to
see that this is a debate. דתנן, because we taught in a
later משנה, Mishnah or actually we taught in a משנה Mishnah, in
זבחים, an earlier משנה, Mishnah הקומץ והלבונה שהקריב אחד מהן בחוץ חייב.
hakometz v'halevonah shehikriv echad meihen bachutz chayav. If you're מקריב makriv even
one of them outside, you're חייב. רבי אליעזר פוטר עד שיקריב את
שניהם. Rabbi Eliezer poter ad sheyakriv es sheneihem. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer. is very consistent, right? The same way he says a כזית
is not enough, the full thing that you're מקטיר maktir is what
מחייב you בחוץ. So
he says here too, you have to be even if it's two
separate objects, the קומץ and the לבונה, levonah you have to be
only when you bring both are you חייב בחוץ chayav bachutz and
therefore in parallel only when I plan on doing both at the
wrong place or the wrong time right would I actually have a
פיגול thought or a פסול thought. So according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer since I need to bring both outside to be חייב I
need to think about both to have an invalidating thought. So the
משנה Mishnah can't be the ברייתא Braisa can't be רבי אליעזר. Rabbi
Eliezer
So the גמרא Gemara says אה לא נצרכה אלא לקומץ דמנחת חוטא.
ah lo nitzrecha ela lekometz deminchas chotei. Okay you're right. According to
רבי אליעזר normally you would not have a פיגול thought unless you
planned on doing something with the קומץ and the לבונה levonah. but
I can give you a place where only having a thought about
the קומץ matters. Where? במנחת חוטא beminchas chotei where there is no
לבונה. levonah. So that's the so רבי חייא goes like רבי אליעזר
and therefore he dropped the או כזית. o k'zayis. Now that seems
a little bizarre that he should switch the whole ברייתא Braisa to
be talking about a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei which is what the
גמרא Gemara asks. The גמרא Gemara says
ואיכפל תנא לאשמועינן קומץ דמנחת חוטא ve'ichpal tana le'ashmi'inan kometz deminchas chotei
where are we that the תנא goes out of his way to
give us this whole story just by the application of מנחת חוטא.
minchas chotei. The גמרא says אין in yes וכן כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רבי אליעזר קומץ דמנחת חוטא הוא רבי אליעזר היא. vechein
ki ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Eliezer kometz deminchas chotei hu Rabbi
Eliezer hi. We're talking about a קומץ of the מנחת חוטא minchas
chotei and this is רבי אליעזר and therefore we didn't say או
כזית. o k'zayis Now actually it is a little bizarre that we
do say meaning yes telling us a חידוש chiddush but we say
this whole thing without mentioning it's a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei but
I think the easier answer is that רבי חייא did not want
to fully rewrite the text. Meaning if you assume there's always a
question about like what was the original text that people were working
off of but if you assume there was an original text that
said או כזית o k'zayis you know למחר lemachar או כזית o
k'zayis. you're going to be מקטיר maktir etcetera. רבי חייא approaches and
says I hold like רבי אליעזר כזית isn't enough I'm crossing out
the כזית from this text. Okay you have to have a thought
to do the whole thing. אה רבי אליעזר Ah Rabbi Eliezer also
requires the לבונה. levonah. I'm not going to go and write into
this text that you're thinking about both this and the לבונה levonah
you know I'm just going to make a few edits and cross
out the או כזית. o k'zayis Now it doesn't it still can
make sense in a case of מנחת חוטא minchas chotei meaning I
think that's the way to think about it. He edited the text
he edited it lightly the least change. He took out the או
כזית o k'zayis. and it still makes sense in a case of
מנחת חוטא. minchas chotei. So now what have we found? According to
רבי אליעזר right this is actually a much better read of רבי
חייא according to
רבי אליעזר. He
once did a Michael Jordan interview let him ask his question go
ahead. He's asking because he thinks the text is wrong because he
thinks the text is missing something? No because he doesn't agree with
it. It's wrong according to the way he פוסקן. paskens. I פוסקן
pasken that a כזית thought is not enough. Okay so what we
have found out is in the process of trying to figure out
the question about what happens if there's not all the שיריים there
does a פיגול thought help? We have now introduced some interesting things
that we hadn't thought about before. Number one the assumption in the
משנה Mishnah that a thought relating to a כזית was enough that
assumes the act done with a כזית is a significant act. By
אכילה achilah it's certainly true. By הקטרה it's debated. רבי אליעזר says
you're only חייב by
בהקטרה be'haktarah outside if you do the whole amount. So according to
him a פיגול thought would only be the whole amount and therefore
רבי חייא takes out the או כזית. Not only that consistent with
רבי אליעזר you're only חייב for הקטרה בחוץ haktarah bachutz when you
do not only the whole amount of one object but all the
objects necessary. So in the case of a מנחה mincha it would
be the קומץ and the לבונה. So a פיגול thought for him
would only be when you are thinking about the קומץ and the
לבונה. Now this is to do both of them incorrectly. This is
not to be confused with מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin bechatzi matir which
I'm sure everybody was worried about which is when did you have
your thought? Are you having your thought during the whole act or
half of the act? Because the other thing our משנה Mishnah did
not discuss is our משנה Mishnah says you're having your thought when
you're doing all these things with the קומץ. What about the fact
that the קומץ is not enough to make the מנחה מותר? mincha
muttar? You also need to do the לבונה. So our משנה Mishnah.
assumes two things. Number one מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin bechatzi matir that
even if your thought was just by the קומץ even though it's
only half of the act half of the process and that your
thought is enough that it's even on just the קומץ itself right
and not on or just the לבונה and it doesn't have to
be on all those things that you have to be מקטיר because
it also says it's enough that it's on a כזית. All right
let's at least finish up to the משנה. Mishnah. So we proved
no we have not proved anything about our question. Okay we just
took רבא'ס Rava's interesting point about רבי חייא'ס Rabbi Chiya's ברייתא Braisa
and went in a different direction. All right so let's just finish
up to the משנה. So much for finishing the פרק. perek. הדר
אמר רבא Hadar amar Rava then רבא says לאו מעליא היא דאמרי.
lav ma'alya hi de'amri. You know what? What I was saying before
is not correct
that you would not have a פיגול problem. Why? דתניא Detanya we
taught in a
ברייתא קודש קדשים היא. kodesh kodashim hi. This is by the לחם.
lechem It might be הוא hu because לחם lechem is masculine. לחם
הפנים. Right no this is not by the מנחה. mincha. This is
by the לחם the לחם הפנים. What does that mean? What does
the ברייתא *Baraita* say? שנפרסה אחת מהם *she-nifresa achat mehem*, אחת מן
החלות *achat min hachalot* or something, כולן פסולות
*kulam pesulot*, that if one of them break they're all invalid. What
is that like? That's basically the מנחה *Mincha* that was חסרה *chasera*,
right? If the מנחה *Mincha* is חסרה *chasera*, you cannot go ahead
and eat the remaining of the שיריים *shirayim*. So now comes and
says רבא *Rava*, היצאת *hayatzata* הני דאיתא גואי *hani de-ika gavai* כשירות
*ksherot*, which suggests that it's only a problem by חסר *chaser*, but
if it was יוצא *yotze*, if one of the loaves was taken
outside, you could eat the remnant of the bread. So here remember
the way we framed the question about how bad is חסר *chaser*,
is it worse than יוצא *yotze* or better than יוצא *yotze*? So
רבא *Rava* says actually I was wrong, it's worse than יוצא *yotze*.
Because this ברייתא *Baraita* says that if one of the loaves of
the לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* broke, you can't eat the remnant. And
the implication would be that if one was יוצא *yotze*, you could
eat the remnant. So יוצא *yotze* of one doesn't affect the rest,
but חסר *chaser* does affect the rest. So חסר *chaser* is worse
than יוצא *yotze*. And therefore and therefore and therefore there would not
be a פיגול *pigul* thought, the פיגול *pigul* thought would not be
relevant. He's retracting his position. What?
Exactly. הדר ביה *hadar bay*, he's retracting his position. Okay, so let's
take a look.
Where are we?
So היצאת *hayatzata* הני דאיתא גואי *hani de-ika gavai* כשירות *ksherot*. מאן
שמיע ליה דאמר *man shamiah leh de-amar* זריקה מועלת ליוצא *zrika mo-elet
le-yotze*? Who says זריקה *zrika* works for יוצא *yotze*? Now this is
a little different, when רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva*. Now רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said it works for even the
bread that's already out. Here you only have one loaf out and
eleven loaves in. Okay, but he still says רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
normally is the one that says that the פיגול *pigul* is still
relevant in these cases. He, וקאמר *ve-ka-amar*, nevertheless it says נפרסה *nifresa*
לא *lo*, that if it's broken they're all פסול *pasul*. So his
basic argument is, and if you think about it you don't even
need this ברייתא *Baraita*, you could have just made this argument by
logic which is, if you have a קרבן *korban* and some of
it is יוצא *yotze*, right, then the rest is כשר *kasher*. But
if some of it is חסר *chaser* by a מנחה *Mincha*, we're
saying the rest becomes פסול *pasul*. So חסר *chaser* is worse than
יוצא *yotze*. However, I don't know that הלכה *halacha* yet by a
מנחה *Mincha*. I would know that by meat. What if I took
a little piece of my מנחה *Mincha* and I brought it outside
the מקדש *Mikdash*? Okay, would that be like חסר *chaser* and the
rest would be invalid? Or would that not be like חסר *chaser*
and the rest would still be okay? You mean being יוצא *yotze*.
Right, if I did יוצא *yotze* with the שיריים *shirayim*, is it
יוצא *yotze* or חסר *chaser*? Is it also a problem of חסר
*chaser* and the rest is no go? So רבא *Rava* says look,
I got a ברייתא *Baraita* here by לחם הפנים *Lechem HaPanim* that
says חסר *chaser* is no good. And somehow I'm going to be
מדייק *medayek* that that means but if it wasn't חסר *chaser*, if
it didn't break, it was just יוצא *yotze*, the rest would be
good. So it's hard to know how he's מדייק *medayek* it, maybe
יוצא *yotze* is also no good. But then he says from this
it proves to me that חסר *chaser* is worse than יוצא *yotze*
and therefore also in terms of the פיגול *pigul* question. So let's
take a look. He assumes that therefore he can prove it. Right,
same like the previous point. That's an excellent point, he's totally reading
his assumptions. But here you're doing it to retract himself. But in
both cases he's reading his assumptions into the evidence. So אמר ליה
אביי *amar leh Abaye*, so אביי *Abaye* said back to him, מי
קתני היצאת *mi katani hayatzata*? No, it doesn't say that if it
was יוצא *yotze* it's still good. דילמא הנטמאת *dilma ha-nitmas* הנך כשירות
*hanach ksherot*. Maybe if it's טמא *tamei* it's still good. מאי טעמא
*mai ta-ama*? דמרצה ציץ *demartze tzitz*. And here we come to the
ציץ *tzitz* again, because since the ציץ *tzitz* is around, it somewhat
alleviates the problem of טומאה *tumah*. אבל יצאת *aval yatzata* לא *lo*,
but maybe if it went out the remnant would be no good.
ורבי אליעזר היא *ve-Rabbi Eliezer hee*, דאמר אין זריקה מועלת ליוצא *de-amar
ein zrika mo-elet le-yotze*. And it would be רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
that would say that when there's a יוצא *yotze* problem זריקה *zrika*
doesn't help and therefore it also doesn't help by a חסר *chaser*
problem. ובדינו דאיבעי ליה למתני נמי יצאת *u-bedino de-iba-i leh lematni nami
yatzata*. So why did it only give the example of חסר *chaser*?
It should because you're right, it really should have said יוצאת *yatzata*
as well. והאי דקתני נפרסה *ve-hai de-katani nifresa*, so why is it
saying broken? הא קמשמע לן *ha kamashma lan*, דאפילו נפרסה *de-afillu nifresa*
דאיתא בפנים *de-itah bifnim*, even if it's broken and it's inside the
מקדש *Mikdash*, it's not יוצא *yotze*, לא מהניא לה הקטרה *lo mahanya
lah haktara*. הקטרה *haktara* does not help and it's just as bad
as יוצא *yotze*. אבל לרבי עקיבא *aval le-Rabbi Akiva* דאמר זריקה מועלת
ליוצא *de-amar zrika mo-elet le-yotze*, according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that
says זריקה *zrika* works for יוצא *yotze* and therefore you know to
make it פיגול *pigul* etc., אפילו חסרון נמי מהניא ליה הקטרה *afillu
chisaron nami mahanya leh haktara*. For חסרון *chisaron* as well the הקטרה
*haktara* would work, which means what? It means like this, there's two
questions, right? The question, first of all, this is not an exact
parallel. There's a problem with this whole thing because when we talk
about רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* with יוצא *yotze*,
we're talking that everything was יוצא *yotze*. Here we're talking only one
loaf is יוצא *yotze*. So the whole analogy breaks down, that's a
difficult point here. But it is an interesting question, which is if
חסר *chaser* a piece is חסר *chaser* makes everything not edible for
a מנחה *Mincha*, what if a piece is טמא *tamei*? What if
a piece is יוצא *yotze*? Does it have the same effect? We
really haven't resolved that, we saw you know because that's the problem,
it's not an exact parallel. But what we have said in the
end is the following. Which we don't know. What we don't know.
We don't know if this ברייתא *Baraita*, what this ברייתא *Baraita* would
assume by... Would it assume יוצא *yotzei* is good? Would it assume
יוצא *yotzei* is no good? So you can't make any inferences from
this ברייתא *braita* that if חסר *chaser* is no good,
that it's even according to the מן דאמר *man de’amar* that יוצא
*yotzei* is good, חסר *chaser* is no good. Maybe it's assuming that
יוצא *yotzei* is also no good. The one shift we have done
is that originally we framed the issue
that I could say that חסר *chaser* is worse than יוצא *yotzei*,
I could say that חסר *chaser* is better than יוצא *yotzei*. Now
at the end of the גמרא *Gemara* we’re sort of saying it’s
the same. Whatever position you would have with
יוצא *yotzei*, whether it could become פיגול *pigul* or would not be
מעילה *me’ilah*, you would have the same position with חסר *chaser*. Meaning
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* it would be
the same debate, right? That’s what we said at the end. This
ברייתא *braita* might be, it might be רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, but
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, the same way he says יוצא *yotzei* is
still relevant, so he would say חסר *chaser* is too. So basically
מחלוקת תנאים *machlokes tannaim*. So basically what we said at the end
is it is dependent on רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer*. Except personally though, I very much like not רבא'ס *Rava's*
ראיה *raya*, but רבא'ס *Rava's* original position, which is: let יוצא *yotzei*
be completely off the table, but חסר *chaser* is fundamentally more a
פסול קרבן *psul korban*. Okay, and again the irony is the more
פסול *pasul* it is, the more your מחשבת פיגול *machsheves pigul* is
irrelevant and the more you don't get it out of the מעילה
*me’ilah* category. The more it's not seen as a weighty פסול *psul*,
an intrinsic פסול *psul*, or פסול *pasul* at all, like I would
suggest, then the more your מחשבת פיגול *machsheves pigul* is relevant because
it's still somewhat connected to the קרבן *korban*. What are we holding
in the end? Okay, so at the end of the day what
happens if it's חסר *chaser*, does פיגול *pigul*... what do we פסקן
*pasken*? What do we פסקן *pasken*? I'd have to check the רמב"ם
*Rambam*. I love it when you
ask what we פסקן *pasken* right now. הלכתא למשיחא *hilchasa limshicha*! All
right. We went a little over. Even over our over.
Oh my gosh. We'll
put them back over there. Where'd he put these? Yeah, talk about
two things to remind you of the students asked: number one, that
if we move the table to move it back, and right, we
shouldn't put those on the windowsill, so the גמרות *Gemoras* are going
to live over there.