Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is כ"ה, chaf hey,
מנחות Menachos 25, and we pick up with the משנה Mishnah and
we are now moving to a totally new topic. Let's take a
look. נטמא הקומץ והקריבו. Nitma hakametz vehikrivo.
So the קומץ kometz became טמא tamei and it was offered up
on the מזבח. mizbeach. הציץ מרצה. Hatzitz meratze. והציץ, ve-hatzitz, the, you
know, gold plate that the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol wears, that allows
it to be accepted, makes it accepted by God, okay, and that's
based on the language of the פסוק pasuk which we will see
in the גמרא. Gemara.
יצא והקריבו אין הציץ מרצה. Yatza vehikrivo ein hatzitz meratze. However, if
the קומץ kometz was taken out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and became פסול pasul because it was יוצא yotze and then you
put it on the מזבח, mizbeach, the ציץ Tzitz is not מרצה.
meratze. The ציץ Tzitz only fixes, as it were, you're not allowed
to put up even if it's טמא, tamei, but if בדיעבד bedieved
you did, the ציץ Tzitz forgives that, as it were, and it
doesn't just mean, it doesn't mean at all that it forgives the
sin, but it
wipes away the problem of the fact that it was טמא tamei
in terms of the validity of the קרבן. korban. It makes the
קרבן korban acceptable regardless of the fact that the קומץ kometz was
טמא. tamei. A parallel would be the blood would be טמא tamei
of an animal קרבן. korban. Okay, so that's the effect the ציץ
Tzitz has: it makes the קרבן korban acceptable when it has the
problem of טומאה tuma and טומאה tuma on the blood or טומאה
tuma on the קומץ, kometz, which is the thing that validates the
קרבן, korban, and it allows the קרבן korban to remain valid after
the fact, but not when it's a problem other than טומאה, tuma,
when the קומץ kometz was taken out of the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. הציץ מרצה על הטמא ואינו מרצה על היוצא. Hatzitz meratze al
hatamei ve-eino meratze al hayotze.
The ציץ Tzitz is מרצה, meratze, makes the קרבן korban acceptable, valid,
for the problem of טומאה, tuma, but not for the problem of
any other problem, and here it's being contrasted to when it's taken
out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So let's see where we
get this from. גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן, Tanoo Rabbanan, we taught in
a ברייתא. braisa.
ונשא אהרן את עון הקדשים. V'nasa Aharon es avon hakodashim. Aaron will
carry the sin of the sacrifices, okay, and that's in the context
of the ציץ. Tzitz. So the ציץ Tzitz allows him to carry,
forgive, as it were, remove the sin of the sacrifices. וכי איזה
עון הוא נושא? V'chi eize avon hu nosei? What sin is he
carrying? Is he removing, lifting up? אם תאמר עון פיגול, Im tomar
avon pigul, if it is the sin of פיגול, pigul, that if
you had a thought of פיגול pigul the קרבן korban would still
be valid because of the
ציץ, Tzitz, הרי כבר נאמר לא יחשב. harei kvar ne'emar lo yeichashev.
By the פסוקים pesukim that we learn out the איסור issur of
פיגול pigul from, you know, they say, "It shall not be considered,"
or not have, you know, not be valid. It explicitly says this
will never be valid, it's categorical.
לא יחשב. Lo yeichashev. ואם תאמר עון נותר, V'im tomar avon nosar,
and if it is the sin of נותר, nosar, הרי כבר נאמר
לא ירצה. harei kvar ne'emar lo yeiraize. It also says in that
context it shall not be acceptable, so it cannot be מרצה meratze
on something the תורה Torah said that it's a, you know, that
the תורה Torah explicitly said לא ירצה. lo yeiraize. Now תוספות Tosafos
points out that we're not really talking about נותר nosar because obviously
נותר nosar the קרבן korban was already valid, there's no way that
here we're talking about validating the קרבן. korban. You don't need the
ציץ Tzitz to fix נותר. nosar. What the ציץ Tzitz fixes is
it makes, you know, the קרבן korban valid, although we'll see some
other things in a minute, okay. But תוספות Tosafos says
that what we mean is intent of נותר, nosar, which is intent
to eat it at the wrong time, and that would turn פיגול
pigul maybe into intent of the wrong place. Okay, so any type
of wrong thought or other invalidity, a wrong place, wrong time, the
ציץ Tzitz will not fix those problems.
הא אינו נושא אלא עון טומאה שהותרה מכללה בציבור. Ha eino nosei
ela avon tuma shehutra miklala b'tzibbur. The only thing it will forgive
is the sin of טומאה, tuma, which we know is in other
times accepted, the תורה Torah will allow sometimes an override of טומאה.
tuma. When? When it's a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur and, you know,
the כהנים kohanim are טמאים temeim or the קרבן korban is טמא.
tamei. You know, that is the principle of טומאה הותרה בציבור. tuma
hutra b'tzibbur. So since sometimes that's overridden, we could imagine that that
is lighter or that would be the one that the תורה Torah
would allow to be forgiven in this case.
Now רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam nicely adds that part of the reason
that it's trying to find something that is in other circumstances is
acceptable is because the end of the פסוק pasuk ונשא אהרן את
עון הקדשים, v'nasa Aharon es avon hakodashim, it says לרצון להם לפני
ה'. l'ratzon lahem lifnei Hashem. It should be לרצון. l'ratzon. That's also,
by the way, the reason why we're using the word מרצה, meratze,
right? Makes it acceptable, makes this קרבן korban valid.
So because it says לרצון להם לפני ה', l'ratzon lahem lifnei Hashem,
there's a sense that this has to be something that at some
other circumstances is considered to be
לרצון. l'ratzon. And that's why we're looking for, we find that טומאה
tuma other times it can be overridden. evidence, so here too that
is what is happening with the ציץ. tzitz. Okay, that's the ברייתא.
braita. Okay, so מתקיף ליה רב זירא, matkif leh Rav Zeira, רב
זירא Rav Zeira challenges ברייתא, braita, it seems like the only thing
he could find that sometimes is מותר mutar under other places is
טומאה. tumah. Let's try to find some other things. אימא עוון יוצא,
Eima avon yotze, how about exactly the thing the משנה mishna had
the problem with, when it's taken out of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, where is that ever overridden or put accept—not permissible, but acceptable?
שהותר מכללו בבמות, Shehutar miklalo bevamos, that we when there's a היתר
הבמות heter habamos and you don't have to bring it in the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, there's no problem of יוצא. yotze. So because
that's, you know, acceptable there, maybe that's what the ציץ tzitz permits.
Now, that's a little funny. When there's היתר במה, heter bamah, there's
no there's no הלכה halacha of יוצא, yotze, there's no reality of
יוצא. yotze. You didn't take it out of any space. Alright, so
it's not that it is יוצא yotze but it's still acceptable. But
nevertheless, you could understand the question. Since sometimes the תורה Torah allows
under certain historical circumstances for things outside of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, so the פסול psul of יוצא yotze is maybe less severe
and maybe that's what it is forgiving. So אמר ליה אביי, amar
leh Abaye, אביי Abaye said back, אמר קרא amar kra לרצון להם
לפני ה׳, leratzon lahem lifnei Hashem, so this is again, you know,
it to be for to be acceptable for them before God. עוון
דלפני ה׳ אין עוון דיוצא לא. Avon d'lifnei Hashem in, avon d'yotze
lo. It's a sin that takes place לפני ה׳, lifnei Hashem, in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not that the problem took place because
it was taken out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, מתקיף
ליה רבי אילא, matkif leh Rabbi Ila, so רבי אילא Rabbi Ila
challenged this idea again that you can only find טומאה tumah as
the case. אימא עוון שמאל, Eima avon smol, how about if the
כהן Kohen carried the קרבן korban with his left hand? Or the
blood rather with his left hand, and that makes it not valid.
Okay, now and שהותר מכללו ביום הכפורים, shehutar miklalo beYom HaKippurim, and
there are times when that's acceptable on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, when
they take the, you know, the incense and the fire pan, the
fire pan in the right hand and the incense in the left
hand. So sometimes the תורה Torah allows it, so maybe that is
the sin that is being forgiven. Alright, so אמר ליה אביי, amar
leh Abaye, אביי Abaye says back very reasonably,
אמר קרא עוון עוון שהיה בו ודחתיה, amar kra avon, avon shehaya
bo vedachtay, לאפוקי יום הכפורים דכשרה בשמאל. lafukei Yom HaKippurim dekesheira b'smol.
No, no, no, it has to be something that is basically problematic
and there are and here it's being sort of made valid. Other
times it is being, you know, like in the case of טומאה
הותרה בציבור, tumah hutra be-tzibur, it's being overridden, but it always is
עוון, avon, is something that's a problem that we're forgiving or that
we're overriding. Whereas on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, that's exactly how you
do the עבודה. avodah. It's true, normally the עבודה avodah is פסול
pasul with the left hand, but on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, it's
not a problem that's being overridden, here's how the תורה Torah prescribes
how the עבודה avodah is supposed to be done. Okay, רב אשי
אמר, Rav Ashi amar, and רב אשי Rav Ashi has another answer
to how you know it's not about a problem of, let's say,
the left hand. רב אשי אמר עוון הקדשים ולא עוון המקדישים. Rav
Ashi amar avon hakodashim velo avon hamakdishim.
He says, and this is a very, I think I think פשט
pshat read of the פסוק, pasuk, okay? It's ונשא את עוון הקדשים,
venasa es avon hakodashim, the sin of the sacrificial objects, okay? There's
something wrong with the sacrifice itself, as opposed to if a כהן
Kohen carried it in his left hand, you know, עבודה avodah was
פסול, pasul, but it's not the קדשים kodashim has some, you know,
has some problem associated with it. And that really would eliminate any
type of a פסול psul of the עבודה. avodah. It has to
be something that's a problem of the קרבן korban itself. All right,
אמר ליה רב סימי בריה דרב אידי לרב אשי. amar leh Rav
Simi brei de-Rav Idi le-Rav Ashi. So now we've we've learned out
how come we wind up on landing that it is just טומאה
tumah that we attribute this פסוק pasuk to, that the ציץ tzitz
carries, lifts up, removes to some degree the sin, לרצון להם leratzon
lahem and is מרצה, meratzeh, makes it acceptable. Okay, so אמר ליה
רב סימי בריה דרב אידי לרב אשי, amar leh Rav Simi brei
de-Rav Idi le-Rav Ashi, so רב סימי Rav Simi the son of
רב אידי Rav Idi said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, ואמרי לה
רב סימי בריה דרב אשי לרב אשי, v'amri lah Rav Simi brei
de-Rav Ashi le-Rav Ashi, and some say רב סימי Rav Simi רב
אשי's Rav Ashi son said to his father רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
ואימא עוון בעל מום שהותר מכללו בעופות. ve'eima avon baal mum shehutar
miklalo be'ofos. Wait a minute, I'm not done. Maybe
there's another type of a thing that's a problem in the קרבן
korban itself, and that would be the קרבן korban would be a
בעל מום. baal mum. So maybe if you בדיעבד bedieved offered up
a בעל מום, baal mum, it's כשר kasher because of the ציץ.
tzitz. Where do we find sometimes a מום mum can be accepted?
Because that's
one of the criteria here. So he says by birds. Why do
you know this? דאמר
מר, de'amar mar, because the master teaches, we teach, תמות וזכרות בבהמה.
tamos vezachros bebehemah. The requirement of תמים tamim and the requirement of
זכר zachar at least by an עולה olah being male, so sometimes
the תורה Torah is מקפיד makpid male, sometimes female, it always says
it has to be תמים tamim unblemished. That's only by קרבנות korbanos
by, you know, animals, mammals. ואין תמות וזכרות בעופות. ve'ein tamos vezachros
be'ofos. When it comes to birds, we don't care male, we don't
care female, we don't care if it's blemished or unblemished. So the
תורה Torah overrides the problem, you know, by birds. That is less
of an overriding, it's like a הותרה מכללו. hutra mikelalo. It's not
always a problem, but it's not the same as טומאה tumah which
as גמרא Gemara said before is an עוון avon that is being
overridden. But let's see how the גמרא Gemara answers it. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, עליך אמר קרא alecha amar kra לא ירצה, lo yeratzeh,
כי לא לרצון יהיה לכם. ki lo leratzon yihiyeh lachem. Similar to
how we ruled out פיגול pigul and נותר, notar, when it speaks
about the problem of a בעל מום, baal mum, it explicitly says
it will not be acceptable. The exact opposite of לרצון. leratzon. לא
ירצה, Lo yeratzeh, לא לרצון. lo leratzon.
So those are things that the ציץ tzitz cannot work for, so
what you are left with is that the ציץ tzitz works for
טומאה tumah that occurs to the blood or the קומץ, kometz, but
the problem of טומאה, tumah, that is what the ציץ tzitz is
מרצה. meratzeh. Okay, now another ברייתא. braita. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our
rabbis taught: דם שנטמא וזרקו, Dam shenitma vezarko, the blood became טמא
tamei and you sprinkled it, exactly our scenario. בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא
הורצה. Beshogeg hurtza bemeizid lo hurtza. If it was sprinkled or thrown,
but this unintentionally, you were not aware that it was טמא tamei
or maybe you didn't realize it was אסור assur to use טמא
tamei blood, then it works. The ציץ tzitz is מרצה, meratzeh, the
קרבן korban is valid. But if it is intentional, you knew that
it was טמא tamei and you shouldn't throw, and you threw it
anyway, then the ציץ tzitz is not מרצה. meratzeh. Now, the גמרא
Gemara is going to say very soon, and this fits into a
whole set of cases like this in גיטין, Gittin, that this is
not a דאורייתא de-oraita point. This is a קנס knas that we
don't want to let you, חוטא נשכר, choteh niskar, benefit from willfully
doing a violation. So even though the ציץ tzitz really is מרצה
meratzeh even if you do it במזיד, bemeizid, דרבנן derabanan we are
not going to let the קרבן korban be valid and we are
going to require you to bring another קרבן korban if it was
במזיד. bemeizid. But we will go by the ציץ מרצה tzitz meratzeh
rule when it is בשוגג. beshogeg. Okay, that's the position of this
ברייתא. braita. במה דברים אמורים, Bameh devarim amurim, when is it true
that we distinguish between שוגג shogeg and מזיד? meizid? ביחיד, Beyachid, if
it's about an individual קרבן. korban. אבל בציבור, Aval betzibbur, but if
it's a communal קרבן, korban, בין בשוגג בין במזיד הורצה, bein beshogeg
bein bemeizid hurtza, whether בשוגג shogeg or מזיד, meizid, it still works.
And now it's funny, like the concept of מזיד meizid isn't even
so relevant by a communal קרבן korban because a communal קרבן, korban,
it's הותרה בציבור. hutra betzibbur. Okay, maybe there's some circumstances where there
was an alternative and you could have done it with another, but
anyway,
by a communal קרבן korban we are not going to make this
קנס knas and we will let it work even if it's מזיד.
meizid. ובעובד כוכבים, U-veoved kochavim,
and when you're dealing with a non-Jew who can bring a קרבן,
korban, בין בשוגג בין במזיד בין באונס בין ברצון, bein beshogeg bein
bemeizid bein be-ones bein beratzon, whether intentional or willful,
whether against their will or willful,
כה עמוד ב, kaf hei amud bet, לא הורצה, lo hurtza, it
is not acceptable. The ציץ tzitz only works for קרבנות korbanot of
בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael as we'll see, because it says לרצון להם,
leratzon lahem, for them, for בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, and it doesn't
fix the problem for non-Jews, and that is understood to be at
a דאורייתא. de-oraita. Now, the question you might be asking is, who
cares if it's הורצה? hurtza? Right, the non-Jew sent it, what's the
נפקא מינה nafka mina if it's הורצה? hurtza? So a couple נפקא
מינה. nafka minas. Number one, the non-Jew maybe took a vow, and
he's sending this קרבן korban to fulfill his vow. And maybe there
is a sense of the bindingness the same way a קרבן, korban,
a non-Jew can bring a קרבן, korban, that sense of the bindingness
of vows—not saying it's exactly one of the שבע מצוות בני נח,
sheva mitzvot Bnei Noach, but it might have a certain metaphysical reality
and it's important for him to be יוצא yotzei his vow. That's
one point. The other point
is, can we eat the meat? Right? It's קודש, kodesh, the non-Jew
sanctified it, and that's part of the חידוש chiddush here, non-Jew can
sanctify קרבנות, korbanot, and the meat cannot be eaten
by the כהנים kohanim unless the קרבן korban was valid. Okay, so
it only works for the קרבן korban of Jews, not the קרבן
korban of non-Jews. Let's take a look, now the גמרא Gemara is
going to spend the rest of the דף daf trying to figure
out this position of this שוגג מזיד shogeg meizid distinction and how
universally it's held. ורמינהי, Ur-minei, the גמרא Gemara says, I'll challenge you.
We have another ברייתא. braita. על מה ציץ מרצה? Al mah tzitz
meratzeh? What does the ציץ tzitz make acceptable? על הדם, Al hadam,
if the blood is טמא, tamei, because we already discussed what problem,
the problem of טומאה. tumah. But what objects? Blood,
the parallel for us would be the
קומץ, kometz, ועל הבשר ועל החלב שנטמא, ve-al habasar ve-al hachalav shenitma,
and on the meat and on the fat that became טמא. tamei.
So first of all, it's interesting the whole idea of the meat
and the fat. The fat is burnt on the מזבח, mizbeach, the
meat is eaten by the owners, neither of those is the
קרבן's korban validity hinge on. The קרבן's korban validity only hinges on
the דם dam or on the קומץ. kometz. So here, if we
are saying there's an idea of ציץ מרצה tzitz meratzeh by these
cases of the חלב chelev burning or of the eating the meat.
We have to be talking to some degree also like alleviating the
sin, not just fixing the problem. All right? So
that's but that's interesting that we've now extending the concept to the
meat and the חלב. Chelev.
Okay, שנתנו Shenatnu בין בשוגג בין במזיד bein beshogeg bein bemezid בין
באונס בין ברצון bein be'ones bein biratzon whether it was willful or
unwillful, accidental or intentional, against one's will or willful. בין ביחיד בין
בציבור Bein beyachid bein betsibbur whether individual or whether communal. So here
it clearly does not make a distinction of שוגג shogeg and מזיד
mezid for the individual, but the previous ברייתא Baraita did. So the
most obvious thing to say is maybe it's a debate. So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef
לא קשיא lo kashya it's not difficult. הא רבי יוסי הא רבנן
Ha Rabbi Yosi ha Rabbanan it's a debate whether we make a
קנס knas we find somebody, you know, in a case of מזיד
mezid or whether we allow it to remain valid. So let's take
a look. דתניא Detanya we taught in a ברייתא Baraita in a
somewhat analogous case, not the same, a case of תרומה. Terumah. אין
תורמין מן הטמא על הטהור. Ein tormin min hatamei al hatahor. You
cannot take תרומה Terumah from טמא tamei grain that, you know, you
have one pile of טמא tamei grain, one pile of טהור tahor
grain, you take the תרומה Terumah from the טמא tamei pile and
you give the כהן Kohen תרומה טמאה Terumah Tmeia and you but
the תרומה Terumah works. It's your intent to make all of the
grain, the טמא tamei and the טהור, tahor, to now be acceptable.
All right? So that you cannot do because you're giving the כהן
Kohen טמא תרומה tamei Terumah when you could have given him טהור
תרומה tahor Terumah when the טהור tahor is part of the equation.
So you cannot take from טמא tamei on טהור. tahor. ואם תרם
Ve'im taram and if you did it, בשוגג תרומתו תרומה במזיד אין
תרומתו תרומה. beshogeg terumato terumah bemezid ein terumato terumah. If it was
unintentional, you didn't realize it was טמא, tamei, you didn't realize it
was a problem, then we're going to allow it to work and
the תרומה Terumah takes effect. If it is במזיד, bemezid, then we
will Rabbinically basically fine you and say you have to treat it
as if the תרומה Terumah was not valid. Okay, that's the first
position. So that's the making a קנס knas by מזיד. mezid. רבי
יוסי אומר בין בשוגג בין במזיד תרומתו תרומה. Rabbi Yosi omer bein
beshogeg bein bemezid terumato terumah. No, even במזיד bemezid בדיעבד bediavad we
will allow it, we don't make a קנס. knas. So it's sort
of similar. It's having with something קודש, Kodesh, although a different type
of קודש, Kodesh, תרומה. Terumah. It's about טומאה tumah and it's a
debate about whether we make a קנס knas for cases of מזיד.
mezid. All right? So that's a very reasonable argument. The ברייתא Baraita
that says that it only works בשוגג beshogeg is the תנא
קמא Tanna Kama here and the ברייתא Baraita that says that it
works even במזיד bemezid is רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. So let's see
where the גמרא Gemara goes.
אמר—the Amar גמרא Gemara says like this: אימר דשמעת ליה לרבי יוסי
Eimar deshamat lei leRabbi Yosi no, one minute. When have you heard
that that's that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says מזיד בדיעבד mezid bediavad
will be okay? דלא קניס Delo kanis that he doesn't make a
fine. But דמרצי ציץ demratze Tzitz fine, that part of the ברייתא
Baraita it will fix. The ברייתא Baraita said that it works even
במזיד. bemezid. But the ברייתא Baraita also said that the ציץ Tzitz
works, the second ברייתא Baraita we read at the top of this
עמוד amud said that the ציץ Tzitz works even for the meat.
Okay, that's a new concept.
ודמרצי ציץ על אכילות Udemratze Tzitz al achilot that the ציץ Tzitz
somehow, you know, validates or does a, you know, lifts up the
sin in some way for the meat, from the things that are
being eaten. So that's a new concept. ודמרצי
ציץ על אכילות מי שמעת ליה? Udemratze Tzitz al achilot mi shamat
lei? Do we know that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that? You're
now making this ברייתא רבי יוסי Baraita Rabbi Yosi because it says
מזיד בדיעבד mezid bediavad is okay. But the ברייתא Baraita also says
the ציץ Tzitz works for the meat. And actually, I'm going to
show you that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says the ציץ Tzitz does
not work for the meat. Let's take a look. דתניא Detanya we
taught
in a ברייתא Baraita רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer הציץ מרצה
על האכילות. hatzitz meratze al ha'achilot. The ציץ Tzitz even lifts up
the sin of meat that became טמא. tamei. רבי יוסי אומר אין
הציץ מרצה על האכילות. Rabbi Yosi omer ein hatzitz meratze al ha'achilot.
No, it does not. So exactly the רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi who
says מזיד mezid בדיעבד bediavad will be okay by תרומה Terumah says
that a ציץ Tzitz doesn't work on the meat. So you can't
make the ברייתא Baraita that says מזיד mezid is okay and the
ציץ Tzitz works on the meat, it doesn't work with for רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yosi.
So the גמרא Gemara says like it does sometimes in these cases,
איפוך. ipoch. Fine, reverse the names. You know, with an oral tradition,
you could understand the names might have gotten reversed. So maybe here
the names were reversed. And we'll read it this way: איפוך. ipoch.
רבי אליעזר אומר אין הציץ מרצה על האכילות רבי יוסי אומר ציץ
מרצה על האכילות. Rabbi Eliezer omer ein hatzitz meratze al ha'achilot Rabbi
Yosi omer Tzitz meratze al ha'achilot. Maybe it דוקא davka was רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi who says it works on the meat and רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says it does not. And if that were
true, then our second ברייתא, Baraita, the one at the top of
this עמוד, amud, could perfectly be רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi says that we don't—בדיעבד מזיד bediavad mezid it'll still be
valid and רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, if we reverse it, says that
it will work on the meat. All right? So but we're not
ending here. מתקיף לה רב ששת Matkif lah Rav Sheshet Rav Sheshet
challenged this. ומי מצית אפכת לה? Umi matzit apchat lah? How can
you reverse these opinions? I'm going to show you you from another
source that it Rabbi Yosi is the one who says it does
not work on the meat. Okay let's take a look.
ותניא, V'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, יכול בשר שנטמא לפני
זריקת דמים יחייבו עליו משום טומאה. Yachol basar shenitma lifnei zrikas damim
yechayavu alav mishum tumah. Okay so now this is a different topic,
I mean we'll see how it'll be relevant, but the topic here
is that if somebody is טמא tamei and eats בשר קדשים basar
kodshim then they're חייב כרת. chayav kares. Okay, if the meat is
טמא tamei it's only a לאו, lav, if they're טמא tamei they're
חייב כרת, chayav kares, if both are טמא tamei that's a discussion.
Okay so this ברייתא Braisa says what if a טמא tamei person
ate the meat of a...
so he's טמא, tamei, if he were to eat the meat of
a קרבן korban he'd be חייב כרת, chayav kares, but he ate
it before the blood was thrown, before the meat was fit to
be eaten, the blood of the קרבן korban has not yet been
thrown on the מזבח. mizbeiach. And it's going to say he is
not חייב. chayav. All right so let's take a look.
יכול בשר שנטמא לפני זריקת דמים יחייבו עליו משום טומאה, Yachol basar
shenitma lifnei zrikas damim yechayavu alav mishum tumah, perhaps meat that became
טמא, tamei, Rashi says another גרסא girsa of this does not say
the meat became טמא tamei because that's not really the focus. The
focus is that the person is טמא. tamei. But it's possible that
meat that you ate before זריקת דם, zrikas dam, perhaps you'd be
חייב כרת chayav kares משום טומאה. mishum tumah. תלמוד לומר כל טהור
יאכל בשר, Talmud lomar kol tahor yochal basar, anybody, only somebody who
is טהור tahor can eat the meat of קרבנות. korbanos. והנפש אשר
תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים אשר לה' וטומאתו עליו, Ve'hanefesh asher tochal basar
mizevach hashelamim asher la'Hashem vetum'aso alav, and somebody who eats the meat
of the שלמים shelamim or really of any קרבן korban and that
person is טמא, tamei, then ונכרתה, venichresa, he gets כרת. kares. So
how do you see that does not include our case of before
זריקת הדם? zrikas hadam? So it says הניתר לטהורים, hanitir lisehorim, the
fact that the פסוק pasuk before saying you can't be טמא tamei
and eat it, started by saying if you're טהור tahor you eat
it. So the type of meat that we are talking about is
meat that can be eaten by a טהור tahor person. הניתר לטהורים,
hanitir lisehorim, the type of meat that is permissible to a טהור
tahor person, חייבין עליו משום טומאה, chayavin alav mishum tumah, you're חייב.
chayav. And that's meat after the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. ושאינו ניתר
לטהורים, veshe'eino nitir lisehorim, meat that's not permissible for a טהור tahor
person, which is the meat of the קרבן korban before זריקת הדם,
zrikas hadam, אין חייבין עליו משום טומאה. ein chayavin alav mishum tumah.
You don't get כרת kares for being טמא. tamei. It's still אסור
assur to eat, it's still
קודש, kodesh, might be מעילה, me'ilah, that's a separate conversation, but it's
not a problem of טומאה tumah because it is not yet מותר
mutar for a טהור tahor person to eat it. Okay so now
the גמרא Gemara continues,
I mean the ברייתא Braisa continues. או אינו אלא נאכל לטהורים חייבין
עליו משום טומאה ושאינו נאכל לטהורים אין חייבין עליו משום טומאה. O
eino ela ne'echal lisehorim chayavin alav mishum tumah veshe'eino ne'echal lisehorim ein
chayavin alav mishum tumah. Maybe the key is not הניתר לטהורים, nitir
lisehorim, which I might have translated as that allowed to be eaten,
but הניתר nitir means has to be made permissible. Maybe the key
difference, the key focus here is meat that actually can right now
be eaten by a טהור tahor person. Okay so that would still
get you off the hook before זריקת דם, zrikas dam, but it
might also get you off the hook from other things. What are
other things that it would get you off the hook of? So
let's take a look. ושאינו נאכל לטהורים אין
חייבין עליו משום טומאה, veshe'eino ne'echal lisehorim ein chayavin alav mishum tumah,
הוציא אני את הלן ואת היוצא, otzi ani es halan ve'es hayotzei,
and that would allow me to also get you off the hook
for meat that became נותר, nosar, it slept over, or meat that
was taken out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Meaning the blood
was thrown on the מזבח, mizbeiach, the meat had a moment when
it was הניתר לטהורים, nitir lisehorim, when it was made permissible to
a טהור tahor person, and now afterwards, you know, it got taken
out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or became נותר. nosar. So
maybe you're off the hook there, maybe you're only חייב chayav for
meat that right now is allowed to be eaten by a טהור
tahor person, right? Why do you say it the key question is
was it was it made permissible when the blood was thrown? Maybe
the key question should be is it permissible right now to be
eaten? So how do you know to get that those you do
not get off the hook for those cases? תלמוד לומר אשר לה'
ריבה, Talmud lomar asher la'Hashem riba, because
it says anybody who eats from מזבח השלמים אשר לה', mizevach hashelamim
asher la'Hashem, that's extra words, so it's coming to include, you know,
there's some cases that you might have thought you're off the hook
for, you're not. Even though these things cannot be eaten right now,
since they had a moment when they were made permissible when the
blood was thrown, you're still going to be חייב chayav if you
eat it when you're טמא. tamei. יכול שאני מרבה את הפיגולים ואת
הנותרות, Yachol she'ani marbe es hapigulim ve'es hanosaros, maybe,
okay, you know, I will also go ahead and say that you
will be חייב chayav for if you're going to be חייב chayav
for לן lan and יוצא, yotzei, maybe you'll also be חייב chayav
for פיגול. pigul. Okay now פיגול pigul is something that was never
permissible because you had a thought, you know,
of to eat it at the wrong time, and that means from
the very moment the blood was thrown, the קרבן korban could not
be eaten, it was already פיגול. pigul. Okay but maybe heck, if
you're including לן lan and יוצא, yotzei, maybe you'll also include פיגול.
pigul. יכול *Yachol* to be for being חייב chayav *Chayav* for יכול
שאני מרבה את הפיגולים *Yachol she'ani merabeh et hapigulim*, maybe you'll also
be חייב chayav *Chayav* for פיגול *Pigul* ואת הנותרות *Ve'et hanotarot* and
things that are leftover which normally means נותר *Notar*, it means לן
*Lann*, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says נותרות היינו לן *Notarot hainu lann*.
What do you mean? Something leftover that's a case of לן *Lann*
and לן *Lann* you actually said you are חייב *Chayav* for. So
אלא אף הפיגולים כנותר *Ella af hapigulim kenotar*, maybe now that you're
saying that לן *Lann* sleeping over is חייב *Chayav* for because it
had a moment of being מותר mutar *Muttar*. If so, maybe also
פיגול *Pigul* you'll be חייב *Chayav* for. Now that actually works that
it's comparing it to נותר *Notar* because פיגול *Pigul* is the thought
of the wrong time. So meat that actually becomes נותר *Notar* you're
still going to be חייב *Chayav* for, maybe when you have a
thought of a wrong time maybe meat that's פיגול *Pigul* you'll also
be חייב *Chayav* for if you ate it when you were טמא
tamei *Tameh*. תלמוד לומר מזבח השלמים *Talmud lomar mizevach hashelamim*, from the
זבח השלמים *Zevach hashelamim*, so that is מיעט *Mi'et*, not everything that
is a זבח השלמים *Zevach hashelamim*. So that's a narrowing word. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has you have an expansive word, a
narrowing word. How do you decide which is in the category, which
things you're חייב *Chayav* for for טומאה tumah *Tumah*, which things you're
פטור *Patur* for? So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ומה ראית לרבות את
אלו ולהוציא את אלו *Uma ra'ita lerabbot et elu ulehotzi et elu*,
on what basis did you include for a חיוב *Chiyuv* the case
of
לן *Lann* and יוצא yotze. *Yotze*, but you got the guy off
the hook if it's a case of פיגול *Pigul*? What's the basis
of distinction?
So it says אחר שריבה הכתוב ומיעט *Achar sheriba hakatuv umi'et*,
so once the פסוק *Pasuk* was expansive and then also was limiting,
אמרת מרבה אני את אלו שהיתה להן שעת כושר *Amarta marbe ani
et elu shehayta lahen sha'at kosher*.
I will include נותר *Notar* and יוצא yotze. *Yotze* which had a
moment when it could be eaten by a טהור tahor *Tahor* person.
When the דם dam *Dam* was thrown, they were still okay. מוציא
אני את אלו שלא היתה להן שעת כושר *Motzi ani et elu
shelo hayta lahen sha'at kosher* and exclude the case of פיגול *Pigul*
which was never, was never had a moment when the meat was
כשר kasher. *Kosher*. So there you're exempt. Okay, so that is a
whole ברייתא braita, *Brayta* that basically says that a טהור tahor *Tahor*
person, that you're exempt from כרת *Karet* if you're טמא tamei *Tameh*
and eat meat of קדשים *Kodshim* if it was never ניתר לטהורים
*Nitar letahorim*, never had a moment where it became permissible. If it
was a case of you know before זריקת הדם zrikat hadam, *Zrikat
hadam* or it's after זריקת הדם zrikat hadam, *Zrikat hadam* but it
was פיגול *Pigul*, it never became permissible. If it was not ניתר
לטהורים *Nitar letahorim*. But if it was ניתר לטהורים *Nitar letahorim* it
became permissible but it's right now it's not אכיל *Achil*, it can't
be eaten because it's נותר *Notar* or יוצא yotze, *Yotze*, that case
you're still going to be חייב *Chayav* for.
So still not exactly clear how it's relevant but hold on.
Okay, ומוציא ואם תאמר *Umotzi ve'im tomar* so the ברייתא braita *Brayta*
goes on and says, asks itself, maybe you will say בשר basar,
שנטמא shenitma, לפני זריקת הדם zrikat hadam, ואכלו לאחר זריקת הדם מפני
מה חייבים עליו משום טומאה tumah. *Basar shenitma lifnei zrikat hadam va'achalo
le'achar zrikat hadam mipnei mah chayavim alav mishum tumah*? So one minute,
if the key question is did it have a שעת כושר *Sha'at
kosher*, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says well I'll give you something
that didn't have a
שעת כושר *Sha'at kosher*. You slaughtered the animal, the meat became טמא
tamei *Tameh* and then you did the זריקת הדם *Zrikat hadam*. In
that case at the moment of זריקת הדם *Zrikat hadam* the meat
was never permissible to be eaten because it was טמא tamei *Tameh*.
Okay? So maybe the answer is okay so you're not חייב *Chayav*
in that case. But no, we are accepting that, we are taking
for granted that in that case you would be חייב *Chayav*. So
why are you חייב *Chayav* when the meat was טמא tamei *Tameh*
and then there was זריקת הדם *Zrikat hadam*? Isn't that a case
that it was never ניתר *Nitar*, it never became permissible? So the
ברייתא braita *Brayta* says no מפני שהציץ מרצה meratzeh *Mipnei shehatzitz mirtze*,
because the ציץ tzitz מרצה meratzeh *Tzitz mirtze*. And now we understand
one of the implications of what it means to be מרצה *Mirtze*
for the meat. Okay? Before I was saying what does מרצה *Mirtze*
for the meat mean? I mean you sinned but you already ate
it. Okay? But here we understand what it means מרצה *Mirtze*. It
means in some הלכות *Halachot* where it matters to say that the
meat is you know doesn't have the status of טומאה tumah, *Tumah*
of invalidity with the full force because of the ציץ tzitz *Tzitz*.
Nobody is saying it's permissible to eat. But because the ציץ tzitz
*Tzitz* somehow alleviates that status we're going to look at it as
if it actually was טהור *Tahor*. So actually in that way it's
going to מחייב *Mechayiv* you. It doesn't get you off the hook.
It actually makes you more חייב *Chayav*. But okay, that's the consequence.
Because the ציץ tzitz *Tzitz* alleviates some of the טומאה tumah *Tumah*
of the meat, even though it was never ניתר לטהורים *Nitar letahorim*,
it was sort of like hypothetically ניתר לטהורים *Nitar letahorim* because if
a טהור *Tahor* person would have eaten from it the ציץ tzitz
*Tzitz* somehow would have like alleviated that sin. And therefore it's somehow
still in that category of ניתר לטהורים *Nitar letahorim* and that's why.
why you’re חייב. So the upshot being according to this ברייתא, braita,
the ציץ tzitz being מרצה on the בשר, basar, it says the
ציץ tzitz is מרצה on the בשר, the ציץ tzitz works for
the meat. So the
and now the גמרא Gemara continues, and now the גמרא Gemara jumps
in: חד משום טומאה וחד משום יוצא לא. Chad mishum tumah vechad
mishum yotze lo. So this ברייתא braita pretty much, you know, says
the ציץ tzitz only works to alleviate the טומאה tumah problem, right?
We’re also talking about problems of taking it out of the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, etc., and it sounds the ציץ tzitz is irrelevant
for that. The ציץ tzitz here is only relevant in this discussion
of when are you חייב if you’re טמא tamei, and eat the
meat. It’s only relevant for a case of טומאה. tumah. Okay, so
now this ברייתא braita says two things: A, the ציץ tzitz works
on meat and B, it only works on טומאה, tumah, not on
יוצא. yotze. Fine. מאן שמעת ליה דאמר אין זריקה מועלת ליוצא רבי
אליעזר. Man shamas lei de’amar ein zerika moeles leyotze Rabbi Eliezer. So
in מעילה, Meila, we know that there’s a position of רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that the ציץ tzitz does not work for יוצא. yotze.
Okay? There, so again, that would be a case that of,
it could be a case of the meat itself, and if the
ציץ tzitz works, it would have implications for its מעילה Meila status.
Again, the ציץ tzitz working doesn’t mean that it becomes מותר to
do, but at some level, we look at it as if the
טומאה tumah isn’t there, and that would have implications for the מעילה
Meila status of the meat. Okay, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer there
says that, what do you call it, that the, that the ציץ
tzitz does not work for יוצא, yotze, which is consistent with this
ברייתא, braita which is talking when you’re טמא tamei, and you eat,
that it assumes that the ציץ tzitz only works for טומאה tumah
and not for יוצא. וקתני, Uketani, so this ברייתא braita, now is
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the ציץ tzitz only works for טומאה. tumah
That was also the position, I should say, of our משנה, mishna,
it only works for טומאה, tumah not for יוצא. וקתני דמרצה ציץ
על אכילות, Uketani dimeratzeh tzitz al achilos, and it says that the
ציץ tzitz works for, for the meat. So here you have a
ברייתא braita that has to be רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because it
limits the ציץ tzitz for טומאה tumah and not for יוצא, and
we know that’s a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer position, okay? And it
also says that the ציץ tzitz works for the meat. So that
proves that the original ברייתא braita that had said that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer said that the ציץ tzitz works for the meat is
accurate, you cannot reverse it. All right, and if you’re remembering going
back, if we can’t reverse that ברייתא, braita then we’re still going
to be stuck because the ברייתא braita that said that the ציץ
tzitz works for the meat says it doesn’t matter, which now we’re
saying has to be רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it says it doesn’t
matter if you’re שוגג shogeg or מזיד, meizid, but we know that
it’s only רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi who says I don’t care, שוגג
shogeg or מזיד. meizid. So what we have is the ברייתא braita
again teaches at the top of the עמוד amud that the ציץ
tzitz works on the meat and it doesn’t matter if you’re שוגג
shogeg or מזיד. meizid. We know that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says
by תרומה terumah I don’t care if you’re שוגג shogeg or מזיד,
meizid, but we know that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the ציץ
Tzitz. works on the meat. And now we have prevented the גמרא
Gemara from reversing the positions. It’s clear from this later ברייתא braita
that about טומאה tumah and whatever, that that is the ברייתא braita
of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, and that it’s also saying that the
ציץ Tzitz works on the meat. So how does our original ברייתא
braita work? We have a רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi position that I
don’t care about מזיד, meizid, and we have a רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer position that it works on the meat. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אלא אמר רב חסדא, Ela amar Rav Chisda,
so says רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, לא קשיא הא רבי אליעזר הא
רבנן. lo kashya, ha Rabbi Eliezer ha rabbanan. That’s not difficult, you
know, the one that says that it, that it works במזיד bemeizid
is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Fine, the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
says that the ציץ Tzitz works on the meat and that therefore
has to be the author of the ברייתא braita at the top,
fine, we'll say רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer also says that the ציץ
Tzitz works even
במזיד. bemeizid. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is going to say what’s your
basis for saying that? But the ברייתא braita at the top is
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it works for the meat, and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer maybe will also say it works במזיד. bemeizid. And the
ones and the ברייתא Braisa, that disagrees will be some רבנן rabbanan
that say it only works בשוגג, beshogeg, not במזיד. bemeizid. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי אליעזר מרצה ציץ אכילות, Eima
deshamas lei leRabbi Eliezer meratzeh tzitz achilos,
one minute, I get that you want to make the ברייתא Braisa
go like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
the ציץ Tzitz works for the
meat. דלא קניס מי שמעת ליה? Delo kanis mi shamas lei? But
that ברייתא Braisa said two things: it works on the meat and
it works even במזיד. bemeizid. Well, where can you find a רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer position that says בדיעבד bedieved things are okay במזיד?
bemeizid? So the גמרא Gemara says, אין, In, yes, I actually do
know of a position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer where he says
that. כי היכי דשמעת ליה לרבי יוסי, Ki heichi deshamas lei leRabbi
Yossi, the same way you earlier quoted רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi by
תרומה terumah where רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says בדיעבד bedieved it’ll be
okay even במזיד, bemeizid, שמעת ליה לרבי אליעזר, shamas lei leRabbi Eliezer,
you also, that’s a position you should have. be aware of Rabbi
Eliezer exactly like Rabbi Yossi, that במזיד bemeizid it's not a problem.
דתניא, De-tanya, I mean, it's a problem לכתחילה lachat'chilah but not בדיעבד.
bediavad. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa רבי אליעזר אומר
בין בשוגג בין במזיד תרומתו תרומה, Rabbi Eliezer omer bein beshogeg bein
bemeizid trumato trumah,
that exactly what Rabbi Yossi said, whether it was בשוגג beshogeg or
במזיד, bemeizid, בדיעבד bediavad if you take from טהור grain on טמא
tamei, grain, טמא tamei grain on טהור grain, בדיעבד bediavad it works.
So the same way he says it by תרומה, Trumah, he'll say
it by the ציץ. Tzitz. Now it's perfect. The ברייתא Braisa said
the ציץ Tzitz works on meat, that's a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
position. Check, check. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer explicitly said meat and it
also we identified him as the author of this ברייתא Braisa about
טומאה tumah. and what type of meat you're חייב on that he
says the ציץ Tzitz works on meat, so check. And רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says the ציץ Tzitz works even or תרומה Trumah works
even במזיד bemeizid בטומאה betumah and therefore presumably he would say the
same by the ציץ Tzitz as well. Perfect! So then the גמרא
Gemara has one last question. אימא דשמעת ליה לרבי אליעזר בתרומה דקלה
בקדשים דחמימי מי שמעת ליה? Eima deshamesh lei leRabbi Eliezer bitrumah dekalah
bekadshim dechamimei mi shemesh lei? Fine,
but when did Rabbi Eliezer say that בדיעבד bediavad it's okay במזיד?
bemeizid? That's by תרומה. Trumah. By קרבנות Korbanot which is more weighty,
you know, תרומה Trumah is relatively light compared to קרבנות, Korbanot, קרבנות
Korbanot which is more weighty, how do you know he would not
say מזיד meizid is a problem? Maybe he'd be stricter there? So
the גמרא Gemara says, you gotta love the answer, the גמרא is
going to say אם כן הא מן תרמיה? im kein ha man
tarmya?
So if that's true, if you want to say, well, we don't
know if he says it by קרבנות, Korbanot, then you're stuck, you
know, you got a ברייתא Braisa. that clearly does say it by
the ציץ. Tzitz
So hypothetically we can make a distinction between that and תרומה, Trumah,
but we gotta figure out who the author of the ברייתא Braisa
is and it works very well for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because
the ציץ tzitz works for the meat and because we know at
least by תרומה, Trumah, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says we're not going
to make a קנס knas if it's מזיד meizid and therefore completely
reasonable to assume that this ברייתא Braisa is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and he says the same by קרבנות. Korbanot. That is one answer,
a very elegant answer. We're going to end with two other answers.
רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says טומאתו בין בשוגג בין במזיד
הורצה זריקתו בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה. Tumato bein beshogeg bein bemeizid
hurtzah zrikato beshogeg hurtzah bemeizid lo hurtzah.
He has a very nice close read of the ברייתא. Braisa He
says look at this ברייתא Braisa at the top of the עמוד.
amud. It says על מה הציץ מרצה על הדם ועל הבשר ועל
החלב שנטמא בין בשוגג בין במזיד. Al mah haTzitz mertzeh al hadam
veal habasar veal hachelev shenitma bein beshogeg bein bemeizid.
That became טמא tamei, whether you are שוגג shogeg or מזיד. meizid.
The טומאה tuma occurred maybe במזיד. bemeizid. So if the טומאה tuma
occurred במזיד bemeizid the ציץ tzitz. will still work. The ברייתא Braisa
before that said only שוגג shogeg was talking about how the זריקת
הדם, okay, that was the moment that was critical for the קרבן
korban becoming כשר. kasher, So if you look at the previous ברייתא
Braisa at the bottom of כ"ה עמוד א', Kaf-Hei Amud Aleph, it
says דם שנטמא וזרקו בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה. dam shenitma uzrako
beshogeg hurtzah bemeizid lo hurtzah.
So it's a brilliant answer. These ברייתות Braisos are completely consistent, that
the ציץ will work if the טומאה tuma happened במזיד, bemeizid, that's
the ברייתא Braisa on the top of עמוד ב', amud beis, but
it will not work if the זריקה zrikah happened במזיד. bemeizid. The
זריקה zrikah is only בשוגג. beshogeg. Great answer! Now רב שילא Rav
Shila is going to say the reverse. רב שילא אמר זריקתו בין
בשוגג בין במזיד הורצה. Rav Shila amar zrikato bein beshogeg bein bemeizid
hurtzah.
No, we'll go easier on you when it comes to the זריקת
הדם, that's not the moment of the actual טומאה. So even though
that seems to be more problematic because that's when you're trying to
make the קרבן korban כשר, he says once the קרבן korban is
טמא, tamei, you know, we'll allow the ציץ to work even if
you're מזיד meizid at the זריקה. zrikah. But הורצה, hurtzah, that works.
טומאתו, tumato, but as far as when it becomes טמא, בשוגג tamei
beshogeg, הורצה במזיד b'meizid לא הורצה. The ציץ will only work when
it became טמא tamei. בשוגג, b'shogeg not when it became טמא במזיד.
tamei bemeizid. So the exact same except the reverse. The two ברייתות
Braisos work together and except the language here is completely consistent with
רבינא Ravina and completely against רב שילא, Rav Shila, which the גמרא
will say. And רב שילא Rav Shila is going to claim that
our ברייתא braita on the עמוד ב' amud beis that says מזיד
שוגג meizid shogeg doesn't matter is how the דם was thrown, exactly
opposite of what it says, and the ברייתא on the bottom of
עמוד א' amud aleph where it says מזיד שוגג meizid shogeg do
matter is how it became טמא, tamei also exactly against the language,
which the גמרא is now going to ask. So the גמרא says
like this. Okay, ולרב שילא הא דקתני, U-leRav Shila ha de-katani, but
according to רב שילא, Rav Shila, that which we taught שנטמא בין
בשוגג בין במזיד, shenitma bein beshogeg bein bemeizid, the language of the
ברייתא here at the top of עמוד ב' amud beis says it
became טמא tamei, whether שוגג shogeg or מזיד, meizid, which that doesn't
matter, that's exactly what
רב חסדא Rav Chisda said, excuse me, רבינא Ravina said. No, הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar,
here's how you have to read it: שנטמא בשוגג וזרקו בין בשוגג
בין במזיד. shenitma b'shogeg v'zarko bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid. Very hard read.
Okay, so when the line says any of these things, שנטמא בין
בשוגג בין במזיד, shenitma bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid, it means שנטמא, shenitma,
big comma, any of these things became טמא, tamei and then you
went ahead and you continued doing the עבודה avoda בין בשוגג בין
במזיד, bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid, and the key verb וזרקו v'zarko is
sort of absent. Okay, תא שמע. Ta shema. So now let's try
to, okay, how about the ברייתא at the bottom of the עמוד
א, amud alef, top of כו עמוד א? Chaf-vav amud alef? דם
שנטמא, dam shenitma, blood that became
טמא, tamei וזרקו בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה. v'zarko b'shogeg hurtza b'meizid
lo hurtza. And it was thrown, if it was במזיד b'meizid, it
doesn't work, בשוגג b'shogeg, it does. So there it's distinguishing שוגג shogeg
and מזיד meizid based on how the blood was thrown, not on
how the blood became טמא. tamei So the Gemara, which is exactly
רבינא Ravina and exactly against רב שילא. Rav Sheila. So the Gemara
says, no, הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's how רב שילא Rav Sheila
would read it: דם שנטמא וזרקו, dam shenitma v'zarko, that's one phrase.
Then you put in a big comma. Okay, you don't put in
the comma after שנטמא, you put it in after וזרקו. v'zarko. Blood
became טמא and you sprinkled the blood, what's the
הלכה? halacha? בין בשוגג בין במזיד, Bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid, and then
it became טמא, whether it was שוגג shogeg or מזיד, meizid, but
you, I'm sorry, וזרקו, v'zarko, so נטמא בשוגג nitma b'shogeg and the
וזרקו v'zarko could be בין בשוגג בין במזיד, bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid,
נטמא בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה. nitma b'shogeg hurtza b'meizid lo hurtza.
So here's how you would read it. As opposed to reading it
דם שנטמא dam shenitma comma וזרקו בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה. v'zarko
b'shogeg hurtza b'meizid lo hurtza. Blood became טמא and then you sprinkled
it במזיד, b'meizid this is the story, and sprinkled it בשוגג, b'shogeg,
that's the story. That's of course the simple way of reading it.
He would read it דם שנטמא וזרקו, dam shenitma v'zarko, blood became
טמא and you sprinkled it, the sprinkling I don't care how the
sprinkling was done. If it was בשוגג, b'shogeg meaning if the טומאה
was בשוגג b'shogeg. it works. If it, meaning the טומאה was במזיד
then it doesn't work. Okay, very, very difficult read. רבינא Ravina has
a very elegant read. So we have two ways of understanding it.
Either there's a debate if שוגג, shogeg, if מזיד meizid works even
מזיד meizid on the זריקת הדם,
or that it matters what we're talking about. I'm just going to
go with רבינא Ravina that the טומאה can be whether שוגג shogeg
or מזיד meizid but the זריקה zrika is only בשוגג. And the
other thing that we've seen is the question of it working on
אכילות, achilot, which at least we've understood a little bit what that
means since it's really about status and not about forgiveness, that how
do we look at the status of the meat in certain areas
where that matters for the הלכה halacha of a טמא person who
eats it or מעילה? me'ila? In those cases the ציץ alleviates its
status and it has consequences. The consequences might actually be worse but
that but nevertheless that is the reality of the mechanism of the
ציץ. Okay, we will end with this.