Good data it's at nineteen we start on the last line of
י"ח עמוד ב' Yud-Chet Amud Beis or three actually three lines from
the bottom middle of the line מאי טעמא דרבנן.
Mai Ta'ama D'rabbanan. Okay so we had seen that there's
a
debate
of
the rabbis and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about whether יציקה Yetzika has
to be done by a כהן. Kohen. The משנה Mishna actually says
that יציקה Yetzika is not מעכב. Ma'akev. The גמרא Gemara immediately reinterpreted
that because it understands that יציקה Yetzika is מעכב Ma'akev based on
the פסוקים Psukim exactly say which פסוקים Psukim and says that it's
not מעכב Ma'akev with a כהן. Kohen. But then we quoted רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who said that you know if a כהן Kohen
doesn't agree to all of the מצוות Mitzvos of the כהונה Kehuna
then he doesn't have a portion in it and one of the
things he listed was יציקה. Yetzika. He listed other things in the
משנה Mishna בלילה Belila etc. other things that came before the קמיצה.
Kmitza. So it said okay רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds that it
requires a כהן Kohen and the חכמים Chachamim hold that it does
not require a כהן. Kohen. I should say I posted something late
last night or early this morning from your perspective to my blog
about this issue about somebody who is not מודה Modeh doesn't have
a portion. Remember the פסוק Pasuk quoted actually was לא יהיה שוק
הימין למנה. Lo yihye shok hayamin limana. So and using the phrase
חלק Chelek a portion in that context could refer to the idea
of a portion in the קרבנות. Korbanot. That's how the רמב"ם Rambam
reads it. The רמב"ם Rambam says if a כהן Kohen does not
agree to one of the עבודות Avodot he's not entitled to a
portion of the קרבנות. Korbanot. It does not actually say that he's
restricted from doing the עבודה. Avoda. However in the תוספתא Tosefta it
sounds like he's restricted from doing the עבודה Avoda and it says
that by a לוי Levi as well and the רמב"ם Rambam actually
פוסק Paskens that by a לוי Levi but not by a כהן.
Kohen. So if you would like to know how Rav Soloveitchik solves
that problem I alluded to it or I mentioned it very quickly
yesterday although not so precisely anyway I posted that. So that's in
terms of רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position that you have to a
כהן Kohen has to agree to all of the עבודות Avodot of
the כהונה Kehuna of which we have יציקה. Yetzika. So now we
have this position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that יציקה Yetzika and
בלילה Belila and these things that precede קמיצה Kmitza are done by
a כהן Kohen and the חכמים Chachamim say they do not need
a כהן. Kohen. So now let's take a look at where the
גמרא Gemara goes with it. So again three lines from the bottom
on י"ח עמוד ב' Yud-Chet Amud Beis
מאי טעמא דרבנן Mai Ta'ama D'rabbanan middle of the line what's the
reasoning of the rabbis. אמר קרא Amar Kra the פסוק Pasuk says
ויצק עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה Veyatzak aleha shemen u'natan aleha levona
and then it says והביאה אל בני אהרן הכהנים vehevia el bnei
Aharon hakohanim and then וקמץ משם. vekamatz misham. So it says he
the owner shall pour on it oil and put on it frankincense
and bring it to the priest to בני אהרן Bnei Aharon and
then they וקמץ משם. vekamatz misham. They
actually literally the פסוק Pasuk actually could sound like even he does
וקמץ משם vekamatz misham but anyway since בני אהרן Bnei Aharon is
plural and he is singular but minimally the כהנים Kohanim are only
introduced prior to the קמיצה. Kmitza. So from there we made the
very reasonable position right at the moment of the קמיצה Kmitza so
we make the reasonable
conclusion קמיצה ואילך מצות כהונה Kmitza va'eilach mitzvat kehuna that the כהנים
Kohanim are only introduced at the moment of קמיצה. Kmitza. Prior to
that a non-כהן Kohen can do anything. So לימוד Limud on יציקה
Yetzika and בלילה Belila so the יציקה Yetzika of the oil actually
if the order is reversed because the יציקה Yetzika is after it's
mixed. בלילה Belila is the mixing with the oil and then after
everything is mixed in there's an additional pouring anyway those two things
are כשר Kasher בזר Bezar can be done by a non-כהן. Kohen.
Very nice read of the פסוק. Pasuk. How does רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon disagree? So the גמרא Gemara says רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon בני
אהרן הכהנים bnei Aharon hakohanim he says when the פסוק Pasuk says
the sons of Aaron the priests מקרא נדרש לפניו ולאחריו Mikra nidrash
lefanav u'l'achara that phrase בני אהרן הכהנים bnei Aharon hakohanim goes not
only forward but backward. So he reads it
as ויצק עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה והביאה בני אהרן הכהנים veyatzak
aleha shemen u'natan aleha levona vehevia bnei Aharon hakohanim which is a
little funny because it even says והביאה vehevia which sounds like they
didn't have it yet but it says he has already brought it
somehow to בני אהרן הכהנים bnei Aharon hakohanim and the בני אהרן
הכהנים bnei Aharon hakohanim did the יציקה Yetzika and the בלילה. Belila.
Very harder to read of the פסוק Pasuk but he claims that
all of it centers around בני אהרן הכהנים. bnei Aharon hakohanim. The
גמרא Gemara is eventually going to reject this read not just because
it's a hard פשט Pshat read but because of another position of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So let's take a look.
Stepping it up a little bit better.
Yeah.
Do we need another גמרא? Gemara? No we're good.
Okay so
says והתניא Vehatanya so now two lines from the top י"ט עמוד
א' Yud-Tet Amud Alef last word did we not teach in a
ברייתא Baraisa ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת באצבעו velakach hakohen midam hachatat be'etzba'o
so now what we really are going oh I'm sorry I skipped
a line last word of the first line וסבר רבי שמעון מקרא
נדרש לפניו ולאחריו Vesavar Rabbi Shimon mikra nidrash lefanav u'l'achara so the
גמרא's Gemara objection now is not going to be based on פשט
Pshat of the פסוק Pasuk but about whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
really buys into this hermeneutic principle. Is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon really
prepared to interpret a פסוק Pasuk based on a middle phrase even
when that phrase clearly is referring to the latter half of the
verse not the first half of the verse and now we're going
to see that he does not say
that. So let's take a look. So we're going to now discuss
a case not this, not directly relevant but to show
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon way he makes this דרשה. drasha. ותניא, Vtanya,
we taught in the ברייתא, braita, ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת באצבעו, v'lakach
hakohen midam hachattat b'etzbo, the כהן kohen shall take from the blood
of the חטאת chattat with his finger, ונתן על קרנות המזבח, venatan
al kornot hamizbeach,
and he will put it on the corners of the altar. So
that's a straight פסוק pasuk about how the blood of a חטאת
chattat is placed. Now you will remember that אצבעו etzbo according to
the גמרא Gemara tells us that we're using your right hand, right,
because it was learned out from the מצורע metzora that אצבע etzba
means right and so on. So the ברייתא braita has the following
דרשה. drasha. It says
באצבעו ולקח, b'etzbo v'lakach, so באצבעו b'etzbo is going on the word
to take, מלמד שלא תהא קבלה אלא בימין. melamed shelo tehe kabala
ela b'yamin. So אצבע etzba signals right hand, ולקח v'lakach is the
catching of the blood, so therefore the catching of the blood you
have to use your right hand.
And then the reading the verse starting at the word אצבע, etzba,
באצבעו ונתן, b'etzbo v'natan, מלמד שלא תהא נתינה אלא בימין, melamed shelo
tehe netina ela b'yamin, and also the placing has to be with
an אצבע etzba meaning with the right hand. So you have to
use the right hand for the catching and the placing. Now actually,
the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is that אצבע etzba does
go on both verbs, but the verb of ולקח v'lakach does not
mean the way the גמרא's Gemara treating it, meaning ולקח הכהן מדם
החטאת באצבעו v'lakach hakohen midam hachattat b'etzbo means you've already have the
blood caught in the vessel, you dip your finger in, ונתן. venatan.
So פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is that the finger's going
on both verbs, you dip your finger in and then you place
it on the corners. But what the גמרא Gemara is doing is
it's reading the word ולקח v'lakach to be the catching of the
blood, and now getting both the catching and the placing are not
with the finger literally, but with the right hand.
Right, because אצבע etzba really does mean finger. Right. And it's a
finger or a hand as the case may be. Right.
So the גמרא Gemara is reading ולקח v'lakach not to mean to
dip, but to mean to catch, and identifying אצבע etzba as just
a way of signaling right, not really signaling finger, unless you're very
adept and can catch a bowl with your finger. Okay, anyway, so
the גמרא Gemara says, that's the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. אמר רבי
שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagreed, וכי נאמר יד
בקבלה? v'chi ne'emar yad b'kabala? Does it really say hand with the
קבלה kabala catching? Now, of course, what could he be questioning? He
could be questioning the fact that it says אצבע, etzba, not יד.
yad. He could be questioning so you can't really say the verb
is talking about catching.
That's a reasonable read of what he said. But anyway, let's read
what he says. He says, come on, it's not saying hand by
catching, הואיל ולא נאמר יד בקבלה, ho'il v'lo ne'emar yad b'kabala, since
it doesn't say it, קיבל בשמאל כשר, kibel bismol kasher, you could
really do the קבלת הדם kabala'at hadam with your left hand. Now,
so what are they debating? So again, simple sense is that they're
debating whether you could reasonably read the פסוק pasuk of אצבע etzba
to be referring to the catching of the blood as opposed to
the dipping of the finger in the blood. But the גמרא Gemara
doesn't say that. ואמר אביי, V'amar Abaye, and אביי Abaye explained over
there, במקרא נדרש לפניו ולאחריו
קמיפלגי, b'mikra nidrash l'fanav ul'acharav kamifligi, that the debate is whether you
can read the word אצבע etzba back to the first half of
the פסוק. pasuk. So presumably the way אביי Abaye framed it, clearly
you could have understood it otherwise, ולקח הכהן v'lakach hakohen everybody understands
that that means catching the blood. But now the חכמים Chachamim say
ולקח הכהן באצבעו, v'lakach hakohen b'etzbo, catch with the אצבע, etzba, not
literally catch with the אצבע, etzba, but the catching is with the
right hand. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, give me a break,
באצבעו b'etzbo only refers to the second half of the פסוק, pasuk,
ולקח הכהן, v'lakach hakohen, באצבעו ונתן. b'etzbo v'natan. Now of course this
is quite bizarre, right, because here the פשט pshat of the פסוק
pasuk is that אצבע etzba is referring to both verbs in the
פסוק. pasuk. But nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is somehow persuaded by this
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not say that, meaning רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says you only read the word forward not backward. And
if that's true in this case of the dipping of the blood,
where context actually suggests you read it both ways, certainly he should
agree by the מנחה. mincha. Okay, so it was a little funny
how the גמרא Gemara framed that debate, but the upshot is the
גמרא Gemara is convinced that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you read
the פסוק pasuk forwards, you do not read the פסוק pasuk forwards
and backwards. So why does he agree, why does he not take
the חכמים's Chachamim very reasonable position that a מנחה mincha the כהנים
kohanim only starts from the act of קמיצה? kmitza?
That's also the question on the רבנן, Rabbanan, no? Because the רבנן
Rabbanan over here say מהקמיצה ואילך, mi'kmitza v'eilech, and the רבנן Rabbanan
over there they say לפניו ולאחריו. l'fanav ul'acharav.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Unless they're different people. No, I think
רש״י Rashi says—one minute—no, that's a later רש״י. Rashi. I mean, again,
what I would say is that that פסוק pasuk is much more
פשט pshat that it's going, that word אצבע etzba is going on
both verbs.
Right, but according to אביי Abaye you're saying it has nothing to
do with—well,
no, what אביי Abaye is saying that even when it's פשט, pshat,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not use it backward. So certainly he
wouldn't use it backward here. So it actually does work. So you're
saying אלא הכא היינו טעמא דרבי שמעון, ela hacha haynu ta'ama d'Rabbi
Shimon, you're right. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon normally would not apply the
word backward. But here's the reason of רבי שמעון: Rabbi Shimon: והביא,
v'hevia, and he shall bring it, ו מוסיף על ענין ראשון. vav
mosif al inyan rishon.
So if you go back to the פסוק pasuk it says... ויצק
עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה והביא בני אהרן הכהנים. Vayatzak aleha shemen
venatan aleha levonah ve'hevi bnei Aharon hakohanim.
So since it says and he shall bring it to the sons
of Aaron the כהנים, kohanim, so the and is connecting the bringing
it to the כהנים kohanim with the mixing and the pouring of
the oil. So it means that it's sort of seeing it all
more or less at the same time. So the ו' vav connects
it all and brings the כהנים kohanim into the picture even in
the first half of the פסוק. posuk. So normally רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would not apply the כהנים kohanim back to the first half,
but because of the linking ו' vav he does. All right, so
if people are getting a little bit lost or a little bored
with the technical aspects, hang in there. Basically the גמרא Gemara is
saying that why does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say that a כהן
kohen has to do the stuff before the קמיצה? kemitza? The פסוק
posuk only mentions the כהנים kohanim starting at the קמיצה. kemitza. And
the answer right now is the ו'. vav. והביא, Ve'hevi, when it
mentions the כהנים, kohanim, connects it to the earlier stages. I don't
know, period. והביא. Ve'hevi. I don't know. Anyway,
so the גמרא Gemara says וסבר רבי שמעון ו' מוסיף על עניין
ראשון? V'savar Rabbi Shimon vav mosif al inyan rishon?
Does
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say that if you introduce a ו' vav
you apply it earlier? אלא מעתה דכתיב ושחט את בן הבקר והקריבו
בני אהרן הכהנים את הדם וזרקו את הדם על המזבח סביב. Ela
me'ata d'chtiv veshachat et ben habakar vehikrivu bnei Aharon hakohanim et hadam
vezarku et hadam al hamizbe'ach saviv.
So here's where it talks about you slaughter a normal animal sacrifice:
you slaughter it, and then the בני אהרן Bnei Aharon take the
blood and sprinkle the blood. So again, since בני אהרן Bnei Aharon
are introduced only after the שחיטה, sh'chitah, we know that the earlier
stages are done or can be done by a non-כהן. kohen. So
we say מקבלה ואילך מצות כהונה—only Mi'kabala ve'eilach mitzvat kehunah from the
capturing of the blood where it says והקריבו vehikrivu does the כהן
kohen get introduced. ללמד על שחיטה שכשירה
בזר—so Lelamed al sh'chitah she'kesherah be'zar the שחיטה sh'chitah can be done
even by a non-כהן. kohen. Now, ואילו לרבי שמעון ו' מוסיף על
עניין ראשון, Ve'ilu l'Rabbi Shimon vav mosif al inyan rishon, but according
to you which רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon once you introduce the ו'
vav you bring the כהנים kohanim earlier into the פסוק, posuk, so
שחיטה הכא נמי תהא פסולה? sh'chitah hacha nami tehei psulah?
Would you say that שחיטה sh'chitah would be not כשר kosher with
a non-כהן? kohen? Okay, which is a very reasonable point. It says
look, we got two פסוקים. psukim. Both פסוקים psukim introduce the כהן,
kohen, one by an animal קרבן, korban, one by a מנחה. mincha.
Both פסוקים psukim only introduce the כהנים kohanim at a certain stage.
By an animal קרבן korban it says ושחט את בן הבקר והקריבו
בני אהרן. Veshachat et ben habakar vehikrivu bnei Aharon. So
בני אהרן Bnei Aharon are only introduced after the שחיטה. sh'chitah. The
other פסוק posuk says ויצק עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה והביא בני
אהרן. Vayatzak aleha shemen venatan aleha levonah ve'hevi bnei Aharon. The בני
אהרן Bnei Aharon are only introduced after you've mixed it with oil
and put on the לבונה. levonah. So the גמרא Gemara is making
a very simple point. If everybody agrees that by שחיטה sh'chitah it
can be done by a non-כהן kohen because בני אהרן Bnei Aharon
are only introduced in the פסוק posuk after שחיטה, sh'chitah, why not
say, why would anybody disagree by a מנחה? mincha? By a מנחה
mincha as well, בני אהרן Bnei Aharon are only introduced after the
oil has been mixed and the לבונה levonah has been placed on.
You're going to tell me you've got an extra ו' vav in
this פסוק? posuk? You have the ו' vav in the other פסוק
posuk as well. So why would רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagree by
a מנחה? mincha? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
שאני
התם—so Shani hatam line שאני התם shani hatam about 15 lines down.
שאני התם—it's Shani hatam different there—דאמר קרא וסמך ושחט. de'amar kra vesamach
veshachat.
The beginning of the פסוק posuk is clearly talking about the owners.
It says וסמך ידו על ראש העולה—was Vesamach yado al rosh ha'olah
that the פסוק? posuk? על ראש קרבנו. al rosh korbano. Ah, וסמך
ידו על ראש קרבנו. Vesamach yado al rosh korbano.
And then it says ושחט veshachat and he slaughtered את בן הבקר.
et ben habakar. So since it says you put your hand on
your קרבן, korban, clearly the beginning of the פסוק posuk is talking
about the owner. So when it says ושחט veshachat we have to
read it as the owner. But when it talks about the מנחה,
mincha, it's not clear who the person is, so he will choose
to read that the whole פסוק posuk is about the כהן. kohen.
Okay, so that's why it's different.
But it is completely ambiguous, the פסוק. posuk. I mean, here I
think isn't the פסוק posuk clear? The פסוק posuk says ויצק ונתן
והביא בני אהרן. Vayatzak venatan ve'hevi bnei Aharon. Actually
the earlier פסוק posuk does make it clear. It says a person
brings a קרבן מנחה להשם. korban mincha l'Hashem. נפש כי תקריב
קרבן
מנחה להשם. Nefesh ki takriv korban mincha l'Hashem. Yeah, I think the
פסוק posuk is actually quite clear, the פשט pshat of the פסוק.
posuk. נפש כי תקריב. Nefesh ki takriv. נפש כי תקריב
קרבן
מנחה להשם סולת יהיה קרבנו ויצק
עליה שמן ונתן עליה לבונה והביא אל בני אהרן
הכהנים.
Nefesh ki takriv korban mincha
l'Hashem solet yihiyeh korbano vayatzak aleha shemen venatan aleha levonah ve'hevi el
bnei Aharon hakohanim. So פשט pshat of the פסוק posuk is unquestionably
you're bringing your מנחה, mincha, you mix it with oil, you put
on the לבונה, levonah, then you bring it to the כהן. kohen.
Okay, so what רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's answer is,
there it does not immediately juxtapose the fact that it's you. It
could be נפש כי תקריב קרבן מנחה להשם, Nefesh ki takriv korban
mincha l'Hashem, סולת יהיה קרבנו, solet yihiyeh korbano, period. ויצק עליה הכהן
Vayatzak aleha hakohen and the כהן kohen is ויצק עליה שמן, vayatzak
aleha shemen, right?
So even though it didn't introduce a new subject explicitly, it could
be implicit that it's the כהן. kohen. As opposed to by the
animal, right, that's how he's reading it, as opposed to the animal
where it says וסמך ידו על ראש קרבנו, vesamach yado al rosh
korbano, it's very clear that those actions are done by the owner.
So that is how Rabbi Shimon is reading it. So let's take
a look.
Okay,
so where is it? וסמך ושחט. V'samach V'shachat. מסמיך בזרה ושחיטה בזרה.
Masmich b'zarah v'shchitah b'zarah.
So the Gemara says if that's true, אם סמיכה בבעלים, im smichah
b'be'alim, if you really want to insist that because of the juxtaposition
of סמיכה ושחיטה, smichah v'shchitah, then I'll take it to one step
further. Why don't we say the same way סמיכה smichah has to
be only the owners, line starting with the word בבעלים, b'be'alim, אף
שחיטה בבעלים. af shchitah b'be'alim. So maybe the שחיטה shchitah is not
only that it's kosher with a non-כהן, Kohein, maybe it must be
done by the owners specifically. So you can't make an argument from
the connection to the word סמיכה smichah because then you would have
to go to reductio ad absurdum and you'd have to say that
the owners have to do the שחיטה shchitah and we never say
that.
Well, we know as a general principle that it's not true. So
the Gemara says no, ההוא לא מצי אמרת. hahu lo matzi amrat.
That we know we would never get to that conclusion that the
owners have to do the שחיטה. shchitah. קל וחומר, Kal v'chomer,
we make a קל וחומר kal v'chomer that the owners don't have
to do the שחיטה. shchitah. Here's the קל וחומר: kal v'chomer: ומה
זריקה דעיקר כפרה לא בעי בעלים, U'mah zrikah d'ikar kaparah lo ba'ei
be'alim, when it comes to the sprinkling of the blood which is
the real atonement of the animal, that does not have to be
done by the owners, that can be done by a כהן. Kohein.
שחיטה דלאו עיקר כפרה, shchitah d'lav ikar kaparah, שחיטה shchitah which is
not the central act of achieving atonement, לא כל שכן lo kol
shekein certainly it should not require a כהן. Kohein.
Right,
exactly, which is exactly the problem of this whole argument that you
could say the קרבן korban has to be done either by the
owners or by the כהנים, Kohanim, not by some unrelated third party.
Right? So that's exactly the point. So סמיכה ושחיטה smichah v'shchitah could
be the owners, the rest could be the fact that you allow
a כהן Kohein doesn't mean that you're going to allow a third
party. So the Gemara is going to say
so
that's what the Gemara's answer is.
וכי תימא, V'chi teima, lest you say no that's not a good
proof, אין דנין אפשר משאי אפשר. ein danin efshar mish'ee efshar. You
can't compare a case where you have options to a case you
don't have options. When it comes to the זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam,
it has to be somebody that's not the owner because it requires
a כהן. Kohein. But when it comes to something that a non-כהן
Kohein is kosher with, שחיטה shchitah or סמיכה, smichah, so maybe I
should say if we allow a non-כהן, Kohein, we will still require
that the owner, meaning the fundamental principle is we want the owner.
At a certain stage you can't have the owner so you have
to use the כהנים. Kohanim. But when you can have the owner,
we want only the owner. Okay? So if you want to make
the argument, connect the שחיטה shchitah to סמיכה, smichah, why not argue
that the owner has to do the שחיטה? shchitah? And we never
say that. So the Gemara says no, here would be my answer.
גלי רחמנא ביום הכפורים, Gali rachmana b'Yom HaKippurim, the Torah makes it
clear on Yom Kippur: ושחט את פר החטאת אשר לו, v'shachat et
par hachatat asher lo, that Aaron the כהן גדול Kohein Gadol slaughters
the פר החטאת par hachatat which is his. So there it emphasizes
he's slaughtering. מכלל דשחיטה דעלמא לא בעינן בעלים, Michlal d'shchitah d'alma lo
ba'inan be'alim, which tells you that normal שחיטה, shchitah, only on Yom
Kippur is there a special requirement that he slaughters his own animal,
normally שחיטה shchitah you do not have to be the owner. Of
course Tosafot says is it really clear that on Yom Kippur it
would be פסול pasul if a non-כהן גדול Kohein Gadol did the
שחיטה? shchitah? But okay, that's a different question. Anyway, the Gemara is
saying no, we already know a principle that שחיטה shchitah does not
require owners. So what now? How do we even get that from
Yom Kippur? Is that the exception? Yes, somehow we learned that that's
the exception. Now how do we learn it's the exception and not
the rule? I
don't because otherwise it would be שני כתובים הבאים כאחד, shnei ketuvim
habaim k'echad, then you wouldn't have to repeat it over in the
other case. But it's a good question. All right, so anyway what
is Rabbi Shimon's position? Rabbi Shimon's position is that the פסוק pasuk
although it is talking about the owner by the מנחה, mincha, when
it gets to the mixing of the oil, it is somewhat ambiguous
and maybe you could say at that stage we're already assuming a
כהן. Kohein. When it gets to the animal sacrifice, the שחיטה shchitah
and then the קבלה, kabbalah, it makes it very clear we were
talking about the owner because it says וסמך ידו על ראש קרבנו.
v'samach yado al rosh korbano. And therefore we're not going to go
so far to say you need the owner by שחיטה, shchitah, we
already know it's not limited to the owner, but at least we
will be clear that we're talking about a non-כהן Kohein until that
moment. Okay, so that's where Rabbi Shimon gets his idea that by
מנחה mincha you require a כהן. Kohein. All right, so now we
continue. אמר רב, Amar Rav, now
so we've understood now the debate of Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים
Chachamim and now we are going to do a little bit, a
very quick revisiting of some issues that we had in זבחים Zevachim
about how do we know when anything is מעכב. me'akeiv. This is
really going on the whole theme of the Mishnah. We're really leaving
Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים. Chachamim. That was a question of whether
you need a כהן. Kohein. The theme of our Mishnah is the
following things: if you don't do them, the מנחה mincha is still
good: יציקה, yetzika, בלילה, belila, תנופה, tnufa, whole big list. Okay, so
we said יציקה yetzika you do have to do, and it just
doesn't need a כהן. Kohein. But basically the list is saying if
you don't do these things it's still good. So the question is,
why should we say you don't need it? Right? If the Torah
says you need it. So we get, we have this principle that
we know from זבחים Zevachim that when it comes to קרבנות, korbanot,
you need שנה עליו הכתוב לעכב. shana alav hakatuv l'akeiv. You need
the Torah to repeat it to tell you that if you don't
do it, it's invalid. Okay, it's a completely bizarre principle. Normally we
assume, right, you never say like: 'Oh, the תורה Torah says eat
מצה Matzah on פסח Pesach now it turns out it didn't say
it twice, if I don't do it, I'm still יוצא.' yotzei. Although
it did say it twice. It's not a good example. But anyway,
the point is is that here, on the one hand of all
the places in the תורה, Torah, the greatest, you know, wealth of
details of exactly how everything is done, you know to the point
that it starts feeling a little repetitive when you're hearing these פרשיות
parshiot during these weeks, you know is by the קרבנות. korbanot. So
for anything you might think oh my god the תורה Torah is
going out of its way to mention every little detail, everything is
מעכב. me'akeiv. But חז"ל Chazal understood differently. Maybe they missed it, in
fact not everything is מעכב. me'akeiv.
Or if everything was מעכב, me'akeiv, why does the תורה Torah have
to constantly repeat itself, you know, and therefore they understood that you
can make a number of mistakes and could still be כשר kasher
and you need the תורה Torah to repeat itself to tell you
what's מעכב. me'akeiv. That explains our משנה mishna why so many of
these parts of the מצוה mitzvah are not a problem because they
were not things that were repeated. So that's what we're going to
look at right now. Let's take a look.
אמר רב, Amar Rav, says רב, Rav,
כל מקום שנאמר תורה וחוקה, kol makom shene'emar Torah vechukah, so it's
line starting with the word תורה, Torah, about the halfway down, every
time the תורה Torah says תורה Torah and חוק, chok, or what
he means both תורה Torah and חוקה, chukah, אינו אלא לעכב. eino
ela l'akeiv. It's
telling you that what's going to follow is מעכב, me'akeiv, means if
you don't do it, it's invalid. So the גמרא Gemara now asks,
קא סלקא דעתך תרתי בעי. kasalka daitach tarti ba'ya. We assume when
he said תורה Torah and חוקה chukah he means that you need
the תורה Torah to say both in order to say it's מעכב.
me'akeiv. כדכתיב, kichtiv, and we do have that once, זאת חקת התורה.
zot chukat hatorah. You see it in פרשת פרה. Parshat Parah. This
is the חוקה chukah of the תורה Torah and it tells you
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, so it says חוק chok and תורה, Torah,
you need to do exactly this ritual. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara is going to say one minute, והרי נזיר, veharei nazir, when
it comes to the נזיר nazir and him ending his נזירות, nezirus,
דלא כתיבא ביה אלא תורה, delo ksiva bei ela Torah, זאת תורת
הנזיר. zot torat hanazir. ואמר רב, Ve'amar Rav, and רב Rav says,
תנופה בנזיר מעכבא. tenufah benazir me'akva.
Even what we normally assume is a part of the עבודה avodah
that is not מעכב, me'akeiv, the waving of the קרבן, korban, that's
usually like a prime example of things that if you don't do
it's still good, by the נזיר nazir it's מעכב. me'akeiv. So the
נזיר nazir it says, you know, you take the- I forget- you
take its hair and you take whatever, let's
look.
הזרוע בשלה,
hazroa beshela, right, exactly, all these parts of the שלמים. shelamim. שלמים
shelamim is like the central קרבן korban although the תורה Torah says
פרשת- parshat ועשה את זבח השלמים וגילח הנזיר פתח אהל מועד ולקח
את שער ראש נזרו. ve'asah es zevach shelamim vegillach hanazir pesach ohel
mo'ed velakach es se'ar rosh nizro. You take the hair, ונתן על
האש, venasan al ha'eish, put it on the fire, ולקח הכהן את
הזרוע בשלה מן האיל, velakach hakohein es hazroa beshela min ha'ayil, you
take a cooked arm from the ram of the שלמים, shelamim, וחלת
מצה אחת מן הסל ורקיק מצה אחד, vechallat matzah achat min hasal
urekik matzah echad, and one of the breads or of each type
of bread, נתן על כפי הנזיר, nasan al kapei hanazir, you put
it on the hands of the נזיר, nazir, והניף אותם הכהן, vehinif
osam hakohein, and you wave them. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says that although that's just תנופה, tenufah, that
is מעכב. me'akeiv.
So it explains that the word תורה Torah that appeared at the
beginning, or at the beginning
of
the whole...
exactly, right. But even so, we're assuming you need both תורה Torah
and חוקה.
chukah. So the- so again, my favorite פסוק pasuk there was the
גמרא Gemara always conveniently
ignores...
Okay, for what? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says: how could it be מעכב me'akeiv if it doesn't
say both תורה Torah and חוקה? chukah? So it says שאני התם,
shani hasam, כיוון דכתיב כן יעשה על תורת נזרו, kivan dichtsiv kein
ye'aseh al torat nizro,
so he shall do, that's, you know, underscoring it, so it's actually
like the גמרא Gemara says כמאן דכתיבא ביה חוקה דמי. keman dichtsiva
bei chukah dami. It's like it says also חוקה, chukah, it's like
reiterates this is the way you do it, that means you really
have to do it exactly this way.
So you need the word תורה Torah but then you have other
ways to re-emphasize it.
You need it to be double- right, exactly, you need to get
double emphasis. So now let's keep on going. והרי תודה, veharei todah,
how about the תודה? todah? דלא כתיבא ביה אלא תורה, delo ksiva
bei ela Torah, it only says תורה Torah by the תודה, todah,
it says וזאת תורת זבח השלמים אשר יקריב להשם אם על תודה
יקריבנו. vezot torat zevach hashelamim asher yakriv l'Hashem im al todah yakrivenu.
ותנן, utnan, and we taught in the משנה, mishna, ארבע שבתודה, arba
shebatodah,
the four different types of loaves that you bring with the תודה,
todah, מעכבין זה את זה, me'akvin zeh es zeh, if you don't
have one of the loaves then all the others are not valid,
you need all four types. So where do you get that idea
that everything is מעכב me'akeiv if it only says תורה? Torah? So
שאני תודה דאיתקיש לנזיר. shani todah de'itkaish lenazir. No, because the תודה
todah is connected to a נזיר, nazir, because the תודה todah is
a type of a שלמים, shelamim, and it says by the נזיר
nazir דכתיב
על זבח תודת שלמיו, dichtsiv al zevach todat shelamav, that you should-
that's not by the נזיר, nazir, by the תודה todah you should
bring these loaves with the תודה todah of his שלמיו, shelamav, ואמר
מר, ve'amar mar, שלמיו לרבות שלמי נזיר. shelamav lerabot shalmei nazir.
That that includes even the שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir for a particular
הלכה. halakha. Not for this הלכה, halakha, we learn out a particular
thing of the שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir from a תודה. todah. But
once we connect the תודה todah to the שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir
we say the same way the שלמי נזיר shalmei nazir is מעכב,
me'akeiv, a תודה todah everything is
מעכב. me'akeiv. So far we've gotten over those two hurdles והרי מצורע
*ve'harei metzora* how about the מצורע *metzora* ולא כתיב ביה אלא Ella,
תורה Torah *velo ktiv bei ela torah* it always says תורה Torah
*torah* by the מצורע *metzora* זאת תהיה תורת המצורע ביום טהרתו והובא
אל הכהן *zot tihye torat hametzora beyom taharato vehuva el hacohen* ולא
כתיב ביה אלא תורה Torah *velo ktiv bei ela torah* ותנן ארבעה
מינים שבמצורע *v'tnan arba'ah minim shebametzora* this is very different than the
four types of the bread of the we just said of the
שלמים *shlamim* the four מינים *minim* of the מצורע *metzora* is ולקח
הכהן עץ ארז ואזוב ושני תולעת *velakach hacohen etz erez ve'ezov ushni
tola'at* right actually that's I'm quoting the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* by וזאת
תהיה *vezot tihye* but it's the same thing. Anyway by the מצורע
*metzora* you slaughter a bird into a vessel and you dip this
in the blood. So you need all those four things. You need
the עץ ארז *etz erez* with the cedar wood, the אזוב *ezov*
hyssop, the red you know string and you need to dip it
into the blood of the bird. You need all those things. Okay
then it doesn't say the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* doesn't repeat repeat it
or say excuse me חוק *chok* to tell you it needs everything.
So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says no שאני התם *shani hatam* there's
different כיון דכתיב De'khitiv: ביה *keivan dechtiv bei* since it says there
זאת תהיה תורת המצורע *zot tihye torat hametzora* this shall be meaning
it shall be this way. So the word תהיה *tihye* is re-emphasizing
כמאן דכתיב dechtiv: ביה חוק דמי *keman dechtiv bei chok dami* it's
like it said חוק *chok*. So now we are sticking to our
you know claim that it's not enough that the תורה Torah *torah*
just says תורה Torah *torah* or חוק *chok*. It has to say
תורה Torah *torah* and maybe it doesn't need חוק *chok* but it
needs to re you know underscore it to tell you it's מעכב
meakev *me'akev* and every place that it's מעכב meakev. *me'akev* it's been
underscored. But now we're going to say one minute והרי יום הכיפורים
*ve'harei yom hakippurim* דלא כתיב ביה אלא חוק *delo ktiv bei ela
chok* until now we've been having times that it only says תורה
Torah *torah*. By יום כיפור *yom kippur* it only says חוק *chok*.
What does it say by יום כיפור *yom kippur*? It says חוקת
עולם
לדורותיכם *chukat olam ledoroteichem*
what the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* רש״י *rashi*
quotes it והיתה לכם לחוקת עולם בחודש השביעי *vehayeta lachem lechukat olam
bachodesh hashevi'i* what והיתה לכם לחוקת עולם בחודש השביעי בעשור לחודש תענו
את נפשותיכם וכל מלאכה לא תעשו *vehayeta lachem lechukat olam bachodesh hashevi'i
be'asor lachodesh ta'anu et nafshoteichem vechol melacha lo ta'asu* is that that
one? Okay anyway it's and set the very end of אחרי *acharei*
of the whole פרשה parsha, *parsha* there in אחרי מות *acharei mot*.
Were you quoting that from memory or from what? You were looking
at רש״י *rashi*. Okay let me quote it in the context. Okay
והיתה זאת
לכם
*vehayeta zot lachem* at the very last פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of the
עבודה avoda *avodah* והיתה זאת לכם לחוקת עולם לכפר על בני ישראל
מכל חטאתם אחת בשנה ויעש כאשר צוה ה׳ את משה *vehayeta zot
lachem lechukat olam lachaper al bnei yisrael mikol chatatam achat bashana vaya'as
ka'asher tziva Hashem et moshe*. Okay so there it says חוק *chok*
it does not say תורה Torah *torah*. Here's the question first of
all.
there's another one about it says והיתה לכם בחודש השביעי
*vehayeta lachem bachodesh hashevi'i* you know there you know. Okay anyway כתיב
והיתה לכם לחוקת עולם בחודש השביעי בעשור לחודש *ktiv vehayeta lachem lechukat
olam bachodesh hashevi'i be'asor lachodesh* what does Izzy use as a source?
I don't know maybe it says it twice. It says והיתה זאת
לכם לחוקת עולם לכפר על בני ישראל מכל חטאתם אחת בשנה *vehayeta
zot
lachem lechukat olam lachaper al bnei yisrael mikol chatatam achat bashana* and
it doesn't say בחודש השביעי *bachodesh hashevi'i*.
Oh it says it twice.
Earlier it says והיתה לכם לחוקת עולם בחודש השביעי בעשור לחודש *vehayeta
lachem lechukat olam bachodesh hashevi'i be'asor lachodesh*
right. Okay let's take a look.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says והרי יום הכיפורים דלא כתיב
ביה אלא חוק *ve'harei yom hakippurim delo ktiv bei ela chok* it
only says חוק *chok* דתנן שני שעירי יום הכיפורים מעכבין זה את
זה *detnan shnei se'irei yom hakippurim me'akvin zeh et zeh* that if
you the two goats are מעכב meakev. *me'akev* one the other and
if you don't have one you can't bring the other. So how
do you learn this principle of מעכב meakev. *me'akev*? Now Michael makes
a good point, why didn't it say that it says חוק *chok*
twice? Maybe you'd understand you need a different type of a word.
You can't, counting the same word twice doesn't count. It's a very
good question. Anyway the גמרא Gemara *gemara* considers that that is a
real big problem. What?
Does it say the word זאת *zot* והיתה זאת לכם
*vehayeta zot lachem*?
Ah the גמרא Gemara *gemara* though before was דורש *doresh* תהיה
*tihye*
not
זאת *zot*.
Maybe there's a different פשט pshat. *pshat* for some reason that it's
more removed.
Oh but it says והיתה
*vehayeta* and the one before did דורש *doresh* the word תהיה *tihye*
right תהיה *tihye* והיתה *vehayeta*. The פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says זאת אליכם
*zot aleichem*. It doesn't say that it's about the עינוי *inuy*. It
says לכפר על בני ישראל *lachaper al bnei yisrael*. So you would
think that that would be a reasonable... no maybe because the first
one is not like רש״י *rashi*. The first one is about the
עינוי *inuy* והיתה לכם לחוקת עולם בחודש השביעי בעשור לחודש תענו את
נפשותיכם וכל מלאכה לא תעשו *vehayeta lachem lechukat olam bachodesh hashevi'i be'asor
lachodesh ta'anu et nafshoteichem vechol melacha lo ta'asu*. So I would actually
argue that funny רש״י *rashi* picked that פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. That's about
עינוי *inuy*. The פסוק pasuk's *pasuk* about the עבודה avoda *avodah* is
the last פסוק pasuk's *pasuk* and that says לכפר על בני ישראל
אחת בשנה *lachaper al bnei yisrael
achat bashana*. Okay anyway so the גמרא Gemara *gemara* she asks a
question. Here it's חוק *chok* and we only says חוק *chok* and
we say it's מעכב meakev? *me'akev*. So what does the גמרא Gemara
*gemara* say?
אלא *ela* rather says the גמרא Gemara *gemara* או תורה Torah או
חוקה *o torah o chukah*. You're right you don't need both. Either
saying תורה Torah *torah* or חוקה *chukah* is enough to taste מעכב
meakev. *me'akev*. And now comes Michael's favorite פסוק pasuk *pasuk* והרי שאר
קרבנות דכתיב de-chtiv, בהו תורה Torah *ve'harei shear korbanot dechtiv behu torah*.
It says תורה *torah* by all the קרבנות *korbanot* right זאת התורה
לעולה למנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמילואים *zot hatorah la'olah lamincha velachatat vela'asham velamilu'im*
right? So it says it by all of the קרבנות *korbanot* ולא
מעכבי *velo me'akvei* and we never say that by all the קרבנות
*korbanot* every single detail is מעכב meakev. *me'akev*. So the word תורה
*torah* by itself can't do it. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says
all right you're right תורה ובעי חוקה חוקה ולא בעי תורה *torah
uva'ei chukah chukah velo ba'ei torah*. The
word
תורה *torah* by itself is
not enough. actually a little imprecise. It needs to say תורה *Torah*
in an emphasized or underscored way, so we have the repetition or
the תהיה *tihiyeh* etc. before. And if it says חוק *chok*, that's
enough to say that you need to do every detail exactly that
way, that's the case of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. Alright, so the
גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says, now that we've got our principle figured out,
the purpose of all of that was to figure out our משנה
mishna *Mishnah*. Because our משנה mishna *Mishnah* says a whole list of
things that are not מעכב meakev. *me'akev* by a מנחה Mincha *minchah*,
and we want to figure out why it's בדיעבד bedieved, *bedi'avad* if
you have a מנחה Mincha *minchah*. So, זאת תורת המנחה *Zot torat
haminchah*, okay. So now we've said that if it says חוק *chok*,
that's enough to tell us that you need every detail. So let's
look if we can explain our משנה mishna *Mishnah*. Okay, so let's
take a look. תורה
בעי
חוקה וחוקה לא
בעי תורה *Torah ba'ei chukah vechukah lo ba'ei Torah*. והא תורה וחוקה
קאמר *Veha Torah vechukah ka'amar*. Didn't you say you need it to
say תורה *Torah* and חוקה *chukah*? הכי קאמר *Hachi ka'amar*, this is
what it means. אף על גב דכתיב תורה *Af al gav dechtiv
Torah*, even if it says תורה *Torah*, אי כתיב חוקה *i ktiv
chukah* אין ein, *in*, ואי לא לא *vei lo lo*. So in
the end it's all about חוק *chok*. But it's not really all
about חוק *chok* because תורה *Torah* reemphasized also means that it's מעכב
meakev. *me'akev*. Now let's look at our משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. Okay, עשרי
מנחה mincha *Asrei minchah*, when it comes to a מנחה mincha, *minchah*,
דכתיב ביה חוקה *dechtiv beih chukah*. It says חוקה *chukah*, as Michael
pointed out. It says what's the פסוק *pasuk* Michael? Yeah, כל זכר
בבני אהרן Aharon יאכלנה חוק עולם *Kol zachar bivnei Aharon yochalena chok
olam*. Right. Now that's about the eating of the מנחה mincha *minchah*,
but for now we're going to assume that that applies to the
whole מנחה mincha *minchah*. Okay, so by מנחה mincha, *minchah* it says
חוק *chok*, דכתיב ביה חוקה *dechtiv beih chukah*. ואמר רב Rav *Ve'amar
Rav*, and רב Rav *Rav* says, כל מקום שהכפיל הכתוב בתורת מנחה
mincha *Kol makom shehikpil hakatuv betorat minchah*, אינו אלא לעכב eino ela
le'akev. *eino ela le'akev*. When the תורה *Torah* repeats itself by the
מנחה mincha *minchah*, and this specifically means repeats itself in צו tzav,
*Tzav*, you know, because there seems to be a lot of repetition
between ויקרא Vayikra *Vayikra* and צו Tzav, *Tzav*. I wrote about that
a little bit, but here רבא *Rava* is saying that the point
is that when it's repeated in צו Tzav? *Tzav*, it tells you
it's מעכב meakev *me'akev*. And if it's not repeated, what it says
about a מנחה mincha *minchah* or other things in ויקרא Vayikra, *Vayikra*
is not מעכב meakev *me'akev*. So we've got a problem. It says
חוק *chok* and you're still telling me that now it has to
be repeated. Okay, כל מקום שהכפיל הכתוב בתורת מנחה mincha אינו אלא
לעכב *Kol makom shehikpil hakatuv betorat minchah eino ela le'akev*. הכפיל אין
*Hikpil in*, only if it's repeated in צו Tzav *Tzav*, לא הכפיל
לא *lo hikpil lo*, not if it's not repeated. And why is
that necessary? Doesn't it say חוק *chok*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says no. שאני התם דשינויה *Shani hatam deshinuya*, but there it's different,
דכי כתיב חוקה אאכילה כתיב *dechi ktiv chukah a'achilah ktiv*. It says
that the eating is a חוק *chok*, as רש"י Rashi *Rashi* quoted
the פסוק *pasuk*, right, כל זכר בבני אהרן Aharon יאכלנה חוק עולם
*Kol zachar bivnei Aharon yochalena chok olam*. So it's a חוק *chok*
that they have to eat it, but it's not talking about the
עבודות *avodot*. So we don't have the word חוק *chok* by the
עבודות *avodot*. So now what we know by מנחה mincha *minchah* is
מעכב meakev. *me'akev*, it's what's repeated in צו Tzav. *Tzav* that had
already been said in ויקרא Vayikra; *Vayikra*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says one minute, והרי לחם הפנים *Vaharei lechem hapanim*, when you come
to the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*, the bread on the שולחן *shulchan*,
דכי כתיב חוקה אאכילה כתיב *dechi ktiv chukah a'achilah ktiv*. It says
חוק *chok* by the eating. It says ויאכלוהו במקום קדוש כי קודש
קדשים kodashim היא לו מאשי ה' חוק עולם *Veyochaluhu bemakom kadosh ki
kodesh kodashim hi lo me'ishei Hashem chok olam*. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* quotes
the פסוק *pasuk*. So it says חוק *chok* by the eating of
the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*. ותנן *Utenan*, and we taught in the
משנה Mishna: *Mishnah*, שני סדרים מעכבין זה את זה שני בזיכין מעכבין
זה את זה *Shnei sedarim me'akvin zeh et zeh, shnei bezichin me'akvin
zeh et zeh*. The two columns of bread are מעכב meakev *me'akev*
one the other. If you don't have one column, the other column
is no good. The two little cups of the לבונה *levonah* are
מעכב meakev, *me'akev* one the other. If you don't have both, you
can't use the other. והבזיכין והסדרים מעכבין זה את זה *Vehabezichin vehasedarim
me'akvin zeh et zeh*. And if you don't have the bread, you
can't have the לבונה *levonah*. If you don't have the לבונה *levonah*,
you don't have the bread. So in simply, so bottom line is,
by the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*, everything is מעכב meakeiv, *me'akev*. Although
there it only says חוק *chok* by the eating, it doesn't say
חוק *chok* by the making or the placing. So there it seems
חוק *chok* by the eating is enough. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אלא כל היכא דכתיב אכילה אכולה מילתא כתיב *Ela kol heicha
dechtiv achilah akulah milta ktiv*. You're right. Even if it says חוק
*chok* just by the eating, it's like it says חוק *chok* by
the whole קרבן korban *korban* and everything is מעכב meakeiv. *me'akev*. So
therefore why do we need the תורה *Torah* to repeat it by
מנחה mincha *minchah*? So שאני התם דשאני *Shani hatam deshanya*, but there
it's different, דאמר קרא מגירסה ומשמנה *de'amar kra migersah umishamnah*, that you
shall take from the מנחה mincha *minchah* from the גרש *geres* which
is the flour and the oil. So from which we say גרש
ושמן מעכבין ואין דבר אחר מעכב Ve'ein davar acher me'akev, *Geres veshemen
me'akvin ve'ein davar acher me'akev*. Only by the flour and the oil,
because it says it גרש *geres*, it שמן *shemen*, which somehow means
it has to be only exactly this way, that is מעכב me'akev.
*me'akev*, other things are not מעכב me'akev? *me'akev*. So basically what the
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has a different read on but not for our
point, but basically, and I know that this is getting a little
technical, but hang in there.
So basically the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying the following, that we're
trying to figure out why in what's the rule by מנחה minchah.
*minchah*, why a lot of things are not מעכב me'akev; *me'akev*. So
the simple answer that רב Rav *Rav* says is because you need
the תורה *Torah* to repeat it in צו Tzav. *Tzav* for it
to be מעכב me'akev, *me'akev*. And anything not repeated in צו Tzav?
*Tzav* is not בדיעבד bedieved *bedi'avad* a problem. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says, oh, but didn't we say you have the idea of חוק
*chok*? And although חוק *chok* is only written on the eating, we
prove from the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* that that's a problem, that
חוק *chok* means it's מעכב me'akev *me'akev*. And the answer is yeah,
but not by a מנחה *minchah*. Since the פסוק *pasuk* emphasizes specific
things are מעכב me'akev, *me'akev*... Having the right amount of flour, the
right amount of oil, that tells us that the general rule by
מנחה, it's things are not מעכב me'akev. until the תורה repeats it.
Okay, so at least by מנחה it needs to be repeated. Now,
now we are going finally that we get our rules down, now
going to look at each עבודה avoda by the מנחה and understand
whether it's necessary or not.
ירושלמי Yerushalmi משנה Mishna somehow means
only its oil has to be full and its flour has to
be full. That's how רש"י Rashi's reads it, תוספות Tosafot, reads that
you can look at תוספות, Tosfos he reads that it actually was
a case where the תורה repeated it. Okay, it has to be
full and it means if you don't have the full amount, it's
מעכב.
me'akev And that's what we're saying.
And only if it says explicitly like it did by the flour
and the oil.
And that's
our משנה mishna that says,
do we say it's כשרה keshera though?
I know, not if you are lacking oil or flour. The full
amount of oil and full amount of flour is מעכב. Right, remember
we talked early משנה Mishnah that if it's גמר ומימעיט, gamar ve'mema'it,
etc. Okay, so let's take a look. גופא, Gufa, two lines down
from the top of the עמוד ב'. amud bet. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, רב Rav: says: כל מקום שהחזיר לך הכתוב בתורת מנחה וצו,
Kol makom shehechezir lecha hakatuv betorat mincha ve'tzav, אינו אלא לעכב.
Whenever the תורה repeats something by a מנחה and צו, Tzav that's
telling us that it's required. ושמואל אמר: U'Shmuel amar: גרש ושמן מעכבי.
Geres ve'shemen me'akvei.
No, only this פסוק גרסה ושמנה, gersah ve'shamnah, only having the right
amount of flour and the right amount of oil is מעכב. ואין
דבר אחר מעכב, nothing else. So that's a pretty radical statement. So
the גמרא says: ולשמואל אף על גב דתנא ביה קרא לא מעכב
ליה? Ve'li'Shmuel af al gav de'tana bei kra lo me'akev lei? Would
שמואל Shmuel say that even when the תורה repeats it, it's not
מעכב? It's funny, the גמרא's problem with שמואל Shmuel is not the
substantive nature of what he's saying like, oh, but that would mean
this and this and this is not מעכב. What bothers them is
the methodology. You know, one of the big principles we have by
קדשים is that when it's repeated, it's מעכב. How could שמואל Shmuel
not agree to that? So the גמרא says, alright, you're right, that's
not what he meant. אלא, here's what he means. כל היכא דתנא
ביה קרא ודאי מעכב. Kol heicha de'tana bei kra vaday meakev. If
the תורה repeats it, it definitely is מעכב. והכא במלא קומצו בקומצו
קמיפלגי. Ve'hacha bimlo kumtzo be'kumtzo kamifligi.
The question is one aspect of the מנחה, whether it's מעכב. The
גמרא understands that since the תורה says in one place, והרים ממנו
בקומצו, ve'herim mimenu be'kumtzo, with his hand. Other time it says מלא
קומצו, melo kumtzo, the fill of his hand. So if it just
said the fill, maybe that's describing a quantity. And maybe I could
measure out a כלי kli that fits my hand, you know, has
the volume of my hand breadth and use the כלי kli because
that's מלא קומצו, melo kumtzo, it's the full fill of my hand,
it's not you know, the measure of my hand. So no, but
because the תורה in one place says בקומצו, be'kumtzo, that means I
have to use my hand itself. Now it doesn't repeat it, so
is that מעכב or can I actually use a כלי? kli? So
that's actually the debate of רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel, do we
use a כלי kli to do the קמיצה? kemitza? Maybe it doesn't
mean if it says I have to be מרים מלא קומצו, merim
melo kumtzo, if it didn't say with my hand, but I have
to lift up the full of my hand, I can do it
with a כלי. kli. Maybe it's just defining a measure. So we
only know because it says בקומצו, be'kumtzo, but it only says it
once. So is that מעכב or not? Okay, so let's take a
look.
דתניא, Detanya, we turn in the ברייתא: Baraita: מלא קומצו בקומצו. Melo
kumtzo be'kumtzo. It normally says מלא קומצו, melo kumtzo, and in one
place it says בקומצו be'kumtzo to tell me שלא יעשה מדה לקומץ,
shelo yaaseh middah le'kometz, that you cannot make a measuring vessel for
the קומץ, kometz, you have to use your hand itself. רב סבר:
Rav savar: הא נמי תנא ביה קרא. Ha nami tana bei kra.
That also was repeated in the פסוק, and if you did it
with a vessel, it's מעכב. דכתיב: ויקרב את המנחה וימלא כפו ממנה,
Ve'hikriv et hamincha ve'yimale chapo mimena, that should he brought he he
should bring forth the מנחה or offer up the מנחה and he
filled his hands with it. So there you took fill his hands,
literally using his hands themselves. ושמואל, Ve'Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel would say
that's actually done from that week's פרשה, right? From the קרבן korban
of the מילואים. miluim. Was that in שמיני Shemini or was that
in was that before שמיני? Shemini? That was during the seven days.
That was שמיני, Shemini, right? שמיני Shemini starts with that was the
מנחה, right, ויקרב את המנחה, ve'hikriv et hamincha, right, that was the
מנחה of the עם, am, וימלא כפו ממנה ויקטר על המזבח. ve'yimale
chapo mimena ve'yakter al hamizbe'ach. Okay, so it just filled his hand,
literally his hand itself.
So the reason why I'd say it like instead of saying
ויקמוץ, ve'yikmot, it says וימלא כפו, ve'yimale chapo, it would have to
be his hand, exactly.
Now even though that's an עובדא, uvda, even though it's a narrative,
that's enough for תנא ביה קרא. tana bei kra. So רב says
that that's מעכב using your hand.
ושמואל, U'Shmuel, and שמואל Shmuel would reject that. דרוש משעה לא ילפינן.
Dorosh mi'sha'ah lo yafinan. No, that was a special one-time thing, it
was a שעה, sha'ah, it was a thing that was done for
that moment, it would not a permanent institution, this קרבן korban, of
the מילואים, miluim, and therefore you can't learn anything out from it.
It's true אהרן used his hand, but you can't learn anything out
from it. Again, he's not rejecting the idea that a narrative can
be seen as a repetition, although it's not a ציווי, tzivuy, but
what he is rejecting is that the narrative of a one-time קרבן,
korban and therefore not relevant. So how does that fit in שמואל's
Shmuel statement of גרסה ושמנה? gersah ve'shamnah? He means if you want
to say when the תורה repeats it's מעכב, it
has... something that is a standard institution, a קרבן korban that's a
regular institution, a קרבן korban like what אהרן did in שמיני, Shmini,
that you can't learn anything else from. Okay, so that we now
have the fascinating thing. We didn't realize this. According to שמואל, Shmuel,
we're constantly talking about קומץ, kometz, קומץ, kometz, קומץ. kometz. According to
שמואל, Shmuel, if you didn't use your hand and you used like
a scoop, if it was the right size, בדיעבד, that would be
okay. Alright, so I I actually need this just reminds me it's
a slight digression but the idea of מלא קומצו melo kumtzo as
opposed to קומצו. kumtzo. There's this משנה Mishnah in עדיות Ediyos where
it says there's a discussion about בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, or no רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, no not בית
הלל, Beis Hillel, some רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right. Who is the
one that learned? I'm sorry, no no no I'm sorry הלל, Hillel,
הלל, Hillel, excuse me, sorry thank you, okay so it was הלל.
Hillel. So הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai are debating
how much מים שאובים mayim sheuvim is פוסל posel the מקוה. mikva.
So it says הלל Hillel says, מלא הין מים שאובים פוסל את
המקוה, melo hin mayim sheuvim posel es hamikva, a fill of a
הין hin of מים שאובים mayim sheuvim is פוסל posel the מקוה,
mikva, אלא שחייב אדם לומר בלשון רבו, ela shechayav adam lomar bilshon
rabbo, but he had to say it the way his רבי rebbe
taught it to him. So what does that mean? What's so, so
there are a lot of מפרשים mefarshim say, well why didn't he
just say הין מים שאובים פוסל את המקוה? hin mayim sheuvim posel
es hamikva? Why did he say מלא הין? melo hin? Because that's
the way his רבי rebbe taught him. Okay, so why did his
רבי rebbe teach it to him that way? So the וילנא גאון
Vilna Gaon has a great פשט. He says because his רבי, rebbe,
the רבי rebbe of הלל, Hillel, was שמעיה ואבטליון Shmaya ve'Avtalyon who
were גרים. geirim. And because they were גרים, geirim, they when they
pronounced the הא hei which is guttural, הין, hin, they couldn't pronounce
the guttural like you know a lot of people can't, non-Jews can't
pronounce the חית ches and it sounded like in, which means אין,
אין מים שאובים פוסל את המקוה. ein mayim sheuvim posel es hamikva.
So they had to say מלא הין melo hin so it would
be clear that they were not saying it אין מים שאובים. ein
mayim sheuvim. It was brilliant. So anyway, so it's just מלא, melo,
the fill means the measure of and that's the difference between מלא
קומצו melo kumtzo and בקומצו. bikumtzo. So now the גמרא says like
this. ולא יליף שמואל דורות משעה? velo yalif Shmuel doros misha'a? Does
שמואל Shmuel not learn out the, you know, a principle for future
generations from a one-time
event? והתנן, vehatnan, we taught in a משנה: Mishnah כלי לח מקדש
את הלח. klei lach mekadesh es halach. We taught this before, that
the measurements for the liquid, liquid measure vessels, sanctifies the liquids that
are put in them. ומידת יבש מקדש את היבש, umidas yavesh mekadesh
es hayavesh, and dry measure vessels sanctify the dry, you know, foods
that are put in them, like the flour. ואין כלי לח מקדש
את היבש ולא מידת יבש מקדש את הלח. ve'ein klei lach mekadesh
es hayavesh velo midas yavesh mekadesh es halach. And however they don't
work cross-purposes, since liquid measures are made only for liquid, if you
put dry food in it, it doesn't work, and similarly dry measures,
if you put liquid in it, it does not sanctify. ואמר שמואל,
ve'amar Shmuel, לא שנו אלא מידות. lo shanu ela middos. That's only
talking about measuring vessels because there you could say a measuring vessel
for liquid is different than a measuring vessel for a solid. אבל
מזרקות, aval mizrakos, but the bowls that are used to catch blood,
but you know it's a bowl, a bowl is generic. So that
מקדש, mekadesh, if you put dry stuff into a bowl, it would
sanctify. דכתיב: שניהם מלאים סולת. shneihem mele'im soles. It says by the
קרבן that the נשיאים Nesi'im brought that they brought these מזרקות, mizrakos,
right, these sort of bowls filled with flour. So you see that
they were filled with flour, presumably we assume that the flour sanctified.
So you see the מזרק mizrak can be used for flour and
therefore it can sanctify even if it was בלול בשמן balul bashamen
and then we said there has to be some dry spots, right?
Well I'll have to check that גמרא again. Okay, so anyway, because
it's true because it did say בלול בשמן, balul bashamen, so how
dry really is it? Right, so you're right, it was with dry
spots, patches or whatever. Anyway, the גמרא says, also here he's learning
it out from a one-time event. So it says, שאני התם דתנא
ביה קרא תריסר זימני. shani hacham detana bei krah treisar zimnei. It
was repeated twelve times even though it was a one-time event. It
was a one-time event that was done twelve times and by repeating
it twelve times, it got to be saying something. It's saying that
this is a general principle you can learn. תוספות Tosfos says in
a brief little one-line saying, דתנא ביה קרא תריסר זימני, detana bei
krah treisar zimnei, you see this תוספות about ten lines down from
the wide lines. He says: אם הכי קשיא אדרבה ולהוי שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד ואין מלמדין. im hachi kashya adrabba velahavei shnei kesuvim habaim
ke'echad ve'ein melamdin. He just
says if so, why wouldn't we say if it's repeated that tells
you it's not a principle? Well okay, maybe if it's repeated once
or twice, but twelve times, that's already a principle. Okay, so שמואל
Shmuel can learn out from the שעה. sha'a.
Okay, does three hundred and twenty times be enough?
I guess, I don't know. אמר ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב.
amar lei Rav Kahana veRav Assi leRav. So רב כהנא Rav Kahana
and רב אסי Rav Assi said to רב: so now we've got
our principle. The תורה has to repeat by a מנחה כדי לעכב.
kedi l'akeiv. The debate of רב and שמואל Shmuel is only the
debate of whether you need בדיעבד to use your hand itself or
even a vessel. Do we say that counts as a repetition? But
now we're going to go עבודה by עבודה to see is the
תורה really repeating it and is it מעכב, does it fit with
our משנה that says so many things are not מעכב. So let's
take a look. אמר ליה. amar lei. Rav Kahana and Rav Assi
to Rav. Rav Kahana and Rav Assi said to Rav: והרי הגשה,
ve-harei hagasha,
touching the vessel that the מנחה is in a vessel and the
כהן kohen touches it to the מזבח mizbe'ach and then he does
the קמיצה, kemitza, okay? And it says אל פני המזבח. el pnei
ha-mizbe'ach. So the touching, והרי
הגשה,
ve-harei hagasha,
where
my—ah, דתנא ביה קרא, de-tana beh kra, it's repeated. It's said in
ויקרא and it's said again in צו, Tzav and each time it
says the כהן kohen brings it to the מזבח, mizbe'ach, ולא מעכב,
ve-lo me'akev, but our משנה says that it's not מעכב. So your
principle doesn't work. So the גמרא says: ומנא תנא בה, u-mana tana
bah, where do you see this repetition in צו? Tzav דכתיב, because
it says in צו—all Tzav of these references are, it's said once
in ויקרא, it's repeated in צו. So we’re not going to quote
the first time it says it in ויקרא; we’re only quoting the
way it’s repeated in צו. So where is it repeated in צו?
Because the פסוק says: זאת תורת המנחה הקרב אותה בני אהרן לפני
ה' אל פני המזבח. Zot torat ha-mincha ha-krev otah bnei Aharon lifnei
Hashem el pnei ha-mizbe'ach. So it says that you bring it to
the מזבח mizbe'ach and then it says you take the קמיצה. kemitza.
So that shows you that—and it's repeated, so why isn't it מעכב?
So the גמרא's answer is: No, ההוא לקבוע
לו מקום הוא דאתא. hahu li-kvo'a lo makom hu de-ata. The reason
the תורה repeats it in צו is not to tell you it's
מעכב; it’s repeated for a different purpose: to tell you exactly where
you touch the מנחה to the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Because we almost have a northeast corner
here—exactly, exactly, דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in the ברייתא: braita: לפני ה'.
lifnei Hashem. So it says he shall bring the מנחה לפני ה'
lifnei Hashem אל פני המזבח. el pnei ha-mizbe'ach. So these two פסוקים
psukim don't exactly—these two descriptions don't exactly work together. יכול במערב? yachol
be-ma'arav? Right? So I mean רש"י Rashi's actually, for once, has a
picture, right? So if you look at רש"י's picture, okay, לפני ה'
lifnei Hashem means facing the היכל. heichal. The היכל heichal is in
the west, so if he’s touching it to the מזבח mizbe'ach and
he’s facing the היכל, heichal, he would be at the western wall
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So maybe it means the western wall. But
now we have another phrase: the פסוק says,
תלמוד לומר—I’m talmud lomar sorry,
third line—אל פני המזבח, el pnei ha-mizbe'ach, the face of the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. And didn't you go up the ramp? That's like the front.
The front is therefore the south. So אי אל פני המזבח, i
el pnei ha-mizbe'ach, so if I want to focus on that phrase,
יכול בדרום? yachol ba-darom? So maybe I just touch it on the
south side of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. תלמוד לומר לפני ה', talmud lomar
lifnei Hashem, which says in front of God, which is the west.
So how do you do both? It's one says implies south, one
implies west. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? הגישה בקרן דרומית מערבית. hagisha be-keren
dromit ma'aravit. So you touch it to the southwest corner, so you
get both לפני ה' lifnei Hashem and אל פני המזבח, el pnei
ha-mizbe'ach, you touch it at a corner, כנגד חודה של קרן, keneged
chudah shel keren, opposite the point of the horn that's at the
top. ודיו, ve-dayo, and that's enough, you're יוצא yotze that way. The
גמרא in סוטה Sotah says ודיו ve-dayo means you don't have to
touch the מנחה itself, it's enough to touch the כלי kli that
the מנחה is in. Right, the flour? Yeah. Okay, so anyway, because
it's so—so the answer is, it's not repeated to tell you it's
מעכב, it's repeated to tell you exactly where you do it. You
do it at the southwest corner. Now that we're on this point,
we're going to just say another thing about this act of הגשה.
hagasha. רבי אליעזר אומר יכול יגישנה למערבה של קרן או לדרומה של
קרן. Rabbi Eliezer omer yachol yagishenah le-ma'aravah shel keren o le-dromah shel
keren. Maybe you have to choose between—maybe you can choose, I could
either do it to the west or the south. I can either
do לפני ה' lifnei Hashem or אל פני המזבח. el pnei ha-mizbe'ach.
Maybe the פסוק means one or the other. Okay, maybe that's the
way to read a פסוק. אמרת, amarta, no, you should say: כל
מקום שאתה מוצא שני מקראות, kol makom she-ata motze shnei mikra'ot, if
you have two פסוקים, psukim, אחד מקיים עצמו ומקיים חבירו, echad mekayem
atzmo u-mekayem chaveiro, by following one, you satisfy its requirement and the
other פסוק's requirements, ואחד מקיים עצמו ומבטל חבירו, ve-echad mekayem atzmo u-mevatel
chaveiro, by following the other, you satisfy the other's requirements but not
the first פסוק's requirements. So if you have to choose—basically he's saying
like this, I don't believe in this corner idea. One פסוק implies
west, the other implies south. How am I going to read them?
Either I'm going to read them A or B. But if I
can choose A or B, that's not good, because if I do
one I won't be doing the other. But actually he says, is
there one of those choice, is either A or B, which in
a way will get both? And he says if there is, that's
the one to pick. So he says, מניחין את שמקיים עצמו ומבטל
חבירו, manichin et she-mekayem atzmo u-mevatel chaveiro, ignore the option that just
does itself and not the other one, ותופסין את שמקיים עצמו ומקיים
חבירו, ve-tofsin et she-mekayem atzmo u-mekayem chaveiro, grab the option that allows
you to fill it literally and also get the other one. Which
is this? כשאתה אומר לפני ה' במערב, kshe-ata omer lifnei Hashem be-ma'arav,
if you emphasize the idea of west, לפני ה', lifnei Hashem, ביטלת
אל פני המזבח, bitalta el pnei ha-mizbe'ach, there's no way that's the
face of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. The west side is not the face
at all. So it cannot mean do the west. But, בדרום, ba-darom,
וכשאתה
אומר אל פני המזבח,
u-kshe-ata
omer
el pnei ha-mizbe'ach, if you emphasize doing the face of the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, the south, בדרום, ba-darom, קיימת לפני ה'. kiyamta lifnei Hashem. Then
you also satisfied in front of God. Now, how is it the
south satisfies in front of God? So the גמרא says: והיכן קיימת?
ve-heichan kiyamta? How do you satisfy that? אמר רב אשי קסבר האי
תנא... Amar Rav Ashi kasvar hai tana... כולו מזבח בצפון קאי. kulo
mizbeach batzafon ka'i. The whole מזבח mizbeach is in the north, not
like רש''י picture. Let's assume that, right, this is the opening of,
it's the door to the היכל. Heichal. The היכל Heichal was a
bit further. Here's my מזבח. mizbeach. So if my מזבח mizbeach was
here, right, and I did פני המזבח, pnei hamizbeach, it would not
be facing the היכל. Heichal. But if the entire מזבח mizbeach is
in the north, and then this the opening, like, here, let's assume
that this door's the opening, and the opening is half in the
north, half in the south, the entire מזבח mizbeach is in the
north, so when I do פני המזבח, pnei hamizbeach, I am also
לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. I am standing right, I'm standing right in
front of the opening to the היכל. Heichal. So he says, no,
no, no, it's not southwest. It's פני המזבח pnei hamizbeach that also
gets you לפני השם lifnei Hashem because the מזבח mizbeach is situated
that you'll be fine. Anyway, so that's where the גמרא end.
ואמר רב
אשי, v'amar
Rav Ashi, okay,
we just did that. Okay, so that is where the גמרא end
for today where basically what he's saying is now we're going to
go through case by case in the משנה to say, does the
list in the משנה which says what's not מעכב fit this principle
of what's repeated in צו or not? So the first real question
to this is what's repeated in צו is הגשה. hagashah. We said
הגשה hagashah is not מעכב, and the answer is the reason הגשה
hagashah is repeated in צו is to tell you where you do
the הגשה: hagashah: southwest corner, or according to this last opinion, the
south, which is also פני המזבח. pnei hamizbeach. And it's not repeated
so to be מעכב. So tomorrow we will continue, it's also לפני
השם. lifnei Hashem. We will continue tomorrow to go through case by
case to see if the principle fits the משנה of what is
and not מעכב by a מנחה.