Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is מנחות נ"א, Menachos
Nun Aleph, מנחות Menachos 51.
We are ahead, so we pick up on the top of נ"א
עמוד ב' Nun Aleph Amud Beis and we'll just do the עמוד
ב' Amud Beis today, just one עמוד. amud. And so we pick
up at the very top of 51b, the משנה, Mishna, and we're
talking about חביתי כהן גדול, Chavitai Kohen Gadol, the מנחה mincha that
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol brings every day, half in the morning,
half in the afternoon. And the previous משנה Mishna dealt with the
case of what happened if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies between
the two and another כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is appointed, then how
does the other כהן גדול Kohen Gadol bring his half. Our משנה
Mishna deals with a different same scenario but different ending. Let's take
a look. לא מינו כהן אחר תחתיו. Lo minu Kohen acher tachtav.
So the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died between the morning חביתין, Chavitin,
half of the חביתין Chavitin and the afternoon half, and they did
not immediately appoint a new כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know, it
takes a little time. משל מי הייתה קריבה? Mishel mi haysah kreiva?
So who would continue now to bring the חביתין, Chavitin, whether for
this afternoon or just generally, who's bringing the חביתין Chavitin during this
interim period? רבי שמעון אומר משל ציבור. Rebbi Shimon omer mishel Tzibur.
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says that it's still, you know, you could
have said nobody brings it, it's brought specifically by a כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, but no, the משנה Mishna assumes it is, and רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon says it's brought from community funds. רבי יהודה אומר
משל יורשים. Rebbi Yehuda omer mishel yorshim. No, it's brought from the
heirs of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So it's still sort of
being brought for the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. You know, you could
sort of say their debate is, is it the idea that this
is supposed to be brought every day in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and it's assigned to the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and then
if there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol the ציבור Tzibur brings it,
or is it something that is being brought for, you know, the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is bringing on behalf of the כהן גדול?
Kohen Gadol? It's a כהן גדול קרבן, Kohen Gadol korban, which seems
more because it normally is coming from his money, so it doesn't
seem it's a ציבור קרבן, Tzibur korban, and therefore if he dies,
the heirs continue to bring it for him. רבי יהודה אומר משל
יורשים, Rebbi Yehuda omer mishel yorshim, ושלמה הייתה קריבה. ushleimah haysah kreiva.
And according to both opinions, when it is being brought for and
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not around on his behalf or
whatever in his absence, either by the ציבור Tzibur or by the
heirs, it is not coming half, it is coming a full עישרון.
issaron. Okay. So the obvious question is, is it a full עישרון
issaron once a day or is it a full עישרון issaron twice
a day? So we will see about this. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן. Tannu Rabbanan. כהן גדול שמת ולא
מינו כהן אחר תחתיו. Kohen Gadol shemeis v'lo minu Kohen acher tachtav.
The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol died and they did not appoint a
new כהן גדול Kohen Gadol immediately. מניין שתהא מנחתו קריבה? Minayin shetehai
minchato kreiva? So we're not even dealing in the between the morning
and the afternoon, now we're just dealing with the general question, right?
How do you know you continue bringing it and who brings it?
Because certainly the logic would have been, okay, no כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, it's not brought. But no. מניין שתהא מנחתו קריבה? Minayin shetehai
minchato kreiva? How do you know that even without a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol you still bring it? And that it is משל יורשים,
mishel yorshim, and that it is from the heirs who are the
ones who pay for it. So this is, of course, רבי יהודה's
Rebbi Yehuda's position. תלמוד לומר והכהן המשיח תחתיו מבניו יעשה אותה. Talmud
lomar v'hakohen hamashiach tachtav mibanav ya'aseh osah. So this is a very
creative read of the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says the כהן
Kohen who will be anointed in his stead of the כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, meaning after the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies, the next
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So it says, you know, the כהן Kohen
who is of his sons who is anointed in his stead shall
make shall bring the קרבן. korban. And the emphasis of מבניו mibanav
or the statement of מבניו mibanav is just to indicate that, you
know, you first look at his children for the next כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol before you look outside of his family. But the way
this is being read is is מבניו יעשה אותה. mibanav ya'aseh osah.
You know, that it when you have to do it and he's
not around, it is from his sons, from his heirs that you
continue doing it. Okay? יכול יקריבנה חציים? Yachol yakrivennah chatzyim? Now maybe
when it's not being brought by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and
when it's brought by the heirs, you do half in the morning,
half in the afternoon. תלמוד לומר אותה. Talmud lomar osah. מבניו יעשה
אותה. Mibanav ya'aseh osah.
When it is coming from his children and they're the one because
he's dead, then you have to make אותה, osah, you have to
do it completely. כולה ולא חציה, Kullah v'lo chetzyah, דברי רבי יהודה.
divrei Rebbi Yehuda. All of it, not half of it, these are
the words of רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. So that's רבי יהודה, Rebbi
Yehuda, where he gets both the idea of the heirs, מבניו יעשה
אותה, mibanav ya'aseh osah, and that it's אותה, osah, that it is
not split half an עישרון issaron in the morning and half in
the afternoon, but it is a full עישרון. issaron.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says, חק
עולם. chok olam. No, the end of the פסוק pasuk says is
an eternal edict. משל עולם. Mishel olam. So it's coming from the
עולם, olam, it's coming from the whole world, from the community. Okay,
this חק עולם chok olam could also be telling you exactly this
point, that even if he's dead, you must continue to do it.
Okay, it's forever, but it's from the עולם. olam. כליל תקטר, kalil
tuktar, שתהא כולה בהקטרה. shetehai kullah behaktarah. So חק עולם כליל תקטר
chok olam kalil tuktar is the end of that פסוק, pasuk, so
it should all be burnt up. So כולה, kullah, like כליל kalil
is כולה, kullah, שתהא כולה בהקטרה, shetehai kullah behaktarah, when it is
coming from the עולם olam you bring it complete, you do not
bring it half. Okay, so that's how each. חוק עולם chok olam
שתהא כולו בהקטרה, shete kulo b'haktara, so חוק עולם כליל תקטיר chok
olam kalil toktar is the end of that פסוק, pasuk, so it
should all be burnt up, so all of it is כולו, kulo,
like כליל kalil is כולו, kulo, שתהא כולו בהקטרה, shete kulo b'haktara,
when it is coming from the עולה olah you bring it complete,
you do not bring it half.
Okay, so that's how each one learns it out from different sections
of the פסוק. pasuk. So now the גמרא Gemara says והאי הכהן
המשיח להכי דאתא, v'hai hakohein hamashiach l'hachi d'ata, according to רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, how can you learn out the מבניו יעשה אותה mib'nav
ya'aseh otah to teach you that it's the heirs? We need that
פסוק pasuk to tell us something else. Is that really what it's
coming to teach you? המיבעי ליה לכדתניא, hamiba'ei lei l'khidetanya, we need
it for what it says in the
ברייתא. braita. זה קרבן אהרן ובניו אשר יקריבו לה' ביום המשח אותו.
zeh korban Aharon u-vanav asher yakrivu l'Hashem b'yom himashach oto. So this
is the actual פסוק, pasuk, you know, let me just read the
whole פרשה parsha actually here, the whole section. Okay, it says like
this, וידבר ה' אל משה לאמר, vayidaber Hashem el Moshe leimor, this
is ויקרא Vayikra ו' י"ב, vav yud-bet, זה קרבן אהרן ובניו אשר
יקריבו לה' ביום המשח אותו עשירית האיפה סולת מנחה תמיד מחציתה בבוקר
ומחציתה בערב. zeh korban Aharon u-vanav asher yakrivu l'Hashem b'yom himashach oto
asirit ha-eiphah solet minchah tamid machatzitah baboker u-machatzitah ba-erev. So, by the
way, we're going to get back to it says אהרן ובניו Aharon
u-vanav and it says ביום המשח אותו, b'yom himashach oto, so it
sounds only once. Okay, so that's the simple sense of the פסוק.
pasuk. על מחבת בשמן תעשה מורבכת תביאנה תופיני מנחת פתים תקריב ריח
ניחוח לה', al machavat bashemen te'aseh murvechet tevi'ena tufinei minchat pitim takriv
reiach nichoach l'Hashem, and it's on fire pan etc. והכהן המשיח תחתיו
מבניו יעשה אותה, v'hakohein hamashiach tachtav mib'nav ya'aseh otah, and the כהן
kohein who is anointed under his in his stead shall do it.
חוק עולם לה' כליל תקטיר chok olam l'Hashem kalil toktar is an
eternal edict, it shall be burnt completely, וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה
לא תאכל, v'chol minchat kohein kalil tihiyeh lo teiachel, and any מנחה
minchah of any כהן kohein has to be complete, meaning burnt completely,
do not eat it. So the simple sense of the פסוקים psukim
could be talking that it's only going to be brought on the
day of, you know, of that they are initiated in and therefore
אהרן Aharon and his children and his sons bring it, and then
in the future it's when you, you know, otherwise you just get
the כהונה kehunah by birth, but in the future the כהן גדול
kohein gadol still has to be initiated into the office, anointed into
the office, so he would bring it on the day that he
was anointed. That is a simple way you could read the simple
פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. However, the גמרא Gemara reads probably
that no, that it is always brought by אהרן Aharon and probably
by because of the חוק עולם, chok olam, constantly forever, it's a
regular קרבן korban that אהרן Aharon brings. Okay, but now we're looking
at what how we're sort of exactly parsing the פסוקים. psukim. So
let's look at it again. יכלו יהיו אהרן ובניו מקריבים קרבן אחד.
yachlu yihiyu Aharon u-vanav makrivim korban echad.
So it says like this, זה קרבן אהרן ובניו אשר יקריבו לה'
ביום המשח אותו. zeh korban Aharon u-vanav asher yakrivu l'Hashem b'yom himashach
oto. יכלו יהיו אהרן ובניו מקריבים קרבן אחד, yachlu yihiyu Aharon u-vanav
makrivim korban echad, maybe they are bringing the exact same קרבן, korban,
right? Exact same הלכה halacha for אהרן Aharon and for the כהן
גדול kohein gadol and for other כהנים? kohanim? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar
אשר יקריבו לה', asher yakrivu l'Hashem, they in the plural, which means
that we're looking at them as a different as a collection of
multiple items, אהרן בפני עצמו ובניו בפני עצמם. Aharon bifnei atzmo u-vanav
bifnei atzmam. Multiple people.
So yes, children and yes אהרן, Aharon, but in different categories. כהן
הדיוט kohein hedyot and כהן גדול. kohein gadol.
So, so that's, so now how is it going to play out?
בניו אלו כהנים הדיוטות. banav eilu kohanim hedyotot. So his sons, that
means the normal כהנים. kohanim. אתה אומר כהנים הדיוטות או אינו אלא
כהנים גדולים? atah omer kohanim hedyotot o eino ela kohanim gedolim?
Maybe, you know, when it says אהרן ובניו, Aharon u-vanav, it really
means like the end of the פסוק. pasuk. It doesn't mean כהנים
הדיוטים, kohanim hedyotim, it means אהרן Aharon and his heirs, the ones
who will become כהן גדול kohein gadol after him. That's not a
bad read because the end the end פסוק pasuk says והכהן המשיח
תחתיו מבניו יעשה אותה. v'hakohein hamashiach tachtav mib'nav ya'aseh otah. So since
that פסוק pasuk is about כהן גדול, kohein gadol, maybe the opening
פסוק, pasuk, זה קרבן אהרן ובניו אשר יקריבו לה' ביום המשח אותו,
zeh korban Aharon u-vanav asher yakrivu l'Hashem b'yom himashach oto,
might mean אהרן Aharon and future descendants that are כהנים גדולים. kohanim
gedolim. Very reasonable read of the פסוק. pasuk. So no, יכל אתה
אומר כהנים הדיוטות או אינו אלא כהנים גדולים, yachol atah omer kohanim
hedyotot o eino ela kohanim gedolim,
maybe that opening אהרן ובניו Aharon u-vanav means future כהנים גדולים? kohanim
gedolim? כשהוא אומר והכהן המשיח תחתיו מבניו, keshehu omer v'hakohein hamashiach tachtav
mib'nav, when the end פסוק pasuk says the next כהן גדול kohein
gadol of his children, הרי כהן גדול אמור. harei kohein gadol amur.
So the end פסוקים psukim are clearly talking about a כהן גדול,
kohein gadol, and it clearly identifies, you know, how that it will
be anointed in his stead. So if that's the בניו banav at
the end of the פסוק, pasuk, המה אני מקיים בניו? ha-mah ani
mekayem banav?
So what is the בניו banav at the beginning of the section,
זה קרבן אהרן ובניו? zeh korban Aharon u-vanav? המה אני מקיים בניו
אלו כהנים הדיוטות. ha-mah ani mekayem banav eilu kohanim hedyotot.
To tell you that the opening section is not talking only about
כהן גדול, kohein gadol, אהרן ובניו Aharon u-vanav in the opening section
talks even about a כהן הדיוט. kohein hedyot. Okay, אם כן נכתוב
קרא הכהן המשיח תחתיו. im kein nichtov kra hakohein hamashiach tachtav.
Okay, so now what's the הלכה halacha there? So okay, so there
is some קרבן korban for כהן הדיוט. kohein hedyot. What is the
קרבן korban for a כהן הדיוט? kohein hedyot? So that is when
a כהן הדיוט kohein hedyot starts his עבודה, avodah, before he starts
his עבודה, avodah, every כהן גדול kohein gadol before the first time
they do the עבודה, avodah, the first thing they do is they
bring a מנחה, minchah, a מנחה minchah of a full עשירית האיפה
סולת, asirit ha-eiphah solet, they bring this מנחה, minchah, as we'll find
out, not that it's split in the morning and the afternoon, okay,
but they just bring one מנחת סולת, minchat solet, actually even the
כהן גדול kohein gadol when he first begins he brings a מנחת
סולת. minchat solet. So the opening part, זה קרבן אהרן ובניו אשר
יקריבו לה', zeh korban Aharon u-vanav asher yakrivu l'Hashem, okay, is to
tell you that all the, you know, any כהן kohein when they
start their עבודה. avodah. They have to bring a מנחה mincha *Mincha*
of סולת soles *Solet*. The end of the פסוק pasuk, *Pasuk* is
going to be specifically the כהן kohen משיח *Kohen Mashiach*, and that's
going to be forever every single day. Okay. Now, but how is
this relevant for us? Because you can't use says the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* the פסוק pasuk *Pasuk* מבניו יעשה אותה *mi-banav ya'aseh otah* to
tell you that the heirs bring the קרבן korban. *Korban* if the
כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol* is dead. We need מבניו יעשה
אותה *mi-banav ya'aseh otah* to tell us the end בניו *banav* is
talking about the heirs of the כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol*,
future כהנים גדולים *Kohanim Gedolim*, so that the opening בניו *banav* is
talking about a regular כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot *Kohen Hedyot*. All right.
So how can you use it to teach you the heirs bring
the קרבן korban *Korban* if we're actually using it to divide this
section, the end half about כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol* and
the opening half about a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot. *Kohen Hedyot*? So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, אם כן לכתוב קרא הכהן המשיח
תחתיו מבניו יעשה *im ken likhtov kra Ha-Kohen ha-Mashiach tachtav mi-banav ya'aseh*.
If it had just been coming, it's sort of doing it in
the reverse. If it had just been coming to teach you the
הלכה halacha *halacha* that the heirs bring it, then that last פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* would have said והכהן המשיח תחתיו בניו יעשה אותה *ve-Ha-Kohen
ha-Mashiach tachtav banav ya'aseh otah*. That would have been explicitly the way
the גמרא *Gemara* is reading it, not a דרשה *drasha*. Okay. So
the next generation, the children should bring it. Okay. So it should
have just said בניו *banav*. So why מבניו *mi-banav*? The reason it
added the מ *mem* מבניו *mi-banav* was to tell you the פשט
pshat? *pshat* that we mean a descendant who is taking his place.
שמע מינה תרתי *shma mina tarti*. Okay. So again, how are we
reading this section? So we're reading it like following. This is the
קרבן korban *Korban* of אהרן *Aharon* and his sons, meaning not his
sons who replace him, but his sons who are כהני הדיוטות *Kohanei
Hedyotot* אשר יקריבו לה' ביום המשח אותו עשירית האיפה סולת soles. מנחה
mincha תמיד *asher yakrivu l-Hashem b-yom himashach oto asirit ha-eifa solet mincha
tamid*. Okay. So when they are anointed, when they don't actually anoint
with oil a normal כהן kohen *Kohen*, but when they begin their
עבודה *Avodah*, every כהן kohen *Kohen* has to bring a מנחה mincha.
*Mincha* to start off their עבודה *Avodah*. And then somehow we understand
that it's shifting specifically to כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol*, not
clear. מחציתה בבוקר ומחציתה בערב machatzitah vaboker umachatzitah ba'erev *machatzitah ba-boker u-machatzitah
ba-erev* and maybe you know the תמיד *tamid* is telling you and
by the way with a כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol* every
single day, half in the morning, half in the afternoon. And then
והכהן המשיח תחתיו מבניו יעשה אותה *ve-Ha-Kohen ha-Mashiach tachtav mi-banav ya'aseh otah*
at the פשט pshat. *pshat* level is future כהנים גדולים *Kohanim Gedolim*
do the same, the one of his children who take his place.
But at the דרש *drash* level it is בניו יעשה אותה *banav
ya'aseh otah* that if he's not around the heirs are the one
that pay for the קרבן *Korban*. Okay. So that's that is according
to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, האי
אותה
מאי עביד ליה *hai otah mai avid lei*? So רבי שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon*, so יעשה אותה *ya'aseh otah* for רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, the
אותה *otah* is coming to tell you when the heirs bring it,
you bring it as one unit. You do not divide it into
two halves. So רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, we know that what he
would do with מבניו יעשה אותה *mi-banav ya'aseh otah* just means future
כהנים גדולים *Kohanim Gedolim*. But what does he do with the אותה
*otah* that emphasizes that it's שלם *shalem*? מיבעי ליה לכהן גדול שמת
ומינו אחר תחתיו שלא יביא חצי עשרון isaron מביתו ולא חצי עשרון
של ראשון *mi-baei lei l-Kohen Gadol she-met u-minu acher tachtav she-lo yavi
chetzi isaron mi-beito ve-lo chetzi isaron shel rishon*. What we taught yesterday,
that it is if it is that if it is הכהן המשיח
תחתיו מבניו *Ha-Kohen ha-Mashiach tachtav mi-banav* actually exactly the פשט *pshat* scenario
of the פסוק *pasuk* that he dies and another כהן Kohen *Kohen*
takes his place, then it is יעשה אותה *ya'aseh otah*. He has
to bring it from a full מנחה mincha, *Mincha*. So if the
כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol* before him died after bringing the
morning one and then he was appointed, he has to now bring
a full מנחה mincha *Mincha*. He is המשיח תחתיו מבניו *ha-Mashiach tachtav
mi-banav*, he's taking his place. יעשה אותה *ya'aseh otah* he brings a
full מנחה mincha *Mincha* and breaks it in half and half for
the afternoon, the other half gets destroyed. Like we taught yesterday. Don't
just bring and start with a half. שלא יביא חצי עשרון מביתו
ולא חצי עשרון של ראשון
*she-lo yavi chetzi isaron mi-beito ve-lo chetzi isaron shel rishon*. And not
don't bring the half of the first guy. ותיפוק ליה מ"ומחציתה" *ve-tipok
lei mi-u-machatzitah*? Why not learn it from where we learned it yesterday?
The extra ו *vav* ומחציתה *u-machatzitah* and the half in the afternoon.
The extra ו *vav* is telling you that even if it's a
new כהן *Kohen*, you have to bring half out of a whole.
ו לא דריש *vav lo darish*. He doesn't make a דרשה *drasha*
from an extra ו *vav* and therefore he learned it from אותה
*otah*. Okay, so רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* the whole end, המשיח תחתיו
מבניו יעשה אותה *ha-Mashiach tachtav mi-banav ya'aseh otah* is the heirs bring
it and it's אותה *otah*, it's complete. For רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*
that end is talking about normal case of a כהן *Kohen* taking
the place of the כהן גדול kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol* and he
has to even when he takes it in the afternoon, he has
to bring it out of a whole קרבן *Korban* מנחה mincha *Mincha*.
He starts with a whole and breaks it in half.
Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this, רבי שמעון האי
אותה מאי עביד ליה *Rabbi Shimon hai otah mai avid lei*? No,
we just did that. ו לא דריש *vav lo darish*. רבי יהודה
האי חק עולם מאי עביד ליה *Rabbi Yehuda hai chok olam mai
avid lei*? So now we're going to go to what does רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* do with רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*-'s פסוק *pasuk*? Okay,
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*-'s פסוק *pasuk* just to tell you the ציבור
tzibbur *tzibur* brings it is חק עולם לה' כליל תקטר kalil tuktar?
*chok olam l-Hashem kalil tuktar*. So what does he do with the
חק עולם *chok olam*? What's the point of saying that? מאי עביד
ליה *mai avid lei*? חוקה לעולם תהא *chukah l-olam tehei*. פשט *Pshat*.
That this is always in force. Okay? It's not just for that
time. generation of Aaron. כליל תקטר kalil tuktar למה לי? Now, why
does it say burn it completely? For Rebbe Shimon burn it completely
to say that when the ציבור tzibbur brings it then you have
to bring the whole unit, you don't divide it into two halves.
Okay, but for for Rebbe Yehuda who learns it's the heirs and
he learns the idea that's whole from a different פסוק, what does
he do with the כליל תקטר? kalil tuktar מיבעי ליה לכדתניא mibaei
leih l'khid'tanya like we taught in the ברייתא. braita. אין לי אלא
עליונה מנחת כהן גדול בכליל תקטר ותחתונה מנחת כהן הדיוט בלא תאכל.
ein li ella elyonah minchat kohen gadol b'kalil tuktar v'tachtonah minchat kohen
hedyot b'lo te'achel. So by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol by the
חביתין chavitin it says, right, it says כליל תקטר kalil tuktar burn
it completely. The next פסוק says וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא
תאכל. v'chol minchat kohen kalil tihyeh lo te'achel. Every מנחה of a
כהן shall be complete, do not eat it.
So it's clear don't eat it, but it's by inference we know
כליל kalil means burn it completely. But it doesn't explicitly say burn
it completely, it just says כליל תהיה. kalil tihyeh. And by the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol it doesn't say explicitly don't eat it. Okay,
so that's what we need we need the כליל kalil תקטר to
link these two. So let's take a look.
אין לי אלא עליונה מנחת כהן גדול בכליל תקטר ותחתונה מנחת כהן
הדיוט בלא תאכל. ein li ella elyonah minchat kohen gadol b'kalil tuktar
v'tachtonah minchat kohen hedyot b'lo te'achel. So I know that a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol. you burn it all and a כהן הדיוט kohen
hedyot you don't eat it. מנין ליתן את האמור של זה בזה
ואת האמור של זה בזה? minayin litein et ha'amur shel zeh bazeh
v'et ha'amur shel zeh bazeh? How do you know that the כליל
תהיה kalil tihyeh of the normal כהן means burn it completely? And
how do you know that the לא תאכל lo te'achel of the
normal כהן applies to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and there's a
לאו lav for the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol eating his מנחה as
well? תלמוד לומר כליל כליל לגזירה שוה. talmud lomar kalil kalil ligzeirah
shavah. It says גזירה שוה. gzeirah shavah. נאמר כאן כליל ונאמר להלן
כליל. ne'emar kan kalil v'ne'emar lehallan kalil. מה כאן בכליל תקטר אף
להלן בכליל תקטר. mah kan b'kalil tuktar af lehallan b'kalil tuktar. The
same way by the כהן גדול the כליל kalil תקטר means it's
fully burnt, so similarly by the כהן הדיוט. kohen hedyot. מה להלן
ליתן לא תעשה על אכילתו mah lehallan litein lo ta'aseh al achilato
and the same way by כהן הדיוט to eat it would be
an actual violation of a לאו, lav, אף כאן ליתן לא תעשה
על אכילתו. af kan litein lo ta'aseh al achilato. Here too it
would be a violation of a לאו. lav. Okay, so the reason
you need
the כליל kalil? is to make the גזירה שוה. gzeirah shavah. Now,
it's a little funny why don't you just need the כליל to
tell you the פשט? Right, which is you have to burn it
completely? I mean that's just the פשט. So but maybe because the
פסוק before says מחציתה בבוקר ומחציתה בערב
it's clear that you are offering up the whole thing on the
מזבח mizbe'ach and you're not just taking a קומץ. komets. And once
that's true what do you need the כליל? So you need it
to make a גזירה שוה gzeirah shavah with the כהן הדיוט. All
right, so that's how we get it but in the end the
debate is who pays for it but everybody agrees that it is
complete and not divided into two halves. So now the גמרא says
like this. וסבר רבי שמעון משל ציבור? v'savar Rebbe Shimon mishel tzibbur?
Does Rebbe Shimon really think that the that it's you bring it
when the כהן גדול is dead from communal funds is דאורייתא, d'oraita,
that that משל ציבור דאורייתא, mishel tzibbur d'oraita, that that's from the
תורה? Torah? והתנן v'hatnan we taught in the משנה. mishnah. אמר רבי
שמעון שבעה דברים התקינו בית דין וזה אחד מהם. amar Rebbe Shimon
shiv'ah devarim hitkinu beit din v'zeh echad mehem. There were seven things
that בית דין beit din established and this is one of them.
The this was what was mentioned just before which was that when
you find female animals in the environs of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, in certain environs you assume that they are שלמים shlamim
and the person who finds them would bring them to the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and then he was required to pay for the
מנחת נסכים minchat nesechim that would go with it. And then people
decided they weren't going to bother returning them and bringing them to
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So then they
decided fine just bring it to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash we'll
offer it up and we the ציבור tzibur. will pay for the
מנחת נסכים. minchat nesechim. So that says so that is so Rebbe
Shimon says that is one of seven things of תקנות takanot that
they made like these are all of a similar genre. Okay let's
see what some of the other ones are. וזה אחד מהן v'zeh
echad mehen and now here are some more. עובד כוכבים ששלח עולתו
ממדינת הים. oved kochavim sheshalach olato mim'dinat hayam. So if a non-Jew
sent an עולה olah from overseas and non-Jews can send their קרבנות
korbanot to be brought.
So שלח עמה נסכים shalach imah nesechim if he sent with it
money to be used for the for the מנחת נסכים minchat nesechim
that goes with it, קריבין משלו kreivin mishelo great you use his
funds to buy it. ואם לאו קריבין משל ציבור. v'im lav kreivin
mishel tzibbur. We're not going to go back to him and say
hey you got to pay extra for the stuff that goes together
with the קרבן. No we will use communal funds to pay for
the מנחת נסכים. minchat nesechim. So another case of an animal without
מנחת נסכים minchat nesechim we can't ask the person bringing it to
supply it we will supply it from communal funds. Similarly another case
very similar to that. וכן גר שמת v'chen ger shemet a גר
ger dies and there's no heirs which only can happen by case
of a גר ger who has no blood relatives if he doesn't
have after he converts. והניח זבחים vehini'ach zvachim and he leaves over
sacrifices. יש לו נסכים yesh lo nesechim if he has presumably money
maybe it's already sanctified or just money to be used towards the
נסכים, nesechim, קריבין משלו kreivin mishelo we use his funds to buy
the מנחת נסכים. minchat nesechim. ואם לאו קריבין משל ציבור v'im lav
kreivin mishel tzibbur and if not it comes from. from the ציבור.
tzibur ותנאי בית דין הוא Vesnai beis din hu and
it's that and now another תקנה, takkanah, it is a stipulation of
the court. ותנאי בית דין הוא, Vesnai beis din hu, excuse me,
and that's a stipulation of the court meaning when they are collecting
communal funds the court has discretion for the קרבנות korbanos each year
the court has discretion how to use it and this is one
of the things that they are stipulating it can be used for.
Okay, כהן גדול שמת ולא מינו כהן אחר תחתיו, Kohen Gadol shemeis
velo minu Kohen acher tachtav, number three or number four of the
seven is the כהן גדול dies and they do not appoint another
כהן in his place. שתי מנחותיו קרבות משל ציבור Shtei minchosav kreivos
mishel tzibur that they use communal funds to bring the מנחה. Very
similar, using communal funds to bring a מנחה, this is not a
מנחה that goes with a קרבן but a מנחה that has to
be brought and the person to bring it is not around. So
it sounds very much like this is a דרבנן derabbanan like this
is a תקנה. takkanah. And by the way I should say if
you are bringing it as a whole as a whole one or
whole עשרון of סולת which is what the הלכה halacha is, then
it's possible that that is a נדבה, nedavah, that's a freewill קרבן
because it's a whole מנחה of סולת. So it sounds like it's
completely rabbinic. So אמר רבי אבהו שתי תקנות הוו. Amar Rabbi Abbahu
shtei takkanos havo. No no no. There are two stages here. דאורייתא
משל ציבור. De'oraisa mishel tzibur. The Torah teaches us that it's brought
from communal funds. כיוון דחזו דקא מידחקא לשכה Keivan dechazu deka midchaka
lishka then they started seeing that that was really making a heavy
demand on communal funds. Why? Because in the time of the second
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash you would have a new כהן גדול each
year and presumably there would go long periods of time without a
כהן גדול. So it was depleting communal funds. So therefore תקנו דלגבי
מיורשין. Tiknu deligavei miyorshin. They established תקנה takkanah number one is fine,
we're going to make the יורשין yorshin pay for it. They'll give
it over to the ציבור but the יורשין yorshin will have to
pay.
כיוון דחזו דקא פשעי בה Keivan dechazu deka pash'ei bah then they
saw that they weren't that the יורשין yorshin were not doing what
they were obligated to do. אוקמה אדאורייתא Ukma ade'oraisa we went back
to the Torah so the תקנה takkanah does not mean it's really
תקנה takkanah the תקנה takkanah was to revert to the Torah הלכה
halacha. that you use the communal funds. All right so now that
we're listing the extra things that were things that were sort of
like established by the בית דין Beis Din here's another one which
is really not like the previous, not about paying for מנחות minchos
but just to finish up some of these things mentioned in the
משנה. mishnah. ועל פרה שלא יהא מועלין באפרה Ve'al parah shelo yehei
mo'alin be'afrah that the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah if
somebody uses them for personal use you do not transgress מעילה. me'ilah.
So the גמרא says דאורייתא היא. De'oraisa hi. So the reason we're
focusing on this, there's even more in the משנה, mishnah, is because
similar to the כהן גדול we have a similar challenge on this
one. The idea that there's no מעילה me'ilah by the ashes is
a Torah הלכה. halacha? What do you mean it's a תקנה? takkanah?
Where do you know it's a Torah הלכה? halacha דתניא Detanya we
learn in the ברייתא. Baraisa. חטאת היא Chatas hi it is a
חטאת chatas by the
פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. מלמד שמועלין בה. Melamed shemo'alin bah. You treat
it like a חטאת chatas so there is an איסור מעילה issur
me'ilah on it. היא, Hi, it is a חטאת, chatas, בה מועלין
באפרה אין מועלין. bah mo'alin be'afrah ein mo'alin. The מעילה me'ilah is
with it,
not with the ashes. Okay so it's a דאורייתא. De'oraisa. So similar
to the question we had by כהן גדול you're telling me it's
a תקנה, takkanah, it looks like it's a דאורייתא. De'oraisa. אמר רב
אשי שתי תקנות הוו Amar Rav Ashi shtei takkanos havo and a
similar answer. There were two stages. דאורייתא בה מועלין באפרה אין מועלין.
De'oraisa bah mo'alin be'afrah ein mo'alin. From the Torah you don't only
are מועל mo'el in it, there's no מעילה me'ilah in the ashes.
כיוון דחזו דקא מזלזלי בה Keivan dechazu deka mezalzeli bah they saw
that people were treating it in a disparaging way. They weren't giving
it enough respect, the ashes of the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. וקעבדי
מינה למכתן Veka'avdi minah lemachtan and they were using it to put
on their wounds because like ashes were supposed to be healing to
wounds. Now I gotta ask you, ashes of a פרה אדומה, Parah
Adumah, that stuff is a fortune. That's what you're using for your
wounds? You're not just going ahead and burning some paper. So maybe
they thought it had some magical qualities as well I don't know.
Also who gave them access to it? You would think that the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would have that stuff locked up very tightly
under lock and key. But okay, somehow when they ruled that the
ashes are not no מעילה me'ilah that led to misuse. גזרו בה
מעילה Gazru bah me'ilah then they said no now there's rabbinic מעילה
me'ilah on the ashes. כיוון דחזו דקא פרשי מספק הזאות Keivan dechazu
deka parshi misafek haza'os then they saw that people did not want
to be sprinkled with the ashes of a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
when they were uncertain if they had encountered a dead body and
if they were טמא מת. tamei meis. Because since they're uncertain they
were saying well if I'm not really טמא tamei and I don't
really need the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah then I'll
transgress מעילה me'ilah because it'll be on me and I don't know
exactly what benefit you'll gain but anyway they wanted to keep a
distance from it that provided that prevented them from going through the
טהרה taharah process when they should have. So therefore אוקמה אדאורייתא Ukma
ade'oraisa they reverted to the Torah הלכה which is there is no
מעילה me'ilah by the ashes. So two things in this משנה mishnah
of רבי שמעון that was challenged that should be sounds like it's
דאורייתא, De'oraisa, this פרה אדומה Parah Adumah ashes that there's no מעילה
me'ilah and our thing that it comes from communal funds and both
of them are and both of them were answered and they were
being framed as תקנות, takkanot, and the answer to both of them
was it was two stages: first a תקנה takkanah that took it
away from the דאורייתא de'oraita and then a תקנה takkanah that restored
it to the דאורייתא. de'oraita. Okay, we will end here for today,
and now we are perfectly in line.