So today's daf דף daf for us is Mem Chet מ"ח, Mem
Chet, amud beis עמוד ב' amud beis in the middle and we
pick up on Mem Chet מ"ח Mem Chet amud aleph עמוד א'.
amud aleph.
Tani Rabbi Chanina Tirsa תני רבי חנינא תירתא Tani Rabbi Chanina Tirsa
or Tirta תירתא. Tirta. The line starts with the word Chanina חנינא
Chanina about two-fifths of the way down. Tani Rabbi Chanina Tirsa kemei
de-Rabbi Yochanan תני רבי חנינא תירתא קמיה דרבי יוחנן. Tani Rabbi Chanina
Tirsa kemei de-Rabbi Yochanan. So Rabbi Chanina Tirsa רבי חנינא תירתא, Rabbi
Chanina Tirsa, the name of a place, taught in front of Rabbi
Yochanan רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan the following Braisa ברייתא: Braisa: Shachat arba
kevasim al shtei challot שחט ארבעה כבשים על שתי חלות. Shachat arba
kevasim al shtei challot. So this is the reverse of what the
earlier Gemara גמרא Gemara were talking about, which was the two Kivsei
Atzeret כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret with four challot חלות. challot. Here you're
doing four kevasim כבשים kevasim with two challot חלות. challot. So clearly
what do you have? You have two kevasim כבשים kevasim which are
good as Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret with their challot חלות,
challot, the other two can't function as Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת. Kivsei
Atzeret. Now you may be shchted שחט shchted them with the kavana
כוונה kavana of Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת, Kivsei Atzeret, so basically Kivsei
Atzeret כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret without their lechem לחם lechem are pasul
פסול. pasul. However, if right, but if they don't become Kivsei Atzeret
כבשי עצרת, Kivsei Atzeret, if they become let's say shlamim שלמים, shlamim,
then they're okay. So we have obviously a difficult situation that two
would just be fine, two if you try to continue to make
them Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret and be-zorek hadam lishmo בזורק
הדם לשמו be-zorek hadam lishmo for all four, then they're pasul פסול.
pasul. It's Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret without the lechem לחם.
lechem. What? Is it bal tosef בל תוסיף? bal tosef? Whatever, it's
pasul פסול, pasul, well I don't know but I don't want to
get into it.
However, if you make it as shlamim שלמים shlamim you'll be okay.
So let's take a look. So here's what you do: Mash'neh shnayim
mehem משנה שניים מהם, Mash'neh shnayim mehem, be-zorek hadam she-lo lishmo בזורק
הדם שלא לשמו. be-zorek hadam she-lo lishmo. So a Kivsei Atzeret כבשי
עצרת Kivsei Atzeret with zorek hadam she-lo lishmo זורק הדם שלא לשמו
zorek hadam she-lo lishmo basically becomes a shlamim שלמים, shlamim, we've seen
that already. And then the other two are going to be good
Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret with their bread and Shalmei Yisrael
שלמי ישראל. Shalmei Yisrael. Okay. So, ve-im ee ata omer kach ואי
אתה אומר כך, ve-im ee ata omer kach, if you don't say
to do that, what's the alternative? The alternative would be let's say
to shcht שחט shcht all of them for Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת,
Kivsei Atzeret, be-zorek hadam בזורק הדם be-zorek hadam for everything lishmo לשמו.
lishmo. So then two of them are going to be pasul פסול.
pasul. So im ata omer kach אם אתה אומר כך im ata
omer kach and you want me to do the right thing and
be-zorek hadam lishmo בזורק הדם לשמו, be-zorek hadam lishmo, hi-shechitah ha-acharonim השחיטה
האחרונים hi-shechitah ha-acharonim the last ones will be Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת
Kivsei Atzeret without the lechem לחם lechem because the first ones will
be good with the lechem לחם, lechem, the last ones will be
without the lechem לחם lechem and they'll be pasul פסול. pasul. Now
of course the other possibility is why not be-zorek בזורק be-zorek the
first two lishmo לשמו lishmo and then do the last two she-lo
lishmo שלא לשמו? she-lo lishmo? Right, that's also an alternative, that should
be okay. So Rashi רש"י Rashi suggests that he thinks maybe that
would be dichuy דיחוי. dichuy. Maybe as soon as I did the
first two lishmo לשמו, lishmo, the last two are still in the
running for being Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת, Kivsei Atzeret, then they're being
nidcha נדחה nidcha and then it's Kivsei Atzeret כבשי עצרת Kivsei Atzeret
which were ra'uy ve-nidcha ראוי ונדחה, ra'uy ve-nidcha, the little bit of
the discussion earlier and they'd be pasul פסול. pasul. So Rashi רש"י's
Rashi not exactly clear whether that's true because remember the Gemara גמרא
Gemara before wasn't so clear also that that would be true, why
maybe you could still be-zorek dam she-lo lishmo בזורק דם שלא לשמו?
be-zorek dam she-lo lishmo? But certainly the recommended thing here is get
the bad ones or select two to be bad and get it
out of the way and then it'll be clear that everything else
will be fine.
I would just say that after you shchted שחט shchted the first
two, then those are the ones and then...
well that's basically the point you're saying, do the first two lishmo
לשמו lishmo and the last two she-lo lishmo שלא לשמו. she-lo lishmo.
I mean or the last two
automatically...
be-zorek
בזורק, be-zorek, I'm saying did I say shcht שחט? shcht? I mean
be-zorek בזורק. be-zorek. Be-zorek בזורק be-zorek the first two lishmo לשמו lishmo
and then mimeila ממילא mimeila the last two can't be anything else.
But the shchitah שחיטה shchitah was already lishmo לשמו. lishmo.
Everything the shchitah שחיטה shchitah was already done here.
Right, so that's what I'm saying is when once you did the
first two lishmo לשמו lishmo and those are the ones, so the
third and the fourth one even if you do it lishmo לשמו...
lishmo...
Oh you think why did the shchitah lishmo שחיטה לשמו shchitah lishmo
even count there? That's an interesting question.
I'm not sure, yeah I think until the core of it is
actually hirtzah הרצה... hirtzah...
let's take just another example, Tamid Shel Shachar תמיד של שחר. Tamid
Shel Shachar. I shcht שחט shcht one thing Tamid Shel Shachar תמיד
של שחר, Tamid Shel Shachar, I haven't be-zorek hadam בזורק הדם be-zorek
hadam yet. I shcht שחט shcht the other thing Tamid Shel Shachar
תמיד של שחר. Tamid Shel Shachar. Presumably if I'm zorek the dam
זורק הדם zorek the dam now of the second one, I've made
the second one Tamid Shel Shachar תמיד של שחר Tamid Shel Shachar
and I've rejected the first one. The shchitah שחיטה shchitah isn't really
koveia קובע, koveia, you know it's the zrikas hadam זריקת הדם. zrikas
hadam. But I hear your point, meaning why don't you say that...
What about according to Rabbi?
Well Rabbi רבי, Rabbi, it's koveia קובע koveia in terms of, oh
the relationship to the lechem לחם. lechem. Yeah that's an interesting question.
So why when the shchitah שחיטה shchitah of the first two, doesn't
that hukvah הוקבע hukvah them with the lechem לחם? lechem?
If you did tnufo zos azika תנופה זו היא הזיקה... tnufo zos
azika... Well
no, Rabbi רבי, Rabbi, it's more about, it's not about the kedusha
קדושה kedusha because that's when it's me-kadesh מקידש me-kadesh the lechem לחם.
lechem. It's not so much when is the kedusha קדושה, kedusha, it's
more about the osa zika עושה זיקה osa zika earlier discussion.
Right, and so the shchitah שחיטה shchitah and the common...
right, right, that's a good question. How if since you didn't
shcht שחט shcht them simultaneously...
Oh they could be simultaneously, the two kohanim כהנים. kohanim.
Oh that's true, yeah that's a good point. It would have to,
if it was... it could be simultaneously, you have multiple kohanim כהנים.
kohanim. If it wasn't simultaneously you might have a good point that
the very fact that the shchitah שחיטה shchitah is osa zika עושה
זיקה osa zika
then automatically defines the latter two as not having lechem לחם. lechem.
That is a very good point. So you might have to say
that it was simultaneous. I wonder if Rashi רש"י Rashi says it
explicitly. Let's just see what Rashi רש"י Rashi says. Ve-eino din ואינו
דין... ve-eino din... no, no Rashi רש"י Rashi doesn't spell it out.
Okay but it's a very good point. It might have to say
that it was simultaneous. Alright, so anyway all four right now... so
Dovry's a good point, we might have to say it's simultaneous, but
right now all of all four are candidates for being it, and
the fact that you did two first, again, bracketing the first, the
first would be a good point not סתם stam first, but first
because of the bread that might be קובע, koveia, but let's assume
it's simultaneous, they're all candidates, so get two out of the way
and you'll be left with the other two. Okay, so that seems
pretty clear, so let's see what the answer is. So אמר ליה,
amar lei, so אמר ליה רבי יוחנן, amar lei Rabbi Yochanan, so
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan took offense at this and he said to
him,
וכי אומר לו לאדם עמוד וחטא בשביל שתזכה? vechi omer lo leadam
amod vachata bishvil shetizkeh? Do you say somebody go and sin in
order that there should be a benefit? Now this is a very
interesting concept which the גמרא Gemara actually explains, discusses at great length
in other places. Now however, normally the phrase is אומרים לו לאדם
חטא כדי שיזכה חברך omrim lo leadam chata kedei sheyizkeh chavercha and
here there's not a חברך. chavercha. So let me tell you why
this is different than a normal case. A normal case, like a
classic example that the גמרא Gemara has is, I go ahead and
I am baking bread on שבת. Shabbat. So I put my bread
in the oven and I make it all nice and I pat
it against the wall, sort of like the way they make it
in the אשתנור eshtanur falafel, and then my bread is baking, but
you know what? I haven't been, I won't have been מחלל שבת
mechallel Shabbat if you take the bread out before it bakes. It
needs to have finished baking in order for me to be מחלל
שבת. mechallel Shabbat. It's a question whether it needs to have been
baked on שבת Shabbat or not. That's not our issue, but it
certainly needs to finish baking for me to have been מחלל שבת.
mechallel Shabbat. So here you're צדיק, tzaddik, Michael, and Michael wants to
save me from my sin of חילול שבת. chillul Shabbat. So Michael
is going to take the bread out of the oven so that
I'm not going to be מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbat. The only problem
is there's an איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan to remove baking bread from
an oven on שבת Shabbat because it's a חכמה ואינה מלאכה, chochma
ve'eina melacha, it's an איסור דרבנן. issur d'rabbanan. Can he do an
איסור דרבנן issur d'rabbanan to save me from my חילול שבת דאורייתא?
chillul Shabbat d'oraitta? Do we say
חטא בשביל שיזכה חברך? chata bishvil sheyizkeh chavercha? חטאו? chatau?
חטא? chata חטא? chata? חטא? chata?
חטא chata? is in a חטא. chata Do we say חטא chet.
בשביל שיזכה חברך? bishvil sheyizkeh chavercha? So within that, there are a
lot of questions. How big is my sin? How big is his
sin? Did I do it במזיד bemezid or בשוגג? beshogeg? You know,
am I
warranting him helping me if I did it במזיד, bemezid, I brought
it on myself. So there's a whole interesting series of questions that's
in other גמרא. Gemara. Here, and it's not me sinning to help
somebody else, it's not me sinning to help myself, it's actually not
even such a big question of sinning, like which עבירה aveira exactly
am I עובר oveir when I'm זורק דם שלא לשמו? zorek dam
shelo lishmo? Okay, maybe I'm עובר, oveir, if you look at the
רמב"ם, Rambam, there's a
מצוה לעשות כל מעשה החטאת כמשפטו mitzvah la'asot kol ma'aseh hachattat kemishpato
or לעשות כל מעשה שלמים כמשפטם la'asot kol ma'aseh shelamim kemishpatam or
something, but it's not even exactly clear about a personal sin. And
תוספות Tosafot more or less makes this point and the better way
to think about this is not that I sin to help you
sin less, the better way to think about this is, do we
allow, like it's a violation of rules of how the מקדש Mikdash
works, right? There's certain ways the מקדש Mikdash works. You're זורק דם
לשמו, zorek dam lishmo, you're not זורק דם שלא לשמו. zorek dam
shelo lishmo. Are we going to allow a violation of those procedures
for an ultimate net gain? Okay, so do we say חטא, chata,
violate one rule so that there will be a net gain? If
I'm זורק דם שלא לשמו, zorek dam shelo lishmo, I salvage the
remaining two קרבנות, korbanot, I bring them as כבשי עצרת. kivshei atzeret.
If I'm not זורק דם שלא לשמו, zorek dam shelo lishmo, let's
say I do everything the right way and I'm זורק zorek it
all לשמו, lishmo,
then two become
פסול. pasul. Okay, but—or רש"י Rashi would say, or, once I do
two לשמו, lishmo, the remaining two become נדחה. nidcheh. So if I
do nothing, then they all get thrown out. So if I do,
but if I do it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, I salvage all
four. So is it worth it for me to violate a rule
to have a net gain? That's the question. But it's not the
technical חטא כדי שתזכה, chata kedei shetizkeh, it's more in terms of
do I violate, you know, sort of like the procedures of the
מקדש Mikdash and is that a warranted type of a trade-off? Okay,
so let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so that's what upset רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan
to yesterday's דף daf where we tried to establish whether it's reasonable
to do something invalid in order to validate.
Yesterday's דף daf is related, but yesterday's דף daf is not whether
it was proper, but whether it worked. Yesterday's דף daf is, once
this thing was נראה ונדחה, nir'eh venidcheh, can I make it שלא
לשמו, shelo lishmo, would that actually make it considered to still be
valid as a שלמים? shelamim? It was נראה ונדחה nir'eh venidcheh etc.
So there the question was: was it effective? Here we know it's
going to be effective, right? Because it's not even yet נראה nireh
yet, you're doing the זריקה zerika whatever, the question is, is it
warranted? Okay, so that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's question. וכי אומר לו
לאדם עמוד וחטא בשביל שתזכה? vechi omer lo leadam amod vachata bishvil
shetizkeh? ודתנן, veditnan, we saw in the משנה, Mishnah,
and again, almost all the examples here are going to be from
קדשים kodashim which sort of shows you're dealing not with the personal
sin, but with the proper types of trade-off. What's the right trade-off
to salvage the situation? ודתנן veditnan in the משנה, Mishnah, איברי חטאת
שנתערבו באיברי עולה, eivarei chattat shenitarvu be'eivarei olah,
so the limbs of a חטאת chattat were mixed with the limbs
of an עולה. olah. What's the הלכה? halacha? The הלכה halacha is
obviously you have to burn the limbs of an עולה olah on
the מזבח. mizbeiach. The קרבנות korbanot are good, you were זורק zorek
the דם dam for the חטאת chattat and the עולה. olah. The
קרבנות korbanot are good.
Now however, we want to finish them correctly. So the limbs of
the חטאת chattat have to be eaten by the כהנים, kohanim, the
limbs of the עולה olah have to be burned on the מזבח.
mizbeiach. They all get mixed together. What can I do? I don't
know which is which. Eating them all is totally out. I'm not
allowed to eat... Meat of an עולה, Olah, that would be violating
מעילה, Meilah, whatever it would be, I'm not allowed to eat the
meat of an עולה. Olah. So the other opportunity is just don't
do anything and let it all become פסול בלינה pasul belinah and
burn it. Okay, that's not great. So the third possibility is burn
it all on the מזבח. Mizbeiach. So then the עולה Olah is
done correctly, the חטאת Chatas I'm actively doing it wrong. Is that
wanted? To do something wrong with the limbs of the חטאת Chatas
in order to salvage the עולה? Olah? Very similar type of a
situation. Let's take a look.
So רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, yeah, do it. יתנו למעלה,
Yitnu lemalah, put everything on the מזבח, Mizbeiach, ורואה אני את בשר
חטאת למעלה כאילו היא עצים. veroeh ani es basar Chatas lemalah keilu
hi eitzim.
And have in mind that the meat of the חטאת Chatas is
not being put there as a הקטרה haktarah of the חטאת. Chatas.
Whichever limbs here from the חטאת, Chatas, those are treated as firewood,
and the other things are being offered up as a הקטרה. haktarah.
Okay, so that makes it a little bit better, but in the
end of the day, you're doing something wrong with the limbs of
the חטאת. Chatas. You're not eating it, you're actively destroying it in
order to salvage the עולה. Olah. That's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says. But the חכמים Chachamim disagree. The חכמים אומרים, Chachamim omrim, the
חכמים Chachamim say, תעובר צורתן, te'aver tzuratan, let their visage be, you
know, decayed, thank you, meaning wait for them to be פסול בלינה,
pasul belinah, wait till the next morning, be just don't act, better
do nothing, ויצאו לבית השריפה, veyeitzu l'veis hasreifah, then everything becomes פסול
pasul and you burn it. Better to just have to get rid
of it all and passively not do anything wrong than to actively
do something wrong with the limbs of the חטאת. Chatas. So it
seems that that's exactly what they're debating, and the חכמים Chachamim say
better to do nothing rather than to actively do one thing wrong
to salvage this situation. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers.
So don't you see that we don't make those trade-offs, says רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמאי, amai, according to you, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to this
תנא, Tanna, לימא עמוד וחטא בכדי שתזכה, leima amod vechatei bichdei shetiski,
get up and sin in order to benefit. So do something wrong
with the חטאת Chatas to salvage the עולה. Olah. So no, גמרא
Gemara says that's not a question. עמוד וחטא בחטאת בשביל שתזכה בחטאת
אמרינן. Amod vechatei bechatas bishvil shetiskei bechatas amrinan. So
you know, we would do it within one category. For that's the
suggestion. So therefore, if it were sinning with a חטאת Chatas but
I salvage a חטאת Chatas situation, that we would say. עמוד וחטא
בחטאת בשביל שתזכה בעולה... Amod vechatei bechatas bishvil shetiskei be'olah...
but to say sin with a חטאת Chatas to benefit the עולה,
Olah, לא אמרינן. lo amrinan. We don't say. So what was the
תנא Tanna situation? Here you have four lambs of עצרת. Atzeres. Actually
two are only going to work, but do one, do a sin
as it were, do something wrong with two of the עצרת Atzeres
lambs or with two שלמים shelamim to salvage two other שלמים. shelamim.
So it's all שלמים, shelamim, they're all intended to be כבשי עצרת,
kivsei Atzeres, all in the same category. That we might say. We're
not going to do it from different categories, and you can't ask
me from different categories. Why is it different? Presumably the difference is
he says look, we're talking on the same category, yes I did
a violation, but then we should at least ask what was the
net? There was a net gain. There was a little violation, זובחם
שלא לשמם, zovcham shelo lishmam, but the net gain was we didn't
have to get rid of two קורבנות, korbanos, we were able to
eat the קורבנות, korbanos, we didn't have to burn them and get
rid of two קורבנות. korbanos. So in the שלמים shelamim column, I
do the math and in the end I wind up with a
net gain. So it's true up there there was a minus, but
at the bottom there's a plus. That maybe I can say. But
if I say, well, in my שלמים shelamim column I definitely have
a net loss, in my חטאת Chatas column I definitely have a
net loss, okay, but in my עולה Olah I had a net
gain, that I'm not willing to tolerate. I'm not willing to say
do something wrong with עולה Olah to benefit something in חטאת. Chatas.
I can't take a step back and say in the end it
all worked out. Okay, because then clearly the violation of the חטאת
Chatas cannot be bracketed. But when within its category, maybe I can
bracket that because of the net gain. That's what the suggestion is.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to try challenge that
again. Let's take a look. ובחדא יוסי מי אמר? Uvechada yosei mi
amar?
Would we say it within one category that you can make this
type of a trade-off? והתניא, Vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita,
now another thing about the lambs of שבועות, Shavuos, כבשי עצרת ששחטן
שלא לשמן או ששחטן בין לפני זמנן ובין לאחר זמנן. kivsei Atzeres
sheshachtan shelo lishman o sheshachtan bein lifnei zmanan uvein le'achar zmanan. You
שחטed shecht the lambs of שבועות Shavuos שלא לשמן, shelo lishman,
okay,
or... which is clearly makes them not good as a כבשי עצרת
kivsei Atzeres but good as a שלמים. shelamim. Or you שחטed shecht
it before שבועות Shavuos or after שבועות, Shavuos, not on the right
day. הדם יזרק והבשר יאכל.
Hadam
yizarek vehabasar yei'achel.
So that easy enough, so it's still going to function as a
שלמים, shelamim, throw the blood and eat the meat as a שלמים.
shelamim. Fine, that was discussed before. Now what happens if, if however,
ואם היה שבת, ve'im hayah Shabbos, if it was שבת. Shabbos. So
here it was, it was שבת Shabbos and you were all eager
to bring כבשי עצרת kivsei Atzeres and you שחטed shecht them and
then all of a sudden you realized that you had miscounted ספירה
Sefirah and you weren't paying attention and actually שבועות Shavuos fell out
yesterday. So you brought these lambs in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Now if it really was שבועות Shavuos they would have been דוחה
שבת. docheh Shabbos. The only problem was it wasn't שבועות Shavuos and
they're not דוחה שבת. docheh Shabbos. So now what do you do
with the blood? Okay, now let's take a look. If you don't
do anything with the blood then it's going to be פסול בלינה
pasul belinah when it comes מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbos, you're not זורק
הדם zorek hadam in the same day, the קורבן's korban פסול, pasul,
and you won't be able to eat the meat, you won't be
able to burn the אימורים, emurim, nothing. If you're זורק הדם... zorek
hadam... today on שבת, Shabbos, so what can you do? Then comes
מוצאי שבת, Motzei Shabbos, it's still the same night, so you're allowed
to burn the אימורים, emurim, you're allowed to eat the meat. So
are you allowed to be זורק הדם? zorek hadam? So here's the
issue with being זורק הדם. zorek hadam. You're not doing any violation
of שבת. Shabbos. There's no איסור דרבנן issur d'rabonon to take some
blood and to throw it against a מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, I take
some blood and throw it against those walls. Worst I could do
is maybe I'm painting my wall, but let's say not, let's say
it's a smooth, you know, surface or whatever, there's no איסור דרבנן
issur d'rabonon on שבת Shabbos and certainly not דאורייתא d'oraisah to throw
blood on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay,
unless maybe there's a מוקצה muktzah but whatever, bracket that, you know,
because it's נולד nolad the new blood, but anyway bracket that. The
problem is within the laws of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, we
don't bring קרבנות korbanos on שבת Shabbos that's not supposed to be
brought today. And therefore, if it really was שבועות, Shavuos, this קרבן
korban should have been brought. But it wasn't שבועות. Shavuos. שבועות Shavuos
is tomorrow. This קרבן korban shouldn't have been brought. So your violation
you already did in terms of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos when you
שחט shechted the animal, okay. But even though there's no שבת Shabbos
violation today, we don't bring
a קרבן korban on שבת Shabbos that's not supposed to be brought
on שבת. Shabbos. We're not going to be זורק הדם. zorek hadam.
So should I violate that מקדש Mikdash rule? It's a regular שלמים.
shlamim. But I'm sorry, even if there's no מלאכה melacha left to
be done, I'm not going to bring a שלמים shlamim on שבת
Shabbos even if all it requires is being זורק הדם. zorek hadam.
So should I go ahead and be זורק הדם zorek hadam to
salvage the situation and violate that מקדש Mikdash rule of not bringing
even זורק הדם zorek hadam of a שלמים shlamim on שבת? Shabbos?
Or should I passively do nothing and let it all become פסול?
posul? That's the question. So let's see what the ברייתא Baraisa says.
Okay, ואם היתה שבת לא יזרוק. v'im haysa Shabbos lo yizrok. Don't
throw the blood. ואם זרק הורצה. v'im zarak hurtza. If you did
throw the blood, הורצה, hurtza, then it's a good קרבן. korban. להקטיר
אימורים לערב. lehaktir emurim l'erev. Let you burn the אימורים emurim that
night and as רש"י Rashi points out, also let you eat the
meat that night. Okay, good. So here I could have salvaged it
by being זורק הדם zorek hadam and I'm not entitled to do
that. Says the גמרא, Gemara, says אמאי? amai? According to you, why
is why was I passive? לימא עמוד חטי בשביל שתזכה. leima emod
chatei bishvil shetizke. Go and sin, be זורק הדם zorek hadam so
you salvage the situation. And the גמרא Gemara says, isn't that sort
of like within the same category? You're sinning with the blood of
this קרבן korban to salvage this קרבן. korban. So that sort of
seems like it's within the same category and we don't let that
happen. גמרא Gemara no, it's still different categories. עמוד חטי בשבת כדי
שתזכה בשבת אמרינן. emod chatei biShabbos kidei shetizke biShabbos amrina. If you
were to do a violation on שבת Shabbos and you would accrue
benefit on שבת, Shabbos, that would be one thing. However, עמוד חטי
בשבת, emod chatei biShabbat, your violation is occurring on שבת, Shabbos, כדי
שתזכה בחול. kidei shetizke bechol. Where's your benefit going to accrue? מוצאי
שבת. Motzei Shabbos. You're going to be able to burn the אימורים
emurim and eat the meat. Not on שבת. Shabbos. So you're going
to you want to allow a violation on שבת Shabbos in order
so something is salvaged מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. That's already different categories
and that we're not willing to consider. לא אמרינן. lo amrina. We
will not say. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara still saying that if
it's separate categories we're not going to say it. But the question
still is if it's one category, ר' יוחנן R' Yochanan still opposes
saying it, but the תנא Tanna was willing to make that trade-off.
Now the גמרא Gemara asks one last question. ובתרי מילי לא אמר?
utarrei mili lo amar?
Is it true we don't say it in two separate categories? I
mean, right, is it true? We're trying to say that in two
separate categories everybody would admit we don't say it. Is that really
true? והתנן. v'hatnan. We've heard in a משנה. Mishnah. Now we're leaving
מקדש Mikdash concerns
and the following.
חבית של תרומה שנשברה בגת עליונה ובתחתונה חולין טמאים.
chavis shel terumah
shenishbera begat elyonah ubatachtonah chulin tmayim. Now you might remember when we
learned עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that the way they had the pressing
floors when they made wine is they had a top floor where
they would basically stomp on the grapes, and then there'd be like
a hole and a funnel or whatever and it would bring it
into a bottom vat and all the the grape juice would collect
there and then they would basically make that into wine. So what
happened? You have in your bottom vat down there, you've got the
grape juice that you pressed. נעבעך, nebach, somebody טמא tmay touched it,
it's חולין טמאים. chulin tmayim. And חולין טמאים chulin tmayim is not
so bad. You know, חולין טמאים chulin tmayim you're allowed to eat.
You know, even if you're a כהן, Kohen, you're allowed to eat
חולין טמאים. chulin tmayim. So okay, you'll still be able to eat
it, not a problem. Up in the top vat, you've got a
barrel of תרומה terumah wine. What happened now? Your barrel of תרומה
terumah wine, טהור, tahor, broke. And the wine is now about to
spill into the bottom vat. What's going to happen when that תרומה
terumah wine spills into the bottom vat? It's going to become תרומה
טמאה. terumah tmayah. It's going to touch the טמא tmay wine. תרומה
טמאה terumah tmayah you're not allowed to drink. Not only is now
you're not going to be able to drink the wine from that
barrel, but now it's mixing in with the wine in the lower
vat and you're not going to be able to even drink your
חולין טמאים. chulin tmayim. So everything is going to get destroyed. So
you're trying to salvage the situation. The תרומה terumah you have you
can't salvage. But maybe you can save the חולין. chulin. And here's
how you want to save it. You have a lot of these
vessels available to you who are standing right by your wine press
that are טמא tmay vessels. So if you catch the תרומה terumah
in these טמא tmay vessels, the תרומה terumah will still be טמא.
tmay. fine, the תרומה's terumah gone, forget about the תרומה. terumah. But
at least it's not going to mix up with the חולין, chullin,
and I'll salvage my חולין. chullin. Am I allowed to do that?
To actively be מטמא metamei the תרומה terumah in order to salvage
the חולין? chullin? That's the question.
I thought the תרומה's terumah sorry already?
It's about to be טמא, tamei, it's pouring into the lower vat.
Right, the חולין chullin down here is טמא, tamei, it's going to
hit the חולין, chullin, become טמא tamei and make everything no good.
So I want to catch it in the middle. But by doing
it, by actively being מטמא metamei the תרומה, terumah, but I salvage
my חולין. chullin. Am I allowed to do this? So let's take
a look. Okay, so it says like this.
אהא תנן חבית של תרומה שנשברה בגת העליונה Aha tnan chavit shel
terumah shenishbera begat ha'elyonah so this barrel broke in the top vat
and the top pressing floor. ובתחתונה חולין טמאין uvetachtonah chullin tme'in and
at the bottom one, in the bottom vat is טמא חולין. tamei
chullin. מודה רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע Modeh Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Yehoshua the
two תנאים tannaim that we'll debate in a minute, at least they
both agree שאם יכול להציל ממנו רביעית
בטהרה
יציל she'im yachol lehatzil mimenu revi'it betaharah yatzil that if you can
at least salvage a רביעית revi'it of תרומה טהורה terumah tehorah then
you have to salvage that רביעית revi'it and you're not allowed to
be מטמא metamei the תרומה. terumah. Okay, because then some of the
תרומה terumah at least can be salvaged. So if the time it
takes you to run into your house, get your טהור tahor vessels,
run out, the most you'll be able to capture is a רביעית,
revi'it, like three four three ounces, that you have to do at
least because then at least you can salvage some of the תרומה.
terumah. But let's say I will not be able to salvage any
of the תרומה. terumah. Am I at least now able to salvage
the חולין? chullin? That's the question. The תרומה terumah is פארפאלן. farfallen.
Can I salvage the חולין? chullin? So let's take a look.
Okay, ואם לאו, ve'im lav, if you can't salvage any of the
תרומה terumah because by keeping
it טהור, tahor, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, so רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says,
תרד ותטמא ואל יטמאנה ביד. tered vetitame ve'al yetame'enah beyad. So I'm
sorry, you cannot actively be מטמא תרומה. metamei terumah. You have to
stand idly by, let the תרומה terumah go into the lower vat,
it becomes תרומה טמאה, terumah tme'ah, it makes everything אסור, assur, the
whole wine has to be thrown out. Better do nothing actively and
never don't do something actively wrong, even if it's going to mean
a net loss. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua says, אף יטמאנה ביד. af yetame'enah beyad. No, actively capture the
תרומה terumah with your טמא tamei vessels, make it טמא, tamei, but
at least you salvage the חולין. chullin. So גמרא Gemara says look,
here you go, you're allowed to do one thing wrong in order
to achieve a net
gain, just like us being זורק הדם zorek hadam wrong in order
to achieve a net gain. Isn't this the same type of a
case? And here from one category to another, you're מטמא תרומה metamei
terumah in order to save חולין. chullin. So גמרא Gemara says שאני
התם דלבי טומאה קאזלא. shani hatam delivei tumah ka'azla. That's not a
good point because there, even if you were totally passive, the תרומה
terumah is going to become טמא tamei anyway. So there רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua can say we can downplay how wrong is it really
to be מטמא metamei it ביד. beyad. How wrong is it to
be מטמא metamei it ביד? beyad? It's about to become טמא tamei
anyway. It's not such a wrong thing to do. So there we'll
allow it even though it's from one category to the next because
we basically say it's going to happen anyway. But other types of
things, we don't say it's going to happen anyway, the blood of
the חטאת chatas were not going to be נזרק שלא לשמה. nizrak
shelo lishmah. They would have been פסול pasul if you sort of
stood idly by. But this particular thing was not going to happen
to it. Can we introduce a new problem in order for a
net gain that we don't know? So that's the גמרא'ס Gemara's question.
It does not leave it resolved. It says basically we will not
do from one category to the next where basically, as I said,
even if the whole מקדש Mikdash benefits, the problem spans out, right?
You know, there was a violation of עולה, olah, there was a
violation of חטאת. chatas. That will be a problem. However, if within
a category there'll be a net gain, maybe we can bracket the
violation and say take a step back, we salvaged the שלמים shlamim
situation, we salvaged the כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret situation, we did that,
we did the best we could there. Okay, and that the גמרא
Gemara does not have an answer for whether that would be good
or not. Okay, so now we are going to move on to
a different topic.
That had to do, so until now we've been learning a lot
with the relationship between the כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret and the bread.
And the most recent two cases is what if the numbers are
wrong? Twice the amount of bread, twice the amount of lambs. Now
we're just going to go straight back to the כבשי עצרת kivsei
atzeret themselves and to certain הלכות halachot about them. So let's take
a look. Okay, כי אתא רב יצחק, Ki ata Rav Yitzchak, when
רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, about half
amount, and then then can you like you know adding another layer.
Right, well that we implicitly have because we basically said that according
to even the חכמים Chachamim or רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Eleazar
veRabbi Shimon that the קדושה kedushah does not occur till the זריקת
הדם, zrikat hadam, he he demanded everything be around בשעת שחיטה. besha'at
shechitah. So even the more extreme position, I mean the one that
you might have thought was a הוה אמינא hava amina for that
you needed everything around בשעת שחיטה. besha'at shechitah. Okay, what would happen
for example if you had both loaves of bread and then you
you know you lost it, how would the גמרא Gemara פסקא? paska?
וכי Vechi once there was זיקה zikah through the שחיטה, shechitah, right,
then the whole קרבן korban becomes פסול. pasul. So really, I mean
to some degree we actually did talk about that. Okay,
so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says, כי
אתא רב יצחק. ki ata Rav Yitzchak. When רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak
came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, תני, tani, he taught the following
ברייתא. Baraita. הכבשים ששחטן שלא כמצוותן hakevasim sheshachtan shelo k’mitzvatan פסולין. psulin.
When you שחט shacht the lambs the wrong way they're פסול, pasul,
וטעונה עיבור צורה. uteuna ibbur tzura. You don't burn them right away;
you wait until they become פסול בלינה. pasul balina. There's some type
of פסול pasul you don't burn right away; you have to wait
a day until it becomes פסול בלינה. pasul balina. I'm not going
to get into that discussion, רש"י, Rashi, תוספות Tosafot and another גמרא.
Gemara. For now we'll just accept it is פסול, pasul, but you
wait until it also becomes פסול בלינה, pasul balina, ויצא לבית השרפה
veyatze l'veit hasreifa and then you burn it. So the question is:
what is this שלא כמצוותן? shelo k'mitzvatan? What did you do wrong
that he is saying it becomes פסול? pasul? So רש"י Rashi first
has it means שלא לשמו shelo lishmo because רש"י Rashi is focused
on the phrase ששחטן. sheshachtan. So what can you do wrong at
the moment of שחיטה? shechita? So at the moment of שחיטה, shechita,
what you've done wrong is שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. The problem is
that the entire גמרא Gemara until now has assumed שלא לשמו shelo
lishmo they're still good as a שלמים shlamim and that is sort
of rule number one from the beginning of זבחים Zevachim that everything
other than a חטאת chatat and a פסח pesach שחיטה shechita that
you did שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is כשר, kasher, לא עלו לבעלים,
lo alu l'vealim, it doesn't count as כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret but
the קרבן korban is כשר. kasher. So רש"י Rashi thinks maybe this
ברייתא Baraita is arguing on that and thinks שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
is no good. But then רש"י Rashi says another thing which more
fits the continuation of the גמרא Gemara and which תוספות Tosafot also
really sort of pushes. So we're going to focus on רש"י's Rashi
second explanation which
is, it's not שלא כמצוותן, shelo k'mitzvatan, the problem was that the
קרבן korban was not...
it's not שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, excuse me.
The קרבן korban was the wrong age. It makes sense שלא כמצוותן,
shelo k'mitzvatan, also שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. I know, but what bothers
רש"י Rashi is the phrase ששחטן. sheshachtan. If the קרבן korban was
the wrong age, the problem happened before שחיטה. shechita. Okay, problem happened
at the time of הקדשה, hakdasha, which is part of what bothers
רש"י. Rashi. But רש"י Rashi in the end says, and it fits
with the continuation of the גמרא, Gemara, that it's supposed to be
a one-year-old קרבן, korban, it's a כבש keves and you brought a
two-year-old. So what happens when you bring a wrong קרבן, korban, is
it totally פסול? pasul? So this ברייתא Baraita said yeah, that's not
כבשי עצרת, kivsei atzeret, totally wrong, it's like you brought a cow
and therefore it's פסול. pasul. Okay, but the other opinion is going
to say no, you know why? Because what happens when כבשי עצרת
kivsei atzeret are done wrong? What do they become? When כבשי עצרת
kivsei atzeret are done wrong, they become שלמים. shlamim. A שלמים shlamim
can bring a קרבן korban that's two years old. So therefore even
if it can't function as כבשי עצרת, kivsei atzeret, why can't we
still salvage it as a שלמים shlamim and make it a two-year-old
שלמים? shlamim? So that's going to be the question. Okay, it was
as opposed to... now the reason it's different is when you do
it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo you're actively redefining it. You're saying, this
is not כבשי עצרת. kivsei atzeret. Okay, so it's a שלמים, shlamim,
געזונטערהייט. gezunterheit. But here you're trying to make it כבשי עצרת, kivsei
atzeret, but it's the wrong... it's, you know, it's the wrong animal,
it's too old. So is that a פסול pasul כבשי עצרת kivsei
atzeret or am I going to say as long as it's in
that same category we'll allow it to be reconfigured as a שלמים?
shlamim? And that's the question. So רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak said it's
פסול. pasul. So let's take a look. אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav
Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman says the following: מר, mar, the
master רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak דמקיש להו לחטאת, demakish lehu l'chatat, he
compares the כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret to a חטאת. chatat. Why? Because
the פסוק pasuk that speaks about bringing the כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret
juxtaposes them. It says, שעיר עזים אחד לחטאת ושני כבשים בני שנה
לזבח שלמים. se'ir izim echad l'chatat ushnei kvasim bnei shana l'zevacḥ shlamim.
Okay, so it juxtaposes the two. So you juxtapose כבשי עצרת kivsei
atzeret to a חטאת chatat and therefore you say, תני פסולה, tani
psula, that it's פסול pasul because the same way a חטאת, chatat,
as we know, any variation of a חטאת chatat is going to
be פסול, pasul, we're very intolerant when it comes to חטאות chataot
variation. So here too any variation is going to be פסול. pasul.
Not only that Michael, I know you know this הלכה, halacha, what's
the הלכה halacha about a חטאת שעברה שנתה? chatat she'avra shnata? Right,
it's one of the חטאות המתות. chataot hametot. So any חטאת chatat
that's too old or any variation, פסול, pasul, end of conversation. So
you link this to a חטאת, chatat, that's your approach. However, תנא
דבי לוי, tana d'bei Levi, why did he link it to the
חטאת? chatat? Because they're juxtaposed in the פרשה, parsha, שעיר עזים אחד
לחטאת ושני כבשים בני שנה לזבח שלמים. se'ir izim echad l'chatat ushnei
kvasim bnei shana l'zevacḥ shlamim. Okay, so תנא דבי לוי, tana d'bei
Levi, דגמר שלמי חובה משלמי נדבה, degamar shalmei chova mishalmei nedava, however,
there is the תנא Tanna of the school of לוי Levi that
says that we're
going to look
at these שלמים shlamim in the context of general שלמים. shlamim. These
are called שלמים shlamim as we know they can sometimes be converted
to שלמים. shlamim. So I'm going to look at them in the
context of general שלמים, shlamim, שלמי נדבה, shalmei nedava, free-will שלמים. shlamim.
So תני כשרין, tani ksheirin, he says that even if you did
it too old it will be כשר. kasher. Where do we have
this? דתני לוי, detani Levi, לוי Levi teaches in a ברייתא, Baraita,
there's actually a תוספתא Tosefta in נזיר Nazir and again, the assumption
here like we've been saying now is this comparison of נזיר Nazir
and its bread to כבשי עצרת kivsei atzeret and its bread. Not
only that, as רש"י Rashi points out, the same juxtaposition of חטאת
chatat to the שלמים shlamim occurs by נזיר Nazir as well. So
the same issues should be true by נזיר. Nazir. Let's take a
look though what we say by a נזיר. Nazir. It says, ושאר
שלמי נזיר ששחטן שלא כמצוותן, v’shear shalmei Nazir sheshachtan shelo k’mitzvatan, if
you שחט shacht the שלמים shlamim of the נזיר Nazir שלא כמצוותן,
shelo k’mitzvatan, which again here we would assume would mean that they
were too old, they were not the right age, okay, so the
ברייתא Baraita says... And anyway even if you take out the parentheses,
it's very clear from the next line, ונאכלים ליום ולילה, vene'echalim leyom
valayla, you can eat them, they're still a כשר קרבן, kasher korban,
ואין טעונים לא לחם ולא זרוע. ve'ein te'unim lo lechem velo zeroa.
You don't treat it as שלמי נזיר. shalmei nazir. What do you
do with שלמי נזיר? shalmei nazir? As we've seen before, like כבשי
עצרת, kivsei atzeret, it comes with bread. So forget the bread now,
it's no longer שלמי נזיר. shalmei nazir. Also, there's a whole thing
that you take one of the arms and you wave it and,
you know, that part of the whole process you do with the
נזיר, nazir, the hair of the נזיר, nazir, you don't do any
of that. It's not שלמי נזיר, shalmei nazir, but it's still שלמים.
shelamim. You still salvaged it even though it was too old. So
you see that when it's too old, you're still able to salvage
it and it's still going to be okay. Now, the one thing
is it still has the חומרא chumra of a day and a
night. Okay, now that's something that we know exists by שלמים shelamim
as well. There's a תודה toda and so on. That is not,
but that doesn't force you to categorize it as שלמי נזיר, shalmei
nazir, but yes, it is interesting that it doesn't totally change. At
least that level of קדושה kedusha still remains, that limited to a
day and a night. Fine, but fundamentally it's כשר, kasher, even though
the animal was too old. So that was, we're going to say
that is what תנא דבי לוי tana devei Levi says there. Presumably
he would say it here as well by כבשי עצרת. kivsei atzeret.
Okay, so let's take a look. Okay, so those are the opposing
positions. Now, until now, I've been saying, and that the reason it
should make sense to salvage this and make this a good קרבן
korban is because at least a two-year-old can be a good שלמים.
shelamim. And let's just consider this to be a generic שלמים. shelamim.
רש״י Rashi makes the point, which will come up later in the
גמרא, Gemara, and I'll just say now a little parenthetically, that it's
even better than that. Let's say I took a נדר neder to
bring a שלמים, shelamim, and I explicitly said I am going to
bring a one-year-old שלמים. shelamim. And I made that נדר. neder. Okay?
And then I took an animal which was two years old and
I set it aside and I said זו נדרי. zu nidri. Right?
But it was a two-year-old animal. And I went ahead and I
brought it. So you know what the הלכה halacha is? It still
counts as a שלמים, shelamim, except I didn't fulfill my obligation. So
there you go. I should have brought a one-year-old, I've brought a
two-year-old. We can still tolerate that violation and say I didn't do
my obligation, but it's still a good שלמים. shelamim. So here too,
it's supposed to be one year old, you brought two years old,
we'll be able to tolerate it and say it's a good שלמים,
shelamim, even though it's no longer כבשי עצרת. kivsei atzeret. Okay, that's
what לוי Levi says. So now the גמרא's Gemara going to have
a ברייתא beraita that proves basically proves לוי Levi and disproves רב
יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, that says we can salvage the situation. Let's take
a look. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this: אשם בן שנה
והביא בן שתים. asham ben shana vehevi ben shtayim. So now there
are some אשמות ashamot that are one-year-old אשמות ashamot and there are
some אשמות ashamot that are two-year-old אשמות. ashamot. I keep on forgetting
which is which. If you look at רש״י, Rashi, he says it.
Let's just take a quick look at רש״י. Rashi. אשם בן שנה,
Asham ben shana, three lines down in the wide lines, כגון דנזיר
טמא ומצורע דכתיב כבש. kegon denazir tamei umetzora dechtiv keves. So the
one-year-old אשמות ashamot are brought by a טמא נזיר tamei nazir who
brings an אשם asham and a מצורע. metzora. And then there are
two-year-old אשמות. ashamot. The next רש״י, Rashi, בן שתים, ben shtayim, כגון
גזלות ואשם kegon gezelot ve'asham that you bring for stealing, ומעילה, ume'ila,
or an אשם asham you bring for מעילה, me'ila, דכתיב איל. dechtiv
ayil. Okay, so there's some אשמות ashamot that the תורה Torah says,
right, you don't have, no, an אשם asham is for a very
specific type of a sin. Sometimes the תורה Torah says a certain
type of אשם asham you have to bring a one-year-old, other times
you have to bring a two-year-old. You did sin A, which was
the one-year-old אשם, asham, and you went ahead and you brought a
two-year-old אשם, asham, or vice versa. You were in the two-year category
and you brought a one-year category. But it's a totally different אשם,
asham, I mean it's for a totally different type of sin, טהרה,
tahara, whatever the situation is. Let's take a look. So אשם בן
שנה והביא בן שתים, asham ben shana vehevi ben shtayim, you had
to bring a one-year-old אשם asham and you brought a two-year-old, or
בן שתים והביא בן שנה, ben shtayim vehevi ben shana, you had
to bring a two-year-old and you brought a one-year-old, פסולים, psulim, they're
פסול, pasul, ותעבור צורתם ויצאו לבית השריפה, veta'avor tzuratan veyetze'u leveit hasereifa,
completely פסול, pasul, wait until they become פסול, pasul, burn them. Okay,
that's by an אשם. asham. However, אבל, aval, what if it was
an obligatory עולה ola that you brought the wrong type of an
animal? עולת נזיר, olat nazir, the עולה ola that a נזיר nazir
brings, עולת יולדת olat yoledet or that a יולדת yoledet brings, someone
who had child, a woman who had just gave birth to a
child, עולת מצורע olat metzora that a מצורע metzora brings at the
end of his טומאה tum'a process, שהיו בן שתי שנים, shehayu ben
shtei shanim, they were two years old, they were supposed to be
one year old, the תורה Torah says כבש, keves, but you brought
two-year-old for an עולה, ola, ושחטן, veshachtan, and you slaughtered it, כשירים,
kesherim, it's כשר. kasher. כללו של דבר, klalo shel davar, the principle
is, כל הכשר בעולת נדבה כשר בעולת חובה. kol hakesher be'olat nedava
kasher be'olat chova. Since for a free-will עולה, ola, a two-year animal
is okay, even though this is supposed to be a one-year עולה
ola and it's an obligation, if you did it as a two-year-old,
we can still salvage it and make it כשר kasher as an
עולה. ola. You didn't fulfill your obligation, but the קרבן korban will
still be considered an עולה. ola. You understand the parallel here, right?
When it comes to כבשי עצרת, kivsei atzeret, it's a שלמים. shelamim.
It's supposed to be one year old, but I made it two
years old. So you know what? We'll still keep it as a
good קרבן. korban. You didn't fulfill your obligation, but it's good because
we know of the phenomenon of two-year-old שלמים. shelamim. You were supposed
to do a one-year-old עולה, ola, that was your obligation. You didn't
do that, you brought it as a two-year-old. You didn't fulfill your
obligation, but it can still be a good עולה, olah, because we
know of the phenomenon of two-year-old עולה. olah. Now, why does that
not work by an אשם? asham? Why don't we say, which is
implicitly the question in the ברייתא, braita, as opposed to bringing a
one-year-old אשם, asham, I brought a two-year-old. Well, why don't we say,
well, let's salvage this situation. There is a phenomenon of two-year-old אשמות,
ashamot, let's salvage it. So, here's the difference. An אשם asham does
not exist as a נדבה. nedava. An אשם asham only exists as
an obligation. So, I can't say, well, I didn't bring my right
אשם, asham, but at least consider it to be a different type
of an אשם. asham. Excuse me, you can't bring a different type
of an אשם, asham, right? An אשם asham you only bring if
you're obligated. You can't consider it a new אשם. asham. Okay, you
can consider something an עולה, olah, it's free-will, and a שלמים shlamim
is free-will. Doesn't be for one or two years old an עולה?
olah? Yeah. Exactly. So even though I did not do my obligatory
שלמים, shlamim, my obligatory עולה, olah, consider it to סתם stam be
a free-will שלמים, shlamim, free-will עולה. olah. I don't have that choice
by an אשם asham and therefore by the אשם, asham, it's going
to be totally פסול pasul because it cannot be a סתם stam
אשם. asham. There is- I can't bring a סתם stam אשם. asham.
Okay, so that's what it says. Now, don't you see the כל
הפסול בחטאת? kol hapassul bechattat? However, that works by an עולה, olah,
but by a חטאת, chattat, the same way a two-year-old חטאת chattat
is no good, a wrong age חטאת chattat is no good, פסול
באשם, pasul be'asham, a wrong age אשם asham is no good and
it's totally פסול, pasul, חוץ משלא לשמו. chutz mishelo lishmo. If you
did it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo by an אשם, asham, that's okay,
which is not the same by חטאת. chattat. But if it's the
wrong age animal, it's going to be okay. So here it's a
great ברייתא, braita, it contradicts רב יצחק. Rav Yitzchak. It says that
even though the animal was too old, it's still a כשר קרבן
kasher korban as long as a free-will קרבן korban exists just like
that. So the גמרא Gemara says don't you see how don't we
disprove רב יצחק? Rav Yitzchak? Yes. How'd they check the animal down
to the חודש chodesh there? That is a good question. I don't
know if they need a birth certificate. I mean, sometimes the גמרא
Gemara speaks about certain types of physical signs to see how old
it is.
But I really don't know the answer to that
about whether it would rely on physical signs or it would need
to know for sure. I mean, obviously, I assume that there's some
things which it's clear it's very young, but other things where maybe
it's a little bit ambiguous, I'm not sure whether it would just
rely on physical signs. That's a very good question. Maybe take the
owner's word for it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says don't you
see that that disproves רב יצחק, Rav Yitzchak, that the קרבן korban
is still כשר? kasher So the גמרא Gemara says okay, האי תנא
תנא דבי לוי הוא, hai tanna tanna devei Levi hu, what a
big deal. We've already said that it's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim,
that there's ברייתות braitot from the school of דבי לוי Devei Levi
that actually say against רב יצחק. Rav Yitzchak. So this is just
from the school of לוי, Levi, fine, so it's part of that
debate. Okay, so here's the debate: an animal is brought, an obligatory
קרבן korban is brought, and it's the wrong age animal. Do we
say this, but it was done לשמו? lishmo? You tried to make
it the right קרבן. korban So do we say right קרבן, korban.
wrong animal פסול? pasul? Or do we say because it's the wrong
age, that allows it to be defined as שלמים, shlamim, as עולה,
olah, not your obligation, but as סתם stam שלמים shlamim or an
עולה? olah? And that's the debate. So one more ברייתא braita about
this. So the גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear, דתני לוי, detani Levi, לוי Levi taught. So we know where
this is going. This is clearly from the house of לוי. Levi.
אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע ששחטן שלא לשמן כשירים. asham nazir ve'asham metzora
sheshachtan shelo lishmon kesherim. So you have these obligatory אשמות ashamot that
you שחט shacht שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's כשר, kasher? ולא עלו
לבעלים לשום חובה, velo alu labealim leshum chovah, that we know. Okay,
כשר, kasher, but the owners have not fulfilled their obligation. שחטן מחוסר
זמן בבעלים, shachtan mechusar zman bibealim, let's say you שחט shacht it
before their time had arrived, meaning that the נזיר nazir was not
yet ready to be טהור, tahor, or of to change his נזירות,
nezirut, or I'm sorry, to be טהור, tahor, or the מצורע metzora
was not yet ready to be טהור, tahor, the time had not
yet come, או שהיו בני שתי שנים ושחטן, o shehayu bnei shtei
shanim veshachtan, or they were too old, they were two years old,
פסולין, psulin, they're פסול. pasul. Okay, that doesn't really say much more
than the earlier ברייתא, braita, but it's just making it clear that
לוי Levi admits that when it comes to an אשם, asham, that
the same principle is not true, that if the אשם asham is
too old we can't salvage the situation. So now the גמרא Gemara
is going to ask why not. So I've already told you one
of the reasons is because it doesn't exist as a free-will קרבן.
korban, But let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says ואי איתא, ve'i ita, if this principle is true
that at least it's a כשר קרבן kasher korban. by a שלמים,
shlamim, ליגמר משלמים. ligmar mishlamim. So let's learn out from שלמים, shlamim,
the same way שלמים shlamim two years old is good, maybe אשם
asham two years old is good. And the question
is not as absurd as it sounds because remember, we do
have an idea of an אשם asham that counts without it coming
as an obligation, when the אשם asham is done שלא לשמו. shelo
lishmo. Like שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's a good קרבן, korban. but
no obligation is satisfied. So let's say the same is true when
the אשם asham is two years old, that it'll be a good
קרבן korban and no obligation will be satisfied and let's learn it
out from a שלמים shlamim because that's what you say occurs by
a שלמים. shlamim. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שלמים משלמים גמר.
shlamim mishlamim gamar. We can learn שלמים Shlamim from a שלמים. Shlamim.
The fact that there's a שלמים Shlamim of, you know, of a
free will that two years old is good, we can say a
שלמים Shlamim of an obligation two years old will be a good
קרבן. korban, However, אשם משלמים לא גמר. Asham mi-Shlamim lo gamar. We
can't learn אשם Asham from a שלמים Shlamim and therefore we can't
say that because a two-year-old שלמים Shlamim works, a two-year-old אשם Asham
will. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but learn it out from
an אשם. Asham. So the גמרא Gemara says ואם גמר שלמים משלמים
ve-im gamar Shlamim mi-Shlamim if you can learn a שלמים Shlamim from
a שלמים, Shlamim, say תיתי היתרת teti hayteret two years old will
be a good קרבן korban the same way there's such a thing
as a two-year-old שלמים, Shlamim, ניגמר נמי אשם מאשם. nigmar nami Asham
me-Asham. Let's learn out an אשם Asham from an אשם. Asham. אשם
נזיר ואשם מצורע, Asham Nazir ve-Asham Metzora, those two אשמות Ashamos which
are one-year-old animals, ואשם גזילות ואשם מעילות ve-Asham gezelot ve-Asham me'ilot from
an אשם גזילות ואשם מעילות Asham gezelot ve-Asham me'ilot which are two-year-old
and we'll say okay, this אשם Asham was wrong, it was supposed
to be one year old it's two years old, but there is
such a thing as a two-year-old אשם Asham so we'll let this
count and there'll be you won't fulfill your obligation but at least
it'll count as a good קרבן korban. because such a thing exists.
Now before we said that we're not going to say that because
such a thing doesn't exist as free will. Okay, but here the
גמרא Gemara wants to push it even further and say forget that
why don't we just say such a phenomenon exists נשקפה לך, nishkafa
lach, it still counts as a good קרבן. korban So let's see
what the answer is. גמרא Gemara says oh or you know if
the reverse happened let's learn it the other way. You brought a
one-year-old when it was supposed to be a two-year-old, אשם גזילות ואשם
מעילות מאשם נזיר ואשם מצורע, Asham gezelot ve-Asham me'ilot me-Asham Nazir ve-Asham
Metzora, let's learn the other way. So why don't we tolerate difference
in age by an אשם Asham since that phenomenon of different-aged אשמות
Ashamos do exist and say that at least it's okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, אמר שימי בר אשי, Amar Shimi bar Ashi,
דנין דבר שלא בהכשרו מדבר שלא בהכשרו. donin davar she-lo be-hachshero mi-davar
she-lo be-hachshero. You can learn one thing that's done incorrectly from another
case that's done incorrectly. ואין דנין דבר שלא בהכשרו מדבר שבהכשרו. ve-ein
donin davar she-lo be-hachshero mi-davar she-be-hachshero. You can't learn from an incorrect
case to a correct case. What does that mean? It means like
this. When we say תיתי היתרת teti hayteret two-year-old still counts, it's
not just because there's such a thing as a two-year-old שלמים. Shlamim.
It's also because what I told you earlier, that even if I
made a נדר neder to bring a one-year-old שלמים Shlamim and I
brought a two-year-old שלמים, Shlamim, the קרבן korban would still be כשר.
kasher, Again, I won't fulfill my obligation but the קרבן korban. would
be כשר. kasher So now we have a perfect analogy. We could
say מאי תיתי היתרת mai teti hayteret where it was supposed to
be one-year-old it was two-year-old, at least it should still be a
כשר קרבן kasher korban. because I know such a thing is true
by שלמים. Shlamim. I know if you're supposed to bring a one-year-old
שלמים Shlamim as a נדר neder and you brought a two-year-old it's
still a כשר kasher. קרבן. korban So I can say here too
as an obligation, it was supposed to be one year old it
was two years old, it's still a כשר kasher. קרבן. korban I
can make that analogy. There it was I did it wrong and
it was still good. I didn't fulfill my obligation but it was
good. So here I did it wrong and it's still good. But
it doesn't work by an אשם. Asham. What are you going to
say by an אשם? Asham? I was supposed to bring a one-year-old
אשם Asham and I brought a two-year-old, let it still be good
because two-year-old אשמות Ashamos exist. But that's when you're supposed to bring
a two-year-old אשם. Asham. We don't have an example where you did
it wrong and it's still good. So you can't learn out דבר
שלא בהכשרו, davar she-lo be-hachshero, you did this case wrong, you brought
a two-year-old, from דבר שבהכשרו, davar she-be-hachshero, when it was supposed to
be when it's supposed to be a two-year-old. יישר כח, Yishar koach,
if it's supposed to be a two-year-old it's good, but the question
is was supposed to be a one-year-old and you did a two-year-old
will that be good. So that you can't learn out. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולא, velo, can you not, והתניא, ve-ha tanya, this
is a thing the גמרא Gemara loves quoting as the one time
we seem to do this type of a learning out, מנין ליוצא
שאם עלה לא ירד. minayin le-yotzei she-im ala lo yered. Remember the
principle that things that are פסול pasul that you put on the
מזבח, mizbeach, once you put them on the מזבח mizbeach and they
start and they're burning you don't have to take them off the
מזבח. mizbeach. One of those examples, one of the cases is if
it went out of the מקדש, Mikdash, it's a יוצא, yotzei, now
you put it on. How do you know that that thing you
don't have to take off? שהרי יוצא כשר בבמה she-harei yotzei kasher
be-bamah because we know יוצא yotzei is not so bad. How do
we know יוצא yotzei is not so bad? Because at the time
of במות bamos there was no problem of being out as the
מקדש. Mikdash. The problem is at the time of במות bamos it
wasn't that we tolerated the פסול psul of יוצא, yotzei, at the
time of במות bamos there was no phenomenon of יוצא. yotzei. There
was no problem, there was no such thing as יוצא, yotzei, you
could bring it anywhere. So גמרא Gemara says אלמא alma we just
did it. We said even when you did something wrong with יוצא,
yotzei, I'll say it's not so bad because there was a time
when יוצא yotzei isn't a problem. So that's learning a violation, דבר
שלא בהכשרו, davar she-lo be-hachshero, from something that actually is fundamentally okay.
הא, ha, we're doing it. גמרא Gemara says no, top of מ"ט
ע"א, mem-tet amud aleph, כאן אהא ד"זאת תורת העולה" ריבה סמך. kan
a-ha de-zot torat ha-olah riba samech. And the תנא Tanna is relying
on the ריבוי, ribui, the inclusion of the phrase of זאת תורת
העולה. zot torat ha-olah. זאת תורת העולה, zot torat ha-olah, you know,
says that anything that's put on the מזבח mizbeach gets to stay.
Now it's not really anything, there are some exceptions, but in principle
pretty much everything. So therefore we're not really learning out from במה.
bamah. במה bamah was just thrown in as a nice little comparison.
But we're really saying any פסול psul that's on the מזבח, mizbeach,
pretty much any standard פסול psul gets to stay. gets to stay
on the מזבח Mizbeach and we're not learning out מדבר שבחובה. Midavar
Shebachovah. So the upshot of this is that if you did the
שלמים Shelamim or the עולה, Olah, the obligatory one, and it was
too old, we tolerate that because we know that such a such
a thing exists for שלמים Shelamim and exists for an עולה. Olah.
And not only does it exist בהכשרו, Behechshero, it even exists שלא
בהכשרו. Shelo Behechshero. That even if I was supposed to bring one
type of a שלמים Shelamim as a נדר Neder and I brought
another one, it still counts as a good קרבן. Korban. So even
when it's true by a חובה Chovah and I do the change,
the קרבן Korban is good even though I don't fulfill my obligation.
But by an אשם Asham it's not that way. In אשם Asham
there's no such thing as an אשם Asham of a נדר. Neder.
So I can't just say at as if I סתם Stam brought
an אשם. Asham. And also the only example of an אשם Asham
of other years is when it's בהכשרו. Behechshero. It's supposed to be
that way. We have no example where those violations are tolerated. Okay,
so now we end with that point. Now we move on. And
actually this next גמרא, Gemara, which is about כבשי עצרת, Kivsei Atzeret,
probably should have been one of the first גמרות Gemarot in זבחים.
Zevachim. Why? Because so much of זבחים Zevachim was about when you
שחט Shacht something שלא לשמו, Shelo Lishmo, right? And there's one important
question we never asked, or maybe you guys asked, but we never
the גמרא Gemara never asked in the whole 30-40 פרקים Prakim of
זבחים Zevachim where we talked about שלא לשמו, Shelo Lishmo, which is
what? What does שלא לשמו Shelo Lishmo mean? I שחט Shacht a
חטאת Chatas לשם Leshem שלמים Shelamim or שלמים Shelamim לשם Leshem עולה.
Olah. Does it mean I know it's a שלמים Shelamim and I'm
trying to make it an עולה, Olah, or does it mean that
I made a mistake and I think it's an עולה? Olah? And
is that also is a mistake also considered שלא לשמו? Shelo Lishmo?
That's a pretty basic question which we've never asked. Here we're asking
that question. So let's take a look. Okay, תני רבה בר בר
חנה קמיה דרב. Tani Rabbah bar bar Chana kimei d'Rav. So רבה
בר בר חנה Rabbah bar bar Chana taught in front of רב.
Rav. כבשי עצרת ששחטן לשום אילים כשרים. Kivsei Atzeret sheshachtan lishum Eilim
kesherim. So you had lambs, which is supposed to be lambs, that's
what we've been talking about, okay, but you basically think that they're
rams. And you're saying I'm שחט-ing Shacht these things, these rams. I'm
שחט-ing Shacht these rams of עצרת. Atzeret. That's what you say. You
think they're rams. Does that invalidate them? They're actually lambs, they're the
correct animal. You just have this crazy thought in your head. Okay?
So he says כשרים ולא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה. Kesherim v'lo alu
l'baalim l'shem chovah. They're כשר Kasher but the owners did not fulfill
their obligation. Now we've never heard of a שלא לשמו Shelo Lishmo
about thinking in your mind that it's the wrong animal, okay? We've
thought about thinking that it's the wrong קרבן, Korban, the wrong בעלים,
Baalim, not thinking it's the wrong animal. He says you're thinking in
your mind it's the wrong animal, that's going to be a פסול.
Psul. It's like שלא לשמו. Shelo Lishmo. So אמר ליה רב, Amar
lei Rav, so רב Rav said back to him, אלו ואלו, Alu
v'alu, give me a break, it's fine, it's fine, okay, it's not
a problem. So you thought they were rams, who cares? Okay, אמר
רב חסדא. Amar Rav Chisda. Now in us to me it makes
a lot of sense, has everything because as I said, who ever
heard of a פסול Psul of שלא לשם Shelo Leshem the right
animal? Okay, the whole idea that קא פסיל ka pasil is a
חידוש. Chidush. But the גמרא Gemara thinks that רב Rav is not
so obvious that it's כשר, Kasher, and it's going to limit what
רב Rav just said. So let's take a look. So אמר רב
חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, מסתברא מילתא דרב, Mistavra milta d'Rav, what רב
Rav said that it's כשר, Kasher, that makes sense, בכסבור אילים ושחטן
לשום כבשים. Bechasavur Eilim v'shachtan lishum Kevashim. That the reason that you
were making an honest mistake. You thought they were rams, and however,
ושחטן לשום כבשים, V'shachtan lishum Kevashim, so basically really limiting רב's Rav
statement, not only you were making an honest mistake, they were lambs,
you said to yourself what the heck is he doing? They're bringing
me rams here for כבשי עצרת. Kivsei Atzeret. They shouldn't be doing
that. When you thought they were rams. They weren't, they were lambs.
That's your case. You don't even know how old they are. So
then when you come to שחט Shacht it you say I'm going
to שחט Shacht these as if they were lambs. They should have
been lambs. For some reason somebody made a mistake brought me rams.
I'm going to שחט Shacht them as if they were lambs. So
in this case the animals are right, what's going on in your
head is right. The animals are lambs, you're thinking lambs. It's just
you happened to be thinking that they're rams. Big deal. We've never
heard that that was a פסול Psul thinking that there were some
mistakes that happened. That would be when רב Rav says it's okay.
אבל כסבור אילים ושחטן לשום אילים, Aval kasavur Eilim v'shachtan lishum Eilim,
if you think they're rams and you're שחט-ing Shacht them as rams,
לא, Lo, that would not be a good קרבן. Korban. Why not?
If you really think they're rams and you שחט Shacht them as
rams, עקירה בטעות הוי עקירה. Akira b'taut havi akira. Even an honest
mistake is still a mistake. Okay? And an עקירה בטעות, Akira b'taut,
an uprooting their definition, changing the definition, even though it's in error,
that's an honest mistake, it still changed the definition. So if you
think they're rams even though you know you're making an honest mistake
and you're saying I'm שחט-ing Shacht these rams, you've redefined them as
not a קרבן. Korban. at אתנן *atnan* כבשי עצרת ופסח *Kivsei Atzeret
u-Pesach*. So there's two חידושים *chidushim* here. חידוש *Chidush* one, which the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just totally glosses over, which to me is a
huge חידוש *chidush*, is that you can פסול pasul *pasul* something, being
יוצא *yotzei*, not פסול pasul פסול passul *pasul pasul*, but it's you're
no longer יוצא *yotzei*, not by just saying שלא לשמו Shelo Lishmo,
*shelo lishma* or לא לשם בעלים *lo l'shem be'alim*, but by saying
that by redefining the animal in front of you. If you're saying
this is a ram and it's a lamb and a ram is
not כשר kasher *kasher*, you've actually said that therefore it can't be
the קרבן korban. *korban* it's supposed to be, and therefore you have
פסול *pasul*-ed. So one is this new category of לשם אילים *l'shem
eilim*, which we never heard before. But the thing the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s going to focus on, which as I said should have been
discussed at the very first דף *daf* of זבחים Zvachim. *Zevachim*, is
what if it's an honest mistake. So here he is saying if
you're honestly making a mistake and you think that it's a ram,
I don't care. An honest mistake is still a mistake, and therefore
it's still going to be פסול *pasul*. Okay? Not פסול *pasul*. You're
not going to be יוצא *yotzei*, meaning the קרבן korban, *korban* is
כשר *kasher*, but it doesn't count as כבשי עצרת *Kivsei Atzeret*. An
honest mistake is still a mistake. That's what he says. And now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to say not necessarily. ורבא אמר *VeRava
amar*, however, רבא Rava *Rava* says עקירה Akira בטעות b'taos לא הויא
עקירה akira. *Akira b'ta'us lo havei akira*. No, if it's an honest
mistake, it's not a problem. Therefore you didn't consciously change their definition,
you just thought they were rams, and therefore that thought is not
valid. And presumably this now would have an effect on all of
זבחים *Zevachim*. When I'm שוחט *shechting* a שלמים shlamim *shlamim* לשם עולה
*l'shem olah* or whatever I'm doing, where we say לא עלו לבעלים
לשם חובה *lo alu l'be'alim l'shem chova*, according to רבא Rava, *Rava*,
that's only when I know it's a שלמים shlamim, *shlamim* and I'm
trying to make it an עולה *olah*. But if I genuinely thought
it was an עולה *olah*, it was an עקירה בטעות *akira b'ta'us*
and I was just making a mistake, now all of a sudden
the קרבן korban *korban* is totally כשר *kasher*. So for everybody who
doesn't have Rivka online or whatever is I think also Yehuda dropped
off, because I know all the people that were so bothered for
all of זבחים *Zevachim* of oh my God the כהן Kohen, *kohen*
is פסול *pasul*-ing up the קרבן korban, *korban* and he gets away
with it, I mean there still are cases like that, but actually
that any honest mistake according to רבא *Rava* is not a problem,
does not change the definition of the קרבן korban *korban*. That's a
huge point that should have been made many many מסכתות *masechtos* ago.
So let's take a look. Okay, so let's at least try to
finish to the משנה *mishna*, go a few more minutes. אמר רבא
ומותבינן אשמעתיה *Amar Rava u'masvinan ashmateih*. So רבא *Rava* said that we
ask on our whole discussion from the following משנה *mishna*. הכהנים שפיגלו
במקדש *Hakohanim shepiglu b'mikdash*, this is a משנה *mishna* in גיטין *Gittin*
and this does talk about the fiscal financial liability that happens when
they פסול *pasul* a קרבן korban. *korban*. If the כהנים *kohanim* did
פיגול pigul *pigul*, מזידין *mezidin* if they were willful and intentional, חייבין
*chayavin* then they have to compensate the owner because they invalidated the
owner's קרבן korban, *korban*. השוגגין *Hashogegin* implicitly if they did it unintentionally,
פטורין *pturin* they don't have to compensate. Okay, that's compensation, but nevertheless
ותניא פיגולן פיגול pigul, *vetanya pigulan pigul*. They still have made פיגול
*pigul*. So you unintentionally made somebody's קרבן Korban *korban* פיגול *pigul*, because
it was an accident you don't have to compensate the person, but
nevertheless it still is פיגול *pigul*. So what is this פיגול *pigul*
that's unintentional? That sounds like an honest mistake. Okay, and isn't this
an example that an honest mistake is still a mistake and is
still a problem? So let's take a look. פיגול *Pigul*, the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* says היכי דמי Heichi dami, *heichi dami*, what's the case?
אילימא דכסבור דחטאת היא וקמחשיב לה לשם שלמים shlamim *Ilima diksavor d'chatas
hi ve'kamachshev lah l'shem shlamim*. So here's the way the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s going to say how could you have a mistake by פיגול
*pigul*? What does that mean? So it means that you thought it
was the wrong קרבן *korban*. It's a חטאת chatas, *chatas* which is
only eaten for one day, you thought it was a שלמים *shlamim*
two days, so you were planning on eating it tomorrow. So that's
a פיגול *pigul* thought, because the planning on eating it tomorrow. But
that's because you made a mistake. You thought it was a שלמים
*shlamim*, an honest mistake. So that's true. הוא וקמחשיב לה לשם שלמים
*Hu vekamachshev lah l'shem shlamim*. You think it's a שלמים *shlamim* and
therefore you're planning to eat it tomorrow like a שלמים *shlamim*. וקתני
פיגולן פיגול *v'kasani pigulan pigul*, it still counts as פיגול *pigul*. אלמא
*Alma* you see עקירה בטעות הויא עקירה akira b'taos havya akira, *akira
b'ta'us havei akira*. Redefining its identity even though it was a mistake
still redefined its identity and still creates פיגול *pigul*. Now it doesn't
really do that, because actually that's actually a fascinating point, right? If
I say to you, if you שחט *shecht*-ed a חטאת לשם שלמים
*chatas l'shem shlamim* and you were planning on eating it tomorrow, what
I would have said would have been that would have been a
שחיטה שלא לשמו Shelo Lishmo *shchita shelo lishma* and לא עלה לבעלים
לשם חובה *lo ala l'be'alim l'shem chova*. I'm not sure I would
have said פיגול *pigul*. I would have said that's basically redefining it
as a שלמים *shlamim*, not as a and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
phrases it as עקירה *akira* is a funny phrase. עקירה *Akira* means
redefining. Actually here we're saying it's פיגול *pigul*. So the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara*'s bracketing all of that. It's saying nevertheless the point is even
an honest mistake, I ignore the fact that it was an honest
mistake, I said you were still planning on eating it tomorrow, that
makes פיגול *pigul*. So there you see mistakes an honest mistake does
not get you off, does not change the הלכה Halacha *halacha*. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. אמר ליה אביי Amar lei
Abaye, *Amar lei Abaye*, אביי Abaye *Abaye* said back, לעולם דידע דחטאת
היא *le'olam deyada d'chatas hi*, so what does it mean that You
thought it was permissible, meaning the שוגג shogeg doesn't have to be
in the act, the שוגג shogeg can be in the violation. When
we say for example, you know when you say "Oh, I didn't
realize," what like "Oh, I did this on שבת, Shabbos, I didn't
realize." What didn't you realize? You didn't realize it was שבת Shabbos
or you didn't realize it was אסור assur to do it? Okay,
so that's what we're saying. When we say if you're a שוגג
shogeg כהן, you don't have to compensate, it says, "Oh yeah, I
knew I was thinking the wrong thing, I knew I'm only supposed
to eat it today and I was thinking to eat it tomorrow,
but I didn't realize it was going to פסול the קרבן. I
wasn't in class that day, nobody told me that." Okay, so that's
the שוגג that he doesn't have to compensate, when he didn't realize
it was פסול the קרבן, but not that he made an honest
mistake about the קרבן's identity. Well, which is which? If you made
an honest mistake about the identity... if you made an honest mistake,
we're trying to say if you made an honest mistake about the
identity of the קרבן, you thought it was a שלמים and it
was a שלמים, you thought it was a שלמים and it was
חטאת, then your thought had no effect. Okay? When you are actually...
when your thought which is the problem one was not because you're
consciously redefining the קרבן but because you actually genuinely think it's something
else, then that does not affect the status of the קרבן. עקירה
בטעות is not an עקירה. So what's the case where you made
פיגול but you don't pay? Where you knew what you were doing,
but you thought it wasn't a violation. Okay, not not a violation,
you thought it would not create פיגול, you thought it wouldn't invalidate
the קרבן, but you very much knew what you were doing, you
knew that you were having a wrong thought. Okay, so now the
גמרא says like this: מתיב רב זירא, Masiv Rav Zeira, רב זירא
Rav Zeira asks from the following: רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer.
Okay, and this is just one last case and with this we'll
wrap up. כל מנחות שנקמצו שלא לשמן כשרות. Kol menachos shenikmetzu shelo
lishmon kshairos. Remember רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he was great. He says,
"I don't care what thinking you're having thought you're having by a
מנחה mincha because the physical reality defines what type of a מנחה
mincha it is." Right? Remember that from a long time back? כל
מנחות שנקמצו שלא לשמן, Kol menachos shenikmetzu shelo lishmon, if you do
it with the wrong type of a מנחה mincha in mind, כשרות,
kshairos, they're כשרות kshairos ועלו לבעלים לשום חובה v'alu l'be'alim l'shum chova
and you fulfill your obligation. Your שלא לשמה shelo lishmo has no
effect. Why? שאינו מן הזבחים דומה לזבחים, She'eino min hazevachim domeh lizevachim,
they're not like animal sacrifices. שהקומץ מחבת לשום מרחשת, Shehakometz machvas l'shum
marcheshes, if you're doing a מחבת machvas and you're thinking it's a
מרחשת, marcheshes, מעשיה מוכיחין עליה שהיא מחבת. ma'aseha mochiachin aleha shehi machvas.
The type of amount of oil and the vessel it's in shows
that it's a מחבת, machvas, your thought is irrelevant. חריבה לשום בלולה,
Chariva l'shum blula, if it's a מנחה mincha without oil and you're
thinking in your mind, "Oh, I'm doing this as a מנחה mincha
with the oil," מעשיה מוכיחין עליה שהיא חריבה. ma'aseha mochiachin aleha shehi
chariva. Who cares about what you're thinking? It's self-evident that it's a
חריבה. chariva. So therefore your thought cannot change the status and it's
totally כשר and the owners fulfilled their obligation. אבל בזבחים אינו כן,
Aval bizevachim eino kein, this is not the way it is by
animal sacrifices. שחיטה אחת לכולן, קבלה אחת לכולן, זריקה אחת לכולן. Shechita
achas l'kulan, kabala achas l'kulan, zrika achas l'kulan. It all looks the
same and therefore your מחשבה machshava matters. But your מחשבה machshava doesn't
matter by a מנחה mincha because it's self-evident. Now how is this
relevant for our discussion? היכי דמי, what's the case where you're having
this wrong thought by this מנחה? mincha? אילימא דידע דמחבת היא וקא
קמץ לה לשום מרחשת, Eileima d'yada d'machvas hi v'ka kametz lah l'shum
marcheshes, you know it's a מחבת machvas and you're thinking it's a
מרחשת. marcheshes. So the גמרא says why would why would רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon say that we can tolerate your thought? כי מעשיה מוכיחין
מאי הוה, Ki ma'aseha mochiachin mai hava, who cares that it's self-evident?
הא מעקר קא עקר ליה. Ha me'aker ka akir lei. The גמרא
is saying like this, if you are willfully trying to redefine it,
"This is a מחבת machvas and you know it's a מחבת machvas
and I say even though it's a מחבת machvas I'm doing this
as if it's a מרחשת," marcheshes, presumably רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
agree that your thought matters there, you're willfully redefining it. So that
can't be the case. So if so... מאי הוה? mai hava? Says
גמרא, אלא לאו דקסבר מרחשת היא וקא קמץ לה לשום מרחשת. ella
lav d'kasavar marcheshes hi v'ka kametz lah l'shum marcheshes. So what רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says is that we use the context to define
is when you're making an honest mistake. Okay? You thought it was
a מרחשת marcheshes and that was your honest mistake. וטעה. v'ta'ah. And
there we say דהכא הוא דמעשיה מוכיחין עליה. d'hacha hu d'ma'aseha mochiachin
aleha. There your thought doesn't redefine it because the context makes it
clear what it is. Okay, so therefore we think that we're talking
here that it was an honest mistake and the reason it gets
salvaged is because the physical reality makes itself evident. הא בעלמא, Ha
b'alma, were it not the case of מעשיה מוכיחין, ma'aseha mochiachin, if
it were not that the context made it evident, עקירה בטעות הויא
עקירה, even an honest mistake is still a problem. Okay, so that's
a pretty good point, the גמרא says, that if רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says I ignore your כוונה, kavana, presumably it's not when your
כוונה kavana is a willful redefinition, presumably it's when your כוונה kavana
was an honest mistake and therefore by a מנחה mincha he can
ignore it. But normally an honest mistake is still a problem. So
the גמרא said no, not necessarily. אמר ליה אביי, אביי said back,
לעולם דידע דמחבת היא, le'olam d'yada d'machvas hi, you know it's a
מחבת machvas וקא קמץ לה לשום מרחשת v'ka kametz lah l'shum marcheshes
and you're trying to redefine it. Yes, you are willfully trying to
redefine it and nevertheless רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon doesn't care about how
explicit willful your thought is. דקאמרת כי מעשה מוכיח למאי הוה, D'ka
amart ki ma'aseh mokhiach le-mai haveh, you said who cares that the
physical reality makes it evident. So רבא לטעמיה, Rava le-taimei, yes, רבא
goes according to his reasoning because this was all going back to
רבא, דאמר רבא מחשבה דלא מינכרא פסל רחמנא, d'amar Rava machshava d'lo
minkara pasal Rachmana, if your thought is not obviously wrong then the
Torah, then your thought matters. מחשבה דמינכרא לא פסל רחמנא, machshava d'minkara
lo pasal Rachmana, if your thought is obviously wrong, it would not
invalidate. So yes, you could be willfully trying to redefine it and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon could say I don't care that you're trying
to redefine it. If the physical reality makes it clear what this
מנחה Mincha is, your attempt to redefine it has no impact. Only
by קרבנות Korbanos where the physical reality is not clear does your
intent make a difference, does your thought make a difference. So at
the end of this גמרא, all of a sudden we've discovered that
there's a possibility that every single case of שלא לשמו, Shelo Lishmo
if it was an honest mistake, is not a problem. That all
the cases of שלא לשמו that we've been learning for the last
four months are only when you know what the קרבן is but
you're willfully trying to redefine it. And the גמרא does not have
a conclusion about that. What is the הלכה about a שלא לשמו
if it is an honest mistake? Is that considered enough to make
to פסול or do we say no, that's just a mistake, that's
not a redefinition? And we end with that which is really a
question that goes all the way through זבחים.