Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ז, mem zayin,
מנחות menachos 47. We are a little bit behind, we pick up
on מ"ו mem vav עמוד ב', amud beis, the one, two,
three, let's see, no sorry, two lines in the wide lines, end
of the line, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Okay, so we'll see if
we can catch up today and maybe even get a little ahead.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught, again מ"ו mem vav עמוד
ב', amud beis, second wide line at the end. שתי הלחם הבאות
בפני עצמן. shtei halechem haba'os bifnei atzman. So if you have the
שתי הלחם shtei halechem coming by themselves, and this is following Rabbi
Akiva that says that they can come without the שני כבשים, shnei
kevasim, but we have yet to discuss well where's the מתיר, matir,
where's the thing put on the מזבח mizbeach to make them permissible?
So let's take a look. יונפו ותעובר צורתן. yunfu v'tu'avar tzurasan. It
says let them be waved and let them... ותעובר צורתן v'tu'avar tzurasan
is normally a phrase that means, literally means
their shape, their visage be degraded, which basically means let them sleep
stay overnight and they become invalid through לינה. lina. ויצאו לבית השריפה,
v'yeitz'u l'veis hasereifa, now that they're פסול pasul because
they've... they're נותר, nosar, now you go ahead and you burn them.
Okay, so this is clearly working within Rabbi Akiva that they can
come by themselves, but the גמרא gemara is going to say well
make up your mind what their status is. Okay, ממה נפשך, manafshach,
like you know, make up your mind, you know, which way do
you want to go. אי לאכילה אתיין, ee l'achila asyan, if according
to Rabbi Akiva you can bring the שתי הלחם shtei halechem when
you bring the שתי הלחם shtei halechem by themselves, you know, they
can be eaten, they don't need a מתיר, matir, which is a
bizarre idea, but maybe that's the case, so ליכלו, lichlu, so eat
them. אי לשריפה אתיין, ee l'sereifa asyan, if Rabbi Akiva is saying
no, you can bring them by themselves because they don't have a
מתיר matir they can't be eaten. So if they can't be eaten
the only thing you can do is burn them. So לישרפינהו לאלתר,
lishrifinu l'alter, so burn them right away. What is this middle position,
wait till they become invalid, you know, and they become נותר nosar
and then burn them the next morning? למה להו עיבור צורה, lamma
lahu ibbur tzurah, why do you have to wait till the next
morning? אמר רבה, amar rabba, says רבה. rabba. רבה, rabba, לעולם לאכילה
אתיין. l'olam l'achila asyan. Okay, according to Rabbi Akiva fundamentally when they
come by themselves even without a מתיר matir you can eat the
שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. גזירה, gezeirah, and
now presumably you do some ritual with them maybe you do the
waving of them and so on. Okay, but anyway, but so then
why, so then why don't we go ahead and eat them? Why
do we burn them? So גזירה שמא יזדמנו להן כבשים לשנה הבאה,
gezeirah shema yizdamnu lahen kevasim l'shana haba'ah, because this year you only
had bread, but hopefully next year you'll have sheep. And if you
eat the bread by itself, what are you going to say next
year with the sheep?
ויאמרו, v'yomru, people will say אשתקד ishtakad last year לא אכלנו לחם
בלא כבשים, lo achalnu lechem belo kevasim, didn't we eat the bread
without the sheep? השתא נמי ניכול, hasha nami neichul, let's also eat
it this year without the sheep. So even though they come together
with the sheep, and when they come together with the sheep the
sheep is the מתיר matir and you need the זריקת הדם, zrikas
hadam, they're going to come to eat them without the... without the
זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Okay. ואינהו
לא ידעי, v'innu lo yadi, they won't realize דאשתקד לא הוו כבשים,
d'ishtakad lo hava kevasim, last year when there were no sheep, אינהו
שרו נפשייהו, innu sharei nafshaihu, they were their own מתיר, matir, you
know, even though nothing went on the מזבח. mizbeach. השתא דאיכא כבשים,
hasha d'ika kevasim, now that they have sheep, כבשים הוא דשרו ליה,
kevasim hu d'sharei lei, even Rabbi Akiva agrees that when it's the
sheep you need the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. So it's a problem
we don't want people to think you can eat the... the bread
without the... by themselves, because they'll come to think you can do
it even when there are the lambs. Okay. And therefore you don't
want to go ahead and burn them... so therefore we're not going
to eat them. We're not going to burn them right away because
now they're קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim they can be eaten in principle.
So you have to wait till they become invalid with לינה. lina.
That's a nice explanation. Okay. אמר רבה, amar rabba, רבה rabba says
מנא אמינא לה, m'na amina la, where do I know that according
to Rabbi Akiva you can in principle eat the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem when they come by themselves? דתנן, ditnan, we taught in the
משנה, mishna, אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rabbi Yehuda, העיד בן בוכרי ביבנה,
heid ben buchri b'yavneh, בן בוכרי ben buchri testified in יבנה, yavneh,
this is a case in... this is all thing by שקלים, shekalim,
okay, that כל כהן ששוקל אינו חוטא. kol kohen sheshokel eino chotei.
That if a כהן kohen contributes his שקל shekel when they did
the collection of the שקלים shekalim to, you know, around אדר adar
time in order to gather up the funds so starting in ניסן
nissan all the communal קרבנות korbanos would be brought from the new
funds that they were raising and they would be brought by communal
funds. So the question is are the כהנים kohanim obligated to contribute
or should they contribute to those funds? Why not? The קרבנות korbanos
are also brought on their behalf if they're communal קרבנות, korbanos, but
because when it so speaks in the תורה torah of collecting the
half שקל, shekel, right, it says כל העובר על הפקודים, kol ha'over
al hapikudim, all that are counted by number. And the לויים levi'im
were not included in that number, so maybe that's telling you the
לויים levi'im don't contribute. You know, it's an interesting question, right, you
know, does the rabbi... Rabbi Weiss used to say, רב אבי Rav
Avi used to say that like... that Rav Soloveitchik said to him
before he went out to serve in a community, he gave him
three... three things to pay attention to. I remember two of them.
One is basically like always be at morning מנין. minyan. But the
other one is be the first to donate when you, you know,
to the שול, shul, like for the annual appeal or whatever. You
could feel hey, the שול shul is paying
me as high... Or are the communal קרבנות korbanot also on their
behalf? So the first opinion was fundamentally they don't contribute to the
communal קרבנות. korbanot. And nevertheless he testified כהן ששוקל אינו חוטא. kohen
sheshokal eino chotei. If you want to give your שקל, shekel, you
won't be sinning, it won't be like there'll be personal funds mixed
up with the communal funds, because when you give your שקל, shekel,
you'll give it with the intent that it be totally owned by
the ציבור. tzibur. Okay. אמר ליה רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Amar leh
Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
responded and he said לא כן, lo ken, no that's not the
right approach, אלא כל כהן שאינו שוקל חוטא, elah kol kohen she’eino
shokal chotei,
that if a כהן kohen doesn't give a שקל, shekel, then he
is then he is sinning. Of course he doesn't sin if he
gives it, he sins if he doesn't give it. Okay, because a
כהן kohen is obligated to contribute to the שקלים. shekalim. אלא שהכהנים
דורשים מקרא זה לעצמן, Elah she’hakohanim dorshim mikra zeh l’atzman, but the
כהנים kohanim would like to get out of giving the שקלים, shekalim,
and they try to defend their position by interpreting the following פסוק
pasuk to their benefit. How do they interpret what's the פסוק? pasuk?
וכל מנחת כהן כליל תהיה לא תאכל. V’chol minchat kohen kalil tihiyeh
lo tei’achel. Every מנחה mincha that a כהן kohen brings should be
totally burnt, it shall not be eaten. And they and here's what
the כהנים kohanim argue, that הואיל ואומר שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים שלנו
הן, ho’il v’omeir shetei halechem v’lechem hapanim shelanu hein, if we contribute
to the communal funds, then the there are some מנחות menachot which
are communal. Which are they? The שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, the לחם
הפנים, lechem hapanim, and the עומר. omer. So if we're gonna have
a portion in those communal מנחות menachot because it's now owned by
a כהן, kohen, at least partly, you'll have to burn it. And
okay, והיך נאכלו, ve’heich ne’echelu,
how can they eat it? So therefore, if you want to be
able to eat those קרבנות, korbanot, the only way you can do
it is with us not contributing. Okay. Now the obvious answer is
is that no, if your personal מנחה mincha gets burned. A מנחה
mincha that you are part of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael and that's
communal doesn't get burned. But anyway, but that's why he says they
דרשן darshan it to their own benefit. Now how is this relevant
to us? Well, let's take a look, because it assumes that you
eat the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and you don't burn it. So
he says עלמא לאכילה אתיין, alma l’achila atyan,
clearly from this, they're assuming the שתי הלחם shtei halechem they're talking
about would be eaten.
Oh, I'm sorry, I skipped a line. הני שתי הלחם היכי דמי?
Hani shtei halechem heichi dami? Which שתי הלחם shtei halechem are we
talking about in this context? אילימא בבאות עם זבח, Ilima b’vo’ot im
sevach, if you're talking about the standard one that comes with the
with the שני כבשים, shnei kvasim, אטו תודה ולחמה מי לא נדבי
כהנים ואכלו להו? atu toda v’lachma mi lo nadvei kohanim v’achlu lehu?
Then they wouldn't have a claim, because when a כהן kohen brings
a תודה, toda, it's not that you burn the bread. They understand
that when you have a type of a thing of an animal
with bread, that's not in the Torah's category of burning a of
a מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen gets totally burned. So if
they were talking about the שתי הלחם shtei halechem with the lambs,
they wouldn't have used it in their argument, ah, we can't own
it because then you'll have to burn it. No, you already know
you don't burn the bread with lambs, you don't do that with
a
תודה. toda. אלא לאו, elah lav, so if they're using it in
their argument, they must be talking about בבאות בפני עצמן, b’vo’ot bifnei
atzman, when you would bring the you know the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem by themselves assuming like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And then oh,
bringing by itself it's just a מנחה. mincha. If we own it,
you'll have to burn it. That's why we shouldn't give the
שקל. shekel. וקתני והיך נאכלו, v’katani heich ne’echelu, okay. עלמא, alma, so
there you see, לאכילה אתיין, l’achila atyan, that even when they would
bring it by themselves, because that's the scenario they were talking about,
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem would be eaten. All right, that seems
like a pretty good proof. Let's see what אביי Abaye responds. אמר
ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, אביי Abaye said back to רבא, Rava,
לעולם בבאות עם זבח. l’olam b’vo’ot im sevach. No, no. This argument
the כהנים kohanim were making, they were talking about a שתי הלחם
shtei halechem that came with the שני כבשים. shnei kvasim. Okay, but
and and you said oh well how could they make an argument?
I mean, תודה toda you don't burn the bread of a כהן.
kohen. So he says ודקשיא לך מתודה ולחמה, v’de’kashya lach mi toda
v’lachma,
from a תודה toda and its bread, לחמי תודה לא אקרי מנחה.
lachmei toda lo ikrei mincha. The Torah says, yeah, bring bread with
a תודה, toda, but it doesn't say call it a מנחה. mincha.
שתי הלחם אקרו מנחה, shtei halechem ikru mincha, but the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem is called a מנחה, mincha, שנאמר בהקריבכם מנחה חדשה להשם.
she’ne’emar b’hakrivchem mincha chadasha l’Hashem. Okay,
so you know they're gonna say look, yes, you don't when we
bring a תודה toda we eat the bread. But that bread isn't
a מנחה. mincha. But by the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, it's called
a מנחה, mincha, and the Torah says a מנחה mincha of a
כהן kohen you have to burn it. So it has nothing to
do with coming with the animal or not coming with the animal.
So their discussion could still have been with the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem with the animals, it doesn't prove שתי הלחם shtei halechem by
themselves are supposed to be eaten. All right. רב יוסף אמר, Rav
Yosef amar, so that's within רבא's Rava answer that it should be
eaten, and maybe he wasn't able to prove it should be eaten,
but that's how he explained this middle state, גזרה gezeira because of
next year when it will come with the lambs. רב יוסף אמר,
Rav Yosef amar, רב יוסף Rav Yosef says לעולם לשריפה אתיין. l’olam
l’sreifa atyan. No, according to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, when you bring
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem by themselves, you have to burn them.
So why don't we burn them? Burn them right away? Why do
you—right, why not? לפי שאין שורפין קדשים ביום טוב lefi she-ein sorfin
kodashim beyom tov
because when do you bring the שתי הלחם? shtei halechem? On שבועות.
Shavuos. So you can't burn קדשים kodashim on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So that's why we wait till tomorrow, not because of נותר, nosar,
but just because we can't burn it on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So there's a real—this could be easily challenged. אמר ליה אביי, Amar
lei Abaye, מי דמי? mi dami? You can't compare it. התם לאו
מצותה בכך, הכא דמצותה בכך לשרפו.
Hasam lav mitzvatah be-khakh, hakha de-mitzvatah
be-khakh lisreifu. He says, no, first of all, yeah, we don't burn
קדשים kodashim on יום טוב Yom Tov when you weren't supposed to
burn them, when the הלכה halacha was eat them, and something happened
and they became טמא. tamei. So therefore, there's no יום טוב Yom
Tov need to burn them. We wait till after יום טוב. Yom
Tov. But here, if what the תורה Torah wants us to do
when שתי הלחם shtei halechem come by themselves is to burn it,
then that's the מצוה, mitzvah, then we burn it on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. מידי דהוה אפר ושעיר יום הכפורים, Midei de-hava a-par ve-sa'ir
Yom HaKippurim, like we do by the, you know, the פר ושעיר
par ve-sa'ir on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, that comes on יום טוב,
Yom Tov, שבת, Shabbos, whatever, and nevertheless we burn it because that's
the מצוה mitzvah of the day. אלא אמר רב יוסף, Ela amar
Rav Yosef, fine,
here's why. It's not because הלכתית halachically you're not allowed to burn
it, okay? But here's why you don't burn it even, you know,
on יום טוב Yom Tov itself. גזירה שמא יזדמנו להם כבשים לאחר
מכאן. Gezeira shema yizdamnu lahem kevasim le-achar mikan.
We're afraid that, you know, that you'll go ahead and you'll be
so eager to burn it, okay? And you'll burn these שתי הלחם
shtei halechem by themselves, and then before the day is out, they'll
find that they—they'll find lambs. And now you'll have destroyed the שתי
הלחם. shtei halechem. So better bring it by itself, don't burn it,
even though the הלכה halacha is that you burn it, because if
you find the lambs, then it'll be שתי הלחם shtei halechem that
came with lambs, and then you'll be able to eat it. Okay.
אמר ליה—so Amar lei אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, תינח זמן
הקרבה תנן. teinach zman hakrava tnan.
That makes sense why we don't burn it when it's possible to
bring the lambs, which is while it's still day. But לבתר הכי
לשרפינהו—why le-vasar hakhi lisreifinhu not burn it once it's nightfall? Why do
you have to wait till the next morning? Once it's nightfall, you
can't bring the lambs anymore. That could have also been asked earlier
with the רב יוסף'ס Rav Yosef's claim that it was a concern
of burning קדשים kodashim on יום טוב—just Yom Tov wait till nightfall.
Okay. So מאי תעובר צורתן—why mai te'uvar tzurasan do you have to
wait until the next morning if it's just a problem of wanting
to give an opportunity for lambs to be found? Sounds like אברהם
Avraham on הר מוריה, Har Moriah, you—you know, the lamb to be
found. Anyway, so—so the גמרא Gemara says, no.
אהיכא—no, I'm sorry, I misread that. So תינח זמן הקרבה לבתר הכי
לשרפינהו? So the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is no. מאי תעובר צורתן נמי
דקתני—when Mai te'uvar tzurasan nami de-katani it says you let their shape,
their image degrade, normally that means you wait till the next morning.
But here, it's a vague enough phrase, it means something else. Here
it means תעובר צורת הקרבתן—the te'uvar tzuras hakravatan period when they can
be offered, let that pass and then burn it. Okay. So that
way of reading it would be: they should be burned, but we're
going to wait not till the next morning, but till nightfall in
the hope that we would find the lamb. So those are two
different ways of reading what you do with the—with the הלכה halacha
that you—you bring the bread by itself but you don't eat it
and you wait and then you burn it. רבא אמר לאכילה אתיין.
Rava amar le-achila ayan. I agree with רבה Rabbah fundamentally it—it should
be eaten,
okay? וגזירה משום דרבה. Ve-gezeira mishum de-Rabbah. And the reason we don't
is the same reason that רבה Rabbah said. You know, don't eat
it by itself because next year it'll come with the lambs, and
when it comes with the lambs, you need the זריקה zrika in
order to eat it. So even this year it's coming by itself,
don't eat it by itself. Okay.
ובלאו מטעמיה. U-velav mi-tamei. But the reason that I know that you're
supposed to eat it is not רבה'ס Rabbah's reason. רבה Rabbah tries
to prove it from this whole story about the כהנים. Kohanim. I
have a better basis to say why according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva you eat it when it comes by itself. אלא מקרא—from Ela
mi-kra a פסוק. pasuk. What's the פסוק? pasuk? ואמר רבא מנא אמינא
לה—where Ve-amar Rava mana amina lah do I know from the פסוק
pasuk that you eat the bread when it comes by itself?
דכתיב מושבותיכם תביאו לחם תנופה שתים שני עשרונים, De-khtiv moshvoteichem tavi'u lechem
tenufa shtayim shnei esronim, whatever, בכורים לה'. bikurim l'Hashem. That's by the
שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, בכורים bikurim to God. So because it calls
it בכורים, bikurim, מה בכור בפני עצמן אף הלחם בפני עצמן. mah
bikur bifnei atzman af halechem bifnei atzman. And this maybe is a
basis for רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's position as well, which we didn't
say before. בכורים Bikurim come by themselves without any animal sacrifice; שתי
הלחם shtei halechem can come by themselves without any animal sacrifice.
ומנא—and U-mena from there I can go one step further: מה בכורים
לאכילה אף
שתי הלחם נמי לאכילה. mah bikurim le-achila af shtei halechem nami le-achila.
The same way you eat בכורים, bikurim, you can eat the שתי
הלחם. shtei halechem. Okay. So it works, you know, in that it's
a type of a בכורים bikurim and that actually is a very
nice model. You know, that's why you don't need a מתיר matir
and that's why you would in principle eat it. But again, we
wouldn't do that in practice because of a גזירה gezeira that when
there will be lambs, you should not get confused and think you
can eat them without the—without the—without the blood on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Okay, top of מ"ז עמוד א'. mem-zayin amud alef. So yesterday we
spoke about the idea about Then we wouldn't do that in practice
because of a גזירה gezeirah that when there will be lambs, you
should not get confused and think you can eat them without the
lambs, without the sprinkling, without the blood on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay,
top of מ"ז עמוד א'. Mem Zayin amud aleph.
So yesterday we spoke about the idea about the
שחיטה shechita being הוקקו זה לזה hukkeku ze la-ze creating a זיקה,
zikah, creating the lambs and the bread as a unit. And we
also in passing mentioned the idea when we talked about the תודה
Toda we explicitly mentioned that the שחיטה shechita also sanctifies the bread,
not just connects it to the כבשים, kvashim, but changes it from
just being owned by the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to actually being
a like having the קדושה kedusha of a קרבן korban with relevant
הלכות halachos of, you know, you can't transfer, you can't be פודה,
podeh, you can't take if you take it out it becomes invalid,
etc., out of ירושלים Yerushalayim in this case and so on. So
that's now we're going to focus on that
by the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. We said that by תודה, Toda,
now we're going to focus on it by the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem by שבועות Shavuos that the שחיטה shechita of the lambs brings
the bread to its full level of קדושה. kedusha. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabanan, our Rabbis taught of מ"ז עמוד א': Mem Zayin amud aleph:
כבשי עצרת אין מקדשין את הלחם אלא בשחיטה. Kivsei atzeres ein mekadeshim
es halechem ela bishchita. They only sanctify the bread, again distinct from
the concept of הוקק, hukkak, they only sanctify it to have a
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf only when you שחט shecht the lambs. כיצד?
Keitzad? What does this mean? שחטן לשמן וזרק דמן לשמן קידש הלחם.
Shachatam lishmo ve-zarak damam lishmo kidesh halechem. You שחט shecht it and
you sprinkled the blood correctly, now the bread is fully sanctified for
the aspects I mentioned, we'll focus on: you can't redeem it and
it becomes invalid if you take it outside. שחטן שלא
לשמן וזרק דמן שלא לשמן לא קידש הלחם. Shachatan shelo lishmo ve-zarak
damam shelo lishmo lo kidesh halechem. If you שחט shecht it שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo and did the זריקה zrika שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo,
so לא קידש הלחם. lo kidesh halechem. Now that obviously leaves open
the cases, the mixed cases. שחטן לשמן וזרק דמן שלא לשמן. Shachatam
lishmo ve-zarak damam shelo lishmo. The שחיטה shechita was done correctly and
the זריקה zrika was done incorrectly. What really sanctifies the bread? Is
it the שחיטה shechita or is it the זריקה? zrika? Okay.
So the first position is קדוש ואינו קדוש דברי רבי. Kadosh ve-eino
kadosh divrei Rabbi. It's in some, you know, middle state. Okay, it's
sanctified by the שחיטה shechita but not fully sanctified because you didn't
have the זריקה. zrika. We'll talk about what that means in a
minute. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אומר לעולם אינו קדוש עד שישחוט לשמן
ויזרוק דמן לשמן. Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon omer le-olam eino kadosh ad
sheyishchot lishmo ve-yizrok damam lishmo. No,
no קדושה kedusha is until both of them happen. Okay, if it's
just שחיטה shechita and then the זריקה zrika was not לשמו, lishmo,
it did not get any קדושה. kedusha. Its entire קדושה kedusha comes
after both a legitimate שחיטה shechita and a legitimate זריקה. zrika. All
right. So I don't want to ruin the end, but I watch
but I'll concretize it for you a little bit. So for the
הלכה halacha of when it will become invalid if you bring it
outside, when will it come to a state where you can't redeem
it, for
you know, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon, it remains
just owned by the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, no קדושת הגוף kedushas
haguf until שחיטה shechita and זריקה zrika and only after זריקה zrika
will it become can not be redeemed and will become invalid if
you bring it outside. For רבי, Rabbi, no, once the שחיטה shechita
occurs, it already gets a level of קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf,
but somehow not full. And now we're going to focus on what
does the not full mean. Okay. Okay, let's go on this one.
מאי טעמא דרבי? Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi? But before we focus on this
middle state, first let's understand where the positions are coming from. What's
the reason of רבי? Rabbi? דכתיב, De-chtiv, the פסוק pasuk says ואת
האיל יעשה זבח שלמים לה' על סל המצות. Ve-es ha-ayil ya'aseh zevach
shelamim l'Hashem al sal hamatzot.
So this is by the נזיר. Nazir. Okay, so we mentioned this
yesterday as well, but, you know, we learn things again from animals
and bread that come together. Okay, so you shall make the איל
ayil זבח שלמים zevach shelamim to ה' Hashem on the with the
מצות matzot that are brought with it. And again, the assumption is
whether it's תודה, Toda, whether it's איל נזיר, ayil Nazir, whether it's
the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, the שחיטה shechita of the animal is
sanctifies the bread to this קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf level. למימרא דשחיטה
מקדשא. Lemaymra de-shechita mekadesha. That shows the שחיטה shechita because it says
יעשה זבח ya'aseh zevach
and זבח zevach means slaughtering. Okay, so יעשה זבח שלמים לה'. ya'aseh
zevach shelamim l'Hashem. It becomes לה' l'Hashem through the שחיטה shechita and
that's when it's על סל המצות, al sal hamatzot, right? And that's
also not that but also the מצה matza comes with it. דשחיטה
מקדשא. De-shechita mekadesha. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון: Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon: יעשה
ya'aseh עד שיעשה כל עשייתו. ad she-ya'aseh kol asiyato. I agree it's
from that פסוק, pasuk, but יעשה זבח שלמים ya'aseh zevach shelamim is
you have to do all of the things for the שלמים, shelamim,
the שחיטה shechita and זריקה zrika and then it is then it
pulls along the סל המצות. sal hamatzot. ורבי, Ve-Rabbi, רבי Rabbi would
say בנמי הכתיב יעשה. benami hachtiv ya'aseh. Shouldn't יעשה ya'aseh be read
to mean all of the things? So no. He would say אי
כתיב זבח יעשה, i kesiv zevach ya'aseh, if it would have said
זבח zevach you shall do, then that means it's already a זבח
zevach and for that זבח zevach you need to do all of
the things, שחיטה, shechita, זריקה zrika and so on. Then אי דסוף
יעשה כדקאמרת, i desof ya'aseh kedeka-amart, it would be like you said.
השתא דכתיב יעשה זבח, Hashta de-chtiv ya'aseh zevach, then it says you
shall make it a זבח, zevach, so what does make it mean?
Make it into a זבח. zevach. A זבח zevach is the slaughtered
thing. So it means slaughtered it.
So במאי יעשה בזביחה, be-mai ya'aseh bi-zvicha, it's through the שחיטה shechita
that it gets its status. Okay, so that's where they learn the
debate. Is it about all the things before the bread becomes קדוש
kadosh? *kadosh* or just the שחיטה shechita *shechita* alone at least brings
it up a level of קדושה kedusha *kedusha*. And now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* okay fine. ורבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון הכתיב זבח *v'Rabbi Eliezer
b'Rabbi Shimon hachtiv zevach*, doesn't it say you know יעשה זבח *ya'aseh
zevach*, so that's shouldn't that emphasize שחיטה shechita, *shechita* is the thing
that does it? No, ההוא מיבעי ליה לכדרבי יוחנן *Hahu mibaei lei
l'chiderabbi Yochanan*. The זבח *zevach* is coming to teach you another הלכה
*halacha*. To teach you what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says.
דאמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan הכל מודים שצריך שיהא לחם lechem בשעת
שחיטה shechita *D'amar Rabbi Yochanan hakol modim shetzarich sheyei lechem b'sha'at shechita*.
Everybody agrees that it has to be bread at the time of
שחיטה shchita *shechita*. So which means that even though for רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer* it's the focus is on the זריקה zerika.
*zrika*, it is the זריקה zerika *zrika* that gives it the קדושה
kedusha *kedusha* before that nothing, but because the תורה Torah *Torah* says
זבח *zevach*, שחיטה shchita *shechita* is a critical moment and the bread
has to be around when you do the שחיטה shchita *shechita*. Okay,
if it's not around then nothing takes off. Okay,
so fine.
So that's the פסוקים *psukim* they're based on. Now we're finally going
to get, I keep on running ahead, we're finally going to get
to this question of this middle state according to רבי Rebbe, *Rebbi*.
מה קדוש kadosh. ואינו קדוש kadosh,
*mai kadosh v'eino kadosh*? What is this middle state for רבי Rebbe
*Rebbi*? אביי Abaye אמר קדוש kadosh, ואינו גמור *Abaye amar kadosh v'eino
gamur*, it's holy but it's not full, which is not so helpful,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will clarify. רבא Rava אמר קדוש kadosh, ואינו
ניתר *Rava amar kadosh v'eino nitar*, it's holy but it is not
become permissible to be eaten. So for רבא *Rava* it actually is
conceptually very very clean. Okay, the שחיטה shchita *shechita* makes it קדוש
kadosh *kadosh*, it has קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf *kdushat haguf*. You can't
redeem it, you can't, if you take it outside it becomes פסול
passul *pasul*. So what does the זריקה zerika, *zrika* do? The זריקה
zerika *zrika* is the מתיר matir. *matir*. Remember we've been talking about
זריקה zerika *zrika* being the מתיר matir. *matir* until something goes on
the מזבח mizbeach. *mizbeach* you're not allowed to eat from it. So
it has full קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf. *kdushat haguf* but when he
said it's אינו קדוש kadosh, *eino kadosh*, what he meant was you
can't eat it yet. You gotta wait for the זריקה zerika *zrika*
in order to eat it, but the קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf *kdushat
haguf* is full. That is very clean. But אביי Abaye *Abaye* seems
like he's one step earlier. It doesn't even have full קדושת הגוף
kedushas haguf. *kdushat haguf*. So what does that mean? So let's take
a look at what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. מאי mai? בינייהו
*mai beinaihu*? What's the difference between them? So איכא בינייהו למיתפס פדיונו
*ika beinaihu l'mitpas pidyono*. Can it transfer the קדושה kedusha *kedusha*? Now
there's, this is a complicated, there's different גרסאות *girsaot* here. I'm, רש"י
Rashi *Rashi*, you know, first explains the גרסא *girsa* we have and
then he says it was totally wrong, so I'm going to read
it based on the second גרסא *girsa* in רש"י Rashi *Rashi* which
רש"י *Rashi* in the end says is the only one that makes
sense. למיתפס פדיונו *l'mitpas pidyono*. So let's see,
so this should be לאביי תפיס פדיונו לרבא לא תפיס פדיונו *l'Abaye
tfis pidyono l'Rava lo tfis pidyono*, the reverse of what we have
it. For אביי *Abaye* the קדושה kedusha, *kedusha* is not yet complete.
So if the קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* is not yet complete through the
שחיטה shchita *shechita*, you can still transfer the קדושה kedusha. *kedusha*, you
can still do a פדיון *pidyon*, right? That was its status before
שחיטה shchita *shechita*, that remains its status now. Okay, for רבא *Rava*
the קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* is complete so you can't be פודה *podeh*
it. All right, so that's nice for אביי *Abaye* that the קדושה
*kedusha* is incomplete and therefore you can still be פודה *podeh* it,
but then for what purpose is it קדוש kadosh *kadosh*? So we'll
have to get back to it. Okay, but that's how we'll read
this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. בשלמא לרבא *bishlama l'Rava*, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says like this. I get according to רבא *Rava*, היינו
דאיכא בין רבי Rebbe לבין רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer ברבי שמעון *hainu
d'ika bein Rebbi l'vein Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon*. That's the difference between
רבי Rebbe? *Rebbi* and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer
b'Rabbi Shimon*. Because רבא *Rava* is saying according to רבי Rebbe *Rebbi*,
it's fully קדוש kadosh *kadosh*, you can't redeem it, you know, can't
take it out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, and
for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon*, you
know, the only thing that's not yet done with it is you're
not yet allowed to eat it. Okay, but for רבי אליעזר Rebbe
Eliezer ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon* it's not קדוש kadosh *kadosh*,
I mean it doesn't have קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf. *kdushat haguf*, you
can take it out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*,
you know, you can redeem it, etc. So that's the clear difference.
אלא לאביי מאי mai? איכא בין רבי Rebbe, לרבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון
*Ela l'Abaye mai ika bein Rebbi l'Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon*? According to
אביי *Abaye* that for רבי Rebbe, *Rebbi* it's not yet fully קדוש
kadosh. *kadosh* even after שחיטה shchita *shechita* and you can still redeem
it, so how is he disagreeing with רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer. ברבי
שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon*? In what way is it קדוש kadosh.
*kadosh* for רבי Rebbe *Rebbi*? איכא בינייהו ליפסולי ביוצא *Ika beinaihu l'ipsulei
b'yotzei*, because I've been telling you two נפקא מינות *nafka minos*. One
is can you redeem it, and the other is is it פסול
passul *pasul* if you take it out of the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash? *Beis Hamikdash*. Okay, so for אביי *Abaye* the שחיטה shchita *shechita*
makes it enough קדוש kadosh, *kadosh* that it's you know that it's
what do you call that it's that it's קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf
*kdushat haguf* and can't be redeemed now. But still, I'm sorry, I
got that wrong. Say it again. For אביי *Abaye* the שחיטה shchita
*shechita* it's, the שחיטה shechita, *shechita* alone does not yet bring it
to a status where it can't be redeemed, but it does bring
it to a status where it has enough קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf.
*kdushat haguf* that if you take it out of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* you will invalidate it. Okay, so one more
time, let's spell this out. For רבי Rebbi *Rebbi*, שחיטה shechita *shechita*
makes it קדוש kadosh *kadosh*. For רבא *Rava* according to רבי Rebbi
*Rebbi* it makes it fully קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*, but you just can't
eat it till the זריקה zerika *zrika*. Okay, and
and רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer b'Rabbi Shimon* would
say no, no
קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf. *kdushat haguf* now, no problem with
פדיון *pidyon*. And that middle state means yes it can't you can't
redeem it, but no, wait, I said said that wrong again. Yes
you can redeem it, okay? It can be redeemed in that way
it is not fully קדוש, okay? But it is פסול passul if
you take it out. And for רבי אלעזר בר שמעון, Rebbe Elazar
bar Shimon, nope, nothing, it's not even פסול passul. if you take
it out. Okay, so very interesting all the question of these middle
stages. אליבא דמאן ודלא כרבי אלעזר בר שמעון, איכא בינייהו לפסול ביוצא.
Aliba d'man v'dela k'Rebbe Elazar bar Shimon, ika beineiyhu lifsul b'yotzei. בעי
מיניה רבי שמואל בר רבי יצחק מרבי חייא בר אבא. Ba'ei minei
Rebbe Shmuel bar Rebbe Yitzchak miRebbe Chiyya bar Abba. Okay, so Shmuel...
so that was the end of that discussion about, you know, different
stages of sanctifying the bread, רבי, Rebbi you know, within רבי Rebbi,
debates and then רבי אלעזר בר שמעון. Rebbe Elazar bar Shimon. Okay.
Okay. בעי מיניה רבי יצחק מרבי חייא בר אבא. Ba'ei minei Rebbe
Yitzchak miRebbe Chiyya bar Abba. כבשי עצרת ששחטן לשמן וזרק דמן שלא
לשמן, אותו לחם מהו באכילה? Kivsei atzeret sheshachtan lishmon v'zarak daman shelo
lishmon, oso lechem mahu ba'achila?
Okay,
so now you slaughtered it לשמה lishma and you did the זריקת
הדם zerikat hadam שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. What's the status of that
bread? All right. So this might depend, רבי Rebbi and רבי אלעזר
בר שמעון, Rebbe Elazar bar Shimon, right? Is it קדוש? When does
it define its status and so on? Can the bread be eaten?
So let's see what he says. אליבא דמאן? Aliba d'man? According to
who are you asking? Let's work it out. אי אליבא דרבי אלעזר
בר שמעון, Ei aliba d'Rebbe Elazar bar Shimon, if according to רבי
אלעזר בר שמעון, Rebbe Elazar bar Shimon, הגמר זריקה היא דמקדשה. hagmar
zerika hi d'makadsha. So it all goes by the זריקה. zerika So
when the זריקה zerika. was שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, you did not,
you know, it was not a legitimate זריקה, zerika. so the bread
never became sanctified. So you can redeem it and then eat it,
but you certainly can't eat it as קדוש. It is not a
קרבן korban that is... it is not something that has קדושה that
can be eaten, okay? The זריקה zerika never brought it to that
level. אי אליבא דרבי, Ei aliba d'Rebbe, if whether... how about רבי?
Rebbi The שחיטה shechita was good. It doesn't matter. בין לאביי בין
לרבא, קדוש ואינו ניתר. Bein l'Abaye bein l'Rava, kadosh v'eino nitar. Both
אביי and רבא agree that the זריקה zerika is still the מתיר.
matir, Even though רבי Rebbi says the קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf. comes
by the שחיטה, shechita the זריקה zerika is still the מתיר. matir
And if the זריקה Zrika. wasn't legitimate, there's no way that you're
going to be able to eat the bread. A very straightforward answer.
אלא אליבא דהאי תנא. Ella aliba dehai tana. Here's where it's an
interesting question. You're right. Within the parameters we set up right now,
everybody agrees that the זריקה Zrika is a מתיר, might even be
a מקדש. makadesh. No way you can eat it without a legitimate
זריקה. zrika But here's my question. Okay, according to the following תנא.
tana. דתני אבוה דרבי ירמיה בר אבא. D'tani avuha d'Rebbe Yirmeya bar
Abba. רבי אבוה Rebbe Avuha the son of רבי ירמיה בר אבא
Rebbe Yirmeya bar Abba teaches. שתי הלחם שיצאו בין שחיטה לזריקה. Shtei
halechem sheyatzu bein shechita l'zerika. So the bread got taken out of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash between שחיטה shechita and זריקה. zrika Let's
assume this is like רבי, Rebbi. so they're פסול passul because they're
outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, Okay, so the bread is
פסול. passul וזרק דמן של כבשים חוץ לזמנן. V'zarak daman shel kevasim
chutz l'zmanan. And then you did the זריקה zerika, of the blood
of the lambs with a thought of פיגול, piggul, to eat it
חוץ לזמנו. chutz l'zmano. All right. So here's the question. The lambs
become פיגול. piggul. Does the status of the, what do you call
it, does the פיגול piggul status also apply to the bread that
became invalid and that was brought out of the בית המקדש? Beis
HaMikdash. Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר, אין בלחם משום פיגול. Rebbe Eliezer omer,
ein balechem mishum piggul. They don't become פיגול. piggul. רבי עקיבא אומר,
יש בלחם משום פיגול. Rebbe Akiva omer, yesh balechem mishum piggul. It
does become פיגול. piggul. What's this debate? אמר רב ששת, הני תנאי
כרבי סבירא להו. Amar Rav Sheshet, hanei tana'ei k'Rebbe sevira lehu. So
I'm going to explain to you the debate. Fundamentally, they agree like
רבי, Rebbi like we said. It's קדוש, it's going to become פסול
passul with יוצא. yotzei. Even אביי agrees for רבי Rebbi, it'll become
פסול pasul with יוצא. yotzei. דאמר שחיטה מקדשת. D'amar shechita mikadeshet. So
now you brought the bread out and it's פסול pasul. for יוצא.
yotzei. מיהו, Mihu, רבי Rabbi אליעזר, so then what's... so here's the
debate. רבי אליעזר לטעמיה דאמר אין זריקה מועלת ליוצא. Rebbe Eliezer l'ta'ameih
d'amar ein zerika mo'elet l'yotzei. רבי עקיבא לטעמיה דאמר זריקה מועלת ליוצא.
Rebbe Akiva l'ta'ameih d'amar zerika mo'elet l'yotzei. Very simple. We've seen this
debate before between רבי Rabbi, אליעזר and רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, whether
זריקה zerika when you do a זריקת פיגול, zerikat piggul, right, that
makes, now the זריקה zerika itself is invalid, it's פיגול, piggul, and
it defines the whole קרבן korban as פיגול. piggul. But does it
also, would it also define as פיגול piggul parts of the קרבן
korban that already became invalid? Okay, or maybe those now are seen
as totally separate from the קרבן. korban. So let's take a look.
דתנן, D'tnan, top of מז ע"ב, mem zayin amud bet, we taught
in the משנה. Mishna. אימורי קדשים קלים שיצאו לפני זריקת דמים. Imurei
kodashim kalim sheyatzu lifnei zerikat damim. You have the אימורים, imurim, the
innards of קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. There's no מעילה me'ila by קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim because they're considered, you know, owned by the owners
and they're going to be eaten by outside of the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash There's no מעילה. me'ila. The only מעילה me'ila of קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim are the אימורים, imurim, the innards, you know, the
intestines or whatever that go up on the מזבח. mizbeach And only
once they become... because that's fully to God, and only once they're
fit for going on the מזבח Mizbeach after the זריקת הדם. zerikat
hadam. So let's say they were taken out of the בית המקדש...
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, they're פסול pasul. with יוצא, yotze, and then
you did the זריקה. zerika Does the זריקה zerika, make them now
designated for the מזבח Mizbeach? and there's מעילה Meilah or not because
they're never going to go on the מזבח? Mizbeach. So רבי אליעזר
אומר אין מועלין בהן, Rabbi Eliezer omer ein moalin bahen, there's no
מעילה Meilah because it was irrelevant to them, they're already פסול. pasul.
ואין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול ונותר וטמא. ve'ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul
venosar vetamei. Similarly, if the זריקה zerika that you had, you did
it with a פיגול pigul thought, that פיגול pigul status wouldn't apply
to them. They're already invalid. It's the second part that's relevant to
us, not the מעילה. Meilah. מעילה Meilah in theory could have been
a different question. ורבי עקיבא אומר מועלין בהן. veRabbi Akiva omer moalin
bahen. No, a מעילה Meilah status does apply to them, even though
they're completely unfit for the מזבח. mizbeach And not only that, that
makes sense I think it should make sense according to everyone, but
whatever. וחייבין עליהם משום פיגול ונותר וטמא. vechayavin aleihem mishum pigul venosar
vetamei. And you're also חייב chayav פיגול, pigul, נותר, nosar, and טמא
tamei even though they have one invalidity, they can get other invalidities
laid upon them and the זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam, the פיגול pigul
זריקת הדם zrikas hadam affects something even if it's already out of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, and already already פסול. pasul Okay, so
מאי? So
מדזריקת פיגול midezrikas pigul ונותר וטמא וחייבין
עליהם משום... מאי? מדזריקת פיגול קבעה ללחם בפיגול. midezrikas pigul kava lalechem
bepigul. So okay, so that's a very beautiful debate of רבי Rabbi
אליעזר and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, they debate whether a זריקת
פיגול zrikas pigul affects a part of the קרבן korban that's already
פסול. passul So then and it's within them that I want to
ask, does a זריקה שלא לשמה zrika shelo lishma of the שתי
הלחם Shtei HaLechem of the lambs, you know, would that make the
לחם would that, you know, would that make the bread permissible to
be eaten? Now that's a little funny, we're talking about invalidities and
he's talking about a validity, but let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay, מאי? What do we say?
So מדזריקת פיגול קבעה ללחם בפיגול ביוצא, midezrikas pigul kava lalechem bepigul
beyotze, if in a case when the stuff is יוצא, yotze, taken
out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. a שחיטת פיגול shchitas pigul
can affect the status and apply a status of פיגול pigul to
something that is, you know, invalid, that is that's already taken out
of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, Okay, so to some degree the
שחיטה shchita, even an invalid שחיטה shchita like of a פיגול pigul
can still be relevant to the other pieces of the קרבן. korban.
If that's true, כבשר, kebasar, so it look so the thing that's
out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash even though it's פסול passul
is treated like normal meat and the פיגול שחיטה pigul shchita affects
it. So זריקה שלא לשמה, zrika shelo lishma, so a זריקה zerika
that's done שלא לשמה shelo lishma of the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
which is invalid, נמי שריא ליה ללחם nami sharya lei lalechem should
also be מתיר the bread. Now there's a million points of difference.
Here we're coming we want an invalid שחיטה shchita to make something
permissible as opposed to the פיגול pigul case it imposes a bad
פיגול pigul status. The other difference of course is that in the
פיגול pigul space, you know, it's all the thing is invalid
and that's sort of is what's it's making raising the question whether
the שחיטה shchita applies to it. Here the bread isn't invalid, it's
just different from the קרבן korban itself. So it's like a lot
of point, it's not the bread the meat of the קרבן korban
itself. So a lot of points of difference. But anyway, שריא ליה
ללחם sharya lei lalechem okay, או דילמא? o dilma? What do we
say? לחומרא אמרינן לקולא לא אמרינן. lachumra amrinan lekula lo amrinan. When
do we say a פיגול pigul שחיטה affects can can have an
effect to impose a status of פיגול? pigul? Okay, but that doesn't
mean that a שחיטה שלא לשמה shchita shelo lishma can work in
a positive way to make the bread able to be eaten. All
right, you know, it's a bizarre comparison as well, right? You can
understand something that invalidates can invalidate another piece of the קרבן. korban.
Why is something that lacks validity, how would it work to make
the bread permissible? It's, you know, it's not just חומרא chumra and
קולא kula like the whole mechanism is different. Anyway, מתקיף לה רב
פפא, Masqif lah Rav Papa, ומי מאי דבאיסטו הבראי פליגי? umi mai
de'eistu habarai pligi? He says I don't even agree that that's necessarily
the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון.
Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. Who says that they're talking about, you know,
when the bread is still outside, whether the שחיטה of the, you
know, makes the bread פיגול, pigul, the שחיטה of the כבשים. kvashim.
דילמא דבאיסטו הבראי דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דאין זריקה מועלת ליוצא. dilma
de'eistu habarai dechulei alma lo pligi de'ein zrika mo'eles leyotze. Maybe when
it's outside, everybody would agree that it's bread, you know, maybe they
debate when the meat of the קרבן, korban, the אימורים imurim are
outside, the שחיטת פיגול shchitas pigul affects. But this is bread, this
is something completely different and therefore maybe everybody would agree if it's
outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. the שחיטה would not make it
פיגול. pigul. We're still in the פיגול pigul discussion, just understand their
פיגול pigul debate. Okay, so maybe everybody would agree the שחיטה of
the שני כבשים shnei kvashim would not make the bread פיגול pigul
if the bread was outside of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ובדאיילו פליגי, uvade'ailu pligi, and their debate about
whether the שחיטת פיגול shchitas pigul of שני כבשים shnei kvashim makes
the bread פיגול... pigul... In a case of יוצא yotzei was when
the bread was then brought, it went out and came back in.
So what's the debate? דרבי אליעזר de-Rabbi Eliezer סבר לה כרבי savar
la ke-Rabbi דאמר שחיטה
מקדש d'amar shechita mekadesh ופסלוהו ביוצא. u'pesalhu beyotzei. And the real question
is, did it ever become invalid? It's the רבי and רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon debate, okay? So the, so, what's
his name, רבי אליעזר here holds like רבי and says that once
you did the שחיטה, now it's going to be פסול passul. with
יוצא. yotzei. It's פסול passul. with יוצא. yotzei. You brought it out,
it's פסול. passul, You bring it back in, it remains פסול. passul
So that case, the שחיטה won't define the bread. You know, the
שחיטה'ס shechita's פיגול piggul makes the meat פיגול, piggul, you know, but
it won't make the bread that is something different from the meat,
different from the קרבן, korban, it won't make that פיגול piggul if
it's already פסול, passul if it's already יוצא. yotzei. That's what he
would hold.
ורבי עקיבא, Ve-Rabbi Akiva, who holds that it does make it פיגול,
piggul, כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון דאמר שחיטה לא מקדשא ולא מיפסלו ביוצא.
ke-Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon d'amar shechita lo mekadesha velo mipaslu beyotzei. It's
because he holds like רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon.
After שחיטה it's still not קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf, It's not פסול
passul when you take it out. You bring it back in, it's
totally like it was before. Okay, now it's a pretty funny that
they're having a discussion about פיגול piggul and they're really debating this
other more general debate. But he says maybe that's their debate, alright?
And it has nothing to do with the bread still being on
the outside. So האי מאי, hai mai, the Gemara says how can
you say that? אי אמרת בשלמא רבי עקיבא כרבי סבירא ליה דאמר
שחיטה מקדש. ei amrat bishlama Rabbi Akiva ke-Rabbi sevira lei d'amar shechita
mekadesh. If you say like we were trying to say that everybody
holds like רבי and the שחיטה makes it קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf,
and when you take it out everybody agrees that it's, that it's
פסול passul, because of
יוצא, yotzei, מקדשא להו. mekadesha lehu. היינו דקאמר רבי עקיבא דקדשי להו
בשחיטה. hainu d'ka'amar Rabbi Akiva d'kadshi lehu bishchita. So then we understand.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the שחיטה makes the bread קדוש, קדושת
הגוף. kadosh kedushas haguf. It goes out, becomes פסול passul with יוצא,
yotzei, ואתייא זריקה קבעה להו בפיגול. ve-asya zerika kav'ah lehu bepiggul. And
then the זריקה, zerika you know, makes it פיגול. piggul. That all
will work because פיגול piggul works on something that has קדושת הגוף.
kedushas haguf Okay, that, that makes sense.
אלא אי אמרת כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סבירא ליה, ela ei amrat
ke-Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon sevira lei, but you're now trying to say
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds that the bread never became invalid because
he holds like
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon דאמר זביחה לא מקדשא.
d'amar zevicha lo mekadesha. That the זביחה zevicha is not מקדש. mekadesh.
זריקת פיגול מי מקדשא. zerikas piggul mi mekadesha. So now, according to
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar Berabbi Shimon, you're going to have
to have the זריקה zerika do two things. According to רבי, the
bread was already קדוש קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. And now the question
is can the זריקה zerika. of פיגול piggul add a פיגול piggul
status to the bread? Okay, that you could have an interesting debate,
the bread is already פסול, passul. can the זריקה zerika. add a
פיגול piggul status to the bread? Okay. But according to רב אלעזר
ברבי שמעון, Rav Elazar Berabbi Shimon, that the bread doesn't have קדושת
הגוף kedushas haguf, now, you can't have פיגול piggul before the thing
has קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf,
And you now are going to try to take an invalid זריקה,
zerika a זריקה zerika, of פיגול, piggul, and you don't only want
it to impose a פיגול piggul status on the bread, you want
it to sanctify the bread and bring the bread up to a
level of קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf. An invalid זריקה zerika cannot have
that effect of raising the bread to a level of קדושת הגוף.
kedushas haguf
Okay. אלא אי אמרת כרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון סבירא ליה דאמר זביחה
לא מקדשא זריקת פיגול מי מקדשא. ela ei amrat ke-Rabbi Elazar Berabbi
Shimon sevira lei d'amar zevicha lo mekadesha zerikas piggul mi mekadesha.
How could the זריקה zerika sanctify the bread and make it פיגול?
piggul? That wouldn't make any sense to think that that's what's being
said here. And how do you know that can't happen? והאמר רב
גידל אמר רב. veha'amar Rav Gidel amar Rav. רב גידל Rav Gidel
says in the name of רב, Rav, זריקת פיגול אינה מביאה לידי
מעילה ואינה מוציאה מידי מעילה. zerikas piggul einah mevia lidei meila ve-einah
motzia midei meila. That a זריקה zerika of פיגול piggul won't make
something, won't change something's מעילה meila status because, okay, what does that
mean? אינה מביאה לידי מעילה, einah mevia lidei meila, it won't make
something מעילה meila status באמורי קדשים קלים. be-imurei kodashim kalim. The אמורי
קדשים קלים, imurei kodashim kalim, which we discussed earlier, it won't raise
them to the status of now being worthy of מעילה meila because
it's an invalid זריקה. zerika, It won't raise the קדושה to make
it worthy of מעילה. meila. ואינה מוציאה מידי מעילה, ve-einah motzia midei
meila, and it also doesn't transform the קדושה to take something out
of the מעילה meila status בבשר קדשי קדשים. bevasar kodshei kodashim. Meat
of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is the reverse what happens with the
זריקה. zrika That was all designated for God. But by קדשים קלים
kodshim kalim it was all the owners. And the זריקה zrika makes
it now fit for the מזבח and designated for God and fit
for מעילה. meila. The meat of קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is all
off limits, it's all God's. But after the זריקה, the כהנים kohanim
are allowed to eat it. So the זריקה takes it out of
the God status and makes it not worthy of מעילה. meila. And
he is saying that a זריקה of פיגול, piggul, פיגול, piggul, a
זריקה of פיגול piggul can make things פיגול. piggul. But because it's
not a valid זריקה, it can't change their other statuses. Okay, it
can't raise the level of קדושה, it can't redefine the level of
קדושה. Makes a lot of sense. So therefore there's no way רבי
עקיבא Rebbe Akiva could be saying that the זריקת פיגול zrikas piggul
works according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rebbe Elazar berabbi Shimon, because
according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar berabbi Shimon you need
the זריקה to give the bread קדושה. So it seems, makes a
lot of sense to me, but the גמרא Gemara says no.
Where were we? The גמרא Gemara says לאו איסופא דרב גידל אמר
רב? lav isosef deRav Giddel amar Rav? One minute, over there in
that discussion in the other גמרא Gemara where this position is put
forward, we challenge his claim. So not necessarily so clear. Okay, so
what have we said now? We have a fascinating debate of רבי
עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar berabbi Shimon whether
the שחיטת פיגול, shechitas piggul, זריקת פיגול zrikas piggul can make bread
that was פסול passul by יוצא yotze by the שתי הלחם Shtei
HaLechem into פיגול. piggul. The easiest way to understand it is part
of a general debate of רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, רבי אליעזר whether
זריקת פיגול zrikas piggul works on something that's already פסול. passul Okay,
and it's just part of that general debate. Okay, there's another way
of interpreting that debate which is, is that the question of whether
the bread actually ever really became פסול posul, with יוצא yotze or
not because of the debate of רבי and
רבי אלעזר. Rebbe Elazar. Excuse me, I think I'm getting mixed up
which רבי אלעזר. Rebbe Elazar.
Anyway, so רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva debates רבי אליעזר. It's רבי and
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rebbe Elazar berabbi Shimon. Anyway, so could be
the debate of רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva and רבי אליעזר is the
debate of רבי and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar berabbi Shimon
about what do you call it, about whether that bread ever became
פסול pazul with יוצא yotze or not. The גמרא Gemara questions that,
questions according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbe Elazar berabbi Shimon who
needs the זריקה to make the bread קדוש, can you have a
זריקת פיגול zrikas piggul make the bread קדוש and make it פיגול?
piggul? So that is what is being questioned right now. Anyway, all
of this was trying to say that within the approach that a
זריקת פיגול zrikas piggul can affect the status, maybe we could also
say that a זריקה שלא לשמה zrika shelo lishma could improve the
status of the bread. Although that seems strange, and as the גמרא
Gemara says, you're trying to go from חומרא chumra to קולא. kula.
Okay. בעי מיניה רבי ירמיה מרבי זירא, ba'ei minei Rebbe Yirmiya meRebbe
Zeira, new question. כבשי עצרת ששחטן לשמן ואבד הלחם מהו שיזרוק דמן
שלא לשמן להתיר בשר באכילה? kivsei Atzeres sheshachtan lishmon ve'avad halechem mahu
sheyizrok daman shelo lishmon lehatir basar be'achila? Okay, so you שחט shacht
them, the lambs לשמה, lishma, and you then lost the bread. Now
because you lost the bread after you שחט shacht it and the
bread was around, we have said that they מעכב זה את זה.
me'akev zeh es zeh. So now that you lost the bread, this
is not going to be a good קרבן korban for, you know,
for שבועות. Shavuos. It's not going to be good שלמים shlamim for
שבועות, Shavuos, the שלמי ציבור. shalmei tzibbur. It's not the שני כבשים.
shnei kevasim. Okay.
But can we fix it the following way? Can we בזרוק bizrok
the דם dam שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, which will take it out
of its status of being,
you know, the כבשי עצרת kivsei Atzeres and turn it into just
a normal שלמים? shlamim? And then we'll be able to eat it.
You know, sort of like what we did before with the תודה,
toda, let's do it here with the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and
therefore make it, and the שני כבשים, shnei kevasim, and now fine,
it won't work with the bread, but let it work as a
normal שלמים. shlamim. Okay. מהו שיזרוק דמן שלא לשמן להתיר בשר באכילה?
mahu sheyizrok daman shelo lishmon lehatir basar be'achila? To let us eat
the meat. אמר ליה יש לך דבר שאינו כשר לשמו וכשר שלא
לשמו? amar lei yesh lach davar she'eino kasher lishmo vekasher shelo lishmo?
One minute, how could something be that if you were זורק zorek
the דם dam the right way, it would be invalid because it's
an invalid שני כבשים, shnei kevasim, you know, but if you're going
to be זורק zorek it as a שלמים, shlamim, all of a
sudden you'll make it
valid? So, ולא, velo, is that not possible? והרי פסח? ve'harei Pesach?
How about the קרבן פסח? korban Pesach?
קודם חצות אינו כשר לשמו. kodem chatzos eino kasher lishmo. If it's
the fourteenth but it's before חצות chatzos and you שחט shacht for
קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, it's invalid. וכשר שלא לשמו. vekasher shelo lishmo.
But if you שחט shacht it for שלמים, shlamim, it's valid. Because
a קרבן פסח korban Pesach doesn't work in the morning of the
fourteenth, but a שלמים shlamim does. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
הכי קמיבעי ליה. hachi kamiba'ei lei. Here's what I mean. I understand
you have that, but here's my point. יש לך דבר שנראה לשמו.
yesh lach davar shenira lishmo. Do you have something that is fit
to be brought for its right reason? That wasn't yet fit. This
case of the שני כבשים, shnei kevasim, they were fit for שני
כבשים. shnei kevasim. They were in the right category. ונדחה מלשמו. venidcha
milishmo. And then now they're in a state where they can't be
brought because the bread is lost.
ואינו כשר לשמו וכשר שלא לשמו? ve'eino kasher lishmo vekasher shelo lishmo?
So how could you have something, once it gets into that category,
it can't be used for that category, now you're going to fix
it by doing it שלא לשמו? shelo lishmo? The גמרא says, ולא,
velo, is that not true? ושוב הרי פסח. veshuv harei Pesach. Again,
look at the פסח. Pesach. פסח אחר זמנו. Pesach achar zemano. פסח
Pesach after פסח. Pesach. You had this animal, you sanctified it for
a פסח, Pesach, and you lost it, you didn't bring it on
פסח, Pesach, and now it is, you know,
now it's like the month after ניסן, Nissan, okay?
It's אייר. Iyar. So in that case, בשאר ימות השנה. bish'ar yemos
hashanah. So, and if you at that case... If you שחט shecht
it as a פסח, Pesach, it is invalid. It is a פסח
Pesach שחט shechted in
אייר, Iyar, but if you go ahead and you שחט shecht שלא
לשמו, shelo lishmo, it is כשר kosher as a שלמים. shelamim. So
something was fit for a פסח, Pesach, can't be used for פסח,
Pesach, you do it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo you're okay. Why not
say the same thing here?
So the גמרא says no, הא, הכי קאמר, ha, hachi ka'amar, here's
what I mean. יש לך דבר שנראה לשמו ונשחט לשמו ונדחה מלשמו
ואינו כשר לשמו וכשר שלא לשמו?
Yesh lcha davar shenir'eh lishmo venishchat lishmo
venidcha milishmo ve'eino kasher lishmo vekasher shelo lishmo? Do you ever have
something that was fit for the right thing, it was שחט shechted
for the right thing, it was on the track of being right,
not just like a live animal of a פסח, Pesach, but it
actually was שחט shechted for the right thing and it got defined
as that thing, okay, ונדחה מלשמו venidcha milishmo and now you can't
continue doing it, like here the bread was lost, ואינו כשר לשמו
ve'eino kasher lishmo and it won't be good if you did it
לשמו, lishmo, וכשר שלא לשמו vekasher shelo lishmo and now you want
it to be כשר kasher שלא לשמו? shelo lishmo? So the גמרא
says, הא! Ha! I got something that works that way too. והרי
תודה! Veharei Toda! How about the תודה? Toda? We talked about it
yesterday.
תודה, Toda, you lose the bread even after שחיטה, you can go
ahead and be זורק הדם zorek hadam שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and
make it כשר. kosher. All we're saying is מושי Moshe should have
started that, make this like the תודה. Toda. Okay, so the גמרא
says what it said yesterday, שאני תודה דרחמנא קרייה שלמים. shani Toda
derachmana karya shelamim. תודה Toda is different, תודה Toda is a type
of a שלמים, shelamim, the תורה called it a שלמים. shelamim. So
if it stops functioning as a תודה, Toda, it can function as
a שלמים. shelamim. But these שתי הלחם, shnei halechem, the שני כבשים,
shnei hakevasim, the funny thing is they're also שלמים, shelamim, but they're
שלמי ציבור, shelmei tzibur, okay? But they never are, but you know
these are like only given their identity in terms of the bread.
And if they're not going to work in terms of the bread,
you don't have a right to actively change their identity, and if
you tried, presumably it wouldn't be valid. I don't know, is the
גמרא just talking לכתחילה lechatchila or is it even talking בדיעבד bedi'eved
that it would not work? Okay, but it seems like it's saying
that even בדיעבד bedi'eved it would not work. Alright, let's just do
a little bit more, you know, we're on such a roll, get
a little ahead. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: שחט
שני כבשים על ארבע חלות. Shechat shnei kevasim al arba chalos. Let's
say you had forty חלות, chalos, no four חלות, chalos, not the
two breads but the four loaves of bread, okay? And now you
שחט shechted the two כבשים. kevasim. So conceptually, two of those four
loaves are קדוש, you just don't know which ones. Okay, it's impossible
to determine, okay, but in the abstract, two are קדוש and two
are not. על ארבע חלות. Al arba chalos. מושך שתים מהן ועושה
תנופה, moshich shtayim mehen ve'oseh tnufo, you take two and you do
the תנופה. tnufa. Top of מ"ח ע"א. Mem Ches Amud Aleph. והשאר
נאכלות בפדיון vehashar ne'echalos bipidyon and the other is you can eat
them after you are redeeming them because you sanctified all four. Basically
what happens is you sanctified all four, the שחיטה made two of
them קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf two of them not. You sort of
don't know which ones, maybe you get to pick which ones, we'll
see. You wave two, those are the ones of קדושת הגוף, kedushas
haguf. those are the ones you'll go the distance with, and the
other two, which the שחיטה only works for, you know, for the
two loaves, is only connected to two loaves, the other two just
have your normal קדושת דמים, kedushas damim, owned by the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash. and you can redeem it. Okay, but it's still a
little funny because like how do you get to decide which two
and which two? אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב חסדא. Amru rabanan kamei deRav
Chisda. The רבנים rabbanim said this in front of
רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. הא, לא כרבי, Ha, lo keRebbi, this is
not going like רבי. Remember רבי and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון? Rabbi
Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon? דאי כרבי, de'i keRebbi, according to רבי, כיון דאמר
שחיטה מקדשה, kivan de'amar shchita mikadsha, since he says the שחיטה is
מקדש, mekadesh, and I was working with that assumption, but let's see
why they'll say it won't work. דפריק להו היכא? diparik lehu heicha?
So where are you going to redeem the loaves of bread? Where
are the loaves of bread going to be when you're actually going
to redeem two of them? אי דפריק להו מאבראי, I diparik lehu
me'avrai, if you're going to take them outside of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash, and redeem them there, so כיון דכתיב לפני השם, kivan
dechsiv lifnei Hashem, איפסלו ביוצא. ipslu beyotze. So you're going to have
to, you're not going to get to decide like which two, okay,
you don't know which two. The way רש"י says it is, you'll
have to take all four of them and you'll say, whichever two
of these are not קדושת הגוף kedushas haguf should be redeemed on
this money, and the other two should remain קדושת הגוף. kedushas haguf
Okay, so you'll have to take, so if you're going to take
all four of them outside and do that there, so then the
two that have קדושת הגוף, kedushas haguf, you don't know which two,
but two out of these four, they'll become פסול, they're outside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, איפסלו ביוצא. Ipslu beyotze. אי גוואי, I gavai,
so fine, so you'll do all of this while it's in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash חולין בעזרה? Hama'ei chulin ba'azarah? Then you're going
to be left with two loaves that are not sanctified that are
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, That's a problem of unsanctified things
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. חולין בעזרה. chulin ba'azarah. Now I
should say, you know, does that mean you can't even just have
food in your pocket in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. that's חולין
בעזרה? chulin ba'azarah? So רש"י says and then the כהנים Kohanim though
are going to eat all four loaves, because again they don't know
which are which, right? It's all in the abstract. So if they're
going to eat all four because two of them are the real
שתי הלחם, shnei halechem, then They're eating all of them as they
are, as if they are קדשים. Kodshim. Okay, and that's a problem
of חולין בעזרה. chulin b'azarah. Alright, so that's the issue. Now, you
could have also said, and רש״י Rashi points this out, you could
also said you would have to, since if that's how you're operating,
then why aren't you waving all four of them? Two are קדושת
הגוף, kedushas haguf two are not, we don't know which is which.
We're going to redeem two, whichever two they are. Okay, so besides
the חולין בעזרה chulin b'azarah question, why should, you should be waving
all four of them. Alright, anyway, but let's see how he answers
the
חולין בעזרה chulin b'azarah question. אמר ליה רב חסדא, amar lei Rav
Chisda, Rav Chisda said back, לעולם כרבי, le'olam k'Rabbi, it really, I
can make it work like Rabbi. ופורק להו גואי, ufarak lehu gavai,
and you do it in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. is where
you redeem them. וחולין ממילא קהוויין, vechulin m'meila k'havian, you're not bringing
חולין chulin into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it happens by itself.
They're already there and then they become חולין. chulin. Okay, how that
works with the point that you're going to eat them because as
if you're eating קדשים, Kodshim, not addressed, but anyway, you didn't actively
bring it in the בית המקדש. You know, it was all קדוש
and then you redeemed it, it wound up that you had חולין
chulin in the עזרה. azarah. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, amar lei
Ravina l'Rav Ashi, so Ravina said to Rav Ashi, והתניא כשהוא פודן
אין פודן אלא בחוץ. v'hatanya k'shehu podan ein podan ela bachutz.
One minute, but we have a ברייתא braisa that says that when
you redeem it, it explicitly says you redeem it out of the
בית המקדש. And that can never work if it was like Rabbi
and that they already had קדושת הגוף. So, so he says, הא
ודאי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון היא. ha vadai Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon
hi. Fine, I concede. Once you have that, it's רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון. Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon. And again, as רש״י Rashi said, if
it were רבי and you had קדושת הגוף and you didn't know
which two, you'd have to do the תנופה tnufa by all four.
So now it's very easy. According to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon, you have four, you שחט shachted it, okay, but
no קדושת הגוף yet. So fine, that works very well. Who gives,
so fine, no קדושת הגוף. You redeem two, you get to decide
which two you redeem and you do it out of the בית
המקדש. Take two out of the בית המקדש, redeem them. You know,
nothing has קדושת הגוף yet.
And then the two that are left, you know, those are the
ones you'll wave and those are the ones that you'll,
you know, will become the bread that has קדושת הגוף when you
do the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. It all works very well. Okay,
by the way, I should mention you do waving before you שחט
shacht and after you שחט. shacht. That's why we're talking that you
שחט shachted it and you still are waving it.
הא ודאי רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון היא.
ha vadai Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi
Shimon hi. דאי רבי הא איפסלו ביוצא. de'ee Rabbi ha ifsilu b'yotzei.
Because if it was Rabbi and you take them out they'll be
פסול with יוצא yotzei as we said. Let's just do a tiny
bit
more. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב לרב אשי, amar lei Rav
Acha brei d'Rav l'Rav Ashi, לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי יוחנן leima tehei
tiuvta d'Rabbi Yochanan מהא דאיתמר. meha d'itmar. תודה ששחטה על שמונים חלות.
Todah sheshachtah al shmonim chalos. So let's say this is a challenge
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan of, of a רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
that we taught by the תודה. Todah. Why? Because here's what we
teach by a תודה. Todah. You שחט shachted a תודה Todah and
again you brought double, like you brought four loaves of bread, there
you brought eighty loaves of bread, because a תודה Todah gets forty.
חזקיה אמר קדשו ארבעים מתוך שמונים. Chezkiah amar kidshu arbaim mitoch shmonim.
Forty become קדוש and not eighty. Okay, only forty out of the
eighty.
רבי יוחנן אמר לא קדשו ארבעים מתוך שמונים. Rabbi Yochanan amar lo
kidshu arbaim mitoch shmonim. So he says no, it's not forty out
of the eighty because you know if it's, if it's too big
then basically, you know,
nothing becomes קדוש. It's the wrong bread, it's eighty, nothing becomes קדוש.
Okay, so here when we said you brought four, we discussed רבי,
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon or whatever, but everybody
is assuming that the, that you know it's קדוש, you know, and
here he says when you bring too many loaves of bread there's
no קדושה. So isn't this a challenge? So it says no. ולאו
איתמר עלה. v'lav itmar alah. It was taught about that, אמר רבי
זירא הכל מודין היכא דאמר ליקדשו ארבעים מתוך שמונים דקדשו. amar Rabbi
Zeira hakol modin heicha d'amar likdeshu arbaim mitoch shmonim d'kadshu. Everybody would
agree, even רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would agree if you said forty
of the eighty should be קדוש that it will work. הכא נמי.
hacha nami. So okay, and the only reason רבי יוחנן said nothing
worked was you tried to make all eighty קדוש. So הכא נמי
hacha nami here too we'll say we're talking about a case דאמר
ליקדשו תרתי מתוך ארבע, d'amar likdeshu tarti mitoch arba, two out of
the four. And then everybody would agree, even רבי יוחנן would agree
it would work but you just don't know which two. So according
to רבי you have the idea that two are קדושת הגוף, you
don't know which two, how do you navigate that? And again, as
רש״י Rashi said, you have to redeem two whichever the two they
are and as רש״י Rashi said, though you'd have to wave all
four of them. And according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon, nothing has קדושת הגוף yet, so you go ahead, you
decide which ones to redeem and you decide which ones to use.
Okay, excellent. We got even a little bit ahead. We will end
here.