ט"ו Tes Vav
but we are on י"ד עמוד ב Yud Dalet Amud Bais about
four lines before the משנה, Mishnah, finishing up the previous סוגיא. Sugya.
We'll do a quick wrap-up of that. Basically the discussion had been
that, you know, we had been talking about חצי מתיר, Chatzi Matir,
which is that you plan when you're doing one of the lambs,
let's say for the two lambs of שבועות, Shavuos, to have a
פיגול Piggul thought either כזית Kezayis in the wrong place but not
the other. Now the גמרא Gemara is turning not to the case
of חצי מתיר Chatzi Matir but to what it calls חצי אכילה
Chatzi Achila or חצי זית Chatzi Zayis that at one full עבודה,
Avodah, the שחיטה Shechitah you think about one half of a כזית
Kezayis and in another full עבודה, Avodah, the זריקה Zrika you think
about another half of a כזית. Kezayis. So we had a ברייתא
Braisa that said that it worked. The question was would it also
work for the middle עבודות? Avodos? So now we had a ברייתא
Braisa that said it didn't work and we're trying to figure out
whether we can identify this as a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. So
we had רבי Rebbe that said that if you do half a
כזית Kezayis with one lamb and half a כזית Kezayis of another
lamb, they don't combine. So the גמרא Gemara says that's not a
proof because that's also a חצי מתיר. Chatzi Matir. It's right, each
lamb is only half of the work. So the גמרא Gemara says
yes, but if he was concerned about if it really was that
a חצי זית Chatzi Zayis and a חצי זית Chatzi Zayis combine
by different עבודות, Avodos, he should have made a גזירה. Gzeira. And
this is the basis that the גמרא Gemara says that when we
see in a lot of the משניות Mishnayos that things are not
פיגול Piggul but they're פסול, Passul, פסול Passul really means פסול דרבנן
Passul D'rabbanan because they're close to פיגול. Piggul. Okay? And the גמרא
Gemara is saying why did רבי Rebbe say this case was totally
מותר? Mutar? Why not say it was פסול? Passul? It must be
because he feels that even if you did a real, you know,
if you did a lamb, if you did a full עבודה Avodah
with a חצי כזית Chatzi Kezayis and another full, it would not
become פיגול, Piggul, so he doesn't need to make a גזירה Gzeira
when you're dealing with also a half of an עבודה, Avodah, a
single lamb. Okay, so it's a little confusing, but the upshot is
is that the פסול Passul in a lot of these משניות Mishnayos
reflects a דרבנן D'rabbanan because it's too close to the real פיגול.
Piggul. So let's just pick that up, wrap that up. The גמרא
Gemara says like this: הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi Nami Mistavra, it is
five lines above the word מתניתין, Matnisin, right? Like and a little
bit to the right. Okay, so five lines directly above the word
מתני... or actually one, two, four lines above the word מתניתין. הכי
נמי מסתברא, Hachi Nami Mistavra, that makes sense. דטעמא דרבנן משום הכי,
D'taama D'rabbanan mishum hachi, that the reason the rabbis in some cases
say פסול Passul is because of their concern about where it will
lead, like a type of a גזירה. Gzeira. הוא. Hu. דקתני סיפא,
Diktani seifa, in this debate about חצי מתיר, Chatzi Matir, just the
classic חצי מתיר Chatzi Matir debate that רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says
it is פיגול Piggul and the rabbis say it's not פיגול Piggul
but it's פסול, Passul, that here's why the rabbis say it's פסול.
Passul. The...
דקתני סיפא, Diktani seifa, the end of the ברייתא Braisa says, משנה
Mishnah says,
מודים חכמים לרבי מאיר במנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות, Modim Chachamim L'Rebbe Meir
B'Minchas Chotei U'Minchas Kenaot, right? The מנחה Mincha of a sinner and
the מנחה Mincha of a סוטה, Sotah, that there is no
לבונה, Levonah, שאם פיגל בקומץ שפיגל, She'im piggel b'kometz she'piggel, וחייבין עליה
כרת, V'chayavin aleha kares, that there, even if you just do your
פיגול Piggul thought by the קומץ, Kometz, you make פיגול Piggul and
you get כרת Kares because there is no לבונה. Levonah. שהקומץ הוא
המתיר, She'hakometz hu hamatir, because all you have there is the קומץ.
Kometz. So even though they debate when you do it only during
the קומץ Kometz and there's לבונה Levonah and you didn't do it
during the לבונה, Levonah, that's a חצי מתיר. Chatzi Matir. They don't
debate when all there is is the קומץ. Kometz. So the גמרא
Gemara says that's pretty obvious. So the גמרא Gemara says הא למה
לי למיתנא כלל? Ha lamma li l'mishna klal? Why does it have
to tell me that? פשיטא. Pshita. Of course. I mean, my god,
there's only one עבודה. Avodah. What would I have thought? So says
no. מי איכא מתיר אחרינא? Mi ika matir achrina? Is there another
מתיר Matir that I could have thought otherwise? אלא. Ela. So rather
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, hold on.
אלא, Ela, says the
גמרא, Gemara, לאו הכא קא משמע לן, Lav hacha ka mashma lan,
it's teaching us דטעמא דקומץ משום דאיכא קומץ דמנחת חוטא דדמי ליה,
D'taama d'kometz mishum d'ika kometz d'minchas chotei d'dami lei, that the reason
when the rabbis say that if you do the thought by the
קמיצה Kmitzoh and not by the לבונה, Levonah, which is the חצי
מתיר, Chatzi Matir, they say it's not פיגול, Piggul, but why did
they also say that it's פסול? Passul? Let it be totally מותר.
Mutar. Is because there's an analogous case where it would really be
פיגול. Piggul. What would the case be where you just did the
קומץ Kometz and it would be פיגול? Piggul? The מנחת חוטא. Minchas
Chotei. So since there are some scenarios where the קומץ Kometz alone
creates פיגול, Piggul, even when it doesn't, even when it's חצי המתיר
Chatzi Hamatir because it's coming with the לבונה, Levonah, they're still going
to say פסול. Passul. גמרא Gemara says, so that is a good
proof. So actually the upshot of this, I know it's a little
complicated about the חצי מתיר Chatzi Matir and the חצי אכילה Chatzi
Achila both coming together, but the important upshot about this is it
addresses the consistent refrain of "it's not פיגול Piggul but it's פסול",
Passul "it's not פיגול Piggul but it's פסול" Passul that we have
in a lot of cases. And the גמרא Gemara is here telling
us that's דרבנן D'rabbanan and that's because there's an analogous case it
really is פיגול. Piggul. So we have to make this פסול, Passul,
we're not going to make it totally מותר, Mutar, that will become,
you know, a slippery slope and won't be good. Okay, so that's
the end of that סוגיא. Sugya. Now we can start on a
new topic. Let's take a look at the
משנה. Mishnah. ניטלה אחת מן החלות Nitla achas min hachalos או אחד
מן הסדרים. o achad min hasedarim. So one of the bread, again
we're very fascinated by, you know, because it's a מנחה Mincha and
it's actually a מנחה Mincha that has something else that מתיר Matir
it, you know, so that's sort of its particularly of interest here
because מנחות Menachos normally have the קומץ Kometz that's מתיר Matir it.
have the two בזיכין. bazichin. Now it's true, מנחה mincha also has
the קומץ kometz and the לבונה, levonah, which we'll get to, but
we're starting with these. So נטמאת—so nitmeis we—so נטמאת אחת מן החלות
או אחת מן הסדרים. nitmeis achas min hachallos o achas min hasedarim.
Let's say it's not a פיגול pigul problem, just סתם stam one
of the חלות challahs became טמא tamei or one of the columns
of bread became טמא. tamei. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says שניהם יצאו
לבית השריפה. shneihem yeitziu l'veis hasreifah. They're all conceived of as one
unit. If like everything became טמא tamei and you have to burn
it all, you can't, you know, it's the קרבן korban is ruined.
שאין קרבן ציבור חלוק. She'ein korban tzibbur chaluk. You do not divide
a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. You always look at it as a
single unit, as a collection, but as a unit. וחכמים Vachachamim say,
no. הטמא בטומאתו והטהור יאכל. Hatamei betumaso vehatahor yeiacheil. The טמא tamei
is טמא tamei and the טהור tahor part you eat. Now, this
is a nice contrast to the previous משנה. mishnah. You remember the
previous משנה, mishnah, we had רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi saying that if
you had a פיגול pigul thought by one of the loaves, then,
you know, the rest of the loaves were okay. And that was
an unusual position because normally we assume when the קרבן korban becomes
פיגול, pigul, everything becomes פיגול, pigul, which is the חכמים. Chachamim. So
here we're saying, in a way, that's true about פיגול, pigul, that
the general position is if you think about part of it, then
the whole thing is פיגול. pigul. But by טומאה, tumah, it's not
that way. One thing becomes טמא, tamei, the rest remains טהור. tahor.
Except for this interesting other voice of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
says no, here too we look at it as one unit, at
least for קרבן ציבור. korban tzibbur. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, so רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says מחלוקת לפני זריקה. machlokes lifnei zrikah. The debate
is if it became טמא tamei before the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam.
That would be in the case of the lambs and the bread,
or before the burning of the לבונה levonah by the
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. אבל לאחר זריקה, Aval l'achar zrikah, דברי הכל
הטמא בטומאתו והטהור יאכל. divrei hakol hatamei betumaso vehatahor yeiacheil. Everybody agrees
that טומאה tumah just affects what it touched and the טהור tahor
things you can eat. So the גמרא Gemara says so why is
לפני זריקה lifnei zrikah any different according to you? ולפני זריקה במה
פליגי? U'lifnei zrikah bamei pligi? So according to you, what's the issue
before זריקה, zrikah, why is it worse? אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav
Pappa, בציץ מרצה על האכילות קמיפלגי. betzitz mirtzeh al ha'achilos kamiflagi. Whether
the ציץ tzitz works for eating בטומאה. betumah. What does this mean?
So now we return to דף ט"ו עמוד א'. daf tes-vav amud
aleph. So here's the story. Normally, I mean, you know, we keep
on revisiting the ציץ tzitz more, you know, sort of little snippets
of it. We have yet to see a very sort of consistent
treatment of the ציץ, tzitz, although we did in one דף daf
in זבחים. Zevachim. But anyway, normally the ציץ tzitz works for things
that are put on the מזבח. mizbeiach. You put something on the
מזבח mizbeiach and it was טמא, tamei, the ציץ tzitz somehow, you
know, because there's this idea that the ציץ tzitz is מרצה על
עוון הקדשים אשר יקדישו בני ישראל, mirtzeh al avon hakodashim asher yakdishu
bnei Yisrael, so it makes it as if the thing was not
טמא tamei or to some degree papers over it. Okay, exactly to
what degree is it fully מרצה? mirtzeh? That's a different question. But
that's when the thing is טמא. tamei. But as the גמרא Gemara
says, is
the ציץ מרצה—not tzitz mirtzeh, מטומאתו ומידיו, mitumaso u'miyadov, that's a different
פסוק—על עוון הקדשים
and לא על עוון המקדישים. v'lo al avon hamakdishim. That it's about
the קרבנות korbanos being טמא, tamei, not about the people being טמא.
tamei. Because of course if the people are טמא, tamei, they're not
allowed to eat just because there's a ציץ. tzitz I mean the
תורה Torah says you're חייב כרת chayav kareis if you're טמא tamei
and you eat a קרבן. korban. So what the ציץ tzitz. generally
works is that you did the הקרבה hakravah and there was a
טומאה tumah problem, the קרבן's korban's still כשר. kasher. But not that
it allows me to eat. So but now we're saying that no,
maybe to some degree it can extend to the people. So here,
or let's say not only I'm טמא, tamei, it's טמא, tamei, but
it's still not going to let me eat. What it does is
it lets the קרבן korban become כשר kasher if it's been brought.
But it's not going to allow me to eat if I'm טמא
tamei or the קרבן korban is טמא. tamei. So let me just
finish the thought. So what does it mean that ציץ מרצה על
האכילות? tzitz mirtzeh al ha'achilos? Because we are going to now assume
that if I'm coming to be זורק את הדם zoreik es hadam
or bring the בזיכין bazichin and the whole קרבן korban cannot be
eaten because remember, by the way, we have a principle by a
מנחה mincha that if it's חסר—now chaser this isn't exactly חסר—but chaser
if it is חסר, chaser, right, then you can't be מקטיר maktir
the קטורת, ktoreis, correct? It's different than an animal קרבן. korban. Animal
קרבן, korban, some of the meat is missing, you go ahead and
you're זורק את הדם. zoreik es hadam. If a מנחה's חסר, mincha's
chaser, you can't be מקטיר maktir the קטורת. ktoreis. So here we're
saying here's the debate. Part of this מנחה mincha is טמא. tamei.
Can I go ahead and slaughter the lambs or be מקריב makriv
the בזיכין? bazichin? Is it חסר? chaser? So we're assuming that would
make it like it's חסר chaser and you would not be able
to do the next stage. But if we say the ציץ tzitz
מרצה, mirtzeh it doesn't let you eat from what's left over, but
it enough papers over the problem that you can now be מקריב
makriv the בזיכין bazichin or the lambs as if everything was okay.
After it's been הוקרב, hukrav, you can't eat from it, it's still
טמא, tamei, but we can sort of ignore it enough to allow
you to be מקריב. makriv. It works to make the קרבן korban
effective. So even though what you're putting on the מזבח mizbeiach is
not the טמא tamei thing—you're putting on the מזבח mizbeiach the כבשים
kvashim or the בזיכין—the bazichin ציץ tzitz covers over the טומאה tumah
problem to allow the קרבן korban to be effective. So let's... So
let's read that and then I'll take the question. רבנן rabbanan סברי
*Rabbanan savri*, the Rabbis hold, הציץ מרצה על אכילות *hatzitz meratzeh al
achilos*, that the ציץ *tzitz* atones for or appeases for the even
the eating aspects, so even though this is not on the thing
being put on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbeach*, it's on the food leftover,
the ציץ *tzitz* sort of brackets it enough that it's considered a
good הקרבה *hakrava* of the lambs or of the בזיכין *vazichin*. ורבי
יהודה סבר *v’Rabbi Yehuda savar*, אין ein... הציץ מרצה על אכילות *ein
hatzitz meratzeh al achilos*. No, it does not help for that and
therefore it's like a מנחה Mincha שחסרה *mincha shechasaira*, and a מנחה
*mincha* that's חסר *chasar* you cannot be מקריב makriv *makriv* the בזיכין
*vazichin* or the lambs. So in the end, רבי יהודה'ס *Rabbi Yehuda's*
position is not like we look at it like the whole טומאה
Tumah *tumah* affects the whole thing, it's that because you've got this
problem and it's like it's חסר *chasar*, now you can't do the
הקרבה *hakrava*. So the reason you have to burn everything is not
because it's like everything is טמא Tamei *tamei*, the reason you have
to burn everything is because you weren't able to be מקריב makriv
*makriv* the קטורת *ketores* or the lambs. רבקה *Rivka*, you had a
question.
I just wanted to ask about the ציץ *tzitz*. Who, every כהן
*Kohen* wears the ציץ *tzitz*?
Just the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*. Right.
Only on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*?
No, he wears it whenever he does the עבודה avoda *avoda*, whenever
he's present in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*.
So that is a question whether the ציץ *tzitz* is only מרצה
*meratzeh* when he's wearing it or the very presence of it, the
possibility of it is מרצה *meratzeh*. Right. Exactly. Exactly. Okay.
What is then that physical importance of the ציץ *tzitz* as opposed
to anything else?
Well, I don't know. I mean, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is trying
to find reasons that at least you could imagine it in, let's
say, some religious realm, not a halachic realm. עוון הקדשים *avon hakodashim*,
the whole way the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* on יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*, his whole עבודה *avoda* is to be מטהר *metaher* the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash* from the טומאות בני ישראל *tumos Bnei
Yisrael*. So the fact that he wears the ציץ *tzitz* and it
says on it קודש להשם *Kodesh LaHashem* and it sort of focuses
on God, somehow that the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*’s function is to
allow for God's presence to continue to remain in the
מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* by somehow cleaning up the טומאה *tumah*. That's at
like a metaphysical level. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* translates it literally,
or halachically, that he is על עוון הקדשים al avon hakodashim אשר
יקדישו בני ישראל להשם *al avon hakodashim asher yakdishu Bnei Yisrael laHashem*,
that somehow because he wears the ציץ *tzitz* or could be wearing
the ציץ *tzitz*, טומאה *tumah* can be somewhat overridden. Now, to some
degree, and it's there, we have ideas: טומאה הותרה בציבור Tumah Hutrah
BeTzibbur *tumah hutra betzibbur* and these types of
ideas. But
if
you would ask me, like, why is it only טומאה *tumah* that's
הותרה בציבור *hutra betzibbur*? Like nothing else is, right? ערלות *arlos* is
not הותרה בציבור *hutra betzibbur* when יהושע *Yehoshua* had to bring the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *Korban Pesach*, you couldn't say everybody's an ערל
*arel*, all the men, and ignore it. You know, other problems are
not, just טומאה *tumah*. So I think it does connect to this
idea of השוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם *hashochein itam besoch tumosam*. That God
basically says, "I know that you sin, and I know that's a
reality of human existence, and nevertheless, I have chosen to make my
presence amongst your טומאה *tumah*." We gotta try to clean up the
טומאה *tumah* as much as possible, that's why you have a יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur* and so on, but there's always going to be
טומאה *tumah* and I'm still deciding to be שוכן אתם בתוך טומאתם
*shochein itam besoch tumosam*. So in that way, the whole existence of
the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* is a sense of an acknowledgment that God's
desire to be בתוך בני ישראל *besoch Bnei Yisrael* will override טומאה
*tumah* problems. So I think that that's like the concept of why
you have טומאה הותרה בציבור Tumah Hutrah BeTzibbur *tumah hutra betzibbur* and
why you can have the ציץ מרצה על הטומאות *tzitz meratzeh al
hatumos* because there's some sense that we're never going to totally get
away with some of the טומאה *tumah*, so we, and nevertheless, God
says, "keep on going forward." So that's the sort of מוסר *musar*
or religious message I would get from this.
Human acknowledgment of the frailty of human existence.
Exactly. Exactly. And that God is saying, yeah, this is a part
of human existence and of human frailty and I'm saying nevertheless I
want to be with you. Yeah.
I think there's a distinction here between טומאה *tumah* and עוון *avon*.
The ציץ *tzitz* does not cancel טומאה *tumah*, it doesn't remove טומאה
*tumah*, but it מרצה
*meratzeh*, lets things go forward. Right. So as opposed to what did
you say, עוון *avon*? Yeah.
Right. So the ציץ *tzitz* is מכפר *mechaper* but it's not מטהר
*metaher*.
Well, I don't know if I would make that difference. I would
make more the difference like it's more like,
right.
Again, I'm not sure I would make the difference between טומאה *tumah*
and עוון *avon* because my whole approach is sort of seeing the
טומאה-עוון *tumah-avon* concepts as very linked, like the עוון *avon* leads to
this metaphysical טומאה *tumah*. But it is a difference between, you're right,
between whether it just
is forestalling the consequences as opposed to actually achieving a oneness and
an atonement. That is completely correct. Yeah.
So that's exactly like the Rav Soloveitchik uses that in his lectures.
He speaks about the difference between, he says it's a difference between
כפרה *kapara* and סליחה *selicha*, but sometimes he also says כפרה *kapara*
and טהרה *tahara*. That כפרה *kapara* basically means you're not going to
get punished right now, but it doesn't really mean that we've cleaned
up the situation. So that I would say, absolutely, yeah. That's the
idea of מרצה *meratzeh*. So, okay. So,
alright, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, alright, so that's the debate and it's really not about... that
whether the טומאה *tumah* applies to the whole object, it's whether you
can move forward when something is טמא Tamei. *tamei*. אמר ליה Amar
lei, רב Rav הונא בריה דרב נחמן לרב פפא *Amar lei Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Nachman l'Rav Pappa*, רב Rav: הונא *Rav Huna* the
son of רב Rav. נחמן *Rav Nachman*, excuse me, said to רב
פפא *Rav Pappa*. והעולין דציץ מרצה על העולין ופליגי *V'ha'olin d'tzitz m'ratzeh
al ha'olin u'pligi*, what about when is an actual thing that's put
on the מזבח Mezbeach *mizbeach*, not something that's eaten, something put on
the מזבח *mizbeach*, עולין *olin* becomes טמא Tamei *tamei*. Everybody agrees that
the ציץ *tzitz*, you know, is effective for things that are put
on the מזבח *mizbeach*. That's the whole point of the ציץ *tzitz*.
And nevertheless, we find the similar debate. How do you see that?
דתניא *D'tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא Baraita, *Braisa*. נטמא אחד מן
הבזיכין *Nitma echad min habazichin*, let's say one of the בזיכין *bazichin*
becomes טמא Tamei *tamei*. רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda's אומר שניהם יעשו בטומאה
BeTumah *Rabbi Yehuda omer shneihem ya'asu b'tumah*. Now, ולחם הפנים *v'lechem hapanim*
is a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibbur *korban tzibbur*. Alright, because it's a
קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibbur *korban tzibbur*, you can go ahead and be
מקריב makriv *makriv* it even בטומאה BeTumah. *b'tumah*. טומאה הותרה בציבור *Tumah
hutra b'tzibbur*. So רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda's *Rabbi Yehuda* is saying, okay,
one of the בזיכין *bazichin* become טמא Tamei *tamei*. Everybody agrees you
can go ahead and be מקריב makriv *makriv*, טומאה הותרה בציבור *tumah
hutra b'tzibbur*. But what רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says is, not only
can you be מקריב makriv *makriv* it, you might as well get
the other one טמא Tamei *tamei* as well. There is no fault,
no foul in getting the other one טמא Tamei *tamei*. You know
why? Because we already conceive of it as if they're both טמא
Tamei *tamei* anyway. Okay, which makes it very clear that his point
has nothing to do with the ציץ *tzitz*, has point has to
do with how we conceive of the unit that became טמא Tamei
*tamei*. Alright, so רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says, שניהם יעשו בטומאה *shneihem
ya'asu b'tumah*, you might as well do them both בטומאה *b'tumah*, get
the other one טמא *tamei*. לפי שאין קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibbur חלוק
*L'fi she'ein korban tzibbur chaluk*, we do not divide a קרבן ציבור
Korban Tzibbur *korban tzibbur*. טומאה *Tumah* affects all parts of it. וחכמים
אומרים הטמא בטומאתו והטהור בטהרתו *V'chachamim omrim hatamei b'tumato v'hatahor b'taharato*. No,
you keep them distinct. Okay, so there you see the טומאה *tumah*
only applies to things. So yes, it's הותרה בציבור *hutra b'tzibbur*, but
you don't go ahead and make more things טמא *tamei* just because
of that. So you see this has nothing to do with the
effectiveness of the ציץ *tzitz*, because if he's allowing you to be
מטמא metamei *metamei*, certainly it's not related to that idea. And anyway,
everybody agrees that the ציץ *tzitz* is effective on things you put
on the מקדש *Mikdash*, on the מזבח *mizbeach*, and still there's a
debate. So it has really nothing to do with the ציץ *tzitz*.
ועוד אמר רב אשי *V'od amar Rav Ashi*, and רב אשי *Rav
Ashi* also says, תא שמע *Tashma*. רבי יהודה אומר אפילו שבט Shevet
אחד טמא וכל השבטים טהורים יעשו בטומאה לפי שאין קרבנות korbanot. ציבור
Tzibbur חלוק *Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu shevet echad tamei v'chol hashvatim tehorim
ya'asu b'tumah l'fi she'ein korbanot tzibbur chaluk*.
So let's say you have a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach *korban Pesach*
where you have an entire שבט Shevet *shevet* that becomes טמא *tamei*.
So first point that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says is, and this
gets us back to debates in הוריות *Horayos*, that a שבט *shevet*
can count as a ציבור mini-Tzibbur *tzibbur*, as a קהל *kahal*, right?
It's sort of like the United States, you know, we tend to
think of, you know, because we tend to think in בית שני
*Bayis Sheni* terms where the שבטים *shvatim* were not significant. But you
know, in בית ראשון *Bayis Rishon* terms, the שבטים *shvatim* had like
their own territory and then there was a federation, you know, sort
of like the states and the federal government. So רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* says that the שבטים *shvatim* have, a שבט *shevet* is a
קהל *kahal* by itself. So if one שבט *shevet* is טמא *tamei*,
so they're allowed to bring the קרבן korban? פסח *korban Pesach* בטומאה
*b'tumah*. טומאה הותרה בציבור *Tumah hutra b'tzibbur*. Once they're allowed to bring
the קרבן korban פסח *korban Pesach* בטומאה *b'tumah*, everybody else can bring
it בטומאה *b'tumah* as well, even though, you know, everybody else, they're
just a minority of the whole ציבור Tzibbur *tzibbur*. Okay, because once
טומאה *tumah* is acknowledged in a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibbur *korban tzibbur*,
it applies, you know, it affects everything. So the same way it
affects the whole object, the whole object is considered טמא *tamei*, here
the whole people are considered טמא *tamei*, and therefore טומאה הותרה בציבור
*tumah hutra b'tzibbur* for everybody. Okay, so you see that has nothing
to do with the ציץ *tzitz*, this is completely irrelevant to the
ציץ *tzitz*. Okay, it has, you know, we don't have objects becoming
טמא *tamei* here, we have people and the whole thing. And the
ציץ *tzitz* has no effect on people. Okay, והכא מאי ציץ מרצה
איכא *v'hacha mai tzitz meratzeh ika*? What type of idea of ציץ
מרצה *tzitz meratzeh*? First of all, the concept isn't relevant, second of
all, it's the people becoming טמא *tamei*, not the קרבן korban *korban*.
And the ציץ *tzitz* is only when it's the קרבן korban *korban*.
ועוד אמר רבינא *V'od ama Ravina*, רבינא *Ravina* says, תא שמע *Tashma*.
נטמא אחת מן החלות או אחת מן הסדרים *Nitma achas min hachalos
o achas min hasedarim*, one of the חלות *chalos* becomes טמא *tamei*
or one of the סדרים *sedarim*, columns of bread. רבי יהודה אומר
שניהם יצאו לבית השריפה *Rabbi Yehuda omer shneihem yetzu l'veis hasreifa*, burn
both. Why? לפי שאין קרבן korban. ציבור חלוק *L'fi she'ein korban tzibbur
chaluk*, because you do not divide a קרבן korban. ציבור *korban tzibbur*.
If one is טמא *tamei*, it's like everything is טמא *tamei*. חכמים
chachamim אומרים הטמא בטומאתו והטהור יאכל *Chachamim omrim hatamei b'tumato v'hatahor yocheil*.
Okay, and so that's our משנה mishna *mishna*. Okay, wonderful. So what's
the point? ואם איתא *V'im issa*, if you're right, that the issue
has to do with the ציץ *tzitz* and only before, you know,
the animals were slaughtered, the blood was splattered, or the בזיכין *bazichim*
were offered up, if it really is just about the ציץ *tzitz*,
so say that reason. ואם איתא לפי שאין הציץ מרצה על האכילות
מיבעי ליה *V'im issa l'fi she'ein hatzitz meratzeh al achilos mibaya lei*.
So don't tell me because you don't divide a קרבן korban ציבור
*korban tzibbur*. Say because you've got a problem that the ציץ *tzitz*
isn't מרצה *meratzeh*, as a whole קרבן korban. *korban* isn't here, and
you can't be מקריב *makriv* the בזיכין *bazichim* or you can't be
זורק *zoreik* the דם dam *dam*. Right? He's not saying that it's
a technical thing that got in the way of you being מקריב
*makriv* the בזיכין *bazichim*. He's saying, we look at the whole thing
like it's טמא *tamei*. Okay, so אלא אמר רבי יוחנן *ela ama
Rabbi Yochanan*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said you're right. לימוד ערוך Limmud
Arukh הוא hu... בפיו של רבי יהודה *Limud aruch hu b'fiv shel
Rabbi Yehuda*, it is a set teaching, an arranged teaching in the
mouth of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, שאין קרבן korban, ציבור חלוק *she'ein
korban tzibbur chaluk*, that you do not have a divided קרבן korban
ציבור *korban tzibbur*. Now what does he add by the word לימוד
ערוך *limud aruch*? So if you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says רבי יהודה לימוד ערוכו *Rabbi Yehuda limud arucho*, so
ששנה
מרבותיו *sheshanah me'rabosav*, he learned it from his rabbis. is רבותיו meaning
because רש"י Rashi is bothered where do you get this from? Right
when we're not quoting a פסוק pasuk we don't have a סברא.
sevara. I mean you know
where did this what's the logic? So he says it must be
he had a tradition. It's interesting you know the very the difference
here when the גמרא Gemara said before אומר היה רבי יהודה Omer
Hayah Reb Yehuda רש"י Rashi said there it didn't mean that we
knew that he used to say it it's just we're speculating on
what the reason is but we're calling we're saying אומר היה Omer
Hayah right he used to say means this is what it's based
on but here לימוד ערוך because there is no good you know
evidence for it or a compelling logic we're assuming that it was
a tradition. All right so that is רבי יהודה reasoning it has
nothing to do with technically you can't be מקריב something so everything
is not good. What it has to do with is he says
if you're dealing with a קרבן korban? ציבור and part becomes טמא
it's like it all becomes טמא. If you're dealing with the ציבור
and a defined mini-ציבור a שבט becomes טמא it's like they're all
טמא and therefore you throw it either you throw it all out
if it's about what you can eat don't eat the remnant of
the don't eat the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem don't eat the לחם
הפנים Lechem HaPanim but if it's something that you're allowed to do
בטומאה like being מקריב it because it's a קרבן korban ציבור so
one בזיך Bazikh became טמא might as well be מטמא both of
them and be מקריב them or if a שבט become טמא everybody
might as well bring the קרבן korban פסח בטומאה. Okay so the
impact of saying we don't divide depends on whether in the case
טומאה means don't eat it because we don't say טומאה הותרה בציבור
lets you eat so then don't eat any but if we say
that it's about being מקריב it then טומאה הותרה בציבור lets everything
happen. Okay so that is רבי יהודה position. Very good.
We see that in זבחים Zevachim with animal קרבן? korban.
No you're right and you know about אין קרבן ציבור חלוק ein
Korban Tzibbur chaluk where do you have like two parts of it?
Well I guess you're because you have tons of קרבן korban? ציבור
so although זבחים Zevachim did focus much more on the קרבן יחיד
Korban Yachids we are going to have like מסכת תמיד Masechet Tamid
which is more about ציבור but why didn't we have a case
where he said let's say that part of the meat became טמא
and you have to throw of a קרבן korban. ציבור and you
have to throw out all the meat. Oh whatever it was
right or some of the דם dam became טמא and you might
as well be well there because you could always use other דם
dam. you're not compelled to use that דם. But yeah you could
have said why didn't we find that he said if a part
of the meat of a קרבן korban, ציבור became טמא you have
to burn all the meat. Right it's a good question you're right
logically you should the גמרא Gemara is not saying this is only
a הלכה halakha by מנחה right it applied it to קרבן korban
פסח so plus yeah it is interesting it didn't come up in
זבחים. Zevachim. Okay so let's look now at the next משנה Mishna
התודה מפגלת את הלחם והלחם אינו מפגל את התודה. HaToda m'pagelat et
haLechem vehaLechem eino m'pagel et haToda. So you know again the whole
idea of פיגול pigul allowed the גמרא Gemara to explore the ideas
of relationships and dependencies in these קרבנות. So you have you're bringing
the lambs I'm sorry you're bringing the קרבן תודה. Korban Toda. A
קרבן תודה Korban Toda comes with forty loaves forty different types of
bread and wafers and whatever and ten of loaves in each. Okay
so when you bring when you're מקריב the תודה Toda you sprinkle
the blood you're now allowed to eat the bread but obviously the
primary קרבן korban. is the תודה Toda the bread is schlepped along
with it. Okay similar like any קרבן נדבה Korban Nedava free will
sacrifice the primary thing is the קרבן korban? what's schlepped along with
it is the מנחת נסכים Minchat Nesakhim right the wine and the
oil and the flour. So because of that relationship that this thing
is sort of dependent on the main קרבן korban. here's how פיגול
pigul works. התודה מפגלת את הלחם. HaToda m'pagelat et haLechem. I am
שוחט shechting the תודה Toda and I am thinking I'm going to
eat the meat tomorrow. So what happens? The תודה Toda becomes פיגול
pigul but you know what else becomes פיגול? pigul? The bread. Because
if the primary becomes פיגול pigul obviously it comes with its attendant
parts okay. והלחם אינו מפגל את התודה. VehaLechem eino m'pagel et haToda.
If I say I'm going to eat the bread tomorrow the bread
becomes פיגול pigul but not the not the תודה. Toda. If I
you know if I you know sort of cut off one of
these one of those you know attendance pieces dependent or dependent pieces
it does not affect the status of the main thing. All right
similarly כיצד keitzad how what's the case? שחט את התודה לאכול ממנו
למחר Shachat et haToda le'ekhol mimenu lemachar I slaughtered the תודה Toda
because I was going to eat from the meat tomorrow.
הלחם מפוגל HaLechem m'pugal so did I skip a line? Yes I
did. היא והלחם מפוגלים. Hi vehaLechem m'pugalim. Both the animal and the
bread are פיגול pigul because once the animal is פיגול pigul it
applies to everything that is dependent on it. ולאכול מן הלחם למחר
Ule'ekhol min haLechem lemachar if I plan just to eat the bread
tomorrow הלחם מפוגל haLechem m'pugal that creates פיגול pigul of the bread
והתודה אינה מפוגלת vehaToda einah m'pugelet but not the main thing itself
not the קרבן. korban הכבשים מפגלין את הלחם והלחם אינו מפגל את
הכבשים. HaKevasim m'paglin et haLechem vehaLechem eino m'pagel et haKevasim. Similarly when
you bring the two lambs on שבועות Shavuot you know it's like
for us שבועות Shavuot we don't you know the only way we
can make it to have any any any character is by staying
up all night and learning תורה. Torah. For the גמרא Gemara
the play that the The שבועות Shavuot, *Shavuos* קרבן Korban *korban* gets
throughout מסכת מנחות *Maseches Menachos* is disproportionate to the degree of acknowledgment
it gets anywhere else. It constantly is coming up because of the
relationship of the lambs to the bread, so you have that interesting
aspect of it and you have the idea that each lamb is
a חצי מכשיר *chatzi machshir*, so it allows for a lot of
interesting sort of discussion. Okay, so you're bringing the two lambs and
so if you make the lambs פיגול pigul *pigul*, they are מפגל
mifageil, *mefagel* the לחם *lechem*. הלחם אינו eino מפגל mifageil? את הכבשים
*Ha'lechem eino mefagel es ha'kvasim*. But the bread does not affect the
status of the lambs. כיצד keitzad? *Keitzad*? And it goes through this
again. השוחט את הכבשים לאכול מהם למחר *Ha'shochet es ha'kvasim le'echol meihem
le'machar*, if you slaughter the lambs to eat from them tomorrow, the
meat, הם והלחם מפוגלין *heim ve'ha'lechem mefugalin*, not only are they פיגול
pigul. *pigul* but the bread is פיגול pigul? *pigul*. לאכול את הלחם
למחר *Le'echol es ha'lechem le'machar*, to eat the bread tomorrow, הלחם מפוגל
*ha'lechem mefugal*, the status applies to the bread, והכבשים אינם מפוגלין *ve'ha'kvasim
einam mefugalin*, but not to the lambs because you only applied it
to the dependent part, it does not affect the main thing. So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*?
What's the reason for this? אילימא משום דרב כהנא *Ileima mishum de'Rav
Kahana*, maybe it's because of what רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* said? דאמר
רב כהנא *de'amar Rav Kahana*, רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* says, מנין ללחמי
תודה todah. שנקראו תודה todah *minayin le'lachmei todah she'nikru todah*? How do
you know that the bread that comes with the תודה todah *todah*
is called the תודה todah *todah* itself? A part of the תודה
todah *todah*? שנאמר והקריב על זבח zevach, התודה חלות *Shene'emar, 've'hikriv al
zevach hatodah challos'*, because of the phrasing of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
it says you should bring on the זבח zevach תודה todah *zevach
todah* the bread. So the juxtaposition, it could have phrased it differently,
so it could have said והקריב חלות על זבח zevach, תודה todah
*ve'hikriv challos al zevach todah* or something like that. So by juxtaposing
the word תודה todah *todah* and חלות *challos*, it's telling you that
חלות *challos* are also part of the תודה todah *todah*. Okay, so
if that's why it works, that it's all one unit, אי הכי
איפכא נמי *i'hachi ippcha nami*? So then when you affect the bread,
you should affect the תודה todah *todah*. It's all defined as the
one single תודה Toda *todah*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, הא
לא lo. קשיא *ha lo kashya*, that's not difficult. לחם איקרי תודה
toda, תודה toda לא איקרי לחם *Lechem ikrei todah, todah lo ikrei
lechem*. The bread is called part of the תודה toda, *todah*, but
תודה toda *todah* is not called bread. So if I'm thinking תודה
toda *todah*, תודה toda, *todah* means everything. If I'm thinking bread, bread
just means bread. It does not mean the meat that comes with
it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, but let's look at
the end of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. אלא הא דתני *Ela ha
d'tani*, הכבשים מפגלין את הלחם והלחם אינו מפגל mifageil. את הכבשים *ha'kvasim
mefaglin es ha'lechem ve'ha'lechem eino mefagel es ha'kvasim*. When you have the
lambs by שבועות Shavuot *Shavuos*, and they become פיגול pigul? *pigul*, the
bread becomes פיגול pigul, *pigul*. But if the bread becomes פיגול pigul
*pigul* it does not affect the lambs. So היכא אשכחן דאיקרי כבשים
לחם *heicha ashchan
de'ikrei kvasim lechem*?
We never have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that says the breads that
come with the lambs on שבועות Shavuot, *Shavuos* are called lambs. So
if you base yourself on a פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*, you're limited to
the one application where it says it in the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אלא האי טעמא *ela hai ta'ama*,
this is the reason. It's not because of what the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* says, it's just because of the underlying logic. לחם גלל תודה
toda *lechem glal todah*, לחם *lechem* comes like we would say בגלל
*biglal*, because of the תודה todah *todah*, it's schlepped along by the
תודה todah, *todah*, ואין התודה גלל דלחם *ve'ein ha'todah glal de'lechem*, and
the תודה todah, *todah* is not coming because of the bread. Now
it really means like dependent on because what's becoming because of sort
of might make you think of like, well what am I focusing
on? And maybe you'll say on שבועות Shavuot? *Shavuos* I focus on
the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem, *shtei ha'lechem*. I'm not focusing on the
lambs, I'm focusing on the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem. *shtei ha'lechem*. I
bring the lambs so I can have this special קרבן Korban *korban*
of שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem. *shtei ha'lechem*. So גלל *glal* does not
really mean like
what's motivating. When I say because, בגלל *biglal*, you think of sort
of like what's motivating me to bring this קרבן Korban *korban* in
the first place. So then you might say well what's motivating me
to bring the קרבן Korban? *korban* on שבועות *Shavuos* is so that
I can have a קרבן Korban *korban* of שתי הלחם shtei halechem.
*shtei ha'lechem*. So גלל *glal* here more means like, the word גלל
*glal* and why we say בגלל *biglal* means because of, is like
the word והגלגל *ve'hagalgal* which means to roll, like this sort of
rolls leads into this, this flows from that. So here גלל *glal*
sort of means what's rolled along with, what's schlepped along with. It's
not a question of what motivates me, it's a question of how
they
operate. So the bringing of the lambs allows the bread to be
good. And that's why, it's another way of saying that the bread
is dependent on the lambs. Okay, so let's read that again. לחם
גלל תודה todah?
*Lechem glal todah*, the bread that comes with the תודה Todah *todah*
is being sort of because of, meaning affected by, drawn by the
תודה Todah; *todah*, ואין תודה גלל דלחם *ve'ein todah glal de'lechem*, and
the תודה *todah* is not drawn by the bread. לחם גלל דכבשים
*Lechem glal de'kvasim*, the bread on שבועות *Shavuos*, even if in our
minds they're primary, are drawn by the כבשים *kvasim*, dependent on the
lambs, ואין כבשים גלל דלחם *ve'ein kvasim glal de'lechem*, and the כבשים
*kvasim* are not drawn and affected or dependent on the bread. Okay,
so וצריכי *u'tzrichi*, and now here's why you needed both cases, the
case of the lambs and the bread and the case of the
תודה *todah*. דאי אשמעינן תודה *De'is ashmi'inan todah*, if it just gave
us the example of תודה *todah*, התם הוא *hasam hu*, there, דכי
מפגל mifageil בלחם לא מפגלא תודה *de'ki mefaga be'lechem lo mefagla todah*.
There what the status of the bread doesn't affect the status of
the תודה *todah*, they're clearly distinct objects, why? משום דלא הוקקו זה
לזה בתנופה *Mishum de'lo huskeku zeh la'zeh be'tnufah*, because you don't do
the same wave. ritual with them. You don't put the bread on
the תודה and wave it all together. So since when you bring
it to the בית המקדש, you don't use the bread in the
rituals, logically you think that they're more distinct. So therefore, when I
do something to the bread, I can say I don't affect the
תודה. That's in the תודה case. אבל כבשים, Avel kvasim, but the
case of the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem the two lambs, דהוקקו זה
לזה בתנופה, de'huskeku ze laze betnufa, you wave those two lambs together
with the two breads of the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. So there
you do a unifying ritual with all of them together. Maybe that
really defines it as a tight unit, as a single unit, and
maybe I would say אימא, eima, I might think כי מיפגל בלחם
ליפגל נמי כבשים, ki mifageil belechem lifagil nami kvasim, that when you
make the bread פיגול pigul? you also make the lambs פיגול. pigul,
They're really maybe it is one tight unit. קא משמע לן, Kamashma
lan, צריכא, tzricha, so it had to tell me both cases. Of
course, you could have made the opposite argument because of the פסוק
pasuk quoted before, right? That the breads of the תודה are called
the תודה and we don't find that by the שתי הלחם. shtei
halechem But the גמרא Gemara is saying in the end, we say
the same thing applies to both. That they are not one single
unit where the bread would affect the meat. They are one unit
and the other thing, the bread is dependent on the animal קרבן.
Korban. So what the status of the animal קרבן Korban applies to
the bread, but not in the reverse, in both of those cases.
Okay, good. That was very straightforward. בעי מיניה רב אליעזר מרב. Bai
minei Rav Eliezer meRav. So רב אליעזר Rav Eliezer asked רב the
following
question. השוחט את התודה ולאכול כזית ממנה ומלחמה למחר. Hashocheit es hatodah
velocheil kezayis mimena u'milachma lemachar. Okay, so you know you're going to
get start getting these cases. If somebody שוחט schechts the תודה and
says, 'I'm going to eat a half of a כזית kezayis of
the תודה and a half of a כזית kezayis of the bread
tomorrow. I'm going to have myself a little תודה sandwich tomorrow.' Okay,
so it's not enough of the thought of the meat alone and
not enough of the thought of the bread alone. Are you going
to be able to combine that and to make פיגול? pigul. And
if so, what will be פיגול? pigul? So let's see what the
question is. Okay,
מהו? mahu? What would be the status? ליפגולי תודה למהו? Lipgulei todah
l'mahu? What's the status? ליפגולי תודה לא מיבעי לי. Lipgulei todah lo
miba'ei li. To change, to say that the תודה becomes פיגול, pigul.
that's not my question. That obviously is not true. Why not? השתא
כולה מלחמא לא מיפגלא. Hashta kula milachma lo mifagla. When I have
like a real good פיגול pigul. thought to eat a כזית kezayis
of the bread, nevertheless the bread can't affect the status of the
animal. So if that's true, ממנה ומלחמה מיבעי? mimena u'milachma miba'ei? This
thought which is more of a hybrid, half of a כזית kezayis
here, half כזית kezayis here, certainly it's not going to affect the
status of the lamb. Now you could say maybe not, maybe because
I'm actually using some of the meat in my thought, that more
like unifies them. But he assumes that no, that it's clear that
anything that needs the bread cannot be used to affect the status
of the קרבן. Korban That is the secondary and dependent and any
thought that is partly related to the bread will not affect the
status of the animal. That's clear to me. כי קמיבעי לי, Ki
kamiba'ei li, what's my question? ליפגולי לחם. Lipgulei lechem. That in this
case of a half of a כזית kezayis of each, can you
make the bread פיגול? pigul. Okay, since the bread is dependent on
the
קרבן, and we know a thought about a כזית kezayis of the
קרבן makes the bread פיגול, pigul, so maybe a thought of a
half of a כזית kezayis plus a half of a כזית kezayis
can also make the bread פיגול. pigul That's a reasonable possibility. מי
מיצטרפא תודה
ליפגולי ללחם? Mi mitztarfa todah lipgulei lechem? Does the תודה combine to
make the bread פיגול? pigul. או דלמא, O dalma, or maybe not,
maybe you need either one כזית kezayis of one or the other,
not a half of each. אמר ליה, amar lei he said, אף
זו. af zo. Yes, I would say even this. הלחם מיפגל והתודה
אינה מיפגלא. Halechem mifageil vehatodah einah mifagela. You're right, the תודה is
not affected, but yes, the bread is affected. The same way a
whole כזית kezayis of the meat, a half a כזית kezayis of
the meat and a half a כזית kezayis of the bread also
says that from the bread's perspective it's all one, and therefore from
the bread's perspective you have a כזית kezayis and the bread is
פיגול. pigul, אמאי? Amai? So the גמרא Gemara says why? לימא קל
וחומר. Leima kal vachomer. Here's a קל וחומר kal vachomer I'll say
why that's not
right. ומה המפגל אין מתפגל. Uma hamifageil ein mitpageil. It's like yesterday,
you have to know your grammar. So the thing that is מפגל,
what is מפגל? The meat, right? The meat now in your scenario,
you have a half of a כזית kezayis of meat and a
half of a כזית kezayis of the bread. So because of the
meat, the bread is becoming, you want to suggest that the bread
is becoming פיגול. pigul. So the meat, this half כזית kezayis of
meat is the מפגל. It's going to participate to make the bread
פיגול. pigul. But it אינו מתפגל. mitpageil. It does not itself become
פיגול, pigul. right? Because we said you're not going to have meat
and bread affecting the status of the meat. Because yes, clear? So
the מפגל is not מתפגל. mitpageil. The thing making the bread פיגול
pigul does not itself become פיגול. piggul הבא לפגל ולא פגל. Haba
lephageil velo phigeil. So let's look at it from the bread's perspective.
The bread might have been attempting to make the meat פיגול, piggul.
but it couldn't have that effect, right? So it didn't even have
the ability to make something else פיגול. piggul, It couldn't make the
meat פיגול. piggul, אינו דין שלא יתפגל? Eino din shelo yitpageil?
Certainly, it should not make itself פיגול. piggul? So if the meat
could make the bread פיגול piggul, but its own status is protected,
so the bread... The bread that can't even make the meat פיגול
piggul certainly should not be able to make itself פיגול. piggul I
mean, okay, that's if you looked at it from a different perspective,
it makes total sense. But within this קל וחומר kal vachomer way
of framing it, that's our question. So the גמרא Gemara says, is
this really the right way to look at this? So the גמרא
Gemara says ומי אמרינן קל וחומר כי האי גוונא, Umi amrinan kal
vachomer ki hai gavna, do we ever say a קל וחומר kal
vachomer like that? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we learned in a ברייתא, Braitisa: המעשה
באחד, ha-ma'aseh be-echad, there's a story with one person שזרע כרמו של
חבירו סמדר, she-zara karmo shel chaveiro semadar,
he planted his friend's vineyard when the vineyard was still like
unripe grapes, and the significance of that is that it still has
the potential of becoming כלאים, kilayim, because once the fruit is fully
formed, it can't become כלאים kilayim anymore. But this was not yet
fully formed. So my friend here had a vineyard and the grapes
were still not were still unripe, and I came and I planted
seeds in his vineyard, and I made a כלאים. kilayim. Now there's
a problem. The problem is אין אדם אוסר
דבר שאינו שלו. Ein adam oser davar she-eino shelo. Can I—now, that's
a little bizarre to apply that to כלאים, kilayim, we've seen it
before, for example, by עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, if I bowed down
to your cow. Okay, and even there, if I do a מעשה,
ma'aseh, if I שחט shacht your cow, I do. Here I did
a מעשה. ma'aseh. But normally, that's if all you have is like
a pure הלכתי halachic state, not a physical reality. If I took
your meat and cooked it with my milk, we would not say
אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, Ein adam oser davar she-eino shelo,
you have a reality of בשר בחלב. basar be-chalav. If I take
your vineyard and plant seeds, you have a reality of mixed seeds
going on here. Nevertheless, unfortunately there's no בבלי Bavli on כלאים, kilayim,
so we're never going to learn it straight. But the גמרא Gemara
does understand that by כלאים, kilayim, questions about דעת da'at and intent
and whatever do play a role. It's not just the physical reality.
So I have not made your vineyard כלאים. kilayim. What about the
seeds that grow from it? Because two things become כלאים, kilayim, the
vine and the plants, the זרעים zeraim that grow from—right? Because it's
a mixture of both. So let's see what happened. ובא מעשה לפני
חכמים, U-ba ma'aseh lifnei chachamim, this case came before the sages ואסרו
את הזרעים והתירו את הגפנים, ve-asru et ha-zeraim ve-hitiru et ha-gepanim, and
they forbade the seeds, whatever grew from them—that is כלאים, kilayim, those
were your seeds—but they permitted the vine, אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו
שלו. ein adam oser davar she-eino shelo. So now the גמרא Gemara
says ואמאי, ve-amai, why is that? לימא קל וחומר, Leima kal vachomer,
let's make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה האוסר, Ma ha-oser, what
is making it forbidden? The vine. The vine is making my vegetables
forbidden, or whatever, my grain. So מה האוסר, ma ha-oser, the vine
which makes it forbidden, אינו נאסר, eino ne'esar, the vine itself does
not become forbidden, it's not כלאים, kilayim, הבא לאסור ולא אסר, ha-ba
le-asor ve-lo asar, my things, my grain that I planted that was
trying to make your vines כלאים kilayim and did not succeed, אינו
דין שלא יתאסר? eino din shelo yitasser? So certainly, they should be
protected and not become אסור. assur. Again, if you look at it
from that perspective, trying and didn't succeed and it's protected, but who
says you frame it that way? You can frame it as you
have כלאים kilayim but there's a principle of אין אדם אוסר דבר
שאינו שלו. ein adam oser davar she-eino shelo. Or, you know, you
have פיגול, piggul. but the meat affects the status of the bread,
the bread doesn't affect the status of the meat. So that's the
גמרא's Gemara point. We don't say קל וחומר kal vachomers that take
things out of their context and just look at them in this
abstract way of the mechanism of אוסר oser and נאסר. ne'esar. If
you did, you would not have that case by the כלאים. kilayim.
So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara, answer is. הכי השתא, Hachi
hashta, what type of a comparison is that? התם קנבוס ולוף אסרה
תורה, Hatam kanvus ve-luf asrah Torah, there the Torah only forbade קנבוס
kanvus and לוף. luf. Now, what is קנבוס kanvus and לוף? luf?
These are two types of grain. קנבוס Kanvus is canvas, I mean,
it's hemp. Right. So what's that? Is that sort of like the—is
that like bamboo, like these big long shoots that grow from—no? I
don't know what it looks like. It's supposed to be similar to
marijuana. Oh, is that so, hemp? Okay. What? Oh, okay. And לוף
luf is—לוף, luf, you probably—you have a picture? You have a picture
of לוף? luf? Isn't לוף luf some type of like a pod
or something, but what is it? Arum palaestinum. Okay, what does it
look like?
It looks like a leaf like basil, I
don't know. Okay. So רש"י Rashi says two reasons why this might
be the only thing that's forbidden.
Now what the
גמרא Gemara really
means is
not the only thing,
because
clearly grain like wheat and barley are forbidden. But here it says
זרעים, zeraim, so it means outside of the grains, the only other
things included in כלאים kilayim would be these. Now what's unique about
these?
רש"י Rashi has two explanations.
One is because the Torah says כרמך זרע כלאים,
karmeca zera kilayim, so it has to all be
like a vineyard,
and these
types of things רש"י says have like clusters
that berries of clusters that are like a vineyard. But I don't
know, is that true in the picture they're selling? Do they have
berry clusters? No berries, no clusters. The other thing רש"י says is
that these things, what, minute, hold on, wait, these things have roots.
And as opposed to most seeds, like most vegetables, where you know
they don't stay year to year, these things have roots and they
grow back year to year. So maybe, so that's what's distinctive about
them. Okay. I don't know. He knew no agriculture. He knew, he
did not. All right, I'll ask that question when it comes up.
All right, he maybe had another tradition, I don't know, I don't
know. Anyway, for whatever reason we say that other than the grains
these are the things that create כלאים. Kilayim. Okay, so let's keep
on going. שאר זרעי מדרבנן. Shar zerai midrabbanan. All other, you know,
all other types of vegetables or plants that are not these and
that are not grains are only rabbinic. מדרבנן הוא דאסירי, Midrabbanan hu
deasiri, are only rabbinically forbidden. האי דעביד איסורא קנסוה רבנן, Hai deavid
issura kansua rabbanan, האי דלא עביד איסורא לא קנסוה רבנן. Hai delo
avid issura lo kansua rabbanan. He says there, there's not a logic
to the mechanism, it's all a fine. Fines you can just focus
on the guilty party, it's
not how the actual things are mechanically operating.
So you did something wrong, you planted
your friend's vineyard כלאים, Kilayim, we're going to fine you and say
your stuff is אסור. assur. Him, he did nothing wrong, it's not
going to be אסור. assur. So it's the whole thing I was
saying before by the way that כלאים Kilayim is not just a
natural state of being mixed, it has to do with other things
and we would say אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו. ein adam
oser davar sheeino shelo. According to this, it's not necessarily what's going
on, it could be כלאים Kilayim is totally based on a natural
state and if it was real wheat everything would be אסור, assur,
forget אין אדם אוסר דבר שאינו שלו, ein adam oser davar sheeino
shelo, but this isn't real כלאים Kilayim so we're going to punish
the guilty party. But it's not based on mechanism, so you can't
ask קל וחומר. kal vachomer. What's not the case, אבל הכא לימא
קל וחומר. aval hacha leima kal vachomer. Here say a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Here it's not about punishing, it's not about fining, it's
about a reality of creating פיגול, piggul so let's say about the
mechanism, are you coming to make something אסור, assur, are you yourself
becoming אסור assur and so on. So the גמרא Gemara thinks that
this קל וחומר kal vachomer makes sense if there's a particular mechanism
going on. Okay and there's no answer yet whether that's a good
question or not. Now the גמרא Gemara, says ואיכא דמתני לה אכבשים.
veika dematni la akvashim. Now we're basically going to have a repeat
of the entire סוגיא sugya just rather than talking about the תודה
and the bread, we're going to talk about the כבשים של שבועות
kvashim shel Shavuot and the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem, So this is
almost word for word a repeat. ואיכא דמתני לה אכבשים. veika dematni
la akvashim. Some say this about the כבשים של שבועות. kvashim shel
Shavuot. בעי מיניה רבי אליעזר מרב. baei minei Rabi Eliezer meRav. רבי
אליעזר Rabi Eliezer asked רב: השוחט את הכבשים לאכול כזית מהן ומלחמן
מהו? hashochet et hakvashim leechol kezayit mehen umilachman mahu? So if you
slaughter the lambs in order to eat a combined כזית, kezayit, half
a כזית kezayit of them and half a כזית kezayit of the
bread, does it create פיגול? piggul לפיגולי כבשים לא קמיבעיא לי. lepigulei
kvashim lo kamibaya li. I am not asking about the lambs becoming
פיגול, piggul. they certainly don't. השתא כולה מלחם לא מפגלי. hashta kula
milacham lo mepaglei. If you have a whole כזית kezayit from the
bread in a real pure פיגול piggul, thought it does not affect
the status of the lambs. מהן ומלחמן מיבעיא? mehen umilachman mibaya? Is
there any question if it's a combined כזית kezayit from them and
from the bread, certainly that's not even a hybrid, that's a hybrid
פיגול piggul. thought, that certainly won't affect their status. They are independent
of the bread. But here's my question: כי קמיבעיא לי, ki kamibaya
li, what's my question? לפיגולי לחם. lepigulei lechem. To make the bread
פיגול. piggul. מי מצטרפי כבשים לפיגולי לחם או לא? mi mitztarfi kvashim
lepigulei lechem o lo? Will the half כזית kezayit from the lambs
combine with the bread to make the bread פיגול piggul, or not?
אמר ליה amar lei, he said to him: אף בזו הלחם מפגל
והכבשים אינם מפגלים. af bezo halechem mifgal vehakvashim einam mifgalim. You're right
the lambs are not פיגול pigul and the bread would be פיגול.
pigul? The half כזית kezayit of the meat of the lambs would
combine with the bread. ואמאי? veamai? The גמרא Gemara. says why is
that true? לימא קל וחומר. leima kal vachomer. Let's say a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה המפגל אינו מתפגל. uma hamapagel eino mitpagel. The
meat which is trying to make the bread פיגול, pigul. it itself
does not become פיגול. pigul. הבא לפגל ולא פיגל אינו דין שלא
יתפגל? haba lepagel velo pigel eino din shelo yitpagel? Certainly it itself
should not become פיגול. pigul ומי אמרינן קל וחומר כי האי גוונא?
umi amrinan kal vachomer ki hai gavna? Is that really a legitimate
קל וחומר? kal vachomer? והתניא מעשה באחד שזרע כרמו של חבירו סמדר
וכו. vehatanya maaseh beechad shezarah karmo shel chaveiro semadar et cetera. The
whole thing about planting in your friend's vineyard with these other seeds.
ואמאי לימא קל וחומר? veamai leima kal vachomer? Why don't we say
the קל וחומר kal vachomer there? מה אוסר אינו נאסר. mah oser
eino neesar. So the same way there the vines which make the
vegetables כלאים, Kilayim, they themselves do not become forbidden. הבא לאסור ולא
אסר אינו דין שלא יאסר? haba leesor velo asar eino din shelo
yeaser? The vegetables which are coming to make the vines forbidden and
did not succeed, certainly they should not become כלאים. Kilayim. So you
see that קל וחומר kal vachomer doesn't make sense. הכי השתא? hachi
hashta? What type of comparison is that? התם קנבוס ולוף אסרה תורה.
hatam kanvas velof asara Torah. The תורה Torah only forbade you know
קנבוס kanvas ולוף, velof, which is what did we say lof was,
some type of a like potted vegetable, no you said something like
basil. Okay. Anyway, אסרה תורה, asra Torah, שאר זרעי מדרבנן הוא דאסירי.
shar zerai midrabbanan hu deasiri. And everything else is rabbinic. האי דעביד
איסורא קנסוה רבנן דלא עביד איסורא לא קנסוה רבנן. hai deavid issura
kansua rabbanan delo avid issura lo kansua rabbanan. The person that did
the wrong thing we punish, the other person we didn't punish. So
there it's just punishing and fining, it's not a natural effect of
the mechanism. אבל הכא aval hacha here when it comes to פיגול,
pigul, לימא leima makes our דף daf a little faster today. Okay,
so there we have the exact same question. It's not resolved. One
opinion says yes, the bread does become פיגול pigul because the half
כזית kezayit of meat combines, and the other says has this קל
וחומר kal vachomer reason to say no. And now the גמרא just
explains is there a significance regarding which case you asked it about.
So let's take a look. מאן דמתקי לה לתודה, man de-matki lah
l'toda, the one that said this question was about the תודה, כל
שכן כבשים. kol she-ken kvashim. Certainly he would have the same position
and the same question and the same position on the bread, on
the lambs of שבועות, because we'll see why in a minute. אמאן
דמתקי לכבשים, a-man de-matki l'kvashim, but the one who asked the question
about the lambs and said that yes, the half of a כזית
kezayit of meat affects the status of the bread, כבשים הוא דהוקקו
זה לזה לתנופה. kvashim hu de-hukkeku ze la-ze l'tnufa. That's because the
lambs of שבועות and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem can be seen
as more of a tight unit, because you wave them together, you
actually do their ritual, one of the rituals together. So there it's
more of a tight unit, so a half of a כזית kezayit
of the lambs can affect the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem, אבל תודה
דלא הוקקו זה לזה לתנופה, aval toda de-lo hukkeku ze la-ze l'tnufa,
but by the תודה where you don't do anything together with the
breads and the תודה, so those are more distinct units, לא. Maybe
even the one that says that the half of a כזית kezayit
of meat affects the bread when it's the two half כזיתים kezayitim
would not say it by a תודה because there they are more
distinct units, not one tight unit. It is interesting by the way,
that although the גמרא at the beginning quoted a פסוק, right, that
the breads of a תודה are called a תודה, by the end,
once it's sort of said this is based on logic of dependencies,
by the end the פסוק isn't counting for anything, meaning we're never
going back to that פסוק and saying maybe because of this פסוק
the תודה and its breads are more seen of one unit. What
makes something a unit is that you do the עבודה together. So
it's all based on the logical issues of dependency or seeing them
as combined or not. Okay. So that was that interesting question about
a half of a כזית kezayit of each. Now, רבי אבא זותי,
Rabbi Abba Zuti, רבי אבא זותי, Rabbi Abba Zuti, interesting words, the
small one or whatever, בעי לה. baei lah. So he asked the
following question, הכי בעי מיניה רבי אלעזר מרב. hachi baei minei Rabbi
Elazar me-Rav. So he didn't really ask the question, he reported, anyway,
here's the question that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar asked from רב. השוחט
את הכבש לאכול כזית מחבירו למחר מהו. ha-shochet et ha-keves lechol kezayit
me-chavero l'machar mahu. So I am שחיטה shechting and this by the
way what we're about to say you'll see pretty much proves that
we're talking about when we say thinking we're talking about saying. I
שחט shecht this lamb, the two lambs of שבועות, and I say
I'm going to eat a כזית kezayit of its חבירו chavero tomorrow.
Okay, what do I mean by חבירו? chavero? I could mean one
of two things. I could mean the other lamb. What else could
I mean? What else is the חבירו chavero of this lamb of
שבועות? The bread. Okay, so which one am I thinking about? So
now clearly this also shows that we're talking about speech, because if
I was thinking, I mean I guess I could report to you,
hey, I just thought I was going to eat it and its
חבירו, chavero, did I make פיגול? pigul But again it makes more
sense that we're talking about speech. What does חבירו chavero mean? That
they're using that language? Yes, חבירו, chavero, that's the question. And the
question is going to be what did you mean by חבירו? chavero?
Okay, I guess the reason I'm thinking that it means speech rather
than thinking and reporting on it is because then I would ask
you well what were you thinking when you said חבירו? chavero? You
might have thought the word חבירו chavero but what did you think
it meant? But here we're going to interpret what it means, we're
not going to ask you what it means. Okay? So, לאכול כזית
מחבירו למחר מהו. lechol kezayit me-chavero l'machar mahu. What's the law? חבירו
כבש משמע, chavero keves mashma, does it mean its fellow lamb? ולא
מפגל, v'lo me-fagel, and it's not פיגול. pigul. Why? Because of the
principle of אין מתיר מפגל מתיר. ein matir me-fagel matir. Right? The
two lambs are making the bread okay, so a thought about the
lamb affects the bread which is dependent on it, but the two
lambs are not dependent one on the other, so what I think
about one lamb does not affect the status of the other. So
if I mean the fellow lamb, no problem. או דלמא לחם משמע,
o dilma lechem mashma, the friend means the bread, ומפגלי, u-mefaglei, and
it did make פיגול. pigul. So אמר ליה, so he said to
him, תניתוה, tinituha, we taught it. שחט אחד מן הכבשים לאכול ממנו
למחר הוא פיגול וחבירו כשר. shachat echad min ha-kvashim lechol mimenu l'machar
hu pigul ve-chavero kasher. That we have a משנה Mishna? coming up
that I slaughter one of the lambs to eat from it the
next day, it's פיגול pigul and our משנה Mishnah said the bread
was פיגול, pigul so the פיגול pigul. affects the thing itself and
it affects the bread, but it doesn't affect the other lamb, because
אין מתיר מפגל מתיר. ein matir me-fagel matir. Ah, but what did
it call the other lamb in this משנה? Mishnah חבירו. chavero. Okay?
So it says הוא... where are we? לאכול ממנו למחר הוא פיגול,
lechol mimenu l'machar hu pigul, the lamb is פיגול Pigul and the
bread, וחבירו כשר, ve-chavero kasher, the fellow lamb is okay. לאכול מחבירו
למחר, lechol mi-chavero l'machar, let's say I'm slaughtering one lamb with the
intent to eat from the fellow lamb tomorrow, שניהם כשרים, shneihem kesherim,
then they're both kosher because אין... מפגל מתיר. mafgil matir. So what
we get out of this instead, in addition to a review of
אין מתיר מפגל מתיר, ein matir mafgil matir, is that the וחברו
v'chaveiro means the other lamb. So the גמרא, so that's what we'll
interpret you meant, and everything is מותר. mutar. אלמא חברו כבש משמע,
alma chaveiro keves mashma, you see it means a lamb. So the
גמרא says no, דלמא דפריש ואמר חברו כבש, dilma d'parish v'amar chaveiro
keves, maybe that's only if you're explicit and you say the fellow
lamb, which probably means that yes, the משנה Mishnah. uses חברו chaveiro
to mean lamb, but that's because the context makes it clear. It
doesn't prove what the word חברו chaveiro means absent the particular context.
What? It's not a term of art. It's not a term of
art? It's not a term of art. Technical term. A particular phrase
that has a specific, oh like a technical term. Right. Okay, right.
So in the context in the משנה it meant the other lamb,
but out of that context it's not clear what it would mean.
What was nice in addition to the question of what lamb meant
is it makes us look at now the whole dependencies, which is
again why the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem, is such a nice little
model. You have two breads and the lambs dependent on it. So
if I think about one, if I'm thinking about one lamb, the
first question to ask is can you be מפגל בחצי מתיר? mefagel
b'chatzi matir? We've alluded to that and we're going to get it
explicitly in the, you know, coming up. The other issue is what
does this one lamb affect? It affects itself, it affects the bread
that's dependent on it, but it doesn't affect the other lamb because
אין מתיר מפגל מתיר ein matir mafgil matir and the other lamb
is not dependent on it. Okay, let's see we can get to
the bottom of the page. Okay, so הזבח מפגל את הנסכים, hazevach
mefagel es hanesachim, so this is like a straight continuation of the
previous idea. If I slaughter a normal freewill sacrifice and I'm bringing
with it נסכים, nesachim, wine and a mix of flour and oil,
so the נסכים nesachim are dependent on the זבח, but the זבח
is not dependent on the נסכים. nesachim. So I slaughter the זבח,
so I make the זבח פיגול, zevach pigul, I plan on eating
it at the wrong time, so that makes also the נסכים פיגול.
nesachim pigul. When is this true? משיקדשו בכלי דברי רבי מאיר. misheyikdeshu
bichli divrei Rabbi Meir. Once the נסכים nesachim have been put into
a כלי, kli, because the question here is going to be when
do these subsidiaries become identified together with the קרבן? Now we didn't
really discuss it by the breads of the תודה and by the
breads of the, what do you call it, and by the breads
of the שתי הלחם, when do they get identified? For some reason
we're discussing it now by the נסכים, nesachim, and רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says when you put the נסכים nesachim in a כלי kli
it gets identified with this קרבן and then the קרבן is going
to affect it. The רבנן were going to see the גמרא will
elaborate say no, you know things like שתי הלחם with the lambs,
there's only one thing you do with שתי הלחם, you bring it
together with the lambs, or you know the breads with the תודה,
although there you could ask because maybe you could bring it with
another תודה, those are identified. But נסכים, nesachim, they're not specifically this
קרבן. You know when they're going to be associated with this קרבן?
When you actually put them on the מזבח. But if something went
wrong, use this נסכים nesachim for a different קרבן. So therefore they
are—since they're not identified as connected to this specific קרבן, what happens
to the קרבן never affects their status. Let's read the משנה. הנסכים
אינם מפגלים את הזבח, hanesachim einam mefaglim es hazevach, so therefore since
that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, this is another application of
these ideas of פיגול. Pigul, הנסכים אינם מפגלים את הזבח. hanesachim einam
mefaglim es hazevach. But if you have a מחשבה machshava that the
נסכים, nesachim, they don't affect the קרבן. כיצד? How is this true?
השוחט את הזבח לאכול ממנו למחר, hashocheit es hazevach le'echol mimenu l'machar,
if you slaughter the sacrifice and you plan on eating it tomorrow,
הוא ונסכיו מפוגלים. hu u'nesachav mefugalim. It and the נסכים nesachim are
פיגול. Pigul להקריב נסכיו למחר, l'hakriv nesachav l'machar, if you're just planning
on eating the נסכים nesachim tomorrow, הנסכים מפוגלים הזבח אינו מפוגל. hanesachim
mefugalim hazevach eino mefugal. So on the one hand it's a straight
application, but
on the other hand the חידוש chiddush is how do the נסכים
nesachim get associated with the קרבן? Quick question Mordechai. This only works
in the context of communal sacrifices, but not קרבן יחיד. korban yachid.
What do you mean where are קרבן יחיד? korban yachid? Why? My
intent—because when you bring to the בית המקדש, I'm bringing, yeah, so
that's the fact that you, so you're saying shouldn't the fact that
I own them both define them as being linked? And the answer
is, right, I understand, and the answer here at least according to
the חכמים Chachamim which we haven't state yet, we're going to state
it in the גמרא, is no, ownership does not make them הלכתית
halachically one קרבן. There's something about their קדושה kedusha and the ways
in which they can be used. Even though I bring them with
the intention of duality and everything? Correct, correct. Of course the funny
thing is why not say the same about the bread that comes
with the תודה? So let's look at the גמרא. We're just finished
to the bottom. תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: נסכי בהמה חייבין עליהם משום
פיגול. niskei behema chayavin aleihem mishum pigul. The נסכים nesachim you can
become פיגול מפני שדם הזבח מתירם ליקרב mipnei shedam hazevach matiram likareiv
because when you bring these the splatters of blood that allows them
now to be brought, so they're one with the קרבן and therefore
when you have a פיגול thought during the blood you can make
them into פיגול. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. אמרו לו לרבי
מאיר, amru lo l'Rabbi Meir, הלא אדם מביא זבחו היום ונסכיו עד
עשרה ימים. halo adam meivi zivcho hayom u'nesachav ad asara yamim. And
here it makes it clear why they're not necessarily. necessarily one tight
unit and they are different than the breads of the תודה and
the שתי הלחם, because you can bring the נסכים Nesachim on a
later day. Now, and that shows that they're not one unit. I
would add to the fact that not only because you do it
separate days that shows it's not unit, but the whole idea of
פיגול is a thought about what? Time. Doing it at the wrong
time. So you cannot say that the time parameters of this קרבן
should define the time parameters of, you know, that from a time
perspective we look at them as unified, because the קרבן have to
be eaten on the day it's brought, and the נסכים Nesachim can
be, you know, done on any later day. So why when I
think to myself, oh, I'm going to sprinkle the נסכים Nesachim tomorrow—not
sprinkle, whatever, put them in the מזבח tomorrow—because you can bring them
tomorrow, right? So even when I make the קרבן פיגול, why should
it affect the status of the נסכים Nesachim if they're not defined
by the time of the קרבן? Okay, so that's what the חכמים
Chachamim say back. אמר להן, Amar lahen, he said back to them:
אף אני לא אמרתי אלא בבואן עם הזבח. Af ani lo amarti
ela bevoin im hazavach. Okay, I agree. If you don't—this is like
Mordechai—if you don't have your נסכים Nesachim with you, then okay, then
they're not one unit. But if you bring them today, then they
are defined with the קרבן and they do have to be brought
today. So אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said back to him: אפשר
לשנותו לזבח אחר. Efshar leshnoso lezavach acher. And here they say, no,
even if you bring it today, there's nothing that specifically identifies it
with this קרבן. Now, again, why is that different than the לחמי
תודה? Lachmei Todah? It could be because since once the תורה Torah
has allowed me to bring them on a later day, the תורה
Torah has specifically said they're not connected. And therefore, even if I
happen to bring them on the same day, it's just they happen
to be here together. That does not define them as being connected.
So they always retain a more independent status. אפשר לזבח אחר. Efshar
lezavach acher. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so אמר רבא Amar Rava says:
קסבר רבי מאיר, Kasavar Rabbi Meir, הוקבעו בשחיטה כלחמי תודה. Hukvu bishchita
kelachmei Todah. No, it might be true that until you שחט shecht
the קרבן then you just happen to have them with you in
the מקדש, and you could bring them tomorrow, but as soon as
they're with you and you שחט shecht the קרבן—this is like Mordechai
was saying—that moment of שחיטה shchiting and them being with you in
the מקדש says they're one, which makes sense, but the חכמים Chachamim
are saying the תורה Torah allowed them to be separate, you can
always choose to separate them. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we taught similarly
in a ברייתא: לוג שמן של מצורע, Log shemen shel matzora, חייבין
עליו משום פיגול, chayavin alav mishum Pigul, ולוג velog of the מצורע
matzora can become פיגול מפני שדם אשם מתירו ליהנא. mipnei shedam asham
matziro leihana. Because the sprinkling of the אשם Asham allows you to
use this לוג, Log, brings—affects their status—to put on the מצורע. matzora.
דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says. אמרו לו לרבי מאיר, Amru lo le Rabbi Meir, they said
to רבי מאיר: Rabbi Meir: והלא אדם מביא אשמו היום ולוגו מכאן
עד עשרה ימים? Vehalo adam meivi ashamo hayom velogo mikan ad asara
yamim? You can bring your לוג Log separate, so it's never defined
as one unit. אמר להן: Amar lahen: אף אני לא אמרתי אלא
בבואן עם האשם. Af ani lo amarti ela bevoin im ha'asham. You're
right, if you don't have it with you, it's not one unit.
But if you have it with you, it is one unit. אמרו
לו, Amru lo, they said to him: אפשר לשנותו לאשם אחר. Efshar
leshnoso le'asham acher.
Even if it's with you, that does not define it as a
unit; you can always use it for something else. אמר רבא: Amar
Rava: קסבר רבי מאיר, Kasavar Rabbi Meir, הוקבעו בשחיטה כלחמי תודה. Hukvu
bishchita kelachmei Todah. The oil
is just like the bread of תודה; when you שחט shecht it,
it becomes one... shhh guys, a little softer... it becomes one unit.
So basically what the issue is is why are these different? Because
once there's a principle that you can bring them on a separate
day, the question is do they ever get brought together defined conceptually
as one unit? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says until you שחט shecht
the—the fact that you have them with you no, but from when
you שחט shecht it and they're with you, that makes them one
unit, and the חכמים say they always retain their independent status.
Good.