Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, Hoshanah Rabbah הושענא רבה, Hoshanah Rabbah,
more or less I guess. I don't know what the proper wish
is,
but on a more serious note, you know, really it's one tragedy
after another in Israel and as we were just discussing, the Daf
דף Daf has recently just been dealing with all these cases of
death and the Mitzvah מצווה, Mitzvah, so you know our hearts and
our Tefilot תפילות Tefilot go out to the injured and really to
everybody in Israel right now. We really should just know of security
and of peace.
Okay, so we begin on Mem Daled Amud Bet מ"ד עמוד ב'
Mem Daled Amud Bet with the Mishnah משנה Mishnah and we're moving
from Tumah טומאה, Tumah, we did the Issurim איסורים Issurim of Tumah
טומאה Tumah and Yayin יין Yayin and Tiglachat תגלחת, Tiglachat,
and two of those were very interesting in terms of their practical
relevance for other areas, Tumah טומאה Tumah for Tumat Kohanim טומאת כהנים
Tumat Kohanim and Tiglachat תגלחת Tiglachat for the general issue of shaving,
and Yayin יין Yayin in an interesting way just occurs to me
now because it became a paradigm for Ta'am k'Ikkar טעם כעיקר, Ta'am
k'Ikkar, so very relevant in the world of Kashrus כשרות. Kashrus. So
each one of those just occurs to me right now actually serves
as a basis for very important areas of Halacha הלכה Halacha elsewhere.
Now we return to more of the rituals associated with the Nazir
נזיר Nazir at the shaving that takes place at the end of
the process of Tumah טומאה Tumah and then the next Mishnah משנה
Mishnah the shaving that takes place at the end of the process
of Taharah טהרה. Taharah. So let's take a look at our Mishnah
משנה. Mishnah.
Tiglachat Tumah Keitzad תגלחת טומאה כיצד, Tiglachat Tumah Keitzad, how would you
do the shaving of impurity? And the meaning, we have a very
specific question that we're asking as we'll see. Hayah mazeh bashlishi u'bashvii
היה מזה בשלישי ובשביעי, Hayah mazeh bashlishi u'bashvii, you would do the
sprinkling of the ashes of the Parah Adumah פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
on day three and day seven, u'm'galei'ach bashvii ומגלח בשביעי, U'm'galei'ach bashvii,
and then shave on day seven, u'meivi korbanosav bashmini ומביא קרבנותיו בשמיני,
U'meivi korbanosav bashmini, and then bring the Korbanos קרבנות Korbanos on day
eight, which is what the Torah תורה Torah says.
Can you hand me a Chumash חומש Chumash here? Should actually, is
there a Chumash חומש Chumash there? Okay, so
it actually says, it actually says by the, oh look at that,
then the line was right and the whatever, thank you, I appreciate
that. So it says, it says, v'chi yamut
meis alav b'feta pit'om v'tamei rosh nizro v'gilach rosho b'yom taharato b'yom
hashvii yigalchennu וכי ימות מת עליו בפתע פתאום וטמא ראש נזרו וגלח
ראשו ביום טהרתו ביום השביעי יגלחנו. V'chi yamut meis alav b'feta pit'om
v'tamei rosh nizro v'gilach rosho b'yom taharato b'yom hashvii yigalchennu. The day
he becomes tahor טהור. tahor. U'v'yom hashmini yavi shtei torim o shenei
b'nei yonah וביום השמיני יביא שתי תורים או שני בני יונה. U'v'yom
hashmini yavi shtei torim o shenei b'nei yonah. The Korban קרבן Korban
is the next day. All right. V'im gilach bashmini meivi korbanosav bo
bayom divrei Rabbi Akiva ואם גילח בשמיני מביא קרבנותיו בו ביום דברי
רבי עקיבא. V'im gilach bashmini meivi korbanosav bo bayom divrei Rabbi Akiva.
And if for some reason he waited to shave until day eight,
you can still bring the Korbanos קרבנות. Korbanos. The Halacha הלכה Halacha
is not that you bring the Korbanos קרבנות Korbanos the day after
you shave. The Halacha הלכה Halacha is you bring the Korbanos קרבנות
Korbanos on day eight. You're supposed to shave on day seven. If
you postponed the shaving, that's also okay, you still bring the Korban
קרבן Korban on day eight. Amar lo Rabbi Tarfon אמר לו רבי
טרפון, Amar lo Rabbi Tarfon, Rabbi Tarfon said to him, mah bein
zeh l'metzora מה בין זה למצורע, Mah bein zeh l'metzora, how is
this different than a Metzora מצורע? Metzora? Because he's taking it for
granted that by a Metzora מצורע Metzora who waits to do his
shaving till day eight, the Korban קרבן Korban is brought on day
nine. Okay, so we'll see in a
minute like why that's taken for granted, but he takes that for
granted and therefore he says so the Nazir נזיר Nazir also if
he waited to shave till day eight he should bring his Korban
קרבן Korban on day nine. Okay, actually the
Metzora מצורע Metzora it's not shaving on day eight, as shaving a
day later but it's a seven-day wait till the Kohen כהן Kohen
visited him again and saw that it wasn't seven days of sprinkling
the ashes of the Parah Adumah פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, it was
seven days till the Kohen כהן Kohen visited him again. Anyway, so
amar lei אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, zeh taharato
tluyah b'yamav זה טהרתו תלויה בימיו, Zeh taharato tluyah b'yamav, by the
case of the Nazir נזיר Nazir his becoming tahor טהור tahor is
dependent on the days, u'metzora taharato tluyah b'tiglachto ומצורע טהרתו תלויה בתגלחתו,
U'metzora taharato tluyah b'tiglachto, but by the Metzora מצורע Metzora the shaving
itself is part of the Taharah טהרה Taharah process. Now what does
that mean? Or how does he know that? So Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
points out that the way he knows it is because by the
Nazir נזיר Nazir it just says v'gilach rosho וגלח ראשו v'gilach rosho
and then it says b'yom hashmini yavi shtei torim וביום השמיני יביא
שתי תורים, b'yom hashmini yavi shtei torim, mentions about shaving but that's
all it says. You shave on day seven b'yom hashvii ביום השביעי
b'yom hashvii but as opposed to, yeah I mean to say it
otherwise, but as opposed to by the Metzora מצורע Metzora where it
says the following.
Okay, it
says, so first there's a whole seven-day process.
He starts with his two birds, right? It looks like it's the
whole beginning of Parshat Tazria פרשת תזריע. Parshat Tazria. V'ra'ah hakohen v'hineih
nirpah nega hatzara'at min hatzarua v'tzivah hakohen v'lakach lamit-taher shtei tzipporim chayot
tehorot v'eitz erez u'shni tola'at v'ezov וראה הכהן והנה נרפא נגע הצרעת
מן הצרוע וצוה הכהן ולקח למטהר שתי צפרים חיות טהרות ועץ ארז
ושני תולעת ואזוב. V'ra'ah hakohen v'hineih nirpah nega hatzara'at min hatzarua v'tzivah
hakohen v'lakach lamit-taher shtei tzipporim chayot tehorot v'eitz erez u'shni tola'at v'ezov.
So he does the thing with the birds and he says v'shillach
et hatzippor hachayah al p'nei hasadeh ושלח את הצפר החיה על פני
השדה, v'shillach et hatzippor hachayah al p'nei hasadeh, I cut out a
little bit. Okay, so he does the whole thing with the birds.
Okay, then after the bird thing, v'khibes hamit-taher b'gadav v'gilach et kol
se'aro v'rachatz bamayim v'taher v'achar yavo el hamachaneh וכיבס המטהר בגדיו וגילח
את כל שערו ורחץ במים וטהר ואחר יבוא אל המחנה. V'khibes hamit-taher
b'gadav v'gilach et kol se'aro v'rachatz bamayim v'taher v'achar yavo el hamachaneh.
So he goes to the Mikveh מקווה. Mikveh. Then v'yashav michutz l'oholo
shivat yamim וישב מחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים, V'yashav michutz l'oholo shivat yamim,
seven-day wait. So seven-day wait after the bird thing, similar to the
Nazir נזיר, Nazir, the Nazir נזיר Nazir was a seven-day wait to
become tahor טהור tahor with the ashes of the Parah Adumah פרה
אדומה, Parah Adumah, this was a seven-day wait after the bird thing.
So so far it's parallel. יגלח את כל שערו, yegaleach et kol
se'aro, את ראשו, et rosho, it says it again, את ראשו ואת
זקנו ואת גבות עיניו,
et rosho v'et zkano v'et
gabot
einav, ואת כל שערו יגלח, v'et kol se'aro yegaleach, וכבס את בגדיו
ורחץ את בשרו במים וטהר. v'chibes et bgadav v'rachatz et bsaro bamayim
v'taher.
So him, after the גילוח, giluach, he has to immerse in a
מקוה, mikvah, he has to וכבס את בגדיו ורחץ את בשרו במים,
v'chibes et bgadav v'rachatz et bsaro bamayim, understood as going to a
מקוה mikvah וטהר. v'taher. And that's part of the טהרה tahara process.
So therefore Rabbi Akiva says is, is that by the מצורע, metzora,
the גילוח giluach is part of the טהרה tahara process, and afterwards
it requires going to a מקוה, mikvah, and only then are you
a—what does a person after they go to a מקוה? mikvah? A
טבול יום. tvul yom. Okay. And therefore the logic is, so until
you do the—if you waited till day eight, he assumed, even if
let's say you went to the מקוה mikvah on day seven, if
you're the מצורע, metzora, it didn't work, right? In order to enable
you to go to the מקוה, mikvah, you have to do the
shaving first. So if you waited till day eight to do the
shaving, even if you did the מקוה mikvah day seven, it didn't
work, so you'll have to do a מקוה mikvah again on day
eight, okay? And then you become a טבול יום. tvul yom. As
a טבול יום, tvul yom, you're not yet done. Since it's clear
that the Torah wants you to wait till the next day after
you go to the מקוה, mikvah, the assumption is the Torah wants
you to be totally out of your טומאה tumah before you bring
the קרבן korban the next day. So if you waited till day
eight, then you did the shaving, you'd have to go to the
מקוה mikvah again, because the מקוה mikvah comes
after. That is the ending of the טהרה tahara process, that makes
you a טבול יום. tvul yom. You have to wait till day
nine to bring your קרבן. korban. That he says there, it's part
of the טהרה tahara process. Whereas
if you go to the נזיר, Nazir, the טהרה tahara process is
just the sprinkling of the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
He's just טמא מת, tamei meis, it's not a unique טהרה. tahara.
He's טמא tamei like anybody else who touched a dead body. Day
three and day seven make you טהור. tahor. The shaving is a
ritual, but it never says you go to the מקוה mikvah after
you shave, so it's not part of the טהרה tahara process. So
if you waited till day eight, so you go to the מקוה
mikvah on day seven after the sprinkling of the ashes of the
פרה אדומה, parah adumah, you're a טבול יום tvul yom on day
seven. Even if you forgot to do the shaving, you're totally טהור
tahor by day eight, you just have to do the shaving ritual.
So he's a very close read of the פסוקים. psukim. He says
the shaving ritual by the מצורע metzora is part of the טהרה
tahara process, it requires מקוה mikvah afterwards, and it requires waiting till
the next day. So if you postponed it a day, you'll have
to bring the קרבן korban on day nine. Whereas by the נזיר
Nazir who's טמא מת, tamei meis, it's a separate ritual, it's not
part of becoming טהור, tahor, so if you postponed it a day,
so what? You do the גילוח giluach and the קרבן korban both
on day eight. Okay, so that's what he says. אמר ליה זה
טהרתו תלויה בימיו ומצורע טהרתו תלויה בתגלחתו, amar leih zeh taharato tluyah
beyamav u'metzora taharato tluyah betiglachto, by just day seven. ומצורע טהרתו תלויה
בתגלחתו, u'metzora taharato tluyah betiglachto, the shaving is part of the טהרה.
tahara. ואין מביא קרבן אלא אם כן העריב שמשו. v'ein meivi korban
ela im kein heriv shimsho. And therefore you can only bring a
קרבן korban after the setting of the sun, not at night obviously,
till the next day, because you're a טבול יום. tvul yom. So
if you went to the מקוה mikvah on day seven without shaving
for a מצורע, metzora, it doesn't matter. Until you go shave and
then go to the מקוה, mikvah, then you're a טבול יום tvul
yom and you can't bring a קרבן korban until the next day,
till day nine.
In all cases the משנה mishnah is a נזיר Nazir that became
טמא, tamei, and now they're talking about thirty days later.
No, no, no, נזיר Nazir to become טמא tamei in order to
restart the נזירות nezirut of טהרה, tahara, he goes through a seven
day טהרה tahara process, brings a קרבן. korban. This is not ending
his נזירות, nezirut, this is restarting the נזירות nezirut of טהרה. tahara.
Okay, alright. So very clear distinction of Rabbi Akiva, one is just
a ritual of נזירות nezirut and the other is a ritual of
טהרה. tahara. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says right this: קיבלה מיניה
או לא? kiblah mineih o lo? Did Rabbi Tarfon accept Rabbi Akiva's
answer or not? We never know how Rabbi Tarfon responded. תא שמע,
ta shema, come and hear, דתני הלל, detani Hillel, Hillel teaches a
ברייתא, braisa, this is not הלל הזקן, Hillel HaZaken, this is the
אמורא Amora Hillel.
גילח בשמיני, gilach bashmini, if he shaved on day eight, okay, מביא
קרבנותיו בתשיעי, meivi korbanotav batshii, he brings the קרבנות korbanot on day
nine. Now of course you say well maybe that's the מצורע, metzora,
right? Who's that talking about, a נזיר Nazir or a
מצורע? metzora? Okay, but תוספות Tosafot says they had a מסורה masorah
that this was talking about a נזיר, Nazir, because if it was
talking about a מצורע metzora everybody agrees to that, we already took
that for granted, that if a מצורע metzora waits to shave till
day eight, he brings his קרבן korban till day nine. But we're
assuming this is talking about a נזיר. Nazir. So then the question
is who is it that says that if a נזיר Nazir postponed
the shaving till day eight, he has to wait another day for
the קרבן? korban? So if you thought that קיבלה מיניה, kiblah mineih,
so if Rabbi Tarfon wound up agreeing to Rabbi Akiva, then nobody
would say you have to wait till day nine, you just do
it on day eight. So we assume this ברייתא braisa is saying
that the נזיר Nazir has to bring it on day nine if
he
postponed—we're talking about a נזיר—if Nazir he postponed his גילוח, giluach, so
the only person that could be is Rabbi Tarfon, assuming Rabbi Tarfon
did not concede to Rabbi Akiva.
Could be before he conceded.
Oh, that maybe it's a משנה ראשונה mishnah rishonah of Rabbi Tarfon.
Alright, I don't know, it's a good point. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says anyway but that at least seems to reflect that position.
אמר רבא, amar Rava, לא קשיא, lo kashya, no, not necessarily, maybe
Rabbi Tarfon conceded to Rabbi Akiva, so why would you have to
wait till day nine? הא דטבל בשביעי הא דלא טבל בשביעי, ha
detaval bashvii ha delo taval bashvii, because really the reason you're waiting
is not because you postponed your... גילוח giluach till day eight, the
reason you've postponed your going to the מקווה mikvah till day eight.
And again, every, so clearly even for the נזיר Nazir for טומאת
מת tumas meis going to the מקווה mikvah you have to go
to the מקווה mikvah and you're only to become a טבול יום
tevul yom and then you're only טהור tahor by the evening. So
if you post, even if you did the sprinkling on day seven,
thank you. If you postponed the מקווה mikvah till day eight, you're
not טהור tahor till day nine and therefore that would be the
case. Of course that is a really bad read of the ברייתא
braisa because then why would it take גילוח בשמיני? giluach bishmini? It
should have said טבל בשמיני, taval bishmini, right? The whole point is
missing. So anyway, it's a very strange response. Certainly the simple sense
of the ברייתא braisa assuming it's talking about a נזיר Nazir shows
it's רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon did not agree to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. Okay, yes.
It's not obvious that טבול יום tevul yom cannot bring קרבנות korbonos
and have them be sacrificed.
Okay, so that is an excellent question.
What is the הלכה halacha about having a טמא tamei person having
קרבנות korbonos brought for him? So the הלכה halacha is ערב וטמא
המשלחין קרבנותיהם arev ve-tamei hamishalchin korbonoseihem is that even though they can't
go into, you know, certain zones in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
they can have somebody bring their קרבנות korbonos for them. The
הלכה למעשה halacha le-ma'aseh is that the טמא tamei is only somebody
who is טמא tamei like שרץ sheretz or נבילה neveila or so
on. If the טמא tamei is a טמא מת tamei meis or
זב zav or זבה zava or מצורע, metzora, they cannot have somebody
bring their קרבן korban for them. That's just הלכה, halacha, you should
know. Okay, but even if assuming we didn't exactly know that or
that was somewhat debated,
תוספות's Tosefos point is it's implicit from the פסוקים pesukim that here
the תורה Torah wants you, whatever the other הלכה halacha is, if
you're a מצורע metzora טבול יום tevul yom and you want to
send a שלמים shlamim in, we can talk about it. But it's
implicit from the פסוקים pesukim that the תורה Torah wants you to
be totally טהור tahor before bringing your relevant קרבן korban because it
says ביום השביעי bayom hashevi'i or מגלח megale'ach
and you go to the מקווה mikvah and the next day you
bring your קרבן. korban. Why didn't it have you bring it that
day, right? Or by the נזיר, Nazir, it says he goes to
the, you know, he's טהור tahor on day seven with the ashes
of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, right, and then we assume he
goes to the מקווה mikvah as well, or whatever, and then on
the next day he brings his קרבן, korban, right? So it's clear
here, that's what תוספות Tosefos says, from the פסוקים pesukim it's clear
that the תורה Torah wanted the נזיר Nazir or the מצורע metzora
to be totally טהור, tahor, to go to the מקווה, mikvah, get
out of the טבול יום tevul yom status, right, in order to,
now of course you could say maybe not, maybe it's just arbitrarily
assigning day eight, it's not related to being or not being a
טבול יום. tevul yom. But anyway, that's what we're like assuming, okay?
So therefore, but yes, it's a good question. Is it really true
that a טבול יום tevul yom can't have a קרבן korban brought
for him? So to some degree we're about to turn to that
question right now. Okay, to some degree the answer might, it probably
makes הלכה halacha yes,
maybe whatever, but it might be very well yes. But, yes of
what?
That a טבול יום tevul yom cannot have a קרבן korban brought
for him, okay? But at least for these קרבנות korbonos תוספות's Tosefos
point is the simple sense of the פסוקים pesukim is that for
bringing the קרבן korban of the מצורע metzora process or the קרבן
korban to start the נזירות טהרה, neziros taharah, the תורה Torah wants
the person fully out of the state out of their state of
טומאה. tumah.
But like for a שלמים, shlamim, you can have someone bring it.
So we could debate whether he could have a שלמים shlamim sent
for him, okay? But at least here, for these קרבנות, korbonos, it
seems clear that the תורה Torah wants him fully out of that
state. Yes.
But the פרה parah was different again. Yeah,
wasn't there something about the rabbis using a טבול יום tevul yom
for
to do the, right, process of the פרה אדומה? parah adumah? But
that was to burn the פרה parah etc. and to do the
whole process of creating the ashes, right, but not to
bring a sacrifice in a way.
No, I mean, and it's not being brought for him and he's
the officiant
and it's not in the עזרה. azara. Anyway, but yeah, okay, so
but yeah, I mean, it is not exactly the same but it's
related. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So now this
question of a טבול יום tevul yom is exactly what we turn
to.
Okay, אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
אשכחינהו לחבריה דרב נתן בר אושעיא, ashkachinu lachavrei de-Rav Nassan bar Oshaya,
I found the colleagues of רב נתן בר אושעיא, Rav Nassan bar
Oshaya, יתבין קמן, yasvin kaman, they were sitting and they were saying
that we've got this ברייתא braisa and here's what this ברייתא braisa
says. Presumably they're quoting this is a ברייתא braisa that they're quoting,
the way תוספות Tosefos understands it. ובא לפני ה' אל פתח אהל
מועד, u-va lifnei Hashem el pesach ohel moed, this is by a
זב. zav. Okay, it says that the זב zav on day seven
goes ahead and he has to bring these two birds and he
sacrifices and he brings them to פתח אהל מועד pesach ohel moed
ונתנם אל הכהן. u-nesanam el hacohen. And I'm sorry, this is on
day eight, okay? So he has the seven-day טהרה taharah process and
on day eight he brings these birds to the כהן. kohen. ונתנם
אל הכהן. u-nesanam el hacohen. אימתיי הוא בא בזמן שהוא טבל ועשה
הערב שמש?
eimasai hu ba bizman
she-hu taval v'asah ha'erev shemesh? So beforehand it said that he would
go to the מקווה, mikvah, could I borrow the חומש chumash here
again?
So says איש איש כי יהיה זב מבשרו
ish ish ki yihiyeh
zav mibsaro and וכי יטהר הזב מזובו וספר לו שבעת ימים לטהרתו
וכיבס בגדיו ורחץ בשרו במים חיים וטהר. v'chi yithar hazav mizovo v'safah
lo shivas yamim letaharato v'chibes begadav v'rachatz besaro bamayim chayim ve-taher. Okay,
so seven days goes to the מקווה mikvah and then... And day
eight he comes to the משכן. Mishkan. Okay, so when he's טובל
toveled on day seven,
he's a טבול יום tvul yom on day seven, and on
day eight he comes to the משכן. Mishkan. So, here's what the
ברייתא baraisa says. אימתי הוא בא בזמן שהוא טבל ועשה הערב שמש,
Emasai hu ba bizman shehu taval ve'oso ha'erev shemesh, when can he
finally come to the משכן Mishkan after he's gone to the מקוה
mikvah and הערב שמש ha'erev shemesh and he's no longer a טבול
יום? tvul yom? אין, In, that's yes. לא טבל ועשה הערב שמש,
Lo taval ve'oso ha'erev shemesh, if he had not done that, if
he was still a טבול יום, tvul yom, לא, lo, he could
not enter onto the משכן Mishkan grounds. אלמא קסבר, Alma kasavar, now
presumably that was, again, you could read this that this was that
the friends were saying all of this. תוספות Tosfos reads that that
this was like a ברייתא baraisa and then this next line was
the colleagues of רב נתן Rav Nasan reflecting on the ברייתא baraisa
or inferring from the ברייתא. baraisa. So the ברייתא baraisa teaches that
he can only enter the מקדש Mikdash grounds after, you know, when
he's no longer טבול יום. tvul yom. So therefore they say, oh,
look, what we can infer from that is, אלמא קסבר, alma kasavar,
you see this ברייתא baraisa is of the opinion,
טבול יום של זב כזב דמי, tvul yom shel zav kezav dami,
that even though he's a טבול יום tvul yom of a זב,
zav, he still has the status of a זב. zav. Why? Because
what's the הלכה? halacha? A זב, zav, this is very relevant למעשה
lemaseh believe it or not, or possibly for a reason I'm about
to tell you. A זב zav is not allowed to enter
onto, into מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, okay, which was in the time
of the מדבר, Midbar, מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. The translation of מחנה
לויה Machaneh Leviyah nowadays is, anybody know? הר הבית. Har Habayis. So
even and he would be transgressing, you know,
by entering it, what if his seven days were over, he went
to the מקוה, mikvah, he was a טבול יום, tvul yom, all
he needed was for nightfall to hit and then he would be
well totally טהור, tahor, although if he had if he saw for
three days he'd have to bring a קרבן korban on day eight
to be totally totally טהור, tahor, but okay,
and we'll get to that in a minute. Would on that day
after having gone to the מקוה mikvah and all he needed was
nightfall and he was a טבול יום, tvul yom, he enter on
הר הבית, Har Habayis, would he still be חייב? chayav? Okay, is
a טבול יום tvul yom of a זב zav like a זב?
zav? That's the question. Now why is this relevant nowadays?
Because the
other people that are relevant that are included in the category of
אסור assur on הר הבית Har Habayis is anybody that has טומאה
יוצא מגופו, tumah yotzei migufo, somebody who is טמא tamei because of
something happening to their body. A מצורע metzora is even worse, okay,
but basically a type of a flow, which includes, yes, women who
are נדה niddah and includes men who have seminal emissions. So when
they lead these tours up on הר הבית Har Habayis and they
say we're going to that they know what they're doing and they're
not going to take you onto the place of the מקום המקדש
makom ha-mikdash itself, they're just going to take you to הר הבית,
Har Habayis, so the assumption is because even if you're טמא מת,
tamei meis, which we assume everybody is nowadays, you're allowed in מחנה
לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, you're allowed in הר הבית, Har Habayis, but you're
not allowed on the actual מקום המקדש. makom ha-mikdash. So they say
fine, we're going to avoid מקום המקדש. makom ha-mikdash. Okay, here's the
only problem. The only problem is is that let's say the woman
is a נדה niddah or let's say the man had a seminal
emission. So what they I again, I don't know, I know that
they tell the men that make sure you have gone to the
מקוה mikvah the day before, sort of solve that problem, okay,
I don't know what they tell the women if you're a נדה
niddah you shouldn't be coming, okay, I hope they do. Anyway, but
let's say they say that to the man. So the thing is
fine, let's say he goes to the מקוה mikvah the day before
and they're going on a 7:00 AM whatever thing and then he
has sex with his wife at night or has a seminal emission
or whatever. So even if he says, even if they say go
to the מקוה mikvah that morning before we start, okay, so he
goes to the מקוה mikvah that morning, fine, he's a טבול יום,
tvul yom, right? So he's a טבול יום tvul yom of a
בעל קרי. ba'al keri. So do they say if you had to
go to the מקוה, mikvah, you know, if you couldn't go to
the מקוה mikvah yesterday and whatever, then don't come on the tour?
I mean I don't think they tell them that. So if he's
a טבול יום tvul yom of a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, okay
now interestingly a נדה niddah would not have the same הלכה, halacha,
she wouldn't be a טבול יום tvul yom till nightfall, but we
can talk about why, but for the man who goes during the
day it would be. But anyway, so would that would a טבול
יום tvul yom of בעל קרי ba'al keri like a טבול יום
tvul yom of a זב zav also be אסור assur to go
on הר הבית, Har Habayis, he'd be חייב chayav for going on
הר הבית? Har Habayis? So that's the question of whether טבול יום
tvul yom of a זב zav is כזב kezav or not. And
they wanted to infer that the answer was yes. Why do they
want to infer that the answer was yes? Because it says, here
you have this זב zav who had to go to the מקוה
mikvah on day seven and says on day eight he can come
to לפני אהל מועד, lifnei ohel moed, which means on day seven
he wasn't able to come לפני אהל מועד lifnei ohel moed and
therefore you see that until day eight he's אסור assur to come
enter into, he's still has that status and אסור assur to go
onto sanctified ground. Yes Charlie, you had a question?
Is it rabbinical that an עם הארץ am ha'aretz is considered the
same as a
זב?
zav? Yeah, but let's not worry about that about there are other
people right that have different restrictions but that's not right, correct.
ובא לפני השם פתח אהל מועד
Uva lifnei
Hashem
petach ohel moed is in is where in is that?
Okay, so we're going to get to that. פתח אהל מועד Petach
Ohel Moed might as well sort of discuss it now because it's
going to come up.
Here's your, here's the
אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, alright? אהל מועד Ohel Moed which here's the
קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, okay, equals the משכן, Mishkan, okay. The פתח
אהל מועד, Petach Ohel Moed, right, this opening here actually, right, is
so this is equal to the מקדש, Mikdash, okay, right? This is
that, right, exactly. Then you've got the whole והחצר, ve-he-chatzer, right? And
even החצר he-chatzer is מקום makom is equal to the מקדש. Mikdash.
Is? Yeah. The thing that is מחנה לוייה Machaneh Leviyah is all
the camp סביב לויים, saviv Leviyim, right? יחנו סביב למשכן אהל מועד
yachanu saviv le-mishkan Ohel Moed and they're protecting the אהל מועד, Ohel
Moed, right? So actually the זב zav before day before he before
he's a טבול יום, tevul yom, as a זב, zav, not only
can't come לפני אהל מועד lifnei Ohel Moed which is in the
חצר chatzer and is in the מקדש Mikdash region, he can't even
come into the מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah. So that's going to be
a question later, why why does the פסוקים pesukim say only on
day eight come into אהל מועד? Ohel Moed? Before day eight he
couldn't even come to מחנה לוייה, Machaneh Leviyah, alright? But we're assuming
right now we're not focusing on that right now.
Could someone explain פתח אהל מועד Petach Ohel Moed is that the
כהן kohen
is inside the מחנה שכינה Machaneh Shechinah or whatever and the person
only approaches as far as the edge of the מחנה? machaneh? No,
because in the normal מקדש, Mikdash, right? In the normal מקדש, Mikdash,
right? You had here, right? You had this is you had you
had
עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim which was part of הר הבית Har HaBayit
so that was מחנה לוייה Machaneh Leviyah together everything was מחנה לוייה,
Machaneh Leviyah, right? And then you had עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael and
then you had
עזרת כהנים Ezrat Kohanim and all of this is מקום המקדש, Makom
HaMikdash, okay? All of this. Right? And then here you had right
here you had the what was the same as the משכן Mishkan
and here you had the מזבח, mizbe'ach, right? But the ישראל Yisrael
could go in for the first eleven אמות amot and that was
all מקום המקדש. Makom HaMikdash. So when you bring it פתח אהל
מועד Petach Ohel Moed you don't stand over here. You actually are
able to go into מקום המקדש, Makom HaMikdash, right? Now obviously you
probably wouldn't go all the way up to here because the מזבח
mizbe'ach would be here, so what literally פתח אהל מועד Petach Ohel
Moed probably means in front present yourself in front of but not
literally right up to, okay? But you would the same way as
a ישראל Yisrael you would bring your קרבן korban and stand here.
And in the משכן Mishkan the מזבח mizbe'ach was in there? Was?
What I'm sorry what did you say?
No, the not the מזבח mizbe'ach of the קרבנות. korbanot. You can't
have it under a roof, right?
Oh, in the actual משכן Mishkan part.
In the משכן, Mishkan, right.
Okay,
so so there's no what's the distinction between inside the אהל מועד
Ohel Moed and right outside the
אהל מועד?
Ohel Moed? Inside and right outside,
that there's another לאו lav of entering in here שלא לצורך עבודה,
shelo l'tzorech avodah,
whatever. But in terms of the issue about how טהור tahor you
have to be, there's really no difference.
I always thought פתח אהל מועד Petach Ohel Moed was
somewhere here you present yourself in front of the אהל מועד Ohel
Moed exactly in front
of the פתח petach correct? Because you have the little
parts, you have the whole קלעים kla'im but the חצר chatzer but
weren't there several levels? You have the part that you have the
כתפות ktefot but then even further on there was yet another one.
No, פתח אהל מועד Petach Ohel Moed just means you present yourself
in front. All right, let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara says
this. All right. So it says
this. אלמא קסבר טבול יום של זב כזב דמי. Alma kasavar tevul
yom shel zav ke-zav dami. So that's what we learn from the
פסוקים pesukim or that's what the ברייתא braita is trying to tell
us.
So אמינא להו אנא, amina lehu ana, so I said back to
them כזב דמי. ke-zav dami. אמינא להו הנך אנא, amina lehu hanach
ana, I said back to them אלא מעתה ela me'ata if that's
true, that's what you can infer from the
פסוק, pasuk, גבי נזיר טמא נמי כתיב gabe nazir tamei nami ketiv
by the נזיר nazir who
became טמא, tamei, יביא שתי תורים אל הכהן אל פתח אהל מועד.
yavi shtei torim el hakohen el petach
Ohel Moed. He says he does that on day eight, right? So
you say the same thing. אימתיה הוא בא בזמן שטבל ועשה הערב
שמש, Eimatei hu ba bizman shetaval ve'asah ha'erev shemesh, say the same
thing, he has to be totally טהור, tahor, not just here's the
shift. What we're saying until now we said and that whole discussion
Shali asked about can't a טמא tamei person send his קרבן? korban?
The whole point was you have to be totally טהור tahor you
can't be a טבול יום tevul yom to bring your קרבן. korban.
Now we're saying it's not just you have to be totally טהור
tahor to bring your
קרבן korban but you have to be totally טהור tahor to enter
onto the grounds. Okay, so he said one minute, if that's true,
then by the נזיר nazir also, when it says wait till day
eight, it's not just saying wait till day eight to bring your
קרבן, korban, it's saying wait till day eight for the נזיר nazir
to enter the grounds. But the נזיר nazir is a טומאת מת
tumat met and now he's a טבול יום tevul yom of טומאת
מת. tumat met. טמא מת Tamei met doesn't have to wait till
day eight to enter into מחנה לוייה Machaneh Leviyah or someone who's
טמא מת tamei met even when he's a fully טמא מת tamei
met can enter into
מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah. מכדי שרי נכנסו היכא קיימן בשערי Michdi sharei
nichnasu heicha kayman bisharei into the עזרת נשים, Ezras Noshim, into מחנה
לוייה. Machaneh Leviya.
The semicircular stairs there. Yeah, exactly. So some people have a picture.
Okay fine, lovely. All right,
anyway people. Okay, התניא באותה ששנויה ברייתא, hatanya b'osa sheshana baraita, טמא
מת tamei meis מותר להיכנס mutar lehikanes למחנה לוייה. l'machaneh Leviya. Somebody
who touched a dead body can go into
מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviya. Not only somebody who touched a dead body,
but אפילו מת עצמו, afilu meis atzmo, you can a dead body
itself can be in מחנה לוייה, Machaneh Leviya, שנאמר shene'emar על הר
הבית, al Har Habayis, ויקח משה את עצמות יוסף עמו. Vayikach Moshe
es atzmos Yosef imo. Moshe took the bones of Yosef with him.
מאי עמו, Mai imo, what does it mean with him? עמו במחיצתו,
Imo b'mechitzoso, that they were right there like you know right next
to like in his boundary, right, you know, in his tent. עמו
במחנה לוייה, Imo b'Machaneh Leviya, there he was in מחנה לוייה Machaneh
Leviya and he had the bones of Yosef. So a dead body
itself. So if you read the פסוקים p'sukim to say you have
to wait till day eight to allow you to enter the grounds,
that's clearly not true by a נזיר. Nazir. A נזיר, Nazir, forget
that he's a טבול יום tvul yom of טמא מת tamei meis
on day seven, even when he was a full טמא מת, tamei
meis, he could have entered into the grounds of מחנה לוייה. Machaneh
Leviya. Okay, so therefore that is not a legitimate read of the
פסוקים. p'sukim. The פסוקים p'sukim might just be saying you have to
wait till day eight to bring your קרבן, korban, but not that
you have to wait till day eight to enter onto the grounds.
Yes.
Bones have the same status as the מת? meis?
Yes, absolutely. Why we even learned that yesterday about you know עצם
כשעורה etzem k'se'ora and about the טומאה tumah of a כהן Kohen
being טמא tamei to bones and when is it? Yes, the answer
is yes.
This is the
פתח האוהל?
Pesach Ha'ohel?
No, that's the פתח Pesach of the חצר. chatzer. This is the
אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. The אהל מועד Ohel Moed has an אהל.
ohel. The אהל מועד Ohel Moed has a tent on top of
it.
So where is פתח אהל מועד Pesach Ohel Moed in here? You
were saying like right... yeah right. And you said you're allowed to
go to where?
No, but it means anywhere in the חצר chatzer you're presenting yourself
to פתח אהל מועד. Pesach Ohel Moed. Okay, but actually I should
have drawn this more like this, that's true.
Okay. Yeah, anyway. What's this issue about עצמות חמורים atzmos chamorim and
do עצמות atzmos have a different status?
Yeah, but that's...
I think I know what you're talking about but that's... what about
the טומאה tumah of a כתבי קודש? kisvei kodesh?
Yeah, but not relevant. We'll talk about that later. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so clearly we're not talking about the issue of the פסוקים p'sukim
is not the issue of entering onto the grounds. Okay, so אלא,
ella, so rather here's what's going on in the פסוקים. p'sukim. Now
here's a slight question about what your גירסא girsa is, like whether
you have the word לא lo in it or not. אלא, Ella,
טבול יום של זב tvul yom shel zav according to תוספות Tosafos
and the ראש Rosh the גירסא girsa is, לאו כזב דמי. lav
k'zav dami. Okay, normally a טבול יום tvul yom of a זב
zav would not be a זב zav for under normal circumstances, but
here the guy is more than just a טבול יום, tvul yom,
right, because what does this זב zav need to get out of
his status of טומאה? tumah? He needs to go to the מקוה
mikvah on day seven, even even by day seven, what's left for
him to do? Go to the מקוה, mikvah, wait for nightfall and
bring a קרבן.
korban. So he is not just a normal טבול יום, tvul yom,
he's a... why the טבול יום tvul yom in a way, one
of the reasons it's so light is that everything is done you
just have to wait for nightfall. You're just waiting. But a טבול
יום tvul yom that also has to bring a קרבן korban the
next day, his status might be seen as not as sort of
naturally transitory. It needs another act to undo to fully מטהר metaher
him.
His waiting is different, his waiting is so that he can bring
the... oh he has to bring the קרבן. korban. Right. As opposed
to a טבול יום tvul yom which is simply...
well, yeah, but I would say it differently, his... he will not
be טהור tahor fully until he brings a קרבן, korban, a normal
טבול יום tvul yom will be fully טהור tahor if he just
waits. Now what would be a case of a זב zav who's
a טבול יום tvul yom that's not also a מחוסר כיפורים? mechussar
kippurim? So the answer is a זב zav who only became a
זב zav through seeing twice. The difference between a זב zav who
sees two times and a זב zav who sees three times
is at three times you need to bring a קרבן, korban, two
times you do not, but either way you're still a זב. zav.
So what אביי, Abaye, the way that תוספות Tosafos and the ראש
Rosh read this is if a זב zav saw twice or we
could say if a בעל קרי, baal keri, okay, and the only
thing you need is going to the מקוה mikvah and then waiting,
okay, so after you've gone to the מקוה mikvah you're לאו כזב
דמי, lav k'zav dami, and if you were to enter the הר
הבית Har Habayis you would not transgress. This guy is different, this
guy actually is has a more the status is even after going
to the מקוה mikvah is... is not as transitory because he has
to bring a קרבן korban the next day so for him the
story is a little bit different. Okay.
What was the distinction between a נזיר Nazir and a מצורע? Metzora?
Well we'll get to that in a minute but let's just finish
the point by the זב. zav. Wait, no questions now, I just
have to finish... no questions right now, we'll get to בזמן הזה.
bazman hazeh. I said no questions. Let's take a look. Okay, אלא,
ella, you'll get your questions in a minute, let's finish this thought.
טבול יום של זב כזב דמי. Tvul yom shel zav k'zav dami.
ואפילו הכי כיון דמחוסר כפרה, Ve'afilu hachi kivun d'mechussar kapara, since again
I'm going to read this the way תוספות Tosafos and the ראש
Rosh does it, since this טבול יום tvul yom is also a
טבול יום tvul yom that needs כפרה kapara the next day, לא
עייל. lo ayil. He cannot go in. Now of course the... The
point is is that so in the end אביי Abaye actually is
reading the פסוקים pesukim that it's an issue about going in, which
is like very strange. His whole point was to argue and say
the פסוקים pesukim are not talking about going in cause it wouldn't
work by the זב, zav, okay? And now he's sort of conceding
the point but just saying it's a special case here. It's a
special case because he's not just a טבול יום, tevul yom, he's
a טבול יום tevul yom that's מחוסר כיפורים... michusar kippurim... כפרה... kapparah...
כיפורים, kippurim, כיפור... כיפורים. kippurim.
Anyway, ואי במחנה לויה קאי, ve'ee bemachaneh leviyah kai, now we've got
a problem, okay? Because what אביי Abaye also didn't say, and this
is, is that the,
is that here, no, no, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. So the other
thing now we're talking about is we're getting back to this question
that if a טבול יום tevul yom of a זב zav who
is מחוסר כיפורים michusar kippurim cannot go in, is still like a
זב, zav, then he's not just אסור assur in מחנה שכינה, machaneh
shechina, he's אסור assur in מחנה לויה. machaneh leviyah. So why does
it say on day eight בא אל פתח אהל מועד? ba el
petach ohel moed? Before day eight he couldn't even come to מחנה
לויה. machaneh leviyah. So we're reading בא אל אהל מועד ba el
ohel moed means on day eight then you're allowed even in מחנה
לויה. machaneh leviyah. So if that's what it's saying, on day eight
you're allowed in מחנה לויה, machaneh leviyah, why does it describe it
as פתח אהל מועד? petach ohel moed? So that's what he's saying.
Okay, ואי במחנה לויה קאי אמאי קרי ליה אהל מועד? ve'ee bemachaneh
leviyah kai amai karei lei ohel moed? למימרא, lemeimra, to tell you,
מה התם מחוסר כפרה לא עייל, ma hatam michusar kapparah lo ayyel,
אף למחנה לויה נמי מחוסר כפרה לא עייל. af lemachaneh leviyah nami
michusar kapparah lo ayyel. And this is going to explain, we're getting
back to the פסוקים, pesukim, the difference between the מצורע metzora and
the זב. zav. Because here's how we learn out that a זב
zav who is מחוסר כיפורים michusar kippurim is not... has a status
of a זב zav and is not allowed. It's not cause the
פסוק pasuk says on day eight he may come, or because it
says it also by a נזיר, nazir, on day eight he may
come, and we know a נזיר nazir can come earlier than day
eight. So the פסוקים pesukim that say on day eight he comes
and brings his קרבן korban is only telling you you need to
wait till he's not a טבול יום tevul yom for the bringing
of the קרבן. korban. Those פסוקים pesukim are not telling you what
space he's allowed to enter. Those פסוקים pesukim are saying wait till
he goes to the מקוה, mikvah, he's not a טבול יום, tevul
yom, the next day... no, it is a problem of him being
a טבול יום tevul yom like that was the discussion רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, but he has to be
not a טבול יום tevul yom to have his קרבן korban brought.
It's not a question of where he may enter. It's clear from
the case of the מצורע metzora who can enter the grounds earlier
that the waiting is a waiting to bring your קרבן. korban. So
the פסוקים pesukim that say you wait till day eight to come,
it's not about coming, it's about bringing your קרבן. korban. Okay. But
here is how we learn out that a זב zav who is
מחוסר כיפורים michusar kippurim is even as... is like a זב zav
and is not allowed to enter into... into... is like a זב
zav and is not allowed to enter into מחנה לויה, machaneh leviyah,
okay? Because... because why does it say he comes to פתח אהל
מועד? petach ohel moed? If... now of course this is a little
circular... if part of the issue is that a זב, zav, before,
you know, can't even come into מחנה לויה, machaneh leviyah, now it's
a little circular because we just said the point is about bringing
the קרבן, korban, not where you may enter, but okay. Anyway, but
he says we're going to assume that it's talking about the זב
zav being in מחנה לויה machaneh leviyah and it still says come
to פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel moed. Well, why is it describing
it that way? So here's why it's describing it that way:
אמאי קרי ליה אהל מועד? amai karei lei ohel moed? למימרא, lemeimra,
this is what tells you, מה התם מחוסר כפרה לא עייל, ma
hatam michusar kapparah lo ayyel, the same way somebody who is מחוסר
כיפורים michusar kippurim cannot enter into אהל מועד ohel moed even if
you're not a טבול יום, tevul yom, even if you've gone to
the מקוה mikvah and it's nightfall and it's the next day and
all you're waiting to do is bring your קרבן, korban, you cannot
enter into מקום המקדש makom hamikdash until you've brought your קרבן. korban.
אף למחנה לויה נמי מחוסר כפרה לא עייל. af lemachaneh leviyah nami
michusar kapparah lo ayyel. So
therefore even in מחנה לויה machaneh leviyah you cannot enter in, at
least if... it's a little funny because here מחוסר כפרה michusar kapparah
does not mean you haven't brought your קרבן, korban, but it means
you're טבול יום tevul yom waiting to bring your קרבן korban the
next day. Okay, והתם מנלן? vehasam minalan? This is getting a little
complicated. Let me finish the sentence and then I'll go back and
unpack it. והתם מנלן, vehasam minalan, where do we know that from?
דתניא: detanya: טמא יהיה עוד טומאתו בו. tamei yiheyeh od tumato bo.
Okay. He shall be טמא, tamei, his טומאה tumah is still with
him. So that's טמא, tamei, remains טמא, tamei, לרבות טבול יום. lerabbos
tevul yom. עוד טומאתו בו, od tumaso bo, לרבות מחוסר כפרה. lerabbos
michusar kapparah. So what we've... what?
Right? טמא יהיה... tamei yiheyeh... that was by טמא מת. tamei meit.
Okay, so here's the point, okay? We know from this פסוק pasuk
טמא יהיה tamei yiheyeh that a טבול יום tevul yom of anything
is אסור assur in... right? Not a טבול יום, tevul yom, excuse
me, מחוסר כפרה... michusar kapparah...
מחוסר כפרה michusar kapparah is אסור assur in מחנה לויה. machaneh leviyah.
Okay, that we know from טמא יהיה, tamei yiheyeh, okay? and certain...
okay, and a טבול יום tevul yom and a טבול יום. tevul
yom. They're אסור assur in מחנה... machaneh... that's... that we know. That
we took for granted. The whole question is a טבול יום tevul
yom of a זב zav like a זב zav was about מחנה
לויה, machaneh leviyah, right? Anybody if you're not let me just make
it simple, if you're not a hundred percent טהור, tahor, you're not
allowed in מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. Even if you're the weakest טומאה
tumah left, טבול יום, tevul yom, מחוסר כפרה, michusar kapparah, you just
have to wait for nightfall, whatever the weakest טומאה, tumah, unless you're
a hundred percent טהור tahor you're not allowed in מחנה שכינה. machaneh
shechina. That's fine. Our only question was מחנה לויה. machaneh leviyah. A
טבול יום Tevul Yom of a זב Zav allowed in מחנה לוייה?
Machaneh Leviyah? זב Zav is not. How about a טבול יום Tevul
Yom of a זב? Zav? Right, that was our question. So now,
where we're learning this out is the פסוקים Psukim that say you
have to wait till day eight. That's just talking about bringing your
קרבן. Korban. They're not emphasizing where you can enter as we already
pointed out by the case of the נזיר. Nazir. But nevertheless, when
it says by the זב, Zav, it says on day eight, it
says, what's it say, ובא אל הכהן, u'va el hakohen, ובא אל
הכהן, u'va el hakohen, what we're saying is that some again it's
a little circular but what we're saying is that that is telling
us that on day eight he's entering into that space, okay? Or
it's somewhat telling us now it's not telling us he was אסור
assur beforehand, that's not true, that's not implicit as we pointed out
by נזיר, Nazir, it's not implied that he was אסור assur beforehand,
but what it is telling us is that on day eight he's
entering into the space that he wasn't entering in earlier than that.
So here you've got your זב, Zav, okay? And it is telling
you that on day eight he's standing in מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah.
Now you cannot infer from that that he was אסור assur beforehand.
That we've already said. But here's what you can infer. Since we
are saying it's circular because we're, but since we're saying that when
the פסוק Pasuk says אל פתח אהל מועד el petach Ohel Moed
it means מחנה לוייה, Machaneh Leviyah, then we're going to say one
minute, why is it describing מחנה לוייה Machaneh Leviyah as פתח אהל
מועד? petach Ohel Moed? Right? This isn't פתח אהל מועד. petach Ohel
Moed. This is פתח אהל מועד. petach Ohel Moed. Why is it
describing it this way? That you should learn out that the same
way a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim is אסור assur in מחנה שכינה,
Machaneh Shechinah, which is פתח אהל מועד, petach Ohel Moed, the זב
Zav also as a earlier as a טבול יום Tevul Yom is
also אסור assur in מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah. So we learn it
out by saying the
words פתח אהל מועד petach Ohel Moed don't mean פתח אהל מועד,
petach Ohel Moed, they mean מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah. And then what
we learn out from there is his status is similar to the
issue of going in. The same way he couldn't go in as
a as a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim as a טבול יום, Tevul
Yom, he could not go in to מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah. But
again here's the trick. Here's the difference, okay? It's complicated. Because
as a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim he can go in to מחנה
לוייה, Machaneh Leviyah, okay? How do I know that? Because what happens,
one minute, not in מחנה לוייה, Machaneh Leviyah, should just put it
oh not in
מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah, okay? This is שכינה, Shechinah, this is מחנה
שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah, מחנה מקדש. Machaneh Mikdash. I thought it was מקדש.
Mikdash. מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah, right, מקדש.
Mikdash. Okay. How do I know מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim can go
into מחנה לוייה? Machaneh Leviyah? Because that's what everybody does who have
to bring their קרבן Korban on the day eight. They're מחוסר כפורים,
mechusar kippurim, they go into מחנה Machaneh they go right up to
the door, right, which
is מחנה לוייה, Machaneh Leviyah, right up to מחנה שכינה. Machaneh Shechinah.
He goes right up to the front door, he hands over his
קרבן. Korban. So of course מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim is allowed in
מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah. So what אביי Abaye is saying that a
מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim is not allowed in מחנה לוייה, Machaneh Leviyah,
he means a טבול יום Tevul Yom that has to bring his
קרבן Korban the next day, okay? So as so a מחוסר כפורים
mechusar kippurim himself cannot go here, okay? Since it describes the זב
Zav as if he were here, we're learning out that there's a
similar restriction here, but not to apply to a מחוסר כפורים mechusar
kippurim because that obviously you can go on day eight you go
and you bring your קרבן, Korban, to apply to a מחוסר mechusar
to apply to a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, not a normal טבול
יום, Tevul Yom, but a טבול יום Tevul Yom who then also
has to bring a קרבן Korban the next day. All right, very
complicated. Bottom line is is that according to אביי, Abaye, the conclusion
is that a normal טבול יום Tevul Yom of a זב Zav
is not like a זב. Zav. And which would have important relevance
for going up to הר הבית Har HaBayit nowadays as a טבול
יום Tevul Yom of a בעל קרי. baal keri. But I should
say that the conclusion of this גמרא Gemara I pointed out to
you that I stuck in the word לאו, lav, right? Our גירסא
girsa says טבול יום של זב כזב דמי. Tevul Yom shel Zav
ke'Zav dami. So and that whole long explanation I just gave, if
you're left a little confused, is because it was not so straight,
I mean I hope I did the best job I could explaining
it, but the logic itself was not so straightforward. So there is
a question what actually the מסקנא maskana is. There is a question
how we פוסק posek about טבול יום של זב Tevul Yom shel
Zav and of a בעל קרי. baal keri. So even though the
way that we just read it that if you're not מחוסר כפורים,
mechusar kippurim, if you don't have to bring a קרבן, Korban, you're
not כזב ke'Zav and you're not like a בעל קרי, baal keri,
and that would solve the whole מקום המקדש Makom HaMikdash the whole
הר הבית Har HaBayit issue, that's not necessarily the way that we
פוסק. posek. Okay. So now, question, yes? So just so I understand,
we're in the משכן Mishkan it is, so מחנה לוייה Machaneh Leviyah
in the משכן Mishkan started after the קלעים, klaim, right? Yeah.
And everything there and then same פתח אהל מועד petach Ohel Moed
is not the קלעים klaim because that would be פתח החצר. petach
hachatzer. Right. And then it'd be somewhere there, we just don't know.
Yeah. Okay, exactly. So if this is not clear, how could anybody
go up to the... Oh because you have to look at what
the ראשונים Rishonim say and how we פוסק.
posek.
And either they tell people like I don't know, maybe they're assuming
that the I think that they
don't I think that they're assuming that we פוסק posek that מחוסר
mechusar that טבול יום Tevul Yom is not of a זב Zav
is not like a זב. Zav. But there are other סוגיות sugyot
that discuss the same issue and I think they're just assuming that
or hoping that that's not the case. Yeah. One piece this piece
is missing for me, so someone is a זב Zav and is
not a טבול יום Tevul Yom anymore,
is מחוסר כפרה mechusar kaparah he can't. Where did he bring the
animal? So that's what we, I think you, I think you had
just stepped out for that, so you'll get your notes from somebody,
one of the other students.
Okay. No, but what he basically, what we said is that a
normal מחוסר כפרה mechusar kaparah of course can go in מחנה לוייה
machaneh leviyah because you go up to the door of אוהל מועד
ohel moed and you give over your קרבן. korban. Like here, you
go through עזרת נשים. ezras nashim. You have to bring your קרבן.
korban. So you're מחוסר כיפורים. mechusar kipurim. So so you bring your
קרבן. korban. You're allowed in מחנה לוייה, machaneh leviyah, but you're not
allowed in מחנה שכינה. machaneh shechinah. Okay. So a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar
kipurim and a טבול יום t'vul yom are not allowed here. But
of course a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kipurim is allowed here. So when
אביי Abaye says this זב zav that is not allowed in מחנה
לוייה machaneh leviyah is a מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kipurim, he doesn't mean
a סתם stam מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kipurim on day eight. Because of
course that זב zav is allowed. What he means is a טבול
יום t'vul yom who's also a מחוסר כיפורים. mechusar kipurim. A זב
zav who's a טבול יום t'vul yom and that's not just a
טבול יום. t'vul yom. You have to wait for nightfall and a
קרבן. korban. That you're not allowed in מחנה לוייה. machaneh leviyah. A
normal טבול יום t'vul yom is, a normal מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kipurim
is. But a טבול יום t'vul yom who has two steps to
go through, nightfall and a קרבן, korban, that's the guy who's not
allowed here. You can say it's on our גירסא. girsa. What? Well,
depends how exactly how you read it. Yeah. Okay. So now that
we will now move on. Okay. Or not. Yeah. Yes. What would
be the surrogate for the קרבן korban and what would one have
to bring? There wouldn't. But conceptually we don't assume that anybody is
a זב zav of three ראיות. reiyos. Okay. The question would be,
okay, and if somebody would be and you wouldn't need to, you
just wouldn't need to not be a טבול יום. t'vul yom. You
couldn't go into מקום—oh, makom you couldn't go into—yeah, you couldn't go
into מקום המקדש, makom hamikdash, but you go on הר הבית. Har
HaBayis. Like a woman who's a יולדת yoledes needs to bring a
קרבן. korban. Okay. But even if she goes to the מקוה mikvah
and doesn't bring a קרבן, korban, she's fine. She's a מחוסר כפרה.
mechusar kaparah. She's not allowed in מקום המקדש, makom hamikdash, but she's
still allowed in מחנה לוייה. machaneh leviyah. The same way if we're
all טמאי מת, temei meis, we're not allowed in מקום המקדש makom
hamikdash and we're allowed in מחנה לוייה. machaneh leviyah. The idea of
going to הר הבית Har HaBayis is going on הר הבית, Har
HaBayis, מחנה לוייה, machaneh leviyah, without going into מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash.
Okay. So let's take a look now at the next משנה. mishnah.
Okay. Now it's a lot easier. תגלחת הטהרה כיצד. Tiglachas hataharah keitzad.
Now it's purely just the steps you go through through the ritual.
What is the ritual of the shaving for at the end of
the—at the end of the 30 days of נזירות, nezirus, at the
end of the whole process? היה מביא ג' בהמות. Haya meivi shalosh
behemot. Three animals. חטאת, עולה, ושלמים. chatas, olah, ushlamim. Okay. And the
תורה Torah says ושחט את השלמים ומגלח עליהם. v'shachat es hashlamim umegalei'ach
aleihem. Now when the תורה Torah says you bring the animal, it
says—it says you bring the חטאת, chatas, bring the עולה, olah, you
bring the שלמים, shlamim, and then it says וגילח את כל שערו.
v'gilach es kol se'aro. Okay. And he shaves. And then it says
he also takes the hair and he puts it under the pot
that's cooking עם השלמים. im hashlamim. Okay. So the משנה mishnah says
what—which one are you מגלח עליו? megalei'ach alav? Like conceptually connect the—which
of the קרבנות korbanos are you shaving on? Somehow conceptually connect the
act of shaving to the bringing of a קרבן. korban. That's not
clear in the פסוקים. p'sukim. The פסוקים p'sukim don't say you bring
this קרבן, korban, you bring this קרבן, korban, you bring this קרבן,
korban, and then it says and then you shave. Okay. What it
does say is you use the hair to cook underneath the פחת.
pachat. It doesn't somehow connect the act of shaving with the ritual
of bringing the קרבן. korban. He already brought a קרבן. korban. Well,
yeah, and has it like sequential after the קרבן, korban, then you
shave. But conceptually the משנה mishnah links it. So it says you
שחט את השלמים shachat es hashlamim and then the shaving somehow takes
place together with that. Okay. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. עליהם
Aleihem is on all the קרבנות. korbanos. Well, that's a good point.
Only on שלמים. shlamim. Yeah, that's a good point. That's a good
point. So, okay. We're going in the end to interpret that he
specifically connects it to the שלמים, shlamim, but you're right, the grammar
here might suggest all of them. Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר לא היה
מגלח אלא על החטאת, Rabbi Eliezer omer lo haya megalei'ach ela al
hachatas, שהחטאת קודמת בכל מקום. shehachatas kodemes bechol makom. No, whenever you
have a list of קרבנות korbanos to bring, you always bring the
חטאת chatas first. And therefore you do it with the חטאת. chatas.
Now who says just because it comes first, who says you shave
with it? Right? I mean, then the פסוקים p'sukim say, yeah, say
you bring the חטאת chatas first, but how you shave with the
שלמים shlamim last. And if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos,
תוספות Tosafos says—and תוספות Tosafos reads עליהם, aleihem, I think שלמים shlamim
is plural, right? Exactly. You can't say שלמים shlamim in the singular,
עליה. aleha. Right? Your שלמים shlamim is לשון רבים. lashon rabbim. It's
like pants. Right? עליהם. Aleihem. So so it's only one. Yeah. So
so תוספות Tosafos interestingly assumes that according to the opinion that you're
shaving on the שלמים, shlamim, that you're also bringing the שלמים shlamim
first. That the—that the first opinion assumes the same logic as רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that if you're shaving with it, you bring it
first. But there's nothing—he begins. Yeah. There's nothing in the משנה mishnah
that indicates that. Anyway, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says if you bring
the חטאת chatas first, you shave with it. ואם גילח על אחת
משלושתן יצא. Veim gilach al achas mishloshtan yatza. But of course that's
just לכתחילה. lechatchila. בדיעבד Bediavad whichever one you shaved with, you're יוצא,
yotzei, whichever order you did it in. רבן גמליאל אומר הביא ג'
בהמות ולא פירש. Rabban Gamliel omer heivi shalosh behemot velo peireish. He
brought three בהמות. behemos. He said, I'm sanctifying these animals for my
קרבנות. korbanos. He didn't say which animal is which. So הראויה לחטאת
תקרב חטאת. hara'uya lachatas tikrav chatas. We quoted this a while ago,
you might remember. הראויה לחטאת תקרב חטאת, לעולה תקרב עולה, ולשלמים תקרב
שלמים. Hara'uya lachatas tikrav chatas, le'olah tikrav olah, ulishlamim tikrav shlamim. So
the קדושה kedusha sort of just winds up defining itself. For all
different. If you look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says this one
line תוספות Tosafos at the bottom הראויה לחטאת. hara'uya lachatas. הראוי לחטאת
כשבה, לעולה כבש, לשלמים איל. Harui l'chatas kisbah, l'olah keves, l'shlamim ayil.
So if you bring three different animals and you say these are
all my קרבנות korbanos for נזיר, nazir, it will sort itself out
which is קדוש kadosh for which. Fine. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: וגילח הנזיר פתח אהל מועד.
V'gilach hanazir pesach ohel moed. בשלמים הכתוב מדבר. Bishlamim hakatuv medaber. שנאמר:
Shene'emar: ושחטו פתח אהל מועד. V'shachato petach ohel moed. Oh well, there
actually it is singular but that might be because it's זבח השלמים
zevach hashlumim so maybe I don't know it's a good question. Anyway,
okay, so anyway right before it says you שחט shacht the שלמים
shlamim and then the פסוק pasuk after the שלמים shlamim is the
shaving, so there the פסוקים psukim it juxtaposes the שלמים shlamim with
the shaving. אתה אומר בשלמים הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא פתח אהל
מועד ממש. Atah omer bishlamim hakatuv medaber o eino ela pesach ohel
moed mamash. Now one minute, maybe when it says ושחטו פתח אהל
מועד, V'shachato petach ohel moed, okay, and then it says וגילח הנזיר,
V'gilach hanazir, excuse me, I misread it. It is not the juxtaposition
of ושחטו V'shachato with וגילח V'gilach which is also true. It is
the linking of the words פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel moed. Okay,
by the נזיר nazir it says וגילח פתח אהל מועד V'gilach petach
ohel moed and by the שלמים shlamim it says ושחטו V'shachato because
this is not the שלמים shlamim of the נזיר. nazir. ושחטו פתח
אהל מועד V'shachato petach ohel moed is just the way in the
beginning of ויקרא Vayikra the פסוק pasuk about the שלמים. shlamim. So
I'm sorry, I misread it. What it's actually saying is that since
the shaving of the נזיר nazir is described as פתח אהל מועד
petach ohel moed and the שלמים shlamim when they're brought is described
as being brought פתח אהל מועד, petach ohel moed, it is telling
you that the shaving of the נזיר nazir is an act connected
with the ritual of the bringing of the שלמים shlamim which has
this אהל מועד ohel moed concept. Okay. By the way, להלכה le'halacha
there's הלכה halacha we learn there from the שלמים shlamim it says
פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed that if the אהל מועד ohel
moed doors are locked, okay, that the שלמים shlamim and even if
it's after daybreak then you שחט shacht the שלמים shlamim it's פסול
pasul because it says פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel moed. So there's
actually a conceptual emphasis of the שלמים shlamim as being פתח אהל
מועד petach ohel moed that we find more than the other קרבנות.
korbanos. So if it describes... yes and we might learn the קרבנות
korbanos from שלמים shlamim but conceptually there's a link of פתח אהל
מועד petach ohel moed with שלמים. shlamim. So if it describes the
shaving of the נזיר nazir פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed we're
saying that is a way of describing that it takes place with
the שלמים. shlamim. Okay. אתה אומר בשלמים הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא
פתח אהל מועד ממש. Atah omer bishlamim hakatuv medaber o eino ela
petach ohel moed mamash. Who says maybe all the פסוק pasuk means
to say is you actually do the shaving פתח אהל מועד petach
ohel moed okay which now we've seen פתח אהל מועד petach ohel
moed literally would be ממש mamash like in מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash.
Right? It wouldn't be over here. Right? It would actually be over
here, which actually would be funny because the נזיר nazir wouldn't be
allowed, he'd be מחוסר כיפורים, mechussar kippurim, he wouldn't even be allowed
there. Okay but anyway, which the גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss. I mean
ironically, because we just discussed that a נזיר nazir and מחוסר כיפורים
mechussar kippurim isn't allowed there. But anyway, oh well I guess he
might not be מחוסר כיפורים mechussar kippurim because oh wait wait he
could have brought his earlier קרבן korban and just not brought the
שלמים. shlamim. That would be the case. He would bring one קרבן
korban which would be enough to... oh wait wait he's a נזיר
טהור, nazir tahor, excuse me he's not a נזיר טמא. nazir tamei.
He's not מחוסר כיפורים. mechussar kippurim. He's totally טהור. tahor. So he
actually would be allowed in מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. It's a נזיר
nazir after thirty days. He's allowed in מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. Maybe
it means he goes in the מקום המקדש makom hamikdash and does
the shaving ממש mamash in מקום המקדש makom hamikdash in עזרת ישראל.
Ezras Yisrael. Maybe it literally means פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel moed.
Okay, so just the linking it to the שלמים, shlamim, okay? או
אינו אלא פתח אהל מועד ממש. O eino ela petach ohel moed
mamash. אמרת אם כן דרך בזיון הוא. Amarta: Im kein derech bizayon
hu. No, clearly the פסוק pasuk doesn't literally mean פתח אהל מועד.
petach ohel moed. That's disrespectful to the מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. So
if it says פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed it means together
with the שלמים. shlamim. Where are they actually getting shaved? We're going
to discuss that in the next משנה. Mishna. רבי אושעיא אומר אינו
צריך הרי אמר תורה Rabbi Oshaya omer: Eino tzarich, harei amar Torah
or some take out the word רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya and just
say this is an elaboration of the previous line. לא תעלה במעלות
על מזבחי. Lo sa'aleh b'maalos al mizbechi. קל וחומר דרך בזיון. Kal
v'chomer derech bizayon. If even in the עבודה avoda you have to
have a ramp so that the כהן kohen doesn't step לא תגלה
ערותך עליו lo sigaleh ervascha alav that's seen as not respectful, the
sort of the stepping which I mean you've got a tunic going
down to the floor and even so that little somehow potential exposure
is not respectful, even דרך עבודה derech avoda how much more so
would we not allow shaving to take place on Temple grounds itself
on מקום המקדש makom hamikdash itself. So clearly the פסוקים psukim mean
something else. They don't mean פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed they
mean together with the שלמים. shlamim. Now interestingly in the brackets here
we have, clearly this is not in the original גירסא girsa some
editor put in נוסח אחר במדרש בפרשת נשא. Nusach acher b'Midrash b'Parshas
Naso. וגילח הנזיר רבי אושעיא אומר בשלמים הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא
אם כך אמרה תורה לא תעלה קל וחומר דרך שלא יגלח פתח
אהל מועד אלא בשלמים הכתוב מדבר. V'gilach hanazir, Rabbi Oshaya omer, bishlamim
hakatuv medaber o eino ela im kach amra Torah, lo sa'aleh, kal
v'chomer derech shelo yigaleach petach ohel moed ela bishlamim hakatuv medaber. Okay,
same point it's just a different version of it. דף רמב. Daf
reish mem beis. רבי יצחק אומר אינו צריך הרי הוא אומר ולקח
את שער ראש נזרו ונתן על האש. Rabbi Yitzchak omer: Eino tzarich,
harei hu omer, v'lakach es sear rosh nizro v'nasan al ha'eish. Okay
so you take the hair and you put it on the fire.
מי שאינו מחוסר אלא לקיחה ונתינה. Mi she'eino mechussar ela l'kichah u'nesinah.
All you've got to do is take the hair and put it
on the fire. יצא זה שמחוסר לקיחה הבאה ונתינה. Yatza zeh she'mechussar
l'kichah, hava'ah u'nesinah. If you shaved here you're not cooking your שלמים
shlamim here. You're cooking your שלמים shlamim out here in the עזרת
נשים Ezras Nashim or you're cooking it somewhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So
if you're shaving here you have to shave and then bring it
to where your שלמים shlamim is and the תורה Torah suggests that
you shave and you immediately put it where your שלמים shlamim is
so clearly you're not in the מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. A quick.
Wait, so you're saying you're shaving outside of מקום המקדש? Makom Hamikdash?
Someplace outside? In עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that's where you're
shaving and that's where you're cooking your שלמים. Shlamim. Okay, now למעשה
l'maiseh there actually was, just to not ruin the surprise, a לשכת
נזירים—I Lishkas Nezirim forget which of these corners it was—but one of
these things was the לשכת נזירים Lishkas Nezirim where they did their
shaving and cooking of the שלמים. Shlamim. They actually had a room
in the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim for their shaving and cooking of
the שלמים. Shlamim. Is any part of שלמים Shlamim ever put on
the מזבח? Mizbeach? The אימורים. Emurim. Yeah, so the נזיר Nazir shaves
and gives the אימורים Emurim to the כהן Kohen and he puts
the אימורים Emurim on the מזבח, Mizbeach, right? And the דם, Dam,
and the דם, Dam, right, and then you take the meat. Right.
וגילח הנזיר פתח אהל מועד. V'gilach Hanozir Pesach Ohel Moed. Now it
wasn't done פתח אהל מועד. Pesach Ohel Moed. It tells you because
it's linked to the לשכת שלמים Lishkas Shlamim which is פתח אהל
מועד. Pesach Ohel Moed. Exactly, that's how we're reading it. Okay, let's
just finish up to the next משנה. Mishnah. Okay. מי שאינו מחוסר
כיפורים ונתנזר יצא זה שהוא מחוסר כיפורים ונתנזר. איכא דאמרי רב יצחק
אמר בשלמים הכתוב מדבר. אתם אומרים בשלמים הכתוב מדבר? אינו אלא פתח
אהל מועד ממש. תלמוד לומר ולקח את שער ראש נזרו—מקום שהוא מבשל
שם היה מגלח.
Mi she-eno mechusar kipurim v'nisnizar yatza zeh shehu mechusar kipurim v'nisnizar. Ika
d'amri Rav Yitzchak amar bishlamim hakatuv midaber. Atem omrim bishlamim hakatuv midaber?
Eino ela Pesach Ohel Moed mamash. Talmud lomar velakach es sear rosh
nizro—makom
shehu mevashel sham hayah megaleach.
Basically the same דרשה. drasha. Okay, he takes it immediately, so it's
the same place where he's doing the cooking.
אבא חנן אומר משום רבי אליעזר: Abba Chanan Omer Mishum Rabbi Eliezer:
וגילח הנזיר פתח אהל מועד, V'gilach Hanozir Pesach Ohel Moed, כל זמן
שאין פתח אהל מועד פתוח אינו מגלח. kol zman she-ein Pesach Ohel
Moed pasuach eino megaleach. So similar to the idea that if you
bring a שלמים Shlamim if the doors have not yet been opened
it's פסול, pasul, if you actually did your shaving with the doors—when
the doors weren't open—it would be an invalid shaving. So he at
least says: I don't have to read the words פתח אהל מועד
Pesach Ohel Moed as a complete just metaphor for saying with the
שלמים. Shlamim. Okay, what it means is when the אהל מועד Ohel
Moed is open, wherever you are, even if you're in the עזרת
נשים, Ezras Nashim, if the doors are open, you're פתח אהל מועד.
Pesach Ohel Moed. Okay, but if the doors are closed, you're not
פתח אהל מועד. Pesach Ohel Moed. So it's a little closer to
a literal reading of the פסוק pasuk than purely symbolic. Okay. רבי
שמעון שזורי אומר: Rabbi Shimon Shezuri Omer: וגילח הנזיר פתח אהל מועד,
V'gilach Hanozir Pesach Ohel Moed, ולא נזירה. v'lo nezirah. Okay, now here
we're moving away from the פתח אהל מועד, Pesach Ohel Moed, it's
a totally different דרשה: drasha: נזיר Nazir ולא נזירה. v'lo nezirah. A
woman would not do it in the same environs. Okay, why? שמא
יתגרו בה פרחי כהונה, shema yisgaru bah pirchei kehunah, because there her
hair's uncovered, so the
young כהנים Kohanim are
looking at her and they're having these sexual urges. Now, is he
saying that an actual נזיר Nazir would be in the courtyard? Or
he's saying: no, a נזיר Nazir would be here, would be this
type of פתח אהל מועד, Pesach Ohel Moed, and a נזירה nezirah
would be—would be off somewhere in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? That's what תוספות Tosafos
assumes. Okay, if you look at תוספות Tosafos he says: ולא נזירה—משמע
דטעמא דקרא שמא יתגרו בה פרחי כהונה אם תגולח פתח אהל מועד
ממש, אלא במדינה תגלח במקום צנוע. v'lo nezirah—mashma d'tama d'kra shema yisgaru
bah pirchei kehunah im tigaleach Pesach Ohel Moed mamash, ela bimdinah tigaleach
bemakom tzanua. So presumably the נזיר Nazir is somewhere here where there
are still פרחי כהונה pirchei kehunah running around and a נזירה nezirah
is somewhere off—somewhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay. אמרו לו, amru lo, we're
going to see in the next משנה Mishnah that about shaving outside
of the מקדש Mikedash completely, shaving in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אמרו לו: amru
lo: לדבריך סוטה תוכיח. lidvarecha sotah sochiach. One minute, obviously we allow
כהנים Kohanim to see a woman with her hair uncovered, how about
the case of the סוטה? Sotah? דכתיב והעמידה לפני ה', dechitiv ve-he'emidah
lifnei Hashem, and we're not afraid that שמא יתגרו בה פרחי כהונה.
shema yisgaru bah pirchei kehunah. We're not afraid of that. אמר להן:
amar lahen: זו כוחלת ופוקסת. zu kocheles u-fokeses. No, this נזירה, nezirah,
she's got her makeup on, she looks nice. Okay, so we're afraid
more about their sexual urges. זו אינה כוחלת ופוקסת, zu einah kocheles
u-fokeses, the סוטה Sotah
is being disheveled and, you
know, and being—going through this, you know, this degrading process. It's like
a type of like eyeshadow, whatever. זו כוחלת... zu kocheles... I don't
know, there are different types of makeup. Okay, anyway, it might or
might not be hair. Anyway, so one looks nice and the other
does not and therefore... I don't know what Seinfeld says. Anyway... It
is a black-blue color from the mineral stibnite. פוקסת? fokeses? כוחלת. kocheles.
Okay, anyway, בקיצור, be-kitzur,
so you could read this to say that the נזיר Nazir ממש
mamash does it here because that's where the כהנים Kohanim are and
a
נזירה nezirah does it here, but we've never seen anybody that says
that a נזיר Nazir ממש mamash does it here, so תוספות Tosafos
is reading it that a נזיר Nazir does it here and the
נזירה nezirah does it somewhere off-graph. Okay, we will continue tomorrow and
see the rest of where the shaving can take place in מקום
המקדש Makom Hamikdash or elsewhere.