Good morning. I am Dan Margulis. Today is Wednesday, September, I forgot
the date. Monday. Monday. I said Wednesday? Monday, September 7th. Good. Okay.
Good morning. Now that everybody knows that I'm a little bit out
of it, no, I'm okay. I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer while
he is in Miami on a special trip for the ישיבה; Yeshiva;
so hopefully he's doing a lot of good learning down there and
hopefully we'll have an interesting דף Daf today. We're starting right at
the beginning of the third פרק Perek of מסכת נזיר; Masechet Nazir;
מי שאמר הריני נזיר Mi She'amar Hareini Nazir is on the towards
the top of ט"ז עמוד א'. Tet Zayin Amud Aleph. And this
first set of משניות Mishnayot doesn't get a lot of treatment only
because so much of this was already covered on ה' עמוד ב'
He Amud Bet just about two weeks ago; so check back in
your notes then, but we'll touch on some of those ideas in
just a moment. So the משנה Mishnah says, מי שאמר הריני נזיר
מגלח ליום שלשים ואחד. Mi she'amar hareini nazir megaleiach leyom shloshim ve'echad.
A person who says סתם, stam, סתם נזיר stam nazir is going
to be the day that he shaves or that she brings her
קרבנות korbanot will be the 31st day. That's because the נזירות nezirut
should be for 30 days and then after the day after, the
morning after is only going to be a partial day, so in
order to have 30 days for the נזירות nezirut you would wait
until the 31st day. ואם גילח ליום שלשים יצא. Ve'im gileach leyom
shloshim yatza. But if such a person who had a סתם נזירות
stam nezirut
went
and shaved and brought the קרבנות korbanot on the 30th day, then
בדיעבד bedi'eved you're יוצא. yotzei. And this goes back, if you remember
on ה' עמוד ב', He Amud Bet, תוספות Tosafot raised the possibility
or makes a rather strong suggestion that the מחלוקת machloket between רב
פדא Rav Pada and רב מתנא Rav Matna on ה', He, דף
ה', Daf He, is really only regarding what the rabbinic status is
because even according to
רב מתנא Rav Matna who's the one who says that you have
to wait until the 31st day, again this is the מחלוקת machloket
about whether how much do we say מקצת היום ככולו miktzat hayom
kekulo or not, so תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות אמר לך בר פדא Tosafot
amar lecha Bar Pada on ה' עמוד ב' He Amud Bet makes
the point that the reason why it works בדיעבד bedi'eved is because
on the 30th day יצא שכן דינו דאורייתא דסתם נזיר יגלח ביום
שלשים, yatza shekein dino de'oraita destam nazir yegaleiach beyom shloshim, that at
the דאורייתא De'oraita level the 30th day is okay and then rabbinically
they then extend that further. So the מחלוקת machloket there is really
only about how much would we take this rabbinic נזירות. nezirut. But
so that's a תוספות Tosafot on ה' עמוד ב' He Amud Bet
that frames this discussion. So that explains why the בדיעבד bedi'eved you
would still be יוצא. yotzei. And then the person, another person says,
הריני נזיר שלשים יום. hareini nazir shloshim yom. If a person was
explicit and said I take a 30 day נזירות nezirut explicitly, אם
גילח ליום שלשים לא יצא. im gileach leyom shloshim lo yatza. So
then if such a person would shave and bring their קרבנות korbanot
on the 30th day you're not יוצא yotzei because once you make
explicit that it's 30 days, not that it's the implicit 30 days
based on סתם נזיר שלשים יום, stam nazir shloshim yom, but if
you make it explicit then you need 30 full
days and we couldn't rely on מקצת היום ככולו. miktzat hayom kekulo.
And again this is an issue of taking מקצת היום ככולו miktzat
hayom kekulo at the beginning and at the end for the same
time period because whatever day you became a נזיר, nazir, that day
counts as if it's a full day even if it's just, you
know, two hours or something before שקיעה. shki'ah. And then now we're
trying to say count at the end as well. And this is
the question that's been dealt with, I mean again this is yesterday's
דף Daf and this continues through, the issues of how do you
count מקצת היום ככולו miktzat hayom kekulo and other contexts where that
comes up, questions of אבילות, aveilus, how do you count the first
day of אבילות aveilus and the end of אבילות, aveilus, both of
them are going to be counted as מקצת היום ככולו. miktzat hayom
kekulo. What about נדה? niddah? What about other kinds of things that
take seven days or take a month or a week or different
kinds of examples. Okay.
חודש ימים. Chodesh yamim.
חודש ימים. Chodesh yamim. So the question of
and again the גמרא Gemara earlier, what was it in the first
פרק, Perek, makes the point that the reason why for the 12
months of אבילות aveilus we don't count מקצת היום ככולו miktzat hayom
kekulo for the last day of the 12 months is because years
are not made up of days, years are made up of months
and so you can't say מקצת החודש ככולו miktzat hachodesh kekulo and
count only, you know, ten days into the month or something like
that.
For the year of אבילות aveilus you can't count.
So the year of אבילות aveilus really does end at שקיעה shki'ah
of the last day of אבילות aveilus of that year because the
and it's I mean it's pretty explicit in the גמרא. Gemara.
נפקא מינה Nafkamina like
what does that mean practically?
Practically meaning a person who's in mourning for their parents they don't
go to, you know, parties and things like that.
It gets into a question in אחרונים achronim about how do you
treat that because maybe if there's no positive activity that you're doing,
maybe it's different than avoiding certain things is different than acting out
positively. And that's an interesting question about which context do we count
מקצת היום ככולו miktzas hayom k'kulo or not, those are a lot
of different issues. Okay. מי שנזר שתי נזיריות, mi shenazar shtei neziriyos,
a person who took two consecutive נזיריות, neziriyos, we've seen this a
lot recently, מגלח את הראשונה יום שלושים ואחד, megaleach es harishona yom
sheloshim v'echad, לכתחילה lechatchila
the person should bring their קרבנות korbanos and shave on the 31st
day, ואת השנייה ליום שישים ואחד, v'es hashniya l'yom shishim v'echad, and
the 61st day should count for the second one because the 31st
day will be split between both נזיריות. neziriyos. And that's because you
bring the קרבנות korbanos in the middle of the day, presumably the
beginning will count for this way and the end of the day
will count for the second one, an interesting why you can count
one day for two different periods of time
gets into that question exactly how do you say מקצת היום ככולו?
miktzas hayom k'kulo? Is that something like when we say רובו ככולו
rubo k'kulo for if there's a majority is maybe different than saying
בטל ברוב? batel b'rov? That when you say בטל ברוב batel b'rov
it becomes nullified or becomes canceled out by the majority, but that
doesn't mean that you're sort of ignoring the other half. When you
say רובו ככולו rubo k'kulo you're sort of saying that whatever's the
majority spreads out and fills the entirety of the whole thing. So
this could be different. מקצת היום ככולו miktzas hayom k'kulo could go
in both directions at once,
the beginning of the day for the first נזירות nezirus and the
end of the day for the second נזירות. nezirus. You have a
question?
Wouldn't that be the case where you bring your קרבנות korbanos on
the 30th day? Here it says to bring the קרבנות korbanos on
the 31st day.
So for the 31st day is
because why, because 30 days right and then this day is already
only counts for the second... sorry you're right. So right, this
נזירות nezirus for the way the משנה Mishna says לכתחילה, lechatchila, the
30 days will be here, 30 days will be here and always
the 30 plus first day or the 60 plus first day is
going to be then the day of קרבנות korbanos but not necessarily
counting for the נזירות, nezirus, you're right. Sorry.
ואם גילח את הראשונה יום שלושים מגלח את השנייה יום שישים, v'im
gilach es harishona yom sheloshim megaleach es hashniya yom shishim, that's a
בדיעבד bedieved case which is what I already said, which is that
the 30th day then is going to count for both the first
part and second part and again even then again בדיעבד bedieved if
you would have shaved on the 59th day will also end up
being okay because that will... and again that was all those calculations
back in the first פרק. perek. Okay. מגלח את הראשונה יום שלושים
מגלח את השנייה יום שישים ואחד ואם גילח יום שישים חסר אחד
יצא. megaleach es harishona yom sheloshim megaleach es hashniya yom shishim v'echad
v'im gilach yom shishim chasar echad yatza. If you shave on the
60 minus one day, then you are יצא. yatza. And often we
see this in משניות, mishnayos, the listing up numbers, round number minus
one. We have ארבעים חסר אחת arbaim chasar achas comes up in
I think only two contexts. Number one is the מלאכות melachos on
שבת Shabbos are 40 minus one, and the number of מכות makkos
that a person gets is 40 minus one for doing various עבירות.
aveiros. It's interesting because the תורה Torah says explicitly ארבעים יכנו לא
יוסיף arbaim yakenu lo yosif and the גמרא Gemara learns out from
that תורה שבעל פה Torah she'beal peh that ארבעים arbaim is meant
to be sort of say the extreme maximum and therefore we can
never give anybody really 40 lashes.
And ארבעים חסר אחת arbaim chasar achas for שבת Shabbos is also
interesting, how is it that the מלאכות melachos of שבת Shabbos are
sort of again what does it mean for something to be 40
minus one? 40 often is a nice round number, lots of things
are a complete unit are 40. So to say 40 minus one
is kind of like inching back off of a complete total. You
know, a מקווה mikvah has 40 סאה seah of water, משה רבינו
Moshe Rabbeinu spent 40 days on הר סיני Har Sinai at least
three times, at least twice maybe three times,
40 years in the desert, things like that. So 40 is kind
of a transitional period or a complete chunk, so then 40 minus
one is sort of saying something else is missing in this calculus.
And again the תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים Amoraim discuss about הלכות שבת
hilchos Shabbos how many מלאכות melachos are there, maybe there are a
few others who got left off the list, so there's some מחלוקת
machlokes about that as well. Okay.
וזו עדות v'zu eidus okay וזו עדות העיד רבי פפייס. v'zu eidus
he'id Rabbi Papyas. So רבי פפייס Rabbi Papyas gave this certain testimony,
this reminds us of מסכת עדיות Masechet Eduyos which is full of
just people coming to the בית דין Beis Din and sharing their
recollection of how the בית דין Beis Din used to פסקן pasken
on these issues back in the olden days and a lot of
הלכות halachos that were forgotten were reintroduced even by asking sort of
people on the street and things like that. Here it's רבי פפייס
Rabbi Papyas but he's one of the תנאים, Tannaim, but it's still
interesting to note that לשון. lashon. So זו עדות העיד רבי פפייס
על מי שנזר שתי נזיריות שאם גילח את הראשונה יום שלושים מגלח
את השנייה ליום שישים. zu eidus he'id Rabbi Papyas al mi shenazar
shtei neziriyos she'im gilach es harishona yom sheloshim megaleach es hashniya l'yom
shishim. If a person shaved on the 30th day, then for the
second נזירות nezirus they would shave on the 60th day. In other
words, still counting 30 days לכתחילה lechatchila for the second one, but
it would be בדיעבד bedieved for the first נזירות. nezirus. ואם גילח
יום שישים חסר אחד יצא v'im gilach yom shishim chasar echad yatza
and exactly. The הלכה halacha from our משנה Mishna Rabbi Papyas is
quoting from an earlier tradition שיום של שלושים עולה לו מן המניין
sheyom shel shloshim oleh lo min haminyan because the 30th day counts
for it, meaning counting for, in this case, both count.
מי שאמר הריני נזיר, mi she'amar hareni nazir, so now what if
a person says I am a נזיר? nazir? נטמא יום שלושים nitma
yom shloshim and he becomes טמא, tamei, in this case טמא מת,
tamei meis, on the 30th day. סותר את הכל, soter es hakol,
it destroys the entire נזירות nezirus and he has to not only
become טהור tahor which is a seven day process, but then he
needs to count a thirty day נזירות nezirus after that in order
to fulfill the נדר. neder. רבי אליעזר אומר אינו סותר אלא שבעה.
Rabbi Eliezer omer eino soter ela shiva.
Now when Rabbi Eliezer says סותר, soter, it doesn't actually even mean
סותר soter at all, what he's saying is you only miss seven
days of the process of טהרה, tahara, but after those seven days
of טהרה tahara for טומאת מת tumas meis you can go immediately
and bring the קרבנות korbanos for your נזירות. nezirus. So then in
other words the fact that he used the word סותר soter is
actually misleading to a certain extent because it doesn't cancel anything, it
doesn't miss out anything for his נדר neder yet.
And in those seven days are you still acting like a נזיר?
nazir?
Well he wouldn't be able to drink wine or shave because he's
still a נזיר nazir or she's still a נזירה nezira from before
and again those prohibitions don't really lift until you bring the קרבנות.
korbanos. But interesting again once someone who is טמא מת, tamei meis,
it's interesting to question is there a prohibition on becoming further again
טמא מת tamei meis in this context? Obviously however if you then
come in contact with right, well whether you would have to count
the seven days again, it's interesting question for כהנים kohanim as well.
I think it was yeah I think it's a מחלוקת machlokes between
the רמב"ם Rambam and the ראב"ד. Ra'avad. It's a relatively well known
ראב"ד. Ra'avad. The ראב"ד Ra'avad basically tries to get rid of the
prohibition on כהנים kohanim becoming טמא למת tamei lemeis nowadays because he
basically says everybody is already טמא מת tamei meis and he introduces
some other ספק safek and it's been much talked about.
It's
because
the ראב"ד Ra'avad doesn't think there's that there's a prohibition the מצוות
לא תעשה mitzvas lo sa'aseh to become טמא tamei wouldn't apply to
someone who is already טמא. tamei. According to the רמב"ם Rambam it
does, it's a prohibition.
Does it make a difference whether it's טמא ספק tamei safek versus
טמא וודאי? tamei vadai?
So I don't remember either exactly, I didn't look inside recently,
but I'll take a look. It's in I think it's in הלכות
אבל, Hilchos Aveil, no it's not הלכות אבל, Hilchos Aveil, now I'm
not remembering, I'll have to go back. הלכות אבל Hilchos Aveil is
where the רמב"ם Rambam talks about the טומאה tuma of כהנים kohanim
so I'll have to take a look there.
It's relatively well known ראב"ד Ra'avad because it gets talked about a
lot but it's not brought להלכה lehalacha because it's obviously a very
radical opinion. Okay. נזיר שהיה סותר את הכל. nazir shehaya soter es
hakol. רבי אליעזר אומר אינו סותר אלא שבעה. Rabbi Eliezer omer eino
soter ela shiva. הריני נזיר שלושים יום, hareni nazir shloshim yom, what
if a person says explicitly I will be נזיר nazir for thirty
days? נטמא יום שלושים סותר את הכל, nitma yom shloshim soter es
hakol, the תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma opinion is identical because in this
case there's no difference just that the 30th day doesn't count, he
has to restart the נזירות nezirus again.
And to that Rabbi Eliezer would agree because Rabbi Eliezer is only
allowing this does not cancel on the 30th day problem because it
was implicit, but if you're explicit then even Rabbi Eliezer would agree
that the 30th day becoming טמא tamei on the 30th day would
be סותר soter the נזירות nezirus and he would say you have
to restart for another thirty days and the גמרא Gemara is going
to explain that. Says the משנה, Mishna, the last part of the
משנה. Mishna. הריני נזיר מאה יום, hareni nazir me'ah yom, what if
a person takes a longer נזירות nezirus for 100 days?
נטמא יום מאה סותר את הכל, nitma yom me'ah soter es hakol,
cancels everything. תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma opinion is consistent. רבי אליעזר אומר
אינו סותר אלא שלושים. Rabbi Eliezer omer eino soter ela shloshim. But
Rabbi Eliezer says now again this is interesting because it seems to
contradict Rabbi Eliezer's opinion. Again it's the last day of the נזירות,
nezirus, so why should a 100 day נזירות nezirus be different than
the 30 day נזירות nezirus where Rabbi Eliezer seems to
allow the טומאה tuma to not cancel the נזירות nezirus on the
last day? It seems like there's a difference between an explicit and
implicit נזירות, nezirus, so anyone who takes a 100 day נזירות nezirus
obviously has to be explicit and Rabbi Eliezer we saw already agreed
that for thirty days נזירות nezirus that was explicit then if you're
explicit then even the 30th day you don't escape the סתירה stira
of the טומאה. tuma. So Rabbi Eliezer here agrees, but he differs
in that he says you only need thirty days because again this
is what we saw in the first פרק, perek, the question of
growing your hair, the fact that a נזיר nazir needs thirty days
of hair growth and thirty days of a נזירות nezirus in a
block, so once the נזיר nazir becomes טמא tamei and has to
shave and has to bring the קרבנות טומאה, korbanos tuma, then to
restart the נזירות nezirus and make up that time he still needs
a full thirty days to do that. Different from Rabbi Eliezer's opinion
earlier where it seemed like seven days just to deal with the
טומאה tuma but actually no problem and that was because it was
implicit, really you're basically finished on the 29th day and then the
30th day was just kind of additional time. Okay. אינו סותר אלא
שלושים. eino soter ela shloshim. נטמא יום מאה ואחד, nitma yom me'ah
ve'echad, what if a person becomes טמא tamei on the 101st day?
That's the day that the person was planning to bring the קרבנות
korbanos and shave
לכתחילה, lechatchila, perfectly good day to do that and the נזירות nezirus
itself... totally finished, so שלושים shloshim and the תנא קמא Tana Kamma
says, agrees to רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's opinion that in that case
it's already after the full period of נזירות, nezirut, then it would
only cancel 30 days for 30 days of hair growth. שלושים יום.
shloshim yom. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר omer אינו סותר אלא שבע.
eino soter ela shiva. And in that context רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
will go back to his opinion where you say אינו סותר אלא
שבע eino soter ela shiva that you would require in order to
become טהור tahor but not actually cancel the נזירות. nezirut. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara picks up on this and the גמרא Gemara says
מי שאמר הריני נזיר ונטמא יום שלושים סותר את הכל. mi she-amar
ha-reni nazir ve-nitma yom shloshim soter et ha-kol. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
אומר omer אינו סותר אלא שבע. eino soter ela shiva. So that's
just a quote from our
משנה. Mishnah. קסבר רבי אלעזר kasavar Rabbi Elazar כל אחד כל אחר
מלאת שבע סותר. kol echad kol achar milot shiva soter. So anything
that happens after the day of מלאת, milot, the day that the
נזירות nezirut is fulfilled, the filled-up day or whatever, the last day
of the נזירות, nezirut, anything after that will only cancel seven days
which is the seven days to become טהור tahor but does not
cancel the נזירות nezirut itself. And this is an interesting point, which
is that taking a נזירות nezirut was the נדר neder for a
specific block of time, which if you become טמא tamei during that
period will actually destroy your ability to have kept the נדר neder
during that time period. Afterwards, there's still the הלכות halachot of being
a נזיר nazir until you get out of it, but it's not
part of the initial נדר neder to be a נזיר. nazir. So
the fact of becoming טמא tamei during that period is prohibited and
you have certain things to do to rectify that, but it does
not cancel or nullify your ability to have kept the נדר נזיר
neder nazir from the beginning. You already had the 30 days. You
already had 100 days. So רבי אליעזר'ס שיטה Rabbi Eliezer's shitta is
anything that's after יום מלאת yom milot then it's שבע סותר, shiva
soter, it only cancels the seven days that you need in order
to become טהור tahor and then to bring your קרבנות korbanot after
that. A person says הריני נזיר שלושים יום hareni nazir shloshim yom
ונטמא יום שלושים סותר את הכל. ve-nitma yom shloshim soter et ha-kol.
So what about the opinion that says if a person says I'll
be a נזיר nazir for 30 days and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
agreed? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agreed to the תנא קמא Tana Kamma
that for a 30-day נזירות nezirut it would cancel the נזירות nezirut
on the 30th day, right? ונטמא יום שלושים סותר את הכל. ve-nitma
yom shloshim soter et ha-kol. לא פליג רבי אלעזר lo palig Rabbi
Elazar דאמר שלמים. de-amar shlemim. Ah, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
no, the case in the משנה Mishnah must have been a case
where a person said explicitly, not just 30 days or perhaps implicit
in the qualification of saying 30 days explicitly is that the person
meant שלושים שלמים, shloshim shlemim, 30 full days, different than his opinion
about 100 days because 100 days there's no question that all you
meant was to make it into a 100-day נזירות. nezirut. But saying
30 days explicitly adds onto what was an implicit נדר נזיר neder
nazir of 30 days נזירות סתם. nezirut stam. So saying 30 explicitly
makes it into something additional, so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer reads that
as דאמר שלמים. de-amar shlemim. Either implicitly or perhaps even explicitly. He
says the משנה Mishnah must have been talking about a case where
he says שלמים. shlemim. Now, what about a case הריני נזיר מאה
יום ונטמא יום מאה סותר את הכל? hareni nazir me-ah yom ve-nitma
yom me-ah soter et ha-kol? The תנא קמא Tana Kamma says סותר
את הכל. soter et ha-kol. רבי אליעזר אומר אינו סותר אלא שלושים.
Rabbi Eliezer omer eino soter ela shloshim. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says it actually cancels 30 days. So that's different because didn't he
say כל שאחר מלאת סותר שבע, kol she-achar milot soter shiva, it
cancels only seven days, and here he's saying it cancels 30 days?
So it sounds like רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's opinions in our משנה
Mishnah seem to contradict. So says back, says the גמרא, Gemara, כולה
כדאבינן בה אליבא דבר פדא ורב מתנא. kulah ke-dahavinan bah aliba de-Bar
Pada ve-Rav Matna. So
this whole מחלוקת machloket is going back to the מחלוקת machloket we
had on ה עמוד ב hei amud bet about between בר פדא
Bar Pada and רב מתנא Rav Matna about how do you count
again, whether it's a long נזירות, nezirut, whether it's a short נזירות,
nezirut, how do we count מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat ha-yom ke-kulo, how
do we count
those cases? We'll take a look there, so if you go to
ה עמוד ב, hei amud bet, just to refresh our memory a
little bit from what last Tuesday. Middle of the דף daf on
ה עמוד ב. hei amud bet. Yeah. Right,
תנא מי שאמר הריני נזיר מגלח יום שלושים. tana mi she-amar ha-reni
nazir megaleach yom shloshim. So it's our משנה Mishnah exactly. The משנה
Mishnah is quoted: מי שאמר הריני נזיר hareini nazir, מגלח יום... sorry,
יום שלושים ואחד. yom shloshim ve-echad. A person who says סתם stam
I'll be a נזיר nazir should shave on... sorry, יום שלושים ואחד.
And should shave on the 31st day. בשלמא לרב מתנא. bishlama le-Rav
Matna. So that's fine for רב מתנא Rav Matna who says 30
days. ניחא אלא לבר פדא קשיא. nicha ela le-Bar Pada kashya. It
seems to be קשיא kashya against בר פדא Bar Pada because בר
פדא Bar Pada said 29 days was okay, so why do you
have to then wait until the 31st day? אמר לך בר פדא
אימא סיפא אם גילח יום שלושים יצא. amar lach Bar Pada eima
seifa im gileach yom shloshim yatza. So בדיעבד be-diavad then you're still
okay if you shave on the 30th day because בר פדא Bar
Pada is saying 29 days is the bare minimum and the 30th
day is just something additional. אלא סיפא מסייעא ליה. ela seifa mesayeia
leh. And the סיפא seifa of that... of this משנה Mishnah supports
בר פדא'ס Bar Pada's position. רישא נעשית כאומר שלמים. reisha na'asit ke-omer
shlemim. So the רישא... reisha... Yeah, from ה עמוד ב. hei amud
bet. Just because that's the מחלוקת machloket that comes up here. So
that the... it's our משנה Mishnah is all the discussion about our
משנה Mishnah as being on דף ה. daf hei. נעשית כאומר שלמים.
na'asit ke-omer shlemim. So then fine, so once you take בר פדא'ס
Bar Pada's opinion, then you can read the רישא reisha of the
משנה Mishnah as being about שלמים. shlemim. So either way, either of
the אמוראים Amoraim can read the משנה Mishnah to fit their opinion
and they just have to kind of... they each have an אוקימתא
okimta to suggest why the משנה Mishnah seems to be contradictory.
And they had to answer רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar on
30 days because רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is according to בר
מתנא. Bar Matna. is that right? רב
מתנא Rav Matna says thirty days and בר פדא Bar Padda says
twenty-nine days.
בר פדא Bar Padda says that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is a
support for him because בר פדא Bar Padda says it's twenty-nine days
so it's really twenty-nine days so
he should all right so רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is like רב
מתנא Rav Matna because the thirtieth day doesn't count as the מלאת
melos because only partially done so far. It would be have to
wait until the thirty-first day to be אחר מלאת.
achar melot. So how do you deal with the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma then?
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of our משנה Mishnah right because
he says
הריני נזיר
מאה יום
hareini nazir mei'ah
yom
נטמא ביום מאה nitma beyom mei'ah סותר את הכל. soter et hakkol.
So that's not like בר פדא Bar Padda because he says only
twenty-nine days, twenty-nine days should be fine. So then he says no,
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is right, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says you
don't have to סותר soter everything rather you really don't need to.
So therefore the
only really need it to be twenty-nine days. So why does רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar say anything? Because he has this whole thing about
יום מלאת. yom melos.
יום מלאת yom melos and therefore the hundredth day is different because
for a longer נזירות nezirus then you still have to make up
the thirty days of hair
growth. I'm having a little bit of trouble. You're right. It is
a little bit tricky to figure out how רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
is explaining his שיטה shita because why right how can he still
require thirty days after the hundred days? It sounds like the timing
has to be different than when he requires only seven days after
after any of the other נזירות nezirot because hundredth day if he
became טמא tamei on the hundredth day so then it's still hundredth
day not hundred and first day. No thank you, I already had.
Okay, I'm sorry about that we'll have to clarify that a little
bit but it seems for sure רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar שיטה shita
is at least a little bit tricky.
Meaning if it's the יום מלאת yom melos of a normal נזיר
nazir then you can you know סותר soter it but if it's
not then you have a whole גידול שער gidul sa'ar kind of
thing.
Wait
if you go to
if you go to the גמרא Gemara on this? Yeah for sure
exact same discussion.
Yeah for sure רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar points that out. הריני נזיר
מאה יום hareini nazir mei'ah yom נטמא ביום מאה nitma beyom mei'ah
סותר את הכל soter et hakkol רבי אלעזר אומר אין סותר אלא
שלשים. Rabbi Elazar omer ein soter ela shloshim. So I wonder if
it's telling us... yeah I think the רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar שיטה
shita
and again if you look in the מפרש Mefarish it's the last
מפרש Mefarish before the משנה Mishnah or no second to last one
דיבור המתחיל dibbur hamatchil כדאמר ריש לקיש k'da'amar Reish Lakish no sorry
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar so רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar opinion is based
on he has a דרשה drasha that says זאת תורת הנזיר ביום
מלאת Zos Toras HaNazir beyom melos that the even on the יום
מלאת yom melos it you have a potential to be counted as
a real נזיר nazir in other words that if you become טמא
tamei you have to restart for thirty days. And so even for
נזירות מרובה nezirus meruba so רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar שיטה shita is
interesting because he says that for the hundred hundred day נזירות nezirus
when you have to restart it and that's what it is right
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar agrees with the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that
when you're explicit about the length of time thirty days or hundred
days you have to totally restart it is סותר את הכל soter
et hakkol because you meant שלמים sheleimim or you even perhaps said
שלמים. sheleimim. The difference is that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar thinks the
נזירות nezirus that you have to make up is only thirty days
is not the full length of the נדר. neder. That's very interesting
because it sounds like what what did you do? You took a
נדר neder to be a נזיר nazir for hundred days and then
on the hundredth day you become טמא. tamei. That as if totally
nullifies your ability to have kept the נדר neder for the hundred
days so presumably you should have to restart the whole נדר. neder.
That's what תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says. And רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
says no it's sufficient for you I mean again you kept ninety-nine
days straight it's frustrating but what רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says basically
is that you can restart with a new נזירות nezirus that's only
thirty days in order to fulfill the נדר. neder. So at no
point would you ever have kept hundred days being a good נזיר
nazir nonetheless to be a נזיר nazir
for thirty days is enough of a נזירות nezirus to fulfill the
נדר neder in that way. So that's an interesting thing about רבי
אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar שיטה shita and that's because based on his דרשה
drasha of זאת תורת הנזיר ביום מלאת Zos Toras HaNazir beyom melos
that even if you become טמא tamei on the יום מלאת yom
melos you count as a quote נזיר nazir in other words to
have thirty day נזירות. nezirus. Okay the next משנה. Mishnah. The משנה
Mishnah says מי שגזר mi she-gazar מי שנזר mi she-nazar how did
I make that mistake? מי שנזר והוא בבית הקברות mi she-nazar vehu
beveit hakvaros a person who takes a נדר neder to become a
נזיר nazir
a person is in a cemetery. So this is
a very interesting question because a person in a cemetery presumably is
already טמא מת. tamei meis. Again the question is what if just
a person was walking down the street and was already טמא מת
tamei meis does the same הלכה halacha apply or not? I think
it's a מחלוקת machlokes in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Yeah תוספות Tosafos and
the ראש Rosh suggest that such a person even if a person
is just already טמא מת tamei meis and walking down the street
the way the משנה Mishnah is explaining is just sort of a
common example or a way to tell us a case of a
person who is טמא מת tamei meis but not necessarily to exclude
other cases. It seems like other ראשונים Rishonim might require specifically being
in the בית הקברות beit hakvaros perhaps because there the מת meis
itself the אבי אבות הטומאה avi avos hatumah providing the טומאה tumah
טומאת מת tumas meis is already right there you're still as if
in contact with. with the אבי אבות הטומאה avi avos hatumah in
a different way, there with טומאה tumah there are certain examples like
that where being in contact with the אב הטומאה av hatumah changes
your relationship to become טהור tahor in a different way, or perhaps
it even just reveals the fact that the person did not intend
really to become a נזיר nazir now at all because he knows,
you know, you're standing in the cemetery, of course you know a
נזיר nazir can't be טמא. tamei. Or perhaps this is a functional
problem in actually how the נזירות neziros can catch hold, because you
can't initially become a נזיר nazir who's already טמא tamei because it
has to be that if you were a נזיר nazir who then
became טמא. tamei. That's and we're going to see the דרשה drasha
about that. So מי שנזר והוא בבית הקברות mi shenazar vehu beveit
hakevaros אפילו היה שם שלושים יום, afilu haya sham shloshim yom, what
if you stayed in the cemetery for thirty days straight? אין עולין
לו מן המנין ואינו מביא קרבן טומאה. ein olin lo min haminyan
ve'eino meivi korban tumah. It doesn't count for the thirty days of
the נזירות neziros because you were טמא tamei the whole time and
perhaps because the נזירות neziros never really caught hold, and אינו מביא
קרבן טומאה eino meivi korban tumah because in order to be required
to bring a קרבן korban for becoming טמא, tamei, you have to
have been טהור tahor who then became טמא tamei and not to
have been already טמא tamei when the נזירות neziros started. Interesting, it
sounds like, I think it's from תוספות, Tosafos, the suggestion that for
sure, according to תוספות, Tosafos, the prohibitions on drinking wine and cutting
your hair would still apply to such a person. The נזירות neziros
catches hold enough to make those prohibitions, but not to actually start
counting the thirty days, and again I think that is also a
bit of a מחלוקת machlokes about how to understand that. Perhaps it's
totally obvious that the נזירות neziros shouldn't even catch hold at all,
and the question is, well what do you do once you leave
the cemetery? Once you leave, yes, question. Maybe this was to ask,
but there's a נזירות neziros and then there's a נדר neder part.
And so maybe the not drinking wine is just like the נדר
neder part of it? Maybe. So you're saying that sort of the
person can somehow attain the status of a נזיר nazir and not
exactly count for the days, but still have the prohibitions. Because he
took a נדר neder not to do that. Right. Exactly. That that
the obligation to be a נזיר nazir for thirty days can only
kick in once once he's טהור tahor and once he's actually counting
the days, but the prohibitions could still take take effect. It's an
interesting suggestion that makes a lot of sense. Okay. ואינו מביא קרבן
טומאה. ve'eino meivi korban tumah. Okay. יצא ונכנס. yatza venichnas. What about
if the person then left the cemetery and came back in? עולין
לו מן המנין ומביא קרבן טומאה. olin lo min haminyan umeivi korban
tumah. Then the person, the days meaning, a person on the first
day of their נזירות neziros was in the cemetery and said הריני
נזיר, nazir and then walked out of the cemetery and walked back
in, then that sounds like it would be enough to then make
them count עולין לו מן המנין olin lo min haminyan and to
bring a קרבן טומאה korban tumah because he is a נזיר nazir
who became טמא. tamei. Again it sounds kind of fishy, how can
that make sense? Maybe he had to become טהור tahor in between.
Maybe you have to accept the נזירות neziros again in between. And
some of the ראשונים, Rishonim, the מפרש Meforaish here says, a person
has to say explicitly, יצא ונכנס yatza venichnas כגון שהזה ושנה וטבל,
kegon shehiza veshana vetaval, a person got the two הזאות haza'os of
מי חטאת mei chatas from the פרה אדומה parah adumah to become
טהור tahor from טמא מת tamei meis וטבל vetaval and went to
the מקוה mikvah וכמפרש בגמרא uchemforaish begemara ואחר כך נכנס ve'achar kach
nichnas and then he went back into the cemetery. In other words,
he had to become טהור tahor and then went back into the
cemetery. עולין לו מן המנין. olin lo min haminyan. נזירות neziros began
once שהזה ושנה וטבל shehiza veshana vetaval ביום שביעי שלו beyom shevi’i
shelo מביא קרבן על הטומאה. meivi korban al hatumah. So that's because
the person became טהור tahor and then became טמא tamei again. It
doesn't sound explicit from the לשון lashon of the משנה, Mishna, but
it seems the only reasonable way to explain how it could be
because a person has to be טהור tahor in order to become
טמא tamei in order to have to bring the קרבן טומאה. korban
tumah. Okay. So עולין לו מן המנין ומביא קרבן. olin lo min
haminyan umeivi korban. רבי אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Elazar omer, לא בו ביום.
lo bo bayom. It does not count if it was on the
same day, meaning the seventh day of the טהרה tahara process. If
you went back into the cemetery on the seventh day of the
טהרה tahara process, the day when the person has become טהור, tahor,
it does not count שנאמר shenemar והימים הראשונים יפלו. vehayamim harishonim yippolu.
The previous days in plural will fall, meaning they don't count for
the נזירות, neziros, עד שיהיו לו ימים ראשונים. ad sheyihyu lo yamim
rishonim. It must be multiple days. You have to have at least
a day and a half, two, to count as two days before
becoming טמא tamei in order for it then to cancel the נזירות
neziros to become טהור tahor again and to restart the נזירות. neziros.
Otherwise you would never even be able to bring the קרבן טומאה
korban tumah because you never had enough of a start. You fizzled
out before you even got going, and in that case it wouldn't
require you to bring the קרבן טומאה korban tumah because the קרבן
טומאה, korban tumah, the גזירת הכתוב gezeiras hakatuv says והימים הראשונים יפלו.
vehayamim harishonim yippolu. The first days, the previous days will fall, will
not count for him. Meaning he's not a נזיר nazir. at all
now or he's just? No, he for sure is a נזיר. nazir
The question is whether he's required to do the whole טהרה tahara
process for a נזיר טמא nazir tamei or whether he can just
do seven days with פרה אדומה parah adumah to become physically טהור
tahor and then just continue with the נזירות, neziros, whether he has
to shave and bring the קרבנות korbanos for a נזיר טמא nazir
tamei or not. So the קרבן טומאה korban tumah is dependent on
the ability of having been sort of substantially טהור tahor first and
then becoming טמא tamei and not having immediately been טהור tahor and
then going back to become טמא tamei again. never had sort of
to establish almost like feet on the ground. It's not exactly like
a חזקה *chazaka* in other kind of places, but to sort of
to get started with the sense of being טהור tahor, *tahor* and
then to have had that get broken. Okay. Yeah, so it's interesting
also the מחלוקת machlokes *machlokes* between תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* and the רמב"ם
Rambam *Rambam* about the two days, right? רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* says
you need two days, ימים ראשונים *yamim rishonim*, two days, plural days.
So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* sounds like the second day of that could
be מקצת היום ככולו miktzas hayom k’kulo *mikzas hayom k'kulo*, and the
רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* seems like maybe it might not be able to
count מקצת היום ככולו *mikzas hayom k'kulo*. So again, how do we
apply מקצת היום ככולו *mikzas hayom k'kulo*, what kind of things? And
again, because the first day of those days is also only half
a day, because whenever you got the seventh day of of a
פרה אדומה parah adumah *parah adumah* on the seventh day and then
that's sometime during the daytime presumably, and then you go to the
מקווה *mikvah* and then you wait until nightfall, but so that day
already counts as like the first day that you were טהור tahor,
*tahor*. So then what about the second day? Could you count מקצת
היום ככולו *mikzas hayom k'kulo* on both days? It would be only,
you know, two, three, four, or maybe twelve or thirteen, fourteen hours,
it wouldn't be even half of a, or it would be just
about half a day to count as two days. So that would
be kind of an interesting suggestion to think about תוספות *Tosafos* and
the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* there. Okay. That's the גמרא *Gemara*. איתמר *itmar*:
מי שנזר והוא בבית הקברות beveit hakevaros? *mi shenazar v'hu b'veis hakvaros*,
a person who was in what was took a נדר neder *neder*
to become a נזיר nazir *nazir* and he is in the cemetery.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר נזירות nezirus חלה עליו *Rabbi Yochanan amar
nezirus chalah alav*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says the נזירות
nezirus *nezirus* counts, it takes hold. וריש לקיש אמר אין נזירות nezirus
חלה עליו *v'Reish Lakish amar ein nezirus chalah alav*. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *Reish Lakish* says the נזירות nezirus *nezirus* does not take effect.
Okay. So why? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר נזירות nezirus חלה
עליו וסבר מטלא טליא וקיימא *Rabbi Yochanan amar nezirus chalah alav v'savar
matla talya v'kayma*. Okay. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says the
reason why the נזירות nezirus *nezirus* takes effect is because he thinks
it is מטלא טליא *matla talya*, it is a hanging thing. In
other words, you are טמא tamei, *tameh* now, but the נזירות nezirus,
*nezirus* has suspended itself on you and is hanging waiting to take
hold until you become טהור tahor. *tahor*. So during that interim period,
the נדר neder *neder* is waiting to take effect, but it functionally
does exist, and that's why the prohibition on drinking wine and things
like that, and also how then you would not have to reinitialize
the נזיר nazir, *nazir* after leaving the cemetery and becoming טהור tahor
*tahor*, it would already be suspended וקיימא *v'kayma*. כיון דמשכחת טהרה tahara
חיילא *keivan d'mishkachat taharah chaila*. As soon as it finds, it's very
interesting the terminology, משכחת טהרה tahara חיילא *mishkachat taharah chaila*, then it
will take effect when it finds the person טהור tahor *tahor*. וריש
לקיש אמר אין נזירות nezirus. חלה עליו *v'Reish Lakish amar ein nezirus
chalah alav*. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* says the נזירות nezirus.
*nezirus* does not take effect. אי הדר ואמר *ei hadar v'amar*, but
what if he goes back and says it again? So then חיילא
עליה *chaila aleih*, then it will take effect. ואי לא לא *v'ei
lo lo*, then if not, not. In other words, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish, *Reish Lakish* is saying saying that you'll be a נזיר nazir.
*nazir* when you're in the cemetery, when you're already טמא מת tamei
meit *tameh meis*, it means nothing because you have to be טהור
tahor, *tahor* in order to be a נזיר nazir, *nazir*. It's almost
like מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה *matneh al mah shekasuv b'Torah* to
a certain extent. You're trying to become a נזיר nazir, *nazir* at
a time when you are not allowed to be a נזיר nazir
*nazir* anyway. So the מצוות mitzvos, *mitzvos* of the תורה
*Torah* are preventing that נדר neder *neder* from taking effect. And again,
going back to the questions we had in נדרים nedarim *Nedarim* about
שבועה נשבע על מה שכתוב בתורה *shvuah nishba al mah shekasuv b'Torah*
and taking a נדר neder על מה שכתוב בתורה *neder al mah
shekasuv b'Torah*, things like that. So here, it almost sounds like ריש
לקיש's Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish's* position might be suggesting like you're trying
to form your נזירות nezirus *nezirus* around something that you have no
control over. You're trying to become a נזיר nazir, *nazir* when you're
טמא tamei *tameh*. Okay. וריש לקיש אמר אין נזירות nezirus? חלה עליה
ואי הדר ואמר חיילא עליה ואי לא לא *v'Reish Lakish amar ein
nezirus chalah aleih v'ei hadar v'amar chaila aleih v'ei lo lo*. Okay.
איתיביה רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
לריש לקיש *eisiveh Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish*. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan.
*Rabbi Yochanan* is now going to have I think three challenges to
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish's* opinion which will be at least
somewhat deflective, and the third one is probably going to be accepted.
That's going to be on the top of יז עמוד א yud
zayin amud aleph. *yud zayin amud aleph*. So איתיביה רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan לריש לקיש: מי שנזר והוא בבית הקברות *eisiveh Rabbi Yochanan l'Reish
Lakish: mi shenazar v'hu b'veis hakvaros*, a person who decides says to
become a נזיר nazir *nazir* in the cemetery, אפילו היה שם שלשים
יום *afilu hayah sham shloshim yom*, if he was there for thirty
days, אינו עולה מן המנין *eino oleh min haminyan* ואינו מביא קרבן
טומאה korban tuma *v'eino meivi korban tumah*. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
*Reish Lakish*... רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says a person who
is in the cemetery for thirty days, it doesn't count and he
does not bring קרבן טומאה korban tuma, *korban tumah*. קרבן טומאה korban
tuma הוא דלא מייתי הא מיחל חיילא עליה *korban tumah hu d'lo
maysei ha michal chaila aleih*. The fact is he's exempted from bringing
the קרבן טומאה korban tumah. *korban tumah*, but that doesn't mean he's
not a נזיר nazir *nazir*. This person is a נזיר nazir, *nazir*
who has an exemption from bringing the קרבן korban. *korban*. And that
sounds like a good proof for רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan's*
position against ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*. אינו עולה מן המנין
*eino oleh min haminyan*. So אינו עולה מן המנין *eino oleh min
haminyan* is because he's טמא tamei. *tameh*. So he has to have
thirty days when he is a נזיר nazir, *nazir* who is טהור
tahor *tahor*. But if he's טמא tamei *tameh* now, he still functions...
he is a נזיר nazir *nazir*, or perhaps even according to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan*, it's just waiting until he becomes טהור
tahor, *tahor*. But the fact is רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*
says, the fact the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* even had to tell me
אינו מביא קרבן טומאה korban tumah, *eino meivi korban tumah* means to
tell me that such a person is a נזיר nazir, *nazir* who
has exemptions. He has etc. he might do something. Meaning אינו עולה
מן המנין *eino oleh min haminyan* means nothing. So look, ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* is going to be able to defend himself.
It's not a knockout proof, but it's at least seems reasonable according
to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* would use
this as his support for his answer. אמר ליה ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *amar leh Reish Lakish*... ריש לקיש Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish* can
defend himself: אינו בתורת טומאה tumah. *eino b'toras tumah*. And you don't
have to bring קרבן טומאה, korban tumah, it's because you're not a
נזיר nazir, at all. So if you're not a נזיר Nazir at
all, of course אין עולים לו מן המנין. ein olim lo min
haminyan. I mean again, it's sort of a strange way of telling
a person, "You're not a נזיר, Nazir it doesn't count for the
30 days of נזירות nezirus, that you don't even have to do
because you're not a נזיר." Nazir It's kind of a strange way
of saying
it; that's also maybe a reason why רבי יוחנן has better support
from that. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, says אינו בתורת טומאה ואינו בתורת
קרבן. eino b’toras tumah v’eino b’toras korban. Okay, another challenge. איתיבי. Isvei.
So רבי יוחנן challenged against ריש לקיש Reish Lakish again. מי שהיה
טמא ונזר אסור
לגלח ולשתות יין וטמא למתים.
mi shehayah tamei v’nazar
asur
legaleiach v’shos yayin v’tamei lamesim. A person who was טמא, tamei this
is from the תוספתא. Tosefta. So a person who was already טמא
tamei, and נזר, nazar, he became a נזיר, Nazir then he's still
prohibited from shaving and drinking wine and becoming טמא למתים. tamei lamesim.
ואם גילח ושתה יין ונטמא למתים הרי זה סופג את הארבעים. v’im
gilach v’shasah yayin v’nitma lamesim harei zeh sofeg es arba’im. Such a
person will get מלקות malkos for violating any of the prohibitions of
a נזיר, Nazir, even if at the time of taking the נזירות
nezirus a person was already טמא. tamei, אי אמרת בשלמא חלה היינו
טעמא דסופג את הארבעים. ei amart bishlama chaila haynu ta’ama d’sofeg es
arba’im. If you say that it's because the נזירות nezirus takes effect,
well that makes sense, that's why you would get punished for violating
those prohibitions. אלא אי אמרת לא חלה, ela i amart lo chaila,
if you, ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish are going to tell me that
the נזירות nezirus will not take effect at all, אמאי סופג את
הארבעים? amai sofeg es arba’im? Why should you, why should you get
any punishment for that? It doesn't make any sense. Okay, so ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish can defend himself: הכא במאי עסקינן ביוצא ונכנס. hacha
b’mai askinan b’yotzei v’nichnas. No, it must have been dealing with a
case where such a person was טמא tamei and then became טהור,
tahor and once becoming טהור, tahor affirmed the initial נזירות nezirus in
some way. And that was a מחלוקת between the מפרש Mefareish and
the מאירי Meiri again about how much do you have to affirm
the נזירות nezirus again once becoming טהור. tahor According to the מפרש,
Mefareish, it sounds like you have to actually verbalize it and say,
"I'm going to be a נזיר Nazir like I said when I
was in the cemetery," or "I'm going to keep what I said
when I was in the cemetery," something like that. So again, it's
kind of like a יד yad or it's
kind of like connecting back to the initial נזירות, nezirus but fundamentally
it's going to take effect now.
And according to the מאירי, Meiri, maybe not even verbal; maybe if
you just mentally re-accept on yourself, you sort of recognize, "Oh, now
that I'm טהור tahor I can become a נזיר," Nazir, maybe that's
even enough.
And again, that's different than a normal נזירות. nezirus So that means
in some respect even ריש לקיש will recognize that what happened in
the cemetery has some kind of a meaning.
הכא במאי עסקינן ביוצא ונכנס. hacha b’mai askinan b’yotzei v’nichnas. And now
a third challenge. איתיבי: Isvei: אין בין טמא שנזר לנזיר טהור שנטמא.
ein bein tamei shenazar l’nazir tahor shenitma. There is no difference between
someone who was already טמא tamei and became a נזיר Nazir
to a נזיר Nazir who was
טהור tahor and then became טמא, tamei אלא
טמא שנזר שביעי שלו עולה לו מן המנין.
ela tamei shenazar shevi’i shelo oleh lo
min haminyan. But a טמא, tamei. a person who was already טמא
tamei, who took
a נדר neder, to become a נזיר, Nazir the שביעי, shevi’i, seventh
day of his purification process of becoming טהור, tahor עולה לו מן
המנין. oleh lo min haminyan. It counts for him as the beginning
of his 30 days of נזירות. nezirut ונזיר טהור שנטמא אין שביעי
שלו עולה לו מן המנין. v’nazir tahor shenitma ein shevi’i shelo oleh
lo min haminyan. And the person who was already a נזיר טהור
nazir tahor and the נזירות nezirut had already started and then became
טמא tamei, and has to wait seven days, become
טהור and bring his קרבנות טומאה korbanos tumah and shave,
such a person, the שביעי, shevi’i, seventh day of the טהרה process
does not count למנין. laminyan. And again, that's getting into the questions
of how do we say again מקצת היום ככולו and finishing one
period and starting another period? And how much, and again what we
had yesterday and two days ago and on Shabbos's דף, daf, how
much do we count overlapping different types of periods, like
if you're a נזיר עולם nazir olam and regular נזיר, Nazir and
how much
can those overlap, and counting נזיר טמא
nazir tamei and נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, how much can those times
overlap as well?
So that was now the third challenge to ריש לקיש's opinion on
top of י"ז עמוד א'. Just one comment about we explain the
challenge.
Okay, so sorry, yeah, you're right. אין טמא שנזר לנזיר טהור שנטמא
טמא שנזר שביעי שלו עולה לו מן המנין
ונזיר טהור שנטמא אין שביעי שלו עולה לו מן המנין.
ein tamei shenazar l’nazir tahor shenitma tamei shenazar shevi’i shelo oleh lo
min
haminyan
v’nazir tahor shenitma ein shevi’i shelo oleh lo min haminyan. ואי סלקא
דעתך לא חלה, v’ei salka da’atach lo chaila, if you, ריש לקיש,
will say that it does not take effect, אמאי עולה לו מן
המנין? amai oleh lo min haminyan? Why should the שביעי, shevi’i, seventh
day already count for the person who was a נזיר Nazir, who
was טמא tamei and became a נזיר, Nazir that he has to
purify seven days and the שביעי, shevi’i, seventh day should already start
counting for the נזירות? nezirut If it wasn't taking effect, you're going
to tell me it didn't take effect, it doesn't matter, so what
does that mean עולה לו מן המנין? oleh lo min haminyan? It
must be that already the initial נזירות, nezirut, like I say, רבי
יוחנן says, the initial
נזירות nezirut, took a hold,
was hovering, waiting to take effect, and as soon as you become
טהור, then it already starts counting. Right? ואי סלקא דעתך לא חלה
אמאי עולה לו מן המנין? v’ei salka da’atach lo chaila amai oleh
lo min haminyan? So and we're
going to have some suggestion of the continuing conversation is going to
pick up from there. מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
is going to have a continuing discussion רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש
starting tomorrow. Just wanted to note the רמב"ם Rambam. in פרק ה'
perek hey of הלכות נזירות Hilchos Nezirus talks about this case right
at the end. The רמב"ם Rambam says: נזיר טהור שטימא עצמו. nazir
tahor shetimmei atzmo. What about a נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, a regular
נזיר, Nazir, who intentionally... makes himself טמא. tamei, It's interesting, the question
is whether this was באונס beones or something else, but a person
who became intentionally טמא, tamei לוקה, loke, gets מכות. makos. Okay, that's
interesting. אף משום לא תאחר לשלמו Af mishum lo seacher leshalmo because
of the obligation not only for a נזיר Nazir to not become
טמא, tamei, he also gets a set of מכות makos for violating
בל תאחר. Bal Tacher. We have to remember נזירות nezirut, is a
נדר neder and נדרים nedarim that you don't keep on time, you
push them off, you're going to be violating בל תאחר Bal Tacher
for making the נדר late. So in this case a נזיר Nazir
who intentionally pushes off his נזירות nezirut until seven days to become
טהור and bring קרבן טומאה korban tumah and then wait another thirty
days, so then that's going to end up being that he's pushed
off your ability to fulfill the נדר and so then you violate
בל תאחר Bal Tacher as well. בל תאחר לשלמו Bal Tacher leshalmo
שהרי איחר נזירותו ועשה מעשה sheharei ichar neziruso ve'asa maise because you
pushed off, excuse me, pushed off the pure נזירות nezirut and quote
עשה מעשה, asa maise, you did an action. We have a principle
in הלכה halacha about a לאו שאין בו מעשה. lav she'ein bo
maise. If you have a prohibition which does not involve doing anything,
usually you don't get מכות makos for that. It's one of the
exceptions to getting מכות. makos. But now here's what the רמב"ם Rambam
says. הלא נאמר שהנזיר שטימא עצמו לוקה ארבע מלכויות, Halo ne'emar shehanazir
shetimei atzmo loke arba malkiyos, a נזיר Nazir, who made himself טמא
tamei gets four different sets of lashes: משום לא יטמא mishum lo
yitma ומשום לא יחל דברו umishum lo yachel devaro ומשום לא תאחר
לשלמו umishum lo seacher leshalmo ומשום לא יבוא אם היתה ביאה וטומאה
כאחת כמו שביארנו. umishum lo yavo im hayesa biah vetuma keachas k'mo
shebe'arnu. Fine. So those different prohibitions. However, what about the person who
was בבית הקברות? If you go a little bit, yeah it's right
before in the רמב"ם. Rambam. I'm sorry I missed the spot. The
רמב"ם Rambam says that a person who is a נזיר Nazir, שהוא
בבית הקברות, shehu beveit hakevaros, the נזיר, Nazir! oh sorry it's the
previous page. A נזיר Nazir. like our case, a person who was
in the בית הקברות beit hakevaros and then took a נדר, such
a person still violates בל יחל דברו Bal Yachel Devaro and בל
תאחר. Bal Tacher. Now I'm going to ask you, would they get
the מלקות? malkus? So he would get מלקות malkus according to the
רמב"ם and the לחם משנה Lechem Mishnah has a very long discussion
about it because it seems like לאו שאין בו מעשה. lav she'ein
bo maise. It sounds like just standing there, standing there and saying
I'm a נזיר, Nazir you didn't do anything. So how do you
understand what the מעשה maise is that you did in order to
get the מלקות? malkus? Either it has to be connected really just
to the speech act itself which is kind of a stretch because
that's not usually what we say, or the fact that you are
actively staying somewhere is enough of an action. That's what he thinks.
So, well no, but so passively or actively or however. So again,
that's part of the question. Again, that's why it's kind of a
stretch of a case. It doesn't sound like much of an action
to be giving you מלקות malkus for, but to sort of intentionally
stay put is an action in regards to that. Other examples of
לאו שאין בו מעשה, lav she'ein bo maise, well lots of them.
A lot of the sort of mental מצוות, mitzvos things like if
you believe in a false god. There's no, you didn't worship anything,
you didn't do anything, so there's no way to punish you for
it because you didn't do anything. Things like that. Trying to think
of other good examples. There's lots of good examples, but that's not
for now. So all those are, all of the also sort of
emotional type of מצוות like לא תשנא את אחיך בלבבך, lo sisna
es achicha bilvavecha, you can't hate other people, things like that. So
many of those there's no way to give you מלקות malkus for
them because they have no active action involved. So here, kind of
an exceptional case because of staying in the cemetery, staying in the
cemetery sort of, you're not doing anything. So despite the fact that
the משנה Mishnah sees, I mean the impression of the משנה Mishnah
is like you know there's no prompt so to speak, right? I
mean he doesn't have to, I mean he doesn't even have to
bring a קרבן טומאה, korban tumah, but he does get מלקות. malkus.
I mean like, well maybe he'll get מלקות malkus according to the
רמב"ם. Again it's not explicit in the משנה Mishnah. at all, it
has to do with how, again reading in all the other material
we know about נדרים nedarim and נזירות nezirut. into this משנה. Mishnah
This משנה at least sounds like sort of, again according to ריש
לקיש it means nothing. The fact is we פוסקין pasken like רבי
יוחנן so it is that there's a נזירות that really exists and
is hovering and that's where the רמב"ם gets that from, is that
once there's really a נזירות then while you were a נזיר Nazir.
who is טמא, tamei so even though you don't bring the קרבן
טומאה korban tumah which is a special obligation based on the fact
that you need to have a period of טהרה and then you
became טמא tamei because it says וטימא ראש נזרו, vetimei es rosh
nizro, he became טמא, tamei but if you were already טמא tamei
when you became a נזיר Nazir, then you're already sort of automatically
violating that prohibition, that puts you in a different situation. I don't
understand, you know, I mean like again like this is my problem
the whole way through. Like when you look at the context, you
know the guy's in the בית הקברות, beit hakevaros, I mean you
kind of know a נזיר Nazir can't become טמא tamei. so how
did he intend it to be later? Well to a certain extent
that may be part of the rationale for ריש לקיש. ריש לקיש,
it makes too much sense. I mean I understand why, so it
makes sense for רבי יוחנן. So רבי יוחנן is going to tell
you ריש לקיש I love you. you're my best friend, but nonetheless
I have all these משניות mishnayot that tell me the opposite. All
these משניות mishnayot sound like you can become a נזיר Nazir when
you're in the cemetery and then you just have violated all the
prohibitions. I hear you, you're really saying it very sharply, which is
that ריש לקיש's position makes a lot of sense. The fact that
we require לב ופיו שוים lev u-piv shavim and things like that,
פיו ולבו שוים, piv u-libo shavim, I said that wrong, and that
we require נדרים and we can say ספק נזירות להקל safek nezirut
l-hakel and things like that, nonetheless, here we're treating it very clearly,
person became a נזיר, Nazir person was טמא מת tamei meit already.
And again, especially with תוספות and the רא"ש, Rosh, it's interesting, it's
not just actively really in the cemetery but it would even apply
to just sort of a normal case of walking around in the
street, which is interesting because like what you're saying Michael, it makes
a lot of sense if you're in the cemetery and you're sort
of very consciously aware of that טומאה. tumah It's like you're really
touching, touching the אבי אבות הטומאה avi avot ha-tumah right now and
it's very different than just being טמא מת tamei meit and walking
down the street and saying, oh, you know, oh I forgot I
was טמא מת tamei meit, whatever, that gives a lot more room
for רבי יוחנן to say, look, this is just how it works.
ריש לקיש would have a harder time explaining that if we take
like the explanation of תוספות and the רא"ש. Rosh. So he is
in רבי יוחנן's opinion, so he is a נזיר Nazir, and he's
sort of off for קרבן טומאה. Right, you have to wait to
become טהור and bring the קרבן. Not the קרבן טומאה, he's exempted
from the קרבן טומאה, but he has seven days where he has
to purify himself and then the נזירות is going to kick in
and even during those seven days he can't drink wine and can't
shave. So okay, so let me understand. So let's make it easy.
So he's in the בית הקברות beit hakevarot for ten days and
he's in it for twenty days, right? אינו עולה לו מן המנין,
eino oleh lo min haminyan, he would have to as soon as
he gets out of the בית הקברות, beit hakevarot, he would have
to purify himself seven days with פרה אדומה and then the נזירות
is going to count. So today's day 17? Day 17 the נזירות
is going to start. And then 30 days later, day 47 is
when it's over. Right. Right. But meanwhile all that time he still
can't do anything else. He still can't drink wine, he still can't
shave, he still can't become טמא מת, tamei meit, even right from
the תוספתא Tosefta it said someone who was טמא tamei, when he
became a נזיר, even while he's still טמא tamei he cannot be
מיטמא למת, mitamei le-meit, and that's what we talked about with כהנים
Kohanim as well, to be מוסיף טומאה mosif tumah on someone who's
already טמא tamei. sounds like the prohibition, the לא תעשה lo ta'aseh
still applies even if there's no additional טומאה that's going to be
imparted. So to some extent he's like a נזיר for longer so
to speak. נזיר for longer, also and just a sense of pushing
it off, but still the נזירות, the prohibitions of נזירות, I'm sorry,
I don't know your name, sorry. חנן. Chanan. חנן, Chanan, so what
חנן Chanan pointed out before really makes a lot of sense, which
is that the counting time is something special for נזירות, but the
prohibitions are much more like a regular נדר seem to be that
it could extend beyond the 30. Just as becoming a נזיר, he
really hasn't said anything because we're all טמא מת, right? No, because
we פוסקין pasken like רבי יוחנן. No, but meaning like it hasn't,
he's not a נזיר, like meaning... He is a נזיר! He is
a נזיר. But like meaning he is a נזיר who doesn't have
to bring a קרבן טומאה because he was never טהור first and
then became טמא. But fundamentally, but wait, but really what רבי יוחנן
is saying is that his full נזירות starts later, right, once he...
No, this full נזירות starts now, but it doesn't count for the
30 days of the נזירות. The 30 days can only be once
he becomes טהור because you have to be טהור to be the
נזיר. So being a נזיר, you can be a נזיר who's טמא,
that's a thing that exists. That's why you have to bring a
קרבן טומאה, that's why every נזיר who becomes טמא has to bring
קרבן טומאה and everything like that. The fact is you can be
a נזיר who is טמא. But the days which count for the
time of being a נזיר, the 30 days, those can only be
when you're טהור and it have to be consecutive. So that's the
difference. Okay, so anyway, I was understanding it... one sec Michael. So
we'll leave off here and everyone can get to מנין minyan if
they're going to try to get to מנין. minyan. Rabbi Linzer hopefully
will be back tomorrow on Tuesday morning and all will be well,
good, he is in Miami.