Good morning, הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabba, מורי morai I guess. I don't
know what the proper what wish is.
But as we were just discussing, unfortunately, the דף Daf has recently
just been dealing with all these cases of death and
this מצוה. mitzvah. So, our hearts and our תפילות tefillot go out
to the injured and really to everybody in Israel right now. We
really should just know of security and of peace.
Okay, so we begin on מ"ד עמוד ב' Mem Dalet Amud Bet
with the משנה. Mishnah. And we're moving from טומאה, Tumah, we did
the איסורים issurim of טומאה Tumah and יין Yayin and תגלחת. Tiglachat.
And two of those were very interesting in terms of their practical
relevance for other areas, טומאה Tumah for טומאת כהנים tumas kohanim and
תגלחת Tiglachat for the general issue of shaving, and יין Yayin in
an interesting way just occurred to me now became a paradigm for
טעם כעיקר. Taam Ke'ikkar. So very relevant in the world of כשרות.
Kashrus. So each one of those just occurred to me right now
actually serves as a basis for very important areas of הלכה halacha
elsewhere. Now we return to more of the rituals associated with the
נזיר Nazir at the shaving that takes place at the end of
the process of טומאה Tumah and then the next משנה, Mishnah, the
shaving that takes place at the end of the process of טהרה.
Taharah. So let's take a look at our
משנה. Mishnah. תגלחת טומאה כיצד? Tiglachat Tumah Keitzad? How would you do
the shaving of טומאה, Tumah, meaning we have a very specific question
that we're asking as we'll see. היה מזה בשלישי ובשביעי, Haya mazeh
bashlishi ubashvii, you would do the sprinkling of the ashes of the
פרה אדומה Parah Adumah on days three and seven, ומגלח בשביעי, umegaleach
bashvii, and then shave on day seven, ומביא קרבנותיו בשמיני, umevi korbanosav
bashmini, and then bring the קרבנות korbanos on day eight, which is
what the תורה Torah says.
Can you hand me a חומש Chumash here? We should actually, is
there a חומש Chumash there? Okay. So,
it actually says by the, oh look at that, and the line
was right and the whatever, thank you, I appreciate that. So it
says, it says: וכי ימות
מת עליו בפתע פתאם וטמא ראש נזרו וגלח ראשו ביום טהרתו ביום
השביעי יגלחנו, V'chi yamut meis alav b'fesa pitoam v'timei rosh nizro v'gilach
rosho b'yom taharato b'yom hashvii yegalchenu, the day he becomes טהור. tahor.
וביום השמיני יביא שתי תורים או שני בני יונה, U'vayom hashmini yavi
shtei torim o shnei b'nei yonah, the קרבנות korbanos is the next
day. All right. ואם גלח בשמיני מביא קרבנותיו בו ביום, Ve'im gilach
bashmini mevi korbanosav bo bayom, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. And
if for some reason he waited to shave until day eight, you
can still bring the קרבנות. korbanos. The הלכה halacha is not that
you bring the קרבנות korbanos the day after you shave. The הלכה
halacha is you bring the קרבנות korbanos on day eight, you're supposed
to shave on day seven. If you postponed the shaving, that's also
okay, you still bring the קרבנות korbanos on day eight. אמר לו
רבי טרפון, Amar lo Rabbi Tarfon, רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said to
him: ומה מה בין זה למצורע? U'mah ma bein zeh l'metzora? How
is this different than a מצורע? metzora? Because he's taking it for
granted that by a מצורע metzora who waits to do his shaving
until day eight, the קרבן korban is brought on day nine. Okay?
So we'll see in a
minute why that's taken for granted but he takes that for granted.
And therefore he says, so the נזיר Nazir also if he waited
to shave until day eight, he should bring his קרבן korban on
day nine. Actually,
by the מצורע metzora it's not shaving on day eight, it's shaving
a day later but it's a seven-day wait until the כהן kohen
visited him again and saw that it wasn't seven days of sprinkling
the ashes of the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, it was seven days
until the כהן kohen visited him again. Anyway, so אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said to him: זה טהרתו תלויה בימיו, Zeh taharato teluyah
b'yamav, by the case of the נזיר, Nazir, him becoming טהור tahor
is dependent on the
days, ומצורע טהרתו תלויה בתגלחתו, umetzora taharato teluyah b'tiglachto, but by the
מצורע metzora the shaving itself is part of the טהרה tahara process.
Now, what does that mean? Or how does he know that? So
the תוספות Tosafot points out that the way he knows it is
because by the נזיר Nazir it just says וגלח ראשו v'gilach rosho
and then it says וביום השמיני יביא שתי תורים. u'vayom hashmini yavi
shtei torim. It mentions about shaving but that's all it says. You
shave on day seven, וביום השביעי. u'vayom hashvii. But as opposed to,
yeah, I mean to say it otherwise. But as opposed to by
the מצורע metzora where it says the
following:
Okay, it
says like this: So first there's a whole seven-day process.
He starts with the two birds, right? It looks like it's the
whole beginning of פרשת תזריע. Parshas Tazria. וראה הכהן והנה נרפא נגע
הצרעת מן הצרוע. V'ra’ah hakohen v'hineh nirpa nega hatzaraat min hatzarua. וצוה
הכהן ולקח למיטהר שתי צפרים חיות טהורות ועץ ארז ושני תולעת ואזוב.
V'tziva hakohen v'lakach lamitaher shtei tzipporim chayot tehorot v'eitz erez u’shni tola’at
v'eizov.
So he does the thing with the birds, and he says ושלח
את הצפר החיה על פני השדה. v'shilach et hatzippor hachayah al pnei
hasadeh.
I cut out a little bit. Okay, so he does the whole
thing with the birds. Okay. Then, after the bird thing, וכבס המיטהר
את בגדיו וגלח את כל שערו ורחץ במים וטהר ואחר יבוא אל
המחנה. v'chibes hamitaher begadav v'gilach kol searo v'rachatz bamayim v'taher v'achar yavo
el hamachaneh. So he goes to the מקוה. mikvah. Then, וישב מחוץ
לאהלו שבעת ימים. v'yashav michutz l'aholo shivat yamim. Seven-day wait. So seven-day
wait after the bird thing. Similar to the
נזיר, Nazir, seven-day wait to become טהור tahor with the ashes of
the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah, this was a seven-day wait after the
bird thing. So so far it's parallel. והיה ביום. V'hayah bayom. והיה
ביום השביעי Vehayah bayom hashvi'i יגלח את כל שערו yegalach et kol
searo את ראשו, at rosho, it says again, את ראשו ואת זקנו
ואת גבת עיניו
et
rosho ve'et
zekano ve'et gabot einav ואת כל שערו יגלח ve'et kol searo yegaleach
וכבס את בגדיו ורחץ את בשרו במים וטהר. vechibes et begadav verachatz
et besaro bamayim vetaher.
So here him, after the גילוח, giluach, he have to immerse in
a מקוה, mikvah, he has to וכבס את כל בגדיו ורחץ את
בשרו במים, vechibes et kol begadav verachatz et besaro bamayim, which is
understood as going to a מקוה, mikvah, וטהר. vetaher. And that's part
of the טהרה taharah process. So therefore Rabbi Akiva says is that
by the מצורע, metzora, the גילוח giluach is part of the טהרה
taharah process, and afterwards it requires going to a מקוה, mikvah, and
only then are you a—what does a person after they go to
a מקוה—טבול יום?
Okay. And therefore the logic is, so until you do the—if you
waited till day eight, he assumed even if let's say you went
to the מקוה mikvah on day seven, if you're the מצורע, metzora,
it didn't work. Right? In order to enable you to go to
the מקוה mikvah you have to do the shaving first. So if
you waited till day eight to do the shaving, even if you
did the מקוה mikvah day seven it didn't work. You'll have to
do a מקוה mikvah again on day eight. Okay. And then you
become a טבול יום. tevul yom? As a טבול יום tevul yom.
you're not yet done. Since it's clear that the תורה Torah wants
you to wait till the next day after you go to the
מקוה, mikvah the assumption is the תורה Torah wants you to be
totally out of your טומאה tumah before you bring the קרבן korban
the next day. So if you waited till day eight, then you
did—to do the shaving—you'd have to go to the מקוה mikvah, again
because the מקוה mikvah comes
after. That is the ending of the טהרה taharah process. That makes
you a טבול יום. tevul yom You have to wait till day
nine to bring your קרבן. korban. That he says there. It's part
of the טהרה taharah process. Whereas if you go back—whereas if you
go to the נזיר, nazir, the טהרה taharah process is just the
sprinkling of the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. He's just
טמא מת. tamei meis. It's not a unique טהרה. taharah. He's טמא
tamei like anybody else who touched a dead body. Day three and
day seven make you טהור. tahor. The shaving is a ritual, but
it never says you go to the מקוה mikvah after you shave.
So it's not part of the טהרה taharah process. So if you
waited till day eight, so you go to the מקוה mikvah on
day seven after the sprinkling of the ashes of the פרה אדומה,
parah adumah, you're a טבול יום tevul yom. on day seven. Even
if you forgot to do the shaving, you're totally טהור tahor by
day eight. You just have to do the גילוח giluach ritual. So
he's—it's a very close read of the פסוקים. pesukim. He says the
shaving ritual by the מצורע metzora is part of the טהרה taharah
process, it requires מקוה mikvah afterwards, and it requires waiting until the
next day. So if you postponed it a day you'll have to
bring the קרבן korban on day nine. Whereas by the נזיר nazir
who's טמא מת, tamei meis, it's a separate ritual. It's not part
of becoming טהור. tahor. So if you postponed it a day, so
what? You do the גילוח giluach and the קרבן korban both on
day eight. Okay. So that's what he says. אמר ליה זה טהרתו
תלויה בימיו, Amar lei zeh taharato teluyah beyamav, by just day seven.
ומצורע טהרתו תלויה בתגלחתו. u'metzora taharato teluyah betiglachto. The טהרה taharah process—the
shaving is part of the טהרה. taharah. ואין מביא קרבן אלא אם
כן העריב שמשו. ve'ein meivi korban ela im kein he'eriv shimsho. And
therefore you can only bring a קרבן korban after the setting of
the sun, not at night, obviously till the next day, because you're
a טבול יום. tevul yom So if you went to the מקוה
mikvah on day seven without shaving, for a מצורע metzora it doesn't
matter. Until you go shave and then go to the מקוה, mikvah
then you're a טבול יום tevul yom. and you can't bring a
קרבן korban until the next day, till day nine.
In all cases the משנה mishnah is a נזיר nazir that became
טמא, tamei, and now they're talking about thirty days later.
No, no, no. נזיר Nazir that became טמא tamei in order to
restart the נזירות טהרה, nezirus taharah, he goes through a seven-day טהרה
taharah process, brings a קרבן. korban. This is not ending his נזירות.
nezirus. This is restarting the נזירות טהרה. nezirus taharah. Okay. Alright, so
very clear distinction of Rabbi Akiva. One is just a ritual of
נזירות, nezirus, and the other is a ritual of טהרה. taharah. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: קיבלה מיניה או לא? Kiblah
minei o lo? Did Rabbi Tarfon accept Rabbi Akiva's answer or not?
We never know how Rabbi Tarfon responded. תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear, דתני הלל, detani Hillel, Hillel teaches a ברייתא. braisa. This
is not הלל הזקן, Hillel Hazaken, this is the אמורא Amora הלל.
Hillel.
גילח בשמיני, Gilach bashmini, if he shaved on day eight,
מביא קרבנותיו בתשיעי, meivi korbanosav batshii, he brings his קרבנות korbanos on
day nine. Now of course you say well maybe that's the מצורע,
metzora, right? Who's that talking about? A נזיר nazir or a
מצורע? metzora? Okay, but תוספות Tosafot says they had a מסורה massorah
that that was talking about a נזיר. nazir. Because if it was
talking about a מצורע metzora everybody agrees to that. We already took
that for granted that if a מצורע metzora waits to shave till
day eight, he brings his קרבן korban till day nine. Okay, but
we're assuming this is talking about a נזיר. nazir. So then the
question is, who is it that says that if a נזיר nazir
postponed the shaving till day eight, he has to wait another day
for the קרבן? korban? So אי סלקא דעתך קיבלה מיניה, Ei salka
dachak kiblah minei, so if Rabbi Tarfon wound up agreeing to Rabbi
Akiva, then nobody would say you have to wait till day nine.
מביא קרבנותיו בשמיני, meivi korbanosav bashmini, we just do it on day
eight. So we assume this ברייתא braisa is saying that the נזיר
nazir has to bring it on day nine if he postponed his
גילוח. giluach. So we're talking about a נזיר nazir if he postponed
his גילוח. giluach. So the only person that could be is Rabbi
Tarfon, assuming Rabbi Tarfon did not concede to Rabbi Akiva.
Well it could be before he conceded.
Oh that maybe it's a משנה ראשונה mishnah rishonah of Rabbi Tarfon.
Alright, I don't know, it's a good point. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says, anyway, but that at least seems to reflect that position.
אמר רבא לא קשיא. Amar Rava lo kashya. No, not necessarily, maybe
Rabbi Tarfon conceded to Rabbi Akiva. So why would you have to
wait till day nine? הא דטבל בשביעי הא דלא טבל בשביעי. Ha
detaval bashvii ha delo taval bashvii. Because really the reason you're waiting
is not because you postponed your— גילוח giluach till day eight, the
reason you've postponed your going to the מקווה mikvah till day eight.
And again, every, so clearly, even for the נזיר nazir for טומאת
מת, tumas meis, going to the מקווה mikvah you have to go
to the מקווה mikvah and you're only till to become a טבול
יום tevul yom and then you're only טהור tahor by the evening.
So if you even if you did the sprinkling on day seven,
thank you. If you postponed the מקווה mikvah till day eight, you're
not טהור tahor till day nine, and therefore that would be the
case. Of course, that is a really bad read of the ברייתא
braisa because then why would it take גילוח בשמיני? giluach b'shmini? It
should have said טבל בשמיני. taval b'shmini. Right? The whole point is
missing. So anyway, it's a very strange response. Certainly, the simple sense
of the ברייתא, braisa, assuming it's talking about a נזיר, nazir, shows
it that רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon did not agree to רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Okay. Yes.
It's not obvious that טבול יום tevul yom cannot bring קרבנות korbonos
and have them be sacrificed.
Okay, so that is an excellent question.
What is the הלכה halacha about having a טמא tamei person having
קרבנות korbonos brought for him? So the הלכה halacha is ערל וטמא
המשלחין קרבנותיהם, arel v'tamei ameshalchin korbonoseihem, that even though they can't go
into, you know, certain zones in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they
can have somebody bring their קרבנות korbonos for them. The הלכה למעשה
halacha l'mayseh is that the טמא, tamei, now by the way, not
by a קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, okay, separate הלכה, halacha, but the
הלכה halacha is that the טמא tamei is only somebody who's like
טמא tamei like שרץ sheretz or נבילה neveila or so on. If
the טמא tamei is a טמא מת tamei meis or זב zav
or זבה zava or מצורע, metzora, they cannot have somebody bring their
קרבן korban for them. That's just the הלכה, halacha, you should know.
Okay, but even if assuming we didn't exactly know that or that
was somewhat debated,
תוספות's Tosafos point is it's implicit from the פסוקים pesukim that here
the תורה Torah wants you, whatever the other הלכה halacha is, if
you're a מצורע metzora טבול יום tevul yom and you want to
send a שלמים shlamim in, we can talk about it. But it's
implicit from the פסוקים pesukim that the תורה Torah wants you to
be totally טהור tahor before bringing your relevant קרבן korban because it
says ביום השביעי או מגלח ba'yom hashvi'i o megale'ach
and you go to the מקווה mikvah and the next day you
bring your קרבן. korban. Why didn't it have you bring it that
day? Right? Or by the נזיר, nazir, it says goes to the
you know he he you know he he's טהור tahor on day
seven with the ashes of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, right, and
we assume he goes to the מקווה mikvah as well or whatever,
and then on the eighth day he brings his קרבן, korban, right?
So it's clear here, that's what תוספות Tosafos says, from the פסוקים
pesukim it's clear that the תורה Torah wanted the נזיר nazir or
the מצורע metzora to be totally טהור, tahor, to go to the
מקווה, mikvah, get out of the טבול יום tevul yom status, right,
in order to. Now of course you could say maybe not, maybe
it's just arbitrarily assigning day eight, it's not related to being not
being a טבול יום. tevul yom But anyway, that's what we're like
assuming, okay? So therefore, but yes, it's a good question. Is it
really true that a טבול יום tevul yom. cannot have a קרבן
korban brought for him? So to some degree we're about to turn
to that question right now. Okay, to some degree the answer might
it probably makes להלכה l'halacha yes, maybe or whatever, but it might
very well yes. Yes what?
That a טבול יום tevul yom cannot have a קרבן korban brought
for him. Okay, but at least for these קרבנות korbonos תוספות's Tosafos
point is the simple sense of the פסוקים pesukim is that for
bringing the קרבן korban of the מצורע metzora process or the קרבן
korban to start the נזירות של טהרה, nezirus of tahara, the תורה
Torah wants the person fully out of the state out of their
state of טומאה. tum'ah.
But like for a שלמים, shlamim, if he has someone res-
So we could debate whether he could have a שלמים shlamim sent
for him, okay, but at least here for these קרבנות korbonos it
seems clear that the תורה Torah wants him fully out of that
state. Yes.
What about the פרה אדומה parah adumah again? Yeah.
Wasn't there something about the rabbis using a טבול יום tevul yom
for
to do the right process of the פרה אדומה? parah adumah? But
that was to burn the פרה, parah, etc., and to do the
whole process of creating the ashes, right? But not to send the
קרבן, korban,
isn't that having a sacrifice brought in a way?
No, I mean, and it's not being brought for him and he's
the and he's the officiant
and it's not in the עזרה. Azara. Anyway, so but yes, okay,
so but yeah, I mean it is not exactly the same but
it's related. Okay, so the מהלך mahalach is like this. So now
this question of a טבול יום tevul yom is exactly what we
turn to. Okay, אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye said,
אשכחינהו לחבריה דרב נתן בר הושעיה, ashkechinhu l'chavrei d'Rav Nosson bar Oshaya,
I found the colleagues of רב נתן בר הושעיה, Rav Nosson bar
Oshaya, דיתבין וקאמרין, d'yasvin v'kamrin, they were sitting and they were saying
that we've got this ברייתא braisa and here's what this ברייתא braisa
says, presumably they're quoting this is a ברייתא braisa that they're quoting,
the way תוספות Tosafos understands it. ובא לפני ה' אל פתח אהל
מועד, u'va lifnei Hashem el pesach ohel moed, this is by a
זב, zav, okay? It says that the זב zav on day seven
goes ahead and he has to bring these two birds and he
sacrifices and he brings them to פתח אהל מועד pesach ohel moed
ונתנם אל הכהן. u'nesanam el hakohein. And he, I'm sorry, this is
on day eight, okay? So he has the seven-day טהרה tahara process
and on day eight he brings these birds to the כהן. kohein.
ונתנם אל הכהן, u'nesanam el hakohein, אימתי הוא בא בזמן שהוא טהור
ועשה הערב שמש.
eimasai hu ba bizman
shehu tavor v'asa ha'erev shemesh. So beforehand it said that he would
go to the מקווה, mikvah, can I borrow the חומש Chumash here
again? So
it says
איש איש כי יהיה זב מבשרו, ish ish ki yihyeh zav mib'saro,
okay, it says וכי יטהר הזב מזובו וספר לו שבעת ימים לטהרתו
וכבס בגדיו ורחץ בשרו במים חיים וטהר. v'chi yithar hazav mizovo v'safar
lo shivas yamim l'taharato v'chibas begadav v'chibes begadav v'rachatz b'saro b'mayim chayim
v'taher. Okay, so seven days, goes to the מקווה, mikvah, and then.
And day eight, he comes to the משכן. Mishkan. Okay, so when
he's טובל tovel on day seven,
he's a טבול יום tevul yom on day seven, and on
day eight he comes to the משכן. Mishkan. So, here's what the
ברייתא braita says: אימתי הוא בא בזמן שטבל ועשה הערב שמש. emasei
hu ba bezman shehu taval v'asah ha'erev shemesh. When can he finally
come to the משכן? Mishkan? After he's gone to the מקוה mikvah,
and הערב שמש ha'erev shemesh and he's no longer a טבול יום.
tvul yom אין, in, that's yes. לא טבל ועשה הערב שמש lo
taval v'asah ha'erev shemesh if he had not done that, if he
was still a טבול יום, tvul yom. לא, lo, he could not
enter into the משכן Mishkan grounds. אלמא קסבר, alma kasavar, now presumably
that was again, you could read this that the friends were saying
all of this, תוספות Tosafot reads that this was like a ברייתא,
braita, and then this next line was the colleagues of רב נתן
Rav Natan reflecting on the ברייתא braita or inferring from the ברייתא.
braita. So the ברייתא braita teaches that he can only enter the
מקדש Mikdash grounds after, you know, when he's no longer טבול יום.
tvul yom, So therefore they say, oh look, what we can infer
from that is, אלמא קסבר, alma kasavar, you see this ברייתא braita
is of the opinion
טבול יום של זב כזב דמי, tvul yom shel zav kezav dami,
that even though he's a טבול יום tvul yom. of a זב,
zav, he still has the status of a זב. zav. Why? Cause
what's the הלכה? halacha? A זב, zav, this is very relevant למעשה
lema'aseh believe it or not or possibly for a reason I'm about
to tell you. A זב zav is not allowed to enter
onto into מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. Okay, which is in the time
of the מדבר midbar מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. The translation of מחנה
לויה Machaneh Leviyah nowadays is, anybody know? הר הבית. Har HaBayit. So
even and he would so he if he'd be transgressing, you know,
by entering in, what if his seven days were over, he went
to the מקוה, mikvah he was a טבול יום, tvul yom all
he needed was for nightfall to hit and then he would be
well totally טהור tahor although
if he saw for three days he'd have to bring a קרבן
korban on day eight to be totally totally טהור, tahor, but okay,
and we'll get to that in a minute. Would on that day
after having gone to the מקוה mikvah, and all he needed was
nightfall and he was a טבול יום, tvul yom, he enter on
הר הבית, Har HaBayit, would he still be חייב? chayav? Okay, is
a טבול יום tvul yom, of a זב zav like a זב?
zav? That's the question. Now why is this relevant nowadays? Because the
other people, no, not women. The other people well yes but that's
not what I'm talking about. The other people that are relevant that
are included in the category of אסור assur on הר הבית Har
HaBayit is anybody that has טומאה יוצא מגופו. tumah yotzei migufo. Somebody
who's טמא tamei because of something happening to their body. I mean
מצורע metzora is even worse, okay, but basically a type of a
flow, which includes yes women who are נדה niddah and includes men
who have seminal emissions. So when they lead these tours up on
הר הבית Har HaBayit and they say we're gonna they know what
they're doing and they're not gonna take you onto the place of
the מקום המקדש makom HaMikdash itself, they're just gonna take you to
הר הבית. Har HaBayit. So the assumption is cause even if you're
טמא מת, tamei meit, which we assume everybody is nowadays, you're allowed
in מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, you're allowed in הר הבית, Har HaBayit,
but you're not allowed on the actual מקום המקדש. makom HaMikdash. So
they say fine, we're gonna avoid מקום המקדש. makom HaMikdash. Okay, here's
the only problem. The only problem is is that let's say the
woman is a נדה niddah or let's say the man had a
seminal emission. So what they I again I don't know I know
that they tell the men that make sure you go have gone
to the מקוה mikvah the day before like sort of solve that
problem. Okay, I don't know I don't know if they tell the
women if you're a נדה niddah you shouldn't be coming, okay. I
hope they do. Anyway, but let's say they say that to the
man. So the thing is fine, let's say he goes to the
מקוה mikvah the day before and they're going on an seven AM
whatever thing and then he has sex with his wife at night
or has a seminal emission or
whatever. So even if they say go to the מקוה mikvah that
morning before we start, okay, so he goes to the מקוה mikvah
that morning. Fine, he's a טבול יום, tvul yom right? So he's
a טבול יום tvul yom, of a בעל קרי. ba'al keri. So
do they say if you had to go to the מקוה mikvah
you know if you couldn't go to the מקוה mikvah yesterday and
whatever then don't come on the tour? I mean I don't think
they tell them that. So if he's a טבול יום tvul yom
of a בעל קרי, ba'al keri, okay, now interest in a נדה
niddah would not have the same הלכה, halacha, she would be a
טבול יום tvul yom till nightfall, but we can talk about why,
but for the man who goes during the day it would be.
But anyway, so would a טבול יום tvul yom of בעל קרי
ba'al keri like a טבול יום tvul yom of a זב zav
also be אסור assur to go on הר הבית, Har HaBayit, he'd
be חייב chayav for going on הר הבית? Har HaBayit? So that's
the question of whether טבול יום tvul yom of a זב zav
is כזב kezav or not. And they wanted to infer that the
answer was yes. Why did they want to infer that the answer
was yes? Because it says here you have this זב zav who
had to go to the מקוה mikvah on day seven and it
says on day eight he can come to the לפני אהל מועד,
lifnei ohel moed, which means on day seven he wasn't able to
come לפני אהל מועד, lifnei ohel moed, and therefore you see that
until day eight he's אסור assur to come enter into he's still
has that status and אסור assur to go onto sanctified ground. Yes
Charlie, you had a question? No, he didn't. Okay, fine.
So is it rabbinical that an עם הארץ am ha'aretz is considered
the same as a זב? zav?
Is it rabbinical that an עם הארץ? am ha'aretz? Yeah, but let's
not worry about that about there are other people right that have
different restrictions. But that's not so right, correct. Okay.
ובא לפתח אהל מועד uva l'petach ohel moed is in, where is
that?
Okay, so we're going to get to that. פתח אהל מועד petach
ohel moed might as well sort of discuss it now because it's
going to come up.
Here's your here's the אהל מועד, ohel moed, right, אהל מועד, ohel
moed, which I you know here's the קדש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, okay,
equals the משכן, mishkan, okay. The פתח אהל מועד, petach ohel moed,
right, this opening here actually, right, is so this is equal to
the מקדש, mikdash, okay. Right. This is that right exactly. Then you've
got the whole חצר, chatzer, right, and even the חצר chatzer is
מקום makom is equal to the מקדש. mikdash. Is it? Yes. The
thing that is מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah is all the camps of
the לויים, Levi'im, right? יחנו סביב למשכן אהל מועד Yachanu saviv lemishkan
ohel moed and they're protecting the אהל מועד, ohel moed, right? So
actually the זב, zav, before day before he let's forget before he's
a טבול יום, tvul yom as a זב, zav, not only can't
come לפני אהל מועד, lifnei ohel moed, which is in the חצר
chatzer and is in the מקדש mikdash region, he can't even come
into the מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. So that's going to be a
question later, why does the פסוקים pesukim say only on day eight
come into אהל מועד? ohel moed? I mean before day eight he
couldn't even come to מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. All right, but we're
assuming right now we're not focusing on that right now.
Wait, bring something up פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed is that
the כהן kohen is inside the מחנה שכינה Machaneh Shechinah or whatever
and the person only approaches as far as the edge of the
מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah.
No,
because in the normal מקדש, mikdash, right, in the normal מקדש, mikdash,
right, you had here, right, you had this is like, you know,
you had, you had what do you call it, you had the
עזרת נשים ezrat nashim which was part of הר הבית, Har HaBayit,
so that was מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah together I mean everything was
מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, right? And then you had עזרת ישראל ezrat
Yisrael and then you had
עזרת כהנים ezrat kohanim and all of this is מקום המקדש, makom
hamikdash, okay, all of this. Right, and here you had, right, here
you had the what was the same as the משכן mishkan and
here you had the מזבח, mizbeach, right? But the ישראל Yisrael could
go in for the first like eleven אמות amot and that was
all מקום המקדש. makom hamikdash. So when you bring it פתח אהל
מועד petach ohel moed you don't stand over here. You actually are
able to go into מקום המקדש, makom hamikdash, right? Now obviously you
probably wouldn't go all the way up to here because the מזבח
mizbeach would be here, you know, so what literally פתח אהל מועד
petach ohel moed probably means in front like, you know, present yourself
in front of but not literally right up to, okay. But you
would the same way as a ישראל Yisrael you would bring your
קרבן korban and stand here.
And in the משכן mishkan the מזבח mizbeach was in there, wasn't
it? What? I'm sorry what?
No, the not the מזבח mizbeach of the קרבנות korbanot you can't
have it under under a roof, right?
Oh in the actual משכן mishkan part...
in the משכן, mishkan, right.
Okay, so there's no what's the distinction between inside the אהל מועד
ohel moed and right outside the
אהל מועד?
ohel moed? Inside and right
outside there's another לאו lav of entering in here שלא לצורך עבודה,
shelo letzorach avodah, you know
whatever. But in terms of like the issue about how טהור tahor
you have to be, there's really no difference.
I always thought פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed was like, you
know,
somewhere here, you present yourself in front of the אהל מועד ohel
moed exactly.
But there's another פתח, petach, right? because like you have the little
parts,
like you know you have the whole קלעים kela'im but the חצר
chatzer but you know weren't there several levels you have the part
that you know you had the כתפות ktefot but then even further
along there was yet another one.
No, פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed just means like you present
yourself in front. All right, let's go on. So the גמרא gemara
says like this. All right. So it says like this, עלמא קסבר
טבול יום של זב כזב דמי. Alma kasavar tevul yom shel zav
kezav dam. So that's what we learned from the פסוקים pesukim or
that's what the ברייתא braita is trying to tell us.
הוה אמינא להו אנא, Hav amina lo ana, so I said back
to them,
אלא מעתה, el ama'at, if that's true that's what you can infer
from the
פסוק, pasuk, גבי נזיר טמא נמי כתיב, gabei nazir tamei nami ketiv,
by the נזיר nazir who
became טמא, tamei, יביא שתי תורים אל הכהן אל פתח אהל מועד.
yavish shtei torim el hakohen el petach
ohel moed. He says he does that on day eight, right? So
you say the same thing. אימתי הוא בא? בזמן שטבל ועשה הערב
שמש, Eimatay hu ba? Bizman shetaval ve'asah ha'erev shemesh, say the same
thing here. He has to be totally טהור, tahor, not just here's
the shift. What we're saying until now we said and that whole
discussion Chali asked about can't a טמא tamei person send his קרבן,
korban, the whole point was you have to be totally טהור tahor
you can't be a טבול יום tevul yom, to bring your קרבן.
korban. Now we're saying it's not just you have to be totally
טהור tahor to bring your קרבן korban for you know but you
have to be totally טהור tahor to enter onto the grounds. Okay.
So he said one minute, if that's true, then by the נזיר
nazir also, when it says wait till day eight, it's not just
saying wait till day eight to bring your קרבן, korban, it's saying
wait till day eight for the נזיר nazir to enter the grounds.
But the נזיר nazir is a טומאת מת, tumat meit, and now
he's a טבול יום tevul yom of טומאת מת. tumat meit. טמא
מת Tme meit doesn't have to wait till day eight to enter
into מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah or somebody who's טמא מת tme meit
even when he's a fully טמא מת tme meit can enter into
מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. מכדי שערי ניקנור היכא קיימי? Michtei sha'arei Niknor
Heicha kaimei? בשערי... Besha'arei... Where would this נזיר Nazir go who's טמא?
Tamei? He'd go up to שער ניקנור. Sha'ar Niknor. שער ניקנור Sha'ar
Niknor is the gate that separated between עזרת ישראל Ezras Yisrael and
עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. So the נזיר Nazir is coming, he's coming
only right into the עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, into מחנה לויה. Machaneh
Leviyah.
In the semi-circular stairs there. Yeah, exactly. So... Oh, my source has
a picture.
Okay, fine. Lovely.
Alright, anyways, people. Okay. והתניא ותניא בברייתא, V'hatanya v'itnesha b'raisa, טמא מת
Tamei Meis מותר להיכנס למחנה לויה. Mutar l'hikaenes l'Machaneh Leviyah. Somebody who
touched a dead body can go into מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. ולא
טמא מת בלבד, V'lo Tamei Meis bilvad, not only somebody who touched
a dead body, אלא אפילו מת עצמו, Ella afilu Meis atzmo, you
can a dead body itself can be in מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah,
שנאמר Shene'emar on הר הבית, Har HaBayis, ויקח משה את עצמות יוסף
עמו, Vayikach Moshe es Atzmos Yosef imo, Moshe took the bones of
Yosef with him. מאי עמו? Mai imo? What does it mean with
him? עמו במחיצתו, Imo b'mechitzaso, that they were right there like, you
know, right next to like in his boundary, right, you know, in
his tent. עמו במחנה לויה, Imo b'Machaneh Leviyah, there he was in
מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah and he had the bones of Yosef. So
a dead body itself. So if you read the פסוקים Psukim to
say you have to wait till day eight to allow you to
enter the grounds, that's clearly not true by a נזיר. Nazir. A
נזיר, Nazir, forget that he's a טבול יום tevul yom of טמא
מת Tamei Meis on day seven, even when he was a full
טמא מת Tamei Meis he could have entered into the grounds of
מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. Okay, so therefore that is not a legitimate
read of the פסוקים. Psukim. The פסוקים Psukim might just be saying
you have to wait till day eight to bring your קרבן, Korban,
but not that you have to wait till day eight to enter
onto the ground. Yes.
Bones have the same status as the מת? Meis?
Yes, absolutely. Right, we even learned that yesterday about, you know, עצם
כשעורה Etsem k'seora and about the טומאה Tuma of a כהן Kohen
being טמא Tamei to bones and when is it... yes, the answer
is yes.
This is פתח אהל
מועד?
Pesach
Ohel
Moed?
No, that's the פתח Pesach of the חצר. Chatzer. Oh, this is
the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. The אהל מועד Ohel Moed has an
אהל. Ohel. The אהל מועד Ohel Moed has a tent on top
of it.
So where is פתח אהל מועד Pesach Ohel Moed in here? You
were saying like right... yeah, right. And you say you're allowed to
go to where?
No, but it means anywhere in the חצר Chatzer you're presenting yourself
to פתח אהל מועד. Pesach Ohel Moed. Okay, but actually I should
have drawn this more like
this. That's true.
Okay, yeah, anyway. Yeah, what's this about עצמות חמורים Atzmos chamurim and
that עצמות Atzmos have a different status?
Yeah, but that's... I think I know what you're talking about, but
that's... what about the טומאה Tuma of a כיסוי הקודש? Kisui HaKodesh?
Yeah, but not relevant. We'll talk about it later. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
So clearly we're not talking about the issue of the פסוקים Psukim
is not the issue of entering onto the grounds. Okay, so אלא,
Ella, so rather here's what's going on in the פסוקים. Psukim. Now,
here's there's a slight question about what your גירסא Girsa is, like
whether you have the word לא Lo in it or not. אלא,
Ella, טבול
יום של זב, Tvul yom shel zav, according to תוספות Tosafot and
the ראש, Rosh, the גירסא Girsa is לאו כזב דמי. Lav k'zav
dami. Okay, normally a טבול יום Tvul Yom of a זב zav
would not be a זב zav for under normal circumstances, but here
the guy is more than just a טבול יום. Tvul yom Right,
because what does this זב zav need to get out of his
status of טומאה? Tuma? He needs to go to the מקוה mikvah
on day seven. Even even by day seven, what's left for him
to do? Go to the מקוה, Mikvah wait for nightfall and
bring a קרבן.
Korban. So he is not just a normal טבול יום, Tvul yom.
like the טבול יום Tvul yom, in a way, one of the
reasons it's so light is that everything is done, you just have
to wait for nightfall. You're just waiting. But here a טבול יום
Tvul yom that also has to bring a קרבן Korban the next
day, his status might be seen as not as sort of naturally
transitory.
It needs another act to undo to fully מטהר metaher him.
His waiting is different. His waiting is so that he can bring
the... or he should bring the קרבן. Korban. Right, whereas a טבול
יום Tvul yom is just simply...
well, yeah, but I would say it differently. He will not be
טהור tahor fully until he brings a קרבן. Korban. A normal טבול
יום Tvul yom will be fully טהור tahor if he just waits.
Now, what would be a case of a זב zav who's a
טבול יום Tvul yom that's not also a מחוסר כפורים? mechussar kippurim?
So the answer is a זב zav who only became a זב
zav through seeing twice. The difference between a זב zav who sees
two times and a זב zav who sees three times is at
three times you need to bring a קרבן, Korban, two times you
do not, but either way you're still a זב. zav. So what
the way תוספות Tosafot and the ראש Rosh read this is if
a זב zav saw twice, or we could say if a בעל
קרי, ba'al keri, okay, and the only thing you need is going
to the מקוה Mikvah, and then waiting, okay, so after you've gone
to the מקוה, Mikvah you're לאו כזב דמי, lav k'zav dami, and
if you were to enter into הר הבית, Har HaBayis, you would
not transgress. This guy is different. This guy actually is has a
more the status even after going to the מקוה Mikvah, is is
not as transitory because he has to bring a קרבן Korban the
next day, so for him the story is a little bit different.
Okay.
So what's the distinction between a נזיר Nazir and a מצורע? Metzora?
Well, we'll get to that in a minute, but let's just finish
the point by the זב. zav. Wait, no questions now. I just
have to finish. No questions right now. We'll get to בזמן הזה.
bizman hazeh. I said no questions. Let's take a look. Okay, אלא,
Ella, you'll get your questions in a minute. Let's finish this thought.
טבול יום של זב כזב דמי, Tvul yom shel zav k'zav dami,
ואפילו הכי, v'afilu hachi, even so, כיון דמחוסר כפרה, keivan d'mechussar kapara,
since
again I'm going to read this the way תוספות Tosafot and the
ראש Rosh does it, since this טבול יום Tvul yom is also
a טבול יום tvul yom that needs כפרה kapara the next day,
לא עייל. lo ayil. He cannot go in. Now, of course... Point
is that so in the end אביי Abaye *Abaye* actually is reading
the פסוקים psukim *pesukim* that it's an issue about going in, which
is like very strange. His whole point was to argue and say
the פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim* are not talking about going in because it
wouldn't work by the זב zav *zav*, okay? And now he's sort
of conceding the point but just saying it's a special case here.
It's a special case because he's not just a טבול יום tvul
yom *tvul yom*, he's a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom* that's
a מחוסר כפרה mechusar kaparah, *michusar kapara*. ואי במחנה לויה קאי
*Ve'ei bemachaneh leviyah kai*, now we've got a problem, okay, because what
אביי Abaye, *Abaye* also didn't say and this
is that here, no, no, I'm sorry, I'm sorry. So the other
thing now we're talking about is we're getting back to this question
that if a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom* of a זב
zav *zav* who's מחוסר כפרה mechussar kaparah *michusar kapara* cannot go in
is still like a זב zav, *zav*, then he's not just אסור
asur *assur* in מחנה שכינה Machneh Shechinah, *machaneh shechinah*, he's אסור asur
*assur* in מחנה לויה Machneh Leviyah? *machaneh leviyah*. So why does it
say on day eight come אל פתח אהל מועד el petach ohel
moed, *el petach ohel moed*? Before day eight he couldn't even come
to מחנה לויה Machneh Leviyah. *machaneh leviyah*. So we're reading 'come to
אהל מועד Ohel Moed *ohel moed*' means on day eight then you're
allowed even in מחנה לויה Machneh Leviyah, *machaneh leviyah*. So if that's
what it's saying on day eight you're allowed in מחנה לויה Machneh
Leviyah *machaneh leviyah*, why does it describe it as פתח אהל מועד
petach ohel moed, *petach ohel moed*? So that's what he's saying. Okay,
ואי במחנה לויה קאי אמאי קרי ליה אהל מועד Ohel moed *ve'ei
bemachaneh leviyah kai amai kari leih ohel moed*? למימרא *Leimra* to tell
you מה התם מחוסר כפרה mechussar kaparah לא עייל אף למחנה לויה
נמי מחוסר כפרה mechussar kaparah, לא עייל *ma hatam michusar kapara lo
ayal af lemachaneh leviyah nami michusar kapara lo ayal*. And this is
going to explain, we're getting back to the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*, the
difference between the מצורע *metzora* and the זב zav, *zav*. Because here's
how we learn out that a זב zav, *zav* who is מחוסר
כפרה *michusar kapara* is not allowed, is has a status of a
זב zav *zav* and is not allowed. It's not because the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* says on day eight he may come or because it
says it also by a נזיר nazir. *nazir*, on day eight he
may come and we know a נזיר nazir, *nazir* can come earlier
than day eight. So the פסוקים *pesukim* that say on day eight
he comes and brings his קרבן korban. *korban* is only telling you
you need to wait till he's not a טבול יום tvul yom,
*tvul yom* for the bringing of the קרבן korban *korban*. Those פסוקים
*pesukim* are not telling you what space he's allowed to enter. Those
פסוקים *pesukim* are saying wait till he goes to the מקוה Mikvah
*mikvah*, he's not a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom*, the next
day, no, it is a problem of him being a טבול יום
tvul yom, *tvul yom* like that was the discussion ר' עקיבא ור'
טרפון *Rabbi Akiva veRabbi Tarfon*, but he has to be not a
טבול יום tvul yom, *tvul yom* to have his קרבן korban. *korban*
brought. It's not a question of where he may enter. It's clear
from the זב zav *zav* from the case of the מצורע *metzora*
who can enter the grounds earlier that the waiting is a waiting
to bring your קרבן korban *korban*. So the פסוקים *pesukim* that say
you wait till day eight to come, it's not about coming, it's
about bringing your קרבן korban. *korban*. Okay. But here is how we
learn out that a זב zav *zav* who's מחוסר כפרה *michusar kapara*
is even at is like a זב zav. *zav* and is not
allowed to enter into or is like a זב zav *zav* and
is not allowed to enter into מחנה לויה Machneh Leviyah. *machaneh leviyah*.
Okay? Because it because why does it say he comes to פתח
אהל מועד petach ohel moed, *petach ohel moed* if, now of course
this is a little circular, if part of the issue is that
a זב zav *zav* before you know can't even come into מחנה
לויה Machneh Leviyah. *machaneh leviyah*. Now it's a little circular because we
just said the point is about bringing the קרבן korban *korban* not
where you may enter, but okay. Anyway, but he says we're going
to assume that it's talking about the זב zav. *zav* being in
מחנה לויה Machneh Leviyah. *machaneh leviyah* and it still says come to
פתח אהל מועד petach ohel moed. *petach ohel moed*. Well, why is
it describing it that way? So here's why it's describing it that
way. אמאי קרי ליה אהל מועד *Amai kari leih ohel moed*? למימרא
*Leimra*, this is what tells you, מה התם מחוסר כפרה לא עייל
*ma hatam michusar kapara lo ayal*, the same way somebody who's מחוסר
כפרה *michusar kapara* cannot enter into אהל מועד *ohel moed* even if
you're not a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom*, even if you've
gone to the מקוה mikvah *mikvah* and it's nightfall and it's the
next day and all you're waiting to do is bring your קרבן
korban, *korban*, you cannot enter into מקום המקדש Makom Hamikdash, *mekom hamikdash*
until you've brought your קרבן korban *korban*. אף למחנה לויה נמי מחוסר
כפרה לא עייל *Af lemachaneh leviyah nami michusar kapara lo ayal*. So
therefore even in מחנה לויה Machneh Leviyah, *machaneh leviyah* you cannot enter
in at least if, it's a little funny because here מחוסר כפרה
*michusar kapara* does not mean you haven't brought your קרבן korban. *korban*,
but it means you're טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom* waiting to
bring your קרבן korban, *korban* the next day. Okay? והא מנלן *Veha
minalan*? It's a little complicated, but just, let me finish the sentence
and then I'll go back and unpack it. והא מנלן *Veha minalan*,
where do we know this from? דתניא *Detanya*, טמא יהיה עוד טומאתו
בו *tamei yihyeh od tumato vo*. Okay? He shall be טמא *tamei*
is טומאתו *tumato* with him. טמא יהיה *Tamei yihyeh* לרבות טבול יום
tvul yom *lerabot tvul yom*, עוד טומאתו בו *od tumato vo* לרבות
מחוסר כפרה *lerabot michusar kapara*. So what we learn, what? Right? טמא
יהיה *Tamei yihyeh*. That was by טמא מת *tamei meit*. Okay, so
here's the point, okay?
We know from this פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* טמא יהיה *tamei yihyeh* that
a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom* of anything is אסור asur
*assur* in, right, not a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom*, excuse
me, מחוסר כפרה *michusar kapara* is אסור asur *assur* in מחנה לויה
Machneh Leviyah. *machaneh leviyah*, okay? That we know from טמא יהיה *tamei
yihyeh*. Okay? And certainly and a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom*
and a טבול יום tevul yom *tvul yom*. They're אסור asur *assur*
in, that we know. That we took for granted. The whole question
is a טבול יום tevul yom *tvul yom* of a זב zav
*zav* like a זב zav *zav* was about מחנה לויה Machneh Leviyah?
*machaneh leviyah*, right? Anybody if you're not, let me just make it
simple, if you're not 100 percent טהור *tahor*, you're not allowed in
מקום המקדש Makom haMikdash *mekom hamikdash*, even if you're the weakest טומאה
*tumah* left, טבול יום tevul yom *tvul yom*, מחוסר כפרה *michusar kapara*,
you just have to wait for nightfall, whatever the weakest טומאה *tumah*,
unless you're 100 percent טהור *tahor* you're not allowed in מחנה שכינה
Machneh Shechinah, *machaneh shechinah*. That's fine. Our only question was מחנה לויה
Machneh Leviyah, *machaneh leviyah*. Is a טבול יום tevul yom, of a
זב zav allowed in מחנה לויה? Machneh Leviyah. זב zav is not.
How about a טבול יום tevul yom of a זב, zav right?
That was our question. So now the way we're learning this out
is the פסוקים that say you have to wait till day eight.
That's just talking about bringing your קרבן. korban, They're not emphasizing where
you can enter as we already pointed out by the case of
the נזיר. Nazir But nevertheless, when it says by the זב, it
says on day eight, it says, what does it say? ובא אל
הכהן. uva el hakohen. ובא אל הכהן, uva el hakohen, what we're
saying is that some, again it's a little circular, but what we're
saying is that that is telling us that on day eight he's
entering into that space, okay? Or it's, it's somewhat telling us now,
it's not telling us he was אסור beforehand. That's not true, that's
not implicit, as we pointed out by נזיר, Nazir it's not implied
that he was אסור beforehand. But what it is telling us is
that on day eight he's entering into the space that he wasn't
entering into earlier than that. So here you've got your זב, okay?
And it is telling you that on day eight he stands in
מחנה לויה. Machneh Leviyah, Now you cannot infer from that that he
was אסור beforehand,
that we've already said. But here's what you can infer. Since we
are saying, it's circular 'cause we're, but since we're saying that when
the פסוק says אל פתח אהל מועד, petach ohel moed, it means
מחנה לויה, Machneh Leviyah then we're going to say one minute, why
is it describing מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah as פתח אהל מועד, petach
ohel moed right? This is not פתח אהל מועד, petach ohel moed,
this is פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel moed Why is it describing
it this way? That you should learn out that the same way
a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kipurim is
אסור in מחנה שכינה, Machneh Shechinah, which is פתח אהל מועד, Pesach
ohel moed the זב also as a, early as a טבול יום
tevul yom is also אסור in מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah So we
learn it out by saying the
words פתח אהל מועד Pesach ohel moed don't mean פתח אהל מועד,
Pesach ohel moed. they mean מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah And then what
we learn out from there is that his status is going to
be similar to the issue of going in. The same way he
couldn't go in as a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kipurim as a טבול
יום, tevul yom. he could not go into מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah.
But again here's the trick. Here's the difference, okay? It's complicated. 'Cause
as a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kipurim he can go into מחנה לויה,
Machaneh Leviyah. okay? How do I know that? Because what happens? One
minute. Not in מחנה לויה. Machaneh Leviyah. I should just put... oh.
Not in מחנה שכינה, Machneh Shechinah, okay? This is שכינה, Shechinah, this
is מחנה שכינה, Machneh Shechinah. מחנה מקדש. Machneh Mikdash. I thought it
was מקדש. Mikdash.
מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shechinah.
right, מקדש, Mikdash, okay. How do I know מחוסר כפורים mechusar kipurim
can go into מחנה לויה? Machaneh Leviyah Because that's what everybody does
who has to bring their קרבן korban, on the day eight. They're
מחוסר כפורים, mechusar kipurim, they go into מחנה, Machneh, they go up
to the, they go right up to the door which is מחנה
לויה, right up to מחנה שכינה. He goes right up to the
front door, he hands over his קרבן. korban So of course מחוסר
כפורים mechusar kipurim is allowed in מחנה לויה. So what אביי Abaye
is saying that a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kipurim is not allowed in
מחנה לויה, he means a טבול יום that has to bring his
קרבן korban. the next day, okay? So as, so a מחוסר כפורים
mechusar kipurim himself cannot go here, okay? Since it describes the זב
as if he were here, we're learning out that there's a similar
restriction here, but not to apply to a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kipurim
because that obviously you can go on day eight you go and
you bring your קרבן. korban, To apply to a, to apply to
a טבול יום, not a normal טבול יום, but a טבול יום
who then also has to bring a קרבן korban. the next day.
All right, it's very complicated. Bottom line is is that according to
אביי, the conclusion is that a normal טבול יום of a זב
is not like a זב. And which would have important relevance for
going up to הר הבית Har Habayit nowadays as a טבול יום
of a בעל קרי. baal keri. But I should say that the
conclusion of this גמרא, Gemara, I pointed out to you that I
stuck in the word לאו, lav, right? Argues that it says טבול
יום של זב כזב דמי. tvul yom shel zav kezav dami. So,
and that whole long explanation I just gave if you're left a
little confused, it's because it was not so straight—I mean I hope
I did the best job I could explaining it, but the logic
itself was not so straightforward. So there is a question what actually
the מסקנא maskana is. There is a question how we פוסקן pasken
about טבול יום of a זב and of a בעל קרי. baal
keri. So even though the way we just read it that if
you're not מחוסר כפורים, mechusar kipurim, if you don't have to bring
a קרבן, korban, you're not כזב kezav and you're not like a
בעל קרי baal keri and that would solve the whole מקום המקדש,
Makom haMikdash, the whole הר הבית Har Habayit issue, that's not necessarily
the way that we פוסקן. pasken. Okay. So now, question?
Yeah, so just so I understand in the משכן Mishkan it is,
so מחנה לויה in the משכן Mishkan started after the קלעים, kla'im,
right?
Yeah,
and everything there and that same פתח אהל מועד Pesach ohel moed.
is not the קלעים kla'im because that would be פתח החצר.
petach hachatzar.
Right, and it must be somewhere there we just don't know.
Yeah, exactly.
So if this is not clear, how could anybody go up to
the...
Go up because you have to look at what the ראשונים Rishonim
say and how we פוסקן pasken and either they tell people like
I don't know maybe they're assuming that the I think that they
don't, I think that they're assuming that we
פוסקן pasken that טבול יום of a זב is not like a
זב. But there are other סוגיות sugyot that discuss the same issue
and I think they're just assuming that or hoping that that's not
the case.
Yes, one piece, this piece is missing for me, so someone's a
זב and is not a טבול יום anymore, he's מחוסר כפרה, he
can't...
No, but what
we basically, what we said is, is that a normal מחוסר כפרה
of course can go in מחנה לויה because you go up to
the door of אהל מועד and you give over your קרבן korban,
like here, you go through עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim, you have to
bring your קרבן. korban, Right. So you're מחוסר כפורים. mechussar kippurim. So
how so you bring your קרבן, korban. you're allowed in מחנה לויה
but you're not allowed in מחנה שכינה. Okay. So a מחוסר כפורים
mechussar kippurim and a טבול יום are not allowed here. But of
course a מחוסר כפרה is allowed here. So when אביי says this
זב that is not allowed in מחנה לויה is a מחוסר כפורים,
mechussar kippurim, he doesn't mean a סתם stam מחוסר כפורים mechussar kippurim
on day eight, because of course that זב is allowed. What he
means is a טבול יום who is also a מחוסר כפורים. mechussar
kippurim. A זב who is a טבול יום and that's not just
a טבול יום, you have to wait for nightfall and a קרבן,
korban, that you're not allowed in מחנה לויה. A normal טבול יום
is, a normal מחוסר כפורים mechussar kippurim is, but a טבול יום
who has two steps to go through, nightfall and a קרבן, that's
the guy who is not allowed here. What? Well, depends exactly how
you do it. Yeah. Okay. So now that we will now move
on.
Okay. Or not. Yes.
What would be the surrogate for the קרבן that one would have
to bring?
There wouldn't. Potentially we don't assume that anybody is a זב of
three ראיות. re'iyot. Okay. The question would be, okay, and if somebody
would be and you wouldn't need to, you just wouldn't need to
not be a
טבול יום. You couldn't go into מקום המקדש Makom haMikdash but you
could go on הר הבית Har haBayit like a woman who is
a יולדת yoledes needs to bring a קרבן. Okay. But even if
she goes to the מקוה and doesn't bring a קרבן, she's fine,
she's a מחוסר כפרה, she's not allowed in מקום המקדש, Makom haMikdash.
but she's still allowed in מחנה לויה. The same way if we're
all טמאי מת, temei meis, we're not allowed in מקום המקדש Makom
HaMikdash and we're allowed in מחנה לויה. The idea of going to
הר הבית Har haBayit is going on הר הבית, Har haBayit, מחנה
לויה without going into מקום המקדש. Okay. So let's take a look
now at the next משנה. mishnah. Okay, now it's a lot easier.
תגלחת הטהרה כיצד? Tiglachat hataharah keitzad? Now it's purely just the steps
you go through through the ritual. What is the ritual of the
shaving for at the end of the, at the end of the
thirty days of נזירות nezirut at the end of the whole process?
היה מביא ג' בהמות,
Haya meivi
gimel behemot, three animals. חטאת עולה ושלמים. Chatat Olah uShelamim. Okay, the
תורה Torah says, ושחט את השלמים
ומגלח עליהם. veshachat et hashelamim umigaleach aleihem. Now when the תורה Torah
says you bring the animal, it says, it says you bring the
חטאת, Chatat, you bring the עולה, Olah, you bring the שלמים, Shelamim,
and then it says וגלח את כל שערו, vegillach et kol se'aro,
okay, and he shaves. And then it says he also takes the
hair and he puts it under the pot that's cooking the שלמים.
Shelamim. Okay, so the משנה mishnah says, what which one are you
מגלח עליו, migaleach alav, like conceptually connect the, which of the קרבנות
korbanot are you shaving on? Somehow conceptually connect the act of shaving
to the bringing of a קרבן. That's not clear in the פסוקים.
It doesn't say you bring this קרבן, you bring this קרבן, you
bring this קרבן, and then it says and then you shave. Okay,
what it does say is you use the hair to cook underneath
the pot. It doesn't somehow connect the act of shaving with the
ritual of bringing the קרבן. He already brought the קרבנות. korbanot. Well
yeah and he has it like sequential after the קרבן, then you
shave. But conceptually the משנה mishnah links it. So it says you
שחט shacht the שלמים Shelamim and then the shaving somehow takes place
together with that. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. עליהם Aleihem is
on all the קרבנות. korbanot. Well
that's a good
point. On שלמים. Shelamim. Yeah, that's a good point. That's a good
point. So okay, we're going to in the end interpret that he
specifically connects it to the שלמים, Shelamim, but you're right, the grammar
here may suggest all of them. Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר לא היה
מגלח אלא על החטאת שהחטאת קודמת בכל מקום. Rabbi Eliezer omer lo
haya migaleach ela al hachatat shehachatat kodemet bechol makom. No, whenever you
have a list of קרבנות korbanot to bring you always bring the
חטאת chatat first, and therefore you do it with the חטאת. chatat.
Now who says just because it comes first? Who says you shave
with it, right? I mean the פסוקים say, yes you bring the
חטאת chatat first but have you shave with the שלמים Shelamim last.
And if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says,
and תוספות Tosafot reads עליהם, aleihem, I think שלמים Shelamim is plural,
right? Exactly. You can't say שלמים Shelamim in the singular, עליה, aleiha,
right? שלמים Shelamim is לשון רבים, lashon rabbim, it's like pants. Exactly,
עליהם. aleihem. So it's more than one. Yeah. So תוספות Tosafot interestingly
assumes that according to the opinion that you're shaving on the שלמים,
Shelamim, that you're also bringing the שלמים Shelamim first. That the, that
the first opinion assumes the same logic as רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
that if you're shaving with it you're bringing it first. But there's
nothing in the משנה mishnah that indicates that. Anyway רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says if you bring the חטאת chatat first you shave with
it. ואם גלח על אחת משלשתן יצא. Ve'im gilach al achat mishloshtan
yatza. But of course that's just לכתחילה. l'chatchila. בדיעבד B'diavad whichever one
you shaved with you're יוצא, yotzei, whichever order you did it in.
רבן גמליאל אומר הביא ג' בהמות ולא פירש. Rabban Gamliel omer heivi
gimel behemot velo peireish. He brought three בהמות, behemot, he said I'm
sanctifying these animals for my קרבנות. korbanot. He didn't say which animal
is which. So הראויה לחטאת תקרב חטאת לעולה תקרב עולה לשלמים תקרב
שלמים. ha'ra'uya l'chatat tikarev chatat l'olah tikarev olah l'shelamim tikarev shelamim. So
the קדושה kedusha sort of just winds up defining itself, each animal
is different. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, this
one line תוספות Tosafot at the bottom, הראויה לחטאת. ha'ra'uya l'chatat. כשבה
*kisbah*, לעולה כבש *l'olah keves*, לשלמים איל *l'shlamim ayil*. So if you
bring three different animals and you say these are all my קרבנות
*korbanot* for נזיר Nazir *nazir*, it'll sort itself out which is קדוש
*kadosh* for which. Fine. Let's take a look at the גמרא *Gemara*.
תנו רבנן *Tanu Rabbanan*: וגילח הנזיר פתח
אהל מועד
V'gilach hanazir
pesach ohel moed, *V'gilach hanazir pesach ohel moed*. בשלמים הכתוב מדבר *Bishlamim
hakatuv medaber*. שנאמר *Shene'emar*: ושחטו פתח אהל מועד Pesach ohel moed, *U'shchato
pesach ohel moed*. Oh well, there actually it is singular, but that
might be because it's זבח השלמים *Zevach Hashlamim*, so might I don't
know, it's a good question. Anyway, okay, so anyway right before it
says you shecht the שלמים Shlamim. *shlamim*, and then the פסוק *pasuk*
after the שלמים Shlamim. *shlamim* is the shaving, so there the פסוקים
*pesukim* it juxtaposes the שלמים Shlamim. *shlamim* with the shaving. את אומר
בשלמים הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא לפתח אהל מועד ממש Mamash *At
omer bishlamim hakatuv medaber o eino ela lipesach ohel moed mamash*? Now,
one minute, maybe when it says ושחטו פתח אהל מועד Pesach ohel
moed *U'shchato pesach ohel moed*, okay, and then it says וגילח הנזיר
*V'gilach hanazir*, oh, excuse me, I misread it. It is not the
juxtaposition of ושחטו *U'shchato* with וגילח *V'gilach*, which is also true. It
is the linking of the words פתח Pesach. אהל מועד *pesach ohel
moed*. Okay. By the נזיר Nazir *nazir* it says וגילח פתח אהל
מועד *V'gilach pesach ohel moed*, and by the שלמים Shlamim *shlamim* it
says ושחטו *U'shchato*, because this is not the שלמים Shlamim *shlamim* of
the נזיר Nazir *nazir*. ושחטו פתח אהל מועד *U'shchato pesach ohel moed*
is just the way in the beginning of ויקרא *Vayikra*, the פסוק
*pasuk* about the שלמים Shlamim. *shlamim*. So I'm sorry, I misread it.
What it's actually saying is is that since the shaving of the
נזיר Nazir *nazir* is described as פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed*
and the שלמים *shlamim* when they're brought is described as being brought
פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed*, it is telling you that the
shaving of the נזיר *nazir* is an act connected with the ritual
of the bringing of the שלמים *shlamim* which has this אהל מועד
*ohel moed* concept. Okay. By the way, להלכה *lehalacha*, there's הלכה *halacha*
we learn out from the שלמים *shlamim* it says פתח אהל מועד
*pesach ohel moed*, that if the אהל מועד *ohel moed*'s doors are
locked, okay, that the שלמים *shlamim* and even if it's after daybreak,
then you shecht the שלמים *shlamim*, it's פסול Pasul, *pasul*, okay, because
it says פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed*. So there's actually a
conceptual emphasis of the שלמים *shlamim* being פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel
moed* that we find more than the other קרבנות *korbanot*. So if
it describes... Yes, and we might learn the קרבנות *korbanot* from שלמים
*shlamim*, but conceptually there's a link of פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel
moed* with שלמים *shlamim*. So if it describes the shaving of the
נזיר *nazir* פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed*, we're saying that is
a way of describing that it takes place with the שלמים *shlamim*.
Okay? את אומר בשלמים הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא לפתח אהל מועד
ממש Mamash *At omer bishlamim hakatuv medaber o eino ela lipesach ohel
moed mamash*? Who says? Maybe all the פסוק *pasuk* means to say
is you actually do the shaving פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed*,
okay, which now we see פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed* literally
would be ממש *mamash* like in מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash*, right? It
wouldn't be over here, right? It would actually be over here, which
actually would be funny because the נזיר *nazir* wouldn't be allowed, he'd
be מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim*, he wouldn't even be allowed there, okay.
But anyway, which the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* doesn't, which the גמרא *Gemara*
doesn't discuss, ironically, because we just discussed that a מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar
kippurim* isn't allowed there. But anyway, ah well, I guess he might
not be מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim* because, oh wait wait, he could
have brought his earlier קרבנות *korbanot* and just not brought the שלמים
*shlamim*. That would be the case. He would bring one קרבן *korban*,
which would be enough to... oh wait wait, he's a נזיר טהור
*nazir tahor*, excuse me, he's not a נזיר טמא *nazir tamei*. He's
not מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim*. He's totally טהור *tahor*. So he actually
would be allowed in מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash*. It's a נזיר *nazir*
after thirty days. He's allowed in מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash*. Maybe it
means he goes in the מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash* and does the
shaving ממש *mamash* in מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash*, in עזרת ישראל *Ezrat
Yisrael*. Maybe it literally means פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed*. Okay?
So as opposed to linking it to the שלמים *shlamim*. Okay. או
אינו אלא פתח אהל מועד ממש *O eino ela pesach ohel moed
mamash*? אמרת אם כן דרך ביזיון הוא *Amarta im ken derech bizayon
hu*. No, clearly the פסוק *pasuk* doesn't literally mean פתח אהל מועד
*pesach ohel moed*. That's disrespectful to the מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash*. So
if it says פתח אהל מועד *pesach ohel moed*, it means together
with the שלמים *shlamim*. Where would he actually be getting shaved? רבי
יאשיה... we're going to discuss that in the next משנה Mishnah: *mishna*.
רבי יאשיה אומר אינו צריך הרי אמר תורה *Rabbi Yoshaya omer eino
tzarich harei amar Torah*: לא תעלה במעלות על מזבחי *Lo ta'aleh b'maalot
al mizbachi*. קל וחומר דרך ביזיון *Kal v'chomer derech bizayon*. If even
in the עבודה *avodah* you have to have a ramp so that
the כהן *kohen* doesn't, you know, step לא תגלה ערותך עליו *lo
tigaleh ervatcha alav*,
that's seen as not respectful, the sort of stepping, which I mean
you got a tunic going down to the floor and even so
that little somehow potential exposure is not respectful even דרך עבודה *derech
avodah*, how much more so would we not allow shaving to take
place on Temple grounds itself, on מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash* itself? So
clearly the פסוקים *pesukim* mean something else. They don't mean פתח אהל
מועד *pesach ohel moed*, they mean together with the שלמים *shlamim*. Now
interestingly in the brackets here we have clearly this is not in
the original גירסא *girsa*, some editor put in נוסח אחר במדרש בפרשת
נשא *Nosach acher b'Midrash b'parashat Naso*. וגילח הנזיר רבי יאשיה אומר בשלמים
הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא אם כן אמרה תורה לא תעלה קל
וחומר דברי שלא יגולח פתח אהל מועד אלא בשלמים הכתוב מדבר *V'gilach
hanazir Rabbi Yoshaya omer bishlamim hakatuv medaber o eino ela im ken
amrah torah lo ta'aleh kal v'chomer divrei shelo yigolach pesach ohel moed
ela bishlamim hakatuv medaber*. Okay, same point, it's just a different version
of it. דף רמב *Daf resh-mem-bet*. דף רמב *Daf resh-mem-bet*. רבי יצחק
אומר אינו צריך הרי אומר *Rabbi Yitzchak omer eino tzarich harei omer*:
ולקח את שער ראש נזרו ונתן על האש *V'lakach et se'ar rosh
nizro v'natan al ha'esh*. Okay, so you take the hair and you
put it on the fire. מי שאינו מחוסר אלא לקיחה ונתינה *Mi
she'eino mechusar ela lekicha u'netina*. All you gotta do is take the
hair and put it on the fire. יצא זה שמחוסר לקיחה הבאה
ונתינה *Yatza zeh shemechusar lekicha hava'ah u'netina*. If you shave here, you're
not cooking your שלמים *shlamim* here. You're cooking your שלמים *shlamim*, you
know, out here in the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim, *Ezrat Nashim* or
you're cooking it somewhere in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. So if you so
if you're shaving here, you have to shave and then bring it
to where your שלמים *shlamim* is. And the תורה *Torah* suggests that
you shave and you immediately put it where your שלמים *shlamim* is,
so clearly you're not in the מקום המקדש *Makom HaMikdash*. Wait, wait,
so you're saying you're shaving outside of מקום מקדש. Mikdash Some place
outside. In עזרת נשים, Ezras Nashim ירושלים. Yerushalayim? That's where you're shaving
and that's where you're cooking your שלמים. Okay, now למעשה L'maise there
actually was, just to not ruin the surprise, a לשכת נזירים, Lishkas
Nezirim, I forget which which of these corners it was, but one
of these things was was the לשכת נזירים Lishkas Nezirim where they
did their shaving and cooking of the שלמים. They actually had a
room in the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim, for their shaving and cooking
of the שלמים. No part of שלמים is ever put on the
מזבח? Mizbeach? The אימורים. Emurim. Yeah, and the דם. Dam. Right, and
then you take the meat. Right. תוספתא Tosefta says וגילח הנזיר פתח
אהל מועד, now it wasn't done פתח אהל מועד to tell you
because it's וגילח על השלמים V'gilach al hashlamim which is פתח. Exactly.
That's how we're reading it. Okay, let's just finish up to the
next משנה. Mishnah Okay, משנה: מי שנשתלח לקיחה ונתינה יצא זה שמשתלח
לקיחה ונתינה. Mi shenishtalach lekicha unetina yatza ze shemishtalach lekicha unetina. איכא
דאמרי Ika d'amri רבי יצחק אומר בשלמים הכתוב מדבר אתה אומר בשלמים
הכתוב מדבר או אינו אלא פתח אהל מועד ממש? Rabbi Yitzchak omer
b'shlamim hakasuv medaber atah omer b'shlamim hakasuv medaber o eino ela pesach
ohel moed mamash? תלמוד לומר ולקח את שער ראש נזרו. Talmud lomar
v'lakach es sa'ar rosh nizro. מקום שהוא מבשל שם היה מגלח. Makom
shehu mevashel sham hayah megale'ach. Basically the same דרשה. Drasha. Okay, he
takes it immediately, so it's the same place where he's doing the
cooking. אבא חנן אומר משום רבי אליעזר וגילח הנזיר פתח אהל מועד
כל זמן שאין פתח אהל מועד פתוח אינו מגלח. Abba Chanan omer
mishum Rabbi Eliezer v'gilach hanazir pesach ohel moed kol zman she'ein pesach
ohel moed pasuach eino megale'ach. So similar to the idea that if
you bring a שלמים if the doors have not yet been opened,
it's פסול, if you actually did your shaving with the doors when
the doors weren't open, it would be an invalid shaving. So he
at least says, I don't have to read the words פתח אהל
מועד as a complete just metaphor for saying with the שלמים. Okay,
what it means is when the אהל מועד is open, wherever you
are, even if you're in the עזרת נשים, if the doors are
open, you're פתח אהל מועד. Okay, but if the doors are closed,
you're not פתח אהל מועד. So it's a little closer to a
literal reading of the פסוק than purely symbolic. Okay. רבי שמעון שזורי
אומר וגילח הנזיר פתח אהל מועד ולא נזירה. Rabbi Shimon Shizuri omer
v'gilach hanazir pesach ohel moed v'lo nezira. Okay, now here we're moving
away from the פתח אהל מועד, there's a totally different דרשה. Drasha.
נזיר ולא נזירה. Nazir v'lo nezira. A woman would not do it
in the same environs. Okay, why? שמא יתגרו בה פרחי כהונה Shema
yisgaru ba pirchei kehuna because there her hair is uncovered, so the
young כהנים Kohanim are looking at her and they're having these sexual
urges. Now is he saying that an actual נזיר would be in
the courtyard or he's saying no, a נזיר would be here, would
be this type of פתח אהל מועד and a נזירה Nezira would
be would be off somewhere in ירושלים? Yerushalayim. That's what תוספות Tosfos
assumes. Okay, if you look at תוספות, Tosfos, he says ולא נזירה
משמע דטעמא דקרא שמא יתגרו בה פרחי כהונה אם תגלח פתח אהל
מועד ממש אלא במדינה תגלח במקום צנוע. V'lo nezira mashma d'ta'ama d'kra
shema yisgaru ba pirchei kehuna im tigalach pesach ohel moed mamash ela
b'medina tigalach b'makom tzanua. So presumably the נזיר is somewhere here where
there are still פרחי כהונה Pirchei kehuna running around and a נזירה
Nezira is somewhere off somewhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, אמרו לו Amru
lo we're going to see in the next משנה that about shaving
outside of the מקדש completely, shaving in ירושלים. אמרו לו לדבריך סוטה
תוכיח, Amru lo l'devarecha sotah tochi'ach, one minute. Obviously we allow כהנים
Kohanim to see a woman with her hair uncovered. How about the
case of the סוטה? Sotah? דכתיב והעמידה לפני ה' ולא חיישינן שמא
יתגרו בה פרחי כהונה. Dichsiv v'he'emidah lifnei Hashem v'lo chashinan shema yisgaru
ba pirchei kehuna. We're not afraid of that. אמר להן זו כוחלת
ופוקסת, Amar lahen zu kocheles u'pokeses, no. This נזירה, Nezira, she's got
her makeup on. She looks nice. Okay, so we're afraid more about
their sexual urges. זו אינה כוחלת ופוקסת, Zu eina kocheles u'pokeses, the
סוטה Sotah is being disheveled and you know and being going through
this you know this degrading process. It's like a type of like
eyeshadow whatever. I don't know, there are different types of makeup. Okay,
anyway it might or might also be hair. Anyway, so one looks
nice and the other does not and therefore what does Seinfeld say?
Anyway, it is a black-blue color from the mineral stibnite. פוקסת? Pokeses?
כוחלת. Kocheles. Okay anyway בקיצור, B'kitzer, so account you could read this
to say that the נזיר ממש does it here because that's where
the כהנים Kohanim are and a נזירה Nezira does it here, but
we've never seen anybody that says that a נזיר ממש does it
here so תוספות Tosfos is reading it that a נזיר does it
here and the נזירה Nezira does it somewhere off-ground. Okay we will
continue tomorrow and see the rest of where the shaving can take
place in מקום המקדש or elsewhere.