Welcome to today's דף daf and שנה טובה. shana tova.
Today's דף daf is פ. Pey. We pick up where we're behind
by an עמוד. amud. We pick up on עט עמוד ב Ayin-Tet
Amud Bet
and we pick up with there's a debate between רב Rav and
רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, excuse me, רב Rav and רב כהנא Rav
Kahana about what happens if the ציבור tzibur is exactly fifty-fifty, what
is the status of whether you do this פסח בטומאה Pesach Bi-Tumah
or not?
And רב Rav says פלגא ופלגא palgoh u-palgoh is like רוב. rov.
הללו עושין לעצמן והללו עושין לעצמן. hallalu osin le-atzman ve-hallalu osin le-atzman.
Each one does its own, each half does its own. And רב
כהנא Rav Kahana says it doesn't count as רוב rov with two
variations within רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. So let's take a look as
the גמרא Gemara continues. The גמרא Gemara says like this: תנן, Tnan,
two lines, three lines from the top, פ עמוד ב. Pey Amud
Bet. Let's see whether we can try to infer from our משנה.
Mishnah. Of course our משנה Mishnah has the classic problem a lot
of משניות mishnayot have, which is the problem of the excluded middle,
that they talk about the case of a רוב rov and a
מיעוט miut and they don't talk about the case of fifty-fifty. So
let's see which way that implies according to the debate of רב
Rav and רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. נטמא הקהל או רובו, Nitmaka hakahal
o rubo, if the entire congregation or the majority became טמא, tamei,
או שהיו הכהנים טמאים והקהל טהורים, o she-hayu hakohanim tme'im ve-hakahal tehorim,
or the כהנים kohanim were טמא tamei and everybody else was טהור,
tahor, יעשה בטומאה. ya'aseh bi-tumah. You do it in טומאה. tumah. So
that suggests only רוב. rov. רובו הוא דעבדי בטומאה, Rubo hu de-avdi
bi-tumah, only with a majority טמא tamei do you do it in
טומאה, tumah, אבל פלגא ופלגא, aval palgoh u-palgoh, the implication is if
it was exactly fifty-fifty, לא
עבדי בראשון, lo avdi be-rishon, you would not do it בטומאה. bi-tumah.
So that would sound like only you need a majority. קשיא לרב.
Kashya le-Rav. It's a difficulty to רב Rav who says that even
if it's fifty-fifty
the טהורים tehorim still do it בטהרה, bi-taharah, but the טמאים tme'im
are allowed to do it
בראשון. be-rishon. So אמר לך רב, amar lach Rav, רב Rav will
say back to you: No, רוב, rov, if
you have a majority then עבדי כולהו בטומאה. avdi kulu bi-tumah. That
defines the entire community and everybody is allowed to do it בטומאה.
bi-tumah. פלגא ופלגא, Palgoh u-palgoh, if it's exactly fifty-fifty, so הללו עושין
לעצמן והללו עושין לעצמן. hallalu osin le-atzman ve-hallalu osin le-atzman.
That's what רב Rav would say. The fifty percent that's טהור tahor
does it by themselves. They're not allowed to become טמא. tamei. They're
not defined by the טמאים. tme'im. But the טמאים tme'im are not
pushed off to פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So yes, you need a
majority for everybody to do בטומאה. bi-tumah. Fifty percent each half does
by its on its own. The גמרא Gemara says you know what?
הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, that actually makes sense that that's
a good read of the משנה. Mishnah. דקתני סיפא, De-ktani seifa, the
end of the משנה Mishnah says: נטמא מיעוט
הקהל. Nitma miut hakahal. If it's the minority, again skipping over the
fifty percent case, if it's the minority, טהורין עושין את הראשון וטמאים
עושין את השני. tehorin osin et harishon u-tme'im osin et hasheni. The
טהור tahor people do פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, the טמא tamei people
do פסח שני Pesach Sheni because they're a minority. So מיעוט הוא
דעבדי בשני. Miut hu de-avdi be-sheni. This works perfectly according to רב.
Rav. Only if they're a minority do they do the פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. אבל פלגא ופלגא, Aval palgoh u-palgoh, if it's exactly fifty-fifty,
לא, lo,
then they wouldn't wait till the פסח שני Pesach Sheni and ועבדי
בראשון ve-avdi be-rishon and they do the פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. הללו
עושין לעצמן והללו עושין לעצמן. hallalu osin le-atzman ve-hallalu osin le-atzman. Each
group would do it by itself. So actually the משנה, Mishnah, although
it skips over the case of fifty-fifty, can be read very easily
according to רב. Rav. You need a majority for everybody to do
בטומאה. bi-tumah. If it's a minority then the טמא tamei people go
פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. The case not addressed is fifty-fifty because then
each half does it by themselves. ואלא קשיא לרב
כהנא. Ve-ella kashya le-Rav Kahana. So our משנה Mishnah is difficult to
רב כהנא Rav Kahana because רב כהנא Rav Kahana says if it's
fifty-fifty
then the טמאים tme'im do it on פסח שני Pesach Sheni or
they don't do it at all, and our משנה Mishnah says that
you need it to be a מיעוט miut for the טמאים tme'im
to do it on פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So אמר לך רב
כהנא: amar lach Rav Kahana: נטמאו מיעוט הקהל. Nitmata miut hakahal. No,
here's why the משנה Mishnah gives the example of the minority that
are טמא. tamei. If it's the minority that's טמא, tamei, then טהורין
עושין את הראשון וטמאים עושין את השני. tehorin osin et harishon u-tme'im
osin et hasheni. That's when
it's
as the משנה Mishnah says, the טהור tahor people do it on
the ראשון, rishon, the טמא tamei people on the שני. sheni. פלגא
ופלגא, Palgoh u-palgoh, if it's exactly fifty-fifty, טהורין עושין את
הראשון, tehorin osin et harishon, then the טהור tahor people would do
it on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, of course, אבל טמאים, aval tme'im,
but the טמאים, tme'im, the impure people, אינם עושים לא רב ראשון
ולא שני. einam osin lo rishon ve-lo sheni.
They wouldn't do it either time. Okay? Because as we said before,
since they're not the majority they don't do פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon,
since they're not a minority they don't do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
So the משנה Mishnah can read fine according to רב כהנא's Rav
Kahana second approach. That's why the, why does the משנה Mishnah say
if it's a minority they do it on פסח שני? Pesach Sheni?
Because if it's fifty percent טמא, tamei, they lose out both ways.
They're not enough to do a פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they're too
much to do a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So the גמרא Gemara
says good. התינח ללישנא בתרא דרב כהנא, Hateinach le-lishna batra de-Rav Kahana,
that's good according to version two of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. אלא
להך לישנא, Ella le-hach lishna, but according to the version one דאמר
רב כהנא, de-amar Rav Kahana, that רב כהנא Rav Kahana says that
even if it's fifty-fifty טהורין עושין את הראשון וטמאים עושין את השני,
tehorin osin et harishon u-tme'im osin et hasheni, that even in a
fifty-fifty case the טהור tahor people do it on the first פסח,
Pesach, the טמא tamei people, the other fifty percent, do it on
the second פסח. Pesach. מאי איכא למימר? Mai ika le-meimar? What can
you say? Why did the משנה Mishnah say that when the טמא
tamei people are a מיעוט miut they do it during פסח שני?
Pesach Sheni? The משנה Mishnah should have said even when the טמא
tamei people are fifty percent they do it on פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. according to version one of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. So אמר
לך רב כהנא, Amar lach Rav Kahana. so רב כהנא Rav Kahana,
would say back to you, הוא הדין דאפילו פלגא ופלגא נמי. ihu
ha-din de-afilu palgo u-palgo nami. You know what? Even if it was
fifty-fifty, the דין din at the end of the משנה Mishnah would
be true. נמי, nami, טהורין עושין את הראשון וטמאין עושין את השני,
tehorin osin et ha-rishon u-tmeiin osin et ha-sheni, it would be the
same הלכה. halakha. והא דקתני מיעוט הקהל, ve-hai di-ktani miut ha-kahal,
so why does the משנה Mishnah say that when a minority is
טמא, tamei, they do פסח שני? Pesach Sheni? It should have said
even if it's fifty percent טמא tamei they do פסח שני Pesach
Sheni according to רב כהנא. Rav Kahana So he would tell you,
you know what, you're really right. It's being a little imprecise. אגב
דתני רישא רובא, agav de-tani reisha ruba, since the first part of
the משנה Mishnah says when it's a majority,
that's when it's a פסח בטומאה, Pesach be-tumah, and there it's only
if it's a majority, that if fifty percent of the טמא tamei
people don't impact the פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. So since in order
to tell you that when is it true that the פסח ראשון
Pesach Rishon you do it בטומאה be-tumah is when it's a majority,
תנא נמי סיפא מיעוטא. tena nami seifa miuta. So the—so we skip
over the middle case, and the end says minority. So everybody agrees
that there's no problem with the beginning of the משנה. Mishnah. The
beginning of the משנה Mishnah says when the majority are טמא, tamei,
you do—it's a פסח Pesach which is done בטומאה. be-tumah. Everybody agrees
you need the majority, even רב Rav that says when it's fifty
percent, that fifty percent can do פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, it would
not affect the rest of the people. The scenario where everybody is
allowed to do it בטומאה be-tumah requires a majority to be טמא.
tamei. Why does the end of the משנה Mishnah say if a
minority is טמא, tamei, you do a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, which
suggests that if it's fifty percent you don't do פסח שני? Pesach
Sheni? That's a problem to רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. So he's going
to say, yeah, it's true, fifty percent also does פסח שני, Pesach
Sheni, the טמאין tmeiin people. The reason it said minority, it's contrast
it to—is, you know, to contrast it to the first case of
majority, but it really would be true that even fifty percent would
do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Okay, so therefore the משנה Mishnah can
read with—according to all three approaches: רב Rav and the two versions
of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to
say we have three different ברייתות, beraitot, and each ברייתא beraita supports
a different version of the three versions we have laid out. תניא
כוותיה דרב, tanya kevata de-Rav, we have a ברייתא beraita that supports
רב, Rav, תניא כוותיה דרב כהנא, tanya kevata de-Rav Kahana, a ברייתא
beraita that supports רב כהנא, Rav Kahana. ותניא כתרי לישני, ve-tanya ke-trei
lishne, according to both versions of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, we have
three different ברייתות, beraitot, each ברייתא beraita supports a different version of
the ones we laid out.
תניא כוותיה דרב, tanya kevata de-Rav, we taught a ברייתא beraita that
supports רב: Rav: הרי שהיו ישראל מחצה טהורין ומחצה טמאין. harei she-hayu
Yisrael mechetza tehorin u-mechetza tmeiin. Israel were—the Jewish people were half טהור
tahor half טמא, tamei, exactly the case we're debating. הללו עושין לעצמן
והללו עושין לעצמן, halalu osin le-atzman ve-halalu osin le-atzman, says just like
רב, Rav, the fifty percent טהור tehor do on their own and
the fifty percent טמא tamei do on their own. The fact that
they're fifty percent טמא tamei is enough to allow them to do
פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. It's enough considered a קהל, kahal, but it's
not enough to define the טהור tehor people. Okay, תניא כלישנא קמא
דרב כהנא, tanya ke-lishna kama de-Rav Kahana, now we taught like version
one of רב כהנא: Rav Kahana, הרי שהיו ישראל מחצה טהורין ומחצה
טמאין, harei she-hayu Yisrael mechetza tehorin u-mechetza tmeiin, it was fifty-fifty. טהורין
עושין את הראשון וטמאין עושין את השני, tehorin osin et ha-rishon u-tmeiin
osin et ha-sheni, simple, the טהור tehor people do the פסח ראשון
Pesach Rishon and the טמא tamei people, since they're not a majority,
they're treated as a minority and they do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
That's version one of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana: ותניא כלישנא בתרא דרב
כהנא, ve-tanya ke-lishna batra de-Rav Kahana, and now we have a ברייתא
beraita that supports version two of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana. which is
the more חידוש: chiddush: הרי שהיו ישראל מחצה טהורין ומחצה טמאין, harei
she-hayu Yisrael mechetza tehorin u-mechetza tmeiin, they were fifty-fifty. טהורין עושין את
הראשון, tehorin osin et ha-rishon, טהור tehor people do the first פסח,
Pesach, of course, וטמאין, ve-tmeiin, and the טמא tamei people that are
neither big enough to be considered the קהל kahal nor small enough
to be considered a minority, fall exactly between the two categories: אינן
עושין לא את הראשון ולא את השני. einan osin lo et ha-rishon
ve-lo et ha-sheni. They don't do the פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon because
they're not the majority, they don't do פסח שני Pesach Sheni because
they're not a minority. Okay, very nice, so it seems good, we
can put this whole issue to rest. Three different opinions, three different
ברייתות. beraitot. But the גמרא Gemara is not satisfied, because since we
have a debate of אמוראים Amoraim and we have ברייתות beraitot that
support each one, presumably as an אמורא Amora you don't want any
תנאי Tannaic source to go against you. So for every one opinion
here, you've got one תנאי Tannaic source that agrees with you and
two that disagree with you. So now we're going to have to
go through the process of explaining how everybody can reconcile the contradictory
ברייתות, beraitot, rather than just saying, you know, it's a three-way מחלוקת
אמוראים, machloket Amoraim, three-way מחלוקת תנאים, machloket Tannaim, each אמורא Amora is
going to try to get their position to be consistent with all
three ברייתות, beraitot, even the two that seem to clearly contradict them.
So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: לרב, le-Rav, first wide line or middle-sized
line,
according to רב, Rav, וללישנא בתרא דרב כהנא u-le-lishna batra de-Rav Kahana
and version two of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, okay, how do they
deal with the ברייתא beraita that supports version one of רב כהנא?
Rav Kahana, הא דתניא, ha di-tanya, the ברייתא beraita that says: טהורין
עושין את הראשון וטמאין עושין את השני, tehorin osin et ha-rishon u-tmeiin
osin et ha-sheni, simple הלכה, halakha, if it's fifty-fifty, then the טהור
tehor people do the first פסח Pesach and the טמא tamei people
do the second, how does that work? According to רב, Rav, the
טמא tamei people should be doing the first, and according to version
two of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana? the טמא tamei people should be
doing neither. So what do you do with the ברייתא beraita that
says the טמא tamei people do the שני? sheni? היכי מתרצי לה,
heichi matretzei lah, how can they, as we would say in yeshivish
language,
טייטש teitch up that ברייתא? beraita? Gotta get a good English word
for that. How do they answer up that
ברייתא? beraita? כגון, kegon, here would be the scenario that רב Rav
and version two of רב כהנא Rav Kahana, would say. 50% טמא
tamay would do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. What would be the scenario?
כגון שהיו ישראל מחצה טהורים ומחצה טמאים, kegon shehayu Yisroel mechtzah tehorim
u-mechtzah tme'im, as it explains it's 50-50, 50% טהור, tahor, 50% טמא.
tamay. But here's what makes the case that tells you that the
טמא tamay people do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. ונשים משלימות לטמאים, ve-nashim
mashlimot le-tme'im, what gets you to be 50% טמא tamay is because
you counted the women's vote. Okay, so this is going to be
a whole discussion about women's suffrage. Not really, but okay. Basically the
issue is, are women obligated in the פסח? Pesach? And there are
a whole range of opinions. There's some opinions that say women are
obligated in the פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, and if they couldn't make
a פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they bring a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
There are those that say women are obligated in פסח ראשון, Pesach
Rishon, but if they didn't bring a פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they
don't bring a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. And there's those that, we'll
see later, it's going to all be spelled out later, but here
we're just referring to that fact. And then there's the third opinion
that says that even in פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, women aren't obligated.
So when you do the math of the census to determine what,
how does the ציבור tzibur divide? Is it more טמא tamay or
more טהור? tahor? Who do you count? Which people do you look
at? So presumably you only look at the people that are obligated
to bring the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So here we're going to
give the scenario that women are not obligated, they're רשות reshut in
פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. So if you count just the men, here
we have a majority that's טהור. tahor. If you count the women,
the women is a little disproportionate, so the women, 51% of the
women are טמא tamay and 49 are טהור. tahor. So if you
add the women's vote as it were, then it breaks down to
50-50. But if you just look at the men's vote, it's majority
that are טהור. tahor. And therefore it really is only going to
be looked at through the men's vote as it were, and it's
going to be looked at as majority טהור. tahor. So let's read
that. And
this is to explain the ברייתא Baraita that says the טמא tamay
people do the פסח. Pesach. What are they doing with women in?
We'll see, as רשות. reshut. Okay, we have a ברייתא Baraita that
says 50-50, the טמא tamay people do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. That's
against two of the three approaches that say 50-50, the טמא tamay
people either would do ראשון Rishon or not at all. So we're
going to turn it into a case where the טמא tamay people
really are the minority, not 50%. It looks like it's 50-50, but
in truth they're in a minority. כגון שהיו ישראל מחצה טהורים ומחצה
טמאים, kegon shehayu Yisroel mechtzah tehorim u-mechtzah tme'im,
but the only reason it's 50% טמא tamay is because we were
counting the women. ונשים משלימות לטמאים, ve-nashim mashlimot le-tme'im, the women are
the ones that make it, are, you know, fill up the numbers
for the טמא tamay people. דקסבר, de-kasvar, so it looks like it's
50-50, but really it's not because, because this ברייתא Baraita is of
the opinion נשים בראשון רשות, nashim be-rishon reshut, that women are an
option, are not an obligation even in פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. So
therefore what we have to do is look behind the numbers, don't
look at the 50-50, get to the people that actually are obligated,
the men. דל נשים מטמאים, dal nashim mi-tme'im, so you subtract the
women's count. And when you subtract them from the טמא, tamay, you
obviously subtract them from the טהור, tahor, but when you subtract them
from both categories, הוו להו טמאים מיעוטא, havu lehu tme'im miyuta, then
you find the real numbers are that the טמא tamay people are
the minority. So therefore, ומיעוטא ידחו לפסח שני, u-miyuta yidchu le-Pesach Sheni,
and that's why the טמא tamay people bring a פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. So how do you explain the ברייתא Baraita that says 50-50,
the טמא tamay people bring פסח שני Pesach Sheni if that's not
your opinion? Because it's a case where it looks like 50% are
טמא, tamay, but really it's only 49% are טמא, tamay, 49% of
the men who would be obligated, and therefore they bring the פסח
שני. Pesach Sheni. Okay, that explains that ברייתא. Baraita. Now let's try
the other ברייתא Baraita that don't work. לרב וללישנא קמא דרב כהנא,
le-Rav u-le-lishna kama de-Rav Kahana, now according to רב Rav and version
one of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana רב Rav says טמא tamay people
do פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. רב כהנא Rav Kahana. says טמא tamay
people do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. הא דתניא טהורים עושים את הראשון
וטמאים אין עושין לא את הראשון ולא את השני. ha de-tanya tehorim
osin et ha-rishon ve-tme'im ein osin lo et ha-rishon ve-lo et ha-sheni.
What do you deal with the ברייתא Baraita that says that if
it's 50% they don't do פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon or פסח שני?
Pesach Sheni? According to רב, Rav, if it's 50% they do פסח
ראשון, Pesach Rishon, and according to version one of רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana they do פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. What do you do with
the ברייתא Baraita that says they don't do either? היכי מתרצי לה?
heichi mitartzai leh? How do you explain it? רב מתרץ לה, Rav
metartzai leh, so רב Rav explains, again, we're going to play with
the numbers. Okay, what is it, who is it that said, what
was that,
Mark Twain? Lies, damn lies and statistics. Okay, so you probably are
familiar with that
one, Charlie. It's
famous. I
know. Okay, so anyway, fine. So okay, we'll all just have to,
you know, we'll play with the numbers. So here's how the 50%
is going to explain why they don't do פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon
or פסח שני Pesach Sheni according to רב. Rav. כגון שהיו ישראל
מחצה טמאים ומחצה טהורים. kegon shehayu Yisroel mechtzah tme'im u-mechtzah tehorim. It
looks like it was 50-50.
But here's what was behind the numbers. ונשים עודפות על הטהורים, ve-nashim
odfot al ha-tehorim,
it really looked like it was 50-50 if you counted the men.
But once you add the women, then actually you have a majority
that's
טהור. tahor. דקסבר, de-kasvar, and this would be of the opinion, this
ברייתא, Baraita, נשים בראשון חובה, nashim be-rishon chovah, that women are... obligation
in פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. So the real numbers therefore, now that
you're counting the women, the real numbers are that you have a
majority טהור tahor and a minority טמא. tamei. Okay, but then at
least you'd say have the minority bring it on פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. Why is the minority not bringing it at all? Because here's
the trick: The first פסח Pesach women are an obligation, ובשני רשות.
u-bishini reshus. But by—but they're an option for the second—for פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. If women don't bring on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they
don't have to bring on פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
They only have to bring on ראשון. Rishon.
If they don't, they're obligated, but if they didn't, okay, if they
didn't bring on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they're exempt from פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. So women are exempt from פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So
therefore, how you count the numbers changes whether you're looking at פסח
ראשון Pesach Rishon or פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. When we're determining what
are the numbers for פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, we say who's obligated
for פסח ראשון? Pesach Rishon? Men and women. So then it's a
majority טהור, tahor, minority טמא. tamei. So the טמא tamei people have
to go perform—go do it on פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, because everybody
agrees if they're a minority. Now you come פסח שני. Pesach Sheni.
Now you say who's—what's the division of the people here, טהור tahor
and טמא tamei people, for פסח שני? Pesach Sheni? Well, so actually
you don't look right now who is טהור tahor and טמא; tamei;
you look of the people here that are obligated in the פסח
שני, Pesach Sheni, what was your story back when the פסח ראשון
Pesach Rishon was being brought? And now you're only discussing the people
that right now might be obligated. You're only discussing now the men,
not the women. Okay, so let's follow this through. He says like
this: ובשני
רשות. u-bishini reshus. ראשון לא עבדי דהוי להו מיעוטא. Rishon lo avdi
d'havi lehu miyuta. So the women—the טמא tamei people aren't going to
be doing the פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon because then we're counting the
women's vote and they're a minority, so they get pushed off to
the פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. ומיעוטא לא עבדי ראשונה. u-miyuta lo avdi
rishona. A minority doesn't do it on ראשון. rishon. ובשני לא עבדי.
u-bishini lo avdi. Now, why will the טמא tamei people not do
פסח שני? Pesach Sheni? Right? רב Rav normally holds that the טמא
tamei people aren't doing it ברשון, bi-rishon, they're doing it בשני. bi-shini.
Because then you look at who are the people obligated now and
what was their status back a month ago? So then you say,
ובשני לא עבדי, u-bishini lo avdi, you can't do it now in
the שני, shini, דל נשים מנייהו, dal nashim minaihu, because now we're
looking only at the men; only the men are obligated now in
אייר. Iyar. So we look at what your status was of this
community, you know, a month ago, so we look at it without
the women. דהוי להו פלגא ופלגא. d'havei lehu palga u-palga. And then
it was fifty-fifty. ופלגא לא עבדי בשני. u-palga lo avdi bi-shini. And
fifty percent won't have the right to do it בשני. bi-shini. It's
a little bit bizarre
though, because it's not—it wasn't פלגא פלגא palga palga before back at
ראשון Rishon after we removed the women's vote.
It's a very strange way of looking at it, right? Here basically,
okay, נשים Nashim had two different... Here was your fifty percent, okay,
of men,
at—this was your story on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, right? You had
fifty-fifty.
And then you had here with the women's vote, okay, you
had—this is טהור tahor and this is טמא, tamei, right?
So with the women's vote, I mean obviously it should be a
lot bigger, but okay, this is what it looks like, right? This
is what it looked like with the women's vote. So there was
a majority here, right, on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, right? So these
guys came—everybody here, these guys all did their פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon.
Everybody here came here to do their פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Now,
who's the only people that are going to do the פסח שני?
Pesach Sheni? The women here are רשות, reshus, not a חובה. chova.
So the people here are these fifty percent of people. Now, everybody
that's shown up in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you have a
hundred percent of these people right that are showing up in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash a month later, let's assume they all managed
to become טהור. tahor. Everybody here, right, the ציבור tzibbur now is
טהור. tahor. But we say, oh wait a minute, are you guys
allowed to do this פסח? Pesach? All you hundred thousand million people
that are showing up here, are you allowed to do your פסח?
Pesach? Well, you're fifty percent of, right? Because we're not looking at
the women now. So you're saying, well, you know, you're fifty percent
of the male קהל, kahal, and that's the people we think about,
we only think about the men right now because it's פסח שני,
Pesach Sheni, we're not thinking about women. So we're saying you're fifty
percent and you're not entitled to bring the פסח שני, Pesach Sheni,
which is very bizarre, right? Because the way we looked at it
back here, we were considering women. But right now when you're coming
to bring your פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, even though now you're a
hundred percent of the people that are showing up to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you're—and you know, and with the women you
were a minority, since you're fifty percent of the male קהל kahal
back a month ago, the numbers might have even shifted, but back
a month ago you were fifty percent of the male קהל, kahal,
we're going to count the numbers now only look at it through
the lens of the male קהל kahal and say that you're not
entitled to do the פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So it's a very
strange idea of how you do the count.
They're all טהור tahor now? Yeah, so it's—isn't that the reason behind
the פסח שני? Pesach Sheni?
Yeah, but you're only—but only a minority
is allowed to do it on the פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, and
right now we consider you no longer a minority. I mean, you
are a minority. of the people who were bringing the פסח ראשון,
Pesach Rishon, but since now we're only looking at men, we look
back a month ago through the male lens. And looking back a
month ago through the men only lens that filters out the women,
we say you're only 50 percent and you're not allowed to do
a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Very strange. Yes.
This relates back to the question of whether it's דחוי dichui or...
No, no, that's going to be explored in a סוגיא sugya coming
up. This is just drawing on that סוגיא. sugya. Okay, so let's
take a look. That's how Rav can explain why it's only,
why they don't do the פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, because you refer
back to the reality of a month ago. ולרב כהנא
דאמר פלגא נמי עבדי בשני, U-le-Rav Kahana d'amar palga nami avdi be-sheni,
and according to Rav Kahana that says 50 percent would normally do
it for שני, sheni, he would, why here are they not doing
it for ראשון rishon or שני? sheni? Again, the same basic way.
היכי מתרץ לה? Heichi metaretz lah? Here's how he'd explain it. כגון
שהיו ישראל מחצה טהורים ומחצה טמאים. Kegon she-hayu Yisrael mechetza tehorim u-mechetza
teme-im. It was 50-50, I mean you could have said the same
scenario, but it makes it a little bit whatever, tweaks it a
little bit. 50-50 on פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, ונשים משלימות לטהורים, ve-nashim
mashlimot le-tehorim, and women would actually the,
and the women actually, it's what made it 50-50 on the פסח
ראשון. Pesach Rishon. If you didn't take the women's vote, it would
have been a minority that would have been טמא. tamei. But because
of the women's vote, you did 50-50. וקסבר נשים בראשון חובה ובשני
רשות, Ve-kasavar nashim be-rishon chova u-ve-sheni reshut, and same idea, they're an
obligation on the פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon and they're, they're not obligated
פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So בראשון לא עבדי דהוו להו פלגא ופלגא.
be-rishon lo avdi de-havu lehu palga u-palga. So they didn't do, the
טמא tamei people, פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon because then you were counting
the women's vote. And with counting the women, it was 50 percent
טמא. tamei. For Rav Kahana, 50 percent טמא tamei doesn't do
פסח
ראשון. Pesach Rishon. בראשון פלגא לא עבדי, be-rishon palga lo avdi, according
to Rav Kahana. Now comes along פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, ובשני נמי
לא עבדי. u-ve-sheni nami lo avdi. Then the טמא tamei people don't
do it. Why not? דל נשים מינייהו שדי מן הטהורים הוו להו
טמאים רובא. dal nashim mineihu shedi min ha-tehorim havu le-hu teme-im ruba.
Because according to Rav Kahana, I might have, I might have misread
it before, but according to Rav Kahana, the only reason the טהור
tahor people were 50 percent was because of the women's vote. Without
the women's vote, the טמא tamei people would have been the majority.
So now comes along פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, and you look back
a month ago through the lens of only looking at men. And
looking back a month ago through the lens of only looking at
men, in that scenario, the טמא tamei people were the majority. ורובא
לא עבדי בשני. ve-ruba lo avdi be-sheni. And therefore a majority is
not entitled to do it the פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Okay, so
according to Rav Kahana, the scenario is, if you actually had the
men's vote, you had, right, you had, what was it? 51 percent
טמא tamei and 49 percent טהור. tahor. But once you're counting the
women's vote, it was exactly equal. Okay, it was exactly equal. They
were exactly equal. They were exactly equal. So therefore he says that
if the טמא tamei is exactly 50 percent, you don't do, you
don't do פסח ראשון, Pesach Rishon, they get pushed off to פסח
שני. Pesach Sheni. Now when you look at פסח שני, Pesach Sheni,
you look back at the numbers based on the men's only, through
the men's only lens. And then you say, "Wait a minute, we
have 51 percent of the people here, you ignore the women." So
looking back at a month ago and looking at only through the
male lens, you have 51 percent. Well my side, 51 percent of
the people aren't entitled to do a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. Okay,
so it's the basic same thing. You can massage the numbers based
on, you know, whether you're counting women or not, but not only
whether you're counting women or not, but on the second vote, a
month later, you're allowed to define the numbers differently because you can
look back by ignoring women, which you weren't ignoring during the first
time.
ורב נחמן אמר הולך אחר
רוב וכו׳
Ve-Rav Nachman amar holech achar
rov ve-chulu would, but it's not, doesn't help us here. So we're
ignoring that possibility. Okay, nobody in the two ways we've explained this.
It doesn't mean there's not a position out there. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so that's how we explain
that
ברייתא. braita. ולרב כהנא הא דתניא. U-le-Rav Kahana ha di-tanya. Now, according
to Rav Kahana, what does he do? We're, so we've explained two
ברייתות, braitas, we're left with the third ברייתא. braita. According to Rav
Kahana, הא דתניא הרי שהיו ישראל מחצה טהורים ומחצה טמאים הללו עושים
לעצמם והללו עושים לעצמם. ha di-tanya harei she-hayu Yisrael mechetza tehorim u-mechetza
teme-im hallalu osim le-atzmam ve-hallalu osim le-atzmam. What does he do with
the ברייתא braita that says 50-50, each group does it by itself?
You know, however you massage the numbers, that's allowing for the possibility
of each group doing it by itself. Rav Kahana seems to fundamentally
reject that idea that you could have two separate parts of כלל
ישראל Klal Yisrael bringing two separate, you know, types of פסח Pesach
on the same day. So how does he deal with that ברייתא?
braita? והכי מתרץ לה? ve-heichi metaretz lah? How would he explain it?
אמר לך רב כהנא. Amar lecha Rav Kahana, So here Rav Kahana
has to concede that he has a תנא tanna that disagrees with
him. תנאי היא. Tanna-ei hi. Yes, there is a, it is a
debate of תנאים. tannaim. I personally hold it's impossible that you could
split up כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael that way, but no matter how
I massage the numbers, I have to admit that that this תנא
tanna holds there's a possibility that half does it by themselves and
half does it by themselves, all on פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. איכא
למאן דאמר מחצה על מחצה כרוב. Ika le-man d'amar mechetza al mechetza
ke-rov. There is a תנא tanna that holds 50-50 is like רוב,
rov, and that would say that then you have two רובים rovs
that are sort of competing. with one another, and they both split
up, and that's that תנא. Tanna. I don't hold of it. ואיכא
למאן דאמר Ve-ika le-man de-amar and then there's the other תנא Tanna
that holds מחצה על מחצה אינו כרוב, machatza al machatza eino ke-rov,
which is the other two versions of the ברייתא baraita which is
my position. And therefore says that if it's 50-50, the 50% טמא
tamei either do פסח שני Pesach Sheni or don't do it at
all. Okay, so very nice. You have this debate, whether it's כרוב,
ke-rov, what the implications would be, and if it's not כרוב, ke-rov,
two possibilities within רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, and you have ברייתות baraitot
that support each position. And then you have this fascinating issue of:
A, do you count women in general, who gets to count for
this question of 50-50? But also this fas- and are women obligated?
But also this fascinating question about can you, when it comes a
month later, redefine what the numbers were because now you're looking at
it through a different lens? Okay,
גופא. gufa. It's
a מחלוקת. machloket. Yes, it's a מחלוקת. machloket. הרי שהיו ישראל, Harei
she-hayu Yisrael, רב כהנא Rav Kahana, just summed up, that's his two
versions were both versions of saying מחצה על מחצה אינו כרוב. machatza
al machatza eino ke-rov. אמר לך amar lecha רב כהנא, Rav Kahana
so גופא, gufa, let's look back at one of the ברייתות. baraitot.
Now we're going to flesh out the full ברייתא. baraita. הרי שהיו
ישראל מחצה טהורים ומחצה טמאים. Harei she-hayu Yisrael machatza tehorim u-machatza tameim.
50-50. הללו עושים לעצמן והללו עושים לעצמן. Halalu osim le-atzman ve-halalu osim
le-atzman. This was the ברייתא baraita that followed רב, Rav, that says
each half does it by themselves. 50% טמא tamei doesn't define the
טהור tahor people, but doesn't get pushed off to פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. Now, היו טמאים עודפים על הטהורים, Hayu tameim odefim al ha-tehorim,
let's say, simple, seems to be a simple scenario. 51% were טמא.
tamei. אפילו אחד, afillu echad, even if it was one person that
tipped the scales. It was like, you know, the...
like who? Like Shasya, this time of year, tipping the scales for
the world?
Oh, there you go. That was an interesting one. But even one
little מעביר ראשון ראשון, ma'avir rishon rishon, whatever. Okay. Anyway, I was
thinking more like Bush-Gore.
Okay. Everybody had to get like a Supreme Court to figure it
out exactly. All goes down to 270 votes. One person makes the
difference. בטומאה, be-tum'ah, אפילו אחד, afillu echad, יעשו בטומאה. ya'asu be-tum'ah. Just
one person makes them a majority, everybody does it בטומאה. be-tum'ah. לפי
שאין קרבן ציבור חלוק. Lefi she-ein korban tzibbur chaluk. And here, that
phrase makes a lot more sense than it did in the context
yesterday. You gotta do, everybody's gotta do it together. You don't split.
Of course, it's very bizarre. A second ago, you did split. You
had 50% doing it one way, 50% doing the other. But I
guess it means, once you have the opportunity, once you're already have
a majority, you don't save the טהור tahor people. Once the majority
is טמא, tamei, then you don't make, you don't try to divide
things and protect the טהור tahor people, everybody does it together. Okay.
רבי אליעזר בן מתיא אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Matya omer, רבי אליעזר
בן מתיא Rabbi Eliezer ben Matya says, אין היחיד מכריע את הציבור
לטומאה. ein ha-yachid machria et ha-tzibbur le-tum'ah. No, one person is not
going to define that the whole ציבור, tzibbur, you know, you know,
tips the scales.
שנאמר, She-ne'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, דף פ עמוד א, Daf Peh
Amud Aleph, לא תוכל לזבוח את הפסח באחד בשעריך, lo tuchal lizbo'ach
et ha-pesach be-achad bishe'arecha, it's like parentheses. You can't shecht the קרבן
פסח korban pesach באחד, be-achad, because of one guy. One guy isn't
going to determine that now everybody is going to do it בטומאה.
be-tum'ah. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, אפילו שבט אחד טמא. afillu
shevet echad tamei. Even if it's not 50% of the people, even
if it's just one discrete unit, one שבט, shevet, one tribe that
is טמא, tamei, presumably 51% טמא, tamei, right? How do you define
what one שבט shevet is טמא? tamei? But okay. But even if
one שבט shevet is טמא, tamei, ושאר כל השבטים טהורים, ve-sha'ar kol
ha-shevatim tehorim, אלו יעשו טהור, elu ya'asu tahor, הללו עושים לעצמן והללו
עושים לעצמן, halalu osim le-atzman ve-halalu osim le-atzman, it's just like 50-50.
The שבט shevet by itself is considered its own type of a
community, its own type of a ציבור, tzibbur, and a ציבור tzibbur
is not pushed off to פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. A ציבור tzibbur
is entitled to do it פסח
ראשון. Pesach Rishon.
They're only one שבט, shevet, so they don't determine everybody else. It's
like the 50-50 case, but they do at least establish themselves as
a ציבור tzibbur that's allowed to do it by פסח ראשון. Pesach
Rishon.
You might suggest they use it as an הוריות.
Horayot. Yes, it's related. מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון, Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Shimon,
what's the reason of רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? קסבר שבט אחד איקרי
קהל. Kasavar shevet echad ikrei kahal. Even one שבט shevet is called
a קהל, kahal, and that, as Michael correctly remembered and רש"י Rashi
refers to, is a discussion in הוריות, Horayot, when it says the
קהל kahal does a sin, and they bring a special קרבן, korban,
פר העלם דבר של ציבור. par helam davar shel tzibbur. According to
some opinions, it's even if it's one שבט. shevet. And that's exactly
this opinion. So it's enough of a קהל kahal that they are
entitled to do it בראשון, be-rishon, not enough to define everybody else
and to say that everybody does it בטומאה. be-tum'ah. ושאר כל השבטים
טהורים יעשו, Ve-sha'ar kol ha-shevatim tehorim ya'asu, now, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
though takes it to the next logical step. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi
Yehuda omer, אפילו שבט אחד טמא ושאר כל השבטים טהורים יעשו בטומאה.
afillu shevet echad tamei ve-sha'ar kol ha-shevatim tehorim ya'asu be-tum'ah. שאין קרבן
ציבור חלוק. She-ein korban tzibbur chaluk. He really believes
in אין קרבן ציבור
חלוק. ein korban tzibbur chaluk. So even if one sense of a
ציבור tzibbur is entitled to do it בטומאה, be-tum'ah, then everybody does
it בטומאה. be-tum'ah. So presumably he would certainly say it in the
50-50 case as well. Once you have a group that is doing
בטומאה be-tum'ah because they by themselves are considered a קהל, kahal, then
that defines the status for all of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael.
He keeps he considers women as part of it.
Yeah, that's interesting too.
Okay, numbers 99, you'd still do it in בטומאה. be-tum'ah.
No, you need one of the שבטים. shevatim. You need one group
that's considered a קהל. kahal. What's considered a קהל kahal would either
be 50% according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma or one שבט.
shevet. But one... Once you have a קהל, Kahal, that קהל Kahal
is entitled to do it בטומאה. be'Tuma. If you add to that
the idea that you never divide the ציבור, Tzibur, even if you
don't have a majority, then once one group does it בטומאה, be'Tuma,
everybody does it בטומאה. be'Tuma. Okay, וסבר סבר va'savar savar רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda סבר savar שבט Shevet אחד Echad איקרי ikri קהל Kahal
והוו ve'havu פלגא palga ופלגא u'palga and it's like the 50/50 case,
and ואין ve'ein קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur, חלוק chaluk add to that
the idea that you never divide a קרבן Korban ציבור Tzibur even
when you don't have a majority, you never divide it, ועבדי ve'avdi
כולהו kuleihu בטומאה be'Tuma then everybody would go ahead and do it
בטומאה. be'Tuma. Okay, so that's a very interesting range of different positions
within this idea of like of variations on the 50/50 case. איתמר.
itmar. Now we're going to look at some at some other at
some scenarios. היו hayu ישראל Yisrael מחצה mechetza טהורים tehorim ומחצה u'mechetza
טמאים, tme'im, it was exactly 50/50. Okay, so what are you going
to do? So we already know what you do, but רב Rav
אמר, amar, now we're going to see a desire to try to,
we don't like the 50/50 case, we want to tip the scales.
So what does רב Rav say? So אמר amar רב Rav מטמאים
metam'im אחד echad מהם mehem בשרץ. be'sheretz. Oh, so get one of
the טהור tahor people to become טמא tamei and tip the scales.
So the גמרא Gemara says not only are you allowed to do
that, why do you need to do that according to רב? Rav?
ואמאי ve'amai why bother? נעבדו ne'avdu הני hanei לחודייהו le'chudaihu והני ve'hanei
לחודייהו. le'chudaihu. Why not just split it? דהא de'ha אמר amar רב,
Rav, רב Rav says הללו halalu עושין osin לעצמן le'atzman והללו ve'halalu
עושין osin לעצמן, le'atzman, that each one does it by themselves. And
you could have said that even though that's what the הלכה halacha
is, רב Rav would prefer to not divide the ציבור, Tzibur meaning
אין קרבן ציבור חלוק ein Korban Tzibur chaluk. not to the extent
that you would say everybody does it בטומאה, be'Tuma, but to the
extent that you would desire not to split them and therefore you
try to tip the scales. But let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. אמר amar
הכא hacha במאי bemai עסקינן, askinan, what are we talking about? דהיו
de'hayu טמאים tme'im עודפים odfim על al הטהורין ha'tehorim אחד. echad. Okay,
so what really was is it wasn't 50/50. There was one extra
vote in the טמא tamei column. אי ei הכי hachi and therefore
you needed to make it, you needed to even it up. גמרא
Gemara says, I'm sorry, not needed to even it up. It was
assuming that one vote wasn't enough, like the opinion in the in
the ברייתא, Baraita, that one vote, one person would not tip the
scales and you needed to turn it into two people. So the
גמרא Gemara says I don't get it. If one person isn't enough
to tip the scales, then it's just like a 50/50 scenario. What's
forcing you to tip the scales? אי ei הכי hachi if that's
true הוו havu להו lehu רובא ruba טמאים. tme'im. So oh, no,
I jumped ahead. If there's one extra person, it's already רוב טמא,
rov tamei? נעבדו ne'avdu כולהו kuleihu בטומאה. be'Tuma. So just do it
בטומאה. be'Tuma. No, סבר savar לה lah כרבי ke'Rabbi אלעזר Elazar בן
ben מתיא Matya דאמר de'amar אין ein היחיד ha'yachid מכריע machria את
et הציבור ha'tzibur לטומאה. le'tuma. He's assuming like רבי Rabbi אלעזר Elazar
בן ben מתיא Matya that one isn't enough to tip the scales.
So one isn't enough, but you do have a majority. So what
are you going to do? So you make it a real majority,
you get another guy טמא. tamei, But the גמרא Gemara says no,
if why not leave the situation as it is? אי ei הכי
hachi הדר hadar קושיא kushya לדוכתא. le'duchta. We're back to our question.
What's forcing you to change the scenario? נעבדו ne'avdu הני hanei לחודייהו
le'chudaihu והני ve'hanei לחודייהו. le'chudaihu. Each group does it by themselves. So
what? One has one extra? If the one extra doesn't count to
determine the status of the טהורים, tehorim, let each group do it
by itself. What is pushing you to say that each one, that
you have to make sure that there's a majority? אלא ela הכי
hachi קאמר. ka'amar. This is what רב Rav would
say. Well, that's what I said is that you could have said
that even though רב Rav allows for קרבן Korban ציבור Tzibur, חלוק,
chaluk he doesn't, he doesn't like it and he would prefer everybody
to be in the same boat. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is
not even contemplating that. It says as long as you allow for
קרבן Korban ציבור Tzibur חלוק, chaluk, then where's what's pushing you to
change the scenario? So let's see what the answer is. And then
take Charlie's question. אי ei הכי hachi if that's true אלא ela
הכי hachi קאמר. ka'amar. Here's what he's saying. אי ei איכא ika
תנא Tana דסבר de'savar ליה leih כתנא ke'Tana קמא Kama דאמר de'amar
פלגא palga ופלגא u'palga לא lo עבדי avdi כולהו kuleihu בטומאה. be'Tuma.
He says, so the גמרא Gemara essentially gets to that. He says,
look, if there exists somebody who holds like my opinion that 50/50
in principle, the 50 percent not being a majority doesn't allow everybody
to do it בטומאה. be'Tuma. Okay, that's my position. It doesn't allow
everybody to do it בטומאה. be'Tuma. I would have each side doing
it by themselves. וסבר ve'savar ליה leih כרבי ke'Rabbi יהודה Yehuda דאמר
de'amar אין ein קרבן Korban ציבור Tzibur חלוק. chaluk, But you also
hold of a different principle which says you're never allowed to split.
So what do you do? Then you're really stuck. Meaning, if you're
of the position that 50 percent טמא, tamei. because it's 50 percent,
they can't get pushed off to פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. They're entitled
to do פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon. because מחצה mechetza כרוב. ke'rov. So
you're entitled to do it and קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach but because
they're actually no bigger than the טהור tahor people, that's not enough
to allow the טהור tahor people to do it בטומאה. be'Tuma. So
that would lead to my position of have them each do it
by themselves. But let's say you also happen to hold that you
won't let the ציבור Tzibur be split. So what are you going
to do? You can't push them off to פסח שני. Pesach Sheni,
You can't do everybody בטומאה be'Tuma because they're not bigger than the
טהור tahor people. So you can't split them. You have no options.
So the only thing that you can do is force the situation
to be one that will work. Get one other person טמא. tamei,
So essentially that is what it's saying. Yes, you have theoretically the
idea of splitting, but you don't want to do that, or you're
not able to do that. Because as opposed to רב Rav who
allows it to split, רב Rav said if somebody held in principle
like me but wouldn't allow a split, in this scenario what you'd
have to do is get
another. There is an opinion that says that even though you can
be טהור tahor that night, that you cannot bring the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach? because right now you're טמא tamei. and רב Rav is
assuming that opinion. Okay, if שרץ טומאה sheretz tumah would allow you
would put you in the טהור tahor category because you'll be טהור
tahor that night, you'd have to make the guy טמא tamei by
a מת. mes. Okay, and we'll see about that and
can you tamei someone with לכתחילה l'chatchila in
order or לכתחילה l'chatchila in order to allow a whole half of
a ציבור Tzibur to bring קרבן פסח?
Korban Pesach So you know they say like almost חטא בשביל שיזכה
חברך?
cheit bishvil sheyizkeh
chaveirecha?
What's the חטא? cheit?
It's you know, because let's say if you were a יחיד yachid
and you did
it, is there an איסור issur to become טמא tamei to שרץ?
sheretz? Is this מבטל? mevatel?
No, but you said it was a מת. mes.
But I'm not going to be מבטל, mevatel, I'm going to bring
it tonight because I'm now טהור tahor tonight. Okay, but in this
scenario you're not being מבטל mevatel from the פסח.
Pesach For an ordinary person who is טמא שרץ tamei sheretz on
ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, right, so what's he supposed
to do?
Well, that's a מחלוקת. machlokes. Some say that you can have the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach brought for you and eat it that night,
and some say no, that you're נדחה nidcheh to פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. So רב Rav is assuming that normally you'd be נדחה nidcheh
to פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, but that allows it now either to
be a majority טמא tamei and everybody to do it בטומאה. b'tumah.
Okay, so
they are allowed to do בטומאה b'tumah now now that you have
a
רוב. rov Doesn't matter, once it's a קרבן Korban ציבור, Tzibur אין
ein קרבן Korban ציבור tzibur חלוק. chaluk. Once it's brought בטומאה b'tumah
it's totally allowed. Look, it's a strange idea which I haven't really
fully unpacked because the גמרא Gemara doesn't fully unpack it, which is
on the one hand you have all of this discussion about טומאה
דחויה בציבור tumah dechuya b'tzibur and various attempts to try to minimize
how you're going to do it בטומאה, b'tumah, whether you look for
טהור כהנים, tahor Kohanim, whether you try to minimize etcetera etcetera. And
then the גמרא Gemara at the same time without bringing in the
דחויה הותרה dechuya hutra discussion basically assumes once it's done בטומאה b'tumah
everybody's allowed to become טמא tamei and don't have to try to
be careful not to become טמא. tamei So exactly how that fits
together with the הותרה דחויה hutra dechuya discussion is not so clear.
But that is the assumption here. Let's continue. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ועולא אמר, V'Ulla amar, now עולא Ulla would say
in such a scenario, because it's the same idea, we want to
get it to be not a fifty-fifty, you don't want to split
the ציבור. tzibur. What are you going to do? So rather than
getting one of the guys טמא, tamei. משלחים אחד מהן לדרך רחוקה.
meshalechin echad mehen l'derech rechoka. Okay.
So he says you get one of the טהור tahor guys, you
send them on a message outside on a mission to leave ירושלים
Yerushalayim and therefore you have a minority now that's טהור. tahor. So
instead of making the טהור tahor guy טמא, tamei, you just get
the טהור tahor guy out of here, you send him away and
then he doesn't count in the vote.
So wait, so we were looking at the census before about מחצה
mechtza and רוב rov. and all that, is that the people in
ירושלים?
Yerushalayim? Presumably we're looking only at the people in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, correct.
So you really could have an overwhelming majority טהור. tahor.
Right, but their vote doesn't count because they're not ראוי ra'uy to
bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach because they're בדרך רחוקה. b'derech rechoka.
So the גמרא Gemara says וייטמא בשרץ. v'yitamei b'sheretz. What's wrong with
רב's Rav solution of just throwing a שרץ sheretz on the guy?
So the גמרא Gemara says קסבר kasavar and here's the issue you
all were talking about: שוחטין וזורקין על טמא שרץ shochtin v'zorkin al
tamei sheretz that being טמא שרץ tamei sheretz would put him in
the טהור tahor category because he's of the opinion that you purely
can bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach. for somebody who's טמא שרץ
tamei sheretz and he'll be טהור tahor that night. So the גמרא
Gemara says וייטמא במת. v'yitamei b'mes. All right, so then have him
become טמא tamei, with מת, mes, that'll do it. The גמרא Gemara
says מדחיתו מחגיגתו. midachisa leh me'chagigato.
No, because if you get him טמא tamei from the מת, mes,
he won't be טהור tahor on the first day of יום טוב.
Yom Tov. If it's a שרץ sheretz he'll be טהור tahor on
the first day of יום טוב, Yom Tov, but if it's a
מת mes he won't and he won't be able to bring his
קרבן חגיגה. Korban Chagigah. So the גמרא Gemara says what's so? There's
seven days to bring the קרבן חגיגה, Korban Chagigah, the last day
you'll be טהור. tahor. גמרא Gemara says and besides we get to
that, it says and so what? You're going to make him טמא
שרץ tamei sheretz so השתא נמי מדחיתו מפסחו. hashta nami midachisa leh
mi'pischo. So in the case of, what, did I read that right?
No, no, no. So it says so what's your alternative? You don't
want to make him טמא במת tamei b'mes because you don't want
to make him unable to bring the חגיגה Chagigah on the first
day יום טוב. Yom Tov. But what's your solution? Send him away.
If you're sending him away then what? He's not going to be
able to bring his קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach The guy you're making
טמא tamei at least he gets to bring a קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach. because it becomes a פסח Pesach which is done בטומאה. b'tumah.
Your solution עולא, Ulla, send a guy away, you're preventing him from
bringing קרבן פסח. korban Pesach?
What about חגיגה? Chagigah?
Well no, because now he could be back by the next morning.
Okay, but certainly anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says אכתי דבי בשני.
achti davi b'sheni. No, he'll bring a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. So
the גמרא Gemara says נו nu if that's your answer במת נמי,
b'mes nami, let the guy become טמא במת tamei b'mes rather than
sending him on some mission and אכתי דבי בשביעי. achti davi b'shevi'i.
He'll become טהור, tahor, right, if he's טמא tamei on ערב פסח,
Erev Pesach, he'll be טמא tamei ערב פסח Erev Pesach and the
first six days of פסח Pesach, and he'll be טהור tahor by
the seventh day of פסח. Pesach You can bring a חגיגה Chagigah
on the seventh day of פסח, Pesach.
so דהוי ליה שמיני שלו. dehavei lei shemini shelo. The seventh day
of פסח Pesach will be his eighth day from becoming טמא. tamei
So why again, why would you prefer to send him away where
he can't do the פסח? Pesach Just make him טמא. tamei. So
קסבר עולא, kasavar Ulla, עולא Ulla is of the opinion כולן תשלומין
דראשון נינהו. kulan tashlumin d'rishon ninhu. When you're allowed to make up
a חגיגה Chagigah on all the other days of יום טוב, Yom
Tov, that's all a makeup for the first day, which means that
you have to have been obligated on the first day and not
done it. If you weren't obligated on the first day, here's an
easy scenario, let's say a kid became בר מצוה *bar mitzvah* in
the on חול המועד *Chol Hamoed*. Okay, does he bring a חגיגה
*chagiga*? So no, 'cause you only bring a חגיגה *chagiga* if you
were obligated and didn't do it. Okay, so he says, since that's
the scenario, if you were טמא tamei. *tamei*, now you could have
said טמא tamei, *tamei* you are obligated, you just weren't able to
do it, but we are considering that טמא tamei *tamei* you weren't
in the category at all and therefore you don't get the option
of doing it on the other days. So דחזי בראשון berishon, חזי
בכולהו *d'chazi b'rishon chazi b'culhu*, if you were fit to bring it
on the first day, it's a little bit funny, we're almost like
rewarding negligence as opposed to things that were out of your control.
If you were able to do it on the first day and
you did it, then you bring it on the other days, you're
fit on the other days. וכל דלא חזי בראשון berishon, *v'chol d'lo
chazi b'rishon*, this guy was טמא tamei *tamei*, who couldn't bring it
on the first day, לא lo. חזי בכולהו *lo chazi b'culhu*, is
not fit. So basically he says I'd rather send the guy away
to make it a מיעוט טהור tahor, *miut tahor*, have him not
able to bring his קרבן פסח korban Pesach *korban pesach*, he'll have
to bring it בשני besheni. *b'sheini*, rather than making him טמא tamei
*tamei*, which seven days, which would become a problem with the חגיגה
*chagiga*. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אמר להו Amar lahu, רב Rav
נחמן *amar lehu Rav Nachman*, so רב Rav נחמן *Rav Nachman* said
to them, I don't know who the them is, maybe עולא *Ulla*
and who was it
רב Rav *Rav*? No, them is his students clearly. זילו ואמרו ליה
לעולא *zilu v'imru lei l'Ulla*, he said to his students you know
what, go tell עולא *Ulla* who says send one guy away, מאן
ציית לך דאקר שיכי ומסגני ברהי *man tzyis lach d'akar shichei v'masganei
b'rahi*. Who's going to listen to you to uproot his pegs and
his tent and run out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* ערב פסח Pesach. *erev
Pesach*? So it's like good luck, okay? Try to send a guy,
here he is, he came all the way to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, it's
ערב פסח Pesach, *erev Pesach*, bringing the קרבן פסח korban Pesach *korban
pesach*, and you're going to, you know what, do us all a
favor, why don't you go out, why don't you leave?
He just bought his ticket online, he flew all the way
here, he paid five
hundred dollars, right?
That's true. They would have to get you some type of a
coupon or bump you to first class next time. Next time you'll
get to be the first group that brings. I don't know. Okay,
so anyway he felt that that was not a practical solution. איתמר
itmar. *itmar*. Now, by the way I should say תוספות *Tosafot* has
a question, just as since when can't you bring a חגיגה *chagiga*
just because you're טמא tamei *tamei*? Have somebody bring it for you,
right? The whole issue of being טמא tamei. *tamei* by your פסח
Pesach *Pesach* is it had to be eaten, so have somebody bring
a חגיגה *chagiga* for you, it doesn't have to be, it just
has to be brought. Somebody has to be, yeah. So תוספות *Tosafot*
says well maybe, right, maybe this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming that
the חגיגה *chagiga*'s like the עולת ראיה *olat reiyah*, and the עולת
ראיה *olat reiyah* is about actually coming into the בית המקדש *Beit
Hamikdash* and therefore you actually have to be present. Of course which
then raises the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* question why the גמרא *Gemara* didn't
say that you're preventing him from being his עולת ראיה *olat reiyah*.
Okay, anyway, איתמר *itmar*. So anyway that's an interesting issue, but conceptually
it's fascinating, like the fifty percent are entitled to do it בראשון
berishon. *b'rishon*, but we can't split the ציבור tzibur *tzibur* so we
have to force it to be a majority. איתמר *itmar*. Now here's
another discussion. היו רובן זבין *hayu ruban zavin*, ומעוטן טמאי מתים tmei
meisim, *u'miutan tmei meitim*. The majority of the people were זבין *zavin*.
Now, if you're only a person that's entitled to do it בראשון
berishon, *b'rishon* is a טמא tamei. מת *tmei meit* or a טמא
tamei, שרץ *tmei sheretz*, I mean if it's טומאה הותרה בציבור tuma
hutra b'tzibur *tumah hutra b'tzibur*, only looks at people that are טמאי
מתים tmei meisim *tmei meitim* or טמא tamei שרץ *tmei sheretz* if
they're otherwise not able to do, if you would say that you
can't bring a קרבן Korban פסח Pesach? *korban pesach* for טמא tamei
שרץ *tmei sheretz*. But the idea is a טומאה tuma *tumah* that
comes from the outside. A
טומאה *tumah* that's a טומאת הגוף *tumas haguf*, somebody's a זב zav,
*zav* or if women are obligated a זבה *zava* or a נידה
*niddah* or a מצורע *metzora*, those people are not allowed to do,
are not allowed to do, you would not say טומאה הותרה Tumah
hutra, בציבור *tumah hutra b'tzibur*. If you had a majority of the
ציבור tzibur? *tzibur* that were זבין *zavin*, you would not say טומאה
הותרה בציבור *tumah hutra b'tzibur*. It's too weighty of a טומאה *tumah*
to say הותרה בציבור *hutra b'tzibur*, and because you don't say טומאה
הותרה בציבור *tumah hutra b'tzibur* by that type of a טומאה *tumah*,
also then obviously their numbers don't count towards the טמא tamei *tamei*
people. When you're doing the vote as it were, right, and whether
to consider a majority טמא tamei *tamei* or not, you only look
at the people who if they're considered to be the majority would
be entitled to do it. So you only look at the people
that are טמאי מתים tmei meisim. *tmei meitim*, you don't look at
the זבין *zavin*. Okay? So here's the scenario. So you have, היו
רובן זבין *hayu ruban zavin*, the majority were זבין *zavin*, which is
not a טומאה הותרה בציבור *tumah hutra b'tzibur* scenario, ומעוטן טמאי מתים
tmei meisim *u'miutan tmei meitim*, the minority are טמאי מתים tmei meisim
*tmei meitim*. So what's the story, so we know the זבין *zavin*
are, well let's take a look. So what's the story? אמר amar
רב *amar Rav*, עושין טמאי מתים tmei meisim, אין עושין לא בראשון
berishon ולא בשני besheni *osin tmei meitim ein osin lo b'rishon v'lo
b'sheini*. The טמאי מתים tmei metim. *tmei meitim* people, they're stuck again.
They don't get to do ראשון Rishon *rishon* or שני Sheni. *sheini*.
Why not? בראשון לא עבדי Be-rishon lo avdi. דהוי מיעוטא *b'rishon lo
avdi d'havei miuta*, they obviously aren't entitled to do it in the
ראשון Rishon *rishon*, they're a minority of the community. Now they're the
entire community that in theory could be bringing, but they're a minority
of all כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael. *Klal Yisrael*, and therefore they are
not entitled to do it בראשון berishon *b'rishon*. ומיעוטא לא עבדי בראשון
lo avdi be-rishon. *u'miuta lo avdi b'rishon*, a minority doesn't do a
ראשון rishon *rishon*. בשני besheni. נמי לא עבדי *b'sheini nami lo avdi*,
now why don't they get to do שני Sheni. *sheini*? Because כהיכא
דעבדי ציבור tzibur, בראשון berishon, עבדי יחיד yachid בשני besheni *k'heicha d'avdi
tzibur b'rishon avdi yachid b'sheini*. When, when is there a הלכה halakha.
*halacha* that people that there exists a פסח שני Pesach Sheni. *Pesach
Sheini*? When there was a פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon *Pesach Rishon* that
was brought by the ציבור tzibur *tzibur*. Okay? In this case, nobody
brought a פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon *Pesach Rishon*. הזבין *ha-zavin* didn't bring
'cause the זב zav. *zav* can never bring a פסח ראשון pesach
rishon *Pesach Rishon* and the טמאי מתים tmei metim? *tmei meitim* didn't
bring 'cause it wasn't רוב rov *rov* of the ציבור tzibur *tzibur*.
So there was no פסח. Pesach? because if there's no פסח ראשון,
pesach rishon there's no פסח שני, Pesach Sheni? okay, which is an
interesting הלכה. halakha כל היכא דלא עבדי ציבור בראשון Kol heicha d'lo
avdi tzibur berishon if there was not a ציבור tzibur? doing it
בראשון, berishon, לא עבדי יחיד בשני lo avdi yachid besheni you would
not have a יחיד yachid doing it בשני. besheni. Now, of course,
an interesting question, what does it mean nobody or does it mean
not a ציבור? tzibur Right, let's say you had sixty percent זבים,
zavim, twenty percent טמאי מתים, tmei metim and twenty percent טהור, tahor,
right? So you had twenty percent of the people still brought בראשון,
be-rishon. but they weren't a ציבור, tzibur. they were just a minority
of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. It seems like even in that scenario,
the allowance of an individual to do בשני besheni is because the
ציבור tzibur did בראשון. be-rishon. But if there's no ציבור tzibur that
did בראשון, be-rishon. the individual cannot do בשני. besheni. Presumably, the זבים,
zavim, it goes without saying, the זבים zavim can't do בשני besheni?
because they're a majority, and a majority can never do בשני. besheni,
Okay, so the זבים zavim can't do בראשון be-rishon? בשני besheni. and
the טמאי מתים tmei metim. can't do בראשון be-rishon.
בשני. besheni, What is the definition of a ציבור?
tzibur Majority of כלל ישראל.
Klal Yisrael Just has to be in other words fifty-one percent. Well,
actually it's
a majority
of כלל ישראל klal Yisrael.
in Jerusalem, right, a whole שבט... shevet...
Oh, a whole שבט, shevet, that's an interesting point. According to those
opinions before that if a שבט shevet were טמא, tamei they would
be entitled to do it בראשון, be-rishon. so in this scenario if
you had a שבט shevet that was טהור, tahor would that allow
everybody else to do it בשני? besheni? Maybe, could be. That's an
interesting point, could be. Okay, but in this case you did not
have a whole שבט, shevet, you did not have a majority of
the people and therefore there's going to be no פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni, They're just a חבורה. chabura. Yeah. It also raises the
question of what if the ציבור tzibur didn't bring it because they
were just
lazy or not whatever, but they were obligated? Presumably, interesting, presumably the
same הלכה halakha, that it's only a יחיד yachid that does בשני,
be-sheni. not the ציבור. tzibur So let's take a look. אמר להו
שמואל, Amar lahu Shmuel, so שמואל Shmuel said to them, so fine.
אמר להו שמואל, Amar lahu Shmuel,
so again, them, them would be his students. Did I skip a
line? No, I'm at the right place. אמר להו שמואל Amar lahu
Shmuel זילו אמרו ליה לאבא, Zilu amru lei l'Abba, go tell אבא,
Abba, which was a way of referring to רב here, ויעשו בני
ישראל את הפסח במועדו, V'ya'asu Bnei Yisrael et ha-Pesach b'moado, מאי עבדת
ליה? mai avdit lei? What are you going to do with the
fact that we're supposed to bring a קרבן פסח? Pesach So you're
saying nobody brings a קרבן פסח Pesach in this scenario במועדו? b'moado?
Do you really nobody you're not you're going to have a scenario
you're not going to allow anybody to bring a קרבן פסח Pesach
on the fourteenth of ניסן? Nisan? No, no, that was a scenario
I gave. In the scenario that I was just trying to discuss
that case and רב's scenario, eighty percent were זבים, zavim, twenty percent
were טמאי מתים. tmei metim So שמואל Shmuel is saying what, in
that case let the טמאי מתים tmei metim. bring it, consider them
the ציבור and say טומאה הותרה בציבור for that twenty percent? You're
going to say nobody, but there's the entire ציבור of the people
that theoretically could bring, right? So you're really going to tell me
nobody's going to bring a פסח? Pesach You have the opportunity to
bring and you're not going to let anybody bring a פסח Pesach,
on the fourteenth of ניסן? Nisan? So אמר להו, so רב said
back to those to שמואל's Shmuel students, זילו אמרו ליה, Zilu amru
lei, go tell back to your רבי, Rebbe, כי הוו כולהו זבים
מאי עבדת ליה? ki havu kulhu zavim mai avdit lei? What would
you do if a hundred percent were זבים? zavim? You wouldn't tell
them to do פסח ראשון. pesach rishon So אלא כיון דלא אפשר
לא אפשר, Ella keivan d'lo efshar lo efshar, yeah, there are some
times you can't bring the פסח on the fourteenth. If a hundred
percent were זבים zavim you couldn't bring it. So הכא נמי לא
אפשר, Hacha nami lo efshar, here too, לא אפשר, lo efshar, that's
the הלכה, I'm sorry, I'm not going to let the טמאי מתים
tmei metim, bring it if they're a minority and it means nobody
brings a פסח on the fourteenth, so be it. Okay. אתמר, Itmar,
it was taught. Another case. היו רובן טמאי מתים ומיעוטן זבים. Hayu
ruban tmei meisim u-mi'utan zavim. Eighty percent, again, we're ignoring טהור tahor
people, eighty percent were טמאי מתים, tmei metim twenty percent were זבים.
zavim. That seems easy
enough, it's a what, not really, it's a פסח הבא בטומאה, Pesach
ha-ba b'tuma, but זבים zavim aren't allowed even in a פסח הבא
בטומאה. Pesach ha-ba b'tuma.
So they would have to come פסח שני. pesach sheni. So let's
take a look. So can they bring a פסח שני? pesach sheni
Why not? The ציבור did it בראשון, be-rishon so let the זבים
zavim do it בשני. be-sheni. So רב הונא אמר, Rav Huna amar,
רב הונא Rav Huna says, אין תשלומין לפסח הבא בטומאה. Ain tashlumin
l'Pesach ha-ba b'tuma. No, the same way we said before, you needed
a ציבור to bring פסח ראשון pesach rishon, in order to enable
יחידים yechidim to bring פסח שני, pesach sheni. you need a ציבור
to bring it בטהרה b'tahara in the פסח ראשון rishon. to allow
a יחיד yachid to bring it בשני, right? Then it sort of
serves as the makeup because it was a טהור tahor one. If
it was a טמא tamei one, it doesn't entitle makeup. So רב
אדא בר אהבה אמר, Rav Adda bar Ahava amar, יש תשלומין לפסח
הבא בטומאה. yesh tashlumin l'Pesach ha-ba b'tuma. No, I'm sorry, even if
it was brought בטומאה, b'tuma, you can may have a makeup if
you were a sort of person who couldn't bring. Anyway, let's say
you were בדרך רחוקה, b'derech rechoka, that would be another question, right?
Let's say it was a פסח which was בא בטומאה ba b'tuma
and forget being a זב, zav you were בדרך רחוקה, b'derech rechoka,
would you be allowed to bring it בשני? Okay, so this is
the debate. So the גמרא says נימא בהא קמיפלגי, neima b'ha kamiflagi,
let's say this is what they debate. דמאן דאמר אין תשלומין לפסח
הבא בטומאה קסבר טומאה דחויה היא בציבור. De-man d'amar ain tashlumin l'Pesach
ha-ba b'tuma kasavar tuma dechuya hi b'tzibur. The one that says that
there's no makeup holds that the טומאה is דחויה, dechuya, which means
that yes, you brought it, but it was still a problematic פסח,
it was still brought בטומאה b'tuma and it was seen as problematic.
And because it was problematic, therefore the idea, right, the classic scenario
is the טהור tahor. people bring on the ראשון and the טמא
tamei. who were טמא in the שני. Sheni. But in this case
If you're saying it was still a טמא people, a טמא פסח,
tamei pesach, then that's not the classic scenario and therefore people are
not entitled to bring בשני. ומאן דאמר U-man de-amar יש תשלומין לפסח
הבא בטומאה, yesh tashlumin le-pesach ha-ba be-tumah, if you say there is
a makeup קסבר טומאה הותרה בציבור. kasvar tumah hutra be-tzibbur. It's as
if it was טהור. tahor. It's as if it was טהור. tahor,
טומאה הותרה, it's like it didn't exist. If it was טהור, tahor.
then it fits into the classic
scenario. So אמר you could say no, לא. דכולי עלמא טומאה דחויה
בציבור. de-kulei alma tumah dechuya be-tzibbur. We can deal with the idea
that we're not claiming it's as if everybody was טהור. tahor It's
just they were טמא. Admittedly they were טמא. ובהא פליגי, U-ve-ha paligi,
but nevertheless this is what they debate. מר סבר Mar savar one
holds,
טהרה מדחיא טומאה לא מדחיא, taharah madchya tumah lo madchya, that only
a טהור פסח tahor pesach pushes off people to bring a פסח
שני. pesach sheni, A טמא פסח tamei pesach doesn't push them off.
Okay. ומר סבר אפילו טומאה נמי מדחיא, U-mar savar afilu tumah nami
madchya, that no, even a טמא פסח, tamei pesach, even when it's
brought בטומאה, be-tumah, that still you can have makeup. It's funny because
it doesn't really explain it, more like just describes it. We have
here טמא פסח. tamei pesach. What are they debating? They're debating whether
when the פסח ראשון is טמא, are you allowed to bring a
פסח שני pesach sheni. or not? All right. Anyway, איתמר. Last case.
We get to the משנה. mishnah. היו
שלישתן זבין ושלישתן טהורין ושלישתן טמאי מתים. Hayu shelishtan zavim u-shelishtan tehorin
u-shelishtan tmei metim. A third זב. You can tell the גמרא's just
having fun. A third טהור tahor and a third טמאי מתים. So
אמר רב מני בר פטי, Amar Rav Mani bar Patti, עושים טמאי
מתים אין עושים לא בראשון ולא בשני. osim tmei metim en osim
lo be-rishon ve-lo be-sheni. Now the טהור tahor people do בראשון. be-rishon.
That's easy. Okay. ברוב. be-rov. They're not a רוב, rov, but they
do בראשון. You don't need a רוב rov do בראשון. Okay. But
how about the טמאי מתים? עושים טמאי מתים אין עושים לא בראשון
ולא בשני. osim tmei metim en osim lo be-rishon ve-lo be-sheni. The
טמאי מתים don't do ראשון or שני. sheni. It's also true about
the זבים, zavim, but we're going to focus on the טמאי מתים.
בראשון לא עבדי. Why don't they do בראשון? Because הגדילו זבין על
טהורין דלא עבדי בטומאה. higdilu zavim al tehorin de-lo avdi be-tumah. Meaning
it's not
a פסח הבא בטומאה. pesach ha-ba be-tumah. Why? Because you count the
טמאי מתים with the טהורים. tehorim. What you really should say is
you don't count the זבים. zavim. Right. The זבים zavim are not...
Is that what it says actually? הגדילו
זבין.
higdilu
zavim.
No, it's what it says. It says the זבים zavim don't count
in the טמא category, in the טמא column because זבים zavim are
never entitled to do פסח ראשון even if it's a פסח הבא
בטומאה. pesach ha-ba be-tumah. So זבים zavim because they never do a
פסח ראשון are not counted in the טמא category. They're counted ironically
in the טהור tahor category, which is another way of saying you
only have thirty-three percent that are טמא that count towards the question
of is it a רוב rov טמא? Because the only people you
count in the טמא category are טמאי מתים. You don't count טהור
tahor people and you don't count זב in the טמא category. So
therefore they're not going to... so it's going to be a פסח
הבא בטהרה. pesach ha-ba be-taharah. So הגדילו זבין על טהורין דלא עבדי
בטומאה הוו להו טמאי
מתים מיעוטא מיעוטא לא עבדי בראשון. higdilu zavim al tehorin de-lo avdi
be-tumah havu lehu tmei metim mi'uta mi'uta lo avdi be-rishon. So number
one is it's not a פסח הבא בטומאה pesach ha-ba be-tumah because
you don't have a majority that's טמא. Okay? The זבים zavim vote
doesn't count.
If it doesn't count though, why don't we just say מחצה על
מחצה mechetza al mechetza because you'll have...
well that's the גמרא's point. You don't... what it says, הגדילו. higdilu.
Ironically the זבים zavim vote gets moved into the טהור tahor category.
Right. Let's just say they don't count at all. Okay. But it's
not true because then you'd be מחצה על מחצה. mechetza al mechetza.
That's the exact point of not saying this. It's saying that the
טמאי מתים, you don't say that they're the majority or they're equal
amount to those who could bring. You say they're a minority of
כלל ישראל. klal Yisrael, Okay. You don't look at it vis-a-vis the
טהור people and the people that could bring. That's part of the
חידוש chiddush here. You look at the entire community whether they could
or not and they're only thirty-three percent. So therefore it's not a
פסח הבא בטומאה. pesach ha-ba be-tumah. Okay. You just said
a רוב rov. can bring on the ראשון. You don't need... you
don't need a רוב. A מיעוט טמאין mi'ut tmei'in is לא עבדי
בראשון. Okay. בשני לא עבדי. Be-sheni lo avdi. Now they can't bring
on the פסח שני. pesach sheni. Why? Because now by the פסח
שני, pesach sheni, you say who are... what was the numbers of
people that didn't bring? Sixty-six percent of the people didn't bring
בראשון. So נצטרפו זבים עם טמאי מתים דלא עבדי בראשון. nitztarfu zavim
im tmei metim de-lo avdi be-rishon. So now you have sixty-six percent
of the קהל kahal didn't bring בראשון. דהוו להו רובא ורובא לא
מייתו לפסח שני. De-havu lehu rova ve-rova lo maytu le-pesach sheni. And
you don't have a majority of the קהל kahal bring a פסח
שני. pesach sheni You only have a יחיד bring the פסח שני.
Okay. So the same would be true by the way if you
figured out by the זבים. zavim. They also wouldn't bring בראשון and
בשני. But even the טמאי מתים where you might say like Michael's
saying, look, just look at the people that theoretically could bring and
it's fifty-fifty and go ahead... Nope. Sorry. Since they're only a third
of the entire כלל ישראל, they don't bring בראשון. And then פסח
שני, there's two-thirds of the people didn't bring פסח ראשון, so there's
not going to be a פסח שני either way.
Okay. We'll have to continue here
tomorrow.