בקר טוב, Boker tov, שנה טובה. Shana Tova. We start today on
פ' א'. Pe Aleph. We are, but we'll start two lines in.
Let me sort of say what we're in the middle of. The
משנה Mishna teaches that the idea of רצוי ציץ, Ritzuy Tzitz, which
is a concept we had before in the context of a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach that the ציבור Tzibur is טמא, Tamei, and whether
the idea is that טומאה Tumah has totally gone away or is
it still there and problematic, and you need the idea that the
תורה Torah
says the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol wears the ציץ, Tzitz, the forehead
gold plate, and that is מרצה. Meratze. It says על עון הקדשים,
Al avon hakodashim, the sin for the sanctified objects. And חז"ל Chazal
understand that in a very הלכתי halachic terms, that קרבנות Korbanot that
otherwise would be invalid because they were טמא Tamei are valid, and
that's the idea of רצוי. Ritzuy. רצוי Ritzuy technically means make acceptable,
desirable, but it's a technical term to mean that makes the קרבן
Korban acceptable
when it is טמא Tamei because of the presence of the ציץ.
Tzitz. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is wearing the ציץ Tzitz or
just the fact the ציץ Tzitz exists, that's the רצוי Ritzuy of
the ציץ. Tzitz. So, A, there was a question in the past
whether we needed that to work together with the idea
of טומאה הותרה בציבור. Tumah hutra b'tzibur. If טומאה Tumah is only
דחויה, Dechuya, pushed overridden but still present, maybe you need the ציץ.
Tzitz. Our discussion is focusing on an individual, forget the ציבור Tzibur
case. A normal case an individual brings a קרבן, Korban, the blood
is טמא, Tamei, the משנה Mishna teaches that if the ציץ Tzitz
allows that to be acceptable, particularly if, maybe only if,
the blood is thrown when you are unaware that it is טמא.
Tamei. If you did it willingly it's a different story, but you're
unaware that it's טמא, Tamei, the ציץ Tzitz says the קרבן Korban
is acceptable anyway. And also by the פסח, Pesach, if the בשר
basar is טמא Tamei and you're unaware, the קרבן Korban is acceptable.
That's the first use case. But, says the משנה, Mishna, it does
not work if the person is טמא, Tamei, only if the meat
is טמא. Tamei. עון הקדשים, Avon hakodashim, okay,
ולא עון המקריבים. v'lo avon hamakrivim. Only when the objects are טמא,
Tamei, the blood is טמא. Tamei. Now, normally it doesn't matter, normally
any קרבן Korban could be brought for you, you're טמא, Tamei, who
cares? You don't have to be in the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
There are two קרבנות Korbanot in particular where it really matters that
you're טמא. Tamei. I mean, in a way almost any קרבן Korban
that's about a process of ending a טהרה Taharah process, if you're
still טמא Tamei it won't work. But anyway, two קרבנות Korbanot in
particular that we're focusing on is the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and
a נזיר. Nazir. Because a פסח Pesach and a נזיר, Nazir, you
become טמא, Tamei, even though those are not קרבנות Korbanot about purifying
you, right? The נזיר Nazir ending his נזירות, nezirot, the פסח Pesach
is the פסח, Pesach, but if you're טמא Tamei then you can't
bring a פסח, Pesach, you have to bring a פסח שני. Pesach
Sheni. Or if you're טמא, Tamei, then your נזירות nezirot has to
start all over again. You can't bring a קרבן Korban at the
end of the נזירות. nezirot. So there if you're טמא, Tamei, the
ציץ Tzitz doesn't help you, the קרבן Korban is no good, even
if you're oblivious to the fact.
Does purification with the נזיר Nazir the חטאת Chatat is חיטוי? chituy?
Yes, but the חיטוי chituy is by a נזיר Nazir who became
טמא, Tamei, there's a purification process. But a נזיר Nazir to end
his טומאה, tumah, it is not about a purification process, he's been
טהור. tahor. No, so there's no purification. חטאת Chatat also comes for
sin, doesn't just, I mean you're correct that חטאת Chatat where we
incorrectly assume חטאת Chatat is only about sin, חטאת Chatat is also
about purification. But anyway, so it does not work if the people
are טמא, Tamei, with the exception says the משנה Mishna of this
interesting category called טומאת התהום, tumat hat'hom, a טומאה tumah of the
depths, which is if the טומאה tumah not only with the person
was unaware of but it was unknowable at the time, then the
ציץ Tzitz says you are טמא Tamei but it was unknowable at
the time, therefore because of the ציץ, Tzitz, your קרבן Korban is
acceptable in a case that you brought a פסח Pesach or you're
a נזיר. Nazir. Normally it should have been a problem, but there's
a special tradition הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha l'Moshe miSinai that the ציץ
Tzitz works for טומאת התהום tumat hat'hom and therefore it is acceptable
if it was a type of a טומאה tumah that was unknowable
at the time. That's the basic הלכה halacha of the
משנה. Mishna. The גמרא Gemara asked at the end of yesterday, what
happens if it's not you the owner are טמא Tamei with this
טומאת התהום tumat hat'hom that the ציץ Tzitz works for, but the
כהן Kohen bringing the פסח Pesach or the כהן Kohen bringing the
קרבן Korban of the נזיר Nazir is טמא Tamei with this טומאת
התהום. tumat hat'hom. Does that work or not for him or only
for the owners? Is the הלכה halacha that it works for the
owners of the קרבן Korban or does it work for anybody involved
in the קרבן? Korban? That was the גמרא's Gemara question. Now, in
the context of trying to determine that, we brought a discussion of
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. I'm not going to now explain how the
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi thing proves or doesn't prove that, we'll get
back to that in a minute. Let's focus on the רבי יוסי.
Rabbi Yosi. רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says if
let's actually pick it up from the bottom, bottom of פ' עמוד
ב', Pe amud bet, התניא. Ha tanya. So the question is would
this idea of טומאת התהום tumat hat'hom work for somebody who might
be a woman who might be a זבה. zava. Now, of course
the idea of טומאת התהום tumat hat'hom is bizarre, normally you think
it means תהום tehom means buried, like it's buried deep underground and
you walked over it and you weren't aware and therefore it was
unknowable. But טומאת התהום tumat hat'hom gets abstracted by the גמרא Gemara
to mean as I
said. not just physically it's in the depths. So what would be
that case? So the גמרא Gemara says, really, that's every single case
of a woman who's a זבה. zavah. What's the הלכה halakha of
a זבה? zavah? A woman bleeds, has blood during not her menstrual
period. So the first day she's טמאה tmeah that day, let's say
she bleeds on a Sunday, it's not during her menstrual period. She's
טמאה tmeah that Sunday. Monday she has to go a day without
bleeding. If she goes Monday without bleeding then she's... she goes to
the מקוה mikveh Monday morning, she goes the rest of the Monday
without bleeding, everything is fine. If she bleeds later in Monday then
it becomes two days of טומאה. tumah. And then she has to
go Tuesday, so she goes to the מקוה mikveh Tuesday morning and
if she's טהורה tehorah the rest of Tuesday that's the end. But
if she bleeds later on Tuesday then it becomes three days in
a row, then she's a זבה גדולה, zavah gedolah, she needs to
have seven clean days. That's the תורה Torah הלכה halakha of a
זבה. zavah. Sunday or Monday where she only needs one day is
called a שומרת יום כנגד יום. shomeret yom kineged yom. She observes
one day of טהרה taharah opposite the day of טומאה. tumah. Now
anytime the woman in that scenario, she bled on Sunday, she went
to the מקוה mikveh Monday morning, right now from 8 a.m. on
Monday after she's gone to the מקוה mikveh till the end of
the day, this is this unknowable period of what its status will
be, right? Because this period, right now nothing's happened, but if she
sees anytime between now and sunset, retroactively she'll have been טמאה tmeah
that whole time. That, says the גמרא, Gemara, is a טומאת התהום.
tum'at hatehom. It's a period of unknowable טומאה. tumah. And what would
happen if she brought the קרבן פסח korban pesach during this period?
Does the idea that the ציץ tzitz works for טומאת התהום tum'at
hatehom is it limited to corpse טומאה tumah or would it apply
to other things as well? That's the גמרא's Gemara question.
It's so powerful, it's just the feeling anyone has when they know
something is different. They go to the doctor and they're waiting for
a diagnosis.
Oh, that's an interesting analogy, right?
There's something that's reality but you can't and don't know what it
is.
That's a very powerful experience.
It's a very nice analogy. Is this
טומאת התהום tum'at hatehom or that's an example?
It's an example. טומאת התהום tum'at hatehom is any טומאה tumah which
is unknowable at the time and only gets found out later.
If the ציץ tzitz only works for טומאה, tumah, does it work
for other...
only for טומאה tumah according to the גמרא. Gemara.
What's the context?
So the ציץ tzitz and טומאה? tumah? Yeah, I don't know, right.
Yeah,
let's... you know, the גמרא Gemara doesn't deal... only purely in sort
of like the הלכה halakhic aspect of it.
Where does this come from?
Well, the תורה Torah does say that ונשא אהרן את עון הקדשים
אשר יקדישו בני ישראל. venasa Aharon et avon hakodashim asher yakdishu bnei
Yisrael. Okay, but what is the idea of the ציץ? tzitz? You
know, one could say, okay, the simple פשט pshat maybe that one
could say about that is that the ציץ tzitz is about carrying
God's name. You know, ציץ tzitz means like looking, always that sense
of consciousness of God's presence. The idea of the גמרא Gemara elsewhere
compares the ציץ tzitz with the תפילין tefillin that is between... on
the head, between the eyes, has God's name, the constant consciousness of
God's presence. He had both?
He did, there was a space for the תפילין. tefillin. But anyway,
the גמרא Gemara makes the comparison and you could say that the
whole idea of... the whole idea of a קרבן korban becoming טמא
tamei is a קרבן korban has sanctity and טומאה tumah often comes
from lack of vigilance, right? Not being constantly conscious and
aware. No, that's true, that's true. No, no, but again, the classic
ציץ tzitz works on if the... if the קרבן korban became טמא,
tamei, not if the person did. So it's a... in a way
there's a counterbalance that the idea there is that it was a
lack of vigilance of something that carried God's name, the קרבן, korban,
and protecting it from that sort of... from being... not careful about
it and then letting other things come in contact with it. You
know, in a way the ציץ tzitz and we say the same
thing by תפילין tefillin is you're carrying God's name and you have
to be conscious about not letting other things distract your focus of
attention. So I think that you can see some type of an
aspect there, but that works... that's the emphasis on the objects that
become טמא. tamei. Let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says like this, והתניא, vehatanya, did we not teach
in a ברייתא, baraita, bottom of פא עמוד ב. peh aleph amud
bet. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, שומרת יום כנגד יום shomeret
yom kineged yom ששחטו וזרקו עליה, sheshachtu vezarku aleha,
a woman who is observing Monday opposite Sunday, Sunday she bled, she
went to the מקוה mikveh Monday morning, right now she was waiting
Monday expecting to be טהורה tehorah and they went and they brought
a קרבן פסח, korban pesach, Monday was ערב פסח erev pesach and
they brought a קרבן פסח korban pesach for her, ואחר כך ראתה,
ve'achar kach ra'atah, and then she bled later on Monday, אינה אוכלת,
einah ochelet, she can't eat that night because she's טמאה, tmeah, ופטורה
מלעשות פסח שני, uph'turah mila'asot pesach sheni, but she doesn't have to
bring a פסח שני. pesach sheni. The קרבן korban was good. Why
was the קרבן korban good? Retroactively we find that she was טמאה
tmeah during that time. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, why is she not
have to bring a פסח, pesach, why was she יוצא? yotzei? לאו
משום דרמא ציץ, Lav mishum derama tzitz,
isn't it because the ציץ tzitz worked for her? So you see
that the ציץ tzitz works for unknowable טומאה, tumah, טומאת התהום, tum'at
hatehom, even when it's not related to a dead body. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רמי, Amar Rami, no, you could say, לא,
lo, it's not... that's not the reason. It has nothing to do
with the ציץ. tzitz. משום דקסבר רבי יוסי מכאן ולהבא היא מטמאה,
Mishum dekasavar Rabbi Yose mikan ule'haba hi mitam'ah,
maybe it has nothing to do with the ציץ, tzitz, maybe רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose holds that a woman who becomes a זבה, zavah,
if she goes to the מקוה mikveh Monday morning and then she
bleeds 3 PM Monday afternoon, that between 8 AM and 3 PM
she was טהורה. tehora. Maybe he says that bleeding on the second
day doesn't turn it into a continuous טומאה tumah retroactive no, it
becomes a new טומאה. tumah. So she was טמאה tamei Sunday, now
she's טמאה tamei again Monday starting at 3 PM, but from the
time she went to the מקווה mikvah until she bled again she
was טהורה tehora and that's why it's good,
even if the sun didn't go down, even if the sun...
right, she was good! So it's the second day of טומאה tumah
for her is an independent day, it's not a continuous and she
can't eat that night because she's טמאה, tmeya, but the קרבן korban
was still good. גמרא Gemara
says, alright, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this.
דתניא, Detanya, can you really say that since we teach in a
ברייתא, braita, רבי יוסי אומר Rebbe Yose omer זב על שתי ראיות,
zav al shtei reiyot,
similar to a זבה zavah is the הלכה halakha of a זב,
zav, except that a זב zav is a man who has a
penile flow, but it's not a semen, it's something else that by
its character is defined as זיבה, zivah, and if he has it,
rather than a woman who's bleeding three days, it's about bleeding not
during the menstrual cycle, by a woman it's about time, by a
man it's about the nature of the flow. By a woman it's
three consecutive days, by a man it is two flows or three
flows, depending on how serious of a טומאה tumah we're talking about,
but it's not about consecutive days. So if he had two of
these
flows, okay, and it's now his seventh day, and ערב פסח Erev
Pesach is the seventh day, so assuming that he goes through all
of today, the seventh day, without another flow, he'll be טהור tahor
tonight and he'll be able to eat his קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
Okay. So ששחטו וזרקו עליו בשביעי שלו, sheshachatu vezarku alav bashvii shelo,
so they brought the קרבן פסח korban pesach for him on his
day seven of his, and after that, and then guess what happened,
of all things, right before nightfall, ראה, ra, he bled, not bled,
he had another flow. So then it turns out that he had
a completely טמא... tamei... he was טמא tamei during that period.
For a woman it has to be blood, and for a man
it has to be something that by its character is defined as
זיבה, zivah, okay? It's not anything other than semen, there's a whole
discussion how to identify
זיבה. zivah. Okay. So and he so he bled after the קרבן
פסח korban pesach was brought. וכן Vechen and similarly שומרת יום כנגד
יום shomeret yom keneged yom in the case we were talking about,
a woman who bled one day and was keeping the next day,
observing it that it should not be... that there should be no
blood. ששחטו וזרקו עליה בשני שלה sheshachatu vezarku aleha basheni shela that
they brought her קרבן פסח korban pesach on her second day, on
Monday. ואחר כך ראתה veachar kach raata and then what would you
know, later Monday that afternoon she bled again. הרי זו מטמאה משכב
ומושב למפרע Harei zu metama mishkav umoshav lemafrea so retroactively anything that
they sat on, the reason we say sat on is because a
זב zav and a זבה zavah have a special הלכה halakha that
things that they're sitting on, even if they're not touching, become טמא
tamei and they even become an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, so it's
a very heavy הלכה halakha and a unique הלכה halakha by זב
zav and זבה. zavah. טומאת מושב, Tumat moshav,
anything they sat on retroactively is טמא. tamei. ופטורין מלעשות פסח שני
upeturin milaasot pesach sheni
and they're exempt from פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, so you see it
says retroactively they are טמא. tamei. So don't tell me it means
during between 10 AM and 3 PM or whatever it was, they're
טהור. tahor. No! It says once they... once he bleeds or he
has a flow, retroactively they were טמא tamei the whole period. So
you see even though they were טמא tamei retroactively, the פסח pesach
is still good. It must be because of the ציץ. tzitz. You
see the ציץ tzitz works even though it's not about a corpse
טומאה. tumah. So no, גמרא Gemara says אמרי, amri, no, not necessarily,
it might have nothing to do with the ציץ. tzitz. מאי למפרע?
מדרבנן. Mai lemafrea? Miderabbanan. No, maybe again רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose says
the
טומאה tumah only begins
on day two, or for the זב zav on day seven. It
only starts up again at the time of the next flow, not
retroactive. Why did it say retroactive? That's rabbinic. So rabbinically we'll consider
it as if you were continuously טמא, tamei, but biblically you were
טהור tahor during that period of having gone to the מקווה mikvah
on day seven for the man or day two for the woman,
you were טהור. tahor. And if there's another flow, biblically it's the
new טומאה tumah begins at the moment of the other flow, and
therefore the פסח pesach was good during that interim. Retroactive, that's only
rabbinic. ואף רב אושעיא סבר מטמא למפרע מדרבנן Veaf Rav Oshaya savar
metama lemafrea miderabbanan and proof that even רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya holds
that there's an idea according to רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yose, we're within
רבי יוסי, Rebbe Yose, that the whole retroactive טומאה tumah is only
rabbinic. Okay, how do you know that? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, רב אושעיא אומר... Rav Oshaya omer... now there's a
little bit of a problem because although רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya is
understood to be the editor of the ברייתא, braita, we never have
a ברייתא braita where רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya is quoted. And later
in the ברייתא braita רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan is going to respond
back to him, and we certainly never have a ברייתא braita where
רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan appears who's an אמורא. Amora. So if you
look at the side they switch the גירסא girsa from דתניא detanya
to אמר רב אושעיא. amar Rav Oshaya. Okay. But it's quite interesting
that it quotes it here as a ברייתא braita but it does
not work. רב אושעיא אומר, Rav Oshaya omer, רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya
says: אבל זב שראה בשביעי שלו, Aval zav shera bashvii shelo, if
a זב zav saw on his seventh day, סותר שלפניו, soter shelifanav,
it retroactively means that there was a continuous טומאה, tumah, it's not
a new טומאה, tumah, it undermines the previous days that were without
flow, and it's a continuous טומאה. tumah. למפרע, Lemafrea, retroactively. אמר ליה
רבי יוחנן, Amar leh Rebbe Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan says to
him... לא יפסיד אלא יומו? lo yafsir ela yomo? So why does
it undermine and make continuous? It should only, you should only lose
out this day. Now that's the simple sense of ר' יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan where he sounds like ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying is
a זב Zav needs seven days, he bleeds on the seventh day.
Fine, you lose day seven. Tomorrow will count as day seven. Now
that is a radical idea because we always say that the seven
days of a זבה Zavah or the seven days of a זב
Zav are continuous. So the גמרא Gemara cannot accept ר' יוחנן's Rabbi
Yochanan's statement on face value even though it sounds like he's saying,
"Let it just count against you for one day." So here's what
the גמרא Gemara says, it rejects the simple read of ר' יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, ממה נפשך. mi-mah
nafshach. Here's the גמרא Gemara like sort of interrupting. Wait, make up
your mind. אי קסבר למפרע הוא מטמא, ei kasavar l'mafrea hu metamei,
if ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds that a flow on the last
day retroactively causes continuous טומאה, tumah, then אפילו כולם נמי נסתר, afilu
kulu nami nistor, then all the previous days should be undermined because
you didn't have seven continuous days. You have to, so it's all
טומאה. tumah. ואי קסבר מכאן ולהבא הוא מטמא, v'ei kasavar mikan u'l'haba
hu metamei, and if he holds that it's a new טומאה, tumah,
יומו נמי לא ליסתר, yomo nami lo listar, it doesn't make you
lose day seven. It's the beginning of a new טומאה, tumah, but
it doesn't make you lose day seven. אלא, Ela, so ר' יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan cannot mean you just lose one day. We've never heard
of such a thing that you just lose one day. You need
a continuous period. אלא אימא, Ela eima, here's what ר' יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan must have said, לא ליסתר ולא יומו.
lo listar v'lo yomo.
He must have said, meaning, he must have said why when you
flow on day seven does it undermine the entire period? It shouldn't
have any effect or maybe it should start a new טומאה, tumah,
but it shouldn't even undermine even one day of the past טומאה.
tumah. Okay, let it start a new טומאה. tumah. So that's what
he's saying. ואמר ליה ר' יאשיה v'amar lei Rabbi Yoshia said back
to ר' יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, ר' יוסי כוותך. Rabbi Yossi kevatcha. Oh,
you want to say that when you have a flow on day
seven it's a new טומאה, tumah, it doesn't undermine the past because
your seven days are already ended as it were in the morning
even though it wasn't the end of seven days. So ר' יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says like you, that if you have a flow on
the last day after the beginning of the day started the טהרה,
taharah, that that's a new טומאה. tumah. What do you mean what's
the point of having seven clean days? Look, one principle that I
haven't said that's important to understand about this is the principle of
מקצת היום ככולו. miktzat hayom k'kulo. It's like the idea of אבלות.
aveilut. Like by אבלות, aveilut, somebody sitting שבעה shivah gets up at
the beginning of their seventh day. So here, the idea is that
this woman, let's take the case of the woman, she bled on
Sunday, she needs Monday to be טהור. tahor. She begins Monday, she
has one hour of טהרה, taharah, that's מקצת היום, miktzat hayom, that's
like all of Monday was טהור tahor and she goes to the
מקוה mikvah 8 a.m. Monday morning. But if she bleeds later, you
can't say the one hour that started Monday counted like all of
Monday if she bled later, it shows you that the end of
Monday was טמא. tamei. And that's therefore it retroactively undermines and is
considered a continuous טומאה. tumah. That's the classic understanding that it's למפרע,
l'mafrea, that it causes it to be continuous when it's a bleeding
anytime later on Monday. Or by the זב. Zav. Day seven of
his, I don't know, Friday, is his day seven. Until now Sunday
through Thursday have been טהור tahor and now Friday also the beginning
was טהור, tahor, he went to the מקוה. mikvah. So that's like
מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat hayom k'kulo, like he's done. But what happens
if he bleeds later on the day? So there you could see
why you could either be of the opinion like we normally assume,
since the day ended with טומאה, tumah, retroactively it's like there was
a bleeding during the seven days and it interrupted it and you
were טמא tamei continuous. That's the למפרע. l'mafrea. But we could also
see ר' יוסי's Rabbi Yossi's position which is no, you started the
day okay, you went to the מקוה, mikvah, anything that happens later
in the day is a new טומאה. tumah. Okay, so that's the
issue here. Your last day begins with טהרה, taharah, whether for a
woman it's only one day, whether for the זב Zav it's seven
days, or a woman it could also be her seventh day if
she was a זבה גדולה, Zavah Gedolah, begins the טהרה, taharah, you
went to the מקוה, mikvah, and then you bleed later. Is that
something completely new or does that mean that retroactively the whole day
was no good? So ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says when you bleed
on day, when this man sees on day seven it should just
be a new טומאה. tumah. And ר' יאשיה Rabbi Yoshia says back
to him, oh you want to say that? ר' יוסי כוותך. Rabbi
Yossi kevatcha. You've got ר' יוסי Rabbi Yossi that goes like you.
Okay, that ר' יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, now we see that ר'
יאשיה Rabbi Yoshia understands like we've been saying, that according to ר'
יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, the טומאה tumah begins anew when it happens later
in that day, in that last day. So the גמרא Gemara says
now how could you say that, והא ר' יוסי אומר מטמא משכב
ומושב למפרע? v'ha Rabbi Yossi omer metamei mishkav u'moshav l'mafrea? Don't we
have the ברייתא braita that we quoted before that ר' יוסי Rabbi
Yossi says when you bleed on day seven or the flow on
day seven, retroactively the entire period was טמא? tamei? אלא לאו שמע
מינה מטמא למפרע מדרבנן. Ela lav shma mina metamei l'mafrea mid'rabbanan. You
see that according to ר' יאשיה, Rabbi Yoshia, when ר' יוסי Rabbi
Yossi says if you have a flow later that day retroactively you
are טמא, tamei, that's only rabbinic. שמע מינה, Shma mina, that's a
good proof. So what have we said until now? We have said
that ר' יוסי Rabbi Yossi says two things. Let's forget the זב
Zav case, we'll focus on the זבה, Zavah, at least have one
case. This זבה, Zavah, she bled but they went to the מקוה
mikvah Monday morning. Okay, and then you brought a קרבן פסח korban
pesach for her in the middle of Monday, and then end of
Monday she bled again. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says it is
a good קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Now, there's two ways of understanding
it. One is he says the normal thing, retroactively she was טמאה
teme’ah all of Monday, but since she was there was no way
of knowing when the פסח pesach was brought, that’s טומאת התהום tum’at
ha-tehom and the ציץ tzitz works. That’s option number one. Option number
two that the גמרא Gemara is saying is no, רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose forget the ציץ. tzitz. He’s saying a special הלכה halakhah about
a זב zav and a זבה zavah that if the last day
started okay, טהור. tahor. If she bleeds later in the day, it's
a new טומאה. tum’ah. And the reason the קרבן פסח korban pesach
was good was because she was טהורה tehorah during that time. Ah,
doesn't רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose say retroactively she's טמאה teme’ah that time?
Yeah, דרבנן, de-rabbanan, but דאורייתא de-oraita she was טהורה tehorah during that
time and that’s why the קרבן פסח korban pesach was good. Now,
she should bring that קרבן לכתחילה. korban le-khatekhilah. Yeah, well she's always
bringing it לכתחילה le-khatekhilah because she doesn't know at that time, but
right, there was no problem with
the קרבן. korban. You didn't need a ציץ. tzitz. There’s nothing problematic
about it. She was completely טהורה tehorah during that time. And this
idea to טומאה דרבנן tum’ah de-rabbanan of משכב ומושב, mishkav u-moshav, is
it the way we treat נידה niddah today? That’s a longer question.
So let's bracket that for now. Yeah, well, maybe it's covered strictly,
but the גמרא Gemara doesn't question the idea that if the person
who brings the קרבן פסח korban pesach but doesn't eat it, they're
off the hook for פסח שני. pesach sheni. Yes, so that was
we did cover that the last few days, okay? You weren't here,
but alright, anyway,
the basic the short answer is the following.
If the פסח pesach when the blood is being thrown, when it’s
being brought, is not edible because the meat is טמא, tamei, for
example, then you’re not יוצא yotzei and you have to bring a
פסח שני. pesach sheni. Actually, there's a position of רבי נתן Rabbi
Natan בדיעבד be-di’avad you are, but let’s assume you’re not. If however
the קרבן korban when it was being brought was fine, but then
afterwards the meat became טמא tamei or afterwards you just decided you
went to bed early, you didn't eat the meat, so you’re יוצא
yotzei your bringing of the פסח pesach because when it was brought
it was fit to be eaten. You didn't do your מצוה mitzvah
of eating the meat that night, the same way you didn't do
your מצוה mitzvah of eating מצה matzah that night, but the חיוב
כרת, hiyuv karet, the obligation of bringing the קרבן פסח korban pesach
you were יוצא yotzei if when it was brought the meat was
fit to be eaten. Okay, so and the פסח שני pesach sheni
is only if you didn't do your מצוה mitzvah of bringing the
פסח, pesach, not if you didn't do your מצוה mitzvah of eating
it. Correct. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
So that’s the question so now we're saying רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says it's a new טומאה. tum’ah. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara goes
back to the issue about ולרבי יוסי u-le-Rabbi Yose about this question
about whether this idea of טומאת התהום tum’at ha-tehom works for the
כהן kohen or just for the בעלים. be’alim. So says the גמרא
Gemara the following.
Okay. ולרבי יוסי השתא דאמרת מכאן ולהבא הוא מטמא. U-le-Rabbi Yose, hashta
de-amrat mi-kan u-le-haba hu metamei. Now that we see it doesn't matter
really for our purposes right now why רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says
for this זבה zavah her קרבן פסח korban pesach worked. Either it
worked because the ציץ tzitz worked for that interim period, or it
worked because she was טהורה tehorah during that interim period. But even
but let's go with number two. He says she's only טמאה teme’ah
from the second bleeding onwards. Okay. מכאן ולהבא הוא מטמא. Mi-kan u-le-haba
hu metamei. למת גופיה אתא למעוטי מאי. Le-met gufeih ata le-ma'utei mai.
So what was the purpose of a ברייתא beraita we quoted yesterday
that says that the ציץ tzitz only works for טומאת התהום tum’at
ha-tehom of a dead body? What is it excluding? So what other
case might I need to think that the ציץ tzitz would work
for? So for זבה zavah I don’t think it needs to work
for because זבה zavah is not even a problem for רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yose, right? She's טהורה tehorah during this unknowable period. So you
don't need it to work for זבה. zavah. It does work for
מת. met. What are you telling me it doesn't work for when
you say it only works for מת? met? So what the גמרא
Gemara argued yesterday is it must be somebody came in contact with
a dead rodent, a שרץ, sheretz, in a way that it was
buried in the ground and it was unknowable and so on. And
it's saying the ציץ tzitz doesn't work for that. But the גמרא
Gemara says but if the בעלים be'alim is טמא tamei a one
day טומאה tum’ah because of a שרץ, sheretz, then he doesn't need
a ציץ. tzitz. You can bring the קרבן פסח korban pesach and
he can eat it tonight. So if it’s saying the ציץ tzitz
doesn't work, it must be who would need the ציץ tzitz to
work? Only if the כהן kohen was טמא. tamei. That would be
a problem if the כהן kohen was טמא tamei when he was
bringing. So you see the idea of the ציץ tzitz is relevant
even to the כהן. kohen. That’s why we got into this whole
conversation. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. למת גופיה אתא למעוטי
מאי. Le-met gufeih ata le-ma'utei mai. What's it coming to exclude? A,
it's not excluding זבה, zavah, that you don't even need it for.
נפשוט מיניה דבכהן והותרה לו טומאת התהום. Nifshot mineih di-bekohen ve-hutrah lo
tum’at ha-tehom. It must be it's coming to exclude a case of
like a שרץ. sheretz. And that's not relevant for the בעלים. be’alim.
It’s only relevant for the כהן. kohen. So you see that basically
the ציץ tzitz works for the כהן kohen as well, and there
by a מת met but not by a שרץ. sheretz. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר amar no you could say לעולם בבעלים, le-olam
bi-be’alim, we're still talking about the בעלים. be’alim. So why do I
need to exclude a שרץ? sheretz? Because ובפסח, u-be-Pesach, he’s bringing a
פסח, Pesach, דקסבר אין שוחטין וזורקין על טמאי שרץ. de-kasavar ein shochtin
ve-zorkin al temei sheretz. No, because he's of the opinion we’ve seen
this before that this is debated, if somebody is טמא tamei today
on the 14th, a one day טומאה, tum’ah, and will be טהור
tahor tonight, can you bring the פסח pesach for him right now?
Right now he’s טמא tamei but tonight he'll be טהור. tahor. So
this author of this ברייתא beraita would assume that a normal person
who’s טמא tamei a one
day טומאה tum’ah could not have a קרבן פסח korban pesach brought
for him. Okay, even if it's just טומאת שרץ. tumas sheretz. So
yes, an אונן onen who has this טומאה tumah would have needed
the ציץ tzitz to help. And the הלכה halacha is, sorry buddy,
the ציץ tzitz only works for טומאת מת, tumas meis, it doesn't
help for other טומאות. tumos. So you've got a one day טומאה
tumah which ironically is even more lenient than a טומאת מת, tumas
meis, but you're not going to be able to bring your קרבן
פסח korban Pesach or if you brought it it's no good. The
ציץ tzitz only works for טומאת מת. tumas meis.
So there's just five guys in the חבורה, chaburah, one guy is
טמא שרץ, tamei sheretz, they bring the קרבן, korban, and
he's out until פסח שני. Pesach Sheini. Right, one guy is טמא
מת tamei meis and he is not aware of it, and one
guy is טמא שרץ tamei sheretz and he is not aware of
it. The guy who was טמא מת tamei meis was יוצא yotzei
his קרבן פסח korban Pesach because of the special הלכה halacha that
the ציץ tzitz works for unknowable טומאה, tumah, not just unknown but
unknowable טומאה tumah for טמאי מת. tmei meis. So he was יוצא.
yotzei. He can't eat it once he finds out, but he was
יוצא. yotzei. And the guy who was טמא שרץ tamei sheretz is
not יוצא yotzei because the הלכה halacha is that the ציץ tzitz
only works for טומאת מת, tumas meis, not טומאת שרץ. tumas sheretz.
It's very bizarre; טומאת שרץ tumas sheretz is more lenient.
And he brings a קרבן korban in פסח שני? Pesach Sheini? Yeah
for sure.
The ציץ tzitz doesn't exempt you from the קרבן, korban,
it only means the קרבן korban you were יוצא yotzei that קרבן.
korban. Yes.
What if he found out later that he stepped on a שרץ?
sheretz? He didn't know.
I don't know, he
stepped... well we're going to discuss that later, okay? The scenarios will
come up later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: now
that we're done, we're not done, we haven't proven either way whether
the ציץ tzitz would work for the כהן, Kohen, but we tried
to prove it, but that's still an open question as to if
the ציץ tzitz works for the כהן. Kohen. We're going to go
back to רבי יוסי's Rebbi Yossi position. אלא לרבי יוסי, Ela leRebbi
Yossi, says the גמרא, Gemara, זבה גמורה היכי משכחת לה? zava gmurah
heichi mishkachas lah? How do you get a woman who is a
זבה גמורה? zava gmurah? Because what happens according to רבי יוסי? Rebbi
Yossi? A woman bleeds on Sunday, then Monday starts off okay, and
then she bleeds later on Monday. So according to him, this is
a new one day טומאה. tumah. It's not two days. Each day
is independent. Sunday טומאה tumah was done when Monday morning came and
she went to the מקוה mikvah and she hadn't bled first thing
Monday morning. Since she bleeds later on Monday, you're telling me it's
something new? So each day is independent. How does he get the
idea of a זבה גדולה, zava gdola, which is three consecutive? According
to him, you're always restarting the process every next day. Continuously. So
the גמרא Gemara says
היכי משכחת לה? heichi mishkachas lah? Number one, בשופך. bishofach. Right, she's
bleeding straight for three days. So that's obviously a pretty
fantastic, you know, circumstance, scenario to be describing. But איבעית אימא, iba'is
eima, right, if you want you could say כגון שרצה כל שני
בין השמשות. kegon sheratza kol shnei bein hashmashos. Thank you, my colleague,
exactly. So basically, what happens is that this woman, right, if
you have Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, right, and this is, I don't know,
this
is when it's sort of Sunday, this is
night, right, into Monday day. So if this is the בין השמשות
bein hashmashos period, right, and she's bleeding the entire בין השמשות bein
hashmashos period here, and the entire בין השמשות bein hashmashos period here,
so then when Monday starts, it did not start
בטהרה. betahara. So the reason רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi says it's a
new thing, why does רבי יוסי Rebbi Yossi say it's new? Because
in a normal scenario, she bleeds sometime on Sunday, Monday starts, here
she's טהור. tahor. This counts as, we said it's like אבילות, aveilus,
sort of מקצת היום ככולו, mikzas hayom kekulo, the day began בטהרה.
betahara. Check. Okay. Then she bleeds later. Oh, that's something new. Right?
She already had her טהור tahor from the beginning of the day.
But if the day began בטומאה betumah because she bled all of
בין השמשות, bein hashmashos, so whenever the day began, it began בטומאה.
betumah. And by the way, in this scenario, it also ended בטומאה.
betumah. And then Tuesday began בטומאה. betumah. There was never a מקצת
היום. mikzas hayom. You can't use a middle of a day as
a מקצת היום. mikzas hayom. To use מקצת היום, mikzas hayom, you
have to use the beginning of the day was okay. Maybe in
some scenarios the end of the day. But here the beginning and
the end were all בטומאה. betumah. So she had no day that
she was even a beginning of a day that she was טהור
tahor to break it up. And therefore it's considered a continuous... He
doesn't say כהרף עין keheref ayin in it?
Yes, I think that is רבי יוסי.
Rebbi Yossi. It's even cold.
That's a good point, that is רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yossi. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay,
I,
by the way, I should make a point though, you know, when
we say, because I am giving the אבילות aveilus parallel, because it's
most common parallel especially about a seven days, the beginning of a
last day. Normally by the אבילות, aveilus, what מקצת היום mikzas hayom
do you need in order to end the שבעה? shiva? It has
to be the beginning of the day. But what, what part of
the day? The morning. We don't say the night before counts, right?
So the question here is, here it sounds like that it's the
beginning of the night that counts, right? Because it says בין השמשות.
bein hashmashos. But even if she began the morning okay, why, why
did it have to have that scenario? Why didn't it say the
scenario of that the night she was טהור tahor and say that
she bled between, you know, between sunrise, between the morning, you know
what I'm saying, from right before sun breaks to the beginning of
the morning? So anyway, that leads to an interesting debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot, which is when we say מקצת היום, mikzas
hayom, do we mean the beginning of the night or do we
mean the beginning of the day? This sounds like the beginning of
the night, but we know from other areas that it's the beginning
of the day, so that's a whole discussion. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara continues. It refers to the morning twilight, whatever, בין השמשות? bein
ha-shemashot? No, the גמרא Gemara never calls it that. תוספות Tosafot has
more ingenious answers. You can look at תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, בעי רב
יוסף. Ba'ei Rav Yosef. So now we're Rav Yosef. So we had
not answered the question whether the ציץ tzitz works for the כהן,
Kohen, but it's possible it does. By a כהן Kohen who's bringing
a פסח Pesach and a and a what do you call it?
And a and a קרבן korban for a נזיר, nazir, because that's
where it matters that the owner should be טהור, tahor, so maybe
the ציץ tzitz also works for the כהן. Kohen. So בעי רב
יוסף, Ba'ei Rav Yosef, Rav Yosef asks, כהן המרצה בתמיד, Kohen ha-meratzeh
be-tamid, let's say if it's possible it works for the כהן, Kohen,
then maybe it could work for the כהן Kohen even by other
קרבנות. korbanot. By the owners, it really matters only by a פסח
Pesach and a נזיר, nazir, that's where it really matters that the
owners are טהור. tahor. But if the if the ציץ tzitz works
for the כהן Kohen being טמא, tamei, maybe it could work for
him by טומאת התהום, tumat ha-tehom, maybe it could work for other
קרבנות korbanot as well. Let's say the כהן Kohen is bringing a
תמיד, tamid, הותרה לו טומאת התהום או לא? hutra lo tumat ha-tehom
o lo? Does this טומאה tumah of the depths, unknowable טומאה, tumah,
does the ציץ tzitz work for that or not? אם תימצי לומר
כהן המרצה בקרבנותיהם, im timtzi lomar Kohen ha-meratzeh be-korbanoteihem, if when the
כהן Kohen is working, is doing the עבודה avodah of the קרבנות
korbanot of the נזיר nazir and the guy bringing the פסח, Pesach,
he even has that in parentheses, הותרה לו טומאת התהום, hutra lo
tumat ha-tehom, if it works for him what's it working for that
קרבן, korban, it works for the owners and for the כהן. Kohen.
כהן המרצה בתמיד מאי, Kohen ha-meratzeh be-tamid mai, what would we say
about him doing another קרבן, korban, a תמיד? tamid? מי אמרינן, mi
amrinan, do we say כי גמירי טומאת התהום,
ki
gemiri tumat ha-tehom, when do we have this הלכה halacha that the
טומאה tumah of the depths is somehow the ציץ tzitz works to
make it acceptable, בפסח, be-Pesach, it's only by קרבן פסח, korban Pesach,
בתמיד לא גמירי, be-tamid lo gemiri, not by other קרבנות? korbanot? או
דילמא, o dilma, or do we say יליף תמיד מפסח, yalif tamid
mi-Pesach, we can make we can learn it out? If it works
by one קרבן korban it works by another, especially if it's a
קרבן korban that's sort of like a fixed time type of a
קרבן korban that we know its that we know sort of overrides
other things. So אמר רבא קל וחומר, amar Rava kal va-chomer, so
Rava says it's a קל וחומר kal va-chomer it should work by
a תמיד tamid if it works by a פסח. Pesach. ומה במקום
שלא הותרה לו טומאה ידועה הותרה לו טומאת התהום, u-mah bi-makom she-lo
hutra lo tumah yeduah hutra lo tumat ha-tehom, in a place where
known טומאה tumah is not permissible, if you the owner are known
to be טמא, tamei, we tell you by the פסח Pesach go
bring a פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. מקום שהותרה טומאה ידועה, makom she-hutra
tumah yeduah, a place where known טומאה tumah would be allowed, which
would be what if a תמיד, tamid, if all the כהנים kohanim
were טמא, tamei, if there's nobody available, then we would allow you
to do it, right? אינו דין שהותרה לו טומאת התהום, eino din
she-hutra lo tumat ha-tehom, certainly we should allow this case of טומאת
התהום. tumat ha-tehom. Now it's a little bit strange, because what do
you mean? פסח Pesach and תמיד tamid are the same, if everybody
who's relevant is טמא, tamei, then it gets then it's allowed for
that case. So it's easier to say we're contrasting it to the
case of the what do you call it? Of the נזיר, nazir,
because a נזיר, nazir, if everybody is טמא, tamei, we still say
okay bring it later when people are טהור. tahor. נזיר Nazir isn't
allowed with טומאה, tumah, it's not a fixed time. Okay, but it
is funny, רש"י Rashi seems to say we're contrasting the תמיד tamid
to the פסח, Pesach, and I don't really understand it. But either
way, the point is if it works for the פסח Pesach it
should work for the תמיד. tamid. So אמרי, amri, so the answer
back is no, ומי דיינינן קל וחומר מהלכה, u-mi dayninan kal va-chomer
me-halacha, since when can you make a קל וחומר, kal va-chomer, use
logic when it comes to a הלכה, halacha, הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai? This idea that the ציץ tzitz works on טומאת התהום
tumat ha-tehom is understood to be הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai.
The very nature of הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai is that
it's arbitrary, so if it's arbitrary you can't use logic to to
determine what its scope is. Okay, is that the reason why this
thing is הלכה למשה מסיני halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai as opposed to something
from the תורה Torah because from the תורה Torah you can do
קל וחומר? kal va-chomer? Somewhat, somewhat, yeah, somewhat. והתניא, ve-hatanya, but we
teach it, don't we teach it in a ברייתא? braita? אמר לו
רבי אליעזר, amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, so Rabbi Eliezer said, עקיבא. Akiva.
So Rabbi Eliezer was debating with Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva was his
student, which is why he calls him by his first name. And
the question was the following: A נזיר nazir has to, you know,
start his טומאה tumah again when he comes in contact with a
dead, but there are some טומאות tumot of a dead body that
actually while they make him טמא, tamei, do not make him start
his נזירות nezirut again. Meaning, and that's called there's a category called
טומאות שהנזיר מגלח עליהן, tumot she-ha-nazir megalach aleihen, the טומאות tumot of
a dead body that a נזיר nazir has to shave and start
his whole process again. So not all types of parts of the
dead body would have that effect. So one thing that does have
that effect is coming
in
contact with a
little piece of bone, then he'd become טמא tamei and have to
start again. Now there's a debate of Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Akiva,
what about if he came in contact with a רביעית revi'it of
blood, like three and a half ounces of blood from a corpse?
Now that generally is more weighty than a piece of bone. A
piece of bone does not cause טומאה tumah in an אוהל. ohel.
A רביעית revi'it of blood of a corpse does cause טומאה tumah
in an אוהל. ohel. So Rabbi Akiva said, וקל וחומר, ve-kal va-chomer,
if a נזיר nazir shaves for the bone, he would have to
shave for the blood. And Rabbi Eliezer says back to him, עקיבא,
Akiva, עצם כשעורה הלכה, etzem ke-se'orah halacha, that the idea that you
said that the bone of a little size of a of a
barley seed, a נזיר nazir has to start over again, that's a
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. רביעית דם קל וחומר, revi'it dam
kal va-chomer, you want to extend that idea that a נזיר nazir
has to start over again to the רביעית revi'it of blood by
a קל וחומר kal va-chomer that blood is more חמור chamur because
blood causes טומאה tumah in an אוהל. ohel. What? Meaning the fact
that it's the שעורה se'orah as opposed to another bigger? No, no,
no, we're not talking about size. We're talking about the fact that
a נזיר nazir has to has to be מגלח. megaleach. The fact
that... The fact that a נזיר Nazir is מגלח megaleiach on a
little piece of bone is a הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai.
You want to apply that idea that a נזיר Nazir shaves and
starts over again from bone to blood by making a קל וחומר
kal v'chomer that blood is more חמור chamur because it causes טומאה
באהל. tumah b'ohel. ואין דנין קל וחומר מהלכה. V'ein danin kal v'chomer
m'halacha. I'm sorry, you can't apply a קל וחומר kal v'chomer to
a הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. The things that a נזיר
Nazir shaves on and starts over again is a list that we
know הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. And you can't add things
to that list based on a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, even if
logically, wow, if the bone is on there, other things should be
on. I'm sorry, it's an arbitrary list, you can't add to it.
So anyway, so you can't determine this case about the כהן kohen
based on a קל וחומר kal v'chomer because who cares whether טומאת
התהום tumas hadhom is more חמור chamur than טומאת השרץ tumas hasharetz
or not, you don't make קל וחומרים kal v'chomers on things that
are הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. And the רש״י Rashi is
actually touching on that I think as well, right? What would be
the actual דאורייתא de'oraisa case? Yeah, touch. אלא אמר רבא ילף מועדו
מועדו מפסח. Ella amar Rava, yalif moado moado m'pesach. So interesting, although
you can't use קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, which is logic, you can
use the other hermeneutic principles. So you can use גזירה שוה. gezeira
shava. So since it says במועדו b'moado by פסח pesach and says
במועדו b'moado by תמיד, tamid, that says, I mean the whole idea
of גזירה שוה gezeira shava is arbitrary, so you can use arbitrary
principles to apply arbitrary laws, you can't use logical principles to apply
arbitrary laws. So if the idea of טומאת התהום tumas hadhom works
for a כהן kohen doing a פסח, pesach, which we haven't decided
yet, maybe it only works for the owner, but if it works
for the כהן, kohen, then it should work for the תמיד tamid
because they both say במועדו b'moado and you can use that to
extend the idea of הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha Lemoshe Misinai. So anyway,
what you see from this, besides the question of does it work
for the כהן, kohen, is that the idea of טומאת התהום tumas
hadhom that the ציץ tzitz works for is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
Lemoshe Misinai. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: וטומאת התהום גופא
היכא כתיבא. v'tumas hadhom gufa heicha ksiva. Now where's it written that
the ציץ tzitz works for טומאת התהום? tumas hadhom? So the whole
point is, so as רש״י Rashi says, what are you talking about?
A second ago you emphasized that it was הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
Lemoshe Misinai. So רש״י Rashi says yes, the גמרא Gemara we just
read a second ago chronologically is later than this discussion. We're going
to see that this discussion we're about to read preceded it and
tried to base it on a פסוק. pasuk. The upshot of this
discussion is it's not based on a פסוק, pasuk, it's הלכה למשה
מסיני, Halacha Lemoshe Misinai, and that's the discussion we just read assumed
the conclusion of the discussion we're about to read. So let's read
this discussion. וטומאת התהום היא גופא היכא כתיבא. V'tumas hadhom he gufa
heicha ksiva. Where is טומאת התהום tumas hadhom written? So אמר רבי
אליעזר אמר קרא, Amar Rabbi Eliezer amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says...
Now remember, the relevance of it is primarily two people: guy bringing
a קרבן פסח korban pesach and a נזיר. Nazir. Okay, so we're
going to quote a פסוק pasuk by a נזיר Nazir first. וכי
ימות מת עליו, V'chi yamus mes alav, if a dead body dies
on him, on the נזיר. Nazir. What does it mean 'on him'?
במחוברת אליו. B'michuveras elav. It has to be clear to him that
he became טמא. tamei. If it's unknown to him he became טמא,
tamei, then it's not a problem, okay, at least he doesn't have
to start his whole process again. The קרבן korban counts. So אשכחן
ashkechan נזיר, nazir, that's fine by a נזיר. Nazir. עושה פסח מנלן?
Oseh pesach minalan? How about a פסח, pesach, that the קרבן, korban,
you were יוצא yotzei his קרבן פסח korban pesach again. The idea
being not that you're not טמא tamei and not that you don't
have to deal with the consequences of that, but if you had
this טומאה tumah unknowable and there was a ציץ, tzitz, your קרבן
korban is acceptable, your קרבן פסח korban pesach worked, your קרבן korban
of the נזיר Nazir worked. So where do you know it's true
by the פסח? pesach? אמר רבי יוחנן אמר קרא, Amar Rabbi Yochanan
amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says: בדרך. baderech. It says, right, או
בדרך רחוקה לכם o baderech rechoka lachem or you're טמא tamei or
you're in a far away place. So it has the word בדרך
baderech right after being טמא. tamei. בדרך רחוקה לכם. Baderech rechoka lachem.
במחוברת לכם. B'michuveras lachem. It has to be something known to you.
So the טומאה tumah connects to the word לכם lachem that it's
a type of טומאה tumah that's known. ריש לקיש אומר, Reish Lakish
omer, כדרך. k'derech. No, just like a path. מה דרך בגלוי, Ma
derech b'galui, the same way paths are exposed, everybody knows where the
streets are, אף טומאה נמי בגלוי. af tumah nami b'galui. It has
to be a טומאה tumah that is known. So that's how we
know that only those טומאות... tumahs... now by the way, if you
actually base it on those פסוקים, psukim, it has nothing to do
with a ציץ, tzitz, then it just means that even the טומאה
tumah itself that's unknowable is not problematic to these הלכות halachas with
or without the ציץ. tzitz. But the גמרא Gemara is now going
to reject this. מתיבי, Meisvei, the גמרא Gemara says, I'll ask you
on this. We have a ברייתא braisa that we're going to quote
in a minute in full. איזו היא טומאת התהום? Eizo hi tumas
hadhom? What's considered a טומאה tumah of depth that is unknowable? כל
שלא הכיר בה אחד בסוף העולם. Kol shelo hikir ba echad b'sof
haolam. Meaning this is the point, not just you don't know it.
You don't know it, that's a classic אונס oines or שוגג shogeg
or whatever, where the ציץ tzitz does not work for that. טומאת
התהום Tumas hadhom is it's unknowable when you came in contact with
it, nobody knew that it was there. הכיר בה אחד בסוף העולם,
Hikir ba echad b'sof haolam, if one person at the opposite side
of the globe knew that the טומאה tumah was there when you
came in contact with it, אין זה טומאת התהום, ein ze tumas
hadhom, it is not a טומאה tumah of the depth, you're טמא,
tamei, was בשוגג, b'shogeg, fine, but you have to bring another קרבן
פסח, korban pesach, the ציץ tzitz does not work in that case.
So how could we have such an extreme definition if we're basing
it from the פסוקים? psukim? If you base it on the פסוקים
psukim you quoted, it would be a much broader category, not so
narrow. Let's take a look. רבי אליעזר דאמר במחוברת אליו, Rabbi Eliezer
d'amar b'michuveras elav, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that quotes the פסוק pasuk
of מת עליו mes alav that it died on you, that it
was clear to you, you were טמא. tamei. So עד דידע הוא,
ad yadei hu, then the only issue is whether you know that
you're טמא tamei or not. It's not that it's unknowable. According to
him as long as it's not... known by you, it should be
considered you're okay, because the פסוק posuk is עליו. alav. רבי יוחנן
דאמר לכם, Rebbi Yochanan d'amar lachem, when he says the פסוק posuk
is והוכחה לכם, v'hichcha lachem, it has to be known to you,
המחוורת לכם, hamchuveres lachem, to you it's known, עד ידי בי תרין.
ad yadi bi trein. So according to him, it should still be
considered טומאת התהום tumas hatehom until two people knew. Any less than
two, it's not known to you in the plural, so it shouldn't
be enough that one person knows to get it out of that
category, you would need two people to know to get it out
of that category. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish דאמר כדרך, d'amar kederech, like
a path, עד ידי כולי עלמא. ad yadi kulei alma. So it
has to be that everybody knows of it. Like streets, everybody knows
where they are. So why is it that as soon as one
person knows, it's not טומאת התהום, tumas hatehom, if it's based on
any of these פסוקים, psukim, right, the definition of טומאת התהום tumas
hatehom should be much broader than only something that's not known to
anyone? Is this similar to the מחלוקת machlokes about the nature of
a ספק safek like a כוי? koy? Like in other words, a
ספק safek which is knowable but we just don't know it, and
unknowable by definition? Yeah, I mean, so that's true, although this is
not by definition because this is still just a question of facts.
It's just everybody is ignorant of the facts. It's not something that,
I mean, you are right though, I would say that the זבה
zava case is more by definition. The very nature of the זבה
zava is it's not that there's a certain dead body and we
don't know where it's buried or whatever, you know, it's that it's
impossible to know until something else happens. But סתם stam a normal
case of טומאת התהום tumas hatehom is that there's a body buried
underground and nobody knows. Exactly. Exactly. אלא, ela, says the גמרא, Gemara,
it can't be based on the פסוק. posuk. If it was based
on the פסוק, posuk, it would be a bigger category. טומאת התהום
הלכתא גמירי לה. tumas hatehom hilchasa gemiri lah. It's a tradition, it's
a הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא. ukra asmachtah
b'alma. The פסוק posuk is just a biblical support, but it's not
really the source of it. Now we get to finally finishing this
discussion of when does it work that the ציץ tzitz works, and
what constitutes the scenario of טומאת התהום. tumas hatehom. One more question.
Yes. This definition seems somewhat manipulatable, or subject to manipulation. In what
way? If you don't search, in the case of the dead body,
you don't know where, so you don't have to excavate, right? Right.
Oh, I don't have time today to excavate, so nobody's going to
know, whatever. Right. So that's a good question. If you know there's
a body buried somewhere here and you don't know exactly where, that's
probably הוי ידוע havei yadu'a that somebody does know about it. Meaning
the question is, you're assuming know about it means you have to
know its exact location, as opposed to if you know it's somewhere
in the region, that might already not be טומאת התהום. tumas hatehom.
Let's see, let's see what the cases are. Okay, the גמרא Gemara
is going to get to describing the scenario in a minute. First,
we have to deal with one final question about when it works.
So let's take a look. אמר מר בר רב אשי, amar Mar
bar Rav Ashi, לא שנו, lo shanu, when does it work that
the ציץ tzitz works if the person became טמא? tamei? Again, remember,
the ציץ tzitz normally works if the blood is טמא tamei or
the meat is טמא, tamei, and you were unaware when it was
זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. By טומאת התהום, tumas hatehom, this unknowable טומאה,
tumah, it works even if you, the owner, is טמא. tamei. Now,
under what scenarios? How much were you aware, at what stage did
you become aware of the problem? So let's take a look. לא
שנו, lo shanu, when does the ציץ tzitz work for טומאת התהום?
tumas hatehom? אלא שנודע לו לאחר זריקה, ela she-noda lo l'achar zerikah,
that you were ignorant when the blood was being thrown. Okay, דכי
אזדריק דם, d'ki izdrik dam, when the blood was thrown, שפיר אזדריק,
shapir izdrik, it was thrown properly. Everybody thought you were טהור, tahor,
it was an unknowable טומאה, tumah, and everything only became revealed afterwards.
אבל נודע לו לפני זריקה, לא מרצה. aval noda lo lifnei zerika
lo meratze, If it became aware before the blood was thrown, then
sorry buddy, you know, before we know there was a problem, before
the זריקת הדם, zerikas hadam, the ציץ tzitz isn't going to work
here. Wasn't that a מחלוקת? machlokes? We were then, you know, somewhat
discussed before, but that wasn't about טומאת התהום. tumas hatehom. That was
about the normal ציץ tzitz work, normally. So מתיבי, meisivei, says the
גמרא, Gemara, asking on this, המוצא מת מושכב לרוחבה של דרך. hamotzei
meis mushkav l'rochbah shel derech, Now we're going to start getting to
the scenarios of טומאת התהום. tumas hatehom. If you found a מת
meis that was basically somebody walked over a path. And then after
the person walked over the path, they excavated it and they found
that there was a dead body that was lying across the entire
width of the path. So it's impossible that the person did not
go over the dead body, because a dead body is טומאה tumah
even if you go over it and it was the entire width
of the path. So wherever the person went, he would have been
טמא. tamei. So that would be a case, המוצא מת מושכב לרוחבה
hamotzei meis mushkav l'rochbah של דרך, shel derech. so לתרומה טמא. l'trumah
tamei. You found this, and if it's for a purpose of תרומה,
trumah, then you have to assume you're טמא. tamei. Even though it
was רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, and we normally say a ספק ברשות
הרבים safek b'reshus harabim is טהור, tahor, this isn't a ספק. safek.
It was the entire width of the path. לנזיר ועושה פסח טהור.
l'Nazir v'oseh pesach tahor. For a נזיר Nazir and the guy who
made a פסח, pesach, that's the case of טומאת התהום, tumas hatehom,
you're טהור. tahor. Okay, because it was unknowable at the time. So
the גמרא Gemara says, one minute. כל טמא וטהור להבא הוא. kol
tamei v'tahor l'haba hu. It didn't say for the נזיר Nazir and
עושה פסח oseh pesach the קרבן korban was good. It says you're
טהור. tahor. You're טהור tahor means that you can act on your
state right now. You can assume, treat yourself as if you're טהור
tahor for something you're about to do. So it sounds like you
discovered after you walked over it that this מת meis was going
across the way, since you're bringing a פסח, pesach, you're טהור, tahor,
no problem, go ahead and bring your קרבן. korban. You're not really
טהור, tahor, but it does still sound like it's לכתחילה. lechatchila. It
doesn't sound like it's just a בדיעבד, b'dieved, so presumably it works
even before you did the זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. אלא, Ella, and
the גמרא Gemara steps out that argument. אלא אי אתמר הכי אתמר,
Ella ee itmar hachi itmar, fine, if it was said, here's how
it was said. אמר בר אבא אשי, Amar Bar Abba Ashi, לא
תימא נודע לו אחר זריקה הוא דמרצה, lo teima noda lo achar
zerika hu d'meratze, don't think that the ציץ tzitz only works for
טומת התהום tumas hatehom only if you became aware after the blood
was thrown, אבל נודע לו לפני זריקה aval noda lo lifnei zerikah,
לא מרצה, lo mirtzeh. but before זריקה zerika it should not work,
אלא אפילו נודע לו לפני זריקה מרצה, ela afilu noda lo lifnei
zerika meratze, even beforehand, which is like shocking. You walked over this
dead body an hour before you brought your קרבן פסח, korban Pesach,
you found out about it, okay, and you say, oh, don't worry,
at the time it was unknowable, there's the ציץ, tzitz, גזונטהייט, gezunte
heit, go bring your קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, even though you know
you're טמא tamei right now. So רש"י Rashi and תוספות, Tosafos, based
on other evidence and a תוספתא Tosefta and other things, pull back.
And they say the גמרא Gemara does not mean that you can
always bring it even before זריקה. zerika. The גמרא Gemara is only
talking about the narrow strip of time between שחיטה shechita and זריקה.
zerika. If you found out before שחיטה, shechita, it doesn't work and
you can't bring it. But after you've שחט shechted the קרבן, korban,
now you found out and the כהן's Kohen got the blood here,
and the process already began, in that scenario you can finish the
process. Since you started the process and it was okay and you
were ignorant and you didn't know and you had the טומת התהום
tumas hatehom and the ציץ tzitz or whatever, after the שחיטה shechita
you can finish. But they do not accept the simple sense of
this גמרא Gemara that you can ממש mamash do it לכתחילה, lechatchila,
that would be way too radical. Fine, so take the narrow רש"י,
Rashi, תוספות Tosafos take. Still, in that case, הותרה hutra or דחויה?
dchuya? Does he have to go to the מקווה? mikvah? Does he
have to bring a קרבן? korban? Right, well the גמרא Gemara says,
well, you have to, no, again, you are really טהור, tahor, although
the phrase, טמא, tamei, although the phrase was טהור, tahor, you're really
טמא בגברא, tamei b'gavra, but the point is לכתחילה lechatchila you can
bring the קרבן פסח korban Pesach according to this. At least it's
הותרה hutra in the sense of if the whole point of the
גמרא Gemara is that the language of טהור tahor is a לכתחילה
lechatchila language, the כהן Kohen finds out and we tell him לכתחילה
בזורק הדם, lechatchila bi-zoreik hadam, which is also shocking. Even by limiting
it to the space between שחיטה shechita and זריקה, zerika, you're still
telling him לכתחילה lechatchila you know the person is טמא, tamei, go
ahead and bring it in anyway. והגברא V'hagavra still is, oh clearly
he has to go to the מקווה. mikvah. Right, the whole idea
again, the technical term of מרצה meratze does not mean it removes
טומאה, tuma, it means it makes the קרבן korban acceptable. יכול לאכול?
Yachol le'echol? No, you cannot eat it. It only means you're יוצא
yotzei the קרבן, korban, cannot eat it, yes. So the whether, so
this idea that it's about discovering the between time of the שחיטה
shechita and זריקה zerika might that have to do with when is
the actual offering technically הלכה halacha because it's at the time of
שחיטה? shechita? No, but clearly the קרבן korban is only considered to
be brought once there was a זריקת הדם, zerikas hadam, but I
mean the עבודה avoda starts at the moment of שחיטה, shechita, right,
which is how they deal with, which is how they explain this
middle position. Okay, we have to, we have five minutes, we're going
to go to the משנה. Mishna. גופא, Gufa, המוצא מת מושכב לרוחבה,
Hamotzei meis mushkav l'rochba, now we're finally going to get to the
scenario of טומת התהום. tumas hatehom. So you found this dead body
buried along the entire length, width of the of the road. של
דרך, Shel derech, לתרומה טמא, l'truma tamei, if it's תרומה truma then
it wasn't a ספק, safek, you definitely it was the whole entire
width, you're definitely טמא. tamei. ולנזיר ולעושה פסח, U'l'nazir u'l'osei pesach, although
you are definitely טמא, tamei, at the time it was unknowable and
it was a literal תהום, tehom, it was buried in the depths.
טהור. Tahor. Which is not lying on the street. No, no, no,
you מוצא, motzei, you dug it up and you found it after
the guy had walked over it. So again, what we say טהור
tahor means, it means that the bringing of the קרבן korban was
acceptable, or if it was found after the שחיטה shechita you could
do the זריקה. zerika. You're not really טהור, tahor, although I know
the language is misleading. במה דברים אמורים שאין לו מקום לעבור? B'meh
devarim amurim she'ein lo makom la'avor? When is that, that for תרומה
truma you're טמא, tamei, if it was found in a way that
there was no way you could have walked over the road without
having walked over the dead body. אבל יש מקום לעבור, Aval yeish
makom la'avor, if the body was by the width of the road
but there was like, I don't know, a foot at an edge
that it did not cover and you don't remember where you walked,
it's possible you were walking at the side of the road. So
in that case אף לתרומה טהור. af l'truma tahor. The principle is
ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים. safek tuma b'reshus harabbim. It's a road, it's
a רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, so even though most likely you walked
over the dead body, since it's possible you walked over that space
where the dead body did not extend, you're טהור. tahor. במה דברים
אמורים, B'meh devarim amurim, now also, when is it true that if
the entire length you're assumed to be טמא tamei for תרומה truma
purposes? שמצאו שלם, Shemetza'o shaleim, that it was a whole body. אבל
משובר מפורק, Aval meshubar m'furak, if it was broken into pieces, טהור,
tahor, then even though it extended the length you're טהור. tahor. Why?
שמא בין הפרקים עבר, Shema bein haprakim avar, maybe you walked between
the gaps between the pieces, assuming the gaps were big enough that
it would have been possible to have walked in a way that
you did not actually step over the body. Okay, now, ובקבר, u'v'kever,
however, if the body was in a grave, אפילו משובר מפורק טמא,
afilu meshubar m'furak tamei, then even if it's in different pieces you're
טמא, tamei, מפני שקבר מצרפו. mipnei she'kever m'tzarpo. There's a הלכה halacha
that if you think about it. Every body has a coffin, and
the coffin is a טפח tefach off the body, so it should
stop the טומאה, tumah, and you should be totally fine. So the
הלכה halacha is that the coffin itself gets the טומאה tumah of
the dead body. And we learn this from פסוקים psukim and whatever.
So if even if it's in little pieces, if it's all in
a coffin, it's not going to help you, because the whole coffin
makes it like one big unit and the entire coffin is a
source of טומאה tumah and it's not going to help the כהן.
Kohen. קבר? Kever? You mean a קבר kever just means buried as
a grave, not in a coffin? No, קבר kever on the guy
right. So רש"י Rashi says, so right. So רש"י Rashi says it
means a coffin. תוספות Tosafot says, first of all תוספות Tosafot is
bothered. תוספות Tosafot says if it's a coffin, how could it be
טומאת התהום? tumath hatehom? Somebody knows about it. Okay. So okay, maybe
it wasn't going back to the טומאת התהום tumath hatehom case, it's
talking about the תרומה truma case. But תוספות Tosafot basically says yes,
it just means that it was intentionally buried, although it still raises
the question, maybe somebody knows about it. So anyway right, תוספות Tosafot
discusses that issue about what קבר kever means, whether it means a
coffin or not. Okay. Now, but we'll keep going. במה דברים אמורים,
Bameh devarim amurim, now when is this true that again, if there's
a little space, you can be טהור tahor even for תרומה truma
because maybe you didn't go over it? במהלך ברגליו, Bimehalech beraglav, if
you're walking on your legs. אבל טעון, Aval ta'un, if you are
carrying a load, או רכוב, o rachuv, or you're on an animal,
טמא, tamei, לפי שהמהלך ברגליו lefi shehimehalech beraglav אפשר שלא יגע ולא
יאהיל. efshar shelo yiga velo ya'ahil. יאהיל? Ya'ahil? יאהל? Ya'ahal? יאהל. Ya'ahal.
Okay. Anyway, it's possible that you could walk without touching or without
going directly over it if there are breaks. אבל טעון או רכוב,
Aval ta'un o rachuv, if you are carrying a load or you're
riding on an animal, אי אפשר שלא יגע ולא יאהיל. i efshar
shelo yiga velo ya'ahil. It's not possible. Why? Presumably, I don't know,
if it's a big long load, so the load will, you know,
create its own אוהל ohel and the טומאה tumah will hit like,
you know, if you have a beam, hit the beam and carry
it to you. Or you'll just have so much weight with you,
you'll be, you know, you won't be able to walk on a
narrow line, you'll be walking all across. Why on top of the
אוהל? ohel? Well, yeah. I, yeah, well no, that's a different question
and בעל חי ba'al chai isn't מפסיק mafsik and so on. But
it's, I still don't get exactly why. I mean, if you're on
a horse, I mean, why don't we just say it depends if
there's a big enough gap for a horse to walk through? I
have to tell you, I don't really understand why. And you're on
the roof of a building that's an אוהל. ohel. What? If you're
on, yeah, then the אוהל ohel stops there, which is what Michael
asks. Why doesn't the horse stop it? But, you know, okay. But
that's animals, whatever. That's, okay, all this we'd have to learn אהלות
Oholot to discuss that more. Now, okay. במה דברים אמורים Bameh devarim
amurim בטומאת התהום. be'tumath hatehom. Now when is it true, going back
to the case of the guy who brings the פסח Pesach that
it's okay, if it was a טומאה tumah of the depths. אבל
טומאה ידועה, Aval tumah yedu'ah, but if it was known to have
been there, you were ignorant but other people knew about it, then
טמא. tamei. ואיזו היא טומאת התהום, Ve'eizo hi tumath hatehom, and this
is what we quoted earlier, כל שלא הכירה אחד בסוף העולם, kol
shelo hekirah echad besof ha'olam, nobody in the entire world was aware
of it. אבל הכירה אחד בסוף העולם, Aval hekirah echad besof ha'olam,
if one person in the world was aware of it, אין זו
טומאת התהום, ein zu tumath hatehom, then it does not work and
even for the guy bringing the פסח, Pesach, even though almost nobody
knew about it, if one person knew about it, sorry, and you
did not fulfill your פסח Pesach obligation. Now, מצאו טמון בתבן בעפר
ובצרורות, Matza'o tamun beteven be'afar u'vitzrorot, if you found the dead body
buried in not in like underneath the ground, but you found it
in straw, in loose dirt, in stones, הרי זה טומאת התהום. harei
zeh tumath hatehom. Again, assuming nobody knew about it, that would still
be considered a טומאה tumah of the depths. במים באפילה ובניקיקי הסלעים,
Bemayim ba'afelah u'venikikei hasla'im, let's say it wasn't known not because it
was buried under some serious like, you know, physical material, but it
was in water, so you could have looked and it was transparent,
or it was dark, but in light time it would have been
known, or it was in a little niche in a cave, but
again, not actually covered up, אין זו טומאת התהום. ein zu tumath
hatehom. That's not טומאת התהום. tumath hatehom. Now why not? So תוספות
Tosafot says because presumably in those scenarios there is someone who knows
about it. You could also say even if nobody knows about it,
it's גלוי, galuy, right, in theory it's not so hard to find
in those cases, it's more you just have to look and you'll
see it. The other case you'd have to uncover, here it's actually
not even covered and therefore it's not in the category. ולא אמרו
אלא טומאת התהום אלא למת בלבד, Velo amru ela tumath hatehom ela
lemet bilvad, which is what started the discussion. This whole הלכה halacha
applies only by מת met and not by שרץ. sheretz. We said
that was the whole point, that it does not apply by שרץ.
sheretz. Our discussion before was what case do we have to exclude
that it could have applied, but the הלכה halacha only applies by
מת. met. Whether it applies by זבה zavah or not was the
discussion, we might not need it by זבה zavah based on רבי
יוסי'ס Rabbi Yose's position. Okay. Shoot.