Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is צדי ו, Tzadi
Vav, and we pick up at the very bottom of צדי ה
עמוד ב Tzadi Hei Amud Bet
with the following. We are dealing with the fact of it's like
now we are sort of in wrap-up mode it seems. We have
the last few משניות mishnayos and the last פרק perek dealing with
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So we're touching on a couple of topics.
It's still a little strange the organization because the משנה mishna we
did right before this was about the difference between פסח ראשון Pesach
Rishon and פסח שני. Pesach Sheini. The משנה mishna that's coming up
is a difference between פסח לדורות Pesach L'doros and the פסח Pesach
that they did in מצרים. Mitzrayim. Smack in the middle is a
discussion about פסח הבא בטומאה. Pesach HaBa B'Tumah. So I'm not exactly
sure why this is here in the middle, but anyway, so we're
discussing that if it's בא בטומאה, ba b'tumah, if everybody else is
eating it when טמא, tamei, so even though this היתר heter does
not apply to people that are טומאה יוצא מגופה tumah yotzei migufa
like a זב zav and a זבה, zava, if they eat they're
not חייב כרת. chayav kares. And then the position of רבי אליעזר
Rebbe Eliezer that says the same is true about ביאת מקדש, bias
mikdash, that the same way other טמא tamei people are able to
enter, even though that היתר heter does not allow and does not
apply to a זב zav and a זבה, zava, if they enter
they're not חייב כרת. chayav kares. And now the גמרא Gemara is
having a fun time trying to figure out like would there still
be some restrictions. So within רבי אליעזר, Rebbe Eliezer, what about going
into the היכל? heichal? Would that still be חייב chayav for a
normal person? Is that place always off-limits? And now within that in
that vein we pick up at the last line of צדי ה
עמוד ב. Tzadi Hei Amud Bet. בעי רב יוסף: Bai Rav Yosef:
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked, דחקו
טמאי מתים ואכלו אימורי פסח הבא בטומאה. dachaku t'mei meisin v'achlu emurei
pesach haba b'tumah. Now we're going back to the רבנן Rabbanan that
say that it's only a היתר heter for eating. Let's still ask
within the eating, let's say the funny דחקו dachaku obviously it's borrowed
from the language of רבא Rava because whoever it was who asked
the question, לבי אליעזר l'Rebbe Eliezer יכול דחקו yachol dachaku which is
a תנא tanna we know forcing your way in which is about
ביאת עזרה. bias azara. He's talking now about eating, but maybe this
forcing your way in because we're about to see what they're going
to eat. If people that are טמא tamei forced their way and
ate from the אימורים emurim from the innards of the פסח pesach
that you burn on the מזבח. mizbayach. Okay, so that's got a
couple of problems. First of all it's קדשים kodshim and that they're
not allowed to eat so it's a prohibition of a זר. zar.
It might be a problem about if it's the חלב, cheilev, it
might be and then eating חלב cheilev would be חייב כרת. chayav
kares. But okay maybe it's not the חלב, cheilev, maybe it's like
the יותרת על הכבד yoseres al hakaved one of the inner organs
that gets burnt. But you're a זר, zar, but besides being a
זר zar would you also be חייב chayav for being a טמא?
tamei? If you ate the אימורים emurim in a time when טמא
tamei people are allowed to eat the meat of the פסח, pesach,
would you also have that prohibition of a טמא tamei eating the
אימורים? emurim? Okay, הבא בטומאה מהו? haba b'tumah mahu? What's the הלכה?
halacha? Top of צדי ו עמוד א. Tzadi Vav Amud Aleph. מדאישתרי
טומאת בשר אישתרי נמי טומאת אימורים? mi d'ishari tumas basar ishari nami
tumas emurim? Do we say since the טומאה tumah of the בשר
basar has been made permissible since you're allowed to eat בשר basar
even though you're טמא, tamei, the same would be true about the
אימורים? emurim? We'll see in a minute. או דילמא, o dilma, or
do we say מאי דאישתרי אישתרי מאי דלא אישתרי לא אישתרי? mai
d'ishari ishari mai d'lo ishari lo ishari? What was permitted was permitted,
what was not was not? To some degree one wonders if this
also is connected to the question of הותרה hutrah or דחויה, d'chuyah,
but not necessarily because here the question is does the whatever it
is we're doing to say it's allowed does it go beyond the
normal parameters of the people we're giving the waiver to? And again
we're not actually saying or the situation that it's ממש מותר mamash
muttar but it would be enough to say you wouldn't be חייב
כרת chayav kares for these acts.
So it's not like the you know eating בשר בחלב basar b'chalav
on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
No
it's different. How is it? No it's more like eating בשר בחלב
basar b'chalav for a person who is פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh and
has to eat on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. We're dealing with a
היתר heter and then does the היתר heter how does it spill
over? Let's read the answer. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: מכדי mechdi let's
take a look. טומאת אימורים מהיכא איתרבי? tumas emurim meicha israbi? How
do you know that there's a prohibition of eating the אימורים emurim
when you're טמא? tamei? Again in addition to the prohibition of a
זר zar eating אימורים emurim everyone's a זר zar even a כהן
kohen for this. How do you know there's a prohibition of being
טמא tamei where do you learn it out from?
מהיכא איתרבי? meicha israbi? מטומאת בשר, mi tumas basar, from the פסוק
pasuk that prohibits eating בשר basar when you're טמא. tamei. דכתיב: d'ksiv:
אשר להשם. asher l'Hashem. It says you know if you eat
מבשר אשר... mibasar asher... כל טהור יאכל בשר... kol tahor yochal basar...
מבשר זבח השלמים אשר להשם וטומאתו עליו. mibasar zeivach hashelamim asher l'Hashem
v'tumasov alov. So why did it have to say מזבח השלמים אשר
להשם? mizeivach hashelamim asher l'Hashem? אשר להשם asher l'Hashem is totally redundant,
it's מזבח השלמים. mizeivach hashelamim. So we say it's לרבות את האימורים
l'rabos es ha'emurim that there's also a prohibition of being a טמא
tamei and eating אימורים emurim again in addition to the prohibition of
a
זר. zar. כל היכא דאיתא טומאת בשר איתא טומאת אימורים. kol heicha
d'isa tumas basar isa tumas emurim. When the prohibition of eating בשר
basar בטומאה b'tumah applies, the prohibition of eating אימורים emurim applies. כל
היכא דליתא טומאת בשר ליתא טומאת אימורים. kol heicha d'lesa tumas basar
lesa tumas emurim. When that prohibition does not apply it does not
apply to the אימורים. emurim. Again it's only the אימורים emurim of
the פסח. pesach. You eat the אימורים emurim of another קרבן, korban,
you eat the בשר basar of another קרבן korban you're חייב. chayav.
But since the בשר basar of the פסח pesach is the prohibition
of טומאה tumah is waived the same is true regarding the אימורים.
emurim.
Just for טומאה tumah though you're still חייב chayav for eating אימורים
emurim anyway because you're a זר. zar.
Right exactly, you just don't get the other חיוב chiyuv for טומאה.
tumah. בעי רבי זירא: Bai Rebbe Zeira: so רבי זירא Rebbe Zeira
asked: אימורי פסח... emurei pesach... פסח מצרים. pesach Mitzrayim. Now that we're
talking about אימורין, imurin, so this is not about the טומאה tumah
question. This actually is a perfect transition to the next משנה. mishnah.
Oh, אימור eimur of the פסח. pesach. I have a question about
that. Let's say when they brought the פסח pesach in Egypt, what
did they do with the אימור? eimur? You know the the the
lintel and the doorposts served as a type of מזבח. mizbe'ach. Lintel,
I spelled lintel something else. Lintel served as a type of מזבח
mizbe'ach that you do the זריקת הדם. zerikat hadam. But how about
the burning of the אימור? eimur? Where did they do that in
מצרים? Mitzrayim?
All right. If they just clarified that this was the איסור issur
of the טומאה tumah of the אימור eimur
and not of the אכילה? achilah? Exactly.
That's an איסור issur of זר, zar, correct.
Okay. So אימורי פסח מצרים היכא אקטירינו? imurei pesach Mitzrayim heicha aktirinu?
How did they how did they burn them up? How'd they offer
them on the altar? So אמר ליה אביי ומאן לימא לן דלא
שביסקי עבדי? amar lei Abaye uman leima lan dela sheviski avdi?
First of all, who says that they didn't go ahead and do
like a nice roasting? Presumably it means maybe they made a little
fire and that represented the fire you know the fire of the
מזבח mizbe'ach the same way the doorpost represented the where you put
the blood of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So number one, maybe they did
something. What do I know? Fire? שביסקי sheviski means roasted. Okay, so
roasted on a spit. Number one. ועוד, ve'od, number
two, התנא רב יוסף ג' מזבחות היו שם. hatana Rav Yosef gimmel
mizbechot hayu sham. There were three altars there.
על המשקוף ועל שתי המזוזות. al hamashkof ve'al shtei hamezuzot.
So those are the three altars. You could put the blood on
any one of them. Okay, so obviously it's a fascinating you know
read backwards of halakhic categories onto that reality. Each one served as
like a מזבח. mizbe'ach. And that's where the זריקת הדם zerikat hadam
was. וסו מידי אחריני לא הוי vesu midei achrinei lo havei and
nothing and there was nothing else so there was no altar so
maybe they didn't you know they didn't burn it at all. Okay,
they showed they just ate it maybe. If again, if it wasn't
the חלב. chelev. Maybe that's what the שביסקי sheviski means also. They
roasted and ate. There's an interesting תוספתא Tosefta about this which I'll
read in a minute. I first want to read the משנה mishnah
because this is a perfect transition to the משנה mishnah about what
they did in פסח מצרים. pesach Mitzrayim. So let's take a look
at the משנה. mishnah. מה בין פסח מצרים לפסח דורות? mah bein
pesach Mitzrayim lepesach dorot? What was the difference between the פסח pesach
they did in מצרים Mitzrayim and the פסח pesach of future generations?
So פסח
מצרים מקחו בעשור. pesach Mitzrayim mikcho be'asor. The משנה mishnah only mentions
a few. The תוספתא Tosefta is much longer. So I'll I'll bring
in the תוספתא Tosefta in a few bit in a few minutes.
פסח מצרים מקחו מבעשור. pesach Mitzrayim mikcho mibe'asor.
פסח מצרים, pesach Mitzrayim, right? It says that בעשור לחודש הזה ויקחו
להם איש שה לבית אבות שה לבית. be'asor lachodesh hazeh veyikchu lahem
ish seh leveit avot seh labayit. Right,
so
there's the מצוה mitzvah of taking it on the tenth day, the
the sheep or the goat and preparing it for the פסח. pesach.
וטעון הזיה באגודת אזוב ועל המשקוף. veta'un hazayah ba'agudat ezov ve'al hamashkof.
You would sprinkle it, first of all, you'd have to use an
אגודת אזוב, agudat ezov, a a bunch of what is this, hyssop
or something. And and number two, you would do it on the
lintel ועל שתי המזוזות ve'al shtei hamezuzot and on the doorposts. To
obviously you would do זריקת הדם zerikat hadam but it wouldn't be
with for the future but it wouldn't be with a hyssop and
it wouldn't be on the door. מזבח. mizbe'ach. ונאכל בחפיזון בלילה vene'echal
bechipazon balaylah and it would be
eaten it would be eaten בחפיזון, bechipazon, it would be eaten you
know quickly, you know
you have to eat it in a rushed manner. And you would
have to eat it בלילה. balaylah. And obviously that's not לדורות. ledorot.
And בלילה אחד, balaylah echad, one night. Of course the lesson is
one minute, that is לדורות ledorot that you eat it בלילה אחד.
balaylah echad. Okay, so we'll get back to that. Okay, ופסח דורות
נוהג כל שבעה. u-pesach dorot noheg kol shiv'ah. And פסח דורות pesach
dorot for future generations, there the point is בלילה אחד balaylah echad
meaning the whole מצוה mitzvah was one night as opposed to as
opposed to פסח דורות. pesach dorot. Although the meat was eaten one
night, the יום טוב Yom Tov applied for the week וחג המצות
vechag hamatzot and the eating of מצה. matzah. Now it's quite interesting
because the משנה mishnah here is conflating or the the exactly the
קרבן פסח korban pesach which we've clearly been talking about all along,
פסח pesach is meant the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Now of course
it doesn't only mean that because the next פרק perek begins ערבי
פסחים, arvei pesachim, you know what would you do and you know
and and the whole so פסח pesach also does mean the יום
טוב. Yom Tov. But the focus here has totally been on the
קרבן korban and to and then to say oh and the other
difference about the פסח מצרים pesach Mitzrayim was now we switch to
פסח pesach of the יום טוב Yom Tov of פסח. pesach. They
didn't really have a יום טוב. Yom Tov. They it only was
only one day whereas לדורות ledorot we have a יום טוב Yom
Tov of seven days. So it conflates those.
Right. Okay. But I'm just saying it's interesting the shift of פסח
pesach from the קרבן korban to פסח pesach of the יום טוב
Yom Tov you know since it's all been about the קרבן korban
the last like five פרקים. prakim. Okay, let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. הגמרא... hagemara... wait.
Yes, yes, mention I had a לשון lashon question. מאי היכא
מיתרבי, mai heicha mitrabi,
is there a difference between that and מנלן? menalan? As it's specifically...
Yeah, I mean specifically
wanting to know if they're inclusive of another category.
Yes, because what we're holding introducing is is that it piggybacked on
the meat so it's like it's using a language of that it's
been it's been you know sort of inclusive,
included as from a פסוק pasuk about the meat. Exactly. Okay, מנלן?
menalan? Speaking about מנלן. menalan. How do you know that that the
differ that it only applies as taking it on the tenth was
only in מצרים? Mitzrayim? דכתיב, dechativ, the פסוק pasuk says דברו אל
כל עדת ישראל לאמר בעשור לחודש הזה ויקחו. dabru el kol adat
Yisrael leimor be'asor lachodesh hazeh veyikchu.
Okay, ישכוח. yishkoach. How do you know that's only for מצרים? Mitzrayim?
So it says זה zeh מקחו בעשור. mikcho be'asor. בעשור לחודש הזה
ויקחו. be'asor lachodesh hazeh veyikchu. So הזה hazeh not only on the
month... But on the this קרבן korban *korban*, this one is taking
it down the tenth, not other קרבנות korbanot *korbanos*. הזה hazeh מקחו
בעשר *hazeh mikcho be-asor* ואין פסח דורות pesach dorot מקחו בעשר *ve'ein
pesach doros mikcho
be-asor*, not for future generations. אלא מעתה ella me'atah *ela me'ata* says
the גמרא gemara *Gemara*, if that's true, והיה לכם למשמרת עד ארבעה
עשר יום *ve'hayah lachem l'mishmeret ad arba'ah asar yom*,
you shall watch it sort of, you know, for four days, which
we learned that means that they're also inspecting it over four days
and, you know, double and triple checking that there are no blemishes.
לחדש *l'chodesh*. So should we say לחדש הזה hazeh *l'chodesh hazeh*? So
should we say the הזה hazeh *hazeh* also says this idea of
inspecting is also only for the קרבן korban. *korban* for פסח מצרים
pesach mitzrayim *Pesach Mitzrayim*? הכא נמי *hacha nami* would we say the
same idea because of the לחדש הזה hazeh *l'chodesh hazeh* that הזה
hazeh טעון ביקור ארבעה ימים bikur arba'ah yamim קודם שחיטה shechita ואין
אחר טעון ביקור bikur *hazeh te'un bikur arba'ah yamim kodem shechitah v'ein
acher te'un bikur*? That only this needs four days of checking for
blemishes and no other קרבן korban *korban*? You can't say that. It's
the same by the first פסוק pasuk? *pasuk*. No. Okay. So asking
for consistency. והתניא Vehatanya, *ve'ha tanya* we taught in a ברייתא braita,
*braisa*, בן בג בג אומר omer *Ben Bag Bag omer*. So בן
בג בג *Ben Bag Bag*, somebody that most of us only know
from פרקי אבות *Pirkei Avos*, actually says something in other halachic discussions.
בן בג בג *Ben Bag Bag* says מניין לתמיד שטעון ביקור ארבעה
ימים bikur arba'ah yamim. קודם שחיטה shechita, *minayin l'tamid she'te'un bikur arba'ah
yamim kodem shechitah*? How do you know that even the תמיד tamid
*Tamid*, the daily sacrifice, you have to be checking it for four
days before you bring it? And therefore they had four days' worth
of sheep in a special chamber where they, you know, they would
be rotating which one was on bat and which one was three
days out and so on, so they'd all be anyway being checked
for four days. Anyway, how do you know that? שנאמר תשמרו tishmoru
להקריב לי במועדו *shene'emar tishmeru l'hakriv li b'mo'ado* by תמיד tamid *Tamid*,
you should observe to do it in its time. ולהלן הוא אומר
*ul'hallan hu omer* and over there by the פסח pesach, *Pesach* it
says by the פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim? *Pesach Mitzrayim* והיה לכם למשמרת
*ve'hayah lachem l'mishmeret*. So תשמרו *tishmeru* and משמרת mishmeret *mishmeret*. So the
same way the משמרת *mishmeret* of the פסח pesach, *Pesach*, the watching,
עד ארבעה עשר יום *ad arba'ah asar yom* is for four days
of inspecting, so תשמרו *tishmeru* of the תמיד tamid, *Tamid* is four
days of inspecting. מה להלן טעון ביקור ארבעה ימים bikur arba'ah yamim
קודם שחיטה shechita אף כאן טעון ביקור ארבעה ימים bikur arba'ah yamim
קודם שחיטה shechita, *mah le-hallan te'un bikur arba'ah yamim kodem shechitah af
kan te'un bikur arba'ah yamim kodem shechitah*. So now we got a
problem. So you say הזה hazeh *hazeh* limits you to פסח מצרים
pesach mitzrayim. *Pesach Mitzrayim* by taking it on the tenth, so if
that's true it should limit פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim? *Pesach Mitzrayim* to
the idea of four days' inspection, and we see it's not limited
to פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim, *Pesach Mitzrayim*, we see it applies even
to the תמיד tamid *Tamid*. So the גמרא gemara, *Gemara* says no,
שני התם דכתיב תשמרו *shani hatam d'chtiv tishmeru*. There there's an extra
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that says תשמרו *tishmeru* by the תמיד tamid, *Tamid*
that tells you you do extend it and you do apply it
outside of the תמיד tamid, *Tamid*. And not only that, by the
way, parenthesis, you're also right that even פסח דורות pesach dorot, *Pesach
Doros* you inspect for four days. It said because by פסח pesach,
*Pesach* as well, פסח pesach, נמי דורות נמי הא כתיב *Pesach nami
Doros nami ha chtiv* it says ועבדת את העבודה va'avadta et ha'avodah,
הזאת בחדש הזה hazeh *ve'avadeta et ha'avodah hazot bachodesh hazeh*. You should
do this service on this month and although החדש הזה hazeh *hachodesh
hazeh* has been saying you only do these things for this קרבן
korban *korban* and not others, here we say different. So את העבודה
הזאת *et ha'avodah hazot*, that's a פסוק pasuk! *pasuk* that speaks future
pointing, right? That's at the end there the פרשה parsha. *parsha* which
talks about you'll come into the land and you'll you know and
speaks about, that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* speaks about the פסח דורות Pesach
dorot? *Pesach Doros*, right? Again I don't have the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
off the top of my head, but anyway, that's the one that
is speaking about you about what happens in the future you'll come
into the land and you do like you do this month at
you know at that time. So therefore that's exactly extending the experience
of פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim. *Pesach Mitzrayim* for the דורות *doros*. ועבדת
ve-avadta את העבודה הזאת *ve'avadeta et ha'avodah hazot* that you're doing for
this עבודה *avodah* in פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim. *Pesach Mitzrayim* בחדש הזה
hazeh *bachodesh hazeh* that month in the future. So this is a
פסוק pasuk: *pasuk* that is all about taking פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim
*Pesach Mitzrayim* and repeating it לדורות ledorot. *l'dorot*. And from there we
learn the idea... So wait, one minute Michael, let me finish the
question. Okay, from there we learn the idea שיהיו כל עבודות חדש
זה zeh כזה *she'yiyu kol avodos chodesh zeh ka-zeh*. All the things
you did in this month by פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim *Pesach Mitzrayim*,
everything you do in the future should be like you did in
the פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim *Pesach Mitzrayim*. So basically you have a
contradiction. We're trying to limit some things to פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim.
*Pesach Mitzrayim* because it says החדש הזה hazeh. *hachodesh hazeh*, but a
later פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* at the end of the פרשה parsha *parsha*
says you do like you did this month, you do like this
קרבן korban *korban*, you're going to do it in the future and
that everything should be like the פסח מצרים pesach mitzrayim *Pesach Mitzrayim*.
So to the end of the דף daf, *daf* what we're going
to be doing is basically trying to say pretty much everything is
included and only a very small number of things are specific to
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach, *Korban Pesach*. How we get to choose,
we'll worry about, but that's going to be the point. So saying
you know what, you're partly right. The idea that the idea that
what do you call it, that מקחו בעשר *mikcho be-asor*, that we
learn is only פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim, *Pesach Mitzrayim* from הזה hazeh.
*hazeh*. But other ideas, we're going to see a whole list of
ideas, but starting with the idea of checking for four days, is
applied to other קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. It's applied to the תמיד *Tamid*
from תשמרו *tishmeru*, it's applied to future פסחים *Psachim* from ועבדת את
העבודה הזאת *ve'avadeta et ha'avodah hazot*. You're right, those things do apply
to other things. The only thing that doesn't is this idea of
מקחו בעשר *mikcho be-asor*. Now of course I'm waiting for Michael or
somebody to ask, one minute, if you don't have to take future
פסחים *Psachim* on the tenth, then how are you still supposed to
check it for four days? Right, in if you if you have
to check it for four days, then you got to take it
on the tenth. So I have two answers to that. My answer
was, well I'll tell you what רש"י's Rashi *Rashi's* answer, my answer
was you could have taken it earlier. Okay. That's one answer. רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says the opposite, if
you
missed... If you didn't do four days, at least do three days,
at least do two days. Okay, so that's an idea that exists
distinct from taking it on the tenth, which is the specific issue
of משכו וקחו, or רש"י Rashi says you could have five sheep
and you're spending four days inspecting them, and at the last minute
you decide I'm going to take this sheep. Whereas פסח מצרים Pesach
Mitzrayim משכו וקחו בעשור meshcho u'kchu ba'asor means that you sanctify it
and you designate the specific one you're going to take on that,
you know, on that day. So the idea of ביקור ארבעה ימים
bikur arba'ah yamim is there have to be sheep, it has to
be from a sheep that has been inspected for four days. It
doesn't mean the קרבן korban, has to be taken on the tenth.
Why does he say, and if you check it earlier, and you
know, because there's also from like,
why not just check the
last day, check it twice on each of the two days, morning
and afternoon?
I mean, you mean do it on alternate days?
No, no, no, like take it on the 12th, right, or if
you check it on the 12th morning twice on the 12th, twice
on the
13th?
Right, why do you need four days? Yeah, it does seem that
it's not, it does seem that exactly, I agree, it does seem
that it's not just to ensure that it's תמים, tamim, it does
seem that there's an idea of תשמרו and משמרת and exactly that
the care that you put into it and the preparation exactly is
part of the idea. What about the חבורה chabura of people that
were attached to פסח מצרים?
Pesach Mitzrayim,
Well,
we're going to get to the חבורה chabura aspect in a minute.
Okay, so the basic point is, yes, you're right, פסח דורות Pesach
dorot, is תשמרו את העבודה הזאת בחודש הזה tishmoru et ha'avodah hazot
bachodesh hazeh is ביקור bikur for ארבעה ימים arba'ah yamim and תמיד
is ביקור ארבעה ימים. bikur arba'ah yamim The one thing we're going
to exclude is משכו וקחו בעשור. meshcho u'kchu ba'asor. So the גמרא
gemara says like this, אלא מעתה ella me'atah, says the גמרא, gemara,
now that we're saying that, where am I? אלא הוא הזה, ella
hu hazeh, yeah אלא הוא הזה, ella hu hazeh, thank you. אלא
הוא הזה ella hu hazeh למעוטי l'ma'utei פסח שני דלא בעי. pesach
sheini d'la ba'ei. So now so what then, what is the function
of the word הזה hazeh that does appear by checking it for
four days? Right? It says, it's what's the פסוק? pasuk It says
והיה לכם למשמרת עד ארבעה עשר יום לחודש הזה. vehaya lachem l'mishmeret
ad arba'ah asar yom lachodesh hazeh. So if we're so focused on
הזה hazeh limiting, so you've now told me that ביקור ארבעה ימים
bikur arba'ah yamim. applies to תמיד and פסח, pesach that's okay, that
does extend, so what does הזה hazeh exclude? No, הזה hazeh excludes
פסח שני pesach sheini which is similar to פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim,
In what way is פסח שני pesach sheini similar to פסח מצרים?
Pesach Mitzrayim. No יום טוב yom tov to it, it's just about
the קרבן. korban Okay, so it says you're right. הזה hazeh by
ביקור ארבעה ימים bikur arba'ah yamim, excludes one קרבן פסח korban Pesach,
שני לדורות. ledorot But otherwise, ביקור ארבעה ימים bikur arba'ah yamim. applies
to תמיד, applies to פסח מצרים, Pesach Mitzrayim. we do extend a
lot of things from פסח, pesach, I mean פסח דורות, Pesach dorot
we do extend a lot of things from פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim
We're excluding two things based on two different הזהs. The הזה that
appears by taking it on the tenth, that's the only קרבן korban?
that applies to is פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim. The הזה that appears
by ביקור ארבעה ימים bikur arba'ah yamim that's excluding פסח שני pesach
sheini from ביקור bikur ארבעה ימים.
Everything else is included.
Now, by the way, it is interesting that we're excluding פסח שני
pesach sheini because, as תוספות tosfot points out, the idea is not
only a תמיד needs ביקור bikur. ארבעה ימים, but all קרבנות korbanot
need ביקור ארבעה ימים. You might have said maybe תמיד, maybe a
פסח, pesach those are like קרבנות ציבור, korbanot tzibbur, maybe קרבן יחיד
korban yachid not, but there's another גמרא gemara. that says all קרבנות
korbanot. do. And according to that other גמרא, gemara that makes it
bizarre that פסח שני pesach sheini should not require ביקור ארבעה ימים
if every single קרבן under the sun does. But that's not the
פשט pshat of this גמרא. gemara The פשט pshat of this גמרא
gemara is that certain things like if you would maybe קרבנות ציבור,
korbanot tzibbur, תמיד, מצרים, mitzrayim, פסח, Pesach, that's ביקור that does not
apply to פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim or to פסח שני. pesach sheini.
Wasn't it דקא בעי, d'ka ba'ei, it's similar to the פסח מצרים
Pesach Mitzrayim in that it's the only a פסח Pesach and not
a יום טוב. yom tov. And therefore the הזה that's limiting ביקור
is limiting something parallel to it that doesn't do ביקור. What about
נתן Natan who makes the חגיגה chagiga exactly like פסח, Pesach agree
with this? I don't know. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like, also in the context of a יום טוב. yom tov. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara. says like this, אלא מעתה, Ella mei-ata,
so now basically the until the end of the דף, what we're
going to be saying is the עמוד, amud, not the צד ב,
tzad bet, is let's just limit everything they did in פסח Pesach
in the פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim. because it says הזה. And the
answer to every single thing is going to be yes, but it
also says ועבדת את העבודה הזאת בחודש הזה, va'avadta et ha'avodah hazot
bachodesh hazeh, which means you replicate what you've done. Okay, so basically
we're going to pretty much say everything gets replicated except a small
number of things we've that are obviously local to פסח מצרים. Pesach
Mitzrayim Let's take a look. אלא מעתה דכתיב ואכלו את הבשר בלילה
הזה. ella me'atah d'chtiv v'achlu et habasar balaila hazeh. There's a lot
of הזה. Here's a little fun homework assignment: go and count the
number of times it says הזה during that פרשה. parsha. Anyway, ואכלו
את הבשר בלילה הזה, v'achlu et habasar balaila hazeh, הכא נמי דזה
נאכל בלילה ואין אחר נאכל בלילה? hacha nami d'zeh ne'echal balaila v'ein
acher ne'echal balaila? So only פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim is eaten at
night? אמר קרא ועבדת את העבודה הזאת. amar k'ra va'avadta et ha'avodah
hazot. So ועבדת את העבודה, you do it, you replicate. אלא מעתה
למה לי? ella me'atah lama li? So what does the הזה doing
over there? כדי דרבי אלעזר בן עזריה ורבי עקיבא. k'dei d'rabbi elazar
ben azaryah v'rabbi akiva. That there's a debate in ברכות, berachot, רבי
אלעזר בן עזריה rabbi elazar ben azaryah and רבי עקיבא. rabbi akiva.
רבי אלעזר בן עזריה rabbi elazar ben azaryah learns out from הזה
that... ואברתי בארץ מצרים Mitzrayim בלילה הזה *V'avarti b'eretz Mitzrayim balaila hazeh*
that you could only eat the קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach* until
חצות chatzot. *Chatzot*. Okay? That's why a lot of people have a,
are מקפיד *makpid* to finish, get to the אפיקומן *Afikoman* by חצות
chatzot. *Chatzot*. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva* says no. הזה *Hazeh*
is not limiting it to חצות Chatzos *Chatzot*. So what's הזה *hazeh*
doing? It's saying that you don't eat it the following night. It
doesn't function like a שלמים shlamim? *shlamim*. A normal שלמים shlamim *shlamim*
is two days and a middle night. Maybe this one would be
two nights and a middle day. So don't think you get the
next night to eat it. No, it's only the night of the
15th, not the night of the 16th. Okay. אלא מעתה Ella mei-ata,
דכתיב *Ella me'atah dechtiv*, let's do another הזה *hazeh* or a similar
thing. וכל ערל arel לא יאכל בו bo *V'chol arel lo yochal
bo*. Again, by פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim *Pesach Mitzrayim*. Any uncircumcised should
not eat from it. So maybe only it? הכא נמי בו אינו
אוכל אבל אוכל בפסח דורות hacha nami bo eino ochel aval ochel
be-Pesach dorot? *Hacha nami bo eino ochel aval ochel b'Pesach dorot*. Maybe
it's okay to eat in a future פסח Pesach, *Pesach* if you're
an ערל arel *arel*? So no. אמר קרא ועבדת Amar Kra ve-avadta,
את העבודה *Amar kra va'avadeta et ha'avodah*. So ועבדת *va'avadeta* says, yeah,
replicate. אלא בו למה לי Ella bo lama li? *Ella bo lamah
li*? So what's the בו bo? *bo* doing by the ערל arel
*arel*? בו bo. אינו אוכל אבל אוכל הוא במצה ומרור *Bo eino
ochel aval ochel hu b'matzah u'maror*. He doesn't eat the פסח Pesach
*Pesach* but he still eats מצה Matzah *matzah* and מרור Maror, *maror*.
Now that is a big question why you needed a פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk* for that because מצה matzah *matzah* and, or I'd say it
two ways. If you're talking about an independent מצוה *mitzvah* of מצה
matzah *matzah*, so why would I think an ערל arel *arel* couldn't
do the independent מצוה *mitzvah* of מצה matzah *matzah*? If you're talking
about, although we'll see later that maybe I would have just thought
to extend it to other מצוות *mitzvot* of the night. If you're
talking about the מצה *matzah* and מרור maror, *maror* eaten with the
קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*, so I get that you're allowing him
to eat these, normally accompany the פסח Pesach, *Pesach*, he doesn't eat
the פסח Pesach *Pesach* but he can eat the stuff that accompanies
it. But why would he want to eat the פסח Pesach. *Pesach*,
the מצה *matzah* and the מרור *maror*? Right? I mean are people
aware of this? I think I've mentioned it before. That conceptually the
תורה Torah *Torah* emphasizes only one מצוה *mitzvah* for the מצה *matzah*
and that's the same מצוה *mitzvah* as the מרור *maror*. Not an
independent מצוה *mitzvah* but the way you eat the קרבן פסח Pesach,
*Korban Pesach*. חז"ל Chazal *Chazal*, מה מצה זו *mah matzah zo*, חז"ל
Chazal *Chazal* have identified a separate מצוה *mitzvah* of אכילת מצה *achilat
matzah* by itself. Now, which is why מרור בזמן הזה דרבנן *maror
b'zman hazeh deRabbanan* because you don't have קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*.
Now if you're not eating the קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*, in
terms of the מצוה *mitzvah* of the accompaniments of the פסח Pesach.
*Pesach*, מצה *matzah* and מרור *maror*, I'd have no motivation to do
that. Right? Why should I bother? Right? So do I, I don't
have a מצוה *mitzvah* of eating מרור דאורייתא בזמן הזה *maror d'Oraita
b'zman hazeh*. The פסוק *pasuk* doesn't have to tell me it's מותר
*mutar* for me to eat מרור *maror* which means I can do
the מצוה *mitzvah* of מרור *maror*. There is no מצוה *mitzvah* of
מרור *maror*. So what why do I need a פסוק *pasuk* to
tell me it's מותר *mutar* for me to eat מרור *maror*? So
maybe the point is okay there's no מצוה *mitzvah*, but if you
wanted to eat מרור *maror*, maybe we would have thought that the
תורה Torah *Torah* would have prohibited me even if there's no מצוה
*mitzvah* because it would have looked like a pseudo-פסח Pesach *Pesach*. So
it has to tell me, no, it's okay, you can eat מרור
*maror*, you don't have to, but you want to eat מרור *maror*,
you know, עס געזונטערהייט *es gezunterheit*. Okay. That's one way of saying.
But again funny that you needed the פסוק *pasuk*. So so no
there's no independent מצוה *mitzvah* of מרור *maror*. So the other argument
would be that מרור *maror* is לאו lav דוקא *lav davka*. We're
talking about the independent מצוה *mitzvah* of מצה *matzah*. And then it's
saying, okay, but you still have a מצוה *mitzvah* of מצה *matzah*.
Don't think that just cause you're, and then we understand because I
might have said if if you're פטור *patur*, maybe all the מצוות
*mitzvot* are תלוים זה zeh בזה *tluyim zeh b'zeh* and if you're
excluded from פסח Pesach. *Pesach* you'd be excluded from מצה *matzah*. But
the inclusion here of מרור *maror* is interesting. But at the end
of the day it's telling me that an ערל arel *arel* does
eat, is מחויב *mechuyav* in מצה *matzah* and is allowed to eat
מרור *maror*. Okay. אלא מעתה ella mei-ata? *Ella me'atah* says the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. So let's do another one. כל בן נכר Ben Neichar,
לא יאכל בו bo. *Kol ben nechar lo yochal bo*. It says
by פסח מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim, *Pesach Mitzrayim*. Anybody who is foreign. Now
the simple sense is a non-Jew, but חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* understood you
don't need a פסוק *pasuk* for a non-Jew. So they understood it
to mean that you are שנתנכרו מעשיו לאביו שבשמים *shenitnachru ma'asav l'Aviv
shebashamayim*. You've become distant and foreign to God. You've basically become an
apostate and given up your faith. Okay and there you're not allowed
to eat from the קרבן פסח Pesach, *Korban Pesach*. So הכא נמי
דבו אינו אוכל אבל אוכל הוא לפסח דורות *hacha nami de'bo eino
ochel aval ochel hu l'Pesach dorot*. We'll say you could eat from
פסח דורות Pesach dorot *Pesach dorot*? No. אמר קרא ועבדת Amar Kra
ve-avadta. *Amar kra va'avadeta*. No, you replicate same הלכה *halacha*. אלא בו
למה לי Ella bo lama li? *Ella bo lamah li*? What do
I need the בו bo *bo* for? בו bo המרת דת hamarat
dat? פוסלת *Bo hamarat dat poselet*. For this guy, for, for the
קרבן פסח Pesach. *Korban Pesach*, excuse me, excuse me, being a renouncing
your faith invalidates you. ואין המרת דת Hamaras Das. פוסלת בתרומה bitruma.
*V'ein hamarat dat poselet b'trumah*. But if you've renounced your faith you
can still go ahead and eat תרומה Terumah. *trumah*. Okay, if it's
מותר *mutar* for you to eat תרומה terumah. *trumah*. Like you would
care. But at least maybe it would be מותר *mutar* for a
כהן *Kohen* father to serve his rebellious son תרומה terumah, *trumah*, okay,
and wouldn't be a violation. Okay and anyway we'll see exactly what
המרת דת Hamaras Das. *hamarat dat* means which we're not going to
go into right now. Okay, so it doesn't apply to תרומה terumah
*trumah* even though תרומה terumah. *trumah* is has a קודש *kodesh* component
to it. איצטריך *Itztarich* now. So that's what the בו bo *bo*'s
are telling you. Now, parenthetically we're saying why does the תורה Torah
*Torah* have to prohibit both an ערל arel *arel* and a בן
נכר Ben Neichar *ben nechar*? Why couldn't it just prohibit one, one
and I'd figure out the other? ואיצטריך למכתב ערל arel ואיצטריך למכתב
בן נכר ben neichar *Ve'itztarich l'michtav arel ve'itztarich l'michtav ben nechar*. דאי
כתב רחמנא ערל *De'ee katav rachmana arel*, had it just said that
an ערל *arel* doesn't eat the קרבן פסח Pesach *Korban Pesach*, משום
דמאיס *mishum de'ma'is*, that there's something like repugnant, there's something physically different
about that, about how a Jewish male should look, the way he's
looking, and maybe that's the problem. אבל בן נכר ben neichar, *Aval
ben nechar*, somebody that basically has, been an apostate, that's not visible,
לא מיאיס *lo me'is*, so maybe it's not so bad. It's very
interesting, like an aesthetic concern. I mean, we do have aesthetic concerns
by קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*, but that's essentially what it's saying. אימא לא,
Eima lo, maybe it wouldn't be excluded. Maybe it's also communal concern,
it's not as visible, though who's looking at the guy's genitalia? It's
not as though, so whom is it visible other than to God?
צריכא. Tsricha. If you had written בן נכר, ben neichar had it
just been בן נכר משום דאין לבו לשמים mishum de-ein libo lashamayim
because he's not doing it as an act of worship. He's not
thinking about God, whatever he's doing, for him it's a secular act.
אבל ערל, Aval arel, לבו לשמים, libo lashamayim, somebody might be uncircumcised
due to no fault of their own, they're from a family of
hemophiliacs and he still could be very פרום. frum. אימא לא, maybe
he wouldn't be excluded. צריכא, Tsricha, you need both. Okay, but again
the בו’s bo there are telling you that it only applies to
פסח, Pesach. not to מצה and מרור, not to תרומה. terumah, אלא
מעתה, תושב ושכיר לא יאכל בו, toshav vesachir lo yochal bo, הכא
נמי בו הוא דאינו אוכל אבל אוכל בפסח דורות? hacha nami bo
hu de-eino ochel aval ochel be-Pesach dorot? The sojourner and the hired
hand don't eat from it. Should I also say that that only
applies to that and not פסח דורות? Pesach Dorot, No. אמר קרא
ועבדת, Amar Kra ve-avadta. the פסוק extends it, replicates it. אלא בו
למה לי? Ella bo lama li? Why's the בו? bo בו אמרת
בהמרת דת ואין אמרת בהמרת דת בתרומה. Bo amart be-hamarat dat ve-ein
amart be-hamarat dat bit-terumah. Now, it's a bizarre line. First of all,
we just said that a sentence ago. Second of all, since when
is the תושב ושכיר toshav vesachir about המרת דת? They're not people
that have rebelled. Presumably they're non-Jews. So basically רש"י completely crossed out
the three lines of גמרא Gemara, we just read. He says this
whole thing of תושב ושכיר toshav vesachir doesn't make sense, he crossed
it out also because, and I don't want to start this conversation,
but actually תושב ושכיר toshav vesachir in rabbinic lens is an עבד
עברי. eved Ivri. A תושב toshav is an עבד עברי eved Ivri
for יובל Yovel who's נרצע, nirtza, and a שכיר sachir is an
עבד עברי eved Ivri for six years. And actually חז"ל say a
תושב ושכיר toshav vesachir do eat in the קרבן פסח, Pesach against
the פסוק! And what they do with the פסוק is they read
the פסוקין pesukim in very interesting ways. So רש"י completely crosses out
these three lines which don't make sense and don't fit in with
other גמרא. Gemara אלא מעתה, ומלתה אתו אז יאכל בו. u-maltah oto
az yochal bo. You circumcise your sons and your slaves and then
they can eat from it, you can eat from it. So הכא
נמי בו bo אינו אוכל אבל אוכל בפסח דורות? But future generations,
even if you have uncircumcised slaves and children, maybe shouldn't be an
exclusion because it says בו. So does ומלתה אתו אז יאכל בו?
u-maltah oto az yochal bo? They do eat it. I'm saying if
they're not מול? mol? If they're not מול, mol, yeah. But maybe
future generations that would not be a barrier because it's only בו.
אמר קרא ועבדת. Amar Kra ve-avadta. No, you replicate. אלא בו למה
לי? So what's the בו doing? בו בכשר ולא בפסול, Bo be-kasher
velo be-pasul, to tell you, like we said before, that if it's
a פסול pasul פסח Pesach you can't break the bones. אלא מעתה
דכתיב אל תאכלו ממנו נא, Ella mei-ata dich-tiv al tochlu mimenu na,
ממנו אי אתה אוכל ולא אוכל נא בפסח דורות? mimenu iy ata
ochel velo ochel na be-Pesach dorot? Maybe again raw should be okay
because it has the limiting words from it. אמר קרא ועבדת. Amar
Kra ve-avadta. No, you replicate. אלא ממנו למה לי? Ella mimenu lama
li? What's the ממנו mimenu doing? לכדרבה אמר רב יוסף. Lich-dirabba amar
Rav Yosef. רבה Rabba in the name of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef,
that basically says that to use it to extend a prohibition of
an ערל eating in מעשר. ma'aser. Part of the reason that you
need this is because an ערל cannot eat תרומה. terumah. So since
an ערל cannot eat תרומה, terumah you might have thought that also
a בן נכר can't eat תרומה terumah in terms of an apostate,
maybe if your slaves aren't נימול nimol they can't eat תרומה. terumah,
There's a good logic for that. If one of the ideas if
you being uncircumcised you can't eat תרומה, maybe everything in this group.
So it should apply to בן נכר, it should apply to your
slaves not being circumcised. No, those things are only by פסח Pesach
and not by תרומה. ואין מילת זכריו ועבדיו מעכבת בתרומה, Ve-ein milat
zcharav ve-avadav me-akevet bit-terumah, right. So by תרומה not. So תרומה yes,
an ערל cannot eat, but don't extend the prohibitions of בן נכר
or of other members of your household not being נימול. nimol. That
does not have an impact by תרומה, yes. How do you understand
what why is the structure of this סוגיא sugya built around אלא
מעתה? In other words, what's the sense? Like, okay, now. Now that
you are saying that the word החודש הזה hachodesh hazeh says this
only applies by פסח מצרים, Pesach Mitzrayim if you're going to look
at the זה zeh word that appears in that פסוק of פסח
מצרים Pesach Mitzrayim to say this act only applies to פסח מצרים,
Pesach Mitzrayim this whole פרשה is filled with זה’s and בו’s. And
if we're going to read them to limit it to פסח מצרים,
Pesach Mitzrayim, we're going to have an absurd conclusion. So we have
to go through every single זה and בו in the פרשה. Now
that you've done it with one, how can you not do it
by all of these? Ah, I get it now that you've done
this. Exactly, yeah. Okay. So it says, where are we? Okay. אלא
מעתה דכתיב ועצם לא תשברו בו, Ella mei-ata dich-tiv ve-etzem lo tishberu
bo, הכא נמי דבו אינו שובר אבל שובר בפסח דורות? Hacha nami
de-bo eino shover aval shover be-Pesach dorot? So בו should maybe the
בו by breaking bones should limit it to פסח מצרים. Pesach Mitzrayim,
אמר קרא ועבדת. No, ועבדת comes to tell you replicate. אלא בו
למה לי? So what's the בו doing? בו בכשר ולא בפסול, Bo
be-kasher velo be-pasul, to tell you like we said before, that if
it's a פסול pasul פסח Pesach you can't break the bones. אלא
מעתה דכתיב אל תאכלו ממנו נא. Ella mei-ata dich-tiv al tochlu mimenu
na. ממנו אי אתה אוכל ולא אוכל נא בפסח דורות? Mimenu iy
ata ochel velo ochel na be-Pesach dorot? Maybe again raw should be
okay because it has the limiting word from it. אמר קרא ועבדת.
No, you replicate. אלא ממנו למה לי? Ella mimenu lama li? What's
the ממנו mimenu doing? לכדרבה אמר רב יוסף. Lich-dirabba amar Rav Yosef.
רבה Rabba in the name of רב יוסף Rav Yosef that basically
says that to use it to extend a prohibition of an ערל
eating in מעשר. ma'aser. So I don't know how he gets it
from that, let's not worry about it. Okay. Anyway. Didn't he say
about ערל before? Yes, but that was about ערל is אסור assur
בתרומה. Anyway, I don't want to worry. So basically there's a whole
thing where we said והזה vehizah limits the idea of מצה and
מרור, and then we have to say so then you should limit
everything. No, we have a ריבוי ribuy which says you replicate everything
and all these limiting words are coming for other purposes. Okay, fine.
Let's continue with the list of things that do not apply לדורות.
ledorot. ופסח דורות נוהג כל שבעה. Upesach dorot noheg kol shivah. אמאי?
Amay? אמאי קאי? Amay kai? Now, I'm sorry, ונאכל בחיפזון, venechal bechipazon,
פתאום, pitom, quickly. מנלן? Minalan? דאמר קרא, De'amar kra, ואכלתם אותו בחיפזון,
ve'achaltem oto bechipazon, אותו נאכל בחיפזון ואין אחר נאכל בחיפזון. oto nechal
bechipazon ve'ein acher nechal bechipazon. So when it makes sense we're going
to use words like הזה and אותו oto to limit it to
פסח Pesach מצרים. Mitzrayim When it doesn't make sense we're going to
say that you replicate everything, okay? So there's some things that at
some level חז"ל understood were only by פסח Pesach מצרים Mitzrayim and
that they were able to hint on words like הזה and אותו
oto when they felt it was limited to פסח Pesach. מצרים. Mitzrayim.
Okay. ופסח דורות נוהג כל שבעה. Upesach dorot noheg kol shivah.
Now פסח Pesach, for generations also seven. אמאי קאי? Amay kai? What's
this going on? אילימא פסח, Ilima Pesach, if the actual פסח, Pesach.
right, which is what we've been talking about, the קרבן, פסח כל
שבעה מי איכא? Pesach kol shivah mi ika? Who eats the פסח
Pesach for seven days? אלא חמץ, Ela chametz, the eating of חמץ,
chametz, that the prohibition, you can't say מצה because although in the
תורה Torah. you eat מצה for seven days, חז"ל understood that that
was a רשות reshut not a חובה. chovah. So what it refers
to is the prohibition of חמץ chametz for seven days. Okay, מכלל
דפסח מצרים לילה אחד ותו לא? michlal dePesach Mitzrayim layla echad veto
lo? So if that's true, it says פסח Pesach, מצרים Mitzrayim is
one night and לדורות seven days. So what's the one night? If
it means the prohibition of חמץ, chametz, so that sounds like in
מצרים they only had the prohibition for that night. So why is
that a problem? והתניא, we learned in a ברייתא, Braita. רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili omer, מנין לפסח מצרים שאין חימוצו נוהג
אלא יום אחד? minayin lePesach Mitzrayim she'ein chimutzo noheg ela yom echad?
How do you know that in מצרים the prohibition of חמץ chametz
was only one day? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, לא יאכל חמץ, lo
ye'achel chametz, וסמיך ליה היום, usamich lei hayom, אתם יוצאים. atem yotzim.
So you read the פסוק: לא יאכל חמץ היום. lo ye'achel chametz
hayom. Okay, it's a different פסוק, right? Don't eat חמץ chametz today
you're going out, but don't eat חמץ chametz today! So what's the
problem? So you see according to him they couldn't eat פסח Pesach,
the whole, sorry, they couldn't eat חמץ chametz the whole day of
the fifteenth. So why does our משנה mishnah say פסח Pesach מצרים
was only לילה אחד? layla echad? If it's talking about חמץ, chametz,
then it should have been the whole day and that should have
been the contrast, not just the night. So the גמרא Gemara says
you're right. Okay, it doesn't mean it. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, לילה
אחד לאו דוקא לפסח דורות, layla echad lav davka lePesach dorot, it's
eaten for one night and that's true for פסח דורות, Pesach Dorot
it's eaten one night, וחמוצו כל היום, vechimutzo kol hayom, ופסח דורות
נוהג כל שבעה, Upesach dorot noheg kol shivah, for פסח Pesach, דורות
seven days חמץ chametz again. Interesting conflating of פסח קרבן Pesach korban
and פסח החג. Pesach hachag. I want to say a few things
before we get to the next משנה. mishnah. Number one is you
understand that if there's a prohibition of חמץ chametz on the whole
day of the fifteenth, the פסוק of ויאפו את הבצק אשר הוציאו
ממצרים עוגות מצות כי לא חמץ כי גורשו ממצרים, vayofu et habatzek
asher hotziu miMitzrayim ugot matzot ki lo chametz ki gorshu miMitzrayim, it
should have said because you told us not to eat חמץ chametz
today! So anyway, it is very hard in the narrative to imagine
that they actually had a prohibition of eating חמץ chametz on the
fifteenth. I don't know what the answer is, I'm pointing out that
problem. Number one. Okay, which is to say that our משנה mishnah
holds לילה אחד layla echad would actually be quite nice in terms
of that narrative. Number one. Number two is I want to read
you because it's just fascinating from the תוספתא Tosefta that lists a
couple of other differences of פסח Pesach מצרים. I'll just read it
quickly. It is, okay, first of all I'll read this is at
the end of פרק ח. perek chet. So first I'll read you
ways similar and ways you would not have imagined, right? We went
through saying everything was similar except one or two. Here's some things
that you might not have imagined. אלו דברים ששוה בהן פסח מצרים
לפסח דורות. Elu devarim sheshaveh bahen Pesach Mitzrayim lePesach dorot. פסח מצרים
בג' כיתות ופסח דורות כיוצא בו. Pesach Mitzrayim be-gimel kitot upesach dorot
keyotzei bo. Right? Did you know that? In מצרים there were three
separate groups, which is pretty fascinating since everybody is שוחט-ing shochet in
their own home. Okay, and one of the contrasts that the תוספתא
Tosefta said before is that פסח Pesach דורות is everybody's doing it
together in one place and פסח מצרים is everybody in their own
home. So what does it mean that you do three shifts? I
have no idea. Okay. פסח מצרים נאמר בו לא תותירו ממנו עד
בוקר כיוצא בו, Pesach Mitzrayim ne'emar bo lo totiru mimenu ad boker
keyotzei bo, etc. Okay. So that's number one, the ג' כיתות. gimel
kitot. Now what are the differences? Here it says the following: אלו
דברים שבין פסח מצרים לפסח דורות. Elu devarim shebein Pesach Mitzrayim lePesach
dorot. שבין Shebein are differences. פסח מצרים מקחו בעשור, Pesach Mitzrayim mikacho
be'asor, שחיטתו בי"ד, shechitato be-yud-daled, okay, ואין חייבין עליו כרת. ve'ein chayavin
alav karet. If you didn't bring it, you're not, שחיטתו בי"ד shechitato
be-yud-daled is not a difference. Anyway, if you didn't bring it, you're
not חייב כרת, chayav karet, right? תורה Torah never said כרת karet
if you don't bring it in מצרים. Maybe you don't get to
go out of מצרים but you don't get כרת. karet. פסח דורות
חייבין עליו כרת. Pesach dorot chayavin alav karet. פסח מצרים לא נהגו
בו דקים וטיבלולין אתנן ומחיר. Pesach Mitzrayim lo nahagu bo dakim vetivlulin
etnan umechire. So it's interesting, the תורה says it has to be
a שה תמים, seh tamim, but it says certain subtle מומים mumim
and certain פסולים psulim that are not about a physical מום, mum,
like אתנן etnan and מחיר, mechir, those only came later in the
תורה. So at the time of פסח מצרים those מומים mumim didn't
apply, those פסולים psulim did not apply. Okay. פסח מצרים נאמר בו
ולקח. Pesach Mitzrayim ne'emar bo velakach. Now this is interesting for those
interested. in the communal aspects of the פסוק. פסח מצרים נאמר בו
ולקח הוא ושכנו, Pesach Mitzrayim ne'emar bo velakach hu ushcheino, ושכנו. ushcheino.
מה שאין כן ma she'ein kein for פסח דורות, it doesn't have
to be your neighbor. The בית bayit idea is not as literal
as household and neighbor. It's any group. Okay? That's what we've been
saying, whereas פסח מצרים was דווקא שכנו. davka shecheino. Now listen to
this. Wait, I'm sorry, meaning it couldn't be like the guy two
doors there? Exactly. Whatever, I don't know exactly the limits of neighbor,
but it had to be either your household or your neighbor. חבורה
chabura was only after יציאת מצרים. Yetziat Mitzrayim. שמעון אומר, Shimon omer,
you'll like this. אומר אני אף פסח דורות כן. omer ani af
Pesach Dorot kein. Even פסח דורות you should do with your neighbors.
Why? וכל כך למה, vechol kach lama, כדי שלא יניח אדם שכנו
הקרוב אל ביתו וילך לעשות פסחו אצל חברו. kedei shelo yaniach adam
shcheino hakarov el beito veyeilech la'asot picho etzel chaveiro. It's important to
foster, you know, a greater sense of community and connection with your
neighbor. And more important to do with your neighbor than go to
your friend who's not your neighbor. כדי לקיים מה שנאמר, kedei lekayem
mah shene'emar, טוב שכן קרוב מאח רחוק. tov shachen karov me'ach rachok.
Okay? According to our גמרא, Gemara so you should try to cultivate
your, you know, neighbors even if it's not your best friend. Okay.
And then it says, פסח מצרים, going back to the גמרא Gemara
about the חלב, chelev, look at this, it's a תוספתא. Tosefta. פסח
מצרים לא היה טעון דמים וחלב לגבי מזבח, Pesach Mitzrayim lo hayah
ta'un damim vechelev legabei mizbe'ach, מה שאין כן פסח דורות. ma she'ein
kein Pesach Dorot. Interesting, it doesn't call the, the doorposts the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. It says there wasn't דמים damim on the מזבח mizbe'ach and
there wasn't חלב. chelev. That answers the חלב chelev questions, okay? And
פסח מצרים you did the doorposts, מה שאין כן פסח דורות. ma
she'ein kein Pesach Dorot. Now listen to this: פסח מצרים נאמר בו
ואתם לא תצאו איש מפתח ביתו, Pesach Mitzrayim ne'emar bo ve'atem lo
tetze'u ish mipetach beito, מה שאין כן פסח דורות. ma she'ein kein
Pesach Dorot. That goes back to the question of how much is
it physically the house, or is it a חבורה? chabura? It also
might be emphasizing the עד בוקר, ad boker, okay, which is the
next line. פסח מצרים כל אחד ואחד שוחט בתוך ביתו, Pesach Mitzrayim
kol echad ve'echad shocheit betoch beito, פסח דורות כל ישראל שוחטין במקום
אחד. Pesach Dorot kol Yisrael shochtin bemakom echad. Again, the communal versus,
you know, everybody together versus in your home. פסח מצרים מקום אכילה
שם תלינה. Pesach Mitzrayim makom achilah sham telinah. You have to sleep
in the house. You're not allowed to leave the house עד בוקר.
ad boker. מה שאין כן פסח דורות אוכלין במקום אחד ולנין במקום
אחר. ma she'ein kein Pesach Dorot ochlin bemakom echad velanin bemakom acher.
You eat your פסח, you don't leave the space, but then you
go home. You don't have to not leave the space for the
whole night. Okay? Again, the angel was visiting. Right, exactly. Anyway, רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov finally says that he says
even פסח מצרים the idea of, of your uncircumcised slaves does not
apply לדורות. He actually says uncircumcised slaves is only, is only for
פסח מצרים according to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov,
against what our גמרא Gemara was saying. Wow. Okay, so I thought
that תוספתא Tosefta does a nice job of filling out the picture.
Yeah. But I just want to understand something. So in פסח מצרים,
so this, when בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael slaughtered it earlier on in
the day, right? We're saying the provision of eating חמץ chametz only
applies from the night of the following day, and they could have
eaten חמץ chametz afterwards, in פסח מצרים, right? In the middle of
the 14th or whatever? After they slaughtered it? Before the night time?
Right? Presumably, yeah, I guess. I guess. Yeah. I don't know, but
I guess that would be a logical conclusion. All right, let's look
now at the next משנה. mishnah. אמר רבי יהושע שמעתי שתמורת פסח
קריבה ותמורת פסח אינה קריבה. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua shamati shetmurat Pesach kreivah
utmurat Pesach einah kreivah. He said, oh my God, it was so
much fun until this point. I, but now we're back to תמורה,
tmurah, okay? and like, and very technical קרבנות issues. So, I've heard
that if you do a תמורה, tmurah, תמורה tmurah is you try
to transfer קדושה kedusha from one קרבן to another. The תורה says
you're prohibited from doing that. And if you do try to do
it, then the other thing becomes, becomes קדוש kadosh and your first
thing remains קדוש. kadosh. Okay? So it's fascinating how much of the
גמרא Gemara. talks about תמורה tmurah because the only way you get
תמורה tmurah is by violating a law. And nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara
just, you know, very easily talks about the phenomenon of a תמורה.
tmurah. So I heard that if you do a תמורה tmurah of
your קרבן פסח, okay, that תמורה, tmurah, can you bring it as
a שלמים? shlamim? Because תמורות tmurot are brought as קרבנות. Can you
bring it as a שלמים shlamim? because a פסח that you're not
bringing gets brought as a שלמים? shlamim Or do you have to
wait until it gets a מום mum and transfer the value and
use the money for a שלמים? shlamim So I've heard that there
are some תמורות tmurot that are brought themselves as שלמים shelamim, and
תמורת פסח אינה קריבה, utmurat Pesach einah kreivah, some are not brought
and you have to transfer the value. ואין לי לפרש, ve'ein li
lefareish, I can't explain the difference. I don't remember the difference between
them. אמר רבי עקיבא אני אפרש. Amar Rabbi Akiva ani afareish. Okay,
well let me explain it. הפסח שנמצא קודם שחיטת הפסח ירעה עד
שיסתאב וימכר ויביא בדמיו שלמים וכן תמורתו. Hapesach shenimtza kodem shechitat Hapesach
yireh ad sheyista'ev veyimacher veyavi bedamav shlamim vechein tmurato. Says, how much
does the animal become a שלמים shelamim, or does it get completely
disqualified and you can only use its value and transfer its קדושה
kedusha if it gets a מום? mum? Says, it depends if it's
נדחה. nidcheh. The idea of דחוי dichui is an idea by קרבנות,
pushed away, stigmatized. So he says, let's say you lost your, your
sheep that you had sanctified as a פסח. And then you sanctified
another one. And then your lost sheep came walking home, and right
before you had, before you got around to shing. So now you
had the old one and the new one. So you're going to
שחט shacht the new one and the old one, you know, you
already sanctified a new one, forget the old one. So then you
are effectively pushing it away. It's there, it's in front of you,
you have the opportunity to שחט shacht it and you're not שחטing
shacht it. That thing which is נדחה, nidcheh, that sheep... cannot be
brought as a שלמים, shelamim, because that was actively put away, it
was stigmatized, and that you have to transfer the value. Similarly, said
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva if you took that פסח, that one that
you pushed away and said I want to transfer that to another
animal, the תמורה Temurah would just be like the original sheep, that
sheep, and also could not be brought itself, would only be able
to be brought in the proceeds. So the basic point is the
תמורה Temurah is just like the sheep. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
don't focus on the תמורה, Temurah, focus on the פסח that it
originates in. A פסח that originally was pushed away and cannot be
brought itself, the same is true about the תמורה. Temurah. Now, אחר
שחיטת הפסח, achar shechitat hapesach, let's say you found the lost sheep
after you brought the new one, then you didn't actively push away
the old one, the old one was missing. That type of a
sheep can be brought automatically as a שלמים, shelamim, so that's קרב
שלמים וכן תמורתו karav shelamim v'chen temurato and the same would be
about the תמורה. Temurah. So basically רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said it's
not a difference about the תמורה, Temurah, it's a difference about the
original פסח. So why are we even discussing a תמורה, Temurah, the
גמרא will talk about it. I also do want to point out
something we said before, normally we say it about רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua were
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva what? רבייים, Rabbeim, and both of them were
old school teachers. Both of them were very much about passing down
the tradition, learning everything, memorizing it and passing it down. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva was new school, he was very much about figuring things
out for yourself and using your intellect and so on. So you
know, it's very appropriate רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says I heard, this
is my tradition, but I can't figure out the difference. So you
know, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says well let me help you out.
Now אפרש A-parish is interesting because he doesn't say it's basically it's
an interpretation of the tradition. You know, I'll make sense of it
for you by using our own logic and being creative and so
on and it's very much evokes the whole הלל Hillel story where
הלל Hillel both sort of figures it out, you know figures the
whole thing out about פסח is brought on שבת Shabbat from פסוקים,
pesukim, and then they, you know according to the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, nobody
listened to him and then he says no, שמעתי משמעיה ואבטליון. Shamati
mi'Shemaya v'Avtalyon. Oh, you heard it? Why didn't you say so? Okay,
so here too רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva not saying I'll figure it
all out myself, I'll work with the tradition but I'm going to
interpret the tradition. I'll help you understand what that tradition is that
you received. How did you get this case from the words in
the משנה Mishna though? What case? אפרש? A-parish? No, ירעה עד שיסתאב
וימכר. yere'e ad sheyista'ev v'yimacher. Oh, ירעה עד שיסתאב, yere'e ad sheyista'ev,
let it let it graze until it gets a blemish, and then
sell it, וימכר, v'yimacher, and you transfer the קדושה kedusha to the
money you got, ויביא בדמי שלמים, v'yavi bidmei shelamim, and you, I
sorry I didn't explain that phrase fully, I didn't read it, I
read it but I didn't say it, and you use that money
to buy a שלמים, shelamim, meaning you don't bring the animal itself
as a שלמים, shelamim. you have to transfer the קדושה kedusha to
money and use the proceeds for a שלמים, shlamim. but you could
only transfer the קדושה kedusha if it has a blemish. So this
was the first, I forget we had to fill in the fact
that there was a first animal and then. No, it said it
before, it said שנמצא הפסח שנמצא, she'nimtza hapesach she'nimtza, if it was
found meant that it was lost for a while and therefore, and
right, and what you do have to fill in is and you
didn't bring it and you brought the other one you had sanctified
etc. etc. that has to be filled in. The key are in
the words of הפסח שנמצא. hapesach she'nimtza. Right. These are all much
larger conversations that are, no no no it's you're right, it's a
total shorthand. Let's start, let's take a look in the גמרא. We're
falling a little behind but thankfully if you take a look on
צ"ט עמוד א' Tzadik Tet Amud Aleph we only have a few
lines because of the end of a whole discussion of פסח. Anyway.
So the גמרא says like this: לימא פסח קרב ופסח אינו קרב,
Leima pesach kareiv u'pesach eino kareiv, now that רבי עקיבא explained it,
it's not about the תמורה, Temurah, it's about the פסח, so why
are we talking about the תמורה? Temurah? You know, it's sort of
like why was his tradition about the תמורה? Temurah? It's funny, not
like why the משנה, Mishna, why was his tradition about the תמורה?
Temurah? It should have been about the פסח. הא קמשמע לן דאיכא
תמורת פסח דלא קרב. Ha kamashma lan d'ika temurat pesach d'lo kareiv.
Ah, because you would have thought it's not true that the פסח
is exactly like the, the תמורה's Temurah exactly like the פסח. Even
if the פסח is stigmatized, that wouldn't apply to the תמורה, Temurah,
the תמורה Temurah was never pushed away, the פסח was pushed away.
So maybe even if the פסח was נדחה nidcheh and can't be
brought, maybe the תמורה Temurah always can be brought as a שלמים.
shlamim. So telling you no, and the חידוש chiddush is A: there's
a difference of נדחה nidcheh and whether it can be brought itself
by the פסח and B: that that distinction continues to the תמורה
Temurah and if the פסח was stigmatized, so was the so was
the תמורה. Temurah. איתמר. Itmar. It was taught. רבה אמר קודם שחיטה
ואחר שחיטה שנינו. Rabba amar: Kodem shechita v'achar shechita shaninu. As the
משנה Mishna says, and key is did you find the old פסח
before or after שחיטה shechita in terms of what defines it as
pushed away. רבי זירא אמר קודם חצות ואחר חצות שנינו. Rabbi Zeira
amar: Kodem chatzot v'achar chatzot shaninu. No, it's not really about שחיטה,
shechita it's about before after חצות. Chatzos Once the time of שחיטה
shechita, arrived and then it was and then if it was found
before and you then it's considered pushed away. But if it was
found after the time of שחיטה, shechita then you're off the hook.
It's not like you're pushing it away, it wasn't around when the
time began, so it's not considered נדחה nidcheh if it if it
showed up after חצות. לרבי זירא הא קתני קודם שחיטת הפסח. leRabbi
Zeira ha katani kodem shechitat hapesach. What do you do with the
משנה? Mishna? It says if it was found before after you שחט
shacht it. אימא קודם זמן שחיטת הפסח, Eima kodem zman shechitas ha-Pesach,
it means the time. כדתניא, Kedisanya, now this is actually a מחלוקת
תנאים machlokes tannaim so you don't have to say the משנה Mishna
agrees with him, the משנה Mishna could be one side because here's
the ברייתא. הפסח שנמצא קודם שחיטה ירעה לאחר שחיטה יקרב, Ha-Pesach she-nimtza
kodem shechita yera'eh le-achar shechita yikares, that's very simply, if it's you
know do you can if it's found before שחיטה shechita. then you
push it away effectively and then you have to use the proceeds,
you have to wait for a blemish. After שחיטה shechita you can
bring it as a שלמים. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer אומר it's not
about שחיטה, shechita קודם חצות ירעה לאחר חצות יקרב. kodem Chatzos yera'eh
le-achar Chatzos yikares. It's about חצות because again if if it was
found after חצות even before you שחט shachted it, you didn't push
it away. It was lost at the important time and it was
considered automatically sort of like out of the picture and therefore you're
it's not considered like an active pushing away. Okay, let's get a
little bit into the next part. אחר שחיטת הפסח יהא שלמים. Achar
shechitas ha-Pesach yehei shlamim. אמר רבא לא שנו אלא שנמצא אחר שחיטה
והמיר בו אחר שחיטה. Amar Rava lo shanu ela she-nimtza achar shechita
ve-hemir bo achar shechita. Okay, it's interesting. We just a line ago
we had המרת דת. Now we have המיר בו hemir bo from
the word of תמורה, tmura, okay, which is basically the same thing,
exchange. Are you exchanging your religion? Are you trying to exchange your
קרבן? So okay, תמורה tmura is also a לאו but better than
המרת דת. Anyway, so if you're so we're only talking about when
is it that it is נדחה nidcheh the תמורה, tmura, if it
was found after שחיטה shechita. and the act of תמורה tmura was
done after שחיטה. shechita, אבל נמצא קודם שחיטה, Aval nimtza kodem shechita,
if it was I'm sorry, when is it not נדחה? nidcheh? When
is it acceptable? If it was found after שחיטה so it wasn't
pushed away and the same by the act of תמורה. tmura. אבל
נמצא קודם שחיטה, Aval nimtza kodem shechita, let's say it was found
before שחיטת הפסח, shechitas ha-Pesach, so that was considered pushed away, נדחה,
nidcheh, it was stigmatized. אבל והמיר בו אחר שחיטה, Aval ve-hemir bo
achar shechita, when you did the act of תמורה tmura it was
after שחיטה so you were never pushing away the תמורה tmura animal,
right? I had already brought my פסח. Now I'm going to do
a תמורה. tmura. This poor sheep right now after I brought my
פסח, this sheep I never pushed away, you know, my I'm first
being introduced to it after I brought my פסח. So maybe the
act of תמורה tmura there, maybe I have to push away the
תמורה, tmura, not just push away the original. This is not the
משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna sounds like the whole point is it's
a carbon copy. If the פסח was pushed away and stigmatized, the
same is the תמורה. tmura. רבא's Rava saying not necessarily. I could
have pushed away the פסח, but if I did the act of
תמורה tmura after הקרבה, hakrava, then I'm not pushing away the תמורה
tmura and the תמורה tmura can be... Because I had an alternative,
because I used the new animal not the old one. But is
this not an act of תמורה? tmura? No, no, no, no, no.
I lost my old one, I sanctified the new one straight. אני
מקדיש זה כפסח. Ani makdish zeh ke-Pesach. Okay? I didn't try to
take away the קדושה kedusha from the old one and then I
used the new one, so I'm effectively saying I'm not interested in
the old one actively choosing another one, that's considered נדחה, nidcheh, that
stigmatizes it. If the old one wasn't found at the time, I
didn't have it as an option to push it away. So that's
considered נדחה. nidcheh. Now the simple sense of our משנה Mishna is
if the old one is נדחה, nidcheh, then any תמורה tmura you
make at any time, the stigma transfers. רבא's Rava saying not necessarily
because that would only be if you made the תמורה tmura before
you brought the פסח, then the bringing of the פסח pushes away
both the old one and the תמורה. tmura. But if the תמורה
tmura was done, the act of תמורה tmura after bringing the פסח,
you never pushed away the תמורה tmura so it's never stigmatized, okay,
which does not sound that way in the משנה. Mishna. Okay, right,
and you bring it straight as a שלמים. אבל נמצא קודם שחיטה
והמיר בו אחר שחיטה תמורתו מכוח Aval nimtza kodem shechita ve-hemir bo
achar shechita tmuraso mi-koach I'm sorry, okay, you know what, I jumped
ahead to the next רבא. Rava. He's saying don't make that distinction.
Later he's going to say make that distinction. Here he's saying don't
make that distinction. Let's read it one more time and we'll end
with that. אמר רבא Amar Rava לא שנו אלא שנמצא אחר שחיטה
והמיר בו אחר שחיטה. lo shanu ela she-nimtza achar shechita ve-hemir bo
achar shechita. אבל נמצא קודם שחיטה, Aval nimtza kodem shechita, when is
it good? It's only good if the פסח was found after שחיטה.
אבל נמצא קודם שחיטה, Aval nimtza kodem shechita, if the פסח was
found before שחיטה, so now there's two animals that are מוקצה, muktza,
right? Yes. Okay, let's just this way, you know what, let's end
here. To be continued tomorrow.