Shalom, today we will be doing a little half שיעור shiur on
פ"ד ע"ב peh daled amud bet to catch up. We start with
the משנה Mishnah about ten lines from the top on פ"ד. peh
daled. הפסח שנזרק דמו ואחר כך נודע שהוא טמא הציץ מרצה. Hapesach
shenizrak damo ve’achar kach noda shehu tamei hatzitz meratzeh.
So again, these are concepts that we've already introduced earlier and here
the משנה Mishnah is introducing them, the idea that the ציץ tzitz
helps to make acceptable a קרבן korban that is brought in טומאה.
tumah. And now we are no longer, in the past we talked
about the idea that maybe you even need the ציץ tzitz to
operate when it's a case of a פסח Pesach that's brought בטומאה
בציבור betumah betzibur because maybe it's only טומאה דחויה בציבור tumah dchuyah
betzibur and the טומאה tumah is still present and problematic. This משנה
Mishnah is dealing with the case of a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid,
of an individual's קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, and that became טמא, tamei,
the person is טהור, tahor, the פסח Pesach became טמא, tamei, and
if you'll remember we are assuming, not like רבי נתן, Rebbi Natan,
we are assuming that if the meat is טמא tamei then you're
not יוצא yotzei your obligation of קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. So basically
you're טהור, tahor, the meat became טמא tamei and you did זריקת
הדם, zerikat hadam, can the ציץ tzitz help to make it acceptable?
So let's take a look. הפסח שנזרק דמו ואחר כך נודע שהוא
טמא. Hapesach shenizrak damo ve'achar kach noda shehu tamei.
So you did the זריקת הדם zerikat hadam on the פסח Pesach
and then you found out that the meat was טמא tamei or
even the דם dam was טמא, tamei, something that would have invalidated
the פסח. Pesach. So הציץ מרצה. hatzitz meratzeh. So as
long, since you were ignorant at the time the ציץ tzitz makes
it acceptable. So although we thought in the previous משנה Mishnah that
if the בשר basar is טמא tamei it's not good and certainly
לכתחילה, lechatchila, probably even בדיעבד, bedieved, that's when you know that it
was טמא. tamei. Here you were not aware and therefore the ציץ
tzitz operates to make it acceptable.
נטמא הגוף אין הציץ מרצה. Nitma haguf ein hatzitz meratzeh. However, if
the person becomes טמא tamei the ציץ tzitz does not help for
that, the ציץ tzitz only helps for the טמא tamei meat, the
objects that are טמא, tamei, the meat or the blood. מפני שאמרו
הנזיר ועושה פסח הציץ מרצה על טומאת הדם ואין הציץ מרצה על
טומאת הגוף mipnei she'amru hanazir ve'oseh pesach hatzitz meratzeh al tumat hadam
ve'ein hatzitz meratzeh al tumat haguf because they said for the נזיר
Nazir and a person bringing קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, the ציץ tzitz
is מרצה, meratzeh, makes means makes קרבן korban acceptable, if the blood
or in the case of the פסח Pesach the meat become טמא,
tamei, but it does not work if the person becomes טמא. tamei.
So
now the reason that we mentioned the נזיר Nazir is particularly also
because of the next section,
so which is the following: נטמא טומאת התהום הציץ מרצה. nitma tumat
hatehom hatzitz meratzeh. There's a special הלכה, halacha, meaning the idea that
the ציץ tzitz is מרצה meratzeh is true by all קרבנות, korbanot,
it's not limited to the קרבן פסח korban Pesach and to the
נזיר. Nazir. But the other הלכה halacha is unique to the פסח
Pesach and נזיר Nazir and that's something called טומאת התהום. tumat hatehom.
טומאת התהום Tumat hatehom literally the טומאה tumah of the depths is
when there is a doubt whether somebody has become טמא tamei or
not. And in that type of a case
the ציץ tzitz even if you're talking about a טומאת הגוף, tumat
haguf, okay, which if the person himself became טמא tamei but it's
a doubtful טומאה, tumah,
then it's not like you definitely become טמא tamei but you're not
aware, it's an actual doubtful case of טומאה tumah altogether, not just
you're ignorant but in some objective way it's doubtful, which we'll talk
about. In that case the ציץ tzitz works even for טומאת הגוף.
tumat haguf. Okay, so basically again what's the הלכה? halacha? The ציץ
tzitz works for the meat or the blood, the objects that become
טמא, tamei, על עוון הקודשים, al avon hakodashim, the sin of the
sanctified objects, the meat or the blood that became טמא, tamei, which
would have invalidated the פסח Pesach because the פסח Pesach even if
the meat is טמא tamei it's invalid if it happens before זריקת
הדם. zerikat hadam. There the ציץ tzitz makes it acceptable if you
were ignorant when the קרבן korban was being brought. But if you
are טמא tamei the ציץ tzitz doesn't help. There is however one
category where you can be טמא tamei and the ציץ tzitz helps
and that's called טומאת התהום, tumat hatehom, not just that you're ignorant
but that it somehow was unknowable at the time. And in that
case the ציץ tzitz makes it acceptable even if it turns out
later that you discover that you had been טמא tamei in the
past. That case, since it was טומאת התהום, tumat hatehom, the ציץ
tzitz makes it acceptable. That is a special הלכה halacha
that only applies to the פסח Pesach and the נזיר. Nazir. And
it's interesting in noting the similarity of the פסח Pesach and the
נזיר Nazir because both of those are הלכות halachot that relate to
the ability to bring the קרבן. korban. Normally a טמא tamei person
can bring a קרבן, korban, but by a פסח Pesach and a
נזיר Nazir those are two cases where if you're טמא tamei you
cannot bring a קרבן. korban. If you're a פסח Pesach you're טמא,
tamei, you're נדחה לפסח שני. nidcheh lepesach sheni. And by a נזיר
Nazir if you're טמא tamei what happens? Then your whole נזירות nezirut
starts over again, so you obviously can't bring the קרבן korban to
terminate the נזירות. nezirut. So those are two cases where you being
טמא בגוף tamei baguf actually undermine the whole ability for the קרבן
korban to be brought. And in that type of a case there's
a special הלכה halacha by נזיר Nazir and the פסח Pesach which
we learn הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe miSinai that the ציץ tzitz
works if it's not just you're ignorant but it's actually considered a
טומאת התהום, tumat hatehom, something that is not knowable which we will
discuss in a minute.
Yes, it does that.
Right, I mean that is interesting that the previous פשט Pshat emphasized
פסח Pesach and נזיר Nazir but we will find out in the
גמרא Gemara that the פסח Pesach and נזיר Nazir are really the
limiting factors to this הלכה Halacha of טומאת התהום. Tumas HaTehom. The
general idea that the ציץ Tzitz is מרוצה Miratzeh on the דם
Dam or on the בשר Basar or more mostly on the דם,
Dam, that's a general הלכה. Halacha.
And practically the טומאת התהום Tumas HaTehom or the טומאת התהום Tumas
HaTehom is
I think that'd be a big problem in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
because there's graves all over the place that people don't know about.
Well, yeah, so we'll take a look at that, okay, what constitutes
that and how much you have to be חושש Choshesh for that.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
The other reason by the way probably mentioned פסח Pesach and נזיר
Nazir as well, not just to say that the טומאת התהום Tumas
HaTehom works, but those are the only probably, you know, the only
two קרבנות Korbanot that if you're טמא Tamei the קרבן Korban is
invalid, right? Again, other קרבנות, Korbanot, so when it says that the
ציץ Tzitz doesn't work when you're טמא, Tamei, the big relevant is,
so the ציץ Tzitz works for the בשר Basar or the דם
Dam by all קרבנות Korbanot if you happen to be ignorant at
the time and it's the בשר Basar or the דם. Dam. But
when you're טמא, Tamei, I can still
have someone else וזרק Vezarak for me,
right, but for a פסח Pesach and a נזיר Nazir when you're
טמא Tamei the קרבן Korban can't be brought. And there it's so
if by another קרבן Korban who cares if you're טמא, Tamei, the
קרבן Korban is still good. But by פסח Pesach and נזיר Nazir
we care and the ציץ Tzitz doesn't work unless it's טומאת התהום.
Tumas HaTehom. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The
גמרא Gemara starts the following by the case where the בשר Basar
or the דם Dam becomes טמא. Tamei. טעמא דנזרק ואחר כך נודע.
Ta'ama denizrak ve'achar kach noda.
The reason that this is acceptable is because it was the דם
Dam was thrown and then you became aware, meaning you were ignorant
at the time and therefore the ציץ Tzitz helps to make it
acceptable. אבל נודע ואחר כך נזרק, Aval noda ve'achar kach nizrak, if
you're aware that the דם Dam was טמא Tamei and then you
did the זריקת הדם, Zrikas HaDam, לא מרוצה, Lo Miratzeh, the ציץ
Tzitz doesn't help for that. Okay, that's like the general הלכה Halacha
we've been saying until now, right, that if the דם Dam is
טמא Tamei or the בשר Basar is טמא, Tamei, פסח Pesach is
no good. ורמינהו, U'reminhu, I'll ask you on this. על מה הציץ
מרוצה? Al mah haTzitz meratzeh? We have a ברייתא Braiysa that says,
what does the ציץ Tzitz work for? על הדם ועל הבשר ועל
החלב, Al haDam ve'al haBasar ve'al haCheilev, דם, Dam, בשר, Basar, or
the fat, you know, to be able to burn that on the
מזבח, Mizbe'ach, שנטמא בין בשוגג בין במזיד, Shenitma bein be'shogeg bein be'meizid,
that became טמא Tamei whether it is unintentional or intentional, בין באונס
בין ברצון, Bein be'oness bein be'ratzon, whether against your will or unknowing
or whether willingly, בין ביחיד בין בציבור, Bein be'yachid bein be'tzibur, whether
an individual's קרבן Korban or ציבור Tzibur קרבן. Korban. ציבור Tzibur maybe
you don't even need the ציץ, Tzitz, that we discussed before. So
anyway, what do you see? You see that it says whether בשוגג
Be'shogeg or במזיד. Be'meizid. So we're interpreting that to mean that even
if you willingly did the זריקת הדם Zrikas HaDam knowing the דם
Dam was טמא, Tamei, the ציץ Tzitz still works. אמר רבינא, Amar
Ravina, said רבינא, Ravina, no, that's not what it means.
טומאתו, Tumaso, means how did it become טמא, Tamei, בין בשוגג בין
במזיד. Bein be'shogeg bein be'meizid. I don't care if the דם Dam
became טמא Tamei willingly or unwillingly, knowingly, unknowingly, that doesn't matter. הורצה,
Hurtzah, it works.
אבל בזריקתו Aval bizrikato but when it comes to how you did
the זריקה, Zrika, when you actually brought the קרבן, Korban, were you
aware of the טומאה Tuma problem, there you have to be unaware.
זריקתו בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה. Zrikato be'shogeg hurtzah be'meizid lo hurtzah.
But as far as the זריקת הדם, Zrikas HaDam, that only works
if you're unaware בשעת זריקה. Be'shas Zrika. So it doesn't matter how
it became טמא Tamei but it does matter what you're aware of
when you do the זריקה. Zrika. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. רבי שילא אמר, Rebbi Shila amar, רבי שילא Rebbi Shila disagrees.
He takes the ברייתא Braiysa at face value. רבי שילא Rebbi Shila
says זריקתו בין בשוגג בין במזיד הורצה. Zrikato bein be'shogeg bein be'meizid
hurtzah. You could know that it's טמא Tamei and do the זריקת
הדם Zrikas HaDam knowing it's טמא Tamei and the ציץ Tzitz makes
it acceptable. Maybe לכתחילה Lechatchila you shouldn't do it, but if you
went ahead and did it, it would be acceptable.
אבל טומאתו בשוגג הורצה במזיד לא הורצה, Aval tumaso be'shogeg hurtzah be'meizid
lo hurtzah, which is bizarre, that if it became טמא Tamei במזיד
Be'meizid then it's no good. Presumably the logic behind that is that
if it were if it knowingly became טמא, Tamei, that is so
much a, you know, a stigma, that's not the right word here,
but you know, an unacceptable, I'm trying to find the fast, my
brain isn't at full capacity, but anyway, if it willingly became טמא,
Tamei, that's not deserving of being sort of atoned for or being
papered over by the ציץ. Tzitz. If the fact that it became
טמא Tamei was unintentional, then that can sort of more be, you
know, the ציץ Tzitz can more can more make it acceptable. So
he said very strange, it's not פשט Pshat of our משנה, Mishna,
but according to רבי שילא Rebbi Shila the issue is that it
has to become טמא בשוגג. Tamei be'shogeg. It doesn't matter how you
did the זריקה. Zrika. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this, אלא הא דתני בין בשוגג בין במזיד, Ela ha detani bein
be'shogeg bein be'meizid, so how would he be the ברייתא Braiysa that
says whether שוגג Shogeg or מזיד? Meizid? הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. נטמא
בשוגג, Nitma be'shogeg, וזרק בו בין בשוגג בין במזיד הורצה. Vezarak bo
bein be'shogeg bein be'meizid hurtzah. As long as it became טמא בשוגג,
Tamei be'shogeg, then I don't care whether you did the זריקה Zrika
knowingly or unknowingly because the issue is the nature of the טומאה,
Tuma, not the nature of the זריקת הדם. Zrikas HaDam. So הא
דתני, Ha detani, how do you handle our משנה Mishna that says
דם שנזרק ואחר כך נודע, Dam shenizrak ve'achar kach noda, that says
you did the זריקה Zrika and then you found out, it sounds
like you had to be ignorant. time of the זריקה *zrika*. טעמא
דנזרק ואחר כך נודע *taama d'nizrak v'acharkach noda*, that sounds like you
did the זריקה *zrika* and then you became aware, אבל נודע ואחר
כך נזרק לאו *aval noda v'acharkach nizrak lav*, it sounds like if
you were aware at the time of the זריקה *zrika* the ציץ
tzitz *tzitz* wouldn't help. לא *lo*, הוה הדין דאפילו נודע ואחר כך
נזרק *hu hadin d'afilu noda v'acharkach nizrak*, really it would be true
even if you knew when you did the זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam*.
והאי דקתני נזרק ואחר כך נודע *v'hai d'katani nizrak v'acharkach noda*, why
then did it give the scenario that you did the זריקה *zrika*
when you were ignorant? משום דבעי למתני סיפא *mishum d'ba'ei l'misni seifa*,
because the end's case of the משנה *mishna* where we say נטמא
הגוף אין הציץ מרצה *nitma haguf ein hatzitz mirtzeh*, that the ציץ
tzitz *tzitz* doesn't work when your person became טמא tamei *tamei*, there
we want to say דאפילו נזרק ואחר כך נודע *d'afilu nizrak v'acharkach
noda*, even if you were ignorant at the time, the ציץ tzitz
*tzitz* isn't going to work if it's yourself who became טמא tamei
*tamei*. לא *lo*, it doesn't work. תני רישא נמי נזרק ואחר כך
נודע *tani reisha nami nizrak v'acharkach noda*. So therefore when we said
the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* does work, we gave the scenario that you
were ignorant at the time, but really for the ציץ tzitz *tzitz*
to work you don't have to be ignorant at the time. So
basically our משנה *mishna* sounds very clearly like the ציץ tzitz *tzitz*
only works if you were ignorant of the problem when you did
the זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam*. We have another ברייתא braita. *braisa* that
seems to say even if you did it willingly. So there are
two approaches in the גמרא Gemara *gemara*. One, which says the first
approach which takes the simple read of our משנה *mishna*, that says
no, for the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* to work, the act that you're
doing that's problematic, the זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam* when the דם *dam*
is טמא tamei *tamei*, the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* will only work if
you're doing that unintentionally, if you're unaware, like the פשט *pshat* of
our משנה *mishna*. When it says I don't care שוגג *shogeg* or
מזיד *meizid*, that means I don't care how it became טמא tamei
*tamei*. But you have to be ignorant when you actually did the
זריקה *zrika* or else the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* isn't going to מרצה
*mirtzeh*. It focuses on the problematic nature of the act of זריקה
*zrika*. That has to be
בשוגג *b'shogeg* for the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* to work. The other approach
emphasizes the ברייתא braita *braisa*. No, actually I don't care if you
did the act willingly. What the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* works if the
nature of the טומאה tumah *tumah* is less problematic. If the טומאה
tumah *tumah* was בשוגג *b'shogeg*, then the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* works. If
the טומאה tumah *tumah* was במזיד *b'meizid*, it doesn't. But the זריקה
*zrika*, that you could do במזיד *b'meizid* as long as the טומאה
tumah *tumah* was בשוגג *b'shogeg*. Okay, so that yes, Charlie.
Practical matter. I'm a כהן kohen *kohen*, I'm טהור tahor *tahor*. Yeah.
The דם *dam* becomes טמא tamei *tamei*. Right. I don't know about—I
put my hand in the דם *dam* to sprinkle it. Under some
circumstances that could make me טמא tamei *tamei*.
Almost no circumstances, because what does it—unless it directly came in contact
with a מת meis? *meis*. Pretty much anything other than a מת
*meis*, the דם *dam* would be a ראשון *rishon* and it would
not affect you. Correct. Okay, that's okay. All right, so all right,
so there you have two opinions. Clearly the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* only
works if there's some degree of unintentionality. Simple sense is that you're
not intentional when you do the זריקה *zrika*, but it could also
be possible that it's enough that it was unintentional when it became
טמא tamei *tamei*. Now we get to the focus, which is going
to be not where it does work, when the objects became טמא
tamei *tamei* and you were unaware, but where it doesn't work when
you yourself became טמא tamei *tamei*. And there even if you were
unaware that you became טמא tamei *tamei*, you were unaware at the
time the קרבן korban? *korban* was brought, it doesn't work. The one
place it does work for פסח Pesach. *pesach* and נזיר Nazir *nazir*,
where it really matters that you're טמא tamei *tamei*, the one place
the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* does work is something called טומאת התהום tumat
hatehom *tumas hatzehom*, which is not that just you were ignorant, but
somehow it was not knowable at the time. And we will clarify
that as we continue today and tomorrow. So let's take a look.
בעי רמי בר חמא *ba'ei rami bar chama*. So רמי בר חמא
*rami bar chama* asks: כהן kohen המרצה בקרבנותיהן *kohen hameratzeh b'korbanoseihen*, הותר
לו טומאת התהום tumat hatehom. או לא *hutar lo tumas hatzehom o
lo*? When we say the טומאת התהום tumat hatehom *tumas hatzehom* became
permitted,
by, you know, the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* works even if the person
becomes טמא *tamei*, this case of טומאת התהום tumat hatehom *tumas hatzehom*,
the טומאה tumah *tumah* of the depths, is that only going to
work for the person bringing the קרבן korban *korban*? Because the only
two קרבנות *korbanos* where it matters that the person bringing it is
טמא *tamei* are—anyway the primary two is פסח Pesach *pesach* and נזיר
Nazir *nazir*. So there it focuses on the person bringing the קרבן
korban *korban* that it works for them. Or what if the כהן
kohen *kohen* is טמא *tamei* and he has a טומאת התהום tumat
hatehom *tumas hatzehom* and he's not aware of it? Will the ציץ
tzitz *tzitz* work for that? Because every קרבן *korban* it matters that
the כהן kohen *kohen* is טמא *tamei*. Only one or two קרבנות
*korbanos* it matters that the owner is טמא *tamei*, but every קרבן
*korban* it matters that the כהן kohen. *kohen* is טמא *tamei*. So
will the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* work for that? כהן kohen, המרצה בקרבנותיהן
*kohen hameratzeh b'korbanoseihen*. And let's say we'll make it even an easier
question. The כהן kohen *kohen* is bringing the קרבן פסח korban Pesach,
*korban pesach*. Not סתם stam *stam* a קרבן *korban*. Or he's bringing
the קרבן *korban* of the נזיר Nazir. *nazir*.
Will the principle of טומאת התהום tumat hatehom *tumas hatzehom* work for
the כהן kohen *kohen* the same way it works for the owner?
So he's bringing their קרבנות *korbanos*. הותר לו טומאת התהום tumas hat’hom
או לא *hutar lo tumas hatzehom o lo*? Does the טומאת התהום
Tumas hat’hom *tumas hatzehom* become permissible, does the ציץ tzitz. *tzitz* work
for that or not? מי אמרינן *mi amrinan* do we say כי
גמירי טומאת התהום tumas hat’hom בבעלים *ki gmeiri tumas hatzehom b'bealim*, when
does this principle apply, this tradition of טומאת התהום tumas hat’hom, *tumas
hatzehom* that the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* works for, is when the owners
of the פסח Pesach *pesach* and the
נזיר *nazir* become—בכהן לא גמירי *b'kohen lo gmeiri*, we don't have that
tradition. או דילמא *o dilma* or maybe it doesn't focus on which
person, בזיבחה גמירי *b'zivcha gmeiri*, the tradition is that for a פסח
Pesach *pesach* and a נזיר *nazir*, טומאת התהום tumas hatehom *tumas hatzehom*
works. I mean the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* works on טומאת התהום *tumas
hatzehom* for any person involved in it. Any person involved in the
קרבן *korban*. לא שנא בכהן ולא שנא בבעלים *lo shna b'kohen v'lo
shna b'bealim*. I don't care if it's the כהן kohein, *kohen* or
the בעלים *bealim*. So is the—is the— Or is the tradition that
it works for the owner of the קרבן, or is the tradition
that it works for any person involved in the קרבן? So אמר
רבא, amar Rava, said רבא, Rava, תא שמע, ta shema, come and
hear, דתניא רבי חייא, de-tanya Rabi Chiya, רבי חייא Rabi Chiya taught
the following
ברייתא. beraisa, לא אמרו טומאת התהום אלא למת בלבד. lo amru tumat
hatehom ela le-mes bilvad. So we're going to see this whole ברייתא
is going to be quoted at the end of tomorrow, but here's
the last line of it is: טומאת התהום only applies to dead
bodies, it doesn't apply to other טומאות. tumot. So the גמרא Gemara
says, למת למעוטי מאי? le-mes l'mautei mai? What are we trying to
exclude? What scenario that might a person have become טמא other than
with a dead body that we're saying that the ציץ tzitz does
not work for that? What are we excluding? מאי לאו למעוטי טומאת
התהום דשרץ? mai lav l'mautei tumat hatehom de-sheretz?
Presumably we mean like it was like a dead rodent, not a
dead body, a dead rodent. Okay, now and if I accidentally came
in contact with a dead rodent in a way that was not
knowable, it was some buried object that my foot kicks in the
sand and nobody could have been aware of it, that in that
type of a case, the ציץ tzitz would not work for me.
Okay, now let's figure this out.
ובמאי עסקינן? u-vemai askinan? What's the case? אילימא בבעלים, eilima b'baalim, I
the owner kicked this dead rodent and wasn't aware of it and
we're saying the ציץ tzitz doesn't work. ובמה? u-vemah? So for whom
do I need the ציץ tzitz to work for in this case?
אי בנזיר, ei b'nazir, if I was a נזיר and I kicked
this dead rodent, so מי מהני ביה? mi mahani beih? The dead
rodent has no effect on me. A נזיר only cares about dead
bodies. כי המת מעלתו אמר רחמנא. ki ha-mes mealoto amar rachmana. So
you wouldn't even need the ציץ tzitz to operate. We don't care
if it's anything other than a dead body, we don't care about
a נזיר. אלא בעושה פסח. ela b'oseh Pesach. So the only person
we would care about if it was not a dead body was
the person bringing the פסח. Pesach. בעושה פסח. b'oseh Pesach. So here
I am, I'm coming to bring my קרבן פסח, korban Pesach I
accidentally kick a dead rodent in the sand that's buried and nobody
knows about it and it's not knowable, and we say the ציץ
tzitz won't work for me and my פסח Pesach, is no good.
Okay, but wait a minute, הניחא. ha nicha. Tell me that the
ציץ tzitz doesn't work and the פסח pesach, is no good. That
works למאן דאמר אין שוחטין וזורקין על טמאי שרץ. l'man d'amar ein
shochtin v'zorkin al tmei sheretz. If you say that
if I'm טמא שרץ tamei sheretz that you can't bring the קרבן
פסח korban Pesach today even though I'll be able to eat it
tonight since I'm טמא right now. So since I'm טמא right now,
even though I can eat it tonight, I can't bring the קרבן
פסח korban Pesach, and therefore the חידוש chiddush is
that the ציץ tzitz won't work to make my קרבן acceptable because
I touched the שרץ sheretz rather than a dead body. All right,
that would make sense.
אלא למאן דאמר שוחטין וזורקין על טמאי שרץ. ela l'man d'amar shochtin
v'zorkin al tmei sheretz. But if you say that if I was
טמא because of touching a dead rodent that I actually can have
the פסח pesach, brought for
me, השתא טומאה ידועה הותרה לו. hashta tumah yeduah hutrah lo. If
even when we know that I touched a dead
rodent, I can bring a קרבן פסח, korban Pesach טומאת התהום לא
כל שכן? tumat hatehom lo kol sheken? It's more so by טומאת
התהום. So what's the case? Again, let's step back. It says like
this. It says the principle that the ציץ tzitz works for טומאת
התהום for buried טומאה tumah, that's not knowable is only true if
the buried טומאה tumah? is a dead body. So what in contrast
to what? So presumably in contrast to, like I said, a dead
rodent or I don't know, a dead carcass of an animal buried
in the sand that I accidentally stepped on that was not knowable,
and that case the ציץ tzitz won't work for me. But why
would I need the ציץ tzitz to work for me? If I'm
bringing my קרבן פסח korban Pesach and I only touched a שרץ
sheretz or a נבילה, neveilah, I don't need the ציץ tzitz to
work for me, right? Now maybe I do, maybe I can't bring
a קרבן פסח korban Pesach even if I'll be טהור tahor tonight,
but let's assume that I'm allowed to bring the קרבן פסח korban
Pesach. if I'm going to be טהור tahor tonight. I don't need
the ציץ to work for me. Even if I knew I touched
it, I could bring the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. So for what
purpose do we have to say the ציץ doesn't work if somebody
touched a dead שרץ? sheretz? For the owners you don't even need
the ציץ to work. So for whom is it relevant that it
doesn't work? So the גמרא Gemara: says, אלא לאו בכהן? ela lav
b'kohen? It must be we're saying that the כהן kohein. accidentally touched
a dead נבילה neveilah or a dead שרץ sheretz and for him...
you mean the כהן גדול? kohen gadol?
No, the כהן kohein doing the פסח. pesach
And for him, if the ציץ doesn't work and he's טמא and
it remains a problem, then the קרבן will be no good. Okay,
so if that's the scenario, ציץ only works for טומאת התהום of
a dead body, not for טומאת התהום of a dead rodent. Now,
you don't even need to talk about that case if the owner
became טמא with a dead rodent, you don't even need the ציץ.
So it's saying if the כהן kohein? became טמא with a dead
rodent, the ציץ doesn't work. Okay, but that suggests that if the
כהן kohein became טמא with a dead body, the ציץ would work.
ושמע מינה הותרה לו טומאת התהום. u-shma mina hutrah lo tumat hatehom.
So you see that in general, the ציץ works not only for
the owner of the פסח, pesach it works even for the כהן.
And therefore we have to say, since it generally works for the
כהן, that's only true about dead bodies, it's not true about dead
rodents where that then if the כהן touched, wound up touching a
dead rodent, he actually would be invalid. ושמע מינה, u-shma mina, and
you see from this, I'm sorry, I read that again, הותרה לו
טומאת התהום, hutrah lo tumat hatehom, that טומאת התהום works for the
כהן as well, not just the owner. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar
Rav Yosef, so that seems like a reasonable proof, but all of
that assumes two assumptions: number one, that the case that we're excluding
is a case of a שרץ. sheretz. There might be another case
that's relevant that we haven't explored yet. And number two, that you
don't need to allow the שרץ sheretz for the owner of the
פסח, pesach because it assumes that an owner of somebody who's טמא
only a one-day טומאה tumah can bring a קרבן פסח. korban pesach,
If we're talking about something other than a שרץ, sheretz, or if
somebody who's טמא with a שרץ sheretz can't bring the קרבן פסח,
korban pesach. then again, we're not talking about the כהן, you could
be talking about the owner. So let's see what the answer is,
or might. But certainly there's no proof we're talking about the כהן.
So אמר רב יוסף לא. Amar Rav Yosef Lo. No, it's not
a proof. לעולם בבעלים, Le’olam b’be’alim, we're talking about the
owners, ובפסח, U’v’pesach, and they're bringing a קרבן פסח. korban pesach. So
why do I care if it's something other than a מת? It
would only be a one-day טומאה which shouldn't be a problem, because
we're not excluding the שרץ sheretz case, we're excluding something
else: ולמעוטי טומאת התהום דזיבה, U’l’me’utei tumas hat’hom d’ziva, a טומאה of
the depths of being a זב zav or a זבה zava if
it's a woman. Now of course that's a little bizarre. Normally you
assume טומאת התהום means the object that's טמא is buried somewhere underground
which is the normal sort of paradigm and you're not aware of
it. If there's a question about having a menstrual flow or a
זב zav flow or a man having a flow, nothing is buried
underground. טומאת התהום gets abstracted to mean, as I said, any טומאת
ספק tumas safeik that's unknowable at the time. So what would be
that case? Here's the case in the
גמרא: Gemara זבה, zava, a woman... exactly, a woman has a one-day
flow one day. What's the הלכה? halacha? She has a vaginal flow
of blood,
also a man who's a זב, zav, or we talk about a
woman who's a זבה, zava, not during her menstrual period. So she
needs, what, that was on Monday. On Tuesday she needs all of
Tuesday not to bleed and then she'll be טהורה. tehorah. If on
Tuesday she bleeds, then she's טהורה tehorah Monday and Tuesday and she
needs to go Wednesday without bleeding. And if she winds up bleeding
on Wednesday and it's three days in a row, then she's a
זבה גדולה, zava gedola, she's טמאה tmeiah for seven days. So let's
say she saw on Monday and now Tuesday is ערב פסח, Erev
Pesach, she wants to bring a קרבן פסח. korban pesach She hasn't
bled yet, but if she bleeds after she brings a קרבן פסח
korban pesach retroactively we'll find out that she's been טמאה tmeiah the
whole time. So that's a case of טומאת התהום at the time
she's bringing her פסח, pesach it is unknowable whether she is טמאה
tmeiah right now or not. That will be determined based on whether
she bleeds later today. Okay, so let's take a look. And that's
what we have to say, that that's where you say that the
ציץ does not work for that because it's not טומאת מת tumas
meis and therefore we could still be talking about the owner. And
therefore since the ציץ doesn't work, if she winds up bleeding retroactively
she was טמאה, tmeiah, the פסח pesach was no good.
So she shouldn't have been allowed to bring her קרבן פסח korban
pesach let's say?
Not if you say the ציץ doesn't work, no.
Meaning she hasn't bled yet.
Can she bring it and take her odds? Maybe. Okay, ולמעוטי טומאת
התהום דזיבה. U’l’me’utei tumas hat’hom d’ziva. So the גמרא Gemara’s says וטומאת
התהום דזיבה לא מרצה? V’tumas hat’hom d’ziva lo mirtza? What,
you're saying it doesn't work? Actually it does work. How do you
know? דתניא, D’tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi
Yosei omer, שומרת יום כנגד יום, shomeres yom k’neged yom, a woman
who watches one day opposite a day. She bled on Monday, she
has to watch Tuesday. ששחטו וזרקו עליה בשני שלה, She’shachatu v’zarku aleha
b’sheini shela,
and they brought the קרבן פסח korban pesach for her on her
second day, meaning Tuesday in my scenario, because it's number day two,
day one was the day she bled. ואחר כך ראתה, V’achar kach
ra’asa, and then she bled after the קרבן פסח was brought on
Tuesday. So what's the הלכה? halacha? It wound up retroactively she was
טמאה tmeiah the whole time. אינה
אוכלת, Eina ocheles, she cannot eat that night because she's טמאה, tmeiah,
ופטורה מלעשות פסח שני. u’p’tura milaasos Pesach Sheini. But she's פטורה p’tura
from פסח שני. Pesach Sheini. Now why is she פטורה p’tura from
פסח שני Pesach Sheini when the פסח was brought, it turns out
retroactively she was טמאה? tmeiah? So what do you see? מאי טעמא,
Mai ta’ama, what's the reason she's פטורה? p’tura? לאו משום דמרצה ציץ?
Lav mishum d’mirtza tzitz?
Don't you think it's because the ציץ actually did work? And since
at that time it was unknowable, it was a type of a
טומאת התהום, the ציץ works. So you can't tell me the ציץ
doesn't work on the case of a זב zav or a זבה
zava which was unknowable, because we actually see according to רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosei it does work. בדיעבד B’di’eved it was good.
And meanwhile we have the opposite, that she's חייב chayav in פסח
שני Pesach Sheini to begin with.
All right, so תוספות Tosafos asks that question, maybe סתם she's פטורה
p’tura from פסח שני. Pesach Sheini. Anyway, so let's just read the
גמרא's Gemara answer and we'll pick up with this tomorrow. אמרי לא.
Amri lo. No, maybe the reason it works in that case is
not because the ציץ works. Maybe the reason it works is the
following reason: משום דקסבר רבי יוסי מכאן ולהבא היא מטמאה. Mishum d’kasvar
Rabbi Yosei mikan u’l’haba hi mitameia. That maybe רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei
holds if a woman bled on Monday,
went to the מקוה mikvah Tuesday morning, and then bled at Tuesday
at 3:00 PM, from 8:00 AM when she went to the מקוה
mikvah until 3:00 PM, she remains טהורה, tehorah, and she only becomes
טמאה tmeiah again at 3:00 PM. So when the פסח was brought,
it's not retroactively she was טמאה tmeiah the whole time. It's a
new טומאה, it's not a continuous one. Of course if that's true,
so let's take a look. The גמרא gemara, says, okay so that's
why she can't eat
tonight because 3:00 PM onward she's טמאה, tmeiah, but she's פטורה p’tura
from bringing a פסח because when the פסח was brought she was
טהורה. tehorah. So גמרא, gemara so you know what, we'll end here
and we'll pick up with this tomorrow, which is the question of
when a זב zav sees or a זבה zava sees after they
did one day's one day, the beginning of the day she was
טהורה tehora and she went to the מקוה mikva and then she
sees again, does it retroactively mean she was טמאה temaya the whole
time or is it a new טומאה? But either way what we're
going to see is that in the case by זבה, zava, at
least according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, if you brought during that
period between the מקוה mikva and later seeing, it will be דיעבד,
di'eved, it will be okay, actually you'll be יוצא, yotzei, either because
the ציץ works, because of a טומאת התהום idea, in which not
known at start, or because you were טהור at the time, it's
a new טומאה later. And this is actually, so either way though
according to רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi it does work. So the גמרא
will sort of in the end get back to this question of
whether the ציץ works for the כהן or not, trying to figure
out what is the scenario that we have to say the ציץ
only works with corpses and not with other things. Does that relate
to the owner or does that relate to the כהן? Can we
prove from that whether the ציץ is operative for the כהן or
not? To be continued tomorrow.
חזק. Chazak.