Okay, so לילה טוב *layla tov*. ערב טוב *erev tov*. Our דף
daf, *daf* is צדי זין *tzaddi zayin* and what we pick up
in the middle of צדי ו עמוד ב *tzaddi vav amud bet*.
And the משנה *mishnah* basically had said that sometimes if a פסח
pesach *pesach*, it started with a discussion of a תמורה tmura *temurah*,
but it moved from there to the issue of a פסח pesach
*pesach* and said that sometimes if a פסח pesach *pesach* itself can
be brought as a שלמים shlamim *shelamim* if it wasn't used on
פסח pesach *pesach*
and sometimes you would have to wait for it to get a
מום *mum*, a blemish, redeem the value, and use the proceeds. What's
the difference? So the משנה *mishnah* gave the difference as if it
was lost and you sanctified another one and then the first one
was found and you שחט *shechted* the new one with the old
one available to you, that's considered like you were דוחה docheh *docheh*,
like you pushed it away. You had it as an option, you
pushed it away. You didn't have a choice, but nevertheless you pushed
it away and therefore it's considered נדחה nidche, *nidcheh*, it's stigmatized and
that can't be used itself and you have to wait for the
use the proceeds. Whereas if it was found after you שחט *shechted*
the new one, then this one was never available to you that
you pushed it away and therefore you can use the קרבן korban
*korban* itself. Okay, and that's the difference between whether the פסח pesach?
*pesach* itself can be used and the משנה *mishnah* says and the
same would be true about the תמורה tmura *temurah*. If you tried
to transfer the פסח pesach *pesach* to another animal, that animal gets
the same status as the פסח pesach, *pesach*, the פסח pesach *pesach*
remains קדוש *kadosh*, the second animal gets the same status and the
תמורה tmura *temurah* as well, whether it can be used or not
would go by whether the original פסח pesach *pesach* can be used
or not.
Yes, and that's רבי Rebbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*'s explanation.
That's רבי Rabbi, עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*'s explanation. Now we're going to go
with how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* discusses some of these parameters. So
we're in the two dots, it's about halfway down the page on
צדי ו עמוד ב *tzaddi vav amud bet*. אחר שחיטת הפסח יבוא
שלמים shlamim. *acher shechitas hapesach yavo shelamim*. So if this happens after
the פסח pesach *pesach* was brought that you found the old one,
then you can bring this קרבן *korban* itself. So אמר רבא Rava
*amar Rava*, לא 'Lo', שנו אלא שנמצא אחר שחיטה shechita, והמיר בו
אחר שחיטה 'v'heimir bo achar shechita', *lo shanu ella shenimtza acher shechita
vehimur bo acher shechita*. When is it that the תמורה tmura *temurah*
can be used? It is when the original פסח pesach. *pesach* was
found after שחיטה shechita. *shechita*, so the original one was never pushed
away, and then the act of תמורה tmura *temurah* was done. Obviously
you can only do the תמורה tmura *temurah* once you have the
original one, was done after שחיטה shechita, *shechita*. That's when it can
be used itself, the תמורה tmura *temurah*. אבל נמצא קודם שחיטה shechita,
*aval nimtza kodem shechita*, let's say the original one was found before
שחיטה shechita *shechita*, so therefore it was perforce pushed away, so it's
נדחה nidcha, *nidcheh*, והמיר בו אחר שחיטה shechita *vehimur bo acher shechita*,
and but you did the תמורה tmura *temurah* after the שחיטה shchita,
*shechita*. So you might think that in that case the תמורה tmura
*temurah* maybe is not so bad because the תמורה tmura *temurah* was
never pushed away, the act of תמורה tmura *temurah* was done after
the פסח pesach. *pesach* had already been brought. So maybe the תמורה
tmura. *temurah* itself can be brought. No, nevertheless that cannot be brought
either. Why? תמורה tmura. אז מכח קדושה kdusha דחויה dchuya. קאתי *temurah
so mikosh kedusha dechuya kaasai* because the תמורה tmura *temurah* is basically
a carbon copy of the original and since the original פסח pesach,
*pesach* was pushed off, the תמורה tmura *temurah* which is its duplicate
and therefore it also is נדחה nidcha? *nidcheh* ולא קריבה *velo kriva*
and cannot be offered. I'm going to just visually do this because
I think it can get confusing.
Yeah, so here
we have
your
little sheep, okay.
So this
is, this
will be your old one, your original, okay. And then it got
lost.
Right, I have to do this right.
Okay,
so here was your original sheep, okay, and it got lost. So
this was at ten AM. Okay, then here you go, here's your
new one and you sanctified that as a פסח pesach; *pesach*, you
sanctified that. Okay, and then here's your going to do the שחיטה
shchita *shechita*. Give me a little שחיטה shchita *shechita*. Okay,
this will be at one PM. Okay, so what is the story?
Where is the original one that got lost? Where was it at
this time? So if it was around, it was נמצא קודם שחיטה
shchita *nimtza kodem shechita*, okay, this then that act of שחיטה shchita
*shechita* what that does when you שחט *shecht* this and you're rejecting
this, so it's דוחה docheh *docheh* then. It pushes that away because
you have the choice and you're שחט *shechting*, you're שחט *shechting* this
one, so you're pushing that one away. That's the case and in
this case this can only be דמי *damah*, they can only be
the proceeds, you can't bring it itself. That's the point that רבי
Rabbi עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* makes. If this was found after the שחיטה
shchita *shechita*, you never pushed it away and it's okay. So the
question is what's the story with if it is this scenario, this
was נדחה nidcha *nidcheh*, and then after שחיטה shchita *shechita* you tried
to make a תמורה tmura *temurah*. You tried to say, oh, let
me go ahead and try to transfer, which doesn't work. So what
is the story of that תמורה tmura *temurah*? Do we say this
was already נדחה nidcha, *nidcheh*, this is basically
coming to be a תמורה tmura. *temurah* for that, so it's also
קדושה kedusha דחויה dchuya, *kedusha dechuya* which is what רבא Rava *Rava*
says, it also is stigmatized, can't be used, or do we say
look, when I got around to sanctify this animal although I've given
way and a תמורה tmura? way. I wasn't rejecting it or whatever;
I was a new sanctity to that animal and therefore I should
be able to bring the תמורה tmura itself, and I should be
able to bring it itself as a שלמים shlamim, and it does
not get the pushed away status that the original one did. So
רבא Rava is saying no, I'm sorry, it comes from the קדושה
kedusha of the original and it itself remains דחויה. dchuya Okay, that
is רבא's Rava statement. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with
it. Okay, איתיביה אביי, Eisvei Abaye, אביי Abaye asked him: 'אם כשב',
'Im kesev', the פסוק posuk speaks about a שלמים. shlamim, If you
bring a lamb, 'מה תלמוד לומר אם כשב'? 'Ma talmud lomar im
kesev'? Why did it have to say 'אם כשב'? 'Im kesev'? Now,
why what's extra? So רש"י Rashi said maybe the 'אם' 'im' is
extra, maybe the word 'כשב' 'kesev' is extra, because the next part
speaks about a goat, so I could have inferred that the first
one was a lamb. Something is seen as being extra. So what's
the point of saying that? 'לרבות תמורת הפסח אחר פסח שקרבה שלמים'.
'Lirabos tmuras hapesach achar pesach shekreiva shlamim'.
To tell you, because this is a פרשה parsha about שלמים, shlamim.
bringing a שלמים, shlamim. that even other things are a שלמים. shlamim.
Even a פסח pesach. that is a תמורה tmura. of a פסח
pesach. if this happened after the original פסח pesach, was brought, after
the new פסח Pesach was brought.
Okay, and you have a
תמורה tmura, of the original ones, that also is brought as a
שלמים. shlamim? So it tells you the הלכה halacha that the תמורה
tmura, in this scenario is brought as a שלמים. shlamim. So אביי
Abaye says like this, okay, so he says: 'היכי דמי', 'Heichi dami',
what's the case that we're talking about bringing the תמורה tmura as
a שלמים? shlamim, 'אילימא שנמצא אחר שחיטה והמיר בו אחר שחיטה', 'Ilimah
she'nimtza achar shechita v'heimir bo achar shechita', if everything happened after שחיטה,
shchita. okay, this is the alternative scenario.
Okay, the alternative scenario is that, I don't know if this is
helping or making it more confusing, but the original one itself was
found only later, only after שחיטה. shchita, So in this case, it
was never נדחה, nidcheh. this was always acceptable, so the תמורה tmura
is always acceptable. Like, there's never a problem.
So that isn't conceivably being brought as someone else's פסח?
Pesach, Well, פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, it's after... oh, because you mean
it's פסח Pesach, itself? Yeah, but you can't transfer ownership of a
פסח, pesach, so anyway, it gets confusing. Okay, anyway.
Okay, but maybe used for פסח שני? Pesach Sheni? Right.
If that's the
scenario, 'היכי דמי'? 'heichi dami'? 'אילימא שנמצא אחר שחיטה והמיר בו אחר
שחיטה פשיטא'! 'Ilimah she'nimtza achar shechita v'heimir bo achar shechita, peshita'! Of
course you can bring the תמורה tmura as a שלמים. shlamim. You
bring the פסח pesach as a שלמים, shlamim, you know, it was
never pushed away. It was lost and now you'll bring it after
פסח pesach as a שלמים. shlamim 'פשיטא, למה לי קרא'? 'Peshita, lama
li kra'? Why do I need a פסוק? posuk? 'אלא לאו', 'Ella
lav', if the פסוק posuk is coming to tell me a חידוש
chidush that I can bring a תמורה of a פסח pesach, as
a שלמים, shlamim, it must have been a scenario where there would
have been a reasonable reason to think I can't. So 'אלא לאו
שנמצא קודם שחיטה', 'Ella lav she'nimtza kodem shechita', it must mean רבא's
Rava scenario, that the original one was found before שחיטה, shchita, 'והמיר
בו אחר שחיטה', shchita and the תמורה act was done after שחיטה,
shchita and in that scenario there's a good reason to think it
can't be a שלמים shlamim. because the original one can't be. So
therefore, and that's what the פסוק posuk would tell me. So if
the פסוק posuk is telling me something, presumably it's telling me that
רבא Rava? is wrong. So the גמרא Gemara says: 'לא', no, you
don't have to say that. 'לא, אם שנמצא אחר שחיטה והמיר בו
אחר שחיטה', 'Lo, im she'nimtza achar shechita v'heimir bo achar shechita', it
could be the simple case where the original one was found after
שחיטה shchita. and the תמורה was after שחיטה shchita. and the original
one itself could be a שלמים, shlamim, so of course the תמורה
can be a שלמים. shlamim? So your whole question was that's obvious!
So the גמרא Gemara says: 'וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא'. 'V'kra asmachta b'alma'.
Okay, so it's obvious, so we didn't really mean it. So the
פסוק posuk isn't really telling me that; the פסוק posuk was just
a support. So he basically quotes this פסוק posuk to tell me
you can bring the תמורת פסח tmuras pesach as a שלמים, shlamim
and the גמרא Gemara says if it's not talking about רבא's Rava.
scenario, it's obvious! So fine, it's obvious, it wasn't really learning it
from that פסוק posuk anyway. Okay, so now that we say it's
an אסמכתא asmachta and it's not teaching that, 'קרא למה לי אתא'?
'Kra lama li ata'? What is the פסוק posuk being מחדש? mechadesh?
Again, assuming somehow the words 'אם כשב' 'im kesev' are seen as
extra words. So that's to tell you something else. 'כדתניא', 'Ki d'tanya',
like we taught in the ברייתא: braisa: 'כשב', 'Kesev', a lamb, 'לרבות
את הפסח לאליה'. 'Lirabos es hapesach l'alya'.
That tells you that because the תורה Torah never tells you what
you do with the fat of a פסח. pesach תורה Torah never
really tells you what you do with the blood of the פסח.
Pesach, We only learn from a general פסוק posuk that says 'ודם
זבחיך ישפך על מזבח ה' אלהיך והבשר תאכל'. 'v'dam zvachecha yishapech al
mizbe'ach Hashem Elokecha v'habasar tochel'. So, so how do we know what
you do with the fat? That's another very general פסוק, posuk, not
about the פסח, Pesach that speaks about
'ועשית', 'v'asisa', what... no, what's the פסוק? posuk? It says 'ואת דמם
תזרק על המזבח ואת חלבם תקטיר'. 'v'es damam tizrok al hamizbeach v'es
chelbum taktir'. Okay, so it just tells you burn their חלב. chelev.
And again, that's not even really about a פסח; Pesach, it's a
very generic פסוק posuk that we apply to a פסח. Pesach. So
we never get any details about what you actually do with the
חלב chelev of the פסח. Pesach, You know, is it exactly like
a שלמים? shlamim Is it different? So that's what this פסוק posuk
is coming to tell you, these extra words by a שלמים shlamim
to tell you by a real פסח, Pesach. you treat the fat
like you would by a שלמים shlamim, because there's never... never enough
detail in the תורה *Torah* about the fats of a פסח Pesach,
*Pesach*. So לרבות את הפסח לאליה *lerabbos es ha-Pesach l'alyah*, and the
חידוש *chiddush* is that it also
is that even the fat tail, the normal חלב *cheilev* is the
fat on the inside, right by sheep the תורה *Torah* when it
speaks about burning the fat on the מזבח *mizbe'ach* always includes the
fat tail. Okay, but again it never says anything by a פסח
Pesach *Pesach* about the
specifics about the fat. So the חידוש *chiddush* of the שלמים shlamim.
*Shlomim* to say אם כשב *im kesev* is to tell you even
if you have something else that's a lamb, a פסח Pesach, *Pesach*
that's a lamb, treat it just like this and burn the fat
tail as well. Okay, so כשהוא אומר אם כשב *kshehu omer im
kesev*, so now כשב *kesev* maybe was telling you a פסח Pesach,
*Pesach* you do the fat tail. What's the word אם *im* telling
you? לרבות פסח Pesach, שעבר שנתו ושלמים הבא מחמת פסח Pesach לכל
מצות שלמים shlamim, *lerabbos Pesach she-avar shnaso v'shlomim habo machmas Pesach l'chol
mitzvas Shlomim*. Basically to tell you the basic הלכה halacha *halacha* that
we've been assuming all along that if you can't bring if the
פסח Pesach, *Pesach* wasn't brought, it gets converted into a שלמים shlamim.
*Shlomim*. And that it follows all the laws of a שלמים shlamim.
*Shlomim*. So a פסח Pesach *Pesach* that is no longer a year
old, okay, or if things that are proceeds of a פסח Pesach
*Pesach*, it got a מום *mum* and you transfer the value, you
didn't bring it as a פסח Pesach *Pesach*, anything like that, the
הלכה halacha? *halacha* is a פסח Pesach *Pesach* that wasn't brought becomes
a שלמים shlamim. *Shlomim*. שטעון סמיכה *she-ta'un smicha*, you put your hands
on it which you know the סמיכה *smicha* which you would not
do by the פסח pesach, *Pesach* itself. ונסכים *ve-nisachim*, the wine and
the flour, ותנופת חזה ושוק *ve-tenufas chazeh ve-shok*, the waving of the
breast and the שוק *shok*, again none of this you do by
a פסח pesach, *Pesach*, but once it gets converted into a שלמים
shlamim, *Shlomim*, all the laws of the שלמים shlamim. *Shlomim* apply to
two bread offerings rather than... Yeah, and the זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam*,
right, although that wasn't being said, correct. Okay, so what are we
doing with this? Not to tell you תמורה *tmurah*, that's obvious. To
tell you number one, a פסח pesach *Pesach* gets converted into a
שלמים shlamim. *Shlomim*. Number two, that a פסח pesach *Pesach* the fats
are treated like even a normal פסח pesach *Pesach* you also do
the fat tail. Okay, and כשהוא אומר ואם עז *ukshehu omer ve-im
ez*, then the תורה *Torah* says but if your שלמים shlamim *Shlomim*
is not a sheep but it's a goat, פסקיה עניינא *paskeih inyana*,
that's somewhat saying ואם *ve-im*, again maybe focusing on the אם *im*
or the ואם *ve-im*, to tell you this is different if it's
a goat. In what way is a goat different? למעט את העז
שאין טעונה אליה *l'me'at es ha-ez she-ein te'una alyah*, to tell you
that whenever you bring a goat sacrifice, maybe a goat פסח pesach
*Pesach* or whatever, but any goat sacrifice, you don't bring a fat
tail. Now, only the sense it said כשב *kesev* includes the פסח
pesach *Pesach* for fat tail, that's if your פסח *Pesach* is a
lamb, but your פסח *Pesach* could also be a goat. And if
it's a goat then you don't bring the fat tail. Again, this
is clear by other קרבנות *korbanos*, but it never gives you detail
by פסח *Pesach* so we're learning it out by parallel by these
words by the שלמים shlamim, *Shlomim*. Now, I do have to say
something about telling you that a goat doesn't bring a fat tail.
Anybody ever see what the tail of a goat looks like?
It looks like this, okay. Even if...
if you ever see what the tail of a sheep looks like,
it is a big fat tail that's like looking at it from
behind that looks like that. A goat doesn't have a fat tail.
You don't have to say don't... don't bring the fat tail of
the goat, it doesn't exist. So רש"י *Rashi* is sort of aware
of this and רש"י *Rashi* says oh, from this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
it's a proof that a goat actually does have a fat tail
because if a goat didn't have a fat tail, why would you
need a פסוק pasuk *passuk* to exclude it? Okay, that is the
assumption of this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but it's not true, so I
don't know what the answer is.
Did they not raise goats in France?
Yeah, I don't know, maybe רש"י *Rashi* means that the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* would have assumed even the simple tail of a goat was
called a fat tail, I really don't know. Anyway, let's move on.
Okay, so that's what you do with the פסוק pasuk? *passuk*, but
that's getting really off track. Our focus is again רבא Rava, *Rava*'s
statement about the תמורה *tmurah* and when, you know, when can it
be brought itself and when only the proceeds. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: איכא דאמתני
לה *Ika d'amslei* ארישא *a-reisha*. Now, some teach this teaching of רבא
Rava, *Rava* not on the end of the משנה *mishna* which says
when it's brought itself, but on the beginning of the משנה *mishna*
when it says you can only use the proceeds. And basically have
רבא *Rava* saying the reverse thing. Okay, and here's the case. הפסח
שנמצא קודם שחיטת הפסח ירעה עד שיסתאב *Ha-pesach shenimtzah kodem shechitas ha-pesach
yireh ad she-yista'ev*, if it was found before שחיטה shechitah *shechita*, then
the original one has to get a blemish, וימכר ויביא בדמיו שלמים
*v'yimacher v'yavi b'damav shlomim*, and use the proceeds for a שלמים *Shlomim*,
you can't bring the original one. וכן תמורתו *V'chein tmurato*, that would
also apply to the תמורה *tmurah*. So okay, that's the case when
it was found before, it's only the proceeds. Now, what is... and
which תמורה *tmurah* are we talking about? אמר רבא לא שנו אלא
שנמצא קודם שחיטה shechitah, והמיר בו קודם שחיטה shechitah, *Amar Rava lo
shanu ela shenimtzah kodem shechita v'himir bo kodem shechita*. When is the
תמורה *tmurah* also not usable itself? If the act of תמורה *tmurah*
was also done before שחיטה shechitah, *shechita*. אבל נמצא קודם שחיטה shechitah
והמיר בו אחר שחיטה shechitah *Aval nimtzah kodem shechita v'himir bo achar
shechita*, but if the act of תמורה *tmurah* was done after שחיטה
shechitah *shechita*, תמורתה קריבה *tmurata kreiva*, you can bring the תמורה *tmurah*.
Right, so as a שלמים *Shlomim*. מאי טעמא *Mai ta'ama*, what's the
reason? כי קבע שחיטה shechitah *Ki kava shechita*, when did the שחיטה
shechitah, *shechita* have an effect to make something נדחה *nidcheh*, pushed off,
מדי דחזי ליה *mi-de-chazi lei*, something that was fit, meaning the other
animal that was already sanctified, מדי דלא חזי ליה לא קבע *mi-de-lo
chazi lei lo kava*, something that it wasn't fit it didn't establish
the set. So basically we're once again dealing with this case, if
it was נדחה *nidcheh* and you did the תמורה *tmurah* here at
this time before... you know, before שחיטה shechitah. *shechita*, okay, basically what
you did was you found this... Then you made a תמורה, and
then you did a שחיטה, shechitah, the שחיטה shechitah would equally be
pushing off the original and the תמורה. These two are both in
the same category; the act of שחיטה shechitah rejects them. So he
says that's the case where you can't bring the תמורה. But in
this case, the שחיטה shechitah pushed this away, then afterwards you did
the תמורה and this was a new act, so when you sanctified
that, the שחיטה shechitah didn't impact this animal, this animal didn't even
exist for all intents and purposes when the שחיטה shechita was being
done. So the שחיטה shechita only pushed away the original one and
therefore, even though this is a copy of the original, it never
was pushed away and you can actually bring the תמורה itself. So
basically it's a way of saying the exact opposite of what he
said before, that, and that is the question: does the תמורה inherit
the status of נדחה, of pushed away, of the original? Or is
it only stigmatized what it itself was נדחה? That is the question.
Now let's take a look. איתיביה אביי, Eisivei Abaye, so Abaye asks
on the previous one, he's asking now even though this is the
reverse position, from a different ברייתא braita but same type of topic.
אם כבש, Im keves, another Tannaitic discussion about this שלמים and אם
כבש, im keves, מה תלמוד לומר, ma talmud lomar, what's that teach
you? לרבות תמורת פסח אחר פסח שקריבה שלמים.
L'rabos tmuras pesach achar pesach
shekriva shlamim. So that's starting off the same way. A תמורת פסח
tmuras pesach after פסח can be brought as a שלמים, as if
everything was after פסח, let's say, after the שחיטה. shechita, יכול אף
לפני פסח כן, Yachol af lifnei pesach kein, maybe even if the
תמורה was done before the פסח, תלמוד לומר talmud lomar הוא. hu.
No, it says by the פסוק pasuk it says הוא, hu, פסח
הוא לה'. Pesach hu l'Adonai. הוא קרב, Hu kareiv, there are some
times where only the original one can be brought, a real פסח,
ואין תמורת פסח קריבה, v'ein tmuras pesach kriva, and sometimes you can't
bring a תמורה. So now we're going to focus on that, the
fact that we're learning out from פסח הוא pesach hu that certain
תמורות tmuros cannot be brought. So it's going to be a similar
argument. היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's
the case that we have to tell me don't bring the תמורה?
אילימא שנמצא קודם שחיטה והמיר בו קודם שחיטה, Ilima shenimtza kodem shchita
v'himir bo kodem shchita, if everything took place before שחיטה, shechita. the
תמורה and the original, and then you did the שחיטה, shechita, פשיטא,
pshita, of course you can't bring the תמורה. למה לי קרא, Lama
li kra, why would I need a פסוק? pasuk Because if the
שחיטה shechita. is rejecting the פסח and it's rejecting the תמורה, I
don't need a פסוק pasuk for that. אלא לאו, Ela lav, if
I needed a פסוק pasuk, to tell me don't bring the תמורה,
it must be for this scenario. שנמצא קודם שחיטה והמיר בו אחר
שחיטה, Shenimtza kodem shchita v'himir bo achar shchita, the original one was
found before שחיטה shechita,
and the תמורה act was done after שחיטה. shechita. In that scenario,
I might have said, yeah, bring the תמורה because that was never
pushed off, that only came into the picture after שחיטה. shechita. And
that would be why the הוא hu is telling me תפלה, tefela,
don't bring it because the original קדושה was from this דחויה, from
this פסח that was pushed off. So the גמרא Gemara actually, even
though it says alright, big deal, you wouldn't have needed a פסוק
had it not been this case, it seems like there's a lot
of available answers to that. The גמרא Gemara actually buys into that
as a question. תיובתא דרבא תיובתא. Tyuvta d'Rava tyuvta. Wow, that is
very strong language. That's like a knockdown question. Why didn't he just
say אסמכתא? asmachta? Why didn't he say big deal, it's obvious אסמכתא?
asmachta? He says well, because we didn't have anything else to do
with the פסוק, so it couldn't have been an אסמכתא. asmachta. Anyway,
whatever. It's not so clear.
Is this one of the six times in ש"ס Shas that אביי
Abaye beats רבא?
Yes, one version of רבא. No, that's like a more when they
maintained a different position; it's not in the back and forth. Anyway,
the upshot of this is that this scenario which we're talking about,
although the sort of proof is to me seems weak, the גמרא
Gemara accepts the proof, that in this scenario, like the first לשון
lashon of רבא, the תמורה is no good. It inherits the דחויה
status, the pushed-off status, the נדחה status of the original, and even
though it itself was never נדחה, it itself, it remains not good
because it inherits that status. So that's basically what we have concluded.
Now we have another a little debate of שמואל Shmuel and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that's going to take us through the whole remainder
of the דף, daf. where שמואל Shmuel is going to say a
cryptic statement and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to say what
we've been saying all along. We're going to spend the whole time
trying to figure out what שמואל Shmuel meant. So let's take a
look. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, said שמואל. Shmuel. כל שבחטאת מתה, Kol
she'b'chatas mesa, anytime you have a הלכה halacha that if a certain
type, that if an animal as a חטאת chatas would have to
be let to die, you basically leave it in a pen and
you let it die because a חטאת chatas that cannot be brought,
you can't do anything else with it, right? It's specifically for this
owner, for this sin. If the owner died or brought another קרבן
or whatever, you can't repurpose the חטאת. chatas. So logically what you
would think you could be able to do is wait for it
to get a blemish, transfer the value and use the proceeds and
make a new חטאת. chatas. But the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai is that in most cases you have to let it die.
There are a few cases you can do that; most cases you
have to let it die. So שמואל Shmuel says all those cases
that were they to occur to a חטאת chatas you would let
it
die, בפסח קרב שלמים. b'pesach kareiv shlamim. If those scenarios, I'll talk
about those scenarios in a minute, occur to a פסח, then you
would bring the פסח itself, you would bring it as a
שלמים. רועה ro'eh, *ro'eh*, any case were to occur to a חטאת
chatat. *Chatas*, you would let it graze until it got a blemish
and transfer the value, בפסח נמי רועה ro'eh *be'Pesach nami ro'eh*. The
הלכה halacha *halacha* would be by the פסח *Pesach* as well, you
can't bring the פסח *Pesach* itself, you have to let it graze
and transfer the value. Now Rashi points out there's no logical connection
here, why the system by פסח *Pesach* seems to be a concern
of is it נידחה *nidcheh* or not. Okay, what does that have
to do with questions of a חטאת chatat, *Chatas* of whether it
is whether you have to let it die or let it graze?
So Rashi actually says there's no logic here, he's just using this
as an organizing principle, סימנא בעלמא *simana be'alma* is what Rashi says.
It's not that somehow they're logically connected, but it just so happens
that similar scenarios lead to these different types of conclusions, okay? So
he says, if you want to know about a פסח *Pesach*, is
it a שלמים *shlamim* or do you have to use the proceeds,
ask yourself what you would do in case of a חטאת chatat.
*Chatas*. Okay, now we're going to unpack that for the rest of
the day, for the night. But רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*
makes a simple statement. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan? אמר אין פסח קרב
karev שלמים אלא שנמצא אחר שחיטה shechita *Rabbi Yochanan amar ein Pesach
karev shlamim ela she'nimtza achar shechita*. Plus everything, plus straight, he's straight
talker, everything we've been saying until now. When do you bring it
itself as a שלמים *shlamim*? If it was found it was lost
and found after שחיטה shechita. *shechita*, because then it was never pushed
away. אבל קודם שחיטה shechita, *aval kodem shechita*, if it was found
before שחיטה shechita *shechita*, לא *lo*, it would not be brought as
a שלמים *shlamim*, fine, because it was pushed away, everything we've been
saying. So the question is, what the heck is שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*
talking about? Now let me first just spend a second to tell
you what are the cases of חטאת chatat, מתה meisa. *Chatas mesa*.
So there's a nice little mnemonic, which is ותמנע *Vitinnah*. ותמנע היתה
פילגש לאליפז בן עמלק *Vitinnah haysa pelagesh le'Lifaz ben Amalek*. Okay, so
seems like a pretty obscure thing that the תורה *Torah* is telling
us. So it serves as a nice mnemonic for telling us the
five חטאות chata'ot, *Chatasos* that you have to let die. ו *vav*
is ולד חטאת chatat, *vlad Chatas*, it gave birth, so obviously it's
not the original but it has the same קדושה *kedusha*, so what
are you going to do with it? ת *tes* is תמורת חטאת
chatat, *tmuras Chatas*, again it has the same קדושה *kedusha* but you
can't use it. מ *mem* is מתו בעליה *mesu be'aleha*, same problem,
right? נ *nun* is נתכפרו באחר *nichperu
be'acher*, so basically a case of אבוד avud *avud*.
It got lost, they brought another
one, and then you found the old one. Okay, so that's like
the cases we've been talking about. And the ע *ayin* is עבר
שנתו *avar shnaso*, it's
no longer a year old. Now by the way, not all of
these are possible by פסח *Pesach*. Which ones are not possible by
פסח *Pesach*? Well, could you figure it out? There's one that's very
obvious, the עבר שנתו *avar shnaso* one. Well, עבר שנתו *avar shnaso*
is a scenario by פסח *Pesach*, right? And that's what so that
could happen and then you that's what would be an issue that
we're going to deal with. It has to be female? Yeah, you
can't have a ולד פסח *vlad Pesach*, פסח *Pesach* is male. חטאת
chatat *Chatas* is female. And תמורה *tmura*, we're not talking about תמורה
*tmura*, we're not talking about the one itself, so that's not relevant.
So the ones that are relevant for us would be these. Okay,
this is our case of אבוד avud *avud*, but also worth discussing
is מתו בעליה *mesu be'aleha* and עבר שנתו *avar shnaso*. So he
says those scenarios, presumably this is what he's saying, you would bring
the פסח *Pesach* itself,
so presumably he's saying all these cases of אבוד avud, *avud* you
would not have a problem of נידחה *nidcheh*, you could always bring
it, it sounds like he's saying. But in the case where you'd
let a חטאת chatat, *Chatas* graze, we don't know what that case
is, then you would have to also let the פסח *Pesach* graze.
So let's try to now understand
what
he is saying. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
מתקיף ליה רב יוסף *mas'ki lei Rav Yosef*, so רב יוסף *Rav
Yosef* asked on this teaching. כללא הוא *kellala hu*, is this thing
that שמואל Shmuel's *Shmuel* says, anytime a חטאת chatat *Chatas* dies as
a פסח *Pesach* you would bring it itself, is this really a
rule, does this principle really hold? הרי חטאת chatat. שעבר שנתו *harei
Chatas she'avar shnaso*, take the case of the ע *ayin*, עבר שנתו
*avar shnaso*, right? Now I just got through telling you that that
ע *ayin* is part of the ותמנע *Vitinnah* and you have to
let it die. Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, that's the normal teaching.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s now going to introduce a teaching of ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* that actually disagrees with this. And ריש לקיש *Reish
Lakish* actually says עבר שנתו *avar shnaso* you let it graze. Okay,
let's take a look. הרי חטאת chatas. שעבר שנתו *harei Chatas she'avar
shnaso*, it's more than a year old, דלרעייה אזלא *de'rei'ia azla*, that
actually as we're going to see according to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*,
it doesn't die, you let it graze and you let it blemish
and do the proceeds. דאמר רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, בן לקיש *de'amar
Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish*, חטאת chatas שעבר שנתו *Chatas she'avar shnaso*, רואין
אותה כאילו היא עומדת בבית הקברות *ro'in osah ke'illu hi omedes be'veis
hakevaros*. If you have a great image, if you have a חטאת
chatas *Chatas* that's over a year old, it's like this poor animal,
you should be able to bring it but you can't get to
it. It's like it was in the cemetery and the כהן *Kohen*
couldn't get to it. Okay, so what do you do with it?
ורועה *ve'ro'eh*, you wait till it to graze and you transfer the
קדושה *kedusha*. So I don't know exactly what's communicated by that imagery
of it's like it's standing in the cemetery, but it is a
nice imagery of sort of saying like there's nothing really wrong with
it, you just can't use it, so we're not going to let
it die, we're going to let it graze and then you're going
to transfer the קדושה *kedusha*. The point being that ריש לקיש *Reish
Lakish* takes out the ע *ayin*, and he says עבר שנתו *avar
shnaso* grazes. So according to that, I mean there's a גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* that tries to work out exactly how it fits with the
general principle, but we're not going to worry about that right now.
Okay, ואילו בפסח ve-ilu be-Pesach, האי גוונא *ve'ilu be'Pesach hai gavna*, now
according to by a פסח *Pesach*, this scenario... In that scenario, קריב
שלמים *kariv shlamim*, if a פסח *pesach*’s more than a year old,
you do bring it as a שלמים *shlamim*, דתניא כשב *de-tanya keves*,
exactly what we talked before, לרבות את הפסח לאליה *lerabos es ha-pesach
l'alya*, כשב *keves* tells you the fat tail for the פסח *pesach*,
כשהוא אומר אם כשב *keshu-omer im keves*, לרבות את הפסח שעברה שנתו
*lerabbos es ha-pesach she-avra shnaso*. We explicitly say, one of the things
that gets converted into a שלמים *shlamim* is a פסח *pesach* that’s
more than a year old. ושלמים הבאים מחמת פסח *ve-shlamim ha-baim machmas
pesach*, or if you actually went ahead and then used proceeds to
buy שלמים *shlamim* etc., that all of those things, לכל מצות שלמים
*le-chol mitzvas shlamim*, that you treat it as a full שלמים *shlamim*.
טעונים סמיכה *teunim smicha*, the hands, ונסכים *ve-nesachim*, the wine and the
flour, ותנופת חזה ושוק *ve-tnufas chazeh ve-shok*, the waving. כשהוא אומר אם
עז *keshu-omer im ez*, הפסיק הענין למד על העז שאין טעונה אליה
*hifsik ha-inyan lamed al ha-ez she-ein teuna alya*. We’re just at the
end of the ברייתא *braisa*. And with a goat you don’t get
the fat tail. Anyway, the point being that a פסח עברה שנתו
*pesach avra shnaso* is a שלמים *shlamim*. Now again, according to the
simple principle, that’s one of the five things that it dies and
it works great for שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*. אבוד avud *avud*, you bring
it as a שלמים *shlamim*, you ignore the problem here of נדחה
*nidche*, עברה שנתו *avra shnaso* you bring it as a שלמים *shlamim*,
but since we are saying according to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, עברה
שנתו *avra shnaso* is taken out, we’re going to take it away.
Now we’ve got a problem. Because a פסח *pesach* in that scenario
is a שלמים *shlamim*, and a חטאת chatas *chattas* in that scenario
gets, goes לרעייה *li-reia*. So if we buy into ריש לקיש *Reish
Lakish*, שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*’s principle does not hold. Okay, so let’s see
what the גמרא Gemara *gemara*’s answer is. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
says, אמר ליה *amar lei*, כי קאמר שמואל Shmuel באבודים *ki kamar
Shmuel be-avudim*, בדחויים לא אמר *bidchuyim lo amar*. So, you know what?
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* wasn’t talking about everything. He said everything but he
didn’t mean everything. He meant in the talking about what we’ve been
discussing, what have we been discussing? When the פסח *pesach* gets lost.
I’m not talking about all the stories. He says, so you know
what? I told you that שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*’s talking about these three
scenarios. The בעלים *baalim* died, נתכפרו באחר *nis-kapru be-acher*, עברה שנתו *avra
shnaso*. But the גמרא *gemara* says no, he’s not talking about every
scenario about what would happen to a פסח *pesach*. He’s talking about
our discussion about when the פסח *pesach* gets lost. So we’re not
going to look at the בעלים *baalim*, and we’re not going to
look at the זמן *zeman*. The only thing he’s saying is, right,
when that’s considered it’s נדחה *nidche*, meaning it’s not a case of
אבוד avud, *avud*. There’s some other problem with it. The בעלים *baalim*
died, it’s too old. When there’s a problem, we’re not talking. We’re
talking that the only thing that happened was that it got lost.
So he says, in a case where it gets lost, if it’s
a חטאת chatas *chattas*, if it would die, then for a פסח
*pesach* it’s a שלמים *shlamim*, and if for a חטאת chatas *chattas*
it would graze, then for a פסח *pesach* it would graze. So
at the end, now what we’ve said, it actually simplifies it a
great deal. What שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* is saying is, do you want
this scenario that it got lost and you found another one? רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says and the משנה *mishna* says and
everything we’ve been saying says it matters before, after שחיטה shechita, *shechita*.
I’m going to tell you that’s not the way to look at
the question of lost, you test it against the issue of how
you would treat it for a חטאת chatas *chattas*. Now therefore, okay,
good. So what we’d like to now know, what’s the next thing
we’d like to know? What would be the different scenarios of a
חטאת *chattas* when it would get lost, whether you would let it
die or whether you would actually redeem it? Okay, so that’s where
we are holding right now within שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*. Okay, ואבוד מי
משכחת לה *ve-avud mi mishkachas lah*? Okay, so you’re telling me he’s
talking about lost חטאות *chattasos*. So where is a case of a
lost חטאת *chattas* that you let it graze? What’s that scenario? So
והרי אבודה בשעת הפרשה *ve-harei avuda bi-shas hafrasha*, לרבנן לרעייה אזלא *le-rabbanan
liriya azla*. In the case where it was lost when you separated
out the new one, that would be a case for the רבנן
*rabbanan* that it actually would graze. What does this mean? We’ll read
it and then we’ll go back and understand it. דתניא *de-tanya*, we
taught in a משנה *mishna*. הפריש חטאתו ואבדה *hifrisha chattaso ve-avda*, he
designated his חטאת *chattas* and then it got lost, just like our
story about the פסח *pesach*. והפריש אחרת תחתיה *ve-hifrisha acheress tachteya*, and
then you separated out a new חטאת *chattas*. ונמצאת הראשונה *ve-nimtzas ha-rishona*,
and you found the original one. והרי שתיהן עומדות *ve-harei shehteihem omudos*,
and they’re both standing in front of you. אחת מהן תקרב *achas
meihen tikareiv*, so you pick one, והשנייה תמות tamut. *ve-hashniya tamus*, דברי
רבי Rabbi *divrei Rabbi*, and the second one you let die, that’s
what רבי *Rabbi* says. So that’s basically, what does that parallel scenario,
does that parallel for us? The case of you found the פסח
*pesach* and then you slaughtered one and it’s a נדחה *nidche*. Okay,
so that actually now is working according to שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel*. The
חטאת *chattas* would die, it would be a נדחה *nidche*, so the
פסח *pesach*, oh, it doesn’t work because according, okay. Anyway, so that’s
what רבי *Rabbi* says, that it would die. Okay, but we’re going
to bracket רבי *Rabbi*, we’re going to look at the חכמים Chachamim,
*chakhamim*. וחכמים אומרים *ve-chakhamim omrim*, אין חטאת מתה meisa. אלא שנמצאת לאחר
שנתכפרו הבעלים *ein chattas mesa ella she-nimtzas le-acher she-nis-kapru ha-baalim*. This is
quite interesting. נדחה *nidche* actually works out in some way better. Okay?
If the חטאת *chattas* was found after you brought, the original one
found after you brought, then that’s the case you have to let
it die. It’s like it has full קדושה *kedusha*, can’t do anything
with it, let it die. הקודם שנתכפרו הבעלים *ha-kodem she-nis-kapru ha-baalim*, if
ironically I think, if you found the original one before they brought
the other one, so meaning and therefore you were דוחה docheh *doche*
it, because you had both and you chose one and rejected the
other, in that case being דוחה *doche* it actually helps you. sort
of stigmatizes it, makes it not full קדושה, and allows you to
transfer to to redeem it. In that case רועה, ro'eh it grazes.
Okay,
so what have we now said? We have now said, I'm going
to erase all this lovely גמרא, that according to שמואל, Shmuel, the
question of do you bring it itself or do you bring the
proceeds depends on how you would treat that in the case of
a lost object by a חטאת. And what do we know? In
exactly this scenario, if it wasn't the פסח, if it was a
חטאת, okay, you have in you have two cases, okay, this case
and this. In the case according to the חכמים, Chachamim, we'll worry
about רבי later. According to the חכמים, Chachamim if it was found
before, assuming these were חטאות, it was found before and you pick
one and you were דוחה this, according to them because you were
דוחה it, that makes it actually something that can be רועה ro'eh
and you you do the proceeds because maybe that like you know
makes it less full קדושה or something like that. If however, it's
what's in this case where you found the original one after and
you were never דוחה it, this one is תמות. Tamut Okay, that's
what the חכמים Chachamim. say if this was a חטאת. Okay, you
with me? Yes? Now, you translate that to שמואל Shmuel language. תמות
Tamut becomes what? תמות becomes for a פסח that you get to
bring it as a פסח, bring it as a פסח. And רועה
ro'eh. means you only bring the proceeds or not bring it as
a פסח, bring it as a שלמים, שלמים. And רועה ro'eh means
you bring the proceeds. Okay, well guess what? That works out perfectly,
right? That's exactly what we've been saying. If you found it before
שחיטה shechita, and you bring the proceeds, it's נדחה. If you found
it after שחיטה, then you've got to bring it itself. That's a
lovely principle of שמואל, Shmuel it works according to the חכמים. chachamim,
The only problem is, it's exactly what everybody's been saying and it's
exactly what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is saying. So how is he
debating רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan. You say the exact same thing just
in a much more confusing language than רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. and
it sounds like they're debating. Okay, so the גמרא because it can't
although it seems perfect but it's so perfect that doesn't he's not
saying anything, the גמרא has to interpret him in a more interesting
way so at least he's saying something new. So here's how the
גמרא is going to interpret him. It says like this: so, so
that's the story by a חטאת, so you would think it's the
exact same by פסח. But in order for שמואל Shmuel. to be
saying something different by פסח, different, it's going to assume that שמואל
Shmuel, adopts the position that it's not the question before or after
שחיטה, but the question of before after חצות. chatzot. Remember that issue
came up yesterday or last דף. So the גמרא says ואילו בפסח,
v'ilu b'pesach, by פסח we'll have to assume in order for שמואל
to be saying something interesting, דהיכא דאבד ונמצא אחר חצות קודם שחיטה
קרב שלמים. de-heicha de-avad ve-nimtza achar chatzot kodem shechitah karev shlamim. According
to פסח, what would happen if it was found if it was
lost and found after חצות chatzot even though it was קרב even
though it was before the שחיטה, it would be brought as a
שלמים. What does that mean? It means that until now we've been
assuming right that the שחיטה matters, right? And the שחיטה defines it's
pushed away. If you remember though, there was a position that says
שחיטה doesn't matter, it's when was it found, if this was noon,
okay, the question is was it found before or after noon? Okay,
so we're going to assume that שמואל is going to be of
the position not שחיטה but noon. So in the case in the
scenario where it was found after noon but before שחיטה, right? Here
was a case, it was found after noon but it was before
שחיטה. If it was a חטאת, what would be the הלכה? If
it was a חטאת, it was before שחיטה, the הלכה would be
רועה. ro'eh But as a פסח, because it's after noon, which is
the key moment when the when you begin to become able to
bring the פסח, since it's after noon, the הלכה for the פסח
is not that it is רועה ro'eh but it's it came, you
know, it came after the the drop dead hour, so that actually
means that as a פסח, as a חטאת it would be רועה
roeh, but as a פסח after חצות chatzot and before שחיטה it's
brought as a שלמים. I I have a feeling I'm confusing everybody
already. But the basic the point is is that yes it seems
to be perfect, the parallel of פסח to שלמים, but then it's
but then basically you're saying exactly what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is
saying. So in order to say so we're going to assume he
holds something different. And therefore we're going to assume that according to
him if after חצות chatzot as a פסח it would be fine,
it would be like after שחיטה and you could bring it as
a שלמים. And then it's not following the rule of a חטאת,
because a חטאת in this scenario after חצות chatzot before שחיטה actually
would be רועה and as a פסח after חצות chatzot and before
שחיטה it's brought as a שלמים. So that according to that this
could be your חגיגה chagigah of the fourteenth? Okay, could we not
go there? Okay, so the גמרא says something. Okay. Okay, so anyway
so that's our problem, somehow we made it from something perfect into
a problem, okay, because we thought he held of the חצות chatzot
position and now it doesn't fit into his category of following the
rule of a חטאת. So the גמרא says... שמואל כרבי סבירא ליה
*Shmuel ke'Rabbi sevira lei* דאמר *de'amar* אבודה למיתה אזלא *avuda lemisa azla*.
No, שמואל *Shmuel* holds like רבי *Rabbi*. רבי *Rabbi* holds I don't
care whether it was found before or after after שחיטה *shchita*. Every
חטאת *chatas* that was lost, I don't care when it was found,
always dies. Now, if you translate רבי *Rabbi*'s position into פסח *Pesach*,
if every חטאת *chatas* always dies no matter when it was found,
then that would mean every פסח *Pesach*, no matter when it was
found, before after שחיטה *shchita*, always is brought as a שלמים *shlamim*.
You never have to worry about the proceeds. Okay, so how does
that fit with the idea that we said there are cases of
proceeds and what anyway would be שמואל *Shmuel*'s cases where he said
it would have to graze? Because שמואל *Shmuel* said there are cases
of grazing. So the גמרא *Gemara* says let's take a look. והא
כל אבודה לרבי מתה meisa, *Ve'ha kol avuda le'Rabbi mesa*. One minute,
but רבי *Rabbi* said that any case of a lost animal by
a חטאת *chatas* would die. ואילו בפסח *Ve'ilu be'Pesach*, by פסח *Pesach*
we know from our משנה *Mishnah* that some cases of a פסח
*Pesach* is the proceeds. Whether it's the issue of before after חצות
chatzos, *chatzos* or before after שחיטה *shchita*, some case is a case
of proceeds. ואילו בפסח היכא דאבד קודם חצות chatzos. *Ve'ilu be'Pesach heicha
de'avad kodem chatzos*, assuming חצות chatzos. *chatzos* is case, ונמצאת קודם חצות
chatzos. *ve'nimtzas kodem chatzos* in the case of before if everything happened
before חצות chatzos. *chatzos*, in that case רועה *ro'eh*, it would graze.
So it's again, you can't if if we're following רבי *Rabbi* that
says every חטאת *chatas* dies, that can't be applied to פסח *Pesach*
because every פסח *Pesach* is not brought as a שלמים *shlamim*. So
the גמרא *Gemara* says קודם חצות chatzos. לאו אבודה היא *kodem chatzos
lav avuda hu*. כדרבא דאמר רבא אבידת לילה לא שמה אבידה *Ke'derava
de'amar Rava avedas layla la shme aveda*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
that yes, but again, remember before how we eliminated every four-fifths of
the issue of חטאת המתה *chatas amesa*? So now we're going to
narrow שמואל *Shmuel*'s discussion as well. He says I'm only talking in
the context of things that are lost. So you tell me oh
wait wait wait, your principle doesn't work in the case of being
found lost and found before חצות chatzos? *chatzos*. He says lost and
found before חצות chatzos *chatzos*, that doesn't even count as lost because
when the relevant time came about, you had it. So I'm not
talking about that case. It doesn't work with my כלל *klal* but
I'm not talking about it. I'm talking only when it officially is
lost. Now, how do you know this idea that not everything is
considered lost? Because the גמרא *Gemara* says you know what, this idea
could apply even to רבי *Rabbi*. Although רבי *Rabbi* said I don't
care when it was lost and when it was found, it always
is מתה meisa? *mesa*, there's an exception. Let's say it was lost
and found at לילה *layla* night. Now, what's the story about night?
At night you can't do what? You can't שחט *shecht*. You can't
bring a קרבן *korban*. So then the reality, the situation of it
being lost is completely outside of the scope of the issues of
its הקרבה *hakrava*. It would have no impact on its ability to
be brought. So that never counts as being lost. רבי *Rabbi* says
that case I'm okay with. Then go ahead and bring it or
whatever or if another one was brought, go ahead and you know
and whatever and you know let it graze. So since there's an
idea that there's a period where it's irrelevant to our concerns, now
a חטאת *chatas* can be brought any day of the year except
at nighttime although you could ask what if it got lost on
שבת *Shabbos*? Can't bring it on שבת *Shabbos*. But okay, but פסח
*Pesach*, so the point is when it's not relevant it's not counted
as lost. So it says same here, if it happened before and
after, now the irony here is it might not be counted as
lost but it certainly affected the status because the פסח *Pesach* was
lost and found before חצות chatzos *chatzos* and then you brought the
other one and now you can this one is considered נדחה *nidche*,
right, and this one you can't you know you have to use
the proceeds. But okay, so now what we've said is שמואל *Shmuel*
is saying I'm only talking about when it was lost and found
in a relevant time frame and within that context I'm saying that
when a חטאת *chatas* you let die which according to רבי *Rabbi*
means always, then by a פסח *Pesach* you would let die which
is a way of saying any פסח *Pesach* that was lost and
found or lost found after חצות chatzos, *chatzos* you would have to
let die. And now we understand how שמואל *Shmuel* is saying something
different from רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. Because רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying before after שחיטה *shchita* and what שמואל
*Shmuel* is saying is no, it's like a חטאת *chatas*. Whenever it's
lost at a relevant time by a חטאת *chatas* you always let
it die. So therefore by a פסח *Pesach* whenever it's lost at
a relevant time meaning after חצות chatzos. *chatzos* you're going to always
you're going to bring it as a did I lose my train
of thought? As a שלמים *shlamim*. Right. So for me he's saying
what's relevant is the time, not the act of שחיטה *shchita*. Following
רבי *Rabbi* that the only exception is lost at night, I would
say the only exception is lost before חצות *chatzos*. Time is what
matters. But when it's lost after חצות *chatzos* or not found till
after חצות *chatzos*, in that case I'm going to say it always
is brought as a שלמים *shlamim*. It's not about שחיטה *shchita*, it's
about the time that it is lost and found. So okay, now
we have sort of you know limited the discussion and we understand
a nice way of disagreeing with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*.
We're not done. So now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: Okay,
אלא רועה לרבי היכי משכחת לה *alla ro'eh le'Rabbi heichi mishkachas lah*?
But we've got a problem. That was so perfect but if שמואל
*Shmuel* says but if... So what is the case of רועה *ro'eh*
that we're talking about, the other case of שמואל *Shmuel*? So let's
take a look. Turn the page. Thank God, as you can see,
it's such a complicated סוגיא sugya *sugya* that there's a lot less
גמרא *Gemara*. Okay, a lot of תוספות *Tosafot*. כדרבי אושיא *K'd'Rebbi Oshiya*.
So we've got שמואל'ס *Shmuel's* case of מתה *meisa* after חצות *chatzos*
and that way he argues with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan*.
What's his case of רועה *ro'eh*? What's that case of a חטאת
*chatat*? Like רבי אושיא *Rebbi Oshiya*. דאמר רבי אושיא *D'amar Rebbi Oshiya*,
הפריש שתי חטאות לאחריות *hifrish shtei chataot l'achrayot*. Let's say it's not
one was lost. You always started with two. How do you start
with two? You basically start by saying, I'm sanctifying this one and
if this gets lost, I'm sanctifying this one as a backup. So
the second one was sanctified not even before the first one was
lost, as a just-in-case. Okay? So in that case, מתכפר באחת מהן
והשניה תרעה *miskaper b'achat mehen v'shniyah tireh*. In that case, the second
one has to graze because it always in a way is נדחה
*nidcha*, like it right, it was always sort of like a backup
and so on. So in that case, that's the case where even
רבי *Rebbi* would agree that it grazes. It's not a case of
lost. And that's a case that if you did that by a
פסח *Pesach*, it would graze. גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, if you
did that by a פסח *Pesach*, it would be a שלמים *shlamim*.
והא אליבא דרבי היי גוונא קרב שלמים *V'ha aliba d'Rebbi hai gavna
kareiv shlamim*. No, that's not true. It's nice that you found an
example of grazing by a חטאת *chatat*, but that's not שמואל'ס *Shmuel's*
principle at all. אלא *Ella* fine, let's try again. שמואל *Shmuel*, forget
רבי *Rebbi*. שמואל *Shmuel*, it's funny, it's going to introduce רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon? *Rebbi Shimon*, but it's going to be very similar to
what it said before by רבי *Rebbi*. שמואל כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה
*Shmuel k'Rebbi Shimon s'vira lei*. שמואל *Shmuel* holds like רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon, *Rebbi Shimon*. דאמר חמש חטאות מתות *D'amar chamesh chataot meitot*. Okay,
that was what I told you before, the five חטאות *chataot*, the
סימן *siman*. And the point about quoting רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* is
that he basically says, he like makes no distinction. Listen, any problem
with a חטאת *chatat*, it dies. I don't believe in this whole
רועה *ro'eh* business by a חטאת *chatat*, never happens. Okay, that's what
רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* says. So basically we're saying שמואל *Shmuel* holds
there's never a רועה *ro'eh* case. Okay, so we're back to what
we said before. The relevant part is any חטאת *chatat* that's lost
at a relevant time, that's called אבוד *avud*, dies, and any פסח
*Pesach* that's lost at a relevant time after חצות *chatzos* is brought
as a שלמים *shlamim*. Okay? And as opposed to before חצות *chatzos*.
Okay? And there's never a scenario of רועה *ro'eh*. All right, that's
the case. So the גמרא *Gemara* says one minute, והא רועה לרבי
שמעון לית ליה כלל *v'ha ro'eh l'Rebbi Shimon leit lei klal*? But
so okay, so you're telling me רבי שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* never holds
of רועה *ro'eh*, but שמואל *Shmuel* says anything that's a חטאת *chatat*
dies is a שלמים *shlamim*, anything that's a חטאת *chatat* is רועה
*ro'eh* by a פסח *Pesach* is brought. And now you're telling me
שמואל *Shmuel* doesn't, there's never a רועה *ro'eh* scenario in שמואל'ס חטאת
*Shmuel's chatat* law. So what was the point of the second half
of his statement? So the גמרא *Gemara* says, you know what? You're
right. שמואל נמי חדא קאמר *Shmuel nami chada ka'amar*. שמואל *Shmuel* really
was only talking about the one scenario. It's never רועה *ro'eh* by
a חטאת *chatat* and it's never רועה *ro'eh* by a שלמים *shlamim*,
by a פסח *Pesach*. It's only the case of מתה *meisa*. So
he says ומאי קא משמע לן *u'mai ka mashma lan*? So basically
what it's saying is here's what we've distilled. שמואל *Shmuel* has this
big global statement, any חטאת *chatat* this and anything this. First of
all, we're saying he's not talking about any scenario, he's talking about
a case of being lost. Number one. Number two is he's not
talking about being lost before חצות *chatzos*, that doesn't count as lost.
He's talking about being lost, you know, as חצות *chatzos* being relevant.
And what he's saying is that in a חטאת *chatat* that always
dies, and in a פסח *Pesach* it's a שלמים
*shlamim*. What about the fact that you say when it grazes by
a חטאת *chatat*? No, I meant it never grazes by a חטאת
*chatat*, so a פסח *Pesach* will never be a, so it's a
null set. Okay, the only relevant set is a חטאת *chatat* always
dies, a פסח *Pesach* always שלמים *shlamim*, and the upshot of all
of this is what matters is חצות *chatzos*. Okay, it's a long,
difficult way of saying not like רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan* that what
matters is שחיטה *shchita*, what matters is חצות *chatzos* because it's a
question of is it defined as lost. And that's where it's relevant
to think of the comparison to a חטאת *chatat*. Lost at night
isn't lost. Lost before חצות *chatzos* isn't lost. When it's defined as
lost, it's about the time, not the שחיטה *shchita*, then it's a
שלמים *shlamim*. If it was beforehand, then it would graze. Okay? And
then so we are basically coming to an end. ומאי קא משמע
לן *u'mai ka mashma lan*, what's the whole point of all of
this? לאפוקי מדרבי יוחנן *L'afpukei mi-Rebbi Yochanan*, to show how he disagrees
with רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan*, דאמר אין פסח קרב שלמים אלא שנמצא
אחר שחיטה *d'amar ein pesach kareiv shlamim ela she-nimtza achar shchita*, that
a פסח *Pesach* is only a שלמים *shlamim* if it happened to
have been after שחיטה *shchita*, אבל קודם שחיטה לא *aval kodem shchita
lo*, that the issue is before and after שחיטה *shchita*. אלמא לרבי
יוחנן שחיטה קבעה *Alma l'Rebbi Yochanan shchita kava*, that for him the
key is שחיטה *shchita*. קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan*, by this
whole analogy to a חטאת *chatat* where it's all about its status
as אבוד *avud* and was it night or day and what time
was it, חצות קבעה *chatzot kava*, that here for him its status
of being
lost. All right, so we are basically done. Now, we have another
10 lines, which basically is just a different way of saying the
סוגיא, coming at it from a slightly different angle, but it's really
a recap. It's no new ideas really introduced here. לישנא אחרינא, lishna
acharina, here was another version of the way that this discussion was
held according to this whole issue. ואילו בפסח, so we're going way
back to the עמוד א' amud aleph discussion when we had the
idea of the חטאת. Remember we said that according to the חכמים,
the חטאת that was found before שחיטה
is רועה, and after שחיטה was a מתה. And that would have
been a perfect comparison to פסח, except then it would have been
רבי יוחנן. Okay, so we're going back to that state, that part
of the conversation. ואילו בפסח היכא דאבד ונמצא אחר חצות קודם שחיטה
יקרב שלמים. v'ilu b'pesach heicha d'avad v'nimtza achar chatzos kodem shechita yikarev
shlamim. So
so here he's filling in what sort of that problem. So it
says, oh, but by פסח, פסח doesn't go by שחיטה, פסח goes
by חצות, so it's not like חטאת where it matters before after
שחיטה. So here the גמרא introduces the possibility of, wait wait, maybe
he holds פסח does go by שחיטה, maybe it works perfectly. שמואל
כרבא סבירא ליה. Shmuel k'Rava sevira lei. No no, maybe שמואל holds
like רבא, דאמר שחיטה קבע, d'amar shechita kava, that it does go
by שחיטה. Right, that would have been great if the סוגיא had
said that. We have an actual difference: is the חטאת graze or
does it die, depends on before and after שחיטה, and that exactly
parallels whether a פסח is a שלמים or whether it grazes right
before after שחיטה. So why not just say that? Finally, it adds,
that would be a very nice reading of שמואל's statement. No, then
it would be too simple. והא מדקאמר רבי יוחנן עלה, v'ha mid'kaamar
Rabbi Yochanan alei, because then he would be saying the same as
רבי יוחנן. רבי יוחנן said אין פסח קרב שלמים אלא שנמצא אחר
שחיטה אבל קודם שחיטה לא. ein pesach karev shlamim ela shenimtza achar
shechita aval kodem shechita lo. רבי יוחנן says that that's exactly the
difference, before after שחיטה. אלמא שחיטה קבע. alma shechita kava. So רבי
יוחנן's whole point is that it's שחיטה determined. מכלל דשמואל סבר חצות
קבע. michlal d'Shmuel savar chatzos kava. So the only reasonable alternative position
שמואל can have is חצות. So it's basically like, you know the
story that they tell, that they say, I have to introduce some
light, a little break in all this גמרא. So somebody once said
to the דובנא מגיד, Dubna Maggid, he says, I don't understand how
you have these amazing משלים, meshalim, they always exactly illustrate the point
that you're trying to illustrate. Like, how do you think of those
משלים? meshalim? He says, let me answer you by a
משל. mashal. Somebody's walking by and saw somebody and he had ten
arrows in a wall and each one was a perfect bullseye. Guy
says, how did you do it? How did you shoot my...? He
says, no, I'm not a good marksman, he says, first I shoot
the arrow, then I go and I paint the bullseye.
So anyway, so the גמרא basically, you have this crazy obscure statement
of שמואל, חטאת blah blah blah. The גמרא knows, look, רבי יוחנן
says שחיטה. The only possible thing שמואל can mean is, what's the
only reasonable, you know, other opinion out there other than to be
arguing for רבי יוחנן other than שחיטה, is חצות. So we know
that we want שמואל's position of this big statement about a חטאת
to wind up saying that what matters is not שחיטה but is
חצות. So any alternate path we can't take according to שמואל. We
can only work with his statement to get it to the conclusion
to say that it's about חצות. So one way of reading שמואל,
it would have been perfect, it would have made the comparison to
a חטאת before and after שחיטה, but then it would have been
saying the same thing. So that can't be what he means. We
have to get him to mean חצות. Okay, that's the bullseye we
have to draw around the arrow.
אלא שמואל כרבי סבירא ליה. ela Shmuel k'Rabbi sevira lei. So how
are we going to get him to mean חצות? He holds like
רבי, דאמר אבוד למיתה אזיל. d'amar avud l'misa azil. Now we're just
back to saying the same thing: every case of אבוד is מתה.
והא כל אבודין לרבי מיתה והפסח היכא דאבד קודם חצות שנמצא קודם
חצות רועה. v'ha kol avudin l'Rabbi misa v'hapesach heicha d'avad kodem chatzos
shenimtza kodem chatzos roeh. No no, but that doesn't prove it because
חצות matters by פסח and by רבי it's always about it. So
קסבר קודם חצות לאו
אבוד הוא וקסבר חצות קבע. kasavar kodem chatzos lav avud hu v'kasavar
chatzos kava. So it's a short version, we don't have to introduce
רבי שמעון, it's try, why bother introducing רבי שמעון? The bottom line
is you take a position, whether it's רבי or רבי שמעון, that
every אבוד is מתה, and you say, what about the cases where
it's not מתה? That's about time, not about שחיטה, and when it's
before חצות it's not called אבוד, and that's the way you get
his statement to mean before after חצות, by saying all אבודים avudim
are מתים meisim and any אבוד is brought as a שלמים, and
the only thing not is something that doesn't have a status of
אבוד, and that would be because it was found before חצות. Okay,
ברוך שפטרנו. baruch shepatranu.