So today's דף daf is למ"ד ו"ו, Lamed Vav, thirty-six, and we
had a wonderful דף daf yesterday talking about what is necessary for
מצה matzah but also to make חמץ chametz and the five grains,
not rice and millet, so that's the whole קטניות kitniyos issue.
We had a discussion whether oats were part of those five grains
and the issue for people that are celiacs and the gluten concern,
what the difference is about saying that things are מחמיץ machmitz because
even rice ferments, so we discussed a very reasonable position that מחמיץ
machmitz specifically meant sort of like the releasing of gases and the
puffing up of the dough that occurs which does not presumably occur
to nearly the same degree in things like rice. And then the
idea that מי פירות, mei peiros, that fruit juices are not מחמיץ,
machmitz, and we're going to see that again today, and there are
two opinions about that, whether it means that they don't become חמץ
chametz at all or they don't create full חמץ, chametz, you're not
חייב כרת, chayav kares, but they create this middle level called
חמץ נוקשה. chametz nuksha. And we will revisit that again today, and
I pointed out that a number of ראשונים Rishonim and the position
of the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch and the dominant position is that
that status of מי פירות mei peiros that they don't create a
problem is when there's no water added, and then maybe it's not
a problem at all, but with water added, it can become חמץ.
chametz. But also, interesting to note and the רמ"א's Rema position is
to, that's the position I should say of the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan
Aruch, that it matters with or without water added, and the רמ"א
Rema however says that we take normally the more stringent opinion that
even without water, fruit juices are a problem, except in a case
we'll be lenient for a חולה choleh and for minors, for sick
person minors, which is why you'll get these egg מצות matzahs on
for פסח, Pesach, כשר לפסח kosher l'Pesach for sick people and for
minors, and whatever, and they'll give you the etc. The only thing
I do want to say again about that is the irony that
even when the רמ"א Rema is stringent about fruit juices without water,
that's only if you let them sit outside without baking them, right?
He's not more stringent with them than he is with like water,
if you add the fruit juices and you put it in the
oven right away. I mean, it might be that you can't let
it, like without working it, as long as you're working the dough,
you don't have to put in the oven. The whole issue of
eighteen minutes is unattended; as long as you're working it,
there's no time limit. So if you work the dough with the
fruit juices and you put it in the oven right away, then
the רמ"א Rema doesn't indicate that he's more stringent than he is
with water,
and with
water that
would be okay. Anyway, those are some of the issues around מי
פירות. mei peiros. And then the rest of the דף daf was
devoted to the part of the משנה Mishnah that spoke about
you
can eat חמץ chametz that doesn't have halachic problems with it, I
mean not חמץ, chametz, excuse me, מצה matzah that doesn't have halachic
problems with it, but cases that maybe are a little bit
ambiguous, דמאי, demai, תרומה, terumah, מעשר ma'aser that תרומה terumah was taken,
but if it's got real halachic problems and can't be eaten like
טבל tevel or מעשר ma'aser that hasn't been redeemed and similar types
of issues, then you cannot eat it. And the question now
we're going to turn to is, okay, I understand it's forbidden to
be eaten, but how does that prove that if I went ahead
and I did eat it, why should I not fulfill the מצוה
mitzvah of מצה matzah as well? And that's the issue we're going
to turn to now, the second part of the משנה Mishnah that
is if the מצה matzah is forbidden to be eaten for some
other reason, not only have you transgressed that other problem, but you
don't fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of מצה. matzah. Yes, Charlie.
So why shouldn't I be able to add some corn or rice
flour to my wheat flour when I'm making מצה?
matzah? No good reason. Okay, moving on. So that's basically the point
I made. So now we pick up though with the second part
that it cannot, forbidden to be eaten for some other reason, that
would prevent you, not only you would transgress, but it'd prevent you
fulfilling the מצוה mitzvah of מצה. matzah. So the גמרא Gemara picks
up on the bottom of למ"ד ה' עמוד ב' Lamed Hey amud
Beis and says the following. We pick up with
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. last of the narrow lines. יכול יוצא אדם
ידי חובתו, Yachol yotzei adam yedei chovaso, maybe you fulfill your obligation
of מצה matzah בטבל שלא נתקן, be-tevel shelo nitkan, with טבל tevel
that has not been fixed, that has the grain has not had
תרומה ומעשר terumah u-maaser taken. So the גמרא Gemara says that's a
little redundant. כל טבל נמי הא לא נתקן. Kol tevel nami ha
lo nitkan. What do you mean? All טבל tevel has not been
fixed. That's the definition of טבל. tevel. אלא בטבל שלא נתקן כל
צרכו, Ella be-tevel shelo nitkan kol tzorcho, even if it has not
been fully fixed, שנטלו ממנו תרומה גדולה, she-natlu mimeno terumah gedolah, let's
say you took the תרומה terumah from the grain, ולא נטלו ממנו
תרומת מעשר, ve-lo natlu mimeno terumas maaser, but you didn't take the
תרומת מעשר, terumas maaser, the tenth of the tenth of the tithes,
once you or מעשר ראשון, maaser rishon, or let's say you took
מעשר ראשון, maaser rishon, and when you removed the מעשר ראשון, maaser
rishon, then there's no תרומת מעשר terumas maaser left. So you took
תרומה terumah from the grain, you took מעשר ראשון, maaser rishon, which
had within it the תרומת מעשר, terumas maaser, so the only thing
that hasn't been taken from the grain is מעשר שני, maaser sheni,
ולא מעשר, ve-lo maaser, תרומת מעשר. terumas maaser. That's a כהן, kohen,
right? Meaning no, I don't have to מעשר me-aser the I'll talk
about that in a minute.
No, you don't have
to, but you took the מעשר maaser from
the grain so you don't have to worry about תרומת מעשר terumas
maaser because it's been removed. You took מעשר maaser from the grain,
any תרומת מעשר terumas maaser was in that מעשר maaser you took
from the grain. You don't have to worry about it now with
what's left. So with what's left, you don't have to worry about
תרומה, terumah, you don't have to worry about תרומת מעשר, terumas maaser,
you don't have to worry about מעשר. maaser. מעשר ראשון בלא מעשר
שני, Maaser rishon belo maaser sheni, or you took מעשר ראשון, maaser
rishon, the one thing you didn't take was מעשר שני. maaser sheni.
ואפילו מעשר עני, Va-afillu maaser ani, and even if it was the
third and the sixth year and the only thing left that you
haven't taken was מעשר עני. maaser ani. מניין? Minayin? How do you
know you don't fulfill your obligation? Now why would it make a
difference? You took two out of three so I would think it's
better. If it's still טבל, tevel, it's still טבל. tevel. The difference
is
that within טבל tevel some of the things you take wind up
being קודש kodesh and wind up having real קדושה kedushah and wind
up being really forbidden in themselves. When I take תרומה, terumah, if
I'm a non-כהן kohen and I eat תרומה, terumah, that's אסור, assur,
not only is it אסור, assur, it's חייב מיתה בידי שמיים. chayav
misah bidei shamayim. It's very serious. Similarly, and this is why it
emphasized תרומת מעשר, terumas maaser, if I take the מעשר ראשון maaser
rishon from it and I go ahead and I eat that מעשר
ראשון maaser rishon without taking תרומת מעשר, terumas maaser, or I take
the תרומת מעשר terumas maaser and I go ahead and I eat
the תרומת מעשר, terumas maaser, תרומת מעשר terumas maaser is like תרומה.
terumah. And if I'm not a כהן kohen and I eat תרומת
מעשר, terumas maaser, I'm also חייב מיתה בידי שמיים. chayav misah bidei
shamayim. So I might think that the status of טבל tevel is
a function of the things that haven't been taken. And when what
hasn't been taken it has in it potential תרומה, terumah, it has
in this grain potential תרומת מעשר, terumas maaser, something that is punishable
by מיתה בידי שמיים misah bidei shamayim if you're a non-כהן, kohen,
then the טבל tevel is very severe. But if I've taken all
of that stuff out and the only thing I haven't taken is
מעשר שני, maaser sheni, well, מעשר שני maaser sheni there's still a
prohibition, you're not allowed to eat מעשר שני maaser sheni out of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Fine, I take מעשר שני, maaser sheni, or it's the
third and the sixth year, the only thing that hasn't been taken
out is מעשר עני. maaser ani. Now do you know what I
transgress by eating מעשר עני? maaser ani? Theft, גזל, gezel, right. But
I don't transgress any prohibition of forbidden food. So if right now
in the טבל tevel the only thing not taken is something that
belongs to somebody else, it belongs to the עניים, aniyim, but it's
not in itself forbidden food, maybe the eating of the טבל tevel
is not such a big deal. So that's what it says, not
true. Even if the only thing left is מעשר עני, maaser ani,
you still transgress the prohibition of טבל. tevel. Now there's an interesting
question. Is the prohibition as weighty? The prohibition of טבל tevel is
also מיתה בידי שמיים. misah bidei shamayim. Let's say this scenario that
the only thing left is מעשר עני maaser ani and I eat
the טבל. tevel. So admittedly I still transgress, but do I get
is it מיתה בידי שמיים, misah bidei shamayim, or maybe that's less
because of exactly this reason. So that's a question. But anyway, that's
the reason that we have this that the גמרא Gemara builds it
up. Even if the only thing I haven't taken is מעשר עני,
maaser ani, מניין, minayin, how do I know that it's still problematic
enough that it still has a status of טבל, tevel, it's not
just גזל, gezel, it still has a status of טבל tevel and
I don't fulfill my obligation of מצה? matzah?
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse teaches, לא תאכל עליו חמץ. Lo
sochel alav chametz. Don't eat on it חמץ chametz on the פסח,
Pesach, and שבעת ימים תאכל עליו מצות. shivas yamim tochal alav matzos.
So the point is that the connection of eating מצה, matzah, it's
really the end of the פסוק, pasuk, to the prohibition of eating
חמץ, chametz, which we've seen before, that tells me מצה matzah can
only be made out of things that can become חמץ. chametz.
מי שאיסורו משום, Mi she-issuro mishum, maybe you fulfill your חוב? chov?
It's not like it's
actual.
מי שאיסורו משום בל תאכל עליו חמץ. Mi she-issuro mishum bal tochal
alav chametz. So the only thing you fulfill the מצווה mitzvah of
מצה matzah with is things that you could transgress חמץ. chametz. So
that I already know. Only the five מינים, minim, only things that
could become חמץ. chametz. But now we go further. No, things that
only have the prohibition of חמץ. chametz. יצא זה Yatza zeh to
exclude this case of טבל tevel or other cases that it's forbidden
to be eaten like we mentioned before, שאין איסורו משום בל תאכל
חמץ אלא משום בל תאכל טבל. she-ein issuro mishum bal tochal chametz
ella mishum bal tochal tevel. There's no prohibition on this of eating
חמץ, chametz, there's only a prohibition of eating טבל. tevel. Now what
does that mean? Just because it's טבל, tevel, there's no prohibition of
also eating חמץ? chametz? So what it's saying is, you
know why you don't fulfill your obligation with מצה matzah of טבל?
tevel? Because מצה matzah of טבל tevel could never become אסור. assur.
because of חמץ. chametz. Even if you let it ferment, and even
if you let it sort of the, you know, whatever rise, you
wouldn't transgress חמץ chametz because you'd only transgress טבל. tevel. Listen, why
not? Why wouldn't you transgress both? So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says,
ואיסורא דחמץ היכא אזל? v'issura de'chametz heicha azal? So where did the
prohibition of חמץ chametz go?
What do you mean? I get you're over on טבל, tevel, but
you should also transgress חמץ. chametz. So אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav
Sheshet, הא מני רבי שמעון היא. Ha-mani Rabbi Shimon hi. This is
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דאמר אין איסור חל על איסור. de'amar ein
issur chal al issur. One just prohibited for one reason, it doesn't
become prohibited for another reason. So since it's already prohibited for טבל,
tevel, even if you were to let it become חמץ, chametz, it
would not be prohibited for חמץ. chametz. So you're doing the מצוה
mitzvah of מצה matzah with something that can never be אסור assur
because of חמץ, chametz, because one prohibition wouldn't take place on top
of another. Now, so Michael says, would it be an איסור מוסיף?
issur mosif? Maybe, because חמץ chametz is an איסור הנאה issur hana'ah
and טבל tevel is אסור assur in some types of הנאה hana'ah
and not all types of הנאה. hana'ah. So it's possible. Whether איסור
הנאה issur hana'ah is considered an איסור מוסיף issur mosif is very
questionable. So the גמרא Gemara assumes not. דתניא, de'tanya, we taught a
ברייתא, Baraita, let's just read this and take Josh's question. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, האוכל נבילה ביום הכיפורים פטור. ha-ochel neveilah b'Yom
HaKippurim patur.
If you eat a נבילה neveilah on יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, you're
exempt because the animal was already a נבילה, neveilah, came along יום
הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, made it אסור assur also because of יום הכיפורים.
Yom HaKippurim. So therefore you don't transgress also on יום הכיפורים Yom
HaKippurim because it was already prohibited. Now I gotta tell you, that's
a very bizarre and that's the paradigmatic example of אין איסור חל
על איסור, ein issur chal al issur, but it's extremely strange because
first of all, the idea that you could eat טרפות treifas on
יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim and not be חייב chayav for יום הכיפורים,
Yom HaKippurim, but okay. But besides conceptually, normally the idea of אין
איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal al issur is an idea
that if this object already has one label, we don't put another
label on it. If we already slapped on this grain טבל, tevel,
then that's already its status, and you can't slap a חמץ chametz
status on it as well. But by יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim, it's
not that the meat becomes אסור, assur, right? It's not like the
status of the meat now is מאכלות אסורות machalos assuros on יום
הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. The meat was נבילה. neveilah. Now I have a
מצוה mitzvah that I have to fast on יום הכיפורים, Yom HaKippurim,
right? So it's not like they're in competition. But nevertheless, this is
the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that if it's already forbidden,
it can't become forbidden again. So what the גמרא Gemara says is
you're right. This idea that you're not יוצא yotzei your obligation with
this type of a מצה matzah is because it could never become
חמץ chametz according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. You can never transgress
חמץ chametz because it already has a prohibition. Which means that our
entire משנה Mishnah that you don't fulfill your obligation for these reasons
is all limited to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and we don't rule
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So technically you would be יוצא yotzei
with all these things if it's only a רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
דרשה. drasha. Let's keep on reading in the גמרא. Gemara. Oh, Charlie
had a question. Yes.
So, I have this טבל, tevel, I take this טבל tevel flour
and I bake חמץ chametz bread out of it. Right, and it
becomes פסח. Pesach. Right. So now חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, I tithed
it.
Right. So then it might take effect. Yes, once you actually take
the תרומות ומעשרות, Terumos u'Maasros, it could be that the other איסור
issur was like hovering over it. So as soon as you remove
the impediment, the other איסור issur does take effect. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara continues. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, רבינא Ravina says, אפילו
תימא רבנן, afilu teima Rabbanan, even if you say the רבנן, Rabbanan,
you know, it's not just רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says that
you're not יוצא. yotzei. Even the רבנן Rabbanan who say that one
איסור issur can take effect. Nevertheless, here's what the דרשה drasha really
means. מי שאיסורו משום בל תאכל חמץ בלבד, Mi she-issuro mishum bal
tochal chametz bilvad,
that the only thing you fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah
with is something that the only other potential prohibition is not eating
חמץ. chametz. יצא זה שאין איסורו משום בל תאכל חמץ בלבד אלא
אף משום בל תאכל טבל, Yatza zeh she-ein issuro mishum bal tochal
chametz bilvad, ela af mishum bal tochal tevel, to exclude a case
of טבל tevel and all the similar cases we discussed that the
prohibition is not just don't eat חמץ, chametz, but also don't eat
טבל. tevel. So meaning, no, the דרשה drasha it does not mean
it has no prohibition of חמץ. chametz. The דרשה drasha means there
can't be any other prohibition going on here. If there's another prohibition,
it's not a good מצה. matzah. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't like
that. מידי בלבד כתיב? Mi-di bilvad ktiv?
The פסוק Pasuk doesn't say, you know, בלבד, bilvad, only חמץ. chametz.
It says, something that's prohibited for חמץ, chametz, you do מצה. matzah.
It doesn't say only prohibited for חמץ. chametz. אלא מחוורתא כדרב ששת,
Ela mivarta k'Rav Sheshet, it's better like רב ששת Rav Sheshet that
it's only going according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says that
you actually wouldn't have the prohibition of חמץ chametz because of these
other prohibitions. So what the גמרא Gemara seems to conclude is that
this entire משנה Mishnah that says you don't fulfill the מצוה mitzvah
of מצה matzah when it's forbidden to be eaten is only רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who says that because it's forbidden to be eaten
for another reason, it could never become אסור assur because of חמץ.
chametz. But according to the חכמים, Chachamim, you actually would fulfill the
מצוה mitzvah of מצה. matzah. Now, that's a little funny that the
whole משנה Mishnah we don't פוסקין paskin like. So a number of
ראשונים, Rishonim, although that seems to be the conclusion of the גמרא,
Gemara, you know, basically wind up concluding otherwise, and concluding that the
משנה Mishnah is even the חכמים. Chachamim. Maybe for some other type
of a דרשה, drasha, or, and here's the interesting thing which is
absent from our גמרא Gemara but רש"י Rashi mentions a number of
times. If I told you you don't fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of
מצה matzah by something that's forbidden to be eaten like טבל, tevel,
what's the immediate reason that would come to your mind why you
don't do it?
Because it's טבל. tevel.
No, but why couldn't you also fulfill fulfill the מצוה mitzvah of
מצה, matzah, do both: transgress טבל Tevel and fulfill the מצוה mitzvah
of מצה. matzah. How about מצוה הבאה בעבירה? Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah? Right,
right, מצוה הבאה בעבירה, Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah, right, a מצוה mitzvah that
comes through the performance of an עבירה. aveirah. And a lot of
ראשונים Rishonim ask, why is that absent from this גמרא? Gemara? We
have an entire גמרא Gemara that discusses not fulfilling, it’s רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, it’s this דרשה. drasha. What about מצוה הבאה בעבירה? Mitzvah
HaBa’ah B’aveirah? So that leads a number of ראשונים Rishonim to say,
to try to figure out a narrow definition, narrower definition of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah to explain its absence from this
גמרא. Gemara. And nevertheless, רש"י Rashi does insist that that’s also going
on here, and it leaves the possibility that according to what we
just read, the whole משנה Mishnah is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but
a number of ראשונים Rishonim actually feel no, in the end even
according to the חכמים Chachamim you don’t fulfill your obligation, and one
possible, very serious possible reason is the idea of מצוה הבאה בעבירה.
Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah. Yes, Charlie?
I find that particularly surprising because the classic מצוה הבאה בעבירה Mitzvah
HaBa’ah B’aveirah is stolen אתרוג, etrog, and if you are eating untithed
produce, one of the problems is you’ve stolen from the person who’s
supposed to get the...
That’s true, right, right, that is true but it’s not exactly the
same as stealing. I will say that one of the differences is,
and you might say this might make it better, might make it
worse, but it gets to the similar issue we just discussed. One
series difference is that a normal מצוה הבאה בעבירה, Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah,
first you did the עבירה aveirah now with the object, you stole
the אתרוג, etrog, now you want to do the מצוה mitzvah with
it. And the logic of that could be once it’s been had
an עבירה aveirah done to it, it becomes like stigmatized, right, in
the גמרא Gemara in סוכה Sukkah compares מצוה הבאה בעבירה Mitzvah HaBa’ah
B’aveirah to a type of a, of a like of a מום,
mum, of a blemish. Okay, so this אתרוג etrog is a stolen
אתרוג, etrog, it’s a blemished אתרוג, etrog, it’s a stigmatized אתרוג, etrog,
you can’t use it for a מצוה. mitzvah. In this case, they
all happened at the same time. You were doing the עבירה aveirah
as you were doing the מצוה, mitzvah, so it’s not like you’re
using a stigmatized object. When you put that מצה matzah in your
mouth, it might be prohibited, but it hasn’t had a, it hasn’t
had a transgression done to it, at least not yet. So that’s
one distinction the ראשונים Rishonim say, that the difference of timing. Yes,
רבקה? Rivka?
What’s the penalty for not eating מצה? matzah? Is that a כרת
kareth if you don’t eat מצה?
matzah? No, not eating מצה matzah is like any other מצוה, mitzvah,
it’s like not taking לולב, lulav, you know, you just don’t get
the מצוה mitzvah of having you, you know, you just have the
passive non-fulfillment of a positive מצוה. mitzvah.
So if
you had a choice, should I transgress טבל Tevel and do the
מצוה mitzvah or not transgress and, you would should passively not, you
know, do the מצוה, mitzvah, it’s much less serious than actively transgressing.
However, it does raise another interesting question which is part of the
מצוה הבאה בעבירה Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah discussion which I’m not going to
get into now, but I will say is the opposite of מצוה
הבאה בעבירה Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah is a concept of עשה דוחה לא
תעשה, aseh docheh lo ta’aseh, right? Right, normally we say that if
they’re in competing, the עשה aseh wins out. So why don’t I
say I could do the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah but I
would transgress טבל, Tevel, so one thing you could say is let’s
call it מצוה הבאה בעבירה, Mitzvah HaBa’ah B’aveirah, the other thing you
could say is let’s say the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah obligates
me and it’s דוחה docheh the לא תעשה lo ta’aseh and if
this is the only מצה matzah I have it should allow me
to do it.
Why do you have an עשה aseh though of מפריש mafreesh the
מעשר ma’aser or the whole thing?
Yeah, that’s a question I’d have to have how much... yeah, I...
that’s not exactly an עשה. aseh. Okay, anyway, I just put that
out there. Let’s keep on going. גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay,
תנו רבנן, tana rabanan, יכול יוצא אדם ידי חובתו במעשר שני בירושלים?
yakhol yotzei adam yedei chovato b’ma’aser sheni biyerushalayim? Maybe you should fulfill
now, we talked about not eating מעשר שני ma’aser sheni out of
ירושלים Yerushalayim because then you transgress, okay, but let’s say you have
your מעשר שני ma’aser sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim and you’re in ירושלים
Yerushalayim for פסח, Pesach,
can you use your מעשר שני ma’aser sheni in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Why
not? You’re allowed to eat it, you have a מצוה mitzvah to
eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Can you use that for your מצה?
matzah? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, the verse teaches,
לחם עוני, lechem oni, right? Calls מצה matzah poor person’s bread, שנאכל
באנינות. ma shene’echal b’aninus. So it’s doing a little play on words:
עוני, oni, it’s reading with an א aleph (אוני), oni which is
a funny thing to do if you’re reading עוני oni correctly as
a guttural letter, but okay, something that can be eaten in אנינות
aninus when a person is a, you know, mourner or an אונן
onen like the first day that the relative has died. Okay, so
and that’s connected to an idea of affliction, meaning it could be
eaten with that degree of like profound sorrow. יצא זה, yatza zeh,
to exclude the case of מעשר שני, ma’aser sheni, שאינו נאכל באנינות.
shene’eno ne’echal b’aninus. You’re not allowed to eat, a person can’t eat
מעשר שני ma’aser sheni if he or she is an אונן, onen,
because the פסוק pasuk says לא אכלתי באוני ממנו. lo achalti b’oni
mimenu. It’s a little play, right? באוני, b’oni, באוני. b’oni. So anyway,
so therefore that’s excluded. So מעשר שני, ma’aser sheni, it’s interesting concept.
What about ושמחת בחגך? simchata b’chagecha? All right, you’re fine, you know,
with some other thing. So מצה matzah which is supposed to symbolize,
you know, affliction cannot be made, it’s an interesting idea, with מעשר
שני ma’aser sheni which is all about an idea of שמחה. simcha.
When it speaks about מעשר שני, ma’aser sheni, eating it before God
it talks about, you know, the whole idea of שמחה simcha of
the eating and not באוני. b’oni. So that’s in a way conflicting
with the מצה matzah symbolizing לחם עוני, lechem oni, אלא בשמחה, ela
b’simcha, דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי. divrei Rabbi Yose HaGelili. That’s what רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili says. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva disagrees, מצות מצות ריבה, matzot matzot riba, it
says מצות matzot in the plural, it says מצות matzot many times,
that’s to tell you you can do it with מעשר שני ma’aser
sheni in ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Specifically to do that?
Yeah. So, okay, just to teach you to... read that, you know,
not to read things in such an exclusive manner. אם כן מה
תלמוד לומר לחם עוני, Im kein mah talmud lomar lechem oni, what
are you doing with לחם עוני? lechem oni? What’s that coming to
teach you? So, like we said yesterday, probably פרט לעיסה שנילושה ביין
ושמן ודבש p’rat l’issah she-niloshah b’yayin v’shemen u-dvash to exclude cases of
making the dough with wine and oil and honey, and therefore that’s
too—that’s sweet and it’s not very plain, and therefore it’s not good
for מצה. matzah.
Meaning the מצוה mitzvah מצה, matzah, because you
could—yeah, yeah, yeah, we’re talking about the מצוה mitzvah מצה. matzah. All
of this discussion is not the מצה matzah for seven days, we’re
talking about what do you do to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה,
mitzvah, we’re talking about if that wasn't clear we're talking here about
מצה matzah the first night to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה. mitzvah.
Okay. So מאי טעמא דרבי עקיבא? mai taama d’Rebbe Akiva? What's the
reason of רבי עקיבא? Rebbe Akiva? Why doesn't he like that דרשה?
drasha? מי כתיב לחם עוני? mi ksiv lechem oni? עני כתיב. ani
ksiv. It's not written עוני oni with a vav, it's written without
the vav, which means poor person's bread is what you emphasize, not
affliction or certainly not
אנינות. aninut. ולרבי יוסי הגלילי, v’l’Rebbe Yossi HaGlili, מי קרינן עני? mi
karinan ani? עוני קרינן. oni karinan. We read it as if it's
written with a vav. And therefore you are—you should make this דרשה
drasha to exclude that it has to have the potential of eaten
with אנינות. aninut. ורבי עקיבא, v’Rebbe Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva would
say, by the way, you realize that if somebody actually were an
אונן, onen, he would not be eating מצה matzah on פסח Pesach
night because he would not be doing מצות. mitzvos. Okay. But anyway,
רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, האי דקרינן ביה עוני, hai d’karinan bei oni,
the purpose of reading it as עוני oni is not to make
this comparison to אנינות, aninut, but is to tell you a different
point. כשמואל, k’Shmuel, like שמואל Shmuel teaches. דאמר שמואל, d’amar Shmuel, לחם
עוני, lechem oni, לחם שעונין עליו דברים הרבה. lechem she-onin alav devarim
harbeh. To connect the מצה, matzah, a, one thing we learn is
that עני, ani, it has to be poor person's bread, that you
don't make it sweet and you don't add these flavors. The other
thing we learn, that's what we learn from עני. ani. The thing
that we learn from עוני oni is that you say things over
the מצה. matzah. What do you say over the מצה? matzah? And
I don't mean המוציא לחם מן הארץ. hamotzi lechem min ha’aretz. You
say the הגדה. Haggadah. The מצה matzah said in the context of
the הגדה, Haggadah, right, כל שלא אמר שלשה דברים אלו בפסח, kol
shelo amar shlosha devarim eilu b’Pesach, פסח מצה ומרור, Pesach Matzah u-Maror,
right? And that the מצה matzah and the הגדה Haggadah are in—are
interconnected. And that’s what we learn from לחם עוני, lechem oni, that
it’s part of the symbolism and it has to be central to
the telling of the הגדה, Haggadah, but not this idea of the
need for אנינות aninut and excluding מעשר שני. maaser sheni. I do
want to point out an interesting רש"י Rashi of עונין עליו דברים
הרבה. onin alav devarim harbeh. רש"י Rashi says about six lines from
the top,
שעונין עליו דברים, she-onin alav devarim, רש"י Rashi says שגומרין עליו את
ההלל ואומרים עליו הגדה. she-gomrin alav es ha-Hallel v’omrim alav Haggadah. So
רש"י Rashi adds the idea of הלל, Hallel, which to us seems
a little strange. Yeah, that is right, we do say הלל Hallel
during the הגדה, Haggadah, but right, it certainly is not something that
for us sticks out with its significance. Nevertheless, it is worth noting
that if you look at early records of like the emphasis of
what they did during the סדר Seder night, like that you'll find
in like, in
Philo, I think and Josephus or whatever, what they emphasize is that
they would eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and they would be
singing songs of praise to God, etc. They wouldn't—the emphasis was not
recounting the story
in some early—in some—in some—some records we have of בית שני bayis
sheni periods when they refer to it, what's emphasized is the eating
of the פסח Pesach and the singing of praises to God for
having taken them out. The emphasis on הגדה Haggadah at the time
by—well, they could have had an informal one, they could have talked
about the story. Anyway, so it is interesting here that רש"י, Rashi,
the first thing רש"י Rashi mentions is the הלל Hallel aspect and
then the הגדה. Haggadah.
Anyway, whole שמחה simcha thing we're talking about.
Okay. Anyway, that is what, that's what רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva does
but not for the דרשה drasha of עוני oni to exclude מעשר
שני. maaser sheni. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, וסבר
רבי עקיבא עיסה שנילושה ביין ושמן ודבש לא? v’savar Rebbe Akiva issah
she-niloshah b’yayin v’shemen u-dvash lo? Does רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva feel, is
this really true, that you cannot be יוצא yotzei with bread made
with wine and oil and honey? והתניא, v’hatanya, we taught a ברייתא,
baraita, אין לשין עיסה בפסח ביין ושמן ודבש. ein lashin issah b’Pesach
b’yayin v’shemen u-dvash.
You cannot go ahead and—now this gets back exactly to our מי
פירות mei peiros discussion—forget the מצוה mitzvah of מצה. matzah. You can't
make bread on פסח Pesach with these fruit juices, because of a
concern that it'll become חמץ. chametz. ואם לש, v’im lash, if you
did, רבן גמליאל אומר תשרף מיד, Rabban Gamliel omer tisoraf miyad, you
have to burn it immediately because he basically feels that not only
can fruit juices become חמץ, chametz, but they can become חמץ chametz
even faster than with water. So therefore you have to go ahead
and burn it immediately. וחכמים אומרים יאכל, va-Chachamim omrim yei’achel, and the
חכמים Chachamim say you can eat it. And that's because they basically
feel that מי פירות mei peiros doesn't become חמץ, chametz, okay, or
certainly not faster than water. So if you went ahead and you
baked this the same way you would bake מצה, matzah, even if
it had fruit juice in it, it's no worse than normal, you
know, water and flour. So you make מצות matzos with fruit juice,
big deal. ואמר רבי עקיבא, v’amar Rebbe Akiva, שבתי הייתה אצל רבי
אליעזר ורבי יהושע. shavti hay’sah etzel Rebbe Eliezer v’Rebbe Yehoshua.
My dwelling was with רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע, Rebbe Eliezer v’Rebbe Yehoshua,
those were רבי עקיבא’s Rebbe Akiva רבייים. Rebbeim. ולשתי להם עיסה, v’lashti
lahem issah,
and I made for them dough. You can just see רבי עקיבא
Rebbe Akiva there in the kitchen making the dough, right? And I
kneaded for them dough ביין ושמן ודבש. b’yayin v’shemen u-dvash. And apparently
it was פסח, Pesach, okay? And I added some, you know, some
of these fruit juices, you know, oil and wine and honey, and
I baked מצות matzos ולא אמרו לי דבר, v’lo amru li davar,
and they didn't—they didn't say anything. They didn't say oh my god
you can't
eat— it doesn't mean it doesn't become חמץ chametz at all, but
at least you go ahead and you bake it, and you treat
it and it's not worse than water, and you can go ahead
and have it.
Especially if you're working it, okay?
Right. Okay. ולא אמרו לי דבר. ve-lo amru li davar. ואף על
פי שאין לשין. ve-af al pi she-ein lashin.
Now,
the משנה Mishnah goes back and says that's the debate of רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. Then it says, even though you can't knead it, meaning according
to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, you're not allowed to knead it with
these fruit juices, מכתפין בו, mekatfin bo, and you can sort of,
you can like smear it on top. You know how after you
make the bread you smear like an egg, an egg שמיר? schmear?
So you can smear it on top. That is not going to
lead it to becoming חמץ. chametz. עשו לתנא קמא. asu l'tana kamma.
That goes back to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says you can't use it as a real sort of the real
liquid of it, but you can put it on afterward. וחכמים אומרים,
ve-chachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim are even more strict than רבן
גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. They say, את שלשין בו מכתפין בו, et she-lashin
bo mekatfin bo, things you can knead the dead bread with, if
they're allowed... But they're חכמים Chachamim because חכמים Chachamim say יוכל. yochal.
Yeah. That's true. Or actually, it's an interesting point. Or maybe they're
just telling רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel to be consistent. So it's a
good question. Okay, but the חכמים Chachamim say, if you can knead
with it, then you can put it on the top of the
bread. ואת שאין לשין בו אין מכתפין בו, ve-et she-ein lashin bo
ein mekatfin bo, and it's things that you think you're not allowed
to knead with, you're not allowed to have as the liquid, אין
מכתפין בו, ein mekatfin bo, you would not be able to put
on the שמיר. schmear. You have to be consistent. If the liquids
are a problem, they're a problem wherever you put them. Okay. ושוין,
ve-shavin, but everybody agrees, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, the חכמים, Chachamim, רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, everybody agrees, not רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, was it
רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel? Yeah,
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel right. Everybody agrees, ושוין שאין לשין את העיסה
בפושרין, ve-shavin she-ein lashin et ha-issah be-posher, that you can't use lukewarm
water, because lukewarm water causes also it to ferment quicker. Okay, so
all of these, and that would be another question, what about smearing
the top with lukewarm water? So there's a question about things you
can't use to knead, and can we make a difference between the
actual kneading as the liquid as a main ingredient and putting it
on at the top. But basically what you have here is the
position of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel on one side, and the חכמים
Chachamim and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva on the other, that רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel says that the fruit juices, again referring back to yesterday,
maybe with the addition of water, maybe by themselves, but whatever the
case is, fruit juices are a problem, can become חמץ, chametz, and
can even make it become חמץ chametz faster, and therefore you can't
deal with fruit juices at all. Whereas רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva the
חכמים Chachamim say, even if in theory it could become חמץ chametz
with water by itself, whatever, it's not worse than water, and you
can go ahead and use it. Okay, so now, you know, obviously
you gotta bake the מצות, matzos, but you can go ahead and
use it. So now the גמרא Gemara says you see רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says you can use fruit juices. So if you can
use fruit juices and they're not a bigger problem of חמץ chametz
than water, why does he say you can't have מצה matzah out
of it? Now the answer's obvious, but let's see the גמרא's Gemara
question. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not
difficult. הא ביום טוב ראשון הא ביום טוב שני. ha be-yom tov
rishon ha be-yom tov sheni. The question isn't, the question is, can
you do the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah with it? Yes, you
can make מצה matzah with fruit juice, just don't eat it סדר
Seder night, eat it the other days of פסח. Pesach. It's not
חמץ. chametz. But for the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah on the
first night, that has to be לחם עוני, lechem oni, that has
to be plain simple bread, that cannot be, you know, tasty sweet
flavored flavored מצה. matzah. Okay, so there's a difference between what is
kosher מצה, matzah, meaning not חמץ, chametz, and that's, you know, there
a lot of things that could be okay, as opposed to the
question of what do you need to be fulfill your מצוה mitzvah
of מצה matzah on the first night, and that would not be
acceptable if you used fruit juices, that would not be poor person's
bread.
So even though he says עני ani is really עוני, oni, and
the עוני oni is the עונים עליו דברים הרבה, onim alav devarim
harbe, he still take, you know, אין מקרא יוצא מידי פשוטו, ein
mikra yotze midei pshuto, right? What? Because רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva the
one that didn't דרשן, darshen, he agrees that it's עוני.
oni. But he says דברים הרבה devarim harbe is also only the
סדר Seder night, you don't say דברים הרבה devarim harbe on the
מצה matzah the rest of the week, and the עני ani is
the סדר Seder night. So the מצה matzah of the special status
of לחם עוני lechem oni and לחם עוני lechem oni and all
those things is the סדר Seder night מצה. matzah. The rest of
the מצות matzos don't need that.
No, no, no, I know, but I'm saying he still says that
you're not יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah with this
stuff that was נילוש במי פירות, nilosh be-mei peirot, even though he
is the one that expounded עוני oni not in a literal sense.
עונים דברים הרבה. onim devarim harbe.
No, the גמרא Gemara al-, no, there's the עני ani the way
it's written, which means without יין ושמן ודבש, yayin ve-shemen ve-devash, and
there's the עוני oni with the ו', vav, which is דברים הרבה.
devarim harbe. That's exactly what the גמרא Gemara says, there's two aspects
to that word. Okay.
Yeah. What was יום טוב שני yom tov sheni then? I'm sorry?
רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, what's יום טוב שני? yom tov sheni? What's
יום? yom?
Yeah, it means any day after the first day יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Oh, you mean why does he call it יום טוב שני?
yom tov sheni?
What does that mean when they...?
Yeah, they just mean the rest of the days of פסח. Pesach.
They don't mean specifically יום טוב. Yom Tov. I know, it's not...
Yeah, it's just a phrase the גמרא Gemara uses. It means the
rest of the days of פסח. Pesach. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says, like you have that in סוכות Sukkos as well, יום
טוב שני yom tov sheni could often doesn't necessarily mean the יום
טוב שני של גלויות, yom tov sheni shel galuyos, it just means
the other days. of the חג. Chag. כדאמר ליה, K'de'amar lei, now
we're going to show this obvious, this difference between the מצה Matzah
of the מצווה Mitzvah and the rest of the night, כדאמר ליה
K'de'amar lei רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua לבניה, livnei, like רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua said to his son.
יומא קמא לא תלושו לי בחלבא, Yoma kama lo talushu li be'chalba,
the first night for פסח Pesach night, don't add milk to the
to the
dough. Okay. We're going to talk about that. And anyway, what, he
wasn't, he didn't have meat at the סדר? Seder? So you know,
maybe maybe he would have had milk and then waited a few
minutes and then washed out his mouth and had meat. Anyway, מטעם
ואילך לושו לי בחלבא, Mita'am va'eilach lushu li be'chalba, but afterwards you
can make מצות Matzos with milk.
The גמרא Gemara says, שילי, Sheili, like only for him?
I don't know, maybe they had, maybe who knows, maybe each person
had their own מצה. Matzah.
I think he's talking about their...
Okay, so the גמרא's Gemara's going to talk say then. Shh, let's
see. והתניא, Vehatanya, the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, didn't we learn
in a ברייתא, Braisa, אין לשין את העיסה בחלב, Ein lashin es
ha'isa be'chalav, that you can never make dough out with milk, meaning
whether it's bread or מצה, Matzah, whatever you're making, ואם לש כל
הפת כולה אסורה, ve'im lash kol hapos kula asura, and if you
did you can never eat the bread? Forget פסח Pesach in general,
you can't have מילכיג milchig bread, we taught this just a little
while ago, מפני הרגל עבירה, mipnei hergel aveira, it leads to sin
because you eat bread with everything and if you have מילכיג milchig
bread you'll wind up eating it with meat. So how could how
could he have, forget the issue of סדר Seder night and the
rest of the nights, how could he eat it the rest of
the nights? אלא הכי קאמר, Ela hachi ka'amar, the... okay so you're
right. This is what he meant. יומא קמא לא תלושו לי בדובשא,
Yoma kama lo talushu li beduvsha, first night don't add honey, מכאן
ואילך לושו לי בדובשא, mikan va'eilach lushu li beduvsha, afterwards add honey.
So that's a way of fixing it, just change what he said.
ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'is eima, if you want you can say, לעולם בחלבא,
le'olam be'chalba, no, he it was talking about milk. So how would
it be okay the rest of the nights? כדאמר רבינא, Kide'amar Ravina,
like רבינא Ravina says, it is allowed, you are allowed to have
מילכיג milchig bread, כעין תורא, ke'ein tura, when you do it, now
there's a question what this word means. רש"י Rashi says it means
like the eye of an ox, meaning you do small little single
single service, you know, like single eating loaves, like tiny little, you
know like like tiny little, what do you call, bite size, right,
bite size loaves. So if you do, you know like like what'd
you say? Garlic knots. Garlic knots. If you do something like that,
so you eat it all in one sitting, so you're not going
to like leave it over and then forget that it was מילכיג
milchig bread.
How do you get כעין תורא ke'ein tura out of that?
Like he says, like the eye of an ox.
Because an eye is small enough to eat in one...
Yeah, it's a small size. It's a way of saying a little
small size, a bite size. What, do you mean make it like
a different...? Okay, wait, a bite size. Other people say כעין תורא
ke'ein tura means כעין ke'ein means similar to, like you know, ועינו
כעין הבדולח, ve'eino ke'ein habdolach, so they mean like you make it
look like an ox. Of course if it looks like an ox
is that supposed to signify מילכיג milchig or פליישיג? fleishig? It's like
writing M on it. So does that mean milk or does that
mean meat? Anyway, somehow others take it to mean that you make
it look different so it's obvious that it's a סימן siman of
what it is, it's a sign of what it is. So there
are ways in which you can have מילכיג milchig bread as long
as there's something that signifies its status or that you won't come
to eat it with something else. הכא נמי כעין תורא, Hacha nami
ke'ein tura, so here too that's what he's talking about. But the
upshot is is that סדר Seder night has higher criteria. There it
cannot be sweet and have additives even if it's not a חמץ
chametz problem. And that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, so and
so we learn עוני oni that it can't be sweet for סדר
Seder night, B, that it has to be that it's connected to
the story of the הגדה Haggadah and of and of הלל, Hallel,
עונין עליו דברים הרבה. onin alav devarim harbei. And the debate of
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel of רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili about can you eat with מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni something that is connected to שמחה, simcha, is that in somehow
contradiction to the idea of לחם עוני? Lechem Oni? Yes.
So it doesn't exist anymore in America, but Wonder Bread was dairy
and yet it had a הכשר. hechsher.
Right, so we discussed this before, I'm not going to get into
detail. I will say that there's a major question, is it enough
that the סימן siman is on the packaging? So if the if
it says OUD, then the סימן siman is on the packaging without
it being on the bread, is that enough? So there's a major
debate about that. Yes.
Quick question, we said so far what we said actually, if I
understood this correctly, that חסרונות chesronos is in the actual making of
it. In other words you make it with like מי פירות mei
peiros or whatever it is, but it doesn't say that like let's
say I decide to put some nice jam on top of it,
you're not יוצא.
yotzei. Right, that's another discussion
about עשייה ושהוי asiya veshehui שמה מבטל מצווה. shema mevatel mitzvah. We'll
discuss that later. Okay,
continuing. Second wide line. וכולם שאין לשין את העיסה בפושרים. Vekulam she'ein
lashim es ha'isa beposhrim. Everybody agrees you can't use lukewarm water, that
would speed up the fermenting process. Okay, so now the גמרא's Gemara's
going to ask, is this really true that we have this anxiety
around lukewarm water? About and
חמץ? chametz? מאי שנא ממנחות? Mai shena mimnachos? How's it different from
a מנחה? Mincha? Now a מנחה Mincha also לא תאפה חמץ, lo
se'afeh chametz, right? מנחה Mincha has to be מצות, Matzos, they can't
be made into חמץ, chametz, it's very clear in the תורה. Torah.
So it's interesting comparisons were beginning to make that things you can't
do that you have to worry about on פסח Pesach you would
also have to worry about in the making of מנחות Minchos because
מנחות Minchos can't be made into חמץ. chametz. Okay, so let's see
what we learn by מנחות. Minchos. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the
משנה Mishnah in מנחות, Menachos, כל המנחות נילושות בפושרים, Kol hamnachos niloshos
beposhrim, you can knead, again with a K, all מנחות Minchos with
lukewarm water, ומשמרן שלא יחמיצו, umeshamran shelo yachmitzu, and you and you
watch them, you guard them so that they should not become חמץ,
chametz, meaning yes, it acknowledges... Let's see what we learned by מנחות
*minchos*. תנן *Tnan*, we taught in the משנה *Mishnah* in מנחות *Menachos*,
כל המנחות נלושות בפושרים *kol haminchos nilloshos be-poshrim*. You can knead, again
with a K, all מנחות *minchos* with lukewarm water, ומשמרן שלא יחמיצו
*umeshmaran shelo yachmitsu*, יחמיצו *yechemitsu*, יחמיצו *yechamitsu*, יחמיצו *yachmitsu*, and you watch
them, you guard them so that they should not become חמץ Chometz,
*chametz*. Meaning yes, it acknowledges that lukewarm is an issue, just says
okay, so be careful, make sure. Now how do you watch them
not to become חמץ Chometz? *chametz*? The basic way is you keep
on kneading the dough. As long as you're kneading the dough, you're
not allowing it to ferment.
So it's okay to use lukewarm water as long as you're careful
is basically the פשט *pshat*. The פשט *pshat*. So now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says so how come this is different? So the answer
is obvious. אם אמרו בזריזין יאמרו בשאין זריזין *Im amru bizerizin yomru
beshein zerizin*? If we're going to just because we're going to allow
it by people that are like that are careful, like in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* and the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*, this
is their whole
job, they're highly focused on this, we're not going to give a
blanket allowance to every בעל הבית *ba'al habayis* to do it. Some
people won't be so careful. So we have to put different limits.
Some of these מצה Matzah, *matzah* factories are pretty זריז *zeriz* to
me.
All right, but here people were doing it at home. Okay, אי
הכי *i hachi* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, if that's true, that
we're so, that we're not concerned because everybody is so careful in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, so ליתס נמי ליתס *lises
nami lises*. Why don't we also allow לתיסה *lisesa*? לתיסה *Lisesa* was,
there's got to be a technical term for this, but you would
put the grain in water to soften up the kernel or the
husk around it, and then
you would remove it like rubbing it between your fingers and that
would get the bran off. And that would allow you to have
white flour and to remove the bran. So it was a process
of removing bran that came by putting the grains in water. And
that you would not do for מנחה Mincha. *minchah* because that would
lead to חמץ Chometz. *chametz*. But the question is, why do we
have to be concerned? We'll just say we're doing it in a
case where in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* everybody is
careful and they'll make sure that they don't leave it around long
enough to become חמץ *chametz*. One minute. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אלמה אמרו בי סורא *alama amru bei Sura*? אמר רב אמר
רבה בר ירמיה אמר שמואל *Amar Rav amar Rabbah bar Yirmiyah amar
Shmuel*, why did we say חיטין שבמנחות *chittin shemenachos*, the wheat that
you use for מנחה Mincha *minchah*, אין לותתין אותן *ein losesin osan*,
you do not do this לתיסה *lisesa*, you do not do this
removal of bran and submerging it in water. So how come we
don't say oh everybody is careful? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
לישה בזריזין איתא *lisha bizerizin isa*. The kneading is done with זריזין
*zerizin*, with the כהנים Kohanim, *Kohanim*. לתיסה *Lisesa*, the removing of the
bran, לאו בזריזין איתא *lav bizerizin isa*, is not because basically it
says you could bring your flour to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beis Hamikdash* and say here is my flour for a מנחה *minchah*
and the כהנים *Kohanim* would then turn it into dough. But you
made the flour and this fine flour and removing of the bran,
you made that at home. So we can't let you, you are
the one who's processing the flour. It's the כהנים *Kohanim* that are
doing it with the dough. So we can't let you do this
process because that you'll do out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash.
*Beis Hamikdash* and every layperson will do that and some people won't
be so careful. But the making of the dough, that's done by
the כהנים *Kohanim*, that we're not afraid. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ולישה מי בזריזין *velisha mi bizerizin*? Since when is it only
the כהנים *Kohanim* that make the dough? והכתיב *Vehaksiv*, the פסוק pasuk,
*pasuk* says, ויצק עליה שמן *veyatzak aleha shemen*, you pour on it
oil, and you prepare the whole
מנחה *minchah*, והביאה אל הכהן *vehevi'ah el hakohen* or אל בני אהרן
Aharon הכהנים *el bnei Aharon hakohanim* and then you bring it to
the כהן Kohen, *Kohen*, and from there we learn מקמיצה ואילך מצות
Matzos. כהונה *mikemitza va'eilach mitzvas kehunah*, the כהנים *Kohanim* only have to
get involved starting at the קמיצה *kemitza*, at the actual offering of
the מנחה *minchah*. לימד על יציקה ובלילה *Limad al yetzika uvelila*, everything
that precedes it, not only the kneading and the baking, even the
pouring of the oil and all of those things and the mixing
of the oil, all of those שכשרה בכל אדם *shekeshera bechol adam*,
you don't need to do with a כהן Kohen *Kohen*. So since
when is it that you take care of making it flour, the
כהן *Kohen* takes care of making it dough? It's not true, you
make the dough also. So why do we assume that that'll be
taken care of okay? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לישה *lisha*,
it's true, kneading, נהי דבזריזין ליתא *nehi debizerizin leisa*, it's true it's
not necessarily the כהנים *Kohanim* who do the kneading. Nevertheless, במקום זריזין
איתא *bemakom zerizin isa*. It's done in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash,
*Beis Hamikdash*. The flour you process at home. And therefore we're afraid
that some people won't be so careful and we can't allow this
use of water when you're doing it at home. However, the kneading
maybe isn't done by the כהנים *Kohanim* but it's done in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. דאמר מר *De'amar mar*, because the
master has taught, בלילה *blila*, not בלילה *balaylah*. בלילה כשירה בזר *Blila
keshera bezar*, it's true the mixing of oil can be done with
a non-כהן *Kohen*, but חוץ לחומת העזרה פסולה *chutz lechomas ha'azarah pesulah*.
Outside of the temple walls is invalid. So you have to, now
of course what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafos* both ask is,
okay, but that's the בלילה *blila*, the earlier stage of kneading maybe
that could be done out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis
Hamikdash*. So basically what רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafos* both say is,
although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't spelling it out, רש"י *Rashi* says
is the kneading has to be done in the בית המקדש *Beis
Hamikdash* because at that stage it has to be put in a
כלי שרת *kli shares*. And the כלי שרת *kli shares*, so you
don't have to make the flour in a כלי שרת *kli shares*,
you bring the flour but you have to knead it in a
כלי שרת *kli shares* and the כלי שרת *kli shares* is only
in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Okay, תוספות *Tosafos* also says that
you have to put it right after you knead it, it has
to go straight into the oven. So you can't knead it at
home and then bring it to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, it's
going to become חמץ *chametz* in the interim. So for whatever reason
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is look, lukewarm water is a problem
but since it's all done in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, the
kneading, we're not, we don't care. We're we're we assume you'll be
on top of it, even if it's not done by the כהנים.
The making of the flour is done out of the בית המקדש
and therefore we don't want you to submerge it in water when
you're making it into fine flour because that will lead to problems.
Yes, Charlie.
Wait a
second, did the כהנים eat מצה, Matzah מצה Matzah, on the מקדש,
Mikdash, מצה, Matzah, yes.
מצה, Matzah yes, and that's the whole point, that they're kneading this
and making מצה Matzah out of it.
Yeah, this is an issue if anyone ever tried to make their
own oat מצה Matzah. because almost all oats are processed with hot
water, and and a lot of rice is also processed in hot
water.
And so it's already had contact with water by the time you
get it. Right, that's why if you know flour, you can't just
buy flour on פסח Pesach and make your own מצה. Matzah You
don't know how it was processed, right. Okay. All right. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא continues.
ומאי שנא ממנחת העומר? U-mai sh'na mi-minchas ha-omer? Now, back to this
issue of לסיסה l'sisah that it's a concern of חמץ, okay, how
is it different than the עומר? Omer? Because the עומר Omer was
again a type of a מנחה. דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, Baraisa, מנחת העומר, Minchas ha-omer, the מנחה that you bring in
the עומר Omer of the new, right, the first cutting of the
of the barley, לא סנסה, lo sansah, you would do this לסיסה
l'sisah to remove the
bran וצוברו אותה צבור vetsover osah tsibur and you put it in
a pile, presumably the pile then the water would would come out,
but nevertheless you would actually process it with water at an earlier
stage. Why are we not concerned that it'll become חמץ? הגמרא Ha-gemara
says, so the גמרא says, ציבור שאני. Tsibur shani. No, the מנחת
העומר Minchas ha-omer is a communal sacrifice. And therefore, it's done in
a very centralized way, right, it's not every individual does it, it's
not even just not even just done in the בית המקדש. It's
done completely supervised. It is the מנחת- Minchas it's the it's a
communal sacrifice, and whoever is in charge is in charge of the
entire process, so there we are kick- over- we are going to
be totally careful and make sure that the process is done you
can, you know, in a way that even if- that we can
allow it to come in contact with water earlier, cause we're going
to be totally on top of it and make sure that it
doesn't become חמץ. Okay. So that's the answer. I should say by
the way it's an interesting little echo of the word. וצוברו אותה
Tsover osah means you make it a pile, and then it says
ציבור שאני, Tsibur shani, which means it's a קרבן ציבור. Korban Tsibur.
But because of that confusion, some people wanted to say ציבור שאני
Tsibur shani the pile, having made it into a pile makes a
difference. So רש"י completely rejects that read. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
So that is the issue about lukewarm water and some parallels to
the בית המקדש. Now, back to this issue of what are the
things that you can make מצה Matzah out of and when they
are prohibited for other reasons or other statuses, like מנחת- Minchas like
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, יכול
יוצא אדם ידי חובתו בביכורים? yakhol yotsei adam yedei khovaso be-bikkurim? Maybe
you could fulfill your obligation with ביכורים, Bikkurim, even in ירושלים? Yerushalayim?
Okay, similar- Last year's ביכורים? Bikkurim? No- similar to I guess, yeah,
it's a good point, it's- or very- ביכורים Bikkurim you were very
late to bring. Okay. So it's- although it's actually true, after some
point you can't bring it. So last year's ביכורים. Bikkurim. Look, it's
flour, you can hold it over. Okay. So- so maybe you could
fulfill your obligation with ביכורים Bikkurim in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, similar to the
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim question. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
the verse teaches, בכל מושבותיכם תאכלו מצות, bekhol moshvoseikhem sokhlu matzos, in
all of your dwelling places you should eat מצות. matzos מצה הנאכלת
בכל מושבותיכם. Matzah hanekheles bekhol moshvoseikhem. So מצה Matzah that can be
eaten in all your dwelling places. יצאו ביכורים שאינן נאכלין בכל מושבותיכם
אלא בירושלים. Yatza bikkurim she-einan nekhalin bekhol moshvoseikhem ela bi-yerushalayim. So even
if you're in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you can't fulfill your obligation because in
theory there's no way it could be eaten out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
It has to be able to be eaten everywhere. דברי רבי יוסי
הגלילי. Divrei Rabbi Yosei Ha-Galili. That's what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosei
Ha-Galili said. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says, no, מצה Matzah מרור, Maror, the Torah connects מצה Matzah to
מרור, Maror, right, על מצות ומרורים. al matzos u-m'rorim. מה מרור שאין
ביכורים, Ma maror she-ein bikkurim, the same way you fulfill the mitzvah
of מרור Maror even though- I
mean, you know, I'm sorry, the same way מרור Maror cannot be
ביכורים Bikkurim because you just don't have מרור Maror that's ביכורים, Bikkurim,
ביכורים Bikkurim is only the שבעת המינים, shivas haminim, אף מצה שאינה
ביכורים. af matzah she-eina bikkurim. So similarly מצה Matzah cannot be ביכורים.
Bikkurim. So he agrees to the הלכה halakha that it can't be
ביכורים Bikkurim but he learns it out from a different פסוק, Pasuk
from the fact that it has to be similar to מרור. Maror.
So the גמרא says, one minute, אם מה מרור שאין במינו ביכורים
אף מצה שאין במינו ביכורים? im ma maror she-ein be-mino bikkurim af
matzah she-ein be-mino bikkurim? If we're going to make that comparison, maybe
we should say that it's not enough that מצה Matzah doesn't happen
to be ביכורים, Bikkurim, maybe מצה Matzah has to be like מרור
Maror that it couldn't even potentially be ביכורים. Bikkurim. And therefore, what
would I do? הוציא חטים ושעורים שיש במינן ביכורים. Otsi chittim u-se'orim
she-yesh be-minan bikkurim. It says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, if you want
to say
מצה- Matzah has to be like מרור, Maror, so maybe I would
say that you can never make מצה Matzah out of wheat and
barley, you only have to use the other three of the five
מינים, minim, cause wheat and barley are the שבעת המינים shivas haminim
and they can become ביכורים, Bikkurim, maybe I have to exclude things
that are even potentially ביכורים. Bikkurim.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, no, מצות מצות ריבה. matzos matzos riba. No,
there we get the language of מצות Matzos. that says don't be
so restrictive. אם מצות מצות ריבה, Im matzos matzos riba, if you're
going to read it that way to be more inclusive, אפילו ביכורים
נמי? afilu bikkurim nami? So why not even include ביכורים, Bikkurim, meaning
again, what is this funny דרשה drasha that it has to be
like מרור Maror etc.? Okay. And if the פסוק Pasuk is vague,
then why should I read it in a restrictive way if רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva generally reads it in a more inclusive way? So
the גמרא says, you know what? You're right. הדר ביה רבי עקיבא.
Hadar beih Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva reversed himself and not
in his position, but learning it out because it's connected to מרור
Maror and in the end he came around to רבי יוסי הגלילי's
Rabbi Yosi HaGlili reason, which is yes, everybody agrees you can't do
it with ביכורים, Bikurim, but for רבי יוסי הגלילי's Rabbi Yosi HaGlili
reason, because it says בכל מושבותיכם Bechol moshvoseichem that מצה Matzah has
to be able to be eaten everywhere and ביכורים Bikurim can't be
eaten everywhere. So how do you know it? דתניא, De-tanya, we taught
on the ברייתא. Baraita. יכול יצא אדם ידי חובתו בביכורים, Yakhol yetzei
adam yedei chovato be-bikurim,
maybe you should fulfill your obligation of מצה Matzah of ביכורים Bikurim
in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? תלמוד לומר בכל מושבותיכם תאכלו מצות, Talmud lomar bechol
moshvoseichem tochlu matzot, in all of your dwelling places eat מצות. Matzos
מצה הנאכלת בכל מושבות, Matzah hane'echelet bechol moshvot,
מצה Matzah that can be eaten everywhere. יצאו ביכורים שאינם נאכלים בכל
מושבות אלא בירושלים, Yatzu bikurim she-einam ne'echelim bechol moshvot ela bi-Yerushalayim,
to exclude ביכורים Bikurim that cannot be, can only be eaten in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So even though you're eating it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, since
it can't be eaten everywhere, you're not יוצא. Yotzei. There's a nice
concept here I think about the sort of sense of, you know,
מצה Matzah. having to have a universal quality, like a fully accessible
quality. It's an interesting idea. On the other hand, it's also fascinating
since in the תורה, Torah, where should everybody be on the first
night of פסח? Pesach?
בירושלים Bi-Yerushalayim anyway, in ירושלים Yerushalayim eating
their קרבן, Korban, eating their קרבן Korban with מצה. Matzah So the
idea that you're not יוצא Yotzei with מצה Matzah. that can't be
eaten out of ירושלים Yerushalayim is pretty interesting, you know, considering the
paradigm of where you're eating מצה. Matzah, Okay, now. יכול שאני מוציא
אף מעשר שני, Yakhol she-ani motzi af ma'aser sheni, now maybe if
I'm going to say things that can only be eaten that ביכורים
Bikurim is no good because it could be only eaten in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, maybe I should also say מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni is no
good because it could only be eaten in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? מצות מצות
ריבה. Matzos matzos ribah.
No, the extra word מצות means be more inclusive. Okay, but why
make the split this way? This is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right?
Now we're going to say it doesn't say who it is, but
we're going to say that it has to be רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is the one who says you
can be יוצא Yotzei with מעשר שני. Ma'aser sheni. So here we
have an opinion that says מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni is good, which
we know is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva against רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi
Yosi HaGlili. And it says ביכורים Bikurim is no good based on
the פסוק Pasuk בכל מושבותיכם. Bechol moshvoseichem. So that's how we learn
that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva excludes ביכורים Bikurim based on the פסוק
Pasuk of בכל מושבותיכם. Bechol moshvoseichem. But now we have to understand
why it's different than מעשר שני, Ma'aser sheni, which is what this
asks. ומה ראית לרבות מעשר שני ולהוציא ביכורים, U-mah ra'ita lerabot ma'aser
sheni ulehotzi bikurim, what makes you include מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni and
exclude ביכורים Bikurim since both of those can only be eaten in
ירושלים Yerushalayim and not outside of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? מרבה אני מעשר שני
שיש לו היתר בכל מושבות. Marbeh ani ma'aser sheni she-yesh lo heter
be-chol moshavot.
No, מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni can be eaten out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Now how could it be out of ירושלים? Yerushalayim? You could
redeem it. But it's going to go even further. Not only can
you redeem it, even once you've brought it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the
normal הלכה Halacha is that once you bring מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you can no longer redeem it. But no, even
after you've brought in and this מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni that you
want to fulfill the מצוה Mitzvah of מצה, Matzah and you've already
brought into ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you're in ירושלים Yerushalayim and you say let
me eat my מעשר שני מצה. Ma'aser sheni matzah. And the point
is no, you can't eat it anywhere else. Now that would be
the הלכה, Halacha, once you've brought it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you can
no longer redeem it. But say no, even after you've brought it
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, there's a way in theory you might be able
to redeem it and eat it outside. What's that way? כדרבי אלעזר,
Ke-Rabbi Elazar, like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says. ומוציא אני ביכורים שאין
להם היתר בכל מושבות, U-motzi ani bikurim she-ein lahem heter be-chol moshavot,
and I exclude ביכורים Bikurim that can never be eaten outside of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. דאמר רבי אלעזר, De-amar Rabbi Elazar, מניין למעשר שני שנטמא,
Minayin le-ma'aser sheni she-nitma, how do you know if מעשר שני Ma'aser
sheni became טמא, Tamei, שפודנהו אפילו בירושלים, She-podnehu afilu bi-Yerushalayim, even if
it's already in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? How do I know that you can
redeem it and eat it outside ירושלים Yerushalayim if it became טמא?
Tamei? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, because if it's טמא Tamei you can't
eat it anymore. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the פסוק Pasuk says כי
לא תוכל שאתו, Ki lo tuchal se'eto, when are you allowed to
redeem it? If you can't carry it up to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And
we're going to make a little play on words. ואין שאת אלא
אכילה, Ve-ein se'et ela achilah, שאת Se'et doesn't just mean carry, it
means eat. שנאמר וישא משאת מאת פניו. Shene'emar vayisa maset me-et panav.
So משאת, Maset, משאות Masaot I think, right? Anyway, that this is
the gifts that יוסף Yosef gave to the brothers, and it says
and it refers to them as משאת, Maset, which means and here
it's assuming that it was food. So you see שאת Se'et means
food and therefore if you can't eat it anymore you're allowed to
redeem it. So basically what do we have in this ברייתא? Baraita?
It says if you're in ירושלים Yerushalayim with your ביכורים Bikurim and
your מעשר שני, Ma'aser sheni, you can't eat your מצה matzah? out
of your ביכורים Bikurim because once the ביכורים Bikurim can never be
eaten out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but you can eat your מעשר שני,
Ma'aser sheni, even though now it can't be eaten out of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, were it to become טמא, Tamei, you would be able to
bring it out of ירושלים Yerushalayim and therefore מעשר שני Ma'aser sheni
is not excluded but ביכורים Bikurim is excluded. So who is this
person
that does not exclude מעשר שני? Ma'aser sheni? רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
And he's excluding ביכורים Bikurim based on the פסוק pasuk of בכל
מושבותיכם. Bechol moshvoseichem. מאן שמעת ליה דאמר במעשר שני נפיק ביה? Man
sham'at leih de-amar be-ma'aser sheni nafik beih?
Who did we learn on the עמוד א׳ amud alef argues with
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili and says you can eat מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim מצה? matzah רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
It's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. וקא ממעט ליה Ve'ka memait lei לביכורים
מבכל מושבותיכם le'bikurim mibechol moshvoseichem
and nevertheless he agrees to the דרשה drasha of רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yose HaGlili by ביכורים. bikurim. He does agree to the דרשה
drasha בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoseichem that it has to be able to
be eaten in theory out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that excludes ביכורים,
bikurim, but for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it does not exclude מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni because מעשר שני Maaser Sheni can still in theory
be eaten out of ירושלים Yerushalayim if it became טמא tamei and
you redeemed it. שמע מינה הדר ביה, Shma mina hader bei, so
you see he reversed the דרשה. drasha. He didn't reverse his position
but he wound up coming along to the דרשה drasha of בכל
מושבותיכם. bechol moshvoseichem. Now the גמרא asks what I was waiting for
Michael to ask, why does רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili need
the דרשה drasha of בכל מושבותיכם? bechol moshvoseichem? Okay, and I was
silencing you. So רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, so the גמרא says רבי
יוסי הגלילי תיפוק ליה מלחם עוני. Rabbi Yose HaGlili teipokei milechem oni.
If he excludes מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, right, מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
might not be able to be excluded like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoseichem because in theory it could be eaten outside
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But he excludes מעשר שני Maaser Sheni because of
לחם עוני, lechem oni, it can't be eaten with אנינות. aninus. Well,
guess what, the same הלכה halacha applies to ביכורים. bikurim. So why
can't he use that same פסוק pasuk for מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
and ביכורים? bikurim? So תיפוק ליה מלחם עוני מי שנאכל באני יצא
זה שאינו נאכל אלא בשמחה. teipokei milechem oni mi sheneachal be'oni yatza
zeh she'eino neachal ela besimcha. Okay, so לחם עוני lechem oni excludes
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni even though it might not be excluded based
on בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoseichem because it could in theory be eaten
out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so use לחם עוני lechem oni to exclude
ביכורים. bikurim. Who needs the other דרשה? drasha? So the גמרא says
סבר לה כרבי שמעון, savar lah ke'Rabbi Shimon, he holds like רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא braisa ביכורים
אסורים לאונן. bikurim asurim le'onen. ביכורים bikurim are linked to מעשר שני,
Maaser Sheni, both of them have to be eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim
and cannot be eaten by an אונן. onen. But רבי שמעון מתיר,
Rabbi Shimon matir, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, ביכורים bikurim is
different than מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, ביכורים bikurim can be eaten by
an אונן. onen. So רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, he excludes
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni because it can't be eaten by an אונן
onen and not because of בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoseichem because in theory
it could be eaten out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And he excludes ביכורים
bikurim which can be eaten by an אונן, onen, so ביכורים bikurim
he excludes based on the פסוק pasuk of בכל מושבותיכם. bechol moshvoseichem.
Now, מאי טעמא דרבנן? mai taama de'rabbanan? What, now let's look at
this debate about ביכורים bikurim being eaten by an אונן. onen. What's
the reason of the רבנן rabbanan that say no? דכתיב לא תוכל
לאכל בשעריך מעשר דגנך ותירשך ויצהרך ובכרת בקרך וצאנך de-chsiv lo suchal
leechol bisharecha maaser degancha tiroshcha ve'yitzharecha bechoros bekarcha vetzonecha and it says
ותרומת ידך u-trumas yadecha in the end. ואמר מר ותרומת ידך, ve'amar
mar trumas yadecha, that thing that says the תרומה trumah of your
hands, this פסוק pasuk is things you can't eat out of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you have to eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So what does it
mean the gift of your hands? אלו ביכורים. elu bikurim. So that
פסוק pasuk of things that have to be eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
one of the things is ביכורים. bikurim. And the other thing it
says is מעשר דגנך. maaser degancha. Now which מעשר, maaser, normally מעשר
maaser is eaten out of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Which מעשר maaser has to
be eaten in ירושלים? Yerushalayim? Only which מעשר? maaser? מעשר שני, Maaser
Sheni, right? So this פסוק pasuk speaks about things that are eaten
in ירושלים Yerushalayim and speaks about מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and speaks
about ביכורים. bikurim. So it links the two. So if מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni cannot be eaten by an אונן, onen, ביכורים bikurim cannot
be eaten by an אונן. onen.
So someone's position is highly
problematic, what we will get there, okay. So אלו ביכורים דאיתקש ביכורים
למעשר. elu bikurim de'itkes bikurim le'maaser. So now the פסוק pasuk speaks
about eating both ביכורים bikurim and מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. מה מעשר אסור לאונן, ma maaser asur le'onen, the same way
מעשר maaser can't be eaten by an אונן, onen, אף ביכורים אסור
לאונן, af bikurim asur le'onen, even ביכורים bikurim cannot. So that's the
simple sense. These are both things you eat in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the
same הלכה halacha applies, can't be either eaten... they're eaten בשמחה, besimcha,
they're not eaten by an אונן. onen. Now how about רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who says that ביכורים bikurim can be eaten by an
אונן? onen? תרומה קרינה רחמנא. truma karina rachmana. No, at the end
of the day the רחמנא Rachmana says ותרומת ידך. trumas yadecha. So
even though it's in the same פסוק with ביכורים, bikurim, it's more
identified as a type of a תרומה. trumah. So that's the status
that applies to it. כתרומה. ke'trumah. מה תרומה מותרת לאונן, ma trumah
muteres le'onen, interestingly תרומה, trumah, although it's holy, can be eaten by
an אונן. onen. It's not eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. You understand the
idea of אונן, onen, I should say, is very much about בית
המקדש related, right? Like when the כהן, you know, the whole thing
about אהרן and משה Moshe says why did you, you know, why
did you burn this חטאת, chatas, you know, they were אוננים. onenim.
An אונן onen can't eat קרבנות, korbanos, right? And you know the
כהן when he becomes, when he loses a relative leaves the בית
המקדש. So things that are eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ירושלים Yerushalayim is
a type of an extension of the בית המקדש, like the eating
in the בית המקדש, there you can understand that there we exclude
אונן. onen. But if something is תרומה, trumah, תרומה trumah is holy
but it's eaten anywhere by כהנים, so אונן onen is not excluded.
So he says is ביכורים bikurim is called a type of a
תרומה trumah and the same way תרומה trumah can be eaten by
an אונן, onen, אף ביכורים מותר לאונן. af bikurim mutar le'onen. So
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, what does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say back
to that? ניהי דהיקש לית ליה, nihidu hekesh leitei, so this is
probably what Mike... I'm sorry, not what does he say back to
that, this is what probably Michael was going to ask. So רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, okay fine, it's not linked to ביכורים, bikurim, it's
not linked to מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. But still, שמחה מי אמיכתב
כתיב בהו? simcha mi amichtav ksiv behu? It still emphasized emphasizes that
ביכורים bikurim are eaten בשמחה, b'simcha, דכתיב ושמחת בכל הטוב. d'khtiv v'samachta
b'khol hatov. So how can you say that you can eat it
as- a person can eat it as an אונן onen if the
whole idea of שמחה simcha is connected to ביכורים? bikurim? So the
גמרא says no, ההוא לזמן שמחה הוא דאתא. hahu l'zman simcha hu
d'ata. That is coming to tell you that the time you bring
ביכורים bikurim is at- is at the time of joy when people
are joyous because of their harvest. What does that mean? דתנן, d'tnan,
מעצרת ועד החג, me'atzeret v'ad hechag, from שבועות Shavuos until- until סוכות,
Sukkos, right? And that's the harvest period.
מביא וקורא. meivi v'korei. That's the true time of שמחה simcha and
that's when you bring ביכורים bikurim and you do the whole מקרא
ביכורים, Mikra Bikurim, right? And you say, you know, ועתה הבאתי את
ראשית פרי האדמה, v'ata heiveiti et reishit pri ha'adama, which is a
whole declaration of joy and שמחה. simcha. That's at the time of
שמחה, simcha, the time of harvest from שבועות Shavuos till סוכות. Sukkos.
סוכות Sukkos is when you gather everything in, the harvest is done.
Although סוכות Sukkos is also, you know, זמן שמחתנו, zman simchateinu, because
it's maybe the apex of that. Okay, by the way, the reason
you start at שבועות Shavuos is because- because you can only bring
the new grain which or the new fruit, the new produce, after-
after, you know, after the שתי הלחם shtei halechem is brought on
שבועות. Shavuos. The שתי הלחם shtei halechem on שבועות Shavuos is- is
considered- it's called ביכורים. bikurim. It is the first offering in the
בית המקדש of the new produce. Okay, other than the עומר. omer.
And therefore, the bringing of the new produce begins only after שבועות.
Shavuos. So it starts after שבועות Shavuos and it goes to- to
סוכות. Sukkos. מהחג ועד חנוכה. me'hechag v'ad Chanukah. It is interesting you
should think it goes through סוכות, Sukkos, but anyway, from סוכות Sukkos
till חנוכה, Chanukah, מביא ואינו קורא. meivi v'eino korei. You can still
bring but you don't make the declaration because it's no longer really
the זמן שמחה. zman simcha. And by חנוכה Chanukah it's already the
winter whatever and clearly you're in a different season.
So anyway, did they even have חנוכה? Chanukah? רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
Yeah, sure. Yeah, yeah, because חנוכה Chanukah was, yeah, yeah.
So anyway, but so the basic answer is yes, ביכורים bikurim are
linked to שמחה simcha in terms of the time of the year,
but in an- ironically not to lead to the הלכה halacha that
an אונן onen wouldn't be able to eat from it. Okay.
Even though it says it
specifically there, it's not דאורייתא. d'oraisa. I understand. I understand. So end
of the day, we'll end here. The end of the day, what
have we seen? We've seen that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that-
that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and ביכורים bikurim can be eaten- you-
even though it's מותר mutar to eat, there's a question whether you
could be יוצא מצה yotzei matzah with it. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose HaGlili excludes מעשר שני Maaser Sheni because it can't be eaten
באוני. b'oni. This contrast of- that מצה matzah cannot, you know, the
contrast of מצה matzah to this idea of שמחה. simcha. מצה matzah
has to still represent this- possibility- this idea of affliction. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is okay, although רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva agrees ביכורים bikurim no, because it has to have this
potential of being able to be eaten everywhere, which is somewhat true
by מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, not true by ביכורים. bikurim. And again,
that's also ironic, a little ironic, because you know- the paradigm of
eating מצה matzah is בירושלים, b'Yerushalayim, and nevertheless we're saying you're not
יוצא yotzei with מצה that cannot be eaten outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
So we'll end here. Question? Yes, Charlie.
The restriction of bringing ביכורים bikurim after חנוכה, Chanukah, that's got to
be a rabbinic prohibition?
Because of חנוכה? Chanukah?
Because חנוכה Chanukah didn't exist?
Yeah, but no. I mean, in theory, you could say that it's
about the time period of the year. It's not specifically the status
of חנוכה. Chanukah. You know, their understanding would be, you know, fine,
so say- you know, say at the beginning of the winter. You
know, it's- so- I mean, it might be the specific identification with-