Today's daf is קג, Kuf Gimmel, we've been discussing the issue about
if somebody was eating שלוש סעודות Shalosh Seudos and then they had
to בענטש bench and say קידוש, Kiddush, do they say it on
one כוס kos or two כוסות? kosos? And the גמרא Gemara's conclusion
is that ideally you say it on two because אין עושין מצות
חבילות חבילות, ein osin mitzvos chavilos chavilos, you don't bundle up מצוות.
mitzvos. Now of course sometimes we say something of the opposite, you
know something used for one מצוה mitzvah do another מצוה mitzvah and
we've pointed out particularly the relevance of this when dealing with the
issue of a כוס kos because a כוס kos gives sort of
weight to the particular act and is very much about sort of
identifying the status of the act. So there's a real sort of
conflict of identity, you know does this... is this a כוס kos
of ברכת המזון Birkas HaMazon or is it a כוס kos of
קידוש? Kiddush? And that's really part of the issue here, which is
why the גמרא Gemara says that when they're doing similar functions although
interestingly even somewhat opposite functions like הבדלה Havdalah and קידוש, Kiddush, הבדלה
Havdalah for let's say שבת Shabbos and קידוש Kiddush for יום טוב
Yom Tov when it's יום טוב Yom Tov follows שבת, Shabbos, but
there they're a type of a similar function, distinguishing קודש kodesh and
חול chol although in different directions, that there you actually can double
up and do double up, you should double up and that's the
discussion we're about to get to. But when they're very distinct functions
like ברכת המזון Birkas HaMazon and קידוש, Kiddush, you're supposed to use
separate כוסות. kosos. And the time you would only use the same
is if you only had one. Now the question was raised that
that's not what we tend to do, you know שולס shuls that
have שלוש סעודות Shalosh Seudos make קידוש Kiddush often will make ברכת
המזון Birkas HaMazon on a כוס kos and then use that כוס
kos for הבדלה Havdalah even though they could have easily could have
get another כוס יין. kos yayin. So interestingly I looked it up
and the הלכה halacha in the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch actually exactly
follows what we had, you know, what we had read. Here's the
הלכה halacha in the שולחן
ערוך.
Shulchan
Aruch.
It's... one minute... hold
on... it's רצ"ט, Reish Tzadik Tes, hold on. Yeah,
here it is. רצ"ט א. Reish Tzadik Tes Alef. כשהיה אוכל וחשכה
שאמרנו שאין צריך
להפסיק גומר סעודתו. Keshehayah ochel vechashachah she'amarnu she'ein tzarich lehafsik gomer seudosu.
Right, not like the גמרא Gemara said earlier that you're מפסיק mafsik
when you're eating a שלוש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos, you're מפסיק mafsik and
פורס מפה poreis mapah for if you're eating on Friday but not
if you're eating late שבת Shabbos afternoon. You're גומר סעודתו, gomer seudosu,
מברך ברכת המזון על הכוס, mevareich Birkas HaMazon al hakos, ואחר כך
מבדיל עליו. ve'achar kach mavdil alav. אם יש לו שני כוסות מברך
ברכת המזון על אחד ומבדיל על אחר.
Im yesh lo shenei
kosos mevareich Birkas HaMazon al echad umavdil al acher.
Exactly like we said. So I did not get a chance to
investigate further but at least the מפרשים meforshim exactly there on the
שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah and others do
not have a comment on the מנהג minhag דווקא davka to always
use one. So it is true. There is, I've seen it a
lot. So it is interesting that I even remember from my days
at ישיבה yeshiva they did that, you know. So it is interesting
given that the גמרא Gemara really says when you have two use
two.
Okay so is it because of the כוס kos or the issue
of the content?
That's the pull of the content. No, the content. So that's true,
meaning it is more about like that same glass of wine. Now
if after you've drunk from it and you refill it, you know,
does that address the פגום, pagum, at what stage is it considered
a different כוס? kos? But here we're not talking about the physical
כוס. kos. If you drank it and rinsed it out and used
more wine, nobody would question that that's two כוסות. kosos. Right.
Okay so you know when you say I'll have another glass of
wine, you don't expect the person to bring you out another glass.
So it's the same idea. All right so now we are discussing
this issue of bundling when you do bundle when קידוש Kiddush and
הבדלה Havdalah come together, and what do you say when שבת Shabbos
leads into יום טוב Yom Tov and you have to make הבדלה
Havdalah for יום טוב Yom Tov and הבדלה Havdalah for שבת Shabbos
and קידוש Kiddush for יום טוב. Yom Tov. What order do you
do, how do you bundle it together? So we pick up with
that at the bottom of קב עמוד ב. Kuf Beis Amud Beis.
גופא. Gufa. יום טוב שחל להיות אחר השבת Yom Tov shechal lihyos
achar haShabbos for יום טוב Yom Tov happens after שבת Shabbos because
if it was שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov you make
הבדלה. Havdalah. יום טוב Yom Tov and שבת Shabbos not because you
make הבדלה Havdalah when you're going for a higher קדושה kedushah to
either חול chol or to a lesser קדושה. kedushah. So you have
to make הבדלה Havdalah for שבת Shabbos and קידוש Kiddush for הבדלה.
Havdalah. So רבא אמר יקנ"ה, Rava amar Yaknah, ייין קידוש נר הבדלה.
Yayin Kiddush Ner Havdalah. So יין Yayin and קידוש, Kiddush, that's your
classic קידוש, Kiddush, and then נר הבדלה. Ner Havdalah. You don't make
another יין yayin because you made it and so then you basically
saying you do קידוש Kiddush and then הבדלה Havdalah without repeating יין.
yayin. Why no בשמים? besamim? We mentioned that yesterday because although there's
not a concept of נשמה יתירה neshamah yeseirah which is the reason
why you make on בשמים besamim on מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos and
not מוצאי יום טוב, Motzei Yom Tov, so there's not a concept
of נשמה יתירה neshamah yeseirah on יום טוב Yom Tov because the
idea is you know your whole this extra soul... spirituality departs from
you, you need to be revived by the בשמים, besamim, that's only
a concept on שבת, Shabbos, not on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Nevertheless,
the fact that שבת Shabbos is leading into יום טוב, Yom Tov,
the whole שמחה simcha of יום טוב Yom Tov substitutes for the
need of בשמים. besamim. So there's not going to be בשמים besamim
when you have this שבת Shabbos going into יום טוב, Yom Tov,
but so you basically according to רב, Rav, you first do קידוש
Kiddush and then you do הבדלה. Havdalah. And שמואל אמר, Shmuel amar,
שמואל Shmuel says the reverse, ינה"ק, Yanhak, יין, yayin, נר, ner, הבדלה,
Havdalah, again no בשמים besamim as we said. You first do הבדלה
Havdalah and then ק', kuf, and then קידוש. Kiddush. You don't need
to do יין yayin again, you've done יין. yayin. So the question
is, do you do קידוש Kiddush and then הבדלה Havdalah or הבדלה
Havdalah and then קידוש? Kiddush? So of course שמואל Shmuel makes sense,
שמואל Shmuel is chronological, you end the previous day before you start
the next day. Why רב Rav says you make קידוש Kiddush first
is not clear. As I said, the רשב"ם Rashbam says either it's
just a question of importance, קידוש Kiddush is more important than הבדלה.
Havdalah. It's more important to sanctify something than to end something's sanctity.
Or because of this idea that we always try to delay הבדלה
Havdalah even somewhat symbolically just a few seconds, to show how reluctant
we are for the שבת Shabbos or for the קדושה kedusha of
the day to depart, as I pointed out like why in שול
shul on חנוכה Chanukah on שבת, Shabbos, you know, you first do
light חנוכה Chanukah candles and then מוצאי שבת Motzei Shabbos and then
you do הבדלה Havdalah even though, you know, just to show we
try to postpone, we're not eager for שבת Shabbos to end. Of
course, שבת Shabbos is over, you couldn't light חנוכה Chanukah candles otherwise,
but symbolically try to postpone הבדלה Havdalah a little bit. So yeah.
What about תדיר ושאינו תדיר? tadir u'sheino tadir? תדיר קודם tadir kodem
is right after.
That's a good point, and that the הבדלה Havdalah of שבת Shabbos
is more תדיר, tadir, so that would even be more weight for
שמואל. Shmuel. Like קידוש Kiddush of הבדלה Havdalah is much less תדיר.
tadir. So it's רב's Rav position. We're going to basically פסקן pasken
a variation of רב's Rav position, we're going to פסקן pasken רב's
Rav position, but שמואל Shmuel I think to me and I assume
to most of us is the one that makes more sense. Okay,
so those are those two positions. Simple question of קידוש Kiddush then
הבדלה, Havdalah, הבדלה Havdalah then קידוש. Kiddush. Now we get to more
interesting sort of potential combinations. רבא אמר, Raba amar, ינה"ק, Yanhak, יהנ"ק,
Yehanak, I don't know, יין, yayin, הבדלה, Havdalah, נר ner and קידוש.
Kiddush. So we get that he basically, meaning the first question is
which comes first, הבדלה Havdalah or קידוש. Kiddush. So he basically is
in שמואל's Shmuel camp, הבדלה Havdalah comes first, הבדלה Havdalah and then
קידוש. Kiddush. So why did the נר ner get removed and put
after the הבדלה Havdalah between the הבדלה Havdalah and the קידוש Kiddush
as opposed to where it normally belongs, which is before the הבדלה?
Havdalah?
So the רשב"ם Rashbam basically says that he wants to have a
separation, he doesn't want הבדלה Havdalah to be immediately juxtaposed, you know,
abutting קידוש. Kiddush. Because they are somewhat sort of working in opposite
directions. One says we're leaving קדושה kedusha and the other says we're
entering קדושה. kedusha. So therefore he wants to create, it's like the
קריאת הכתובה krias hakesuba between קידושין kiddushin and נישואין. nisuin. So you
have נר, ner, you have יין yayin and הבדלה, Havdalah, but you
don't want to go straight from saying המבדיל בין קודש לחול hamavdil
bein kodesh lechol to מקדש ישראל. mekadesh Yisrael. Okay, or not המבדיל
בין קודש לחול, hamavdil bein kodesh lechol, המבדיל בין קודש לקודש. bein
kodesh lekodesh. So you have נר, ner, which is a little bit
of a break, allows you to put that aside, take a break
and then transition into the קידוש. Kiddush. So he basically is in
the שמואל Shmuel camp but he needs a little bit of a
breather between the two. לוי אמר, Levi amar, now לוי Levi says
קני"ה. Kanya. So he's basically in the רב Rav camp, קידוש Kiddush
comes first, קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה, Havdalah, but then this is bizarre,
right? יין yayin and נר ner in the middle, and like what's
the whole order here going on? So he basically says that he's,
this is the רשב"ם's Rashbam explanation, that the concern of לוי Levi
is, he's in רב's Rav camp but if you had יין yayin
anywhere earlier it would seem like it's connected to קידוש Kiddush and
not to הבדלה. Havdalah. Okay, so therefore we need, right, it's sort
of like it's obvious that if you're going to have קידוש, Kiddush,
קידוש Kiddush comes with יין yayin and anything that would separate it,
since הבדלה's Havdalah coming at the end, anything that would separate it
would seem like you did הבדלה Havdalah without יין. yayin. So we
need to have יין yayin right before הבדלה Havdalah and even though
normally we have יין, yayin, נר, ner, הבדלה, Havdalah, but if we
did that יין yayin would be juxtaposed to קידוש Kiddush and you
would assume it's the יין yayin of קידוש. Kiddush. So because קידוש
Kiddush is coming first, the יין yayin is going to be assumed
to be a part of it unless you postpone it as much
as possible. So קני"ה Kanya is קידוש? Kiddush? Yes, but that nobody
is doubting the fact that the יין yayin is going on the
קידוש. Kiddush. Okay, the קידוש Kiddush comes first, we always assume that
the יין yayin will be associated with it. But if you didn't
have יין yayin juxtaposed with הבדלה, Havdalah, people would assume הבדלה Havdalah
was completely separate and not related to יין. yayin. Okay, that's how
he explains it. רבנן אמרי, Rabbanan amri, קינ"ה. Kina. And the rabbis
say קידוש, Kiddush, יין, yayin, נר, ner, הבדלה. Havdalah. So again in
the רב Rav camp that קידוש Kiddush comes first, but then not
with this concern that you need to juxtapose יין yayin and הבדלה.
Havdalah. קידוש Kiddush comes first and then you do יין, yayin, נר,
ner, הבדלה, Havdalah, a classic הבדלה. Havdalah. We moved the יין yayin
away from the beginning by now having the יין yayin after the
קידוש, Kiddush, right? רב Rav said יקנ"ה, Yakna, you do the normal
standard קידוש, Kiddush, יין yayin and קידוש. Kiddush. He says no, we
to make the יין yayin more going on both we put it
after the קידוש. Kiddush. So since it comes after the קידוש Kiddush
it both goes more on the קידוש Kiddush and on the הבדלה.
Havdalah. And once it's in the middle then you can have the
normal. A variation again of רב, Rav, and a question about this
issue of how to make the יין Yayin most relevant to both
as... מר בריה דרבינא Mar breh de-Ravina אמר amar נקי"ה Nekiah or
נקי"ה: Nakiah: נר, Ner, קידוש, Kiddush, יין, Yayin, הבדלה. Havdalah.
So he again is in the רב Rav camp; קידוש Kiddush comes
first, and in order for the יין Yayin to equally go on
the קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה, Havdalah, he wants the יין Yayin to
be juxtaposed immediately to both. So he has to have
קי"ה: Kiah: קידוש, Kiddush, יין, Yayin, הבדלה. Havdalah. That for him is
the only way that יין Yayin will equally go on the קידוש
Kiddush and the הבדלה. Havdalah. Once you're having that, since נר Ner
always comes before הבדלה, Havdalah, he put נר Ner way at the
beginning. Yes.
Could we reclarrify
the centrality of יין? Yayin? In other words, if you say that
it's associated with some form of עונג Oneg or שמחת שבת Simchas
Shabbos and the start of שבת Shabbos meal, why would you have
that at הבדלה? Havdalah?
It's not as much עונג, Oneg, it's not meal-based like you do
it, you know, I mean certainly our practice, for example, is that
you also do it at a ברית, Bris, under the חופה. Chuppah.
I mean the basically the reason the גמרא Gemara says, although it
is true the basic two places you do have יין Yayin required
in the
גמרא, Gemara, or three if you count it depends how you count,
is קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה Havdalah and then also ברכת המזון. Birkat
Hamazon. So ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon is definitely with the meal, קידוש
Kiddush we know is about a meal, הבדלה Havdalah less so. And
the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that the יין Yayin is because of
like עונג. Oneg. The גמרא Gemara says אינו אומרים שירה אלא על
היין. eno omrim shirah ella al hayayin. From the קרבנות, Korbanot, when
they did the ניסוך היין, nisuch hayayin, the לויים, leviyim, you know,
they did the שירה. shirah. So and there it seems to actually
be a way of saying that when you do some type of...
so you could say specifically דברי שבח. divrei shevach. Of course, we
do plenty of דברי שבח divrei shevach in our דאווענען davening and
in our liturgy that we don't require יין. Yayin. So I think
it's a type of a דברי שבח divrei shevach that we want
to give sort of ritual weight is the way I would just
explain it, you know, to make it a momentous significant thing. I
would not define it... so if you want to say give it
an element of שמחה, simcha, but more to give it like the
שירה shirah and the שבח, shevach, you know, some significant weight.
So just finally so that I really contextualize it because the weight
is...
it might not be evident to us anymore but the weight is
actually the weight of מקדש. Mikdash. In other words, if it's original
antecedence location, the ניסוך היין, nisuch hayayin, so it's a transposition of
that.
Yes. So I mean right, it's a... yeah, I mean that is
definitely true seeing how the גמרא Gemara appropriates certain מקדש Mikdash realities
and uses them within liturgy and as the sort of basis. How
much that remains in our consciousness is a question.
But my thinking is why wouldn't you want to finish one before
you start the other? When יום טוב Yom Tov is finished to
say הבדלה Havdalah and then do the קידוש.
Kiddush. I agree with you. שמואל Shmuel makes the most sense. Finish
one before you start the other. I'm with you, but most of
the אמוראים Amoraim seem to be in the רב's Rav camp, which
is
that first you do the קידוש Kiddush and then הבדלה. Havdalah. Maybe
also if you did the הבדלה Havdalah and then the קידוש Kiddush
in that one second of transition between the two, you're sort of
you're left without either. So maybe they want to make sure that
there's some overlap. But I agree of course with דב, Dov, that
makes more sense, but most are in רב's Rav camp. Look, the
other thing that I thought... that I thought דב Dov was going
to say was that... too many דבs Dov here, was that... was
that why... why does it matter where you made the ברכה berakha
of יין? Yayin? The fact that you're holding the כוס יין kos
Yayin should be enough because if you think about it, the example
I gave you the other day is, you know, if you were
in the middle of a סעודה seudah and you did a פורש
מפה ומקדש poresh mappah u-mekaddesh and you happened to be drinking wine
during that סעודה, seudah, you don't do בורא פרי הגפן, borei peri
hagafen, you just do קידוש Kiddush holding a כוס יין kos Yayin
without the בורא פרי הגפן. borei peri hagafen. So... but you're making
the ברכה berakha
already...
right, that's true, but once you're making the ברכה, berakha, it's true,
it could exist without it, but once you're having it, that obviously
will have an impact in how what its identity is, how it's
grouped, what it's identified with and therefore you have all of these
variations that want to figure out the best way to make the
יין Yayin relate both to the קידוש Kiddush and the הבדלה Havdalah
within the camp of רב Rav that we're going to do the
קידוש Kiddush first. These are all variations of רב. Rav. Okay, so
let's take a look, one more opinion. מרתא אמר משמיה דרבי יהושע.
Marta amar mishmei de-Rabbi Yehoshua. Now מרתא Marta says in the name
of רבי יהושע: Rabbi Yehoshua: נהי"ק. Nihak. Who is מרתא? Marta? I
have no idea. נר, Ner, יין, Yayin, הבדלה, Havdalah, קידוש. Kiddush. Okay,
so here you've got here who do you have? You've got obviously
you've got somebody finally in שמואל's Shmuel camp, הבדלה Havdalah preceding קידוש.
Kiddush. Why do you reverse the order and do נר Ner and
then
יין? Yayin?
So... so... in a regular מוצאי שבת Motza'ei Shabbos you do נר
Ner first also?
Yeah, but first you do יין. Yayin. Why did he reverse יין
Yayin and נר, Ner, right?
No, I'm saying...
you normally we do יין, Yayin, נר, Ner, הבדלה. Havdalah. I mean...
so I'm wondering if he'd say like...
oh, no, no, no, this is all just for this.
Okay, so... so... hold on, let me just check the רשב"ם Rashbam
what he says here. So
do
you
have one for the נהי"ק? Nihak?
Yes. Over here.
No, he has the נהיק *nahik*.
Yes, נהיק *nahik*.
That was where was נהיק *nahik*? Oh, he had נהיק *nahik* instead
of
ניהק
*nihak*.
He had נהיק
*nahik* for this משום
רבי Rebbe יהושע *mishum Rabbi Yehoshua*.
משום רבי יהושע בן חנניה *mishum Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Chananya* נהיק *nahik*. Yeah, he had a totally different one.
He
had a נהיק *nahik*. He doesn't have a ניהק *nihak*. So can
we figure this one out? What would be the reason for ניהק
*nihak*? So he has הבדלה Havdalah, *havdalah* coming before קידוש Kiddush *kiddush*.
I guess he want... the logic I assume would be is that
you want to have the יין yayin *yain* not be separated from
the קידוש Kiddush *kiddush*. If you did ינהק *yanhak*, then יין *yain*
would be at the very opposite ends of the קידוש Kiddush *kiddush*
and again it's a similar concern in the reverse. It would be
a you know within the camp of שמואל *Shmuel*, הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah*
precedes קידוש Kiddush *kiddush* but still a concern of how do you
get יין *yain* to be related to both. So he wants יין
*yain* to precede הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah* as it usually does but he
wants it to be at least a little more related to קידוש
*kiddush* so he reverses the order of the נר Ner, *neir* and
the יין *yain*. Okay, so all of these are variations of either
first you decide are you in רב Rav. *Rav*'s camp or שמואל
*Shmuel*'s camp and then you have to figure out how to get
the יין *yain* connected to both within what parameters. Okay. שלחו ליה
אבוה דשמואל לרבי *Shalchu lei avuh deShmuel leRabbi*. So the father of
שמואל *Shmuel* sent to רבי *Rabbi*. ילמדנו רבינו *Yelamdeinu Rabbeinu*. So this
is already in you know the end of the tannaic period. Let
our master teach us because שמואל *Shmuel*, רב Rav. *Rav* and שמואל
*Shmuel* are like first generation אמוראים *Amoraim*. So here שמואל *Shmuel*'s father
was sending to רבי *Rabbi*, end of the תנאים *Tannaim*. ילמדנו רבינו
*Yelamdeinu Rabbeinu*, סדר הבדלות havdalos? היך *Seder havdalot heich*? How do you
do הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah*? Meaning how do you do הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah*
when it's הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah* and קידוש *kiddush*? שלח ליה *Shalach lei*,
he sent back to him, כך אמר amar, רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
שאמר משום אביו שאמר משום רבי יהושע בן חנניה *Kach amar Rabbi
Yishmael berabbi Yossi she'amar mishum aviv she'amar mishum Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*.
So now we get a tannaic opinion. Until now it's all been
a amoraic opinion. נהיק *Nahik*. So נר Ner הבדלה Havdalah יין קידוש
*neir havdalah yain kiddush*. So again there it's a שמואל *Shmuel* idea,
הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah* precedes, and the יין *yain* comes exactly in between
הבדלה Havdalah, *havdalah* and קידוש *kiddush* so it equally goes on both.
Okay. אמר רבי חנניה משום רבי יהושע בן חנניה *Amar Rabbi Chananya
mishum Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*. So רבי חנניה *Rabbi Chananya* said in
the name of רבי יהושע בן חנניה *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*. Maybe
it was רבי יהושע *Rabbi
Yehoshua*'s son.
אמר רבי חנניה *Amar Rabbi Chananya*, משל דרבי יהושע בן חנניה *mashal
deRabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya*. What is the what type of a משל
*mashal* explains this idea of הבדלה Havdalah, *havdalah* preceding? Sort of the
whole שמואל *Shmuel* idea. Here you go, Joe, he's exactly going to
explain the logic why הבדלה Havdalah *havdalah* should precede. למלך שיוצא *Lemelech
sheyotzei*, the king is going out. שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos* is the king.
We often call it the queen, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually
in more than one place calls שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* the king. Okay,
so the king if the king goes out, you're having the king
visit you then the king leaves, ואפרכוס נכנס *ve'aparchos nichnas*, and then
like the governor comes in. Okay, so the king is leaving and
the governor is coming. So what do you do when you're having
that happen? So what would you do? מלוים את המלך *Melavin et
hamelech*, first you attend to the king. First you accompany the king
out of your house to the gate or wherever, ואחר כך *ve'achar
kach* יוצאים לקראת אפרכוס *yotzim likrat aparchos*. And then you go out
to welcome in the governor. Okay, so to welcome in the senator
or the governor, whoever it is. Okay, so
therefore, yes, you see שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* out before you welcome יום
טוב Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. Maybe it's first, it's the one that
was already there but also there's a difference of it's also weightier,
שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* is the מלך *melech*. So you attend to the
מלך *melech* first before you bring in יום טוב Yom Tov. *Yom
Tov*. Of course that could exactly be what רב Rav, *Rav*'s problem
is, is that that just all the more downgrades the significance of
the יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* that's entering. I don't know,
but anyway because you would think get rid of שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*,
you know, completely finish it and now you focus on יום טוב
Yom Tov. *Yom Tov*. So you sort of really do understand the
persuasive you know position of שמואל *Shmuel*. Okay, so let's see מאי
הוי עלה *mai hava ala*? What was the פשט *pshat*? You know
basically which comes first, קידוש *kiddush* or הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah*? And also
how does the יין *yain* factor in? So אביי Abaye: אמר יקזנ"ה
Yakzneh *Abaye amar yakznah*. So אביי *Abaye* says יין קידוש זמן Yayin,
Kiddush, Zman, נר Ner הבדלה Havdalah. *yain kiddush zman neir havdalah*. So
again like רב Rav *Rav*, קידוש *kiddush* first, then זמן Zman. *zman*,
because we forgot זמן Zman *zman*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said before
we had been talking about שביעי של פסח Shevi'i shel Pesach *Shevii
shel Pesach* where there was no זמן Zman *zman*. So now we
have to פסקן *pasken* the previous debate and also discuss when do
you say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *shehecheyanu*. So אביי *Abaye* says basically straight like
שמואל *Shmuel*, יין קידוש זמן Zman, *yain kiddush zman*, that's a full
קידוש *kiddush*, נר Ner הבדלה Havdalah. *neir havdalah*. So that's a I
mean I mean it's a full רב Rav *Rav*. Like a straight
רב Rav, *Rav*. קידוש *kiddush* and then הבדלה Havdalah *havdalah*. Fine. ורבא
אמר יקנה"ז Yaknahaz. *VeRava amar yaknaz*,
which is how we ruled by the way. יין קידוש נר Ner
הבדלה Havdalah זמן Zman *yain kiddush neir havdalah zman*. So it's again
like רב Rav *Rav* but he postpones the זיין *zayin*, the זמן
Zman. *zman* till the very end. Okay, which is a little bit
which is a little bit
strange. Why postpone it till the very end? So let me just
see what the רשב"ם Rashbam, *Rashbam* says.
It's a total wrap around. Right, you bracket it. You sort of
bracketing הבדלה Havdalah. *havdalah*.
Oh no, the way the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* just says it is
because we always say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu *shehecheyanu* at the end. Whenever we're
saying
קידוש *kiddush*. right, and then we say שהחיינו. Shehecheyanu So therefore we
want to keep שהחיינו even if it's a modified קידוש of הבדלה,
Havdalah we just keep it at the end even though it doesn't
go on the הבדלה. Havdalah, What were you saying though?
Kiddush just goes- Yes,
but why does it not- but again the logic is more אביי:
יין, קידוש, זמן, Zman right, and then הבדלה. Havdalah. No? But maybe,
look, maybe the problem would be that then if you're following a
רבא Rava thing, the problem is that you end with, you know,
הבדלה. Havdalah You end with downplaying יום טוב. Yom Tov. It hasn't
ended with focusing, so going back to שהחיינו restates the significance of
the new זמן. Zman So I guess that makes sense.
Yeah, the זמן only relates to יום טוב. Yom Tov, Whereas זמן
relates to this specific moment in time, which includes the transitional space
between יום טוב and שבת.
Yeah, there's no evidence to that. I mean the גמרא Gemara for
example said on שביעי של פסח you wouldn't make זמן, right? That's
exactly that case where you're having the same transition. The זמן is
about the קדושה Kedusha of יום טוב.
Right, you're already making זמן. Right. Because you have יום טוב. And
now what is- what should be in your mind when you're making
this ברכה? Berakhah? Is it this specific זמן or is it only
related- I see.
So you might as well have the concept of שהחיינו once you're
already saying it broadened that context and include the reality of הבדלה.
Havdalah.
It's true it's a distinct moment.
Right. That's true, doesn't happen too frequently. Right. Okay, I hear. So
that's the way we rule. So basically קידוש comes first and then
הבדלה. Havdalah. Opposite I think of what most of us would have
said. And then זמן comes at the end, either because it always
comes at the end, or because we said it's a way of
ending with the positive, the new aspect of יום טוב, or as
David is saying, it also relates to the הבדלה Havdalah. part as
well. והלכתא כרבא. V'hilkhata k'Rava. And we rule like רבא, Rava, and
that's what we do. יקנה"ז. Yaknahaz. Okay. So I gotta tell you,
with all of these, with all of these, you know, little- what
are they called? Acronyms, right, you know, I can't remember all the
different possibilities, but I do remember יקנה"ז. Yaknahaz. So
I don't know- Yeah, I know. But also- so anyway, so rather
than having to look in a סידור, Siddur, I just go through
יקנה"ז. Yaknahaz.
Whenever- I know קני"ה Kanyeh or נקי"ה Nikyeh sounds easier to remember
than- That's why it won.
Oh, because it was easier to pronounce. For branding. Exactly. Right. יקזנ"ה
doesn't- doesn't like- doesn't like fall off the tongue like יקנה"ז. Okay.
Anyway, רב הונא בר יהודה איקלע לבי רבא. Rav Huna bar Yehuda
ikla l'bei Rava. So רב הונא בר יהודה- Rav Huna bar Yehuda
now we're going to have some like interesting stories, and actually it's
going to be interesting, the ארמית Aramaic even seems to change a
little bit in the- in the following discussion, like a little bit
more of the vernacular. Let's take a look. רב הונא בר יהודה
איקלע לבי רבא. Rav Huna bar Yehuda ikla l'bei Rava. So רב
הונא בר יהודה Rav Huna bar Yehuda came to the house of
רבא. Rava. אייתו לקמיה Aitu l'kamei and it was- שבת he came
for שלש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos, and then they were done.
Whatever, forget שלש סעודות, Shalosh Seudos, they came to learn, and then
it was time for הבדלה. Havdalah, אייתו לקמייהו מאור ובשמים. Aitu l'kameihu
maor u'besamim. So now, the question now that we're talking about הבדלה,
Havdala. what order do you do? אש Esh or בשמים Besamim first?
בריך רבא אבשמים ברישא והדר אמאור. Barikh Rava a'besamim be'reisha ve'hadar a'maor.
He did בשמים Besamim first and then מאור, Maor, which is what
we do, right? We do יין, בשמים, נר, הבדלה. Yayin, Besamim, Ner,
Havdalah.
So he did בשמים Besamim first. והדר מאור. Ve'hadar maor. אמר ליה,
Amar leih,
so רב הונא בר יהודה Rav Huna bar Yehuda said to him,
והא בין בית שמאי ובין בית הלל מאור ברישא. Ve'ha bein Beit
Shammai u'vein Beit Hillel maor be'reisha. One minute, we know there's a
debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai about
הבדלה, Havdala but they both agree that you say בורא מאורי האש
Borei Meorei Ha-esh first. והדר בשמים. Ve'hadar besamim. ומהי? U'mai hi? What's
the debate? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in the משנה Mishnah in ברכות:
Berakhot: בית שמאי אומרים נר ומזון ובשמים והבדלה. Beit Shammai omerim ner
u'mazon u'besamim ve'havdalah.
So now we are talking about מזון, Mazon, ברכת המזון. Birkat Ha-mazon.
So now we're talking about the scenario we talked about when you
have only one כוס Kos and you're doing both ברכת המזון Birkat
Ha-mazon and הבדלה Havdala? on the same כוס. Kos. And how do
you wrap those together? So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says: first נר,
ner. then ברכת המזון, Birkat Ha-mazon, then בשמים Besamim and הבדלה. Havdala
Why to stick ברכת המזון Birkat Ha-mazon in the middle? I don't
know. I should mention, though, one thing that is important to appreciate
about moving נר ner around or בשמים Besamim around is that you
can make the ברכה Berakhah בורא מאורי האש Borei Meorei Ha-esh independent
of the הבדלה. havdala You can make בורא מיני בשמים Borei Minei
Besamim independent of
הבדלה. The הבדלה על הכוס al ha-kos specifically is the ברכה Berakhah
of המבדיל. Ha-mavdil. The other ברכות, Berakhot, and if for some reason
you didn't have an אש Esh around or you didn't have בשמים
Besamim around, right, you could make it later if you made הבדלה
without them. And there's even discussion about how critical is it to
make sure that you find בשמים Besamim if it's hard to get
בשמים Besamim and so on. Right. So anyway, with that in mind,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says: do the נר ner first. Again, still
unclear why to have- to have ברכת המזון Birkat Ha-mazon interrupt it,
but nevertheless, you know, at least we understand it's not such an
integral part of the הבדלה. So do the נר ner, first.
And then ברכת המזון, בשמים, והבדלה. Birkat Ha-mazon, besamim, ve'havdalah. ובית הלל
אומרים
נר ובשמים ומזון והבדלה. U'veit Hillel omerim ner u'besamim u'mazon ve'havdalah. No,
you do נר ner, and בשמים, Besamim, both parts of the הבדלה
that aren't הבדלה, then ברכת המזון Birkat Ha-mazon and הבדלה. Part of
the reason here might be similar to all of our discussions before:
you want the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri Ha-gefen that you're going
to make at הבדלה to relate also to the ברכת המזון. Birkat
Ha-mazon. So how are we going to get the ברכת המזון... Birkat
Ha-mazon... on a little bit incorporated into the הבדלה. Do we put
it one step in or two steps in? And the more you
get ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon incorporated, the more you're pushing away other
elements of the הבדלה. So that seems to be the debate of
בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. They all agree
that the basic order is מאור, Meor, בשמים, Besamim, הבדלה. We need
to bring the ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon somewhat in to get the
יין on it. How much in do you bring it? So he
says, but either way they both agree that מאור meor comes first.
So עני רבא בתראי, ani Rava batrei, so רבא Rava responded, notice
that's funny language, עני רבא בתראי, ani Rava batrei, like that's actually
a type of language you find sometimes in מדרש, Midrash, like one,
you know, one person
says this, and then עני בתראי, ani batrei, and then he responded
with a different approach to the מדרש. Midrash. So it's interesting some
of the Aramaic in the section we're going to be reading. עני
רבא בתראי, ani Rava batrei, so רבא Rava responded and אמר, זו
דברי רבי מאיר, zu divrei Rabbi Meir, yeah,
but that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's take on the debate of בית
הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. אבל רבי יהודה אומר,
aval Rabbi Yehuda omer, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda has a different
take on their debate. לא נחלקו בית שמאי ובית הלל על המזון
שהוא בתחילה ועל הבדלה שהיא בסוף. lo necheleku Beit Shammai u-Beit Hillel
al hamazon she-hu bit-tchilah ve-al Havdalah she-hi besof. No, that's wrong, you
got the debate completely wrong. בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי
Beit Shammai both agree ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon comes first. Makes sense.
And yeah, you do it all by itself, none of this weird
mixing, and then you do הבדלה, even if you're doing one כוס
kos on both. על מה נחלקו? al mah necheleku? What was the
debate? על המאור ועל הבשמים, al hameor ve-al habesamim, the order of
אש esh and בשמים. besamim. בית שמאי אומרים מאור ואחר כך בשמים
ובית הלל אומרים בשמים ואחר כך מאור. Beit Shammai omrim meor ve-achar
kach besamim u-Beit Hillel omrim besamim ve-achar kach meor.
So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says מאור meor and then בשמים, besamim,
and בית הלל Beit Hillel says בשמים besamim and מאור. meor. ואמר
רבי יוחנן נהגו עם כבית הלל ואליבא דרבי יהודה. ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan
nagu am ke-Beit Hillel ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda. And we take רבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yehuda's take on בית, Beit, on that debate, and we and
we take the approach of בית הלל Beit Hillel and that's why
we do בשמים besamim first and then נר. Now interestingly there's no
discussion even in the רשב"ם, Rashbam I mean there's no discussion before
what the reasons are, but the רשב"ם Rashbam provided it. There's no
discussion here what the question is for the order. Let me though
tell you what the purpose of the נר is cause people often
confuse that, you know, I think get that wrong and it's important
to talk about that cause we'll also see something how it ties
in in a minute. You know people assume that the basic reason
for the נר מוצאי שבת motza'ei Shabbat is because you couldn't, you
know, make fire on שבת, so it's part of what distinguishes בין
קודש לחול, ben kodesh le-chol, now you're making fire, you couldn't make
fire before. But actually the גמרא Gemara emphasizes that the reason for
the נר, it's more about אש esh than it is about נר,
and it's because that was the first creative act, right, we had
that before of אדם הראשון. Adam HaRishon. I sent out that whole
little clip from Tom Hanks, and what was what was the name
of that movie? Castaway? Castaway? Yeah, yeah, yeah, and he makes fire
and whatever, the amazing it was an amazing clip. Anyway, so you
know, the fact that, you know, fire was the first profound human
creative act that, you know, allowed civilization to get started and that
according to the מדרש Midrash that's what אדם הראשון Adam HaRishon did
מוצאי שבת. motza'ei Shabbat. If you want to sort of explain it,
you know, in a little more vis-, you know, or like it
was a, the first significant creative act of, you know, human beings.
And it emphasizes the fact that we begin the weekday and we
begin a week of activity and of creation and of engaging the
world, you know, וכבשוה ve-chivshuha and so on. So that's the significance
of it. It also has the other significance, which is why you
also do it on מוצאי יום כיפור, motza'ei Yom Kippur, because you
couldn't make אש, esh, but on מוצאי יום כיפור motza'ei Yom Kippur
you don't make new fire, because the idea of new fire is
specifically towards because of the מוצאי שבת motza'ei Shabbat and that's why
דווקא davka by יום כיפור Yom Kippur you use old fire and
by מוצאי שבת motza'ei Shabbat you use new fire. So with that
in mind, I'm just saying to to think about what should come
first, בשמים besamim first or or אש esh first. You know, I
you know,
I guess I see more the position of בית הלל Beit Hillel
that if you see בשמים besamim is sort of like reviving you,
שבת left and you need to be revived and you need strength,
so after you get a little revived, now you start your אש
esh and your creativity and so on. I don't, you know, but
I'm sure you could come up with a reason for בית שמאי
Beit Shammai that reverses the order but we do בית הלל. Beit
Hillel. דוב Dov and then רב צבי?
Rav Tzvi? רב עוזיאל Rav Uziel has a really beautiful, very short
תשובה teshuvah about why you don't say בורא מאורי האש Borei Meorei
Ha-Esh every time during the week you you see light. Right, right,
yeah, because that flame מוצאי שבת motza'ei Shabbat is actually the flame
of creation. Ah!
A nice little symbolic. It's very beautiful.
Right, but I should say about that and while we're talking about
it I'll just say one minute, it is not a ברכת הנהנין,
birkat hanehenin, it is a ברכת השבח, birkat hashevach, meaning it's not
like you have to make a ברכה berakhah to get הנאה hana'ah
from fire, you see the fire and that gives you שבח shevach
to God, you know, again relating to particularly this phenomenon about אש
esh in general and אש esh as a human, it's interesting giving
שבח shevach to God because בצלם אלוהים betzelem Elokim and all with
God's assistance, you know, and when the גמרא Gemara describes how אדם
הראשון Adam HaRishon made fire it says, you know, it says I
forget the exact לשון lashon but it's basically, no, but it was
basically like נכנס בו, nichnas bo, you know, מעין, me-ein, you know,
some like an element of his Creator entered into him and he
was able to make fire, you know, sort of the idea of
the divine human partnership, it's not stealing fire from the God and
so on. So you're but anyway you're giving שבח shevach to God
for this aspect of human creativity but with you know צלם אלוהים
tzelem Elokim anyway because. Because it’s a ברכת השבח, birkas hashevach,
the way ברכת השבח birkas hashevachs work is you first appreciate the
phenomena and then you give the שבח, shevach, which is why the
גמרא Gemara says you don't make the ברכה beracha on the אש
aish עד שיאותו לאורו ad sheye'ousu le'oro until
you derive benefit. So the real practice is, and I have no
idea why ninety-nine percent of people do it otherwise, is first you
do the thing with the hand, you get benefit, and then you
make the ברכה. beracha. Now of course it's okay to not do
the thing with the hands; you're looking at the fire, you're getting
benefit just by looking at it. But the way people do it,
it seems to send the message like it's a type of a
ברכת הנהנין, birkas hanenin, which it is not. It is a ברכת
השבח. birkas hashevach. Rivka, what did you want to say?
I just wanted to comment on this מחלוקת. machlokes. It seems like
this discussion with this generation right from רב מאיר Rav Meir and
רבי all the way down. Right. And the rabbis were not giving
any פסק psak at all. Everybody was doing their own opinion and
what were the people supposed to do in the meantime? What were
they doing?
Well, there was probably a multiplicity of legitimate approaches. Right, so you
are correct, the idea that sometimes, you know, it gets decided at
the grassroots and the influence that the practice has on the פסק
psak is definitely the case, you know, is definitely true. I mean
a lot of, you know, the תוספות, Tosafos, the בעלי אשכנז, Baalei
Ashkenaz, and like the ערוך השולחן, Aruch Hashulchan, if you look more
recently, it's if a certain approach has been accepted and adopted, that
gives a lot of weight to the fact that that's the פסק.
psak. The people, that's what I mean. That's what I mean. Correct,
correct. So it could have been a nice time of, you know,
plurality and multiple
possibilities. But you're right.
The quote was מוצאי שבת נתן הקדוש ברוך הוא דעה באדם הראשון
מעין
דוגמה של מעלה.
Motzaei Shabbos nasna Hakadosh Baruch Hu de'a be'Adam Harishon
me'ein dugma shel ma'ala.
Okay, thank you.
יישר כח. Yasher koach.
Is this the only other model for making a ברכה beracha after
an activity would be ברכת המזון? Birkas Hamazon?
No, but ברכת המזון Birkas Hamazon you see, you know, you רואה
אילנות טובות, ro'eh ilanos tovos, you know,
you see the קשת, keshes, you hear all those types of things—thunder,
lightning—those are all the ברכות השבח, birchos hashevach, right? And you don't
make the ברכה beracha for the rainbow until you see it.
Yeah, but you could know that your tree is blossoming or whatever,
you know, and you make the ברכה beracha and then you open
your eyes. Tell me, you know. But you're right, anyway. Okay, let's
take a look. רב יעקב בר אבא איקלע לבי רבא. Rav Yaakov
bar Abba ikla levei Rava. So רב יעקב בר אבא Rav Yaakov
bar Abba came
again, somebody else visited the house of רבא. Rava. חזייה דבירך בורא
פרי הגפן אכסא קמא. Chazya devareich Borei Pri Hagafen a'casa kama. So
here it was Maariv and just like during the week, and he
made בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen when they, you know, started
the meal, they started drinking, they drank a lot of wine during
their meals. והדר בירך אכסא דברכתא Ve'hadar vareich a'casa de'bircasa and then
when it came time to benching, he benched על הכוס al hacos
and he made a ברכה beracha like we do after benching, בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen and he drank from the כוס. cos.
ואשתי Ve'ishtai and he drank. אמר ליה למה לך כולי האי? Amar
lei lama lach kulei hai? Why do you have to do another
ברכה beracha בורא פרי הגפן? Borei Pri Hagafen? הברוך לן מר חדא
זימנא, Havarich lan Mar chada zimna, you already made the ברכה beracha
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen for us, notice for us, like
he was מוציא motzi them. But okay, you already made a בורא
פרי הגפן Borei Pri Hagafen during the meal, this is the end
of the meal, it's benching, the drinking of the wine should be
like the wine during the meal and the בורא פרי הגפן Borei
Pri Hagafen should count for it. אמר ליה Amar lei he said
to him, כי הוינא בי ריש גלותא הכי עבדינן, ki havina bei
Reish Galusa hachi avdinan, when I was in the house of the
ריש גלותא, Reish Galusa, that's what we used to do. This is
pretty funny, I mean, excuse me buddy, who's the rabbi, you or
the ריש גלותא? Reish Galusa? You know, but anyway, so he said
that was the practice in the house of the ריש גלותא, Reish
Galusa, we made it again, we made it again. אמר ליה Amar
lei so he said to him, תינח בי ריש גלותא tinach bei
Reish Galusa fine, in the house of the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa
I get it, דהכי עבדי dehachi avdi that's how you did it,
דספק מייתי לן ספק לא מייתי לן, desafek mayisai lan safek lo
mayisai lan, there we're not the בעל הבית. baal habayis. So we're
not the בעל הבית, baal habayis, we don't know if they're going
to give us more wine. So anytime they decide to give us
more wine, we have to make another בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Pri
Hagafen. הכא המנא כסא קמן Hacha hamana casa kaman in this case,
the cup is right there, right, we've already during the meal, you
know, you're the בעל הבית, baal habayis, the cup is there, the
wine is there, we know we're going to use it for ברכת
המזון. Birkas Hamazon. בדעתין עלויה, Bedaitin alavei, our intention is about—it's about
subjective דעת. daas. Our intention is that we're going to drink from
the כוס cos after ברכת המזון, Birkas Hamazon, so why should anybody,
you know, need to make another ברכה? beracha? אמר ליה Amar lei
he said back to him, אנא עבדי כתלמידי דרב, ana avdi k'talmidei
deRav, I'm following the students of רב. Rav דרב ברונא ורב חננאל
תלמידי דרב הוו, De'Rav Bruna v'Rav Chananel talmidei deRav havu, these two
rabbis, רב ברונא Rav Bruna and רב חננאל Rav Chananel were students
of רב. Rav יתבי בסעודתא Yasvi besudasa and they were sitting in
a meal. קאי עלייהו רב ייבא סבא, Ka'ei alaihu Rav Yeiva Saba,
רב ייבא סבא, Rav Yeiva Saba, it's a funny name but actually
he does come up, רב ייבא סבא Rav Yeiva Saba the elder
was attending to them, he actually was like the שמש, shamash, okay.
אמרו ליה הבו לן ונבריך. Amru lei havu lan venivrich. So they
said to him, go bring us wine so we can make ברכת
המזון. Birkas Hamazon. לסוף אמרו ליה L'sof amru lei so by the
time it took him to go get the wine and he brought
the wine and then he came, they said, you know what, הבו
לן ונשתי, havu lan venishti, we decided we'd like to drink a
little bit more before we ran into ברכת המזון. Birkas Hamazon. Once
you've used ברכת המזון
Birkas Hamazon you can't really...
אמר להו Amar lehu he said to them, הכי אמר רב, hachi
amar Rav, so here the attendant, the שמש, shamash, is telling the
guests, by the way, you're students of רב, Rav you should know
what רב Rav says about this. רב Rav says, כיון דאמריתו הבו
לן ונבריך, keivan d'amrisu havu lan venivrich, as soon as you said
'Hey let's bench', like רבותי נברך, rabbosai nevareich, you
know... Yeah, but forget זימון, zimmun, you've just indicated verbally that you're
moving on to בענטשונג. bentshung. Okay, so then דעתייכו, da'ataychu, so איסורו
לכו למשתי, isuru lechu l'mishtei, you can no longer drink. מאי טעמא,
mai taama, why? דאסחיתו דעתייכו, d'asichtu da'ataychu, because you have a היסח
הדעת. hessech hadaas. Here is this issue that we were discussing before,
this subjective היסח הדעת. hessech hadaas. The statement let's bench means you're
done with the meal, and now if you wanted to drink more,
you'd have to make another ברכה. bracha. Now I should point out
that the simple לשון lashon is it's אסור, assur, to
maybe even if you wanted to make another ברכה, bracha, you have
to bench, you said you're going to bench. But most ראשונים rishonim
don't read it that way. Most ראשונים rishonim understand it just means
if you wanted to drink more, you'd have to make another ברכה.
bracha.
Anything שהכל, shehakol, make a שהכל shehakol mid-meal?
What, yeah, I mean presumably you're done with your eating. Anything now
is not related to the סעודה seuda and therefore would require another
ברכה. bracha. Now, by the way, a lot of ראשונים rishonim point
out, and I don't want to go into the details about this,
it relates to the issue we had before about שינוי מקום, shinui
makom, that it's more easy to require circumstances where more happened that
you'll be required to make another ברכה ראשונה, bracha rishona, but you
can often make a ברכה אחרונה bracha achrona going on everything. So
even if you had a היסח הדעת hessech hadaas and you wanted
to drink more wine and you had to make another בורא פרי
הגפן, Borei Peri HaGafen, the רשב"ם says, there's a long discussion in
תוספות, Tosafos, but basically the רשב"ם says you make a, you're going
to do the benching, that'll go on everything. You don't have to
make a separate ברכה אחרונה, bracha achrona, but you would have to
make a new ברכה ראשונה. bracha rishona. So basically he says you
want more wine, you don't want to bench, very nice, but again
reading it this way, אסור, assur, but אסור assur meaning at least
you'd have to make another ברכה bracha if you wanted to do
it. So how is that relevant? It's relevant because you see even
saying let's bench creates a היסח hessech and any more drinking of
wine, even if it was part of the meal, would be defined
as separate and need a new ברכה. bracha. So קל וחומר kal
v'chomer when you actually bench, right, that you have to then say
a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen to drink that wine even
though it's connected to the benching and the meal. But as soon
as you transition into benching, you've already ended the meal and anything
else requires a new ברכה. bracha. And based on this, so that's
the answer why we do this and we say בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Peri HaGafen at the end. The ראש Rosh points out that
this explains why benching is different than anything else על הכוס. al
hakos. Everything else על הכוס, al hakos, as we've just been discussing
indirectly, you always do the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen first.
Benching, you do the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen last. Why
is it? Because if you were to do the בורא פרי הגפן
Borei Peri HaGafen first, right, and then you would start the ברוך
אתה השם, Baruch Atah Hashem, you know, הזן את העולם hazan es
ha'olam etc., as soon as you moved into the הזן את העולם,
hazan es ha'olam, you've separated everything that preceded it, that was all
prior to the meal. Now you still can't drink the wine at
the end because the בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen was cut
off. The moving into the ברכת המזון birchas hamazon even if it
was juxtaposed is defining that everything else is past and if you
want to do something new, even drink the wine of ברכת המזון,
birchas hamazon, you need a בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Peri HaGafen. And
that's the way we do that. Okay, ברכה לבטלה? bracha levatala? Yeah,
and anyway you'd have to make another בורא פרי הגפן. Borei Peri
HaGafen. So that's why we do it at the end. Okay, so
אמימר מר זוטרא ורב אשי. Amemar Mar Zutra v'Rav Ashi. Now another
story about people at a meal. אמימר מר זוטרא ורב אשי, Amemar
Mar Zutra v'Rav Ashi, these three rabbis, הוו יתבי בסעודתא, hava yasvei
b'seudata, they were sitting at a meal, וקאי עלייהו רב אחא בריה
דרבא, v'kaai aleihu Rav Acha brei d'Rava, and רב אחא Rav Acha
the son of רבא Rava was attending to them. אמימר בריך על
כל כסא וכסא. Amemar barich al kol kassa v'kassa. So then the
question is
what ברכה bracha do you make on the wine? The wine at
the beginning, wine in the middle, wine of ברכת המזון? birchas hamazon?
אמימר Amemar made a ברכה bracha on every single cup of wine.
He basically figured he didn't know that they were going to give
him more wine or something and he had a היסח הדעת, hessech
hadaas, so he felt every single cup of wine he had to
make a ברכה bracha on. Okay,
ומר זוטרא בריך אכסא קמא ואכסא בתרא. u'Mar Zutra barich akassa kamma
v'akassa batra. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra did what we just said. The
first cup, and that covered all the first glass, that covered everything
because he knew they were drinking wine during the meal, but not
the כסא דברכת המזון. kassa d'birchas hamazon. That objectively was separated from
the meal. That was a separate ברכה. bracha. רב אשי בריך אכסא
קמא ותו לא בריך. Rav Ashi barich akassa kamma v'tu lo barich.
And רב אשי Rav Ashi said he disagreed with this. He says
no, even the cup of ברכת המזון birchas hamazon goes after the
בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen in the meal and therefore you
don't make a בורא פרי הגפן Borei Peri HaGafen on the כוסא
דברכת המזון. kossa d'birchas hamazon. So אמר להו רב אחא בר רבא,
amar lehu Rav Acha bar Rava, אנן כמאן נעביד? anan k'man naavid?
So רב אחא בר רבא Rav Acha bar Rava who was attending
these three rabbis said, how should we, what should we do?
So
basically
mean, so what's the פסק psak and why is everybody doing something
different? אמימר אמר, Amemar amar, so אמימר Amemar said נמלכנא. nimlachana. The
reason I made a ברכה bracha on every separate כוס kos is
I was always changing my mind. I figured okay, just one. All
right fine, just one more. No more after this. Okay fine, fine,
one more but that's
it. So after every cup of wine it was a new decision,
I had to make a new ברכה. bracha. All right, מר זוטרא
אמר, Mar Zutra amar, that's a
nice way of being kind to his host I guess.
מר זוטרא אמר, Mar Zutra amar, אנן דעתינן כתלמידי דרב, anan d'atin
k'talmidei d'Rav, I'm following what we just said, the students of רב,
that ברכת המזון... birchas hamazon... I mean actually it's funny by the
way, notice who gets the credit. The students of רב were not
the ones who said it, it was רב ייבא סבא Rav Yeba
Saba who told the students of רב what רב said. Okay, but
anyway one minute. So I am following that teaching of רב *Rav*
that was told to the students of רב *Rav* is actually a
more accurate way of saying it. That basically when that as soon
as you move into ברכת המזון Birkat Hamazon. *Birkat HaMazon*, it's a
הפסק *hefsek* and therefore you need a ברכה bracha. *beracha* for the
כוס *kos* of ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon*. רבא Rava אמר לא כתלמידי
דרב *Rava amar lo k'talmidei de-Rav*. No, I'm sorry, we don't rule
like that. The ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon* is connected to it maybe
and therefore even when you're moving in you still haven't the meal
is still going on until you make it and maybe even until
you do the בורא פרי הגפן *borei pri hagafen* after all of
that connects to the meal. And now what's his proof? דיום טוב
שחל להיות אחר שבת *D'Yom Tov she-chal lihyot achar Shabbat*, let's say
a יום טוב *Yom Tov* falls out after שבת *Shabbat* like we've
been talking. ואמר רב יקנה *V'amar Rav yaknah* and רב *Rav* says
יקנה *yaknah*. Now what does that prove? יין *Yayin*, קידוש *kiddush*, נר
*ner*, הבדלה *havdalah*. So it's confusing what does that have to do
with ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon* yes ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon* no? So
the basic you know proof seems to be we didn't require two
בורא פרי הגפן *borei pri hagafens*. The יין *yayin* on קידוש *kiddush*
could also go on the יין *yayin* of הבדלה *havdalah*. And therefore
we don't say the קידוש *kiddush* defines one move and the הבדלה
*havdalah* another thing. So here too the wine from the meal goes
for the wine after the meal. That's actually a pretty good argument.
I don't think so. Let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. ולאו
היא *Velavi*, it's not a good comparison. התם עקר דעתייהו ממשתייא *Hatam
ikar daitaihu mi-mishtaya*
when you move on to בענטשינג *benching* you've decided you're done with
your eating, done with your drinking. The move to בענטשינג *benching* is
an end to the meal. הכא *Hacha* by יקנה *yaknah* לא עקר
דעתייהו ממשתייא *lo akar daitaihu mi-mishtaya*. Just because you do both קידוש
*kiddush* and הבדלה *havdalah* doesn't separate the two. So it's not like
ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon*. ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon*, yes, sometimes you can
juxtapose things with wine and do multiple things, but ברכת המזון *Birkat
HaMazon* is an objective הפסק *hefsek* and therefore even when you say
you want to move into it you have to make another ברכה
bracha *beracha* and therefore we do a בורא פרי הגפן *borei pri
hagafen* at the end.
Yes. I'm going to ask you, I mean I'm not convinced. I
don't understand why the גמרא *Gemara* didn't say נמלך אנא *nimlach ana*
after after he said הב לן ונבריך *havlan u-nivrich*. It's הב לן
ונבריך *havlan u-nivrich* and then if you second-guess and you say you
know what I kind of want to have another. Right.
So meaning why isn't it obvious that's a הפסק *hefsek*?
Is it an עקירת הדעת *akirat ha-da'at*? Why can't you say נמלך
אנא *nimlach ana* after having said הב לן *havlan*?
You could, but the גמרא *Gemara*
is so objectively...
yeah, that's the גמרא *Gemara*'s חידוש *chiddush* that even though you could
say yeah I thought to בענטש *bench* but partially I was still
a little bit thinking maybe I would continue, meaning we don't measure
it by that same question of did you have הסח הדעת *hesech
ha-da'at*. Whatever was going on in your head, objectively the act of
בענטשינג *benching* or saying you're moving in
that's קובע *kovei'a*. That's exactly the point. This is an objective measure
and we don't try to figure out what's in your head, whereas
נמלך *nimlach* is more like you know and if you were equivocating
in your own mind and you sort of were planning then it
would not be the same הפסק *hefsek*.
Interesting switching from one date to another and declaring that as an
objective measure of saying that you know you're...
Yeah, but it doesn't say you're done with drinking. It doesn't relate
to the reality of drinking and eating and the need to make
a ברכה bracha *beracha*. Maybe it would be a conceptual reason to
say you should have another ברכה bracha *beracha* you know in terms
of defining these as separate acts, but it's not the same power
of ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon*. Okay,
now I want to tell you read you a line from תוספות
Tosafos. *Tosafot* because as I said תוספות *Tosafot* has this whole discussion
about
when you have to make a ברכה bracha. *beracha* when things come
towards the end of the meal. Is בענטשינג *benching* always like dessert?
You bring dessert at the end, you're totally done with the rest
of your eating. Sometimes in our house often in our house we
stop and completely clear the table you know everything and then we
bring out the dessert clearly it's not part of the סעודה *seudah*.
You make a ברכה bracha. *beracha* on it. Okay, but we call
it לא בא מחמת הסעודה *lo ba machmat haseudah* which for us
will mean it's not something brought for filling you up it's brought
just for the taste it comes completely after the meal. So there's
actually a discussion so you make a ברכה ראשונה *beracha rishona*. There's
actually a discussion whether you have to make a ברכה אחרונה *beracha
achrona* or does the בענטשינג *benching* go on it? So תוספות *Tosafot*
has this whole discussion does the בענטשינג *benching* go on it or
not like you know like this issue about you know if you
said הב לן ונברך *havlan u-nevarech* and then you had another cup
of wine would the בענטשינג *benching* go on it? The general assumption
is yes, but I want to show you the end of תוספות
*Tosafot* where תוספות *Tosafot* says like this. This is the end of
the תוספות *Tosafot* that started on the previous page. He says ומיהו
אנו *Umihu anu*, the line starts with the word אנו *anu* like
four lines before the end of six lines before the end of
תוספות *Tosafot*. He says אין אנו מסלקים ידינו מפת עד ברכת המזון
*ein anu mesalkim yadeinu mi-pat ad Birkat HaMazon*. He says for them
there would come a time they'd remove the table, they'd be done
with the bread and then they might continue drinking and they might
have dessert and then there could be a question about you know
does the ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon* go on it? But us, we
eat bread straight up to the ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon* והכל קרוי
תוך הסעודה ואין שום דבר טעון ברכה אחריו *v'hakol korei toch ha-seudah
v'ein shum davar taun beracha acharav*. Now maybe still a ברכה לפניו
*beracha lefanav* if it's considered לא בא מחמת הסעודה *lo ba machmat
haseudah* like dessert or whatnot maybe, but certainly there's no question even
if in the גמרא *Gemara* maybe there were times you'd make a
separate ברכה אחרונה *beracha achrona* for us we have פת *pat* throughout
and certainly the ברכת המזון *Birkat HaMazon* goes on it. The ברכת
המזון *Birkat HaMazon* פוטר *poteir*. ומימי החכמים היו מסיחין מן הפת בעקירת
השולחן קודם ברכת המזון ואז היו רגילים לשתות יין ולאכול פירות *Umi-mei
hachachamim hayu mesichin min hapat b'akirat hashulchan kodem Birkat HaMazon v'az hayu
regilin lishtot yayin v'le'echol peirot*. So I just thought it's interesting contrasting
those sort of you know anthropological you know societal differences. and for
him the question of does it require a separate ברכה אחרונה is
really a moot point with his reality that it would all be
bread right up to the בענטשין. benching. Yes.
Did he raise it as I just wanted to clarify when you're
saying not meant to fill you up does that mean that even
if they were to bring out cake which is מזונות mezonos you
still wouldn't make a מזונות mezonos because it's dessert and it's not
meant to fill you up?
Yeah I mean but again the cake issue is a debated issue
because that objectively because it's מזונות mezonos might always be defined as
it sates and whatever and it's קביעת סעודה.
kevius seudah.
Yeah. All right candy definitely you make a separate ברכה. Okay. All
right let's go on. Okay now
now oh but before I do want to tell you one thing
about one other תוספות. Oh you know what let's finish this and
then go back hopefully we'll have time. So the גמרא says like
this.
Okay now כי מטא לאבדולי Ki mta l'avdulei now came time for
הבדלה. Presumably this wasn't this previous case where we didn't even discuss
that it was שבת it's going back to the case before where
it says they came to the house of רב and whatever and
he made the first ברכה and then he made the ברכה on
ברכת המזון. So now it's time to make הבדלה in that story
before with רב or with רבא Rava excuse me not with רב
with רבא Rava קם שמעיה kam shmaya so רבא's Rava שמש shamash
got up his attendant ואדליק אבוקה משרגא v'adlik avuka misharga and rather
than using a simple candle he lit a torch. אמר ליה למה
לך כולי האי Amar lei lama lach kulei hai why did you
have to make light a torch for הבדלה? הא מנחא שרגא ha
mancha sharga you have a candle. אמר ליה שמעא
מדעתא דנפשיה עבד Amar lei shmaya m'daata d'nafshei avid my שמש shamash
is just doing it on his own he's not I didn't tell
him to do that he just I don't know why he did
that it's his own his own שטות. shtus. So אמר ליה amar
lei so whoever it was who was there at רבא's Rava house
I forget who it was now I think רב יעקב בר אבא
Rav Yaakov bar Abba said back to him don't give me that.
אמר ליה אי לאו שמיע ליה מיניה דמר לא הוה עביד Amar
lei ee lav shmiya lei minei d'mar lo hava avid if your
שמש shamash hadn't heard you tell him to do this he wouldn't
do it so don't push me off I want to know why
why you're why you're lighting the torch. אמר ליה ולא סבר ליה
מר Amar lei v'lo savar lei mar maybe he was testing him
I don't know what but doesn't the master hold הא לא שמיע
לך אבוקה להבדלה מצוה מן המובחר ha lo shmiya lach avuka l'havdala
mitzvah min hamuvchar haven't you heard that it's ideally to have it
not from a candle but to have it from a torch from
multiple wicks and this line of course starts the whole הבדלה candle
industry. So about the whole idea of having multiple wicks. Now exactly
why is not spelled out. Exactly why is not spelled out but
again it might have to do with the idea of the emphasis
on אש eish and not just on light and on the whole
idea of fire and the power of fire you multiple flames definitely
is a part of that. Okay.
Read one more line we're getting to do a little bit more.
Okay we have to end by the way on Tuesdays at 8:25
because there's a group that meets here.
So the גמרא says like this. פתח ואמר Pasach v'amar so then
רבא Rava was saying קידוש רבא was saying קידוש and here's what
he said. המבדיל בין קודש לחול בין אור לחושך בין ישראל לעמים
בין יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה. Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol bein or
l'choshech bein Yisrael l'amim bein yom hashvii l'sheses y'mei hamaaseh. That sounds
pretty familiar. So אמר ליה למה
לך כולי האי Amar lei lama lach kulei hai it's like the
question about the about the candle about the torch. Why do you
have to say so many המבדיל המבדיל המבדיל Hamavdil Hamavdil Hamavdil all
these הבדלות? havdalos והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב המבדיל בין קודש לחול
זו היא הבדלתו של רבי יהודה
הנשיא. V'ha'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol zu hi
havdalaso shel Rabbi Yehuda haNasi. All you have to say is המבדיל
בין קודש לחול Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol not just in the חתימה
chasima but even in the text itself. You don't have to say
the בין ישראל לעמים בין יום השביעי bein Yisrael l'amim bein yom
hashvii etc just say המבדיל בין קודש לחול. Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol.
אמר ליה אנא כהא סבירא
לי Amar lei ana k'ha sevira li I hold like this other
teaching דאמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי יהושע הפוחת לא יפחות
משלוש d'amar Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Yehoshua hapoches lo yifchos mi'gimel if
you say the fewest number of ways in which there's a separation
you know in the world in Torah and הלכה halacha you should
not say fewer than three types of הבדלות והמוסיף לא יוסיף על
שבע V'hamosif lo yosif al sheva if you want to add even
more you shouldn't go more than seven. So I see this as
an idea to say the different ways in which הבדלה takes place
and God is מבדיל mavdil not just בין קודש לחול. bein kodesh
l'chol. אמר ליה Amar lei he said to him והא לא תלתא
אמרת ולא שבע אמרת v'ha lo slasa amart v'lo sheva amart but
you didn't say three or seven. Four! So even do the minimum
or the maximum what's with four? Three? אמר ליה איברא Amar lei
ivra it's true you're right I didn't say three I said four
but בין יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה bein yom hashvii l'sheses y'mei
hamaaseh or maybe איברא ivra the truth is the following בין יום
השביעי לששת ימי המעשה מעין חתימה היא bein yom hashvii l'sheses y'mei
hamaaseh me'ein chasima hi when I said המבדיל בין קודש לחול בין
אור לחושך בין ישראל לעמים Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol bein or l'choshech
bein Yisrael l'amim those were my three. Why did I go back
and say בין יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה bein yom hashvii l'sheses
y'mei hamaaseh because before you make the final ברכה the חתימה chasima
המבדיל בין קודש לחול Hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol you have to lead
into it. You need the line that you say before the final
ברכה. There is our general rule in ברכות brachos צריכה שתהא מעין
חתימה tzricha shetehei me'ein chasima it has to be connected to evoke
the theme of that final ברכה. So I had to go back
and say you know בין יום השביעי לששת ימי המעשה bein yom
hashvii l'sheses y'mei hamaaseh but okay you've done the order fine whatever
anyway he said in principle it is three. Now before we enter
we'll pick up with this we're not done with the נוסח של
הבדלה nusach shel Havdala but I did want to bring your attention
briefly to To this תוספות *Tosafot* about רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, ברוך
הכסא קמא ובתר הכי ברוך *Baruch hakesseh kamma u'vatar hechi barukh*. Because
that made it sound that if it were—this is basically what Michael's
adding—if it wasn't for ברכת המזון *Birkat Hamazon*, you could use the
same כוס *kos*, right, multiple times. And this leads תוספות *Tosafot* to
a question about, and you don't make another בורא פרי הגפן *Borei
Peri Hagefen*, if it weren't for this reality of ברכת המזון *Birkat
Hamazon*. So תוספות *Tosafot* says, so why in the סדר *Seder* do
we make a בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Peri Hagefen* before every cup
of wine? Right? I mean, I get why you make it after
cup two, because after cup two comes ברכת המזון *Birkat Hamazon*. But
you should really only make it on cup one and on cup
three. And the fact that you're saying הגדה *Haggadah* and הלל *Hallel*,
the גמרא *Gemara* says ברכת המזון *Birkat Hamazon* separates, but everything—you're planning
on drinking more wine, you know second cup is coming up, you
know the fourth cup is coming up, why do you make a
new בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Peri Hagefen*? The general ספרדי *Sephardi* practice
is to not make בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Peri Hagefen* only on
one and three. Correct. Interesting. So it's a big debate in the
ראשונים *Rishonim* whether you make a בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Peri Hagefen*
on every כוס *kos* or whether you make it only on one
and three based on this גמרא *Gemara*. Those that say only one
and three—oh, on every כוס *kos*—either argue that somehow the length of
the הגדה *Haggadah* or the length of the הלל *Hallel* that occurs
between three and four creates a הפסק *hefsek* like ברכת המזון *Birkat
Hamazon* creates a הפסק *hefsek*, although it's not such an obvious argument.
Or the idea of, right, to more ritualize it, but the גמרא
*Gemara* never says that. The גמרא *Gemara* says we want to have
a separate כוס *kos* and the assumption would have to be and
we want to make a בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Peri Hagefen* on
it. But there's a major debate, the גמרא *Gemara* never discusses the
ברכה *berakha* of בורא פרי הגפן *Borei Peri Hagefen* and based on
this גמרא *Gemara*, a logical position would be only making it on
one and three and not on one, two, three, and four. Okay,
so we'll more about this tomorrow. Goodbye Rabbi.
Yep. מזל טוב *Mazel tov*.
People,
people have to transition out quickly because another thing is starting in
here.
Does it have to be in color?
What? Base color?
If
you don't have your—it's not לעיכובא *le'ikuva* having the color, so if
you don't have it then you know use whatever single light you
have. Yeah.