Okay, so today's topic is דף קטז. daf Kuf Tes Zayin. We
pick up at the bottom of עמוד ב amud bais and we
have gotten through most parts of the הגדה Haggadah and we're up
to the הלל Hallel pre-מוציא
מצה, motzi matzah, but we pick up first with a discussion because
that connects to the statement of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel of כל
שלא אמר שלשה דברים אלו בפסח kol shelo amar sheloshah devarim elu
b'Pesach and the tying in of the foods to the story of
the פסח. Pesach. We start with actually the question, right? כי ישאלך
בנך מחר לאמר מה זאת ki yishalcha bincha machar l'amor mah zot
about the questions of the children, which primarily are about the foods.
We had spoken before about the סדר seder plate before every person,
integrating the foods in that way. And then we have the response
at the end, פסח מצה מרור, Pesach, matzah, maror, which in a
way responds to the questions of the child and ties in the
foods and their symbolism. So with that in mind, let's take a
look now as we have the following statement. אמר
רב אחא, Amar Rav Acha, it is three lines after the גמרא
Gemara begins where it says ג"מ ב gimmel mem beis in big
bold, it's about ten lines from the bottom. Line starts with the
word אלא שנראה כח קדשך בחוץ. ella she'nireh koach kadshecha bachutz. That's
on קטז עמוד ב. Kuf Tes Zayin amud bais. אמר רב אחא
בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, סומא פטור מלומר הגדה. suma
patur mi'lomar Haggadah. A blind person is exempt from saying the הגדה.
Haggadah.
כתיב הכא Kasiv hacha בעבור זה. ba'avur zeh. It says here, right,
you shall tell your child to say בעבור זה עשה ה' לי
בצאתי ממצרים. ba'avur zeh asah Hashem li b'tzeisi miMitzrayim. And what do
we say in the הגדה? Haggadah? בעבור זה לא אמרתי אלא בשעה
שיש מצה ומרור מונחים לפניך. ba'avur zeh lo amarti ella b'shaas she'yesh
matzah u'maror munachim lefanecha. So בעבור זה ba'avur zeh is understood by
חז"ל Chazal meaning that you're describing the meaning of the foods, of
the ritual foods, and that that's part of the telling of the
story. So that's what it says about the telling of the הגדה.
Haggadah. וכתיב התם U'kesiv hasam and it says by a בן סורר
ומורה: ben soreir u'moreh: בננו זה, bneinu zeh, this our son. מה
להלן Mah lehallan פרט לסומין. prat le'sumin.
There we have an accepted דרשה, drasha, an understanding that it's meant
to exclude if either the parents are blind because they can't say
this our son, they can't point him
out directly. אף כאן Af kan פרט לסומין. prat le'sumin. Here too,
if you can't say זה, zeh, you can't see it and relate
to it through sight, although you relate to it through touch and
eating, but somehow the understanding of זה zeh means a certain type
of immediate connection through sight and therefore you can't really fully tell
the story. Tying in of course to the רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel's
point of לא יצא ידי חובתו lo yatza yedei chovato of the
need to really connect to the foods in order to fulfill the
obligation. Is that the מצוה mitzvah of הגדה Haggadah then?
No, they're understanding it as part of the מצוה mitzvah of הגדה.
Haggadah.
Interesting.
Yeah, in the case of בן סורר ומורה, ben soreir u'moreh, the
motivation of the rabbis was clearly to
exclude it.
Right, the rabbis are trying to eliminate the category of בן סורר
ומורה. ben soreir u'moreh. That's not the case here. Let's see where
the גמרא Gemara goes with it. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: איני, Inei, is this really
true? ואמר מרימר, Ve'amar Mareimar, didn't מרימר Mareimar say: שאלתינהו לרבנן דבי
רב יוסף, she'iltinu le'rabbanan de'vei Rav Yosef, I asked the רבנן, rabbanan,
again רבנן rabbanan mean like the rabbinic students in the house of
רב יוסף Rav Yosef or the ישיבה yeshiva of רב יוסף. Rav
Yosef. מאן דאמר הגדה בי רב יוסף, Man de'amar Haggadah bei Rav
Yosef, who is the one there that recites the הגדה? Haggadah? אמרו,
Amru, they said: רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. It was רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef was blind. מאן דאמר הגדה בי
רב ששת, Man de'amar Haggadah bei Rav Sheshet, who says the הגדה
Haggadah in the house or the ישיבה yeshiva of רב ששת? Rav
Sheshet? אמרו, Amru, רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, who was also blind. ששת.
Sheshet. Now what's also fascinating is what we are finding out is
that there was one reciter of the הגדה, Haggadah, right? Now we
had discussed before about everybody having a סדר seder plate, people asking
and someone answering, and if you think about it, right, the way
it forms, the child asks and the father answers, the wife asks
and the husband answers. It sounds like only one person is really
doing the narrating. Everybody else is playing their part by asking and
discussing or whatever, but one person is basically doing the narrating, which
is interesting because you know in terms of the question about being
מוציא motzi the מצוה mitzvah of סיפור יציאת מצרים, sippur yetzias Mitzrayim,
you know, now everybody is מחמיר, machmir, oh I gotta go back
and read every single word, I was out for five minutes, I
gotta catch up in the הגדה, Haggadah, right? But am I יוצא
yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of סיפור יציאת מצרים sippur yetzias Mitzrayim if
I'm the one asking and you're the one telling me the answer?
Right? Because I'm not telling the story, you're telling the story, but
together we're achieving the סיפור sippur of יציאת מצרים. yetzias Mitzrayim. And
especially if you consider that everybody needs to have the סדר seder
plate in front of them, which is what the גמרא Gemara said
before. Now I tried to connect that to that that's part of
סיפור יציאת מצרים. sippur yetzias Mitzrayim. The ראשונים Rishonim more say that
that is actually because if you're making a ברכה bracha you want
to eat it right away. But it would be a little ironic
that I need to have the מצה matzah and מרור maror in
front of me but I'm not actually telling the story. But you
could still understand I'm responding to what's this מצה matzah and מרור
maror about? But anyway, I think it's worth noting what's clear from
here is that there was one reciter of the הגדה. Haggadah. Now
another way of saying it is not to say, and this is
really what it sounds like from the גמרא, Gemara, is not to
say like we're יוצא yotzei because we're all playing our parts, I'm
doing the asking and you're doing the telling, but it's more like
we say that you read the מגילה Megillah for me, שומע כעונה,
shomea ke'oneh, and therefore yes. we all have to say it, you
say it, I listen, it's like I said it. Okay, so it's
more than just I ask, I'm יוצא שומע כעונה, yotzei shomea keoneh,
and that seems to be the point of the גמרא. Gemara. How
could רב ששת Rav Sheshet say it if he's blind, and a
blind person is פטור, patur, right, how could he be מוציא motzi
everybody else who's obligated? All right, so let's take a look what
it says. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you see that a
blind person is not פטור. patur. So the גמרא Gemara says קסבר,
kasavar, no, they're of the opinion כל דתיקון רבנן כעין דאורייתא תיקון.
kol d'tikon rabanan k'ein d'oraisa tikun. Did I skip a line? Yes,
I skipped a line. Okay, גמרא Gemara says like: אמר רב ששת
קסברי רבנן מצה בזמן הזה דרבנן. amar Rav Sheshet kasavar rabanan matzah
bizman hazeh d'rabanan. No,
those Rabbis hold that מצה matzah nowadays is only rabbinic, because מצה
matzah מרור maror are both connected to the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
מכאן, Mikaan, if מצה's matzah rabbinic, because the בעבור זה's ba'avur zeh
the whole link of the הגדה Haggadah to the מצה, matzah, right,
and to the מצוות mitzvas of eating, so then if מצה's matzah
rabbinic, הגדה's Haggadah rabbinic. So according to that, everything we do on
סדר Seder night is totally rabbinic. The מצה, matzah, the הגדה, Haggadah,
probably only thing that's דאורייתא d'oraisa is the קידוש kiddush and ברכת
המזון. birchas hamazon. So they feel it's all rabbinic. If it's all
rabbinic, you can be מוציא—then motzi a blind person is okay. So
גמרא Gemara says: מכלל דרב אחא בר יעקב סבר מצה בזמן הזה
דאורייתא? miklal d'Rav Achai bar Yaakov savar matzah bizman hazeh d'oraisa? Do
you mean to tell me that רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Achai
bar Yaakov who says a blind person is פטור patur says מצה's
matzah biblical? והא רב אחא בר יעקב הוא דאמר מצה בזמן הזה
דרבנן. veha Rav Achai bar Yaakov hu d'amar matzah bizman hazeh d'rabanan.
We're going to find out shortly that he's actually of the opinion
that it's rabbinic, and nevertheless he says a blind person is exempt.
So גמרא Gemara says: קסבר כל דתיקון רבנן כעין דאורייתא תיקון. kasavar
kol d'tikon rabanan k'ein d'oraisa tikun.
Yes, he holds it's rabbinic, but even if it's rabbinic, they would
still pattern it after the דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So biblically a blind person
is exempt, he would say a blind person is exempt even nowadays,
even if it's rabbinic. So the גמרא Gemara says: רב ששת ורב
יוסף נמי אודאי כל דתיקון רבנן כעין דאורייתא תיקון. Rav Sheshet v'Rav
Yosef nami avadai kol d'tikon rabanan k'ein d'oraisa tikun. Do רב ששת
Rav Sheshet and רב יוסף Rav Yosef certainly also agree to that
idea that even if it's rabbinic nowadays it'll pattern after the דאורייתא?
d'oraisa? So if a blind person is exempt, they say should not
have been מוציא motzi the rest of the household with their recital
of the הגדה. Haggadah. So the גמרא Gemara says: You're right. They
actually reject the whole idea that a blind person is exempt. The
גמרא Gemara says: הכי השתא. hachi hashta. What type of comparison was
that to the בן סורר ומורה? ben sorer u'moreh? Now they're going
to challenge that whole idea of רב אחא בר יעקב. Rav Acha
bar Yaakov. בשלמא התם, bishlama hasam, there it makes sense, איבעי ליה
למכתב בננו הוא. yihavei lei l'michtav baneinu hu. The פסוק pasuk could
have said
our son, he our son. וכתיב בננו זה. ukasiv baneinu zeh.
It already said בננו. baneinu. Why did it have to say זה?
zeh? The extra זה zeh is like really pointing a finger at
him. So that's telling you that they have to be directly seeing
him. שמע מינה פרט לסומא. shaman mina perat l'suma. That's coming to
exempt a blind person. That's the זה's zeh extra הוא דאתי hu
d'asit coming. אבל הכא אי לאו בעבור זה, aval hacha ilav ba'avur
zeh, here if it's not said בעבור זה, מאי למכתב? ba'avur zeh
mai l'michtav? What should it have said? It wants to say the
סיפור sippur is the reason we tell the story is because and
connected to the food. It needs the word זה. zeh. I mean,
actually part of the problem is that you don't even know what
the זה zeh refers to in that פסוק. pasuk. You know, והגדת
לבנך ביום ההוא לאמר בעבור זה עשה ה' לי בצאתי ממצרים. v'higadta
l'vincha bayom hahu leimor ba'avur zeh asah Hashem li b'tzeisi miMitzrayim. בעבור
Ba'avur what? Right? So חז"ל Chazal tell us that בעבור זה ba'avur
zeh, means the מצה matzah מרור, maror, but it's not like there's
an object that has been identified yet. If when it says בננו
baneinu it didn't need to say זה. zeh. Here, I'm saying because
of something, so it needed the word זה. zeh. I mean, it
still leaves open what the something is,
but
it
needed זה zeh to identify some object of that verb. So בעבור
זה ba'avur zeh מאי למכתב? mai l'michtav? אלא בעבור מצה ומרור דאתי.
ela ba'avur matzah u'maror d'asit. It's coming to say because of the
sake of מצה matzah and מרור. maror. And therefore it's not—the זה
zeh is not extra, it's needed. Now, I do want to point
something out, which is that probably, you know, there's one thing missing
from the בעבור זה, ba'avur zeh, right? Which is what? What—what else
besides מצה matzah and מרור? maror? פסח. Pesach. Okay? And חז"ל Chazal
could have said בעבור זה ba'avur zeh meant the פסח Pesach because
then the הגדה Haggadah nowadays would all be דרבנן. d'rabanan. Okay? But
it's a little bit ironic because clearly in the פסוקים, pesukim, what
is the most dominant of the מצוות mitzvos of the night of
the eating is the פסח, Pesach, right? And I think the בעבור
זה ba'avur zeh is in response to the—in response to מה העבודה
הזאת לכם? mah ha'avodah hazos lachem?
No, I was trying to—just trying to say what I was trying
to say before. Is—שבעת ימים תאכל מצות, shivas yamim tochal matzos, וביום
השביעי חג לה'. u'bayom hashvii chag l'Hashem. מצות יאכל את שבעת הימים
ולא יראה לך חמץ ולא יראה לך שאור בכל גבלך.
matzos ye'acheil eis shivas hayamim v'lo
yeira'eh
l'cha chameitz v'lo yeira'eh l'cha se'or b'chol gevulecha. Then והגדת לבנך ביום
ההוא לאמר בעבור זה עשה... v'higadta l'vincha bayom hahu leimor ba'avur zeh
asah...
Okay, so there's בעבור זה ba'avur zeh going on,
the eating of the מצה matzah and not having the חמץ. chametz.
Okay, so there you're right. So there, okay, so in that case
actually it does fit better because the context is in the אכילת
מצה, achilas matzah, so it is—it's okay, there it does make sense
that the פסח Pesach is being excluded. That's fine. So anyway, what's
worth coming out from this גמרא Gemara is the following, is that
number one, again, within the—it's like the sense of רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, כל שלא אמר שלשה דברים אלו בפסח, kol shelo amar shlosha
devarim eilu b'Pesach, the very tight tie-in of the מצוה mitzvah הגדה
Haggadah to the מצוות mitzvos of the eating of the night. Number
one, the thing that is actually agreed upon is that if מצה
matzah was דרבנן, d'rabanan, הגדה Haggadah would be דרבנן. d'rabanan. That the—that
clearly the מצה matzah relies on—the obligation of הגדה Haggadah is
to... and that's how we know you say it that night and
so on, but since it's not clear in the פסוקים psukim that
the מצוה mitzvah of הגדה haggadah is that night. If you look
at the פסוקים psukim closely, that's why the whole הגדה haggadah opens
with יכול מראש חודש, Yachol me-rosh chodesh, יכול מבעוד יום. Yachol mib-od
yom. It's not clear when you're saying it. חז"ל Chazal make it
that you say it because of the פסוק pasuk of בעבור זה
ba'avur zeh that connects it to the things that you are doing,
the ritual eatings you're doing that night. Which means that were the
מצוה mitzvah of מצה matzah דרבנן, d'rabannan, there would not be a
מצוה mitzvah of הגדה. haggadah. The only reason הגדה haggadah is דאורייתא
d'oraisa is because מצה matzah is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. That's point number one.
Point number two is רבן גמליאל'ס Rabban Gamliel's statement which is כל
שלא אמר שלושה דברים אלו. kol shelo amar shlosha devarim eilu. Now
some ראשונים Rishonim take that literally. If you really don't in your
הגדה haggadah describe the significance of the פסח, Pesach, of the מצה
matzah and מרור—presumably maror דאורייתא d'oraisa would only have to be the
מצה matzah nowadays but anyway—if you don't describe the significance of those
objects, you're not יוצא. yotzei. The מצוה mitzvah of הגדה haggadah really
does require integrating those objects. Some say it means you're not ideally
יוצא, yotzei, בדיעבד b'di'eved you're יוצא, yotzei, but certainly fundamentally it's very
integrated. And as I said, the whole שאלות she'eilos that you're responding
to are questions about the eatings of that night. To the point
that the גמרא Gemara thinks it's possible that if you can't directly
see them, that that would not be able to fulfill the obligation
and סומא פטור. suma patur. That it rejects. Okay, but still what
is not being rejected is this tight tie-in to the אכילה, achilah,
to the מצה, matzah, מרור maror and פסח Pesach when there was
of the evening. And the other thing again to underscore also is
the idea that it was clear that the way they had the
סדר seder arrangement was that some ask and the leader answers. One
person is saying, and is that a type of שומע כעונה? shomei'a
k'oneh? Is that a type of everybody is part of this telling
of the story? You don't have to necessarily narrate it yourself, but
it's very clear that that was the structure. ישר כח. Yasher koach.
Yes, but how could you even have the הוה אמינא hava amina
that the מצה matzah would be דרבנן? d'rabannan? Because there's no פסח?
Pesach? Oh, because there's no פסח. Pesach. Okay.
פשט Pshat of the פסוקים psukim is that מצה...
matzah... right, פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim is either מצה matzah
seven days or מצה matzah is only with the פסח. Pesach. It's
a very big חידוש chiddush to say as we do that מצה
matzah exists as an independent מצוה mitzvah just for the first night.
And the second thing on my printed page of the גמרא Gemara
there's another indication in רש"י Rashi that there'd be a משנה. Mishnah.
But what... Yeah, yeah, we had a huge משנה. Mishnah. We had
a huge משנה. Mishnah. The רשב"ם Rashbam makes it clear that the
way he had it was he broke it up into two משניות.
mishnayos. Okay. So the משנה Mishnah we have before... some comments to
the רשב"ם Rashbam above and that was just going after the comments
on the גמרא Gemara to the comments... Yeah, the רשב"ם Rashbam had
the second half of the משנה Mishnah as a separate משנה. Mishnah.
Okay. And now we pick up with the second half of the
משנה. Mishnah. לפיכך... Lefichach... Yes, Rivka. Yes, the statement 'whatever the rabbi
says is so-so.' That seems like an arrogant kind of statement, but
my question is: who is included under רבנן? rabbanan? Every rabbi? All
the rabbis? כל דתקון רבנן כעין דאורייתא תקון. Kol d'tikkun rabbanan k'ein
d'oraisa tikkun. It means a general rabbinic approach. Yeah. All of them?
Yeah, yeah. It means the general approach is that when we extend
biblical מצוות mitzvos or when we pattern a rabbinic מצוה mitzvah after
a biblical מצוה, mitzvah, we try to follow the structure of the
biblical... No, no. It's talking about a rabbinic approach. But that's building
in an ongoing evolutionary process that as time goes on, whatever the
rabbis decide it's like it's in the תורה. Torah. No, they're not
saying it's like it's in the תורה. Torah. כעין דאורייתא תיקון K'ein
d'oraisa tikkun means the way they make their תקנה takkana is trying
to follow the example set in the תורה. Torah. So they're trying
to use the pattern and the structures that exist in the תורה.
Torah. They're not saying it has תורה Torah weight. They're saying they
take their cue from the way the תורה Torah created the מצוות
mitzvos and created the obligations and who's obligated and who's exempt, and
they will make their rabbinic institutions in a similar manner as the
biblical ones. That's what it's saying. It's talking about the way in
which they create the shape of their תקנות, takkunos, not the weight
of their תקנות. takkunos. If you're broken, it would still be... Where
is that? Actually, it's just in reference to מצה. matzah. Right, that's
what Michael was saying. So I stand corrected on that point. Other
parts do connect to the... like when it says מה העבודה הזאת
לכם, mah ha-avodah ha-zos lachem, that's talking about the עבודה avodah of
the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Right. But yes, I stand corrected. The
בעבור זה, ba'avur zeh, although it's funny that חז"ל Chazal throw in
the מרור, maror, okay, because מרור maror is rabbinic nowadays. But yes,
in the context, בעבור זה ba'avur zeh is very much בעבור מצה.
ba'avur matzah. Okay. Fine. Moving on. לפיכך אנחנו חייבים. Lefichach anachnu chayavim.
Therefore obligated. אמר רב חסדא אמר רב יוחנן. Amar Rav Chisda amar
Rav Yochanan. So now we get into a whole bit of a
digression because we mentioned ונאמר לפניו שירה חדשה הללויה. v'nomar lefanav shira
chadasha Hallelujah. So now we're going to discuss הללויה. Hallelujah. ונאמר לפניו
הללויה. v'nomar lefanav Hallelujah. Okay. אמר רב יוחנן. Amar Rav Yochanan. הללויה,
Hallelujah, כס יה, Kes Yah, ידיד יה, Yedid Yah, אחת הן. achas
hen. So are these words as they appear in תורה Torah and
תנ"ך, Tanach, are they one word or two words? So then the
question is going to be: is the יה Yah
by itself and therefore the name of God and therefore קודש? kodesh?
So he says הללויה Hallelujah is one word, כס יה, Kes Yah,
which we say is two words.
כי יד על כס יה מלחמה לה׳ בעמלק, Ki Yad Al Kaisa
Ya Milchama L'Hashem B'Amalek, and yes, and either you can check and
ידידיה Yedidya which is one of the names of שלמה. Shlomo. So
those are all one word. רב Rav אמר amar כסיה Kaisa Ya
ומרחביה u'Merchavya אחת הן. achas hen.
כסיה Kaisa Ya and מרחביה Merchavya are one word, he doesn't address
the other two. רבה Rabba אמר amar מרחביה בלבד, Merchavya bilvad, only
מרחביה Merchavya is one word, all
the others are two words. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya Lehu, so מרחביה Merchavya
is I think here spelled as two, רב חסדא מאי, Rav Chisda
Mai, רב חסדא Rav Chisda didn't address מרחביה. Merchavya. What did he
say? תיקו, Teiku, we don't know. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya Lehu, ידידיה Yedidya
לרב מאי?
L'Rav Mai? What would רב Rav say about ידידיה? Yedidya? Because רב
Rav said כסיה Kaisa Ya and מרחביה, Merchavya, he didn't say only
כסיה Kaisa Ya and מרחביה, Merchavya, so what would he say about
ידידיה? Yedidya? What would he say about הללויה? Hallelujah? So the גמרא
Gemara says תא שמע דאמר רב Ta Shma d'amar Rav, ידידיה Yedidya
נחלק לשנים, nechlakh l'shnayim, that he says clearly ידידיה Yedidya is two.
That לפיכך l'fichach ידיד חול יה קודש, Yedid chol Ya Kodesh, that
actually that word
is a separate word of God, it's not all one word with
a God you know sort of suffix to it, it's two separate
words and the יה Ya part is קודש. Kodesh. And in a
ספר תורה Sefer Torah כסיה Kaisa Ya was written, that's what it
would according to רב חסדא Rav Chisda אמר רב יוחנן, amar Rav
Yochanan, that's the way it would seem unless you find that there's
another כסיה Kaisa Ya somewhere in the תורה, Torah, somewhere in תנ״ך.
Tanakh. What does מרחביה Merchavya mean? I'd have to look, I assume
it's a name of a place, you know. ענני במרחביה, Anani B'Merchavya,
oh that's true, ענני במרחב יה. Anani B'merchav Ya. So what does
it mean if it doesn't mean God answered me broadly? Right, it
does mean broadly but מרחב, merchav, oh you mean if it's two
words, yeah, מרחב, merchav, God answered me broadly. Yeah, but ענני Anani
could be, God could be the assumed subject and God answered me
במרחב, b'merchav, right, ענני במרחב. Anani B'merchav. He answered me with an
openness, with expansiveness, the God as the subject is assumed, right. So
what does יה Ya do? So we'll see in a minute, יה
Ya might just be a way of like of a you know
of an emphasize, what's the word? Like what's the word very, what's
that called? Like an intensifier, right. So it might be just like
a that type of an intensifier, it doesn't mean God. You know,
in שלמה's Shlomo name it means God, but in הללויה Hallelujah it
means God, other places it might just be as we'll see in
a minute, it might just be an intensifier. Okay, but yes, you're
right, במרחביה b'Merchavya is that פסוק pasuk in הלל Hallel exactly, ענני
במרחב יה. Anani B'merchav Ya. And here we see יה Ya looks,
רב Rav says מרחביה Merchavya is one, we read it, we have
it as two, right? So let's take a look. So maybe we
פסקן, pasken, actually yes, so let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says איבעיא להו, Iba'ya Lehu, הללויה Hallelujah לרב מאי? L'Rav Mai?
What would רב Rav say about הללויה? Hallelujah? He didn't address the
הללויה Hallelujah case. Actually, didn't רבה Rabba say בלבד? bilvad? Oh, no,
that was רבה Rabba who said בלבד. bilvad. Oh, רב Rav just
said כסיה Kaisa Ya and מרחביה. Merchavya. What would רב Rav say
about הללויה? Hallelujah? תא שמע Ta Shma דאמר רב, d'amar Rav רב
Rav said חזינא תהלי דבי חביבי, chazina Thilli d'bei Chavivi, I saw
the תהלים, Tehillim, a ספר תהלים Sefer Tehillim in the house of
my beloved one, which was talking about his uncle רב חסדא, Rav
Chisda, דכתיב בהו הללו בחד גיסא, d'chtiv behu Hallu b'chad gisa, the
word הללו Hallu is written at the end of one line, ויה
בחד גיסא, v'Ya b'chad gisa, and יה Ya at the beginning of
the next line. So he understood it's two words, if it was
one word you don't split a word. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda
but רב Rav was in disagreement? Presumably he did not, he did
not say that he disagreed with it, so we're assuming that that's
his position. ופליגא דרבי יהושע בן לוי, U'pliga d'Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi,
that argues with רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, דאמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי, d'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, מאי הללויה? Mai
Hallelujah? What does הללויה Hallelujah mean? הללוהו בהילולים הרבה, Hallulhu b'hillulim harbeh,
and here's what I was saying a minute ago to Dov, the
יה Ya even if it's one word, right, it doesn't mean praise
God, that presumably is what it would mean if it was two
words. So הללויה Hallelujah means, you know, you know, give many praises,
the יה Ya is an intensifier. Of course it could mean God
but it could just still be one one you know one word.
Anyway, but here he understands that the יה Ya in that case
could be an intensifier. ופליגא דידיה אדידיה, U'pliga dideyh a'dideyh, and he
argues on himself, not in terms of whether it's one word or
two words but what the יה Ya suffix means. דאמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי, D'amar Rabbi Yehoshua Ben Levi, בעשרה מאמרות
של שבח נאמר
ספר תהלים,
B'asara ma'amaros shel
shevach ne'emar
Sefer Tehillim, ספר תהלים Sefer Tehillim has
ten different words that it uses for praise, for the תהלים Tehillim
that are in there, you know, and what are they? בניצוח, B'nitzuach,
ניצוח, Nitzuach, למנצח מזמור לדוד, Lamnatzeach Mizmor L'David, בניגון, B'nigun, you know,
also some type of instrument,
במשכיל, B'maskil, משכיל לדוד, Maskil L'David, מזמור, Mizmor, שיר, Shir, אשרי, Ashrei,
אשרי האיש אשר לא הלך, Ashrei Ha'ish Asher Lo Halach, תהילה לדוד,
Tehilla L'David, תהילה, Tehilla, בתפילה, B'tefilla, ובהודאה, v'B'hoda'ah, ובהללויה. v'B'Hallelujah. גדול מכולן
הללויה, Gadol mi'kulan Hallelujah, the one that creates that emphasizes the greatest
sense of praise and song is הללויה, Hallelujah, why? שכולל שם ושבח
בבת אחת, Shekolel Shem v'Shevach b'vas achas, because that has God's name
in the name of praise itself. So again he tells that it's
one word but he holds the יה Ya there means God. So
הללויה Hallelujah means praise God, but as one word, not as two
separate words. Okay, where are we? Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל,
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, שיר שבתורה משה וישראל אמרוהו בשעה שעלו
מן הים. Shir she'baTorah Moshe v'Yisrael amruhu b'shaa she'alu min hayam. So
it's clear of course that אז ישיר Az Yashir was said with
משה Moshe and בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael when they came up from
the ים סוף. Yam Suf. והלל זה מי אמרו? V'Hallel zeh mi
amaro? But who said הלל? Hallel? Okay, which is the whole הלל
Hallel we always incorporate into all of our... ימים טובים yamim tovim
and our מצוות, mitzvos, and who said it? Where did it, when
was it, where did it originate? Why don't they think it was
just? Let's take a look. So, נביאים שביניהם תיקנו להם לישראל, Nevi'im
she-beineihem tiknu lahem le-Yisrael, so he according to him he says that
it was the prophets, now this doesn't tell you exactly when, which
prophets, but the prophets amongst them established for Israel that they would
say it על כל פרק ופרק al kol perek va-perek on every
on every designated time, which the רשב"ם Rashbam says means at every
holiday, on every יום טוב, yom tov, number one, ועל כל צרה
וצרה, ve-al kol tzarah va-tzarah, and also in any time of affliction
שלא תבוא עליהן, she-lo tavo aleihen, God willing it should never happen,
וכשנגאלין, u-kshe-nigalin, when they're redeemed אומרים אותו על גאולתן. omerim oso al
geulasan. They say it on their redemption. So meaning that presumably is
coming to include something like פורים, Purim, not פורים Purim because they
don't say it, חנוכה, Chanukah, I don't know what other thing it
would be, חנוכה. Chanukah. Anyway, you know, but the fact about saying
it at at moments of redemption. Now some that's the way the
רשב"ם Rashbam reads it that פרק ופרק perek va-perek already identify יום
טוב. yom tov. You could say פרק ופרק וצרה וצרה perek va-perek
ve-tzarah va-tzarah is all basically a one way of saying the same
thing that whenever something tragic happened they would say it on the
גאולה. geulah. But the problem is that something like, you know, סוכות
Succos is not about צרה שלא תבוא עליהם. tzarah she-lo tavo aleihem.
So so it really is why the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it as
פרק ופרק perek va-perek is יום טוב yom tov and על כל
צרה שלא תבוא עליהם. al kol tzarah she-lo tavo aleihem. Of course
what falls in the שלא כל צרה שלא תבוא עליהם she-lo kol
tzarah she-lo tavo aleihem other than, right, סוכות Succos not, שבועות Shavuos
not, פסח, Pesach, yes, okay, that that would all be called פרק.
perek. So what is it? Is it פסח Pesach and חנוכה? Chanukah?
Yes. Those are really the only other times they say הלל, Hallel,
the נביאים, nevi'im, it could be that you know the מלך בני
עמון Melech Bnei Amon and you know there's always wars. Right. So
what it could mean is is that they would say this not
in some formal like not in the way we have it currently
in our סידור. siddur. What they're really saying is throughout the biblical
period, throughout the period of the נביאים, nevi'im, this was the way,
the standard way in which בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael would praise God
even when you know not in some ritualized you know fixed time
as we have it associated with holidays. This was always these פרקים
perakim in תהילים, Tehillim, yes and I do think that that is
the correct point, that they're saying these פרקים perakim in תהילים Tehillim
were always the ones used historically to praise God at various ימים
טובים, yamim tovim, at various times of צרה, tzarah, and we continue
that practice today, you know, in the context in which we say
it, which also, you know, raises important questions about the issue about
like establishing this for יום העצמאות Yom HaAtzmaut and יום ירושלים Yom
Yerushalayim and so on once you sort of lay that idea that
this has always historically been what we have said. Yes. I just
wanted to make sure that I understood the modifying of שלא תבוא
עליהם. she-lo tavo aleihem. So שלא תבוא עליהם she-lo tavo aleihem is
a parenthetical remark. Yes. Yes. Like we mentioned צרה, tzarah, we don't
we're not trying to say that you say it before prophylactically. No
no no no no. So שלא תבוא עליהם she-lo tavo aleihem is
parenthetical. God willing it should never happen when it happens they would
say it על גאולתן. al geulasan. Okay, so according to that, it's
right, not necessarily emphasizing our current liturgy, but our current but you
know that it was always said historically at these moments, and now
we say it as well. But again, what it does give is
it gives a little punch because now we don't identify הלל Hallel
so much as redemption from צרה, tzarah, you know, maybe we do
when we're saying it on פסח. Pesach. But anyway, but here it's
saying that that was really like a prime use of it. תניא
היה רבי מאיר אומר. Tanya haya Rabi Meir omer. We taught in
a ברייתא, braisa, רבי מאיר Rabi Meir used to say כל תשבחות
האמורות בספר תהילים, kol tushbachos ha-amuros be-sefer Tehillim, כולם דוד אמרם. kulam
David amram. דוד David said all of them. שנאמר Shene'emar because it
says, this is right in the middle of תהילים, Tehillim, כלו תפילות
דוד בן ישי. kalu tefillos David ben Yishai. The prayers of דוד
בן ישי David ben Yishai are ceased, meaning if you read that
פסוק pasuk literally it means everything after that פסוק pasuk was not
from דוד. David. Okay, problem is that there are things afterwards that
say that they're from דוד. David. Anyway, אל תקרי כלו אלא כל
אלו. al tikri kalu ela kol elu. Don't read ceased, but all
of these. כל אלו kol elu meaning all the ones not just
before but everything in the whole book is from דוד. David. So
דוד David wrote every single thing in תהילים, Tehillim, even the ones
that say תפילה למשה, tefillah le-Moshe, לבני קרח מזמור, le-vnei Korach mizmor,
it means that he's doing it in their name but it doesn't
mean that they wrote it. Okay. So הלל זה מי אמרו? Hallel
zeh mi amru? So who wrote the הלל? Hallel? Fascinating. After saying
everything is from דוד, David, somehow there was still a sense that
the הלל Hallel was this like ancient thing and we'll see the
גמרא Gemara is going to say something that would was always said
and therefore we question whether it's really possible that it was only
דוד, David, what what it was דוד David who said it or
whether it had been said earlier. So מי אמרו? mi amru? Who
wrote it? רבי יוסי אומר. Rabi Yossi omer. רבי יוסי Rabi Yossi
says, אלעזר בני אומר. Elazar beni omer. אלעזר Elazar my son says,
משה וישראל אמרוהו, Moshe ve-Yisrael amruhu, that it actually existed way back
when, it was said by משה וישראל Moshe ve-Yisrael בשעה שעלו מן
הים. be-sha'ah she-alu min ha-yam. So before, you know, which is contrast
before we said when they were עולים מן הים olim min ha-yam
they said אז ישיר, Az Yashir, now we're saying and but you
understand it's like well when they got up they said אז ישיר,
Az Yashir, who said הלל? Hallel? So in a way it's it's
almost laying the groundwork for saying, you know what, the same way
they said אז ישיר Az Yashir they said הלל. Hallel. They they
established right they established this became the way of praising God in
future as well.
אז ישיר Az Yashir was just for the ים. yam. הלל Hallel
was a something that became established
to always say at a particularly at a time of גאולה. geulah.
So that's what אלעזר Elazar my son says. וחלוקין עליו חבריו לא
מה שדוד אמר v'chalukin alav chaveirav lo mah sheDavid amar and his
colleagues disagree and say that's a little bit going a little too
far. No, I'm sorry, let's assume דוד David said it like the
rest of תהלים. Tehillim. ונראה דברי. v'nireh divrei. You know what? I
actually think he's right. Why do I think he's right? אפשר ישראל
שחטו את פסחיהן ונטלו לולביהן ולא אמרו שירה. efshar Yisrael shachtu et
pischeihen v'natlu lulaveihen v'lo amru shirah. Is it possible we had this
before that ישראל Yisrael all those years before דוד David were slaughtering
their קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and taking their לולב lulav and not
singing, not saying praise? Obviously, they must have been praising God, and
if they must have been praising God, somehow, I don't know, obviously
it must have been this text. And therefore, it must be that
this text predated דוד. David. It could not have been that we
didn't have some way of praising God with some type of a
text prior to דוד. David. דבר אחר, davar acher, another explanation of
why I think it must have existed earlier. פסלו של מיכה עומד
בבכי. pislo shel Michah omeid b'vechi. The idol of מיכה Michah was
standing in בבכי b'vechi in crying, but you know the רשב"ם Rashbam
says it's a euphemism meaning standing around and laughing, meaning it's clear
that you know they had this idol of מיכה Michah which is
earlier in תנ"ך. Tanakh. But there's a suggestion here that it existed
even up to the time of דוד. David. וישראל אומרים את ההלל
v'Yisrael omrim et haHallel and at that time דוד David would write
a הלל Hallel that says in it, you know, that all of
the פסלים psalim should be, what's the פסוק pasuk from הלל? Hallel?
עינים להם ולא יראו, אזנים להם ולא ישמעו, einayim lahem v'lo yiru,
oznayim lahem v'lo yishme'u, right, etc. So couldn't it be it was
composed at a time when there was still עבודה זרה avodah zarah
in the land? It must have been composed earlier, maybe in that
short little honeymoon period between יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim and the עגל.
Eigel. So at that time, so it must have been composed before
there was עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Anyway, that's a stranger answer. But
it's fascinating the point because, okay, let's assume that you say it
must be they must have used some form of way of saying
הלל Hallel to God until the time of דוד. David. It didn't
mean it had to be this text. Why are we assuming this
text? Now obviously, the fact that the second פרק perek says בצאת
ישראל ממצרים, b'tzeit Yisrael miMitzrayim, you know, gives us a push to
say it was like maybe written at that time. But still the
astounding how could it be, you know, must doesn't lead you to
say necessarily this text. The other thing that's interesting is the shift,
right? We've had כל פרק ופרק kol perek u'perek which relates to
according to the רשב"ם Rashbam as יום טוב. Yom Tov. We've had
a particular emphasis of historically they would use this at times when
צרה tzarah was come to them that they would and they would
be redeemed, this is what they would sing out to God. בשעה
שנוטלין לולביהן ושוחטין את פסחיהן. b'sha'ah she'notlin lulaveihen v'shochtin et pischeihen. What
does that have to do? That's not בעת צרה, b'eit tzarah, you
know, he made that whole shift. Obviously, משה Moshe said it and
they should always say it when they're נגאלו nige'alu and they're עולים
מן הים olim min haYam and all of a sudden, oh, of
course משה Moshe had to say it because they needed something to
say when they were taking their לולב. lulav. So you know, it's
what are the assumed sort of motivators or obligators to say הלל?
Hallel? You know, why is where is it so obvious that הלל
Hallel must be said? We have three things put out there: יום
טוב, Yom Tov, right, גאולה, Geulah, and somehow the doing of these
מצוות. mitzvot. Now what's the significance of the doing of these מצוות
mitzvot is not clear to me. It could tie into יום טוב
Yom Tov and let's say the שמחת יום טוב simchat Yom Tov
and so on and maybe particularly when you're doing the מצוות, mitzvot,
it's a type of תפילה. tefillah. If we think about the shaking
of the לולב, lulav, right, we do in שול shul or whatever,
the type of a תפילה, tefillah, the bringing of the קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, you're in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So maybe it's
also like within the יום טוב Yom Tov context but particularly in
that moment of connecting to God and doing these מצוות mitzvot and
that's where you have to connect it to the הלל. Hallel. That
seems to be why it connects it to those two. It's interesting,
it doesn't connect it to when you sit in a סוכה, sukkah,
right? We sit in a סוכה sukkah not say, we don't say
הלל Hallel when we sit in a סוכה. sukkah. So again, it's
a type of a ritual of a יום טוב Yom Tov that's
really seen as a type of a תפילה. tefillah. What's also interesting
I should say and remind you is the גמרא Gemara earlier said
that when you bring a פסח שני, Pesach Sheini, you say הלל
Hallel at the bringing of the פסח Pesach but not at the
eating of the פסח. Pesach. And so there seems that this הלל
Hallel of the eating of the פסח Pesach requires this like יום
טוב Yom Tov component. And so somehow the שחיטה shechitah of the
פסח Pesach has greater weight even without יום טוב Yom Tov you
can have it, but you can understand, again, you're in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, so that creates that greater sense. Whereas when you're
not in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you're taking your לולב lulav
or you're eating the פסח, Pesach, it's a combination of it also
being a יום טוב. Yom Tov. So it's interesting the intersection of
יום טוב Yom Tov plus these rituals which have a תפילה tefillah
component. But those are three separate ideas about where we see it's
so obvious that you have to say הלל, Hallel, and because of
that push the גמרא Gemara wants to assume that this has been
ancient and they've always been doing it and always been doing it
with this text, which is fascinating. Yeah, it's interesting that taking the
לולב, lulav, I mean, ושמחתם לפני ה' אלקיכם. u'shmachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeichem.
It's like משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu was taking a לולב, lulav, you
know, having ערבות, aravot, ערבי נחל arvei nachal in the מדבר? Midbar?
I mean, it's just it seems very interesting that they're even doing
it at that path point, you know? Alright, I'm going to hang
there. Okay, fine. But it is true that the end of the
לולב lulav is ושמחתם לפני ה' אלקיכם u'shmachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeichem and
again there it does, yes, as the point I was making, connects
the לולב lulav to in this sort of connecting with God, encountering
God and so on. Now what I do would like, you know
what, I would like to point out, I have this whole thing
I'm not going to read it, but if people want, the רמב"ן,
Ramban, רמב"ם Rambam in the beginning of ספר מצוות Sefer Mitzvot go,
you know sort of critiques the בה"ג Ba'hag who has his... list
of 613 and רמב"ם *Rambam* felt he did it without any system
and without any rules. And one of the things that he felt,
so he begins his ספר המצוות *Sefer Hamitzvos* with 14 rules of
how to determine whether something is a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* or not.
And the first one is, you only count things that are biblical
מצוות *mitzvos* not rabbinic. And he critiques the בה"ג *Bahag* for including
rabbinic things like נר חנוכה *Ner Chanukah*. One of the things that
he critiques the בה"ג *Bahag* for including is הלל Hallel? *Hallel*. He
says, how could the בה"ג *Bahag* think הלל Hallel *Hallel* is דאורייתא
*de-Oraisa*? I mean, you know, we say תהלים Tehillim *Tehillim* there that
was written by דוד המלך *Dovid Hamelech*. So how could he think
it was דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*? So the רמב"ן *Ramban* has a long defense
of the בה"ג *Bahag* in general, but particularly on this. He says,
first of all, I don't understand what's bothering you רמב"ם *Rambam*. You
say דאווענען *davenning* every day is דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*. דאווענען *Davenning* clearly the
text wasn't written till אנשי כנסת הגדולה *Anshei Knesses Hagedolah*. So you
could have a biblical obligation without the text having been the particular
text having been written till much later. בענטשן *Benching* is דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*.
Doesn't mean that this particular text had to be written earlier. So
הלל Hallel. *Hallel* could be דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*, it's just the text was
written later. And he says besides which, if you read פסחים *Pesachim*,
you see there are many opinions that the text actually was much
earlier. And anyway, so whether the text always existed or not is
he says number one it could have existed earlier, and number two
even if it didn't, the obligation could be דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*. And he
says I really think says the רמב"ן *Ramban* that הלל Hallel *Hallel*
is דאורייתא *de-Oraisa* and he quotes other גמרות *Gemaras* that make it
sound like הלל Hallel *Hallel* might actually be דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*. So then
he asks himself, if it's דאורייתא *de-Oraisa*, where's the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*?
Yeah, what's the פסוק pasuk? *pasuk* say that it's מן התורה *min
ha-Torah*? So he says either הלכה halacha, למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai*,
okay, that's a... or he says maybe this is part of the
מצות שמחת יום טוב *mitzvas simchas yom tov* and therefore maybe part
of שמחת יום טוב *simchas yom tov* the way of doing שמחה
simcha, *simcha*, you know, ושמחת לפני ה' *v'samachta l'fnei Hashem* whereas שמחה
simcha. *simcha* is בבשר ושלמים *b'basar u'shlamim*, שמחה simcha *simcha* is not
just filling of your stomach, it's in the encounter of God and
part of the שמחה *simcha* is the saying of הלל Hallel *Hallel*
before God, again, not necessarily this text. Okay, but that's interesting because
that underscores the פרק perek? ופרק *perek u'perek*, you know, that idea
that it's a יום טוב *yom tov* and it's connected to שמחת
יום טוב *simchas yom tov* and as we've seen there are these
three ideas: פרק perek. ופרק *perek u'perek*, גאולה geulah, *geulah*, and this
idea of נוטלים לולביהם *notlim lulaveihem* which connects to the יום טוב
*yom tov* but in particular mode connecting to the יום טוב *yom
tov*. Yes. For that argument, we ought to be singing הלל Hallel
*Hallel* in the סוכה *Sukkah*. Well, you say you don't do it,
you don't have to do it every minute, right? You do it
on יום טוב *yom tov*. So fine, we do it on יום
טוב *yom tov*, we do it in שול *shul*, yeah. I thought
the רמב"ם *Rambam*'s argument was that עבודה שבלב *avoda shebalev* is דאורייתא
*de-Oraisa* but the text... Yes, so that's what the רמב"ן *Ramban* says.
If that's what the רמב"ן *Ramban* says, you רמב"ם *Rambam* are willing
to concede that by תפילה tefillah *tfila*, why do you think it's
absurd to say the same thing if you say make the same
argument by הלל Hallel. *Hallel*? And the רמב"ן *Ramban* actually says that
הלל Hallel *Hallel* is דאורייתא *de-Oraisa* and he really thinks it's possible
that and he says when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says נביאים שביניהם
תיקנו *neviim shebeinehem tiknu*, that could also be saying who are the
נביאים שביניהם *neviim shebeinehem*? משה *Moshe*, מרים *Miriam*, אהרן *Aharon*. So he
thinks that even that line of נביאים שביניהם *neviim shebeinehem* is a
saying that this really is very ancient. And that's in the רמב"ן
*Ramban*'s השגות *hassagous* on ספר המצוות *Sefer Hamitzvos*. Yeah, if you want
I have a copy of it here. Let's keep on going. תנו
רבנן tanu rabbanan, *Tanu rabanan*. כל שיר ושבחות שנאמרו בספר תהלים Tehillim,
*Kol shir u'shvachot shene'emru b'sefer Tehillim*, so all of the praises that
are said in תהלים *Tehillim*, רבי Rebbe אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* אומר *omer*
כנגד עצמו אמרם *k'neged atzmo amram*. He said it about himself, you
know you read some of them and it's בבורחו מפני אבשלום בנו
*b'borcho mipnei Avshalom b'no* or whatever, you know it sounds like he's
talking about his own travails. רבי Rebbe יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* אומר *omer*
כנגד ציבור אמרם *k'neged tzibbur amram*. No, he said them representing the,
you know, what what has faced or what will face, you know,
he said it in the voice for the sake of that's when
he said it, but when he was that's that was the context
the historical context in which he said it, but when he was
saying it he was saying it to speak for כלל ישראל *Klal
Yisrael*. Okay. So וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim, *v'chachamim omrim* ישנם כנגד ציבור
וישנם כנגד עצמו *yeshnem k'neged tzibbur v'yeshnem k'neged atzmo*. Some he's speaking
for himself, some he's speaking for כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael*. האמור בלשון
יחיד *Hamur bilashon yachid* when they're
in the in the first person in the first person singular כנגד
עצמו *k'neged atzmo*.
האמור *Hamur* they're about himself. האמור בלשון רבים *Hamur bilashon rabim* when
they're said in the plural כנגד ציבור *k'neged tzibbur*. Okay, that's a
nice distinction.
ניצוח וניגון *Nitzuach v'niggun* now we
have a traditions about what some of these opening words mean, you
know, some people
say there's a question what some of
them mean, some people mean they're like signals to exactly the music
that
was supposed to be played along. Anyway so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ניצוח וניגון *nitzuach v'niggun* when a
תהלים *Tehillim* opens with that, תפילה tefillah לעתיד לבוא *tfila l'atid lavo*.
It means that it is a focused on a prophecy or a
hope for the future. משכיל *Maskil* על ידי תורגמן *al yedei turgeman*.
When it says משכיל *maskil* it means that it was recited through
some type of a translator or you know he somebody would say
it and another person would repeat it.
So that's somehow they
understood that was what משכיל *maskil* meant. They really understand what you
were saying? Yeah well מזמור *Mizmor* how about מזמור *mizmor*? I'm sorry
לדוד מזמור LeDavid Mizmor *L'Dovid Mizmor*. למלמד ששרתה עליו שכינה shechina. ואחר
כך אמר שירה *L'malmed she-sharta alav shchina v'acharkach amar shira*. So first
it was לדוד *L'Dovid* got and then it was מזמור *mizmor*. First
he had divine inspiration and then he he he sang this. מזמור
לדוד Mizmor LeDavid, *Mizmor L'Dovid* if first it says מזמור *mizmor* and
then it says לדוד *L'Dovid*, so למלמד שאמר שירה *l'malmed she-amar shira*
first he said the song and then it was לדוד *L'Dovid* and
then ואחר כך שרתה עליו שכינה shechina *v'acharkach sharta alav shchina* then
he had divine you know the שכינה shechina *shchina* rested upon him,
which I don't understand what does that mean? Does that well first
of all... Okay, ספר דברים. Okay, למדך lamadcha to ללמדך, lelamedcha, to
teach you, so this all connects in about he sang and then
there was the שכינה. shechina Why did the שכינה wait until after
he sang? To teach you שאינה שכינה שורה לא מתוך עצלות ולא
מתוך עצבות, she'eina shechina shora lo mitoch atzlut velo mitoch atzvut, the
שכינה does not rest upon a person not if they're lazy, not
if they're sad, ולא מתוך שחוק velo mitoch sechok or if they're
frivolous, ולא מתוך קלות ראש, velo mitoch kalut rosh, that's frivolous or
joking around, ולא מתוך דברים בטלים, velo mitoch devarim betelim, not if
you're just, you know, engaged in trivial matters, אלא מתוך דבר שמחה
של מצוה. ela mitoch devar simcha shel mitzvah. The way a person
gets the divine, you know, the שכינה to reside upon them is
that they're doing a מצוה mitzvah and it's and they're getting joy
from the מצוה mitzvah that they are doing. שנאמר, shene'emar, so we
have that by the whole לדוד מזמור or מזמור לדוד, and now
another פסוק. pasuk. ועתה קחו לי מנגן, ve'atah kchu li menagen, take
for me a, you know, a music player. והיה כנגן המנגן ותהי
עליו יד ה'. vehaya kenagen hamenagen vatehi alav yad Hashem. When he
plays, when the musician plays, then the divine inspiration rested upon him.
That and therefore you see you have to be in this joy
state for divine inspiration. But what was the מצוה mitzvah there? The
מצוה was he wanted divine inspiration to reside upon him. Exactly. All
right, moving on. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav, וכן לדבר הלכה, vechen ledvar halacha, it's also for הלכה, halacha
you have to be in a good mood, you have to have
some שמחה, you can't be too anguished or troubled. אמר רב נחמן,
Amar Rav Nachman, it would be really hard to get a פסק
psak if you always had to wait for someone to be in
a... אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, וכן לחלום טוב, vechen lachalom
tov, if you want to have a good dream you should go
to sleep in a state of, you know, joy and שמחה של
מצוה. simcha shel mitzvah. איני? eini? Is that true? ואמר רב גידל
אמר רב, ve'amar Rav Gidel Amar Rav, כל תלמיד חכם היושב לפני
רבו ואין שפתותיו נוטפות מר תכוינה. kol talmid chacham hayoshev lifnei rabbo
ve'ein siftotav notfot mar tichzena. This is challenging the idea that was
said before in the name of רב Rav that with דבר הלכה
dvar halacha you need שמחה. Here we say what's said in the
name of רב Rav that any student that's sitting in front of
his רבי Rebbe and the student's lips are not dripping bitterness like
they're not trembling, right, they're not in dread, so they should be
burned, the lips should be burned, so you have to be in
this dread when you're learning, not in joy. שנאמר שפתותיו שושנים, shene'emar
siftotav shoshanim, his lips are like roses, נוטפות מור עובר, notfot mor
over, they drip with, you know, myrrh, which is a very like
a, you know, beautiful fragrance, so that is, you know, passing myrrh.
אל תקרי שושנים, al tikrei shoshanim, don't read roses, אלא ששונים, ela
sheshonim, lips that are learning. אל תקרי מור עובר, al tikrei mor
over, don't read myrrh, אלא מר עבר. ela mar avar. עובר over
is like passing? Yeah, so anyway, but I think abundant. Oh, מור
עובר mor over abundant myrrh. Okay, that's probably right, probably right. אלא
מר עבר. ela mar avar. So read it rather a, you know,
bitterness that passes over their lips. If they don't have bitterness passing
over their lips, then they can't be learning. So anyway, what about
why you can't study תורה Torah during תשעה באב Tisha B'Av because
of the joy of study? Okay, okay, so let's finish let's see
where the גמרא Gemara, goes. Okay, so so it says לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא ברבה הא בתלמידא. ha berabba ha
betalmida. Answer number one is the רבי's Rebbe allowed to be happy,
the student has to be trembling. Okay, keep that in mind everyone.
So you have to have awe of your רבי Rebbe, and the
רבי's allowed to have the שמחה of engaging in the תורה Torah
and he's the one doing הלכה halacha. and he's the one doing
the הלכה. halacha And if you want you can say הא והא
ברבה, ha veha berabba, they're both actually true about the רבי, ולא
קשיא, velo kashya, it's not difficult. הא מקמי דפתח הא לבתר דפתח.
ha mikmei depatach ha levatar depatach. Is it when you begin or
after you begin? כי הא דרבה, ki ha deRabba, like רבה, Rabba,
מקמי דפתח לרבנן, mikmei depatach lerabbanan, before he opened up to the
again the rabbinic students, אמר מילתא דבדיחותא, amar milta debidichuta, he said
like a little he said a joke, he opened with a joke
or something something a little bit lighthearted. ובדחו רבנן, uvadu rabbanan, and
everybody laughed and you know got them in a good mood. ולבסוף
יתיב באימתא, ulevasof yativ be'eimta, then he sat with a sense of
awe, רבה Rabba himself, ופתח בשמעתא, upatach beshmata, and he opened up.
So presumably it also applies to the student. But the point is
you open to put yourself in a good frame of mind and
then you enter into the nevertheless a sense of awe. Which one
also wonders, you know, whether really are those necessarily contradictory? Can you
have some joy of גילו ברעדה, gilu bir'ada, joy of engaging in
it with a proper sense of the awe and the, you know,
of what it means to be learning תורת ה'? Torat Hashem? But
here the גמרא Gemara is attaining a balance. You want to start
in a way... before you start the שיעור shiur you could be
nervous so... that's interesting. And afterwards, after you get the געשמאק geshmak
of learning. That's interesting. You know, anyway but I will tell you,
you tell a joke people people that's well hopefully the joke helps
them remember everything else you've said but they'll certainly remember the joke.
All right, had such an opportunity to change מור mor to מר.
mar. Right. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, they wanted to use it at
a דרשה. drasha. תנו רבנן, our rabbis taught. הלל זה מי אמרו?
hallel zeh mi amro? We're back to that. Who said הלל? Hallel
Again the sense that it had to be ancient, right, so... Mi
amrah מי אמרה? mi amrah? Rabbi Eliezer omer רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer, Moshe v'Yisrael amru b'sha'ah she'amdu al hayam משה וישראל אמרו
בשעה שעמדו על הים. Moshe v'Yisrael amru b'sha'ah she'amdu al hayam. Moshe
and Yisrael when they stood by the Yam ים, Yam, not when
they were oleh min hayam עולה מן הים. oleh min hayam. And
this is fascinating. This is going to turn the Hallel הלל Hallel
into a prayer as well for geulah גאולה, geulah, not just a
thanks for geulah גאולה, geulah. but a prayer for geulah גאולה. geulah.
Hem amru הם אמרו, Hem amru, one minute, hem amru הם אמרו,
hem amru, lo lanu Hashem לא לנו השם, lo lanu Hashem, not
for us God, meaning lo lanu לא לנו lo lanu is sort
of to say help us, you know, but help us not for
our sake, but for Your sake. But it's a sense of like,
you know, Ana Hashem hoshiah na אנא השם הושיעה נא, Ana Hashem
hoshiah na, right? There's our elements there of bakashah בקשה bakashah in
the Hallel הלל. Hallel. Lo lanu לא לנו, lo lanu, lo lanu
Hashem lo lanu לא לנו השם לא לנו. lo lanu Hashem lo
lanu. Meshiva Ruach Hakodesh משיבה רוח הקודש Meshiva Ruach Hakodesh and God
responds, the heavenly spirit responds, v'omer lahem ואומר להם, v'omer lahem, l'ma'ani
l'ma'ani e'eseh למעני למעני אעשה. l'ma'ani l'ma'ani e'eseh. I will save you
for My sake. Don't worry, I will save you and it'll be
for My sake, not for your sake. Because it's for Our sake,
we're not worthy, but God will do it for God's sake. Interesting
of course, that's from Yeshayahu ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. So, alright. Rabbi Yehuda omer
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Yehoshua v'Yisrael amru b'sha'ah she'amdu aleihem
malchei Kanaan יהושע וישראל אמרו בשעה שעמדו עליהם מלכי כנען, Yehoshua v'Yisrael
amru b'sha'ah she'amdu aleihem malchei Kanaan, when they were Yehoshua and Yisrael
when they were fighting the kings of Canaan. Hem amru lo lanu
הם אמרו לא לנו, Hem amru lo lanu, meshiva v'chulu משיבה וכולי.
meshiva v'chulu. Rabbi Eliezer HaModai omer רבי אליעזר המודעי אומר, Rabbi Eliezer
HaModai omer, Devorah u'Barak amru b'sha'ah she'amad aleihem Sisra דבורה וברק אמרו
בשעה שעמד עליהם סיסרא. Devorah u'Barak amru b'sha'ah she'amad aleihem Sisra. Devorah,
Barak, hem amru lo lanu הם אמרו לא לנו, hem amru lo
lanu, v'Ruach Hakodesh meshiva v'omeret lahem משיבה ואומרת להם, v'Ruach Hakodesh meshiva
v'omeret lahem, l'ma'ani l'ma'ani e'eseh למעני למעני אעשה. l'ma'ani l'ma'ani e'eseh. Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah omer רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah omer, Chizkiyah v'siato amruah חזקיה וסיעתו אמרוה, Chizkiyah v'siato amruah, b'sha'ah
she'amad aleihem Sancheiriv בשעה שעמד עליהם סנחריב. b'sha'ah she'amad aleihem Sancheiriv. Hem
amru lo lanu הם אמרו לא לנו, Hem amru lo lanu, meshiva
v'chulu משיבה וכולי. meshiva v'chulu. Rabbi Akiva omer רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi
Akiva omer, Chananyah Mishael v'Azaryah amruah חנניה מישאל ועזריה אמרוה. Chananyah Mishael
v'Azaryah amruah. No, it was always Chananyah Mishael v'Azaryah, b'sha'ah she'amad aleihem
Nevuchadnetzar rasha בשעה שעמד עליהם נבוכדנצר רשע. b'sha'ah she'amad aleihem Nevuchadnetzar rasha.
Hem amru lo lanu הם אמרו לא לנו, Hem amru lo lanu,
meshiva v'chulu משיבה וכולי. meshiva v'chulu. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer, we're going in historical order if
you haven't figured that out. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer רבי יוסי הגלילי
אומר, Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer, Mordechai v'Esther amruah בשעה שעמד עליהם המן
הרשע. Mordechai v'Esther amruah b'sha'ah she'amad aleihem Haman harasha. Hem amru lo
lanu הם אמרו לא לנו, Hem amru lo lanu, meshiva v'chulu משיבה
וכולי. meshiva v'chulu. Okay, now the Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam says, he says
there's one interpretation which he doesn't like, but I think reads nicely,
which is nobody's arguing. You know, it's all a way of saying
this was always said at all periods and at all times, as
you know, through history. But whatever, and it also reminds you of
some of like the types of things that you get for like
the Selichot סליחות Selichot and the things that were said at a
ta'anit תענית, ta'anit, right? You know, where, you know, Mi she'anah l'Avraham
Avinu מי שענה לאברהם אבינו, Mi she'anah l'Avraham Avinu, mi she'anah מי
שענה, mi she'anah, mi she'anah מי שענה, mi she'anah, and some of
the most ancient Selichot סליחות Selichot and tefillah תפילה tefillah. were that
type of a structure of, you know, who ya'aneinu מי יעננו, who
ya'aneinu, who ya'aneinu מי יעננו, who ya'aneinu, and so on. And here
you get it, but you get it in the Hallel הלל context
which is seeing this as being said at these times. And again,
what's fascinating is it's pointing to the end of Hallel הלל where
there's elements of tefillah תפילה and bakashah בקשה bakashah for geulah גאולה.
The petitioning, one imagines that they're obviously embracing also the beginning of
the Hallel הלל where when they were saved, then they opened up
with the Hallel הלל for their redemption. So it's just pointing out
though that, and you know, it's also more interesting if you've got
that tension and uncertainty for redemption, then you have the redemption and
then you have the Hallel הלל. It's funny that the order is
reversed, but they're pointing out that the Hallel הלל contains also those
moments beforehand with the petition and the tefillah תפילה. Vachachamim omrim וחכמים
אומרים, and the sages say, Nevi'im shebeineihem tiknu l'Yisrael sheyihu omrim oso
al kol perek u'perek v'al kol tzarah v'tzarah shelo tavo aleihem ul'Yisrael
u'keshenigalin omrim oso al geulatan נביאים שביניהם תיקנו לישראל שיהו אומרים אותו
על כל פרק ופרק ועל כל צרה וצרה שלא תבוא עליהם ולישראל
וכשניגאלין אומרים אותו על גאולתם. Nevi'im shebeineihem tiknu l'Yisrael sheyihu omrim oso
al kol perek u'perek v'al kol tzarah v'tzarah shelo tavo aleihem ul'Yisrael
u'keshenigalin omrim oso al geulatan. And I think the way that the
Chachamim חכמים Chachamim are different is, yes, they're saying it was ancient
and always said, but they're talking about it was said al geulatan
על גאולתם, al geulatan, not necessarily at the moment of threat. Okay,
let's move on. Amar Rav Chisda אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda,
Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah sof perek סוף פרק. sof perek. Now when Hallelujah
הללויה Hallelujah appears in Tehillim תהילים, Tehillim, does it end one perek
פרק? perek. Does it end or does it begin the next pasuk
פסוק? pasuk It's not always clear. So he says it always ends
a perek פרק. perek When there's a question, when there's one Hallelujah
הללויה Hallelujah between the end of one and the beginning of another,
Rava bar Rav Huna amar רבה בר רב הונא אמר, Rava bar
Rav Huna amar, Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah reish pirka ריש פירקא. reish pirka.
No, it begins a perek פרק. perek. Amar Rav Chisda אמר רב
חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, chazeinu l'tilai d'bei Rav Chanin bar Rav חזינו
לתילי דבי רב חנין בר רב, chazeinu l'tilai d'bei Rav Chanin bar
Rav, I saw in the Sefer Tehillim ספר תהילים Sefer Tehillim of
Rav Chanin bar Rav, d'chasivu Hallelujah b'emtza pirka דכתיבו הללויה באמצע פירקא,
d'chasivu Hallelujah b'emtza pirka, that it had the word Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah
between the two prakim פרקים. prakim. So kama misafka leh מספקא ליה,
misafka leh, he didn't know which one, put it in the end
of one, beginning of the other, he situated it exactly between two.
Amar Rav Chanin bar Rava אמר רב חנין בר רבא, Amar Rav
Chanin bar Rava, Rav Chanin bar Rava says, as opposed to Rav
Chanin bar Rav which we just quoted, Hakol modin הכל מודים, Hakol
modin, everybody agrees, bitihilat Hashem yedaber pi viyvarech kol basar shem kodsho
l'olam va'ed בתהילת השם ידבר פי ויברך כל בשר שם קדשו לעולם
ועד, bitihilat Hashem yedaber pi viyvarech kol basar shem kodsho l'olam va'ed,
de'Hallelujah dibasrei reish pirka דהללויה דבתריה ריש פירקא. de'Hallelujah dibasrei reish pirka.
That the Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah that follows it is the beginning of
a perek פרק perek. and that's the way it appears in our
Tehillim תהילים. Tehillim. Venachnu nevarech Kah me'ata v'ad olam Hallelujah ואנחנו נברך
יה מעתה ועד עולם הללויה, Venachnu nevarech Kah me'ata v'ad olam Hallelujah,
is that what he thinks? What? He says the Hallelujah הללויה. Hallelujah.
Yeah, bitihilat Hashem yedaber pi viyvarech kol basar shem kodsho l'olam va'ed
בתהילת השם ידבר פי ויברך כל בשר שם קדשו לעולם ועד, bitihilat
Hashem yedaber pi viyvarech kol basar shem kodsho l'olam va'ed, period, and
Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah begins the next perek פרק. perek And you can
check in your Tehillim תהילים, Tehillim, Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah begins the next
perek פרק. perek. No, we're talking about this pasuk פסוק. pasuk Okay,
reish pirka ריש פירקא. reish pirka. Okay. Hallelujah dibasrei reish pirka הללויה
דבתריה ריש פירקא. Hallelujah dibasrei reish pirka. Rasha yireh v'ka'as shinav yachrok
v'namas ta'avat resha'im toved רשע יראה וכעס שניו יחרוק ונמס תאוות רשעים
תאבד, Rasha yireh v'ka'as shinav yachrok v'namas ta'avat resha'im toved, Hallelujah dibasrei
reish pirka הללויה דבתריה ריש פירקא. Hallelujah dibasrei reish pirka. So again,
and if you look, this is the way it is in our
Tehillim תהילים, Tehillim, the Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah that ends that really isn't
ending there, it's beginning the next one. And actually in a number
of these ones, the next perek פרק perek. begins Hallelujah Halelu es
Hashem הללויה הללו את השם. Hallelujah Halelu es Hashem. So therefore it
actually makes sense that the Hallelujah הללויה Hallelujah begins the next one
because it feeds into Halelu es Hashem הללו את השם. Halelu es
Hashem. But not all of them are like that. Tells you what
the scrolls looked like where there's no numbering of the pesukim פסוקים.
pesukim. Well, there presumably was a break between the prakim פרקים. prakim.
Right, but still. שעמדים בבית השם הללויה, She-omdim beveis Hashem Hallelujah, so
הללויה Hallelujah is בתרי ריש פירקא. batrei reish pirka. So also there,
קראי מוסיפין, Kray mosefin, and those that are sort of masters of
the text, of reading the פסוקים, pesukim, they add after אלו, elu,
the following: מנחל בדרך ישתה על כן ירים ראש, Minachal bederech yishteh
al kein yarim rosh, הללויה דבתרי ריש פירקא. Hallelujah de-batrei reish pirka.
The הללויה Hallelujah there begins the next one. ראשית חכמה יראת השם
שכל טוב לכל עשיהם, Reishis chachmah yiras Hashem sechel tov le-chol oseihem,
הללויה דבתרי ריש פירקא. Hallelujah de-batrei reish pirka. You can see by
all these that you could have easily ended with הללויה, Hallelujah, right?
But no, in these cases הללויה Hallelujah is the beginning of the
next one. נימא כתנאי. Nimei ketannai. What? תהלת השם ידבר פי ויברך
כל בשר שם קדשו לעולם ועד Tehillat Hashem yedaber pi viyvareich kol
basar shem kodsho le-olam va-ed ואנחנו נברך יה מעתה ועד עולם הללויה.
Vaanachnu nevareich ya mei-atah ve-ad olam Hallelujah. Right. הללויה הללו עבדי השם.
Hallelujah Hallelu avdei Hashem. Yeah, so but if you look in, that's
the way we say it, but if you look in a ספר
תהלים, Sefer Tehillim, I'm sorry, I wasn't focusing in on what you
were saying. But if you look in a ספר תהלים, Sefer Tehillim,
do we have a ספר תהלים Sefer Tehillim here? If you actually
look, that's why it says הללויה Hallelujah twice cause that's how we
say it during דאבנינג. davening. But if you actually look in a
ספר תהלים, Sefer Tehillim, that's not the way it is, right? קנ"ה,
Kuf mem hei, the way it exists in תהלים is: תהלת השם
ידבר פי ויברך כל בשר שם קדשו לעולם ועד Tehillat Hashem yedaber
pi viyvareich kol basar shem kodsho le-olam va-ed and then קנ"ו kuf
mem vav is הללויה הללי נפשי את השם. Hallelujah Halleli nafshi es
Hashem. So when we say it, אשרי, Ashrei, this last פסוק pasuk
is not, does not end in הללויה. Hallelujah. And when we say
it in אשרי, Ashrei, it's fascinating because if you have this גמרא,
Gemara you have the way we have it in תהלים, and when
we say it in אשרי Ashrei we end with הללויה Hallelujah and
then we begin הללויה Hallelujah the next one, and that and which
is קנ"ו, kuf mem vav, which is the next פרק. perek. But
in the ספר תהלים Sefer Tehillim we only have one הללויה, Hallelujah,
which is why it was printed twice here because obviously influenced by
the תפלה. tefillah. Okay. Now, נימא כתנאי, nimei ketannai, let's say this
is like a debate of תנאים. tannaim. And now we're actually going
to tie back into our משנה. Mishnah. עד היכן הוא אומר? Ad
heichan hu omeir? How far do you say the הלל before the
ברכה brachah of the הגדה? Haggadah? בית שמאי אומרים עד אם הבנים
שמחה. Beis Shammai omrim ad eim habanim simeichah. What was the question?
How far do you say the הלל before the הגדה, Haggadah, before
the end, before the ברכה brachah of the הגדה? Haggadah? בית שמאי
Beis Shammai says until אם הבנים שמחה, eim habanim simeichah, which is
the last פסוק pasuk in the first פרק. perek. ובית הלל אומרים
עד חלמיש למעינו מים, U-Veis Hillel omrim ad halamish le-mayno mayim, the
last פסוק pasuk in the second פרק. perek. ותניא אידך, Ve-tanya idach,
we have another ברייתא, baraita, עד היכן הוא אומר, ad heichan hu
omeir, how far do you say? בית שמאי אומרים עד בצאת ישראל
ממצרים, Beis Shammai omrim ad betzeis Yisrael mi-Mitzrayim, which is the first
פסוק pasuk in the second פרק. perek ובית הלל אומרים עד לא
לנו השם לא לנו, u-Veis Hillel omrim ad lo lanu Hashem lo
lanu, which is the first פסוק in the third פרק. perek. So
this is basically the same thing except are they quoting the last
פרק perek they say or up until but not including the first,
you know, the next פרק. perek, So but what does the גמרא
Gemara say? So what does that really doesn't seem to prove anything.
But the גמרא Gemara is going to say that the reason that
we are saying it in different ways is because of different approaches
where the הללויה Hallelujah begins, where the הללויה Hallelujah is attached to.
מאי לאו בהא קא מיפלגי? Mai lav be-ha ka mipligi? Because the
end of the פסוק in the first פרק perek. is... I need
this again. בצאת ישראל... Be-tzeis Yisrael... So it says מושיבי עקרת הבית
אם הבנים שמחה הללויה בצאת ישראל ממצרים. moshivi akkeres habayis eim habanim
simeichah Hallelujah betzeis Yisrael mi-Mitzrayim. So where does the הללויה Hallelujah go?
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: מאי לאו בהא קא מיפלגי? Mai
lav be-ha ka mipligi? למאן דאמר עד אם הבנים שמחה, Le-man de-amar
ad eim habanim simeichah, if you're saying you say it until אם
הבנים שמחה, eim habanim simeichah, the word after אם הבנים שמחה eim
habanim simeichah is הללויה. Hallelujah. So if you just said עד אם
הבנים שמחה, ad eim habanim simeichah, סבר הללויה ריש פירקא. savar Hallelujah
reish pirka. So you hold that הללויה Hallelujah is the beginning of
the פרק, perek, so you say it until אם הבנים שמחה eim
habanim simeichah and you don't say the word הללויה, Hallelujah, that begins
the next one. ולמאן דאמר עד בצאת ישראל, U-le-man de-amar ad betzeis
Yisrael, and the one that says you say it until the words
בצאת ישראל, betzeis Yisrael, סבר הללויה סוף פירקא, savar Hallelujah sof pirka,
that הללויה Hallelujah is the end of the previous one. He didn't
say you say it until הללויה בצאת ישראל, Hallelujah betzeis Yisrael, you
just said you said it until בצאת ישראל, betzeis Yisrael, so the
הללויה Hallelujah was attached to the previous פרק. Okay, הללויה סוף פירקא.
Hallelujah sof pirka. So that's a cute way of understanding why they're
saying it differently, because either neither statement included the הללויה, Hallelujah, so
they must be debating, you know, which one the הללויה Hallelujah is
attached to. So רב חסדא מתרץ לטעמיה. Rav Chisda meitartz lei litaimei.
רב חסדא Rav Chisda will explain according to his reasoning. דכולי עלמא
סברי הללויה סוף פירקא. De-kulei alma savri Hallelujah sof pirka. Everybody holds
הללויה Hallelujah is the end of a פרק, and it's אם הבנים
שמחה הללויה. eim habanim simeichah Hallelujah. מאן דאמר עד בצאת ישראל שפיר,
Man de-amar ad betzeis Yisrael shapir, so the one that says you
say until בצאת ישראל, betzeis Yisrael, that's good, because it starts with
בצאת ישראל. betzeis Yisrael. ומאן דאמר עד אם הבנים שמחה, U-man de-amar
ad eim habanim simeichah, the one that says you say until אם
הבנים שמחה, eim habanim simeichah, עד ועד בכלל. ad ve-ad bichlal. He
doesn't mean up until and not including, he means up until אם
הבנים eim habanim and including אם הבנים. eim habanim. Okay, but that
was like obvious, that part of what they were saying was one
was saying inclusive and one was saying until but not including. It
still doesn't answer the הללויה. Hallelujah. So the גמרא Gemara says: ונימא
עד הללויה? Ve-neima ad Hallelujah? So why does he say עד אם
הבנים שמחה? ad eim habanim simeichah? Say you say up until הללויה.
Hallelujah. So the גמרא says: Okay, וכי תימא דלא ידעינן היי הללויה?
vechi teima de-lo yadnan hai Hallelujah? If we wouldn't have known which
הללויה, Hallelujah, there's a lot of הללויה Hallelujahs in the הלל. ונימא
הללויה של אם הבנים שמחה? Ve-neima Hallelujah shel eim habanim simeichah? קשיא.
Kasha. Okay, so in the end the גמרא says they're really differing
whether when they say you say until, does until mean until and
including? But of course what they didn't answer is why wasn't הללויה
Hallelujah included? So קשיא. kashia. Alright, but it really means אם הבנים
שמחה הללויה. em habanim semeicha Hallelujah. רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar
Rav Huna מתרץ לטעמיה metaretz leta'ameih דכולי עלמא dechulei alma הללויה Hallelujah
ריש פירקא. reish pirka. Everybody says הללויה Hallelujah is the beginning and
it should be הללויה בצאת ישראל. Hallelujah betzeit Yisrael. מאן דאמר עד
אם הבנים שמחה Man de'amar ad em habanim semeicha שפיר shapir cause
that's the end. ומאן דאמר עד בצאת ישראל, U'man de'amar ad betzeit
Yisrael, why until בצאת ישראל? betzeit Yisrael? סבר עד ולא עד בכלל
Savar ad velo ad bichlal means up until בצאת ישראל betzeit Yisrael
but not including. Okay, but that was obvious. Nevertheless, ונימא עד הללויה.
v'neima ad Hallelujah. Say, say it until הללויה. Hallelujah. וכי תימא דלא
ידעינן הי הללויה, Vechi teima delo yadinan hai Hallelujah, we wouldn't know
which one. נימא עד הללויה שבצאת ישראל, Neima ad Hallelujah shebetzeit Yisrael,
say it until the הללויה Hallelujah of בצאת ישראל. betzeit Yisrael. קשיא.
Kashia. נו, Nu, it's difficult. Okay, but הגמרא the Gemara interestingly does
point out that הללויה Hallelujah is absent in both of those statements
and might be a part of this basis of what do you
call it, of whether הללויה Hallelujah ends or begins. We will have
to end here. I know we're a little bit behind, but luckily
the last דף daf is very short, so not to worry. Okay,
הלכה is הללויה Hallelujah was ריש
פירקא.
reish
pirka.