Good
morning and happy July 4th. Today’s דף daf. *daf* is יד *Yud
Daled*, 14 in פסחים *Pesachim*. The משנה Mishnah: *Mishna* states: רבי חנינא
Rabbi Chanina סגן הכהנים אומר *Rabbi Chanina Segan HaKohanim omer*, מימיהם של
כהנים mi-mei-hem shel kohanim, לא נמנעו מלשרוף את הבשר שנטמא בולד הטומאה
עם הבשר שנטמא באב הטומאה *mi-yemeihem shel kohanim lo nimneu milisrof et
habasar she-nitma bivlad hatuma im habasar she-nitma be-av hatuma*. רבי חנינא Rabbi
Chanina *Rabbi Chanina* the vice כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* said: In all
the days of the כהנים kohanim, *Kohanim*, they never refrained from burning
meat which was טמא Tamei *tamei* בולד הטומאה *bivlad hatuma*. In other
words, it became טמא Tamei *tamei* from a ראשון Rishon. *rishon*, so
it’s a שני לטומאה Sheni Letumah. *sheni letuma*, עם הבשר שנטמא באב
הטומאה *im habasar she-nitma be-av hatuma* together with meat that became טמא
Tamei *tamei* from an אב הטומאה Av Hatumah. *av hatuma*. So just
to review quickly the levels of טומאה Tumah *tuma* are: אבי אבות
הטומאה *avi avot hatuma*, the granddaddy of טומאה tumah *tuma*, is the
dead body itself. Someone who becomes, and by the way as we
will see, there’s a special extension of that to metal. Anything that’s
a sword or like the sword, if
it comes in contact with the dead body becomes itself like the
dead body. The next level is something that touches the dead body
which is an אב הטומאה av hatumah *av hatuma*. Something which is
touched by that is a ראשון לטומאה Rishon Letumah. *rishon letuma*, also
called by the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* here as ולד הטומאה Vlad Hatumah,
*vlad hatuma*, the child, because of the termination of the higher level.
And then you have שני Sheni. *sheni*, שלישי shelishi, *shlishi*, and רביעי
*revii*. And not everything can become שני Sheni. *sheni*, שלישי shelishi, *shlishi*,
or רביעי *revii*. Generally speaking, just אוכלין ומשקין *ochlin u’mashkin*, food and
drink, and at the lower levels perhaps just תרומה Terumah *teruma* and
or קדשים Kodshim *kodshim*. So if the concern here is making
something more טמא tamei. *tamei* than it is already or taking something
that is טהור Tahor *tahor* and making it טמא tamei. *tamei*, the
extenuating circumstances regarding burning something, burning these things are that they’re about
to be destroyed anyway or they’re in the process of being destroyed.
Should we or should we not be concerned with increasing their level
of טומאה tumah. *tuma* or in making them טמא tamei. *tamei* in
the first place? So רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina *Rabbi Chanina* is stating
it was always the practice that a ראשון rishon. *rishon* meat that
was being burned,
presumably this is קדשים kodshim *kodshim* that was leftover,
if it was being burned, then it didn’t matter if you mixed
together a ראשון לטומאה Rishon Letumah *rishon letuma* and a שני לטומאה
Sheni Letumah *sheni letuma*.
Well, that’s what it appears to be talking about. The גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* will discuss exactly what levels. אף על פי שמוסיפין טומאה tumah
על טומאתו *af al pi she-mosifin tuma al tumato*, even though you
raise the טומאה tumah *tuma* by one, by a level. הוסיף רבי
עקיבא hosif Rabbi Akiva, ואמר *hosif Rabbi Akiva ve-amar*, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* added on to that: מימיהם של כהנים לא נמנעו
מלהדליק mi-mei-hem shel kohanim lo nimneu mi-le-hadlik. את השמן שנפסל בטבול יום
בנר שנטמא בטמא מת betamei meis. *mi-yemeihem shel kohanim lo nimneu milahadlik
et hashemen she-nifsal bitvul yom bener she-nitma bitmei meit*.
They also did not refrain from lighting the מנורה Menorah *menorah* or
whatever they were lighting with oil that was נפסל בטבול יום *nifsal
bitvul yom*. The word פסול psul, *pasul* is used for levels below,
I believe below ראשון לטומאה Rishon Letumah. *rishon letuma*, because the levels
below that cannot do not always pass on their טומאה tumah? *tuma*
to all other things. So the word נפסל *nifsal* is used. So
something that is, we’ll see what level, but let’s presume right now
a שני לטומאה Sheni Letumah. *sheni letuma* does not, it’s okay to
mix it while you’re burning it with something that touched a טמא
מת tamei meis, *tamei meit*,
which
would be an אב הטומאה av hatumah *av hatuma*.
No, it would be a ראשון לטומאה Rishon Letumah? *rishon letuma*. Something
that was made טמא tamei *tamei* by someone who was a טמא
tamei מת *tamei meit*, who had touched a מת *meit*. So the
person who touched the מת *meit* is an אב הטומאה av hatumah
*av hatuma* and what he touches is a ראשון לטומאה rishon letumah
*rishon letuma*. So that oil, a ראשון לטומאה rishon letumah, *rishon letuma*,
can be mixed with the שני לטומאה sheni letumah. *sheni letuma* oil
while it’s being burned. אף על פי שמוסיפין טומאה tumah על טומאתו
*af al pi she-mosifin tuma al tumato*, even though the טומאה tumah
*tuma* level is being increased. אמר רבי מאיר מדבריהם למדנו Amar Rebbe
Meir, midivreihem lamadnu. *amar Rabbi Meir midivrehem lamadnu*. What is this relevant
to us? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says: From this we
see ששורפין תרומה Terumah טהורה עם הטמאה *she-sorfin teruma tehora im hatmeia*,
that you can take תרומה Terumah. *teruma* which is טהורה *tehora* and
burn it on ערב פסח Erev Pesach *Erev Pesach* if it’s חמץ
Chametz *chametz*, you burn it together with the טמאה Temeiah *tmeia* תרומה
Terumah *teruma*, and you don’t have to worry about increasing the level
of טומאה tumah *tuma* or actually giving it a level of giving
it טומאה tumah *tuma* in this case because we’re talking about תרומה
Terumah טהורה *teruma tehora* together with תרומה Terumah טמאה Temeiah. *teruma tmeia*.
Because it’s being burned, therefore it’s not a concern. אמר רבי יוסי,
Amar Rabbi Yossi אין היא המידה. Ein Hi Hamiddah. רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi disagrees; that's not the that's not a good comparison. You cannot
learn the rules about חמץ Chametz, in this case from the rules
about burning תרומה Terumah, or קדשים kodashim and the גמרא Gemara will
explain why. ומודים רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע Umodim Rabbi Eliezer Verabbi Yehoshua
and both רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua who
argue about something else which we will come to in a minute,
ששורפין זו לעצמה וזו לעצמה. Shesorfin Zu Le'atzmah Vezu Le'atzmah. Both רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua agree that you have
to burn חמץ, chametz the טמא tamei תרומה Terumah separately from the
טהור tahor תרומה. Terumah על מה נחלקו? Al Mah Nechlaku? What were
they arguing about, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua,
that they both both admitted this? על התלויה ועל הטמאה, Al Hateluyah
Ve'al Hatemeiah, something that תרומה Terumah that is טמאה or תרומה terumah
that is a ספק טומאה Safek Tumah you can burn together with
תרומה terumah, which is טמאה. שרבי אליעזר אומר תשרף זו לעצמה וזו
לעצמה. Sherabbi Eliezer Omer Tisaref Zu Le'atzmah Vezu Le'atzmah. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says burn each one separately. ורבי יהושע אומר שתיהן כאחת.
Verabbi Yehoshua Omer
Sheteihen Ke'achas.
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says no they can the ספק טומאה Safek
Tumah and the טומאה tumah can be burnt together. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says מכדי, Michdi, what levels are we talking about? בשר
שנטמא בולד הטומאה, Basar Shenitma Bevlad Hatumah, מה הוי? Mah Havei?
The first case in the משנה: Mishnah, meat which which was became
טמא tamei by touching a ולד הטומאה, vlad hatumah. in other words
a ראשון לטומאה. rishon le-tumah So a person who is ראשון לטומאה
rishon le-tumah touches the תרומה, terumah it becomes what? שני. Sheni. מה
הוי שני? Mah Havei Sheni?
It's a שני לטומאה. sheni letumah. So it's a שני. Sheni. כי
שריף ליה בהדי בשר שנטמא באב הטומאה, Ki Sharif Lei Bahadei Basar
Shenitma Be'av Hatumah, now you're the משנה's Mishnah case was burning it
together with meat that became טמא tamei, through contact with an אב
הטומאה. And what is that? מה הוי? Mah Havei?
So that's a ראשון. rishon So when you mix them together, מה
הוי? Mah Havei?
שני. Sheni. So you're talking about a שני לטומאה sheni letumah coming
into contact with a ראשון rishon לטומאה. So what happens to the
ראשון לטומאה? It becomes a שני
לטומאה. sheni letumah ושני הוא. Vesheni Hu. So שני ושני הוא. Sheni
Vesheni Hu. So...
Hold on.
Hello?
Hi, Sam. Randy and Boaz, there's a bunch of us that are
locked out of the building downstairs.
Oh, the the door on the left is open. Did you try
the door on the left?
We checked it.
Alright, coming right up.
Alright. Alright, so apparently a number of people were under the mistaken
impression that the door was locked, the front door to the שול
Shul was locked. So, I think we will probably when they arrive
go back to the beginning.
So everybody take take five and we will start again in case
you found that confusing you'll have another chance to to encounter it
in a moment.
But how would I have gotten in if you couldn't get in?
You thought I locked the door behind me to keep you out?
I found
your cell
phone on your
seat but I realized
it had to be you.
Ah, very good. Okay, you have to give me the announcement now.
Okay. Probably nobody told them that either.
I guess. Usually it's the other side. The door on the right
is open so I also tried the door and I thought oh
I forgot to open the building. No, usually the one on the
right is locked but
I tried the combination and it wouldn't work for me. Uh-huh. Alright.
So we're דף י"ד, Daf Yud Daled,
so
I'll give you all a minute.
So I'll give you all a minute just
to
find the place and then we will begin again. I've been talking
to myself and the computer here.
I don't even know if there's anyone on the other end.
Okay, ready? So we're in the משנה Mishnah, *mishnah* at the top
of י"ד עמוד א' *yud daled amud aleph*, asking the indulgence of
anybody who might be watching online for the repetition. So I hope
that you had a chance to read the introduction I distributed courtesy
of Artscroll and what I hope was fair use policy yesterday. But
basically there are several levels of טומאה tumah *tumah*. You have the
dead body itself which is called the granddaddy, the אבי אבות הטומאה
*avi avos hatumah*. Something that it touches becomes an אב הטומאה *av
hatumah*, and down the line ראשון *rishon*, שני Sheni. *sheni*, שלישי shlishi?
*shlishi*, and רביעי *revi'i*, although there are different rules about what not
everything can become that level, and once you get beyond שני sheni.
*sheni*, it's there are different rules about like only תרומה terumah, *trumah*,
only קדשים kodashim *kodshim* can and only food or only drink can
be it'll be transmitted that way. But we will see some of
the details.
And the problem the משנה mishna *mishnah* is dealing with initially is
can you burn
can you make something more טמא tamei. *tamei* while you are destroying
it? So if you have קדשים kodashim *kodshim* that needs to be
burnt or תרומה terumah. *trumah* that needs to be burnt or חמץ
chametz *chametz* that needs to be or that needs to be burnt,
then is it a problem to mix different levels of טומאה tumah
*tumah* and make something more טמא tamei *tamei* or make it טמא
tamei *tamei* in the first place?
So we'll see what the משנה mishna *mishnah* has to say about
that. רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina סגן הכהנים אומר *Rabbi Chanina Sgan HaKohanim
omer*, Rabbi Chanina the vice כהן גדול *kohen gadol* said: מימיהם של
כהנים לא נמנעו מלשרוף את הבשר שנטמא בוולד הטומאה עם הבשר שנטמא
באב הטומאה *Mimeihem shel kohanim lo nimnu milisrof es habasar shenitma b'vlad
hatumah im habasar shenitma b'av hatumah*. So for in all the days
of the כהנים *kohanim* they never refrained from burning meat which became
טמא tamei *tamei* from a ולד vlad, הטומאה *vlad hatumah*, which is
the משנה mishna *mishnah*'s term for a ראשון לטומאה *rishon l'tumah*.
So something that is touched by a ראשון לטומאה *rishon l'tumah* becomes
what? A שני לטומאה sheni letumah *sheni l'tumah*. So they took on
the one hand a שני לטומאה sheni letumah *sheni l'tumah* and burned
it together with עם הבשר שנטמא באב הטומאה *im habasar shenitma b'av
hatumah*, meat that became טמא tamei *tamei* through contact with an אב
הטומאה *av hatumah*, which means it is a ראשון *rishon*, right? So
presumably we're talking about a ראשון לטומאה *rishon l'tumah* and a שני
Sheni. לטומאה *sheni l'tumah* being burned together, and we're not concerned with
with the with it making adding on a level of טומאה tumah
*tumah*. אף על פי שמוסיפין טומאה tumah על טומאתו *Af al pi
shemosifin tumah al tumaso*, even though we're increasing the level of טומאה
tumah *tumah* because it's being burned. הוסיף רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. ואמר
*Hosif Rabbi Akiva v'amar*, Rabbi Akiva added onto that: מימיהם של כהנים
לא נמנעו מלהדליק את השמן *Mimeihem shel kohanim lo nimnu milahadlik es
hashemen*, the same similar kind of statement about oil that you're burning,
שנפסל בטבול יום *shenifsal b'tvul yom*. Now here we use the word
נפסל *nifsal*, פסול pasul *pasul*, because anything that is beyond a second
level, beyond a שני sheni לטומאה *sheni l'tumah*, it in most cases
it cannot it does not pass on its טומאה tumah. *tumah* to
other things with certain exceptions. So we instead of the word טמא
tamei, *tamei* we use פסול *pasul*.
So it's it's פסול *pasul* and it can't be used in the
temple service.
So שנפסל בטבול יום *shenifsal b'tvul yom*, so this is a level
of שלישי לטומאה shelishi letumah, *shlishi l'tumah*. It came in contact with
a טבול יום tvul yom *tvul yom*, which is a person who
is awaiting
he's gone to the מקווה *mikvah* he's done all the things he's
just waiting for the sun to set. So if he touches this
oil it becomes a שלישי לטומאה shlishi letumah, *shlishi l'tumah*. בנר שנטמא
בטמא מת *B'ner shenitma b'tmei meit* with a with a נר ner,
*ner*, with a candle, we'll see exactly what kind of candle in
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* we'll discuss that, but some implement
in
an implement that נטמא בטמא מת *nitma b'tmei meit*, that is טמא
tamei, *tamei* by having touched a person who touched a dead body,
in other words a ראשון לטומאה *rishon l'tumah*, right? אף על פי
שמוסיפין טומאה tumah על טומאתו *Af al pi shemosifin tumah al tumaso*,
even though you're adding on טומאה tumah *tumah*, a טומאה tumah *tumah*
level because it's being burned. אמר רבי מאיר Amar Rabbi Meir.
*Amar Rabbi Meir*, why do they burn?
For light.
Oh,
so
they were allowed in the מקדש *mikdash* they were allowed to use...
not sure if we're referring to the מקדש *mikdash*, but we're referring
to תרומה teruma *trumah*. We're referring to
תרומה trumah *trumah*. It's told me they're... oh yeah, you're right. מימיהם
של כהנים *Mimeihem
shel kohanim*, you're right, you're right. They could even be burning in
their private residence. Yeah, but anybody can burn anybody can can use...
yeah, actually the גמרא Gemara *gemara* will point this out that anyone
can use תרומה trumah *trumah*. You can't you can't consume the oil
of תרומה trumah *trumah*. אמר
רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir מדבריהם למדנו, midevareihem lamadnu,
what does this have to do with us? So רבי מאיר Rebbe
Meir says from this we learn ששורפין תרומה טהורה עם הטמאה בפסח.
shesorfin Terumah tehorah im hatameah bePesach. So on ערב פסח Erev Pesach.
it's time to burn your חמץ chametz and you have תרומה trumah
which is חמץ Chametz. and some of it is טהור tahor and
some of it is טמא. tamei. So רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says
well we can see from here that you can mix them together
because in the process of burning it it apparently doesn't matter if
you make it טמא. tamei
But the גמרא Gemara will discuss, well first of all right here
in the משנה, mishna אמר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi אינו היא המדה.
eino hi hamiddah. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi. says no, this is not
a good analogy and the גמרא gemara will discuss why,
why it's not why you can't take a lesson about חמץ chametz
and תרומה trumah from קדשים kodashim or תרומה trumah of different טומאה
tumah levels.
ומודים רבי אליעזר ורבי יהושע, Umodim Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Yehoshua, he says
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua both agree
ששורפין זו לעצמה וזו לעצמה shesorfin zu leatzmah vezu leatzmah that you
have two fires, one for the טמאה תרומה, tameah Terumah, one for
the טהורה תרומה tehorah Terumah on ערב פסח.
Now when he says that they both agree what are they arguing
about? על מה נחלקו? Al mah necheleku? What do רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua disagree? על התלויה ועל הטמאה Al
hateluyah ve'al hatameah about burning together ספק טמא safek tamei and definitely
טמא. tamei So there they have a disagreement שרבי אליעזר אומר sheRabbi
Eliezer omer תשרף זו לעצמה וזו לעצמה. tisaref zu leatzmah vezu leatzmah.
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the ספק safek is enough to make
sure you keep them separate, burn them separately, ורבי יהושע אומר veRabbi
Yehoshua omer שתיהן כאחת sheteihen ke'achas and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says
no, if it's only a ספק טומאה safek tumah you can burn
that together with the definite טומאה. tumah
But they both agree that if it's definitely טהור tahor. and definitely
טמא tamei they both agree that you have to burn it separately
in accordance with the view of רבי יוסי. Okay, מכדי, michtei, now
the גמרא's gemara going to analyze what levels of טומאה tumah, are
we talking about? בשר שנטמא בולד הטומאה. Basar shenitma bivlad hatumah. The
first case in the משנה mishna mentioned meat which had become טמא
tamei through contact with a ולד הטומאה. מה הוי? Mah havei?
So what level is that? שני. sheni. That's a שני sheni, לטומאה.
כי שריף ליה בהדי בשר שנטמא באב הטומאה Ki saref lei bahadi
basar shenitma be'av hatumah now you want to burn it together with
meat that touched an אב הטומאה so it is a ראשון. מה
הוי? Mah havei? שני. sheini
So
when this מה הוי? Mah havei? שני. sheini So
then
the
ראשון לטומאה becomes a
שני. מה הוי? Mah havei?
שני. Right the
שני remains a
שני. So מה מוסיף לו טומאה על
טומאתו?
mah mosif lo tumah al
tumato? So in what sense are you adding טומאה tumah, to it?
אם איכא im ika in what sense is that? Right? אמר רב
יהודה Amar Rav Yehudah הכא בולד ולד עסקינן hacha bivlad vlad askinan
דהוה ליה שלישי. dehavei lei shelishi. What
he's changing the version of the משנה, mishna rather than saying it's
טמא tamei by touching a ולד, it means it's טמא tamei, by
touching a ולד ולד, vlad vlad, in other words the second degree
is touching a שלישי, shlishi וקסבר vechasavar שלישי מותר לעשותו שני shelishi
mutar la'asoso sheni and he holds that it's alright to make a
שלישי לטומאה, it's not a problem to make it more טמא, tamei
to make it a שני לטומאה.
So the גמרא gemara challenges that, והא אין אוכל מטמא אוכל? veha
ein ochel metamei ochel? But isn't it the case that at that
level, at the level of שלישי, a food does not, in this
case food does not pass on that level of טומאה? tumah, You
can only pass that on to liquids. דתניא Detanya we have a
ברייתא, Baraita, יכול יהיה אוכל מטמא אוכל? yakhol yiheyeh ochel metamei ochel?
I might think that the ברייתא Baraita says I might think that
at the level of שני לטומאה אוכל ochel can מטמא metamei other
אוכל, ochel, other food? תלמוד לומר וכי Talmud lomar vekhi I might
think that the ברייתא braisa says I might think that at the
level of שני לטומאה אוכל ochel can מטמא, mitamei, food can מטמא
mitamei other אוכל, ochel, other food. תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, וכי יותן
מים על זרע ונפל מנבלתם עליו. ve-chi yutan mayim al zera ve-nafal
mi-nivlatam alav. The פסוק pasuk says when water comes onto a seed
and and then יותן מים על זרע ונפל מנבלתם עליו. yutan mayim
al zera ve-nafal mi-nivlatam alav. The פסוק pasuk says when water comes
onto a seed and then comes into contact with a נבלה, neveilah,
טמא הוא, tamei hu, then it is טמא. tamei So the דרשה
drasha is הוא טמא ואין עושה כיוצא בו טמא. hu tamei ve-ein
oseh kayotzei bo tamei. That food itself becomes טמא tamei. but doesn't
make, doesn't transmit its טומאה tumah to other food,
rather which is not stated right here in the ברייתא braisa but
rather it can only make liquids טמא tamei at that level. הניח
לה לאביי haniach lah le-Abaye דאמר לא שנו אלא בחולין. de-amar lo
shanu ela be-chulin. So that's okay if we say that אביי Abaye
applies this פסוק pasuk and this הלכה halacha only to חולין, chulin,
אבל בתרומה ובקדשים עושה כיוצא בהן. aval be-terumah u-ve-kodashim oseh kayotzei bo
hen.
אביי Abaye says that with תרומה trumah and קדשים kodashim food does
make food טמא tamei. at the שני לטומאה level. So fine, so
that's what our משנה mishna is talking about.
אלא ולרב אדא בר אהבה משמי דראבא נמי, ella u-le-Rav Adda bar
Ahava mishmei de-Rava namei, and also according to רב אדא, Rav Adda,
דאמר לא שנו אלא בחולין ותרומה אבל בקדשים עושה כיוצא בהן. de-amar
lo shanu ela be-chulin ve-terumah aval be-kodashim oseh kayotzei bo hen. Even
רב אדא Rav Adda who says this rule applies to חולין chulin
and תרומה, trumah but קדשים kodashim, he says food can make food
טמא tamei, at that level. שפיר, shapir, that's okay, so that's what
our משנה mishna. is talking about about קדשים in the first case
is what we're talking about now.
אלא לרבינא?
ella le-Ravina? Get two fires, one for חולין chulin and תרומה terumah
you make two?
No. So what, so according to this, so according to these two
positions, when the משנה mishna says
מימיהם של כהנים, in all the days of the כהנים, they never
refrained from burning these two things together, so fine, I understand, because
we're talking about קדשים and קדשים does transmit טומאה tumah. and so
we can see from here so there is a חידוש chidush there
that it's okay to burn these two things together because you're burning,
because you're destroying them. Okay. אבל אלא לרבינא משמי דראבא דאמר מקרא
מלא דברי הכתוב, aval ella le-Ravina mishmei de-Rava de-amar mikra malei divrei
ha-kasuv, but according to רבינא Ravina who says this rule is all-encompassing
that at the level of שני לטומאה food does not pass on
טומאה tumah. to food, so what's the משנה mishna, talking about? Or
why would they even consider having two separate fires? The טומאה tumah,
does not pass on, what are we talking about?
לא שנא חולין ולא שנא תרומה ולא שנא קדשים. lo shana chulin
ve-lo shana terumah ve-lo shana kodashim. The rule applies of non-transmission from
food to food applies to anything; תרומה, terumah קדשים, חולין, chulin, אינו
עושה כיוצא בו. eino oseh kayotzei bo. It doesn't transmit the same
level, it doesn't transmit טומאה tumah. to a similar thing to another
food. מאי איכא למימר? mai ika le-meimar? What's the משנה mishna talking
about? The גמרא Gemara answers הכא במאי עסקינן דאיכא משקין בהדי בשר.
hacha mai askinan de-ika mashkin
bahadi basar. We're talking about,
I
find this hard to visualize, but there's liquid on the surface of
the meat. Okay,
so that which I just said that food does not transmit the
טומאה tumah level to other food does not apply to liquids. It
does, otherwise you'd never have what is a שלישי? A שלישי is
liquids. Food transmits טומאה tumah. to
liquids and so if the משנה mishna is talking about meat which
had liquid on the surface, that's why it's a חידוש chidush to
say you can burn them together because even though you're making that
liquid טמא, tamei, more טמא, tamei it's okay to burn them together
because you're burning them. Okay. דקא
מטמי מחמת משקין, de-ka mitamei machamat mashkin,
because the טומאה is applied to the liquid. The גמרא Gemara says
אי הכי האי עם הבשר שנטמא באב הטומאה, i hachi hai im
ha-basar she-nitma be-av ha-tumah, why does the משנה mishna specify the meat?
It should have said עם הבשר ומשקין מבעי ליה. im ha-basar ve-mashkin
miba'ei lei. It should have said that there's liquid on top of
the meat, why didn't it say anything? Which is kind of a
strange question because the גמרא Gemara constantly is attributing implicit things in
the משנה. mishna, But anyway, אלא נהי דאין אוכל מטמא אוכל מדאורייתא,
ella nehi de-ein ochel mitamei ochel mi-de-oraisa, okay, we have a different
approach now. Maybe מדאורייתא mi-de-oraisa I agree that אוכל ochel does not
מטמא mitamei אוכל ochel at the level of שני, אבל מדרבנן מיהו
מטמי, aval mi-derabbanan mihu mitamei, but מדרבנן mi-derabbanan you still, there is
still that transmission of טומאה from אוכל ochel to אוכל ochel even
according to רבינא Ravina who says there is no such transmission מדאורייתא,
mi-de-oraisa, מדרבנן mi-derabbanan
there is and so that's why the משנה mishna is telling us
that it's only because it's being burnt that you can put them
together.
Okay. Okay, now the next case in the משנה, Mishna. the oil,
burning the oil of תרומה. terumah. הוסיף רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva added, מימיהם של כהנים לא נמנעו מלהדליק. They never
refrained from burning the oil of different levels of
טומאה with a נר, with a candle, or we'll see what kind
of candle we're talking about which had a different level of טומאה.
מכדי, michte,
so what are we talking about? Let's see. שמן שנפסל בטבול יום.
shemen she-nifsal bi-t’vul yom. What the משנה Mishna said was שמן. shemen.
the oil that was became פסול *pasul* by contact with the טבול
יום *tvul yom*, with a person waiting for his טהרה *tahara* to
be completed. מאי הוי *mai havei*, what level is that? שלישי *shlishi*.
So the oil is a שלישי לטומאה *shlishi letuma*.
והטבול יום הוא
שני *vehatvul yom hu sheni*? Yeah, right. וכי מדליק ליה בנר שנטמא
בטמי מת *vekhi madlik lei bener shenitma betmei meis*. Now you're lighting
it with what the משנה Mishna? *mishna* called a candle that became
טמא *tamei* by touching a טמי מת *tmei meis*, by touching a
person who is an אב הטומאה *av hatuma*. So the candle is
what?
One second, שנטמא בטמי מת *shenitma betmei meis*. מאי הוי *mai havei*?
שני *sheni*.
Why is it a שני *sheni*? I was going to say ראשון
*rishon*. One second.
Okay, so yes, so what the it's interpreting the משנה Mishna *mishna*
as follows: the candle or the implement was טמא *tamei* by touching
someone who, yes, שנטמא בטמי מת *shenitma betmei meis*, by touching someone
who was טמא *tamei* through contact with a טמי מת *tmei meis*.
So someone touched a טמי מת *tmei meis*, he becomes
a ראשון לטומאה
*rishon letuma*, and the candle that he touched becomes a שני *sheni*.
So מאי הוי שני *mai havei sheni*. So the oil is a
שלישי *shlishi*, the candle is a שני *sheni*. Candle's the wrong word,
as we'll see, but I can't think of the right word. מאי
קמשמע לן *mai kamashma lan*? So שלישי מותר לעשותו שני *shlishi mutar
laasoto sheni*. So what's it telling us here? You have the oil
which is a שלישי *shlishi* and it's okay if it becomes, if
you make it a שני *sheni* in the process of lighting it.
היינו הך *hainu hach*? So same question as before.
What's
the היינו הך *hainu hach*?
The same thing as the meat and קודש *kodesh*, right? So what
are you, what's the news? What is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi
Akiva* telling us different? אמר רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *amar Rabbi Yehuda*,
הכא בנר של מתכת עסקינן *hacha bener shel matechet askinan*. We're talking
about a candle, not a metal candle, lamp is the better word.
We're talking about a metal lamp. Now there's a special rule about
metal,
as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will point out right now, that metal
by coming in contact with a dead body attains the same level,
not a level lower. So metal which touches a dead body becomes
an אבי אבות הטומאה *avi avos hatuma*. Okay?
And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains right away, דרחמנא אמר *drachmana amar*,
the Torah says, בחלל חרב *bechalal cherev*, a person who in describing
the person who died and the level of טומאה *tuma* uses the
word with the sword. חרב הרי הוא כחלל *cherev harei hu kechalal*.
The sword and the חלל *chalal* and the corpse are on the
same level. והוי ליה אב הטומאה *vehavei lei av hatuma*. So the
person who touches the sword becomes not a ראשון *rishon* but an
אב הטומאה *av hatuma*, and the person who touches him or the
lamp that he,
when the person touches the lamp, it becomes, it's on the same—ah,
so the person becomes
a—one second, where does the lamp fit in?
As he jumping—you're not jumping one level from שלישי *shlishi* to ראשון
*rishon*, you're jumping two levels then when you mix them.
Right. Yeah. So I guess, yeah, what we see from the פסוק
*pasuk*, what the פסוק *pasuk* is generalized to say that metal attains
the same level as the one who touches it. So if it's
touched two levels, exactly. The metal lamp becomes a ראשון *rishon* because
it touches a ראשון *rishon*,
and the oil is a שלישי *shlishi*. והוי ליה אב הטומאה *vehavei
lei av hatuma*. וקסבר שלישי מותר לעשותו ראשון *vechasavar shlishi mutar laasoto
rishon*. So now, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* is adding
on here is you can make a שלישי לטומאה *shlishi letuma* into
a ראשון לטומאה *rishon letuma*, jump two levels.
Okay, that makes sense. ומאי דוחקיה דרבי יהודה לאוקמי בנר של מתכת
*umai duchkeih deRabbi Yehuda leokmei bener shel matechet*? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says well, you could have gone a different way. You could have
explained, explained the משנה Mishna, *mishna* as follows, rather than specifying that
the lamp must be a metal lamp. נוקמה בנר של חרס *nukmeh
bener shel cheres*, maybe we're talking about a clay lamp. ומאי הוסיף
*umai hosif* and what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* add
on? A different strategy here to interpret רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi
Akiva*. דאילו התם hasam, טמא וטמא *deilu hatam tamei vetamei*, there we
have, in the first case, we have טמא וטמא *tamei vetamei*. You
have a ראשון לטומאה *rishon letuma* and a שני לטומאה *sheni letuma*,
right? ואילו הכא פסול וטמא *veilu hacha pasul vetamei*. Here we have
a שלישי לטומאה *shlishi letuma* which does not contaminate other things. That's
why it's called פסול *pasul* rather than טמא *tamei*. So
the first part of the משנה Mishna, *mishna* רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina
*Rabbi Chanina* is telling us that
you can mix a ראשון *rishon*... So
it's still one level, but it's kind of jumping a category, right?
Jumping from the category of פסול to טמא. So even though it's
just one level, there is still a חידוש chiddush here of רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva? Makes sense? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so yeah, so
why don't we go that way? אמר רבא מתניתין קשיא ליה. Amar
Rava, matnitin kashya lei. So then the משנה mishnah. makes it difficult
to explain it that way. מה אירייא דתני נר שנטמא בטמא מת?
mai irya detanei ner shenitma
betamei meis?
The language of the משנה is a lamp that became טמא בטמא
מת. ליתני שנטמא בשרץ. litnei shenitma besheretz. Why is it specifically referring
to טומאה coming from a dead body? Let it use the טומאה
coming from a שרץ. sheretz. In which case, that—so he's saying that
the fact that the משנה, that רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva case specifies
טומאת מת tumas meis and not טומאת שרץ, tumas sheretz, that indicates
that what he's talking about is the first—רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda explanation,
which is that it's a metal lamp and it's jumping two levels.
Okay? So again we had two ways to explain what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is adding. The first one is according to רבי יהודה
that it's jumping two levels. And that's—that—if
in order to understand that from רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva we would
have to say it's a metal lamp, right? And the other way,
רבא's Rava explanation was, no, it's only jumping one level but it's
also jumping a category. So what the גמרא is—where we are now
is that we're preferring that first opinion because the משנה specified a
lamp that was טמא through a dead body rather than a
שרץ. sheretz. אלא איזהו דבר שחלוקה טומאתו בין טומאת מת לשרץ הוי
אומר זה מתכת,
ela eizehu davar shechaluka tumato bein tumas
meis lesheretz hevei omer zeh mateschet, it's metal.
So since we specified טמא מת, the חידוש chiddush of רבי עקיבא
is probably that we're talking about a metal lamp and therefore the
חידוש chiddush is that it's a two-level jump of טומאה that he's
permitting.
אמר רבא שמע מינה קסבר רבי עקיבא טומאת משקין לטמא אחרים דאורייתא.
Amar Rava, shma mina kasvar Rabbi Akiva tumas mashkin letamei acherim deoraisa.
Rava says, okay, so what we see about רבי עקיבא that he
holds that—that—the טומאה of liquids to make other things טמא is דאורייתא.
deoraisa. דאי סלקא דעתך דרבנן, de'ee salka daitach derabbanan, let's see, האי
נר מאי קמהניא להאי שמן? hai ner mai kimehanya lehai shemen? What
is the lamp doing to the oil? אי לפסולי גופיה הא פסיל
וקאי. ee lefuslei gufeh ha pasil vekaei. If to make the oil
פסול, in other words make it a שלישי לטומאה, what's already—I mean
to make it unfit for use in the המקדש, hamikdash,
it's already פסול וקאי. pasul vekaei.
So the גמרא interjects, ממאי דילמא לטמאה אחרים מדרבנן?
mimai dilma letamei acherim
miderabbanan?
So the גמרא says, alright, so you want to say therefore that
we see that דאורייתא deoraisa מטמא metamei other things? Maybe not, maybe
only דרבנן. derabbanan. So the rejoinder is, אם מדרבנן מאי אירייא באב
הטומאה אפילו בראשון ובשני נמי. im miderabbanan mai irya be'av hatumah afilu
berishon uvesheini nami.
So what do you have to deal with the אב הטומאה like
all this ראשון and שני business, this is all דרבנן derabbanan in
the first place. So if we're talking about דרבנןs derabbanan then why
specify a case that involves an אב הטומאה which is דאורייתא? deoraisa?
So the fact that we're specifying that level of טומאה to prove—to
make the point means that we're talking about דאורייתא. deoraisa. דתנן, detnan,
how do I know that about ראשון and שני that it's דרבנן?
derabbanan? דתנן כל הפוסל את התרומה מטמא משקין להיות תחילה. detnan kol
haposel es hateruma metamei mashkin lehiyot techila. Anything that makes תרומה פסול
can make liquids טמא as a ראשון לטומאה, that's what תחילה techila
means. חוץ מטבול יום, chutz mitvul yom,
except for a טבול יום which is an exception. אלא שמע מינה
דאורייתא. ela shma mina deoraisa. So therefore we must be talking about
דאורייתא. deoraisa. Okay. Okay,
well that's what it's going to be like for the next week
or so, so fasten your seatbelts. אמר רבי מאיר.
Aren't they interesting, the context? Yeah, right?
Where we're embedded,
in our terms we could view it as medical or psychological. Yeah,
yeah, medical. Where they couldn't—they intuitively felt maybe metal has some disease
that caused some sort of chemical reaction.
I thought they only had clay lamps, you know? A metal thing
was expensive, right? Yeah, but all the archaeology they always find
is clay lamps.
Clay was cheap.
Yeah, was probably less, less available, but certainly existed. As you say,
the מנורה Menorah was a, was a metal lamp. מנורה was gold.
Right, or brass. Right.
So imagine if you were a wealthy person and you had the
resources, you could have a gold lamp. Okay, so going on in
the משנה. So now רבי מאיר tried to apply this to חמץ.
chametz אמר רבי מאיר מדבריהם למדנו. Midivreihem lamadnu.
From these, from what they said, רבי חנינא and רבי עקיבא, we
can see that you can burn תרומה of חמץ chametz? together with
I'm sorry, תרומה חמץ chametz, which is טמא together with טהור. tahar
מדבריהם midivreihem. למדנו. The גמרא says from which
case, רבי חנינא or רבי עקיבא? From the meat or the oil
case. אילימא מדברי רבי חנינא סגן הכהנים, Ileima midivrei Rabbi Chanina Segan
ha-Kohanim, so
first let's examine the first case of burning the meat together. מי
דמי? Mi domei? Can you compare this to the חמץ? chametz. התם
טמא וטמא הכא טהור וטמא. Hasam tamei ve-tamei, hacha tahar ve-tamei. So
the case of the meat was changing its level of טומאה, but
we weren't talking about taking something טהור tahor? and making it טמא,
right? So how can you apply that to burning תרומה that's
טמא together with תרומה that's טהור? tahor Then you're taking something and
making it... now maybe that's allowed, but you can't prove it from
רבי חנינא because he's talking about a lesser degree of contamination. ואלא
מדברי רבי עקיבא, Ve-ela midivrei Rabbi Akiva, so what you're gonna say
from the רבי עקיבא's case of the oil and the lamp. מי
דמי, Mi domei, is it the same? התם פסול וטמא הכא טהור
וטמא. Hasam passul ve-tamei, hacha tahar ve-tamei. Again,
same thing. רבי עקיבא's case involves changing the level and the category
of טומאה, but not making it טמא in the first place. נימא
קסבר רבי מאיר מתניתין באבי טומאה דאורייתא Neima kasavar Rebbe Meir matnitin
be-avi tumah de-oraita וולד הטומאה דרבנן. ve-vlad ha-tumah de-rabbanan.
Maybe what רבי מאיר has to hold is that, that
אבי טומאה avi tumah is real טומאה, it's דאורייתא, de-oraita, and the
ראשון לטומאה or anything below it is
דרבנן. de-rabbanan. דמדאורייתא טהור מעליא. De-midoraisa tahar malya. So the corresponding case
of תרומה that's חמץ, if it's a,
if you're talking about mixing תרומה which is אבי טומאה avi tumah
and תרומה which is וולד הטומאה. vlad ha-tumah. So מדאורייתא mid-oraita there's
no problem because וולד הטומאה, vlad ha-tumah, ראשון לטומאה doesn't exist מדאורייתא,
mid-oraita, right? So
there's
no issue there מדאורייתא. mid-oraita. ומאי מדבריהם, Ve-mai midivreihem, and
what are we, who are we learning from? מדברי רבי חנינא סגן
הכהנים. Midivrei Rabbi Chanina Segan ha-Kohanim. And we're learning from רבי חנינא
who's talking about the meat, the mixing of the meat.
One is דאורייתא de-oraita and one
is... one is טמא דאורייתא, tamei de-oraita, the other is not.
So we can see you can do the same thing with חמץ.
אמר ריש לקיש משום בר קפרא מתניתין באבי טומאה דאורייתא Amar Reish
Lakish mishum Bar Kappara, matnitin be-avi tumah de-oraita וולד הטומאה דאורייתא. ve-vlad
ha-tumah de-oraita. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said no, the משנה's talking about
levels of טומאה which are דאורייתא. de-oraita. ומאי מדבריהם Ve-mai midivreihem and
what are we learning from in the משנה? מדברי רבי אלעזר ורבי
יהושע, Midivrei Rabbi Elazar ve-Rabbi Yehoshua, from the,
from the end of the משנה which is רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua who say that you have to burn
them separately, if it's,
if one is definitely... one second. No, no, no,
from the argument of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
which is only about the ספק טומאה safek tumah burnt together with
the טומאה. But one of them holds that if
it's... wait a second, both of them held the other way. Hold
a second.
Okay,
so we'll see from which statement רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar רבי יהושע,
Rabbi Yehoshua, not the one in our משנה, but here רבי יהושע.
Rabbi Yehoshua. Which רבי יהושע? Rabbi Yehoshua? אילימא הא דרבי יהושע דתנן,
Ileima ha de-Rabbi Yehoshua de-tanan, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua who said in
the משנה, חבית של תרומה שנולדה לה ספק, ספק טומאה, chavis shel
trumah she-nolda la safek, sfek tumah,
you have a barrel of תרומה that you have a doubt whether
it's טמא. רבי אליעזר אומר אם היתה מונחת במקום התורפה יניחנה במקום
המוצנע. Rabbi Eliezer omer im hayeta munachat be-makom ha-turpah yanihenna be-makom ha-muntznah.
If it was in the מקום התורפה makom ha-turpah which is a
place that an open area, then you should put it in a
hidden area. ואם היתה מגולה, Ve-im hayeta megula, and if it was
open, if it was unsealed, יכסנה, yechasenna, you should cover it. In
other words, you should continue to protect it against definite טומאה. So
you have something that's a ספק טומאה, sofek tumah, but you should
still be careful with it not to let it come in contact
with טומאה, because if it's not טמא in the first place, then
you're making it, then you're exposing it to טומאה. רבי יהושע אומר,
Rabbi Yehoshua omer, Rabbi Yehoshua says, אם היתה מונחת במקום המוצנע יניחנה
במקום התורפה. im hoyso munachas b'makom hamutzna yanichena b'makom haturfa. On the
contrary, if it's in a, you should try to, you should encourage
it to become a definite, to get definite טומאה so you'll know
what to do with it, you'll be able to burn it. ואם
היתה מכוסה יגלה, v'im hoyso mechuso yegale, and if it was covered
you should uncover it to make it easier
for
it to become טמא.
So this Rabbi Yehoshua implies that what?
Implies that that it that it's better to make it טמא, right?
If you have something that's that's doubtful, it's better to make it
טמא, so I guess so that you can burn it. So the
גמרא says, wait, מי דמי? mi dami? Is that is that the
same thing? התם, גרמא בעלמא. grama b'alma. Oh, that's that's to put
in an open place and hope that it gets טומאה. Like you're
kind
of causing it but not directly, right? You're encouraging it. הכא בידיים,
hacha b'yadayim, here you're talking about taking it and actually mixing it
together and burning it. אלא
הא רבי יהושע. ela ha Rabbi Yehoshua. Okay, I think we're going
to stop here for today because this is as far as I
prepared and we're well into the next דף. So tomorrow we will
discover which Rabbi Yehoshua it is that that
that Rabbi Meir deduces you can mix תרומה together,
although, you know, it's strange. It's like מדבריהם. It's like it's in
the same משנה. So it seems I probably the גמרא will come
back to that, that it seems like he must be learning either
from רבי חנינא or רבי עקיבא that you can mix the טהור
תרומה with the טמא תרומה. But we shall see as time goes
on.
So my
my father
warned me, I told him that the