Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, good morning. Thank you to everybody who
stopped for me and we pick up at the top of צדיק
ה עמוד א. Tzadik Hey Amud Aleph. Before we leave, because I
lost out on all of the fun yesterday with not getting to
talk about the גמרא's Gemara cosmology or whatever astronomy, I wanted to
make a few very brief points. First,
about the whole issue of פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon and פסח שני.
Pesach Sheni. The משנה, Mishnah,
the גמרא Gemara seemed to give a strange explanation of the משנה,
Mishnah, and I just wanted to tell you what the רמב"ם's Rambam
read of it was, which is all of the מפרשי המשנה Meforshei
HaMishnah follow the רמב"ם Rambam and for once against the גמרא. Gemara.
The גמרא Gemara says, the משנה Mishnah says: What is the difference
between פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon and, what's the difference between דרך רחוקה
Derech Rechoka
and somebody who, the first משנה, Mishnah, and somebody that, for example,
was a שוגג shogeg or מזיד? mezid? Why did the תורה Torah
have to say דרך רחוקה? Derech Rechoka? And the end of the
line, and the last line in the משנה Mishnah was: שאלו פטורים
מכרת ואלו חייבים בהכרת. she-elu paturim mi-karet ve-elu chayavim be-hikaret. Which the
גמרא Gemara seemed to explain meant that אלו חייבים elu chayavim is
somebody who was מזיד, mezid, which isn't the question the משנה Mishnah
asks. If you remember, the משנה Mishnah asked: Why did the תורה
Torah say טמא tamei and דרך רחוקה? Derech Rechoka? So the רמב"ם
Rambam actually reads the משנה Mishnah like פשט. p'shat. And the רמב"ם
Rambam says that the point of the משנה Mishnah is, is that
if you were טמא tamei and דרך רחוקה Derech Rechoka and then
for some reason you failed to do a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni,
you're still פטור patur from כרת, karet, because that is a category
of פטור. ptur. Whereas if you were, let's say, a שוגג shogeg
for some other reason and then you were a מזיד mezid for
פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, then you're חייב chayav in כרת. karet. Okay?
That there's a fundamental difference, and this is an issue that came
up, Michael and I were talking about, like the position that even
standing one step out of the עזרה Azara or being a טמא
שרץ tamei sheretz who can go in the מקוה mikvah and nevertheless
you're פטור, patur, that this is a category of פטור. ptur. And
for the רמב"ם Rambam what that means is: Okay, sure, make a
פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, that'll be nice, you'll have an opportunity to
bring a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, but it's not like you need
to bring a פסח שני Pesach Sheni to get out of כרת.
karet. You're fundamentally פטור patur because you were טמא tamei or דרך
רחוקה. Derech Rechoka. And that's in contrast to the person who was
just a שוגג shogeg or מזיד mezid for some other reason or
an אונס ones even, and that person needs the פסח שני Pesach
Sheni or they're חייב chayav in כרת. karet. So, real conceptual major
difference in terms of just פשט p'shat of the משנה, Mishnah, completely
not what the גמרא Gemara said, but interestingly for once it's not
only like, sometimes you'll have the גמרא Gemara say a whole explanation
and the גרא Gra gives you a read of the משנה Mishnah
that's the real פשט. p'shat. Here it's the רמב"ם Rambam that gives
you the real פשט p'shat of the משנה, Mishnah, and all of
the מפרשים, meforshim, the ברטנורא, Bartenura, everybody really like follows in the
רמב"ם, Rambam, ignoring the גמרא's Gemara read of the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, the distinction you just made, did רמב"ם Rambam say the distinction
as the distinction between a תיקון tikkun and תשלומין? tashlumin?
Yes, so to some degree it's, it's connected on a תיקון tikkun
and תשלומין tashlumin and that discussion in the גמרא, Gemara, although if
you remember the גמרא's Gemara discussion of those things
did not have an example where you could be מזיד mezid on
the שני sheni
and we could go through it. But anyway, but it's somewhat related.
It's somewhat related. For the רמב"ם, Rambam, the גמרא Gemara basically assumed
that you needed the תיקון tikkun or the תשלומין tashlumin and the
רמב"ם's Rambam חידוש chiddush is טמא ודרך רחוקה tamei ve-derech rechoka you
more have a total פטור. ptur. Now, in terms of the issue
about the whole sun and the רקיע rakia and the גלגל galgal
and so on, I assume that you discussed, I know Dov shared
with me that
you did not do total pre-Copernican whatever cosmology, but I assume you
understood that the basic assumption was, is that the רקיע rakia was
this like opaque dome and the sun went like this, right, and
then went through the thickness of the dome, which is why it's,
I'm sorry.
We had a very similar diagram.
Okay, which is why at, which is why from עלות השחר alos
ha-shachar to הנץ ha-netz and from שקיעה shkia to צאת, tzeis, there's
some light because there's some light escaping through the thickness of the
dome and then according to חז"ל Chazal it goes above the dome
and חכמי אומות העולם chachmei umot ha-olam goes below. Now, a couple
of points just briefly about that discussion in the גמרא. Gemara. Number
one is that the fact that the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי
נצחו דבריהם מדברינו amar Rebbe, nitzchu divreihem mi-divreinu is a basis for
some, the פשט p'shat of that גמרא Gemara is that חז"ל Chazal
are willing to concede on scientific points, that they don't necessarily consider
themselves to be the authorities of science. And that's very important for
the רמב"ם Rambam who made a big issue about the fact that
חז"ל Chazal weren't scientists and it's not a problem saying that their
science was wrong or their medicine was wrong and so on. There
are those that feel that that's very threatening to the authority of
חז"ל Chazal to say they got anything wrong, even science. And therefore,
for example, there was a note there by רבי עקיבא איגר, Rabbi
Akiva Eiger, I don't know if you saw in the side, who
basically says, if you take a look on the צדיק ד עמוד
ב Tzadik Dalet Amud Beis in the גליון הש"ס, Gilyon HaShas, ונראין
דבריהם, ve-nir'in divreihem, lower left hand corner if you have this, he
says, עיין גליון הש"ס, ayin Gilyon HaShas, השגותינו על המעוברת, hasagotenu al
ha-me'uberet, דכתב משמיה דרבינו תם, de-katav mishmei de-Rabbeinu Tam, דאף על גב
דנצחו חכמי אומות העולם את חכמי ישראל, de-af al gav de-nitzchu chachmei
umot ha-olam et chachmei Yisrael, even though they sort of, you know,
were victorious, the non-Jewish wise men, היינו נצחון בטענות, haynu nitzachon beta'anot,
that only meant they had better proofs, אבל האמת כחכמי ישראל, aval
ha-emet kachachmei Yisrael, but in the end. but in the end we're
always right anyway, okay? So I don't care about your proofs, I
know that we're right, proof-shmoof, והיינו דאמרינן בתפילה v'hainu d'amrinan b'tefillah בוקע
חלוני רקיע. boke'ach chalonei rakia. That's why it has to go through
the windows of the רקיע rakia because you see חז"ל Chazal had
it right all along. So anyway, that's an important question for whether
you can accept that חז"ל Chazal made mistakes in science, number one.
Number two, in terms of הלכה למעשה, halacha l'maaseh, some very important
things that emerge from this גמרא Gemara is, first of all, how
long does it take to walk a מיל? mil? If you remember
there were two שיטות shitot in the גמרא... Gemara...
or there were two, but I'm going to tell you there were
three, right?
There was one that it was forty מיל mil minus five at
each end, which meant thirty מיל mil for twelve hours, okay? Equals
twelve hours, okay, 720 minutes. Okay, another one was forty minus four
at each end, which gave you thirty-two. But there's two ways of
reading that גמרא. Gemara. That גמרא Gemara says forty מיל mil and
there's four at each end. It might have meant there's forty and
four for the entire day, for the twelve hours of the day,
right? If you remember that line in the גמרא Gemara forty and
four at each end, is it forty minus the four or in
addition to the four? So another possible reading is forty מיל. mil.
How much is a מיל? mil? If you go like this, a
מיל mil is 24 minutes. If you go like this, a מיל
mil is 22 and a half, and if you go like this,
and it's 40 for 12 hours, a מיל mil is 18 minutes.
We actually rule that a מיל mil is 18 minutes. Okay, that
is very relevant for issues about like how long can you leave
your bread out before it becomes חמץ, chametz, you know? 18 minutes!
The time it takes to walk a מיל. mil.
Okay, so what's the source for that? What? There's a source for
that?
Yes, this is the source although it's debated, some say 22 and
a half, some say 24. Now a מיל mil is about a
kilometer, so to me, 18 seems more accurate, but again it depends
if you're going on a paved road or flat road or not.
Now, another important thing is that this גמרא Gemara says, how long
does this גמרא Gemara say this from שקיעה shkiah to צאת הכוכבים?
tzeit hakochavim?
Anybody remember? Four, five מיל, mil, which is if you do the
math, even if מיל mil is 18, four מיל mil is 72,
five מיל mil is 90. And by the way, just for fun,
if your מיל mil were 24, this would be 120 minutes. So
you might have heard of שיטת רבינו תם shitat Rabbeinu Tam that
שבת Shabbat is not out until 72 minutes after, takes this גמרא
Gemara seriously that four מיל mil till צאת, tzeit, and you have
72 minutes. Now, does it change based on latitude and based on
season? Okay, that's debated, but you start with this as your baseline.
Some people, that's not enough for them to be מחמיר machmir just
like that. Some people wait 90 minutes and some people actually wait
120 minutes based on the most מחמיר machmir position of רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam plus the most מחמיר machmir position of the what do
you call it of the of the מיל. mil. Now, that's how
you get שיטת רבינו תם. shitat Rabbeinu Tam. One word about how
come we don't rule that way: because the גמרא Gemara in שבת
Shabbat that talks about how long is it from שקיעה shkiah to
צאת tzeit has a long discussion about צאת, tzeit, speaks about three
stars getting dark and basically says three-quarters of a מיל. mil. Three-quarters
of a מיל mil by the way would be about 13 and
a half minutes. So anyway, and the הגר"א The Gra and the
גאונים Geonim and the הגר"א The Gra all say that גמרא Gemara
is the real גמרא, Gemara, that's when שבת Shabbat starts. This גמרא
Gemara is not talking about when three stars come out, this גמרא
Gemara and therefore we have to end with our cosmology, this גמרא
Gemara is talking about it wanted to know how long it takes
the sun to pass through the thickness, right? So for the sun
to pass through the thickness, why is that the same as the
period of צאת tzeit for it to pass through the thickness? Because
as it's passing through the thickness, what else is happening in the
thickness is the stars that are at the top are descending down
so they can be seen, and they're also traveling the thickness. So
when the sun has traveled the entire thickness, now there's stars throughout
the thickness. So as the sun starts its travel, you'll start getting
a few stars, and that's the three stars of צאת הכוכבים. tzeit
hakochavim. When the sun has finished its travel, you'll see all of
the stars because even the ones at the very top will have
traveled down, and that's the four מיל mil or the five מיל.
mil.
That's why צאת הכוכבים tzeit hakochavim הלכה halachah is 20 minutes after
שקיעה. shkiah.
So according to the הגר"א The Gra and the גאונים Geonim and
other reasons of and the reading of the גמרא Gemara in שבת,
Shabbat, it's really 13 and a half minutes, that's too soon for
anybody. So you know, I don't know. Anyway, so even in Israel
where they go by the הגר"א, The Gra, they go by about
20-25 minutes, okay, but and the basic way, look, what they're doing
is they're saying if there's a גמרא Gemara that has a הלכה
halachic discussion of when שבת Shabbat begins, that's the גמרא Gemara that
should dictate for הלכות שבת. hilchot Shabbat. This גמרא Gemara is not
about the הלכה halachic צאת הכוכבים tzeit hakochavim and when the next
day begins, it's a גמרא Gemara about cosmology. So if there's a
contradiction that this talks about four מיל mil and that talks about
a three-quarters of a מיל, mil, fine. This is talking about something
else. other than the halakhic issue of when the next day begins.
And therefore they explain that it has to do with this issue
of all the stars traveling traveling down and that's the way for
explaining this גמרא. Gemara. I will also say by the way that
geography matters because רש"י Rashi because all the רמב"ן Ramban and all
the בעלי התוספות Baalei HaTosafos and רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam and everybody
who read that way of 72 minutes were living in like, you
know, France and Germany where it gets dark very late. Whereas the
וילנא גאון, Vilna Gaon, you know, well he was also sort of
living there, but he at least first of all you get a
better read of the גמרא Gemara and if you think about Israel,
Israel gets dark a lot faster. So how those different reads emerge
is should be straightforward. Yes.
In there are parts of Northern Europe where 72 minutes in the
summer actually is still light out.
I can imagine. That's very interesting. Alright, so there you go.
Has nobody has it not occurred to anybody that like the sun
must be moving at different speed at night or that is describing
the longer path.
Oh, you mean how do you deal with the summer and the
winter issue?
Yeah. Well not even even on the equinox, right, the inside of
the dome is shorter than the
Oh, that's a good question.
Yeah, but also the winter and the summer. Right.
Well the inside and the outside, well I imagine that difference is
that whether it's traveling a straight line or whether you know it
travels like this, right? So that you could sort of account for
but if you think about it making a circle, right, you know
if you think about it making an oval, whatever, and what would
be an oval whatever. Anyway I don't know. Alright, let's yes.
But wasn't the understanding that the term חכמי ישראל Chachmei Yisrael here
means חז"ל Chazal and not scientists?
No, it might very well mean scientists.
Yeah, yeah, versus חכמי אומות העולם, Chachmei Umos Haolam, right, the astronomers.
Exactly. Exactly.
And not
necessarily רבנים. Rabbanim.
I agree.
Okay, let's take a look now. משנה. Mishna. מה בין פסח ראשון
לשני? Ma bein Pesach Rishon l'Sheini? What's the difference between פסח ראשון
Pesach Rishon and פסח שני? Pesach Sheini?
We've been discussing how you know you're חיוב Chayav of פסח שני
Pesach Sheini and so on, circumstances in which you bring it. How
is the actual performance of the פסח ראשון Pesach Rishon different from
that of the פסח שני? Pesach Sheini? הראשון אסור בבל יראה ובל
ימצא. HaRishon assur b'bal yeira'eh u'bal yimatzei. The first one is actually
during יום טוב Yom Tov or it precedes יום טוב Yom Tov
and it's connected also to חג המצות. Chag HaMatzos. So therefore there's
a prohibition of owning חמץ Chometz at the night of eating it
and the day before also, you know, the תשביתו Tashbisu begins etc.
the day
before. Okay. And there's an איסור Issur of לא תשחט על חמץ
דם זבחי. Lo tishchat al chometz dam zivchi. So the problem of
חמץ Chometz is there, it's all connected with חג המצות. Chag HaMatzos.
והשני חמץ ומצה עמו בבית. VehaSheini chometz u'matzah imo babayis. So the
second one, go ahead, have חמץ Chometz with you in the house.
Maybe not in the well actually who knows maybe you could even,
I mean it doesn't say that but in theory you could have
like a כורך koreich sandwich that's real bread.
Well although you have to have מצה Matzah too. We're going to
get to that. You have to eat it על מצות ומרורים. al
matzos u'merorim. That's an but I wonder if that excludes the idea
of also having bread. Bread. Exactly. Exactly. והשני. VehaSheini. Okay. Now הראשון
טעון הלל באכילתו. haRishon taun Hallel b'achilaso. The first one you say
הלל Hallel when you eat it. והשני אין טעון הלל באכילתו. vehaSheini
ein taun Hallel b'achilaso. You don't say הלל Hallel when you eat
it. But we're going to discuss וזה וזה, vezeh vezeh, the next
sentence, טעונים הלל בעשייתן. teunim Hallel be'asiyasan.
If you remember when it describes the bringing of the פסח Pesach
and the three groups and so on, so you don't have any
three groups here,
but
but you do still have הלל Hallel when you are bringing it,
just not when you are eating it, which is interesting. ונאכלים צלי
על מצות
ומרורים. v'neechalim tzali al matzos u'merorim. And again the normal sort of
way in which it's eaten, how you treat the actual meat, you
roast it and you eat it with מצה Matzah and מרור, maror,
which is actually in the פסוק, Pasuk, right? על מצות ומרורים יאכלוהו.
al matzos u'merorim yochluhu. I mean even by the פסח שני, Pesach
Sheini, right? ככל חוקת הפסח יעשו אותו. kechol chukas haPesach yaasu oso.
Right. Okay. ודוחים
את השבת. v'dochin es haShabbos. Interestingly because it's במועדו b'moado even though
it's not a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur as I keep on telling
you it's actually I believe a משנה Mishna in ערכין. Erchin. Anyway
I can't remember where the משנה Mishna is. Anyway that it's not
really based on it being קרבן ציבור, korban tzibbur, it's really based
on it being just a חיוב שקבוע לה זמן. chiyuv she'kavuah lah
zeman. And since this has the קבוע זמן kavuah zeman it would
be דוחה את השבת. docheh es haShabbos. We will see about being
דוחה את הטומאה. docheh es haTumah. Okay, so let's take a look
now at the גמרא. Gemara. I want to say something also about
הלל בעשייתן, Hallel be'asiyasan, about באכילתן, b'achilasan, but we'll get to that
in a few minutes. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. ככל חוקת הפסח יעשו
אותו. Kechol chukas haPesach yaasu oso. It says by the פסח שני.
Pesach Sheini. במצוות שבגופו הכתוב מדבר. B'mitzvos shebegufo haksav medaber. We're talking
about things about the body of the פסח Pesach itself, for example
like צלי אש. tzli eish. מצוות שעל גופו מניין? Mitzvos she'al gufo
minayin? How about things that accompany the actual meat of the פסח
Pesach but are not the meat of the פסח Pesach itself? Which
means, תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, על מצות ומרורים יאכלוהו. al matzos u'merorim
yochluhu. So that's why the Torah said it also refers to eating
it with מצה Matzah and מרור. maror. יכול אפילו מצוות שלא על
גופו? Yachol afilu mitzvos shelo al gufo? Maybe things completely unrelated to
the body of the פסח Pesach like בל יראה ובל ימצא? bal
yeira'eh u'bal yimatzei? תלמוד לומר ועצם לא ישברו בו. Talmud lomar v'etzem
lo yishberu vo. It again repeats by the פסח שני. Pesach Sheini.
Why does it have to repeat that? It already said ככל חוקת
הפסח kechol chukas haPesach and it added מצות ומרור matzos u'maror which
is a little bit not about the body of the פסח Pesach
itself, so why did it have to repeat ועצם לא ישברו בו?
v'etzem lo yishberu vo? מקיש ועצם *maki'sh v'etzem* to tell you to
make a analogy based on that, or an extension based on that
category. מקיש ועצם מה עצם מיוחד מצוה שבגופו mitzvah shebegupo, *maki'sh v'etzem
mah etzem miyuchad mitzvah she-be-gufo*, the same way that is about the
body of the פסח pesach, *Pesach* itself and now because of מצה
matzah *matzah* and מרור maror, *maror* we know, or things directly connected
to the body. אף כל מצוה שבגופו mitzvah shebegupo, *af kol mitzvah
she-be-gufo*. We're limiting ourselves to things about the actual body of the
פסח pesach *Pesach* itself and not things that are extraneous like ביעור
ביומו *bi'ur beyomo*. Even, and I should say, and this is not
as obvious but it will be, even if ביעור ביומו *bi'ur beyomo*
is conceptually linked to the פסח pesach? *Pesach* like לא תשחט על
חמץ דם זבחי lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi. *lo tishchat al
chametz dam zivchi*. We're not just talking about ביעור ביומו *bi'ur beyomo*
that night. We're talking about the שחיטת הפסח *shchitas haPesach*, but since
it's not something that you actually do together with the body of
the פסח Pesach *Pesach*, you don't eat it like the מצה matzah.
*matzah* and מרור *maror*, that is considered חוץ מגופו *chutz me-gufo* and
therefore not prohibited.
What kind of analogy is this? In other words, usually it's just
as it applies in this case it applies in the other case.
Here it's just as it applies in the first case we're going
to extend and beyond what it applies in the second case and
make it bigger.
No, we're going to limit it. That just like ועצם לא ישברו
בו ve-etzem lo yishberu vo, *v'etzem lo yishberu bo* relates to the
body of the פסח Pesach *Pesach* itself... oh, you mean what was
the הוה אמינא *hava amina* you're saying? Oh, the גמרא gemara. *Gemara*
will discuss. הוה אמינא *hava amina* could have been ככל חוקת הפסח
*ke-chol chukat haPesach* is just a כלל klal *klal*, maybe it's כל
כל דבר *kol kol davar*, anything related to the פסח Pesach *Pesach*.
Okay, so sort of like a כלל ופרט klal u'prat, *klal u'prat*,
and then you have the other part which is so. All right.
So איסי בן יהודה אומר יעשו אותו ya'asu oto *Isi ben Yehuda
omer, ya'asu oto*. You don't need ועצם לא ישברו ve-etzem lo yishberu
בו bo *v'etzem lo yishberu bo* to limit it to things of
the body. He doesn't disagree with the הלכה *halacha* just with the
derivation. יעשו אותו ya'asu oto במצוה שבגופו הכתוב מדבר *ya'asu
oto be-mitzvah she-be-gufo hakatuv medaber*. It's talking about it, the things relating
to it itself. So again just a question of derivation not really
of... the גמרא gemara *Gemara* will ask it. Okay now, אמר מר
*amar mar*, let's take a look at this, begin to unpack this.
יכול yakhol, אף מצוה mitzvah, שלא גופו *yachol af mitzvah she-lo gufo*,
maybe, now it asks your question, Joe. Maybe not only about the
פסח Pesach? *Pesach* and מצה matzah, *matzah* and מרור *maror*, maybe it
would apply to anything even not about the body of the פסח
pesach *Pesach* itself. What do you mean? הא מצה matzah. במצוה שבגופו
הכתוב מדבר *ha matza be-mitzvah she-be-gufo hakatuv medaber*? You're just saying that
the פסוקים pesukim *psukim* are talking about מצוה שבגופו mitzvah shebegupo. *mitzvah
she-be-gufo*? So הכי קאמר השתא דאמרת *hachi ka'amar hachasht de'amarta* מצה matzah,
*matzah* and מרור *maror* יכול *yachol*, now that we have מצה matzah,
*matzah* and מרור *maror* that start expanding it and we're not just
talking about the body of the פסח pesach? *Pesach*, we're talking about
things connected even if they're not physically the body of the פסח
pesach. *Pesach* itself, אמא יעשו אותו ya'asu oto לאו דוקא lav davka
*amma ya'asu oto lav davka*? So we see יעשו ya'asu אותו oto
*ya'asu oto*, the אותו oto, *oto* is לאו דוקא lav davka. *lav
davka*, means anything. It
means anything related to it. אימא הוה ליה כפרט וכלל *eima hava
lei k'prat u'klal*? Now maybe I read the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* like
a פרט prat *prat* and a כלל *klal*. Now, ונעשה כלל מוסיף
על הפרט *ve'na'aseh klal mosif al hapat* it's a interesting פרט prat
וכלל *prat u'klal* cause but the ואפילו כל מילי נמי *va'afillu kol
milei nami* even anything. So what's the כלל *klal*? The כלל *klal*
could be ככל חוקת הפסח יעשו אותו kechol chukat hapesach ya'asu oto.
*ke-chol chukat haPesach ya'asu oto* or it could be, yeah, the כלל
*klal* is ככל חוקת הפסח יעשו אותו oto *ke-chol chukat haPesach ya'asu
oto*. So once I've said that the אותו oto *oto* is a
little לאו דוקא lav davka. *lav davka*, the word אותו oto *oto*,
not to limit it to גופו *gufo* itself and I learn that
from מצה matzah *matzah* and מרור *maror*, so ככל חוקת הפסח *ke-chol
chukat haPesach* should be a כלל *klal*, maybe I'll include everything. Now
it told me that the אותו *oto* is לאו דוקא lav davka,
*lav davka*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, and I'll even
include like ביעור ביומו *bi'ur beyomo*. So קמ"ל
*k'mashma lan*, not that way. ועצם לא ישברו בו *v'etzem lo yishberu
bo*, we mean it when we say אותו *oto* and בו *bo*,
it's only the actual things that relate to the body of the
פסח pesach? *Pesach* itself. Okay, now איסי בן יהודה *Isi ben Yehuda*
is basically again doesn't disagree. He just says that
נו *nu*, that you learn it out from יעשו אותו *ya'asu oto*.
So he says look, אותו *oto* is דוקא *davka*, I didn't need
to, I wouldn't have assumed אותו *oto* was לאו lav דוקא *lav
davka*, I knew אותו *oto* was דוקא *davka*. I don't need your
extra פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* about מצה matzah *matzah* and מרור *maror*. So
האי עצם מאי עביד ליה *hai etzem mai avid lei*? So if
he doesn't need the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, why does the תורה *Torah*
say ועצם לא ישברו בו *v'etzem lo yishberu bo* since we already
know you do it like you do the קרבן פסח korban pesach?
*Korban Pesach*? So which is again is a funny question because it's
still expanding the אותו *oto* a little bit to not be גופו
*gufo* itself but על גופו al gufo. *al gufo*. But anyway what
does he do with it? מיבעי ליה לאחד עצם שיש בו מוח
ואחד עצם שאין בו מוח *mi-bayei lei le-echad etzem she-yesh bo moach
ve-echad etzem she-ein bo moach*. You might remember going back a week
or two that we said that the אותו *oto* is coming, the
extra פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of ועצם לא ישברו בו *v'etzem lo yishberu
bo* by פסח שני pesach sheni, *Pesach Sheni* is coming to tell
me that the prohibition applies even if there is no marrow in
the bone, it's still prohibited. Now there was a whole, oh no
I'm sorry, I said it the wrong way. Even if there is
marrow in the bone, it's still prohibited and we don't say the
עשה asei, *asseh* of eating the meat of the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach *Korban Pesach* overrides the לא תעשה lo ta'asei, *lo ta'aseh* of
breaking the bone. So why did the תורה *Torah* repeat breaking the
bone? You're right, it didn't need to tell you by פסח שני
pesach sheni *Pesach Sheni*, but it told you to tell you a
general הלכה *halacha* of breaking bones by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach, *Korban
Pesach* even if you have to get to the marrow, it's still
forbidden. ורבנן האי יעשו אותו מאי עבדי ליה *ve-rabbanan hai ya'asu oto
mai avidi lei*? What do the רבנן *Rabbanan* do with the יעשו
אותו *ya'asu oto* once they see, once the תורה *Torah* says sort
of ועצם לא ישברו בו *v'etzem lo yishberu bo* is limiting it
to the body itself, what's יעשו אותו *ya'asu oto*? מיבעי ליה שאין
שוחטין את הפסח על היחיד she'ein shochtin et hapesach al hayachid, *mi-bayei
lei she-ein shochtin et haPesach al hayachid*. דכמה דאפשר להדורי מהדרינן d'kama
d'efshar lehadurei mahadrinan, *de-kama de-efshar l'hiddurei mahadrinan*. So the יעשו אותו?
Did I say, did I skip a line? What's this רבנן האי
יעשו אותו מאי עבדי ליה? Rabbanan hai ya'asu oto mai avdi leh?
Didn't you just say that that's the מצוה שבגופו, mitzvah shebegufa. that's
how we started?
Yeah, but once we're saying that מצה ומרור matzah umaror might have
led me to read אותו as לאו lav? דוקא and you need
ועצם לא תשברו v'etzem lo tishberu בו to tell me מצוה שבגופו,
mitzvah shebegufa you no longer need the יעשו אותו as מצוה שבגופו.
mitzvah shebegufa So what do you do with the אותו, right? I
mean, in the end we're saying we needed the whole פסוק pasuk
of עצם לא תשברו etzem lo tishberu to tell me אותו was
לאו lav דוקא. If he hadn't said עצם לא תשברו etzem lo
tishberu I never would have thought אותו was לאו דוקא. But the
Rabbis thought it was. So if that was לאו דוקא, why is
the Torah saying it? So they're saying, so the יעשו אותו is
because it's לשון רבים lashon rabim and לשון יחיד. lashon yachid. יעשו
plural, אותו singular. To tell you that ideally by פסח שני, pesach
sheni you should try to do it in a חבורה, chaburah, you
should not do it as an individual. Okay,
to tell you שאין שוחטין את הפסח על היחיד, דכמה דאפשר להדורי
מהדרינן, lehadurei mahadrinan as much as it's possible to get a
group. Meaning, it wouldn't be, you know, אסור asur to do it,
in the פסח ראשון pesach rishon you can say it's אסור asur
and there was the debate about that right, because all of כלל
ישראל klal yisrael is bringing it. פסח שני pesach sheni hopefully it's
just a handful. So we're not going to say that it's restricted
to doing it, you know, with more than one person, but we
could say that ideally יעשו אותו will allude to it, will suggest
the idea of having multiple people do it, do one פסח, pesach
and the idea of a חבורה, chaburah, which is actually quite nice
because yeah, well, מהדרינן mahadrinan means we try to seek after, like
לכתחילה, l'chatchila, it's not the word of הידור מצוה, hidur mitzvah, no.
No, but I will say, it gets back to the discussion about
פסח pesach as social מצוה, mitzvah, and this whole idea of בבית
אחד bebayit echad and with other people, so that actually now we're
having the idea of how much we try to recreate that by
פסח שני pesach sheni where פסח שני pesach sheni, is all about
the people that were left behind, the people that weren't part of
the, you know, ולא יכלו, velo yachlu, you know, למה נגרע לבלתי
הקריב את קרבן ה' במועדו בתוך בני ישראל. lamah nigara levilti hakriv
et korban Hashem bemo'ado betoch b'nei yisrael. Like the whole idea is
you're bringing it with כלל ישראל klal yisrael and you're doing it
part of בני ישראל, b'nei yisrael, so it's all this idea of
national, you know, part of the nation and part of a larger
sense of belonging. So it's actually interesting. On the one hand you
could say, yeah, you blew it, now you've just got the פסח
שני pesach sheni which is for יחידים, yechidim, or you could say
let's try to recreate that as much as possible. So I think
that idea of חבורה chaburah is a very interesting one. Yes.
You know, at first I read להדורי lehadurei, מהדרינן mahadrinan, as like
going around looking for other people. Yep. But then I thought maybe
this הידור מצוה, hidur mitzvah, there's a quantitative dimension to the definition
of הידור מצוה, hidur mitzvah, you spend more money,
more of this, more of that.
Right. So you're convinced though...
Yeah, I mean just in terms of פשט, pshat, להדורי, yeah, it
would,
מהדרינן, mehadrenan we try to go after it as much as possible.
I don't think it's saying like the חפצא cheftza of the פסוק,
pasuk yeah, the verb here is about is about like לחזור אחריו.
lachzor acharav. I should say by the way that רש"י Rashi says
לחזור אחריו lachzor acharav goes so far to say that if I'm
the only person who's going to be bringing a פסח שני, pesach
sheni? everybody else magically managed to be טהור tahor and בדרך רחוקה,
b'derech rechoka, I don't know how that would happen, we would actually
intentionally make somebody טמא tamei so I could have somebody to bring
a פסח שני Pesach Sheni. with me.
Wow. How do we know that? I mean like...
I don't know how רש"י Rashi knows that. I don't see that
in the גמרא. Gemara Is it some kind of ראשון? rishon? Yeah.
Yeah. How would we know that you're the only one?
Yeah, I don't know. Okay. If we don't have to deal with
the issue of like bringing קדשים kodeshim מחוץ לחומה, michutz lachoma, right?
From חבורה, chaburah, you don't have restrictions on going from one חבורה
chaburah to another?
Yeah, so that's a big question about right about לא תוציא מן
הבשר. lo totzi min habasar. So hold on, we're going to get
to details, right? But once you do, do you have an idea
of חבורה chaburah altogether by this by the פסח? pesach Is an
important question. Okay, תנו רבנן. t'nu rabbanan. So let's see. Our Rabbis
taught: ככל חוקת הפסח יעשו אותו. יכול כשם שהראשון אסור בבל יראה
ובל ימצא כך שני אסור בבל יראה ובל ימצא? yakhol keshem sheharishon
asur b'bal yeira'eh u'val yimatzei kach sheni asur b'bal yeira'eh u'val yimatzei?
So this is again retreading the same ground except going more details
in terms of what's included and what's excluded. תלמוד לומר: talmud lomar:
על מצות ומרורים יאכלוהו. al matzot u'merorim yochluhu. So you should eat
it with מצה and מרור, meaning only things like that, which is
only things that are על גופו. al gufo ואין לי אלא מצות
עשה. v'ein li ela mitzvat aseh. Now I only know. Now this
is going to sort of say the following, like I only know
to exclude... Normally when we have a כלל ופרט, a פרט prat
is excluding. We assume everything's included and the פרט prat. would exclude.
So the normal thing to do here would be to say what
are the things that we're going to exclude from your obligation of
פסח שני? Pesach Sheni, The גמרא Gemara is going to read this
as we want both... and תוספות Tosafot says this is completely gratuitous.
It's just for the sake of pointing things out, but it's not
really the דרשה. drasha. But as we go through and say what's
excluded, we're going to find a parallel thing that's included. Okay. So,
ואין לי אלא מצות עשה, v'ein li ela mitzvat aseh, which again
basically means that a מצות עשה mitzvat aseh that is not על
גופו al gufo would be excluded because by parallel to the idea
of על מצות ומרורים, al matzot u'merorim, that's על גופו al gufo
included, so a מצות עשה mitzvat aseh that's not על גופו al
gufo would be excluded. מצות לא תעשה מנין? mitzvat lo ta'aseh minayin?
How do I know... to exclude מצות לא תעשה mitzvot lo ta'aseis
that are not related to the body of the פסח pesach itself?
Like חמץ. chametz.
Right, right, one is the מצוה, mitzvah let's say the positive מצוה
mitzvah of תשביתו. tashbitu. How do I know about the negative מצוה
mitzvah about בל יראה ובל ימצא? bal yeira'eh u-val yimatzei? תלמוד לומר
talmud lomar לא תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי. lo tishchat al chametz
dam zivchi. תלמוד לומר talmud lomar לא ישאירו ממנו עד בוקר. lo
yash'iru mimenu ad boker. Okay. נותר, notar, the Torah repeats by פסח
שני. Pesach Sheni So again, only something that is again about the
body, even a לא תעשה, lo ta'asei a לא תעשה lo ta'asei
that's not about the body of the פסח Pesach, would not apply.
ואין לי אלא מצות לא תעשה שניתק לעשה. ve-ein li ela mitzvat
lo ta'asei she-nitak la'asei. Now that's only the prohibition of נותר notar
connected to the positive מצוה mitzvah. of והנותר ממנו באש תשרפו, ve-hanotar
mimenu ba-esh tisrofu, a positive מצוה. mitzvah So מצות לא תעשה גמור
מנין? mitzvot lo ta'asei gamur minayin? How do I know about a
straight vanilla simple לא תעשה lo ta'asei. that that also is that
if it's not about the body of the פסח Pesach, it's also
excluded? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar ועצם לא ישברו בו, don't break it,
which is a straight לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. מה פרט מפורש, mah
prat meforash, so now we have seen that we have an explicit
listing, the three things the Torah listed: מצות ומרורים, matzot u-merorim, לא
ישאירו ממנו, lo yash'iru mimenu, and ועצם לא ישברו very nicely fall
into the three different categories of prohibitions or obligations that חז"ל chazal
normally delineate. מה פרט מפורש, mah prat meforash, מצות עשה, mitzvot asei,
one is a positive מצוה mitzvah על מצות ומרורים, al matzot u-merorim,
ולא תעשה שניתק לעשה ve-lo ta'asei she-nitak la'asei which is לא ישאירו
ממנו lo yash'iru mimenu connected to an עשה, asei ולא תעשה גמור
ve-lo ta'asei gamur and a straight לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. אף כל
מצות עשה ולא תעשה שניתק לעשה ולא תעשה גמור... af kol mitzvat
asei ve-lo ta'asei she-nitak la'asei ve-lo ta'asei gamur... גמור. gamur. So the
same is true by all those. Now the same is true that
by all of those are what? That they're included or excluded? So
again, the simple function of a פרט prat. would be any one
of those that is not על גופו al gufo is excluded because
it's not like the פרט. prat, It has to be any of
those things are included if they're על גופו al gufo. and they're
like the פרט. prat, But the גמרא Gemara is going to point
out what are the things that are in those categories that are
excluded and what are the things that are in those categories that
are included. Or again although תוספות Tosafot says you normally don't need
to include something extra by a פרט, you're just exclusion by a
פרט, but the גמרא Gemara is going to do it for the
fun of it. So let's take a look.
Yes? You said something about the language of לא תעשה שניתק לעשה,
lo ta'asei she-nitak la'asei, it seems to mean the opposite really, right?
Yeah, meaning that the idea it could mean that the עשה asei,
is top of... yeah and ניתק nitak yeah and let's bracket that
because it's actually there's a whole discussion about the relationship of the
לא תעשה שניתק לעשה lo ta'asei she-nitak la'asei and let's just bracket
that for now. But it's a good point what exactly that word
ניתק nitak
means. Okay. לנתק lenatek often means to separate, not to be connected
to. Yes, that's a very good point. It might mean that the
לא... I'll just say one sentence, it might mean the לא תעשה
lo ta'asei. is sort of undermined by the עשה, asei that the
עשה asei comes to be מתקן metaken the לא תעשה. Okay, so
תיקון, tikun, by the way, is the same letters as ניתק. nitak.
You can do something with that. Okay so anyway, now בכללי דמצות
דמצות ומרורים מאי קמרבי? bi-chlalei de-mitzvot de-matzot u-merorim mai ka-marbei? What's included?
Again we're including for the fun of it. Another thing included similar
as which is a מצות עשה, mitzvah asei, צלי אש, tzli esh,
roasted. ובפרטי מאי מימעיט? u-ve-pratei mai mema'it?
Something that's a simple מצות עשה mitzvah asei that is not על
גופו. al gufo What would that be excluding? תשביתו שאור tashbitu se'or
is a positive מצוה mitzvah of destroying שאור. se'or. So the גמרא
Gemara says איפכא אנא ipcha ana again how do I know whether
to include or exclude? מצות דגופיה עדיף mitzvot de-gufeih adif again the
key principle here that's not being stated is we're including the ones
that are על גופו al gufo. and excluding the ones that are
not על גופו. בכללי דלא ישאירו ממנו עד בוקר מאי קמרבי? bi-chlalei
de-lo yash'iru mimenu ad boker mai ka-marbei?
In the כלל of לא ישאירו lo yash'iru of נותר, notar, what
are you including? Again an עשה aseh that's ניתק nitak to a
לא תעשה. What also would apply to the פסח? Pesach לא תוציא
ממנו lo totzi mimenu and here you go Michael, taking it out
of the בית, bayit, out of the חבורה. chaburah. So interestingly we
learn and this is nowhere in the פסוקים and this is a
real שקלא וטריא shakla ve-tarya right? Is the פסח שני, pesach sheni?
is it done בחבורה? be-chaburah? You might think the whole idea of
פסח שני pesach sheni is a couple of יחידים, yechidim, you're no
longer in this communal experience. And now we find out number one
מהדרינן on having חבורה chaburah and number two the prohibitions of לא
תוציא lo totzi apply.
And all the other rules of חבורה.
chaburah. And all the other things presumably apply to חבורה. chaburah. Now
what exactly is it ניתק לעשה nitak la'asei is not clear. רש"י
Rashi says this גמרא Gemara assumes not like any of the other
גמרות Gemarot we read that if you were מוציא חוץ לחבורה motzi
chutz la-chaburah you could be מתקן metaken it by bringing it back
into the חבורה. chaburah. And it says בבית אחד יאכל be-vayit echad
yei'achel that would be the תיקון. tikun. And רש"י Rashi says it's
not like anything we learned because everything we learned in the past
said that it becomes פסול pasul as soon as you bring it
outside of the house. Okay. So the parenthesis which is clearly a
later gloss in the גמרא Gemara and that's why it's being sort
of parenthesized out but is bothered by this same issue: how is
this similar to נותר? notar? This is not ניתק לעשה. nitak la'asei.
So the parenthesis says דדמי ליה דהאי פסול בנותר והאי פסול ביוצא.
de-dami lei de-hai pasul be-notar ve-hai pasul be-yotzei. It's similar in the
way that it's a פסול, psul, נותר notar creates an invalidity and
being מוציא motzi it חוץ לבית chutz la-bayit creates an invalidity. So
that would be something like נותר notar that's included. ובפרטי מאי
מימעיט? u-ve-pratei mai mema'it? What's like נותר notar that's excluded? בל יראה
ובל ימצא, bal yeira'eh u-val yimatzei,
the simple prohibition. of owning חמץ, chametz, which is חוץ לגופא, chutz
legufa, okay, and it's ניתק לעשה. nitak la-aseh. What's the עשה that
it's ניתק nitak to? לא יראה ולא ימצא lo yeira'eh v'lo yimatzei
תשביתו. tashbisu. Right.
It's so, you know, so, and we might as well read the
parentheses. Again, this gloss. דדמי ליה דהאי אינו לוקה דהוי לאו שניתק
לעשה והאי אינו לוקה דהוי לאו שניתק לעשה d'dami lei d'hai eino
lokei d'havei lav she'nitak la'aseh v'hai eino lokei d'havei lav she'nitak la'aseh
here because of תשביתו. tashbisu. So that's excluded.
What's the לאו ולא תוציאו ממנו? v'lo totziu mimenu?
From the בית, bayis, from the חבורה. chaburah. מן הבשר חוצה. min
habasar chutza. Okay. Right.
אי בעית אימא,
ei bayis
eima,
maybe I should reverse it? מצוה דגופיה עדיף. mitzvah d'gufei adif. No,
again, the key dividing line is whether it relates to the body
of the פסח Pesach or not. Okay. בכלליה דעצם לא תשברו בו
b'klaleih d'etzem lo sishberu bo מאי קא מרבה? mai ka marbeh?
What's similar to עצם לא תשברו בו, etzem lo sishberu bo, a
simple לאו? אל תאכלו ממנו נא, al tochlu mimenu na,
don't eat raw. בפרט מאי קא ממעט? b'prat mai ka m'mait? לא
תשחט על חמץ דם זבחי. lo tishchat al chametz dam zivchi? Now
that's a חידוש, chiddush, you know, cause you could say נותר, nosar,
you know, being מוציא חוץ לבית, motzi chutz labayis, so that's a
לאו that's related to it, not related to how you eat it,
but how you treat it. Maybe this prohibition about לא תשחט lo
tishchat על חמץ chametz דם זבחי? רש״י Rashi says although there's no
תשביתו tashbisu or בל יראה ובל ימצא, bal yeira'eh u-val yimatzei, fine,
you can buy your חמץ chametz. after you've שחט-ed shecht it, but
maybe when you're שחט-ing shecht it you should be prohibited to own
חמץ. chametz. That even that is considered to be חוץ לגופא. chutz
legufa. It's not about how you're what you're doing with the meat
itself in the ways the other things are. You're being מוציא motzi
the meat out of the בית, bayis, you're מותיר mosir the meat.
Here it's just you're שחט-ing shecht the animal and you happen to
own חמץ. It's not something you're doing with the meat. אי בעית
אימא, ei bayis eima, מצוה דגופיה עדיף. mitzvah d'gufei adif. Okay, so
there you have these distinctions of על גופא al gufa and חוץ
לגופא chutz legufa with I still think that the לא תשחט is
the bigger חידוש. chiddush. Okay, now let's continue about other differences. הלל
פעמים הראשון טעון הלל באכילתו. Hallel pe'amim harishon taun Hallel b'achilaso. The
first one you do הלל Hallel when you eat it, not the
second one, but both you do הלל Hallel when you bring it.
מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? Where is this from? אמר רב
יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק אמר קרא, amar Rav Yochanan mishum
Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, השיר יהיה
לכם כליל התקדש חג. hashir yihyeh lachem k'leil hiskadesh chag. There really
are two questions here. How do you know you say הלל Hallel
when you eat the פסח ראשון pesach rishon altogether? And number two
is, how do you know that you don't say it on פסח
שני? Pesach Sheni So the פסוק pasuk. says that song that you
will sing at the time of ultimate גאולה geula will be for
you like the like the night sanctified with the, you know, with
with the
הלל. Hallel. So what night is sanctified sanctified with a holiday? The
night that you're singing because it's שיר. shir. What night could it
be other than the night of eating the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach,
Okay, I mean, we don't he's he's not talking about saying זמירות
zmiros in your סוכה. sukka. סוכה? sukka? Right. לילה המקודש לחג טעון
הלל. layla hamkudash l'chag taun Hallel. So it's only one that's connected
to a חג, chag, to חג המצות. chag hamatzos. לילה שאין מקודש
לחג אין טעון הלל, layla she'ein mkudash l'chag ein taun Hallel, not
one not connected to a חג. chag. Now, I want to pause
here for a moment. So it seems like a bit of a
stretch, but okay, fine, whatever. But nevertheless, we have the idea of
saying הלל באכילתו. Hallel b'achilaso. Now what is not said relating to
whether what you do or don't do with the פסח? Pesach. What
do we do סדר Seder night that's the central part of our
סדר Seder night? What? ארבע כוסות? Arba Kosos? Not ארבע כוסות. Arba
Kosos. Yes, but I'm talking about a דאורייתא.
d'oraisa. Oh. I'm sorry, wait, I'm sorry.
I'm talking about a דאורייתא d'oraisa that we do on סדר Seder
night that's not being discussed here.
אכילת מצה? Achilas Matzah?
מגיד! Maggid! The מצוה mitzvah of הגדה, hagadda, the מצוה mitzvah of
telling סיפור יציאת מצרים. sippur yetzias Mitzrayim. Is that something you're supposed
to do or not? Which raises a really important question about the
relationship of מגיד maggid to the פסח. Pesach Right? When we have
the statement, and we'll discuss this plenty when we get to the
next פרק, perek, כל שלא אמר שלושה דברים אלו בפסח לא יצא
ידי חובתו ואלו הם פסח מצה ומרור. kol she'lo amar shlosha devarim
eilu b'pesach lo yatza yedei chovaso v'eilu hein pesach matzah u'maror. Let's
say you didn't, forget whether he means it literally לא יצא lo
yatza or not, but let's say you didn't say it, what have
you been not יוצא ידי חובה yotzei yedei chova of? מגיד maggid
or or or
פסח? Pesach Maybe or מצה. Maybe if you don't explicate what you're
why you're eating the פסח Pesach and why you're eating the מצה,
you haven't done a full קיום kiyum of פסח Pesach, and מצה.
Or maybe you're not יוצא yotzei fully מגיד, maggid, or maybe both.
So one minute, so to the degree that you understand that the
מצוה mitzvah of מגיד maggid is connected to מצה, right? For example,
the גמרא Gemara says if מצה בזמן הזה matzah bizman hazeh is
דרבנן, drabbanan, מגיד maggid is דרבנן. drabbanan. If that's true about מצה,
I would think it's true about the פסח Pesach. itself. So the
question is, if it's connected and it's part of the מצוה mitzvah
of how you eat the פסח Pesach and how you eat the
מצה is by contextualizing it and symbolizing it and giving the explanation,
it's not it's not just that they help your מגיד, maggid, your
מגיד maggid helps give meaning to them, then you would have thought
maybe that even on פסח שני Pesach Sheni you would have to
say מגיד. maggid. Now what?
לא יצאת בידי כל מצוה lo yatzasa b'yadei kol mitzvah like סוכות,
sukkos, you know, is למען ידעו דורותיכם, l'maan yeidu doroseichem, but nobody
says that if you don't סוכה sukka you're going to say, "I
have מכוון," mechaven, or or or whatever that... Right.
By the way, there is a ב״ח Bach that basically wants to
say that because of למען ידעו דורותיכם l'maan yeidu doroseichem he does
say בדיעבד, b'diavad, but he said you really are חייב chayiv to
be thinking about that. But anyway, but you don't have a מצוה
mitzvah of מגיד maggid on סוכות. sukkos. You have a מצוה mitzvah
of מגיד. maggid. So my question is, does מגיד? maggid? Now, obviously
the answer... The answer goes now, so it's not discussed, but it
might be if that's how you eat it. If you eat it
through the telling of the story, the same way שיעור. shiur. Anyway,
the point is that the same way שיעור shiur is excluding, you
could assume מגיד maggid is excluded as well. And מגיד maggid again,
even if when you are eating the פסח, Pesach it's part of
how you eat the פסח, Pesach, it could be presumably it has
independent status as well. And anyway, מגיד maggid is connected to the
יום טוב, Yom Tov, the חג המצות Chag HaMatzos if you will,
not to אכילת פסח. achilas Pesach. Okay, so, and that could be
just like this line of הלל התקדש חג, Hallel hiskadesh chag, that
yes, it's in the context of eating the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach.
and yes maybe it even enhances the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach but
at the end of the day it is connected to חג המצות
Chag HaMatzos and not and not to אכילת הפסח. achilas HaPesach. Right,
but I did want to point out it is not so פשוט,
poshut, either the A, it's interesting it's not discussing הלל. Hallel. B,
it's not discussing מגיד. maggid. That's interesting in its own. B, it's
not so פשוט. poshut. You would have thought, I get it that
the answer is that הלל's Hallel connected to the חג, chag, but
normally we don't say a הלל בלילה Hallel balailah and this is
a הלל Hallel that's also connected to the פסח Pesach and I
might have said even without the חג chag you would have said
the הלל. Hallel. Now I do want to say something about מגיד
maggid and הלל Hallel and the גמרא's Gemara assumption that you say
הלל. Hallel. If you look at the
pre-Mishnaic evidence or the extra-Mishnaic evidence in Philo
and Josephus, I believe particularly in Philo where he describes the eating
of the קרבן korban. פסח, Pesach I want to see if I
can if I can pull it down. He describes the eating of
the קרבן korban פסח. Pesach I have it on my finger but
I forgot to I forgot to pull it off. Anyway, he mentions
that they would stand in the... No, but it's in a source
sheet that I have, but that's a good question. But also in
the book of Jubilees, which is sort of early... I think the
dating for that is earlier than the time of the משנה, Mishna,
I'm pretty positive. Yes. So anyway, there too when it describes the
אכילת פסח, achilas Pesach, it says that they would eat it and
sing song and rejoice and praise God throughout the night. And it
basically mentions הלל Hallel with no mention of מגיד. maggid. So it's
again as רבי Rebbe says, it's therefore significant that this משנה Mishna
is discussing the הלל Hallel question and not the מגיד maggid question
and it seems to some degree that is more deeply connected to
the פסח Pesach, at least at an earlier stage than the מגיד
maggid itself. Yes, so I once read...
I once read an academic exposé a long time ago that there
was always שירה shira with קרבנות. korbanos.
There was always where there was always שירה shira in the bringing
of קרבנות, korbanos, also in the eating of קרבנות. korbanos. Interesting.
What if I brought my שלמים? shlamim? And that's why at the
end of דאווענינג davening in שחרית, Shacharis, you have the juxtaposition
in נוסח אשכנז nusach Ashkenaz of the of the שירים shirim with
the קרבנות, korbanos, the repetition of some of the קרבנות. korbanos. You
always have שירה shira with
קרבן. korban, No קרבן korban would be at the end of דאווענינג.
davening.
What? No קרבנות korbanos at the very end of שחרית? Shacharis? By
the way, a little bit, a little snippet of the קרבנות. korbanos.
For אשכנז Ashkenaz and we have it in the beginning.
In the beginning, yes.
Okay, anyway here I actually found. Let me read it to you.
Amazing what you can do with your apps nowadays. Okay, here we
go. So it says...
You can't give the שיעור shiur on שבת. Shabbos. Anyway... I thought
I had it.
Okay, here we go. Jubilees. Okay, so now Jubilees tells the story
of the first פסח. But it seems obviously it's sort of
extrapolating back. There's a word for that, to extrapolate back. Anyway, and
the plague was very... what? And the plague was very grievous in
Egypt and there was no house in Egypt that there was no
one who died and there was much weeping and lamentation. And all
of Israel was eating the flesh of the paschal lamb and drinking
the wine and was lauding and blessing and giving thanks to the
Lord the God of their fathers and was ready to go forth
from under the yoke of Egypt. So they had eating the פסח
with הלל. Hallel. Now in Philo you have also earlier than the
משנה, Mishna, and each house is at this time invested with the
character and dignity of a temple. The victim, meaning the sacrifice, being
sacrificed so as to make suitable feast for the man who has
provided it, and those who are collected to share in the feast
being all duly purified with holy ablutions. And those who are to
share in the feast come together not as they do to other
entertainments, here goes with the sort of Greek entertainments, to gratify their
bellies with wine and meat, but to fulfill their hereditary custom with
prayer and songs of praise. No מגיד, maggid, but yes שירה. shira.
So very interesting. Yes, so as we announce שירה, shira, the
מוסף Mussaf of שבת Shabbos at the end after מוסף Mussaf you
have פיטום הקטורת? Pitum Haketores? Yes, and then you have השיר שהלוים.
Hashir Shehaleviyim. Right, right, right, right.
Oh, the שיר, shir, right, but normally that's assumed to be with
the הקרבת קרבן. hakravas korban. One last question then we gotta move
on.
מגיד maggid is discussed in the next chapter. Yes, but they don't
mention פסח שני Pesach Sheni in the next... Right, right, right.
So that's my point. Okay, but the... But again, even if it
doesn't apply, which I assume it doesn't if הלל Hallel doesn't discuss
it, I think it's significant that מגיד Magid is ignored here. Okay,
moving on. זה וזה טעונים הלל בעשייתן. Zeh v'zeh te'unim Hallel b'asiyasan.
Both of them you do הלל Hallel when you bring it. מאי
טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אי בעית אימא I ba'is eima
לילה קמימעי laila kamimai יום לא קמימעי. yom lo kamimai. It was
only said כליל התקדש חג, k'leil hiskadesh chag, only excluded the הלל
Hallel of the night, not of the day. Okay, and I think
I've mentioned before by the way that those people have a מנהג
minhag of saying הלל Hallel in שול shul at פסח night which
we almost never do. Could be to try to reproduce the הלל
Hallel of the הקרבת הפסח. hakravas ha'Pesach. I heard something
about the
Rebbi too.
Yeah,
I know.
But then we never do on other ימים טובים
Yomim Tovim so whatever. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eima,
if you want
I can say, אפשר efshar the reason is
אפשר ישראל שוחטין את פסחיהן ונוטלין לולביהן ואין אומרין הלל? efshar Yisrael
shochtin es pisecheihen v'notlin lulaveihen v'ein omrin Hallel? How do I know
that they said הלל? Hallel? Because it says, like, how do I
know that יעקב אבינו Yaakov Avinu wore a שטריימל? shtreimel? Would he
have gone out without a שטריימל? shtreimel? How do I know they
said הלל? Hallel? Because, right? How could they bring the פסח without
הלל? Hallel? Now, exactly. So it's first of all I should say
that that's a surprising statement. We'll discuss it more, to discuss it
at greater length in the next פרק. perek. But first of all
it says, you know, the רמב"ן Ramban says that based on this,
this sort of self-evident idea that הלל Hallel is דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, at
least for certain things like during the time of these מצוות, mitzvos,
you know, maybe not related to the חג. chag. Now of course,
you know, the question is how could it be דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, דוד
המלך, Dovid haMelech, you know, wrote הספר תהלים. haSefer Tehillim. Right, exactly
what תהלים, Tehillim, you know, exactly what you say for הלל, Hallel,
that's not דאורייתא d'Oraisa like תפילה tefilla question, but the idea of
saying שירה shira together with doing these things. Now of course the
point though is, as Michael
said, okay,
first of
all there's two הללים Hallels to think about: הלל Hallel because of
the קדושת החג kedushas ha'chag and הלל Hallel with the עשיית מצוות.
asiyas mitzvos.
Here it's emphasizing עשיית מצוות. asiyas mitzvos. But why all of a
sudden, you know, the הקרבת הפסח hakravas ha'Pesach and not the אכילת
הפסח?
achilas ha'Pesach? Right, so I don't, you know, to me I didn't
get a chance to fully research it but I looked around quickly
and I didn't see a discussion. If I find something tomorrow I'll
tell you. But again, to me that's like, again, you could say,
well that's why the פסוק pasuk.
is ממעט mima'et that, if it wasn't for
the פסוק pasuk we would have said.
But nevertheless the sort of intuitive thing
is אפשר ישראל שוחטין את פסחיהן. efshar Yisrael shochtin es pisecheihen. It's
not אפשר ישראל אוכלין את
פסחיהן.
efshar Yisrael
ochlin es pisecheihen. Now you could have said again, the הלל Hallel
connected with the קרבן, korban. but that's normally the לויים Levi'im
and that's not what's being said here.
It's talking about a הלל Hallel per connected with מצוות mitzvos that
are about, you
know, חג מצוות, chag mitzvos, שמחה מצוות. simcha mitzvos. So I don't
know why it's more self-evident in the הקרבה hakrava and not in
the אכילה.
achila. All right, נאכלין צלי. ne'echalin tzali. Now you eat it, they
both are eaten roasted and they both דוחה שבת. doche Shabbos. שבת
Shabbos ולא טומאה. v'lo tumah. It's only דוחה שבת, doche Shabbos, not
טומאה. tumah. מתניתין דלא כרבי יהודה, Masnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Yehuda, not like
Rabbi Yehuda. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braisa: דוחה את
השבת ואינה דוחה את הטומאה. doche es ha'Shabbos v'eina docha es ha'tumah.
They override שבת, Shabbos, not טומאה. tumah. רבי יהודה אומר אף דוחה
את הטומאה. Rabbi Yehuda omer af docha es ha'tumah. No, if it's
a fixed time, it'll override טומאה. tumah. So מאי טעמא דתנא קמא,
mai ta'ama d'tana kamma, assuming again that means that everybody is טמא.
tamei. Everybody who was supposed to bring the פסח שני Pesach Sheni?
is now טמא. tamei. Okay, or all the כהנים kohanim are now
טמא. tamei. מאי טעמא דתנא קמא, mai ta'ama d'tana kamma, what's the
reason of the תנא קמא tana kamma that it says it doesn't
override טומאה? tumah? מפני הטומאה דחיסו ויחזור ויעשה בטומאה? mipnei ha'tumah dechiso
v'yachzor v'ya'aseh b'tumah? The whole reason you didn't bring the פסח ראשון
Pesach Rishon was because you were טמא. tamei. And they say, okay,
you couldn't bring it since you were טמא, tamei, now we'll bring
it and you're טמא? tamei? Okay, again, now maybe everybody is טמא,
tamei, but doesn't matter, it's the whole point is lost, right? רבי
יהודה התורה חזרה עליו לעשותו בטהרה. Rabbi Yehuda ha'Torah chazra alav la'asoso
b'tahara. The Torah wants you to try to do it בטהרה, b'tahara,
you blew your first chance. לא זכה יעשה בטומאה. lo zachah ya'aseh
b'tumah. Okay, so it was bizarre, let it be bizarre, but you
still have to bring a קרבן korban. פסח and, you know, and
it should be over and טומאה tumah should override, it's a fixed
obligation. Okay, תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. פסח ראשון דוחה את השבת פסח
שני אינו דוחה את השבת. Pesach rishon doche es ha'Shabbos Pesach sheni
eino doche es ha'Shabbos. Is this טומאת מת tumas meis or is
it just טומאת שרץ או זב? tumas sheretz o zav? I don't
know. Presumably it would be the same as the ways it would
be דוחה doche by פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon. Okay, so now here
this ברייתא braisa assumes it doesn't even override שבת. Shabbos. פסח ראשון
דוחה את הטומאה פסח שני אינו דוחה את הטומאה. Pesach rishon doche
es ha'tumah Pesach sheni eino doche es ha'tumah. So here this is
bizarre, it reversed it, that פסח שני Pesach Sheini, is דוחה טומאה
doche tumah but not שבת. Shabbos. פסח ראשון טעון לינה פסח שני
טעון לינה. Pesach rishon ta'un lina Pesach sheni ta'un lina. So and
they both require לינה lina because the פסוק pasuk says when you
bring the פסח, right, it says ופנית בבקר והלכת לאהליך, u'fanisa v'voker
v'halachta l'ohalecha, that you have to stay over that night, you don't
finish eating it and leave, okay? So let's just unpack this. דוחה
את הטומאה כמאן כרבי יהודה. Doche es ha'tumah k'man k'Rabbi Yehuda. It
overrides טומאה, tumah, that's like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that says yes,
it overrides טומאה tumah like any other, you know, whatever, קרבן קבוע
לזמן. korban kavua l'zman. ורבי יהודה אית ליה טעון לינה? U'Rabbi Yehuda
is lei ta'un lina? And for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would it
require לינה? lina? והתניא רבי יהודה אומר מנין לפסח שני שאינו טעון
לינה? V'hatanya Rabbi Yehuda omer minayin l'Pesach Sheni she'eino ta'un lina? How
do I know that you don't have to sleep over the night
for פסח שני? Pesach Sheini שנאמר ופנית בבקר והלכת לאהליך. shene'emar u'fanisa
v'voker v'halachta l'ohalecha. וכתיב ששת ימים תאכל מצות U'ksiv sheishes yamim tochal
matzos the next פסוק. pasuk הנאכל לשישה, Hane'echal l'shisha, something that the
חג chag continues later that there's eating of מצה for six days,
טעון לינה. ta'un lina. שאינו נאכל לשישה אין טעון לינה. She'eino ne'echal
l'shisha ein ta'un lina. So how could it be רבי יהודה? Rabbi
Yehuda? How could it say it's דוחה את הטומאה doche es ha'tumah
and then say... that it's טעונה לינה, t'unah linah, that's not רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position. So גמרא Gemara. says fine, תרי תנאי אליבא
דרבי יהודה. trei tannai aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda. There's a debate of תנאים
Tannaim according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, now, but of course
what's interesting is this גמרא Gemara. did not discuss, I didn't misread
it, did I? Is that— maybe I misread it about דוחה את
השבת? docheh es haShabbos? Yes, this bottom says דוחה. docheh. Oh, oh,
both it says. Okay, דוחה את השבת docheh es haShabbos פסח שני,
Pesach Sheini yeah, because the גמרא didn't discuss it. Fine. Both is
דוחה את השבת. docheh es haShabbos. Fine. We— nobody is questioning דוחה
את השבת. docheh es haShabbos. So I misread that before. The only
question is whether it's טעונה לינה t'unah linah and whether it's דוחה
טומאה. docheh tumah. תוספות Tosafos has a long discussion whether every קרבן
korban might be טעונה לינה, t'unah linah, not just פסח. And therefore
there's other גמרות Gemoros that sound like that. And therefore what would
you be doing excluding פסח from that? But פסח שני Pesach Sheini.
from that. I want to read you a fascinating line in the
תוספתא Tosefta about this idea that following— that I think that it's
not טעונה לינה t'unah linah פסח שני Pesach Sheini, against our משנה.
Mishna. Which means you go for that one day and you stay
overnight. Yeah. No, but not טעונה לינה t'unah linah means you leave.
You eat it that night and you can leave ירושלים Yerushalayim as
long as you're not going חוץ לתחום. chutz l'techum. You can leave
ירושלים Yerushalayim that night. Oh well, it's פסח שני. Pesach Sheini. You
eat it, then you jump in your car and you drive back
that night. That's if you're not— if it's not טעונה לינה. t'unah
linah. You don't perform— doing מלאכה. melacha. Right. If you were טעונה
לינה, t'unah linah, then you'd have to stay over that night, overnight.
Right. And so like that idea of jumping in your car and
going back, I want to read you this one line from the
תוספתא Tosefta which is— תוספתא Tosefta you're saying you're reading? Yeah, hold
on. Right, so it says like this. It says הראשון דוחה את
השבת השני דוחה את השבת הראשון טעון לינה והשני טעון לינה רבי
יהודה אומר אין השני טעון לינה אלא כיצד הוא עושה? Harishon docheh
es haShabbos hasheini docheh es haShabbos Harishon taun linah v'hasheini taun linah
Rabbi Yehuda omer ein hasheini taun linah ela keitzad hu oseh? This
colorful line was missing from our גמרא. נכנס ושוחט פסחו בעזרה ויוצא
ומספר תספורת בית פגי. Nichnas v'shocheit pischo ba'azarah v'yotzei u'mesapeir tisporet Beis
Pagi. So I was hoping you're not required to do that, but
it says even if a guy has to go ahead and be
מטמא metamei to his father just died and he has to become
טמא tamei or what not, and he has to leave ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
let him leave ירושלים, Yerushalayim, let him become טמא, tamei, let him
be בדרך רחוקה bederech rechoka and טמא, tamei, all those things right—
bring your פסח and then go take care of it. Now, it
should've said go bring your פסח, eat the meat and then go.
But remember again, the עיקר ikar is להקריב את הפסח. l'hakriv es
haPesach. Even though there's obviously a מצוה mitzvah. of אכילת הבשר. achilas
habasar. But you can eat it— no, he's jumping in his car.
No, that again, you can't take it חוץ לירושלים. chutz l'Yerushalayim. Okay,
now let's get started on the next משנה. Mishna. He doesn't wait
until like the night to eat it then? פסח שני, Pesach Sheini.
he eats it like during the day? Which is— which is right?
No, no, no, you eat it at— well, that's not discussed until
when could you eat it, but presumably it's the, you know, נותר
nosar applies, so it's עד הבוקר. ad haboker. Presumably it's the— you
know, it's only eaten that night like the פסח ראשון. Pesach Rishon.
That's clearly a מצוה שבגופו. Yeah, exactly. הדרש, Hadrash, right, is ואכלו
את הבשר בלילה הזה. v'achlu es habasar balaila hazeh. So I mean,
presumably that's a מצוה. I don't see מצוה שבגופו גדול מזו, gadol
mizo, you know. But— but you're doing your שחיטה shechita on the
15th? No, it says עד הבוקר ad haboker and that's explicit in
the פסוק. You do your שחיטה shechita on the 14th? You do
the שחיטה shechita on the 14th of the פסח שני. Yeah, I
mean, yeah, it says— yeah, it is... The only question would be
can you eat it prior to שקיעה shkiya of the 15th? And
no, I mean, I don't think there's a מצוה שבגופו גדול מזו.
gadol mizo. Okay. הפסח שבא בטומאה. Hapesach sheba b'tumah. Okay, now of
course you thought we were— we were free from the טומאה. tumah.
No, no, no. Can't get out of it. הפסח שבא בטומאה לא
יאכלו ממנו זבים וזבות נדות ויולדות. Hapesach sheba b'tumah lo yochlu mimenu
zavim v'zavos nidos v'yoldos. I have no idea what this is doing
after discussion of פסח שני. Okay, but anyway, if you had a
case that the ציבור tzibur was טמא tamei and it's brought בטומאה—
b'tumah I'm sorry, you're talking about פסח ראשון? Pesach Rishon? פסח ראשון.
Pesach Rishon. לא יאכלו ממנו זבים וזבות נדות ויולדות. Lo yochlu mimenu
zavim v'zavos nidos v'yoldos. You can't eat from it if your טומאה
tumah is only from an external source like a מת meis or
a שרץ, sheretz, not a טומאה יוצא מגופו tumah yotzei migufa that
does not make רוב הציבור rov hatzibur טמא tamei to be דוחה
docheh and it does not allow a person with that status to
eat from the פסח either. Even though it's being brought בטומאה b'tumah
and everybody else is טמא, tamei, this is a— you know, worse
status of טומאה, tumah, a more personal status of טומאה tumah that
is not overridden. So a זב zav or זבה, zava, a נדה
niddah or a woman who's just given birth, they cannot eat, הם
פטורים מן הכרת. hem pturim min hakareis. But because it is a
פסח that's נאכל בטומאה, ne'echal b'tumah, they don't get the normal כרת
kareis you would get if you are טמא tamei and ate from
a קרבן. korban, רבי אליעזר פוטר אף על ביאת מקדש. Rabbi Eliezer
poter af al bias mikdash. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says even if
they got— went into the עזרה azarah during the time the פסח
was being brought, they are פטור. pattur. Maybe even that we'll talk
about later, but if it's a time when טמא tamei people can
enter the עזרה, azarah, then it is also you cannot be חייב
chayav for entering the עזרה. azarah. So although your status is a
זב, זבה, נדה, יולדת zav zava niddah yoledes and so on, you
are prohibited still eating from פסח, although it's brought בטומאה, b'tumah, but
the fact that it is brought בטומאה... b'tumah... means we can't be
מחייב mechayav you כרת karet for eating it, presumably there's still an
איסור, issur, an איסור עשה, issur asei, some type of an איסור,
issur, and according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer we can't even be
מחייב mechayav you for being נכנס nichnas into the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash since other people who are טמא tamei are doing that as
well. Let's see a little bit of the גמרא. תנו רבנן: Tanu
Rabbanan: זבים וזבות נדות ויולדות שאכלו פסח שבא בטומאה יכול יהיו חייבין,
Zavim veZavot Niddot veYoldot she'achlu Pesach sheba betumah yakhol yihyu chayavin, maybe
you'd be חייב chayav כרת karet if you ate from it when
other people were טמא. tamei. תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: כל טהור יאכל
בשר. Kol tahor yokhal basar. The פסוק says you have to be
טהור tahor to eat meat, and that's the פסוק we're talking about
getting כרת karet if you're טמא, tamei, eating a קרבן. korban And
then it says והנפש אשר תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים אשר לה' וטומאתו
עליו ונכרתה. Ve'hanefesh asher tokhal basar mizevach hashelamim asher l'Hashem vetumato alav
venikhretah. Okay, and then it says you get כרת karet if you're
טמא. tamei. But that, so but those are connected. נאכל לטהורים ne'ekhal
letahorim when it's כל טהור יאכל בשר, kol tahor yokhal basar, when
it's being limited to טהור tahor people, then חייבין עליו משום טמא,
chayavin alav mishum tamei, חייב chayav for being טמא. tamei. שאינו נאכל
לטהורים, she'eino ne'ekhal letahorim, a קרבן korban that actually, it's not really
the time, it's more like the חפצא cheftza of the קרבן, a
קרבן that is now not restricted to טהור tahor people, this type
of meat can be eaten by טמא tamei people, אין טמאים חייבין
עליו משום טמא. ein tme'im chayavin alav mishum tamei. You're not חייב
chayav כרת karet for eating it. You're only חייב chayav כרת karet
for a type of a meat of a קרבן that's limited to
טהור tahor people. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: יכול, now רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is going to discuss entering into the בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, same logic. יכול דחקו זבים ונכנסו לעזרה? yakhol dacheku zavim
venikhnasu la'azarah? Right,
the פסח הבא בטומאה, Pesach habah betumah, יכול יהיו חייבין? yakhol yihyu
chayavim? If זבים zavim force their way
in, somehow זבים ומצורעים, zavim umtzora'im, and they needed to be part
of the excitement and they force their way in when it was
בא בטומאה, bah betumah, maybe they'd be חייב chayav כרת? karet? תלמוד
לומר: Talmud lomar: וישלחו מן המחנה כל צרוע וכל זב וכל טמא
לנפש. vishalkhu min hamachaneh kol tsarua vekhol zav vekhol tamei lanafesh. Send
all these people out, זבים, zavim, מצורעים, metzora'im, and טמאי מתים. tmei
meitim. בזמן שטמאי מתים משתלחים, Bizman she'tmei meitim mishtalkhin, when the טמאי
מתים tmei meitim are being kicked out of the camp, out of
the, which טמא מת tamei meit is only outside of the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, זבים ומצורעים משתלחים. zavim umtzora'im mishtalkhin. That's also when
they are kicked out. אין טמאי מת משתלחים אין זבים ומצורעים משתלחים.
Ein tmei meit mishtalkhin ein zavim umtzora'im mishtalkhin. Now, that doesn't mean
it's מותר. muttar. Again, presumably there is still some איסור, issur, איסור
עשה, issur asei, איסור לאו, issur lav, it's not חייב chayav כרת,
karet, because of this, it's a time when even to other, when
טמא tamei people can enter into the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. בעי
רבי יוסף: Ba'ei Rabbi Yosef: now רבי יוסף Rabbi Yosef said דחקו
טמאי מתים ונכנסו להיכל בפסח הבא בטומאה מהו? dacheku tmei meitim venikhnasu
laheikhal bePesach habah betumah mahu? Let's say you have a guy who's
a טמא מת tamei meit and he goes further than he's allowed.
He doesn't just go into the עזרה, azarah, he goes all the
way into the היכל. heikhal. Normally ישראל Yisrael are never allowed in
the היכל. heikhal. Okay, and he goes and he's טמא. tamei. What's
the story? Would he be
חייב? chayav? Okay, מדישתרי טומאת עזרה אישתרי נמי טומאת היכל? mid'ishtaray tumat
azarah ishtaray nami tumat heikhal? Would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say look,
once he's allowing, you know, not allowing but not being מחייב mechayav
people for going into the עזרה, azarah, maybe the same is true
into the היכל? heikhal? או דלמא מה דאישתרי אישתרי מה דלא אישתרי
לא אישתרי. Od dilma, ma d'ishtaray ishtaray, ma d'lo ishtaray lo ishtaray.
No, it's only this particular place, the עזרה, azarah, not the היכל.
heikhal.
So it is true, once the עזרה azarah was allowed for טמאי
מתים, tmei meitim, even if you're זב zav or מצורע metzora we
can't be מחייב mechayav you. But that's the עזרה, azarah, that's not
the היכל. heikhal. היכל Heikhal is different.
אמר רבא: Amar Rava: yeah, that's the second
business.
אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק says וישלחו
מן המחנה vishalkhu min hamachaneh אפילו מקצת מחנה. afilu miktzat machaneh. No,
even from part of the camp, היכל heikhal is a separate place,
it's מן המחנה, min hamachaneh, it's not the same as the עזרה
azarah and that remains off-limits. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, so that would
say it's אסור assur and you're חייב. chayav. But some say the
opposite. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אמר קרא amar kra וישלחו מן המחנה
vishalkhu min hamachaneh ומחוץ למחנה תשלחום, umikhutz lamachaneh tishalkhum, כל היכא דקרינן
ביה kol heikha d'karinan beh ומחוץ למחנה תשלחום, umikhutz lamachaneh tishalkhum, same
idea, anytime then anybody has to leave the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
then קרינן ביה karinan beh וישלחו מן המחנה, vishalkhu min hamachaneh, you
also have to leave the מן המחנה, min hamachaneh, even the partial,
even the היכל. heikhal. But here since again טמא tamei people are
allowed in the עזרה, azarah, they would not transgress or they would
not be חייב chayav if they even went so far to go
into the היכל. heikhal.