Okay
good morning, it's today is דף י"ז Daf Yud Zayin 17. We're
starting from ט"ז עמוד ב' Tes Zayin Amud Beis towards the bottom,
fourth line from the bottom, תא שמע. Tashma.
And what are we trying to establish? So we're dealing with this
is the end of dealing with the opinion of רב Rav interpreting
יוסי בן יועזר. Yosi ben Yoezer.
And what was רב's Rav interpretation of
יוסי בן יועזר? Yosi ben Yoezer? That there is no טומאת משקין,
Tumath Mashkin, about liquids that are טמא. Tamei. And רב's Rav opinion
was that this is a דאורייתא, D'Oraisa, there's no טומאה Tumah for
משקין. Mashkin. Before we start this last proof, let's look at the
פסוק Pasuk in חגי. Haggai.
חגי Haggai is talking to the כהנים Kohanim post-exile,
and he's kind of quizzing them as a parable, he's quizzing them
on טומאה
וטהרה.
Tumah
and Tahara. כה אמר ה' צבאות, Ko amar Hashem Tzeva'os, so says
God, שאל נא את הכהנים תורה לאמר, Sha'al na es ha-Kohanim Torah
leimor, ask the כהנים Kohanim a שאלה, Shaila, ask them the הלכה.
Halacha. הן ישא איש בשר קודש בכנף בגדו, Hein yisa ish b'sar
kodesh bichnaf bigdo, I'm going to translate this literally, the גמרא Gemara
will interpret it a little bit differently. If a person carries holy
meat in the corner of his garment, ונגע בכנפו אל
הלחם ואל הנזיד ואל היין ואל השמן ואל כל מאכל, v'naga bichnafo
el ha-lechem v'el ha-nazid v'el ha-yayin v'el ha-shemen v'el kol ma'achal, and
he touches the corner of his garment to bread, to meat, stew,
to wine or oil or anything that you could eat, does it
become holy? Now it could be that holy here means טמא, Tamei,
as the גמרא Gemara will interpret it because as we'll see in
the follow-on, that's that this is a parable for the טומאה Tumah
of the people.
ויענו הכהנים ויאמרו לא, V'ya'anu ha-Kohanim v'yomru lo, and the כהנים Kohanim
said no, this is not a problem. ויאמר חגי, V'yomar Haggai, so
חגי Haggai said to them, אם יגע טמא נפש בכל אלה,
Im yiga t'mei nefesh
b'chol eileh, what if someone is himself טמא Tamei by having touched
a dead body? If he touches any of these things, היטמא, ha-yitma,
do they become טמא? Tamei? ויענו הכהנים ויאמרו יטמא, V'ya'anu ha-Kohanim v'yomru
yitma, and they said yes, it does become טמא. Tamei. ויען חגי
ויאמר, V'yaan Haggai v'yomar, so חגי Haggai said to them, כן העם
הזה וכן הגוי הזה לפני נאם ה', Ken ha-am ha-zeh v'chen ha-goy
ha-zeh lefanai neum Hashem, so too is this nation, וכן כל מעשה
ידיהם, v'chen kol ma'aseh yedeihem, and so is everything that they do,
ואשר יקריבו שם טמא הוא, v'asher yakrivu sham tamei hu, everything that
they bring on the מזבח, Mizbeach, everything they bring is טמא. Tamei.
So it seems like you know what's apparently going on here is
that חגי Haggai is trying to elicit from them a case in
which something is טמא Tamei because he wants to extend the metaphor
to the people themselves. But as is its way, the גמרא Gemara
has a little bit different take on it. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. תא שמע, Tashma, the גמרא Gemara quotes the
first פסוק, Pasuk, הן ישא איש בשר קודש בכנף בגדו.
Hein yisa ish b'sar kodesh
bichnaf bigdo. Now this is the way, the גמרא Gemara doesn't say
this explicitly, but if you look at רש"י Rashi and it's the
only way to understand the גמרא Gemara I think, this is how
the גמרא Gemara interprets this פסוק. Pasuk. If a person carrying בשר
קודש, b'sar kodesh, first of all definitely talking about טומאה, Tumah, בכנף
בגדו, bichnaf bigdo,
in the corner of his garment. Now
the גמרא Gemara is assuming that there is some source of טומאה
Tumah in his garment, and the source of טומאה Tumah is a
שרץ. Sheretz. He's carrying a שרץ Sheretz in his garment and the
שרץ, Sheretz,
a dead one, yes, thank you. ונגע בכנפו אל הלחם, v'naga bichnafo
el ha-lechem, and the שרץ Sheretz in the corner of his garment
touches bread, and bread touches נזיד, nazid, the stew, and the stew
touches wine, and the wine touches oil. So there's a chain. It's
not that he's going around touching everything, but it's a chain of
things that from the שרץ Sheretz to the bread, to the stew,
to the wine, to the oil. ואל כל מאכל, v'el kol ma'achal,
now oddly ואל כל מאכל v'el kol ma'achal is not, the גמרא
Gemara never picks up on as a fifth state in the chain,
it just totally ignores that, which is incomprehensible.
Yeah, the שרץ Sheretz is in the garment which is
touching,
yeah, you would think, but that is definitely not the way the
גמרא Gemara
is going here, even though that seems to be clearly the, yes
it does, it does say that, it says a lot of things
which the גמרא Gemara is reinterpreting, so I don't even know where
to begin, you know. So you're right, but let's just try to
figure out how this thing works, and let's try to figure out
what the גמרא Gemara is trying to derive. from all this. That's
better.
So anyway, so ויעמדו הכהנים, Vaya'amdu ha-Kohanim, ויאמרו לו. Vaya'amru lo. The
כהנים Kohanim says no, this is not a problem. This is not
טמא. tamei. ואמר רב, Ve'amar Rav,
אשתבש כהני. ishtabesh kahanei. And רב Rav says the כהנים Kohanim made
a mistake, that really it is טמא, tamei, right? Now we've been
saying that רב Rav holds that liquids can't become טמא, tamei, right?
So what's up with that? So how can רב Rav say that
the כהנים Kohanim were wrong? גמרא Gemara says, מדי הוא טעמא אלא
לרב, midei hu ta'ama ella leRav, this is first of all, is
only a question according to רב. Rav. רב, Rav, משקה בית מטבחיא
טמא. mashkeh beit mitbechaya tamei. What רב Rav was talking about was
only
the slaughterhouse liquids, and he was talking about יוסי בן יועזר's Yose
ben Yoezer testimony, but משקה במדבחיא מטמא. mashkeh bemadbechaya metamei. But here
we're talking about
liquids that see the, he's changing the word now to מדבחיא, madbechaya,
which is מזבח, mizbe'ach, the דלת dalet and the זין zayin are
interchangeable.
So liquids
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, those become טמא. tamei. What are liquids that
go on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Other than, well obviously there's blood, and
there's water, right, which is on סוכות, Sukkot, you have the ניסוך
המים, nisuch hamayim, so those things are also covered by the בית
מטבחיא, beit mitbechaya, the slaughterhouse, but also on the מזבח mizbe'ach there
are two other liquids that you encounter: wine and oil, right? Wine
is the נסך, nesach, the wine offering that goes with most קרבנות,
korbanot, and oil mixed in with a מנחה, mincha, that goes on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So when the פסוק pasuk in חגי Haggai refers
to יין ושמן, yayin veshemen, we're now not talking anymore about בית
מטבחיא, beit mitbechaya, the slaughterhouse, we're talking about בית מדבחיא, beit madbechaya,
י"ז yud-zayin at the top, י"ז עמוד א', yud-zayin amud aleph, third
line.
משקה בית מדבחיא מטמא. mashkeh beit madbechaya metamei. So רב Rav does,
this is not difficult according to רב, Rav, because we're not talking
about blood, we're talking about, we're not talking about יוסי בן יועזר's
Yose ben Yoezer statement which had to do with only the blood
of the slaughterhouse, now we're talking about oil and wine and it's
perfectly non-contradictory for רב Rav to say that they can become
טמא. tamei. גופא. Gufa. רב אמר אשתבש כהני. Rav amar ishtabesh kahanei.
So we just said that רב Rav said the כהנים Kohanim made
a mistake when they said that
the oil and the wine were טהור tahor in that case. ושמואל
אמר לא אשתבש כהני. U-Shmuel amar lo ishtabesh kahanei. שמואל Shmuel says
no, they were right, it is טהור. tahor. רב אמר אשתבש כהני,
Rav amar ishtabesh kahanei, רביעי בקודש בעו מינייהו. revii bakodesh ba'u mineihu.
He says,
רב Rav said they made a mistake
because he's asking them a case of רביעי, revii, because as I
said, it's a chain, right? So you have the שרץ, sheretz, touches
the bread, that's
a ראשון, rishon, touches the stew, that's a שני, sheni, which touches
the wine, which is a שלישי, shelishi, which touches the oil, that's
a רביעי. revii. So can there be any further טומאה? tumah? No,
right? Once you have a רביעי לטומאה, revii letumah, it can't מטמא
metamei anything else.
So they were asking him about a רביעי, revii, ואמרו ליה
טהור.
va'amru lei
tahor. Actually, not dealing with touching anything else, but רב's Rav position
then is that, and the כהנים's Kohanim position was
that you don't have a רביעי לטומאה revii letumah from a שרץ.
sheretz. ואמרו ליה טהור. Va'amru lei tahor. ושמואל אמר... U-Shmuel amar...
and that's why they were mistaken, because really you can have a
רביעי לטומאה. revii letumah. Of course, right. Yeah, right, in קדשים. kodshim.
And
really you can have a רביעי לטומאה, revii letumah, so when the
כהנים Kohanim said טהור, tahor, that's why רב Rav said they were
mistaken, right? ושמואל אמר לא אשתבש כהני. U-Shmuel amar lo ishtabesh kahanei.
שמואל Shmuel says no, they didn't make a mistake, because שמואל Shmuel
is going to interpret the question a little bit differently.
חמישי בקודש בעו מינייהו, Chamishi bakodesh ba'u mineihu, because they were asking
about a fifth level. How do you get to a חמישי chamishi
level?
The גמרא Gemara will come to that in a second. ואמרו ליה
טהור. Va'amru lei tahor. So they said טהור tahor and they were
correct because there is no חמישי. chamishi. So in other words, the
argument between רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel was what was חגי's Haggai
question? Was it a רביעי לטומאה, revii letumah, in which case the
correct answer is טמא, tamei, but the כהנים Kohanim said טהור tahor
as a mistake? Or was it חגי's Haggai question about a חמישי
לטומאה chamishi letumah and the כהנים Kohanim said טהור tahor and according
to שמואל Shmuel they were right if it's a חמישי chamishi because
there is no חמישי לטומאה. chamishi letumah.
And now let's see how they both interpret the case.
בשלמא לרב היינו דכתיב ארבעה. Bishlama leRav hainu deksiv arba'ah. So I
understand it seems like it fits the פסוק pasuk to say that
there were four levels of טומאה tumah we're talking about here: לחם,
lechem, נזיד, nezid, יין, yayin, ושמן. shemen. אלא לשמואל חמישה מנלן? Ella
leShmuel chamisha menaslan? Where's the fifth level according to שמואל? Shmuel? So
you know, a number of things. I mean, I would have said,
what's מכל מאכל mikol ma'achal which it says afterwards? But that's not
where the גמרא Gemara goes. ושמואל מנלן? U-leShmuel menaslan? Exactly touch with
the or through whatever, but by using the word בכנפו be-chnafo instead
of כנפו knafo במה שנגע בכנפו. be-mah she-naga be-chnafo. The bread was
not touched by the שרץ sheretz itself. The bread was touched by
something else that touched the שרץ, sheretz, which isn't mentioned in the
פסוק. pasuk. That's how you get the question really is about חמישי
לטומאה chamishi le-tumah when the כהנים kohanim said טהור, tahor, they were
correct according to שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, so it's a little difficult because...
okay. So כנף kanaf really means the corner of his garment, but
the גמרא Gemara has interpreted it as the טמא tamei thing in
the corner of his garment, the שרץ sheretz itself. Okay, so that's
step one that you have to take. ונגע בכנפו ve-naga be-chnafo the
גמרא Gemara interprets as the שרץ sheretz which was in the corner
of his garment touched the לחם, lechem, the bread. But it doesn't
work, no. Agreed. Sorry, can't help you there. Okay, yeah, yeah. Okay,
תא שמע. ta shema. So let's continue to what are we trying
to prove here? Right. Okay, so let's see if we can analyze
whether רב Rav is correct or not about this פסוק pasuk in
חגי. Chaggai. ויאמר חגי vayomer Chaggai אם יטמא. im yitma. This is
the continuation I read before. אם יגע טמא נפש בכל אלה היטמא?
im yiga tamei nefesh be-chol eleh hayitma? So חגי Chaggai said okay
what if a טמא tamei person, a person who has contacted a
dead body touches any of these things, then is it טמא? tamei?
ויענו הכהנים ויאמרו יטמא. vaya'anu ha-kohanim vayomru yitma. And the כהנים kohanim
said yes in that case it's טמא. tamei. בשלמא לשמואל bishlama lishmuel
מדלא הוו משתבשי התם נמי לא משתבשי. midela havo mishtabshi hatam nami
lo mishtabshi. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel says that the כהנים kohanim know
what they're talking about, so they're correct here as well. So what's
the case here? I mean we have to be talking about a
רביעי לטומאה revi'i le-tumah in this case when the טמא נפש tamei
nefesh himself touches the לחם. lechem. So the טמא נפש tamei nefesh
is an אב הטומאה, av ha-tumah, the לחם lechem is a ראשון
rishon etc. and then you get to the oil which is a
רביעי revi'i in the second question. In the second question of חגי,
Chaggai, we're talking about a רביעי revi'i and so the כהנים kohanim
are once again correct that there is such a thing as a
רביעי לטומאה revi'i le-tumah as טמא. tamei. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel is
consistent or at least שמואל's Shmuel view of the כהנים kohanim are
consistent. They're right. They're right in the first case that חמישי לטומאה
chamishi le-tumah is טהור tahor and they're right in the second case
that a רביעי לטומאה revi'i le-tumah is טמא. tamei. Yes? Okay. אלא
לרב מאי שנא הכא דאישתבוש ומאי שנא התם דלא אישתבוש? ella lerav
mai shena hacha de-ishtabush u-mai shena hatam de-la ishtabush? Right, right, which
is why everyone agrees there's no such thing as a חמישי. chamishi.
Are we talking about a חמישי chamishi or not? Yes, right. אלא
לרב מאי שנא הכא דאישתבוש ומאי שנא התם דלא אישתבוש? ella lerav
mai shena hacha de-ishtabush u-mai shena hatam de-la ishtabush? According to רב,
Rav, why are they... if they are wrong in one case, why
are they right in the other case? אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה בקיאין הן בטומאת מת ואין בקיאין בטומאת שרץ. amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha bki'in hen be-tum'at met ve-ein bki'in be-tum'at
sheretz. Because they know the rules of טומאה tumah from a dead
person, but they don't know so well the rules from a שרץ.
sheretz. Okay, you know that's one difference between the two cases. רבינא
אמר התם רביעי הכא שלישי. Ravina amar hatam revi'i hacha shlishi.
רבינא Ravina says no, what we're talking about is not
the difference between according
to רב Rav not
the difference between a רביעי לטומאה revi'i le-tumah and a חמישי chamishi
but the difference between a רביעי לטומאה revi'i le-tumah and a שלישי
לטומאה. shlishi le-tumah. So again since the case is different because you
go from אב av to ראשון rishon שני sheni שלישי. shlishi. If
you're only up to שלישי shlishi then so they knew the rules
of שלישי לטומאה, shlishi le-tumah, they didn't know the rules of רביעי
לטומאה. revi'i le-tumah. That's why there can be a difference, why they're
mistaken in one case and not and correct in the other case.
Okay, it's a little strange but whatever. תא שמע. ta shema. Let's
analyze it further see if we can bring another... So the פסוק
posuk continues, ויען חגי ויאמר, Vaya'an Chagai vayomar, so חגי Chagai said
to them, כן העם הזה וכן הגוי הזה לפני נאם ה׳. ken
ha'am hazeh v'chen hagoy hazeh l'fanai ne'um Hashem. So too is this
nation טמא. tamei. Okay. בשלמא לרב היינו דכתיב טמא. Bishlama l'Rav haynu
de-chtiv tamei. Okay, so according to רב Rav that's why they answered,
they answered טמא, tamei, so he responds טמא tamei that the people
are טמא. tamei. אלא לשמואל אמאי טמא? Ela l'Shmuel amai tamei? According
to שמואל Shmuel in the first case, the case that he gave
them was טהור, tahor, so why is he saying so too is
the people טמא? tamei? It doesn't make sense. So the גמרא Gemara
answers no, he's not making a statement. אתמוהי קא מתמה. Atmuhei ka
matma. He's actually as a question mark here. He's asking, oh, so
are these people טמא? tamei? In other words, he's saying something positive
about the people. He's saying, oh, you said the case I gave
you you said טהור, tahor, so are the people טמא? tamei? Rhetorical
question, of course not, they're also טהור, tahor, they're also reliable, good
people or whatever. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't like this, and certainly,
I mean, the whole point of the נביאים אחרונים Nevi'im Acharonim is
to tell the people not how great they're doing but how lousy
they're doing. והא וכן כל מעשה ידיהם כתיב, V'ha v'chen kol ma'aseh
yedeihem ktiv, and doesn't it say and so too everything that they're
doing? I mean the context implies that חגי Chagai is trying to
make an analogy to the people misbehaving and being טמא tamei analogously,
so how can you say that, how can you reinterpret that to
be a compliment? אמר זוטרא ואיתימא רב אשי מתוך שקלקלו את מעשיהם
מעלה עליהם הכתוב כאילו הקריבו בטומאה. Amar Zutra v'itema Rav Ashi mitoch
she-kilkelu et ma'aseihem ma'aleh aleihem hakatuv k'ilu hikrivu b'tumah. This is more
like the נביאים אחרונים Nevi'im Acharonim that we are familiar with. Because
the people are not behaving correctly, what חגי Chagai is saying is
וכן כל מעשה ידיהם, v'chen kol ma'aseh yedeihem, however their deeds are
so bad that it's as if they are טמא. tamei. So in
other words, yes the people are טהור, tahor, but they're misbehaving in
such a way that it's as if they're טמא. tamei. So in
other words, it's not that חגי Chagai is asking the question, it's
that he is calling them טמא tamei metaphorically? Well, yeah, it's both
actually, it's like what we're kind of twisting this around to say
that maybe חגי Chagai is indeed asking that rhetorical question that oh,
so maybe the people are really טהור, tahor, but look at what
they're doing, they're doing such nasty things that we have to say
they're as if they're טמא. tamei. But according to רש״י Rashi it's
way interesting. Which רש״י? Rashi? רש״י Rashi says לאחר זמן שקלקלו מעשיהם
בבית שני בשאר עבירות. l'achar zman she-kilkelu ma'aseihem b'Bayit Sheni b'sha'ar aveirot.
One second, which רש״י? Rashi? שקלקלו מעשיהם בבית שני בשאר עבירות. she-kilkelu
ma'aseihem b'Bayit Sheni b'sha'ar aveirot. Oh okay, so he's putting the future,
okay, yeah, I see, okay, okay, how could they be reproached for
something that they haven't done yet? Interesting. Well, משה Moshe reproves the
people by saying that I know what you're going to do after
I die. Oh, that's really a stretch. What's the point of this
whole tangent? Well, we encountered before you came in we encountered this
passage in חגי Chagai and in an attempt to kind of unravel
the details of טומאה וטהרה Tumah v'Taharah again. In the גמרא? Gemara?
Yes, so now the גמרא Gemara is kind of going off on
a tangent trying to understand what's going on in this passage. I
understand, but this little tangent is about the people. Is that the
people, yeah, what does that do with the discussion between רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel as to whether, oh, because the whole passage is
חגי Chagai says he asks the כהנים Kohanim a couple questions and
he says well, here's a case, what would you say, טמא tamei
or טהור? tahor? And they answer correctly or incorrectly, and once he
gets the answer he says well, so too are the people, the
people are like
this too, they're טמא tamei also.
So it almost has to be back up to the point that
he's asking a question
that perforce must elicit the answer טמא.
tamei. Yeah, yeah, that's right.
Right.
Maybe
that's why he kept asking until he got the answer he wanted.
Because he wants to say so too the people, exactly, yeah, no,
you're messing up my
metaphor.
Okay. גופא רב תני משקי בית מטבחיא
ולוי תני משקי בי
מטבחיא. Gufa Rav tanei mashkei beit mitbachaya v'Levi tanei
mashkei be
mitbachaya. So we had this
name before, יוסי בן יועזר, Yosei ben Yoezer, who said that the
liquids in the בית מטבחיא beit mitbachaya in a certain place are
טהור מדאורייתא, tahor mi-d'oraisa, yeah, מדאורייתא mi-d'oraisa they're טהור. tahor. So רב
Rav says what place is that, בית מטבחיא, beit mitbachaya, the slaughterhouse,
and לוי Levi says בי מטבחיא, be mitbachaya, the מזבח, mizbe'ach, which
is more inclusive because it also includes wine and oil, there are
two other liquids that are involved with the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Levi, so
let's look at Levi's opinion about the that it's the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
הניחא אי סבירא ליה כשמואל, Hanicha isvira lei kishmuel, Levi is okay
if we say that he agrees with Shmuel, דאמר דחן מלטמא טומאת
אחרים, de'amar dachun miletamei tumas acheirim, that he interpreted Yossi ben Yoezer
when he said it's טהור, tahor, Shmuel says that means טהור tahor
from it can't make something else טמא, tamei, אבל טומאת עצמן יש
להם, aval tumas atzman yesh lahem, but the liquids themselves can become
טמא. tamei. And that's Shmuel's interpretation of Yossi ben Yoezer. אשכחת לה,
ashkachas la, so this works out, דנגעי כולהו ברישא, denagei kuleihu berisha,
if all of these liquids touched a ראשון לטומאה. rishon letuma. So
then they become טמא, tamei, but they can't be מטמא metamei other
things. אלא אי סבר לה כרב, ela i savar la kerav, דאמר
דחן ממש, de'amar dachun mamash, but if he interprets Yossi ben Yoezer
in accordance with Rav that says דחן ממש, dachun mamash, that the
liquids themselves are טהור, tahor, היכי אשכחת לה, heichi ashkachat la, how
can this be that these liquids don't contract טומאה? tuma? על כרחך
כשמואל סבירא ליה, al karchach kishmuel sevira lei, so he must hold
in that like Shmuel that the liquids can become טמא tamei themselves
but not be מטמא metamei other things. ולשמואל, uleshmuel, and according to
Shmuel, it's a little confusing because we have two positions of Shmuel
we're talking about here. But according to Shmuel הניחא אי סבר לה
כרב, hanicha i savar la kerav, דתני משקה בית מטבחיא. detani mashkei
beis mitbachaya. Now looking at from Shmuel's perspective, Shmuel who said that
the liquid itself can become טמא tamei but can't be מטמא metamei
other things, הניחא אי סבר לה כרב. hanicha i savar la kerav.
So that's okay if he interprets the statement about בית מטבחיא beis
mitbachaya to be the slaughterhouse. אבל משקה בית מטבחיא אחריני נמי מטמו,
aval mashkei beis mitbachaya acharinei nami mitamu, but if we're talking about
the liquids of the מזבח mizbe'ach like wine and oil, they can
also be מטמא metamei other things. Wait a second. Yeah, wine and
oil can according to Shmuel and even according to Shmuel who interprets
Yossi ben Yoezer, so it comes out that oil and wine are
מטמא metamei other things. So Gemara says, רביעי הוא דלא עביד חמישי.
revi'i hu delo avid chamishi. When we say that they can't be
מטמא metamei other things, we must be talking about where it's a
case of רביעי לטומאה, revi'i letuma, so then it can't be מטמא
metamei other things because there is no fifth level. השלישי עביד רביעי,
hashlishi avid revi'i, but if we're talking about a שלישי לטומאה, shlishi
letuma, it can make another level of טומאה. tuma. So what's the
problem? I skipped a line. I'm sorry. השלישי עביד רביעי. hashlishi avid
revi'i. אלא אי סבר לה כלוי, ela i savar la kelevi, right,
but if Shmuel holds like Levi, דתני משקה בית מטבחיא, detani mashkei
beis mitbachaya, but if we're talking about the wine and the oil,
מאי איריא רביעי דלא עביד חמישי? mai irya revi'i delo avid chamishi?
Why are you resorting to saying that it's a רביעי לטומאה revi'i
letuma and can't make a חמישי? chamishi? אפילו שני ושלישי נמי לא
עבדי. afilu sheini veshlishi nami lo avdei. Even it can't even make
another level of טומאה tuma because it's a מזבח mizbe'ach item. So
going back to the, so just a second, so regarding the כהנים,
kohanim, is it the difference that it's talking about additional liquids or
is it the difference the environment that it's the בית מטבחיא beis
mitbachaya as opposed to the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Is it that more liquids
are being added because you're talking about the מזבח mizbe'ach or is
it that something about the משקין mashkin of the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Okay,
I missed something, I missed something, I missed something. The Shmuel, the
opinion of Shmuel we're discussing is the opinion about whether the כהנים
kohanim made a mistake. Okay, so if we're talking about, so why
do you have to resort to saying it was a רביעי revi'i
making חמישי chamishi and that's why it couldn't make other things טמא?
tamei? Since we're talking about wine and oil, Shmuel should have said
that it doesn't, you don't have to go to the fourth and
fifth level because if Shmuel is saying that the בית מטבחיא, beis
mitbachaya, that the מזבח mizbe'ach liquids can't make other things טמא, tamei,
that means even a שני ושלישי לטומאה sheini veshlishi letuma can't make
other things טמא tamei if they are מזבח mizbe'ach liquids. So why
do you have to resort to the רביעי חמישי Revii Chamishi? level
to explain it? אלא Elah I lost my place. Do we know
why that is, by the way, or that's just a working assumption?
A working assumption and the גמרא Gemara will ask that question, 'Where
does this come from?' It might be הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai as we will see. In other words, once you're in the
מזבח Mizbeach environment, it's a different transfer of טומאה Tuma rule than
if you're in the slaughterhouse environment. Right. And על כרחך כרב סבירא
ליה, Al Korchacha K'Rav Sviralei, so we have to say that לוי,
Levi, לוי Levi who says בי מטבחיא Bei Mitbachaya must hold like
רב Rav that the כהנים Kohanim made a mistake. That really the
answer should have been טמא Tamei in the case of the רביעי
Revii חמישי? Chamishi Yeah. That they didn't understand he was asking about
חמישי. Chamishi. They didn't understand that he was asking about חמישי, Chamishi,
that's why they made the mistake, according to רב, Rav, yeah. Okay.
Going further. תני כוותיה דרב תני כוותיה דלוי. Tani Kevati DeRav Tani
Kevati DeLevi. So we have in dealing with what רבי יוסי בן
יועזר... Rabbi Yosi Ben Yoezer... Sorry, you said he didn't understand they
were talking about חמישי לטומאה Chamishi Letuma or that he didn't understand
they were talking about liquids at the מזבח Mizbeach as opposed to
liquids in the slaughterhouse? That's what I don't understand, that's right. You
have... okay, what the גמרא Gemara concludes, yeah, yeah, what the גמרא
Gemara concludes is that רב's Rav opinion is בי מטבחיא, Bei Mitbachaya,
that we're only exempting liquids that are basically in the from the
slaughterhouse, i.e., blood and water. We're not exempting wine and oil. Therefore,
that's why we're interpreting the פסוק Pasuk in חגי, Chaggai, which deals
with wine and oil, as this chain of רביעי Revii and חמישי,
Chamishi, and that's why they made a mistake. Okay? If we had
if we understood יוסי בן יועזר Yosi Ben Yoezer as saying that
even wine and oil cannot become טמא Tamei themselves, then we wouldn't
have had the same interpretation of the verse in חגי, Chaggai, right?
Does that answer your question? Because it's all part of the same
question: was wine and oil two different categories? Well, a different category
from blood and water. At least... what do you mean? Yeah. Yeah.
Okay, so now we're going to try and figure out who's right
regarding the statement of יוסי בן יועזר, Yosi Ben Yoezer, which liquids
are exempt from טומאה? Tuma? Is it מזבח Mizbeach or מטבח, Mitbach,
right? מטבחיא Mitbachaya or מדבחיא? Midbachaya? Is it slaughterhouse liquids, blood and
water, or is it also מזבח Mizbeach liquids, which also includes oil
and wine? And that's the מחלוקת Machlokes of רב Rav and לוי.
Levi. תני כוותיה דרב תני כוותיה דלוי. Tani Kevati DeRav Tani Kevati
DeLevi. We have a ברייתא Braisa supporting each one. תני כוותיה דלוי,
Tani Kevati DeLevi, we have support for לוי Levi that says the
מזבח Mizbeach and it includes wine and oil. הדם והיין והשמן והמים.
Hadom VeHayayin VeHaShemen VeHamayim. These four liquids: blood, wine, oil, and water.
משקה בי מטבחיא, Mashke Bei Mitbachaya, which are the מזבח Mizbeach liquids,
שנטמאו בפנים She-nitmu bifnim that became טמא Tamei inside the מקדש. Mikdash.
So we see right away where the גמרא Gemara is going with
this, right? That clearly these do become טמא. Tamei. והוציאן לחוץ, VeHotzi-an
Lachutz, and then you took them outside, טהורין, Tehorin, then they are
then they are okay, then they are טהור. Tahor. Wait, so they're
טמא Tamei and they just walk out of the temple and they're
טהור? Tahor? Right. Mistakenly, I mean you're not supposed to do that.
But I don't follow that. They can't they can't be מטמא Metamei
other things. Their טומאה Tuma is restricted to inside the מקדש. Mikdash.
So you fix it by just taking them outside? Yeah, but you're
not supposed to take them outside. Or maybe you do fix it.
Good question. Maybe so. I mean what are you supposed to do
with them when they become טמא? Tamei? I assume you're supposed to
burn them. But the question is not what you do with them,
but what is their status regarding contacting other things. So this ברייתא
Braisa is saying that if they since when they became טמא, Tamei,
I guess the way I understand it is since when they became
טמא Tamei it was in the מקדש Mikdash where they were מזבח
Mizbeach items and so their kind of טומאה Tuma was not מטמא
Metamei other things. When you take them outside, they still aren't מטמא
Metamei other things. But they themselves according to רב Rav are טמא,
Tamei, yes? Yes, it goes back to חגי. Chaggai. רש"י Rashi says...
Yeah, רש"י Rashi says טהורין מלטמא אחרים. Tehorin militamei acherim. הם עצמם
ודאי טמאים. Heim Atzmam Vadai Tme'in. Yes, so they remain טמא. Tamei.
Right, so we're interpreting the ברייתא Braisa when it says טהורין, Tehorin,
it doesn't mean that they themselves. That's also a stretch. Yeah, it's
a long stretch. Well, but we've seen that throughout this discussion that
interpreting טהור tahor in some cases as being טמא tamei itself but
not being מטמא metamei something else. Now the ברייתא Braisa continues, נטמאו
בחוץ והכניסן בפנים, nitme'u bachutz vehichnisan bifnim, what if something became טמא
tamei outside the מקדש Mikdash and then you brought it inside? טמאים,
tmei'im, then they are מטמא metamei other things. So that, so this
does show that this supports the idea that יוסי בן יועזר Yosei
ben Yoezer was talking about liquids, מזבח mizbeach liquids becoming טמא, tamei,
because it says specifically the four liquids of the מזבח mizbeach and
it referred to them becoming טמא. tamei. הגמרא The Gemara says, איני,
eini, is that so? והא אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי משקי בית
מדבחיא לא אמרו דכן אלא במקומן. ve-ha amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi
mashkei beis midbachaya lo amru dochan ela bimcoman. Didn't רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi say, okay, so when we said that
the מזבח mizbeach liquids are טהור, tahor, that's only if they're in
their original place. מאי לאו, mai lav, what does that mean in
their place? מאי לאו למעוטי נטמאו בפנים והוציאן לחוץ, mai lav le-ma'utei
nitme'u bifnim ve-hotzian lachutz, doesn't that mean when they stay in their
original place in the מקדש? Mikdash? But if they became טמא tamei
inside and you took them outside, then doesn't that take them out
of the דכן dochan category, out of the טהור tahor category? הגמרא
The Gemara says, לא למעוטי נטמאו בחוץ והכניסן בפנים, lo le-ma'utei nitme'u
bachutz vehichnisan bifnim, maybe it's excluding the other way around, the second
case of the ברייתא, Braisa, when they became טמא tamei outside and
left their place outside and came inside, that's when, that's what רבי
יהושע בן לוי Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi was talking about and that's
in accordance with the ברייתא, Braisa, that they're טמאים tmei'im or they
can make other things טמא tamei when they come from outside to
the inside. But הגמרא the Gemara doesn't like that. והא במקומן קאמר,
ve-ha bimcoman ka-amar, in their place, we're talking about קדשים, kodshim, where
is their place? In the מקדש. Mikdash. So, so it doesn't really
seem to, you can't really interpret רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabi Yehoshua
ben Levi that way. הגמרא The Gemara says, הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar,
this is what it means to say. לא אמרו דכן אלא שנטמאו
במקומן. lo amru dochan ela she-nitme'u bimcoman. יוסי בן יועזר, Yosei ben
Yoezer, this is what it meant to say, or רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi meant to say, that he only said
טהור tahor when they become טמא tamei in their original, in their
place. What does that mean? They're טהור tahor only when they're contaminated
in their place. And when רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabi Yehoshua ben
Levi said לא אמרו דכן אלא במקומן, lo amru dochan ela bimcoman,
ah, so he, instead of saying לא אמרו דכן אלא במקומן, lo
amru dochan ela bimcoman, he should have said לא אמרו דכן אלא
שנטמאו במקומן. lo amru dochan ela she-nitme'u bimcoman. Where did the טומאה
tumah take place, so where did the טומאה tumah arise? In their
place, in the מקדש. Mikdash. So we're recasting what רבי יהושע בן
לוי Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi said to fit the ברייתא, Braisa, right?
The ברייתא Braisa said when is something טהור tahor in the sense
that it can't be מטמא metamei something else? When it starts, it
becomes טמא tamei in the מקדש Mikdash and you take it out,
and it has no power to be מטמא metamei something else. And
that's also what רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi said,
so that it jibes with the ברייתא. Braisa. Anyway, this ברייתא, Braisa,
the point of bringing this ברייתא Braisa was as a support to
לוי, Levi, לוי Levi that the, that מזבח mizbeach liquids including wine
and oil can become טמא, tamei, and that's clear from the ברייתא.
Braisa. תניא כוותיה דרב. Tanya kevasei de-Rav. Now we have a ברייתא
Braisa that supports רב, Rav, that says בבית מדבחיא, be-midbachaya, that the
liquids that are exempt from טומאה tumah are the only the blood
and the water of the slaughterhouse. הדם והמים משקי בית מדבחיא שנטמאו,
Ha-dam ve-ha-mayim mashkei beis midbachaya she-nitme'u, blood and water which are the,
I wonder if this is really part of the ברייתא Braisa or
if this is parenthetical, הגמרא the Gemara is inserting, by the way,
yeah, it's a good point, because it's Aramaic. Anyway, so these, the
blood and the water which are the slaughterhouse liquids שנטמאו she-nitme'u that
became טמא, tamei, so right away we see where הגמרא the Gemara
is going with this again, that clearly the ברייתא Braisa indicates which
liquids can become טמא, tamei, שנטמאו דם ומים, she-nitme'u dam u-mayim, so
this is what רב Rav is dealing is interpreting יוסי בן יועזר.
Yosei ben Yoezer. Anyway, שנטמאו בין בכלים בין בקרקע טהורים, she-nitme'u ben
be-keilim ben be-karka tehorim, whether they are in vessels or whether they
are still on the ground, they are טהורים. tehorim. And again, טהור
tahor means, I think טהור tahor here means that they can't be...
many other things. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer בכלים bakelim טמאים
tmei'im בקרקע bakarka טהורים. tehorim. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if they're
in vessels then they are טמא, tameh, if they're still in the
ground they're טהור. tahor. So this ברייתא braita is a support of
רב Rav that the בית מטבחיא beyt mitbachaya the slaughterhouse liquids, blood
and water, which are taken out of the, which cannot become טמא
tameh or can't be מטמא metameh other things depending on how we
read this. Okay. אמר רב פפא. amar Rav Pappa. רב פפא Rav
Pappa has a new point to add about this whole thing. אפילו
מן דאמר טומאת משקין דאורייתא. afillu man de-amar tumat mashkin de-Oraita. Even
if you say that liquids can become טמא tameh מדאורייתא, mi-de-Oraita, משקי
בית מטבחיא הלכתא גמירי לה. mashkei beyt mitbachaya hilchata gmeiri la. So
even in general if liquids can become טמא, tameh, but there's a
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai that blood and water, the, in
the slaughterhouse liquids in the המקדש ha-Mikdash do not become טמא. tameh.
הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai. אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב
נתן לרב פפא. amar lei Rav Huna brei de-Rav Natan le-Rav Pappa.
So רב הונא Rav Huna asked him, אלא הא דאמר רבי אלעזר
אין טומאה למשקין כל עיקר. ela ha de-amar Rabbi Elazar ein tumah
le-mashkin kol ikkar. Didn't רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar say in our משנה
Mishnah we've been dealing with, אין טומאה למשקין כל עיקר? ein tumah
le-mashkin kol ikkar? Liquids, there's no liquid טומאה tumah at all, right?
So you're telling me that only that הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe
mi-Sinai only the blood and the water of the slaughterhouse have no
טומאה, tumah, how can רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar deduce from that that
no liquid can have טומאה? tumah? And the proof that רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar brings is תדע שהרי העיד יוסי בן יועזר איש צרידה
על משקי בית מטבחיא דכן. teda sheharei he-id Yosi ben Yoezer ish
Tsreda al mashkei beyt mitbachaya dachan. His proof was, look, the slaughterhouse
liquids don't have טומאה, tumah, so therefore no liquid can have טומאה.
tumah. ואי הלכתא גמירי לה, ve-i hilchata gmeiri la, if it's all
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai that the slaughterhouse liquids have no
טומאה, tumah, מי גמרינן מינה? mi gamrinan mina? Can you deduce from
that? הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai only applies to itself. It's
not you can't extend it to liquids in general. אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי, amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, בהא רבי שמעון דאמר טומאת
משקין דאורייתא? be-ha Rabbi Shimon de-amar tumat mashkin de-Oraita? Didn't רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon say that liquids can contract טומאה tumah מדאורייתא? mi-de-Oraita? דתניא,
de-tanya, רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אומרים לכלים טהורים ולאוכלין טמאים. Rabbi Yosi
ve-Rabbi Shimon omrim le-kelim tehorim ve-l'ochlin tmei'im. The ברייתא braita said that
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said לכלים טהורים
ולאוכלין טמאים. le-kelim tehorim ve-l'ochlin tmei'im. The liquid, one second, ah, yes,
talking about the same liquids of the slaughterhouse, if they were in
כלים, kelim, if they were in vessels they're טמא, tameh, but if
they're in the ground they're טהור. tahor. ואי הלכתא היא, ve-i hilchata
hi, and if it's הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai, מה לי
בכלים מה לי בקרקע? ma li be-kelim ma li be-karka? What's the
difference if they're in כלים kelim or in the ground? If the
הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai is there's no טומאה tumah for
them, there's no טומאה tumah for them. So that's the second question
to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya.
Yeah, this is a good question on רב פפא Rav Pappa and
it does not resolve it. אמר רב פפא. amar Rav Pappa. רב
פפא Rav Pappa continues, הא דאמרה בקרקע טהורים, ha d'amra be-karka tehorim,
when you said that if they're in the ground they're טהור, tahor,
these liquids, לא שנו אלא מים. lo shanu ela mayim. What liquid
were we talking about? We're talking about water that's still in the
ground because it makes sense because the source of water is in
the ground. אבל דם לא. aval dam lo. But we're not talking
about blood if it's in the ground because blood starts in the
animal, right? ומים נמי. ve-mayim nami. And even water, לא אמרן אלא
דהוי רביעית.
lo amran ela
de-havi revit. So it's not totally that it's because they're in the
ground, it's because
of water being enough to make up a מקוה, mikveh,
not a מקוה, mikveh, sorry.
And that's why it's exempt in the ground.
Yeah, and that's what the גמרא's Gemara about to say. Yeah, ולא
אמרן אלא דהוי רביעית. ve-lo amran ela de-havi revit. And this is
only if the water that's collected in the
ground is at least a רביעית. revit. Why a רביעית? revit?
Because a
רביעית revit דחזי להטביל ביה מחטין וצינורות. de-chazi l'hatbil beih machtin ve-tsinorot.
I didn't know this, but apparently a רביעית revit of water is
enough, I guess מדאורייתא, mi-de-Oraita, to immerse needles and what are these
other things? צינורות tsinorot are called spinning forks, whatever, very small metal
implements. If you want to be מטהר metaher them, you don't need
to take them to a big מקוה, mikveh, you can take if
you have a רביעית revit of water that's good enough in the
ground. This is news on me, but I'll take the גמרא Gemara
at its word. Sorry, lost my place again. אבל לא רביעית טמאין
revias aval lo revias tamein but if it's less than a רביעית
revias of water in the ground then that's that doesn't that doesn't
save it and that. Come on we didn't even get an answer.
Who said yesterday that there's no answers? Yeah. Right. אמר מר. Amar
Mar. In other words instead of instead of an answer there is
a matrix of different ways of thinking about it. Right and we've
tried to kind of iron out all the different permutations of who
aligns with who, but that's as far as we get. Of course
there is an answer right שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch has an answer
probably on this somewhere. No doubt. Well the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch
doesn't deal so much with קדשים Kodshim but the other codifiers רמב״ם
Rambam I'm sure. They can usually figure it out. They usually tell
you. Oh by having the little references on the side. I did
not pay much attention to that I have to admit. All right
אמר מר. Amar Mar. Now we're going back to our to the
original not original but the argument that was on the top of
ט״ז Tes Zayin right where we had those that four way argument
about ספק משקה טמא. safek mashkeh tamei. Where was it from? לכל
טמא. Lakol tamei. Yeah, so when when we were discussing the ברייתא
Braisah about if you have a ספק safek of טומאה tumah for
for liquids, so so far we've been discussing mostly רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir that said that the לתמי אחרים טהור litamei acherim tahor that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said that the liquids themselves are טמא tamei
and the but they can't be מטמא metamei anything. And רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar agreed with him. The next actor in this drama was
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said לכל טמא Lakol
tamei meaning in for all cases of doubt we have to assume
that they're טמא tamei when the liquids come into contact with something
else. למימרא דסבר רבי יהודה טומאת משקין לטמא טומאת כלים דאורייתא. Lemeimra
desavar Rabbi Yehuda tumas mashkin letamei tumas keilim de'Oraisa. Does this mean
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds that liquids tamei liquids coming into
contact with vessels that מדאורייתא mi-de'Oraisa that's טמא? tamei? I mean that
would explain why he says vessel would be טמא דאורייתא. tamei de'Oraisa.
Right right because that would explain why he says if it's a
ספק safek you have to rule strictly that it's טמא. tamei. Usually
the reason for that is because it's דאורייתא de'Oraisa and if you
have a ספק דאורייתא safek de'Oraisa you have to be strict right.
So does that does that mean so so does that mean that
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda holds that liquids can be מטמא כלים metamei
keilim מדאורייתא? mi-de'Oraisa? והתנן Vehatnan but we have a משנה. Mishnah. כל
הכלים שיש להם אחוריים ותוך Kol hakeilim sheyesh lahem achorayim vesoch if
you have something that has an inside and an outside כגון הכרים
kegon hakarim like pillows והכסתות ve-haksasos and cushions והשקין ve-hasakim sacks המרצופין.
ha-martzufin. What's that? המרצופין martzufin are are leather bags thank you. So
it has an inside and outside. נטמא תוכו נטמא גבו. Nitma socho
nitma gavo. If the inside becomes טמא tamei the outside becomes טמא.
tamei. נטמא גבו לא נטמא תוכו Nitma gavo lo nitma socho but
if the outside becomes טמא tamei the inside is still safe. אמר
רבי יהודה Amar Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says our
same רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. במה דברים אמורים שנטמו מחמת משקין. Bamei
devarim amurim shenitmu machmas mashkin. That's only if they became if you
spilled your coffee on your on your cushion and the coffee was
טמא. tamei. אבל נטמו מחמת שרץ Aval nitmu machmas sheretz but if
they directly came into contact with a שרץ sheretz then נטמא תוכו
נטמא גבו נטמא גבו נטמא תוכו. nitma socho nitma gavo nitma gavo
nitma socho. Then it doesn't matter if it touch the inside the
whole thing is טמא tamei if it touch the outside the whole
thing is טמא. tamei. דאי סלקא דעתך טומאת משקין לטמא כלים דאורייתא
De-i salka dachas tumas mashkin letamei keilim de'Oraisa and if it's biblical
that tamei liquids can be מטמא metamei other things מאי לי נטמא
מחמת משקין מאי לי נטמא מחמת שרץ. mai li nitma machmas mashkin
mai li nitma machmas sheretz. So why is there a different rule?
You should treat exactly just like the שרץ. sheretz. Exactly as he
does. Why this leniency of if it only touches the inside then
the outside is is okay? Like what doesn't make sense. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel חזר בו רבי יהודה.
Chazar bo Rabbi Yehuda. רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel
says רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually changed his mind you're right this
is a valid שאלה she'eilah and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda backed off
from saying that the טומאת משקין tumas mashkin is דאורייתא. de'Oraisa. רבינא
אמר. Ravina Amar. רבינא Ravina says לעולם לא הדר Le'olam lo hadar
no we don't have to say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda changed his
mind. So how do you explain the difference between the שרץ sheretz
itself being מטמא metamei the cushion and the liquid being מטמא metamei
the cushion? Somebody said nobody really heard him claiming that they heard
him testify. Yeah I was wondering about that. Even with the possibility
to resolve the contradiction of his own position to surmise that he
must have changed his mind. And then he said nobody really heard,
it's just claiming that they heard him just fine. Yeah, I was
wondering about that. Even the possibility to resolve the contradiction of his
own position to surmise that he must have changed his mind. Yeah,
well, you could go, that's, I was wondering about that. I mean,
it also could be, it could be that the first one said
I heard that he changed his mind, and the other one said
not necessarily, maybe it's not so, you could have explained it this
way, so it's unclear. Yeah. Was רבינא Ravina later? Yeah, רבינא Ravina
is definitely later. He didn't live in the same time. Yeah, no,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is a תנא tanna and these are אמוראים
amoraim who are discussing these things. רבינא Ravina is at the end
of the, yeah. And what about רב יהודה? Rav Yehuda? What about
שמואל, Shmuel, when was שמואל? Shmuel? רב ושמואל? Rav v'Shmuel? Yeah. They
were early, they were year 200. They were the first generation of
אמוראים. amoraim. Oh, so that's interesting. The סתמא stama in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and, that's interesting. So רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, the סתם
גמרא stam Gemara is about the sixth century of the common era.
So that's interesting because רב יהודה Rav Yehuda must have been early
and so it's more likely that he was saying, "I actually heard
that, you know, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the תנא tanna changed his
mind." Like us making a claim that we heard that the מהר"ל
Maharal of Prague in the 1600s changed his mind about a specific
joke he taught me. Right. Rather than his contemporary who would report
it. Well, no, but here's the other way around. It's like, it's
like, you know, it's like the... no, no, it's the other way
around here. I know what John Hancock meant. Yeah, it's the
other way
around here. It's
like the grandson of
somebody
from the מהר"ל Maharal שול shul said, "Oh, the מהר"ל Maharal changed
his mind," and we, 300 years later, saying, "Maybe he didn't change
his mind." Right. But anyway, so how does רבינא Ravina say maybe
he didn't change his mind? הא במשקין, Ha b'mashkin, what's the difference
between the liquids and the שרץ? sheretz? הא במשקין הבאים מחמת ידים
הא במשקין הבאים מחמת שרץ. Ha b'mashkin habayim machmas yadayim, ha b'mashkin
habayim machmas sheretz. Talking about two different kinds of משקין mashkin טומאה.
tumah. You have liquid that becomes טמא מחמת ידים. tamei machmas yadayim.
So that means that you have a presumption that your hands are
טמא tamei unless you've washed them and paid attention not to touch
anything טמא. tamei. But if you're just going about your daily business,
you have to assume that your hands came into contact with something
טמא. tamei. That's certainly a rabbinic level of טומאה. tumah. And so
when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that we can be more lenient
with that, that's the kind of טומאה tumah we're talking about. And
you assumed there was only one kind of liquid. Right, right. You
have two different statements, right, two different things, he's talking about two
different... the other טומאה tumah he's talking about is when you know
that your hands came into contact with a שרץ, sheretz, so then
you know they're טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי
אדתני במה דברים אמורים שניתנו מחמת משקין, i hachi adtani bameh devarim
amurim shenitnu machmas mashkin, so the משנה Mishnah that we quoted, what's
the two cases that the משנה Mishnah referred to? One is became
טמא tamei through liquid, and the other is became טמא tamei through
a שרץ. sheretz. But that's not... if the distinction that it should,
no, the distinction they should have said is ולתני בדידה, v'litnei bidida,
make a finer distinction: במה דברים אמורים במשקין הבאים מחמת ידים, bameh
devarim amurim b'mashkin habayim machmas yadayim, when do I say that the
liquids are you can be lenient with the טומאה tumah of the
liquids? When it's טומאה דרבנן, tumah d'rabbanan, טומאה tumah that came from
your hands. אבל במשקין הבאים מחמת שרץ, Aval b'mashkin habayim machmas sheretz,
but if you have liquid that came into contact with a שרץ
sheretz and you know it's טמא tamei and it's a טומאה דאורייתא,
tumah d'oraisa, נטמא תוכו נטמא גבו נטמא גבו נטמא תוכו, nitma tocho
nitma gabo, nitma gabo nitma tocho, then you would say there that
you have to be strict and everything, the inside, outside, everything is
טמא. tamei. The fact that the משנה Mishnah didn't use that distinction
between the two cases indicates אלמא הא דשני מעיקרא חזר בו רבי
יהודה. alma ha d'shani me'ikara chozar bo Rabbi Yehuda. We actually do
end up saying that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda must have changed his
mind because the משנה Mishnah is against him. It makes sense because
the במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim specifically is asking please clarify
the details so we know exactly what the case is. Right, right,
right. So if you didn't come along and say, exactly. Yeah. Well,
what it meant was this distinction, when it was asking for a
distinction and it didn't say it. Yeah. It makes sense. Yeah. Okay,
I don't want to start the because we're going to just the
next piece goes well into next דף daf and we're almost out
of time. So stop here בבעיא להו, b'iba'ya lehu, yeah. Okay, thank
you. יישר כוח. Shkoyach. Good. Thanks. יישר כוח. Shkoyach. Lost my glasses.
You lost your glasses, it's good you didn't lose your mind. I'm
findable.