Exactly. Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. All right, today's דף daf is
ס"ב. Samech Bet. We picked up on the bottom of
ס"א ע"ב, Samech Aleph Amud Bet, and we are in the middle
of a debate of רבה Rabba and רב חסדא Rav Chisda about
מחשבת אוכלים בזריקה, Machshevet Ochlim BiZrika, which is the משנה Mishna as
we discussed yesterday, speaks about a פסול psul which is unique to
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, which is you're having in mind the right
owners but you're thinking only of those that are not able to
eat. They're ערל, arel, טמא, tamei, they're not physically able to eat.
And that's a פסול psul by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and it
specifically relates to the שחיטה shechita because איש לפי אכלו תכסו על
השה. ish lefi ochlo tachossu al haseh. השחט, Hashchet, the way חז"ל
Chazal understand, and because the eating, א, A, the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach is about the eating and that's why it matters that you
שוחט shocht it for the sake of אוכליו ochlav or certainly not
for the sake of non-אוכליו. ochlav. And ב, B, the eating is
only possible through the act of שחיטה. shechita. So therefore it's unique
to the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and it's unique to the act
of שחיטה, shechita, and it's only when you're thinking of all that
the all the people you're thinking of are invalid. If it's mixed,
it's not a פסול. psul. The debate of רבה Rabba and רב
חסדא Rav Chisda is what if at the moment of שחיטה, shechita,
which is the critical moment, you're thinking not that you're שוחט-ing shochet
it for those invalid people, but you're planning on doing the זריקה
zrika for those invalid people. So on the one hand it's at
the moment of שחיטה, shechita, on the other hand the thought relates
to the act of זריקה. zrika. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
it invalidates and רבה Rabba says it does not invalidate. And we
tried to prove it one way or another from a ברייתא, braisa,
which in the end could not be shown either way. So now
we pick up with אלא אמר רב אשי, Ela Amar Rav Ashi,
the very last line on ס"א ע"ב. Samech Aleph Amud Bet.
Rather, says רב אשי, Rav Ashi, רב חסדא ורבה בהאי קרא קמיפלגי.
Rav Chisda VeRabba BeHai Kra Kamifligi. It's quite fascinating. You know normally
the idea of linking something to a debate of a פסוק pasuk
is normally a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. And here's a later אמורא
Amora saying this debate of אמוראים Amoraim really goes back to how
you interpret the following פסוק: pasuk: ונרצה לו לכפר עליו. Venirtza Lo
LeChapper Alav. So it shall be for him,
find favor for him to atone for him. This is about a
normal bringing of a קרבן korban and the זריקת הדם zrikat hadam
that it is atoned ונרצה לו. venirtza lo. That is where it
finds ריצוי. ritzui. Okay, this is a פסוק pasuk about an עולה,
olah, correct, of an עולה. olah. And it's the very beginning of
ויקרא. Veyikra. And it is for to atone for, you know, an
עולה, olah, exactly the function of an עולה, olah, but the קרבן
korban counts for it atones for the owner. Now what he is
doing, since he's quoting a פסוק pasuk about an עולה, olah, is
he's shifting the focus from קרבן פסח Korban Pesach to a general
issue. And according to the way רש"י Rashi explains it, he what
רב אשי Rav Ashi is claiming is they're not debating what they
seem to be debating about שלא לאוכליו, shelo le'ochlav, which is unique
to a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. What they're actually debating is the
question of שלא למנויו, shelo limnuiav,
that actually you're having in intent a wrong owner, not a somebody
who can't eat, but somebody who is not the owner. And in
that way, it goes to an issue by normal קרבנות. korbanot. ונרצה
לו לכפר עליו, Venirtza Lo LeChapper Alav, it has to be for
the sake of the owner. But if you remember as we said
yesterday, what has to be for the sake of the owner by
a normal קרבן? korban? The זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, because it is
the זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, the throwing of the blood, that achieves
the atonement, ונרצה לו. venirtza lo. That is where it finds ריצוי.
ritzui. Okay, so this is a פסוק pasuk by general קרבנות korbanot
that the זריקת הדם zrikat hadam has to be for the sake
of the owner. And this is their debate. It's about owner, it's
not about אוכליו. ochlav. It's not, you know, this special פסול psul
by קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. One minute, let's see how he frames
it,
because they are
talking about a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So let's see how he
frames it. It's a general obligation that זריקת הדם zrikat hadam has
to be for the sake of the owners, also true by קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. And he's saying their debate in קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach is about this generic
problem of לשם בעליו. leshem ba'alav. It's not about לשם אוכליו. leshem
ochlav. Okay, now let's just one minute, let's see how he frames
it because they are talking about a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So
let's see how he frames it. עליו ולא חברו, Alav Velo Chaveiro,
and from there we learn it has to be for the sake
of the owners, not for a non-owner. Again, that's a general פסול
psul by all קרבנות korbanot by זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. So what's
the debate? The debate here is when you are intending for ערלים,
arelim, right, that's the case. You did the שחיטה shechita for the
sake of ערלים arelim to do the זריקה zrika for
ערלים. arelim. So ערלים arelim are not what we thought until now,
owners who can't eat, they are actually non-owners who can't eat. Okay,
so you think to yourself what do I care? Non-owners are non-owners,
either way it should be invalid. He says, nah, this is the
debate. Non-owners who can't eat might not be as bad as non-owners
who can eat. Because they're not in the פרשה parsha at all.
Let's take a look. עליו, Alav, it has to be for the
owners ולא חברו velo chaveiro and not for somebody else, his colleague.
רבה סבר חברו דומיא דידי. Rabba savar chaveiro dumya didei. רבה Rabba
says the invalidity of thinking of a different person, of a different
owner, is only somebody who is similar to the owner. Meaning in
the, as Michael says in the ישיביש Yeshivish parlance, in the same
פרשה. parsha. Okay, that he's actually in the same
category. the discussion. מהו דבר כפרה אף חבירו דבר כפרה mah hu
de-bar kapparah af chaveiro de-bar kapparah the same way he is somebody
for whom כפרה kapparah is possible, you have to be thinking about
a colleague for whom it's a relevant קרבן. korban. Now so you
can try to imagine
let's say a non-Jew, that's not a problem?
Right, so let's say for example you were thinking about a non-Jew
who's not in the פרשה parsha of the, you know, Jewish פרשה
parsha of קרבנות. korbanot. A non-Jew could bring a קרבן, korban, but
not in like our פרשה parsha of קרבנות, korbanot, right? Or you
could imagine another thing. Let's say you were bringing a חטאת chatat
for a יולדת yoledet and you were thinking about a man, right?
Somebody who really could not is not relevant to this קרבן. korban.
So that's what Rava is saying. If you're not relevant to this
קרבן, korban, thinking about an irrelevant person has no impact. מהו דבר
כפרה אף חבירו דבר כפרה mah hu de-bar kapparah af chaveiro de-bar
kapparah לאפוקי האי ערל. le-appukei hai arel. So therefore when you're thinking
about an uncircumcised person and again, the problem is not he's an
owner who can't eat, he's a non-owner who can't eat. But in
that case דלאו בר כפרה הוא. de-lav bar kapparah hu. Since he
is not in the פרשה parsha of bringing a קרבן פסח, korban
pesach, כפרה kapparah here is being used generally meaning the קרבן korban
being for him. So therefore thinking about him does not invalidate. רב
חסדא Rav Chisda סבר savar now רב חסדא Rav Chisda holds האי
ערל נמי. hai arel nami. No, even this ערל. arel. כיון דבר
חיובא הוא keivan de-bar chiyuva hu since he's a Jew and obligated
in the קרבן פסח korban pesach בר כפרה הוא. bar kapparah hu.
He is considered in the פרשה parsha of a קרבן פסח. korban
pesach. Ah, right now he can't bring because he has a ברית
מילה brit milah הואיל דאי בעי מתקן נפשיה. ho'il de-i ba'ei matkan
nafshei. Since in theory he could any he could get a ברית
מילה, brit milah, he's not considered completely out of the פרשה. parsha.
There's an incidental reason, meaning the way we would say it is,
there's an incidental reason he's not able to do it, but he
is not categorically excluded. Now you could say a common example, right,
as opposed to someone who's not Jewish. Or a man for a
יולדת. yoledet. Or a man for a יולדת, yoledet, exactly. Now what
you could ask is, we give as an example sometimes the ערל
arel because we don't want to make him a bad guy, so
we give the example that he's a hemophiliac and he's not able
to get it. Would that mean דאי בעי מתקן נפשיה de-i ba'ei
matkan nafshei in theory he could? No, in theory he can't because
obviously it would be סכנת נפשות. sakanat nefashot. But the question still
is, how do you read this רב חסדא Rav Chisda הואיל? ho'il?
Maybe the הואיל ho'il is not necessarily, although the גמרא Gemara will
read it more practically, we'll see that in a minute, you could
argue that he's not saying in practice he could get a ברית
מילה brit milah but what he's saying is the problem here is
an incidental problem. It's not a categorical exclusion.
So it wouldn't matter if you were an אונן.
onain. Right. Exactly.
It's a person to whom ברית מילה brit milah applies, to whom
קרבן פסח korban pesach applies,
circumstances have right have conspired to make it impossible. And a hemophiliac
also.
It wouldn't matter that he were a hemophiliac.
Right, I think so, but we'll see that the גמרא, Gemara, you
could read it that way. We'll see what the גמרא Gemara does
with this הואיל ho'il statement.
Okay, I could be living in Gat reading from the גמרא Gemara
the fact that I
don't have the, you know, capability. Exactly. Exactly. Yeah, surely.
The first tier of argument here is about an עולה olah which
isn't even eaten.
Right, so that was exactly what I
was saying.
We are shifting the, you know, scene of the debate. We are
shifting the discussion. It is no longer about being לאוכליו le-ochlav and
you need to have in פסח. pesach. It's and then the question
is does זריקה zarika matter in the discussion of קרבן פסח korban
pesach of the לאוכליו? le-ochlav? It's about wrong owners, which is all
about זריקה. zarika. So the fact that you're thinking about זריקה, zarika,
that's exactly the thought that invalidates the thinking of זריקה zarika regarding
wrong owners. It is rather a discussion not about a unique קרבן
פסח korban pesach requirement, about a
generic בעלים be-alim
requirement, שלא לשמו בעליו she-lo lishmo be-alav is the problem here, not
לאוכליו. le-ochlav. It's a generic issue that applies to all קרבנות korbanot
at the moment of זריקה. zarika. And the only reason according to
him we're discussing פסח pesach is it allows for interesting exploration of
what happens when you're doing a שלא לשמו מנוייו she-lo lishmo minuyav
if that other person you're thinking about is completely irrelevant to the
discussion. So as I said a nice a nice example would be
you're bringing a חטאת chatat of a יולדת yoledet and you're thinking
about it's for a man. Okay? Now maybe you genericize חטאת chatat
is שייך shayach for a man. Okay, but the point is it's
not about a unique קרבן פסח korban pesach requirement. קרבן פסח korban
pesach is just a circumstance to explore this
question of שלא לשמו בעליו she-lo lishmo be-alav when the בעלים be-alim
are irrelevant to the קרבן. korban. Does that
invalidate? Dov, you had wanted to say something earlier.
I just wondered whether or not conceptually what allows them to do
this is the language of למנוייו. le-minuyav. In other words, all of
a sudden they're not talking about
לאוכליו, le-ochlav, they're doing מנוייו. minuyav.
Right, so that is correct. שלא למנוייו she-lo le-minuyav that's a קרבן
פסח korban pesach word.
Correct. So לא לאוכליו lo le-ochlav is the unique קרבן פסח korban
pesach problem. לא מנוייו lo minuyav on the one hand relates to
קרבן פסח korban pesach realities, to being, you know, to
being sort
of buying in but whatever
participating, being part of the חבורה chabura of the קרבן פסח korban
pesach relates to the idea of מנוייו. minuyav. מנוייו minuyav is not
a phrase you would use by another קרבן. korban. But the reality
of שלא למנוייו she-lo le-minuyav is essentially the reality of שלא לשמו
בעליו. she-lo lishmo be-alav. Exactly. Exactly.
They've made the קרבן פסח korban pesach a
דמי. dumi.
Exactly. But until now we have been talking about אוכלא, ochla, now
we're talking about מינויה, minuya, which becomes a general issue of שלא
לשמו בעלים. shelo lishmo be-alim. Okay, so that's the issue. Not about
unique קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, about thinking about owners who are not
relevant. And an example of that, when you're doing this זריקה zrika
or planning on this זריקה, zrika, and the example of that is
ערל areil for קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Is he considered irrelevant or
not? So now the גמרא Gemara says the following: وמי אית ליה
לרב חסדא הואיל Umi islei le-Rav Chisda ho'il does רב חסדא Rav
Chisda hold of this principle of הואיל? ho'il? Since theoretically he could
be in the פרשה, parsha, that's enough to make him in the
פרשה. parsha. So does he hold of this idea of הואיל? ho'il?
והא
אתמר v'ha itmar it was taught, and you remember this was wasn't
so long ago, about three weeks ago, האופה מיום טוב לחול ha-ofeh
mi-yom tov le-chol if somebody is baking or cooking from יום טוב
Yom Tov to the weekday, does he get lashes? רב חסדא אמר
לוקה, Rav Chisda amar loka, רבא אמר אינו לוקה. Rava amar eino
loka. רבא אמר אינו לוקה, Rava amar eino loka, you don't get
lashes,
אמינא הואיל ומיקלעי ליה אורחים חזי ליה aminah ho'il v'miklei lei orchim
chazi lei since were guests to drop by, this food would be
fit for the guests. הכא נמי חזי ליה hacha nami chazi lei
here too it's fit. You're just cooking, which made the food fit
to be eaten on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So as long as
it's made for the sake of the food, even if there's nobody
around to eat it, that's not considered a violation on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. In theory, somebody could eat it. And רב חסדא Rav
Chisda said לוקה, loka, I'm sorry, you get lashes. לא אמינא הואיל
lo aminah ho'il we don't say since, because
right there was not an impending need to do it. Nobody needed
it for eating. So since it was not needed for eating, even
though it was cooking, which was an eating מלאכה, melacha, you still
have violated. Now, you or I would have said: What the heck
does that debate have to do with this debate other than that
it uses the same word of הואיל? ho'il? Right? Meaning each debate
you would frame in its own terms. In this הלכה halacha that
you can't do מלאכה melacha on יום טוב Yom Tov except for
the sake of eating, how do you frame that? Does it mean
eating-related מלאכות melachas are allowed? Cooking is allowed, like, fundamentally because it
makes the food fit for eating, or, you know, it may say
it a different way: as long as what you're producing is theoretically
fit for eating with enough, right? Or does it say no, you
need the sort of the immediate need to give you a license
to do it. And if you don't have that immediate need to
make the food, you don't have that license. Okay. Here, it's a
different question. What defines somebody's in the category or out of the
category? Right now, technically, you're out of the category; in a more
fundamental way, you're out. Obviously, you could hold different positions on those
different questions, even though both of them raise the question of, like,
the hypothetical or theoretical versus the very brass tacks pragmatics. There's no
need to be consistent across those categories. Each one would seem unique
to its own הלכתי halachic area. So the way the גמרא Gemara
links these two is really something I don't understand. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara answers.
So the גמרא Gemara says here רב חסדא Rav Chisda did not
hold that you don't
say theoretically by the cooking, and over there by the שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo he says theoretically you could be in the פרשה. parsha.
So which one is it? So the גמרא Gemara says: בשלמא
דרבא אדרבא לא קשיא bishlama de-Rava ad de-Rava lo kashya it's not
a problem רבא Rava against himself, right? That in the case of
the ערל areil he says that you're
practically out of the פרשה parsha and in the case of cooking
he says you're theoretically there could be guests. That's not a problem.
הכא מחוסר מעשה התם לא מחוסר מעשה. hacha mechusar ma'aseh hatam lo
mechusar ma'aseh. By the case of the ערל, areil, you're more... it's
not so easy to say theoretically you're in the פרשה. parsha. You
would require a significant act, the act of ברית מילה. bris milah.
By the case of cooking, it's more possible to say theoretically, you
know, this could be eaten because it doesn't require some shift and
change of status and to do a ברית מילה, bris milah, just
requires somebody to drop by and knock on your door. Okay. So
maybe in both רבא Rava in principle holds, the way the גמרא
Gemara sort of, you know, unifying these cases of הואיל, ho'il, theoretically
this could happen so it's okay, except it doesn't apply to cases
like an ערל areil which is much more... it's not so easy
to say theoretically, there's the barrier, there's the hurdle of having to
do a significant act. That's how רבא Rava should work, fundamentally he
holds of
הואיל. ho'il. אלא דרב חסדא אדרב חסדא קשיא ela de-Rav Chisda ad
de-Rav Chisda kashya but how do you deal with רב חסדא's Rav
Chisda
contradiction? Because if he's basically going to say הואיל ho'il by the
guy getting a ברית מילה bris milah and that puts him in
the פרשה, parsha, you should say הואיל ho'il that guests could drop
by for the cooking. So אמרי amri so you could say no.
כי לית ליה לרב חסדא הואיל ki leis lei le-Rav Chisda ho'il
when does he not hold of הואיל? ho'il? Like in the case
of the cooking,
לקולא. le-kula. Right. He rejects הואיל ho'il in the case of cooking
because that would be a leniency. We say hypothetically somebody could be
here, okay, it's not a problem that you cook. That he doesn't
hold of. לחומרא le-chumra in our case, to say hypothetically the ערל
areil could be in the category,
אית ליה is lei he does hold that since hypothetically he could
be in the category, that's a problem. Now תוספות Tosafot says again
bracketing the idea that obviously each category could be. תוספות Tosafot says
I don't understand this לקולא לחומרא, lekula l'chumra, that's a very type
of a
rabbinic concern. Now either biblically we look at this hypothetical categories or
we don't. To say well we'll do it to be lenient and
not to be strict is sort of a rabbinic issue. So תוספות
Tosafot actually claims in רב חסדא Rav Chisda that that's what he
has to say. He says according to רב חסדא Rav Chisda in
principle he does not hold of הואיל. ho'il. And that's why he
says you get lashes on when you cook on יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Okay, and therefore in principle רב חסדא Rav Chisda this is
what תוספות Tosafot says really would agree with רבא Raba this ערל
arel is out of the category and you're okay. But to be
strict rabbinically he's going to say he's in the category and you
invalidated the קרבן. korban. That leads תוספות Tosafot to a very interesting
questions. Wait a minute. You mean the קרבן פסח korban Pesach is
only
invalid rabbinically? So then how did this guy fulfill his biblical obligation
to bring the קרבן פסח? korban Pesach? I mean he brought it
and he's not going to bring it on פסח שני Pesach Sheni
because biblically it was okay. What does it mean to be have
a rabbinically invalidated
קרבן פסח? korban Pesach? What is this guy going to do for
his obligation?
What prevents him from fulfilling his תורה Torah obligation?
So what תוספות Tosafot says is it's not a problem because here
we invalidated it at the moment of שחיטה. shchita. When you were
שוחט shochet you were planning on זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. And therefore
what the rabbis are telling you is don't do the זריקת הדם.
zrikat hadam. So because they're telling you not to do the זריקת
הדם zrikat hadam you never get to be יוצא yotzei anyway. תוספות
Tosafot explains this as a rabbinic problem. I don't think that's necessarily
true. You know the issue of הואיל ho'il even if again sort
of seeing these as great categories to compare, do we say theoretically
how do we deal with the theoretical possibility of something? So it
could just be your general orientation
is that
problems we all know that if something's like what does it take
like it takes one bad apple to spoil the bunch. If something
is a little bit problematic it's a problem. So the case that
this guy is theoretically in the פרשה parsha this
ערל, arel, the fact that there's somebody that is somewhat in the
פרשה parsha let's say הואיל ho'il is sort of somewhat right is
enough to create a problem. So that could invalidate. But the fact
when I
cook it's maybe somewhat possible to be eaten theoretically somebody could drop
by it's in this gray area that's not enough to give me
a license. To give me a license to cook on יום טוב
Yom Tov I need there to
be a clear need. For something to be a problem once it's
already a quasi problem it's a problem. I think you could deal
with the קולא חומרא kula chumra without having to resort
to saying it's a rabbinic issue. This is a gray area of
this case of situations but they're not just situations but of cooking
versus פסח. Pesach. No but the idea of קולא kula and חומרא
chumra makes sense if we acknowledge that הואיל ho'il makes something a
gray category. How much should we care about the fact that hypothetically
you could eat the קרבן פסח? korban Pesach? How much do we
care about the fact that hypothetically you could eat it? So how
you deal with gray categories might be different. Problems might be different
than what you need to give something a license to give something
a מתיר mattir in order to do something. Yes Michael.
And
the מחלוקת machloket of the ערל arel specifically about ערל arel as
opposed to non-Jew or just being an example an ערל arel and?
No because a non-Jew you wouldn't have this הואיל ho'il discussion right.
Now the interesting question would be about somebody who is טמא tamei
who you could say הואיל ho'il he could go to the מקוה.
mikvah. What would they say about somebody who is טמא tamei and
who is טמא מת tmei meit on his second day? So he
couldn't go to the מקוה mikvah now he'd go to מקוה mikvah
after which raises the question of how much does הואיל ho'il really
need practically you can do it now or how much does הואיל
ho'il just mean it's a circumstantial problem and not a category problem
right? And I don't think that I think an open
question.
Yes Charlie? Either a rabbinic טומאה tumah would prevent you from bringing
a קרבן פסח? korban Pesach?
Yes. But that's easier because then you're not even bringing it to
begin with. תוספות Tosafot here was sort of first assuming you did
the זריקת הדם zrikat hadam and we're still telling you no good.
And then תוספות's Tosafot's answer was no no no we're telling you
don't do the זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. Okay let's continue. Says מר
Mar says like this: אמר ליה מר זוטרא
בריה דרב מרי לרבינא.
Amlei Mar Zutra brei
d'Rav Mari l'Ravina. So מר זוטרא Mar Zutra son of רב מרי
Rav Mari said to רבינא. Ravina. קתני הואיל וערלה פסולה. Ktani ho'il
v'orla psula.
Now he's going back to fine that was the end of the
discussion of this debate of רבא Raba and רב חסדא Rav Chisda
about you have a קרבנא korbana to do זריקה zrika לערלה l'orla
לערלים. l'arelim.
And this last approach was that it wasn't about אוכלא ochla but
it was about מינוייא minuya and it was about שלא לשם בעלים.
shelo l'shem ba'alim. Now we're going back to the ברייתא baraita that
we quoted that wanted to learn out
the basis for saying מקצת ערלים miktzat arelin that a thought about
some people being ערל arel and some not does not invalidate and
it said let's learn it out from טומאה. tumah. Having some טומאה
tumah and not other טומאה tumah doesn't invalidate. So the same should
be true about ערל. arel. So the גמרא Gemara is now going
to unpack that. Let's take a look. אמר ליה מר
זוטרא בריה דרב מרי לרבינא.
Amlei Mar
Zutra brei d'Rav Mari l'Ravina. קתני Ktani we taught in the ברייתא
baraita we learned yesterday: הואיל וערלה פוסלת וטומאה פוסלת. ho v'orla poseles
v'tuma poseles. Let's compare ערלה orla to טומאה. tumah. They both invalidate
the קרבן. korban. מה טומאה לא עשה בה מקצת טומאה ככל טומאה
Ma tumah lo asa bah miktzat tumah k'chol tumah the same way
by טומאה tumah some טומאה tumah doesn't invalidate you need כל טומאה,
chol tumah, אף ערלה לא עשה מקצת ערלה ככל ערלה af orla
lo asa miktzat orla k'chol orla by ערלה orla as well only
you would need everybody to be an ערל arel or think about
all the ערלים arelim in order to. In the חבורה. chaburah. Okay,
or at least thinking only about the ערלים arelim and not about
the others, of the other people. Says גמרא, Gemara, האי טומאה היכי
דמי? Hai tumah heichi dami? What's this case of טומאה tumah that
we take for granted that partial טומאה tumah is not a problem?
אילימא בטומאת גברא, Ileima betumat gavra, if it's the most obvious analogy,
some of the people are טמא tamei and some are not, so
then ומאי לא עשה בה מקצת טומאה ככל טומאה? u'mai lo asah
bah miktzat tumah kechol tumah? What does it mean that some being
some טומאה tumah is not as bad as all טומאה? tumah? דאיכא
ארבעה וחמישה גברי טמאי וארבעה וחמישה
גברי טהורי. De'ika arba vechamisha gavre teme'im ve'arba vechamisha gavre tehorim. The
גמרא Gemara now actually gives you some concrete image of what we're
talking about. If there are four or five people that are טמא
tamei and four or five people that are טהור, tahor, לא פסלי
להו טמאים לטהורים? lo pasli lehu teme'im lit'horim? The presence of the
טמאים teme'im doesn't invalidate the טהורים tehorim because it's a mix and
the חבורה chaburah is a mix and you're thinking about both. So
and we say the same that's true by טמאים teme'im it should
be true by a mix of ערלים arelim and מולים, mulim, circumcised
and uncircumcised. גבי ערלה
נמי הא לא פסלה. Gabbi orlah nami ha lo pasla. So okay,
if that's what you already know by טומאה, tumah, well we know
the same thing by ערלה. orlah. גבי ערלה נמי הא לא פסלה
דתנן למולים ולערלים כשר. Gabbi orlah nami ha lo pasla d'tenan limulim
vela'arelim kasher. We know that a mix of circumcised uncircumcised is כשר
kasher the same way טמא tamei and טהור. tahor. ומאי שנא טומאה
דפשיטא ליה, U'mai shena tumah depeshita lei, so how did the author
of this ברייתא braita take for granted that הלכה halacha by טומאה
tumah that some טמא tamei people aren't a problem,
ומאי שנא ערלה דמיסתפקא ליה, u'mai shena orlah demistapka lei, but by
ערלה orlah he didn't know the same הלכה? halacha? Right, meaning the
analogy was so powerful. Look, if some people being טמא tamei and
some is טהור tahor okay, the same should be true about some
being ערלים arelim and some not and some being and some being
and some being circumcised. But the גמרא Gemara is saying yeah, the
analogy is so powerful because they're the exact same case. Why would
the author have known the הלכה halacha by the טמאים teme'im and
not have known the הלכה halacha by the ערלים arelim and then
think you can prove ערל arel from טמאים? teme'im?
You have to think about each individual person?
No, you don't have to think about anything. The best thing is
to not think. I'm serious.
I guess now we understand from the remarks yesterday, but in other
words what's the thought? That I'm thinking about חבורה chaburah X, and
I subliminally know—right, I'm thinking about חבורה. chaburah. There's some טמאים teme'im
in there.
I'm thinking about
ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, יוני Yoni and George and Sally and Polly
and I happen to know who's who.
Yeah, it's a good question. I don't know, it's a good question.
I thought you also were going to say something else. If I
am thinking particularly ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, לוי, Levi, יהודה, Yehudah, I
just let's say I just don't know that ראובן Reuven happens to
be an ערל. arel. Right? Do I have to know that he's
an ערל? arel? You know, so I don't know, that's all very
good question. Alright, anyway let's see. So if we're comparing ערלים arelim
to טמאים, teme'im, so how do we know one without knowing the
other? אלא טומאה בטומאת בשר. Ela tumah betumat basar. It must be
we're not comparing it to טמא tamei people because then we would
obviously it would be obviously the same as ערל. arel. We would
know that, either they both would be a question or neither would
be a question. It must be we're comparing the case of people
being ערל arel to the idea of meat being טמא, tamei, the
meat of the קרבן. korban. So then what does it mean some
isn't a problem, only all's the problem? ומאי לא עשה בה מקצת
טומאה ככל טומאה? u'mai lo asah bah miktzat tumah kechol tumah? What
does it mean we didn't make some like all? ואילו אטמא חד
מאיברים, Ve'illu itma chad me'eivarim,
if one of the limbs of the קרבן korban becomes
טמא—this tamei is after it's been שחט, shechted, a קרבן korban can't
be טמא tamei when it's
alive—האי דאטמא שרפינן ליה, hai de'itma sarfinan lei, the one that became
טמא tamei we burn, ואידך אכלינן ליה, ve'idach achlinan lei, the other
one we eat. Okay, meaning part of it becoming טמא tamei doesn't
affect the rest of it. The rest of what's what's bad is
bad, what's good is good. Okay, so therefore it's not the same
as it all becoming טמא. tamei. So therefore we'll say the same
way by טומאה, tumah, טומאה tumah on some doesn't invalidate everything, by
ערל, arel, having some ערל arel doesn't invalidate everything. Okay, it's a
loose analogy but that would be the analogy. במאי אוקימתא בטומאת בשר?
Bimai u'kamtah betumat basar? So what are you saying, this ברייתא braita
is talking about it's making a comparison to the טומאה tumah of
the meat? אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, let's look at the end of
the ברייתא. braita. When it argues whether to compare to טומאה tumah
or whether to compare to a פיגול pigul thought. So what do
you remember that was the ברייתא braita yesterday? So the גמרא Gemara
said דון דבר שאינו נוהג בכל הזבחים מדבר שאינו נוהג בכל הזבחים.
don davar she'eino noheg bechol sevachim midavar she'eino noheg bechol sevachim. Let's
compare טומאה tumah to ערלה orlah that both of those are not
universal, they both are unique to קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Meaning קרבן
פסח korban Pesach it's invalid if the owners are ערלים arelim and
it's invalid if the owners are טמאים. teme'im. Other קרבנות korbanot can
be brought for ערלים arelim and טמאים teme'im even if they can't
be eaten. So let's compare those two that are unique to קרבן
פסח. korban Pesach. ואל יוכיח זמן Ve'al yokhiach zman and let's not
talk about פיגול pigul and a wrong time שנוהג בכל הזבחים shenoheg
bechol sevachim that's universal. So the גמרא Gemara says ומאי טומאה? u'mai
tumah? So what does it mean when it says טומאה tumah is
unique to קרבן פסח? korban Pesach? אי נימא טומאת בשר, I'neima tumat
basar, if it were what you're saying, that the discussion of טומאה
tumah is about the meat being טמא, tamei, not about the owners
being טמא tamei but the meat being טמא, tamei, אמאי אינו נוהג
בכל הזבחים? amai eino noheg bechol sevachim? What do you mean it
doesn't apply? טמא tamei meat is universal. אלא פשיטא, Ela peshita, when
it says טומאה tumah and ערל arel are unique to קרבן פסח,
korban Pesach, it means בטומאת גברא, betumat gavra, when the people are
טמאים. teme'im. ומאי אינו נוהג בכל הזבחים? U'mai eino noheg bechol sevachim?
What does it mean it doesn't apply to other קרבנות? korbanot? ואילו
בכל הזבחים ערל וטמא משלחים קרבנותיהן. Ve'illu bechol hasevachim arel vetamei meshallachin
korbanoteihen. By normal קרבנות korbanot where if you're an ערל arel or
you're טמא tamei you can't eat your
קרבן... korban... because the
Korban Pesach קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is all about eating, and since
they can't eat, it's an invalid korban קרבן. korban. So obviously saying
arel ערל arel and tumah טומאה tumah are unique to Pesach פסח
Pesach means we're talking about tamei טמא tamei people, not tamei טמא
tamei meat. But if we're talking about tamei טמא tamei people, how
come we think it's different than the arel ערל arel to begin
with? So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, reisha betumas basar veseifa betumas
gavrei רישא בטומאת בשר וסיפא בטומאת גברי, reisha betumas basar veseifa betumas
gavrei, the beginning, the analogy is to tamei טמא tamei meat. By
the end you're saying, oh look they work together, but they only
work together when you're talking about tamei טמא tamei people, not when
you're talking about tamei טמא tamei meat. So does that make sense?
So amar lei אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him
in אין, in, yeah, shem tumah keparech שם טומאה כפרך, shem tumah
keparech, we're talking about it's not a parech because it's actually an
answer not a question, but anyway, yeah, you know, generically it's all
tumah טומאה, tumah, so we're able to compare it all. So which
means look, you know, we're going to try to make an analogy
to the case of the tumah טומאה tumah of the meat which
is not a great analogy, but because we're assuming we don't yet
know the halacha הלכה halacha about tumah טומאה tumah of people. Okay,
but then when we're saying should we compare it to tumah טומאה
tumah of meat or should we compare it to people? We'll say,
well, tumah טומאה tumah generically speaking is unique to korban קרבן, korban,
you know, has unique aspects to Korban Pesach קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
and therefore it makes more sense to compare it to the tumah
טומאה tumah of meat, although in this particular case about the tumah
טומאה tumah of the meat it's not unique to Pesach פסח, Pesach,
but generically as a category tumah טומאה tumah and arel ערל arel
are unique to Korban Pesach קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, so therefore they
more can be learned one from the other. That's answer number one.
Ve'iba'it eima ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, I'll give you a better answer.
Actually, even when it comes to the meat, tumah טומאה tumah of
the meat is more a halacha הלכה halacha by Korban Pesach קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. Is more, you know, what do we mean by
that? Seifa nami betumas basar סיפא נמי בטומאת בשר, seifa nami betumas
basar, even when it says it's unique to Pesach פסח, Pesach, that's
also true in a certain way about the tumah טומאה tumah of
the meat. Umai eino noheg bechol hazvachim ומאי אינו נוהג בכל הזבחים,
umai eino noheg bechol hazvachim, what does it mean it's not relevant
to other korbanos קרבנות? korbanos? In the following way. Bechol hazvachim bein
shenitma chelev uvasar kayam בכל הזבחים בין שנטמא חלב ובשר קיים, bechol
hazvachim bein shenitma chelev uvasar kayam, in other korbanos קרבנות, korbanos, there's
an opinion, what happens if you have no fat and no meat,
it's all become tamei טמא, tamei, can you do zerikas hadam זריקת
הדם? zerikas hadam? So there's one opinion that says yes, the korban
קרבן korban is only about the dam דם, dam, just do the
zerika זריקה. zerika. There's another opinion that says no, you need there
to be something that the dam דם dam is being matir מתיר.
matir. So you need there either to be the fat that can
then be burned on the altar, or you need there to be
the meat that can then be eaten. If you have neither, then
you can't do the zerikas hadam זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. You need
one. In other korbanos קרבנות. korbanos. All korbanos קרבנות. korbanos.
Ah, so the dam דם, dam, zerikas hadam זריקת הדם zerikas hadam
is the matir מתיר matir for the achila אכילה achila of the
meat or the or the
achilas mizbeiach אכילת מזבח achilas mizbeiach of the chelev חלב. chelev. It's
it's the mechaper מכפר mechaper of the korban קרבן, korban, but according
to one opinion of a tanna תנא, tanna, you cannot do it
unless there is something for it to then be matir מתיר.
matir. So just
as human beings don't consume blood and the blood is nizrak נזרק.
nizrak. Right. Legavoah לגבוה legavoah doesn't consume the...
right. Certainly nobody disagrees that you need the zerikas hadam זריקת הדם
zerikas hadam if you want to burn the chelev חלב, chelev, nobody
disagrees. The question is if you don't have the chelev חלב chelev
to burn, can you do the zerikas hadam זריקת הדם? zerikas hadam?
Logically you'd say sure, we won't have the chelev חלב, chelev, we
won't have the meat, but at least I'll get my kapparah כפרה,
kappara, at least we'll do the zerika זריקה. zerika. But there's actually
one opinion that says so everybody agrees in order to be able
to eat the meat and do the and do the and do
the burning of the eimurim אימורים eimurim you need zerika זריקה. zerika.
The question is if you don't have the meat and the eimurim
אימורים, eimurim, can you still do the zerika זריקה zerika just to
get the kapparah כפרה? kappara? Okay, that's debated. We're going to assume
the answer is no. You need there to be one or the
other, the meat or the chelev חלב chelev in order to allow
you to do the zerika זריקה, zerika, but one or another suffices.
Pesach פסח Pesach you need, you need... exactly, exactly. That's why other
korbanos קרבנות. korbanos. Let's read that. Bechol hazvachim bein shenitma chelev uvasar
kayam בכל הזבחים בין שנטמא חלב ובשר קיים, bechol hazvachim bein shenitma
chelev uvasar kayam, whether it's the fat that is tamei טמא tamei
and the meat is around, bein shenitma basar vechelev kayam בין שנטמא
בשר וחלב קיים, bein shenitma basar vechelev kayam, or whether it's the
meat that's tamei טמא tamei and the fat is around, zorek es
hadam זורק את הדם, zorek es hadam, you can do zerikas hadam
זריקת הדם zerikas hadam because something now will be consumed, either by
you or the mizbeiach מזבח, mizbeiach, and that allows you to do
zerikas hadam זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. Ve'ilu bepesach ואילו בפסח, ve'ilu bepesach,
but by Pesach פסח, Pesach, that's not the story as Michael has
already intuited. Nitma chelev uvasar kayam נטמא חלב ובשר קיים, nitma chelev
uvasar kayam, if the fat is tamei טמא tamei and you've got
the meat, fine, zorek es hadam זורק את הדם, zorek es hadam,
do the zerika זריקה. zerika. But if nitma basar vechelev kayam נטמא
בשר וחלב קיים, nitma basar vechelev kayam, if the meat is tamei
טמא tamei and the fat is around, eino zorek es hadam אינו
זורק את הדם, eino zorek es hadam, you can't do the zerikas
hadam זריקת הדם. zerikas hadam. Why not? Because what have I been
telling you for the last few days? Pesach פסח Pesach is all
about eating. So if the zerikas hadam זריקת הדם zerikas hadam will
not be matir achila מתיר אכילה matir achila because there's no meat
left to be eaten, it's all tamei טמא, tamei, there's no point
in bringing it, you don't do a zerikas hadam זריקת הדם. zerikas
hadam. Okay, so when we say tumas basar טומאת בשר tumas basar
is unique to Pesach פסח, Pesach, actually that is true, there is
a way that tumas basar טומאת בשר tumas basar is unique to
Pesach פסח, Pesach, because tumas basar טומאת בשר tumas basar can prevent
you from bringing the korban קרבן, korban, and in other korbanos קרבנות
korbanos tumas basar טומאת בשר tumas basar alone will never prevent you
from bringing the korban קרבן. korban. So yes, we're making the analogy
of people that are arel ערל arel to meat that is tamei
טמא. tamei. Some meat tamei טמא tamei is not a problem, some
people arel ערל arel should not be a problem, and we can
also say that those two have special Korban Pesach קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach halachos הלכות halachos because those two even טומאה בשר Tumah basar
has a special status by פסח Pesach which will prevent you from
bringing the קרבן. Korban. Yes,
Michael?
Let's say I was טהור Tahor at the time, you know, the
קרבן's, Korban you know, in the פרשה. Parshah. Yeah, then became טמא
Tamei later in the day. Do I have to go bring a
פסח שני Pesach Sheini even though the first one, this first one,
you know, I was יוצא? Yotzei?
No, so it was, it was נזרק Nizrak for you when you
were when you were טהור, Tahor, but then למעשה L'maaseh you were
unable to eat it. Right. Okay, so we'll talk about that later.
Is it the same with the meat, right? I mean it was
טהור Tahor at the time and then later on in the day,
the whole thing became טמא. Tamei.
Right. Right. So we'll talk about that later.
And meat can't become טמא Tamei until after שחיטה. Shechitah.
Correct.
Okay.
Basic question also, קרבן פסח Korban Pesach unlike every other קרבן Korban
is roasted whole on a spit. Correct. With the חלב Cheilev inside.
That's an interesting debate, a discussion of רמב״ם Rambam and ראב״ד Ra'avad
about that whole issue about the חלב. Cheilev. Okay. There's a great
ראב״ד Ra'avad about that, but we'll talk about that later when we
come to the roasting of it. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. So that's how we're explaining this, comparing it to
טומאת בשר. Tumas basar. במאי אוקימתא בטומאת בשר? Bemai okimta b'tumas basar?
So what is the analogy going on here? People that are ערל,
Arel, some of them, to meat that is טמא. Tamei. אימא סיפא,
Eima seifa, let's go to the very end of the ברייתא. Baraisa.
דנים דבר שלא הותר מכללו Danim davar shelo hutar miklalo when we're
trying to argue that we should learn it for we should learn
ערל Arel from פיגול Pigul and not from טומאה. Tumah. דנים דבר
שלא הותר מכללו, Danim davar shelo hutar miklalo, you learn something that
has is never given a license. ערל Arel is never given a
license and פיגול Pigul is never given a license, meaning license maybe
the wrong word, but anyway is never made permissible. No, is never
made permissible. No, is never made permissible. דנים דבר שלא הותר מכללו,
Danim davar shelo hutar miklalo, so you learn ערל Arel from פיגול,
Pigul, both of those have never are never given an opportunity are
never sort of made permissible. ואל תוכח טומאה V'al tochiach Tumah and
you should not learn it out from the case of טומאה Tumah
שהרי הותרה מכללה. Sheharei hutrah miklalah. Because טומאה Tumah sometimes is allowed,
when? טומאה הותרה בציבור. Tumah hutrah b'tzibur. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, טומאה הותרה בציבור Tumah hutrah b'tzibur is when people
are טמא, Tamei, not when the meat is
טמא. Tamei. אמרת בשלמא Amart b'shlama ואי תימא V'ei teima בטומאת בשר,
B'tumas basar, if it's the טומאה Tumah of the meat, היכא הותרה?
Heicha hutrah? Since when do we ever allow the טמא Tamei meat?
We allow טמא Tamei people. And when we say טומאה הותרה בציבור,
Tumah hutrah b'tzibur, we let you bring the קרבן, Korban, we don't
let you eat the קרבן. Korban. אלא פשיטא בטומאת גברי. Ela peshita
b'tumas gavrei. So we're talking about when people are טמא. Tamei. והיכא
הותרה מכללה בציבור? V'heicha hutrah miklalah b'tzibur? And when do we say
it's allowed? When the ציבור Tzibur is טמא. Tamei. So again we
got the problem. רישא בטומאת בשר, Reisha b'tumas basar, the beginning you're
trying to make an analogy between people that are ערל Arel and
meat that is טמא. Tamei. סיפא בטומאת גברי, Seifa b'tumas gavrei, and
in the end you want to challenge that analogy by saying, "Oh
no, טומאה Tumah is different because it gets overridden." But that's a
different type of טומאה, Tumah, that's when people are טמא. Tamei. So
what's the comparison? גמרא Gemara says, "אין, In, yeah, שם טומאה כחדא,
Shem Tumah kachada, it's still all about טומאה." Tumah. So we can
use that to challenge the analogy because sometimes טומאה, Tumah, the category
of טומאה Tumah is different even though we're talking about people, not
about meat. So okay, that's not such an interesting answer. Now comes
a more interesting answer. ואי בעית אימא, V'ei ba'is eima, if you
want, I'll tell you, כולה בטומאת בשר. Kula b'tumas basar. Yes, it
could be consistently talking about טומאת בשר, Tumas basar, and even the
טומאת בשר Tumas basar is overridden by קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Why?
והיכא הותרה בטומאת פסח? V'heicha hutrah b'tumas Pesach? Because when a פסח
Pesach is brought בטומאה, B'tumah, when a normal קרבן Korban is brought
בטומאה, B'tumah, you bring the קרבן Korban and you don't eat it
because you're still טמא. Tamei. But when a פסח Pesach is brought
בטומאה, B'tumah, what do you think happens? You bring the קרבן Korban
and you eat it because the whole point of bringing the פסח
Pesach is to eat it. And if you're eating it and you're
טמא, Tamei, guess what happens to the קרבן? Korban? The קרבן's Korban
also טמא. Tamei. So by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach we allow the
fact that the טמא Tamei meat to be
eaten. Normally, right, בציבור, B'tzibur, בציבור. B'tzibur. Normally we only allow for
a קרבן Korban for טמא Tamei people to bring it, okay, and
we're not allowing טמא Tamei meat to be eaten. But by קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach we allow טמא Tamei meat to be eaten by
case of ציבור. Tzibur. דתנן, Detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah,
פסח הבא בטומאה נאכל בטומאה. Pesach haba b'tumah ne'echal b'tumah. A פסח
Pesach that was brought בטומאה B'tumah can be eaten even though you're
טמא, Tamei, even though it's טמא, Tamei, שלא בא מתחילתו אלא לאכילה.
Shelo ba mitchilato ela l'achilah. Okay, it was only brought from the
very beginning for the sake of eating. So actually in this discussion,
which seemed to be one of, you know, a technical issue, are
we talking about טומאת בשר, Tumas basar, טומאת גברי, Tumas gavrei, we
actually found out two very powerful ideas by the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach because it's brought for the sake because it's coming for the
sake of eating. Number one is that if the meat is טמא,
Tamei, don't do זריקת הדם Zrikas hadam as opposed to other קרבנות.
Korbanos. Number two is, when you're bringing it בטומאה, B'tumah, so other
קרבנות Korbanos you wouldn't eat, but here you actually have a license
to eat it as well even though you're טמא Tamei and the
meat is טמא. Tamei.
Can you become טמא Tamei after you joined a חבורה? Chaburah?
Yeah, that's like Michael's question.
Let's say it was brought for the חבורה? Chaburah?
Or you can't join any חבורה, Chaburah, it doesn't do you any
good, you're טמא. Tamei.
No, but what if someone, you have another חבורה Chaburah down the
street, everyone's everyone's טמא Tamei in that?
What are they going to do?
Some people טמא, Tamei, all people טמא. Tamei. בציבור. B'tzibur. No, טמא
Tamei person, that's not בציבור. B'tzibur. בציבור B'tzibur is the entire כלל
ישראל, Klal Yisrael, okay,
51% of all the כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael.
It's not by חבורה. Chaburah. No.
No, no, no, no, it's by all of כלל ישראל. Klal Yisrael.
Now, we're going to have an interesting discussion later on about women's
obligation in the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and whether the ציבור tzibur
there is—is men, is women, how do you count the ציבור, tzibur,
but it is about all of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, like looking
at the entire population. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
so מתיב רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע. mativ Rav Huna brei d'Rav
Yehoshua. רב הונא-ס Rav Huna's בן רב יהושע ben Rav Yehoshua asked
on this—on based on this ברייתא. baraita. Let's take a look. הפסח
שעבר שנתו, haPesach she'avar shenato, our—our famous category, fun category, this is
going to keep on repeating, which is the פסח Pesach that is
either aged out, thank you, or right it's not on פסח. Pesach.
We have two cases where פסח Pesach becomes a שלמים. shelamim. One
is today isn't the 14th of ניסן. Nisan. It's either too early
or too late. And we said already before that when it's after
the 14th of ניסן, Nisan, then it's more automatically a שלמים shelamim
because because, you know, you missed your chance. Right? When it's פורים,
Purim, you have to change its status because it still could be
a פסח. Pesach. That was what we discussed yesterday. There's another variation
on that theme of a פסח Pesach becoming a שלמים, shelamim, not
that it isn't the 14th of ניסן, Nisan, but that it is
the 14th of ניסן, Nisan, but this animal is aged out, is
too old, is more than a year old, so could never be
a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. And there too because it's never possible
to be קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at this stage, it's automatically a
שלמים, shelamim, but it still has this like פסח Pesach substrate, but
right now its status is as a שלמים. shelamim. So let's take
a look.
הפסח שעבר שנתו, haPesach she'avar shenato, you got a פסח Pesach that's
more than a year old. שחטו בזמנו, shechato bizmano, you שחט shecht
it now on the 14th לשמו, lishmo, for the sake of a
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay? It's a שלמים shelamim effectively, and you're
שחט-ינג shechting it as a פסח. Pesach. וכן, vechen, or even a
more simple case, שוחט אחרים לשם פסח בזמנו, shochet acherim l'shem Pesach
bizmano, you take a straight שלמים, shelamim, a straight שלמים shelamim and
you שחט shecht it on the 14th for the sake of קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. What's the הלכה? halacha? So what's the normal הלכה
halacha if you take a שלמים shelamim and you שחט shecht it
for the sake of an עולה? olah? Right? Like it says in
the first פרק. perek. Normal case of שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, when
you're not dealing with a פסח Pesach or a חטאת. chatat. A
שלמים shelamim you do for the sake of an עולה olah is,
Michael, כשר kosher or פסול? pasul?
You're talking about שינוי השם.
shinuy hashem. A פסח Pesach for the sake of an
עולה—just—not olah פסח, Pesach, a שלמים shelamim for the sake of an
עולה. olah. First משנה mishna in זבחים: Zevachim: כל הזבחים שנזבחו שלא
לשמן כשרין אלא שלא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה. kol hazevachim shenizbechu shelo
lishman kesherin ela shelo alu l'baalim l'shem chova. Right? Only a פסח
Pesach and a חטאת chatat become invalid שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Other
קרבנות korbanot שלא לשמו shelo lishmo are valid except they don't count
for the owner. So if you're שחט-ינג shechting here a שלמים shelamim
for the sake of a פסח, Pesach, you would say it should
be at least כשר, kosher, you should be able to bring it.
Okay, it should be a good שלמים. shelamim. Okay, but the question
here is going to be, one minute,
now it's today's the day that if you were to שחט shecht
a פסח Pesach for a שלמים, shelamim, you would invalidate the פסח.
Pesach. So maybe by mirror image if you שחט shecht a שלמים
shelamim for a פסח, Pesach, you should invalidate the שלמים. shelamim. Okay,
it's a funny type of an argument, but that's the question. Okay?
Will a שלא לשמו shelo lishmo which normally is not a problem
by a שלמים, shelamim, will לשם פסח l'shem Pesach on the 14th
be an invalidity for a שלמים? shelamim? Yes.
So what if he שחט-עד shechted it
after חצות chatzot but before they got around to bringing the קרבן
תמיד? Korban Tamid? At that point you could in theory bring both
a שלמים shelamim and a פסח. Pesach.
You could bring the שלמים shelamim right now also, as long as
you did it before the קרבן תמיד. Korban Tamid. Oh, yeah, but
בדיעבד bediavad it would be good. That wouldn't matter. Okay. הפסח—so haPesach
let's take a look. הפסח שעבר שנתו ושחטו בזמנו לשמו. haPesach she'avar
shenato u'shechato bizmano lishmo. וכן השוחט אחרים לשם פסח בזמנו. vechen hashochet
acherim l'shem Pesach bizmano. Simpler case. שלמים לשם פסח shelamim l'shem Pesach
on the 14th. Right? So logically it should be okay, but maybe
by comparison to the reverse case it should be no good. רבי
אליעזר פוסל. Rabbi Eliezer posel. ורבי יהושע מכשיר. veRabbi Yehoshua machshir. רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says it is good. So okay, all right, that's
very interesting. How's that relevant to our discussion? טעמא בזמנו. taama bizmano.
The reason they're having this debate is that we're talking on the
14th. הא שלא בזמנו, ha shelo bizmano, if it was the 13th
or was פורים Purim and you had this one-year-old קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach that had aged out or whatever, you just had a שלמים
shelamim and you שחט-עד shechted it on פורים לשם פסח, Purim l'shem
Pesach, כשר. kosher. Everybody would agree it would be כשר kosher because
it would be a normal case of שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. ואמאי?
ve'amai? Why is that true? נימא הואיל ובזמנו פוסל שלא בזמנו נמי
פוסל. neima ho'il u'bizmano posel shelo bizmano nami posel. We're going back
to the הואיל. ho'il. We thought we had left that behind us.
So if you're going to say הואיל, ho'il, that this guy could
be ערל, arel, could be a נימול, a nimol, and the fact
that he theoretically could get a ברית מילה bris milah invalidates, let's
also say here a הואיל ho'il to invalidate. Since in theory we
could have waited till פסח Pesach and not שחט-עד shechted it on
פורים, Purim, and שחט-עד shechted it on פסח לשם פסח Pesach l'shem
Pesach and that would invalidate, even when we שחט shecht it on
פורים לשם פסח, Purim l'shem Pesach, it should invalidate. I gotta tell
you, I'll just state I'm throwing up my hands. Right? The way
we could easily compare הואיל-ס ho'ils between some so completely different categories.
Right? The question is, is an ערל arel in the category or
out of the category, since theoretically he could be a נימול. a
nimol. And to compare that to a case of if you're... exactly
this שלמים shelamim on פורים, Purim, so do we say since had
you waited till פסח Pesach it would have been invalid? If you
שחטed shecht today on פורים, Purim, it should be invalid. I don't
understand it. Anyway, that’s just a question. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav
Papa, so says רב פפא, Rav Papa, no, שני התם. shani hatam.
There it’s different. There the פסוק pasuk makes it very clear, it’s
only about doing it on the fourteenth. דאמר קרא, De'amar kra, the
verse says, ואמרתם זבח פסח הוא. V'amartem zevach pesach hu. This is
the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, only this. הוא, Hu, the first thing
we learn from that is הוא בדווקא ולא הוא לשם אחרים. hu
b'davka v'lo hu l'shem acherim. Actually here we learn the basis for
the first משנה, mishna, which the גמרא Gemara never told us, which
is to the second משנה, mishna, whatever. How do you know a
פסח pesach לשם l'shem another קרבן korban is פסול? pasul? Right? We
said a חטאת chatas and a פסח pesach are the only two
קרבנות korbanot that when for the sake of another קרבן korban is
invalid. Where do you know it about a קרבן פסח? korban pesach?
So we learn it from this פסוק pasuk of הוא, hu, זבח
פסח הוא. zevach pesach hu. Only when it’s לשם פסח. l'shem Pesach.
When you do a
פסח pesach לשם l'shem some other קרבן korban you invalidate it. So
number one, that tells us the principle we’ve been working with for
the last few days. Now, the other point it tells us is
ולא אחרים לשמו. v'lo acherim lishmo. The same way according to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer you can't do a פסח pesach for another קרבן,
korban, you can’t do another קרבן korban for a פסח pesach and
that invalidates it. That is the basis of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
that says the reverse also invalidates. So what do we say? So
the argument would be the following. בזמנו, Bizmano, in the time, on
the fourteenth, שהוא פסול לשם אחרים, she'hu pasul l'shem acherim, when the
פסח pesach becomes invalidated when you do it for the sake of
another קרבן, korban, that’s the time, the fourteenth, אחרים פסולין לשמו, acherim
psulin lishmo, that you invalidate other קרבנות korbanot when you do it
for the sake of a פסח. pesach. This is the day that
the status of פסח pesach is, you know, matters. Matters when you
change it away from being that status, matters when you try to
make other things into a פסח. שלא בזמנו Pesach shelo bizmano on
some other day, on פורים Purim or, you know, or on שבועות,
Shavuos, שהוא כשר לשם אחרים, she'hu kasher l'shem acherim, that if you
did a פסח pesach. for the sake of something else it would
be כשר. kasher. פסח pesach שלא בזמנו Shelo bizmano is כשר, kasher,
it becomes a שלמים. shelamim.
This is agreed upon by everybody, or was this part of...?
No, no, it's explaining רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position. אחרים כשרים לשמו,
Acherim ksherim lishmo, others would also be כשרים. ksherim. So basically, the
answer is it was a very strange question. The question was why
is it פסול pasul on, why is it כשר kasher on פורים,
Purim, why don’t we say, well, since had you waited for פסח
Pesach it would be פסול, pasul, it's פסול pasul on פורים, Purim,
the same way we say, well, since this guy could get a
ברית מילה? bris milah? And the answer is no, that’s the הלכה.
halacha. The הלכה halacha is that the day that matters when you
do פסח, pesach, the status of פסח, pesach, is on the fourteenth.
So we don't consider other days, we learn it from the פסוק,
pasuk, we only consider this day, and therefore פסח pesach is invalid
when done for other קרבנות, korbanot, other קרבנות korbanot are invalid when
done for the פסח. pesach. Okay.
Yes, and the explanation to the pronunciation. שינוי השם Shinuy hashem with
all קרבנות, korbanot, כשרים שלא בשמן ופסולין לשם קרבן אחר. ksherim shelo
bishmon u'psulin l'shem korban acher. שינוי השם Shinuy hashem for פסח, pesach,
so פסח pesach for another קרבן korban is always פסול, pasul, unless
on פסח, Pesach, on
ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, right?
But if I do a פסח pesach לשם שלמים l'shem shelamim after
or before פסח, Pesach, then
it's good, then it's a שלמים. shelamim. Right.
And the other way around, שאר קרבן לשם פסח, shear korban l'shem
pesach, on,
according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's פסול, pasul, according to רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua it's
כשר, kasher, and then on all other dates everybody agrees it's כשר.
kasher. Okay, now we get to a very nice little story. Okay,
רב שמלאי אתא לקמיה דרבי יוחנן. Rav Simlai ata l'kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan.
רב שמלאי Rav Simlai came to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, ניתני לי מר ספר יוחסין, nitni li mar sefer yuchsin,
let the master teach me the book of genealogies. רש״י Rashi says
this means it sort of it might be, as we know חז״ל
Chazal were very concerned about יוחסין, yuchsin, the fourth פרק perek of
קידושין, Kiddushin, and it might have been like a record of, you
know, who’s from a good family, who’s from a מיוחס, meyuchas, who’s
not, who is, who’s a concern of a ממזר. mamzer. But רש״י
Rashi says that here it means a type of a Tannaitic דרשות,
drashot, you know, sort of like מדרשי תנאים midreshei tannaim on the
book of דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim, because דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim is
all about who’s the son of who, who’s the son of who,
it’s all about genealogies. So he said, teach me this. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to him, מהיכן את?
me'heichan at? Where do you come from? אמר ליה מלוד, Amar lei
mi-Lod, I come from לוד. Lod. והיכן מותבך? V'heichan movtach? So you
were born in לוד, Lod, where are you living now? בנהרדעא, B'Neharde'a,
I went over to בבל, Bavel, I live in נהרדעא. Neharde'a. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, אין דונין, ein donin, you don't teach, or some
say אין שונין, ein shonin, you don't teach the book of יוחסין
yuchsin לא ללודים ולא לנהרדעים. lo l'Lodim v'lo l'Neharde'im.
You don't teach it to anybody from לוד Lod and anybody from
נהרדעא, Neharde'a, וכל שכן דאת מלוד ומותבך בנהרדעא, v'chol shekein d'at mi-Lod
u-movtach b'Neharde'a, you come from לוד Lod and you're living in נהרדעא.
Neharde'a. So what type of answer is that? So רש״י Rashi said,
either he just wasn't interested in teaching him ספר יוחסין, sefer yuchsin,
so this was an excuse, or he says that maybe actually people
from those places had some real questions about them, about ממזרות mamzerut
and whatnot, and you don't want to be talking about that stuff.
You know, that's the whole issue about, no, no, oh, if it's,
right, that would not make it about דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim, that
would make it about actual real genealogies בזמן הזה bizman hazeh and
the whole issue about not wanting to be, you know, the whole,
as the whole interesting thing about ממזרות mamzerut and, you know, sort
of, you know, try, you know, not trying to publicize issues and
so on. Anyway, so he didn't want to teach it to him.
He says אין דונין, ein donin,
yeah, so the side says אין שונין. ein shonin. Okay, which is
probably the better גרסא *girsa*, or certainly the easier גרסא *girsa*. Okay,
so now כפייה *kafyei*, so he sort of persuaded him, a little
bit he forced him, but you know, he nudged him, he persuaded
him, and וארצי *artzi*, fine, he finally agreed. So fine, I'll teach
it to you. אמר ליה *amar lei*, נישנייה בג' ירחי *nisnaya b'gimal
yarchei*, I want to learn it in three months. So שקל קלא
פתק ביה *shakal kala paska bei*, he took a clod of earth
and he threw it at him. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* to רב
שמלאי *Rav Simlai*. אמר ליה *amar lei*, he said to him, ומה
ברוריה *u'mah Brurya*, what, you know, what consider ברוריה *Brurya*, דביתיה דרבי
מאיר *deveiteih d'Rabbi Meir*, she was the wife of רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir*, ברתיה דרבי חנניה בן תרדיון *barteih d'Rabbi Chananya ben Teradyon*, and
the daughter of רבי חנניה בן תרדיון *Rabbi Chananya ben Teradyon*, דתניא
תלת
מאה שמעתתא ביומא *de-tanya tlas mei shmaiteta b'yoma*, in one day she
was able to learn 300 different, you know, discussions, סוגיות *sugyos*, מג'
מאה רבוותא *mi-gimal mei ravasa* from 300 different rabbis, and even, obviously
300 is usually an exaggeration number, but anyways, ואפילו הכי לא יצאה
ידי חובתה בתלת שנין *va'afilu hachi lo yaksa yedei chovasa bi-tlas shnin*,
and even so she was so prodigious at, you know, in her
learning in one day, and even she could not master this in
three years, the ספר יוחסין Sefer Yuchsin, *Sefer Yuchasin*. ואת *ve'at*, and
you, אמרת בתלתא ירחי *amarta bi-tlasa yarchei*, and you think you're going
to do it in three months? So quite fascinating this whole using
ברוריה *Brurya* as the example of, you know, of what a, you
know, of what sort of stellar learning is. Also, it's interesting that
he gives her ייחוס *yichus*. In a discussion of ספר יוחסין Sefer
Yuchsin *Sefer Yuchasin* is giving her ייחוס *yichus*, you know, and maybe
that's also like a dig. You're from Lod and Neharde'a, those people
have bad ייחוס *yichus*. ברוריה *Brurya*, who had great ייחוס *yichus*, and
she was so prodigious she couldn't do it in three years, and
you think you're going to do it in three months? What did
you want to say Rivka?
ידי חובתה *yedei chovasa*.
Meaning her חובה *chovah* of being able to satisfactorily master this material.
I know, I know it is an interesting phrase. Yeah, but that
seems to be what it means in this context. רש"י *Rashi* says
לא יכלה לשנותה בג' שנים *lo yachlah lishnosah bi-shalosh shanim*, like could
not like master this material.
Yeah, she had great ייחוס *yichus* but her husband was descended from
converts.
Okay, that's a good point too. All right, so now the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this. כי קם ואזל *ki shakam v'azilsa*,
so basically he managed to end the conversation there. We're not talking
about this. Fine. כי קם ואזל *ki shakam v'azilsa*, they were, they
were then moving, you know, and they, they got up and they
were moving along. אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said to him,
רבי *Rebbi*, so he figured, all right, I've got to get something
out of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. So he switched the topic. מה
בין לשמו ושלא לשמו Lishmo v'shelo lishmo, *mah bein lishmo v'shelo lishmo*,
now you see what he's doing. So he said, all right, let's
talk learning. Why, what's the difference between לשמו ושלא לשמו Lishmo v'shelo
lishmo, *lishmo v'shelo lishmo*, where a partial invalid intent, a שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo *shelo lishmo* intent invalidates, ולאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו *v'lo'ochlav v'shelo lo'ochlav*,
a mix of right eaters and wrong eaters, where a partial invalid
intent does not invalidate. Why is שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* more of
a weighty invalidity than שלא לאוכליו Shelo l'ochlav *shelo lo'ochlav*, comparing the
two משניות *mishnayos* that we've been looking at. שינוי השם *shinuy hashem*,
right? שינוי השם *shinuy hashem*, yeah, what did I say? Okay. שינוי
השם *shinuy hashem* even for partial like intent, שינוי השם *shinuy hashem*
is worse than a partial wrong eaters. One invalidates and one does
not. אמר ליה *amar lei*, הו וצורבא מרבנן את *ho v'tzurba m'rabanan
at*, ah, fine, I see that you're at least a bit of
a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham, *talmid chacham*, you know how to ask
a question about משניות *mishnayos*. תא אימא לך *tav eima lach*, I'll
tell you. So it's interesting, sounds like this guy was a total
stranger, some guy comes knocking on his door, he doesn't know who
he is, he wants to learn ספר יוחסין Sefer Yuchsin, *Sefer Yuchasin*,
presumably, the way the מהרש"א *Maharsha* explains or we'll see it later,
whether it is this מדרש *midrash* on דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim, *Divrei
Hayamim*, but if it really is about how people are מיוחס *meyuchas*,
that's very protected material, and therefore you don't want to teach it
to other people. So he kept on pushing him off, and now
maybe this guy's feeling bad, he wants to at least show his
credentials, that he's not just some, some guy, and so he starts
asking a לומדות *lomdus* question. So, okay, fine, I see you're a
תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*, I'm still not going to teach you ספר
יוחסין *Sefer Yuchasin*, but let's talk about your question. Okay, again, there's
got to be something more about the relationship of this discussion with
ספר יוחסין *Sefer Yuchasin*, I haven't figured it out, but anyway, come
let me answer your question. לשמו ושלא לשמו פסולה בגופו *lishmo v'shelo
lishmo psula b'gufo*. The issue of שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* is more
of a strong invalidity because it is what?
I don't know, the rabbis, secret cipher בגופו *b'gufo*, because it's, because
it's intrinsic to the identity of the קרבן korban *korban*. לאוכליו ושלא
לאוכליו L'ochlav v'shelo l'ochlav, *lo'ochlav v'shelo lo'ochlav*, that invalidity אין פסולה בגופו
*ein psula b'gufo*. It's more external, who's the owner, it's not intrinsic
to the identity. So number one, לשמו *lishmo* is a more intrinsic
invalidity. לשמו ושלא לשמו אי אפשר לברר efshar levareir, איסורה *lishmo v'shelo
lishmo ee efshar l'varer issurah*. לשמו ושלא לשמו *lishmo v'shelo lishmo* you
can't distinguish, meaning if I'm saying I'm שחטינג *shechting* it לשמו *lishmo*
and שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*, which part of it is לשמו *lishmo*
and which part of it is שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo*? Right? It's
all sort of pervasive throughout the entire קרבן *korban*. לאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו
L'ochlav v'shelo l'ochlav *lo'ochlav v'shelo lo'ochlav*, if I'm שחטינג *shechting* it for
you know eaters and those that, some that can eat and some
that cannot eat, אפשר לברר איסורה *efshar l'varer issurah*, you can distinguish.
How can you distinguish? First of all, the specific people who are
the right eaters, who are the wrong eaters are very well defined.
And the way רש"י *Rashi* explains it, when they come to eat
the קרבן *korban*, there will be people that are the right people,
there will be people... people that are eating, people that are able
to eat will be eating their portion and people that aren't able
to eat will be eating their portion, and you'll know which is
the good portion and which is the bad. So that invalidity is
not as pervasive.
לאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו, אפשר לברר, I just said. לשמו ושלא לשמו, ישנו
בארבע עבודות. yeshno b'arba avodot. ושלא לשמו פסול V'shelo lishmo pasul is
a universal פסול. psul. It applies by other קרבנות korbanot and it
applies at all four of the עבודות. avodot. לאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו, the
idea of wrong eaters אינו בארבע עבודות. eino b'arba avodot. It's not
at all four עבודות, avodot, it's only by the שחיטה. shechita. לשמו
ושלא לשמו, ישנו בציבור כביחיד. yeshno b'tzibur k'v'yachid. The idea of שלא
לשמו applies by a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur like it does by
יחיד. yachid. לאוכליו ושלא לאוכליו אינו בציבור כביחיד. eino b'tzibur k'v'yachid. שלא
לאוכליו shelo l'ochlav doesn't apply to קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. You know
why it doesn't apply to קרבן ציבור? korban tzibur? Because שלא לאוכליו
Shelo l'ochlav
only
applies to a קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. So that's really what it
should have said. It should have said that one is by all
קרבנות korbanot and the other is just by קרבן פסח. korban Pesach.
But okay. שלא לאוכליו doesn't apply by anything that's not a קרבן
פסח, korban Pesach, doesn't apply by a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur.
There's no eating on the קרבן תמיד? tamid?
Fine. Okay, that's a good point. רב אשי, Rav Ashi, well you
have קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur like, you know, שלמי עצרת shalmei atzeret
that are not a תמיד. tamid.
They're eaten by the כהנים.
kohanim. Yeah, fine. Okay. And not all כהנים kohanim can eat it.
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, פסולו בגופו ואי אפשר לברר איסורו,
psulo b'gufo v'i efshar levareir issuro, that was the end of the
story. רב אשי Rav Ashi says, פסולו בגופו ואי אפשר לברר איסורו
חדא מילתא היא. psulo b'gufo v'i efshar levareir issuro chada milta hi.
The intrinsic פסול psul and saying it's non-differentiated
is essentially saying the same point. דמאי טעם אמר פסולו בגופו? D'mai
ta'am amar psulo b'gufo?
Why are we saying it's intrinsic? משום דאי אפשר לברר איסורו mishum
d'i efshar levareir issuro because it's pervasive, because it's not differentiated. Now
you could have said different, right? פסולו בגופו Psulo b'gufo is because
it speaks to its identity whereas the owner doesn't speak to its
identity. But he says those are more or less the same point.
Fine. Now to wrap up the discussion of ספר יוחסין, אמר רמי
בר רב יהודה אמר רב amar Rami bar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
מיום שנגנז ספר יוחסין, miyom shenignaz Sefer Yuchsin, the day this ספר
יוחסין was hidden. What does hidden mean? So again, if it's like
מדרש תנאים Midrash Tannaim on דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim רש״י Rashi says
it means it was lost. But if it's like this book that
we're really keeping track of, you know, which families people are coming
from and who has a questionable status, then it literally means we
hid it. We don't want it to be public knowledge. It's sort
of like, you know, what is that דור ישרים, Dor Yeshorim, right?
That they'll give you a number. You know the דור ישרים, Dor
Yeshorim, they do the testing, the genetic testing for the whatever, Tay-Sachs?
They don't tell you. They'll give you a number, but they don't
want to like stigmatize you and then you can check your number
with somebody else's number. So it's a similar idea. If it's a
real ספר יוחסין, we don't want to let that information out to
the public. But why learn it? That's a good question. And he
certainly didn't want to teach it to a non תלמיד חכם, to
somebody that he didn't know he could trust. Okay, anyway, no, no,
no, no, no, that was a while ago. Yeah, it is, right,
that she had access to that very private, secret information. Anyway, from
the day that it was hidden, תשש כחן של חכמים, tashash kochan
shel chachamim, the strength of the חכמים chachamim has been sapped, וכהה
מאור עיניהם, v'cheiha me'or eineihem, and the light of their eyes has
been dimmed.
Because the genetic stock has been tainted?
Maybe that's what it means. Or if it's talking about a מדרש
תנאים Midrash Tannaim because we don't have access to this amazing font
of knowledge. And then one last point about that, אמר מר זוטרא
amar Mar Zutra בין אצלא לאצל, bein Etzla l'Atzel, and this is
why רש״י Rashi says it's a מדרש תנאים, Midrash Tannaim, because there's
a פרק perek in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim, that starts by saying,
"These are the children of אצל," Atzel, and then you go, and
then it's a whole פרק perek and then it wraps up by
saying, "These are the children of אצל." Atzel. So a big פרק
perek in דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim, on that one פרק, perek, the
eighth פרק perek of דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim, the discussions around it
sort of, the material relating to that פרק, perek, טענו ארבע מאה
גמלי דדרשא, tanu arba mei'a gamlei d'drasha, four
hundred camels
laden down with the דרשות drashot that could be said on that
one פרק. perek. So that certainly seems that this is about דרשות
drashot said on this book of דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim which is
so amazing, right? Because דברי הימים is like the most boring book
of תנ״ך, Tanakh, right? So maybe what it's saying is that made
it like ripe material for creative דרשות. drashot. Why do I have
to know he is the son of him, the son of him?
So we do plays with words and we use this as an
opportunity to do very fanciful types of מדרשים midrashim and then it
says all of that was lost. Okay, and on that cheery note,
we'll stop there.
Okay, we'll finish today. We caught the book of those. Yeah, they
have the book of those.