Today's דף daf. *daf* is למד גימל *Lamed Gimmel* 33. We pick
up though in the middle of למד ב עמוד ב *Lamed Bet
Amud Bet*, so we're a bit behind but we will catch up
because the last דף *daf* is practically basically a quarter of a
דף *daf*.
And we pick up where in the middle of discussing the פסוקים
psukim *psukim* of מלכויות malchuyot, *malchuyos*, זכרונות zichronot *zichronos*, and שופרות shofrot
*shofros*.
And we pick up with, we had a debate of whether פרטות
*pratot* were like זכרונות zichronot *zichronos* or not and the idea of
mentioning something only about an individual, not about a ציבור *tzibur*. Difference
between things about Jews versus non-Jews. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* goes like this. It is about exactly across the line on
the top of רבינו חננאל *Rabbeinu Chananel* on the
right hand margin. The line starts with the word דמיא *damya*. And
then there's a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Okay, so it's about ten lines
down in the medium-sized lines. Exactly ten lines down in the medium-sized
line. Okay. שאו שערים ראשיכם והנשאו פתחי עולם ויבא מלך Melech. הכבוד
*Se'u she'arim rasheichem vehinas'u pitchei olam veyavo Melech Hakavod*. So there you
got מלך *Melech*. מי זה מלך הכבוד ה' עזוז וגבור *Mi zeh
Melech Hakavod Hashem izuz vegibor*.
So that's מלך *Melech* twice. ה' גבור מלחמה שאו שערים ראשיכם ושאו
פתחי עולם ויבא מלך הכבוד *Hashem gibor milchama se'u she'arim rasheichem use'u
pitchei olam veyavo Melech Hakavod*. That's מלך *Melech* three times. מי הוא
זה מלך הכבוד *Mi hu zeh Melech Hakavod*. That's four times. ה'
צבאות הוא מלך הכבוד סלה *Hashem tzeva'ot hu Melech Hakavod selah*. Five
times. Okay. Well, it's since anyway, you only need three from כתובים
Ketuvim, *Ktuvim*, but that already gets you five. So let's take a
look. ראשונה שתים שניה שלוש דברי רבי יוסי divrei Rabbi Yose. *Rishona
shtayim shniya shalosh divrei Rabbi Yose*. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose *Rabbi
Yose* says, like we assumed, the first פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, half of
the first פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is two, שאו שערים ראשיכם ויבא מלך
הכבוד מי זה מלך הכבוד *Se'u she'arim rasheichem veyavo Melech Hakavod mi
zeh Melech Hakavod*. And then the next פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, שאו שערים
ראשיכם ושאו פתחי עולם ויבא מלך מי זה מלך ה' צבאות הוא
מלך *Se'u she'arim rasheichem use'u pitchei olam veyavo Melech mi zeh Melech
Hashem tzeva'ot hu Melech* is three. So you could use one פסוק
pasuk, *pasuk* to get you two, you could use the second פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* to get you three. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר ראשונה
אחת שניה שתים *Rabbi Yehuda Omer rishona achas shniya shtayim*. No, the
first one only counts for one and the second only for two,
because within the פסוקים psukim *psukim* are questions. מי הוא זה מלך
הכבוד *Mi hu zeh Melech Hakavod*. מי זה מלך הכבוד *Mi zeh
Melech Hakavod*. So it's not yet identifying, although you could say it's
rhetorical, but it's not yet identifying God as מלך *Melech*. So the
question מי זה מלך הכבוד *mi zeh Melech Hakavod* does not count
as one of the מלכויות malchuyot. *Malchuyos*. Okay. But what is interesting
is that you could have one פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that counts as
more than once. That if you have multiple mentions in a פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*, it could count for two, even though so it's not
just x number of פסוקים psukim *psukim*, it's really x number of
mentions within the פסוקים psukim *psukim*. Okay. זמרו אלהים זמרו זמרו למלכנו
זמרו כי מלך כל הארץ אלהים שתים דברי רבי יוסי divrei Rabbi
Yose. *Zimru Elohim zamru zamru le'malkeinu zamru ki melech kol ha'aretz elohim
shtayim divrei Rabbi Yose*.
So again, מלכנו *malkeinu* and מלך כל הארץ *melech kol ha'aretz*. דברי
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Divrei Rabbi Yose*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda? אומר
אחת *Rabbi Yehuda omer achas*, one. Now why only one? Because רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says מלכנו *malkeinu* is only our God, and the idea
here is מלך על כל הארץ *melech al kol ha'aretz*. So therefore
it doesn't count. So interestingly, although you could focus on ישראל Yisrael,
*Yisrael* when it comes to the issue about, you know, bad things
and if it's a bad זכרון *zichron* for the non-Jews you can
say it and so on, when it comes to the issue of
מלכות malchut, *malchus*, that has to be universal.
Or at least according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. והשוין
במלך אלהים על גוים אלהים ישב על כסא קדשו שהיא אחת *V'shavin
bemolach elohim al goyim elohim yashav al kisei kodsho she'achas*.
That's only one. First of all it's על גוים *al goyim*, so
it's the whole world, and number two, sitting on the throne, although
it evokes the idea of kingship, is not actually the language of
מלך *Melech*. So that only counts as one. זכרון שיש בו תרועה
truah. כגון שבתון זכרון תרועה zichron truah מקרא makrei, קדש אומרים עם
הזכרונות ואומרים עם השופרות דברי רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi? *Zichron sheyeish bo
teruah kegon shabbaton zichron teruah mikra kodesh omrin im hazichronos v'omrin im
hashofros divrei Rabbi Yose*.
You can double purpose it. You can repeat that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
and have it once to count for זכרון *zichron* and then again
to count for a תרועה truah *teruah*. דברי רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
*Divrei Rabbi Yose*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* consistently seems to have narrower definitions here
than רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, *Rabbi Yose*. אינו אומר אלא עם הזכרונות
בלבד *Eino omer ela im hazichronos bilvad*. You only say it by
the זכרונות Zichronot, *zichronos*. Now why? So you could say, you know,
why not say it only in the תרועות teruot. *teruos*? So say
you get to choose one but you can't do it twice. So
רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* says the reason is because the word תרועה truah
*teruah* is not the word of שופר shofar *shofar*. And as we
know, תרועה truah. *teruah* even appears by חצוצרות chatzotzrot *chatzotzrot*. So therefore
he discounts that as counting for שופר shofar. *shofar*, it can only
count for זכרון *zichron*. מלכות malchut שיש בו תרועה truah *Malchus sheyeish
bo teruah*. How about a similar case by מלכות malchut. *malchus*? כגון
ה' אלהיו עמו ותרועת מלך בו *Kegon Hashem Elokav imo uteruas melech
bo*. אומרים עם המלכויות ואומרים עם השופרות דברי רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
*Omrin im hamalchuyos v'omrin im hashofros divrei Rabbi Yose*. Again רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi Yose* says you could use it twice. דברי רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi *Divrei Rabbi Yose*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אומר אינו
אומר אלא עם המלכויות בלבד *Rabbi Yehuda omer eino omer ela im
hamalchuyos bilvad*. Only מלכויות malchuyot *malchuyos*. Again רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says for
the same reason because תרועה truah. *teruah* here does not explicitly say
שופר shofar, *shofar*. And that actually we see now explicitly discussed in
this third case. תרועה truah שאינה עמה לא כלום *Teruah she'eini ima
lo klum*. The word תרועה truah. *teruah* by itself. כגון יום תרועה
יהיה לכם yom truah yihiyeh lachem *Kegon yom teruah yiheyeh lachem*. Okay,
which is a pretty relevant פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*.
אומרים עם השופרות דברי רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
*Omrim im hashofros divrei Rabbi Yose*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, אומר אינו
אומר כל עיקר *Rabbi Yehuda omer eino omer kol ikar*. You can't
even say the very פסוק *pasuk* that it says by ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*, זכרון תרועה zichron teruah, *zichron teruah*, יום תרועה
Yom Truah, *yom teruah*, can't count for שופרות shofrot *shofros* because it
doesn't say שופר shofar *shofar*. Okay, so quite interesting. It has to
specifically emphasize the שופר shofar *shofar* aspect of it, not the תרועה
truah *teruah*. Which does raise an interesting question. Since the תורה Torah,
*Torah* characterizes it as a יום תרועה yom truah *yom teruah* and
a זכרון תרועה truah. *zichron teruah*, right, even though we learn out
from יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* the idea of שופר shofar *shofar*, why
didn't we have the third ברכה bracha, *bracha* be תרועות teruot. *teruos*?
Why is the third ברכה bracha *bracha* שופרות shofrot *shofros*? Right? So
it is interesting, maybe דווקא *davka* to underscore that no, חז"ל *Chazal*
are telling us it's a שופר shofar *shofar* and we need to
be... Focus on that, maybe because there’s a lot of other פסוקים
psukim about שופר shofar that we want to specifically evoke. There’s also
an interesting question of the difference between תקיעה tkiya and תרועה. truah
You know, the רמב״ן Ramban discusses, we’ll discuss the exact way we
do the מצוה mitzvah later, but the רמב״ן Ramban discusses from a
Kabbalistic idea that like תקיעה tkiya is מדת הרחמים midas harachamim and
תרועה teruah is מדת הדין. midas hadin. Like תרועה teruah. is like
the staccato, it’s like more some sense of like, I don’t know,
like being hit or something. It’s not as victorious as the as
the as the תקיעה, tkiya, if you think, if you look in
the פסוקים psukim. by בהעלותך, Bhaaloscha, right, or it’s more like wailing
and crying out, which we know is the language of תרועה. teruah.
If you look in בהעלותך Bhaaloscha where it discusses the חצוצרות Chatzotzros
and how they’re used differently.
The שברים shvarim is like a wail.
Yeah, but שברים shvarim and תרועה teruah are like the same, because
it’s just a question of how to interpret תרועה. teruah
So, I mean, on the one hand, so the תקיעה tkiya is
used to gather the camps, right, and תרועה teruah is used to
move them forward, so I’m not sure that exactly matches. But anyway,
it says: וכי תבאו מלחמה בארצכם והרעתם בחצצרות. V’chi-tavo’u milchamah b’artzechem vaharei’otem
bachatzotzrot.
So when there’s a war, it’s תרועה. teruah וביום שמחתכם ותקעתם בחצצרות.
Uvyom simchatchem utkatem bachatzotzrot. And שמחה simcha is תקיעה. tkiya.
So
that clearly seems to indicate a difference there. So it could be
that even though it’s a יום תרועה, teruah which according to this
idea is like a יום הדין Yom HaDin and so on, maybe
we didn’t want to overemphasize the תרועה teruah, aspect, right, because of
that more negative connotation, so therefore the emphasis of it as שופרות
Shofaros, and not as a תרועה. teruah Which also again שופרות Shofaros?
allows you to quote פסוקים psukim by הר סיני, Har Sinai, gives
you a wider range of פסוקים psukim to be quoted. Okay. אם
השלים מתחיל בתורה ומשלים בנביא. Im hishlim, matchil b'Torah umashlim b'Navi. רבי
יוסי אומר אם השלים בתורה יצא. Rabbi Yose omer im hishlim b'Torah
yatza.
So
the גמרא Gemara says: אם השלים, im hishlim, בדיעבד, b'diavad, אבל לכתחילה
לא? aval l'chatchila lo?
What do you mean, but if you finish with תורה, Torah. only
בדיעבד? b'diavad? והתניא Ve'h tanya רבי יוסי אומר המשלים בתורה הרי זה
משובח? Rabbi Yose omer hamashlim b'Torah harei zeh meshubach?
You should end with תורה. Torah אימא
משלים. Eima mashlim. So fine, change the text, it says אם השלים
im hishlim and it says and you should be משלים. mashlim. Of
course they’re a bit forced because it also says the word יצא,
yatza, which means בדיעבד. b'diavad. So the גמרא Gemara says: והא אם
השלים תני? Ve'ha im hishlim tni?
You can’t do that, it says 'if you finish'. בדיעבד, b'diavad, אין
לכתחילה לא? in l'chatchila lo? הכי קאמר: Hachi ka'amar: מתחיל בתורה ומשלים
בנביא. matchil b'Torah u'mashlim b'Navi.
You start with תורה Torah. and end with נביא. Navi. רבי יוסי
אומר
משלים בתורה ואם השלים בנביא יצא. Rabbi Yose omer mashlim b'Torah ve'im
hishlim b'Navi yatza.
So we again we alter the text to have רבי יוסי saying
בדיעבד b'diavad if it’s נביא Navi you’re יוצא, yotzei,
but you should end with תורה. Torah. And that’s what we do,
we have three of each and then we end with a tenth
פסוק of תורה. Torah. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we have
a ברייתא baraita similarly, אמר רבי אליעזר בר רבי יוסי ותיקין היו
משלימין אותו
בתורה. Amar Rabbi Eliezer bar Rabbi Yose: vatikin hayu mashlimin oto b'Torah.
The ותיקין, vatikin, like, you know, an ancient tradition or the particularly
פרום frum ones would end with a פסוק in the
תורה. Torah. בשלמא Bishlama זכרונות ושופרות shofrot איכא טובא. ika tuvah.
There’s plenty of פסוקים psukim. by זכרונות and שופרות Shofaros even in
the תורה. Torah, אלא מלכויות, Ela malchuyot,
but if we’re now going to have to have three of תורה,
Torah, three of כתובים, three of נביאים Nevi'im and end with תורה,
Torah we’re going to need four פסוקים psukim, of תורה Torah? from
each category. So מלכויות, malchuyot. תלתא דהויין. tlata de'haviyan.
There’s only three מלכויות. malchuyot. What are the three מלכויות malchuyot. in
the תורה? Torah ה׳ אלהיו עמו ותרועת מלך בו, Hashem Elokav imo
utruat melech bo, ויהי בישורון מלך, vayehi b'Yeshurun melech, and ה׳ ימלך
לעולם ועד. Hashem yimloch l'olam va'ed.
And if you’re going to need to be משלים בתורה, mashlim b'Torah,
you’re going to need a fourth פסוק of מלכויות. Malchuyot, ואנן בעינן
עשר וליכא? V'anan be'inan asar v'leka? And
we’re going to need ten, which we wrapped up by מלכויות. שבע
הויין? Shva havyan? אמר רב הונא תא
שמע,
Amar Rav
Huna ta shema, come here, we have a ברייתא: baraita: שמע ישראל.
Shma Yisrael. תא שמע, Ta shema, שמע ישראל ה׳ אלהינו ה׳ אחד,
Shma Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad, מלכות, malchut. דברי רבי
יוסי. That counts as מלכות malchut? because it’s God as king and
as singular king presumably over the whole world. Not king, God, but
the singular God over the whole world evokes an idea of מלכות.
malchut. Again, interesting because until now we’ve been very exacting and demanding
the exact term. Even God sitting on the throne isn’t a מלכות.
malchut.
Is this the primary location in ש״ס Shas of that association that
שמע Shma is מלכות?
malchut Yeah, that
שמע Shma is associated with מלכויות.
Yeah, yeah, this is in the קריאת שמע, krias shma, it’s just
using this פסוק about מלכות. malchut.
Right, but it’s also such a foundational
association, right, that it’s about קבלת עול מלכות שמים. kabbalas ol malchus
shamayim. Yeah, exactly. קבלת עול... kabbalas ol... that’s a good point, קבלת
עול מלכות שמים kabbalas ol malchus shamayim is a phrase that’s used
in other contexts about שמע, Shma, so you’re right, I hadn’t thought
about that but you’re right, the association with it of עול מלכות
שמים ol malchus shamayim is a is a מלכות. malchut.
Right, but it’s not a mention of מלכות malchut, anywhere.
Right, that is a good point, the עול מלכות שמים ol malchus
shamayim is that theme of מלכות. malchut. That’s a good point. Yep.
רבי יהודה אומר אינה מלכות. Rabbi Yehuda omer einah malchut. Now we
know רבי יהודה is more restrictive, so he’s not prepared to count
this as מלכות. Malchus Okay, now
but we’re a little stuck, we need a fourth. וידעת היום והשבת
אל לבבך כי ה׳ הוא האלהים אין עוד. V'yadata hayom vahashevota el
l'vavecha ki Hashem hu ha'Elokim ein od. So again, God is the
only God, מלכות, Malchus דברי רבי יוסי. רבי יהודה אומר אינה מלכות.
Rabbi Yehuda omer einah malchut. It’s not מלכות. Malchus אתה הראת לדעת
כי ה׳ הוא האלהים אין עוד מלבדו. Ata hareita ladaat ki Hashem
hu ha'Elokim ein od milvado. Oh, the only God... Which is like,
okay, so what do you do for רבי יהודה? So it doesn't
exactly tell us. By the way, it does raise an interesting question
of what the point of מלכות Malchus is. Is the point of
מלכות Malchus basically like there are no other gods, God is the
singular God and maybe in the sense also of the evoking of
creation, God created the world, God is all powerful?
So then you get it from those פסוקים. p'sukim If מלכות Malchus,
also suggests an idea of
דין, din, of the king as sort of power
over his subjects, then some of these פסוקים psukim like שמע ישראל
ה' אלקינו ה' אחד Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu Hashem Echad don't exactly
evoke that same sense. So I think there's also a question here
about what the idea of מלכות Malchus, is. So anyway, if you
want to look at what we actually do, right? So because we
incorporate מלכות with קדושת היום kedushas hayom as we've been saying, so
we start with אתה זכרתנו Atah zachartanu and then we say מקרא
קדש יהיה לכם, mikra kodesh yihiyeh lachem, right? That's actually מוסף. Musaf.
Because it's מוסף Musaf we're also
going to have the קדושת היום kedushas hayom is also going to
have the קרבנות korbanos of מוסף. Musaf. So we have ומנחתם ונסכיהם
ובחודש השביעי Uminchasam veniskeihem uvachodesh hashvii and then we do עלינו לשבח
לאדון הכל, Aleinu leshabei'ach la'adon hakol, right? And עלינו Aleinu used to
only be in the מוסף שמונה עשרה, Musaf Shmoneh Esrei, here it
got extracted, right? And then it goes, ואנחנו כורעים ומשתחוים לפני מלך
מלכי המלכים. V'anachnu korim umishtachavim lifnei Melech Malchei HaMelachim. So עלינו Aleinu
introduces מלכות, וידעת היום והשבות כי ה' הוא האלקים בשמים ממעל ועל
הארץ מתחת אין עוד, Veyadata hayom vehasheivosa ki Hashem hu ha'Elokim bashamayim
mima'al veal ha'aretz mitachas ein od, which is one of the פסוקים
psukim. we just quoted here; that's the end of the first פסוק,
but it doesn't yet say מלך. על כן נקוה Al kein nekaveh
etc., okay, where was it? לפניך... ככתוב בתורתך ה' ימלוך לעולם ועד.
lifanecha... kakatuv beTorasecha Hashem yimloch le'olam va'ed. So that's one that everybody
can agree on. ונאמר לא הביט און ביעקב ולא ראה עמל בישראל
ה' אלקיו עמו ותרועת מלך בו. Vene'emar lo hibit aven beYaakov velo
ra'ah amal beYisrael Hashem Elokav imo utru'as melech bo. ונאמר ויהי בישורון
מלך בהתאסף ראשי עם יחד שבטי ישראל. Vene'emar vayehi biYishurun melech behis'asef
roshei am yachad shivtei Yisrael. So those are the three we know
of, plus the כי ה' הוא האלקים ki Hashem hu ha'Elokim which
was debated. ובדברי קדשך כתוב לאמר ועל ידי עבדיך כתוב לאמר ובתורתך
כתוב לאמר שמע ישראל ה' אלקינו ה' אחד. Uvidivrei kodshecha kasuv leimor
v'al yedei avadecha kasuv leimor uvTorasecha kasuv leimor Shema Yisrael Hashem Elokeinu
Hashem Echad. Okay, so in the end we obviously get back to
the שמע ישראל. Shema Yisrael. Okay. By the way, I should also
say because we're going to be discussing the לימוד limud from חצוצרות
Chatzotzros when we get to שופרות, Shofaros, right? What are the ones
we say by שופרות? Shofaros, So we start with אתה נגלית בענן
כבודך Atah nigleisa ba'anan kevodecha evoking הר סיני, Har Sinai, right? And
then there's a lot of שופרות Shofaros about הר סיני. Har Sinai.
ויהי קול שופר חזק מאד. Vayehi kol shofar chazak me'od. ויהי קול
השופר הולך וחזק מאד. Vayehi kol hashofar holeich vechazeik me'od. וכל העם
רואים את הקולות ואת הלפידים ואת קול השופר. Vechol ha'am ro'im es
hakolos ve'es halapidim ve'es kol hashofar. ובדברי קדשך כתוב לאמר ועל ידי
עבדיך כתוב לאמר אלקינו ואלקי אבותינו תקע בשופר גדול לחרותנו ושא נס
לקבץ גלויותינו וכו' כאמור וביום שמחתכם ובמועדיכם ובראשי חדשיכם ותקעתם בחצוצרות על
עולותיכם. Uvidivrei kodshecha kasuv leimor v'al yedei avadecha kasuv leimor Elokeinu v'Elokei
avoseinu teka b'shofar gadol lecheirusenu vesa nes lekabetz galuyoseinu etc. kaamur uveyom
simchaschem uvemoadeichem uveroshei chodsheichem uskatem bachatzotzros al olosaychem. So since חצוצרות Chatzotzros,
serve as a basis for some of the ideas, even though it's
a חצוצרות, Chatzotzros. we quote that at the end of שופרות, Shofrot,
okay? כי אתה שומע קול שופר ומאזין תרועה ואין דומה לך ברוך
אתה ה' שומע קול תרועת עמו ישראל ברחמים. Ki Atah shomei'a kol
shofar uma'azin teruah ve'ein domeh lach baruch Atah Hashem shomei'a kol teruas
amo Yisrael berachamim. So it's quite interesting that we have as the
last of the שופרות, shofrot we have the פסוק of the חצוצרות.
So, right, so that's pretty fascinating, right? That the פסוק that actually
is ובתקעתם בחצוצרות על עולותיכם ועל זבחי שלמיכם והיו לכם לזכרון. usekatem
bachatzotzros al olosaychem ve'al zivchei shalmeichem vehayu lachem lezikaron. So that is...
the גמרא Gemara, doesn't point that out, but we don't only do
something a little bit questionable in terms of the last פסוק by
the מלכות, we do it by the שופרות shofrot as well. We
get through this other פסוק וביום שמחתכם. uveyom simchaschem. Okay, so let's
take a look now at the משנה. Mishnah. העובר לפני התיבה ביום
טוב של ראש השנה. Ha'over lifnei hateivah beyom tov shel Rosh Hashanah.
So somebody is now the person who passes in front of the
ark, meaning the one who is leading the שמונה עשרה, Shmoneh Esrei,
the בעל שחרית, Ba'al Shacharis, the בעל תפילה, Ba'al Tefillah, the שליח
ציבור. shliach tzibbur. השני מתקיע. hasheini maski'a. So the second one is
the בעל תוקע, Ba'al Tokeia, which basically indicates that you do the
תקיעות tekios during מוסף. Musaf. ובשעת ההלל, Ubishas haHallel, at a time
when there's הלל—not Hallel on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah? we don't say
הלל—but Hallel when you do say הלל, Hallel, הראשון מקרא את ההלל.
harishon makrei es haHallel. Okay, whatever. Anyway, מקרא, makrei, מקרא, yeah. Okay.
The first one is the one that reads the הלל, Hallel, recites
the הלל, Hallel, because you say הלל Hallel with שחרית, Shacharis, as
we know we do; the בעל שחרית, Ba'al Shacharis, שחרית, Shacharis, חזרת
הש"ץ Chazaras haShatz flows right into הלל. Hallel. Okay. So here we
have it in—here we have that the תקיעה tekiah is in מוסף
Musaf and the question is going to be why. In terms of
the difference עובר over as opposed to היורד, hayoreid, I've read some
articles on that. It has to do with—I'm trying to remember what
it has to do with, with where the ארון aron was and
whether the ארון aron was like elevated and—I don't know. It has
to do with some changing המעמקים. Hamamakim. Yeah, yeah, but right, but
some changing that idea that you would, I think, read from an
actual like depression. in the ground, I don't think is evident in
the, in the, you know, synagogues that they've uncovered from the, from
the, you know, turn of the, from the turn of the millennium
period, you know, from the תנאיטיק Tannaitic period. I think part of
the difference has to be where the, whether there was an ארון
Aron and when the ארון Aron was brought in and where the
ארון Aron was situated, whether it's called יורד לפני התיבה Yored Lifne
HaTeiva or עומד לפני התיבה. Omed Lifne HaTeiva. There's an article that
I read that I just don't remember the particulars about that. This
משנה Mishnah have implied that they said הלל Hallel on ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashanah. No, no, that's why it says ובשאר ההלל u'bishar haHallel
meaning at a time when you will be saying הלל, Hallel, not
now. Okay, otherwise it would have said הראשון מקריא את ההלל harishon
makria et haHallel והשני vehasheini you know, does the תקיעה, tkiyah, but
there is no הלל Hallel now. Okay, and we have a מקריא
הלל, makria Hallel, we talk about קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema because they
were, they read it from a קלף. klaf. So always קריאת הלל,
Kriyat Hallel, why is that the verb? Well, I mean it is
reading פסוקים. But I thought the תפילות tfillot were recited by heart
basically. You mean does it have a sense that it's being read
from a קלף? klaf? It's always the verb basically, קרא את ההלל.
kro et haHallel. Yeah, it's interesting. I don't know. I don't know.
It's a good question. Okay, מאי שנא שני מתקיע? mai shna sheini
matkia? Why do you do it at מוסף? Musaf? משום דברוב עם
הדרת מלך. mishum de'berov am hadrat melech. You want everybody to be
in שול shul by then. Okay, which is, it's always fascinating whether
the שול shul decides to have the תקיעות tkiyot and then do
the rabbi speak, or first do the rabbi speak and then have
the תקיעות. tkiyot. Which one one they really want to make sure
everybody is there for. Okay, anyway, אי הכי ihachi says the גמרא,
Gemara if that's true, הלל נמי נימא בשני Hallel nami neima be'sheini
משום דברוב עם הדרת מלך. mishum de'berov am hadrat melech. So anytime
we have like a special thing to that day like הלל, Hallel,
you know, and especially if it's about the type of a communal
תפילה tfila or communal praise, whatever it is, let's do that at
מוסף Musaf too and get everybody there. אלא מאי שנא הלל דבראשון?
Ella mai shna Hallel de'berishon? Why do you do it during שחרית?
Shacharit? משום דזריזים מקדימים למצוות. mishum de'zrizim makdimim lemitzvot. You'd rather do
it earlier. So you, you know, you do מצוות mitzvot earlier rather
than later. So תקיעה נמי נעביד בראשון tkiyah nami naivid berishon משום
דזריזים מקדימים למצוות. mishum de'zrizim makdimim lemitzvot. So אמר רבי יוחנן בשעת
גזירת המלכות שנו. amar Rabbi Yochanan be'shat gzerat hamalchut shanu. Yeah, you're
right, this was taught when there was a edict from the government.
What does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says that it was forbidden
in order to, you know, to blow בשופר. be'shofar. So we had
to wait till the government spies left and we did it and
therefore we had to do it later. They got tired, you know,
they they spent two hours nothing was happening, three hours, four hours
nothing was happening, finally they left, so we did the תקיעות. tkiyot.
תוספות Tosafot gives a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says a even a better
explanation about that. If you take a look, בשעת גזירת המלכות שנו
be'shat gzerat hamalchut shanu says תוספות. Tosafot. ואף על פי שבטלה גזירת
המלכות, ve'af al pi shebatlah gzerat hamalchut, first of all, why don't
you say well nowadays there's no גזירת המלכות, gzerat hamalchut, let's move
it back to שחרית? Shacharit? He says לא עבדינן כמעיקרא, lo avidnan
ke'meikara, we don't go back אף על גב דזריזים מקדימים למצוות af
al gav de'zrizim makdimim lemitzvot דחשינן שמיחזיר דבר לקלקולו. de'chashinan she'mayachzir davar
le'kikulo. You know, maybe things will get bad again and we'll keep
it where it is. Okay, לפירוש הירושלמי ניחא טפי leperush haYerushalmi nicha
tfei דמפרש שם שדימו האויבים, de'mifaresh sham she'dimu haoyvim, it wasn't just
some edict not to blow the שופר. shofar, The enemies of the
Jews misinterpreted. They thought כנתאספו לתקוע, k'nit'asu litkoa, they thought everybody was
gathering and they were blowing the שופר, shofar. תרועת מלחמה. tru'at milchama.
So what do you do, you blow a שופר shofar as a
way of like calling people to gather and go to war. ועמדו
עליהם והרגום, ve'amdu aleihem ve'haragum, and it led to a, you know,
it led to them fighting against them and killing them. ולכך תיקנו
תקיעות וברכות במוסף u'lekach tiknu tkiyot u'vrachot be'Musaf דכי חזו דקרין בקריאת
שמע de'ki chazu de'krin biKriyat Shema ומתפללים וקורין בתורה וחוזרין ומתפללים ותוקעים.
u'mitpalelin ve'korin baTorah ve'chozrin u'mitpalelin ve'tokin. So they do all this שול
shul stuff first, אמרי בנימוסייהו הנהו עסקי, amri binimusei hinhu askin, ah
they're just doing their rituals, בחוקותם ובתורתם, be'chukotam u'v'toratam, and therefore we
don't, it's obviously they understand it properly. Now all these are very
secondary reasons. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi gives also a more intrinsic reason and
it quotes it, I think it ties it into the fact that
in the פסוקים, you know, they're connected to the קרבן מוסף. Korban
Musaf. The תרועה teruah. where it says, you know, יום תרועה teruah
זכרון תרועה teruah appears in the context of the מוספים Musafim and
it does raise, you know, the idea that if מוסף Musaf is
about like the identity of the day, it's about the קרבן korban
that's unique to the day and the identity of the day, you
want to do the תקיעות tkiyot during that, you know, period that's
also about, the תקיעות tkiyot are not just a מצווה mitzvah that
happens to fall today but it's about the identity, יום תרועה יהיה
לכם Yom Teruah yihiyeh lachem, and therefore you want to do it,
you know, at the time of the מוסף. Musaf. So the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi gives a more intrinsic reason to this, but you know, ברוב
עם הדרת מלך berov am hadrat melech works as well and that
certainly is true. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara. תוספות. Tosafot. In other
words your enemies are all all armed and waiting to attack you,
yeah, da da da. Exactly. All right, next משנה. Mishnah. Well, no,
תוספות Tosafot didn't say they're trying to find an excuse, he thought
they really misinterpreted. Okay, I'm sorry, not next משנה, Mishnah, גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, מי דקאמר בשעת ההלל mi de'ka amar be'shat haHallel מכלל דראש
השנה ליכא הלל. mikhlal de'Rosh Hashanah leika Hallel. Because it says when
you would say הלל, Hallel, it's clear that you don't say it
on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? אמר רבי אבהו
אמרו מלאכי השרת לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar Rabbi Abbahu amru malachei
hasharet lifne Hakadosh Baruch Hu, the heavenly angels said to God, ריבונו
של עולם Ribono Shel Olam מפני מה אין ישראל אומרים שירה לפניך
בראש השנה וביום כיפור? mipnei ma ein Yisrael omrim shirah lefanecha be'Rosh
Hashanah u'veYom Kippur? Why are they not singing your song? אמר להם
amar lahem he said to them, אפשר מלך יושב על כיסא דין
וספרי חיים וספרי מתים פתוחים לפניו וישראל אומרים שירה? efshar melech yoshev
al kise din v'sifrei chayim v'sifrei meitim ptuchim lefanav v'Yisrael omrim shirah?
Would it be appropriate where their whole lives are hanging in the
balance that they should be praising me? It's not a day, it's
a day of awe, it's not a day of שמחה, simcha, which
does raise interesting questions in general about attitudes. attitudes towards ראש השנה
Rosh Hashana. and to what degree is שמחה simcha appropriate for ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashana? There's a whole question, are you allowed to fast
on ראש השנה? Rosh Hashana. So, some פוסקים poskim said, yes, even
though normally you can't fast on יום טוב Yom Tov because of
שמחה, simcha, as a יום הדין, Yom HaDin, you are allowed to
fast and you see here that like the idea of awe and
דין din weighs out over against שמחה simcha just by the fact
that you don't say הלל. Hallel. Others said you're not allowed to
fast and they actually quoted another מדרש midrash and the מדרש midrash
says the angels say to God, God, why is it that or
it's not the angels singing to God, but anyway, it says like
a normal person he comes for דין din and he's dressed in
black and he's covered in ashes, but ישראל, they come and they're
dressed in their nice white clothes and in their clean clothes and
in like in this joyous approach because they're confident that הקדוש ברוך
הוא Hakadosh Baruch Hu will find, will be דן אותם לזכות. dan
otam l'zechut. So there's like this sense of awe but it's combined
with also a sense of, it's also a question of כבני מרון,
kidnei maron, like troops standing for inspection or like the sheep walking
at the mountain pass. How what exactly, how do you combine those
two types of themes? So this other מדרש midrash speaks about דוקא
davka it's a type of a דין din that we have a
sense of pride and joy and confidence in. So it raises as
interesting questions about which sort of theme dominates and as I say
there's a real question about people who wanted to fast all ראש
השנה. Rosh Hashana, And they tell a story that somebody said I
think it was to the בית הלוי, Beis HaLevi, רב יוסף דב
הלוי סולובייצ'יק, Rav Yosef Dov HaLevi Soloveitchik, not the רב, Rav, but
the רב's Rav's great-grandfather. Anyway, says, yeah, you rabbis you're also מחמיר,
machmir, like I'm sick of it. He says, what do you mean?
He says I'm a big מיקל. meikel. People say it's אסור assur
to fast on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, I think it's מותר. muttar.
Just like to give a couple of examples like that. Alright, anyway,
שופר של ראש השנה אין מעבירין עליו את התחום. shofar shel Rosh
Hashana ein ma'avirin alav et hat-chum. The שופר shofar, for ראש השנה,
Rosh Hashana, you cannot, again, so funny ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, יום
טוב של ראש השנה, Yom Tov shel Rosh Hashana, שופר של ראש
השנה, shofar shel Rosh Hashana, I mean what else, okay, but anyway,
שופר של ראש
השנה אין מעבירין עליו את התחום.
shofar
shel Rosh
Hashana ein ma'avirin alav et hat-chum. Even though it's a מצוה דאורייתא,
mitzvah d'Oraisa, you cannot carry it beyond the תחום tchum
in order to help somebody do the מצוה mitzvah or to bring
it into town ואין מפקחין עליו את הגל, ve-ein mefaktin alav et
hagal, you can't uncover if it's under a pile of stones ולא
עולין באילן, v'lo olim b'ilan, you can't go up a tree ולא
רוכבין על גבי בהמה, v'lo rochvin al gabei behema, you can't ride
a בהמה behema ולא שטין על פני המים, v'lo shatin al penei
hamayim, you can't swim, put like have a float and go get
it from some I don't know across the river. By the way,
you will notice that most of these things, עולין באילן, olim b'ilan,
רוכבין על גבי בהמה, rochvin al gabei behema, שטין על פני המים,
shatin al penei hamayim, is a משנה mishna we taught earlier in
ביצה Beitzah about the classic list of what is a שבות, shevut,
what is like a rabbinically type of a thing you can't do
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So here it's saying like even though
these are rabbinic, you still can't do it for the sake of
the מצוה. mitzvah.
ואין חותכין אותו בין בדבר שהוא משום שבות
ובין בדבר שהוא משום לא תעשה.
ve-ein chotchin oto bein bidavar shehu
mishum shevut
uvein bidavar shehu mishum lo ta'aseh. You can't cut it, meaning like
just to trim it, cut to like to shorten it, whether you're
doing something that's only a rabbinic prohibition, whether it's a biblical prohibition,
we'll see what that would be. אבל אם רצה ליתן לתוכו מים
או יין, aval im ratza litten letocho mayim o yayin, if you
want to put water or wine in it in order to clean
it out, ייתן, yitten, that you can do. There's no prohibition there.
אין מעכבין את התינוקות מלתקוע. ein ma'achivin et hatinokot militkoa. You don't
prevent the kids from blowing אבל מתעסקין עמהם עד שילמדו. aval mit'askin
imahem ad sheyilmedu. But you involve yourself with them until they learn.
So you can actively participate in and get them to blow in
order to learn how to blow. מתעסקין, mit'askin, now what does that
exactly mean? We'll unpack that. והמתעסק לא יצא. vehamit'asek lo yatza. If
you're just fooling around and you're maybe trying to help them but
you're not trying to do the מצוה, mitzvah, you don't fulfill your
obligation, gets back to the כוונה kavanah issue. והשומע מן המתעסק לא
יצא. vehashomea min hamit'asek lo yatza. And if you heard from somebody
that was not intending to do the מצוה mitzvah or just for
fooling around with it, then you also do not fulfill your
obligation, again going back
to the issue of כוונה. kavanah. So there's a lot in this
משנה, mishna, it's actually two or three משניות mishnayot placed, pasted together.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
Why can you not override יום טוב? Yom Tov? שופר עשה הוא
ויום טוב עשה ולא תעשה ואין עשה דוחה לא תעשה ועשה. shofar
asei hu ve-Yom Tov asei v'lo ta'aseh ve-ein asei docheh lo ta'aseh
ve-asei. So why you can't biblically violate, do a biblical violation, it's
clear. A positive מצוה mitzvah doesn't override a positive and a negative.
But how about a rabbinic? עולין באילן ולא רוכבין על גבי בהמה.
olim b'ilan v'lo rochvin al gabei behema. The גמרא Gemara says השתא
דרבנן אמרת לא, hashta d'rabbanan amrat lo, so once you say you
cannot do the דרבנן, d'rabbanan, דאורייתא מיבעיא? d'Oraisa miba'aya? Of course. What
do you mean בין משום שבות בין משום לא תעשה? bein mishum
shevut bein mishum lo ta'aseh? You can't do the דרבנן, d'rabbanan, certainly
you can't do the דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. Alright, זו אין צריך לומר זו
קתני. zu ein tzarich lomar zu ktanei. Yeah, fine, this and it
goes without saying that. But again, the גמרא Gemara doesn't seem to
need to justify why you cannot violate a דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Once it's
justified why you can't violate a דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, it's assuming that a
דרבנן d'rabbanan goes hand in hand. Right, once fundamentally שופר shofar, doesn't
override יום טוב Yom Tov at the דאורייתא d'Oraisa level, we're also
not going to let it override יום טוב Yom Tov at the
דרבנן d'rabbanan level.
Okay, now that's not always so obvious, like, for example, if you
think about on שבת, Shabbos, what can you do on
שבת Shabbos for צורך מצוה? tzorch mitzvah? So our general approach is
שבות דשבות. shevut d'shevut. But besides מילה, milah, like just in terms
of דרבנן, d'rabbanan, so since you can't violate שבת Shabbos in general
for a מצוה, mitzvah, but if it's a שבות דשבות. shevut d'shevut.
The position of the ערוך Aruch that says you can even override
שבת Shabbat for a single דרבנן d'rabbanan in order to do a
מצוה. mitzvah. Yeah, we can override a single דרבנן d'rabbanan for in
order to do a מצוה mitzvah in order to do a מצוה
mitzvah on שבת. Shabbat. So just because, you know, the יום טוב
Yom Tov itself is... the day itself, the biblical aspects can't be
overridden, it doesn't mean there wouldn't be scenarios where the rabbinic aspects
can be overridden. Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara doesn't feel a need to
justify that. Once we've explained why you can't override יום טוב, Yom
Tov, you can't override the דרבנן d'rabbanans as well, the שבותים shvutim
also in order to do the מצוה. mitzvah. How that fits into
the ערוך'ס Aruch's general sort of structure is not clear, but that's
what... but the גמרא Gemara doesn't even need to... doesn't need to
justify that.
Yeah,
I don't know if you want to go there, but before I
moved to Riverdale, I had several people, several questions, and the practice
of having the doorman push the button on the elevator was described
as a שבות דשבות, shvus d'shvus, in the way it works.
Right, because that's a... a non-Jew, so that's one דרבנן d'rabbanan and
the electricity when it's not involved a... like incandescent lights is generally
seen to be at most a דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So, but that's anyway,
that's other שבת Shabbos questions. But yeah, okay, moving on though. So
you don't override דאורייתא d'oraisas and somehow also not דרבנן. d'rabbanans. ואין
חותכין אותו בין בדבר שהוא משום שבות V'ein chotchin oso bein b'davar
she'hu mishum shvus דף לג עמוד א, Daf 33a,
finally to today's דף. ואין חותכין אותו בין בדבר שהוא משום שבות
ובין בדבר שהוא משום לא תעשה. V'ein chotchin oso bein b'davar she'hu
mishum shvus v'bein b'davar she'hu mishum lo sa'aseh. So the גמרא Gemara
says משום שבות, mishum shvus, a rabbinic way of trimming the שופר
shofar. would be מגל, magal, a type of a knife that's not
the normal knife you'd use. I don't know how they translate it
there. A sickle. So take a sickle to your שופר shofar is
a little unusual, so it's a שינוי. shinui. Okay, משום לא תעשה,
mishum lo sa'aseh, סכין, sakin, a normal knife, and then it's a
normal way of doing it, and it's a problem of תיקון כלי,
tikkun kli, you're fixing a something. So the גמרא Gemara says השתא
משום שבות אמרת לא, hashta mishum shvus amart lo, once you say
you can't do it rabbinically, לא תעשה מבעיא, lo sa'aseh mibaya, do
you have to tell me you can't do a biblical violation? זו
ואין צריך לומר זו קתני, zu v'ein tzarich lomar zu katani, same
point, fine, it goes without saying, once we said דרבנן d'rabbanan we'll
mention the דאורייתא. d'oraisa. אבל אם רצה להדיח יתן לתוכו מים או
יין, Aval im ratza l'hadiach yiten l'socho mayim o yayin, but you
can put liquid in it to clean it out. מים או יין
אין, Mayim o yayin in, water and wine yes, מי רגלים לא,
mei raglayim lo, not urine. So, I don't know, somehow the fact
that they're even thinking about it means that it would have done
a... some type of a good job in terms of cleaning. Maybe
it's the... the what do you call it? The... what does urine
have? Nitrogen? Or something? I don't know. Whatever... what? Yeah. Anyway, whatever
it has, they somehow... somehow they felt that it would have done
a good job, but nevertheless, it's not appropriate. So מתניתין מני אבא
שאול היא, Masnisin mani Abba Shaul hi, it's אבא שאול'ס Abba Shaul's
תנא. tanna. דתניא אבא שאול אומר מים או יין מותר כדי לצחצחו
D'tanya Abba Shaul omer mayim o yayin mutar k'dei l'tzachzacho because it
cleans it out. מי רגלים אסור מפני הכבוד, Mei raglayim assur mipnei
hakavod, it's not respectful for a שופר, shofar
a מצוה mitzvah object, to to have put urine through it. Same
with the... the
right, the קטורת. ketores. אין מעכבין את התינוקות מלתקוע. Ein m'akvin es
hatinokos miltkoah. Now we get to this issue about the kids, not
interfering with their desire to blow the שופר. shofar So the גמרא
Gemara first says
הנשים מעכבין, hanashim m'akvin, it would sound like women you prevent, meaning
not only are maybe women not obligated, which he's never explicitly said,
we sort of implicitly said, we did say it once when we
were dealing with יובל, Yovel, but anyway, but you wouldn't even let
them do it. Now, why should you not let women do it,
even if they're not obligated and, you know, even if you say
they get no שכר schar for it, what should be the problem?
So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi. רש"י Rashi says
a pretty extreme thing. רש"י rashi says the first narrow line: הנשים
מעכבין דפטורות לגמרי דמצות עשה שהזמן גרמא היא וכי תקעי איכא בל
תוסיף. Hanashim m'akvin d'pturos l'gamrei d'mitzvas aseh shehazman grama hi v'chi takei
ika bal tosef. There's
בל תוסיף. bal tosef. Do you remember we had a whole בל
תוסיף bal tosef discussion? So that's a pretty bizarre that it would
be בל תוסיף. bal tosef. First of all, it suggests that women
get no credit at all for doing it. And number two, בל
תוסיף bal tosef normally is "I'm doing the מצוה mitzvah and I'm
expanding it," not somebody who's not obligated is to it. So pretty
much all the ראשונים rishonim argue on רש"י. rashi Some want to
rephrase it as, "it's near to בל תוסיף." bal tosef. You know,
still, it's inappropriate you're... you're adopting something that's not relevant to you,
you're somehow expanding, you know, it's inappropriate you're expanding the normal boundaries
of the מצוה. mitzvah. Mostly though, ראשונים rishonim understand that the concern
more is the same type of a concern that, you know, might
apply to the kids as well, which is if the מצוה mitzvah
isn't relevant to you, then, you know, normally a שופר shofar. on
סוכות Sukkos would be מוקצה muktzeh and blowing it would be a...
like a making music on יום טוב Yom Tov which you're not
supposed to do. So it's not really a type of a בל
תוסיף bal tosef problem, but it's a problem that if it's not
relevant to you then there are possible other incidental issues that make
it inappropriate, which wouldn't mean that there's always a problem to do
a מצוה mitzvah that isn't relevant to you, but sometimes there might
be if it's, you know, and that gets to the issue that
the גמרא Gemara, is about to quote by סמיכה. smicha. So let's
take a look. והתניא, V'hanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, this
is one of very famous גמרות Gemaras about this issue of women's
relationship to time-bound מצוות. mitzvos. You know, even though they're פטור, patur,
what is... what is their potential relationship to it? But we taught
in a ברייתא, braisa, אין מעכבין לא את הנשים ולא את התינוקות
מלתקוע ביום טוב, Ein m'akvin lo es hanashim v'lo es hatinokos miltkoah
b'Yom Tov,
that you... you allow women to blow as well if they want
to. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult. הא רבי יהודה הא רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון, Ha
Rabbi Yehuda ha Rabbi Yosi v'Rabbi Shimon, it's a debate of רבי
יהודה on one side and רבי יוסי and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
on the other side. So בני ישראל Benei Yisrael do סמיכה smicha
on קרבנות korbanot and not בנות ישראל, benot Yisrael, women don't do
סמיכה smicha on קרבנות, korbanot, put their hands on it, דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's what רבי יהודה says. רבי יוסי ורבי
שמעון אומרים, Rabbi Yosi ve-Rabbi Shimon omrim, נשים סומכות רשות. nashim somchot
reshut. They're not obligated but they're allowed to. So this is a
debate: women's relationship to מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה—is mitzvot asei shehazman grama
it completely off-limits, or are they allowed to if they want? Now,
why should there be a problem even if they're not obligated? So
again, רש"י might say, בעל תוספות, Ba'al Tosafot, other ראשונים rishonim say
by the קרבן, korban, that if the קרבן korban is something that's
קדשים, kodshim, and by סמיכה smicha you put your weight on it,
you put your hands and you lean on it, that would be
inappropriate unless there would be a מצוה mitzvah type of a some
element of a מצוה mitzvah going on there. So this becomes the
question of: do we allow, like, you know, even if there are
some incidental secondary problems, do we allow women to do it, but,
you know, to do this מצוה mitzvah and ignore those secondary problems?
Now the question might be: if we do, if the answer is
yes, we do allow women, right? We—whatever—הלכה, halacha, why—how do you ignore
those secondary problems of מוקצה muktza or, you know, using קדשים kodshim
and so on? So there's two answers. One answer is כדי לעשות
נחת רוח לנשים. kedei la'asot nachat ruach lenashim. I mean, this comes
up in another סוגיא sugya as well—חגיגה—which Chagigah is: yeah, really it
is a problem but, you know, we want to make women feel
more included, so we weigh some of those rabbinic concerns. Okay, so
on the one hand, that's nice. It's a statement about inclusion and
the values of inclusion overriding some types of concerns. But on the
other hand, it doesn't intrinsically say something about women's relationship to the
מצוה. mitzvah. The stronger approach is to say: look, just because they're
exempt from the מצוה mitzvah doesn't mean they're excluded from the מצוה.
mitzvah. And if they actually do the מצוה, mitzvah, you know, it's
like אינו מצווה ועושה, eino metzuveh ve'oseh, they get שכר. schar. So
it's not like it's a problematic... they're actually blowing שופר, shofar. they
might as well be tooting a trumpet, but it makes them feel
good so we let them do it even though there's a מוקצה
muktza problem. No, if they choose to blow the שופר, shofar they're
doing the מצוה mitzvah of שופר. shofar It's optional, but they're still
doing the מצוה, mitzvah, and therefore those problems fall away. So that
becomes a very central question, and there's a lot of questions wrapped
up here. First of all, how do we פסקן? pasken? Like רבי
יהודה or like רבי יוסי? Right? Which way? Do women have that
allowance or not? So you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot, first
line, he says אמר רבינו תם, amar Rabbeinu Tam, אף על גב
דסתמא דספרא כרבי יהודה, af al gav desatama desifra ke-Rabbi Yehuda, although
there's a סתם משנה stam mishna or ספרא Sifra like רבי יהודה
that women don't do סמיכה, smicha, הלכה כרבי יוסי. halacha ke-Rabbi Yosi.
How do we know that women do do סמיכה? smicha? Number one:
דנימוקו עמו. denimuko imo. Normally we פסקן pasken like רבי יוסי because
we say רבי יוסי, his reason is with him—that's a general approach
that רבי יוסי knows what he's talking about—ומעשה רב. uma'aseh rav. There's
a precedent. Now מעשה רב ma'aseh rav normally means a rabbi acted
this way, so it wasn't just theoretical, it was actually practice. Let's
see what the precedent is. דמוציא תפילין מיכל בת שאול הייתה מנחת
תפילין. demotzi tefillin Michal bat Shaul hayata menachat tefillin. מיכל, Michal, the
daughter of שאול, Shaul, wore תפילין. tefillin. ואשתו של יונה הייתה עולה
לרגל, ve'ishto shel Yona hayata olah laregel, and יונה's Yona wife, famous
גמרא, Gemara. was עולה לרגל. olah laregel. I love it. That's מעשה
רב. ma'aseh rav. Who was the רב rav there? מיכל Michal and
יונה's Yona wife. They were the רב. rav. But anyway, but there
actually was precedent, not even in the rabbinic period, in the pre-rabbinic
period. Okay, וההוא עובדא דפרק אין דורשין דאייתינהו לעזרת נשים וסמכו עלייהו
נשים. ve-hahu uvda deperek ein dorshin de-aitinhu le-ezrat nashim ve-samchu aleihu nashim.
Another story, actually with the rabbis, where women did סמיכה smicha on
a קרבן korban and so on. So תוספות Tosafot says no, no,
no, we פסקן pasken that it's allowed. It's interesting, although רמב"ם Rambam
פסקנס, paskens, for example, that women do not do סמיכה, smicha, like
רבי יהודה, are not allowed to do סמיכה, smicha, רמב"ם Rambam says
like if a woman wants to put on ציצית, tzitzit, you know,
she can put it on and make a ברכה, bracha because it's
a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה, mitzvot asei shehazman grama, you know, it's
אינו מצווה ועושה. eino metzuveh ve'oseh. So somehow he split his vote,
רמב"ם. Rambam. But the first thing that's established is that we פסקן
pasken like רבי יוסי that if a woman wants to, they can.
But then the next question is—and that presumably overrides these secondary rabbinic
concerns—but then the remainder of this תוספות Tosafot is devoted to the
critical question of not just saying whether women does it and we
can ignore those secondary concerns, but you know what the remaining question
is? Is a woman going to make a ברכה bracha, when she
makes a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה? mitzvot asei shehazman grama? And תוספות
Tosafot basically tries to make a strong argument, although he goes back
and forth whether he can actually legitimately make that argument, that whether
women make the ברכה bracha? or not if they're not obligated. And
אשכנזי Ashkenazi practice is women do make a ברכה, bracha ספרדי Sefardi
practice is women do not. Now why do women make a ברכה?
bracha, How could they say וצונו vetzivanu if they're not מצווה? metzuveh?
This again gets to the question of what is the relationship to
מצות עשה שהזמן גרמה. mitzvot asei shehazman grama. So one answer is:
וצונו vetzivanu means כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. We personally as women weren't
commanded, but we the Jewish people were commanded. Okay, and that's what
it means, and again somewhat says that women are really a little
bit, you know, excluded, and but אהנמי, e-hanami, the ברכה bracha. is
still somehow relevant as part of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael. But there's
another approach in the ראשונים rishonim that says, like I was saying
before, that the exemption is not exclusion. So women also were commanded.
They might they can exempt themselves, right? They have an exemption, but
the exemption only comes after the fact that they are commanded. And
if they waive the exemption, then they once again, you know, get
into that category of being commanded. And not at the same level
as men, they can't be מוציא motzi men again because then they
do have the- they do have the exemption, but actually they can
are seen as fundamentally commanded as well, fundamentally commanded with an exemption.
So this raises these really important questions about women's obligation and when
they do a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא, mitzvot asei shehazman grama, how
much are they considered to be doing a מצוה, mitzvah, getting שכר
schar for a מצוה, mitzvah, even at some level מצווה metzuveh in
it that they could say the ברכה, bracha that it overrides other
concerns or how much not? And that's really like a major, major
issue. And I should say that for ספרדים, Sefardim, although רמב"ם Rambam
פוסקים, poskin, you know, women can blow the שופר shofar, and can
put on ציצית tzitzit and can do whatever, the רמב"ם Rambam says-
I might have missaid it before, I think I missaid it before.
The רמב"ם Rambam says you don't make a ברכה. bracha, I think
I said what I didn't mean- I misspoke. I'm sorry, I misspoke.
The רמב"ם Rambam says women do not make a ברכה bracha on
this since they're not מצווה. metzuveh. And you know, in ספרדי Sefardi
communities, I've noticed that women seem- and I think I've said this
before- feel much less motivated to do some of these מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמא, mitzvot asei shehazman grama, and I think it's since they're
not making a ברכה, bracha, the clear message, the strong, you know,
message which is not verbalized is this isn't really a מצוה. mitzvah.
I mean, I still remember for you, I still remember I was
once in a- at a- in a ספרדי Sefardi home for סוכות
Sukkot and I, you know, woke up in the morning and I
took לולב lulav and אתרוג- etrog or I came home from שול
shul and then I said to the בעלת הבית, baalat habayit, I
said, do you want to- here- and I just meant, look, do
you want to take it? She said, no, why would I want
to do that? Like, I was so shocked, you know? Why on
earth? Like completely not relevant to me. Now I think even that
being said, when it comes to שופר shofar on ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah. like, all women really, you know, see themselves as being מחויבות
mechuyavot and I think someone would be shocked to hear that they're
not actually technically חייבות. chayavot. But nevertheless, the making of the ברכה
bracha sends a very powerful message. So it is important that number
one, how do we פסקן, pasken, like רבי יוסי according to תוספות,
Tosafot, and even the רמב"ם Rambam who doesn't פסקן pasken like רבי
יוסי by קרבנות korbanot פוסקים poskin him by other מצוות. mitzvot. But
and number two, you know, so the other secondary concerns are waived.
And number two, but by saying women actually make a ברכה, bracha.
it's really sends this strong message that it's not just, oh, we
let you do this if you want to because it makes you
feel nice, but it really makes a strong point about this really
being a מצוה mitzvah for you- for you as well. Okay, so
that's very central, very important issues in our current religious life emerge
from this גמרא. Gemara Yeah, and the קידוש kiddush and the המוציא
Hamotzi on שבת. Shabbat. So קידוש kiddush is different because קידוש kiddush
is connected זכור zachor to שמור. shamor. So there are obviously some
time-bound מצוות mitzvot or מצה matzah because מצה matzah is connected to
the איסור issur of eating חמץ. chametz. So there are exceptions to
that rule, right? And she would be המוציאה? hamotzia? Yes, exactly. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אבל מתעסקין בהן- Aval
mitaskin bahen back to the issue of תינוקות, tinokot, about kids, letting
them blow the שופר shofar. and fool around with the שופר. shofar,
So the first thing said, you don't stop them. But the next
thing said, you actually actively involve yourselves in having them blow the
שופר. shofar, Okay. Now again, the issue might be on a normal
יום טוב, Yom Tov, a question of like making music on יום
טוב Yom Tov when it's not in the context of a מצוה.
mitzvah. Okay, so we just got through saying whether women can do
it, but how about kids? They're not doing- you know, for them
it's not a מצוה. mitzvah. Can they go ahead and be blowing
these musical instruments? So אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, אפילו בשבת,
afilu b'Shabbat, and not only- and this is the real shocker- not
only on יום טוב Yom Tov where for other people it is
a מצוה, mitzvah, but you even let them do this on שבת
Shabbat where it's no- nobody is doing the מצוה mitzvah today. תניא
נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it's taught similarly, מתעסקין בהן עד שילמדו
אפילו בשבת. mitaskin bahen ad sheyilmedu afilu b'Shabbat. ואין מעכבין את התינוקות
מלתקוע בשבת, V'ein me'akvin et hatinokot militkoa b'Shabbat, ואין צריך לומר ביום
טוב. v'ein tzarich lomar b'Yom Tov. So again, both statements, you can
actively involve yourself and you don't interfere. And even on שבת, Shabbat,
which is a real shocker, because it's one thing to say, you
know, on יום טוב Yom Tov where for everybody else it's a
מצוה, mitzvah, you can do it too, but on שבת Shabbat nobody
is doing it and we're going to let the kids do it.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, הגופא קשיא, hagufa kashya, and also
it's internally contradictory. אמרת Amart מתעסקין בהן עד שילמדו. mitaskin bahen ad
sheyilmedu. First you say you actively involve yourself, אפילו בשבת, afilu b'Shabbat,
אלמא לכתחילה אמרינן להו תקעו, al-ma l'chatchila amrinan leihu teka-oo, you say
לכתחילה l'chatchila we tell them to blow. We actually involve- actively involve
ourselves. והדר תנן, V'hadar tenan, and then it says אין מעכבין, ein
me'akvin, you don't interfere. עיכובא הוא דלא מעכבין. Ikuva hu d'lo me'akvin.
Interference we don't do. הא לכתחילה לא, Ha l'chatchila lo, but לכתחילה
l'chatchila we don't try to encourage them to blow. לא קשיא. Lo
kashya. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not
difficult. כאן בקטן שהגיע לחינוך כאן בקטן שלא הגיע לחינוך. Kan b'katan
shehigia l'chinuch, kan b'katan shelo higia l'chinuch. Is the קטן katan at
the age of חינוך chinuch or not? Now which way does this
go? So- so first I'll give you the easier answer. The easier
answer is before the age of חינוך, chinuch, then you know, it's
not really- we can actually actively, even though it's שבת Shabbat and
obviously nobody should be blowing the שופר shofar, on שבת, Shabbat, we
can actually encourage them to blow because you know, it's pre-חינוך, chinuch,
so there's not a concern of שבת Shabbat violation of rabbinic types
of things. Once they're at the חינוך chinuch age, then we don't
interfere, maybe normally as a parent your kid picks up מוקצה muktzah
you'll interfere, but today it's even though it's שבת, Shabbat, it's also
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah, So you don't interfere because נישט געפערלאך nisht
geferlach that they're blowing a שופר shofar on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah.
and there's a good idea there too that they're connecting to the
idea of שופר, shofar. but you won't interfere even though it's also
שבת. Shabbos. So you won't actively do it because it is שבת.
Shabbos. Okay, so that's one explanation. The other explanation goes the opposite
way. The opposite way is, no, for somebody pre-חינוך, Chinuch, we won't
interfere, but we won't be involved in it. For somebody at the
age of חינוך, Chinuch, there's yes, there's the חינוך Chinuch of שבת,
Shabbos, but there's also the חינוך Chinuch of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah,
So maybe we'll even encourage them to blow. Maybe we feel a
little deprived we're not hearing the שופר shofar in שול shul on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah so we'll try to encourage our kids to
blow the שופר. shofar Now, that is a little bizarre because, again,
how could we encourage them to do it if it is שבת?
Shabbos? But תוספות Tosafos nevertheless says maybe yes, there's שבת, Shabbos, but
it's also ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and maybe that gives us a
certain amount of latitude. I will say that in the שולחן ערוך,
Shulchan Aruch, you do not and there's a whole question here that
I didn't get into, some actually have the גרסא girsa of אמר
לו בשבת, amar lo b'Shabbos, not אפילו בשבת. afilu b'Shabbos. So in
שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, you do not have the גרסא girsa of
you do not have the פסק psak that gives any latitude on
שבת. Shabbos. What you do have is the פסק psak that gives
latitude on a normal יום טוב Yom Tov for kids to blow,
and the רמ"א Rama actually פסקענס paskens if it's not שבת, Shabbos,
then the רמ"א Rama פסקענס paskens clearly it makes more sense to
be actively involved with kids that are הגיע לחינוך. higia l'chinuch. Here's
a day that everybody's in the שול shul hearing the שופר, shofar,
even if the kid didn't make it to the שול, shul, you
can actively involve, you can blow the שופר, shofar encourage him to
blow the שופר, shofar you could blow the שופר shofar. for him.
You can do these things. Also a few days ago we learned
that you can make a ברכה bracha even when you're normally not
entitled for the sake of חינוך. Chinuch. So here once he's הגיע
לחינוך higia l'chinuch and it's not שבת, Shabbos, it's just יום טוב,
Yom Tov, you can actively be blowing the שופר. shofar לא הגיע
לחינוך—not. lo higia l'chinuch And this raises an important question. Is the
שופר—now shofar it's not מוקצה muktzah because you can always use it
for somebody who hasn't yet heard the תקיעות. tekios. But are you
allowed to blow the שופר shofar for fun on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah, after you've heard the תקיעות tekios in שול? shul? Does the
general prohibition of making music on יום טוב Yom Tov revert after
you've done the מצוה mitzvah or is it only like overriding during
the doing of the מצוה mitzvah or anything that's part of the
מנהג, minhag, the מאה קולות, meah kolos, anything that's for the sake
of the מצוה? mitzvah? But as soon as it's you're done, I'm
just fooling around, I got a שופר, shofar it's ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah. toot toot, I'm having fun, maybe that's אסור assur because it's
making music on יום טוב. Yom Tov. What about ללמד? lelamed? ללמד
lelamed is included in like this idea of מתעסקין misaskin and legitimate.
So the רמ"א Rama basically rules, that is correct, it is forbidden.
You cannot just fool around and blow your שופר shofar. for fun
on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah The ט"ז Tas argues. The ט"ז Tas
says on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, the שופר shofar cannot be considered
problematic in any way, like any type of blowing is okay. But
the רמ"א Rama rules it is problematic and therefore the רמ"א Rama
rules, that's the חידוש chiddush of what we're saying here. Forget the
שבת Shabbos aspect which complicates it, but at least what we're saying
is that if you're not doing a מצוה, mitzvah, then you can't
be blowing a שופר. shofar.
However, if you are doing it for kids that are the age
of חינוך Chinuch and it's about חינוך Chinuch and it's about creating,
even if it's not technically teaching how to do it, just creating
a שופר shofar experience on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah then that's legitimate.
מתעסקין בהם עד שיכלו. misaskin bahem ad sheyichlu. Okay, so that raises
that interesting question of is there some general problem of blowing the
שופר shofar when it's not in a מצוה mitzvah or in a
חינוך Chinuch context? So you, the adult is going to have to
blow in order to teach the child? What? The adult is going
to have to show... Right, so that's the point. So that would
be okay. That would be okay. Right. So according to that read
that we're not talking about שבת, Shabbos, we're just talking about יום
טוב, Yom Tov, then מתעסקין בהם misaskin bahem could even mean that
you could blow it if it's in the all in the process
of חינוך. Chinuch. Right. ומתעסק לא יצא. umisasek lo yatza. If you're
just trying, you weren't trying to do the מצוה, mitzvah, you were
just trying to teach the kid or you were trying to, I
don't know, fool around and then you're not יוצא yotza because you
didn't have intent. The גמרא Gemara says התוקע לשיר. hatokea lashir. This
would seem to suggest that it's only because you're מתעסק. misasek. מתעסק
misasek means like it's completely incidental. But if you're trying to make
the right sounds but with a different intent, like you're doing it
for music, יצא. yatza. It sounds like you would be. מתעסק misasek
is like completely incidental. Only that not יצא. yatza. לימא מסייעא ליה
לרבא. leima mesayeia lei l'Rava. Let's say this supports רבא. Rava. דאמר
רבא, de'amar Rava, התוקע לשיר יצא. hatokea lashir yatza. If you're doing
it intentionally even if you're not doing it for the sake of
the מצוה, mitzvah, like you're doing it for music, you are יוצא.
yotza. The גמרא Gemara says no, דילמא תוקע לשיר נמי מתעסק קרי
ליה. dilma tokea lashir nami misasek kari lei. You don't know how
big the category of מתעסק misasek is. מתעסק misasek could mean anytime
you're not doing it for the מצוה, mitzvah, we're calling it מתעסק.
misasek. So you don't exactly know where to draw the line that
מתעסק misasek might mean if it's not being done for the מצוה
mitzvah you're not יוצא. yotza. הא שומע מן המתעסק לא יצא. ha
shomeia min hamisasek lo yatza. If you heard it from somebody who's
מתעסק, misasek, you're not יוצא. yotza. אבל aval the גמרא gemara, השומע
מן המשמיע לעצמו מאי. hashomeia min hamashmia l'atzmo mai. This gets to
another question of כוונה. kavana. Not כוונה kavana to do the מצוה,
mitzvah, but כוונה kavana to be מוציא motzi somebody. Because this seems
to indicate that the only problem is that the guy wasn't intending
to do the מצוה mitzvah and you heard his תקיעה. tekiah. But
if he was intending to do the מצוה mitzvah for himself, the
implication is you would be יוצא, yotza, even though he wasn't intending
to be מוציא motzi you. לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי זירא. leima tehvei
tiyuvta deRabbi Zeira. Even let's say this is a contradiction to רבי
זירא, Rabbi Zeira, דאמר ליה רבי זירא לשמעיה, d'amar lei Rabbi Zeira
l'shamaei, רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira told his attendant, איכווין ותקע לי, ikavein
u-tkah li, have כוונה kavanah to blow for me, it's not enough
to have כוונה kavanah to blow, you have to do it for
me to be מוציא motzi me, and that's not said in the
משנה. Mishna. Gemara says, no, דילמא איידי דתני רישא מתעסק תנא סיפא
נמי מתעסק. dilma ayidi d'tani resha mitasek tana seifa nami mitasek. Since
we talked about you blowing and you being מתעסק, mitasek, we talked
about somebody else hearing it and you being מתעסק, mitasek, but it's
actually if somebody actually wants to hear and be יוצא, yotzei, it's
not enough that you have כוונה kavanah to do the מצוה, mitzvah,
it could very well be you need כוונה kavanah to be מוציא
motzi him. Okay, so a really packed משנה Mishna there with these
issues about, you know, what's the nature of blowing the שופר shofar.
on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, after you've done the מצוה, mitzvah, what's
the whole issue with women and their relationship to שופר shofar and
מצוות עשה שהזמן גרמא mitzvat aseh she'hazman grama and תוספות's Tosafot whole
idea there also לברך, l'varech, so a lot there. Now we turn
to the actual act of blowing the שופר.
shofar, Let's take a look.
סדר תקיעות, seder tkiot, the way you do the תקיעות tkiot on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, שלוש של שלוש שלוש, shalosh shel shalosh shalosh,
three sets, מלכויות, זכרונות, and שופרות, so whatever, and each set is
made up of three sounds, תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. tekiah teruah tekiah. So
why we do, right, you know, you know, תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah
teruah tekiah, תקיעה שברים תקיעה, tekiah shevarim tekiah, whatever, we'll talk about,
but biblically שופר shofar. is nine קולות. kolot. Okay, תקיעה תרועה תקיעה
tekiah teruah tekiah three times. That's what it is. Okay, we're going
to learn from a פסוק, as I'll tell you, it says תרועה
teruah. three times. יום תרועה teruah יהיה לכם, זכרון תרועה, teruah twice
on ראש השנה, one by יובל, Yovel, והעברת שופר תרועה, v'ha'avarta shofar
teruah, so that we learn three תרועות. teruot, And we're going to
learn from other פסוקים that a תקיעה tekiah always comes before and
after a תרועה. teruah, So therefore that is going to get us
biblically nine קולות. kolot. Okay, so three sets of three each. So,
okay, now, שיעור תקיעה כשלש תרועות. shiur tekiah k'shalosh teruot. The length
of a תקיעה tekiah is the length of three תרועות. teruot Now
it's very obviously there's a big תוספות, Tosafot, very complicated exactly what
it's saying. I'll give you like one of the standard explanations. Standard
explanation is that not only is the length of a תקיעה tekiah
like three תרועות, teruot, but that three תרועות teruot. is the sound
of the תרועה. teruah So that's a תקיעה tekiah and the sound
of a תרועה teruah. is da-ta-ta, okay, or da-ta-ta. So that is
a תרועה teruah and they're the same length. So as one would
say in, in quantity and quality a תרועה teruah is a fragmented
תקיעה. tekiah. Right. Now again, the text isn't clear, our assumption is
the only difference between the תרועה teruah and the תקיעה tekiah is
how long the sound goes. There is a position of the רמב"ן
Ramban that maybe it's actually a different sound, like one is the
straight sound, the other is a wooh-wooh-wooh type of a sound. So
there is actually some questions, but we assume that the only difference
is how long it is. So a תקיעה tekiah equals three תרועות,
teruot, which again, we're going to assume that also means that to
make a תרועה teruah you have to make three תרועות. teruos. Okay.
שיעור תרועה כשלש יבבות. shiur teruah k'shalosh yevavot. And a תרועה, teruah?
each individual sound here is three beats. A יבבה yevavah is considered
to be a beat. Okay. So how, what is the minimum size
of a תרועה teruah of a dit, of a duh? It's the
size of whatever three beats is, okay, you know, so you can
figure out, I don't know, how much it is, but three tiny
little sounds. Okay. So that is the, that's the, but again, the
presumption is you're making one solid sound and three sounds a third
long, and each of these sounds is the length of three beats.
תקע בראשונה ומשך בשניה כשתים. takah b'rishonah u-mashach b'shniyah k'shtayim. Now here's
stuff we've seen before. If you made the one תקיעה, tekiah, the
first תקיעה tekiah of this set, and then for the second תקיעה,
tekiah, because each of these get a תקיעה tekiah before and after,
the second תקיעה tekiah here you did long enough that it's the
double length, right? Because this means a תקיעה tekiah is nine beats
according to this. And you did a תקיעה tekiah that was eighteen
beats. So let it count as the end of this תקיעה tekiah
and the beginning of that one. So no, אין בידו אלא אחת,
ein b'yado ela achat, it only counts as one, and we've seen
that before. Okay, you can't break up a תקיעה tekiah in the
middle. מי שבירך ואחר כך נתזמן לו שופר. mi she'berach v'achar kach
nitman lo shofar. Somebody made the ברכות brachot and then he got
the שופר. shofar, He didn't have the שופר shofar when he was
doing the ברכה. bracha Which ברכה berachah are we talking about? Not
the ברכה berachah. of לשמוע קול שופר lishmoa kol shofar because... מלכויות
זכרונות ושופרות, malchuyot zichronot veshofrot, which means that and this is key
again, according to the משנה mishnah everything we've seen, where does שופר
shofar occur? During שמנה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. During מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. malchuyot
zichronot veshofrot. אם אינו תוקע למה הוא מזכיר, im eino tokeia lama
hu mazkir, right? And the בעל המאור baal hamaor says it and
it occurs during שמנה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. Those were considered to be
the ברכות berachot of the שופר. shofar Giving the whole context, you
know sort of framing the שופר shofar was מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. malchuyot
zichronot veshofrot. In the גמרא, Gemara you do not have a ברכה
berachah אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו. asher kidishanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu. That developed afterwards
when we also developed the מנהג minhag of doing a series of
תקיעות tekios before שמנה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. So if you're not doing
it in the context of שמנה עשרה, shmoneh esrei, you're just doing
straight תקיעות, tekios, well we need a ברכה. berachah Let's come up
with a ברכת המצוה birchat hamitzvah אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו. asher kidishanu
b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu. Then it becomes a whole question is the גרסא girsa
לשמוע קול שופר lishmoa kol shofar or לתקוע litkoa or you know
or על תקיעת שופר? al tekiat shofar? What is exactly the מצוה?
mitzvah? But anyway but that developed once the שופרות themselves were stripped
out of the שמנה עשרה, shmoneh esrei, not removed from but you
know you have the שופרות without the enveloping ברכות. berachot. They exist
prior, what ברכה are we going to make? But that's not the
context of the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah is it's incorporated in
the ברכות berachot of the שמנה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. So therefore the
משנה mishnah asks a question, when it came to מוסף, musaf, you
didn't have a שופר, shofar so you went ahead you דאוונד davened
מוסף. musaf. So now מי שבירך ואחר כך נזדמן לו שופר. mi
shebeireich ve'achar kach nizdamen lo shofar. Now you've got a שופר. shofar.
What do you do? Maybe I shouldn't do the תקיעות tekios at
all? Maybe I only do it during שמנה עשרה? shmoneh esrei? So
says, let's just read it. So it says, so you went ahead
you דאוונד davened שמנה עשרה shmoneh esrei without the שופר, shofar, normally
they always come together. So what do you do? תוקע ומריע ותוקע
שלש פעמים. tokeia u-meiri u-tokeia shalosh peamim. So if you have to
you'll do the שופר shofar. naked from the שמנה עשרה. shmoneh esrei.
You'll do it without the ברכות. berachot. Notice by the way it
doesn't say now make a ברכה of לשמוע קול שופר. lishmoa kol
shofar. Okay again the משנה mishnah only knows of the ברכות berachot
of שמנה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. So if something happened and you didn't
have the שופר shofar and you דאוונד davened שמנה עשרה, shmoneh esrei,
so first of all you're יוצא yotzei שמנה עשרה shmoneh esrei without
the שופר shofar, and בדיעבד bedieved you're יוצא yotzei שופר shofar. without
the שמנה עשרה. shmoneh esrei. Go ahead and do the שופר shofar
by itself. כשם ששליח צבור חייב כך כל יחיד ויחיד חייב. k'shem
she'shliach tzibur chayav kach kol yachid v'yachid chayav. The same way the
שליח צבור shliach tzibur is obligated, every individual's obligated. Does that mean
in שמנה עשרה? shmoneh esrei? It maybe in the פשט pshat it
might also mean in the שופר. shofar If the שליח צבור shliach
tzibur is the one that is blowing the שופר, don't confuse it
to think that this is some communal obligation. No, it's a personal
obligation as well. רבן גמליאל אומר שליח צבור מוציא את הרבים ידי
חובתן. rabban gamliel omer shliach tzibur motzi et harabim yedei chovatan. Now
that already seems to be that we're not talking about the שופר.
That seems to be that we're talking about the שמנה עשרה. shmoneh
esrei. And then it would be saying the following because not people
did not have סדורים. siddurim. So there's a big problem with מלכויות
זכרונות ושופרות malchuyot zichronot veshofrot if people don't have סדורים. siddurim. How
the heck am I supposed to be able to know the פסוקים
to say? Okay so I'm supposed to memorize the שמנה עשרה, shmoneh
esrei, you know what, once a year I say it. So the
same first thing is don't think the שליח צבור, shliach tzibur, you
know, is the only one obligated. You've got to somehow say the
שמנה עשרה shmoneh esrei yourself. I don't know how you're going to
know the פסוקים. You've got to say it yourself. And רבן גמליאל
rabban gamliel says no no no. The שליח צבור shliach tzibur can
be מוציא motzi me. So this becomes the challenge of saying the
מוסף שמנה עשרה musaf shmoneh esrei with the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות malchuyot
zichronot veshofrot and we'll see that'll be the last סוגיא sugya we'll
do. We'll see how that unpacks. Okay, you wanted to say something
דוב? dov? I wanted to say the שופר without the ברכות, berachot,
the other way, you did not have a שופר, you went ahead
and said מוסף musaf without the שופר. Is that a ברכה לבטלה?
berachah levatalah? No, so that again that's what the משנה mishnah is
מחדש, mechadesh, that בדיעבד bedieved you can have מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות malchuyot
zichronot veshofrot without שופר and שופר without מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. malchuyot zichronot
veshofrot. It's a huge חידוש chiddush in both directions because we always
consider them to be intrinsically you know intertwined. Okay so let's take
a look. והתניא שיעור תקיעה כתרועה. vehatanya shiur tekiah k'teruah. One minute,
we have a ברייתא braita that says now the תקיעה tekiah equals
three תרועות, teruot, a תקיעה tekiah equals one תרועה. teruah So it
says אמר אביי תנא דידן כחשיב תקיעה דכולו בבי ותרועה דכולו בבי.
amar abaye tanna didan k'chasiv tekiah d'chulu bavi u-teruah d'chulu bavi. Our
תנא tanna is counting all of the תקיעות tekios and all of
the תרועות. teruot, ותנא ברא כחשיב חד בבא ותו לא. ve-tanna bara
k'chasiv chad bava ve-tu la. And the other תנא tanna is counting
one of the units. Now what the heck that means again is
unclear. רש"י seems to interpret it to mean that one is saying
you know a תקיעה tekiah equals, you know when we say a
תקיעה tekiah equals a תרועה teruah what we mean is one תקיעה
tekiah equals one תרועה teruah, the entire length. When we say a
תקיעה tekiah equals three תרועות, teruot. you know we mean maybe three
תקיעות tekios equal three תרועות, teruot like all these תקיעות tekios equal
all those תרועות. Or תקיעה tekiah equals the three voices of a
תרועה. teruah It's a very hard statement to unpack exactly what that
meant. Yes. Doesn't it mean that the length of a תרועה is
one third length of a תקיעה? tekiah? Yes. So right so you
could say exactly that's what I was trying to say which is
a תקיעה tekiah equals a תרועה means the entire the three sounds
combined the entire unit all combined and a תקיעה tekiah equals three
תרועות means each individual sound that's part of it. That's the easiest
thing to say. It doesn't sound like that's exactly how רש"י is
translating it, but that's the easiest thing to say that it equals
three if you count each. It equals the individual sounds of a
תרועה, it equals a תרועה if you count the entire length of
the תרועה. Okay. All right, let's just assume that's the explanation because
this is a notoriously difficult passage. Okay, and I'll just read one
more sentence and then we'll end. כי תרועה כג' יבבות, Ki teruah
k'gimmel yevavot, and each תרועה is three beats, דתניא שיעור תרועה כשלוש
שברים, d'tanya shiur teruah k'shalosh shevarim, that a תרועה is not three
beats, but a תרועה is actually three שברים shevarim is like longer
sounds. So אמר אביי בהא בהדי פליגי. Amar Abaye b'ha bahadi pligi.
Okay, you're right. This they definitely argue about. דכתיב יום תרועה יהיה
לכם, Dichtiv yom teruah yihiyeh lachem, a day of תרועה will be
for you. So what's תרועה? ומתרגמינן, Um'targeminan, the Aramaic translation is, יום
יבבא יהא לכון, Yom yevava yehei l'chon, a day of wailing. So
what's wailing? דכתיב באמה דסיסרא, Dichtiv b'imei d'Sisra, it says by סיסרא's
Sisra mother, בעד החלון נשקפה ותיבב אם סיסרא, Ba'ad hachalon nishkefa vateyabev
em Sisra, the mother of סיסרא Sisra by the window was wailing.
So how do you wail? מר סבר גנוחי גנח, Mar savar genuchi
ganach, you like moan, oh, oh, oh, so that's one. ומר סבר
ילולי יליל, Umar savar yeluli yalil, you wail like when we let's
say word yell, right? It's like, you know, they some ספרדים Sephardim
can do that well, right? How you do that? Fine fish. So
anyway, or if you want to think about crying it's like, it's
like, but then like that, so those are two interpretations. So how
does that map onto here? Again, it seems to be that this
becomes the longer idea becomes a שבר shever and the smaller idea
becomes a יבבה. yevava. Okay. And then again, it's exactly it's confusing
how that exactly translates into our assumption, but our assumption of it
is that there's one approach which is three שברים, shevarim, da da
da, and one approach where a תרועה is three יבבות, yevavot, which
might just mean da da da, and that's it. But the way
we've translated it, it means because this starts with three and each
one of these equals three smaller sounds, that the other version is
nine, da da da da da da da da da. Okay. But
again, it's exact not exactly clear how to fit all that in
the words of the ברייתות braitot and the משנה. mishnah. It could
be according to the משנה mishnah all you have to do for
תרועה is da da da, right? But there are two interpretations of
what a תרועה is. Okay. In the גמרא—in the תורה you only
have תרועה, but now we have two interpretations. Either moan is a
תרועה or a wail. Okay. And that is either medium-sized sound or
a staccato type of sound. It's not a theological difference, it's two
different interpretations.