Okay, so today's דף daf is ל"ה, lamed hey, the final דף
daf of מסכת ראש השנה, Masechet Rosh Hashanah, and we pick up
in the middle of ל"ד ע"ב. Lamed Dalet Amud Bet. מי
שבירך Mi sheberach בירך beireich ואחר כך נתמנה לו veachar kach nitmana
lo שופר shofar תוקע מריע ותוקע. tokeia marea vetokeia. So you already
made the ברכות, brachos, you go ahead and you do the תקיעות
tkiyot after. So clear here once again the משנה Mishna makes it
clear that the ברכות brachos are the ברכות brachos of מלכויות זכרונות
ושופרות. Malchuyos Zichronos veshofros. That's how you could make the ברכות brachos
without the שופר. shofar. And what it's telling you is that although
those two are intimately intertwined, if
they can't exist by themselves, if you don't have a שופר, shofar,
you go ahead and דאווען daven שמונה עשרה Shmone Esrei without it.
You do מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyos Zichronos veshofros and then when you
do get a שופר, shofar, you can do שופר shofar without it
and you do it by itself. It makes no mention of any
ברכה bracha you're doing שופר shofar by itself, as we mentioned, that
ברכה bracha develops later in the time of the גאונים, Geonim, particularly
once it becomes a fixed feature to do תקיעות tkiyot outside of
שמונה עשרה. Shmone Esrei. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, about
eight lines before the lines get wide.
טעמא, Tama, the reason says the גמרא, Gemara, is דלא הוה ליה
שופר מעיקרא, delo havei lei shofar meikara, that you didn't have a
שופר shofar initially. That's the whole point. הא הוה ליה שופר מעיקרא,
Ha havei lei shofar meikara, once you did have a שופר, shofar,
כי שמע להו אסדר ברכות שמע להו. ki shama lehu aseder brachos
shama lehu. You'll hear them during the ברכות brachos itself. It's so,
I mean, in a way it's funny, right, because משנה Mishna never
out and out says you do מלכויות... Malchuyos... well, actually it does,
you know, and it's funny that here it has to infer it,
you know, when it discusses the סדר הברכות, seder habrachos, it says
אומר, omer, you
know, מלכויות ותוקע, Malchuyos vetokeia, you know, שופרות ותוקע, shofros vetokeia, you
know, זכרונות ותוקע. zichronos vetokeia. The only point you had was you
had the position of רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
who says that you say מלכויות Malchuyos in קדושת היום kedushat hayom
ואינו תוקע, ve'eino tokeia, and then you do, you know, קדושת היום
ותוקע זכרונות ותוקע kedushat hayom vetokeia zichronot vetokeia etc. But there the
משנה Mishna explicitly says that you do the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyos
Zichronos veshofros together with the שופרות. shofros. They're intimately connected as רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva objects to the idea that you could have them
separate. אם אינו תוקע למה הוא מזכיר Im eino tokeia lama hu
mazkir says רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But anyway, so there it's explicit.
Here the גמרא's Gemara saying it's inferred, but again, that that is
clearly the taken-for-granted assumption. Fine. Okay, now רב פפא בר שמואל קם
לצלויי. Rav Pappa bar Shmuel kam letzaluye. רב פפא בר שמואל Rav
Pappa bar Shmuel got up to דאווען. daven. אמר ליה לשמעיה, Amar
lei lishmaie, he said to his attendant, כי נהירנא לך, ki nahirna
lach, when I signal you, תקע לי, tka li, blow for me.
So presumably this is that he's דאווענינג davening privately, and he is,
right, it didn't say he was עובר לפני התיבה, over lifnei hateiva,
and he's so he's and therefore there's no and therefore because he's
דאווענינג davening privately and silently, nobody knows what he's up to. So
he has to tell the guy that's his attendant: I'll give you
the signal, that means I've just finished זכרונות zichronos and then you
blow and then you do the תקיעות. tkiyot. Okay. Right.
What does that look like? Is he standing there, there's no סידור,
siddur, there's nothing he's reading, he's saying these פסוקים psukim authentically, whatever
the תפילה tefilla was at that time by heart. Right.
Yes. Yeah, that's presumably, yes, correct. Yep. I mean, we'll get to
the problem of people knowing it without any סידורים siddurim in a
minute, but okay. So אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא
Rava said to him, לא אמרו אלא בחבר עיר. lo amru ela
bechaver ir. No,
they only said you do תקיעות tkiyot during שמונה עשרה Shmone Esrei
בחבר עיר, bechaver ir, which is an interesting phrase which רש"י Rashi
explains to mean when there is a מנין. minyan. Okay, when there's
something that represents the community. Okay. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly, כשהוא שומען שומען על הסדר ועל סדר הברכות, keshehu
shoman shoman al haseder ve'al seder habrachos,
when you hear them, you hear them in the order and in
the order of the ברכות. brachos. Not exactly clear what על הסדר
al haseder means unless it's coming to indicate it
means, you know, תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tkia trua tkia as opposed to
just
random ordering of the sounds. But the bigger חידוש chiddush is you
hear them על סדר הברכות. al seder habrachos.
Where were we? במה דברים אמורים, Bemei devarim amurim, when is this
true? בחבר עיר, bechaver ir, with a מנין. minyan. אבל שלא בחבר
עיר, Aval shelo bechaver ir, when it's not with a מנין, minyan,
שומען על הסדר, shoman al haseder, you still have to hear תוקע
מריע ותוקע, tokeia marea vetokeia, you have to hear the full complement,
ושלא על סדר ברכות, veshelo al seder brachos, and you do not
hear them with the שמונה עשרה. Shmone Esrei. ויחיד שלא תקע חבירו
תוקע לו. Veyachid shelo taka chavero tokeia lo.
If somebody has not blown the שופר, shofar, so you can have
somebody blow for you. ויחיד שלא בירך אין חבירו מברך עליו. Veyachid
shelo berach ein chavero mevarech alav.
If you didn't do the שמונה עשרה, Shmone Esrei, you can't have
somebody do the שמונה עשרה Shmone Esrei for you. I'll read this
whole thing and then we'll unpack it phrase by phrase. It's a
pretty,
like it's saying a lot in a few words. ומצוה בתוקעין יותר
מן המברכין. Umitzvah betokein yoteir min hamevarchin.
And there's a מצוה mitzvah for those, to the blowers more than
for the blessers. Okay, the more important מצוה mitzvah is the תקיעות,
tkiyot, not the שמונה עשרה. Shmone Esrei. כיצד, Keitzad, how does this
play out?
שתי עיירות, Shti ayarot, there are two villages. באחת תוקעין ובאחת מברכין.
Be'achat tokin uve'achat mevarchin. One of them has the בעל תוקע. baal
tokeia. The other one knows how to do שמונה עשרה. Shmone Esrei.
So you have to make your choice, God forbid they should get
together for ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah.
Okay, so you let them last year.
Exactly. So do you go to the one that you'll hear the
תקיעות tkiyot but nobody there knows the שמונה עשרה Shmone Esrei or
do you want to go to the one that... or you'll hear
the שמונה עשרה Shmonah Esrei and you'll hear חזרת הש"ץ Chazaras Hashatz
and you could be יוצא yotzei or be part of that שמונה
עשרה. Shmonah Esrei. So what do you do? הולכין למקום שתוקעין ואין
הולכין למקום שמברכין. Holchin limakom shetokein ve'ein holchin limakom shemevarchin. You go
to the one that they do the תקיעות tkiyos not the one
that they do the ברכות brachos the ברכות. brachos. גמרא Gmara says
פשיטא pshita obviously. הא דאורייתא הא דרבנן. Hai d'oraisa hai d'rabbanan. תקיעות
Tkiyos are biblical, the תפילה tfila
and the מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros are rabbinic. That's
important because רש"י Rashi many places indicates that it's biblical, yet this
is rabbinic. I'll discuss that in a minute. So the גמרא Gmara
says לא צריכא lo tsricha no,
the whole חידוש chidush is דאע"ג דהא ודאי והא ספק d'af al
gav d'ha vadai v'ha safek even though in one you know you
will definitely get a בעל תפילה ba'al tfila and the other you
might not even get a בעל תוקע. ba'al tokeia. You would still
choose the ספק safek of the דאורייתא d'oraisa or ספק safek to
get the תקיעות tkiyot over the ודאי vadai of being able to
get the תפילה. tfila. Okay so there's a lot to unpack here.
Let's maybe just start with the last point because it's the one
most elaborated on and then we'll go back to the earlier phrases.
The idea that the תקיעות tkiyot are דאורייתא d'oraisa and the מלכויות
malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros are דרבנן. d'rabbanan. I think we
tend to take that for granted because you know the תורה Torah
does say יום תרועה יהיה לכם yom trua yiheye lachem and זכרון
תרועה יהיה לכם zichron trua yiheye lachem even though it doesn't exactly
spell out what that means and how many תקיעות tkiyot and how
many תרועות truot etc. whereas מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros
are much not less stated explicitly and they're much more like you
know teased out from the פסוקים. psukim. And in general I think
we have an assumption that outside of שמע Shma and it's even
debated by שמע Shma you know liturgy or maybe an outside of
ברכת המזון birchat hamazon you know liturgy tends to be
assumed to be דרבנן d'rabbanan maybe also outside of ברכת התורה. birchat
hatorah. But you know something like מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות
shofros I think we tend to assume that that's דרבנן d'rabbanan and
the גמרא Gmara here reinforces it and says you would do the
ספק דאורייתא safek d'oraisa over the ודאי דרבנן. vadai d'rabbanan. The problem
with this is רש"י Rashi in a number of places and the
ראשונים rishonim you know sort of bring this גמרא Gmara particularly the
רמב"ן Ramban to challenge him, seems to indicate that he really understands
מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros to be דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So
they say well what do you do with this גמרא? Gmara? Now
רש"י's Rashi answer which רש"י Rashi doesn't say but is the answer
רש"י Rashi would say ties back to the רש"י Rashi we did
at the end of the day yesterday where the גמרא Gmara said
that the גמרא Gmara said that what was the phrase there that
תקיעות מעכבות
זו את זו ברכות מעכבות זו את זו tkiyot m'akvot zo et
zo brachot m'akvot zo et zo which most ראשונים rishonim
interpret to mean you have to do all the תקיעות tkiyot you're
not יוצא yotzei with you know you don't get partial credit for
partial תקיעות tkiyot or you have to do all מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות
zichronos and שופרות shofros you don't get partial credit for doing some.
But רש"י Rashi interprets it for me that no you're not יוצא
yotzei the תקיעות tkiyot without the ברכות brachot and you're not יוצא
yotzei the ברכות brachot without the תקיעות tkiyot that they really have
to come together. Now of course here it says that they don't
come that they can come separate the משנה mishna says they can
come separate. So what you have to say that רש"י Rashi means
is that there are two levels but when they come together that's
like a higher sense of a fulfillment of a קיום kiyum of
the מצוה mitzvah and it really is an impaired מצוה mitzvah when
they come separate. And that is how רש"י Rashi presumably would answer
the דאורייתא דרבנן d'oraisa d'rabbanan question. If you have it that one
place is only doing the תקיעות tkiyot and one place is only
doing the מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros at that stage
when they're separate then only the שופר shofar only the תקיעות tkiyot
are דאורייתא. d'oraisa. מלכויות Malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros don't exist
דאורייתא d'oraisa outside of the תקיעות. tkiyot. So if they're separated then
they become a דרבנן d'rabbanan you know and only the תקיעות tkiyot
are דאורייתא. d'oraisa. But רש"י Rashi would still say that at a
דאורייתא d'oraisa level you're supposed to do the תקיעות tkiyot together with
מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros and that's what the גמרא
Gmara yesterday meant at מעכבות זו את זו. m'akvot zo et zo.
So it is a דאורייתא d'oraisa if you do it together with
with the תקיעות tkiyot so the דאורייתא d'oraisa is to do it
with the תקיעות. tkiyot. And therefore it is מעכבות זו את זו
m'akvot zo et zo if you don't do it with the תקיעות
tkiyot you're not יוצא דאורייתא yotzei d'oraisa מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and
שופרות. shofros. So that is a very important position of רש"י Rashi
that really stresses that this is not just some סתם stahm liturgy
you know this is really a דאורייתא d'oraisa part of the תקיעות.
tkiyot. And even this case in the end isn't a proof against
him because this case in the end is when they're coming separate.
I understand to say on some level isn't that true of קיום
כל מצות kiyum kol mitzvot with a blessing say I do not
make the ברכה bracha of לולב lulav but I take the לולב
lulav that's not מעכב m'akvei etc. I would be יוצא yotzei the
מצוה mitzvah but not as an integrated halachic...
Okay so two things. First of all here I'm saying at a
דאורייתא d'oraisa level that רש"י's Rashi claim is that דאורייתא d'oraisa מלכויות
malchiyos there's a מצוה mitzvah of there's an idea of מלכויות malchiyos
זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros together with the שופר. shofar. So that's
number one. Normally all ברכות brachot or whatever are דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Number
two is whether if you do a מצוה mitzvah without the ברכה
bracha is it a lower level of the מצוה mitzvah at a
דרבנן d'rabbanan level or is it just you didn't do the obligation
of a ברכה. bracha. People tend to distinguish between normal ברכת המצוה
birchat hamitzvah where they say it's just that you haven't done your
חיוב chiyuv of the ברכה bracha but it hasn't impacted on the
קיום המצוה kiyum hamitzvah as opposed to קריאת שמע. krias shma. By
קריאת שמע krias shma there's an idea of קריאת שמע עם ברכותיה
krias shma im birchoteha and if you can't do the ברכות brachot
it really is an impaired קריאת שמע. krias shma. And that's different
than other מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah where it's seen to be more
independent. But yes but here my point is not just higher or
lower קיום kiyum my point is also that there's a דאורייתא d'oraisa
מלכויות malchiyos זכרונות zichronos and שופרות shofros according to רש"י. Rashi. So
that's the end of this about דאורייתא דרבנן. d'oraisa d'rabbanan. Now if
we go back... Go back, let's say a little bit about this
idea about doing it in the מניין, minyan, doing it during שמונה
עשרה. shmonah esrei. So it says דוקא davka you don't do it
when you're not, you know, when you're not with a מניין, minyan,
which number one would be a support for those that have the
practice to say that you only do it during חזרת הש״ץ, chazaras
hashatz, because the argument could be if you do it during silent
שמונה עשרה, shmonah esrei, right, then when you're in a מניין, minyan,
then why shouldn't you continue to do it in silent שמונה עשרה
shmonah esrei when you're outside of a מניין? minyan? So at the
face of this, this is an idea that the idea of doing
it is only דוקא davka during חזרת הש״ץ chazaras hashatz when you
really have the תפילת הציבור tefillas hatzibur coming all together. You know,
Rav Soloveitchik has a nice way of conceptualizing the difference of your
תפילת לחש tefillas lachash when you're in a מניין minyan as opposed
to the חזרת הש״ץ, chazaras hashatz, where he says your תפילת לחש
tefillas lachash in a מניין minyan is your תפילה בציבור, tefillah b'tzibur,
your תפילה tefillah taking place in the presence of a ציבור, tzibur,
whereas the חזרת הש״ץ chazaras hashatz is the תפילת הציבור. tefillas hatzibur.
It is the entire community as a unit praying through the mouthpiece
of the חזן. chazzan. And then what this would be saying is
that this power of combining the מלכויות, malchiyos, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות
shofros together with the תקיעות tekios and having this as one sort
of unified prayer is something that comes as the sort of as
the entire ציבור, tzibur, the unity of the ציבור tzibur is expressing
their תפילות. tefillos. But as each individual, you know, there it's not
this is not like the, it doesn't have the power in order
to warrant the bringing together, the integration of the שופר shofar together
with the מלכויות, malchiyos, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות. shofros. I would say
maybe to make it a little bit sharper that if you learn
out מלכויות, malchiyos, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות shofros from the חצוצרות, chatzotzros,
where it says
על הצר הצורר אתכם והרעותם בחצוצרות al hatzar hatzorer eschem v'hareyosem bachatzotzros
etc., so that's about a communal way of calling out. The חצוצרות
chatzotzros represent something that is done at the communal level, the communal
way of שמחה, simcha, the communal way of calling out, and therefore
that's where it occurs sort of in that type of a context
of the מלכויות, malchiyos, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות shofros as a communal
prayer. Those that say that you do it even בתפילת לחש, bitfillas
lachash, but when you're בציבור, bitzibur, would have to argue, would have
to say that even there there's a same sense of doing it
as
a community. There's a personal sense, but we're all דאווענינג davening our
personal prayers as a community, and there is therefore still a communal
dimension even during the תפילת לחש, tefillas lachash, which you don't have
when you're דאווענינג davening סתם stam all by yourself. But what this
sort of says is that that power of the integration of the
two, whether it's to give meaning to the תקיעות tekios or maybe
what makes more sense is the תקיעות tekios as a way of
conveying our prayers, calling out to God, that's at the communal level,
not at the individual level, which also then gets us to
the next statement, which is what do you call it? Which is
ויחיד
שלא תקע חברו תוקע לו ויחיד שלא בירך חברו מברך עליו, yachid
shelo taka chaveiro tokeia lo v'yachid shelo beirach chaveiro mevareich alav, that
even as an individual, you could be יוצא yotzei here in תקיעות,
tekios, presumably based on a type of a שומע כעונה. shomeia k'oneh.
Okay, so that's okay. Although there's an idea of the community doing
it, the תקיעות tekios with מלכויות, malchiyos, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות, shofros,
you can be יוצא yotzei somebody else through his תקיעות. tekios. But
you cannot be יוצא yotzei somebody else's תפילות. tefillos. Now why not?
So that's in a way, it's a good lead-in to the discussion
we're about to have here of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel saying whether
the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur is מוציא. motzi. But what this reflects
is the general assumption that for
שמונה עשרה, shmonah esrei, the role of the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur
is for somebody who's a בור bur or an עם הארץ am
haaretz who doesn't know the שמונה עשרה shmonah esrei by heart, and
they therefore they allow the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur to be their
vehicle of דאווענינג. davening. Whereas I know, I know, that's a lot
of us, but that's in the גמרא. gemara. Anyway, that's when it
was an oral culture.
And but why the question should come, even if I'm and this
will be a perfect lead-in to the next part of the משנה,
mishnah, even if I'm not an עם הארץ, am haaretz, why can't
somebody דאווען davven and I'm listening and שומע כעונה? shomeia k'oneh? If
somebody can be תוקע tokeia for me, why can't I be יוצא
yotzei שומע כעונה? shomeia k'oneh? And here a number of ראשונים rishonim
quote a ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says that שומע כעונה shomeia k'oneh does
not work by תפילה tefillah and by קריאת שמע keriyas shema and
maybe by something like
ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon,
because it basically and, if you think about it, ברכת המזון birchas
hamazon requires a זימון zimmun and תפילה tefillah requires a מניין minyan
and a שליח ציבור, shliach tzibur, right? Think about that, forget also
the חבר chaver and the עם הארץ. am haaretz. Why can't I
just listen privately to your שמונה עשרה, shmonah esrei, with two people
דאווענינג davening next to each other, and I'll just listen and I'll
be יוצא yotzei שומע כעונה? shomeia k'oneh? And the answer is that
these things are supposed to be things that come from you. It's
only appropriate that you pray your prayers, your prayers about your expressing
your feeling, your communication to God. It's not somebody else communicates with
God and you say, oh yeah, me too. You know, while you're
there speaking to God, give him my regards, me too, right? Or
if you know You got הנאה, hana'ah, you're the one, you know,
who should be מברך. mivarech. You can't, you're not supposed to be
piggybacking on somebody else. That has to be coming from, initiated from
you.
And that's what אמן amen is itself, though.
No, but אמן amen is, yes, you are, you are agreeing, but
it wasn't initiated by you. It was initiated by somebody else. And
the expression, for example, of thank You God for this food, or
God, you know, I am praying You, it's not like he prayed
to You and I said me too. It has to basically start
with being mine. As opposed to something like, you know, which is
more about less of a תפילה tefillah and more of a מצוה.
mitzvah. If you think about like reading the מגילה, megillah, you know,
it doesn't at the end of the day it has to initiate
with me and my desire to read the מגילה, megillah, you know,
or something like, I don't know, קידוש. kiddush. Right there, you know,
when it's much less sort of personal and fundamentally rooted in something
that has to start with, you know, coming from me. So that's
what the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says to explain why you need the institution
of זימון zimmun or שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur to be יוצא, yotzei,
and that's what it says here: for תקיעות teki'os you can have
somebody blow for you, but for the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei you
cannot. Okay, so it's a very sort of packed ברייתא, braisa, but
there we have these important ideas about the combination of מלכויות, malchuyos,
זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות shofros together with the תקיעות teki'os only in
the context of the ציבור. tzibbur. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues, and this is a perfect follow-up to what we just said.
תניא: tanya: כשם ששליח ציבור חייב כך כל יחיד ויחיד חייב. kesheim
sheshliach tzibbur chayav kach kol yachid veyachid chayav.
The same way the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur is obligated, every individual
has to דאוון daven their own שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei as well.
And רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says no, the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur
מוציא motzi everybody their שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. And obviously there's a
particular point of discussing this here because most people will not be
able to know the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and know all the
מלכויות, malchuyos, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות. shofros. Let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says תניא, tanya, we saw in the ברייתא, braisa,
אמרו לו לרבן גמליאל, amru lo l'Rabban Gamliel, they said to רבן
גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, לדבריך למה ציבור מתפללין? lidvarecha lamah tzibbur mispallelin? According
to you, that you're all being יוצא yotzei through the חזרת הש"ץ,
chazaras hashatz, why does everybody bother doing their private שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh
Esrei? אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them, כדי להסדיר שליח
ציבור תפילתו, kedei lehasdir shliach tzibbur tefillaso,
to give the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur an opportunity to, you know,
prepare the שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. He'll say it once to get
it straight in his head and then he'll be able to say
it, but there's really very little purpose.
Now, that takes רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel to the next level. That
has רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel not just saying that you can be
יוצא yotzei through the שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur and everybody—you don't need
to be an עם הארץ—everybody am ha'aretz can be יוצא yotzei because
everybody is an עם הארץ am ha'aretz when it comes to מלכויות,
malchuyos, זכרונות, zichronos, and שופרות. shofros. But what he actually seems to
be saying is that there's no idea of a תפילת יחיד tefillas
yachid on—at least on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Maybe he's even saying it for the rest of the year,
but he's saying if you're in שול, shul, you don't have to
worry about your private שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Maybe if you're דאוונינג
davening at home, fine, you'll do a private, but if you're in
שול, shul, you only are a participant in the communal שמונה עשרה.
Shemoneh Esrei. And the only reason you would bother saying your private
one is just to give an opportunity for the שליח ציבור. shliach
tzibbur. Very powerful idea, right? We don't have to worry about our
private שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei in the context of the ציבור. tzibbur.
We're praying to God in a different mode. We're praying as part
of, part of the community, and that really is—is—suffices. There's really no
real purpose, you know, no תפילה tefillah purpose for you to be
דאוונינג davening your private שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei.
Do we assume that he has—he only men in mind when he's
making those comments?
Yeah, I mean—yeah, but I'm
not—that—when—yes. But—well, I mean—but—but—I mean in terms of are
women—look, there's two questions there, neither of which we're really going to
get into, but one is where's the discussion about whether, you know,
who constitutes a מנין. minyan. But the other is, assuming women are—are
not part of the מנין, minyan, when they are present, are they
considered to be part of the ציבור tzibbur regardless? And there the
general answer to the second is yes, that when they're present they
are considered part of the ציבור, tzibbur, you know, but there are
some that will disagree and say even when they are, they're just
דאוונינג davening as יחידים. yechidim. But that doesn't tend to be our
assumption. Okay, but here again it's a very powerful idea that fundamentally
it's only a תפילת ציבור tefillas tzibbur when you're present in the
ציבור. tzibbur. You don't have to worry about your תפילת לחש. tefillas
lachash. אמרו לו לרבן גמליאל—so amru lo l'Rabban Gamliel now רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel said back to them—לדבריכם, lidvareichem, according to you, that the
שליח ציבור shliach tzibbur isn't מוציא motzi anybody, למה שליח ציבור יורד
לפני התיבה? lamah shliach tzibbur yored lifnei hateivah? Why do we even
bother with חזרת הש"ץ? chazaras hashatz? אמרו לו, amru lo, they said
to him, כדי להוציא את שאינו בקי, kedei lehotzi es she'eino baki,
in order to be מוציא motzi the person that isn't a בקי.
baki. Of course there's a role for him, but the role isn't
to create a communal prayer that now nobody has to דאוון. daven.
The role is just for those that aren't able to דאוון, daven,
he could—they connect to him and he's their mouthpiece, but not that
now it's everybody's תפילה tefillah even those that are able to דאוון.
daven.
Or even if it is everybody's תפילה, tefillah, it's not that they're
יוצא yotzei their private obligation. Yeah, let's say it in a better
way. Maybe we don't deny the idea that the שליח ציבור shliach
tzibbur is the mouthpiece for the community and represents communal תפילה, tefillah,
but that doesn't discharge individuals of their obligation. The only thing that
discharges them is the case of the אינו בקי. eino baki. Okay.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, although it
does sound that the Rabbis are saying the first version, that there's
no idea of communal תפילה, tefillah, the only thing he's doing is
being מוציא motzi the אינו בקי. eino baki. And if that... If
that's the way you read it, you really have extreme positions. רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* is saying there's no real idea of
private תפילה tefillah *tefillah* in the context of a מניין *minyan*, of
a ציבור *tzibur*, and the Rabbis are saying there's no real idea
of communal תפילה tefillah *tefillah*. He's only there as a technical way
of helping out the אינו בקי baki, *eino baki*. So that really
could be interpreted as radical different concepts of what the שליח ציבור's
shaliach tzibur *shliach tzibur's* role is, and whether there's a תפילה tefillah
*tefillah* communal תפילה tefillah *tefillah* going on here or not. So let's
take a look. אמר להם *Amar lahem*, he said back to them,
כשם שמוציא את שאינו בקי כך מוציא motzi. את הבקי *keshem shemotzi
et she'eino baki kach motzi et habaki*. No, I disagree with you.
The same way it works for the אינו בקי *eino baki*, it
works for the בקי *baki*, presumably because he will say, because the
way it works is that it's a communal תפילה tefillah. *tefillah*, and
that therefore works for the אינו בקי *eino baki* and it also
works for the בקי *baki*. Fine. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan מודים חכמים Chachamim לרבן גמליאל *Amar Rabba bar
Bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan modim chachamim le-Rabban Gamliel*, the חכמים Chachamim
*chachamim* actually reversed themselves. They wound up conceding to רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel, *Rabban Gamliel*. ורב אמר עדיין היא מחלוקת *Ve-Rav amar adayin hi
machloket*. No, it's still a debate. שמע רבי חייא בריה דרבה בר
נחמני *Shama Rabbi Chiya brei de-Rabba bar Nachmani*, so רבי חייא בר
נחמני *Rabbi Chiya bar Nachmani* heard this position. אזל אמרה לשמעתא קמי
דרב דימי בר חיננא *Azal amrah lishmatah qamei de-Rav Dimi bar Chinena*.
He went over and he told this to רב Rav, דימי בר
חיננא *Rav Dimi bar Chinena* that there is a position that the
חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* concede, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says the
חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* concede it to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*.
אמר ליה הכי אמר רב Amar Rav. *Amar leh hachi amar Rav*
and רב חיננא *Rav Chinena* said back what we said after the
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* quote. No, here's what רב *Rav*
says: עדיין היא מחלוקת *adayin hi machloket*. It's still a debate. אמר
ליה רבה בר בר חנה נמי הכי קאמר *Amar leh Rabba bar
Bar Chana nami hachi qamar*. I'm sorry. אמר ליה רבה בר בר
חנה נמי הכי קאמר *Amar leh Rabba bar Bar Chana nami hachi
qamar*. So I want to know how to
read it.
אמר ליה רבה בר בר חנה *Amar leh
Rabba bar Bar Chana*, where are we?
Yeah. נמי הכי קאמר *nami hachi qamar*. He also said the same
thing.
כי אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, להא שמעתא *Ki amar Rabbi Yochanan
le-ha shmatah* and he said to him, okay. אמר ליה *Amar leh*,
he said to him, רבה בר בר חנה נמי הכי קאמר *Rabba
bar Bar Chana nami hachi qamar*. You know what, this is also
what רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar Bar Chana* said. Because before
we had רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar Bar Chana* saying that
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said that the חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* agree. So
now we have רב דימי *Rav Dimi* saying that רב *Rav* says
עדיין היא מחלוקת *adayin hi machloket*. And the response is, you know
what, your statement that עדיין היא מחלוקת *adayin hi machloket* is what
רב *Rav* said, רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar Bar Chana* also
said his position that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says they agree in
a slightly different way. כי אמר רבי יוחנן להא שמעתא *Ki amar
Rabbi Yochanan le-ha shmatah*, when רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said this over
and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said that מודים חכמים Chachamim, *modim chachamim*,
אמר ליה ריש לקיש *Amar leh Resh Lakish*, איפלג עליה ריש לקיש
*iflag alei Resh Lakish*. ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* disagreed with him ואמר
עדיין היא מחלוקת *ve-amar adayin hi machloket*, it's still a debate. So
we have רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* saying that the חכמים Chachamim *chachamim*
concede. We have רב *Rav* saying עדיין היא מחלוקת *adayin hi machloket*.
And we have a version that ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* also said
back to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* עדיין היא מחלוקת *adayin hi machloket*.
Okay, but still רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is saying the חכמים Chachamim
*chachamim* conceded. ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי *U-mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi*?
Did רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* really say that?
Oh, actually I just see from רש״י *Rashi* that I misread it.
רש״י *Rashi* said the way it should have been read was רבה
בר בר חנה נמי הכי קאמר *Rabba bar Bar Chana nami hachi
qamar*. So אמר ליה *amar leh*, he said back to him, רבה
qamar*. That's actually also what רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar Bar
Chana* said. All right, anyway, just to get that right. Anyway, רבה
בר בר חנה *Rabba bar Bar Chana* also when he said that
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said that it was מודים *modim*, רבה בר
בר חנה *Rabba bar Bar Chana* also added that ריש לקיש *Resh
Lakish* said נמי היא מחלוקת *nami hi machloket*. So you're telling me
רב *Rav* says נמי היא מחלוקת *nami hi machloket*? You know what,
that's also what רבה בר בר חנה *Rabba bar Bar Chana* said
that ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* pushed back on רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
in the same way. Okay. Right. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says
like this: ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי *U-mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi*?
Did רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* really say this, that the
חכמים Chachamim. *chachamim* conceded? ואמר רבי חנה ציפוראה אמר רבי יוחנן הלכתא
hilchata, כרבן גמליאל *Ve-amar Rabbi Chanah Tzippora'ah amar Rabbi Yochanan hilchata ke-Rabban
Gamliel*. We rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*. So if
we rule הלכתא *hilchata*, מכלל mikhlal דפליגי *mi-khlal de-peligi*. If we rule
it means it's still a matter of debate. So bottom line, it
doesn't affect the הלכה halacha *halakha* whether you say the חכמים Chachamim
*chachamim* conceded or whether you say they didn't concede but we rule
like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*. But it is a question
of whether they're still arguing or not. And if רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* says that we פוסקין pasken *paskin* like them, it means the
חכמים *chachamim* did not concede. So let's take a look. So we're
trying to figure this out, whether according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
the חכמים *chachamim* conceded or not. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this, top of ל״ה עמוד א׳ *lamed-he amud aleph*, כי סליק
רבי אבא מימי *ki saliq Rabbi Abba mi-yammi*, when רבי אבא *Rabbi
Abba* came up from the ocean, he returned from a sea journey,
פירשה *pirshah*, he explained רבי יוחנן's *Rabbi Yochanan's* statement the following way:
מודים חכמים לרבן גמליאל *modim chachamim le-Rabban Gamliel*. Where do the חכמים
*chachamim* concede to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel*? בברכות דראש השנה
ושל יום הכיפורים *be-vrakhos de-Rosh Hashanah ve-shel Yom Kippurim*. When it comes
to the davenings of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. *Rosh Hashanah* and יום
הכיפורים *Yom Kippurim*. Those are long davenings and there, obviously, you need
the שליח ציבור shaliach tzibur *shliach tzibur* to be מוציא motzi *motzi*
everybody because really nobody really knows them well. Now, by the way,
where did יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* come from? Until now
it's all been about ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*. So you
could just say, well, once we're talking about it we'll also add
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* which is complicated. But יום כיפור
Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, I mean the וידויים *vidduyim* maybe are complicated,
but certainly it's not, but the וידוי *viddui* we say, but the
וידוי *viddui* we say, but the private שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei *Shemoneh
Esrei* is not so complicated, the וידוי *viddui* we say after the
private שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei*. So what's
so complicated? So... So the רן Ran says יום כיפור Yom Kippur
he means what יום כיפור Yom Kippur, has always been meaning in
this פרק. perek. What has יום כיפור Yom Kippur always been meaning
in this פרק? perek? יובל. Yovel. יום כיפור Yom Kippur, of יובל,
Yovel, which we said is the same ברכות brachos as ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah So actually when he says מודין בראש השנה וביום הכיפורים,
modin b'Rosh Hashanah u'v'Yom HaKippurim, which is a very funny, normally ראש
השנה ויום כיפור Rosh Hashanah v'Yom Kippur doesn't normally mean that when
they come together, but he says, you know, that's what we've been
talking about when we talked about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, יום כיפור
Yom Kippur, of יובל, Yovel, which you have the same ברכות. brachos.
Okay, so that's an interesting read of that. So let's take a
look. ברכות של ראש השנה ושל יום הכיפורים brachos shel Rosh Hashanah
v'shel Yom HaKippurim והלכה, v'halacha, so that's where even the חכמים concede
to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that the שליח ציבור shaliach tzibur is
מוציא. motzi והלכה מכלל דפליגי, v'halacha miklal d'pligi, when we say we
rule like רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel. which implies that there's an argument,
בברכות של כל השנה, bi'brachos shel kol hashanah, that's the rest of
the year, that they have the same debate, which is a חידוש,
chidush, we wouldn't have it's not clear that רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel?
says his position the rest of the year, but maybe but it's
but he's saying he does, and therefore it's the same debate for
the rest of the year and we even rule like רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel, there as well. איני, ini, says the גמרא, Gemara is
that really true? ואמר רב חנה ציפוראה אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כרבן
גמליאל. v'amar Rav Chana Tzippora amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'Rabban Gamliel. That
quote of רב חנה ציפוראה Rav Chana Tzippora in the name of
רבי יוחנן that we rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel. didn't end
with those words. It said הלכה כרבן גמליאל בברכות של ראש השנה
ושל יום הכיפורים. halacha k'Rabban Gamliel bi'brachos shel Rosh Hashanah v'shel Yom
HaKippurim. We rule like רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel. in the case of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. which means that
that's the case that they're debating. They they still are debating that.
So now we've got a problem. רבי יוחנן rules like רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel in the case of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur which means that that case is still open for
debate, and he also says the חכמים conceded to רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel, So which case does the חכמים concede to רבן גמליאל? Rabban
Gamliel. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק
מאן מודים, ela amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak man modim, when we
said the חכמים conceded to רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel it wasn't the
חכמים in our משנה. mishna. It was a different חכמים, רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. There's a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir out there, what he
meant is there are other rabbis who agree with רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel, It's not just רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel, There's a רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that agrees to רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel. as well that
the שליח ציבור shaliach tzibur מוציא motzi everybody. והלכה מכלל דפליגי, v'halacha
miklal d'pligi, and when he says we פוסקין pasken like רבן גמליאל,
Rabban Gamliel. that means רבנן. Rabbanan. That means that the rabbis of
our משנה mishna still argue with רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So the
rabbis of our משנה mishna argue with רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel. in
all cases, and he's saying we פוסקין pasken like רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, and there's a חכמים who agree with רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel
there's a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that agrees to רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel Let me just read it. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, ברכות של ראש השנה ושל יום הכיפורים שליח ציבור מוציא
את הרבים ידי חובתן דברי רבי מאיר. brachos shel Rosh Hashanah v'shel
Yom HaKippurim shaliach tzibur motzi es harabim yedei chovasan divrei Rabbi Meir.
וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, and the חכמים say, כשם ששליח ציבור חייב
כך כל יחיד ויחיד חייב. keshem she'shaliach tzibur chayav kach kol yachid
v'yachid chayav. So basically you have the same as our משנה, mishna,
except the difference of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir with רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel So now we're going to say that רבי יוחנן never meant
what people thought he meant. When he said מודין, modin, all he
meant to say was there's another תנא tanna out there who agrees
to רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel Okay, that's statement one. Statement two is
we פוסקין pasken like רבן גמליאל. Now the now however notice because
it says specifically ברכות של ראש השנה ושל יום הכיפורים שליח ציבור
מוציא. brachos shel Rosh Hashanah v'shel Yom HaKippurim shaliach tzibur motzi. And
in our משנה mishna it just said כשם ששליח ציבור מוציא. keshem
she'shaliach tzibur motzi. It didn't limit it. But the earlier quote as
well of רבי יוחנן, we rule like רבן גמליאל, said בברכות של
ראש השנה ושל יום הכיפורים. bi'brachos shel Rosh Hashanah v'shel Yom HaKippurim.
So there is a sense here that either the whole debate is
only during ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur otherwise
we would agree that the שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibbur is not מוציא
motzi the בקי, or or number one even the whole debate is
limited to that, or if the debate possibly is broader we only
פוסקין pasken like רבן גמליאל in that case. So we are conceding
though that this idea that the שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibbur could be
מוציא motzi everyone makes a lot more sense by ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur And now we're going to ask
why. The answer's pretty obvious but we're going to ask why. So
let's see it. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי שנא הני, mai
shna hani, why are those different, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום
כיפור's דאוונינג, davening, that either that's why we that's where we פוסקין
like רבן גמליאל or that's the place where רבן גמליאל says his
position? אילימא משום דנפישי קראי, ilima mishum d'nafishei krai, because there's a
lot of verses, ואמר רב חננאל אמר רב, v'amar Rav Chananel amar
Rav, רב חננאל Rav Chananel says in the name of רב, כיון
שאמר ובתורתך כתוב לאמר שוב אינו צריך. keivan she'amar u'v'soroscha kasuv leimor
shuv eino tzarich. All you have to say is, "And so it
says in Your Torah," without actually quoting the פסוק. pasuk. So you
don't have to worry about the פסוקים. pesukim. So what's the big
deal? אלא משום דאוושי ברכות. ela mishum d'avshei brachos. No, because there
are a lot of ברכות, brachos, even though you can just say
ובתורתך כתוב לאמר, u'v'soroscha kasuv leimor, nevertheless there's three ברכות, brachos, there's
מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות, Malchiyos, Zichronos, u'Shofros, even without all the פסוקים pesukim
that's a lot. Now the way I just read this, which is
probably the simplest way to read it, not the way רש"י Rashi
reads it, is that you don't actually have to say the ברכות.
brachos. You can just say
ובתורתך כתוב לאמר, u'v'soroscha kasuv leimor, which is pretty funny because we
had debate before which is, what do you have to do for
מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות? Malchiyos, Zichronos, u'Shofros? And some said ten and some
said seven or three, we never got to fewer than three. So
how could the גמרא Gemara here say that it's enough to say
ובתורתך כתוב לאמר? u'v'soroscha kasuv leimor? So תוספות Tosfos gives one explanation
which says, it's like you got to pick. If you start saying
פסוקים, pesukim, that's where you have to say a minimum, you know,
you have to say a minimum of of ten or of three
or of whatever, right? But if you don't start saying
פסוקים pesukim You should just say whatever by giving an example you
say the מלכויות Malchuyot and you say כמו שכתוב בתורתך kemo shekatuv
betoratcha without elaborating, כמו שכתוב על ידי נביאך, kemo shekatuv al yedei
nevi'echa, כמו שכתוב בדברי קדשך kemo shekatuv b'divrei kodshecha and that’s it
and you’re done. But if you start saying פסוקים psukim then you
gotta say all of them.
Okay, but did it mean you don’t have to say the ברכות
berachot though?
No, you have to say the ברכות. berachot. You have to say
ברוך אתה ה' מלך על כל הארץ. Baruch Atah Hashem Melech al
kol ha'aretz. You have to say or שומע קול תרועת עמו ישראל
ברחמים. Shomea kol teruat amo Yisrael berachamim. But the question is how
could you say you don’t have to say the פסוקים? psukim? Before
we had to say that at least you had to say three
פסוקים. psukim. So תוספות'ס Tosafot's read is yeah you're right, but that's
if you choose to say פסוקים. psukim. If you don't choose to
say פסוקים, psukim, instead of quoting all the פסוקים, psukim, you just
say וכן כתוב בדברי קדשך, v'chen katuv b'divrei kodshecha, וכן כתוב בתורתך
v'chen katuv b'toratcha and you don't have to elaborate. הר"ן HaRan has
a slightly different read and then I'll tell you what רש"י Rashi
says. I just want to check the הר"ן HaRan against to remind
myself.
He agrees also that the פשט pshat here is that there's a
way of not saying the פסוקים, psukim, but he says it's specifically
tied in the פסק'נינג paskening the minimalist version earlier that you only
need to say a total of three פסוקים. psukim. One from, right,
remember the position before, who was it, רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri who says you only need to say three פסוקים
psukim per ברכה, beracha, one from the תורה, Torah, one from the
כתובים Ketuvim and one from and one from נביאים. Nevi'im. And then
he says according to that he
says, hold
on, I forgot to say the important other point. Okay fine, that's
that
and he
says, he said earlier at the end of that debate of ten
or three the רי"ף Rif says yeah but later we say all
you have to say is ובתורתך כתוב לאמר. ubetoratcha katuv lemor. So
the רי"ף Rif reads it as if the גמרא Gemara is basically
a third, a different opinion from the idea of ten or three.
The רי"ף Rif says, he quotes the debate about the whole thing
and he says like this: ג' כנגד כהנים לויים וישראלים, gimmel keneged
Kohanim Leviyim v'Yisraelim, הלכה כרבי יוחנן בן נורי. Halacha k'Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri. Then he says: אסיקנא בסוף פירקא אמר רב חננאל כיון שאמר
ובתורתך כתוב לאמר שוב אינו צריך וכן הלכתא. assikna besof pirka amar
Rav Chananel keivan she'amar ubetoratcha katuv lemor shuv eino tzarich v'chen hilchata.
And so it's
like okay yeah it's a debate and we פסקן pasken that way.
So the ר"ן'ס Ran's version is, one minute, the ר"ן Ran wants
to read the רי"ף Rif that the רי"ף Rif is saying that
this is a way of doing the idea of saying three פסוקים.
psukim. Since according to רבי יוחנן בן נורי'ס Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri's
position that you only need three פסוקים, psukim, it's one each from
תורה, Torah, כתובים Ketuvim. and נביאים, Nevi'im, therefore you could say וכן
כתוב בתורתך, v'chen katuv b'toratcha, וכן כתוב בדברי קדשך v'chen katuv b'divrei
kodshecha and that וכן כתוב v'chen katuv counts as a פסוק. pasuk.
So this is an interpretation of רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri. It certainly wouldn't work according to the חכמים. According to
the חכמים you need ten,
saying these phrases wouldn't work. But he wants to read this position
as an interpretation of רבי יוחנן בן נורי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri.
We פסקן pasken רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri three,
one each from תורה, נביאים, וכתובים, Torah, Nevi'im, u'Ketuvim,
and therefore if you just say וכן כתוב בתורתך, v'chen katuv b'toratcha,
וכן כתוב בדברי קדשך v'chen katuv b'divrei kodshecha that counts as a
פסוק pasuk and you're יוצא. yotzei.
Okay so these are so far two reads and now I'm going
to tell you רש"י'ס Rashi's read. But both of these read the
גמרא Gemara. that instead of saying the פסוקים psukim you can say
וכן כתוב בתורתך. v'chen katuv b'toratcha. Okay, תוספות Tosafot either says you
pick your track, you start saying פסוקים psukim you have to say
a minimum number or you don't say פסוקים psukim at all. הר"ן
HaRan interpreting the רי"ף Rif says this is an interpretation of the
idea of three פסוקים, psukim, that these phrases count as in the
place of one פסוק pasuk each and that gets you one from
תורה, Torah one from נביאים, one from כתובים.
רש"י Rashi refuses to read it this way and רש"י Rashi says
that where it says there are too many פסוקים psukim it's not
referring to מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. Malchuyot, Zichronot, v'Shofrot. Where it says there's
too many פסוקים psukim it means the פסוקים psukim of מוסף. Musaf.
Okay, now how many פסוקים psukim are there in מוסף? Musaf? There's
מוסף Musaf of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and there's מוסף Musaf of
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. There's too many פסוקים psukim because
for the מוסף Musaf part of it, the קרבן korban part of
it, there's too many פסוקים. psukim. At the end there's no, for
the קרבן korban part of it you can say ובתורתך כתוב לאמר.
ubetoratcha katuv lemor. Okay, but for the part you can't say that
for is the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. Malchuyot, Zichronot, v'Shofrot. So when the
גמרא Gemara then says דנפישי ברכות dinpishi berachot for רש"י Rashi that
means the פסוקים psukim of מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות. Malchuyot, Zichronot, v'Shofrot. It's
a very hard word because why would we use the word פסוקים
psukim and why would we focus on the problem of the פסוקים
psukim for the מוסף Musaf and not use the word פסוקים psukim
to focus on the length of the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות? Malchuyot, Zichronot,
v'Shofrot? But that's רש"י'ס Rashi's position and therefore רש"י'ס Rashi's position is
that when you say the מוסף Musaf you don't have to quote
the פסוקים psukim of the מוסף, Musaf, but when you say מלכויות
זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot, Zichronot, v'Shofrot you have to quote all the פסוקים.
psukim. תוספות Tosafot winds up פסק'נינג paskening the exact opposite. When you
say the מוסף Musaf you have to say the פסוקים psukim because
there why would you have to say the פסוקים psukim for the
מוסף? Musaf? Can you think of the religious theological reason why it
wouldn't be enough to say we will bring
a מוסף כמו שכתוב בתורתך, Musaf kemo shekatuv betoratcha, why you'd have
to?
What? You don't know which one it is?
Okay maybe to specify what it is, but more than that the
תפילה tfilla, replaces.
Right, if you
want the תפילה tfilla, to count as a מוסף. Musaf. If you
want the תפילה tefillah to count as a מוסף, Musaf, you might
have to say the words of the פסוקים psukim about the bringing
of it to be count as the מוסף. Musaf. So if you
look at the end of תוספות, Tosafot, אילמא משום דנפישי, eileima mishum
d'nafishei, תוספות Tosafot says like this: אבל מקראות של מוסף צריך להזכיר
לעולם שהם במקום הקרבנות. aval mikraot shel Musaf tzarich l'hazkir l'olam sheheim
b'makom hakorbanot.
Okay, let's start with the אבל aval about ten lines before the
end of תוספות. Tosafot. It says אבל יכול להוציא עצמו לגמרי על
ידי בתורתך כתוב לאמר. aval yakhol l'hotzi atzmo l'gamrei al yedei b'Toratecha
katuv leimor. That's by the פסוקים psukim of
מפטיר maftir of זכור Zachor and so together. אבל מקראות של מוסף
צריך להזכיר לעולם שהם במקום הקרבנות. aval mikraot shel Musaf tzarich l'hazkir
l'olam sheheim b'makom hakorbanot. And therefore במקום הקרבנות b'makom hakorbanot you have
to verbalize the פסוקים. psukim. Now, and now he says, however, אבל
מוסף דראש חודש אין צריך להזכיר בראש השנה. aval Musaf d'Rosh Chodesh
ein tzarich l'hazkir b'Rosh Hashanah. This is the idea of ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh being hidden. Because רש"י Rashi actually said you have to
say the both מוסף Musaf of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. and מוסף
Musaf of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So here תוספות Tosafot is saying—saying
first of all, you have to say the פסוקים. psukim. You can't
get out of saying the פסוקים. psukim. But number two is you
don't say the ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. אלא שדי לו במה שאמר
מלבד עולת החודש ומנחתה. ela sheday lo b'mah sheamar milvad olat hachodesh
u'minchatah. שבה זה נכלל כל מוספי ראש חודש העולות. shebezeh nichlal kol
musafei Rosh Chodesh ha'olot. וכדי להזכיר גם השעיר שהוא חטאת יאמר בשני
שעירים לכפר ושני תמידים כהלכתן. u'kedei l'hazkir gam hase'ir shehu chatat yomar
b'shnei se'irim l'chaper u'shnei tmidim k'hilchatan. Which is exactly our נוסח. nusach.
Okay? So a lot of interesting debate. רש"י Rashi says you have
to mention ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh but you don't have to mention
the פסוקים. psukim. תוספות Tosafot says
you have to mention the פסוקים psukim but you are not supposed
to explicitly mention ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh because of the ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah, identity dominate. There was another explanation about why not to
mention ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Oh yeah, the ר"ן Ran says a
fascinating explanation of why not to mention ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Because
if you emphasize it's ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, people will say, oh,
it's a ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, but we know on every two-day
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh that the real day is day two. So
they'll come to downvalue day one. So we don't want to remind
people that this day also has a status of ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh because it will lead to undermining of the value of day
one. So interesting issues around the מוסף Musaf part.
Can I say something else but could you just help me out,
I'm now, now I'm
confused. These מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot we stay, say, said
in שחרית? Shacharit?
No. So here's a debate. And thank you, that allows me to
say the other one I was going to say. So I said
a few days ago that according to the בעל המאור Ba'al HaMa'or
they said מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot in every תפילה tefillah
of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah
Right, according to the most ראשונים Rishonim and the way we פסקן,
pasken, we only said it in מוסף. Musaf. So the whole debate
here is about the מוסף. Musaf. Can the
שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibbur be מוציא motzi people for the מוסף. Musaf.
Number one. Number two is that also is an important point that
the ר"ן Ran says. The ר"ן Ran says that when we פסקן
pasken like רבן גמליאל because of the ברכות brachot of מלכויות זכרונות
ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot that they're so long and lengthy, etc., then
he says there's a position that we only פסקן pasken like him
as far as being יוצא yotzei that חיוב chiyuv applies. And therefore
the חיוב chiyuv of the ברכות. brachot. And therefore the special ברכות.
brachot. And therefore he says that in some שולס shuls there's a
מנהג minhag that the individual says only seven ברכות brachot of שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei and hears the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot
in the חזרת הש"ץ. Chazarat HaShatz. And therefore you get both. Meaning
the חזרת הש"ץ Chazarat HaShatz allows me to be יוצא מלכויות זכרונות
ושופרות, yotzei Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot, but doesn't allow me to be יוצא
yotzei the rest of the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei because the rest
of the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei I should know it. It's a
standard מוסף שמונה עשרה. Musaf Shemoneh Esrei. So that I have to
דאוון daven myself. Very bizarre that you combine the two. But it
gets back to the idea we said earlier that the תקיעות tkiyot
during שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei. is only in the repetition. And if
you think about the power of it, if your private שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei you don't even say מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot
if you follow this, it only gets said in the repetition and
that's also the only place that you have this תקיעות. tkiyot. So
then it really brings the power of all of this into the
communal aspect of the תפילה. tefillah, Only during the חזרת הש"ץ Chazarat
HaShatz do we do the תקיעות tkiyot and only during the חזרת
הש"ץ Chazarat HaShatz are we going to do the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות.
Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot. That's what the ר"ן Ran says can emerge from
this גמרא. Gemara You're יוצא yotzei through the שליח ציבור shaliach tzibbur
for the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot Zichronot v'Shofrot and therefore you don't
say them privately. You don't, maybe you don't have to, maybe even
you shouldn't. Because like we said, maybe his whole idea is that
that's the communal prayer. But what you are supposed to say privately
is your normal שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei You say seven ברכות. brachot.
And then he concedes that the מנהג minhag now is that everybody
says the full שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei. and the שליח ציבור shaliach
tzibbur also repeats it. Okay, so I hope that answered your question?
Okay fine, it was a missing piece there.
Which שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei.
we're talking about.
Right. And also just every time it says הלכתא, the implication seems
to be methodologically that it's like we know this, right, that the
minority opinion is still חל, chal, still relevant potentially for the future.
So this nomenclature reinforces that concept, right, that every time we פסקן
pasken a הלכה it's not לעולמי עד l'olmei ad necessarily if there's
a מכלל Yeah, but that could just be a historical question.
It shows that you are assuming that they were arguing because,
not that they, but that's, that's my question. Is it only historical?
Right.
Well, no, there is דעת יחיד, daas yachid, you're right about the
idea of a דעת יחיד. daas yachid. I agree, but I don't
think that's necessarily the point the גמרא's Gemara, making. Okay fine.
All right. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב אלעזר, Amar Rav Elazar, said רב אלעזר. Rav Elazar. Okay.
So what did we conclude? I'm sorry, did I skip a line?
I did. גופא. Gufa. אמר רב חננא אמר רב כל השח בתורת
חסד ולומר שובה והשיבה, Amar Rav Chanana amar Rav kol hashach b'Torat
chesed v'lomar shuvah v'hashivah, סגי מיניה, sagi minei, הני מילי ביחיד. hanei
mili b'yachid. That's in your private שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei, As we've
been saying, we're going to give you more latitude. You don't have
to say out all the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, אבל בתורת חסד, aval
b'Torat chesed, it's a different way presumably of dealing with this issue
of not knowing the שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. One is that the
שליח ציבור shaliach tzibbur. is מוציא motzi you, one is you can
say it בתורת חסד. b'Torat chesed. אבל בציבור לא, Aval b'tzibbur lo,
but maybe the communal שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei that we really require
that at least the שליח ציבור shaliach tzibbur knows what he's doing
and you've got to do it right. Says the גמרא, Gemara איתמר,
Itmar, no, it was taught, אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי אחד יחיד
ואחד ציבור כל השח בתורת חסד ולומר שובה והשיבה. Amar Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi echad yachid v'echad tzibbur kol hashach b'Torat chesed v'lomar shuvah
v'hashivah. That that actually is an option even for the שליח ציבור.
shaliach tzibur Again, hopefully not, because you want to be saying the
full שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei Okay, so what do we have? We
have that there's a debate of the שליח ציבור shaliach tzibur being
מוציא motzi you. We פוסקים pasken that he is מוציא motzi you
for the מוסף Musaf of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah? for מלכויות זכרונות
ושופרות Malchuyot, Zichronot, v'Shofrot of the שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei that has
מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות, Malchuyot, Zichronot, v'Shofrot, because it's assumed that most people
don't know it. And there's two ways of reading that: either like
the whole שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei he's מוציא motzi you, which is
the simple sense, or the interesting way that I quoted to you
that he's מוציא motzi you for the מלכויות זכרונות ושופרות Malchuyot, Zichronot,
v'Shofrot and you still do the private one, which leads to a
reality of that the full שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is only said
in the חזרת הש"ץ Chazarat HaShatz when the תקיעות tkiyot are being
done and really bringing those two entities tightly together. Okay. אמר רב
אליעזר, Amar Rav Eliezer, said רב אליעזר, Rav Eliezer, לעולם יסדיר אדם
תפלתו ואחר כך יתפלל. L'olam yasdir adam tfilato v'achar kach yitpallel. A
person should always first order his prayer and then דאוון. daven. So
get it straight in your head what you're going to say and
then actually דאוון, daven, especially if you don't have a סידור. siddur.
You've got to make sure you sort of have it all in
order up in your head. אמר רב אבא, Amar Rav Abba, said
רב אבא, said Rav Abba, מסתברא מילתא דרבי אליעזר בברכות של ראש
השנה ושל יום הכפורים ושל פרקים. mistabra milta d'Rabbi Eliezer b'vrachot shel
Rosh Hashanah v'shel Yom HaKippurim v'shel prakim. That makes sense if you're
דאוונינג davening a שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei, that you don't usually דאוון:
daven: ראש השנה and יום כיפור—again we discussed what יום כיפור could
mean in this context—or some type of thing you say only from
time to time like, you know, a שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei. of
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Okay. So those things you've got to like
spend time beforehand. It's like saying you've got to practice your ליינינג
leining before you, you know, before you ליינינג. lein. Don't get up
and do your ליינינג leining without spending time practicing it. Fine. That's
if you don't normally know it. אבל בכל השנה לא. Aval b'chol
hashanah lo. But if it's your בר מצווה פרשה, Bar Mitzvah parsha,
then you don't have to practice it. So this is saying, you
know, so here you've got to understand, if you don't have a
סידור, siddur, you've got to practice your דאוונינג davening if it's something
you don't normally דאוון. daven. But if it's the daily תפילה, you
don't have to; that's something that you know by heart. Okay. איני?
Ini? Is that really true? והא רב יהודה מסדר צלותיה ומצלי. V'ha
Rav Yehuda msadeir tzloitei u'matzli. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda would on a
regular, like whenever he would דאוון, daven, first order his דאוונינג davening
and then דאוון. daven. שאני רב יהודה. Shani Rav Yehuda. No, רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda is different. כיוון דמצלי מתלתין יומין לתלתין יומין. Keivan
d'matzli mitlatin yomin l'tlatin yomin. He would only דאוון daven once a
month. Okay. Because this goes to a גמרא Gemara that people that
are learning תורה Torah all the time are even exempt from דאוונינג.
davening. So he was learning תורה all the time and he would
only דאוון daven once a month because רש"י Rashi said he would
finish going over all of his learning, like he'd חזר ש"ס chazar
Shas once a month. So when he finished all of his learning,
he'd take a little bit of a break from learning and then
he would do his דאוונינג. davening. He would דאוון. daven. So, so
since he only דאוונס davens once a month, once a month, כפרקים
דמי, k'prakim dami, it's like a יום טוב Yom Tov דאוונינג davening
for him, and therefore he first has to get it straight in
his head. That's a fantastic principle for teenagers, you know what I
mean? It's like, up the ante in the classroom and let them
דאוון daven once. There you go. Okay, so by the way, I
do want to, I do want to say that, you know, I
do want to say that it's, it's not clear what the גמרא
means exactly by מסדר. msadeir. I've been translating it as like 'get
it straight in your head', 'practice it', but there's a sense that
there's something a little bit more concrete and specific that is being
referred to. Technical term in תפילה, liturgical development. Yeah, I don't, but,
well, that's true because it's also when it talks about right, we
talk about the actually creating the שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei. it says
הסדרן, Hasadran, right? So there's this sense of putting them in order.
And again, I don't know, it could also mean that there were
like mnemonics, not mnemonics, there were mental devices used, like they had
developed particularly in Greece, you know, for rhetoric, like the arguments you're
going to make when you speak, you know, about how to remember
which comes next. Like you imagine yourself walking through a house, so
you know, when you think about the door, you're thinking about like
that's the first, you know, somehow connects mentally to the first argument
you're going to make, and then the hallway the next, and like,
you know, so you know when to say like 'I haven't gotten
up to there' or something. Anyway, there's like interesting things about that.
So it seems like there might be something actually more technical that's
being referred to about how you are organizing your דאוונינג. davening. But
anyway, the point is, get it down so you know it. Okay.
אמר רב. אמר רבי אבא בר אבירא אמר רב שמעון חסידא: Amar
Rabbi Abba bar Avira Amar Rav Shimon Chasida: פוטר היה רבן גמליאל
אפילו עם שבשדות. Poter haya Rabban Gamliel afilu am she'basadot. Rabban Gamliel
would exempt even the people in the fields, people that aren't in
שול. shul. Now, are they not coming to שול shul on ראש
השנה? Or does this mean that Rabban Gamliel originally set his position
by all דאווענינג? davening? And if he set his position by all
דאווענינג, davening, then even if you're working in the fields and you
can't come to שול shul for שחרית Shacharit or מנחה, Mincha, whatever,
you're exempt because there's a תפילת הציבור tefillat hatzibur going on and
there's a שליח ציבור going on. Which by the way speaks to
the power that it's not just a type of שומע כעונה. shomea
k'oneh. It is the idea of the entire the דאווענינג davening of
the entire community, you know, and it represents the entire community, and
it's the one שליח ציבור speaking for the entire community and it
is the sense of communal prayer, not I'm being מוציא you, your
individual חיוב. chiyuv. No, you're part of communal prayer. So if you're
part of communal prayer, you know, you're part of our town as
well. You might not make it to שול, shul, you might, you
know, be out in the fields, but when we are doing the
תפילה of our town and our communal prayer, that's for the entire
town. And therefore even if you don't make it to שול, shul,
you're included. Okay. ולא מיבעיא V'lo miba'ya so the גמרא says פוטר...
poter... ולא מיבעיא... v'lo miba'ya... wait a minute, it's sounding like you're
saying even the people in the fields and it goes without saying
the people that are still in the town. ולא מיבעיא הני דקיימי
הכא? V'lo miba'ya hanei d'kaimei hacha? Wait a minute, it's sounding like
you're saying even the people in the fields and it goes without
saying the people that are still in the town. אדרבה, Aderaba, הני
אניסי, hanei anisei, those that are in the fields are אנוס, anus,
right? They can't get to the village for דאווענינג. davening. הני לא
אניסי, Hanei lo anisei, the people that are in town, what are
they doing not being in שול? shul? So maybe the fact that
they're staying in their homes, they're not coming to שול, shul, they're
basically sort of being פורש מן הציבור. poresh min hatzibur. They're saying
we don't want to be part of the community and the community's
prayer. So maybe they should be more excluded. דתני אבא בריה דרב
בנימין בר חייא, d'tani Abba brei d'Rav Binyamin bar Chiya, עם שאחורי
כהנים, am she'achorei kohanim, the people that are behind the כהנים, kohanim,
right, you know, when they're doing the ברכת כהנים birkat kohanim and
they're at their back, אינם בכלל ברכה, einam bichlal bracha, are not
included because they are putting themselves out of the presence, like the
community that's being blessed by standing, you know, in a different place.
So therefore here too we should say that you're setting yourself apart
from the community since you could come and you don't. אלא כי
אתא רבין אמר רבי יעקב בר אידי אמר רבי שמעון חסידא: Ella
ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida:
לא פטר רבן גמליאל אלא עם שבשדות. Lo patar Rabban Gamliel ella
am she'basadot. He's only exempting those that are in the fields, meaning
in terms of people that aren't in שול. shul. He also exempts
the people that are in שול, shul, but מאי טעמא mai ta'ama
why? משום דאניסי במלאכה, mishum d'anisei bim'lacha, because they have no choice,
they have to be, you know, harvesting the wheat, they can't come
for מנחה Mincha or שחרית Shacharit and מעריב. Maariv. אבל בעיר לא,
Aval ba'ir lo, but if you're in the city, you're not יוצא.
yotzei. Now what does it mean what state would you not be
יוצא? yotzei? So if you look at the side, it clarifies it.
It says אין פירוש אין שליח ציבור מוציא עד דאתו לבי כנישתא.
Ein peirush ein shaliach tzibur motzi ad d'atu l'vei knishta. You have
to come to שול shul because obviously Rabban Gamliel says he's מוציא
those in שול. shul. ושמעו מראשיתה ועד סופה, v'shamu me'reshitah v'ad sofah,
that's another interesting question. What puts you outside the community? I'm in
שול, shul, fine, but I wasn't there while they were saying שמונה
עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. I was only there for part of שמונה עשרה.
So at least the interpretation that the רן has and based on
the ריף Rif is that you have to be in שול shul
and hear the whole thing. Okay. So but either you're out in
the fields and there's no way you can be here or you're
here and you're hearing the whole thing. Any space in between, you're
separating yourself out from what it means to be sort of included
in this prayer. But again the power of Rabban Gamliel is that
he's not saying it's a type of שומע כעונה. shomea k'oneh. Remember
Rabban Gamliel says in principle you don't even need to be saying
your private שמונה עשרה. When you have the תפילה in שול shul
or when you're included in the prayer of the שול shul because
you have no choice and you can't be here, so then actually
that is the תפילת הציבור tefillat hatzibur without שומע כעונה shomea k'oneh
and therefore there's no point of doing your own private תפילה, you
were part of the תפילת הציבור. tefillat hatzibur. Okay. הדרן עלך יום
טוב וסליקא לה מסכת ראש השנה. Hadran alach Yom Tov u'slika lah
masechet Rosh Hashanah. ישר כח Yasher koach to everyone and we'll see
you tomorrow when we move on to תענית. Taanit.