Recording the little one too? Ah. Okay,
good morning. Today's דף daf is
סנהדרין כ"ד, Sanhedrin Kaf-daled, 24. We are on the bottom of כ"ג
עמוד ב', Kaf-gimel Amud Bet, כי אתא רב דימי. Ki Ata Rav
Dimi. Yesterday
we went through many different interpretations of our משנה mishna about זה
פוסל דיינו של זה וזה פוסל דיינו של זה. zeh posel dayano
shel zeh ve-zeh posel dayano shel zeh. We just saw כי אתא
רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki Ata Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan,
מחלוקת בשתי כיתי עדים. machloket bi-shtei kittei edim. We used רמב"ם's Rambam
פשט pshat that it's talking about the claimant brings two sets of
witnesses, and רמב"ם Rambam says that because he brought two sets of
witnesses, it's clear that he knows that at least one of the
witnesses is an invalid witness and therefore if the other litigant claims
that one of them is invalid, the onus is on the person
who brought four witnesses to prove that all of his witnesses are
כשר. kosher. Now we're going to have another interpretation that comes from
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן. Ki Ata
Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan. Where? At the very bottom. 23b. 25? 23?
Yeah, כ"ג, Kaf-gimel, just at the bottom.
At the very bottom of 23 on the last line.
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן,
רישא בעדים פסולין ודיינין כשרין מיגי דפסלי עדים נמי דייני.
Ki Ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, Reisha be-edim pesulin ve-dayanim kesherin migei
de-paslei edim nami dayane. Sorry, let me try this again.
רישא בעדים פסולין ודיינין כשרין מיגו דפסלי עדים פסלי נמי דייני. Reisha
be-edim pesulin ve-dayanim kesherin migo de-paslei edim paslei nami dayane. So, רבין
Ravin comes and says that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said that the
רישא, reisha, זה פוסל דיינו של זה וזה פוסל דיינו של זה,
zeh posel dayano shel zeh ve-zeh posel dayano shel zeh, means that
if one litigant proves that the other litigant's judge is invalid,
since... sorry, he proves that the עדים edim are invalid. Even if
the דיינים dayanim are כשר, kosher, because we say that the עדים
edim are invalid, we also say that the דיינים, dayanim, the judges,
are invalid. I don't understand what kind of comparison that is. That
makes no sense. Like, you know, well you come with another
עד, ed, right, and I prove it like you're קרוב. karov. I
mean, the other עד ed is a קרוב. karov. I mean, like,
they make... you know... Okay, so we'll talk about it what this
means in a second. It's a little bit strange. Yes. סיפא
בדיינים פסולין בעדים כשרין. Seifa bi-dayanim pesulin be-edim kesherin. The סיפא, seifa,
זה פוסל דיינו של זה וזה פוסל דיינים של זה, zeh posel
dayano shel zeh ve-zeh posel dayanim shel zeh, is a case where
one litigant proves that the other litigant's judges are פסול, pasul,
and since we say that the judges are invalid, we also say
the witnesses are invalid. מיגו דפסלי דייני פסלי נמי עדים. Migo de-paslei
dayane paslei nami edim. Because the whole process is פסול. pasul. Right.
That's a good idea. The whole, once you say that one of
them is פסול, pasul, the whole court has become פסול pasul and
you have to start from scratch. But still, I mean, it's a
different function than an עד. ed. I know. You can't have a
trial if the judges, if the דיינים dayanim have been... if the
עדים edim have been...
if the עדים edim are פסול, pasul, then the judges may be
then all... it's like a hung jury. Sorry, a mistrial. Yeah, if
the search warrant is found invalid, the whole thing. If you have
a mistrial in American law, you have a new... you start over,
you might have a new judge... probably not a new judge, but
you have a new jury,
although you bring the same witnesses. Right. Interesting.
So this is because the litigant is bringing both the witnesses and
the judges and that דיין dayan that he selected? Right. So it
comes as a
group
in other words. Yeah, but that affects in another case. If you
say you're פסול, pasul, right, that means you're really פסול. pasul. So
how can you say because an עד ed is פסול, pasul, therefore
a דיין dayan is פסול, pasul, and say that he can't judge
another case? So רש"י Rashi explains as follows.
דיבור המתחיל רבין, Dibbur hamatchil Ravin, actually let's finish. רבין סבר. Ravin
savar.
The first line of the narrow lines in רש"י. Rashi. אמרינן מיגו
בעלמא. Amrinan migo be-alma. It's a general מיגו. migo. מיגו migo here,
I know we have the general... we have another idea of what
מיגו migo is. One person makes a claim and we believe that
claim because he could have made a different claim. That's not quite
what it means here. Here it just means... it just means since.
Because. מיגו migo is the Aramaic for מתוך. mitoch. Right. Since. Because.
Right. דקיימא הכא טעמא משום מיגו הוא ואי לאו. De-kayma hacha ta'ama
mishum migo hu ve-ilav.
No,
that's not the right one. Sorry,
at the third wide line. סיפא. Seifa. שנמצאו דבריו אמת. Shenimtzu devarav
emet. That
the litigant who made the claim that the other one's דיין dayan
or עד ed was פסול, pasul,
we believe because he's telling the truth על הדיינים שפסולים הם ומשום
הכי. al ha-dayanim she-pesulin hem u-mishum hachi. מהימנינן להו אהדי אליבא דרבי
מאיר. mahamininan lehu ahadi aliba d'Rabbi Meir.
So because he told the truth, we've proved that he told the
truth about one of the two, we believe him about the other
of the two. Which presumably means that if the other litigant brings
proof that in fact they are כשר, kosher, it might not work,
even according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Right, if ראובן Reuven brings
two witnesses,
שמואל Shmuel proves that one of his witnesses... שמואל Shmuel claims that
his דיינים dayanim and his עדים eidim are פסול, pasul, and he
proves that
one of the עדים eidim is פסול, pasul, we believe שמואל Shmuel
that the דיינים dayanim are also פסול. pasul. Does that make sense?
Yes, because if שמואל Shmuel hadn't known...
שמואל Shmuel knows that the עדים eidim are פסול, pasul, he could
have just claimed that the עדים eidim are פסול. pasul. But because
he... it doesn't make total sense. It's a kind of a weird
thing. And the גמרא Gemara also has... the גמרא's Gemara also uncomfortable
with it. We have to move on. Okay.
פסלי נמי עדים. pasli nami eidim. מתיב ליה רבא. metiv lei Rava.
בשלמא מיגו דפסלי עדים פסלי נמי דייני. bishlama migo d'pasli eidim pasli
nami dayani. It makes sense to me that because you would פסול
pasul the עדים eidim you would also פסול pasul the דיינים. dayanim.
Why?
איכא בי דינא אחרינא. ika bei dina achrina. You can find other
דיינים. dayanim. It's not the end of the world to say 'Okay,
we
need a new judge,' but I'm trying to relate it to American
law. We need a new jury, I already said it earlier. We
need a new jury, right? אלא מיגו דפסלי דייני פסלי נמי עדים
והא עדים טפי ליכא. ela migo d'pasli dayani pasli nami eidim veha
eidim tafi leika. You're going to say that because the דיינים dayanim
are פסול pasul the עדים eidim are also פסול? pasul? What if
there are no other עדים? eidim? Then the whole trial, then the
litigant, the claimant has no more legal recourse just because we proved
that one of the דיינים dayanim was פסול. pasul. לא צריכא דאיכא
כת אחר. lo tzricha d'ika kat acher. No, this is only... you
only use this ruling according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir if there's
another pair of witnesses.
This is a much more important than the judge because that's the
basis of the whole incrimination. Exactly. And if you don't have them
anymore then the claimant has no more legal recourse, which is a
big problem. Everything rests on the witnesses. Exactly. You can find other
דיינים. dayanim. The דיינים dayanim aren't as important as
עיקר ikar to the case. הא ליכא כת אחר מאי? ha leika
kat acher mai? What happens if there's no כת אחר? kat acher?
הכי נמי דלא מצי פסלי. hachi nami d'lo matzi paslei. Here too
we would not...
if there is no other pair of witnesses then even if you
prove that one of the דיין dayan is פסול, pasul, the עדים
eidim are not automatically made פסול. pasul. היינו דרב דימי. hainu d'Rav
Dimi. But that's the same as רב דימי, Rav Dimi, right? Yesterday
we saw רב דימי Rav Dimi who said that if there are
two sets of witnesses and he proves that one set of witnesses
is פסול pasul then the other...
it only רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir שיטה shita only exists in a
world where there are two sets of witnesses, which is the same
as רב דימי. Rav Dimi. איכא בינייהו מיגו. ika beiniyahu migo. They
disagree on whether or not we say this מיגו migo or not.
דמר סבר אמרינן מיגו ומר סבר לא אמרינן מיגו. demar savar amrinan
migo umar savar lo amrinan migo.
רבין אמר רבי יוחנן Rabin amar Rabbi Yochanan says that we do
hold by this מיגו, migo, therefore he can פסול pasul
the דיינים. dayanim. Right. משום מיגו, meshum migo, okay, he can therefore
פסול pasul the דיינים, dayanim, right, and now, just now. And the
other one says no. Therefore the דיין dayan would be פסול pasul
forever? By the way, that's an interesting... that's a good question. In
these trials do they have appeals?
I don't think so. There was no appellate court. No, but everything
rests... ערעור. irur. ערעור irur is maybe the later... modern Hebrew. ערעור
irur is... No, we have this.
What about it? ערעור irur
is to appeal, yeah. But that's an appeal within the first trial
saying
this דיין dayan is פסול. pasul. It's
not like you
don't
like what he ruled. Once you accept the
ruling, it's all over. Once it's been
rendered, I'm sure it's something that comes up in the מסכת masechet
later. I haven't learned the whole thing but also I'm not sure,
but it might be. But the evidence is really the witnesses. Life
and death was on the basis of the witnesses. Right, we're talking
about monetary law here.
Right. Just like in today's... well not...
חזקה chazaka can be a witness. Or the שטר shtar is a
witness, like
sort of you can bring material... we have materials that also serve
as witnesses or
evidence, thank you, evidence. Okay. But again, somehow I don't understanding like
you know, just פסול pasul an עד, eid, now you're saying this
judge can never judge again. I mean, do you think... We might
not be saying that. We might just be saying he doesn't
work in this case because
there's no proof that he actually... I'm just looking at my cheat
sheet here that has some ראשונים rishonim to
see... עד דפסלינהו בעינייהו, ad d'paslinhu b'einihu, okay, you're... You're a גזלן
*gazlan*, you know, whatever it is. And that's what we're talking about
as we said before, might be
פגם משפחה *pegam mishpacha*. No, he said פסול pasul. *pasul* was like
פגם משפחה *pegam mishpacha*, you're an עבד *eved*, right? That's it, you
can never be a judge. Ah but right, but a קרוב *karov*
is a פסול pasul. *pasul* witness and he can, right, I know,
but it depends on, you know, depends what we mean by that,
how פסול pasul *pasul* are we saying this is? If, if, so
that's a question, that's a good question. That's not, I mean, it's
a good question but we don't have to, we can't answer it
with what time we have, with what source we have. Okay. גופא
*Gufa*. We're going to go back to a quote that we saw
yesterday. אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish, פה קדוש יאמר דבר זה
תני עדו *Amar Reish Lakish peh kadosh yomar davar zeh tani edo*.
So
one of the solutions was זה פסול pasul עדו של זה וזה
פסול pasul עדו של זה *zeh pasul edo shel zeh vezeh pasul
edo shel zeh*. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* said no, it
just means עדו *edo*, one of his witnesses,
or his one witness, that if one person brought one witness,
then the other litigant, even after he accepts the witness as kosher
by himself, he can still פסול pasul *posul* it. איני *Ini*? Is
this really true? והא אמר עולא הרואה את ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
בבית המדרש כאילו עוקר הרים וטוחנן זה בזה *Veha amar Ulla haroeh
et Reish Lakish beveit hamidrash keilu oker harim vetochenan zeh bazeh*. We're
not going to go into until the end of this גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* to the next משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. There's אגדתא *Agadata* about comparing
the differences between תורה Torah. *Torah* of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz
Yisrael* and the תורה Torah *Torah* of בבל Bavel *Bavel*. So ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*, who is from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
*Eretz Yisrael*,
the איני *ini* means not about תני עדו *tani edo*, it's really
about פה קדוש יאמר דבר זה *peh kadosh yomar davar zeh*. The
idea being that would ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* really have
said such a great thing about someone else when ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *Reish Lakish* himself was such a great scholar? Why not? Why
can't he? Okay, so it's going to change, it's going to change
what he says, what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to be confused
by it also. בבית המדרש *Beveit hamidrash*, anyone who saw ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* בבית המדרש *beveit hamidrash*, he was an עוקר
הרים *oker harim*, he would uproot mountains and he would טוחנן זה
בזה *tochenan zeh bazeh*, grind them together, which רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says
it means that nothing, he made everything straightforward and simple.
Let's see בבבא קמא *beBava Kama*. אמר רבינא *Amar Ravina*, no. וטוחנן
זה בזה *Vetochenan zeh bazeh*, says רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, מטיח ומקיש זה
בזה *matiach umakish zeh bazeh*, he would rub them and strike them
together. עלמא חריפא טובא הוה מיקרי ליה לרבי מאיר דרך ענווה פה
קדוש *Alma charifa tuva hava mikrei lei leRabbi Meir derech anava peh
kadosh*. So he was very חריף *charif*, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish
Lakish* was very חריף *charif*, which is also important here in the
comparison. He was very חריף *charif* and but he made things straightforward
and he was being humble when he said פה קדוש *peh kadosh*
about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. אמר רבינא
*Amar Ravina*, but wait a second says רבינא *Ravina*, והלוא כל הרואה
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir בבית המדרש כאילו עוקר הרי הרים וטוחנן זה
בזה *vehalo kol haroeh Rabbi Meir beveit hamidrash keilu oker harei harim
vetochenan zeh bazeh*, he would uproot the mountains of mountains and grind
them together. הכי קאמר *Hachi ka'amar*, this is what the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* meant when it said איני *ini*. בא וראה כמה מחבבין זה
את זה *Bo ureh kama mechabevin zeh et zeh*, come and see
how much they respect and love one another, that would be the
scholars of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*. כי הא דיתיב רבי
Rabbi... *Ki ha deyativ Rabbi*, the scholars of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
*Eretz Yisrael* love one another and they're not חריף *charif* with, they're
not harsh with one another. דיתיב רבי Rabbi... וקאמר אסור להטמין את
הצונן *Deyativ Rabbi veka'amar asur lehatmin et hatzonen*, because look at the
following case where they're מחבבין זה את זה *mechabevin zeh et zeh*,
where they treat each other lovingly. There's a time when רבי *Rabbi*
said it is אסור *asur* on שבת *Shabbat* to להטמין *lehatmin* cold
things, to even put cold things in insulation. רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* explained
this would be because this is really another whole עניין *inyan*, but
this would be because it might lead to
insulating hot things which we know is אסור דרבנן *asur derabbanan*.
So רבי *Rabbi* says it's also אסור *asur* to insulate cold things
leading into שבת *Shabbat*.
אמר לפניו רבי ישמעאל *Amar lefanav Rabbi Yishmael*, רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי
אבא *Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi Abba*, my father, says רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael*, which would be רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*, התיר להטמין את
הצונן *hitir lehatmin et hatzonen*. אמר לו כבר הורה זקן *Amar lo
kvar hora zaken*. So even though רבי *Rabbi* really thought that it
should be אסור *asur* to insulate cold things leading into שבת *Shabbat*,
because רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* tells him that his father permitted it,
רבי *Rabbi* says okay, a זקן *zaken* already made this ruling and
therefore I take back what I said, because they're מחבבין זה את
זה *mechabevin zeh et zeh*, they love one another, and because he
respects רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* and he learns that רבי יוסי *Rabbi
Yossi* made this ruling, he takes back his ruling. They didn't have
refrigerators. Right. אמר רב פפה בא וראה כמה מחבבין זה את זה
דאילו רבי יוסי קיים היה כפוף ויושב kafuf veyoshev לפני רבי דהא
רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי ממלא מקום אבותיו memale makom avotav *Amar Rav
Pappa bo ureh kama mechabevin zeh et zeh de'ilu Rabbi Yossi kayam
haya kafuf veyoshev lifnei Rabbi deha Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yossi memale
makom avotav*. If רבי
יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* had still been alive, רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* would
have, or רבי *Rabbi* would have sat with him and would have
learned with him until
they. could agree on a ruling here instead of just maybe
disproving one another like they do in בבל Bavel and and this
is proven because Rabbi Ishmael filled the place of Rabbi Yose which
means
my understanding it is that Rebbe is a greater scholar anyway and
ever since he is יכפוף וישב yekafuf veyoshev before Rebbe
he would sort of be subservient to Rebbe almost in terms of
level of scholarship what does it mean by כפוף ויושב kafuf veyoshev
that's what I'm saying he would be bent over and sit in
front of him humbly humbly yeah that's the thing meaning he would
have sat over he would be subservient to Rebbe almost in terms
of level of scholarship and yet nevertheless Rebbe is saying okay you
ruled exactly even though Rebbe was a greater תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham
exactly yeah that's what it says ממלא מקום אבותיו says רשי Rashi,
means חשוב כאביו chashuv ke-aviv he's as important as his father and
even so he he sat and humbled himself in front of Rebbe
meaning that Rebbe was really a greater Torah scholar than
Rabbi Yose but even so he accepted Rabbi Yose's opinion because he
already חור הזקן hor hazaken so it also here says although Rabbi
Yose was greater than Rebbe in Torah knowledge he submitted to Rebbe
in deference to his position as נשיא Nasi so as not to
render halachic rulings in Rebbe's presence ah so Rabbi Ishmael was a
greater Torah scholar than Rebbe it says about Rabbi Yose and Rebbe
I'm saying when we say that he would have sat before him
in deference Rabbi Yose would have sat before Rebbe in deference I
see just because they suggest because Rebbe was a נשיא Nasi okay
okay so Rabbi Yose was a greater scholar than Rebbe but Rebbe
was the נשיא Nasi therefore Rabbi Ishmael who filled the place of
Rabbi Yose was sitting in front of... yeah Rabbi Ishmael who is
Rabbi Yose's son sat and was humble in front of Rebbe but
they would say even Rabbi Yose himself would have humbled himself because
he was the נשיא Nasi right right back to the other explanation
that said Rebbe is a greater scholar I don't think that takes
meaning like if you're saying he's doing it because he's a נשיא
Nasi but well it says ממלא מקום אבותיו הוה והיה כפוף ויושב
לפני רבי memale makom avotav havah vehayah kafuf veyoshev lifnei Rebbe even
Rabbi Yose would have done... been in the same position okay ודקאמר
vedeka-amar כבר חור הזקן kevar hor hazaken and even right even so
even though Rabbi Yose would be כפוף ויושב Rebbe is the one
who said כבר חור הזקן kevar hor hazaken even though Rabbi Yose
would have been right even though right okay אמר רב אושעיא Amar
Rav Oshaya מאי דכתיב ואקח לי את שני מקלות קראתי לנועם ולאחד
קראתי לחובלים mai dechtiv va-ekach li et shenei maklot karati lenoam ule-echad
karati lechovelim it's a quote from זכריה Zechariah there are two staffs
זכריה Zechariah is saying is prophesying God's words he has two staffs
one is called לנועם lenoam one what beauty and one is called
לחובלים lechovelim which means how does Artscroll translate like destruction basically right
מן החבול min hachavol I think I think the פסוק pasuk I
think it means something else in the context of the פסוק pasuk
חובל chovel is also a thug assault or assaulters okay נועם noam
we have to okay מחבל mechabel in modern Hebrew is to damage
is a terrorist מחבל mechabel is a terrorist so this is exactly
exactly it's ארץ ישראל versus בבל Bavel נועם noam אלו תלמידי חכמים
שבארץ ישראל elu talmidei chachamim shebe-Eretz Yisrael right the pleasant part is
students
in ארץ ישראל שמנעימין זה לזה she-man'imin zeh la-zeh שמנעימין זה לזה
she-man'imin zeh la-zeh same שורש shoresh as נועם noam they're pleasant to
one another בהלכה ba-halacha חובלים אלו תלמידי חכמים שבבבל chovelim elu talmidei
chachamim shebe-Bavel שמחבלים זה לזה בהלכה she-mechabelim zeh la-zeh ba-halacha they're harsh
with one... the students in בבל Bavel. are harsh with one another
the students of ארץ ישראל are kind to one another it's important
to note in רשי Rashi that he says because of בבל's Bavel?
approach to הלכה halacha they actually lose something in their learning that
the approach in
I don't want to take too much time finding it because there's
a lot to cover but let me see if I can
under חובלים chovelim maybe
דקמנצחי זה לזה בדברי ברייתא
ושמועתא dekamnatzchi zeh la-zeh bedivrei baraita ushemuata right
because right if you in other words if you sit in conversation
with someone who disagrees with you you're going to develop more ideas
than if you just argue with someone
who has different opinions as you. Strictly in the context of the
destruction of the Temple, Second Temple, strictly because they didn't respect each
other, you know, so you hear this saying in Israel, they did
respect each other, you know, the scholars. Right. Yeah. Right, it wasn't
necessarily the scholars that
were... 200 years.
This is when, before or after?
This is after? Is that... yeah, this is all
after. Okay. שמח לב ירושלים. Simach lev Yerushalayim. Okay, and then another
another quote from זכריה Zechariah ויאמר אלי אלה שני בני היצהר העומדים
וגומר Vayomer elai eleh shenei venei hayitzhar haomedim vegomer ושני זיתים ushnei
zeitim which is from an earlier
פסוק pasuk עליה. aleha. There were two olive trees upon this thing
and there were two
בני יצהר. benei yitzhar. יצהר Yitzhar אמר רבי יצחק אלו תלמידי חכמים
שבארץ ישראל שנוחים זה לזה בהלכה. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak elu talmidei chachamim
shebe’eretz Yisrael shenochin zeh lazeh bahalachah. These יצהר... yitzhar... this verse proves
that the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim in ארץ ישראל are nice to
one another כשמן זית, keshemen zayit, they're like olive oil. Like wine.
יצהרך. Yitzharecha.
Freshly pressed oil. No, it's oil. It's oil. Thank you. תירוש Tirosh
is wine. Right. כשמן זית. Keshemen zayit. They're nice to each other
like
שמן זית. shemen zayit. ושני זיתים עליה Ushnei zeitim aleha אלו תלמידי
חכמים שבבבל שמרירין זה לזה. elu talmidei chachamim shebeBavel shemeririn zeh lazeh.
They're bitter to one
another. תירושך ויצהרך. Tiroshcha veyitzharecha.
תירוש ויצהר Tirosh veyitzhar is wine and oil. Okay. They're bitter to
one another
like an olive. If you've ever eaten a raw olive off of
a tree, they are really bitter. Like the taste sticks in your
mouth for 10 minutes. Okay. The מסורת הש"ס Masoret Hashas says היינו
אילן של זית hainu ilan shel zayit like a tree, like I
guess if you eat the tree, but I think it's talking about
the actual olive, which is very bitter. Okay. Another פסוק pasuk from
זכריה Zechariah ואשא עיני וארא והנה שתים נשים יוצאות ורוח בכנפיהם Va’esa
einai va’ere vehineh shetayim nashim yotzot veruach bechanfeihem ולהנה כנפים ככנפי החסידה
ulahenah knafayim kechanfei hachasidah yeah ותשאנה את האיפה vatisenah et ha’eifah and
they carried away this tub בין השמים ובין הארץ bein hashamayim uvein
ha’aretz between the sky and the land ואמר אל המלאך הדובר בי
אנה המה מוליכות את האיפה va’omar el hamalach hadover bi anah heimah
molichot et ha’eifah and I said where are they taking where are
they taking this tub? ויאמר אלי לבנות לה בית בארץ שנער. Vayomer
elai livnot lah bayit be’eretz Shinar. To build for it a house
in the land of Shinar. לה. Lah. It's important to note, it's
going to come up. לה Lah here in the פסוק pasuk does
not have a מפיק ה, mapik heh, which normally it would if
it's talking about a possessive לה lah with
a מפיק ה. mapik heh. Okay. It's interesting, this is in the
בבלי, Bavli, you know, they really, they criticize themselves and praise the...
right. So the stork's wings and the wind in them represents vanity
and the wind in them is גסות רוח gasut ruach is haughtiness,
I guess. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחי זו חנופה
וגסות רוח. Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai zo chanufah
vegasut ruach. This is flattery and arrogance שירדו לבבל sheyardu leBavel that
went to בבל. Bavel. וגסות הרוח לבבל נחית. Vegasut haruach leBavel nachit.
Did גסות רוח, gasut ruach, did haughtiness really go to בבל? Bavel
והא אמר מר, Veha amar Mar, there's we have this statement from
a certain master, עשרה קבים גסות ירדו לעולם תשעה נטלה עילם ואחת
כל העולם כולו. Asarah kabim gasut yardu la’olam tishah natlah Elam ve’achat
kol ha’olam kulo. There were only 10 units of גסות רוח gasut
ruach that went down to the
world, nine of them went to עילם, Elam, and one went, was
distributed throughout the rest of the
world. עילם Elam is Iran area, Persia, yeah, thank you. You know,
10 measures of beauty, nine went to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Exactly. Why are
you
nine? ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Exactly. So it's really, right, it's the polar opposite
of that except what's interesting is that in order to be here,
even the גסות רוח gasut ruach is also represented by beauty, right,
the beauty of a stork's wings, the חנופה chanufah is sort of
self-primping, right, you're making yourself look nice, and certainly in Persia, they
had a lot of riches and a lot of beauty, but along
with it was this גסות רוח gasut ruach which makes it less
beautiful, I think. אין, In, yes. לבבל נחית. LeBavel nachit. It did
this גסות רוח gasut ruach actually did go to בבל. Bavel ואישתרבובי
דאישתרבב Ve’ishtarbovei de’ishtarbav and they got confused on their way out לעילם.
le’Elam. Like spread, like spread, spread. ואישתרבובי דאישתרבב לעילם. Ve’ishtarbovei de’ishtarbav le’Elam.
It got confused and they went to עילם. Elam. Yes, because why?
Because שנער Shinar is in עילם. Elam. I see, and then it
subsequently moved to עילם. Elam. אישתרבוב Ishtarbov is to be is to
be confused and to get mixed up. גסות רוח. Gasut ruach. I
read one of the, one פירוש pirush
says that they got, they were trying to go to בבל Bavel
and they got confused and they went to עילם. Elam. דיקא נמי
דכתיב לבנו לה בית בארץ שנער. Dika nami dechtiv livno la bayit
be'eretz Shinar. This is the can read closely also that the ה
Heh doesn't have a mapik in it, therefore it means they got
confused and they ended up, oh sorry, they went to build a
house in שנער, Shinar, but they didn't actually end up in שנער,
Shinar, they ended up in עילם. Elam. Where's שנער? Shinar? I believe
in the locative אמה אחת לבידה. ama achat levida. I'm not sure.
It's not where the house is before. Is it not where the
השרון? HaSharon? Oh, okay. There's okay. The footnote there doesn't tell you
where שנער Shinar is? Somewhere in the Middle East. General region of
Mesopotamia. דניאל Daniel was in עילם. Elam. עילם, Elam, right. So that
would be, right, that's Persia. אשר בעילם המדינה ולא רבת תורה. Asher
be'Elam hamedina velo rabat Torah. No, yeah, I'm not sure. והאמר מר
סימן לגסות הרוח עניות ועניות לבבל נחית. Veha'amar mar siman legasut haruach
aniyut ve'aniyut leBavel nachit. One symbol of גסות הרוח gasut haruach is
poverty. And is בבל Bavel poor? Yeah, that's the point, that's the
question. Meaning, you say they go to בבל Bavel? and nowhere else,
but, you know, but בבל's Bavel, still poor. Yeah, in which case
they should have גסות הרוח. gasut haruach. And we also know the
opposite to be true, to be untrue, right? Persia, which we just
said has a lot of גסות הרוח gasut haruach is also not
poor. מאי עניות עניות תורה דכתיב אחות לנו קטנה ושדים אין לה.
Mai aniyut aniyut Torah dechtiv achot lanu ktana veshadayim ein la. It's
actually poverty of תורה. Torah. We have a little sister and she
has no breasts. The little sister here being, the little sister here
being Persia, and she has no breasts meaning the little sister here
I think רש״י Rashi says is דניאל, Daniel, and nobody is there
to listen to דניאל's Daniel תורה Torah in עילם. Elam. Meaning that
they are poor in תורה. Torah They have גסות הרוח gasut haruach
and they're poor in תורה Torah. there. אמר רבי יוחנן זו עילם.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan zo Elam. This is עילם. Elam. שזכתה ללמוד ולא
זכתה ללמד. shezachata lilmod velo zachata lelamed. That דניאל Daniel learned תורה
Torah but he was not זוכה zoche to teach any תורה. Torah
מאי בבל? Mai Bavel? What is the meaning of this word בבל?
Bavel. אמר רבי יוחנן בלולה במקרא בלולה במשנה בלולה בתלמוד. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan belula beMikra belula beMishna belula beTalmud. So now they finally compliment
the תורה Torah of בבל, Bavel, that all three sources of תורה
are mixed together in בבל. Bavel That you have פסוקים, psukim, you
have משנה, Mishna, and you have תלמוד Talmud all together in the
תלמוד בבלי. Talmud Bavli. Puns on words: בבל, בלולה. belula. Right, that's
what they're saying the meaning of this word בבל is. במחשכים הושיבני
כמתי עולם אמר רבי ירמיה זה תלמודה של בבל. Bemachshakim hoshivani kemetei
olam amar Rabbi Yirmiya ze Talmudah shel Bavel. I sit in darkness.
You make me sit in darkness. הושיבני שאין נוחין זה עם זה
ותלמודא ספק בידם. hoshivani she'ein nochin ze im ze vetalmuda safek beyadam.
Right? They are harsh with one another and they are in darkness
because they contradict one another and they argue, therefore their תורה is
in fact lacking. The תוספות Tosafot seem to read בלולה במקרא belula
beMikra as sort of a good thing. פירוש רבנו תם. Pirush Rabbeinu
Tam. This is the first one on the page, בלולה במקרא. belula
beMikra. פירוש רבנו תם דבתלמוד שלנו אנו פוטרים עצמנו ממה שאמרו חכמים
לעולם ישלש אדם שנותיו שליש במקרא שליש במשנה שליש בש״ס. Pirush Rabbeinu
Tam debetalmud shelanu anu potrim atzmenu mima she'amru chachamim le'olam yeshalesh adam
shnotav shlish beMikra shlish beMishna shlish beShas. The תלמוד Talmud says that
you should split your days three ways: one in learning תנ״ך, Tanach,
one third learning משנה, mishna. and one third learning תלמוד, Talmud, but
because in the תלמוד בבלי Talmud Bavli all three of those are
mixed together, you actually are יוצא yotzei all three and you don't
have to split your time between all three because you can learn
all three by just learning the בבלי. Bavli. There's always a rivalry
between Israel and Babylon. That's right. Just like today. Okay, next משנה.
mishna We saw this משנה mishna quoted yesterday. אמר לו נאמנה עלי
אבא נאמנה עלי אביך נאמנין עלי שלשה רועי בקר רבי מאיר אומר
יכול לחזור בו וחכמים אומרים אינו יכול לחזור בו. Amar lo ne'emana
alai aba ne'emana alai avicha ne'emanin alai shlosha ro'ei bakar Rabbi Meir
omer yachol lachzor bo vechachamim omrim eino yachol lachzor bo. Again, we
see that when one person says to the other, your father, my
father, or these three cow herders should be permitted as either עדים
edim or דיינים. dayanim. There's a מחלוקת machloket about what this משנה
Mishna means, מחלוקת ראשונים. machloket Rishonim. Right. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
he can renege on his word because מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin מדאורייתא
mide'oraita they are פסול. pasul חכמים Chachamim say once you accept them
as כשר, kosher, you can't go back. היה חייב לחברו שבועה. Haya
chayav lachavero shvua. If one of the litigants has to take a
שבועה. shvua. The other one ואמר לו דור לי בחיי ראשך v'amar
lo dor li b'chayei roshecha, רבי מאיר מעכב וחכמים אין מעכבין. Rabbi
Meir me'akeiv vechachamim ein me'akvin. So instead of taking this hard, this
real heavy שבועה shevuah דאורייתא, d'oraisa, he can take, he can swear
on his own life and be יוצא yotzei his שבועה. shevuah. Rabbi
Meir says he can go back on it and the חכמים Chachamim
say you can't go back on it. Again, because one doesn't actually
work דאורייתא d'oraisa and the other, sorry, the שבועה shevuah doesn't actually
work דאורייתא, d'oraisa, Rabbi Meir says because that doesn't work דאורייתא, d'oraisa,
he can go back, and the חכמים Chachamim say, no, once you
accept that it's okay, you can't go back on it. Okay גמרא.
אמר רב דימי בריה דרב נחמן בריה דרב יוסף Amar Rav Dimi
breih deRav Nachman breih deRav Yosef כגון דקבלי עליה בחד. kegon dekablei
alei bechad. This משנה Mishna is talking about when, when Rabbi נאמן
עלי אביך נאמנין עלי שלושה רועי בקר ne'eman alai avicha ne'emanin alai
shlosha ro'ei vakar is talking about when he accepts that witness as
one of two or one of three עדים eidim or witnesses depending
on which side of the מחלוקת machlokes you fall in ראשונים. Rishonim.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מחלוקת במחול לך אבל באתן לך דברי
הכל יכול לחזור בו ורבי יוחנן אמר באתן לך מחלוקת. Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel machlokes bemachol lach aval be'eten lach divrei hakol yachol
lachazor bo veRabbi Yochanan amar be'eten lach machlokes. There's a מחלוקת machlokes
here about who is saying, who is accepting these witnesses as כשר
kosher even though מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin they are פסול. pasul Is
it the, is it the, hang on. אמר שמואל מחלוקת במחול לך.
Amar Shmuel machlokes bemachol lach. שמואל Shmuel says the disagreement between the
חכמים Chachamim and Rabbi Meir is that the one who is owed
the money says, I will forgive your debt if these witnesses testify
against me, even though they're technically not כשר kosher witnesses. אבל באתן
לך דברי הכל יכול לחזור בו, Aval be'eten lach divrei hakol yachol
lachazor bo, but if the person who says, I will give you,
the person who owes the money accepts these פסול pasul witnesses as
כשר, kosher, everybody agrees that he can go back because, because דאורייתא,
d'oraisa, in order to pay המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, hamotzi mechaveiro alav
hara'aya, the person who is extracting money, he is the one who
needs to give, to bring the proof. Therefore really everybody agrees that
he can go back on it, and but Rabbi Yochanan disagrees. He
says that even, he says that the person who says, the debtor
says, I accept these פסול pasul witnesses as כשר, kosher, that's where
the disagreement is. Okay, איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, באתן לך מחלוקת אבל
במחול לך דברי הכל אין יכול לחזור בו או דלמא בין בזה
ובין בזה מחלוקת. be'eten lach machlokes aval bemachol lach divrei hakol ein
yachol lachazor bo o dilma bein bezeh uvein bezeh machlokes. So the
question is asked about Rabbi Yochanan's שיטה shita who said באתן לך
מחלוקת. be'eten lach machlokes. Is it a מחלוקת machlokes באתן לך be'eten
lach but everybody agrees אין יכול לחזור בו ein yachol lachazor bo
if the person, Rabbi Yochanan says if the debtor says, I accept
these פסול pasul witnesses, then יכול לחזור בו. yachol lachazor bo. So
is it if the, oh my gosh, this is so difficult, okay,
sorry. The Rabbi Yochanan says that the, the debtor says, I will
pay you if this פסול pasul witness testifies against me, and that
is where the מחלוקת machlokes lies. So the question is raised: באתן
לך מחלוקת אבל במחול לך דברי הכל אין יכול לחזור בו? be'eten
lach machlokes aval bemachol lach divrei hakol ein yachol lachazor bo? Is
Rabbi Yochanan's שיטה shita that if the debtor says, I will pay
you if this פסול pasul witness testifies against me, that's where the
מחלוקת machlokes is, but if the creditor says that I accept these
פסול pasul witnesses, everybody agrees that that is binding and there's no
מחלוקת, machlokes, or או דלמא בין בזה ובין בזה, o dilma bein
bezeh uvein bezeh, maybe there's a מחלוקת machlokes about both of them?
תא שמע. Ta shema. We're going to bring a proof. דאמר רבא
מחלוקת באתן לך אבל במחול לך דברי הכל אין יכול לחזור בו.
De'amar Rava machlokes be'eten lach aval bemachol lach divrei hakol ein yachol
lachazor bo. רבא Rava says that there's a מחלוקת machlokes באתן לך,
be'eten lach, which is what Rabbi Yochanan said, but במחול לך, bemachol
lach, if the debtor says, I will forgive your loan if this
פסול pasul witness testifies against me, he can not go back on
it. אי אמרת בשלמא באתן לך מחלוקת אבל במחול לך דברי הכל
אין יכול לחזור בו, Ei amrat bishlama be'eten lach machlokes aval bemachol
lach divrei hakol ein yachol lachazor bo, that so if you fall
on one side of this question of Rabbi Yochanan, then רבא Rava
supports your opinion that the מחלוקת machlokes is in מחול לך machol
lach that the debtor, that if the debtor says he's going to
forgive it, everybody agrees that he can't go back, but if the
creditor vice versa, if the debtor says, I will pay you, then
there is a מחלוקת machlokes רבי מאיר וחכמים, Rabbi Meir veChachamim, but
if the creditor says, I will forgive your loan, there is not
a מחלוקת machlokes and everybody agrees that he can't go back on
it. רבא דאמר כרבי יוחנן, Rava de'amar keRabbi Yochanan, then, then רבא
Rava agrees with Rabbi Yochanan. אלא אי אמרת בין בזו ובין בזו
מחלוקת, Ella ee amrat bein b'zo bein b'zo machlokes, רבא דאמר כמאן?
Rava de'amar keman? If both if there's a מחלוקת machlokes באתן b'eten
and מחול, machul, then who is רבא'ס Rava's opinion like? רבא טעמא
דנפשיה קאמר. Rava ta'ama d'nafshei ka'amar. רבא Rava has his own
opinion. So now we have three sides to this מחלוקת. machlokes. We
have: there is a מחלוקת machlokes in אתן לך eten lecha and
in מחול לך; machul lecha; there is only a מחלוקת machlokes in
מחול לך; machul lecha; and there is only a מחלוקת machlokes in
אתן לך. eten lecha. יישר כוח. Yasher koach. Thanks. Okay. It's going
to get
worse. איתיביה רב אחא בר תחליפא לרבא. Eiseivei Rav Acha bar Tachlifa
l'Rava. רב
אחא Rav Acha brings a tries to bring a rejection of this
opinion that we just saw from רבא, Rava, that there is a
מחלוקת machlokes in אתן לך eten lecha and not a מחלוקת machlokes
in מחול לך. machul lecha. היה חייב לחברו שבועה, Haya chayav l'chavero
shevua,
if a person is obligated to make a שבועה shevua
in court, ואמר לו ve'amar lo דור לי בחיי ראשך, dor li
bechayei roshecha רבי מאיר אומר יכול לחזור בו וחכמים אומרים אין יכול
לחזור בו. Rebbe Meir omer yachol lachzor bo v'Chachamim omrim ein yachol
lachzor bo. Where are we?
We are on the last two lines of כ"ד עמוד א'. Kaf
daled amud aleph. So the משנה Mishna, taught that if one person
is required to make a שבועה, shevua, and the other person says,
take take an oath on your life instead of this more חמור
chamur oath that you that is required
to
take in the name using the name of God as a very
heavy oath, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that he can go back
on it and the חכמים Chachamim say he cannot go back on
it. Now, רבא Rava said, oh, okay, we have he pointed, מאי
לאו באותן הנשבעין ולא משלמין דהוה ליה כמחול לך? mai lav b'oten
hanishba'in v'lo meshalmin d'hava lei kemachul lecha? Are we not talking about
a שבועה shevua that the debtor takes and then is is no
longer required—we're now on כ"ד עמוד ב' Kaf daled amud beis at
the top—are we not talking about באותן הנשבעין ולא משלמין? b'oten hanishba'in
v'lo meshalmin? Are we not talking about באותן הנשבעין b'oten hanishba'in says
רש"י, לפטור עצמן שלא ישלמו דתובע קאמר ליה דור לי ואני מחול
לך? liftor atzman shelo yeshalmu detoveia ka'amar lei dor li va'ani machul
lecha? Are we not talking about a case where the debtor said
to the creditor, take this שבועה shevua and you're then פטור pattur
from paying me, you no longer have to pay me? Which would
be a case of מחול לך, machul lecha, which would prove that
there is a מחלוקת machlokes by מחול לך machul lecha and therefore
רבא Rava is wrong. דהוה ליה כמחול לך, Dehava lei kemachul lecha,
that's like מחול לך. machul lecha. לא, באותן הנשבעין ונוטלין דהוה ליה
כאתן לך. Lo, b'oten hanishba'in venotlin dehava lei ke'eten lecha. This is
actually a case where the where the person taking the שבועה shevua
says fine, I'll take a שבועה shevua on my own life, and
then I will pay you part or all of what I owe
you. הנשבעין ונוטלין Hanishba'in venotlin says רש"י, השכיר והנגזל וכיוצא בהן דנתבע
קאמר ליה דור לי ואתן לך. hasachir vehanigzal vechayotzei bahen denitba ka'amar
lei dor li ve'eten lecha. That the שומר שכר shomer sachar or
the שומר shomer who had something stolen from him—no sorry—the paid guardian
and then something was stolen or something similar, דנתבע, denitba, that he
is the he is having the claim against him, I don't remember
the case. In any case, it's a case where the person takes
an oath and then pays part of what he owes, I believe.
Okay. ונוטלין דהוה ליה כאתן לך. Venotlin dehava lei ke'eten lecha. So
now we have we've held up רבא'ס Rava's opinion, now we still
have three sides to this מחלוקת. machlokes. והא תנא ליה רישא תנא
תולה בדעת אחרים ותנא תולה בדעת עצמו. Veha tana lei reisha tana
toleh bedaas acherim vetana toleh bedaas atzmo. I need my cheat sheet
please. Did I skip something? ונוטלין דהוה ליה כאתן לך. Venotlin dehava
lei ke'eten lecha. והא תנא ליה רישא. Veha tana lei reisha. Ah
right. We got to learn that in but if we're talking about
והא תנא ליה רישא, veha tana lei reisha, we already learned that
what we just claimed to learn from the סיפא seifa of the
משנה, Mishna. we already learned in the רישא reisha of the משנה.
Mishna רש"י says והא תנא ליה רישא דאוקמה באתן לך בתרתי למה
לי. veha tana lei reisha d'ukmah b'eten lecha betartei lama li. We
already learned in the in the רישא reisha of the משנה Mishna
that if the person if the debtor says if the creditor says...
we already learned in the רישא reisha of the משנה Mishna if
the debtor says I will pay you if we accept this פסול
pasul witness, so we don't need to learn it again in the
סיפא seifa about the שבועה. shevua. Right? We just tried to say
that the שבועה shevua was about אתן לך, eten lecha, but we
learned in the beginning of the משנה Mishna that אתן לך... eten
lecha...
about אתן לך. eten lecha. Therefore the סיפא seifa of the משנה
Mishnah, must be about מחול לך. machul lecha. No,
and then the גמרא is going to say no, we actually do
need both parts and רבא'ס Rava's opinion can still stand up. והא
תנא ליה... רישא. vehah tanna lei reisha. We already learned that in
the רישא, reisha. תנא תולה... tanna tole...
תנא ליה רישא
תנא. tanna lei reisha tanna.
I'm not sure how to parse that. מהו נשפך, mah hoh nishpach,
מהו נשפך, mah hoh nishpach, והא תנא
ליה תנא ליה רישא. vehah tanna lei tanna lei reisha.
Okay, yeah, והא תנא ליה Veha tana lei... רישא. reisha, We already
learned that in the רישא reisha that again that אתן לך, eten
lach, there's a מחלוקת. machloket. Therefore if the סיפא seifa is also
about אתן לך, eten lach, then it seems redundant. And then the
גמרא is going to say no we actually do need both. תנא
תולה בדעת אחרים ותנא תולה בדעת עצמו. Tanna tole bedat acherim vetanna
tole bedat atzmo.
That the רישא reisha of the משנה, Mishnah אבא ואביך, abba veavicha,
is about other people coming in, other פסול pasul people coming in,
and the סיפא seifa of the משנה Mishnah is about
the debtor's own דעת. dat. צריכה, tzericha, and we need both. דאי
תנא תולה בדעת אחרים בהא קאמר רבי מאיר דמצי הדר ביה משום
דלא גמר ומקני. De'i tanna tole bedat acherim bahaka amar Rabbi Meir
dematze hadar be mishum dlo gamar umakne. דאמר מי יימר דמזכי ליה,
de'amar mi yeimar demazkei lei, אבל... aval... we need both because רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir would say that in the beginning if it's תולה
בדעת אחרים, tole bedat acherim, if you're using someone else's דעת, dat,
אבא או אביך, abba o avicha, that's where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is חולק holek on the חכמים, Chachamim, he can go back because
maybe he didn't fully set his mind on them being כשר kosher
because maybe he thinks that this witness is going to testify in
his favor. אבל תולה בדעת עצמו אימא מודי להו לרבנן. Aval tole
bedat atzmo eima modei lahu lerabbanan. But if he's תולה tole on
his own דעת, dat, then in fact he was obviously settled his
mind on it because it's his own... he says it, therefore he
is committed to this דין. din. And he would and even רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir would agree with the חכמים. Chachamim. ואי אשמעינן בהא
בהא קאמרי רבנן אבל בההיא אימא מודי לרבנן. Ve'i ashmieinan bah, bah
ka-amrei rabbanan aval bahahi eima modei lerabbanan. And the and the opposite
is also true that רבנן Rabbanan say that you can be חוזר
בו, chozer bo,
if we only
learned...
if we only learned the רישא. reisha.
Right and then if we only learned the סיפא, seifa, maybe the
חכמים... Chachamim... the חכמים Chachamim would be חולק holek on רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir to say that because it's דעת עצמו, dat atzmo, he
can't be חוזר בו, chozer bo, but maybe the חכמים Chachamim would
say that if it's דעת אחרים, dat acherim, then he could in
fact go back on it because he wasn't... he didn't fully have
it in his mind to accept these witnesses.
Okay.
צריכה, tzericha, that's why you need both parts and רבא's Rava opinion
still stands. אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish. מחלוקת, machloket, okay now
we're going to have another similar
מחלוקת machloket as we had between רבא, Rava, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and רבי...
where we had רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, we had שמואל, Shmuel, שמואל,
Shmuel, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, רבא, Rava, now we're going to have
a similar another similar מחלוקת. machloket. אמר ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish אמר
ריש לקיש מחלוקת לפני
גמר דין אבל לאחר גמר דין דברי הכל אין יכול לחזור בו.
Amar Reish Lakish machloket lifnei gmar din aval le'achar gmar din divrei
hakol ein yachol lachazor bo. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says that
this מחלוקת, machloket, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים, Chachamim, is
about before they completely finished the judgment. But after they finish the
judgment, everybody agrees that you can't go back. So the litigants,
say the debtor, right we have
ראובן ושמואל. Reuven veShmuel. ראובן Reuven brings his father, שמואל Shmuel says
I'll believe your father is a witness, the father bears witness, שמואל
Shmuel loses the case, according to ריש לקיש he can no longer
even according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir... he can't go back on
it anymore. He can't go back to do what? He can't say
at once the judgment is final, he can't go back and say
I changed my mind you can't use your father as a
witness. No appeals?
Right, that's what he's saying. Right. ורבי יוחנן אמר לאחר גמר דין
מחלוקת. VeRabbi Yochanan amar le'achar gmar din machloket. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says no actually there is a מחלוקת machloket about after after
the דין din is finished. No appeals even after the trial?
I don't know. If you find new evidence after the trial is
done now you have to go back on something it maybe different
in a capital case.
I don't know.
A capital case is a whole other thing. Okay we have to
keep going here. If there was no statute of limitations. That's out
of the purview here. ורבי יוחנן אמר לאחר גמר דין מחלוקת. VeRabbi
Yochanan amar le'achar gmar din machloket. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
even after the judgment comes back the litigants can still go back
and say I no longer accept this פסול witness or this פסול
דיין pasul dayan as a דיין dayan or a witness. איבעיא להו
*Iba'ya lehu*. לאחר גמר דין מחלוקת l'achar gemar din machloket. אבל לפני
גמר דין דברי הכל יכול לחזור aval lifnei gmar din divrei hakol
yachol lachazor. בו *Leachar gmar din machloket aval lifnei gmar din divrei
hakol yachol lachazor bo*. According to the opinion of ריש לקיש *Reish
Lakish*. No, according to the opinion of ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* who
said לפני גמר דין lifnei gmar din, *lifnei gmar din*. איבעיא להו
*Iba'ya lehu*. לאחר גמר דין l'achar gemar din מחלוקת machlokes *Leachar gmar
din machloket*. Sorry. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan* who said לאחר
גמר דין achar gemar din. *leachar gmar din* is מחלוקת machlokes *machloket*.
The question is, you just said that after the דין *din* there's
a מחלוקת machlokes *machloket* רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir וחכמים *Rabbi Meir v'chachamim*,
אבל לפני גמר דין gmar din, *aval lifnei gmar din* but before
the judgment is finished דברי הכל divrei hakol. יכול לחזור בו yakhol
lachzor bo *divrei hakol yachol lachazor bo*, do the חכמים chachamim *chachamim*
agree with רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* before the judgment is
finished that each one can go back and say, I don't actually
accept your פסול *pasul* witness or פסול *pasul* judge? או דלמא *O
delma* or perhaps בין בזו בין בזו מחלוקת machlokes... *bein b'zo bein
b'zo machloket*. Maybe the חכמים chachamim. *chachamim* even agree before גמר דין
gmar din *gmar din*. Maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* agrees
with the חכמים chachamim. *chachamim*. No, maybe there's still a מחלוקת machlokes
*machloket* even before. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says that once
you say I accept this פסול *pasul* witness or judge, you can
never go back on it and the חכמים chachamim *chachamim* always say
you can go back on it. תא שמע דאמר רבא tashma damar
Rava *Ta shema d'amar Rava*, קיבל עליו קרוב או פסול kibel alav
karov o pasul לפני גמר דין יכול לחזור בו lifnei gmar din
yachol lachazor bo. לאחר גמר דין אין יכול לחזור le-achar gmar din
ein yachol lachazor. בו *kibel alav karov o pasul lifnei gmar
din yachol lachazor bo leachar gmar din ein yachol lachazor bo*. רבא
Rava
*Rava* says that if someone accepts a קרוב או פסול *karov o
pasul* witness before the end of the judgment he can go back
on it. A קרוב *karov* is a relative. A קרוב *karov* is
a relative. If he accepts a relative or someone else who is
otherwise פסול *pasul*
before the judgment is laid down, he can go back on it,
which would be the opinion of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*.
לאחר גמר דין אין יכול לחזור le-achar gmar din ein yachol lachazor,
בו *Leachar gmar din ein yachol lachazor bo*. Afterwards he can't go
back on it, which would be the opinion of the חכמים chachamim
*chachamim*. אי אמר בשלמא לאחר גמר דין gmar din. מחלוקת machlokes אבל
לפני גמר דין דברי הכל יכול לחזור aval lifne gemar din divre
hakol yakhol lachzor, בו *I amar bishlama leachar gmar din machloket aval
lifnei gmar din divrei hakol yachol lachazor bo*, רבא דאמר כרבי יוחנן
ואליבא דרבנן Rava de'amar kerabbi Yochanan va'aliba derabbanan. *Rava d'amar k'Rabbi Yochanan
v'aliba d'rabanan*. Okay. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
*Rabbi Yochanan* said that, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan,
*Rabbi Yochanan* said אחר גמר דין achar gemar din, *achar gmar din*
there's a מחלוקת machlokes *machloket*. The question is raised, before גמר דין
gmar din? *gmar din* is there a מחלוקת machlokes *machloket* or does
everybody agree that he can go back. רבא Rava *Rava* comes along
and says
before the דין *din* is finished he can go back on it,
but after the דין *din* is finished,
after the דין *din* is finished he cannot go back on it,
which would be the opinion of the רבנן Rabbanan. *rabanan*. If he's
saying the opinion of the רבנן *rabanan* according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan*, then what he's saying is... Wait.
רבא Rava דאמר כרבי
יוחנן
ואליבא דרבנן *Rava d'amar k'Rabbi Yochanan v'aliba d'rabanan*. That doesn't seem right.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. אמר לאחר גמר דין gmar din. מחלוקת machlokes.
*Rabbi Yochanan amar leachar gmar din machloket*, but he just said אין
יכול לחזור ein yachol lachazor? בו אחר גמר דין gmar din *ein
yachol lachazor bo achar gmar din*. אחר גמר דין gmar din מחלוקת
machlokes. *Achar gmar din machloket*. איבעיא להו *Iba'ya lehu*. לאחר גמר דין
gmar din מחלוקת machlokes אבל לפני גמר דין דברי הכל יכול לחזור
lifne gemar din divre hakol yakhol lachzor. בו או דלמא בין בזו
בין בזו מחלוקת machlokes *Leachar gmar din machloket aval lifnei gmar din
divrei hakol yachol lachazor bo o delma bein b'zo bein b'zo machloket*.
Okay, I have to make a chart.
So you have ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish*.
This is לפני *lifnei*, this is אחר גמר דין gmar din
*achar gmar din*. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*
says לפני גמר דין gemar din, מחלוקת machlokes *lifnei gmar din machloket*,
right?
Let me know if I write something wrong just based on my
memory. מחלוקת machlokes *Machloket*. אחר גמר דין gemar din אין יכול yachol,
דברי הכל divrei hakol *Achar
gmar din ein yachol divrei hakol*.
Is that right? Yeah, cannot go back. And רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* says לאחר גמר דין gemar din מחלוקת
machlokes *leachar gmar din machloket*. So the question becomes here: is
it מחלוקת machlokes *machloket*
or is it
יכול לחזור yachol lachazor *yachol lachazor*? And that's what do the חכמים
chachamim? *chachamim* think?
Is it מחלוקת machlokes *machloket* or does everybody agree יכול לחזור yachol
lachazor בו *yachol lachazor bo*? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan אמר לאחר גמר
דין gemar din
מחלוקת machlokes. *Rabbi Yochanan amar leachar gmar din machloket*. איבעיא להו לאחר
גמר דין gemar din, *Iba'ya lehu leachar gmar din*. גמר דין g'mar
din מחלוקת machlokes אבל לפני גמר דין דברי הכל יכול לחזור. yachol
lachazor, לדברי הכל, lidivrei hakol, or is it even a מחלוקת machlokes
here that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say אין יכול לחזור? yachol
lachazor? So רבא Rava comes along and says
תא שמע
דאמר רבא קיבל עליו קרוב או פסול damar Rava kibel alav karov
o pasul לפני גמר דין יכול
לחזור בו. lifnei gmar din yachol lachazor bo That would be this.
אחר גמר דין אינו יכול לחזור בו. achar gmar din eino yachol
lachazor bo. רבא אמר Rava amar to רבי... I got lost again.
דאמר רבא damar Rava, קיבל עליו קרוב או פסול לפני גמר דין
יכול לחזור בו lifnei gmar din yachol lachazor bo, אבל לאחר גמר
דין אין יכול לחזור בו. aval achar gmar din ein yachol lachazor
bo.
That's
אליבא דרבנן. aliba de-rabbanan. אלא יכול לחזור בו, ela yachol lachazor bo,
which would be דברי הכל.
Or it's according to
רבנן. לאחר גמר דין אין יכול yachol. לחזור. Right. רבי מאיר... Rabbi
Meir
gosh, why am I so confused? Okay. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says, we know for sure that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, according
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan we know for sure says that after
the גמר דין, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds that you can go
back on it, and the חכמים chachamim hold that you cannot go
back on it. The question
is: Does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. hold that before גמר דין you
can go back on it? רבא Rava, says that
לפני גמר דין יכול לחזור בו, which could either be רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan or
the חכמים. chachamim לאחר גמר דין אין יכול לחזור, which רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir we know for sure does not say after גמר דין.
Therefore this has to be the שיטה shita of the חכמים. chachamim
Does that make sense? What do you mean by the word מחלוקת
machloket there? מחלוקת... machloket no, I don't understand the word... no no,
the מחלוקת machloket is... there's two options. יכול לחזור or לא יכול
לחזור. lo yachol lachazor. This is לדברי הכל. lidivrei hakol. So they
should be on the side, like ריש לקיש, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan
and then דברי הכל would be another... this within... so this
מחלוקת machloket here represents חכמים chachamim say... right, so maybe our chart
was improved if we have ריש לקיש, רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan. and
then חכמים Chachamim and we just state each one's opinion
because when we write... this is all רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
No, sorry, this is
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Sorry, we don't need ריש לקיש at this
point. We know what ריש לקיש thinks. We don't really need this.
ריש לקיש thinks that there's a מחלוקת machloket here and there's no
מחלוקת machloket here. So, okay, he can't think... sorry, he can't think
there is a מחלוקת. machloket He has to have an opinion about
the מחלוקת. machloket. So he thinks that they can only have one
of two opinions: יכול לחזור or לא יכול לחזור. lo yachol lachazor.
No,
because there ריש לקיש and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, are not having
a מחלוקת machloket. about יכול לחזור, אינו יכול לחזור. eino yachol lachazor.
They're having a מחלוקת machloket about when
the מחלוקת machloket in the משנה Mishnah is.
Is the מחלוקת machloket. in the משנה Mishnah taking place before or
after גמר דין? Yeah? Okay. So, מחלוקת machloket here... we know רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. came along and said there's a מחלוקת אחר גמר
דין, machlokes achar gmar din, right? The מחלוקת in the משנה Mishnah
is talking about after גמר דין. The question is, before גמר דין
is there still a מחלוקת רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. חכמים? Chachamim, Or
does even רבי מאיר Rabi Meir agree before גמר דין that
he can go back on it? No, sorry, this is why I'm
confused because I kept saying it backwards. Do even the חכמים Chachamim
think before גמר דין he can go back on it? Right, חכמים
Chachamim, say... in the משנה mishna we know חכמים Chachamim
אינו יכול eino yachol and רבי מאיר says יכול, right?
I can't write this morning.
רבי מאיר says יכול.
So we know רבי יוחנן said that this... so this is what's
represented by the word מחלוקת. Okay? So we know רבי יוחנן said
this מחלוקת exists here. The question is: Does this מחלוקת exist here
as well, לפני גמר דין, or do even the חכמים agree before
גמר דין with רבי מאיר יכול לחזור? Good? Okay. So then רבא
Rava says...
boy this isn't going to work very well for the voice recording,
sorry people out there in podcast
land... דאמר רבא, I hate when I listen to a podcast and
they describe things that they see. I can't stand it and they
don't describe it, you just have to watch on YouTube. Okay, so
רבא says, בפני גמר דין יכול לחזור בו, bifne gemar din yakhol
lachzor bo, which is a question, right? That could be right now
either the חכמים or רבי מאיר. ולאחר גמר דין אין יכול לחזור
בו, ul'achar gemar din ein yakhol lachzor bo, which is the חכמים,
right? It can't be רבי מאיר according to רבי יוחנן. Therefore, אי
אמרת בשלמא לאחר גמר דין מחלוקת, ei amrat bishlama l'achar gemar din
machloket, boom, אבל לפני גמר דין דברי הכל יכול לחזור, רבא דאמר
כרבי יוחנן ואליבא דרבנן. אלא אי אמרת בין בזה ובין בזה, ela
ei amrat bein beze uvein beze, אי אמרת בין בזה ובין בזה
מחלוקת, ei amrat bein beze uvein beze machloket, if you're going to
say there's a מחלוקת here and here, רבא דאמר כמאן? Rava de'amar
keman? רבא'ס Rava's שיטה shitta makes no sense. אלא לאו שמע מינה
לאחר גמר דין מחלוקת, ela lav shema mina l'achar gemar din machloket,
שמע מינה. shema mina. There's a מחלוקת לאחר גמר דין according to
רבי יוחנן. This is according to רבא, according to רבי יוחנן. There's
a מחלוקת about אחר גמר דין, but לפני גמר דין דברי הכל
יכול
לחזור.
This person has called me twice, so I'll call them back in
a minute. Okay.
Good.
So רבא says that according to רבי יוחנן, there's a מחלוקת after
גמר דין, but before גמר דין the חכמים agree with רבי מאיר.
שמע מינה לאחר גמר דין מחלוקת. shema mina l'achar gemar din machloket.
Okay. Let's try to get a few more lines done before we,
cause tomorrow we have a whole another... I guess we'll try to
get to this משנה mishna here. שלח ליה רב נחמן בר רב
חסדא לרב נחמן בר יצחק, shlach le rav Nachman bar rav Chisda
l'rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, ילמדנו רבינו, yelamdenu rabbeinu, teach us rabbi, לפני
גמר דין מחלוקת או לאחר גמר דין מחלוקת? lifne gemar din machloket
o l'achar gemar din machloket? So again, same question. Before גמר דין
מחלוקת or after? Now this is trying to decide between ריש לקיש
and רבי יוחנן. Where's the מחלוקת taking place in the... where's the
מחלוקת in our משנה mishnah taking place? Before they finish the judgment
or after they finish the judgment? והלכה כדברי מי? vehalakha kedivre mi?
And who's the הלכה halakha like? שלח ליה, shlach le, they said,
לאחר גמר דין מחלוקת. After the גמר דין is a מחלוקת. והלכה
machloket vehalakha... כדברי חכמים, and the הלכה halakha is like דברי חכמים,
divre Chachamim, that יכול לחזור בו before גמר דין, but אינו יכול
לחזור בו eino yakhol lachzor bo לאחר גמר דין. רב אשי אמר
הכי שלח ליה, rav Ashi amar hachi shlach le, באתן לך מחלוקת
או במחול לך מחלוקת? be'eten lekha machloket o be'machul lekha machloket? Actually,
the letter that was sent was about our first מחלוקת. Is it
the creditor or the debtor who is accepting the פסול witness or
דיין? dayan? והלכה כדברי מי? vehalakha kedivre mi? And who's the הלכה
halakha like? שלח ליה באתן לך מחלוקת. shlach le be'eten lekha machloket.
The מחלוקת is באתן לך, be'eten lekha, is that the debtor says
'I will, I will pay you'.
I'm sorry, I have to take this, this person's calling me three
times.
Hello.
Yeah.
This is not a good time.
Right, well it's scheduled, it's scheduled for Thursday, and today's Wednesday.
Yep. Okay. Bye.
Sorry.
Okay. מחלוקת
והלכה... רב
אשי. rav Ashi. So we have רב אשי. rav Ashi. אמר הכי.
amar hachi. שלח ליה באתן לך
מחלוקת shlach le be'eten lekha machloket או במחול לך מחלוקת? o be'machul
lekha machloket? Who is saying 'I accept your פסול witness or דיין'?
dayan
והלכה כדברי מי? vehalakha kedivre mi? And who's the הלכה halakha like?
באתן לך מחלוקת. be'eten lekha machloket. The מחלוקת is like the debtor
says 'I will accept your פסול witness or פסול judge', והלכה כדברי
חכמים, vehalakha kedivre Chachamim,
and the הלכה halakha is like that of the חכמים, that אינו
יכול לחזור בו. eino yakhol lachzor bo. בסורא מתנו הכי, besura matnu
hachi, in סורא Sura they taught like we just said, ובפומבדיתא מתנו
הכי, uvepumbedita matnu hachi, they teach the following: אמר רב חנינא בר
שלמיא שלחו ליה מבי רב לשמואל ילמדנו רבינו. amar rav Chanina bar
Shalmaya shalchu le mibei rav li'shmuel yelamdenu rabbeinu. ילמדנו רבינו לפני גמר
דין וקנו מידו מאי. yelamdenu rabbeinu lifnei g'mar din vekanu miyado mai.
Excuse me. If this all happened before גמר דין and but there
was an act of קנין kinyan done, what's the הלכה? halacha? שלח
להו, shalach lehu, he sends back, אין לאחר קנין כלום. ein leachar
kinyan klum. After a קנין kinyan is done, you can't change anything
that's happened. Therefore, there's no, once a קנין kinyan is done, there's
no מחלוקת. Even the, even רבי מאיר agrees with the חכמים if
a קנין kinyan is done, then... What's a קנין? kinyan? A, oh
sorry, an act of acquisition is done. Of when? Of money. קנין
kinyan is money. But how does that take place in the? The,
the debtor says, "I will pay you, I accept your פסול witness
and I will pay you if he testifies against me," and then
he pays and there's an act of קנין kinyan done, then everything
is set in stone and there's no longer any room to go
back because קנין kinyan is the final word and it also becomes
clear, right, we had a מחלוקת at the beginning of the page,
is it, maybe it's about גמר דעת. g'mar da'at. So if there's
an act of קנין kinyan done and he pays them, then obviously
there's a גמר דעת g'mar da'at there, therefore the word is final.
Okay, we'll stop there for today and continue tomorrow with the משנה
on the bottom of כ"ד עמוד ב', Kaf Daled Amud Bet, God
willing.