Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is צדי Tsadi סנהדרין
Sanhedrin 90 we pick up where we finished the פרק perek and
starting a new one we pick up at the bottom of פט
עמוד ב Peh Tet Amud Bet 89B תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan six
lines from the bottom near the end of a line we're in
the middle of a discussion about a case of a נביא navi
who
testifies not testifies prophesies something that he did not a prophecy he
did not receive or prophesies in the name of another god and
that's חנק chenek and as and also people that did not listen
to the words of a prophet which is מיתה בידי שמים misa
b'yedei shamayim which leads to a whole question how do you know
who is a prophet whether you're obligated to listen to them why
did יצחק Yitzchak listen to אברהם Avraham which gets us into the
whole אגדתא agadata about עקידת יצחק akeidas Yitzchak but now we are
going to deal with a case that has come up before not
somebody who prophesies in the name of עבודה זרה avoda zara but
somebody who has says that they have a prophecy and is telling
people to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara and that appears in the
תורה Torah right before the פרשה parsha of מסית mases and we
know that a מסית mases an individual who entices people to עבודה
זרה avoda zara gets סקילה skila so what about somebody who is
prophesies and tells people to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara so let's
take a look six lines from the bottom פט עמוד ב Peh
Tet Amud Bet תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan נביא שהדיח בסקילה navi shehidiach
biskila so he is trying to push people off the path and
get them to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara gets סקילה skila just
like the מסית mases רבי שמעון אומר בחנק Rabbi Shimon Omer be'chenek
נביא navi gets חנק chenek מדיחי עיר הנדחת בסקילה midichei ir nidachas
biskila how about the people that cause the entire city to worship
עבודה זרה avoda zara they get סקילה skila we know that the
people themselves get חרב cherev but what about the מדיחין medichin they
get סקילה skila רבי שמעון אומר בחנק Rabbi Shimon Omer be'chenek Rabbi
Shimon says בחנק be'chenek
now if an individual who is מסית mases gets סקילה skila it
makes sense that a נביא navi who is מסית mases or somebody
who is מסית את הרבים mases es harabbim should also get סקילה
skila the weightiest of punishments it's quite shocking that Rabbi Shimon says
both of those get חנק chenek so let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says about this okay נביא שהדיח בסקילה navi shehidiach biskila מאי
טעמא דרבנן mai ta'ama de'rabbanan
what's the reason the Rabbis say that אתיא הדחה הדחה ממסית asya
hadacha hadacha mimases
the same way מסית mases which appears right after the נביא navi
case of getting people to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara says כי
ביקש להדיחך ki vikaish lehadichacha and here also it says כי ביקש
להדיחך ki vikaish lehadichacha
so it's the exact same language so the same way we know
that a מסית mases gets סקילה skila the same is true about
a נביא navi that is doing the same thing מה להלן בסקילה
אף כאן בסקילה ma le'halan biskila af kan biskila ורבי שמעון v'Rabbi
Shimon and Rabbi Shimon would say מיתה כתיב ביה misa ksiv bei
no it just says ומת u'mas so that's a simple מיתה misa
וכל מיתה אמורה בתורה סתם אינה אלא חנק v'kol misa amura batorah
stam eina ela chenek so that's just straight חנק chenek I don't
buy the גזירה שוה gezeira shava again quite ironic that the נביא
navi gets a lesser punishment than the normal individual that's מסית mases
מדיחי עיר הנדחת בסקילה midichei ir nidachas biskila
now how about the מדיחי עיר הנדחת midichei ir nidachas so the
Rabbis are consistent if the מסית mases is getting סקילה skila everybody's
getting סקילה skila for causing people to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara
מאי טעמא דרבנן mai ta'ama de'rabbanan
what's the reason of the Rabbis גמרי הדחה הדחה gamri hadacha hadacha
because they make the same גזירה שוה gezeira shava as well
here או ממסית או מנביא שהדיח o mimases o minavi shehidiach here
also
it's called an עיר הנדחת ir hanidachas they were מדיח mediach says
the same word הדחה hadacha and therefore everyone we already know that
the מסית mases gets סקילה skila and we said the נביא navi
gets סקילה skila that causes עבודה זרה avoda zara so מדיחי עיר
הנדחת midichei ir nidachas also get סקילה skila ורבי שמעון v'Rabbi Shimon
but Rabbi Shimon would say גמרי הדחה הדחה מנביא gamri hadacha hadacha
minavi no
no no I am going to link it to the נביא navi
I've established that the נביא navi is just says ומת u'mas a
simple חנק chenek so the same is going to be true about
מדיחי עיר הנדחת midichei ir nidachas so quite interesting these two things
which you would think are more חמור chamur actually get a lesser
form of
מיתה misa וליגמר ממסית v'ligmar mimases why doesn't he learn it out
from
מסית mases דנין מסית רבים ממסית רבים danin mases rabbim mimases rabbim
no because I have the מדיחי עיר הנדחת midichei ir nidachas they're
causing a whole city to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara I have
the נביא navi the context in the תורה Torah is the נביא
navi is trying to get the masses to worship עבודה זרה avoda
zara since I'm going to say that the נביא navi is going
to get חנק chenek I'll say the same about מדיחי עיר הנדחת
midichei ir nidachas it's both cases of רבים rabbim ואין דנין מסית
רבים ממסית יחיד v'ein danin mases rabbim mimases yachid and I won't
learn it out from the case of יחיד yachid again it points
to the irony but that's a special case of
סקילה skila אדרבה דנין הדיוט מהדיוט ואין דנין הדיוט מנביא aderaba danin
hediyot me'hediyot v'ein danin hediyot minavi no let's say the opposite you
know let's make נביא navi a special case but מדיחי עיר הנדחת
midichei ir nidachas are normal people so if an individual is מדיח
mediach individuals gets סקילה skila so when they're individuals who are not
נביאים nevi'im are מדיח mediach an entire city they should certainly get
סקילה skila or not certainly but at least make that גזירה שוה
gezeira shava those are more similar so the גמרא Gemara says רבי
שמעון כיון שהדיח אין לך הדיוט גדול מזה Rabbi Shimon keivan shehidiach
ein lecha hediyot gadol mizeh but Rabbi Shimon says you know a
נביא navi who is telling people to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara
is not functioning as a true נביא navi so that does not
make him a special category so once I establish that the נביא
navi gets חנק chenek I'm going to say the same about מדיחי
עיר הנדחת midichei ir nidachas okay quite ironic אמר רב חסדא Amar
Rav Chisda says רב חסדא Rav Chisda מחלוקת בעוקר הגוף דעבודה כוכבים
machlokes be'oker haguf de'avoda kochavim the debate of the Rabbis and Rabbi
Shimon by a נביא navi is a case of עוקר הגוף דעבודה
כוכבים oker haguf de'avoda kochavim וקיום מקצת וביטול מקצת דעבודה כוכבים v'kiyum
miktzas u'bitul miktzas de'avoda kochavim so this case of the נביא שהדיח
navi shehidiach is talking about a case of either that he is
עוקר כל הגוף, oker kol haguf, he is saying like there's no
עבודה זרה avoda zara in the world, you go ahead worship all
עבודה זרהs avoda zara that you want, God is telling me to
tell you this, or בעוקר הגוף דעבודת כוכבים ba'oker haguf d'avodas kochavim
or כיצד קיום מקצת וביטול מקצת דעבודת כוכבים. keitzad kiyum miktzas u-vittul
miktzas d'avodas kochavim. This עבודה זרה avoda zara you can worship, that
one you can't. He's telling you to do it partially. Either way,
that's the case in the Torah and they're debating, is it סקילה
sekila or חנק? chenek? Why? Because what's the פסוקים pesukim in the
Torah, here are the פסוקים. pesukim. So this is דברים י"ג. Devarim
Yud Gimmel. כי יקום בקרבך נביא או חולם חלום ונתן אליך אות
או מופת ובא האות והמופת אשר דבר אליך לאמר נלכה אחרי אלוהים
אחרים אשר לא ידעתם ונעבדם. Ki yakum bekirbecha navi o cholem chalom
venatan elecha os o mofes uva ha'os vehamofes asher diber elecha l'emor
nelcha acharei elohim acherim asher lo yedatam vena'avdem.
So he's מדיח את הרבים, mediach es harabbim, אלוהים אחרים, elohim acherim,
and then it says לא תשמע אל דברי הנביא ההוא כי מנסה
אתכם lo tishmah el divrei hanavi hahu ki menaseh eschem etc. אחרי
ה' אלוהיכם תלכו acharei Hashem elokeichem telechu והנביא ההוא או חולם החלום
ההוא יומת כי דבר סרה על ה' אלוהיכם המוציא אתכם מארץ מצרים
והפודך מבית עבדים להדיחך. vehanavi hahu o cholem hachalom hahu yumas ki
diber sarah al Hashem elokeichem hamotzi eschem me'eretz mitzrayim vehapodecha mibes avadim
lehadi-chacha.
So there's the להדיחך lehadi-chacha that makes the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah
to the מסית, meisit, which is exactly the next פסוק pasuk is
the classic מסית, meisit, מן הדרך min haderech from the way, even
מקצת הדרך. miktzas haderech. So beginning it says let's worship עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, that's עוקר כל הגוף, oker kol haguf, and then it's
מן הדרך min haderech even a case of just some עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. Both of those are what's being referred to in the
פסוק. pasuk. רחמנא אמר מן הדרך אפילו מקצת הדרך. Rachmana amar min
haderech afilu miktzas haderech. אבל, Aval, third line from the top here,
עוקר הגוף דשאר מצוות דברי הכל בחנק. oker haguf d'shar mitzvos divrei
hakol b'chenek. If it's a case that somebody just
says going back to the case of our משנה, mishna, that's actually
a completely different case in the Torah, that's not דברים י"ג, Devarim
Yud Gimmel, that's דברים י"ח, Devarim Yud Ches, where it's speaking about
not somebody that's telling you to worship עבודה זרה avoda zara but
a נביא navi that is testifying falsely, a
נביא שקר. navi sheker. They're both שקר sheker but anyway it's a
different category. That's דברים י"ח. Devarim Yud Ches. And that case in
דברים י"ח, Devarim Yud Ches, if you remember in our משנה, mishna,
was a case of a נביא שקר navi sheker was בחנק. b'chenek.
So that's different than a נביא שהדיח. navi she'hidi'ach. And that's a
case of somebody that is... so that
is
דברים
י"ח כ', Devarim Yud Ches Chaf, אך הנביא
אשר יזיד לדבר דבר בשמי את אשר לא צויתיו לדבר ואשר ידבר
בשם אלוהים אחרים ומת הנביא ההוא. ach hanavi asher yazid ledaber davar
bishmi es asher lo tzivisiv ledaber va'asher yedaber beshem elohim acherim umes
hanavi hahu. That's simple מיתה, misa, that's חנק, chenek, that's not a
case of נביא שהדיח, navi she'hidi'ach, that's just נביא שקר. navi sheker.
And one of the ways you know he's a נביא שקר navi
sheker is that he's עוקר כל הגוף. oker kol haguf. He says
there's no longer a מצוה mitzvah to wear תפילין. tefillin. If he's
just עוקר מקצת הגוף oker miktzas haguf like אליהו בהר הכרמל, Eliyahu
b'Har HaKarmel, sometimes you can override temporarily, but an עוקר כל הגוף,
oker kol haguf, that's a
נביא שקר. navi sheker. אבל עוקר הגוף דשאר מצוות דברי הכל בחנק.
Aval oker haguf d'shar mitzvos divrei hakol b'chenek. That puts him in
the simple נביא שקר navi sheker category, everybody agrees that's חנק. chenek.
וקיום מקצת וביטול מקצת דבשאר מצוות, Ve-kiyum miktzas u-vittul miktzas debishar mitzvos,
and if it's just telling you to not completely eradicate but like
a partial override like אליהו בהר הכרמל, Eliyahu b'Har HaKarmel,
דברי הכל פטור, divrei hakol pator, everybody says he's exempt, not just
exempt, like that sometimes
happens. So that's distinguishing between נביא שהדיח navi she'hidi'ach and נביא שקר.
navi sheker. מסיב רב המנונא, Masiv Rav Hamnuna, רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna
challenged that. ללכת, Laleches, it says the פסוק pasuk is again והנביא
ההוא או חולם החלום ההוא יומת כי דבר סרה על ה' אלוהיכם
המוציא אתכם מארץ מצרים והפודך מבית עבדים להדיחך מן הדרך אשר צוך
ה' אלוהיך ללכת בה. vehanavi hahu o cholem hachalom hahu yumas ki
diber sarah al Hashem elokeichem hamotzi eschem me'eretz mitzrayim vehapodecha mibes avadim
lehadi-chacha min haderech asher tzivecha Hashem elokecha laleches bah. Again this is
דברים י"ג Devarim Yud Gimmel by the נביא שהדיח. navi she'hidi'ach. So
now we're going to do a דרשה drasha on ללכת בה. laleches
bah. Here's a ברייתא. braisa. ללכת זו מצות עשה בה זו מצות
לא תעשה. Laleches zu mitzvas asei bah zu mitzvas lo sa'asei. So
it sounds like this case of the נביא שהדיח navi she'hidi'ach it
could involve telling you to violate a מצות עשה. mitzvas asei. And
we're saying this is all telling you to worship עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. So he says one minute, that doesn't fit your category. אי
סלקא דעתך בעבודת כוכבים Ei salka dachshach b'avodas kochavim and if you're
limiting דברים י"ג Devarim Yud Gimmel to the case where they're saying
סקילה sekila according to the רבנן Rabbanan and it's a case of
עבודה זרה avoda zara which is clearly the context of the פסוק,
pasuk, but עשה בעבודת כוכבים היכי משכחת לה, asei b'avodas kochavim heichi
mishkachas lah, what's the scenario that you have that? That there was
a מצות עשה mitzvas asei of עבודה זרה avoda zara he's telling
you to violate. It's all לא תעשהs. lo sa'asei תרגמה רב חסדא
ונתצתם. Targema Rav Chisda venitatztem. The מצוה mitzvah to destroy the places
of worship.
So that's fascinating. If a נביא navi tells you to not do
the positive מצוה mitzvah to destroy the places of worship of עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, not even tells you to worship עבודה זרה, avoda
zara, that would put him in the נביא שהדיח navi she'hidi'ach category.
Not a נביא שקר navi sheker category, a נביא שהדיח navi she'hidi'ach
category just telling you not to destroy the places of worship. So
that's one way of reading it, trying to incorporate this דרשה drasha
of ללכת, laleches, but still keeping דברים י"ג Devarim Yud Gimmel to
all be about worshipping עבודה זרה. avoda zara. רב המנונא אמר, Rav
Hamnuna amar, now רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna says no, מחלוקת בעוקר הגוף
בין בעבודת כוכבים בין בשאר מצוות וקיום מקצת וביטול מקצת דעבודת כוכבים
רחמנא אמר מן הדרך אפילו מקצת הדרך. machlokas b'oker haguf bein b'avodas
kochavim bein b'shar mitzvos v'kiyum miktzas u-vittul miktzas d'avodas kochavim Rachmana amar
min haderech afilu miktzas haderech.
רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna says no, I actually think that if a
נביא navi is עוקר כל הגוף oker kol haguf that puts him
in the נביא שהדיח navi she'hidi'ach category. A נביא navi who is
telling you the דברים י"ג Devarim Yud Gimmel category. A נביא navi
who is telling you whether it's to worship עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah,
you know, all עבודה זרה's Avodah Zarah מותר, muttar, some עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah מותר, muttar, or he's trying to be מבטל mivatel part
of the תורה, Torah, there's no longer מצות ציצית, mitzvos tzitzis, that
is ultimately being מבטל mivatel part of the תורה Torah is conceptually
in the same category of telling you to be worship עבודה זרה.
Avodah Zarah. It's not just that he's telling you something false. He's
fundamentally challenging the core faith. So it's an interesting conceptual point. So
he puts עוקר כל הגוף oker kol haguf in this נביא שהדיח
navi shehidiyach category and says according to the רבנן Rabbanan who say
סקילה, skila, that would not be a נביא שקר, navi sheker, that
would be in the נביא שהדיח navi shehidiyach category. Okay. בין בין
בשאר מצוות קיום מקצת וביטול מקצת דעבודת כוכבים ודעבודת כוכב bein bein
b'shahr mitzvos kiyum miktzas u'bitul miktzas d'avodas kochavim u'd'avodas kochav רחמנא אמר
מן הדרך אפילו מקצת הדרך. Rachmana amar min haderech afilu miktzas haderech.
אבל קיום מקצת וביטול מקצת בשאר מצוות דברי הכל פטור. aval kiyum
miktzas u'bitul miktzas b'shahr mitzvos divrei hakol patur. Okay,
but again if it's other מצוות mitzvos like אליהו הנביא Eliyahu Hanavi
on הר הכרמל, Har HaCarmel, like you know אברהם ויצחק Avraham v'Yitzchak
or whatever, that temporary override that's possible that God is saying. So
that's a really fascinating and that would be the ללכת, laleches, ללכת
laleches is even a מצות עשה mitzvas asei if he's totally trying
to eradicate a מצות עשה. mitzvas asei. Okay, so that is a
fascinating conceptual point that that makes him not just a נביא שקר,
navi sheker, somebody who's trying to re-represent that there's no longer this
מצוה mitzvah in the תורה Torah fundamentally is a נביא שהדיח navi
shehidiyach category. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tnu Rabanan, next point. המתנבא לעקור דבר
מן התורה חייב לקיים מקצת ולבטל מקצת רבי שמעון פוטר ובעבודת כוכבים
אפילו אמר היום עבדו למחר בטלו
דברי הכל בטלו? Hamisnabe l'akor davar min hatorah chayav l'kayem miktzas u'levatel
miktzas Rabi Shimon patur u'b'avodas kochavim afilu amar hayom ovdo l'machar batlo
divrei hakol batlo? No, not next point. We're still within, we're still
within our debate. Okay, but now we're going to see how this
ברייתא braisa fits within this debate of you know of רב המנונא
Rav Hamnuna
and רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. So let's take a look. Okay. המתנבא
לעקור דבר מן התורה, Hamisnabe l'akor davar min hatorah, if somebody's tries
to uproot it gives prophecy to uproot an entire principle in the
תורה, Torah, חייב, chayav, he's חייב. chayav.
We don't know חייב chayav yet for what. לקיים מקצת ולבטל מקצת
רבי שמעון פוטר, L'kayem miktzas u'levatel miktzas Rabi Shimon patur, to establish
some and uproot some רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon exempts, which is fascinating
because it's not just רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon exempts, that actually happens
sometimes okay like we established. ובעבודת כוכבים U'b'avodas kochavim but by עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah אפילו אמר היום עבדו למחר בטלו, afilu amar hayom
ovdo l'machar batlo,
even if he says just for today worship it in that case
דברי הכל חייב, divrei hakol chayav, everybody agrees, not only רבי שמעון
Rabi Shimon everybody agrees you're חייב. chayav. So this is a very
unclear ברייתא, braisa, so let's see how we unpack this. אביי סבר
כרב חסדא, Abaye savra k'Rav Chisda, אביי Abaye holds like רב חסדא
Rav Chisda that basically says that anything that's not עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah related is in the נביא שקר navi sheker category. Okay. ומתרצה
כרב חסדא U'metartzah k'Rav Chisda and
explains it like רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. רבא סבר כרב המנונא ומתרצה
כרב המנונא Rava savra k'Rav Hamnuna metartzah k'Rav Hamnuna and רבא Rava
goes like רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna that עוקר הכל oker hakol is
in the נביא שהדיח navi shehidiyach category. So let's see how this
works out. אביי סבר כרב חסדא ומתרצה כרב חסדא. Abaye savra k'Rav
Chisda metartzah k'Rav Chisda. המתנבא לעקור דבר מן התורה, Hamisnabe l'akor davar
min hatorah, if you're trying to uproot something completely דברי הכל בחנק
divrei hakol b'chenek then you're in the נביא navi but not עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah related, סתם stam uprooting something, that puts you in
the נביא שקר navi sheker category that's דברים י"ח, Devarim Yud Ches,
that's our משנה, Mishna, that's חנק. chenek. Okay. So המתנבא לעקור דבר
מן התורה חייב, hamisnabe l'akor davar min hatorah chayav, meaning חייב chayav
with חנק chenek and no debate. לקיים מקצת ולבטל מקצת, L'kayem miktzas
u'levatel miktzas,
if it is to do do we're in the שאר מצוות shahr
mitzvos not in עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah category, to override you know
to temporarily override partially etc not a total עוקר, oker, רבי שמעון
פוטר ורבנן Rabi Shimon poter u'd'ravanan it doesn't just mean רבי שמעון
Rabi Shimon it means רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon and the רבנן. Rabbanan.
Okay, רש"י Rashi explains like why you had to make the point
of רבי שמעון. Rabi Shimon. But we'll bracket that for now. But
the first part of this ברייתא braisa forget the fact that it
just says רבי שמעון, Rabi Shimon, it's talking about שאר מצוות shahr
mitzvos and it's saying חייב chayav and חנק chenek if it's עוקר
הכל, oker hakol, if it's מקצת miktzas then that's not a נביא
שקר. navi sheker. ובעבודת כוכבים U'b'avodas kochavim
and then continuing to read the ברייתא braisa אפילו אמר היום עבדו
למחר בטלו דברי הכל חייב. afilu amar hayom ovdo l'machar batlo divrei
hakol chayav. ובעבודת כוכבים אפילו אמר היום עבדו למחר בטלו חייב מר
כי איתיה ומר כי איתיה, U'b'avodas kochavim afilu amar hayom ovdo l'machar
batlo chayav mar k'isay mar k'isay, each one according to the reason
that puts you in the נביא שהדיח navi shehidiyach category and that's
either סקילה skila or חנק chenek depending if you're a רבי שמעון
Rabi Shimon or a רבנן. Rabbanan. Okay that's a very simple read
other than why it specifically said רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon says that
you're פטור. patur. But that's a nice split, first half of the
ברייתא's braisa שאר מצוות shahr mitzvos and the next half is about
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Okay,
where were we? רבא סבר כרב המנונא, Rava savra k'Rav Hamnuna,
רבא Rava holds like רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna that if it's עוקר
הכל oker hakol it's in the נביא שהדיח navi shehidiyach category. ומתרצה
כרב המנונא, U'metartzah k'Rav Hamnuna, המתנבא לעקור דבר מן התורה, hamisnabe l'akor
davar min hatorah,
if you are trying to uproot something completely בין בעבודת כוכבים בין
בשאר מצוות חייב. bein b'avodas kochavim bein b'shahr mitzvos chayav. So המתנבא
לעקור דבר מן התורה, hamisnabe l'akor davar min hatorah, it doesn't say
שאר מצוות, shahr mitzvos, that's maybe an easier read I don't care
if it's עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. I don't care if it's עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, I don't care if it's שאר מצוות, shear mitzvos,
it's not specific. If you're coming to be עוקר דבר מן התורה,
oker davar min hatorah, you're חייב, chayav, you're in the נביא שהדיח
navi shehidiach category. מר כי איתא ומר כי איתא. Mar ki isa
u'mar ki isa. Whether it's סקילה skila or חנק chenek depends how
you feel about נביא שהדיח. navi shehidiach. But that's the דברים י"ג
Devarim Yud Gimmel category. לקיים מקצת ולבטל מקצת בשאר מצוות, L'kayem miktzas
u'levatel miktzas b'shear mitzvos, if it's,
you know, keeping partially and overriding partially by other מצוות, mitzvos, רבי
שמעון פוטר והוא הדין לרבנן. Rabbi Shimon patur v'hu hadin l'Rabbanan. Same
problem why it specifically says says רבי שמעון פוטר, Rabbi Shimon patur,
but now we're moving on to שאר מצוות. shear mitzvos. Okay, keeping
part and uproot part, everybody if it's שאר מצוות shear mitzvos everybody
agrees you're exempt. ובעבודת כוכבים, U'vavodas kochavim, מר כי איתא ומר כי
איתא. Mar ki isa u'mar ki isa. ובעבודת כוכבים U'vavodas kochavim אפילו
אמר היום עבדוה ולמחר בטלוה חייב. afilu omar hayom avduha u'lemachar batluha
chayav. מר כי איתא ומר
כי איתא Mar ki isa u'mar ki isa by עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. If it is even if it's today worship it and tomorrow
not, that's ביטול מקצת וקיום מקצת, bitul miktzas v'kiyum miktzas, everybody would
say you're חייב, chayav, you're in the נביא שהדיח navi shehidiach category,
each one מר כי איתא ומר כי איתא, mar ki isa u'mar
ki isa, either סקילה skila or חנק. chenek. So basically, the point
is is that the first line that says המתנבא לעקור דבר מן
התורה חייב, Hamitnabi l'akor davar min hatorah chayav, right, is either
according to one approach is only talking about, you know, well
whatever, I'm not going to review the whole thing. Anyway, bottom line
is each way works according to their various opinions and we're still
back to the question about whether ביטול מקצת, bitul miktzas, whether עוקר
כל הגוף oker kol haguf by שאר מצוות shear mitzvos falls into
the נביא שהדיח navi shehidiach category or in the נביא שקר navi
sheker category. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב יוחנן: Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav Yochanan: Said רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of
רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, בכל יאמר לך הנביא עבור על דברי תורה
שמע לו חוץ מעבודת כוכבים.
Bechol yomar lecha hanavi avor al divrei Torah shema
lo chutz m'avodas kochavim. No matter if if a נביא navi tells
you to be over on something, that's ביטול מקצת וקיום מקצת bitul
miktzas v'kiyum miktzas like we established, somebody who's established as a נביא,
navi, then you have to listen to him, even if it's violating
something, except for when it comes to עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
because as we said, you know, עבודה זרה avoda zara is always
in the נביא שהדיח navi shehidiach category, שאפילו מעמיד לך חמה באמצע
הרקיע, she'afilu ma'amid lecha chama b'emtza harakia, even if he were to
have the sun stand still, אל תשמע לו, al tishma lo, don't
listen to him. תניא רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר: Tanya, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili
omer: הגיע תורה לסוף דעתה של עבודה כוכבים ולפיכך נתנה תורה ממשלה
בה. Higi'ah Torah l'sof da'atah shel avoda kochavim u'lefikach nasna Torah memshala
bah.
The תורה Torah got, you know, went down, you know, the תורה
Torah like assessed the dangers of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, לפיכך נתנה
תורה ממשלה בה, lefikach nasna Torah memshala bah, this is actually a
little hard to parse. The תורה Torah assessed the dangers of עבודה
זרה avoda zara and even gave power to people prophesying in the
name of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, sort of like the תורה Torah
wanted to see how well you could withstand temptation, seems to be
what it's saying. שאפילו מעמיד לך חמה באמצע הרקיע אל תשמע לו,
She'afilu ma'amid lecha chama b'emtza harakia al tishma lo,
that even if you stand make the sun stand in the middle
of the sky, meaning somehow God has given the ability for people
to create these wonders and it knows that there's a power of
עבודה זרה avoda zara or of draw to עבודה זרה avoda zara
and tells you therefore no matter what they do, you have to
learn to withstand that. Okay, but anyway, but it's again a little
unclear the תורה Torah went down to the depth and therefore gave
mastery. I don't exactly know exactly how to parse that sentence, but
the point still is, you know, you the תורה Torah allows you
to be greatly tempted and you have to withstand it. אמר רבי
עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva responds is חס ושלום
chas v'shalom שקדוש ברוך הוא מעמיד חמה לעוברי רצונו. she'Hakadosh Baruch Hu
ma'amid chama l'ovrei retzono. God forbid that God would allow those who
violate his will, give this power to people to tempt others to
do עבודה זרה. avoda zara. אלא כגון חנניה בן עזור שמתחילתו נביא
אמת ולבסוף נביא שקר. Ella k'gon Chananya ben Azur she'mitchilaso navi emes
u'levasof navi sheker.
The way somebody could try to persuade you is that somebody could
do a tremendous sign because initially they were a true prophet and
God gave them a power as a true prophet. Then they became
a רשע rasha after they had established themselves and that's maybe how
they'll persuade you, because of what they were able to do when
they were a true prophet. All right, last part of the
משנה, mishna, who gets חנק chenek is those that עדים זוממים edim
zomemim for a בת כהן bas Kohen or the person that has
sex with a בת כהן bas Kohen who's married, who commits adultery
with her because only she gets שריפה sreifa but all the men
involved, whether they're the false עדים edim or whether they're the adulterer,
get חנק chenek like a normal case of אשת איש. eishess ish.
מנא הני מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where do we know this from?
אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא: Amar Rav Acha b'reih d'Rav Ika:
דתניא רבי יוסי אומר מה תלמוד לומר ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם לעשות
לאחיו? D'tanya, Rabbi Yossi omer: Mah talmud lomar v'asisem lo ka'asher zamam
la'asos l'achiv? Do to him what he wanted to do to his
brother. לפי שכל המזוממים שבתורה זוממיהם ובועליהם כיוצא בהם. Lefi shekol hamzumamim
shebaTorah zomemeihem u'vo'aleihem k'yotzei bahem. Any
place it's about, you know, people that made עדים זוממים, edim zomemim,
whether it is the people that are found to be עדים זוממים
edim zomemim or the cases of people that have עריות, arayos, whatever
have forbidden sex with women, normally it would all everybody would get
the same punishment. Okay, but בת כהן, bas Kohen, היא בשריפה ואין
בועלה בשריפה. hi b'sreifa v'ein bo'alah b'sreifa. But by כהן Kohen it
says by, you know, היא באש תשרף, hi ba'esh tisaref, so she
gets שריפה sreifa but none of the... the other men do. So
in that case, זוממים, zomemim, איני יודע אם לא הוקשו, eini yodeia
im lo hukshu,
so therefore the man gets שריפה, sreifa, not he, she gets שריפה,
sreifa, not the man. זוממים zomemim when it comes to the עדים,
Eidim, איני יודע אם לא הוקשו eini yodeia im lo hukshu should
they be connected to the man in that category or הוקשו hukshu
to her? כשהוא אומר לעשות לאחיו, keshu omer la'asos leachiv, you should
do what they wanted to do to the brother, לאחיו ולא לאחותו,
leachiv velo leachoso, not what they wanted to do to their sister.
In this case, where the man and the woman have split judgments,
the עדים זוממים Eidim zomemim follow the judgment of the man. הדרן
עלך אלו הן הנחנקין hadran alach eilu hein hanichnakin and with that
we finish the פרקים perakim about מיתות בית דין misos beis din
and we turn to this last פרק perek which is about עולם
הבא, Olam HaBa, the famous פרק perek of כל ישראל יש להם
חלק לעולם הבא. kol Yisrael yeish lahem cheilek l'Olam HaBa. Now I
will leave a lot of this introduction of this פרק perek till
tomorrow and we'll do a nice introduction in the beginning tomorrow. For
here I'll just say that there's a debate whether this is in
genuine the last פרק. perek. In some way it would be nice,
now that we're done with all the cases of מיתות בית דין
misos beis din we're going to speak about, you know, just cause
you get מיתות בית דין misos beis din doesn't mean you don't
get עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, the people that are excluded from עולם
הבא Olam HaBa are a very tiny set. So that would make
it stand that it's the last פרק. perek. However, the end of
this פרק perek actually deals with cases of מיתות בית דין misos
beis din and gets back in and in really all of the
standard
editions or whatever, you know, or
manuscripts or whatever, this is actually the tenth פרק perek and אלו
הן הנחנקין eilu hein hanichnakin is the eleventh פרק, perek, which means
that סנהדרין Sanhedrin sort of ends a little abruptly
from where we just ended. But for some have that the פרק
perek we just ended was the last פרק perek and כל ישראל
kol Yisrael and you know and חלק Cheilek is actually the penultimate
פרק. perek. But anyway the way it is in our ש"ס Shas
it is the last פרק. perek. So let's take a look at
this. כל ישראל יש להם חלק לעולם הבא, kol Yisrael yeish lahem
cheilek l'Olam HaBa, all Israel has a portion in the world to
come, שנאמר ועמך כולם צדיקים לעולם יירשו ארץ נצר מטעי מעשה ידי
להתפאר, shenemar ve'ameich kulam tzadikim le'olam yirshu aretz netzer matai ma'aseh yadai
lehispa'er, they will inherit the earth and here means the world to
come, my creatures in order that I get glory from. ואלו שאין
להם חלק לעולם הבא, ve'eilu she'ein lahem cheilek l'Olam HaBa, however the
following don't have a portion in עולם הבא. Olam HaBa. האומר אין
תחיית המתים מן התורה, ha'omer ein techiyas hameisim min haTorah, there's no
such thing as resurrection based in the תורה, Torah, maybe you believe
in resurrection but you don't believe that it's from the תורה, Torah,
ואין תורה מן השמים, ve'ein Torah min hashamayim, תורה Torah is not
from heaven, ואפיקורס, ve'apikorus, the אפיקורס apikorus which usually means the heretic
but we'll see how the גמרא Gemara explains what that is. רבי
עקיבא אומר אף הקורא בספרים חיצוניים, Rabbi Akiva omer af hakorei bisforim
chitzoniyim, even if somebody reads in the external books like the things
that were put out, you know,
rejected from the canon, again we'll see about that in the גמרא,
Gemara, the pseudepigrapha or other things. והלוחש על המכה, vehalochesh al hamakah,
somebody who whispers an incantation over a wound in order to heal
it, ואומר כל המחלה אשר שמתי במצרים לא אשים עליך כי אני
ה' רופאך, ve'omer kol hamachalah asher samti bemitzrayim lo asim alecha ki
ani Hashem rofecha, even if you quote a פסוק, pasuk, I got
him healing you, so it seems like maybe a type of a
תפילה, tefilah, that doesn't have a portion in the world to come.
Now obviously these seem to be very different categories, people that deny
major principles of faith, עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, תחיית המתים, techiyas hameisim,
as opposed to people that do things that are a little, I
don't know, say smack of sectarianism or smack of a little magic,
right, the ספרים חיצוניים, seforim chitzoniyim, לוחש על המכה, lochesh al hamakah,
it's a little funny that that's, you know, but maybe that point
of sectarianism is exactly the point that חז"ל Chazal are trying to
draw lines that who's in and who's out, you know, there were
sects at that time of חז"ל Chazal who maybe didn't believe in
תחיית המתים, techiyas hameisim, didn't believe in תורה מן השמים, Torah min
hashamayim, and you know, and there's the differences, are you part of
us or not part of us? It weren't here based on practice
but on belief. So maybe some of these other activities of רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva are also sectarian even though they're not actual core
principles of faith. Again, very strange what this combination is. אבא שאול
אומר אף ההוגה את השם באותיותיו, Abba Shaul omer af hahogeh es
Hashem be'osyosov, even somebody who articulates God's name exactly as it's written
with its letters. Okay, so those are general categories. Now I should
pause and say also that כל ישראל יש להם חלק לעולם הבא
kol Yisrael yeish lahem cheilek l'Olam HaBa is not an originally part
of this משנה. Mishnah. And actually רש"י Rashi even says that it
wasn't part of the משנה Mishnah but that רש"י Rashi was crossed
out, but the מהרש"א Maharsha sort of preserves that רש"י. Rashi. The
משנה Mishnah actually began אלו שאין להם חלק לעולם הבא, eilu she'ein
lahem cheilek l'Olam HaBa, the following don't have a portion. But that's
a very harsh way to begin it, so you know, somebody tagged
this on, this line, no, no, no, everybody has except the following
who we're going to say doesn't have, which is a very comforting
type of an opening, כל ישראל יש להם חלק לעולם הבא. kol
Yisrael yeish lahem cheilek l'Olam HaBa. You know, the problem is that
it goes against other teachings, which is
that more common in ש"ס, Shas, that only צדיקים tzadikim have a
חלק לעולם הבא, cheilek l'Olam HaBa, right, like the classic thing, like
you know, that on ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you know, the צדיקים
tzadikim are immediately given עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, the רשעים reshaim you
know גיהנום Gehennom and the בינונים beionim are, you know, are sort
of suspended or whatever for judgment. Or when somebody is מגייר, megayer,
you know, you basically say to him don't think just because you're
going to be a Jew you're going to get עולם הבא, Olam
HaBa, עולם הבא אינו אלא לצדיקים. Olam HaBa eino ela letzadikim. So
this משנה Mishnah tries... tries to bridge that gap by saying ועמך
כולם צדיקים. v'amech kulam tzadikim. Everybody by default is a צדיק. tzadik.
But there really is a very different strand of belief whether fundamentally
everybody gets עולם הבא olam haba until you're kicked out, you know,
because of the cases in this משנה mishna or do you have
to like earn עולם הבא olam haba only צדיקים tzadikim get it.
Okay, let's keep on reading the משנה. mishna. שלשה מלכים וארבעה הדיוטות
אין להם חלק לעולם הבא. shlosha melachim v'arba hedyotot ein lahem chelek
l'olam haba. Of the sort of historical figures, three kings and four
commoners don't have a portion. שלשה מלכים ירבעם אחאב ומנשה. shlosha melachim
Yerovam Achav u'Menashe. Okay, so those were particularly wicked kings. רבי יהודה
אומר מנשה יש לו חלק לעולם הבא, Rabbi Yehuda omer Menashe yesh
lo chelek l'olam haba, שנאמר ויתפלל אליו, shenemar vayitpalel eilav, you know
מנשה Menashe prayed to God, וישמע תחינתו וישיבהו ירושלים למלכותו, vayishma t'chinato
vayasheivehu Yerushalayim l'malchuto, and God heard his
importuning and restored him to Jerusalem, to his kingship. אמרו לו למלכותו
השיבו ולא לחיי עולם הבא. amru lo l'malchuto heishivo v'lo l'chayei olam
haba. Yeah, God gave him back this worldly things, but he did
not get the world to come. ארבע הדיוטות, arba hedyotot, who are
the four commoners? בלעם ודואג ואחיתופל וגחזי. Bilam v'Doeg v'Achitofel v'Geichazi. Okay,
so fascinating. We'll see all about this in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. וכל כך למה? v'chol kach
lama? So why does, now we're talking really about the first case
of somebody who says אין תחיית המתים מן התורה. ein techiyat hameitim
min HaTorah. Why does he not get עולם הבא? olam haba? הוא
כפר בתחיית המתים לפיכך לא יהיה לו חלק בתחיית המתים. hu kafar
b'techiyat hameitim l'fichach lo yihiyeh lo chelek b'techiyat hameitim. Well, if you're
denying תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim, then you don't deserve a portion of
getting תחיית המתים. techiyat hameitim. Now, what that winds up doing is
basically identifying עולם הבא olam haba with תחיית המתים. techiyat hameitim. And
this really gets to a question of what is עולם הבא. olam
haba. You know, the standard understanding in the גמרא Gemara is that
עולם הבא olam haba is the world that will be coming later
in our historical reality. What's going to happen at the end of
times when, you know, there's the מלחמת גוג ומגוג milchemet Gog u'Magog
and there's תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim and ימות המשיח. yemot HaMashiach.
And that's why it speaks about who is going to stand לעולם
הבא. l'olam haba. The dead will be, you know, will be resurrected.
There will be a final judgment day. That's like the standard פשט
pshat here of עולם הבא. olam haba. And that's why it says
if you don't believe in תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim, you're not going
to get it. That is very different than the עולם הבא olam
haba that was the focus of רמב"ם, Rambam, which was the world
that is going to come for the individual, not in world history.
What am I going to get after I personally die? Where will
my soul go? The world of souls up in heaven. A world
that lives right now at the same time as this world, just
it's a spiritual world, and it's where my soul will go. That
is not the פשט pshat of the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara
focuses very much on the world that will come later in our
history. Okay. So, שכל מדותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא מדה כנגד מדה.
shekol midotav shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu mida k'neged mida.
All of God's attributes are measure for measure. דאמר רבי שמואל בר
נחמני אמר רבי יונתן מנין שכל מדותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא מדה
כנגד מדה. d'amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi Yonatan minayin shekol
midotav shel HaKadosh Baruch Hu mida k'neged mida.
How do you know God's measures are measure for measure? שנאמר ויאמר
אלישע שמעו דבר ה' כעת מחר סאה סולת בשקל וסאתים שעורים בשקל
בשער שמרון. shenemar vayomer Elisha shimu devar Hashem ka'et machar se'ah solet
b'shekel v'satayim se'orim b'shekel b'sha'ar Shomron. So this was the time of
the famine and the people were besieged and אלישע Elisha said tomorrow
it'll be like, you know, the grain will be so cheap, you
know, an enormous amount of grain for a very small amount of
money in the gates of שמרון. Shomron. וכתיב ויען השליש אשר המלך
נשען על ידו את איש האלקים ויאמר, u'chtiv vay'an hashlish asher hamelech
nishan al yado et ish ha'elokim vayomer, and the officer said, הנה
ה' עושה ארובות בשמים היה יהיה הדבר הזה. hinei Hashem oseh arubot
bashamayim hayihyeh hadavar hazeh. God is going to make what? Windows in
the heaven? Can such a thing be? So he mocked, he did
not believe what the נביא navi was saying. ויאמר, vayomer, and אלישע
Elisha said to him, הנך רואה בעיניך ומשם לא תאכל. hincha ro'eh
b'einecha u'misham lo tochal. You will see and you won't eat. Top
of צדיק ע"ב. tzadik amud bet. וכתיב, v'chtiv,
and the verse said, ויהי לו כן, vayehi lo chein, and that
is exactly what happened. וירמסו אותו העם בשער וימות. vayer'm'su oto ha'am
b'sha'ar vayamot. And then basically the armies that were besieging the city
were destroyed and all of their food was available to the people
and that's how they were able to get all of that food
and the people rushed out and they crushed the officer that was
by the gate. Okay, so that was like מדה כנגד מדה. mida
k'neged mida. All right, you know, he sort of mocked what was
going to happen about the grain and it was also בשער שמרון,
b'sha'ar Shomron, he was the officer of the gate and he was
therefore trampled at the gate. Okay. And, okay,
and he was like destroyed, you know, killed by the people who
were going to benefit from the prophecy of the נביא. navi. So
now the גמרא Gemara says ודילמא קללת אלישע גרמה לו? v'dilma kilelat
Elisha garma lo?
So maybe it's not because God is מדה כנגד מדה, mida k'neged
mida, you know, it was very specifically because אלישע Elisha passed this
decree on him. It doesn't show that God naturally operates מדה כנגד
מדה. mida k'neged mida. דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב קללת חכם אפילו
על חנם היא באה. d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav kilelat chacham afilu
al chinam hi ba'ah. That the curse of a wise person, even
if it's for not a good, justified reason will come true. Certainly
here was a justified reason, so it doesn't have to be based
on God's general principles of operating. So the גמרא Gemara says no,
אם כן לכתוב קרא וירמסהו וימות. im kein lichtov kra vayer'm'seihu vayamot.
Just say they trampled him and he died. מאי בשער? mai b'sha'ar?
What does it mean they trampled him in the gate? על עסקי
שער, al iskei sha'ar, because of the way he was sort of
mocking in the gate and that sort of shows that there is
a general principle about מדה כנגד מדה, mida k'neged mida, you know,
that is operating. The גמרא Gemara might also be referring to the
idea that שער sha'ar
normally refers to the price of grain and part of what the
prophecy was about was about the price of grain, so that could
also be echoing that and the מידה כנגד מידה. midah keneged midah.
All right. Moving on. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan is our
גרסא girsa or some don't have that. מניין לתחיית המתים מן התורה?
Minayin l'techiyat hameitim min haTorah?
So now that you say that, you know, somebody who denies it's
from the Torah, it's not enough to just believe, you have to
believe it's from the Torah. Where do you get it from the
Torah? Now what's going to be fascinating is what do we mean
by the Torah? Do we mean the five books of Moses? Do
we mean נ"ך, Nach, תנ"ך? Tanach? Later the גמרא Gemara is going
to quote from פסוקים pesukim in נ"ך, Nach, but of course the
most explicit פסוקים pesukim are in דניאל, Daniel, you know, that דניאל
Daniel speaks about משכילים כזוהר הרקיע, maskilim k'zohar harakia, you know, ורבים
מישני אדמת עפר יקיצו, v'rabbim mi-yshenei admat afar yakitzu,
many from those who are sleeping in the dirt will wake up.
What's fascinating is that the proofs from the גמרא, Gemara, even when
it goes beyond the five books of Moses, don't quote the most
explicit פסוקים pesukim in דניאל. Daniel. But let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, שנאמר, shene'emar, okay, ונתתם ממנו את
תרומת ה' לאהרן הכהן, unatatem mimenu et terumat Hashem l'Aharon HaKohen, so
you shall give from it the תרומה terumah of God to אהרן
Aharon the כהן. Kohen. So and that's talking about when you go
into the land, you know, and you're taking from the grain, וכי
אהרן לעולם קיים? vechi Aharon l'olam kayam? Would אהרן Aharon really be
alive when you're taking the תרומה? terumah? והלא לא נכנס לארץ ישראל?
vahalo lo nichnas l'Eretz Yisrael? He's not going into ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael to give him תרומה. terumah. אלא מלמד שעתיד להחיות, ela melamed
she'atid l'hachayot, in the end, he will be resurrected, וישראל נותנים לו
תרומה, v'Yisrael notnim lo terumah, and we will give אהרן Aharon תרומה.
terumah. מכאן לתחיית המתים מן התורה. mikan l'techiyat hameitim min haTorah. Here's
where you see it from the Torah. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא Dvei
Rabbi Yishmael tana לאהרן l'Aharon כאהרן. k'Aharon. No, it means like אהרן.
Aharon. It doesn't literally mean אהרן. Aharon. מה אהרן חבר אף בניו
חברים, mah Aharon chaver af banav chaverim, when you give it to
a כהן Kohen it has to be a כהן Kohen like אהרן
Aharon who's a חבר chaver who can be trusted on טומאה וטהרה.
tumah v'taharah. And now we're going to digress a little. אמר רבי
שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar
Rabbi Yochanan, מניין שאין נותנין תרומה לכהן עם הארץ? minayin she'ein notnim
terumah l'Kohen am ha'aretz? How do you know you can't give תרומה
terumah to a כהן Kohen who's an עם הארץ? am ha'aretz? Because
he might go ahead and become טמא tamei and eat it בטומאה,
b'tumah, and it's classic like לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, but maybe you
would think well you have a מצוה mitzvah of giving it and
that, you know, and that's his responsibility. שנאמר, shene'emar, ויאמר לעם יושבי
ירושלים לתת מנת הכהנים והלויים למען יחזקו בתורת ה'. vayomer la'am yoshvei
Yerushalayim latet menat haKohanim v'haLevi'im lema'an yechezku b'Torat Hashem. He said to
the people who dwell in ירושלים Yerushalayim to give, you know, the
portion of the כהנים Kohanim and the לויים Levi'im that they should
strengthen in the Torah of God. כל המחזיק בתורת ה'. kol hamachzik
b'Torat Hashem. So the principle is it's to strengthen in the Torah.
כל המחזיק בתורת ה' יש לו מנת ושאינו מחזיק בתורת ה' אין
לו מנת. kol hamachzik b'Torat Hashem yesh lo manat v'she'eino machzik b'Torat
Hashem ein lo manat. If you're strong in God's Torah you deserve
a portion, if not, not. אמר רב אחא בר אדא אמר רב
יהודה, Amar Rav Acha bar Adda amar Rav Yehuda, כל הנותן תרומה
לכהן עם הארץ, kol hanoten terumah l'Kohen am ha'aretz, if you give
תרומה terumah to a כהן Kohen who's an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
כאילו נותנה לפני ארי. ke'ilu notnah lifnei ari.
It's like giving it to a lion. מה ארי ספק דורס ואוכל
ספק אינו דורס ואוכל. mah ari safek dores v'ochel safek eino dores
v'ochel. The same way by a lion you don't know if he'll
trample it and eat it or you know if he'll claw into
his food and eat it or not. אף כהן עם הארץ ספק
אוכלה בטהרה ספק אוכלה בטומאה. af Kohen am ha'aretz safek ochlah b'taharah
safek ochlah b'tumah. Similarly here you don't know how he's going to
eat it; is he going to eat it in a proper way
or in a non-proper way, בטהרה b'taharah or בטומאה? b'tumah? ורבי יוחנן
אמר אף גרם לו מיתה. V'Rabbi Yochanan amar af garam lo mitah.
You're going to bring about his death, שנאמר ומתו בו כי יחללוהו.
shene'emar umetu vo ki yechalelu'u. They'll die when it if they eat
it, you know, if they violate it, if they eat it בטומאה.
b'tumah. Right? I mean some of this seems obvious like basic principles
about לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, but you know, I mean but again
you're not giving him a דבר עבירה, davar aveira, you're giving him
תרומה, terumah, but you're giving it to someone, you know, normally לפני
עיוור lifnei iver is if you give somebody like a חזיר. chazir.
You know, here you're giving him תרומה, terumah, but you're giving it
to him when he maybe can't be held, you know, you can't
be trusted. Okay. דבי רבי אליעזר בן יעקב תנא אף משיאו עוון
אשמה. Dvei Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov tana af masio avon ashmah. You
cause him to bring about himself like sin and, um, you know,
iniquity, שנאמר והשיאו אותם עוון אשמה באכלם את קדשיהם, shene'emar v'hisi'u otam
avon ashmah b'ochlam et kodsheihem, which is a פסוק pasuk about eating
תרומה terumah בטומאה. b'tumah. Okay. תניא רבי סימאי אומר Tanya Rabbi Simai
omer back to תחיית המתים, techiyat hameitim, מניין לתחיית המתים מן התורה?
minayin l'techiyat hameitim min haTorah? שנאמר וגם הקימותי את בריתי אתם לתת
להם את ארץ כנען. shene'emar v'gam hakimoti et briti itam latet lahem
et Eretz Kena'an. I will establish my my covenant with them, the
אבות, avot, to give them the land of כנען. Kena'an. לתת להם
את ארץ כנען, Latet lahem et Eretz Kena'an, לכם לא נאמר, lachem
lo ne'emar, it didn't say to give you their descendants, אלא להם,
ela lahem, to give them, the אבות. avot. מכאן לתחיית המתים מן
התורה. Mikan l'techiyat hameitim min haTorah. Okay, that's cute. שאלו מינים את
רבן גמליאל. Sha'alu minim et Rabban Gamliel. Second second light light, the
the heretics, often means the Christian Jewish Christians, asked רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא מחיה מתים? Minayin she'Hakadosh Baruch Hu mechayeh
meitim? Where do you get this idea that God will resurrect the
dead? אמר להם מן התורה ומן הנביאים ומן הכתובים. Amar lahem min
haTorah u'min haNevi'im u'min haKetuvim. I can bring it to you from
anyway. So anyway, this was תחיית המתים מן התורה techiyat hameitim min
haTorah before we got to the heretics, these were all פסוקים pesukim
in the Torah. Okay now when the מינים minim are asking, because
the משנה Mishnah says you have to believe it's מן התורה, min
haTorah, that it's sourced ultimately in the Torah. But now when the
מינים minim are asking he's going to quote other פסוקים pesukim as
well even beyond the Torah. And some of those, like I said,
דניאל Daniel is the most explicit but some of those are going
to be more explicit, you know, not more explicit than דניאל Daniel
but more explicit than the ones in the Torah. ולא קיבלו ממנו
V'lo kiblu mimenu and they didn't accept it. מן התורה דכתיב ויאמר
ה' אל משה הנך שוכב עם אבותיך וקם, Min haTorah dechtiv Vayomer
Hashem el Moshe hinecha shochev im avotecha v'kam, "Behold, you are lying
going to lie down with your with your fathers and rise up."
So obviously, אמרו לו וקם העם הזה וזנה. amru lo v'kam ha'am
hazeh v'zanah.
Okay, they said no that doesn't prove it, the simple reading of
the פסוק pasuk is
הנך שוכב עם אבותיך
hinecha shochev im
avotecha period, וקם העם הזה וזנה אחרי אלוהי נכר
הארץ, v'kam ha'am hazeh v'zanah acharei elohei nechar ha'aretz, not you. will
wake up, you know,
the corpse will rise up and they will rejoice those that, you
know, sleep in the dirt. Okay, so you know, could be understood
metaphorically referring to the people, the nation, it's like they're dead, they'll
be resurrected, but but it could be read literally. Okay, כי טל
אורות טלך וארץ רפאים תפיל ki tal orot talecha ve'aretz refaim tapil
because the the dew of light is your dew. ודילמא מתים שהחיה
יחזקאל vedilma metim shehechya yechezkel
and they said no, it doesn't mean that there'll be a general
תחיית המתים, tchiyat hametim, maybe it means the one type of case
with יחזקאל yechezkel with the dry you know the dry bones, but
doesn't prove that there's going to be a general resurrection for the
whole world. מן הכתובים דכתיב min haktuvim dechtiv וחכך כיין הטוב vechichecha
keyayin hatov from the כתובים ktuvim it says
your cheek is like good wine הולך לדודי למישרים holech ledodi lemeisharim
goes to my beloved straight away דובב שפתי ישנים dovev siftei yeshenim
cause to
to murmur the the lips of those who are asleep. So like
we'll resurrect the dead. So ודילמא רחושי מרחשן שפוותיה בעלמא vedilma richushei
merchashan sefvateih be'alma
maybe it just means their lips the מינים minim said back will
will murmur but it doesn't mean that there'll be a true resurrection.
כדרבי יוחנן דאמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק כל מי
שנאמר הלכה בשמו ki deRabbi Yochanan d'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon
ben Yehotzadak kol mi shene'emar halacha bishmo as Rabbi Yochanan said in
the name of Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak anybody who says a הלכה
halacha in the name of somebody who is dead בשמו בעולם הזה
bishmo ba'olam hazeh in this world שפתותיו דובבות בקבר siftotav dovvot bakever
you cause his lips to murmur in the grave. Very nice image.
Like you know you're resurrecting you're keeping his teaching alive. שנאמר דובב
שפתי ישנים. shene'emar dovev siftei yeshenim.
Okay, so therefore none of those proved it because they had an
answer to everything. עד שאמר להם מקרא זה ad she'amar lahem mikra
ze until he quoted them this פסוק pasuk אשר נשבע ה' לאבותיכם
לתת להם asher nishba Hashem la'avoteichem latet lahem going back to the
תורה. Torah. God swears to the forefathers to give them. לכם לא
נאמר lachem lo ne'emar to give you it doesn't say אלא להם
ela lahem to them. מכאן לתחיית המתים מן התורה mikan letchiyat hametim
min haTorah here you get it from the תורה. Torah. ויש אומרים
מן המקרא הזה אמר להם ve'yesh omrim min hamikra hazeh amar lahem
and some say he said to them from the following פסוק pasuk
ואתם הדבקים בה' אלוהיכם חיים כולכם היום ve'atem hadeveikim baHashem elokeichem chayim
kulchem hayom you who were cleaving to Hashem you are all alive
to this very day. מה היום כולכם חיים אף לעולם הבא כולכם
חיים ma hayom kulchem chayim af le'olam haba kulchem chayim the same
way like today you are all alive you will always remain alive
even לעולם הבא. le'olam haba. Okay, so we will end here for
now.