Okay له÷ّ
èهل *Boker Tov*, today's مَ *daf* is ٌ"ل *Samech Bet*, 162. We
pick up towards the bottom of ٌ"à ٍîهم ل' *Samech Aleph Amud
Bet*, 61B, àéْîّ *Itmar*, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 lines down
and we're in the middle of discussing ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah *Avodah
Zarah* and what constitutes an act of ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah. *Avodah
Zarah* that you are çééل îéْن chayav misah, *chayav misa*. Interesting, this
is not in îٌëْ ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah *Maseches Avodah Zarah* at
all; the definition of the acts of ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah. *Avodah
Zarah* for which you're çééل îéْن chayav misah. *chayav misa* or which
are forbidden are right here in ًٌنمّéï Sanhedrin *Sanhedrin*. Okay, so àéْîّ
*Itmar*, it was taught: نٍهلم ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي Avodat Kochavim. îàنلن هîéّàن me'ahavah
u-mi-yirah. *Haoved Avodas Kochavim meahava umeyirah*. What if somebody worships ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي
*Avodas Kochavim*, does the act which we've been talking about, bowing down,
slaughtering an animal, sprinkling the blood, pouring libations, etc., or any
of the ٍلهمن avodah, *avodah* that is unique for that ٍلهمن وّن
avodah zarah *Avodah Zarah*? So does the actual act that is defined
as the act of ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah, *Avodah Zarah*, but it
is done îàنلن هîéّàن me'ahava umiyirah, *meahava umeyirah*, from love and out
of fear and not out of true belief. Now what does this
mean love and fear? So ّù"é Rashi *Rashi*, if you take a
look, says five lines before the lines get wide: îàنلن هîéّàن, me-ahavah
u-mi-yirah îàنلْ àمي هîéّàْ àمي هىà çùلن لىéلن ىàىهنهْ *meahava umeyirah, meahavas
adam umeyiras adam velo chashva beliba lelohut*, out of fear and love
for a person. You know, in the Middle Ages and the times
of the ّàùهًéي *Rishonim*, the reason Jews converted to Christianity was not
because they believed in it, but it was out of a desire
to get ahead in society or out of àنلن ahavah *ahavah*, you
know, financial, societal advancement, or out of fear, fear of a forced
conversion and oppression and so on. But not done out of actual
belief. And if somebody does an act of ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah
*Avodah Zarah* with in that you know does the full act and
does it knowing that this is you know sacrifices an animal before
Zeus, you know, or ôٍهّ ىôٍهّ *Peor L'Peor* and understands that this
is an ٍلهمن avodah *avodah* towards the ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah *Avodah
Zarah* but is not doing it out of any belief, is are
you still çééل chayav *chayav*? Is that the definition of ٍلهمن وّن
avodah zarah. *Avodah Zarah*? Which is actually quite interesting, right?
Because there are two types of cases mentioned in the îùًن *Mishna*.
First it speaks about all the different types of ٍلهمن Avodah *avodah*,
and then it says هنî÷لى ٍىéه لàىهن *vehamikabel alav beloha* and somebody
who accepts it as a god and says you know you are
my god.
So what happens, you know, normally we assume that the act of
ٍلهمن Avodah *avodah* is implicitly accepting it as a god, but what
happens if we know that's not true? It's just the ٍلهمن Avodah
*avodah*, it's an act of worship but without that acceptance of this
as a god. Is that considered an act of ٍلهمن وّن avodah
zarah. *Avodah Zarah* or not? That's the way ّù"é *Rashi* and most
of the ّàùهًéي *Rishonim* explain it. I'll go back in a minute
and talk about how ّîل"ي Rambam *Rambam* explains îàنلن هîéّàن mei'ahava u'miyira.
*meahava umeyirah*. Okay,
but basically the act but without the attendant belief, but understanding that
this is what is defined as an act of worshipping ٍلهمن وّن
avodah zarah. *Avodah Zarah*. àلéé Abaye. àîّ çééل chayav *Abaye amar chayav*,
Abaye says you're çééل chayav. *chayav*. ّلà Rava àîّ ôèهّ patur, *Rava
amar patur*, Rava says you're exempt. àلéé Abaye àîّ çééل chayav منà
ôىçéن *Abaye amar chayav deha palchia*, look you did the act, that's
defined as an act of ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah, *Avodah Zarah*, right?
It's not about your belief system, it's about the act of worship.
ّلà Rava àîّ ôèهّ patur, àé ÷éلىن ٍىéن لàىهن àéï àé ىà
ىà *Rava amar patur ei kiblah alei beloha in ei lo lo*,
you're exempt, if you accepted it as a god, yes, if no,
no. Now it's actually interesting if you think about it because there's
another form of ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah. *Avodah Zarah* which is worshipping
God through images, you know, and you actually are intending to worship
God but you're doing it through an image. But this is I
guess is not that either because there's no actual worship and belief
that's attendant with this at all, but it is the full act.
So what is the story? And so let's take a look at
how the âîّà Gemara *Gemara* tries to prove it. هàîّ àلéé v'amar
Abaye, îًà àîéًà ىن mna amina la, *V'amar Abaye mina amina lah*,
so Abaye says where do I get this from? مًْï *detnan*, we've
taught in our îùًن *Mishna*: نٍهلم ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي àçم نٍهلم *Haoved Avodas
Kochavim echad haoved*, etc., etc. And then it says whether you worship
and then it gives the last of the specific things: îولç î÷èéّ
هîًٌê îùْçهن *mezabeach maktir venasech mishtachaveh* and so on. So what's the
meaning of saying worship and then giving the specific list? îàé ىàه
Lav àçم نٍهلم îàنلن هîéّàن *mai lav echad haoved meahava umeyirah*? So
doesn't that extra phrase "if you worship" it means if you worship
regardless of your motivation or of your attendant belief? هّلà VeRava àîّ
ىê ىà *V'Rava amar lach lo*, and Rava will say to you
no, ëمîùًé ّلé Rebbi éّîéن *k'd'mishanei Rabbi Yirmiya* like Rabbi Yirmiya has
been explaining, like we've been talking about until now, that ٍهلم *oved*
would refer to a case about you know when you're ٍهلم ëمّëن
*oved kidarka* and the other cases about slaughtering and incense and all
of that, libations, that's even if it's ùىà ëمّëن *shelo kidarka* because
those are classic forms of ٍلهمن Avodah *avodah*. Okay, so that really
proves very little. àîّ àلéé Abaye îًà àîéًà ىن *Amar Abaye mina
amina lah*, so Abaye will say okay, here's another where another place
I get it from, مًْéà detanya, *detanya*, we taught in a لّééْà
braisa. *braisa*: ىà ْùْçهن ىني lo tishtachaveh lahem هىà ٍْلمي v'lo ta'avdem,
*Lo tishtachaveh lahem velo saovdem*, do not bow down to them and
don't worship them. ىني lahem àé àْن îùْçهن àلى àْن îùْçهن ىàمي
ëîهْê *Lahem atah mishtachaveh aval atah mishtachaveh la'adam kemoscha*, you don't you
can't bow down to an idol but you can bow down to
a person who's a human being just like you are. I mean
that happens all the time in the ْهّن Torah *Torah*, you know,
ٍùه éٍ÷ل *Esav Yaakov*, Yaakov bows down to ٍùه *Esav*, you bow
you bow down as a form of greeting, you know, maybe a
show of subservience. But not a show of worship, of divinity. éëهى
àôéىه ًٍلم ëنîï? Maybe you'd even be allowed to bow down to
somebody who is treating themselves as a god and is asking to
be worshipped like نîï. Haman. Now we don't know that's true about
نîï, Haman, all we know is that people bowed down, but that's
presumed to be the reason why, you know, çو"ى Chazal read that
into the story in order to explain why îّمëé Mordechai would not
bow down. If it was just a show of, you know, of
servitude or you know, of recognizing نîï's Haman authority, why would îّمëé
Mordechai have provoked him like that? But it must be that نîï
Haman was, treated himself as a god. So maybe that would be
permitted? ْىîهم ىهîّ Talmud lomar هىà ٍْلمي, v'lo ta'avdem do not worship
them. So not only ىà ْùْçهن ىني Lo tishtachaveh lahem but, oh
excuse me, but هىà ٍْلمي v'lo ta'avdem if ىني don't ْùْçهن ىني
tishtachaveh lahem ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah, but هىà ٍْلمي Velo ta’avdeim. that
extra phrase is coming to include even human beings who treat
themselves as gods. Okay, but now we've got a problem. هنà نîï
îéّàن نهن نهن ًٍلم. veha Haman mi-yirah havah havah ne'evad. نîï, Haman,
people worshipped him out of fear, out of fear of the consequences
if they did not worship him, assuming again that he's treating himself
as a god. What he would do to them, what àçùهّهù Achashverosh
would do to them, and nevertheless it's saying that that was forbidden
and would be considered to be ٍلهمن وّن. avodah zarah So that
proves like
àلéé. Abaye. هّلà and ّلà Rava, would say back, no, ëنîï هىà
ëنîï. keHaman v'lo keHaman. No,
it means like نîï, Haman, but not exactly that case. ëنîï مàéنه
âهôéن ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي, keHaman de'ihu gufei avodat kochavim,
like نîï Haman meaning you can't bow down to a person if
that is treating themselves as a god, just like نîï Haman treated
himself as a god. But هىà ëنîï v'lo keHaman it's not exactly
analogous مàéىه نîï îéّàن هنëà ىàه îéّàن de'ilu Haman mi-yirah v'hacha lav
mi-yirah
that by نîï Haman had they bowed down to him they would
not have been çééل chayav because that would have been, it would
not have been çééل chayav for ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah because they
would have done it out of fear, they did not really accept
نîï Haman as a god. But if there's a case where somebody
bows down to a human being and does it out of true
belief, that is an act of ٍلهمن وّن. avodah zarah, But in
the نîï, Haman, so we're using نîï Haman as an example of
a human being who treats himself as a god, but if they
had bowed down it would not have been an act of ٍلهمن
وّن avodah zarah, because they would have done it out of éّàن.
yirah. Now you might be asking that if that's true then why
didn't îّمëé Mordechai do it? Okay, so, so, you know, it could
just be that ىâلé, legabei, you know so ْهٌôهْ Tosafot discusses this
and others discuss it, you know, that he that,
so if you take a look at the ْهٌôهْ ّلà àîّ Tosafot
Rava amar at the bottom, like six lines from the bottom, he
says, or seven lines: هàي ْàîّ ىّلà àîàé ىà نùْçهن îّمëé ىنîï?
ve'im tomar leRava amai lo hishtachaveh Mordechai leHaman? And so why didn't
he bow down? هéù àهîّéي لًْçهîà هلîمّù ùنéه ِىîéي ٍى ىله. ve-yesh
omrim baTanchuma u-va-midrash shehayu tzelamim al libo. Okay, because he was wearing
idols so it actually would have been. Now of course that even
if there was idols that he was wearing it was still îàنلن
هîéّàن. All right, so that's not really a full answer, unless he
was concerned that it would be encouraging other people to worship ٍلهمن
وّن, avodah zarah people would not see the difference. àé ًîé îùهي
÷éمهù نùي. ee nami mishum kiddush Hashem.
Okay, so and that and ْهٌôهْ Tosafot says ÷éمهù نùي kiddush Hashem
again it was a time of ùîم shmad or there was a
concern again that it would do that other people would be encouraged
to be ٍهلم ٍلهمن وّن oved avodah zarah actually even though this
would not have actually been çééل. chayav All right, but àéï نëé
ًîé ein hachi nami would not have been ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah
had he done it. Now I want to pause here for a
second and say, you know there's one question which is is it
ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah, to be çééل îéْن, chayav misah. and the
other question is are you allowed to do it? Right, or how
bad is it if you're allowed to do it? Because ْهٌôهْ Tosafot
asks the obvious question. ْهٌôهْ Tosafot says, I don't get it. If
according to ّلà Rava you're not çééل îéّàن, chayav mi-yirah, then how
come every case of éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ, yehareg v'al ya'avor, why are
you supposed to give up your life? Okay, if somebody holds a
gun to your head and it says bow down or if not
I'll kill you, you should bow down because you're not doing an
act of ٍلهمن وّن. avodah zarah. All right, very good question. So
ْهٌôهْ Tosafot says, very important question, ْهٌôهْ Tosafot says like this: àٍ"â
ملôّ÷ af al gav de-perek top of ْهٌôهْ ّلà, Tosafot Rava, àٍ"â
ملôّ÷ لï ٌهّّ هîهّن àîّ لٍلهمْ ëهëلéي éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ éù àهîّéي
مçééل ىîٌهّ ٍِîه ىëْçéىن îëى î÷هي نéëà مىà îٌّ ٍِîه ىà îéçééل
îéْن. af al gav de-ve-perek ben sorer u-moreh amar ba-avodat kochavim yehareg
v'al ya'avor yesh omrim de-chayav limsor atzmo le-chatchilah mi-kol makom heicha de-lo
masar atzmo lo michayav misah. Yes,
you have to give up your life. Okay, because the idea, the
obligation to give up your life is not the question of whether
the act is considered technically an act of ٍلهمن وّن. avodah zarah,
You know, it's an interesting question whether you have to give up
your life before, if you're threatened, if you're being threatened that they'll
kill you unless you convert to Islam. Everybody agrees Islam isn't ٍلهمن
وّن. avodah zarah. The where we learn out the idea of éنّâ
هàى éٍلهّ yehareg v'al ya'avor is هàنلْ àْ ن' àىهنéê, v'ahavta et
Hashem Elokecha, loving your God, not betraying God, not betraying your faith.
Okay, let's say somebody holds a gun to your head and says
deny God, deny your religion, accept atheism, accept communism. It's not ٍلهمن
وّن, avodah zarah? okay? Is éنّâ هàى? yehareg v'al? So ْهٌôهْ Tosafot
says the act, what demands éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ yehareg v'al ya'avor is
not necessarily the same thing as whether if you went ahead and
did it you did an act of ٍلهمن وّن. avoda zara. ّîل"ي
Rambam makes a similar distinction elsewhere in his àéâّْ ْéîï Iggeret Teiman
dealing with people that converted and now they wanted to come back.
ّîل"ي Rambam says even though it was éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ yehareg v'al
ya'avor that you should have given up your life, at the end
of the day when you did it, you did it because there
was a gun to your head. So maybe you were like îوéم
meizid on the îِهن mitzvah of îٌéّْ ًôù, mesiras nefesh, of martyrdom,
of هàنلْ àْ ن× àى÷éê. v'ahavta es Hashem Elokecha. Okay, that you,
you violated, but in terms of the act of ٍلهمن وّن, avoda
zara you were an àهًٌ, ones, it was a gun to your
head. Alright, so that's another interesting angle, but you know, from ْهٌôهْ
Tosafos saying it's not even ٍلهمن وّن avoda zara according to ّلà,
Rava you didn't really believe, but nevertheless it was éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ
yehareg v'al ya'avor because it would be seen, you know, by the
non-Jew, by people, whatever, it's an act of betraying God and it's
an act of violating هàنلْ àْ ن× àى÷éê v'ahavta es Hashem Elokecha
even though it's not an act of ٍلهمن وّن avoda zara per
se. ْهٌôهْ Tosafos has other answers, but that one is certainly the
most pointed and the most important. Okay, so that could be, by
the way, another explanation, going back to that point, about
why ّلà Rava did not bow down to نîï. Haman. It could
have been éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ yehareg v'al ya'avor to bow down to
نîï Haman because he's treating himself as a god, and even if
it was out of îéّàن miyira etc., still éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ. yehareg
v'al ya'avor. Alright,
so now we continue. هàîّ àلéé, Abaye,
five lines from the bottom, àلéé Abaye said, îًà àîéًà ىن, where
do I know this from? مًْéà, De-tanya, ëنï îùéç لٍلهمْ ëهëلéي, Kohen
Mashiach b'avodas kochavim,
if you have a case of a ëنï âمهى, Kohen Gadol, now
Torah normally by ëنï âمهى, Kohen Gadol, if he sins, he brings
a different type of a çèàْ chatas offering than a éùّàى. Yisrael.
éùّàى Yisrael normally brings a ùٍéّن, seirah, a goat, or a ùéن,
seya, a female goat or sheep. ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol brings an
ox, a ôّ, par, okay, and not only is it a different
çèàْ chatas offering, but it requires both that he rules incorrectly to
himself, he ôهٌ÷ paskens that it's îهّْ, mutar, and then he goes
ahead and he acts on it. It's learned out from the ôّ
نٍىي ملّ ùى ِéلهّ par helam davar shel tzibur from the case
of when the لéْ مéï, beis din, the ًٌنمّéï rules incorrectly. Now,
however, when it comes to ٍلهمن وّن, avoda zara. the Torah says
that even for a normal éùّàى, Yisrael, you bring a different ÷ّلï
korban if it's a sin لùهââ, b'shogeg, you know, done unintentionally for
ٍلهمن وّن, avoda zara. it's not a female sheep or goat, it's
a male goat, it's a ùٍéّ. seir. Okay, and we learn out
that the same is true for the ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol as
well. So now that the ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol is bringing the
same çèàْ chatas offering as a éùّàى, Yisrael, what is the story?
Does he still go by the ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol rules and
only if he ôهٌ÷ paskens for himself and does it, or does
he go by the éùّàى Yisrael rules and even if he just,
no ôٌ÷ psak for himself, just accidentally does the act, he's çééل
chayav the çèàْ chatas offering? So that's the issue. ëنï îùéç لٍلهمْ
ëهëلéي, Kohen Mashiach b'avodas kochavim, ّلé Rebbi says لùâéâْ îٍùن, bishgigas ma'aseh,
it's sufficient that he does the act of ٍلهمن وّن لùهââ avoda
zara beshogeg, and he does not go by the normal ëنï âمهى
Kohen Gadol rules of having to ôهٌ÷ pasken for himself about it
first. هçëîéي vachachamim say لنٍىي ملّ, be'helam davar, no, it also requires
that he ôهٌ÷ paskens for himself first, it still follows the normal
ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol rules even though the ÷ّلï korban is the
same as that for a normal éùّàى. Yisrael. And that's the next
line. هùهéï, v'shavin, and they also agree ùëùٍéّن ëéçéم, she'k'seirah k'yachid, excuse
me I said goat, I meant ùٍéّن, seirah, a female goat, everybody
agrees that it is like an individual,
like the normal ÷ّلï korban of a normal, you know, of a
normal éùّàى Yisrael that is a female goat. In that way, he
is like a éùّàى, Yisrael, but the question is, does the question
of the need for ôٌ÷ paskening for himself still follow the rules
of the ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol or not? Okay, هùهéï, v'shavin, and
they also agree ùàéï îلéà
àùي ْىهé, she'ein mevi asham taluy, that a ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol
never brings an àùي ْىهé asham taluy if he has a doubt
whether he committed a sin and is çééل chayav a çèàْ chatas
offering, because his ÷ّلï korban is different than that of a éùّàى,
Yisrael, he does not bring an àùي ْىهé, asham taluy, the âîّà
Gemara, learns that out elsewhere, and also he doesn't even bring an
àùي ْىهé asham taluy even for ٍلهمن وّن avoda zara if he
has a doubt, even according to ّلé that says he follows the
normal rule of a éùّàى. Yisrael. Okay, but anyway, that's not really
our topic. The point is is that we're discussing a ëنï âمهى
Kohen Gadol by ٍلهمن وّن, avoda zara is it enough just for
him to do the act لùهââ b'shogeg or does he also have
to ôهٌ÷ pasken for himself? Now, that's going to get us to
àلéé's Abaye, case. Let's take a look at how. نéé ùâéâْ îٍùن
مٍلهمْ ëهëلéي نéëé مîé, hai shgigas ma'aseh d'avodas kochavim heichi dami,
what's the case that he accidentally, you know, sinned? Now, normally how
do you accidentally sin? Let's say for ùلْ, Shabbos, you can sin
that you could sort of like forget it's ùلْ, Shabbos, or you
could forget that this is forbidden on ùلْ. Shabbos. Okay, so let's
talk about ٍلهمن وّن. avoda zara. What would it mean to make
a mistake and to accidentally sin? You could forget that this thing
is an ٍلهمن وّن, avoda zara you know, you're bowing down because,
I don't know, you're greeting somebody or whatever, we'll see in the
case of the âîّà, Gemara you didn't realize the thing in front
of you was an ٍلهمن وّن. avoda zara. Well, then the âîّà's
Gemara going to say then you haven't sinned at all. Okay, so
the other case would be that you thought it was îهّْ. mutar.
Okay, well the âîّà's Gemara going to say what's that case and
it's going to use that to get to àلéé. Abaye Let's take
a look. Okay, نéé ùâéâْ îٍùن مٍلهمْ ëهëلéي نéëé مîé, hai shgigas
ma'aseh d'avodas kochavim heichi dami, what's the case that you had
a mistake and were ٍلّ over ٍلهمن وّن? avoda zara, But remember,
because it's a ëنï âمهى Kohen Gadol and we're saying whether it
doesn't require
it's just a mistaken act without a wrong ôٌ÷ psak for yourself.
So let's take a look how that could be. نé ùââْ îٍùن
مٍلهمن وّن نéëé مîé? hei shgegat ma’aseh de’avoda zara heichi dami? What's
the case? àéëà مٍلّ àلéْ نëًٌْ هنùْçهن ىه نّé ىله ىùîéي. ika
de'avar abei hakneset ve-hishtachava lo harei libo lashamayim. If he thought that
this place which was a لéْ ٍلهمن وّن, beit avoda zara, he
actually thought that he was in a ùهى shul and he bowed
down, he bowed down to it, like he's not worshipping the ùهى,
shul, he bowed down in it, in front of it, worshipping God,
then that has nothing to do îàنلن هîéّàن, then you're actually just
worshipping God in front of an ٍلهمن وّن. avoda zara That's not
even a ùهââ shogeg at all. That's not an act of ٍلهمن
وّن Avodah Zarah at all. Okay, àىà مçوà àًمّèà هنùْçهن ىن. ela
dechaza andarta vehishtachava lah. Okay, no, he saw a statue and he
bowed down to a statue, you know, of, I don't know, of
Hadrian or something. àé ÷لىéن ٍىéن لàىهن, ei kablei alei be'eloah, îوéم
نهà. meizid hu, So if he was, you know, bowing down not
as a sign of respect to the emperor but to show that
he treated the emperor as a god, so then that's not a
ùهââ, shogeg, that's a îوéم. meizid مَ ٌ"ل ٍîهم à. daf samech-bet
amud aleph. هàé ىà ÷لىéن ٍىéن لàىهن, ve-ei lo kablei alei be'eloah,
and if he did not accept Hadrian as his god, he just
bowed down as a show of respect, ىà ëىهي نهà, lo klum
hu, then it's not ٍلهمن وّن لùهââ, avoda zara beshogeg? it's not
ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah at all. So the âîّà Gemara says, what's
the case of ٍلهمن وّن لùهââ? avoda zara beshogeg Either you know
you're doing it, either you think it's, you're not treating it as
a
god, okay, you're praying to God or you're doing it as a
sign of respect, then it's not the act at all, or you're
treating it as a god and then it's not لùهââ. b'shogeg àىà
ىàه îàنلن هîéّàن. ela lav me'ahava umiyirah.
The only case that makes sense is àنلن هéّàن. ahava veyirah. Now
why did the âîّà Gemara not say, we'll get that the case
that you did it لùهââ beshogeg. is you thought it was permitted?
You thought it was, you know, permitted to do وéلهç zivuach or
÷éèهّ kitor or ًéٌهê nisuch or whatever it was? Because remember, they
couldn't say that. Why couldn't it say that? Because remember, we're talking
about a case where it was a ëنï âمهى kohen gadol only
did it through mistaken action but not through نٍىي ملّ, he'elam davar,
not through ôٌ÷ًéًâ paskening for himself, not through a mistaken ôٌ÷. psak.
So if he thought that it was permitted,
that's he was نٍىي ملّ. he'elam davar. But we're trying to get
a case where there was no نٍىي ملّ, he'elam davar, there was
only ùââْ îٍùن. shigegat ma'aseh. So what's the scenario? Ah, àنلن هéّàن.
ahava veyirah. He thought it was permitted to bow down out of
àنلن هéّàن, ahava veyirah, and that's the case. Now, you'll say to
me, that's again a case of ôٌ÷ًéًâ paskening for yourself. He made
a mistake in the نىëن, halacha, he made a mistake in the
ôٌ÷. psak. But the âîّà Gemara here is assuming, it seems a
bit of hair splitting, but the âîّà Gemara here is assuming that's
not نٍىي ملّ he'elam davar because he wasn't saying that something wasn't
an act of ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah that was an act of
ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah, He just thought that it was permissible under
these circumstances and it really was forbidden. But he recognized that the
act was considered an act of ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah Okay, to
me that's very, very hair splitting. But the âîّà Gemara somehow thinks
that according to àلéé, Abaye you can get a case of ùââْ
îٍùن shigegat ma'aseh without نٍىي ملّ, he'elam davar, without a wrong ôٌ÷,
psak, if the ôٌ÷, psak, if the wrong نىëن halachic understanding was
about àنلن هéّàن, ahava veyirah, which is not exactly about the act
itself. He thought it was permitted and he was wrong. It's really
like àلéé Abaye that it really is ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah? itself.
So ّلà Rava would say to you, so what would ّلà Rava,
say back? No, لàهîّ îهّْ. be'omer mutar. No, no, no, he thought
ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah. is totally permitted. Okay, and that was his,
that was how he did it لùهââ. beshogeg Okay, that's also a
wrong ôٌ÷. psak. So the âîّà Gemara says, àهîّ îهّْ نééًه نٍىي
ملّ. omer mutar haynu he'elam davar. No, that's a case of wrong
ôٌ÷ psak and we're looking for just a case of wrong action,
not wrong ôٌ÷. psak. So the âîّà Gemara says, no, لàهîّ îهّْ
ىâîّé. be'omer mutar legamrei. When he thinks, you know, again, I don't
know how somebody gets to be ëنï âمهى kohen gadol and doesn't
realize that there's an àéٌهّ issur in the ْهّن Torah: of ٍلهمن
وّن. Avodah Zarah, But he thinks ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah, is totally
permitted. Okay, that's not... and therefore that... and he worshipped ٍلهمن وّن.
Avodah Zarah That's a case of ùââْ îٍùن. shigegat ma'aseh. Why is
it not نٍىي ملّ? he'elam davar? نٍىي ملّ ÷éهي î÷ِْ هلéèهى î÷ِْ.
he'elam davar kiyum miktzat uvitul miktzat. Because نٍىي ملّ he'elam davar is
a case where you know the basic parameters but you got a
detail wrong. All right, so the âîّà Gemara has a very difficult
time of finding a case where somebody could be ٍهلّ ٍلهمن وّن
لùهââ over avoda zara beshogeg without getting the نىëن halacha wrong. Because
if you got the facts wrong, by ùلْ Shabbat you could forget
it's ùلْ Shabbat and then you're still being îçىى ùلْ. mechalel Shabbat.
But by ٍلهمن وّن, avoda zara, if you get the facts wrong,
right, that you think that this is a synagogue, or you know,
or you're not doing it because, you know, you're doing it out
of respect or something like that, it's not ùهââ, shogeg, you're not
doing the act at all. So it seems like by ٍلهمن وّن
avoda zara the case has to be, the only way you do
ٍلهمن وّن avoda zara لùهââ beshogeg. is if you get the نىëن
halacha wrong. But the âîّà Gemara has two cases of getting the
نىëن halacha wrong that would not technically be considered the normal نٍىي
ملّ he'elam davar of a ëنï âمهى. kohen gadol. One is you
thought everything was permitted, that's so grossly wrong that that's not ôٌ÷ًéًâ
paskening incorrectly, that's like just gross ignorance, and that's considered doing the
sin without نٍىي ملّ, he'elam davar, okay, or with too much نٍىي
ملّ. he'elam davar. And the other case is àلéé, if you think,
if you think àنلن هéّàن. ahava veyirah. is not çééل chayav because
it's not directly about the act, that also would not be a
case of نٍىي ملّ. Helem Davar. All right, those are the two
interpretations, but we have not yet proven àلéé or ّلà Rava, and
we really that is the end of that debate. Okay, now the
âîّà's Gemara going to reference it in the next piece, but before
we go on, I just want to say something about ّîل"ي's Rambam
position. We already said one thing very important about this debate, about
the difference about éنّâ هàى éٍلهّ yehareg ve-al ya'avor and the definition
of what constitutes ٍلهمن وّن avoda zara that's çééل îéْن. chayav misa
ّîل"ي Rambam says something very different about àنلن هéّàن. ahavah ve-yirah. ّîل"ي
Rambam, says îàنلن
هîéّàن that you're not çééل chayav according to ّلà, Rava which is
how we ôهٌ÷ï, pasken, is that you're doing it from àنلن هéّàن
ahavah ve-yirah of the god. That you basically are doing it because
you're afraid of the consequences of if you violate the will of
the god, or that you are afraid of getting... oh, no, that's
éّàن, yirah, or àنلن ahava you want the god to bestow you
with goodness. That is not real ٍلهمْ ٍلهمن وّن avodat Avodah Zarah
that you're çééل Chayav for. Which is pretty amazing because isn't that
like how most people are ٍهلم ٍلهمن وّن oved Avodah Zarah because
they want something from the god? And it sounds like from ّîل"ي,
Rambam I mean he actually says if you only do it out
of those reasons you're not çééل Chayav. until you accept this ٍلهمن
وّن avoda zara as a god. Well, what does it mean to
accept it as a god? You already believing that it's going to
do good or bad for you. So it sounds like for ّîل"ي
Rambam that believing that it has powers and believing that the actions
you are going to do are going to curry favor with it
or avoid its displeasure is not really accepting it as a god.
Really, what, you know, it could just be a force in the
universe that you're trying to placate. Really accepting something as a god
is that you're doing it because you believe that this being is
supreme and therefore you do what the being wills because it is
the supreme being or a supreme being. Okay. And anything short of
that for ّîل"ي Rambam. is not the real àîهًن, emunah, it's just
currying favor with the forces of the universe. Quite fascinating. Okay, so
a very rigorous definition of the faith that is needed to be
çééل Chayav. for ٍلهمن وّن avoda zara, for ّîل"ي. All right, so
now we continue. ًْé ّلé, ّلé وëàé ÷îéن مّلé éهçًï. Tani Rabbi,
Rabbi Zakkai kamei de-Rabbi Yochanan. So ّلé وëàé Rabbi Zakkai taught in
front of ّلé éهçًï. Rabbi Yochanan. ولç ه÷éèّ هًéٌê هنùْçههن لنٍىي àçم
àéًه çééل àىà àçْ. Zivach ve-kitar ve-nisach ve-hishtachavah be-helem echad eino chayav
ela achat. If
somebody did all the ٍلهمهْ avodot of ٍلهمن وّن, avoda zara. I
mean at least the classic ones that you're çééل chayav for no
matter what the idol is, what the ٍلهمن وّن avoda zara. is,
right? You slaughtered, you burned on the fire, you did the libation,
you bowed down, and it was all in one state of forgetfulness,
okay, that again you thought that it was îهّْ mutar to do
all of these types of acts. Okay. Since those are all forms
of ٍلهمن, Avodah he says you're really only... so you only bring
one ÷ّلï çèàْ korban chatas لùهââ be-shogeg because it's like you just
did the same ٍلéّن aveirah again and again. If somebody ate çىل,
chelev, which is you're çééل ëّْ, chayav kares, and if you do
it لùهââ be-shogeg you bring a çèàْ. chatas. And if somebody forgot
that çىل chelev was àٌهّ, asur, or if somebody thought the food
in front of him wasn't çىل, chelev, and he ate one ëوéْ
kezayis and another and another, and he did not remember in the
middle that çىل chelev was àٌهّ. asur. He didn't realize... he didn't
stop remembering in the middle that it was çىل chelev and then
forget again, okay, it was all in one state of ignorance or
forgetfulness, that's called نٍىي àçم, helem echad, then he would only bring
one ÷ّلï korban no matter how many ëوéْéي kezayisim you ate. So
similarly, all of these are just forms of ٍلهمن avoda and you
would only bring one ÷ّلï korban if it was all لنٍىي àçم.
be-helem echad.
àîّ ىéن, Amar lei, so ّلé éهçًï Rabbi Yochanan said back to
this ّلé وëàé: Rabbi Zakkai: ôه÷ ًْé ىلّà. Puk tani li-vara. Go
teach it outside. Meaning this is not an acceptable part of the
canon. I don't agree with this ruling even if you have it
as some source that handed it down. àîّ ّلé àلà, Amar Rabbi
Abba, نà مّلé وëàé îçىه÷ْ ّلé éهٌé هّلé ًْï. Ha de-Rabbi Zakkai
machloket Rabbi Yosi ve-Rabbi Natan. So now we're going to see why
he did not accept it. Okay. So ّلé àلà Rabbi Abba said,
that which ّلé وëàé Rabbi Zakkai said,
îçىه÷ْ ّلé éهٌé هّلé ًْï, machloket Rabbi Yosi ve-Rabbi Natan, whether to
treat these as different acts, different like types of ٍلéّهْ aveirot or
all just variations of the same. مًْéà, Detanya, we taught a لّééْà.
Braisa. نلٍّن ىىàه éِàن ملّé ّلé éهٌé. Havarah le-lav yatza, divrei Rabbi
Yosi. It says in the ْهّن: Torah ىà ْلٍّه àù لëى îهùلهْéëي
لéهي نùلْ. Lo te-va'aru esh be-chol moshvoteichem be-yom ha-Shabbat. Okay, why does
it specifically speak about fire if it already said don't do any
îىàëن? melachah? So there's a debate why it's singling out fire. ّلé
éهٌé Rabbi Yosi says that it's coming to tell you that it's
a negative prohibition, and actually fire, which one would think is the
most paradigmatic form of çéىهى ùلْ, chillul Shabbat, but according to ّلé
éهٌé, Rabbi Yosi, it's only a negative prohibition, you're not çééل chayav
îéْن. Misah That's why it's singled out. ّلé ًْï àهîّ ىçى÷ éِàن.
Rabbi Natan omer le-challek yatza. No, it's coming to distinguish it and
to say that it is treated separate from the other îىàëهْ. melachot.
And once one îىàëن melachah is treated separate from the other îىàëهْ,
melachot, from that we learn out that all the îىàëهْ melachot are
seen as separate from one another. So that... and which leads to
the نىëن halachah that if you do multiple îىàëهْ melachot in one
state of forgetfulness, that you bring multiple çèàهْ chataot according to ّلé
ًْï. Rabbi Natan. That you learn out from the fact that the
ْهّن Torah. singled out fire. You don't look at every single îىàëن
Melacha as just a form of çéىهى ùلْ. Chillul Shabbos. You look
at it as a distinct type of ٍلéّن Aveira and therefore you
will bring multiple çèàهْ. Chataot. Okay, ىçى÷. Lechalaik. So now the âîّà
Gemara says like this. So how is this, this should be exactly
the same question about ٍلهمن وّن? Avodah Zarah, And why did ّلé
éهçًï Rebbi Yochanan so reject it altogether? ىîàï مàîّ نلٍّن ىىàه éِàْ,
Leman de’amar hav’arah lelave yatzat, according to ّلé éهٌé Rebbi Yossi that
says نلٍّن Hav’arah is a simple negative prohibition but there's not a
principle of, but we don't learn from it that each one is
treated separately. نùْçهàن ًîé ىىàه éِàْ. Hishtachavayah nami lelave yatzat. So we
know ىà ْùْçهن lo tish-tachaveh ىني is singled out from هىà ٍْلمي.
Velo ta’avdeim, It’s the specific ٍلهمن avoda. that is singled out, just
like fire is the specific îىàëن Melacha that is singled out in
the ْهّن. Torah نùْçهàن, Hishtachavayah, a prostration, is the single ٍلهمن avoda.
that is singled out from the other ٍلهمهْ. Avodot. So do you
learn from that to treat every ٍلهمن avoda as a distinct ٍلéّن?
Aveira? Well, that should be dependent on the debate. For ّلé éهٌé,
Rebbi Yossi, no. You learn from that to treat it as a
negative prohibition, but not as a distinct ٍلéّن. Aveira. Now ّù"é deals
with the question, what would it mean that you wouldn't get îéْن
Misah for نùْçهàن? Hishtachavayah? It says نùْçهàن Hishtachavayah a number of times,
so you would get îéْن for نùْçهàن. Hishtachavayah. But anyway the point
being, for ّلé éهٌé, Rebbi Yossi, you don't learn from this singling
out to treat it as a separate
prohibition and therefore you would only get one, which is what this
ًْà Tanna said, even if you do multiple things you only bring
one ÷ّلï. Korban. ىîàï مàîّ نلٍّن ىçى÷ éِàْ, Leman de’amar hav’arah lechalaik
yatzat, but according to ّلé ًْï Rebbi Nassan that says from fire
you learn out to treat each one as distinct, نùْçهàن ًîé ىçى÷
éِàْ. Hishtachavayah nami lechalaik yatzat. So you'd say the same about prostration.
It was part of هىà ٍْلمي, it was singled out to tell
you that for every single ٍلهمن avoda it’s treated as a separate
ٍلهمن and even in one state of forgetfulness you bring multiple çèàهْ.
Chataot. So he said, I don't get why ّلé éهçًï Rebbi Yochanan
completely rejected this لّééْà. Braisa, It works very well with ّلé éهٌé
Rebbi Yossi that says by fire we don't treat it as a
basis for singling out and treating each one separately, and we similarly
would not treat نùْçهàن Hishtachavayah to teach you that you treat each
one separately. îْ÷éَ ىن ّل éهٌَ, Maskif lah Rav Yosef, ّل éهٌَ
Rav Yosef said, no no no, you cannot say that the debate
by fire is the same debate here by ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah
îْ÷éَ ىن ّل éهٌَ, Maskif lah Rav Yosef, مéىîà ٍم ëàï ىà
÷àîّ ّلé éهٌé نْي نلٍّن ىىàه éِàْ, Dilma ad kan lo ka’amar
Rebbi Yossi hatam hav’arah lelave yatzat, why did ّلé éهٌé Rebbi Yossi
say that fire is just a ىàه and we don't learn it
to treat each îىàëن Melacha as separate? مًô÷à ىéن ٌéمهّ îىàëهْ îàçْ
îنًن Denafka leh sidur melachos me’achas meihena because he already knows the
principle that you treat each îىàëن Melacha separate. From the ôٌه÷ Pasuk
it says that if somebody does a sin îàçْ îنًن, Me’achas meihena,
from one of these sins, then he would bring a ÷ّلï. Korban.
Okay, and from that phrase îàçْ îنًن, Me’achas meihena, from one, from
these,
we're going to learn this idea that each one is treated as
separate, each one of the îىàëهْ. Melachot. Okay, we'll see that in
a minute. So since he already knows that each îىàëن Melacha is
treated separately, he can say نلٍّن Hav’arah is coming to tell you
a different point, just a negative prohibition. But when it comes to
ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah, he would agree that the first thing you
do is you learn from a ôٌه÷ Pasuk that each one is
treated separately and therefore by ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah. نùْçهàن Hishtachavayah would
be telling you each one is treated separately and that's why ّلé
éهçًï Rebbi Yochanan did not like it. Everybody would agree by ٍلهمن
وّن Avodah Zarah, each one is treated separately just like everybody agrees
by ùلْ Shabbos that each îىàëن Melacha is treated separately. Okay, now
let's see how he learns this out from îàçْ îنًن. Me’achas meihena.
مًْéà, we taught in a لّééْà, braita. ّلé éهٌé àهîّ, Rebbi Yossi
omer, هٍùن îàçْ îنًن, Ve’asah me’achas meihena,
and if somebody sins and does from one from these, ôٍîéي ùçééل
àçْ ٍى ëهىï, Pe’amim shechayav achas al kulan,
there are sometimes where you would bring one ÷ّلï Korban even if
you did multiple îىàëهْ, Melachot, هôٍîéي ùçééل ٍى ëى àçْ هàçْ, Upe’amim
shechayav al kol achas ve’achas,
and sometimes you'd bring multiple ÷ّلًهْ Korbanot on multiple îىàëهْ. Melachot. Okay,
now how does he learn it out and what does this exactly
mean? àîّ ّل éهًْï îàé èٍîà مّلé éهٌé, Amar Rav Yonatan mai
ta’ama deRebbi Yossi, let me explain to you the reason of ّلé
éهٌé. Rebbi Yossi. مëْéل هٍùن îàçْ îنًن. Dechsiv ve’asah me’achas meihena. Okay,
that's the ôٌه÷, Pasuk, you do from one from these. And we
learn the following different things. Number one, àçْ, îàçْ, نًن, îنًن, achat
me'achat heina meheinah one, from one, many, from many. That's as we'll
see, all of these are different things we'll learn out, we'll see
them in a minute. àçْ ùنéà نًن هنًن ùنéà àçْ, Achas she’hi
heina veheina she’hi achas, one that is many and many that is
one. So now we're going to spell this out. àçْ, Achas, one,
ùîٍهï, Shimon, you did the standard ٍلéّن, Aveira, you had an intent
to write the name ùîٍهï Shimon on ùلْ, Shabbos, you wrote the
name, you're çééل chayav a çèàْ Chatas if you did it لùهââ.
Beshogeg.
îàçْ, Me’achas, from one, ùي îùîٍهï. Sheim miShimon. If you wrote ù'
î' Shin Mem and you stopped there and you didn't finish writing
ùîٍهï, Shimon, but since you intended to write those two letters and
those two letters is already a full word, ùي, Sheim, so therefore
you now are çééل. chayav, Okay, so even if you intended to
do àçْ Achas, but you only wound up doing îàçْ, Me’achas, as
long as that's a full îىàëن Melacha you're still çééل. chayav That's
what we learn from àçْ Achas and îàçْ. Me’achas, نًن, Heina, what
does نًن Heina, tell me? but that there are àلهْ îىàëن avot
melacha on ùلْ, Shabbas, there are multiple forms of çéىهى ùلْ. chilul
Shabbat. îنًن, Meiheina, from many. ْهىمهْ, toldot, something that derives from the
àلهْ, avot, it tells you ْهىمهْ. toldot. So from that we've learned
out ùي îùîٍهï, shem miShimon, we've learned out àلهْ avos and ْهىمهْ,
toldados, and that is now we're going to learn out something, that
is from the fact it says the î, mem, îàçْ îنًن, me'achat
meheinah, and now we're going to learn something from the juxtaposition of
the two words.
àçْ ùنéà نًن, achat she'hi heina, you can have one that is
many. What does that mean? ùââْ ùلْ هùéââْ îىàëهْ. shegagas Shabbas v'shigagas
melachos. If you knew it was ùلْ, Shabbas, but you forgot individual
îىàëهْ, melachos, you forgot that it was àٌهّ assur to make a
fire, you forgot it was àٌهّ assur to knead bread, you forgot
it was àٌهّ assur to pick fruit, so then because your forgetfulness
is a distinct forgetfulness for each îىàëن, melacha, you bring multiple çèàهْ.
chataot. Each نٍىي, he'elam, each forgetfulness, each ignorance, defines it as a
separate act. That would be a case where it would be multiple.
نًن ùنéà àçْ, heina she'hi achat, now you can have times of
doing multiple things but you're only going to bring one ÷ّلï. korban.
ùââْ ùلْ هومهï îىàëهْ, shegagas Shabbas v'zadon melachos, that you knew that
different îىàëهْ melachos were àٌهّ, assur, you know it's àٌهّ assur to
knead bread and to grind and to pick fruit, but you forgot
it was ùلْ. Shabbas. Since it is one thing you forgot, that
makes it all things puts everything in the same category and means
you only bring one ÷ّلï. korban. So what do you see from
this? You see that there is a principle of çéىه÷ îىàëهْ chiluk
melachos that you learn from îàçْ îنًن, me'achat meheinah, and as long
as your forgetting each thing each thing has its own act of
ignorance or forgetting, then you would go ahead and bring multiple sin
offerings. So even ّلé éهٌé Rebbe Yosi already knows there is a
principle of çéىه÷ îىàëهْ, chiluk melachos, and therefore he was able to
use the principle of àù eish to tell you a different thing,
of that it is a what do you call it, that it
is a ىىàه
éِàْ. l'lav yatza. àلى نëà, aval hacha, so you see that by
ùلْ Shabbas he knows the idea of çéىه÷ îىàëهْ chiluk melachos and
that is what he does with àù. eish. àلى نëà aval hacha
by ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah, مىà ًô÷à ىéن çéىه÷ îىàëهْ îمهëْà àçّéْé,
d'lo nafkalei chiluk melachos miduchta achriti, there is nowhere else to learn
out the idea of treating each ٍلهمن of ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah.
as a separate act, مëهىé ٍىîà نùْçهن ىçى÷ éِàْ. d'kulei alma hishtachava
l'chalek yatza. Everybody would agree that the fact that it says ىà
ْùْçهن singles it out from ىà ٍْلمي lo ta'ovdeim is to tell
you that you treat each act of ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah distinctly.
That is a very strong argument. It is basically look, when it
comes to ùلْ Shabbas everybody agrees to çéىه÷ îىàëهْ, chiluk melachos, so
when it is going to come to ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah everybody
is going to agree to çéىه÷ ٍلهمهْ chiluk avodos as
well, doesn't matter ّلé éهٌé Rebbe Yosi or whoever or ّلé ًْï,
Rebbe Nosson, and that is why ّلé éهçًï Rebbe Yochanan rejected that
لّééْà. braisa. çéىه÷ îىàëهْ مٍلهمْ ëهëلéي ًîé ْéôه÷ ىéن îàçْ îنًن. chiluk
melachos d'avodas kochavim nami teipokei me'achat meheinah. So now the âîّà Gemara.
has a separate question. Why are we sort of saying that he
is learning out
çéىه÷ îىàëهْ chiluk melachos of ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah from the idea
of what do you call it from the idea of نùْçهن? hishtachava?
Why you made a very good point that you have this whole
ôٌه÷ pasuk îàçْ îنًن. me'achat meheinah. So why can't let's learn and
so yes we're agreeing with you everybody should agree that there is
çéىه÷ ٍلهمهْ chiluk avodos from ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah. but why learn
it out from نùْçهن? hishtachava? Learn it out from îàçْ îنًن, me'achat
meheinah, that's not specifically about ùلْ, Shabbas, that's a ôٌه÷ pasuk in
general about a ÷ّلï çèàْ. korban chatas. ًîé ْéôه÷ ىéن îàçْ îنًن.
nami teipokei me'achat meheinah. àçْ Achas
and here we're going to go the whole ôٌه÷, pasuk, àçْ achat
îàçْ Me’achas. نًن Heina îنًن meheinah, and apply the whole thing for
ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah Let's see how we'll do it. àçْ ولéçن.
achat zvicha.
One is you shecht the animal, that's a full act. îàçْ, me'achat,
so ٌéîï àçم, siman echad, if you only shechted one, the trachea
or the esophagus not both, the same way îàçْ me'achat is ùي
îùîٍهï, shem miShimon, îàçْ me'achat is one ٌéîï siman of the animal.
نًن, heina, àلهْ, avot, ولéçن ÷éèهّ ًéٌهê هنùْçهن. ziviyach kitor nisuch v'hishtachava.
So نًن, heina, multiple, these is all of the different primary acts
of ٍلهمن. îنًن, meheinah, ْهىمهْ, toldot, and îنًن meheinah we could have
a similar idea of ْهىمهْ toldot by ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah. What
would that be? ùéلّ î÷ى ىôًéن. shiber makel l'faneha. Let's say instead
of slaughtering an animal you broke a stick. Well it is sort
of you're taking an object that you're offering and you're doing an
act of breaking it. This is another discussion in another âîّà. Gemara
That is considered like ùçéèن. shechita. Now that seems a little bizarre
that that should be like ùçéèن. shechita. Remember we're talking about a
case that that's not the normal way of ٍلهمن. We're only making
you çééل chayav by ùçéèن shechita if it's not the normal ٍلهمن
because it's the classic form in which a classic worship because it's
based on a ôٌه÷. pasuk. And nevertheless we say that the same
way a classic work of shechting an animal, it would also be
breaking a stick. The âîّà Gemara qualifies it only if normally you
use this type of a stick to do forms of worship that
are the normal way, like you normally dance with a stick in
front of it, so the stick is considered to be a meaningful
thing for this idol, then breaking it becomes a type of a
ùçéèن. shechita. It's a strange idea but anyway that's what. What we
learn after from îàçْ Mei'achas or îنًن, Mei'heina, which is an idea
of ْهىمهْ. Toldos. àçْ ëنًن, Achas ki heina, ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah.
ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي.
And now we're going to get to our point about çéىه÷ îىàëهْ
chiluk melachos or çéىه÷ ٍلهمهْ. chiluk avodos. One which is many. You
know that ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah? is àٌهّ, asur, you know this
is an ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah, but you forgot that it was
àٌهّ asur to do ًéٌهê nisuch and you forgot it was àٌهّ
asur to do نùْçهéن hishtachavaya and for each one then you're going
to bring a separate çèàْ chatas because it's a different forgetfulness. نًن
ùنéà àçْ, Heina she'hi achas, multiple which is one, ùââْ ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي
shiggas Avodas Kochavim لومهï ٍلهمهْ. bezadon avodos. You knew that these separate
ٍلهمهْ avodos were àٌهّ, asur, but you forgot ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah,
Now we're going to get back to what does it mean forgetting
ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah because if you didn't realize this thing was
an ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah you haven't even done the sin at
all. Okay, but anyway, let's go ahead and learn out from this,
why do we learn it out from نùْçهéن? hishtachava? Now we're sort
of saying yes, yes, it makes sense, everybody would say çéىه÷ îىàëهْ
chiluk melachos and you bring multiple ÷ّلًهْ korbanos if you forget the
depth, the different forms of ٍلهمن for ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah. Okay,
so but the question is why learn it out from نùْçهéن, hishtachava,
why not learn it out from îàçْ îنًن? Mei'achas Mei'heina? So let's
see what the âîّà Gemara says.
Okay, so before it answers it, we're going to try to now
figure out what's that scenario that you forgot ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah
but you knew that these things were àٌهّ? asur? Okay, what exactly
are you forgetting? نàé ùââْ ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي نéëé مîé? Hai shiggas Avodas
Kochavim heichi dami?
What's the case? àé ÷ٌلّ لéْ نëًٌْ نéà هنùْçهن ىن, Ee kasavar
beisa knesses hi v'hishtachavei lei, you thought it was a shul and
you were bowing down and you were praying to God, okay, نّé
ىله ىùîéي. harei libo lashamayim. Okay, then it's
then it's not ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah at all, it's not a
ùهââ. shogeg. It's not like forgetting it's Shabbos where you actually wind
up doing îىàëن melacha on Shabbos. Here it's not ٍلهمن وّن Avodah
Zarah if you don't realize that this if you think that you're
praying to God. àىà مçوà àًمّْà هٌâéم ىن, Ela d'chazan darta v'sagid
lei, this sounds familiar. Okay, you see a statue and you bow
down to it. Okay, what's the scenario? àé ÷لىن ٍىéن îوéم, Ee
kibla alei meizid, if you accepted it as a god, again you're
not a ùهââ, shogeg, then you're worshipping ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah àé
ىà ÷لىن ٍىéن ىàه ëىهي نهà, Ee lo kibla alei lo klumu,
and if you're doing it as a form of just respect, it's
not ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah? at all. So what's the case? You
can understand the case where you don't realize certain acts are considered
the prohibited act of ٍلهمن وّن. avodah zarah, I mean why you're
doing it لëىى, be-chal, but okay, you didn't realize it was لçéهل
îéْن be-chayav misa of ٍلهمن وّن. avodah zarah. But what's the case
that you knew the acts were prohibited and you forgot or you
were ignorant about something and it's still going to be an act
of ٍلهمن وّن? avodah zarah If you're ignorant that this is an
idol, then it's not ٍلهمن وّن, avodah zarah and if you know
it is and you're believing in it, then it's then it's not
ùهââ. shogeg. àىà îàنلن هîéّàن. Ela mei'ahava u'miyira. So now we're circling
back. It must be the case is you know it's an idol,
you know that these acts are forbidden ٍلهمن وّن, avodah zarah but
your ùهââ shogeg was that you thought you weren't çééل chayav îéْن
if you did it out of àنلن ahava and éّàن, yira, and
that was your ùهââ. shogeg. So and therefore you did all these
different acts. So since it was one basic thing that you forgot,
like forgetting it's Shabbos, you didn't forget separately ùçéèن shechita and ًéٌهê
nisuch and نùْçهéن. hishtachavaya. No, there was one thing you forgot. By
Shabbos, you forgot it's Shabbos. By here, you forgot you thought that
it was permitted even though it was àنلن ahava and éّàن. yira.
Okay, and therefore it was one thing you forgot, so you did
ٍلهمن وّن avodah zarah. لùهââ beshogeg and but you're only going to
bring one ÷ّلï. korban. All right. So now the âîّà Gemara says
نà ًéçà ىàلéé مàîّ çééل. Hacha nicha l'Abaye d'amar chayav. For that
works for Abaye that says àنلن and éّàن yira it is ٍلهمن
وّن Avoda Zara and you are çééل chayav and you made a
mistake and you thought it was it wasn't ٍلهمن وّن. Avoda Zara
àىà ىّلà مàîّ ôèهّ îàé àéëà ىîéîّ? Ela l'Rava d'amar patur mai
ika l'meimar? But for Rava you're stuck. What can you say? There's
no explanation. You can't say you thought it was because you're right,
it isn't ٍلهمن وّن Avoda Zara, if you do it under those
circumstances. So you wouldn't bring a çèàْ chatas if you only did
it îàنلن هîéّàن. àىà لàهîّ îهّْ. Ela b'omer mutar.
Okay, fine. So for Rava the case is that you thought the
whole thing was permitted. Now you thought there's no àéٌهّ issur ٍلهمن
وّن Avoda Zara. before, like we said before. Okay, so the funny
thing is then you don't really have a case of لومهï ٍلهمهْ,
zedon avodos, right? You don't it's not like you know نùْçهéن hishtachava
is àٌهّ, asur, you know ولéçن zivvach is àٌهّ, asur, you know
whatever. It's actually you think everything is permitted and nevertheless because it's
all-inclusive, all right, then you're only going to bring one ÷ّلï. korban.
So the âîّà Gemara says ْéôùهè لٍéà ملٍé ّلà îّل ًçîï. tipshotei
ba'ei minei Rava mei'Rav Nachman. So if that's true we can use
this to conclude what Rava asked Rav Nachman. نٍىي ون هون لéمه
îنه? Heilem zeh v'zeh biyado mahu?
So he says let's say you both forgot it was Shabbos and
you forgot the specific things were forbidden on Shabbos. Do we say
that that's one ÷ّلï korban because you forgot Shabbos and that would
have led to doing multiple ٍلéّهْ, aveiros, or do we say because
you forgot each individual thing as well was forbidden, you bring multiple
÷ّلًهْ? korbanos? ْéôùهè مàéًه çééل àىà àçْ. tipshotei eino chayav ela achas.
Since that's essentially what you're reading here to this ٍلهمن وّن Avoda
Zara, case, you would have to conclude that if you totally forgot
ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah. like totally forgetting it was Shabbos and forgetting
that the things themselves were forbidden, that it would only be one
÷ّلï. korban. So the âîّà Gemara says àىà àçْ نëé ىà ÷ùéà
هْéôùهè. ela achas hachi lo kasha v'tipshotei. Yes,
fine. Okay, you could have concluded that, maybe àéï نëé ًîé. ein
hachi nami. So what did we say? We said that... There was
an argument that if you did multiple ٍلهمهْ avodahs you're only çééل
chayav. once. Okay. And presumably even if you forgot that each one
separately more and that was rejected. âîّà Gemara says why is it
rejected? Maybe it's like similar to the idea that نلٍّن havarah is
ىىàه éِàْ. lelav yatzas. And the âîّà Gemara said like ّلé éهٌé
Rebbi Yosi says no, because even ّلé éهٌé Rebbi Yosi agrees that
there's an idea of çéىه÷ îىàëهْ chiluk melachos by ùلْ, Shabbos, so
and that's the starting place, that's the first thing you establish. So
here too everybody would agree that there would be çéىه÷ îىàëهْ, chiluk
melachos, çéىه÷ ٍلهمهْ, chiluk avodahs, they learn it out from نùْçهéن. hishtachavayah.
And then the âîّà Gemara just says well why do you have
to learn it okay, it's not really debating that point, but why
do you have to learn it out from نùْçهéن, hishtachavayah, why do
you learn it out îن àçْ îنًن? me'achas mehena? And it shows
how you could have learned it out. And the basic answer is
like okay, maybe according to àلéé you could have learned it out
because the idea of forgetting the one overarching thing would have been
àنلن هéّàن ahava veyirah but for ّلà, the only scenario for forgetting
an overarching thing like forgetting it was ùلْ Shabbos would be actually
thinking that everything was totally permissible. Okay. And then in that case
you would only bring one ÷ّلï. korban.
All right. Now the âîّà Gemara goes on like this. هîé îِéْ
îه÷îْ ىنًé ÷ّàé لٍلهمْ ëهëلéي? Umi matzis mokmes lahani kraei ba'avodas kochavim?
How could you suggest that these ôٌه÷éي pesukim of îن àçْ îنًن
me'achas mehena would apply to ٍلهمن وّن? Avodah Zarah? Why? مàéىه نëà
ëْéل لîùéç ôّ هلًùéà ùٍéّ هلéçéم ëùلن هùٍéّن.
D'ilu hacha ksiv bimshiach par uv'nasi sa'ir
uv'yachid kisbah us'irah.
In this section in the ْهّن Torah where it speaks about îن
àçْ îنًن me'achas mehena is where it's talking about the normal ÷ّلï
çèàْ korban chatas that people bring and it says an individual brings
a ëùلن هùٍéّن, kisbah us'irah, a goat or a sheep, a ًùéà,
nasi, which is like a îىê, melech, you know, brings a goat,
and the îùهç îىçîن—excuse mashuach milchamah me, a ëنï îùéç, kohen mashiach,
meaning a ëنï âمهى kohen gadol brings a ôّ. par. It's exactly
in the section of the ْهّن Torah where it's talking about the
standard ÷ّلï çèàْ korban chatat that are brought whether by an individual
or a ëنï âمهى kohen gadol or a king. Okay. هàéىه لٍلهمْ
ëهëلéي ًْï, V'ilu ba'avodas kochavim tnan,
but we know when it comes to ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah هùهéï
ùلùٍéّن ëéçéم, v'shavin shebish'irah k'yachid, that everybody agrees that it's the same
÷ّلï. korban. It is not these distinctions of a ôّ par or
whatever that whether ëنï âمهى, kohen gadol, whether a îىê, melech, whether
an individual, everybody brings the same she-goat if it is a ÷ّلï
korban of ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah So the âîّà Gemara says هْه
ىà îéمé v'su lo mi'idi and that is the end of that
discussion. Meaning that you could not learn out from îن àçْ îنًن,
me'achas mehena, which remember is not said by ùلْ, Shabbos, it's just
said generically by a ÷ّلï çèàْ. korban chatas. So we say can
we learn and we apply it to ùلْ Shabbos to learn all
these principles of àلهْ هْهىمهْ, avos toldos, you know, multiple ÷ّلًهْ, korbanos,
single ÷ّلï korban and etc. And then the question was could we
have applied it to ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah, and we did different
permutations, maybe we could, but now the âîّà Gemara is saying you
know what, forget that. You can't apply this to ٍلهمن وّن Avodah
Zarah. because the whole context in the ْهّن is talking about when
people bring different ÷ّلًهْ korbanos based on are you a ëنï âمهى
kohen gadol or whatever, and when it comes to ٍلهمن وّن Avodah
Zarah they bring the same ÷ّلï. korban. So clearly this îن àçْ
îنًن me'achas mehena is not talking about ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah Okay
fine. Anyway bottom line is we still learn the idea from نùْçهéن
hishtachavayah that there is çéىه÷
ٍلهمهْ. chiluk avodahs. هْه ىà îéمé. V'su lo mi'idi. ëé àْà ّل
ùîهàى لّ éنهمن àîّ Ki ata Rav Shmuel bar Yehuda amar when
ùîهàى لّ éنهمن Shmuel bar Yehuda came he
said top of ٌ"ç ٍ"ل. samech ches amud beis. نëé ًْé ÷îéن.
Hachi tani kameih. No, no. What the ًْà tanna taught in front
of ّلé éهçًï Rebbi Yochanan was not the idea of you know
that of only bringing one ÷ّلï korban for multiple ٍلهمهْ avodahs and
that's what got ّلé éهçًï Rebbi Yochanan upset and rejected it. No,
that's not what he taught. He taught a different لّééْà. braisa نëé
ًْé ÷îéن. Hachi tani kameih. çهîّ لùلْ îùàّ îِهْ هçهîّ لùàّ îِهْ
îلùلْ. Chomer be'Shabbos mish'ar mitzvos vechomer b'sh'ar mitzvos mi'be'Shabbos. There's ways that
ùلْ Shabbos is stricter than other îِههْ mitzvos and other îِههْ mitzvos
are stricter than ùلْ. Shabbos. çهîّ لùلْ ùùلْ ٍùن ùْéي لنٍىي àçم
çééل ٍى ëى àçْ هàçْ. Chomer be'Shabbos she'Shabbos asah shtayim be'he'elam echad
chayav al kol achas ve'achas. By ùلْ Shabbos if you do two
meaning two separate îىàëهْ melachos
in
one state of forgetfulness you bring separate çèàهْ chataos as we have
discussed as long as you forgot each one sort of separately. îن
ùàéï ëï لùàّ îِهْ. Ma she'ein kein b'sh'ar mitzvos. By other îِههْ
mitzvos if you do you know multiple things, you eat çىل cheilev
and çىل cheilev or whatever, because there's not an idea of separate
îىàëهْ, melachos, it's all seen as the same act, you're only going
to bring one ÷ّلï. korban. هçهîّ
لùàّ îِهْ îلùلْ. Vechomer b'sh'ar mitzvos mi'be'Shabbos. Now how is other îِههْ
mitzvos more strict than ùلْ? Shabbos? ùلùàّ îِهْ ùهââ لىà îْëهéï çééل.
Shebish'ar mitzvos shogeg belo miskavein chayav. In other îِههْ mitzvos if you
were ùهââ shogeg unintentionally you still have to bring a
÷ّلï. korban. Now îن ùàéï ëï لùلْ. ma she'ein kein b'Shabbos. Now
what do you mean by ùلْ? Shabbos? Of course you bring a
÷ّلï korban when you're ùهââ. shogeg. But we'll see what the âîّà
Gemara is going to mean. It's going to mean a case of
like îٌٍْ÷. misasek. You were trying to do one thing and you
actually wound up doing another thing. So by certain other sins, nevertheless
you'll be çééل, chayav but by ùلْ Shabbos if you're îٌٍْ÷, misasek,
îىàëْ îçùلْ àٌّن ْهّن, meleches machsheves asra Torah, because it was unintentional
and you were trying to do something else, you're totally ôèهّ, patur
you don't even bring a ÷ّلï. korban. Okay now let's take a
look. Now we're going to unpack this. And ّلé éهçًï Rebbi Yochanan
rejected that. But first we have to understand it before we understand
why ّلé éهçًï Rebbi Yochanan rejected it. àîّ îّ. Amar Mar. So
let's go back and unpack it. çهîّ لùلْ ùùلْ ٍùن ùْéي. Chomer
be'Shabbos she'Shabbos asah shtayim. نéëé مîé? Heichi dami? What's the case that
by ùلْ Shabbos it says that... If that is you do two,
you bring two ÷ّلًهْ. korbanos. àéىéîà مٍلéم ÷ِéّن هèçéًن, Ilima d’avid ktzira
v’techina,
you do different îىàëهْ, melachos, you cut something and you grind it.
مëههْéن âلé ùàّ îِههْ مçىل همي. D’chvasay gabi shear mitzvos d’chalav v’dam.
So,
you know, the funny thing about ùلْ Shabbos and ٍلهمن وّن Avodah
Zarah is that there are very different discrete acts that are all
part of like one big ٍلéّن. aveira. Okay, you know, like by
ùلْ Shabbos it’s don’t do any îىàëن, melacha, but that’s defined as
thirty-nine very distinct categories. And the çéمهù chiddush is that each one
of those categories, even though it’s basically the ٍلéّن aveira of çéىهى
ùلْ, chilul Shabbos, is considered distinct and you would bring a separate
÷ّلï. korban. And the same by ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah is what
we’ve been saying: نùْçهéن, hishtachavaya, وéلهç, zivuch, ÷éèهّ, kitur, each one is
seen as distinct and you’d bring a separate ÷ّلï. korban. Okay, by
other ٍلéّهْ, aveiros, there’s none of this. It’s all—it doesn’t matter if
you eat çىل chelev from this part of the animal or that
part of the animal, or if you chew it or you swallow
it, it’s all the same àéٌهّ, issur, so you’re only going to
bring one ÷ّلï. korban. Okay, but the âîّà Gemara here is initially
comparing different îىàëهْ melachos by ùلْ Shabbos to two totally separate ٍلéّهْ.
aveiros. Okay, so let’s take a look. àéىéîà مٍلéم ÷ِéّن هèçéًن مëههْéن
âلé ùàّ îِههْ مçىل همي, Ilima d’avid ktzira v’techina d’chvasay gabi shear
mitzvos d’chalav v’dam, and you were to compare, you know, grinding and
cutting something on ùلْ Shabbos to çىل chelev and مي, dam, two
real separate ٍلéّهْ. aveiros. نëà ّْْé îçééل هنëà ّْْé îçééل, Hacha tarti
mechayev v’hacha tarti mechayev, in both cases you would bring two ÷ّلًهْ.
korbanos. àىà âلé ùàّ îِههْ مàéًه çééل àىà àçْ نéëé مîé? Ela
gabi shear mitzvos d'eino chayav ela achas heichi dami? مàëى çىل هçىل.
D’achal chelev v’chelev.
Okay, so by ùلْ Shabbos you would have to say—so the case
that you only bring one ÷ّلï korban by other îىàëهْ melachos is
it’s îîù mamash the same ٍلéّن, aveira, çىل chelev and çىل. chelev.
So مëههْéن âلé ùلْ مٍلم ÷ِéّن ه÷ِéّن. D’chvasay gabi Shabbos d’avid ktzira
v’ktzira. So if you really want to make the analogy by ùلْ,
Shabbos, then you’re going to have to say that you did two
acts of the same îىàëن, melacha, ÷ِéّن ktzira and ÷ِéّن. ktzira. نëà
çمà îçééل هنëà çمà îçééل. Hacha chada mechayev v’hacha chada mechayev. So
in both cases it’s only one. هنééًه مàîّ ىéن ôه÷ ًْé ىلّà.
V’hainu d’amar lei puk tani livra. And that’s why he said go
teach it outside, meaning what? Meaning you can’t make an analogy
unless,
you know, they’re analogous. So if you’re talking about other ٍلéّهْ aveiros
that it’s çىل chelev and çىل, chelev, then the thing by ùلْ
Shabbos that’s the same is ÷ِéّن ktzira and ÷ِéّن. ktzira. Okay, you
can’t say oh by ùلْ Shabbos it’s two and here it’s one
if by ùلْ Shabbos you’re talking about ÷ِéّن ktzira and èçéًن techina
and here you’re talking about çىل chelev and çىل. chelev. You would
need something parallel that would be, you know, something distinct and yet
you’re only çééل chayav one. All right, so that’s why it says
this doesn’t make sense. Either we’re talking about ùلْ Shabbos it’s ÷ِéّن
ktzira and ÷ِéّن ktzira and here it’s çىل chelev and çىل chelev
and then in both cases it’s one, or it’s ÷ِéّن ktzira and
èçéًن techina and here it’s çىل chelev and مي dam and in
both cases it’s two. Okay, to say that there’s a really different
نىëن, halacha, you’d have to find me something like ùلْ Shabbos that
has sub-subcategories
and even with the subcategories and you do different ones, you’re only
çééل chayav. only one. Now of course that case could be ٍلهمن
وّن, Avodah Zarah but let’s take a look. Okay, so the âîّà
Gemara says هنà ÷ùéà, V’ha kashya, why is it different, a problem?
مéىîà ىٍهىي àéîà ىê مٍلم ÷ِéّن هèçéًن هîن ùàéï ëï لùàّ îِههْ
ëâهï ٍلهمْ ëهëلéي. Dilma l’olam eima lach d’avid ktzira v’techina u’ma she’ein
ken b’shear mitzvos k’gon avodas kochavim.
So it works perfectly. Okay, yes, by ùلْ Shabbos you do two
îىàëهْ, melachos, ÷ِéّن ktzira and èçéًن techina and you’re çééل chayav. two
çèàهْ, chataos, whereas other ٍلéّهْ, aveiros, there are two cases—there’s a case
of subcategories, so it is analogous, subcategories. They’re only going to be
çééل chayav. one. What is that going to be? ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah
Zarah ëمّلé àîé مàîّ ّلé àîé وéلç ه÷éèّ هًéٌê لنٍىي àçم àéًه
çééل àىà àçْ. K’deRabbi Ami d’amar Rabbi Ami ziveich v’kitar v’niseich b’he’elam
echad eino chayav ela achas.
Okay, now that seems very similar to what we said before, except
before we threw in نùْçهéن. hishtachavaya. Okay, but now we seem to
be considering the possibility of this. All right, so maybe, okay, maybe
with نùْçهéن, hishtachavaya, maybe نùْçهéن hishtachavaya is clearly distinct from وéلهç, zivuch,
÷éèهّ, kitur, and ًéٌهê. nisuch. Those are separate categories. But وéلهç, zivuch,
÷éèهّ, kitur, and ًéٌهê, nisuch, which are all learned from the one
ôٌه÷ pasuk of ىà ٍْلمي, lo sa’avdem, okay, maybe those are not
distinct from each other. Okay, so before we were saying نùْçهéن hishtachavaya
plus those things you bring multiple çèàهْ. chataos. But maybe if it’s
just—not نùْçهéن—just hishtachavaya the things that are in the category of ىà
ٍْلمي, lo sa’avdem, وéلهç, zivuch, ÷éèهّ, kitur, and ًéٌهê, nisuch, that’s where—now
ّلé àîé Rabbi Ami is saying that is only one category and
you only bring one. So that’s a case like ùلْ. Shabbos. Conceptually
they’re subcategories and separate acts, but nevertheless you only bring one, whereas
by ùلْ, Shabbos, subcategories and separate acts, àلهْ, avos, you are going
to bring multiple ones. Okay, àىà—so ela that would work very well.
Now so pause. So what’s important that we just said is this
sheds light on what we were saying before. It makes it sound
like before when the âîّà Gemara was so insistent that you would
bring multiple çèàهْ chataos by ٍلهمن وّن, Avodah Zarah that was probably
more about نùْçهéن hishtachavaya being separate from these three that are learned
out from ىà ٍْلمي. lo sa’avdem. But if you’re just doing the
ones that are in the ىà ٍْلمي lo sa’avdem category, maybe àéï
نëé ًîé, ein hachi nami, only one çèàْ. chatas. And maybe that’s
what’s going on in this لّééْà braisa that’s saying that it is
different from ùلْ. Shabbos. In that respect.
So the âîّà Gemara says no, ىà îéْه÷îà ىéن لٍلهمْ ëهëلéي. Lo
Mitukmei Lei be'Avodas Kochavim. No,
it's not going to work with ٍلهمن وّن. Avodah Zarah Why? م÷ًْé
ٌéôà, Dekatani Seifa, çهîّ. Chomer. çهîّ لùلْ îùàّ îِههْ, Chomer bi-Shabbos mi-sh'ar
mitzvos, because we have to make it work out at the end,
okay? ùلùàّ îِههْ, She-bi-sh'ar mitzvos, ùهââ لىà îْëههï çééل. shogeg be-lo miskaven
chayav.
So it says by you know by ùلْ Shabbos if you're îٌٍْ÷,
mis'asek, you're trying to do one thing you do another thing, you're
ôèهّ, patur you don't bring a ÷ّلï, korban, but other îِههْ mitzvos
if you're îٌٍْ÷, mis'asek, you're çééل. chayav Well, how is that going
to work by ٍلهمن وّن? Avodah Zarah Okay. ùهââ لىà îْëههï لٍلهمْ
ëهëلéي نéëé مîé? Shogeg be-lo miskaven be-Avodas Kochavim heichi dami? What's the
case? àé م÷ٌلّ لéْ نëًٌْ نهà هنùْçهن ىه, Iy de-kasavar Beis ha-Knesses
hu v'hishtachaveh lo, نّé لىله ىùîéي. harei belibo la-Shamayim. A classic case
of îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek actually by ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah. would be that
you're bowing down in front of an idol but you pray to
God and you think that this is whatever, it's a لéْ ٍلهمن
وّن Beis Avoda Zarah but you think it's a لéْ نëًٌْ. Beis
ha-Knesses. Okay, well guess what, you're totally ôèهّ patur in that case.
àىà مçوà àًمّْà هٌâéم ىن. Ela de-chaza andarta v'sagid lah. Okay, it's
a statue and you're bowing down to it. Again, àé ÷لىéن ٍىéن
لàىهن, iy kibleih aleih be-Eloha, îوéم meizid. نهà, hu. if you accepted
it as a god you're îوéم. meizid. ىà ÷لىéن ٍىéن Lo kibleih
aleih and if you're just doing it as an act of respect
so ىà ëىهي نهà, lo klumu, it's nothing. So you can't say
that it would work out quite nicely to say by ùلْ Shabbos
there's an idea of çéىه÷ îىàëهْ chiluk melachos and multiple ÷ّلًهْ, korbanos,
by ٍلهمن وّن Avodah Zarah at least if you're stick with in
the category of ىà ٍْلمي, lo sa'avdeim, وéلهç ÷éèهّ هًéٌهê zivuch kitor
v'nisuch even though those are different acts it's really not çéىه÷ chiluk
and it's all just one ÷ّلï. korban. That contrast would be very
nice. But to say a reverse distinction by îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek that îٌٍْ÷
mis'asek you're ôèهّ patur by ùلْ Shabbos and çééل chayav by ٍلهمن
وّن, that's not true, there's no case of îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek that you're
çééل chayav by ٍلهمن وّن. So àىà ela so the âîّà Gemara
says îàنلن هîééّàن. me-ahava me-yirah. Maybe the case is àنلن ééّàن ahava
yirah now that's not exactly clear to me why that's considered îٌٍْ÷
mis'asek but okay. Maybe here's the case by ٍلهمن وّن that you're
ôèهّ patur on. Okay if you went ahead by ùلْ Shabbos and
you thought that it was you know îهّْ mutar to do something
îàنلن هîééّàن me-ahava me-yirah you'd still okay the problem is that there
you'd also be çééل. chayav But okay. نًéçà ىàلéé مàîّ çééل àىà
ىّلà مàîّ ôèهّ îàé àéëà ىîéîّ? Ha nicha l'Abaye d'amar chayav ela
l'Rava d'amar patur mai ika le-meimar?
àىà لàهîّ îهّْ. Ela be-omer mutar. Okay. So fine. So we went
through the same thing. By àلéé you could be making a mistake
that you could be saying you know you could think that àنلن
هééّàن ahava ve-yirah is îهّْ mutar and it's really àٌهّ. assur. But
for ّلà that's not it is really not îهّْ mutar but anyway
it's really not çééل. chayav Fine àهîّ îهّْ. omer mutar. That's the
case. So we're back we keep on going back that what is
the mistake that you can make by ٍلهمن وّن when it's not
about the particular acts, it's that you think everything is totally permissible.
Okay but then you know you're in that case by ùلْ Shabbos
you're also çééل. chayav So it's not that you're ôèهّ patur by
other things and çééل chayav by ùلْ Shabbos and excuse me çééل
chayav a ÷ّلï korban by other things and ôèهّ patur by ùلْ.
Shabbos. So the âîّà says àىà لàهîّ îهّْ. ela be-omer mutar. So
where are we? îن ùëï لùلْ مôèهّ ىâîّé. mah she-ken bi-Shabbos de-patur
legamre. Wait a minute, but if that's true if it's îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek
you could say there are certain things that you're çééل chayav by
îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek by other ٍلéّهْ averos not ٍلهمن وّن but you're ôèهّ
îٌٍْ÷ patur mis'asek by ùلْ. Shabbos. But by ٍلهمن وّن there's no
îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek that you're çééل chayav on. So if you want to
say you're çééل chayav a ÷ّلï korban by other things by ٍلهمن
وّن you're going to say àهîّ îهّْ. omer mutar. Okay but you're
also çééل chayav on ùلْ Shabbos in that case. ٍم ëàï ىà
لٍé îéًéن ّل îّل ًçîï نٍىي ون هون àé ىôé çم àé
ىôé ّْْé. Ad kan lo ba'ei minei Rav mi-Rav Nachman he'elem zeh
v'zeh ileifi l'had ileifi l'tartei. But until now when we're saying you
know if you forget both of them you know both that it's
ùلْ Shabbos and the particular îىàëهْ melachos the question is do you
bring multiple ÷ّلًهْ korbanos or just one
÷ّلï. korban. ôèهّ ىâîّé ىéëà ىîàï مàîّ. Patur legamre leika le-man de-amar.
So but nobody says that you'd totally be exempt. Okay so therefore
you could not have a case where we say that àهîّ îهّْ
omer mutar is çééل chayav by ٍلهمن وّن çééل a ÷ّلï korban
and ôèهّ by ùلْ. Shabbos. Obviously àهîّ îهّْ omer mutar is also
going to be çééل by ùلْ. Shabbos. So what have we said?
We've said now first of all we made it clear it seems
that it could be that if you do وéلهç ÷éèهّ هًéٌهê zivuch
kitor v'nisuch because that's all based on ىà ٍْلمي lo sa'avdeim you
really only do bring one ÷ّلï. korban. So the beginning part of
the لّééْà braisa that says multiple îىàëهْ melachos by ùلْ Shabbos is
multiple ÷ّلًهْ korbanos but by something else is only one, that could
work very nicely by ٍلهمن وّن because ٍلهمن وّن you do have
sub-categories وéلهç ÷éèهّ هًéٌهê zivuch kitor v'nisuch and it could be you
are çééل only one they're all in the category of ىà ٍْلمي.
lo sa'avdeim. But it doesn't work with the end of the لّééْà
braisa because the end of the لّééْà braisa. says îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek is
ôèهّ by ùلْ Shabbos and çééل by other things and you really
don't have a case of îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek that's çééل by ٍلهمن وّن
if it's îٌٍْ÷ mis'asek it's not ٍلهمن وّن. The only case by
ٍلهمن وّن that would seem somewhat analogous is àهîّ îهّْ omer mutar
but of course that case you would be çééل a ÷ّلï korban
by ùلْ Shabbos as well. So we'll pick up here tomorrow to
see what would be the way that you might be able to
read the end of that لّééْà.