Boker tov
בוקר טוב, Boker tov, good morning. We are, today's daf דף daf
is Samech Hei ס"ה, Samech Hei, 65. We are on Samech Dalet
amud bet ס"ד עמוד ב', Samech Dalet amud bet,
the first wide line, Rabbi Yossi bar Abin Chanina רבי יוסי בר
אבין חנינא, Rabbi Yossi bar Abin Chanina, let's get to it.
Again, I'm going to need your help here a little bit because
I did not prepare this part. Okay. Amar Rabbi Yossi bar Abin
Chanina אמר רבי יוסי בר אבין חנינא: Amar Rabbi Yossi bar Abin
Chanina: Shalosh kritot b'avodah zarah שלש כריתות בעבודה זרה. Shalosh kritot b'avodah
zarah. Lama
למה? Lama? Why are there three different kritot כריתות, kritot, I guess
stated in the Torah?
Why are there three different kritot כריתות kritot stated in the Torah
by
avodah zarah עבודה זרה? avodah zarah?
Achat
k'darkah ve-achat she-lo k'darkah אחת כדרכה ואחת
שלא כדרכה. Achat k'darkah ve-achat she-lo k'darkah. So one is to teach
if you worship avodah zarah עבודה זרה avodah zarah the way that
it's supposed to be worshipped, like throwing stones at Markolis מרקוליס. Markolis.
Ve-achat she-lo k'darkah ואחת שלא כדרכה, Ve-achat she-lo k'darkah, if you worship
it not in a way that it's supposed to be worshipped. Ve-achat
le-molech ואחת למולך, Ve-achat le-molech, I guess meaning sending your kid to
die for the sake of Molech מולך, Molech, which means sacrificing your
kid. Two of those three are actually about Molech מולך Molech specifically.
Lo k'darkah שלא כדרכה? Lo k'darkah? Interesting, okay. Kareit כרת, Kareit, kareit
כרת. kareit. No,
the two of those three verses it refers to are about Molech
מולך. Molech. Okay, but we learned a general rule
from one of them we learned a general rule about lo k'darkah
שלא כדרכה lo k'darkah and one of them we learned about Molech
מולך. Molech. Ve-le-man d'amar Molech
avodah
zarah hi ולמאן דאמר מולך עבודה זרה היא, Ve-le-man d'amar Molech avodah
zarah hi, what about the person who says sending your kid to
Molech מולך Molech is just another category of avodah zarah
עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Kareit b'Molech lama li כרת במולך למה לי,
Kareit b'Molech lama li, so what is that extra kareit כרת kareit
doing there? Le-ma'avir beno she-lo k'darkah למעביר בנו שלא כדרכה. Le-ma'avir beno
she-lo k'darkah. So sending your kid to avodah zarah עבודה זרה avodah
zarah she-lo k'darkah שלא כדרכה she-lo k'darkah meaning what,
meaning meaning you did it to Molech מולך Molech but you didn't
do it the proper
way they usually do it. Like you know, instead of passing through
the fire you whatever it is, did it backwards or something, you
know, right? O b'sha'ar avodah zarah she-ein darko be-kach she-lo matzinu ela
zivuach ve-kitor ve-nizuch ve-hishtachavaya או בשאר עבודה זרה שאין דרכו בכך שלא
מצינו אלא זבוח וקיטור וניסוך והשתחויה. O b'sha'ar avodah zarah she-ein darko
be-kach she-lo matzinu ela zivuach ve-kitor ve-nizuch ve-hishtachavaya. Or possibly sacrificing your
kid to a different avodah zarah עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
That's what it sounds like from Rashi רש"י. Rashi. Right, could be
taken that way also. Is that what the footnote says?
Passing his son through the fire for an idol when it's not
the usual
manner. Right, sacrificing, so there it is. So for someone who says
Molech מולך Molech is just another form of avodah zarah עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, what that kareit כרת kareit chayav kareit חייב כרת chayav
kareit teaches you is he-avir beno
le-Markolis העביר בנו למרקוליס. He-avir beno le-Markolis. Exactly, exactly. That's a lo
k'darkah שלא כדרכה lo k'darkah and it's a separate, but for some
reason it's a separate chiyuv חיוב. chiyuv. Right, but our mishna משנה
mishna isn't reflecting that because you know it just says zivuach kitor
ve-hishtachavaya זבוח קיטור והשתחויה, zivuach kitor ve-hishtachavaya, right? Nizuch ניסוך, nizuch, but
it didn't say you know he-avir beno העביר בנו. he-avir beno. Because
you're not chayav skila חייב סקילה chayav skila for that, you're just
chayav kareit חייב כרת. chayav kareit.
We mentioned yesterday by the way it might not actually burn the
child, it might be some ritual where he goes between tests through
fire or over fire and survives. Interesting. The problem with that is
there's actually a lot of documentation of child sacrifice in... But it
isn't sacrifice, meaning like the pshat פשט pshat is that you actually
don't die. If you think about what the brit ברית brit was,
you know like the brit bein ha-betarim ברית בין הבתרים, brit bein
ha-betarim, you pass through it, right? That's what a brit ברית brit
was. In other words you were abrogating your brit ברית brit with
God and instead you're forming it into a covenant with avodah zarah
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. That's exactly the pattern of what... you pass
through the fire... but there is a lot of stopping of but
at least not specifically. Anyway.
Okay, anyway. Although pshat פשט pshat for being ma'avir מעביר ma'avir something
through esh אש esh might not be passing through like that because
you pass kelim כלים kelim through fire right by the
kelim כלים kelim that they conquered you pass through esh אש esh
that's probably unless it is the same some sort of ritual but
that would be a little peculiar. Okay. U-le-man d'amar megadef avodah zarah
hi ולמאן דאמר מגדף עבודה זרה היא, U-le-man d'amar megadef avodah zarah
hi, what about the person who says that megadef מגדף megadef is
just another form of avodah zarah עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, kareit b'megadef
lama li כרת במגדף למה לי? Kareit b'megadef lama li? Why do
we have the chiyuv חיוב chiyuv of kareit כרת kareit by megadef
מגדף? megadef? Like detanya דתניא detanya as we learn in the following
braita ברייתא, braita, Hikaret tikaret הכרת תכרת, Hikaret tikaret, hikaret ba-olam ha-zeh
הכרת בעולם הזה, Hikaret ba-olam ha-zeh, tikaret la-olam ha-ba תכרת לעולם הבא.
Tikaret la-olam ha-ba. So you have two kareits כרת, kareits, you have
two kritot כריתות, kritot, one ba-olam ha-zeh בעולם הזה ba-olam ha-zeh and
one la-olam ha-ba לעולם הבא. la-olam ha-ba. There's another point which is
פשט Pshat and this is interpreted this way in מסכת כריתות Masechet
Kritot of the third verse, the one from במדבר, Bamidbar, it specifically
talks about blasphemy, not עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. Anyway, במדבר
ט״ו? Bamidbar 15? Yeah. מגדף, Megadef, etc., etc.
But what they're saying is that blasphemy is subsumed under the category
of עבודה זרה Avoda Zara according to this opinion. So this is
saying, well so this is saying that when you do מגדף Megadef
or when you do עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, I guess when you
do עבודה זרה Avoda Zara in general, הכרת תכרת Hakaret Tikaret means
you get you get two כריתות, Kritot, one בעולם הזה Baolam Hazeh
and one בעולם הבא. Baolam Haba. It sounds like there was a
previous מחלוקת Makhloket about whether מגדף Megadef is or is not עבודה
זרה Avoda Zara and they're saying for the one who says it
is עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, exactly. We can't say what we said
originally why there were three so we have to have a new
reason why there were three because מגדף Megadef is a form of
עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. Therefore it's עולם הזה ובעולם הבא. Olam Hazeh
ve-Baolam Haba. Okay. דרבי עקיבא, De-Rabbi Akiva, that's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
אמר לו רבי ישמאל והלא כבר נאמר ונכרתה וכי שלושה עולמים יש?
Amar lo Rabbi Yishmael ve-halo kvar ne-emar ve-nikhrata ve-khi shelosha olamim yesh?
So we already learned somewhere else, ונכרתה הנפש ההיא, Ve-nikhrata hanefesh ha-hi,
right, we already learned somewhere else that someone who does עבודה זרה
Avoda Zara gets כרת. Karet.
So we already know בעולם הזה ובעולם הבא Baolam Hazeh u-Baolam Haba
and what are there three worlds? עולם הזה, עולם הבא, ועולם הבא
אחרינא? Olam Hazeh, Olam Haba, ve-Olam Haba acharina? No. אלא ונכרתה בעולם
הזה הכרת לעולם הבא תכרת דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. Ella ve-nikhrata
ba-olam hazeh hicharet le-olam haba tikaret dibra torah kile-shon bnei adam. So
it's just a case of the repetition is just a case of
דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, Dibra Torah kile-shon bnei adam, that it's
extra emphasis on this on this כרת. Karet. Okay. Step. Great. Top
of ס״ה עמוד א׳, Samech Hey Amud Alef, we start a new
משנה, Mishnah, more people who are חייב סקילה. Chayav Skila. בעל
אוב, Baal-ov, sorry, we're going to define to explain the previous משנה,
Mishnah, בעל אוב, Baal-ov, אינו חייב עד שימלל... Eino chayav ad she-yimallel...
no.
Okay,
so two more people who are חייב סקילה: Chayav Skila: בעל אוב
Baal-ov and then it defines, then we're going to define what a
בעל אוב Baal-ov is. זה פיתום המדבר משחיו. Zeh Pitom ha-medaber mi-shichyo.
This is a פיתום Pitom
which is just like the name of the type of witchcraft that
this is, who speaks from his armpit.
וידוני, Ve-yidoni, and someone who is a וידוני Yidoni which is זה
המדבר בפיו, Zeh ha-medaber be-piv, someone who speaks from his mouth. And
we're going to, the גמרא's Gemara going to talk about what exactly
that means, we might not get to it today. הרי אלו בסקילה.
Harei elu bi-skila. These two are death by סקילה Skila והנשאל בהם
באזהרה. ve-hanish'al ba-hem be-azharah. And someone who seeks out one of these
two people in order to ask them about the future or in
order to ask them to necromance for them, they have an אזהרה
Azharah which is possibly you have to bring a קרבן. Korban. What
about like just going to a fortune teller? Is that a problem?
Going to any of this?
Like a modern day fortune teller? Like a tarot card? אריה, Arieh,
a tarot? The problem with that is, I mean I guess not
specifically, presumably there is a problem with it. Isn't it about maybe
want to know the future? Doesn't the תורה Torah say in תמים
Tamim shouldn't want to know the future? I'm not sure.
I guess if you don't really believe in it or is it
just curiosity, entertainment, whatever? Right. I would I would guess that that
would be included in והנשאל בהם ve-hanish'al ba-hem even if it's not
the same level of maybe it's a דרבנן De-rabbanan version of it
or something but that's what I would guess. I would not recommend
going to fortune tellers
for two reasons: one it's probably אסור Assur and two it's a
waste of money.
So. And it's אסור Assur to waste money. Right and it's אסור
Assur to waste money, exactly. So two two איסורים Issurim there. עושר
בלעבירה Osher bi-levirah or something? Right, that's what some people
say.
Some people say it is אסור Assur but that's for like different
that's for different reasons. Okay.
Okay so we're going to prepare this, we're going to compare this
משנה Mishnah to a משנה Mishnah in כריתות. Kritot. מאי שנא הכא
דתני בעל אוב וידוני ומאי שנא גבי כריתות דתני בעל אוב ושביק
לידוני? Mai shna hakha de-tanei Baal-ov ve-yidoni u-mai shna gabei Kritot de-tanei
Baal-ov ve-shavik li-yidoni?
So the משנה Mishnah in כריתות Kritot says,
if you look in רש״י, Rashi, בכריתות כקשי לכל כריתות שבתורה שחייבין
עליהם על שגגetan חטאת ותנן בעל אוב ולא תני ידוני. be-Kritot ke-kashi
le-khol Kritot she-ba-Torah she-chayavin aleihem al shgigatan chatat ve-tanan Baal-ov ve-lo tanei
yidoni.
So over there when it
does it have information, does it say it talk about modern... No,
it's just you know because המלך שאול Ha-Melech Shaul went to find
out information about the future. Right. That's right. I think that's right,
maybe that's why they didn't... He conjured up the ghost of שמואל
הנביא. Shmuel Ha-Navi. Well, she did. She did, he sought it out
though, that's the problem. Sought it out? Sought it out, thank you.
So you mean... Right.
Okay, so מאי שנא הכא דקתני בעל אוב וידעוני, Mai shna hacha
dekatani baal ov v'yidoni, why do we see here that someone who
does בעל אוב baal ov or the ידעוני yidoni thing is חייב
סקילה? chayav skila? And מאי שנא גבי כריתות דקתני בעל אוב ושייר
לידעוני? mai shna gabei kreetot dekatani baal ov v'shayar l'yidoni? How come
אוב ov and ידעוני yidoni are not taught by כריתות kreetot
that if you do it by accident you're חייב חטאת chayav chatas
and if you do it on purpose you're
חייב כרת? chayav kares? Meaning it's sort of the same thing. Who
cares if it's speech or offput from the mouth, right? What's the
difference? Stop. Okay, so that's one answer. רבי יוחנן אמר הואיל ושניהם
בלאו אחד נאמרו. Rabbi Yochanan amar ho'il u'shneihem b'lav echad neemru. Rabbi
Yochanan says
oh, it means both of them in כריתות, kreetot, it only teaches
one because they're taught together. So sort of the same thing. What's
the difference for רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? ריש לקיש אמר ידעוני לפי
שאין בו
מעשה. Reish Lakish amar yidoni lefi she'ein bo maaseh. So ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish comes along and says no, it's because ידעוני yidoni is
left out because there is no מעשה maaseh involved, and the גמרא
Gemara will talk about what exactly מעשה maaseh is. לרבי יוחנן מאי
שנא בעל אוב דנקט, L'Rabbi Yochanan mai shna baal ov d'nakat, how
come according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan if both ידעוני yidoni and
בעל אוב baal ov are included in the משנה Mishna in כריתות
kreetot even though it doesn't say both, how come it says בעל
אוב baal ov and it doesn't say ידעוני? yidoni? משום דפתח ביה
קרא mishum d'patach bei kra because when the תורה Torah talks about
them it talks about בעל אוב baal ov first, it always says
בעל אוב או ידעוני, baal ov o yidoni, בעל אוב וידעוני, baal
ov v'yidoni, so it just uses the first one. Okay, now we're
going to talk about, we're going to ask the question how come
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish does not agree with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and then we're going to do the other way around. ריש לקיש
מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבי יוחנן, Reish Lakish mai taama lo amar
k'Rabbi Yochanan, how come ריש לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't agree with רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that both אוב ov and ידעוני yidoni are technically
included in the משנה Mishna in כריתות? kreetot? אמר רב פפא חלוקין
הן במיתה Amar Rav Pappa chalukin hen b'meetah because they are separated
in the verse about חייב chayav when you're חייב מיתה chayav meetah
for them, they're separated in the פסוק pasuk therefore they can't be
considered as רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, they can't be considered to
have been שניהם בלאו אחד נאמרו. shneihem b'lav echad neemru.
If you look in רש"י, Rashi, first wide line, first real wide
line, first of the really wide lines, thank you. אוב כתיב חלוקין
הן במיתה כשפירש סקילה ov ktiv chalukin hen b'meetah keshepirash skila and
when the תורה Torah talks about being חייב סקילה chayav skila for
them הכי תנא קרא hachi tana kra
the פסוק pasuk separates them כי יהיה בהם אוב או ידעוני. ki
yihyeh bahem ov o yidoni. So the או o separates them, therefore
if you just teach one of them you can't assume that the
other one is included according to ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. מאי טעמא
דאמר רב פפא חלוקין הן במיתה. Mai taama d'amar Rav Pappa chalukin
hen b'meetah.
So how come רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't agree with ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish that they are separated in the פסוק? pasuk? No, but
didn't ריש לקיש Reish Lakish say לפי שאין בו מעשה? lefi she'ein
bo maaseh? Right, so this is the question is how come ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish doesn't agree with רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that they're
both included in one sentence because, right, you could say oh because
of the אין בו מעשה, ein bo maaseh, right? Like that could
be the answer that the גמרא Gemara could give, but it doesn't.
It says because they're חלוקין chalukin in the פסוק. pasuk. But how
come רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ignores this חילוק chiluk in the פסוק?
pasuk? Because חלוקה דלאו שמה חלוקה, chaluka d'lav sh'mah chaluka, you can
consider when the תורה Torah gives a לאו, lav, a מצות לא
תעשה mitzvot lo taaseh it's called a חלוקה chaluka and then if
you look in the הגהות הב"ח Hagahot HaBach he has another חלוקה,
chaluka, he has another חלוקה chaluka here, so it's דלאו שמה חלוקה
חלוקה דמיתה לא שמה חלוקה. d'lav sh'mah chaluka, chaluka d'meetah lo sh'mah
chaluka. So when the גמרא Gemara when the תורה Torah talks about
a חייב chayav when you're חייב מיתה chayav meetah it's not called
a חלוקה. chaluka. So the word או o in a פסוק pasuk
about a regular לא תעשה lo taaseh is called a חלוקה chaluka
according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but if it's talking about being
put to death then it's not called a חלוקה. chaluka.
Okay, now we're going to do the other way around. רבי יוחנן
מאי טעמא לא אמר כריש לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan mai taama lo amar
k'Reish Lakish, how come רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't agree with ריש
לקיש? Reish Lakish? Right, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says that
when the משנה Mishna in כריתות kreetot talks about בעל אוב baal
ov it's only talking about בעל אוב baal ov and not talking
about a ידעוני. yidoni. I'm sorry, so he thinks that you don't
get כרת kares for being a ידעוני? yidoni? Exactly. So according to
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you don't get כרת kares for ידעוני yidoni
because there's no מעשה maaseh and in order to get כרת kares
you have there has to be a מעשה. maaseh. So what do
you get?
A regular
לא תעשה. lo taaseh. If you do it במזיד b'mayzid and התראה
hatra'ah you get סקילה, skila, but if you just do it without
that, I think it comes with, I think, I think generally above
it seems like בעל אוב baal ov I'm not sure
because it seems like there's death, there's כרת kares and
there's מיתת בית דין meetat beit din here. So I'm not sure
how those two go together. I think maybe you get it's possible
you get both,
but meaning you don't get מיתת בית דין meetat beit din if
you potentially then got כרת. kares. I guess it's oh here's what
it is: it's מיתת בית דין Beis Din *mitat beit din* with
התראה *hatra'ah* and במזיד *b'meizid*. במזיד *b'meizid* and התראה *hatra'ah* you get
מיתת בית דין *mitat beit din*, במזיד *b'meizid* without התראה *hatra'ah* and
עדים *edim* you get כרת Karet, *kareit*, בשוגג *b'shogeg* you have to
bring a קרבן *korban*. Right. So what happens if you don't even
then? So if you get if it's we've seen other משניות *mishnayos*
would say that for both one you get סקילה skila *skila*. But
so the חילוק *chiluk* would be that what? You get כרת kares
*kareit* if you're the אוב *ov* with the you know if you
don't technically have the requirements fulfilled by the עדים *edim* התראה *hatra'ah*
something's wrong with התראה *hatra'ah* or whatever.
So they so the thinking is that you get כרת kares. *kareit*
for being a בעל אוב Baal Ov, *ba'al ov* but you just
be עובר *over* a לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*. You'd be עובר *over*
the לא תעשה *lo ta'aseh*. I think if you do it במזיד
*b'meizid* you still get כרת kares. *kareit*, but if you do it
בשוגג *b'shogeg* then you don't then there's no שוגג בלי מעשה Maaseh,
*shogeg beli ma'aseh* there's no
there's no חובה *chovah* of קרבן *korban* of a קרבן חטאת *korban
chatas*. But
I thought the whole point is it's not in the משנה Mishna
*mishna* of כריתות Kritot *kereisos* which means they wouldn't get כרת kares,
*kareit*, right? Is that the point? Oh, maybe you're right. Hold on,
I think רש"י Rashi *Rashi* explains it.
Sorry, I'm just trying to understand what happens. It's not mentioned because
oh I think it's first of all one commandment, it's included in
the other one. That's according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*,
but according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish, *Reish Lakish* it's not included
because there's no מעשה Maaseh, *ma'aseh*. So therefore right there's I guess
there's no כרת kares *kareit* by a yeah there's no כרת kares
*kareit* by a it's weird like meaning like it's just two extremes.
You think that like alright because of a technicality he'll at least
get כרת kares *kareit*, you know what I'm saying? Like it just
seems a lot... right it's weird that there's no... there's סקילה *skila*
you know what I mean? Like it just seems so... yep. Just
you know it's like totally opposite ends of the spectrum. But that's
the way he reads this משנה *mishna* and the system
because there's no מעשה Maaseh. *ma'aseh*. But we'll talk about what that
means. Okay.
Okay, so that's why ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish* we just
said why ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish Lakish* doesn't agree with רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*. Now we're going to do the other
way around. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* מאי טעמא לא אמר
כריש לקיש *mai ta'ama lo amar k'Reish Lakish*? How come רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* doesn't agree with ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish
Lakish* that because there's no מעשה Maaseh, *ma'aseh* in in ידעוני Yidoni,
*yidoni* there shouldn't be כרת kares? *kareit*? אמר לך *amar lach* מתניתין
דכריתות *matnisin de'kereisos* רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva היא *Rabbi Akiva hi*. That
משנה *mishna* is taught according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*
דאמר *d'amar* לא בעינן מעשה Maaseh. *lo ba'inan ma'aseh* that according to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* there's no מעשה Maaseh *ma'aseh* required
in order to get כרת kares. *kareit*. ריש לקיש Resh Lakish *Reish
Lakish* נהי דלא בעי רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva מעשה Maaseh. רבה *nehi
d'lo ba'i Rabbi Akiva ma'aseh rabbah* מעשה Maaseh, זוטא בעי
*ma'aseh zuta ba'i*. So and even according to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
*Reish Lakish* if that משנה *mishna* is taught according to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* requires
no sorry and according to the reason ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish
Lakish* doesn't say that משנה *mishna* is according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva* is because even according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
oh now I'm confused.
He says even without action you need to bring a חטאת *chatas*.
Right, even without even according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* who says...
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to talk about what that means
because obviously there's some action being done here when you're doing
ידעוני Yidoni *yidoni* and אוב *ov*, right? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going
to talk about what exactly it means. This most of this סוגיא
Sugya *sugya* going forward is going to be about what a מעשה
Maaseh *ma'aseh* is, like what's a מעשה עבירה ma'aseh aveirah *ma'aseh aveirah*.
מגדף Megadef, מאי מעשה איכא Mai Maaseh Ika? *megadef mai ma'aseh ika*?
כי אמר ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *ki amar
Reish Lakish* okay yeah
so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says this משנה *mishna* is
taught according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
doesn't require a מעשה Maaseh. *ma'aseh* therefore he leaves out ידעוני Yidoni
*yidoni*.
But according to ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*, even though רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says לא בעינן מעשה Maaseh, *lo ba'inan ma'aseh* even
though רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says לא בעינן מעשה Maaseh? *lo ba'inan
ma'aseh*, according to ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* מעשה Maaseh, רבה *ma'aseh rabbah*
דלא בעי רבי עקיבא מעשה Maaseh רבה *d'lo ba'i Rabbi Akiva ma'aseh
rabbah*, he doesn't require a big מעשה Maaseh. *ma'aseh*, מעשה Maaseh זוטא
בעי *ma'aseh zuta ba'i*. He requires a little a little מעשה Maaseh
*ma'aseh* which a ידעוני Yidoni *yidoni* is not doing. Okay? מגדף Megadef?
מאי מעשה איכא Mai Maaseh Ika? *megadef mai ma'aseh ika*? But what
about a מגדף Megadef *megadef*? What מעשה Maaseh. *ma'aseh* is involved in
a
מגדף megadef *megadef*
which we know from the תורה Torah *Torah* that it's punished by
כרת karet? *kareit*? So yeah we just saw that. Right, exactly. So
how come a מגדף megadef *megadef* is punished by כרת *kareit* if
there's no מעשה Maaseh, *ma'aseh* what's the מעשה Maaseh, *ma'aseh* in a
מגדף megadef *megadef*? מאי מעשה Maaseh איכא *mai ma'aseh ika*? According to
the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* who require
right רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* require a
מעשה Maaseh *ma'aseh*.
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* requires a מעשה Maaseh *ma'aseh*...
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* doesn't require a מעשה Maaseh *ma'aseh* meaning now
I confused myself, sorry.
The רבנן Rabbanan require a big מעשה, Maaseh? the רבי עקיבא requires
a little מעשה, Maaseh and by בעל אוב, Baal Ov by ידעוני,
there’s no big מעשה. Maaseh, Okay, so that’s why רבי עקיבא leaves
it out of that משנה of... okay.
So, מגדף, megaddef מאי מעשה Maaseh. איכא? What about a מגדף? מאי
מעשה איכא? עקימת שפתיו הוי מעשה. Mai Maaseh Ika? Akimat Sefatav Havei
Maaseh. So bending of the lips is a מעשה, ma'aseh. which
is basically means it’s a מחלוקת Machloket about is talking a מעשה.
ma'aseh This comes up, I heard someone quote this גמרא Gemara, about
the question of, like, electronics on שבת, Shabbat,
like Alexa with Amazon or, like, Hey Google or Siri, right? Is
talking to your device, does that count as a מעשה ma'aseh. on
שבת? Shabbat? And so this סוגיא can apply there. So I still
don’t understand the thing then with the מגדף and the ידעוני in
terms of... so the גמרא’s Gemara going to have a problem with
that. Okay, I believe. Again, this is a difficult גמרא, Gemara I
didn’t have as much time as I would’ve liked to prepare it.
מאי מעשה ma'aseh איכא? עקימת שפתיו הוי מעשה. Akimat Sefatav Havei Maaseh.
So bending of the lips is a מעשה. ma'aseh It’s interesting also
that it’s talking about the movement of the lips and not the
sounding of a voice, because it’s the bone speaks, not...
exactly. Exactly. But you move your lips, but the bone speaks. בעל
אוב, מאי מעשה איכא? Baal Ov, Mai Maaseh Ika? What about a
בעל אוב Baal Ov who we said
is someone who speaks from his armpits? הכשת זרועותיו
הוי מעשה, Hakashat Zeroatav Havei Maaseh, moving the arms is a מעשה,
ma'aseh.
which so it seems like the הוה אמינא Hava Amina of the
גמרא is that a מעשה maaseh. is something that has, like, an
effect on the physical environment around you, but what it’s coming to
say is no, even movement of your body counts as a מעשה.
maaseh. Which nowadays we would say obviously that’s a מעשה, maaseh but
somehow the גמרא has a different conception of what exactly doing something
is.
דאפילו רבנן, D’afilo Rabbanan, and is it the case that even according
to the רבנן Rabbanan the waving of the arms is a מעשה?
maaseh? Again, the רבנן Rabbanan require a מעשה, maaseh. רבי עקיבא requires
a small מעשה maaseh and not a big מעשה. maaseh. The רבנן
Rabbanan require a big מעשה maaseh. according to ריש לקיש,
and this is a... there’s a ברייתא Braita over in כריתות Kritot,
that says basically the רבנן Rabbanan do not disagree.
רבנן Rabbanan agree
that
a בעל אוב Ba'al Ov is חייב Chayav in כריתות, Kritos in
כרת, which would imply that the רבנן Rabbanan agree that waving of
the arms is a מעשה maaseh. because רבנן Rabbanan, require a
מעשה. maaseh. והתניא אינו חייב אלא על דבר שיש בו מעשה כגון
זביחה קטור וניסוך והשתחוואה. Vehatanya eino chayav ela al davar sheyesh bo
maaseh kegon zevicha kittur venisuch vehashtachavah. But we learned in a ברייתא:
Braita: he’s only חייב Chayav for something that
has a
מעשה, maaseh. like slaughtering, burning incense, pouring a libation, and bowing. ואמר
ריש לקיש, Ve'amar Resh Lakish, מן תנא השתחוואה רבי עקיבא היא דאמר
לא בעינן מעשה. Man Tanna Hashtachavah Rabbi Akiva Hi D’amar Lo Bayinan
Maaseh. So this ברייתא Braita is according to... this ברייתא Braita has
to be according to רבי עקיבא because it talks about השתחוואה Hashtachavah
as a מעשה, maaseh. and רבי עקיבא is the one who doesn’t
require a מעשה maaseh.
to be חייב כרת, Chayav Karet, meaning that
according to ריש לקיש the רבנן Rabbanan would not consider השתחוואה Hashtachavah
a big enough מעשה maaseh. in order to be חייב כרת, Chayav
Karet, but רבי עקיבא does.
רבי יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא רבנן כפיפת קומתו לרבנן הוי מעשה. Rabbi
Yochanan amar afilu teima Rabbanan, kefifat komato l’Rabbanan havei maaseh. And רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says according to the רבנן Rabbanan bowing is a
big enough מעשה ma'aseh in order to be חייב כרת. Chayav Karet.
השתא לריש לקיש כפיפת קומתו לרבנן לא הוי מעשה. Hashta l’Resh Lakish
kefifat komato l’Rabbanan lo havei maaseh. Now, according to ריש לקיש who
just said that bowing is not considered a מעשה according to the
רבנן, Rabbanan הכשת זרועותיו דבעל אוב הוי מעשה? Hakashat zeroatav d’Baal Ov
havei maaseh? Can waving of the arms
according to ריש לקיש according to the רבנן Rabbanan really be considered
a מעשה?
Apparently bowing is more of a מעשה than waving of the arms,
and since ריש לקיש says that the רבנן Rabbanan do not consider
bowing a מעשה, waving of the arms can also not be a
מעשה. כי קאמר ריש לקיש נמי לרבי עקיבא. Ki ka’amar Resh Lakish
nami l’Rabbi Akiva. No, when we... we were mistaken and we said
that ריש לקיש also according to רבי עקיבא. No, we were mistaken
and we said that ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* was actually talking about
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. Agrees that that ברייתא baraita *baraita* is according
to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, meaning that both... Wait, one second, or
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. No, because we said רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
he... רבי עקיבא נמי לרבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva nami lerabbi akiva*... This
is where I really got lost in trying to prepare and maybe
so maybe you can help me. What is... I can just I
can read to you the... Yeah,
I read the ArtScroll still didn't quite get it. Can anyone help
me out here? Wait what what's... just according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* but not according to the...
You're asking who is this most recent ברייתא baraita. *baraita*? Right, but
the problem is ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* said that it's according to
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. So I think what I think what it's
saying is that the משנה *Mishnah* in כריתות *Keritot*
is also according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, according to ריש לקיש
*Reish Lakish*. And even... yes, that's the פשט *pshat*. The משנה *Mishnah*
in כריתות *Keritot* is also ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* is saying the
משנה *Mishnah* in כריתות *Keritot* is also according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva*. Therefore
we don't have to worry about the waving of the arms. What
okay so what was the problem? The problem was we have השתחוואה
*hishtachavah*... Right, because the
ברייתא baraita *baraita*, the משנה *Mishnah*... it's listed as a מעשה *ma'aseh*.
Right, the משנה *Mishnah* in כריתות *Keritot* said that בעל אוב Ba'al
Ov *ba'al ov* is חייב כרת chayav kares. *chayav karet* and a
פיטום המדבר משיחיו *pitom hamidaber mishichyo*
or משיח... yeah, משיחיו *mishichyo* is not חייב כרת chayav kares *chayav
karet*. ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* said
that it's not included because it doesn't have a מעשה *ma'aseh*,
but the problem is that according to the רבנן Rabbanan. *Rabbanan*,
ידעוני *yidooni* would have a מעשה *ma'aseh*
because it has the bending of the lips.
So then we're going to say no, according to even according to
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*, the משנה *Mishnah* in כריתות *Keritot* was
about was according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* who says you don't
require a מעשה *ma'aseh*. אבל לרבנן כי קאמר ריש לקיש נמי לרבי
עקיבא אלא לרבנן
לא *Aval lerabbanan ki ka-amar Reish Lakish nami lerabbi akiva ala lerabbanan
lo*. According to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, waving of the arms is
a מעשה *ma'aseh* and according to the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* it's not
a מעשה *ma'aseh*, which is why the
משנה *Mishnah* in כריתות *Keritot* only taught בעל אוב ba'al ov *ba'al
ov*, but now we're going to have a problem. אי הכי יצא
מגדף ובעל אוב
מיבעיא *Ie hachi yatza
megadef u-va'al ov mibaya*.
The רבנן *Rabbanan* should have disagreed in the ברייתא baraita *baraita* in
כריתות *Keritot* and they should have said that a מגדף *megadef* and
a בעל אוב *ba'al ov* are not חייב chayav *chayav* in כריתות
*Keritot*, but we only said מגדף *megadef* is not חייב chayav *chayav*
in the כרת *karet*.
There's a ברייתא *baraita* in כריתות *Keritot* that says the רבנן *Rabbanan*
disagree with רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* and say that מגדף *megadef* is
not חייב chayav *chayav* in כרת *karet*, but since we just concluded
that a בעל אוב *ba'al ov* is also not חייב chayav *chayav*
in כרת *karet*, the ברייתא *baraita* in כריתות *Keritot* should have said
the רבנן *Rabbanan* also disagree with רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* on a
בעל אוב מיבעיא לה *ba'al ov mibaya la*. אלא אמר עולא *Ela
amar Ulla*, rather עולא *Ulla* says במקטר לשד *bimekter lashed*. We're talking
about a case where someone tries to raise a sorry someone who
burns incense to a demon. אמר ליה רבא Rava במקטר לשד עובד
עבודה זרה oved avodah zarah. הוא *Amar lei Rava bimekter lashed oved
avodah zarah hu*. But רבא Rava *Rava* disagrees and says that someone
who burns incense to a שד shed *shed* is actually doing עבודה
זרה avodah zarah *avodah zarah*.
So then רבא Rava *Rava* comes with yet another explanation of what...
hold on... that the incense is not offered to worship it's not
offered to worship it's offered as a... oh, right... like a...
some... that a בעל אוב *ba'al ov* is actually someone who burns
incense to a שד shed *shed*. במקטר לחבר *Bimekter lechaver*. Right...
first
it's first it's במקטר לשד *bimekter lashed*, someone who burns incense to
a demon,
that a בעל אוב
*ba'al ov*... דקתני בכריתות
*de-katani be-keritot*... yeah okay
so רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says in the middle of the wide lines
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 up, he says במקטר
לשד בעל אוב דקתני בכריתות *bimekter lashed ba'al ov de-katani be-keritot*, the
kind of... בעל אוב that's taught in כריתות that you're חייב chayav
כרת for is is someone who burns incense to a שד which
is obviously a מעשה. דמודו בי רבנן בהכי עסקינן Demodu bei Rabbanan
behachi askinan שמקטר לפני השד shemekater lifnei hashed הממונה על אותו דבר
דהוי מעשה גמור hamumuneh al oto davar dehavi ma'aseh gamur that even
the רבנן agree that burning a burning
incense to a שד is a מעשה which is why over there
it's taught as a חיוב כרת chiyuv kares and here it's not
because here we're talking about waving the arms. Sorry, it's not there
talking about waving of arms or speaking from your mouth because neither
of those according to the רבנן are מעשה עבירה so there it's
talking about burning a burning incense where it says it's בעל אוב
and it doesn't teach ידעוני because according to רבנן ידעוני does not
have a מעשה.
Okay? Uh-huh. Now
I have to find where we were... רבא מקטר לשד. Rava mekater
lashed.
Okay
so then רבא Rava comes back and says no it can't be
talking about מקטר לשד mekater lashed because מקטר לשד עובד עבודת כוכבים
הוא mekater lashed oved avodat kochavim hu
because that's that's actually עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim and that's a different
איסור. issur. That's not בעל אוב
that's עובד עבודה זרה. avodah zarah אלא אמר רבא במקטר לחבר Ella
amar Rava bemekater l'chever or חבר. cheber. Someone who burns incense to
a
dead person which is like necromancy I believe. אמר ליה אביי. Amar
lei Abaye. אביי Abaye says המקטר לחבר חובר חבר הוא. Hamekater l'chever
chover chever hu.
That's someone who there's an explicit איסור issur in the תורה Torah
about it and it's someone and in the תורה Torah it is
not someone it's someone ואינו אלא בלאו ve'eino ela belav says רש"י
meaning it's someone who is חייב מלקות chayav malkut
someone who's someone's חייב to get lashes from בית דין and not
someone who's חייב כרת. And then רבא's response is אין והתורה אמרה
חובר זה בסקילה. In vehatorah amrah chover zeh b'skilah. And the תורה
Torah. says that a person who does who does this thing חובר
חבר chover chever actually is required is חייב בסקילה chayav b'skilah and
not only in lashes. But there's
still there's still a kind of person who's חייב מלקות chayav malkut
even according to
even according to רבא there's someone who does a חובר חבר chover
chever and is חייב מלקות chayav malkut and who is that? חובר
חבר אחד חבר גדול ואחד חבר קטן ואפילו נחשים
ועקרבים. Chover chever echad chever gadol ve'echad chever katan ve'afilu nechasim ve'akrabim.
Someone who through witchcraft summons animals to fight with one another is
someone who is חייב מלקות chayav malkut but is not חייב בסקילה.
chayav b'skilah. Okay. אמר אביי הלכך האי מן דצמי זיבורא ועקרבא אע"ג
דקמיכוין דלא ליזקו אסור. Amar Abaye hilchach hai man d'tzami zibura ve'akraba
af al gav d'kamichaven d'la lizku assur. So אביי Abaye says therefore
someone who conjures up bees and scorpions in order to in order
for one to kill the other אע"ג דקמיכוין דלא af al gav
d'kamichaven d'la even though he's not trying to injure anyone it's still
אסור assur and that person is חייב in מלקות. malkut. Okay. Now
we're going all the way back to
we're going all the way back to the question
of השתחוויה hashtachavayah right? So the one you just did
scorpions are deadly? Yes. So you're surrounded by scorpions you're trying to
get bees to kill the scorpion or hornets or wasps to kill
the scorpion. Isn't that פיקוח נפש? pikuach nefesh? Yeah there's a note
רש"י says if it's to save your life you can do it.
There you go. Okay.
Although I wonder if anyone disagrees because this is maybe a kind
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah. and עבודה זרה is not something that
you're allowed to do even to save your life. Right. So that's
probably a question about like where this falls in terms of different
kinds of עבודה זרה. Okay so we're going all the way back
to when we said that השתחוויה hashtachavayah that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said
that bowing is a מעשה according to the רבנן.
So we're going to ask a question on that. ורבי יוחנן מאי
שנא דכפיפת קומתו לרבנן הוי מעשה ואטמיצת שפתיו לא הוי מעשה. V'Rabbi
Yochanan mai shna d'kfifat komato l'Rabbanan havei ma'aseh ve'atmitzat sefataiv lo havei
ma'aseh.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. holds that bowing according to the רבנן is
a מעשה but moving your lips is not a מעשה. It seems
like they're both the same thing because you're basically just doing an
action with your body that has no effect on the physical world.
How come they're different? אמר רבא שאני מגדף הואיל וישנו בלב. Amar
Rava shani megadef ho'il v'yeshno b'leiv. A מגדף
is different
because
it's from his heart,
and דאווענינג davenning is not from the heart. מיתיבי רב זירא, Meitivei
Rav Zeira, but רב זירא Rav Zeira disagreed. יצאו עדים זוממין שאין
בהן מעשה. Yatzu eidim zomemin she'ein bahen maaseh. But עדים
זוממין, eidim zomemin, there's a—there are a lot of גרסא girsa problems
here, but I'm going to read it the way I want to
read it. מיתיבי רב זירא. Meitivei Rav Zeira. רב זירא Rav Zeira
says יצאו עדים זוממין. Yatzu eidim zomemin. עדים זוממין Eidim zomemin are
not חייב כרת even if the עדות eidus they do is about
כרת. עדים זוממין Eidim zomemin as a reminder, you do according to
them כאשר זמם, kaasher zamam, right? They tried to—they gave
עדות eidus that would be מחייב mechayev someone else in כרת. They
should be כרת, but they don't actually get כרת because all they're
doing—because there's no מעשה. Right? רב זירא, Rav Zeira, יצאו עדים זוממין
שאין בהן מעשה. yatzu eidim zomemin she'ein bahen maaseh. There is no
מעשה. ואמאי? הא ליתנהו בלב? V'amai? Ha litnehu b'leiv? Let us also
say that their testimony came from the heart? אמר רבא
שאני—so Amar Rava shani how come they're not considered to have done
a מעשה while a מגדף is considered to have done a מעשה?
אמר רבא שאני עדים זוממין הואיל
וישנן בקול. Amar Rava shani eidim zomemin ho'il v'yeshnan b'kol.
So רבא says it's different because
there is a—because they
use their voices. It's not about the bending of the lips, it's
about their voices, and the voice really has no מעשה. It's not
about מלב, mileiv, it's about הקול. hakol. וקול לרבי יוחנן לאו מעשה
הוא? V'kol l'Rabbi Yochanan lav maaseh hu? But
is—right, we just said that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds that
from the heart is a מעשה but הקול hakol is not a
מעשה. But now we're going to say that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan,
does hold that a voice, that saying something, is a מעשה. והא
איתמר, V'ha itmar, we have the following אמוראית מחלוקת. Amorait machlokes. חסמה
בקול והנהיגה בקול. Chasama b'kol v'hinhiga b'kol.
If you muzzle an animal with your voice, presumably if it's threshing
and it starts to eat and you yell at it to
stop eating, that would be muzzling with your voice, or you lead
two animals that are strapped together as כלאים, kilayim, you lead them
with your voice. רבי יוחנן אמר חייב וריש לקיש אמר פטור. Rabbi
Yochanan amar chayav v'Reish Lakish amar patur. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan? says
you're חייב in that thing and ריש לקיש says you're פטור. patur.
So there's מחלוקת machlokes רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש לקיש as
to whether or not saying something is a מעשה. And this is
really where the thing I mentioned about שבת Shabbos and electronics comes
in.
But if you look in the עין משפט, Ein Mishpat, the להלכה
l'halacha comes down on the side of רבי יוחנן. So speaking is
a מעשה.
רבי יוחנן אמר חייב אקימת פיו הוי מעשה וריש לקיש אמר פטור
אקימת פיו לא הוי מעשה. Rabbi Yochanan amar chayav akimat piv havei
maaseh v'Reish Lakish amar patur akimat piv lo havei maaseh. So רבי
יוחנן says you're חייב because moving your lips is a מעשה. ריש
לקיש says you're פטור patur because moving your lips is not a
מעשה. אלא אמר רבא שאני עדים זוממין הואיל וישנן בראייה. Ella amar
Rava shani eidim zomemin ho'il v'yeshnan b'reiah.
עדים זוממין Eidim zomemin are different because their action was done in
ראייה reiah is what the וילנא ש"ס Vilna Shas says. But the
רי"ף Rif changes the גרסא girsa to that they said "I." If
you look in—where are these two asterisks?
If you look in—there it is. דרב אלפס כתב בשם רב האי
גרסתו הואיל וישנן באי. D'Rav Alfas katav b'shem Rav Hai girsato ho'il
v'yeshnan b'ai. ועיין שם שהאריך בפירושו. V'ayen sham shehe'erich b'feirusho. So in
the רי"ף Rif changes the גרסא girsa to that they said "I,"
but that's still a
problem because that's still just something that happens בקול. b'kol. Why do
you even need this? עדים זוממין Eidim zomemin is explicit in תורה.
But
they don't get כרת because there's no מעשה. So how come עדים
זוממין eidim zomemin don't get כרת but someone who is מגדף does
get כרת? What's the difference between their— They might get executed. They
might get executed, but there's no כרת. So this is a problematic—the
problem with saying that it's in ראייה, reiah, it's in what they
saw, is that what they saw has nothing to do with being
an עד זומם, eid zomem, right? The testimony is what is the
problem.
So the רי"ף Rif changes the גרסא girsa to that they said
"I," but that's still a problem because we just said that speaking—maybe
there's something different about speaking in a court proceeding that somehow
the action of the whole court proceeding gets
attributed to them or makes their speech more
weighty or something?
But the point is they're not—there is no מעשה. Yeah.
And according to, we just said that מגדף is a מעשה because
you say something. According to רבי יוחנן, wait, how do you mean
according to רבי יוחנן? רבי יוחנן so someone in a situation where
they're not going to get סקילה where you have to rely on
כרת? By definition, that's a good question. There needs to be the
court. That's a good question. A lot's been written about this. Yeah,
I'm sure a lot has been written. Page 13 by the way.
Yeah, I see. Let's see. Let's do, let's just do this next
ברייתא because it's going to define and then it's just a few
lines and then there's another ברייתא. תנו רבנן: Tano Rabbanan: בעל אוב
זה המדבר בפיו בין הפרקים. ba'al ov ze hamedaber be'piv bein haprakim.
A בעל אוב is someone who speaks using the space in between
their joints, ובין אצילי ידיו ubein atzilei yadav and from the armpits.
ידעוני זה המניח עצם ידוע בפיו, Yedoni ze hamaniach etzem yadua befiv,
someone who takes a bone from this animal called a ידוע yadua
and puts it in his mouth, והוא מדבר מאליו, vehu medaber me'elav,
and the bone speaks
from its own. Right. Like ventriloquism. Exactly. מיתיבי, Meitivei, we have a
problem with this ברייתא because there's another ברייתא that disagrees with it:
והיה כאוב מארץ קולך. Vehaya k'ov me'eretz kolech. Sorry, מיתיבי Meitivei from
the פסוק passuk והיה כאוב מארץ קולך. Vehaya k'ov me'eretz kolech. That's
very interesting actually that there's a מיתיבי Meitivei from usually מיתיבי Meitivei
is from a tannaic source. Right. This is much earlier than a
תנא. tanna. Right. So really מיתיבי Meitivei means we have a problem
from a more authoritative source and obviously this is more authoritative. והיה
כאוב מארץ קולך, Vehaya k'ov me'eretz kolech, it sounds like from the
פסוק passuk מאי לאו דמשתעי כארחיה mai lav demishtaei keorchei that it
comes straight from the ground naturally and not that you have to
do something and put the bone in your mouth and have it
talk. לא, דסליק ויתבי בין הפרקים. lo, desalika veyatvei bein haprakim. No,
that the demon or the dead thing comes up and sits in
between the joints and speaks from there ומשתעי umishtaei
and and it's heard from
there. תא שמע, Tashma, another another challenge. It's going to be the
same kind of challenge, but: ותאמר האשה אל שאול אלהים ראיתי עולים
מן הארץ. Vatomer ha'isha el Shaul elohim ra'iti olim min ha'aretz. I
saw these messengers of God come up from the ground. מאי לאו
דמשתעי כארחיה, mai lav demishtaei keorchei, is it not that they heard
directly from the ground and not that they go and dwell in
something else and are heard from there? לא, דיתבי בין הפרקים ומשתעי.
lo, deyatvei bein haprakim umishtaei. No, they go up and they and
they go between bones and they they make their voices heard from
from joints and they're not heard directly from the ground. We'll have
to stop there and I'll continue to talk but the ראש ישיבה
Rosh Yeshiva now. Is it the same idea that when the כהן
גדול... Kohen Gadol...