טוב. Tov. Today's דף Daf is דף נ. Daf Nun. We won't
be doing the ירושלמי Yerushalmi today. We pick up with the bottom
of מ"ט עמוד ב Mem Tet Amud Bet at the two dots,
three lines from the bottom, where we have the order סקילה שריפה
הרג חנק Sekila Sereifa Hereg Chenek and where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
in the משנה, Mishna, everybody agrees to the two pairs. By the
way, it's interesting because we had learned that there were two cemeteries,
graves, in בית דין, Beis Din, one for the weightier ones, סקילה
Sekila and שריפה, Sereifa, and one for the
lighter executions, those who have been executed הרג Hereg and חנק. Chenek.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees to those two pairs but he reverses
the order in each pair. So instead of סקילה שריפה, Sekila Sereifa,
he has שריפה סקילה, Sereifa Sekila, and instead of הרג חנק, Hereg
Chenek, he has חנק הרג. Chenek Hereg. So in today's דף Daf
is really just going to all be devoted to figuring out how
the Rabbis get their order and how רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon gets
his order. Okay, סקילה חמורה משריפה, Sekila chamura miSereifa, סקילה Sekila is
weightier, שכן ניתנה למגדף ולעובד עבודה זרה. shekein nitna l'magadef u'l'oveid avodah
zarah.
So we know סקילה, Sekila, we had actually mentioned it in the
previous פרק Perek because that dealt with the stoning and the hanging,
and one of the hangings was כי קללת אלוהים תלוי. Ki Kilalas
Elokim Taluy. So anyway, who gets סקילה? Sekila? Somebody who blasphemes God
and worships idols. So that indicates that it's the heaviest one because
obviously that's some of the heaviest sins.
So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי חומרי? Mai chumrei? And what is
that weightiness? שכן פושט ידו בעיקר. Shekein posheit yado b'ikar. Somebody is
directly rebelling against God, so clearly that would indicate that that's the
weightier punishment
if that's what's designated for those sins. אדרבה, Adaraba, say the opposite,
שריפה חמורה שכן ניתנה לבת כהן שזינתה. Sereifa chamura shekein nitna l'vas
kohen shezinza. Right? ובת כהן כי תחל לזנות את אביה היא מחללת
באש תשרף. Uvas kohen ki tachel lehiznos es aviah hi mechalleles boish
tisareif. If a daughter of a כהן Kohen begins to fornicate, and
what exactly does that mean? Committed adultery, we'll see more about that
in a minute. Anyway, then she has to be burned by a
fire. Now, if you ask me, it would seem that עובד עבודה
זרה oveid avodah zarah is worse than that. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ומאי חומרי, U'mai chumrei, why would I think that gives it
weight? שכן מחללת את אביה. Shekein mechalleles es aviah. It's not only
maybe a sin against God, it's a sin against person, it brings
shame to the family. So maybe that's weightier. Now, קסברי רבנן, Kasvari
rabanan, the Rabbis are of the opinion, נשואה יצאה לשריפה ולא ארוסה.
nesuah yatzah l'sereifa v'lo arusa. Okay, now here, this is going to
be a core issue in terms of understanding how the פסוקים psukim
line up. Okay, but we know the פסוקים psukim are pretty clear
that by a case of adultery by a בת ישראל, bat Yisroel,
okay,
by a בת ישראל, bat Yisroel, we know that by a case
of adultery, okay, נשואה nesuah gets חנק chenek
and ארוסה arusa
gets
סקילה. sekila. Okay.
So
that's clear in the פסוקים. psukim. Okay. So then the question is,
and then it says by a בת כהן bat kohen that she
gets שריפה. sereifa. Now, the assumption of course is, so this tells
us that סקילה sekila is more חמור chamur than חנק, chenek, because
again the assumption is that an ארוסה arusa is a weightier sin.
Why is it assumed that? Okay, but it's assumed that way because
basically she
is bringing shame to her father's house, not only she's sort of
sinning against her husband, she's bringing shame to her father's house, she's
in her father's house, that's the way the פסוקים psukim frame it,
they frame it about that, that she's put it in the context
of בית אביה. beis aviah. So that's just taken for granted that
it's assumed that that's weightier. Okay. So that is, so we get
that. Now here, the question is which בת כהן bat kohen gets
שריפה? sereifa? If both of these get שריפה, sereifa, and again the
assumption is a בת כהן bat kohen is worse than a בת
ישראל, bat Yisroel, את אביה היא מחללת es aviah hi mechalleles etc.,
she's singled out, then it would mean that שריפה sereifa is weightier
than סקילה. sekila. Right? You get that? Because if both of these
get it and it's assumed that this is weightier. Now if however,
so that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going to say. But
the חכמים Chachamim say, not based on any proof of the פסוק
pasuk but just based on their general philosophy, they're going to say
that no, we're going to say that this is what when the
תורה Torah says שריפה sereifa it's talking about נשואה, nesuah, whereas this
we're going to assume, not based on any פסוק, pasuk, we're going
to assume that that remains סקילה. sekila.
Why did you say it like a few times?
I don't know. I have no explanation, Michael. Okay, so this is
not a proof for them, but it's the way they handle the
פסוקים. psukim. Now the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like oh, this
is their proof. Their proof is that סקילה, sekila, again because assuming
that ארוסה arusa is worse than a נשואה, nesuah, so clearly סקילה
sekila is worse than שריפה sereifa because a נשואה nesuah is שריפה
sereifa and an ארוסה arusa is סקילה. sekila. But you didn't prove
that. You just assumed that and you read the פסוקים psukim like
that, right? You could have the much more obvious read would be
that everything gets שריפה sereifa and שריפה sereifa is the worst. So
that's why there's a long רש"י, Rashi, and the long רש"י Rashi
says, the גמרא Gemara sounds like it's proving something right now but
it's not proving anything. What it's doing is it's taking its assumptions,
it's reading it into the פסוקים, psukim, and then it's reading it
right back. Okay, so this is... The גמרא's Gemara reading not proving
right now that סקילה skila is worse than שריפה, sreifa, it's assuming
that and reading it into the פסוקים. psukim. And by assuming that
and reading it into the פסוקים, psukim, we're going to say the
שריפה sreifa is limited up here to the נשואה, nesua, and the
worst punishment for the ארוסה, arusa, they're going to assert is the
same and is the סקילה. skila. Okay, so that's how they manage,
you know, or, you know, work with the פסוקים, psukim, but it's
not proving anything. So let's just read that in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, קסברי רבנן, kasvari rabbanan, the Rabbis are of the opinion, נשואה
יוצאה לשריפה ולא ארוסה. nesua yotza l'sreifa v'lo arusa. The נשואה בת
כהן nesua bas kohen gets שריפה, sreifa, not the ארוסה. arusa. ומידי
דאפטר רחמנא ארוסה בסקילה, u'midei d'aftar rachmana arusa b'skila, so since the
ארוסה's arusa getting סקילה, skila, which is heavier than שריפה, sreifa, okay,
שמע מינה סקילה חמורה. shma mina skila chamura. You see סקילה's skila
weightier. Now again, the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like we're proving
something. רש"י Rashi says we didn't prove anything. We just assumed סקילה
skila was weightier, we read the פסוקים psukim that way, and now
we're reading it back out of the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so רש"י
Rashi says yeah, the גמרא's Gemara a little bit like, you know,
not precise. Okay, really, the reason we're assuming סקילה skila is weightier
is what we said in the previous עמוד. amud. That if, if
the idolator and the blasphemer get סקילה, skila, then that has to
be the weightiest. Okay, forget that a בת כהן bas kohen gets
שריפה. sreifa. Give me a break. Idolator and blasphemer is a weightier
sin. So we start with the assumption that סקילה skila is weightier
and then this is just how we manage the פסוקים, psukim, but
it doesn't prove anything. Okay, but isn't burning more painful?
Probably,
but pushing them off...
you're right, the גמרא Gemara never... so you're right, the גמרא Gemara
never in this whole discussion assumes that the way we determine how
severe the punishment is, is how disfiguring or painful or bad it
is for the person experiencing it. By the way, the way we
do burning is also
a more humane way than you would imagine. We don't actually burn
the person alive. We pour some molten lead down the person's throat,
so not pleasant either, but it's a lot more pleasant than burning
alive. Okay, anyway, but you're right, the גמרא Gemara never assumes that
we'll use the actual experience of it to determine the ranking. We're
just going to use the sin that it's punishment for to try
to assess how weighty it is. Okay, so שמע מינה סקילה חמורה.
shma mina skila chamura. Now, so that's how we know that סקילה
skila is weightier than שריפה, sreifa, not, you know, we sort of
worked it into the פסוקים, psukim, we just sort of know it
because we're asserting that it is, we're asserting that that's got to
be the most serious
punishment because it's for the idolator. Now, סקילה חמורה משריפה. skila chamura
mi'sreifa. And now we're going to go through all of them. Okay,
so here's what we're going to do: סקילה, skila, then שריפה, sreifa,
סייף sayif or הרג, hereg,
and
חנק. chenek. Okay, so how do we know סקילה skila is greater
than שריפה? sreifa? Because, well, we fit it into these פסוקים psukim
here, but we're basically saying פשטה ידו בעיקר. pashta yado b'ikar.
Okay, that's why it's weightier because it's פשטה ידו בעיקר, pashta yado
b'ikar, so it's got to be worse. How do we know it's
greater than סייף sayif and הרג? hereg?
Okay,
so סקילה חמורה מסייף. skila chamura mi'sayif. How do we know it's
greater than סייף? sayif? שכן ניתנה למגדף ולעובד כוכבים, sheken nitna l'megadef
u'l'oved kochavim, same point. ומה חומר כדאמרינן. u'ma chomer k'damrinan. Okay, because
it's פשטה ידו בעיקר, pashta yado b'ikar, it's got to be the
weightiest punishment because it's for the idolator. So אדרבה, aderaba, סייף חמור.
sayif chamur. Hey, wait a minute, how about death by the sword?
שכן ניתנה לאנשי עיר הנידחת, sheken nitna l'anshei ir ha'nidachat, that's what
you do when you wipe out the city that commits עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. That's also עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So don't go telling
me a punishment for עבודה זרה avoda zara has to be the
weightiest. סייף sayif is also a punishment for עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
How do we know סקילה skila is a weightier punishment?
ומה חומר u'ma chomer and I'll prove to you maybe it's even
weightier than a normal idolator. שכן ממונם אבד, sheken mamonam avad, you
destroy the money of עיר הנידחת. ir ha'nidachat. So that's a real
weighty punishment. Okay, so let's say that סייף sayif is weightier. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמרת איזה כוח מרובה כוח המדיח או כוח
הנידח. amarta eizeh koach merubeh koach ha'madiach o koach ha'nidach. Okay, because
here's how we'll figure it out. Because if you had to choose,
whose punishment would you give as a weightier one? The one who
pushes everybody away, makes everybody worship עבודה זרה, avoda zara, or the
people who do the worship? So presumably it's
the inciter and the person to blame for the whole thing and
so on.
הוי אומר, כוח המדיח. hevei omer koach hamadiach, It must be the
one that is pushing them and is getting them to be עובדי
עבודה זרה. ovdei avoda zara. ותניא, v'tanya, and we've taught in a
ברייתא, braisa, which we'll prove later on, מדיחי עיר הנידחת, madichei ir
ha'nidachat, the one that pushes the city to עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
בסקילה, b'skila, gets סקילה. skila. So okay, although both of these are
פשטה ידו בעיקר, pashta yado b'ikar, you know that סקילה skila is
weightier. Why is סקילה... skila... I mean when I put it here
it makes it sound like... well, that's why the that thing... it
looks like it's referring to that thing. Okay, so סקילה skila is
weightier than
שריפה. sreifa. Okay, how do we know that it's greater than חנק?
Chenek? So
סקילה חמור מחנק שכן ניתן למגדף ולעובד כוכבים. Skila Chamur Mi'Chenek She'ken
Nitan Le'Megadef U'Le'Oved Kochavim. Well, it's the punishment you get for עבודה
זרה. Avoda Zara. That's obviously got to be the weightiest. ומאי חומרא
כדאמרינן, U'Mai Chumra Ke'Damrinan, and it's what we said. אדרבה חנק חמור
שכן ניתן למכה אביו ואמו, Adaraba Chenek Chamur She'ken Nitan Le'Makeh Aviv
Ve'Imo, that you what do you mean? חנק Chenek is what you
get for somebody who smites a father and mother. ומאי חומרא שכן
הוקש כבודם לכבוד המקום, U'Mai Chumra She'ken Hukash Kevodam Li'Kvod Ha'Makom, and
the parents are way as they're the respect to parents is similar
to the respect to God, so that should be right up there.
Now תוספות Tosafos says it can't be more than God. I mean
if God—so תוספות Tosafos says okay, but maybe they should be equal.
Okay, still, how do we know סקילה Skila is weightier? Maybe cursing—what's
your question? Okay, so תוספות Tosafos asks that question. Okay, so anyway,
we can't worry about all those things. Anyway, because you get סקילה
Skila for cursing, that's true. I know.
Okay, okay. שכן הוקש כבודם לכבוד המקום. She'ken Hukash Kevodam Li'Kvod Ha'Makom.
So how do we know it's weightier than חנק? Chenek? מידי דאמר
רחמנא לארוסה בת ישראל מכלל נשואה בת ישראל מחנק וסקילה שמע מינה
סקילה חמורה. Midei De'Amar Rachmana Le'Arusa Bat Yisrael Mi'Klal Nesua Bat Yisrael
Me'Chenek U'Skila She'ma Mina Skila Chamura. No,
we know it's weightier because of this, and this is in the
פסוקים Pesukim that an ארוסה Arusa gets סקילה Skila and a נשואה
Nesua gets חנק. Chenek. Now, of course, how do you know that
the ארוסה Arusa is worse? But again, the assumption is that it
is because it's a context of בית אביה Beit Aviha and it
brings shame to her father's house and all of that. So that
shows you that סקילה Skila is worse than חנק Chenek because of—so
that is סקילה Skila is worse than חנק, Chenek, that you know
because of ארוסה Arusa versus נשואה. Nesua. Okay, so now we've proven
that סקילה Skila is greater than all those three. Now what we
have to do is prove that שרפה Sreifa is better than these
two, right? And then I'm going to prove סייף Sayaf is better,
weightier, worse, whatever fine.
Okay, okay.
שרפה חמור מסייף. Sreifa Chamur Mi'Sayaf. שרפה Sreifa is weightier than סייף.
Sayaf. שכן ניתן לבת כהן שזינתה. She'ken Nitan Le'Bat Kohen She'Zinta. Okay,
because ah, it's got to be a weighty sin if you get
it to the בת כהן Bat Kohen gets it. ומאי חומרא שכן
מחללת אביה, U'Mai Chumra She'ken Mechalelat Aviha, and what's weighty is that
she desecrates her father's house. אדרבה סייף חמור שכן ניתן לאנשי עיר
הנדחת. Adaraba Sayaf Chamur She'ken Nitan Le'Anshei Ir Ha'Nidachat. Oh, what do
you mean? I mean סייף Sayaf is pretty weighty, you do it
to wipe out the city of ex-idol-idolatry. ומאי חומרא שכן ממונם אבד.
U'Mai Chumra She'ken Mamonam Avad. It's not just idolatry, you even destroy
all their money. That's true, סייף Sayaf seems pretty darn
worst, weightier. נאמר אביה בסקילה ונאמר אביה בשרפה. Ne'emar Aviha Bi'Skila Ve'Ne'emar
Aviha Bi'Sreifa. By both of those sins by the case of the
בת כהן Bat Kohen who gets שרפה Sreifa and by the by
the ארוסה Arusa who gets סקילה, Skila, it says אביה. Aviha. What's
the פסוק? Pasuk? רשי Rashi says let's see, רשי Rashi says let's
see, רשי. Rashi.
את אביה היא מחללת. Et Aviha Hi Mechalelat.
את אביה היא מחללת. Et Aviha Hi Mechalelat. We already said. And
what's the one
by—oh,
לזנות בית אביה. Liznot Beit Aviha. Okay, that's what it says, לזנות
בית אביה Liznot Beit Aviha here, by this
one,
לזנות בית
אביה.
Liznot
Beit
Aviha.
לזנות בית אביה. Liznot Beit Aviha.
What? No, and the שרפה Sreifa is את אביה היא מחללת. Et
Aviha Hi Mechalelat. את
אביה היא מחללת.
Et Aviha Hi
Mechalelat. Okay, so נאמר אביה בסקילה ונאמר אביה בשרפה מה אביה אמור
בסקילה סקילה חמור מסייף. Ne'emar Aviha Bi'Skila Ve'Ne'emar Aviha Bi'Sreifa Ma Aviha
Ha'Amur Bi'Skila Skila Chamur Mi'Sayaf. So the same way we've proven here
that סקילה Skila is weightier than סייף. Sayaf. Okay, so this סקילה
Skila here is weightier than סייף. Sayaf. So this שרפה Sreifa with
also mentions אביה Aviha is also going to be weightier than סייף.
Sayaf. So the basic way, how do we know שרפה Sreifa is
weightier than סייף? Sayaf? This is really because of a גזירה שוה.
Gezeira Shava. Okay, that's just a גזירה שוה. Gezeira Shava.
How do we know a גזירה שוה Gezeira Shava you know is
is trumping פשט ידו בעיקר? Pashat Yado Be'Ikar?
What can I tell you? Because we because we have a system
that we got to work out. Okay, it's clear that we're sort
of starting and working
backwards. Okay, so okay. Forgot my place. מה
אביה אמור בסקילה סקילה חמור מסייף אף אביה אמור בשרפה שרפה חמור
מסייף. Ma Aviha Ha'Amur Bi'Skila Skila Chamur Mi'Sayaf Af Aviha Ha'Amur Bi'Sreifa
Sreifa Chamur Mi'Sayaf. שרפה חמור מחנק. Sreifa Chamur Mi'Chenek. How do we
know שרפה Sreifa is weightier than חנק? Chenek? שכן ניתן לבת כהן
שזינתה. She'ken Nitan Le'Bat Kohen She'Zinta. A בת כהן Bat Kohen gets
it, that's pretty weighty. ומאי חומרא כדאמרן U'Mai Chumra Ke'Damran because you
desecrate her father's house. אדרבה חנק חמור שכן ניתן למכה אביו ואמו.
Adaraba Chenek Chamur She'ken Nitan Le'Makeh Aviv Ve'Imo. What do you mean?
חנק Chenek you get for smiting a parent. ומאי חומרא שכן הוקש
כבודם לכבוד המקום U'Mai Chumra She'ken Hukash Kevodam Li'Kvod Ha'Makom and that's
pretty weighty, that's like hitting God. Yeah, or whatever, you know their
honor's due to the honor of God. מידי דאמר רחמנא לנשואה בת
כהן מכלל נשואה בת ישראל מחנק לשרפה שמע מינה שרפה חמורה. Midei
De'Amar Rachmana Le'Nesua Bat Kohen Mi'Klal Nesua Bat Yisrael Me'Chenek Le'Sreifa She'ma
Mina Sreifa Chamura. No no no, this is an easy one because
here a בת כהן Bat Kohen gets שרפה Sreifa and a בת
ישראל Bat Yisrael gets חנק, Chenek, right? Yes. So that shows you
שרפה Sreifa is more חמור Chamur than חנק. Chenek.
Of course the way רבנן Rabanan read that in that he gets
that the שרפה Sreifa is—no, everybody agrees that a בת כהן Bat
Kohen gets שרפה. Sreifa. Okay, for what? For at least for נשואה,
Nesua, if not for both, but certainly it's weightier than חנק. Chenek.
Nobody says you don't get it for נשואה. Nesua. Okay, so שרפה
Sreifa is weightier than סייף Sayaf by גזירה שוה, Gezeira Shava, and
it's weightier than חנק Chenek based on the fact that. Okay. Okay,
סייף חמור מחנק שכן ניתן לאנשי עיר הנדחת. saif chamur me-chenek shekein
nitan le-anshei ir ha-nidachas. You give it to the אנשי עיר הנדחת.
anshei ir ha-nidachas. That's pretty
weighty.
ומה חומרא שכן לממונא אבד? u-mah chumra shekein le-mamona avad? And it's
pretty serious, not only is it עבודה זרה avoda zara but you
destroy their money. אדרבה חנק חמור שכן ניתן למכה אביו ואמו. adra-bah
chenek chamur shekein nitan le-makeh aviv ve-imo. ומה חומרא שכן הוקש כבודם
לכבוד המקום? u-mah chumra shekein hukash kevodam li-kvod ha-makom?
Okay, but still, I don't know, חנק chenek is for, you know,
is about parents, and that's pretty weighty. אפילו הכי פושט ידו בעיקר
עדיף. afilu hachi poshet yado be-ikar adif. Now, okay, we can't really,
you know, it's similar to what רש"י Rashi said of how we
know סקילה skila is more weighty than שריפה. sreifa. Things that are
about עבודה זרה avoda zara have got to be weightier than things
that are not about עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Okay? So the way
we know סייף saif is greater than חנק chenek is that this
is for עבודה זרה avoda zara and this isn't for עבודה זרה.
avoda zara.
That didn't work before to put the שריפה, sreifa, you know, in
the secondary position.
I understand, I don't know, what can I tell you, man?
So we end up right back where we started.
Well, we well we tried to prove what we set out to
prove. So this is how the רבנן Rabbanan prove their hierarchy. Okay,
now we switch to רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon. Okay, so what we're
going to do for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is we're going to
start the other way, right, we're going to start by first proving
that שריפה sreifa is better than all the rest.
I mean it's going to be חנק chenek and then הרג hereg
for him, he says it's going to be his order. Okay, so
we're going to prove שריפה sreifa is greater, then we're going to
prove סקילה skila is greater than these two, and then חנק chenek
is greater than הרג. hereg. Okay.
That's
interesting.
Alright. רבי שמעון אומר, Rebbi Shimon omer, so the גמרא Gemara says,
שריפה חמורה מסקילה שכן ניתנה לבת כהן שזינתה. sreifa chamura mi-skila shekein
nitenes le-bas kohen she-zisnasa. Okay? ומה חומרא שכן מחללה את אביה. u-mah
chumra shekein mechallela es aviha. So שריפה sreifa is pretty weighty, it's
for a בת כהן. Bas Kohen. אדרבה סקילה חמורה שכן ניתנת למגדף
ולעובד עבודת כוכבים. adra-bah skila chamura shekein nitenes le-migaidef u-le-oveid avodas kochavim.
What do you mean? סקילה skila is even weightier, it's for עבודה
זרה avoda zara and מגדף, migaidef, right? That's like logically that's pretty
weighty. So how you know why would you put שריפה sreifa higher
up than that? Okay. ומה חומרא שכן פשט ידו בעיקר. u-mah chumra
shekein pashat yado be-ikar. רבי שמעון לטעמיה. Rebbi Shimon le-taameih. And now
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is going to go according to his reasoning
based on בת כהן. Bas Kohen. דאמר אחת ארוסה ואחת נשואה יצאו
לשריפה. de-amar achas arusah ve-achas nisuah yatze'u le-sreifa. So this really is,
for the חכמים, Chachamim, it's how we manage the פסוקים pesukim that
they wouldn't contradict their system. We managed the פסוקים pesukim by saying
שריפה sreifa is only for נשואה, nisuah, which allowed סקילה skila to
be the weightiest, so that didn't contradict their system, right? Everybody with
me, right? In terms of that, right? But the simple sense of
the פסוקים pesukim is that שריפה sreifa is for everything by a
בת כהן. Bas Kohen. So שריפה sreifa is for everything, that's,
that's רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon's point of departure. So סקילה skila is
weightier than חנק, chenek, and שריפה sreifa is weightier than both of
them because a בת כהן Bas Kohen we're assuming if it's singled
out or whatever and there's more חילול chilul that that's going to
be weightier. So how do you know שריפה sreifa is weightier than
סקילה? skila? Because of the בת כהן Bas Kohen example. Okay, so
this you know is weightier because of the בת כהן Bas Kohen
example.
So that means that incest is worse than עבודה זרה? avoda zara?
You know, you can't make those types of statements, what can I
tell you? I mean you're right, you know, once you, can you
go ahead and use the hierarchy of the מיתות misos to say
that's sort of where the גמרא Gemara starts? But since the גמרא
Gemara resolved some of it things by external proofs, right? I mean
it would be a funny conclusion to say something like that, you
know.
Like you said, otherwise I don't want
to mess up the... yeah.
But there's other places where sins between us and השם Hashem get
lesser punishment than sins between us and...
I understand that.
Okay, here's a homework assignment. I understand that, meaning once the גמרא
Gemara is number one giving a ranking. Now okay, let me just
say one thing which I don't know if it was mentioned when
Michael read the משנה Mishnah and the גמרא Gemara will come up
to this. What is the point of giving the ranking? Like who
cares? So the really halachic who cares about this whole ranking is
if somebody, right, has been given two death sentences, you give them
the weightier one. That's the only who cares. Okay, but you are
right that since or whichever, to divide it into two groups, to
divide it into four is for this purpose. So it is true
that in order to determine it, the גמרא Gemara assumes that we
can look at the weightiness of the sin and determine how to
rank. Some of the ways it does rank is based on their
assumption of the weightiness of the sin and some of it is
based on external types of proofs, you know, like something like this
or whatever.
So once you're done though, the halachic implication is if somebody is
liable both, which one you give them. But you could say great,
now let's go back, now we've broken the code, now we're going
to go back and look at all the death penalties and determine
which sins the תורה Torah considers to be weightier than which ones.
Okay, I'm just telling you, you know, געזונטהייט, gezuntheit, I find it
very hard to come up with a system that makes sense based
on that. So I will give a little homework assignment for everybody,
you have a day off from work today, it's Labor Day, you
can use your extra time. Go and you know look in the
רמב"ם Rambam in הלכות סנהדרין Hilchos Sanhedrin he lists all of the
punishments for all the various... מיתות בית דין, misos beis din, all
the different sins, and tell me if you can come up with
some type of a system, okay? To me it does seem sometimes
it's a little arbitrary, but I do understand if the גמרא Gemara
is trying to infer from its understanding of the weightiness that's gonna
go ahead and say like Michael said, okay? So זנות של בת
כהן znus of a bas kohein has to be a worse sin
than עובד עבודה זרה. oved avoda zara. Alright, so see if you
can come up with a system. But we're going to now continue
to really explain all of the different sins. But we're going to
continue. Okay, so it says like this. דאמר אחד ארוסה ואחד נשואה
יתא לשריפה. de-amar echad arusah ve-echad nesu'ah yata l'sereifa. ודחף רחמנא לארוסה
בת כהן מכלל ארוסה בת ישראל מסקילה לשריפה, ve-dhaft rachmana l'arusah bas
kohein miklal arusah bas yisrael mi-skilah l'sereifa, שמע מינה שריפה חמורה. shema
mina sereifa chamura. שריפה חמורה מחנק שכן ניתנה לבת כהן שזינתה. sereifa
chamura me-chenek she-ken nitnah l'bas kohein she-zinstah. Okay, שריפה's sereifa got to
be pretty weighty, a בת כהן bas kohein gets it, and therefore
it's weightier than חנק. chenek. ומה חומרא כמאן? u-mah chamura k'aman? אדרבה
חנק חמור שכן ניתן למכה אביו ואמו. adderaba chenek chamur she-ken nitan
l'makeh aviv ve-imo. What do you mean? חנק chenek is getting for
somebody who smites a parent. ומה חומרא שכן הוקש כבודם לכבוד המקום.
u-mah chamura she-ken hukash kvodam l'kvod ha-makom.
That's got to be pretty weighty because it's comparable to the honor
of God. Of course if שריפה sereifa trumps an עבודה זרה avoda
zara sin, it should probably trump a מכה אביו ואמו makeh aviv
ve-imo sin, but anyway. So the גמרא Gemara says no, again we
can prove שריפה's sereifa weightier than חנק. chenek. מדחף רחמנא לנשואה בת
כהן מכלל נשואה בת ישראל מחנק לשריפה, mi-dhaft rachmana l'nesu'ah bas kohein
miklal nesu'ah bas yisrael me-chenek l'sereifa, שמע מינה שריפה חמורה. shema mina
sereifa chamura. That's easy again. שריפה's sereifa weightier than חנק chenek because
שריפה's sereifa weightier than סקילה skilah because a בת כהן bas kohein
gets it who's an ארוסה arusah rather than סקילה. שריפה's skilah sreifah
weightier than חנק chenek that a נשואה בת כהן nesu'ah bas kohein
gets it rather than חנק, chenek, right? So שריפה sereifa is clearly
weightier than those two. Okay, so it's weightier than this and weightier
than this because of the בת כהן bas kohein reason again. Now
how do we know שריפה's sereifa weightier than הרג? hereg? Alright. שריפה
חמורה מסייף שכן
ניתנה לבת כהן שזינתה. sereifa chamura mi-sayif she-ken
nitnah l'bas kohein she-zinstah.
Well
we're going to assume it's weighty because of the בת כהן. bas
kohein. ומה חומרא כמאן? u-mah chamura k'aman? אדרבה סייף חמור שכן ניתן
לאנשי עיר הנדחת. adderaba sayif chamur she-ken nitan l'anshei ir nidachas. What
do you mean? סייף sayif you wipe out the whole עיר הנדחת
ir nidachas of עבודה זרה. avoda zara. That's pretty weighty. Why is
that weighty? שכן ממונם אבד. she-ken mamonam avad. It's not just normal
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, but it's even you know it's a whole
city and you destroy their money so presumably that's a pretty weighty
punishment. אמרת וכי איזה כח מרובה כח המדיח או כח הנידח? amarta
v'chi eizeh ko'ach merubeh ko'ach ha-madi'ach o ko'ach ha-nidach? No,
because which is going to be a weightier sin and a weightier
punishment, the one who pushes them or the people who are pushed?
הוי אומר כח המדיח. havei omer ko'ach ha-madi'ach. Obviously you're going to
give a weightier punishment to the one who pushes them astray. Okay,
now what does the מדיח עיר הנדחת madi'ach ir nidachas get is
סקילה. skilah.
So סקילה skilah. is clearly going to be weightier than הרג. hereg.
This is the מדיח עיר הנדחת madi'ach ir nidachas and this is
the עיר הנדחת ir nidachas itself. So סקילה's skilah weightier than הרג
hereg and שריפה's sereifa weightier than סקילה, skilah you do your transitive
axiom of inequality. Okay,
people don't remember that from mathematics? Axial of inequality. Alright,
right? A is greater than B, B is greater than C, so
A is greater than C.
I learned that small גמרא Gemara at college in Cambridge.
Exactly, exactly. Hey, that was high school. Okay, ובחם אמרת חנק שחמור
מסייף שריפה חמורה ממנו. u-v'cham amarta chenek she-chamur mi-sayif sereifa chamura mimenu.
So חנק chenek is weightier than סייף. sayif. Oh wait a minute.
Okay, I'm sorry, but I got wrong. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually
holds, the חכמים Chachamim held that מדיח עיר הנדחת madi'ach ir nidachas
gets סקילה. skilah, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds that מדיח עיר הנדחת
madi'ach ir nidachas gets חנק, chenek, but it still allows for a
קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. Okay, so this is עיר הנדחת ir nidachas
and this for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, חכמים Chachamim say that the
מדיחים madi'achim get סקילה, skilah. but for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon this
is מדיח עיר הנדחת. madi'ach ir nidachas. Okay, so so so חנק
chenek
so the מדיחים madi'achim clearly is weightier than the נידחנים. nidachanim. And
if שריפה sereifa trumps חנק chenek because we know up here from
בת כהן, bas kohein, it's going to trump הרג hereg as well.
Okay, so ומה חנק שחמור מסייף, u-mah chenek she-chamur mi-sayif, so חנק
chenek is weightier than סייף sayif because the מדיח madi'ach is worse
than the נידח, nidach, שריפה חמורה ממנו, sereifa chamura mimenu, and שריפה's
sereifa worse than
חנק, chenek, so סייף קל וחומר sayif kal va-chomer שכן she-ken certainly
by סייף. sayif.
Okay, so that's how we get it. שריפה's sereifa weightier than these
two because of בת כהן, bas kohein, and it's weightier than הרג
hereg because we rank הרג hereg below חנק chenek based on the
עיר הנדחת, ir nidachas, the מדיח madi'ach and the נידח. nidach. Okay,
so that's how we got שריפה sereifa weightier than those. Now we're
going to do סקילה skilah, weightier than these two.
Okay, so סקילה חמורה מחנק. skilah chamura mi-chenek. סקילה skilah is weightier
than חנק. chenek. So שכן ניתנה למגדף ולעובד עבודת כוכבים. she-ken nitnah
l'megadef u-l'oved avodas kochavim. Because come on, סקילה's skilah for a מגדף
megadef and עובד עבודה זרה. oved avoda zara. ומה חומרא כמאן? u-mah
chamura k'aman? And its weightiness is for that sin. So אדרבה חנק
חמור, adderaba chenek chamur, חנק chenek should be weightier שכן ניתן למכה
אביו ואמו, she-ken nitan l'makeh aviv ve-imo, ומה חומרא שכן הוקש כבודם
לכבוד המקום. u-mah chamura she-ken hukash kvodam l'kvod ha-makom. Alright but okay,
חנק chenek is for smiting a parent and that's pretty weighty, that's
comparable to the honor of God. But after all so how do
you know that סקילה's skilah weightier than חנק? chenek? That's an easy
one. Back to the בת... bas... ארוסה arusah versus a נשואה nesu'ah
of the בת ישראל. bas yisrael. So מדחף רחמנא לארוסה בת ישראל
מכלל נשואה בת ישראל מחנק לסקילה. mi-dhaft rachmana l'arusah bas yisrael miklal
nesu'ah bas yisrael me-chenek l'skilah. שמע מינה סקילה חמורה. shma mina skilah
chamurah. Nope,
from the ארוסה arusah versus נשואה nesuah you know that סקילה skilah
is חמורה. chamurah. Okay, so how do we know here that, let's
use a different color, how do we know here that סקילה skilah
is weightier than חנק? chenek? Cause of ארוסה arusah versus נשואה. nesuah.
Okay now, how are we going to know that סקילה skilah is
weightier than הרג? hereg? Okay, so שמע מינה סקילה חמורה, shma mina
skilah chamurah, סקילה חמורה מסייף שכן ניתנה למגדף. skilah chamurah misayaf sheken
nitnah l'megadef. Okay,
we're going to start with assumption סקילה skilah is weightier because the
מגדף megadef gets it and the idolater? אדרבה סייף חמור שכן ניתנה
לאנשי עיר הנידחת. aderabah sayaf chamur sheken nitnah l'anshei ir hanidachas. What
do you mean? סייף sayaf is worse, that you wipe out the
whole city of idolators. ומה חומרא שכן ממונם אבד? umah chumrah sheken
mamonam avad? And it's a pretty weighty punishment because you're also destroying
their property. אמרת? amarta?
No, we're going to go back to the מדיח madiach and the
נידח. nidach. וכי איזה כוח המרובה? vechi eizeh koach hamerubah? Which is
weightier? כוח המדיח או כוח הנידח? koach hamadiach o koach hanidach? The
one who pushes or the one who's pushed?
הוי אומר כוח המדיח, hevei omer koach hamadiach. the one who pushes.
וקל וחומר ומה חנק שחמור מסייף? vekal vachomer umah chenek shechamur misayaf?
Because we know that this is חנק chenek is weightier than הרג?
hereg? Because this is what the מדיח עיר הנידחת madiach ir hanidachas
gets and this is what the עיר הנידחת ir hanidachas gets. So
that tells us that, and we obviously assume that the מדיח madiach
gets something worse. So we know that חנק chenek is worse than
הרג. hereg. Okay, and once חנק chenek is worse than הרג hereg
and סקילה skilah is worse than חנק chenek based on this, so
סקילה skilah is also going to be worse than הרג. hereg. Okay,
because this just creates that hierarchy. So then we're just going to
extend it. Okay. So ומה חנק שחמור מסייף, umah chenek shechamur misayaf,
חנק chenek is weightier than סייף sayaf because of the מדיח עיר
הנידחת, madiach ir hanidachas, סקילה חמורה הימנו. skilah chamurah heimenu. סקילה skilah
is weightier than it. סייף הקל לא כל שכן? sayaf hakal lo
kol sheken? So certainly that it is going to, so certainly סקילה
skilah will be worse than סייף. sayaf. If סקילה skilah is worse
than חנק, chenek, סקילה skilah is going to be worse than סייף
sayaf because of this, this already ranks these two. And that's going
to now do our last job. Our last job is going to
be showing how do we know that חנק chenek is weightier than
הרג? hereg? And that's that's what we're working off of the מדיח
madiach and the נידח. nidach. Once we got that it allowed us
to do what we needed to do by
סקילה. skilah
Okay. So חנק חמור מסייף. chenek chamur misayaf. How do you know
חנק chenek is weightier than סייף? sayaf? שכן ניתנה למכה אביו ואמו.
sheken nitnah l'makeh aviv v'imo. So first we're going to start with,
well חנק chenek you get for hitting a father.
ומה חומרא כדאמרינן אדרבה סייף חמור שכן ניתנה לאנשי עיר הנידחת. umah
chumrah kid'amrinan aderabah sayaf chamur sheken nitnah l'anshei ir hanidachas. ומה חומרא
שכן ממונם אבד? umah chumrah sheken mamonam avad? What do you mean?
סייף sayaf you wipe out the city. אמרת וכי איזה כוח מרובה
כוח המדיח? amarta vechi eizeh koach merubah koach hamadiach? What?
This was a?
This was an easy one. Right. כוח הנידח כוח המדיח, koach hanidach
koach hamadiach, הוי אומר hevei omer, כוח המדיח. koach ha'madiach. ותניא מדיח
עיר הנידחת בסקילה. v'tanyah madiach ir hanidachas b'skilah. Now we're going to
actually quote the source. מדיח עיר הנידחת בסקילה, madiach ir hanidachas b'skilah,
that we referenced earlier when we were dealing with the רבנן. rabanan.
רבי שמעון אומר בחנק. Rabbi Shimon omer b'chenek. אין חנק. ein chenek.
Okay, so we did it. We ranked it for רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was the easy one by the way.
Once he put שריפה sereifa here, then you got שריפה sreifah weightier
than these two. You got סקילה skilah. weightier than חנק. chenek. You
got most of your system worked out. Okay, except he had חנק
chenek worse than הרג, hereg, which was a little surprising, but that's
because of the מדיח עיר הנידחת madiach ir hanidachas and the נידחים.
nidachim. Okay. So that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. All right.
And then what's הרג? hereg?
What are the two different opinions of what סובר sover really?
Of what who gets?
מדיח. madiach. So why does one say a subverter of the city?
מדיח? madiach? Yeah, we haven't learned it out. It's based on how
they read the פסוקים. psukim. We haven't learned it out yet. Okay.
Okay, yes. Okay. So for the רבנן rabanan we've got
סקילה skilah
שריפה sreifah and then הרג חנק. hereg chenek. And for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon we have שריפה
סקילה, sreifah skilah,
oops,
סקילה skilah
and then חנק
הרג. chenek hereg. Okay, each one of them gets reversed. Fine.
Is there something back that we can learn out from עיר הנידחת?
ir hanidachas? עיר הנידחת ir hanidachas something like, I don't know what
it's something like that?
The analogy for? No?
I'm not sure what you're referring to. Okay. All right. So now
the גמרא gemara is like this.
מרגלא בפומיה... margla b'pumeh... where am I?
מרגלא בפומיה דרב יוחנן. margla b'pumeh d'Rav Yochanan. It was a pearl
in the mouth of רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, means like a favorite
saying of his. רש"י Rashi says it means that it was something
that he did not have from a, you know, that he did
not have from a tradition like from a משנה mishna or ברייתא.
braisa. It was his own saying, something he sort of, you know,
developed himself. It was a pearl in his mouth was nice phrase.
מרגלא בפומיה margla b'pumeh is used in later rabbinic literature like מרגלא
בפומיה. margla b'pumeh. Okay, anyway. מרגלא בפומיה דרב יוחנן נערה מאורסה בת
כהן שזינתה בסקילה. margla b'pumeh d'Rav Yochanan na'ara me'urasa bas Kohen shezinsa
b'skilah. We've got a נערה מאורסה na'ara me'urasa who does, who's also
בת כהן, bas Kohen, she committed, okay, that's this one here, the
נערה מאורסה, na'ara me'urasa, the ארוסה arusah who's a בת כהן. bas
Kohen. So is she going to get סקילה skilah or שריפה? sreifah?
That is the question. one of the major, sort of, locuses of
the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן. Rabanan. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says every בת כהן bas kohen gets שריפה, sreifah,
שריפה sreifah is weightier, the חכמים Chachamim say no no no no
no, only the נשואה nesuah gets שריפה, sreifah, the ארוסה arusah gets
סקילה, skilah, okay, and that allows סקילה skilah to remain weightier. Okay,
so that's where he's going to start. נערה מאורסה בת כהן שזינתה
בסקילה. Naarah Meorasah bas kohen she'zinseh biskilah. So she would get סקילה.
skilah. ורבי שמעון אומר בשריפה. V'Rabbi Shimon omer besreifah. She would get
שריפה, sreifah, that's exactly their debate, how to read the פסוקים psukim
and therefore which is weightier, שריפה sreifah or סקילה. skilah. Okay. Similarly,
זינתה מאביה. Zinseh me'aviha. Let's say, let's say this נערה מאורסה naarah
meorasah actually commits adultery with her own father. Okay? Now the
sin of sleeping with a daughter or daughter sleeping with a father
is שריפה. sreifah. So she is not a בת כהן, bas kohen,
she's just your standard נערה מאורסה naarah meorasah which everybody agrees gets
סקילה, skilah, but she then went ahead and did this act of
adultery
with her father, which gets שריפה. sreifah. So that's a person who
did two sins, you give them the weightier one. Which would be
the weightier one?
Well, it depends on who you are.
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, she would get שריפה sreifah the same way
when she moves into the בת כהן bas kohen category, you know,
she's a normal בת ישראל, bas Yisrael, she's a normal person who
gets סקילה skilah but she's now also a בת כהן bas kohen
and she gets שריפה, sreifah, so she gets שריפה, sreifah, that's for
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So similarly when she moves into the father
category, she gets שריפה, sreifah, that's the weightier one. But for the
חכמים, Chachamim, the סקילה skilah always remains the weightier one. So, you
know, even as a בת כהן bas kohen she gets סקילה skilah
and even with her father she would get סקילה. skilah. סקילה skilah
remains the weightier one. Let's just read the line then take a
question. So, זינתה מאביה
בסקילה.
Zinseh
me'aviha biskilah. Similarly, סקילה skilah would be the weightier one for being
a נערה מאורסה. naarah meorasah. רבי שמעון אומר בשריפה Rabbi Shimon omer
besreifah and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says בשריפה. besreifah. מאי קמשמע לן?
Mai kamashma lan? What's this teaching us? רבנן נשואה יצאת לשריפה ולא
ארוסה, Rabanan nesuah yatza'at lisreifah v'lo arusah, that once the תורה Torah
says שריפה sreifah here, the rabbis limit it to the נשואה. nesuah.
They keep the ארוסה arusah at the סקילה skilah level because for
them that's the weightier punishment. רבי שמעון אחת ארוסה ואחת נשואה יצאת
לשריפה, Rabbi Shimon achas arusah v'achas nesuah yatza'at lisreifah, and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon they both get
שריפה. sreifah. וטעמא מאי? V'ta'ama mai? Why? משום דלרבנן סקילה חמורה ולרבי
שמעון שריפה חמורה. Mishum d'le'Rabanan skilah chamura v'le'Rabbi Shimon sreifah chamura. Because
for the רבנן, Rabanan, סקילה skilah is weightier so we have to,
we can't have שריפה sreifah here get, you know, replace סקילה, skilah,
and for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon שריפה sreifah is weightier. נפקא מינה
למי שנתחייב שתי מיתות בית דין Nafka mina le'mi shenischayeiv shtei misos
beis din and in general the implication is, somebody is deserving two
punishments, נידון בחמורה nidon b'chamura
and they get the weightier one. So in a way you could
think about that that's what happened here. בת ישראל Bas Yisrael gets
סקילה. skilah. Now she deserves a second punishment, not really, it's the
same sin, but you know, a second punishment for a בת כהן.
bas kohen. So if you think that שריפה sreifah is weightier, then
שריפה sreifah will take, will trump. That's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says.
If you think that סקילה skilah is weightier, then no, it's just
going to remain at סקילה. skilah. And the same would be true
if this בת ישראל bas Yisrael would have her act of adultery
would be with her father. Okay, which is a sin of שריפה.
sreifah. So רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, שריפה, sreifah, you know, wins out
because it's weightier and for and for the רבנן, Rabanan, סקילה skilah
remains the weightier one and she gets סקילה. skilah. Yes, Jenna you
had a question.
I was just going to say, she still gets kind of the
punishment of disgracing her father's
house,
even when her father was the disgracer? Yeah, I mean that's true,
that's assumed to be the case. Although would it matter in that
case because both the בת כהן bas kohen status is a שריפה
sreifah status and the sex with the father is a שריפה? sreifah?
So there's no, but the ארוסה arusah versus נשואה, nesuah, the reason
we're saying ארוסה arusah is worse is because of בית אביה.
beis aviha. Well, that's true, yeah. You've already disgraced, right. That's true,
yeah, that's a good point. That's a good point. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. All right, see that one wasn't,
that one's better than we thought it was going to go. I
thought it was going to be, anyway. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Oh my god you should try to do the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi on this, it's impossible. Okay anyway the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay. Now מאי רבי שמעון? Mai Rabbi Shimon? Where is this רבי
שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? This, where do we see them meaning we're all
saying that their debate, the crux of their debate is around reading
these פסוקים, psukim, but we haven't seen them explicitly debate these פסוקים.
psukim. So here we're going to see it.
דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Braitah, רבי שמעון אומר שתי
כללות נאמרו בבת כהן. Rabbi Shimon omer shtei kelalos neemru be'vas kohen.
So there are two different categories of a בת כהן, bas kohen,
a נשואה nesuah and an ארוסה. arusah. So the גמרא Gemara says
בבת כהן ולא בבת ישראל? Be'vas kohen v'lo be'vas Yisrael? What do
you mean? Only a בת כהן? bas kohen? A בת ישראל bas
Yisrael also, there's a נשואה nesuah and an ארוסה arusah and two
different levels of punishment. Now אימא אף בבת כהן, Eima af be'vas
kohen, meaning okay fine, but the starting point for a בת כהן
bas kohen is the same as the point of departure for a
בת ישראל, bas Yisrael, that you would start with חנק chenek for
נשואה nesuah and סקילה skilah for an ארוסה. arusah. That would be
your starting point for everybody, בת ישראל bas Yisrael or בת כהן.
bas kohen. Okay. So that was your starting point, והוציא הכתוב נשואה
מכלל נשואה וארוסה מכלל ארוסה. V'hotzia hakasuv nesuah miklal nesuah v'arusah miklal
arusah. So this was our starting point and then when we're dealing
with a בת כהן, bas kohen, it said oh, a נשואה בת
כהן nesuah bas kohen is different than a נשואה בת ישראל, nesuah
bas Yisrael, שריפה sreifah rather than חנק. chenek.
And and and an ארוסה בת כהן arusah bas kohen is different
than an ארוסה בת ישראל, arusah bas Yisrael, it's שריפה sreifah rather
than סקילה. skilah. So the starting point... It took her out of
both of those categories of חנק chenek and סקילה skila and replaced
both of those things with שריפה. sreifa. Okay? Everybody with me?
והוציא הכתוב נשואה מכלל נשואה. vehotzi hakatuv nesua miklal nesua. You hear?
Yes, yes!
But how do
we know that it applies to...?
That's just his read of the פסוק. pasuk. It says ובת כהן
בשריפה. ubas Kohen besreifa. But we start with this is the story
about ישראל, Yisrael, and then we say שריפה. sreifa. Well, that says
the נשואה's nesua going to be different and the ארוסה's arusa going
to be different and it's not going to be חנק chenek and
סקילה, skila, it's going to be שריפה sreifa for each.
Okay? והוציא הכתוב נשואה מכלל נשואה וארוסה מכלל ארוסה. vehotzi hakatuv nesua
miklal nesua vearusa miklal arusa. מה כשהוציא הכתוב נשואה מכלל נשואה להחמיר.
mah keshehotzi hakatuv nesua miklal nesua lehachmir. So the same way obviously
the this, שריפה sreifa is obviously a worse punishment than
חנק. chenek. אף כשהוציא הכתוב ארוסה מכלל ארוסה להחמיר. af keshehotzi hakatuv
arusa miklal arusa lehachmir. So clearly שריפה sreifa is going to also
be worse than סקילה. skila. בת כהן bat Kohen is going to
be worse than בת ישראל. bat Yisrael. Once you assume that this
applies to both categories of נשואה nesua and ארוסה, arusa, this tells
you that שריפה sreifa is weightier than סקילה skila because that's what
we've been saying all along. It's just the ברייתא baraisa now is
just spelling it out. Okay, now, now that we're talking about that,
that tells us our basic principle that this is talking about both
types of women. Good,
and that implicitly therefore שריפה's sreifa worse than סקילה. skila. Now we're
going to say some other things about a בת כהן. bat Kohen.
Okay?
וזוממי... vezomemei... where are we? להחמיר. lehachmir. זוממי נשואה בת כהן בכלל
זוממי נשואה בת ישראל וזוממי ארוסה בת כהן בכלל זוממי ארוסה בת
ישראל. zomemei nesua bat Kohen bikelal zomemei nesua bat Yisrael vezomemei arusa
bat Kohen bikelal zomemei arusa bat Yisrael. So the פסוק pasuk says
את אביה
היא מחללת באש תשרף.
es aviha hi mechaleles
ba'eish tisareif. Okay? את אביה היא מחללת באש
תשרף.
es aviha hi mechaleles
ba'eish tisareif. So it's תשרף, tisareif, so it's היא בשריפה ולא
זוממיה בשריפה. hi besreifa velo zomemeiha besreifa. So because there is a
particular weight of the fact of מחללת בית אביה, mechaleles beis aviha,
it's somehow seen like, and this is strange, because you know, whatever,
עדים זוממים edim zomemim you always just attach the same thing to
the זוממים zomemim even though they didn't do it themselves, right? So,
you know, I don't know if a murderer is שופך דם, shofeich
dam, the זוממים zomemim aren't שופכי דם, shofchei dam, but you give
them the same punishment. But here it's understood that if they're זוממים,
zomemim, people that try to lie and to say witnesses that she
did it, so while you attach to them the sin of adultery,
you don't attach to them the sin of מחללת בית אביה. mechaleles
beis aviha. I don't really understand it. Only she gets the punishment
of שריפה sreifa for מחללת בית אביה. mechaleles beis aviha. The זוממים
zomemim would get the punishment as if she weren't a בת כהן.
bat Kohen. You strip the special status of a בת כהן bat
Kohen to apply to the זוממים. zomemim. Maybe it's something of a
male and a female thing. No, I'm serious. Like most sins, right,
I mean, you know, it doesn't matter who the perpetrator is, man
or woman. I mean, even a sin of adultery which requires a
man and a woman, it wouldn't, you know, the sin and the
punishment doesn't matter which role you're playing. Okay, whereas this can only
be something that the woman can be מחללת בית אביה. mechaleles beis
aviha. The adulterer wasn't מחלל mechalel the father's house, if you think
about it, right? So she was מחללת mechaleles the father's house but
the adulterer wasn't. So even though they don't know who the adulterer
was and they're just lying and coming to testify falsely against her,
you treat them in the man's role and not in the woman's
role. And therefore if they're זוממים zomemim here, they get the punishment
that the non-בת כהן bat Kohen would get because this is also
the same punishment like that the man would get. Okay, so זוממי
בת כהן zomemei bat Kohen of a נשואה nesua gets the בת
ישראל bat Yisrael punishment of a נשואה. nesua. And the זוממי בת
כהן zomemei bat Kohen of an ארוסה arusa gets the בת ישראל
bat Yisrael punishment, which would be remove her special כהן Kohen status,
you know, and apply that. So let me just read that again.
Okay, זוממי נשואה בת כהן בכלל זוממי נשואה בת ישראל, zomemei nesua
bat Kohen bikelal zomemei nesua bat Yisrael, they would get the same
punishment as if they would have been זוממים zomemim about a בת
ישראל. bat Yisrael. וזוממי ארוסה בת כהן בכלל זוממי ארוסה בת ישראל.
vezomemei arusa bat Kohen bikelal zomemei arusa bat Yisrael. Okay, yeah, you
had a question, Michael?
I mean, it's interesting you'd say you don't know the adulterer, but
you have to know enough to know that
he was Jewish, you know, things like that.
Right, it's true, but we still have those cases. Okay, תנו רבנן.
tanu rabbanan. So that's another little interesting parenthesis about the בת כהן
bat Kohen that it's only about her, not about... by the way,
we haven't discussed this either, I just told you, but the punishment
to her would not apply to him, the man, and also wouldn't
apply to the זוממים. zomemim. Okay, it's a special status that only
applies to her.
Why the זוממים? zomemim?
Yeah, whatever. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Okay, ובת איש כהן כי תחל
לזנות. uvat ish kohen ki teichel liznos. Okay, now that we're going
to talk about בת כהן, bat Kohen, this is so much the
crux of these debates, let's talk about this פסוק pasuk a little
bit more. Okay, ובת כהן, uvat Kohen, איש כהן, ish Kohen, כי
תחל. ki teichel. יכול אפילו חיללה את השבת, yachol afilu chillela es
hashabbos, okay, כי תחל ki teichel and את אביה היא מחללת. es
aviha hi mechaleles. It's in... and what does the first תחל... teichel...
I obviously, okay, but what does the first תחל... teichel... does the
first תחל teichel mean begin? Or is it also echoing when she
desecrates לזנות? liznos? Because את אביה היא מחללת. es aviha hi mechaleles.
So anyway, we're bracketing for a moment the word לזנות liznos and
saying what's the first תחל? teichel? Maybe it's talking about חילול שבת
chilul Shabbos and maybe that brings desecration to her father's house. יכול
אפילו חיללה את השבת תלמוד לומר לזנות. Yachol afilu chilila es hashabbos
talmud lomar liznos. Okay. והחילול שבזנות הכתוב מדבר, v'hachillul shebiznus hakatuv medaber,
a desecration that comes through fornication, through sex. Okay. יכול אפילו פנויה,
yachol afilu pnuyah, now maybe לזנות liznos means even the reasonable read
of the פסוקים, psukim, right, as the פסוקים psukim just say כי
תחל לזנות, ki techel liznos, she is a daughter, it doesn't say
and the פסוקים psukim usually tell you when she's ארוסה arusah or
נשואה. nesuah. Okay, maybe it just means maybe that's a shame, a
dishonored, the כהן Kohen house is supposed to be this higher level
etc. יכול אפילו פנויה, yachol afilu pnuyah, נאמר כאן אביה ונאמר להלן
אביה. ne'emar kan aviha v'ne'emar lehalan aviha. It says by the את
אביה, es aviha, what was it, by the ארוסה arusah here? We
had it before, by לזנות בית אביה.
liznos
beis aviha.
Okay, by the by the ארוסה arusah it says לזנות בית אביה.
liznos beis aviha. לזנות
בית אביה, liznos
beis
aviha,
it also has לזנות liznos by the way and אביה היא מחללת.
aviha hi mechalelet. So מה להלן זנות עם זיקת הבעל, mah lehalan
znus im zikas habaal, there the תורה Torah is explicit right when
it talks about the ארוסה arusah that it means and it says
מאורסה לאיש me'orasah l'ish that she has a relationship to her husband,
אף כאן זנות עם זיקת הבעל af kan znus im zikas habaal
here too. So we know it's זנות znus because it's לזנות liznos
and based on the אביה aviha and the comparison of לזנות liznos
and בית אביה beis aviha etc. we know it means she's married.
Okay. Now we don't know is she נשואה nesuah or ארוסה, arusah,
that's the debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים. Chachamim.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says fine, that's all we know she's married
and she had sex, so therefore it's I don't know it's everybody
נשואה nesuah or ארוסה. arusah. The rabbis to accommodate their way-ness of
סקילה skilah have to limit this to נשואה. nesuah. Okay, but that's
to accommodate their position. Okay. Now
so it says like this, או אינו אומר אביה אלא להוציא את
כל אדם, o eino omer aviha ela l'hotzi es kol adam, oh
no maybe it means maybe it means את אביה היא מחללת, et
aviha hi mechalelet, maybe it means like that that idea we had
before that that case we had before, maybe it means she actually
had intercourse with her father. Okay, maybe that's the case of the
פסוק pasuk that she had intercourse with her father. Okay, no כשהוא
אומר היא מחללת, keshu omer hi mechalelet, she is desecrating her father's
household and not sort of like what Jenna said her father isn't
the one desecrating his own household, she's desecrating. הרי אומר כל אדם
אמור, harei omer kol adam amur, so it means that she's having
sex with somebody else. היכן אני מקיים אביה, heichan ani mekayem aviha,
so what's the purpose of אביה aviha therefore if נאמר כאן אביה
ונאמר להלן אביה ne'emar kan aviha v'ne'emar lehalan aviha again to link
it to the נערה מאורסה. na'arah me'orasah. מה להלן זנות עם זיקת
הבעל אף כאן זנות עם זיקת הבעל. mah lehalan znus im zikas
habaal af kan znus im zikas habaal. Okay, so we have לזנות,
liznos, we have it means she's doing זנות, znus, אביה aviha links
it to the אביה aviha here that she is a married woman.
Okay, אם מה להלן נערה והיא ארוסה אף כאן נערה והיא ארוסה.
im mah lehalan na'arah v'hi arusah af kan na'arah v'hi arusah. Now
as long as we're linking them, why don't we say against רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the רבנן, Rabbanan, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
it's both נשואה nesuah and ארוסה arusah right, the רבנן Rabbanan says
it's just נשואה nesuah to allow ארוסה arusah to remain סקילה. skilah.
But if we're linking it with אביה aviha and לזנות liznos and
so on, why not say this is only talking about a נערה
מאורסה? na'arah me'orasah? That would be actually quite reasonable. The תורה Torah
elsewhere says את אביה et aviha like לזנות בית אביה, liznos beis
aviha, here it speaks about לזנות liznos and בית אביה, beis aviha,
so maybe let's just say that both of them is נערה מאורסה.
na'arah me'orasah. And you know why? Not just a word link, בית
אביה beis aviha means she hasn't yet moved out of her father's
house, she's not yet off and living with her husband as a
נשואה, nesuah, so the פשט pshat of בית אביה beis aviha would
be an ארוסה. arusah. So why no nobody says that that the
case of בת כהן bas Kohen is just an ארוסה, arusah, but
why not say it? Okay, so אם מה להלן נערה והיא ארוסה
אף כאן נערה והיא ארוסה, im mah lehalan na'arah v'hi arusah af
kan na'arah v'hi arusah, נערה ונשואה, na'arah u'nesuah, if she's a נערה
na'arah and she's a נשואה, nesuah, בוגרת, bogeres, or let's say she's
not a נערה, na'arah, let's say she's a בוגרת והיא ארוסה, bogeres
v'hi arusah, בוגרת ונשואה, bogeres u'nesuah, ואפילו היא זקנה מנין? v'afilu hi
zkenah minayin? So how do you know fine we sort of said
that פשט pshat is that this works of course with רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that it's talking about נערה מאורסה na'arah me'orasah right, that's
בית אביה beis aviha etc. How do you know to expand it
to talk about everything? And certainly the רבנן Rabbanan say it's talking
only about a נשואה. nesuah. תלמוד לומר ובת כהן כי תחל לזנות,
talmud lomar u'vas Kohen ki techel liznos, so מכל מקום, mikol makom,
okay, so the is that the extra ו, vav, ובת כהן? u'vas
Kohen? Is it the fact that it's described as a בת כהן
bas Kohen and it doesn't describe her as a נערה na'arah right?
Because every other place the תורה Torah says כי תהיה נערה מאורסה
לאיש ki tihyeh na'arah me'orasah l'ish or whatever it always starts with
describing her as a נערה. na'arah. Here it starts by describing her
as a בת כהן bas Kohen which is pretty generic because she's
always everybody's a mother's child so
everyone everyone is and whatever however old she is she's always a
בת כהן. bas Kohen. Okay, so anyway that's how we know that
it's applying so because we have the case that she's married based
on the link to נערה מאורסה, na'arah me'orasah, we have the בת
כהן bas Kohen that tells us it's talking about any any marriage,
any age, that's what applies this is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it
applies to all. cases of a בת כהן. Bat Kohen. Let's read
one more line. Look at that, ha! We actually finished the דף,
daf, let's read one more line. בת כהן, Bat Kohen, אין לי
אלא שנישאת לכהן, ein li ela she-nisas le-Kohen, and I only know
if she's married to a כהן. Kohen. נישאת ללוי לישראל לעובד כוכבים
לחלל לממזר לנתין מנין? Nisas le-Levi, le-Yisrael, le-Akum, le-Chalal, le-Mamzer, le-Nasin, minayin?
How do I know if she's only married to a כהן? Kohen?
It doesn't say that she...
I know. So רש"י Rashi says והוה אמינא ve-hava mina or the
גמרא Gemara says how do I know that? But somehow maybe because
it's about her status of a כהן, Kohen, maybe I would think
that if she was married to ישראל Yisrael she wouldn't have the
full בת כהן Bas Kohen status. It's a funny הוה אמינא. hava
mina. Okay, the same way it was a הוה אמינא hava mina
we're talking about חילול שבת. chillul Shabbos. We're just putting out the
הוה אמינא hava mina to reject it. How do I know even
if she's married to a כהן, Kohen, a לוי, Levi, I mean
a לוי ישראל? Levi Yisrael? Now נתין Nasin and ממזר Mamzer are
interesting, at least ממזר Mamzer you could say, but עובד כוכבים Akum
is interesting. עובד כוכבים, Akum, it's not even a binding marriage. Okay,
so we'll have to worry about all of this. But anyway...
what about a כותי? Cuthite? What?
It seems like it... we'll see about it tomorrow. Anyway, תוספתא Tosefta
says different. Yeah, some have כותי Kuti or whatever. But כותי Kuti
is finally... that's always a question whether that's a... whether that's a
censorship. Anyway, we'll worry about it tomorrow. Okay, how do I know
even if she's not married to a כהן, Kohen, even if her
marriage is באיסור? be-issur? Okay, as long as it's binding, right? A
marriage to a ממזר Mamzer is באיסור, be-issur, but it's binding. A
marriage to like a relative isn't even binding. But how do I
know any state of being married? Of course the non-Jew is shocking,
because the non-Jew we would assume of course is not binding. Anyway,
תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ובת איש כהן, u-vas ish Kohen, אף על
פי שאינה כהנת. af al pi she-eina Kohenes. Even though her marriage
some degree removes... it's always fascinating the גמרא's Gemara phrase of כהנת,
Kohenes, right? It's usually somebody... women are usually defined in reference to
their father: בת ישראל, Bat Yisrael, בת כהן, Bat Kohen, and so
on. Right, to what degree sometimes there's actually a הלכה, halacha, for
example, that you could give like the מתנות כהונה matnas kehuna of
like זרוע לחיים וקיבה, zroa le-chayayim ve-keiva, you could actually give it
to a בת כהן. Bat Kohen. It doesn't have to give it
only to a כהן. Kohen. Sometimes a woman actually has a status...
is a recognized status of a כהנת. Kohenes. So here it's sort
of saying, here it's enough that she's a בת כהן. Bat Kohen.
We're not concerned that her personally she has a full כהן Kohen
status, which could be seen somehow to be compromised by the fact
that she's married to a non-כהן. Kohen. As long as she's a
בת כהן, Bat Kohen, whatever that her her own personal identity is,
how purely Kohanic her personal identity is, she's a בת כהן, Bat
Kohen, and that's it. So it was a very funny הוה אמינא.
hava mina. Okay, but anyway we'll continue... we'll continue with this tomorrow.
Yes, one last question?
What about a כהן Kohen that he marries someone he's not supposed
to, does he become a חלל?
chalal? No, the כהן Kohen when he does a forbidden marriage, the
children are חללים, chalalim, but his personal status is not compromised.