Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is פ"ג, Peh Gimmel,
Sanhedrin 83, we pick up at the bottom of פ"ב עמוד ב',
Peh Bet amud Bet, two lines from the bottom, and we are
dealing with the question about the statement in the משנה, mishna, which
is listing various things of קנאים פוגעים בו kanaim pogim bo and
had one example, although it didn't put it in the קנאים פוגעים
בו kanaim pogim bo category, but of a כהן kohen who does
the עבודה avoda when he is טמא, tamei, and it says that
his colleagues the כהנים kohanim would take him out and crack his
head open. And the question is: is that evidence that there's a
sense of a חיוב מיתה בידי שמים chiyuv misa bidei shamayim here,
that there's a deserving of the death penalty in heaven or else
we wouldn't have license to do that, or is it evidence that
it isn't, because if God is going to take care of him,
why do we need to take care of him? And the גמרא's
Gemara inclination is very much the former, that the fact that we're
doing these extra-legal or allowing people to be killed or so on
shows that at some level we think that they are deserving of
death either primarily in heaven. So now the גמרא Gemara is going
to challenge that. Let's
take a look. איתיבי, Eitivi, I will challenge this. Here we have
a
ברייתא Breita
that teaches the following. היוצק והבולל והפותת המולח המניף המגיש והמסדר את
השולחן, Hayotzek vehabolel vehapotet hamoleach hamenif hamagish vehamessader et hashulchan, so these
are all different various עבודות avodot that are not גמר עבודה, gmar
avoda, that are a middle stage. And the basic principle about all
of them is that you are not going to be חייב chayav
when you do it outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash with a
קרבן korban where there's an איסור של שחוטי חוץ issur of shchutei
chutz of שחיטת shechting קרבנות korbanot outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
throwing the blood, burning the fats, or burning incense, but all of
those which are based on פסוקים psukim are a final act of
service, of offering the item, the קרבן, korban, and therefore you're not
חייב chayav if you do any intermediary act, something that's not called
as an עבודה תמה, avoda tama, not a complete act, a completed
act. So what is this? Pouring the oil on a מנחה, mincha,
הבולל habolel mixing the oil, הפותת hapotet after the מנחה mincha has
been baked, breaking it into pieces,
והמולח vehamoleach you put the salt on it before you offer it
up on the altar, המניף hamenif you wave it, that actually happens
before you put the salt on it, המגיש hamagish touching the מנחה
mincha to the corner of the altar, והמסדר את השולחן vehamessader et
hashulchan putting the bread on the table even though that would think
maybe that is, you're putting it on the table, but the actual
offering of that is the burning of the incense that was on
the table once every week on שבת. Shabbat. המטיב את הנרות Hameitiv
et hanerot cleaning out the נרות nerot of the מנורה, menorah, not
the lighting of the מנורה, menorah, you're actually exempt for the lighting
of the מנורה menorah for a different reason because somewhat surprisingly ironically
that's not an עבודה. avoda. והקומץ Vehakomet if you take the handbreadth
of the מנחה mincha back to the מנחה, mincha, והמקבל הדם vehamikabel
hadam if you catch the blood of the קרבן korban because you're
not actually throwing the blood yet, it's not finished. All of those
things בחוץ פטור, bechutz patur, if you do it outside the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash you are exempt, you do not get the punishment
of שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, and you
which would be כרת karet so you don't get כרת, karet, ואין
חייבין עליהם ve-ein chayavin aleihem and also because these are intermediary stages
you are not liable for, top of פ"ג עמוד א' Peh Gimmel
amud Alef now, לא משום זרות ולא משום טומאה, lo mishum zarut
velo mishum tumah,
not if a זר, zar, a non-כהן, kohen, does the עבודה. avoda.
So a non-כהן kohen who does the עבודה avoda at the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash is also חייב מיתה בידי שמים, chayav misa bidei
shamayim, but that is but again because this is an intermediary stage
you are not
חייב מיתה chayav misa ולא משום טומאה velo mishum tumah if a
כהן kohen who is טמא tamei does the עבודה, avoda, our question
about what type of liability there is there, so you are not
liable for whatever the liability is with this intermediary עבודה. avoda. ולא
משום מחוסר בגדים Velo mishum mechussar bgadim or the violation of doing
עבודה avoda if you're not wearing the בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, ולא
משום רחיצת ידים ורגלים velo mishum rachatzat yadayim veraglayim and also the
violation of doing the עבודה avoda if you have not washed your
hands if you're a כהן kohen and feet. Okay, so in all
of those cases you are not liable. Now most of the things
on the list we assume are either חייב כרת chayav karet or
חייב מיתה, chayav misa, so that should really seem to answer, meaning
if you were to do an עבודה תמה avoda tama if you
were to do a complete עבודה, avoda, and that should seem to
answer this question about the status of doing the עבודה avoda if
you are טמא, tamei, which is what the גמרא Gemara says. It
says like this: it says המקטיר חייב, hamaktir chayav, so if you
were actually to offer something up, not do an intermediary עבודה, avoda,
but throw the blood, burn something on the altar, you would be
חייב. chayav. So what חיוב chiyuv are we talking about? What is
the context here of the
חיוב? chiyuv? מאי לאו מיתה? Mai lav misa? Presumably it's talking about
מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim because mostly what we're talking about
here
is מיתה misa or כרת. karet. מאי לאו מיתה? Mai lav misa?
לא בלאו. Lo belav. No, it just means a negative prohibition, just
because it's in this list does not prove. that it is חייב
מיתה chayav misah the case of doing the עבודה avodah if you're
טמא. tamei. So the גמרא gemara says, one minute, that doesn't really
work. אלא זר נמי לאזהרה? ela zar nami le-azharah? So do you
think therefore like the other things on this list, when we're talking
about what it means to be חייב, chayav, you know we're only
if you did an עבודה תמה avodah tamah we're only talking about
a simple negative prohibition? דכתיב והזר הקרב יומת, de-chasiv ve-zar karev yumas,
that's explicit that the non כהן kohein who does the עבודה avodah
is חייב מיתה. chayav misah. So clearly other things on this list
are חייב מיתה, chayav misah, so isn't the same true about בידי
שמים, bidei shamayim, you know isn't the same true about the טומאה?
tumah? So the גמרא gemara says, no, הא כדיתיה והא כדיתיה. ha
kidiseih ve-ha kidiseih. Each one based on what the prohibition is. Most
of the things on the list are כרת kares or חייב מיתה,
chayav misah, but when we're dealing with the issue about טמא, tamei,
maybe we're only dealing with the simple negative prohibition. That's the response
back. Obviously all of the evidence is pointing to the idea that
it is חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav misah bidei shamayim. So now
the גמרא gemara is not giving up. So גמרא gemara says like
this, מכלל דיוצק ובולל לאו נמי לא? mikhlal de-yotzek u-bolel lav nami
lo? So one minute, so that would mean that if we're talking
only about a simple negative prohibition for even when you do a
final עבודה, avodah, that when you do one of these intermediary עבודות
avodas like pouring the oil or mixing it, you wouldn't even transgress
a negative prohibition? There would be no transgression? Meaning we assumed that
this ברייתא braisa was saying that if you didn't do a final
עבודה, avodah, you don't get כרת kares or מיתה, misah, but you
do get a negative prohibition.
But now if you're saying that we're only talking about a negative
prohibition even when it's something like offering it up, so then when
you do an intermediary thing you don't even violate anything? לאו נמי
לא? lav nami lo? והתניא ותנו ברייתא, ve-ha tanyuh ve-tanu braisa, אזהרה
ליוצק ובולל מנין? azharah le-yotzek u-bolel minayin? How do you know that
there is a negative prohibition for, you know, doing the pouring the
oil and mixing it up? And the context here very specifically is
when the כהן kohein is טמא. tamei. תלמוד לומר קדושים יהיו, talmud
lomar kedoshim yihyu, you shall be holy, ולא יחללו, ve-lo yechalelu, and
they shall not violate. And so that means and that's in the
context of doing the עבודה avodah and when they are טמא tamei
they are not considered to be קדושים. kedoshim. That is so and
whatever the exact לימוד limud is from that פסוק, pasuk, it's clear
that it's saying that there is a negative prohibition even for an
intermediary עבודה. avodah. So,
מדרבנן וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא? mi-drabbanan ve-kra asmachta be-alma? Oh maybe that's only
rabbinically, maybe it doesn't really mean that there's a biblical violation, maybe
the biblical violation is really only when you do the final עבודה
avodah and it's no more than a simple negative prohibition. But we're
not done. מתיבי, meisive, I will challenge this. We have an explicit
ברייתא braisa that says ואלו הן שבמיתה, ve-eilu hein she-be-misah, the following
things are חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav misah bidei shamayim. And in
that list it explicitly lists טמא ששימש, tamei she-shimmesh, a טמא tamei
a כהן kohein that does the עבודה avodah when he is טמא.
tamei. So it is explicit, which is of course which was implicit
by everything before. And the גמרא gemara says תיובתא, tiyufta, okay, that
is an absolute challenge on the argument that it is not חייב
מיתה. chayav misah. The כהן kohein is חייב מיתה בידי שמים chayav
misah bidei shamayim which gives us the license for the כהנים kohanim
to go out and to break his head open and also fits
the entire list that of everything on this list which are either
כרת kares or חייב מיתה בידי שמים chayav misah bidei shamayim which
are very similar, that in those types of things you would get
the כרת kares or מיתה בידי שמים misah bidei shamayim if you
did an עבודה תמה avodah tamah the sort of a final עבודה,
avodah, but not for an intermediary one which would be a simple
negative prohibition. Okay, so now we're going to continue. It says the
following. Now we're going to actually look at that entire ברייתא braisa
that lists all these things that a כהן kohein would be or
somebody would be חייב מיתה chayav misah for in the context of
עבודה, avodah, מיתה בידי שמים misah bidei shamayim or כרת. kares. גופא,
gufa, let's look at that entire entire text. ואלו שבמיתה: ve-eilu she-be-misah:
the following are מיתה. misah. האוכל את הטבל, ha-ochel es ha-tevel, a
non כהן kohein or actually anybody who eats
טבל, tevel, grain that has not had תרומה trumah taken from it.
וכהן טמא שאכל תרומה טהורה, ve-kohein tamei she-achal trumah tehorah, or if
a כהן kohein is טמא tamei when he eats תרומה, trumah, that
also is חייב מיתה בידי שמים chayav misah bidei shamayim because a
כהן kohein when he's טהור tahor can eat תרומה, trumah, but also
but if he's טמא tamei and the תרומה trumah is טהורה, tehorah,
then it is חייב מיתה. chayav misah. וזר שאכל את התרומה, ve-zar
she-achal es ha-trumah, and a non כהן kohein who eats תרומה. trumah.
So there's a consistency as we're seeing here a sort of equality
between a non כהן kohein doing it and a כהן kohein when
he is טמא. tamei. We were talking before about the עבודה. avodah.
Here it's talking about eating תרומה, trumah, excuse me. וזר ששימש, ve-zar
she-shimmesh, a non כהן kohein who does the עבודה avodah in the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. וטמא ששימש, ve-tamei she-shimmesh, and a כהן kohein
who's טמא tamei who does עבודה avodah in בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
again that equation. וטבול יום ששימש, u-tvul yom she-shimmesh, even if he's
not fully טמא, tamei, even if he has gone to the מקוה
mikvah it just has not been nightfall so his טומאה tumah has
not completely been taken away. There's still the residual טומאה. tumah. Even
that is considered טמא tamei and serving in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash is חייב מיתה. chayav misah. ומחוסר בגדים, u-mechussar begadim, if he's
not wearing בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah because then as we'll see then
he doesn't have the full status of a כהן. kohein. ומחוסר כפרה,
u-mechussar kapparah, and this really should have been listed before in the
טמא tamei discussion: somebody who was טמא tamei and that the טומאה
tumah ends not just with nightfall after going to the מקוה mikvah
but with a קרבן korban the next morning. And until he brings
like somebody like a זב zav for example. And until he brings
a קרבן korban the next morning, he is not a hundred percent
טהור. tahor. That person is also considered טמא. tamei.
ומחוסר כפרה, u'mechusar kapara, ושלא רחץ ידים ורגלים, v'shelo rachatz yadayim v'raglayim,
if he does not wash his hands and feet before doing the
עבודה. avoda. ושתויי יין, u'shtu'ei yayin, or if he's drunk. ופרועי ראש,
u'fru'ei rosh, or if his head has grown for more than thirty
days, his hair. All those are doing an עבודה avoda in a
way that violates, desecrates the עבודה, avoda, and also you are חייב
מיתה. chayav mita. אבל ערל, aval arel, but if the כהן kohen
is just not circumcised for whatever reason, maybe for a medical reason
or other reasons,
so in that case the הלכה halacha actually is that also the
עבודה avoda is desecrating, it does not count the עבודה avoda that
was done, the offering of the קרבן, korban, but nevertheless we're going
to see this next list, even though it is מחלל העבודה, mechalel
ha'avoda,
the כהן kohen himself is not חייב מיתה, chayav mita, is not
deserving of מיתה בידי שמים. mita bidei shamayim. ואונן, v'onen, or if
he has just suffered an immediate death in the family in the
status of אנינות. aninut. ויושב, v'yoshev, or sitting, because you have to
do the עבודה avoda standing. All of those cases, even though it's
מחלל העבודה, mechalel ha'avoda, אינם במיתה אלא באזהרה. einam b'mita ela b'azhara.
They're not חייב מיתה chayav mita in heaven, but they are violating
a negative prohibition. So this just is the full ברייתא braita that
shows that if a כהן kohen is טמא, tamei, it's the same
as being a non-כהן kohen and חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav mita
bidei shamayim. Now we're going to have some issues of debate. בעל
מום, ba'al mum, what's the story about a כהן kohen with a
blemish? רבי Rebbi אומר במיתה. omer b'mita. רבי Rebbi would say that
that would have totally taken him out of the כהן kohen category
for this purpose. I should mention that a בעל מום ba'al mum
does eat in the קרבנות, korbanot, but for the purpose of עבודה,
avoda, it is similar to being טמא, tamei, and he's חייב מיתה.
chayav mita. וחכמים אומרים באזהרה. v'chachamim omrim b'azhara. No, it's a simple
negative prohibition. We'll see about that debate. המזיד במעילה, hameizid b'meila, let's
say somebody, this is not really of the same nature, we're not
really talking about כהן kohen types of things, but if somebody was
מזיד, meizid, intentional, and he did מעילה, meila, he violated the use
of sanctified objects, in that case רבי Rebbi אומר במיתה, omer b'mita,
רבי Rebbi says he's deserving of death, וחכמים אומרים באזהרה, v'chachamim omrim
b'azhara, again death in heaven and the חכמים chachamim say no, only
a simple negative prohibition. This actually should have been relevant to the
earlier discussion of הגונב את הקסוה, hagonev et hakasva, somebody who steals
a כלי שרת, kli sharet, which also was in that קנאים פוגעים
בו, kana'im pog'im bo, works better with רבי's Rebbi's position of
במיתה. b'mita. Now we are going to go through each one of
these and see the basis for it. האוכל את הטבל מנלן, ha'ochel
et hatevel minalan, how do you know that somebody who eats טבל
tevel gets
מיתה בידי שמים? mita bidei shamayim? דאמר שמואל משום רבי אליעזר, d'amar
Shmuel mishum Rabbi Eliezer, מנין לאוכל את הטבל שהוא במיתה, minayin l'ochel
et hatevel shehu b'mita, it directly addresses this. How do you know
that somebody who eats טבל tevel is deserving of death in heaven?
דכתיב, d'chtiv, because the verse says, ולא יחללו את קדשי בני ישראל
את אשר ירימו להשם. v'lo yechalelu et kodshei b'nei Yisrael et asher
yarimu l'Hashem. They should not violate the sanctified things of בני ישראל,
b'nei Yisrael, and the context here is תרומה, teruma, that which they
will take as תרומה teruma to God. So the context is תרומה.
teruma. That might be about a prohibition of a זר zar who
eats תרומה. teruma. But the דרשה drasha is בעתידים לתרום הכתוב מדבר.
ba'atidim litrom hakatuv medaber. It, את אשר ירימו, et asher yarimu, the
ירימו yarimu is in the future, something that will have תרומה teruma
taken from it. So טבל, tevel, the grain that will have תרומה
teruma taken from it, if you go ahead and eat it, you
have then that is חייב מיתה. chayav mita. And that, by the
way, is even though the grain has a status of טבל tevel
after the תרומה teruma is taken but before the מעשר ma'aser is
taken. Based on this, it should not be חייב מיתה, chayav mita,
and that actually is how the רמב"ם Rambam rules. So that's how
you know that it's חייב מיתה chayav mita because that's anyway how
you know that it's a violation of this verse of ולא יחללו.
v'lo yechalelu. Now, how do we know it's חייב מיתה? chayav mita?
Logically that makes sense because it's connected to the תרומה. teruma. But
how do you know that?
ויליף חילול חילול מתרומה, v'yalif chillul chillul mitruma, because here it says
ולא יחללו, v'lo yechalelu, and by תרומה teruma also it says a
similar פסוק. pasuk.
By תרומה teruma it says
ומתו בו כי יחללהו, u'metu vo ki yechalelehu, that they will die
when they desecrate it. And the context there is a כהן kohen
who is טמא tamei who eats תרומה. teruma. That was, as we
saw, also on the list, and we're going to get to that
in the גמרא. gemara. So since we're going to understand that that
פסוק pasuk is talking about a כהן טמא kohen tamei who eats
תרומה teruma and it says ומתו בו, u'metu vo, they'll die, and
here it says ולא יחללו, v'lo yechalelu, so the חילול חילול chillul
chillul also we're talking about תרומה teruma in both cases, like one
that is taken, one that has yet to be taken. That tells
us that it is במיתה. b'mita. ויליף חילול חילול מתרומה, v'yalif chillul
חילול מתרומה, מה להלן במיתה אף כאן במיתה. ma halan b'mita af
kan b'mita. Just as there it's mita, here too it's mita. So
the גמרא gemara says וניליף חילול חילול מנותר. v'neilif chillul chillul minotar.
One minute, but we have a פסוק pasuk of נותר. notar. By
נותר notar it says כי את קדש השם חילל, ki et kodesh
Hashem chillel, because the sanctified thing of God he has been מחלל.
mechallel. And we say that that is in the context of נותר,
notar, and by נותר notar it is כרת. karet. So even though
in an earlier list when we were talking about שחוטי חוץ shechutei
chutz and so on, we were mentioning some things that were כרת
karet and some things that were חייב מיתה בידי שמים, chayav mita
bidei shamayim, and those are, there's similarities there, they both are a
form of heavenly death or excision, but here this list that we're
dealing with right now is specifically things that are מיתה בידי שמים.
mita bidei shamayim. So the גמרא gemara says, how do you know...
Because a נותר nosar we know is כרת, karet, it’s explicit and
it says כי את קדש
ה' חילל.
ki es kodesh
Hashem chilal. So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says מה להלן בכרת אף כאן בכרת. ma lehalan bekaret
af kan bekaret. No, מסתברא mistavra it makes sense מתרומה הוה ליה
למילף. mitrumah hava leh lemilaf. תרומה Terumah is a better thing to
learn תבל tevel from. שכן תרומה sheken trumah
because here's all the ways in which תבל tevel is similar to
תרומה. trumah. First of all, they're both תרומה, trumah, meaning תבל tevel
has תרומה trumah yet to be taken and תרומה trumah is actual
תרומה. trumah. That's pretty strong. חוץ לארץ, chootz la’aretz, both of them
do not apply in חוץ לארץ, chootz la’aretz, whereas נותר, nosar, I
mean you can't take a קרבן korban outside of ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, you can't even take it outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but it applied
when there was the משכן Mishkan in the desert in a way
that and תרומה trumah did not. So these do not apply at
all in חוץ לארץ. chootz la’aretz. הותרה, hutra, it is it can
become permissible, meaning the תבל tevel you can take תרומה trumah and
make it permissible, and the case of a כהן Kohen who is
טמא, tamei, he can go to the מקוה. mikvah. So there's ways
that it becomes permitted. Once something is נותר, notar, it's stuck at
being נותר. notar. ברבים. berabbim. It's a funny הותרה ברבים hutra berabbim
but it's a little play on words. It doesn't mean permissible in
the masses, it means that the language of חילל, chilal, לא יחללו,
lo yechalelu, excuse me it says by both of them לא יחללו,
lo yechalelu, whereas by the נותר nosar it says קדש ה' חילל
kodesh Hashem chilal in the singular. So again, that's another point of
connection. פירות, peirot, they both apply to grain, whereas נותר nosar does
not. Now actually נותר nosar does apply to a מנחה mincha but
that's when it's already been turned into flour. Here it applies when
the thing is still growing from the ground, you know, in its
early grain stage. Okay, פירות. peirot. פיגול ונותר, pigul venosar, and the
status of פיגול ונותר pigul venosar don't apply to them because they're
not קרבנות. korbanot. So תרומה trumah and תבל tevel are very, very
similar. So that's why we learn from תרומה. trumah. So the גמרא
Gemara says אדרבה מנותר הוה ליה למילף. aderaba minosar hava leh lemilaf.
No, say the opposite, you should learn out from נותר. nosar. Why?
שכן פסול אוכל sheken psul ochel because by both of them the
excuse me פסול אוכל psul ochel the food is פסול. pasul. You
know, one is that it is תבל, tevel, the other is that
it's נותר, nosar, as opposed to the case of the כהן Kohen
who is טמא tamei who eats the תרומה, trumah, he's טמא tamei
but the תרומה trumah is totally okay. אין לו היתר במקוה. ein
lo heter bemikvah. Both of those can't be fixed by going to
a מקוה, mikvah, תבל tevel or נותר, nosar, but the כהן Kohen
can be fixed by going to the מקוה, mikvah, the כהן Kohen
who is טמא. tamei. So those are two points of comparison. So
the גמרא Gemara says the obvious point הני נפישי. hani nefishei. First
of all, no, the connection of תבל tevel to תרומה, trumah, the
points of comparison are much, much greater and therefore that's what we're
going to learn out. רבינא אמר חילול דרבים מחילול דרבים עדיף. Ravina
amar chillul derabbim mechillul derabbim adif. And רבינא Ravina just says look,
at the end of the day it’s a גזירה שוה. gzera shava.
So forgetting even all those substantive points of connection, it says by
תרומה חילל trumah chillal and it says ולא יחללו velo yechalelu and
it says and it says by תבל, tevel, you know ולא יחללו,
velo yechalelu, so יחללו yechalelu is the exact same word, that’s the
connection. So that's how we know it is מיתה בידי שמים misa
biyedei shamayim and it is not a case of כרת. karet. Okay,
so now next next one. וכהן טמא שאכל תרומה טהורה מנלן? veKohen
tamei she'achal Terumah tehorah minalan? How do you know a כהן טמא
Kohen tamei who eats תרומה? Terumah? And this is exactly the case
that we were referring to before. דאמר שמואל, d'amar Shmuel, so it's
the same שמואל, Shmuel, you know, this is the first part but
earlier we saw the second stage. מניין לכהן טמא שאכל תרומה טהורה
שהיא במיתה בידי שמים? minayin leKohen tamei she'achal Terumah tehorah shehi bemisa
biyedei shamayim? How do you know it's heavenly death? דכתיב ושמרו את
משמרתי ולא ישאו עליו חטא ומתו בו כי יחללהו. deksiv veshamru es
mishmarti velo yisu alav cheit umesu vo ki yechaleluhu. The כי ki
by the way is not there in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, and
the context was one in the in the פסוקים psukim of טומאה
tumah and משמרתי, mishmarti, מה משמרת, ma mishmeres, which often is associated
with תרומה, trumah, but the explicit context in the פסוקים psukim there
is about a כהן Kohen being טמא. tamei. And it says and
they will die if they desecrated it, so that is being טמא
tamei and eating תרומה. trumah. Also רש"י Rashi points out that the
פסוקים psukim speak about after you go to the מקוה mikvah and
after the sunset then it's okay to eat. And so even though
earlier in the פסוקים psukim was explicitly about קרבנות, korbanot, the only
thing that's
okay once the sun sets and before you
bring your קרבן korban the next morning, before מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kippurim,
is the case תרומה. Terumah. So from that context also we can
infer that תרומה trumah is being referred to as well. Okay, so
מיתה בידי שמים, misa biyedei shamayim, fine. טהורה אין טמאה לא. tehorah
ein tmeiah lo. Now the גמרא Gemara comments, so you're only if
the תרומה trumah is טהורה, tehorah, is טהור, tahor, but if it's
a כהן טמא Kohen tamei eating תרומה טמאה Terumah tmeiah you would
not get מיתה בידי שמים. misa biyedei shamayim. Why is that? דאמר
שמואל, d'amar Shmuel, again שמואל Shmuel had a lot to say here
because שמואל Shmuel said, אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi Elazar, מניין לכהן
טמא שאכל תרומה טמאה שאינו במיתה? minayin leKohen tamei she'achal Terumah tmeiah
she'eino bemisa? How do you know when the תרומה trumah is טמאה
tmeiah it's not מיתה? misa? שנאמר ומתו בו כי יחללהו. shene'emar umesu
vo ki yechaleluhu. You die because you have desecrated it. And now
top of page פ"ג עמוד א', pei gimmel amud alef, פרט לזו
שמחוללת ועומדת, perat lazu shemechuleles veomedes, as opposed to תרומה טמאה Terumah
tmeiah where it is already desecrated because it became טמא. tamei. Of
course the question is how can you eat it without making it
טמא tamei when you hold it in your hand? So it could...
that somebody puts it in your mouth, or could be that somehow
we're talking about some case where it never came in contact with
water after it was harvested, so some type of a way in
which you did not make it טמא tamei and therefore when you're
טמא tamei and it is טהור tahor and the eating is is
desecrating it because you're טמא, tamei, that is when you're חייב מיתה.
chayav misa. Next case, וזר שאכל את התרומה, vezar she'achal es haterumah,
a non-כהן kohen who eats תרומה, terumah, again this comparison between the
non-כהן kohen and the כהן טמא. kohen tamei. אמר רב, amar rav,
זר שאכל את התרומה לוקה, zar she'achal es haterumah lokei, he only
gets lashes, okay, I mean you would get lashes even if you
get מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim because it is a a
negative prohibition. But by saying לוקה lokei it suggests that there is
no heavier punishment. אמרו ליה רב כהנא ורב אסי לרב, amru lei
rav kahana verav assi lerav, רב כהנא rav kahana and רב אסי
rav assi said to רב, rav, לימא מר במיתה, leima mar bemisa,
why not say that you're חייב מיתה? chayav misa? Rather than quoting
a ברייתא braisa they go straight to the פסוק, pasuk, דכתיב וכל
זר לא יאכל קדש, dichsiv vechol zar lo yochal kodesh, and and
so the context here is the following: it's exactly the פסוקים pesukim
we've been quoting before and it says like this, you know, the
פסוק pasuk says ושמרו את משמרתי ולא ישאו עליו חטא ומתו בו
כי יחללהו, veshamru es mishmarti velo yisu alav cheit umesu vo ki
yichalleluho, which is a כהן טמא kohen tamei that eats תרומה, terumah,
so and it says that's מיתה, misa, אני ה' מקדשם, ani Hashem
mekadeisham, I am God who makes them holy, and then the immediate
next פסוק pasuk is וכל זר לא יאכל קדש, vechol zar lo
yochal kodesh, and any non-כהן kohen cannot eat קדש kodesh and here
again the context is תרומה. terumah. So it's juxtaposed to the previous
פסוק, pasuk, we should say that you should get מיתה misa for
this as well. It says no, he says אני ה' מקדשם הפסיק
העניין. ani Hashem mekadeisham hifsik hainyan. No, because after it says the
כהן טמא kohen tamei gets מיתה, misa, it says אני ה' מקדשם,
ani Hashem mekadeisham, I make them the כהנים kohanim holy, which sort
of ends the paragraph, and now we're on a new topic about
a non-כהן, kohen, so it doesn't, that you can't connect it to
the מיתה misa of the previous פסוק. pasuk. That's a very reasonable
read of the פסוק. pasuk. But now we got a problem. Our
ברייתא, braisa, מיתיבי, meisivei, ask you on this: ואלו הן שבמיתה זר
האוכל את התרומה. ve'eilu hein shebemisa zar haohel es haterumah. Here the
ones that are מיתה misa and it lists explicitly a non-כהן kohen
who eats תרומה. terumah. So the גמרא gemara says מתניתא דרב קא
רמית? masnisa derav ka ramis? You're trying to challenge רב rav with
a ברייתא? braisa? רב תנא הוא ופליג, rav tanna hu ufalig, רב
rav was the generation of transitioning between the תנאים tannaim and אמוראים,
amoraim, he is entitled to argue on a משנה mishna or a
ברייתא. braisa. So although this ברייתא braisa says that the זר, zar,
the non-כהן kohen is just like the כהן טמא, kohen tamei, which
makes a lot of sense, and gets מיתה בידי שמים, misa bidei
shamayim, רב rav says you cannot really justify that based on the
פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, next one, וזר ששימש, vezar sheshimeish, a non-כהן kohen
who serves in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, דכתיב והזר הקרב יומת.
dichsiv vehazar hakareiv yumos. That's three words explicit in the תורה, Torah,
the non-כהן kohen who serves, who comes close to the מזבח mizbeiach
to serve will get מיתה. misa. וטמא ששימש, vetamei sheshimeish, a כהן
kohen who is טמא tamei who does the עבודה, avoda, which is
how we got onto this topic and we proved it from the
ברייתא, braisa, but now we're going to try to see how we
where we actually learn it out from. Okay, וטמא ששימש, vetamei sheshimeish,
so it says כדבעי מיניה רב חייא בר אבין מרב יוסף. kideva'ei
minei rav chiya bar avin meirav yosef. So this was רב חייא
בר אבין rav chiya bar avin asked רב יוסף rav yosef this
question: מנין לטמא ששימש שהוא במיתה? minayin letamei sheshimeish shehu bemisa? How
do you know a כהן kohen who is טמא tamei gets מיתה,
misa, which we proved but how do you know it? דכתיב דברו
אל אהרן ואל בניו וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל, dichsiv dabru el aharon
ve'el banav veyinazru mikodeshei venei yisrael, they shall separate themselves from the
holy things of Israel when they are טמא, tamei, ולא יחללו את
שם קדשי. velo yechalelu es shem kodshi. So again we have the
being מחלל, mechallel, all right, and when they are טמא, tamei, so
it's explicitly telling them don't do the עבודה avoda when you are
טמא, tamei, but it doesn't say what the punishment is. But it
has that word יחללו, yechalelu, ויליף חילול חילול מתרומה. veyalif chillul chillul
miterumah. By תרומה terumah we have seen it says ומתו בו כי
יחללהו, umesu vo ki yichalleluho, so we have the חילול חילול chillul
chillul by תרומה. terumah. מה להלן במיתה, ma lahan bemisa, the same
way תרומה terumah when you are טמא tamei that is מיתה בידי
שמים, misa bidei shamayim, אף כאן במיתה, af kan bemisa, here too
it is מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim and makes sense, you
know, eating תרומה terumah is מיתה בידי שמים misa bidei shamayim if
you're a כהן טמא, kohen tamei, doing the עבודה avoda seems that
doing the עבודה avoda is even worse, okay, but certainly based on
these פסוקים pesukim we link it. So now again the גמרא gemara
says ונילף חילול חילול מנותר? vneilaf chillul chillul minosar? Same question as
before, why not learn it out from נותר nosar which is כרת
kareis but not מיתה בידי שמים? misa bidei shamayim? מה להלן כרת
אף כאן כרת. ma lahan kareis af kan kareis. Because by נותר
nosar as we said it says, you know, כי את קדש ה'
חילל. ki es kodesh Hashem chillail. So let's learn it out from
נותר. nosar. מה להלן כרת אף כאן כרת. ma lahan kareis af
kan kareis. No, מסתברא מתרומה הוה ליה למילף. mistabra miterumah hava lei
lemilaf. Learning out the עבודה avoda when the כהן kohen is טמא
tamei from a כהן kohen being טמא tamei with תרומה, terumah, that's
more of a connection. Why? שכן גוף, shekein guf, טמא, tamei, first
of all the person is טמא tamei as opposed to נותר. nosar.
גוף, guf, it's about the person, either, you know, and טמא, tamei,
it's about the person being טמא, tamei, whereas the נותר nosar is
not about the person and not about טומאה. tumah. מקוה, mikveh, it's
fixed by going to the מקוה. ברבים, mikveh berabbim, and again מקוה
mikveh. ברבים, berabbim, it means that the language יחללו yechalelu is by
both of them. אדרבה, aderabba, says the גמרא, gemara, I could say
the opposite, מנותר הוה ליה למילף, minosar hava lei lemilaf, שכן קודש,
shekein kodesh, the נותר nosar and doing the עבודה avoda in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash are both like קודש, kodesh, I mean תרומה
terumah is... also called, but this is, you know, this is really
like inner קודש, kodesh, not תרומה terumah is קודש kodesh in the
גבולין, gevulin, outside of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. פנים, Panim, and
then that's like inner בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So פנים, panim, שכן
קודש, sheken kodesh, פנים, panim, פיגול, pigul, נותר ונותר, notar venosar, and
פיגול pigul and נותר nosar are both relevant in the case of
עבודה, avodah, not relevant by תרומה. terumah. So it's true, you know,
there's a lot of comparisons to תרומה, terumah, the כהן kohen being
טמא tamei doing the עבודה avodah טמא, tamei, but the world of
עבודה avodah is also similar to the world of נותר. nosar. So
maybe that should be how we learn it out. So the גמרא
Gemara says what it said earlier, חילול דרבים חילול דרבים עדיף. chilul
derabim chilul derabim adif. Here, you know, maybe it is a good
logical, equally weighted in terms of substantively, but at the end of
the day, it says יחללו yechalelu both by תרומה terumah and by
doing the עבודה avodah when you're טמא, tamei, so that's where we're
learning it out. So that's how we learn, a כהן kohen who's
טמא tamei and eats תרומה terumah gets מיתה בידי שמים, misa bidei
shamayim, and a כהן kohen who is טמא tamei and does the
עבודה avodah gets מיתה בידי שמים, misa bidei shamayim, and the same
for a זר zar eats תרומה terumah or a זר zar does
the עבודה. avodah. Okay, טבול יום ששימש. tvul yom sheshimesh. Now it's
not only if you're fully טמא, tamei, even if you've gone to
the מקווה mikvah and it just has not been sunset, which is
the status of טבול יום, tvul yom, which you have like the
status of like second degree derivative. But even that is enough to
be חייב מיתה בידי שמים. chayav misa bidei shamayim. מנלן, Menalan, where
do you know this from? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
braisa, רבי סימאי אומר, Rabbi Simai omer, רמז לטבול יום שאם עבד
חילל מניין? remez letvul yom she-im avad chilel minayin? How do you
know about that a טבול יום tvul yom who does the עבודה,
avodah, he desecrates the עבודה, avodah, it doesn't count, the קרבן korban
is not valid? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, קדושים יהיו לאלהיהם ולא יחללו.
kedoshim yihyu leloheihem velo yechalelu. Okay, since they should be holy and
they shall not desecrate. We quoted that earlier; it's a פסוק pasuk
that gets used in a couple of different ways. אם אינו עניין
לטמא ששימש, Im eino inyan letame sheshimesh, now you don't need that
for the basic point that you cannot be טמא tamei when you
do the עבודה, avodah, because that we learned out דדווקא מוינזרו, dedavka
miveyinazru, that's more the explicit פסוק, pasuk, וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל, veyinazru
mikadshei benei yisrael, so they shall separate themselves when they are טמא.
tamei. So this קדושים יהיו ולא יחללו, kedoshim yihyu velo yechalelu, which
sort of is like extra, we've already, you know, what's it including?
We've already said a lot specifically. So we're going to say תנהו
עניין לטבול יום, tenahu inyan letvul yom, it's an extra degree of
separating yourself out, even if you're only a טבול יום, tvul yom,
you would desecrate the עבודה. avodah. Now, that's desecrating the עבודה. avodah.
How do you know that you are חייב מיתה בידי שמים? chayav
misa bidei shamayim? So then it says לטבול יום ששימש, letvul yom
sheshimesh, ויליף חילול חילול מתרומה, veyalif chilul chilul mitrumah, and now that
we say that it's, you know, ולא יחללו, velo yechalelu, and again
the יחללו yechalelu in the רבים rabim and so on, we learn
it out from תרומה, terumah, מה להלן במיתה אף כאן במיתה. ma
hallan bemisa af kan bemisa. The same way there it's מיתה, misa,
here too it's מיתה. misa. And the גמרא Gemara does not have
to review, oh, let's learn it out from נותר, nosar, because it
already established that the יחללו יחללו yechalelu yechalelu is the stronger connection.
So not only a full טמא, tamei, even a טבול יום. tvul
yom. And then we're going to go even the next step, which
is מחוסרי כיפורים, mechusarei kippurim, that's coming next, but for some bizarre
reason we interrupt it with a different type of a category. ומחוסר
בגדים מנלן? Umechusar begadim minalan? How do you know a כהן kohen
not wearing the בגדי כהונה? bigdei kehunah? אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי
יוחנן ומטו בה משמיה דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Abahu amar
Rabbi Yochanan umatu bah mishmei de-Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon. So רבי אבהו
Rabbi Abahu said in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and
some say רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון, Rabbi Elazar berabbi Shimon, וחגרת אותם
אבנט. vechagarta osam avnet. It says you shall, you know, bind, whatever,
belt them with the belt. And the end of the פסוק pasuk
is אהרן ובניו וחבשת להם מגבעות והייתה להם כהונה לחוקת עולם. Aharon
uvanav vechavashta lahem migbaos vehaysa lahem kehunah lechukas olam. After you put
on the בגדים, begadim, the כהונה kehunah will be for an eternal
edict. ומילאת יד אהרן ויד בניו. Umileisa yad Aharon veyad banav. Okay,
so from there we learn the very important principle בזמן שבגדיהם עליהם
כהונתם עליהם. bizman shebigdeihem aleihem kehunasam aleihem. When they're wearing the בגדים,
begadim, then they have the full status of being כהנים. kohanim. This
is for the purpose of serving in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Doesn't mean a כהן kohen that's not wearing the בגדים begadim can
become טמא למתים tamei lemeisim or other types of things, that's quite
obvious, even though some ignorant people would like to say otherwise, anyway.
Okay, בזמן שבגדיהם עליהם כהונתם עליהם אין בגדיהם עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם.
bizman shebigdeihem aleihem kehunasam aleihem ein bigdeihem aleihem ein kehunasam aleihem. When
they are not wearing their בגדים, begadim, okay, I said I said
that a little harshly before. Anyway, when they are not wearing their
בגדים, begadim, their כהונה kehunah is not on them, they are not
full status of כהנים, kohanim, and therefore it would be like a
זר zar who does the עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. והוו להו זרים, Vehavu lehu zarim, they become זרים, zarim, ואמר
מר זר ששימש במיתה, veamar mar zar sheshimesh bemisa, and we've already
taught that a זר zar who does the עבודה avodah is חייב
מיתה. chayav misa. Now because this was just in the פסוקים pesukim
we just read, you know, the other day in שול, shul, I
should mention, you know, if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafos,
אין בגדיהם עליהם, ein bigdeihem aleihem, he says הקשה רב יעקב דאורלינש,
hiksha Rav Yaakov deOrleans, והמיתה כתיב בהדיא גבי מחוסר בגדים, vehamisa ksiv
beheydya gabi mechusar begadim, it's an explicit פסוק, pasuk, we read it
in פרשת תצוה, Parshas Tetzaveh, in פרשת תצוה. Parshas Tetzaveh. Okay, it
says, so ותירץ, veteretz, and he says דההוא מיתה ממכנסיים כתיב כדמשמע
פשטיה דקרא. dehahu misa mimichnesayim ksiv kidemashma peshatei dekra. Okay, if you
take a look at the פסוקים, pesukim, it speaks about that they
should wear מכנסי בד לכסות בשר ערווה, michnesai bad lechasos besar ervah,
you know, and right afterwards it says and if, you know, that
they should not go in and die. So he says in that
context it could be read, and רש"י Rashi there on the פסוקים
pesukim actually read it to be talking about מיתה misa if you're
not wearing any of the בגדים begadim you're חייב מיתה, chayav misa,
but the רמב"ן Ramban there says Basically what תוספות Tosafot says here,
he says, you know, maybe that could be פשט peshat of the
פסוקים pesukim but clearly it's not the way the גמרא Gemara understood.
The גמרא Gemara because since the גמרא Gemara had to learn from
the idea of אין בגדיהם עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם, ein bigdeihem aleihem
ein kehunatam aleihem, you know, then the understands that פסוק pasuk which
is explicit that says if you're not wearing it you should not,
you know, you'll die, is referring specifically to the case of the
מכנסיים, michnasayim, the underwear essentially. Okay, so that is how we know
that מחוסר בגדים. mechusar begadim. Okay, okay, ומחוסר כפורים מנלן? u'mechusar kippurim
minalan? How do you know if he's lacking atonement? Meaning he's like
a זב zav and he went to the מקוה mikvah but now
he has to bring a קרבן korban and now he's even like
a third-degree derivative טמא. tamei. How do you know even that is
in the category of טמא tamei in order to be like a
טמא tamei who does the עבודה? avodah? אמר רב הונא מדבר קרא
Amar Rav Huna midbar kra because the פסוק pasuk says וכיפר עליה
הכהן וטהרה, v'chipper aleha hakohen v'taherah, the כהן kohen shall atone for
her, the woman who, you know, in a case of a woman
who's bringing such a קרבן, korban, and she shall become pure. וטהרה
מכלל שהיא טמאה, v'taherah miklal shehi tmeiah, it shows you that until
that קרבן korban is brought, the person still has a status of
being טמא. tamei. ואמר מר טמא ששימש במיתה. v'amar mar tamei sheshimish
b'misa. So once we established that even מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim has
a status of being טמא, tamei, that just goes, reverts to the
general rule that a טמא tamei כהן kohen is חייב מיתה. chayav
misa. Now, of course, the question to ask is then why didn't
we say that by, you know, לא העריב שמשו, lo heeriv shimsho,
by טבול יום? tvul yom? That person is even more טמא tamei
than the מחוסר כפורים. mechusar kippurim. So why don't we just say
he's טמא tamei and therefore we've already established that a טמא tamei
person? And the answer of course is because his it's a weaker
טומאה. tumah. So then how can we say it here by the
מחוסר כפורים? mechusar kippurim? So תוספות Tosafot actually says you're right, we
would not have made that argument by the מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim
had we not already established it based on the earlier פסוק pasuk
by טבול יום. tvul yom. But since the earlier פסוק pasuk by
טבול יום tvul yom shows us that even a diminished טומאה tumah
is still טמא, tamei, then we are going to learn from this
פסוק pasuk of וטהרה v'taherah that that טומאה tumah that the person
has that's implicit in this פסוק pasuk is just like the טבול
יום tvul yom also a status of טומאה tumah and will be
חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Okay. ושתוי יין u'shtuyei yayin if you're drunk,
דכתיב, d'chtiv, I'm sorry, skipped a line, ושלא רחץ ידים ורגלים, u'shelo
rachatz yadayim v'raglayim, if they have not washed hands and feet, מנלן?
minalan? This is explicit פסוק, pasuk, דכתיב בבואם אל אהל מועד ירחצו
מים ולא ימותו, d'chtiv b'voam el ohel moed yirchatzu mayim v'lo yamutu,
quite clear, that they should wash themselves and not die. ושתוי יין
u'shtuyei yayin דכתיב, d'chtiv, יין ושכר אל תשת אתה ובניך אתך בבואכם
אל אהל מועד, yayin v'shichar al tesht atah u'vanecha itcha b'voachem el
ohel moed, you know, whatever ולא ימותו. v'lo yamutu. Same idea, don't
drink so you will not be חייב מיתה. chayav misa. ופרוע ראש,
u'farua rosh, and if their hair has grown wild, דכתיב d'chtiv ראשם
לא יגלחו ופרע לא ישלחו. rosham lo yegaleichu u'fera lo yeshaleichu. Okay,
this is not in the תורה, Torah, you know, this is a
פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, וכתיב בתריה u'chtiv batrei ויין לא ישתו.
v'yayin lo yishtu. Okay, and they should not drink. איתקש פרוע ראש
לשתוי יין, itkesh parua rosh l'shtuyei yayin, so they're connected. מה שתוי
יין במיתה, mah shtuyei yayin b'misa, the same way somebody who's drunk
gets מיתה, misa, אף פרוע ראש במיתה, af parua rosh b'misa, similarly
somebody whose hair grows wild. Now, you're normally not allowed to learn
הלכה halacha from פסוקים pesukim in תנ״ך, Tanach, but you know, how
much is this exactly הלכה? halacha? It's about חייב מיתה בידי שמים,
chayav misa bidei shamayim, it's not about any הלכה halacha that we
enact. And also, you know, often the גמרא Gemara says like, you
know, יחזקאל Yechezkel is just showing us what was already sort of
known or implicit. Okay, so we will end here.