Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is קל"ב, Kuf
Lamed Beis, and we start five lines from the top at the
two dots. עד כאן, Ad kan, so we have basically seen how
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's opinion that even מכשירין, machshirin, even preparatory things
can be done for מצוות, mitzvot, can be done on שבת, Shabbat,
even interestingly if the מצווה mitzvah itself normally wouldn't override שבת, Shabbat,
like שופר shofar or סוכה, sukkah, there's no need to override שבת,
Shabbat, nevertheless we learn that even the preparatory things can be done,
so it's quite a broad and bold position. The Rabbis disagree and
now we turn to the question about okay, but at least we
all agree that מילה mila itself overrides שבת. Shabbat. Where do we
know that from?
So let's take a look.
About six lines from the top, קל"ב. Kuf Lamed Beis. עד כאן
לא פליגי רבנן עליה, Ad kan lo pligi Rabbanan alei, until now
the Rabbis only argue on him, on רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, אלא
במכשירי מילה, ela bemachshirei mila, about the preparatory things for the ברית
מילה, bris mila, אבל מילה גופא דברי הכל דוחה שבת, aval mila
gufa divrei hakol docha Shabbat, but the מילה mila itself, everybody agrees
overrides שבת. Shabbat. So here you go Rifka, your question מנלן, minalan,
where do we know that from? אמר עולא הלכה, Amar Ula halacha,
it's a tradition, הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe miSinai, וכן אמר רבי
יצחק הלכה, v'chen amar Rabbi Yitzchak halacha, okay,
that ends the discussion, but not really.
מיתיבי, Meisivei, the גמרא Gemara says I'll ask you on this. מניין
לפיקוח נפש שדוחה את השבת? Minayin l'pikuach nefesh shedocheh es haShabbos? This
is a classic גמרא, Gemara, it's also תוספתא Tosefta here that's quoted
in יומא, Yoma, about where the idea that risk of life overrides
שבת. Shabbos. We had it in passing, well not so much in
passing anyway, about a woman giving childbirth, but interestingly a lot of
the discussion is in יומא Yoma where it talks about a building
falling on somebody and uncovering it in order to save somebody's life.
It also talks about feeding people on יום כיפור Yom Kippur if
they need to for risk of life. And anyway there the גמרא
Gemara quotes this ברייתא braisa which is a תוספתא Tosefta and it
says how do you know that פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh overrides שבת?
Shabbos? רבי אלעזר בן עזריה אומר, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah omer, מה
מילה, ma mila, he learns it from מילה. mila. מה מילה שהיא
אחת מאיבריו של אדם דוחה את השבת, ma mila shehi achas mei'evarei
shel adam docha es haShabbos, מילה mila is only one of a
person's limbs,
it overrides שבת, Shabbos, קל וחומר לפיקוח נפש שדוחה את השבת, kal
v'chomer l'pikuach nefesh shedocheh es haShabbos, so for the sake of מילה
mila we'd override שבת, Shabbos, certainly for an entire person's life. Now
what exactly exact type of comparison is that? But okay it doesn't
matter, for us what's important is that it assumes that ברית מילה
bris mila overrides שבת, Shabbos, it takes it for granted. Now what
does that say to the issue about where we know it from?
From the following. ואי סלקא דעתך הלכה, v'i salka deitach halacha, if
you say that ברית מילה bris mila we only know not from
a פסוק, pasuk, but we only know that it overrides שבת Shabbat
from a הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe miSinai, קל וחומר מהלכה מיאתי,
kal v'chomer mei'halacha mei'asi, we normally don't, we cannot make a קל
וחומר kal v'chomer based on הלכה. halacha. The whole idea of saying
something is הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe miSinai normally means that it's
like an arbitrary ruling. It doesn't necessarily fit into the larger system,
it's a standalone ruling. So if it's a standalone ruling then you
can't use it and apply the normal types of logic and abstract
it and derive from it, it's basically just an exception. So we
would not be able to apply a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, and
I'll give you an example of that. ותניא, v'tanya, we taught in
the ברייתא, braisa, אמר לו רבי אליעזר, amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, עקיבא,
Akiva, to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, he said עקיבא, Akiva, עצם כשעורה
מטמא הלכה. etzem kese'orah metamei halacha. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wanted
to say that if you have a רביעית revi'is of blood, like
three and a half ounces of blood from a dead body, that
we know first of all that that causes טומאה. tumah. We know
it causes טומאה tumah under a roof, it's considered representative of the
entire person. Now the question is there's a third issue by טומאת
מת, tumas meis, normally the two questions are does it cause טומאה
tumah by touch, does it cause טומאה tumah under the roof, not
everything causes טומאה tumah under a roof, you need a certain amount
and a certain type. And then there's a third question which is
called טומאה שהנזיר מגלח עליהם. tumah she'hanazir megalei'ach aleihem. If you have
a טומאה tumah that a נזיר, nazir, there's some things that are
טומאת מת tumas meis that are not considered a type of a
טומאת מת tumas meis that forces a נזיר nazir to shave his
hair and to restart his נזירות, neziros, only a subset. It's also
that similarly only those types of טומאות tumos that a נזיר nazir
shaves over are the טומאות מת tumos meis that a כהן kohen
is prohibited against. There are some types of a טומאת מת tumas
meis that a כהן kohen would not be prohibited about, you know
again not the obvious one about the entire dead body, but little
pieces of a body under certain circumstances, okay? So the question was
this טומאה tumah of blood, of a רביעית revi'is of blood, which
does cause טומאה tumah under a roof and nobody disagrees with that,
would it also be a טומאה tumah that a נזיר nazir would
shave over, that a כהן kohen would be prohibited against? So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wants to make a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. He
says we know that a little piece of bone, עצם כשעורה, etzem
kese'orah, a bone the size of a barley bean,
causes טומאה tumah and a נזיר nazir shaves over it. And that
טומאה tumah of a little piece of bone would only be if
you touch it, not under the same roof. We also know that
a רביעית revi'is of blood causes טומאה tumah and that's so strong
it's even טומאה tumah under the same roof. So if a bone
causes טומאה tumah that you shave over, then blood which causes טומאה
tumah even under the same roof certainly should be טומאה tumah that
you shave for. That's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. To which
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says back to him עקיבא, Akiva, עצם כשעורה
מטמא. etzem kese'orah metamei. הלכה. halacha. The fact that a bone, the
piece of a bone the size of a barley bean causes טומאה
tumah is הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai. רביעית דם revi'is dam
קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. And you want to use a קל וחומר
kal v'chomer from that to a רביעית revi'is of blood to say
if there you shave, a נזיר Nazir has to shave and a
כהן Kohen is prohibited, certainly by blood? So ואין דנין קל וחומר
מהלכה, v'ein danin kal v'chomer me'halacha, I'm sorry, you cannot make a
קל וחומר kal v'chomer based on a הלכה. halacha. So therefore you
cannot say that מילה milah is a הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'Moshe
mi'Sinai, at least not according to רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azarya who's making a קל וחומר kal v'chomer based on it.
At least there's got to be another opinion out there about where
we know ברית מילה bris milah overrides שבת. Shabbos. אלא אמר רבי
אלעזר, Ela amar Rabbi Elazar, so rather רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said
אתיא אות אות. atya os os. It's a גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah.
It says by שבת Shabbos כי אות היא ביני וביניכם, ki os
hi beini uveineichem, שבת Shabbos is an אות os and ברית מילה
bris milah is an אות. os. Okay, והיה לאות ברית, v'hayah l'os
bris, so the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah somehow tells us that it's
done even on שבת. Shabbos. I mean doesn't tell us it's stronger
than שבת, Shabbos, but somehow tells what's called an אות os is
done on the אות. os. ברית מילה bris milah is done on
שבת. Shabbos. אלא מעתה, Ela me'atah, says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's
true, תפילין דכתיב בהם אות לדחי שבת? tefillin dechtiv bahem os lidchi
Shabbos? How about תפילין? tefillin? It's תפילין tefillin is also called
והיו לאות על ידך, v'hayu l'os al yadecha, it should be for
an אות os on your hand. So it should also override שבת.
Shabbos. I don't know exactly what the circumstances are that תפילין tefillin
would override, I mean how you get it, you know, mostly be
מכשירי תפילין, machshirei tefillin, the act of putting it on. But anyway,
in principle, let's say תפילין tefillin overrides שבת. Shabbos. Okay, so forget
that. אלא אתיא ברית ברית. Ela atya bris bris. Here's another גזירה
שוה. gezeirah shavah.
מילה Milah is called a ברית, bris, right? וערל זכר אשר לא
ימול בשר ערלתו את בריתי הפר. v'arel zachar asher lo yimol besar
orlaso es brisi heifir. I mean ברית מילה bris milah is called
a ברית bris all the time. And שבת Shabbos is called a
ברית, bris, right? לדורותם ברית עולם. l'dorosam bris olam. So
מילה milah which is a ברית bris can be done on שבת
Shabbos which is a ברית. bris. I do want to point out
a little bit the irony here, which is: how do you know
that תפילין, tefillin, we don't wear תפילין tefillin on שבת? Shabbos? So
because of אות. os. Because it's called אות. os. So you don't
wear תפילין tefillin because since שבת Shabbos is already an אות, os,
you don't do תפילין tefillin which is an אות. os.
So somehow here we're saying the opposite. Because they're called the same
thing, that means you do it even on the same day.
But there is an opinion that we do wear them on שבת.
Shabbos.
I know, but still there's an irony here. Anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says okay, גדול דכתיב ביה ברית לדחי שבת. gadol dechtiv bei
bris lidchi Shabbos. By an adult, the פסוק pasuk says the only
time it says ברית bris by
ברית מילה bris milah is וערל זכר אשר לא ימול בשר ערלתו
את בריתי הפר. v'arel zachar asher lo yimol besar orlaso es brisi
heifir.
So it speaks, it says you have annulled my covenant, but it
speaks about somebody who has willingly not done a ברית מילה bris
milah to himself. So that only talks about an adult, okay, because
a child doesn't get כרת, kares, he hasn't chosen not to do
it. So where the only time it says ברית, bris, interestingly, by
ברית מילה bris milah is about an adult who is choosing not
to do it. So therefore it says how do you know
that this idea would apply to a ברית מילה bris milah of
an infant? גדול דכתיב ביה ברית לדחי שבת. Gadol dechtiv bei bris
lidchi Shabbos. And by the way we would never override שבת Shabbos
for ברית מילה bris milah of an adult because it wouldn't be
on the eighth day. Okay, so you'd come to a wrong conclusion.
And b, it would not be and you would not know that
an infant's ברית bris would override שבת. Shabbos. אלא אתיא דורות דורות.
Ela atya doros doros. Okay, we'll go another word. By שבת Shabbos
it says לדורותם ברית עולם. l'dorosam bris olam. And by ברית מילה
bris milah it says ובן שמנת ימים, uven shemonas yamim, and here
it's the eighth day, an eighth-day-old child, ימול לכם כל זכר לדרתיכם.
yimol lachem kol zachar l'doroseichem. So both of them it says generations.
Somehow it tells you ברית מילה bris milah is done on שבת.
Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says ציצית דכתיב ביה דורות לדחי שבת.
tzitzis dechtiv bei doros lidchi Shabbos. So if that's true, how about
ציצית? tzitzis? It also says דורות doros by ציצית. tzitzis. So it
says so let that override שבת. Shabbos. Again exactly hard to understand
not hard to understand. Why would you wear ציצית tzitzis on שבת?
Shabbos? Well right, but you wouldn't wear them let's say if there
was I don't know an eighth... I mean again what would be
the context in which it would be חילול שבת, chilul Shabbos, right?
Typing... tying them, but again that would be like מכשירין, machshirim, it
wouldn't be the actual act itself. Anyway, but in principle, would we
even suggest that ציצית tzitzis could override שבת? Shabbos? אלא אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק. Ela amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak. Okay, so now
we're saying fine, you asked me all these other cases, but here's
going to be the home run. דנין אות ברית ודורות. Danin os
bris v'doros. All three of those words is said both by שבת
Shabbos and by ברית מילה. bris milah. It's an אות, os, it's
a ברית, bris, it's for generations. אתיא אות ברית ודורות Atya os
bris v'doros לאפוקי הנך דחד חד אית בהו l'afukei hanach dechad chad
is behu it has one of those but it doesn't say all
three. Okay, and this is interesting by the way, to notice the
fact that, you know, the use of all these three terms in
both of these cases about how central sort of this is seen
in terms of, you know, Jewish identity issues I would say. I
mean, the ברית bris for the men, but I would say for
example, you know, being מחלל שבת בפרהסיא mechaleil Shabbos b'farhesia was the
classic way in which somebody
basically set themselves apart from the Jewish community and was basically considered,
you know, disqualified and all these types of things. In the modern
period when, you know, most Jews were
non-שבת Shabbos observant... A whole shift sort of occurred within the sort
of פסק הלכה psak halacha and you basically, you know, that חילול
שבת chilul shabbos was no longer a form a basis for exclusion,
you know, different arguments like like תינוק שנשבה tinok shenishba and other
types of arguments which is, okay, nowadays חילול שבת chilul shabbos is
not a form of exclusion. But so is there any lines? Are
there any like, you know, sharp lines? And for some, it still
was the issue of ברית מילה. bris milah. If a man like
willingly rejected, you know, chose like he, you know, as a, you
know, as a principled position not to do ברית מילה, bris milah,
then that would be like okay that's somebody that you're not, you
know, can not be seen as a part of the Jewish community.
It raises interesting questions, you know, where do our lines exist nowadays?
Because, you know, those are questions about what is left as sort
of central to that sense of, you know, Jewish identity. So it
is interesting here, again I realize it's very male oriented, but it
is interesting here that these three words, ברית, bris, דורות, doros, and
לדורותם l'dorosam are both by שבת shabbos and by ברית מילה. bris
milah. So that's at least one position of the גמרא. gemara. Okay.
רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says אמר
קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says,
אמר קרא, amar kra, ביום, bayom, ביום, אפילו בשבת. bayom afilu b'Shabbos,
It says ביום השמיני bayom hashmini like we said before, the eighth
day, and somehow ביום bayom, means it has to be today, even
on שבת. shabbos. Before we said that we learned from there according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the idea of מכשירין machshirin even the
preparatory, here we're saying we learn from that that the ברית מילה
bris milah itself is done on שבת. shabbos. So אמר ליה ריש
לקיש לרבי יוחנן, amar lei Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אלא מעתה מחוסרי כפרה, ella
maata mechusrei kapparah,
how about people that need to bring a קרבן korban in order
to become טהור? tahor? דכתיב ביה ביום. dichtiv bei bayom. It says
there as well ביום השמיני, bayom hashmini, ביום השביעי, bayom hashvii, you
know, on the seventh day, the eighth day they bring their קרבן,
korban, so would we there also say that you do it even
on שבת? shabbos? Okay, so הכא נמי דדחי שבת? hacha nami d'dachi
shabbos? Would it also override שבת? shabbos? So every time it says
ביום bayom it overrides שבת? shabbos? No. ההוא מבעי ליה ביום ולא
בלילה. hahu mibaei lei bayom v'lo b'lailah. That tells you something else.
You do it at daytime, not nighttime. גמרא gemara says הכא נמי
מבעי ליה ביום ולא בלילה. hacha nami mibaei lei bayom v'lo b'lailah.
So the same thing for ברית מילה. bris milah. The word ביום
bayom teaches you it's in the daytime, not nighttime. No, ההוא מבין
שמונת ימים נפקא. hahu miben shemonas yamim nafka.
There we learn it from eight days old, so the ימים yamim
there tells me, although it's funny there the days refers to the
age of the infant, but anyway from that from that word of
ימים yamim we've learned daytime. The extra ביום bayom tells you even
on שבת. shabbos. So גמרא gemara says האי נמי מביום צותו נפקא.
hai nami mibayom tzavaso nafka. So what? By קרבנות korbanos it says
that on the day that God commanded משה, Moshe, from where we
learn that's talking in the context of קרבנות korbanos that all קרבנות
korbanos are brought on the daytime and nevertheless you have an extra
ביום, bayom so let's say that even these קרבנות korbanos are brought
on שבת, shabbos, which we know isn't true. So the גמרא gemara
says no. אף על גב דנפקא מביום צותו, af al gav d'nafka
mibayom tzavaso, although we know from the words "the day that God
commanded" that קרבנות korbanos are generally brought in the
daytime, איצטריך. itztrich. You still need to tell me again that the
קרבנות korbanos that are brought to end the impurity period of various
people also has to be in the day. Why? סלקא דעתך אמינא,
salka daatach amina, I might have thought, הואיל וחס רחמנא עליה לאתויי
בדלות, hoil v'chas rachmana alei l'asuyei b'dalus, the Torah in these cases
of people that are מחוסרי כפרה mechusrei kapparah basically says, you know,
if you don't have the money to bring this type of a
קרבן, korban, you can bring birds and if you don't have the
money for birds, you can bring like a grain sacrifice. The Torah
basically has a tremendous חידוש chiddush which is gives you a sliding
scale by these people who have to end their impurity period. So
maybe if the Torah is being so lenient and making it so
easy on them, maybe it would let them do it even at
night. I don't know, that's quite a, you know, obviously a different
type of a thing to say you don't have to spend as
much money to say you can do it the night before, night
before, anyway, but once the Torah is introducing this whole new idea,
maybe all the rules fall off and maybe you could have even
done it at night. So I might have said בלילה נמי ליתי,
b'lailah nami leisei, so maybe you could bring it at night. קא
משמע לן, ka mashma lan, it has to say ביום. bayom, So
basically our question is ביום, bayom. how can that mean even on
שבת? shabbos? It says ביום bayom, by these קרבנות korbanos and it
doesn't mean on שבת. shabbos. So the answer is it had to
say ביום bayom to emphasize these things are in the daytime. Don't
think that all the rules have changed by these קרבנות. korbanos. So
מתקיף ליה רב אבינא, matkif lei Rav Avina, רב אבינא Rav Avina
asks, אלא מעתה יהא זר כשר בהן? ella maata yeha zar kasher
bahen? ויהא אונן כשר בהן? v'yehei onen kasher bahen? So says how
could you even have thought that the rules have changed by these
קרבנות? korbanos? So would we suggest like a non-כהן kohen could have
brought those קרבנות? korbanos? Would we suggest somebody in mourning who had
just lost a relative could bring, an אונן, onen, you know, the
day that the relative died, could bring those קרבנות? korbanos? You know,
clearly we would never have thought that all the rules change. If
we thought the rules change, so then so then even if you
tell me that it has to be the daytime because they have
an extra פסוק, pasuk, maybe everything else is different. So the גמרא
gemara says no. הא אהדריה קרא. ha ahadrei kra. Once the פסוק
pasuk went back and said the rules haven't changed, it has to
be the daytime, okay, then we know that all the other things
rules haven't changed either. So for a second we
had a possibility that the rules might change since the Torah allowed
a sliding scale. It said ביום bayom to teach me the rules
haven't changed and now we're back to where we always were. But
at the end of the day, you know, and don't even it
has to be daytime, it has to be a כהן, kohen, all
the rules apply. But anyway ביום bayom here is not to tell
me it overrides שבת, shabbos, but it is but that is what
the word. ביום bayom tells me by ברית מילה. bris milah. Okay,
so that's answer number two. So answer number one was the same
word it uses by שבת, Shabbos, אות, os, ברית לדורותם. bris ledorosom.
Answer number two was the word ביום. bayom Now we're going to
get a third answer. רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov
אמר אמר קרא amar amar kra the פסוק passuk says שמיני shmini
ואפילו, va'afte, שמיני shmini ואפילו בשבת, va'afillu b'Shabbos,
even on שבת. Shabbat. Now of course you could say it has
to tell you the eighth day to tell you the eighth day,
but you could have said ובן שמונת ימים, u'ben shmonat yamim, you
already said an eighth-day old infant. By re-emphasizing שמיני, shmini, it means
the eighth day regardless, even if it falls out on שבת. Shabbos.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, האי שמיני מיבעי ליה למעוטי שביעי. hai shmini
mibae lei l'imei t'vi'i. So one minute, like I just said, eighth,
it has to tell you not a seven-day old baby. No, שמיני
shmini ובן שמונת ימים u'ben shmonat yamim נפקא, nafka, it says eighth-day
old child. So why again do you have to say on the
eighth day? So the גמרא Gemara says וחד מיבעי ליה, vechad mibae
lei,
you still need to tell me the eighth day. חד למעוטי שביעי,
chad l'imei t'vi'i, one to say בן שמונת ימים ben shmonat yamim
means saying it can't be seven days old, it has to be
eight days old, וחד למעוטי תשיעי, vechad l'imei t'shi'i,
and on the eighth day is to tell me, right, a child
that is ten days old is also eight days old. So if
it just said בן שמונת ימים, ben shmonat yamim, it wouldn't have
said that there's an emphasis on exactly שמיני. shmini. It would have
said that there's a minimum that it be eight days old. To
say it again eighth day to tell me that it's supposed to
be exactly on the eighth day, but that still wouldn't necessarily tell
you שבת, Shabbos, it's just telling you eighth day rather than ninth
day. ואימא חד, v'im chad, had it just been one, הוה אמינא
שביעי הוא דלא מטא זמניה, hava amina t'vi'i hu d'lo matti zmanei,
by seven days it's not yet of the right age, אבל משמיני
ואילך, aval mishmini va'aylach, once it's eight days old and onwards, זמניה
הוא, zmanei hu, it's all of the same whether day eight, day
nine or whatever. So it repeats eight to tell me that eight
specifically and not nine, so maybe but not necessarily to tell me
even on שבת. Shabbos. אלא מחוורתא כרבי יוחנן, ela mivarta k'Rabbi Yochanan,
so רבי יוחנן'ס Rabbi Yochanan's approach is better that learns it out
from the word ביום bayom. and not from the word שמיני. shmini.
So we have different ways to learn out that ברית מילה bris
milah is done on שבת. Shabbat.
Okay, תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן, tanya k'vosei d'Rabbi Yochanan, we taught like
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ודלא כרב אחא בר יעקב, u'dlo k'Rav Acha
bar Yaakov, not like רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov
because we start with the שמיני shmini but we move to the
word ביום. bayom Here's what the ברייתא braita says. שמיני ימול, shmini
yimol, you have a ברית מילה bris milah on the eighth day,
אפילו בשבת, afilu b'shabbos. even if it falls out on שבת. Shabbos.
ומה אני מקיים מחלליה מות
יומת, u'mani mekayem mechaleleha mot yumos, what about the פסוק passuk that
says those who violate שבת Shabbos will be put to death? Right,
I mean, this is a violation of שבת. Shabbos. בשאר מלאכות חוץ
ממילה, b'sh'ar melachos chutz mimilah,
fine, it means everything else other than ברית מילה, bris milah, but
ברית מילה bris milah can be done on שבת. Shabbos. או אינה
אלא אפילו מילה, o einah ela afilu milah, maybe not, maybe even
ברית מילה bris milah cannot be done on שבת. Shabbos. ומה אני
מקיים שמיני, u'mani mekayem shmini, so what do I do with the
fact that the תורה Torah emphasizes eight days, day eight? ימול חוץ
בשבת, yimol chutz b'Shabbos, when it doesn't fall out on שבת. Shabbos.
תלמוד לומר ביום אפילו בשבת. talmud lomar bayom afilu b'Shabbos. So fine,
had it just been the word eighth day, I could have argued
either way, yes שבת, Shabbos, no שבת. Shabbos. The extra word ביום
bayom. tells me it has to be on שבת. Shabbos. So in
the end that's like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan because it learns it
out from the word ביום. bayom Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says אמר רבא Amar Rava האי תנא מעיקרא מאי קא ניחא ליה
ולבסוף מאי קא קשיא ליה. hai tanna mei'ikara mai ka nichaleh u'besof
mai ka kasha leh. What was originally bothering this תנא tanna that
he thought you could learn it out from שמיני shmini and then
what he resolved that he was allowed to find that we could
learn it out from ביום. bayom. Now this is interesting, the גמרא'ס
Gemara's going to do this more than once. And sometimes you find
this in like מדרשי הלכה. Midreshei Halacha. That מדרשי הלכה Midreshei Halacha
will sort of say, well maybe it means this, or maybe not,
maybe it means that, so the פסוק passuk says this. And there's
very little sort of
like reasons given. It all very much just says, you know, you
could have gone this way, you could have say this, you know,
but maybe you could say that, and then of course a פסוק
passuk and says because of this extra פסוק passuk we learn the
following. So what's interesting is, and that's not so different from what
the גמרא Gemara just did, it says ביום bayom. אפילו בשבת, afilu
b'Shabbos, בשמיני אפילו בשבת. b'shmini afilu b'Shabbos. But the fact is once
the מדרשי הלכה Midreshei Halacha starts sort of almost starting a conversation,
they say well maybe you could say that, well maybe you could
say this, you know, the גמרא Gemara sort of wants to see
that there's more like some reasons and arguments on each side rather
than just like a technical question of are there פסוקים. pesukim. But
it's interesting to note that shift. The מדרשי הלכה Midreshei Halacha from
the תנאי Tannaitic period is just sort of saying arbitrarily you could
have argued either way and an extra פסוק passuk tells you this.
But once we're sort of saying you could argue, the גמרא Gemara
wants to say well what's the argument, what would be what would
be the reasons behind each position? So let's take a look now
at what the גמרא Gemara sort of inserts into this conversation.
הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what it says: שמיני ימול אפילו
בשבת, shmini yimol afilu b'Shabbos, you maybe I would say you do
it even on שבת. Shabbos. ומה אני מקיים מחלליה מות יומת, u'mani
mekayem mechaleleha mot yumos, how about the fact that if you violate
שבת Shabbos you're put to death? So that's בשאר מלאכות חוץ ממילה,
b'sh'ar melachos chutz mimilah, it's other than מילה, milah, אבל מילה דחי,
aval milah dachi, but מילה milah would override. Now that was just
what the ברייתא braita said, but now the גמרא Gemara wants to
insert what is the argument why, what's pushing you to say that
מילה milah should override שבת? Shabbos? מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what should
be the argument? קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And now we are shifting
from an arbitrary quoting of פסוקים pesukim to arguments why מילה milah
should דוחה שבת. docha Shabbos. קל וחומר, kal vachomer, what's the קל
וחומר? kal vachomer? ומה צרעת שדוחה את העבודה ועבודה דוחה את השבת,
u'ma tzara'at she'docha et ha'avodah ve'avodah docha et ha'Shabbos, here's the קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. If somebody has a כהן kohen has... leprosy on
a צרעת tzaraat on a part of his body, he cannot do
the עבודה. avodah. Okay, or here's another example: a person has צרעת
tzaraat on him himself, he cannot eat the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
even though those are very important things, eat the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach to do the עבודה. avodah. צרעת tzaraat trumps. And we don't
say now, of course צרעת tzaraat trumps, you're טמא. tamei. But if
there's a way to solve the צרעת tzaraat problem, what's a way
to solve the צרעת tzaraat problem?
Well, knock it off
and let him look at it. Yes, that is true. But the
other way to solve it is cut it off. Let's say it's
a piece of skin that could just be cut off. Okay, so
it's אסור. assur. There's a biblical prohibition to cut off צרעת tzaraat
rather than to deal with it. So why don't we say okay,
but you know what, here I have this עבודה avodah that's not
going to get done, here I have this קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
that's not going to get eaten. Maybe I should cut off the
צרעת tzaraat in order to enable me to do that. We say
no, we're sorry, the prohibition of צרעת tzaraat is more important and
you're not allowed to cut it off in order to enable you
to do the עבודה. avodah. So what trumps between the decision of
cutting צרעת tzaraat versus doing the עבודה? avodah? Cutting צרעת tzaraat is
trumps. That's, okay, this is going to be the transitive axiom of
inequality. צרעת tzaraat is greater than עבודה, avodah, cutting off the צרעת,
tzaraat, the prohibition. Now, עבודה דוחה שבת. avodah docheh Shabbos. Let's say
you have the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach to be brought on שבת,
Shabbos, or you have the כהן Kohen has to do עבודה avodah
on שבת. Shabbos. Do you do it on שבת? Shabbos? Do you
do עבודה בית המקדש? avodah Beis HaMikdash? You do, you do the
עבודה בית המקדש avodah Beis HaMikdash on שבת. Shabbos. So עבודה avodah
is greater than שבת. Shabbos. Cutting off צרעת tzaraat is greater than
עבודה. avodah. עבודה avodah is greater than שבת. Shabbos. So by the
transitive axiom of inequality, cutting off צרעת tzaraat is greater, is more
important than שבת. Shabbos. Now let's keep on going. מילה milah now,
ועבודה דוחה שבת, v'avodah docheh Shabbos, מילה דוחה אותה. milah docheh otah.
So let's say though you had a choice between doing a, there
was a צרעת tzaraat on the person's foreskin. Would you do the
ברית מילה? bris milah? And the הלכה halacha is that you do.
מילה milah trumps צרעת. tzaraat. Okay, so no, it's not circular. מילה
milah overrides the prohibition of צרעת. tzaraat. Prohibition of cutting off צרעת
tzaraat is more important than the עבודה. avodah. עבודה avodah is more
important than שבת. Shabbos. So מילה milah is the most important thing.
So
מילה milah is greater than צרעת, tzaraat, צרעת tzaraat is greater than
עבודה, avodah, עבודה avodah is greater than שבת, Shabbos, so מילה milah
overrides שבת. Shabbos. There you go. Okay, so שבת נדחית מפני עבודה,
Shabbos nidchis mipnei avodah,
so שבת Shabbos that's pushed off for the sake of the עבודה,
avodah, אינו דין שתהא מילה דוחהו. eino din she'tehei milah dochehu. So
if צרעת tzaraat pushes off עבודה avodah but anyway, you got it,
מילה milah ultimately should trump everything and should be דוחה שבת. docheh
Shabbos. So that's the argument. So that's now we've moved from פסוקים
psukim to a real argument. Okay, ומה
אני מקיים? u'mah ani mekayem? What do I do with, okay I'm
sorry, ומאי איהו דקאמר. u'mai ihu d'ka'amar. So that was a nice
argument. So what was the, what would be the response back? הדר
אמר ומי יימר דצרעת חמורה. hadar amar u'mi yeimar d'tzaraat chamurah. No,
no, no. Maybe the reason צרעת tzaraat
trumps עבודה avodah is not because צרעת tzaraat is more weighty. דילמא
שבת חמורה. dilma Shabbos chamurah. Maybe really שבת Shabbos is more weighty,
שכן יש בו עונשין ואזהרות הרבה, sheken yesh bo onshin v'azharot harbeh,
because it has like a lot of these prohibitions, so you know.
ומי יימר משום דחמירה צרעת
היא.
u'mi yeimar mishum d'chamirah
tzaraat hi. Maybe, and how do you know that when we say
צרעת tzaraat trumps, it's because צרעת tzaraat is more weighty? דילמא משום
גברא הוא דלא חזי. dilma mishum gavra hu d'lo chazi. Maybe it's
just because the person is not fit. What does this mean? It
means it's not really that צרעת tzaraat is more important than the
עבודה. avodah. What it really, I mean the first line is, let
me go back and read it. Yeah, the first line, meaning meaning
maybe it's really not that צרעת tzaraat is more important than the
עבודה. avodah. Maybe really what it is is that even if you
were, the גמרא Gemara is going to say this later, even if
you were to cut off the צרעת, tzaraat, the person would still
be טמא. tamei. You would not solve the problem today. You would
only solve the problem for tomorrow. Today's עבודה avodah he can't do.
You'd cut off the צרעת, tzaraat, he'd have to go to the
מקוה, mikvah, he would only be טהור tahor tonight, he'd only be
able to do the עבודה avodah tomorrow. So the fact
that you don't cut off the צרעת tzaraat to allow him to
do the עבודה avodah is not because the prohibition of צרעת tzaraat
is more weighty than the עבודה avodah that lets you keep up
your whole transitive axiom of inequality. It's because regardless the person is
טמא tamei and cutting off the צרעת tzaraat is not going to
immediately help that. So there goes your whole beautiful argument. Okay, דילמא
משום גברא הוא דלא חזי. dilma mishum gavra hu d'lo chazi. ומה
אני מקיים שמונת ימים חוץ משבת. u'mah ani mekayem shmonat yamim chutz
mi'Shabbos. So then I'm back to saying that it doesn't override שבת
Shabbos because I don't have my whole argument. תלמוד לומר ביום אפילו
בשבת. talmud lomar bayom afilu b'Shabbos. So then you need the פסוק
ביום pasuk bayom to tell me in the end the פסוק pasuk
does trump. But what we've done differently is we've moved it out
as again since the way it's set up is maybe you could
say this way, maybe you could say that way, the גמרא Gemara
wanted to give reasons for arguing both ways. And one reason to
argue that you could do ברית מילה bris milah on שבת Shabbos
is by this whole transitive axiom of inequality about צרעת, tzaraat, עבודה,
avodah, עבודה, avodah, שבת, Shabbos, מילה, milah, צרעת, tzaraat, and then therefore
it trumps everything. And then the גמרא Gemara says yeah but the
צרעת tzaraat thing doesn't really prove anything because maybe even if you
had to cut it off, the guy would still be טמא tamei
so it really doesn't help. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara is going to go on, but I do
want to actually take a pause and mention something because there's this
fascinating. I think it's of the רדב"ז Radbaz that he was asked
if somebody—this is an extremely important practical תשובה—he Teshuvah was asked if
somebody
basically says to someone, let me cut off your arm or I
will kill פלוני. Ploni. Okay. So do you have to give up
your limb to save somebody else's life? Now normally this is, you
know, becomes in other contexts about like, you know, organ donation or
do you have to risk, you know, do you have to run
into a burning building to save somebody's life? How much risk do
you have to subject yourself to and, you know, in order to
save somebody else's life?
Depends on how much you like פלוני. Ploni. Right? Depends on how
much you like פלוני.
Ploni. פלוני, Ploni, right, right. So anyway so here was the person
who asked the question tried to argue the following way. He said
look, you don't override שבת Shabbos to save a limb, you only
override שבת Shabbos to save a life. Now that's true in theory.
In practice almost all cases we say that anytime a limb is
at risk, a life is at risk and whatever, that's another conversation,
we'll see that later. But anyway this is the way the person
asked the question. He says you don't override שבת Shabbos to save
a limb so שבת Shabbos is greater than a limb. But you
do override שבת Shabbos to save a life. So a life is
greater than שבת. Shabbos. שבת Shabbos is greater than a limb. So
therefore a life is greater than a limb, the transitive axiom of
inequality just like we do here, so you should have to give
up your limb to save somebody else's life, right? So that was
the argument. So basically the
רדב"ז Radbaz says, you don't give up your life for a based
on a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. It's an argument that, anyway,
he rejects the whole thing and he basically argues, he says that
you you do not have to, you know, you're allowed to, you
know, there are limits to how much of a demand we can
make on you even for when somebody else's life is at stake.
It's a very important and relevant תשובה, Teshuvah, but it's interesting it
uses a similar type of a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. Yes, Charlie.
Back to the עבודה Avodah of overriding שבת. Shabbat. We do the
communal עבודה Avodah on שבת, Shabbat, but private offerings are not brought
on שבת. Shabbat.
Yeah, I that's true but still, I mean, okay, but still wouldn't
affect the קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, right? I mean עבודה Avodah at
least communal עבודה Avodah and צרעת Tzara'at is and צרעת Tzara'at gets
in the way of communal עבודה. Avodah. So okay the קל וחומר
Kal Vachomer still works. So and the גמרא Gemara is saying in
the end, how do you know, maybe it's not that צרעת Tzara'at
is more important than שבת. Shabbos. The logic is of course that
שבת Shabbos is more important than צרעת. Tzara'at. שבת Shabbos has all
these prohibitions, it's חיוב כרת Chiyuv Karis and so on. The reason
צרעת Tzara'at trumps here is a very indirect reason, not because צרעת
Tzara'at is really more important than שבת. Shabbos. Yes, רבקה. Rivka.
The fact they had to go through all these contortions to justify
מילה Milah on שבת Shabbos doesn't that indicate they really had a
problem? Wasn't clear to them.
No, I would argue the opposite. I would say that they took
it totally for granted that מילה Milah overrides שבת Shabbos and they
just had to backwards fit it in and come up with
explanations.
If it's הלכה Halakha then that's
it.
Yeah, the only reason the גמרא Gemara rejected הלכה, Halakha, it really
seems that הלכה Halakha is probably the right answer, you know, they
just had it by tradition. The only reason the גמרא Gemara rejected
it was because of this קל וחומר Kal Vachomer and, you know,
that רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah used it as
a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. So רש"י Rashi by the way says
fine according to him it's not הלכה למשה מסיני Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai
but according to other approaches it might actually be הלכה למשה מסיני.
Halakha L'Moshe MiSinai. So I think it's similar to the whole issue
like when we're going to get in יומא Yoma which we quoted
פה עמוד א, poh amud aleph, how do you know that, you
know, שבת Shabbos you override for פיקוח נפש? Pikuach Nefesh? And the
גמרא Gemara quotes like a half a dozen or more דרשות. Drashot.
And at the end of the day none of them are so
convincing, but what it really shows you is that they already knew
the הלכה. Halakha. Meaning we take it for granted that פיקוח נפש
Pikuach Nefesh overrides שבת. Shabbos. We take it for granted you do
ברית מילה Brit Milah on שבת. Shabbos. Where do you know it
from? I don't know let's go figure it out. Okay, so really
I would argue the exact opposite that the הלכה Halakha was clear,
the דרשות Drashot were something that were sort of being sort of
figured out in hindsight afterwards. By the פיקוח נפש Pikuach Nefesh by
the way you know that because פיקוח נפש Pikuach Nefesh overriding שבת
Shabbos is actually the earliest
documented תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh that we have because it
comes up in the Book of Maccabees that first they refused to
fight on שבת Shabbos and they got and they got slaughtered and
then they said it must be God that wants us to protect
ourselves and whatever. They sort of intuited the idea that פיקוח נפש
Pikuach Nefesh דוחה שבת docheh Shabbos and then you find whatever it
is two hundred years later about more two hundred fifty years later
whatever that the גמרא Gemara is saying מניין לפיקוח נפש שדוחה את
השבת? minayin l'Pikuach Nefesh she'docheh et haShabbat? You know they took it
for granted. We already knew it but now we have to come
up with פסוקים. Psukim. So that's what I think is happening here.
Yes.
But a little earlier than the time the משנה Mishnah was written
down, in the Christian scriptures Jesus is getting in trouble in trouble
for healing on שבת. Shabbat. Right. So there must have been some
people who didn't buy this.
He was getting in trouble for healing on שבת. Shabbat. Right. Yeah,
not פיקוח נפש Pikuach Nefesh though. Those stories were not פיקוח נפש
Pikuach Nefesh stories. Okay, we'll talk about that some other time. Okay,
anyway so מילה Milah is
different because
is the emphasis upon being circumcised or on the eighth day?
Eighth day. You would only override for an שמיני מילה, Shemini Milah,
not for others, only
an שמיני מילה. Shemini Milah. Again, I
don't read the גמרא Gemara that way.
I understand, but I just don't read the גמרא Gemara that way
that they were grappling with the הלכה, Halacha, they were grappling with
the basis of the הלכה, Halacha, that the הלכה Halacha was taken
for granted. Okay, let's see as the גמרא Gemara continues. תנו רבנן:
Tano Rabbanan: מילה דוחה את הצרעת בין בזמנו בין שלא בזמנו. Milah
docha es hatzara'as, bein bizmano bein shelo bizmano. Now that we've discussed
that you do a ברית מילה bris milah even if there's leprosy
on the foreskin, so this is true even if it's not an
eighth day מילה. milah. You need an eighth day מילה milah to
override שבת, Shabbos, but whenever you're doing the ברית מילה bris milah
it overrides צרעת, tzara'as, even if there's צרעת tzara'as on the foreskin.
יום טוב אינה דוחה אלא בזמנו בלבד. Yom Tov eina docha ela
bizmano bilvad. However, מילה milah does not override יום טוב, Yom Tov,
and let alone שבת, Shabbos, unless it's eighth day. So you need
eighth day מילה milah because that's part of the reason it overrides,
like it's supposed to be today, so it has to be an
eighth day מילה milah to override שבת Shabbos or יום טוב. Yom
Tov. But for cutting the foreskin off with צרעת tzara'as doesn't matter
whether it's בזמנו bizmano or not. Although you could say wait till
the צרעת tzara'as goes away, but you don't have to. Okay, מנאני
מילי? minani mili? Where do you know this? That it overrides צרעת?
tzara'as? דתנו רבנן: DeTano Rabbanan: ימול בשר ערלתו, yimol besar orlaso, you
should cut off the flesh, אף על פי שיש שם בהרת, af
al pi sheyesh sham baheres, somehow that emphasis cut it off regardless,
or maybe we'll see the word of בשר, besar, the flesh, which
maybe could have just said ימול ערלתו. yimol orlaso. It's saying even
if there's a, there's a spot of צרעת, tzara'as, יקוץ, yikotz, you
should cut it off. ומני מקיים הישמר בנגע הצרעת, umani mikayem hishamer
benega hatzara'as, what about the fact that you're supposed to protect and
guard yourself regarding צרעת, tzara'as, which means don't cut it off?
בשאר מקומות הגוף חוץ ממילה, bish'ar mekomos ha-gufe chutz mi-milah, on other
parts of your body, not on the foreskin. או אינו אלא אפילו
מילה? o eino ela afilu milah? Maybe even on the foreskin? ומני
מקיים ימול בשר ערלתו? umani mikayem yimol besar orlaso? בזמן שאין בו
בהרת. bizman she-ein bo baheres. This is a very similar structure to
what we said before. So maybe even on the foreskin don't cut
it off, and you only do a ברית מילה bris milah when
there's no צרעת tzara'as there. תלמוד לומר: בשר. Talmud lomar basar, The
extra word בשר, besar. could have just said ימול ערלתו, yimol orlaso,
ואף על פי שיש שם בהרת, ve-af al pi she-yesh sham baheres,
even if there's a צרעת. tzara'as. אמר רבא: Amar Rava: So again
because we're sort of back and forth, it seemed to say you
could say this, you could say that, the גמרא Gemara wants to
understand what would have been the logical argument to say each way.
Okay, so, אמר רבא: Amar Rava: האי תנא מעיקרא מאי ניחליה, hai
tana me-ikara mai nichlei, in the beginning why did it think that
it had a good reason to say cut it off? ובסופא
מאי קשייא ליה, u-ve-sofa mai kashyelei, and then why did it say
that maybe not? And in the end had to make recourse to
a פסוק? pasuk? So the גמרא Gemara says: הכי
קאמר, hachi ka-amar, this is what it said: ימול בשר ערלתו ואף
על פי שיש בו בהרת. yimol besar orlaso ve-af al pi she-yesh
bo baheres. First you thought you cut it off even with the
צרעת. tzara'as. ומני מקיים הישמר בנגע הצרעת? u-mani mikayem hishamer benega hatzara'as?
What about the prohibition? בשאר מקומות הגוף חוץ ממילה, bish'ar mekomos ha-gufe
chutz mi-milah, when it's not the foreskin. אפילו מילה דוחה צרעת. afilu
milah dochas tzara'as. But מילה milah would. So so far that's what
the ברייתא braisa essentially said, but this isn't on a פסוק. pasuk.
רבא Rava is now going to insert what the argument would have
been. Okay, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What would be the argument to
say cut it off? דאתי מקל וחומר. de-asi mi-kal va-chomer. You make
a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. Now this קל וחומר kal va-chomer is
going to be similar to what we said before, except using the
conclusion. We've already concluded that מילה milah overrides שבת, Shabbos, right? That
was the earlier גמרא. Gemara. Now that we've concluded that, we're going
to use that information. Here's the קל וחומר: kal va-chomer: ומה שבת
חמורה מילה דוחה אותה, u-ma Shabbos chamura milah docha eslah, so שבת
Shabbos is weighty, מילה milah overrides it, so again מילה milah is
greater than שבת. Shabbos. צרעת לא כל שכן? tzara'as lo kol she-ken?
So how much more so should מילה milah override צרעת? tzara'as? If
you were to ask somebody: what's weightier, שבת Shabbos or צרעת? tzara'as?
Of course they would say שבת. Shabbos. So if מילה milah trumps
שבת, Shabbos, מילה milah should certainly trump צרעת. tzara'as. Pretty good argument.
Okay, ומאי או אינו דקאמר? u-mai o eino de-ka-amar? So why did
it push back? What would be the reaction response to that? הדר
קאמר, hadar ka-amar, here's what it said: ממאי דשבת חמירא? mi-mai de-Shabbos
chamira? What makes you think שבת Shabbos is weightier than צרעת? tzara'as?
Although obviously that would be the intuitive position. דילמא צרעת חמירא. dilma
tzara'as chamira.
Maybe צרעת tzara'as is weightier than שבת. Shabbos. Maybe מילה milah trumps
שבת, Shabbos, but it doesn't trump צרעת. tzara'as. צרעת tzara'as maybe is
more important than שבת. Shabbos. Why would I think צרעת tzara'as is
more important than שבת? Shabbos? שכן, she-ken, like we said before, דוחה
עבודה, docha avoda, because צרעת tzara'as trumps the עבודה, avoda, ועבודה דוחה
את השבת, va-avoda docha es ha-Shabbos, and עבודה avoda trumps שבת. Shabbos.
So it's not so obvious. Maybe צרעת tzara'as is weightier. Maybe מילה
milah overrides שבת Shabbos and it doesn't override צרעת. tzara'as. תלמוד לומר
בשר ואף על פי שיש שם בהרת. Talmud lomar: Besar ve-af al
pi she-yesh sham baheres. So therefore the word tells you, no, the
extra בשר besar, tells you it overrides צרעת. tzara'as. Okay, so since
you could have argued either way, שבת Shabbos is weightier or צרעת
tzara'as is weightier based on this צרעת tzara'as עבודה avoda שבת. Shabbos.
So before we said even if you started knowing that מילה milah
overrides צרעת, tzara'as, you couldn't have learned that it overrides שבת Shabbos
because maybe צרעת tzara'as is weightier and you needed a פסוק pasuk
by שבת. Shabbos. Here we're saying the flip: even if you start
knowing that מילה milah overrides שבת, Shabbos, you can't learn that it
overrides צרעת tzara'as because I could have made an argument that צרעת
tzara'as is weightier and therefore you need a separate פסוק. pasuk. So
you need a פסוק pasuk for each one.
Okay. לשנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another way of saying this: מילה דוחה
את הצרעת מאי טעמא? milah dochas hatzara'as mai ta'ama? Why is מילה
milah override צרעת? tzara'as? דאתי עשה ודחי לא תעשה. de-asi asei ve-dachi
lo sa'asei.
Because the עשה, asei, the מצות עשה mitzvas asei of מילה... milah...
overrides the לא תעשה lo taase of צרעת, tzoraas, meaning maybe the
argument that מילה milah should trump צרעת, tzoraas, now we're shifting gears,
forget this like which is weightier שבת Shabbos or it's צרעת. tzoraas.
Forget that. Here's a simple argument why you should do ברית מילה
bris milah on צרעת. tzoraas. You have a מצות עשה mitzvas ase
to do ברית מילה, bris milah, a prohibition of cutting off צרעת,
tzoraas, a positive מצוה mitzvah trumps a negative. עשה דוחה לא תעשה.
Ase doche lo taase. Okay, and that's forget שבת, Shabbos, forget מילה
milah trumping שבת. Shabbos. Very simple. The מצוה mitzvah of מילה milah
is a מצות עשה, mitzvas ase, it overrides צרעת tzoraas which is
לא תעשה. lo taase. That's a good argument why it should override.
ומהי אונא דקאמר, Umai oino dekaamar, so what's the pushback? הדר קאמר
אימא דאמרינן דאתי עשה ודחי לא תעשה, Hadar kaamar eima damrinan daasi
ase vedachi lo taase, when do we say an עשה ase overrides
לא תעשה גרידא, lo taase greda, when it's a לא תעשה lo
taase by itself? האי, Hai, this idea of not cutting off צרעת,
tzoraas, עשה ולא תעשה הוא, ase velo taase hu, it's a positive
and a negative. The negative is השמר בנגע הצרעת, hishamer benega hatzoraas,
guard yourself, which is understood to be a לא תעשה. lo taase.
And the עשה ase is לשמור ולעשות, lishmor velaasos, so there's a
positive and a negative. So מילה milah cannot override צרעת tzoraas by
the simple equation of עשה ase trumping לא תעשה. lo taase. Okay,
so therefore you're stuck. ומה אני מקיים וביום השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו,
Uma ani mekayem uveyom hashmini yimol bsar orlato, and the מצוה mitzvah
of מילה milah is בזמן שאין בה בהרת, bizman she'ein bah baheres,
maybe when there's no צרעת. tzoraas. So forgetting the whole שבת Shabbos
comparison, it should have trumped צרעת tzoraas because of עשה דוחה לא
תעשה. ase doche lo taase. Maybe yes or maybe not, because maybe
צרעת tzoraas is also another עשה. ase. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: בשר,
besar so you have an extra פסוק, passuk, the flesh. ואף על
פי שיש שם בהרת, Veaf al pi sheyesh sham baheres, even though
there is a בהרת. baheres. Okay. So either way now, whether you
wanted to learn it because it overrides שבת, Shabbos, it should override
צרעת, tzoraas, or you wanted to learn it from עשה ase and
לא תעשה, lo taase, at the end of the day we can't
learn it by a logical argument and we learn it from the
word בשר. basar. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to have a problem
about how you can learn it from the word בשר basar because
בשר basar is not said in all cases of מילה. milah. Let's
take a look. תינח גדול דכתיב ביה בשר, Teinech gadol dichtsiv bei
basar, by an adult it says the word בשר. basar. It says
ואשר לא ימול את בשר ערלתו ונכרתה. Veasher lo yimol es basar
orlato venichresa. If a person who did not circumcise the flesh of
the foreskin, he will be cut off, ונכרתה. venichresa. So who gets
כרת? kares? Only an adult gets כרת. kares. An infant, a minor,
doesn't get כרת. kares. So the word בשר basar is only said
by an adult. So maybe only an adult's ברית מילה bris milah
overrides שבת. Shabbos.
קטן נמי כתיב ביה בשר, Katan nami ksiv bei basar, now it
also does say it by an eight-day-old infant. It says וביום השמיני
ימול בשר ערלתו. uveyom hashmini yimol bsar orlato. That's the פסוק passuk
Rashi quotes it.
Where is it? וביום
השמיני ימול בשר ערלתו,
uveyom hashmini
yimol bsar orlato, very straightforward. Okay, right? So וביום השמיני ימול בשר
ערלתו. uveyom hashmini yimol bsar orlato. So by an eight-day-old infant it
says בשר basar and by an adult it says בשר. basar. But
it doesn't say בשר basar by בינוני מנלן. beinoni minalan. How about
a בינוני? beinoni? Okay, what's a בינוני? beinoni? Sometimes we say a
בינוני beinoni is a guy that's exactly equal in his merits and
his demerits, you know. But here בינוני beinoni means you're no longer
an adult yet, so you don't get כרת, kares, but you're not
eight days old, an infant more than eight days old. It doesn't
say בשר basar by any time the תורה Torah refers to him.
So maybe his ברית מילה bris milah would not override צרעת. tzoraas.
Okay, maybe only the eight-day-old and you could even make an argument,
eight-day-old is because it's the eighth day, that's a special weight. An
adult, there's a special weight of the fact that he would get
כרת. kares. So maybe those override, there it says בשר, basar, but
maybe somebody in the middle ground, it's not the eighth day and
he's not even an adult, maybe it doesn't override צרעת. tzoraas. Okay,
so and there's no word בשר. basar. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר אביי אתיא מביניא. Amar Abaye asya mibeinayah. Fine, you learn it
from the common denominator. מגדול לא אתיא, Migadol lo asya, you can't
learn it straight from a גדול, gadol, שכן ענוש כרת, sheken anush
kares, he has the weightier aspect that he gets כרת. kares. מקטן
לא אתיא, Mikatan lo asya, from an eight-day-old infant you can't learn
that it overrides, שכן מילה בזמנה, sheken milah bizmanah, it's the eighth
day. Each one of them has something weightier. But הצד השוה שבהן,
hatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator, neither one has the weightiness of
the other. So the common denominator שכן המול דוחה את הצרעת, sheken
hamol doche es hatzoraas, that you do a ברית מילה bris milah
and it overrides צרעת. tzoraas. אף כל שהמול דוחה את הצרעת, Af
kol shehamol doche es hatzoraas, everybody's ברית מילה bris milah overrides צרעת.
tzoraas. So we've learned now that it overrides צרעת tzoraas from the
word בשר, basar, and even though it doesn't say בשר basar in
all cases, we learn it out from the common denominator. Question?
Okay, yes. But we only do a ברית bris on שבת Shabbos
if it actually is the eighth day, not any time.
Right, for שבת. Shabbos. Here we're talking about overriding צרעת. tzoraas. Okay,
so what have we said so far? How do we know ברית
מילה bris milah overrides שבת? Shabbos? We've said הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha
l'Moshe m'Sinai, בשמיני, bishmini, ביום, bayom, אות ברית לדורות, os bris l'doros,
various strange פסוקים. psukim. We've also tried to argue it logically from
a קל וחומר kal vachomer from צרעת, tzoraas, but said that קל
וחומר kal vachomer isn't necessarily great because צרעת tzoraas isn't necessarily weightier,
it might just be that it gets in the way of doing
the עבודה. avodah. Okay. How do we know that מילה milah overrides,
now that only eighth day מילה milah overrides שבת. Shabbos. מילה milah
at any time overrides צרעת. tzoraas. How do we know it? We
could have tried to argue it logically from עשה דוחה לא תעשה
ase doche lo taase or from a comparison to ברית מילה bris
milah to שבת. Shabbos. But at the end of the day, those
couldn't have carried the weight by themselves. So So we learn it
from the extra word בשר basar and that tells us that מילה
Milah even not the eighth day overrides צרעת. Tzara'as. So that's basically
what we concluded: eighth day מילה Milah overrides שבת, Shabbos, מילה Milah
at any time overrides צרעת. Tzara'as. Now we just wrap this up
with the following discussion.
אמר רבא אמר מילה בזמנה דחיא לא צריכא קרא. Amar Rava amar
Milah bizmana dechaya lo tzricha kra. An eighth day מילה Milah that
it overrides צרעת Tzara'as you didn't need a פסוק pasuk for that.
That's clearly a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה שבת דחמירה דחיא צרעת
לא
כל שכן? Umah Shabbos dechamira dacha Tzara'as lo kol sheken? So if
שבת Shabbos which is weightier it overrides, how much more so should
it override צרעת? Tzara'as? So since you didn't need the פסוק pasuk
of בשר basar for the eighth day מילה, Milah, that פסוק pasuk
is coming to tell you somebody older than eight days. That was
our question. How do you know somebody older than eight days? So
the answer is because eighth day you could learn it totally by
the argument that if it overrides שבת Shabbos it overrides צרעת. Tzara'as.
So אמר ליה רב ספרא לרבא, Amar leh Rav Safra leRava, so
we're really repeating things we said before. ממאי דשבת חמירה? Mimai deShabbos
chamira? What makes you think that שבת Shabbos is weightier than צרעת?
Tzara'as? דילמא צרעת חמירה? Dilma Tzara'as chamira? Maybe צרעת Tzara'as is weightier?
Again, sounds bizarre, but here's the argument. שכן דחיא עבודה, Sheken dacha
avoda, צרעת Tzara'as trumps עבודה, avoda, you don't cut it off to
do the עבודה, avoda, ועבודה דחיא שבת, ve'avoda dacha Shabbos, and עבודה
avoda trumps שבת, Shabbos, so צרעת Tzara'as is weightier than שבת. Shabbos.
גמרא Gemara says no. התם לאו משום דחמירה צרעת, Hatam lav mishum
dechamira Tzara'as,
it's not because צרעת Tzara'as is weightier than שבת Shabbos or weightier
than the עבודה, avoda, אלא משום דגברא הוא דלא חזי, Ella mishum
degavra hu delo chazi, even if you were to cut off the
צרעת Tzara'as the גברא gavra would not be able to do the
עבודה avoda today, he would only have to at least wait until
tomorrow. אמאי? Amay? Says the גמרא, Gemara, why wouldn't he be fit?
וליקץ בהרתא וליעבד? Velikatz baharta veliyavad? Cut it off and let him
do the עבודה. avoda. So it really is true that it's weightier
than the עבודה, avoda, just cut it off. גמרא Gemara says no.
מחוסר טבילה הוא, Mechusar tevillah hu, he'd have to go to the
מקוה. mikvah. And since he'd have to go to the מקוה, mikvah,
he would only be able to do the עבודה avoda the next
day after the sun had set. So therefore it's not that the
prohibition of cutting off the צרעת Tzara'as is weightier than doing the
עבודה, avoda, it's that there's no immediate
עבודה avoda that would trump. It would only be for the future
and to not do something for the future is a different conversation,
but not right here. It's not that צרעת Tzara'as trumps, it's that
there's no עבודה avoda today that's going to be possible to be
done regardless. גמרא Gemara says תינח נגעים טמאים? tenach nega'im tmey'im? I
get it when it's a נגע nega that is טמא. tamei. נגעים
טהורים מאי איכא למימר? Nega'im tehorim may ika lemeimar?
How about if it's a נגע nega that's טהור? tahor? There could
be certain נגעים nega'im that don't make you טמא tamei and that
there still is, because they have to be inspected by the כהן,
Kohen, still a prohibition of cutting them off. So
why by those, you know, how by those, let me just
check רש"י Rashi a second. Starting to see תוספות Tosafot here.
Yeah, one second.
So basically according to רש"י Rashi the question is that I'll still
prove that the prohibition of cutting off צרעת Tzara'as is weightier because
you could have צרעת Tzara'as which is preventing the כהן Kohen from
doing the עבודה, avoda, you wouldn't cut it off even if the
cutting off would allow him to do the עבודה. avoda. How would
it allow him to do the עבודה? avoda? Because he wouldn't be
טמא. tamei. It could be a צרעת Tzara'as that he's not טמא,
tamei, he doesn't have to wait till tomorrow, he could do the
עבודה avoda today and even so you're not cutting it off because
you're not allowed to cut off a צרעת Tzara'as that is טהור.
tahor. So therefore you see that it actually is true that the
צרעת Tzara'as is weightier than the עבודה. avoda. So let's take a
look. אלא אמר רב אשי: Ella amar Rav Ashi: היכא אמרינן דאתי
עשה ודחי לא תעשה? Hechi amrina de'ati aseh vedachi lo ta'aseh? כגון
מילה בצרעת. Kegon milah betzara'as.
So when do we say that an עשה aseh comes and overrides
a לא תעשה? lo ta'aseh? That would be like מילה milah in
צרעת. Tzara'as. אי נמי ציצית וכלאים. Inami tzitzis vekilayim.
So when those two are, meaning here he's explaining why we don't
cut off the צרעת Tzara'as to let you do the עבודה, avoda,
even if you don't have to go to the מקוה mikvah and
you could do the עבודה avoda right now, we still don't cut
it off. Why not? And he says it's not because צרעת Tzara'as
is weightier but it's because they're not coming in direct confrontation. When
do we say one thing trumps another, an עשה aseh overrides לא
תעשה? lo ta'aseh? For example, מילה milah you cut off the צרעת
Tzara'as because when you're doing the מילה, milah, when you're overriding the
לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, cutting off the צרעת Tzara'as is the moment
that you're doing the מילה. milah. Or אי נמי ציצית וכלאים. Inami
tzitzis vekilayim. If you put on ציצית tzitzis on a linen garment,
the blue string has to be made out of wool. So therefore
you're doing כלאים kilayim at the exact moment you're violating the prohibition
of כלאים, kilayim, you're doing the מצוה mitzvah of ציצית. tzitzis. So
when do we say one thing can override another, it trumps, let's
say עשה דוחה לא תעשה? aseh docheh lo ta'aseh? It's because at
the exact moment, בעידנא דמתעקר לאו, be'idna demit'akar lav, at the moment
the prohibition is being violated, קמוקים עשה, kamukim aseh, you're fulfilling the
עשה, aseh, like you're cutting off the צרעת Tzara'as but you're doing
the מילה. milah. הכא Hacha here,
here's why you don't cut off... צרעת tzara'at and let the guy
do עבודה, avodah, even if he could do עבודה avodah today. It's
not because the צרעת tzara'at is weightier, it's not weightier than עבודה,
avodah, but because they're not really in direct
confrontation. בעידנא דמיתעקר לאו, be'idna de'mit'akar lav, when you cut off the
צרעת, tzara'at, לא קמוקמי עשה, lo kamukim aseh, you're not being מקיים
mekayem the עשה. aseh. So the argument says way, צרעת tzara'at is
weightier than שבת Shabbos because of this whole transitive axiom of inequality,
we have two answers. One answer is that it's not weightier. Even
if you cut it off, he can't do the עבודה, avodah, so
it's not really like it's going to enable him to do the
עבודה avodah today. And the other answer is even if he could
do the עבודה avodah today, it was טהור צרעת, tahor tzara'at, but
it's not at the moment you violate, so the fact that you
don't do it is not because it's weightier, the fact that you
don't do it is because they're not directly confronting. If they were
directly confronting, עבודה avodah would trump. But because it's only, it's not
a direct confrontation, nothing allows you at this moment to violate the
prohibition. והא דרב ורב ספרא, veha de-Rav ve-Rav Safra, now the גמרא
Gemara ends. This issue of רב Rav and רב ספרא Rav Safra
is a תנאי, tannai, it's a debate of תנאים. tannaim. דתניא, detanya,
דף פ"ג ע"ב, daf peh gimmel amud bet, בשר ואף על פי
שיש שם בהרת ימול, basar ve'af al pi she'yesh sham baheret yimol,
דברי רבי יאשיה. divrei Rabbi Yoshiya. So he learns that you cut
off the צרעת tzara'at from the word בשר. basar. Okay, even if
there's צרעת. tzara'at. רבי יונתן אומר, Rabbi Yonatan omer, אינו צריך, eino
tzarich, you don't need to tell me that in eighth day מילה
milah you don't do it, שבת חמורה דוחה צרעת לא כל שכן,
Shabbat chamura docha tzara'at lo kol she'ken, if it overrides שבת, Shabbat,
how much more so should it not, should it override צרעת, tzara'at,
at least for the eighth day. So what do you have here?
You basically have eighth day מילה milah overrides שבת, Shabbat, non-eighth day
מילה milah you cut the צרעת tzara'at overrides צרעת. tzara'at. What is
the logic why you do it? From both of those we have,
we have a couple of פסוקים, pesukim, possible, whatever, but in צרעת
tzara'at we also have a פסוק. pasuk. You can't say עשה דוחה
לא תעשה aseh docheh lo ta'aseh by the מילה milah and צרעת
tzara'at although they are directly confronting because the prohibition of צרעת tzara'at
is also a positive מצוה. mitzvah. So you learn it from an
extra thing of בשר. basar. In the larger context, there's a question
of can you make this bizarre argument that צרעת tzara'at is weightier
than עבודה avodah and then שבת. Shabbat. עבודה avodah trumps שבת, Shabbat,
צרעת tzara'at overrides עבודה. avodah. And the גמרא Gemara pushes back. It's
not that צרעת tzara'at is so weighty. There's a reason why, either
because even if you cut it off, you're still going to be
טמא, tamei, or even if you say when you cut it off
you'll be טהור, tahor, but it's not directly confronting the עבודה. avodah.
So the fact that you don't do it doesn't prove that it's
weightier, it just proves that you don't have the override of the
עבודה avodah because they're not in direct confrontation. And therefore you really
cannot argue that צרעת tzara'at is weightier. Okay, we'll continue with מילה
milah on שבת Shabbat tomorrow. All right.