Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ד' עמוד א',
dalet amud alef, שבועות Shavuos 4, and we pick up eleven lines
down on דף ד' daf dalet where it says
במאי אוקימתא. b'mai okimta. And the issue that we're dealing with right
now is פשט p'shat in the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah said,
or who is it going according to? The משנה Mishnah said that
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumas mikdash v'kodshav, someone is טמא tamei and enters
into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or טמא tamei and eats a
קרבן korban is שתים שהן ארבע, shtayim she'hen arba, two that is
four. The two that is four is that you know that the
two that everyone agrees that you're חייב chayav or that's obvious is
that you are unaware that you are טמא. tamei. And then the
two things you could do wrong there is either eat a קרבן
korban or go into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The two that
are four is that those exact same scenarios that you went into
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or ate a קרבן, korban, but instead
of not being aware that you were טמא, tamei, you were not
aware that you were eating a קרבן korban or not aware you
were going into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. That's the two that's
four over there. And then it says שבועה Shavuah is two that
is four. The two that is four is a שבועה Shavuah to
the future. You say, you know, להרע או להיטיב, l'hara o l'hetiv,
I will eat something and you don't eat it, I won't eat
it and you do eat
it. Okay, and then you would bring a קרבן korban for that
if you did not do your שבועה. Shavuah. And then the four
is that it's referring to the past.
You took a שבועה, Shavuah, I ate when you didn't eat, or
I didn't eat when you did eat. Okay, so that's the two
that is four, and then it also goes on about צרעת Tzaraat
and about שבת Shabbos and so on. So the גמרא Gemara has
a problem. The problem the גמרא Gemara has is that these two
opinions of two that is four for טומאה tumah and for
שבועה Shavuah do not fit to any one תנא. Tanna. When it
comes to the issue of
טומאה, tumah, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're only חייב chayav a
קרבן korban if you forget that you were טמא, tamei, not if
you forgot that it was the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or that
you were eating
קדשים. kodshim. It's only רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says the two
that is four, that it even includes forgetting בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and forgetting קדשים. kodshim. So the first part can only go like
רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. The second part, the two that is four
that you bring a קרבן korban for a שבועה Shavuah not only
in the future but in the past, that is a רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva position. Only רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says you don't bring
a קרבן korban for the past. So the first part, the two
that is four by טומאה, tumah, is only a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael position, and the second part, two that is four by a
שבועה, Shavuah, is only a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position. How do
we make sense of it? So yesterday what we said was, and
that's how the גמרא Gemara is going to pick up today, במאי
אוקימתא, b'mai okimta, so how did you explain the
משנה? Mishnah? כרבי ישמעאל ולמלקות, k'Rabbi Yishmael u'l'malkus, that fine, it's all
going like רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, but we're not talking about a
קרבן, korban, we're talking about מלקות. malkus. So that you actually intentionally
eat a קרבן korban when you're טמא tamei or you go into
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash when you're טמא tamei and you get
מלקות. malkus. Or you go ahead and you're warned not to take
a false שבועה Shavuah and you take a false שבועה Shavuah and
you get מלקות. malkus. And that's where everyone would agree, and that's
where that could work for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael because the two
that is four. Because it doesn't matter, future or past, it's not
about not knowing that you're טמא tamei or whatever, everything is done
intentionally and willfully and you get מלקות malkus for it and the
whole משנה Mishnah is talking about מלקות. malkus. Now one of the
cases of a שבועה Shavuah actually was passive, right? You say that
you will eat and you passively don't eat. So we said yesterday,
fine, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael would say that you get מלקות malkus
even for passive. So now we are saying the whole משנה, Mishnah,
the way we solved the problem, is it's going that you're willful
and that it's for מלקות. malkus. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to say, wait, let's see if this could work. מראות נגעים מאי
מלקות איכא? mar'os nega'im mai malkus ika? Okay, but the משנה Mishnah
also tells two that is four by צרעת. Tzaraat. So what's the
case of מלקות malkus for that? If it's about קרבן, korban, תוספות
Tosafos says it could be that after your צרעת Tzaraat is over
you bring a קרבן. korban. But if it's about מלקות, malkus, what
מלקות malkus is there? You're just טמא. tamei. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, בקוצץ בהרתו. bikotzes baharto. We would be talking that you
would cut off your leprous spot, it's not leprous whatever, your צרעת,
Tzaraat, so that you won't become טמא. tamei. כרבי
אבין אמר רבי אילעאי, k'Rabbi Avin amar Rabbi Illai, like רבי אבין
Rabbi Avin says in the name of רבי אילעאי, Rabbi Illai, דאמר
de'amar רבי אבין Rabbi Avin אמר amar רבי אילעאי Rabbi Illai כל
מקום שנאמר השמר פן ואל אינו אלא לא תעשה. kol makom shene'emar
hishamer pen v'al eino ela lo sa'asei. Whenever the תורה Torah says
lest, don't, or forfend, or whatever, השמר פן ואל, hishamer pen v'al,
it is a לא תעשה, lo sa'asei, a negative prohibition. So the
תורה Torah says השמר בנגע הצרעת, hishamer b'nega hatzaraat, guard yourself regarding
the affliction of צרעת. Tzaraat. And חז"ל Chazal understand what that means
is that you are prohibited from cutting off your צרעת Tzaraat to
prevent yourself from becoming טמא. tamei. So that would be a case
where you would get מלקות malkus in the צרעת Tzaraat scenario, two
that are four, you have to know what makes you טמא tamei
for צרעת. Tzaraat. Now תוספות Tosafos asks that it seems from another
גמרא Gemara that actually you transgress and get מלקות malkus even if
something might be צרעת Tzaraat and you're just... trying to prevent the
כהן Kohein from seeing it and you're trying to prevent the risk.
So, you know, why is it sounding here like only if it's
actual צרעת? tzaraas? But be that as it may, that would be
the scenario of מלקות malkus if we wanted to say the whole
משנה mishna was מלקות. malkus. So now the גמרא Gemara says,
okay,
but now let's move on to the שבת Shabbos case. יציאות שבת
מה מלקות איכא? yetzios Shabbos mah malkus ika? לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת
בית דין הוא? lav shenitan le'azharas misas beis din hu?
So it says okay, but the משנה mishna also says there's two
ways, you know, carrying on שבת Shabbos is two that is four.
How do you get מלקות malkus for carrying on שבת? Shabbos? The
negative prohibition of שבת, Shabbos, you know, do not do work on
שבת Shabbos is a negative prohibition the punishment which is execution in
the court, מיתת בית דין. misas beis din. וכל לאו שניתן לאזהרת
מיתת בית דין אין לוקין עליו. v'chol lav shenitan le'azharas misas beis
din ein lokin alav. Any negative prohibition whose punishment is, you know,
execution in the
court you can't get מלקות malkus for it. Meaning if somebody said
to you don't carry on שבת Shabbos because you'll get מלקות. malkus.
So now they can't put this person to death because and he
said I don't care and I'm going to do it anyway. They
can't put him to death because he hasn't been warned about that
he'll be put to death. Can they give him מלקות? malkus? And
the general answer is no. This negative prohibition, the punishment assigned to
it was מיתת בית דין. misas beis din. So even though this
person transgressed a negative prohibition there's no way you can give him
מלקות malkus for that. You don't just say generically any negative prohibition
you can get מלקות. malkus. Okay, so now שבת Shabbos doesn't work
if we're talking about מלקות. malkus. It works for קרבן korban if
you did it בשוגג b'shogeg but it doesn't work for מלקות. malkus.
So the גמרא Gemara says ומשום הכי קמוקמינא כרבי ישמעאל. v'shum hacha
kamukmina k'rabbi yishmael. That's why we said that the משנה mishna when
it's talking about מלקות malkus is going like רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
Why? Because there's another position of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. דאמר רבי
ישמעאל d'amar Rabbi Yishmael happens to be of the position that לאו
שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין לוקין עליו. lav shenitan le'azharas misas beis
din lokin alav. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is actually of the position
that even a negative prohibition that the punishment is execution, if you
warned the guy not that he would be executed but you warned
him he would get lashes you would be able to give lashes.
Okay, so now we're saying the whole משנה mishna is רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. You know you get מלקות malkus for going into the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash טמא tamei or eating a קרבן korban טמא.
tamei. And the whole משנה mishna is מלקות. malkus. So that would
be going into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or eating a קרבן.
korban. That would be taking a שבועה shevuah for the future or
the past. That would be cutting off your, you know, your צרעת
tzaraas and that would be carrying on שבת. Shabbos. All of those
could be מלקות malkus scenarios. But the גמרא Gemara is not buying
it yet. So let's keep on reading. הא ha
says the גמרא, Gemara, one minute. הלאו הכי קאים כרבי עקיבא? halav
hachi kaim k'rabbi akiva? You're saying oh we said it was רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael to deal with this problem that שבת Shabbos you
can get מלקות. malkus. So are you suggesting that we could have
said the משנה mishna was רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? We only got
here because the משנה mishna didn't work like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
You know, קשיא דידיעות. kasha d'yedios.
So you're saying ah that's why we said רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
to deal with the שבת Shabbos problem. No we said it was
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael because the whole thing of the טומאה tumah
doesn't work according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
doesn't agree to the two that is four by the טומאה. tumah.
So why did you say that you know the whole reason for
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was the שבת Shabbos reason? There's also the
טומאה tumah reason that that needs to go like רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. So the גמרא Gemara says no.
לאו אמרת רבי ישמעאל היא למלקות רבי עקיבא נמי היא למלקות. lav
amarta Rabbi Yishmael hi l'malkus Rabbi Akiva nami hi l'malkus. גמרא Gemara
says no no no no. When did we say that the משנה
mishna didn't work like רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? That the two that
is four for טומאה? tumah? When we thought we were talking about
a קרבן. korban. And then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you only
bring a קרבן korban if you forget that you're טמא tamei not
if you forget the מקדש וקדשיו. mikdash v'kodshov.
Okay that's why we said that the first part couldn't be רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. But now that we said we're not dealing in
קרבן korban land anymore we're only in מלקות malkus land then there's
no debate. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael all
their debates were about קרבן. korban. So now that we're not talking
about קרבן, korban, טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumas mikdash v'kodshov could be רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, שבועות shevuos could be
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael if you bracket
the לאו שאין בו מעשה lav she'ein bo ma'aseh part of it.
Everything could go like everybody because it's all about מלקות malkus it's
not their קרבן korban debate. But we had to say רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael because only according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael do you
get מלקות malkus for שבת. Shabbos. All right the only thing is
we also have to say it was him because of לאו שאין
בו מעשה lav she'ein bo ma'aseh but whatever. The גמרא Gemara is
still not going to stick with this anyway. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this,
it's not buying it. אי
הכי i hachi says the
גמרא Gemara ידיעות התראות מיבעי ליה. yedios hatra'os mibei lei. Why did
it say becoming aware of טומאה tumah if it's a case that
you're intentional and you're getting מלקות? malkus? It should have said if
you're warned about טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא Gemara says הא לא
קשיא ha lo kasha that's not difficult. תני ידיעות דהתראות. tani yedios
d'hatra'os. It means you were aware that you were warned and you
were aware of it. Okay that's obviously a very bad read. We
never use the word ידיעות yedios except in the context of you
not having initially been aware. But so and now the גמרא Gemara
is going to deal the sort of final blow that you cannot
say our משנה mishna is about מלקות. malkus. אי הכי, Iy hachi,
says the גמרא, Gemara, שתים שהן ארבע, shtayim she-hen arba, תרתי הוא
דהוין. tartai hu de-avyan. First of all, says the גמרא, Gemara, if
we’re talking about מלקות, malkus, what does the משנה Mishnah mean two
that is four by טומאה? tumah? There’s only two scenarios by טומאה
tumah if you’re doing it intentionally. You’re טמא tamai and you go
into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you’re טמא tamai and you eat
קדשים. kodshim. The only way you get four is because you’re talking
about what did you forget? Did you forget you were טמא tamai
or did you forget that it was the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash?
Did you forget you were טמא tamai or did you forget that
you were eating that it was קדשים? kodshim? But you can’t have
four if you’re talking about willful. If you’re talking about willful, you
only have two. ותו, Ve-su, and also, אלא שיהיה ידיעה בתחילה וידיעה
בסוף והעלם בינתיים. ela she-yehei yediya ba-techila ve-yediya ba-sof ve-helam bein-tayim. The
משנה Mishnah says we’re talking about a case where you knew at
the beginning that you were טמא tamai and that it was קדשים,
kodshim, and you knew at the end, and you became and you
were unaware in the middle. That’s the only time that you bring
a קרבן. korban. Fine, that idea ידיעה בתחילה ידיעה בסוף העלם בינתיים
yediya ba-techila yediya ba-sof helam bein-tayim is the criteria for bringing a
קרבן. korban.
But but הלמה למלקות מה עבידתייהו? ha-lama le-malkus mah avidatyeihu? But if
we’re talking about getting lashes, then there’s no scenario that you became
unaware. Lashes is all about being מזיד meizid and willful. ותו, Ve-su,
and in addition, הרי זה בעולה ויורד. harei zeh be-oleh ve-yored. That’s
like the knockout punch. We could have just started with that. The
end of the משנה Mishnah says, you know, if you do this
or whatever, by these cases of טומאה, tumah, you bring a קרבן
עולה ויורד. korban oleh ve-yored. So we’re clearly talking about קרבן. korban.
You cannot say the משנה Mishnah is טומאה. tumah. Is excuse me
מלקות. malkus. So we’re back to square one. Okay, we’re clearly talking
about a קרבן. korban. But the two that is four by the
טומאה, tumah, that’s only a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael position. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says you’re only חייב chayav if you forget the טומאה,
tumah, not if you forget the קרבן korban or the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So the ability to have two that is four is
only a רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. By שבועה, shavuah, the ability to
have two that is four, that includes also a past שבועה, shavuah,
is only רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So now that it’s a קרבן
korban we got a problem. Clause one is רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
clause two is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא אמר רב יוסף, ela amar Rav Yosef, so rather says רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, רבי היא ונסיב לה אליבא דתנאי. Rebbi hee ve-nasiv
lah aliba de-tannai. Fine, it can’t be all רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
or all רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. But the editor of the משנה
Mishnah is רבי, Rebbi, רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi, and he
is taking one opinion of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and one opinion
of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. He’s taking two different תנאים tannaim and
putting them together. Okay, בידיעות נסיב לה כרבי ישמעאל. bi-yedi'os nasiv lah
ke-Rabbi Yishmael. When it came to the טומאה tumah case, you know,
he said he took the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael position that it
applies even forgetting מקדש וקדשים. Mikdash ve-Kodshim.
Okay. בשבועות נסיב לה כרבי עקיבא. bi-shvu'os nasiv lah ke-Rabbi Akiva. And
when it came to the שבועות shvu'os case, he took the רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position that says it applies even to the past.
And you could understand why. Here he is, he wants to collect
two that are four. He got two that’s four by שבת, Shabbos,
two that’s four by נגעים. nega'im. So you have a two that’s
four by שבועה, shavuah, a two that’s four by טומאת מקדש וקדשיו.
tumas mikdash ve-kadashav. So okay, one goes like one תנא, tanna, one
goes like the other תנא. tanna. They’re not inherently contradictory. There’s no
reason you have to hold one way by one and you can’t
hold the other way by the other. So he wants to just
collect all the twos that are fours. Okay, but he doesn’t have
to be going like any one particular תנא. tanna. Ah, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר
רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב כהנא. amrisa le-shma'ta
kameih de-Rav Kahana. I said this position of רב יוסף Rav Yosef
in front of רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, that רב יוסף Rav Yosef
said that the author of the משנה Mishnah was רבי Rebbi and
he’s taking different
תנאים. tannaim. ואמר לי, ve-amar lee, and רב כהנא Rav Kahana said
to me, לא תימא נסיב לה אליבא דתנאי וליה לא סבירא ליה.
lo teima nasiv lah aliba de-tannai ve-lei lo sevira lei. Don’t say
what I just said a minute ago, that רבי Rebbi is adopting
putting in the משנה Mishnah different positions of תנאים tannaim but he
himself doesn’t hold like that. You know, he himself we don’t know,
he could be an all רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva man, an all
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael man. Any but he’s just collecting cases in
the משנה Mishnah of two that are four. Don’t say that. Rather,
אלא רבי טעמיה דנפשיה מפרש. ela Rebbi ta'ameh de-nafsheh mefaresh. רבי Rebbi
actually holds like both positions in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי Rebbi holds
that when it comes to טומאה, tumah, we hold two that is
four, which is a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael position. And he says
that when it comes to שבועות, shvu'os, we hold two that is
four, which is a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position. Okay, and now
we’re going to show how he holds each one of those. דתניא,
De-tanya, now okay, as we taught in the ברייתא. braisa. מנין שאינו
חייב אלא על שיש בו ידיעה בתחילה וידיעה בסוף והעלם בינתיים? minal
she-eino chayav ela al she-yesh bo yediya ba-techila ve-yediya ba-sof ve-helam bein-tayim?
How do we know this basic principle that when it comes to
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumas mikdash ve-kadashav, you know,
it’s not enough that you were ignorant and that you were aware?
That’s every קרבן korban that you bring בשוגג, be-shogeg, right?
Somebody didn’t forgot that it was שבת Shabbos and they went ahead
and they did something. Or they didn’t know that something was אסור
assur on שבת Shabbos and they did it and then they became
aware. At the time you did the sin you weren’t aware and
then obviously you became aware later or you wouldn’t bring a קרבן.
korban. By טומאה, tumah, by טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumas mikdash ve-kadashav, there’s
an additional requirement that you did know and you forgot. There was
a ידיעה yediya even בתחילה. ba-techila. You knew you were טמא, tamai,
you knew it was the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. And you forgot,
and then you sinned, and then you became aware. So where do
we get this idea that by טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumas mikdash vekodshav
you have to have known at the beginning? So the גמרא gemara
says like this, מניין ש, minayin she, it’s a ברייתא braisa says
like this, מניין שאינו חייב אלא שיש בו ידיעה בתחילה וידיעה בסוף
והעלם בינתיים. minayin she’eino chayav ela sheyesh bo yedia batchila viyedia basof
ve’helam beintayim. תלמוד לומר ונעלם ונעלם שתי פעמים דברי רבי עקיבא. talmud
lomar venelam venelam shtei pe’amim divrei rebbe akiva. Right? The תורה torah
says, it says ונעלם. venelam. Okay? ונעלם ממנו והוא טמא ואשם ונעלם
ממנו. venelam mimenu vehu tamei ve’ashem venelam mimenu.
So it says twice that it was hidden from you. So to
say it was hidden twice means in a way suggesting that there
had to be two things you knew. Okay? So or you had
to know twice. All right? So you knew initially and then you
forgot, and then you knew again at the end. That’s how רבי
עקיבא rebbe akiva learns that you have to have known initially. רבי
אומר, rebbe omer, רבי rebbe says, אינו צריך, eino tzarich, you don’t
need it to say ונעלם venelam twice. הרי הוא אומר, harei hu
omer, the פסוק pasuk says, ונעלם, venelam, the very fact that it
says it was hidden from you, top of דף ד עמוד ב,
daf daled amud beis, מכלל דידע. mikelal deyada. Okay? Means that you
knew. Because somehow he understands ונעלם venelam means it became hidden from
you. You knew and then it became hidden. Now the גמרא’s gemara’s
going to question that. Maybe ונעלם venelam means you never knew. But
רבי rebbe is saying from one ונעלם, venelam, which I am reading
as it became hidden, I can infer that initially you knew. And
then you obviously then wind up knowing again that you had sinned
or else you wouldn’t bring a קרבן. korban. And it also says
the פסוק pasuk והוא ידע, vehu yada, it says ונעלם ממנו והוא
ידע venelam mimenu vehu yada and you knew, הרי כאן שתי ידיעות.
harei kan shtei yedios. So the first ונעלם venelam suggests you knew
and you forgot, and the second one says and now you remembered
again. So that’s how you know there has to be a ידיעה
yedia in the beginning and a ידיעה yedia at the end. So
he’s not disagreeing with רבי עקיבא rebbe akiva that there needs ידיעה
yedia at the beginning and the ידיעה yedia at the end, but
he’s learning it out with only one ונעלם, venelam, not two ונעלמים.
venelamim. So now the גמרא gemara says, and this is the part
that’s relevant for us, אם כן מה תלמוד לומר ונעלם ונעלם? im
kein mah talmud lomar venelam venelam? So why does it say ונעלם
venelam twice if you only need one? לחייב על העלם טומאה ועל
העלם מקדש, lechayev al helam tuma ve’al helam mikdash, to tell you
that there are two types of categories you can that can be
hidden from you. It could be hidden from you that you’re טמא
tamei and it could be hidden from you that it’s the בית
המקדש beis hamikdash or that it’s קדשים. kodshim. Okay? So now we
clearly רבי rebbe is saying against רבי עקיבא rebbe akiva that you
bring the קרבן korban of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumas mikdash vekodshav, he’s
holding like רבי ישמעאל rebbe yishmael that even if it’s hidden from
you not just that you’re טמא tamei but even in the scenario
when it’s hidden from you מקדש mikdash and קדשים. kodshim. So that’s
how we know רבי rebbe himself personally holds by the first case
of the משנה, mishna, two that are four by טומאת מקדש וקדשיו
tumas mikdash vekodshav like רבי ישמעאל. rebbe yishmael. Okay, so now the
גמרא gemara says, good, that was good going. Okay, אשכחן בידיעות דאיתיה
לטעמיה דנפשיה. ashkechan biyedi'os d'islei ta’ama d'nafshei.
Great. You proved the first part of the משנה mishna about טומאה,
tuma, he holds like רבי ישמעאל, rebbe yishmael, two that is four,
and that you’re חייב chayav on also being נעלם ne’elam מקדש וקדשים.
mikdash vekodshim. So שבועות דלית ליה טעמיה דנפשיה מנלן? shavuos d’leis lei
ta’amei d’nafshei minalan? So when it comes to שבועות, shavuos, when it
comes to actually the idea of, you know, that you bring a
קרבן korban for both future שבועות shavuos and past שבועות shavuos where
we don’t see
that
he has expressed his own opinion. We don’t know, רבי rebbe never
expressed his own opinion by the שבועות shavuos that the it applies
the קרבן korban applies even to the case of the past. So
if that’s true, דלית ליה טעמיה דנפשיה, d’leis lei ta’amei d’nafshei, he’s
never expressed his opinion by the קרבן korban by the שבועה, shavuah,
מנלן? minalan? How do you, where do you come off saying that
רבי rebbe himself also holds in that case like רבי עקיבא rebbe
akiva that it applies to שבועה shavuah in the past as well?
So the גמרא gemara says, סברה הוא, sevara hu, we can figure
it out logically. Why? You’re right. We don’t have any text that
proves it, but it is logical. רבי עקיבא מאי טעמא קמחייב לשעבר?
rebbe akiva mai ta’ama kimechayev l’she’avar? Why does רבי עקיבא rebbe akiva
say that a שבועה shavuah you’re חייב chayav not just for the
future but the case of the קרבן korban also applies to a
past שבועה, shavuah, שבועה shavuah referring to the past? דדריש ריבוי ומיעוט,
didarish ribuy u’miyut, because he makes he uses his principle of interpreting
when the תורה torah uses broad phrases and narrow phrases, it’s the
his hermeneutic principle is ריבוי ומיעוט. ribuy u’miyut. I’ll explain that in
a minute. רבי נמי דריש ריבוי ומיעוט. rebbe nami darish ribuy u’miyut.
רבי rebbe also says uses the ריבוי ribuy and מיעוט miyut approach.
Now, what is ריבוי ומיעוט? ribuy u’miyut? So ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy u’miyut
is in contrast to כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u’ferat u’klal. All right?
Classic example is ועשית מנורת זהב טהור מקשה תיעשה המנורה. ve’asisa menoras
zahav tahor miksha te’aseh hamenora. So the way חז"ל chazal read it,
ועשית מנורה ve’asisa menora is a general statement. זהב טהור zahav tahor
is very specific. And then תיעשה המנורה te’aseh hamenora is very general.
Can the מנורה menora be made out of other metals? Can it
be made out of wood, etc.? So it depends how broad you
make that based on whether you hold ריבוי ribuy and מיעוט miyut
or כלל ופרט. klal u’ferat. Now let’s start with כלל ופרט. klal
u’ferat. Everybody knows כלל ופרט klal u’ferat and כלל ופרט וכלל. klal
u’ferat u’klal. כלל ופרט klal u’ferat means that we that looks at
the concrete thing as as being as actually being the one thing,
the specific... specific instantiation of the כלל. klal. So for example, if
you know my wife tells me, go to the store and get
something for dinner, fish. Okay, then I'm saying like okay, she wants
fish. It's true she said get something for dinner which was general,
but then she was specific, she said fish. Okay, so I have
to go get fish. Alright, so that's כלל ופרט. klal uprat. It
thinks that once it makes it specific, all you have is the
specific. And then it and then she but then she goes on
and she makes it more general. You know, get something for dinner,
fish, just get something. Alright, so when she first said fish, it
sounded like that's all she wanted. Now it's כלל ופרט וכלל, klal
uprat ukhlal, she's being more general, so just get something, I'm going
to assume means something like fish. You know, maybe like chicken, you
know, but like don't go ahead and get steak, don't go ahead
and get a vegetarian dish, I don't know, depends which way you
go there. But okay, something that's close enough to fish but not
something that would be considered radically different. That's because I initially assumed
that the פרט prat was only that thing. That's the principle of
כלל ופרט וכלל. klal uprat ukhlal. You apply it to the
מנורה, menorah, ועשית מנורת, ve'asita menorat, you can make it out of
anything, זהב, zahav, only gold, תעשה את המנורה. ta'aseh et hamenorah. So
okay, so now we went from only gold to being more broad,
so any metal. But things that aren't metal, no. Alright, that would
be the כלל ופרט וכלל. klal uprat ukhlal.
How is ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי ribbuy umi'ut veribbuy different?
ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי ribbuy umi'ut veribbuy doesn't buy that
the specific case is the only case because then you wouldn't have
said something general to begin with. So going back to this case,
my wife says get something for dinner, fish, so why didn't she
just say get fish? Why did she say get something, fish? So
already I assume that the fish is not a פרט, prat, is
not specifying, לפרט, lepharet, it's not specifying, it is a מיעוט, mi'ut,
it is narrowing. So already by the time once she said get
something and then fish, it's not just fish. Those two work together,
general and narrowing, to say things like fish, you know, maybe chicken,
maybe tofu, but don't get something that's no protein and don't get
something that's a steak. Okay, already I have so by the second
stage of ריבוי ומיעוט, ribbuy umi'ut, you're already where you would be
at the third stage of כלל ופרט וכלל. klal uprat ukhlal. You
already are saying that you've narrowed it but you've not specified and
it's something like the specific example. Then when you get to the
next ריבוי, ribbuy, go ahead and just you know get something, now
pretty much means you know get anything you want, except don't get
junk food, alright, get something healthy. Alright, so the so ריבוי ומיעוט
וריבוי ribbuy umi'ut veribbuy gets you to is always going to be
broader than כלל ופרט וכלל. klal uprat ukhlal. Okay, and the only
thing that where כלל ופרט וכלל klal uprat ukhlal by the end
says anything only something like the specific example, you abstract the specific
example. ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי ribbuy umi'ut veribbuy says by ריבוי ומיעוט ribbuy
umi'ut you've already abstracted the specific. By the time you get to
the next ריבוי, ribbuy, you've included everything except something that is the
most different. So going back to the case of the מנורה, menorah,
it would be, you know, when it says make a מנורה, menorah,
then it says gold, already those two work together to say make
it out of any metal. And then when it says again make
it out of a מנורה, menorah, now you can even make it
out of wood. The thing you can't make it out of is
pottery, that would be considered totally different. Okay, now what does that
have to do so that's the general debate. And how what does
that have to do with us? So with us, you know, the
פסוק pasuk says, you know, כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים להרע או להטיב
לכל אשר יבטא אדם בשבועה. ki tishava levate bisefatayim lehara o lehetiv
lekhol asher yivate adam bishvuah.
If you enunciate to do good or to do evil, anything that
a person will enunciate. So if you do כלל ופרט וכלל, klal
uprat ukhlal,
so if you do כלל ופרט וכלל, klal uprat ukhlal, then you
know
so when it first says כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים להרע או להטיב,
ki tishava levate bisefatayim lehara o lehetiv, doing good or evil, the
broader so that's all you have, somebody actually going to like do
something good or something bad. So then when it goes ahead because
כלל ופרט klal uprat you just have the פרט. prat. Then when
it broadens it again, לכל אשר יבטא, lekhol asher yivate, it's anything
like good or bad, but it's which but means future oriented, so
it's still in the future, but it's not just good or bad,
even things that are neither good nor bad. Okay, so if you're
כלל ופרט וכלל, klal uprat ukhlal, you're limited to the future and
you've only broadened it to one degree. If you're ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי,
ribbuy umi'ut veribbuy, at once you said, you know, כי תשבע לבטא
בשפתים להרע או
להטיב, ki tishava levate bisefatayim lehara o lehetiv, you had the ריבוי
ribbuy לבטא levate is anything, להרע או להטיב lehara o lehetiv is
more narrow, already there you're anything future oriented. So then when you
broaden it again, לכל אשר יבטא אדם, lekhol asher yivate adam, now
you're including a wider swath and you're even including things that are
past oriented. So if you do ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי, ribbuy umi'ut veribbuy,
you wind up including even a שבועה shvuah for the past. Okay,
that was a lot. explanation, but that's how we're going to know
that רבי Rebbi holds that the שבועות shvuot apply to the past,
because רבי Rebbi holds of the hermeneutic principle of ריבוי ומיעוט ribui
u'mi'ut and ריבוי, ribui, which is broadening, narrowing, broadening, which ends you
up with a broader category than כלל ופרט. klal u'prat. So let's
take a look. And I should say that the one thing that
would be excluded, what's considered different from all of those that would
not be included, so for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that is נשבע
לבטל את המצוה, nishba levatel et hamitzvah, okay, which is a completely
different category from everything we've been talking about. So let's take a
look. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva after the parentheses. רבי עקיבא מאי טעמא
קמחייב לשעבר? Rabbi Akiva mai taama kamchayev lesha'avar? Why does רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva say you're חייב chayav by a שבועה shvua in the
past? דדרש ריבוי ומיעוט. didarash ribui u'mi'ut. רבי נמי דרש ריבוי ומיעוט.
Rebbi nami darash ribui u'mi'ut. Hey, we also know that רבי Rebbi
follows this hermeneutic principle and therefore he's obviously going would say that
a שבועה shvua applies to the past, so we know he holds
that טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash v'kodashav from, you know, ונעלם ונעלם
v'ne'elam v'ne'elam applies even when it's hidden מקדש וקדשיו. mikdash v'kodashav.
That's the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael position. And by שבועות, shvuot, we
know he does ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u'mi'ut and he'll say the שבועות
shvuot apply to the past. That's the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva position.
So he personally holds of both of those positions. Okay. דתניא, detanya,
how do we know this is the principle he uses? We taught
in a ברייתא. braisa. רבי אומר בכל פודים בכור אדם חוץ מן
השטרות. Rebbi omer bechol podin bechor adam chutz min hashtarot.
You can be redeem a בכור bechor of a, you know, human
one with anything except with a שטר shtar because a שטר shtar
is the most different from, it's not something that has intrinsic value.
It's only used, you know, to represent a debt, but it doesn't
have any intrinsic value. ורבנן אמרי, verabbanan amri, and the Rabbis say,
בכל פודים בכור אדם חוץ מעבדים ושטרות וקרקעות. bechol podin bechor adam
chutz me'avadim ushtarot vekarka'ot. No,
it's not only you can't use קרקע, karka, you also can't use
slaves and you also can't use land because the תורה Torah speaks
about five שקלים shkalim and for them slaves and land are not
similar enough to שקלים shkalim because land is real estate, it's not
chattel, and slaves are connected to land. So you see that רבי
Rebbi is has a broader category than the
רבנן. Rabbanan. ומאי טעמא דרבי? umai taama deRebbi? And we explain, what's
the reason of רבי? דרש ריבוי ומיעוט. Rebbi darash ribui u'mi'ut? ופדיו
מבן חודש, upidyav miben chodesh, it's
the redemption of the בכור bechor is from when one month, ריבה,
ribah, that's a general statement. בערכך כסף חמשת שקלים, be'erkcha kesef chameshet
shkalim,
silver, you know, five שקל, shekel, that is מיעט, mi'at, that narrows.
It's not פרט, prat, it's not specifying, it's narrowing. So that, you
know, תפדה, tifdeh, now it says you shall redeem, חזר וריבה, chazar
veribah, now that's broadening again. ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי, ribui u'mi'ut u'ribui, so
that's your now, that's what you have: broad, narrowing, broadening. ריבה הכל,
ribah hakol, מאי ריבה? mai ribah? כל מילי. kol milei. So first,
the first statement included everything. ומאי מיעט? umai mi'at? When it became
narrow, מיעט שטרות. mi'at shtarot. In the end, you know, you have
when you had maybe just the מיעט, mi'at, maybe you would have
excluded also land and slaves, but then you had the final ריבוי,
ribui, which broadened it again, so now the only thing you're going
to exclude is the thing that is the most different, something that
has no intrinsic value, שטרות. shtarot. ורבנן דרשי כלל ופרט. verabbanan darshi
klal u'prat.
But the רבנן Rabbanan do the כלל ופרט klal u'prat approach. ופדיו
מבן חודש כלל, upidyav miben chodesh klal,
that's a general statement. בערכך כסף חמשת שקלים פרט, be'erkcha kesef chameshet
shkalim prat, not narrowing, specifying. So by the time you're now at
the five שקל, shekel, it can only be silver coins. Okay, and
then תפדה חזר וכלל. tifdeh chazar veklal. Now we're going to broaden
it. כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. klal u'prat
u'khlal i ata dan ela ke'ein haprat. It's only something similar to
the specific. מה הפרט מפורש דבר המטלטל וגופו ממון אף כל דבר
המטלטל וגופו ממון, mah haprat meforash davar hamitaltel vegufan mamon af kol
davar hamitaltel vegufan mamon, the same way the specific thing of silver
is something that is chattel and intrinsic value, אף כל דבר המטלטל
וגופו ממון af kol davar hamitaltel vegufan mamon will include everything that
is intrinsic value and chattel. יצאו קרקעות שאינם
מטלטלין, yatzu karka'ot she'einam mitaltelin, exclude קרקע karka which is not, you
know, land which is not movable. יצאו עבדים שהוקשו
לקרקעות, yatzu avadim shehukshu lekarka'ot, exclude slaves which are connected to land.
יצאו שטרות, yatzu shtarot, and also exclude promissory notes, שטר shtar if
I didn't explain that before, שטר shtar is like an IOU, it's
a promissory note, אף על פי שמטלטלין, af al pi shemitaltelin, even
though they're chattel, אין גופן ממון, ein gufan mamon, it's a promissory
note, it doesn't have its own value, it's used to collect something.
Okay, so again, so the point is for the רבנן Rabbanan it
only has to be something like silver, so that makes it more
demands and it has to be chattel and have intrinsic value, and
for רבי, Rebbi? anything except that which is most dislike silver, so
we would just exclude promissory notes. So because רבי Rebbi, is ריבוי
ומיעוט ribui u'mi'ut and he has a broader, he would also more
broadly include a שבועה shvua past-oriented. All right, the גמרא Gemara did
a pretty good job there showing how רבי Rebbi holds those two
positions. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes. אמר ליה רבינא לאמימר,
amar lei Ravina le'Ameimar, רבינא Ravina said to אמימר, Ameimar, רבי Rebbi
דרש ריבוי ומיעוט? darash ribui u'mi'ut. Are you telling me רבי Rebbi
is a goes by ריבוי ומיעוט? ribui u'mi'ut? הא ורבי כלל ופרט
דרש. ha veRebbi klal u'prat darash. I'll show you where רבי, Rebbi,
you know... Are you telling me רבי *Rebbe* goes by ריבוי ומיעוט
ribui u'miut, *ribbuy umiut*? הא בבא רבי כלל ופרט klal u'prat. דרש
*Ha bava Rebbe klal u'prat darash*, I'll show you where רבי *Rebbe*,
you know, does כלל ופרט klal u'prat, *klal u'prat*, דתניא *De-tanya* we
taught in a ברייתא *Braisa*: מרצע *Martzea*, right, this is talking about,
you know, these the slave that basically you want to stay so
you pierce his ear with an awl, so it says אין לי
אלא מרצע *Ein li ela martzea*, I only know that you can
use like an awl. מניין לרבות הסוב והסירה והמחט והמקדח והמכתב *Minayin
l'rabos ha-sov veha-sira veha-machat veha-makdeach veha-michtav*, how do I know that you
can use like you know a like like a thorn or like
a sharpened piece of wood and a and you know and like
a a metal
a metal needle and something used for inscribing? How do I know
you can use other types of things that can pierce a hole?
תלמוד לומר ולקחת
*Talmud lomar ve-lakach*. Okay, you shall take.
Excuse me, there was a chipsheck there, that should be ולקחתה *ve-lakachta*,
you shall take. But anyway, כל דבר הניטל ביד *Kol davar ha-nital
b'yad*, anything taken in the hand. דברי רבי יאשיה ברבי יהודה *Divrei
Rabbi Yoshiya b'Rebbe Yehuda*. Okay, so he's not doing a כלל ופרט
klal u'prat, *klal u'prat* approach. He's just seems just totally focusing on
ולקחתה *ve-lakachta*. רבי אומר *Rebbe omer*, we'll see about that. מרצע *Martzea*,
no, it has to be like the מרצע *martzea*, like the awl.
מה מרצע מיוחד של מתכת אף כל של מתכת *Ma martzea meyuchad
shel mateches af kol shel mateches*, it only has to be only
something of metal, not anything that you can take in the hand.
All right, so how are they different? What's the basis of their
difference? ואמרינן *Ve-amrinan* and we said, במאי קמיפלגי *B'mai kamiflagi*, what's at
the at the at the core of their debate? רבי דריש כלל
ופרט klal u'prat. ורבי יאשיה ברבי יהודה דריש ריבוי ומיעוט *Rebbe darish
klal u'prat ve'Rabbi Yoshiya b'Rebbe Yehuda darish ribbuy umiut*. רבי *Rebbe* does
כלל ופרט *klal u'prat* and רבי יאשיה ברבי יהודה *Rabbi Yoshiya b'Rebbe
Yehuda* says ריבוי ומיעוט *ribbuy umiut*.
So we're not going to go and unpack the פסוק *pasuk*, but
basically you see that again that you know that רבי יאשיה ברבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yoshiya b'Rebbe Yehuda* has a very broad category, anything taken
in the hand. You can't use something affixed to the ground. That
reflects the ריבוי ומיעוט *ribbuy umiut* approach that you're left with something
very broad, only something totally dissimilar. And רבי *Rebbe*, who says it
has to be just like the specific, that the case of the
awl, that is כלל ופרט *klal u'prat* approach that it has to
be it's not everything, it has to be similar to the specific
example. So now we've got a problem. You wanted to argue that
רבי *Rebbe* holds ריבוי ומיעוט *ribbuy umiut*, here he holds כלל ופרט
*klal u'prat*. Actually, it's an internal problem, okay? One place he's doing
one, place he's doing the other. So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says. דף ה עמוד א *Daf heh amud aleph*, we'll
just get to the two lines. אין *In*, yes. Two dots. דעלמא
כללי ופרטי דריש *D'alma klallei u'prattei darish*, really he generally holds כלל
ופרט *klal u'prat*. והכא היינו טעמא *Vehacha haynu taama*, but here what
is the reason, meaning in the case of פדיון pidyon, הבן *Pidyon
HaBen*? So now we're making פדיון הבן *Pidyon HaBen* the exception, which
is not going to be the way we wanted to go. So
why in פדיון הבן *Pidyon HaBen* does he adopt the broader approach?
דתניא דבי רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael *De-tanya d'bei Rabbi Yishmael*, like we
taught in the house of רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*, דתניא
דבי רבי ישמעאל במים במים שני פעמים *De-tanya d'bei Rabbi Yishmael b'mayim
b'mayim shtei pe'amim*. It says במים *b'mayim* twice. It says you know,
this is a דרשה *drasha* about eating the various like types of
fish and creatures in the water. And somebody and over there, you
know, there was a תנא *Tanna* that wanted to say, it says
במים *b'mayim*, זו שחו בכל אשר במים *zo she-cha b'chol asher b'mayim*,
you know, and then it says again במים *b'mayim* and then it
says בימים ובנחלים *b'yamim u'vanachalim*. And then it said and in the
oceans and in the seas. So they wanted to do a כלל
פרט וכלל *klal prat u'klal*. במים *B'mayim* is general, any body of
water, בימים ובנחלים *b'yamim u'vanachalim* is a פרט *prat*, and then it
said again במים *b'mayim*, which is a general, so they were going
to do a כלל פרט וכלל *klal prat u'klal*. And רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael* rejects it because he says that actually the במים *b'mayim*,
it's the במים *b'mayim* appears twice and only then you get בימים
ובנחלים *b'yamim u'vanachalim*. It doesn't go general specific general, it's general general
specific. במים במים שני פעמים אין זה כלל ופרט אלא ריבוי ומיעוט
*B'mayim b'mayim shtei pe'amim ein zeh klal u'prat ela ribbuy umiut*, that
even if you normally hold of the כלל ופרט *klal u'prat* approach,
when the כללין *klallin* appear side by side, then that is going
to be even broader, that's going to land you with a ריבוי
ומיעוט *ribbuy umiut* type of approach. Okay? And
that's what you have here because it's ופדויו מבן חודש *u'fduyo miben
chodesh*, which we said was the כלל *klal*, and then it's תפדה
*tifdeh*, which is the next כלל *klal*, and then it is בערכך
כסף חמשת שקלים *b'erkecha kesef chameshet shekalim*. So now the גמרא *Gemara*'s
going to say you got me. רבי *Rebbe* looks like is really
כלל ופרט *klal u'prat* as we see by the case of the
awl and the עבד *eved*, and the fact that he's broader by
the case of the עבד *eved* is not that he's generally a
ריבוי ומיעוט *ribbuy umiut* man, but because there it says the two
general statements are side by side, ופדויו תפדה *u'fduyo tifdeh*, and only
then it says the פרט *prat*. That's why he winds up being
broader. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says, אין זה אלא ריבוי
ומיעוט *ein zeh ela ribbuy umiut*. So אמר רבינא *Amar Ravina*, ורבנן
*verabanan*, and the rabbis,
you know, by the case of פדיון הבן *Pidyon HaBen* that would
still say that we still are going to look at it as
a כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal, *klal u'prat u'klal*. So אמר
רבינא כדאמרי במערבא *Amar Ravina k'damri b'maarava*, like they say in במערבא
*b'maarava*, ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*, כל מקום שאתה מוצא שתי כללות הסמוכות
זה לזה *kol makom she-ata motzei shtei klalos ha-smuchos zeh la-zeh*, if
you have two of the general statements immediately juxtaposed and then the
specific, הטל פרט ביניהם *hatel prat beineihem*, so then take the פרט
*prat* and stick it between them, ודונם בכלל ופרט *ve-donam b'klal u'prat*.
And then it becomes. So we have a debate if you generally
approach something with כלל ופרט, what do you do when it's כלל
כלל ופרט? klal klal u'prat? So one approach says that's still a
כלל ופרט וכלל, and then Rebbi says no, that's already broader, that's
like a ריבוי ומיעוט, that'll be a much broader category. Fine. But
that's only because of that תוספות Tosafos there by פדיון, Rebbi still
is כלל ופרט. So now we can't claim that Rebbi holds that
שבועות shavuos his own position is that שבועות shavuos apply to the
past, you know, the קרבן, korban, since he's a כלל ופרט, he
would wind up holding, you know, like רבי ישמעאל that a שבועה
shavuah would only be future oriented for the קרבן. korban. So the
גמרא says השתא דאמרת hashtah d'amart Rebbi כללי ופרטי דרש, klalli u'prati
darish, now that you've admitted that Rebbi goes כלל ופרט, בעל כרחך
ba'al korchacha קשיא kashya שבועות shavuos he does not he himself does
not hold the case of שבועות, shavuos, for him שבועות shavuos would
only be in the future, right, and that so therefore אלא בשבועות
נסיב אליבא דרבי עקיבא וליה לא סבירא ליה. ela b'shavuos nasiv aliba
d'Rebbi Akiva u'lei lo sevira lei. So we are we are forced
to concede that yes, Rebbi in the case of
טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, tumas mikdash v'kodashav, he goes like he quotes רבי
ישמעאל and he holds like him, that's two that is four that
applies even to forgetting מקדש mikdash and קדשיו, kodashav, but the two
that is four by שבועות shavuos that applies even to the past,
he personally would not agree with that. He would say only the
future because he goes כלל ופרט. But he is quoting the position
of רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that he doesn't hold in order to
get another case of two that is four. Okay, we will end
here.