Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is כ"ה, Chaf Hey,
שבועות Shavuos 25, we pick up at the משנה Mishnah and we're
continuing in the discussion about the קרבן Korban for שבועת ביטוי Shavuot
Bituy
for a שבועה shevuah in the להרע או להיטיב ולכל אשר יבטא
האדם בשבועה lehara o leheitiv u'lechol asher yevatei ha'adam bishvuah in the
future to do good, to do bad, anything a person takes an
oath ונעלם ממנו v'ne'elam mimenu and then it's but בשוגג b'shogeg transgresses
the oath and brings a קרבן עולה ויורד. Korban Oleh V'Yored. So
let's take a look at the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah here
talks about some of the basic parameters
and some of the things that we've referenced already earlier. אחד דברים
של עצמו ואחד דברים של אחרים. Echad devarim shel atzmo v'echad devarim
shel acherim. This שבועה shevuah applies to whether it's referring to yourself,
something that you're going to do, or whether it's referring to something
that involves other people. We'll see what this means in a minute.
Not exactly something somebody else is going to do, if you take
a שבועה shevuah that, you know, ראובן Reuven will give שמעון Shimon
a hundred dollars, that's not in your control and that would not
be included. So we'll see what that means in a minute. ואחד
דברים שיש בהן ממש ואחד דברים שאין בהן ממש, V'echad devarim she'yesh
bahen mamash v'echad devarim she'ein bahen mamash, whether it is something that
has substance or something that doesn't have substance, whether it relates to
a physical thing or not. We'll see also in the minute what
that means. כיצד? Keitzad? So very conveniently the משנה Mishnah now illustrates
the cases. אמר שבועה שאתן לפלוני ושלא אתן, Amar shevuah she'etein l'ploni
v'shelo etein, if you, it doesn't have to give the example of
a שבועה shevuah relating to yourself, so the first example it gives
is the שבועה shevuah relating to somebody else, I'll give somebody, you
know, a hundred dollars or I won't give it. שנתתי ושלא נתתי,
She'natati v'shelo natati, or in the past I have given or I
have not given. Those are, that's an example of something that involves
somebody else that still is within your control.
Now, שאישן ושלא אישן, she'ishan v'shelo ishan, I will sleep or I
won't sleep, שישנתי ושלא ישנתי, she'yashanti v'shelo yashanti, that I slept or
I did not sleep. So that's an example of דבר שאין בו
ממש. davar she'ein bo mamash. It doesn't relate to a physical object,
it's this abstract idea of sleeping.
שאזרוק צר לים ושלא אזרוק שזרקתי ושלא זרקתי. She'ezrok tzor l'yam v'shelo
ezrok she'zarakti v'shelo zarakti. Similarly, רש"י Rashi says this is an idea
of אין בו ממש ein bo mamash that really doesn't, it's not
that it's not physical, but there's no benefit. It's a completely neutral
act, it's sort of not להרע lehara or not להיטיב leheitiv that
I will throw a rock into the ocean or I won't throw
it, I did throw or I didn't throw. So it's a positive
and a negative, להרע או להיטיב lehara o leheitiv or negative and
positive, and also past and future. And now we're going to see
that there's actually a debate about to what degree does it really
relate to the past as well because להרע ולהיטיב lehara u'leheitiv in
the פסוק pasuk is only future-oriented and this is something that we've
seen before. רבי ישמעאל אומר אינו חייב אלא על
העתיד לבוא, Rabbi Yishmael omer eino chayav ela al ha'atid lavo, you're
only חייב chayav for a שבועת ביטוי shevuat bituy for this קרבן
korban if it relates to something you will or won't do in
the future, שנאמר להרע או להיטיב, shene'emar lehara o leheitiv, to do
bad or to do good. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi
Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to him, אם כן אין לי
אלא דברים שיש בהן הרע והטבה. im kein ein li ela devarim
she'yesh bahen hara v'hatava. If you're going to be such a literalist
then it should only be things that are actually about doing something
that's like helpful or harmful. דברים שאינם של הרע והטבה מנין? Devarim
she'einam shel hara v'hatava minayin? How do you know if it's something
completely neutral like throwing a rock into the sea?
אמר לו מריבוי הכתוב, Amar lo mi'ribui hakasuv, because the פסוק pasuk
is more
expansive, it says להרע להיטיב לכל אשר יבטא האדם בשבועה lehara l'heitiv
l'chol asher yevatei ha'adam bishvuah for anything that a person enunciates a
שבועה. shevuah. So that's broad and that includes not only bad and
good, but it still has to be something in the future. So
he said back to him, אם ריבה הכתוב לכך ריבה הכתוב לכך.
im ribah hakasuv l'kach, ribah hakasuv l'kach. Well, once you're expanding it
beyond the literal meaning then why do you stop at including neutral
things? Once you're not only להרע להיטיב, lehara l'heitiv, it should also
include things that are in the past as well. Okay and we
will see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a
look. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, so the גמרא Gemara starts not by
getting drilling down into the specifics of the משנה Mishnah but starts
also by contrasting this משנה Mishnah to what would be something parallel
relating to a
נדר. neder. חומר בנדרים מבשבועות חומר בשבועות מנדרים. Chomer bin'darim mibishvuot, chomer
bishvuot mindarim. There's ways in which vows, a נדר neder which relates
to the status of an object, קונם konam this thing is forbidden
to me like a קרבן, korban, okay,
is more stringent, actually here means a broader scope, than a שבועה
shevuah and there are ways in which a שבועה shevuah has a
broader scope than a נדר. neder. חומר בנדרים שהנדרים חלים על דבר
מצוה כדבר רשות, Chomer bin'darim she'nedarim chalim al devar mitzvah k'dvar reshut,
מה שאין כן בשבועות. mah she'kein bishvuot. A נדר neder takes effect
even on מצוה mitzvah objects and even ultimately leading to the contravention
of a מצוה mitzvah which is not by a שבועה. shevuah. If
a שבועה shevuah somebody takes a שבועה shevuah that I won't sleep
in a סוכה sukkah or in a סוכה sukkah I won't take
a לולב, lulav, so that's going against his obligation. מושבע ועומד מהר
סיני, mushba v'omed m'har sinai, he can't take a שבועה shevuah to
contravene an obligation, to obligate him to do something that the תורה
Torah forbids him from doing. And therefore the שבועה shevuah does not
take effect. As opposed to a נדר neder which relates to the
object. If somebody takes a נדר neder that the סוכה sukkah is
forbidden to him, the לולב lulav is forbidden to him, something of
that nature, then He's not directly contravening his obligation, but when it
comes time to sit in the סוכה sukkah he's not able to
because the סוכה sukkah is forbidden. So in that way, a נדר
neder can prevent a מצוה mitzvah from being done in a way
that a שבועה shvua cannot because a שבועה shvua confronts it head-on
and it cannot really contravene your תורה Torah obligation, but a נדר
neder only relates to the object. Okay,
חומר בשבועות. chomer bishvuos. Now there's a way in which שבועה shvua
is broader, שהשבועה חלה על דבר שאין בו ממש כדבר שיש בו
ממש. shehashvua chala al davar she'ein bo mamash kedavar sheyesh bo mamash.
A שבועה shvua takes effect even on things without substance. So a
person can say a שבועה shvua that he won't sleep. מה שאין
כן בנדרים, ma she'ein kein binedarim, but a נדר neder only relates
to the object. So you can't make sleep forbidden, that's not a
physical object, and therefore that will not work. Now a person could
say my eyes are forbidden to me for sleep, so there's maybe
ways in which you can get at that, but fundamentally the sleep
per se cannot be forbidden. Okay, so that was a nice contrast
to שבועות shvuos and נדרים. nedarim. We haven't been dealing with נדרים
nedarim a lot yet, but this is
helping bringing that into the conversation. Now back to the משנה: mishna:
כיצד אומר שבועה שאיתן לפלוני ושלא איתן. keitzad omer shvua she'etein l'ploni
veshelo etein. So an example about a שבועה shvua that involves somebody
else that's still under your control is whether you'll give something or
not give something. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי איתן? mai etein?
What does that mean? אילימא צדקה לעני, ilima tzedaka l'ani, if it
means that you're taking a שבועה shvua that you'll give צדקה tzedaka
to a poor person, מושבע ועומד מהר סיני הוא, mushba ve'omed mehar
Sinai hu, then that שבועה shvua is not חל chal because you're
already obligated. We'll see in a minute why you can't doubly make
yourself obligated, שנאמר ונתון תתן לו. shene'emar venason titein lo.
You have to give if somebody's asking for צדקה. tzedaka. So that
we can't be talking about a שבועה shvua about giving צדקה, tzedaka,
that wouldn't have effect. אלא מתנה לעשיר. ela matana l'ashir. Fine, we're
talking about a gift to a rich person, and that's why the
שבועה shvua will work. שאשן ושלא אשן, she'ishan veshelo ishan,
that I'll sleep or that I won't sleep. איני, eini, is this
really true that a שבועה shvua that you won't sleep takes effect?
ואמר רבי יוחנן אומר שבועה שלא אישן ג' ימים מלקין אותו וישן
לאלתר. ve'amar Rabbi Yochanan omer shvua shelo ishan gimel yamim malkin oso
veyashen le'altar. Somebody takes a שבועה shvua they won't sleep for three
days, you give them מלקות malkus because it's a
שבועת שוא shvuat shav I should rather say. Like it's saying that
somebody would take a שבועה shvua that they would flap their arms
and start flying. So a שבועה shvua that's patently false is a
שבועת שוא shvuat shav and they get מלקות malkus for that because
it's not possible, the גמרא Gemara believes, to go three days without
sleeping. So a שבועה shvua to do something that is patently false
is a שבועת שוא shvuat shav and it's not a שבועת ביטוי
shvuat bitui which is the case in the תורה Torah for קרבן
עולה ויורד. korban oleh veyored. So how here can a שבועה shvua
that you won't sleep, which the גמרא Gemara presumably understands it to
mean won't sleep ever, be in the category of the שבועה shvua
of עולה ויורד? oleh veyored? So the גמרא Gemara says התם דאמר
ג' הכא דלא אמר ג'. hasam d'amar gimel hacha d'lo amar gimel.
So
that's when you said three days and that's not possible, so that's
שבועת שוא shvuat shav and you get מלקות malkus right away and
then you might as well go and sleep, the שבועה shvua didn't
take effect, but it was a שבועת שוא. shvuat shav. Whereas in
our case you didn't say three days. So if you just said
I won't sleep, by context maybe it means tonight, we're not going
to assume that it means forever. We're going to assume it means
something else based on the context and it would not be a
שבועת שוא shvuat shav and then it would depend whether you would
actually live up to it or not live up to it. Okay,
שיזרוק צרור לים ושלא יזרוק. sheyizrok tzror l'yam veshelo yizrok. So I'll
throw a rock in the sea or I won't throw. איתמר, itmar,
it was taught: שבועה
שזרק פלוני צרור לים ושלא זרק. shvua shezarak ploni tzror l'yam veshelo
zarak. So we know that if you were to say a שבועה
shvua in the future, ראובן Reuven will throw a rock into the
sea or not, it's not חל chal because that's not under your
control. What about if you framed it in the past
according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that you're חייב chayav for a
שבועה shvua in the past? A שבועה shvua that ראובן Reuven did
throw a rock into the sea or didn't, that's something that you
could have knowledge about. So why would you need it to be
under your control as long as it's something you could have knowledge
about and you should be חייב chayav about it for the past
if it is not true? רב אמר חייב. Rav amar chayav. So
רב Rav says חייב, chayav, that makes sense. ושמואל אמר פטור. uShmuel
amar patur. But שמואל Shmuel says you're exempt. רב אמר חייב איתא
בלאו הכי. Rav amar chayav ita belav hachi. So רב Rav says
it's חייב chayav because the real test for whether something is a
good שבועה shvua for שבועת ביטוי, shvuat bitui, other than what we're
saying that it has to be like under your control if it's
future-oriented, the other real test is can you say it in the
negative and the positive? That's להרע או להיטיב. lehara o lehiteiv. So
therefore since you could say somebody did throw a rock into the
sea or ראובן Reuven did not throw, you can imagine a שבועה
shvua both in the positive and negative, so therefore you're חייב chayav
if you're saying it and it's not true. That's the only real
test: can it be made if it's in the positive, can it
be made in the negative and vice versa? ושמואל אמר פטור. uShmuel
amar patur. But שמואל Shmuel says you're פטור. patur. Why? Because ליתא
בלהבא. leisa b'lehaba.
Because there's another criteria for something is a good שבועה. shvua. Even
according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that a שבועה shvua is חייב
chayav in the past, it's only if it could be made into
a שבועה shvua about the future because ultimately the paradigm... It's deriving
from להרע או להיטיב. lehara u'leheitiv. So something has to be able
to have a form of future-oriented להרע או להיטיב, lehara u'leheitiv, not
only positive and negative. So since you said a שבועה shvuah that
ראובן Reuven did not throw or did throw, you know, a rock
in the sea, but you cannot be it would not be a
שבועה shvuah if you said ראובן Reuven will throw because that's not
under your control. So since that would not be a שבועה shvuah
in the future, you're also not חייב chayav for it as a
שבועה shvuah in the past for this קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh
v'yored. Okay, so that is the interesting question, you know, even according
to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that you're חייב chayav in a שבועה
shvuah in the past, is it only if it is it only
based on the model of the שבועה shvuah in the future and
only if it could be framed also future-oriented?
So let's take a look. לימא בפלוגתא דרבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא קמיפלגי?
lima be-flugta d'Rabbi Yishmael v'Rabbi Akiva kamifligi? So a little bizarrely the
גמרא, Gemara, you know, even though I've explained it and this is
where the גמרא's Gemara going to land that it's a debate within
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that you're חייב chayav in the past, the
גמרא Gemara first wants to make it even like a simpler point.
Oh, maybe they're just debating רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva or רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Yishmael, you know,
not what's the parameters of being חייב chayav in the past, but
whether you're חייב chayav in the past at all. Okay, קמיפלגי. kamifligi.
דתנן detnan רבי ישמעאל אומר אינו חייב אלא לעתיד לבוא, Rabbi Yishmael
omer eino chayav ela le-asid lavo, שנאמר shene'emar להרע או להיטיב, lehara
u'leheitiv, אמר לו רבי עקיבא אם כן אין לי אלא דברים שיש
בהם הרע והטבה. amar lo Rabbi Akiva im kein ein li ela
devarim she-yesh bahem hara v'hatavah.
If you're going to be so literal, then it's only should be
good or bad. דברים שאין בהם הרע והטבה מניין? devarim she-ein bahem
hara v'hatavah minayin? How do you know if it's if it's just
if it's just neutral? אמר לו ריבוי הכתוב amar lo ribui ha-katuv
because it says לכל אשר יבטא. le-chol asher yevatei. אמר ליה אם
ריבוי הכתוב לכך ריבוי הכתוב לכך. amar lei im ribui ha-katuv le-kach
ribui ha-katuv le-kach. If you're going to include neutral, you might as
well include past. Okay, that we know in our משנה. mishnah. רב
דאמר כרבי עקיבא. Rav d'amar k'Rabbi Akiva. So רב Rav who said
you're חייב chayav when you say ראובן Reuven threw a rock in
the sea, he's like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you're חייב chayav in
the past. ושמואל דאמר כרבי ישמעאל u-Shmuel d'amar k'Rabbi Yishmael and שמואל
Shmuel says like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael you're not חייב chayav in
the past. Now obviously that's not the point because then they would
not be debating by just such a specific case of ראובן Reuven
throwing something in the sea. So the גמרא Gemara says, rejects it.
אליבא דרבי ישמעאל כולי עלמא לא פליגי. aliba d'Rabbi Yishmael kulei alma
lo peligi. No, for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael they wouldn't even have
been bothered discussing the point about רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. התם מילתא
דאיתא להבא לא מחייב ליה רבי ישמעאל. hatam milta d'ita le-haba lo
mechayev lei Rabbi Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael does not doesn't have
any חיוב chiyuv for the past. Even a past that could be
in the future. Even if you said I didn't throw a rock
in the sea and you could say it in the future, I
will throw a rock in the sea, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael just
categorically says you're not חייב chayav for things in the past. So
if that's true, מילתא דליתא להבא מיבעיא? milta d'leisa le-haba mibaya? There's
no question that something that you could not even frame in the
future, certainly he wouldn't be מחייב mechayev you because he just completely
rules out a שבועה shvuah that relates to the past. So it
would have been a completely boring debate between רב Rav and שמואל.
Shmuel. So they're not talking about רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. כי פליגי
אליבא דרבי עקיבא. ki peligi aliba d'Rabbi Akiva. They're arguing according to
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רב דאמר כרבי עקיבא. Rav d'amar k'Rabbi Akiva.
רב Rav simply says look רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're חייב
chayav in the past so you're חייב chayav in the past, you're
also חייב chayav if you say ראובן Reuven threw a rock in
the sea. ושמואל אמר u-Shmuel amar and שמואל Shmuel would say no.
עד כאן לא מחייב רבי עקיבא התם לשעבר אלא מילתא דאיתא להבא
מחייב רבי עקיבא לשעבר. ad kan lo mechayev Rabbi Akiva hatam le-she'avar
ela milta d'ita le-haba mechayev Rabbi Akiva le-she'avar. Yes,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're חייב chayav in the past, but
only based on the model of the future. You're only חייב chayav
in something in the past that you could be חייב chayav and
you could be a שבועת ביטוי shvuas bitui for as future-oriented. So
to say I ate something because you could say I will eat
something. But to say ראובן Reuven threw a rock in the sea,
since you can't say ראובן Reuven will throw a rock in the
sea because that's not under your control, that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
would not go that far. לשעבר. le-she'avar. אבל מידי דליתא להבא, aval
midi d'leisa le-haba, something that you could not
a past thing that you would not be a שבועת ביטוי shvuas
bitui were you to frame it in the future, like something that
relates to somebody else, לא, lo, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would not
say that. Obviously that's their debate. How far would רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva go in to say that you're חייב chayav in the past?
Would it have to be based on something that could be done
in the future orientation? Okay, לימא בפלוגתא lima be-flugta top now of
כ"ה עמוד ב'. chaf hey amud bet. Let's say it's this is
dependent on the debate דרבי יהודה בן בתירה ורבנן קמיפלגי. d'Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beseira v'Rabbanan kamifligi. Of רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben
Beseira and the רבנן. Rabbanan. What is their debate? Their debate is
about a different parameter of whether you can reverse a שבועה shvuah
in a certain way. דתנן detnan we taught in the משנה mishnah
coming up in two days. נשבע לבטל את המצוה ולא ביטל פטור.
nishba levatel es ha-mitzvah lo bita patur. If somebody takes an oath
to negate a מצווה, mitzvah, an oath I won't sleep in a
סוכה, sukkah, then he's פטור, patur, you know, from the קרבן korban
because that's not חל chal because you're not able to take a
שבועה shvuah to contravene an obligation. Alright, nobody disagrees with that. Now
לקיים את המצוה ולא קיים פטור. le-kayem es ha-mitzvah lo kiyem patur.
How about if you take a שבועה shvuah that you will sit
in a סוכה sukkah and you don't? So the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says you're פטור. patur. A שבועה shvuah to obligate you on
something you're already obligated in is not חל. chal. Not so clear
why not. והמשנה אומרת היה בדין שיהיה חייב כדברי רבי יהודה בן
בתירה. v'ha-mishnah omeres haya ba-din she-yehei chayav ke-divrei Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira.
Actually logically you should be חייב chayav which actually is the position
of רבי יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira. Why? דאמר רבי
יהודה בן בתירה d'amar Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira ומה אם הרשות שאינו
מושבע מהר סיני הרי הוא חייב עליה. u-ma im ha-reshus she-eino mushba
me-Har Sinai harei hu chayav aleha.
Something neutral, I'll eat this ham- I'll throw a rock in the
sea. You have no obligation to do it. But when you take
a שבועה, shvuah, then you're obligated and if you violate, you're חייב
chayav a קרבן. korban. So therefore something that you're already obligated, so
you're doubling your obligation. How much more so should it be a
problem not to do it and should you have to bring a
קרבן? korban? So ומה אם דבר הרשות שאינו מושבע עליה מהר סיני
הרי הוא חייב עליה, uma im davar hareshus she'eino mushba aleha meiHar
Sinai harei hu chayav aleha, מצוה? mitzvah? When it comes to a
מצוה mitzvah שמושבע עליה מהר סיני shemushba aleha meiHar Sinai that you're
already obligated to take a לולב. lulav. And now you're adding on
the obligation another שבועה. shvuah. So אינו דין שיהיה חייב עליה, eino
din sheyeheye chayav aleha,
how much more so should now you have an obligation to take
the לולב lulav doubly and if you violate, you should violate your
שבועה. shvuah. There's another way of saying why should the fact that
you already have a חיוב chiyuv to do it mean that you
can't obligate yourself with it with a שבועה? shvuah? Good question. So
what's the answer? אמרו לו, amru lo, so the חכמים Chachamim said
back to him, לא, lo,
no, it's not the same. אם אמרת בשבועת הרשות שכן עשה בו
לאו והן, im amarta bishvuas hareshus sheken asah bo lav vahen, if
you say you'll eat a hamburger, then you could say it in
the negative, you won't eat a hamburger. So that's the type of
שבועה shvuah you're חייב chayav a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh veyored,
one that could be reversed לאו והן. lav vahen. תאמר בשבועת מצוה,
tomar bishvuas mitzvah, when
you take a שבועה shvuah I'll take a לולב, lulav, so שכן
לא עשה בו לאו והן, sheken lo asah bo lav vahen, you
can't reverse it. We all agree that a שבועה shvuah that you
won't take a לולב lulav is אין חל ein chal because you're
coming to negate and contravene your obligation. And therefore even a שבועה
shvuah that you will take a לולב lulav is אין חל, ein
chal, you know, for this חיוב chiyuv of עולה ויורד oleh veyored
because it can't be reversed. So now we understand, you know, normally
we say that it's a שבועה לבטל את המצוה shvuah levatel es
hamitzvah you're מושבע ועומד, mushba ve'omed, and שבועה לקיים את המצוה shvuah
lekayem es hamitzvah you're מושבע ועומד. mushba ve'omed. But it's not exactly
clear. לבטל levatel we understand, you can't take a שבועה shvuah to
negate an obligation. But why because you're obligated can't the שבועה shvuah
be חל? chal? And the answer is, you know, or maybe it's
not right to say it can't be חל, chal, but the point
is you can't be חייב chayav a קרבן korban of עולה ויורד
oleh veyored because it's less a לאו והן. lav vahen. So that
idea להרע או להיטיב lehara o leheitiv says if you want to
be חייב chayav a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh veyored, it has
to pass this test of להרע או להיטיב. lehara o leheitiv. And
a שבועה לקיים את המצוה shvuah lekayem es hamitzvah doesn't pass that
test. Fine, that's the debate of the חכמים Chachamim and רבי יהודה
בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to
say, ah, so you see what they're debating is: does something have
to be reversible? So maybe that's like an analogy to our case.
So let's see what it says. Okay, so
נימא רב דאמר כרבי יהודה בן בתירה. neimar Rav de'amar keRabbi Yehuda
ben Beseira. רב, Rav, let's say רב Rav says like רבי יהודה
בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira. רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beseira doesn't need לאו והן, lav vahen, right, as long as
the way it's formulated works it should work. And here too, רב
Rav says it doesn't need to be להבא, lehaba, you don't have
to be able to transfer past to future. As long as the
way it's formulated works it works.
ושמואל דאמר כרבנן, uShmuel de'amar keRabbanan, and שמואל Shmuel would say like
the רבנן: Rabbanan: No, it needs to be reversible. It needs to
be able to be לאו והן lav vahen and it needs to
be able to be, if it's past, to be said in the
future. So okay, there's a certain analogy there. But now the גמרא's
Gemara going to make a hierarchy. לא, lo, says the גמרא, Gemara,
אליבא דרבי יהודה בן בתירה כולי עלמא לא פליגי. aliba deRabbi Yehuda
ben Beseira kulei alma lo peligi. According to רבי יהודה בן בתירה,
Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira, if he doesn't need לאו והן, lav vahen,
everybody would agree that he also would not need להבא. lehaba. Okay,
because it's more clear that you should require the לאו והן lav
vahen criterion. Why? השתא לאו והן לא בעי, hashta lav vahen lo
ba'ei, if he doesn't even require לאו והן, lav vahen, which is
more explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk says one thing
to describe the שבועה: shvuah: it's להרע או להיטיב. lehara o leheitiv.
Okay, and therefore that is
very suggestive or very much implied by the פסוק pasuk that something
has to be able to be both לאו והן. lav vahen. So
if רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira doesn't even read
that into the פסוק pasuk and doesn't require לאו והן lav vahen
even though the פסוק pasuk says להרע או להיטיב, lehara o leheitiv,
so how much more so would it not bother him that something
could not be framed in the future?
להבא ולשעבר בעי? lehaba uleshe'avar ba'ei? Why should he require that something
could both be past and future? כי פליגי אליבא דרבנן. ki peligi
aliba deRabbanan. The question is for the רבנן Rabbanan who do require
לאו והן. lav vahen. Okay,
so שמואל כרבנן. Shmuel keRabbanan. שמואל Shmuel says look, the same way
the רבנן Rabbanan say להרע או להיטיב, lehara o leheitiv, it has
to be both able to be positive and negative. It also, something
in the past has to be able to be framed in the
future. That makes sense. ורב veRav but רב Rav would say no.
כי מחייבי רבנן בלאו והן ki mechayvi Rabbanan belav vahen the רבנן,
Rabbanan, when do the רבנן Rabbanan say you're exempt if you can't
do the לאו והן? lav vahen? לאו והן lav vahen is definitely
a criterion for this שבועת ביטוי shvuas bitui and the קרבן עולה
ויורד. korban oleh veyored. Why? דכתיב, dechtiv, it's in the פסוק, pasuk,
להרע או להיטיב. lehara o leheitiv. So for a שבועה shvuah to
be חייב chayav
for ביטוי bitui and for the קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh veyored,
it has to be able to be both, if it's in the
past, it has to be able to be framed in the future.
Excuse me, I jumped that, it has to be לאו והן. lav
vahen. Everybody agrees להרע או להיטיב lehara o leheitiv is that it
has to be able to be said both in the positive and
the negative. That of course, if you want to be חייב chayav
for... Wait, and you know, for the קרבן עולה ויורד, Korban Oleh
V'Yored, it has to be able to be both. If it's in
the past, it has to be able to be framed in the
future. Excuse me, I flipped that. If it's, it has to be
לאו והן. Lav v'Hein. Everybody agrees to הראוי להיטיב Ha-ra'uy L'Heitiv that
it has to be able to be said both in the positive
and the negative. That, of course, if you want to be חייב
Chayav for שבועת ביטוי Shvuat Bituy for the קרבן עולה ויורד Korban
Oleh V'Yored בהדיא, Be'hedya, because that's an explicitly stated in the פסוק,
Pasuk, the negative and the positive. אבל לבבא דשעבר, Aval l'bava d'she'avar,
this idea that if it's on the past, it has to be
able to be framed in the future to be ריבויא דקרא, ribbuya
de-kra, so we only know that the past based on the כל
אשר יבטא. kol asher yivata. It's a very generic umbrella inclusive type
of a thing. There's no way basis to read in from there
that it needs to be able to be formulated in the future.
So מחייב, mechayev, so that they would say חייב chayav even if
you can't make it in the future. Okay, so this is very
nice. So now we've got like different debates, a hierarchy. Number one,
there's a debate about whether you need something to be לאו והן
lav ve-hein in order to be חייב. chayav. רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
that's like the thing that's most obvious because it says להרע או
להיטיב, l'hareia o le-heitiv, but even so, you know, רבי יהודה בן
בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira says that you don't, and that's why
he's מחייב mechayev you if you take a שבועה לקיים את המצוה.
shvua lekayem es ha-mitzvah. Okay, that's רבי יהודה בן בתירה. Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira.
That's an outline position. Generally, it's assumed everybody agrees לאו והן, lav
ve-hein, להרע או להיטיב. l'hareia o le-heitiv. The debate of רב ושמואל
Rav u-Shmuel is: do you need something in the past to be
able to be framed in the future? On the one hand, the
paradigm is the future, and on the other hand, there's no פסוק
pasuk to base that requirement on like there is by להרע או
להיטיב. l'hareia o le-heitiv. So that's the debate of רב ושמואל. Rav
u-Shmuel. Okay, מתיב רב המנונא. meitiv Rav Hamnuna.
So now רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna is going to, you know, challenge
the position of שמואל. Shmuel. Let's take a look. Okay, and try
to bring in—try to bring a source that's, you know, that's a
proof to רב. Rav. Okay, so let's take a look. Okay,
and it says like,
and this is based also the משנה Mishna at the end of
the פרק. perek. Hold on, I just—okay.
לא אכלתי היום ולא הנחתי תפילין היום. lo achalti hayom v'lo hinachti
tefillin hayom. If somebody says, you know, I didn't eat today and
I didn't put on תפילין tefillin today, משביע אני עליך, mashbia ani
aleicha, and the person says I'm posing on you a שבועה, shvua,
like make a שבועה shvua to me that that's true, ואמר אמן,
v'amar amen, and the person said yes, said אמן, amen, which is
כמוציא שבועה מפיו דמי, k'motzi shvua mi-piv dami, like he took the
שבועה shvua himself, חייב. chayav. He's חייב. chayav. Okay, so those are,
by the way, two cases of לשעבר, l'she'avar, like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. But the question is: are they able to be formulated in
the future, which is a requirement that שמואל Shmuel has? בשלמא לא
אכלתי איתא בלא אוכל. bishlama lo achalti isah b'lo ochel. So, I
didn't eat today or yesterday or whatever, that could be formulated in
the future: I won't. So that makes sense that that's חייב. chayav.
Nobody, you know, at least within רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, everybody would
agree. אלא לא הנחתי, ella lo hinachti, but I didn't put on
תפילין tefillin today, מי איתא בלא אניח? mi isah b'lo aniach? You
can't make that in the future: I won't put on תפילין. tefillin.
Because, as we've already seen, you can't make a שבועה, shvua, you
know, you're not חייב קרבן chayav korban if you make a שבועה
shvua that you won't do a מצוה. mitzvah. It's a שבועה shvua
to contravene an obligation. So here's a perfect example of a שבועה
shvua in the past that doesn't work in the future, and the
משנה Mishna said you're חייב. chayav. Great proof like רב. Rav. הוא
מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה. hu moitiv lah v'hu mefarek lah. So
רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna raised this question and he also suggested the
answer. What was the answer?
לסטמא קתני. le-stama katani. Even though the משנה Mishna says you're חייב,
chayav, it's not חייב chayav in the same way. לא אכלתי לקרבן.
lo achalti l'korban. If somebody says I didn't eat, then that would
be a full חיוב שבועה chiyuv shvua and if—meaning that would be
the חיוב שבועה chiyuv shvua that we're talking about in this פרק,
perek, that they would bring a קרבן korban if they, you know,
ונעלם ממנו v'ne'elam mimenu and they did it בשוגג. b'shogeg. Okay, that
because it could also be in the future. However, לא הנחתי, lo
hinachti, if somebody says I didn't put on תפילין למלקות, tefillin l'malkus,
then you would only be חייב chayav if you did it במזיד
b'meizid to get מלקות. malkus. Right, because במזיד b'meizid it's just the
whole—all these requirements, להרע או להיטיב, l'hareia o le-heitiv, is it only
להבא l'haba or even לשעבר, l'she'avar, the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva or רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? All of these issues, does it
have to be able to be reversible? All of these things is
only within the פסוקים psukim that are describing the קרבן עולה ויורד
korban oleh ve-yored for the שבועת ביטוי. shvuat bituy. When it comes
to the question of מלקות, malkus, it just says לא תשבעו בשמי
לשקר, lo tishavu vishmi lashaker, לא תשא שם. lo sisa shem. Okay,
so for מלקות malkus there are really none of these requirements. So
when it says לא הנחתי תפילין, lo hinachti tefillin, that's only for
מלקות. malkus. Now, that is a very bizarre read. Right, the whole
פרק perek is talking about the קרבן, korban, and why in this
example when it gives—when it talks about לא הנחתי תפילין lo hinachti
tefillin would it say something that you're לא חייב קרבן lo chayav
korban for if it was בשוגג b'shogeg and only that you're חייב,
chayav, you know, מלקות malkus for if it's במזיד? b'meizid? So it's
a very hard read. But anyway, that's how שמואל Shmuel would answer.
The simple reading of that משנה Mishna is according to רב, Rav,
that לא הנחתי תפילין lo hinachti tefillin you're חייב קרבן chayav korban
if it was בשוגג b'shogeg and even though you cannot frame it
in the future. Okay. But so that's at least a prima facie
certainly evidence like רב. Rav.
Now, מתיב רבא Rava, *masiv Rava*. רבא *Rava* asks, איזהי שבועת שוא
*aizi hi shvuat shav*? Another משנה *mishna* coming up. נשבע לבטל את
הידוע לאדם *nishba levatel et hayaduah la-adam*. What is a שבועת שוא
*shvuat shav*? If you take an oath to, you know, say something
that is patently true or patently false, that's not a שבועת שקר
*shvuat sheker*, everybody knows it's false. שבועת שקר *shvuat sheker* is when
you're deceiving people. Okay, and that's a שבועת שוא *shvuat shav*. So,
ואמר *v'amar*, for example, you said על עמוד של אבן שהוא של
זהב *al amud shel even shehu shel zahav*, on a pillar of
stone that it's gold. ואמר עולא *v'amar Ulla*, and עולא *Ulla* explained,
והוא שניכר לג' בני אדם *v'hu shenikar l'gimmel bnei adam*. It has
to be that at least three people know this, you know, because
if people, if only one or two people know it, and most
people don't know it and you're saying it, then it's a שבועת
שקר *shvuat sheker*, then it's, you know, then you're deceiving people like
when you say I didn't borrow money and you did borrow money.
A lie is a lie. What makes it שוא *shav* is that
everybody knows it's a lie and then it's just stupid and silly
and empty. Okay, fine. So, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says טעמא דניכר
*taima d'nikar*. So, okay, because people know that it's stone, that it's
a שבועת שוא *shvuat shav*. הא לא ניכר *ha lo nikar*, עובר
משום שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui, *over mishum shvuat bitoy*. But the implication
is that if you said that this stone thing, I don't know,
somehow it was painted, you know, with and looked gold, and you
said it was gold and people, you know, didn't, it wasn't obvious
that it was stone, then it would not be a שבועת שוא
*shvuat shav* and it would be a שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui. *shvuat
bitoy*, so presumably חייב chayav א קרבן korban, *chayav a korban*. But
now we got a problem, it's ליתא להבא *leisa l'haba*, or a
problem according to שמואל *Shmuel*. It's לאו lav להבא *lav l'haba*. You
can't say I will make it gold. הא אינו בידך של זהב
*ha einu b'yadecha shel zahav*.
So, why when you say this thing is gold are you חייב
chayav *chayav* if it's not obvious? You know, or if it's not
obvious that it's false. Why are you חייב chayav *chayav* since you
can't frame
the שבועה shvua *shvua* in the future? You can't turn stone into
gold, that would not be חל *chal* as a שבועה shvua *shvua*
for the future, it's not בידך *b'yadecha*. So, that seems to be
evidence like רב Rav, *Rav*, but this is really a much weaker
proof than the previous one. הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה *hu
masiv lah v'hu mefarek lah*. He asks it and he answered it.
ניכר *nikar*, if it is obvious that it is stone and you
say it's gold, עובר משום שבועת שוא *over mishum shvuat shav*, then
you're חייב chayav *chayav* for שבועת שוא *shvuat shav* and you get
מלכות *malchus* for that. לא ניכר *lo nikar*, if it's not clear
if it's gold or stone and you're lying, עובר משום שבועת שקר
*over mishum shvuat sheker*. Who says it's קרבן korban ביטוי bitui. *korban
bitoy*? Right there, when it's being contrasted to שבועת שוא *shvuat shav*,
we're no longer discussing the parameters of קרבן korban *korban*. We're saying,
you know, let me tell you there are things that aren't שקר
*sheker* but that are שוא *shav*. If you say something that's patently
false or patently true, it's a שבועת שוא *shvuat shav*. So, the
only thing that that suggests is, and if it weren't patently false,
it would be a שבועת שקר *shvuat sheker*, but we're not saying
you'd be חייב chayav א קרבן korban, *chayav a korban*. Okay, we're
no longer talking about קרבן korban *korban* in this parameter, we're just
contrasting שוא *shav* to שקר *sheker*. So, it means that if you
did it במזיד bemeizid. *bimeizid*, you get מלכות *malchus* for שקר *sheker*.
Whether you're חייב chayav א קרבן korban. *chayav a korban* or not,
that's not even the discussion. Okay, that is certainly פשט *pshat* of
that משנה *mishna*. All right. אמר אביי Abaye, *amar Abaye*. So, we
haven't really come down on רב *Rav* or שמואל *Shmuel*’s side, although
רב *Rav* does seem to be more evidence by the תפילין *tefillin*
case. ומודה רב
*u'modeh Rav*, now רב *Rav* would agree באומר לחבירו שבועה shvua שאני
יודע לך עדות edut *b'omer l'chaveiro shvua she-ani yodeiah lecha eidus*, that
if somebody took a שבועה shvua *shvua* that I know testimony for
you, ואשתכח דלא ידע ליה *v'ishtachach d'lo yada leh*, and it turned
out that he was making a mistake, he didn't know, he thought
he knew,
whatever, so that would seem to be a case of שבועת ביטוי
shvuat bitui. *shvuat bitoy* and you're חייב chayav א קרבן korban, *chayav
a korban*. דפטור *depattur*, nevertheless, you're פטור *pattur*. Why?
Isn't that, it is להבא *l'haba*, you know, you could say that,
I'm sorry,
you don't need להבא *l'haba*, right? I mean, you can't say a
שבועה *shvua* that I will know עדות edut *eidus*, fine, but you
don't need להבא *l'haba*. So, why would you be פטור *pattur* according
to רב *Rav*? Because הוה ליה ליתא בכלל שאיני יודע לך עדות
edut *hava lei leisa b'khlal she-eini yodeiah lecha eidus*, because it's not
in לאו והן lav vehen *lav v'hen*. Okay, if you say I
know עדות edut. *eidus* for you, then that's a שבועה *shvua*. But
if you say I don't know עדות edut, *eidus*, now that's also
a שבועה *shvua*, but it's not a שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui *shvuat
bitoy*, it's a שבועת עדות shvuas edos *shvuat eidus*. That's going to
be the next פרק *perek*. That's the next, it's also in the
פסוק pasuk *passuk*, right? ושמעה קול אלה והוא עד או ראה או
ידע אם לוא יגיד ונשא עונו *v'shama kol alah v'hu eid o
ra-ah o yadah im lo yagid v'nasa avono*, that somebody makes you
take an oath to come testify and you swear you don't know
testimony and you're lying, then you bring a קרבן *korban*, also עולה
ויורד *oleh v'yored*, but it's in the category of שבועת העדות shvuat
ha'edut *shvuat ha-eidus*. So, the חידוש *chiddush* of אביי *Abaye* here is
even though it is בלאו והן belav vehen, *belav v'hen*, since the
לאו *lav* and הן *hen* are different categories, that's not considered איתא
בלאו והן *isa belav v'hen*. So, when you say I know עדות
edut *eidus*, that's the הן *hen*, and that's a שבועת ביטוי shvuat
bitui *shvuat bitoy*, but you're not חייב chayav *chayav* because the negative,
I don't know עדות edut *eidus*, is a different category, not the
שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui. *shvuat bitoy* category, but the שבועת העדות shvuat
ha'edut, *shvuat ha-eidus* category. So, that's definitely a חידוש *chiddush* that that's
considered to be not in the category of לאו והן lav vehen
*lav v'hen*. Hopefully that’s בכלל *bechlal* שאיני יודע לך עדות edut *she'eini
yodeia lecha edus*. ידעתי ולא ידעתי *Yadati velo yadati*, I know testimony
or I don’t know testimony, מחלוקת *machloikes*, that’s the debate because that
is in לאו והן *lav vehein*, but it’s not in the future.
You can’t say I will know testimony. How do you know about
that? So that’s a debate of רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. It’s in
the past but it can’t be made in the future. העדתי ולא
העדתי *He'adati velo he'adati*, similarly I testified, I didn’t testify, also is
the מחלוקת *machloikes*. It is in לאו והן *lav vehein*, but why
is it not future-oriented? Because a שבועה *shvua* that I will testify
or I won’t testify is either a שבועה לקיים את המצווה *shvua
lekayem es hamitzvah* or לבטל את המצווה *levatel es hamitzvah*. So therefore
that’s not a שבועה *shvua* that’s relevant to the קרבן *korban* category,
as we’ve discussed, those שבועות *shvuos* don’t work and therefore this is
the debate of רב ושמואל *Rav u'Shmuel*. בשלמא לשמואל דאמר מלתא דליתא
בלהבא לא מחייב עלה דשעבר *Bishlama leShmuel de’amar milsa deleisa belehaba lo
mechayev alah deshe’avar*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
ask a really good question. Why is שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut, *Shvuas
Ha'edus* its own category? When somebody testifies I don’t know עדות edut,
*edus* for you and they’re lying, isn’t that really just a case
of a שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui *Shvuas Bitoy* according to רבי עקיבא
*Rabbi Akiva*, a past-oriented שבועה *shvua* or at least non-future oriented שבועה
*shvua*? So why do you need a separate category of שבועת העדות
shvuat ha'edut *Shvuas Ha'edus*? So now let’s see what the גמרא *Gemara*
says. It works for שמואל *Shmuel*. בשלמא לשמואל דאמר מלתא דליתא בלהבא
לא מחייב עלה דשעבר *Bishlama leShmuel de’amar milsa deleisa belehaba lo mechayev
alah deshe’avar*. שמואל *Shmuel* says something that even if it’s that something
that doesn’t have a future version, there’s no חיוב chiyuv, *chiyuv* for
the past. להכי אפקיה רחמנא לשבועת העדות מכלל michlal, שבועת ביטוי shvuat
bitui *Lehachi afkei rachmana lishvuas ha’edus michlal shvuas bitoy*. That’s why we
needed a separate category of שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut *Shvuas Ha'edus*. Why?
Because if you said I don’t know testimony for you, you would
not be חייב chayav *chayiv* for שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui. *Shvuas Bitoy*
because there’s no future version of it. I will know testimony for
you, I won’t know testimony for you. Since there’s no future version,
I don’t know testimony, past-oriented, there’s no חיוב *chiyuv* for שבועת ביטוי
shvuat bitui *Shvuas Bitoy* because there’s no future version. And therefore there
had to be a new category of שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut *Shvuas
Ha'edus*. Makes a lot of sense. אלא לרב למאי הלכתא אפקיה רחמנא
*Ela leRav lemai hilchasa afkei rachmana*? But according to רב *Rav*, why
did the תורה Torah *Torah* make a category of שבועת העדות shvuat
ha'edut *Shvuas Ha'edus*? If somebody says I don’t know testimony, so that’s
past-oriented.
It is לאו והן *lav vehein*, you could say I do know
testimony,
and okay, it’s not future-oriented, but we don’t need it to be
able to be made into the future. So the classic שבועת העדות
shvuat ha'edut *Shvuas Ha'edus*, I don’t know testimony for you, why did
the תורה Torah *Torah* have to create that as a separate category?
Why couldn’t that just be a standard שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui. *Shvuas
Bitoy*? Now I should say that שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut, *Shvuas Ha'edus*
also has special criteria. It’s only if somebody is fit to testify.
Has to be a not פסול *passul* person, not a relative, a
man, an adult and so on. It’s only if what’s at stake
is something of real concrete monetary implication. So we have this category
of שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut, *Shvuas Ha'edus* with all these criteria. Why
did the תורה Torah *Torah* create it at all? Every שבועת העדות
shvuat ha'edut, *Shvuas Ha'edus* is a שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui *Shvuas Bitoy*
according to רב *Rav*, it’s past-oriented. Excellent question. אמרו רבנן קמיה דאביי
*Amru rabbanan kamei de’Abaye*, so the רבנן *rabbanan* which is like the
rabbinic students said to אביי *Abaye*, they had the answer. לחייובי עליה
תרתי *Lechiyuvey aleih tarti*. You’re right. Every שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut. *Shvuas
Ha'edus* is a שבועת ביטוי shvuat bitui. *Shvuas Bitoy* according to רב
*Rav*, it’s in this other category called שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut *Shvuas
Ha'edus* because now you get two קרבנות korbanot, *korbanos*, one for שבועת
העדות shvuat ha'edut, *Shvuas Ha'edus* and one for שבועת ביטוי shvuas bitui
*Shvuas Bitoy*. אמר להו amar lehu, *Amar lehu*, so אביי *Abaye* said
back to them, תרתי לא מצית אמרת *tarti lo matzis amras*. No,
no, no, you can’t say somebody is חייב *chayiv* two קרבנות *korbanos*
for שבועת העדות *Shvuas Ha'edus*. Why? דתניא *Detanya*, we taught in a
ברייתא *Braisa*, לאחת מאלה *le'achas me'eileh*. It says if a person sins
of one of these, one of the three categories that you bring
a קרבן עולה ויורד *korban oleh veyored*. לאחת אתה מחייבו ואי אתה
מחייבו שתים *Le’achas atah mechayvo ve’ee atah mechayvo shtayim*. You can only
be מחייב *mechayev* him for one. You can’t get double jeopardy. Right,
the תורה Torah *Torah* is clear if you did the שבועת העדות
*Shvuas Ha'edus* thing, that’s going to be one קרבן *korban*. It’s not
that if you do the שבועת העדות *Shvuas Ha'edus* you bring two
קרבנות *korbanos*, one for עדות edut *edus* and one for ביטוי bitui.
*bitoy*. So that cannot be the answer why the תורה Torah *Torah*
created a separate category of עדות edut, *edus* to get two because
you don’t get two. ואלא לאביי למאי הלכתא אפקיה רחמנא *Ve'ela le'Abaye
lemai hilchasa afkei rachmana*? So then for אביי *Abaye* what is the
answer? Why did the תורה Torah *Torah* create a new category called
שבועת העדות *Shvuas Ha'edus*? לכדתניא *Lechidetanya*, for what we taught in a
ברייתא *Braisa*, בכולן נאמר ונעלם וכאן לא נאמר ונעלם *Bechullan ne’emar vene’elam
vechan lo ne’emar vene’elam*. By שבועת העדות *Shvuas Ha'edus*, by טומאה *tumah*,
by שבועת ביטוי shvuas bitui. *Shvuas Bitoy*, the תורה Torah *Torah* says
ונעלם ממנו *vene’elam mimenu*, that it was hidden from him, he wasn’t
aware that he forgot about the שבועה *shvua*, he forgot about the
טומאה *tumah*. But by שבועת העדות *Shvuas Ha'edus*, it just says that
he swore falsely. It doesn’t say ונעלם *vene’elam* and that teaches you
לחיוב על המזיד כשוגג *lechayev al hamayzid keshogeg*. It’s actually quite strange,
bringing a קרבן *korban* by מזיד meizid. *mayzid*, but that’s the הלכה
*halacha* שבועת העדות *Shvuas Ha'edus*. Even if somebody willfully and knowingly lies
and swears that they don’t know. שבועת העדות, they bring a קרבן,
even though it's a case of מזיד. meizid, So the reason the
תורה created a special category—could have just said it's all שבועת ביטוי,
bitui. sure. But it created a special category of שבועת העדות to
say when it is in the עדות edut category, then you're חייב
even if it's במזיד. So אמר ליה רבנן לאביי, amar lei rabanan
le'Abaye, so the rabbis said to Abaye, so okay, we can see
that that's also an answer, that when it's in the עדות edut
category, it's מזיד, meizid, you're חייב even מזיד, meizid but אימא, eima,
why not say במזיד מחייב חדא, bemeizid mechayev chada, when it's מזיד
meizid you're in the עדות category and that's the one קרבן of
שבועת העדות, בשוגג
מחייב תרתי, beshogeg mechayev tarti, but we still want to argue that
when you're בשוגג beshogeg by שבועת העדות, you're both חייב for שבועת
העדות and for שבועת ביטוי. bitui, So אמר להו, so he said
back to them, I don't understand, that's what I've been saying.
לאו היינו דאמרי לכו, lav hainu de'amri lechu, isn't this what I
already told you? לאחת, אחת אתה מחייב ואי אתה מחייב שתים. le'achat,
achat atah mechayev ve'ee atah mechayev shtayim. So, no, the פסוק pasuk,
says only one קרבן for one act. So I both A, I'm
being מחדש mechadesh something you guys didn't point out, that because of
the שבועת העדות category, you're חייב for מזיד meizid. if you fall
into that, which would not be if there was just a generic
שבועת ביטוי. bitui, And number two, even when you're בשוגג, beshogeg, the
תורה is telling you you're just in the שבועת העדות category, only
one חיוב, not two חיובים. chiyuvim. Okay, but the reason the תורה
created this new category was for the sake of מזיד. meizid ואי
במזיד
ואי תרתי מי קתני, ve'ee bemeizid ve'ee tarti mi katanei, and the
תורה when it's coming saying only one and not two, can't be
talking about the מזיד meizid. scenario, because then there's only the case
of עדות. So if the תורה is going out of its way
to say one and not two, it means in a case of
שוגג, shogeg, still you're only going to bring one קרבן, only for
עדות, not also for ביטוי. רבא אמר, Rava amar, now Rava just
says the same thing but he just says you don't need the
פסוק, you know, מאחת me'achat to tell you that. It's just by
virtue of its being its own category, it means it's just taking
it completely out of the שבועת ביטוי categorization and creating a completely
new category. משום דהוי דבר שבכלל, mishum dehavah davar shebachlal, because שבועת
העדות was already in the general category of שבועת ביטוי according to
Rava, ויצא לידון בדבר חדש, veyatza lidon bedavar chadash, and now it
was made to be given a new status, status of שבועת העדות
to say you're חייב even מזיד. meizid, אין לך בו אלא חידושו
בלבד, ein lecha bo ela chiddusho bilvad, and once it is in
a new category, you only treat it by its new category. So
basically the תורה created this thing called שבועת העדות, the reason it
created it was for the sake of מזיד, meizid, that if you're
in that category you're חייב מזיד, mazed, but once this category exists,
then if something's in this category, it's only עדות and not ביטוי.
All right, now the גמרא has one last question about this.
מכלל, michlal, so that's the answer that it's in its own separate
category. But Abaye said
fundamentally you should be חייב two קרבנות, one for עדות and one
for ביטוי. It is also ביטוי, you know, it's not completely separate,
it's עדות and also ביטוי, but only one קרבן because of מאחת.
me'achat. So מכלל, from that you can infer דאביי סבר איתא לשבועה
בעולם, de'Abaye savar itah lishvuah ba'olam, that even in a שבועת העדות,
it still is in the category of שבועת ביטוי. It's just you
only bring one קרבן. But one minute, that goes against what Abaye
said just a little while ago. והאמר אביי, veha'amar Abaye, didn't Abaye
say מודה רב באומר לחבירו שבועה שאני יודע לך עדות ואשתכח דלא
ידע ליה דפטור הואיל וליתא באני יודע לך עדות, modeh Rav be'omer
lechaveiro shvua she'ani yode'a lacha edut ve'ishtakach delo yada leh depatur ho'il
veleitah be'ani yode'a lacha edut,
that if somebody said a שבועה that I do know עדות, then
even according to Rav you'd be exempt because 'I do know' it's
not בלאו והן, because the negative 'I don't know' while that would
be a good שבועה would be a שבועה of a different type,
would be a שבועת העדות, right? Remember Abaye said that? A שבועה
I do know עדות you're not חייב because the לאו version, 'I
don't know עדות,' is not a שבועת ביטוי but a שבועת העדות.
And therefore it's considered that it's not לאו והן both in the
שבועת ביטוי category. But we just said that Abaye says that a
שבועת העדות is also a שבועת ביטוי. So now actually it does
exist in the לאו והן version. Excellent question. So the גמרא says
הדר ביה אביי מההיא. hadar beih Abaye mehahi. All right, Abaye retracted
himself, he's no longer, not exactly clear which one, but it sounds
like the first one. You know, he's now saying it is also
a שבועת ביטוי and therefore 'I know עדות' you would be חייב
because the reverse 'I don't know עדות' is also a שבועת ביטוי.
שבועת ביטוי and שבועת העדות, but also שבועת ביטוי. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it
eima, and if you want you could say top of כו עמוד
ב, kaf vav amud bet, חדא מינייהו רב פפא אמרה, chada mineihu
Rav Pappa amrah, Abaye sometimes said things in the name of Rav
Pappa, so you're right, these two statements don't go together, and one
of them is Rav Pappa and one of them
is
Abaye. What is it in the end? According to אביי, it might
be, based on which version or whatever, it is both שבועת ביטוי
and שבועת עדות shvuas edos but you only bring one קרבן, and
according to רב, רבא, excuse me, no, once the תורה created the
category of שבועת עדות shvuas edos with the נפקא מינא nafka mina
of מזיד, it's only שבועת עדות and not שבועת ביטוי. Okay, we'll
stop here.