Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"ח, Lamed Chet,
שבועות Shvuos 38, we pick up about two-thirds of the way down
on ל"ז עמוד ב׳, Lamed Zayin Amud Bet, first line with the
lines get wide. אמר ליה רב ירמיה ליה רבי אבהו, Amar lei
Rav Yirmiyah lei Rabbi Abahu, and we are talking about the question
of that you don't take a שבועה shvua by שיבוד קרקעות shibud
karkos when there's a lien on land. So the example in the
גמרא Gemara is if there was a loan with a שטר shtar
and that created a lien, then you would not take a שבועה
shvua because קרקע karka is excluded from the שבועה shvua and from
all of the applications of קרבן korban and so on. And the
גמרא Gemara said this was a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
and רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Eleazar, and we concluded that רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan once, one that said you do not take a שבועה shvua
and you're not חייב, chayav, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said you
are חייב. chayav.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: לימא רבי יוחנן
ורבי אלעזר, Leima Rabbi Yochanan ve-Rabbi Elazar, let's say רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, the אמוראים, Amora'im, בפלוגתא דרבי אליעזר
ורבנן קמיפלגי, be-plugta de-Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbanan kamiflegi, they are following the debate
of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the תנא, Tanna, and the Rabbis. דתנן,
Detnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, or דתניא de-tanya in the
ברייתא, Baraita, and this is about obligations about גזילה gezeilah and שקר,
sheker, and whether that applies to land. הגוזל שדה מחברו ושטפה נהר,
Ha-gozel sadeh me-chavero ve-shatafah nahar, somebody steals a field from his friend,
basically claims that it's his, moves the boundary line, and then it
got flooded by a river. חייב להעמיד לו שדה דברי רבי אליעזר.
Chayav leha'amid lo sadeh, divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
well, you took the field, you are a גנב ganav or גזלן,
gazlan, and now you have an obligation to return the גזילה. gezeilah.
And now it's not the same field, it's flooded, so it's like
you stole a car and the car got wrecked, you have an
obligation to now pay for the car that you stole, pay for
the field that you stole. וחכמים אומרים אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך.
Ve-chachamim omrim: omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha. But the sages say, you
could say look, it's your field, it got flooded, I never took
it. There's no גזילה gezeilah by קרקעות. karkos. I never actually,
it's not an object that I was able to pick up and
remove from you, so most of the time it's even like physically
you can't do the act of stealing it, and even if you
could conceptualize ways in which you could steal it, it nevertheless is
categorically excluded. So since it was never stolen, it's conceptual like I
was preventing you from getting onto your land, but I never stole
it. Therefore I have no obligation to return it. And when it
got flooded, it was your field that got flooded. Okay, so that's
the question of whether גזילה gezeilah includes קרקע karka or not. דברי
רבי אליעזר וחכמים אומרים אומר לו הרי שלך לפניך. Divrei Rabbi Eliezer
ve-chachamim omrim: omer lo harei shelcha lefanecha. ואמרינן, Ve-amrinan,
and we said over there in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, במאי קמיפלגי?
Be-mai kamiflegi? What's the debate? רבי אליעזר דריש ריבוי ומיעוט ורבנן דרשי
כלל ופרט. Rabbi Eliezer darish ribui u-mi'ut ve-Rabbanan darshi klal u-prat. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer does ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u-mi'ut and the Rabbanan כלל
ופרט. klal u-prat. We've discussed this before, ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u-mi'ut winds
up including more things than כלל ופרט. klal u-prat. And now let's
apply it. רבי אליעזר דריש ריבוי ומיעוט. Rabbi Eliezer darish ribui u-mi'ut.
וכחש בעמיתו, Ve-chichesh ba-amito,
he denies his friend, and this is denying that you owe something,
and then it says והשיב את הגזילה אשר גזל, ve-heshiv et ha-gezeilah
asher gazal, and when you admit it, you have to return the
גזילה. gezeilah. So it is in the context of denial, not outright
theft, theft through denial, but nevertheless from this we see the obligation
of גזילה. gezeilah. Okay, ריבה, Riba, so that's inclusive, anything you deny,
בפיקדון או בתשומת יד, be-pikadon o bi-tshumat yad, whether
with a something that's been given over to be watched, or some
other type of an encroachment, מיעט, mi'et,
so that's only very specific types of things, maybe chattel or things
like that, או מכל אשר ישבע עליו לשקר, o mi-kol asher yishava
alav lashaker,
or anything that you would swear falsely, חזר וריבה, chazar ve-riba, that's
again כל אשר kol asher is inclusive.
So ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי, ribui u-mi'ut ve-ribui, ריבה הכל. riba hakol. מאי
ריבה? ריבה כל מילי. Mai riba? Riba kol milei. So the first
thing is all-inclusive, everybody agrees that the first time that it says
a general statement, that includes everything. The debates of ריבוי ומיעוט ribui
u-mi'ut and כלל ופרט klal u-prat start playing out now when we
get to the specificity. Okay, everything is included. ומאי מיעט? מיעט שטרות.
U-mai mi'et? Mi'et shtarot. Okay, so then, I'm sorry, this is already
after you have ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי. ribui u-mi'ut ve-ribui. So the way
ריבוי ומיעוט וריבוי ribui u-mi'ut ve-ribui works is that when you have
ריבוי ribui that's everything, מיעוט mi'ut is saying like is giving you
an example of the types of things, but it doesn't mean only
the things that have been specified, it's a narrowing of the ריבוי
ribui of the all-inclusive. Okay, so by the time you get to
ריבוי ומיעוט, ribui u-mi'ut, it's the same as כלל פרט וכלל. klal
prat u-klal. כלל ופרט Klal u-prat is כלל klal is everything, פרט
prat is specifically, not limiting, specifically, only the things mentioned in the
list. And then by the time you get to the next כלל,
klal, now it's everything like the list. Okay, that idea of everything
like the list is already where you are at stage two by
ריבוי ומיעוט, ribui u-mi'ut, because מיעט mi'et is not specifying, it's narrowing.
So when it said גזל, תשומת יד, או בפיקדון או בתשומת יד
gezel, tshumat yad, o be-pikadon o bi-tshumat yad etc.,
that was like examples. ples, but it really means anything like this
category. And then when you get to the next ריבה, ribba, the
you know, that's now is all included, like is broadening again. So
what you're left with is only excluding things that are the most
dissimilar to the פרט, prat, to the specific. You already included similar
when you had ריבוי ומיעוט, ribui u-miut, the next ריבוי ribui says
the only thing you're going to include exclude is something that is
fully dissimilar. Okay, so what's fully dissimilar?
So ומאי מיעט מיעט שטרות. u-mai mi'eit? Mi'eit shtarot. A שטר, shtar,
a שטר shtar is an IOU, it has no intrinsic value. So
land is like chattel, it's an object of real intrinsic value. So
the only thing we're going to—so we're not going to exclude land,
we're only going to exclude from the obligations of גזילה gezeila a
שטר. shtar. If I steal a promissory note from you and it
gets destroyed, I don't have to pay you back the loan. I
didn't actually steal the loan, I only stole the promissory note which
didn't have any intrinsic value. Okay, so that's Rabbi Eliezer.
מיעט שטרות. mi'eit shtarot. So מהי ריבוי ריבוי הכל מילי, mai ribui?
Ribui ha-kol mili, so at the second ריבוי ribui you've included everything
and the only thing you've excluded is שטרות. shtarot. ורבנן דרשי כלל
ופרט, ve-rabbanan darshi klal u-prat, and the Rabbanan do כלל ופרט. klal
u-prat. וכי יחטא באמיתו כלל, ve-chi yecheta be-amito klal, בפיקדון או בתשומת
יד או בגזל פרט, be-pikadon o bit'sumat yad o be-gezel prat, so
the פרט prat now is only the specific things mentioned. או מכל
אשר ישבע עליו חזר וכלל, o mi-kol asher yishava alav chazar ve-klal,
and then you get the broadening from the specific list. כלל ופרט
וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. klal u-prat u-klal i ata
dan ela ke-ein ha-prat. So when you get to stage three there,
now you're abstracting it to anything like the specific list. מה הפרט
מפורש דבר המיטלטל וגופו ממון, ma ha-prat meforash davar ha-mitaltel ve-gufo mamon,
so that list is things that are not only גופו ממון, gufo
mamon, intrinsic value, to exclude a שטר, shtar, but also things that
are chattel, movables. Okay, אף כל דבר המיטלטל וגופו ממון, af kol
davar ha-mitaltel ve-gufo mamon, so anything that's chattel and also that's movable
and that is intrinsic value. יצאו קרקעות שאין מטלטלין, yatz'u karka'ot she-ein
mitaltelin, so this excludes land which is not movable. Okay, Rabbi Eliezer
was happy to include it, it had intrinsic value, but the Rabbis
exclude it because it is not movable. יצאו עבדים שהוקשו לקרקעות, yatz'u
avadim she-huk'shu le-karka'ot, slaves are excluded because they're connected to land, might
have reflecting the idea, you know, that slaves fundamentally work the land
and they were conceptually connected in that way or they're human beings,
so that way they're fundamentally out of the standard category of like,
you know, objects that can be owned. יצאו שטרות, yatz'u shtarot, and
we're going to exclude שטרות shtarot שאף על פי שמטלטל אין גופן
ממון, she-af al pi she-mitaltel ein gufan mamon, even though they can
be moved, they don't have intrinsic value. Okay. So מן דמחייב כרבי
אליעזר, man de-mechayev ke-Rabbi Eliezer, so now it works out very well.
You know, Rabbi Elazar who says you're חייב chayav when you make
a שבועה shvu'a on the, you know, on something that has liens
and on קרקע karka is like Rabbi Eliezer that says you're חייב
chayav when you steal קרקע, karka, that they only exclude שטרות shtarot
and they include
קרקע. karka. מן דפטר כרבנן, man de-patar ke-rabbanan, Rabbi Yochanan who says
you're פטור patur when you take a—about a שבועה shvu'a relating to
קרקע karka or to liens, כרבנן, ke-rabbanan, would be like the Rabbanan
that say that you're פטור patur when you steal קרקע. karka. Yep,
it very much seems like it's the exact debate. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, especially also because the פסוק pasuk וכי יחטא באמיתו,
ve-chi yecheta be-amito, right, is in the context of a שבועה. shvu'a.
We learn from it both the obligations of גזל gezel but it's
also a פסוק pasuk that's talking about a שבועה. shvu'a. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה
לא, amar lei lo, no, it—you don't—you're not forced into that one-to-one
matchup. מן דמחייב כרבי אליעזר, man de-mechayev ke-Rabbi Eliezer, you're right, you
know, Rabbi Elazar who says you're חייב chayav for a שבועה, shvu'a,
the only person he could be following would be Rabbi Eliezer that
says that you're חייב chayav for גזל gezel by קרקע. karka. So
you have to go within the approach of Rabbi Eliezer; if you're
חייב chayav for גזל gezel of קרקע, karka, the approach that you're
חייב chayav for a שבועה shvu'a fits within that approach.
Okay, but ומן דפטר כרבי יוחנן u-man de-patar ke-Rabbi Yochanan that exempts
you for a שבועה shvu'a for קרקע, karka, he could claim that
Rabbi Eliezer works even according to him.
ומן דפטר מלא בהא אפילו רבי אליעזר מודה, u-man de-patar mela be-ha
afilu Rabbi Eliezer modeh, when it comes to the שבועה, shvu'a, even
Rabbi Eliezer who says yes, there's גזל gezel by קרקע karka would
agree with me that there's no שבועה shvu'a by קרקע. karka. Why?
דרחמנא אמר מכל, de-rachmana amar mi-kol, מכל אשר ישבע עליו לשקר, mi-kol
asher yishava alav la-sheker, from anything that you take an oath, ולא
הכל, ve-lo ha-kol, and not everything, but מכל, mi-kol, it's even a
smaller category. So even though it's ממש mamash the same פסוק, pasuk,
the claim is, Rabbi Yochanan's claim is the same Rabbi Eliezer that
includes קרקע karka for גזל gezel would have a narrower category for
שבועה shvu'a because it says מכל אשר ישבע עליו. mi-kol asher yishava
alav. Okay. That is then the question now, can קרקע karka be
stolen and also is there a שבועה shvu'a on קרקע karka and
even is there a שבועה shvu'a when there are liens? Okay. אמר
רב פפא משמיה דרבא, amar Rav Pappa mishmeih de-Rava, Rava said in
the name of—Rav Pappa in the name of Rava said, מתניתין נמי
דיקא, matnitin nami dika, our Mishna can also be like a close
reading of the text of our Mishna supports the position of Rabbi
Yochanan that it does not apply to קרקע. karka. Why?
דקתני, de-katani, our Mishna says, גנבת את שורי והוא אומר... ganavta et
shori ve-hu omer... אמר רב פפא משמיה דרבא Amar Rav Pappa mishmei
deRava Rava said in the name of Rava Rav Pappa in the
name of Rava said מתניתין נמי דייקא Matnitin nami deika our Mishnah
can also be like a close reading of the text of our
Mishnah supports the position of Rabbi Yochanan that it does not apply
to קרקע. karka. Why? דקתני de-katani our Mishnah says גנבת את שורי
והוא אמר לא גנבתי משביעני אני ואמר אמן חייב. Ganavta et shori
ve-hu amar lo ganavti mashbiani ani ve-amar amen chayav. It gives an
example that somebody claims you stole my ox. ואילו גנבת את עבדי
לא קתני. ve-ilu ganavta et avdi lo katani. Why didn't it give
an example of stealing a slave? Okay, the fact that it chose
the example of ox when it could have chosen the example of
slave and that would have been a bigger חידוש chidush that even
though slaves are like קרקע karka but it chose, you know, so
if that were true that you're חייב chayav on קרקע karka it
should have given that example. So the only reason it didn't give
that example מאי טעמא? mai taama? What's the only reason to explain
it didn't give that example? לאו משום דעבד הוקש לקרקעות ואין מביאין
קרבן על כפירת שיעבוד קרקעות? Lav mishum de-eved hukash le-karkaot ve-ein meviin
korban al kfirat shibud karkaot? The only explanation would be because קרקע
karka is not included. Otherwise, it should have given slaves, that would
have been an even bigger חידוש. chidush. All right, doesn't seem like
the most overwhelming proof but a, you know, argument from silence, but
okay. אמר רב פפי משמיה דרבא Amar Rav Papi mishmei de-Rava אימא
סיפא. eima seifa. I will counter that by another line that could
be read to include קרקע. karka. Why? It says זה כלל, ze
klal, this is the general principle. כל המשלם על פי עצמו חייב.
kol ha-meshalem al pi atzmo chayav. Anything you would pay for if
you would admit you're חייב chayav for שבועת הפיקדון shvuat ha-pikadon meaning
excluding קנס, knas, something that your admission would obligate you. וכל שאינו
משלם על פי עצמו פטור, ve-kol she-eino meshalem al pi atzmo patur,
but if it's something that you would not be obligated like a
קנס knas if you admitted it, you'd be exempt. Okay, so that
excludes קנס. knas. זה כלל לאתויי מאי? ze klal laatuyei mai? When
it says anything that you would be חייב chayav if you admitted,
that's a very general statement. What's that including? לאו לאתויי גנבת את
עבדי? Lav laatuyei ganavta et avdi? On the face of it, anything
would include you stole my slave. So two arguments from silence, one
to be more, you know, exclusive, one to be more inclusive, they
neutralize one another. Top of למד חית עמוד א. lamed chet amud
aleph. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. Ella me-ha lika le-mishma mina. Okay
fine, you can't really prove anything from either argument from silence. Very
good. That's the debate about whether it applies by קרקע karka and
by עבדים. avadim. Now we move to the next part of the
משנה. Mishnah. This is going to get a little technical here. Let's
remind
ourselves what the משנה Mishnah was saying. So in the משנה Mishnah
we have the following. I'll read the משנה Mishnah again. היו חמשה
תובעין אותו. Hayu chamisha tovin oto. Five different people were telling, were
demanding from him to give something back. אמרו לו תן לנו פיקדון
שיש לנו בידך. Amru lo ten lanu pikadon she-yesh lanu be-yadecha. Give
us the, you know, פיקדון pikadon that we gave you. So he
says שבועה שאין לכם בידי. shvua she-ein lachem be-yadi.
Nope, I don't have anything of yours. אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino
chayav ella achat. שבועה שאין לך בידי ולא לך ולא לך חייב
על כל אחת ואחת. Shvua she-ein lecha be-yadi ve-lo lecha ve-lo lecha
chayav al kol achat ve-achat. That if you say not you and
not you and not you, then each one is a separate שבועה.
shvua. רבי אלעזר אומר עד שיאמר
שבועה באחרונה. Rabbi Elazar omer ad she-yomar shvua ba-achrona. You would have
to say שבועה shvua I don't have not you and not you
and not you שבועה. shvua. And only saying the שבועה shvua at
the end means that each one is a separate שבועה. shvua. רבי
שמעון אומר עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד. Rabbi Shimon omer ad
she-yomar shvua le-kol echad ve-echad. Rabbi Shimon says no, it's never a
separate שבועה shvua unless you say שבועה shvua I don't have for
you and שבועה shvua I don't have for you and שבועה shvua
I don't have for you. So fine, so the משנה Mishnah actually
is pretty straightforward. When you say you, not you, not you, not
you, does that make it separate שבועות shvuot or do you have
to add the word שבועה shvua at the end as well or
do you have to say שבועה shvua with each one? So that's
pretty straightforward. It gets complicated because the גמרא Gemara introduces from a
ברייתא braita a debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So hold on and fasten your
seatbelts. Okay and תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, our Rabbis taught. שבועת הפיקדון
כיצד? Shvuat ha-pikadon keitzad? תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, three lines from the
top למד חית עמוד א. lamed chet amud aleph.
כלל, Klal, if you made a general statement that put everything in
the same category, אינו חייב אלא אחת, eino chayav ella achat, then
it's only one שבועה. shvua. פרט, Prat, if you specified, חייב על
כל אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achat ve-achat, you're חייב chayav for
each individual person. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what Rabbi
Meir says. So presumably that means if you said I don't have
anything of yours, that's one שבועה shvua like the משנה Mishnah said.
If it said not you, not you, not you, not you, that's
פרט prat specifying, then it's separate שבועות. shvuot. But then you have
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה אומר שבועה לא לך ולא לך
ולא לך חייב על כל אחת ואחת. Rabbi Yehuda omer shvua lo
lecha ve-lo lecha ve-lo lecha chayav al kol achat ve-achat. If you
say not you, not you, not you, חייב chayav on every one.
Well, that sounded just like Rabbi Meir's case of פרט. prat. So
we're going to get into a whole discussion, what is the debate
of Rabbi Yehuda's statement, how is that different than Rabbi Meir's case
of פרט? prat? רבי אלעזר אומר לא לך ולא לך ולא לך
שבועה חייב על כל אחת ואחת. Rabbi Elazar omer lo lecha ve-lo
lecha ve-lo lecha shvua chayav al kol achat ve-achat. Now it's like
the משנה Mishnah according to him you have to say שבועה shvua
at the end for each one to be a separate שבועה. shvua.
רבי שמעון אומר עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד. Rabbi Shimon omer
ad she-yomar shvua le-kol echad ve-echad. You have to say שבועה shvua
for each one. Fine. So what was newly introduced here was Rabbi
Yehuda's לא לך ולא לך ולא לך lo lecha ve-lo lecha ve-lo
lecha and how is that different from Rabbi Meir's פרט? prat? So
let's take a look. This is going to be a whole debate.
רש״י Rashi tells us how to read this. We're just going to
read it like רש״י. Rashi. Okay.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. כללו של
רבי מאיר פרטו של רבי יהודה. Klalo shel Rabbi Meir prato shel
Rabbi Yehuda. Rabbi Yehuda's לא לך ולא לך ולא לך lo lecha
ve-lo lecha ve-lo lecha
we're going to claim that that is what Rabbi Meir meant when
Rabbi Meir said if you כללו klalo if if you make a
כלל klal if you put them all in the same category it's
only one meaning for him the
ו. vav. ולא לך ולא לך ולא לך velo lecha velo lecha
velo lecha makes them all one group. Okay, that actually makes some
sense. So then what would be the פרט prat of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir without the ו? vav? לא לך, לא לך, לא לך.
lo lecha, lo lecha, lo lecha. All right, that's rabbi sense. כללו
של רבי מאיר, Klalo shel Rabbi Meir, פרטו של רבי יהודה. Prato
shel Rabbi Yehuda. When רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda פרט prat ולא לך,
velo lecha, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would make a כלל klal
and would make only one. Here's the sentence that's harder. כללו של
רבי יהודה, Klalo shel Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda כלל. klal.
Now, what is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda כלל? klal? We don't know.
So he's going to tell us that רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda כלל
klal is what? פרטו של רבי מאיר. Prato shel Rabbi Meir. רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir פרט. prat. So what we're saying is רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says if you say, if you say ולא לך ולא
לך ולא לך, velo lecha velo lecha velo lecha, it's one category.
לא לך, לא לך, לא לך, lo lecha, lo lecha, lo lecha,
it's separate. That makes sense. But now we're saying that רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says
ולא ולא ולא velo velo velo is separate,
and okay, you could say even that is separate, but now we're
saying something that's really hard. לא לך, לא לך, לא לך lo
lecha, lo lecha, lo lecha without the ו, vavs, that actually makes
it one category. Doesn't make a lot of sense, very hard to
understand. Okay, let's now look at the next position.
רבי יוחנן אמר לא הכל מודים בולא לך שהוא פרט ולא נחלקו
אלא בלא לך שרבי מאיר אומר פרט ורבי יהודה אומר כלל. Rabbi
Yochanan amar lo hakol modim bevelo lecha shehu prat velo necheleku ela
belo lecha sheRabbi Meir omer prat veRabbi Yehuda omer klal. Everybody actually
says that when you say ולא לך, velo lecha, when רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda said ולא לך ולא ולא ולא לך velo lecha velo
velo velo lecha is a פרט, prat, is separate, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir would agree that those are separate. Okay, so what's the debate?
So the debate is if you said לא לך, לא לך, לא
לך, lo lecha, lo lecha, lo lecha, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said
that that also would be a פרט. prat. But רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda is saying no, without the ו vav it's a כלל. klal.
So both in the first statement and the second, you have the
idea that the possibility that without the ו vav it could be
more of a כלל klal than with the ו. vav. I really
can't understand that. Unless maybe you say that when you say the
ולא, velo, it's I'm taking the word שבועה shvua that you said
and also applying it to this other ולא velo and to this
other ולא. velo. Without the ו, vav, it stands, you know, I'm
not extending the word שבועה, shvua, so maybe I have to see
it as a group. I really don't get it. Okay, so don't
try to understand it, or if you try to understand it let
me know what you come up with. But anyway, you have to
just accept that it's, that there's an idea going in this גמרא
Gemara that without the ו vav it's more of a group and
a כלל, klal, with the ו vav it more stands out. So
it's, everyone is separate. So you have the first position, which is
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, that basically
say רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon are inverses
of one
another, I mean רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
That for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the ו vavs are a כלל
klal and without the ו vavs it's a פרט. prat. That makes
sense. And for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir the ו vavs are a
פרט prat and without the ו vavs is a כלל. klal. And
then you've got the position of, of what do you call it?
Of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that everybody agrees the ו vavs are
a פרט. prat. And the question is, the debate is whether, you
know, without the ו, vavs, for that for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
it's a, it's a פרט, prat, and for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
it's a כלל. klal. It's hard to keep track of all this.
Okay, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
ואיזהו כללו של רבי מאיר? Ve'eizehu klalo shel Rabbi Meir? So if
for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir with or without the ו vav it's
a פרט, prat, what would be the כלל? klal? שבועה שאין לכם
בידי. Shvua she'ein lachem beyadi. The simple case of a כלל, klal,
שבועה שאין לכם בידי. shvua she'ein lachem beyadi. Fine.
All right. במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamiflegi? Where is this debate coming from,
these two different interpretations? So rather than telling us the logic, the
גמרא Gemara is telling us the textual derivation. שמואל דייק מברייתא ורבי
יוחנן דייק ממתניתין. Shmuel dayek mibraita veRabbi Yochanan dayek mimatnitin. שמואל Shmuel
focuses on the ברייתא braita which we started with, and רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan goes back to the
משנה. Mishna. שמואל דייק מברייתא. Shmuel dayek mibraita. מכדי אמר רבי יהודה
ולא לך פרטא הוי.
Midei amar Rabbi Yehuda velo
lecha prata havei. Since רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying when you
say it with the ו vavs it's separate,
מכלל דשמיע ליה לרבי מאיר דאמר כללא הוי. miklal deshmiya lei leRabbi
Meir damar klala havei. So if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is saying
I am going to tell us that with the ו vavs it's
separate, the only way to read that is if he assumed that
for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it was all one category, and he's
saying no, no, no, with the ו vavs it's separate categories. That's
why he says with the ו vavs you're going to bring separate
קרבנות. korbanot. It suggests that for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir in exactly
that case with the ו vavs it's only going to be one
קרבן. korban. That is pretty much פשט. pshat. Okay. מכלל דשמיע ליה
לרבי מאיר דאמר כללא הוי ואמר ליה רבי יהודה פרטא הוי. Miklal
deshmiya lei leRabbi Meir damar klala havei ve'amar lei Rabbi Yehuda prata
havei.
Now that's fine. That's why we think that, you know, it doesn't
explain why he inverted it in terms of, you know, that רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir כלל klal is רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda פרט, prat,
but okay. At least to understand that when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
said that the ו vavs are separate קרבנות, korbanot, the implication of
the ברייתא braita is that for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it would
be one קרבן. korban. And that genuinely is the פשט. pshat. רבי
יוחנן אמר לא תרווייהו לרבי מאיר פרטא הוי. Rabbi Yochanan amar lo
travaihu leRabbi Meir prata havei.
No,
no, no, I'm going to tell... say that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* says with or without the ו vov. *vav*s, it's a
פרט prat. *prat*? So why did רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehudah*
say with the ו vovs. *vav*s, it's a פרט prat. *prat*? רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* agrees to that. ואמר ליה רבי Rebbi
יהודה *veamar lei Rabbi Yehudah*, and רבי Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* said:
בולו לך מודינא לך *b'velo lecha modina lach*, בלא לך פליגינא לך
*b'lo lecha pligina lach*. No, no, no. You say both of them
are a פרט prat, *prat*. I, רבי Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah*, am
saying only with the ו vovs *vav* is it a פרט prat
*prat*, but without, it's going to be a כלל klal? *klal*. So
he says—so it's not a good דיוק *diyuk* because—but that's how he's
going to read the ברייתא braita *baraita*. ושמואל *Ushmuel*, and because שמואל
*Shmuel* could say back to you, עד דאודי ליה אודויי ליפלוג ליה
פלוגי *ada odlei aduyei liflog lei pligei*. So he says that's not
how you debate. You don't debate by saying, oh, here's the position
I agree with. You debate by saying the position you disagree with.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* reads it that when רבי
Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* says with the ו vovs? *vav*s are separate
קרבנות *korbanot*, what he's saying is, that's the only part I agree
with you about. But without—but I disagree on your claim that without
the ו vov *vav*s is separate קרבנות *korbanot*. Okay. And and but
but so but you, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*, hold of
both. Here's the part that I agree with: the with the ו
vov *vav*s. And שמואל *Shmuel* reasonably says, if that was—if שמואל *Shmuel*
said both, then רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* should say, here's
the one I disagree with, not here's the one I agree with.
So שמואל *Shmuel* has a very good דיוק *diyuk* from the ברייתא
braita *baraita* that רבי Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah*'s לא לך ולא לך
ולא לך lo l'cha v'lo l'cha v'lo l'cha *lo lecha velo lecha
velo lecha*, each one is separate. From the fact that רבי Rebbi.
יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* said, "this is my position," it implies that for
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir*, all of that is one category.
Okay, let's see what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* gets from
the משנה Mishnah *mishna*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's דייק ממתניתין *Rabbi Yochanan
dayek mimasnisa*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's *Rabbi Yochanan* infers it from the
משנה Mishnah *mishna*. מדקאמר רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. שבועה shvua שאין לכם
lachem בידי *mi deka'amar Rabbi Meir shevuah she'ein lachem beyadi*. We're assuming
that our משנה Mishnah *mishna*'s רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*, סתם
משנה Mishnah *stam mishna*'s רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. So what
case in our משנה Mishnah *mishna* did it say is considered one
קרבן korban *korban*? When you said אין לכם בידי *ein lachem beyadi*,
which is no לך *lecha*s and ולא לך v'lo lecha *velo lecha*s,
it's just אין לכם *ein lachem*. כלל הוי *klal hava* says since
in the משנה Mishnah *mishna* for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
that's a כלל *klal*, מכלל *miklal* the implication would be that any
specification of לא לך lo lecha *lo lecha* with or without a
ו vov *vav* is a פרט prat. *prat*, since the only כלל
*klal* in the משנה Mishnah *mishna* is אין לכם *ein lachem*. Okay.
דולא לך פרט prat. הוי דאי סלקא דעתך ולא לך v'lo lecha
כלל הוי *d'velo lecha prat hava di salka daitach velo lecha klal
hava*. If for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* any version of
the לא לך lo lecha *lo lecha* with or without the ו
vov. *vav* would be a פרט prat, *prat*—רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir* of the משנה Mishnah *mishna*—הוי אדמשמע לן שבועה shvua שאין לכם
בידי *hava ad mashmalan shevuah she'ein lachem beyadi*. Why did the משנה
Mishnah *mishna* give us the example that אין לכם *ein lachem* is
a כלל *klal* and only one קרבן *korban*? לשמעינן שבועה shvuah לא
לך ולא לך v'lo lecha ולא לך *lishmian shevuah lo lecha velo
lecha velo lecha*. Let us tell us that there's a version of
the לא לך *lo lecha*s where it's a כלל *klal* when you
have a ו vov *vav*, וכל שכן שבועה shvuah שאין לכם בידי
*kol shekein shevuah she'ein lachem beyadi*. Okay, and certainly if you said
אין לכם *ein lachem*. So he's right. If you assume our משנה
Mishnah *mishna* is רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, our משנה Mishnah *mishna* sounds
like the only thing that is a כלל *klal* is לכם *lachem*,
and everything else would be a פרט prat *prat*. And that's why
he's going to claim that even in the ברייתא braita *baraita*, רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* holds all the variations are a פרט prat *prat*,
and רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah* is only agreeing with him in one
of them. Okay. ושמואל *Ushmuel*, and שמואל *Shmuel* would say אמר *amar*,
and שמואל
*Shmuel* would say back to you: כל אומר ולא לך כאומר שבועה
shvuah, שאין לכם בידי דמי *kol omer velo lecha k'omer shevuah she'ein
lachem beyadi dami*. Not the most convincing answer. Yes, the משנה mishnah
*mishna* said אין לכם *ein lachem*, but רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* assumes
that ולא לך ולא לך *velo lecha velo lecha* is just the
same as לכם *lachem*. The ו vov *vav*s combine it, so he
didn't have to spell it out particularly. Okay, fine. So what we
have is that for רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah*, the ו vovs *vav*s
are—everybody sort of agrees—are separate; without the ו vov. *vav*s it's one.
Don't ask me about that, but that everybody agrees with for רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah*. And the debate is: what does רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* say? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan? *Rabbi Yochanan* says from the משנה
mishnah *mishna* it sounds like רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* would say everything
is a פרט prat *prat* because the only thing that for רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* is a כלל *klal* is לא לכם lo lachem
*lo lachem*. And שמואל *Shmuel* would say no, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
is the inverse of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehudah*. Okay. And the only
thing that's a כלל *klal* would be the ולא לך *velo lecha*,
and the other would
be—the only thing that's a פרט *prat*, I should have said, is
without the ו vav, *vav*. Once you add the ולא לך *velo
lecha*, that becomes the כלל *klal*. Okay. תא שמע Ta shema *ta
shma*, "come and hear," says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
תנן *tsna*, excuse me, לא לך ולא לך ולא לך *lo lecha
velo lecha velo lecha*. So our משנה mishnah, *mishna*—the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
version of our משנה mishnah *mishna* was with the ו vav, *vav*s
and that was making it a פרט *prat*, and this was רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. So again, this supports רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan's *Rabbi
Yochanan* that anything other than לכם *lachem* is going to be a
פרט *prat* for רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says: תני לא לך *tani lo lecha*. Take out the ו *vav*s
from the משנה mishnah *mishna*, have it read לא לך *lo lecha*.
Okay, that's how שמואל *Shmuel* would respond. תא שמע ta shma *ta
shma*, let's look later in the משנה mishnah. *mishna*: תן לי פקדון
ותשומת יד וגזל pikadon v'tzumat yad v'gezel? ואבידה *ten li pikadon utshumat
yad v'gezel v'aveida*. So again you have the ו *vav*s combining it
and the משנה mishna *mishna* considers that to be multiple שבועות shvuot,
*shevuot*. Again, it's a proof that for the משנה mishna. *mishna*, for
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, anything other than
לכם *lachem* is in. Those cases wheat barley spelt it has ו
and the משנה mishna. assumes they're separate. It shows you for רבי
מאיר anything that's not לכם is considered separate even with the ו.
גמרא Gemara says תני שעורין כוסמין כוסמין Tani seorin kusmin kusmin take
out the ו. So the גמרא Gemara finally gets fed up. גמרא
Gemara says והאי תנא כל הכי שביש תני ואזיל? ve'hai tana kol
hachi shabish tani ve'azil?
Really you want me to expect our version of the משנה mishna?
is all with the ו and you're saying that's a mistake that's
a mistake that's a mistake it meant without the ו? If that
is a core part of the debate of רבי מאיר and רבי
יהודה the תנא tana is not going to get it wrong in
all those cases. So you gotta admit that our משנה Mishnah. it
sounds like any לא לך with or without the ו is a
פרט. So that seems to be a nice proof for רבי יוחנן's
Rabbi Yochanan version of רבי מאיר. So the גמרא Gemara says okay
I admit that's the משנה Mishnah but I'm going to claim it's
not רבי מאיר. גמרא Gemara says like this אלא מני רבי היא
ella mani Rebbi hi this is really the position of רבי דאמר
לא שנא כזית כזית ולא שנא כזית וכזית פרטה הוי. d'amar lo
shna k'zayis k'zayis ve'lo shna k'zayis u'kzayis pratah havei. There actually is
a position of רבי that and this is in a debate about
if somebody basically
is שחיטה shechting a קרבן and has a thought about פיגול pigul
which is to eat at the wrong time and a thought about
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and basically what he says is or thinks
is says is I plan to eat a כזית kzayis tomorrow and
a
כזית kzayis outside of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So רבי says
I don't care if you said כזית kzayis tomorrow כזית kzayis outside
or כזית kzayis tomorrow and כזית kzayis outside okay each one either
way those are separate thoughts and since they're separate thoughts we don't
treat it as if you said them both as one statement. And
what's the relevance of that? That if the first thought is the
פיגול pigul thought I plan to eat a כזית kzayis tomorrow then
you say and a כזית kzayis outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
but because we separate those as two things you've already made it
פיגול. pigul. And then saying כזית kzayis outside doesn't stop it from
being פיגול. pigul. If we treated that whole thing as one thought
and one statement then because that one statement also had the outside
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it wouldn't be פיגול. pigul. Okay but
bottom line is the question is also when do we say it's
one statement of all these things and when is it separate statements?
And רבי there says whether you used a ו or didn't use
a ו they're separate statements. גמרא Gemara says fine our משנה Mishnah
you're right
every version of לא לך is a separate statement separate שבועה shvuah.
but it's following רבי I'm not going to concede that it's רבי
מאיר. Okay. תא שמע ta shma. says the גמרא gemara מדידי mideidei
let's try to prove it from רבי מאיר's own statement. רבי מאיר
אומר אפילו חיטה ושעורה וכוסמת חייב על כל אחת ואחת. Rabbi Meir
omer afilu chita u'seora ve'kusemes chayav al kol achas ve'achas. So now
we have רבי מאיר in the משנה Mishnah saying even if you
say חיטה chita not
חיטין chitin but חיטה chita כוסמת kusemes and so we'll have to
see what they're debating about but each one is a separate שבועה
shvuah and he uses a ו. So you see for רבי מאיר
also the ו is still separate. גמרא gemara. says תני חיטה שעורה
כוסמת. Tani chita seora kusemes. Okay now we don't have to change
all of the cases in the משנה Mishnah you're right the earlier
cases in the משנה are all with a ו that's רבי. By
the time now you get to this one statement of רבי מאיר
here we could say the משנה kept the ו because it was
doing it earlier but really for רבי מאיר the statement would only
be without the ו. All right so that's a דוחק duchak but
certainly is פשט pshat of the משנה is that anything that isn't
לא לכם is seen as separate. Now the גמרא gemara finally turns
to this issue of חיטה chita כוסמת kusemes what's this debate about?
מאי אפילו? Mai afilu? What does it mean even if you just
said חיטה chita כוסמת? kusemes? אמר רב אחא בריה דרב איקא אפילו
חיטה בכלל חיטין ושעורה בכלל שעורין וכוסמת בכלל כוסמין Amar Rav Acha
brei d'Rav Ika afilu chita bichlal chitin ve'seora bichlal seorin ve'kusemes bichlal
kusmin
that even if you say
חיטה chita you don't mean one grain of wheat you don't mean
one grain of barley. חיטה chita is saying the generic the category
and therefore it is a
טענה tana that has a שווה פרוטה shvei pruta if it wasn't
a שווה פרוטה shvei pruta then you wouldn't be חייב. chayav. So
even though the person is talking about חיטה chita we interpret it
to mean חיטין chitin we don't interpret it to mean one grain.
Okay so now let's take a look. תן לי חיטין ושעורין. Ten
li chitin u'seorin. אמר רבי יוחנן פרוטה מכולא מצטרפת. Amar Rabbi Yochanan
pruta mikula mitztarefes. So רבי יוחנן says let's say in this case
he says
you owe me חיטין chitin שעורין seorin or whatever and each one
by themselves is not a פרוטה pruta but he says but all
those three categories combined the wheat the spelt the barley comes to
a פרוטה pruta he says that would combine to be מחייב mechayiv
you. Now the question is what are we talking about when you
made them פרטים prats or when you made it a כלל?
So to understand this we're going to have to first see a
different debate in the משנה when we're dealing with a case of
פרט. So let's take a look. So פליגי בר אבא ורבינא. pleigi
Bar Abba v'Ravina. חד אמר אפרטי מחייב אכללי לא מחייב. chad amar
apratei mechayev aklalei lo mechayev.
In the משנה when you have a case of פרט, you know,
אין לך בידי חטים, ein l'cha b'yadi chitin, you know, not חטים
chitin and not שעורים se'orin and not כוסמין. kusmin.
Okay,
whether with the ו, without the ו, it's a case of a
פרט and you're חייב chayav for each one. So he says when
the משנה says you're חייב chayav for each one, that's all you're
חייב. chayav. Those three. Not on, there's no general חיוב chiyuv as
well for all three of them combined. וחד אמר, v'chad amar, and
the other one says, אכללי נמי מחייב. aklalei nami mechayev. When it
says you're חייב על כל אחת ואחת, chayav al kol achat v'achat,
it means one שבועה shvuah for חטים, chitin, one for שעורים, se'orin,
one for כוסמין, kusmin, and when you said אין לך בידי ein
l'cha b'yadi before you got to saying חטים ולא כוסמין ושעורים, chitin
v'lo kusmin v'se'orin, that was also a שבועה shvuah that you don't
have anything and that referred to all three together. So in the
חיובים chiyuvim of the משנה, of the פרטים, pratim, you know, one
opinion here is saying that in addition to the individual שבועה, shvuah.
there's also a generic שבועה. shvuah? Okay, now, אכללי נמי מחייב. aklalei
nami mechayev. Now, the גמרא gemara says,
so now when רבי יוחנן said you can even if you only
have a פרוטה prutah from the wheat and barley and כוסמין kusmin
and spelt combined, if you say that when those are separate שבועות,
shvuot, there's no generic one that brings them all together, then רבי
יוחנן's statement is not talking about the case of פרט. רבי יוחנן's
statement would only be when you said אין לך בידי כלום, ein
l'cha b'yadi klum, only in the case of the משנה
when you are mamish have just one category. Then the question is
what's the חידוש chiddush of רבי יוחנן? But the other opinion would
say that רבי יוחנן's statement is even in the case of פרט.
And what רבי יוחנן is saying is in the case of משנה
of פרט, if you only have a third of a פרוטה prutah
for each one, then even though you wouldn't get the individual שבועות,
shvuot. you could still be מצטרף mitztaref them because every case of
the cases of פרט there's also one generic שבועה shvuah that brings
them all together. That's a really nice חידוש chiddush then. Okay, now,
אכללי נמי מחייב. aklalei nami mechayev. Now, let's take a look. תא
שמע Ta shema, says the גמרא. gemara I'm sorry, so גמרא Gemara.
not תא שמע. והתני רבי חייא הרי כאן חמש עשרה חטאות. v'ha
tani Rabbi Chiya harei kan chamish esrei chataot. ואי איתא עשרים הוין.
v'i ita esrim havyun. So one minute, we have a ברייתא braita
that רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says that there are in the case
of five people are demanding from him, and you know, and you
had
חטים שעורים וכוסמין. chitin se'orin v'kusmin. So each one is demanding three
things, right in the case of the פרטים. pratim. So there's a
ברייתא רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says oh in that case you have
five people each one is saying חטים chitin and you say לא
לך ולא לך ולא לך and you say לא לך לא חטים
שעורים וכוסמין ולא לך לא חטים שעורים וכוסמין lo l'cha lo chitin
se'orin v'kusmin v'lo l'cha lo chitin se'orin v'kusmin etc. So you do
the math, five times three and you have fifteen. ואי איתא v'i
ita and if each one of those cases of פרט would also
have a generic חיוב chiyuv of all of them combined, so עשרים
הוין, esrim havyun, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya should have said there
are twenty שבועות. shvuot, So גמרא Gemara. says האי תנא דפרטי קחשיב
דכללי לא קחשיב. hai tanna d'pratei k'chashiv d'klalei lo k'chashiv. Yes
it's true, there would be twenty שבועות, shvuot. but when רבי חייא
Rabbi Chiya said fifteen, he was saying you have fifteen specific שבועות.
shvuot You have a total of twenty, you have five general, but
you have fifteen specific. It's pretty funny once you're going to list
them the point should be to tell me the full number. Okay,
והתני רבי חייא הרי כאן עשרים חטאות. v'ha tani Rabbi Chiya harei
kan esrim chataot. So one minute though, we have another ברייתא that
he says that there are twenty חטאות. chataot. Okay,
so actually the way רש"י Rashi explains that, that actually now is
והתני v'ha tani is actually sometimes a supportive proof because if one
statement of רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is fifteen and one statement is
twenty, rather than saying he's contradicting himself or there's contradictory traditions, the
only way to reconcile them is saying twenty is when he's counting
both the specific and the general שבועה shvuah. and fifteen is only
when he's counting the specific. So if that's true, then bringing them
together is evidence that there are in each one of them a
general שבועה shevua. as well.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, ההיא אפקדון ותשומת יד וגזל ואבידה.
hahi apikadon v'tsumat yad v'gezel v'aveidah. No, no, no, that version of
twenty, I'm going to insist you know that you only count that
there's only the specific, there's no general, or even if there is
a general, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya is just counting the specific. And
nevertheless there's two different cases in the משנה. The case of
חטים שעורים וכוסמין, chitin se'orin v'kusmin, that's three, and the case of
you know פקדון תשומת יד גזל ואבידה pikadon tsumat yad gezel v'aveidah
which is four. So the ברייתא that says fifteen, you know five
different people demanding, it's five times the three חטים כוסמין ושעורים. chitin
kusmin v'se'orin. The one that says twenty is the case of five
times the four פקדון תשומת יד גזל ואבידה. pikadon tsumat yad gezel
v'aveidah. Okay, but either way you can't prove anything from the fifteen
and twenty and yes obviously he's just counting the specifics, but he
might that might not be rejecting the idea that there are also
are general שבועות shavuos. going around going on there as well. Okay,
בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן. ba'ei minei Rava me'Rav Nachman. So Rava
asked Rav Nachman: היו חמשה תובעין אותו ואמרו לו תן לנו פקדון
ותשומת יד וגזל ואבידה שיש לנו בידך. Hayu chamisha tovin oto v'amru
lo ten lanu pikadon v'tzumat yad v'gezel va'aveida sheyesh lanu beyadecha. אמר
לאחד מהם שבועה שאין לך בידי פקדון ותשומת יד וגזל ואבידה ולא
לך ולא לך ולא לך ולא לך מהו? Amar le'echad mehem shavua
she'ein lecha beyadi pikadon v'tzumat yad v'gezel va'aveida v'lo lecha v'lo lecha
v'lo lecha v'lo lecha mahu? Okay,
so now here's a new case, which is
that we know when you make a
פרט each one is individual, and we know that's true about people,
different people demanding and different objects. But can you once you get
all that working with one case, can you then replicate it with
the others? So for the first guy you said you don't have
גזל ואבידה תשומת יד gezel va'aveida tzumat yad etc., and then you
say the ולא לךs of the other people. Does that carry over
for each one of them the פרטים pratim that you said for
the first guy? חדא מחייב או דילמא כל חדא וחדא מחייב? Chada
mechayev o dilma kol chada v'chada mechayev?
Okay, do you say that only on the first one—I
mean on the other ones where you say ולא לך ולא לך
ולא לך, v'lo lecha v'lo lecha v'lo lecha, in those you only
are חייב chayav for generic because you did not specify פקדון ותשומת
יד pikadon v'tzumat yad, וגזל? So you would be חייב chayav four
for the first one and four more for the next four, total
of eight. Is that what you say because you didn't repeat the
גזל פקדון ותשומת יד gezel pikadon v'tzumat yad or do you say,
top of ל"ח עמוד ב', lamed chet amud beis,
כל חדא וחדא מחייב? kol chada v'chada mechayev? That no, that once
you have the four different ones for the first guy, פקדון ותשומת
יד, then the ולא לך carries those four to each one of
the next guys, and then you would actually have 16 or 20,
excuse me. תא שמע, we have an answer. דתני רב חייא הרי
כאן עשרים חטאות. Detani Rav Chiya harei kan esrim chata'os. So he
says 20. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אי דפריש, Ei
deparish, if it's a case where for each guy you said, you
don't have גזל פקדון תשומת יד אבידה, gezel pikadon tzumat yad aveida,
the next guy, and you don't have גזל פקדון תשומת יד אבידה...
gezel pikadon tzumat yad aveida... if it was that you really spelled
it out, so רבי חייא מניינא אתא לאשמועינן? Rabbi Chiya minyana ata
l'ashmi'einan? What, רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya has to tell us how to
do math? אלא לאו דלא פריש? Ela lav delo parish? The only
reason רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya would be saying that would be combining
the case of the top case of the משנה of different people
and the bottom case of different objects and say, well, if you
bring them all together you get 20 or 15, is to tell
me that you don't even have to be fully specific.
The חידוש chiddush is that even if you just brought them together
in one case and then you continued on with the ולא לךs,
that would just bring those multiple ones to each guy. The Gemara
says: אלא לאו דלא פריש ושמע מינה פרטא הוה. Ela lav delo
parish ushma mina prata hava. And the Gemara feels that yes, the
fact that he bothered to give a number, it wasn't just to
do math, it was to tell us that this would be a
way of carrying over the separate שבועות.
Okay, last case of the
משנה. אנסת ופיתית את בתי. Anasta ufisita es biti. So you raped
or whatever seduced my daughter.
So there's a debate in the משנה. What's the debate in the
משנה?
The חכמים Chachamim say, the חכמים Chachamim say that you're חייב chayav
even though there's קנס knas by אונס ופיתוי, ones v'pittuy, the חמשים
כסף, chamishim kesef, etc. They still say you're חייב chayav because in
that claim is also the demands of נזק, nezek, of פגם, pegam,
of things that are real ממון. mamon. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says you're פטור pattur and he says because you don't pay for
קנס. knas. Okay, but the question is what do you mean, there's
more than just קנס knas here? So let's take a look at
the Gemara. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן מאי טעמא
דרבי שמעון? Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan mai ta'ama
d'Rabbi Shimon? Why is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon just looking at this
as קנס? knas? הואיל ועיקר קנס
הוא
תובע. Ho'il v'ikar knas hu toveia. Because the fundamental thing that you're
focusing on is the fifty כסף. kesef. Maybe that's generally a lot
more than the בושת ופגם. boshes v'pegam. So since that's the primary
thing that you're demanding when you are making this claim and saying
you raped my daughter and you have to pay, your focus is
fundamentally on the fifty, that's seen as the claim and that's seen
as the claim that's being rejected, even though there are other claims
that are coming along as well. Okay.
So the Gemara says: אמר רבא משלו דרבי שמעון למה הדבר דומה?
Amar Rava mashlo d'Rabbi Shimon lema hadavar domeh? What would this be
similar to? לאדם שאמר לחבירו תן לי חטין ושעורין וכוסמין שיש לי
בידך. L'adam she'amar l'chaveiro ten li chitin use'orin u'chusmin sheyesh li beyadecha.
Give me wheat and barley and spelt that you have. אמר לו
שבועה שאין לך בידי חטין. Amar lo shavua she'ein lecha beyadi chitin.
And he just denies the wheat. Okay. ואשתכח, V'ishtakach,
and the wheat is the more expensive one. דחטין הוא דלית ליה.
Dechitin hu d'leis lei. It's true, he didn't own the חטין. chitin.
השעורין וכוסמין אית ליה. Has'orin u'chusmin is lei. But he did owe
the שעורין וכוסמין. s'orin u'chusmin. דפטור. Depattur. So according to רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, okay, do you say that—so wait, forget רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon first, so you're פטור pattur in that case because why? As
the Gemara says now the next line: דכי אשתבע אחטין אקושטא אשתבע.
Dechi ishtaba achitin akushta ishtaba. When he takes the oath
that you don't have חטין, chitin, he's telling the truth. And he
never took the oath about the כוסמין והשעורין. kusmin v'has'orin. So
even though he was implicitly denying it or he didn't address
it— that if the really what it's about is the 50 כסף
kesef *kesef*, then he's taking a שבועה shevua. *shevuah*—now, it's he's lying
though in this case as well, but he's taking a שבועה shevua.
*shevuah* on the thing that you're פטור patur? *patur* on. Now, that
is not a great analogy. So אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*,
אביי *Abaye* said, מי דמי *mi dami*, how can you compare the
cases? התם בחיטין קכפר ליה ובשעורין ובכוסמין לא קכפר ליה *hasam bechitin
kakafar lei bes'orin uvekusmin lo kakafar lei*. In the case you gave,
he rejected the חיטין *chitin*, he didn't deny the שעורין *se'orin* and
the כוסמין *kusmin*. So you're not חייב chayav *chayav* on the שעורין
*se'orin* and the כוסמין *kusmin* because he didn't deny them. Okay? הכא
בכולא מילתא הוא דקכפר ליה *hacha bechula milta hu dekakafar lei*. Here
he's saying "I didn't rape your daughter," he's denying everything. Okay? So
and he's taking a שבועה shevua *shevuah* on it. So הלא דמיא
*halo damya*, if you want to make an analogy, אלא אמר לחבירו
תן לי חיטין שעורין וכוסמין שיש לי בידך *ela omer lachaveiro ten
li chitin se'orin vekusmin sheyesh li beyadecha*. So he says, you know,
give me these three that you have. And he says שבועה shevua.
שאין לך בידי כלום *shevuah she'ein lecha beyadi klum*. And he says
"Nope, you're lying, I don't owe you anything," similar to "you raped
my daughter" and he says "no". ואשתכח דחיטין הוא דלית ליה שעורין
וכוסמין אית ליה *ve'ishtakach dechitin hu deleit lei se'orin vekusmin it lei*.
And in the end it turns out that he really didn't owe
him חיטין *chitin*, but he did owe him שעורין *se'orin* and כוסמין
*kusmin*. That's a good analogy. A, the guy totally lied with the
שבועה shevua. *shevuah*, but you could claim the עיקר *ikar* focus was
on the wheat and that he wasn't lying about. So, okay, so
that's a good analogy and maybe in that case you're פטור patur?
*patur*. So he says no, דמחייב *demichayiv*, but it's transparently obvious that
in that case you're חייב chayav *chayav*. You're taking a שבועה shevua
*shevuah* you don't owe money and you do actually owe the שעורין
*se'orin* and the כוסמין *kusmin* which were part of the טענה ta'ana
*ta'ana*, even though they weren't the עיקר *ikar* part of the טענה
ta'ana *ta'ana*, you're חייב Chayav, *chayav*. You took a שבועה shevua, *shevuah*
falsely against the טענה taina. *ta'ana*. So I still don't get how
רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* makes sense. אלא כי אתא רבין אמר רבי
יוחנן לדיברי רבי שמעון קנס הוא תובע ולא בושת ופגם *ela ki
ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan ledivrei Rabbi Shimon knas hu toveia velo
boshet upgam*. You're right, it's not עיקר קנס *ikar knas* he's תובע
*toveia*. For רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*, when you say "I'm not the
מפתה *mefateh* of your daughter," you're not even asking for the בושת
ופגם *boshet upgam*. I don't know how he knows that, but okay.
But לדיברי חכמים Chachamim אף בושת ופגם הוא תובע *ledivrei chachamim af
boshet upgam hu toveia*. No, obviously when you're saying it, you're asking
for everything. במאי קמיפלגי *bemai kamiflagi*? So what's, how do you explain
that? אמר רב פפא רבי שמעון סבר לא שביק איניש מידי דקייץ
ובתר מידי דלא קייץ *amar Rav Pappa Rabbi Shimon savar lo shevik
inish midi dekayitz uvatia midi dlo kayitz*. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says,
look, 50 קנס *knas* is a well-defined sum. If I'm coming and
demanding from you money, I'm only focused on the 50 קנס *knas*.
It's not the 50 is the עיקר *ikar* plus also the other
stuff. I'm not—the other stuff is a separate court case. I'm not
even thinking about it now. I'm only going to focus on the
thing that is well-defined. ורבנן סברי לא שביק מידי דאי מודי ביה
לא מיפטר ובתר מידי דאי מודי ביה מיפטר *verabbanan savri lo shevik
midi de'ei modi bei lo miftar uvatia midi de'ei modi bei miftar*.
No, a person isn't going to ignore the part of the claim
that, you know, the guy will not be able to get out
of if he admits to, and only focus on the קנס *knas*
and the קנס *knas* he can get out of if he admits
to. So he's never going to not be also demanding the ממון
*mamon* part of it. Okay. הדרן עלך שבועת הפקדון *hadran alach shevuat
hapikadon*. That is the end of שבועת הפקדון *shevuat hapikadon*. And now
let us get go look at the משנה *mishna* for start with
the next פרק perek *perek* with שבועת הדיינים *shevuat hadayanim*. Okay, so
until now we've been dealing with a קרבן *korban* that's in—a שבועה
shevua *shevuah* that's imposed by either a person took on their own,
you know, שבועת ביטוי *shevuat bituy*, or imposed by a party by
a demand, and now we're going to get to a שבועה shevua
*shevuah* that is imposed by the בית דין *beit din*, שבועת הדיינים
*shevuat hadayanim*. So let's take a look. שבועת הדיינים *shevuat hadayanim*. So
a שבועה shevua *shevuah* of that a judge is imposed, which is
the case of, you know, there's one of an עד אחד *ed
echad*, but we're focusing on מודה במקצת modeh be'miktzat. *modeh bemiktzat*. הטענה
שתי כסף kesef,
*hata'ana shtei chesef*. So the claim about how much you owe, right?
Like the basic structure of מודה במקצת modeh be'miktzat, *modeh bemiktzat* is
ראובן *Reuven* says to שמעון *Shimon* "You owe me a hundred dollars"
and שמעון *Shimon* says "I only owe you fifty" and he has
to take a שבועה *shevuah* on the other fifty. So we're going
to discuss how big does the claim have to be, how big
does the denial have to be. So the original claim has to
be, you know, שתי כסף kesef. *shtei chesef*, שתי מעות כסף kesef
*shtei ma'ot kesef*. שתי כסף kesef *shtei chesef*. וההודאה
בשוה פרוטה peruta. *vehahoda'ah bishaveh perutah*. And you—but and—so ראובן *Reuven* says
"You owe me שתי כסף kesef. *shtei chesef*" and as long as,
you know, שמעון *Shimon* concedes a פרוטה peruta *perutah* and he denies
the rest, that's considered a הודאה *hoda'ah*. But any concession of less
than a פרוטה peruta, *perutah* is not a הודאה *hoda'ah*. Now, the
question is how much does he have to deny, right? So we'll
see, that's not as clear. But let's keep on reading. ואם אין
הודאה ממין הטענה mimain hata'ana. פטור patur *ve'im ein hoda'ah mimin hata'ana
patur*. And he has another הלכה *halacha*. You have to admit to
something that was part of the challenge—of the claim, not something external
to the claim. כיצד *keitzad*? How does this play out? שתי כסף
kesef לי בידך *shtei chesef li beyadecha*. He says, ראובן *Reuven* says
to שמעון *Shimon* "You owe me שתי כסף kesef *shtei chesef*". אין
לך בידי אלא פרוטה Ein lecha beyadi ela peruta. *ein lecha beyadi
ela perutah*. "Nope, you know, I only admit to a פרוטה peruta,
*perutah*. I deny the
rest." exempt. Now why are you פטור? Patur,
Okay, why are you פטור? patur That exactly seems to be the
case of our משנה. He demanded two כסף kesef and he admitted
to a פרוטה. peruta So there's two ways of reading this. This
is going to be a debate in the גמרא. Gemara The easy
way to read it is that when the משנה says the טענה
taina. is two כסף, kesef it really means that what is being
denied is at least two כסף. kesef So when the demand is
only two כסף kesef and you're conceding a פרוטה peruta, and therefore
you're denying two כסף kesef minus a פרוטה, peruta you're not denying
enough to be חייב chayav. a מודה במקצת. modeh be'miktzat. So according
to this to be חייב Chayav. a מודה במקצת, modeh be'miktzat, you
actually need to deny a significant amount, two a full two כסף.
kesef. The other version of this is, no, the משנה is what
it sounds like. As long as you admit to a פרוטה, peruta.
you know, then there's no amount that you have to deny. As
long as you admit to a פרוטה peruta or as long as
you deny a פרוטה, peruta. you could admit to a פרוטה peruta
and deny two כסף kesef. minus a פרוטה. peruta You could admit
to two כסף minus a פרוטה peruta and deny one פרוטה. peruta.
Either way you make a מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat As long as
the claim is two כסף and there's a פרוטה peruta. worth of
admission and a פרוטה worth of denial, that is enough to make
a שבועה. Okay, if that's true, why in this case are you
פטור? patur שתי כסף לי בידך אין לך בידי אלא פרוטה פטור.
Shtei kesef li beyadcha ein lecha beyadi ela peruta patur. So according
to this read, the reason you're פטור Patur, is because it's not
ממין הטענה. mimain hata'ana That two כסף does not mean two hundred
dollars and then you admitted to one penny. Two כסף actually means
like two pounds of silver, very strange that now we're shifting what
it means, and then you admit to a פרוטה which is like
copper. So therefore you're not keeping ממין הטענה mimin hatana, because you're
not really talking about cash, you're really talking about precious metals. Alright,
don't worry about that too much now, we'll get to that in
the גמרא. Gemara It's easier to understand the משנה that the reason
you're exempt is because you have to deny a full two כסף
worth. שתי כסף ופרוטה Shtei kesef u'peruta and then it continues, שתי
כסף ופרוטה לי בידך, shtei kesef u'peruta li beyadcha, you owe me
two כסף plus a פרוטה. אין לך בידי Ein lecha beyadi, אלא
פרוטה. No, I only owe you a פרוטה. חייב, chayav you're חייב.
chayav. Why? Because now you denied a full two כסף. So it
reads very simply if the point of the משנה is that you
have to deny a full two כסף. מנה לי בידך, Maneh li
beyadcha, you owe me a hundred dollars. אין לך בידי, Ein lecha
beyadi, I don't owe you anything. פטור, Patur. you're exempt because there's
no מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat. you're כופר הכל. kofer hakol. מנה לי
בידך, Maneh li beyadcha, you owe me a hundred dollars. אין לך
בידי אלא חמישים דינר. Ein lecha beyadi ela chamishim dinar.
No, only fifty. חייב. chayav All right, that's straightforward. מנה לאבא בידך.
Maneh l'abba beyadcha.
So my father gave you a hundred dollars. אין לך בידי אלא
חמישים דינר פטור. Ein lecha beyadi ela chamishim dinar patur.
No, only fifty, you're exempt, מפני שהוא כמשיב אבידה, mipnei shehu k'meishiv
aveidah,
because that is like you are returning a lost object. What does
that mean? It means that since you are not the one who
lent money, right, I could easily just have said, no, I כופר
הכל, kofer hakol, I don't owe you anything. This gets back to
like a general statement that the גמרא deals with, which is, why
if when you deny it all, you're exempt, why when you admit
it are you חייב chayav a שבועה? Why don't you have a
מיגו? migo? I should not have to make a שבועה because if
I were lying, I just would have denied all of it. And
the basic answer that רבא Rava gives in the גמרא is, well,
you can't say I could have just easily denied all of it
because you would never be that brazen to somebody that did this
wonderful thing and lent you this money. Okay, so because you can't,
and therefore you're almost compelled to admit to part of it. So
you can't say I should be פטור Patur. because I could have
denied it all. Ah, but if you're not the guy that lent
me money, if it was your father who lent me money
and you don't have any direct knowledge of it, ah, I would
feel if I wanted to lie, I could just deny it all.
I could just say, you know, that I never borrowed anything. So
in that case, since the person making the טענה taina is not
the person who I am indebted to and who lent me the
money, then if I partly admit, I'm פטור patur. because I could
have just totally denied. מפני שהוא כמשיב אבידה. Mipnei shehu k'meishiv aveidah.
It's like I'm returning to you a lost object, you know, I
could have easily have said I owe you nothing. Okay. מנה לי
בידך, Maneh li beyadcha,
you owe me a hundred dollars. אמר לו הן, Amar lo hen,
yes. למחר אמר לו תנהו לי, Lemachar amar lo tneihu li, give
it to me. נתתיו לך, Netativ lach, I've already given it to
you. פטור, patur. you're
exempt
because even though you admitted you owed the money, that doesn't mean
that you couldn't now between now and tomorrow have paid him back.
אין לך בידי, if you say no, I never borrowed it, חייב.
chayav Now this חייב chayav, is not חייב chayav a שבועה. Now
you're חייב Chayav because you already admitted yesterday you owed the money
and now you're denying it. So you're already bound. by your admission
yesterday. Okay. מנה לי בידך Maneh li beyadcha you owe me one
hundred dollars. אמר לו הן Amar lo hen yes. אל תתנהו לי
אלא בעדים. Al titnehu li ela beedim. So now we're going beyond
the question about מודה במקצת modeh bemiktzat and about circumstances of getting
back the money when there's a claim that you owed me money.
Okay. Don't give it to me except with witnesses. למחר אמר לו
תנהו לי. Lemachar amar lo tnehu li. And then the next day
he says, okay, give it to me. נתתיו לך Natativ lach said
I gave it to you. Now חייב, chayav. in this case you're
חייב Chayav. even though normally you're believed to say I gave it
back to you once you've admitted that you owed the money. You
would be believed afterwards to say you actually paid it up. But
when the demand was made that you could only, I only will
receive payment, I only will accept your payment with witnesses, you're not
believed to say you paid it unless you produced those witnesses. בפני
שצריך ליתנו בעדים. Bifnei shetzarich litno beedim. We made the condition that
you have to produce witnesses. That it has to be witnesses present.
Okay. Back to מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzat? That was a little digression.
ליטרא זהב יש לי בידך. Litra zahav yesh li beyadcha. You have
a pound, I gave you a pound of gold. אין לך בידי
אלא ליטרא כסף. Ein lecha beyadi ela litra kessef. Only a pound
of silver. פטור. Patur. You're exempt. Because here as opposed to before
where it seemed like the issue was how much do you have
to concede to, how much do you have to deny, and we
were talking about cash, here we're talking about precious metals. Okay. And
a pound of silver is not a מודה במקצת to a pound
of gold. It's you're admitting to something that was not being demanded
from you. Okay. It doesn't matter that it's worth a portion of
it. It's a completely different object. דינר זהב יש לי בידך. Dinar
zahav yesh li beyadcha. You have a gold dinar.
אין לך בידי אלא דינר כסף, Ein lecha beyadi ela dinar kessef,
טרסיות, trasiyot, פונדיות, pundaityot, או פרוטה o perutah or other types of
coins. חייב chayav in that case you are חייב. chayav. Why? שהכל
מין מטבע אחת Shehakol min matbeah achat because it's all cash. When
you say a gold dinar, a silver, a silver dinar is מודה
ממין הטענה modeh mimin hatana because what you're really demanding is a
certain amount of money. And a silver dinar is less of an
amount of money. It's not a fundamentally different object. Okay. כור
תבואה לי בידך. Kor tevuah li beyadcha. Somebody says you have a
whatever, a bundle or whatever כור kor is some large volume of
תבואה tevuah I gave to you. אין לך בידי אלא לתך קטנית.
Ein lecha beyadi ela letekh kitnit. No no no only like a
half of a box of legumes. פטור. You're exempt because again it's
not ממין הטענה, mimin hatana. it's a different thing. כור פירות לי
בידך. Kor peirot li beyadcha. אין לך בידי אלא לתך קטנית. Ein
lecha beyadi ela letekh kitnit. חייב. chayav. שקטנית בכלל פירות. Shekitnit bichlal
peirot.
If you say I gave you a box of fruit, of produce,
and he said yeah it's only half a box of legumes, that
is חייב chayav. because that is a type of produce.
פירות Peirot in the Mishnah often means produce, not fruit. Like also
פרי האדמה. pri haadamah. טענו חטין והודה לו בשעורין Tano chittin vehodu
lo bseorim פטור.
So that's what we've been talking about. If I said you owe
me grain and you said wheat and you said no only barley,
you're exempt. רבן גמליאל מחייב. Rabban Gamliel mechayav. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
says you're חייב. So this is sort of like doubling back on
the point of ממין הטענה. mimin hatana. Here we see that רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says you're חייב.
Even though all the cases we gave so far follow the position
that you're פטור. הטוען לחברו בכד שמן והודה לו בקנקנים. Hatone lachavero
bkad shemen vehodu lo bkankanim. אדמון אומר הוא והודה לו מקצת ממין
הטענה ישבה.
Admon omer ho vehodu
lo miktzat mimin hatana yeshvah. וחכמים אומרים אין הודאה ממין הטענה. Vachachamim
omrim ein hodah mimin hatana. Okay.
Somebody says you have
I have a hundred barrels of oil in your house. And you
say
well I do owe you a hundred barrels, but empty barrels, not
barrels of oil. So is that a מודה במקצת? Or when I'm
saying a hundred barrels I'm really totally just focused on the oil
and the barrels aren't really part of the טענה. Okay.
So in that case אדמון Admon says that's a you are admitting,
you're admitting to the barrels, that's part of the טענה. And חכמים
say no, you're really the real טענה is about the oil. אמר
רבן גמליאל רואה אני את דברי אדמון. Amar Rabban Gamliel roeh ani
et divrei Admon. אדמון'ס Admon's position actually makes sense. There is an
acknowledgment of that. Now of course
it's a little funny because רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel does not mean
טענו חטין והודה לו בשעורין. tano chittin vehodu lo bseorim. So for
him it doesn't even have to be ממין הטענה. So anyway the
Gemara will worry about that. Okay. טענו כלים וקרקעות והודה בכלים וכפר
בקרקעות. Tano keilim vekarkaot vehodu bkeilim vekhafar bkarkaot.
So now we're getting to the principle we started today with which
is that you're exempt when it comes to קרקע. karka. So if
somebody said you owe me a chair and a piece of land.
And you admitted to the chair or denied the land. בקרקעות וכפר
בכלים. Bekarkaot vekhafar bkeilim. Or you admitted to the קרקע karka and
you denied the כלים. keilim. פטור. In those cases you're exempt. Because
whether the land is part of what you're admitting and therefore well
certainly if the land is part of what you're denying so you're
swearing on it there's no שבועה. But even if it's part of
what you're admitting there's no שבועה. הודה במקצת על קרקעות פטור. Hodu
bemiktzat alkarkaot patur. Let's say you denied the כלים keilim and you
denied the land half of the land but you
admitted to half. Okay. So in that case you're exempt. Why? Because
because you at least because Because the only admission was made up
of קרקע, karka, and therefore that is not an admission that's מחייב
mechayev you, that obligates you.
במקצת הכלים חייב, bemiktzas hakeilim chayav, but let's flip it. Let's say,
you know, he demanded כלים keilim and קרקע, karka, and you said,
I deny קרקע karka completely, and I deny half of the כלים
keilim and I admit to half of the כלים. keilim. In that
case, you're חייב. Why? Because the admission has כלים, keilim, so the
admission of כלים keilim is check, and the denial, part of the
denial had כלים, keilim, check. So as long as you have an
admission of כלים keilim and a denial of כלים, keilim, זוקק, zokak,
that's enough for a שבועה. Okay? And then you can, you'd be
obligated to make a שבועה on the קרקע karka as well.
שנכסים שאין להם אחריות זוקקין את הנכסים שיש להם אחריות להישבע עליהם.
shenechasim she-ein lahem achrayus zokkin es hanechasim sheyesh lahem achrayus lehishava aleihem.
So as long as כלים keilim was part of the admission and
כלים keilim was part of the denial, now you would have to
make a שבועה. But if part, but if the admission was wholly
made up of קרקע karka or if the denial was wholly made
up of קרקע, karka, there can be no שבועה. אין נשבעין
על טענת חרש שוטה וקטן. ein nishvaim al tanas cheresh shoteh vekatan.
You do not take a שבועה if the person demanding it is
a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh vekatan. Has to be an adult
and a בר דעת. bar daas. ואין משביעין את הקטן, ve-ein mashbiin
es hakatan, and you cannot make a, force a קטן katan to
make a שבועה, אבל נשבעין לקטן ולהקדש, aval nishvaim lekatan ulehekdesh, but
you will take a שבועה to a קטן katan and to הקדש.
hekdesh. That's not so clear what it means. It sounded like before
you don't take a שבועה to קטן, katan, here it's saying you
do take a שבועה to קטן. katan. The גמרא will describe. So
that was all the משניות mishnayos of the פרק we just read,
and now we're going to start to unpack it bit by bit.
We'll pick up here tomorrow.