גוטער וואך, Gutter vokh, today's דף daf is כט, Chaf Tes, and
we pick up at the bottom of כח עמוד ב, Chaf Ches
Amud Bais, and we have now done a transition from סוטה Sotah
to תרומה, Terumah, which somewhat
interestingly is going to be the focus of today's דף, daf, not
so much because of the link of סוטה Sotah to תרומה Terumah
but because our משנה mishna of this פרק perek had a whole
series of דרשות drashos of בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא, Bo Bayom
Darash Rabbi Akiva, and some the initial ones had to do with
טומאה, tumah, so we will see about that. But anyway, the initial
connection had been that סוטה Sotah we learned out from it the
principle of if she goes into seclusion, ייחוד, yichud, she is presumed
to be טמאה. tmeia. The הלכה halacha is that a סוטה Sotah
is ודאי אסור vadai assur based on the ספק, safek, and the
תוספות Tosafos points out that means until that gets clarified with the
water once it's gone through the formal procedure. And the תוספות Tosafos
points out that means even if it retroactively turns out that she
had not committed adultery or she knows she hasn't committed adultery, if
she nevertheless violates that status of טומאה, tumah, like she sleeps with
her husband, they transgress because right now her status is definitely אסור
assur based on the ספק, safek, it's not just ספק אסור. safek
assur. So from that we learned out the principle of ספק טומאה
ברשות היחיד. safek tumah bereshut hayachid. Again, this interesting now transition from
the phrase טומאה tumah by סוטה, Sotah, which has its own specific
set of meanings to the idea of טומאה tumah in other places
in the תורה. Torah. And the idea also that the parameters are
now just the very much the formal aspects of a רשות היחיד,
reshut hayachid, יש בו דעת לישאל, yesh bo da'at lisha'el, etc. So
תוספות'ס Tosafos's first point, by the way, just to round out what
we said yesterday was he says I don't understand the reason she's
אסור assur by the סוטה Sotah is because there's רגלים לדבר raglayim
ladavar and in case of a טומאה tumah it's like a fifty-fifty
doubt, where's the רגלים לדבר? raglayim ladavar? And תוספות Tosafos introduced an
important idea that actually the קינוי kinuy and סתירה stira just make
it fifty-fifty, don't make it more likely than not, but without the
קינוי kinuy and סתירה stira it wouldn't even really be considered a
ספק. safek. So that's an important way about thinking about סוטה, Sotah,
which we have not really focused on until now.
Although the תורה Torah she really presented as a fait
accompli, well no, the תורה Torah presents it that the husband is
jealous, so the משנה mishna more presents it like a fait accompli.
Alright, that's his jealousy, I don't think
you could say from the תורה'ס Torah's perspective the משנה mishna presents
it like she's definitely guilty. Anyway, and then we had a brief
discussion, we did not go into the תוספות, Tosafos, that רשות היחיד
reshut hayachid clearly also doesn't really mean רשות היחיד reshut hayachid like
it does by שבת, Shabbos, it has more to do with a
private location. And the other interesting הלכה halacha is ספק טומאה ברשות
היחיד safek tumah bereshut hayachid and the other point the גמרא Gemara
made is only if there is somebody there that's יש בו דעת
לישאל, yesh bo da'at lisha'el, it's not just like you don't know
if a frog hopped on a loaf of bread and nobody else
was around, that would be אין בו דעת לישאל. ein bo da'at
lisha'el. It has to be or there's an infant, there has to
be case like a סוטה, Sotah, that there's somebody there who in
theory could ask about what the circumstances were. And as I explained
my theory about that was that one way of understanding why it's
ודאי טמא vadai tme because of the ספק safek is that making
things ודאי טמא vadai tme until it's clarified, okay it's a little
unfair for the woman, or a lot unfair for the woman, this
presumption of guilt, but anyway, but that sort of forces maybe people
with information, hopefully can force things to clarify
themselves, people to come forward, people to remember, so that only it's
helpful if there is somebody there that might actually know something. So
it's only ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah bereshut hayachid when there's
יש בו דעת לישאל. yesh bo da'at lisha'el. Okay, so that's where
we left off in the גמרא. Gemara. So now let's go, I
guess we can re-read that from four lines from the top and
then we'll transition to the new topic. ומכאן אמרו, u-mikan amru, from
four lines from the top on כח עמוד ב, Chaf Ches Amud
Bais, מכאן אמרו, mikan amru, from here they said, דבר שיש בו
דעת לישאל ברשות היחיד, davar she-yesh bo da'at lisha'el bereshut hayachid, if
there was somebody present who could be asked about it, doesn't mean
he knew or she knew whatever but in theory could be asked,
and it's in a private domain, ספיקו טמא, sfeiko tme, and if
there's a doubt if טומאה tumah touched something it's טמא, tme, וברשות
הרבים ספיקו טהור, u-v'reshut harabbim sfeiko tahor, if it's in a public
domain its ספק safek is טהור, tahor, ושאין בו דעת לישאל, v'she-ein
bo da'at lisha'el, and if nobody is there who can be asked,
בין ברשות היחיד בין ברשות הרבים ספיקו טהור, bein bereshut hayachid bein
bereshut harabbim sfeiko tahor, either way we assume it is טהור, tahor,
so you need the combination of factors יש בו דעת לישאל yesh
bo da'at lisha'el and רשות היחיד reshut hayachid to say ספיקו טמא.
sfeiko tme. Okay, so that was the end of yesterday. Now the
גמרא, Gemara, if you remember also, had we learned out three things
from נטמאה, nitm'ah, אסור לבעל אסור לבועל, assur l'ba'al assur l'bo'el, and
she cannot eat תרומה, terumah, which means if she's married to a
כהן kohen she can't eat תרומה terumah because the adultery or the
suspected adultery compromises her marriage. But ב, b, even if she's not
married to a כהן, kohen, she's a בת כהן, bas kohen, she
can't eat תרומה terumah because this act would also seem to invalidate
her. And from that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael responded to רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and said oh so I'll learn a קל וחומר kal
vachomer therefore that she also is forbidden to marry a כהן, kohen,
because there are women who are forbidden to marry a כהן kohen
who can eat תרומה. terumah. So if this woman who cannot eat
תרומה, terumah, then how much more so should she be forbidden to
marry a כהן, kohen, meaning assuming that her husband right now dies
and she's an אלמנה, almanah, nevertheless the fact that she has committed
adultery makes her forbidden not just לבעל ולבועל l'ba'al u-l'bo'el or suspected
of committing adultery, also makes her אסור לכהן. assur l'kohen.
Who can eat תרומה terumah and not marry a כהן?
kohen? גרושה גרושה, grusha grusha, who is a daughter of a כהן.
kohen. Okay.
So no one would suggest this
would
make her a זונה zonah which For רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Ishmael, אמר
רבי עקיבא. Amar Rabbi Akiva. So now as far as רבי ישמעאל's
Rabbi Ishmael concerned, אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, תרומה ומהדרי אי
וכהונה, Trumah umhadrei ee u-kehunah, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, oh, she's
אסור assur in תרומה. Trumah. And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says, oh
well, why don't you just learn עקיבא, Akiva, I'll make a קל
וחומר kal vachomer that she's אסור assur in כהונה. kehunah. So who
says that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva didn't—I mean, it sounds like he
was arguing with רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but who said רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva was arguing? Really, he's just adding to what רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva said. So the גמרא Gemara says, ותו, v'su, and in
addition, let's say רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, you know, if רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva doesn't have רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Ishmael קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, כהונה מנליה? kehunah minalei? Where
does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva know this idea of כהונה kehunah from?
Okay, does he agree with רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that you learn
it from a קל וחומר? kal vachomer? וכי תימא כהונה לא צריכא
קרא, V'chi teima kehunah lo tzericha kra, maybe he feels I don't
need a פסוק pasuk for כהונה. kehunah. Why don't I need a
פסוק pasuk to tell me that she's אסור assur for a כהן?
Kohen? דף כ"ט עמוד
א'. Daf kaph tet amud aleph. שרי, Sharei, here you go, what
Michael said. אסור בה ספק זונה כזונה. Assur bah safek zonah k'zonah.
Since she's presumed a סוטה sotah is presumed to have committed adultery
until we clarify it, that's אסור ספק כודאי. assur safek k'vada'i. So
maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva just assumes a woman who commits adultery,
it's not just אסור לבעל ואסור לבועל, assur l'ba'al v'assur l'bo'el, that
would give her status of a זונה. zonah. And if that would
give her status of a זונה zonah and she now is a
ספק safek having done it, so the הלכה halachah of ספק כודאי,
safek k'vada'i, we would treat her like a זונה, zonah, so from
there you could figure out that she's אסורה לכהונה, assurah l'kehunah, so
we don't need a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so if that's true, so
תרומה נמי לא צריכא קרא? Trumah nami lo tzirchei kra? Then why
does he need a פסוק pasuk to tell me that she's אסור
בתרומה? assur b'Trumah? שרי אסור בה ספק זונה כזונה. Sharei assur bah
safek zonah k'zonah. Presumably the status of זונה zonah would equally defile
her from eating תרומה. Trumah. How do you know? Because the פסוק
pasuk says, ובת כהן כי תהיה לאיש זר היא בתרומת הקדשים לא
תאכל. U'bat Kohen ki tihyeh l'ish zar, hi b'trumat hakodashim lo tochel.
Now, that literally means that she's married to another man and therefore
she's no longer part of the כהן's Kohen household. However, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva could דרשן darshen it, and he does דרשן darshen it,
I don't want to explain why now based on other סוגיות, sugyas,
that כי תהיה ki tihyeh means if she has sex with another
man, and איש זר, ish zar, a man that she is forbidden
to have sex with, not just a non-כהן. Kohen. And therefore that
would defile her from תרומה. Trumah. So once you would say that
we don't need a פסוק pasuk because of course a woman who
commits adultery would be a זונה zonah and that would be אסור
בכהונה, assur b'kehunah, so okay, so make her also אסור בתרומה. assur
b'Trumah. Why do you need a פסוק pasuk of ונטמאה v'nitma'ah to
tell you that? So basically why does he need a פסוק pasuk
to tell me she's אסור בתרומה assur b'Trumah and not כהונה? kehunah?
Where does he learn כהונה kehunah from? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא, Ela, fine.
לרבי עקיבא ארבעה קראי כתיבי. L'Rabbi Akiva arba'ei krai ktiva. There are
four פסוקים. psukim. Now what are the four פסוקים? psukim? It says
ונטמאה v'nitma'ah three times, but one of the three times it says
ונטמאה. v'nitma'ah. Okay, once it says היא נטמאה, hi nitma'ah, היא נכבשה,
hi nichbeshah, you know, I forget the exact פסוקים. psukim. Anyway, one
of them says ונטמאה, v'nitma'ah, the עד אין בה. ed ein bah.
So
remember רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns from the extra ו's. vavs. So
you have three ונטמאה's v'nitma'ah plus one ו, vav, that's four things
that you can learn out. ארבעה קראי כתיבי. arba'ei krai ktiva. חד
לבעל, Chad l'ba'al, one that she's forbidden to the בעל. ba'al. חד
לבועל, Chad l'bo'el, one to the בועל. bo'el. וחד לכהונה, V'chad l'kehunah,
one that maybe the idea that she is presumed to have committed
adultery or she has committed adultery would not be enough in itself
that we wouldn't have known on our own that that would label
her זונה. zonah. So the פסוק pasuk tells me that no, that
if she has committed adultery or she's a סוטה, sotah, so she's
presumed to have done it, therefore she's אסורה assurah to a כהן.
Kohen. וחד לתרומה, V'chad l'Trumah, and she's אסורה assurah to תרומה, Trumah,
even if she's like a בת כהן bat Kohen or whatever, she's
אסורה assurah for תרומה. Trumah. So you have four פסוקים, psukim, three
ונטמאה's v'nitma'ah and one ו. vav. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael and the
other? Yeah, so for whatever reason, it doesn't spell out why you
couldn't have learned one from—well, we'll get to it a little bit,
but it certainly doesn't spell out like why we couldn't just have
assumed she's a זונה. zonah. לרבי ישמעאל תלת קראי כתיבי. L'Rabbi Ishmael
tlat krai ktiva. It says three times, because he doesn't learn the
ו. vav. So he only has three ונטמאה's. v'nitma'ah חד לבעל וחד
לבועל וחד לתרומה. Chad l'ba'al v'chad l'bo'el v'chad l'Trumah. So the third
one is telling you תרומה. Trumah. But that's why רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Ishmael needs a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So we've answered all our
questions. That רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva presumably learns out כהונה kehunah from
the ו vav and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael is basically saying back,
I don't need your ו, vav, I'll learn it out from a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, so what's
his—וחד לכהונה אתא בקל וחומר. v'chad l'kehunah ata b'kal vachomer. And the
קל וחומר kal vachomer is: if some women who can't marry כהנים,
Kohanim, a גרושה gerushah who's a
בת כהן, bat Kohen, can still eat תרומה, Trumah, a woman who
can't eat תרומה, Trumah, that I learn out from the third ונטמאה,
v'nitma'ah, certainly she should not be able to marry a כהן. Kohen.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: לרבי ישמעאל, L'Rabbi Ishmael,
now according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that learns תרומה Trumah and
then makes a קל וחומר kal vachomer from תרומה Trumah to כהונה,
kehunah, מאי דאצטריך קרא לתרומה וכהונה אתא בקל וחומר? mmai d'itzrecha kra
l'Trumah v'kehunah ata b'kal vachomer?
How do you know that the פסוק pasuk tells you תרומה Trumah
and once it tells you תרומה, Trumah, now we can make a
קל וחומר—if kal vachomer she can't eat תרומה, Trumah, how much more
so could she not marry a כהן? Kohen? דילמא, Dilma, why don't
I sort of go the—say the opposite? דאצטריך לכהונה. K'itzrecha l'kehunah.
Maybe the פסוק, pasuk, the third ונטמאה, v'nitma'ah, is telling me she's
אסורה לכהן assurah lekohen if she committed adultery or she's a סוטה
sotah and then the husband dies. And if all I know is
that she's אסורה assurah to a כהן, Kohen, תרומה שריא, Trumah sharya,
תרומה Trumah would be permitted. Because I've already established there are women
who are אסור assur to marry a כהן Kohen who can—who still
can eat תרומה. Trumah. Who is that? A גרושה בת כהן, gerushah
bat Kohen, right? A גרושה בת כהן gerushah bat Kohen can't marry
a כהן Kohen but can eat תרומה. Trumah. So maybe the third...
מיעוט mi'at tells me she's אסור assur to a כהן, Kohen, but
I would not be maybe because she still would be she's a
בת כהן Bas Kohen entitled to eat תרומה. Terumah. Okay, which by
the way makes sense because if you just read the פסוקים, pesukim,
right? I mean, it's sort of what we're saying. The פסוקים pesukim
make it clear that there are a lot of women a כהן
Kohen can't marry: אשה חללה זונה גרושה, isha challalah zonah gerushah, etc.
All these women are אסור assur to marry a כהן, Kohen, but
it's not so clear what type of a בת כהן Bas Kohen
can't eat תרומה. Terumah. The פסוקים pesukim it's only a בת כהן
Bas Kohen who marries a- who marries out, who marries a ישראל.
Yisrael. There's no sense that if a בת כהן Bas Kohen did
some forbidden act of sex that that would invalidate her from eating
תרומה. Terumah. Right? So saying the same thing: maybe this woman who
commits adultery or is a סוטה, Sotah, maybe she's אסור לכהן assur
le-Kohen because we know a lot of women are אסור לכהן, assur
le-Kohen, but we don't know necessarily that she's אסור בתרומה. assur be-Terumah.
Okay, so how does- how does he say the פסוק pasuk teach
me תרומה Terumah and I make a קל וחומר kal va-chomer כהן?
Kohen? Maybe it should say אסור לכהן assur le-Kohen and maybe she
should be permitted to eat תרומה Terumah if she's a בת כהן.
Bas Kohen. Okay? דתרומה שריא. de-Terumah sharya. So אמר לך amar lach
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael will say to you, מסתברא דומיא דבעל ובועל.
mistavera dumya de-ba'al u-vo'el. No, I have the third נטמאה, nitme'ah, I
want to make it it's- it's sort of similar to the נטמאהs
nitme'ah of the בעל ba'al and the בועל. bo'el. In what way
is it similar? מה בעל ובועל מחיים אף תרומה נמי מחיים. mah
ba'al u-vo'el m'chayim af Terumah nami m'chayim.
The בעל ba'al and בועל bo'el is that she's forbidden now to
the husband and the suspected adulterer even like while everybody is still
alive. If you say she's אסור בתרומה, assur be-Terumah, that would also
be now that everybody's alive. She's a בת כהן, Bas Kohen, she
remains אסור- assur she's now becomes אסור בתרומה. assur be-Terumah If you
said that the relevance is she can't marry a כהן, Kohen, what's
the only scenario where I would have a הוה אמינא hava amina
she can marry a כהן? Kohen? She's married to this guy, she
commits adultery. What's- how's- what's the only case where she could now
marry another guy who's a כהן Kohen if what happens to her
husband? He dies. No, no. How does she become free now to
marry a כהן? Kohen? The husband has to die. He can't divorce
her because then she's a גרושה. gerushah. So the only scenario that
I need to discuss if she can marry a כהן Kohen is
if her current husband dies. Okay? So he said, I don't want
to assume the third נטמאה nitme'ah is talking only in a scenario
where her current husband dies. I want to assume the third נטמאה
nitme'ah is immediately relevant. Okay? And the case of the immediately relevant
like בעל ובועל ba'al u-vo'el would be תרומה. Terumah. The relevance of
אסור לכהונה assur le-kehunah would only be if the current husband dies.
So מה בעל ובועל מחיים אף תרומה מחיים אפוקי כהונה דאחר מיתה.
mah ba'al u-vo'el m'chayim af Terumah m'chayim apukei kehunah de-achar misah.
So once the third נטמאה nitme'ah tells me she's אסור בתרומה assur
be-Terumah, because that's what is immediately relevant, now I can make a
קל וחומר kal va-chomer they, oh, she's אסור בתרומה, assur be-Terumah. then
she's definitely going to be אסור לכהן. assur le-Kohen. Okay? So רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael gets the four by saying בעל, בועל ba'al, bo'el
and תרומה. Terumah. תרומה Terumah I know because it's immediately relevant and
then you use the קל וחומר kal va-chomer to get you כהן.
Kohen. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, I don't need your קל וחומר,
kal va-chomer, I have an extra ו vav and that tells me
תרומה Terumah and כהן. Kohen.
Okay, so a woman is married to a כהן, Kohen, she commits
adultery, she can't become a גרושה, gerushah, like- I didn't- She
can become a גרושה, gerushah, but you don't need a פסוק pasuk
to tell me she's אסור- assur the fact- why do I need
a פסוק pasuk to tell me a woman who committed adultery is
אסור assur to a כהן? Kohen? Of course she's אסור assur to
a כהן, Kohen, she's married. So what would be the scenario where
I would need it to tell me she's אסור assur to a
כהן? Kohen? Not if she got divorced from her husband, then also
of course she's אסור to a כהן, Kohen, she's a גרושה. gerushah.
The only relevance of the הלכה halacha that a woman who commits
adultery becomes אסור to a כהן Kohen is if her current husband
dies.
Divorcee? Divorcee. So let me- I'm just while all this is going
on while she's in the status of having to drink the water,
husband still has to support her, right? Yes. But he can't give
her תרומה. Terumah.
Right, correct.
Yeah, that's a good point.
You're right. Actually, we haven't spoken about that. That's an excellent point
about the financial implications of her status of being a סוטה. Sotah.
One would imagine, yeah, you're right. I mean, it's true they're not
having sex and you have to be מברר mevarer it. But, yeah,
there's been no indication that it impacts his financial- as long as
ongoing financial obligations. Yeah, you're right, but she would be אסור בתרומה.
asur bitruma. It's a good point. Yeah.
Okay. So רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, now רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, okay,
we have the question about why does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva not
like the קל וחומר kal va-chomer of רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael? It's
a good קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. So why does he need the
extra ו? vav? Why doesn't he say like רבי ישמעאל? Rabbi Yishmael?
Alright, why doesn't he say- we'll see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Why didn't he say you get three נטמאהs, nitme'ah the third one
is talking about תרומה Terumah because that's מחיים, m'chayim, and then the
קל וחומר kal va-chomer will apply it to even the איסור כהונה?
issur kehunah? So the גמרא Gemara says, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would tell you דומיא דבעל ובועל לית ליה. dumya
de-ba'al u-vo'el leis lei. No, I don't buy this idea that the
third נטמאה nitme'ah has to be like the בעל ובועל ba'al u-vo'el
and has to be immediately relevant. I'll say let me say the
third נטמאה nitme'ah is the lesser חידוש. chiddush. The lesser חידוש chiddush
is אסור לכהונה assur le-kehunah and I wouldn't have known תרומה. Terumah.
So therefore I needed the ו. vav. I don't have a קל
וחומר. kal va-chomer. I'm not going to jump by saying the third
נטמאה nitme'ah is תרומה. Terumah. I'll say the third נטמאה nitme'ah is
איסור כהונה. issur kehunah. Okay. So דומיא דבעל ובועל לית ליה. dumya
de-ba'al u-vo'el leis lei. He doesn't allow the idea of the בעל
ובועל ba'al u-vo'el comparison to say we can assume it's applying to
תרומה. Terumah. ואינמי איתא v'inami isah or even if I said, you
know, you're right, if I only had three נטמאה. nitme'ah. or even
if I said you're right if I only had three נטמאהs Nitzmaah
I would have said איסור תרומה Isur T'rumah because that's immediately relevant
and I could have had a קל וחומר kal v'chomer that would
have told me אסור לכהונה. asur l'kehunah. But nevertheless I'm going to
use my ו vav to tell it to me anyway. מילתא דאתי
בקל וחומר טרח וכתב לה קרא. milsa d'asi b'kal v'chomer tarach v'kasav
lah kra. Something I could have learned from a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer nevertheless the תורה Torah wants to tell it to me explicitly.
Okay so in the end of the day I'm going to learn
it from the וs vav and whatever and I'm not going to
fundamentally say it's three plus a קל וחומר kal v'chomer I'm going
to say it's four indications in the פסוקים. psukim.
But that's a huge assumption isn't it? Yeah like I could learn
it from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer so I'm not bothered by
the fact that the פסוק pasuk also is telling me that. And
if you don't have a פסוק pasuk you might rely on but
if you have a פסוק pasuk? then the קל וחומר kal v'chomer
should invalidate the קל וחומר kal v'chomer if you have a פסוק?
pasuk No no they're both saying the same thing they're not conflicting.
He's saying it's not a problem for me that the פסוק pasuk?
is superfluous. Well look in a way it's a nice counterpart to
you know the statement in the גמרא Gemara that says something like
you know למה לי קרא סברא הוא. lama li kra sevara hu.
In the way the גמרא Gemara is very
shocking you know radical in its assumption about like you know this
is the whole idea of תורה שבעל פה Torah she'baal peh but
in the assumption about how much our sort of own intellectual or
rational you know sort of understanding is of equal weight to that
of what's
you know what the מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha or what the פסוקים
psukim are telling us. The fact that the גמרא Gemara can say
למה לי קרא סברא הוא lama li kra sevara hu why bother
with a פסוק? pasuk. I could just figure it out on my
own. Actually that's interesting it's going to factor into what we're about
to learn in a minute you know sort of says like okay
so the human סברא sevara has equal weight to something explicit in
the פסוק. pasuk Actually there's some גמרות Gemorot that are even more
radical and say you know שביק לקרא דדחיק ואוקי אנפשיה. shavik l'kra
d'dachik v'oki anafshay. Like he forgets you know like put the פסוק
pasuk aside it's a difficult פסוק pasuk he's going to just explain
it based on the way that makes sense. So it basically says
that if I've got a way of reading it that I think
makes sense I'm going to bracket certain difficult פסוקים psukim or interpret
them in a less than פשט pshat way because I'm going to
be dictated by what logically makes sense. So it really shows right
the power of reason and that role of תורה שבעל פה. Torah
she'baal peh. That being said it's not you know so that's like
the strength of that. That being said it's not like you take
a position like you know and therefore that's so powerful that
the פסוק pasuk would be out of place to say something that
I could learn out from my own סברא. sevara. You know? No
it's not so bad to have your own idea
reaffirmed by an explicit statement in the תורה. Torah. So that's the
flip side of it you know מילתא דאתי בקל וחומר טרח וכתב
לה קרא. milsa d'asi b'kal v'chomer tarach v'kasav lah kra. Yeah the
פסוק pasuk didn't have to say it it would have been just
as good to learn it from סברא sevara or you know but
nevertheless it's you don't have to say that it's a problem that
the פסוק pasuk also said it. Okay?
It's convenient or you know to learn something extra or well that's
just the way it is.
Just saying now that's an interesting point when you frame what your
סברא sevara is what your position is are you saying I learn
it from three פסוקים psukim plus a קל וחומר kal v'chomer and
parenthetically it is through the פסוק pasuk also indicates it but my
basic point is my קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? Or you saying no
my basic point
is the extra ו? vav? Right which is what the גמרא Gemara
seems to have framed it you know why did you need the
extra ו? vav? Why do you need that? Couldn't you have learned
from a קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? Yeah but I could have learned
it from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer but in the end the
פסוק pasuk. didn't demand that of me it gave me an extra
ו. vav. I don't know anyway it's basically a statement of equivalency
here okay? So now the גמרא Gemara moves on. Okay אמר רב
גידל אמר רב amar Rav Gidal amar Rav דבר שיש בו דעת
לישאל davar she'yesh bo da'at l'isha'el doubling back to what we did
at the end of yesterday and I repeated the beginning of today.
Something the idea that if there's two in a place of רשות
היחיד reshus hayachid
it still needs to be somebody who can be asked about it
to say ספק טמא safek tamei and if there's nobody who can
be asked about it it's ספק טהור. safek tahor.
That is not learned only really from the סוטה Sotah category. That's
learned somewhere else. The relevance of דבר שיש בו דעת לישאל davar
she'yesh bo da'at l'isha'el okay ואין בו דעת לישאל v'ein bo da'at
l'isha'el or the relevance of whether somebody is around who could be
asked or not מהאי קרא נפקא. me'hai kra nafka. We don't really
learn it from סוטה Sotah we really learn it from the following
פסוק. pasuk והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא לא יאכל. v'habasar asher yiga
b'chol tamei lo ye'achel. Okay and flesh of a קרבן korban that
touches something טמא tamei shall not be eaten. So וודאי טמא הוא
דלא יאכל. vadai tamei hu d'lo ye'achel. If you know it's הבשר
אשר יגע habasar asher yiga you're definite that it touched something טמא
tamei then don't eat
it. הספק טמא ספק טהור hasafek tamei safek tahor יאכל. ye'achel. It
can be
eaten.
יאכל ye'achel according to... יאכל ye'achel according
to... what is it?
יאכל. ye'achel. That's what I said. Okay okay. הספק טהור לא יאכל.
hasafek tahor lo ye'achel. Okay אלא לאו שמע מינה. ela lav shma
mina. Okay so that פסוק pasuk. says that you have to definitely
know it's טמא. tamei. ספק טהור. safek tahor. אימא סיפא. eima seifa.
Look at the end of the פסוק. pasuk והבשר v'habasar as far
as meat of a קרבן korban is concerned כל טהור יאכל בשר.
kol tahor yochal basar. If you're טהור tahor you can eat it.
So וודאי טהור הוא דיאכל בשר. vadai tahor hu d'yochal basar. Only
if you know you're טהור tahor you can eat it. הספק טמא
וספק טהור hasafek tamei v'safek tahor if you don't know if it's
a doubt לא יאכל. lo yochal. So what is it? The beginning
of the פסוק pasuk says it's only a problem if you know
it's
Wait,
one is the meat and the other is the person.
I understand, so you could have made that difference, but that's not
what he's saying. Right? Maybe you could have said if there's a
doubt about the meat, it's ספק טמא, safek tamei, if it's a
doubt about the, it's ספק טהור, safek tahor, if it's a doubt
about the person, ספק טמא. safek tamei. You could have said that,
because a person could always go to a מקוה. mikvah. Okay, but
that's not what he's saying. But it's a good point. אבל לאו
שמע מינה, Aval lav shma mina, here's what he's saying. כאן שיש
בו דעת לשאול, Kan sheyesh bo da'at lish'ol, כאן שאין בו דעת
לשאול. kan she'ein bo da'at lish'ol. In a way it's a difference
of the person, but not whether the person is טמא tamei but
whether there's a person on the scene. So if all you have
is הבשר, habasar, you just have the meat and nothing else and
you don't know if something טמא tamei touched the meat and there's,
you know, but so you just have the object of the meat
that's present on the scene, then ספק טהור. safek tahor. It's not
a problem unless it's definitely טמא tamei if there's a doubt it's
טהור, tahor, that's אין בו דעת לשאול. ein bo da'at lish'ol. If
it's והבשר כל טהור יאכל בשר, vehabasar col tahor yochal basar,
you're on the scene, a person is on the scene, then if
there's a doubt you have to assume it's טמא, tamei, you have
to know for certain that it's טהור. tahor. Okay so if all
you have is the meat on the scene, אין בו דעת לשאול,
ein bo da'at lish'ol, ספק טהור. safek tahor. If you have a
person on the scene, כל טהור, col tahor, then you have to,
ספק טמא, safek tamei, you have to know that you're definitely, what?
Doesn't it say יש בו דעת? yesh bo da'at?
Well, we would have to add the רשות היחיד reshuto hayachid part
from סוטה, Sotah, which is what the גמרא Gemara is about to
say. Okay, so this is where we learn this, but we don't
learn this from סוטה.
Sotah. Can I ask this question? But when it says כאן שיש
בו דעת, kan sheyesh bo da'at, what's it mean? The piece of
meat? You can't ask, you can't ask a קרבן. korban.
No, בו bo in the scene I guess, or something. In the,
the circumstances.
That's not very concrete.
No, the circumstances, the circumstances I believe is יש בו. yesh bo.
Okay, so,
yeah, or whatever, the people or objects that are involved or the
circumstances. Okay. ואיצטריך דרב גידל אמר רב, Ve'itztrach d'Rav Giddel amar Rav,
איצטריך למגמר מסוטה. itztrach lemigmar miSotah. And now the גמרא Gemara is
saying actually we need both דרשות. drashos. We need the והבשר vehabasar
דרשה drasha and we need the סוטה Sotah model. Okay, דאי מדרב
הוי אמינא de'ee mid'Rav havay amina בין ברשות היחיד בין ברשות הרבים.
bein birshut hayachid bein birshut harabim. Like my girlfriend, if you just
had this about the meat, you would have said private and public
domain doesn't matter, it's just יש בו yesh bo or
אין בו. ein bo. Okay, so איצטריך למגמר מסוטה. itztrach lemigmar miSotah.
So סוטה Sotah tells you no, it's only like when they go
into private is it a
ספק טמא. safek tamei. ואי מסוטה הוי אמינא ve'ee miSotah havay amina
עד דאיכא דעת נוגע ומגיע. ad d'ika da'at nogeya umagiya. Ah, by
סוטה Sotah there are two people who know what's going on, right?
The man and the woman. So therefore transferring it to a טומאה
tumah case, both you would, it would only apply if the toucher
and the touchee had דעת. da'at. So when it's applied to a
rodent and objects, it would only apply to a טמא tamei person
touched a טהור tahor person and maybe that would be only time
we would say ספק טמא, safek tamei, that would be most similar
to סוטה. Sotah. So צריכא, tzricha, so therefore this is teaching you
no, it doesn't require both parties to know, it just requires somebody
there to know what's going on.
More like, this is more like an electronics thing. Like let's say
you had like a video camera, you can't ask the rodent, it's
just recording.
Yeah, I don't think so. I think it's very formalistic these הלכות
halachos of ספק טומאה. safek tumah. Okay, now we go back to
the משנה, Mishnah, and interestingly, we're going to stay on the טומאה
tumah discussion, not because of סוטה Sotah but because of the בו
ביום דרש רבי עקיבא, bo bayom darash Rabbi Akiva, right? We had
a series of things רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva sort of exfoliated. So
the, and the case in the משנה, Mishnah, the first case was
this idea about how do we know that, what do you call
it? That food can make, no, that you can turn something, that
food can become טמא tamei of the third degree derivation, a שלישי.
shelishi. So just to remind you, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns from
the פסוק pasuk. כלי חרס kli cheres that says וכל אשר יפול
מהם אל תוכו יטמא. vechol asher yipol mehem el tocho yitma. כלי
חרס אשר יפול מהם אל תוכו כל אשר בתוכו יטמא. Kli cheres
asher yipol mehem el tocho, kol asher betocho yitma.
What is it? Let's say the whole פסוק. pasuk.
It's quoted in משנה, Mishnah, כלי חרס אשר יפול מהם אל תוכו
כל אשר בתוכו
יטמא.
kli cheres asher yipol mehem el tocho, kol asher
betocho yitma.
כל אשר בתוכו יטמא. Kol asher betocho yitma. So basically כלי חרס
kli cheres is a ראשון, rishon, there's a שרץ sheretz in a
כלי חרס, kli cheres, so it made it into a ראשון, rishon,
שרץ sheretz is an אב. av. Anything in the כלי חרס kli
cheres is a שני, sheni, okay? Because it always goes down one
degree. And it says anything in a כלי חרס kli cheres will
be יטמא, yitma, shall become טמא, tamei, which means okay, a שני.
sheni. But רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva דרשה drasha is יטמא, yitamei, will
have the ability to make a yet another thing טמא tamei to
turn it into a שלישי. shelishi. To which the גמרא, Gemara, who
was it that responded? מי גלה עפר מעיניך? Mi gala afar me'eynecha?
Was it like nice line. אמר רבי יהושע.
Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua.
אמר רבי יהושע מי גלה עפר מעיניך רבן יוחנן בן זכאי? Amar
Rabbi Yehoshua, mi gala afar me'eynecha Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai? רבן יוחנן
בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, who would take the dust out
of your eyes? Presumably he was dead, so you know, wake you
up out of the grave and shake the dust out of your
eyes, because you said we only know the idea of a שלישי
בתרומה shelishi bitrumah from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, and the later generation, was questioned here, by the way,
tying back to our previous discussion about קל וחומר kal vachomer versus
פסוק. pasuk. Since we only know it from a קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, a later generation might question the idea of a שלישי בתרומה
shelishi bitrumah because if it's learned out from סברא sevara you can
raise a counter סברא. sevara. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva shows that
it's based on a פסוק. pasuk, Okay, so that was the משנה.
Mishnah. Again, very interesting because we just had that, קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, פסוק, pasuk, and here actually it's saying it's better that it's
a פסוק, pasuk then the סברא sevara can't be challenged. Okay, so
anyways, that's the idea. And now what we're going to do is
focus on the idea that food can become a שלישי לתרומה. shlishi
litruma. Okay, so let's take a look.
בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא Bo bayom darash Rabbi Akiva וכל כלי
חרש. vechol kli cheres. ומאחר דאינו, ume'achar de'eino, since
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says אינו מקרא מן התורה, eino mikra min
haTorah, you said that the idea of שלישי shlishi doesn't have a
basis in the פסוקים psukim and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva showed that
it had a basis in the פסוקים. psukim. So the גמרא Gemara
is saying I already told you the idea of the קל וחומר
kal vachomer that wasn't in the משנה. Mishna. ומאחר דאינו, ume'achar de'eino,
if there's no basis in the פסוקים, psukim, למה טמא? lama tamei?
Why before רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva were we assuming that food could
become a שלישי לתרומה, shlishi litruma, that it was טמא tamei if
there was no פסוק pasuk prior to רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav מן התורה אינו,
min haTorah eino, yes it's not a פסוק pasuk that tells you
that it's טמא. tamei. But I mean דין קל וחומר יש לו,
din kal vachomer yesh lo, we assumed that there was an idea
of a שלישי shlishi based on a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, at
least a שלישי shlishi for תרומה. truma. Okay, and now we're going
to spend the rest of the day figuring out these קל וחומרים.
kal vachomers. Okay, and now here's the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה
טבול יום uma tevul yom שמוותר בחולין shemutar bechulin פסול בתרומה. pasul
bitruma. A guy who goes to the מקוה mikva and he's waiting
for nightfall to be טהור. tahor. ובא השמש וטהר ואחר יאכל מן
הקדשים כי לחמו הוא, uva hashemesh vetaher ve'achar yochal min hakodashim ki
lachmo hu, right, so when the sun sets he's טהור tahor and
then he can eat from the קדשים kodashim which includes תרומה. truma.
So the פסוקים psukim make it clear that he's gone to the
מקוה, mikva, it hasn't yet been sunset, that's called טבול יום, tevul
yom, he was טובל tovel today but it's still the day that
he was טובל, tovel, it hasn't been sunset and he's אסור בתרומה.
beterumah Okay, so that's the idea. So ומה טבול יום uma tevul
yom שמוותר בחולין, shemutar bechulin, he can eat non-sanctified things and presumably
he would not be considered טמא tamei if he touched non-sanctified things,
פסול בתרומה, pasul bitruma, nevertheless he can't eat תרומה truma and the
presumption is right he can't eat תרומה truma and that if he
touches תרומה truma he makes it טמא, tamei, he defiles it. Okay,
so that's a טבול יום. tevul yom.
ככר שני שפסול בחולין, kikar sheini shepasul bechullin, a second loaf of
bread which we know does become טמא tamei even if it's חולין,
chulin, so אינו דין שיעשה שלישי בתרומה? eino din sheyaaseh shlishi betrumah,
How much more so should it be able to make another loaf
of bread that it touches that's תרומה truma טמא. tamei. Now there's
obviously a little bit of a difference here, right, because this guy,
right, like what's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Like this guy, he
is not the food that's a שני, sheni, meaning we're... the
guy is somebody who he is טהור tahor is allowed to touch
חולין, chulin, is not allowed to eat תרומה. truma. And the comparison
is, and therefore food that is itself טמא tamei vis-a-vis חולין chulin
is able... must be... make a problem when it touches תרומה. truma.
Am I not being clear? I understand... well that's the point. The
point is what... maybe I'm trying... I'm not being clear about what's
unclear maybe. The point is like this. Structurally it would be the
same if you would say the following. If you would say object
X is טהור tahor but it still makes תרומה
טמאה. truma tmeia. So object Y that is טמא, tamei, how much
more so should it make תרומה טמאה. truma tmeia. That would be
a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, right? That would be a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Don't worry about the טבול יום. tevul yom. Let's talk
about what the structure of the קל וחומר kal vachomer should look
like. Okay? We want to say that this object, this loaf of
bread that is a שני sheni for חולין chulin should certainly be
able to make תרומה טמאה. truma tmeia. So the קל וחומר kal
vachomer would be if you would have an object that would not
be טמא tamei for חולין, chulin, would be considered טהור tahor vis-a-vis
חולין chulin and it would make תרומה טמאה, truma tmeia, how much
more so an object that is טמא tamei for חולין chulin should
be able to make תרומה טמאה. truma tmeia.
I just don't understand how the טבול יום... tevul yom...
Okay, I'm getting there. I'm saying that's what it should look like,
right, if you wanted to make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. You'd
have to say take an object that is טהור tahor for חולין
chulin can make תרומה טמאה, truma tmeia, how much more so an
object that's טמא tamei for חולין chulin should be able to make
תרומה טמאה. truma tmeia. The problem is is that a טבול יום,
tevul yom, he's not exactly an object of חולין chulin that's טהור.
tahor. He's a person that's allowed to eat חולין. chulin. Okay, but
we're sort of glossing over that...
it's a gray area. Well not...
we're not talking about ספק. safek. The point is there's a difference
between the object being טהור. tahor. Okay, the object of the food,
right, I wish I had a whiteboard here. The object of the
food, if this object, if we were to say this object, okay
it's חולין chulin and it's טהור tahor and nevertheless if it touches
תרומה truma it makes it טמא, tamei, then קל וחומר kal vachomer
another object if it's חולין chulin and it's טמא, tamei, if it
touches תרומה truma it makes it טמא. tamei. So that's the קל
וחומר kal vachomer we want to make. The problem is is that
what we're saying... this object is not an object, it's a person
and we're not saying the point is that he's טהור, tahor, we're
saying if he's allowed to eat חולין chulin and nevertheless he's not
allowed to eat... he's not allowed to touch תרומה truma or eat
תרומה, truma, this thing which is טמא tamei as חולין, chulin, how
much more so should
it make.
It’s comparing a person to a loaf of bread.
Yeah, that’s an interesting point.
It’s that same thing as like
the סוטה sota and the meat and whatever.
The idea is it’s a thing that’s like you could right a
consciousness and a thing that doesn’t.
Right, right, and here we’ve got a person. That’s a very good
point. Yeah.
I think does a טבול יום tevul yom have essentially the status
of a שני בטומאה? sheini betumah?
Yes, but and that’s part of what the קל וחומר kal vachomer
is based on, but it’s only like by analogy because it’s most
of the הלכות halachos are similar, but he’s not actually considered a
שני, sheini, he’s considered a טבול יום. tevul yom. So anyway, let’s
acknowledge that this is a little bit the analogy is a little
weak, but that’s the argument. So let’s read it again. A little
weak. Okay. Don’t think about it for too long. Okay. ומה טבול
יום שמותר בחולין, uma tevul yom shemutar bechullin, a טבול יום tevul
yom can eat חולין, chullin, פוסל בתרומה, poseil betrumah, he invalidates
תרומה. trumah. ככר שני kikar sheni שפסול בחולין, shepasul bechulin, a loaf
of bread which as חולין chullin is
טמא, tamei, המה שכן, hamacha m'so, אינו דין שיעשה שלישי בתרומה, eino
din sheyaaseh shlishi betrumah. how much more so if this itself is
intrinsically טמא, tamei, okay, a טבול יום tevul yom isn’t really fully
טמא, tamei, he’s just got some residual טומאה. tumah. Maybe say it
that way, a טבול יום tevul yom just has some residual טומאה
tumah and nevertheless he makes a problem for תרומה. trumah. A ככר
שני kikar sheini which is real טמא, tamei, maybe that’s a nicer
way of thinking about it. Okay, so a טבול יום tevul yom
has residual טומאה tumah and he makes and he makes חולין chullin
תרומה trumah טומאה tumah and he makes תרומה trumah a problem. A
ככר שני kikar sheini which has real טומאה, tumah, אינו דין eino
din שיעשה שלישי בתרומה. sheya'aseh shlishi bitruma? How much more so should
it pass its טומאה tumah on to תרומה. trumah. Okay, so that’s
the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. איכא למיפרך, ika lemifrach, one minute, that
could be challenged. מה לטבול יום שכן אב הטומאה. mah letevul yom
shekein avi hatumah. So one minute, I said that the טבול יום’s
tevul yom is weaker because it’s residual. It might be only residual,
but it’s residual starting from something weightier. The guy himself was, let’s
say an אב הטומאה. avi hatumah. Let’s say he was a בעל
קרי baal keri or whatever he was or let’s say he directly
touched a שרץ. sheretz. No, if he directly touched a שרץ sheretz
he’d be a no he’d be a ראשון, rishon, he got it
directly from an אב. av. Okay, fine, you don’t even have to
go that far. He touched a שרץ, sheretz, so he got his
טומאה tumah from an אב, av, he started as an אב av
or ראשון. rishon. So it might only be residual but it started
higher, as opposed to this loaf of bread, it got it started
as a שני. sheini. So yes, maybe the residual טומאה tumah of
a בעל קרי baal keri is stronger than the than the at
the outset טומאה tumah of a שני. sheini. Okay. מה לטבול יום
שכן אב הטומאה, mah letevul yom shekein avi hatumah, that’s why he’s
a problem for תרומה, trumah, it would not be true by something
that started its life as a שני. sheini. גמרא gemara says fine.
תיתי מטבול יום דשרץ. teisi mitevul yom desheretz. Okay, actually no. So
oh, so I jumped ahead. So the אב הטומאה avi hatumah would
be he would be let’s say he’d been a בעל קרי, baal
keri, he started as an אב הטומאה. avi hatumah. So גמרא gemara
says I’ll give you a טבול יום tevul yom that has residual
that didn’t start as an אב, av, he touched a שרץ, sheretz,
he started as a ראשון. rishon. Okay, so if the residual טומאה
tumah of a ראשון rishon can be a problem for תרומה, trumah,
how much more so should real שני לטומאה sheini letumah be a
problem for אב הטומאה... avi hatumah... right, okay, so that’s the argument,
right, they corrected that, they corrected that, right.
Okay, so we’ve got a guy, he touched a שרץ, sheretz, he’s
a ראשון, rishon, he went to the מקוה, mikvah, so he has
only residual טומאה tumah from a ראשון rishon and that’s that’s powerful
enough to make a what do you call it, to make a
to be a problem for תרומה, trumah, how much more so is
something that is really טמא tamei even if it’s only טמא tamei
as a שני. sheini. Now you I think you might still have
made a difference, but let’s see what the גמרא gemara says. טבול
יום דשרץ. tevul yom desheretz. No, מה לטבול יום דשרץ שכן במינו
אב הטומאה. mah letevul yom desheretz shekein bemino avi hatumah. No, even
in the case of טבול יום דשרץ, tevul yom desheretz, so
one minute...
let me just double check רש"י...
Rashi... מה במינו וזהו אדם שבמת
נעשה אב הטומאה, mah baminu
vezo adam shebemais naaseh avi
hatumah, right, meaning, right,
right, meaning, right, right, meaning, it’s true that he only touched a
שרץ, sheretz, but in theory a person can be a can be
a ראשון, rishon, right? It’s true right now he started his life,
I’m sorry, in theory a person can be a I’m sorry, hold
on, an אב, av, one minute, one minute,
right, right, right. Right, in theory a person could be an אב,
av, exactly. Whereas whereas a whereas food can never be an אב.
av. Food can even if food were to touch a מת, mais,
the way a person becomes an אב av if it’s not something
that happens to him himself like he becomes a זב zav or
מצורע. metzora. It never becomes an אב av as he touches a
מת. meis. Okay, but food even if food touches a מת, meis,
it never becomes an אב. av. So we're basically still saying you
cannot assume that the residual טומאה tuma of a person is weaker
than the שני sheini of food. Number one, that person's טומאה tuma
might have started at a much higher level. Number two, even if
it didn't start at a higher level, טומאה tuma of persons might
by its very nature be weightier than טומאה tuma of foods because
in theory people can become אב הטומאות, av hatuma'os, so therefore maybe
there's something that's more weighty about his טומאה tuma and you can't
make a קל וחומר kal vachomer from the residual טומאה tuma of
a person to the שני sheini of food. That's very interesting.
Even if food touches a מת?
meis? Yeah, it becomes a ראשון, rishon, it does not become an
אב. av.
Yeah, if the רש"י Rashi says like about four lines down in
the narrow lines, טומאת אוכל שאינה נעשית אב הטומאה אפילו על ידי
מת דכתיב וכל אשר יגע בו הטמא יטמא מהכא נפקא לן דבמת
נטמאו ואומר וכלים וכולי Tum'at ochel she'einah na'aseit av hatumah afilu al
yedei meis dechtiv vechol asher yiga bo hatamei yitma meihacha nafka lan
d'vemeis nitma'u v'omer vecheilim v'chulu anyway etc. etc. Okay, so that, yeah,
it does not become an אב. av. Yeah.
נבלה neveilah is just a ראשון? rishon?
No, it is an אב, av, but it's not—it's true, I mean,
first of all, it's not exactly food, it's considered a נבלה, neveilah,
it's not fit for being eaten and so on—I mean it's fit
for a non-Jew to eat etc.—but that's not also like—that's not also
like becoming טמא tamei from the outside. We're talking about טומאה tuma
contracted from the outside, not about thing's intrinsic identity. Okay. So again,
the argument is that if a guy with residual טומאה tuma invalidates
תרומה, terumah, certainly something that was a שני. sheini. And the גמרא
Gemara says no, residual טומאה tuma of a person might be weightier.
A, it might have started at a higher level, and B, the
טומאה tuma of people might be intrinsically weightier than the טומאה tuma
of foods.
That's very interesting, even if it didn't start from a source, it's
thicker or weightier or more powerful.
Exactly, exactly. Now, by the way, you know this גמרא Gemara is
complicated because there's not one תוספות Tosafos on it and then it's
all רש"י Rashi on both sides of the דף. daf.
I wonder where I'm going to find that רש"י.
Rashi. Yeah, yeah, the רש"י, Rashi, right, the רש"י Rashi starts on
the outside margin, not the inside margin here.
I knew you
were going to tell me that right now. Okay, מה לכלי חרס,
Mah l'kli cheres, okay, מה לטבול יום דשרץ שכן במינו אב הטומאה.
Mah l'tveul yom d'sheretz sheken bemino av hatumah. No,
at least there it's in a category of things that could be
very weighty. So again, residual טומאה tuma of a טבול יום tveul
yom might be weightier than the טומאת שני tumat sheini of food.
So the גמרא Gemara says כלי חרס יוכיח. kli cheres yochiach. Wait,
wait, wait. I can prove it from a כלי חרס. kli cheres.
What can I prove from a כלי חרס? kli cheres?
That a כלי חרס kli cheres can also not become an אב
הטומאה av hatumah like food, and I know that a כלי חרס
kli cheres can make תרומה terumah פסול. pasul. Now, of course it's
a little funny because I only know כלי חרס kli cheres can
make תרומה terumah פסול pasul when the כלי חרס kli cheres is
a ראשון, rishon, okay, but here what I'm going to do is
I'm going to make a צד השווה. tzad hashaveh. I know a
person with residual טומאה, tuma, a טבול יום, tveul yom, okay, can
make תרומה terumah a problem. I know that a כלי חרס kli
cheres that is a ראשון rishon and that has no—can never become
an אב—I av know that that can make תרומה terumah a problem.
So I'm going to say, I'm going to learn from the case
of the person that something that is a
שני sheini can invalidate תרומה. terumah. You'll say, 'Wait, you can't learn
from a person. A person could in theory be even an אב.'
av. I'll say, 'Okay, I'll learn from כלי חרס.' kli cheres. You'll
tell me, 'Wait, you can't because that also can't be an אב
av and it can make תרומה terumah a problem. Ah, but כלי
חרס, kli cheres, you know, we're not dealing with residual טומאה. tuma.
כלי חרס kli cheres we're dealing with a ראשון.' rishon. Okay, I'll
go back to the person who is the case of residual טומאה.
tuma. That's only—that's until שלישי, shlishi, so you're understanding—but we're learning that
out—but we only know that a כלי חרס—the kli cheres תוספות Tosafos
discusses כלי חרס kli cheres as an אב? av? No, כלי חרס
kli cheres isn't a שני. sheini. Only food can be a שני.
sheini. Okay, so basically I really need a whiteboard but basically what
I've got is I've got a כלי חרס, kli cheres,
I've
got a כלי חרס, kli cheres, let me write on that wall
over there, I'd love that, I've got a כלי חרס kli cheres
which is a ראשון, rishon, okay, which can never be an אב,
av, but it can make תרומה terumah a problem, okay, but that's
not helpful, I want to learn that a שני sheini can make
תרומה terumah a problem. Okay, so I'll learn from the case of
the person with residual טומאה. tuma. That's very weak, that's only residual,
presumably it's even weaker than a שני, sheini, and that can make
תרומה terumah a problem. Ah, but I can't learn from a person
because a person could in theory could even be an אב. av.
Okay, well a כלי חרס kli cheres can't be an אב. av.
Ah, but you can't learn from a כלי חרס kli cheres because
that's starting with ראשון rishon טומאה, tuma, not residual. I'll learn from
a person. So I'll combine the two and I get a person
with residual טומאה tuma can make תרומה terumah a problem, and a
כלי חרס kli cheres that's a ראשון rishon can make תרומה terumah
a problem. So the צד השווה tzad hashaveh is that anything with,
like you know, that's even at a שני sheini level
which is comparable to the residual, even a שני sheini level can
make תרומה terumah a problem even if it doesn't have the ability
to ever itself become an אב. av. Because yes. Did you get
all of that? I hope so.
The כלי חרס kli cheres and the person. A person can become
טהור tahor and in fact its residual will become טהור tahor with
no action performed, but a כלי חרס kli cheres can never become
טהור tahor if once it becomes טמא. tamei.
Okay, so you're saying that that would make it weightier maybe and
therefore not through, yeah, maybe. You're right, I'll start, I'll tell them
if they don't get that elevator fixed,
we're gonna start writing on the windows.
They should just put whiteboards. Glass is better than whiteboards. It's clearer,
it'll make us more high tech. Okay great, it's just shown 10
years ago they had a plastic that the kids
would put over the television so they could write on it.
Okay
but it's a very good...
Alright alright, I see you guys are just trying to look to
distract yourselves from this גמרא. Gemara. Let's go on. Okay, so it
says, okay, מה לכיכר של תרומה שכן מטמא, ma l'kichar she'trumah she'kein
metamei, so גמרא Gemara says, so we'll learn it out, so from
a צד השוה tzad hashaveh between טבול יום tvul yom and כלי
חרס kli cheres that things can become a, that תרומה trumah can
become a שלישי. shlishi. No, מה כלי חרס, ma kli cheres, what
he wanted to say, or no, Charlie wanted to say that כלי
חרס kli cheres you can't be מיטהר במקוה. metaher b'mikvah. But let's
see what this says: מה כלי חרס שכן מטמא מאוירו. ma kli
cheres she'kein metamei m'aviro. Ah!
So כלי חרס
kli cheres is more חמור chamur that it makes things טמא tamei
even not through touch. It could have said מה כלי חרס ma
kli cheres that we're talking about a ראשון rishon and not about
a שני. sheni. But anyway the גמרא Gemara says טבול יום יוכיח.
tvul yom yochiach. Okay, but a טבול יום tvul yom has to
be through touch, וחזר הדין, v'chozer hadin, and it goes back and
forth. לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה. lo
rei zeh k'rei zeh v'lo rei zeh k'rei zeh. Each one's distinctive
characteristics are not found in the other one. הצד השוה שבהם, hatzad
hashaveh shebahem, the common denominator between the two of them, שמותרים בחולין.
she'muttarin b'chullin.
They themselves are, you know, it's a level of טומאה tumah that
would not be a problem by חולין. chullin. Okay, it's actually interesting,
the כלי חרס kli cheres actually, I don't know what מותר בחולין
muttar b'chullin means because the כלי חרס kli cheres actually does make
חולין chullin into a שני. sheni. Let me see what רש"י Rashi
says about that, one minute. מה הצד השוה שבהם שמטמאין תרומה והיו
קרויין טמאים. ma hatzad hashaveh shebahem she'metamin trumah v'hayu kroyin tmeim.
Oh yeah, רש"י Rashi takes out the גרסא girsa שמותר בחולין she'muttar
b'chullin because he says it doesn't make any sense. Because
a כלי חרס kli cheres actually does make חולין chullin into a
שני. sheni. רש"י's הצד השוה שבהם, Rashi's hatzad hashaveh shebahem, he has
the גרסא girsa is שמטמאין. she'metamin. Okay, the הצד השוה tzad hashaveh
is they transfer טומאה. tumah. Okay, a כלי חרס kli cheres makes,
is a ראשון rishon and makes food into a שני. sheni. And
a טבול יום tvul yom makes the תרומה trumah that he touches
invalid. So both of these are מטמאין metamin ופוסלין בתרומה u'poslin b'trumah
and create a problem with תרומה. trumah. כל שכן כיכר שני, kol
sheken kichar sheni, how much more so כיכר שני, kichar sheni,
which is, well we don't know it's מטמא metamei yet, but we
know it is טמא, tamei, שפוסל בחולין, she'posel b'chullin, that it, if
it's חולין chullin
it's already invalid, that a שני של חולין sheni shel chullin is
a problem, פוסל בתרומה, posel b'trumah, how much more so should it
invalidate תרומה. trumah. So there's some צד השוה tzad hashaveh which fundamentally
we're learning it out from the residual טומאה tumah of a טבול
יום tvul yom that makes חולין chullin a problem, but there are
things that make that that maybe are
make it more חמור chamur than the food, the fact that it's
residual and it might have started at a higher level, the fact
that it's a person. So we sort of discount those more חמור
chamur things by the comparison to the כלי חרס. kli cheres. Okay,
of course the כלי חרס kli cheres is a ראשון, rishon, not
a שני. sheni. The bottom line is we're sort of, we're mostly
learning from the טבול יום tvul yom who has only residual טומאה
tumah and טומאה tumah and is a problem for תרומה trumah that
certainly for a שני sheni for food that's a שני sheni that's
real טומאה tumah will it make a problem for תרומה. trumah. Yes.
So do we use the צד השוה tzad hashaveh instead of the
קל וחומר? kal vachomer? I'm sorry? Do we use the tzad hashaveh
instead of the kal vachomer? No, a צד השוה tzad hashaveh is
when the קל וחומר kal vachomer fails.
So it actually,
yeah I'm trying to remember,
is it based on a קל וחומר kal vachomer logic?
Yeah, the way you usually get to a צד השוה tzad hashaveh
is you try to say let's learn it from X. Now when
we want to start by learning it from X, let's learn it
as a קל וחומר kal vachomer from X or let's learn it
from X as a בנין אב, binyan av, as a paradigm. Okay,
but you want to start by learning it from X and then
oh wait, you can't necessarily learn it from X whether it's a
קל וחומר kal vachomer whatever because of this weakness and
then you look at another place,
it's also a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Yeah, we start with a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It also, you find it a lot in
the מדרש הלכה. Midrash Halacha. The מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha says והלא
דין הוא, v'halo din hu, which often introduces a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. If you're trying to say it by here, if the speaker
says, no because you could, you could say it's not exactly the
same... וחזר הדין. v'chozer hadin. The phrase of וחזר הדין v'chozer hadin
starts והלא דין הוא, v'halo din hu, so וחזר הדין v'chozer hadin
is you're taking this logical derivation and you're jumping back and forth
and you know, discounting the counterarguments until you get to this צד
השוה. tzad hashaveh. Yeah.
So we've lost our קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
Yeah, so it's really no longer a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, it's
really more of a צד השוה, tzad hashaveh, which is a weak,
yeah, which is an argument more by like analogy than by קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, right? Or by, you know...
But I mean, the first, now our first category is no longer
קל kal because we've
pointed out some חמור chamur aspects? Exactly. Exactly, that it starts with
a higher level or that it's, that it's possible to become an
אב הטומאה? av hatumah?
Does it make חולין טמא, chullin tamei, right? Our whole point was
that it doesn't, which is what made it...
no, it is true that a טבול יום tvul yom does not
make חולין טמא, chullin tamei, but a טבול יום tvul yom still
makes the תרומה... trumah... be weightier because his טומאה tumah started at
a higher level and he himself could theoretically become an אב av
and so on. So the fact that a טבול יום tvul yom
has the ability to make תרומה terumah a problem doesn't prove that
food has the ability to make תרומה terumah a problem.
Right, okay, I'm just because we go by רש"י'ס Rashi's version where
we change it from מטמא.
mitamei. Right, right.
So then if it's I mean the whole...
Oh yeah, רש"י Rashi says מטמא. mitamei. When רש"י Rashi says מטמאים,
mitammim, no I'm sorry, I think I even misstated it. When רש"י
Rashi says מטמאים mitammim he doesn't make other things טמא. tamei. You're
right because that's really the whole thing that's up for question. He
really just doesn't mean it's just called טמא. tamei. A טבול יום
tvul yom is called טמא, tamei, כלי חרס kli cheres is called
טמא tamei and they create problems for תרומה. terumah. So certainly a
כיכר שני kikar sheini which is called טמא tamei should make a
problem for תרומה. terumah. Right, so you're right.
It's really so it's not מטמא בחולין, mitamei b'chullin, it's just
they're called טמא, tamei, right? So for רש"י Rashi at the end
of the day, the צד השוה tzad hashaveh is is that a
טבול יום tvul yom and a כלי חרס kli cheres are called
טמא tamei and they make תרומה terumah a problem, so anything that's
called טמא tamei which would include אוכל שני ochel sheini should make
תרומה terumah a problem, yeah.
I was just going to say, it's very powerful they change the
hermeneutic, they want to come to the same place.
Right, well that often happens very often, we start with a קל
וחומר kal v'chomer and we end up with a צד השוה. tzad
hashaveh. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this, okay? So let's
read it again: לא ראי זה כראי זה צד השוה שבהן ש
lo reizeh k'reizeh tzad hashaveh shebehen she- well instead of מותרים בחולין
mutarin b'chullin we'll read שמטמאים, shemitammim, they're the things that are called
טמא tamei ופוסלין בתרומה u'poslin b'terumah and they invalidate תרומה. terumah. כל
שכן, kol shekein, it's interesting that it says כל שכן kol shekein
because once it's a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, but okay, כיכר שני,
kikar sheini, you know, אף אני אביא af ani avi is rather
more than the כל שכן. kol shekein. Similarly, a כיכר שני שפסול
בחולין kikar sheini shepasul b'chullin or again רש"י Rashi would say שמטמא—it's
shemitamei called טמא—דפוסל בתרומה. Okay, so that's the צד השוה. tzad hashaveh.
ודור אחר פרך, v'dor acher pareich, now he said that was until
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva came along, we only had a דרשה. drasha.
So what the דרשה drasha is is that some or you know,
not a דרשה, drasha, excuse me, a logical derivation is that another
generation could challenge it. What would the other generation say? No, מה
לצד השוה שבהן שכן יש בהן צד חמור. mah l'tzad hashaveh shebahen
she-kein yesh bahen tzad chamur. Now this צד חמור tzad chamur is
actually it's like it's the challenge to any צד השוה, tzad hashaveh,
okay? Because if you have to think about it, there's a real
problem with like a צד השוה, tzad hashaveh, right? Here's the problem
with a צד השוה. tzad hashaveh. The צד השוה tzad hashaveh is
is like I've got these two guys that are both like basketball
superstars. So this guy is seven feet tall and this other guy
is like super fast. So the צד השוה שבהן tzad hashaveh shebahen
is that they're guys. So I'll bring any guy will be a
basketball superstar, okay? Because it's obviously not about height because this other
guy isn't tall. It's obviously not about speed because this other guy
isn't fast. So obviously it's just about, you know, being a guy
in a uniform that makes you a basketball superstar. Okay, so obviously
that's a problem with every צד השוה, tzad hashaveh, that maybe it
is the distinctive characteristics and there's more than one distinctive characteristic that
can lead to the הלכה. halakha. Okay, so that's the response of
a צד חמור. tzad chamur. צד חמור tzad chamur says you can't
do a צד השוה tzad hashaveh because maybe each thing's distinctive characteristic
is what's rather problem is is that that's a really good response,
but then you might as well just throw out every single צד
השוה tzad hashaveh in the ש"ס. shas. תוספות Tosafot tries to sometimes
explain that when we challenge צד השוה tzad hashaveh we're actually finding
something similar of the two distinctive characteristics even though it's very vague
and abstract. Anyway, but that's the point. The point is at the
end of the day you learned it out from a צד השוה
tzad hashaveh but okay, even if it's a צד השוה tzad hashaveh
that's not a strong derivation. Each one of those things had something
distinctive going for it that could explain its power and food that's
a שני sheini doesn't have those distinctive characteristics, so maybe food that's
a שני sheini cannot פסול תרומה. pasul terumah. Okay, שכן יש בהן
צד חמור shekein yesh bahen tzad chamur and therefore thank you רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that you now you've given us a דרשה, drasha,
so we're saved because now we can actually learn out the idea
of a שלישי shelishi for תרומה terumah from the פסוק pasuk, and
we don't have to do it based on this צד השוה. tzad
hashaveh.
What was the again the חמור chamur part in this particular instance?
One of them, the כלי חרס kli cheres is מטמא מאוירה mitamei
me'avira and the טבול יום tvul yom either starts with a higher
level of טומאה tumah or he himself could become an אב. av.
Okay. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai צד חמור לא
פרך tzad chamur lo pareich and רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai wasn't bothering with that because you know, if you bothered
with a צד חמור tzad chamur you'll never do a צד השוה
tzad hashaveh in your life, so he wasn't bothered. But רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua said thank God at least now we got a פסוק,
it saves us from any challenge. Okay. תניא, Tanyah, that was the
idea of an idea of how we know שלישי בתרומה. shelishi b'terumah.
Now as long as we're on this fun topic, we're going to
discuss how do we know the idea
that קודש kodesh can become a רביעי? revi? תרומה terumah can be
a שלישי shelishi and קודש kodesh can be פסול pasul when they
touch a even when they touch a שלישי, shelishi, okay? So the
גמרא gemara says like this: תניא Tanyah we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, אמר רבי יוסי מניין לרביעי בקודש שפסול? Amar Rabbi Yose: minayin
l'revi bakodesh shepasul? So we know now שלישי shelishi about a תרומה,
terumah, how do we know about a רביעי revi by קודש kodesh
by קרבנות? korbanot? ודין הוא, v'din hu, a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
ומה מחוסר כיפורים u'mah mechussar kippurim that we started learning out the
idea of טבול יום tvul yom of שלישי בתרומה shelishi b'terumah from
the fact that a טבול יום tvul yom can't eat תרומה. terumah.
Okay, but... There's one level down from a טבול יום, tevul yom,
one level even more residual. What's even more residual than a טבול
יום? tevul yom? מחוסר כיפורים. mechusar kipurim. Somebody that his טהרה tahara
process ends not when the sun sets but when he brings a
קרבן korban the next morning, okay, like you know like a זב
zav or a יולדת. yoledet. They bring a קרבן korban the next
morning. So as of sunset they're no longer טבול יום tevul yom
but they are awaiting their קרבן, korban, מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kipurim and
כיפורים kipurim and only once they bring their קרבן korban are they
totally טהור. tahor. What's their status after the sunset before their קרבן
korban is brought? That they cannot eat קרבנות. korbanot. They're אסור בקודש.
assur bekodesh. So the same residual טומאה tuma of a טבול יום
tevul yom teaches me that a שני sheni makes a שלישי shlishi
by תרומה terumah because there's something that שני sheni would be at
least as powerful as residual טומאה tuma of the טבול יום. tevul
yom. So the residual טומאה tuma after sunset of מחוסר כיפורים mechusar
kipurim is assumed to be a שלישי shlishi of טומאה tuma is
assumed to be at least as weighty as that. So if a
guy who's awaiting his קרבן korban can't eat, can't eat קרבנות, korbanot,
so presumably something that's a שלישי shlishi which is really טמא, tamei
not just residual, right? Certainly that should create a problem and should
be מטמא metamei something that's a קרבן. korban. That's... it's a very
parallel argument, okay? It presumes these analogies, but once you presume those
analogies, if a טבול יום tevul yom can't eat תרומה terumah a
שני sheni can't touch תרומה, terumah, if a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kipurim
can't eat קרבנות korbanot a שלישי shlishi can't touch קרבנות. korbanot. Okay.
מניין
לרביעי בקודש שפסול ודין הוא. minayin lerevii bekodesh shepasul vedin hu. מה
מחוסר כיפורים שמותר בתרומה, ma mechusar kipurim shemutar beterumah, so a guy
who's awaiting his קרבן korban can eat תרומה, terumah, פסול בקודש, pasul
bekodesh, can't eat קרבנות, korbanot, so שלישי שפסול בתרומה, shlishi shepasul beterumah,
שלישי shlishi that is really a level of טומאה tuma that invalidates
תרומה, terumah, if so, if something was תרומה terumah it's been invalidated
because it touched שלישי. shlishi. אינו דין שיעשה רביעי בקודש? eino din
sheyaaseh revii bekodesh? How much more so should it be should it
have the power that it should invalidate a קרבן korban if it
touches a קרבן? korban? Okay, so something that's a שלישי shlishi בתרומה
should be able to invalidate a קרבן. korban.
Wait, what you're saying that if a תרומה terumah touches a שלישי
shlishi it's invalidated?
No. That's what, that's the problem with the analogy. No. If תרומה
terumah itself is a שלישי shlishi it became invalidated. You're going to
tell me that the comparison is not exact. I right, I agree.
That's what we said from the beginning. Okay, just have to accept
it. The the the analogy is if a guy who's a שלישי,
shlishi, not a שלישי, shlishi, if a guy who's a מחוסר כיפורים
mechusar kipurim can eat תרומה terumah and he has the power to
invalidate קרבן, korban, so תרומה terumah which as a שלישי shlishi has
become invalidated because it was a שלישי shlishi should certainly be able
to invalidate a קרבן korban by touching. It's not an exact analogy,
but that's the that's the argument. Okay? Right.
Analogizing people to exactly...
okay. Okay. So, ולמדנו שלישי לקודש מן התורה. velamadnu shlishi lekodesh min
hatorah. Now we know that a that something that is a שלישי
shlishi that's a קרבן korban is from the תורה Torah we know
that that invalidates קרבנות. korbanot. We didn't know it invalidated תרומה terumah
but we know it invalidates קרבנות. korbanot. How we know that שלישי
shlishi invalidate that if a קרבן korban is a שלישי shlishi it's
invalid we'll see in a minute, but we already know from the
תורה Torah that if a קרבן korban is a שלישי shlishi it's
invalid. ורביעי מקל וחומר כאמרן verevii mikal vachomer keamran and now we
learn the idea that even if it's a קרבן korban that's a
רביעי, revii, that we learn from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, the
קל וחומר kal vachomer we just put out
there. שלישי לקודש מן התורה מנלן? shlishi lekodesh min hatorah minalan? דכתיב:
dechtiv: והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא לא יאכל. vehabasar asher yiga bechol
tamei lo yeachel. So the meat that touches anything טמא tamei, cannot
be eaten, and that's קרבן korban meat. Now what's טמא? tamei מי
לא עסקינן דנגע בשני? mi lo askinan denaga besheni?
Remember what does the תורה Torah call טמא? tamei? The תורה Torah
called the food that fell into the כלי חרס kli cheres טמא,
tamei? right? And that that food was only a שני, sheni, the
כלי חרס, kli cheres, the שרץ sheretz made the כלי חרס kli
cheres a ראשון, rishon, food that fell into it the תורה Torah
called it טמא, tamei, יטמא. yitma. So this food that is טמא,
tamei, now it tells me anything טמא tamei, including food that's a
שני sheni that touches a קרבן korban invalidates the קרבן. korban. So
the פסוקים pesukim make it clear that if a קרבן korban is
a that if a קרבן korban if it becomes a שלישי shlishi
is invalid. Okay? מי לא עסקינן דנגע בשני? mi lo askinan denaga
besheni? ואמר רחמנא לא יאכל. veamar rachmana lo yeachel. Okay,
so we know already from the פסוקים pesukim that if a קרבן
korban is a שלישי shlishi it's invalid. ורביעי מקל וחומר כאמרן, verevii
mikal vachomer keamran,
and we learned out that a רביעי revii is invalid if it's
a... from a קל וחומר kal vachomer that if a מחוסר כיפורים
mechusar kipurim can't eat a קרבן korban and that's very residual, how
much more so if something is a שלישי shlishi and it touches
a קרבן korban should it invalidate it? Okay? אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan. So that seems like a reasonable דרשה drasha I mean
once you buy in the analogy of people to the to the
objects, it seems reasonable. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan טעם דרבי
אני יודע. taam deRabbi ani yodea.
I don't know what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei is talking about. רבי
Rabbi is just a רבי Rabbi is like the an honorific, right?
I don't know what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei is talking about. מהו?
mahu? שהרי תשובתו בצידו. sheharei teshuvato betzido.
There's an immediate counter-example. What's the immediate counter-example? אוכל הבא מחמת טבול
יום יוכיח. ochel haba machmas tevul yom yochiach. How about food that...
Touched. Okay, now, what's that הלכה? halacha? שפסול בתרומה ואינו עושה רביעי
בקודש. She-pasul bitruma ve-eino oseh revii bakodesh.
That, that thing invalidates תרומה, truma, but it does not invalidate קודש,
kodesh, meaning that if you actually have, okay, what's a שלישי? shlishi?
A שלישי shlishi is food that touched a שני, sheni, right? Okay,
so תרומה truma that touched—well, תרומה truma that touched a שני. sheni.
I really need a whiteboard. Okay, but it's תרומה truma that touched
a שני. sheni. Now, we have analogized a טבול יום tvul yom
to a שני, sheni, correct? That was our whole previous דרשה. drasha.
Now, so if you have food that touched a שני, sheni, it's
a שלישי. shlishi. What would be about food that touched a טבול
יום? tvul yom? What would that status be? Okay, if you want
to argue that a שלישי shlishi of תרומה truma should invalidate קרבנות,
korbanot, right? A שלישי shlishi of תרומה truma should invalidate קרבנות korbanot
because you want to analogize it from a טבול יום tvul yom
who then became a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim and he can
invalidate קרבנות. korbanot. But one minute, but then logically the food touched
by a טבול יום tvul yom should also be able to invalidate
קרבנות, korbanot, right? You've got this line, which is the foods, and
this line, which is the people. The person starts off as a
ראשון, rishon, goes to the—oh, forget it. It's—I'm
following—I know you're following, but it's 8:30 and we need—we'll have to
do it tomorrow. Maybe I'll make sure we have some form of
a whiteboard or something, or maybe I'll draw up some diagrams. Anyway,
we'll continue here tomorrow. To be continued.
Bring the whiteboard from my office. מחוסר כפרה. Mechusar kapara.