Alright, today's דף daf is דף ל, Daf Lamed,
and we're going to get through this discussion about שלישי shlishi and
רביעי בטומאה, revii bitumah, which was what we're deep in the middle
of. So we're going to pick up at the bottom of כט
עמוד ב Chaf Tet Amud Bet and we'll do it as following.
So the whole point was that we learned out there's an idea
of שלישי בתרומה shlishi bitrumah from an idea that a טבול יום
tvul yom cannot eat תרומה, trumah, and we're learning that there's an
idea of a רביעי revii בתרומה bitrumah for קדשים, kodashim, for קודש,
kodesh, by the idea that a מחוסר כיפורים mechussar kippurim cannot eat
קדשים. kodashim. And again, the basic comparison if we'll try to simplify
it is that if a person with residual טומאה tumah
is forbidden to eat a particular thing, then something that is actually
טמא tamei should make that thing other thing טמא. tamei. So a
person who's a טבול יום, tvul yom, residual טומאה, tumah, can't eat
תרומה, trumah, but he can eat חולין. chullin. So something that itself
is חולין chullin and is טמא, tamei, a שני, sheini, should be
able to make תרומה trumah טמא. tamei. And similarly, if a person
who is residual טומאה, tumah, a מחוסר כיפורים, mechussar kippurim, cannot eat
קדשים, kodashim, then something that is actually טמא tamei for even though
he can eat תרומה, trumah, then something that is actually טמא tamei
for תרומה, trumah, a שלישי, shlishi, can make קדשים kodashim into a
רביעי. revii. Okay, that's the basic structure of the argument. So now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. And these are all these
are all like הלכה למשה מסיני? Halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai?
No, they're all learned out, and that's part of the discussion of
the גמרא Gemara from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer or גזירה שווה.
gezerah shavah. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so now רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said about twenty lines from the bottom line starts with
the word יוחנן. Yochanan. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, טעם ברבי
איני יודע, ta'am b'Rebbi eini yodea, I don't understand this whole דרשה
drashah of רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yose. Why? מה הוא מה הוא? ma
hu ma hu? שהרי תשובתו בצידו, sheharei teshuvato b'tzido, the response is
right there on its side. אוכל הבא מחמת טבול יום, ochel habah
machmat tvul yom, and I will show you something that doesn't fit
this pattern. What's that? אוכל הבא מחמת טבול יום יוכיח. ochel habah
machmat tvul yom yochiach. So you wanted to prove from a מחוסר
כיפורים mechussar kippurim who can eat תרומה trumah but can't eat קדשים
kodashim to a שלישי בתרומה. shlishi bitrumah. Let me give you something
that doesn't fit that pattern. Okay, if you have food that was
touched by a טבול יום, tvul yom, so food meaning תרומה trumah
that was touched by a טבול יום, tvul yom, that would be
effectively a שלישי, shlishi, right? So based on your argument, what should
that do? That should be able to make קדשים kodashim into a
רביעי. revii. Okay, so אוכל הבא מחמת טבול יום יוכיח ochel habah
machmat tvul yom yochiach שפסול בתרומה, shepassul bitrumah, that it's תרומה trumah
that invalidates, ואינו עושה רביעי בקודש, v'eino oseh revii bakodesh, it does
not go on to the רביעי בקודש. revii bakodesh. So things coming
from people with residual טומאה tumah anyway, so it doesn't always work.
Okay, so just because a מחוסר כיפורים mechussar kippurim can't
eat קודש kodesh does not mean that other analogous things would פוסל
posel קודש, kodesh, because here's something touched by a טבול יום, tvul
yom, food, that also
invalidates תרומה trumah but does not pass on to invalidate קודש. kodesh.
So why should you say that it's true by a שלישי shlishi
that all went straight through food? That a שלישי shlishi is, right,
something touched a food that became a ראשון, rishon, the food touched
something שני, שלישי, sheini shlishi, it's all food like all turtles all
the way down, it's all food all the way down. Okay, so
that we're saying makes קודש kodesh into a רביעי, revii, but he
says by analogy to the מחוסר כיפורים. mechussar kippurim. Well, how is
it different than food touched by a טבול יום, tvul yom, which
פוסל posel תרומה trumah and doesn't make קודש kodesh into a רביעי?
revii? Now how do you know it doesn't make קודש kodesh into
a רביעי? revii? דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Braitah. אבא
שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, טבול יום תחילה לקודש. tvul yom tchilah
lakodesh. So אבא שאול Abba Shaul has a חומרא chumra דרבנן. d'rabbanan.
He basically says a טבול יום tvul yom that when it comes
to issues of קדשים kodashim is treated actually like a ראשון. rishon.
Okay, so means מטמא שנים ופוסל אחד. metamei shnayim u'lifsol echad. So
two things become טמא, tamei, meaning a טבול יום tvul yom touches
something for קודש kodesh purposes, we're going to treat him even though
normally we treat him like a שני, sheini, for קודש kodesh purposes
we're going to treat him like a ראשון. rishon. So he touches
food that makes the food for these purposes into a שני, sheini,
the food touches other food makes it into a שלישי, shlishi, that's
supposed to that's מטמא שנים, metamei shnayim, and that food that's a
שלישי shlishi, touches קודש, kodesh, makes it פוסל, passul, that's רביעי בקודש
revii bakodesh and it's פוסל לקודש. posel lakodesh. מטמא שנים ופוסל אחד.
metamei shnayim u'lifsol echad. Now the difference between the word פוסל posel
and מטמא metamei is מטמא metamei is טומאה tumah that can then
be passed on to the next stage. פוסל passul is that it's
invalid but it doesn't get passed on. So basically what he's saying
is a טבול יום tvul yom for קודש kodesh purposes, this is
a דין דרבנן, din d'rabbanan, okay,
but it's treated as a ראשון. rishon. That's what he says. רבי
מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, no, מטמא אחד ופוסל אחד. metamei echad
u'posel echad. It's treated as a שני, sheini, which is sort of
how we normally treat a טבול יום, tvul yom, he פוסל posel
תרומה, trumah, so here he's מטמא אחד, metamei echad, he makes תרומה
trumah into a שלישי, shlishi and that תרומה trumah makes קודש kodesh
into a רביעי. revii. So according to these first two opinions, actually,
by טבול יום tvul yom it does proceed on to a רביעי.
revii. So the real challenge is the
חכמים. Chachamim. חכמים אומרים, Chachamim omrim, כשם שפוסל אוכלי תרומה ומשקה תרומה,
k'shem sheposel ochlei trumah umashkeh trumah, the same way a טבול יום
tvul yom invalidates תרומה trumah food and liquid, כך פוסל אוכלי קודש
ומשקה קודש, kach פוסל ochlei kodesh umashkeh kodesh, it invalidates קדשים kodashim
food and liquid, but it does not go on. So טבול יום
tvul yom stops at a שלישי, shlishi, and the food that it
invalidated as a שלישי shlishi, does not. make קודשים Kodshim into a
רביעי. revii. So we're assuming like the חכמים. Chachamim. So we're saying,
how do you argue the fact that a מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim
makes קודשים Kodshim פסול, pasul, that that makes food that's a שלישי
shlishi of תרומה Terumah passes it on for קודשים Kodshim to be
a רביעי? revii? Here you have something
that's פסול pasul for תרומה Terumah and doesn't go on to a
רביעי. revii. תרומה Terumah that was touched by a טבול יום. Tevul
Yom. All right, I really wish I had a whiteboard, but I
think you got the basic structure, okay? That the same logic, here
something is פסול pasul for תרומה, Terumah, it doesn't pass on. So
how can you assume that food that's a שלישי shelishi passes on
to a רביעי? revii? So the גמרא Gemara says, מתיקיף לה רב
פפא, Matkif leh Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa challenges. במאי
כרבי יוסי כרבנן סבירא ליה? Be-mai ke-Rabbi Yose ke-Rabbanan sevira leh? Your
only question is according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, and the רבנן Rabbanan
say that טבול יום Tevul Yom stops at a שלישי shelishi and
it doesn't go on to a רביעי. revii. דלמא כאבא שאול סבירא
ליה? Dilma ke-Abba Shaul sevira leh? Maybe he holds like אבא שאול?
Abba Shaul? דאמר לטמא שנים ולפסול אחד, De-amar le-tammei shenayim u-le-fasel echad,
that says it's even, it does go all the way on to
a רביעי. revii. It's even more powerful. It's treated like a טבול
יום Tevul Yom is treated like a ראשון. rishon. And as רש"י
Rashi points out, even though the idea that a טבול יום Tevul
Yom would be treated like a ראשון rishon is a clear דרבנן,
de-rabbanan, but nevertheless underlying אבא שאול Abba Shaul is the basic principle
that the טומאה tuma that comes from a טבול יום Tevul Yom
can pass all the way down to a קדשים Kodshim to a
רביעי. revii. So there's not a counterexample. Only according to the חכמים.
Chachamim. But if we hold that a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, the
טומאה tuma can pass and make קדשים Kodshim into a רביעי revii
eventually, so the same would be that a שלישי shelishi for תרומה
Terumah can make a רביעי. revii. Okay.
אי סלקא דעתך I-sal-ka da-atach says the גמרא, Gemara, no, that can't
be. Because אי סלקא דעתך אבא שאול סבירא ליה, I-sal-ka da-atach Abba
Shaul sevira leh, having held like אבא שאול, Abba Shaul,
ליתי לרביעי בקודש מאוכל הבא מחמת טבול יום. le-yeti le-revii be-Kodesh me-ochel
she-ba me-achamat Tevul Yom. There are basically three scenarios about making קדשים
Kodshim into a רביעי, revii, okay? There's the case that we sort
of know about, the מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim can make, you know,
can't eat קדשים Kodshim or makes קדשים Kodshim טמא, tamei, that's like
the paradigm. Then there's the case we're trying to apply to, which
is a שלישי shelishi בבתרומה be-Terumah makes a רביעי. revii. Then there's
the case here that we're looking at, the wildcard, is it a
consistent example or a counterexample? And that's the case of food touched
by a טבול יום. Tevul Yom. So first we said food touched
by a טבול יום Tevul Yom is a counterexample, okay? Now we're
saying, no, no, no, according to אבא שאול Abba Shaul who argues
on the חכמים, Chachamim, it's a consistent example. Food touched by a
טבול יום Tevul Yom passes it on from a שלישי shelishi to
a רביעי. revii. So now we're saying, oh, but if it was
a consistent example, why didn't he learn from that? Why'd he run
to the case of מחוסר כיפורים? Mechussar Kippurim? So I'm going to
show you that it's not a consistent example because if it is,
that actually would have served as his proof, okay? Are people with
me here? Sort of enough that we can get through it and
then move on to the next topic? That's what I was figuring.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, ליתי לרביעי בקודש מאוכל הבא
מחמת טבול יום. le-yeti le-revii be-Kodesh me-ochel she-ba me-achamat Tevul Yom. ומה
אוכל הבא מחמת טבול יום U-mah ochel ha-ba me-achamat Tevul Yom דטבול
יום גופיה מותר בחולין, de-Tevul Yom gufei mutar be-chulin, even when it
starts with a טבול יום Tevul Yom who himself can eat חולין,
chulin,
so it starts, you know, very weak, אמרת amart עושה רביעי בקודש,
oseh revii be-Kodesh,
the טומאה tuma goes all the way down to make רביעי בקודש.
revii be-Kodesh. אוכל שלישי הבא מחמת שני? Ochel shelishi ha-ba me-achamat sheni?
If it's coming not from a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, but it's
coming from a שני? sheini, Right, the שני sheni? is the originator,
right? The parallel to the טבול יום Tevul Yom is food that's
a שני. sheni So if a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, his טומאה
tuma can go down two levels to make קדשים Kodshim into a
רביעי, revii, then שני sheni. that is
טמא, tamei, that, you know, a טבול יום Tevul Yom can eat
חולין, chulin, שני sheni that's actually חולין chulin is טמא, tamei, then
certainly that טומאה tuma should be able to go down two levels
to make קדשים Kodshim into
a רביעי. revii. So שלישי הבא מחמת שני shelishi ha-ba me-achamat sheni
דשני גופיה אסור בחולין, de-sheni gufei assur be-chulin, אינו דין שעושה רביעי
בקודש? eino din she-oseh revii be-Kodesh? Okay. So therefore the גמרא Gemara
is saying, why are you learning from מחוסר כיפורים? Mechussar Kippurim? The
case of that, how can you learn from מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim
that שלישי shelishi can make a רביעי? revii? The case of food
that comes from a טבול יום Tevul Yom is a counterexample. And
if you say that the case of food that comes from a
טבול יום Tevul Yom isn't a counterexample but is actually consistent, then
why aren't you learning from that case? Okay, because that case actually
is like, if a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, which is מותר בחולין,
mutar be-chulin, his טומאה tuma can go down two levels to be
a רביעי בקודש, revii be-Kodesh, certainly שני, sheni which itself is חולין
טמאים, chulin tameim, can go down two levels to make a רביעי
בקודש.
revii be-Kodesh. An object being a סוף טומאה Sof Tuma as opposed
to someone...
I understand, we discussed that yesterday. Let's, yeah, yes, but we're going
to bracket that. Okay, וכי תימא, Ve-chi teima, no, the reason you
don't want to learn from a טבול יום Tevul Yom to apply
to the idea of, if a טבול יום's Tevul Yom's טומאה tuma
can go down two levels, a שני's sheni, טומאה tuma can go
down two levels, וכי תימא משום דאיכא למפרך, ve-chi teima mishum de-ika
le-mifrach, you can challenge it. מה לטבול יום שכן אב טומאה? Mah
le-Tevul Yom she-ken av tuma?
No, no, no, you can't learn from a טבול יום Tevul Yom
and say, oh, if it works by a טבול יום Tevul Yom
with residual טומאה tuma going down two levels, it works by food
that's טמא tamei to go down two levels. That you can't say
because a טבול יום Tevul Yom started as an אב, av, or
he didn't start as an אב, av, he could be an אב,
av, okay, not necessarily started, but at least he could be an
אב. av. So the גמרא Gemara says, so you can't learn it
from food that could never be an אב. av. So, but then
that same challenge is relevant
to the
מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim case. מה למחוסר כיפורים שכן... Mah le-Mechussar Kippurim
she-ken...
So basically
just to sort of sum this up so that thankfully we can
move on okay? To sum this up the point is the following.
How do we learn out that שני sheni's food that's a שני
sheni makes a שלישי? shelishi Because a טבול יום tevul yom who
can't eat...
who's okay with חולין chulin makes תרומה terumah a problem. So food
חולין chulin itself that's a שני sheni should make תרומה terumah a
problem. That's that לימוד. limud. And the analogy for how do we
know that תרומה terumah that's a שלישי shlishi? makes קדשים kodshim a
רביעי revii is because a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim that can eat
תרומה terumah can not eat or you know קדשים, kodshim, right? So
therefore תרומה terumah itself that's טמא tamei should certainly be able to
be מטמא metamei קדשים. kodshim. Okay, I know it's not the exact
same but that's the analogy. If the person who's okay with object
X cannot eat or touch object Y, then if object X itself
is טמא tamei then certainly it should be able to pass on
the טומאה tumah to object Y. That's the analogy. So by a
טבול יום tevul yom we allow that to get us to תרומה
terumah and by מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim we allow that to get
us from תרומה terumah that's טמא tamei to קדשים. kodshim. And the
only thing that the גמרא Gemara ended with is saying that there's
a counter example to that which is food that derives from a
טבול יום tevul yom you know one degree down is תרומה טמאה
terumah temeiah but that doesn't go all the way down to קדשים.
kodshim. So that's according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. So that's the counter
example. The גמרא Gemara says no, maybe we פוסקין pasken that it
does go down to קדשים kodshim and it's not a counter example.
So the גמרא Gemara says well if it's not a counter example
then it should have been used as the paradigm. Okay and why
are you so... so therefore it's not fully satisfied. What is the
story with that case? Either it's a counter example or if it's
not a counter example then why wasn't it learned used as the
basis for the הלכה. halacha. And then the final point that the
גמרא Gemara made is is that making this לימוד limud from a
person to food is not necessarily besides that it's not exactly the
same case is not necessarily great because maybe the person's טומאה tumah
although it's residual maybe to some degree it's weightier because the person
could have been an אב. av. And that's a challenge that you
could raise to whether you're learning out from מחוסר כפורים mechusar kippurim
or whether you're learning out from two degrees derivation from the case
of the טבול יום tevul yom that's like a relevant critique that
for some reason we did not raise. Okay? But that's basically how
we learn out the idea of שלישי shlishi by תרומה terumah and
רביעי revii by קודש kodesh and now we're going to go on.
That objection... that objection could have been raised at the beginning of
the entire deliberation.
It was but then the גמרא Gemara did like a צד השוה
tzad hashaveh by כלי חרס keli cheres and then...
very nice framing though I mean it's really the whole thing is
framed by
that thing about persons and objects and as you pointed out that's
part of the whole point about סוטה Sotah that a person being
טמא tamei and then we learn out of objects being טמא. tamei.
Okay let's go on all this
though I have one question. What happened to the turtle?
Yeah exactly.
So now we have one last discussion about this שני sheni and
שלישי shlishi stuff which is a little bit easier and then thankfully
we move on. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אמר רב אסי... Amar Rav Assi... no we move
on
today. אמר רב אסי אמר רב. Amar Rav Assi amar Rav. אמרי
לה אמר רבה בר בר אסי אמר רב Amri lei amar Rabba
bar bar Assi amar Rav or רבה Rabba the son of אסי
Assi said in the name of רב. Rav. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, all these תנאים, Tannaim,
כולהו סבירא להו kulu seviru leu they all hold דאין שני עושה
שלישי בחולין. de-ein sheni oseh shlishi be-chulin. That a שלישי shlishi only
goes up through תרומה terumah not... a תרומה terumah can become a
שלישי shlishi not חולין. chulin. Now that is well yes well first
of all all the לימודים limudim we did today and yesterday were
about תרומה. terumah. You'll remember, right? A טבול יום tevul yom can't
eat תרומה. terumah. So that shows us that a שני sheni could
make תרומה terumah into a שלישי. shlishi It was all about תרומה.
terumah. However רש"י Rashi on the משנה Mishnah pointed out although I
don't think the גמרא Gemara made it clear that because רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva learns out that שני sheni is עושה שלישי oseh shlishi
from the פסוק pasuk of כל אשר יפול מהם אל תוכו יטמא,
kol asher yipol me-hem el tocho yitma, יטמא לטמא אחרים. yitma le-tamei
acherim. So the loaf of bread that falls in the כלי חרס
keli cheres is טמא tamei to make other things טמא tamei to
make other things into a שלישי. shlishi. That it sounds like רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying based on that פסוק pasuk that a
שני sheni is עושה שלישי oseh shlishi even by חולין. chulin. But
until now the לימוד limud has only been by תרומה terumah and
now the גמרא Gemara is reinforcing that and saying I'm going to
give you a whole list of תנאים Tannaim that hold the whole
idea of שלישי shlishi. is limited to a case of תרומה. terumah.
Okay now we're going to go through them. רבי מאיר דתנן Rabbi
Meir detnan רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because we taught in the
משנה. Mishnah. כל הטעון ביאת מים מדברי סופרים Kol hataun bi-at mayim
midivrei soferim anything that has to go into the מקוה mikvah מדרבנן.
miderabbanan. What has to go into the מקוה mikvah מדרבנן? miderabbanan? The
best example about that or coming into water מדרבנן miderabbanan is your
hands. Your hands are considered and the reason you wash your hands
before you eat bread is because they would wash their hands before
they ate תרומה terumah because hands דרבנן derabbanan because you don't know
what they're touching or whatever דרבנן derabbanan just gave them a default
status as a שני לטומאה. sheni le-tuma. Now of course דאורייתא de-oraita
that's impossible because you can't have part of your body טמא tamei
and not the other but דרבנן. derabbanan. that's דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So because
שני sheni can't handle תרומה, terumah, they could handle bread. Classic תרומה
terumah was of course grain and bread, etcetera, and that ultimately led
to the practice that even non-כהנים kohanim wash before they eat bread.
Okay, so that's a classic example. There are other cases as well
that somebody is טמא מדרבנן. tamei mid'rabbanan. But anybody who's טמא מדרבנן,
tamei mid'rabbanan, the טומאה tumah that דרבנן d'rabbanan assigned people when it
was a pure, meaning it wasn't a derivation of a דאורייתא d'oraita
טומאה. tumah. It was some totally independent thing that they said it
makes you טמא, tamei, like I don't know, handling ספרי קודש Sifrei
Kodesh or other types of things, okay, they made you into a
שני. sheni So כל הטמא מדברי סופרים, kol hatomei midivrei sofrim, so
you're a שני, sheni. מטמא את הקודש, metamei et hakodesh, if you
touch קודש kodesh you make it טמא, tamei, ופסול את התרומה, upasul
et haterumah, and you make תרומה terumah פסול. pasul. The difference between
פסול pasul
and מטמא metamei again is that מטמא metamei means it can go
on one level. So if you touch קודש kodesh you made it
a שלישי shlishi and that can make קודש kodesh into a רביעי.
revii. Like because קודש kodesh goes up to רביעי. revii. If you
touch, me and another קודש? kodesh? Another קודש kodesh into a רביעי.
revii. That's מטמא את הקודש. metamei et hakodesh. If you touch תרומה
terumah right, then it invalidates the תרומה terumah but it does not
pass it on.
Yeah but the תרומה terumah touched קודש?
kodesh? That's true, the תרומה terumah could touch קודש. kodesh. Yes, but
within the world of תרומה terumah it's פסול את התרומה, posel et
haterumah, it doesn't go on. Okay, so פסול את התרומה. posel et
haterumah. So your שני sheni, made a שלישי. shlishi ומותר בחולין ובמעשר.
umutar bechulin ube-ma'aser. But you can handle חולין chulin and מעשר. ma'aser.
So you're a שני, sheni you can handle חולין. chulin. חולין chulin
does not get affected. So that's clear that שני sheni, is not
עושה שלישי בחולין. oseh shlishi bechulin. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir.
One minute, וחכמים עושים במעשר. vachachamim osim be-ma'aser. And the חכמים chachamim
say not by מעשר, ma'aser, okay, what's exactly the debate about מעשר
ma'aser we won't discuss although it's interesting unless it's מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni it's not.
מעשר ma'aser is not really קודש.
kodesh. Right.
So, they're treating it like קודש. kodesh.
They're treating it at least for these טומאה tumah purposes. At least
for these דרבנן d'rabbanan purposes. Okay,
no, I mean it's not, I don't think it is, I think
it has some other reasons. But anyway, okay, so there you go
that both רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים. chachamim. רש"י Rashi
said it could have said רבי מאיר וחכמים, Rabbi Meir vechachamim, but
we don't know who the חכמים chachamim are. They both are very
clear that שני sheni does not make a שלישי shlishi. בחולין. bechulin.
It only makes it by תרומה terumah and מעשר ma'aser is debated.
Okay, so that's that position, that it doesn't go by חולין. chulin.
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, now how about רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yose? הא
דאמרן, ha d'amaran, that's the whole derivation we had right before of
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose that he learned out that you get a
רביעי revii בקודש, bekodesh, you learn it out from מחוסר כיפורים. mechussar
kippurim. Now how did that tell you that he doesn't hold that
there's a שלישי shlishi בחולין? bechulin? Because of what he didn't say.
דאם איתא, de-im ita, if he held as an idea of a
שלישי shlishi בחולין, bechulin, ליתי לרביעי בתרומה וחמישי בקודש. leisei lerevii biterumah
vachamishi bekodesh. Then if חולין chulin itself could have gone up to
a שלישי, shlishi
then תרומה terumah should have been able to go up to a
רביעי revii and קודש kodesh should have been able to go up
to a חמישי. chamishi. Okay, because the whole way we sort of
learned it out was, just to remind you, we learned it out
that if a טבול יום tvul yom makes תרומה terumah טמא, tamei,
and a טבול יום tvul yom is מותר בחולין. mutar bechulin. So
something that is חולין chulin טמא tamei should certainly be able to
make תרומה terumah טמא. tamei. Okay, that was the לימוד. limud. Now,
what is the lowest level of חולין chulin that could be טמא?
tamei? We've been assuming שני. sheni So therefore that can make תרומה
terumah to a שלישי. shlishi, But if חולין chulin could be a
שלישי, shlishi. then it should have been oh, so טבול יום tvul
yom who's מותר בחולין mutar bechulin can make תרומה terumah טמא, tamei,
so חולין chulin טמא tamei as a שלישי shlishi, should be able
to make תרומה terumah טמא tamei as a רביעי revii and then
you should be able to take it one further level for קודש.
kodesh. So since we didn't do that, clearly he holds that חולין
chulin is only a שני sheni. and it's only תרומה terumah that
gets to be a שלישי.
shlishi The more קודש kodesh an object is, the more susceptible it
is.
There it is.
And the more it can attract even weaker and weaker forms of...
There you go. It's like... It's like... It's like צדיקים הקדוש ברוך
הוא מדקדק עליהם כחוט השערה.
tzaddikim hakadosh
baruch hu medakdek aleihem kechut hasa'arah.
They're more susceptible
or the... Or that's why, you know, they had to with the
whole יהודה ותמר Yehuda and Tamar story you had to distract the...
the שטן Satan so he's always trying to anyway interfere with anyway,
moving on. Okay, so... We can bring we could do a lot
of מדרשי midrashic קבלי kabbalistic stuff on that point but yes it's
a very legitimate point. The more קודש kodesh it is, the more
it attracts the forces of כוחות הטומאה. kochos hatumah. Okay anyway so
or the more the even the very residual כוחות הטומאה kochos hatumah
are able to adhere to it. Right, that is our קבלה Kabbalah
for the day. Moving on, רבי אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Elazar omer, okay...
No one will believe this קבלה. Kabbalah.
No one will believe it, you know, guy goes into his
friend who's this very esteemed scientist and he sees up on his
wall he's got the the... what's the... the חמסה? Chamsah? You know
the חמסה... Chamsah... חמסה... Chamsa... חמסה... Chamsah... חמסה. Chamsa. So he says
to him, I don't understand, like, you know, a super rationalist like
you, I mean, you think this stuff is נארישקייט, narishkeit, what are
you doing with it up on your wall? He says, says, yeah
yeah yeah I know it's נארישקייט narishkeit but I've heard even if
you don't believe it it sometimes works. All right, anyway so the
גמרא gemara says... Okay, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose הא דאמרן, ha
d'amaran, רבי אלעזר... Rabbi Elazar... We needed a break there. רבי יהושע
*Rabbi Yehoshua*, רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*, תנן *tnan*. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi
Eliezer omer, *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, האוכל אוכל ראשון rishon, *ha-ochel ochel rishon*,
ראשון rishon. *rishon*. If somebody eats food that's a ראשון rishon. *rishon*,
you become a ראשון rishon, *rishon*. שני sheni *sheni*, שני sheini *sheni*.
If you eat food, you are what you eat. If you eat
שני sheini *sheni*, you become a שני sheini, *sheni*. שלישי shlishi. *shlishi*,
שלישי shlishi, *shlishi*. Now תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says one of the reasons
for this is, I mean there's a whole long תוספות *Tosafos* where
he figures out what this is about. He says there was actually
two levels of a גזירה *gezeirah*. One גזירה *gezeirah* is if you
eat it, the first level of the גזירה *gezeirah* is if you
eat something, then like if you let's say eat food that's a
שני sheni. *sheni*, you can't drink תרומה Terumah, *terumah* or eat תרומה
Terumah *terumah*. Why? Because it'll look to people, like people will say,
I don't understand, that תרומה Terumah *terumah* is going down your throat
and it's going into your stomach which has that שני sheni *sheni*
in it and it's being מטמא *metamei* in your stomach. So therefore,
some tell you, therefore the initial גזירה *gezeirah* was if you eat
something like let's say a שני sheni, *sheni*, you can't then eat
תרומה Terumah, *terumah*. You can't eat מעשר שני sheni *Maaser Sheni* with
מעשר שני sheni, *Maaser Sheni* in your stomach? What can I tell
you? That was about something about how people would perceive it. The
next level was not just that you can't, the next, that's what
this big תוספות *Tosafos* is about. You should be happy that we
have a big תוספות *Tosafos*, I'm summarizing it for you in ten
seconds and therefore the דף *daf* is shorter. So the next point
that the תוספות *Tosafos* makes though is that second level of the
גזירה *gezeirah* was that after you eat it, then actually you are
treated like that level even if you just touch something. And the
reason? I don't know exactly sure. So anyway, if you eat ראשון
rishon, *rishon* you're a ראשון *rishon*, a שני *sheni* you're a שני
*sheni*, a שלישי shlishi, *shlishi* you're a שלישי shlishi? *shlishi*. Okay. רבי
יהושע אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua omer*, האוכל אוכל ראשון ואוכל שני שני *ha-ochel
ochel rishon ve-ochel sheni sheni*. No no no. They never made a
guy into a ראשון *rishon* by eating non-קודש Kodesh, *kodesh*, by eating
food that's טמא tamei. *tamei*. To be a ראשון *rishon* you've got
to touch an אב הטומאה *av ha-tumah*. So שני *sheni* is our
first level of טומאה tumah *tumah* for טומאה tumah דרבנן *tumah de-rabbanan*.
So if you ate a ראשון *rishon* or a שני *sheni* you
become a שני *sheni*. שלישי shlishi. *shlishi*, if you ate שלישי shlishi.
*shlishi* then you become שני בקודש baKodesh. ואין שני בתרומה *sheni be-kodesh
ve-ein sheni be-terumah*. בתרומה *be-terumah*, then you become a שני *sheni* for
purposes of touching קודש Kodesh *kodesh*. So if you were to touch
קודש *kodesh* you'd make it into a שלישי shlishi. *shlishi* and then
that would make other קודש *kodesh* into a רביעי revi'i *revii*, but
it would not be treated as a שני *sheni* for touching תרומה
terumah. *terumah*. Okay, so, now, now what type of stuff did you
eat that when you ate a שלישי shlishi. *shlishi*, what food did
you eat that was a שלישי shlishi. *shlishi*? So it says: בחולין
b'chullin. שנעשו על טהרת התרומה *be-chulin she-naasu al taharas ha-terumah*. Or if
you ate חולין Chullin, *chulin* that was treated as תרומה terumah *terumah*,
that could be a שלישי shlishi *shlishi*. So here's another הלכה halacha
*halacha*. The same way תרומה terumah *terumah* can be a שלישי shlishi.
*shlishi*, if somebody is a כהן kohein *kohen* and has a lot
of תרומה terumah *terumah* in their house and they're going to be
very מקפיד *makpid* and they're going to say, we're not going to
start having different standards for when we eat תרומה terumah *terumah* and
when we eat non-תרומה terumah. *terumah*. You know there's always תרומה terumah,
*terumah* around. It's sort of like a week before פסח *Pesach* in
my house you can't have any חמץ *chametz* in the house starting
a week before פסח *Pesach*. You know whatever, I'm not treating תרומה
terumah. *terumah* and non-תרומה terumah. *terumah* differently. Every dairy equipment? Everybody treats
everything as תרומה terumah. *terumah*. Okay so your practice is to treat
חולין Chullin *chulin* as if it's תרומה terumah *terumah* and to
eat it with the same degree of care.
So that's חולין Chullin שנעשו על טהרת התרומה *chulin she-naasu al taharas
ha-terumah*. So the הלכה halacha *halacha* is, sort of like before we
said you are what you eat, so this is also like a
self-fulfilling prophecy. If you treat the חולין chullin? *chulin* like תרומה terumah.
*terumah*, then הלכתית *halachically* דרבנן *de-rabbanan*, we let it get the same
level of טומאה tumah *tumah* as תרומה terumah *terumah*. So if you
have a שני *sheni* that touches normal חולין chullin. *chulin*, nothing. But
if you have a שני *sheni* that touches חולין chullin. *chulin* that
you are treating as תרומה terumah *terumah*, that becomes a שלישי shlishi.
*shlishi*. Okay. Can I ask you just a quick question? Yes. The
כהן kohein *kohen*, do they have like different כלים *keilim* for תרומה
*terumah* and חולין chullin *chulin*? They might have depending on if they
have guests or other types of things. I completely understand. Yeah they
definitely did, no kidding. I never thought about that, oh don't use
that bowl, that's a תרומה *terumah* bowl. And you can't, you can't,
it's better if you have non-כהן kohein *kohen* guests. Yeah, פרווה *parve*
for תרומה *terumah*. But did they have issues of בליעה *bliah* and
פליטה *plitah*? Yeah, for sure. The full kitchen? Wow, the whole כשרות
*kashrus* for תרומה *terumah*. Apparently, yep. Okay, so, completely in 6 T.E.
תרומה *terumah* pudding. Yeah, very holy. Then you need חולין chullin *chulin*
and תרומה *terumah* for קודש *kodesh*, then you need חולין chullin, *chulin*
and תרומה *terumah* for קודש *kodesh* and well no, because meat and
dairy would not be תרומה *terumah*. תרומה *terumah* would only be פרווה
*parve* of grain stuff, so meat and dairy anyway. I mean I
guess if you mixed it up in the other stuff. I guess
if you used turquoise plates. Alright, moving up, moving up. Alright, בחולין
שנעשו על טהרת התרומה *be-chulin she-naasu al taharas ha-terumah*. So that's the
type of stuff that can be a שלישי shlishi *shlishi* that if
you eat it would make you a שני *sheni* for קודש *kodesh*.
Anyway, the point being that what can become a שלישי shlishi. *shlishi*?
תרומה *terumah* or חולין chullin *chulin* that was treated as תרומה *terumah*
as על טהרת התרומה *al taharas ha-terumah*. אין *in*, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, על טהרת התרומה אין *al taharas ha-terumah in*, only
if it was treated על טהרת התרומה *al taharas ha-terumah* does it
become a שלישי shlishi. *shlishi*. על טהרת הקודש לא lo *al taharas
ha-kodesh lo*, not if it was treated על טהרת הקודש *al taharas
ha-kodesh*. Now רש"י Rashi. *Rashi*'s גרסא *girsa* is, it should be, רש"י
Rashi *Rashi*'s גרסא *girsa* is חולין chullin לא lo *chulin lo*, which
is the simpler point. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*'s point is also it's like
if you tried to treat חולין chullin. *chulin* as קודש *kodesh* that's
too absurd, so it's meaningless. So it's like just standard חולין chullin.
*chulin*. Either way, אלמא קסבר אין שני עושה שלישי בחולין ein sheni
oseh shlishi b'chullin *alma kasavar ein sheni oseh shlishi be-chulin*. The only
way חולין chullin *chulin* becomes a שלישי shlishi *shlishi* is if it's
תרומה *terumah* or treated as תרומה *terumah*. Standard חולין chullin. *chulin* does
not become a שלישי shlishi. *shlishi*. So that is רבי יהושע *Rabbi
Yehoshua*. Now Rabbi Elazar, דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא. baraita. רבי
אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Elazar Omer, שלושתן שוין. shloshtan shavin. The following three
things are all the same. הראשון שבקודש Harishon shebaKodesh ושבחולין v'shebaChullin ושבתרומה.
v'shebaTerumah. If you have something, whether it's קודש, חולין, chullin or תרומה,
and it's a ראשון, מטמא שנים, metamei shnayim, it goes down two
levels, שני שלישי, shlishi, ופוסל אחד uposel echad בקודש.
baKodesh So it goes all the way to a רביעי revi'i.
בקודש and then it stops. That's why the word is פוסל, posel,
because it stops at רביעי. revi'i. מטמא אחד ופוסל אחד בתרומה. metamei
echad uposel echad baTerumah. If you're in a תרומה world, it goes
down two levels. It makes a שני and then a שלישי, shlishi
and then it stops. ופוסל אחד בחולין. uposel echad baChullin. And if
you're in a חולין chullin. world, it only goes down to a
שני and then it stops. Okay, so it's a very nice way
of saying it, that basically by חולין chullin it ends at a
שני, תרומה ends at a שלישי, shlishi and קודש ends at a
רביעי. That's Rabbi Elazar. רבי אליעזר דתנן. Rabbi Eliezer d'tnan. רבי אליעזר
אומר, חלה ניטלת מן הטהורה על הטמאה. challah nitelet min hatahorah al
hatameiah. חלה challah can be taken now. What happens if you have
חלה טמאה? challah t'meiah? Right? Then the dough is טמא. tamei. When
you're מפריש mafrish the חלה, challah, חלה challah is like תרומה, it
becomes תרומה טמאה. Terumah t'meiah. The כהן can't eat it. He can
only burn it, use it as fuel. So obviously it's not good
for the כהן to have it to be טמא. tamei, So you're
supposed to be careful about that. Now if you accidentally got your
dough טמא, tamei you can go ahead and be מפריש חלה טמאה
mafrish challah t'meiah on your טמא tamei, dough. But Rabbi Eliezer says
that no, basically what we're going to do is we're going to
fine you and we're going to say that even if let me
just double-check רש"י. Rashi No, I'm sorry. If you did it במזיד,
b'meizid, if you did it במזיד, b'meizid, not if you did it
by accident. But if you were מזיד meizid in getting your dough
טמא, tamei, like you knew, yeah, your hands are טמא, tamei, don't
handle it, I don't care, I'm going to handle it, whatever, you
got your dough טמא, tamei then we're going to demand that you
actually be מפריש טהור mafrish tahor dough on your טמא tamei. dough.
So that the חלה challah you give the כהן will actually be
טהור חלה. tahor challah. Because if you have these two pieces of
dough, right? So rather than taking a חלה challah from this and
a חלה challah from this, you can actually put them all together
and take one חלה challah equal to the amount of חלה challah
you're supposed to give is one twenty-fourth, like four percent. Okay, so
you can take that, you take that. So if you have two
loaves of bread, just take the, and this is like I don't
know, ten units and this is ten units, you would take what
did I say four percent? This is a hundred units and this
is a hundred units, so you would take like eight units from
the טהור tahor to go on both the טהור tahor and the
טמאה. tameiah. That's what you would do if you were irresponsible and
got one of the doughs טמא. tamei So that's all great, except
that there's a problem. The problem is that when you take חלה,
challah, the loaves should all be connected, the dough should all be
connected. Now if you try to touch this טמא tamei. dough to
this טהור tahor dough, you've got a little bit of a problem,
which is you're going to make it טמא. tamei, Okay? So how
can we demand that you take the quantity of טהור tahor dough
on both doughs and have the doughs connected? Can't even have the
same table surface? Not at least לכתחילה, l'chatchila, okay? לכתחילה l'chatchila it
should all be somehow touching. I mean there's questions בדיעבד, b'diavad, other
types of things, in the same basket, but now we're assuming that
they should be touching. So what we're going to do is we're
going to take some טהור tahor dough, okay? I'll take a little
dough from this, I always use my cup and then I spill
it. I'm going to take a little, this is my piece of
gum. I'm going to take a little piece of dough from this
big big loaf here, and what I'm going to do is this
dough is going to be a small amount, it's going to be
less than a כביצה. k'beitzah. Now the power of being less than
a כביצה k'beitzah is that less than a כביצה, k'beitzah, even though
it will become טמא, tamei it won't pass the טומאה tumah on.
Okay? So what I'm going to do is I'm going to put
this little less than a כביצה k'beitzah between the two loaves of
bread. So it's going to make it one big loaf, A is
touching B is touching C, but the A טמא tamei. touching B,
the less than a כביצה, k'beitzah, will not be able to pass
the טומאה tumah. on to C. So it's all one big thing
and everything is connected and now I'm going to take the חלה
challah from the טהור tahor dough. Okay? You have a question? All
right. Okay. So כיצד, keitzad, חלה ניטלת מן הטהורה על הטמאה. challah
nitelet min hatahorah al hatameiah. כיצד, keitzad, what do you do? שתי
עיסות אחת טהורה ואחת טמאה, shtei isos achas tehorah v'achas t'meiah, one
is טהור tahor and one is טמא. tamei? נוטל כדי חלה מעיסה
שלא הורמה חלתה, notel k'dei challah m'isah shelo hurmah challatah, so you're
going to take the quantity of the חלה challah from the bread
that has not had חלה challah taken. Once you have חלה challah
taken from dough, you cannot take it again. So both have to
have חלה challah that has not been taken from them. And this
really should have been beforehand: ונותן פחות מכביצה באמצע, v'noten pachos mikbeitzah
ba'emtza, less than a כביצה k'beitzah dough between the two loaves of
bread of the quantities of dough, כדי ליטול מן המוקף, k'dei litol
min hamukaf, that it should all be considered like connected. Okay? So
that's what he says. Now וחכמים אוסרין, v'Chachamim osrin, and the חכמים
Chachamim forbid. Now why they forbid? Presumably they're concerned that the טומאה
tumah will pass off. Okay? ודתניא, udtanya, now another ברייתא baraita says
כביצה, k'beitzah, that Rabbi Eliezer even allowed it to be done by
a כביצה. k'beitzah. So let's bracket the פחות מכביצה. pachos mikbeitzah. idea
which is not as interesting because if it's less than a כביצה
k'beitzah it's not going to pass it on. It doesn't tell us
anything about the levels of טומאה and let's focus on the ברייתא
beraita that has that Rabbi Eliezer even allows it by a כביצה.
k'beitzah. So how does he allow it by כביצה? k'beitzah? Why doesn't
it go from here to here to there? Right, that's the question.
How does he allow it by כביצה? k'beitzah? So let's take a
look. סברו savru we assumed אידי ואידי באיסור ראשונה idi v'idi b'isur
rishonah that the tamei loaf is a ראשון. Okay and we also
assumed חולין הטבולים לחלה לא כחלה דמו chullin ha'tevulim l'challah lo k'challah
damu and we assumed that now the חלה challah itself is going
to be תרומה. What is the status of the dough pre the
removal of the חלה? challah? Is it like... it's טבל. tevel. Is
it... so what's its status in terms of קבלת טומאה? kabbalas tumah?
Basically is טבל... tevel... does it... is it מקבל טומאה mekabel tumah
like תרומה because it has potential תרומה here or unactualized תרומה here?
Or right now there's no תרומה and it's treated like חולין? chullin
Does טבל tevel become a שלישי? shlishi. That's the question. So we're
assuming that טבל tevel is treated like תרומה. Okay, חולין הטבולים לחלה...
chullin ha'tevulim l'challah... I'm sorry, it's not treated like חולין. chullin Excuse
me, it's not. לא כחלה דמו... lo k'challah damu... it is not
treated like חלה, challah, it's treated like חולין. So now this loaf
is a ראשון. If it has a כביצה k'beitzah of bread, the
כביצה k'beitzah of dough in the middle becomes a שני. And that
שני doesn't pass it on to the other loaf... to the other
quantity of dough because it can't make it into a שלישי. shlishi.
So you see that he says that a חולין does not become
a שלישי. shlishi. And the reason the חכמים Chachamim would argue would
be presumably because the חכמים Chachamim would say that חולין does become
a שלישי. Okay, you got it? So you got big dough one,
כביצה k'beitzah in the middle, big dough two. So it's ראשון, שני,
שלישי. And if everything is treated like a חולין, he says you
don't have to worry about that because חולין doesn't become a שלישי.
Or the table can become... no, it's... but he does not. Rabbi
Eliezer says you don't have to worry about it, you could use
a כביצה k'beitzah in between. The חכמים Chachamim say you can't. So
the question is, what's the חכמים's Chachamim logic? Okay, so מאי לאו
בהא קמיפלגי. mai lav b'ha kamipelgi. This must be what they debate.
מר סבר Mar savar אין שני עושה שלישי בחולין sheni oseh shlishi
b'chullin. that the שני does not make a שלישי בחולין. So that's
what Rabbi Eliezer holds, the third loaf is safe. Okay. ומר סבר
U'mar savar and the חכמים Chachamim hold שני עושה שלישי בחולין. So
it's not safe, it goes on to a שלישי. But at least
Rabbi Eliezer holds that חולין doesn't become a שלישי. So now the
point is, you know what? Maybe the חכמים Chachamim agree with that.
אמר רב מרי בריה דרב כהנא Amar Rav Mari brei d'Rav Kahana
דכולי עלמא אין שני עושה שלישי בחולין. d'chulei alma ein sheni oseh
shlishi b'chullin. Heck, we've already listed so many תנאים Tannaim that hold
there's no שלישי by חולין. I'll say even the חכמים Chachamim agree
with it. So what's their problem? Why are they concerned here with
having the כביצה k'beitzah of bread in between? והכא בחולין הטבולים לחלה
קמיפלגי v'hacha b'chullin ha'tevulim l'challah kamipelgi what Charlie said. Because it's not
so פשוט pashut that we treat this as חולין. It's חולין that
has unactualized חלה challah in it. מר סבר כחלה דמו Mar savar
k'challah damu the חכמים Chachamim say it's like חלה, challah, it's like
תרומה, so it does become a שלישי. So you can't do this
trick of sticking... of having like three loaves of bread here. ומר
סבר לא כחלה דמו. U'mar savar lo k'challah damu. No, it's like
חולין. So everybody agrees it's ראשון, שני, שלישי. And the question does
the third one become a שלישי depends on whether we treat it
as חולין or as תרומה. ואיבעית אימא V'iba'is eima if you want
I could say דכולי עלמא חולין הטבולים לחלה לא כחלה דמו. d'chulei
alma chullin ha'tevulim l'challah lo k'challah damu. Number one, everybody says it's
like חולין. Number two, ואין שני עושה שלישי בחולין. v'ein sheni oseh
shlishi b'chullin. Everybody agrees it can't become a שלישי. So if everybody
agrees it's חולין and it can't become a שלישי, why do the
חכמים Chachamim have a hard time about doing this thing about putting
this כביצה k'beitzah of dough between them? והכא במותר לגרום טומאה לחולין
שבחוצה לארץ קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'mutar ligrom tumah l'chullin she'b'chutz la'aretz kamipelgi. Are
you allowed to make חולין טמא? tamei. Because at least what you're
doing is you're making this כביצה k'beitzah of dough in the middle
טמא. And the חכמים Chachamim might be saying, it's a nice idea
that you're going to get it all connected and you'll take חלה
challah on both, but as a result of that you're spreading טומאה.
You're spreading טומאה to this כביצה k'beitzah of dough in the middle.
ומר סבר אסור לגרום טומאה לחולין שבחוצה לארץ. U'mar savar asur ligrom
tumah l'chullin she'b'chutz la'aretz. So one says, yeah I will allow it,
certainly for the purpose of being able to be מפריש חלה טהורה
mafrish challah tehorah on everything combined. And the other says no, I'm
sorry, I will not allow it. So there could be a lot
of things that that's about, but certainly the... one of the things
that emerges is that you... שלישי ends at תרומה. So pretty much
almost everybody holds a שלישי ends at תרומה. But again, רש"י Rashi
says in the משנה Mishna it sounds like Rabbi Eliezer would say...
I mean... I mean excuse me, only תרומה can be a שלישי.
But as... but as רש"י pointed out, it sounds from the משנה
Mishna that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who learns from a פסוק pasuk
of יטמא לטמא אחרים yitma l'tamei acherim and there's nothing in that
פסוק pasuk indicating תרומה. It sounds that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would
actually say based on the פסוק pasuk that even חולין can become
a שלישי. But everybody clearly the... consensus is that only תרומה becomes
a שלישי. All right, now we can take a breath. We are
now done with that. That was a very... that was probably the
most technically difficult גמרא Gemara. that we're going to be dealing with
in the whole מסכת. Masechet. Yes. You should be glad I didn't
leave one day earlier. You are getting such easy גמרא. Gemara You
are going to be so glad I did not leave a day
earlier. Yeah, yes, exactly. And the analogous discussion about any any wheat
that you haven't taken תרומה from. Okay. And right? Okay. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בו ביום דרש רבי
עקיבא. Bo bayom darash Rabbi Akiva. So this the second... the third
דרשה drasha about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was the פסוקים pesukim about
the ערי הלויים arei ha-Leviyim say they have a thousand אמה ammah
around their cities and then another פסוק pasuk says two thousand. So
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said a thousand for their for their like...
whatever, their fields or their yards, and two thousand is the city
limits and so there we learn the idea that a תחום tchum
is two thousand אמה. ammah. And the other opinion in the משנה
mishna was no, a thousand of sort of like of unused space
and then two thousand for their vineyards and their fields. So the
גמרא Gemara asks... The opposite basically? Well, I don't know the opposite,
well I don't know if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva had the fields
in the thousand, he might have just had more like yards. But
anyway, the גמרא Gemara says במאי קמיפלגי? be-mai kamifligi? What's the debate?
מר סבר תחומין דאורייתא ומר סבר דרבנן. mar savar tchumin de-oraita u-mar
savar de-rabbanan. So if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns the idea of
two thousand אמה ammah city limits from the from these פסוקים, pesukim,
presumably what's the point? Why do I care that there's two thousand
אמה ammah city limits? Presumably it's relevant for a הלכה halacha that
you're not allowed to leave city limits on שבת Shabbat and that
there's an idea that תחומין tchumin is a דאורייתא de-oraita concept of
two thousand אמה. ammah. And the other who doesn't say that that's
what's going on in the פסוק, pasuk, it's just talking about the
where their fields and vineyards, does not have that as a basis
for the idea of תחומין דאורייתא. tchumin de-oraita. Now תוספות points out,
you know, huh? Like first of all, maybe I maybe even though
I think that the פסוק pasuk is talking about the לויים Leviyim
having fields and vineyards, maybe I can still use it as a
basis to teach me a different הלכה as well, that there is
an idea of תחומין דאורייתא. tchumin de-oraita. Or maybe I can learn
out תחומין דאורייתא tchumin de-oraita from another פסוק. pasuk. Like it's not
so clear that this is that that they have to fall into
these two camps. But at least what it does tell you minimally
is that presumably that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying. Because
for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, if it's not giving the area to
the לויים, Leviyim, what's the נפקא מינה nafka mina of saying that
it's two thousand אמה ammah is their city limit? So at least
for him, presumably it's telling you a הלכה about הלכות שבת. hilchot
Shabbat. But it's not but the other one who disagrees could learn
out the idea of תחומין דאורייתא tchumin de-oraita from another place. Although
one could have argued that there's another relevance about knowing what the
city limits are for the ערי הלויים arei ha-Leviyim other than הלכות
שבת. hilchot Shabbat. What could the other relevance be? Any thoughts? And
even if they don't get any of the real estate of the
two thousand אמה, ammah, but just to tell say that that's defined
as a city limit. How do the ערי... what? Thank you. The
ערי לויים function as ערי מקלט. arei miklat. Right? When are you
considered to be in the עיר מקלט? ir miklat? Right? So it
is interesting that the גמרא Gemara. decides to make this a debate
about whether תחומין tchumin is דאורייתא de-oraita or not. Okay, let's continue.
תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: בו ביום דרש רבי עקיבא. Bo bayom darash
Rabbi Akiva. Now we have the fun דרשה drasha which was about
the... the אז ישיר משה. Az yashir Moshe. Right? That רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva said it was like reading... like somebody who read the
הלל. Hallel. Says it לאמר. lemor. What does it mean he said
to say? It sounded like it was responsive. So he said that
that he said it and they responded. And what's his name responded
back, who was it? So it says כקורא את ההלל ke-korei et
ha-Hallel and רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia says כקורין את שמע ke-korin et
Shema and לא כקורא את ההלל. lo ke-korei et ha-Hallel. So let's
see what that's about. תנו רבנן: tanu rabbanan: בו ביום דרש רבי
עקיבא, Bo bayom darash Rabbi Akiva, בשעה שעלו ישראל מן הים, be-sha'ah
she-alu Yisrael min ha-yam, when they came up from the sea, נתנו
עיניהם לומר שירה, natnu eineihem lomar shirah, they gave their eyes meaning
they they planned to say שירה. shirah. וכיצד אמרו שירה? ve-keitzad amru
shirah? How did they say שירה? shirah? Because you know they didn't
necessarily all have the ability to say it, who was going to
be able to compose a שירה shirah on the spot? So כגדול
המקרא את ההלל. ke-gadol ha-makrei et ha-Hallel. Like when an adult reads
the הלל Hallel for the ציבור. tzibbur. Right, again also imagine that
you would often have a very illiterate congregation which is why you
have the whole institution of שליח ציבור shaliach tzibbur and חזרת הש"ץ
chazarat ha-Shatz because people were mostly illiterate. So how would you read
the הלל? Hallel? So the way if you have an adult reading
the הלל, Hallel, here's what you would do. והן עונין אחריו ראשי
פרקים. ve-hen onin acharayiv rashei prakim. The people wouldn't know all of
the text. They would just say the beginning of each section. משה
אמר אשירה לה'. Moshe amar ashirah la-Shem. והן אומרים אשירה לה'. ve-hen
omrim ashirah la-Shem. משה אומר כי גאה גאה. Moshe omer ki ga'oh
ga'ah. והן אומרים כי גאה גאה. ve-hen omrim ki ga'oh ga'ah. והן
אומרים אשירה לה'. ve-hen omrim ashirah la-Shem. So everything משה Moshe would
say their response would be the same two words, אשירה לה', ashirah
la-Shem, which actually is a beautiful way of responding, right? It's like...
it's like what we do הודו לה' כי טוב, Hodu la-Shem ki
tov, הודו לה' כי טוב. Hodu la-Shem ki tov. Right? It's actually
a very appropriate type of way of responding. It's not like, you
know, but but it's the אשירה לה', ashirah la-Shem, הודו לה' כי
טוב Hodu la-Shem ki tov and that's the אמן Amen essentially, the
way that you participate and you're responsive for the שליח ציבור shaliach
tzibbur who knows all the words. Okay, so that's what משה Moshe
would... that's how they would do it. That's the לאמר. lemor. רבי
אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר: Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi
Yossi ha-Gelili omer: No, כקטן המקרא את ההלל. ke-katan ha-makrei et ha-Hallel.
Not like an adult who's מוציא motzi that... and essentially they just
have to say אמן. Amen. I make a ברכה, bracha, you say
אמן, Amen, you're יוצא, yotzei, but if a minor is saying a
ברכה bracha for me, I can't just say אמן, Amen, you don't
say שומע כעונה, Shome'a K'oneh, he's not able to discharge me and
all I have to do is participate. I actually have to say
the text myself. So if the minor knows the text and I
don't, it's not enough for me to say אמן, Amen, I have
to do repeat after me. I have to say all those words
myself. Okay, so if you have a minor who's the one reading
הלל Hallel for the ציבור, tzibbur, they have to repeat every single
word. They repeat after him every word he said. משה Moshe said
אשירה להשם Ashira LaShem and they say אשירה להשם. Ashira LaShem. משה
Moshe said כי גאה גאה ki ga'oh ga'ah and they say כי
גאה גאה. ki ga'oh ga'ah. So every single word משה Moshe said,
they repeated, which can also explain how they learned how they knew
what to say, because they just repeat after me, everyone. Okay, so
if they had a קטן katan lead הלל Hallel in the past?
Yeah, I mean you have a משנה. Mishna. If you're not supposed
to, it says תבוא מארה tavo me'eirah etc., but sometimes that was
the only literate person in the community or who could do it.
We were assuming that the leader had text in front... okay, so
maybe I should... maybe literate is the wrong word, you know, I
don't necessarily mean reading a written text, but somebody... what is the
word, fluent, I don't know, but somebody who was conversant, exactly, you
know. Okay, weren't you supposed to read מקרא mikra from text rather
than memorize? Yeah, not in a תפילה tefillah context. I think you
don't have to say הלל Hallel as מקריא את ההלל. makri et
ha-hallel. Yeah, but you have to have מקרא קריאת שמע. mikra kriat
shema. Did they? Yeah, I learned it from Rabbi Bergman. Rabbi Bergman
years ago, a שיעור, shiur, said the פשט peshat of קריאת שמע
Kriat Shema was they opened the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and they
read the קריאה. Kria. Really? Yeah, that's what he said. What's the
evidence for it? Thirty years ago. Okay, fine. Alright, so it's a
הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai, you have a מסורה masorah thirty
years already. I'm still thinking about that turtle. Okay, fine. Alright. רבי
נחמיה אומר: Rabbi Nechemiah omer: כסופר הפורס על שמע בבית הכנסת. k'sofer
haporeis al shema b'veit haknesset. Like when a סופר, sofer, the interesting
phrase here is פורס, poreis, right, whole discussion what that word means,
but anyway. So, רש"י says it means like פרוס החג pros-hachag is
the period before יום טוב, Yom Tov, it means when you begin
the שמע Shema starting from the ברכות. brachot. There's a lot of
discussion what פורס על שמע poreis al shema means, but anyway, it's
like when they would read שמע Shema in the שול. shul. How
would that be different? שהוא פותח תחילה והן עונין אחריו. she-hu potei'ach
techila v'hein onin acharav. So actually it would not be responsive, it
wouldn't even be responsive word for word. It's somebody would start, it's
sort of like we דאוון. daven. The guy says שמע Shema and
then all of a sudden everybody knows what to say. So the
person opens it but then everybody is saying it in unison. So
is it that they do a responsive of a single text of
a single responsive reading? Do they respond word for word or do
they all sort of say it in unison? Okay, so במאי קמיפלגי,
be-mai kamiflagi, what do they debate about? רבי עקיבא סבר לאמר אמילתא
קמייתא. Rabbi Akiva savar lemor a-milta kamaitha. Rabbi Akiva says לאמר lemor
means that you respond based on the opening word. So they are
constantly going to respond like, you know, it's... ויאמרו לאמר אשירה להשם
כי גאה גאה. vayomru lemor ashira laShem ki ga'oh ga'ah. So Rabbi
Akiva says that's the לאמר, lemor, אשירה להשם, Ashira LaShem, just those
two words. That's what they responded on those first words. אמילתא קמייתא.
a-milta kamaitha. Where are we? רבי אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי
סבר לאמר אכל מילתא ומילתא. Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGelili
savar lemor a-kol milta u-milta. No, לאמר lemor means for the entire
text they were responsive, every word משה Moshe said they responded. ורבנן
סברי ויאמרו דאמר כולהו. v'rabbanan savri vayomru d'amar kulehu. He brackets the
לאמר, lemor, it wasn't really responsive. ויאמרו, Vayomru, everybody said it, everybody
said the entire thing at the same time. בהדי הדדי, bahadi hadadi,
they said it all at the same time. לאמר, lemor, so then
what does לאמר lemor mean? לאמר lemor suggests that there was some
responsiveness. דפתח משה ברישא. d'patach Moshe b'reisha. He opened it, he said
אז ישיר az yashir and then everybody said it in unison with
him. The problem of course with him is is that how did
everybody else know the words? Who taught them the words? Okay, so
that's going to be the next גמרא. Gemara תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
we taught. דרש רבי יוסי הגלילי. Darash Rabbi Yose HaGelili. Rabbi Yose
HaGelili taught. Remember, Rabbi Yose is the one that said they all
said it in unison. So he's got to explain, it's one thing
to say that משה Moshe composed it on the spot. But how
did everybody else learn it if they said it in unison? So
that Rabbi Yose HaGelili has to say. So let's take a look.
Rabbi Yose HaGelili says, בשעה שעלו ישראל מן הים, b'sha'ah she-alu Yisrael
min hayam, נתנו עיניהם לומר שירה, natnu eineihem lomar shira, they wanted
to say שירה. shira. וכיצד אמרו שירה, v'keitzad amru shira, how did
they say it? Before we said משה Moshe taught them, but according
to him how did they all know to say exactly what they
said? So עול מוטל על ברכי אמו, ol mutal al birkei imo,
you had a... an infant on or a toddler... like an עול...
ol... רש"י says it's a little older than an infant. Yeah, you
had a toddler on his mother's lap, ותינוק יונק משדי אמו, v'tinok
yonek mishadei imo, and an infant suckling from its mother's breast, כיון
שראו את השכינה keivan she-ra'u et ha-Shechina And when they saw the
divine presence revealed itself on the, at ים סוף, Yam Suf, עולל
הגביה צוארו, olel higbi'a tzavaro, so the toddler lifted up his head,
his neck, ותינוק שמט דד מפיו, vetinok shamata dad mipiv, and the
infant released the breast from the nipple from his mouth, ואמרו, veamru,
and they said זה אלי ואנוהו. ze Eli veanvehu. So even the
infants very graphic image even the infants opened up. You want to
know how the people knew how to say it? Even the infants
knew how to say it. It was a miracle, what do you
want? You don't have to say Moshe taught it to them. They
were so inspired by the divine presence that they were all imbued
with prophecy and with song at that moment. So it's kosher to
breastfeed in shul. Oh, there you go. שנאמר, shenemar, as it says.
I remember this being brought at a bris. Okay, there you go.
שנאמר, shenemar, now here's why he was mentioning עולל olel and יונק.
yonek. מפי עוללים ויונקים יסדת עוז. mipi ollim veyonkim yisadta oz. From
the mouths of toddlers and infants you have made a foundation of
strength. Probably because it's also עוז oz is probably a play on
עזי וזמרת יה, ozzi vezimrat ya, right, so the עוז. oz. היה
רבי מאיר אומר, haya Rabbi Meir omer, מנין שאפילו עוברים שבמעי אמן,
minayin sheafilu ubarim shebim'ei imman, הא, ha, I'll do you one better.
How do I know even the fetuses in their mother's womb? They
didn't even have to be born yet. אמרו שירה, amru shira, said
שירה. shira. שנאמר, shenemar, as it says, במקהלות, bemakhelot, in the gatherings,
when they gathered by the ים, Yam, ברכו אלהים, barechu Elohim, bless
God, ה', Hashem, the Lord, ממקור ישראל, mimmekor Yisrael, from the wellsprings
of Israel, the מקור. mekor. So the מקור mekor is the womb
which nurtures the child. Okay, so then the גמרא Gemara says, so
now there's an interesting other line here which is a question of
if it belongs. והלא לא חזו, vahalo lo chazu, but they couldn't
see anything. It's one thing the infants, they saw the divine presence,
but what did the fetuses see? So אמר רבי תנחום, amar Rabbi
Tanchum, so the infants you could say זה אלי ואנוהו, ze Eli
veanvehu, they saw something because at least they had eyes, they were
born. What did the fetuses see? So אמר רבי תנחום, amar Rabbi
Tanchum, כרס נעשה להם כאספקלריה המאירה וראו. keres na'asa lahem keaspaklarya hameira
verau. The womb became like a transparent lit glass, a seeing glass,
and they saw through the womb and they were able to see
the divine presence. It was like an ultrasound movie on the inside
of the. There you go. I mean, מקור mekor is an anatomical
term. Yeah, מקור mekor is the rabbinic word for the womb, or
for the uterus, yeah. Okay, בו ביום, bo bayom, let's see if
we can get to the משנה Mishnah here. בו ביום דרש רבי
יהושע בן הורקנוס שלא עבד איוב אלא מאהבה. bo bayom darash Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Hurkanos shelo avad Iyov ela meahava. Iyov served out of
love, because based on the פסוק pasuk that says הן יקטלני לו
איחל, hen yikteleni lo ayachel, even if God will kill me I
will long for, have my faith in God. So there, but the
משנה Mishnah goes on to say but we don't know if לו
lo means for Him I will have my longing and my faith
or it means לא with an אלף, alef, I will not have
any faith in him. So the גמרא Gemara says בו ביום דרש
רבי יהושע בן הורקנוס ועבדו וכו'. bo bayom darash Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Hurkanos veavado vechu'. ולחזי האי "לא" בלאמד אלף כתיב או בלאמד ויו
כתיב. veleichezei hai "lo" belamed alef ketiv o belamed vav ketiv. And
let's see this "lo", is it written with a לאמד אלף lammed
alef then it's לא הוא, hu, then it means I won't have
any faith anymore, if it's written with a לאמד ויו, lammed vav,
לו lo הוא, hu, I will have my faith in him. So
what does it mean, the משנה Mishnah said עדיין הדבר שקול, adayin
hadavar shakol, it's not clear from the פסוק. pasuk. And they had
to go to another פסוק. pasuk. What do you mean it's not
clear from the פסוק? pasuk? Let's take a look, is it לאמד
אלף lammed alef or לאמד ויו? lammed vav? Of course, the interesting
thing is it's written לאמד אלף lammed alef but the דרשה derasha
is לאמד ויו. lammed vav. But the גמרא Gemara says no, וכל
היכא דכתיב בלאמד אלף "לא" הוא. vechol heicha dechetiv belamed alef "lo"
hu. Do you mean to tell me anytime you see it's written
with an אלף alef it means "lo" in the sense of no?
אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, בכל צרתם לא צר, bechol tzaratam lo tzar,
in all of their affliction, reading with the "lo" as an אלף,
alef, He, God is not afflicted. Is that how you're supposed to
read it? God isn't bothered by our affliction? דכתיב בלאמד אלף הכי
נמי ד"לא" הוא? dechetiv belamed alef hachi nami de "lo" hu? That
God isn't afflicted by our affliction? וכי תימא הכי נמי, vechi teima
hachi nami, why not, God's God? הכתיב ומלאך פניו הושיעם. hachetiv umalach
panav hoshia'am. No, that the angel saves them, which means that it
did affect God. So we actually read that בכל צרתם, bechol tzaratam,
in all their affliction, לו צר lo tzar with a ויו, vav,
that God is afflicted. אלא משמע הכי ומשמע הכי. ela mashma hachi
umashma hachi. It's interesting, it doesn't say קרי וכתיב. keri uchtiv. It
says an אלף, alef, even written with an אלף alef could mean
with a ויו. vav. Now this is very interesting, I didn't check
with any Bible scholars, but there definitely are, think about the Hebrew
word הוא, hu, ה-ו-א, he vav alef, which is often read as
not "hu" but as "hi", and that was an alternate spelling of
the word "hi" was with a ויו, vav, not with a יוד.
yod. Okay, so maybe that actually is true, I mean the standardization
of spelling only happened later. Right, orthography, the אלף alef is a
placeholder for a vowel. Right, so it's like "Sarah" with a ה
hei at the end. It's a placeholder. Right, so it could very
well be that "lo" with an אלף alef means "lo" with a
ויו. vav. So I really do wonder what they found in Dead
Sea Scrolls and other types of. Inscriptions, you know, where I, but
I think that that's a, you know, that that's quite possible that
it really has both possible meanings. Okay, so the גמרא says, okay,
אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata,
תניא, tanya, we've taught in a ברייתא. Beraisa. רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi
Meir omer, נאמר ירא אלוקים באיוב, ne'emar yere Elokim be'Iyov, that he
was fearing God, and נאמר ירא אלוקים באברהם, ne'emar yere Elokim be'Avraham,
כי עתה ידעתי כי ירא אלוקים אתה. ki ata yadati ki yere
Elokim ata. מה ירא אלוקים האמור באברהם מאהבה, ma yere Elokim ha'amur
be'Avraham me'ahava, fearing does not mean that it wasn't out of love,
you know, maybe it means fearing together with the love, but it
doesn't mean, but you know, אף ירא אלוקים האמור באיוב, af yere
Elokim ha'amur be'Iyov, it doesn't mean only out of fear, but it
means מאהבה, me'ahava, out of love. Obviously it's a bigger point by
איוב Iyov because איוב Iyov was so afflicted and you know, beset
obviously by suffering, to say it still came out of a place
of love, you know, is a very powerful statement. ואברהם גופיה מנלן,
ve'Avraham gufei minalan, how do you know Avraham did it out of
love? דכתיב, dechtiv, זרע אברהם אוהבי, zera Avraham ohavi, because he's called
the one who loves me. מה איכא בין עושה מאהבה לעושה מיראה?
ma ika bein oseh me'ahava le'oseh miyira? What's the difference? Not—it's interesting,
it would be nice if they would describe what's the difference in
terms of their religious lives, how they act, but it's actually going
to talk about the difference in terms of their reward. הא דתניא,
ha detanya, רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer,
איכא הא דתניא, ika ha detanya, it is, הא דתניא, ha detanya,
the difference is what רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar
says. גדול העושה מאהבה יותר מן העושה מיראה, gadol ha'oseh me'ahava yoter
min ha'oseh miyira, שזה תלוי לאלף דור, sheze taluy le'elef dor, the
one who does it מיראה miyira gets rewarded for a thousand generations,
וזה, veze, the one who does it מאהבה, me'ahava, לאלפיים דור, le'alpayim
dor, two thousand. הכא כתיב, hacha ktiv, לאלפיים, le'alpayim, what is it?
לאלפים, le'alafim, right? לאלפים לאוהבי ולשומרי מצותי, le'alafim le'ohavai uleshomrei mitzvotai, for
thousands of generations for those who love me, ואז כתיב, ve'az ktiv,
ולשומרי מצותיו לאלף דור. uleshomrei mitzvotav le'elef dor. So only a thousand,
not thousand, thousands. התם נמי כתיב, hatam nami ktiv, לאוהביו ולשומרי מצותיו
לאלף דור? le'ohavav uleshomrei mitzvotav le'elef dor? לאוהביו le'ohavav is also mentioned
where it says אלף דור elef dor and only says a thousand?
No, לאלף דור, le'elef dor, הא דסמיך ליה והא דלא סמיך ליה.
ha desamech lei veha dela samech lei. No, no. The question is
what is the word that's juxtaposed? In the first פסוק, pasuk, אלפים
alafim is juxtaposed to לאוהבי, le'ohavai, and then שומרי מצותי shomrei mitzvotai
comes next. In the other פסוק, pasuk, it's לאוהביו ולשומרי מצותיו לאלף
דור. le'ohavav uleshomrei mitzvotav le'elef dor. So אלף דור elef dor is
juxtaposed to שומרי מצותיו. shomrei mitzvotav. So you could be very scrupulous
in שומרי מצוות, shomrei mitzvot, and but not do it to the
same degree מאהבה. me'ahava. Okay, last point. הנהו תרי תלמידי דהוו יתבי
קמיה דרבא. hanhu trei talmidei dehavu yasvei kamey deRava. Two students were
sitting in front of רבא. Rava. חד אמר ליה, chad amar lei,
אקריון בחלמיי, akryun bechalmai, I heard read to me in my dream:
מה רב טובך אשר צפנת ליראיך. ma rav tuvcha asher tzafanta lirei'echa.
How great is your good God that you have treasured, put away,
stored away for those who fear you. וחד אמר ליה, vechad amar
lei, אקריון בחלמיי, akryun bechalmai, I had read to me in my
dream: וישמחו בך כל חוסי בך, veyismechu vecha kol chosei vach, and
will rejoice in you all who put their trust in you, לעולם
ירננו ויעלצו בך אוהבי שמך, le'olam yeranenu ve'ya'altzu vach ohavei shemecha, forever
will they rejoice and burst forth in song those who love your
name. אמר להו, amar lehu, so רבא Rava said to them: תרווייכו
רבנן צדיקי גמורי אתון. travaychu rabbanan tzadikei gmurei atun. You're both צדיקים
גמורים, tzadikim gemurim, you are. מר מאהבה ומר מיראה, mar me'ahava umar
miyira, one of you though is a ירא אלוקים, yere Elokim, right,
ליראיך, lirei'echa, and the other does it out of אהבה. ahava. הדרן
עלך השולח. Hadran alach haShole'ach. All right, so we'll end with that.