So today's דף daf is מ"ג, mem gimmel, and we pick up
at the very top of מ"ג. mem gimmel.
And we're dealing with the issue of why is it that according
to the משנה mishnah you would take the לולב lulav both in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and out of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash on שבת Shabbos
when the first day יום טוב Yom Tov fell on שבת. Shabbos.
So the question is:
why wouldn't you take it? I mean for us we don't take
it even the first day יום טוב Yom Tov falls out on
שבת, Shabbos, but the first thing the גמרא Gemara has to figure
out is why don't you take it when שבת Shabbos falls out
on חול המועד. Chol Hamoed. So let's pick up actually from, let's
read that again because it's so important, from the גמרא Gemara three
lines from the bottom on מ"ב עמוד ב'. mem bais amud bais.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי, amai, why should it be a
problem even during the week where שבת Shabbos falls out on חול
המועד? Chol Hamoed? Take לולב lulav then. טלטול בעלמא הוא, tiltul b'alma
hu, it's just מוקצה. muktzah. לדחי שבת, lidchi Shabbos, let שבת Shabbos
override מוקצה muktzah concerns. So אמר רבה: amar Rabba: גזירה שמא יטלנו
בידו וילך אצל בקי ללמוד. gezeirah shema yitlenu beyado veyeileich eitzel baki
lilmod.
We're afraid you'll pick it up and you'll walk out of the
house in order to, and there won't be an עירוב, eiruv, in
order to have somebody teach you, teach you the ברכות, brachos, teach
you to do the נענועים, na'anuim, ויעבירנו ד' אמות ברשות הרבים, v'yavirnu
daled amos b'reshus harabim, and you'll accidentally carry it in רשות הרבים.
reshus harabim. And therefore the reason on חול המועד Chol Hamoed you
don't do it on שבת Shabbos is you might come to carry
it. Now as he pointed out, רבה Rabba is picking up on
hints in the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah already spoke about you
would bring it to the שול shul ahead of time, you would
bring it to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash ahead of time. It
spoke about if somebody accidentally carried it on שבת Shabbos in order
to do the מצוה, mitzvah, they're exempt from a חטאת chatas because
they were being involved in a מצוה. mitzvah. But nevertheless, it clearly
acknowledges that there's this real concern of carrying. So רבה Rabba says
that's the reason that it is not done on חול המועד. Chol
Hamoed. I should say two things. First of all, as I already
said yesterday, that's רבה Rabba's reason. It's not in the משנה. mishnah.
It's possible that there were other reasons as well and we'll discuss
maybe בירושלמי b'Yerushalmi doesn't really have רבה Rabba's reason. Anyway, we'll discuss
other possibilities a little bit as we continue, but that's רבה Rabba's
explanation and that's assumed to be the reason, although again we should
note that it's not necessarily stated earlier than רבה. Rabba. Number two,
the fact that רבה Rabba says that they forbade you to take
לולב lulav because of this concern, and let's actually read the next
line, and the next line isn't even רבה, Rabba, the next line
is גמרא Gemara commenting on
רבה: Rabba: והיינו טעמא דשופר והיינו טעמא דמגילה. v'hainu taama d'shofar v'hainu
taama d'megillah. By the way, that's also the reason you don't blow
שופר shofar on שבת Shabbos when it's יום טוב Yom Tov is
שבת, Shabbos, when ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is שבת, Shabbos, and it's
the reason you don't read the מגילה. megillah. This isn't relevant to
us because the 14th never falls out on שבת, Shabbos, but in
ירושלים Yerushalayim walled cities you don't read, and in the גמרא Gemara
it could have happened, you don't read מגילה megillah on שבת Shabbos
because of a concern that you'll carry it. Now again, the משניות
mishnayos are clear that you don't blow שופר shofar on שבת Shabbos
and they're clear you don't read מגילה megillah on שבת. Shabbos. The
reason is not said. The reason here is taken from רבה Rabba
and extended to these cases. Now it should be noted that when
there's a whole debate as you might be aware about like whether
you need six
what constitutes a רשות הרבים reshus harabim to be a biblical רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim. The גמרא Gemara speaks about like wide major streets,
but the גאונים Geonim add the requirement of 600,000 people using it.
That requirement is not mentioned anywhere in the גמרא. Gemara. Because of
that requirement, that allows us often to have an עירוב eiruv to
assume we're not dealing with a real רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. You
know
sometimes the phrase even becomes oh there's no רשות הרבים reshus harabim
nowadays, to which of course the response is what? And like in
the time of the גמרא Gemara and in the משנה mishnah there
were 600,000 people who would use major streets? Where did that happen?
And part of the challenge to that idea that you'd have that
criteria for רשות הרבים reshus harabim is the fact that we make
these גזירות gezeiros of not doing a מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah d'oraissa like
blowing שופר shofar or taking לולב lulav because you might accidentally carry.
And that גזירה gezeira would only be if there's a real concern
of biblical transgression. Well clearly then it suggests the idea that a
רשות הרבים reshus harabim was a prevalent reality in the time of
the משנה mishnah and גמרא, Gemara, if that would have been the
basis for forbidding you to do these biblical מצוות. mitzvos. So that's
a critique that some people raise against the idea, ראשונים Rishonim raise,
that there's this 600,000 criteria because that would make רשות הרבים reshus
harabim very rare, and it does not sound if it becomes the
basis for completely not doing a biblical מצוה, mitzvah, it doesn't sound
like it's so rare. So that's just an interesting point about that
discussion. It's also an interesting issue תוספות Tosfos and רש"י Rashi discuss
why it says carry it ד' אמות ברשות הרבים daled amos b'reshus
harabim instead of carrying it from your house out into the street,
which is the more immediate thing you would do is you would
step out of your house, right? So תוספות Tosfos says well it's
more obvious there like when you make that transition indoors to outdoors,
there are more signals to you to stop you, you'll be aware
like oh I can't step out of the house it's שבת, Shabbos,
whereas once you're in the street, of course how did you get
it out to the street to carry it ד' אמות daled amos
if you didn't bring it out of your house? Anyway but that
is an issue that gets raised as well. But this idea of
a concern of carrying as is the explanation of. explanation that is
given by רב Rav and then extended by the גמרא Gemara to
explain לולב, Lulav, שופר, Shofar, and מגילה Megilla why we don't do
it on שבת. Shabbat.
Right, did I understand correctly? Did he say that
the descriptor of 600,000 as the defining criteria is Geonic, it's not
in the גמרא? Gemara?
Right, I mean, the גאונים Geonim claim that it is true to
the גמרא, Gemara, they don't say they're making it up, but it
is not mentioned anywhere in the גמרא. Gemara.
And is רבא Rava second generation אמורא? Amora?
Yes, I believe that's correct, yes. All right, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי ei
hachi says the גמרא Gemara two lines from the top, יום ראשון
נמי, yom rishon nami,
if it's that is the concern you might carry it, then you
should not be able to do it even when יום טוב Yom
Tov falls out on to even even if the first day יום
טוב Yom Tov is שבת. Shabbos. Now again, we don't do it,
but again, remember in the משנה, Mishna, they would do it in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and out of the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, they would take לולב Lulav on first day יום טוב Yom
Tov even if it was שבת. Shabbos. So if says the גמרא
Gemara your concern is you might carry it, what makes the first
day special? So the גמרא Gemara says ראשון התקינו ליה רבנן בביתו.
rishon hatkinu lei rabanan beveiso. No, the first day after that big
you
know mess in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that with the fighting
and all of that, they said keep taking it home, don't leave
your house with your לולב. Lulav. So there's no concern that people
will come to carry it. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
If that's true, התינח אחר תקנה, haineich achar takkana, that's fine after
they had all that fighting and they made the תקנה, takkana, but
קודם תקנה מאי? kodem takkana mai? But it was clear from the
משנה Mishna that before they had that תקנה, takkana, they were still
taking it on שבת. Shabbos. That's why they that's why they brought
it to שול shul the day before so they could take it
on שבת. Shabbos. So clearly, even before the אי תקנה ai takkana
that you have to bring it at home, they were allowed to
take it on שבת Shabbos on the first day. Why is that
if it's a concern you might come to carry? So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי איכא למימר, mai ika l'meimar, what can you say?
אלא, ella, fine, here's the difference, which is the obvious difference. ראשון
דאיתא מן התורה בגבולין, rishon d'isah minei hatorah bigvulin, the first day
which is a biblical מצוה mitzvah even out of the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, לא גזרו בהו רבנן. lo gazru behu rabanan. The רבנן
rabanan said we'll let you take it the first day even though
it's שבת, Shabbos, we're not going to be so concerned you'll carry
it that we won't negate the biblical מצוה. mitzvah. We'll let you
go ahead and take it. Obviously, prepare, bring it to שול shul
ahead of time, don't don't carry, but we're going to let you
take it on the first day יום טוב Yom Tov which is
biblical. לא
גזרו בהו רבנן. lo gazru behu rabanan. One minute. הנך, hanach, the
other days of חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, דליתנהו מן התורה בגבולין d'leisnhu
minei hatorah bigvulin that is not biblical מצוה mitzvah out of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, גזרו בהו רבנן gazru behu rabanan there the
רבנן rabanan said, no, I'm sorry don't take it on חול המועד,
Chol HaMoed, you can take it on the first day which is
biblical, not the other days. Now why did the גמרא Gemara have
to say is biblical out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash not
out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Just say, first day is
biblical, they let you take it; the other days are rabbinic, they
didn't let you take it if it's שבת. Shabbos. And the answer
is because you'll remember our משנה Mishna is talking about in the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right, our משנה Mishna says how would you
take it, you'd bring it up to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
ערב שבת erev Shabbos etc. So our משנה Mishna that's talking in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash says you would take the לולב Lulav
seven days if the first day יום טוב Yom Tov was שבת
Shabbos and six day if שבת Shabbos fell out on חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. So our משנה Mishna makes it clear that if שבת
Shabbos fell out on חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, you would not take
it on שבת Shabbos even in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Our
משנה Mishna is describing what they would do in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and says they would not take it on שבת Shabbos
חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So the question is why not? In the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, even on חול המועד Chol HaMoed it's biblical.
So if biblical is a reason to take it on שבת, Shabbos,
let me take it on חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. So the answer
is no, because even though it's biblical here in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, it's not biblical out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and therefore it's not weighty enough to take it on שבת. Shabbos.
Our concern of carrying will override. So that's the גמרא's Gemara answer.
We have a concern about carrying, we're not going to let you
take it on חול המועד Chol HaMoed where it's not biblical out
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and even in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash it's not as weighty because it's most of the places
it's not biblical. That concern of carrying will override. But the first
day where it's biblical for everyone, that day that you can take
it even on שבת, Shabbos, the מצוה mitzvah is more important in
that context than the concern you might forget and you might carry.
Okay, so that's according to the משנה Mishna that you did take
it on שבת. Shabbos. Now we're going to have to get to
the question about but we don't take it on שבת. Shabbos. So
what's that about? Yes.
So when we say that the biblical מצוה mitzvah overrides the concern
of carrying on שבת, Shabbat, that means that it's מותר mutar to
carry it on?
No, no, no, no. Absolutely not. Absolutely, I yeah. No, no, no,
well, I was trying not to be ambiguous, but I'll repeat it,
that all it is that that obviously you can even if there's
a biblical מצוה, mitzvah, you cannot violate שבת. Shabbos. The whole discussion
earlier was if you accidentally violate accidentally violated שבת Shabbos in the
performance of the מצוה mitzvah does that get you off of a
חטאת? chatas? Right, but clearly it's prohibited. The question always is, though,
we have these concerns, how much, you know, are you going to
let your those concerns override other important things that need to be
done? So the question is we will let you take it on
first day יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*.
Obviously you have to be sure you don't carry. Bring it to
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* on Friday, bring it to
your שול shul *shul* on Friday. If you didn't bring it to
your שול shul *shul*, make sure not to take it out of
your house. But we're still going to let you take it and
say we're not going to be so concerned you might forget that
we're going to stop you from doing the biblical מצוה Mitzvah? *mitzvah*.
So the prohibition of course completely exists, but if the first day
is, if it's the first day and it's biblical, we're going to
say take precautions but do the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*. We're not going
to let our anxieties and our concerns
override that, right.
So similar to a ברית מילה *bris milah* on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*
and all the things have to be prepared before שבת Shabbat.
*Shabbos*. Exactly, exactly. Okay, so that's the position right now, that yes
obviously it's completely forbidden to carry it on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* even
if you're doing the מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah*, but are we going to
stop you from doing it or are we going to trust you
to take the necessary precautions? So here we're saying that in the
משנה Mishna *Mishna* it's clear you could take it on שבת Shabbat,
*Shabbos* as long as you took the necessary precautions. When it's a
biblical מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah* everywhere on the first day, we are going
to trust you to take the necessary precautions. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אי הכי *ee hachi*, if that's
true says the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*, האידנא נמי *ha idna nami*, so
nowadays why don't we take it nowadays on first day יום טוב
Yom Tov, *Yom Tov* falls out on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*? The משנה
Mishna *Mishna* says you do, why don't we do it? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: אנן לא ידעינן בקביעא דירחא Anan lo yedinan
b'kivia d'yarcha. *anan lo yedinan bekivu'a deyarcha*, we don't know when exactly
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* is, which doesn't mean we literally
don't know because we have a fixed calendar, but it means we
act as if we don't know. We live outside of ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* in a reality
of keeping two days יום טוב Yom Tov, *Yom Tov*, of pretending
like we lived at the time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash,
*Beis Hamikdash* where we weren't sure if we lived outside of Israel
when they established ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*. And therefore we
can't say oh today it's definitely biblical, because we're living in this
virtual reality as if it was the time of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* where we would never know exactly is this
the first day יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov* or is tomorrow
the first day יום yom טוב *Yom Tov*. So because we're in
that uncertainty or in that virtual
uncertainty, that mock uncertainty as it were, we do not therefore take
it on the first day. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says fine,
אינהו דיידעי בקביעא דירחא *inhu d'yeidi bekivu'a deyarcha*, those who live in
Israel who don't live in that virtual uncertainty, they live as if
they know when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* was made, meaning
and they live in that reality that they would be at the
time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash* where they would
know when ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* was. So for people who live
in Israel and only keep one day יום yom טוב *Yom Tov*,
לדחי *lidchi*, let it override. Why don't they take the לולב Lulav
*lulav* on the first day יום yom טוב *Yom Tov* on שבת
Shabbat, *Shabbos* in Israel like they did at the time of the
משנה mishna *Mishna*? So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says: אין הכי נמי
*ein hachi nami*, you know what? You're right, they do. דתני חדא
*detani chada*, because one משנה mishna *Mishna* says: ביום Bayom, טוב הראשון
HaRishon, שחל להיות בשבת כל המוליכין את לולביהם להר הבית *beyom tov
harishon shechal lihyos beshabbos kol hamolichin es lulaveihem lehar habayis*, our משנה
mishna *Mishna* says that when יום טוב *Yom Tov* fell out on
שבת Shabbat *Shabbos* they would bring their לולבים *lulavim* to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beis Hamikdash* from the day before. ותנן אידך *vesnan
idach*, and the other משנה mishna *Mishna* said that we learned at
the end of last פרק *perek*: לבית הכנסת *lebeis haknesses*, that on
ערב שבת Shabbat. *erev Shabbos* they would bring it to their שול
*shul*. So שמע מינה *shma mina*, so what's the explanation? Would they
bring it to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* or would
they bring it to the שול *shul*? Now it could be depends
how close you live to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*.
But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to translate it the following
way: כאן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים כאן בזמן שאין בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash קיים *kan b'zman she'Beis Hamikdash kayam, kan b'zman she'ein Beis Hamikdash
kayam*, that it's talking about two different times of history. At the
time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* they would bring
it on Friday to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. When
after the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* they would bring it
on Friday to their local שולס *shuls*.
So שמע מינה *shma mina*, so that is a good proof. So
right now what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is the fact
that an earlier משנה mishna *Mishna* said they would bring it to
the שולס *shuls* on ערב שבת Shabbat. *erev Shabbos* means when there
was no longer a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash* they would
still go ahead and take it at שול *shul* on שבת Shabbat.
*Shabbos*. You'd prepare ahead of time and you'd take it on שבת
Shabbat *Shabbos*. And that shows you that nowadays in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* at least it shows you that you could take
the לולב Lulav *lulav* on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos*. So according to the
conclusion of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here, now there's not going to
be the conclusion at the end of the דף daf *daf*, but
right now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is basically concluding that in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* when the first day יום טוב *Yom
Tov* falls out on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, thank you so much, you
would actually take the לולב Lulav, *lulav* on the first day יום
טוב *Yom Tov*. Has anybody ever been in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael,
*Eretz Yisrael* on סוכות Succos *Sukkos*? Ever been in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael* on סוכות Succos *Sukkos* when the first day יום
טוב *Yom Tov* falls out on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*? Do we take
it on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*? No, we don't take it on שבת
Shabbat. *Shabbos*. But right now that is the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*'s conclusion
and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying that that's פשט Pshat *pshat*
of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* that says that they would take it
to שול *shul* ערב שבת Shabbat, *erev Shabbos* is talking even nowadays
with no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, that's what you do
in Israel. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to reject that
later, but right now that is the position of the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. So we're going to circle back to that. The other question
to ask which we'll circle back to
is why it's more taken for granted, for example, that שופר Shofar,
*shofar* was not taken, was not blown
on, well, let me take a minute to talk about that right
now. So according to So according to this, the משנה Mishnah, says
that לולב Lulav, was taken on שבת, Shabbat, at least out of
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. at least in Israel. And the גמרא
Gemara even thinks that's what we do nowadays. But if anybody ever
learned ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, you learned that when ראש השנה Rosh
Hashana falls out on שבת, Shabbat, they didn't do it in the,
you know, locally in shuls, things. They maybe did it in the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. but they didn't do it locally. So what's
the difference? What? On שופר, Shofar, on שבת. Shabbat, So why is
it when ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, by the way, it's the same
year, ראש השנה Rosh Hashana falls out on שבת, Shabbat, סוכות Succos,
falls out on שבת, Shabbat, why is it that if ראש השנה
Rosh Hashana falls out on שבת, Shabbos they never took it outside
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. blew it outside the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash. whereas if סוכות Succos fell out on שבת, Shabbos according
to this, they would take it outside of the בית המקדש? Beis
HaMikdash? And according to the גמרא, Gemara even thinks even up till
today. So what's the difference? So תוספות Tosafos says two differences, two
important differences. Number one is that שופר, Shofar the first day of
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana, basically almost nobody knew when ראש השנה Rosh
Hashana was, right? By סוכות, Succos there were two weeks to find
out when the first day of סוכות Succos was, because you know,
it had been determined two weeks ago. On ראש השנה, Rosh Hashana,
only people in the immediate environs of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash,
knew. So following the idea that the גמרא Gemara said before, we're
not going to, we do have concerns you might come to carry
it. Are those, is that going to stop us from doing the
מצוה? Mitzvah. Well, the less we're certain we're doing a biblical מצוה
mitzvah today, because today might not be the first day of יום
טוב, then the less we're going to allow you to go ahead
and do it. So one easy explanation why it was clear you
don't blow the שופר Shofar, on שבת Shabbos and not so clear
about the לולב Lulav was because it was a lot less clear
what was the first day of ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. That's an
easy answer. The other answer תוספות Tosafos says gets to another point
I was making, which is that there are other explanations other than
a concern of carrying which might inform why you don't do it
on שבת. Shabbos And תוספות Tosafos says when you're taking the לולב,
Lulav all you're doing is you're just moving something, like maybe it's
a מוקצה Muktzah thing, big deal. It's not considered a big challenge
to the idea of שבת. Shabbos So therefore on the first day
יום טוב, we'll let you take it. Whereas by שופר, Shofar. you're
blowing a שופר. Shofar That's like a musical instrument, that's a skilled
labor, it's not technically a מלאכה, Melacha, but it is like a
skill, you know, a craft and a skill to blow, play a
musical instrument. So that is intrinsically more problematic on שבת. Shabbos, So
therefore it was always obvious that you weren't going to blow the
שופר Shofar, on שבת Shabbos, out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash
Whereas by לולב, Lulav which a) it's less of a real violation
of שבת, Shabbos you know, at an experiential level, it's just shaking
something, it's rabbinic and it's not the same degree of problematic, and
it's more obvious what day is the first day of יום טוב,
that's why according to the משנה Mishnah. you would take the לולב
Lulav even on שבת Shabbos if the first day יום טוב fell
out on שבת. Shabbos Okay, so according to the גמרא Gemara you
would do it by the לולב Lulav. at least in Israel, where
you would know when ראש חודש would be, maybe not in בבל,
Bavel, but yes in Israel. And we're still going to have to
figure out why we don't do it nowadays. But לולב Lulav, is
in the משנה Mishnah more accepted to be done on שבת Shabbos?
than the blowing of the שופר, which it's taken for granted is
not. Okay, let's now continue in the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, דאיתא מן התורה בגבולין מנלן? De'isa min HaTorah
bi-gvulin minalan? Where do you know that it's a מצוה mitzvah. to
take the לולב Lulav, outside of the בית המקדש on the first
day? Pretty funny, it's a pretty clear פסוק. Pasuk. The bigger חידוש
Chiddush is that it's a מצוה mitzvah in the בית המקדש for
the whole week, but okay. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Braisa, ולקחתם, Ulekachtem, you shall take for yourselves a, you know, beautiful
fruit etc. So ולקחתם Ulekachtem in the plural, שתהא לקיחה ביד כל
אחד ואחד, she-tei lekicha biyad kol echad ve-echad, we discussed this before,
the plural language means one person doesn't take it for the collective,
but every individual takes it. משלכם, Mishelachem, ולקחתם לכם Ulekachtem lachem
and also לכם, Lachem, ולקחתם Ulekachtem is every individual. לכם Lachem for
you, משלכם, mishelachem, it means it has to belong to you. לאו
משל של שותפות וגזול, lav mishel shel shutafus ve-gazul, these are things
we've seen before. On the first day you can't use a borrowed
or stolen לולב. Lulav? ביום, Bayom on the first, ביום הראשון Bayom
HaRishon is the פסוק. Pasuk. ואפילו בשבת. Ve-afillu be-Shabbat. The day
means whatever happens on that day, that day it's going to be
done regardless, even if it falls out, even if it's שבת. Shabbos
ראשון, Rishon, the first day, אפילו בגבולין, afillu bi-gvulin, even,
meaning that's just פשט Pshat, of the פסוק. Pasuk. The first day
everybody has a מצוה. mitzvah? The idea of לפני השם, Lifnei Hashem,
which it said at the end, which is understood to be the
בית המקדש, that's for the whole week, but ראשון, Rishon, no qualifiers,
ראשון Rishon everybody has the obligation on the first day. הראשון, HaRishon,
the extra ה is זה הראשון. ללמד שאינו דוחה אלא יום טוב
הראשון בלבד. Lelamed she-eino docheh ela Yom Tov HaRishon bilvad. That the
idea that we said before that ביום it takes place even on
שבת, Shabbos? that's only on הראשון, that's only on the first day,
not on the other days even in the בית המקדש. So פשט,
this is basically an אסמכתא, Asmachta, the גמרא's Gemara going to try
to read it like it's a real דרשה, Drasha, but the fact
that it basically is learning from the פסוק Pasuk that you can
do it even on שבת, Shabbos. but only the first day you
can do it on שבת, Shabbos, not חול המועד Chol HaMoed that
you can't do on שבת, Shabbos, right, that's basically a rabbinic issue
about yes doing it on שבת, Shabbos not doing it on שבת,
Shabbos, only the first day, not חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, so this
is sort of hint, you know, learned from the פסוק. Pasuk. hanging
that on a פסוק *pasuk*. ביום *Bayom* even on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*.
הראשון *Harishon* but only שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* is on the first day
can you do it on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, on חול המועד *Chol
Hamoed* not. So that's what's going on here, but the גמרא *Gemara*
is going to try to read this now not as an אסמכתא
*asmachta*, but as a real דרשה *drasha*, so let's see what the
גמרא *Gemara* does with it. Yeah.
How do you make that determination?
That it's an אסמכתא *asmachta*? Well, I don't because the גמרא *Gemara*
is going to actually try to claim that it's a real דרשה
*drasha*.
But the fact, the idea to even
raise—well, first of all because it does happen in מדרש הלכה *Midrash
Halacha* and the גמרא *Gemara* says it explicitly. And also because the
difference about can you do it on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* on the
first day יום טוב *Yom Tov* as opposed to חול המועד *Chol
Hamoed*, we've clearly indicated before are rabbinic concerns, right? So those aren't
biblical issues. So we know from a minute ago that those are
rabbinic concerns. So clearly then, if it's following the—what we laid out
earlier—then it has to be just an אסמכתא *asmachta*. But the גמרא
*Gemara* is going to try to read it as a real דרשה
*drasha*, so let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* does with it.
Yeah, I just have one last question about that. So in general,
is it accurate to say that if—if we do have a situation
where it's an אסמכתא *asmachta* and not a real דרשה *drasha*, it's
generally to support a rabbinic concern or sometimes do they have an
אסמכתא *asmachta* when it's a הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai*?
You could have an אסמכתא *asmachta*. It's rare to have an אסמכתא
*asmachta* for a הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai*, although you had
it before. When, in the beginning of the מסכתא *masechta*, you had
it about שיעורים *shiurim*. ארץ חטה ושעורה *eretz chitah u'se'orah*, כל הפסוק
הזה לשיעורין נאמר *kol hapasuk hazeh l'shiurin ne'emar*. And the גמרא *Gemara*
says that those שיעורין *shiurin* are really הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai* and this is really an אסמכתא *asmachta*. Yeah. Yeah. Well, no,
but the—but the דרשה *drasha* didn't say it. First it presented it
as that the whole thing—that all the שיעורין *shiurin* are learned out
from that פסוק *pasuk* and then the גמרא *Gemara* says, no, really
we know שיעורין *shiurin* הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai* and that's
an אסמכתא *asmachta*. So you do have it. All right, so the
גמרא *Gemara* now continues. אמר מר *amar mar*. ביום ואפילו
בשבת *Bayom va'afilu b'Shabbos*. So you can take it on the first
day even on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. מכדי *Michdi*, let's take a look,
says the גמרא *Gemara*. טלטול בעלמא הוא *Tiltul b'alma hu*. It's just
מוקצה *muktsa*. איצטריך קרא למישרי טלטול *Itztarich kra l'mishrei tiltul*? How could
you have a real biblical דרשה *drasha* to say, oh, you could
take the לולב Lulav *lulav* on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*? It's a rabbinic
concern. What would a biblical פסוק *pasuk* be teaching you about that?
Clearly, you don't need a פסוק *pasuk* to tell me it's—you override
מוקצה *muktsa*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no. מכדי טלטול בעלמא הוא,
איצטריך קרא למישרי טלטול *Michdi tiltul b'alma hu, itztarich kra l'mishrei tiltul*?
אמר רבא *Amar Rava*, says רבא *Rava*—excuse me, אמר רבה *Amar Rabbah*—well,
נצרכה אלא למכשירי לולב Lulav *nitzrecha ela l'machshirei lulav*. So he, rather
than saying it's an אסמכתא *asmachta*, he says you really do need
the פסוק *pasuk*. And what the פסוק *pasuk* is coming to do
is it's coming to allow you to prepare the לולב Lulav *lulav*
on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, even if you really have to violate שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos*, you're allowed to make it on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*. Now,
we don't פסקן *pasken* that way. This follows, though, the position of
ואליבא דהאי תנא *va'aliba d'hai tanna*, the following תנא *tanna*. דתניא *Detanya*,
we taught in a ברייתא *Baraisa*. לולב Lulav וכל מכשיריו דוחה את
השבת דברי רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Lulav v'chol machshirav docheh es haShabbos,
divrei Rabbi Eliezer*. So there actually is a position that you can
violate שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* in order to do לולב lulav *lulav*. That's
what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says. Now, we know, for
example, there are two things that are חידושים *chiddushim* in this statement.
For example, there are some מצוות *mitzvos* that violate שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*,
like ברית מילה *bris milah*. You ברית מילה *bris milah* not violate,
but override שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*. Let's say you didn't pre—do the necessary
preparations ahead of time. You didn't sharpen the knife. You didn't—you have
to carry the, you know, the scalpel or whatever it is across
a רשות הרבים *reshus harabbim* in order to do the ברית מילה
*bris milah* and so on. Are you allowed to do the preparations
for the ברית מילה *bris milah* on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* or just
the act of the ברית מילה *bris milah*? So רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* comes along with this tremendous חידוש *chiddush* and says that מכשירי
מילה *machshirei milah* also דוחה את השבת *docheh es haShabbos*. He basically
even says if you need to chop down a tree to make
a fire in order to heat up your knife to sharpen your
knife on שבת Shabbat? *Shabbos* for the ברית מילה *bris milah*, you're
allowed to do it. Okay, so that's a tremendous חידוש *chiddush*. You
can do all these preparations that you could have taken care of
ahead of time, not just the act. But that's one thing to
say in the context of ברית מילה *bris milah* where the act
itself we already know, knows, does override שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*. Then he
just—well, once the act overrides שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, even all the preparations
would override as well. Here by לולב lulav *lulav*, he's going one
step further because לולב lulav. *lulav* in itself doesn't override שבת *Shabbos*.
We never have an idea that, oh, you're allowed to violate שבת
*Shabbos* in order to take לולב lulav *lulav*. So he says two
חידושים *chiddushim*. Number one is actually you can. Let's say, I don't
know what the scenario would be, but somehow if you had to
carry the לולב lulav *lulav* in order to be יוצא *yotzei* the
לולב lulav, *lulav*, you had to bring it in a רשות הרבים
*reshus harabbim*—no, actually, here's a better example: you had to chop down
the לולב lulav. *lulav* from the tree, still connected to the tree
or something. He says that number one, the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of
לולב lulav *lulav* overrides שבת *Shabbos*—well, that's already—that's a מכשירין *machshirin* to
chop down from the tree. The מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* overrides שבת *Shabbos*
and the preparations override שבת *Shabbos*.
So, but you can't eat lunch in your mother-in-law's סוכה Sukkah. *sukkah*
on סוכות Succos, *Sukkos* because of
the
same רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*, that's true. So I don't know what
to tell you about that.
So anyway, it's a tremendous חידוש *chiddush*. Number one is when you
start with a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* that's acknowledged that it overrides שבת
*Shabbos* like ברית מילה *bris milah*, according to רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
you could do all the preparations. And number two, that he says
that לולב lulav *lulav*, even though the תורה *Torah* never tells you
it overrides שבת *Shabbos*, he says actually לולב lulav *lulav* does override
שבת *Shabbos* and you could do לולב lulav, *lulav* and all the
preparations to get a לולב *lulav* on שבת *Shabbos*. So that's what
this דרשה *drasha*— So with this דרשה *drasha* that says that לולב
*Lulav* overrides שבת *Shabbat*, that's רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* actually does say that, that it overrides biblical violations of שבת
*Shabbat* in order to do לולב *Lulav*, because it's something that has
to be done today. It's like the same way we say במועדו
*be-mo'ado* allows you to do a פסח *Pesach* on שבת *Shabbat*, you
know, so לולב *Lulav*, today is the day for לולב *Lulav*. You
could violate שבת *Shabbat* in order to do לולב *Lulav*. Amazing idea.
Okay, we don't פוסקן *pasken* this way. So he says לולב וכל
מכשיריה דוחין את השבת דברי רבי אליעזר *Lulav ve-chol machshireha dochin et
ha-shabbat divei Rabbi Eliezer*. That's what רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says. מאי
טעמא דרבי אליעזר *Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer*? What's the reasoning of רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*? אמר קרא *amar kra*, because of what we just
said, ביום *ba-yom*, on the first day, ואפילו בשבת *ve-afillu be-shabbat*. So
the same like במועדו *be-mo'ado* by פסח *Pesach* means even on שבת
*Shabbat*, ביום הראשון *ba-yom ha-rishon* by לולב *Lulav* means even on שבת
*Shabbat*, whatever you need to do. Okay, ורבנן האי ביום מאי עבדי
ליה *ve-rabbanan hai ba-yom mai avdi lei*? So what do the Rabbis
do with the word ביום *ba-yom*? מיבעי ליה *mibaei lei*, they need
it, ביום ולא בלילה *ba-yom ve-lo ba-layla*, more very more simple דרשה
*drasha*, that the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of לולב *Lulav* is a day
לולב *Lulav*, it's not a night מצוה *mitzvah*. רבי אליעזר ביום ולא
בלילה מנא ליה *Rabbi Eliezer ba-yom ve-lo ba-layla mna lei*? Where does
he know לולב *Lulav* is only a daytime מצוה *mitzvah*, not night?
נפקא ליה מסיפא דקרא *nafka lei misefa de-kra*: ושמחתם לפני ה׳ אלהיכם
שבעת ימים yamim *u-smachtem lifnei Hashem elokeichem shivat yamim*, rejoice before God
seven days, which is then the מצוה *mitzvah* of לולב *Lulav* in
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* for seven days. ימים ולא לילות
*yamim ve-lo leilot*, only days, not nights. It's a day מצוה *mitzvah*.
That's where he learns it from. ורבנן *ve-rabbanan*, the Rabbis, what do
you do with the ימים *yamim* by the end of the פסוק
*pasuk* since you already know the idea that it's a daytime מצוה
*mitzvah*? אי מהתם *ima hatam*, had it just been the end of
the פסוק *pasuk*, הוי אמינא ימים ימים מסוכה *havi amina yamim yamim
mi-sukka*. The words days by the seven days would not have told
me daytime only because there's another idea of days in the plural
by סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* which means daytime and nighttime. מה להלן ימים
ואפילו לילות *mah
halan yamim ve-afillu leilot*, the same way days in the plural by
סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* means all the days, day and night, אף כאן
נמי ימים ואפילו לילות *af kan nami yamim ve-afillu leilot*, maybe if
it had just been the end of the פסוק *pasuk* by rejoicing
before God seven
days, I would have said it meant night. So therefore, I need
it to say ביום *ba-yom* in the singular and to say it
again, and you know, if you say seven days, that's a sense
of the whole continuity of time which includes the nighttimes. One day
and the singular and only talking about one suggests daytime. So that's
what ביום *ba-yom* is teaching me. I could not have learned it
out from the word ימים *yamim*. I need the word ביום *ba-yom*
and it is not to tell me that לולב *Lulav* overrides שבת
*Shabbat*. לולב *Lulav* does not override שבת *Shabbat*. Okay, so the גמרא
*Gemara* says והתם בסוכה גופא מנלן *ve-hatam be-sukka gufa minolan*? And where
do you know that סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* itself applies even at night?
תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan*, we taught in a ברייתא *braita*: בסכות תשבו
Basukkos teshvu שבעת ימים *ba-sukkot teshvu shivat yamim*, dwell in a סוכה
Sukkah, *Sukkah* seven days. ימים ואפילו לילות *yamim ve-afillu leilot*, days means
even the intervening nights. אתה אומר ימים ואפילו לילות *ata omer yamim
ve-afillu leilot*? You say day even night? או אינו אלא ימים ולא
לילות *o eino ela yamim ve-lo leilot*? Maybe days mean even סוכה
Sukkah *Sukkah* is only a daytime מצוה *mitzvah*? ודין הוא *ve-din hu*,
and I can make a logical derivation about that. נאמר כאן ימים
*ne'emar kan yamim*, it says by סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* days, seven days,
ונאמר בלולב ימים *ve-ne'emar be-lulav yamim*, and it says by לולב *Lulav*
days, seven days, at least in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. מה
להלן ימים ולא לילות *mah halan yamim ve-lo leilot*, the same way
there where we're assuming we know the end result, the same way
there we know it's a daytime מצוה *mitzvah*, אף כאן ימים ולא
לילות *af kan yamim ve-lo leilot*, maybe סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* is also
only a daytime מצוה *mitzvah*. So that would be an argument that
סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* would only be daytime. או כלך לדרך זו O
klach l'derech zu, *o kallech le-derech zu*, or maybe go this on
this path, the opposite way, an additional way. נאמר כאן ימים *ne'emar
kan yamim*, it says by סוכה Sukkah *Sukkah* seven days, ונאמר במלואים
ימים *ve-ne'emar be-miluim yamim*. We've had this before, learned סוכה *Sukkah* from
the מלואים *miluim*, which is actually sort of the context of the
פרשיות *parshiyot* these
days. So it says by the time that the כהנים kohanim *kohanim*
would stay in the משכן Mishkan *Mishkan* when it was being initially
constructed, that they should stay seven days. יום ולילה *yom va-layla*, there
it's explicit. It says dwell in the משכן *Mishkan* יום ולילה *yom
va-layla*. So מה להלן ימים ואפילו לילות אף כאן ימים ואפילו לילות
Ma le'hallan yamim ve'afilu leilos af kan yamim ve'afilu leilos. *mah halan
yamim ve-afillu leilot af kan yamim ve-afillu leilot*. The same way there
it's day and night, which is explicit in the פסוק *pasuk*, סוכה
*Sukkah* is also day and night. So you have you can compare
it to מלואים *miluim*, you can compare it to לולב *Lulav*. So
נראה למי דומה *nireh le-mi domeh*. Let's figure out which one it's
more similar to. דנים דבר שמצותו כל היום מדבר שמצותו כל היום
*danim davar she-mitzvato kol ha-yom mi-davar she-mitzvato kol ha-yom*. Let's prove סוכה
*Sukkah* from מלואים *miluim* because they apply the entire day, meaning it's
not one moment in time, like it's just a continuity. You're in
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, they were in the משכן *Mishkan* seven
days straight continuously. You sit in the סוכה *Sukkah*, it's a continuous
מצוה *mitzvah*. ואל יוכיח דבר שמצותו שעה אחת *ve-al yokhiach davar she-mitzvato
sha'ah achat*, and let it not let's not use as an example
לולב *Lulav* which is a momentary act to apply to לולב *Lulav*,
to apply to סוכה *Sukkah*. סוכה *Sukkah* and the מלואים *miluim* are
very similar. It's a continuity of living. So if the מלואים *miluim*
is a continuity of living with nights, the same is true by
סוכה *Sukkah*. And you should not try to learn it out from
לולב *Lulav* which is a momentary single act. That's a very logical
point. Also you can even say that מלואים *miluim* is a similar,
you know, act that you're doing. It's dwelling in a place. So
you're dwelling... dwelling in the משכן, you're dwelling in the סוכה. That's
much more comparable than learning it out from לולב, which is a
single distinct type of an act. או כלך לדרך זו, or go
on this way. דנין דבר שמצוותו לדורות Dani'in davar she'mitzvaso l'doros מדבר
שמצוותו לדורות, midavar she'mitzvaso l'doros, let's learn out from sort of a
מצוה that applies in future in all generations, סוכה and לולב, ואל
יוכיח מילואים ve'al yochi'ach miluim and let's not prove it from מילואים
Miluim שאינו נוהג לדורות she'eino noheig l'doros that was a one-time thing,
it was not an ongoing מצוה. So which one is it? Is
it like מילואים Miluim or is it like לולב? Is it a
nighttime מצוה סוכה or only a daytime מצוה? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
so the verse teaches תשבו תשבו לגזירה שוה. Teshvu teshvu l'gezeira shava.
By סוכה it says בסכות תשבו basukkos teshvu and by מילואים Miluim
it says you shall dwell, תשבו יומם ולילה. teshvu yomam valaila. So
the word same verb links the two. And again it's not even
just one of those technical גזירה שוות, gezeira shavos, it actually is
the same action in both the מילואים Miluim and the סוכה, you're
dwelling in a place for seven days. So נאמר כאן תשבו ne'emar
kan teshvu by בסכות תשבו ונאמר במילואים תשבו, vene'emar b'miluim teshvu, you
shall dwell day and night. מה להלן ימים ואפילו לילות אף כאן
ימים ואפילו לילות. So the same way there day and night, here
day and night. So again this is repeating something we've seen before,
learning part of the aspects of the מצות סוכה mitzvas Sukkah from
the מילואים, Miluim, a dwelling in a place for seven days, and
we pointed out at the time this connects to other themes about
סוכה about sort of the presence of God and the same way
the כהנים kohanim were in the משכן for seven days and the
מקדש Mikdash connection and so on. Anyway for us it's just a
wrap up of the discussion that רבי אליעזר learns from the word
יום by לולב that it overrides שבת and really overrides biblical שבת
whereas the חכמים Chachamim say יום just means daytime. And then it
gets to this issue about and because we know that סוכה that
means nighttime, so ימים by סוכה means including night because we see
by מילואים. Miluim. So you need the יום by לולב to say
no, לולב is not like סוכה and it's and it's only daytime
not nighttime.
So סוכה is not a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא? mitzvas asei she'hazman
grama?
It is, it's גרמא grama for seven days but it's not I
mean it's not within those seven days it's continuous but it's not
but the עשה שהזמן גרמא asei she'hazman grama means it only applies
seven days out of the year.
So שבת is a מצות עשה שהזמן גרמא? mitzvas asei she'hazman grama?
Well שבת anyway you have the לא תעשה lo sa'asei and the
עשה asei is linked to the לא תעשה. lo sa'asei. So yes.
So that's why שבת is not part of that discussion. All right.
All right, so the גמרא says like this. Okay so that is
the end of the discussion for now about לולב on שבת, the
radical idea of רבי אליעזר that it ממש mamash overrides biblical שבת,
the idea that for us it overrides when it is דאורייתא de'oraisa
we know what the first day is, in ארץ ישראל Yisrael we
would take it we would obviously it would not override שבת you'd
prepare it ahead of time you'd bring it to the שול ahead
of time and so on but we would allow you to take
it on שבת on the first day. That's what the גמרא is
saying, that is not our practice even in ישראל Israel and we
will see when we get to the end of the דף why
how that switches. But right now we're working with some משניות mishnayos
that you would take it in ארץ ישראל at least even on
שבת on the first day. Okay so now we turn to the
second part of the משנה Mishnah which is the ערבה, aravah, the
waving of the
willows. So in the בית המקדש again the משנה Mishnah. is situated
in the בית המקדש. So it says that they would take the
ערבה aravah six and seven days. Because what they would do in
the מקדש Mikdash is actually if you turn, let's turn the page
for a minute, turn to מה עמוד א, mem hey amud aleph,
so you see what how the משנה Mishnah describes what they would
do with the ערבה aravah in the בית המקדש. So on מה
עמוד א mem hey amud aleph the משנה Mishnah here reads the
following. מצות ערבה כיצד, Mitzvas aravah keitzad, what would be the מצוה
of taking the ערבה aravah again in the בית המקדש. מקום היה
למטה מירושלים ונקרא מוצא. Makom haya lemata mi'Yerushalayim v'nikra Motza. יורדים לשם
ומלקטים משם מרביות של ערבה, Yordim l'sham u'melaktim mi'sham murbiyos shel aravah,
so they'd go to this place and they get all of these
big branches of ערבות. aravos. ובאים וזוקפים אותן בצידי המזבח. U'vaim v'zokfim
osan b'tzidei ha'mizbei'ach. So
they would sort of stick them in the ground by the edge
of the of the altar. וראשיהם כפופים על גבי המזבח. V'rosheihem k'fufim
al gabei ha'mizbei'ach.
And their heads would like lean over hang over the top of
the altar. Now these would basically be the כהנים kohanim would do
this because only the כהנים Kohanim, were allowed on all sides of
the altar. ותקעו והריעו ותקעו V'saku v'heriu v'saku and they'd do תקיעה
תרועה תקיעה. tekia terua tekia. So this is what they would do
for seven days in the בית המקדש. They would do a sticking
of ערבה aravah branches over around the מזבח. mizbei'ach. Okay looked, obviously
it evokes that whole theme of water like we bring, we bring
vegetation into the שול and flowers or whatever, so this they'd have
surrounded by ערבות aravos the the מזבח mizbei'ach every day of seven
days. בכל יום מקיפין את המזבח פעם אחת ואומרין אנא ה' הושיעה
נא אנא ה' הצליחה נא. B'chol yom makifin es ha'mizbei'ach pa'am achas
v'omrin Ana Hashem hoshia na Ana Hashem hatzlicha na. So now you
sort of see where we get our basis for הושענות. Hoshanos. Every
day they would march around the מזבח mizbei'ach once. רבי יהודה אומר
אני והו הושיעה נא. Rabbi Yehuda omer ani v'ho hoshia na. אותו
היום, Oso ha'yom, that day meaning day seven which we've learned is
a special day for ערבה, aravah, מקיפין את המזבח שבע פעמים, makifin
es ha'mizbei'ach sheva pe'amim, seven times. Okay our הושענא רבה. Hoshana Rabba.
So let's take a look now back at the גמרא. So our
משנה Mishnah said that this ערבה aravah thing they'd do for seven
days in the בית המקדש. That if the seventh day fell out
on שבת *Shabbos*, they would do it even on שבת *Shabbos*. If
one of the other days fell out on שבת *Shabbos*, then they
would not do it on שבת *Shabbos*, then
they would not do it on שבת *Shabbat*. Okay, so sometimes six,
sometimes seven, depending on whether שבת *Shabbos* fell out on the seventh
day or not. The גמרא *Gemara* says like this. ערבה Arava, בשביעי
מאי טעמא דחיא שבת *Arava b'shvii mai tama dachya Shabbos*? Why does
it override שבת *Shabbos* on the seventh day? Okay, meaning, you know,
I mean we've already introduced the idea that we shouldn't do it
on שבת *Shabbos* because it might lead to שבת *Shabbos* violation. That
we introduced when talking about לולב *Lulav*. Now, why then did לולב
*Lulav* we allowed the first day? Because the first day was מן
התורה *min haTorah*. So why by ערבה Arava. *arava*, what's special about
the seventh day? We've got the problem. Problem is you might come
to lead to שבת *Shabbos* violation. What's special about the seventh day,
that when the seventh day was שבת *Shabbos* we let it be
done on the seventh day? So let's take a look. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, כי אמר רבי יוחנן כדי לפרסמה שהיא מן התורה
*ki amar Rabbi Yochanan k'dei l'farsma shehi min haTorah*, in order to
publicize that it's biblical. Now, maybe this is the first you're hearing
that it's biblical, right? Where is it? How do you know it's
biblical? תורה *Torah* never says do the ערבות *aravos* in the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. So you might remember a גמרא *Gemara* earlier that
had two, that mentioned two דרשות *drashos*. One was ערבי נחל *arvei
nachal*, ערבי *arvei* in the plural, אחת ללולב ואחת למקדש *achas l'Lulav
v'achas l'Mikdash*. I think was the phrase. That there was the double
language said that there was a separate מצוה *mitzvah* of ערבה Arava
*arava* in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* and it's learned from the
double language ערבי *arvei*. And another approach said it's not learned from
the word ערבי *arvei*, it's just a הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha l'Moshe
m'Sinai*. Okay, but there is an, but there is the, the assumption
is, is that this ritual of the ערבה Arava *arava* in the
בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is biblical. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says,
so we have to make sure allow it one day to override
שבת *Shabbat*. Again, it's not a biblical violation. It's just overriding concerns,
right? We're not going to be concerned that it'll lead to a
שבת *Shabbos* violation. Okay, we have to allow it one day on
שבת *Shabbat* so people should understand this is not just some crazy
ritual, this is a real biblical thing. And they'll see that because
they'll see that we'll even do it sometimes on שבת *Shabbos*. Okay,
so that's what he said. כדי לפרסמה שהיא מן התורה *K'dei l'farsma
shehi min haTorah*, to publicize that this really is something that is
biblical. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אי הכי *ei hachi*, if that's
true, לולב נמי לידחי כדי לפרסמה שהוא מן התורה *Lulav nami lidchi
k'dei l'farsma shehu min haTorah*. Let לולב *Lulav* on חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed* override as well so people should know that it's biblical. Now,
know what that, what's biblical? The first day people know it's biblical.
But what might people not realize by לולב *Lulav* is biblical? The
other days, right? So here the point is you're doing this in
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Okay, and people might not realize that
the ערבה aravah *arava* is biblical, so we let ערבה aravah *arava*
be done on שבת *Shabbos*. People might not realize, says the גמרא
*Gemara*, that the other days of לולב *Lulav* in the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash* is biblical. So let's allow another day to override שבת
*Shabbat*, not only the first day. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, no,
לולב גזירה משום דרבה *Lulav gezeira mishum d'Rabba*. We can't let you
take לולב *Lulav* on שבת *Shabbos* in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*
on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*. You might come to carry. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, אי הכי ערבה aravah נמי ניגזור *ei hachi arava
nami nigzor*. So same issue. So you're basically saying don't worry about
רבה *Rabba*'s concerns in order to publicize. So if you want, so
say, so why is still לולב *Lulav* did and then ערבה aravah
*arava*? We know what the concerns are. But by ערבה aravah *arava*
we want to publicize. So let's also publicize לולב *Lulav*, that לולב
*Lulav* in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is biblical on חול המועד
*Chol HaMoed*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, no. ערבה aravah. שלוחי בית
דין Shluchei Beis Din. מייתי לה, לולב לכל מסור *Arava shluchei beis
din maysei lah, Lulav l'chol masar*. ערבה aravah *Arava* is handled by
שלוחי בית דין *shluchei beis din*. Meaning what happens? If you remember,
we just read the משנה Mishnah *mishna*, it says they would send
down people, they'd gather the ערבות *aravos*. ערבה aravah, *Arava* was done
all, it was not basically a big public thing. Even ערבה aravah.
*arava* in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, you know, messengers of בית
דין *beis din* would gather the ערבות *aravos*. Who would put the
ערבות *aravos* by the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*? כהנים *Kohanim*. It would not
be a big public thing. So therefore, we can allow it to
be done on שבת *Shabbos*, and we're not so concerned. Whereas לולב
*Lulav*, when it was done in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, what
did we read in the משנה Mishnah *mishna*? We read that everybody
came to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. There those concerns are going
to be heightened concerns. Now, the other day I think it was
Sam, I think it was you who asked, so I don't get
it, but at least let the כהנים *Kohanim* take it in the
בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* on חול המועד *Chol HaMoed*, the לולב *Lulav*,
right? So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* basically addresses that. And תוספות *Tosafos* says
look, if we're not letting fundamentally it's something that everybody can do.
So once we're disallowing everybody to do the לולב *Lulav* on שבת
*Shabbos*, we're not going to only allow the כהנים *Kohanim*. But as
opposed to the ערבה aravah *arava*, which starts by something that is
uniquely a כהן *Kohen* ritual. So there, it's not like you don't
do it and you do do it. In general, it's only done
by the כהנים *Kohanim*. That we can allow on שבת *Shabbos*. So
what is the גמרא *Gemara* saying? The גמרא *Gemara* is saying the
following: there's no biblical violation in any of this. It's all rabbinic
concerns. Are we going to allow those rabbinic concerns to get in
the way of doing the מצוה *mitzvah*? By לולב *Lulav*, we're going
to let you do the biblical מצוה *mitzvah* on the first day
where everybody has to, but we're not going to let you do
it in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. which is biblical in the
בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*, but only in
the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*, we will allow on day seven in
order that people should realize how important it is that it is
a biblical idea. So let's allow לולב *Lulav* on חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed* because it's biblical in the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* and let
people know that it's biblical in the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. No,
לולב *Lulav* is too much of a public event. So we're only
going to allow it on day one where it is biblical for
everyone. We're not going to allow it on the other days. ערבה
aravah *Aravah*, which is a more controlled ritual and limited ritual, that
we will allow even, you know, we will allow in the בית
המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* even on שבת *Shabbat* when the seventh day is
שבת *Shabbat* so that people are aware that this is a biblical
מצוה *mitzvah* in the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*. Yeah?
Did you have any thoughts? You know, there's so many קרבנות *korbanot*
offered on סוכות Succos *Sukkot*. How'd they do that with all these
branches covering over on the מזבח *mizbe'ach*?
I mean the מזבח *mizbe'ach* was big, was 32 אמות *amot*, it
was like
50 feet amount of
No, this,
they're surrounding the base and there's a little overhang at the edge.
Like imagine you just have like a little canopy like on top
of you. Yeah, I do imagine. Yeah.
Okay, no, I get you. No, I want to see you have
a green... You want to see me draw? Where's the... all right,
big... It looks like תפילין *tefillin*.
It
looks like Jim Nantz.
All right, whatever. Anyway. ערבה aravah *Aravah*!
Anyway,
besides...
now it looks like I don't know what it looks like. Anyway,
it didn't jut out as much, but okay. Just a general idea.
Anyway fine, whatever they did. Okay, anyway, all right, they had little
things. Anyway fine, whatever. And then you have them go on like
this, you know, right? And here are those things and the corner
would go up and you'd have like little... it would be very
well-spaced, right? What's the problem?
I should I want to see a כהן *Kohen*...
All right,
anyway, 32 אמות *amot* at the base, yeah, 50 feet or so,
yeah,
huge base.
It only went up, it only became like 28 at the top.
It's not, it's not this big protrusion. Yeah, yeah, what? They obviously
left a path to get to...
Yeah, I mean you had this, I
mean it wasn't right at the base around the side. What? I
mean they had Italian gardens. What?
You just had something like that. You know, but the overhang could
have been like 10 feet high and you're still walking around here.
How high was it?
What?
How high was it? It was, how high was I'm trying to
remember... I know it was
32 at the base, 12 אמות *amot* or something, yeah, something pretty...
whole willow trees, willow branches had to be huge...
you can get... Okay, anyway, all right. Yes?
The calendar was engineered so that הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana Rabbah*
could not be...
Okay, so we're going to get to that. That was not yet
at the time that this was being written but that will be
the case. So let's keep on reading. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
like this: אי הכי *I hachi* says the גמרא *Gemara*, כל יומא
נמי לדחי *kol yoma nami lidchi*. So look, says the גמרא *Gemara*,
why pick day seven? They're all it's biblical every day, so let
every day let it always override שבת *Shabbat*, you know, ערבה aravah,
*Aravah*. Again, not override because there's no violation, but let it be
done on שבת *Shabbat*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: אתי לספוקי בלולב
*Ati lisfaku'ei b'lulav*. No, that will undermine the special nature of לולב
*Lulav*. Now you're letting ערבה aravah. *Aravah* override שבת *Shabbat* whenever שבת
*Shabbat* falls out and לולב *Lulav* can only be done on שבת
*Shabbat* on the first day. So you don't want ערבה aravah. *Aravah*
to be more important than לולב *Lulav*. So you have to give
ערבה aravah, *Aravah* just one day that it can only that it
can be done on שבת *Shabbat*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: ולדחי
ביום טוב ראשון *V'lidchi b'yom tov rishon*. Okay, let's make it the
same day. When the first day יום טוב *Yom Tov* falls out
on שבת *Shabbat*, you do both לולב *Lulav* and ערבה aravah *Aravah*.
Why give it a separate day? So the גמרא *Gemara* says: No,
לא מוכחא מילתא *lo mukcha miltah*. It's not then obvious that ערבה
aravah *Aravah* is what's going on here, that it's because of ערבה
aravah *Aravah*. The whole point, the whole special nature of ערבה aravah
*Aravah* is lost, that was the whole point of allowing it to
be done in the first place. אמרי amri, *Amrei*, people will say,
לולב הוא דקדחי *Lulav hu d'kadachi*. Oh yeah, you know why we're
doing this stuff on שבת *Shabbat*? Because we're doing it because of
לולב *Lulav*. Once we're doing לולב *Lulav*, we do the ערבה aravah
*Aravah* thing as well. But nobody recognizes the importance of the ערבה
*Aravah* ritual. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: ולדחי בחד מהנך *V'lidchi b'chad
me'hanei*. Okay,
fine, we get you want to give it only one day, not
every day. You want to give it a distinct day. Why give
it day seven? Give it one of the other days. Says no,
כיון דקמפקת ליה מראשון *kivan d'kamfatkeis lomei rishon*,
once it can't be day one, אוקמה אשביעי *ukmah shevi'i*, you give
it the seventh day. You know, any middle day gets lost. Beginning
or the end are very distinct points. Okay now, by the way,
that's interesting because as I read to you from the following משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* and as we know in our experience, הושענא רבה Hoshana
Rabba *Hoshana Rabbah* is a special day, right? And you do a
whole thing and you do it seven times and the whole thing.
So why didn't the גמרא *Gemara* say here the reason we gave
it day seven was the day to override שבת *Shabbat* was day
seven was the big deal, it was הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana
Rabbah*, etc.? It sounds a little bit from this גמרא *Gemara* that
it worked in the opposite, that the reason day seven became... became
the big deal and became הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba was because we
needed to pick one special day for ערבה, and once it wasn't
going to be day one, we picked day seven. Now that's not
normally the sense you get. Normally the sense you get is that
you're building up to a climax, right? You walk around every day,
sort of like the whole יריחו Yericho story, you know? You walk
and you walk, and then day seven, like that's the, that's when
it all comes to a culmination. So it is funny that the
גמרא didn't just say because day seven is the special day of
ערבה. It sounds like it came through the back door. We had
to pick a day to be the special day. It wasn't going
to be day one, so we'll pick day seven. All right. Anyways,
the גמרא says like this. אי הכי האידנא נמי לידחי. Ei hachi
ha'idna nami lidchi.
So let it override today. So today, why don't we do הושענא
רבה Hoshana Rabba on שבת? Why don't we take it on שבת
out of the בית המקדש? Now the point is, רש''י Rashi and
תוספות both ask, one minute, the only way we said that we
allow it was because there was, it was not a used public
ritual, that it was done just by the כהנים, you know? So
what's this question, do it today? Today it's become a public ritual.
So they say, well, maybe we should do it today in also
like in a more controlled fashion, only somehow let it be done
in a supervised way with שלוחי בית דין. It's a funny question
because we've already explained that the only way we were allowing it
was because it was a more limited ritual. Anyway, let's see what
the גמרא's answer is. אנן לא ידעינן בקביעא דירחא.
We don't know when ראש חודש is, so we don't really know
which day is exactly day seven, or we pretend like we don't
know. And therefore we don't have those earlier allowances. So the גמרא
says, אינהו דידעי בקביעא דירחא לידחו? Inhu d'yadi b'kivia d'yarcha lidchu?
So those in ארץ ישראל that know when ראש חודש is, let
it be done. Why don't they do a הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba
ritual on שבת? So the גמרא says, כי אתא בר הדיא אמר,
Ki ata Bar Hadya amar, when בר הדיא Bar Hadya came,
he said from ארץ ישראל, he said, לא איקלע, Lo ikla, it
never happened. הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba never fell out on שבת. Now,
by the way, that is the way that our current calendar works.
Because if anybody knows the basic mnemonic, anybody knows this? If you
don't know this, you should learn this. It's basically לא אד''ו ראש
Lo adu rosh
and לא בד''ו פסח. Lo bedu pesach. So ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
never falls out on Sunday, Wednesday, and Friday. Now ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah and סוכות Succos? fall out, the first day of סוכות Succos
fall out on the same day. So סוכות, Succos the first day
of סוכות never falls out on Sunday, Wednesday, and Friday. Now הושענא
רבה Hoshana Rabba is which day of סוכות? Day seven. So for
הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba, to be שבת, what day of the week
would the first day of סוכות have to be? If הושענא רבה
Hoshana Rabba is שבת, come on, count it up. If this is
שבת and that's day seven, Sunday is day one, right? So if
הושענא Hoshana רבה is on שבת, okay, then סוכות would have to
be on day one, but it's לא אד''ו ראש. Lo adu rosh.
So in our current calendar, הושענא רבה will never fall out on
שבת. Okay? So but the time the גמרא was being written, they
did not have the fixed calendar, but they just are saying it
never fell out that way, which means that they constructed it
so it would not fall out that way. Now that's a little
bit bizarre because the basic point is, you know what? If it
were to fall out that way, it would override שבת. But we
did not want to have to deal with that, allowing this whole
הושענא ritual to override שבת because it's not even biblical nowadays anymore,
it's not in the בית המקדש, so we made sure it would
never actually happen. That was the first answer. So כי אתא רבין,
Ki ata Ravin, when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל וכל נחותי
v'chol nechusei and all those that made ירידה, yerida, that's what it
literally means, with him, all those coming from ישראל to בבל, Bavel,
אמרי, they said, איקלע. Ikla. No, actually, it has fallen out on
שבת ולא אידחי, v'lo idchi, and we didn't let it override. Now
why not? According to the משנה, Mishnah you should override שבת, הושענא
רבה, or override be done on שבת. ואלא קשיא, V'ela kashya, but
it's difficult. So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, מאן לימא לן
דערבה בנטילה, Man leima lan d'arava b'netila, who told you that the
act of ערבה that they would do in the בית המקדש that
we said is done seven days and is done on שבת, just
means like the holding of the ערבה and the or the walking
around of the altar like we mentioned? דילמא בזקיפה. Dilma b'zekifa. Remember
when we read the משנה, Mishnah the first point is that they
would put it by the altar. And therefore what? So therefore he's
saying
our current ritual of walking around and הושענא רבה and whatever is
not the ritual mentioned in the משנה. The ritual mentioned in the
משנה is the putting of it by the side of the altar.
And therefore, he says, it actually is something that we don't do
nowadays. So your argument, if the משנה let it be done on
שבת, let's do it nowadays on שבת, we don't do what was
done in the משנה. The thing the משנה was talking about was
putting it by the altar. What we do So is a different
thing, it's just the walking around. So איתיבי esvei אביי, Abaye, אביי
Abaye asked on this. לולב וערבה שישה ושבעה. Lulav v'aravah shishah v'shivah.
You would do לולב and ערבה six and seven days. מאי לאו,
mai lav, so the fact that it's talking about לולב and ערבה
in the same breath, לולב כערבה, lulav k'aravah, מאי לאו כלולב? mai
lav k'lulav? It must mean that what you did with the ערבה
like what you did by the לולב. מה לולב בנטילה אף ערבה
בנטילה. ma lulav b'netilah af aravah b'netilah. So the same way by
לולב we're just talking about holding it, by ערבה also. So yes,
the ritual in the משנה is not the ritual of planting it
by the altar. The ritual of the משנה is the marching with
it. And we do it nowadays and we should do it on
שבת. So גמרא says, מי איריא, mi'iri, is that a proof? הכי
איתא והכי איתא. hachi issa v'hachi issa. Each one is according to
its parameters. So לולב by holding and ערבה maybe the משנה was
only talking about the planting by the altar. Okay, איתיבי esvei
אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye is going to cry again. בכל יום מקיפין
את המזבח פעם אחת. bechol yom makkifin es hamizbeach paam achas. This
is the משנה we read. Every day they walk around the altar
once. ואותו היום שבע פעמים, v'oso hayom sheva peamim, and that day
they'd walk around seven times. מאי לאו בערבה. mai lav b'aravah. So
you see the משנה emphasizes the ritual of walking around, and it
means walking around with the ערבה. So that's the ritual and that
we do nowadays. גמרא says, לא
בלולב. lo b'lulav. No, maybe the walking around the ערבה ritual was
just the putting it by the altar and the walking around was
what we did by the לולב, that's what we do nowadays is
we do a marching around with a לולב. But we have ערבה,
alright, but it's not specifically the מצוה of ערבה.
The מצוה of ערבה that is underscored in the משנה that's done
seven days including שבת is the מצוה of the מזבח, that's the
argument, which is not done today, which is why we don't do
it on שבת. Okay, whereas the other rituals were more focused on
the whole לולב experience. So גמרא says, אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה בערבה, amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha b'aravah, but
doesn't רב נחמן Rav Nachman say that no, it was done with
the ערבה alone, it was an ערבה ritual. אמר ליה, amar lei,
he said back, הוא אמר לך בערבה שקויח. hu amar lach b'aravah
shkoach. He said it was an ערבה, דאנא אמינא בלולב, d'ana aminah
b'lulav, but I don't agree, I think it was a לולב and
that explains why we don't do it on שבת because they would
not do a marching ritual with the ערבה. איתמר, itmar, it was
taught, רבי אליעזר אומר בלולב, Rabbi Eliezer omer b'lulav, רב שמואל בר
נחמן אמר רבי חנינא בערבה. Rav Shmuel bar Nachman amar Rabbi Chanina
b'aravah. So it was a debate, was the marching ritual with a
לולב or was it with an ערבה. וכן אמר רב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה בערבה. v'chein amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha
b'aravah. Now okay, so אמר ליה amar lei so and just to
end this, אמר רבא לרב יצחק בריה דרבה בר בר חנה, amar
Rava l'Rav Yitzchak brei d'Rabbah bar bar Chana, בר אורייא, bar urya,
son of a lion, תא ואימא לך מילתא מעליותא דהוה אמר אבוך.
ta v'eima lach milsa maalyasa d'havi amri abuch. Let me tell you
a great thing your father used to say. הדנן, hadnan, that that
the משנה says בכל יום מקיפין את המזבח פעם אחת ואותו היום
שבע פעמים, bechol yom makkifin es hamizbeach paam achas v'oso hayom makkifin
es hamizbeach sheva peamim, that they did a seven-day marching ritual. הכי
אמר אבוך משמיה דרבי אלעזר בלולב. hachi amar abuch mishmei d'Rabbi Elazar
b'lulav. It was with a לולב, not the ערבה, and that's why
we don't do the ערבה ritual today because the ערבה ritual was
really about the altar. Okay, so we will pick up with here
tomorrow, but the question we're left with is why nowadays do we
not do the ערבה ritual on שבת? And the current answer, the
one answer the גמרא is kind of leaning is either we manipulated
the calendar so we don't have to deal with it, or number
two, the ritual of the ערבה that was done on שבת was
by the altar and the ritual we do of the marching was
not the focus of the ערבה ritual. And that's the reason we
don't do it on שבת because we don't have that ritual anymore.
But we're going to wrap this discussion up, we still haven't finished
it, we'll continue it tomorrow. Okay.