בוקר טוב *Boker Tov*, today's דף *daf* is מ"ד *Mem Dalet* 44,
we're at the end of מ"ג עמוד ב' *Mem Gimmel Amud Bet*,
we're in the middle of discussing the מצוה mitzvah *Mitzvah* of ערבה
arava *Arava*, and what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* has said so far,
and this is going to be the focus for the rest of
the דף *daf* today, is number one, the assumption that taking the
ערבה arava *Arava* in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash? *Beis Hamikdash* is
biblical. I reminded you that an earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara* attributed it
either to the verse of ערבי arvei נחל *Arvei Nachal* in the
double language, or a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai *Halacha L'Moshe
MiSinai*, and we're going to see that repeated in a few minutes.
And it would be biblical all seven days, and but because it
was obviously not as known that this was biblical,
they allowed it to be taken, although it was never a מצוה
mitzvah *Mitzvah* out of the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*, in contrast to לולב
lulav, *Lulav*, they nevertheless allowed it to be taken one day on
שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat* so that people should be aware that it's biblical.
And because the first day wouldn't have been obvious, they chose the
seventh day. That seems to be how the seventh day for us
הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana Rabba* got its weight and got its
significance. Again, they wouldn't violate שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*, it just meant that
they would not be concerned that it could lead to possible problems.
And another issue that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* mentions about why those
concerns aren't really so present is because it is not a free-for-all,
it's not that everybody comes to the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* and every
individual does it. It is something that is basically controlled by the
מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash* authorities, by בית דין Beit Din *Beis Din*, by
the כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim*. So that is the idea that it's seven
days, and if הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana Rabba* falls out on
שבת Shabbat. *Shabbos*, they do it even on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* in
the מקדש Mikdash? *Mikdash*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s question right now
is why don't we take it on הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana
Rabba* out of the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*? Because as we learned before,
I mean even if our practice in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz *Chutz
La'aretz* has changed or whatever, we'll revisit that, but at least according
to the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, they would take the לולב lulav *Lulav*
on the first day on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*. Then why don't we
in parallel out of the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* take the ערבה arava
*Arava* on the seventh day, on הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana Rabba*
on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*? Why don't we do it even on שבת
Shabbat, *Shabbat*? So the first answer the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is well,
maybe in theory you could, but we've arranged the calendar to avoid
that from ever happening. We'll get back to that in a minute.
But the other answer is no, actually it has happened that הושענא
רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana Rabba* fell out on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* and
they don't take it out of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis
Hamikdash*. So again the question is why is that different then at
least according to the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* that they would take the
לולב lulav, *Lulav* when the first day was on שבת Shabbat? *Shabbat*
out of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*? And right now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is, whoa, whoa, wait a minute, says
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, let's understand what exactly is the practice we're
referring to. What was the later משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* said that what
they would do in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* is that they would
stick these palm branches by the מזבח mizbeach *Mizbeach* and it would
have this overhang on the מזבח mizbeach *Mizbeach*, and it also refers
to a procession around the מזבח mizbeach *Mizbeach*.
So what was the practice in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* that was
the primary? If it was fundamentally putting it by the מזבח mizbeach
*Mizbeach*, then we can't do it out of the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*,
so therefore the whole question is moot, right? So therefore that's why
we don't do it on שבת Shabbat? *Shabbat*, because we're not really
doing what the primary action was. But if the primary action was
the procession, then you actually have a good question. But the response
is no, maybe the procession was done with the לולב lulav *Lulav*,
maybe the real thing with the ערבה arava, *Arava* was the thing
by the מזבח mizbeach? *Mizbeach*. So that now is our issue. What
was the real thing done by the מזבח mizbeach, *Mizbeach*, meaning they
did both, but one maybe was with the לולב lulav *Lulav*, but
what was the focus of what they did in the מקדש Mikdash,
*Mikdash*? Was it the sticking it by the מזבח *Mizbeach*, so then
there's really just not a real practice of that out of the
מקדש mikdash. *Mikdash*, or is it the procession or maybe just the
holding on it because there's also not a מזבח *Mizbeach* also, but
if it's more walking in some type of a procession, maybe we
can say we are really doing that. And therefore that will help
explain why we do or don't do it on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*,
as maybe we don't really ever really redo what's being done in
the מקדש mikdash. *Mikdash*. Why would you say
you need מזבח *Mizbeach* for the procession? That you could say, you
could say.
But we will see that a phrase that's going to be used
in a minute that might indicate that if it's not about the
sticking it by the מזבח *Mizbeach*, it's more an activity than having
it surround the מזבח *Mizbeach*, maybe we could be seen as doing
that type of an activity outside. So that's the issue. What was
the focus in the מקדש mikdash. *Mikdash* and therefore how much are
what we are doing really a continuation of that, which might help
explain why we don't do it on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up with this in the following. It says
איתיבי *Aiseivei*, it starts with the line that says לולב lulav *Lulav*,
about 10 lines from the bottom. Little asterisk. לולב lulav *Lulav* overrides
שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* בתחילתו *b'tchilato*,
so we have a ברייתא braita *Braita*, תוספתא *Tosefta*, that says לולב
lulav *Lulav* overrides שבת Shabbat *Shabbat* not again literally, but we don't
have to worry about שבת Shabbos *Shabbat* possible inadvertent שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*
violations. You're allowed to take the לולב lulav. *Lulav* on שבת Shabbat?
*Shabbat* on the first day בתחילתו *b'tchilato*, the beginning of the חג
*Chag*. וערבה בסופו *V'arava b'sofo*, and the ערבה arava, *Arava* overrides שבת
Shabbat *Shabbat* at the end, meaning הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshana Rabba*
if it falls out on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*, you can take the
ערבה arava, *Arava* on שבת Shabbat. *Shabbat*. פעם אחת *Pam achat*, now
that might be talking about the מקדש mikdash. *Mikdash*. פעם אחת חל
שביעי של ערבה aravah להיות בשבת *Pam achat chal shvii shel Arava
lihyot b'Shabbat*, once הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba. *Hoshana Rabba*, שביעי של ערבה
aravah *shvii shel Arava*, fell out on שבת Shabbat *Shabbat*. והביאו מרביות
של ערבה aravah. מערב שבת, Shabbat and they brought like huge bundles
of ערבה aravah on Friday because, again, you have to, you can't
violate שבת. Shabbat You can take it on שבת, Shabbat but you
have to be very careful to do the preparations beforehand. והניחום בעזרה,
veheni'chum ba'azara, and they put them in the courtyard. הכירו בהן בייתוסים,
hikiru bahen baitusim, and the בייתוסים Baitusites saw what was going on.
It's interesting, normally the opponents of the rabbis are the צדוקים, Tzedukim,
but בייתוסים Baitusim was another sect at that time, and also according
to this, you know, this is not in the תורה, Torah, it's
not explicit, so the בייתוסים Baitusites were opposed to this practice. And
they saw what was going on, ונטלום, unetalum, and they stole the
ערבות, aravas, וכבשום תחת אבנים, vechevashum tachat avanim, and they buried them
under stones, and which is מוקצה. muktzeh. למחר, lemachar, the next day,
הכירו בהן עם הארץ, hikiru bahen am ha'aretz, the, you know, the
people of the land, the common people saw what had happened, and
they didn't want to not do their very exciting ערבה aravah. ritual.
ושרטום מתחת אבנים, vesharatum mitachat avanim,
they pulled them out from underneath the rocks, והביאום הכהנים, vehevi'um hakohanim,
and then the כהנים Kohanim brought them into the עזרה, azara, וזקפום
בצידי המזבח, vezakfum betzidei hamizbe'ach,
and they stuck them by the sides of the altar. לפי, lefi,
why did all this happen? לפי שאין בייתוסים מודים שחיבוט ערבה דוחה
את השבת, lefi she'ein baitusim modim shechibut arava doche et haShabbat, because
the בייתוסים Baitusites do not agree that the חיבוט ערבה chibut arava
overrides שבת. Shabbat. Now, there's a couple of fascinating parts about that
story. Number one is why did it need the עם הארץ am
ha'aretz to take it under from under the rocks? Big deal, it's
מוקצה. muktzeh. Shouldn't they be willing to override מוקצה? muktzeh? And presumably
the answer is no. Even if they let them take the ערבה
aravah on שבת, Shabbat, as we said, they didn't actually allow to
override a prohibition. They just said, we'll allow you to do it.
But interestingly, although the ערבות aravas might be considered מוקצה, muktzeh, but
whatever it is, no, that you're allowed, but some other issue, like
moving a rock, that presumably they wouldn't have done. So you needed
the עם הארץ am ha'aretz who weren't so מקפיד makpid on it
to remove it from under the rock. Although it does say, it
didn't say that they lifted off the rock, it says they pulled
it from under the rocks. Maybe that's like טלטול מן הצד, tiltul
min hatzad, which is allowed by מוקצה. muktzeh. So number one, a
fascinating thing is that the rocks became an impediment, you know,
because even if they're allowing it on שבת, Shabbat, it doesn't mean
they're allowing everything. The other fascinating thing is it did not say
that the בייתוסים Baitusites
rejected the whole practice. Notice what it says the בייתוסים Baitusites didn't
agree. They didn't agree שחיבוט ערבה דוחה את השבת. shechibut arava doche
et haShabbat.
They didn't agree to do it on שבת. Shabbat And what do
you mean דוחה? doche? What do you mean override? What violation is
being done? So it's quite fascinating, right? The בייתוסים Baitusites fundamentally were
okay with the ritual, they just didn't like it on שבת, Shabbat,
okay? They didn't have a problem, you know, but what, what, what
was the real שבת Shabbat, problem other than some vague concern of
where it might lead? So that's point one. That's just an interesting
footnote about that whole story. Why is it relevant for us? Well,
if you wanted to infer from here what was the primary act
that was done by the ערבה, Arava what would you say based
on this story? That's the question at hand. Was it about putting
it by the altar or was it by walking with it? וזקפום.
vezakfum. Ah, so Dov jumps to the line וזקפום, vezakfum, which is
what the גמרא Gemara does. But if you were to have asked
me, I would have started by the line where it says והביאום
הכהנים וזקפום בצידי המזבח, vehevi'um hakohanim vezakfum betzidei hamizbe'ach, seemed to emphasize
the placing of it, that was the big deal. But actually the
גמרא Gemara reads it this ברייתא braita, like Dov did. And the
גמרא Gemara focuses on the word שחיבוט ערבה דוחה את השבת. shechibut
arava doche et haShabbat. That that is the verb, that is the
key act. Now, what is חיבוט ערבה? chibut arava? So חיבוט chibut
could be, right, like when you say לחבוט, lachbot, you know, it
could mean like to hit. And we actually know the practice of
banging the ערבות. aravas. But interestingly, that hasn't been mentioned yet. And
interestingly the גמרא Gemara is assuming that the word חיבוט chibut means
something like the carrying or the waving of the ערבה, Arava okay?
And therefore, since it describes the key act as חיבוט, chibut, and
חיבוט chibut here is understood as taking or carrying or waving, therefore
the גמרא Gemara says
אלמא, alma, you see, בנטילה היא. benetila hi. The fundamental act is
the taking of the ערבה, Arava not the placing by the altar.
תיובתא. tiyuvta. That is an ultimate contradiction that proves that point. And
therefore we're back to square one. If the basic act in the
מקדש mikdash. was the holding and the shaking and the taking, why
could it not also be done, why is it not done outside
of the מקדש mikdash, on שבת? Shabbat. That was our question. And
don't tell me, oh, we don't really do the real thing. Because
you know what? If it's really about the taking of it, like
the taking of a לולב, lulav we could do it out of
the מקדש. mikdash, So they say why don't we do it on
הושענא רבא Hoshana Rabba on שבת? Shabbat. According to the גמרא Gemara
where that actually could happen, that הושענא רבא Hoshana Rabba falls on
שבת. Shabbat. So we're back to that question. Dov has a question
before
we...
I mean, isn't this the first time we saw חידוש, Chidush, right?
Yes. And we're going to see it again. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ואלו נדחו, V'Eilu Nidchu, so why doesn't it override? Why don't
we do it on שבת Shabbat, out of the
מקדש? Mikdash דכיון דאנן לא דחינן אינהו נמי לא דחי. D'keivan d'anan
lo dachinan inhu nami lo dachi. No, because so since we in
outside of Israel, since this is going back to the same thing
that we explained about why we don't take the לולב lulav on
the first day outside of Israel where we don't, we act as
if we don't know which is really the right
calendar day. So therefore we're not going to override שבת Shabbat because
there's always an element of doubt what day it is. So therefore
they're not going to do it even in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
That's why it never appeared in the משנה Mishnah? to do it
outside of the מקדש. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. So
the גמרא Gemara says
דהאי יום טוב ראשון דלדידן לא דחי לדידהו דחי. D'hai yom tov
rishon delididan lo dachi lididu dachi. One minute, but by לולב, lulav
there is a day לולב lulav they do take it in ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. The משנה Mishnah made it sound like in לולב
lulav they took in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael on the first day
of יום טוב Yom Tov on שבת Shabbat even though we don't
take that, we don't do it out of Israel. אמרי, Amri, top
of מד עמוד א, Mem Dalet Amud Aleph, you can say
לדידן נמי לא דחי. Lididun nami lo dachi. No, you're wrong. They
don't take the לולב lulav in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael on שבת
Shabbat, either on the first day, against the משנה. Mishnah That actually
is our practice. In Israel they do not take the לולב Lulav
on the first day if it's שבת. Shabbat? So what about the
fact that it says you do it in the משנה? Mishnah ואלא
קשיא הני תרתי, Ve'ela kasha hani tarti, what about the contradiction of
משניות, Mishnayot, or the contradiction but the juxtaposition of the two משניות
Mishnayot that seem to indicate you did it in Israel
when it fell out on שבת? Shabbat? דתניא חדא, Detanya chada, one
משנה Mishnah. says כל המוליכין את לולביהן להר הבית, Kol hamolichin et
lulaveihen l'Har HaBayit, everybody would prepare for שבת Shabbat by bringing their
לולבים lulavim to the
הר הבית. Har HaBayit. ותנן אידך, V'itnan idach, the other משנה Mishnah
says לבית הכנסת. L'beit ha-knesset. And how, so what was it? Would
they take it to שול Shul or would they take it to
the
בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash ומתרצינן Umetartzinan and we explained
yesterday, כאן בזמן שבית המקדש קיים כאן בזמן שאין בית המקדש קיים,
Kan bizman sheBeit HaMikdash kayyam kan bizman she'ein Beit HaMikdash kayyam, that
when there's a temple they went, they would take it in the
temple. When there wasn't a temple they would take it in the
שול. Shul. And they would take it on שבת. Shabbat The משנה
Mishnah makes it clear that they would take it on שבת. Shabbat
So how can you tell me we don't take the לולב Lulav,
you don't take on שבת Shabbos if it's יום טוב? Yom Tov?
So the גמרא Gemara says לא. Lo. No, that's not the way
to read the משנה. Mishnah, אידי ואידי בזמן שבית המקדש קיים. Idi
v'idi bizman sheBeit HaMikdash kayyam. The משניות Mishnayot could be talking both
in the time of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, ולא קשיא, V'lo
kasha, so which was it? Was it in the מקדש or was
it in the
שול? Shul? כאן במקדש כאן בגבולין, Kan beMikdash kan begivulin, it depends
where you are. If you're living in the environs of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
you go on שבת Shabbos to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and
you take the לולב. Lulav If you're living outside of the
immediate environs of הר הבית, Har HaBayit, you go and you take
it in the שול. Shul. So is it true that the משניות
Mishnayot have you taking it on שבת Shabbos in שול? Shul? Yes.
But maybe only at the time of the temple. Nowadays where there's
no temple and therefore out of Israel we always keep two days
יום טוב, Yom Tov, so for sort of consistency of practice, even
in Israel we're not going to take the לולב Lulav on the
first day יום טוב. Yom Tov. Since we don't take the לולב
Lulav on the first day יום טוב Yom Tov out of Israel,
we're not going to take it in Israel either. And that's why
we don't take ערבה Arava. out of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash,
also even in Israel because we're not going to take it out
of Israel. So the basic answer of the גמרא Gemara is the
following: לולב Lulav, is taken the first day on שבת Shabbos in
the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash. ערבה Arava the seventh day on שבת.
Shabbos. It used to be that לולב Lulav was taken even out
of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. the first day on שבת, Shabbos,
but that was in Israel. Now that the established practice is that
out of Israel we keep two days יום טוב Yom Tov and
therefore we always act as if there's a doubt, and therefore we
won't take it on שבת, Shabbos they don't take לולב Lulav on
שבת Shabbos. anymore in Israel either. And the same is true about
the ערבה. Arava What the גמרא Gemara is saying is in theory
you're right, maybe originally the ערבה Arava was taken in all of
Israel on the הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba on שבת, but since now
it's not done that way out of Israel because of the idea
of ספיקא דיומא, sfeika d'yoma, we don't do it in Israel either.
So it's the same story, the same הלכה. halacha. In theory it
should be done in Israel on שבת, but it's not because it's
not done in חוץ לארץ because of ספיקא דיומא. sfeika d'yoma. Okay,
so that is the conclusion of לולב Lulav and ערבה. Arava Now
by the way,
so the תוספות Tosafot does raise an interesting question, which is the
גמרא Gemara raised the issue of הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba, never falling
on שבת. And the גמרא Gemara said, you know what, הושענא רבה
Hoshana Rabba could fall on שבת. But this says okay, that's all
very nice, but we've now constructed the calendar that הושענא רבה Hoshana
Rabba never falls on שבת. That's just the way the calendar is
constructed. And תוספות Tosafot says isn't this ironic? We've constructed the calendar
so הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba never falls on שבת, so the whole
discussion of the גמרא Gemara actually is now a moot point because
we will never have הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba, on שבת and you'll
always be able to take the ערבה Arava on הושענא רבה. Hoshana
Rabba. But guess what can fall on שבת with our calendar? First
day of סוכות. Sukkot. Not only the first day of סוכות, Sukkot,
but if the first day of סוכות Sukkot is falling on שבת,
what else is falling on שבת? First
day—no, not פסח. Pesach.
First
day of ראש
השנה.
Rosh Hashanah. Right. So we will allow the calendar to happen so
that you won't take לולב Lulav and you won't blow שופר Shofar
on the biblical days, but don't worry you'll always be able to
do הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabbah. with the ערבה Arava thing. So תוספות
Tosafot says it's quite ironic. So if you take a look back
at תוספות Tosafot לא איקלא Lo Ikla מ"ג ע"ב, Mem Gimmel Amud
Bet, תוספות Tosafot says like this: he says, he says, ויש לומר
veyesh
lomar or like it's I don't know where it is, two-thirds down,
the line starts with ודאורייתא. ve'de'oraita. He says so those that are
דאורייתא de'oraita לא חיישינן, lo chashinan, we're not concerned that you won't
do the biblical מצוה mitzvah and we allow it to be on
שבת? ויש לומר Veyesh lomar you could say אין הכי נמי ein
hachi nami דהני דכתיבי בהדיא, dahani diktivi behedya, things that are explicit
in the תורה, Torah, שופר Shofar and
לולב, Lulav. לא אתי לפקפוקי בהו, lo asi lefakpuki behu, if on
one year it falls out on שבת and you don't do it,
it's not going to undermine the institution, because people understand that it's
a real serious obligation. אבל Aval ערבה Arava דרבנן, de'rabbanan, ערבה Arava
which is rabbinic meaning out of the מקדש it's rabbinic, so אתי
לפקפוקי בהו, asi lefakpuki behu, so people it'll undermine the institution if
we don't do it, so you know what, it's right, we want
to ensure that you always do ערבות, Aravas, you always have הושענא
רבה, Hoshanah Rabbah and okay sometimes you won't do the biblical מצוה
mitzvah but at least those won't be undermined. Okay, and then תוספות
Tosafot has other explanations about ways in which it could be שופר
Shofar you could still do it and if there's a בית דין
etc. etc. Anyway, okay. Yes, or לולב Lulav. he says there are
two days of יום טוב, Yom Tov, so right, so that's the
other thing, so if you look at the end
right, to דתוקע d'toke'a שופר Shofar and לולב Lulav. even though they're
not on
the first day, you don't do the biblical, you do it on
the second day right. So if you look that's the next answer
תוספות Tosafot says, ועוד דמספק עבדינן תרי יומי וכי יומא מיקלי יום
ראשון בשבת אין כאן ביטול לגמרי דתקע בשני, ve'od demisafek avidna trei
yoma vekhi yoma mikle yom rishon beShabbat ein kan bittul legamre d'toke'a
besheni, there you go exactly what you said. So yeah, we'll allow
the first day of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and סוכות Sukkot to
fall on שבת but we're going to ensure that הושענא רבה Hoshana
Raba. never does so we always get to do ערבה. Arava Although
the גמרא Gemara we're dealing with the possibility that הושענא רבה Hoshana
Raba. could be on שבת and said if that what happened you
wouldn't do ערבה Arava because now because of ספקא דיומא Safeka deYoma
we don't do these things even in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay,
so now back to מ"ד ע"א Mem Dalet Amud Aleph by about
six lines from the top. אמר ליה אביי לרבא, Amar lei Abaye
leRava, so אביי Abaye said to רבא, Rava, מאי שנא Mai shna
לולב Lulav דעבדינן ליה שבעה זכר למקדש, d'avidna lei shiva zecher leMikdash,
why out of the temple do we do a seven-day commemoration of
לולב, Lulav, right we do it all seven days, that was the
תקנה takkana of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai, ומאי
שנא u'mai shna ערבה Arava? דלא עבדינן ליה שבעה זכר למקדש, delo
avidna lei shiva zecher leMikdash, ערבה Arava we don't do it seven
days, they did it seven days in the מקדש but we only
do ערבה Arava one day. By the way you could even strengthen
the question, רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai never made
a תקנה takkana to do ערבה Arava out of the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash right? רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai made
a תקנה takkana to do לולב Lulav all seven days out of
the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. Not only did he not make ערבה
Arava. all seven days, the משנה never mentions a practice to do
ערבה Arava, out of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash That practice seemed
to develop after the period of רבן יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabban Yochanan
ben Zakkai. Okay, is that clear? In the מקדש you would do
ערבה Arava seven days, that's assumed to be biblical, and לולב Lulav
seven days. רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai came along
and said let's take the seven days of לולב lulav in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, and do it seven days everywhere. ערבה Arava
he said nothing. Even later, post-משנה it seems, there developed a practice,
I don't know post or pre, whatever, it's not in the משנה,
it doesn't seem with רבן יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai,
there developed a practice to do ערבה Arava, on הושענא רבה Hoshana
Raba. out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash So A, he never
made the תקנה, takkana, it was a later תקנה, takkana, and number
two it was only one day not seven. Why did we make
a bigger deal out of לולב Lulav than we did about הושענא
רבה, Hoshana Raba. about the ערבה? Aravah So that's his question to
רבא. Rava. מאי שנא Mai shna ערבה aravah דלא עבדינן ליה שבעה
זכר למקדש. delo avidna lei shiva zecher leMikdash. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so רבא Rava said back to him, הואיל ואדם יוצא בו ידי
חובתו בערבה שבלולב. ho'il ve'adam yotze bo yedei chovato ba'arava shebalulav. We
didn't have to do seven days because you know what, of ערבה
aravah, out of the מקדש, you're taking an ערבה aravah all seven
days anyway, it's in your לולב. lulav So you didn't need to
do a special thing for ערבה. aravah So he said, אמר ליה,
amar lei, ההוא משום לולב הוא דקא עביד ליה, ahu mishum lulav
hu deka avid lei,
don't give me that answer, that doesn't commemorate ערבה, aravah, that's just
wrapped up into the לולב. lulav, You're doing it as part of
the לולב. lulav. וכי תימא דקא מגבה ליה והדר מגבה ליה, Vekhi
teima deka magbi lei vehadar magbi lei, okay one moment, maybe you
take your לולב lulav for לולב, Lulav you put it down and
you pick it up again, you pick it up the second time
in order to be יוצא yotze ערבה aravah so we do it
all seven days. He says you can't tell me that, המעשה בכל
יום דלא קא עבדינן הכי, hama'aseh bechol yom delo ka avdinan hachi,
look around you, you know if you look at daily practice nobody
picks it up twice. So the reality, give me a break, nobody
is doing a commemoration for ערבה aravah on other days other than
הושענא רבה. Hoshanah Rabbah. Why not? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב זביד משמיה דרבא, amar Rav Zavid mishmei deRava, לולב דאורייתא עבדינן
שבעה זכר למקדש, Lulav de'oraita avdinan shiva zecher leMikdash, ערבה דרבנן לא
עבדינן ליה שבעה זכר למקדש. Arava de'rabbanan lo avdinan lei shiva zecher
leMikdash.
לולב lulav is biblical, so we're going to commemorate for, meaning it
sounds like what the גמרא Gemara is saying is לולב lulav in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? is biblical so we'll commemorate it all
seven days. ערבה, aravah? this is the way
it sounds... ערבה aravah is not biblical even in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash. so we're not going to do a commemoration outside the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. for all seven days. The גמרא Gemara says,
one minute. למאן, Leman, who are you saying that ערבה aravah. is
not a biblical thing in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash. אילימא לאבא
שאול, Ileima l'Abba Shaul, if you're saying according to אבא שאול, Abba
Shaul, דאמר de'amar ערבי נחל כתיב, arvei nachal kesiv,
it says ערבי in the plural, שתים, shtayim, to tell you two
מצות mitzvos of ערבה, Aravah אחת ללולב ואחת למקדש. achas l'lulav v'achas
l'mikdash.
There's the ערבה aravah that's for לולב Lulav and there's a separate
מצוה mitzvah. of ערבה aravah? in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash It
is biblical in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. אלא רבנן, Ela rabanan,
if it's according to the Rabbis, הלכתא גמירי לה. hilchosa g'miri lah.
They know that by a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai. that
it's biblical in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, דאמר רב אסי אמר
רבי יוחנן משום רבי נחוניא איש בקעת בית חורתן, De'amar Rav Assi
amar Rav Yochanan mishum Rabbi Nechunya ish Bikas Beis Chorsan,
so there's a teaching in the name of רב אסי Rav Assi
in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, עשר נטיעות, esser netiyot,
ten plantings, I'm not going to revisit that, that has to do
about working the land on שמיטה shmita if there are ten trees
within a certain area, וניסוך המים, v'nisuch hamayim, the pouring of the
water on the מזבח during the seven days of סוכות, Sukkos,
excuse me, I skipped the keyword, ערבה, Aravah taking the ערבה aravah.
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, all seven days, וניסוך המים, v'nisuch
hamayim, the pouring of the water, הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai.
It's הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai So what do you mean?
It's biblical in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. לולב lulav, is biblical,
ערבה aravah, is biblical. Why do we do a seven-day commemoration for
לולב lulav, and not for ערבה? aravah אלא אמר רב זביד משמיה
דרבא, Ela amar Rav Zevid mishmei de'Rava, so רב זביד Rav Zevid
says in the name of רבא, Rava, לולב, lulav, you missed, this
really seems like it's a reframing of what was said before. It
is about being biblical, but biblical where? לולב דאיכא עיקר מן התורה
בגבולין, Lulav de'ika ikar min haTorah bigvulin, there's fundamentally outside of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. there's a biblical מצוה mitzvah of לולב. lulav.
You start with a basis of a biblical מצוה. mitzvah The first
day is biblical out of the מקדש. Once you have the biblical
anchor, עבדינן ליה שבעה זכר למקדש, avdinan leh shiva zecher le'mikdash, we
can build on the basic core מצוה mitzvah of לולב lulav of
one day and extend it for seven days as a זכר למקדש
zecher le'mikdash because we're building on the core מצוה mitzvah of the
one day. ערבה דלית לה עיקר מן התורה בגבולין, Aravah de'leis lah
ikar min haTorah bigvulin,
ערבה aravah, doesn't even get started biblically outside of the מקדש. There's
no foundation for it out of the מקדש. So therefore, לא עבדינן
שבעה זכר למקדש, lo avdinan shiva zecher le'mikdash, you're not going to
make a seven-day מצוה mitzvah of ערבה. aravah. It's like יש מאין,
yesh me'ayin, right?
You're making it in a vacuum. לולב lulav. you start with a
one-day practice, so we can say, you know what, extend the practice
for all seven days, that is what we'll do זכר למקדש zecher
le'mikdash but you start with a one-day practice, we're just going to
extend it. ערבה aravah, you start with nothing out of the מקדש.
So if we're going to do something, the most we're going to
do is a one-day commemoration. It would be way too much to
create a seven-day thing out of nothing. So we're going to do
a one-day commemoration and that is the difference. Okay, so now we
understand, ערבה aravah. and לולב lulav. are biblical in the מקדש. They
would override שבת on their respective days. In theory it should override
שבת out of the מקדש, but we don't do it because of
ספיקא דיומא sefeika deyoma and that becomes a standard practice even in
ישראל. Yisrael. Why do we do a seven days with לולב lulav
and one day with ערבה? aravah לולב lulav. is, starts with a
one-day דאורייתא, de'Oraisa, we extend it seven. ערבה aravah starts with zero,
so we only give it one day, הושענא רבה. Hoshanah Rabbah? Okay,
yes.
Can you explain the difference between say about the ערבה דלית לה
עיקר מן התורה aravah de'leis lah ikar min haTorah and saying simultaneously
that it's דאורייתא? de'Oraisa?
That's what I've been saying, it's דאורייתא de'Oraisa in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash. דלית לה עיקר מן התורה בגבולין,
de'leis lah ikar min
haTorah
bigvulin, out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, Point.
Okay? Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara, says like this. Okay. אמר
ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, said ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, כהנים בעלי
מומין נכנסין בין האולם ולמזבח כדי לצאת בערבה. Kohanim ba'alei mumim nichnasin
bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach kedei latzet b'aravah. כהנים Kohanim that have
blemishes were allowed to go between the אולם ulam and the מזבח
in order to be יוצא yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of ערבה. arava
Now you might remember from all of our discussions about, about, you
know, whatever, יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, something like this. Okay, fine.
Anyway,
fine. So if this is your מקדש,
okay, and here's your מזבח and here's your ramp, okay, this area
here, this here, actually it would be like this. This area here,
this is the אולם, ulam, the היכל heichal and the u-,
this area here is בין האולם ולמזבח, bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach, okay?
Now that is considered rabbinically to be a higher level of קדושה,
kedusha, right, this is עזרת כהנים ezrat kohanim and there's a small
area here where the עזרת ישראל, ezrat Yisrael, okay, fine. Anyway,
all of these different spaces have higher levels of קדושה kedusha but
mostly it's all rabbinic. Biblically all of the עזרה azarah has the
same status, but the rabbis created gradations. So this area בין האולם
ולמזבח, bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach, you know, when you're about to start, you
know, is considered a higher level of קדושה kedusha than the rest
of the עזרה. azarah. What is the... status of בין האולם ולמזבח,
bein ha'ulam vela'mizbeach, בעלי מומים, ba'alei mumim, כהנים Kohanim with blemishes, but
they can't do the עבודה, avodah, but they could be in the
עזרה, Azarah, but they're not allowed בין האולם ולמזבח. bein ha'ulam vela'mizbeach.
What ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is saying is when you're going to
do your rituals, carrying your ערבה, arava just a bunch of little
men carrying their ערבות aravot and doing their rituals. Okay. Now I
got to start. Okay. Every,
we're doing our little, give you a nice sense for what they
would do. Doing our nice little ערבה arava, rituals, right? That
could be interesting. Anyway, here we go. Okay, so we're doing our
little rituals, he says that the בעלי מומים ba'alei mumim could be
part of the procession. And they could go בין האולם ולמזבח, bein
ha'ulam vela'mizbeach, they would override that normal concern in order to do
the מצוה mitzvah of ערבה, arava לצאת בערבה. latzeit ba'aravah. Okay, so
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Are there two sets of ערבות, aravot, one set that they're holding
and one set that's stuck in the ground?
No, it seems it would be the same, but you will also
remember the discussion earlier was maybe they did it with לולב, lulav
the procession, but the conclusion of the earlier גמרא Gemara was no,
the procession was with the ערבה. arava And it seems that they
would do both, as they'd do a procession and then they'd stick
it in the ground.
So it would seem. Okay, so אמר ריש לקיש כהנים בעלי מומים
נכנסים בין האולם ולמזבח כדי לצאת בערבה. amar Reish Lakish Kohanim ba'alei
mumim nichnasim bein ha'ulam vela'mizbeach kedei latzeit ba'aravah. אמר
ליה רבי יוחנן, amar lei Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
hits back at him, מי אמרה? mi amrah? Says who? So the
גמרא Gemara says now, so the גמרא Gemara says מי אמרה, mi
amrah, says who? הא את אמרת, ha at amrat, you say it.
את אמרת רבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן משום אבא חילקיה איש בית
חורסן עשר נטיעות ערבה וניסוך המים, at amrat Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Abba Hilkiya ish beit chorsan eser netiot aravah venisuch hamayim,
like we said before, these three things, the ten plantings, the ערבה,
arava, the pouring of the water, הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'Moshe mi'Sinai
is biblical. So you say it's an obligation. So the question is,
but what do you mean? What he seems to have been bothered
by was the statement that it could be כהנים בעלי מומים. Kohanim
ba'alei mumim. What, what do you prove, right, that even כהנים with
blemishes, what do you prove by just saying that he says it's
an obligation? So there are two points that רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot make. Number one is the phrase that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
used was לצאת. latzeit. לצאת latzeit sounds like it is a,
right, that it's a personal obligation that you have to be יוצא,
yotzei, right? That's what it sounds like. So it sounded like ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was challenging and said who
says it's really an obligation? What do you mean לצאת? latzeit? Who
actually, I don't believe it's a real obligation. So it says, what
do you mean you don't believe it's a real obligation? You say
it's an obligation. Okay. תוספות Tosafot also says if we're going to
override the rabbinic concern of allowing בעלי מומים ba'alei mumim here, that
means we would only override
that rabbinic concern if we thought it was a biblical obligation. So
therefore the גמרא Gemara thought that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was saying,
who says the בעל מום ba'al mum can do it? Who says
it's biblical? גמרא Gemara, says, what do you mean? You say it's
biblical. You say it's הלכה למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe miSinai. and that's
why you can do it. So what's bothering you? So let's see
what's bothering
him.
So the גמרא Gemara says אלא, ela, says the גמרא, Gemara מי
אמרה בנטילה דילמא בזקיפה? mi amrah b'netilah dilma b'zkifah?
Who said the מצוה mitzvah is taking it? Maybe the מצוה mitzvah
is sticking it in the ground. Right? Now why should that matter
in terms of the בעלי מומים ba'alei mumim issue? So what the
מצוה mitzvah is sticking it in the ground, let the כהן Kohen
still do it. So can you think why it would matter? If
the מצוה mitzvah, wasn't the procession, the מצוה mitzvah was sticking it
in the ground, why would that not justify the כהן בעל מום
Kohen ba'al mum to do it? Yeah? They could stick it on
the other side. Exactly. That's what תוספות Tosafot says. תוספות Tosafot says,
if it's a procession and you're part of it, so you've got
to go all the way around. But if it's just sticking, then
you could stick it without going around. So maybe the real מצוה,
mitzvah going back to our other question, maybe the real מצוה mitzvah
is the sticking and you could do this part, you don't have
to do that part. רש"י Rashi has even a more fascinating read.
רש"י Rashi says if the idea is a procession, then it's like
a personal obligation, and every כהן, Kohen, like taking the לולב, lulav.
you've got to shake a לולב, lulav you know what you've got
to do? You've got to walk around with an ערבה. arava It's
a personal obligation. And if you're בעל מום, ba'al mum, you still
got to do it. But if it's sticking it in the ground,
he says it's not that you as an individual have to stick
it, it's that you want the מזבח surrounded by ערבות. aravot. Somebody's
got to do it, it doesn't have to be you. So that's
also a fascinating conceptual shift. Is the idea of the מצוה mitzvah
of ערבה arava, in the מקדש a personal obligation that every כהן
Kohen has to walk around and do this, or is it about
no, in the end of the day there has to be ערבה
arava, surrounding the מזבח? Like I always wonder the guy who's standing
up with the ספר תורה Sefer Torah during הושענא רבה Hoshanah Rabbah.
and holding the ספר תורה. Sefer Torah. Is he saying to himself
like I'm not being יוצא הושענות yotzei hoshanas because I'm not walking
around? I think that. You think that?
Like I don't want to be given that.
Right. So we all tend to think in terms of, we all
tend to think in all areas of הלכה halacha in terms of,
like it's all about my personal obligation. But says who? Maybe the
nature of the practice of הושענא Hoshana is the whole thing that
happens in the שול, shul, that one guy is with the ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, other guys are walking around and as a... This
is how we're as a שול shul doing it, it's not about
your personal חיוב chiyuv to walk around da da da da. So
that's the question. If it's a personal obligation, okay, then a בעל
מום's ba'al mum gotta do it. But if it's just about making
sure there are ערבות aravos planted by the מזבח, who says that
a בעל מום ba'al mum has to do it and who says
he's allowed to do it? So that's his question. Okay, מי אמרה
בנטילה דילמא בזקיפה? mi amra binetila dilma bezekifa? Maybe it's about the
sticking in the floor. מי אמרה בבעלי מומים? mi amra beba'alei mumim?
And even if it is about the procession, who says that you
do it with a בעל מום? ba'al mum? דילמא בתמימים? dilma betmimim?
Maybe maybe even the procession is limited to תמימים tmimim even if
it is about a procession. Okay, so that was what רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan was challenging. I get that it's biblical. I'm not sure
I agree that a בעל מום ba'al mum can do it. A,
the earlier question, is it more about the taking or more about
the planting? And B, I'm not so sure that that includes a
בעל מום. ba'al mum. אתמר, Itmar, now we have another issue. רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi,
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהושע בן לוי. Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi. חד אמר ערבה יסוד נביאים, Chad amar arava yesod
nevi'im, one says ערבה arava is a foundation of the נביאים, nevi'im,
which means they found, they laid the foundation of the practice, which
רש"י Rashi basically says means they legislated it, they demanded that people
do it. וחד אמר, Vechad amar, and the other one says, ערבה
מנהג נביאים. arava minhag nevi'im. They didn't actually legislate it, they just
like began this as a custom and people followed the custom. Now,
it's דברי סופרים. divrei sofrim.
Right,
what about the fact that we just said it's biblical? Now we'll
get to that in a minute, but first we have this debate
about how much it came from the prop, that it was נביאים,
nevi'im, but was it that a legislated practice or just an adop,
like a מנהג? minhag? So it says, the גמרא Gemara says, תסתיים
tistayem let's conclude דרבי יוחנן הוא דאמר יסוד נביאים. deRabbi Yochanan hu
de'amar yesod nevi'im. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the one who says
that it was a foundation of the נביאים. nevi'im. דאמר רבי אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן ערבה יסוד נביאים היא De'amar Rabbi Abba amar Rabbi
Yochanan arava yesod nevi'im hi because we have a statement in the
name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that it's a יסוד נביאים, yesod
nevi'im, that it was legislated. תסתיים, Tistayem, that's a good proof. Now
the גמרא Gemara turns to the obvious question that תוספות Tosafos ask.
אמר ליה רבי זירא לרבי אבא, Amar lei Rabbi Zeira leRabbi Abba,
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira said to רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, מי אמר
רבי יוחנן הכי? mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Could רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan really say that it was only from the נביאים? nevi'im? והאמר
רבי יוחנן משום רבי נחוניא איש בקעת בית חורסן עשרה נטיעות ערבה
וניסוך המים הלכה למשה מסיני. Ve'ha'amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Nechunya ish
bik'at beis chorsan asara netiot arava venisuch hamayim halacha leMoshe miSinai.
We've been saying that it's all הלכה למשה מסיני. halacha leMoshe miSinai.
Maybe it's even in a פסוק, pasuk, but at least it's הלכה
למשה מסיני. How could you say it's only the נביאים? nevi'im? So
גמרא Gemara says, אשתומם כשעה חדא. ishtomem kesha'a chada. According to the
דניאל, Daniel, he was like dumbfounded for a second. Like he keep,
he was like you know, he didn't have a response. He was
struck dumb. Oh my god, that's a good question. Yeah, didn't we
just say it was biblical? What do you mean נביאים? nevi'im? ואמר,
Ve'amar, and then he came up and he said, here's the answer.
שכחום וחזר ויסדום. Shachachum vechazar veyisdum.
Really it is biblical, it's a tradition going back to משה. Moshe.
What do we mean when we say it came from the prophet?
We mean that the tradition was lost and the נביאים nevi'im came
and they re-established an ancient tradition. So it was re-established by the
נביאים nevi'im but it still is biblical. That's what we're saying now.
The one who said מנהג נביאים minhag nevi'im might really say it's
not biblical at all, but יסוד נביאים yesod nevi'im means they re-established
a practice. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי?
umi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Did רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say
that? That it was forgotten and re-established? והאמר רבי יוחנן, Ve'ha'amar Rabbi
Yochanan, what
didn't רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say, דילהון אממי דילהון היא dilhon ammi
dilhon hi is really theirs. What does that mean? So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan was in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And when he, this
is the way רש"י, Rashi, it's a מחלוקת machlokes רש"י Rashi תוספות
Tosafos how to read this. But when he was tea, he learned
from רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. רב כהנא Rav Kahana went and exiled
from בבל, Bavel, went at, well exile, anyway, left בבל, Bavel, ran
away from בבל, Bavel, go to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and he
came the pride of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan learned a lot of תורה Torah from רב כהנא. Rav Kahana.
And רב כהנא Rav Kahana what originally had come from בבל. Bavel.
And then when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was teaching his students in
ישראל, Israel, he would say to them, hey you guys, you think
you're in ישראל Israel and you have the תורה Torah and says,
you know, you never left ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and like you
you dismiss the תורה Torah of גלות? galus? You should know, דילהון
אממי דילהון הוא, dilhon ammi dilhon hu, what you guys say דילהון
אממי דילהון הוא, dilhon ammi dilhon hu, it really is all, it
all comes from בבל Bavel because I learned all my תורה Torah
from רב כהנא Rav Kahana who came from בבל. Bavel. It's actually
quite fascinating, I was in ישראל Israel like two months ago and
I went to a ישיבה, yeshiva, ישיבת פתח תקוה Yeshiva Petach Tikva
I gave a שיעור shiur for like, you know, whatever the סוגיה
sugya was that they were learning. I gave a, you know, it's
so funny because I come off the plane, I can't talk a
five-minute conversation in Hebrew, but I came to the ישיבה yeshiva I
gave an hour and a half שיעור shiur in Hebrew. So anyway,
just depends on what what sort of let's, vocabulary you're drawing on.
Anyway, afterwards one of the ר"מים ramim came over to me and
he said, it's so important for the guys to hear that שיעור
shiur he says because they don't think there's any תורה Torah in
בבל. Bavel. They only think there's תורה Torah in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. So anyway,
so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was saying, hey guys, I got to
tell you, you think you're all, you think the only תורה Torah
is in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it all comes from בבל. Bavel.
So why is that relevant? So רש"י Rashi says the point is,
it's saying as how could רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say that we
forgot our מסורה? mesora? Meaning the explanation, the logical explanation that we
forgot the מסורה mesora is, you know, we went into exile, we
lost the tradition, we forgot the מסורה. mesora. But רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says that even in בבל Bavel they didn't lose the tradition
even when they went into exile. That's why רש"י Rashi reads it.
It's a funny type of a question, just what, it's impossible to
forget anything? Anyway, the גמרא Gemara rejects the idea that רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan would really say that it was forgotten and reestablished. So
we're back to the question: is it biblical or is it from
the prophets? So לא קשיא, lo kashya, the גמרא, Gemara it's not
difficult. כאן במקדש כאן בגבולין. kan b'Mikdash, kan b'gvulin.
Oh,
look, of course it's biblical in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The
question is the practice to do it out of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash Where does that come from? That's what we're saying, that
that comes from the prophets. Okay, so a minute ago I said
that it's not רבי יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai, right,
taking the ערבה arava out of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash right?
רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai only made a תקנה
takana by לולב. We don't see any mention of רבי יוחנן בן
זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai by ערבה, arava. but we also don't
see any mention in the משניות Mishnayot of the practice to do
ערבה arava, out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash So גמרא Gemara
here is saying the practice to do ערבה arava. out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is very ancient, goes back to the נביאים.
nevi'im. Okay, so this is interesting because people, I think, don't have
this clear, what the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara is. People, a
lot of people know this debate, מנהג נביאים, minhag nevi'im, יסוד נביאים,
yesod nevi'im, but the גמרא's Gemara conclusion is that's a debate of
the out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, practice. In the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash, it's assumed to be דאורייתא, d'oraysa, out of the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. to sort of mimic and continue the practice,
or mimic the practice that was in the בית המקדש, that is
seen as being either legislated or practiced by the נביאים, nevi'im, and
that's what this debate is about. Okay. אמר רבי אמי, Amar Rebbi
Ami, says רבי אמי, Rebbi Ami, ערבה צריכה שיעור, arava tzericha shiur,
when you're doing this ערבה, arava now we're talking about the practice
we do on הושענא רבה. We've established that that is a זכר
למקדש, zecher l'mikdash, a one-day זכר, zecher, something that comes from the
נביאים, nevi'im, and we do it, and we're going to do some
waving or something, you know, we're seeing where we get the idea
of doing a procession. Now we're talking about the details of that
practice of הושענא רבה. So he says, that needs a שיעור, shiur,
there's a minimum amount that you need in order to be יוצא.
yotzei. דאינה ניטלת אלא בפני עצמה. d'einah niteles ela bifnei atzmah.
You have to take the ערבה arava separately. You do not take
the ערבה, arava, you don't just, you're not יוצא yotzei by just
taking the לולב on הושענא רבה. ואין אדם יוצא ידי חובתו בערבה
שבלולב. v'ein adam yotzei yedei chovato b'arava she-balulav.
Like I said, you're not יוצא yotzei by taking it in the
לולב. So the גמרא Gemara says, aren't those last two points redundant?
It's like, you know,
the same thing. כיון דאמר מר, keivan d'amar mar, since you just
said דאינה ניטלת אלא בפני עצמה, einah niteles ela bifnei atzmah, you
can only take it by itself, פשיטא peshita דאין אדם יוצא בערבה
שבלולב. d'ein adam yotzei b'arava she-balulav. That's the same the same as
you're not יוצא yotzei when you take it in the לולב. He
said you had to take it by itself. No, no, the גמרא
Gemara. says no. מהו דתימא, mah d'seima, I might have thought, הני
מילי היכא דלא אגבהי והדר אגבהי, hani milei heicha d'lo agbei v'hadar
agbei, you're not יוצא yotzei in the לולב if you just do
it if you don't pick it up twice. אבל אגבהי והדר אגבהי,
aval agbei v'hadar agbei, if you pick it up and pick it
up again, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe then you are יוצא yotzei
because it's a separate picking up for the sake of ערבה, arava
קא משמע לן kamashma lan that if you want to do the
ערבה out of the בית המקדש, that practice, you pick it up,
you have to take ערבה separate from the לולב. It doesn't matter
even if you pick up the לולב twice. Okay. קא משמע לן.
kamashma lan. דרב חסדא אמר רבי יצחק, d'Rav Chisda amar Rabbi Yitzchak,
אדם יוצא ידי חובתו בערבה שבלולב. adam yotzei yedei chovato b'arava she-balulav.
But רב חסדא Rav Chisda disagrees. He says you are, you do
fulfill your obligation by taking it in the לולב. So according to
him, you didn't even have to do anything distinct. You're just when
you take your לולב on the seventh day, you're יוצא yotzei the
מצוה mitzvah of ערבה. Maybe he felt you had to pick it
up twice, he doesn't say. Okay. וכמה שיעורה? v'kamah shiura? So that's
the issue about taking it separately. Now what's the minimum size? So
here it does not give a שיעור shiur in terms of height,
but in terms of the amount of leaves. אמר רב נחמן, Amar
Rav Nachman, ג' בדי עלין לחין. gimmel badei alin lachin.
Three sticks with fresh leaves. רש"י Rashi reads it means three sticks,
he reads the word בד bad as a separate stick of the
ערבה, twig. Three twigs with fresh leaves. The ראש Rosh reads it
as no, it means
on one twig there had to be three groups of leaves. He
reads the בד, bad, you know, like a little bunch of like
a grouping of leaves. But anyway we'll read it like רש"י. Rashi.
Three stick, three twigs with fresh leaves. ורב אשי ורב ששת אמרי,
v'Rav Ashi v'Rav Sheishesh amar, אפילו עלה אחת ובד אחד. afilu ala
achas u-vad echad. Even one, one leaf and one twig. So גמרא
Gemara says, עלה אחד ובד אחד סלקא דעתך? ala echad u-vad echad
salka daitach? Literally one twig and one leaf? Meaning let's say you
have a twig and a leaf separate from one another. You got
one little stick with no leaves on it and one leaf. Yoi!
One stick and one leaf? That's your יוצא? yotzei? So the גמרא
Gemara says, that's what that means?
It doesn't mean just a twig with one leaf?
Well, that's how the גמרא's Gemara going to correct it. אלא אימא,
ela eima, אפילו עלה אחד בבד אחד. afilu ala echad b'vad echad.
No, we mean one twig with one leaf. Okay, so even if
you just have one twig with one leaf, according to him that's
enough for the ערבה. Of course as רש"י Rashi says nowadays we
bring huge bunches of fresh ערבות aravas and the whole thing, but
technically you're יוצא yotzei with a very minimal ערבה for הושענא רבה.
אמר איווא, Amar Eva, says איווא, Eva, הוי קאימנא קמיה דרבי אלעזר
בר צדוק. havi kaimna kamei d'Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok. Now איווא Eva
was like the, like a, like a, we'll see in a minute
he was... I think רב'ס Rav's father-in-law, he was a, like he
was an early generation אמורא Amora or a very late תנא. Tanna.
So he says I was standing in front of ר' אליעזר בר
צדוק, Rebbi Eliezer bar Tzadok, ואייתי ההוא גברא ערבה קמיה, v'ayisi hahu
gavra arava kumei, and a certain man brought an ערבה in front
of him. And it was presumably
הושענא רבה. חביט חביט ולא בריך. chavit chavit v'lo barich. He took
it, חביט חביט, chavit chavit, and he didn't make the ברכה. bracha.
So what's again חביט chavit mean? It could mean, normally חביט chavit
means to bang, which is our practice, but חיבוט ערבות, chibut aravos,
but again if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says חביט
חביט, chavit chavit, רש"י Rashi says לשון ניענוע, lashon nianua, he shook
it. Okay, that's the phrase we have before about חיבוט chibut which
the גמרא is understood to mean to take, to hold, something of
that nature. He didn't make a ברכה. bracha. So now we're getting
to the question, do we make a ברכה bracha on the practice
of הושענא רבה? So חביט חביט ולא בריך. chavit chavit v'lo barich.
קסבר, kasavar, he's of the opinion מנהג נביאים הוא, minhag nevi'im hu,
it's only a practice of the נביאים, nevi'im, you don't make a
ברכה bracha on a מנהג, minhag, if it was a legislated you
would make a ברכה, bracha, but a מנהג minhag you don't make
a ברכה. bracha. This becomes that גמרא that you don't make a
ברכה bracha on a מנהג minhag because a huge source for the
ראשונים Rishonim in discussing when do we, do we ever make ברכות
brachos for מנהגים. minhagim. And the big area that there's a debate
about do you make a ברכה bracha for is saying חצי הלל
Chatzi Hallel on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, which is not a strict
obligation, the גמרא calls it a מנהג. minhag. Would you make a
ברכה bracha on הלל ראש חודש Hallel Rosh Chodesh or should you
learn from this גמרא that you never make a ברכה bracha on
מנהגים? minhagim? And an important distinction that תוספות Tosafos points out is,
it might depend on the nature of the מנהג, minhag, not the
weight of the מנהג minhag but the nature actually of the practice.
Something like shaking a stick, ערבה, okay, it does not become a
מצוה mitzvah act if it's not legislated, if it's just a מנהג.
minhag. מנהג Minhag doesn't turn this into a significantly religious מצוה mitzvah
act that you could say אשר קדשנו במצותיו. asher kidshanu b'mitzvotav. You
won't get that by if it's just a מנהג. minhag. You need
it to be rabbinically at least legislated to get that weight. But
he says saying הלל, Hallel, saying הלל Hallel of course it's a
מצוה act whether it's legislated or not, you're praising God. So therefore
it's more legitimate to say הלל Hallel a מצוה and say אשר
קדשנו במצותיו asher kidshanu b'mitzvotav even if it's only a מנהג minhag
because in by its very nature it's more of a religious act
than something like waving a stick. Waving a stick only becomes a
religious act if God or the rabbis say so, not out of
a מנהג. minhag. But saying הלל Hallel is always a religious act
and therefore you're, it's more legitimate to make a ברכה. bracha. But
this does become, that's at least תוספות'ס Tosafos's זאג, zog, but this
does become a very important source for the discussion of do you
make a ברכה bracha by מנהג. minhag. Okay, so that's the answer.
Oh, you didn't make a ברכה, bracha, we see it's only a
מנהג. minhag. אבוא וחזקיה בני ברתיה דרב. Avoh v'Chizkiyah bnei bartei d'Rav.
So now אבוא Avoh and חזקיה Chizkiyah were the, were רב'ס Rav's
nephews, the sons of the brother of רב. Rav. Now רב Rav
was like a transition figure between תנאים Tannaim and אמוראים. Amoraim. So
before I said אבוא Avoh was in front of ר' אליעזר בר
צדוק, Rebbi Eliezer bar Tzadok, אבוא Avoh was the next generation, he
was an אמורא, Amora, ר' אליעזר בר צדוק Rebbi Eliezer bar Tzadok
was like right at that also cusp like רב Rav I said,
either a late generation תנא Tanna or an early, early אמורא Amora
and so on. Okay, so now אבוא Avoh was and חזקיה Chizkiyah
were רב'ס Rav's nephews. אייתו ערבה לקמיה דרב, aisyu arava l'kamei d'Rav,
they brought an ערבה in front of רב, Rav, presumably again we're
talking about הושענא רבה. חביט חביט ולא בריך. chavit chavit v'lo barich.
Again, same story like the things that אבוא Avoh himself witnessed. They
did the waving or whatever חביט chavit means and they didn't make
a ברכה. bracha. קסבר מנהג נביאים הוא. kasavar minhag nevi'im hu. Again,
following that practice of that person that came in front of ר'
אליעזר בר צדוק, Rebbi Eliezer bar Tzadok, they waved it without a
ברכה bracha because it's only a custom of the נביאים. nevi'im. It's
not a תקנה, takana, it's not a legislated practice out of the
בית המקדש. אמר אבוא, Amar Avoh, now that we're having אבוא Avoh
tell about stories about ר' אליעזר בר צדוק, Rebbi Eliezer bar Tzadok,
we get two more stories about ר' אליעזר בר צדוק Rebbi Eliezer
bar Tzadok that really aren't relevant, okay, but they're interesting stories. Because
about, okay, אמר אבוא, Amar Avoh, הוי קאימנא קמיה דרבי אליעזר בר
צדוק, havi ka-imna kumei d'Rebbi Eliezer bar Tzadok, I was in front
of ר' אליעזר בר צדוק. Rebbi Eliezer bar Tzadok. אתא לקמיה ההוא
גברא, asa l'kamei hahu gavra, a certain man came in front of
him. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, קריתא אית לי,
karyasa is li, I have, I own many cities or villages, כרמיא
אית לי, karmaya is li, and there are vineyards in the villages,
זיתא אית לי, zeisa is li, and there are olive trees in
the villages, דאתו בני קריתא, d'asu bnei karyasa, people of the village
come, ומכסכסין בכרמיא, u'mchaskesin b'karmaya, they basically like a hoe in the,
in the vineyards, you know, like, like, whatever it's called with, you
know, they, they move the dirt, they, in the vineyard, this was
on שמיטה, Shmita, ואוכלין בזיתא, v'ochlin b'zeisa,
and they eat olives as their, you know, they're, they're given olives
from the olive trees for their payment.
Does it mean they shake the branches?
No. אריך או לא אריך? arich o lo arich? Is it a
good thing to do or not a good thing? Okay, by the
way what's fascinating is this whole passage is very much in vernacular
Aramaic, I'm assuming it might be ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael Aramaic, I'm
not a grammarian but it's not a type of Aramaic you normally
see in the גמרא. אמר ליה, amar lei, so he said back
to him, לא אריך, lo arich, it's not right what you're doing,
it's שמיטה. Shmita. Now we would think what's not right is letting
them hoe the land. land. We're going to see what really bothered
him wasn't the hoeing of the land but the paying them with
the olives, because you're not supposed to do business with שמיטה Shemitah
produce. So הוי שבק ליה ואזיל havy shavik lei ve-azil so the
man accepted it. Okay, thank you, I'll stop the practice. And he
left. אמר Amar so now Reb Elazar bar Tzadok said presumably to
Aivo, כדו הוינא דיירי בארעא הדא ארבעין שנין. Kadu havina dayari be-ara
hada arbein shanin.
So far I've been living in this year land for 40 years
in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael ולא חמיתי בר אינש velo chamisi bar
inish and I have not yet seen a person, בר אינש bar
inish the son of man, I've yet to see a person מהלך
באורחן דתקנין mahalach be-orchun de-taknin
going in the right path, right אורח orech is דרך, derech, דרך
ישר. derech yashar. I've yet to see a person going in the
דרך ישר derech yashar the right path כדן kedein as this man.
That's quite fascinating. Here he was and he was letting his people
until this point do work on שמיטה Shemitah and pay them. So
the interesting thing is yeah okay everybody makes mistakes, but you know
what? It bothered him enough that he wasn't certain that it was
okay that he came and he asked a שיילה. shaila. Not only
that, when I gave him an answer he didn't argue with me.
He didn't say oh my god but if you don't allow it
how am I going to do it, I'm going to lose so
much money. He accepted the answer and he's going to act on
it. That's a דרך ישר. derech yashar. I've never seen somebody that's
so willing to you know change course and accept the ruling with
all whatever the consequences is like this type of a person. Very
high praise. Okay. וחזר ואתי ואמר ליה ve-chazar ve-asi ve-amar lei then
he came back this man and said to him, מאי מעבדי mai
ma'avdi you know what, could you help me out here, like exactly
what do I need to do to fix the practice? Okay, I
was ready to fix it but then I realized I'd better ask
a follow-up question. Because the logical thing you would think is to
say is stop hoeing the vineyard. So אמר ליה amar lei he
said to him, אפקיר זיתך
לחשוכייא afkeir zeisacha le-chashuchaya make renounce ownership of your olive trees to
the poor, חשוכייא chashuchaya is an Aramaic word for poor, a very
uncommon word. But basically it's שמיטה, Shemitah, so stop protecting your olive
trees, let the olive trees be free for all, let the poor
eat off the olive trees. ותן פריטך לקסקוסיי כרמין ve-tein pritecha le-kaskusei
carmin
and give money, pay the people that do the hoeing, don't pay
'em with the olive trees. You can't do business with the olives.
The olives are supposed to be free for everyone. But the people
that are doing the hoeing, pay 'em out of your pocket, pay
'em with hard cash. Okay, so now it's a fascinating thing. The
only thing that bothered him was the olive trees, that he was
paying them with olives and that he wasn't freeing the olive trees.
But how could you be working in the vineyards? Isn't it שמיטה?
Shemitah? So the גמרא says וקסקוסיי מי שרי ve-kaskusei mi shari since
when is it permissible to be like you know plowing the land,
or not plowing but whatever, hoeing the land on שמיטה Shemitah in
a vineyard? והתניא Ve-hatanya we taught in a ברייתא, והשביעית ve-hashvi'is and
on the seventh year תשמטנה tishmitena
you should let it lay fallow ונטשתה u-netashtah you should abandon it.
תשמטנה Tishmitena מלקסקס mi-lekaskes
you should free your hand from doing this hoeing, the pushing of
the dirt. ונטשתה u-netashtah you should abandon it מלסקל mi-lesakel don't remove
stones. Okay. So the גמרא says אמר רב עוקבא בר חמא, Amar
Rav Ukva bar Chama, תרי קסקוסיי הוי. trei kiskusei havei. There are
two forms of קסקוס. kiskus. Now קסקוס kiskus is not
making furrows in order to plant seed, which is I guess what
we normally call what, hoeing? What do you call when you make
furrows and then you plant seeds? Is that the hoeing? I think
it's called hoeing. No, anyway, whatever. That is clearly עבודת קרקע avodas
karka and that's clearly אסור assur on שמיטה. Shemitah. Like the making
of the furrows and the planting of the seeds. What you have
here is you're not planting seeds. Plowing! That's plowing! There you go.
Plowing. Thank you. Okay, so what exactly is hoeing? I think this
is hoeing.
Hoeing is fiddling around.
That's what this is. This is hoeing. So right. So that's what
this is. So plowing is biblically forbidden. You know,
that is basically or whatever, we'll learn about it in many contexts.
But that's basically making the soil able to plant seeds, to grow
the seeds. That's עבודה avodah on שמיטה. Shemitah. This, the vines are
growing. You're just pushing around the dirt in order that the vines
don't get ruined, that they get you know that the dirt is
in the right place. It's not right. It's not the same type
of basically plowing for planting purposes. And therefore sometimes it's permissible. Okay,
there are two types. Okay, so תרי קסקוסיי הוי. trei kiskusei havei.
חד סתומי פילי, Chad simei pilei, one is filling up holes, basically
the roots of the vines are exposed and you're doing it to
cover up the roots of the vines. And if you don't do
it, the vines will wither. So you're not actually encouraging growth, you're
just preventing them from being destroyed. That you're allowed to do on
שמיטה. Shemitah. You can take necessary precautions so the things doesn't get
ruined. So if you're filling up holes and covering up gaps and
covering up exposed roots, that you're allowed to do. חד, Chad, the
other one, אברויי אילני, avruyei ilanei, strengthens the tree, actually actually like
you know encourages growth. That you're not allowed to do. That's like
watering and planting. That you're not allowed to do. But covering the
roots... to prevent it from withering, that you are allowed to do.
Okay. So the גמרא says אברויי אילני אסור, avruei ilanei assur, strengthening
the trees is forbidden, ססומי פילי, susumei pilei, filling the gaps, שרי
sharei that's permissible. Okay, one last story with אבו Eivo and רבי
אלעזר בר צדוק. Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok.
What?
Why is it not permissible to water?
Well, because it's שמיטה Shmita and that's tending to the crop. To
do it to prevent, to prevent them from being destroyed, maybe yes.
We'll talk about that when we get to מועד קטן. Moed Katan.
Let's just do the last story. אמר אבו משום רבי אלעזר בר
צדוק, Amar Eivo mishum Rabbi Elazar bar Tzadok, אל ילך אדם בערבי
שבתות יותר מג׳ פרסאות. al yelech adam be'arvei shabbatos yoser migimel parsa'os.
Don't travel more than three parsa'os, like three, a mil is like
a kilometer and a parsa is four mil. So this would be
twelve kilometers. Twelve kilometers is like what?
Like eight miles. Okay, don't go more than eight miles, and this
was without cars, on ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. אמר רב כהנא לא
אמרו אלא לביתו. Amar Rav Kahana lo amru ela leveiso. Now you
would think it means don't leave your house on that type of
a trip. But he's saying no, it means if you're, don't travel
to your house longer than that. You know, if it's going to
be like eight miles, could be a half day's journey. Don't set
out on such a long journey ערב שבת Erev Shabbos to get
back home. Stay where you are and make שבת where you are.
A parsa's how many mil?
A parsa is four mil. Okay. אבל לאושפיזא, Aval le'ushpiza, but if
you're heading to an inn, אמידי דנקיט סמיך, amidi denakit samich, and
that's okay, because you'll stop at whatever inn you can stop at.
You're not going to expect them to have prepared food for you.
You're assuming you'll eat
whatever you're carrying with you. But if you're going to come home,
and you come home five minutes before, I would say you're afraid
that you're not going to get home in time. Okay, but you'll
come home five minutes before שבת and you'll expect a nice meal
to be made, and they weren't expecting you home. Don't show up
at your house five minutes before שבת. Stop at an inn, fine,
you're expecting you'll only get what you brought with you anyway. ואיכא
דאמרי, Ve'ika de'amri, others say אמר רב כהנא amar Rav Kahana לא
נצרכה אלא אפילו לביתו. lo nitzrecha ela afilu leveiso. No, certainly don't
go to an inn. You'll be upset, they won't have food prepared,
and so on. But you might think, oh, but my home I
can go. At my home, I just want to be home for
שבת, I don't care what food I have. No, even then don't
go, because you'll think you don't care, but then you'll get there,
you'll be upset that there's no food for you to eat. אמר
רב כהנא בדידי הוה עובדא, Amar Rav Kahana bedidi hava uvda, this
happened to me, ואפילו כסא דהרסנא לא אשכחי. ve'afilu kasa deharsena lo
ashkechi. I came home right before שבת and they didn't even have
for me a little herring. כסא דהרסנא Kasa deharsena is like a
fish with some type of a batter, but it's a very basic
dish that they would have on שבת. So he says, you know
what? It's true. Don't say oh, I'll go home, I just want
to be home, I don't really care. No, you'll get home, you'll
be really annoyed that there's nothing for you to eat. Okay, end
of the סוגיא. sugya.
Rabbi?
Yeah. There's a note here that
says
the רמב״ן Ramban says חביטות chavitos
instead of דישות. dishos.
Beating. That's what I've been mentioning. Yeah. So was it רמב״ן Ramban
or רמב״ם? Rambam? רמב״ן Ramban with an ן. nun.
Yeah, תוספות רי״ד, Tosafos Rid, yeah.
Yeah, that's where our practice is about beating them. Right.
Thank you.