Today's דף *daf* is כ"א *Kaf Aleph* and we
pick up
at the bottom of כ"א עמוד ב' *Kaf Amud Bet*. We are
wrapping up some of these issues about ולד vlad *vlad* and תמורה
tmura, *tmurah* of different types of קרבנות korbanot, *korbanot*. And in the
last משנה mishna, *mishna* we had this whole question about
an אשם Asham *asham* and the ולד vlad? תמורת אשם tmuras Asham
*vlad tmurat asham* etc. And the main question in the משנה mishna
*mishna* was what do you do with an אשם Asham *asham* that
can't be brought as a קרבן korban. *korban* because it's a תמורה
tmura, *tmurah* or נתכפרו בעליו באחר *nitkapru ba'alav beacher* and there was
a three-way debate. The position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
says you let them die which
the משנה mishna *mishna* in the beginning of זבחים *Zevachim* makes it
clear because he equates אשם Asham, *asham* to a חטאת chatas, *chatat*
although the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here makes it sound like it was
a גזירה *gezeira*.
And the other two positions about רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* and the
תנא Tanna. קמא *Tanna Kamma* that says the money either goes for
a communal עולה Olah. *olah* or a private עולה Olah *olah*. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* picks up with it and says
the following. בעי מיניה רבי אבין בר חייא מרבי אבין בר כהנא
*Ba'ei minei Rabbi Avin bar Chiya me'Rabbi Avin bar Kahana*. It is
five lines from the wide lines on כ"א עמוד ב' *Kaf Amud
Bet*. So בעי מיניה רבי אבין בר חייא מרבי אבין בר כהנא
*ba'ei minei Rabbi Avin bar Chiya me'Rabbi Avin bar Kahana* הפרישה נקבה
nekeiva לאשם בנה מה שיקרב עולה Olah, *hifrisha nekeva le'asham benah
mah sheyikrav olah*. If you might remember actually it was an explicit
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* earlier which the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* will reference. You
sanctified a female for an אשם Asham, *asham* we had cases like
that where you sanctified the wrong gender animal.
What's the story with the child? Can the child be an עולה
Olah, *olah*? Since in the end what you're going to have to
do now if this animal itself gets a מום mum *mum* you'll
redeem it and you
can since anyway the animal the אשם Asham. *asham* cannot be brought
as an אשם Asham *asham* and we know that things that cannot
be brought and especially the story of a child of an אשם
Asham *asham* presumably is that it grazes and you use the proceeds
for buying an עולה Olah, *olah*. So what about if the animal
itself is a male can't you bring the animal itself as an
עולה Olah. *olah*? So this actually came up in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* before because we had cases before
which were very similar or actually the exact same case let's see
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does with this. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this תפשוטה מדרבי יוחנן בר חנינא *tifshotei mid'Rabbi Yochanan
bar Chanina* how about just concluding from our earlier discussion דאמר מודה
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *d'amar modeh Rabbi Eliezer* that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* agrees. If you remember what that discussion was was
that the משנה mishna, *mishna* before had a case about the exact
case in the משנה mishna *mishna* was a תמורת עולה Olah. וולד
תמורת עולה olah
*tmurat olah v'vlad tmurat olah* and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
says הוא עצמו יקרב עולה ola? *hu atzmo yikrav olah*. So if
you made a female an עולה *olah* or actually the case in
the משנה mishna, *mishna* was that you made a male an עולה
*olah* and then you had a תמורה tmura *tmurah* and then you
had the child that he says once you hit a male you're
able to bring it as an עולה *olah*. So logically you would
say the same is true if you had a female as an
אשם Asham *asham* you had a child once you hit a male
why not bring it as an אשם asham *asham* or bring it
as an עולה *olah* since that's what happens with an אשם asham?
*asham* that gets derailed. And here however the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said
רבי יוחנן בר חנינא *Rabbi Yochanan bar Chanina* said no that's different.
Why is that different? So the reason it was given was different
is because there it's not the same as the קדושה kedusha *kedusha*
of the original one. The קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* of the original one
was for the sake of an אשם *asham*. Here the argument is
bring it as an עולה *olah*. Since it's not the same in
the case in the משנה mishna *mishna* it was an עולה *olah*
that you were now bringing as an עולה *olah* so it was
the same as the original.
Here the first one you did either with a female עולה *olah*
or male עולה *olah* and then it went to a תמורה tmura
*tmurah* but the one you want to bring at the bottom when
you hit male again is the same as the original קדושה kedusha
*kedusha* of an עולה *olah*. Here when you finally get to a
male what you do with an אשם *asham* that sort of derailed
is you bring it as an עולה *olah* so it's not the
same as the original קדושה kedusha. *kedusha*.
What wasn't the first one brought as a first the first case
that was a male? Why wasn't it itself?
It might have been but there also was then the תמורה tmura
*tmurah* and the ולד vlad *vlad* or whatever. So those were two
scenarios the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* dealt with before about what happens if
the first there are two cases one is the first is a
female the other is the first is a male then you do
a תמורה tmura, *tmurah*. Okay but in all those cases the one
at the bottom of the chain when you're bringing the male it's
the same as the original קדושה kedusha. *kedusha*. Whereas here the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* said earlier that he wouldn't say the same if the
first was a קדושה kedusha *kedusha* of an אשם *asham* and then
because you were dealing now with a ולד vlad. *vlad* or a
תמורה tmura *tmurah* whatever that it was going to be an עולה
*olah*. So that was a different קדושה kedusha *kedusha* than the original
and you couldn't bring it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this so why don't you just conclude it we discussed this earlier?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא Lo, שמיע ליה *lo shmi'a
lei*. He didn't hear about that earlier discussion. Maybe he doesn't agree
with it. So he wanted to know he was asking the same
question and he wasn't part of the earlier discussion he wanted to
figure it out for himself. So מאי *mai*? So the question was
so what would be the הלכה halacha *halacha*? So actually it's going
to come to the different conclusion than we came to before. אמר
ליה Amar lei בנה יקרב עולה *amar lei benah yikrav olah*. Yeah
you could bring an עולה *olah*. Even if you start with an
אשם *asham* a female אשם *asham* once you hit male and rather
than use the proceeds for an עולה *olah* might as well bring
the thing itself as an עולה *olah*.
What is the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying that there was that whole
רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina* thing? Why are they saying מאי *mai* then
now?
What do you mean?
No, he
asked
the question, where was it? רב אבין Reb Avin asked רב אבין
בר כהנא Reb Avin bar Kahana what he thought and he thought
different than the earlier גמרא's Gemara discussion of the גמרא. Gemara He
thought that you could bring it as an עולה. אמר ליה Amar
lei, בן קרבולס, ben Karbolas, so גמרא Gemara says האי מאי? hai
mai? So he didn't like the answer because he was still convinced
by the earlier logic of the גמרא. Gemara. עד כאן לא קאמר
Ad kan lo ka'amar רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אלא מפריש נקבה לעולה
ela mafrish nekeiva l'Olah דאיכא שם עולה עמו. d'ika shem Olah imo.
When does he say that? When you started with, when the original
קדושה kedusha, was an עולה and now you're bringing an עולה, so
the descendant that you're bringing, the derivative is the same as the
original
קדושה. kedusha אבל גבי אשם Aval gabei Asham דליכא שם עולה עמו,
d'leika shem Olah imo, by an אשם where the original קדושה kedusha
was an אשם and now you're bringing the child or the ולד
vlad or the תמורה, tmura whatever you're bringing is you're bringing it
as an עולה, it's not the same as the original
קדושה. kedusha אפילו רבי אליעזר מודי, Afilu Rabbi Eliezer modei, even רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, should agree, which is basically what the גמרא Gemara
earlier said, but here that was exactly, he bought into that logic.
So he says you can't compare the cases. אמר ליה, Amar lei
he said back, no, I don't think רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. is
so specific. I think רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. is a more general
position. אמר ליה amar lei טעמא דרבי אליעזר ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer לאו
משום דשם עולה עמו. lav mishum d'shem Olah imo. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer doesn't require that when you hit the male that could be
brought that it has the same, that it be identical to the
original קדושה. kedusha אלא משום דחזי לאקרובה, Ela mishum d'chazi l'akrava, as
soon as you're able to bring it, so you bring it. והאי
נמי חזי לאקרובה, V'hai nami chazi l'akrava, and you can bring it.
So he says, yeah, I don't agree with the earlier discussion. The
earlier discussion drives it very narrow, when would you say that when
you have the child of the female or the child of the
תמורה, temurah when can you bring the thing itself? And it said
only when it has the same קדושה kedusha, as the mother. I
don't think he's so specific. I think he says that if you
can for, if you have something that derives and you're able to
bring the thing itself, why should you bother redeeming it and using
the proceeds? Just go ahead and bring the thing itself. It doesn't
have to have the same קדושה kedusha as the mother as where
it originated from. Okay, איתיבי, eitvei, I'll ask you on this our
משנה, mishna. because our משנה mishna was talking about if you remember
the child of a תמורה temurah of an אשם, so it was
a similar case. You sanctified an אשם, then you had a תמורה
temurah which was a female, then you had children. And the whole
discussion in our משנה mishna was, okay, you wait for it, what
do you do? Do you let it die? Do you use the
proceeds for an עולה, do you use the proceeds for an עולת
יחיד, Olas yachid, an עולת ציבור? Olas tzibur? Nobody in our משנה,
mishnah. including רבי אליעזר, nobody in our משנה mishnah. said, oh, if
the child is a male you can bring the child itself. How
does that fit in with your claim that he would say you
could bring the child once you hit the male? So it says
איתיבי eitvei our משנה, mishnah ולדותן וולד ולדותן עד סוף כל העולם
יביא בדמיהם עולה, vladon u'vlad vladon ad sof kol ha'olam yavi bidmeihem
Olah, and those are the words of רבי אליעזר. Use the proceeds
for an עולה. בדמיהן אין, Bidmeihen in, their proceeds yes, עצמן לא,
atzman lo, you cannot bring the animal itself even though now you've
hit a male. Now of course there actually could be an easy
answer to this which the גמרא Gemara doesn't say, it seems to
me an easy answer, but let's read the גמרא's Gemara answer. Okay,
I'll tell you, the easy answer could be that our משנה mishnah.
is talking about you first do a תמורה temurah and then you
have the kids. Well when you do a תמורה, temurah. right, the
הלכה halacha is is that a תמורת אשם has to graze and
so on and you know the money has to go out what
you know it has to be has to be you know you
have to wait for it to get a מום mum and then
you use the proceeds. So you could say the child would follow
that. Whereas the question that we were asking was when you sanctified
a נקבה nekeiva for an אשם. The הלכה halacha. of a נקבה
nekeiva for an אשם never was in the category of wait till
it gets a מום mum and use the proceeds, meaning it was
never in that, remember the category is that a חטאת, the five
חטאות chatas you let die, when you have the parallel by an
אשם you have to wait till it gets a מום mum and
use the proceeds for an עולה. So you hit that when you
get to a תמורה temurah. and then you can say there it
that passes down then to the kids and the kids also follow
the same הלכה. halacha But when you מקדיש makdish a נקבה nekeiva.
for an אשם you're not even in that category yet, so maybe
the kids can more be brought themselves. Although because he expressed that
his logic is that I don't care about the earlier level of
קדושה, kedusha, once this thing can be brought you bring it, so
the גמרא Gemara is saying that should be the same principle in
the משנה. mishnah, Even if you went through a תמורה temurah and
now you have the kids, if the thing itself can be brought
and is a male, why should you wait to use the proceeds?
Bring the thing itself. That's how you're explaining the logic of רבי
אליעזר. So the גמרא Gemara says how do you explain why in
the משנה mishna you don't bring the thing itself? So it says
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שילדה נקבה. hacha b'mai askinan k'gon she'yalda nekeiva.
All right, you're right, if it was a male you could bring
the thing itself. But we're talking about that the kid was a
female. So the גמרא Gemara says ועד סוף עולם לא אוליד זכר?
v'ad sof olam lo ulid zachar? It says ולדותן וולד ולדותן עד
סוף
כל העולם. vlad u'vlad vlad ad sof kol ha'olam. So you're saying
the scenario in the משנה mishna, is that a thousand generations it
didn't have one female male? So it says אמר ליה משנינן שינויי
דחיקא בבבל. meshanyinan shinuyei d'chika b'Vavel.
I'll give you one of those like you know very forced Babylonian
answers. Yes, כגון שילדה נקבה עד סוף העולם. k'gon she'yalda nekeiva ad
sof ha'olam. Like it had females for the rest of its life.
So it's very fascinating that they frame these like קוועטש kvech answers
as you know those are the way the Babylonians answer their questions,
you know they give קוועטש kvech answers, which actually is interesting in
a larger analysis of the difference between the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
אמוראים Amoraim and the בבלי Bavli אמוראים. Amoraim. Yeah, here are some
אמוראים. Amoraim.
Apparently from the way he framed the answer רב אבין probably in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, רב אבין בר כהנא, Reb Avin bar Kahana,
yeah. So
but the גמרא Gemara actually other people have other גרסאות girsas which
says that the גמרא Gemara, then went on to say the fact
that you said you're going to give a bad answer means you
have to Theoretically like a better answer. So what is that better
answer? Well, the better answer wasn't so much better, so but anyway,
it wasn't such a crazy scenario as
you take a look at the שיטה מקובצת. Shita Mekubetzet. He says
that when it says, it's not such a better answer, so when
it says you use their money, it means if it's a female
you use their money. If it's a male you bring the thing
itself. Rather than describing that the scenario is all females, it's saying
that we're assuming in the case of a female, but in the
case, you know, there's missing, a missing caption or something.
Is missing words.
Yeah, or is right, it's not addressing, yeah, it's not a significantly
different answer. The הגר"א the Gra suggests yet another possibility, yes.
This looks derogatory towards the Babylonians, but this was compiled by Babylonians.
Yeah, it is interesting actually sometimes the בבלי Bavli transmits negative attitudes
of the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael אמוראים Amoraim to
about the בבלאים, Bavloim, like one famous phrase is כמה בבלאי טפשאי?
Kamma Bavloei Tipshaei?
No, well that, but no, but it's, you know, כיון, keivan, what
is it, since you live באתרא חשוכה, ba'aracha chashocha, I mean מילין
חשוכין milin chashochin like because, you know, בבל Bavel didn't get a
lot of sunshine or whatever, so they said you live in a
dark land, you say dark words. So it's interesting sometimes they like
transmit those like some of those negative attitudes. Okay, anyway, thankfully now
we are done with that very sort of complicated discussions, but I,
you know, fascinating about when you can't bring the original thing if
it's a wrong gender let's say. First of all, if you remember
there was a discussion about does that count as a מום mum
or a better way to frame it is because it's not relevant,
can it, did it never get קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf and can
you redeem it? That was one question when you sanctify a נקבה.
nekeiva But then there's other questions which is whether you מקדיש makdish
a נקבה nekeiva. or you מקדיש makdish a זכר zachar and then
you do תמורה temurah? to a נקבה. nekeiva Under what circumstances can
if you when you hit a male, can you bring the one
itself? And that was the position of רבי אליעזר and we were
trying to define how does he say that in all cases, only
in cases when it has a similar קדושה kedusha to the mother
and so on. So that was a couple of דפים dappim on
that and that sort of ends that discussion and now we end
the פרק perek with a much more easy discussion as we move
from אשם and עולה to בכור bechor and מעשר. ma'aser. Let's take
a look at the משנה. mishna תמורת הבכור והמעשר, Temurat habechor ve'hama'aser,
the תמורה Temurah. of a בכור bechor and מעשר. ma'aser.
Now you will remember that the הלכה halacha בכור ומעשר bechor u'maiser
is is that you don't bring their תמורה temurah as a קרבן.
korban. The גמרא Gemara learns it out from a פסוק. pasuk. First
of all, let's start with this. If they get a blemish you
don't redeem them. Why not? Because they, the פסוק pasuk says לא
ימכר, lo yimacher, it says לא ימכר ולא יגאל lo yimacher velo
yiga'el or לא יפדה, lo yipadeh, by בכור ומעשר bechor u'maiser it
says you cannot redeem it. So the הלכה halacha here is bizarre,
different than all other קרבנות, korbanot? that you don't redeem it, but
you eat it outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It remains, it
retains the קדושה kedusha and you eat it without bringing it as
a קרבן. korban. You שוחט shecht it and you eat it outside
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. בכור Bechor is eaten by the כהן
kohen because you give it to the כהן, kohen, מעשר maiser by
anybody. That's one way in which they're different. The other way in
which they're different is that they don't, that if you make a
תמורה temurah with them you don't, you're not מקרב makriv the תמורה.
temurah, The גמרא Gemara learns it out from פסוקים, pesukim, but again,
as I keep on saying, the logic is, is you know,
there's a very compelling logic, which is that you don't instill קדושת
בכור kedushat bechor and קדושת מעשר kedushat ma'aser on any animal. Part
of it has to do with reality that first of all בכור
bechor you don't instill the קדושה kedusha at all, and but and
מעשר ma'aser you do, but it's only on the tenth animal. Part
of it has to do with the reality that it is the
בכור, bechor, it is the מעשר. ma'aser. And therefore when you transfer
קדושה kedusha to something that isn't בכור bechor and isn't מעשר, ma'aser,
in the end it's not going to have the same status as
בכור bechor and מעשר, ma'aser, it's not going to be able to
be brought as a קרבן. korban, So what are you going to
do with it then? You can't bring it as a קרבן, korban.
so you wait till it gets a מום mum. and you eat
it outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Here's one case where you
don't have to worry about redeeming it or letting it die or
anything like that, you're going to eat it outside the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. Okay, but they do have this different הלכה halacha, about
תמורה. temurah So let's take a look at the משנה. mishna תמורת
הבכור והמעשר, Temurat habechor ve'hama'aser,
if you have תמורה temurah from בכור bechor and מעשר, maiser, ולדן
וולד ולדן, vladan u'vlad vladan, or the children of בכור bechor and
מעשר. maiser. Now of course by בכור bechor it can only be
male, מעשר ma'aser can be female, so you can have direct children
of the מעשר ma'aser itself. Anyway, עד סוף העולם, ad sof ha'olam,
till the end of the world, הרי אלו כבכור וכמעשר, harei elu
kebechor u'kema'aser, they're like בכור bechor and מעשר, maiser, they have the
same קדושה, kedusha. but not that you can bring them as a
קרבן. korban, ויאכלו במומם לבעלים, Veyeachlu bemumam labe'alim, and but you have
to wait till they get a blemish and then they're eaten by
their owners, either the כהן kohen or the ישראל. Yisrael. So you
can't bring them as a קרבן, korban if they get a blemish
you don't redeem them, you eat them outside the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
Now the question is are there ולד? vlad Or is that only
going on the תמורה? temurah תמורה.
tmura Or by a מעשר ma'aser which going on the ולד vlad
themselves, which is also the other important הלכה, halacha once and you
see the basic same הלכה halacha for תמורה tmura and ולד. vlad
The same way you're not מקרב makriv a תמורה tmura. of a
בכור bechor and מעשר, maiser, you're not מקרב makriv the ולד vlad
of a מעשר ma'aser or the ולד vlad, of a תמורה, tmura.
but that's more obvious. But even if a מעשר ma'aser directly is
a female and gives birth, since it's not מעשר ma'aser itself, you're
not מקרב makriv it. Okay, so you wait till they get a
מום. mum, Now it says, the משנה mishna asks itself, מה בין
בכור ומעשר לבין כל הקדשים? mah bein bechor u'maiser levein kol hakodashim?
It's very funny that it runs it sort of after like it
did that previous משנה. mishna What is the difference between these two
שיטות? shitot? The גמרא Gemara said, remember, previous משנה, Mishnah anyway, what's
the difference between בכור bechor and מעשר ma'aser and other קרבנות? korbanot
שכל הקדשים נמכרין באיטליז ונשחטין באיטליז ונשקלין בליטרא. Shekol hakodashim nimkarin be'itliz
venishchatin be'itliz venishkalin belitra.
All קדשים kodashim if they get a מום, mum, you're talking specifically
if they get a מום, mum, can be sold in the sort
of meat market, שוחטed shecht in the meat market, and they can
be weighed out by, you know, by the pound. What does this
mean? If I have a קרבן korban. that has a מום, mum,
what I do? I redeem the money at the value and I
use that money to buy another animal for a קרבן. korban, So
how do I determine what the value of this animal is? Well,
the value of this animal is how much I can get when
I sell it. So, if now how do I have to sell
it? If you tell me I can only sell it wholesale, I'm
not going to get as much money. If you allow me to
sell it retail, I'll get more money. So therefore basically חז"ל Chazal
said although it's not so respectful for an animal that once was
a קרבן, korban it's פסולי המוקדשין psulei hamukdashin now, to go ahead
and שחט shecht it in the meat market and sell it in
the meat market and weigh it out, but in the end that's
going to allow you to get more money for it, right, once
it's redeemed, and that will mean that when the value you transfer
it onto will be higher. So therefore we want you to get
maximum profit out of this or maximum money so that when you
transfer the value, the money that goes towards the next קרבן korban,
is at a higher market as at a higher value rather than
a lesser one. That's why all other קרבנות korbanot. where in the
end you're going to transfer the value and buy another קרבן, korban
so we want to give you the option of selling it at
or the ability to sell it at a high price. However, חוץ
מן הבכור והמעשר. chutz min habechor vehama'aser. By בכור ומעשר bechor uma'aser
we don't let you שחט shecht it in the marketplace and sell
it in the marketplace and sell it by the pound. If you're
going to sell it, you can only do it private and wholesale.
Why? Because הקדש hekdesh is not going to see a קרבן korban.
out of this, right, you're not going to transfer the value and
buy another קרבן. korban You're just going to eat this yourself. So
since you're going to eat it yourself, we're not so invested in
you making a bigger profit. You know, it's not helping הקדש hekdesh
and we're more interested that you show the respect to the קרבנות.
korbanot, And therefore since this has a קרבן korban with a מום,
mum we do not want it to be sold in such, you
know, and like treated just like meat in the meat market, and
therefore we'll only let you sell it private. Of course you could
also point out another difference, which is that when you ultimately do
sell the other קרבנות, korbanot you've already transferred the קדושה kedusha. away.
So they're now just things that were once קדוש. kadosh. The בכור
bechor and the מעשר ma'aser still have the קדושה, kedusha okay, but
the way it's normally framed is that in the first case, if
you sell it at a higher price, הקדש hekdesh gets more money.
This case, you're the only one who's going to profit. Okay. Yes.
You're selling the תמורה tmura or you're selling the...
No, no, this is the original one that got a blemish. Okay.
And what are you going to if you're going to eat what
are you going to eat if you're selling?
So no, if it's your בכור ומעשר, bechor uma'aser, you can eat
it yourself or you can sell it to someone who will eat
it. You're allowed to sell it. Yeah, and they'll eat it. Right.
You don't have to sell it.
You don't have to, right, right. You don't have to sell the
other one either. Once you redeem the value, you can eat the
steak. Okay, so fine. All right, so the גמרא Gemara is saying
ויש להם פדיון ותמורתן פדיון. veyesh lahem pidyon utmuratan pidyon. Now
again, another difference between בכור ומעשר bechor uma'aser and other קרבנות korbanot
that have a מום mum, is יש להם פדיון ותמורתן פדיון. yesh
lahem pidyon utmuratan pidyon. Other animals that get a מום, mum. you
can redeem them and you can redeem their תמורה tmura. if their
תמורה has a מום. mum, חוץ מן הבכור והמעשר. chutz min habechor
vehama'aser. But בכור ומעשר bechor uma'aser you don't redeem it with a
מום, mum you eat it with a מום mum. outside of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
ובאים מחוצה לארץ. uvaim michutza la'aretz. And all other קרבנות korbanot, you
can come from bring from חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. חוץ מן הבכור
והמעשר. chutz min habechor vehama'aser. Now that's should be a little shocking,
right? You would assume if these things have קדושה kedusha. and the
קדושה kedusha is independent on ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, then why can't
you bring a קרבן korban from חוצה לארץ? chutz la'aretz? So we
will, if you remember, we did discuss this in בכורות Bechorot and
we'll discuss it again, but let's just read what רש"י Rashi says.
שאם באו תמימים יקרבו. she'im bau tmimim yikrevu. You're not supposed to
bring them from חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but if somebody went ahead
and brought them, well, if they're unblemished, fine, then we'll bring them
as a קרבן korban, בדיעבד. bedi'avad. ואם בעלי מומין יאכלו במומם לבעלים.
ve'im ba'alei mumin ye'achlu bemumam labe'alim. And if they have a blemish,
then we'll say obviously even if you brought them to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, so what, you still can't bring it as a קרבן,
korban eat them outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash with their מום.
mum. אמר רבי שמעון. Amar Rabbi Shimon.
Now רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon explains
why we don't want to accept בכור ומעשר bechor uma'aser from חוצה
לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Let's take a look. מה טעם? Ma ta'am? What's
the reason we don't want to accept them from חוצה לארץ? chutz
la'aretz? שהבכור והמעשר יש להם פרנסה ממקומם. shehabechor vehama'aser yesh lahem parnasa
mimkomam. בכור ומעשר bechor uma'aser can be eaten in חוצה לארץ. chutz
la'aretz. How can they be eaten in חוצה לארץ? chutz la'aretz? Well,
if you wait, they can be eaten how? If they get a
מום. mum, So therefore any other if I מקדיש makdish a קרבן
korban in חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz, I'm going to have to bring
a קרבן korban to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Even if this
one gets a מום, mum, I'll have to transfer the value and
bring bring, you know, and bring another קרבן korban. in its stead.
בכור ומעשר bechor uma'aser there's a way I could eat it outside
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So he says since those can be
eaten, you know, they can be sort of they have a פרנסה,
parnasa, they can be sustained where they are, meaning you can deal
with them where they are, then deal with them where they are,
don't bring them as a קרבן. korban ושאר כל הקדשים אף על
פי שנולד בהם מום הרי אלו בקדושתן. veshar kol hakodashim af al
pi shenolad bahem mum harei elu bikdushatan. But other קרבנות, korbanot, even
if they get a מום, mum you're going to have to transfer
the value and bring it, so of course we'll accept the קרבן
korban from חוץ chutz so you don't have a choice. Now that's
of course very bizarre. We get that you have a choice, but
why would we want people to stay in חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz
and not use an opportunity to come to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and to bring a קרבן korban in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
You know, it explains sort of why maybe me who lives in
חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz in my in my self-interest not to שלעפ
shlep to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael because I could just wait till
it gets a blemish. But why actually we would say we're not
interested in it, we'd rather you deal with it where you are
rather than bring a קרבן korban is not at all clear and,
you know, it's it's going to remain a question. תוספות Tosafot sort
of deals with it as well.
Yes. It might be a practical thing. They've already got logistical problems
dealing with all the people coming
for the festivals and to add each one bringing lots of בכור,
bechor, lots of מעשר ma'aser animals, it would be the largest stockyard
in the in the world.
That could be, I guess assuming that the people most... were going
to be visiting during during the רגלים, regalim, where everywhere it's already
crazy busy. Yeah, right. And מעשר maaser animals also.
You have to be מפריש מעשר בהמה, mafrish maaser behema, not מעשר
דגן, maaser dagan, מעשר בהמה, maaser behema, and then the thing is
we'd prefer, you know, you waited until it got a מום mum,
and ate it outside of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash instead of
bringing it to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Right.
But did people do that?
Well, we're going to get to a פרק perek in which it's
going to be just a fascinating פרק. perek. The name of the
פרק perek is the first משנה Mishnah of the פרק perek is
כיצד מערימין על הבכור. Keitzad Maarimin Al HaBechor. How do you scheme
so that you don't have to do it? Okay.
So, but and people
and people criticize us now when we try to find workarounds. חז"ל
Chazal was into workarounds.
Well, we actually use those as the model. All right.
Find workarounds.
Yes. In other cases, that's true too. Right. There you go. All
right, let's take a look. So anyway, that is a question we
will revisit that question, let's about why we're trying to avoid bringing
them to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara אמר רבא בר רב אדא בעו במערבא. Amar
Rava Bar Rav Adda bau b'Maarava. So he asks, they say they
asked in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael the following question. המטיל מום בתמורת
בכור ומעשר מהו. HaMatil mum b'tmurat bechor u'maaser mahu. If you remember,
there's an איסור issur to be מטיל מום בקדשים. matil mum b'kodashim.
What about if you make a מום, mum you make a blemish
intentionally in an animal that's תמורת מעשר, tmurat maaser, תמורת בכור, tmurat
bechor, or ולד מעשר? vlad maaser? You can't bring it as a
קרבן korban. anyway. So making a מום mum? is not preventing it
from getting to the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. There's no way you
can bring it to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because it's a
תמורה or ולד of מעשר maaser and בכור, bechor, which we said
are never קרבן. korban Is there a prohibition to make a מום?
mum This is a very relevant question because if I'm stuck with
the תמורה or ולד of מעשר בכור, maaser bechor, I'd rather just
make the מום mum and eat it rather than having it, you
know, hang around. So am I allowed to make a מום mum,
since I anyway can't bring it to the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash?
So מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say כיון דלא קרבי לא
מחייב, keivan d'lo karvei lo mechayev, since they're not brought as קרבנות,
korbanot, you don't transgress if you make a מום, mum you haven't
really impacted it? או דלמא כיון דקדשי מחייב, o dilma keivan d'kadshei
mechayev, or do we say no, it doesn't matter, it's a קרבן
korban and you're prohibited making a מום mum in a קרבן korban.
and it's not relevant to whether it's going to prevent it from
being brought or not? אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי
Abaye said back to him, ותיבעי לך המטיל מום בתשיעי מעשר. v'tiba'ei
lach hamatil mum b'tshii maaser. There's another case which actually is can't
be brought as a קרבן. korban What's the case that can't be
brought as a קרבן korban. without a blemish? Is the if you
called the ninth animal when you they were going out of the
fence, ten, you miscounted. If you remember way back in בכורות Bechorot
we said that that's קדוש ואינו קרב. kadosh v'eino karev. It's just
like the case of the ולד and the תמורה. It has קדושת
מעשר kedushat maaser but because it's not the tenth, you can't bring
it as a קרבן. korban? So that's the eleventh. The
eleventh you bring but that's a שלמים. shlamim. Let's ask there as
well, can you make a מום mum. since anyway it can't be
brought as a קרבן? korban, Now if you remember the cases we
had before, you could have also asked it about a lot of
other cases, like what about if it's a נקבה nekeiva, for an
עולה? What if about if it's a טרפה, treifa, right? All these
other things where you can't bring them as a קרבן, korban you're
waiting around for it to be a מום. mum Now are you
allowed to make a מום mum if anyway it can't be brought?
So that's the question. So he says,
אלא, ela, so why didn't you ask about the case of the
ninth for מעשר? maaser? אלא מאי שנא תשיעי דלא קמיבעיא לך, ela
mai shna tshii d'lo kamiba'ei lach, why didn't you ask that? דרחמנא
מיעטיה, d'rachmana miatei, because it's excluded from being מעשר. maaser. How do
you know it? It says עשירי, asiri, the tenth is קודש, kodesh,
והוציא תשיעי, v'hotzi tshii, that the tenth is not. הכא נמי רחמנא
מיעטינהו, hacha nami rachmana miatinhu, here too the Torah excluded it. לא
תיפדה קודש הם, lo tipadeh kodesh hem, it cannot be redeemed, they
are קודש. kodesh. הם קרבים ואין תמורתן קריבה, hem kreivin v'ein tmuratan
kriva, only they are brought, not their תמורה. And therefore since we
learn that their תמורה and ולד, of course you can there's no
problem making a מום mum or certainly you don't transgress the lashes.
Now of course this is a little circular as the גמרא Gemara
itself is going to make it clear in the next statement. Because
all these פסוקים psukim say is that they're not brought. They don't
address the question of a קרבן korban. that has קדושה kedusha, that
isn't brought, is there prohibition to make a מום mum. or not?
Right? So he says, so basically he answers, well, why didn't you
ask the other case? Presumably you took that for granted. So for
whatever reason you took that for granted, you should take this for
granted as well. Okay, but it still is a little circular because
there's nothing in that case the other case itself that indicates the
question of what is the story about making a מום. mum. All
it tells you is that you can't bring it as a קרבן.
korban? But that's the case they're talking about.
So you just ask on that.
Okay, anyway, so the גמרא Gemara itself now we'll see sort of
acknowledges that it's circular because there's another version of this that goes
the other direction. Let's take a look. רב פנחס בריה דרב חסדא
מתני לה הכי. Rav Pinchas brei d'Rav Chisda matni lah hachi. רב
פנחס בריה דרב חסדא Rav Pinchas brei d'Rav Chisda said this was
the version of the discussion. אמר רב אחא בריה דרב אדא בעו
במערבא. Amar Rav Acha brei d'Rav Adda bau b'Maarava. They asked in
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. המטיל מום בתשיעי מעשר, HaMatil mum b'tshii maaser,
so they asked about the they did ask about the other case.
Can you make a blemish in the ninth one that you called
מעשר, maaser, which also you can't bring as a קרבן? korban? מהו?
mahu? אמר ליה ותיבעי לך המטיל מום בתמורת בכור ומעשר, Amar lei
v'tiba'ei lach hamatil mum b'tmurat bechor u'maaser,
why didn't you ask about the case of, you know, תמורת בכור
ומעשר, tmurat bechor u'maaser, our משנה, which also can't be brought as
a קרבן? korban. אלא מאי שנא תמורת בכור ומעשר דלא קמיבעיא לך,
ela mai shna tmurat bechor u'maaser d'lo kamiba'ei lach,
why did you not bother asking there? דרחמנא מיעטינהו, d'rachmana miatinhu, they're
excluded from being brought. קודש הם הם קרבים ואין תמורתן קריבה, kodesh
hem hem kreivin v'ein tmuratan kriva,
only they can be brought and not their תמורה. So you took
it for granted that since they can't be brought, there's no problem
about making a מום. mum, תשיעי מעשר נמי רחמנא מיעטיה, tshii maaser
nami rachmana miatei,
here too it can't be brought as a קרבן. korban?
העשירי והוציא את התשיעי, ha'asiri v'hotzi et hatshii, only the
tenth and not the ninth. takes the other one for granted. Maybe
that was the one that occurred to him, that was the context
of what they were learning. But at least the response that came
back sort of was committed to the idea, you know, clearly it's
not in the פסוקים, psukim, but sort of take, you know, already
assumed that since it can't be brought there's not a problem with
a מום, mum, and therefore said, so if in this other one
there isn't a problem, then it's the same true here as well.
So the גמרא Gemara seems to conclude that there isn't a problem
making a מום, mum although again, it's really not, you know, there's
no evidence brought to that. It's just the assumption, you know, that's
really what, you know, is that what begging the question is? It's
been, anyway, I don't know, there's an objective, there's basically a phrase
that the assumption you read in and then you come back and
you read that same assumption back out after, you know, you're basically
reading back out the assumption you read in. But that's at least
what his position, which was, is that if it can't be brought
there's no problem, which is a big נפקא מינה. nafka mina. All
the cases that, at least not all, at least these cases, you
know, don't have to wait around and maybe misuse it or whatever,
just make a מום mum and be done with it. And then
that raises the question about how about all those other things? How
about נקבה, nekeiva how about טרפה? treifa? Now maybe you could distinguish,
maybe you could say here the nature of the קדושה kedusha from
the very beginning was a different quality of a קדושה. kedusha But,
you know, maybe that's true also when you're מקדיש makdish a נקבה
that it was a different type of a קדושה. kedusha So it
raises the interesting questions there as well. Now תוספות Tosafot says, so
that's one question, can you make a מום mum in an unblemished
animal that can't be brought as a קרבן? korban, And here the
גמרא Gemara says that at least by the cases it's dealing with
the answer seems to be yes. Now תוספות Tosafot says, why did
the גמרא Gemara not put this in the context of a discussion
it has over in מנחות, Menachot, which is can you make a
מום mum? in an animal that already has a מום? mum Isn't
that essentially the same question? It can't be brought as a קרבן,
korban can you make a מום mum in it? So תוספות Tosafot
says it's not the same question, because even if you said that
you're allowed to make a מום mum, in a מום, mum. you
might say here you're not, because there, not only can it not
be brought, but it already has a מום. mum So physically adding
another מום mum does not make an unblemished into a blemished, it
was already blemished. So there it might be prohibited and here permitted.
He said also the opposite is true. There it might be prohibited
and here it's permitted because there the original קדושה kedusha was full,
it was able to be brought and then it got off track,
but it started as a full קדושה. kedusha So there it might
retain the prohibition of making a מום Mum, even when it gets
a blemish. Here the original קדושה kedusha never would have been able
to be brought and therefore it might be permitted. Says תוספות, Tosafot,
it is a similar question but the outcomes are not interdependent. Okay,
so very interesting question and very relevant also if you're dealing with
these types of animals.
Yeah, there's not a good reason why he would be motivated to,
but the גמרא Gemara just asks as a hypothetical whether it would
be prohibited. Okay, ובאות תמימים. Uva'ot tmimim. Now if they came, now
we go on that it says that about bringing from חוץ לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, that's a fascinating issue. So here our משנה says לכתחילה
lechatchila you don't bring, but בדיעבד bedi'avad if you bring it's okay.
רמינהו, Remineihu, I'll ask you on this, מן האנטיגנוס העלה בכורות מבבל,
Min ha'Antignos he'ela bechorot miBavel, here we have a משנה from חלה
Challa that says that Antignos brought up בכורות bechorot from בבל Bavel
ולא קיבלו ממנו, velo kiblu mimenu, even בדיעבד bedi'avad they refused it.
They said go back home, wait till it gets a blemish, don't
bother us. Okay, so how, our משנה is different, our משנה says
you would accept it if it was done. So גמרא Gemara says
אמר רב חסדא לא קשיא, Amar Rav Chisda lo kashya, הא רבי
ישמעאל הא רבי עקיבא, ha Rabbi Yishmael ha Rabbi Akiva, it's a
debate of Rabbi Yishmael and Rabbi Akiva whether בדיעבד bedi'avad you accept
it. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yossi omer, ג' דברים משום ג' זקנים, Gimel devarim mishum gimel
zkeinim, he had three traditions from three different elders. Rabbi Yishmael, Rabbi
Akiva, and I forget the third one. But anyway, we'll start with
Rabbi Yishmael and Rabbi Akiva. So here was his tradition from Rabbi
Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yishmael omer, יכול יעלה אדם מעשר שני
בזמן הזה ויאכלנו בירושלים, Yachol ya'aleh adam ma'aser sheni bazman hazeh veyochlenu
biYerushalayim, maybe you could bring מעשר שני ma'aser sheni nowadays and eat
it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Meaning even ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael after the
חורבן? churban? Yes, because the implicit question here is and is the
following, is that מעשר שני ma'aser sheni you have to eat in
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but it is one of the few things that you
eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim without being directly in reference to the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Right? קדשים קלים Kodashim kalim you first bring as
a קרבן korban and then you eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. בכור, Bechor,
you bring as a קרבן korban, and then you eat in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. ביכורים, Bikurim, you do a ritual in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash and then you eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Here you just
straight eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And it seems that his question
is, although we'll see how this plays out in the גמרא, Gemara
does ירושלים Yerushalayim have a status not dependent on the בית המקדש?
Beit HaMikdash? Yes, we don't have a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash nowadays,
so maybe he's taking for granted you couldn't eat ביכורים bikurim and
בכור bechor and well, anyway, those, you know, you can't bring a
בכור, bechor, but ביכורים bikurim or whatever you can get, eat those,
those sort of are ירושלים Yerushalayim as the suburbs of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash and they don't have a status when there's no
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But how about מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni? Maybe
that's not based on its connection to the מקדש Mikdash and maybe
you can eat in ירושלים Yerushalayim even בזמן הזה. bazman hazeh. Okay,
so that's his question. ויאכלנו בירושלים בדין, Veyochlenu biYerushalayim badin, now maybe
you could learn it out from just a direct logical derivation. בכור
טעון הבאת מקום ומעשר טעון הבאת מקום, Bechor ta'un hava'at makom uma'aser
ta'un hava'at makom, you have to bring a בכור bechor to ירושלים
Yerushalayim and you have to bring מעשר. ma'aser. מה בכור אינו נאכל
אלא בפני הבית, Mah bechor eino ne'echal ela bifnei habayit, the same
way you can
only eat a בכור bechor when there's a בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
because you can't bring it without
a בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, אף מעשר אינו נאכל אלא בפני הבית,
af ma'aser eino ne'echal ela bifnei habayit, maybe מעשר ma'aser as well.
לא, no, that's not a good argument. אם אמרת בבכור שכן טעון
דמים ואימורים לגבי מזבח, Im amarta bevechor sheken ta'un damim ve'imurim legabei
mizbe'ach, בכור bechor has to be brought as a קרבן, Korban you
do the blood and the innerds on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So of
course that requires... אמרת ביכורים bikurim. טעונים הבאת מקום *amarta bikurim te'unim
havat makom* ומעשר טעון הבאת מקום *u'maaser taun havat makom*. Okay, let's
try it this way. How about ביכורים bikurim. *bikurim*? Those you bring
to ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* and מעשר ma'aser.
*maaser* you bring to ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*.
מה ביכורים אינן נאכלין אלא בפני הבית *mah bikurim einan ne'echalin ela
bifnei habayit*, the same way ביכורים *bikurim* you only do it when
there's a בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, אף מעשר ma'aser. אינו
נאכל אלא בפני הבית *af maaser eino ne'echal ela bifnei habayit*, מעשר
ma'aser? *maaser* should be the same. So at least that's more similar,
it's not a קרבן Korban, ביכורים *korban bikurim*. But the ברייתא *braita*
says back or whatever the argument says back, no, מה לביכורים שכן
טעונים הנחה *mah le'bikurim sheken te'unim hanacha*. No, ביכורים *bikurim* still are
still connected to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. It says
והנחתו לפני ה' אלהיך *vehinachto lifnei Hashem Elokecha*, you do a ritual
sort of waving and placing in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis
Hamikdash*. תאמר במעשר דלא Tomar B'maaser Delo. *tomar be'maaser delo*, maybe so
מעשר ma'aser, *maaser* maybe מעשר ma'aser. *maaser* is not like that. So
maybe therefore it's a very nicely articulated question. בכור bechor. *bechor* and
ביכורים *bikurim* are connected to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*.
So the eating in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* is as an extension of
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. That you would not do
בזמן הזה Bizman hazeh, *bizman hazeh*. But how about מעשר ma'aser. *maaser*?
Maybe that's independent of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*. תלמוד
לומר Talmud Lomar. *talmud lomar*, so that the verse teaches, ואכלת לפני
ה' אלהיך מעשר ma'aser דגנך תירשך ויצהרך ובכרת בקרך וצאנך *ve'achalta lifnei
Hashem Elokecha maaser degancha tiroshcha ve'yitzharecha u'bechorot bekarcha ve'tzonecha*. So eat before
God your מעשר ma'aser? *maaser* and your בכור bechor, *bechor*, so it
connects the two. הקיש מעשר ma'aser לבכור *hikish maaser le'bechor*, it connects
מעשר ma'aser *maaser* to בכור bechor *bechor*. מה בכור bechor. אינו נאכל
אלא בפני הבית אף מעשר ma'aser. אינו נאכל אלא בפני הבית *mah
bechor eino ne'echal ela bifnei habayit af maaser eino ne'echal ela bifnei
habayit*. So the same way your בכור bechor *bechor* requires a בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, מעשר ma'aser, *maaser* requires a בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. And we learn it from the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk*. Okay, now again what it doesn't tell us is what is
the פסוק Pasuk, *pasuk* teaching us? Is it teaching us that מעשר
ma'aser. *maaser*'s ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* status for מעשר Maaser *maaser* is also
seen as an extension of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*,
or is it saying no, the ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* status for מעשר
Maaser. *maaser* is independent of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*,
but even so it's linked, you know, arbitrarily somewhat, somewhat, you know,
somewhat to בכור bechor, *bechor*. So it's an interesting conceptual question whether
I still think, how do I think of the ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*
vis-a-vis מעשר Maaser *maaser*? Do I think of it as an extension
of the מקדש Mikdash, *mikdash* or not? But however I answer that,
based on the link of the פסוק *pasuk*, you don't bring it
when there's no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis Hamikdash*. Now, when you
don't bring בכור bechor *bechor*. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* first of
all says why did you need a פסוק *pasuk*? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* first says ולהדר דינא וליתי במה הצד *u'lehadar dina ve'leiti
be'ma hatzad*, why don't you bring it from the common denominator between,
prove it from ביכורים *bikurim* and בכור bechor *bechor*? You rejected, oh
you can't learn it from בכור bechor, *bechor* because that you sprinkle
the blood. You can't learn it from ביכורים *bikurim*, that you do
a placing before the altar, okay? But what the distinct qualities of
of בכור bechor *bechor* and ביכורים *bikurim*, you know, you can eliminate
and at the end of the day you could say for both
of those it's in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* and you don't do without
a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. So why, you know, the
basic point is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* normally says is you
can't say oh that's different because of X. If the same difference
that בכור bechor *bechor* has is not the difference that ביכורים *bikurim*
has, you can't say that X is the determining factor. So if
the reason בכור bechor *bechor* is different is because the blood is
sprinkled on the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*, well that doesn't happen by ביכורים
*bikurim*. So clearly that's not the determining factor. If the reason ביכורים
*bikurim* is different is because you have this ritual waving and placing,
well that doesn't happen by בכור bechor *bechor*. So that's not the
determining factor. So obviously it means that anything that has to be
in ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim* means a בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. So the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says why the conclusion is still the same. The
conclusion is the same but why did you need a פסוק *pasuk*?
Why didn't you learn it out from the common denominator? So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, אמר רב אשי משום דאיכא למימר מה
להצד השוה שבהן שיש בהן צד מזבח mizbe'ach. *Amar Rav Ashi mishum
de'ika lemeimar mah le'hatzad hashaveh shebahen sheyesh bahen tzad mizbe'ach*. That's right.
Here at least you could say fine, the exact rituals in the
בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* are not the same. But בכור bechor *bechor*
and מעשר Maaser *maaser* both have a same quality, that they have
some ritual in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* relating to the altar.
And therefore that we take for granted no בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*
you don't do them. But מעשר Maaser *maaser* that has no ritual
in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, maybe that you could do nowadays.
Right? So that's a great question. What is the way we relate
ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* for מעשר Maaser. *maaser*? It's based on the בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* or not based on the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*?
In the end we don't really have a full answer to the
conceptual question, but we still say halachically it's linked to בכור bechor
*bechor*. And therefore you don't bring it nowadays. Okay, now the גמרא
*Gemara* analyzes this, we have yet to go back and answer our
first question. We're first going to spend a little time to analyzing
this. ומה קסבר *u'mai kasavar*? Now what is the opinion of this
תנא *tanna* that is not certain, is certain that you don't do
בכור bechor, *bechor* nowadays but is not certain about מעשר Maaser, *maaser*?
אי קסבר קדושה kedusha ראשונה קידשה לשעתה וקידשה לעתיד לבוא vekidsha le'atid
lavo, *ei kasavar kedusha rishona kidsha lishata ve'kidsha le'atid lavo*, if he
thinks that the first קדושה kedusha *kedusha* remains even until today, so
if there's still קדושה kedusha *kedusha* nowadays, the assumption here is that
whatever we say about the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* of ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael *Eretz Yisrael*, we say about the קדושה kedusha. *kedusha* of the
מקום המקדש makom hamikdash, *makom hamikdash*. So if there's still קדושה kedusha,
*kedusha* in מקום המקדש makom hamikdash *makom hamikdash* nowadays, so therefore לא
שנא בכור bechor ולא שנא מעשר Maaser. בני אבונינהו *lo shena bechor
velo shena maaser bnei abuninhu*, you can even bring בכור bechor *bechor*
nowadays. Now you say oh there's no בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, there's
no מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*, fine, so build a מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*. You
don't need a בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, build a מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach*,
put up some curtains, in theory you could even bring בכור Bechor
*bechor* nowadays, which by the way as you might know, every פסח
*Pesach* which we're coming up to, there's always a group that petitions,
headed by Rav Steinzaltz, to be able to bring קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach, *korban Pesach* on הר הבית *Har Habayit*. Cause if you basically
פסקן *pasken* that הר הבית *Har Habayit*... you didn't know about this?
I know about this, like that would make everyone in ירושלים Yerushalayim.
*Yerushalayim* a חייב כרת *chayav kares* for doing it. Oh, that's your
concern. Okay, anyway. All right, we'll talk about that some other time.
Anyway, so right now, anyway, anyway, so basically it says... If the
if the הר הבית is מקום מקדש makom mikdash still has קדושה,
kedusha, then in theory, even you could in theory even bring בכור.
Bechor So if in theory you could bring בכור, Bechor? you should
be allowed to bring מעשר. Maaser Just that practically there's no מזבח,
mizbe'ach. but at least in principle, you're still allowed able and allowed
to bring בכור Bechor nowadays, so you should bring מעשר. Maaser I'm
sorry, and you can't say the same thing for any of the
other קרבנות, Korbanos, like... You could. According... Right. Like an אשם? Yeah.
Just build a מזבח. mizbe'ach, Yeah. No, no, nowadays you can't because
everybody's טמא. tamei. So the only argument to do it for is
to do it for קרבן Korban, פסח, which is טומאה הותרה בציבור.
tumah hutrah betzibur. And you can't say you can't say do it
for the קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur because we don't have a תרומת
הלשכה, trumat halishkah, so we don't have we don't have the funds
to do a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. Okay. Anyway, so the גמרא
says like this... You could bring... What? ביכורים. And you could do
ביכורים. You could do, right, right, maybe it requires מזבח, mizbe'ach. build
a מזבח, mizbe'ach, but at least in principle, it's still relevant nowadays.
So מי קא משמע לן? mi ka mashma lan? Michael, תוספות. Tosafot.
Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Yeah, everybody's going to do
that. Okay, anyway, the גמרא says like this. דאי סלקא דעתך... de'i
salka da'atach... where... דאי סלקא דעתך קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה ולא קידשה
לעתיד לבוא, de'i salka da'atach kedusha rishona kidsha lesha'atah velo kidsha le'atid
lavo, and if you say that the בית המקדש doesn't have קדושה
kedusha nowadays, so אפילו בכור נמי תיבעי לך, afilu bechor nami tibei
lach, you should even ask about בכור. Bechor. Now that's a little
strange, and רש"י, Rashi, a second version of רש"י, Rashi, a later
רש"י, Rashi, and and תוספות Tosafot have a different גירסא. girsa. The
גירסא girsa that I have here is, and if there is no
קדושה Kedusha nowadays, why are you bothering asking for מעשר? Maaser? Of
course you can't bring מעשר, Maaser because if there's no קדושה Kedusha,
of מקום המקדש, makom hamikdash. there's no קדושה Kedushah of ירושלים, Yerushalayim
and of course it would be irrelevant to bring מעשר. Maaser So
the גמרא says make up your mind. If every place still has
קדושה Kedushah nowadays, so you should in theory be able to bring
בכור Bechor and therefore you should be able to bring מעשר. Maaser
If the מקום המקדש makom hamikdash ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't have קדושה nowadays,
then the same by the same token you can't bring בכור, Bechor,
you can't bring מעשר Maaser because ירושלים Yerushalayim doesn't have קדושה nowadays.
So where what where do you think you're dealing with this middle
space where it's obvious you don't bring בכור Bechor but not so
sure about מעשר? Maaser Now of course maybe it's בכור Bechor נמי...
nami... yeah, or no, it's basically אפילו מעשר נמי, afilu ma'aser nami,
you know, it should be פשוט pashut it should be נמי לא.
nami lo. They they have גירסא. girsa. Anyway, so so the so
the obvious answer is or the obvious, you know, interesting conceptual answer,
this comes up a couple of times, is the גמרא often assumes
that the status of all of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is similar
to the status of מקום המקדש. In theory they could be different,
right? There could still be קדושה in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
not in מקום המקדש or vice versa. The רמב"ם Rambam actually פוסק
paskens that that in the period between the first and second בית
המקדש, there was no קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushat Eretz Yisrael but there
was still קדושת מקום המקדש. kedushat makom hamikdash. So they're not necessarily
linked. So actually you could have assumed that exactly this assumption was,
there is קדושת ארץ ישראל, kedushat Eretz Yisrael, there is קדושת ירושלים
kedushat Yerushalayim maybe independent of the מקדש, Mikdash. but after חורבן הבית
churban habayit there's no קדושת מקדש. kedushat mikdash. And therefore, if there's
no קדושת מקדש kedushat mikdash you can't bring בכור, Bechor but that's
the question, does מעשר Maaser. require קדושת מקדש? kedushat mikdash? Right, maybe
מעשר Maaser is independent and maybe there's קדושת ארץ ישראל kedushat Eretz
Yisrael and ירושלים Yerushalayim without being קדושת מקדש. kedushat mikdash. That's how
I think you could have understood the question. The גמרא does not
say that here, it assumes that they are linked. So let's take
a look. So the גמרא says make up your mind. If every
place has קדושה you should be able to do everything. If no
place has קדושה you should be able to do nothing. What's your
question? So the גמרא says הכא במאי עסקינן. hacha bemai askinan. So
the גמרא says לעולם קסבר קדושה ראשונה קידשה לשעתה. le'olam kasavar kedusha
rishona kidsha lesha'atah. Now the גירסא girsa that in the end רש"י
Rashi even רש"י Rashi agrees to and תוספות Tosafot certainly insists on
is וקידשה לעתיד לבוא, because otherwise it really doesn't make any sense.
Really every place has קדושה. Okay? So therefore in theory you should
be able to bring בכור Bechor and מעשר. Maaser But although it
has קדושה, you can't bring בכור Bechor unless there's actually a מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Now it's sort of really realizing that it's not just about
the קדושה, you need the physical מזבח. Mizbeach. Okay. Now what would
be a scenario, now if you just said if you can't bring
it because there's no מזבח, Mizbeach. you can't apply that הלכה halacha
to מעשר, Maaser. because then there's no דין din that you can't
eat בכור Bechor. nowadays, then then it's just the practical problem that
there's no מזבח. Mizbeach. So the גמרא describes a scenario where there
isn't a practical problem but there's still a הלכה halacha that you
can't do בכור Bechor nowadays. I'm sorry, can you say that one
part again? Yes, that if you basically said there is קדושה but
you can't bring בכור Bechor practically because there's no מזבח, Mizbeach. then
you can't apply the הלכה halacha of בכור Bechor. to מעשר. Maaser
But that's not a הלכה halacha of בכור, Bechor. that's just practically
we don't have a מזבח. Mizbeach So the גמרא is going to
describe a scenario where practically you have what you need and even
so there's a הלכה Halacha? that you can't do בכור Bechor nowadays.
I don't like the scenario. So let's yes, exactly. So let's take
a look. דהכא במאי עסקינן, dehacha bemai askinan, what are we talking
about? כגון שנזרק דמו של בכור בפני הבית, kegon shenizrak damo shel
bechor bifnei habayit, you brought a בכור Bechor to the בית המקדש,
they did זריקת הדם, zerikat hadam, this was all happening on like
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av of the last time of the last day
of the standing of the בית המקדש, וחריב הבית, vechariv habayit, and
then, you know, the Romans came in and destroyed the בית המקדש,
okay, then ועדיין בשרו קיים, ve'adayin besaro kayam, now it's the tenth
of אב Av and now of course you' the בכור Bechor was
brought on the מזבח. Mizbeach. Now you don't have a מזבח. Mizbeach
What's the הלכה? Halacha So you can't just say it's a practical
problem because I actually did the הקרבה Hakrava on the מזבח. Mizbeach
Nevertheless, the הלכה Halacha, is you're not allowed to eat the meat.
Why not? כיון Kivan because of the following הלכה, Halacha כיון דאי
איתא לדם לאו בר זביחה הוא, Kivan de'ee issa ledam lavar zvika
hu, since now you're not able to do זריקת הדם... Zrikas hadam...
לאו בר זביחה הוא, Lavar zvika hu, אתי בשר יליף מדם. Asi
basar yalif midam. So you... but in theory if I wanted to
bring it today I couldn't, there's no longer בית המקדש. So therefore
I can't eat the meat because I can't eat the meat at
a time when I can't do זריקת הדם. Zrikas hadam. So there's
actually a הלכה Halacha that I can't eat the meat right now.
ואתי מעשר ויליף מבכור. Ve'asi maaser veyalif mibechor. And then from מעשר
Maaser? we learn out to בכור Bechor and say if you can't
eat the meat, you can't eat the מעשר. Maaser So basically the
short version of this answer is is that yes we assume there
is קדושה and therefore we wanted to ask can I eat מעשר
שני Maaser sheni בירושלים? B'Yerushalayim? Why can't I eat בכור? Bechor I
can't eat בכור Bechor. because there's no... there's no מזבח. So since
there's a... because there's no מזבח there's a הלכה Halacha, that I
can't... it's both a practical problem and a הלכה, Halacha but I
can't eat בכור. Bechor From that I go ahead and I apply
that to מעשר Maaser and I say I also can't eat מעשר
Maaser without a מזבח. Now again this seems to be saying conceptually
that the eating of מעשר Maaser is because of looking at ירושלים
Yerushalayim as a type of a suburb of the מקדש. Mikdash, Okay,
but again maybe not, maybe it's just an arbitrary link. Alright, so
that's how we answer that problem and now the גמרא says has
a few remaining questions. ומי ילפינן קודש מהדדי? Umi yalfinan kodesh me'adadi?
How can you learn one case of קדשים Kodshim from another? Meaning
what did we do? We said since you can't do זריקת הדם
Zrikas hadam you can't eat the meat. Since you can't eat the
meat of a בכור Bechor you can't eat the מעשר שני. Maaser
sheni. So that's a double link. ואמר רבי יוחנן כל התורה כולה
למדין למד מן למד חוץ מקדשים. V'amar Rabbi Yochanan kol hatorah kulah
lemedin lamed min lamed chutz mikodshim. You might remember this, in כל
התורה כולה Kol hatorah kulah we can derive one הלכה Halacha if
you derived A if you derived if you learned out a הלכה
from from A to B then you can learn out the then
from B to C. We can do that in כל התורה כולה
Kol hatorah kulah except by קדשים. Kodshim. By קדשים Kodshim you can't
do a daisy chain. So how can you do a daisy chain?
Blood to meat of the בכור, Bechor. meat of the בכור Bechor.
to מעשר. So the גמרא says שאין למדין למד מן למד. She'ein
lemedin lamed min lamed. There you cannot daisy chain it. So the
גמרא says מעשר חולין הוא. Maaser chullin hu. Ah, since at the
end of the day you're applying it to מעשר, at certainly vis-a-vis
קרבנות, Korbanos it's not considered קודש. Kodesh. There's a whole question whether
you consider מעשר שני Maaser sheni ממון גבוה, Mamon gavoah, ממון הדיוט.
Mamon hedyot. So it doesn't mean completely הקדש, Hekdesh, but it's not
קרבנות Korbanos, הקדש. Hekdesh. So therefore it's excluded from this limit. So
the גמרא says wait a minute, הני למאן דאמר בתר למד אזלינן.
Hani leman d'amar basar lamed azlinan. That's good if you go by
the by the status of C. If C isn't קרבנות, Korbanos then
you can daisy chain it. You go by the final application. אלא
למאן דאמר בתר מלמד אזלינן, Ella leman d'amar basar melamed azlinan, but
if you go by the A and B, if those are קדשים,
Kodshim, then you cannot daisy chain. So A and B are still
קדשים, Kodshim, so you're not allowed to daisy chain. You got it?
You can't daisy chain by קדשים. Kodshim. What if A and B
are קדשים Kodshim and C is not? So it says if you
say you go by A and B, then you can't. So מאי
למימרא? Mai lemeimra? So how can you sort of apply it? בשר
ודם חדא מילתא היא. Basar vedam chada milsa hi. Okay, meat and
the blood are fundamentally the same thing. It's not applying one to
the other, they're really the same package and therefore we can apply
it to מעשר. So that is the end of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. But again the point of... what? It seems like a bit
of a last... yeah I know you needed to learn it but
it's saying you're learning it because essentially they're the same, you're not
really learning. Okay anyway so it seems like רבי פפא Rabbi Pappa
asks a great question. Nowadays can you eat מעשר בירושלים B'Yerushalayim which
is really a question of whether the status of ירושלים Yerushalayim. nowadays
for מעשר for everything else it's based on the בית המקדש. No
בית המקדש obviously you can't eat things in ירושלים. Yerushalayim What's the
story with מעשר? And it learns it out from בכור Bechor that
the same way בכור Bechor you don't eat nowadays in ירושלים because
of its relationship to the מזבח and the מקדש, מעשר as well
not. So even though it has קדושה, it might have קדושת ארץ
ישראל, Kedushas Eretz Yisrael, קדושת ירושלים, Kedushas Yerushalayim, קדושת מקדש, Kedushas Mikdash,
nevertheless it's linked to the actual presence of a מזבח and the
ability to bring it and that's true by בכור Bechor and through
בכור Bechor it's true by מעשר as well. Okay that's רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. Now we get to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva which is
why we introduced this. The גמרא says like this. No it introduced
it like three teachings right? Yeah this is the first. This the
first was רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael now רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. We
introduced it in order to explain the contradiction of ever of you
know of our משנה whether you can accept בכור. Bechor Let's take
a look. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, now רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says, יכול יעלה בכור מחוץ לארץ Yachol yaaleh bechor michutz la'aretz
and here is our case. Maybe you should be able to bring
a בכור Bechor from outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael לארץ La'aretz
בזמן שבית המקדש קיים Bizman sheBeis Hamikdash kayam when there's a בית
המקדש ויקריבנו Veyakrivenu and bring it as a קרבן Korban, בדיעבד Bedieved
even בדיעבד, Bedieved, תלמוד לומר ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך מעשר דגנך תירשך
ויצהרך ובכרת בקרך וצאנך. Talmud lomar veachalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha maaser degancha
tiroshcha veyitzharecha bechoros bekarcha vetzonecha. The same פסוק רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
quoted to teach me about מעשר בזמן הזה, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is quoting the link between בכור Bechor and מעשר is to tell
me about בכור. And what does it tell me? ממקום שאתה מעלה
מעשר דגן אתה מעלה בכור. Mimakom she'atah maaleh maaser dagan atah maaleh
bechor. From the same place that you bring your grain you can
bring your בכור. וממקום שאי אתה מעלה מעשר דגן Umimakom she'ee atah
maaleh maaser dagan where you don't bring מעשר of your grain outside
of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. why not, why בדיעבד Bedieved not? And
if you remember when we learned בכורות, Bechoros, what I suggested was
that if you think about it the whole the גמרא, the תורה,
Torah, it's not just about like the קדושה of the land and
that transfers to the grain and therefore it's only relevant by things
that grow from the ground and it's not relevant to animals and
so on. That's one way of thinking about it. But the other
way of thinking about it is less about the if you would
the dirt of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. and more about the sort
of political entity and the nation of בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael living
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael And if that's where the תורה Torah
primarily conceives of, here's where you're engaged in agriculture and all of
your obligations of agriculture is תרומות ומעשרות Trumos U'maasros and בכור and
מעשר בהמה Maaser Behemah and so on. So that's when you're partaking
in that sort of national reality of בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael living
in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael, When you're outside of it, then it
doesn't have the same significance of bringing a בכור and a מעשר.
Bringing a קרבן, fine to bring a קרבן, a normal קרבן, but
בכור and מעשר is part of the normal products of the year,
of the agricultural year. And that's part of the nation of ישראל
Yisrael living in the land of ישראל Yisrael and not חוץ לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz. That's I think what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is saying,
and therefore it's not ראוי למזבח. Ra'uy L'mizbeach. You wait for it
to get a מום, Mum. you eat it without the מום. You
had a question Charlie? Yes, so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael learns מעשר
from בכור and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns בכור from מעשר. Yes.
So if you accept both of them, you've got circularity. Well, except
they're learning different things from that, so. Well, yeah, but it doesn't
make sense to. No, you can do that. You can learn in
both directions as long as you're learning different things. You learn this
quality to that and that quality to that. But the גמרא or
תוספות Tosafos understands presumably that they're debating and because רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael wouldn't agree to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and that's the position
in our משנה that בדיעבד Bedieved you can bring the בכור. Yes.
Do you go by like where the בכור is or where the
owner is? Yeah, that's a good question. Presumably where the בכור is,
but that's an interesting question like if you lived in both places,
that's a good question. Okay. Yes, but there's another element here because
in the time that we're discussing, there were communities both in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael, and בבל. Bavel. Right. So even though you could
say not everybody is, but there's. Yeah, but sort of like the
תורה, Torah, it's sort of the תורה's Torah understanding of where is
a national life of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, it doesn't happen to
be where they happen to be living. Like the תורה's Torah understanding
is that that's it. But I'm saying there's both, like there are
two centers, right? You have very strong. Right, in practice, but in
terms of what's sort of acknowledged as having religious significance, from the
תורה's Torah perspective, when we're living in בבל, Bavel, we have lost
our sort of like it's a type of a national death. No,
but what's the we? Like I said, in the medieval period where
there were like a dozen Jews living in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael.
you could say Jews outside ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, but here you
have both. You do have a community in ארץ ישראל. I don't
know to what extent they were engaged in agriculture. Right. So for
those people in that community, they would bring בכור. But if you're.
Oh, I see, I misunderstood you to say. Yeah, I'm saying right,
I'm saying that for when you're part of that national life in
ארץ ישראל, that's when you bring בכור. If it happens to be
in and because that's the whole idea of בכור and מעשר is
the yearly product of the agricultural endeavor. Okay, before I run out
of time, let me just say that. Yeah, well, according to בדיעבד
Bedieved you wouldn't do it, right? What? Right, even בדיעבד. Bedieved. Okay,
let's finish this פרק Perek in the next ten minutes. So, let's
take a look. Okay, now where are we? אמר רב פפא. Amar
Rav Pappa. יתבי בן עזאי אומר. Yasvei Ben Azzai Omer. Now בן
עזאי Ben Azzai was the third person who learned from this פסוק,
the third תנא. יכול מעלה מעשר שני יאכלנו בכל הרואה. Yachol Maaleh
Maaser Sheni Yochlenu Bechol Haroeh. Now let's say when you bring מעשר
שני, Maaser Sheni, maybe you're not limited to the area within the
walls of ירושלים. Maybe you can eat it with all the places
that can be seen from ירושלים. Which we know מגילה, Megillah, right,
we know that there's an idea that what places read the מגילה
Megillah on the fifteenth, it's the walled cities and everything that can
be seen from within the walled cities. And this if you, this
I believe is similar to רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael question. How do
you define the קדושה of ירושלים for מעשר? If it's an extension
of the בית המקדש, then it ends by the walls. That we
know and we're going to see that קרבנות Korbanos. ends by the
walls. But if it's the concept of ירושלים as a city, not
defined by the בית המקדש, so sometimes the concepts we have of
a city and the surrounding areas is called הרואה. Haroeh. So maybe
מעשר can be eaten there as well. Yes. The walls of ירושלים
in בית שני Bayis Sheni were built by נחמיה. Nechemiah. Right. And
the בית המקדש existed before those walls were created. Yeah, okay, so
I'm not going to get into right now how that works, but
there's ways in which you do הקדשה Hakdashah of ירושלים and you
can expand the city limits and whatever, so but still the assumption
is that those walls define the, we require a separate הקדשה Hakdashah
to define the parameters of ירושלים for קרבנות. So ודין הוא. V'din
Hu. Now maybe I could learn it out just by logical derivation.
בכור טעון הבאת מקום ומעשר טעון הבאת מקום. Bechor Taun Havaas Makom
U'maaser Taun Havaas Makom. Both בכור and מעשר have to be eaten
in ירושלים. מה בכור אינו נאכל אלא לפנים מן החומה אף מעשר
אינו נאכל אלא לפנים מן החומה. Mah Bechor Eino Ne'echal Ela Lifnim
Min Hachomah Af Maaser Eino Ne'echal Ela Lifnim Min Hachomah. The same
way בכור is within the walls, מעשר is within the walls. לא
מה לבכור שכן טעון מתן דמים ואימורים לגבי מזבח. Lo Mah L'bechor
Shekein Taun Matan Damim V'imurim Legabei Mizbeach. בכור is brought on the
altar and therefore ירושלים for בכור is defined by the walls. תאמר
במעשר דלא. מעשר is not brought on the altar, maybe it's not
defined by the walls. תלמוד לומר. So we connect מעשר *Maaser* to
בכור *Bechor*. מקיש מעשר לבכור *Makish Maaser lebechor*. מה בכור נאכל לפנים
מן החומה *Mah Bechor ne'echal lifnim min hachoma*, the same way בכור
*Bechor* is within the walls, מעשר *Maaser* is within the walls. So
this is very similar to Rabbi Ishmael. Rabbi Ishmael wants to know,
can you bring it בזמן הזה *bizman hazeh*? He wants to know
how do you define ירושלים *Yerushalayim*? But the basic point is, is
ירושלים *Yerushalayim* for מעשר *Maaser* the same conceptually as for בכור *Bechor*?
For בכור *Bechor* it's an extension of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*,
requires a בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, is limited by walls. By מעשר
*Maaser*, is it or is it not? And the answer here is,
yes, it follows the same הלכות *halachos*. So now the גמרא *Gemara*
says, where do we even get this idea of כל הרואה *kol
haroeh*? מאי קשיא ליה דקאמר יכול אמרת *Mai kashya lei dekamar yachol
amarta*? Where did we even get this idea to think that כל
הרואה *kol haroeh* is a significant status? הא דתנן *Ha detnan*, because
we do have that, because we taught in the משנה *Mishnah*, אין
בין שילה לירושלים *Ein bein Shilo liYerushalayim*, when there was the משכן
*Mishkan* was in שילה *Shilo*, the differences between שילה *Shilo* and ירושלים
*Yerushalayim* were the following in terms of the status of the surrounding
area of where you eat the קרבנות *korbanos*. אלא שבשילה אוכלין קדשים
קלים ומעשר שני בכל הרואה *Ela shebeShilo ochlin kodashim kalim uMaaser sheini
bechol haroeh*. In שילה *Shilo* you would eat קדשים קלים *kodashim kalim*
and מעשר שני *Maaser sheini* wherever you could see from the משכן
*Mishkan*. ובירושלים לפנים מן החומה *UviYerushalayim lifnim min hachoma*. In ירושלים *Yerushalayim*
it's within the walls. So you see, וכאן וכאן קדשי קדשים לפנים
מן הקלעים *Vekan vekan kodshei kodashim lifnim min hakla'im*. In both places
the קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* are only within the actual temple environs
itself. So מהו דתימא בירושלים ליתי מעשר שני בכל הרואה *Mahu deteima
biYerushalayim leisei Maaser sheini bechol haroeh*? So maybe apply what we have
by שילה *Shilo* to ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and say כל הרואה *kol haroeh*
has some significant status? קא משמע לן *Ka mashma lan* that it
doesn't, that it's only the walls even for the הלכה *halacha* of
מעשר *Maaser*. Now the interesting thing of course is that שילה *Shilo*
didn't have walls. So because it didn't have walls, כל הרואה *kol
haroeh* was the substitute for walls. And it was כל הרואה *kol
haroeh* not from שילה *Shilo* but כל הרואה *kol haroeh* from the
משכן *Mishkan*. So in a sense, what do you define as the
environs of the משכן *Mishkan* or the extended environs is כל הרואה
*kol haroeh*. Here what we're really doing is going one step further
and saying even with the wall, כל הרואה *kol haroeh* is included
in the city limits. And actually the better analogy probably would have
been the מגילה *Megillah*, where actually כל הרואה *kol haroeh* is considered
connected to the city and you read it on ט"ו *Tes-Vav* and
not on י"ד *Yud-Daled*. But again, the conceptual question is, is it
an extension of the מקדש *Mikdash* which requires מקדש *Mikdash* and walls,
or is it somehow a different definition of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*? And it
seems to conclude very much that it follows the הלכה *halacha* of
the extension of the מקדש *Mikdash*. That's looking from the walls. Presumably,
right, from anywhere in... So כל הרואה ירושלים *kol haroeh Yerushalayim* doesn't
mean that you can see ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, it means ירושלים *Yerushalayim* can
see you? Yeah, although that's discussed in the מגילה *Megillah*, but yes,
the פשט *pshat* is that you're in ירושלים *Yerushalayim* anywhere that you
can see from. Okay, is it more rural? Well, ירושלים *Yerushalayim* is
on top, it depends, right, depends on the topography. Okay, let's finish
up. אחרים אומרים יכול יהיה בכור שעבר שנתו כפסולי המוקדשין *Acherim omrim
yachol yehei Bechor she'avar shenaso kifsulei hamukdashim*. Now there's a third opinion,
maybe I would say that, I mean whatever, another opinion, maybe I
would say that בכור שעבר שנתו כפסולי המוקדשין ויפסל *Bechor she'avar shenaso
kifsulei hamukdashim veyipasel*, that maybe a בכור *Bechor*, one other thing we
want to learn from the link of מעשר *Maaser* to בכור *Bechor*,
maybe I would say that when a בכור *Bechor* is no longer
a year old, because it says by בכור *Bechor*, לפני ה' אלהיך
תאכלנו שנה בשנה *Lifnei Hashem Elokecha tochlenu shana veshana*, on a yearly
basis. And we learn that there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to bring בכור
*Bechor* within the first year. But it is not like קרבנות *korbanos*
where it says it can only be brought a year old. It's
not a definition of what makes a valid animal only within a
year. It's my personal obligation to bring it within the first year.
But it's still a כשר קרבן *kasher korban* afterwards. And that's what
this is asking. Maybe not that way. Maybe I would say if
it's more than a year old, it's not a כשר קרבן *kasher
korban*, right, like it has to do with the age of the
animal. יכול יהיה בכור שעבר שנתו כפסולי המוקדשין ויפסל *Yachol yehei Bechor
she'avar shenaso kifsulei hamukdashim veyipasel*, and maybe it would be invalid? תלמוד
לומר מעשר דגנך תירשך ויצהרך *Talmud lomar Maaser degancha tiroshcha veyitzharecha*. מקיש
בכור למעשר *Makish Bechor leMaaser*, connects בכור *Bechor* to מעשר *Maaser*. מה
מעשר אינו נפסל משנה לחברתה *Mah Maaser eino nifsal mishana lachaverta*, the
same way I can eat מעשר *Maaser* years later, right, the תורה
*Torah* even has a whole ritual of clearing out my מעשר *Maaser*
every third year, אף בכור אינו נפסל משנה לחברתה *af Bechor eino
nifsal mishana lachaverta*. So even if I've transgressed my obligation or sort
of whatever neglected my obligation to bring it within the year, it
does not become invalid. We also don't want him to be עובר
בבל תאחר *over beval te'acher*. ולרבנן דמקישי ליה לטיבותא אחרינא משנה לחברתה
מנא להו *Ulerabbanan demakishi lei letivusa achrina mishana lachaverta mana lehu*? According
to all the other rabbis above that use the פסוק *pasuk* to
teach you other things about the environs of ירושלים *Yerushalayim* and the
other types of things, where do they get this idea that it's
not פסול *pasul* the next year? נפקא להו מן לפני ה' אלהיך
תאכלנו שנה בשנה *Nafka lehu min Lifnei Hashem Elokecha tochlenu shana veshana*.
ויש אם לבכור שאינו נפסל משנה לחברתה *Veyesh em lebechor she'eino nifsal
mishana lachaverta*. So they actually the דרשה *drasha* of שנה בשנה *shana
veshana* they read it as from one year to the next year,
not make sure you do it every year, which is of course
פשט *pshat* and they also read it that way, but it's even
כשר *kasher* from one year to the next. ולאחרים לפני ה' אלהיך
תאכלנו שנה בשנה מאי דרשי ביה *Ule'acherim Lifnei Hashem Elokecha tochlenu shana
veshana mai darshi bei*? So if you already learned out that it's
not good the next year, I mean that excuse me that it
remains good the next year, what do you do with the פסוק
שנה בשנה *pasuk shana veshana*? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא יום אחד משנה זו
ויום אחד משנה אחרת *Mibayei lei lechadetanya yom echad mishana zu veyom
echad mishana acheres*, that you say you should eat בכור *Bechor* משנה
לשנה *mishana leshana*, you can eat a בכור *Bechor* שנה בשנה *shana
veshana* from one year to the next. How do you eat a
בכור *Bechor* over two years? ערב ראש השנה וראש השנה *Erev Rosh
Hashanah veRosh Hashanah*. You eat it in one year and the next.
So therefore, so that teaches you, לימד על הבכור שנאכל לשני ימים
ולילה אחד *Limed al haBechor shene'echal lishnei yamim velaila echad*, that a
בכור *Bechor* can be eaten for two days because you can toggle
the eating in two different years. ורבנן דלמדו שנה בשנה לומר שאינו
נפסל לאחר שנה *Verabbanan delamdu shana veshana lomar she'eino nifsal achar shana*,
the rabbis who learn שנה בשנה *shana veshana* to tell you it's
not פסול *pasul* at the end of a year after a year,
where do they learn it's eaten for two days? שנאכל לשני ימים
ולילה אחד מנא להו *Shene'echal lishnei yamim velaila echad mana lehu*? אמר
קרא יהיה לך כחזה *Amar kra yiheyeh lach kehazeh*. יהיה לך כחזה
התנופה, that the Torah says I'm giving the כהן Kohen a בכור
like the חזה התנופה, chazeh hatnufa, like the wave breasts of a
שלמים, Shelamim, and that's eaten for two days, so בכור is also
eaten for two days. הדרן עלך כל פסולי המוקדשין. Hadran Alach Kol
Pesulei HaMukdashin.