Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov.
So today's דף daf is דף ט' daf tes and we pick
up at the bottom of ח' עמוד ב' chet amud bet
and we are at the two dots, גופא. gufa. Okay, so we
finally worked through why I need a פסוק, pasuk, oh thank you,
why I need a פסוק pasuk to teach me that what do
you call it, that there's no יבום yibum in the case of
ערווה ervah
because basically I would have tried to have learned it out one
way or another from אחות אשה achos ishah because already יבום yibum
overrides that aspect of ערווה ervah and that's why you needed the
פסוק pasuk of עליה aleha to put the case of wife's sister
in a יבום yibum context. That was one דרשה drasha and the
other דרשה drasha was רבי'ס Rabbi's which was less clear, more was
being read into the פסוק pasuk which was from ולקח ויבמה. ve-lakach
ve-yibmah. Only she and not somebody else indicating that there are cases
of יבום yibum where it will not apply where there is some
where the מצוה mitzvah cannot be done, a case of ערווה ervah
or case of צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. And the other really important
point is that the גמרא Gemara says once you're introducing the idea
of צרת ערווה tzarat ervah you could have a reasonable assumption that
the idea of צרה tzara applies in general even not in the
case of יבום. yibum. A man dies, I can't marry one of
his wives because she's forbidden to me, she's an ערווה, ervah, maybe
the other one is also forbidden, צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. So there
had to be a very clear emphasis that צרת ערווה tzarat ervah
is only in the context of יבום yibum and the logic is
since there's no מצות יבום mitzvat yibum to the co-wife of an
ערווה ervah then she becomes forbidden on the basis of אשת אח.
eshet ach. At least that seems to be the simplest explanation. Okay
so now we pick up from the two dots to look at
רבי'ס Rabbi's דרשה drasha based on ולקח ויבמה. ve-lakach ve-yibmah. גופא. Gufa.
So it's about fifteen lines from the bottom on ח' עמוד ב'.
chet amud bet. גופא. Gufa. רבי אומר: Rabbi omer: ולקח ויבמה. ve-lakach
ve-yibmah. It could have said ולקח ve-lakach although it really couldn't but
okay. And it says ולקחה ve-lakacha and it could have said
ויבם ve-yibem and it says ויבמה ve-yibmah לאסור צרות ערוות. le-asur tzarot
ervayot. Okay to say that not only she is there a מצוה
mitzvah of יבום, yibum, not somebody else, not an ערווה ervah and
not a צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. The גמרא Gemara before said רבא
Rava said ערווה ervah we could take for granted but not also
a צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. The גמרא Gemara says מכדי צרה היכא
כתיבא? madi tzara heicha ksiva? First of all how do you get
the idea of צרה tzara into this פסוק? pasuk? Where do you
see that in the פסוק? pasuk? ועוד צרה מלצרור נפקא. ve-od tzara
mi-litzror nafka. The גמרא Gemara really doesn't want to give up the
earlier דרשה. drasha. It's so good, it's got the word לצרור litzror
in the פסוק. pasuk. It's talking about an ערווה, ervah, it's talking
about wife's sister, so that should be our פסוק. pasuk. How are
you going to get it out of this פסוק? pasuk? So the
גמרא Gemara says לצרור מפקא ליה רבי לרבי שמעון. litzror nafke Rabbi
le-Rabbi Shimon. No. לצרור Litzror רבי Rabbi needs that דרשה drasha for
לצרור litzror to tell you something else.
צרה
או לא הכא כתיבא? tzara oh not hacha ksiva? שאי היכא כתיבא.
shei heicha ksiva. And as opposed to so that's question number one
what do we do with לצרור litzror we have a different דרשה
drasha and we're going to talk about what that דרשה drasha is
in a minute. Okay? And in terms of, actually no, רש"י Rashi
doesn't we don't talk about that דרשה drasha here. רש"י Rashi just
refers to it. Let me just quickly review the רש"י Rashi one
minute. Okay
so the idea there is actually we're going to see a lot
of this in a little bit is the case of the following.
Two brothers are married to two sisters. Okay
so ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are married to רחל Rachel and
לאה. Leah. Okay ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon both die. Now לוי
Levi has a מצות יבום. mitzvat yibum. Okay now you would say
okay לוי Levi is not forbidden on either רחל Rachel or לאה,
Leah, right? Let him choose which one he wants to do יבום
yibum on. He can't do יבום yibum with both because then they'll
be wife's sister but he could do יבום yibum with one. But
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says he can't do יבום. yibum. You know
why he can't do יבום? yibum? Because since he has an obligation
to do יבום yibum to both רחל Rachel and לאה Leah therefore
that's considered זיקה, zika, right? A quasi connection
some element of the dead brother's marriage continues and the understanding of
זיקה zika is there's some remnant of the dead brother's marriage that
now continues with the live brother and when יבום yibum is done
then it's fully manifest and becomes a full marriage. That's a way
of understanding how יבום yibum work. It actualizes that potential. That's called
זיקה. zika. So he now has a זיקה zika to both of
these women. If he does יבום yibum with one if he does
יבום yibum with רחל Rachel then he is now married to אחות
לא אשתו achot lo ishto but אחות זיקוקתו. achot zikukato. The sister
of the other of לאה Leah who he has a זיקה zika
to. You sort of see that problem? So if you see זיקה
zika as a quasi קידושין kiddushin
so to do יבום yibum with one makes him fully married to
the sister of the other who he is זקוק zakuk to. Okay
and that is a problem. Okay so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon gets
that so take a look at רש"י Rashi he says the following
לרבי שמעון le-Rabbi Shimon it's right near the הגהות הב"ח hagahot ha-bach
on the left hand margin פרק ארבעה
אחים ג' אחים שנים מהם נשואים... perek arba achim gimmel achim shnayim
mehem nosuim... Who died first?
No, we'll talk about that later. הרי אלו חולצות ולא מתייבמות Harei
elu chaltzos velo misyabmos מפני ששם זקוקתה עליו מכח שני אחיו, mipnei
sheshem zekukasa alav mikayach shnei achav, אחיו. achav. וזיקה הוי כקצת קידושין.
V'zika havei k'ktzat kiddushin. Okay,
so he has a זיקה zika and that's a quasi קידושין. kiddushin.
ואם מייבם חדא מינייהו, V'im meyabbem chada minaihu, כנס אחות זקוקתו בחייה,
kanas achos zekukaso bechayeha, וזקוקתו הוי כאישתו. v'zekukaso havei ke-ishto. Okay,
so that's the problem. אבל חליצה בעי Avel chalitza ba'i and then
he has to do חליצה chalitza and if you skip about four
lines, דיליף טעמא d'yalif ta'ama לצרור. litzror. בשעה שנעשו צרות זו לזו,
Besha'ah shena'asu tzaros zu lezu, when the two different ייבום yibbum יבמות
yevamos are צרות, tzaros, are sort of competing one another, okay, כגון
הכא דנעשו
האחיות צרות זו לזו בזיקה, k'gon hacha dena'asu hachayos tzaros zu lezu
be-zika, לא יהיה לך ליקוחין אפילו באחת מהן. lo yiheye lecha likuchin
afilu be-achas mehen. You can't even do it. So he sees that
this is a biblical idea. So that's what he does with לצרור.
litzror. So רבי, Rebbi, who does not learn out the idea of
the normal case of a צרת ערווה tzaras ervah from לצרור, litzror,
but לצרור litzror is such a good word, it talks about צרה,
tzarah, what are you going to do with it? Oh, we do
it for a special case. Not a normal צרת ערווה, tzaras ervah,
we do it for a case of two separate מצוות ייבום mitzvas
yibbum from two separate brothers where the two women are somewhat צרות
tzaros to one another, are an ערווה ervah to each other. Okay,
and that creates a problem because if you actualize the marriage with
one, you create a quasi ערווה, ervah, you know, you're over because
of the other one. Okay, so that's what he does with לצרור
litzror and we'll see plenty of that a little bit later today.
Okay, that idea of אחות זקוקה. achos zekuka. So, now what does
he do with how does he read צרה tzarah into the verse
of ולקחה? v'lakcha? Where do you get an idea of צרה tzarah
from that פסוק? pasuk? Right?
So and now it says צרה היכא כתיבא, tzarah heicha ksiva, back
to the גמרא. Gemara. And where is צרה tzarah written? So that's
what he so לצרור litzror he does another דרשה. drasha. Now how
does he read צרה tzarah into the פסוק pasuk of ולקחה v'lakcha
because it says ולקחה v'lakcha and it could have said ולקח v'lakach
and instead it says ולקחה. v'lakcha. So הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, here's
how we're going to read it into the פסוק. pasuk. אי תנא
לימא קרא ולקח, Ee tena leima kra v'lakach,
מאי ולקחה? mai v'lakcha? What does ולקחה v'lakcha tell you by the
מצות ייבום? mitzvas yibbum? כל היכא דאיכא תרי ליקוחין, Kol heicha d'ika
srei likuchin, that means that in a case where there are two
marriages that could happen, meaning that there's a מצות ייבום mitzvas yibbum
and there are two wives, there's a choice, right? ולקחה V'lakcha suggests
ולקחה היא ולא אחרת, v'lakcha hi v'lo acher, right? ולקחה V'lakcha suggests
this one not that one. So if there's a choosing this one
not that one, it only can be choice if there are two.
If there are two to choose from. So already because the פסוק
pasuk specifies shall take her, implied and not the other, or you
don't have to take the other or whatever, that means that there
are two wives now, or two women to do ייבום yibbum to.
Okay, at least two. Fine. It's the case where the brother was
married to two wives. Okay, that's point number one. כל היכא דאיכא
תרי ליקוחין, Kol heicha d'ika srei likuchin, so there are two wives
now, דאי בעי נסיב האי ואי בעי נסיב האי. d'ee ba'i nasiv
hai v'ee ba'i nasiv hai. If you're in a position where you
could be לוקח lokeach this one ולקחה v'lakcha or you could be
לוקח lokeach that one ולקחה, v'lakcha, שרי, sharei, you're good, then there's
a מצות ייבום. mitzvas yibbum. ואי לא, V'ee lo, but if you
can't choose, if you can't do ליקוחין likuchin with either one, תרווייהו
אסירין, trevaihu asirin, they're both forbidden. So that's how he gets the
idea of צרה tzarah into the פסוק. pasuk. Remember we said yesterday
that there's no מצוה mitzvah of ייבום yibbum by ערווה, ervah, we
take for granted. So if we take it for granted, then the
פסוק pasuk here is coming and saying ולקחה, v'lakcha, you have to
be in the position that there are two women, when there are
two women, you can choose to take one of them. If you
cannot choose to take either one because one of them is an
ערווה, ervah, then there's no מצות ייבום mitzvas yibbum at all. Okay,
still reading the line into the פסוק, pasuk, but maybe a little
bit more understandable. Okay, and now what does ויבמה v'yibma tell me?
במקום יבום הוא דאסירא צרה שלא במקום יבום שריא צרה, B'makom yibum
hu d'asira tzarah shelo b'makom yibum sharya tzarah, like we said before.
The מצוה, mitzvah, the idea of צרה tzarah creates a problem only
in the context of ייבום. yibbum. That's where כח koach of an
ערווה ervah is an issue. In a normal case, כח koach of
an ערווה ervah is not a problem. That's what he does with
it. Fine. Now we got his דרשה. drasha. Now now what we're
going to get to today is the normal type of a thing
that the גמרא Gemara often does, which is this person learns it
from this פסוק, pasuk, this person learns it from that פסוק. pasuk.
What do you do with each other's פסוקים? psukim? So we already
told me what רבי Rebbi did with לצרור. litzror. He learned this
idea of two separate יבומים yibbumim from two separate brothers and when
they're, you know, sisters and so on, you can't do it with
either one. הזיקה, Hazika, אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. That's what he did
with the rabbis' פסוק pasuk of לצרור. litzror. Now we're going to
have to figure out what the rabbis do with רבי's Rebbi's פסוק
pasuk of ולקחה, v'lakcha, why it needed the extra ה, hei, ויבמה,
v'yibma, why it needed to specify her and not another one. And
it's going to go back and forth saying what do you do
with this פסוק? pasuk? Well, then how does he learn it out?
What does he do with that פסוק? pasuk? How does he learn
it out? And figure the whole thing out. I still remember back
way back many years when I was like teaching a שיעור shiur
about this and like the גמרא... Gemara... Because we're going to see
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to go back and forth: what do
you do with his פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, what do you do with
his פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, what do you do with his פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*? So I said, like, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s just working
out the math, and I had, like, a mathematician in the room,
and she was very offended. She said, "Math?" She said, "That's not
math, that's accounting." So
what, arithmetic? No, no, it's not even that; it's accounting.
Yes. In a normal case of ייבום yibbum *yibum*, let's say a
brother dies, two wives, no children, and two other brothers left, right?
One brother takes one of them, doesn't take both, right? Does the
other brother then have the other one, or
is it only one of them? No. בית אחד הוא בונה ואינו
בונה שני בתים *bayis echad hu boneh ve-eino boneh shenei batim*. One,
the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* ייבום yibbum. *yibum* is done with one woman
and then it's done, okay? No matter how many brothers there are,
correct, correct.
This structure of this סוגיא *sugya* is going to be like the
סוגיא *sugya* in ברכות *Berachos*
with והיה *vehayah*, exactly, exactly. So let's take a look. So we're
going to leave the world of ייבום yibbum. *yibum* for a while
to deal with פסוקים pesukim, *pesukim*, and then when you get back
to a very intense application of ייבום yibbum. *yibum*. So let's take
a look. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: ורבנן
האי ולקחה מאי עבדי ליה *ve-Rabbanan hai ve-lakacha mai avdi leh*? What
do they do with the ה hei? *hei* of ולקחה *ve-lakacha*, which
is seen here as being extra? מיבעי ליה לרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא
דאמר רבי Rebbe, יוסי ברבי חנינא ולקחה מלמד שמגרשה בגט ומחזירה *miba-ei
leh le-Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina de-amar Rabbi Yose berabbi Chanina ve-lakacha melamed
she-megarshah be-get u-machzirah*. Now, this is a very important conceptual idea. What
ולקחה *ve-lakacha* is telling you is two things. Number one is that
once ייבום *yibum* is done, it's like ליקוחין *likuchin*. It's like marriage.
What's the חידוש chiddush, *chiddush* of that? Two important חידושים *chiddushim*. Number
one is, after ייבום *yibum* is done, there can be divorce. He
can give her a גט *get*. You might have thought that this
is permanent now, there's a מצוה *mitzvah* ייבום *yibum*, maybe it's permanent.
Here's even a bigger חידוש *chiddush*: after he divorces her, if she
doesn't marry another man, he can remarry her. She does not revert
to being אחות אשתו v'achot ishto, *achos ishto*. So even though he
did the מצוה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibum* in a way that there
was closure on that, not only with the original act of—we spoke
about that the other day—you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* even, you
might have thought that once the first act of sex is done,
they can't continue to have sex, she remains אחות אשתו *achos ishto*,
but no, we don't say that. Fine. But maybe that's for the
duration of the marriage. Maybe once there's closure on that and then
there was a divorce, maybe then she reverts? No, he can go
ahead and remarry her. And that's what ולקחה *ve-lakacha* is saying, is
once the מצוה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibum* is done, we look at
this as a normal קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin*, as a normal marriage; there
can be a גט *get*, and there can even be a remarry,
okay, שמגרשה בגט ומחזירה *she-megarshah be-get u-machzirah*. So that's very important. ויבמה
*ve-yibmah*—now, what do you do with the extra ה *hei*? You should
be מייבם *meyabem* her. The extra, it could have said ויבם *ve-yibam*
apparently. על כרחה *al korchah*—that's going to be the very, whatever, you
know, sort of morally challenging discussion—but that the act of ייבום *yibum*
can be done even against her will. It's not allowed, but if
he forced himself on her, and even if she did not want
to become his wife, the act of ייבום *yibum* as opposed to
קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin*—קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin* has to be ברצונה *birtsonah*, right, the
woman has to agree to it—but here the concept is because the
זיקה *zikah* transfers, there's already a quasi-קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin* in place. And
therefore, the act of sex just actualizes the potential of what's already
there, and therefore even if there was no intention, not only if
he forced her, even if he wasn't—he didn't realize she was his
sister-in-law, right, he just thought he was sleeping with some, with some
other woman, there was no intention of ייבום *yibum*. Or the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* even has a more absurd case where he falls off
a roof and accidentally has sex with her—we'll see that, that's always
a case that everybody likes having a good laugh—what? Anyway, the point
is, nobody's intention matters. So the idea is it's not specifically about
על כרחה *al korchah*, it's even על כרחה *al korchah*, as
I said, it's
more, it's broader than that, and that intention doesn't usually work, right?
Exactly, you normally need כוונה *kavanah*, here you do not. So somehow
that's learned out from
the
extra ה *hei*. Okay, ורבי לרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא *ve-Rebbi le-Rabbi Yose
berabbi
Chanina*—so where does רבי Rebbe *Rebbi* now get these ideas from since
he learns out ולקחה ויבמה *ve-lakacha ve-yibmah* to tell me about צרה
*tzarah*? מאישה נפקא *mi-ishah nafqah*. It says ולקחה לו לאשה *ve-lakachah lo
le-ishah*, for a wife. So he says, what? Oh no, לאשה *le-ishah*
for a wife. Okay, so that says it has normal status of
wife, normal status of wife, divorce and remarry, like we said before.
Okay, now that's the idea that there can be divorce and remarry.
How about the idea of על כרחה *al korchah*? מיבמה יבא עליה
aleha. נפקא ליה *mi-yevamah yavo aleiha nafqah leh*. The brother-in-law shall come
onto her, you know, or enter into her to be more sort
of literal, so that again means somehow the way it just describes
it seems like it'll happen regardless, it's gonna happen. So somehow even
if it happens against her intention, it's going to be valid. ורבי
האי עליה מאי עביד ליה? V'Rebbi hai aleha mai avid lei? And
particularly learn from the word עליה. aleha So
that's what he does with those פסוקים, psukim that's how everybody learns
out everybody else's הלכה. halakha.
Yes, according to the way you're conceptualizing it, then חליצה chalitza is
a kind of גירושין. geirushin.
Yes, and which is why a כהן Kohen is אסור assur to
a חלוצה chalutza because it's a type of a גרושה. gerusha. Now,
although the בבלי Bavli consistently says that חלוצה chalutza is a דרבנן,
derabbanan, there's actually a lot of סוגיות sugyot and insight whatever, make
it sound like חלוצה chalutza might even have been understood by some
to be דאורייתא. de'oraita. So that is correct, חליצה chalitza is a
type of a גירושין. geirushin. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. says,
okay, so now we figured out what do the Rabbis do with
לקחה ויבמה, lekacha v'yibma, the extra ה? Now we have to say
what does Rebbi do with the פסוק pasuk of the Rabbis? Because
remember the Rabbis here, the רבנן, Rabbanan, said how do where do
you know צרת ערוה tzorat ervah from the case of אחות אשה,
achot isha, ואשה אל אחתה לא תקח לצרר, v'isha el achotah lo
tikach litzror, ערות צרה? ervat tzarah? How do you know this was
in a context of יבום? yibum? לגלות ערות צרה עליה בחייה. Legallot
ervat tzarah aleha bechayeiha. The עליה aleha. here links to the יבמה
יבוא עליה, yevamah yavo aleha, right? So that's how the Rabbis learn
out צרת ערוה. tzorat ervah. So this is the keyword עליה. aleha.
So now we're going to have to figure out what Rebbi is
going to do with the פסוק pasuk of עליה. aleha? So let's
take a look. ורבי האי עליה Aleha מאי עביד ליה? What does
Rebbi do with the פסוק pasuk of עליה? aleha So מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא, miba'ei lei lekhaditanya, like we taught in the ברייתא, baraita, לכדתנן
lekhaditnan really.
אין חייבין בית דין אלא על דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת. Ein
chayavin beit din ela al davar shezdonoh kareth v'shigagato chatat. So the
בית דין, beit din, you know there's a הלכה halakha of פר
העלם דבר של ציבור. par helam davar shel tzibbur. בית דין Beit
din rules incorrectly, everybody goes and sins, if it's רוב rov of
כלל ישראל Kelal Yisrael then בית דין beit din has to bring
a special קרבן, korban, a special bull, פר העלם דבר. par helam
davar. So what type of a sin did they rule incorrectly on
that people followed them? It's a type of a sin that אלא
על דבר שזדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת ela al davar shezdonoh kareth v'shigagato
chatat that if you did it במזיד bemezid you would be punishable
by כרת, kareth, and if a normal individual did it בשגגה beshigaga
ושגגתו v'shigagato he would bring a חטאת. chatat. Okay, so that's the
type of sin בית דין beit din is חייב chayav for. וכן
משיח, V'khen mashiach, and similarly the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, it's using
משיח mashiach because it's the פסוק pasuk in the תורה, Torah, והכהן
המשיח תחתיו מבניו, v'hakohen hamashiach tachtav mibanav, okay, who brings a special
קרבן korban when he sins and also when he rules and sins,
that's also only a type of a sin that you would be
מזיד mezid if you did it בכרת. bekareth. ולא בעבודת כוכבים, Veloh
ba'avodat kokhavim, there's also a special
קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur when the כלל ישראל Kelal Yisrael sins בשוגג
beshogeg by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So what type of sin of
עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Bet you didn't know there are different types
of sins of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Only the sin of עבודה
זרה avodah zarah אלא דבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת ושגגתו חטאת. ela
davar shechayavin al zdonoh kareth v'shigagato chatat. Only the type of sin
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah that if you did it במזיד bemezid
you'd get כרת kareth or worse, מיתה misa if there were witnesses,
and if you did it בשוגג beshogeg an individual would bring a
חטאת. chatat. When that type of a sin of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah gets done by the ציבור, tzibbur, they bring their special קרבן
עבודה זרה. korban avodah zarah. Now you're probably saying I thought all
עבודה זרה avodah zarah was חייב מיתה. chayav misa. Well, there is
a type of עבודה זרה avodah zarah that isn't a classic עבודה
avodah that is אסור assur in a לאו lav and not במיתה.
bemisa. If you take a look, רש"י Rashi says, רש"י Rashi two
lines from the top, אלא על דבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת ושגגתו
חטאת, ela al davar shechayavin al zdonoh kareth v'shigagato chatat, כגון זבוח
וקיטוח וניסוך והשתחויה. k'gon zivvuch v'kittuach v'nissukh v'hishtachava'ah. Okay, those are your
some of your like your classic עבודות, avodot, slaughtering an animal to
a pagan god, right, burning incense, doing a libation, bowing down. אבל
מחבק ומנשק, Aval mechabbek umenashek, if you do other forms that show
your love, your fidelity, but they're not actual technical עבודות, avodot, so
לא, lo, you would not be חייב chayav in מיתה misa or
כרת, kareth, you would only be עובר over on a לאו. lav.
So if the ציבור tzibbur acted incorrectly there, they would not bring
their special קרבן. korban. So the basic idea here is the world
of קרבנות korbanot is pretty much limited, there are some exceptions like
an עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, but basically the world of חטאת, chatat,
whether by case of a יחיד yachid which we're going to get
to or by a ציבור tzibbur or by בית דין beit din
or whatever, is limited to the types of sins that you get
כרת kareth for if you do it במזיד. bemezid. Now how are
we going to learn that out? עליה aleha is going to be
key, just if you're wondering, this is a sin that you get
כרת kareth for, right, all the עריות arayot end with ונכרתו, venikhretu,
okay, and the עליה aleiha, is going to link us to a
פסוק pasuk about a חטאת, chatat, about a sin offering. So that's
where we're going, that אחות אשה achot isha because of עליה aleiha
doesn't tell you something about צרת ערוה tzorat ervah that we got
elsewhere according to Rebbi, it tells you something about a קרבן חטאת.
korban chatat. Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay, so that's about like yeah, okay, but
but what we're going to learn out from it is a general
rule about חייב כרת. chayav kareth. Okay, so that's about ציבור tzibbur
and משיח מלחמה. mashiach milkhama. ותנן נמי, Vetnan nami, we also taught
a משנה, Mishnah, by an individual, כל מצוה שבתורה שחייבין על זדונה
כרת ועל שגגתה חטאת, kol mitzvah shebatorah shechayavin al zdonoh kareth v'shigagato
chatat, any sin that you would get כרת kareth for if you
did it במזיד bemezid and you'd bring a חטאת chatat if you
did it בשוגג, beshogeg, יחיד מביא כשבה ושעירה, yachid meivi kisba u'seirah,
then a private individual brings a female sheep or a goat. If
he brings a חטאת, chatas, it's a little bit circular, it's any
sin you bring a חטאת chatas for, private individual brings a חטאת.
chatas. Actually the שגגתו חטאת shigagato chatas is a little superfluous, what
it really means is, any sin that you would do if you
did it במזיד be'mayzid you'd get כרת, kares, that's a sin that
you are חייב chayav a חטאת chatas for if you do it
בשוגג. beshogeg. And therefore the individual brings a female sheep or goat.
נשיא, Nasi, it's just going to tell you the animals, but the
point is, the point is not to tell you animals, the point
is to tell you this is the type of sin that you
bring a חטאת chatas for, whether it's an individual or is a
נשיא Nasi or as a משיח Mashiach or as a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol etc. So נשיא מביא שעיר, Nasi meivi se'ir, so the
נשיא, Nasi, the special קרבן korban of a נשיא Nasi or of
a king is a male goat. משיח ובית דין מביאין פר, Mashiach
u-Beis Din meivi'in par, so the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and the
בית דין Beis Din bring a bull. ובעבודת כוכבים uv'avodat kochavim and
if it was a sin of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, יחיד נשיא
ומשיח מביאין שעירה, Yachid, Nasi, u'Mashiach meivi'in se'irah, so there's no difference
here between individuals, even a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, even a king,
all bring or normal lay individual all bring a female goat. ציבור
מביא פר ושעיר, tzibur meivi par v'se'ir, and ציבור tzibur for עבודה
זרה avodah zarah brings a both an ox and a goat, male
goat. פר לעולה ושעיר לחטאת. par l'olah v'se'ir l'chatas. Okay, so we're
not going to worry about the animals, these are basically פסוקים pesukim,
in the תורה. Torah. The חידוש, the basic point is though, all
of these קרבן חטאת, korban chatas, whether individual or communal, whether about
עבודה זרה avodah zarah or other things are only types of sins
that you get כרת kares for. And we're going to learn it
out because of
אשה אל אחותה.
ishah el achotah. Ox or a bull?
I'm sorry, what's the difference?
Male or female?
No, no, cow is female.
What's the difference between an ox and a bull? Are the same?
No, I think a bull is a castrated ox, right? I think
so.
A steer is a steer.
Okay, I don't know what the difference between an ox and a
bull is, do you know?
זכר או נקבה? zachar o nekeivah?
Right, I know, but ox and bull are two English words for
זכר. zachar.
Ox I think is, an ox can't reproduce.
Really? I thought that was a bull.
No, that's just a steer.
Okay, we're going to find out from Charlie. Okay.
חילוק בין פר לשור, chiluk bein par l'shor, right?
Oh, yeah, so what is the difference between a פר par and
a שור? shor?
Oxen are often castrated but it isn't automatic. Aha. An ox is
a bovine trained as a draft animal.
Okay, so bull is probably a more general word.
Bull is an intact male bovine.
Got it. Okay, so bull, bull. יישר כוח. yasher koach. Okay. מנלן
הני מילי? minalan hanei milei? Where do you know this from? דתנו
רבנן. d'tanu rabbanan. ונודעה החטאת אשר חטאו עליה, v'noda hachatat asher chatu
aleiha, the sin will be, they will be in, you know, it
will be known, the sin that they sinned on. So רבי אומר,
Rebbe omer, so what type of sin is it? נאמר כאן, nemar
kan, here is the word, עליה, aleiha אשר חטאו עליה, asher chatu
aleiha, ונאמר להלן עליה, v'nemar lehalan aleiha, it tells you by אחות
אשה, achot ishah, notice it's the same רבי, Rebbi because רבי Rebbi
doesn't use אחות אשה achot ishah for צרת ערוה. tzarat ervah. So
he can use the עליה aleiha by אחות אשה achot ishah to
tell you the type of sin that you bring a חטאת chatas
for. נאמר כאן עליה ונאמר להלן עליה, nemar kan aleiha v'nemar lehalan
aleiha, מה להלן דבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת, mah
lehalan davar shechayavin al zedono kares v'al shigagato chatas, the same way
by אחות אשה, achot ishah, by the עריות, arayot, it's something you
get כרת kares for. Now we don't know you bring a חטאת
chatas for, that's really the question at hand, so שגגתו חטאת shigagato
chatas is always just sort of thrown in there. But the point
being we know you get כרת kares for the עריות, arayot, okay,
and for אחות אשה. achot ishah. אף כאן, af kan, so when
it talks about bringing a חטאת, chatas, דבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת
ועל שגגתו חטאת, davar shechayavin al zedono kares v'al shigagato chatas, we
find out that a חטאת chatas is something that you get if
you do a sin that you're חייב כרת chayav kares for if
you do it בשוגג. beshogeg. So the עליה aleiha. means that אחות
אשה achot ishah serves as the basis, not for ערוה ervah and
צרת ערוה, tzarat ervah, but for what you bring a חטאת chatas
for. אשכחן ציבור, ashkechan tzibur, now that's the פסוק pasuk by ציבור,
tzibur, it says ונודעה החטאת אשר חטאו עליה. v'noda hachatat asher chatu
aleiha. Okay. משיח מנלן? Mashiach minalan? How do you know by the
case of the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? דכתיב במשיח, dichtiv b'mashiach, it
says אם הכהן המשיח יחטא לאשמת העם. im hacohen hamashiach yecheta l'ashmat
ha'am.
It's sort of the blame or the guilt of the people if
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol sins. That's פשט. peshat. But let's see
what we do halachically with the words לאשמת העם. l'ashmat ha'am. So
it says הרי משיח כציבור, harei mashiach k'tzibur,
so the גמרא Gemara understands that the word לאשמת העם l'ashmat ha'am
doesn't just mean the people have to bear this guilt if the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol sinned, but it means his sin is equivalent
to the sin of the people. The sin of the people is,
right, when all the people sin, which is the case of ציבור,
tzibur, which preceded it. What's the case of ציבור tzibur that preceded
it? In the beginning it right, of ויקרא, Vayikra, right, when it
introduces the חטאת, chatas, first it starts with sort of if the
higher people sin and then it gets down to the lay people
as it were. So it starts with ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו
ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל. v'im kol adat yisrael yishgu v'ne'elam davar mei'einei
hakahal.
So that's חטאת הציבור. chatas hatzibur. I mean for חז"ל Chazal it
means that the בית דין הגדול פסקן Beis Din Hagadol paskan and
so on, but anyway it's חטאת הציבור. chatas hatzibur. Okay, and then
that's the אשר חטאו עליה. asher chatu aleiha. So we've established that
that's כרת. kares. Then it says אשר נשיא יחטא ועשה מכל מצות
ה' אלהיו אשר לא תעשינה ואשם. asher nasi yecheta v'asah mikol mitzvot
Hashem Elokav asher lo t'aseinah v'ashem. Oh, we're going to get, wait
a minute, okay,
where's the כהן גדול? Kohen Gadol? Oh, I'm sorry, no, no, the
first one is כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. אם הכהן המשיח יחטא לאשמת
העם. im hacohen hamashiach yecheta l'ashmat ha'am. The second one is ואם
כל עדת ישראל ישגו. v'im kol adat yisrael yishgu. So by the
ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו v'im kol adat yisrael yishgu we learn
out that it's כרת. kares. The כהן גדול Kohen Gadol precedes it
and it's called equivalent to the sin. people, so for him also,
it's a similar type of a sin. It is כרת. kareis. What?
Yes!
He has to bring his own קרבן korban now in people's responsibility.
Whatever. That's so okay, the גמרא Gemara anyway is reading it in
a more technical way, it's the same type of sin the people
sin about. Okay, so I won't get into the theology of the
פסוקים, pesukim but there's anyway but okay. הרי משיח כציבור. harei Mashiach
k'tzibbur. Now יחיד yachid and נשיא, nasi, how do you know about
so again, I'm sorry that people have to turn here, we're going
to get them
to put up a whiteboard. Where's the marker? This side of the
board or this side? Doesn't matter. So you have right,
you have, okay, אם הכהן המשיח, im ha-Kohen ha-Mashiach,
אם הכהן המשיח יחטא לאשמת
העם,
im ha-Kohen ha-Mashiach yecheta le-ashmat
ha-am,
that's the first one. Then you have the case of ציבור tzibbur
which is ואם כל עדת ישראל ישגו, v'im kol adat Yisrael yishgu,
and in this one it says אשר חטאו עליה. asher chatu aleiha.
Okay. So that's where we get the עליה aleiha, כרת kareis לכל
המצוות. l'chol ha-mitzvos.
Okay, and then the next פסוקים pesukim is by the נשיא, nasi,
אשר נשיא יחטא, asher nasi yecheta,
and then by
the ונפש אחת תחטא. v'nefesh achas techeta. Okay, ונפש אחת תחטא. v'nefesh
achas techeta. So, okay we have נשיא, nasi, נפש, nefesh, עדת ישראל,
adat Yisrael, כהן המשיח. Kohen ha-Mashiach.
Okay, so this tells me כרת. kareis. אשמת העם ashmat ha-am tells
me it's equivalent to the ציבור tzibbur sin, so we get כרת
kareis by the כהן משיח. Kohen Mashiach. Where are we going to
know it from the what do you call it, from the nu,
from the
about the נשיא nasi and the יחיד? yachid? So wait a minute.
All right.
ונשיא, v'nasi, so מצות מצות. mitzvos mitzvos. יחיד ונשיא yachid v'nasi מצות
מצות. mitzvos mitzvos. By the יחיד yachid and the נשיא nasi it
says, right, אחת מכל מצות השם. achas mikol mitzvos Hashem. For אשר
נשיא יחטא ועשה
אחת מכל מצות השם.
asher nasi yecheta v'asa achas
mikol mitzvos Hashem. Okay. And by the יחיד yachid it
says ונפש אחת תחטא ועשתה אחת מכל מצות. v'nefesh achas techeta v'asata
achas mikol mitzvos. ועשתה אחת
מכל מצות.
v'asata achas
mikol mitzvos. So we got מצות mitzvos and where does it where
else does it say מצות? mitzvos? It says
מצות mitzvos
by...
ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל. v'ne'elam davar m'einei ha-kahal.
But where does it say מצות mitzvos earlier? It says ועשו אחת
מכל מצות.
v'asu achas mikol mitzvos. Thank you.
ועשו אחת מכל מצות. v'asu achas mikol mitzvos.
Okay, why do you need a third one? What? גזירה שוה gezeirah
shavah was between the middle ones.
This told me כרת, kareis, this starts out with כרת kareis because
of עליה. aleiha Okay, אשמת העם ashmat ha-am got me this, right?
And מצות mitzvos and מצות mitzvos here link to this מצות mitzvos
and get me to be able to apply it here because of
מצות. mitzvos. Okay, that links it down here. Okay, that's how we
know it starts with עליה, aleha. that's how we know everything is
חייב כרת. chayav kareis. Okay.
דלא בעבודת כוכבים אלא דבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת.
d'la ba-avodas kochavim ela davar she-chayavin al z'dono kareis v'al shigagato chatas.
Now similar by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. How do you know to
limit it that way? ציבור בעבודת כוכבים tzibbur ba-avodas kochavim יליף מעיני
מעיני. yalif m'einei m'einei. So there are so here we get to
not ויקרא Vayikra but במדבר ט"ו. Bamidbar Tes-Vav. Here are the פסוקים
pesukim in במדבר ט"ו. Bamidbar Tes-Vav. 24.
Thank you. So first we start with the ציבור. tzibbur.
So no, so first starts with 22, וכי תשגו ולא תעשו את
כל המצות האלה אשר דבר השם אל משה. v'chi tishgu v'lo sa'asu
es kol ha-mitzvos ha-eileh asher diber Hashem el Moshe.
So חז"ל Chazal say what's כל המצות? kol ha-mitzvos? What what is
equivalent to כל המצות? kol ha-mitzvos? They say it's עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. את כל אשר צוה השם אלקיכם אליכם ביד משה מן
היום אשר צוה השם
והלאה לדורותיכם.
es kol asher tzivah Hashem Elokeichem aleichem b'yad Moshe min hayom asher
tzivah Hashem va'haleilah l'doroseichem.
והיה אם מעיני העדה נעשתה לשגגה ועשו כל העדה פר בן בקר
וכו'.
v'hayah im m'einei ha-eidah
ne'esetah lishgagah v'asu kol ha-eidah par ben bakar v'chu. ונפש אחת תחטא
בשגגה והקריבה עז בת שנתה לחטאת. v'nefesh achas techeta bishgagah v'hikrivah ez
bas shnasah l'chatas. Okay, so those are the פסוקים pesukim by עבודה
זרה, avodah zarah, learned from מכל מצות. mikol mitzvos. So where do
we know it? So it says יליף מעיני מעיני. yalif m'einei m'einei.
Because here it says והיה אם מעיני העדה נעשתה לשגגה. v'hayah im
m'einei ha-eidah ne'esetah lishgagah. So by in במדבר Bamidbar in the case
of ציבור tzibbur here by עבודה זרה avodah zarah in במדבר Bamidbar
it says מעיני מעיני העדה. m'einei m'einei ha-eidah. And back here
in ויקרא Vayikra ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל.
v'ne'elam davar
m'einei ha-kahal. There we have ונעלם דבר מעיני הקהל. v'ne'elam davar m'einei
ha-kahal. Okay, so you have עיני einei here and עיני einei
here.
So this is still
the
source, right? עליה aleha gives you כרת. kareis. We get it up
to כהן משיח Kohen Mashiach because of אשמת העם. ashmat ha-am. We
get it to נשיא nasi and יחיד yachid because of מצות מצות.
mitzvos mitzvos. And we get it to ציבור tzibbur of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah because you also have מעיני m'einei here. So מעיני מעיני
m'einei m'einei gets... Okay, so that's מעיני מעיני. me'einei me'einei. יחיד, Yachid,
נשיא, Nasi, משיח. Mashiach. How do you know individuals, even individuals like
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and the king, how do you know
they also are limited to this type of a thing? ואם נפש
אחת. Ve'im nefesh achat. Okay, אחד יחיד ואחד נשיא ואחד משיח במשמע.
echad yachid ve'echad nasi ve'echad mashiach bemashma. So it says one soul.
The next case is ואם נפש אחת. v'im nefesh achat. So the
פסוק pasuk says נפש אחת nefesh achat means any individual, anybody that's
not a ציבור. tzibur. So it includes so נפש אחת nefesh achat
means whether it is a נשיא, Nasi, משיח, Mashiach, or יחיד. Yachid.
Anybody is a נפש אחת nefesh achat and the ואם v'im is
links it to the previous one. So it connects it, and if,
means it's a continuation of this דין. din. So if this is
a דאב כרת, d'av kareit, then this is a דאב כרת. d'av
kareit. Okay?
So אחד יחיד ואחד נשיא ואחד משיח במשמע. echad yachid ve'echad nasi
ve'echad mashiach bemashma. And ו vav מוסיף על עניין ראשון mosif al
inyan rishon וילמד תחתון מן העליון v'yelamed tachton min ha'elyon and the
ו vav you learn the second case of the יחיד Yachid by
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah from the higher case from the ציבור Tzibur
of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
Okay, why in the case before we have נשיא Nasi and נפש?
nefesh? Because the last one was נפש אחת תכתוב? nefesh achat tichtov?
Yeah, you probably could have done it with the ו vav there.
Is it ואם? v'im? Did I quote the פסוק pasuk correctly? I
could have. It might be a case of למד מן למד lamed
min lamed but it's a yeah you wouldn't want to do that
because then it's למד מן למד דקרקשי lamed min lamed dekarkeshi and
you don't want to do that. Okay, anyway but it is a
ו vav I think. Yeah.
Anyway that's that. Okay.
Okay, ורבנן האי סברא מנלהו? vrabbanan hai s'vara minalhu? Oh great, now
we know what רבי Rebbi did with עליה. aleha He got a
lot out of that פסוק pasuk about wife sister. Okay, now if
that עליה is telling you הלכה halacha of צרת ערווה, tzarat ervah,
where do you get all of this from? ורבנן האי סברא מנלהו,
vrabbanan hai s'vara minalhu, the rabbis who use עליה for יבום, yibum,
where do they get all this from? נפקא להו מדי מקרי ליה
רב יהושע לבריה, nafkah lehu midei mikrei lei Rav Yehoshua livrei, from
what רב יהושע Rav Yehoshua read to his son. The תורה Torah
says in the case of במדבר, Bamidbar, תורה אחת יהיה לכם לעושה
בשגגה, torah achat yihyeh lachem l'oseh bishgagah, right? That's how it speaks
about at the end of these cases of the קרבן korban of
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. And then the next פסוק pasuk, is והנפש
אשר תעשה ביד רמה את ה' הוא מגדף ונכרתה. v'hanefesh asher ta'aseh
b'yad ramah et Hashem hu megadef v'nichratah. Okay, so that's comes after
these פסוקים of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. It speaks about somebody who
is who does it with an outstretched hand, with a raised hand,
במזיד, b'meizid, is cursing God, but there's a debate in חז"ל Chazal
whether מגדף megadef there means to curse or whether מגדף megadef means
somehow is like defying God by doing עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So
some of חז"ל Chazal read that as עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, which
is how this is being read. So we see right afterwards it
speaks about doing עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and getting כרת kareit ונכרתה.
v'nichratah. הוקשה כל
התורה כולה לעבודת כוכבים. huksha kol hatorah kullah l'avodat kochavim. מה עבודת
כוכבים דבר שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת. mah avodat kochavim
davar shechayavin al zedono kareit v'al shigagato chatat. So since that פסוק
pasuk, speaks about getting כרת kareit אשר תעשה ביד רמה asher ta'aseh
b'yad ramah and the פסוק pasuk. that immediately preceded it was תורה
אחת יהיה לכם לעושה בשגגה, torah achat yihyeh lachem l'oseh bishgagah, one
הלכה halacha for anybody who does a sin בשוגג, bishogeg, everybody who
does a sin בשוגג bishogeg is the same הלכה. halacha. So it's
all similar to עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. It's all about a type
of a sin that you get כרת kareit for. אף כל דבר
שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת. af kol davar shechayavin al
zedono kareit v'al shigagato chatat.
Great, so you don't need all these links. תורה אחת Torah achat
gets you everybody, but it only gets לעושה, l'oseh, it only gets
you individuals.
So it gets you this and it gets you this and this,
but it doesn't get you right the ציבור tzibur cases, right? It
doesn't get you the ציבור tzibur here, it doesn't get you the
ציבור tzibur here. So it might get you all the individual cases,
but it doesn't get you the
two ציבור tzibur cases, because it says לעושה בשגגה. l'oseh bishgagah. Okay,
it gets you משיח, mashiach, it gets you נשיא nasi by עבודה
זרה, Avodah Zarah, by שאר מצוות, shar mitzvot, but it doesn't get
you ציבור. tzibur. Okay, אשכחן יחיד ונשיא ומשיח, ashkan yachid v'nasi u'mashiach,
we have so good that will establish an individual, a king, and
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol בין בעבודת כוכבים בין בשאר מצוות, bein
b'avodat kochavim bein b'shar mitzvot, whether עבודה זרה avodah zarah whether שאר
מצוות, shar mitzvot, תורה אחת, torah achat, it's all the same הלכה.
halacha.
But אלא ציבור בשאר מצוות מנלן? ella tzibur b'shar mitzvot minalan? Where
do you get the idea of a ציבור tzibur בשאר מצוות b'shar
mitzvot and ציבור tzibur by עבודה זרה avodah zarah also? I'm sorry,
skipped a line.
מצוות ציבור בעבודת כוכבים מנלן. mitzvot tzibur b'avodat kochavim minalan. אמר קרא
ואם נפש וילמד עליון מתחתון. amar kra v'im nefesh v'yelamed elyon mitachton.
We do the reverse. We start off by knowing this,
a יחיד yachid is only by case of כרת, kareit, and the
ואם v'im tells you that they're linked. So if they're linked, you
can learn the top from the bottom. Okay, so here we start,
we go up to the case of ציבור. tzibur. Can you figure
out how we're going to get the ציבור tzibur over here to
be עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? ואם. V'im. No, we're going to reverse
the
מעיני. me'einei. מעיני Me'einei is going to win back there. So the
flow reverses.
Okay, it starts with the יחיד yachid and then the flow reverses
back up.
Okay, so okay. ואמר קרא ואם נפש וילמד עליון מתחתון. v'amar kra
v'im nefesh v'yelamed elyon mitachton. אלא ציבור בשאר מצוות מנלן? ella tzibur
b'shar mitzvot minalan? Where do you know ציבור tzibur בשאר מצוות? b'shar
mitzvot? יליף מעיני מעיני. yalif me'einei me'einei. Okay fine. Phew. So now
we did all that. We now have everybody learns out that normal
sins that you get כרת kareit for you bring a קרבן korban
for whether יחיד yachid or ציבור. tzibur. And how what
מה עביד ליה? mai avid lei? Keeps on going until we get
to a point where we can sort of tie up all the
loose ends. So מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibei lei lechidetanya, like we taught
in the ברייתא. braisa. לפי שמצינו
שחילק הכתוב בין יחידים למרובים. lefi shematzinu shechillek hakatuv bein yechidim lemerubim.
So because I have to say something that this whole enterprise of
what do you do with this פסוק, pasuk what do you do
with that פסוק, pasuk etc., is something you only get in the
סתם stam in the בבלי. Bavli. You don't get it in any
of the Tannaitic works, right? In the ספרא, Sifra, the ספרי, Sifrei,
the מכילתא Mechilta where they דרשן darshan thing. Nobody cares about what
you do with the other person's פסוק. pasuk Okay, this is stuff
of the enterprise of the סתם stam of the בבלי. Bavli. Anyway,
okay, so מה עביד ליה? mai avid lei? What does רבי Rabbi:
do with
תורה אחת? torah achas? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא. mibei lei lechidetanya. לפי שמצינו
שחילק הכתוב בין יחידים למרובים. lefi shematzinu shechillek hakatuv bein yechidim lemerubim.
Since we find by עבודה זרה avodah zarah there's a different treatment
of an individual who does עבודה זרה avodah zarah and a ציבור
tzibbur who does עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. יחידים בסקילה. yechidim biskilah. Individuals
get stoned. ולפיכך ממונם פלט. ulefichach mamonam palat. And therefore—I don't know
what's exactly therefore, but it's seen as less severe than—than sword, which
is going to be like an עיר הנדחת. ir hanidachas. But also,
therefore and also their money is not destroyed.
You use a weird punishment.
Yeah, so it depends which way you go. So that's why the
לפיכך lefichach is funny. So let's bracket the לפיכך. lefichach. Okay, let's
just say they get סקילה skilah and their money is not destroyed.
מרובים בסייף ולפיכך ממונם אבד. merubim besayif ulefichach mamonam avad. And when
the ציבור tzibbur does it, עיר הנדחת, ir hanidachas, it's by the
sword and their money is destroyed. So we see this difference by
יחיד yachid and ציבור tzibbur by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
יכול נחלוק בקרבנותיהם? yachol nachlok bekurbanoseihem?
Maybe therefore there should be a difference when an individual does עבודה
זרה avodah zarah and a
ציבור tzibbur does—now that's not this ציבור. tzibbur. This ציבור tzibbur does
have a separate קרבן, korban,
but that's meaning because it says מעיני העדה. me'einay ha'edah. חז"ל Chazal
read it to mean that בית דין פסק. beis din pasak. What
the גמרא Gemara is asking is let's say a whole city worshipped
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. No בית דין. beis din. Everybody just worshipped
עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but they did it בשוגג. beshogeg. They actually
thought it was מותר. muttar. Okay, so in that type of a
case, if they did it במזיד bemezid it would be an עיר
הנדחת. ir hanidachas. So maybe if they do it בשוגג, beshogeg, the
same way if they do it במזיד bemezid they have a special
status, maybe if the city does it בשוגג, beshogeg, they bring a
special קרבן. korban. Okay. יכול
נחלוק בקרבנותיהם? yachol nachlok bekurbanoseihem? תלמוד לומר תורה אחת יהיה לכם. talmud
lomar torah achas yihyeh lachem. One הלכה. halachah. העושה בשגגה, ha'oseh bishgagah,
which is written in the context here of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
And then—and therefore it's all the same. It doesn't matter if it's
an individual or a city—same קרבן. korban. So that's what he does
with it. Right, exactly. מתקיף לה רבי—no, maskif lah Rebbi not this
ציבור. tzibbur. Don't confuse us.
We're not talking about this. This is דווקא בית דין. davka beis
din.
We mean any—whether you're an individual or whether you're 10,000 individuals and
you're all in the city, it's the same קרבן. korban. Same קרבן.
korban. Now, that's what an individual brings for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Okay. Now, so that's what רבי Rabbi does with
תורה אחת. torah achas. We're almost done. מתקיף לה רבי חלקיה מהגרוניא.
maskif lah Rebbi Chilkiya meHagronya. רבי חלקיה מהגרוניא Rebbi Chilkiya meHagronya asked,
טעמא דכתב רחמנא תורה אחת יהיה לכם. taama dechasav rachamana torah achas
yihyeh lachem. You say you needed the פסוק pasuk of תורה אחת
torah achas to tell you if—if a city does עבודה זרה avodah
zarah it's not a different קרבן. korban. הא לאו הכי הוה אמינא
נחלוק. ha lav hachi hava amina nachlok. If it weren't for that,
I would have said let—that we should have a separate קרבן. korban.
מאי לייתיה? mai layisye? What type of—what קרבן korban should they bring?
לייתיה פר? layisye par? Should they have brought a—not ox, but a
bull? Should they have brought a bull? ציבור בשאר מצוות הוא דמייתיה.
tzibbur bishar mitzvos hu demayisye. No, that's already something that the ציבור
tzibbur brings.
כשבה? kisbah? How about a sheep, a female sheep? יחיד בשאר מצוות
הוא דמייתיה. yachid bishar mitzvos hu demayisye. So that's a private individual.
שעיר? sa'ir? A male goat. נשיא בשאר מצוות הוא דמייתיה. nasi bishar
mitzvos hu demayisye. That's what a נשיא nasi brings. פר לעולה ושעיר
לחטאת? par le'olah vesa'ir lechatas? So maybe they should bring a—an—a bull
for an עולה olah and a שעיר sa'ir for a חטאת. chatas.
ציבור בעבודה זרה הוא דמייתיה. tzibbur be'avodah zarah hu demayisye. So that's
a—that's what a ציבור tzibbur does by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. אלא
מאי? ella mai? So what should you say? שעירה? se'irah? A female
goat. יחיד נמי היינו קרבנו. yachid nami hainu kurbano. That also works
for a יחיד yachid by—by a normal חטאת. chatas. So what's left?
Now, it's funny if you're keeping math, there are things left. Okay.
A bird. Well, but even if you forget bird. Okay. So anyway,
right. So anyway,
if you look at the תוספות, Tosafos, מאי לייתיה, mai layisye, two-three
lines before the end of that תוספות. Tosafos. וקשיא דלייתיה כבש או
איל. vekashe delayisye keves o ayil. What about a—male sheep or a
ram? Okay. Okay. Anyway,
so—and תוספות Tosafos and even if you had some other thing that
that was being used for, why didn't the גמרא Gemara at least
even suggest it? So it seems like a pretty weird question. A,
why we would assume it would have to be different than everything
else, and B, you didn't use up all the animals. But anyway,
so back to the גמרא. Gemara ואלא מאי? ve'ella mai? Oh, we
just did that. No, you still need the פסוק pasuk of תורה
אחת. Torah achat. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka da'atakh amina, חוב ציבור בהוראה,
hov tzibbur be-hora'ah, since when the ציבור tzibbur פסקנ'ס paskens and by
עבודה זרה avodah zarah and everybody follows it, right, that is that
פסוק other פרשת במדבר, parshat Bamidbar, מייתו פר לעולה ושעיר לחטאת, meisu
par l'olah v'sayir l'chatas, they bring a bull for an עולה olah
and a goat for
חטאת. chatas. אינו נמי, Inu nami, so maybe when a city sins
by עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, נייתו איפכא, neisu ipcha, maybe they would
do the reverse, a שעיר לעולה sayir l'olah and a פר לחטאת.
par l'chatas. Okay, which we don't ever, we have, well no, you
have. Okay, anyway, anyway fine. Okay. So אינמי inami or I would
say צריך ואין לו תקנה, tzarich v'ein lo takana, maybe they have
to bring something different but they can't because there's nothing left to
bring, which again so bizarre. Anyway, קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan.
So that would have been the הוה אמינא. hava amina. Okay, very
bizarre that was not the world's best question. Anyway, אמר ליה רבי
לרבי אמר ליה לוי לרבי. amar lei Rabbi l'Rabbi, amar lei Levi
l'Rabbi. Okay, we are done. So now we are done with what
everybody does with everybody else's פסוק and we're done with why I,
where I learn out צרת ערווה, tzorat ervah, why I needed a
פסוק by צרת ערווה, tzorat ervah, where I learned it out from
and that צרת ערווה tzorat ervah only applies במקום מצוה, b'makom mitzvah,
it doesn't apply שלא במקום מצוה. shelo b'makom mitzvah. Take a breath.
Now, are you done with your breath? Now, now we get back,
we get back to the משנה mishna and we ask a different
set of questions. We're done with the source of צרת ערווה tzorat
ervah that took us a good seven דף. daf. Now we're going
to ask another question. In that whole list of the משנה, mishna,
somebody is missing.
Let us remind ourselves who is listed in the משנה. mishna. Moshe,
do you want to read us the
משנה? mishna?
Okay.
The different opinions in the משנה? mishna?
No, no, there's no different opinions in the משנה. mishna.
Well, just sort of read us the משנה. mishna. ואלו חמש עשרה
נשים פוטרות את צרותיהן ואת צרות צרותיהן מן החליצה ומן היבום עד
סוף העולם,
ואלו הן: בתו,
Ve-elu hamisha asar nashim potrot et tzoroteihen v'et tzorot tzoroteihen min hachalitza
v'min hayibbum
ad sof
ha'olam, v'elu hein: bito,
בת בתו, bat bito,
בת בנו, bat bino,
right, בת אשתו, bat ishto, ובת בנה.
v'bat bina. Okay, well no.
So this is all, this is all a version of בתו. bito.
Okay, then you have oh, and בת אשתו, bat ishto, yeah,
and then you בת בנו
bat bino and בת בתו.
bat bito.
Okay, בת בתו. bat bito. So this is all a variation of
בתו, bito, either בתו bito or his various sort of
stepdaughter and granddaughter, right? Stepdaughter and
step-granddaughter and daughter and daughter and daughter and granddaughter. Okay, yep. Next
set.
Then חמותו. chamoto. Okay.
אם חמותו im chamoto ואם חמיו.
v'im chamiv. Then you have אחותו. achoto. What? אם חמיו, im chamiv,
so this is one generation up, okay? So this is that בתו,
bito, daughter, this is חמותו, chamoto, mother-in-law. Mother-in-law.
Okay,
yep. And then you have אחותו. achoto.
What? Then you have אחותו. achoto. Then you have אחותו מאמו. achoto
me'imo.
אחותו, achoto, okay? So you see it, right? Down, one generation down,
one generation
up, lateral generation,
right, sister. Yeah. Also אחותו מאמו, achoto me'imo, then
אחות אמו, achot imo, ואחות אשתו, v'achot ishto, ואשת אחיו. v'eshet achiv.
Okay, okay, so that's variation of sister although here we're going generations
up, אחות אמו, achot imo, right, and אחות אשתו, but it's variations
of
sisters.
Then
אשת
אחיו
מאמו,
eshet achiv
me'imo,
right, yep, ואשת אחיו שלא היה
בעולמו,
v'eshet achiv shelo hayah
b'olamo, right, right, וכלתו. v'kallato.
שלא היה, shelo hayah, right, and כלתו. kallato. Which is, which is
אשת בנו. eshet bino. אשת בנו. eshet bino. So that's variations of
people that he's related to through marriage. Isn't he right? Somebody who
was his relative's wife. His brother's wife, right? His well I'm sorry
his
mother's his what? Yeah, yeah, his brother, his half-brother's wife, his brother's
wife in a different variation and his son's wife. Okay, so that's
people he's related to, his relatives' wives. Okay, so these are the
four categories and the fifteen. Who's missing? Anybody notice it? There is
somebody who's obviously missing. We just mother.
Why do we go to mother-in-law? What about mother?
Why isn't his mother there? Now how could his brother be married
to his mother? Tell me how could his brother be married to
his mother?
Half-brother on the father's side, right? So whatever happened to that? They're
brothers on the father's side, they have different mothers, so his brother
could be married to his mother. Why not? So that's the question.
Okay, let's take a look. אמר ליה לוי לרבי. amar lei Levi
l'Rabbi. So לוי Levi said to רבי: מאי איריא דתני ט"ו? mai
irya d'tani teish-vav? Why is it only fifteen? ליתני ט"ז, lisni teish-zayin,
say sixteen. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבי said back to him:
כמדומה לי שאין לו מוח בקדקדו. kimduman li she'ein lo moach b'kadkado.
It seems to me you don't have a brain in your head.
This is how you encourage questions, right, by this type of response.
Okay, so what happened to no such thing as a bad question?
Anyway, it seems like a pretty reasonable question. So מאי דעתך, Mai
deitcha, what do you think? What should be mentioned? אמו, Imo, his
mother? So אנוסת אביו, Anussas aviv, who is a woman his father
raped. Now again, we pointed out and I just continue to be,
you know, bothered by this, which is why when you talk about
a case of a, you know, of sex outside of marriage does
the גמרא Gemara need to describe it in the context of אנוסה,
Anussa, rape? Why could it describe it as מפותה, Mefuta, you know,
a woman seduced by his father, meaning just consensual sex? Okay, I
don't know, but אנוסת אביו Anussas aviv is a way of saying
a woman his father had sex with who was not his, who
his father wasn't married to.
Okay, so now, why is it assuming that mother, we've already described,
right here you could have a case of, I don't know,
you could have a case of, oh, why don't we do this,
רחל ולאה. Rachel v'Leah. So you have
יעקב, Yaakov, okay, יעקב ורחל Yaakov v'Rachel you have יוסף, Yosef, and
you have
יעקב ולאה Yaakov v'Leah and you have ראובן. Reuven. Okay, so now,
okay, they're brothers, right, but they don't share, well actually it's tough
because רחל ולאה Rachel v'Leah are sisters, but ignore that רחל ולאה
Rachel v'Leah are sisters for now. Okay, so anyway, we'll have to
make this somebody else. Okay, we'll make it דבורה Devorah and Sarah
for now. Okay. Anyway, so ראובן Reuven can marry רחל, Rachel, right?
Because it's, she's not his mother. Okay, except that he can't marry
his father's wife. So it might not be his mother, but it's
his father's wife. Even if יעקב Yaakov has died, he's forbidden to
marry his father's wife. אה, Ah, but there's a way he could
marry יוסף's Yosef and he could marry רחל Rachel if
יעקב Yaakov
was never married to רחל, Rachel, right? If they were never married,
so then it's not his father's wife, it's just a woman his
father slept with. Well you can still marry her. So he can
marry her, that's אנוסת אביו, Anussas aviv, which basically means, right, not,
again, why choose אנוסה? Anussa? I don't know, but it's a woman
his father slept with but not his father's wife. Yes?
In in in the case of אנוסת אביו, Anussas aviv, yes, she
is a זונה, Zonah, right?
No, you mean, you mean as far as a כהן Kohen is
concerned? Or as far as the לאו Lav of לא יהיה קדשה?
Lo yihiyeh kedeshah?
I don't know.
As far as a כהן Kohen is concerned, not, who has consensual
sex, yes, is not, so not as far as a כהן Kohen
is concerned. That זונה Zonah is only in somebody that's לא תפיסי
קידושין, Lo tefesei kiddushin, meaning that they couldn't theoretically be married, not
that למעשה L'maaseh they weren't married. As far as the לאו Lav
of לא יהיה קדשה, Lo yihiyeh kedeshah, that's a major מחלוקת ראשונים.
Machlokes Rishonim. According to the רמב"ם Rambam that would be the לאו
Lav probably of לא יהיה קדשה. Lo yihiyeh kedeshah.
And אנוסה Anussa is also?
No, no.
So, oh, because they didn't want to have the woman being over
on the לאו Lav of לא יהיה קדשה, Lo yihiyeh kedeshah, so
they had him raping her to make it better.
Maybe. Could be, you know, I was I was thinking in a
similar way. They'd rather have one of them sinning than two of
them sinning. So
he's the one doing it, she didn't do anything wrong. Again, it's
still disturbing for me to describe it that way, but that's a
possibility.
But that's a מחלוקת. Machlokes.
Okay, so thank you. You're jumping ahead. So he says, where do
you think you're going to get
mother that is not that is not already forbidden to the brother,
that's not the father's wife? If it is a woman the father
had sex with that wasn't his wife. So let's take a look.
So מאי דעתך, Mai deitcha, אמו אנוסת אביו? Imo anussas aviv? The
case of mother who was a woman his father raped, not not
his father's wife. So אמו אנוסת אביו, Imo anussas aviv, that scenario's
פלוגתא דרבי יהודה ורבנן היא. Plugta d'Rebbe Yehuda v'Rabbanan hi. That's a
debate of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and the רבנן, Rabbanan, which Micah
remembered that according to some, according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, a
man not only cannot marry his father's wife, a man cannot even
marry a woman that her father slept with. So ראובן Reuven would
never according to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda be able to marry רחל.
Rachel. רחל Rachel would either be his father's wife, or רחל Rachel
would be a woman his father slept with anyway, אנוסת אביו, Anussas
aviv, and according to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda that scenario would never
happen.
And this is why it's a stupid question because it's a מחלוקת.
Machlokes.
Yes, because you should have figured this out, right?
Exactly. Okay. ובפלוגתא לא קמיירי, U'v'plugta lo k'mairi, so the גמרא Gemara
says, and and are we not talking about matters of debate? For
איסור מצוה Issur mitzvah ואיסור קדושה, v'Issur kedushah, we will find later
that there are other women who are not עריות, Arayos, but who
might be prohibited for the brother to marry. What would that be?
איסור מצוה Issur mitzvah is the what they refer to as forbidden
מדרבנן. Mi'derabbanan. Okay, so forbidden מדרבנן Mi'derabbanan is not interesting, that obviously
won't have implications on the תורה Torah level. But איסור קדושה Issur
kedushah is more interesting. איסור קדושה Issur kedushah would be let's say
my brother is married to a woman who's let's say a ממזרת.
Mamzeres. Okay, or also he was over on an איסור, Issur, fine.
But now I can't but the קידושין Kiddushin. still is binding. Okay,
you transgressed, but the קידושין Kiddushin is binding. By an ערוה, Ervah,
the קידושין kiddushin. isn't binding. By an איסור לאו, Issur lav, an
איסור כרת, Issur kares, there's no קידושין kiddushin even if you try
to do קידושין. An איסור לאו Issur lav you transgress, but the
קידושין is binding. So my brother is married to a woman who's
let's say a ממזרת. Mamzeres. Okay, I now have a מצוות יבום.
Mitzvas Yibum. I can't do the מצוות יבום Mitzvas Yibum because I
would be over on the איסור Issur of marrying a ממזרת, Mamzeres,
right? But
it's... and if I were to do ייבום presumably it would be
a binding קידושין. It's not like it all goes away, the potential
of a legal קידושין still exists here. Okay, but I'm not allowed
to execute it. So in that case we say you do חליצה
chalitza and you don't do ייבום. There's enough still there that you
have to do חליצה, chalitza, but because you're not allowed to execute
it you don't do ייבום. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, we'll worry
about צרות tzaros later, but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva treats איסור לאו issur lav like איסור כרת. issur kareis.
And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says you're totally exempt. And another example
of that is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the offspring of an
איסור לאו issur lav is a ממזר. mamzer. We don't rule that
way. We only rule the offspring of an איסור כרת. issur kareis.
So he's saying here's another case. According to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
we have a lot of other things we can add to this
list. Right? We can add וכל איסורי לאוין. vechol issurei lavin. And
we didn't. So you see that this list is dealing with matters
that are
contested. Okay, of course it's a little different because you could actually
say no, the list is listing those of them that are uncontested.
Okay, but anyway, that's the גמרא's question. How about those דפליגי רבי
עקיבא ורבנן? depligi Rabbi Akiva verabbanan? But so here's the question, not
why isn't it in our list, but דקתני בפרקין, dekatani bepirkin, דקתני
dekatani and it's in the משנה, Mishnah, the debate of רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva and the רבנן. rabbanan. Not that it's not in our
משנה, Mishnah, that's fine, our משנה Mishnah is the uncontested group, but
it's in a later משנה. Mishnah. So you see משניות mishnayos are
dealing with matters that are contested. So the גמרא says no, בפרקין
קאמינא. bepirkin ka’amina. That's the second פרק. perek. We mean in the
first פרק. perek. In our פרק perek it's dealing with unanimous opinions
and therefore we don't want to get into the רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda about אנוסת אביו, anusas aviv, we don't want to get into
the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva about חייבי לאוין. chayvei lavin. We're dealing
with unanimous opinions. So let's just read one more line. The גמרא
says one minute, ובית שמאי מתירין את הצרות לאחים. uVeis Shammai matirin
es hatzaros la’achim. Okay, we've been having all these דרשות drashos of
צרת ערווה, tzaras ervah, right? And the other day we were saying
it seems like everybody starts with the assumption that צרת ערווה tzaras
ervah is a problem. We're going to find out that בית שמאי
Beis Shammai has a big קולא kula or others call it a
קולא, kula, it might be a חומרא chumra because you demand ייבום.
But anyway, בית שמאי Beis Shammai says there's no category of צרת
ערווה. tzaras ervah. You still have a מצוה of ייבום או חליצה
yibbum o chalitza by צרת ערווה. tzaras ervah. So this list is
not universal because it started by
saying פוטרות צרותיהן. potros tzaroseihen. So the whole list is a בית
הלל Beis Hillel list. How can you tell me they're only dealing
with unanimous? The whole list is a בית הלל Beis Hillel list.
בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't hold of צרות. tzaros. So the גמרא
says right, so the
גמרא says ובית שמאי במקום בית הלל אינה משנה. uVeis Shammai bimkom
Beis Hillel einah mishnah. Alright, בית שמאי Beis Shammai doesn't count. So
a בית הלל Beis Hillel position is considered a unanimous. So that's
why it's such a stupid question because you should have realized that
we're only dealing with unanimous opinions and the issue of אנוסת אביו
anusas aviv is a matter of debate.
Okay, everything's automatic at the end. בית שמאי Beis Shammai is dismissed
and we end as a מחלוקת. machlokes.
So we will continue with this tomorrow. This stupid question, which is
not such a stupid question, we will continue with this tomorrow.