Okay, בוקר טוב *boker tov*. Today's דף daf *daf* is ק"י *kuf
yud* 110. We are, I think, two weeks or less away from
the end of the מסכתא *masechtah*. We pick up in the bottom
of ק"ט עמוד ב' *kuf tet amud bet*, רבן גמליאל אומר מיאנה
*Rabban Gamliel Omer Mi'enah*. So now רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* said that
this girl, you remember, this was a case where a man had
קידושי קטנה kiddushei ktanah? *kiddushei ketannah* through which was not through the
father, and then he had a ייבום *yibbum* obligation with his דרבנן
derabbanan. *derabbanan* wife's sister. So what is he supposed to do? How
does he get out of that situation? So one opinion of רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* was he tell the girl, you teach the girl
to do מיאון miun. *mi'un*. רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says if she
does מיאון miun *mi'un*, great. If not, wait till she grows up
and then she will become his real wife, his דאורייתא deoraisa. *de-oraita*
wife, and then the sister can walk away without חליצה chalitzah. *chalitzah*.
So the obvious question here is, without anything, because it's an ערווה
ervah *ervah*, right? Wife's sister. So the obvious question is, it's very
nice that now she became the wife's sister, the woman he had
a מצווה mitzvah *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibbum* with, but when the מצווה
*mitzvah* of ייבום *yibbum* began, right, that was not the case. Everybody
understand the scenario? Right? I'm just, I made this a little too
confusing because I did this vertically when I should have done this
horizontally. But anyway, right? Here you've got the guy. He's married to
קידושי קטנה kiddushei ktanah *kiddushei ketannah*, right, to רחל Rachel *Rachel*. And
then his brother dies. And now he has a מצווה *mitzvah* of
ייבום דאורייתא d'oraysa *yibbum de-oraita*, right, or זיקה zika *zikah*, whatever, to
לאה Leah *Leah*. Right? So what's he supposed to do? But sister,
right? So one approach is, well, have רחל Rachel, *Rachel* do מיאון
miun *mi'un* and then he can go ahead and do this. The
other is what רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says, is if she does
it, great. But if not, wait till she becomes an adult and
then they'll really be married and then לאה *Leah* will be an
ערווה ervah *ervah*. But the problem is, but she only became an
ערווה ervah *ervah* after the מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibbum* began, right?
The מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibbum* already began as soon as the
other guy died. And at that stage, she was not an ערווה
ervah *ervah* because he wasn't really married to
רחל Rachel, *Rachel*.
This is a rabbinic ערווה ervah. *ervah*, not a דאורייתא d'oraysa *de-oraita*.
So how can she walk away? Maybe we should say that since
at the moment that מצווה ייבום *mitzvah yibbum* began,
this was only דרבנן derabanan *derabbanan*, this מצווה *mitzvah* never goes away.
So he's not allowed to do ייבום *yibbum* now that he's married
to her, but at least he might have to do חליצה chalitza,
*chalitzah*. Why is לאה *Leah* allowed to walk away now just because
she became an ערווה ervah *ervah* now? Okay, so let's take a
look at what the גמרא gemara *gemara* says. בעי מיני רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar מרב *Ba'i minei Rabbi Elazar mi-Rav*. רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
asked רב Rav *Rav*. מה טעמא דרבן גמליאל *Ma ta'ama de-Rabban Gamliel*?
What's the reason of רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* that says that לאה
*Leah* now can walk away now that רחל *Rachel* has become an
adult? Is it משום דקסבר קידושי קטנה kiddushei ktanah מתלא תלו *mishum
de-kasavar kiddushei ketannah mitla talu*, that the קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* to רחל
*Rachel* were suspended? וכי גדלה godla, גדלי בהדה *Ve-chi gadlah gadli bahadah*?
And when רחל *Rachel* becomes an adult, then the קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin*
basically grows up with her. It's an interesting phrase. But anyway, meaning
that actually, it's not that he does a new קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*
with רחל *Rachel*. When רחל *Rachel* becomes an adult, somehow the old
קידושין kiddushin? *kiddushin* finally kicks in. Which is a fascinating idea, right?
Because until now we thought the whole thing was קידושין דרבנן kiddushin
d'rabanan, *kiddushin derabbanan*. And now actually finding, you know what, maybe not.
Maybe look, a קטנה ktanah *ketannah* is somebody who eventually, you know,
sort of like אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם *adam makneh davar
she-lo ba le-olam*. Right, a קטנה ktanah *ketannah* is somebody who eventually
will be able to be his wife דאורייתא d'oraysa? *de-oraita*. So maybe
when he does the act even when she's a קטנה ktanah *ketannah*,
it's sort of held in abeyance and finally takes effect when she
grows up. But essentially, it's not a new קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*. It's
the old one. And since it's the old one, therefore לאה *Leah*
is completely out of the
picture. Because then even
when לאה *Leah* became, even when the מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibbum*
began, to some degree, you know, at least in hindsight, רחל *Rachel*
was already his wife.
או דלמא *Od dilma*? Or do we say, משום דקסבר המקדש אחות
achos יבמה yevamah. נפטרה יבמה והלכה לה nifterah yevamah vehalchah lah. *mishum
de-kasavar ha-mekadesh achot yevamah, nifterah yevamah ve-halchah lah*? No, what happened before
with רחל *Rachel* had absolutely no דאורייתא d'oraysa *de-oraita* meaning. However, now
that רחל *Rachel* has become an adult, now he's doing a new
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* with her. And therefore, because he's doing a new
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*, לאה *Leah* walks away. So what does that mean?
That means that if you have a man has a מצווה *mitzvah*
of ייבום *yibbum* with a woman and he hasn't been doing the
מצווה *mitzvah*, he hasn't done חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*, and then he decides
to marry the woman's sister
or the woman's
mom or the woman's daughter, right? So he created the ערווה ervah
*ervah* situation after the מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibbum* began. Everybody get
that case? You understand? Right? Forget, think about another case. Brother died,
guy's got a מצווה *mitzvah* of ייבום *yibbum* with this woman. Okay,
he's not doing anything. He says I'm ignoring you and goes out
and he marries her mother or sister or her daughter, right? So
he now created an ערווה ervah. *ervah* situation,
like אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato. *achot zikukaso*, wonderful, but he went ahead
and did it anyway. Okay? So he now created an ערווה *ervah*
situation, what's the story with this woman? Can she walk away? She
says, oh good, now I'm an ערווה *ervah*, I don't need חליצה
chalitza *chalitzah*. Or do we say no, since you created that situation
afterwards, you still you still have to do חליצה. chalitzah So that's
the question. Do we say Rachel grows up, she has a מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibum here. This is only דרבנן. d'rabbanan Rachel grows
up, now he marries Rachel, now he created an ערווה situation, and
now Leah walks away. Okay? So even though the ערווה was created
later, yes?
So the זיקה zika relationship is just you're ignoring it?
You're ignoring it, right. Okay? And then what is the consequence? So
that's the other possibility. או דילמא קסבר o dilma kasavar המקדש אחות
יבמתו hamikadesh achos yevamato a man who marries the sister of the
woman he had a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum with, his sister...
נפטרה יבמה והלכה לה. Even though he created the ערווה situation after
the זיקה zika began, nevertheless, she walks away and you don't even
have to do חליצה. chalitzah, And therefore the real the situation is
that now he is marrying Rachel. It's not the old קידושין, kiddushin
it's new קידושין. kiddushin אי בעל אין ei baal in and if
we want to make a new קידושין, kiddushin well what's the קידושין?
kiddushin. קידושין kiddushin is כסף שטר וביאה. kesef shtar uviah. He's not
given her a ring, he's not writing out a שטר. shtar. So
the only thing that creates a new קידושין kiddushin now with Rachel
is that they're continuing to have sex. So אי בעל אין ei
baal in and if he has sex yes, אי לא בעל לא
ei lo baal lo and not not. Okay? So it's two questions.
One question is a יבום yibum question: can you create an ערווה
situation after the זיקה zika? began and undermine the זיקה? zika Right?
That's a יבום yibum question. The other question is a קטנה ktana
question: what do we say if קידושי קטנה? kiddushei ktana We say
when she grows up, she becomes married דאורייתא. de-Oraisa Is that the
old קידושין kiddushin. kicks in, right, and קידושי קטנה kiddushei ktana was
held in abeyance, or do we say no, it's a new קידושין
kiddushin? that you've done and it would only take effect after there's
been sex? Okay? So that's the question. Good. These are very good
core questions to be asking. So the גמרא's gemara not going to
focus on the יבום yibum question, it's going to focus on the
קטנה ktana question.
Okay. So let's take a
look.
אמר רב ששת. amar Rav Sheshes. So
רב ששת Rav Sheshes says אמינא כי ניים ושכיב רב אמרה להאי
שמעתא amina ki nayim veshachiv Rav amrah lehai shamata I said that
רב Rav must have been dozing off when he was saying this
thing. דחזינא... dechazina... רב ששת Rav Sheshes likes saying that a lot.
דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא. braisa. Maybe רב Rav had
a problem with dozing off. דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא.
braisa. I have some students like that. דתניא detanya nobody in this
room. דתניא המקדש את הקטנה detanya hamikadesh es haktanah קידושיה תלויין. kiddusheha
tluyin.
The man who does קידושין kiddushin. with a minor, the קידושין kiddushin,
is suspended. That seems pretty clear to say that once she grows
up it automatically kicks in. You don't need to do a new
קידושין. kiddushin, So מאי לאו mai lav תלויין. tluyin. What does תלויין
tluyin mean? לאו דכי גדלה גדלה בהדה? lav dechi gadlah gadlah bahadah?
Doesn't it mean that once she grows up the קידושין kiddushin, grows
up with her? It takes effect automatically. So the גמרא gemara says
ואף על גב דלא בעל veaf al gav delo baal even though
there was no sex. אמר ליה רב אבין בר רב נחמן amar
leh Rav Avin bar Rav Nachman המקדש דקטנה מטלייתא וקיימא hamikadesh dektanah
mitalyasa vekayma it says not necessarily, the matter of a קטנה ktana
מטלייתא וקיימא mitalyasa vekayma is in abeyance. אי בעל אין, ei baal
in, אי לא בעל לא. ei lo baal lo. No, he gave
רב Rav what said it's totally reasonable, maybe only once they've had
sex. דאמרה deamrah because she can say look, הוא עדיף מינאי, hu
adif minai, he is better than me, he's got a power that
I don't have, he can divorce me against my will. ואנא עדיפנא
מיניה, veana adifna mineh, but I've got a power that he doesn't
have, I can also walk away. So because of that, I don't
want... so therefore as long as I have not slept with him
again after I've grown up, I am not, you know, I'm not
necessarily ready to give up on my state... on my right to
do מיאון. miun, And it doesn't necessarily and the קידושין kiddushin is
not necessarily going to kick in. I'm not exactly clear to me
why the point here... what point the גמרא's gemara making about saying
he's got a power and she has a power. But basically all
that he is saying is that this situation is not yet resolved.
So מטלייתא mitalyasa doesn't mean it's ready to take effect when she
grows up, it means it's unresolved and it will be base... and
it will be determined based on whether they do have sex, whether
they decide to create a new קידושין. kiddushin So this is the
key question: is קידושי קטנה kiddushei katanah. held in abeyance, right, and
automatically kicks in, or do you need a new act of sex,
a new act of קידושין? kiddushin, Okay, so that's the question. וסבר
רב אי בעל אין אי לא בעל לא? vesavar Rav ei baal
in ei lo baal lo? So now the גמרא gemara doesn't have
an answer. Now it's just רב Rav has this question and the
גמרא's Gemara going to say can רב Rav really,
one minute...
oh no no, רב Rav responded. רבי אלעזר asked the question of
רב Rav and רב Rav responded you definitely need ביאה, biah, right?
Right, that's what רב Rav responded. אמר ליה, amar leh, where was
it... where was the response?
Right, right. היינו טעמא דרבן גמליאל משום דקסבר המקדש אחות יבמתו נפטרה
יבמה והלכה לה אי בעל אין אי לא בעל לא. hainu taama
deRabban Gamliel mishum dekasavar hamikadesh achos yevamato nifterah yevamah vehalchah lah ei
baal in ei lo baal lo.
I might have skipped over that line because it was exactly the
same as the previous case, sorry if I did I apologize. Anyway,
that was the question רב Rav responded to. רב אלעזר Rav Elazar
asked רב Rav what is it? Is it based on ביאה biah
or not? And רב Rav says yes, it is based on ביאה.
biah. You actually need a new act of קידושין. kiddushin And רב
ששת Rav Sheshet says no, he must have been sleeping. You don't
need a new act of קידושין, kiddushin. it kicks in immediately. And
the גמרא Gemara reaffirms: No, רב Rav actually is saying you need
a new act of קידושין, kiddushin okay? So now we have רב
אלעזר Rav Elazar asks the question, and it turns out to be
a debate of רב Rav and רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. רב Rav
says you need a new act of ביאה, biah, and רב ששת
Rav Sheshet says you do not. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: וסבר רב יבעל איני לא יבעל לא? V'savar Rav yiba'al
inee lo yiba'al lo? Does רב Rav really hold that only with
a new act of ביאה, biah, a new act of קידושין, kiddushin.
is she married? והא איתמר, V'ha itmar, we talked, קטנה שלא מיאנה
והגדילה, ktana shelo miana v'higdila,
a young girl that did not do מיאון miun and now she's
grown up. ועמדה וניסת v'amda v'nisat and she goes out and marries
another guy, okay? What's the position? Got it? She grew up and
then she accepted the קידושין kiddushin. from another guy. So רב אמר
אינה צריכה גט מהשני, Rav amar eina tzricha get meharsheni, the second
thing is meaningless, she doesn't need a גט. get. ושמואל אמר צריכה
גט מהשני, u'Shmuel amar tzricha get meharsheni, she does. So what's the
issue? She grew up with guy number one, she's an adult. A
married woman accepts קידושין kiddushin from another man, she doesn't need a
גט. get. So clearly what רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel are debating
is when she becomes an adult, is she automatically מקודשת mekudeshet to
her first husband? Like biblically מקודשת. mekudeshet. And רב Rav seems to
say she is, automatically. That seems to be that you don't need
a new act of קידושין, kiddushin. right? Everybody gets the scenario? She
grew up with husband number one, she's an adult, right? And she
accepts קידושין kiddushin from another man, which is a way of saying
is she already מקודשת mekudeshet to guy number one? And רב Rav
says yes she is, she doesn't need
a גט. get. Okay, so how could רב Rav therefore be the
one to say she needs a new act of ביאה? biah? So
top of קיח עמוד א, kuf yud chet amud aleph,
מאי לאו, mai lav, are we not talking the case דלא בעל,
d'lo ba'al, that she didn't have sex with guy number one? And
that's the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Without having sex
with guy number one now that she's an adult, is she married
to him or not? And רב Rav seems to be saying yes
she is married to him. גמרא Gemara says לא דבעל, lo d'ba'al,
no, we're talking about that she did have sex with guy number
one. So and that's why רב Rav. says that she's married to
him and she doesn't have to get a גט get from the
second guy. So גמרא Gemara says one minute, אי דבעל, ee d'ba'al,
if she had sex from guy number one, מאי טעמא דשמואל? mai
ta'ama d'Shmuel? Why could שמואל Shmuel say she's not married, right? How
could the קטנה ktana not be married? She grew up with guy
number one, they've had sex now that she's an adult, how could
they not be married? Right, good question. Everybody with me here? So
גמרא Gemara, says מאי טעמא דשמואל? mai ta'ama d'Shmuel? קסבר כל הבועל
על דעת קידושין הראשונים הוא בועל. kasavar kol habo'el al da'at kiddushin
harishonim hu bo'el. Very important not only for קטנה katanah but for
a lot of הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh issues around עגונה. aguna. שמואל
Shmuel is of the opinion that as they continue, anybody who has
sex is doing it in the framework of the original קידושין. kiddushin.
Okay, so therefore what שמואל Shmuel is saying is, since the original
קידושין kiddushin, was קידושי קטנה kiddushei katana and
right? And it was only קידושין דרבנן, kiddushin de-rabbanan. even when they
continued to have sex when she's an adult, we don't look at
this as a new act of קידושין. kiddushin, We look at this
as a continuation of the marriage that started when she was a
minor, and therefore it never is a new act of קידושין. kiddushin.
Alright, so again let me focus you all because this is like
such a core question, not just about קטנה katanah, but in general.
So again, a קטנה katanah grows up. Is she now married to
guy number one? Okay, so there's three possibilities. Possibility number one is
she's automatically married to guy number one, the original קידושין kiddushin. kicks
in automatically even without sex. That's the position of רב ששת. Rav
Sheshet. Possibility number two is she's married to guy number one if
they continue to have sex, that's a new act of קידושין. kiddushin.
That's רב. Rav. Possibility number three is even if they continue to
have sex, she's not married דאורייתא de'oraita to guy number one. One
minute, she's not married דאורייתא de'oraita to guy number one because that
sex is in the context of the קידושין kiddushin. that began earlier
and it's not seen as a new act of קידושין. kiddushin, So
of course according to that the question is, according to שמואל Shmuel
are you therefore saying that קידושי קטנה kiddushei katana she never gets
married to the guy דאורייתא? de'oraita So it would have to be,
unless they make it explicit. They would have to say: Now that
you're an adult, let's, let's go to the bedroom and make this
official, or something like that, right? They'd have to officially acknowledge that
now we are, this is a new reality, we are creating a
new קידושין, kiddushin and it's not just a continuation of the old
relationship.
But let me ask this question then. I mean, so then what
emerges from that then is according to two opinions, do not necessarily
marry even when she's a גדולה, gdola, right?
Well, no, depends if she's had sex.
Right, not necessarily. I mean she turns 12.
She turns 12 and no sex, then she's only automatically married according
to רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. Once she's had sex, she's married according
to רב. Rav Once she's had sex and it's explicitly labeled in
the context of creating a new קידושין, kiddushin she's married according to
שמואל. Shmuel.
Right, but my point was according to at least two, according to
these two opinions though, she doesn't automatically.
Like so
then why can't she do מיאון miun. then?
She could do מיאון, the question is she doesn't want to, right?
But she could, even she's a גדולה gdola though?
Yes, quite possibly. I mean, that's the question whether חז"ל Chazal instituted
מיאון when she's a גדולה. gdola. It might be that she's not
yet married דאורייתא d'oraisa but they might not have instituted מיאון. That's
a question. That's a good question. Once
she's
a גדולה... gdola...
Right. According to שמואל, Shmuel, if they don't like make something explicit
like a neon sign or something,
right, you don't need a neon sign but right, fine then.
So basically it's זנות. znus.
Not זנות, znus, it's a continuation of the old rabbinic marriage, of
the rabbinic institution of קידושי קטנה. kiddushei katana Not זנות. znus. It
wasn't זנות znus before,
but
they're still within that context of the rabbinic קידושין. kiddushin. It's not
a new דאורייתא קידושין.
d'oraisa kiddushin So a גדולה gedolah could still be operating within the
framework of this rabbinic קידושין.
kiddushin Right. Exactly. Until you make it something new. Yep, that's correct.
That so that is a three-way debate. Now, the שמואל's Shmuel position
is and the debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel outside of
קטנה ketana is extremely important because you have a case of a
classic way that רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein would deal with
issues about ממזר mamzer and עגונה agunah would be to say, well,
if we go back and look at the original marriage and we
find out that the original marriage, the עדים edim were פסול, pasul,
right, then we could say that they were never really married and
therefore the woman doesn't need a גט get and therefore the kids
she has with the next husband are not ממזרים. mamzerim. Let's פסול
pasul the original קידושין. kiddushin, Right, that's what רב משה Rav Moshe
would say. Ah, what about the fact that they continued to have
sex for twenty years? And why don't we look at every single
act of sex that they've had as a potential new מעשה קידושין?
ma'aseh kiddushin? Which רב משה Rav Moshe said, no, כל הבועל על
דעת קידושין הראשונים הוא בועל. kol ha-bo'el al da'as kiddushin ha-rishonim hu
bo'el. It was all done in the context of the original קידושין,
kiddushin, and the original קידושין kiddushin was פסול, pasul, and therefore, right,
which is a little bit different. The גמרא, Gemara it's the original
קידושין kiddushin was a קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin derabanan. So that frames the
later acts of sex. רב משה Rav Moshe is saying doesn't matter,
the original thing was never nobody would think about having the new
act of sex as a new act of קידושין. kiddushin? They were
thinking when they were having sex that it was in the context
of what they had imagined
was their already קידושין kiddushin? status. So nobody was intending for this
to be a new act and therefore they are and therefore they're
not married. And therefore you don't need a גט. get. רב יהודה
הרצל הנקין, Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin, I'm sorry, רב יוסף אליהו הנקין
Rav Yosef Eliyahu Henkin disagreed and he actually said they might not
have been intending for it to be a new act of קידושין,
kiddushin but part of what the קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah is about
is about the reality of, you know, of having sex within a
marital context even if you're not intending for it to effect a
קידושין, kiddushin that reality of being as husband and wife, not just
sleeping with another person, which could be, you know, זנות, znus, but
doing it in a marital context creates קידושין kiddushin, automatically. And therefore
he said that רב משה's Rav Moshe approach would not help for
cases of ממזרות mamzerus and עגונה. agunah. And to some degree, that
could be the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav
says the ביאה biah creates a new קידושין kiddushin. and שמואל Shmuel
says it does not. So the interesting question is what's behind רב's
Rav position? Is רב's Rav position basically saying he has כוונה kavanah
when they have sex when she's an adult, they have intent to
make this a קידושין? kiddushin, Or is רב Rav saying even without
intent, the reality of having sex now in this context automatically creates
a new קידושין? kiddushin So this is the debate of רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel by קטנה, ketana, but in theory, it could be
applied elsewhere. And the גמרא Gemara. actually now looks at it elsewhere.
So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, והא פליגי בה חדא זימנא. Ve-ha pligi bah chada
zimna. Why are they debating this by קטנה ketana who grows up,
they already debated this issue in an earlier time? דאתמר, De-isamar, it
was taught, קידש על תנאי וכנס סתם. Kidesh al tnai ve-chanas stam.
Another very important discussion around עגונה agunah issues. The קידושין kiddushin? is
done on תנאי tnai
and then they start living together, כנסה, chanasah, right, which is נישואין
nisuin סתם stam without reiterating the תנאי. tnai. If you reiterated the
תנאי, tnai, it's one thing, but you didn't reiterate the תנאי tnai
and then you started living together and having sex. רב
אמר צריכה הימנו גט. Rav amar tzrichah heimonu get. So you need
a גט get because the continued act of sex is either a
new act of קידושין kiddushin or it at least overrides the תנאי.
tnai. ושמואל אמר אינה צריכה הימנו גט. U-Shmuel amar einah tzrichah heimonu
get. No, you don't need a גט. get. The continued act of
sex is all defined by the context of the original קידושין, kiddushin
by the context of the original תנאי. tnai. Yeah, clear? So they're
saying the same thing. רב Rav says the act of sex now
overrides and creates a new reality and שמואל Shmuel says it's defined
by the earlier context. Okay. ושמואל אמר אינה צריכה הימנו גט. U-Shmuel
amar einah tzrichah heimonu get. So here שמואל Shmuel is being מקיל.
meikel. Okay. So what's the reason? רב אמר צריכה הימנו גט כיון
דנסבה אחולי אחליה לתנאיה. Rav amar tzrichah heimonu get keivan de-nasbah achulei
achleh le-snaia. Since he married her,
he waived his תנאי, tnai, his stipulation, his condition. Now that's a
little different than saying that the ביאה biah creates a new act
of קידושין. kiddushin רש"י Rashi actually here says it's a new act
of קידושין, kiddushin but it's not the פשט pshat of the גמרא.
Gemara The פשט pshat of the גמרא Gemara is that he waived
it, but the point is the reality of sleeping together now overrides
any previous sort of context. אחולי אחליה לתנאיה. Achulei achleh le-snaia. ושמואל
אמר אינה צריכה הימנו גט. U-Shmuel amar einah tzrichah heimonu get. She
does not need a גט get from him because the תנאי tnai
is still binding and כל הבועל על דעת קידושין הראשונים הוא בועל.
kol ha-bo'el al da'as kiddushin ha-rishonim hu bo'el. The continued act of
sex is defined by the earlier context. So does the act of
sex now override... override the earlier framing or is it defined by
the earlier framing? Right?
If she wants to marry a second guy?
Yeah, if they want to get divorced now. Okay. צריכא, Tzericha, no
you need to tell me in both cases. דאיתמר בהא, de'itmar beha,
if you had told me in that original in the case of
the תנאי tnai that רב Rav says that it's that it overrides
the earlier context, I would have said בהא קאמר רב, beha ka'amar
Rav, that's where רב Rav says the ביאה biah overrides the earlier
context משום דאיכא תנאי, mishum de'ika tnai, because the תנאי tnai is
explicit, וכיון דבעל אחליה לתנאיה. vekeivan debaal achlei letnaya. So therefore you
could say that when he has sex he's aware of the תנאי,
tnai, for God's sake he made the תנאי, tnai, so he means
for the sex to override the תנאי. tnai. אבל בהא, aval beha,
but in the case of a קטנה ketana where the where the
you know the the דרבנן d'rabbanan. status is not explicit, he married
this girl, there's nothing that's staring him in the face that's saying
it's obvious that a new קידושין kiddushin is needed, right? He's been
married to her for the last five years. Why would he think
he needs to do a new קידושין? kiddushin אבל בהא, aval beha,
אימא מודה ליה לשמואל, eima modeh leh leShmuel, maybe he would agree
to שמואל Shmuel that the sex doesn't create a new reality because
he's not aware that a new reality is needed. ואי אתמר בהא,
ve'itmar beha, and now say the reverse. If it had just said
in the case by the קטנה, ketana בהא קאמר שמואל, beha ka'amar
Shmuel, that's when שמואל Shmuel says it's defined by the earlier context
because he's not directly confronting the problem. אבל בהא, aval beha, in
the case of the תנאי tnai where the problem is obvious, אימא
מודה ליה לרב, eima modeh leh leRav, maybe he would agree to
רב Rav that the ביאה biah would be intentionally done to override
the existing תנאי. tnai. צריכא, tzericha, you need to tell me in
both cases. תוספות Tosafot has a has a different גרסא girsa which
basically whatever same you know which says another way that I would
have thought except that the logic could have been the reverse. Anyway
doesn't matter. Okay, I mean it does but for I moving on.
ומי אמר רב? Umi amar Rav? Did רב Rav really say כי
בעל איני לא בעל לא, ki baal ini lo baal lo, that
only if you've had sex is is the קידושין kiddushin. of the
קטנה katana, דאורייתא d'oraisa now that she's an adult? והא ההוא עובדא,
Veha hahu uvda, we had a story דבי נרש debei Narash in
a place in נרש Narash דקדשה כשהיא קטנה, dekadsha keshehi ketana, a
man married a woman when she was a קטנה katana and again
not with the father so it was only קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin derabanan
גדלה, godla, and then she became an adult. ואותבה בי כורסייא, veotiva
bei korsaia, and they had a ride in the chariot or whatever
this בי כורסייא bei korsaia was, a special chair that they would
do when they were bringing her to the חופה. chuppah. Okay, so
mean the point though being is they haven't yet had חופה, chuppah,
okay, so they haven't yet had sex, but she's an adult. You
ready? So she's an adult, גדלה, and they're getting ready to have
the חופה, chuppah, getting ready to have sex, but they haven't had
sex yet and then what happened? ואותבה בי כורסייא ואתא אחרינא, veotiva
bei korsaia ve'ata achrina, another person came וחטפה מיניה, vechatfa mineih, and
grabbed her away, took her out of the limousine, took her to
the to the top of the Empire State Building, made a very
romantic proposal and she said yes. Okay, so רב הונא ורב חננאל
תלמידי דרב הוו התם, Rav Huna veRav Chananel talmidei deRav havu hatam,
רב הונא Rav Huna and רב חננאל, Rav Chananel, the students of
רב Rav were there, ולא אצריכוה גט מבתרא, velo atzrichua get mibatra,
and she said she doesn't need a גט get from the second
guy, that wasn't effective. Go back you're married to the first guy.
Why is she married to the first guy? She only had קידושין
kiddushin as a קטנה katana and she hasn't had sex yet as
a גדולה. gedola. It sounds like רב's position through his תלמידים talmidim
is that the קידושין kiddushin automatically kicks in. You don't need sex.
So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Papa, so
רב פפא Rav Papa said no no no בנרש מינסב נסיבי והדר
מותבי אבכורסייא. beNarash minsav nesivei vehadar motvei avkorsaia. In נרש Narash first
they have the חופה chuppah and the couple has sleeps together and
then they ride in the limousine. So then they do the limo.
So therefore therefore the second קידושין kiddushin was after sex and it
still and still you need the sex in order to make it
the קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin de'oraita. So then what was the חידוש chiddush
there? I don't know to tell you that that's that they do
it the other order I don't know. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi
amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi takes the case more כפשוטו kipshuto and
says look you're right it was before sex and דאורייתא d'oraisa she
wasn't yet married to the guy number one but here's why the
קידושין kiddushin of guy number two did not work. הוא עשה שלא
כהוגן, Hu asa shelo ke'hogen, he acted improperly you know to steal
her from under the חופה chuppah as it were. אנן נמי נעביד
ליה שלא כהוגן, Anan nami na'avid leh shelo ke'hogen, so we're going
to act with him improperly לפיכך עשו בו שלא כהוגן, lefikach asu
bo shelo ke'hogen, therefore they acted with him improperly meaning they you
know they they used they they were more you know sort of
strong-armed about their tactics the rabbis, I mean it's not morally improper
but you know doing things a little
bit out of order ואפקינהו רבנן לקידושין מיניה.
ve'afkinhu rabanan lekiddushin mineih. Listen to the end of the sentence so
technically you're right the second guy's קידושין kiddushin should have kicked in
but the rabbis said you're acting completely in violation of any proper
you know moral you know ethical conduct and therefore we refuse to
recognize your קידושין. kiddushin. Even though it was דאורייתא de’oraisa the second
guy? No but it doesn't matter she accepted קידושי כסף, kiddushei kesef,
okay? Even though she took קידושין דאורייתא kiddushin de'oraita from the second
guy only קידושין דרבנן kiddushin d'rabbanan. from the first? Right but we
still do הפקעת קידושין hafka'at kiddushin with the second guy. So the
גמרא Gemara, says תינח דקדיש בכספא, teinach dekadish bechaspa, fine if he
gave her money because presumably if the second guy gave her money
they could sort of say הפקר hefker הפקר *hefker*, but קידש בביאה
מאי *kiddush bevi'ah mai*, let's say he's had sex with the second
guy? What are the רבנים *rabbanim* going to do to do הפקעת
קידושין kiddushin *hafka'as kiddushin*? It says no, even so, שויוה רבנן rabbanan
לבעילתו בעילת זנות znus *shavyuh rabbanan levilaso bevilas zenus*. The רבנים *rabbanim*
went ahead and made it בעילת זנות *beilas zenus*. They basically said
we don't recognize the second קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin*. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל
*Amar Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel*, and
now to end this סוגיא *sugya*, רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* says הלכה
halacha, כרבי אלעזר *halacha k'Rabbi Elazar*.
After all that, we rule
like רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*, which is in that case about the
sisters, we teach the קטנה *ketanah* to do מיאון *mi'un*. וכן אמר
רבי אלעזר *V'chein amar Rabbi Elazar*, הלכה halacha כרבי אלעזר *halacha k'Rabbi
Elazar*, the אמורא *Amora* says הלכה כרבי אלעזר *halacha k'Rabbi Elazar* about
teaching the קטנה *ketanah* to do מיאון *mi'un*. Now, I want to
say something about this הפקעת קידושין kiddushin *hafka'as kiddushin*. This הפקעת קידושין
*hafka'as kiddushin* is very strange because it is case-specific. Normally it's like,
oh, we looked at this, we don't like this הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as
kiddushin*. Normally הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin* is based on we've set certain
rules. In the following case, there will be הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*
and so on. That's number one which makes this הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as
kiddushin* strange. The other thing which makes this הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*
strange is that often the ראשונים *Rishonim* use the logic that the
reason הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin* works is because we assume that כל
דמקדש אדעתא דרבנן d'rabbanan מקדש *kol d'mekadesh ada'ata d'rabbanan mekadesh*, that you
want to work within the rabbinic framework, okay? But this is a
guy that clearly doesn't want to and as תוספות *Tosafot* points out,
it doesn't say כל המקדש אדעתא דרבנן d'rabbanan, מקדש *kol hamekadesh ada'ata
d'rabbanan mekadesh* in this case because he's not doing it אדעתא דרבנן
d'rabbanan. *ada'ata d'rabbanan*. He's going ahead and doing, you know, some despicable
thing. So therefore, if that's true, how does הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*
work in this case? So if you take a look at תוספות
*Tosafot*, very important תוספות *Tosafot*, לפיכך עשו לו שלא כהוגן ואפקיעינהו קידושין
מיניה *Lefichach asu lo shelo k'hogen v'afki'inhu kiddushin minei*. מספקא לרי אי
טעמא דאפקעינהו משום דכל המקדש אדעתא דרבנן d'rabbanan. מקדש *Mesapka l'Ri i
ta'ama d'afki'inhu mishum d'kol hamekadesh ada'ata d'rabbanan mekadesh* או משום דיש כח
ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה *o mishum d'yesh koach b'yad chachamim
la'akor davar min haTorah*. Maybe they can just say, remember that סוגיא
*sugya* before? We override the תורה Torah *Torah*. Okay, דלא נזכר כאן
כמו שהוזכר בכל מקום כל דמקדש אדעתא דרבנן de’rabbanan, מקדש *d'lo nizkar
kan k'mo shehuzkar b'chol makom kol d'mekadesh ada'ata d'rabbanan mekadesh*. Because it
doesn't say it like it says it elsewhere. So maybe we can
just do it because we're like the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says שלא
כהוגן *shelo k'hogen*. We're going to strongarm and override the דאורייתא d'oraisa.
*de'oraisa*. So the best answer is that it splits on the scenarios.
Most of the cases of הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin* are cases where
we have defined the rules at the outset. If somebody goes ahead
and sends a גט get. *get* to his wife and is מבטל
*mevatel* it שלא בפני השליח *shelo bifnei hashaliach*, then the קידושין *kiddushin*
will be, you know, that'll the קידושין *kiddushin* will be undermined, there
will be הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin* and so on. That's a case
where somebody is working within the rabbinic system, we've defined the parameters
from the get-go, and that's based on the principle of כל דמקדש
אדעתא דרבנן de’rabbanan. מקדש *kol d'mekadesh ada'ata d'rabbanan mekadesh*. You're working within
the system as we set it up. There are a few cases
where the person is working outside of the system, clearly violating any
rules, not wanting to do it אדעתא דרבנן de’rabbanan. *ada'ata d'rabbanan*, and
there if we want to do הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*, we're going
to have to do it in a more strongarm way. We're going
to have to do it more as שלא כהוגן *shelo k'hogen* and
use the principle of יש כח ביד חכמים לעקור דבר מן התורה
*yesh koach b'yad chachamim la'akor davar min haTorah*. So the סוגיות *sugyos*
line up well in terms of this is the only סוגיא *sugya*
that says שלא כהוגן *shelo k'hogen*, this is the only סוגיא *sugya*
that does not say כל דמקדש אדעתא דרבנן de’rabbanan. מקדש *kol d'mekadesh
ada'ata d'rabbanan mekadesh*, and the other סוגיות *sugyos* don't have a problem
with it and say it is אדעתא דרבנן de’rabbanan. *ada'ata d'rabbanan* and
a lot of it has to do with this is very case-specific
with a guy acting outside of the rules. The other thing that
should be said is still nevertheless, you know, what does it do?
The רבנים *rabbanim* can walk around and say, I don't like the
way you're treating your wife, הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*. Like what does
it, you know, what is it? They can case-by-case decide to do
הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*? So the other thing that's important to note
here is that it's a case where what he did wrong was
the very act of קידושין *kiddushin* itself. So part of the הפקעת
קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin* here is refusing to recognize the קידושין *kiddushin* from
the get-go, saying that קידושין *kiddushin* was so outrageous that we never
recognized it as valid, the actual act of קידושין *kiddushin* itself.
It would be very different if we just said, oh we don't
like the way you're treating your
wife, הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*.
Okay, so it's important to think about those things because they play
a role in contemporary issues around this. Yes? Two things. First of
all, you can't say from the get-go. Thank you, all right, okay.
רב'ס *Rav's* position in which the קידושין *kiddushin* and with the first
guy sort of overrides
the תנאי *tnai* as it were. It's the ביאה bi'ah *bi'ah*. Right,
right. Is that the same as saying that the ביאה bi'ah *bi'ah*
is like a גילוי מילתא *gilluy milta*, like that was always his
intent? No, because it was always his intent, we're not claiming that
when he made the תנאי *tnai* when he did קידושין *kiddushin* it
was his intent, but we are... but that was because...
but the we are saying the assumption there would be
that if a problem was found out before they actually had sex,
then he didn't want it to be binding, right? But once they've...
once they've moved on to the second stage, right, the assumption is
that he didn't care about that anymore. He cared about it until
now, but now that we're deciding to have sex and live together,
then I don't want the תנאי *tnai* to be binding from this
point on. Right, it's not retroactive. No, no, no, right. And that
לשון *lashon* of עד חוליה *ad chulya*, that's like it nullifies, מבטל
*mevatel*. Yeah, it's like מחילה *mechila*. It's from the word of מחילה
*mechila*, right, it's to be מוחל *mochel*, right. All right. So very
important issues here. Number one, the issue of הפקעת קידושין *hafka'as kiddushin*.
without כל המקדש אדעתא דרבנן de’rabbanan. with the framing of הוא עשה
שלא כהוגן hu asa shelo k'hogen case-specific, but from the very beginning
of the קידושין itself. And number two, the question about how does
קידושי קטנה work when she becomes an adult? Is it automatic? Is
it only after sex? And even after sex, to what degree do
we say that the sex after קידושין is framed by the קידושין
or redefined and overrides what the previous context was? There are all
these things extremely important in contemporary issues around קידושין and עגונה aguna
and so on. Let's take a look now at the what? So
can we move on? Okay. Let's look at the next משנה. mishna.
מי שהיה נשוי לשתי יתומות קטנות, mi shehaya nasui l'shtei yetomot katanot,
a person was married to two minor orphans, okay. And if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, נכריות, nochriyot, they were non-Jewish women, no I'm
kidding. They mean in this context they were not sisters, okay. Obviously,
couldn't be married to two sisters. Anyway, was married to two, you
know, so he had these two קידושי קטנה going on. ומת, u-met,
and then he died. ביאתה או חליצתה של אחת מהן פוטרת צרתה.
bi'ata o chalitzata shel achat mehen poteret tzarata. So then the brother,
if he does ביאה bi’ah or חליצה, chalitzah? he exempts the co-wife,
because it's all in the same פרשה, parsha, right? These are both
קידושי דרבנן. kiddushei d'rabbanan. Right, you got the case? He marries to
two minors, right, he's married to רחל and I don't know, דבורה,
Dvorah, okay. And then he dies. Okay, I don't know what happened
to my black marker. Okay, and then he dies. So the brother
here, שמעון, Shimon, right, he's got two מצוות יבום דרבנן, mitzvot yibum
d'rabbanan, right? Because both of these are his brother's דרבנן d'rabanan wife.
So now he's got a מצווה of יבום yibum with both of
these דרבנן. d'rabanan But they're in the same category. So once we're
within the דרבנן d'rabanan, world of where קידושי קטנה works, then then
these are on an equal footing, so it works like any other
יבום. yibum. He does יבום yibum with one or חליצה chalitzah. with
one and the other one gets off, because they're all within the
same category. Okay. וכן שתי חרשות, v'chen shtei chereshot, and two same
if they're both a deaf-mute, which is like a קטנה, they don't
they can't be in a קידושין דאורייתא, kiddushin d'oraisa, but they can
be in a קידושין דרבנן. kiddushin d'rabbanan. Now, קטנה וחרשת, katana v'chereshet,
let's say however one is a קטנה and the other is an
adult but a deaf-mute. So both of those are considered to be
קידושי דרבנן, kiddushei d'rabbanan, right? A deaf-mute is not considered to be
a person of legal standing in הלכה, but it is a קידושין
דרבנן. kiddushin d'rabanan, There we say that they're working in that they're
not, even though it's both דרבנן, d'rabanan, they're like different statuses. So
they're not seen to be on the same footing. Well, we'll see
in the גמרא, Gemara it's okay, but somehow it's like not clear
whether we רבנן rabbanan created the same type of רבנן קידושין by
a קטנה as we did by a חרשת. chereshet. And we'll see
some of that in the גמרא. So since it's not exactly clear,
maybe one of them is more, let's frame it this way, one
of them is more the עיקר ikar wife of ראובן Reuven than
the other. Maybe one of them has more standing vis-a-vis the relationship
to ראובן Reuven than the other, and you don't know which is
which. So therefore doing ביאה bi’ah. or יבום yibum with one doesn't
get the other off the hook, because you might have done יבום
yibum or חליצה chalitzah with the one who's in a lower standing,
less of the core wife. And therefore doing it with her would
not set off the one who had a stronger relationship to ראובן.
Reuven. You got it? So one of these has a here, maybe
because, you know, let's say, right, there actually this is a good
good that I have different colors, okay. So let's say the black
and the red represent different types of of הלכתי halachic relationships. And
one of them is in a stronger relationship with ראובן. Reuven. So
similarly to שמעון, Shimon, right, the זיקה zika transfers. So he's got
a he's got one type of a relationship with רחל, one type
of a זיקה zika with רחל, and a different type of a
זיקה zika. with with לאה or whatever, with דבורה, Dvorah, right? And
you don't know which is the stronger זיקה. zikah. So if you
act on one, it doesn't necessarily get out the other one because
you don't know which is the stronger one. What? Even even with
that. What? Even right because then it would be אחות אשתו, achot
ishto, uh, it then it would be right what I wanted, right,
because one of them would be אסור assur too, right, one of
them would be the stronger and the right, exactly. What? In this
case the deaf-mute she's an adult, right. So I should draw I
should draw some figure. Okay. Right, okay, here. Okay. What was the
reason why she doesn't have this status? Just a דרבנן. derabbanan Just
they're not allowed to in דאורייתא d'oraisa they're not allowed, not allowed
to, but she's not considered a a legal like she doesn't have
legal standing in in the legal system. So therefore she can't enter
into a דאורייתא קידושין. d'oraisa kiddushin Okay. So so that's what it
says. אין ביאת אחת מהן פוטרת צרתה. ein bi'at achat mehen poteret
tzarata. פיקחת וחרשת, pikachas v'chereshet, now let's say one is an adult
with you know who's not a deaf-mute and the other's a deaf-mute
adult. So one is דאורייתא d'oraisa, and one is דרבנן. derabbanan, So
ביאת הפיקחת פוטרת החרשת. bi'at ha'pikachas poteres ha'chereshet. So if you act
on the יבום yibum with the... with the adult who is not
a deaf-mute the דאורייתא d'oraisa *De'oraita*, that obviously gets the חירשת *Chereshet*
off the hook. And similarly, חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza* with the adult would
get the חירשת *Chereshet* off or the פיקח pikeach *Pikeach*, the non-חירשת
*Chereshet* would get the חירשת *Chereshet* off the hook. Where were they?
ביאת פיקח pike'ach פוטרת החירשת ואין ביאת החירשת פוטרת את הפיקח *Biat
pikach poteret hachereshet ve'ein biat hachereshet poteret et hapikach*. Okay, גדולה וקטנה
*Gedola uktana*, similarly an adult and a minor. So the adult is
דאורייתא de'oraita. *De'oraita*, the minor is דרבנן derabbanan *De'rabbanan*. So ביאת הגדולה
פוטרת הקטנה ואין ביאת הקטנה פוטרת הגדולה *Biat hagedola poteret haktana ve'ein
biat haktana poteret hagedola*. The sex or חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza* with the
adult gets the minor off the hook because that's only its a
that's only a דרבנן derabbanan. *De'rabbanan*. But the ביאה bi’ah *Bia* or
the חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza* with the minor doesn't get the adult off
the hook because because the what you do at the דרבנן derabbanan
*De'rabbanan* level can't impact the דאורייתא de'oraita. *De'oraita* זיקה zika *Zika* with
the adult. Okay, is that clear everybody? Yeah. So if they're the
same standing, one exempts the other. If they're clearly different standings, one's
a דאורייתא de'oraita *De'oraita* and the other's a דרבנן derabbanan *De'rabbanan*, then
acting on the דאורייתא de'oraita *De'oraita* clearly releases the other. If they're
both דרבנן derabbanan. *De'rabbanan* but questionable who has a stronger standing, that's
when you gotta act on both of them. That's when you're never
going to get one to exempt the other. Okay, so now the
גמרא *Gemara* says like this. וחירשת בת חליצה chalitzah היא *Vechereshet bat
chalitza hi*? How could it say, right, that if they're both at
the same standing, they're both קטנות *Ktanot*, you do ביאה biah *Bia*
or חליצה chalitza *Chalitza* with one of them? That's fine. But and
then it says if they're both חרשות *Chereshot*, you do ביאה biah
*Bia* or חליצה chalitza, *Chalitza* with one of them. How can you
do חליצה chalitza. *Chalitza* with a חירשת *Chereshet*? Now you could say
how could you do חליצה chalitza *Chalitza* with a קטנה *Ktana*, right?
Remember the discussion before, could a קטנה *Ktana* do חליצה chalitza *Chalitza*?
So there's two answers. Number one is there is an opinion that
a קטנה *Ktana* can do חליצה chalitza. *Chalitza*. And number two is
fine, wait till she becomes an adult. But at least חליצה chalitza.
*Chalitza* is worth discussing. Whereas by a חירשת *Chereshet*, the גמרא *Gemara*
is going to say you can never do חליצה chalitza. *Chalitza*. So
how could the משנה Mishna *Mishnah* suggest in the case of two
חרשות *Chereshot*, do ביאה biah *Bia* or חליצה chalitza. *Chalitza* with one
of them? וחירשת בת חליצה chalitza היא *Vechereshet bat chalitza hi*? ותנן
*Vetenan*, we taught in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. חירש נחלץ *Cheresh nechalatz*?
Wait, if the קידושין *Kiddushin* is non-בת חליצה chalitzah *Bat chalitza* דרבנן
derabbanan. *De'rabbanan*. Ah, so that's the question. דרבנן derabbanan. *De'rabbanan* is if
the whole קידושין *Kiddushin* is דרבנן derabbanan *De'rabbanan*, maybe the חליצה chalitzah.
*Chalitza* could also be דרבנן derabbanan *De'rabbanan*. Excellent, let's see what the
גמרא *Gemara* says. חירש נחלץ *Cheresh nechalatz*, if the חירש *Cheresh* was
the one, the brother-in-law, and he was the subject of חליצה chalitzah
*Chalitza*, או חירשת שחלצה *O chereshet shechaletza*, or the חירשת *Chereshet* did
חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza*, וחולצת מן הקטן *Vecholtzet min haktan*, or the guy
was a minor, the man, חליצתה פסולה *Chalitzata pesula*, it's invalid. If
the woman was a minor, we know it's a debate. So here
you see that the חירשת *Chereshet* cannot do חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza*. So
how could the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* suggest that? אמר רב גידל אמר
רב *Amar Rav Gidel amar Rav*, so ביאה *Bia*, you're right. When
the משנה Mishna. *Mishnah* says, speaks about two קטנות *Ktanot*, and then
it says and the same would be true about two חרשות *Chereshot*,
it meant the ביאה *Bia* case would be the same by two
חרשות *Chereshot*. But you're right, חליצה chalitzah *Chalitza* wouldn't work by the
חירש *Cheresh* case. Okay, רבא אמר *Rava amar*, now רבא *Rava* says
what Michael says. What do you mean ביאה *Bia*? What? The משנה
Mishna *Mishnah* said if you have two קטנות *Ktanot*, then you do
ביאה *Bia* or חליצה chalitzah. *Chalitza* with one of them. יבום yibum,
*Yibum*, יבום yibum *Yibum*. רבא אמר אפילו תימא אחליצה *Rava amar afilu
teima achalitza*. No, you could talk about חליצה chalitza *Chalitza* by a
חירשת *Chereshet*. How could you talk about it? So רבא *Rava* says
what Michael says. כאן בחירשת מעיקרא כאן דפיקח ואחר כך נשתרשה *Kan
bechereshet me'ikara, kan depikeach ve'achar kach nishtaresha*. When we said a חירשת
*Chereshet* can't do חליצה chalitza. *Chalitza*, right, the question is what was
the nature of her marriage to the dead guy? If she married
ראובן Reuven. *Reuven* when she was well, and then she became a
חירשת *Chereshet*, so she had a דאורייתא de'oraita *De'oraita* marriage to ראובן
*Reuven*. Now there's a דאורייתא *De'oraita* need for חליצה chalitza *Chalitza*. There's
a דאורייתא *De'oraita* need for חליצה chalitza, *Chalitza*, a חירשת *Chereshet* can't
do חליצה chalitza *Chalitza*. You're stuck, I'm sorry. If however she married
ראובן *Reuven* when she was a חירשת *Chereshet*, her whole her whole
relationship is in the דרבנן derabbanan, *De'rabbanan* world. So if דרבנן derabbanan,
*De'rabbanan* she was married to ראובן *Reuven* and she only has a
דרבנן derabbanan. *De'rabbanan* requirement of חליצה *Chalitza*, we'll let her do חליצה
*Chalitza*. The same way we let her get married to ראובן *Reuven*,
even though she was a חירשת *Chereshet*, we'll let her do חליצה
*Chalitza* with שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, even though she's a חירשת *Chereshet*. Very
reasonable position, right Michael? So what? I hope they say that. Okay,
so כאן בחירשת מעיקרא *Kan bechereshet me'ikara*, was she always a חירשת
*Chereshet*, or כאן דפיקח ואחר כך נשתרשה *Kan depikeach ve'achar kach nishtaresha*,
or did she marry ראובן *Reuven* when she was okay well and
then became a חירשת *Chereshet*? חירשת מעיקרא *Chereshet me'ikara*, if she was
always a חירשת *Chereshet* even when she married ראובן *Reuven*, כי היכי
דעל *Ki heichi de'al*, the same way she entered into the marriage
and that was only rabbinic, הכי נפיק *Hachi nefik*, she'll leave, she'll
leave not the marriage but she'll leave, you know, her relationship with
שמעון *Shimon* by doing a חליצה *Chalitza* even though it's only a
דרבנן derabbanan, *De'rabbanan* חליצה *Chalitza*. פיקח pike'ach ואחר כך נשתרשה *Pikeach ve'achar
kach nishtaresha*, if however she was well when she married ראובן *Reuven*
and it was a דאורייתא *De'oraita* marriage, and now she's a חירשת
*Chereshet*, now you have a דאורייתא *De'oraita* need for חליצה *Chalitza*. לא
דמעכבא בה קריאה *Lo dema'akva ba kria*, and because she cannot do
the reciting of the verses. Remember, that's why the גמרא *Gemara* said
that a חירשת *Chereshet* interestingly cannot do חליצה *Chalitza*, it didn't focus
on her not being a בר דעת bar da’as, *Bar da'at*, it
focused on her inability to recite the verses which is fascinating and
we mentioned that at the time. Okay, so that's the same thing,
it's an indication that she's not. No, because you have the case
of an אילם *Ilen*. You have a case of somebody who's not
deaf but is a mute. You know, so anyway I don't want
to get into. But it’s interesting that the גמרא focuses on that
and it could have said the more fundamental reason that she’s not
a בר דעת, bar da’as. and the fact that it’s not suggests
that maybe the גמרא is not so certain that she’s not fully
a בר דעת. bar da’as Okay, but anyway, I mentioned that last
time we did this. I don’t want to go into it now.
איתיבי אביי, Eiseivei Abaye, so אביי Abaye asked. So that’s the argument.
Can a חרשת chereshet do חליצה if her original marriage was as
a חרשת? chereshet? Okay, it’s a very reasonable position, right? But is
it true? איתיבי אביי, Eiseivei Abaye, so אביי Abaye asked, וחרשת מעיקרא
בת חליצה? ve’chereshet me’ikara bas chalitzah? Can a somebody who was always
a חרשת chereshet do חליצה, even if she was even if the
marriage was as a חרשת? chereshet? התנן. Ha’tnan. Now I want to
tell you the remainder of this דף daf today as of much
of it we’ll get through is basically an analysis of the huge
משנה mishna we’re about to come up to when we begin the
next פרק. perek. So just to show you what’s there, we’re Thursday,
so Friday, שבת, Shabbos, what שבת Shabbos’s דף daf is going to
look like, we start the next פרק, perek, this is the size
of the משנה mishnah in the פרק. perek. That’s חרש. Cheresh. What
we’re going to do today is quote pretty much every single section
of this משנה. mishna So what we’re doing today is giving you
a head start on the דף we’re going to do on שבת.
Shabbos. So let’s take a look. So אביי Abaye said is this
really true that a חרשת chereshet who was married as a חרשת
chereshet can do חליצה? התנן, Ha’tnan, we taught in the משנה. mishna,
שני אחים, Shnei achim, two brothers. אחד פקח ואחד חרש. echad pike’ach
ve’echad cheresh. One is hearing and the other’s a חרש. cheresh. I’ve
gotta come up with another word other than well. Hearing. Thank you.
Alright. One is hearing and the other is a חרש. cheresh. נשואין
לשתי נכריות. nesuin lish’tei nochriyos. They’re married to two unrelated women. אחת
פקחת ואחת חרשת. achas pikachas ve’achas chereshet. One hearing and one חרשת,
chereshet, and it’s a match. מת חרש בעל חרשת. meis cheresh ba’al
chereshet. So the חרש, cheresh, the husband of the חרשת chereshet died.
מה יעשה פקח בעל פקחת? mah ya’aseh pike’ach ba’al pikachas? What should
the פקח pike’ach do? Meaning, so now his brother died, he has
a מצות יבום. mitzvas yibum. His מצות יבום mitzvas yibum though is
with this woman who is a דרבנן, derabbanan, right, married to his
brother, whatever, they were both deaf, it’s a דרבנן. derabbanan! So he
has a דרבנן מצות יבום. de’rabbanan mitzvas yibum. What can he do?
What’s the big deal? What can he do? Right? So what can
he do? So it says מה יעשה, mah ya’aseh, כונס, koneis, he
does יבום, yibum, ואם רצה להוציא יוציא, ve’im ratzah lehotzi yotzi, and
if he doesn’t want to and they don’t want to stay married,
give her a גט. get. But what is he not doing here?
What’s the other option that he’s not doing? חליצה. Why not? Why
not? Because she’s a חרשת. chereshet. Okay, so so basically, no, once
he does דרבנן. But basically what it’s saying is what this משנה
mishna is telling you is חליצה is not an option. If you
don’t want to stay married to this woman or you don’t want
to marry her, you can’t do חליצה now, she’s a חרשת. chereshet.
What you have to do is do ביאה and then give her
a גט. get? Okay, so this is basically making a very strong
statement that חליצה is not on the table. Okay, and the and
אביי Abaye’s point is going to be it sounds like she was
always a חרשת. chereshet. Right? It sounds like a חרש cheresh married
a חרשת, chereshet, sounds like they were always that. Okay. It’s such
a minor difference though between a חליצה דרבנן chalitzah de’rabbanan and a
גט דרבנן. get de’rabbanan. It’s a minor difference? He’s going to have
to have sex with her and then give her a גט? get
That’s not a big deal? Oh, wait a second. He has to
have sex? Yes. Have to have ביאה. Because you can’t give a
גט get to a גט get doesn’t release a woman from a
יבום yibum, obligation. Only חליצה releases a woman. You have to act
on the יבום, yibum, no, you have to act on the יבום,
yibum make her make her his wife, and then give a גט
get. as a wife, not as a as a יבמה. So you
can’t say that יוציא yotzi in this context means יחלוץ. yachlotz. No,
it doesn’t. ואם רצה להוציא ve’im ratzah lehotzi after he’s כונס. koneis.
First step is כונס, koneis, second step is אם רצה להוציא. im
ratzah lehotzi. Exactly, that’s what it is. מת פקח בעל פקחת. meis
pike’ach ba’al pikachas. We had the מאמר ma’amar case before. He had
to give a גט. get Did he have to sleep also first
with that? No, in a normal case he gives he gives a
גט get. to undo the מאמר ma’amar and then he still has
to do חליצה to undo the זיקה. zika Correct. Now, מת פקח
בעל פקחת. meis pike’ach ba’al pikachas. Now, in the reverse case, that
the hearing person died, so now the חרש cheresh has a מצות
יבום דאורייתא, mitzvas yibum de’oraisa, right, with his sister-in-law? This is his
brother? No, he’s דרבנן. Sorry. But the חרש cheresh himself is only
דרבנן. What does it matter? He’s got a מצות יבום דאורייתא. mitzvas
yibum de’oraisa. So let’s see what he’s supposed to do. What do
you mean? Who cares what his marriage is to his other wife?
He can have sex. So let’s take a look. מת פקח בעל
פקחת מה יעשה חרש בעל חרשת. meis pike’ach ba’al pikachas mah ya’aseh
cheresh ba’al chereshet. כונס, koneis, he can have ביאה and do the
מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum and that will be binding, I mean
even even a קטן katan does יבום yibum it’s binding and so
on, it’s an act of sex. Okay? ואינו מוציא לעולם. ve’eino motzi
le’olam. But because he’s a חרש, cheresh, he can never give his
wife a גט. get. Okay. And as opposed to his wife who’s
a חרשת. chereshet. His wife who’s a חרשת chereshet he can give
her a גט. get. Why? Because he’s only married to her דרבנן.
But this wife, because it came through יבום yibum, and through his
act of sex, that creates a קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin de’oraisa. Which is
interesting, you would think a חרש cheresh who’s not a בר דעת
bar daas, could never have a קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin de’oraisa. No. His
act of קידושין is not cannot be binding, so what he does
with if he marries a סתם stam woman, חרשת chereshet or not,
he’s not married to her דאורייתא and therefore he can divorce her.
But if he marries his sister-in-law... law creates a קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin
d'oraisa. Now he can never divorce her. Wait, so he is a,
he is not a בר דעת, bar daas so he can never
give a גט. get Right, but but his ביאה can be binding
דאורייתא. Yeah, you don't need, you don't need to be a בר
דעת bar da'as to have sex, okay? Go talk about the whole
ביאה with DJ. I know what stage it's on. Okay, fine. But,
no, but there's something, of course he can have sex. And it's
binding דאורייתא because it's because it's... No, no, יבום yibum, works even
שלא מדעת, shelo m'daas, even בעל כרחו, baal korcho, right? The act,
the act of sex effectuates the, the זיקה zika that, you know,
that the old and it automatically makes it a real thing. But
you could make up more, so so every act of זנות then
should be binding as... No, in a context of, we're not saying
ביאה creates קידושין. We're saying that when there's a זיקה and there's
a transfer of the דאורייתא קידושין relationship that the brother had with
his wife and is now transferred in a potential state... No, it's
a דאורייתא קידושין with the woman and it's now transferred in its
potential state of זיקה to the brother חרש, cheresh, and that potential
is actualized when sex takes place without דעת, daas, without דעת. daas.
But you can still make the argument... I don't, enough. Moving on.
I, yes, you can make a lot of arguments. That's the point
here. Moving on. Okay. So, and so we're going to have a
lot of fun on שבת Shabbos because these are the issues. All
right. Now, okay, מאי לאו mai lav בחרשת מעיקרא? b'cheresha mei'ikara? Are
we not talking about a case that this woman was always a
חרשת? cheresha? And therefore her marriage to the brother, the חרש, cheresh,
was a דרבנן marriage, and nevertheless we are saying the חליצה is
not on the table. If the חרש cheresh dies, she cannot do
חליצה, even though her marriage was only a דרבנן marriage. וקתני כונס
ואין חולץ לה, v'ka-tani kones v'ein choletz lah, and only have the
option in the first part of this about sex. We do not
have, about יבום, yibum, we do not have the option of חליצה.
So you see that even though her marriage to שמעון the חרש
cheresh who was a חרש cheresh was only דרבנן, she cannot do
חליצה with ראובן. So, לא בפיקח ונסתחרש הוא דאמר. lo, b'pikaiach v'nistacharesh
hu d'amar. Maybe we're talking about that she originally had to be
both of them, both she and her husband originally were hearing, they
had a קידושין marriage דאורייתא, and then they became a חרש. cheresh.
And therefore both of them, and therefore now, because it's a קידושין
דאורייתא, kiddushin d'oraisa, now she's not able to go ahead and do
חליצה with the brother. But if originally it was only a קידושין
דרבנן, kiddushin d'rabanan, she was a חרשת cheresha originally, she could do
חליצה. Okay, so that's how we're going to get out of it.
Basically, we're going to go through that whole big משנה mishna in
the next פרק perek and do this answer every time. The next
פרק perek makes it clear that a חרשת cheresha cannot do חליצה.
It sounds like we're dealing with cases where the woman was a
חרשת cheresha from the get-go and that she therefore her original marriage
to the original husband, her marriage to the original husband was only
דרבנן, and nevertheless she cannot do חליצה. And the answer always is
going to be is: no, she it was originally she was originally
hearing and it was her marriage דאורייתא and now she became a
חרשת cheresha and that's why she can't do חליצה. And if she
learned to read, she can read? I don't know, that's just what
I was going to add. In other words, then we're assuming here
that this woman can't read. Because if they could read, then would
there be a different approach to this whole? You mean in terms
of thinking about them as בני דעה? bnei deia? Yes, that has
to do with the history of הלכה and how the category of
חרשת cheresha developed over time, particularly when, you know, schools for the
deaf were developed and people and it was very clear that they
were בני דעה. bnei deia. So, yeah, that's a separate... But the
גט get, usually does say בפיקח ונסתחרש? b'pikaiach v'nistacharesh? Right, I know.
So that's why these are weak answers. Okay, let's try to get
a little bit further here. תא שמע, ta shema, שני אחים פיקחין
נשואין שתי נכריות, shnei achim pikchin nesu'in shtei nochriyot, two hearing brothers
married to two unrelated women, אחת פיקחת ואחת חרשת, achat pikechet v'achat
cheresha, one of the women is hearing, the other is not. מת
פיקח בעל חרשת, meit pikaiach baal cheresha, and now the husband of
the deaf woman died. So presumably again it was a קידושין דרבנן,
kiddushin derabbanan assuming it was a חרשת מעיקרא. cheresha mei'ikara. מה יעשה
פיקח אח פיקח? mah ya'aseh pikaiach ach pikaiach? What does the hearing
brother do? כונס, kones, he can do יבום, yibum ואם רצה להוציא
יוציא, v'im ratza l'hotzi yotzi, and if he wants to, after he's
done יבום, yibum to give her a גט, get. go ahead. But
you can't do חליצה because she is a חרשת. cheresha. Okay. מת
פיקח בעל פיקחת, meit pikaiach baal pikechet, let's say the hearing husband
died. So now what does the... this is now this is a
hearing brother. So he's completely a, so he's, so now it's an
easy case. It's a hearing brother with a hearing sister-in-law, everybody can
do anything they want to do. Okay. So מה יעשה פיקח בעל
חרשת? mah ya'aseh pikaiach baal cheresha? או חולץ או מייבם. o choletz
o miyabem. מאי לאו, mai lav, מדאיהו פיקח מעיקרא? midei'ihu pikaiach mei'ikara?
Since the guy that's hearing was always hearing, right? So we're assuming,
meaning we're not talking about anybody changed... realities. So הכי נמי חרשת
מעיקרא hachi nami chereshet meikara when talking about the woman who is
deaf, we're talking that she was always deaf. And even though she
was always deaf and her marriage was only a דרבנן marriage, חליצה
is not on the table. וקתני כונס אם חולץ לא, vekatani kones
im choletz lo, only יבום yibum not חליצה. מה שמע מיניה? mah
shemineya? Why? Is that a proof? הכי דהכא והכי דהכא. hachi dehacha
vehachi dehacha. Yes, the guy was the guy that was always hearing,
but when we deal with her, it was a case where she
became deaf later. So again, all these scenarios basically sound like even
though she was always deaf and the marriage was only דרבנן, she
can't do חליצה and the consistent answer is maybe we're talking about
the case that she entered in the marriage hearing and she became
deaf later. And that's why she can't. Let's try again. איתיביה eitiveia
שני אחים, shnei achim, two brothers, אחד פיקח ואחד חרש, echad pikeach
ve-echad cheresh, one hearing one not. נשואין שתי אחיות, nisu'in shtei achayot,
married to two sisters, אחת פיקחת ואחת חרשת, achat pikachat ve-achat chereshet,
one hearing one not, and it is again matched. מת חרש בעל
חרשת. met cheresh ba'al chereshet. So the non-hearing one dies. And now
his wife who is again presumably דרבנן and she's a חרשת. chereshet.
מה יעשה פיקח בעל פיקחת? mah ya'aseh pikeach ba'al pikachat? What does
the hearing one do? תצא tetzei now but the point is they
are now sisters. Right? שתי אחיות. shtei achayot. That's the new factor.
They're sisters. So now he's married, the hearing one is married to
Leah. What's he going to do with Rachel here? Right? He can't
do חליצה because she's a חרשת. chereshet. He can't do יבום yibum
because sister. So מה יעשה פיקח בעל פיקחת? mah ya'aseh pikeach ba'al
pikachat? תצא משום אחות אשה. tetzei mishum achot ishah. That's easy. So
fine. It's an ערווה. She walks away. He's married to his wife
דאורייתא. This is his wife's sister. She walks away. Easy. Now how
about מת פיקח בעל פיקחת? met pikeach ba'al pikachat? Now what if
the hearing one dies? מה יעשה חרש בעל חרשת? mah ya'aseh cheresh
ba'al chereshet? Now you got a problem because the deaf one he's
married to Rachel דרבנן. He's got a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum
to Leah דאורייתא. So Leah can't walk away because it's not because
there's not an ערווה דאורייתא here. There's a real מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibum and there's not an ערווה because he's not really married
to Rachel. Leah can't walk away, I understand, but from the תורה
perspective he's sleeping with Rachel. He's not married to Rachel, right? So
there's still a דאורייתא מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum, with Leah. So
she can't walk away דאורייתא because it's not a case of ערווה.
So he can't do יבום yibum with her דרבנן we won't allow
that because דרבנן he's married to Rachel. Okay. Then he can't do
חליצה because he's a חרש. cheresh. And he can't divorce Rachel? So
he could divorce Rachel. Let's take a look. So what is he
going to do? מוציא את אשתו בגט. motzi et ishto beget. So
Michael got it. So divorce Rachel. Now how can he divorce Rachel?
He's a חרש. cheresh. חרש cheresh can't give a גט. Ah, but
the whole marriage was only דרבנן. So therefore he can divorce Rachel.
Right? Because the whole marriage was only דרבנן. מוציא את אשתו בגט
ואשת אחיו אסורה עליו לעולם. motzi et ishto beget ve-eshet achiv asurah
alav le'olam. But then he still cannot- but this is worse. Michael
said now do יבום, yibum right? But he can't do יבום yibbum
because now Leah will be אחות גרושתו, achot gerushato, אחות אשתו. achot
ishto. Right? But it's really דרבנן. Doesn't matter! We're not making the
דרבנן disappear. So even after he divorces his wife, Leah's still stuck.
He can't do חליצה with her because he's a חרש. cheresh. Can't
do יבום because it's his דרבנן wife's sister. Okay, so why does
he have to divorce Rachel? Because to sleep with her would be
אחות זקוקתו. So what happens to Leah though? So Rachel gets divorced
and Leah's stuck. Leah's an עגונה agunah for her life. That's what
I'm saying. Why would you say אפקינהו רבנן? afkineihu rabbanan? I don't
know, I don't know. So anyway, bottom line is we'll all argue
about all this on שבת. Shabbat. Here the point is that it's
showing you that a חרשת chereshet cannot do חליצה. Okay, וכי תימא.
vechi teima. Now here it's the man, okay? So meaning what we're
trying to prove is that the scenarios in this משנה mishna. are
with people that always had the status. Right? So here we're dealing
with the man, the man being a חרש. cheresh. וכי תימא הכי
נמי בפיקח ואחר כך נסחרש. vechi teima hachi nami bepikeach ve'achar kach
nischaresh. So this guy, right, who's the חרש cheresh who's now stuck
and he can't, right, because he's got Leah there, the יבום דאורייתא,
yibum de'oraita, that whole scenario we described? And we're saying like- so
the basic point is that we're saying that he is able to
divorce his wife, right? Everybody remember the scenario we just described? He's
married to Rachel דרבנן, Leah's a יבום דאורייתא, yibum de'oraita, he has
to divorce Rachel. How could he divorce Rachel if he's a חרש?
cheresh? Well, he only married her as a חרש cheresh as well.
So that proves he married her as a חרש. cheresh. Right? Everybody
with me? Because he can divorce her as a חרש, cheresh, obviously
he married her as a חרש. cheresh. וכי תימא הכי נמי בפיקח
ואחר כך נסחרש. vechi teima hachi nami bepikeach ve'achar kach nischaresh. If
you say first he was a פיקח and then he became a
חרש, cheresh, מי מצי מפיק? mi matzi mapik? He can't divorce her.
דתנן detnan נסחרש הוא מוציא נשתטית לא יוציא. nischaresh hu motzi nishtatet
lo yotzi. If he became a חרש, cheresh, he can- she can
be divorced. If she became a נשתטית, nishtatet, I won't go into
that, but that's basically because we feel that a שוטה shotah or
woman can't protect herself and she'll be taken- people will take sexual
advantage of her. Okay. But she can be divorced. Because divorce from
the woman's side is אפילו בעל כרחה. afilu ba'al korcha. However, נתחרש
הוא nischaresh hu or נשתטה הוא—if nishtateh hu he became a חרש
cheresh or a שוטה shoteh and not a בר דעת לא יוציא
עולמית. lo yotzi olamis. He can't divorce her. So obviously, if he's
divorcing Rachel, he must have married Rachel as a חרש, cheresh, and
that allows him to divorce her. אלא לאו דחרש מעיקרא. ela lav
decheresh me'ikara. So that case had to be, when it talks about
the man as a חרש cheresh divorcing his wife, it had to
be that he was always a חרש. cheresh. ומדהוא חרש מעיקרא—since umidehu
cheresh me'ikara at least one case we can clearly identify the חרש
cheresh in this משנה is somebody who was always a חרש, cheresh,
הכי נמי חרשת מעיקרא. hachi nami chereshes me'ikara. When we're talking about
the woman as a חרשת, chereshes, it means she was always a
חרשת, chereshes, and nevertheless we say חליצה is not on the table.
הכי נמי חרשת מעיקרא. hachi nami chereshes me'ikara. ומדאחותו חרשת מעיקרא—and umide'achoso
chereshes me'ikara since in the scenario that we're dealing with of the
sisters, the woman is a חרשת chereshes from the get-go, נכריות נמי
חרשת מעיקרא—so nochriyos nami chereshes me'ikara the very beginning of the משנה,
the woman when—is a case of a חרשת. chereshes. דתנן גבי נכריות
desnan gabei nochriyos and it says, כונס אין חולץ לא. kones in
cholets lo. Okay. So basically we have proven that one of the
cases in the משנה when the man is a חרש cheresh is
that he was always a חרש. cheresh. And therefore presumably when the
woman is a חרשת, chereshes, she was always a חרשת. chereshes. And
the משנה says that even though she was always a חרשת chereshes
she can't do חליצה. So you see that even when a woman
enters a marriage as a חרשת chereshes and only דרבנן, she's not
allowed to do חליצה if her husband dies. So אשתיק, ishtik, he
was silent. Oh, you made a—yeah, you got—everybody in that case... yeah.
In that case, he has to divorce his פיקח wife and the
חרשת chereshes is an עגונה לעולם. aguna le'olam. No, no, no, she
was a חרשת chereshes wife and
the פיקח is עגונה לעולם. aguna le'olam. And she's a חרשת chereshes
and because what can he do?
He can't do חליצה, he's a חרש. cheresh.
He can't do יבום because she's
אחות אשתו achos ishto or אחות גרושתו. achos gerusahso. So he's stuck.
Even though it was דרבנן.
Even though it was דרבנן, but within the דרבנן, she's an עגונה
דרבנן. aguna derabbanan. Yeah. It's—I mean it's a real tragedy. Great. I
don't know, we're overtime. We could talk about it more tomorrow, but
we're going to end here. Okay, tomorrow we're going to pick up
with this. Basically, we've gone through that whole complicated משנה.
We've raised a lot of disturbing questions.
But
what we have seen is that it seems very clearly that a
חרשת chereshes cannot do חליצה even if the original marriage was as
a חרשת. chereshes. Okay, and we will continue with this tomorrow. But
wait, question: Is it to say that like, you know, he was
not married to her as a חרש cheresh to a חרשת, chereshes,
just say he was not ever married to her, just sleeping with
her? So she's אחות of someone who... Yeah, but we don't say
that. We've instituted קידושין דרבנן for a חרש. cheresh. But in this
case... דרבנן! Ah yes, you know, do you want a legal system
that every single time we're going to... we've done it before! I
know. And this is just to help someone. I do, I do
understand.