Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody.
Today's דף, daf, well, officially today's דף daf is דף ל. Daf
Lamed. We are on כט עמוד ב. Khaf Tet Amud Bet. I'm
going to start us back very quickly—I know this is a little
bit—it's not smart given that we're behind, but from the bottom of
כט עמוד א, Khaf Tet Amud Aleph, just because I read the
גמרא Gemara yesterday slightly incorrectly, I want to correct that and also
we need to anyway reframe what we're talking about. So if we
go to כט עמוד א, Khaf Tet Amud Aleph, we'll pick up
with אמר רבי אלעזר לא תימא, Amar Rabbi Elazar lo teima, five
lines from the bottom. The משנה Mishnah basically said that ראובן ושמעון
Reuven and Shimon died, leaving two sisters, you know, as two sister-in-laws,
רחל ולאה. Rachel and Leah. So לוי, Levi, but before שמעון Shimon
died, ראובן Reuven died, excuse me, then לוי Levi did מאמר mamar
with רחל. Rachel. And that's already pretty close to doing יבום. yibum.
And then שמעון Shimon died. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai says, well,
you already basically are married to רחל, Rachel, לאה Leah walks away,
which is fascinating, which basically says that מאמר mamar according to בית
שמאי Beit Shammai counts as יבום. yibum. It not only gets rid
of the problem of אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, which is rabbinic, but
it lets לאה Leah walk away completely as a, you know, as
a יבמה yevamah who's an ערווה. ervah. So that seems like there's
a real דאורייתא de'oraita status to that.
And where בית הלל Beit Hillel says, I'm sorry, now they're both
אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, you've got to do חליצה chalitzah with לאה
Leah and חליצה chalitzah with רחל, Rachel, a גט get to counteract
the מאמר. mamar. So we have here the idea that בית שמאי
Beit Shammai really says that the מאמר mamar is quite powerful. And
the גמרא Gemara wants to figure out exactly how powerful. So let's
pick up five lines from the bottom of כט עמוד א. Khaf
Tet Amud Aleph. אמר רבי אלעזר לא תימא מאמר לבית שמאי קונה
קניין גמור. Amar Rabbi Elazar lo teima mamar le'veit Shammai koneh kinyan
gamur.
Don't say מאמר mamar for בית שמאי Beit Shammai is a full
קניין; kinyan; it's like it's actually the exact same as יבום. yibum.
דאי בעא לאפוקי סגי ליה בגיטא. De'ei ba'ei lafokei sagi lei begita.
And
what would be the evidence of this, or what would be a
full קניין, kinyan, that after, if he wanted to now divorce from
רחל, Rachel, he would only have to give her a גט? get?
After יבום, yibum, then it's like they're totally married; there's no remnant
of the יבום yibum component left. And if they want to get
divorced, it's not חליצה; chalitzah; it's a גט. get. So would that
be true according to בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? He says no. Even
after the מאמר, mamar, and even if it sort of frees רחל—even
Rachel if it frees לאה Leah to walk away without יבום yibum
or חליצה—it's chalitzah not one hundred percent done. There's, if he wanted
to get divorced at this stage from רחל, Rachel, it would need
both a גט get and חליצה. chalitzah. אלא מאמר לבית שמאי אינו
קונה אלא לדחות בצרה בלבד. Ela mamar le'veit Shammai eino koneh ela
lidchot batzara bilvad. What it does is it pushes off לאה. Leah.
It says לאה Leah is enough of a, you know, of an
ערווה ervah
even on a דאורייתא de'oraita level, but it does not mean that
the יבום yibum status has completely gone away vis-a-vis רחל. Rachel. It's
still a little bit left in terms of solidifying that. Interesting to
exactly how you would exactly frame that, but nevertheless it hasn't completely
finished with רחל, Rachel, but it's enough to free לאה Leah from
any obligation.
Is it stronger than קידושין? kiddushin?
No, it's not stronger. Oh, what do you mean it's not stronger?
If he was married to רחל—whatever—it's Rachel not stronger. No, no, no.
Not stronger.
Not stronger. You need more, but it's not because it's stronger; it's
because it hasn't gotten rid of the יבום yibum obligation. Okay. אמר
רב אבין אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rav Avin af anan nami
tanina. That's implicit in the משנה. Mishnah. Why? Because two days ago
we learned that in a case not here
where they died sequentially, but in a similar case of they died,
let's say, at the same time or whatever, or you didn't do
anything until they had both died, that it says there that לוי
ויהודה, Levi and Yehuda, when you know, cannot go ahead and do
יבום yibum with רחל ולאה, Rachel and Leah, because each one is
אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato when no מאמר mamar had been done. Okay,
but בית שמאי Beit Shammai says if they went ahead and did
יבום, yibum, יקיימו, yekayyemu, they can stay married to רחל ולאה. Rachel
and Leah. יקיימו בדיעבד לכתחילה לא. Yekayyemu bedieved lechatchila lo. Only בדיעבד,
bedieved, not לכתחילה. lechatchila. But you're going to say, one minute, if
מאמר mamar really, here's a proof that מאמר mamar is not one
hundred percent. Because if מאמר mamar was one hundred percent, there would
be a solution here for בית שמאי Beit Shammai in the second
case, even if nobody had done anything yet, to allow them to
get married לכתחילה. lechatchila. What would be the solution? ואי סלקא דעתך
מאמר לבית שמאי קונה קניין גמור, Ve'ee salka daitach mamar le'veit Shammai
koneh kinyan gamur, if it was one hundred percent, so יעשה מאמר
ויקנה וזה יעשה מאמר ויקנה וזה יעשה מאמר ויקנה. ya'aseh mamar veyikneh
veze ya'aseh mamar veyikneh veze ya'aseh mamar veyikneh. So he says, I
got a perfect idea. So they can't do יבום, yibum, it's אחות
זקוקתו. achot zekukato. But nobody said you can't do מאמר. mamar. It's
only you can't have sex with אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. So go
ahead and do מאמר. mamar. Okay? And
then if this was really one hundred percent, so now רחל Rachel
is one hundred percent married to לוי, Levi, so לאה Leah is
now irrelevant, no longer a זיקה. zika. So now that לאה Leah
is no longer a זיקה, zika, now he can consummate it with
רחל. Rachel. And then יהודה Yehuda will do the same with לאה.
Leah. So if מאמר mamar really worked one hundred percent, there would
be a solution here: do מאמר, mamar, which is allowed, get לאה
Leah off, and then go ahead and finish it with— So the
גמרא Gemara says look, that's a question if מאמר ma'amar is 100
percent or not 100 percent. אלא מאי, Ela mai, so what, you
think that this makes sense if you say דוחה, docheh, that מאמר
ma'amar just pushes לאה Leah off and it's not 100 percent with
רחל? Rachel? דחייה גמורה? Dichiya gemura? If it fully pushes לאה Leah
off, you have the same question. It's not any better according to
you. זה יעשה מאמר וידחה וזה יעשה מאמר וידחה. Ze ya'aseh ma'amar
ve-yidcheh ve-ze ya'aseh ma'amar ve-yidcheh. Either way it's the same question. What
we see from בית שמאי Beit Shammai up here is that once
there's מאמר, ma'amar, however you understand whether the relationship with רחל Rachel
is 100 percent, לאה Leah is free. So whether it's 100 percent
or not לאה Leah is free. So it's the same question down
here. Let him do מאמר, ma'amar, get לאה Leah out of the
picture, and then finish. It doesn't prove whether it's 100 percent or
not, either way it's a question, why can't you do מאמר ma'amar
and get לאה Leah out of the picture? אלא מאי אית לך
למימר, Ela mai it lach lemamar, what's the explanation? What's the only
way of explaining why the top works and the bottom doesn't work?
מאמר דהיתרא דחי דאיסורא לא דחי, Ma'amar de-heteira dachi de-issura lo dachi,
because you'll say that up here when לוי Levi did מאמר ma'amar
with רחל, Rachel, שמעון Shimon hadn't died yet. So a מאמר ma'amar
done when he could have done יבום, yibbum, that will define it
as a full relationship or strong relationship so that when לאה Leah
becomes a widow, she's out of the picture. Whereas here where there's
already a problem of אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato and he can't do
יבום, yibbum, the מאמר ma'amar does not have an effect. הכא נמי,
Hacha nami, even if you say מאמר ma'amar works 100 percent, that's
only when it comes in an uncomplicated scenario. הכא נמי מאמר אפילו
למאן דאמר מאמר קונה קנין גמור, Hacha nami ma'amar afilu le-man de-amar
ma'amar koneh kinyan gamur, even if I were to claim that מאמר
ma'amar was 100 percent, so what would that be? מאמר דהיתרא קני
דאיסורא לא קני, Ma'amar de-heteira kani de-issura lo kani, only if it's
היתר heter not if it's איסור. issur. Okay, so the basic point
is that the difference down here is that the מאמר ma'amar here
you can't do a מאמר ma'amar to solve the problem. Once everything
is אסור, assur, מאמר ma'amar isn't going to work. But here the
מאמר ma'amar came in before לאה Leah became a widow, created a
relationship with רחל, Rachel, and then לאה Leah is a widow, then
she's out of the picture, she can walk away. So the question
we have right now is,
is מאמר ma'amar 100 percent with רחל, Rachel, קנין גמור, kinyan gamur,
and that it's only therefore needs a גט? get? Or, although מאמר
ma'amar gets לאה Leah off and lets him consummate with רחל, Rachel,
it's not yet 100 percent and there's still a remnant of the
יבום yibbum aspect there, and if he wanted to divorce her he
would need a גט get plus חליצה? chalitza? Okay, so that's the
question, whether it's קנין גמור, kinyan gamur, okay,
which is all of this is with רחל, Rachel, לאה's Leah off
either way, קנין גמור kinyan gamur and therefore you just have a
גט get if you wanted to get divorced, or it's דחייה גמורה.
dichiya gemura. דחייה גמורה Dichiya gemura means that לאה's Leah out of
the picture, but the relationship here is not complete, and therefore with
רחל Rachel if you wanted to get divorced you would need a
גט get plus חליצה. chalitza.
Okay,
because there's still some remnant of the יבום yibbum still around.
All
right, now interesting, we're going further. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this. רב אשי מתני הכי. Rav Ashi matni hachi. Here's how רב
אשי Rav Ashi teaches, and it's not a question of קנין גמור
kinyan gamur versus דחייה גמורה, dichiya gemura, but a different way of
understanding בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. אמר רב אלעזר, Amar Rav Elazar, לא
תימא מאמר לבית שמאי דחי דחייה גמורה. lo teima ma'amar le-Beit Shammai
dachi dichiya gemura. Don't say like was just said before by who
was it, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, that it's דחייה גמורה, dichiya gemura,
that לאה Leah is pushed off but this is not yet complete.
Don't say this, we're not going to go back to this, we're
going to go one even less than this. Don't say it's a
דחייה גמורה dichiya gemura that pushes לאה Leah fully off, וצרתה חליצה
נמי לא בעיא, ve-tzaratah chalitza nami lo ba'aya, לאה Leah doesn't even
need חליצה, chalitza, אלא דוחה ומשייר הוא. ela docheh u-meshayer hu. Yes,
it pushes לאה Leah off, but there's some remnant even vis-a-vis לאה,
Leah, which basically means, very different than the משנה Mishnah sounds and
the גמרא's Gemara going to ask from the משנה, Mishnah, it's strong
enough to let him consummate with רחל, Rachel, so there is not
a problem of אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. There's like not enough of
a זיקה zika to make לאה Leah a problem, so he can
finish with רחל, Rachel, it's not אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. But maybe
it's only דרבנן, de-rabbanan, maybe it's not דאורייתא. de-oraita. Remember אחות זקוקתו
achot zekukato problem is all דרבנן de-rabbanan anyway. So there still is
some connection to לאה Leah and therefore he would still need to
do חליצה chalitza with לאה. Leah. Now the משנה Mishnah doesn't sound
like that, the משנה Mishnah sounds like לאה Leah just walks away.
So the גמרא's Gemara going to pretty much reject this. Let's take
a look. Right,
אמר רב אבין, Amar Rav Avin, אנן נמי תנינא. anan nami tanina.
So first we're going to try to prove it like we did
before. בית שמאי אומרים יקיימו, Beit Shammai omrim yekayemu, that they can
בדיעבד be-diavad if in the bottom case they can stay married if
they did it when they weren't supposed to. יקיימו אין לכתחילה לא,
Yekayemu ein lechatchila lo, only בדיעבד be-diavad not לכתחילה. lechatchila. ואי סלקא
דעתך מאמר לבית שמאי דחי דחייה גמורה, Ve-isalka datach ma'amar le-Beit Shammai
dachi dichiya gemura, and now this is a better point of why
we're trying to prove it, if here according to, if once you
did מאמר ma'amar לאה Leah was completely pushed away and it removed
the problem of אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, so זה יעשה מאמר וידחה
וזה יעשה מאמר וידחה, ze ya'aseh ma'amar ve-yidcheh ve-ze ya'aseh ma'amar ve-yidcheh,
why don't we solve this problem by doing מאמר, ma'amar, getting rid
of. sort of pushing the other wife out of the picture and
then finishing it. So the גמרא Gemara says again similar type of
an answer. והא קתני, Ve-Ha Ka Tani, no you can't say that
says the גמרא. Gemara. That's not a proof. Just because you couldn't
solve the problem down here doesn't mean that there's still some remnant
of a relationship. Because our משנה Mishnah is very clear that there
is no remnant of a relationship with Leah. והא קתני, Ve-Ha Ka
Tani, our משנה Mishnah says בית שמאי אומרים Beit Shammai Omrim אשתו
עמו וידחה, Ishto Imo Ve-Yidacheh,
his wife Rachel is with him and, sorry I skipped a line,
אשתו עמו והלזו תצא משום אחות אשה, Ishto Imo Ve-Ha-Lezu Tetzei Mi-Shum
Achot Ishah, his wife Rachel is his, sorry, it's not 'with him'
it's 'his wife', אשתו עמו Ishto Imo is his wife Rachel is
with him, והלזו תצא משום אחות אשה Ve-Ha-Lezu Tetzei Mi-Shum Achot Ishah
and Leah walks away, she's his wife's sister. So you see that
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says that Leah walks away. There's no חליצה,
Chalitzah, any חליצה Chalitzah needing to be done with Leah. מאמר Ma'amar
actually has a דאורייתא De-Oraita status and Leah really walks away. So
אלא יבמה דחזיא לכולהו חזיא למקצתה, Ela Yevamah De-Chazya Le-Kulu Chazya Le-Miktzata,
so what's the explanation of why it works here not down here?
So the same thing it said before about מאמר דהיתרא Ma'amar De-Heiteira
except using a different language. אלא, Ela, says the גמרא, Gemara,
יבמה דחזיא לכולהו חזיא למקצתה, Yevamah De-Chazya Le-Kulu Chazya Le-Miktzata, this sister-in-law
that could have had יבום Yibum for her, a partial מאמר Ma'amar
is meaningful. Okay? יבמה דלא חזיא לכולהו, Yevamah De-Lo Chazya Le-Kulu, the
sister-in-laws down here that could not have had יבום Yibum because it
was אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zikukato,
so לא חזיא למקצתה, Lo Chazya Le-Miktzata, then even the מאמר Ma'amar
is not meaningful. Which is another way of saying a מאמר דהיתרא
Ma'amar De-Heiteira works, a מאמר דאיסורא Ma'amar De-Issura does not work. So
the גמרא Gemara tried to suggest maybe it's קנין גמור. Kinyan Gamur.
Okay, did not have a reason not to say it, but nevertheless
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah preferred this idea, okay, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah
preferred the idea that it's partial, okay, although you could in theory
have said it's קנין גמור. Kinyan Gamur. Then רב אשי Rav Ashi
tries to say that you still have to do חליצה Chalitzah with
Leah, but that clearly was against the משנה, Mishnah, that that was
משייר Meshayer that he still had some relationship with Leah, but that
clearly is against the משנה. Mishnah. So the one we are sort
of most focusing on is the possibility that it is, yet Leah
is completely out of the picture, but his relationship with רחל Rachel
is not yet 100%. However, the גמרא Gemara now is going to,
it's going to look like go back to the possibility we passed
over before and say maybe his relationship with רחל Rachel really is
ממש Mamash 100%, and he would only have to do a גט,
Get, not a גט Get and חליצה. Chalitzah. So those are the
two possibilities within בית שמאי Beit Shammai we're contemplating. By the way,
how do we understand that how this מאמר Ma'amar could have a
biblical implication and get Leah off? Right? I mean, until now we've
all been saying that מאמר Ma'amar is דרבנן. De-Rabbanan. So the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi says gives a פסוק Pasuk for בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. And
here's the ירושלמי'ס Yerushalmi's פסוק Pasuk for בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, it's
יבמה יבא
עליה ולקחה לו לאשה
ויבמה.
Yevamah Yavo Aleha Ve-Lakachah Lo
Le-Ishah
Ve-Yivemah. I think that's the פסוק. Pasuk. That's what it says. ויבמה
Ve-Yivemah is יבום, Yibum, and ולקחה לו לאשה Ve-Lakachah Lo Le-Ishah is
מאמר קידושין. Ma'amar Kiddushin. Wow. And that
actually קידושין Kiddushin is also a way of, if not doing a
hundred percent, you know, that's the question, you hear some things that
are not exactly the same in terms of the impact of it,
but basically sees that קידושין Kiddushin is part of the, is a
דאורייתא De-Oraita component or could be a דאורייתא De-Oraita component of יבום.
Yibum. So that is בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. What? That's a good
דרשה. Derashah. Yeah, it's a good דרשה, Derashah, not bad, right? Certainly
better than a lot of other דרשות. Derashot. Alright. So now the
גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say like this. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava, רבא.
Rava. So רבא Rava asked, מאמר לבית שמאי, Ma'amar Le-Beit Shammai, assuming
for בית שמאי Beit Shammai מאמר Ma'amar is a
real type of a קנין, Kinyan, maybe even a קנין גמור, Kinyan
Gamur, now we're going to push it even further. Maybe not only
is it קנין גמור Kinyan Gamur which we said the implication would
be that it would just be a גט Get with רחל Rachel
not even חליצה, Chalitzah, but maybe it's even more than קידושין. Kiddushin.
How could it be more than קידושין? Kiddushin? What's more than קידושין?
Kiddushin? נישואין. Nissu'in. So let's take a look. בעי רבא, Ba'ei Rava,
רבא Rava asked, מאמר לבית
שמאי נישואין עושה או אירוסין עושה? Ma'amar Le-Beit Shammai Nissu'in Oseh O
Erusin Oseh? So does it do נישואין? Nissu'in? Is it like even
with חופה? Chuppah? Or is it just like קידושין? Kiddushin? Okay, which
is pretty funny, all you do is you do קידושין, Kiddushin, הרי
את מקודשת לי, Harei At Mekudeshet Li, you haven't done יבום Yibum
which is the act of sex which is like נישואין. Nissu'in. Why
would you think that? Yeah, so let's take a look. Well, this
isn't rabbinic according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, remember. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה אביי, Amar Lei Abaye, אביי
Abaye said, למאי הלכתא? Le-Mai Hilchata? What's the implication? What do you
want to suggest to say that it's like נישואין? Nissu'in? אילימא ליורשה
ולטמא לה ולהפר נדריה, Ilima Le-Yorshah U-Le-Tameh Lah U-Le-Hafer Nedareha, here's what
happens between, you know, that נישואין Nissu'in adds to קידושין. Kiddushin. After
נישואין Nissu'in the husband inherits his wife, if he's a כהן Kohen
he can become טמא Tameh to her, and he can annul her
vows even without her father's participation. Okay, there's a lot of other
things also, some are דאורייתא, De-Oraita, some are דרבנן, De-Rabbanan, we'll worry
about that in a few weeks. But okay, here's a handful of
things that נישואין Nissu'in adds. and you want to say that maybe
after מאמר Ma'amar by יבום, Yibum, all those things have now changed,
just like by נשואין. Nisuin. One minute, רבא Rava says, why would
this be more weightier than a standard קידושין? Kiddushin? השתא ארוסה בעלמא,
Hashta arusa be'alma, a standard ארוסה arusa who had קידושין, Kiddushin, תני
רב חייא, Tani Rav Chiyya, ארוסה אשתו ארוסה, arusa ishto arusa, if
his wife is an ארוסה arusa and there's not been yet נשואין,
Nisuin, לא אונן, lo onen, if she dies, then he does not
have an אונן onen status to her, ולא מטמא לה, velo mitamei
lah, and if he's a כהן, Kohen, he doesn't become טמא tamei
to her, וכן היא, vechen hi, and she, לא אוננת, lo onenet,
if he dies, she's not an אונן onen to him, ולא מטמא
לו, velo mitamei lo, she doesn't become טמא tamei to him. Now
people say that's just רש"י Rashi says it's just thrown in because
she never would be a כהן, Kohen, she'd be a בת כהן,
Bas Kohen, she would never have any restrictions of becoming טמא. tamei.
Alright, other ראשונים Rishonim try to say maybe it's ברגל, baregel, you're
not supposed to be טמא ברגל. tamei baregel. Anyway, okay, but it's
just קידושין, Kiddushin, yet you don't have yet these laws
of אבילות aveilus and אנינות. aninus.
מתה אינה יורשה, meta einah yorshah, if she dies he does not
inherit her. מתו, mesu, however, if he dies, גובה כתובתה, govah kesuvatah,
she can still collect her כתובה kesuvah in a case when a
כתובה kesuvah was written from the קידושין. Kiddushin. So anyway, the point
is that all of these sort of
זכויות, zechuyos, sort of rights and changes of status, happen at נשואין,
Nisuin, even when we're talking in a standard case of קידושין Kiddushin
and נשואין. Nisuin. So if that's true by a classic קידושין, Kiddushin,
those rights haven't yet changed, those statuses haven't changed, so
מאמר מבעיא, Ma'amar mibaya, is there any question that with מאמר Ma'amar
you don't have those? Now what is the קל וחומר? kal vachomer?
Why
is it obvious that if you don't have it by אירוסין eirusin
you won't have it by מאמר? Ma'amar? So רש"י Rashi says, if
you look at
רש"י, Rashi,
השתא ארוסה, hashta arusa, it's like three lines over where it says
דף כ"ה daf chaf-hei in that margin on the left between the
גמרא Gemara and
רש"י. Rashi. השתא ארוסה דקידושי דידה דאורייתא, Hashta arusa de-Kiddushei didah de-Oraisa,
even when it's biblical, תני רב חייא אינה יורשה ואינו מטמא לה.
tani Rav Chiyya einah yorshah ve'eino mitamei lah. מאמר יבמי מדרבנן הוא
דמדאורייתא יבמה יבא עליה כתיב רחמנא. Ma'amar yavmi miderrabbanan hu demide'oraisa yevamah
yavo aleha kesiv rachmana. מבעיא? mibaya? So
how could מאמר, Ma'amar, which is only rabbinic, give you those things
if קידושין, Kiddushin, which is דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, does not? Now the ראשונים
Rishonim ask what is רש"י Rashi talking about? We're dealing here according
to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, and according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai
he thinks that מאמר Ma'amar has to be biblical because it lets
לאה Leah walk away without חליצה. chalitzah. So they say for example,
the ריטב"א Ritva says he doesn't like רש"י'ס פשט, Rashi's pshat, we're
assuming מאמר Ma'amar like בית שמאי Beis Shammai is biblical, that's what
let לאה Leah walk away. But nevertheless it's not as weighty as
קידושין. Kiddushin. Now in what way is it not as weighty as
קידושין? Kiddushin? It demands a גט. get. So he says there's another
גמרא Gemara that says what would be the consequence if the woman
would actually sleep with another man after this מאמר Ma'amar before the
act of יבום. Yibum. So another גמרא Gemara says that it would
not be considered the adultery that you're חייב מיתה chayav misah for.
Okay, it'll be the לאו lav that she couldn't marry another man
while she's waiting for יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitzah, but even if
this creates a status of אשתו, ishto, it's not with the full
weight of אשת איש. eisheth ish. So we're taking that for granted.
Even if it's a דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, even if maybe now it's only
a גט get without חליצה, chalitzah, or maybe we're assuming חליצה chalitzah
would be needed so it's not a hundred percent, but even if
it's דאורייתא de-Oraisa and it lets לאה Leah walk away, it's not
the full weight as if it were a classic case of קידושין.
Kiddushin. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says if a normal קידושין Kiddushin
is not נשואין, Nisuin, you don't have those rights or you don't
have those changes of status, so why should this, which
has not yet gotten to the same level even if it is
דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, why should this count as נשואין? Nisuin? So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says.
What does this mean that it should count as נשואין? Nisuin? So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר ליה, amar lei, so he
said to him, השתא לא עביד בה מאמר. hashta lo avid bah
Ma'amar. I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
ואלא, ve-ela, about six lines before the lines get wide. ואלא לענין
מסירה לחופה מאי? Ve-ela le-inyan mesirah le-chuppah mai? The question is about
the need, not about those rights, those rights don't kick in after
מאמר, Ma'amar, those different statuses. The question is about whether you're going
to need an act of נשואין Nisuin later.
ואלא לענין מסירה לחופה מאי? Ve-ela le-inyan mesirah le-chuppah mai? נישואין עושה,
Nisuin osah, does this count as a חופה, chuppah, ולא בעיא מסירה
לחופה, velo ba'aya mesirah le-chuppah, and then you won't later need to
have a חופה? chuppah? או דילמא אירוסין עושה ובעיא מסירה לחופה, O
dilma eirusin osah ve-ba'aya mesirah le-chuppah, or maybe it's only אירוסין eirusin
and you will need? Now what does this mean? Does this mean
that we think that a normal case of יבום Yibum after they
do יבום Yibum they have to do some act of going under
the חופה chuppah and do some act of נשואין? Nisuin? Like we
never heard of anything like that. Okay, but maybe he thinks that
and who knows. So anyway, so here his question is or maybe
as we're going to see that he basically thinks that once you
start down the קידושין Kiddushin path by doing מאמר, Ma'amar, you didn't
go straight to יבום, Yibum, you did מאמר Ma'amar which is essentially
קידושין, Kiddushin, maybe now Because he started down the path in דרבנן
derabanan you're supposed to do that before you do ייבום, yibum, maybe
now דרבנן derabanan we're going to demand for there to be a
נישואין nesuin as well. So here's רבא'ס Rava's question. Now they did,
they did אירוסין, erusin, they did מאמר maamar and now they're going
to have sex and do ייבום. yibum. Do they also need a
חופה? chuppah? Do they need a נישואין? nesuin? Or can they just
go straight and do the ייבום yibum or do they also need
a נישואין? nesuin? Which is a reasonable question, you could ask it
even not according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, right? At a דרבנן
derabanan level. You do מאמר, maamar, do they also want me to
do a נישואין? nesuin? Okay, but here we're asking the question according
to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So let's take a look. או דילמא
אירוסין עושה בה נסועין לא בעי? Od dilma erusin ose ba nisuin
lo bei? אמר ליה, Amar lei, השתא לא עבד בה מאמר כתיב.
Hashta lo avad ba maamar ketiv. So I sort of just told
you a little bit of the גמרא Gemara ahead. If he did
not do מאמר, maamar, the verse says the classic, forget the whole
מאמר maamar thing. Even בית שמאי Beit Shammai admits that you don't
have to do מאמר, maamar, even if it works at a דאורייתא
deoraisa level. So if you don't do מאמר, maamar, it says יבמה
יבא עליה yevamah yavo aleha that the brother-in-law shall have sex with
her, enter into her, ועל כרחה, veal korcha, even against her will.
So now why it says ועל כרחה veal korcha here is not
clear, why it's emphasizing this, always a very obviously difficult הלכה halacha
to deal with, but it seems to be saying that if they're
doing it sort of willingly and consensually, then that maybe itself is
חופה. chuppah. So why isn't every act of sex, it gets to
the whole question of what חופה chuppah is, but every act of
once they're actually having sex as a married couple, that itself should
be a חופה, chuppah, even like in a forget a ייבום yibum
case, a normal case, right? They do the קידושין kiddushin and then
they start living together as husband and wife, that counts as חופה.
chuppah. Okay, so how here would you ever have a case of
an act of ייבום yibum that wouldn't itself already be an act
of חופה? chuppah? Only if she wasn't really agreeing to it. Okay,
again, very difficult that that's
the only way, not to do חליצה chalitzah if she doesn't agree
to it.
Yeah, I understand, you shouldn't, and we're going to see that, that
בית דין Beis Din is going to try to compel him to
do חליצה, chalitzah, but הלכתא, halachically, if he went ahead and did
it, it would still work even if he shouldn't have. Nobody's saying
he should have, but if he did, it would be effective, and
that's very difficult, right? I'd like to understand at least some of
the בעל כרחה'ס baal korchas are not like literal rapes, but she
somewhat, like she doesn't want to but she's going along type of
a thing, but nevertheless, it's still very, very difficult.
I really can't make it better.
Yeah. קידושין kiddushin can't be בעל כרחה. baal korcha. Right, but the
sex can be. Okay, so if there was a case of a
normal couple had קידושין kiddushin and then they started living together as
husband and wife, that counts as נישואין. nisuin. But in this case,
what if it was a case that was not consensual sex, it
wouldn't count as נישואין. nisuin. Here he says what about this case?
Okay, so here he says look, if the normal act of ייבום,
yibum, non-consensual sex, still works, so how could you say and that's
full then with all the changes of statuses, how here could you
say that you need
an idea of מסירה לחופה?
mesirah lechuppah? Any sex automatically makes her נשואה, nesuah, gives her full
status. So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, so the גמרא Gemara says,
עבד בה מאמר מבעיא? avad ba maamar mibaya? So if there's מאמר,
maamar, why should you ask? Of course once they have sex that's
going to count, however that sex took place. So אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said back to him, yes, שאני אומר, shani omer, because
I say כל העושה מאמר ביבמתו, kol haose maamar biyivimto, anybody who
does מאמר maamar with his sister-in-law, פרחה הימנה זיקת יבמין. parcha heimena
zikas yivamin. It actually again it now essentially says שאני אומר, shani
omer, because still presumably we're working within בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. But
I say once according at least to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, once
you do מאמר, maamar, the whole aspect of ייבום yibum goes away,
like maybe again like we said before, not even חליצה chalitzah would
be needed, דחלה זיקת אירוסין, dechalah zikas erusin, you're totally within the
קידושין kiddushin track. So again, bracketing the very difficult גמרא Gemara about
sex בעל כרחה, baal korcha, this is a fascinating type of a
model, that once we say מאמר maamar works דאורייתא deoraisa for בית
שמאי Beit Shammai and so it makes Leah אחות אישה achos isha
etc., right? Maybe it completely shifts the whole track. If you go
ahead and you do ייבום, yibum, that works one way, that's about
the act of sex and maybe it'll even work even בעל כרחה.
baal korcha. But once however he puts himself on a different track,
he does the לקיחה לו לאשה, likicha lo leishah, not the יבמה,
yevamah, he starts on that track, then maybe that works according to
the normal type of a קידושין kiddushin model, and therefore you would
need a normal type of a מסירה לחופה. mesirah lechuppah. Okay, so
that then becomes the question. And according to that presumably if that's
true that you're on a different track and there's no more זיקה,
zikah, then presumably here again it would be up here, you wouldn't
even need חליצה, chalitzah, it would only be a גט. get. Okay,
so that's his question, whether there's going to have to be a
חופה chuppah here as well, if you're putting yourself on a different
track the answer is yes, if you're still on the ייבום yibum
track the answer is no. Okay, so מאי, mai, what's the הלכה?
halacha? תא שמע, ta shema, שומרת יבם, shomeres yavam, a woman waiting
for ייבום, yibum, בין יבם אחד בין שני יבמין, bein yavam echad
bein shenei yevamin, whether there are two brothers-in-law or one brother-in-law, so
there's some זיקה zikah with this woman. So רבי אליעזר אומר יפר.
Rabbi Eliezer omer yafer. And now what happens if she goes and
makes a נדר? neder? Can these men be מפר meifer her נדר?
neder? Okay, these men that are her quasi-husband. Now remember the הלכה
halacha that if there's קידושין kiddushin without נישואין, nissuin, the הפרת נדרים
hafarat nedarim takes place as a combination of the husband, the ארוס,
arus, and the father. Okay, so here for them to be able
to do it alone, you would have to sort of give her
almost like a נשואה nissua status, okay, and there's also the question,
what if there are two of them? Then it's not even clear
who's going to be the one that's going to sort of actualize
the זיקה. zika. So let's take a look. So this woman who's
waiting for יבום, yibum, רבי אליעזר אומר יפר, Rabbi Eliezer omer yafer,
that the man, the brother-in-law can do, can annul the vows. רבי
יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, well we'll see what that means. Okay,
רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi Yehoshua omer, let's say, let's say it means
either one can do it. רבי יהושע אומר לאחד ולא לשנים, Rabbi
Yehoshua omer leachad velo lishnayim, only if there's one brother-in-law can he
annul the vows, but if there are two, they cannot because neither
of them have a strong enough relationship with her. רבי עקיבא אומר
לא לאחד ולא לשנים, Rabbi Akiva omer lo leachad velo lishnayim, not
even two but even one cannot annul the vows, the זיקה zika
is not strong enough. ובעינא בה. Vaveina bah. And then we ask
on this. בשלמא רבי עקיבא, Bishlama Rabbi Akiva, I get רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, סבר אין זיקה אפילו לאחד, savar ein zika afilu leachad,
that the זיקה zika even with one doesn't exist or is not
significant enough to allow him to annul the vows. רבי יהושע לאחד
יש זיקה לתרי אין זיקה. Rabbi Yehoshua leachad yesh zika letrei ein
zika. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua also makes sense that there's with
one there's a זיקה zika because and it's clearly about him so
he can annul the vows and not with two. Again we're sort
of ignoring the נישואין nissuin question, but we'll get back to that.
אלא רבי אליעזר? Ella Rabbi Eliezer? But רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
doesn't distinguish? מיהא נמי דקסבר יש זיקה, Mi nami dekisavar yesh zika,
let him hold that there is זיקה. zika. בשלמא לאחד מיפר, Bishlama
leachad meifer, I get that if there's one he can be מפר.
meifer. אלא לשנים אמאי? Ella lishnayim amai? How can you do it
with two? Meaning how can, you know, how can one of them,
a, you have to say that each person even though it's not
clear who's going to do the יבום, yibum, each person has a
strong enough זיקה. zika. But even if that's true, how can you
say one of them does הפרה? hafara? Wouldn't you need both of
them to do הפרה? hafara? So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so that's our question. ואמר רבי אמי, Ve'amar Rabbi
Ami, and said רבי אמי Rabbi Ami בר אבא bar Abba or
whoever, said רבי אמי Rabbi Ami הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha bemai askinan,
here's the case we're talking about. כגון דעבד בה מאמר, Kegon de'avid
bah ma'amar, that the guy that it's not just a simple case
of a woman waiting for יבום, yibum, an act of מאמר ma'amar
was already done with this woman by one of the guys. ובבית
שמאי דאמר מאמר קונה קניין גמור, Ube'beishammai de'amar ma'amar koneh kinyan gamur,
and it's בית שמאי Beishammai and that's why he can go ahead
and do the הפרת נדרים. hafarat nedarim. So we have said that
this case is talking with מאמר. ma'amar. So now that they're talking
with מאמר, ma'amar, we see our answer. אי אמרת בשלמא נישואין עושה,
I amarta bishlama nissuin osah, if מאמר ma'amar makes her like נישואין,
nissuin, משום הכי מיפר. mishum hachi meifer. Now, now we under... by
the way, so that explains רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Why does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say one guy? Because only one guy did מאמר
ma'amar and it focuses on that one guy and takes out the
other. But now that we've introduced מאמר ma'amar to this scenario, we
see that with מאמר, ma'amar, she's like a נשואה nissua and there
could be הפרת נדרים. hafarat nedarim. So that shows that מאמר ma'amar
works to create her like a נשואה nissua status. Now by the
way, this is going back to the original way the גמרא Gemara
framed it. If you remember the גמרא Gemara said no, no, no,
הפרת נדרים hafarat nedarim whatever, that wouldn't work, we're only talking about
whether she needs חופה. chuppah. Now we're going back to the easier
way of framing the question which is no, maybe really מאמר ma'amar
jumps her automatically to a נשואה nissua status and you can do
הפרת נדרים. hafarat nedarim. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, that's clearly
how we're explaining this issue of הפרת נדרים, hafarat nedarim, that there
was מאמר ma'amar and she has a נשואה nissua status. So the
גמרא Gemara says בשלמא, bishlama, אי אמרת בשלמא נישואין עושה, i amarta
bishlama nissuin osah, if it's like a נישואין, nissuin, משום הכי מיפר,
mishum hachi meifer, that's why they can be מפר meifer and there's
only a question, one or two or whatever. אלא אי אמרת אירוסין
עושה, Ella i amarta eirusin osah, but if it only is at
the אירוסין eirusin level, היכי מצי מיפר? heichi mati meifer? How can
he do הפרה? hafara? It needs to be done together with the
father. דתנן, Detnan, נערה המאורסה אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה. naara hameorasa avia
uvaala mefirim nedareha. So it should have had to say together with
the father. Now, somebody's going to say wait, wait, what if the
father's dead? Maybe that scenario? Okay, so תוספות Tosafot has already thought
about that, so let's look at תוספות, Tosafot, he says, אביה ובעלה
מפירין נדריה, avia uvaala mefirim nedareha, ואם אין לא אב
או שאינה ברשות
האב לא מצי מיפר כדאמרינן בנדרים.
veim ein la av o sheeina
birshus
haav lo mati meifer kidamrinan bindarim. Okay, so the husband, the ארוס
arus cannot do it without a father, even if there is no
father. And by the way, even if the father's alive, he's irrelevant
now. Why? Because she got married to another man. So although the
father is irrelevant, right, so, you know, or might be around depending
if she was ארוס arus to the other man or נשואה nissua
to the other man.
Anyway, so it's
still he shouldn't be able to do it if it's just an
ארוס arus and an ארוסה arusah status. So one minute. אלא אי
אמרת אלא היכי מצי מיפר והתנן נערה המאורסה אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה?
Ella i amarta ella heichi mati meifer vehatnan naara hameorasa avia
uvaala mefirim nedareha? So אמר רב נחמן. amar Rav Nachman. So you
see it's a pretty good proof that there's מאמר ma'amar and we're
assuming it allows for הפרת נדרים. hafarat nedarim. So according to בית
שמאי, Beishammai, מאמר נישואין עושה. ma'amar nissuin osah. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, מאי מיפר מיפר ברשות האב. mai
meifer meifer birshus haav. Okay, it doesn't mean by himself, it means
together with the father. יפר יפירו. yafer yaferu. I understand, the גמרא
Gemara is going to say that. It means together with the father
and we're still going to insist that it's אירוסין. eirusin. So the
גמרא Gemara says רבי אליעזר דאמר מאמר לבית שמאי אינו קונה אלא
לדחות לצרה בלבד. Rebbe Eliezer de'amar Maamar le'Beis Shammai eino koneh ela
lidchos letzarah bilvad. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
האי, Hai, all of this discussion was assuming מאמר Maamar could be
קונה קניין גמור. koneh kinyan gamur. Okay but according to what we
said earlier that רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer said that it's not קונה
koneh even and it only sort of pushes the צרה tzara off
but it's not really קונה. koneh. So according to that right and
he even said it's משייר. meshayer. So אמאי מיפר בשותפות? ammai meifer
bishutafus? How how does any of this work? We're back to the
problem. All of the possibility that something was working here was assuming
that it was קונה קניין גמור. koneh kinyan gamur. And therefore it
either made her an ארוסה arusa and therefore he could do it
together with the father which was a weak answer but okay or
it made her a נשואה. nissua. Okay but both of those assumed
at least that you were in the קניין גמור kinyan gamur category.
So when you weren't down here with the משייר meshayer so if
if according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai it's not even full so
how does any of this work? Even at the ארוסה arusa level
it doesn't work because it's not even it's not full. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמאי מיפר בשותפות? ammai meifer bishutafus? אמר לך רבי
אליעזר Amar lach Rebbe Eliezer אימא דאמרי אנא אינו קונה אלא לדחות
לצרה eima de'amri ana eino koneh ela lidchos letzara when did I
say that his relationship with רחל Rachel is not strong enough except
to push off לאה Leah but it's not really full with רחל
Rachel בלבד דלא סגי לה בגיט bilvad delo sagi la be'get that
a גט get won't be enough you need a גט get and
חליצה. chalitza. He hasn't okay but if that's true how still how
could you do הפרת נדרים? haforas nedarim? I mean that requires to
be an ארוסה arusa if not a נשואה. nissua. אלא בעי נמי
חליצה Ella bai nami chalitza but הפרת נדרים מי אמרינן? haforas nedarim
mi amrinan? But maybe he can still do הפרת נדרים. haforas nedarim.
So which is again quite
a strange story so I don't get it so why? I mean
it still begs the question why? I mean if she's still going
to need a חליצה chalitza and it's not complete why can he
do הפרת נדרים? haforas nedarim? Maybe he really says that you've got
two things going on here. She's both an ארוסה arusa and at
the ארוסה arusa level he can do הפרת נדרים haforas nedarim with
the father. But she still has it left being a יבמה yevama
and from that perspective she needs חליצה. chalitza. So we're not saying
she's not an ארוסה. arusa. The קידושין kiddushin is a hundred percent
but it hasn't yet removed the יבמה yevama status. Even by בית
שמאי? Beis Shammai? Yeah well that's what we're saying so that's what
he was saying his thing according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Okay
so that's one answer. ואיבעית אימא Ve'ibayeis eima and if you want
you could say אמר לך רבי אליעזר amar lach Rebbe Eliezer רב
נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak מי ניחא? mi nicha? I
don't get it even if you say קניין גמור kinyan gamur this
is not a good answer just
to say he's
doing it with the father. מי קתני יפירו? Mi katani yafeiru? It
doesn't say they will annul. יפר קתני. Yafeir katani. One. So it's
not a good answer. Don't tell me he's doing it with the
father. So even if it's אירוסין erusin this this doesn't make sense.
So then why are they annulling it? אלא הכא במאי עסקינן Ella
hacha bemai askinan what's the case? שעמדה בדין ופסקו לה מזונות משלו.
She'amda bedin ve'pasku la mezonos mishelo. Basically it was a case where
all of the brothers were refusing to do anything about it. I
don't want to do יבום yibbum I don't want to do חליצה
chalitza don't bother me about it. So what they did is she
took him to a court case. You've got to do something buddy.
And the בית דין Beis Din basically said until you act on
this you are not we're going to treat her like your wife
and you're going to have to support her you're going to have
to pay for her you know for her upkeep מזונות. mezonos. And
in and yeah and then hopefully then that'll get him to to
get him to act one way or the other way. Prenuptial agreement?
There you go. So in that case once he's already supporting her
and he has a financial sort of relationship and responsibility towards her
even though halachically the גמרא's Gemara going to say she's not an
ארוסה arusa or נשואה nissua yet but we can assume that her
vows are going to be done you know implicitly assuming the husband
agrees assuming not the husband but the brother-in-law because she wants she
sort of she wants the relationship to work. וכדרב פנחס משמיה דרבא
דאמר רב פנחס משמיה דרבא כל הנודרת על דעת בעלה היא נודרת.
U'che'Rav Pinchas mishmei de'Rava de'amar Rav Pinchas mishmei de'Rava kol hanoderes al
daas baalah hi noderes. So it's not the classic הפרת נדרים haforas
nedarim that he has to hear within twenty-four hours or whatever it's
just an assumption that she's going to do it you know pending
his agreement. Of course if that's true who needs the תורה's Torah
category of הפרת נדרים? haforas nedarim? Just always say that the wife
does it pending the husband's agreement. But the גמרא Gemara makes it
a not a technical הפרת נדרים haforas nedarim like an implicit stipulation
and תנאי tnay because of a unique type of a relationship. Okay
so that's sort of how it deals with it but for us
I want to remind us we have some amazing possibilities in בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. First of all it sounds like if לאה Leah
walks away without חליצה chalitza it's דאורייתא. De'Oraisa. מאמר Maamar the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi learned it from לקחה לו לאשה. likacha lo le'ishah. How complete
is it? We have the possibility that it's full קידושין kiddushin all
they need now is a גט get wouldn't need חליצה. chalitza. Even
further maybe it's נשואין nissuin that you הפרת נדרים haforas nedarim and
all those types of things. Or we have things that are a
little bit less than full קידושין. kiddushin. Both needs a גט get
and חליצה chalitza although even there the גמרא Gemara suggested that that
might not be because it's not a hundred percent. It might be
a hundred percent in terms of she's his wife it's a full
ארוסה arusa but he also still retains a status of a יבמה
yevama until he actually does the act of יבום. yibbum. That's a
way of understanding like a double status not a partial status. Okay
but again as I told you another גמרא Gemara says it would
still not have the consequence of like אשת איש eishes ish you
know so. so it still is an interesting type of a status
here and the idea that once you put
yourself
on a track of מאמר, ma'amar, you
might now be on a completely different track, that like רבה Rabba
said it removes זיקת יבמין, zikas yavamin, you switched the whole dynamic
and the relationship. Okay, quite fascinating according to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
Now we finally turn to today's דף, daf, top of ל״א עמוד
א. lamed-alef amud alef. Okay, it'll go quicker, but we only have
about 22 minutes. Let's see how far we can go. I'm sure
if I just read it and don't explain it, we'll get caught
up. Okay, שלושה אחים. Shlosha Achim. This most of this will be
pretty straightforward. Ha ha. שלושה אחים, שנים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות, Shlosha
Achim, shnayim me-hem nesuim shtei achayot, three brothers, two married to two
sisters, like our classic case, ואחד נשוי נכרית, ve-echad nasui nachris, and
one is married to an unrelated woman. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות, Met
echad mi-ba'alei ha-achayot, so these are going to be all different, these
are going to be all different permutations of the of this case.
Okay, you've got ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon married again to our
רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, and you've got לוי Levi here married
to דבורה, Dvorah, okay, not related. Okay, and the whole question is
going to be who is going to die and who is going
to marry whom and in what order? Okay, so let's go through
this. Okay, מת אחד מבעלי האחיות, Met echad mi-ba'alei ha-achayot, one of
the ones married to the sister dies, שמעון Shimon died, וכנס נשוי
נכרית את אשתו, ve-kanas nesui nachris et ishto, okay, so ראובן Reuven
died, לאה Leah did יבום, yibum, וכנס נשוי נכרית את אשתו, ve-kanas
nesui nachris et ishto, ומת, u-met, and then לוי Levi died. הראשונה,
Ha-rishona, the first woman, רחל, Rachel, she was the one that first
became the widow, okay, הראשונה, ha-rishona, so now you tell me, שמעון
Shimon here has רחל Rachel and דבורה. Dvorah. רחל Rachel is his
wife's sister, right? דבורה Dvorah נכרית. nachris. Okay, but this is an
ערוה erva and this is צרת הערוה, tzoras ha-erva, right, cause they
were both married to לוי Levi at this stage. So that's what
the משנה mishnah says. הראשונה יוצאת משום אחות אשה, Ha-rishona yotzei mi-shum
achot isha, רחל Rachel walks away because of his wife's sister, והשנייה
ve-shniya and דבורה Dvorah walks away משום צרתה. mi-shum tzorata. עשה בה
מאמר ומת, Asa ba ma'amar u-met, now if שמעון Shimon went ahead
and, I'm sorry, if לוי Levi instead of doing יבום yibum did
מאמר, ma'amar, back to that, and then he died, now we're dealing
with בית הלל, Beit Hillel, not בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, so רחל
Rachel isn't really his what, it's, well, רחל Rachel is his wife's
sister, but she's only an ערוה erva in the יבום yibum category
cause she's sort of quasi-married to לוי, Levi, right? Right? So so
this only sort of affect is going to affect דבורה׳ס Dvorah's status
because she's quasi-married to לוי. Levi. So דבורה Dvorah is not really
צרת ערוה, tzoras erva, דבורה Dvorah is sort of צרת quasi-ערוה. tzoras
erva. Okay, I gotta stop thinking בית שמאי Beit Shammai now. No
longer בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Okay, so in that case, ומת, נכרית
חולצת ולא מתיבמת. u-met, nachris choletzet ve-lo mityabemet. So so רחל Rachel
obviously walks away because if she were fully married to לוי Levi
she'd be an ערוה, erva. so she's quasi-married, she she's an ערוה,
erva, she walks away, but דבורה Dvorah needs חליצה, chalitza, can't have
יבום yibum because rabbinically she's a צרת quasi-ערוה. tzoras erva Okay, but
at least but at least does need חליצה chalitza because because רחל
Rachel was not really married to לוי. Levi. A דרבנן d'rabbanan חליצה
chalitza as it were? Yeah. So טעמא דעבד בה מאמר, Ta'ama de-avad
ba ma'amar, so the only reason says the גמרא gemara that שמעון
Shimon has to, that the, you know, that דבורה Dvorah is in
a problematic status is because לוי Levi did מאמר ma'amar and made
רחל Rachel his quasi-wife, okay, and that now makes דבורה Dvorah quasi-צרת
tzoras ערוה. erva, הא לא עבד בה מאמר, נכרית יבומי נמי מיבמת.
Ha lo avad ba ma'amar, nachris yivumei nami miyammat. If he had
not done מאמר, ma'amar, the implication of the משנה mishnah is, ראובן
Reuven dies, okay, לוי Levi did nothing and then לוי Levi died.
So שמעון Shimon here, obviously he's nothing but רחל Rachel because it's
his wife's sister, but he could go ahead and do יבום yibum
with דבורה. Dvorah. Why not? That's the implication of the משנה. mishnah.
If there was no מאמר, ma'amar, there'd be no relationship here and
he'd be free to do יבום yibum with דבורה. Dvorah. So the
גמרא gemara says, so what does that show you? אמר רב נחמן
זאת אומרת אין זיקה ואפילו בחד אחא. Amar Rav Nachman: Zot omeret,
ein zika ve-afillu be-chad acha. There's no זיקה zika even with one
brother, as opposed to before we were all talking about אחות זקוקתו
achot zikukato or whatever. He's saying this משנה mishnah at least holds
there's no זיקה. zika. Why? Because לוי Levi might not have done
מאמר ma'amar with רחל, Rachel, but guess what he has with רחל?
Rachel? A זיקה, zika, right? Even if he did nothing, he had
a זיקה. zika. So after לוי Levi died and שמעון Shimon didn't
have a זיקה, zika, right? Because it was his wife's sister. So
there was only one relevant brother that could do יבום, yibum, there
was one brother and there was a זיקה, zika, then he died.
Why doesn't שמעון Shimon say, oh, we're back to being a type
of a צרת tzoras ערוה erva. because רחל Rachel was a quasi-wife
based on the זיקה? zika? We don't say that. So you see
that the זיקה zika is not meaningful and אין זיקה. ein zika.
Okay, and therefore if he didn't do יבום, yibum, רחל Rachel is
irrelevant, and if he didn't do מאמר, ma'amar, רחל Rachel is irrelevant
and he can go ahead and do יבום yibum with דבורה. Dvorah.
All right, we're going to reassess that later, but that's what we're
saying now. Next משנה: mishnah: שלושה אחים, Shlosha Achim, same case except
different order of dying and יבום. yibum. שלושה אחים, shlosha achim, שנים
מהם נשואים שתי אחיות, shnayim mehem nesuyim shtei achayot, two married to
two sisters, ואחד מהם נשוי נכרית, ve'echad mehem nasui nochrit, מת נשוי
נכרית. met nasui nochrit. Now what happened is, not that ראובן Reuven
dies first, but לוי Levi dies first. Okay? So step number one
is that לוי Levi dies. מת נשוי נכרית. met nasui nochrit. וכנס
אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו. vechanas echad miba'alei ha'achayot et ishto. And
then step number two is here, ראובן Reuven right, he's married to
רחל. Rachel. Now he also does יבום yibum with דבורה. Devorah. Okay,
that's step number two. Then guess what's going to happen to ראובן?
Reuven? Okay, מת met מבעלי האחיות את אשתו miba'alei ha'achayot et ishto
ומת. umet. And then ראובן Reuven dies. Okay, so now we've got
שמעון Shimon again. Now we've got שמעון Shimon with with two wives,
right, with one is ערווה erva and one is צרת ערווה. tzarat
erva. So that's the same הלכה. halacha. Okay, so in that case,
ומת הראשונה יוצאה משום אחות אשה umet harishona yotzei mishum achot isha
והשנייה משום צרתה פטורה. vehashniya mishum tzarata ptura. עשה בה מאמר ומת.
asa ba maamar umet. Let's say instead of doing יבום, yibum, he
had done מאמר maamar with דבורה Devorah and then he died. So
what's the הלכה? halacha? נכרית חולצת ולא מתייבמת. nochrit choletzet velo mityabemet.
Same story that she does חליצה chalitza not יבום. yibum. Now this
is like the flip, right? Case number one was that he had
done מאמר maamar with, that you know, לוי Levi had done מאמר
maamar with רחל. Rachel. So רחל Rachel was sort of like the,
was the ערווה erva who was quasi the wife, who was the
quasi wife, right? That was the case, right? And לאה Leah was
the צרה. tzara. Okay? In this case, A and B, in this
case, the מאמר maamar was with דבורה. Devorah. Right? And then he
died. So in this case, right, the ערווה erva is the wife,
right, the real wife here is רחל Rachel and that's the real
ערווה. erva. The ערווה erva is the wife and דבורה Devorah is
the quasi צרת ערווה. tzarat erva. You got that? Okay. So that's
the flip of the other case. Okay? Here the ערווה erva is
the actual relationship, רחל Rachel walks away, and she's like the quasi
צרת ערווה, tzarat erva, but according מדאורייתא mide'oraita though, right, שמעון Shimon
would have to do יבום yibum with דבורה Devorah because מדאורייתא mide'oraita
when לוי Levi died, שמעון Shimon also could have done יבום yibum
with דבורה. Devorah. And that doesn't go away. So even though now
he's done מאמר maamar okay and made her a quasi צרת ערווה,
tzarat erva, right, שמעון Shimon still needs to do חליצה chalitza to
get דבורה Devorah to free דבורה. Devorah. Okay? So in this case
though, this case was a quasi, the ערווה erva was the quasi
wife, here the ערווה erva is the definite wife and she's the
צרה tzara is the quasi צרת ערווה. tzarat erva. So the גמרא
Gemara says, הא תו למה לי? ha tu lama li? Why do
I need the second case? היינו הך, hainu hach, it's essentially the
same, that the מאמר maamar sort of pulls the other woman into
the picture and then it's not דאורייתא de'oraita so you still need
to do חליצה. chalitza. So the גמרא Gemara says, השתא, hashta, not
only is it the same, it's like a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
ומה התם דאחות אשה הויא צרה לנכרית, uma hatam de'achot isha havya
tzara lenochrit, when the, when the wife's sister was the צרה tzara
to the real wife, right, in the first case, the real wife
was דבורה, Devorah, the wife's sister was she was quasi married, that
was the one that was being connected through the מאמר. maamar. And
nevertheless that was enough to problematize יבום yibum with דבורה. Devorah. ומה
התם דאחות אשה הויא צרה לנכרית, uma hatam de'achot isha havya tzara
lenochrit, and אחות אשה achot isha was the one that through the
מאמר maamar got connected to דבורה Devorah where there was a real
obligation of יבום. yibum. And nevertheless, ואמרת נכרית אסורה, ve'amarta nochrit asura,
and nevertheless you have to do חליצה chalitza with דבורה Devorah even
though that was the real obligation and the ערווה erva was only
quasi brought in. הכא hacha here the real wife is רחל, Rachel,
so it starts with being fundamentally problematic. הכא דנכרית הויא צרה לאחות
אשה, hacha denochrit havya tzara le'achot isha, the wife's sister, the ערווה,
erva, is the real wife, and it's דבורה Devorah that's being quasi
pulled in. לא כל שכן, lo kol sheken, how much more so
are you not going to be able to do יבום yibum with
דבורה Devorah and going to have to do חליצה. chalitza. So the
second case, it's the same הלכה halacha and if anything it's more
obvious than the first משנה. mishna. Okay? Because here the basic obligation
to דבורה Devorah was—דבורה Devorah wasn't even the real wife. So the
גמרא Gemara says, תנא הכא תנא ברישא. tana hacha tana bereisha. You
know what? You're right. This second משנה mishna is much more obvious.
And therefore this משנה mishna was the first משנה mishna that was
taught when these הלכות halachot were learned. והא חזיא ליה ושרייא. veha
chazya lei vesharya. And he actually initially actually there was a thinking
that the, I'm sorry, תנא הכא תנא ברישא. tana hacha tana bereisha.
No, first he taught the one above, right? And then, wait a
minute, I'm sorry, no, no, I was right the first time. Okay,
first he taught this one, the one where דבורה Devorah is only
being brought in in a quasi way, in a quasi way. And
this is the one that's more obvious that she's going to need—
chalitza that you’re not going to be able to do ייבום *yibbum*.
והך חזי להיתירא ושריא *Vehach chazi lehetera vesharia*, and he actually initially
the תנא *Tana* thought that the first משנה mishna *Mishna* would be
allowed, in the first משנה mishna *Mishna* where דבורה *Devorah* was the
real wife, and רחל *Rachel* was the one that was quasi brought
in, he figured well look, if דבורה *Devorah*’s the real wife, well
maybe we should even allow you to do ייבום *yibbum*, since רחל
*Rachel* is being brought in through this מאמר *ma'amar*, and the real
obligation is with דבורה *Devorah*. So he maybe even thought that in
the first משנה mishna, *Mishna* to allow ייבום *yibbum*. Okay, והדר חזי
לאיסורא *Vahadar chazi le'issura*. And then he thought no, we should actually
make that case forbidden as well. Okay. So really you’re right, the
first one is the second משנה mishna. *Mishna*’s much more obvious, the
first משנה mishna. *Mishna* was like a later move to make even
that case forbidden. ואיידי דחביבא ליה אקדמה *Ve'idi dechaviva lei akdama*. And
because that second משנה mishna. *Mishna* was like a dear to him,
the author, because he realized like oh, this is a חידוש chiddush?
*chiddush*, we're even going to make this case forbidden. So he said
it first. ומשנה לא זזה ממקומה *Umishneh lo zaz mimkomah*, but then
he didn’t take out the second משנה *Mishna* even though the second
משנה *Mishna* now became superfluous and obvious. Okay. So it’s basically saying
you’re right, the first one is more obvious, but the first one,
I’m sorry, the, once you say the first one the second one
is obvious, but nevertheless we taught both. The first one actually was
the next move, the bigger חידוש chiddush? *chiddush*. By the way, תוספות
*Tosafot* just says why would, why was it so very complicated, why
don’t you just say what you normally say, which is you know,
זו ואין צריך לומר זו *zu ve'ein tzarich lomar zu*. X and
it goes without saying, you know, the next one. תוספות *Tosafot* says
that you can say if you throw in two extra words or
an extra line in order to, which is really superfluous, you could
say it goes without saying this other case. Here you have a
whole extra משנה *Mishna*, you’ve redescribed the whole scenario, so you’re not
going to just say that that was done like you know just,
and by the way it goes without saying. So we have this
whole explanation that it was a move to go from one to
the other. Okay, but now we're saying whether the זיקה *zika* brings
in the, whether the basic obligation is here, the basic obligation is
to דבורה *Devorah*, okay, and the מאמר *ma'amar* that brings in a
quasi ערווה *ervah*, there you really could have thought who cares the
basic obligation is to דבורה *Devorah* do ייבום *yibbum*, nevertheless we say
even in this case do חליצה *chalitza*, and then it goes without
saying when the basic obligation was to the, when the wife was
basically the ערווה *ervah*, so it started out without any ייבום *yibbum*
and דבורה *Devorah* was brought in this quasi way that there’s not
going to be ייבום *yibbum* with דבורה *Devorah* there’s only going to
be חליצה *chalitza*. Okay. Next משנה *Mishna*. Third scenario. שלושה אחים *Sheloshah
achin*. שניים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות ואחד נשוי נכרית *Shenayim meihem nesuyim
shetei achayot ve'echad nasui nachrit*. Same start off. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות
וכנס נשוי נכרית את אשתו *Met echad miba'alei ha'achayot vechanas nasui nachrit
et ishto*. So sounds like we said before, what else is like
it that can be done? We’ve had the one married to דבורה
*Devorah* dying and we’ve had the one married to רחל *Rachel* dying.
The one married to לאה *Leah* is just for, is just the
parallel of the one married to רחל *Rachel*. What's the other possibility?
So the other possibility is not who gets married, but who then
dies after the marriage. Okay. So. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות *Met echad
miba'alei ha'achayot*, ראובן *Reuven* dies. Then לוי *Levi* of course does ייבום
*yibbum* because he's the only one that can do ייבום *yibbum* here.
But then instead of לוי *Levi* dying, here's what happens. וכנס נשוי
נכרית את אשתו ומתה אשתו של שני *Vechanas nasui nachrit et ishto
umetah ishto shel sheni*. Okay, ואחר כך מת נשוי נכרית *ve'achar kach
met nasui nachrit*. Then לאה *Leah* dies. Okay? So this happened: 1
ראובן *Reuven* dies, 2 ייבום *yibbum*, 3 לאה *Leah* dies, and now
finally okay what's going to happen? And now... did I get that
right? I don't think so. No. שמעון *Shimon* didn't die and there's
nothing left to happen. Excuse me. Excuse me. Then there's nothing left
to happen. Then לוי *Levi* dies. Right. Then לוי *Levi* dies. Okay.
Thank you. Then לוי *Levi* dies. So now שמעון *Shimon* has רחל
*Rachel* and דבורה *Devorah* before him. Okay. Is רחל *Rachel* אחות אשתו
achos ishto *achot ishto*? No, he’s, right, לאה *Leah* has died. If
he only divorced לאה *Leah*, right, it would be because אחות אשתו
achos ishto, *achot ishto*’s even while she’s divorced or whatever, but we'll
talk about that, but, okay, I mean, but right now לאה *Leah*
has died. So רחל *Rachel*’s no longer אחות אשתו achos ishto, *achot
ishto*. And now when רחל *Rachel* and דבורה *Devorah* fall before him,
there’s no ערווה *ervah* anymore because לאה *Leah* had died before that
event occurred. Okay, so in that case, so נשוי נכרית ומת נשוי
נכרית *nasui nachrit umet nasui nachrit*, right, and then לוי *Levi* dies.
הרי זו אסורה assurah, עליו עולמית הואיל ונתאסרה עליו שעת אחת *Harei
zu asurah alav olamit ho'il vene'esrah alav sha'at achat*. So what the
משנה *Mishna* says actually is not that way, that actually that, that
רחל *Rachel* remains forbidden to him עולמית *olamit* because she was אסורה
עליו שעת אחת *asurah alav sha'at achat*. What was the שעת אחת
*sha'at achat*? The שעת אחת *sha'at achat* was that ראובן *Reuven* died,
at that stage לאה *Leah* hadn't died yet, right? So רחל *Rachel*
became here at stage one אחות אשתו achos ishto *achot ishto*. So
then even though by stage three she stopped being אחות אשתו, achos
ishto and that by stage four now there's a מצוה יבום, mitzvah
yibbum, that status of אחות אשתו achos ishto that happened at stage
one still remains. Alright? Yes, have I lost everybody by now? Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב:
Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: כל יבמה שאינה נקראת בה בשעת נפילה
יבמה יבוא עליה הרי היא כאשת אח שיש לה בנים ואסורה. Kol
yevama she'einah nikre'et ba be-sha'at nefilah yevamah yavo aleiha, harei hi ke-eshet
ach she-yesh lah banim ve-asurah. Any sister-in-law that was not able to
do יבום yibbum at the time that she became a widow, then
she then she remains a brother's wife, an ערוה ervah of אשת
אח, eshet ach, and she remains forbidden. Okay, which basically is this
case. Reuven died, he couldn't do יבום yibbum at this moment, she's
אחות אשתו, okay, so even though that status is going to change
and Leah is going to die later on, alright, nevertheless she is
going to remain forbidden. You know why? Because even if she doesn't
remain אחות אשתו, the moment that he, Reuven, died and he couldn't
do יבום, yibbum, she became not only אחות אשתו but what else
did she become? She became another ערוה. ervah. If you can't do
יבום, yibbum, what does she become? An אשת אחיו, eshet achis, right?
So if at the act, the moment of this death, you know,
that's בשעת מיתה be-sha'at mitah you cannot say יבמה יבוא עליה, yevamah
yavo aleiha, then what this to add to whatever ערוה ervah status
is, she also becomes אשת אחיו, eshet achiv, right? Because that's what
she is, brother's wife without a מצוה יבום. mitzvah yibbum. So then
even when the אחות אשתו goes away because Leah dies, she's going
to remain forbidden as dead brother's wife. Yes? Sort of? You are
going to be tested on this tomorrow. Okay. So, okay, so, הרי
היא כאשת אח שיש לה בנים. harei hi ke-eshet ach she-yesh lah
banim. Once she was forbidden, she remains like a brother's wife with
children, meaning a brother's wife for whom there was no מצוה יבום,
mitzvah yibbum, ואסורה ve-asurah and she remains forbidden even when she stops
being the wife's sister. So מאי קא משמע לן? mai kamashma lan?
Why is that a חידוש? תנינא, tenina, that's what our משנה says.
הרי זו אסורה עליו לעולם הואיל וניאסרה עליו שעה אחת. Harei zu
asurah alav le-olam ho'il ve-ne'esrah alav sha'ah achat. It's exactly what our
משנה says, that even when she stops being wife's sister, she continues
to be forbidden to Shimon. So the גמרא Gemara says, מה? mah?
I might have thought Rav Rav Yehuda Rava is taking it one
step further. מהו דתימא הני מילי היכא דלא חזיא ליה בנפילה ראשונה.
Mahu de-teima hani mili heicha de-lo chazei leh bi-nefilah rishonah. That is,
in this case, in the case in the משנה, she remained אשת
אחיו eshet achiv the entire period while she was while she had
the status of being a יבמה yevama
and then Levi did יבום yibbum to her, right?
But her status vis-a-vis Shimon did not change the entire time that
she was free, it only came after she was married to Levi.
So that's a more like enduring status where his when he had
her יבום, yibbum, he could have had a יבום yibbum relationship to
her, she was always אחות אשתו and then she got married to
Levi. And her status only changed later, Leah only died later. So
that's one thing to say that if she in that entire period
she was אסורה, she always remains forbidden.
That's the משנה.
אבל היכא דחזיא ליה בנפילה ראשונה אימא תשתרי קא משמע לן. Aval
heicha de-chazei leh bi-nefilah rishonah eima tishri kamashma lan. Let's say you
had a different case. Let's say you had that Reuven died and
then before Levi did יבום, yibbum, Leah died. Okay? Right? What if
Reuven died and then before Levi did יבום, yibbum, nothing happened yet,
Reuven died and then Leah died? Okay? So then while she was
in a potential יבום yibbum relationship with Shimon, right? Because nobody had
enacted yet on her יבום yibbum status, her status changed. She stopped
being his wife's sister. Maybe that would allow us to reassess if
a change of status occurred before while she was still in that
first period. And that's what Rav is saying that it does not.
It all goes by the moment of death. Okay. So גמרא Gemara
says, הא נמי תנינא, ha nami tenina, but that's also something we
teach in a משנה. שני אחים נשואים שתי אחיות, Shnei achim nesuyim
shtei achayot, two brothers married to two sisters. מת אחד מהם ואחר
כך מתה אשתו של שני. Met ech me-hem ve-achar kach meta ishto
shel sheni. One died, okay, Reuven died and so now you have
Rachel, who is Shimon's wife's sister, can't do יבום. yibbum. And then
what happens? Nobody's done anything, obviously, there's only one brother, there's only
Shimon. Okay, he can't do anything. And then ואחר כך מתה אשתו
של שני, ve-achar kach meta ishto shel sheni, and then Leah dies.
So now Rachel stops being his wife's sister. Okay? Maybe do יבום?
yibbum? No. הרי זו אסורה עליו לעולם הואיל וניאסרה עליו שעה אחת.
Harei zu asurah alav le-olam ho'il ve-ne'esrah alav sha'ah achat. Exact same
הלכה. halacha. So here's a case where her status changes before יבום
yibbum is done and it doesn't matter. So what why is Rav
a חידוש? That's a משנה. It says no, that's a little different.
התם הוא דאידחי לה מהאי ביתא לגמרי.
Hatam hu
de-idchi lah me-hai beita le-gamrei.
That case where there's only one brother, Reuven dies and it's Shimon's
wife's sister and he can't do anything, there's nobody around that could
do יבום. yibbum. So we might say Shimon can't do יבום, yibbum,
no other brother... There's end of story. She's אסור *assur* period, we've
finished the whole process. אבל הכא לא אידחי ליה מהאי ביתא לגמרי
*Aval hacha lo itchilei me'hai bayis legamrei* here, when ראובן *Reuven* dies,
it's not the end of the story with רחל *Rachel*, because רחל
*Rachel* could still have יבום *yibum* with לוי *Levi*. So she's still
in process. We're still figuring out what her status is going to
be. It's not the end of the story. If there's only שמעון
*Shimon* and שמעון *Shimon* can't do יבום *yibum* with her, we're done.
Here we're not done. She still is waiting for יבום *yibum* or
חליצה *chalitzah* with לוי *Levi*. So since we're not done, maybe her
status changes, maybe she'll be permissible even to שמעון *Shimon*. Okay, אבל
הכא דלא אידחי ליה מהאי ביתא לגמרי אימא מיגו דחזיא להאי גיסא
נכרית חזיא נמי להאי *Aval hacha d'lo itchilei me'hai bayis legamrei, eima
migo de'chazyei le'hai nisa nochris chazyei nami lehai*. Maybe now the same
way she's permissible to לוי *Levi*, now maybe that שמעון *Shimon*'s wife
died, maybe she'll become permissible to שמעון *Shimon*. קמשמע לן *Kamashmalan* that
we don't say that, that it all goes by the moment of
death, and the reason is for what I said, that since when
ראובן *Reuven* dies, she's אסור *assur* to שמעון *Shimon* because אחות אשתו
*achos ishto*, she also becomes אסור *assur* as אשת אחיו *eshes achiv*.
And that even when אחות אשתו *achos ishto* goes away, the dead
brother's wife's איסור *issur* is still going to remain. That's not going
to change. Okay, do we have time to do one more משנה
*mishnah*? I have 8:28, what time do you have? So far, okay,
we have 8:29 now, we'll just read the משנה *mishnah*. Okay, שלושה
אחים שנים הם נשואים שתי אחיות *Shlosha achim, shenayim hem nesu'im shtei
achayot*. Sounds familiar. ואחד נשוי נכרית *Ve'echad nasu nochris*. Now, no death.
Divorce. גירש אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו *Geirash echad miba'alei ha'achayot et
ishto*. Okay, so here we go. ראובן *Reuven*, שמעון *Shimon*, married to
רחל *Rachel* and לאה *Leah*. לוי *Levi* is married to דבורה *Devorah*.
Now what happened? גירש אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו *Geirash echad miba'alei
ha'achayot et ishto*. שמעון *Shimon* now divorces לאה *Leah*. Okay, okay, so
לאה *Leah* didn't die,
he divorced לאה *Leah*. ומת נשוי
נכרית *U'meis nasu nochris*, and now לוי *Levi* dies. וכנסה המגרש *Vikinsah
hamgaresh*, and now שמעון *Shimon* can go ahead and marry and do
יבום *yibum* with דבורה *Devorah*. Okay, because this is why? Because this
is not, she's not אחות אשתו *achos ishto*, she's אחות *achos* of
his ex-wife. Okay, it's interesting. If she was אחות אשתו *achos ishto*,
wait, אחות אשתו *achos ishto* is אסור *assur* as long as the
woman is alive. Right, it's only בחייה *bechayeya*. Right, I'm sorry, right.
So that wouldn't matter, thank you, thank you, okay. So he goes
ahead and does יבום *yibum* with דבורה *Devorah*, which is totally fine.
Okay, thank you, right. וכנסה המגרש ומת *Vikinsah hamgaresh u'meis*, and then
שמעון *Shimon* dies. Okay, so now, okay, so now is there any
problem for ראובן *Reuven* to do יבום *yibum* with דבורה *Devorah*? No,
it's שמעון *Shimon*'s ex-wife, unrelated, and he has no מצוה *mitzvah* of
יבום *yibum* with לאה *Leah* because they got divorced. So there's no
ערווה *ervah* there. I mean, there's
an ערווה *ervah* where he can't
marry לאה *Leah*, but she's not
in the category of יבום *yibum* because they were divorced. So since
she's out of יבום *yibum*, right, so since she's out of יבום
*yibum*, his only relationship is with דבורה *Devorah*, and he can go
ahead and do יבום *yibum* with דבורה *Devorah*. Right, זו היא שאמרו
*Zu hi she'amru*, so ומת זו היא שאמרו כולן שמתו או נתגרשו
צרותיהן מותרות *u'meis, zu hi she'amru kulan shemeisu o nitgarshtu tzaroseihen mutaros*.
So if they die, we won't worry about the die right now,
that was sort of some of the cases before, but anyway if
they got divorced, right, if לאה *Leah* had died, right, then also
she'd be out of the picture and he could do יבום *yibum*
with דבורה *Devorah*. Or if she was divorced, now he can go
ahead and do יבום *yibum* with דבורה *Devorah*. She's out of the
picture, she's not part of the יבום *yibum* equation. Okay, to see
more about this tomorrow.