All right בוקר טוב. boqer tov. Today's דף, daf, well officially it's
נח, nun-chet, but we're a דף daf behind, so we will do
נז, nun-zayin, we'll see if we can get up to נח. nun-chet.
We pick up at the bottom of נו עמוד ב nun-vav amud
bet at the משנה. mishna. So let's take a look.
And we have just done with very significant גמרות, gemaras, particularly around
one the halachic definition of the act of sex, but also significantly
questions about the status of a wife of a כהן kohen who
is raped and is forbidden to her husband, also a very הלכה
halacha that has a lot of very tragic consequences. And yeah, and
that different ways in which הלכה halacha tries to sort of deal
with it and find workarounds to that, which didn't come up in
the דף. daf. But anyway, now we pick up on the next
משנה, mishna, also staying within the issue of כהן. kohen. Let's take
a look. And now we're really into the part of יבמות, yevamos,
as you've probably already sensed, that deals with issues of personal status.
נתאלמנה לכהן גדול גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט, nis'almanah le-kohen gadol grushah ve-chalutzah
le-kohen hedyot,
so things that we know are situations that we know are forbidden
in terms of having sex with a כהן. kohen. So a woman
having sex with a כהן, kohen, so you have a אלמנה, almanah,
a widow with a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, doesn't happen too often,
but it presents an interesting case in הלכה. halacha. Or a גרושה
grushah or a חלוצה chalutzah with a normal
כהן. kohen. מן האירוסין לא יאכלו בתרומה. min ha-erusin lo yokhelu bi-trumah.
If it's only אירוסין, erusin, right the whole איסור issur is transgressed
when it's נישואין, nisuin, when actually they have, you know, actually gone
under the חופה chuppah and then eventually and then have sex. So
then they actually transgress. Now in that act of forbidden sex what
happens is, is that the woman besides transgressing the negative prohibition, through
a forbidden act of sex with a כהן, kohen, the woman also
becomes a חללה. chalalah. Now who cares that she's a חללה, chalalah,
she's already forbidden to a כהן. kohen. Well for the אלמנה almanah
to a כהן גדול kohen gadol it's relevant, because then she's lost
to a normal כהן. kohen. Even for the גרושה grushah and חלוצה
chalutzah to a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot it's relevant because in that
status if she was a בת כהן, bas kohen, a daughter of
a כהן, kohen, she could eat תרומה trumah if her husband then
dies. Then she goes back to her, to her father's house assuming
she has no kids or whatever. But if she becomes a חללה,
chalalah, similarly the way a כהן kohen who is a חלל chalal
loses his קדושת כהונה, kedushas kehunah, if she becomes a חללה, chalalah,
she also gets disqualified even from eating תרומה trumah from her father's
house, even if she's a בת כהן. bas kohen. Okay, so all
of that happens after the act of sex. But if it's מן
האירוסין לא יאכלו, min ha-erusin lo yokhelu, so that's if it was
after נישואין. nisuin. But מן האירוסין, min ha-erusin, how about if it's
just אירוסין erusin and it's not yet נישואין? nisuin? Nevertheless says the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that we're going to find out in the
גמרא gemara is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, לא יאכלו בתרומה. lo yokhelu
bi-trumah. We since אירוסין erusin is just one step away from נישואין,
nisuin, why else do you have אירוסין erusin unless you're planning on
going to the חופה chuppah eventually and doing נישואין? nisuin? It's like
they've already had sex and therefore she, it's like she's already become
a חללה, chalalah, at least rabbinically, and therefore she cannot eat תרומה.
trumah. That is what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. ורבי אליעזר ורבי
שמעון מכשירין. ve-Rabbi Eliezer ve-Rabbi Shimon makhshirin. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allow it. Now
what is not clear because it's only אירוסין erusin it's not yet
נישואין. nisuin. Now what's not clear from the גמרא gemara and these
two opinions in רש"י, Rashi, it's a debate of רש"י Rashi and
תוספות, Tosafos, is are we talking about a ישראלית yisraelis who is
married to a כהן? kohen?
And then the question is, if it's a legitimate marriage she's entitled
to eat in תרומה trumah and the question is, would this entitle
her to eat in תרומה? trumah? That's one way of understanding this
case. That it is about a ישראלית yisraelis married to a כהן.
kohen. The problem with that is is that a normal ישראלית yisraelis
who is married to a כהן kohen she can only eat in
תרומה trumah after נישואין. nisuin. So how could anybody say מן האירוסין
min ha-erusin you could eat the תרומה? trumah? There's a double problem.
Number one it's only אירוסין erusin and normally you need to be
נישואין nisuin before you can eat in תרומה. trumah. And number two
is it's אירוסין erusin that is leading up to a איסור ביאה
issur biah to a case, to something problematic. So how could anybody
in that case say that you can eat in תרומה? trumah? Okay,
so that's difficulties. I'm not רש"י, Rashi, nevertheless defends that read. I'm
not going to
get into, I'm not going to
spell that
out, okay, but you should understand that
one possible read here though we're talking about a ישראלית. yisraelis. We're
going to bracket that because that obviously raises a lot of questions.
We're going to talk about a more simple, simpler, it's none of
this simple, but we're going to talk about the simpler approach here,
which is we're talking about a בת כהן bas kohen who is
married to a כהן. kohen. Okay, and therefore she's already entitled to
eat תרומה trumah because she's a daughter of a כהן kohen and
she's eating her father's תרומה. trumah. So therefore the question is not
what entitles her but can there be something that disqualifies her? So
therefore that's the issue. So says רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir yes, if
she has קידושין kiddushin to a כהן kohen she's now disqualified because
we look at that as that they're about to have sex, I
mean when they have the נישואין nisuin they'll have sex, that's what's
coming around the corner, and therefore once she has sex with a
כהן kohen and she's
a
גרושה. grushah. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say no, she until now
was eating תרומה terumah by virtue of her father, even though she
now has קידושין kiddushin to a כהן, kohen, and if that would
eventually translate into נישואין nissuin and into marriage and into sex, then
she would be disqualified. Right now they have not yet had sex,
it's only קידושין, kiddushin, it's not yet חופה, chuppah, it's not yet
נישואין, nissuin, it's not yet sex, and therefore she can continue to
eat תרומה terumah by virtue of her father.
Does the husband status? What? The כהן גדול? kohen gadol?
Yeah, the כהן kohen status doesn't change, it's only hers. Yeah, yeah,
yeah, exactly. So okay, so תרומה terumah is not a punishment, it's
a question about how your status has impacted. Okay, so again, we're
going to read this case like the first approach of רש"י, Rashi,
like the position of תוספות, Tosafot, that we're talking about a בת
כהן bat kohen who's entitled to eat תרומה, terumah, but does the
fact that she's now in a relationship that if it gets to
the next stage will make her a חללה, chalala, is she still
entitled to eat תרומה terumah as a result? And רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says no, we look at it as if they're about to
have sex, and therefore she's a חללה, chalala, she can't eat תרומה,
terumah, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say
she can still eat תרומה terumah by virtue not of her husband
but by virtue of her father. נתאלמנה או נתגרשה מן הנישואין פסולה
מן התרומה. Nis'almanah o nisgareshah min hanissuin pesulah min haterumah.
Now let's say they became an אלמנה almanah or גרושה grusha after
נישואין. nissuin. They actually, this actually,
this relationship became one of נישואין, nissuin, not just אירוסין. erusin. They
actually went to the חופה. chuppah. Okay, then she really did become
a חללה. chalala. Then even if now her husband divorces her or
dies, now she really is invalidated. Once she's gone into the חופה,
chuppah, then it doesn't matter if the husband drops dead the next
minute. Once they've actually had sex, we'll discuss in the גמרא Gemara
what if they've had חופה chuppah without sex, but once they've actually
been in the חופה chuppah in the context of having sex, have
had sex and so on, then she fully is a חללה. chalala.
And then even if her husband drops dead, she remains a חללה
chalala and she can't eat תרומה. terumah. Everybody agrees to that. מן
האירוסין כשרות. min ha'erusin kesherot. However, if his husband drops dead during
אירוסין, erusin, they're kosher, and presumably that's even according to רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. Even according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says that
when they're in this קידושין kiddushin relationship, she's פסול pasul because they're
about to be having sex, let's say it never consummated and let's
say he died, the כהן. kohen. Then she goes back to her
acceptable status. Okay, is that sort of clear the cases we're talking
about? Yeah, okay. Question?
Yeah, Dov, what's the question?
Yeah, the question is like
regarding Michael's question. The woman when she becomes a חללה chalala in
any of these scenarios loses her entitlement to תרומה, terumah, but a
man never loses his entitlement to תרומה. terumah.
Well, correct, I mean he could be born a חלל, chalal, but
otherwise he does not. Correct. That has to do with a lot
of
halakhicities about the woman being a little bit more seen as an
object whose status can change and the man less so. So that
is correct.
So even though this man is eating תרומה terumah in his household,
we're not worried he's going to give to his wife who can't
eat the
תרומה? terumah?
Well, yeah, there are rabbinic issues around a concern that he might
feed her תרומה terumah or whatever, but let's not worry about those
right now. Okay, anyway, wow, okay, I've got to get rid of
that other eraser. Junk. Okay, anyway, fine. All right, so let's take
a look. Nice, I just switched it. All right, so תני, Tanni,
ותנא ברייתא. v'tana baraita. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, קל וחומר:
kal v'chomer: ומה קידושי רשות אין מאכילין קידושי עבירה לא כל שכן?
u'mah kiddushei reshut ein ma'achilin, kiddushei averah lo kol sheken?
In the case of קידושי רשות, kiddushei reshut, which is a
ישראל Yisrael who is married to a כהן, kohen, right, to a
בת כהן, bat kohen, so that case she can't eat תרומה terumah
as a result of that. So here where it's קידושי עבירה, kiddushei
averah, what?
Mean אירוסין erusin she still can't eat? אירוסין. erusin.
Well, if a בת כהן bat kohen who's married to ישראל Yisrael
she can never eat תרומה. terumah. Okay, so if it's so in
a case of that case that she's
not allowed to eat תרומה terumah as soon as a בת כהן
bat kohen marries a ישראל, Yisrael, she sort of is out of
her father's category, out of her father's household, and she's already invalidated
of eating תרומה. terumah. So קידושי עבירה לא כל שכן? kiddushei averah
lo kol sheken? This case certainly, look, the fact that she's married
pulls her out of her father's category and the fact that she's
married to a כהן kohen but it's a קידושי עבירה kiddushei averah
should exclude her from eating תרומה. terumah. Okay, so אמרו לו, amru
lo, they said back to him, לא, lo, not necessarily, אם אמרת
בקידושי רשות שכן אין לו להאכיל במקום אחר. im amarta b'kiddushei reshut
sheken ein lo lehachil b'makom acher.
In that case, the ישראל Yisrael never is able to
have anybody eat תרומה terumah on his account. תאמר בקידושי עבירה שכן
יש לו להאכיל במקום אחר? Tomar b'kiddushei averah sheken yesh lo lehachil
b'makom acher?
In the case of קידושי עבירה, kiddushei averah, this כהן kohen if
he was married to another woman, she would eat on his account.
So certainly here, you know, she can eat on his account. Now,
of course, it's not exactly true and this is what gets the
whole thing very complicated because in another case by קידושין. kiddushin. or
you don't yet eat on behalf of the of the כהן, Kohen,
by קידושין, kiddushin, you know, I mean on behalf of the marriage,
you're still, you know, normally it needs to be נישואין, nissuin, not
just קידושין. kiddushin. So anyway, I mean there's whole questions about the
גרסא, girsa, but basically let's just, just to make sure that we're
clear here, okay? So here you have a כהן, Kohen, okay, he's
the dad, okay, and you have a בת כהן, bas Kohen, okay?
So she eats תרומה terumah as a result of her father, okay?
She also happens to be a גרושה grusha from another relationship, let's
say, okay? And then you've got this other כהן Kohen over here,
alright, and they've... how is it that these things so quickly need
to be cracked? Okay, you've got this other כהן Kohen here, okay,
and they have קידושין, kiddushin, okay? So that's the case in the
משנה. Mishnah. So comes along רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, and רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says, look,
she can't eat because she can't... the fact that she has קידושין
kiddushin here, that makes it... if this were to be נישואין, nissuin,
that would be נישואי איסור, nissuay issur, and she would become a
חללה, chalalah, so even in this state she can't eat, and she's
not eating on behalf of her father because this קידושין kiddushin is
sort of פוסל posel her, makes her as if she was a
חללה. chalalah. Comes along, you know, רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon and say, no, it's only קידושין kiddushin yet, it's
not yet נישואין, nissuin, she's not yet a חללה, chalalah, and she
can therefore sort of still eat, but presumably she's like still eating
on account of her father, right? Because this isn't going to be
able to...
if this would become נישואין, nissuin, that would make her a חללה,
chalalah, that would be אסור, assur, but they're saying, okay, it's not
yet נישואין nissuin and she's still eating on account of the father,
to which רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says back to you in the
ברייתא, Baraisa, but I don't understand, in a normal case if this
guy weren't a כהן Kohen but ישראל, Yisrael, the קידושין kiddushin would
pull her away from her father's house.
She can't
eat once she's קידושין kiddushin to another man, she's no longer eating
on account of her father, okay? So it's sort of like this
middle state. Until it's נישואין, nissuin, you don't eat on account of
your husband, but once it's קידושין, kiddushin, you're no longer eating on
account of your father. So רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says, I don't
get it, if this was a ישראל, Yisrael, this would pull her
away from eating on account of her father, so if it's a
כהן Kohen and it's an עבירה, aveirah, it should certainly pull her
away. And the response is an interesting response because the response is
basically no, because the marriage to a כהן Kohen is somehow better
than marriage to ישראל. Yisrael. It's true that this is a marriage
of איסור, issur, and if it would actually consummate it would make
her a חללה, chalalah, but nevertheless, being married to a כהן Kohen
is a better state to be in in terms of eating תרומה
terumah than married to ישראל. Yisrael. So if she were married to
ישראל Yisrael she wouldn't eat, that's true, because then it would pull
her away from her father's house, but married to a כהן, Kohen,
although married in an עבירה aveirah context, is still going to be
enough that it's in this perfect middle zone. She hasn't yet had
sex, so she's not a חללה, chalalah, that's true, and she's married
to a כהן Kohen so she's still within the כהן Kohen realm,
and therefore she can still eat תרומה, terumah, okay? And that's what
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon say back.
The status of being a חללה chalalah never gets reversed, correct?
Right, correct, חללה, chalalah, that would be true, but it hasn't happened
yet. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי אלעזר
אמר רבי אושעיא פצוע דכא כהן שקידש בת ישראל באנו למחלוקת רבי
מאיר ורבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון. Amar Rebbi Elazar amar Rebbi Oshaya, ptzua
daka Kohen shekiddesh bas Yisrael, banu lemachlokes Rebbi Meir veRebbi Eliezer veRebbi
Shimon.
If you have a פצוע דכא, ptzua daka, a כהן Kohen who's
a פצוע דכא, ptzua daka, who has, you know, some crushed testicles
and therefore is not allowed to marry anybody, including... and he marries
a בת... bas... now this גרסא girsa is בת ישראל, bas Yisrael,
which assumes that we're talking here about not the בת כהן bas
Kohen scenario. תוספות Tosafos says that was a wrong גרסא girsa that
רש"י Rashi had, it really is a גרסא girsa of בת כהן.
bas Kohen. So we're going to read it all as בת כהן
bas Kohen and try to somewhat simplify it. So he married a
בת כהן, bas Kohen, okay? So similar case, except rather than her
being the גרושה, grusha, the problem was the other way, the problem
was was that he was here a פצוע דכא. ptzua daka. Okay,
but similarly, if it translates into נישואין nissuin and have sex, he
makes her a חללה. chalalah. So he said it's the same story.
A כהן Kohen married, is he going to pull her away, is
it like they've had sex and invalidate her, or is she still
going to be, no, they haven't had sex yet and it's not
a ישראל, Yisrael, if it was a ישראל Yisrael it would pull
her away, but because it's a כהן, Kohen, it's still within the
כהונה kehunah realm, and she's not yet pulled away from her father's
house, she hasn't had yet sex him... with him to invalidate her,
so everything is still okay. So he says it's the same debate.
So פצוע דכא כהן שקידש בת כהן, Ptzua daka Kohen shekiddesh bas
Kohen, we'll read it, באנו למחלוקת רבי מאיר ורבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון.
banu lemachlokes Rebbi Meir veRebbi Eliezer veRebbi Shimon. דרבי מאיר דאמר משתמרת
לביאת פצוע דאורייתא לא אכלה, DeRebbi Meir de'amar mishtameres levias ptzua de'Oraisa
lo achla, according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir that says that a
woman who is being held, you know, in anticipation of having forbidden
sex that is biblically forbidden, ביאת פצוע דאורייתא, bias ptzua de'Oraisa, because
later we could discuss rabbinically forbidden sex, but this is biblically, so
that's she's about on the cusp of that, that's what's around the
corner, so therefore לא אכלה, lo achla, she can't eat, it's like
she already became a חללה. chalalah. הכא נמי לא אכלה, Hacha nami
lo achla, here too also she can't eat. ורבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון
דאמרי משתמרת לביאת פצוע דאורייתא אכלה, VeRebbi Eliezer veRebbi Shimon de'amri mishtameres
levias ptzua de'Oraisa achla, according to רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and רבי
שמעון Rebbi Shimon that says no,
she can eat because right now she's like in... she's escaped either
problematic category. She's not married to ישראל, Yisrael, and she is married
to a כהן, Kohen, so that keeps her in the כהן Kohen
realm, and she hasn't yet had sex. נימא *nima* says who? דילמא
הכא לא קאמרי רבי אליעזר רבי שמעון התם אלא דיש לו להאכיל
במקום אחר אבל הכא דאין לו להאכיל במקום אחר לא *dilma hacha
lo ka’amri Rabbi Eliezer Rabbi Shimon hatam ela d’yesh lo lehachil b’makom
acher aval hacha d’ein lo lehachil b’makom acher lo*.
No,
they said when the problem was with her, when she was the
גרושה grusha *grushah*, her marriage to the כהן kohen *Kohen* was enough
to keep her within the כהן kohen. *Kohen* realm because this כהן
kohen *Kohen*, if he were married to somebody else, would, you know,
would somebody else would eat on his account. There would be a
marriage that, right, because normally this, if he weren't a פצוע דכא
ptzua daka *ptzua daka*, he was a normal כהן kohen *Kohen*, if
he was married to any other woman, especially if it was נישואין
nisuin *nisuin*, not just קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin*, right, that woman would eat
on his account. So her being married to the כהן kohen *Kohen*
doesn't like pull her away from the תרומה terumah. *trumah* reality because
this type of marriage to a כהן kohen *Kohen* is a type
of כהן Kohen *Kohen* that could normally through him people he's married
to eat on his behalf, even though right now not, and normally
it’s after נישואין nisuin *nisuin*, whatever, I know it's pretty funny the
way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is sort of glossing over certain things.
But at least that would be the case in that scenario.
That’s the case in דיש לו להאכיל במקום אחר *d’yesh lo lehachil
b’makom acher*.
Right, but if he were a פצוע דכא ptzua daka. *ptzua daka*,
ignoring what her status was, he’s a type of a כהן Kohen
*Kohen* that normally nobody can eat on his account because a כהן
Kohen *Kohen* who himself is a פצוע דכא ptzua daka *ptzua daka*
is not allowed to marry basically anyone. Nobody he married would become
a חללה chalala. *chalalah* through the act of sex. Anybody he would
marry would not be ever be able to eat תרומה terumah *trumah*
on his account.
He’s right. No wife would ever be able to eat תרומה terumah
*trumah* on his account. And therefore, it’s like a ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael*.
So the same way we conceded that if she’s married to a
ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael* that pulls her out of the תרומה terumah. *trumah*
realm, married to a כהן Kohen *Kohen* who never could have anybody
eat תרומה terumah *trumah* on her account also pulls her out of
the תרומה terumah *trumah* realm. So you understand there’s two points. One
point is we’re not going to consider it like he already had
sex. She’s not going to be a חללה chalala. *chalalah*. That’s רבי
אליעזר רבי שמעון *Rabbi Eliezer Rabbi Shimon*. That’s fine. We’re not going
to consider like they already had sex. But she’s married to a
guy, but what about the fact that she’s married to this type
of a guy? If she’s married to ישראל Yisrael, *Yisrael* that should
pull her out. No, she’s married to a כהן Kohen *Kohen* she’s
still within the תרומה terumah. *trumah* realm. But what if she’s married
to a כהן Kohen *Kohen* that’s a פצוע דכא ptzua daka. *ptzua
daka*? That should be like married to ישראל Yisrael *Yisrael* and that
should pull her out even if it’s not like they’ve already had
sex, okay? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says דיש לו להאכיל במקום
אחר
אבל הכא
דאין לו להאכיל במקום אחר
לא *d’yesh lo lehachil b’makom acher aval hacha d’ein lo lehachil b’makom
acher lo*. You can have ביאה Biah *bi’ah* with a פצוע דכא
ptzua daka *ptzua daka*. It’s not something that’s impossible. אבל הכא דיש
לו להאכיל במקום אחר אבל הכא דאין לו להאכיל במקום אחר לא
*aval hacha d’yesh lo lehachil b’makom acher aval hacha d’ein lo lehachil
b’makom acher lo*. וכי תימא הכא נמי יש לו להאכיל *v’chei teima
hacha nami yesh lo lehachil*. No, maybe a כהן kohen *Kohen* who’s
a פצוע דכא ptzua daka. *ptzua daka* could have other people eat
on his account, women he’s married to. What’s the case? בבת גרים
gerim, *b’vat gerim*. Let’s say he’s allowed, now he can’t marry a
גיורת giyoret, *giyoret* because a כהן kohen *Kohen* is אסור assur *assur*
in a גיורת giyoret *giyoret*, but how about the child of a
גר ger *ger* or of a גיורת giyores *giyoret*? So we’re going
to see in a minute that that’s a whole debate whether, right,
it says לא יבא פצוע דכא ptzua daka. וכרות שפכה בקהל ה’
*lo yavo ptzua daka u’chrut shofchah b’kehal Hashem*. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* understands that קהל ה’ Kahal Hashem. *Kehal Hashem* is to exclude
a category of גר ger *ger*, כמאן דתנא קהל ה’ Kahal Hashem.
*k’man d’tana Kehal Hashem* is read to mean naturally born Jews. So
what about somebody who’s not him or herself a גר ger. *ger*
but is the child of a גר ger, *ger*? Is that person
allowed to marry a פצוע דכא ptzua daka *ptzua daka*? Is that
פצוע *ptzua* allowed to marry a ממזר mamzer *mamzer* or a ממזרת
*mamzeret*? So let’s say the answer to that is yes, okay, we’re
going to see that’s debated, but let’s say the answer to that
is yes. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says this כהן kohen *Kohen*
if he marries a בת גר bas ger, *bat ger*, so A,
because the woman herself is not a גר ger *ger* he’s allowed
to marry her, but because she’s a בת גר bas ger, *bat
ger* he’s allowed to marry her even though he’s a פצוע דכא
ptzua daka *ptzua daka*, that woman could eat תרומה terumah *trumah* on
his behalf. So therefore this is a כהן kohen *Kohen* who still
somebody can eat תרומה terumah *trumah* on his behalf. So in this
case of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* this woman could still eat תרומה terumah
*trumah* on his behalf. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says וכי תימא
הכא נמי יש לו להאכיל בבת גרים gerim *v’chei teima hacha nami
yesh lo lehachil b’vat gerim*. והא בעיא בעא ליה רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan מרבי אושעיא *v’ha ba’ei ba’ei lei Rabbi Yochanan me'Rabbi Oshaya*. But
this whole statement about כהן פצוע דכא kohen ptzua daka *Kohen ptzua
daka* was a statement of רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya. *Rabbi Oshaya* that
he said it's the same debate. But רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan *Rabbi
Yochanan* himself asked רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya *Rabbi Oshaya* exactly this כהן
kohen, *Kohen* question: can a כהן kohen *Kohen* who is married to
a בת גרים bat gerim. *bat gerim* can the woman eat תרומה
terumah *trumah*? ולא פשט ליה *v'lo pashat lei*. And he didn't have
an answer. So he, so we’re going to see that in a
minute. So therefore why does רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya *Rabbi Oshaya*, who
doesn’t know if a פצוע דכא ptzua daka *ptzua daka* married to
a בת bas? כהן kohen *bat Kohen* can the woman eat, why
does he assume that this is the same case? Maybe the same
way a ישראל Yisrael. *Yisrael* would take this woman away from the
תרומה trumah. *trumah* status, maybe being married to a כהן kohen *Kohen*
who's a פצוע דכא ptzua daka. *ptzua daka* who never can have
any woman married to him eat on his behalf, maybe that also
should pull her out of that status even if we don’t make
her a pseudo-חללה chalala *pseudo-chalalah* like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says איתמר itmar. *itmar*. So here’s some
so
so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says so wait it was said that
the following debate and this might answer our question. אביי Abaye אמר
הואיל ומאכילה בלא ביאה *Abaye amar ho’il u’machilah belo bi’ah*. He can
eat her without having had sex. He can have her eat without
having had sex with her. So what happens if this פצוע דכא
ptzua daka *ptzua daka*... right is basically married to a
so רש״י Rashi says that the case is by the way that
it's not so clear לא ידע lo yada just means to haven't
had sex but רש״י explains that the כהן kohen? was married to
her and then he became a פצוע דכא ptzua daka. later. Okay
so he became
and he didn't have sex with her from the time he became
a פצוע דכא. ptzua daka So the נישואין nisuin was good because
at the time of the נישואין nisuin. he was not a פצוע
דכא ptzua daka and therefore she was a fully אשת כהן eshet
kohen and she was eating תרומה. trumah Now he became a פצוע
דכא. ptzua daka. If he would have sex with her now that
he is a פצוע דכא ptzua daka he would invalidate her make
her into a חללה. chalala. But as long as he hasn't...
it's not about קהל השם kehal Hashem I mean it's
not about קהל השם kehal Hashem anymore. It's about yeah because it's
not just about the act of crush, it's not just about the
act
of קידושין. kidushin Okay he would make her a חללה. Challalah, So
therefore now that he hasn't so that would be if he actually
had sex now that he became but as long as he hasn't
had sex she's not a חללה Challalah, and it's a full marriage
and it's a fully legitimate marriage because it was done when he
was not a פצוע דכא. ptzua daka So now she can eat
תרומה trumah? on his behalf even though he's a פצוע דכא. ptzua
daka. So you can have a case where פצוע דכא ptzua daka.
can be married to a woman eating תרומה trumah, on her behalf
on his behalf. So therefore the fact that he's a פצוע דכא
ptzua daka and his קידושין Kiddushin with this woman doesn't fully pull
her out of the context of eating תרומה. trumah. It's a type
of relationship that in some scenarios she could still be eating תרומה
Terumah on his behalf. One minute. רבא אמר Rava amar הוא מאכילה
בעבדיו ובשפחתו הכנענית. ho machila b'avadav u'v'shifchato haknaanit. רבא Rava gives logical
answer. Nah a פצוע דכא ptzua daka can never have his wife
eat תרומה terumah but his slaves can eat תרומה. terumah? Okay it
doesn't completely redefine his status as a כהן. kohen. So therefore his
slaves can still eat תרומה terumah. and therefore this type of relationship
is still better than a ישראל Yisrael relationship. If she was married
to ישראל it would pull her out. Married to a כהן kohen.
does not pull her out even a כהן kohen פצוע דכא ptzua
daka. because he's still a type of person that other people even
if not wives eat תרומה Terumah on his behalf. אביי אמר כרבא
Abaye amar ke'Rava קנין דאישות מקנין דאישות ילפינן ולא ילפינן קנין דאישות
מקנין דעבדים. kinyan d'ishut mikinyan d'ishut yalfinan v'lo yalfinan kinyan d'ishut mikinyan
d'avadim.
We're looking for a parallel case where somebody who he's married to
eats תרומה Terumah on his behalf not just slaves that he owns.
And therefore that's not relevant for our discussion. So the גמרא Gemara
says ורבא אמר כאביי v'Rava amar k'Abaye שאני התם שכבר אכלה. shani
hatam she'kvar achla.
No because you can't bring a proof from a case where she
was married and then he became a פצוע דכא. ptzua daka, That
doesn't prove that a פצוע דכא ptzua daka, can have somebody eat
on his behalf. That's because they were already married from before he
became a פצוע דכא. ptsuah daka, It's not relevant to the discussion.
ואביי v'Abaye אביי would say back no שכבר אכלה לא אמרינן. she'kvar
achla lo amrinan. No
you can't say that the fact that it happened earlier makes what
you know is what dictates. How do you know that? ואי לא
תימא הכי v'i lo tema hachi
if you say we always go by an earlier status if you
think an earlier status is going to dictate so בת ישראל שנישאת
לכהן ומת תאכל שכבר אכלה? bat Yisrael she'niset l'kohen u'met tochal she'kvar
achla?
How about a בת ישראל bat Yisrael who's married to a כהן
kohen and the כהן Kohen dies? So say oh well she should
continue to eat because she ate when she was married. Obviously we
don't say that. So you see that we don't say that early
status dictates. So even though in this case it's true they were
married when she was when he wasn't a פצוע דכא ptsuah daka,
it's not that
she's only eating on account of that. There must be something still
in the relationship that allows her to eat. Because we never just
say whatever happened earlier remains the case. It still has to be
a legitimate relationship right now. So you see that the fact that
she continues to eat even though he's a פצוע דכא ptsuah daka.
is not just based on the past.
Right it's relevant to the status
even as a פצוע דכא. ptsuah daka. Right it might be true
that they better not have sex now that will change everything. But
it's right now in this current status she's still eating based on
the current status not just on the past status. ורבא v'Rava רבא
Rava would say back no התם פקע קנינו. hatam paka kinyano. Sure
when the כהן Kohen, dies she doesn't continue to eat because then
the whole relationship has severed. He's dead. הכא לא פקע קנינו. hacha
lo paka kinyano. Here the relationship hasn't severed but nevertheless she's still
eating so it's a continuation of the earlier relationship. But she's still
eating based on the earlier relationship she's not eating based on the
current relationship. So you can't tell me you'll get a scenario where
a woman who's married to a פצוע דכא ptsuah daka, eats תרומה
Terumah proves that a פצוע דכא ptsuah daka can be feeding you
know she can be eating on his account even though he's a
פצוע דכא. ptsuah daka. No she's eating on a fact that's a
continuation of a relationship that preceded the fact that he became a
פצוע דכא. ptsuah daka? Okay anyway so we see the issue. The
issue is that you've got this case and in this scenario one
of two things could invalidate it. Number one is the fact that
it's about to be a בעולה beulah should make her like a
חללה. Challalah? That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. But the other
point is that the fact that she's married to this guy should
pull her away from her father's house. Normally she could only eat
when it's על ידי נישואין. alei yedei nisuin. And here there's no
and נישואין nissuin would be the worst. There's no נישואין. nissuin? So
here but normally though אירוסין erusin would be enough to pull her
away from the father. father's house even though they were not yet
by נשואין. nisuin. And nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara is saying that since
she's married to a כהן Kohen, rather than a ישראל, that's enough
to keep her in the realm of eating תרומה. And you're managed
to be able to eat תרומה even though if either if the
relationship would consummate actually it would invalidate her. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. גופא. Gufa. Let's go back and look at the
issue itself. בעי מיניה רבי יוחנן מרבי אושעיא. Bei minei Rebbi Yochanan
me-Rebbi Oshaya. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan asked רבי אושעיא. Rebbi Oshaya פצוע
דכא כהן שנשא בת גרים מהו שיאכילנה בתרומה? Ptzua daka Kohen she-nasa
bat gerim mahu she-yachilenah be-trumah? So this is the question that רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan asked רבי אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya. and we said רבי
אושעיא Rebbi Oshaya didn't have an answer to. Okay, what is the
story of a forget our whole case about קידושין Kiddushin, without נשואין
nisuin and so on. The simple case of a פצוע דכא ptsuah
daka, that's simple case, anyway, that's married to a
בת גרים. bat gerim, So meaning there's no עבירה, aveirah, okay? She's
not a גיורת, giyores. so there's no problem in that way. And
she's a בת גרים, bat gerim so presumably there's no איסור פצוע
דכא issur ptzua daka in that case. So can he feed her
in תרומה? אישתיק. Ishtik. He was silent. ולא אמר ליה ולא מידי.
Ve-lo amar lei ve-lo midi. He didn't respond. לסוף
אתא גברא רבא אחרינא. Le-sof ata gavra raba achrina. Another afterwards, while
I mean I don't know
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan wasn't getting an answer, another great person came.
ובעי מיניה מילתא אחרינא U-bei minei milta achrina and asked רבי אושעיא
Rebbi Oshaya a question, a different question. ופשט ליה. U-pashat lei. And
he responded to him. He gave him a he resolved it. ומאן
ניהו האי אחרינא ריש לקיש? U-man nihu hai achrina Resh Lakish? Who
was this other person? ריש לקיש Resh Lakish asked him. So אמר
ליה רבי יהודה נשיאה לרבי אושעיא. Amar lei Rebbi Yehuda Nesia le-Rebbi
Oshaya. So רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rebbi Yehuda Nesia, not רבי יהודה הנשיא,
Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi, רבי יהודה נשיאה Rebbi Yehuda Nesia is the grandson
of רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rebbi Yehuda HaNasi, said to רבי אושעיא. אטו
רבי יוחנן לאו גברא רבא הוא? Atu Rebbi Yochanan lav gavra raba
hu? I don't understand, you gave ריש לקיש Resh Lakish an answer,
you didn't give רבי יוחנן an answer? רבי יוחנן is also a
great person. So אמר ליה. Amar lei. He said to
him. דקא בעי מינאי מילתא דלאו פשיטא לי. De-ka bei minai milta
de-lav pshita li. No, I did not answer him because I didn't
think he was worthy of an answer. I didn't answer him because
he asked me a question that has no answer, that I didn't
know the answer. That's why I didn't answer him. Not because he
wasn't deserving, but because I didn't know. So now let's see why
wasn't now the גמרא, Gemara the whole question of the continuation here
is is רבי אושעיא himself spelling it out or the גמרא Gemara
analyzing? רש"י Rashi says that this is the גמרא Gemara now analyzing,
yes, why רבי אושעיא had such a hard time answering this question.
Yes, you translated the דלאו פשיטא לי de-lav pshita li two different
ways. It's like there's no it's like a תיקו teiku or he
didn't know the answer.
Yeah, so the גמרא Gemara so he says that there is no
answer to it. But the גמרא Gemara is now going to ask
why is there no answer to it? So let's take a look.
No no, so it starts like this. למן. Leman. According to whom
do you think there's no answer? אי רבי
יהודה. Ei Rebbi Yehuda. If it's according to רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda.
So, I just lost my place. אי רבי יהודה בין בקדושתיה קאי
בין בלאו בקדושתיה קאי
לא אכלה. Ei Rebbi Yehuda bein bi-kdushateih kaei bein be-lav bi-kdushateih kaei
lo achlah. Whether he maintains his קדושה kdusha or not, she doesn't
eat. Now what does that mean? So first of all, there's two
questions here. One question is is בקדושתיה קאי? bi-kdushateih kaei? Whether a
כהן Kohen who's a פצוע דכא ptsuah daka is considered does that
impact? You know, there's an איסור issur now for him to marry,
but does it impact his קדושה kdusha status? Why might it impact
his קדושה kdusha status? Maybe the גמרא Gemara thinks, and it's funny
question why it would think this because this is not necessarily unique
about a כהן Kohen aspect, it's a general הלכה halacha about marrying,
but the גמרא Gemara thinks maybe the איסורים issurim of who a
כהן Kohen is allowed to marry might not apply to a כהן
Kohen who's a פצוע דכא. ptsuah daka Maybe he would of course
it would be a bit ironic because he'd be אסור assur anyway
because of פצוע דכא, ptsuah daka but maybe he would not be
אסור assur let's say if he would marry a גיורת giyores. or
something. It would impact his status vis-a-vis that. Not impact his status
vis-a-vis eating תרומה, but impact his status in terms of the איסורי
issurei women who he's אסור assur to marry, yes?
Would this be a מום mum that would prevent him from doing
the
עבודה? avodah?
דוכן? Duchan?
Well, דוכן duchan is a different question but the עבודה. avodah. Yeah,
yeah, I'm pretty positive, yeah, it's on the list there. ומעוך וכתות
ונתוק וכרות. U-mauch ve-katut ve-natuk ve-charut. Yeah,
so yes it would. But that's anyway, but that doesn't have status
normally to the questions of marriage and eating תרומה. Okay. Okay. So,
so that's question number one is, is do the איסורים issurim of
who he can marry continue to apply? That's בקדושתיה קאי. bi-kdushateih kaei.
The other question is whether קהל גרים kehal gerim and this is
the debate that the גמרא Gemara is going to get to about
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yossi, whether קהל גרים
איקרי קהל kehal gerim ikrei kahal or not. Whether exactly the question
we raised before, whether people that are descendants of גרים, gerim? we
know for example as I said that cases when it says בקהל
השם bi-kehal Hashem like פצוע דכא, Ptzua Daka כרות שפכה, khrut shofcha,
ממזר Mamzer and so on, that's okay that those people and גרים
gerim? can intermarry, marry one another. However, what's this story about descendants
of גרים? gerim Do those restrictions still apply or not to descendants
of גרים? Gerim. And that's the question whether קהל גרים, kehal gerim,
not the גר ger, himself, but the community of גרים gerim as
it were, for later descendants, do they still have a distinct status
or not? And that's the question whether קהל גרים. kehal gerim. And
that's a debate of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי. Rebbi
Yossi. That's what we're referring to. So let's take a look how
this spells out. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. And
that's a debate of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי. Rebbi
Yossi. That's what we're referring to. So let's take a look. אי
רבי יהודה בין בקדושתיה קאי בין בלאו בקדושתיה קאי לא אכלה. Ei
Rebbi Yehuda bein bi-kdushateih kaei bein be-lav bi-kdushateih kaei lo achlah. Whether
the כהן Kohen retains his קדושה kdusha or not she can't eat.
Why not? So let's spell it out. אי בקדושתיה קאי, Ei bikdushasei
kai, if he retains his קדושה kedusha and he's not allowed to
marry a איסורי כהונה, issurei kehuna, so לא אכלה, lo achla, דאמר
מר, De-amar mar, because the master said, and this really, the master
meaning is really a ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda position, בת גר כבת
חלל זכר, Bas ger ke-bas chalal zachar, that the descendant of a
גר ger. is like the descendant of a חלל. chalal. We don't
פוסקן pasken this way, thank God, it would have enormous impact, but
it basically means that a כהן Kohen is not allowed to marry
the descendant of a גר. ger Okay, imagine if we had that
הלכה. halacha. Right, not only could a כהן Kohen not marry a
גר, ger. he'd have to know if there's any גר ger anywhere
up the chain, and not only is the mother a גר, ger
even if the father is a גר. ger. Okay, so according to
this, if she's a בת גר, bas ger. you think, oh, you're
going to solve the problem. How are you going to solve the
problem? Because if it's a בת גר, bas ger. then a כהן
Kohen can marry her. But that's not true according to ר' יהודה,
Reb Yehuda, a כהן Kohen cannot marry a בת גר. bas ger.
So number one, assuming that the איסורי כהונה issurei kehuna still apply
to him, the women he can't marry, it's not going to help
the fact that she's a בת גר. bas ger. Okay, number one.
So A, if he still has full קדושת כהונה, kedushas kehuna, he
can't marry, and he's a פצוע דכא, Ptzua Daka, you're not going
to say, oh, I'll get a solution, let him marry a בת
גר. bas ger. No, that's not a solution according to ר' יהודה,
Reb Yehuda, he can't marry a בת גר. bas ger ואי לאו
בקדושתיה קאי, Ve-ei lav bikdushasei kai, and if he doesn't have קדושת
כהונה kedushas kehuna in the sense that he's allowed, there's no restrictions
who he can marry, although he's still a פצוע דכא, Ptzua Daka
but as a כהן, Kohen no restrictions he can still marry. So
fine, so no restrictions who he can marry from a כהן Kohen
perspective. Let's have him marry a גיורת giyores. or a בת גר.
bas ger. Okay, and why will that be good? From the כהן
Kohen status not a problem, he's not restricted for a גר Ger,
or גיורת. giyores. לאו בקדושתיה קאי. Lav bikdushasei kai. And from the
כרות שפכה kerus shofcha issue, not a problem because somebody who is
a כרות שפכה kerus shofcha can marry a גר. Ger. So we
solved the problem. Okay. So ואי לאו בקדושתיה קאי, Ve-ei lav bikdushasei
kai, so לא אכלה. lo achla. Why? דהמינן כהג"מ איקרי קהל, De-haminan
ka-hagam ikrei kahal, because it might be true that from his perspective
he can go ahead and say, okay look, no איסור issur status
and so on. But a descendant of a גר Ger according to
ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda is still, you know, is considered a קהל,
kahal, meaning has the is not like a גר Ger from the
perspective that they're אסור assur. with a כרות שפכה. kerus shofcha. I'm
I think I have to make a chart. Okay. Here you've got,
okay there's two aspects here right? There's כרות שפכה. kerus shofcha. Okay,
that's the כהן Kohen status, or פצוע דכא. Ptzua Daka Guess we're
talking about פצוע דכא. Ptzua Daka פצוע דכא, Ptzua Daka who can
פצוע דכא Ptzua Daka marry? Okay, who can he marry? He can
marry a גר. ger Okay, that he can marry. That the גמרא
Gemara says, or גר גיורת ger giyores right? גיורת. giyores? He's allowed
to marry. Okay, that's clear. All right. Now, can he marry a
בת גר bas ger. or not? Okay, now because the question is
he can't marry קהל ה'. Kahal Hashem So is this considered, so
this is because he came initially from the outside it's not considered
קהל ה'. Kahal Hashem How about a בת? Is that considered קהל
ה' Kahal Hashem? or not? Okay. So if it's איקרי קהל, ikrei
kahal, the descendants, then אסור. assur. Okay, then it is קהל ה'
kahal Hashem and then it's אסור. assur. Okay, then it would be
אסור. asur. If it's לא איקרי, lo ikrei, then it's מותר. muttar.
Okay, then it's מותר. muttar. Okay, that's a פצוע דכא. Ptzua Daka
Now okay what? איקרי קהל, ikrei kahal, is it considered קהל ה'?
kahal Hashem, Is it the קול, kol, does it call, does it
call the קהל? kahal? So basically is it a community of people
that he is not allowed to marry into, a פצוע דכא? Ptzua
Daka Okay, בת גר. bas ger בת גר. bas ger Okay, so
that's so okay now how about a כהן? Kohen So you may
be here... here we'll make it like this. Okay. גיורת. giyores? So
like this. And בת גר bas ger and גיורת. giyores? Okay, that's
that way. Okay. Okay. And now you've got here is a פצוע
דכא, Ptzua Daka this guy's a פצוע דכא Ptzua Daka and a
כהן. kohen, Okay, and a כהן. kohen. So can a פצוע דכא
psua daka marry a גיורת? giyoret Check. Can a כהן kohen marry
a גיורת? giyoret X. Okay. Can a פצוע דכא psua daka, marry
a בת גר bas ger or a whatever בת גיורת? bas giyores?
So if it's if it's איקרי קהל, ikrei kahal, then X. If
it's not קהל, kahal, לא קהל, lo kahal, then check. Okay. Can
a כהן kohen. marry a בת גר bas ger or גיורת? giyoret
Okay, so that is the position. ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda says we
just said that he's a בת גר Bat Ger is כבת ke-bas
is כבת חלל, ke-bas chalal, like we just had that statement. בת
גר Bat Ger. is כבת חלל ke-bas chalal and he's not allowed
to. Okay. We're going to see that ר' יוסי Reb Yosi is
going to say we haven't... it's a bit too easily is allowed.
Now, we want to know is there any way a פצוע דכא
כהן Ptzua Daka Kohen can have a כשר kosher marriage here? Okay?
With a okay. So, can you match it up that you get
two checks? Well, with a גיורת giyoret, herself, no, because a פצוע
דכא psua daka. we know is מותר mutar by גיורת giyoret, and
we know a כהן kohen. is אסור. asur Okay? Now, unless a
פצוע דכא כהן Ptzua Daka Kohen is לאו בקדושתיה קאי. lav bikdushatia
kai. If he's לאו בקדושתיה קאי, lav bikdushatia kai, right, he doesn't
maintain his קדושה, kedusha, then he might be able to, you know,
just do the גיורת giyoret, category. Can a פצוע דכא כהן Ptzua
Daka Kohen marry a בת גיורת? Bat Giyoret? Okay, so from the,
so if it's בקדושתיה קאי, bikdushatia kai, the גמרא Gemara said he
has a full status of כהן, kohen. then according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda cannot, right, because a בת גר Bat Ger. is another
is a woman that a כהן, kohen. the same way a כהן
kohen. can't marry a גר, ger he can't marry a בת גר.
Bat Ger Yes? That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. How about
if he's, if he's לאו בקדושתיה קאי lav bikdushatia kai and you
don't have to worry about the כהן kohen, status? You don't have
to worry about the כהן kohen, status, לאו בקדושתיה קאי, lav bikdushatia
kai, then it's a problem because he still says קהל גרים איקרי
קהל, Kehal Gerim ikri Kehal, right? And he can't marry her. Right?
So that's what the גמרא Gemara. says. אי רבי יהודה בין בקדושתיה
בין בלאו בקדושתיה, Ei Rabbi Yehuda bein bikdushatia bein belav bikdushatia, so
let's say it again. אי רבי יהודה בין בקדושתיה בין בלאו בקדושתיה,
Ei Rabbi Yehuda bein bikdushatia bein belav bikdushatia, if we have to
worry about the כהן kohen, status, so לא אכלה, lo achla, דאמר
מר בת גר זכר כבת חלל זכר, de-amar mar Bat Ger zachar
ke-Bat Chalal zachar, then you can't because he says that the same
way a כהן kohen is אסור asur a גיורת, giyoret, he is
אסור asur in a בת גיורת. Bat Giyoret. אי לאו בקדושתיה קאי,
Ei lav bikdushatia kai, and if he's forget the כהן kohen status,
that's not relevant, he's a פצוע דכא, psua daka so לא אכלה
דאמרינן קהל גרים איקרי קהל, lo achla de-amrinan Kehal Gerim ikri Kehal,
then you can't do it because a קהל גרים Kehal Gerim is
somebody a פצוע דכא psua daka? is not allowed to marry into.
Ironically, of course, who could a כהן kohen marry in this case?
If it's לאו בקדושתיה קאי, lav bikdushatia kai, he could marry a
גיורת, giyoret, right? Because he's לאו בקדושתיה קאי, lav bikdushatia kai, so
you don't have to worry about the כהן kohen, status, so a
פצוע דכא psua daka can marry, but he can't marry, he can't
marry a בת גר. Bat Ger, Okay? Because a בת גר Bat
Ger, no longer is קהל השם. Kehal Hashem. The היתר heter for
a פצוע דכא psua daka. is only in a גיורת, giyoret not
in the second generation according to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay? So
if we're asking about a בת גר, Bat Ger then either way
he can't. If he, you look at the כהן kohen, status, he
obviously can't, because a כהן's kohen not allowed to marry according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda a בת גר, Bat Ger the same way
he can't marry a גר. ger, But even if you ignore the
כהן kohen status he can't, because according to him a בת גר
Bat Ger or בת גיורת Bat Giyoret is considered to be like
any Jewish woman, and a פצוע דכא psua daka can't marry a
בת גר Bat Ger or בת גיורת. Bat Giyoret. So according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda there's no way he can marry a בת
גר Bat Ger? and therefore the woman would never be able to
eat תרומה on account of this type of a marriage. Yes. What's
the argument for a בת גר גיורת Bat Ger Giyoret not being
a regular Jewish woman? Look, it's—I understand. We tend to be thinking
only in terms of, like, oh, okay, so the mother converts, she's
Jewish, etc., and it's a real problem because, you know, because on
the one hand the whole thing of, like, ומשפט אחד יהיה לכם
u-mishpat echad yihiyeh lachem and not to make any distinctions between גר
ger, and non-גר ger and so on, but nevertheless as we're going
to continue to learn יבמות, Yevamot, we're going to see that the
idea that person did not was not sort of, you know, naturally
born Jew according to some תנאים, Tannaim, of some פוסקים, poskim, whatever
some positions continue to frame not only that person, but you know,
even the descendants in a somewhat different category. So, yes. Is that
בת גר bat ger or בת גיורת Bat Giyoret status for one
generation only or does it continue? No, it would continue. Which would
be pretty amazing, right? So, yeah. What if you have a convert
married to a convert whose child marries the son or daughter of
a convert who married a convert? All right, we'll see, we'll be
seeing plenty of this. So let's take a look. The זכר zachar
piece is a significant, in other words, no, even even זכר. zachar.
Okay. ואמר רבי יוסי בין בקדושתיה קאי בין לאו בקדושתיה קאי. Ve-amar
Rabbi Yosi bein bikdushatia kai bein belav bikdushatia kai. According to רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi either way אכלה. achla. בקדושתיה קאי אכלה דהא אמר
גר שנתגייר בתו כשרה לכהונה. Bikdushatia kai achla de-ha amar Ger she-nitgayer
bito keshera li-kehuna. Because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi actually says that a
בת גיורת, Bat Giyoret, right, is, you know, being is totally מותר.
mutar. That there's no problem. A כהן kohen is אסור asur in
a גיורת, giyoret but he's not אסור assur in a second generation.
So even with his כהונה Kehuna status, no problem. Now how about
his פצוע דכא psua daka, status? Okay. So number one is, and
thankfully we פסקן pasken that way. Imagine if we wouldn't פסקן pasken
that way, then a כהן kohen would not only have to worry
about if the woman he was dating was a גיורת, giyoret but
if she descended from גרים. gerim Okay. But he says, no, רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that a כהן kohen can marry a בת
גיורת. Bat Giyoret. רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. So from the כהונה Kehuna
status, no problem. How about the פצוע דכא psua daka, status? אי
לאו בקדושתיה קאי. Ei lav bikdushatia kai. Now it also says even
without לאו בקדושתיה קאי, lav bikdushatia kai, the point is he has
to address the פצוע דכא psua daka? status. What about the פצוע
דכא psua daka? status? What about that? So can he marry, can
a פצוע דכא psue daka? marry a בת גר? bat ger So
אי לאו בקדושתיה קאי... ei lav bikdushatia kai... אחרתא דאמר קהל גרים
לא איקרי קהל. achrata deamar kahal gerim lo ikrai kahal. Yes, because
the descendants of גרים are not considered קהל kahal in the sense
that there's no restrictions of a פצוע דכא psue daka? intermarrying. So
you have to notice the irony, by the way. It's quite ironic
that he says on the one hand a בת גיורת bat giyoret
is so much of a Jew that there's no problem vis-a-vis כהן,
kohen right? We don't sort of, we don't say she's in a
different category. On the other hand, she's still not seen as a
normal Jew, as a naturally born Jew, and she can go ahead
and marry a פצוע דכא, psue daka right? And the same reverse
pattern with רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says a
daughter of a גר ger is still enough of a גר ger?
that she can't marry a כהן. kohen On the other hand, she's
enough of a ישראל that she can't marry a פצוע דכא. psue
daka Okay, so logically, you know, it's funny, right, because you would
think it would be either-or. But anyway, רב יוסי Rav Yossi is
lenient in both, and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda strict in both. So
the גמרא Gemara winds up saying, so look,
I don't understand the question. According to רב יוסי, Rav Yossi, obviously
פצוע דכא psue daka can be married to a בת גרים bas
gerim and she could eat. And according to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
obviously she could not and she can't eat. So what's the question?
So the גמרא says, אלא אליבא דהאי תנא, ela aliba dehai tana,
according to the following תנא, tana, דתנן, detnan, דרבי אליעזר בן יעקב
אומר, deRabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer, אשה בת גרים לא תינשא לכהונה
עד שתהא אמה מישראל, isha bat gerim lo tinase lekehuna ad shetei
ima miYisrael, that a woman who is the who is descendant of
גרים cannot marry a כהן kohen. until her mother is
Jewish. So basically, that meaning that, so what do you see
from this? Hold on let me just check רש"י Rashi one second.
Right. That he basically says that if you have a father who's
a גר, ger she can marry a כהן. kohen A mother who's
a גר, ger, she cannot. Okay, so and here's the question. So
let's assume so her mother was ישראל. And now he said that
if her mother is ישראל fine, now she can marry a כהן.
Kohen? So what we want to understand though is what's the story
vis-a-vis פצוע דכא? psue daka, Okay, alright, עד שתהא אמה מישראל. ad
shetei ima miYisrael. So והכי קמיבעיא ליה, vehachi kamibaia leh, here's the
question. And it's really not a question of תרומה as much as
it's a question about marrying a כהן. Kohen, כשרות מתווספא בה. kashrut
mitvasfa bah. When, right, if this position would say if she was
normally the daughter of a גיורת she could not marry a כהן.
Kohen, But the fact that her mother is ישראלית Yisraelit even though
her father is a גר ger, allows her to marry a כהן.
Kohen So what do we say happens when her mother becomes a
is a ישראלית? Yisraelit? What does that add to her status? Does
it add a greater sense of כשרות, kashrut, meaning that כשרות kashrut
is a concept vis-a-vis a כהן, Kohen. it makes her more כשרה
keshera to a כהן, Kohen. but doesn't change her status from the
perspective of קהל? kahal? And therefore ואכלה, veachla, so she can still
go ahead and marry a פצוע דכא psue daka and eat. או
דילמא קדושה מתווספא בה, o dilma kedusha mitvasfa bah, or maybe if
her mother is ישראלית Yisraelit then it makes her more of this
קהל ה' kahal Hashem, and she's considered more קדוש kadosh ולא אכלה
velo achla
and she can't eat and she's אסור assur, to a
פצוע דכא. psue daka So what it basically is saying is, it's
a little
confusing but it's basically is saying is, we've
been not distinguishing between a בת גר bat ger and a בת
גיורת. bat giyoret. Comes along a position that actually says no, that
a בת גר bat ger, is different, right, this position is whose
this position? Who was the one here? Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. Okay,
so this is so
רבי אליעזר
בן
יעקב
Rabbi Eliezer
ben
Yaakov distinguishes between a בת גר bat ger? and a בת גיורת.
bat giyoret. Okay? And he says the following, and he says that
it as far as the כהן, Kohen can you marry somebody who's
a בת גר, can a כהן Kohen marry a בת גר? Yes.
Can he marry a בת גיורת? bat giyoret? No. Okay? So somehow
there's something better about being אמה מישראל ima miYisrael that lets her
marry. So the question is, if being אמה מישראל ima miYisrael turns
what otherwise would have been an X into a check, what
does it do to this box?
What does it do to the question
of whether a
פצוע דכא psue daka can marry
somebody who is
descendant from a גר and a and a Jewish woman. So maybe
being אמה מישראל ima miYisrael makes her more כשר, kasher, כשר kasher
here understood as כשר kasher for כהונה, kehuna, but doesn't make her
more קהל ה', kahal Hashem so presumably let's
start over here. If it was a בת גיורת, bat giyoret,
the same way a
כהן Kohen, is אסור, assur if her mother is a גיורת presumably
it would be okay for a פצוע דכא, psue daka right? Presumably
it'd be sort of like this. Normally we assume that these two
are the mirror image, right? So the question is, if that's the
story if her mother is a גיורת that she can't marry a
כהן Kohen but she can marry a פצוע דכא, psue daka she's
not קהל kahal, ה', right, not קהל, kahal what happens when her
mother is a ישראלית, Yisraelit, but her ישראלית, Yisraelit, but her father's
a גר? So does that make her more כשר, kasher, meaning כשר
kasher to a כהן, but it doesn't affect her status for קהל
kahal and therefore she remains מותר mutar to a פצוע דכא? psue
daka Or does it even make her more קדוש kadosh which somehow
means that it even affects her status for קהל and makes her
more קהל ה' and makes her אסור assur. to a פצוע דכא?
Petzua Daka Okay, so that's the question. Yeah, I don't know, I
don't want to get into that, I mean whatever, it's not- you
can't simplify this issue. Okay. Anyway so the גמרא says תא שמע,
Tashma, come and hear. So that's the question. The question is according
to this תנא, Tanna, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, it's either all מותר mutar or all אסור. assur
Is it possible according to this תנא Tanna that אמה מישראל Eema
mi-Yisrael would be a case that it would be enough of a
Jew to be enough of a whatever of a non-גר to be
מותר mutar to a כהן, but nevertheless not holy enough to be
אסור assur to a פצוע דכא? Maybe also מותר mutar to a
פצוע דכא? Okay, so the גמרא says תא שמע. Tashma. יתיב רב
אחא בר קטינא מדרומא. Yasiv Rav Aha bar Katinah me-Daroma. רב אחא
בר קטינא Rav Aha bar Katinah came from the south, אתא ואייתי
מתניתא בידיה, ata ve-aisei masnisa be-yadei, he brought a ברייתא Braitah in
his hand. מנין לפצוע דכא כהן שנשא בת גרים שמאכילה בתרומה? minayin
le-petzua daka kohen she-nasa bas gerim she-ma'achila be-terumah? How do you know
a פצוע דכא כהן who is married to a בת גרים bas
gerim. can have her eat תרומה? שנאמר וכהן כי יקנה נפש קנין
כספו היא יאכל בו. she-ne'emar ve-kohen ki yikneh nefesh kinyan kaspo hi
yochal bo. So למה, le-ma, so anyway he says it says נפש
קנין כספו. nefesh kinyan kaspo. כהן is coming to include a case
of being married to a פצוע דכא being married to a בת
גרים. bas gerim I don't know how he gets it from that
פסוק. pasuk. Okay, but למה, le-ma, now who do you need this
פסוק pasuk for? אי דרבי יהודה האמר בין בשעתה קאי בין לאו
בשעתה קאי לא אכלה. iy de-Rabbi Yehuda ha-amar bein bish'asa kayei bein
lav bish'asa kayei lo achla. According to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
wouldn't be the הלכה. halacha. We just got through proving that a
פצוע דכא married to a בת גרים bas gerim, did not eat.
ואי דרבי יוסי למה לי קרא האמר בין בשעתה קאי בין לאו
בשעתה קאי אכלה. ve-iy de-Rabbi Yossi la-ma li kra ha-amar bein bish'asa
kayei bein lav bish'asa kayei achla. We said that either way she
could eat and you don't need a פסוק. pasuk. אלא לאו דרבי
אליעזר בן יעקב. ella lav de-Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. It must be
according to רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov that we
didn't know according to him, notice this בת גרים, which means a-
we're reading it to be the father is a גר, we didn't
know according to him when the mother was Jewish and the father
was a גר, we knew that the כהן could marry her, we
did not know what the story is with פצוע דכא, if a
פצוע דכא could marry her. ושמע מינה כשירה היא ותוסף בה אחר.
u-shma mina kashira hi ve-tosaf bah acher. She's more כשרה kashira that
a כהן can marry her, but not more קדוש, kadosh, so therefore
not off limits from a פצוע דכא perspective and therefore a פצוע
דכא כהן can marry her, and if a פצוע דכא כהן can
marry her therefore she can eat תרומה. שמע מינה. shma mina. Okay,
we've proven that. So that was quite complicated, but I think you
get the basic idea. Normally we would have expected that the פצוע
דכא and the כהן would be reverse of one another, but comes
along what do you call it, but comes along this גמרא according
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi raises the
possibility that they're not reverse, that actually you could have both be
מותר mutar or both be אסור and there's a difference between the
עיקרי קהל ikri kahal question and whether it's כשרה kashira or אסורה
assura to a כהן. Okay, that was fun. Now we get to
something actually easier. איתמר. רב אמר. Rav amar. Yes, see that we
might actually not get more than a דף daf behind. יש חופה
לפסולות yesh chuppah le-pesulos or לפסולות, le-pesulos, ושמואל אמר אין חופה לפסולות.
ve-Shmuel amar ein chuppah le-pesulos. Is there a concept of חופה chuppah
to a woman who is פסולה? pesulah? Now what does this mean?
So first what you need to know is that there's an interesting
debate in the ראשונים, Rishonim, two interesting debates. One is whether חופת
נדה chuppas niddah is a good חופה chuppah or not. If your
woman is a נדה niddah when there's a חופה, chuppah, if חופה's
chuppah whole idea is about to be having sex and so on,
can- can you have a נישואין nissuin. when the woman is a
נדה niddah and can you say שבע ברכות sheva berachos and so
on. So the ספרדים Sefardim say actually רמב"ם Rambam says you're not
allowed to, למעשה le-maise of course we do it whatever anyway, the
אשכנזים Ashkenazim say you are. But that's a- reflecting the idea that
a חופה chuppah is like coming together in the house and about
to be having sex and is it meaningful and are you- is
it an act of נישואין? Nisuin. Now that's questioning of is it
considered חופה chuppah and therefore can you say the שבע ברכות sheva
berachos etcetera. Here we're asking like the reverse case, which is you
went ahead and you did a חופה chuppah with a woman who
is פסולה, pesulah, I just gave the נדה, niddah, I hope it
doesn't distract you as a relevant contemporary example. But let's- but that's
a woman who's in a temporary status of not being able to
have sex. But let's say it's a woman that the- that you're-
that actually it's never able to be having- to be getting together,
it's a כהן with a גרושה Gerushah type of a case or
I don't know, a פצוע דכא with a woman or whatever the
case might be where actually they can never really הלכתית halachically are
allowed to be consummating the marriage, and you go ahead and you
have חופה chuppah anyway. Does it have meaning, that act of חופה?
chuppah? Okay, now you could ask the question for example like does
he start having to support her? Do all the other obligations of
the כתובה ketubah kick in, right? Other הלכות halachos about a כתובה
ketubah about הפרת נדרים, haforas nedarim, התרת, hataras, you know, all these
statuses that change at the time of נישואין. Nisuin What happens if
it's in a context where the- where they're actually not allowed to
be having sex? Okay, that's one way of asking the question. Our
גמרא seems to focus very- it'll get to that tomorrow which is
really today's דף, daf, but anyway, but today what it seems to
be focusing on is whether actually it- it goes ahead and makes
it as if they've already had sex, not just like... But is
she considered a נשואה Nesua for all the relevant הלכות Halachos of
being a נשואה? Nesua? But it seems to ask the question of
is the fact that they've had חופה Chuppah even without sex, like
she's already had sex to invalidate her if in these cases of
this איסור Issur if she's אסורה Assurah to a כהן? So if
you have basically an אלמנה Almanah to a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
or גרושה Gerushah to a כהן הדיוט, Kohen Hedyot, all these cases,
and they've had חופה Chuppah without sex, does that make her a
חללה, Challalah. right? So you understand a גרושה Gerushah, might already not
be allowed to marry a כהן, but if she's a daughter of
a כהן, she can go back and eat the תרומה from her
father. If she has sex with a כהן as a גרושה, she's
a חללה, Challalah. she can't. Let's say she didn't have sex with
a כהן. Let's say she just had חופה Chuppah with a כהן.
Okay. Does that now make her a חללה? Challalah? It's similar to
the case of our משנה. Mishnah. Our משנה Mishnah רבי מאיר said
just being קידושין with a כהן makes it as if she's had
sex and a חללה. What if we ratchet it up one, not
just קידושין, you actually had חופה Chuppah but you haven't had sex
yet? Would that affect your status? Okay. So let's take a look
at the גמרא. יש חופה לפסולות? Yesh chuppah lepesulot? And if they
do have sex, does the כהן have to divorce her? Yeah, he
has to divorce her even without having sex. But yeah. Okay. יש
חופה לפסולות. Yesh chuppah lepesulot. ורב... VeRav... so רב Rav says yes,
ושמואל אמר אין חופה לפסולות. u'Shmuel amar ein chuppah lepesulot. No, it's
not meaningful. אמר שמואל ומודי לי אבא, Amar Shmuel u'modei li Abba,
אבא Abba which is his way of referring to רב. Rav. Now
that's actually interesting because רש"י Rashi says אבא Abba is just a
term of respect. If you take a quick look at תוספות, Tosafot,
אמר שמואל ומודי לי אבא, Amar Shmuel u'modei li Abba, תוספות Tosafot
says לאו כמה שפירש בקונטרס לשון חשיבות אלא כך היה שמו של
רב כדפירש בערוך. Lav kemah shepeirush bekuntres lashon chashivut ela kach hayah
shemo shel Rav kedapeirush be'Aruch. Okay, so there's a question whether רב
Rav is because, you know, it's like רב, Rav, if you have
רב אבא, Rav Abba, right? Does that sort of become, I mean
it certainly might become like רבא, Rava, but does it also become
like רב? Rav? Anyway. Okay. So רב Rav would agree to me
בתינוקת פחותה מבת שלש שנים ויום אחד betinoket p'chusa mibas shalosh shanim
veyom echad if the חופה Chuppah was done with a woman who
wasn't yet fit to be having, halachically wasn't even recognized as sex,
a girl under three years old and one day. הואיל ואין לה
ביאה אין לה חופה. Ho'il v'ein lah biah ein lah chuppah. In
that case, certainly even if you did an act of חופה, Chuppah,
it would not be considered as if you had an act of
sex. אמר רבא אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rava af anan nami
tanina. Yeah, we taught like that, that under three is not considered
to be an act of sex. בת שלש שנים ויום אחד מתקדשת
בביאה. Bat shalosh shanim veyom echad mitkadeshet beviah. קידושי ביאה Kiddushei biah
works once she's three years old and a day. Again, this is
quite horrific imagining this, but the גמרא defines it an act of
sex once she's three years old and less than that not. ואם
בא עליה יבם קנאה Ve'im ba aleha yavam k'na'ah and an act
of יבום Yibbum works at that stage because that's all about an
act of sex. וחייבין עליה משום אשת איש Vechayavin aleha mishum eshet
ish and if she was, her father married her off and somebody
had sex with her, that would be an act of adultery. ומטמאה
את בועלה U'metamah et bo'alah and if she's a נידה, Niddah, so
the טומאה Tumah of נידה Niddah transfers to the man she has
sex with. לטמא משכב תחתון כעליון Letamei mishkav tachton ke'elyon to make
the upper משכב, Mishkav, the upper thing he's sitting on like the
lower thing. I'm not going to discuss that at all right now,
anyway we'll worry about that some other time when we get to
נידה. Niddah. Anyway, he gets her טומאה Tumah because it's an act
of sex. ניסת לכהן, Niset leKohen, if she's married to a כהן,
this three-year-old and one-day girl, then אוכלת בתרומה, ochelet b'terumah, she can
eat תרומה because again, you eat תרומה by virtue of being married
to a כהן in a context of נישואין. It's considered נישואין only
in a context where sex is possible. בא עליה אחד מכל הפסולים,
Ba aleha echad mikol hapesulim, if one of the invalid people like,
I don't know, a ממזר or whatever, פצוע דכא has sex with
her, פסלה, paslah, invalidates her because it's an again, an act of
forbidden sex makes her חללה. בת שלש שנים ויום אחד הוא דמיפסלה
בביאה, Bat shalosh shanim veyom echad hu demipsala beviah, מיפסלה בחופה. mipsala
bechuppah. So when she's three years old and a day, so an
act of sex would invalidate her. So here it spells out very
clearly what חופה לפסולות Chuppah lepesulot means, the act of חופה Chuppah
would invalidate her, would be like they've had sex. הפחותה מבת שלש
שנים ויום אחד דלא מיפסלה בביאה, Hap'chusa mibas shalosh shanim veyom echad
dela mipsala beviah, less than that, that the act of ביאה would
not invalidate her, לא מיפסלה נמי בחופה, lo mipsala nami bechuppah, שמע
מינה. shema mina. That's a good point. So now all we said
is the question is having חופה, Chuppah, is that like having had
sex for the נפקא מינה Nafkah mina of would it basically make
this woman like a חללה? Okay. So that's I guess where unfortunately
we're going to have to leave off for today, being a full
דף Daf behind. Good thing we didn't get more behind. Okay. Why
did they really have sex?