All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is י"ט. Yud
Tes. We pick up on י"ח עמוד ב' Yud Ches Amud Beis
at the משנה. mishna. We just went through a whole long discussion
about whether there is זיקה zika or not and whether, you know,
which again, does that mean in an absolute sense, but anyway, whether
זיקה zika creates an איסור issur of relationship even to a woman
you aren't married to, to her relatives and so on. Does it
continue even after מיתה? misa? And now we are going to move
to the next משנה, mishna, which is getting us back to the
case of אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. eishes achiv shelo hayah be'olamo.
Everybody remembers the phrase yesterday, בזיקה. bezika. No, צרת אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו בזיקה. tzaras eishes achiv shelo hayah be'olamo bezika. Okay, but
anyway, we're back to אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, eishes achiv shelo
hayah be'olamo, but it will not surprise you that we will also
be revisiting the זיקה zika question today as well. So let's take
a look at what we have in the משנה. mishna.
שלא היה בעולמה, shelo hayah be'olama, not בעולמו. be'olamo.
No, בעולמו. be'olamo. He wasn't alive when the brother was alive. No,
when the brother was alive
means that they never shared life in the world at the same
time. And that's true about the two brothers, they were never both
alive at the same time.
שני אחים שמת אחד מהם.
shnei achim shemet echad meihem. Okay, so again, this is going to
be the case about אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, eishes achiv shelo
hayah be'olamo, but the question about when. So ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon,
and לוי. Levi. ראובן Reuven is married to רחל. Rachel.
ראובן Reuven dies, and then שמעון, Shimon, and then לוי Levi is
born. So the key question here is, when did שמעון Shimon do
יבום yibum with רחל? Rachel? Did he do יבום yibum with רחל
Rachel before לוי Levi was born or after לוי Levi was born?
And the difference is, until now we've been talking that he did
יבום yibum with רחל Rachel after לוי Levi was born. So when
לוי Levi was born, לוי Levi encountered רחל Rachel as אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו, eishes achiv shelo hayah be'olamo, right, as an ערוה.
erva. But if שמעון Shimon did יבום yibum with רחל Rachel before
לוי Levi was born, then by the time לוי Levi was born,
maybe he totally just relates to רחל Rachel as שמעון's Shimon wife,
and ראובן's Reuven wife is irrelevant, and therefore maybe the whole past
goes away and then when שמעון Shimon dies it's a מצוה mitzvah
of יבום. yibum. So that's what our משנה mishna turns to. שני
אחים, shnei achim, two brothers, שמעון Shimon and ראובן. Reuven. ומת אחד
מהם, umet echad meihem, ראובן Reuven died. And then, before לוי Levi
was born, ויבם השני את אשת אחיו, veyibam hashaini es eishes achiv,
שמעון Shimon did יבום yibum with רחל. Rachel. ואחר כך נולד להם
אח, ve'acharkach nolad lahem ach, and then לוי Levi was born. So
when לוי Levi came into the world, רחל Rachel was with שמעון's
Shimon wife. The fact that she'd been married to ראובן Reuven beforehand
was like, you know, past history. Okay, and then ומת, umet, and
then שמעון Shimon dies. הראשונה יוצאת משום אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו.
harishona yotzei mishum eishes achiv shelo hayah be'olamo. So the משנה mishna
says, doesn't matter. Since this רחל Rachel is still אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו, eishes achiv shelo hayah be'olamo, even though when לוי Levi
was born she was already married to שמעון, Shimon, nevertheless, there's a
reality she has an איסור issur of אשת אח eishes ach to
future brothers, okay, to future brothers that are to be born.
הראשונה יוצאת משום אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו harishona yotzei mishum eishes
achiv shelo hayah be'olamo and השניה, hashniya, if שמעון Shimon happened to
be married to a second wife, הרי זו צרת אשת אח, hareizo
tzaras eishes ach, that would be צרת אשת אח. tzaras eishes ach.
עשה בה מאמר ומת, asa bah maamar umet, now if שמעון Shimon
did מאמר maamar but not יבום yibum and then he died, then
we know that there's that really she is, there's not really she's
not really an ערוה erva because, I mean, since she's not married
to שמעון Shimon biblically, דאורייתא, de'oraisa, right,
so therefore it's not really a case of צרת ערוה tzaras erva
because לוי Levi really doesn't have an obligation of יבום yibum to
her דאורייתא, de'oraisa, but Rabbinically she's seen to be like שמעון's Shimon
wife. So therefore, in that case, he's not going to obviously do
יבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, she's אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, eishes
achiv shelo hayah be'olamo, but as far as the co-wife is concerned,
so השניה חולצת ולא מתייבמת. hashniya choletzes velo misyabemes. You don't do
יבום yibum because it looks like צרת ערוה, tzaras erva, but you
can't let her walk away without anything because halachically only really this
co-wife is really the only real wife דאורייתא. de'oraisa. Okay, so that's
what we saw before, but that's not the part about מאמר maamar
is not new or interesting for us right now, that was a
lot of what we discussed yesterday. What's new and interesting for us
is that it doesn't matter according to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
here that even when לוי Levi was born she was already married
to שמעון. Shimon. That's irrelevant. She remains אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו.
eishes achiv shelo hayah be'olamo. But now comes רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
and says, רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, מייבם לאיזה מהן שירצה,
miyabem le'eizeh meihen sheyirtzeh, not in the מאמר maamar case, back to
the first case, okay, in the רישא, reisha, that he can actually
do יבום, yibum, either to רחל Rachel or with a co-wife, או
חולץ לאיזה מהן שירצה. o cholets le'eizeh meihen sheyirtzeh. But the fact
that she is no longer אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eishes achiv
shelo hayah be'olamo since by the time לוי Levi is born she
is already married to שמעון. Shimon. Okay. So that is a nice
debate, does that status change if יבום Yibbum has already occurred and
then לוי Levi is born afterwards?
I'm sorry, and in the מאמר Ma'amar case, do you do חליצה
Chalitzah to the, you know, clinical the original widow, and then the
the other wife of שמעון Shimon if he if he
no no you don't do anything to the widow.
Right, no, she's just nothing.
No, in the מאמר Ma'amar case, you do חליצה Chalitzah to the
co-wife. רחל Rachel you don't do.
Right, that's what I meant, the first, the first one, nothing happens
to her, she just goes.
Correct. Correct. Correct. אמר רב אושעיא, Amar Rav Oshaya, חולק עליו רבי
שמעון אף לרישא. Cholek alav Rabbi Shimon af le-reisha. Now רב אושעיא
Rav Oshaya is going to make our life complicated because he is
going to say while the structure of the משנה Mishnah certainly implies
that רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon idea that it's not a problem anymore
of אשת אחיו Eshes Achiv because she's already married to שמעון Shimon
seems to make a lot of sense only if לוי Levi is
born after, you know, שמעון Shimon has done יבום, Yibbum, and that's
certainly the structure of the משנה. Mishnah. And that, by the way,
is what רב פפא Rav Pappa is going to say at the
bottom of י"ט עמוד א', Yud Tes Amud Alef, and we're going
to go like רב פפא, Rav Pappa, so not to ruin the
surprise for you, but if you get frustrated with the next עמוד,
Amud, just know we're going to reject this position. But nevertheless, רב
אושעיא's Rav Oshaya claiming that this idea that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says it's not a problem of אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, Eshes
Achiv she-lo hayah be-olamo, that would be true even if לוי Levi
was born before the יבום Yibbum had taken place, even in the
case of the רישא. Reisha. Okay, which is crazy, it doesn't seem
like it's what the משנה Mishnah is saying, and it's hard to
understand the logic for that. So let's take a look. אמר רב
אושעיא, Amar Rav Oshaya, חולק עליו רבי שמעון אף לרישא. Cholek alav
Rabbi Shimon af le-reisha. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would disagree and say
it's not a problem even in the first case, even if לוי
Levi was born before the יבום Yibbum had taken place. ממאי? Mimai?
Where do you know this from? מדקתני משנה יתירה, Mi-de-katani Mishnah Yesreirah,
בבא דרישא. Bava de-reisha. Because the whole first משנה Mishnah is superfluous.
The whole first משנה Mishnah where לוי Levi was born before the
יבום, Yibbum, okay, you didn't have to tell me that. You could
have just taught the second משנה. Mishnah. Why? למאן קתני לה? Le-man
katani lah? What was the purpose of the first משנה Mishnah where
לוי Levi was born before the יבום? Yibbum? אילימא לרבנן? Eleima le-Rabbanan?
If it's for the rabbis? השתא יבום ולבסוף נולד, Hashta Yibbum u-levsof
nolad, in the case where the second משנה, Mishnah, יבום Yibbum had
already occurred and then לוי Levi was born, דכי אשכח בה בהיתירא
אשכח, De-chi askach bah be-heteira askach, that when לוי Levi found רחל,
Rachel, meaning when לוי Levi came into the world, רחל Rachel was
in a היתר Heter situation, married to his brother, no longer in
the context of אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. Eshes Achiv she-lo hayah
be-olamo. So if in the second משנה Mishnah אסרי רבנן, Asri Rabbanan,
the rabbis still say it's a problem, so נולד ואחר כך יבום,
Nolad ve-achar kach Yibbum, in the first משנה Mishnah where לוי Levi
was born and then the יבום Yibbum took place, מיבעיא? Mibaya? Is
there any question? Of course she's אסור Assur to him. So you
don't need the first. According to the rabbis, the חידוש Chiddush is
the second משנה, Mishnah, that even in the case where יבום Yibbum
had already taken place, she remains forbidden. I, I see I'm going
to have to draw this on the board.
Although it's not conceptually complicated, I think some visual might help. Okay,
so here's
the רישא, Reisha, first משנה. Mishnah. You see
what it means by the first and the second משנה Mishnah is
the רישא, Reisha, משנה Mishnah one, right, משנה Mishnah two, our משנה,
Mishnah, סיפא, Seifa, okay. So
in the first משנה, Mishnah, okay,
you had ראובן Reuven married to רחל Rachel and שמעון Shimon was
around. That's step one, let's just, this is a better way to
do it. Okay, step two is ראובן Reuven died.
Step three is that,
and then you have here רחל Rachel who is, okay, then you
have, right, then you, sorry.
Step three is that לוי Levi is born, okay, born.
And therefore רחל Rachel becomes אשת אחיו
שלא
היה בעולמו.
Eshes Achiv she-lo hayah
be-olamo. לוי Levi is born and then step four is we'll have
a wedding, שמעון Shimon and רחל Rachel
get married.
Did לוי Levi go to the wedding?
Yeah, לוי Levi went to the wedding. Okay, so here by step,
by step number three, רחל Rachel is,
use red, רחל Rachel is an ערוה, Ervah, and that doesn't change
for
לוי, Levi, right, she's an ערוה Ervah vis-a-vis לוי. Levi. And that
doesn't change for לוי Levi even after they get married, even after
שמעון Shimon gets married. So that case is pretty obvious that it's
a problem. So if you're going to say it's אסור, Assur, right,
obviously, you know, this is the more obvious,
what, you don't say
what's up there?
That רחל Rachel is אסור Assur to לוי. Levi.
רחל Rachel is אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו Eshes Achiv she-lo hayah
be-olamo if שמעון Shimon dies. Right.
So in the second case, so number one is the same, okay,
you have ראובן, Reuven, רחל, Rachel, and שמעון Shimon around. Step number
two is the same,
ראובן Reuven died and רחל Rachel is
just around. Now here's where they reverse.
Then now לוי Levi is born. So what is the relationship here
of לוי Levi to רחל? Rachel? Right? That's the question. Now that
לוי Levi is born and רחל Rachel is already married to שמעון,
Shimon, maybe her past relationship to ראובן Reuven is irrelevant and maybe
she's not seen as his אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. eshes achiv
shelo haya be'olamo. And when שמעון Shimon dies maybe he'll be able,
לוי Levi will be able to do יבום. Yibbum. So that's what
right now what he's applying. So that's what—so that's what רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, oh, according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he says great, you're golden. Right? In this case,
רחל Rachel is not a problem because when you were born, she
was already married to שמעון. Shimon. So now what רב אושעיה Rav
Oshaya is saying is, okay. This is our second משנה. mishna. If
the rabbis say, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's okay and
the—you know, the רבנן, rabbanan, the תנא קמא tana kamma say it's
no good, they say ערוה. ervah. Okay? That even in this case,
she's an ערוה, ervah, okay? Because nevertheless, even though they were already
married, she still carries over—she retains the status, you know, that she
had over here. Okay? So here's what רב אושעיה Rav Oshaya is
saying. If the rabbis say even here it's no good—in this case,
you could easily understand רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position that it should
be fine—then you don't have to teach me this משנה mishna according
to the rabbis. Obviously this is no good. She became an ערוה
ervah before לוי Levi was born, right? I mean, right? I mean,
she became an ערוה ervah before they got married. So why did
we have our first משנה? mishna? It wasn't to tell me that
for the רבנן rabbanan it's a problem, to tell me this is
a problem for the רבנן rabbanan and then obviously this is going
to be a problem. So the only reason to tell me this
first משנה mishna was to let you know that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would say that even this משנה mishna is okay, that even
here, even though she's אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, eshes achiv shelo
haya be'olamo, that transforms after שמעון Shimon marries her and it goes
away. Okay? So that is what רב אושעיה's Rav Oshaya argument is.
If—if
why not just teach this משנה? mishna? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
it's okay and the rabbis say it's no good, and even in
this extreme
case the rabbis say it's no good, as this is the only
case that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's okay. Why do you
need this first משנה? mishna?
The only reason you need this first משנה mishna what's counterbalancing?
Just to—just to lay out the scenario.
I understand. So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say, that's
what רב פפא's Rav Pappa going to say. But he wants to
say, ah, it's superfluous.
He's saying it's superfluous.
We could've figured it all out from this משנה. mishna. The only
reason to tell me this is if you want to be מחדש
mechadesh to me that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would מתיר matir even
that case.
I'm sorry to interrupt, I want to ask just something very, very
basic. In the first scenario,
there's a—there's a wedding, right? Yeah. Okay. So then if שמעון Shimon
dies,
is לוי Levi חייב chayav in יבום Yibbum for the wife?
In the first scenario? Yeah. No, that's the whole point, because she's
ערוה. ervah. She remains an ערוה. ervah. That's the point of the
משנה. mishna.
I understand that. I—what I don't get is it's always the case
that the woman who had been an ערוה ervah then is always...
No. The יבום Yibbum overrides the ערוה ervah of the current marriage,
but she had an ערוה ervah status from her previous marriage, and
she carries it with her into this marriage. So it's like—it's like
he married his daughter. It's like the first משנה, mishna, where there's
a different ערוה ervah that's in the picture. Okay?
Yep. Alright. So—alright, so that's רב אושעיה's Rav Oshaya argument, that the
first משנה mishna is obviously a bigger problem, and you don't need—if
the rabbis have a problem with the second משנה mishna they certainly
do with the first
משנה. mishna. אלא לאו Ela lav רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon איצטריך, itztarich,
it's telling me for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so that ותנא רישא
להודיע כחו דרבי שמעון, ve'tana reisha lehodeia kocho de'Rabbi Shimon, so the
first משנה's mishna a חידוש chiddush of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that
even if לוי Levi was born before יבום, Yibbum, he remains forbidden...
I'm sorry, that even if לוי Levi was born before יבום, Yibbum,
she becomes permitted. להודיע
כחו דרבי שמעון. lehodeia kocho de'Rabbi Shimon. ותנא סיפא להודיע כחו דרבנן,
ve'tana seifa lehodeia kocho de'rabbanan, the סיפא seifa is the חידוש chiddush
of the רבנן, rabbanan, that even if יבום Yibbum occurred—even if לוי
Levi was born after
יבום—according Yibbum to the רבנן rabbanan she remains forbidden. Okay, so להודיע
כחו דרבנן. lehodeia kocho de'rabbanan. ובדין הוא דניפליג Uve'din hu deniflig רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon ברישא, bereisha, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon really should
have spoken up in the first משנה, mishna, because that's his big
חידוש chiddush according to this, that even in that first משנה mishna
he'll say that she's permitted.
אלא נטרו להו לרבנן עד דמסיימי למילתייהו, Ela natru lehu lerabbanan ad
demesaymi lemilsaihu, he wanted to give the rabbis a chance to finish
what they were saying. Okay, והדר פליג עלייהו, vehadar palig aleihu, and
then he voiced his opposition, but he—after they got through their whole
sentence he voiced his opposition, but his opposition was relevant even to
the beginning.
Isn't that always the case in a מחלוקת, machlokes, that one person
states their opinion and then another...
I know, but he has to say it here because there are
two scenarios, and you should be arguing on the first scenario.
Oh, instead of bringing a different scenario...
Why did you wait to argue on the second scenario? You should've
voiced—okay, he wanted to voice it, but he let them lay
out... All right. So anyway, now we have that according to רבי
שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, he—an enormous חידוש, chiddush, that even if לוי Levi
comes into the world before יבום, yibum, רחל Rachel is permitted. So
let's take a
look. אלא אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו לרבי שמעון היכי משכחת לה?
ella eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo l'Rebbi Shimon heichi mashkachas lah? So
okay, one minute. If that's true, when will you ever have a
scenario of אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo
according to you? Because even if לוי Levi is born, רחל Rachel
hasn't had יבום yibum and she's
okay. So היכי משכחת לה? heichi mashkachas lah? Says the גמרא: Gemara:
בחד אחא ומית ונולד לו אח. b'chad acha u'meis v'nolad lo ach.
ונולד לו
אח. v'nolad lo ach. Says the גמרא: Gemara: Yeah, you know how
you'll have it because okay, I have to tell you now why
the גמרא Gemara is going to
say—let me ask you: Why do you think with רב אושעיא's Rav
Oshaya weird idea that even in this case רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon
says it's allowed, why do you think that's going to be? Why
should it be allowed in this case? Isn't she אשת אחי שלא
היה בעולמו, eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo, right? She certainly is at
stage number three or she seems to be. So how do you
think רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya could say that רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan
will say it's not a problem?
Once שמעון Shimon does
יבום—right. yibum So you could say yes, at
this stage it is a problem, but as soon as שמעון Shimon
does יבום, yibum, her whole status
changes. If she was לוי's Levi daughter, that status wouldn't change. But
since this is a status based on relationships to brothers,
that
status gets redefined after יבום. yibum. That I think is the most
normal thing to say. What we're going to find out is that
the גמרא Gemara is going to develop it that that's actually not
what רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya is saying. רב אושעיא Rav Oshaya is
actually saying: You know why לוי Levi is not—you know why she's
not a problem here? Because even though it's similar but it's even
sharper, because here you would have to say it transformed. It started
as ערווה ervah and it transformed. גמרא Gemara says: Yeah, I would
say this but I know I got it I would say too,
but the גמרא Gemara says no, it doesn't transform. Even when she
was born, she was already—רחל Rachel was already, even before לוי Levi
was born, רחל Rachel was already
in a relationship with שמעון Shimon even though it wasn't יבום. yibum.
It was זיקה. zikah. So what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say is that if she is a זיקה zikah with him, right,
if she's a זיקה zikah with him, then when he's born, it's
the marriage—it's already she's already in a relationship with שמעון. Shimon. Okay?
So that's how the גמרא Gemara is going to explain it. It's
not the יבום yibum necessarily that transformed and then she went from
being ערווה ervah to not ערווה, ervah, it's that when לוי Levi
was born in this case, she's already not an ערווה ervah because
she's already sort of in a relationship with שמעון. Shimon. Okay? So
that's how the גמרא Gemara is going to explain it. So then
the גמרא Gemara wants to say: So when will you ever have
a case of אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו? eshas achiv shelo hayah
b'olamo?
So the first answer is: No, you'll have a case of אשת
אחי שלא היה בעולמו eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo if there's only
two brothers. ראובן Reuven is married to רחל. Rachel. ראובן Reuven dies
and then שמעון Shimon is born—and let's say לוי, Levi, we'll often
do that. ראובן Reuven dies and then לוי Levi is born. So
then רחל Rachel is אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו. eshas achiv shelo
hayah b'olamo. Okay, you won't have the case of our משנה Mishnah
where it will be one of the fifteen ערוות ervos that's married
to a brother and then there'll be a צרת ערווה tzaras ervah
case. But if you want to just know when will you have
a scenario of אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו, eshas achiv shelo hayah
b'olamo, sure, if you take שמעון Shimon out of the picture, you'll
have אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו. eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo. It's
שמעון's Shimon presence, either because of זיקה zikah or יבום yibum that
transforms it. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says: אשת אחי שלא היה
בעולמו היכי משכחת לה eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo heichi mashkachas lah
according to רבי שמעון? Rebbi Shimon? So the answer is: בחד אחא
ומית ונולד לו אח. b'chad acha u'meis v'nolad lo ach. You take
out שמעון. Shimon. ראובן Reuven died and then לוי Levi is born.
In that case, רחל Rachel is אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו. eshas
achiv shelo hayah b'olamo. You don't have שמעון Shimon to transform her
status. אינמי בתרי ולא יבם ולא מית. inami b'trei v'lo yibem v'lo
meis. Or שמעון Shimon never did יבום. yibum. So as long as
שמעון Shimon hasn't done יבום, yibum, if לוי Levi were to have
sex with רחל, Rachel, that would be אשת אחי שלא היה בעולמו.
eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo. So this—it's only because he does שמעון
Shimon that it transforms. So this
line seems to say that it is שמעון's Shimon act of יבום
yibum that actually transforms her status, right? Which is what we would
have said. But the גמרא Gemara is actually going to sort of
gloss over that and really speak much more that it's the זיקה
zikah that transforms her status. So let's keep on going.
And if you say יבום, yibum, let's discuss
what we're usually going to do. Yeah. Okay. So again, it is
a little bit of a question with the גמרא Gemara we're about
to read—is it necessary that the יבום yibum took place
in the end or not? According to this, he hadn't done יבום
yibum yet. It's—that's sort of a temporary status, right? אשת אחי שלא
היה בעולמו. eshas achiv shelo hayah b'olamo. Right? Until the יבום. yibum.
Right. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא יבם
ואחר כך נולד. bishlama yibem v'achar kach nolad. Now the גמרא Gemara
is going to spell out the logic, okay? בשלמא יבם ואחר כך
נולד, bishlama yibem v'achar kach nolad, I get the second משנה Mishnah
why רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would have to say it's okay if
לוי Levi is born and she's already יבום yibum has occurred, כי
אתיא בהיתרא אתיא. ki asya b'heitera asya. When לוי Levi found רחל,
Rachel, she was already in a state of היתר. heiter. She was
married to שמעון. Shimon. Again, not exactly היתר, heiter, but it's something
that could be היתר heiter if שמעון Shimon dies and so on.
So she's in a new relationship. relationship. אלא נולד אחר היבום, Ela
nolad achar ha-yibum, if לוי Levi was born and then יבום yibum
took place, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? So how is רחל Rachel not
an ערווה? ervah? So again we would have said, well maybe she
is but she got transformed, but that's not what the גמרא Gemara
says. The גמרא Gemara says now, קסבר יש זיקה, Kasavar yesh zika,
number one, זיקה zika is a phenomenon. Now how far, what's the
power of זיקה, zika, that's always a question. Until now we discussed
זיקה zika as making relatives forbidden, you know, sort of like אחות
זקוקתו. achot zikukato. Here we're going to go further, קסבר יש זיקה
Kasavar yesh zika וזיקה ככנוסה דמיא. ve-zika ke-knusa damya. Not only is
there זיקה, zika, זיקה zika is like they're already fully married. כנוסה
knusa is—is a word for sort of saying like he was מיבם
meyabem her. Okay, it's also a word that could be used in
a קידושין kiddushin context of נישואין. nisu'in. Okay. So it's not only
יש זיקה, yesh zika, יש זיקה yesh zika and it really is
like, you know, the יבום yibum has already occurred to—I mean obviously
to some degree, not עד הסוף, ad ha-sof, you have to still
do a מצוה mitzva of יבום. yibum. So therefore when לוי Levi
was born, the זיקה zika with שמעון Shimon was strong enough that
already רחל Rachel was no longer seen as אשת ראובן. eshet Reuven.
She was already seen as אשת שמעון—שמעון'ס wife. Yep. Okay. מתיב ליה
רב יוסף, Masiv lei Rav Yosef, so that's רב אושעיא'ס Rav Oshaya's
claim of what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say. So מתיב ליה
רב יוסף, Masiv lei Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks on
this. השתא זיקה ומאמר מספקא ליה לרבי שמעון אי ככנוסה דמיא אי
לא ככנוסה דמיא. Hashta zika u-ma'amar misafeka lei le-Rabbi Shimon ei ke-knusa
damya ei lo ke-knusa damya. I will show you that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon actually doesn't know if the combination of זיקה zika and
מאמר ma'amar makes the woman like כנוסה, knusa, like he's already fully
married. Okay. I'll show you that in a minute. Then, זיקה לחודה
מיבעיא? zika le-chuda mibaya? There's not even a question about זיקה zika
by itself. You can't tell me for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon זיקה
zika makes it like he's already married to שמעון. Shimon. I'm going
to show you for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even זיקה zika plus
מאמר ma'amar
is doubtful whether that does enough. What's the case? מאי
היא? Mai hi? What's the case? דתנן: De-tenan: שלושה אחים נשואים שלוש
נשים נכריות. Shlosha achim nesu'im shalosh nashim nochriyot. Three brothers married to
three unrelated women, that's what the word נכריות nochriyot means here.
ומת אחד מהם ועשה בה שני
מאמר ומת.
U-mes echad me-hem ve-asa bah
sheni ma'amar u-mes.
Okay, and one died, this—here, we'll do this, because we did this
on שבת Shabbos with the figurines or whatever they're called. Okay, manipulate,
basically manipulate them. So here what you have is—I'll describe the scenario.
You've got, okay, רחל Rachel here is married to ראובן, Reuven, and
you've got שמעון Shimon and לוי. Levi. I don't know if this
is going to—I'll use the board. Rabbi Lynch, just quick while you're
doing this, quick question. Only the word יבם yabam assumes that there
was a sexual relationship to consummate the—the— זיקה zika does not and
כנוסה knusa does not? Right. כנוסה knusa is more her state, but
yes, correct. Okay, so here you've got—I'm going to write this. Let's
look down here. Okay, so here you've got, okay, and she's entered—ראובן,
Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, לוי. Levi. Great relationship. Okay, so שמעון Shimon is
married to שרה, Sarah, I'm going to use his wife. ראובן Reuven
is married to רחל. Rachel. Okay. ראובן Reuven dies. שמעון Shimon does
the זיקה, zika, שמעון Shimon does מאמר ma'amar with רחל, Rachel, but
he has not been מיבם meyabem her yet. Okay. Yes? And then
of course what happens? He dies. שמעון Shimon dies. We'll lodge him
on the board. So fine. Now, what's לוי'ס Levi's story vis-a-vis רחל?
Rachel? If he hadn't done מאמר ma'amar to רחל, Rachel, לוי Levi
would do—could do יבום yibum with רחל Rachel because she had been
ראובן'ס Reuven's wife. If שמעון Shimon had done יבום yibum with רחל,
Rachel, לוי Levi could do יבום yibum with רחל Rachel because she's
שמעון'ס Shimon's wife and ראובן'ס—her Reuven's status as ראובן'ס Reuven's wife is
irrelevant. Transformed. In this case though, רחל Rachel has a dual status.
לוי'ס Levi's relationship to her is, number one, there's a יבום yibum
as ראובן'ס Reuven's wife, right? That's one possibility. And number two, a
יבום yibum as שמעון'ס Shimon's pseudo-wife because of the מאמר. ma'amar. Okay,
right? You got that? Now, because since it was only the מאמר
ma'amar and not a real יבום, yibum, she still—her identity as ראובן'ס
Reuven's wife still obtains, right? So therefore רחל Rachel now to לוי
Levi has a—has a double זיקה. zika. A זיקה zika from—right, from
two different brothers on her. The דאורייתא de-oraita זיקה zika as ראובן'ס
Reuven's brother and the דרבנן de-rabbanan זיקה zika as שמעון'ס—as Shimon's
שמעון'ס Shimon's wife through the מאמר. ma'amar. And therefore we're going to
say that only—you—that that's going—they learn from a פסוק, pasuk, actually it's
not really a פסוק pasuk because it's all דרבנן, de-rabbanan, but okay,
they learn that you
cannot do יבום yibum in that case. You can only do יבום
yibum if there's a relationship—if
she's connected—if it's a זיקה zika of
one brother, not competing זיקות. zikot. So she just—she does חליצה chalitza
with both, right? Well, yes. Yes, so he would have to do
יבום, yibum, but then it starts looking like צרת ערווה, tzarat ervah,
so he does חליצה chalitza for the צרה. tzara. Okay. So you
just—you just do it with both? Yeah, he has to do חליצה
chalitza with both because דאורייתא de-oraita this doesn't exist. So דאורייתא de-oraita
he has to actually do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza with both.
So even though דרבנן de-rabbanan because of this dual status we don't
let him do יבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, he has to wind
up doing חליצה chalitza with both. That is correct. Okay, so that's
the הלכה. halacha. So let's take a look at how that plays,
how that's relevant for us. Okay, so ומת אחד מהם *u'meis echad
meihem*, Reuven died. ועשה השני מאמר ma'amar, *v'asa hasheini
maamar*, and then Shimon did a מאמר ma'amar *maamar* with רחל Rachel
*Rochel*. ומת *u'meis*, and then Shimon dies. הרי אלו *harei eilu*, both
women חולצות *cholsos* ולא מתייבמות *v'lo misyabmos*. See, Michael exactly got it.
Okay, because דאורייתא de'oraita *d'Oraisa* he has a חיוב *chiyuv* on each
one separately, one from Reuven and one from Shimon. So he can't
get out of that. But we're not going to let him act
on it because of רחל Rachel *Rochel*'s double status. And therefore that
makes, that then makes שרה Sarah *Sarah* a type of, a type
of ערוה erva *ervah*, so a צרת ערוה *tzaras ervah*. Okay, שנאמר
shene-emar, *shenemar*, ומת אחד מהם *u'meis echad meihem*, one
dies, יבמה יבא עליה *yevamah yavo aleha*. מי שיש לה זיקת יבם
אחד *mi she'yesh lah zikas yavam echad*, so a woman who there's
only זיקה zika *zika* of one brother. ולא שיש לה זיקת שני
יבמים zikat shenei yevamim. *v'lo she'yesh lah zikas shenei yevamin*, not now
רחל Rachel *Rochel* that is connected to לוי Levi *Levi* both through
ראובן Reuven *Reuven* and through שמעון Shimon *Shimon*. Okay, so that's the
הלכה halacha. *halacha*. We've actually seen that before if you remember. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer*, מיבם לאיזו מהן שירצה וחולץ
לשנייה *meyabem l'eizo meihen she'yirtzeh v'choleitz lashniyah*. No, he denies that there's
a problem of a double זיקה zika *zika*. He's not bothered with
this double זיקה zika? *zika* idea. I don't buy into this double
זיקה zika *zika* problem. So if he doesn't buy into this double
זיקה zika. *zika* problem, then you should say do ייבום yibum, *yibum*
with one and you could even do ייבום yibum *yibum* with both,
right? If you don't buy into the double זיקה zika? *zika* problem,
you do ייבום yibum *yibum* with רחל Rachel *Rochel* as אשת ראובן
Reuven... *eisheis Reuven* and ייבום yibum *yibum* with שרה Sarah *Sarah* as
אשת שמעון eshet Shimon *eisheis Shimon*. But no, he says do ייבום
yibum *yibum* with whichever one you want because I don't see this
double status problem, but the other needs חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*. Why does
the other need חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*?
Why can't you do ייבום yibum *yibum* with the other one?
So let's take a look. There might be a problem. Well no,
let's take a look. Let's let the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* say. Okay.
יבומי תרוייהו לא *yabomei tarvaihu lo*. Why not do ייבום yibum *yibum*
with both? דילמא dilma, יש זיקה yesh zika והוי שתי
יבמות הבאות מבית אחד *dilma yeish zika v'havei shtei yevamos habaos mibeis
echad*.
So he's saying like this.
The reason is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
*Rabbi Shimon* does not hold that רחל Rachel *Rochel* has a dual
status problem. But here's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*'s question. Maybe
because of the מאמר ma'amar *maamar* with שמעון Shimon *Shimon*, maybe רחל
Rachel *Rochel* really is fully שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s wife. You know, ככנוסה
דמיא k'knusa damya. *k'chnusah damya*. That's the idea. זיקה zika *zika* and
מאמר ma'amar ככנוסה דמיא k'knusa damya, *maamar k'chnusah
damya*. And
if I really consider her to be fully שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s wife
because of מאמר ma'amar *maamar* and זיקה zika *zika*, then when שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* died, could לוי Levi *Levi* do ייבום yibum *yibum* with
both? No. You can only do ייבום yibum *yibum* with one of
your brother's wives and then the others are exempt, right? So he's
not going to let him do ייבום yibum *yibum* with both because
she might be fully שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s wife. Why does he have
to do חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* with the other?
Because she might not be fully שמעון Shimon.
*Shimon*'s wife, and then she's ראובן Reuven *Reuven*'s wife and
then you have to do them separate, because the act of one
doesn't affect the other.
Oh, is that considered like a חליצה chalitza דרבנן *chalitzah d'Rabbanan*? No,
it sounds like the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying it's actually he
has a real ספק safek *safek* what רחל Rachel *Rochel*'s status is.
He doesn't buy into that she's a dual status. He says her
status is a ספק safek, *safek*. I don't know whether to treat
רחל Rachel *Rochel* with the presence of זיקה zika *zika* and מאמר
ma'amar *maamar* as ראובן Reuven *Reuven*'s wife or שמעון Shimon, *Shimon*'s wife.
So to treat her, so if you want to do ייבום Yibum
*yibum* with רחל Rachel. *Rochel* because hey, there's no double status, so
do ייבום Yibum *yibum* either as ראובן Reuven *Reuven* or as שמעון
Shimon, *Shimon*. But what's שרה Sarah. *Sarah*'s story? So you can't do
ייבום Yibum *yibum* with שרה Sarah *Sarah* because she might have been
שמעון Shimon... *Shimon*'s wife, רחל Rachel *Rochel* might have been שמעון Shimon
*Shimon*'s wife, you can't do, so you would have to do חליצה
chalitza *chalitzah* with שרה Sarah? *Sarah*. You can't ignore שרה Sarah *Sarah*
because רחל Rachel, *Rochel* might have been ראובן Reuven *Reuven*'s wife. So
therefore you have to do חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*. Is that clear? Right,
I mean, ספק safek. רחל Rachel *safek Rochel* can't marry a כהן
*kohen* either because she just, because she had חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*. Right.
Right. It's a חליצת ספק safek. *chalitzas safek*. So let's read that
again. יבומי תרוייהו לא *yabomei tarvaihu lo*. You can't do ייבום *yibum*
both with רחל Rachel *Rochel* and with שרה Sarah. *Sarah*. דילמא יש
זיקה zika *dilma yeish zika*. Maybe there's זיקה zika *zika* plus מאמר
ma'amar, *maamar*, and maybe רחל Rachel *Rochel* is fully שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s
wife. And therefore, if she's fully שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s wife, you can't
do ייבום *yibum* to two wives of one brother. והוי שתי יבמות
הבאות מבית אחד *v'havei shtei yevamos habaos mibeis echad*. Two sisters-in-law from
one household, you can't do ייבום *yibum* with both. So you can't
do ייבום *yibum* with both of them. יבומי חדא ופטר אידך *yabomei
chada u'fatar idach*. Let's do ייבום *yibum* with רחל Rachel *Rochel* and
forget שרה *Sarah* because, ah, I did ייבום *yibum* with one, the
other one is off. No, that you can't do. דילמא אין זיקה
ein zika, ככנוסה *dilma ein zika k'chnusah*. Maybe she's not considered שמעון
Shimon *Shimon*'s wife, maybe she's ראובן Reuven *Reuven*'s wife. והוו להו שתי
יבמות הבאות משני בתים *v'havu lehu shtei yevamos habaos mishnei batim*. And
they're coming from a different brother. So therefore you have to do
ייבום *yibum* with one and חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* with the other. Okay.
So as opposed to the Rabbis that say she has a dual
status, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says she has a doubtful
status. So she's either treated as ראובן Reuven *Reuven*'s wife or treated
as שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s wife. Okay. So what do you see from
this, as everybody's eyes glossing over, do people have the, okay, stop
checking your cell phones people, everybody. So okay, so if she has
a doubt, so what we see is that a woman who has
זיקה zika *zika* plus מאמר ma'amar *maamar* might be fully considered to
be that man's wife, but might not. And that's what the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* is saying. You cannot tell me back here that, remember
back here רחל Rachel *Rochel*... Gets out of the problem for לוי
Levi because the זיקה zika. makes her like שמעון's Shimon wife and
he doesn't have a problem. We see that even when there's זיקה
zika and מאמר, ma'amar there's a question to what degree she is
considered the next man's wife or not. Remind us where the פסוק
pasuk that laid the foundation for זיקה? zika, There is no פסוק.
pasuk. That's what I said the other day. The גמרא, Gemara the
גמרא—well Gemara the fascinating thing about זיקה zika is that the גמרא,
Gemara it's completely a דאורייתא de'oraita idea, and the גמרא Gemara just
assumes that that's the mechanism that's at work with ייבום, but it
doesn't base it on any פסוק. pasuk. And there is an idea
of אין זיקה, zika but you know, but that's like an assumption
of what is the underlying mechanism without the פסוק pasuk actually talking
about it. Okay. So, aha. Okay. So anyway, ואבושעיה... Va'Aboshaya... okay, so
the גמרא Gemara. says אלמא מספקא ליה. alma mesapka lei. So you
see that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. says that this case of רחל
Rachel, that שמעון Shimon did מאמר ma'amar to is maybe שמעון's Shimon
wife, maybe ראובן's Reuven wife, okay, and that's with מאמר ma'amar plus
זיקה. zika So how can you tell me that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would say לוי's Levi. no problem over there with רחל Rachel?
because she's already like שמעון's Shimon wife because of זיקה? zika If
זיקה zika. plus מאמר ma'amar, might not work, how could זיקה zika
alone work? Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא מדאורייתא הכי נמי דמיבמא חדא
ומפטרא חדא. vechi teima mide'oraita hachi nami demiyabma chada umifatra chada. Maybe
you'll say like this: really רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say in
this case down here that the presence of זיקה zika really makes
רחל Rachel fully שמעון's Shimon wife. And really דאורייתא de'oraisa he could
just have done ייבום with רחל Rachel, and שרה would have been
off the hook. And he really holds זיקה ככנוסה דמיא. zika ke'knusa
damya. מדאורייתא
ומפטרא. mide'oraita umifatra. ומדרבנן הוא דאסור. umiderabbanan hu de'asur. And it's only
reason he has to do a חליצה chalitza with שרה is מדרבנן,
miderabbanan, גזירה משום שיאמרו שתי יבמות הבאות משני בתים חדא מיבמא ואידך
מיפטרא בלא כלום, gezeira mishum sheyomeru shtei yevamot haba'ot mishnei batim chada
miyabma ve'idach mifatra bela klum, because people will say if you have
two sister-in-laws that come from two different brothers,
you just have to do ייבום with one and you can ignore
the other one. So now what we're saying is—this is getting confusing,
I know, as if it weren't confusing enough. But remember, we're saying
here, the claim is that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says רחל Rachel,
is not
a problem when לוי Levi, is born. Why is רחל Rachel. not
a problem? Because רחל Rachel already has זיקה zika to שמעון Shimon.
and that makes her like she's already married to שמעון. So רבי
אושעיא's Rabbi Oshaya claim is that רחל's Rachel זיקה zika to שמעון,
זיקה zika to שמעון, makes her strong enough, is strong enough that
by the time לוי Levi is born, she's good. Okay? So that's
זיקה ככנוסה zika ke'knusa according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon Okay, so
that's רבי אושעיא's Rabbi Oshaya claim. But then you've got this story
down here. Okay, I'm going to write it a little bit higher
up so you can see it. Then you've got this story down
here—maybe I'll do it all to the same direction.
שמעון...
ראובן... Reuven no, I'll do it like this. ראובן is married to...
yeah,
ראובן is married to רחל. Rachel שמעון married to שרה. And לוי.
Levi They're all around at the same time. Okay. ראובן dies. So
now שמעון's relationship to רחל Rachel is with מאמר ma'amar plus זיקה.
zika
And here though you have מאמר ma'amar and זיקה zika that שמעון
is now related to both of them, right? לוי, Levi we saw
from that, that לוי Levi cannot do ייבום with one and forget
the other. So if שמעון was really considered just by the זיקה,
zika if she was really considered fully married to רחל, Rachel he
could have done ייבום with one and forget the other. But he
can't, he has to do ייבום with one and חליצה chalitza with
the other. So that shows that this relationship is not fully like
they're married, right? Yeah? Everybody with me? So now the גמרא Gemara
will say: wait, no, I'm going to claim right back here that
actually even זיקה zika alone, they are really fully married as it
were. And לוי Levi really could just do ייבום with רחל Rachel
and walk away.
And שרה could walk away. It's מחזי. mechazei. But why do we
demand that he do חליצה chalitza with שרה? Right. For the appearances.
Even though הלכתא hilchata these are both fully שמעון's wife and you
could just do one and forget about the other, the appearance is
that רחל is ראובן's wife and
שרה is שמעון's wife. And if you let him just do ייבום
with one and forget the other then people will say if you
have two wives from two different brothers, you can do the ייבום
with one of them and forget about the other one. So because
it looks like רחל is ראובן's wife, we demand that he do
a חליצה chalitza with שרה. But maybe really זיקה zika is enough
and really she is fully שמעון's wife. Okay. So that's the question.
So next...
I just want to...
No, I want to read it first in the גמרא. Gemara Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so where were we? So וכי תימא מדאורייתא הכי נמי דמיבמא חדא
ומפטרא חדא. vechi teima mide'oraita hachi nami demiyabma chada umifatra chada. Really
he could just do ייבום with one. and the other could walk
away, and מדרבנן הוא דאסור, miderabbanan hu de'asur, but it's just מדרבנן
miderabbanan we demand that Levi do חליצה chalitza with Sarah. Why?
Because מדרבנן הוא דאסור, miderabbanan hu de'asur, גזירה משום שמא ימות ואיזהו
יבמות הבאות משני בתים חדא מיבם ואידך מיפטרה בלא כלום, gezeira mishum
shema yamut ve'eizehu yevamos habaos mishnei batim chada miyabbem ve'idach miftara belo
klum, because it looks like Rachel is Reuben's wife, and then people
will say you have two different wives coming from two different brothers,
you do יבום yibbum with one and you can ignore the other.
So because of appearances, we won't allow it. But maybe אין הכי
נמי, ein hachi nami, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon will say that זיקה
zika alone, certainly זיקה zika plus מאמר, Ma'amar actually makes the woman
fully considered to be דאורייתא like the man's wife. And that would
therefore be why it would not be a case of אשת אח
שלא היה בעולמו eishet ach shelo haya be'olamo by the time Levi
is born. Yes, you had a question, Dov?
Yeah, I just wanted to just wanted to check the conceptualization of
this of זיקה. zika In other words, if basically they're saying that
my sister-in-law, in a way, is a wife-like relationship to me.
Is that what you'd say?
Yeah, in the context of a מצוות יבום. mitzat yibbum. Yeah. That's
what כקנוסה דמי keknusa dami means. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
that's all very nice, but we have a ברייתא braisa that makes
it clear that that's not what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying,
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is about her ספק safek status like
we said before. So let's take a look. טעמיה דרבי שמעון משום
מאמר ולאו מאמר הוא. ta'ameih deRabbi Shimon mishum ma'amar velav ma'amar hu.
That's not true. It's not because זיקה zika alone makes it the
wife, but it's a גזירה. gezeira. No. It's because
the מאמר that Shimon did to Rachel might make Rachel like his
wife. And that it's the מאמר is important and that it's a
ספק, safek it's not a גזירה. gezeira. Okay. How do you know
this? דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא. braisa. אמר להם רבי
שמעון לחכמים, amar lahem Rabbi Shimon lachachamim, Rabbi Shimon said to the
חכמים: chachamim: אם מאמרו של שני מאמר, im ma'amaro shel sheni ma'amar,
if Shimon's מאמר is meaningful, אשת שני הוא בועל, eishet sheni hu
bo'el, then Levi can do יבום yibbum with Rachel because she's Shimon's
wife. ואם מאמרו של שני אינו מאמר, ve'im ma'amaro shel sheni eino
ma'amar, and if it's not meaningful, אשת ראשון הוא בועל, eishet rishon
hu bo'el, then he could also do יבום yibbum with Rachel as
Reuben's wife. So what he's saying is I don't understand why you
say he can never do יבום yibbum with Rachel. Rachel is either
Reuben's wife or Shimon's wife. And the rabbis say, no, no, no,
she's like a little bit of both, right? So whereas the rabbis
say she has a double status, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says she's
either... no, he's either-or, it's a ספק. It's not double, it's a
ספק. But let him do יבום yibbum either as Reuben's wife or
as Shimon's wife. But you see that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon has
a doubt what status she has. So it is not that the
זיקה zika definitely makes her Shimon's wife. There's a question what status
she has. Okay? Let's just read it. So he says: ואם
מאמרו של שני אינו מאמר אשת ראשון הוא בועל. ve'im ma'amaro shel
sheni eino ma'amar eishet rishon hu bo'el. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei
Abaye, ולא שני לך, velo shani lach, okay, אביי Abaye still going
to try, it seems pretty clear, but אביי Abaye still going to
try to preserve it. ולא שני לך בין זיקת יבם אחד לזיקת
שני יבמים?
velo shani lach bein zikat yavam echad
lezikat shenei yevamim? You don't think there could be a difference between
whether there's one brother-in-law or two brothers-in-law? דילמא, כי אמר רבי שמעון
זיקה כקנוסה דמיא, ki amar Rabbi Shimon zika keknusa damya, maybe זיקה
zika works and it makes her like a wife, but that's ביבם
אחד, beyavam echad, when there's only one brother-in-law, so it's clear who
the זיקה zika is to. אבל בשני יבמים לא, aval beshnei yevamim
lo, but not when two brothers-in-law. Which means what? We're really not
giving it up. Okay, fine. I concede that in this case it's
not a גזירה. gezeira. In this case, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon is
very clear that his issue is that we don't know whether Rachel
is considered Shimon's wife or considered Levi's Reuben's wife. So there's a
question whether זיקה zika. and מאמר really works. But here's what he
says. Here's how זיקה zekah really will make her like Shimon's wife.
What's the difference? Here the זיקה zekah, occurred before Levi was born.
The זיקה zekah occurred before Levi was born, there was only זיקה
zekah, to only one clear brother. So in this case זיקה zekah
alone works to make it like Shimon's wife. In this case, when
Reuben died, Rachel has a זיקה zekah both to Shimon and to
Levi. So that's why you can't say that it's clear that Rachel
is considered Shimon's wife even with the מאמר, because there's also Levi
in the picture. Okay? So here he should have a ספק as
to Rachel's status, זיקה zekah and מאמר might not be enough because
Levi is in the picture. Here זיקה Zika could totally make her
like Shimon's wife. Okay, so we're still maintaining that within רבי אושעיא
Rabbi Oshaya that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon would say this case is
okay, it's because זיקה Zika makes her like Shimon's wife, and that
that would work in a case when there's only one brother. You
had a question, Dov? Yeah?
Well, I have a question. You could say in the case that
there's three brothers, the חכמים chachamim would always say it's אסור asur
because you have זיקת שני יבמים. Yeah. No, but even... forget מאמר
or anything like that, right? In other words, if a brother... if
there's three brothers, right? None of the brothers is married. But this
one brother...
I'm going to confuse people. I'll ask answer you after. It's confusing
enough as it is. Let's keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay, so that's what אביי Abaye does. אביי Abaye
still wants to hold on to this idea and say זיקה Zika
works with one brother, and that gets her out of the ערווה
erva problem. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, ומשני ליה לרבי שמעון? u'mishani lei l'Rebbi Shimon? גמרא Gemara says
okay, fine. So now we have a hypothetical argument for Rebbi Oshaya
that Rebbi Shimon would sort of say this case is okay, and
the only way to explain it is Abaye's way, that when there's
only one brother around, the זיקה Zika is ככנוסה דמיא. ke-knusa damya
So the גמרא Gemara, is saying really? Does Rebbi Shimon really hold
of that difference, that one brother makes her ככנוסה דמיא, Keknusah damya,
two brothers not, and so on, and that that's his position here
that he argues even on this case? והתניא, ve'hatanya, let's look at
what we have in a ברייתא. braita. כלל אמר רבי שמעון, klal
amar Rebbi Shimon, Rebbi Shimon had a general
principle, and כל שהלידה קודמת לנישואין, kol she'haleida kodemes l'nisuin, לא חולצת
ולא מתייבמת. lo choletzes velo mityabemes. If the birth of Levi came
before Shimon and what do you call it, Shimon and what do
you call it, Shimon and Rachel, if the birth of Levi, right,
came before Shimon did יבום, yibum, that's נישואין. nisuin. It's interesting, he's
calling יבום yibum here נישואין. nisuin. So then, right, so then he's
going to say what we always know, that Rebbi Shimon is saying
that even in this case, that Rebbi Shimon concedes this case because
Levi is born before יבום, yibum, so Rachel is already אשת אחיו
שלא היה בעולמו. eshet achiv shelo hayah beolamo. Okay, so this is
going to be a ברייתא braita where Rebbi Shimon is going to
black and white say that he concedes that the first משנה mishna
is a problem because Rachel has there hasn't yet been יבום yibum
with Rachel. So let's read that.
Okay,
והתניא. ve'hatanya. כלל אמר רבי שמעון. klal amar Rebbi Shimon. כל שהלידה
קודמת לנישואין. kol she'haleida kodemes l'nisuin. If Levi was born before there
was יבום yibum with Rachel, לא חולצת ולא מתייבמת. lo choletzes velo
mityabemes. You don't need חליצה chalitza or יבום. yibum. Rachel is אסור
assur to him, אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, eshet achiv shelo hayah
beolamo, everybody walks away. נישואין קודמין ללידה, nisuin kodmin l'leida, if first
there was יבום yibum and then Levi was born, או חולצת או
מתייבמת, o choletzes o mityabemes, then he has a full obligation to
Rachel and you either do חליצה chalitza or יבום, yibum, right? Normal
case. So you see that it's very clear. Rebbi Shimon says his
position only in the second משנה, mishna, not in the first משנה.
mishna. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו ביבם אחד? mai lav
beyavam echad? So you see presumably we're talking that there's only Shimon
around before Levi is born, וקתני לא חולצת ולא מתייבמת, ve'katani lo
choletzes velo mityabemes, and you see that even though Shimon is the
only guy around, that the זיקה Zika is not enough to make
her like Shimon's wife and she's considered an ערוה and there's no
חליצה or יבום. yibum. הגמרא HaGemara says לא בשני יבמין. lo bishnei
yevamin. So as if this wasn't complicated enough, okay, we're saying actually
not only is Shimon around in this case before Levi is born,
if Shimon's around, so not only have you Shimon over here and
Levi's going to come later, I don't know, you have Yissachar. Okay.
So therefore because you have two brothers before Levi is born, when
Reuben dies the reason Rachel is going to be a problem for
Levi is because there's two brothers so there's not a clear זיקה.
Zika So you're right, we have a ברייתא braita that says Rebbi
Shimon concedes this case, but we're going to try to argue the
reason he concedes this case is that there are two brothers,
so therefore Rachel remains a problem. But if there was only one
brother,
Rachel would be like Shimon's wife and it wouldn't be a problem.
Now that's a very weak read,
no question about that, that's a very weak read of that ברייתא.
braita. The ברייתא braita seems to be very black and white and
the גמרא Gemara is going to admit to that. So let's just
get through this. מאי לאו ביבם אחד? mai lav beyavam echad? לא
בשני יבמין. lo bishnei yevamin. No, the reason that we have Rebbi
Shimon conceding that case is because there's Shimon and Yissachar around, so
we don't know, so Rachel's status remains אשת אחיו. eshet achiv. אבל,
aval, so the גמרא, Gemara what would you say? ביבם אחד מאי?
beyavam echad mai? What would you say if there's just Shimon? הכי
נמי או חולצת או מתייבמת? hachi nami o choletzes o mityabemes? Then
you would say that she would be like Shimon's wife and that
there wouldn't be a problem, Levi could go ahead and do חליצה
with her? אי הכי אדתני נישואין קודמין ללידה או חולצת או מתייבמת,
ei hachi adatani nisuin kodmin l'leida o choletzes o mityabemes, why then
to make her allowed did we have to give the case that
first there was יבום yibum and then Levi was born? ליתני בדידיה,
lisni bedidei, say even in a case when Levi was born before
יבום yibum you could have a case where she's permitted. במה דברים
אמורים בשני יבמין. bameh devarim amurim bishnei yevamin. When does Rachel remain
a problem? If there's Shimon and Yissachar around and then Levi is
born. אבל ביבם אחד, aval beyavam echad, if there's only Shimon around,
so then she's like Shimon's wife, so then and then Levi's born,
או חולצת או מתייבמת. o choletzes o mityabemes. So clearly it should
have given that case if that case really would be מותר. mutar.
הגמרא HaGemara says כולה בשני יבמין קמיירי. kulah bishnei yevamin kamayiri. No,
we want to talk about how this would play out with two
brothers with like, you know, Shimon and Yissachar before Levi is born
and therefore we're doing the variations within that rather than switching that
scenario to be one brother. All right, the גמרא Gemara still isn't
happy. ואלא מאי כלל? ve'ela mai klal? But then why does it
mean כלל אמר רבי שמעון? klal amar Rebbi Shimon? כלל אמר רבי
שמעון klal amar Rebbi Shimon is he's telling you this is the
only thing you have to look at, right? What the גמרא Gemara
is saying is You know, the that well if there was יששכר
Issachar around then the whole thing would just that would be one
thing because two brothers you're telling me are one brother really? But
כלל אמר רבי שמעון Klal amar Rebbe Shimon says there's only one
question that's relevant: was לוי Levi born before יבום yibum or was
לוי Levi. born after יבום? yibum? So basically, it's all very confusing,
but the upshot is that the גמרא Gemara is saying רב אושיה
Rav Oshaya please don't tell me that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon would
say that this case is a problem, that this case is okay
and that the זיקה gets רחל out of being the problem. We
have a ברייתא braita that very clearly says that רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon says the only thing that matters is was לוי Levi born
before יבום yibum or after, and makes it clear that if לוי
Levi. was born before יבום, yibum, he concedes that רחל is a
problem. Okay, so that's where we are and that's going to lead
to rejecting רב אושיה Rav Oshaya and just reading the פשט pshat
of the משנה mishna that the only case רבי Rebbe. שמעון disagrees
with is the case of what do you call it, is the
case of when יבום yibum occurred before לידה. leida. Yeah, you had
a question?
It seems like the תלמוד Talmud is building a case that whenever
there's a type of ספק with זיקה, nothing can bolster it. מאמר
doesn't help, in other words זיקה has to be unambiguous in order,
right?
I don't know if I would make that type of statement. Okay.
Is this the רב אושיה Rav Oshaya the תנא tanna who collected
ברייתות? braitot?
No,
no, that's רבי אושיה, Rebbe Oshaya, that's רבי. This is רב אושיה.
Rav Oshaya. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, ועוד.
ve-od. So anyway we have a clear ברייתא braita that makes it
clear that רבי שמעון says I'm only talking about a case where
first there was יבום yibum and then לידה. leida. The other case
I would concede is a
problem. ועוד, Ve-od, and in addition, מתיב רב אושיה. mative Rav Oshaya.
So רב אושיה, Rav Oshaya, so now we have a little bit
of a problem because רב אושיה Rav Oshaya was the one before
that said this whole thing. So if you look back, the גמרא
Gemara says somehow this gets to Charlie's question, רבי אושיה.
Rebbe
Oshaya.
Anyway back there, and here's רב אושיה.
Rav Oshaya. This is somebody else.
Somebody else is asking this question. ג' אחים, Gimmel achim, three
brothers. שנים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות, Shtayim mehem nesuim shtay achayot, two
of them are married to two sisters, או אישה ובתה, o isha
u-vitta,
a woman and her daughter, או אישה ובת בתה, o isha u-vat
bitta, או אישה ובת בנה. o isha u-vat bina. Basically the two
brothers are married to two women who you couldn't, a third party
couldn't be married to both of them at the same
time. ומתו, U-metu, and then they both die. Okay? So ראובן and
שמעון are married to two women who are, would be a problem
to be married to together. ראובן and שמעון both die, here's לוי.
Levi What does לוי Levi do? Okay? So you got the scenario
here? ראובן is married to רחל, שמעון is married to her sister
לאה. Leah. Okay, we have to lose the alliteration. Okay, they both
die and now you've got לוי. So what should לוי do? So
you could say well he can't do יבום yibum with both. So
he can't do יבום yibum with one, and the other one is
an ערווה erva and she walks away. That's it. Right. The problem
is what if he does יבום yibum with רחל? It winds up
that he is now having sex with אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato.
Right?
He already now he's got a זיקה, I'll do it, I'll try
to do זיקה with a dotted line because it's like unactualized. He's
got a זיקה with both of them. Right? If he goes ahead
and consummates with either one, then he's having sex with אחות זקוקתו,
achot zekukato, or over to mother and daughter he's having sex with
בת זקוקתו bat zekukato or אם זקוקתו. em zekukato. Okay, so he
can't consummate with either one. All right, so let's take a look.
And then doing חליצה won't help and
doing
חליצה with one won't help because they're from separate brothers. You have
to do חליצה with both. Okay. So why can't he do
חליצה
with one and then יבום yibum with the other? That could be
פסול. pasul. Let's take a look. ג' אחים שנים מהם נשואים שתי
אחיות או אישה ובתה או אישה ובת בנה או אישה ובת בתה
הרי אלו חולצות ולא מתייבמות. Gimmel achim shtayim mehem nesuim shtay achayot
o isha u-vitta o isha u-vat bina o isha u-vat bitta haray
elu choltzot ve-lo mityabmot. You do חליצה and you don't do יבום.
yibum. Okay, now why you can't do חליצה with one and יבום
yibum with the other, we'll hold that, that's a good question. רבי
שמעון פוטר. Rebbe Shimon potair. Now רבי שמעון exempts, which presumably means
that you do not have to, that he's going to have a
special פסוק pasuk that he's going to say in this scenario where
you have competing יבומים, yibumim, it gets everybody off the hook. You
just walk away, everybody walks away. Right. So it is a pretty
funny idea, but okay, I mean whatever, but that's what he says.
Now ואי סלקא דעתך חזר רבי שמעון זיקה ככנוסה דמיא, ve-i salka
daitach chazar Rebbe Shimon zekah ke-knusa damya,
one minute, your whole argument, remember, the whole argument here to explain
why רחל wouldn't be a problem is the זיקה makes her already
like married to שמעון. If that's true, ליבם לקמייתא ותיפטר אידך.
leyaben lekamaita ve-tiftar
idach. So he says so if she's already
like
ככנוסה דמיא like she's...
Oh no no, the keyword is לקמייתא. Lekamaisa.
Okay, Reuven and Shimon did not die at the same
time. So, if he already had a זיקה to רחל, okay, if
he already had a זיקה to רחל, right, and it was like
they were already married and then that's stage one and then stage
two Shimon Shimon here who's married to לאה Leah dies, okay, as
soon as Shimon dies, לאה Leah already becomes לאה's Leah already an
ערווה. Erva. He's already married to רחל. She's already an ערווה. Erva.
There's no זיקה to לאה. Leah. Right? So if זיקה ככנוסה דמיא,
Zika keknusah damya, then the first one who dies,
it's like he's married already. And then, and then that's just an
ערווה. Erva. לאה Leah is just an ערווה Erva to him. So
the scenario the way you did it a second ago was the
assumption the two brothers died simultaneously?
Well, I wasn't spelling out the as, spelling out the consequence here.
Okay, if they haven't we'll get to that. Okay. Yeah?
Does זיקה only take effect after one of the brothers dies? Right.
It's not a זיקה from,
oh from the time of marriage? No. Certainly not to say ככנוסה
דמיא, can't be like he's married to the woman while the husband's
still married. Right. Okay.
Okay, ואיכא דאמרי שמעון זיקה ככנוסה דמיא
Ve-ika d'amrei Shimon zika
keknusah damya וייבם לקמייתא. veyabem lekamaisa. So the first one do ייבום
ותיפטר אידך, vesiftar idach, the other one should get off. So אמר
רב עמרם Amar Rav Amram מאי פוטר נמי mai poter nami פוטר
בשנייה. poter bishniya. When it says he exempts, it doesn't mean he
says that he exempts both of the wives. It means the second
wife is exempt. Okay, so that's, okay, because remember it just says
Rebbe Shimon says פוטר. poter. So it means exactly what you said.
He does ייבום with the first one and the second one is
exempt. So the גמרא says one minute, והתניא ve-hatanya Rebbe Shimon פוטר
בשתיהן. poter bishteihen. He exempts both of them. So אמר רבא Amar
Rava שנייה שבזוג זה והשנייה שבזוג זה. Shniya she-bezug zeh ve-hashniya she-bezug
zeh. The second of both pairs. What does that mean? So Rava
has a very strange read of the משנה. Mishna. You know how
the ברייתא Braisa said, you know the ברייתא Braisa said two sisters,
or mother and daughter, or mother and granddaughter, etc.? Rava is going
to say that actually we're not saying "or," we're actually saying "and."
There are Reuven and Shimon are married to multiple pairs of wives.
So first they're married to רחל and לאה Leah that are sisters.
Okay, then they're married and that's one, then he's also married to,
and instead of being married to רחל and לאה, Leah, he's married
to, you know, I don't know who, whatever, we'll have to do
granddaughters, but we'll do here, we'll do here, we'll do mother, mom
and daughter. Okay, so they're married, he's married to multiple pairs. And
each one of those pairs are problem. And then, so then Reuven
dies. So then לוי here has a זיקה to both of them,
which you can't, because רחל because these two sisters could be married
to both of these. So it's like he's already married to these.
Then Shimon dies. So when it says he פוטר בשתיהן, poter bishteihen,
it means both לאה Leah is off the hook and the daughter's
off the hook. Okay, so that's a very bizarre read of the
ברייתא. Braisa. And let's just read sort of read that and wrap
up for today. So he says, שנייה שבזוג זה ושנייה שבזוג זה
Shniya she-bezug zeh ve-shniya she-bezug zeh means both of Shimon's wives. So
the גמרא says קטעי רבא. Katai Rava. And the גמרא immediately says
Rava's making a mistake בארבע זוגי, be-arba zugei, and saying that they're
married to like four pairs, right? Because it said sister, mother-daughter, mother-granddaughter,
another mother-granddaughter. So Rava thinks that the two brothers are married to
four pairs of wives. So it says חדא דאו או קתני. Chada
d'o o katani. It says "or or or," not "and and and."
We're okay? Okay, ועוד ve-od Rebbe Shimon פוטר בארבעתן מבעי ליה. poter
be-arbatan mibaei lei. Because if you're Rava shouldn't it have said בשתיהן?
bishteihen? If you're reading the ברייתא Braisa that they're married to all
of these women, it should have said and all four of them.
Anyway, so it's very clear that Rebbe Shimon, you know, basically says
both are off and Rebbe Shimon does not hold that זיקה ככנוסה
דמיא. Zika keknusah damya. ועוד תניא, Ve-od tanya, Rebbe Shimon פוטר בשתיהן
מן החליצה ומן הייבום, poter bishteihen min hachalitza umin hayibum, שנאמר, ואשה
אל אחתה לא תקח לצרור. Ve'isha el achotah lo tikach litzror. Do
not take a woman and her sister to compete. בשעה שנעשו צרות
זו לזו, B'sha'ah shene'asu tzaros zu la-zu, at the time when they're
two women that are like competing, so going back to the simple
case here of רחל and לאה Leah and Shimon and Reuven, רחל
and לאה, Leah, Shimon and Reuven both die, these two women are
being צרות tzaros because can't marry both of them. So in a
sense they're competing. So, and so the point is when it's a
scenario where the two are competing,
לא יקח, lo yikach, don't take even one of them.
Okay, and that's a relevance for a ייבום הלכה. halacha, בשעה שנעשו
צרות זו לזו לא יהיו לקוחין אפילו באחת מהן. B'sha'ah shene'asu tzaros
zu la-zu lo yehiyu l'kuchin afilu be-achas meihen. And so we're back
to our point that if Rebbe Shimon held יש זיקה and that's
what got. Rachel in that first scenario, then this shouldn't be a
הלכה, then you should just be stick with the first one, with
the wife of the first one who died.
אלא אמר רב אשי, Ella amar Rav Ashi, אי דנפול בזה אחר
זה, I d’naful bezeh achar zeh, if Reuven died and then Shimon
died, the women fell to him one after the other. הכי נמי,
Hachi nami, you'd be right, just stick with the first wife because
רבי שמעון holds זיקה ככנוסה zika k’kenusa etc. הכא במאי עסקינן דנפול
בבת אחת. Hacha b’mai askinan d’naful b’vat achat. They died exactly at
the same time. רבי שמעון סבר לה כרבי יוסי הגלילי דאמר אפשר
לצמצם, Rebbi Shimon savar lah k’Rebbi Yossi HaGlili d’amar efshar l’tzamtzem, and
Rebbi Shimon holds like Rebbi Yossi HaGlili who says it's possible to
say things happen simultaneously and therefore ממש mamash simultaneously, and that's why
you have this case of לצרור litzror and they're both exempt. But
if it was sequential, אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, it would
go by the first one. All of this is trying to preserve
a very weak read that Rebbi Shimon argues in the first case
and we had a clear ברייתא braita that said Rebbi Shimon says
it only matters which one died first. So basically we're going to
totally reject Rebbi Shimon. I just want to read one more sentence
so you just see the opposing position. רב פפא אמר ביבם ואחר
כך נולד פליגי רבי שמעון. Rav Papa amar b’yibum v’achar kach nolad
peligi Rebbi Shimon. When it's first יבום yibum and then born, that's
where Rebbi Shimon says רחל is no longer a problem. בנולד ואחר
כך יבם, B’nolad v’achar kach yibum, but if Levi was born and
then the יבום yibum took place, לא פליגי, lo peligi, they do
not disagree, which is exactly what Rebbi Shimon said in the ברייתא.
braita. The only thing that matters is did Levi, was Levi born
before יבום yibum or after יבום? yibum? So Rebbi Shimon only argues
in this case, he does not argue in this case. So we
will resume tomorrow with Rebbi Shimon with רב פפא Rav Papa put
רב הושעיה Rav Hoshaia behind.