Okay בוקר
טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf officially ל"א, Lamed Aleph, we pick
up at the bottom of ל"א עמוד א'. Lamed Amud Aleph. We're
going to read again, we're going to start again with the משנה.
Mishna. Okay, the משנה's Mishna dealing with variations of the case of
three brothers, two married to two sisters, one married to a third
woman, and what are the various permutations. So let's take a look.
שלושה אחים שניים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות ואחד נשוי נכרית. Sheloshah achim
shenayim mehem nesuim shetei achayot ve'echad nasui nochrit. Okay, two brothers married
to two sisters, one married to a third woman. גירש אחד מבעלי
האחיות את אשתו. Gerash echad mibaalei ha'achayot et ishto. So let's again
do this, our nice brand-new markers. Okay, we've got ראובן Reuven and
שמעון Shimon married to רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, and then the
third one here is לוי Levi married to דבורה. Devorah. Now, so
what happens?
So גירש אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו. Gerash echad mibaalei ha'achayot et
ishto. Ah, now we'll see what we can, how we can use
the different markers. Okay, so he basically divorces לאה. Leah. Okay, he
divorces לאה. Leah. Okay, then what happens? She's out of the picture.
גירש אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו ומת נשוי נכרית. Gerash echad mibaalei
ha'achayot et ishto umet nasui nochrit. Stage number two is לוי Levi
dies. This is stage number one, this is stage number two. מת
נשוי נכרית. Met nasui nochrit. וכנסה המגרש, Ve'kinsah hamgaresh, and then שמעון
Shimon marries דבורה. Devorah. That's stage number three, marries, does יבום Yibum
with דבורה. Devorah. Okay, that's stage number three. וכנסה המגרש ומת, Ve'kinsah
hamgaresh umet, and then שמעון Shimon dies. So let's take a look.
When לוי Levi died, right, רחל Rachel or שמעון Shimon could have
done יבום Yibum with דבורה. Devorah. Wait, a correction. What, I mean
ראובן Reuven or שמעון, Shimon, I'm sorry. When לוי Levi died, ראובן
Reuven or שמעון Shimon could have done יבום Yibum with דבורה. Devorah.
Okay, שמעון Shimon did יבום Yibum with דבורה. Devorah. Okay, now when
he did יבום Yibum with דבורה, Devorah, brought דבורה Devorah in, and
לאה Leah was already out of the picture. So now, when שמעון
Shimon dies, okay, when שמעון Shimon dies, so דבורה's Devorah totally okay
with ראובן. Reuven. The problem was רחל Rachel and לאה, Leah, לאה
Leah was already out of the picture from the moment even before
he died, לאה Leah was out of the picture, even before he
even married דבורה. Devorah. So now that שמעון Shimon is dead, ראובן
Reuven can go ahead and do יבום Yibum with
דבורה. Devorah. So זו היא שאמרו וכולן שמתו או נתגרשו, zo hi
she'amru ve'chulan shemetu o nisgareshu, all of these ערבות ervot if they
died or were divorced, צרותיהן מותרות. tzarotehen mutarot. They're out of the
picture and their צרות, tzarot, דבורה Devorah is now מותר muttar to
ראובן Reuven because לאה Leah was already out of the picture. Now
this is an extreme case. Here is a case where step number
one was לאה Leah was out of the picture, right? So she
was out of the picture way from the beginning. A more interesting
case, as you might remember, is first he married דבורה Devorah and
then he divorced לאה. Leah. So there was a time period where
those two were co-wives, would that have problematized דבורה Devorah forever to
ראובן? Reuven? Okay, but in this case it's easy, לאה Leah was
way out of the picture before anything started. All right, so that's
an easy case. The גמרא Gemara is now going to explore some
of the middle cases that have not been looked at the משנה.
Mishna. Okay, so let's take a look, and it's also going to
get to this question of whether the משניות Mishnayot are assuming יש
זיקה Yesh Zika or אין זיקה. Ein Zika. So let's take a
look. טעמא Taama says the גמרא, Gemara, the reason this works
is
דגירש ואחר כך מת, degirash ve'acharkach met, that first שמעון Shimon divorced
לאה, Leah, and then he married דבורה Devorah and then he died.
So לאה Leah was out of the picture way before שמעון Shimon
died and way before the whole picture, the whole thing, I'm sorry,
even before לוי, Levi, he's always going to be, he's always going
to be divorced before שמעון Shimon died. לאה Leah was out of
the picture before לוי Levi died, even before דבורה Devorah became relevant
to the conversation, לאה Leah was already out of the picture. That's
why this thing works. אבל מת ואחר כך גירש, Aval met ve'acharch
geresh, let's say first לוי Levi died, okay, and דבורה Devorah was
now in the picture, and then שמעון Shimon divorced לאה. Leah. Okay,
מת ואחר כך גירש. met ve'acharch geresh. Maybe now it's already problematic
as soon as לוי Levi died, even before there's been יבום, Yibum,
even before there's been יבום. Yibum. Why would that be problematic? לוי
Levi has died, if that were number one that occurred, that לוי
Levi had died, what would happen at this stage? If this was
the first thing that would happen
at this stage.
So the way you're saying that לוי Levi died number first, לאה
Leah is not yet divorced.
Okay, what would happen? So, all right, I don't know, divorce her
and then marry דבורה, Devorah, what should be the issue? What relationship
does שמעון Shimon right now have to דבורה? Devorah? Any relationship? זיקה,
Zika, essentially. Okay, he's got the זיקה, Zika, good, we'll use orange
for זיקה. Zika. He's got the זיקה. Zika. If יש זיקה, Yesh
Zika, if יש זיקה, Yesh Zika, so now דבורה Devorah is a
צרת ערווה, tzarat ervah, right, vis-a-vis ראובן, Reuven, right, so maybe that
problematizes דבורה Devorah even now, even after divorce and after death, the
whole thing. So the משנה's Mishna saying, the גמרא's Gemara saying the
משנה Mishna gave an extreme case, got לאה Leah out of the
picture first thing. If לאה Leah hadn't been out of the picture
first thing, presumably there would be a problem as soon as לוי
Levi died, because this would create a זיקה Zika and that would
problematize דבורה Devorah for ראובן. Reuven. But so that implies יש זיקה.
Yesh Zika. So let's take a look. טעמא דגירש ואחר כך מת,
Taama degirash ve'acharch met, אבל... aval... made, if the first thing that
happened was לוי Levy died, ואחר כך גירשה v'achar kach girashah and
then לאה Leah was out of the picture,
אסורה, asurah, presumably דבורה Dvorah would be forbidden to ראובן Reuven because
she would have immediately been sort of צרת לאה, tzarat Leah, צרת
ערווה tzarat ervah or quasi-צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. So what do you
see? You see אמר רב אשי זו אומרת Amar Rav Ashi zos
omeret from this we can infer יש זיקה אפילו בתרי אחי yesh
zikah afilu bitrei achei that there is a זיקה zikah even with
two brothers, because as soon as לוי Levy died, ראובן Reuven could
have done יבום yibum with דבורה. Dvorah. ראובן Reuven had a זיקה.
zikah. So and we know when there are two brothers, it is
harder to say זיקה zikah because no one necessarily is going to
be the one that is actually going to act on it. So
even in a case of two brothers, this זיקה zikah is strong
enough to problematize דבורה Dvorah that now שמעון Shimon dies, דבורה Dvorah
is a צרת ערווה tzarat ervah or quasi-צרת ערווה. tzarat ervah. So
that is a pretty strong statement of זיקה. zikah. But we got
a problem. If you remember earlier, we said אין זיקה ein zikah
even with one brother. So the גמרא Gemara says ולרב אשי קשיא
דרב נחמן, u'l'Rav Ashi kashya d'Rav Nachman, what about what רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said? רב נחמן Rav Nachman learned out אין זיקה ein
zikah even by one brother. So what was רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's
proof that אין זיקה ein zikah even by one brother? Now we
got to go back and remember that. That was all the way
back yesterday.
So what was that case?
That was the משנה Mishna that said you had ראובן Reuven and
שמעון Shimon and לוי, Levy, right? ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon and
רחל Rachel and לאה Leah and here you had לוי Levy and
דבורה. Dvorah.
Okay, and what does the משנה Mishna say? That משנה Mishna at
the top said
מת אחד בעלי אחיות meis echad ba'alei achayot that ראובן Reuven died,
וכנס השני את אשתו v'kanas hasheini es ishto and then לוי Levy
did here, I am sorry, not כנס, kanas, another case is
עשה בה מאמר ומת, asah bah ma'amar u'meis, if he did מאמר
ma'amar with רחל Rachel and then he died. Okay, so he sort
of brought רחל Rachel into his relationship here, then שמעון Shimon cannot
do יבום yibum with דבורה Dvorah because now דבורה Dvorah has become
like a צרת ערווה tzarat ervah after he has done מאמר ma'amar
with רחל. Rachel. So the גמרא Gemara says why do you have
to do מאמר ma'amar with רחל? Rachel? Why? Right! The זיקה zikah
should have been a problem and there is only one relevant brother.
שמעון Shimon is not relevant because he is married to לאה. Leah.
So here it is only one brother and רחל Rachel only created
a problem after מאמר. ma'amar. The זיקה zikah alone was not enough
to pull her in. So how come here the משנה Mishna sounds
like even with two brothers the זיקה zikah pulls דבורה Dvorah in?
What is the story? יש זיקה, yesh zikah, אין זיקה? ein zikah?
One brother sounds like you need מאמר, ma'amar, two brothers sounds like
there is already a problem. So the גמרא Gemara says ולרב אשי
קשיא
דרב נחמן,
u'l'Rav Ashi
kashya d'Rav Nachman, רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's point from here that אין
זיקה. ein zikah. אמר לך רב אשי הוא הדין דאף על גב
דלא עבד בה מאמר, Amar lach Rav Ashi hu hadin d'af al
gav d'lo avad bah ma'amar, you know what? You are right. This
would have been a problem even without מאמר. ma'amar. The זיקה zikah
itself would have been a problem. And as soon as ראובן Reuven
dies and then לוי Levy dies, you already have צרת ערווה tzarat
ervah because of the זיקה, zikah, of the זיקה zikah this way,
because of the זיקה. zikah. That would have been enough. You are
right. So why did it say he did מאמר ma'amar with רחל
Rachel if the problem existed automatically?
Okay, ואף על גב דלא עבד מאמר נחית מכלל חליצה יבומי לא
מיבמה, v'af al gav d'lo avad ma'amar nachis michlal chalitzah yibumi lo
miyabma, דבורה Dvorah would have had to get חליצה chalitzah not יבום.
yibum. The מאמר ma'amar already would have pulled רחל Rachel in. והא
דקתני מאמר, v'ha d'katani ma'amar, so why did it say he did
מאמר ma'amar with רחל Rachel if the problem existed automatically? לאפוקי מבית
שמאי דאמרי מאמר קונה קניין גמור l'apuki mi'Beis Shammai d'amri ma'amar koneh
kinyan gamur to tell you not that מאמר ma'amar creates the problem,
but that מאמר ma'amar does not solve the problem. According to בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, maybe if you did מאמר, ma'amar, here we will
do blue for מאמר, ma'amar, now I am getting too caught up
with all my colors. Okay, if you did מאמר, ma'amar, maybe that
pulled רחל Rachel in fully and it made her fully לוי'ס Levy's
wife and it pulled her in fully, then לאה Leah could walk
out without חליצה, chalitzah, right? Because it is a real צרת ערווה.
tzarat ervah. Okay, so it told you without מאמר, ma'amar, רחל'ס Rachel's
already pulled in by זיקה zikah and it is a problem. You
cannot do יבום yibum with לאה. Leah. I mean I am sorry
I didn't mean לאה Leah walk out. שמעון Shimon would not be
I am sorry he could not do יבום yibum with דבורה Dvorah
because רחל'ס Rachel's already pulled into the equation. But he still needs
to do
חליצה chalitzah because the זיקה zikah is
not דאורייתא, d'oraisa, it is not full. But once with זיקה zikah
רחל'ס Rachel's pulled in, שמעון Shimon has to do חליצה chalitzah with
דבורה. Dvorah. He cannot do יבום. yibum. It creates a problem. Maybe,
however, with מאמר, ma'amar, רחל'ס Rachel's fully pulled in and דבורה Dvorah
can walk off without חליצה, chalitzah, maybe like בית שמאי? Beis Shammai?
No. קא משמע לן דלא כבית שמאי. Ka mashma lan d'lo k'Beis
Shammai. Okay, so that is one way of reading these
משניות mishnayot that זיקה zikah creates the problem, pulls דבורה Dvorah in
here, pulls רחל Rachel in here. And the only reason it said
מאמר ma'amar was to tell you it did not make her fully
the wife that even חליצה chalitzah would not be an issue. Now
I am holding off on the questions because we have to now
look at it in the flip. ולרב נחמן קשיא דרב אשי, U'l'Rav
Nachman kashya d'Rav Ashi, now רב נחמן Rav Nachman said the opposite.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman said that רחל Rachel is
only a problem because of מאמר. ma'amar. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said
אין זיקה אפילו בחד, ein zikah afilu b'chad, even though לוי Levy
is the only relevant brother here and there is only a one-person
זיקה, zikah, that is not enough to make רחל Rachel a problem.
He says from this
משנה. Mishna. So if that's true, why does our משנה Mishnah say
that לאה Leah has to be divorced first? Even if לאה Leah
isn't be divorced first, this זיקה Zika should not be meaningful. This
זיקה Zika should not pull in דבורה Devorah and should not create
an issue. If you if it's true that זיקה Zika does nothing
that you need מאמר. Ma'amar. So now we're going to act it
in the flip because רב נחמן Rav Nachman wants to read all
the משניות Mishnayot that אין זיקה. Ein Zika. ורב נחמן קשיא דרב
אשי, U'l'Rav Nachman kashya d'Rav Ashi, according to רב נחמן Rav Nachman
that there's אין זיקה Ein Zika and you needed מאמר Ma'amar over
here, then how about here? Why does this sound like if לאה
Leah wasn't the first one divorced, we've got a problem because of
זיקה? Zika? וכי תימא V'chi Teima and if you say הוא הדין
דאפילו מיתת אח ואחר כך גירוש צרתה מותרת. Hu Hadin d'afilu metat
ach v'achar kach gerush tzarata muteret. So and if you say yeah
the משנה Mishnah didn't mean that לאה Leah had to be the
first one divorced. It would have worked the other way. Even if
לוי Levi first died and then לאה Leah was divorced, it also
would have been same story. Okay? Is that that right? So even
if לוי Levi died the זיקה Zika would not have been a
problem, then לאה Leah got divorced and then he married דבורה, Devorah,
so שמעון Shimon can go ahead and do יבום Yibum with דבורה.
Devorah. Okay? Even though it gives the scenario that לאה Leah was
divorced first, it doesn't mean that exclusively, that's not the only way
this is true. לוי Levi could have died first and זיקה Zika
would not have been meaningful, and as long as לאה Leah was
taken out of the picture before שמעון Shimon married דבורה, Devorah, everything
would have been okay. Have I lost everybody or you guys live?
Okay fine. So וכי תימא V'chi Teima and if you say הוא
הדין דאפילו מיתת אח ואחר כך גירוש צרתה מותרת. Hu Hadin d'afilu
metat ach v'achar kach gerush tzarata muteret. You know what? You're right.
It it would have been the same even if לאה Leah had
not been the one divorced first. That first לוי Levi died and
then לאה Leah was divorced according to רב נחמן Rav Nachman who
wants to read everything of אין זיקה. Ein Zika. Now we're working
through everything with אין זיקה. Ein Zika. אלא זו למעוטי מאי? Ela
zu l'me'utei mai? So when the משנה Mishnah says this is the
case when they said that if the ערוה Ervah is divorced it's
everything's okay, this is the case sounds like there's another case that
wouldn't be true. Okay? So it does sound like we're not allowing
all cases. So what case would not work when the in the
case of גירוש? Geirush? So what is it coming to exclude? למעוטי
כנס ואחר כך גירש. L'me'utei kanas v'achar kach geireish. Ah, there's three
scenarios. One scenario is the first scenario is what we have in
our משנה, Mishnah, okay, which is לאה Leah is divorced first and
out of the picture first. That's an easy case. Okay? And obviously
everything's going to be okay. B is לוי Levi dies
and
then לאה Leah is divorced. Okay? So in that case, okay, לוי's
Levi's died so that might maybe created a זיקה. Zika. And that's
the question of יש זיקה Yesh Zika or not. Okay? But we
could say you know what? That's also okay, אין זיקה, Ein Zika,
and as long as לאה Leah gets divorced right away and gets
out of the picture, okay, אין זיקה Ein Zika we're all right.
But there's the third possibility, which is what? לוי Levi dies,
okay, שמעון Shimon does יבום Yibum with with דבורה, Devorah, okay, so
now שמעון Shimon right here is married to דבורה Devorah and לאה,
Leah, and then שמעון Shimon dies. Okay? In that case, okay,
דבורה Devorah had become like צרת ערוה Tzarat Ervah to ראובן. Reuven.
I'm sorry, no no. And then, excuse me, לאה Leah is divorced.
Obviously that case would be good. Okay? Then לאה Leah is divorced
and then and then שמעון Shimon dies. So in this case, this
case basically you had זיקה Zika and then לאה Leah was out
of the picture. In this case you had much more than זיקה
Zika then לאה Leah was out of the picture. You had יבום
Yibum and then לאה Leah is out, and then you have death.
He dies. Okay? So there you actually have them married, then לאה
Leah is divorced and then she's out of the picture only before
שמעון Shimon dies. Okay, that case is like all right, since they
were both married to שמעון Shimon at the same time, even though
she got out of the picture before he died, it doesn't matter.
They were married to שמעון Shimon at the same time and that's
what we're excluding. Okay? So let's take a look. It says so
אלא זו למעוטי מאי למעוטי כנס ואחר כך גירש, Ela zu l'me'utei
mai l'me'utei kanas v'achar kach geireish, that שמעון Shimon actually married דבורה
Devorah and then he divorced לאה. Leah. So it wasn't just there
was a זיקה Zika and then he died. They were actually married
and then and then he divorced and then he died. So in
that case, right, לאה Leah only got out of the picture before
he died but but she was they were both married but he
was married to both of them at the same time. And that
case, even though she's out of the picture before he dies, it's
still a case of צרת ערוה. Tzarat Ervah. So you might remember
that this is a debate we had before whether you go by
the time of marriage to determine צרת ערוה Tzarat Ervah or the
time of death. Okay. הניחא, Hani'cha, that's good if סבר לה כרבי
ירמיה, sabar lah k'Rabbi Yirmeyah, who feels like רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah
which said way back at the begin you know I don't know
two three weeks ago, תברא, tavrah, divide the משניות, Mishnayot, מי ששנה
זו לא שנה זו. mi sheshana zu lo shana zu. This the
author of one משנה Mishnah is not the author of the same,
there was a problem
of... דהאי תנא סבר מיתה מפלת והאי תנא סבר גירושין ראשון מפילין.
de-hai tanna savar mitah mapelet ve-hai tanna savar gerushin rishon mappilin. And
the question is is the obligation of יבום yibbum defined at the
time of death מיתה מפלת mitah mapelet makes them fall in front
of the brother-in-law or is it defined at the time of the
marriage? Okay, so since there's a debate there's an opinion that says
that it's defined at the time of marriage before the time of
death. So when our משנה mishnah says as long as לאה Leah
is divorced it's okay and it seems to say but not in
every case but in the case it drew it didn't all it
meant to exclude was not that it mattered whether she was divorced
and then the brother died or the brother died and then she
was divorced, that wouldn't matter אין זיקה. ein zika. What it meant
to exclude was she's got to be divorced before שמעון Shimon married
her. Okay? I don't care I don't care here whether first she
was divorced and then he died or first he died and then
she was divorced but she does have to be divorced before שמעון
Shimon married her because if שמעון Shimon was married to both at
the same time that creates צרת ערוה. tzarat ervah. Okay, and don't
tell me that as long as he divorced her before he died
that's good enough, it's not true. He has to divorce her before
he married the other woman. Okay, he can't be married to both
at the same time. All right, so that would be how to
read the משנה. mishnah. אלא אי סבר לה כרבא ella ee savar
lah ke-Rava that's fine if there's an opinion that you go by
the time of marriage. But if he holds like רבא Rava דאמר
לעולם חד תנא הוא וזו אין צריך לומר זו קתני, de-amar le-olam
chad tanna hu ve-zu ein tzarich lomar zu katani, it's all one
author of the משנה. mishnah. Again we won't worry about exactly which
משניות mishnayot they were dealing with but basically רבא Rava's of the
opinion that you always go by the time of death. Okay, so
now forget יש זיקה yesh zika or אין זיקה ein zika we
have a very simple question: if you determine צרת ערוה tzarat ervah
by the time of death why did we have to give the
scenario that לאה Leah was divorced way up front? There's a much
bigger חידוש. chiddush. The bigger חידוש chiddush is that שמעון Shimon marries
דבורה Devorah and לאה Leah is divorced only before שמעון Shimon dies.
That's what רבא Rava'd say. רבא Rava'd say that'd be fine. Just
get לאה Leah out of the picture before you die then you're
fine. Okay, so why did we give the scenario that she was
out of the picture the very first thing? Give a much bigger
חידוש, chiddush, marry דבורה Devorah and then divorce לאה. Leah. Okay, why
not? So
זו למעוטי מאי zu limutei mai when our משנה mishnah says only
this case works by גירושין gerushin what's it excluding since you actually
would say that there are many cases of גירושין gerushin that would
work? על כרחך כרבי ירמיה סבירא ליה. al korcha ke-Rabbi Yirmiyah svira
lei. So it must be that if you're sort of saying actually
we're not yet asking how does רבא Rava work, we're saying how
does רב זירא Rav Zeira that said אין זיקה, ein zika, and
since he's sort of saying אין זיקה ein zika so in that
case this order could switch who dies and who divorces first. So
if that's true what are we excluding? We're excluding the case of
married and died. But that would only work if you say if
you say נשואין ראשונים מפילין nissuin rishonim mappilin because if you say
you go by the time of death there's nothing left to exclude.
According to רבא Rava there seems to be nothing left to exclude.
All cases seem anytime she's divorced before death seems to work. So
therefore it must be we're not going like רבא Rava and it
must be that the case we are excluding is the case when
first he married her and then he died. That case would remain
problematic. Okay, so you got to what we have is the following.
You have I don't know if I'm using the markers too much
now that I'm confusing people but you have okay you've got
you've got the idea that you go by נשואין ראשונים. nissuin rishonim.
Okay, so in that case it goes by they can't be married
at the same time. So there are two scenarios where they're not
married at the same
time: first לאה Leah is divorced and then and then and then
לוי Levi dies or לוי Levi dies and then לאה Leah is
divorced. Either way either way in either of these cases שמעון Shimon
is not married to both of them. Okay, שמעון Shimon is not
married to both which is great because that's what we need because
you go by נשואין ראשונים. nissuin rishonim. The only difference here is
that if לוי Levi dies first you might have זיקה. zika. Does
זיקה zika create a problem? So if you say אין זיקה ein
zika both of these are okay because שמעון Shimon isn't married to
them both at the same time. Okay, but here's a third case.
The third case is that
basically שמעון Shimon marries both שמעון Shimon marries דבורה Devorah and then
he
gets
יבום yibbum
דבורה Devorah and then and then לאה Leah is divorced. In that
case and then he dies. In that case right he's married to
both.
He just then divorces before he dies. Divorces before he dies. Okay,
before he dies. That would only work if you don't say נשואין
ראשונים nissuin rishonim but if you say מיתה מפלת mitah mapelet you
go by the time of death.
So now what the גמרא Gemara is saying is like this. If
you say אין זיקה, ein zika, so this case also works as
long as he's not married to both of them at the same
time, we don't have to worry about the זיקה. zika. What's being
excluded? What's being excluded is case number three, when he was married
to both of them and then he divorced before he died. That
still would not be good because we don't say מיתה מפלת, misa
mapeles, we say בנישואין ראשונים. binissu'in rishonim. If you were to פסקן
pasken מיתה מפלת, misa mapeles, he'd be in a bind, because then
all three cases are okay, nothing is left to be excluded. So
since he includes number two because of אין זיקה, ein zika, what
he's left with excluding is case number three, where they were married
at the same time and she was divorced just before death. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Now the question is, if you
פסקן pasken number three what are you left with? That's what the
גמרא's Gemara going to ask next. Okay, but we're not yet, but
we're first asking it from the perspective of אין זיקה. ein zika.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
על כרחך רב ירמיה סבירא ליה, al kurchak Rav Yirmiyah s'vira leh,
he must hold by רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah that we go by
נישואין ראשונים, nissu'in rishonim, not by מיתה, misa, and we're therefore left
with being able to exclude case number three. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ולרבא, u-l'Rava, okay, but now the real question is, if you
פסקן pasken case number three works, הניחא אי סבירא ליה כרב אשי,
ha-nicha i-savra leh k'Rav Ashi, זו היא למעוטי מת בלא גירש. zu
hi l'muta meis b'lo geireish. So רבא, Rava, what's left to exclude?
All three of these cases are totally fine because as long as
לאה Leah is divorced before שמעון Shimon dies. So what's the משנה
Mishna excluding? What case wouldn't work about גירש? geireish? All these cases
work. So the גמרא Gemara says there's one case that wouldn't work.
If he holds like רב אשי, Rav Ashi, right, רב אשי Rav
Ashi holds יש זיקה, yesh zika, so how's that going to be
an issue? What's one case that won't work? אי סבירא ליה כרב
אשי, i-savra leh k'Rav Ashi, זו היא למעוטי zu hi l'muta here's
a case you can exclude: מת בלא גירש. meis b'lo geireish. Okay,
which is, now it doesn't mean just that שמעון Shimon dies without
divorcing לאה. Leah. That's obvious. Then he's married, that's a case of
צרת ערוה. tzaras erva. Right, he's married to דבורה Devorah and לאה.
Leah. Of course not. No, it doesn't mean that. It means, let
me just double check רש"י Rashi to make sure I'm saying this
right.
Oh, right. So the case would be that here would be the
scenario we'd be excluding. לאה Leah dies, if we פסקן pasken יש
זיקה, yesh zika, okay? לוי Levi dies and then שמעון Shimon has
a זיקה, zika, right? And then you know what happens? שמעון Shimon
dies. Okay, so now if he died before he had a chance
to divorce לאה, Leah, it was מת בלא גירש, meis b'lo geireish,
but it was also before he married דבורה. Devorah. Okay, he didn't
marry דבורה, Devorah, it was just his זיקה, zika, and then he
died. So that זיקה zika already, if you say יש זיקה, yesh
zika, that זיקה zika already makes דבורה, Devorah, right, צרת ערוה, tzaras
erva, and now ראובן Reuven can't do anything, right? He can't do
יבום yibbum with דבורה Devorah because by at this moment there was
already צרת ערוה tzaras erva because of the זיקה. zika. So if
you פסקן pasken any of these cases where divorce occurred at any
time before שמעון Shimon died, it works. We all go by the
time of death. Ironically, the one case that doesn't work is the
case when his relationship with דבורה Devorah was the weakest. It was
just זיקה, zika, but nevertheless, since לאה Leah was never divorced, that
would be a problem. Okay, so according to רבא, Rava, that's the
one case you exclude. אלא אי סבירא ליה כרב אשי, Ella i-savra
leh k'Rav Ashi, so that works. הניחא אי סבירא ליה כרב אשי,
ha-nicha i-savra leh k'Rav Ashi, זו היא למעוטי מת בלא גירש. zu
hi l'muta meis b'lo geireish. Okay, because of the זיקה zika and
then since there was never a divorce, that זיקה zika would have
created a problem. אלא אי סבירא ליה כרב נחמן, Ella i-savra leh
k'Rav Nachman, but if he פסקנס paskens like רב נחמן Rav Nachman
that says that there is אין זיקה, ein zika, זו היא למעוטי
מאי? zu hi l'muta mai? There's nothing left to exclude. Any case
of divorce before death works, and any case of dying before divorce
works because the זיקה's zika meaningless. על כרחך כרב אשי סבירא ליה.
al kurchak k'Rav Ashi s'vira leh. So רבא Rava has to hold
like רב אשי. Rav Ashi. Okay? So if you hold אין זיקה,
ein zika, you're including these cases and the only case left to
exclude is שמעון Shimon marrying דבורה Devorah and
then divorcing. Okay, that wouldn't work because that's a divorce after you're
married to both. Okay, that's left to exclude. If you פסקן pasken
that even that case is okay, any time she's divorced before death
it always works, you go by the moment of death, then any
divorce works. So what's this משנה Mishna excluding? It's excluding the case
of no divorce, that this זיקה zika alone creates a problem and
if he dies with no divorce, even though this is very weak,
since she is not out of the picture even at the time
of death, that's what case that remains a problem. Okay, if you
say יש זיקה. yesh zika. So we worked it out whether you
say יש זיקה yesh zika or אין זיקה. ein zika. Yes, Charlie?
Back to this first one with רב אשי Rav Ashi and they
conclude they're excluding the opinion of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
Isn't it kind of rare for an אמורא Amora to have to
worry about excluding the opinion of בית שמאי?
Beit Shammai? Yeah, that's the point. You know, clearly though בית שמאי
Beit Shammai here seems to have a much sturdier, stronger, and viable
voice in this מסכת masechet so far in the ייבום yibum cases,
and he does elsewhere like your ideas, oh let's just have everybody
do חליצה chalitzah in order to satisfy בית שמאי's Beit Shammai position,
you know, and the whole געוואלד gevalt that the גמרא Gemara had
a whole discussion
before אירוסין אוסר נישואין אוסר erusin oser nissuin oser according to בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. So the בית שמאי's Beit Shammai opinions here seem
to carry a bit more weight and are considered more seriously than
elsewhere, so that is yeah definitely true. Okay, let's go on. וכולן
vekullan switching gears now okay, I mean not totally, it's never totally,
but it is a different type of discussion.
וכולן שהיו בהן vekullan shehayu bahen no more brothers and sisters. Okay,
we're going back way to the first משנה Mishnah about ערווה ervah
and צרת ערווה tzoras ervah and we've said one way that they
sort of get out of the picture is if the ערווה ervah
is divorced or has died before marriage or before the other one
is married or at least before the husband died. That was the
question of נישואין nissuin or מיתה. misa. But one way it's dealt
with is divorce or death. Here's though another thing which is maybe
they're questionably out of the picture. Now they're not questionably dead, that
would be like brain death nowadays. Okay, but they could be questionably
divorced and they could be questionably married. Okay, so let's say the
ערווה ervah may be in the picture, may not be in the
picture. What's the story then? וכולן vekullan all these ערוות שהיו בהן
קידושין או גירושין בספק ervos shehayu bahen kiddushin o geirushin besafek we
don't know if they were married, right? ראובן Reuven was married to
דבורה Devora and to maybe רחל. Rachel. Okay, and רחל Rachel would
be the ערווה ervah to you know his brother. No רחל Rachel
and לאה, Leah, just used to be the ערווה ervah to his
brother. רחל Rachel is ראובן's Reuven daughter, alright? And we don't know
if שמעון Shimon is married to רחל Rachel or not. Is she
an ערווה? ervah? Is she part of the equation or not? How
do we not know she's married to ראובן? Reuven?
Either ספק קידושין safek kiddushin or ספק גירושין. safek geirushin. Okay, right,
so that's the issue. Is רחל Rachel in the picture? הרי אלו
harei eilu in those cases צרותיהן tzrosan
דבורה Devora right who definitely is in the picture חולצות ולא מתייבמות
chotzos velo misyabmos have to get חליצה chalitzah not ייבום. yibum. Can't
do ייבום yibum cause maybe רחל Rachel is in the picture and
she's צרת ערווה tzoras ervah and it's אסור assur to do ייבום.
yibum. But you can't walk away cause maybe רחל Rachel isn't in
the picture and then you need to do חליצה chalitzah or ייבום.
yibum. So the solution in all those cases of ספק safek is
you do חליצה chalitzah not ייבום. yibum. רחל Rachel you don't have
to worry about. רחל Rachel if she's not in the picture doesn't
need anything, and if she is in the picture she's an ערווה.
ervah. Okay, so רחל Rachel isn't the issue. But the question is
what does it do to the status of לאה? Leah? It throws
לאה Leah in a ספק safek and therefore לאה Leah needs חליצה
chalitzah not ייבום. yibum. כיצד ספק קידושין keitzad safek kiddushin what's a
scenario of ספק קידושין? safek kiddushin? זרק לה קידושין ספק קרוב לו
ספק קרוב לה zarak la kiddushin safek karov lo safek karov lah
זו היא ספק קידושין. zu hi safek kiddushin. Man says הרי את
מקודשת לי בטבעת זו harei at mekudeshes li betabaas zu catch okay
and he throws the ring and it falls smack between the two
of them. And you don't know whether it's closer to him or
closer to her. Now in the משנה Mishnah it sounds like it
all goes by who it's closer to. The problem is that there's
not exactly a קניין kinyan known as it was closer to me.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara sort of speaks about and רש"י Rashi
brings it in there is a קניין kinyan of ארבע אמות arba
amos within your ארבע אמות. arba amos. So רש"י Rashi describes the
scenario that they're exactly eight אמות amos apart okay I don't know
if this like a model for their future marriage right you have
to keep your own private space anyway and the exact midline is
where their two ארבע אמות arba amos the edges of their two
ארבע אמות arba amos touch. And you don't know whether it fell
in my ארבע אמות arba amos or in her ארבע אמות arba
amos you know in the man's or in the woman's. So you
don't know if she ever did a קניין kinyan on the כסף
קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Okay, that would be a case of זהו ספק
קידושין. zehu safek kiddushin. That's a case of you don't know if
רחל Rachel ever got married to שמעון. Shimon. ספק גירושין safek geirushin
now let's say she definitely was married and but you don't know
if she was divorced. Now you would say maybe a similar case,
you threw the גט, get, you don't know if it got into
her side or didn't get to her side. Interestingly though the משנה
Mishnah switches gears and is not going to deal with a case
of ספק safek but actually a case of a rabbinically פסול גירושין
pasul geirushin which actually is דאורייתא d'Oraisa כשר. kasher. And what's that
case?
And therefore it's called ספק safek because rabbinically it's פסול pasul but
really is a different category. Okay, so what's that case? זהו ספק
גירושין כתב בכתב ידו ואין עליו עדים
zehu safek geirushin kasav
bichesav yado veein alav edim
so it doesn't have witnesses signing on the bottom of the גט
get but it's in his own handwriting. יש עליו עדים ואין בו
זמן yesh alav edim veein bo zman or it has witnesses the
problem is that it doesn't have a date which is a different
type of a problem. או יש בו זמן ואין בו אלא עד
אחד o yesh bo zman veein bo ela ed echad it's got
a date and it's not written in his handwriting it doesn't have
two witnesses but has עד אחד. ed echad. So basically there's three
cases: handwritten,
עד אחד, ed echad, or no זמן. zman. But the language by
the way this is interesting in terms of like oral mnemonic right
why didn't they just say it simpler? הרי שלושה גיטין פסולים harei
shelosha gittin psulin כתב ידו kesav yado אין בו זמן ein bo
zman עד אחד. ed echad. But the way it's phrased sort of
carries you from one to the next. Do you see the way
it's written it says... Right? It says like, כתב בכתב ידו ואין
עליו עדים. kasav b'ksav yado v'ein alav edim. יש עליו עדים ואין
בו זמן. yesh alav edim v'ein bo zman. יש בו זמן ואין
בו עד אחד, yesh bo zman v'ein bo aid echad, right? So
it's nice the way sort of you get all three, it's a
little wordy, but it gets you to all three cases. All those
are rabbinically פסול pasul גט, get, ואין
בו אלא עד אחד, v'ein bo ela aid echad, זהו ספק גירושין,
zehu sofek gerushin, we're calling it ספק. sofek. It's not really ספק,
sofek, it's דאורייתא d'raisa כשר kasher דרבנן d'rabonon פסול, pasul, but we
treat it therefore as this woman is quasi-divorced.
Okay, and therefore you have to go play it safe both ways
as it were, treat her as half and half, and you do
חליצה chalitza and not גירושין geirushin to the other woman. All right.
So now the גמרא Gemara points out, why didn't it give the
simple parallel case by גירושין? geirushin? ואילו בגירושין ספק קרוב לו ספק
קרוב לה לא קתני. v'ilu b'geirushin sofek karov lo sofek karov lah
lo katani. It doesn't give that case about did the גט get
get into her space or not into her space? So מאי טעמא,
mai taama, what's the reason? So the גמרא Gemara first thinks that
the reason is that that case actually would not change her status.
She's definitely married to רחל, Rachel, throws her a ספק גט safek
get which maybe got to her maybe didn't, her status is not
ספק, sofek she's still definitely married to him. Why would she still
be definitely married to him? This is a principle called חזקה. chazaka.
She has her status quo is his wife. We don't know if
that status quo changed. We don't know if she got the גט.
get So her status quo remains the same and she's not a
ספק גרושה, sofek gerusha, she's definitely married to the guy.
So then flip it the other way, ספק קידושין, sofek kiddushin, she's
ודאי vadi not married to him, why don't you keep that status
quo, right? So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say.
Let's take a look. אמר רבא, Amar Rabba, אישה זו, isha zo,
now we're not currently worry about רחל Rachel in the משנה, Mishnah,
we're worried about her co-wife there, potential co-wife דבורה. Devora. This woman,
בחזקת היתר ליבם עומדת, bechezkas heter l'yavam omedes, right? Before he did
this ספק גט, safek get, this woman was also a צרת ערווה.
tzaras erva. She was going to be free to marry anyway. The
same way רחל Rachel was ודאי vadi married and that was her
status quo, דבורה Devora status quo was ודאי vadi not having to
worry about יבום, yibum, okay? ומספק אתה בא ואוסרה? umisofek ata ba
u'osra? Now you're coming and say, oh wait, maybe רחל Rachel was
divorced and therefore you can't go ahead and marry somebody else, you
need
חליצה. chalitza. אל תאסרנה מספק. al tosrena misofek. Don't do that out
of doubt. Let her keep her status quo. Okay, so a funny
way of saying it like, you're not entitled, she has a right.
Okay, but anyway the point is her status quo, keep everybody with
their status quo. All right, so ספק גירושין sofek gerushin would not
affect, now, would not affect
רחל Rachel status. Now it's an interesting question, would the גמרא Gemara
really say that that רחל Rachel now could, you know, what would
be I guess the consequence? Well actually it's not such a bad
consequence because she still couldn't marry another man. Anyway, the question is
is the גמרא Gemara being prepared to say that even in terms
of רחל Rachel that we're not worried about רחל Rachel status, that's
the status quo, or at least in terms of דבורה Devora the
co-wife where, you know, it's much weightier about the question about the
married woman's status, right? You know, because that's like a whole question
of adultery and so on. The question about the יבום yibum aspect
of marrying some other guy is a less weighty question. But the
גמרא Gemara is not really making that distinction, it's basically saying just
keep everything at the status quo. So ספק גט safek get, would
not change דבורה Devora status. So the גמרא Gemara says if that's
true, say the same thing about a ספק קידושין, sofek kiddushin, keep
everything at the status quo. The גמרא Gemara says like this, אי
הכי, i hachi, בקידושין נמי נימא, b'kiddushin nami neima, אישה זו בחזקת
היתר ליבם עומדת. isha zo bechezkas heter l'yavam omedes. This woman דבורה,
Devora, before he maybe married רחל, Rachel, דבורה Devora could have had
יבום yibum with the brother-in-law, okay? ומספק אתה בא ואוסרה? umisofek ata
ba u'osra? Now you're coming and say, oh wait, maybe her status
changed, maybe the guy married רחל Rachel as well. אל תאסרנה מספק,
al tosrena misofek, don't change her status from מותרת, muteres, let her
remain allowed to do יבום. yibum. Okay, so basically in either case
keep the status quo. גמרא Gemara says no, התם לחומרא. hasam l'chumra.
We're being מחמיר. machmir. Okay, because what are the cases? If you
don't know if the husband married רחל, Rachel, so maybe this woman,
right, דבורה, Devora, right, she had been allowed to do יבום, yibum,
maybe now she should be forbidden to do יבום. yibum. Okay, so
that's a serious question, right? Maybe it's going to be a case
about an issue of איסור אשת אח וחיוב כרת issur eshes ach
v'chiyuv kares and so on. So even though the status quo would
say let her do יבום, yibum, we're going to say oh, just
play it safe, don't do יבום, yibum, do חליצה. chalitza. It's true
the status quo should say you could still go ahead and do
יבום, yibum, play it safe. Okay, in principle you're right, we're going
to be דרבנן d'rabonon play it safe, don't do יבום, yibum, do
חליצה. chalitza. The other case, right, basically where ספק sofek, גט, get.
דבורה Devora was free to marry some other guy, okay? So we're
saying and now we're saying okay, we don't know if that status
changed, go ahead and marry another guy. We're not going to ask
that you do חליצה. chalitza. Well why don't we play it safe
there? Say don't marry another guy until you do חליצה. chalitza. Well
first thing to appreciate is that the weight of that is much
less. Marrying another guy without חליצה chalitza is a simple לאו, lav,
it's not like an איסור כרת. issur kares. But the גמרא Gemara
anyway is going to get to that, but at this stage the
גמרא Gemara says in principle you're right, both cases go to status
quo, but this case where maybe he married רחל, Rachel, we're not
going to... allow her to do ייבום, yibbum, because even though you're
right in principle okay let's play it safe. ייבום's yibbum a pretty
scary thing if you're not allowed to do it, so just go
ahead and do חליצה. chalitzah. So the גמרא Gemara says השתא התם
לחומרא, hashta hatam l'chumra, we're being מחמיר. machmir. האי חומרא דאתי לידי
קולא, hai chumra d'asi lidei kula, the גמרא Gemara says that's a
חומרא chumra that's just going to lead to a leniency. What's the
leniency? זימנין דאזיל איהו ומקדש לה לאחותה. zimnin d'azil ihu u'mekadesh lah
l'achosa. I guess I'll just erase all of this.
Okay, so here you have the case of ספק קידושין. safek kiddushin.
What's the case of ספק קידושין? safek kiddushin? Okay, שמעון Shimon is
married to דבורה Devorah
and maybe
he's married to, okay, רחל. Rachel. Okay, so in this type of
a case, דבורה's Devorah status quo before that act happened was, what
was it? מותר ליבם, mutar l'yabam, right? Okay, now this creates a
ספק. sofek Okay, so this creates a ספק. sofek Does that really,
is that really going to impact it? They say, you know what,
just go ahead and play it safe, you don't want to have
somebody doing ייבום yibbum to דבורה Devorah if she really, if she
really has become אסור. assur. All right, in principle she should be
able to keep her status quo, and you know, and ראובן Reuven
here should be able, should be able to do ייבום yibbum to
דבורה, Devorah, but you know, that's, that's pretty dangerous. So in principle
you're right, but just do חליצה. chalitzah.
So the גמרא... Gemara... Maybe he was married to like לאה Leah
then?
Forget who he's married to, right? ראובן Reuven I'm sorry, רחל Rachel
is ראובן's Reuven daughter, okay, that's, he's,
he's רחל's Rachel father, okay? We're not dealing with sisters anymore, okay?
So in this case, if שמעון Shimon had married רחל, Rachel, דבורה's
Devorah out of the picture. But it's not the case. So why
would you say, okay, but status quo, go ahead and do ייבום
yibbum with דבורה? Devorah? No, you know in principle you're right, but
it's pretty scary so let's do חליצה. chalitzah. We'll be מחמיר. machmir.
So the גמרא Gemara says that's a חומרא דאתי לידי קולא. chumra
d'asi lidei kula. What's the חומרא דאתי לידי קולא? chumra d'asi lidei
kula? Think about the following case. Okay, it says like this: חומרא
דאתי לידי קולא הוא זימנין דאזיל איהו ומקדש לה לאחותה קידושי ודאי.
chumra d'asi lidei kula hu zimnin d'azil ihu u'mekadesh lah l'achosa kiddushei
vadai. Okay,
so let's say he goes along and marries, let me just look
across here,
right. So basically, so let's say after having done a ספק קידושין
safek kiddushin to רחל, Rachel, he went ahead and now here's where
לאה Leah comes into the picture. He did a ודאי קידושין vadai
kiddushin to לאה. Leah. Okay? That just,
he went ahead, he didn't know if the money got to רחל
Rachel or not, he decided I'm going to go ahead and marry
לאה. Leah.
He did, he may be,
no, he hasn't slept with her yet. We're going to figure out
what the consequences of that are. If he really is married to
רחל, Rachel, then that would be meaningless. If he wasn't, that worked.
Okay, so he went ahead, he didn't ask anybody, that's what he
did. אי נמי, ei nami, says the גמרא, Gemara, okay, one minute,
ואי נמי זימנין דאתי אחר ומקדש לה לדידה קידושי ודאי. v'ei nami
zimnin d'asi acher u'mekadesh lah l'didah kiddushei vadai. Or
another scenario, okay, somebody else came, I don't know, here we'll have
our friend ברק Barak again, and he's going to go ahead and
marry רחל. Rachel. Okay? So if, let's say after this act of
ספק קידושין, safek kiddushin, some people started doing weird stuff, okay, and
they did other קידושין kiddushin in the picture. So what will the
consequence be now if we say to ראובן Reuven do חליצה chalitzah
don't do ייבום? yibbum? If we say to ראובן Reuven do חליצה
chalitzah to דבורה, Devorah, don't do ייבום, yibbum, in principle we could
go by the status quo, דבורה Devorah remains מותר, mutar, she should
remain single, we should go by the status quo, right? But we're
going to say play it safe, just do חליצה. chalitzah. So חליצה
chalitzah sends the message that, that, what? That what does חליצה chalitzah
send the message?
That ייבום yibbum could have happened. That he wait, did I say
this right?
This is קידושי ספק, kiddushei safek,
so,
I'm sorry, wait. Hold on. Hold on.
אי, ei,
right, if ראובן Reuven כנס kanas do ייבום yibbum to דבורה, Devorah,
it means, right, right, right, right, right, right. So it's not that
ראובן Reuven is doing חליצה, chalitzah, that's funny, because you know people
don't see the absence of ייבום, yibbum, they see the presence of
חליצה. chalitzah. But we'll get to the fact that he did חליצה
chalitzah in a minute, because that sends the opposite message. Doing חליצה
chalitzah sends the message that רחל Rachel that רחל Rachel is not
married. Okay, but that's the גמרא's Gemara not initial step. The initial
step is if we don't let ראובן Reuven do ייבום, yibbum, okay,
the absence of doing ייבום. yibbum. If we don't let him do
ייבום, yibbum, then that sends the message that רחל Rachel is married,
right? If you focus on the fact that he said I want
to do ייבום yibbum and they said you're not allowed, okay, that
would send the message to people that רחל Rachel is married to
שמעון. Shimon. That's why he's not allowed. Oh, if רחל's Rachel married
to שמעון, Shimon, then ברק Barak will assume my marriage didn't work,
and לאה Leah will assume the marriage didn't work. But in principle
since we keep status quo, she's actually not married to שמעון. Shimon.
She's married to ברק Barak or he's married to לאה. Leah. Okay,
so we'll send a problematic message because the message will be that
this works when in principle it didn't work and... There'll be real
consequences from that. Yes? You had a question? No? Okay. Wait, no,
no, let's read that. Okay. וכיון דאתא למימר לצורך יבומי, Ukivan de'ata
l'emar l'tzorech yebumei,
since you're sending the message: Don't do יבום yibum with Devorah, אמרי,
amrei, the only reason you can't do יבום yibum is it must
be the קידושין kiddushin worked, the קמא קידושין, kama kiddushin, the קידושין
kiddushin that Shimon did to Rachel worked, and that's why we won't
allow יבום, yibum, and therefore this stuff we don't have to worry
about. Okay? ודבתר לאו קידושין, ud'batar lav kiddushin, but that's actually not
true, it's actually the opposite and there'll be terrible consequences. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says: One minute, it's not really the absence
of יבום yibum we've got here, we have a presence of חליצה.
chalitzah. And if anything, that sends the right message. Okay? If he
is doing חליצה chalitzah to Devorah, right? Then that sends the message
that he's not married to Rachel. Why? You wouldn't do חליצה chalitzah
if Rachel was in the picture. So the חליצה chalitzah actually sends
the right message, so that's okay.
Why? So you're doing חליצה chalitzah because you don't want to do
יבום yibum with her?
I understand. But the possibility of חליצה chalitzah is only possible if
Rachel's out of the picture. So that exactly reflects the facts. The
status quo is that Rachel is single, that's the real principle in
הלכה. halacha. So what we're saying is this is a no-cost חומרא.
chumra. Why is it a no-cost חומרא? chumra? The הלכה halacha is
that status quo Rachel is not married to Shimon after a ספק
קידושין. safek kiddushin. That's the הלכה. halacha. Go ahead and do חליצה,
chalitzah, okay? What message will it send? It'll send the message that
Rachel's out of the picture. Okay? The only thing is we're not
going to let him do יבום, yibum, but that's not a problematic
message. People don't see the absence of יבום, yibum, they see the
presence of חליצה, chalitzah,
and that actually sends the accurate message.
And the other two קידושין kiddushin both worked.
And these things will work, right. Okay? Let me just finish and
then I'll take the question. וכיון דקמתבעי חליצה, v'kevan d'kamatba'ei chalitzah, since
you're demanding חליצה, chalitzah, מידע ידיע דחומרא בעלמא הוא, meida yedaya d'chumra
b'alma hu, then it's perfect, people know. Okay, since they don't let
him do יבום yibum but they demand חליצה, chalitzah, or they saw
the חליצה, chalitzah, so the right message got sent. The demand of
חליצה chalitzah maybe sent the primary message that this was not- did
not work. You go by status quo. And the fact that we
in principle could have- he could have done יבום, yibum, that's okay,
that's a חומרא. chumra. But no bad message is sent. People see
the חליצה chalitzah which therefore- which therefore sends the right message that
Rachel is not married to Shimon. Now, question.
Are we elevating חליצה chalitzah to an active positive act rather than
just the default position?
Yeah, well it is an act. I mean, it's something you do.
You go ahead and do it. As a default position where you
can't do יבום. yibum.
No, you have to do the act of חליצה, chalitzah, right. And
that's necessary, right, in order to free the woman from the relationship,
she needs an act of חליצה. chalitzah. חליצה chalitzah is not the
absence of יבום. yibum. חליצה chalitzah is the actual act. Taking off
the shoe, the spitting, the whole thing.
Right, but
it's not- we're almost implying here it's not only done when you
don't want to do יבום. yibum.
It's also done when they don't let you do יבום. yibum.
In principle, he could do יבום, yibum, yeah true, I concede the
point, Rachel really is status quo is out of the picture. We're
going to be מחמיר machmir and not allow it, but we're still
going to demand חליצה. chalitzah. Right, and that'll send the right message.
I may have misunderstood but before I thought that the man has
the option to do יבום yibum or חליצה. chalitzah.
He does. Until the Rabbis get involved and say there's some cases
we won't let you do יבום. yibum.
But now חליצה chalitzah as an independent positive act.
There are times when the Rabbis because of like all range of
types of חומרות, chumras, אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato and all these types
of things, don't allow יבום, yibum, but there's still a דאורייתא de'oraisa
connection there and the only way that can be addressed if we're
not allowing יבום yibum is through חליצה. chalitzah.
Okay? All right, so that's what the גמרא Gemara says. You know
what? You're right. We go by status quo, but this case is
a no-cost חומרא, chumra, okay? Because he basically does חליצה, chalitzah, which
is consistent with Rachel not being in the picture, and the only
thing is we're not letting him do יבום, yibum, but that doesn't-
that doesn't undermine the fact that the basic message is that Rachel
is not married. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי גירושין
נמי לתני. ei hachi gerushin nami litni.
So why not go back to the case of גירושין? gerushin? What
would be the case of a ספק גירושין? safek gerushin? Not the
case of the משנה, mishnah, but the parallel case of a ספק
גירושין. safek gerushin. The parallel case of a ספק גירושין safek gerushin
where you would go by the status quo is you have Shimon
is definitely married
to Rachel and Devorah, okay? And then there's a questionable גט. get,
Okay? So there's a question
here, was she taken out of the picture with a גט? get
Okay, so in that case the status quo of Devorah was- and
again Reuven who is Rachel's father...
Okay, so in that case the status quo of Devorah before the
questionable גט get, was מותרת לשוק, muteres lashuk, right? That she wouldn't
have to worry because she was a צרת ערוה. tzarat ervah. And
in principle we're saying before... And now that in principle, you keep
the status quo, you allow her to be מותרת לשוק, muteres lashuk,
and you don't ask, oh, maybe it changed and maybe Rachel's out
of the picture and maybe he has to do חליצה. chalitza. We're
not going to ask him to do חליצה. chalitza. Okay. הגמרא The
Gemara says why not? Have him do חליצה, chalitza, let it be
a חומרא. chumra. So now we're going to see what the consequences
of the negative message that will be sent by the חליצה. chalitza.
אי הכי, Ei hachi, גירושי Gerushi נמי nami ליתני ולצריך חליצה. lisni
uletzrich chalitza. Why not have a חומרא chumra there and make him
do חליצה? chalitza? מידי דהידי דחומרא בעלמא הוא. Midi dehydei dechumra be'alma
hu. People will know, the משנה Mishna said only by a ספק
sofek גט get. which is really a דרבנן פסול גט, d'rabbanan pasul
get, right? The first statement that רבא Rava made is since the
משנה Mishna did not have the parallel of a real ספק safek.
by a גט get? of whether it got to her or not,
that case you would go by status quo. You would ignore the
גט get and you'd go by status quo. So the question is,
why not have a חומרא? chumra? So we're going to have to
explain how a חומרא chumra here is going to come at a
cost. Okay, so here we're going according to רבא, Rava, we keep
the status quo and we let דבורה Devorah go ahead and marry,
we don't demand anything. What will be the cost of a חליצה?
chalitza? How will that be interpreted? So הגמרא the Gemara says still
go ahead and do a
חליצה, chalitza, ולצריך חליצה, uletzrich chalitza, ומידי דהידי דחומרא בעלמא הוא, umidi
dehydei dechumra be'alma hu, people will know it's a חומרא, chumra, right?
How will people know it's a חומרא? chumra? I don't know, because
you're not allowing ייבום. yibbum. So somehow they'll know it's a חומרא.
chumra. Of course, I don't know how you send the message that
you didn't allow ייבום. yibbum. People see חליצה chalitza and they assume
that there was a real relationship. So if he were to do
חליצה, chalitza, people would say oh, if she did חליצה, chalitza, the
only reason he's doing חליצה chalitza is that רחל Rachel must be
divorced. And then רחל Rachel can go ahead and marry another
man, right? She can marry another man because שמעון's Shimon already dead.
But let's say she married a man before she died, okay? You
can figure out the consequences. If he does חליצה, chalitza, it sends
the message that רחל Rachel is divorced. And that's not the case.
In a ספק safek. גט, get it's a status quo and we
assume that she's still married to him. Okay. So here, חליצה chalitza
sends the right message, that רחל Rachel is out of the picture.
Here, חליצה chalitza sends the wrong message. It sends the message that
רחל Rachel is out of the picture when she really is in
the picture. Okay. So הגמרא the Gemara says like this.
So, לא אם אתה אומר חולצת מתייבמת. Lo, im atah omer choletzes
misyabemes.
It's not sending the right message. If you do חליצה, chalitza, people
will assume that רחל Rachel is out of the picture and you
could do ייבום. yibbum. So הגמרא the Gemara says, הכא נמי אם
אתה אומר חולצת מתייבמת. Hacha nami im atah omer choletzes misyabemes.
So here too, if you do חליצה chalitza with דבורה, Devorah, he'll
come to do ייבום yibbum with דבורה. Devorah. So הגמרא the Gemara
says, alright, but big deal. Here he really could do ייבום yibbum
with דבורה. Devorah. Okay. הגמרא The Gemara says, ותתייבם ואין בכך כלום.
Vesisyabbem ve'ein bekach klum. Okay,
so let it be ייבום. yibbum. Meaning we don't want to, we're
מחמיר, machmir, but big deal if you make a mistake. Meaning here
the message of חליצה chalitza is a message that ייבום yibbum might
be possible. Okay. And here ייבום yibbum really is possible. So doing
חליצה chalitza has a very low cost. You're not sending the wrong
message to people, and if he somehow gets confused and chooses to
do ייבום yibbum with דבורה, Devorah, big deal. Basically רחל Rachel really
wasn't in the picture anyway. Here though, רחל Rachel really is in
the picture, we go by status quo. א', Aleph, חליצה chalitza sends
the wrong message. ב', Beis, even if people understand that it's somehow
a חומרא chumra because they see we wouldn't allow ייבום, yibbum, we
demanded חליצה. chalitza. Nevertheless, once you're doing חליצה, chalitza, חליצה's chalitza one
step away from doing ייבום, yibbum, and here it would really be
a major problem. Because here רחל Rachel is in the picture and
ייבום yibbum is a very serious issue of ערווה. erva. Okay? So
the basic simple explanation is we do go by status quo. Here
we can demand חליצה chalitza because it's consistent with the right status.
Here we're not going to allow חליצה chalitza because it actually is
sending the opposite message and allowing for the exact wrong type of
behavior. All right, so let's see where הגמרא the Gemara goes with
this. Okay.
גירושין? Gerushin? Yes, גירושין, gerushin, divorce. Okay. And not allowing. We're not
allowing חליצה. chalitza. Well what we're actually doing is we're not requiring
חליצה. chalitza. We're letting you go by the status quo where because
the ספק safek גט, get you go by status quo, רחל Rachel
still married, and we're letting דבורה Devorah walk off without anything. We're
actually being much more lenient here. We're not requiring חליצה chalitza as
a stringency because to require חליצה chalitza would be counterproductive. Okay, it
would send the exact wrong message. And therefore we're going to, it's
better to actually not be מחמיר. machmir. You know, חומרות chumros don't
often come at cost. Okay, so that's the issue. Now הגמרא the
Gemara says like this. Okay.
So, the basic principle of רבא's Rava whole idea is you keep
the חזקה, chazakah, whether married or divorced and there's a ספק, safek,
in principle you go by the
חזקה. chazakah. איתיביה אביי. Eisiviah Abaye. Abaye asked, here's a
case. נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו, ואין ידוע איזה מהם מת
ראשון. nafal habayis alav v'al bas achiv v'ein yadua eizeh meihem meis
rishon. So
basically ראובן Reuven who
is רחל's Rachel father.
is married to—where am I going to draw this? At the blackboard.
Okay, so
ראובן Reuven
and
שמעון. Shimon.
What's the case?
נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו. Nafal habayis alav ve'al bas achiv,
Hold on.
Right, and it's his niece. Hold on one minute. Be his daughter.
Right. Okay, fine.
So שמעון Shimon is married to—well, we'll do it the same way
we did it before. רחל Rachel is ראובן's Reuven daughter. Okay, so
here שמעון Shimon is married to רחל. Rachel. Okay, that's ראובן's Reuven
daughter. That's בת אחיו. bas achiv. ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven is רחל's
Rachel father.
Okay, רחל's Rachel father. That's the case. Okay? So basically רחל Rachel
is an ערווה ervah to ראובן. Reuven. Okay? And שמעון Shimon is
married to רחל Rachel and he's also married to דבורה. Devorah. Right
then he and רחל Rachel go on a vacation. They didn't invite
דבורה. Devorah.
So and the house fell on them and they both died.
Okay.
So now ראובן Reuven can go ahead and do יבום yibum with
דבורה. Devorah. רחל Rachel is out of the picture. Of course, is
she out of the picture? Who died first? If רחל Rachel died
first, this by the way is assuming מיתה מפולת. misa mapoles. Talk
about מפולת mapoles for those who know that. Anyway, if רחל Rachel
died first and it matters what happens at the time of death,
then when שמעון Shimon died, then only דבורה Devorah was in the
picture and then he could do יבום. yibum. But if שמעון Shimon
died first, then it was צרת ערווה tzaras ervah and he can't.
So what do you do? נפל הבית עליו ועל בת אחיו nafal
habayis alav v'al bas achiv. ואין ידוע איזה מהם מת ראשון. ve'ein
yaduah eizeh meihem meis rishon. You don't know which one. צרתה חולצת
ולא מתיבמת. tzarasa choletzes v'lo misyabemes. So what are you left to
do in a case of ספק? safek? You do חליצה chalitza not
יבום. yibum. ראובן Reuven does it with דבורה. Devorah. But now let's
apply רבה's Raba logic about the status quo. אמאי? amai? הכא נמי
נימא. hacha nami neima. So before the house fell down, what was
דבורה's Devorah status quo? דבורה's Devorah status quo was מותרת לשוק. mutteres
l'shuk. Right? That was her status quo. Right?
Yes? Everybody understand? Yeah. Okay, so let her retain her status quo
and let her go ahead and walk away. Okay? So אמאי? amai?
הכא נמי נימא אשה זו בחזקת היתר לשוק עומדת ומספק אתה בא
לאוסרה אל תאסרנה מספק. hacha nami neima isha zu b'chezkes heter l'shuk
omedes umisafek ata ba l'osrah al teaserena misafek. So why are you
going to demand חליצה? chalitza? וכי תימא הכא נמי לחומרא. v'chi teima
hacha nami l'chumra. Let's be מחמיר. machmir. No. חומרא דאתי לידי קולא
הוא. chumra d'asi lidei kula hu. שמא תאמר חולצת מתיבמת. shema tomar
choletzes misyabemes. Right? ראובן's Reuven going to think, oh, if I do
חליצה chalitza to דבורה, Devorah, I could do יבום yibum to דבורה.
Devorah. Okay? And the status quo actually is that she is—the fact
that she's מותרת לשוק mutteres l'shuk means that she's an ערווה ervah
to ראובן. Reuven. Right? So חליצה chalitza is very dangerous here because
in principle she's a real ערווה ervah to ראובן. Reuven. She's really
אסור assur to ראובן. Reuven. So חליצה chalitza in a case—could lead
to יבום yibum just like here, חליצה chalitza could lead to a
case of יבום yibum when she's really אסור. assur. When she's really
אסור assur to ראובן, Reuven, you don't want her to do חליצה
chalitza because that could lead to יבום. yibum. So the same could
be true here. The status quo is that she's really אסור assur
to ראובן. Reuven. So how could we allow חליצה chalitza to lead
to יבום? yibum?
So the גמרא Gemara says he'll get confused?
Something like that. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, or other
people look at a similar case, גירושין דשכיחי גזרו בהו רבנן. geirushin
dishchiachi gazru behu rabbanan. מפולת דלא שכיחי לא גזרו בהו רבנן. mapoles
d'lo shechiachi lo gazru behu rabbanan. So since the whole thing is,
it's funny because we start by we want to do a חומרא
chumra of חליצה. chalitza. But are we afraid of the cost of
the חומרא? chumra? So here we're not afraid of the cost of
the חומרא. chumra. This case is so rare. So how many times
is it going to happen? If we say do חליצה, chalitza, you
know, oh one of those times instead of doing חליצה chalitza somebody's
going to do יבום. yibum. This case barely ever happens. So here
we can go ahead and be מחמיר machmir and demand חליצה. chalitza.
This type of cases of divorce—divorce sadly is more common. So we
can't allow in this case חליצה chalitza because one of these cases
somebody will wind up doing יבום yibum and that's a real cost.
Okay.
Do we have a case that somebody, you know, was חושש choshesh
for two of them together?
I don't care. Yes, yes.
אינמי. inami. גירושין דקיימא ערווה דקמוכח וצרתה קמצרכה חליצה אמרו קמו בה
רבנן בגיטא דגיטא מעליא הוא. geirushin d'kayma ervah d'kamochach v'tzarasa kamitzracha chalitza
amru kamu bah rabbanan b'gita d'gita maalya hu. Okay, here you understand
how this could lead to חליצה. chalitza. Why? Because in this case,
people will say look, רחל Rachel is around. So why is he
allowed to—why is he doing חליצה chalitza to דבורה? Devorah? Isn't רחל
Rachel here? Doesn't that make דבורה Devorah a צרת ערווה? tzaras ervah?
So the fact that they're saying חליצה, chalitza, it must be that
they looked into the case and they realized that רחל Rachel was
really divorced, else there would not have been חליצה chalitza because people
are going to wonder what's the story with this חליצה. chalitza. So
people will say it must be the rabbis realized רחל Rachel was
really divorced and that's why the חליצה chalitza is. And if that's
true, that's going to lead to negative con—you know, bad consequences. People
will draw the exact wrong conclusions. Okay? So they will say or
he'll come up to do
יבום. yibum. Okay? So he says וקמצרכה חליצה אמרו קמו בה רבנן
בגיטא דגיטא מעליא הוא ואתו ליבומי לצרה. v'kamitzracha chalitza amru kamu bah
rabbanan b'gita d'gita maalya hu v'asu l'yibumei l'tzarah. And then that'll lead
to, right, doing
יבום. yibum. How could you do
חליצה? chalitza? But מפולת, mappolat, מי קמו ביה רבנן במפולת? mi kamu
bei Rabbanan bemappolat? But if a building fell on him in this
case, they'd say, why is he doing חליצה chalitzah with דבורה? Devorah?
First of all, they won't ask the question so much, because רחא
Rakha isn't in the picture. So they're not going to start
wondering like what happened to רחא, Rakha, this and that and the
other. And the other thing is that people, well actually forget what
I just said because that's not what the גמרא Gemara is saying.
Anyway, the point is that people won't say the Rabbis went ahead
and figured
out when the building fell. That's not something that's normally in the
Rabbinic purview. Determining whether a גט get is good or not is
something in the Rabbinic purview. Determining who the building fell on first
tends not to be. So since here it's about a building, people
will not say, oh because it's a חליצה, chalitzah, they must have
known what order things happened. They can more understand that you're doing
a חליצה chalitzah by ספק safek and they won't act on it.
Whereas here, they'll assume that you're doing a חליצה chalitzah because you
figured out the case, and they're afraid that they will. And in
one case they won't and therefore you walk free because the חליצה
chalitzah comes at too big of a cost.
Okay, we'll stop here. Okay, that's enough.