Okay,
good evening everyone. Can't say בוקר טוב. boker tov. Okay, so today's
דף daf or tomorrow's דף daf הושענא רבה Hoshanah Rabbah י"א, yud
alef, but we're going to pick up on י"א עמוד ב, yud
amud bet, and אמר ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן. amlei Reish Lakish
le-Rabbi Yochanan. Now, I think it's worth mentioning something. We have now
been through about nine דף daf because we start on ד', daled,
and until now, we basically the first real amoraic statement, new amoraic
statement referring to the משנה mishna was this discussion between לוי Levi
and רבי Rebbi and why the משנה mishna says fifteen not sixteen.
Until then, it had all been basically the סתם, stam, not based
on any statements of אמוראים. amoraim. First a whole long discussion about
why would I have had a הוה אמינא hava amina that you
could do יבום במקום ערוה, yibbum bemakom ervah, a whole discussion about
what do you call it about עשה דוחה לא תעשה, aseh doche
lo ta'aseh, about what I would have learned out from
אשת אח, eshet ach, and then we got into a whole long
discussion. I'm already forgetting what our whole long discussion had been most
recently. Oh, what does everybody do with everybody else's פסוק, pasuk, you
know all of that. Oh, no, because רבי, Rebbi, רבי Rebbi had
another source. And then,
and then we finally got this issue about fifteen not sixteen. So
it's actually worth noting that the really only new comments other than
this whole discussion of the סתם stam on the משנה mishna was
this question about what the source is for ערוה וצרת ערוה ervah
vetzarat ervah and why the משנה mishna is fifteen and not sixteen.
From this point on, until in a way you can sort of
see a lot of what we just did in the last week
and a half, a huge, I don't know, opening סוגיא sugya introduction
by the סתם. stam. But from this point, I don't know if
you noticed that, how much of the whole narrative was סתם stam
and all of that, how little you had of the actual opinions
of אמוראים amoraim sort of coming head-to-head and being worked out. From
this point on, it's going to be more standard גמרא Gemara that
way and I think in a way, therefore, I don't know if
I could say easier סוגיות sugyas because סוגיות sugyas in יבמות Yevamot
aren't easy, but at least not as much of these long extended
סוגיות, sugyas, much more familiar in terms of statements of אמוראים amoraim
and back and forth between those two opinions and so on. So
that's what we're about to begin now at with where we pick
up on י"א עמוד ב. yud amud bet. You had a question,
Charlie? Okay. So אמר ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן, amlei Reish Lakish
le-Rabbi Yochanan, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said now to רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, ללוי דאמר דאינו נמי קתני, le-Levi de'amar de-inu nami katani,
according to לוי Levi who says that he wants to have sixteen
in the משנה, mishna, including mother, אנוסת אביו. anusat aviv. Okay, and
he's willing to deal with even a בדיעבד bedi'eved the משנה mishna
could list בדיעבד, bedi'eved, okay, because אנוסת אביו anusat aviv here, my
mother, who is אנוסת אביו, anusat aviv, right, if לוי Levi wants
to include that, so that לכתחילה, lechatchila,
you know, לוי Levi can marry ראובן's Reuven mother who was, who
was not יעקב's Yaakov wife. That's a לכתחילה. lechatchila. But according to
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, remember, אנוסת אביו anusat aviv is אסור, asur,
there's a לאו. lav. So the גמרא's Gemara saying, but לוי Levi
apparently wanted to have sixteen in the משנה mishna and presumably even
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, he wants the משנה mishna to
have mother, who is not the father's wife, even according to רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, so he's willing to say include it in this
list of fifteen and he wants to make it sixteen are cases
where even בדיעבד bedi'eved you could be married to somebody. So בדיעבד
bedi'eved according even though אנוסת אביו anusat aviv is אסור asur to,
to a son according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's not כרת
karet and בדיעבד bedi'eved he could be married. So according to לוי
Levi that's willing to have בדיעבדs bedi'eved listed in the משנה, mishna,
ליתני החולץ ליבמתו וחזר וקידשה ומת בלא בנים. listni hacholetz liyvimto vechazar
vekiddesha umet belo banim.
So now all of that is a way to get to what's
going to be our next major discussion, which is the status of
somebody who does חליצה chalitzah and then remarries. Okay, so you have
ראובן Reuven is married to, we don't even have to worry about
sisters anymore, it's a very easy thing. Okay, you have ראובן Reuven
is married to רחל Rachel and you have שמעון Shimon and לוי.
Levi.
ראובן Reuven dies.
שמעון Shimon does
יבום. yibbum. Okay, actually let's say ראובן Reuven is married to רחל
Rachel and דבורה. Devorah. Okay, not related. For once, no
ערוה. ervah. Okay, שמעון Shimon does חליצה. chalitzah. I guess I need
another color. Okay, I don't know what we'll call this, anyway, חליצה.
chalitzah. He does חליצה chalitzah with דבורה. Devorah. Okay, so now he
does חליצה chalitzah with דבורה, Devorah, now everybody is done. Everybody can
go home, right? רחל Rachel is פטור, patar, לוי Levi doesn't have
to do it, one brother does one act, either חליצה chalitzah or
יבום yibbum and everybody goes home. That's the general
הלכה. halakha. Now, here's the question. Okay, everybody goes home, we're all
done. What now would happen if שמעון Shimon would go ahead and
marry דבורה Devorah or have sex with דבורה? Devorah? Would
that be אשת אח eshet ach and חייב יבום chayav yibbum because
he just did חליצה chalitzah to her, right, or would that be
different because he had the potential of doing יבום? yibbum? What would
happen if שמעון Shimon went ahead and had sex with רחל? Rachel?
What would happen if לוי Levi went ahead and had sex with
דבורה Devorah or רחל? Rachel? So חליצה, chalitzah, right, gets everybody off.
But now what is the status of these women after חליצה chalitzah
was done to the brothers? Okay, and that is going to depend...
The big debate of ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* and רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan*. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* is
going to assume, I'll simplify it, I mean not simplify, I'll simplify
it now, I'll clarify it in a minute, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
*Reish Lakish* is going to assume that after חליצה chalitzah, *chalitzah* is
done, basically everybody goes back to being an איסור כרת issur kares
*issur kareis*. Okay? There's one exception to that, we'll worry about it
in a minute, but I'm going to simplify it now. ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* assumes everybody becomes an איסור כרת issur kares.
*issur kareis*. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, *Rebbi Yochanan* assumes even after חליצה
chalitzah. *chalitzah* is done, there's like an איסור לאו issur lav *issur
lav* to remarry, but no longer is anybody considered אשת אח eishes
ach. *eishes ach*. Okay? So this is the big debate of רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan *Rebbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*,
we'll make it more precise in a minute, but let's just get
through this discussion and then we'll get to unpacking it. Okay? So
אמר ליה Amlei, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish לרבי יוחנן *Amar Lei Reish
Lakish leRebbi Yochanan*: לוי Levi, דאמר דאי נמי תני ליתני *Levi de'amar
de'inami tani lisni*. So if the משנה mishnah *mishnah* of 15 is
willing to include 16, אנוסה anusa, ופתויה *anusa u-fetuya* we're willing to
deal with בדיעבד bediyeved *bidi'avad*, here's another בדיעבד b'di'avad *bidi'avad*: ליתני *lisni*
the following case: החולץ ליבמתו ha-choleitz le-yevamto. וחזר וקידשה ומת בלא בנים
*hacholetz liyvimto vechazar vekiddsha umeis belo banim*.
So שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* did חליצה chalitzah, *chalitzah* to דבורה Dvora *Devora*
and then after he did חליצה chalitzah *chalitzah* to דבורה Dvora, *Devora*,
so this was stage one, and then stage two, let's get לוי
Levi *Levi* down here somewhere, after stage
two is he went ahead and he married her. Okay? Now, okay,
so that was בדיעבד *bidi'avad*, he's not allowed to marry her, right,
after he did חליצה chalitzah. *chalitzah*, that's it, right? And that's based
on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of אשר לא יבנה asher lo yivneh,
את בית אחיו *asher lo yivneh es beis achiv*, right, this is
after חליצה chalitzah, *chalitzah*, כיון שלא בנה keivan shelo bana, שוב אינו
בונה *kivan shelo banah shuv eino boneh*.
Okay? Once you're done, you're done.
So he's not allowed to remarry דבורה Dvora *Devora*. He goes ahead
and he does remarry דבורה Dvora *Devora*, that's בדיעבד *bidi'avad*. But he
says, ah, but here's another case we could have listed in our
משנה mishnah. *mishnah*. Because now what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan, *Rebbi Yochanan*
is going to assume, what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* is
assumed, is he basically assumes, now I'll get to be more precise,
he basically assumes that שמעון Shimon *Shimon* who did חליצה chalitzah *chalitzah*
to דבורה Dvora *Devora* is אסור assur בלאו *assur belav* to now
remarry her. That's an איסור לאו issur lav *issur lav*. Why? Based
on this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*: אשר לא יבנה lo yivneh. *asher lo
yivneh*, כיון שלא בנה שוב אינו בונה *kivan shelo banah shuv eino
boneh*. So basically this פסוק posuk *pasuk* is read don't redo it
after you've done it. Don't go marry her after you've done it.
He's a לאו lav *lav*. But for everybody else, says ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish. *Reish Lakish*, it's an איסור כרת issur kares. *issur kareis*.
Okay? He, because he had this relationship to her, it's no longer
a simple case of אשת אח eishes ach. *eishes ach*, it's this
new איסור issur *issur* of כיון שלא בנה *kivan shelo banah*. But
לוי Levi, *Levi* is איסור כרת issur kares *issur kareis* to דבורה
Dvora. *Devora* and איסור כרת issur kares *issur kareis* to רחל Rochel
*Rachel*. Okay? Because they go back to being אשת אח eishes ach.
*eishes ach*. Not only that, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* is also an איסור
כרת issur kareis. *issur kareis*, you know who to? To רחל Rochel
*Rachel*. Okay? That's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* thinks. Everybody
goes back to being an איסור כרת issur kareis, *issur kareis* with
the one exception, I know this is much more complicated than it
is, but with the one exception of שמעון Shimon *Shimon* and דבורה
Dvora *Devora* to who he did חליצה chalitzah *chalitzah* to, that gets
restructured as a special new איסור issur, יבום yibum, *issur yibum*. So
what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* says is: I've got a
scenario that we should have added to our 15. What's the scenario?
שמעון Shimon, *Shimon* goes ahead, does חליצה chalitzah, *chalitzah* to דבורה Dvora
*Devora* and then remarries her. Okay? He wasn't allowed to do it,
but it's only an איסור לאו issur lav, *issur lav*, so בדיעבד
*bidi'avad* it's binding, the קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* is binding, and then שמעון
Shimon, *Shimon* dies. So ראובן Reuven *Reuven* now is דבורה Devorah *Devora*
is אסור assur *assur* to him as an איסור כרת issur kareis,
*issur kareis*. That's what, I'm not ראובן Reuven *Reuven*, לוי Levi *Levi*,
right? That's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* says. So why
didn't we have that case? Here's another case of an ערוה erva.
*ervah*, somebody who was חלוצת *chalutzas* of a brother that got remarried,
now שמעון Shimon *Shimon* dies, so now דבורה Devorah, *Devora* goes back
to being שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s wife, legal wife, because this was only
an איסור לאו issur lav. *issur lav*, and then לוי Levi *Levi*
has a מצות יבום mitzvah d'yibum *mitzvot yibum*, but it's an איסור
issur ערוה *issur ervah* because when ראובן Reuven *Reuven* died she became
אשת אח eishes ach. *eishes ach*.
And שמעון Shimon *Shimon* had another wife, that wife would be exempted
by,
yes, but let's not go there right now. Okay? But yes, that's
true actually. But let's not go there. Okay? So anyway, that's his
question. החולץ ליבמתו ha-choleitz le-yevamto. וחזר וקידשה ומת בלא בנים *hacholetz liyvimto
vechazar vekiddsha umeis belo banim*, דמיגו דאי אסורה *demigo
dee'assura*, and now since, oh actually right, that actually was the case
we were dealing with, that שמעון Shimon *Shimon* was also married legally
unrelated to רחל Rochel. *Rachel*. Okay? So they're right, that's the co-wife.
Okay? So that's why actually we should put it over there. Okay,
שמעון Shimon *Shimon*'s wife. Anyway fine, I know this is getting way
too complicated. Anyway, he's also married to רחל Rochel, *Rachel*, so that's
a co-wife, that's a צרה tzora *tzarah*, she's a צרה tzora, *tzarah*
to דבורה Devorah *Devora*. Okay? So that's a scenario. He remarries דבורה
Devorah, *Devora*, she becomes an ערוה *ervah* to לוי Levi *Levi*. Okay?
So he dies, so then this, she's an ערוה *ervah* to him,
and that's צרת ערוה *tzaras ervah*. Why wasn't that mentioned in the
משנה Mishna *mishnah*? אמר ליה *Amar lei*, yes,
I'm not clear on
something, this isn't so
clear,
yes, he's married to
רחל Rachel, *Rachel*.
Right. So that's the case of of of of חלוצה chalutza that
was remarried. Okay. So why isn't that listed? So אמר ליה, he
said to him, לפי שאינה בצרת צרה. lefi she-einah b'tzoras tzora.
So he said, here's why. Because our משנה wanted to mention cases
of ערווה ervah and צרה tzara, and צרת צרה. tzoras tzora. Right?
Remember what the case of צרת צרה tzoras tzora would be? רחל
Rachel goes, she's a צרה, tzara. she marries another brother, and then
her co-wife, right, is a צרת צרה. tzoras tzora. Remember that case?
Yes? Okay. So that you cannot have her marrying another brother. You
can't have a צרת צרה. tzoras tzora. Why? Because any other brother,
right, all the brothers that she could marry that would do another
יבום, yibum right, are all brothers from the same father, right? שמעון,
Shimon לוי, Levi. יהודה, Yehuda, right, or whatever, everybody. They're all brothers
from the same אב. av. Okay. So for all of the brothers,
we could have a case of צרת צרה tzoras tzora because she
could be one brother's daughter and not the other brother, and she
could be only a problem to one brother and not a problem
to any of the others. But here, the whole problem is she's
אסור assur to all of the brothers because this was a woman
that was a father's—a brother, a paternal brother's wife, right? So דבורה
Devorah, here is going to be, right, דבורה, Devorah, there was a
מצות יבום yibum that fell on all the brothers. שמעון Shimon did
חליצה, chalitzah, then remarried her. The חלוצה made her back into brother's
wife for all these brothers. So now the co-wife here can't marry
anybody else because that co-wife is equally, right, אסור assur to all
of the brothers, right? When now שמעון Shimon dies, דבורה Devorah, is
אסור assur to all the brothers, and רחל Rachel is אסור assur
to all the brothers. So you don't have a case of צרת
צרה. tzoras tzora. So the גמרא Gemara says, this is such a
difficult way to find to get to the debate of רבי יוחנן
וריש לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish, which is actually going to
be more straightforward. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולימא ליה חייבי לאווין
היא וחייבי לאווין בני חליצה ויבום נינהו. ve-leima lei chayavei lavin hi
ve-chayavei lavin benei chalitzah ve-yibum ninhu.
Why didn't רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan say, hey ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish,
I think דבורה Devorah, is not an איסור כרת issur kareis. to
the brothers? I think that she's only an איסור לאו issur lav
to the brothers. I don't believe that everybody goes back to being
an איסור כרת. issur kareis So the גמרא Gemara says, לדבריו קאמר
ליה. ledivarav ka'amar lei.
He's saying within ריש לקיש's Resh Lakish. own approach. לדידי, ledidi, as
far as I'm concerned, says רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan חייבי לאווין היא.
chayavei lavin hi.
A woman who has had יבום yibum, done and then remarries the
guy, that's—she's only an איסור לאו issur lav. to the other brothers,
and the—and her co-wife, everybody's only an איסור לאו, issur lav, no
איסור כרת. issur kareis. Okay? וחייבי לאווין בני חליצה ויבום נינהו. ve-chayavei
lavin benei chalitzah ve-yibum ninhu.
And in those cases, you know, you there if you, you know,
if you did יבום yibum, it would be binding, and you have
to do חליצה. chalitza It's not an ערווה. ervah. It doesn't deserve
to be mentioned in the משנה. אלא לדידך, ela ledidach,
but according to you, the reason you asked the question was חייבי
כריתות נינהו, chayavei krisos ninhu, that you think that דבורה Devorah. is
an איסור כרת issur karei? to the other brothers. So according to
you, לפי שאינה בצרת צרה. lefi she-einah b'tzoras tzora. The reason is
that it's not a צרת צרה. tzoras tzora. Okay.
So basically that was a very complicated
way of finally getting us to the debate of רבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש, Rabbi Yochanan and Reish Lakish, which we are going to say
right now. איתמר. itmar. החולץ ליבמתו.
This is of course where we should have started. החולץ ליבמתו.
Somebody who does חליצה, chalitza וחזר וקדשה, ve-chozar ve-kidshah, and remarry her.
אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, הוא אין חייב על החלוצה כרת.
hu ein chayav al ha-chalutza kares.
He, if—he remarried this woman he did חליצה chalitza to, so again
let's try to draw this in a less confusing way now. Okay.
ראובן Reuven is married to רחל. Rachel? שמעון Shimon is married
to, is married to דבורה. Devorah. Then ראובן Reuven, dies. He does
חליצה. chalitza I need more colors. You know what?
Anyway, let's get—I have a
blue. Check that's dry-erase.
Okay. So blue will be חליצה, chalitza okay? So he does חליצה
chalitza. to רחל, Rachel, okay?
And then after doing חליצה chalitza, he goes ahead and—other way around,
other direction—remarries her. חזר וקדשה. chozar ve-kidshah. Okay?
So that's the case.
All right? So חזר וקדשה. chozar ve-kidshah.
So she is a woman that after חליצה, chalitza, based on this
idea כיון שבנה שוב לא יבנה, keivan shebanah shuv lo yivneh, he
could have done יבום, yibum he did חליצה, chalitza. he had a
relationship with her, her relationship to him now is defined in the
context of יבום, yibum of his כיון שבנה שוב לא יבנה. keivan
shebanah shuv lo yivneh. Everybody agrees that this is an איסור לאו.
issur lav, Okay. That's an איסור לאו issur lav, based on that.
Okay? That's what we've got there. What the question is going to
be: what is the story about דבורה Devorah and what is the
story about the other brothers?
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish. said דבורה Devorah, is an איסור כרת issur
karei. and the other brothers are
every Everybody reverts to being brother's wife, the only exception is the
one woman who had חליצה chalitza done to her, her status is
defined within the יבום yibum world, everybody else reverts to being אשת
אח. eishes ach. Okay? So he does, so if now, so if,
פיין. fayn. So that's that, whereas, that's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
says. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan. says everybody is in the same boat
of an איסור לאו. issur lav, All right? So that's what we
have. Let's read that. אחות יבמתו וחלוצתו וקרובתה. achot yevamto ve'chalutzato u'krovata.
אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, הוא אינו חייב על החלוצה כרת.
hu eino chayav al ha'chalitza kareis. He, שמעון, Shimon who goes back
and marries רחל, Rachel is not חייב כרת. chayav kareis. She now
relates to him only within the יבום yibum world context, so it's
an איסור לאו, issur lav it's not an איסור כרת. issur karei.
והאחים חייבים על החלוצה כרת. ve'ha'achim chayavim al ha'chalitza kareis.
But לוי Levi now, his relationship with רחל Rachel will be an
איסור כרת, issur karei. okay? Because that remains, here we'll do red
for כרת. kareis. Okay? So that's כרת. kareis. That goes back to
being אשת אח. eishes ach.
Okay? והאחים חייבים על החלוצה כרת, ve'ha'achim chayavim al ha'chalitza kareis, על
הצרה בין הוא ובין האחים חייבים על הצרה כרת.
al ha'tzara
bein hu u'vein ha'achim chayavim al ha'tzara kareis. And
by הצרה, ha'tzara, okay? Oh, הצרה. ha'tzara. I, yeah, but I did
it wrong again. I'm sorry, I apologize, because like I said last
time, yes, דבורה Devorah. is the צרה, tzarah. but she's ראובן'ס Reuven's
צרה. She was from here, okay?
So he could have done חליצה chalitza, to either רחל Rachel. or
דבורה, Devorah right? He did it to one of them, so his
relationship, again, this is the one he did חליצה chalitza. to, so
that relationship is redefined in יבום yibum context, special יבום yibum status.
Everybody else is an איסור כרת, issur karei okay? And even him
to דבורה Devorah is an איסור כרת. issur karei. The only person
who's not an איסור כרת Issur Kares is him with the woman
he did חליצה chalitza to. That exists within the יבום yibum world,
but everybody else goes back to being אשת אח. eishes ach.
But wait, doesn't he did the חליצה chalitza to רחל? Rachel Yes.
I don't understand why he can remarry her.
He can't. It's an איסור לאו, issur lav, כיון שלא בנה, so
he is עובר over on the איסור לאו, issur lav. but it
is a special יבום איסור. yibum issur. Once he was, he related
to her in the יבום מצוה, yibum mitzvah, his ongoing relationship to
her is within the יבום yibum world and it's an איסור issur
of remarrying.
So from the first time he should ליבם אותה? lyabem osa? Right,
that's what, right, exactly.
That would have solved everything. Okay, so that's what ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish. says. A special relationship here, everybody else goes back to being
אשת אח. eishes ach. בין הוא ובין האחים חייבים על הצרה כרת.
bein hu u'vein ha'achim chayavim al ha'tzara kareis. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rebbi
Yochanan amar, בין הוא ובין האחים אינם חייבים לא על החלוצה כרת
ולא על הצרה כרת. bein hu u'vein ha'achim einam chayavim lo al
ha'chalitza kareis ve'lo al ha'tzara kareis.
Nope, everybody is a new איסור, issur okay? It's not, they don't
go back to being אשת אח. eshes ach His relationship with דבורה,
Devorah, לוי'ס Levi's relationship with רחל, Rachel דבורה, Devorah it's all a
new איסור issur but not an איסור כרת. Issur Kares? Now the
גמרא'ס Gemara's going to spell it out. Okay, מאי טעמא דריש לקיש?
mai ta'ama de'Reish Lakish? אמר קרא, amar kra, אשר לא יבנה, כיון
שלא בנה שוב לא יבנה. keivan shelo bana shuv lo yivneh. Okay?
So you're not allowed to remarry after you've done חליצה. chalitza איהו
הוא דקאי בלא יבנה. ihu hu de'ka'ei be'lo yivneh. He, שמעון, Shimon.
who did חליצה, chalitza he has this new איסור issur, to רחל
Rachel, called לא יבנה. אבל אחיו, aval achiv, his brother לוי, Levi
כי דקאי קאי. ki de'ka'ei ka'ei. He never had a יבום yibum
relationship with רחל Rachel or with דבורה, so it remains אשת אח.
eshes ach, ועל דידה הוא דקאי בלא יבנה. ve'al didah hu de'ka'ei
be'lo yivneh. And even שמעון'ס Shimon's relationship is only with
רחל. Rachel, אהצרה, a'hatzara, but דבורה, כי דקאי קאי, ki de'ka'ei ka'ei,
he never had a יבום yibum, relationship with דבורה, so that goes
back to אשת אח. Okay? So it makes sense. This got redefined
in the יבום yibum world, everything else had a potential of יבום,
yibum but in the end that potential didn't actualize, so it goes
back to the איסור issur of אשת אח. That's what ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish says. Okay? And that's why he asks why didn't we
include this scenario in the משנה because it's another ערוה. רבי יוחנן,
Rebbi Yochanan,
now what's רבי יוחנן'ס Rebbi Yochanan's reason?
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan would tell you, one minute, מי איכא מידי
דמעיקרא אי בעי האי חליץ ואי בעי האי חליץ? mi ika midi
de'me'ikara ei ba'ei hai chalitz ve'ei ba'ei hai chalitz?
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says this doesn't make any sense. Before anybody
did anything, שמעון Shimon could have done חליצה, chalitza לוי Levi could
have done חליצה. chalitza They equally could have, meaning the potential was
there equally for שמעון Shimon? and לוי Levi and for רחל Rachel,
and דבורה. Any of those relationships could have existed. They could have
done חליצה chalitza. with anybody, could have done יבום yibum with anyone.
אי בעי להאי חליץ ואי בעי להאי חליץ. ei ba'ei le'hai chalitz
ve'ei ba'ei le'hai chalitz. If wanted to, it could have been שמעון
Shimon doing חליצה, chalitza, could have been לוי Levi doing חליצה. chalitza.
ואי בעי
להאי חליץ ואי בעי להאי חליץ. ve'ei ba'ei le'hai chalitz ve'ei ba'ei
le'hai chalitz. And they could have done חליצה chalitza to רחל Rachel.
or they could have done חליצה chalitza to דבורה. So any of
this relationship here could have equally been with דבורה and could have
equally been with לוי. Levi, So they all should be treated in
that context of that יבום yibum world because they all have the
opportunity to do it. So if there's now a new איסור issur
because חליצה chalitza was done, it should be equal to everyone. Okay?
And now he's going to even sharpen it further. So of the
והשתא דקיילא בכרעי? V'hashta dekayala bekarei? So he could have done חליצה
chalitza with anybody, you know, any man and any of the women
could have done חליצה chalitza with one another and now all of
a sudden they could have even said they could have done יבום
yibum with one another and now all of a sudden they go
to an איסור כרת? Issur Kares. That doesn't make sense. אלא, Ella,
and now he clarifies why not, and this becomes a very important
conceptual idea within יבמות. Yevamos. So here we're really getting now to
the heart of understanding the mechanism.
איהו שליחותא דאחין קעביד. Ihu shlichusa d'achin ka'avid. He is doing the
agency of the brothers.
איהי שליחותא דצרה קעבדה, Ihi shlichusa d'tzara ka'avda, and she is doing
the agency of her co-wife.
What he is saying is, so
besides the idea, look, everybody had the potential, we should look at
them through the יבום yibum lens and not through אשת אח lens.
That's one way of saying it.
But he goes even further and he says when שמעון Shimon here
does חליצה chalitza. with רחל, Rachel? any of the brothers could have
done חליצה. chalitza. So שמעון is basically representing, he's there like a
שליח ציבור, shliach tzibur, okay, he's representing לוי Levi. and יהודה. Yehuda.
He's representing all of them. And when רחל Rachel, receives חליצה, chalitza.
well, any of the co-wives could have received חליצה. chalitza So she
is representing all of the co-wives, okay?
So what that means is, so what do we actually say happened?
You know what we actually say happened? All of the brothers effectively
did חליצה chalitza to all of the co, to all of the
wives, okay? So everybody, instead of this in theory they could have
done it, in practice we look at it as that everybody did
it with everyone else and therefore everybody has the same status. So
if this is a special איסור, issur? not brother's wife, but a
new איסור issur in the יבום yibum. world, okay, that איסור issur
now applies to all the brothers and all the co-wives because it's
like they all went through the חליצה chalitza. process. Yes.
There's a third position which was not brought up, which is the
possibility that all of the wives are an איסור כרת. Issur Kares.
Yes, but that for some reason is not, we'll see there's even
Tannaitic evidence why they started with the, they everybody agreed by the,
by the woman at least to whom חליצה chalitza was done. Okay,
so that's רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan Fascinating new debate. How do you
look at it? Do you look at only those two parties did
it and everybody else is exempt, or do you look at it
as all the parties did it? איתיבי. Aiseivi. Now we're going to
get to trying to prove who's right. Now it's like a classic
סוגיא. sugya. You have רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan you have ריש לקיש,
Resh Lakish let's mount up the evidence. איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש.
Aiseivi Rebbi Yochanan l'Reish Lakish. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan asked ריש
לקיש. החולץ ליבמתו וחזר וקדשה ומת, Hacholaitz l'yivmosei v'chazar v'kidsha u'meis, צריכה
חליצה מן האחין. tzricha chalitza min ha'achin.
So this is a ברייתא braisa we have, okay? החולץ ליבמתו וחזר
וקדשה, Hacholaitz l'yivmosei v'chazar v'kidsha,
we're back to this case where שמעון and רחל, Rachel חולץ וחזר
וקדשה, cholaiz v'chazar v'kidsha,
and then שמעון died. צריכה חליצה מן האחין. tzricha chalitza min ha'achin.
So there you go. It says what happens after שמעון died, it
says that לוי Levi and יהודה, Yehuda, if שמעון now died, he
wasn't allowed to remarry רחל, Rachel, but nevertheless he did, okay, and
now he dies, okay. So לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda have to
do חליצה Halitzah with רחל. Rachel Now according to ריש לקיש, what's
לוי Levi and יהודה's Yehuda relationship to רחל? Rachel What would what's
the nature of the איסור?
issur An איסור כרת.
Issur Kares? So there's no חליצה Halitzah in איסור כרת. Issur Kares?
So the ברייתא braisa says they have to do חליצה. chalitzah So
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says to me that works. There's an איסור
לאו, issur lav. פיצי שבנה שוב אינו בונה pitzi shebanah shuv eino
boneh to רחל, Rachel. but an איסור לאו issur lav doesn't get
you out of חליצה. chalitzah? So therefore they would they can't do
יבום yibum. because there's this איסור לאו, issur lav. but they would
still have to do חליצה. chalitzah. So there's a clear ברייתא braisa
proves my position. Yes.
So we have the irony that ריש לקיש by being more מחמיר
machmir by declaring her an איסור כרת Issur Kares. is freeing her
from having to do חליצה chalitzah or יבום.
yibum That is correct. That is correct. If you're more מחמיר machmir
on her status, then it turns out to be a קולא kula
in terms of the requirements of חליצה chalitzah and יבום. Yibbum. Okay,
so here it says this proves my case. צריכה חליצה מן האחין.
tzricha chalitza min ha'achin.
That works. Okay. בשלמא לדידי, Bishlama l'didi,
according to me it works. אמינא חייבי לאוין נינהו Amina chayavei lavin
ninhu that the איסור issur is just a new איסור לאו. issur
lav, היינו דצריכה חליצה מן האחין, Hainu d'tzricha chalitza min ha'achin,
that's why you need חליצה. chalitzah.
אלא לדידך, Ella l'didach, according to you, אמאי צריכה חליצה? amai tzricha
chalitza? It's an איסור כרת. Issur Kares. Okay, pretty good proof. Now
he says back, wait one minute. ולטעמיך, U'l'tamaich, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
says back, ריש לקיש says back, according to you, אימא סיפא. eima
seifa. You only quoted the first half of the ברייתא. braisa. Here's
the second half of the ברייתא. braisa. עמד אחד מן האחין וקדשה,
Amad echad min ha'achin v'kidsha,
now if one of these brothers לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda goes
ahead and marries רחל Rachel, after שמעון died, וקדשה, v'kidsha, אין לה
עליו כלום. ein la alav klum. So he has no relationship to
him, meaning it's not binding, okay? So that's crazy. He says, according
to you, there was an איסור לאו. issur lav. If they actually
went ahead with יבום Yibbum which they shouldn't have done, it would
have been binding, okay? He says ואי חייבי לאוין נינהו אמאי אין
לה עליו כלום? v'ee chayavei lavin ninhu amai ein la alav klum?
So basically you have a contradictory ברייתא. braisa. The ברייתא braisa says
what happens in this scenario. First it says that they have to
do חליצה chalitzah with רחל, Rachel and then it says but if
they went ahead and קדשה kidsha or you could also say יבמה,
yivma, if they went ahead and had a relationship, it's nothing. So
it doesn't, it's not binding. The only time something isn't binding is
if it's an איסור כרת Issur Kares, *issur kares*.
Okay, but the only time you have to do חליצה chalitzah. *chalitza*
is if it's an איסור לאו issur lav *issur lav*. So we've
got a contradiction. What's, what's the story? Do they have to do
חליצה chalitzah, *chalitza*? Then it should be binding. If it's not binding,
they shouldn't have to do חליצה chalitza *chalitza*. Okay, so the ברייתא
baraita. *braita* doesn't work.
It's not consistent.
It can't work consistently with Yohanan or Resh Lakish.
So now we're going to try to reconcile it according to each
approach. So he says like this. אמר רב Rav ששת *Amar Rav
Sheshes*, סופא אתיא כרבי עקיבא דאמר אין קידושין kiddushin. תופסין בחייבי לאוין
*seifa asya ke-Rabbi Akiva d'amar ein kiddushin tofsin be-chayvei lavin*. Yeah, the
end of it is a different opinion.
Here it says you do חליצה chalitza, *chalitza* because it's only an
איסור לאו issur lav.
*issur lav*, and the end where it says it's not binding, that's
a different opinion. That's Rabbi Akiva's position, who says איסור לאו issur
lav *issur lav* is like an איסור issur כרת *issur kares* and
it's not binding. So according to Rabbi Akiva, you wouldn't have to
do חליצה chalitza. *chalitza* either. He says איסור לאו issur lav, *issur
lav* and איסור issur כרת *issur kares* are the same. But he's
saying the ברייתא braisa, *braita* is two halves. This, everybody agrees it's
an איסור issur לאו lav. *issur lav*. The first half follows the
normal opinion that לאו lav *lav* is different than כרת *kares* and
you do, and you do חליצה chalitza. *chalitza*. And the second half
follows Rabbi Akiva that says the לאו lav *lav* is like כרת
*kares* and you, and it's not binding. סופא אתיא כרבי עקיבא דאמר
אין קידושין kiddushin, תופסין בחייבי לאוין *seifa asya ke-Rabbi Akiva d'amar ein
kiddushin tofsin be-chayvei lavin*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says וליתני לדיברי
רבי עקיבא אין לו עליו כלום *u-lisni le-divrei Rabbi Akiva ein lo
alav klum*. If the second half of the ברייתא *braita* is only
Rabbi Akiva's position and it's against the first half which says חייבי
לאו lav *chayvei lav* is different, the end of the ברייתא *braita*
should have said: According to Rabbi Akiva, it would not be binding.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קשיא *kashya*. Okay, that's difficult. Top
of דף י"א עמוד א' *daf yod aleph amud aleph*. So the
first answer which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* isn't happy with is the
two halves of the ברייתא *braita* are two different opinions. They, they
don't work consistent. Now we're going to try another way to reconcile
it. רב Rav, אשי סבר לה savar lah כריש לקיש *Rav Ashi
savar lah ke-Resh Lakish*. Rav Ashi holds like Resh Lakish. ומתרץ לה
umitaretz lah כרבי שמעון *u-metareitz lah ke-Rabbi Shimon*. And he is going
to reconcile the ברייתא *braita* according to Rabbi Shimon. We'll see what
this means in a minute. רבינא Ravina סבר לה כרבי יוחנן keRabbi
Yochanan *Ravina savar lah ke-Rabbi Yochanan*. Now everybody's taking sides, okay? Resh
Lakish and Rabbi Yochanan, Ravina and Rav Ashi. Ravina holds like Rabbi
Yochanan. ומתרץ כרבנן *u-metareitz
ke-rabbanan*. And he's going to reconcile the ברייתא *braita* like the rabbis
of Rabbi Shimon. Just wait. Okay. Now we're going to spell it
out. רב Rav אשי סבר לה כריש לקיש ומתרץ לה כרבי שמעון
*Rav Ashi savar lah ke-Resh Lakish u-metareitz lah ke-Rabbi Shimon*. החולץ ליבמתו
וחזר וקידשה *ha-choleitz li-yevamto ve-chazar ve-kiddashah*, צריכה חליצה chalitza מן האחין *tzrichah
chalitza min ha-achin*.
Now according to Resh Lakish, this part makes sense. If you went
ahead and went through with the יבום yibbum *yibum* or the קידושין
*kiddushin*, nothing happens because it's an איסור issur כרת *issur kares*. The
problem is going to be why is חליצה chalitza. *chalitza* necessary? It's
an איסור issur כרת *issur kares*. So here's what he's going to
say. Remember Rabbi, well, let's read it and then okay, here's what
he says. He says, החולץ ליבמתו וחזר וקידשה צריכה חליצה chalitza, מן
האחין *ha-choleitz li-yevamto ve-chazar ve-kiddashah tzrichah chalitza min ha-achin*. What's the scenario
you need to do חליצה chalitza *chalitza*? מאן אחין אחין הנולדים hanoladin.
*man achin achim ha-noladim*.
It means new brothers, brothers that were recently born. תימא כרבי שמעון
*teima ke-Rabbi Shimon*. According to Rabbi Shimon.
You'll remember that Rabbi Shimon says that if a brother is born
after the second brother married the wife of אחיו שלא היה בעולמו
shelo haya beolamo, *achiv she-lo haya be-olamo*, anyway the new person who's
born, he only relates to this woman in the way he came
into the world, in the status she had when she came into
the world. You sort of remember that with Rabbi Shimon? Yes, vaguely.
Okay. So what happens? שמעון *Shimon* died, okay, and he died though
after he had done what? After he had remarried רחל Rachel *Rachel*,
right? And then לוי Levi *Levi* ויהודה *ve-Yehuda* were born, what, or
לוי Levi *Levi* was born. What relationship does he find רחל *Rachel*
in when he's born? רחל *Rachel* is who to him when לוי
Levi *Levi* is now born? Sister-in-law. שמעון *Shimon*'s wife. Yeah. לוי *Levi*
was over on an איסור issur *issur*, but it's binding, it's שמעון
*Shimon*'s wife. So שמעון *Shimon*'s wife is not איסור issur כרת *issur
kares*. שמעון *Shimon*'s going to die from מצוות יבום mitzvah of yibbum.
*mitzvas yibum*. He does this past history completely irrelevant to לוי *Levi*.
לוי *Levi* was born after that was all past history. So when
does it say that you do חליצה chalitza. *chalitza*? You did חליצה
chalitza *chalitza* if לוי *Levi* was born after that was all past
history and he came into the world when she was already שמעון
*Shimon*'s wife.
He could do יבום yibbum, *yibum*.
Okay. So that's, so that's that. So אחים הנולדים
*achim ha-noladim*, newly born brothers. תימא כרבי שמעון *teima ke-Rabbi Shimon*. אמר
אחד מן הנולדים בקידושין *amar echad min ha-noladim be-kiddushin*, when is the
case that it doesn't work even בדיעבד *be-di'avad*, not if they were
newly born, but if they were had already been born. So actually
let's switch the birth order, okay? יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* was born later,
okay, here, between, between חליצה *chalitza* and קידושין *kiddushin* is when, you
know, we'll just have whatever. יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* was already alive when
all of this was happening, okay? So in that case, יהודה Yehuda
*Yehuda*'s alive, for יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* it's an איסור issur, כרת *issur
kares*. So the second part of the ברייתא *braita* that says it's
an איסור כרת *issur kares* and it's not binding is for יהודה
Yehuda *Yehuda* who was alive when all of this is happening. That's
הנולדים *ha-noladim*, he was, he was already born when all of this
was happening. The first part of the ברייתא *braita* that says that
חליצה *chalitza* is required, that's for לוי *Levi* who was born after
all of this happened, right? I switched יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda*, I don't
know why, yeah. I switched it.
לוי *Levi* had to, but anyway, יהודה Yehuda *Yehuda* was,
whatever. Anyway, fine. So לוי was around when all this was happening,
so for him it's an איסור כרת and בדיעבד nothing will work,
but יהודה Yehuda who was then born later, right, for יהודה Yehuda?
it's a he it's all past history and for him he could
go ahead and do חליצה or do יבום. yibbum Okay, I think
I confused you a little with reversing יהודה Yehuda and לוי, but
you understand the point, okay? What for whom is it an איסור
כרת? For somebody who was around when this was happening. For whom
does it say that's נולדים? noladin? For whom does it say that
you can still do חליצה or maybe even יבום yibbum with the
woman? For somebody who was born after and the and that everything
else was ancient history, that's ילודים. yeludim. So that's how it works
according to ריש לקיש, yes.
So this doesn't follow that principle that one brother is doing the
other brother's
well this is ריש לקיש. So that's where working that's how it
works according to ריש לקיש. Okay, now okay רבינא Ravina סבר
לה כרבי יוחנן and רבינא holds like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan ומתרץ
לה לדרבנן. leDerabbanan. Now he's going to make this all work according
to the רבנן Rabbanan who argue on רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. It
doesn't matter when you're born. החולץ ליבמתו וחזר וקדשה צריכה חליצה מן
האחים. hacholetz liyvimto vachazar vekidsah tzerichah chalitzah min ha'achim. So that's the
easy case, right, because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds that's the standard,
the standard is an איסור לאו lav. and חליצה still needs to
be done. Okay, מאן אחים אחים הנולדים? man achim achim hanoladin? כמאן
כרבי יוחנן. keman keRabbi Yochanan. And that would be by brothers that
were around at the time,
so right now
according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan it's the opposite. According to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who has an איסור חליצה, issur chalitzah, who I
mean who has a requirement of חליצה? לוי. לוי is around when
all of this is happening. What does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say?
Every that all the brothers have an איסור לאו. lav So לוי
is around when all this is happening, it's an איסור לאו, lav.
he still has to do חליצה. That's הנולדים. Okay, now we're going
to find out how יהודה Yehuda who's born later is actually going
to be an איסור כרת. Why? Let's take a look. Okay, one
minute. וחזר וקדשה צריכה חליצה מן האחים. vachazar vekidsah tzerichah chalitzah min
ha'achim. מאן אחים אחים הנולדים? man achim achim hanoladin? כמאן
כרבי יוחנן. keman keRabbi Yochanan. Okay,
so
לוי who was around when all of it was happening he still
has to do חליצה because it's an איסור לאו. lav. אמר אחד
מן הילודים, amar echad min hayeludim,
now a newly born brother like יהודה Yehuda comes along וקדשה vekidsah
אין לה עליו כלום. ein lah alav klum. Then it's not binding
at all, it's an איסור כרת. כמאן כרבנן keman keRabbanan like the
רבנן. Rabbanan. What does that mean?
Because why is יהודה Yehuda?
here an איסור כרת? Because when now I gotta remember why is
יהודה Yehuda an איסור כרת? Hold on. He was born
before
I mean through the חליצה he was existent during the חליצה. Because
right, because יהודה is, you know who
רחל is
to יהודה? אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו. eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo.
Yeah, right, right, שלא היה בעולמו, right. So he was born after
all this happened, he never had a מצוות יבום. mitzvah of yibbum
He never had a מצוות יבום mitzvah of yibbum, for שמעון. So
if there's no מצוות יבום, mitzvah of yibbum, of course it's an
איסור כרת. Okay, so לוי was around, he had a מצוות יבום,
mitzvah of yibbum but for him it just becomes an איסור לאו
lav according to רבי יוחנן everybody everybody is an איסור לאו. lav.
יהודה who's born, the newborn brother, oh forget all of this חליצה
קידושין whatever, the newborn brother he doesn't have a מצוות יבום mitzvah
of yibbum. אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו eshet achiv shelo haya beolamo
and it's an איסור כרת. Okay, so we solved the ברייתא. We
still have the debate of ריש לקיש and רבי יוחנן and a
very interesting conceptual debate of are you representing everybody or you're doing
your own thing? Let's take a look. Okay, איתמר הבא על יבמתו
itmar haba al yevamto okay ובא אחד מן האחים על צרתה. uva
echad min ha'achim al tzaratah. This is going to be a fascinating
application of the debate of רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש.
Okay, now let me get to draw a new page. Let's say
here we have ראובן Reuven, who is married to רחל and דבורה,
not related.
He dies. לוי goes ahead and he does his מצוות יבום. mitzvas
yibbum? Okay, יישר כח. yasher koach. Now comes along יהודה and יהודה
has sex with דבורה.
What is דבורה's relationship now it's יבום yibbum not חליצה. The debate
of רבי יוחנן and ריש לקיש was once one of them had
חליצה, what's everybody else's status, right? So here you could ask a
similar question once one of them had יבום, yibbum, what's everybody else's
status? Okay, so what do you think? לוי did יבום yibbum? with
רחל. What do you think ריש לקיש would say is the relationship
of דבורה to
יהודה? איסור כרת, right? This is the unique יבום yibbum. relationship. This
is defined in יבום yibbum. terms and all other relationships, לוי to
דבורה, יהודה to דבורה to רחל, all of all other relationships are
איסור כרת *issur kareit*. That's what ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says. What
does רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* say? Everybody is allowed! Everybody is redefined
in יבום yibbum *yibbum* terms and everybody is allowed. So let's take
a look.
But he didn't specifically say it for יבום yibum, *yibbum*.
No, but he talked about the mechanism of representing. All right, so
you can say you represent by חליצה *chalitzah*, you don't represent by
יבום yibum *yibbum*. יבום *yibbum*'s a little more intimate than חליצה *chalitzah*.
That's true, but okay. איתמר הבא על יבמה ובא אחד מן האחים
על צרתה *Itmar Haba al yevamah uva echad min ha'achim al tzarratah*.
פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא *Peligi ba Rav Acha v'Ravina*. This is
the debate of רב אחא *Rav Acha* and רבינא *Ravina*. Now remember,
right, we just got through saying that רב אשי *Rav Ashi* and
רבינא *Ravina*—רבינא *Ravina* holds like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. We don't know
what רב אחא *Rav Acha* holds, but we're about to find out.
חד אמר בכרת וחד אמר בעשה *Chad amar b'kareit v'chad amar b'asei*.
One says it's an איסור כרת *issur kareit*, the other says עשה
*asei*. Why עשה *asei* and not a לאו *lav*? Because it's different.
It's not he did חליצה *chalitzah*, he can't remarry, it's that he
did יבום *yibbum* and here's another thing. We learn—one thing we learn
out is אשר לא בנה את בית אחיו *asher lo vana et
beit achiv*—so that שלא בנה *shelo vana* is somehow treated as a
לאו *lav*. The other thing we learn out from this פסוק posuk.
*pasuk* is בית אחד הוא בונה *bayit echad hu boneh*, בית אחד
הוא בונה ואינו בונה שני בתים *bayit echad hu boneh v'eino boneh
shene batim*. Okay? Which means ואינו בונה שני בתים *v'eino boneh shene
batim*. Which means that לוי *Levi* did יבום *yibbum* with רחב *Rachav*,
he can't also do יבום *yibbum* with דבורה *Devorah*. Okay? Only one
יבום *yibbum*, only one—the woman you did חליצה *chalitzah* to, you don't
remarry, right? And only one יבום *yibbum*, not two יבומים *yibbums*. This
somehow is understood, I guess because of בית אחד הוא בונה *bayit
echad hu boneh*—this is שלא בנה *shelo vana*, here it's בית אחד
הוא בונה *bayit echad hu boneh*. Somehow this is understood as an
איסור עשה issur asei *issur asei*. So in the case of יבום
*yibbum*, לוי *Levi*'s relationship with דבורה *Devorah*—לוי *Levi* did יבום *yibbum* with
רחב *Rachav*, if he were to do יבום *yibbum* with דבורה *Devorah*
it would be an איסור עשה *issur asei*. Okay? So that's לוי
*Levi*. So that—and now according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, the same
is going to be true for יהודה *Yehuda*, right? So that's just
why it calls it an איסור עשה *issur asei*. It's what we
said before, I'm just explaining why it's an איסור עשה *issur asei*.
חד אמר בכרת *Chad amar b'kareit*, following a ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*
approach, וחד אמר בעשה *v'chad amar b'asei*. מאן דאמר בכרת כריש לקיש
*Man d'amar b'kareit k'Reish Lakish*, everybody who's not in the לוי *Levi*-רחב
*Rachav*-דבורה *Devorah* relationship goes back to an איסור כרת *issur kareit*, ומאן
דאמר בעשה כרבי יוחנן *u'man d'amar b'asei k'Rabbi Yochanan*, and the one
that says עשה *asei* is like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, and everybody
has the same status, it's looked at through the יבום *yibbum* lens,
it's this new איסור עשה *issur asei*. All right, and by the
way we know it's רבינא *Ravina* who says like רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* based on the earlier discussion. So great, we have a ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, we have רבינא *Ravina*
against רב אשי *Rav Ashi* and רב אחא *Rav Acha*, and we
have a very consistent series of debates. Okay, moving on. Then
that really is the end of that for now. Okay, so put
a period there. Now we have introduced a really nice question of
the mechanism of יבום *yibbum* and חליצה *chalitzah*. Is it one person
just and one and one and one wife, or are they representing
everybody? And once that act is done, at least for the initial
participants and maybe for everyone, it is looked at now not through
אשת אח *eshet ach*, but through these new איסורין issurin *issurin* of
forbidden to remarry after חליצה *chalitzah* and forbidden to do יבום *yibbum*
with the other wife. Yes.
Is it unusual for אמוראים *Amoraim* as late as רבינא *Ravina* and
רב אשי *Rav Ashi* to be taking up sides with תנאים *Tannaim*?
Well, which תנאים *Tannaim*? רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש
לקיש
*Reish Lakish*... No, they're not תנאים *Tannaim*.
They're—רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* are not תנאים
*Tannaim*.
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*...
Oh, no, they're just explaining the ברייתא *baraita* according to them.
They're not actually signing up. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
next, now—so that's really the end of that סוגיא sugya. *sugaya*, although
we'll probably revisit it and rethink about those—the mechanism. But that's the
end of that really central סוגיא *sugaya* about how—how everything works. Now
we're going to get on to other questions which are going to
sort of be like: who else isn't on this list? And some
of these things were things that we already got a sneak peek
at way at the beginning. Some of this might sound a little
familiar. So here's—some people who weren't on this list and maybe should
be. אמר רב *Amar Rav*—okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב *Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav*. צרת סוטה sota. אסורה *Tzarrat sotah asurah*. טומאה tumah
כתיבא *Tum'ah ktiva*. Now סוטה Sota, *sotah* here means, as we're going
to find out in a minute, not just a woman suspected of
adultery, but a woman who committed adultery. Okay? And the פסוק posuk
*pasuk* by a woman who suspected says—I'm going to have to—no, I'm
going to leave that out, that's too interesting to read. Anyway, the
פסוק posuk *pasuk* by סוטה Sota, *sotah* says ונסתרה והיא נטמאה v'nistrah
v'hi nitma'ah, *v'nistara v'hi nitma'ah*. Okay? That's if she did commit adultery,
or it says ונסתרה והיא לא נטמאה *v'nistara v'hi lo nitma'ah*. But
it basically says, right? And the other is ונסתרה והיא לא נטמאה
*v'nistara v'hi lo nitma'ah*, which basically means that if she committed adultery,
the adultery would be defined as טומאה tumah. *tum'ah*. Okay? And that
makes her forbidden to her husband. We're going to find later what
פסוק posuk *pasuk* says that she's forbidden, but the idea of טומאה
*tum'ah*—like when the תורה Torah *Torah* speaks about the איסור עריות arayot
*issur arayot*, לא תטמאו בכל אלה כי בכל אלה נטמאו הגויים אשר
אני משלח מפניכם *lo titam'u b'chol eleh ki b'chol eleh nitm'u hagoyim
asher ani m'shaleach mipneichem*, right? So איסור עריות arayot, *issur arayot* are
described as a type of... So what he says is, here you
have something fascinating. This woman who committed adultery, okay? This would be
ראובן *Reuven*, we'll go back to ראובן *Reuven* and רחל *Rachel* here.
So this woman who committed adultery, she is אסור assur, *Asur* to
him, but it's really only an איסור לאו *Issur Lav* of the
husband and wife sleeping together if she committed adultery. However, because it's
called טומאה *Tumah*, since it's called טומאה *Tumah*, it basically is like
an ערוה *Ervah* and there's no מצוה *Mitzvah* of יבום *Yibbum*. That's
what's being argued for, like שמעון *Shimon* and so on. I want
to point out an irony here, though, which is: she is טמאה
t'meiah. *Temeiah*, as it were, to ראובן *Reuven*. Right? You know the
הלכה *Halacha* is a woman who commits adultery is אסור לבעל ואסור
לבועל *Asur LeBaal VeAsur LeBoel*. Can't have sex with the man she
committed adultery with and with her husband. Right? רחל *Rachel* is not...
her טומאה *Tumah* doesn't relate to anybody else other than her husband.
Right? And the... right? Nevertheless, when ראובן *Reuven* dies and שמעון *Shimon*
is here, we say, oh, she's טמאה t'meiah. *Temeiah* and that's like
an עריות arayot. *Arayos*, and שמעון *Shimon* doesn't have to do יבום
*Yibbum* with her. So I just want to point out, the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* doesn't make this point, that it's ironic that yes, she
might be called טמאה t'meiah. *Temeiah* and you could say טמאה t'meiah,
*Temeiah* is like an ערוה *Ervah*, but we're saying something else. Not
only is that her relationship to ראובן *Reuven*, that carries over to
שמעון *Shimon* now, and then it's like, and then he doesn't even
have a מצות יבום *Mitzvas Yibbum*. That's what רב *Rav* is saying.
Let's read that. And now, not only does he say it about
the סוטה sota, *Sotah*, he says it about her צרה *Tzarah*. If
she's like an ערוה *Ervah* and there's no מצוה *Mitzvah* of יבום
*Yibbum*, then there also wouldn't be no מצוה *Mitzvah* of יבום *Yibbum*
on the צרה *Tzarah* as well, okay? So why wasn't she in
the משנה *Mishna*? Well, we're going to have to worry about that.
That's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of discussed that a little bit
earlier. Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב צרת סוטה sota, אסורה טומאה
כתיב בה *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav Tzaras Sotah Asura Tumah Kesiv
Bah* by the סוטה sota *Sotah* כעריות *KeArayos*, and once she's like
an ערוה *Ervah* and there's no מצות יבום *Mitzvas Yibbum* with her,
then there's no מצות יבום *Mitzvas Yibbum* with the צרה *Tzarah*. מתיב
רב חסדא *Masiv Rav Chisda*, it's רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* asked on
this. רב שמעון אומר ביאה או חליצתה מאחיו הראשון פוטרת צרתה *Rav
Shimon Omer Biah O Chalitzatah MeAchiv HaRishon Poteres Tzaratah*. Well, that was
clear. So what does this mean? So he says, אוי גוואלד *Oy
Gevalt*, so many new ideas to introduce. So what he says is
the following. He says we have a case of another poor woman,
לאה *Leah*, whose husband goes to מדינת הים *Medinas Hayam*. Her husband
is, I don't know, we'll make it here some other people. I
don't know who we're going to make it, anyway, it's okay, fine,
we'll do יוסף Yosef. *Yosef*. יוסף Yosef, *Yosef* goes to מדינת הים
*Medinas Hayam*, his brother sold him to מצרים *Mitzrayim*. So יוסף Yosef.
*Yosef* goes to מדינת הים *Medinas Hayam*, okay? And she thinks he's
dead. All right? And then a witness comes and says, oh, I
saw your husband, he died. She gets remarried to somebody else. She
gets remarried to, I don't know, to ברק *Barak*. Okay? So we're
using ברק *Barak*. She gets remarried to ברק *Barak*. Then, this is
a whole later פרקים *Perakim*. Then what happens? יוסף *Yosef* shows up.
Okay? So now, what's the actual status of לאה *Leah*? She thought
she was legitimately marrying ברק *Barak*, but she actually was still married
to יוסף *Yosef*. So effectively she's committed adultery with ברק *Barak* unwittingly.
Okay? Also, though, she can't go... so she can't go back to
יוסף *Yosef*, but she can't go back to ברק *Barak* because you
know he was the one like she's also the בועל *Boel* and
whatever and she's sort of married to both. So basically the הלכה
*Halacha* is אסורה לזה ולזה תצא מזה ומזה *Asura LeZeh ULeZeh Teitzi
MiZeh UmiZeh*, very harsh consequences. She has to be divorced from both
of them and so on. That's the whole story. Now, what happens
is while she's in that status and before she's been divorced, guess
what? יוסף *Yosef* dies. And now you've got his brother בנימין Binyamin
*Binyamin*. Okay? Now, does he have to do חליצה *Chalitzah* or יבום
*Yibbum* to לאה *Leah*? לאה *Leah* was in a status where she
couldn't continue living with יוסף *Yosef* and so on. Does she have
to continue doing... does he have a מצות יבום *Mitzvas Yibbum* because
basically she's sort of like the סוטה sota, *Sotah* in the fact
that she committed adultery although it was unwitting. Okay, so that's the
question of what is בנימין *Binyamin*'s story with לאה *Leah*. So let's
take a look. So it says רב שמעון אומר ביאה או חליצתה
מאחיו הראשון פוטרת צרתה *Rav Shimon Omer Biah O Chalitzatah MeAchiv HaRishon
Poteres Tzaratah*. The brother of the first one, first one is יוסף
*Yosef*, not ברק *Barak*. So his brother בנימין *Binyamin*, if she has
ביאה *Biah* or חליצה *Chalitzah* with בנימין *Binyamin*, then her צרה *Tzarah*
gets off. Which basically means that although בנימין *Binyamin* is... although we
basically say that she's אסורה לזה ולזה *Asura LeZeh ULeZeh*, there she
really still is יוסף *Yosef*'s wife. And therefore בנימין *Binyamin* really could
do חליצה *Chalitzah* or יבום *Yibbum*. He's not supposed to, whatever, but
if he did it would work and it would have the impact
on the צרה *Tzarah*... on the צרות *Tzaros* etc. ביאה *Biah* is
יבום *Yibbum*. Is יבום *Yibbum*, right. So we see that יבום *Yibbum*
still is relevant even in this case. Now there's an obvious answer.
So the answer is אמר לך רב amar lach Rav, אמינא לך
אנא סוטה sota דאורייתא *Amar Lach Rav Amina Lach Ana Sotah DeOraisa*.
I was talking to you about a real סוטה sota. *Sotah*, a
woman who willfully committed adultery. ואת אמרת לי סוטה sota, דרבנן de'rabbanan
*VeAt Amart Li Sotah DeRabbanan*? You told me a rabbinic סוטה sota
*Sotah*, meaning this woman, this poor woman, she listened to the עד
*Ed*, she got remarried, it wasn't her fault. So we're going to
have to deal with why we have all of these harsh consequences,
but at the end of the day, she's really... And she really
should be מותר mutar to go back to יוסף. So the fact
that we say she shouldn't go back to יוסף, that's all of
those are rabbinic, you know, stringencies. Okay, so therefore she really was
unwitting and אנוס onus etc. רש״י Rashi says brings in a whole
concept of אנוסה, anusa as it were, not אנוסה anusa like rape,
but אנוסה like completely unwitting and therefore she really should be מותר
mutar to יוסף. So the whole thing is rabbinic. So of course
בנימין still can do חליצה or יבום, at least בדיעבד with her.
So the גמרא Gemara says ודקארי לה מאי קארי לה, v'dikari lah
mai ka'ari lah, so that's a very good point. What were you
even thinking to ask from that case? That clearly is a case
of rabbinic stringencies, she's not really a סוטה. sotah, So קסבר כל
דתקון רבנן כעין דאורייתא תקון, kasavar kol detikkun rabanan ke'ein d'oraita tikkun,
no, because assume that even though it is rabbinic, we would pattern
it after the biblical law. All right, so that's not relevant. But
we're still going to try to figure out the story of a
woman who committed adultery, is she like עריות arayot. in the case
of יבום? מתיב רב אשי, Masiv Rav Ashi, נכנסה עמו לסתר ושהתה
עמו כדי טומאה, nichnesah immo l'seter v'shahash immo k'dei tumah, this is
ממש mamash from סוטה, sotah right from the beginning of סוטה, sotah
it says that if she went with this suspected man into private
privacy and they spent there long enough time that they could have
had sex, אסורה לביתה ואסורה לאכול בתרומה. asurah l'beitah v'asurah l'echol b'trumah.
She can't go back, she can't have sex with her husband now
because she's a סוטה, sotah, classic סוטה, sotah one suspected of adultery.
And if she's married to a כהן kohen she can't eat תרומה
trumah because she's until that relationship gets clarified. So we're not going
to worry about the תרומה. trumah. Now אם מת, im meis, now
what happens if this woman suspected of adultery before anything got clarified,
ראובן died? חולצת ולא מתייבמת. chaletzet v'lo misyabemet. Do חליצה, don't do
יבום. We don't want you to do יבום. I mean she was
אסור to ראובן, so שמעון shouldn't be doing יבום with her, I
mean we could talk more about why that is, but the point
is you still have to do חליצה. So this is exactly the
case, right? Here, forget this H, here's the case. Okay, רחל was
suspected of adultery, she did definitely commit adultery. And what does it
say that happens in this case with שמעון? It says do חליצה.
So there you see, רחל isn't an ערווה. erva. I mean she's
not like עריות, arayot. right? She maybe he shouldn't marry her because
there was an איסור with her to be with ראובן, she was
suspected of adultery, but שמעון still has to treat her as somebody
she has a חיוב chiyuv to do חליצה to. So you see
that she's not an עריות. arayos, Is that clear? Right? This is
exactly the case, a woman suspected of adultery and it says there's
still a חיוב chiyuv חליצה. So now there's another easy answer, and
not an easy, but anyway, אמר לך רב, so רב will say
back to you, אמינא לך אנא סוטה ודאי. amina lach ana sota
vaday. I was talking about a woman who definitely committed adultery. It's
quite fascinating the word סוטה Sotah, becomes to mean a woman who
committed adultery, right? We hear the word סוטה, Sotah. we think it's
a woman suspected of adultery. But he says I was talking about
a woman who definitely committed adultery. That woman, when it says ונסתרה
והיא נטמאה, v'nistrah v'hi nitma'ah, she committed adultery, she has a status
of עריות. arayos? The whole story of the סוטה Sotah? in the
תורה Torah is we don't know. So if we don't know then
maybe she's still מותר and maybe she didn't and therefore שמעון will
still have to do חליצה, okay, because we don't know, but if
we know then she's like עריות. Okay, ומאי שנא סוטה ודאי? u'mai
shna sota vaday? So now the גמרא Gemara says ומאי שנא סוטה
ודאי, u'mai shna sota vaday, why is סוטה ודאי sota vaday different
that you say there's no מצוות יבום? משום דכתיב בה טומאה, mishum
dichsiv bah tumah, it says ונסתרה והיא נטמאה, vehini nitma'ah. she's called
טמאה. t'meiah, סוטה ספק נמי טומאה כתיב בה? sota safek nami tumah
ksiv bah? So the word טומאה equally applies to a woman suspected
of adultery. Where do you know this? דתניא, d'tanya, we learned a
ברייתא, רבי יוסי בן כיפר אומר משום רבי אליעזר: Yosei ben Kipar
omer mishum Rabbi Eliezer: המחזיר גרושתו מן הנישואין. hamachzir grushaso min hanisuin.
Now we're going to deal with where we know the איסור of
סוטה. It's not from a פסוק pasuk by סוטה, we only know
the word טומאה. I'm going to have to erase this beautiful picture
here. Do you know where we know the איסור of סוטה from?
From the story of המחזיר גרושתו. machzir grushaso. What does it say?
A woman divorces his wife, והלכה והייתה לאיש אחר, v'halchah v'hayesah l'ish
acher, actually that's where we learn הלכות גירושין hilchos gerushin from, והייתה
לאיש אחר. v'hayesah l'ish acher. לא יוכל בעלה הראשון אשר שלחה לשוב
לקחתה לו לאשה, lo yuchal ba'alah harishon asher shilchah lashuv l'kachat-ah lo
l'ishah, לשוב lashuv whatever, אחרי אשר הוטמאה. acharei asher hutama'ah. Okay, so
what we are going to say is this becomes an איסור for
any man to go back and have sex with his wife once
she is considered to be become טמאה. t'meiah So the פסוק pasuk
means that she went and she married another man. Okay? And that's
considered הוטמאה. hutama'ah. But the גמרא Gemara is going to say the
real הוטמאה, hutama'ah, everything was legitimate, right? So that's maybe what, but
the real הוטמאה hutama'ah is committing adultery. So here we learn that
a woman who commits adultery is called טמאה. t'meiah Here we learn
when a woman is considered טמאה, t'meiah, she cannot go back and
be with her husband. Okay? You got that? And in a way
you understand the קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Here it was even legitimate
to marry the second guy but still... So that's what we're going
to say. רבי יוסי בן הכיפר Reb Yosi ben Hachifar first says
that no, this פסוק is not talking about adultery, it's coming to
clarify what is the איסור of מחזיר גרושתו. Machzir Grushaso. Let's take
a look. רבי יוסי בן כיפר אומר משום רבי אלעזר. Reb Yosi
ben Kiphar Omer mishum Reb Elazar. המחזיר גרושתו מן הנשואין אסורה. Hamachzir
grushaso min hanissuin asura. A man cannot only not remarry his wife
if he was married, נשואין, nissuin, meaning could have, you know, living
together with the other man. So because then they could have had
sex and then you could call it הוטמאה. hutama'ah. But מן האירוסין,
min haerusin, if she only had אירוסין erusin with the other man,
so they weren't yet starting to live together, so they weren't in
a context of having sex. So in that case מותרת, muteres, he
can actually remarry his wife even after she married somebody else. משום
שנאמר אחרי אשר הוטמאה. mishum shenemar acharei asher hutama'ah. The reason it
says הוטמאה hutama'ah is to clarify that the איסור applies only if
she actually not slept with another man but could have slept with
him because there was already נשואין. nissuin. What? אישור פריון הנשים? ishur
piryon hanashim? The, I don't know how to say this, it's like
police of the fertility of the woman. Aha. Oh, yeah, because what
because you're everybody's trying to control who she sleeps with and whose
child it might be. So that raises a question what is the
problem if she got legitimately remarried to the second one and then
legitimately divorced, why can't she go back, why is that called הוטמאה?
hutama'ah? So what you're saying is, which I think is very reasonable,
is the issue about starting to raise questions about whose child it
might be maybe and that becomes all these דרבנן issues about הבחנה
havchanah and so on. The רמב"ן Ramban says it's a problem of
a concern of wife swapping. Like people would divorce their wives for
the night, swap wives and then remarry them the next morning. So
that's what he says that that's coming what's coming to do. But
yes, but according to רבי יוסי בן כיפר Reb Yosi ben Kiphar
he says the word אחרי אשר הוטמאה acharei asher hutama'ah is to
tell you it's only if with the second man there was נשואין.
nissuin. Which is a very reasonable read of the פסוק. וחכמים אומרים,
ve'chachamim omrim, but the sages say, אחת זו ואחת זו אסורה. achas
zu ve'achas zu asura. No, it says והלכה והייתה לאיש אחר. vehalcha
vehayta le'ish acher. הייתה hayta means קידושין. So even if with the
second man it was only קידושין, she's still אסור to go back
to her husband. So if that's true, why does it say הוטמאה?
hutama'ah? הוטמאה hutama'ah sounds like she could have been sleeping with a
second man. ואמאי קרי לה, ve'amai kari lei, I'm sorry, אלא מה
אני מקיים אחרי הוטמאה, ela mani mikyama acharei hutama'ah, לרבות סוטה שנסתרה.
lerabot sotah shenistara. To tell you that there's a general איסור of
going back and being with the husband after the woman is declared
טמאה, t'meiah. which means that's the basis of the איסור for סוטה,
because here we learn going back to the husband after טמאה t'meiah,
is אסור, and here we learn that a סוטה is called טמאה
t'meiah. and that's the basis. Now, why did we just quote that?
Because רב, because we said that this idea that a סוטה is
טמאה, t'meiah right, only is by a סוטה ודאי, sotah vaday, a
woman who committed adultery. That's who's called טמאה. t'meiah But here the
phrase is, it says what does הוטמאה hutama'ah come to include? What
did the phrase say? סוטה שנסתרה, sotah shenistara, not נבעלה. nivala. Okay?
So when we so here we're saying that this איסור הוטמאה hutama'ah
includes a woman who is suspect, נסתרה. nistara. So how could you
say there's a difference in terms of ייבום yibbum and חליצה between
a definite a woman who committed adultery definitely, she's טמאה, teme'ah. but
a סוטה, a woman suspected is not? Here it says that this
איסור applies to a woman who is went נסתרה, nistara, this presumably
means suspected. So you see both of them are considered טמאה. teme'ah,
So the גמרא says there shouldn't be a ו vav here. מאי
נסתרה נבעלה. mai nistara nivala. No, it means definitely had sex, that
who is who the לאו applies to. ואמאי קרי לה נסתרה, ve'amai
kari lei nistara, so why did it say נסתרה nistara why didn't
it say נבעלה? nivala? לישנא מעליא נקט, lishna ma'aliya nakat, it likes
to be a little euphemistic. Okay. So now the גמרא says נבעלה,
nivala, טומאה בהדיא כתיבא. tuma behedaya kesiva. Why do you need a
פסוק if we're talking about really having committed adultery, we already said
והיא נטמאה. So why do you need to reinforce that with this
פסוק over here? So I already gave you the answer, because this
tells you her status, it doesn't tell you that there's an איסור,
this is making it a לאו. This is making it לא תעשה.
lo ta'aseh. So גמרא says, ונסתרה והיא בהדיא כתיבא ונסתרה והיא נטמאה.
ve'nistara vehini behedaya kesiva ve'nistara vehini nitma'ah. So why do you need
it to say over here for מחזיר גרושתו? machzir grushaso? לאוקמה ליה
בלאו, lemakma leh belav, to also have a לאו apply to it.
So what we've learned out here is that this פסוק by מחזיר
גרושתו machzir grushaso is the source of the איסור סוטה, issur sotah,
but what we are saying is that this status of a סוטה
as טמאה and an איסור לאו is only a woman who definitely
committed adultery. And that woman says רב is there's no מצווה mitzvah
of ייבום yibbum with and therefore there would be no ייבום yibbum
with the צרה. She's like טמאה like עריות, but if she's only
suspected. pected, then we don't know, maybe she also didn't commit adultery
and then she's totally not טמאה. So for a woman who's suspected,
it's a ספק safek and then you'd have to do חליצה. But
a woman who ודאי vadai did it is טמאה, איסור לאו, and
has all that status. We'll just read one more line and finish
this idea, and then we'll call it an evening. So the גמרא
says like this: For רבי יוסי בן כיפור, Rabbi Yosi ben Kifur,
now רבי יוסי בן כיפור Rabbi Yosi ben Kifur who did not
use this פסוק for סוטה, he had it all about מחזיר גרושתו.
machzir gerushato. So רבי יוסי בן כיפור, Rabbi Yosi ben Kifur, לאו
בסוטה ליתא ליה. lav be-Sotah leisa lei. He doesn't have a לאו
for סוטה. Okay? Because this פסוק is all by מחזיר גרושתו, machzir
gerushato, which is quite fascinating. I mean, presumably there's some problem, an
איסור עשה or something, but he doesn't have a לאו by a
case of an adultery. And it's ironic, but here's what he says:
ואפילו זנאי נמי, ve-afillu zenai nami, even a woman who definitely committed—I'm
reading the תוספות—definitely Tosafot committed adultery, there's no לאו. The only לאו
in the תורה is in a case—this is ironic—where it was legitimate.
If she was divorced and legitimately remarried and then going back to
her husband, that's a לאו. לא יוכל בעלה הראשון לשוב לקחתה. Lo
yuchal ba'alah ha-rishon lashuv lekachtah. But a worse case, a case of
adultery, no לאו. Right? Quite ironic. Okay, but it says it, right?
So ואפילו זנאי נמי, ve-afillu zenai nami, מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? הויו
ואישות כתיב בה. Havayu ve-ishus ketiv bah. Because these פסוקים pesukim talk
about her legitimately remarrying the other guy, the second guy. So this
לאו only applies when she legitimately was married to the other guy
and then wants to come back to her husband. But when she
actually committed adultery with the second guy, no לאו. So I can't
explain that, okay? But the גמרא obviously points out the irony about
that. Alright, and we will end with—I think this is a good
place to end for now. So it's already quite late. So but
that's good. You see we are in a very different rhythm now
of the גמרא in terms of introducing new concepts to יבום, working
out the proof as opposed to these long סתמים stams that we
had for like ten דפין, dafin, a different type of a structure
of a סוגיא. What we've done now is we've discussed, right, the
whole רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש—we Rabbi Yochanan Resh Lakish discussed the new
איסורין that apply after יבום and חליצה are done. The רבי יוחנן
וריש לקיש Rabbi Yochanan Resh Lakish debate about whether that is only
with the woman to whom and the man who did that act,
they have a new framing but everybody else goes back to אשת
אח, or do we say that everybody is like a—participated in that
act? That was רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rabbi Yochanan Resh Lakish. And
now we've been focusing on, should we add to this list סוטה?
A woman who commits adultery, does she also have a status of
עריות? And now we're going to continue tomorrow, whatever, over יום טוב
Yom Tov or whatever it is, anyway, dealing with—dealing with another woman
who we might want to add to this list, who's just now
introduced, which is מחזיר גרושתו. machzir gerushato. So should מחזיר גרושתו machzir
gerushato be on this list? That's what we're—that's what's coming up next.