Okay בוקר טוב.
boker tov. So today's דף daf is ח chet and we're actually
a little bit ahead and we pick up about where are we
about 15 lines down.
Line starts with the word אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי. amar leh
rav acha mi-difti. It's about four lines under where it says ויקרא
יח vayikra yud-chet in the margin, in the little margin between the
גמרא Gemara and רש"י. Rashi. Okay, so what we had done is
we had finally come to the after many דפים dapin established why
I thought why I might have thought that the מצוה Mitzvah of
יבום Yibum would apply even in a case of עריות Arayot and
after working through a whole issue of עשה דוחה לא תעשה Aseh
Docheh Lo Taaseh and then discovering that that really would not have
created a good basis for it because that would not apply in
a place that there's כרת, Kares, the גמרא Gemara finally says well
look, the whole case of יבום Yibum anyway is a case of
עריות, Arayot, brother's wife, so therefore that could have given me a
basis to assume that it would apply in case of other עריות,
Arayot, although of course another עריות Arayot adds two עריות, Arayot, brother's
wife plus the other one. Nevertheless based on either a logic about
כיון דאשתרי אשתרי, keivan de-ishtari ishtari, if one thing is being allowed
in order to enable this to happen then another thing should be
allowed, which might be limited to certain cases where the allowance came
first and then the problem arose. Or the last thing we said
is that since there's a פסוק pasuk that links all the עריות,
Arayot, maybe what's true about one is true about the others. So
that would have been the basis about why I would have thought
this would have applied and that's why I needed the פסוק pasuk
that says עליה, aleha, to remind you what that פסוק pasuk is,
it's
the פסוק pasuk is by
wife's sister and I'll write it out because we're actually going to
be looking at that פסוק pasuk more closely today.
It's ואשה אל אחתה לא תקח לצרר,
ve-ishah el
achotah lo tikach litzror, that's a good word, לגלות ערותה עליה
בחייה.
legalot ervatah
aleha be-chayeha. Okay, so don't marry a wife's sister and this word
עליה aleha becomes a magic word to link to יבמה יבא עליה.
yevamah yavo
aleha. So to tell me that this prohibition of wife's sister applies
even in a case of יבום. Yibum. Okay, so I would have
thought that maybe יבום Yibum overrides other עריות? Arayot? No, the עליה
aleha links it and tells me that it applies even in the
case of יבום. Yibum. So now we pick up with that. אמר
ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא. amar leh rav acha mi-difti le-ravina. So
רב אחא מדפתי Rav Acha mi-Difti said to רבינא, Ravina, מכדי, mikdi,
let's take a look. כל העריות איתקוש לאשת אח ואיתקוש לאחות אשה.
kol arayot itka'u le-eshet ach ve-itka'u le-achot isha.
So we've got a פסוק pasuk that basically said all the עריות
Arayot are linked to one another. So we and now we have
two עריות. Arayot. We have wife's brother, that's it, I keep on
doing that again, brother's wife, we have brother's wife which tells me
it's overridden for יבום, Yibum, and we have wife's sister based on
this link of עליה aleha that tells me it's not overridden for
יבום, Yibum, the prohibition still holds even in the case of יבום.
Yibum. So which one should be the rule? Right? Why do I
assume that wife's sister is the rule, maybe brother's wife is the
rule? So
מאי חזית דאקשת לאחות אשה, mai chazit de-akshat le-achot isha,
why did you choose to link all the other עריות Arayot to
wife's sister and to say that everybody is אסור asur in a
case of יבום? Yibum? אקשינהו לאשת אח, akshinu le-eshet ach, link it
to wife's brother—brother's wife—and say that everybody is allowed in a case
of יבום, Yibum, maybe with the one exception of wife's sister. Okay,
so that's a good so that's his question, let's see the answer.
אי בעית אימא, ei ba'it eima, I'll give you two answers. It's
a good question, except of course what the גמרא Gemara said before,
which is that brother's wife, that's always the case of יבום Yibum
in itself, whereas these other עריות Arayot have that plus an additional
עריות Arayot added to it.
So that was a good question from a methodology standpoint. Right. Exactly.
So you're going to be able to marry your mother?
Well right, that's the question somebody else was asking when we finished
yesterday, which is you mean to tell me according to the גמרא's
Gemara הוה אמינא hava amina like somebody could wind up having to
marry their sister because of יבום Yibum or something? Okay, it would
only have to be a half-sister because it would have to be
somebody who the brother was allowed to marry, but anyway. Yeah, but
the גמרא Gemara is not dealing with the emotional or the taboo
or any of those things that we associate with these incest issues.
It's dealing with a purely formal, right, but the גמרא Gemara hasn't
brought that concern into it. Exactly. The גמרא Gemara deals with just
the formal perspective of do the איסור issur apply or not. So
let's take a look.
So אי בעית אימא, ei ba'it eima, if you want I can
tell you, לקולא ולחומרא, le-kula u-le-chumra, if you have a choice to
link something to be stricter or to be stringent—to be lenient—לחומרא מקשינן.
le-chumra makshinan. So you know you have to like do it in
the more strict way. I mean that should just be like a
type of a play it safe rule. If you don't know which
way to link, you're going to take the one that is going
to be more strict. ואי בעית אימא, ve-ei ba'it eima, if you
want I could say, and this is what I was saying to
Dose a second ago, הכא תרי איסורי והכא חד איסורא. hacha terei
issurei ve-hacha chad issura. תרי מתרי ילפינן. trei mi-trei yalfanan. The case
of any other עריות Arayot in a case of יבום Yibum has
two איסורין. issurin. It has brother's wife, which you always have, plus
the other עריות. Arayot. Wife's Sister, sister,
mother-in-law, daughter-in-law, whatever the case might be. You have the two—you have
brother's wife plus the other one, which is exactly what you have
here. Wife's sister is the general issue of brother's wife who has
a place of יבום, yibbum, plus the new issue, the additional one
of this עריות. arayot. So when we have another ערוה erva in
a case of יבום, yibbum, it's more similar to this. It has
the brother's wife issue plus its other status of being an ערוה.
erva. Okay, הכא תרי איסורי והכא תרי איסורי, hacha t'rei issurei vehacha
t'rei issurei, so in another ערוה erva in a case of יבום
yibbum you have two איסורים, issurim, brother's wife plus its own status
as ערוה, erva, and here by wife sister you have two איסורים.
issurim. דתרי מתרי ילפינן, de-t'rei mit'rei yalfinnan, we'll learn two from two,
אבל הכא חד איסור ותרי מחד לא ילפינן, aval hacha chad issur
ve-t'rei me-chad lo yalfinnan, but in the case of the simple case
of יבום, yibbum, brother's wife by itself, it's only one איסור. issur.
And that's not a good basis for something that's brother's wife plus
another problem, so we're not going to learn two from one, which
is I think clearly the answer, right? This is much more—serves as
a paradigm for other עריות arayot in a case of יבום yibbum
than the simple case of יבום. yibbum. Okay, רבא אמר, Rava amar,
so that's where we're up to now. We have wife's sister, and
that becomes the source to tell us it doesn't apply in a
case of ערוה, erva, no matter even if we might have had
a הוה אמינא hava amina to just learn out from brother's wife
to say that it did.
It does have to do with the word עליה. aleha.
It does have to do with the word עליה. aleha. עליה aleha
tells me that the prohibition of wife's sister applies in a case
of יבום. yibbum. This prohibition of don't marry your wife's sister, עליה
aleha is telling me even holds in a case of יבום. yibbum.
That's the source. רבא אמר ערוה גופא לא צריכא קרא דאין עשה
דוחה לא תעשה שיש בו כרת.
Rava amar erva gufah lo tzricha kra de-ein asei docheh
lo ta'asei she-yesh bo kares. רבא Rava says, you know what, I
didn't need a פסוק. pasuk. I didn't need the פסוק pasuk עליה.
aleha. It never would have occurred to me that you could have
a case of יבום yibbum in a case of ערוה erva because
an עשה asei doesn't override a לא תעשה lo ta'asei that has
כרת. kares. Now if we just stop for a moment, the answer
should be one minute, that's all very nice, but we just left
yesterday saying we have a stronger הוה אמינא, hava amina, the stronger
הוה אמינא hava amina was like כיון דאישתרי אישתרי, kivan de-ishtrei ishtrei,
right? So תוספות Tosafot says, okay, but that's עולא's Ulla position, there's
no proof that רבא Rava holds of כיון דאישתרי אישתרי, kivan de-ishtrei
ishtrei, so רבא Rava would say there's no basis, just cause brother's
wife is allowed, there's no basis to assume that other עריות arayot
should be made permissible. There's actually a nice little nuance point about
the תוספות Tosafot where he says רבא אומר Rava omer that even
within עולא's Ulla כיון דאישתרי אישתרי, kivan de-ishtrei ishtrei, it's not really
comparable to our case. Let's—he says like this. If you look at
תוספות Tosafot רבא אמר ערוה גופא לא צריכא קרא, Rava amar erva
gufah lo tzricha kra, ואם תאמר והלא כל הפחות איצטריך לנושא ומת
ומת אח אח נשא שני, ve-im tomar ve-halo kol ha-pachos itrich li-nosay
ve-mes ve-mes ach ach nachas chai, הואיל ואישתרי אישתרי, hovei ve-ishtrei ishtrei,
right? He—תוספות Tosafot addressed the עשה דוחה לא תעשה, asei docheh lo
ta'asei, we pretty much reject that anyway, what about the most recent
argument to say it should be allowed, this כיון דאישתרי אישתרי? kivan
de-ishtrei ishtrei? Says ויש לומר דרבא לית ליה דעולא, ve-yesh lomar de-Rava
leis lei de-Ulla, one easy answer is he doesn't hold of that
principle. וסבר דביאה במקצת לא שמה ביאה, ve-savar de-bi'ah be-mikzas lo shma
bi-yah, you don't even have to come onto that because he didn't
have עולא's Ulla same problems. ועוד אומרי, ve-od omri, this is a
nice distinction, דיש לחלק, de-yesh lechalek, דגבי בעל קרי, de-gabbei ba'al keri,
remember that was the case of אישתרי אישתרי ishtrei ishtrei that the
same way he could put in the thumbs because of being a
מצורע, metzora, you could put in the thumbs because of a בעל
קרי. ba'al keri. דבעל קרי ומצורע—I'm de-ba'al keri u-metzora sorry, דשם טומאה
אחת היא, de-shem tumah achas hi, אמרינן הואיל ואישתרי אישתרי. amrinan hovei
ve-ishtrei ishtrei.
If a guy is טמא, tamei, he might be טמא tamei because
he's a מצורע, metzora, he might be טמא tamei because he's a
בעל קרי, ba'al keri, he might have both. But basically there's one
problem here. If he were to go into the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, we would say he did one איסור. issur. What איסור issur
did he do by going into the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? A
טמא tamei person going into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, in the
end of the day I don't care how he's טמא, tamei, the
איסור issur is a טמא tamei person going into the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. So they're both at the same level, that's not what's
relevant, but the point is the איסור issur is the same. It
doesn't matter where your source of טומאה tumah is. So if the
תורה Torah is waiving or somehow making an allowance for the איסור
issur of טמא tamei going into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to
allow the fingers to go in, it's not a new איסור issur
if you're טמא tamei from a different perspective. Okay, so there we
could say
הואיל ואישתרי אישתרי, hovei ve-ishtrei ishtrei,
אבל הכא דשני שמות הן, aval hacha de-shnei shemos hein, לא אמרינן
הואיל ואישתרי אישתרי. lo amrinan hovei ve-ishtrei ishtrei. Here
if somebody is not only brother's wife but also wife's sister, it's
not like one איסור issur was allowed. Just cause the תורה Torah
made an allowance for the prohibition of brother's wife doesn't mean it's
going to make an allowance for a completely different prohibition called wife's
sister. So even if you hold of a mechanism of הואיל ואישתרי
אישתרי, hovei ve-ishtrei ishtrei, that's when it was all the exact same
איסור issur that was being overridden. Here we allowed one איסור, issur,
אשת אח, eshes ach, doesn't mean we'll allow a different איסור issur
of אחות אשה. achos isha. Okay, so that I think is a
nice conceptual distinction between the cases, and basically what we have is
רבא Rava is not impressed with the recent הוה אמינא hava amina
of הואיל ואישתרי אישתרי, hovei ve-ishtrei ishtrei, you never would have assumed
from brother's wife to have allowed a different prohibition. Different איסור ערוה,
issur ervah, you would never have assumed עשה asei could override a
לא תעשה שיש בו כרת, lo ta'asei sheyesh bo kareis, so רבא
Rava says you didn't need this whole פסוק. pasuk. I never had
a הוה אמינא hava amina that you could allow יבום yibbum in
a case of ערוה. ervah.
I have to say I don't get that. In one case, it's
an איסור טומאה issur tumah regardless of how you come to it.
In the other case, it's an איסור ערוה issur ervah no
matter No, you're doing two separate איסורים. issurim. It's like saying if
you're allowed to do something
Ah, the איסור issur is entering into the
מקדש Mikdash because you're טמא. tamei. It doesn't matter how you're טמא.
tamei. You've transgressed one prohibition, entering the מקדש, Mikdash,
whereas Being טמא tamei for both reasons.
Right. Exactly. Whereas if you said like, oh, well we're going to
allow you to do something on שבת, Shabbos, we'll also allow you
to do it on a שבת Shabbos that's a יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. But when I'm doing it on שבת Shabbos that's a יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, I'm doing two separate איסורים, issurim, you know. So
now it might be true, you know, that whatever, but okay, but
it's not the same one prohibition that's being allowed. All right, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. So רבא אמר ערוה לא צריכה
קרא. Rava amar ervah lo tzericha kra. You know what? We don't
need this פסוק pasuk עליה aleha because דאין עשה דוחה לא תעשה
שיש בו כרת. de'ein asei doche lo ta'asei sheyesh bo kareis. It
never would have been a possibility to think that the מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibbum would have overridden ערוה. ervah. כי איצטריך קרא, ki
itztarich kra, what do you need the פסוק pasuk for? למסר צרה.
le'maseir tzarah. To now finally what he's saying, let's not forget that
this פסוק pasuk told me two important things. First, that the prohibition
of ערוה ervah holds in case of יבום, yibbum, and then the
other half of our משנה, Mishnah, לצרור, litzror, that not only is
the ערוה ervah פטורה peturah from יבום, yibbum, but the צרה tzarah
is פטורה peturah from יבום. yibbum. So רבא Rava says you've completely
misunderstood the ברייתא. braisa. When the ברייתא braisa wanted to link this
פסוק pasuk to יבום, yibbum, it didn't need to do it for
the sake of the ערוה. ervah. You could never have thought you
could do יבום yibbum in a case of ערוה. ervah. It's a
לא תעשה שיש בו כרת. lo ta'asei sheyesh bo kareis. Why could
I have thought that יבום yibbum could have overridden ערוה? ervah? But
I needed to get יבום yibbum into this פסוק pasuk to get
me to the word לצרור litzror to tell me that when you
don't have to do יבום yibbum because the one woman, one of
your brother's wives is an ערוה, ervah, you don't do יבום yibbum
for the other woman, for the צרה. tzarah. And that is how
our משנה Mishnah opens. חמש עשרה נשים פוטרות צרותיהן chamesh esrei nashim
potros tzoreoseihen emphasizes the חידוש chiddush of the exemption of the צרה,
tzarah, right? The משנה Mishnah emphasizes the exemption of the צרה, tzarah,
not the exemption of the ערוה. ervah. That it takes for granted.
So what was עליה? aleha?
עליה aleha gets linked to יבמה יבא עליה yevamah yavo aleha and
puts the פסוק pasuk in the context of יבום. yibbum. Once you're
telling me that the prohibition of wife's sister applies in the context
of יבום, yibbum, which I anyway knew, said רבא, Rava, but you
got the פסוק pasuk talking about it, then it will say that
even the צרה tzarah is also exempt. Okay, so that's what רבא
Rava says. You guys says you got it wrong. We don't need
ערוה ervah to be the issue. We need the פסוק pasuk to
be יבום yibbum so we could get to לצרור. litzror. Okay. כי
תני
כי איצטריך קרא למסר צרה. ki tany ki itztarich kra le'maseir tzarah.
The פסוק pasuk needed to be talking about יבום yibbum so we
could get to the idea that the צרה tzarah is forbidden. All
right. So now the גמרא Gemara says, hold on, למסר צרה. le'maseir
tzarah. Okay.
וערוה לא צריכה קרא? ve'ervah lo tzericha kra? You're telling me that
ערוה ervah doesn't need a פסוק? pasuk? That we don't need a
פסוק pasuk to say that יבום yibbum does not apply in a
case of ערוה? ervah? והתניא אין לי אלא היא. ve'hatanya ein li
ela hi. The ברייתא braisa itself, the language of the ברייתא braisa
that all of this was jumped off of, that looked at this
פסוק pasuk of wife's sister and עליה aleha etc. it's the language
of it suggests that the first חידוש chiddush is is that this
applies does not apply in a case of ערוה. ervah. That is
what partly we're being מחדש. mechadesh. והתניא, ve'hatanya the ברייתא braisa teaches,
אין לי אלא היא. ein li ela hi. I only know that
יבום yibbum doesn't apply to the ערוה ervah once we did the
עליה aleha thing. משום צרתה. mishum tzaratah. Wait
a minute. Did I skip a line?
והתניא ve'hatanya, אין לי אלא היא. ein li ela hi. The answer
is, no, משום צרתה. mishum tzaratah. It doesn't yes, it said I
only know her. How do I know the צרה? tzarah? So רבא
Rava said, yeah, but when it said I only know the ערוה,
ervah, we didn't need to prove the ערוה. ervah. It was just
establishing that the פסוק pasuk was about ערוה ervah so we could
get to the case of צרתה, tzaratah, right? So the classic way,
the language that the ברייתא braisa uses is, look, I have עליה
aleha that tells me יבום yibbum doesn't apply in a case of
ערוה. ervah. Now, how do I know about צרה? tzarah? Ah, לצרור
litzror tells me צרה. tzarah. So says but don't you see wasn't
the first statement, look, you see יבום yibbum doesn't apply in a
case of ערוה? ervah? Says, yeah, but that was just to get
to the לצרור litzror part of it. We didn't really need to
prove that, that we could have figured out ourselves. That was just
to get to the לצרור litzror part of it.
You want to remind us where's this original ברייתא? braisa?
Yeah, you might have forgotten since we've been spending four דפין dappin
talking about עשה דוחה לא תעשה. asei doche lo ta'asei. So the
original ברייתא braisa is I think ג' ע"ב. gimmel amud beis. Let's
see if that's where it is. If you want to look at
it again. Right. מנא הני מילי mena hanei milei דתנו רבנן detanu
rabanan like eight lines from the top on ג' ע"ב. gimmel amud
beis. אשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור. isha el achosah lo tikach
litzror. עליה aleha מה תלמוד לומר? mah talmud lomar? לפי שנאמר יבמה
יבוא עליה Yevamah yavo aleha, *lefi shenemar yivama yavo aleha*, שומע אני
אפילו במקום bimkom אחות אשה achot ishah ואחות אשה מהתורה *shome'a ani
afilu bimkom achos isha v'achos isha m'hatorah*, כתוב מדבר *kasuv medaber*, נאמר
כאן עליה aleha ונאמר להלן עליה aleha, *ne'emar kan aleha v'ne'emar lehallan
aleha*, מה להלן במקום מצוה bemakom mitzvah אף כאן במקום מצוה bimkom
mitzvah *mah lehallan bimkom mitzvah af kan bimkom mitzvah*, ואמר רחמנא לא
lo, תקח *v'amar rachmana lo sikach*. So first he uses the עליה
aleha *aleha* to say no מצוה Mitzvah *mitzvah* in a case of
ערוה Ervah *erva*. אין לי אלא היא *ein li ela hi*? Okay,
sorry. צרתה מניין *tzarasa minayin*? תלמוד לומר לצרור litzror, *talmud lomar litzror*.
ואין לי אלא צרתה, צרת צרתה מניין *v'ein li ela tzarasa, tzaras
tzarasa minayin*? תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar* like to double לצרור litzror, *litzror*
instead of לצר *latzor*. But the first thing it establishes is that
it applies in a case of ערוה Ervah *erva*. So Rava's answer
is it's just doing that to get to the לצרור litzror *litzror*.
Okay, the real ערוה Ervah *erva* we knew anyway but we got
to establish that's the פסוק Pasuk. *pasuk* to get to the לצרור
l'tzror. *litzror*. והתניא אין לי אלא היא *v'ha tanya ein li ela
hi*? So the answer is משום צרתה *mishum tzarasa*. והקתני אין לי
אלא הן *v'ha katana ein li ela hen*? One minute, but then
it says that it goes on to say how do we know
to link this to all, remember the next question was, how do
we know to link this to all the other עריות arayot, *arayos*?
And then it linked it to other עריות arayot, *arayos*. And then
it said, okay, that's true about all other עריות arayot *arayos*. What
about the צרה Tzarah *tzara* of the other עריות arayos *arayos*, right?
So you see that the first thing though it's doing is it's
sort of establishing that this applies to other עריות arayos *arayos*, which
again seems to suggest that you need a פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* to
tell me no יבום Yibum *yibum* in a case of ערוה Ervah
*erva*. So the same answer: משום צרתיהן *mishum tzaraseihen*. It didn't need
to tell me the ערוה Ervah *erva* case of other עריות arayos
*arayos*, it needed to link it to other עריות arayot, *arayos* so
that I could then apply it to the צרה Tzarah. *tzara* of
the other עריות arayot *arayos*. Okay, so is that clear? Meaning what
Rava is saying is, right, remember what we did? Basically, what we
did is we proved first because of the עליה aleha. *aleha* that
no יבום Yibum. *yibum*, you know, in a case of אשת אחות
אשה *eshes achos isha*. That was proof number one because of the
עליה aleha, *aleha*. אחות אשה *achos isha*, okay, that we learned from
the עליה aleha *aleha* which put it in a case of יבום
Yibum *yibum*. Then we said no יבום Yibum *yibum* for צרה Tzarah.
*tzara* and צרת צרתה *tzaras tzarasa*. And that was learned from לצרור
litzror *litzror*.
Now all of that is אחות אשה *achos isha*. Then we had
to say how do we apply it to the other עריות *arayos*?
I forget what we used to apply to the other עריות *arayos*.
What does it say? ואין לי אלא הן, צרתה מניין, אמר מה
אחות אשה מיוחדת שהיא ערוה Ervah וחייבין עליה aleha, *v'ein li ela
hen,
tzarasa minayin, amar mah achos isha meyuchades she-hi erva v'chayavin aleha*...
so basically it did it by a מה מצינו *mah matzinu*. Okay,
then we basically said no יבום Yibum, *yibum* by other עריות *arayos*,
okay, that was based on essentially a מה מצינו *mah matzinu*. And
similarly, no יבום Yibum. *yibum* by the צרה Tzarah *tzara* and צרת
צרתה *tzaras tzarasa*...
מה מצינו *mah matzinu*.
Like a, like a, analogy? What is it? It's like a, but,
trying to think of the right word. But anyway, it's like the
same way, it's just using it as an example. Since we see
this, we apply it to other similar cases. A paradigm. Okay, no
צרת צרתה *tzaras tzarasa* we of other עריות *arayos*, okay, and that
we also learn out I think from a מה מצינו *mah matzinu*
if memory serves. Okay, so what Rava is saying is, the whole
part, this was, that was the ברייתא *braisa*. So what Rava is
saying is the whole purpose of this is we already knew this.
And we already knew no יבום Yibum, *yibum* in the case of
אחות אשה *achos isha* and no יבום Yibum. *yibum* by other עריות
*arayos* because why would I have thought that? How could I have
thought that יבום Yibum. *yibum* overrides those cases? The only reason the
ברייתא *braisa* went through this was to get to these cases. The
idea of צרה Tzarah *tzara*, that's something that I would not have
figured out by myself. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, yeah, but
the language of the ברייתא *braisa* first has to first proves this.
So Rava's saying, sure, you first needed to get the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk* talking about this so you could get to here. Oh, but
then the ברייתא *braisa* needs to prove no יבום Yibum, *yibum* by
other עריות *arayos*. Rava says, yeah, not that we needed to prove
that, but we needed to get the case talking about it so
we could get to the next state that it doesn't apply even
by the צרה Tzarah. *tzara* of those cases. Okay? So Rava is
saying the whole point of the ברייתא *braisa* is to tell you
the הלכה halacha. *halacha* of צרות tzarot *tzaros*. And it only goes
through these cases of אחות אשה *achos isha* and other עריות *arayos*
themselves to get to the case of the צרה Tzarah. *tzara*. I
don't know if that made it any clearer. But all right. So
now we continue. So that's what Rava says. Okay, תא שמע *ta
shema*, come and hear. רבי Rebbi אומר *Rabbi omer*, ולקח velakach ולקחה,
velakachah ויבם veyibam ויבמה veyibmah. *v'lakach v'lakacha, v'yibam v'yibma*.
So meaning the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* says by יבום Yibum. *yibum*, what's
actually the פסוקים Psukim. *pesukim* by יבום Yibum. *yibum*? Why not? So,
it says... Sorry, the
משנה mishnah. *mishnah* itself says that the 15 women exempt their צרות
tzarot. *tzaros*.
Yes,
but Rava is saying is... no, no one's debating the הלכה halacha
*halacha*. But the question is we didn't need a פסוק Pasuk *pasuk*
for that, Rava is saying. That we should have figured out ourselves.
We never would have had a הוה אמינא hava amina *hava amina*
that you could override the איסור issur *issur* of ערוה Ervah. *erva*.
Okay? And the fact that the ברייתא *braisa* seems to be trying
to prove it, Rava's saying it's only trying to get to teaching
you the הלכה halacha. *halacha* of צרה Tzarah. *tzara*. It doesn't need
to prove that case. It just needs the פסוקים Psukim. *pesukim* to
be talking about that case so it could get to the הלכה
halacha *halacha* of צרה Tzarah, *tzara*.
Okay? Yes? All right. So it says like this. So it says,
כי *ki*... כי ישבו אחים יחדיו מת אחד מהם ובן אין לו
לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר. That's the prohibition for her
to marry another man before she does יבום yibum, or חליצה. Chalitzah.
יבמה yibmah. יבוא עליה, aleha,
her brother-in-law shall come on to her, enter into her, have sex,
ולקחה לו לאשה ויבמה velakachah lo leishah veyibmah
and take her for him for a wife and do the act
of יבום. yibum. Okay? So Rabbi's is going to be bothered which
why it had to be the, the why it had to say
her in those two cases. Why didn't it just say יבמה יבוא
עליה ולקח לו לאשה ויבם? yevamah yavo aleha velakach lo leishah veyibam?
Okay, which is pretty funny because those are words that sort of
do need an object of the verb. But nevertheless, he's going to
ask why it had to say ולקחה velakachah. and ויבמה. veyibmah. So
let's take a look. It could have said ולקח velakach and it
says ולקחה. velakachah It could have said ויבם veyibam or ויבם and
it says ויבמה. veyibmah. So what's that tell you? לאתויי צרות ועריות
leatuyei tzarot vaarayot
to tell you that ה Heh is being saying only her. There
are other women who this would not apply to in a similar
case that this would not, right? It's sort of like her you
do יבום yibum to, her you take. But not other related women.
So meaning, not only in a normal case do you do this,
but in a case where she's an ערוה Ervah. you don't. And
in the case when she's a צרה Tzarah, of an ערוה Ervah
you don't. Okay? It's only her, her seems to suggest to exclude
other people. So and he learned it from two words ולקח velakach
and יבמה. yibmah. One tells me only her and not when she's
an ערוה Ervah, and the other says only her and not in
the case of צרת ערוה. tzarat ervah. A different דרשה Drasha than
we had. None of this whole thing about wife's sister.
This is a different דרשה, Drasha, ולקחה velakachah and ויבמה. veyibmah. Of
course, the problem here is that you have to read a lot
into that. Even if, you know, there's nothing that hints towards the
idea of ערוה Ervah and צרת ערוה, tzarat ervah, you have to
come with that assumptions and then be able to find that in
the פסוק. pasuk Let's just get a little bit further. So the
גמרא Gemara says so you see that's against רבא Rava because there
he needed one פסוק pasuk about ערוה erva and a פסוק pasuk
about צרה. Tzarah. And according to you, רבא, Rava, he should have
only needed one פסוק pasuk about צרה. Tzarah ערוה erva. we should
have been able to figure it out ourselves. So the גמרא Gemara
says,
אימא לאתויי צרות של עריות. eima leatuyei tzarot shel arayot. Don't read
it to say to make two things forbidden, צרה Tzarah and ערוה.
erva, It really should be reading to make one thing forbidden, the
צרה Tzarah. of an ערוה. erva ערוה erva, we would have known
ourselves. The extra ה Heh is telling me and not even a
צרה. tzara. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואתרי קראי קא נסיב לה.
veatrei kraei ka nasiv lah. But he's got two פסוקים. psukim He's
got ולקח and ולקחה velakachah and יבמה. Yevama, According to you, you
only need to exclude one case: צרת ערוה. tzarat ervah. So the
גמרא Gemara says, he says, מאי לאו חדא לערוה וחדא לצרה? mai
lav chada leervah vechada letzarah? I'm sorry, I skipped a line.
ואתרי קראי קא נסיב לה. veatrei kraei ka nasiv lah. So מאי
לאו חדא לערוה וחדא לצרה? mai lav chada leervah vechada letzarah? It
seems like one is first telling you the idea of ערוה, erva
we need a פסוק pasuk for that, and the next is telling
you the idea of צרה. tzara הגמרא Gemara says, לא, no, אידי
ואידי לצרה. aidi vaaidi letzarah. They're both coming to tell me that
you don't do יבום yibum by case of צרה. tzara
חדא למעוטי צרה במקום מצוה וחדא למשרי צרה שלא במקום מצוה. chada
lemiautei tzarah bemakom mitzvah vechada lemishrei tzarah shelo bemakom mitzvah. Remember we
had this idea before that the problem of צרה, tzara. don't think
that there's a general rule of צרה, tzara that if I can't
marry a somebody unrelated to me is married to two women, one
of them is my wife's sister, that oh well, since I can't,
and then he dies, she's not my brother, just some stranger. Okay?
So since I can't marry my wife's sister, I can't also marry
her co-wife. No, right? You might think there's a general idea called
צרה. tzara, Anybody who's been a co-wife of an ערוה erva. is
forbidden to me. So that's obviously not the case. The case is
that צרה tzara. is because of the idea that there's no מצוה
Mitzvah of יבום, yibum, then that creates the problem. But it's not
a general issue. So that צרה שלא במקום מצוה tzarah shelo bemakom
mitzvah is מותר. mutar. Okay? Somebody who was a co-wife to a
woman forbidden to me, I'm allowed to marry her. I'm only not
allow... it's only that I don't have a מצוה Mitzvah of יבום.
yibum. And once I don't have a מצוה Mitzvah of יבום, yibum,
then she becomes forbidden to me as my brother's wife. Okay? So
we needed two פסוקים. psukim One to tell you that צרה tzara.
is
forbidden במקום מצוה bimkom mitzvah, when it's a context of יבום. yibum,
So let's read that again. אידי ואידי לצרה חדא למעוטי צרה במקום
מצוה. aidi vaaidi letzarah chada lemiautei tzarah bemakom mitzvah. One to tell
me the idea of co-wife is a problem in the context of
יבום. yibum. A co-wife of a woman forbidden to me who I
have a מצוה Mitzvah of יבום, yibbum, she also becomes forbidden to
me because then she becomes my brother's wife without the מצוה mitzvah
of יבום. yibbum, וחדא vechada and the other למשרי צרה שלא במקום
מצוה lemishrei tzarah shelo bemakom mitzvah to tell me a co-wife of
a woman forbidden to me in a different context is not a
problem. Okay? And that that is allowed. Exactly how you get it
from the idea of ולקחה velakachah and ויבמה. veyibmah So it's not...
so it's no longer רש"י Rashi says about the ה Heh of
ויבמה veyibmah to say her exclusively and not somebody else. It's to
say ולקחה v'lekacha means only her, not a צרה. tzara But ויבמה
v'yibma when this is occurring in a context of יבום. yibbum. Okay?
So as opposed to, here I'm going to erase this. Okay?
So one דרשה Drasha here is אחות אשה that the case of...
how it links it to a case of יבום, yibbum, that's one
דרשה, drasha, and רבי's דרשה Rebbi's drasha is ולקחה ויבמה. v'lakacha v'yibma.
Okay,
and the first the simple read of that is her and not
an ערוה erva and then her and not צרת ערוה, tzarat erva,
a totally different דרשה. drasha Okay, of course this reads a lot
more into it than here at least we're talking about ערוה. erva,
But then רבא Rava who says you don't need a פסוק pasuk
for ערוה, erva? that we could have figured out ourselves, says no,
what you really need it is her and not a צרה. tzara
And this one is ויבמה v'yibma, in a case of יבום. yibbum.
In a case of יבום yibbum, then there's no, then the מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibbum, does not apply to its צרה tzara and
its צרה tzara becomes forbidden to you. But in a case that's
not יבום, yibbum. the co-wife of an ערוה ervah is not forbidden
to you. It's only forbidden to you צרה ויבמה tzara v'yibma in
a case of יבום. yibbum Okay, that's how רבא Rava will read
that דרשה drasha. of רבי. Rebbi. You had a question?
Yeah, no, so there's no מחלוקת machloket about the הלכה. halacha They're
all, it's all
exactly. Exactly. So how do I understand the הוה אמינא of the
גמרא Gemara, that the הלכה halacha is a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
l'Moshe m'Sinai or it's בעצם be'etzem תורה שבעל פה Torah she'ba'al peh
and they're looking for ways of understanding it.
Right. So that's a good point. So in general there's a debate
both of contemporary Talmud scholars and of the ראשונים Rishonim about when
you have דרשות drashot in the גמרא, Gemara how much did they
start with the מסורה mesorah and they went back to then retroactively,
you know, find a basis for it in the פסוקים psukim but
they started with the actual tradition of the הלכה. halacha And how
much did they actually not know what the הלכה halakha is and
then they went and they looked at the פסוקים psukim. and they
figured it out based on that. And not surprisingly, the best answer
is probably yes and yes. You know, sometimes it's one way, sometimes
it's another way. There are sometimes where it sounds very clear like
when we did עשה דוחה לא תעשה aseh docheh lo ta'aseh that
nobody really questioned what conclusion we were going to come out with.
We had to find some basis for it. Here too, nobody really
questions the idea that there's an exemption by ערוה, ervah you know,
and by צרות tzarot although we'll see a בית שמאי ובית הלל
Beit Shammai u'Beit Hillel coming up about some aspect of that. But
at least whatever, it seems like here that there's an accepted conclusion
that we're all going back and trying to find a basis especially
רבי's Rebbi, דרשה drasha which there's not even a hint for that
idea in the פסוקים psukim of ערוה ervah and צרה. tzara. You
have to read it all in. Here at least you can see
it more implicit in the פסוקים. psukim. So sometimes one gets the
impression they knew the הלכה halakha and they were working backwards to
find a basis. Other times one gets the impression that they really
were trying to figure out the הלכה halacha and derive it.
And is that part, is that implied to you that listen we're
satisfied to follow the הלכה that's our מסורה mesorah but our rational
mind needs a way of making it more coherent to us as
a kind of אסמכתא asmachta sense? I'm not sure if the link
of the פסוקים psukim. is to make it more coherent and it
would be understood in sort of אסמכתא asmachta sense, like oh, it's
nice to have a link. I think it's understood to be that
if we really believe that this is the right interpretation, then we
believe that there has to be able to be some way that
it's we can find a basis for it in the פסוקים. psukim.
Meaning, you know, it has to be somehow that it's somehow embedded
in the text that we have found. So I don't think it's
just like a nice mnemonic and it links it.
I think that there's a deeper
religious sense that this is the tradition that we have, it's got
to be somewhere here in the פסוקים. psukim Let's find it. So
yeah.
And when you say חדא דמיותר סברא ובמקום מצוה, chada d'miyater sevara
u'bimkom mitzvah, isn't the other one then presupposed, the complementary? What? You
already said that one פסוק pasuk is to say...
No, I only know that once I have the ויבמה, v'yibma meaning
I needed the ויבמה v'yibma to clarify that this was במקום מצוה
bimkom mitzvah. that the Torah was saying that. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara. says like this. So let's continue. Okay. מאי טעמא ויבם
ויבמה במקום יבום הוא דאסירא צרה שלא במקום יבום שריא צרה mai
ta'ama v'yibem v'yibma bimkom yibum hu d'asira tzara shelo bimkom yibum sharya
tzara what we just said, I just did read the lines in
the גמרא. Gemara
In the context of יבום, yibbum, that's where it says you can
never that it's the צרה tzara is excluded from the מצוה mitzvah
of יבום, yibbum not in not in the case of יבום. yibbum,
Okay. אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi מתניתין נמי
דייקא matnitin nami dayka I knew a little because I knew this
line so I already introduced it earlier. He says רבא's Rava idea
that the real חידוש chiddush is צרה, tzara not ערוה. ervah ערוה
ervah would have been obvious, is implicit in the משנה. mishnah How
do I know that? דקתני חמש עשרה נשים פוטרות צרותיהן. d'katani chamesh
esreh nashim potrot tzaroteihen.
The משנה mishnah said fifteen women exempt their צרות. tzarot. It takes
the idea that they themselves are exempt for granted. The חידוש chiddush
of the משנה mishnah is that their צרות tzarot. are exempt. Okay.
ואילו פטורות ופוטרות
לא
קתני. v'ilu pturot u'potrot lo katani. It didn't say fifteen women are
exempt and they exempt their צרות. It just said they exempt their
צרות. It took it for granted that they were exempt. So שמע
מינה. shma mina. You the גמרא Gemara says you know you're right.
That sounds like a very good read of the משנה that we
can take it for granted it doesn't apply to ערוה, ervah, the
חידוש chiddush is the idea of צרה. tzara Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. ומאי שנא ערוה דלא צריכא קרא? u'mai shna
erva d'lo tzricha kra? So why and so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, one minute. Why is it that you didn't need a
פסוק pasuk by ערוה? ervah, Could have figured that out by yourself,
right? דאין עשה דוחה לא
תעשה שיש בו כרת. De-ein ase doche lo ta'ase she-ba-karet. Because just
מצות יבום mitzvot yibbum shouldn't override a prohibition of עריות, a new
prohibition of עריות, that's not the case that it's always the case
of brother's wife. So I could have just figured that out myself.
So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, צרה נמי לא תיבעי
קרא. tzara nami lo tiba'i kra. You shouldn't need a פסוק pasuk
for צרה. tzara, Why not? משום דאין עשה דוחה לא תעשה שיש
בו כרת, Mishum de-ein ase doche lo ta'ase she-ba-karet, because a צרה
tzara. is similarly a לא תעשה שיש בו כרת. lo ta'ase she-ba-karet.
Now the question is, really? How would I have known without a
פסוק pasuk that a צרה tzara
was an איסור שיש בו כרת? issur she-ba-karet? Where am I getting
that from? I never even know of an idea of צרה tzara,
if you don't start showing it to me in the פסוקים. pesukim.
So let's take a look at רש״י Rashi about six lines, eight
lines from the bottom.
What, is it really כרת? karet?
Well, it is כרת, karet, but the reason צרה tzara becomes כרת
karet is because once there's no מצוה של יבום mitzva shel yibbum
she becomes the איסור issur of brother's wife.
So it's not כרת. karet. Now that becomes—look, this becomes
an interesting discussion in the ראשונים rishonim along which is the concept
of צרה. tzara At the end of the day, is she an
ערוה ervah. on her own terms? There's this ערוה ervah called צרת
ערוה, tzarat ervah, you know, and so on? Or is it once
the once you have the חידוש chiddush that there's no מצוה של
יבום, mitzva shel yibbum, then she falls into the general—the real הלכה
of צרת ערוה tzarat ervah is no מצות יבום. mitzvot yibbum. Once
that's true, then she falls into the standard category of wife's brother
with no מצוה של יבום.
mitzva shel yibbum.
She's relabeled as the standard wife's brother with no מצוה של יבום.
mitzva shel yibbum. So רש״י Rashi on the עמוד ב׳ amud beis
when we get to ח׳ עמוד ב׳ ches amud beis after he
says that explicitly, that she just naturally falls into the category of
wife's brother, but it's not so clear. Sometimes you get a sense
that some ראשונים rishonim want to see her as this status in
itself of צרת ערוה. tzarat ervah. Okay, so let's just read this
רש״י Rashi and then I'll take your question. צרה נמי לא תיבעי,
Tzara nami lo tiba'is, רש״י Rashi says, עליה קרא לדרשה דאין עשה
דוחה לא תעשה שיש בו כרת, aleha kra le-drasha de-ein ase doche
lo ta'ase she-ba-karet, דכתיב de-ksiv so you wouldn't need the עליה aleha.
for דרשה. drasha. Why not? Now how do you know this is
a לא תעשה שיש בו כרת? lo ta'ase she-ba-karet? לצרור דמשמע לא
אחות אשה ולא צרתה, Litzror de-mashma lo achos isha velo tzarasa, וכתיב
כרת בסוף עריות. u-ksiv kares b'sof arayos. So רש״י Rashi says that
the גמרא's Gemara question is, I don't need a פסוק pasuk. meaning
I don't need to put this פסוק pasuk in the context of
יבום, yibbum. right? That's what רבא Rava says. I don't need to
put this פסוק pasuk. in the context of יבום, yibbum only I
only needed to do it for the purpose of לצרור, litzror. but
I didn't need to put it because obviously this would have applied
anyway in the case of יבום. yibbum, So what the גמרא Gemara
is saying is, but you know what? Without that link to יבום,
yibbum okay, לצרור, litzror the גמרא Gemara is saying is, forget יבום.
yibum, I would have just read this, don't marry your wife's sister
or or your wife's sister's co-wife, meaning not even in a case
of יבום, yibum right? I would have read it that way. So
if I would have read the פסוק pasuk this way, it would
have told me that there's an איסור עריות issur arayos called the
your wife your wife's sister's co-wife. צרת ערוה Tzaras ervah would have
been a general איסור עריות, issur arayos, not just by a יבום,
yibum. right? If that's how I would have read the לצרור litzror
without linking it to יבום. yibum And then comes along the פסוקים
psukim, at the end and says ונכרתו, v'nichresu, everybody gets כרת. karet.
So you get כרת karet for wife sister and you get כרת
karet for your co-wife sister. So why did I need to link
this to יבום yibum by the עליה, aleha right? יבמה, now there's
an obvious answer. If I would not have linked this to יבום,
yibum then sure I would have said that צרת ערוה tzaras ervah
gets כרת, karet, but I what I would have said too much,
because what would I have said?
Even in a
non even in a non-יבום yibum case, right? If I would have
read this פסוק pasuk without יבום, yibum. I would have said, sure,
there's ערוה ervah, for wife sister and ערוה ervah for צרה tzara,
and I would have known צרה tzara was a problem, but I
wouldn't have limited it to a case of יבום. yibum I would
have said צרה's tzara a problem even when even my my wife's
sister's co-wife who's has nothing who's married to a stranger. So you
needed to link it to יבום yibum, not to tell me there's
a problem with צרה, tzara but actually to limit the problem of
צרה. tzara To tell me the problem of צרה tzara is limited
to a case of יבום, yibum yes.
No, just what what's the case where it's not
it's not a
יבום yibum and his wife.
Right.
ראובן's Reuven wife's
sister is
married to a complete stranger, and this and one guy's married—ראובן Reuven
is married to רחל, Rachel, okay? Somebody else, I don't know, לוט,
Lot, is married to to לאה, Leah, okay? And he's also married
to ען. Ann. So when לוט Lot dies, ראובן Reuven can't marry
לאה, Leah, right? He so because his wife's sister. Maybe there's a
principle of צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah. He also can't marry ען, Ann,
who was a co-wife to his wife's sister, right? That's צרה שלא
במקום מצוה. tzara shelo b'makom mitzva. Maybe there would have been a
general concept of one degree removed from an ערוה ervah that is
also becomes an ערוה, ervah, okay? And that answer is that it
does not. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
so אמר ליה רב אחא בר ביבי למר לרבינא הכי קאמר משמיה
דרבא, amlei Rav Acha bar Bibbi le-Mar la-Ravina hachi qamar mishmei de-Rava,
here's the answer here's what רבא Rava says the answer is. צרה
נמי לא איצטריכא, Tzara nami lo itzrecha, you know what, you're right.
Without a link to יבום yibum from wife's sister, we would have
said wife's sister is forbidden and wife's sister's co-wife is forbidden in
a general case. Keep prescribed, but here's why we needed the case
of יבום, yibum. we needed to limit, not to make it more
forbidden, to make it more permissive: למשרי צרתה שלא במקום מצוה. le-mishrei
tzarata shelo bi-mekom mitzva. To
tell me that the idea of co-wife is only a problem in
a יבום yibum. context. מאי טעמא אמר קרא עליה? mai ta'ama amar
kra aleha? במקום עליה הוא דאסירה. bi-mekom aleha hu d'asira. The עליה
aleha links it to יבום. yibum When you're dealing in a יבום
yibum context, co-wife is a problem. שלא במקום עליה, shelo bi-mekom aleha,
in a non-יבום yibum context, שריא, sharya, it's okay. Alright? So now
we are back to we have two דרשות, drashot, okay, רבא Rava
and we're reading these דרשות drashot through רבא's Rava lens, we take
it for granted that an ערווה erva is not there's no מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibum. in a case of ערווה. erva. So what
do we need the דרשות drashot for? So one דרשה drasha is
רבי, Rebbi, ולקחת ve-lakachat to tell me there's also a concept of
צרה, tzara. that you don't do מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum by
צרת ערווה. tzarat erva. But again, only in a case of יבום.
yibum The idea of co-wife being a problem is only when it's
my brother's co-wife, only in a יבום yibum case is there that
problem. Similarly, this דרשה drasha that this prohibition of wife's sister applies
in the case of יבום, yibum I already knew that you can't
have יבום yibbum, in a case of ערווה, erva, but I needed
it to tell it to me to tell me to make this
יבום yibbum, to tell me the principle that there's a problem of
co-wife. Now without linking it, I would have said there is a
problem of co-wife, but I would have been too general about that.
I would have said you can never marry the co-wife of an
ערווה. erva. So it links it to יבום yibbum to tell me
no, no, the problem of co-wife is when it occurs when it's
my brother's wife's co-wife, okay, it occurs in the case of יבום.
yibbum Alright, so that's basically the same type of דרשה drasha that
according to רבא Rava we know ערווה erva would have been no
good. The דרשות drashot tell us צרה tzara and the דרשות drashot
have to clarify that this issue of צרה tzara. is limited to
a problem in the context of יבום. yibbum, Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה רמי בר חמא לרבא: Amar
lei Rami bar Chama le-Rava: אימא, eima, right? Here, should I by
the way let me just illustrate this if I hope I'm not...
okay.
Here it is, במקום what the גמרא's Gemara. calling במקום מצוה, bimkom
mitzvah, which means במקום יבום.
bimkom yibum. You have ראובן Reuven
married to רחל Rachel
and
שמעון—what Shimon did I write?—שמעון Shimon married to לאה. Leah. So ראובן
Reuven is married to רחל Rachel and to who should we say?
And to דבורה. Dvorah. Okay, somebody from a different generation, from a
different place in תנ"ך, Tanach, so you won't confuse it. Okay. So,
right, ראובן Reuven dies—and in your case ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon
are brothers? What? Yeah, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are brothers
and רחל Rachel and לאה Leah are sisters. So she's צרה, tzara
so she's צרת ערווה. tzarat erva. Okay, that's במקום מצוה. b'makom mitzvah
So what we basically say is, since you have no מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibbum, to רחל, Rachel, you have no מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibbum, to דבורה. Dvorah. Once you have no מצוה mitzvah of
יבום yibbum, to דבורה, Dvorah, what does דבורה Dvorah become? אשת אח.
eshet ach. Okay, and that's why she's forbidden. But the basic חידוש
chiddush is צרת ערווה tzarat erva there is no מצות יבום. mitzvat
yibum. Once there's no מצות יבום, mitzvat yibum, then she becomes אסור
assur because she is אשת אח. eshet ach. Okay? You don't have
to do anything, no חליצה, chalitza, no nothing. Correct. Now שלא במקום
מצוה, shelo bi-mekom mitzvah,
you have
the same thing except here שמעון Shimon married to לאה, Leah, except
here it would be some good set... okay. You have
גדעון. Gideon. Right.
גדעון Gideon is married to רחל Rachel and to דבורה. Dvorah. So
in this case, right, when גדעון Gideon dies, okay, he can't marry
רחל Rachel because it's his wife's sister, but of course he can
marry דבורה. Dvorah. Why not? Totally permitted. So this is it's מותר
mutar שלא במקום מצוה. shelo bi-mekom mitzvah. But you might have thought,
but here's what we have to be clear, you might have thought
maybe the idea of צרת ערווה tzarat erva is not just that
there's no מצות יבום. mitzvat yibum. Maybe צרת ערווה tzarat erva means
one degree removed there's also an ערווה. erva. And since she was
connected by being a co-wife, the same way רחל Rachel is an
ערווה, erva, דבורה Dvorah is an ערווה. erva. And that it would
even apply when some stranger גדעון Gideon dies. So it's telling me
no, צרת ערווה tzarat erva is only an issue, the צרה tzarah
is only an עריות is only a problem when it occurs
when it is in the context of יבום. yibbum, Yes. The top
case, the במקום מצוה, mitzvah but isn't that a circular reasoning? Like
we start we start it by saying you're not allowed to marry
your brother's wife, but יבום yibbum, overrides that. Yeah. But it doesn't
override ערווה erva situations, other ערווה erva situations. And here you're not
allowed to marry your brother's wife, but your sister's... brother's wife which
is supposed to be רחל Rachel and דבורה. Dvorah. But
יבום yibbum. overrides that. So now I do have to marry both
of them.
No, no. Well, you don't do יבום yibbum. to both wives.
No, no. Well, no.
In a normal case, you only do יבום yibbum, to one wife.
Right, right.
Either-or. Either-or. Right. It overrides either. But רחל Rachel is prohibited because
it's my wife's sister.
Right. And therefore there's also a concept that when there's no מצות
יבום mitzvat yibum with one woman... the reason why, the reason why,
the reason why the צרה tzarah, or whatever is prohibited is because
it's my brother's
wife again.
Once I say that there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibbum. let
me give you in a simpler example. Let's say my brother had
kids, right, then everybody here is prohibited because of my brother's wife,
right? Once there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום, yibum, then all of
them they become it goes back to the default category of brother's
wife, right? Let's say my brother was sterile or these women were
sterile. They'd all be אסור assur because of brother's wife. So once
the מצוה mitzvah. of יבום yibum, goes off, it becomes into the
category of brother's wife. So that's what we're saying about צרת ערוה
tzaras ervah as well. Or stays in the category, right.
But the reason for, but the reason all, all I'm saying is
the reason why the מצוה mitzvah goes off
is because the חידוש chidush of צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah. There's a
חידוש chidush of ערוה, ervah there's no מצוה.
mitzvah And the reason there's a חידוש chidush of צרת ערוה tzaras
ervah is because it's...
No, not because it's brother's wife, but because it's a צרה tzarah
of my wife's sister. The צרת ערוה tzaras ervah has nothing to
do with brother's wife. The צרת ערוה, tzaras ervah, she's a צרה
tzarah. to my wife's sister, to a new ערוה. arayah. That's why
the מצוה mitzvah goes off. Not because of brother's wife. It's the
new ערוה ervah, status of רחל. Rachel. It's the fact that רחל's
Rachel my wife's sister and she's a צרה tzarah, to her in
the capacity of wife sister that it goes off.
Yes. And how do we know that
יבום's yibum, off for one of them? Alright, we'll worry about that
as we go along. Okay, בית אחד הוא בונה ואינו בונה שני
בתים. bayis echad hu boneh v'eino boneh shenei batim. We'll worry about
that later. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר ליה
רמי בר חמא לרבא אימא הערוה גופא שלא במקום מצוה תשתרי. Amar
lei Rami bar Hama l'Rava eima ha-ervah gufah shelo b'makom mitzvah tishteri.
So he says, look, hey, heck, as long as you're allowing צרה
שלא במקום מצוה, tzara shelo b'makom mitzvah, that's now you really see
the formalism here and how absurd it's getting. If you're allowing צרה
שלא במקום מצוה, tzara shelo b'makom mitzvah, if you're allowing דבורה Devorah
in this case, why not allow רחל? Rachel? Why not say that
all the prohibitions of עריות are only במקום יבום? b'makom yibbum?
Okay. אימא הערוה גופא שלא במקום מצוה תשתרי. Eima ervah gufah shelo
b'makom mitzvah tishteri. So גמרא Gemara says,
whoa, get a hold of yourself. So לאו קל וחומר הוא? lav
kal v'chomer hu? במקום מצוה אסירא, b'makom mitzvah asira, if the prohibition
of wife's sister, for example, applies even in a case of יבום,
yibum, שלא במקום מצוה שריא? shelo b'makom mitzvah sharya? You think it's,
it should be permitted in another case? So אמר ליה, amar lei,
צרה דחיא. tzara dachyia. But let's look at צרה. tzarah. Again, if
you think about צרה tzarah. as a type of an ערוה, ervah
not just a, an exemption from יבום, yibum not just an exclusion
from יבום, yibum then it's a reasonable point. Well, let's look at
what you say by צרה. tzarah דבמקום מצוה אסירא, de-b'makom mitzvah asira,
in a case of יבום, yibum, the co-wife is forbidden, שלא במקום
מצוה שריא, shelo b'makom mitzvah sharya, in a non-case of יבום, yibum
the co-wife is permissible. So אמר ליה, amar lei, תטום עליך קרא.
tatim alecha k'ra.
So rather than giving a logical argument like I would say, that
that's because there's no מצוה mitzvah? of יבום, yibum. it's not because
she's an ערוה in her own sort of capacity, in her own
capacity, he answers based on a פסוק. pasuk. He says, regarding you,
the verse says בחייה, be-chayeha, כל שבחייה. kol shebe-chayeha.
He says, oh, you know what? That טקא's takka a good question.
The only way we know that the מצוה mitzvah of ערוה applies
even שלא במקום מצוה shelo b'makom mitzvah is because it says בחייה.
be-chayeha. As long as the wife's sister is alive, as long as
my wife is alive, the sister is forbidden. So that means like
in all cases, right? As long as my wife is alive, the
sister is forbidden, even meaning even in situations where it's not a
יבום. yibum. You know, it's a very general prohibition. So it's quite
funny that you needed a פסוק pasuk to reject this, you know,
because again, the logic here is that this is only because of
the mechanics of יבום. yibum But the גמרא's Gemara saying, if we
think of צרה tzarah. as an ערוה, so if that ערוה's limited
to יבום, yibum maybe all עריות are limited to יבום. yibum. No,
בחייה be-chayeha shows you a very broad application of the ערוה.
But this hasn't been said before. No, correct. Now my wife dies
and my brother dies. Right, right. So now we're going to... I
can then marry that sister in law?
Yes, that's the פסוק בחייה. pasuk be-chayeha. Correct. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemorah, says, one minute. So האי בחייה מיבעי ליה? hai be-chayeha
mibayei lei? Wait a minute, you need the word בחייה be-chayeha to
tell me a much more basic הלכה about wife's sister, to tell
me למיעוטי לאחר מיתה, l'mo-tei achar mita,
that after my wife dies, I can marry her sister, the basic
point of what the word בחייה be-chayeha is saying. ההוא מואשה אל
אחותה נפקא ליה. hahu me-v'ishah el achosah nafka lei.
That's learned from the word 'a woman onto her sister' or you
know 'with her sister.' So obviously there's a sense that they're together,
right, and they're rubbing up against each other לצרור. litzror So I
could have inferred that when she's dead, it's permissible. One minute. אם
מואשה אל אחותה, im me-v'ishah el achosah, if I just had that,
הוה אמינא נתגרשה שריא. hava amina nisgareshah sharya. Yeah. So I would
have thought fine, then it's enough that I'm not married to my
first wife, I can then marry her sister because then they're not
competing with one another, right? תלמוד לומר בחייה, talmud lomar be-chayeha, כל
שבחייה. kol shebe-chayeha.
That's what you need בחייה be-chayeha to tell me, as long as
the first wife is alive, even if I've divorced her, I still
cannot marry the sister. דאף על גב דנתגרשה לא. de-af al gav
de-nisgareshah lo. So don't tell me that בחייה... be-chayeha... is telling me
about that it applies שלא במקום מצוה. shelo bimkom mitzvah. בחייה bechayeha
you need just for פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk אלא אמר
רב הונא, Ella amar Rav Huna,
this by the way, I assume that this is a חידוש chiddush
to some people, right? That why wife's sister remains a problem even
after you've divorced, cause you could understand the logic, right? Well why
should it be? I've divorced her. But most of the עריות by
the way do apply even after the original connection has been severed.
And but here even though wife's sister you דווקא davka would have
thought that, בחייה bechayeha is telling you as long as she's alive
it remains a problem. אלא אמר רב הונא בר תחליפא משמיה דרבא,
Ella amar Rav Huna bar Tachlifa mishmei deRava, תרי קראי כתיבי. trei
krai ktivi. There's two פסוקים. כתיב ואישה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור,
וכתיב לגלות ערותה. דחדא משמע.
ksiv ve'ishah el achotah lo tikach litzror u-chsiv legalos
ervatah dechada mashma.
So here we have, one says ואישה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור,
ve'ishah el achotah lo tikach litzror, which means that you cannot, let
me just check רש"י Rashi what he holds for a second.
Okay, right. So he says look, the פסוק pasuk, here ואישה אל
אחותה לא תקח לצרור, ve'ishah el achotah lo tikach litzror, actually let's
move this פסוק pasuk. לצרור up here, okay, לצרור. Okay, so this
is no longer relevant.
Okay, so what he says is here, when it says ואישה אל
אחותה לא תקח לצרור, ve'ishah el achotah lo tikach litzror, that shows
me she and the צרה tzarah are אסור. assur. Okay, are אסורה.
assurah. Okay, לגלות ערותה עליה legalos ervatah aleha because ואישה ve'ishah and
לצרור means the צרה, tzarah. that's how we've been reading it. So
she and... not only is the sister prohibited... okay, not she meaning
the wife, wife's sister. Okay, wife's sister and the צרה tzarah is
forbidden. Okay, two people are forbidden. לגלות ערותה, legalos ervatah, לצרור doesn't
appear in the next half of the פסוק. pasuk ערותה ervatah is
singular. So that says only she is forbidden, no צרה. tzarah So
half the פסוק pasuk suggests a problem of צרה, tzarah the other
half of the פסוק pasuk suggests there isn't the problem of צרה.
tzarah So let's take a look and read it.
So תרי קראי
כתיבי. trei krai ktivi. כתיב... ksiv...
wait, תרי קראי, trei krai, קראי krai there means two
sections of the פסוק, pasuk correct. כתיב ואישה אל אחותה לא תקח
לצרור ksiv ve'ishah el achotah lo tikach litzror, וכתיב לגלות ערותה uchsiv
legalos ervatah. דחדא משמע. dechada mashma. So that's only she, not a
צרה. tzarah הא כיצד? Ha keitzad? How do you reconcile this? במקום
מצוה שתיהם אסורות. bimkom mitzvah shteihem asuros. In a case of יבום,
yibum. she and the צרה tzarah are forbidden. שלא במקום מצוה, shelo
bimkom mitzvah, in a non-case of יבום, yibum. היא אסורה וצרתה מותרת,
hi asurah vetzaratah muteres, only she and not the צרה. tzarah, And
that's your answer. How do you know that she remains forbidden not
in a case of מצוה? mitzvah So there are two halves to
the פסוק. pasuk The first half is talking about מקום מצוה, mkom
mitzvah, case of יבום, yibum okay? And therefore it's she and the
צרה tzarah forbidden. The second half repeats that she's forbidden, so she
remains forbidden not in a case of יבום, yibum. but not the
צרה. tzarah Says the גמרא, Gemorah איפכא אנא, ipcha ana, what about
let's reverse it? במקום מצוה היא אסורה וצרתה מותרת שלא במקום מצוה
שתיהם אסורות. bimkom mitzvah hi asurah vetzaratah muteres shelo bimkom mitzvah shteihem
asuros. Why don't I say she and the צרה tzarah are both
forbidden not in a case of יבום yibum. and in the case
of יבום yibum only she is forbidden? Now that's not as absurd
as it might sound, because certainly not as absurd as the previous
question, because if it's only in the case of יבום, yibum, in
the case of יבום yibum she is forbidden, there's a reason you'd
want to make the צרה tzarah permissible. Why? יבום. yibum In order
to enable יבום. yibum So maybe a צרה tzarah is a general
ערוה, there's a general concept of co-wife of an ערוה is also
forbidden, and that applies in general, even non-יבום cases, but in יבום
cases we'll override the צרה tzarah. idea in order to enable יבום.
So maybe let's reverse exactly what you're saying.
Yeah, another way of establishing the brother's name.
Exactly. Exactly. So the גמרא Gemorah, says how about reversing it?
אם כן לא יאמר עליה. Im kein lo yomar aleha. If that's
true, says the גמרא, Gemara, it did not have to say עליה.
aleha So it could have... meaning this is a funny answer, meaning
without the עליה, aleha,
I would have said... עליה aleha links it to יבום. So somehow
without the עליה, aleha I would have said exactly that, meaning it's
the answer sort of that's so logical that that can't be what
the פסוק could have said. Because without the עליה, I would have
said, okay, here the פסוק says a woman and her צרה tzarah.
are forbidden, here it says just the woman. How am I going
to reconcile it? So the most logical thing would have to have
been to give greater allowance in the case of יבום. To say
oh, well maybe there's not a צרה tzarah, problem in the case
of יבום that'll allow for יבום. So that's how I would have
read it anyway cause that's the logical thing, give the greater allowance
to the case of יבום. Then the תורה Torah goes ahead and
explicitly links it to יבום with the word עליה. So if it's
linking it to יבום, somehow that is telling me something different than
I would have expected and it tells me to reverse it. Okay?
It's a very strange answer, especially I'm waiting for Michael to ask,
that the עליה word links it to יבום but we're saying that
the top half of the פסוק is the יבום case, cause that's
the case that forbids the צרה, tzarah, and the bottom half is
the non-יבום case. So anyway, what? Yeah Michael, why won't you ask
me that? It's more logical. All right, anyway, all right, it's getting
a little complicated, but you get the idea. The גמרא, Gemara, what's
fascinating about this is that the גמרא, Gemara once it introduces the
idea that צרה's a problem, really says well she should be a
problem in all cases and really grapples with that in a serious
way, whereas the best answer seems to be what the גמרא Gemara
hasn't said, that צרה is not an ערווה ervah in her own
capacity, it's just something that changes the laws of ייבום. yibum. But
okay, that's what the גמרא is dealing with. Okay,
where were we?
אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא, Amar lei Rav Ashi l'Rav Kahana,
Rav Ashi said to Rav Kahana, ממאי דהאי
עליה לאיסורא,
mimmay de-hai
aleha l'issura, how do you know עליה is coming to tell me
that there's an איסור צרה in a case of ייבום? yibum? דילמא
להיתרא, dilma l'hetera, maybe it's coming to allow? What do you mean?
והכי קאמר רחמנא, v'hachi ka'amar rachmana, ואשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור,
v'isha el achotah lo tikach litzror, לא היא ולא צרתה, lo hi
v'lo tzartah, שלא במקום עליה. shelo b'makom aleha. Maybe it's saying
again, maybe ואשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור, v'isha el achotah lo
tikach litzror, there's a problem of wife's sister and צרה in the
general case, again, we have a צרה being a problem in general,
maybe to read it that way? ולגלות ערוותה עליה בחייה, ul'galot ervatah
aleha b'chayeha, maybe עליה is telling me that this is a problem,
but if it's a case of עליה, if it's a case of
ייבום, yibum, maybe it's not a problem at all. Somehow the link
of ייבום yibum is telling me, and it's not clear why the
link of ייבום yibum would be telling me that in ייבום yibum
it would override, but maybe the fact that the first has the
פסוק without the עליה is telling me the real problem is שלא
במקום ייבום. shelo b'makom yibum. When you deal with the second half,
במקום ייבום, b'makom yibum, maybe everything is permissible, okay,
so maybe maybe ייבום yibum overrides ערווה? ervah? אבל במקום עליה שתיהן
מותרות. aval b'makom aleha shtehen mutarot. הגמרא Gemara says no, אם כן
לגלות ערווה דחדא היכי משכחת לה? im ken legalot ervah de-chada heichi
mashkachat lah? That doesn't work with what we've been saying because then
you don't because this says they're both אסור, assur, לגלות ערוותה legalot
ervatah says there's a case where just she is אסור assur and
according to your construct you never have just she is אסור, assur,
שלא במקום ייבום shelo b'makom yibum they're both אסור assur you're suggesting
and במקום ייבום b'makom yibum they're both permissible. But that's not true,
לגלות ערוותה legalot ervatah says that there's still a problem, there are
cases where it's just she alone is a problem. Okay, so where
would you find that? היכי משכחת לה? heichi mashkachat lah? אי במקום
מצוה שתיהן מותרות, i b'makom mitzvah shtehen mutarot, according to your argument
in a case of מצוה they should both be permissible, ואי שלא
במקום מצוה שתיהן אסורות, v'i shelo b'makom mitzvah shtehen asurot, and in
a case of non-מצוה they should both be forbidden. So that doesn't
work. End of the day, that was very complicated, but end of
the day what you basically have is you've got two sources of
the idea of ייבום yibum of that it doesn't apply by עריות,
and what רבא Rava really says is that you really that you
really it doesn't apply by אחותה לא תקח לצרור, achotah lo tikach
litzror, fine, לגלות ערוותה
עליה בחייה,
legalot ervatah aleha
b'chayeha, עליה being the key word here בחייה. b'chayeha. Okay, so basically
רבא Rava says ערווה ervah we already know is אסור, assur, that
you could have figured out by yourself, of course it doesn't override
ערווה, ervah, the big חידוש chiddush is
לצרור to tell you צרה. So we established this פסוק is talking
about ייבום yibum in order to get you צרה. Or for רבי,
ולקחה לו לאשה ויבמה, v'lekacha lo l'isha v'yibma, ולקחה is excluding צרה,
only she not the צרה, and again ויבמה in a context of
ייבום. yibum. And the purpose of emphasizing that this is in a
context of ייבום yibum is to tell me this somewhat ironic idea
that צרת ערווה tzarat ervah is not a general problem, it does
not apply when they're married to this גולם goylem guy, okay, it's
not like because you were a co-wife to an ערווה ervah you
become an ערווה, ervah, it is not a general problem, it does
not apply שלא במקום מצוה, shelo b'makom mitzvah, it does apply במקום
מצוה because once there's no מצוות ייבום mitzvat yibum on the co-wife,
that's why the co-wife becomes forbidden, not that she's considered an עריות
in her own but but the הלכה is that there's no מצוות
ייבום mitzvat yibum and then she becomes forbidden. Okay, so we've dealt
with the פסוקים, we're not totally done but we will pick up
with the two dots on this tomorrow. All right, and we lost
our lead.
Yeah, tomorrow's דף daf is is what?