Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. So today's דף daf is ע''ד, Ayin
Daled, 74, and we picked up
about ten lines down, or twelve lines down, right above the line
that starts with the word תשמע. Tashma. All right, and the issue
here at stake is, the issue here at stake is, again, whether
an ערל arel is able to eat מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. So
we had a ברייתא braita that said an ערל arel is not
allowed to eat מעשר, Maaser, and the גמרא Gemara tried to claim
it meant מעשר בהמה, Maaser Behema, which was clearly not the פשט.
pshat. So then it said it's מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon in רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that there's actually a position that מעשר ראשון Maaser
Rishon is forbidden to זרים, zarim, and therefore that's similar to תרומה
truma and therefore ערל arel is more explainable, and we'd rather say
that than מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Of course, this is a radical
idea of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that מעשר ראשון Maaser Rishon is
אסור assur to non-כהנים. Kohanim. But that's how the גמרא Gemara is
getting out of this proof. So let's try again. תשמע, Tashma, come
and hear. So again, line starting with the word תשמע, Tashma, about
twelve lines down. דתני רבי חייא בר רב מדפתי, De-tanei Rabbi Chiya
bar Rav mi-Difti, רבי חייא, Rabbi Chiya, the son of רב, Rav,
of דפתי, Difti, teaches a ברייתא: braita: ערל אסור בשתי מעשרות, Arel
assur bi-shtei maasrot, an ערל arel is
forbidden in two מעשרות. maasrot. מאי לאו אחד מעשר דגן ואחד מעשר
בהמה? Mai lav, ehad maaser dagan ve-ehad maaser behema?
Presumably the מעשר maaser of grain and the מעשר maaser of animal.
מעשר בהמה Maaser Behema because it's קדשים, kodshim, but the מעשר maaser
of grain shows you that an ערל arel is אסור assur in
מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. So the גמרא Gemara says, No. הכא נמי
מעשר ראשון ורבי מאיר. Hacha nami maaser rishon ve-Rabbi Meir. No, we'll
get out of that again, we'll claim that the thing other than
מעשר בהמה maaser behema is מעשר ראשון maaser rishon according to רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that treats it like תרומה truma and that's why
an ערל arel is forbidden. תשמע, Tashma, come and hear. אונן אסור
במעשר ומותר בתרומה ובפרה. Onen assur be-maaser ve-muttar be-truma u-ve-para.
So
what we're going to do here is we're going to look at
three things: מעשר, maaser, תרומה, truma, and פרה אדומה. para aduma. And
מעשר maaser here clearly from all the cases means מעשר שני. Maaser
Sheni. There's no way of getting around that as you'll see from
the cases. And what we're going to do is, this is like
a cute little thing, we'll say X is forbidden to A but
מותר muttar to B and C. Then we'll say Y is forbidden
to B but מותר muttar to A and C. Z is forbidden
to C but מותר muttar to A and B. And we're going
to keep on switching, like it's always going to be forbidden to
one of them and מותר muttar to the other two, and each
one and we're changing the groupings. So let's take a look. Okay,
so אונן, onen, somebody
who's אונן, onen, אסור במעשר, assur be-maaser, can't eat מעשר שני. Maaser
Sheni. That's what we know, לא אכלתי באוני ממנו. lo achalti be-oni
mimenu. אסור במעשר, Assur be-maaser, ומותר בתרומה ובפרה. u-muttar be-truma u-ve-para. Can
eat תרומה, truma, because that's what we learned earlier on, right? That
אונן onen is only אסור במעשר, assur be-maaser, it's מותר בתרומה, muttar
be-truma, and can actually do the עבודה avoda of the פרה אדומה
para aduma because although that's interesting you might think that that's like
קדשים, kodshim, but because but an אונן onen can't eat קדשים, kodshim,
but this isn't actually eating and it's also not a קרבן, korban,
a פרה אדומה para aduma is considered בדק הבית bedek habayit and
not a קרבן. korban. So an אונן onen can do the פרה
אדומה. para aduma.
Okay, yeah,
what
kind of things are involved? Means the sprinkling or the burning? Presumably
all of it, right. Okay, so that's so an אונן onen is
allowed. Now רש''י Rashi sort of points out that it's a קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, if a טבול יום tvul yom can do פרה
אדומה para aduma certainly an אונן onen can do פרה אדומה. para
aduma. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says that it
doesn't always go together. תוספות Tosafot says look at תוספות Tosafot אונן
מותר בפרה דלא גרע מטבול יום,
onen muttar be-para de-lo gara mi-tvul
yom,
ואלא גב דאונן אסור במעשר וטבול יום מותר. ve-ala gav de-onen assur
be-maaser ve-tvul yom muttar. You can have somebody like a מעשר maaser
is always strange, right? מעשר maaser is very bizarre. It's the one
thing that an אונן onen is forbidden in,
and although even though a טבול יום tvul yom is permissible. So
here too, just because a טבול יום tvul yom can do פרה
אדומה para aduma how do you know he can be in he
can do it when he's an אונן? onen? So תוספות Tosafot says
היינו לאכילה. hainu le-achila. Okay, the only thing we're saying an אונן
onen can't do is eat מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, but לנגיעה תרוייהו
שרי. le-negi'ah travayhu sharei. Nobody is saying he can't touch מעשר שני.
Maaser Sheni. So again, an אונן onen is forbidden to eat מעשר
שני, Maaser Sheni, but he's permissible to eat תרומה truma and he's
permissible to do the עבודה avoda of the פרה אדומה. para aduma.
By the way, if you want to understand maybe a little bit
of why is it that an אונן onen that it's more strict
by מעשר שני maaser sheni than תרומה, truma, right? Why is it?
Normally תרומה truma is more strict, so why is an אונן onen
can't eat מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and can eat תרומה? truma? It's
because again remember מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is somewhat like a קרבן.
korban. You bring it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and you only eat it
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? So therefore the same way an אונן onen
is אסור assur in a קרבן, korban, an אונן onen is אסור
assur in מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. תרומה, Truma, although it has more
קדושה, kedusha, is eaten everywhere, and therefore is less קרבן-like. korban So
I think that that's a way of understanding why that's true. But
again, an אונן onen can do the פרה אדומה para aduma because
that is not about eating and that's not a קרבן, korban, and
an אונן onen can do the פרה אדומה. para aduma. So that
is the אונן onen is אסור במעשר assur be-maaser and מותר muttar
in the other two. טבול יום, Tvul yom, אסור בתרומה. assur be-truma.
A טבול יום tvul yom can't eat תרומה truma because a טבול
יום tvul yom is a שני sheni and makes תרומה truma a
שלישי, shlishi, so can't even touch תרומה. truma. ומותר בפרה, u-muttar be-para,
can touch a פרה אדומה, para aduma, that's the... also to do
the עבודה *avodah*, remember that's the famous הלכה halachah *halakha* that טהור
tahor מכלל דאיכא טמא tamei. *tahor m'khlal d'hika tamei* that they made
sure that they had a טבול יום Tvul Yom, *tvul yom* do
the פרה אדומה parah aduma, *parah adumah*. ומותר בפרה *Umutar b'parah*, ובמעשר
*ub'maaser*,
and can eat מעשר שני ma'aser sheini *maaser sheni*, sure, why not?
Okay, so that's in terms of a טבול יום Tvul Yom. *tvul
yom*. מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim
*Mechusar kippurim*. Now, somebody who has gone to the מקווה *mikvah*, it's
been nightfall, but is waiting to bring a קרבן korban, *korban* the
next day, so it's even a weaker טומאה tumah, *tumah* than a
טבול יום *tvul yom*. So אסור assur בפרה *assur b'parah*, can't do
the עבודה *avodah* of פרה אדומה parah aduma. *parah adumah*, but מותר
בתרומה *mutar b'trumah*. Can do תרומה trumah *trumah*, why? Because a person
who's a טבול יום *tvul yom* is more like a שלישי *shlishi*,
and that doesn't have any effect on תרומה trumah *trumah*, תרומה terumah,
*trumah* only a שני *sheni* has an effect, have, I'm sorry, מחוסר
כיפורים mechusar kippurim *mechusar kippurim* is like a שלישי *shlishi*, and therefore
doesn't have any effect on תרומה trumah, *trumah*. ובמעשר *Ub'maaser*. Now if
you're paying attention you should ask what, right? If the טבול יום
*tvul yom* can do the פרה *parah*, then מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim
*mechusar kippurim* is one degree less, right? The טבול יום *tvul yom*
is the guy that went to the מקווה *mikvah* and it's not
yet nightfall. מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim *Mechusar kippurim* is the guy that
it's nightfall but hasn't brought the קרבן korban, *korban* the next day.
So if a guy's מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim *mechusar kippurim* can't do
the פרה אדומה parah aduma. *parah adumah*, why could a טבול יום
*tvul yom* do the פרה אדומה parah aduma, *parah adumah*? Pretty good
question. So the answer is that somebody who is a טבול יום
*tvul yom* in the process of מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim *mechusar kippurim*.
Let's take an example that a woman is a,
well no, יולדת yoledet. *yoledes* is complicated because it's eighty days. A
woman is a זבה *zavah*, okay?
And so she goes ahead and she goes to the מקווה *mikvah*,
then it's nightfall, then she's going to bring her קרבן korban, *korban*
the next day, okay? So that woman even after she's, when she's
a טבול יום *tvul yom*, but what's left in the process is
not only nightfall but also bringing a קרבן korban, *korban*, she also
can't do the פרה אדומה parah aduma, *parah adumah*. When we say
somebody can do the פרה אדומה parah aduma *parah adumah* as a
טבול יום *tvul yom*, that means that all that's remained is the
night to come, no new activity, no קרבן korban *korban* is, there's
going to be nothing that you're going to have to do in
the process, it'll all just end by itself in the next few
hours. So that's somebody, you know, touched a dead body and had
the sprinkling on three and seven and you're just waiting for nightfall.
Touched a dead carcass of an animal, went to the מקווה *mikvah*,
is waiting for nightfall. So that person that all they have to
do is wait a few hours, that person can do the פרה
אדומה parah aduma *parah adumah*. But somebody who has to bring a
קרבן korban. *korban*, they cannot do the פרה אדומה parah aduma, *parah
adumah* after they've gone to the מקווה *mikvah*, and they can't even
do the פרה אדומה parah aduma. *parah adumah* after nightfall before they've
brought the קרבן korban, *korban*. Okay, so that's the mix of things.
מותר *Mutar* with A and אסור Assur. *assur* with B and C,
and then and then going around, each one of them is a
different one. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this:
So why is that a proof? So that's the proof because the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ואי איתא *v'ee issa*, if it's true that
an ערל arel *arel* can eat מעשר ma'aser *maaser*, then here's
another way we could have done the configuration, another thing that would
have fit for this. תני ערל arel אסור בתרומה *Tni arel assur
b'trumah*, an ערל arel. *arel* can't eat תרומה trumah *trumah* as we
know, ומותר בפרה *umutar b'parah*, can do the פרה אדומה *parah adumah*,
no reason not, ובמעשר *ub'maaser*, and could eat מעשר ma'aser. *maaser*. So
the fact that it didn't have this and this would have fit
perfectly in the pattern you're dealing with shows that an ערל arel.
*arel* is אסור במעשר *assur b'maaser*. So all of the evidence is
showing that an ערל arel *arel* is אסור במעשר *assur b'maaser* pretty
much everything we've quoted. Anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tries to get
out of it again and says no, האי תנא tanna דבי רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva הוא דמרבי ליה ערל arel כטמא *hai tanna d'vei
Rabbi Akiva hu d'marbei lei arel k'tamei*. No, this also would be
like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rabbi Akiva*, going like a position we
said earlier that רבא *Rava* resisted, but a position that we're assuming
would take רבי עקיבא'ס *Rabbi Akiva's* statement by תרומה trumah *trumah* and
saying that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* would say for all
cases where a טמא tamei *tamei* is forbidden because of his personal
status, not because he'll make something טמא tamei *tamei*, but because of
his personal status, an ערל arel. *arel* is also forbidden. And therefore
the same way a טמא tamei. *tamei* cannot do פרה אדומה *parah
adumah* because it says ואסף איש טהור tahor. *v'assaf ish tahor*, an
ערל arel *arel* can also not do פרה אדומה *parah adumah*, right?
Remember we said that before by רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*? So we're
saying that here too. And therefore even if an ערל arel *arel*
can eat מעשר ma'aser. *maaser*, it can't fit this pattern. We couldn't
say an ערל arel *arel* is אסור בתרומה *assur b'trumah* and מותר
במעשר ובפרה *mutar b'maaser ub'parah* because this ברייתא braita *braita* might be
going like רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* that would say an ערל arel
*arel* can't do פרה אדומה *parah adumah*. You got it? So therefore
the ערל arel. *arel* could not have fit this pattern and that's
why we did not teach it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this: so we still have a lot of proofs
from ברייתות braitot *braitas* that an ערל *arel* can't eat מעשר שני
ma'aser sheini. *maaser sheni*, but we're trying to get out of all
of them.
What?
מעשר ma'aser, ראשון *Maaser rishon*,
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, whatever else we said. Okay. Now דתניא *detanya*,
now that we're talking about רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* making an ערל
*arel* like a טמא tamei *tamei* we're going to go back and
revisit that. דתניא *Detanya*, רבי עקיבא אומר איש איש לרבות את הערל
*Rabbi Akiva omer ish ish l'rabos es ha'arel*. Right? Somebody who is
טמא tamei, *tamei* cannot eat תרומה trumah. *trumah* and he says the
double language of איש איש *ish ish* says an ערל *arel* can't
eat תרומה trumah *trumah* and we're saying that means it's for all
cases of personal status an ערל *arel* is like a טמא tamei,
*tamei*. Now ומאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי עקיבא *uman tanna d'palig alei
d'Rabbi Akiva*, interesting now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* asks it did. It
didn't ask earlier, but now the גמרא Gemara asks to identify the
תנא who disagrees with רבי עקיבא and says that an ערל is
not like a טמא. tamei? So the גמרא Gemara says, תנא דרבי
יוסף הבבלי, Tanna de'Rabbi Yosef haBavli, it's the תנא קמא tanna kamma
of the ברייתא braita, of יוסף הבבלי. Yosef haBavli. What does this
mean? דתניא בברייתא: De'tanya be'braita: שריפת אונן ומחוסר כיפורים כשרה. Sreifat onen
u'mechusar kippurim kesheira.
רבי יוסף הבבלי אומר אונן כשרה ומחוסר כיפורים פסולה. Rabbi Yosef haBavli
omer onen kesheira u'mechusar kippurim pesula. So we already know that a
מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim cannot do the פרה אדומה, cannot do the
שריפת פרה אדומה, sreifat parah aduma, right? That we taught a minute
ago. What about an אונן? onen? So until now we've been assuming
an אונן onen can do the פרה אדומה. Okay, so here that's
what the תנא קמא tanna kamma says. An אונן onen and a
מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim can do the שריפה sreifa of the פרה
אדומה. רבי יוסף הבבלי Rabbi Yosef haBavli though says no, מחוסר כיפורים
mechusar kippurim is פסולה pesula as we've said, but an אונן onen
is
כשרה. kesheira. Okay, because he doesn't, you know, I'm sorry, did I
say that wrong?
I just reversed the order.
אונן כשרה Onen kesheira ומחוסר, u'mechusar, right,
מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim is פסולה pesula as we said, but nevertheless
an אונן. onen. Oh wait, אונן כשרה onen kesheira is what we
said earlier, right? Earlier we said that an אונן onen is מותר
בפרה, mutar be'parah, right, I'm sorry. So יוסף הבבלי Yosef haBavli is
saying exactly what we said earlier, that מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim is
פסול pasul and an אונן onen is כשר. kasher. But the תנא
קמא tanna kamma says
oh, no, no, the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, oh everyone, I'm sorry,
I got it confused. Everybody agrees that an אונן onen is כשר,
kasher, that's what we said before. The תנא קמא tanna kamma goes
so far to say מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim is כשר. kasher. Right,
hold on let me just check רש״י Rashi where that's just one
sec.
Okay, so right, so רש״י Rashi doesn't say why. But okay, so
למי דאמר, le'mi de'amar, so the תנא קמא tanna kamma says an
אונן onen is כשר kasher to do the פרה אדומה, that's what
we said, there's no פסוק pasuk to exclude it, but even a
מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim is, we said a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim.
can't do the פרה אדומה, the תנא קמא tanna kamma says he
can. רבי יוסף הבבלי Rabbi Yosef haBavli says an אונן onen I
can see is כשר, kasher, but a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim is
פסול. pasul. Now what the heck does this have to do with
the question of an ערל like a טמא tamei, or not? So
רש״י Rashi says, well, the same way they're debating whether a מחוסר
כיפורים Mechusar Kippurim. can do the פרה אדומה or not, they would
debate whether an אונן onen could do the פרה אדומה or not.
So תוספות Tosfot says, I mean, not אונן, onen, they would debate
whether an ערל. I'm sorry, I don't know why I'm slipping up
there. They'd debate whether an ערל. I'm testing you all, you're all
on the ball, good. Okay, so the same way they debate whether
מחוסר כיפורים Mechusar Kippurim. can do the פרה אדומה, they would debate
whether an ערל would do the פרה אדומה. So that's what רש״י
Rashi says. תוספות Tosfot says, who says one has to do with
the other? Especially if you think the issue of ערל is whether
you categorize him as טמא tamei. or not, what does that have
to do with where you put the מחוסר כיפורים Mechusar Kippurim, category?
Those are different considerations. So תוספות Tosfot has a completely different text
of the ברייתא, braita okay? I'm not going to worry you with
it, but I just want to point out that it's not exactly
clear how this ברייתא is proving it. תוספות Tosfot has a completely
different text which has them explicitly arguing about ערל. Our text doesn't
have them mention ערל at all, and רש״י Rashi says it's an
inference by analogy. תוספות Tosfot says the analogy makes absolutely no sense,
he has a completely different text.
Was there a text of רש״י Rashi that didn't have it?
Yeah, it seems quite, there seem to be a number of texts
floating around. It doesn't sound like he just rewrote the text, it
actually seems like there's different סוגיות sugyot and different texts floating around
with it.
Is there an idea that the מילה milah is like a קרבן,
korban. it's similar to a קרבן, korban, and then therefore the analogy
to a מחוסר? mechusar? Oh no, they don't have, a מחוסר כיפורים
Mechusar Kippurim has to do with, no, it's a קרבן, korban. he's
waiting for a קרבן, korban, right?
I don't know, maybe, maybe. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: So anyway that's the again this רבי עקיבא, we're
reintroduced to רבי עקיבא that says that an ערל is like a
טמא. tamei, But we're still back to our question whether an ערל
can eat מעשר ma'aser. or not,
and all the evidence in the ברייתות braitot, is cannot, but the
גמרא Gemara is trying to get out of it. ואף רבי יצחק
סבר ערל אסור במעשר. V'af Rabbi Yitzchak savar arel assur be'ma'aser. But
you know what? Besides the ברייתות, רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak also holds
an ערל can't eat מעשר. ma'aser? דאמר רבי יצחק מנין לערל שאסור
במעשר נאמר ממנו במעשר לא אכלתי באוני ממנו ונאמר ממנו בפסח אל
תאכלו ממנו נא לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר
De'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, minayin
le'arel she'assur be'ma'aser? Ne'emar mimennu be'ma'aser "lo achalti be'oni mimennu", v'ne'emar mimennu
be'pesach "al tochlu mimennu na", "lo totiru mimennu ad boker" etc. מה
ממנו האמור בפסח ערל אסור בו, Mah mimennu ha'amur be'pesach arel assur
bo,
the same way ממנו mimennu means only, you know, now of
course ממנו mimennu literally means you can eat from it and it
excludes eating from other things, but somehow we're still learning ממנו mimennu
means like only you can eat from it and other people can't.
So somehow ממנו mimennu means not an ערל. אף ממנו האמור במעשר
ערל אסור בו. Af mimennu ha'amur be'ma'aser arel assur bo.
Okay,
so we make a link, a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. So now
the גמרא Gemara says מופני, mufni, now it's got to be that
the words are free because if the words are being used to
do their normal function in the פסוק pasuk then they can't be
used for a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. And even though they could
be used like a היקש hekesh or something, maybe they could be
used for a weak גזירה שוה gezeira shava if the words are
being used for their normal function, but that could always be challenged
by a logical challenge. דאי לא מופני, De'i lo mufni, because if
they weren't, the words weren't free, so איכא למיפרך, ika le'mifrach, then
the גזירה שוה gezeira shava wouldn't stand because it could be challenged.
How could it be challenged? מה לפסח שכן חייבין עליו משום פיגול
ונותר וטמא, Mah le-Pesach she-kein chayavin alav mishum pigul ve-notar ve-tamei, because
פסח Pesach is more weighty than מצות. matzos. As we said before,
you transgress for פיגול pigul and נותר notar and a טמא tamei,
person for קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Okay. And okay, so therefore we
would
have therefore it's not the same as מעשר. maaser. So therefore you
need the word to be extra. Says the גמרא, Gemara says like
this: לאי אפנויי מופני. Le-ai afnuyei mufnei.
In what way is it really? I mean, you're also אסור בטומאה
assur betumah by מעשר, maaser. but different ways. And anyway, certainly the
difference about פיגול pigul and נותר. notar. Now, לאי אפנויי מופני, Le-ai
afnuyei mufnei, and indeed it really is
extra, it really is free. מאי מופני? Mai mufni? Where is it
free? אמר רבא אמר רב יצחק: Amar Rava amar Rav Yitzchak: תלתא
ממנו כתיבי. Tlata mimenu ketivi. It says ממנו mimenu three times by
פסח. Pesach. חד לגופא, Chad legufa, one because it's had to say
אל תאכלו ממנו, Al tochlu mimenu, the grammar demands it. וחד לגזירה
שוה, Ve-chad legezeirah shavah, one is free to make the גזירה שוה.
gezeirah shavah. וחד, Ve-chad,
I don't know, למאן דאמר le-man de-amar now and the third is
for based on the פסוק pasuk that says והנותר ממנו עד בוקר
ביום השלישי באש ישרף. Ve-hanotar mimenu ad boker bayom hashlishi ba-esh yisaref.
Okay, that's by the נותר, notar, right? So that פסוק pasuk says,
so what do we, what is this פסוק pasuk needed for? והנותר
ממנו עד בוקר. Ve-hanotar mimenu ad boker. Is that the פסוק? pasuk?
ביום השלישי. Bayom hashlishi.
Am I quoting the פסוק pasuk right?
No, but פסח Pesach doesn't have ביום השלישי.
bayom hashlishi. I'm sorry, not
פסח. Pesach. עד בוקר באש תשרופו. Ad boker ba-esh tisrofu. Okay.
Alright. So what does that so what does that do? So first
we're going to look at what the פסוק pasuk is doing. So
let's take a look. וחד למאן דאמר בא הכתוב וליתן לך עשה
אחר לא תעשה. Ve-chad le-man de-amar ba hakatuv u-litein lecha asei achar
lo ta'asei.
One says the reason for this פסוק pasuk is after it says
לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר. Lo totiru mimenu ad boker.
Oh no, oh there are there are there's three: לא תאכלו ממנו,
Lo
tochlu
mimenu, yeah, then לא
תותירו ממנו עד
בוקר,
Lo totiru mimenu
ad
boker, yeah, then והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש
תשרופו.
Ve-hanotar mimenu ad boker
ba-esh tisrofu.
Right, באש תשרופו, ba-esh tisrofu, thank you. Okay. So, okay, so what
is the reason of what is the need for this פסוק? pasuk?
Okay, because somehow we, you know, otherwise we maybe would have known
that you have to burn it. So there's a debate a debate
what that פסוק pasuk is doing. So למאן דאמר בא הכתוב וליתן
לך עשה אחר לא תעשה, Le-man de-amar ba hakatuv u-litein lecha asei
achar lo ta'asei, one says the reason for this באש תשרופו ba-esh
tisrofu is to say that this מצוות עשה mitzvas asei of burning
נותר notar is linked to the לא תעשה lo ta'asei of don't
leaving it over, so you don't get lashes for leaving it over
because it's ניתק לעשה. nitak la-asei. Okay, that's just saying what the
purpose of this whole clause is, okay, to tell you that the
מצוה mitzvah to burn it is linked to the negative to not
to not leave it over. So איידי דכתיב נותר כתיב נמי ממנו.
Aidi de-chtiv notar chtiv nami mimenu. Alright, so since we needed this
whole phrase, we threw in ממנו, mimenu, but ממנו mimenu really isn't
doing anything. ולמאן דאמר ליתן לך בוקר שני לשרפתו, U-le-man de-amar litein
lecha boker sheini lesreifato,
the other says no, the real reason for this פסוק pasuk is
not to say it's ניתק לעשה, nitak la-asei, there's a debate whether
you conceptualize נותר notar as ניתק לעשה nitak la-asei or not, we're
not going to talk about that now, but the purpose of this
is for the extra phrase עד בוקר, ad boker, because it already
says עד בוקר ad boker up here. Why does it repeat עד
בוקר, ad boker, why didn't it say והנותר ממנו באש תשרופו? ve-hanotar
mimenu ba-esh tisrofu? To tell you that you don't burn it on
the next morning because the next morning is יום טוב, yom tov,
right? If you left it over from the night before, from the
סדר Seder night, the next morning is יום טוב. yom tov. You
wait for the following בוקר, boker, the morning of the 16th, not
the morning of the 15th, and then you burn it.
That's ליתן לו בוקר שני לשרפתו, litein lo boker sheini lesreifato, to
wait to the second morning to burn it. So למאן דאמר ליתן
לו בוקר שני לשרפתו, le-man de-amar litein lo boker sheini lesreifato, to
wait to the second morning to burn it, so איידי דכתב עד
בוקר כתיב נמי ממנו. aidi de-chtav ad boker chtiv nami mimenu. So
again, since it needed this phrase for the עד בוקר, ad boker,
it wrote the ממנו. mimenu. So the basic point is, the third
ממנו mimenu is really not doing anything, the third ממנו mimenu is
because the whole phrase was needed, it threw in the ממנו. mimenu.
But we have an extra ממנו mimenu by פסח Pesach for the
גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah.
Now,
תלתא ממנו כתיבי במעשר, Tlata mimenu ketivi be-ma'aser, and there are
threes by מעשר. maaser. Okay, what are the threes by מעשר? maaser
לא בערתי ממנו באוני, Lo vi'arti mimenu be-oni, ולא ביערתי ממנו בטמא,
velo vi'arti mimenu be-tamei, ולא נתנתי ממנו למת. velo natati mimenu le-meit.
So
חד לגופא, chad legufa, one because you have to say we're talking
about it, like you need it in the to just function grammatically.
וחד לדרבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן, ve-chad le-di-Rabbi Abbahu amar Rabbi Yochanan,
one is for what Rabbi Abbahu said in the name of Rabbi
Yochanan, if you remember, he said that you can that you
can that
oh, only from this ולא ביערתי ממנו בטמא, velo vi'arti mimenu be-tamei,
only from מעשר שני ma'aser sheini can you not burn it when
it's טמא, tamei, but you can burn תרומה trumah when it's טמא,
tamei. right? Remember that, that you can burn תרומה trumah. when it's
טמא? tamei So the prohibition of ביערתי ממנו בטמא vi'arti mimenu be-tamei
only applies by מעשר שני. maaser sheni, וחד לדרבי שמעון בן לקיש,
ve-chad le-di-Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, and one for ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
דאמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש אמר רבי סמיא: de-amar Rabbi Shimon ben
Lakish amar Rabbi Samya: מניין למעשר שני שנטמא שמותר לסוכו? minayin le-ma'aser
sheini shenitma she-mutar lesucho? Now here's a very strange הלכה halacha. that
is interesting balance of what we talked yesterday. Yesterday we taught that
if your מעשר שני ma'aser sheni. becomes טמא, tamei, you cannot burn
it and destroy it. Now we're going... to find that ironically, even
though you can't burn it and benefit from it as fuel and
as light, you can anoint it on your body. So you're not
allowed to eat it, so you think if you can't eat it,
you can't, you know, use it on your body in other ways,
right? How do you know you're allowed to?
שנאמר ולא נתתי ממנו למת. Shene'emar velo nattati mimenu lemet. למת הוא
דלא נתתי, Lemet hu delo nattati, but to a living
person, נתתי, nattati, I did do it. That would be okay when
it was טמא. Tamei Now what is a way that a dead
person can use it that a living person can too? They're not
eating it, the dead. So
איזה דבר ששוה בחי ובמת? eizeh davar sheshaveh bechai uvemet? הוי אומר
סיכה, Hevei omer sichah, it would be anointing. So when it was
טמא, Tamei, I didn't anoint it on the dead, presumably I could
anoint it on the live, and that's how you learn out that
even though you can't burn it, you can anoint it. Okay, or
whatever, yeah. מתקיף לה, Matkif lah, basically you have to continue to
use it for like bodily הנאה, hana'ah, but you can't eat it
or drink it. Okay, so it's very strange, right? And normally we
say that sort of like anointing is like drinking.
Okay, and nevertheless, it's like having a light.
Anointing is the wrong word. What's the word?
It really is.
סיכה's Sichah like just rubbing it in.
Yeah, it's got to be...
it's translated as anointing, but anointing is like a ritual type of
a thing. Anyway, fine. Okay, now,
applying it, anyway, so that's interesting. So in a way, the reason
you can't burn it is not because you can't use it for
anything, it's because it's טמא, Tamei it's that
the only thing you're allowed to use it for is forms of
consumption. So when it's טמא, Tamei there's no... that's still not a
legitimate form of consumption. But סיכה, sichah, because you're not eating or
drinking, is a legitimate form of consumption. Okay, which is a very
strange הלכה. Halacha So מתקיף לה מר זוטרא, Matkif lah Mar Zutra,
מר זוטרא Mar Zutra asked on this, ואימא ליקח לו ארון ותכריכין.
ve'eimah likkach lo aron vetachrichin.
Maybe what it's saying is that I didn't sell the שמן, shemen,
the מעשר ma'aser, שני, and buy a coffin and shrouds and therefore,
let's ignore the coffin. I didn't buy shrouds. But maybe what it's
telling you is that what I could do is sell it and
buy clothes for myself. That's something both the living and the dead
can use. So אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna
brei de-Rav Yehoshua, no, ממנו מגופו. mimenu migufa. It says I didn't...
from it. From it means to use it directly. You don't make
shrouds out of apples, okay? So you're not using it directly. So
clearly we're talking about direct use. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar,
לא נתתי דומיא דלא אכלתי, lo nattati dumya delo achalti,
another way of showing that it means a direct use. It says
I didn't give it to a dead, similar to I didn't eat.
מה להלן מגופו, mah hallan migufa, the same way eating means directly
consuming it, אף כאן מגופו. af kan migufa. So giving it to
the dead means a direct use of it as anointing. Okay. So
anyway, those are the three פסוקים pesukim that we have by מעשר.
ma'aser. But only one of the words by פסח Pesach is free.
We don't have any of the words free by מעשר. ma'aser Okay,
now this comes to an interesting question. When you make a גזירה
שוה, gezeirah shavah, do the words at both ends have to be
free to make it an iron-clad גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, or does
only one word have to be free? Exactly. So that's what מר
mar says. So וכתי מופנה מצד אחד הוא. ve-kati mufneh mitsad echad
hu. So okay, it's only free from one side. Only one word
by קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is open. הניחא למאן דאמר למדין ואין
משיבין. Haniicha leman de'amar lemadin ve'ein meshivin.
That's good if you say that even if only one of the
two ends, you know, nodes are free, you can make a גזירה
שוה gezeirah shavah and you can't... and you can't like critique it.
אלא למאן דאמר למדין ומשיבין, Ella leman de'amar lemadin umeshivin,
but if you say that if only one of the nodes is
free, it's a גזירה שוה מצד אחד. gezeirah shavah mitsad echad. Yes,
you can make a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, but it also could
be critiqued. מאי איכא למימר? Mai ikka lemeimar? What could you say?
Because this could be critiqued because פסח Pesach is obviously more weighty
than מעשר. ma'aser So the גמרא says הא דאביי מדרב נחמן אמר
רבה בר אבוה. ha de-Abaye mi-de-Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha. You
know what? We'll get both sides open. The teaching of אביי Abaye
that he said ממנו mimenu you can't consume בטומאה, be-tumah, but you
can burn בטומאה be-tumah תרומה, trumah. say we don't need the ממנו.
mimenu. We could learn the idea that you can use תרומה בטומאה
terumah be-tumah from another... from another teaching. דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה, De'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, מאי דכתיב mai
dichetiiv ואני הנה נתתי לך את משמרת תרומתי? va'ani hineh nattati lecha
et mishmeret terumotai? I have given you the... I think the פסוק
pasuk is תרומתי. terumati. What? How do we read it, Dov?
את
משמרת תרומתי
Et mishmeret terumoti
or תרומותי? terumotai? תרומותי. terumotai. Oh, it is תרומותי. terumotai. Okay, fine.
I have given you the guarding of my תרומות terumot in the
plural. בשתי תרומות הכתוב מדבר, Bish'tei terumot hakatuv medabber, it's talking about
two תרומות. terumot. אחד תרומה טהורה ואחד תרומה טמאה,
echad terumah tehorah ve-echad
terumah teme'ah, whether it's טהור tahor. or טמא. Tamei Even טמא there's
a way in which you protect it and make use of it.
ואמר לה רחמנא
לך. ve-amar leh Rachmana lecha. So it's yours. נתתי לך, Nattati lecha,
שלך תהא, shelcha tehei, that even תרומה טמאה terumah teme'ah you have
a use for it, להסיקה תחת תבשילך. lehasikah tachat tavshilcha. You can
use it to burn for making your fire under your stove. Okay,
so we don't need the ממנו mimenu by מעשר ma'aser to tell
me you can burn תרומה טמאה, terumah teme'ah, we learn it from
a different פסוק. pasuk. So we have ממנו mimenu free at both
ends. And the end of this conclusion is we have... The whole
string of ברייתות *braitot* that pretty much show that ערל *arel* cannot
eat מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*, and we end by another אמורא *amora* רבי
יצחק *Rabbi Yitzchak* also saying an ערל *arel* cannot eat מעשר ma'aser.
*ma'aser* based on a link to קרבן korban פסח *korban pesach*, which
is where we started before. And although we acknowledge that קרבן Korban
פסח *korban pesach* is weightier, nevertheless we have a solid גזרה שוה
*gezeirah shavah*, and that tells us that an ערל *arel* is אסור
בפסח *assur bepesach*, אסור בתרומה *assur biterumah*, and our conclusion is also
אסור במעשר שני *assur bema'aser sheini*. And now we finally move on
to the next clause of the משנה *mishna*. So that was all
the name of our פרק *perek* הערל *he'arel*, an ערל *arel* can't
eat תרומה trumah, *terumah*, and now we get to the more obvious
part of the statement of the משנה *mishna*, וכל הטמאים *vechol hatmei'im*,
any all טמא *tamei* people can't eat תרומה trumah *terumah*. Okay, but
let's see how do we know that? Let's take a look. And
let's see who's included in that. So two lines from the bottom,
וכל הטמאים *vechol hatmei'im*, מנלן menalan? הני מילי *minalan hanei mili*, where
is this from? אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי ישמעאל *Amar Rabbi Yochanan
mishum Rabbi Yishmael*, אמר קרא Amar kra, *amar kra*, the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* says איש איש מזרע אהרן והוא צרוע או זב בקדשים bekodshim,
לא יאכל עד אשר יטהר *ish ish mizeira aharon vehu tzarua o
zav bakkodashim lo yochal ad asher yithar*. Okay, והנגע בכל טמא נפש
nefesh. *vehanogei'a bechol tmei nefesh*, what's the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*? והטמא בכל
טמא נפש nefesh? *vehatamei bechol tmei nefesh*... oh איש אשר תצא ממנו
שכבת זרע *ish asher teitzei mimenu shichvat zara*. So there's a whole
list of טמאים *tmei'im* in that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, okay. So what
we have to decide is two things. What does, okay, איש איש
*ish ish*, right, מזרע אהרן *mizeira aharon* והוא *vehu*, so
here are the טמאים *tmei'im*, צרוע או זב *tzarua o zav*. Okay,
then בקדשים לא יאכל *bakkodashim lo yochal*, anyway
so קדשים kodshim. *kodashim*.
Okay, או איש *o
ish*,
what is it?
What is it? או איש אשר תגע בכל טמא נפש nefesh *o
ish asher tiga bechol tmei nefesh*... am I quoting
am I doing the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* right?
בכל טמא נפש nefesh *bechol tmei
nefesh*, או איש אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע *o ish asher teitzei
mimenu shichvat zara*. Okay, so אשר תצא ממנו *asher teitzei mimenu*, thank
you, שכבת זרע
*shichvat zara*.
Okay, so we've got a lot of different טמאים *tmei'im* here, שכבת
זרע *shichvat zara*, טמא נפש nefesh, *tmei nefesh*, which okay...
and the next verse continues...
a lot of different טמאים *tmei'im*, what can they not eat? קדשים
kodshim, *kodashim*. So what's קדשים Kodshim, *kodashim*? We're going to say that
this is talking about תרומה trumah. *terumah* and therefore all these טמאים
*tmei'im*, כל הטמאים *kol hatmei'im* are אסורה בתרומה *assura biterumah* because we're
going to say the קדשים Kodshim *kodashim* refers to תרומה trumah *terumah*.
Let's see how we do that. Okay, איזהו דבר ששוה בזרעו של
אהרן *eizehu davar sheshaveh bezar'o shel aharon*, it says מזרע אהרן *mizeira
aharon*.
What is a type of קדשים Kodshim *kodashim* that all of the
seed of אהרן *Aharon* can eat? Okay, not קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*, who
can't eat קרבנות korbanot. *korbanot* from the seed of אהרן *Aharon*? The
קדשי קדשים Kodshim, *kodshei kodashim* at least. Who can't eat them?
What? Okay, but that's even before you get to חללה *chalalah*, there's
like the joke about what do you call somebody this is actually
the joke for our פרק *perek*. What do you call somebody without
a ברית מילה *bris milah*? An ערל *arel*? No, how about a
girl?
So who is the זרע אהרן *zera aharon* that can't eat קדשים
Kodshim *kodashim*? Our girls, right? Women can't eat קדשי קדשים Kodshim. *kodshei
kodashim*, only the men.
בני אהרן ולא בנות אהרן *bnei aharon velo bnot aharon*.
Yeah, exactly. So איזהו דבר ששוה בזרעו של אהרן *eizehu davar sheshaveh
bezar'o shel aharon*, what is the קדשים Kodshim. *kodashim* that all the
זרע אהרן *zera aharon* can eat? הוי אומר זו תרומה trumah *havei
omer zo terumah*, that's תרומה trumah *terumah*. So we're talking about תרומה
Truma *terumah* because it's זרע אהרן *zera aharon*. ואימא ve'eima בחזה ושוק
*ve'eima bechazeh veshok*? How about the קדשים Kodshim קלים *kodshim kalim*, when
the כהן *kohen* gets the חזה ושוק *chazeh vehashok*, the breast and
the thigh of the שלמים *shelamim*, that's קדשים Kodshim. קלים *kodshim kalim*.
And the בנות כהנים kohanim. *bnot kohanim* can eat it. So maybe
that is maybe that's what we're referring to? No, אינה בחוזרת *eina
bechozeret*. If a woman, if a בת כהן *bat kohen* is married
to a ישראל *yisrael* and he dies and she has no children,
she can go back to eating תרומה Truma. *terumah*. We've discussed that,
right? But we learn from a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that she cannot
go back to eating קדשים Kodshim. קלים *kodshim kalim* of her father,
of... so therefore this thing that is שוה בכל זרע אהרן *shaveh
bechol zera aharon*, the most global thing that זרע אהרן *zera aharon*
can eat is
תרומה Truma, *terumah*.
Okay, תרומה Truma נמי *terumah nami*, so אינה בחללה *eina bechalalah*. Okay,
I'll give you something that זרע אהרן *zera aharon* can't eat even
by תרומה Truma *terumah*.
I mean even by תרומה Truma. *terumah* there's a זרע *zera* that
cannot eat it, a חללה *chalalah*, a woman who is born like
from a forbidden relationship. This חללה לאו זרעו דאהרן הוא *chalalah lav
zaro de-aharon hu*. It's not his seed, it doesn't mean it's not
his child, obviously it's child, he has all of the parental obligations,
they have all the כיבוד אב ואם *kibbud av va'eim* obligation, but
it means it's not like his זרע מיוחס *zera meyuchas*. It's not
considered... no longer it's considered like a כהן *kohen*. If it was
a boy he wouldn't be considered a כהן *kohen*. Okay, so therefore
because it says זרע אהרן *zera aharon* we say we're talking about
תרומה Truma *terumah*. Okay, גמרא *gemara* says like this: וממאי דהאי עד
אשר יטהר עד דאיכא הערב שמש *umimai de'hai ad asher yithar ad
de'ika ha'erev shemesh*? Now how do you know it says בקדשים לא
יאכל עד אשר יטהר *bakkodashim lo yochal ad asher yithar*... oh whoops
I forgot that part so part of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. Okay,
so the next part of the... These are the טמאים *tmei'im* but
it says ובקדשים לא יאכל עד אשר יטהר *u-vakadashim lo yokhal ad
asher yithar*. So now we say okay, we've established that קדשים Kodshim
*kadashim* means תרומה Truma *truma* because of זרע אהרן *zera aharon*. Okay.
So this means תרומה Truma? *truma* because of זרע אהרן *zera aharon*.
Now, how טמא *tamei* are you going to be till you're still
אסור *asur* in תרומה Truma. *truma*? Right? What do we say? Who
can't eat תרומה Truma *truma*? Not only if you're טמא *tamei*, but
even if you are a טבול יום *tvul yom*. But if you're
a מחוסר כפורים *mechussar kippurim* you can't eat תרומה Truma, *truma*. So
how do you know עד אשר יטהר *ad asher yithar* means until
they're until you until like it's הערב שמש *ha'erev shemesh* and that
so excludes טבול יום *tvul yom* but it allows for מחוסר כפורים
*mechussar kippurim*? How do we know that? Okay. So, וממאי דהאי עד
אשר יטהר עד דאיכא הערב שמש *u-mimai de'hai ad asher yithar ad
d'ika ha'erev shemesh*? אימא עד דמייתי כפרה *eima ad d'meiti kappara*? Maybe
it means until you're totally טהור tahor. *tahor*. Maybe even you have
to bring a קרבן Korban *korban*. Maybe even a מחוסר כפורים *mechussar
kippurim* is forbidden in תרומה Truma. *truma*. לא סלקא דעתך *lo sal'ka
da'tach*. That doesn't make sense. דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל בזב בעל שתי
ראיות ומצורע מוסגר הכתוב מדבר *detanya d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, be'zav ba'al shtei
re'iyot u-metzora musgar hakatuv medaber*. דומיא דטמא נפש *dumya d'tmei nefesh*. מה
טמא נפש לאו בר כפרה הוא הני נמי לאו בני כפרה נינהו
*mah tmei nefesh lav bar kappara hu, hani nami lav b'nei kappara
ninhu*. Now, these are the only two guys here that could be
bringing a קרבן Korban *korban*, צרוע *tzaru'a* and זב *zav*. These are
the people that you could say, a צרוע *tzaru'a* and a זב
*zav*, עד אשר יטהר *ad asher yithar*, when does a צרוע *tzaru'a*
and זב *zav* become totally טהור tahor. *tahor*? When they bring their
קרבן Korban *korban*. So maybe until you bring the קרבן Korban. *korban*
you're אסור *asur* in תרומה *truma*. So it says no, because these
two guys, okay, somebody who got contact with a dead or somebody
who had touched a dead, or somebody who is שכבת זרע *shichvat
zera*, they don't bring a קרבן Korban *korban*. So these guys עד
אשר יטהר *ad asher yithar* can only mean until the sunset, מקווה
*mikva* and the sunset, because these guys don't bring a קרבן Korban.
*korban*. So these guys here are guys that don't have to bring
a קרבן Korban? *korban*. How does a צרוע *tzaru'a* and a זב
*zav* not have to bring a קרבן Korban. *korban*? Their earlier stages
in the process. Okay, a זב *zav* that only saw twice and
not three days is טמא *tamei* for seven days but doesn't bring
a קרבן Korban *korban*. A צרוע *tzaru'a* who's at a certain stage
of being confined but not the final stage, מוסגר *musgar* not מוחלט
*muchlat*, waits, you know, seven days, does a טהרה *tahara* process, but
doesn't bring a קרבן Korban, *korban*. So the same way these guys
are not in a קרבן Korban *korban* process, we're talking here about
a צרוע *tzaru'a* and a זב *zav* that are not in a
קרבן Korban, *korban* process. And all of them, no, none of them
are מחוסרי כפורים *mechussarei kippurim*. Or rather they're all going to be
טבול יום *tvul yom*. They're all going to be all right and
all of them עד אשר יטהר *ad asher yithar* means until it
becomes nightfall, okay? So that clear? Not a קרבן Korban *korban* here,
so therefore not a קרבן Korban, *korban* there.
Since it's possible to have a זב *zav* and a צרוע *tzaru'a*
be a טבול יום *tvul yom* because they're they've only had two
ראיות *re'iyot* like you said, is the גמרא *Gemara* saying that therefore
all cases of צרוע *tzaru'a* and זב *zav* are going to be
considered as if they're טבול יום
*tvul yom* even
if they have to bring a
קרבן Korban *korban*?
No, what we're saying is that we're going to read the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* that the same way these guys aren't in the process
of a קרבן Korban *korban*, these guys aren't in the process of
all right, and עד אשר יטהר *ad asher yithar* means until they
go to the מקווה *mikva*. Now, and then I mean until it's
night. Then what we're going to say is, but therefore once it's
nightfall, even if you're in the process of bringing a קרבן *korban*,
you can still eat תרומה *truma*.
We're going to say, right?
But then the גמרא *Gemara* is going to say you can't do
that. Even if I accept your read of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
all I get out of it is that if all you have
to do is wait for nightfall, then you can eat תרומה *truma*.
That doesn't prove to me that for somebody that's in a longer
process that they're done by the time of nightfall. The guy that's
in the longer process might need to bring the קרבן
*korban* before he can eat. That's not a bigger leap than connecting
those two guys with the other two.
No, what it's just making a claim what the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
is talking about. The other point is even if I concede that
point, it doesn't get you to where you need to go. So
let's take a look. It says like this. Let's read it again.
דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל בזב בעל שתי ראיות ומצורע מוסגר הכתוב מדבר
*detanya d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, be'zav ba'al shtei re'iyot u-metzora musgar hakatuv medaber*.
So that's a type of a זב *zav* and a מצורע *metzora*
that don't bring a קרבן *korban*. דומיא דטמא נפש *dumya d'tmei nefesh*,
like the guy who is טמא *tamei* by touching a dead body.
מה טמא נפש לאו בר כפרה הוא הני נמי לאו בני כפרה
נינהו *mah tmei nefesh lav bar kappara hu, hani nami lav b'nei
kappara ninhu*. The same way that guy doesn't bring a קרבן *korban*,
we're talking here about a צרוע *tzaru'a* and זב *zav* that are
not in the process of bringing a קרבן *korban*. And for so
therefore the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* means go to the מקווה *mikva*, wait
for nightfall, you're done, and then you can eat תרומה *truma*. גמרא
*Gemara* says fine, let that be the פסוק Pasuk. *pasuk*. אימא הני
מילי דלאו בני כפרה *eima hani mili d'lav b'nei kappara*. Fine, if
somebody doesn't have to bring a קרבן *korban*, all they have to
wait for is nightfall. אבל דבר כפרה *aval de-bar kappara*, but if
somebody is obligated in a קרבן *korban*, אימא עד דמייתי כפרה *eima
ad d'meiti kappara*, that for them they have to finish their process
and they have to bring a קרבן *korban* before they can eat.
That's a very reasonable argument. ותו הא דתנן *ve-tu, ha d'tnan*, that
which we taught in the משנה *Mishna*: טבל ועלה אוכל במעשר *taval
ve-alah okhel be-ma'aser*, הערב שמש אוכל בתרומה *he'erev shemesh okhel be-truma*. If
somebody goes to the מקווה *mikva*, now they went to the מקווה
*mikva*, what's their status? Before nightfall they are called a... anybody? טבול
יום *tvul yom*. טבול יום *tvul yom* can eat מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*,
can't eat תרומה *truma*.
That's what we've been talking about, right? So טבל ועלה אוכל במעשר
*taval ve-alah okhel be-ma'aser*. הערב שמש *he'erev shemesh*, now it's nightfall, what
can you do? אוכל בתרומה. Right? Now you are a, now, now,
okay, because even if you presumably are מחוסר כיפורים. Mechusar Kippurim הביא
כפרה, hevi kapparah, you brought your כיפורים, kippurim, אוכל בקדשים. ochel bekodshim.
So that's a very nice, gives you the right, the three level
strata. Right. Now, so the גמרא says, so that מנלן? menalan? Where
do we know that from? Meaning the presumably the additional question it's
asking is how do we know that מחוסר כיפורים is אסור בקדשים,
right? We haven't established that yet. Okay, or so let's take a
look. So גמרא says like this: מנלן? So אמר רבא אמר רב
חסדא, amar Rava amar Rav Chisda, תלתא קראי כתיבי. telata karai ketivi.
There are three פסוקים. psukim. כתיב, ketiv, it says, לא יאכל מן
הקדשים כי אם רחץ בשרו במים. lo yochal min hakodashim ki im
rachatz besaro bamayim.
Okay, you cannot eat from קרבנות Korbanos until you've gone to the
מקוה. mikvah. הרחץ טהור, harachatz tahor,
which basically says or you say הקדשים hakodashim until you've gone to
the מקוה, mikvah, which basically says as soon as you've gone to
the מקוה, mikvah, you're טהור. Tahor וכתיב ובא השמש וטהר. ukhtiv uva
hashemesh vetaher.
That when the sun sets you're טהור. Tahor. ואחר יאכל מן הקדשים.
ve'achar yochal min hakodashim. Okay, and then you eat קדשים. Kodshim Okay,
וכתיב ukhtiv and the third, so one פסוק Pasuk says after the
מקוה, mikvah, one says after sunset, וכתיב ukhtiv and the third פסוק
says, וכפר עליה הכהן וטהרה. vechipper aleiha hakohen vetaherah. After you bring
your קרבן you're טהור. Tahor So it's actually three פסוקים psukim all
indicate a different point in which you're טהור. Tahor. How do you
make sense of it? הכיצד? hakeitzad? How do you divvy this up?
כאן למעשר, כאן לתרומה, כאן לקדשים. kan lema'aser, kan letrumah, kan lekodshim.
We'll divvy it up based on the different severities of the things
you're eating. If you're eating מעשר, ma'aser. all you have to do
is go to the מקוה. mikvah. If you're eating תרומה, you have
to wait for nightfall. If you're eating קדשים, Kodshim. you have to
wait till you bring your קרבן. Now, again we're going to ask
type of question, how do you know exactly what the ranking is?
ואיפוך אנא, ve'eippoch ana, let me reverse that. No, מסתברא mistabra
meaning at least let's reverse תרומה and מעשר. Maaser Maybe מעשר Maaser.
is more weighty. No, מסתברא תרומה עדיפא, mistabra trumah adifa, תרומה is
weightier, שכן מחפ"ז. sheken mechpaz.
Anybody remember what that means? מחפ"ז mechpaz is מיתה בידי שמים, misa
bidei shamayim, חומש chomesh if you eat it unintentionally, פ pei is
it doesn't have פדיון pidyon and מעשר has פדיון, pidyon, and ז
zayin is זר. zar. Okay,
it can only by כהנים. kohanim. אדרבה מעשר עדיף, adaraba ma'aser adif,
מעשר is more weighty, שכן הדס"טב. sheken hadastav.
It's a good myrtle. Okay, so what's הדס"טב? hadastav? ה hei is
הבאת מקום, hava'as makom, okay, you bring it, you have to bring
it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ד dalet is you do וידוי. vidui. ס
samech is
אסור לאונן, assur le'onen, that's a little bit trickier, okay, you would
have had an אל"ף, alef, but anyway, anyway, an אונן onen can't
eat מעשר and as we know interestingly an אונן onen can eat
תרומה. וט veteit is טומאה, that you know you get, you know
you're not allowed to benefit from it or whatever, burn it when
it's טמא, we just discussed. And the ב bet is ביעור, biur,
you have to destroy it every three years. Get rid of, you
know, clean it out of your house every three years. So how
do you know that תרומה is more weighty? אמר אפילו הכי מיתה
עדיפא. amar afilu hachi misa adifa. All right, but the חייב מיתה
chayav misa when you eat תרומה בטומאה betumah that's more weighty. רבא
אמר, Rava amar, so that's how you know that if we're going
to divvy it up, the weakest is תרומה. רבא אמר בלא מיתה
עדיפא נמי לא מצית אמרת. Rava amar belo misa adifa nami lo
matzis amart. No, even without going to מיתה misa makes it more
weighty, I know that the פסוק that says just going to the
מקוה mikvah is enough can't be talking about תרומה. Why?
אמר קרא נפש. amar kra nefesh.
Because the פסוק says, נפש אשר תיגע בו וטמאה כי אם רחץ
בשרו במים. nefesh asher tiga bo vetame'ah ki im rachatz besaro bamayim.
So the פסוק that says just go to the מקוה mikvah speaks
about a נפש. So what does it mean נפש? איזה דבר ששוה
בכל נפש? eizeh davar sheshaveh bechol nefesh? If it was talking about
תרומה, תרומה can't be eaten by everyone, only by כהנים. So here
it's talking about a נפש that wants to eat
קודש. kodesh. The only type of thing that all people can eat
that's קודש kodesh is
מעשר. Okay, איזה דבר ששוה בכל נפש הוי אומר זה מעשר.
eizeh davar sheshaveh bechol nefesh hevei
omer zeh ma'aser.
מעשר שני. So therefore the פסוק says that a נפש and there
כי אם רחץ בשרו במים. ki im rachatz besaro bamayim. Okay, so
we got one פסוק that says just go to the מקוה, mikvah,
either because מעשר is the weakest or because of the word נפש,
that's talking about מעשר. And then the next פסוקים, psukim, next פסוק
says wait to nightfall, that's the next weightiest thing, תרומה. And then
the third פסוק says wait till you bring your קרבן, that is
for eating קרבנות. But the גמרא says, you know what? Fine, you've
explained the ranking. But you know what you still haven't answered? What
you still haven't answered is maybe for תרומה it's enough to wait
for nightfall if you don't have to bring a קרבן. But maybe
when you're obligated to bring a קרבן, maybe even for תרומה you
only you have to you can only eat once you've brought once
you've totally finished the process. So we're still back to that question.
ואימא back to the question. הני מילי היכא דלאו בר כפרה. hani
mili heicha delav bar kapparah. All of that that by תרומה it's
enough to wait for nightfall is when you don't have to bring
a קרבן. אבל היכא דבר כפרה עד דמייתי כפרה? aval heicha debar
kapparah ad demayisi kapparah? But if you need a קרבן, maybe you're
not done till you're done? אמר אביי תרי קראי כתיבי ביולדת. amar
Abayei terei krai ketivi beyoledet. There are two פסוקים psukim by יולדת.
Yoledes, Okay, now we're going to show we're going to talk about
somebody in the process of bringing a קרבן who nevertheless can eat.
תרומה before the קרבן is brought.
Even when a קרבן is required.
Right. So who is that person? A יולדת, Yoledes? a woman who's
given birth. So what's the הלכה by a יולדת? Yoledes A יולדת
is טמא based on boy or girl. Let's take the boy case
for, for, you double the numbers for a girl, seven days. At
the end of seven days she goes to the מקוה. Mikvah. After
that point if she bleeds, it's not טמא, okay? It's called דם
טוהר. Dam Tohar. But she's not fully טהור Tahor until she brings
her קרבן at the end of forty days. So think about this
a minute. She's gone to the מקוה Mikvah at the end of
seven days. So she's a טבול יום, okay? So she's,
but there's still a whole process, she's not going to bring a
קרבן for thirty-three more days. So she's considered a טבולת יום ארוך.
Tvulus Yom Aroch. Her nightfall doesn't occur until the night before she's
going to bring the קרבן. So for the next thirty-three days she's
a טבול יום. She can eat מעשר but not תרומה. The night
before day forty she is now מחוסר כיפורים. And now she can
eat תרומה, okay? And then the next morning she brings her קרבן
and she can eat even קדשים, okay? So she's a טבולת יום
ארוך. Tvulus Yom Aroch. She's got thirty-three days before her nightfall occurs.
Now let's take a look at it. Okay, כתיב, Ksiv, it says
עד מלאות ימי טהרה, Ad milos yemei tahara, that she is טמא
until the days of purity are done. It's called purity because even
blood, even if she bleeds during that time she's טהור. Tahor So
it says כיון שמלאו ימיה, Keivan shemolu yameha, this פסוק says that
once her days are done טהורה, Tehora, that she is טהור Tahor
as soon as, so by the, you know, by night before day
forty she's already טהור. Tahor That, that's when she's only מחוסר כיפורים.
That's one פסוק. וכתיב, V'ksiv, but then it says וכפר עליה הכהן
וטהרה, V'chiper aleha hakohen v'tahera, that she's טהור Tahor when she brings
her קרבן. So what's the story with this woman? Is she טהור
Tahor the night before or is she טהור Tahor when she brings
her קרבן? הכיצד? Hakeitzad? כאן לתרומה כאן לקדשים. Kan l'truma kan l'kodshim.
So for תרומה it's the night before and for קדשים it's when
she brings her קרבן. So we finally have pinpointed a person that
is מחוסר כיפורים, is a בר קרבן, Bar Korban, needs a קרבן
and nevertheless the night before is considered טהור Tahor to some degree.
So what does that mean? For תרומה purposes that a מחוסר כיפורים
is טהור Tahor. for something. What is that thing? For תרומה. So
now the גמרא is going to ask the next question about the
ranking. You've proven that תרומה is higher in the ranking than מעשר.
But how do you know that קדשים is the highest in the
ranking? Maybe תרומה is the highest? For us the answer should seem
obvious, but let's let the גמרא spell it out. ואיפוך אנא? V'eifoch
ana? Good, you proved your point that there's an early stage of
מחוסר כיפורים that you're טהור for some things. But maybe you reverse?
Maybe you're טהור for קדשים, not you're טהור for תרומה? No, מסתברא
קודש חמור. Mistabra kodesh chamur. No, no, no, קדשים is the weightiest.
How do you know? שכן פנקכ"ס. Sheken pinkakas. Of course you all
remember what that means.
Yeah. פיגול, Pigul, נותר, Nosar, קרבן, okay. עין Ayin is מעילה, Meila,
כף Chaf is what, what, כרת.
Kares. Thank you. And
סמך Samech is,
סמך Samech
is, I don't see it, סמך Samech
is אסור. Okay. That's how I thought as well. Okay. Fine. That's
that. None of that is true by תרומה. תרומה is מטמא באונן,
Mitama b'onen, you don't get כרת, Kares, you get מיתה בידי שמים.
Misa b'yedei shamayim. אדרבה, Adaraba, תרומה חמורה. Truma chamura. שכן מחפ"ז. Sheken
machpaz. מיתה בידי שמים, Misa b'yedei shamayim, חומש, Chumash, no פדיון Pidyon
by תרומה, yes פדיון Pidyon by קדשים. And it's אסור לזר Assur
l'zar and there are some קרבנות that are מותר לזר. Mutar l'zar.
No, הנך נפישן. Hanch nefishan. No, it's more things that are weightier
by קדשים. רבה אמר בלא הנך נפישן לאו מטעמא דאמרת. Rabba amar
belo hanch nefishan lav m'tama d'amart. Even without saying there are more
things that are weightier, that are more things, it's clear what the
פסוק is referring to.
אמר קרא, וכפר עליה הכהן וטהרה, V'chiper aleha hakohen v'tahera, it says
by the קרבן he brings the atonement, the קרבן, and she becomes
טהורה. Tehora. מכלל שהיא טמאה, Miklal shehi tmei'a, you see that before
the קרבן is brought, not only is she not allowed to eat
something, but she actually is considered as her status of טמאה. Tmei'a.
Okay. ואי סלקא דעתך בקדשים, V'ei salka dach l'kodshim, if you think
that once it's ערב שמש Erev shemesh she can eat קדשים even
before bringing the קרבן, but we've now established that before bringing the
קרבן she is still seen as טמאה. Tmei'a. So somebody who's seen
as טמאה Tmei'a would never be able to eat קדשים. איקרי כאן
והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא
לא יאכל. Ikri kan v'habasar asher yiga b'chol tamei lo yei'achel. Right?
It's explicit that a טמא person cannot eat the meat of
קדשים. אלא שמע מינה בתרומה. Ela shma mina b'truma.
But maybe that's what it means, that if she's טמאה Tmei'a she
makes the קרבן טמא and so on. Anyway, it can't be. Since
since the person would still be טמאה, Tmei'a, by קדשים you have
to be one hundred percent טהור. So even if you don't think
קדשים are weightier, still we would not allow for somebody with a
personal status of טמאה Tmei'a to eat קדשים. That would be infeasible.
So therefore if the person might still to some degree be considered
טמאה Tmei'a and be able to eat
תרומה. Can she eat קדשים *kodashim*? If it's שלמים *shelamim* she could,
yes, yes. You mentioned before, I'm not holding, could you
just,
where does מעשר ראשון *ma'aser rishon*
fit in?
Not in this at all. מעשר ראשון *ma'aser rishon* is totally חולין
*chullin* except for רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. We're not talking about רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir*.
That's what I wanted to... so it's considered totally חולין *chullin*.
Totally חולין *chullin* except for רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, but that's a
very outlier שיטה *shita*. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this. Okay, yes.
This is a question comparing קדשים *kodashim* and תרומה *terumah*. On one
hand we say מיתה *misah* is חמורה *chamura*, on the other hand
we say כרת *kares* is חמורה *chamura*. What's the difference?
Yesterday we read that yesterday, the difference between מידי שמים *midei shamayim*...
No, no, no, yesterday we said כרת *kares* is עדיפא *adifa*. Here
we didn't say מיתה *misah* is עדיפא *adifa*. Where do we say
מיתה *misah* is עדיפא *adifa*?
במ"ח פ"ז *B'machpaz*.
Oh, yeah, that's true. It was. The גמרא's *Gemara's* going to in
the end say, I think the גמרא's *Gemara's* going to get to
that. You mean we didn't explicitly say מ' *mem* beats out a
כ' *kaf*. We said it's this collection and that collection, but you're
right, by putting, by allowing for both lists, we're being a little
inconsistent. I think the גמרא's *Gemara's* going to in the end sort
of say that. Okay. You're right. No, here it could have said
that. It could have said even so כרת *kares* is עדיפא *adifa*,
which is what it said yesterday even with the list. Yesterday it
had both lists, מ"ח פ"ז *Machpaz* and whatever, and it said yeah
but the כרת *kares* is the more weighty one. Okay, so now
the גמרא *Gemara* says like this.
Okay.
Okay. So now we've just established א' *alef* that there's a hierarchy
and what the hierarchy is: מעשר *ma'aser*, תרומה *terumah*, and קדשים *kodashim*.
And we've established that even somebody who's in the process of bringing
a קרבן *korban*, this יולדת *yoledes*, is טהור *tahor* for something the
night before and that must mean טהור *tahor* for תרומה *terumah*. Okay.
So now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. מתקיף לה רב ששת
*Maskif lah Rav Sheshes*, רב ששת בריה דרב אידי *Rav Sheshe brei
deRav Idi* asks on this, ומי מצית אמרת תרומה כתיבה הכא *umi
matsis amrat terumah kesiva hacha*, how could you say, fine, we've established
this whole thing, this is תרומה *terumah*, this קדש *kodesh* means תרומה
*terumah*, עד אשר יטהר *ad asher yithar* means going to the מקווה
*mikvah* at nightfall and even if you have to bring the קרבן
*korban*, you're still fine once it's nightfall. So he says, how could
you say we're talking here
about
תרומה *terumah*? דהא תניא *Deha tanya*, we taught in a
ברייתא *braisa*, דבר אל בני ישראל *daber el b'nei Yisrael*, speak to
בני ישראל *b'nei Yisrael*, okay, this is about a case of יולדת
*yoledes*. אין לי אלא בני ישראל *Ein li ela b'nei Yisrael*, I
only know that בני ישראל *b'nei Yisrael*, actually בנות ישראל *b'nos Yisrael*
become טומאת לידה *tumas leida*. גיורת ושפחה משוחררת מנין *Giueres v'shifcha meshuchreres
minayin*, how do I know a convert and a freed slave woman
also have טומאת יולדת *tumas yoledes*? Now again, I have to tell
you that I always find it troubling that the פסוקים *pesukim* all
say כגר כאזרח יהיה מכם משפט אחד יהיה לכם לגר ולאזרח הארץ
*kager k'ezrach yihiyeh mikem mishpat echad yihiyeh lachem lager v'laezrach ha'aretz* etc.,
and the מדרשי הלכה *midrashei halacha* often have to learn out that
a certain פסוק *pasuk* that refers to בני ישראל *b'nei Yisrael* also
refers to גרים *geirim*. Okay, it often does that in מדרשי הלכה
*midrashei halacha* which maintains גרי *geiri* as a separate category. So here
it's saying even if you know that Jewish women are טומאת לידה
*tumas leida*, how do you know it applies to a גיורת *giyuress*?
Or שפחה משוחררת *shifcha meshuchreres* is interesting because normally that's in the
same category of convert, but תוספות *Tosafot* actually points out that even
a שפחה אינה משוחררת *shifcha einah meshuchreres* has טומאת לידה *tumas leida*
because somebody who's still a slave still has the laws of a
Jew, right? Except that they don't have, they have the obligations of
women, but they still have the laws of Jews. Okay, so תלמוד
לומר *talmud lomar* anyway, the פסוק *pasuk* says, how do you know
טומאת לידה *tumas leida* applies to a גיורת *giyuress*? תלמוד לומר *Talmud
lomar* אשה *isha*, אשה כי תזריע *isha ki sazria* is coming to
include any woman. ואי סלקא דעתך בתרומה *ve'i salka dachas b'terumah*, if
these פסוקים *pesukim* about her being טמא *tamei* and eating the night
before were referring to תרומה *terumah*, גיורת ושפחה בנות מיכל תרומה נינהו
*giyuress v'shifcha b'nos meichal terumah ninhu*, since when can a גיורת *giyuress*
and a שפחה *shifcha* eat תרומה *terumah*? So obviously we can't be
talking about תרומה *terumah*. Okay, it's funny, they could eat קרבנות *korbanos*,
they could eat שלמים *shelamim*, but they couldn't eat תרומה *terumah*. So
אמר רבא *amar Rava*, ולו *v'lo*, is it not? והא כתיב *v'ha
kesiv* בכל קודש לא תיגע *bechol kodesh lo tiga*, so לרבות את
התרומה *l'rabos es haterumah*. It's clear it is talking about תרומה *terumah*
because בכל קודש *bechol kodesh* we say includes even תרומה *terumah*. And
from there we learn that somebody who is a before nightfall, who's
a טבול יום *tevul yom* during that 33 days that she's a
טבול יום ארוך *tevul yom aroch*, we learn that she cannot touch
תרומה *terumah* or eat תרומה *terumah*. אלא *Ela*, and presumably if it
means even eat תרומה *terumah*, we see we are talking about תרומה
*terumah*. So what do you do with the fact that we say
we're talking even about a גיורת *giyuress*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
אלא קרא מילי מילי קחשיב *ela kra milei milei kachashiv*. Alright, so
it's different segments of the פסוק *pasuk*. One פסוק *pasuk* is telling
you we're talking even about a גיורת *giyuress*, but another part where
we're telling you about certain laws of טומאה וטהרה *tuma v'tahara* will
be talking about a תרומה *terumah* even if it's not directly relevant
to a גיורת *giyuress*. Just because we say, oh, by the way,
this applies to a גיורת *giyuress* doesn't mean that that's the dominant
point of the פסוקים *pesukim*. So the פסוקים *pesukim* are still talking
about תרומה *terumah* and they're still saying this הלכה *halacha* that she
is אסור בתרומה *asur b'terumah* during this long period, but מותר *mutar*
the night before. Once she's a מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim*. And now
let's just read one more line and the גמרא *gemara* says like
this, תלתא קראי כתיבי *telassa kraei kseivi*, it has three פסוקים *psukim*,
once again three פסוקים *psukim*. ותלתא קראי בתרומה למה לי *v-telassa kraei
betruma lama li*? Why do I need three פסוקים *psukim*? צריכי *tzrichi*.
דאי מאד אשר יטהר *d-ee mei ad asher yithar*, that you're טמא
*tamei* until you become טהור *tahor*, yikes, that's this פסוק *pasuk* that
somebody can't eat תרומה *truma* until they're טהור *tahor*. So לא ידנא
במאי *lo yadana bemai*, I wouldn't know how do you become טהור
*tahor*. כתב רחמנא ובא השמש וטהר *ksav rachmana u-ba hashemesh ve-taher*, then
that's the other פסוק *pasuk* we quoted earlier that says when the
sun sets, so after sunset, that's when you can eat תרומה *truma*.
ואי כתב ובא השמש *v-ee ksav u-ba hashemesh*, if it had just
said after sunset you can eat תרומה *truma*, I would have said
הני מילי דלאו בר כפרה *hanni mili delav bar kapara*, that's somebody
who doesn't have to bring a קורבן *korban*, אבל דבר כפרה *aval
de-bar kapara*, if somebody has to bring a קורבן *korban*, אימא עד
מייתי כפרה *eima ad meisei kapara*, maybe that's what we've been dealing
with, maybe until you bring the קורבן *korban*. כתב רחמנא *ksav rachmana*,
that's why you need the פסוק *pasuk* by the יולדת *yoledes*, עד
מלאת *ad milos*, that she can't eat it until the full period
is over and until it's nightfall, it's the night before she brings
the קורבן *korban*, that even a woman who is in the process
of bringing a קורבן *korban* can eat תרומה *truma* the night before.
Now why couldn't you just have had that one פסוק *pasuk*? אי
כתב רחמנא עד מלאת *ee ksav rachmana ad milos*, which would have
told me even somebody in the process of a קורבן *korban* is
okay the night before, הוה אמינא אפילו בלא טבילה *hava amina afilu
belo tevila*, that wouldn't have told me the idea, that might have
just said the night before is enough, we wouldn't have known the
idea you gotta go to the מקוה *mikveh*. כתב רחמנא עד אשר
יטהר *ksav rachmana ad asher yithar*. Okay, it says now you gotta
go to the מקוה *mikveh*. Alright? So this עד אשר יטהר *ad
asher yithar* said you gotta go to the מקוה *mikveh*, okay, ובא
השמש *u-ba hashemesh* says going to the מקוה *mikveh* is not enough,
you gotta wait till nightfall, and the פסוק *pasuk* of עד מלאת
*ad milos* says even if you're in the process of bringing a
קורבן *korban*, once it's nightfall, the night before the קורבן *korban*, you're
okay, you can eat תרומה *truma* at that stage. Alright, so that's
how we know a טבול יום *tvul yom* cannot eat תרומה *truma*,
but a מחוסר כיפורים *mechusar kippurim* can eat תרומה *truma*.
Alright.