Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ע"ג. ayin gimmel.
We're in the middle of הערל, HaArel, the whole פרק perek dealing
with aspects related to a man who is uncircumcised and we pick
up with בעי מיניה, boei minei, three lines from the top. So
let's take a look. One of the most recent questions we dealt
with, which is a somewhat obscure question about whether an ערל arel
can
do the הזאה, hazah, do the sprinkling of the ashes of the
פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Two different opinions. The one that said was
not, was attributed to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, who said by תרומה
terumah he learned out ערל arel from a פסוק pasuk that referred
to people who were טמא. tamei. So I just want to remind
us that that led the גמרא Gemara to making a broad statement
or broadening רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and saying that in all issues
where a טמא tamei person would be invalidated because of personal status,
not because he's transferring טומאה tuma but because of personal status, an
ערל arel would also be invalid in all areas. רבא Rava disagreed,
but this was an interesting position that the גמרא Gemara
suggested, you know, is a would be a position of רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Okay, we now pick up three lines from the top
on ע"ג ע"א. ayin gimmel amud aleph. בעי מיניה מרב ששת. boei
minei meiRav Sheshet. So now here's a new question. They asked from
רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, ערל מהו במעשר? arel mahu bemaaser? Can an
ערל arel eat מעשר? maaser? מעשר maaser specifically being מעשר שני maaser
sheni because מעשר ראשון maaser rishon it goes to the לוי Levi
and מעשר עני maaser ani that goes to the עניים, ani'im, there's
never a question whether it has, you know, it's always assumed not
to have any קדושה, kedusha, not to have any sanctity. It's completely,
you know, it has no laws. You can it's a gift that's
given to the לוי Levi or a gift that's given to the
עני, ani, but there's no status to the actual
תבואה tevuah itself. This is very different now of we'll see actually
an opinion about מעשר maaser as opposed obviously to תרומה terumah which
is only eaten by the כהן. kohen. And there's also we'll see
an opinion that wants to give some קדושה kedusha to מעשר ראשון,
maaser rishon, but generally it's assumed not. The only מעשר maaser that
has a sense of קדושה kedusha is מעשר שני. maaser sheni. It
has to be eaten in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. If you don't want to
bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you have to redeem it, the whole
idea of redeeming the sanctity onto money. And it's limited to what
it can be used for. It
cannot be well, there's an actual question about whether it has a
specific number of things it can't be used for or the way
רש"י Rashi says is that it can only be used for eating
or drinking or anointing, direct sort of like bodily things that are
for, you know, directly ingested by the body. So that is the
status of מעשר שני. maaser sheni. So then the question is, given
that it has that קדושה kedusha and given that we know that
an ערל arel can't eat תרומה, terumah, what would be the story
about מעשר שני? maaser sheni? So בעי מיניה מרב ששת ערל מהו
במעשר. boei minei meiRav Sheshet arel mahu bemaaser. What's the story of
an ערל arel by מעשר? maaser? כי היכי דיליף פסח ממעשר לענין
אנינות, ki heichi deyalif Pesach mimaaser leinyan aninut,
do we say the same way that we learned פסח Pesach from
מעשר maaser when it comes to אנינות? aninut? Right? So this was
an earlier discussion in the גמרא, Gemara, לא אכלתי באוני ממנו, lo
achalti be'oni mimenu, a person who's an אונן onen who's just, you
know, had an immediate relative die cannot eat מעשר maaser and from
there we learned that that person can also not eat a קרבן
פסח. korban Pesach. So יליף נמי מעשר מפסח לענין ערלות? yalif nami
maaser miPesach leinyan areilut? So the same way we'll say in the
reverse, so then so we'll learn it in the opposite direction. An
ערל arel cannot eat the קרבן פסח korban Pesach and therefore an
ערל arel cannot eat מעשר. maaser. או דילמא, o dilma, or do
we say חמיר מקל יליף קל מחמיר לא יליף? chamir mikal yalif,
kal michamir lo yalif? No, you can't do that. פסח Pesach is
obviously more weighty. פסח Pesach is קדשים. kodshim.
So if something is not valid by מעשר, maaser, an אונן, onen,
then certainly it's not valid by it's not acceptable by the more
weighty thing, by the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. So that's how you
learn in that direction. But it doesn't go the opposite way. Just
because the weighty קרבן פסח korban Pesach an ערל arel is not
allowed to eat doesn't tell you that the same would be true
with מעשר שני, maaser sheni, which is less weighty. Okay, קל וחומר
kal vachomer works in one direction, not in two. Of course תוספות
Tosafot says that the who it's not necessarily maybe the גמרא's Gemara
question is is it based on a קל וחומר kal vachomer or
is it based on a היקש? hekesh? If it's based on a
היקש hekesh that the two are just linked, so it doesn't matter
which one is more weighty. Okay, so that's the question. Do we
learn from פסח Pesach that מעשר maaser that an ערל arel cannot
eat מעשר? maaser?
So אמרו ליה, amru lei, he said to them, so these are
to those who asked רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet
responded back to the group. תניתוה, tenituha, we learned it. Where do
we learn it? In a משנה Mishna in ביכורים. Bikkurim. התרומה והביכורים
חייבים עליהם מיתה וחומש. haterumah vehabikkurim chayavim aleihem mita vechomesh.
So we're going to have a list of things that תרומה terumah
is like ביכורים bikkurim and is different in that way from a
מעשר שני. maaser sheni. Okay, so everything listed here is by תרומה
terumah and ביכורים bikkurim and not by מעשר שני. maaser sheni. So
let's point out by the way that the in the way, if
you were to ask me, I would have said that ביכורים bikkurim
is more similar to מעשר שני maaser sheni than to תרומה. terumah.
Why? Because with both of them, right, you bring them to the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. They have this קדושה kedusha and they're brought
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, well מעשר שני maaser sheni to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ביכורים
bikkurim to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and so on. But there's
an element in which they're like
תרומה. terumah. is given to the כהן Kohen *Kohen* and ביכורים Bikkurim
*Bikurim* is given to the כהן Kohen *Kohen*. And, you know, ביכורים
Bikkurim, *Bikurim* is understood that it can only be eaten by כהנים
kohanim, *Kohanim*, it cannot be eaten by ישראל *Yisrael*. So it has
elements of תרומה Teruma. *Terumah*, right, only eaten by כהנים *Kohanim*, given
to the כהן kohen *Kohen*, you know, it's אסור assur *assur* for
a non-כהן kohen *Kohen* to eat it. Some elements that are like
מעשר Maaser? *Maaser* that it's brought to ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim*, here the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit Hamikdash*, and so therefore we will see
ways in which it's similar to מעשר Maaser, *Maaser*, ways in which
it's similar to תרומה Teruma *Terumah*. So the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* starts
out, right, and it's learned from a verse which I was going
to, where I was going to get to, which is learned from
a verse of תרומת ידך Srumas yadecha. *Terumat Yadecha*. Okay, but that's
a מדרש *Midrash*. I'm saying even before we get to the, you
know, even before we get to the rabbinic hermeneutics, just in terms
of its laws you see how it has both components. So this
we're going to start by the way in which it's similar to
ביכורים bikkurim *Bikurim*. Okay, so let's take a look. התרומה והביכורים *Haterumah
vehabikurim*, I mean, ביכורים bikkurim, *Bikurim* is similar to תרומה Teruma *Terumah*.
התרומה והביכורים חייבים עליהם מיתה misah, *Haterumah vehabikurim chayavim aleihem mitah*. If
a non-כהן kohen *Kohen* eats it, you're חייב מיתה Chayav Misa *chayav
mitah*. We know that by תרומה Teruma. *Terumah*, ומתו בו כי יחללהו
*umetu vo ki yechalelehu*, and as Michael has correctly said, ביכורים bikkurim
*Bikurim* is learned from the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* תרומת ידך terumat yadecha
*Terumat Yadecha*, so that link basically allows us to assign and assume
that these same laws would apply. Okay,
so מיתה misah *mitah* וחומש V'chomesh, *vachomesh*. If a non-כהן Kohen, *Kohen*
eats it בשוגג b'shogeg *beshogeg*, then he has to pay back the
כהן Kohen *Kohen* the principal plus a fifth. Okay, that does not
apply by מעשר Maaser *Maaser*, it can't apply by מעשר שני Maaser
Sheini, *Maaser Sheni* because non-כהנים *Kohanim* eat מעשר שני Maaser Sheini *Maaser
Sheni*. But the law that you have to pay back the כהן
kohen, *Kohen* with a fifth applies by תרומה Teruma *Terumah* and ביכורים
bikkurim *Bikurim* if you eat it unintentionally. ואסורים
לזרים *Veasurim lezarim*, it's forbidden to non-כהנים *Kohanim*, which is pretty implicit
by the מיתה *mitah* and the חומש chomesh *chomesh*. So anyway, it
tells us right to figure out what it's adding. All right, but
anyway, שהן נכסי כהן Nichsei Kohen. *shehen nichsei Kohen*. Now they are
owned by the כהן kohen, *Kohen*. Now that's, okay, is that, again,
is that saying anything different than that you give it to the
כהן kohen *Kohen*? So here, yes, it is. And in a way
this is actually a leniency of תרומה Teruma *Terumah* and ביכורים bikkurim,
*Bikurim* that doesn't apply to מעשר maaser? *Maaser*. That תרומה Teruma *Terumah*
and ביכורים bikkurim *Bikurim* you give it to the כהן kohen. *Kohen*,
the כהן kohen *Kohen* could do whatever he wants with it. Now,
within, meaning he can't like destroy it, but what it means is
he could use it to, he could go to a store and
purchase a suit with it. Okay, and the guy's going to say,
well, I'm not a כהן kohen *Kohen*, what am I going to
do with this תרומה Teruma *Terumah*? He says, well, you know, you
can sell it to another כהן kohen, *Kohen*. So תרומה Teruma *Terumah*
doesn't have the same market value as non-תרומה Teruma *Terumah* because it's
only accessible, it can only be bought by כהנים *Kohanim*, and you
have to be very, it can't get טמא Tamei *tamei*, and you
have all these, I mean only eaten by כהנים *Kohanim*, and you
can't get it טמא Tamei? *tamei*, and it has whatever. So it's
a lot, much more of a pain in the neck than just
buying simple grain, okay? So maybe it costs, I don't know, a
third of the cost of normal grain. But nevertheless, the guy could
go to the store and say, here it is, and whatever the
market value is. And if the storekeeper wants to take it, he
takes the תרומה Teruma *Terumah* and he gives the guy the suit.
And then the storekeeper, who is a non-כהן kohen. *Kohen*, you know,
again, he can't like misuse it, but he can go ahead and
trade it with somebody else. So תרומה Teruma *Terumah* is basically, it
has limits in terms of how it actually can get consumed,
okay, but it cannot, but you can go ahead and treat it
like your property. There's no limits. As opposed to מעשר שני Maaser
Sheini *Maaser Sheni*, מעשר שני Maaser Sheini *Maaser Sheni* you cannot go
to a store and buy something with your מעשר שני maaser sheni
*Maaser Sheni*. מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* can only be used,
it cannot be used for סחורה *sechorah*, for like, you know, transactions.
It can only, I mean it can be used, it can only
be used as a way to directly consume it and, you know,
and get benefit from it, eat it, drink it, anoint from it,
and so on. So that is the way in which it's different.
Another example which is, you know, seen in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is a sort of similar type of, a type of a transaction
is also the classic example is קידושי אישה *Kiddushei Ishah*. A כהן
*Kohen* gives תרומה Teruma *Terumah* to a woman and says הרי את
מקודשת לי בתרומה זו *harei at mekudeshet li b'terumah zo*. Even though
the woman isn't a כהן *Kohen*, of course once she accepts it,
after נישואין *Nisuin* she'll be able to eat it.
But anyway, so,
but you can't do that with מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni*.
מעשר שני maaser sheni. *Maaser Sheni* is not treated as your property.
It's basically something that certainly you don't have permission to engage in
סחורה *sechorah* with. Now what בדיעבד *bediavad* would happen if somebody gave
it to a woman, would it be valid or not, even though
he's not allowed to engage in סחורה *sechorah*? Does it still count
as this person's property or not? That's all dependent on a debate
of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים *Chachamim*, which
is whether מעשר שני maaser sheni. *Maaser Sheni* is called ממון גבוה
Mamon Gavoah. *mammon gavoha* or ממון הדיוט *mammon hedyot*. So, you know,
is it God's food and you're just eating God's food as it
were, right, or is it considered like yours with קדושה Kedusha *kedusha*,
with limits, and so on? So the point I'm making is that
there's two questions here. One question is what are you allowed to
do with it. You're not allowed by מעשר שני maaser sheni, *Maaser
Sheni* to use it in transactions. You're only allowed to benefit from
it. תרומה Teruma, *Terumah* you can and ביכורים bikkurim *Bikurim* you can
use in transactions. There's another question which, okay, you weren't allowed to
do it, but bottom line, is it considered yours or not? Okay,
and that might actually be, you know, a question about a debate
of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים *Chachamim* about how to
see מעשר שני maaser sheni, *Maaser Sheni*. Let's say I buy a
cow with my מעשר שני maaser sheni *Maaser Sheni* money because I
plan on שוחט shochet, *shochet*-ing it. And then my cow goes and
gores somebody. Right, is it my animal that it gored? Right, so
there's questions of ownership that aren't exactly about whether you can do
transactions. Phil, you had a question.
Anything that you can fully legally own and then get חייב מיתה
Chayav Misa for using? It's like such, seems like such an odd
idea that you can fully have legal ownership of something that you
get a death penalty for using.
Wait wait wait no, the חייב מיתה chayav misa, is when a
non-כהן eats it.
Yes, so if a non-כהן owns תרומה.
Teruma Oh I see, and then he would get, he's חייב מיתה
chayav misa. to eat it? Yeah because that's sure, you could own,
I mean you could own חמץ Chometz and I mean although, you
can even own חלב Cheilev and eat the חלב Cheilev and be
חייב כרת. Chayav Kareis. Ownership is not about whether the food is
considered כשר Kosher or טרף, Treif, right? The חיוב מיתה Chiyuv Misa
is not from the stealing nature, it's from the violating of the
קדושה Kedusha, nature of it, right? Or קרבן, Korban, I mean that's
the interesting question, right? You sanctify an animal as a שלמים Shelamim
or something like that, you know? So שלמים Shelamim actually wouldn't be...
but anyway, whatever it would be. So there, yeah, those sometimes because
it's about... right, right exactly, yes, yes, was there...
yeah you had a question?
מעשר שני, maaser sheni, can you exchange that for coins and then
take that to Jerusalem? Yes, so then isn't that a trans... what
does the person do for you who you gave it to for
the coins? What does he do with the מעשר?
maaser, No you transfer it on
your own coins and then you take the money and go to
Jerusalem and then you have to use it to buy food or
whatever.
But what is the original מעשר שני Maaser Sheni. then? What happens
to that original produce?
Then you can do whatever you want with it.
Yeah, yeah. Alright, so okay, so that's the difference. So this is
considered, so a) by the תרומה trumah you have the ability to
use it to do what you want and it's yours.
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni you have very much more strict limits about
what you can do with it. You can't use it in transactions
and it might not even be considered yours as I said if
it's like רבי מאיר if you say ממון גבוה. Okay, that's נכסי
כהן. ועוד אחת, Ve-od achas, וערב אחד במאה Ve-erev echad bemeah if
they get mixed up, תרומה trumah. and ביכורים bikkurim in other grain
or other fruits or whatever, it's only בטל Battel if there's a
hundred times as much of it. Whereas by מעשר, maaser רש״י Rashi
says רוב. Rov. I don't know why רש״י Rashi is assuming רוב
Rov and not like ששים Shishim or whatever, but you certainly don't
need a hundred. Okay, there's a special הלכה Halacha that you need
a hundred by תרומה. trumah One of the explanations is because תרומה
trumah maybe, you know, is, you know you take like... at תרומה
trumah you can take even one and exempt the whole granary. But
the sense is that, you know like, and the standard amount of
תרומה trumah is actually two percent. But nonetheless, it's seen that like
תרומה trumah is the power, thank you...
of even a small amount of תרומה trumah, for a large amount
of grain and so תרומה trumah is only בטל, Battel, you know,
in one in a hundred. It's a special stringency the Rabbis gave
by תרומה trumah, and by...
sorry I didn't get your connection. You're saying because you don't take
so much, therefore you want to be more חמור Chamur on the
other hand and only be בטל Battel in one in a hundred?
No. I'm saying because תרומה trumah is so powerful that a small
amount of תרומה trumah can exempt the huge pile of grain, that
power means that it doesn't get בטל Battel with normal proportions. You
need a lot more, so you need a hundred. Okay. So for
whatever reason the Rabbis are more חמור Chamur by a lot of
these agricultural things: ערלה, Orlah, כלאים, Kilayim, תרומה, trumah that the ביטול
Bittul needs more than just רוב Rov or ששים, Shishim, needs a
hundred. And they apply the same thing to
ביכורים, bikkurim but מעשר maaser. has the normal rule, which would be
רוב Rov or maybe ששים. Shishim. רש״י Rashi here says רוב. Rov.
Okay, so that's one in a hundred, that's a special stringency. וטעונין
רחיצת ידים. U-teunin rechitzas yadayim. Now because they have קדושה, Kedusha, I
mean מעשר שני Maaser Sheni also has a קדושה, Kedusha but the...
but the קדושה kedushah of תרומה trumah, makes it more susceptible for
טומאה. Tumah. Right? You might remember when we did all these things
about טומאה, Tumah, that a... somebody... an אב הטומאה Av Ha-tumah is
the source, right? And that
can... okay. So here you have a source of טומאה, Tumah, let's
say it's a dead... let's say it's a dead cow. Okay, I'll
make a cow. Can't make a tail. Okay, I don't want to
do a dead person because that would make it an אבי אבות.
Avi Avos. Okay, so that's an אב הטומאה, Av Ha-tumah, okay. So
who can become טמא Tamei by an אב הטומאה? Av Ha-tumah? People,
right? Food. That's my food. Okay,
and... yeah well we'll do people,
vessels... what would a vessel look like, a teacup? Yeah. Okay, a
vessel, I don't know if that's an M, and food. Okay, so
I don't know, excuse... excuse the art. That's an אב. Av. I
like... I'm doing pictograms now. Okay, somebody goes ahead and touches the
אב. Av.
He touches it. Okay, he becomes a ראשון, Rishon, one degree removed.
Okay, what can he make טמא? Tamei?
Okay,
only food. Okay, because then the food becomes a שני. Sheini. Okay,
that's it. Okay, so then comes along and here you've got your
food which he touched, right? Maybe it goes this way.
And that's a שני Sheini because the only thing he can make
טמא tamei, is the food. Now, what can the food make טמא?
tamei, So the only thing... Food can make טמא, tamei. I don't
know how I'm going to draw תרומה trumah here. Okay, but anyway,
okay, it's תרומה. trumah.
Okay. So then he can only make תרומה trumah. טמא, tamei. תרומה
Terumah becomes a שלישי shlishi and תרומה Terumah can only make קודשים
kodshim טמא. tamei, I don't know. Okay. All right? So anyway, all
right? So that's the thing. Now, so a שני sheni can only
make תרומה Terumah טמא. Tamei It's a special הלכה halacha or קודשים.
kodshim. Okay? So that is only by תרומה Terumah, and because of
the extra קדושה kedushah of תרומה, Terumah, that קדושה kedushah is ביכורים
bikkurim has a similar קדושה kedushah but again it seems that מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni. not. Now again you see that מעשר שני's Maaser
Sheni, תרומה Terumah is weaker because of a, only a כהן eats
תרומה, Terumah. only a כהן eats ביכורים, bikkurim a non-כהן who eats
it is חייב מיתה, chayav misa right, that points obviously to a
very restricted
type, a קדושה kedushah. that has to be, that's very, is very
restricted and hence therefore a high level of קדושה. kedushah So therefore
something with the קדושה kedushah. of תרומה Terumah and ביכורים bikkurim can
become a שלישי, shlishi, but something that is מעשר שני ma’aser sheni
cannot, it does not have the same type of קדושה. kedushah, So
what does that, let's just read it in the words. So all
of that is טעונים רחיצת ידיים, teunim rechitzat yadayim, your hands are
considered שני, sheni, okay? Your, the basically חז"ל Chazal said your hands
are שני, sheni, which meant that before touching תרומה Terumah you gotta
wash your hands. So before touching תרומה Terumah and ביכורים bikkurim. you
have to wash your hands but not before touching מעשר שני. ma’aser
sheni Doesn't have the same level of קדושה, kedusha right? It's not
as restricted. Non-כוהנים kohanim eat it. You're not חייב מיתה. chayav mita
So that's רחיצת ידיים. rechitzat yadayim. והערב שמש, ve-ha'arev shemesh, same idea.
Guy is טמא, Tamei. goes to the מקווה, mikveh, he's not, he's
not fully טהור tahor until nightfall. That's considered, that's he requiring הערב
שמש, ha'arev shemesh, the setting of the sun. What is his status
after the מקווה mikveh before nightfall? Effectively like a שני. sheni. So
therefore he cannot touch תרומה, Terumah cannot touch ביכורים, Bikkurim but no
problem in terms of touching מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni Okay, there was
a question.
Yeah, this חייב מיתה is בידי שמיים. biydei shamayim. Yes, correct.
Good clarification.
So מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, let's say it's נטמא, nitma, doesn't do
anything, right? I mean, I mean...
Well, we'll get to מעשר שני שנטמא maaser sheni she-nitma in a
bit. Okay. So, okay. Now, that's the list. Now, what does that
have to do with our question of whether an ערל arel can
eat מעשר? maaser. So let's take a look. ואי איתא, ve-im issa,
okay, if it's true that an ערל arel cannot eat מעשר, maaser
then there's another point of distinction he could have made. נתני ערל
אסור בהן, nisni arel assur be-hen, I'm sorry, if it's, if an
ערל arel can eat מעשר maaser then it should have said: נתני
ערל אסור בהן, nisni arel assur be-hen, an ערל arel can't eat
תרומה Terumah because that's what we've estab-, what we've established that way
at the beginning of the פרק, perek, and can't eat ביכורים Bikkurim.
because again ביכורים Bikkurim is learned from תרומה. Terumah מה שאין כן
במעשר, ma she-ken be-maaser, but he could eat מעשר. maaser, So since
it doesn't use the idea of an ערל arel as a point
of distinction, it would make it, it would seem to imply that
an ערל arel cannot eat מעשר. maaser, Because if an ערל arel
could eat מעשר Maaser that would be another point of distinction. That
seems like a pretty good proof. So what's the גמרא's Gemara answer?
תנא ושייר. tana ve-shayar. It's an abbreviated list. Okay, he left, he
left things off. He שייר, shayar, it's not a complete list. It's
not an exhaustive list. And you can't prove anything by the fact
that it wasn't included. Okay.
ומאי שייר דהאי שייר? u-mai shayar de-hai shayar? What did it leave
off that it also left off this? Meaning the גמרא Gemara will
say I can accept the idea that it's not an exhaustive list
as long as you left off a few, at least two things.
If you've only left off one thing that doesn't make any sense.
If you're listing absolutely all the differences except one, you should list
the final one and then it would be a complete list. So
I can only accept it if you left off more than one.
So what else was not included in the list? ומאי שייר דהאי
שייר? mai shayar de-hai shayar? שייר דקתני סיפא. shayar de-katani seifa. We
left off something from the end of the משנה. Mishnah. Let's look
at the end of the משנה. Mishnah יש במעשר וביכורים מה שאין
כן בתרומה. yesh be-maaser u-vikkurim ma she-ein ken bi-trumah.
There are comparisons to מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni ביכורים Bikkurim? that are
not true about תרומה. Terumah. Okay? So then some of this will
be the more obvious things. שמעשר והביכורים טעונים הבאת מקום. she-maaser ve-ha-bikkurim
teunim ha-va'at makom.
They both have to be brought to a particular place and a
similar place. מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is brought to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ביכורים
Bikkurim, is brought to the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash, Okay. וטעונים וידוי. ve-teunim vidui. And they have
a declaration. Right? By the ביכורים Bikkurim you have the whole story
ארמי אובד אבי, Arami oved avi, people I think are familiar with
that פסוק. Pasuk Right? By the מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni right? You
bring it and you say לא אכלתי באוני ממנו ולא ביערתי ממנו
בטמא. lo achalti ve-oni mimenu ve-lo bi-arti mimenu be-tamei. That's where we
learn out that an אונן onen is אסור assur במעשר שני. be-maaser
sheni. So there's a ritual about them. There's a bringing to the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, a bringing to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, an act of
declaration.
ואסור לאונן. ve-assur le-onen. And an אונן onen can't eat it. That's
לא אכלתי באוני ממנו. lo achalti ve-oni mimenu. And again we somehow
learn out ביכורים Bikkurim, from מעשר Maaser because ביכורים Bikkurim, based on
what we sort of want to link it to it various times
is learned out from one or the other. Okay? רבי שמעון מתיר
Rabbi Shimon matir but רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually says no, actually
an אונן, onen, it's true מעשר, Maaser
an אונן onen can't eat מעשר, Maaser but an אונן onen can
eat ביכורים. Bikkurim וחייבין בביעור. ve-chayavin be-bi'ur.
Now another הלכה halacha is is that you have to destroy them.
What does that mean that you have to destroy them? So that
means that if you wait... waited till the third year and you
did not sort of bring your ביכורים Bikkurim. *bikkurim* to ירושלים Yerushalayim
*Yerushalayim* and you did not bring your מעשר שני Maaser Sheni *ma'aser
sheni* to ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* by the end of the third year,
right, you bring it all to ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim* and you distribute
it there and you say, you know, you know הנה *hinei* what's
the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* ביערתי Biarti הקדש מן הבית וגם נתתיו ללוי
לגר ליתום ולאלמנה ככל
מצותך
אשר צויתני *bi'arti hakodesh min habayit vegam
netativ lalevi lager layatom vela'almana kechol mitzvat'cha
asher
tzivitani* alright whatever, don't worry about it right now. Fine. Anyway so
you bring it and you say ביערתי bi’arti, הקדש מן הבית וגם
נתתיו ללוי לגר ליתום ולאלמנה ככל מצותך אשר צויתני *bi'arti hakodesh min
habayit vegam netativ lalevi lager layatom vela'almana kechol mitzvat'cha asher tzivitani*, right?
So you do that, you clean out your house, and you do
that at the end of three years and you bring it all
to ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, which doesn't apply by תרומה truma *terumah*, meaning
the תרומה truma *terumah* eventually has to get to a כהן *kohen*,
but there's not this idea that at the end of three years
you do this whole rich- you know bringing it and distributing it
and doing this whole ritual וידוי *viduy* that comes with it, that
doesn't apply by תרומה truma *terumah*. Okay, דף *daf* 15, okay thank
you. So that מע- *ma-* וחייבים בביעור *vachayavim bevieur*, ורבי שמעון v’rabbi
Shimon, פוטר *veRabbi Shimon poter*. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*
exempts. Okay. So again there are two- so רבי- *Rabbi-* meaning ביכורים
Bikkurim? *bikkurim* he exempts. So these last two things about אונן Onen
*onen* and ביעור *bieur*, they clearly apply by מעשר Maaser *ma'aser*. The
תנא קמא Tana Kama *tanna kamma* says they also apply by ביכורים
bikurim. *bikkurim* and רבי שמעון rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* doesn't- doesn't extend
it to ביכורים bikurim. *bikkurim*. Okay, so that's parenthetical we'll get back
to that debate later. But they clearly do apply to מעשר Maaser
*ma'aser*. Anyway these are ways in which מעשר Maaser *ma'aser* and ביכורים
bikurim *bikkurim* are similar and they're different from תרומה truma, *terumah*. But
that's not a complete list. Why is it not a complete list?
ואילו אסור assur לבער מהן בטמא *ve'ilu asur leva'er meihen betamei*, there's
two other things that are not included in the list. Number one,
you can't destroy it when it's טמא Tamei *tamei*. What do you
do by תרומה truma, *terumah* when תרומה truma. *terumah* becomes טמא Tamei,
*tamei*? It's a classic case in a lot of משניות *mishnayot*, like
the משנה Mishnah. *mishna* in במה מדליקין *Bameh Madlikin*, right, what do-
you know we speak about שמן שריפה *shemen sereifa* which is anyway-
it's the idea that when תרומה truma. *terumah* becomes טמא tamei, *tamei*
you burn it. You burn it and you benefit from it, you
use it as fuel, you know, as oil to light for your
candles. That's what you do by תרומה truma. *terumah*. But by מעשר
Maaser *ma'aser*, the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* explicitly says לא ביערתי ממנו בטמא
Lo biarti mimenu betame. *lo bi'arti mimennu betamei*. So actually by מעשר
Maaser *ma'aser* you would think- it's quite interesting, right, you would think
Micah might be thinking what happens if your מעשר ma’aser *ma'aser* becomes
טמא tamei *tamei*, but actually you're not allowed to eat your מעשר
ma’aser, *ma'aser* and your ביכורים bikurim. *bikkurim* when it's טמא tamei *tamei*.
Now you would think that if you're not allowed to eat it,
what should I do? Throw it away? Why don't I just burn
it and benefit from it? And that- you know what's wrong? But
actually the הלכה Halacha *halacha* is no, you have to actually dispose
of it. You're not allowed to burn it and benefit from it,
which is exactly- exactly what you're supposed to do with תרומה truma,
*terumah* when it becomes טמא tamei *tamei*. So this is the לא
ביערתי ממנו בטמא Lo biarti mimenu betame *lo bi'arti mimennu betamei*. Now
it's interesting, you would have thought that ביכורים bikurim *bikkurim* might have
been similar, you know, because ביכורים bikurim *bikkurim* is basically- has the
קדושה kedusha *kedusha* of תרומה truma *terumah*, so you would think like
the scope of what you can use it for would be similar
and how you use it would be similar to תרומה truma, *terumah*.
But nevertheless ביכורים bikurim *bikkurim* is- is learned out from מעשר ma’aser,
*ma'aser* and neither of them are you allowed to destroy when they
are טמא tamei, *tamei*, you just basically dispose of them. I mean
I think רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says here- no he doesn't say- what
he says... yeah... אלא אסור assur לבער בטמא
ולא *ela asur leva'er betamei velo*- no he doesn't say what you
do with it. But anyway you- but you just dispose of it.
That's number one. ואוכלן בטומאת עצמן לוקה v’ochlan b’tumat atzman lokei. *ve'ochlan
betumat atzman lokei*. And number two if the ביכורים bikurim, *bikkurim* or
the מעשר ma’aser. *ma'aser* become טמא tamei, *tamei* and you eat them,
not when you're טמא tamei *tamei*, it's טמא tamei. *tamei* and you
eat it, you get lashings. We'll see why, because it's based on
the פסוק Pasuk, *pasuk* לא ביערתי ממנו בטמא Lo biarti mimenu betame.
*lo bi'arti mimennu betamei*. מה שאין כן בתרומה mah she'ein kein bitrumah.
*mah she'ein kein biterumah*. And that doesn't apply by תרומה truma *terumah*.
לא קתני *lok tani*, and we didn't list that. אלמא תנא ושיער
*alma tana veshayar*. You see we are leaving things off the list.
Meaning what's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying? It's a little hard, we're
sort of losing the forest for the trees. So- there- so let
me start- step us back. Okay, the question was, do you remember
what the question was? The question was, can an ערל Arel *arel*
eat מעשר ma’aser. *ma'aser*? Right. The attempt to bring an evidence was,
here's a משנה Mishnah *mishna* that says the following ways תרומה terumah.
*terumah* and ביכורים bikurim *bikkurim* are the same, מעשר ma’aser, *ma'aser* is
different. And it listed a whole series of ways, okay? Now, we
know that an ערל Arel *arel* can't eat תרומה terumah *terumah* and
ביכורים Bikkurim *bikkurim*. We know he can't eat תרומה terumah *terumah*, that's
our whole פרק *perek*. Okay, so he can't eat תרומה terumah *terumah*
and ביכורים Bikkurim *bikkurim*. So it could have used, if an ערל
Arel *arel* is allowed to eat תרומה Terumah, *truma*, it could have
used that as a difference. Be- תרומה Terumah *terumah* and ביכורים Bikkurim
*bikkurim* no ערל Arel *arel*, מעשר ma’aser *ma'aser* yes ערל Arel *arel*.
So since that wasn't given as a point of difference, it seems
to indicate that an ערל arel? *arel* cannot eat מעשר ma’aser. *ma'aser*.
That's basically why we're doing all of this. Since it wasn't given
as a point of difference. And the answer is no, the משנה
Mishnah *mishna* is not listing all of the differences. So yes maybe
that is a difference, maybe an ערל arel *arel* is allowed to
eat מעשר ma’aser. *ma'aser*, but it's not being listed, the משנה *mishna*
isn't listing everything. How do I know the משנה *mishna* isn't listing
everything? Because at the end of the משנה *mishna* is a different
list and it also leaves off two things. What's the list at
the end of the משנה *mishna*? The list at the end of
the משנה *mishna* is מעשר ma’aser *ma'aser* and ביכורים Bikkurim *bikkurim* are
similar in certain ways that תרומה Terumah? *terumah* is different from. The
most obvious Most obvious ways that they're similar is you bring them
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, or ירושלים, Yerushalayim you make a
declaration and so on. There are other ways in which they're similar
and תרומה Terumah, is different. In that list, the גמרא Gemara says
two things are left off, and two points of difference are left
off. So that shows you that we're dealing with non-exhaustive lists, non-complete
lists, and since we're dealing with non-complete lists, there's nothing you can
infer from the idea that we didn't discuss ערל arel and מעשר
שני. Maaser Sheni So we don't know in the end, but the
fact that it wasn't made a difference does not prove that they're
the same, okay? These lists are incomplete lists. What are the ways,
by the way, in which—what are the things that were left off
in terms of the way that ביכורים Bikkurim and מעשר ma’aser. are
similar and תרומה Terumah. is different? Based on the פסוק pasuk of
לא ביערתי ממנו בטמא. lo bi’arti mimenu b’tamei, That פסוק pasuk לא
ביערתי ממנו בטמא lo bi’arti mimenu b’tamei, tells you number one, if
it's טמא tamei you're not allowed to—you're not allowed to burn it,
whereas by תרומה Terumah that's exactly what you do, is that you
light—you know, you burn it and you use it for light, for
fuel, when it's טמא. tamei, And similarly it also tells you when
it's טמא tamei? you're not allowed to eat it. Okay, consume—ביערתי is
also consuming it, whereas תרומה, Terumah and you get lashes, it's a
לא תעשה, Lo saase, whereas by תרומה, Terumah although you're not allowed
to consume it if it's טמא, tamei you don't get lashes. So
both of those are based on the פסוק pasuk, לא ביערתי ממנו
בטמא. lo bi’arti mimenu b’tamei, Those things were not on the list.
So again, it shows you that we're not dealing with complete lists.
Okay? More or less? Yeah?
Why is it—I don't understand, why does—I would argue this like more
simply. In other words, an ערל cannot eat תרומה Terumah and ביכורים.
Bikkurim ערל was not included—ערל is different. I'm sorry, מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni is different.
How do you know מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is different? It's different
in some ways, it's similar in other ways.
Right? That's the whole point. There's certain ways in which it's similar,
there's certain ways in which it's different. How do you know whether
ערל goes in column A or column B? Is it in the
similar column or the different column? That's the question. And you can't
prove anything from that it wasn't on a list because we're not—these
lists are not complete—are not exhaustive. Right.
Okay, that's generally a question with the lists. Right. כמו מציאות, Kemo
metzius, also. Right.
Right. I still remember, you know sometimes, you know—I always like—I always
like those clever—you know, billboards they have on the highway like you
saw—anyway, so I still remember one that was from an airline that
basically said something like—it was, it said something like this. It said
like, New York, you know, California, something like this, and then it
said—then it had a few others and it said, an abbreviated list
of some of the places that we go to.
So I thought that was cute.
Anyway, alright. דעשורנו עונן, Deasurono onen, רבי שמעון מתיר. Rabbi Shimon mattir.
So now let's take a look at some of the points that
were debated. Again, the way in which מעשר ma’aser. and ביכורים Bikkurim
are similar are the obvious ones. You bring them to ירושלים Yerushalayim
or בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you make a declaration. How about the
less obvious ways? The ways that are, you know, not explicitly in
the פסוקים. Psukim. So we know that an אונן Onen doesn't eat
מעשר maaser because it
says—you know—לא אכלתי באוני ממנו Lo achalti beoni mimenu as part of
the declaration of מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. But do you apply that
to ביכורים? So the תנא קמא tanna kamma says yes, and an
אונן Onen. can't eat ביכורים, and רבי שמעון rabbi Shimon says no.
So the גמרא Gemara says מנא להו, Mena lehu, where do they
get this from? To link it to ביכורים or not link it
to ביכורים, this הלכה about an
אונן. onen דכתיב, Dechisiv, לא תוכל לאכול בשעריך מעשר דגנך תירשך ויצהרך
ותרומת ידך.
Lo suchal leechol bisharecha maaser deganecha tiroshcha
veyitzharecha u'srumas yadecha. You can't eat in your gates, right, your מעשר
maaser and your תרומה. Terumah Now this is a very difficult פסוק,
pasuk because of course you can eat מעשר Ma'aser and תרומה Terumah.
in your gates. מעשר Ma'aser, goes to the לוי, Levi, right? Your
gates means your cities as opposed to
ירושלים. Yerushalayim מעשר Ma'aser, goes to the לוי, Levi, תרומה Terumah. goes
to the כהן, they eat it, it's called חולין, Chullin, it's called
קדשי גבולין, Kodshei gevulin, stuff that's given in the, you know, outer
regions, not in ירושלים. Yerushalayim, So of course it's eaten in your
gates. So what does it mean it's not? So חז"ל Chazal have
to say that the מעשר Ma'aser, being referred to here is—what is
the מעשר Ma'aser, that can't be eaten in your gates? מעשר שני,
Maaser Sheni unless you're living in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But what's the תרומה
Terumah that can't be eaten in your gates? So they say the
only thing that's called תרומה Terumah that can't be eaten in the
cities and only in ירושלים Yerushalayim, is ביכורים, because ביכורים is called,
right, תרומת ידך. terumat yadecha Okay? Or not called, but we say—ואמר
מר, V'amar Mar, תרומת ידך אלו ביכורים. Srumas yadecha elu bikkurim. We
claim—the point—what we say is the word תרומה Terumah, there refers to
ביכורים. Now does it actually say the word תרומה Terumah by ביכורים?
Hold on. Or the word הרימותי? Harimosi? Let's take a look, I
don't remember.
Yeah, doesn't it say הרימותי? Harimosi? To say to lift it up
and put it in the—yeah,
yeah, כהן lifts it up... ולקחת
מראשית...
V'lakachta m'reishis...
והניחו... V'hinnicho... ועתה הנה הבאתי... V'ata hinei heveisi...
it never says הרימותי. Harimosi. It never says תרומה. Terumah But somehow
because it's something that you... you bring with your hands to the
כהן, we say that תרומת ידך means ביכורים. Okay, so those, that’s
the מעשר Ma'aser that can’t be eaten in your gates is מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni, and the תרומת ידך is ביכורים. Okay, ואמר מר
v’amar mar תרומת ידך אלו ביכורים. terumat yadecha elu bikurim. והקיש ביכורים
למעשר, v’hikish bikurim l’ma’aser, so in that פסוק pasuk it is linking
ביכורים and מעשר, Ma'aser those are two things, מעשר Maaser, שני that
you can’t eat in your gates.
מה מעשר אסור לאונן, mah ma’aser asur l’onen, the same way an
אונן onen can’t eat מעשר, Maaser אף ביכורים אסור לאונן, af bikurim
asur l’onen, so an אונן onein. can’t eat ביכורים. Okay, cause they’re
linked. ורבי שמעון, רבי שמעון rabbi Shimon would say back, תרומה קרינו
רחמנא, truma karinu rachmana, no, they’re more תרומה Terumah than they are
מעשר. Maaser It might be for this idea that you have to
eat it in ירושלים Yerushalayim, or whatever or bring it to ירושלים
Yerushalayim, etc. you know that is true, but in terms of its
basic identity, its basic identity is much more that of תרומה Terumah
than it is that of מעשר. Maaser. מה תרומה מותרת לאונן אף
ביכורים מותרת לאונן. mah truma muteret l’onen af bikurim muteret l’onen. Okay,
which by the way I gotta tell you רבי שמעון's rabbi Shimon
position is more persuasive, right? Okay, it’s very nice that ביכורים is
like תרומה Terumah. that you bring it to the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash. you bring it and you make a declaration. But if at
the end of the day it’s owned by the כהן, can only
be eaten by כהנים, it has the same קדושה kedusha, of תרומה,
Terumah right, if you eat it you’re חייב מיתה or you pay
חומש you know or you have to pay it back with a
fifth, all those things are exactly like תרומה, Terumah its fundamental קדושה
kedusha and status is like תרומה. Terumah. So that you understand רבי
שמעון's rabbi Shimon position, which is I’m not going to link it
to ביכורים more than I have to. Its basic identity is that
of תרומה. Terumah Okay, אף ביכורים מותרת לאונן. af bikurim muteret l’onen.
Now, same as the next debate, וחייבין בביעור, v’chayavin bi-biur, the תנא
קמא tanna kamma says that after three years you gotta clean it
out of the house. רבי שמעון פוטר, rabbi Shimon poter, רבי שמעון
rabbi Shimon, exempts, same point. מר מקיש, mar makish, the תנא קמא
tanna kamma links it to מעשר, Maaser. which you clear out of
the house every three years. ומר לא מקיש, u-mar lo makish, and
the other one doesn't. Okay, so very nice. רבי שמעון is taking
a minimalist position. I really see ביכורים as תרומה. Terumah, I’ll only
say it’s like מעשר in the most obvious ways. Okay. ואסור לבער
מהן בטומאה, v’asur l’va’er me-hen b’tuma, now, ואוכלן בטומאת עצמן לוקה. Now,
this last the two the גמרא Gemara said are not included in
the list, okay, that shows that it’s not exhaustive, is that you
cannot that you can’t destroy it when it’s טמא, tamei you can’t
like burn it which is what you do by תרומה, Terumah, and
if it is טמא tamei and you eat it you actually get
lashes, as opposed to תרומה Terumah it’s not as weighty of a
punishment. Okay, מנלן? minalan? And all that is linked to the verse
of לא ביערתי ממנו בטמא, lo biarti mimenu betamei. which is a
verse by מעשר. מנלן? minalan? דתניא d’tanya we taught in a ברייתא
Baraita רבי שמעון אומר rabbi Shimon omer לא ביערתי lo biarti, ממנו
mimenu, בטמא, I did not consume it in טומאה. tuma. What does
in טומאה tuma mean? בין שאני טמא והוא טהור, bein she-ani tamei
v’hu tahor, whether I was טמא tamei and it was טהור, tahor,
or, which is the classic case where if you eat something קודש
kodesh when you’re טמא tamei it’s the most weighty because the thing
itself is still in its pristine state. או בין שאני טהור והוא
טמא, o bein she-ani tahor v’hu tamei, if I am טהור tahor
and it is טמא, tamei, even if it somehow became defiled, I
didn’t consume it. Now, I didn’t consume it, ביערתי, includes burning it.
So you’re not allowed to be מבער m’va’er it, you’re not allowed
to burn it, right, you know when it is טמא, tamei you
have to somehow put it aside and let it rot. Okay, very
strange sort of position that you’re in but that’s what you have
to do with it. Okay and that is distinct again from תרומה,
Terumah. תרומה Terumah. exactly what a כהן does when it’s טמא tamei.
is he uses it for fuel, he uses it for oil. Okay
so that's where you learn that. והיכא מוזהר על אכילתו? v’heicha muzhar
al achilato? That now again that’s at least by מעשר. How we
know it’s true by ביכורים, that might be part of the same
debate of the תנא קמא and רבי שמעון, you know whether you
generally link ביכורים to מעשר or not. But at least it’s true
by מעשר. Now, והיכא מוזהר על אכילתו, v’heicha muzhar al achilato,
then the ברייתא Baraita goes on and it says now that’s how
you say that you’re not allowed to burn it when it’s טמא.
tamei How do you know when it’s טמא tamei you’re not allowed
to eat it? So איני יודע, eini yodeia, I don’t know, and
then the ברייתא, Baraita, it’s like funny because the גמרא Gemara interrupts
the ברייתא. Baraita.
The ברייתא Baraita would say like this, it’s like this: okay that
tells you that you don’t burn it when it’s טמא, tamei how
do you know you’re not allowed to eat it when it’s טמא?
tamei I don't know, comes along the פסוק and teaches: לא ביערתי
ממנו mimenu בטמא, that’s the ברייתא. Baraita. But the גמרא Gemara interrupts
it when it got to the words I don’t know and wouldn’t
let it give the answer. Okay so here's the ברייתא: Baraita: והיכא
מוזהר על אכילתו, v’heicha muzhar al achilato, how do you know you’re
not allowed, you know you get lashes, you know it’s a real
pro you know if you eat it when you are when you
know when in טומאה? tuma? איני יודע, eini yodeia, I don’t know.
And then the גמרא Gemara says: so comes along the פסוק, but
before the גמרא Gemara can say the ברייתא Baraita gives the גמרא
Gemara says: what do you mean? What do you mean you don't
know? טומאת הגוף בהדיא כתיב ביה, tumat ha-guf be-hedya ktiv beih, it
says explicitly if you’re טמא tamei, you’re not allowed to eat מעשר.
It says נפש אשר תגע בו וטמאה עד הערב, nefesh asher tiga
bo v’tame’ah ad ha’erev, if a somebody touches this and
becomes טמא tamei. he becomes טמא tamei, until nightfall, ולא יאכל מן
הקדשים, v’lo yochal min ha-kodashim, he can’t eat holy things. בשרו במים
besaro bamayim and presumably and מעשר שני is clearly included in קדשים.
Kodashim. So what do you mean you don't know that you can't
eat it בטומאה? betumah? So the גמרא Gemara says no no no,
you didn't understand the question. הכי קמיבעיא ליה. hachi kamibaya lei. טומאת
עצמו מנלן? Tumat atzmo minalan? I know that if you're טמא tamei.
and it's טהור, tahor, you can't eat it. But how do you
know that you can't eat it if it's טמא tamei, and you're
טהור? tahor? And you understand why that's different because if it became
טמא, tamei. it somehow got defiled and lost its status, and that's
never as weighty when it's טמא tamei, as when you're טמא. tamei.
So how do you know when it's טמא tamei, you're not allowed
to eat it? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך מעשר
דגנך. lo tuchal leechol bisharecha maaser deganecha. So this is you can't
eat your מעשר in your gates, which the simple sense means you
don't eat it outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim but ולהלן אומר, ulhalan omer, but
now let's see what a פסוק says about the things you do
eat in your gates. בשעריך תאכלנו. bisharecha tochelenu. Okay, this is about
קדשים kodashim that became פסול pasul and then you redeem them. And
then it says after you've redeemed them, you can eat them in
your gates, you no longer have to bring it to ירושלים. Yerushalayim,
הטמא והטהור יחדיו, hatamei vehatahor yachdav, the טמא tamei person and the
טהור tahor person can eat it sitting together together. כצבי וכאייל, katzvi
vecha'ayal, the same way you would eat a צבי tzvi and an
אייל, ayal, a deer and a what's an אייל? ayal? Ibex, a
mountain goat, something, what, a hart? Yeah, I don't know animals. What's
a hart?
It's another, it's just like, it's another deer.
It's a deer? Oh I thought an אייל ayal was some type
of...
אייל ayal I think is a ram.
No, no that's no, no. איל ayil is a ram. אייל ayal
is a like, it's... what? I thought it was an ibex. Okay,
anyway, whatever אייל ayal is. Now, why does the, why does the
Torah compare it to a צבי tzvi and an אייל? ayal? What's
distinctive about a צבי tzvi and an אייל? ayal? This was something
that was קדשים, kodshim, it became פסול, pasul, you redeemed it, and
it says you could eat it just like you would eat a
deer. Why doesn't it say you could eat it just like you'd
eat a cow? What's unique about a deer?
A deer can never be a קרבן. korban.
Thank you. A deer cannot be a קרבן. korban. So, although this
was a קרבן korban and it was redeemed, don't worry about it
anymore, it's like a deer, you can eat it outside the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. you can eat it בטומאה, betumah, הטמא והטהור יחדיו,
hatamei vehatahor yachdav, etc. Okay, fine. That's things that you eat outside
the בית המקדש. Now, ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, vetana dbei Rabbi Yishmael,
so Rabbi Yishmael taught: אפילו טמא וטהור אוכלין על שולחן אחד בקערה
אחת. afilu tamei vetahor ochlin al shulchan echad bekara achas. So a
טמא tamei, and a טהור tahor person can eat them at the
same table, from the same plate, ואינם חוששין, ve'einam chosheshin, and what
does that... and they don't have to worry, which means what? That
the טמא tamei. person will touch it, it'll become טמא, tamei, and
then the טהור tahor person will eat it. So basically means a
טהור tahor person is allowed to eat this קדשים kodshim that was
redeemed even though it became טמא. tamei That's what eating in the
gates means. Eating in the gates means, it's actually a very nice
דרשה, derashah, like sometimes the דרשה derashah seem very technical, but here
it's actually telling you no, the Torah is talking that the type
of eating you do in your gates, eating you do not related
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim. your sort of non-קודש kodesh related eating, it can
be eaten anywhere, it can be eaten בטומאה, betumah, no problem. So
then something that's only eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not in your gates,
מעשר שני, besides requiring ירושלים, Yerushalayim, presumably also is not, would not
be allowed to have that type of eating בטומאה, betumah, right? That's
a clear, like that's like the thing. Eating in the gates is
בטומאה, betumah, eating in ירושלים is not בטומאה. betumah. Okay? And therefore
you know that if it becomes טמא, tamei you're not allowed to
eat it.
וקאמר רחמנא אהו דאמרי לך התם בשעריך תאכלנו, v'ka'amar Rachmana ahu de'amri
lach hatam bisharecha tochelenu,
that type of a thing that I told you in another case,
eating in your gates means the eating בטומאה, betumah, הכא לא תוכל.
hacha lo tuchal. Here you can't. So when it says לא תוכל
לאכל בשעריך מעשר דגנך, lo tuchal leechol bisharecha maaser deganecha,
it means your מעשר שני you can't eat out of ירושלים, but
you know what else it means? Don't eat your מעשר שני like
you eat things outside of ירושלים. Don't eat your מעשר שני when
it's טמא. tamei Okay, so לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך lo tuchal leechol
bisharecha doesn't just mean don't eat it outside, don't eat it in
the way you eat things outside of ירושלים, don't eat it בטומאה.
betumah. Okay, so that's how you learn that if the מעשר שני
is טמא, tamei, you're not allowed to eat it and presumably, and
then the question is whether you would learn ביכורים from מעשר שני
and apply that to ביכורים as well. Okay. מה שאין כן בתרומה.
So now we've got the, the, the ideas... the things that are
distinctive about מעשר שני and maybe ביכורים but they don't apply to
תרומה. Terumah Now the... so we're looking at the last two. The
last two is both about cases when the thing became טמא. tamei,
When the thing became... when מעשר became טמא, tamei; don't destroy it,
don't burn it, and don't eat it. Both of those by תרומה
Terumah you're allowed to burn it and get benefit from it, that's
what you're supposed to do with it, and although you're not allowed
to eat it, if you do you don't get lashes. מנלן? minalan?
Where do we know that תרומה Terumah is different? אמר רבי אבהו,
amar Rabbi Abahu,
דאמר רבי יוחנן, de'amar Rabbi Yochanan, דאמר קרא, de'amar kra, the verse
says, לא ביערתי ממנו בטמא. Right? That's where the basis of the
idea that you don't burn מעשר שני that becomes טמא. tamei. ממנו
אי אתה מבעיר, mimenu ee ata mavir, from it you can't destroy
when it's טמא, tamei. אבל אתה מבעיר שמן של תרומה שנטמא, aval
ata mavir shemen shel terumah shenitma, but oil of תרומה Terumah that
became טמא tamei? you can burn. Okay, so that's obviously a lot
of latitude how to read this. That verse ואימא ממנו אי אתה
מבעיר אבל אתה מבעיר שמן של קודש שנטמאה. V'eimah mimenu iyatah mavir
aval atah mavir shemen shel kodesh shenitmah. Why don't I say heck,
as long as it's saying just don't burn it בטומאה, b'tumah, maybe
I'll say okay, but oil of קרבנות, korbanot, of קודש, kodesh, like
I sanctified oil to use in a מנחה. mincha. If that became
טמא, tamei, maybe I should be allowed to burn that? How do
I know to allow תרומה, Terumah maybe I could allow other things,
even more
weighty
things? So ואימא ממנו אי אתה מבעיר אבל אתה מבעיר שמן של
קודש שנטמאה. V'eimah mimenu iyatah mavir aval atah mavir shemen shel kodesh
shenitmah. Someone says one minute, לאו קל וחומר הוא? lav kal vachomer
hu? It's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה מעשר הקל, Uma ma'aser
hakal, מעשר which is less, which is lighter, אמרה תורה לא ביערתי
ממנו בטמא, amrah Torah lo biarti mimenu b'tamei, you can't burn it
when it's טמא. tamei. קודש חמור לא כל שכן? Kodesh chamur lo
kol shekein? How much more so can you not do קודש. kodesh.
Someone says אי הכי תרומה נמי קל וחומר הוא? ei hachi Terumah
nami kal vachomer hu? Okay, but תרומה Terumah should also be part
of the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If you can't burn מעשר, how
could you burn תרומה? Terumah No, הכתיב ממנו. ha ktiv mimenu. No,
because it says ממנו, which means there are some things you can
burn. ומה ראית? Uma ra'ita? So you understand what we have here?
We have it very bizarre, right? Here you've got מעשר, which we
say is, which is טמא, which we say don't, right? That's לא
ביערתי,
right,
don't do it.
Okay, then we have תרומה, Terumah, which is more weighty, which we
say check, because ממנו comes to say only מעשר, not תרומה. And
then we have קדשים, kodshim, which is even weightier, which we say
again X. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says well, of course it's
got to be אסור assur because it's a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
Well, תרומה's also a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Oh well, we excluded
one thing. One thing you're allowed to do בטומאה. b'tumah. So how
do you know to exclude תרומה rather than to exclude קדשים? kodshim?
I mean of course you could say at least it's, at least
it's less weighty, but then like you're leapfrogging, it's bizarre, right? So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says okay,
הכתיב ממנו ומה ראית. ha ktiv mimenu uma ra'ita. What lets you
sort of say that we're going to take a, you know, say
תרומה is the lighter one to be, to be given this allowance,
but not קדשים? kodshim? So מסתברא קודש לא ממעטינן. mistabra kodesh lo
m'matinan. It makes sense that קדשים kodshim overall is considered much
weightier, so we're not going to be so eager to give this
leniency.
שכן, Shekein, because what do you say for קדשים, kodshim, because פנקכ"ס.
pinkakas. Okay, that's a little abbreviation of all the ways in which
קודש kodesh is more weighty than everything else. What are the ways?
פיגול, pigul, now we're going to spell out each letter. נותר, nosar,
right, only the idea of פיגול pigul and נותר nosar only applies
to קרבנות, korbanot, right, having a wrong thought when you're שוחט, when
you're מקריב makriv it, letting it stay over, you know, an extra
day then you have to burn it, that's only by קרבנות. korbanot.
קרבן, korban, it's called a קרבן, korban, which רש"י says means you
bring it in the בית המקדש. מעילה, me'ilah, if you misuse it
you transgress מעילה, me'ilah, which doesn't apply even though you can't misuse
like תרומה and whatever, מעשר, you don't get מעילה. me'ilah. כרת, kares,
if you eat them when you're טמא you get כרת. kares. Okay,
and ואסור לאונן. v'assur l'onein. It's אסור assur to an אונן. onein.
And at least תרומה is מותר muttar to an אונן. So these
are all ways in which קדשים kodshim is more weightier than תרומה.
הגמרא HaGemara says אדרבה תרומה לא ממעטינן. aderaba Terumah lo m'matinan.
Let's not exclude תרומה. Here are ways in which תרומה's weightier than
קרבנות. korbanot. שכן מחפ"ז. Shekein machpaz. What's,
what does that mean? מיתה, if you eat תרומה you're חייב מיתה
בידי שמים chayav misah b'yedei shamayim and a non-כהן. וחומש, if a
non-כהן eats it בשוגג he pays back the כהן the principal and
a fifth. ואין לה פדיון, V'ein lah pidyon, you can't redeem תרומה,
you can't transfer its קדושה, but you can transfer the קדושה of
a קרבנות korbanot if it, if it gets a
מום. mum. ואסורה לזרים, V'asurah l'zarim, and it can't be eaten by
a non-כהן, but there are some קרבנות korbanot like שלמים shlamim that
can be eaten by a non-כהן. So it, it admits that it's
going to be ironic. Okay, it's going to be אסור by מעשר
and מותר muttar by something weightier. But we'd at least like to
apply although that irony is going to be in place, we'd at
least like to apply that allowance to a, to the lighter case,
not the heavier case. So which is heavier? Is קדשים kodshim heavier
or is תרומה heavier? Why do you think קדשים kodshim is heavier
because it's got these things, well תרומה's more weighty because it's got
these other things. So the גמרא Gemara says no, הנך נפישן, hanech
nefishan, they're more, it's like six against four. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eimah,
and if you want we could hone in on one difference, כרת
עדיפא. kares adifa. This is quite fascinating. It says that כרת kares
is worse than מיתה בידי שמים. misah b'yedei shamayim. You get כרת
kares if you're טמא and you eat and you eat קרבנות, korbanot,
and you only get מיתה by and somehow כרת kares is seen
as worse than מיתה בידי שמים, misah b'yedei shamayim, which is quite
fascinating. Okay, so anyway, but that's how we come, we say yes,
it's ironic, but it really once it's אסור by מעשר to burn
it and הנאה hana'ah from it בטומאה, b'tumah, it should be אסור
by everything weightier, but something is excluded, we'll exclude תרומה and give
it a leniency because תרומה is less weighty than קדשים. kodshim. Okay,
yes.
Just remind us, what's כרת, kares,
what's the difference between כרת kares and מיתה בידי שמים? misah b'yedei
shamayim?
Yeah, I'm not exactly sure. There are big תוספותים Tosafosim that try
to figure it out.
Yes. פיגול ונותר pigul venotar could not even in theory apply to
תרומה. Correct. So how can they—well, all
right, the גמרא Gemara isn't isn't worried about that.
Yeah, according to the note. Okay.
No, it's fine.
Guys' childhood. Okay.
I don't
I don't know what to say. Okay, fine. Moving on. But that's
the point, that the תורה Torah doesn't create an opportunity for that.
All right. Moving on. So, all right.
The—so that's how you know that you have this allowance by תרומה
that you burn it and you get benefit from it. By קדשים,
Kodashim, if something becomes טמא you have to burn it, but that's
just a way of destroying it respectfully, but you don't actually benefit
from it as you're destroying it, as opposed to תרומה which you
do. Okay? But these other things you are not allowed to destroy
it בטומאה, betumah,
only תרומה. ואוכלן בטומאת עצמן לוקה מה שאין כן בתרומה. ve'ochlan betumat
atzman lokei mah she'ein kein bi'Terumah. The last one: if the thing
becomes טמא, okay fine, by תרומה we said you're allowed to burn
it and use it as fuel, but you can't eat it. Okay,
so nobody is saying that you can eat it. But there's still
a difference. By מעשר, if you eat when it's טמא, you get
lashes because that's by the לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך, lo tuchal le'echol
bish'arecha, which is a לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, which we said means
you cannot eat it like you eat things in your gate. You
can't eat it when it's טמא; it's a לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh.
By תרומה, you don't get lashes. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא says, מילקא הוא דלא לקי, milka hu d'lo laki, so
you don't get lashes by תרומה, הא איסורא איכא, ha issura ika,
you're still not allowed to eat תרומה that's טמא. So מנלן, menalan,
where do you get this from? אמר קרא, amar kra, בשעריך תאכלנו,
bish'arecha tochelenu, right? That is לזה ולא לאחר. lezeh velo l'acher. So
you get that you're not allowed to eat
תרומה בטומאה Terumah betumah because when the פסוק says by again the
קדשים Kodashim that you redeem that you eat in your gates and
you eat בטומאה, betumah, it says בשעריך תאכלנו, bish'arecha tochelenu, you should
eat it in your gate. It you eat in your gates, but
not other things. And again, gates here meaning when it's טמא. So
what are the other things that you don't eat when it's טמא?
תרומה. Okay, בשעריך תאכלנו לזה ולא לאחר. bish'arecha tochelenu lezeh velo l'acher.
This idea that the קדשים Kodashim you redeem you eat in your
gates and you eat it the way you eat it in your
gates בטומאה, betumah, that doesn't apply to other things. It doesn't apply
to תרומה. Okay. ולאו הבא מכלל עשה עשה, velav haba michlal aseh
aseh, and a negative that derives from a positive is a positive.
So since it doesn't say "don't eat תרומה in your gate," it
says "this you eat in your gate," which is interpreted to mean
"this you eat when it's טמא," we infer don't eat תרומה when
תרומה is טמא. But that's a negative that's inferred from a positive,
and therefore you would only be transgressing the positive מצוה mitzvah of
eating, and that's why you do not get lashes, but it is
forbidden. אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, מרישא נמי שמעת מינה, mereisha
nami shamat mina, דתנא ושייר. dtana v'shayer. So now, getting back to
why we brought this all in to begin with. He says, "You
know what? You don't have to go to the end of the
משנה to prove that it's an abbreviated list, that we didn't include
everything." Right? Remember again, that was the proof, that תרומה and ביכורים
are linked and מעשר are similar and מעשר is different and he
says, "Well, why wasn't ערלה Orlah on the list?" and we said,
"Well, maybe it's not a complete list." And then we looked at
the end of the משנה. So רב אשי Rav Ashi says you
don't have to go to the end of the משנה to look
at things that were left off of the list. I can even
earlier, even at the beginning of the משנה things were left off
of the list. Where do you get
it?
דתנא ושייר. dtana v'shayer. מדלא קתני, midlo ktani, top of ע"ד
ע"א, ayin daled amud aleph, ונוהגים בשאר שני שבוע. venohagim bish'ar shenei
shavua. I'll give you some things that apply to תרומה and ביכורים
that don't apply to מעשר שני. Number one: תרומה and ביכורים apply
during every year of the שמיטה Shemittah cycle. מעשר שני applies only
during year three and year six. That's a pretty big difference. Okay.
Number two: ואין להם פדיון. ve'ein lahem pidyon. תרומה and ביכורים you
can't redeem; you have to do with the thing itself. מעשר שני,
if you don't want to schlepp to ירושלים, you redeem it and
you take some money. מה שאין כן במעשר. mah she'ein kein be'Maaser.
So those are two very easy things that it could have said
and it didn't say, so you see it's not a complete list.
שמע מינה. shma mina. The גמרא says that's a good point. So
we could have saved ourselves this entire עמוד amud if he had
spoken up a little earlier. Okay, so it's not a complete list,
so you can't infer anything from the absence of ערלה. Orlah. Okay,
let's just finish this up, just read a few more lines. תא
שמע. ta shema. נשתיירו בו ציצין המעכבין את המילה. nishtayeru vo tzitzin
hame'akvin es hamilah. We got a ברייתא braisa that says that if
some of the pieces of flesh that are necessary for the ברית
מילה Brit Milah were not cut away, then is a person still
an ערל? הרי זה אינו אוכל לא בתרומה ולא בפסח ולא בקדשים
ולא במעשר. harei zeh eino ochel lo bi'Terumah velo be'Pesach velo be'Kodashim
velo be'Maaser. This person can't eat, so here's explicitly it's telling you:
here are the things an ערל is forbidden in. What can he
not eat? תרומה, פסח, Pesach, קדשים, Kodashim, and מעשר. So there's a
ברייתא braisa that explicitly says an ערל can't eat מעשר. So מאי
לאו מעשר. mai lav Maaser. does it mean מעשר *ma'aser* of grain?
No, מעשר בהמה *ma'aser behemah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* gets a way
out of it. No, it's the מעשר *ma'aser* you give from your
animals which is a קרבן *korban*, so it's another way of saying
he can't eat קדשות *kodashot*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says מעשר בהמה
*ma'aser behemah* היינו קדשים *hainu kodshim*. So we already said you can't
eat קדשים *kodshim*. So why would it say מעשר *ma'aser*? So the
גמרא *Gemara* says ולטעמיך *u-le-ta'amech*, מי לא תנן פסח ותני קדשים *mi
lo tenan Pesach ve-tani kodshim*? So the גמרא *Gemara* says so what?
The משנה *Mishnah* is a little redundant anyway. It says don't eat
פסח *Pesach* and don't eat קדשים *kodshim*. Why do you have to
say פסח *Pesach* and קדשים *kodshim*? Just say don't eat קדשים *kodshim*.
Now בשלמא פסח וקדשים צריכא *bishlama Pesach ve-kodshim tzerichah*. Had to tell
me both פסח *Pesach* and קדשים *kodshim*. Why? צריכא *tzerichah*. דאי תנא
פסח *de-ei tana Pesach*, if it had just said don't eat פסח
*Pesach*, משום דערל בפסח כתיבא *mishum de-arel be-Pesach ketivah*. That's where it's
explicit, right? It says כל ערל לא יאכל בו *kol arel lo
yokhal bo*. אבל קדשים *aval kodshim*, normal קרבנות *korbanot*, אימא לא *eima
lo*, maybe he could eat. ודאי תנא קדשים *ve-de-ei tana kodshim*, had
it just said don't eat קדשים *kodshim*, הוה אמינא מאי קדשים *hava
amina mai kodshim*, I would have interpreted the word קדשים *kodshim* to
mean פסח *Pesach*. So it had to say קדשים *kodshim* and פסח
*Pesach*, so it's clear that קדשים *kodshim* means all קרבנות *korbanot*. So
that makes sense. אלא מעשר בהמה למה לי *ela ma'aser behemah lamma
li*? So why would it have to tell you מעשר בהמה *ma'aser
behemah*? Which is obviously a very good point. מעשר *ma'aser* does not
mean מעשר בהמה *ma'aser behemah*. Okay, it already covered it with the
word קרבנות *korbanot*. So it's very clear that an ערל *arel* cannot
eat מעשר *ma'aser*. Here it's clear. The גמרא *Gemara* has another way
out of it. אלא מעשר ראשון רבי מאיר היא דאמר מעשר ראשון
אסור לזרים *ela ma'aser rishon Rabbi Meir hi de-amar ma'aser rishon asur
le-zarim*. There is a bizarre position of רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that
says the same way תרומה *trumah* a non-כהן *Kohen* can't eat, מעשר
*ma'aser* a non-לוי *Levi* cannot eat. Okay, and מעשר ראשון *ma'aser rishon*
cannot be eaten by a non-כהן *Kohen*. And therefore the גמרא *Gemara*
is saying that would make more sense because to say that an
ערל *arel* is forbidden. Okay, because look, an ערל *arel* is forbidden
by קרבנות *korbanot*, and an ערל *arel* is forbidden by תרומה *trumah*,
right? Those are the things that the eating is very like restrictive.
And although קרבנות *korbanot* sometimes are eaten by ישראל *Yisrael*, mostly they're
eaten by כהנים *Kohanim*. So the גמרא *Gemara* if it had to
pick one מעשר *ma'aser* which it would rather say an ערל *arel*
can't eat, it would rather say, I mean it's more obvious for
the גמרא *Gemara* would be מעשר ראשון *ma'aser rishon* according to רבי
מאיר *Rabbi Meir* that says it's forbidden to non-לויים *Leviyim*, because that's
more similar like the idea of restricting the people that can eat
it. It's more similar to the idea of תרומה *trumah* and קדשים
*kodshim*. Okay, so we have a ברייתא *braita* that pretty explicitly says
that an ערל *arel* can't eat מעשר *ma'aser*. But the גמרא *Gemara*'s
concluding at least saying that that might not be מעשר שני *ma'aser
sheni*, we might rather say it's a רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* position
of מעשר ראשון *ma'aser rishon* that treats it somewhat like תרומה *trumah*,
and that says that a non-לוי *Levi* can't eat מעשר ראשון *ma'aser
rishon*, which is a very bizarre position, but that is what it
is sort of at least saying that it's not conclusive that an
ערל *arel* cannot eat מעשר שני *ma'aser sheni*. Stay more on the
גמרא
*Gemara*.
Alright, they had the first bit...
yeah, it's not just the arel-ishness...
right?
Because Rabbi...