Good morning. Okay, so today's דף daf is today's דף daf is
כ"ז. Chof Zayin. We are very short, we are an עמוד amud
behind but a very short עמוד, amud, so here's hoping we catch
up. We pick up at the very bottom of כ"ו עמוד א'
Chof Vav Amud Aleph and we are discussing this משנה Mishnah here
about the four brothers and neither brother can do ייבום yibum because
it's אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, משנה Mishnah we've had a couple times.
Each does חליצה, chalitzah, but then we had the alternative explanation of
the משנה, Mishnah, which is that the real problem is אסור לבטל
מצות יבמין. assur levatel mitzvas yabmin. That if לוי Levi goes ahead
and does ייבום yibum with רחל, Rochel, then we're afraid that יהודה
Yehuda will die. לאה Leah will wind up being אחות אשתו, achos
ishto, she can't get either חליצה chalitzah or ייבום, yibum, and therefore
we have לוי Levi do חליצה chalitzah so that even if יהודה
Yehuda dies, לוי Levi would still be able to go ahead and
do חליצה chalitzah with לאה. Leah. All right, so let's take a
look now as the גמרא Gemara picks up with that on the
bottom of כ"ו עמוד א'. Chof Vav Amud Aleph. The גמרא Gemara
says like this, two lines from the bottom, אי הכי I hachi
if that's true says the גמרא, Gemara, that the concern is אסור
לבטל מצות יבמין, assur levatel mitzvas yabmin, תלתא נמי tlosa nami why
did it have to give a case of four brothers? Why not
give a case of three brothers? If the issue was the issue
problem of אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, so we understand yes is it
true with three brothers as well sure. לוי Levi can't do ייבום
yibum with either woman because of אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, he has
to do חליצה chalitzah with both women, fine. But there's a חידוש
chidush of talking about four brothers because the זיקה zika is weaker
if there are two brothers left behind. If both לוי Levi and
יהודה Yehuda have a זיקה, zika, there's more of a reason to
argue that it's not a problem of אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso because
it's not necessarily לוי's Levi זיקה zika not necessarily יהודה's Yehuda זיקה.
zika. So there's a חידוש chidush of four brothers that there's a
problem of אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso even with two brothers, even with
two remaining brothers. But if it's the idea of אסור לבטל מצות
יבמין, assur levatel mitzvas yabmin, then even with three it's a problem,
because let's say לוי, Levi, because then what will happen, then you
don't even need the possibility that יהודה Yehuda will die. Then לוי
Levi shouldn't go ahead and do ייבום yibum with רחל Rochel because
he leaves לאה Leah out cold. If he does ייבום yibum with
רחל, Rochel, לאה Leah becomes אשת איש, eshes ishto, אחות אשתו achos
ishto and no ייבום, yibum, no חליצה. chalitzah. So even with three
brothers the הלכה halacha should be לוי Levi can't do ייבום yibum
because he'll be מבטל מצות יבמין mevatel mitzvas yabmin with the other
sister. So the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי תלתא נמי? I hachi
tlosa nami? So the גמרא Gemara says לא מיבעיא קאמר, lo mibaya
ka'mar, you're right, but that's more obvious. לא מיבעיא תלתא דקא מבטל
מצות יבמין Lo mibaya tlosa devari batel mitzvas yabmin if there are
three and לוי's Levi the only one left behind, of course he
can't do ייבום yibum with רחל Rochel because לאה Leah is left
out. אלא אבל ארבע Ela aval arba but four, even if לוי
Levi does ייבום yibum with רחל, Rochel, most likely יהודה Yehuda will
still be alive to do either ייבום yibum or חליצה chalitzah with
לאה. Leah. So that's a חידוש chidush that I'm concerned that יהודה's
Yehuda going to drop dead. אבל ארבע למיתה לא חיישינן, Aval arba
lemisa lo chashinan, I would say I wouldn't be concerned that יהודה
Yehuda would drop dead, קא משמע לן kamashmalan that I am. אי
הכי I hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, that's what's going on says
about אסור לבטל מצות יבמין, assur levatel mitzvas yabmin,
חמישה נמי? chamisha nami? So why don't you tell me, where's my
pen?
We got here יששכר. Yissachar. Okay, so why don't I say what
about this case, three are left behind. Can לוי Levi do ייבום?
yibum? לוי Levi will do ייבום yibum with רחל, Rochel, maybe יהודה
Yehuda and יששכר Yissachar will die. Okay? How far am I going
to go with it? So the גמרא Gemara finally says no, you
know what, we're not going to go that far. למיתה דתרי לא
חיישינן, Lemisa detrei lo chashinan, we're not going to be afraid that
two people will die.
One in a million that two people will drop dead at the
same time.
Exactly. So before anyone of them gets a chance to do ייבום
yibum or חליצה. chalitzah. So yes, it's pretty far-fetched, this concern that
one of them will drop dead and then and then I mean
how big a deal is it that לאה Leah won't get ייבום
yibum or חליצה chalitzah if she winds up being freed from the
obligation anyway?
But right exactly, but anyway we're only concerned that one will drop
dead not two. So yes it's obvious if there's only לוי, Levi,
then לאה Leah immediately loses the מצות, mitzvas, you know the מצות
יבמין mitzvas yabmin goes away. Even if there's one around, we're afraid
he'll drop dead and that then we'll lose that opportunity. But with
two already we won't be afraid.
Okay.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא בר הונא אמר רב: Rava bar
Huna amar Rav: שלוש אחיות יבמות שנפלו לפני שני אחים יבמים. Shalosh
achayos yevamos shenaplu lifnei shenei achim yevamim. Okay, so
back to two surviving brothers except we have now three sisters. Okay,
I don't know who we're going to call רחל Rochel and לאה's
Leah sister.
בלהה, Bilhah, no that's confusing.
Okay, anyway well I don't know, we'll just call her שרה. Sarah.
Okay fine. Then you have fine. Then you have down here יששכר
Yissachar and זבולון. Zevulun. Okay,
so we'll just for... So just pretend that all these three are
sisters, okay? שרה's Sarah רחל Rachel and לאה's Leah sister. Now, three,
I'm sorry. So yeah, three sisters and right,
so now they and then all of the... all of these guys
died. And now you have two brothers and they have three sisters,
each of which they have a מצוה mitzvah of... a זיקה zikah
to, a מצוה ייבום mitzvah yibum to, right? And there's no ערוה
ervah because they were... they're sisters to... they're sisters and they were
married to different men, but to them none of them is אסור,
asur, okay? But any act of ייבום yibum if you hold יש
זיקה, yesh zikah, any act of ייבום yibum is אחות זקוקתו. achot
zikukato. So it's just a bigger case of אחות זקוקתו, achot zikukato,
but that there's three women to deal with. So the question is,
when there are two women, we know what you do. One does
חליצה chalitzah with one, right? And one does חליצה chalitzah with the
other. Now let me just remind you, why did when there were
two women, why didn't יששכר Issachar go ahead and do... well actually
it doesn't say that he can't. Wait, what did it say? Hold
on. It says הרי אלו חולצות, harei elu chotzot, right? It doesn't
say that they have to do with two. We haven't even discussed,
that's what we're going to get into, but in the case of
let's say two, could יששכר Issachar do חליצה chalitzah with both? We
don't see why not, right? Why not let יששכר Issachar do חליצה
chalitzah with both? Okay. So, therefore,
so, so but now we're going to see what the story's going
to be with this case and how this is going to divide
up. Hold on, let me just make sure I'm giving you it
straight one second. Give it one second.
In
principle... wait a minute...
one minute...
in principle,
right, one minute, in principle, now I'm getting confused, actually we had
this, we had this, right? In principle, in this case,
hold on a
second... one second... help me remember guys. In principle in this case,
where you had two, right? Okay, so we'll do יששכר Issachar and
זבולון Zebulun again. Okay.
Okay, so
יששכר Issachar does חליצה chalitzah with רחל, Rachel, right? So he cannot
do ייבום yibum with לאה Leah because that would be אחות חלוצתו.
achot chalutzato. And he can't do... and he can't... so he does
חליצה chalitzah with לאה. Leah. But why can't זבולון Zebulun do ייבום
yibum with לאה, Leah, right?
We talked about it.
Oh, he can't. Oh, they actually... that's actually the point is that
if actually רחל Rachel had חליצה chalitzah done first and then שמעון
Shimon died, then he can, then it's not זיקתו zikato or חלוצתו.
chalutzato. The point is is that if both of them were around...
well actually anyway...
except that he did at one point
have a זיקה, zikah, but then the זיקה zikah went away. Anyway
we're going to get back to that, okay? About that case that
maybe that, you know, to what degree maybe should לאה Leah be
able to do it with... yeah we actually had that, that they
flip over and they do it with the other one, so actually
we had that. Okay, but so it's interesting therefore that our משנה
Mishnah says חולצות ולא מתייבמות chotzot velo mityabmot
because in theory there could be a way we actually had that
that one does חליצה chalitzah and the other winds up doing ייבום,
yibum, we'd have to have that there. All right, for some reason
that's not in the משנה, Mishnah, it just occurred to me that
that's not in the משנה. Mishnah.
Anyway, now we're dealing with it that you've got three.
Okay, so what's going to happen? So let's take a look. All
right, so until now we don't know that it matters who's doing
the חליצה chalitzah and as I said it's even possible that if
one does the חליצה chalitzah the other might be able to do
the ייבום yibum but let's take a look. Okay, אמר רבא בר
רב הונא אמר רב שלש אחיות יבמות שנפלו לפני שני
אחים יבמים זה חולץ לאחת וזה חולץ לאחת ואמצעית צריכה חליצה משניהם.
Amar Rava bar Rav Huna amar Rav shalosh achayot yevamot shenafelu lifnei
shnei achim yevamim zeh choletz leachot vezeh choletz leachot ve'emtza'it tzerichah chalitzah
mishneihem. So one gets חליצה chalitzah from one, one gets חליצה chalitzah
from the other and the middle one, which really means the last
one, not the middle one, gets the חליצה chalitzah from both of
them. Now, the way we'll spell out this case is in the
גמרא, Gemara, the case is going to be that we're talking about
that they did it sort of as they were dying, or whatever,
meaning I don't mean literally as each brother was dying. Okay, and
the reason it's going to be sort of called... so here's what
happened, okay, and here's יששכר Issachar and זבולון. Zebulun. So the
גמרא Gemara will say, as ראובן Reuven dies, so ראובן Reuven dies,
יששכר Issachar does חליצה chalitzah with רחל. Rachel.
Then שמעון Shimon dies and זבולון Zebulun does חליצה chalitzah with לאה.
Leah.
We're going to do ייבום. yibum.
Well yeah, that's what we were discussing, but for now...
were those brothers all four...
yeah, all five of them are brothers, okay.
Right, okay, and they...
and then לוי Levi dies and then שרה Sarah needs חליצה chalitzah
from both of them. The reason she's called middle, so to speak,
even though she's last, is in a way she's like in the
middle of יששכר. Issachar. and זבולון. Zevulun. Okay, so she's like caught
between them and she gets חליצה chalitzah from both. So the question
is, why does she need חליצה chalitzah from both and why is
there a preference that זבולון Zevulun does חליצה chalitzah to לאה Leah
rather than יששכר? Yissachar?
Why does she need חליצה? chalitzah?
We'll discuss. Well what do you mean why she needs חליצה chalitzah
at all?
Because they're all sisters.
You mean why can't she get
יבום? yibum? No, okay because of because of אחות חלוצתו achos chalutzaso
that's only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. No, they all need
חליצה chalitzah here. All need חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, but anyway, so it's
אחות חלוצתו, achos chalutzaso, but anyway the point is why does, a,
is there a preference for זבולון Zevulun to do
חליצה chalitzah to לאה Leah rather than יששכר, Yissachar, and why do
both of them get חליצה, chalitzah, and why does שרה Sarah need
חליצה chalitzah from both of them?
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, they do חליצה, chalitzah, no, she does.
All right, all right, because that's because we're talking about who needs
to do it. All right, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. So it's going to spell out what the logic is between
this. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei
Rava, מדקאמרת אמצעי צריכה חליצה משתיהם, mideka'amret emtza'i tzericha chalitzah mishteihem, since
you're saying that the middle, the last one, needs חליצה chalitzah from
both of them, קסבר יש זיקה. kasavar yeish zika. Presumably you hold
the problem here is יש זיקה. yeish zika. Now, you תוספות Tosfos
are saying how do you know, maybe this could work within the
idea of אסור לבטל מצות יבומין? asur l'vattel mitzvas yibumin?
We're not going to unpack that. But this is working within the
assumption of יש זיקה. yeish zika. והוה לה חליצה פסולה. v'hava lah
chalitzah pesulah. And now I understand what's bothering you. What's bothering you
is that it's an invalid חליצה, chalitzah, which doesn't mean invalid, it
means like a less than full חליצה, chalitzah, דחליצה פסולה צריך לחזור
על כל האחין. d'chalitzah pesulah tzarich lachzor al kol ha'achin. And a
less than full חליצה, chalitzah, you need to get it from all
the brothers, not just one brother. So this is... shh... this is
a new principle that you have to know that's going to guide
us throughout today's דף daf and also we'll encounter in an ongoing
way, which is an idea that we know if there are six
wives, right? Guy dies, six wives, you do יבום yibum or חליצה
chalitzah with one of them, then you're done. All of the other
ones are free, right? Don't need חליצה, chalitzah, don't need יבום, yibum,
you're not allowed to do יבום yibum with them. It's done once
you do it with one wife. Okay,
but let's say for some reason there is a weaker זיקה zika
with one of the women. Why would that be? So, let's take
a scenario. Here's like a, here are some possible scenarios. One is
one of the wives of these six wives is אחות זקוקתו. achos
zekukaso. If she was really your wife's אחות אשתו, achos ishto, then
she'd be an ערוה ervah and everybody would be פטור patur and
you'd go home. But she's not אחות אשתו, achos ishto, it's a
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. She's אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. So with this one of
these six wives, you have a slightly weaker connection because rabbinically that's
problematic. In that type of a case, okay, if you go ahead
and do the חליצה chalitzah with that woman, then she actually needs
חליצה chalitzah from all the brothers because the relationship with her, since
the relationship is weaker—I shouldn't have introduced the co-wives, I'm jumping into
another case—but let's just take one woman. ראובן Reuven died.
Let's take another one. Let's get back to the top of the
board in a minute. ראובן Reuven here is married to רחל. Rachel.
Okay, and there's לוי Levi and יהודה. Yehudah.
ראובן Reuven died. If for some reason the זיקה zika here is
a weaker זיקה, zika, okay, then we say the act of חליצה
chalitzah from one brother doesn't totally free her. Because the act is
weaker because—it's a little ironic—because the relationship is weaker, the חליצה chalitzah
is also weaker and less meaningful and it has to be gotten
from all the brothers. So what would be a case that that
relationship is weaker? So תוספות Tosfos summarizes it nicely. If you look
at the end of this תוספות Tosfos here, וחליצה פסולה צריך לחזור,
v'chalitzah pesulah tzarich lachzor, you see there's a little ב' beis about
two-thirds down in that תוספות, Tosfos, a little ב' beis in square
brackets. Do you see that? Yep.
Okay. אלא נראה לרי דלא חשיבא חליצה פסולה אלא אחות זקוקתו למאן
דאמר יש זיקה. Ela nireh l'ri d'lo chashiva chalitzah pesulah ela achos
zekukaso l'man d'amar yeish zika. Okay, either רחל Rachel here is an
אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, so for some reason they've got some other
woman here that, you know,
they've got לאה Leah here that they also have a זיקה zika
to, so that makes רחל Rachel into an אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso,
not a real ערוה ervah but a quasi-ערוה, ervah, quasi-אחות אשתו. achos
ishto. או אחות חלוצתו, O achos chalutzaso,
or they did חליצה chalitzah to לאה, Leah, so רחל Rachel is
אחות חלוצתו, achos chalutzaso, לכולי עלמא. l'chulei alma. ובעלת הגט ובעלת מאמר.
U'ba'alas haget u'ba'alas ma'amar. And
we'll see that in a minute. Let's say for some reason, ironically,
you already started the process of doing חליצה chalitzah with רחל. Rachel.
Now, what does it mean started the process? You gave רחל Rachel
a גט. get. Now, what does a גט get mean? We're supposed
to do חליצה. chalitzah. גט get isn't meaningful. But we're going to
find out that if you give a woman a גט get in
the—you know, that was a woman that you were supposed to do
חליצה chalitzah and instead you gave her a גט, get, you make
it impossible now to do יבום. yibum. It wasn't needed, nobody demanded
it, but it has enough weight that it makes it impossible to
do יבום. yibum. You go and you do חליצה, chalitzah, because חליצה
chalitzah is the... Wait, what does a גט get mean? We're supposed
to do חליצה, chalitza, גט get isn't meaningful. But we're going to
find out that if you give a woman a גט get in
the, you know, that this was a woman that you were supposed
to do חליצה chalitza and instead you gave her a גט, get,
you make it impossible now to do יבום. yibum. It wasn't needed,
nobody demanded it, but it has enough weight that it makes it
impossible to do יבום. yibum. You go and you do חליצה chalitza
because חליצה chalitza is דאורייתא. de'oraisa. גט get in this case is
only rabbinic. It wasn't even asked for, but if you did it,
you—so if they gave a גט get to רחל, Rochel, right, now
the act because, ironically,
the relationship is weaker. They can't do יבום yibum because the relationship
is weaker. The act of חליצה chalitza is now less meaningful. So
in all those cases, and we'll see more of them later, if
there's a weaker זיקה, zika, the act of חליצה chalitza is less
meaningful and therefore she has to get it from all the existing
brothers. Okay, so that is the principle of
חליצה פסולה chalitza pesula חזור על כל האחין. chazor al kol ha'achin.
Okay, so now here's what we're going to say. So that's going
to explain why שרה Sarah needs a חליצה chalitza from both because
what is שרה Sarah to each of them? אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzaso.
Each one did חליצה chalitza with a different woman. שרה Sarah is
אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzaso. וחלוצה לזבולון היא לאה, vechalutza leZvulun hi Leah,
so she's אחות לאה. achos Leah. וחלוצה ליששכר היא רחל, vechalutza leYissacher
hi Rochel, she's אחות רחל. achos Rochel. So she is אחות חלוצתו,
achos chalutzaso, she needs a חליצה chalitza from both. But then the
גמרא's Gemara question is, but why does רחל Rochel need a חליצה
chalitza from both? Because רחל Rochel is אחות זיקוקתו. achos zikukaso. Right?
So she also has a weaker relationship and she'll need a חליצה
chalitza from both. So let's take a look. Okay, wait, because no,
no, we're going to read it and then I'm just going to
read two more lines and then you'll have your question. Okay. אי
הכי ei hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, קמייתא נמי.
kameisa nami. So רחל Rochel and לאה Leah should also need two
חליצות chalitzos because it's אחות זיקוקתו achos zikukaso for all the brothers.
So it must be, you know what? אי דנפלו בבת אחת הכי
נמי. ei denafelu bevbas achas hachi nami. If ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon,
ולוי Levi all died at the same time, you're right. Then every
woman is אחות זיקוקתו achos zikukaso and they each need two חליצות.
chalitzos. But הכא במאי עסקינן? hacha bemai askinan? What are we talking
about? הכא נמי, hacha nami, לא צריכא דנפלו זו אחר זו. lo
tzericha denafelu zu achar zu. So that's why I laid it out
for you, they died sequentially. So נפלה חדא חלצה לה ראובן. nefla
chada chaltza lah Reuven.
So when—so it's talking about these here is ראובן Reuven and שמעון,
Shimon, so I'm sorry, not that, let's keep the גמרא's Gemara nomenclature.
We'll do that, this is יששכר, Yissacher, זבולון, Zvulun, and who? And
נפתלי. Naftali. Okay, fine. So, okay, and this is ראובן Reuven and
שמעון. Shimon. Okay. So the first guy died, so רחל, Rochel, total
total obligation. No other sister, full זיקה, zika, so that's a total
חליצה. chalitza. It's not a חליצה פסולה, chalitza pesula, it's a complete
חליצה. chalitza. Now after that happened, then זבולון Zvulun died. So what's
לאה? Leah? So with ראובן, Reuven, what's לאה Leah to ראובן? Reuven?
אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzaso. So vis-a-vis ראובן, Reuven, if ראובן Reuven were
to do חליצה, chalitza, it would be a חליצה פסולה. chalitza pesula.
But what's she to שמעון? Shimon? Not אחות חלוצתו achos chalutzaso and
not אחות זיקוקתו achos zikukaso because the זיקה zika has been removed.
So therefore שמעון Shimon does it and she only needs one because
it's a completely acceptable חליצה chalitza that she got from שמעון. Shimon.
Okay, but then by the time now that נפתלי Naftali dies, שרה
Sarah is אחות חלוצתו achos chalutzaso of both of them. And therefore
any חליצה chalitza done to her is a חליצה פסולה chalitza pesula
and therefore she needs to get it from all the brothers.
Okay, so לא צריכא דנפלו זו אחר זו. lo tzericha denafelu zu
achar zu. נפלה חדא חלצה לה ראובן. nefla chada chaltza lah Reuven.
נפלה אידך, nefla idach, then the next one died, חלצה לה שמעון.
chaltza lah Shimon. So שמעון Shimon did חליצה chalitza with לאה. Leah.
So that was also completely okay. לאה Leah was not אחות חלוצתו,
achos chalutzaso, not אחות זיקוקתו achos zikukaso because רחל Rochel had already
been taken care of and so that was a total 100% חליצה.
chalitza. He could have even done יבום yibum we discussed, right? If
he wanted to he could have done יבום yibum in that case.
So נפלה אידך, nefla idach, then finally the third one becomes available
whatever,
then חלץ להאי ומפקי זיקתיה חלץ להאי ומפקי זיקתיה. chalatz lehai mafki
zikasei chalatz lehai mafki zikasei. Each one has to do a חליצה
chalitza to remove the זיקה, zika, but each חליצה chalitza is a
weaker חליצה chalitza because it is a case of אחות חלוצתו achos
chalutzaso and that's why she needs it from both of them. Now
what were the questions?
Yeah.
Did you mention a גט get from a זיקה zika bond?
Yeah, a גט get has a דרבנן derabbanan
effect that it prevents, it doesn't free the woman, but it prevents
doing יבום. yibum.
So for whatever reason if a man wanted to, I don't know
why, maybe the woman was anxious that he was going to do
יבום yibum and whatever it was, but he decides to give a
גט, get, he locks out his possibility of doing יבום yibum rather
than doing חליצה.
chalitza.
Then he has to do חליצה, chalitza, right?
Oh then he does.
Yeah exactly, yeah.
Just one restatement of cases. In other words, a זיקה, zika, she's
אחות זיקוקתו achos zikukaso is a type of ערוה, erva, correct? דרבנן.
derabbanan. דרבנן. derabbanan. Yeah. So in normal cases of יבום yibum or
חליצה, chalitza, the wife normally would have been an ערוה, erva, the
husband died, the brother marries her.
You mean a standard אשת אח? eishesh ach? Yeah. Correct.
So just remind me, why isn't the same principle operative?
Because that's the first משנה, mishna, what the גמרא Gemara said, which
is although we are מתיר mattir the איסור issur of... ערוות אח,
ervas ach, all the other ערוות ervas create obstacles, and that's the
first משנה, mishna, and that's why any other ערווה, erva, she's פטור
pattur and the צרות tzaras are פטור. pattur.
So this is a spin-off
דרבנן derabbanan of אחות אשה. achos isha.
Exactly. Our paradigm is still being developed.
Exactly, it's a type of an אחות אשה. achos isha. It's a
different ערווה. erva. The ערווה erva of אשת אחותו eshes achoso is
the only one that יבום yibbum takes care of. You had a
question?
So would you define חליצה פסולה chalitza pesula as a חליצה chalitza
that takes place in a situation where there could not be יבום?
yibbum?
So that is what רש״י Rashi says. So if you look at
רש״י, Rashi, רש״י Rashi says, תוספות Tosafot is a little bit more
precise. רש״י Rashi says about eight lines, ten lines
down in the narrow lines, the line starting with the word כלומר,
klomar, רש״י Rashi says, כלומר גרועה או חלוצה דמי פסולה, klomar gerua
o chalutza demi pesula, but it means second-rate, שאי אם רצה ליבם
אינו יכול. she'im ratza leyabbem eino yachol. Okay? So it's exactly what
you said, Jonathan. It means in a case where יבום yibbum is
not possible. תוספות Tosafot says that that's a little bit too broad
of a definition. It's sort of like, you know, what was it
when Einstein came and corrected Newton? Like, it wasn't that Newton was
wrong, it was just he didn't, it was a little imprecise. Okay?
So, yes, it's true that all the cases of חליצה פסולה chalitza
pesula is when יבום yibbum is impossible. But תוספות Tosafot says there
are cases where יבום yibbum is impossible that we wouldn't call חליצה
פסולה. chalitza pesula. So it has to be a specific scenario that
the reason יבום yibbum is impossible is because there's something weaker or
that's been problematized about the זיקה. zika. In that there could be
a scenario where you don't do it for other reasons and that
wouldn't fall in this category. Okay? But if it's easier to think
about רש״י׳ס Rashi's reason, that's a general, that's a general way to
cover it, okay? But it's a little imprecise. Alright, so let's take
a look now as the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this: ואמר רב, va'amar Rav, and doesn't רב Rav
say אין זיקה? ein zika? How could this whole thing is explained
now because of this idea of חליצה פסולה צריך לחזור על כל
האחים? chalitza pesula tzarich lachzor al kol ha'achim? It has to do
with an issue of זיקה zika and אחות זיקוקתו achos zikukoso and
אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzato. But רב Rav is the one who says
it and רב Rav says אין זיקה, ein zika, that we're not
afraid, we don't worry about זיקה, zika, and we don't worry about,
meaning obviously there is this concept but we don't call, create problems
like אחות זיקוקתו. achos zikukoso. So he wouldn't have any of those
issues. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, לדברי אומר יש זיקה קאמר.
ledivrei omer yesh zika ka'amar. Okay, he was saying according to the
approach of יש זיקה. yesh zika. Maybe this is not his personal
approach, but according to that approach, that would be the הלכה halacha
here. Fine, that's רב׳ס Rav's position. ושמואל אמר, u'Shmuel amar, now what
does שמואל Shmuel say you do in this scenario? אחד חולץ לכולן.
echad choletz lekullan. שמואל Shmuel says, I don't buy any of this.
Let ראובן Reuven go ahead and do חליצה chalitza to all three
women. Okay? So, he presumably does not hold of the problem of
חליצה פסולה, chalitza pesula, right? Because ראובן, Reuven, as soon as זבולון
Zevulun dies, לאה Leah is אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzato. He says, who
cares? Let him do it. Then נפתלי Naftali dies, שרה Sara is
אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzato. Let ראובן Reuven do it. You don't prefer,
a) you don't have to go to all the other brothers, and
b) you don't prefer the stronger חליצה, chalitza, you can even do
the weaker חליצה. chalitza. Okay? Do you understand? It's weaker because it's
been problematized for ראובן Reuven and not for שמעון. Shimon. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara says, that's שמואל. Shmuel. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: מכדי, michdi,
one minute, let's take a look. שמעינן ליה לשמואל דאמר חליצה מעליא
בעינן. shaminon lei le'Shmuel de'amar chalitza ma'alya bi'inan. We know that שמואל
Shmuel normally says you need a good חליצה. chalitza. Now of course
everybody says you need a good חליצה. chalitza. But again it means
a, you need a higher rate חליצה. chalitza. If you can choose
between a what רש״י Rashi called a גרוע, gerua, a second-rate חליצה,
chalitza, or a first-rate חליצה, chalitza, you'll always prefer the first rate,
okay? And here, as soon as זבולון Zevulun dies, even forget the
idea of צריך לחזור על כל האחים. tzarich lachzor al kol ha'achim.
Forget צריך לחזור. tzarich lachzor. Let's assume only one חליצה. chalitza. Whose
חליצה chalitza would you rather לאה Leah get? ראובן׳ס Reuven's חליצה chalitza
or שמעון׳ס Shimon's חליצה? chalitza? שמעון׳ס Shimon's חליצה chalitza is first rate,
because שמעון׳ס Shimon's relationship was full, he could do יבום, yibbum, whereas
ראובן Reuven couldn't do יבום. yibbum. It's אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzato. So
even forgetting how many חליצות chalitzas you need, shouldn't we prefer a
first-rate חליצה chalitza over a second rate? And we know that שמואל
Shmuel holds that. How do you know that שמואל Shmuel holds that?
דאמר שמואל, de'amar Shmuel, כ״ו ע״א, kaf-vav amud aleph, see that only
those three lines only took us a half hour, דאמר שמואל חלץ
לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות. de'amar Shmuel chalatz l'achayos lo nifteru tzarot. Okay,
so you have a case of, okay, this is what I was
getting a little confused with before. You have a case of,
again,
here's יששכר Yissachar and זבולון Zevulun on this side because the גמרא
Gemara winds up using ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon as the surviving
brothers. Okay? So, you have a case of, he's married to רחל,
Rachel, and he married to לאה, Leah, and רחל Rachel also has
a co-wife called דבורה, Devorah, and she has a co-wife called, what
should she be called? נעמי, Naomi, thank you. Thank you, somebody from
a different section of תנ״ך. Tanach. Okay. So, okay, so basically, so
those two,
so and there's only one other guy left, ראובן. Reuven. Okay, we
don't have to worry about two brothers. These two guys die. Okay,
so here's the הלכה. halakha.
חלץ לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות. Chalatz l'achayot lo niftaru tzarot. If ראובן...
Reuven... can ראובן Reuven do let's start this way, this is now
these four women that are in front of ראובן. Reuven. Can he
do יבום yibum with רחל? Rachel? No, because רחל Rachel is אחות
זקוקתו, achot zekukato, right? And he can't do יבום yibum with לאה.
Leah. Now, can he do יבום yibum with דבורה? Devora? Well, it's
a little bit better, but if we're going to call אחות זקוקתו
achot zekukato sort of like אחות אשתו, achot ishto, then she's going
to be like sort of like צרת ערווה, tzarat erva, right? Okay,
but it is one degree removed. This is already a quasi, you
know, ערווה, erva, and this is one degree removed. So even though
he can't do יבום yibum with דבורה, Devora, his relationship with דבורה
Devora is stronger than his relationship with רחל. Rachel. Okay. So in
this case, if he were to do חליצה chalitza with רחל, Rachel,
which is the weaker חליצה, chalitza, that's the סוג ב', sug bet,
okay, second rate חליצה, chalitza, דבורה Devora doesn't get off the hook.
But because... but because it was only a second rate חליצה. chalitza.
But if he did the חליצה chalitza with דבורה, Devora, which is
a relatively first rate, not a... okay, it's a better חליצה, chalitza,
then רחל Rachel does get off the hook. So that shows that
there is a preference for a first rate over a second rate,
and a first rate is more powerful. A first rate will get
the צרה tzara off the hook, whereas a second rate will not.
And therefore, we should assume that he would here, ראובן Reuven should
not, we should not allow the second rate חליצה, chalitza, we should
demand the first rate.
The חליצה chalitza with דבורה Devora would be stronger because ראובן's Reuven
connection with דבורה Devora is weaker?
No, because the איסור issur to דבורה Devora is weaker.
In fact, the איסור issur is weaker.
Right. So the connection is stronger. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. דאורייתא De'oraita makes a difference. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: חלץ לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות. Chalatz l'achayot lo niftaru
tzarot. So therefore, but the reverse would be if it was חלץ
לצרות נפטרו אחיות. Chalatz l'tzarot niftaru achayot. So the weaker חליצה chalitza
is less powerful. And if the weaker חליצה chalitza is less powerful,
here שמעון Shimon should be the one doing חליצה chalitza to לאה.
Leah. We shouldn't let ראובן Reuven do חליצה chalitza to לאה. Leah.
That's a, that's a weaker חליצה. chalitza. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this:
So היכא דקיימא חליצה דשמעון חליצה כשרה חליץ ליה ראובן חליצה פסולה?
Heicha d'kayma chalitza d'Shimon chalitza kishera chalitz lei Reuven chalitza pesula? So
if שמעון Shimon could do a top rate חליצה, chalitza, we're going
to let ראובן Reuven do a second rate חליצה? chalitza? So the
גמרא Gemara says, alright, that was a pretty good question. So when
שמואל Shmuel said we're going to reread שמואל Shmuel radically and then
when we go back to the original reading. Okay, but here's first
the radical reread of שמואל. Shmuel. When שמואל Shmuel said one brother
does חליצה chalitza to all of them, when he said מאי אחד
חולץ לכולן נמי דקאמר? Mai echad choletz l'chulan nami d'ka'amar? אמצעית. Emtzait.
He didn't really mean one brother does חליצה chalitza to all of
them. What he meant was that he was just arguing on the
idea that צרה tzara needed two חליצות. chalitzot. Okay, so he agrees,
ראובן Reuven did it with רחל, Rachel, שמעון Shimon did חליצה chalitza
with לאה, Leah, but when he says one brother does it with
all, he didn't mean all, all. He meant by the time you
get to שרה, Sarah, one brother is enough, you don't need it
from both brothers. Okay, so he's just arguing on the idea that
you could ever invent, you would ever need it from multiple brothers.
Okay, so he was saying yes, here you prefer the higher level
חליצה, chalitza, but by the time you get to שרה Sarah and
either brother is going to get a, give her a סוג ב'
sug bet חליצה, chalitza, she doesn't need it from both, one brother
is enough. Okay, so that's all he was arguing on, you don't
need from both, one brother is enough. So the גמרא, Gemara, that's
not what he said, and that's what the גמרא Gemara is going
to say. Okay, והא כולן קאמר? V'ha kulan ka'amar? It says one
brother does it for all of them, okay, and you're just saying
שמעון Shimon just did it for the last two. So the גמרא
Gemara says, כיון דרובא גביה, Keivan d'rubba gabei, since שמעון Shimon did
it for two out of the three, קרי ליה כולן. karie lei
kulan. Okay, fine. Okay, now that's a weak answer, but at least
what it has you doing is saying that שמואל Shmuel might be
debating the idea that if you get a סוג ב' sug bet
חליצה, chalitza, you need it from all the brothers. And maybe he's
just saying no, you know, maybe just one brother is enough. That's
a reread of שמואל. Shmuel. But now I'm going to go back
to the original read, that ראובן Reuven can do it with all
of them. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, if I want I'll say, כי
קאמר שמואל חליצה מעליא בעינן, Ki ka'amar Shmuel chalitza ma'alya ba'inan, when
is שמואל Shmuel say in this case that you need
the top grade חליצה chalitza in order to get דבורה Devora off
the hook? Right, this is a סוג ב' sug bet חליצה chalitza
and this is a סוג א' sug aleph חליצה, chalitza, and you
need the סוג א' sug aleph חליצה chalitza here. The סוג א'
sug aleph חליצה chalitza gets רחל Rachel off the hook, the סוג
ב' sug bet does not get רחל Rachel off the hook. So
he clearly prefers the סוג א' sug aleph חליצה. chalitza. So when
is that true? כי קאמר שמואל חליצה מעליא בעינן הני מילי למפתר
צרתה. Ki ka'amar Shmuel chalitza ma'alya ba'inan hani mili l'miptar tzarata. Yes,
if you need to get a co-wife off the hook, then top
grade חליצה chalitza is needed. אבל למפתר נפשה, Aval l'miptar nafsha, for
it to be effective for the woman itself, פטרה, patra, that's enough
to have even a second rate חליצה. chalitza. So שמואל Shmuel does
not... the top. So שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel does not say that
you always must do the top-grade חליצה. chalitzah. שמואל Shmuel says a
lower-grade חליצה chalitzah doesn't get the wife off the hook, the co-wife
off the hook. The top-grade חליצה chalitzah gets the co-wife off the
hook. But here שמואל's Shmuel saying, you know what? Shimon can go
ahead and do all three. Okay? Yes. Is this a
second-grade חליצה chalitzah to Leah? Sure. But Leah doesn't have any co-wives.
Okay? So שמואל Shmuel actually says, I don't have a problem with
a second-grade חליצה chalitzah as long as there are no co-wives. So
he can do it here and then yes you could have had
a better חליצה chalitzah here, but let him do the second-grade חליצה
chalitzah and everybody's fine. Which has him saying two things: A, you
can use a second-grade חליצה chalitzah even if you have a, you
can allow for that even if you have the option of a
top grade; and B, he doesn't hold חליצה פסולה צריך להחזיר על
כל האחים. chalitzah pesulah tzarich lehachazir al kol ha'achim. That's even the
bigger חידוש, chiddush, right? Which is that even though he's doing weaker
חליצות, chalitzas, it's enough to get it from one brother. You don't
have this idea of getting it from all the brothers. Okay, so
that's the major debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav
says you need it from all brothers,
okay? And שמואל Shmuel says you just need it from one. What
do you do about a second-grade חליצה? chalitzah? Second grade, not like
as opposed to third grade. Okay, second-grade חליצה.
chalitzah. Okay.
רב Rav says you need it from all brothers and שמואל Shmuel
says you just need it from one. And because and שמואל Shmuel
goes so far to say, I'll allow you to do a second
grade even if you have a first grade available.
Isn't שמואל Shmuel the bigger חידוש? chiddush?
But I mean the whole, okay, רב Rav is the bigger חידוש.
chiddush. You started with רב, Rav, so שמואל's Shmuel a חידוש chiddush
now that he's rejecting that. Fine.
Okay. Fine. I agree with you, רב Rav is really the חידוש.
chiddush. Okay. Now. גופא. Gufah. Yes.
Is there a note here that the רי"ף Rif says רב Rav
stated what you just said? Right. And then there's a note from
תוספות Tosafos that as for himself, however, he holds...
Oh
yeah, yeah.
The גמרא Gemara says that we know that רב Rav in another
place holds אין זיקה. ein zika. So if you hold אין זיקה
ein zika then all of the assumptions here are different because you
don't even start with a case of אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. Okay,
so alright, whatever. That's why there's a footnote. Let's not let that
bother us. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
גופא. Gufah. Let's go back to what we said. אמר שמואל: Amar
Shmuel: חלץ לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות.
Chalatz le'achayot lo
niptaru tzarot. Okay, לצרות נפטרו אחיות. letzarot niptaru achayot. So we're back
to this case. You do it with Rachel, doesn't get Devorah off
the hook. You do it with Devorah, gets Rachel off the hook.
And the same true with Zvulun's wives.
Okay. Okay. חלץ לבעלת הגט לא נפטרה צרה.
Chalatz leba'alat haget lo
niptara tzara. לצרה נפטרה בעלת הגט. Letzara niptara ba'alat haget. Let's say
there was not a case, the reason this was problematic was not
because Rachel was and here's where we're getting other scenarios of חליצה
פסולה. chalitzah pesulah. Other scenarios of second-grade חליצות. chalitzas. Okay. One was
it was Rachel was weaker because it was אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato.
The other case is that Reuven, I really need color markers. Reuven,
this was the case, and Reuven went ahead and before anything he
gave her a גט. get. I have a little dyslexia there. He
gave her a גט. get. Okay? Which means that now Rachel's, her
relationship to Rachel is weaker, ironically, because he's already started the process,
as it were, for he has to do חליצה chalitzah with Rachel,
he can't do יבום. yibbum. So it's the same idea. If she's
a בעלת הגט, ba'alat haget, then it's a second-grade חליצה chalitzah to
her, so it won't get Devorah off the hook, but with Devorah
he has a totally fine relationship with or full relationship with, so
the חליצה chalitzah with Devorah will get Rachel off the hook. Same
idea, except instead of as opposed to אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato it's
a case of בעלת הגט. ba'alat haget. חלץ לבעלת הגט לא נפטרה
צרה. Chalatz leba'alat haget lo niptara tzara. לצרה נפטרה בעלת הגט. Letzara
niptara ba'alat haget. Now how about a third case? How about חלץ
לבעלת מאמר? chalatz leba'at ma'amar? As opposed to a גט get here,
ironically, he did something that you would say would strengthen the relationship.
He did מאמר. ma'amar. מאמר ma'amar is קידושין. kiddushin. He actually gave
her a ring, he said "הרי את מקודשת." Harei at mekudeshet.
Which he says הרי את harei at mu-meretly?
Yeah, I don't know what he said.
Okay, anyway, whatever he said. Okay, anyway. Okay, but she's still not
his wife because he hasn't done יבום. yibbum. It would with a
normal woman it would have worked, in this case it doesn't, but
it's the first stage, it's the דרבנן d'rabbanan קידושין kiddushin that precedes
the דאורייתא, d'oraita, you know, נישואין nissuin if you want, יבום. yibbum.
Okay? So it's a stronger relationship with Rachel. But ironically, anytime you
sort of move off the center, you, you know, you change the
parameters. Because Rachel is now more his wife, חליצה chalitzah is less
relevant. Right? You understand the dynamic? No. He can do חליצה, chalitzah,
but he actually now has to do both חליצה chalitzah and a
גט. get. Once you do מאמר ma'amar you even need a גט
get to negate the מאמר ma'amar and חליצה chalitzah to negate the
זיקה. zika. But the point is, because he is now seen as
quasi his wife, because he strengthened the זיקה, zika, חליצה chalitzah is
less relevant, because if she was fully his wife you can't do
חליצה chalitzah to your wife, you only do חליצה, chalitzah, right? So
whenever the sister-in-law moves off the center, right, either because she becomes
more distant to him, so חליצה chalitzah is like, she's quasi an
ערווה, ervah, חליצה's chalitzah not relevant by an ערווה, ervah, or she
becomes more close to him, and therefore she's quasi his wife, well
חליצה's chalitzah not relevant. for a wife. So anytime the זיקה zika
*zika* changes, interestingly, either when it gets weaker or even gets stronger,
but it makes חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* less relevant, we get to a
case of considering a second-grade חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*, a חליצה chalitza פסולה
*chalitzah pesulah*, okay? So let's just read that.
So, right, Rachel in this case would need a גט *get* and
חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*, and even if you basically did that, gave her
גט *get* and well actually it's interesting too, if he gave her
the גט *get* first and then the חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*, would at
that stage the חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* have moved up to a first
grade? Probably not because then it would be she would be sort
of like גרושתו *gerushaso* and whatever. I don't think that matters, okay?
So in this case again, because her status has shifted and it's
not the classic one, it's a weaker חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* and this
חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* doesn't exempt the צרות tzaros *tzaros*.
Do we need צרות tzaros *tzaros* all the time now?
I don't know, whatever. Okay, so it says like this, let's read
that. חלץ לבעלת המאמר לא נפטרה צרה. tzara, לצרה נפטרה בעלת המאמר.
Okay, so let's just read the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. I saw there
were some questions but let's have the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* clarify this
for us a little bit. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this,
one moment I just want to check רש"י Rashi *Rashi* for one
thing.
Yes, so רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, in the, by the way, to
answer Michael's question, that the case was you did חליצה chalitza *chalitzah*
to Rachel, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* describes it before you gave the גט
*get*. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* doesn't spell out the exact thing I'd
have to check but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* implies that if you'd already
given the גט *get* to Rachel things might except no, actually not,
because then it's going to become a case that she'll be a
בעלת הגט *ba'alas haget*. Okay, anyway, so I don't know, it could
probably it doesn't matter, probably if he did it before then she's
more his wife, if he did it after the גט *get* then
it's she's a בעלת הגט *ba'alas haget*. But anyway, רש"י *Rashi* describes
the scenario here when there had not been a גט *get* given,
there was a מאמר *mamar* and then a חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* immediately
followed. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
מאי שנא לאחיות,
what's the difference when the case when you had sisters and Rachel's
problem was it was אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso, ולא נפטרו צרות דהויא
לה אחות אשה בזיקה, d'lo nifteru tzaros, d'havya lah achos isha b'zika,
interesting, that before we had the phrase אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso here
framing it a little different. But when there was the whole other
case about you know the other sister, so it was a weaker,
it was a weaker חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* because it was אחות זקוקתו,
achos zekukaso חלץ לצרות נמי לא נפטרו אחיות דהויא לה צרת אחות
אשה בזיקה. chalatz l'tzaros nami lo nifteru achayos d'havya lah tzaros achos
isha b'zika. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says he don't he can't do יבום *yibum* with
Devorah, right? Whatever problem he had with Rachel because now she's like
a quasi ערוה *ervah* אחות זקוקתו, achos zkukaso,
okay? So Devorah is צרת אחות זקוקתו, tzaros achos zekukaso, she's צרת
tzaras ערוה *tzaras ervah*. Okay point is, okay but it's one degree
removed. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
קסבר שמואל Shmuel. אין זיקה. ein zika, So the first answer the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the better answer is, like I said and that
we'll get to, that it's one degree removed and therefore yes neither
of them are סוג א, they're both סוג ב, sug bet, okay?
But there's a סוג ב sug bet and there's a סוג ג.
sug gimel. Alright, so fine. Okay, but let's first see but that's
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s now question, that when Rachel is a quasi
ערוה *ervah* because of אחות זקוקתו, achos zkukaso. Devorah is a צרות
tzaros *tzaros* quasi ערוה *ervah*, why is doing חליצה chalitza. *chalitzah* to
her any better than doing it to Rachel? So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. קסבר שמואל Shmuel. אין זיקה. ein zika...
So now everything we've been explaining has been assuming that Shmuel holds
יש זיקה yesh zika, *yesh zika*, right? And that's why all these
cases of אחות זקוקתו achos zkukaso. and blah blah blah blah and
it's a סוג ב sug bet etc. Now we're saying Shmuel holds
אין זיקה ein zika, *ein zika*. Of course if Shmuel holds אין
זיקה ein zika. *ein zika* then go ahead and do יבום *yibum*
with Rachel, okay? So let's take a look. קסבר שמואל Shmuel אין
זיקה. ein zika. והאמר שמואל יש זיקה? V'ha'amar Shmuel yesh zika?
לדברי האומר אין זיקה. L'divrei ha'omer ein zika.
Oh,
this is within the idea of אין זיקה zika, *ein zika*. Of
course אי הכי ee hachi,
if that's true okay so now we're getting back not to the
case of מאמר *mamar* and גט *get*, but to the case of
sisters.
Okay, and this case Rachel we were saying was אחות זקוקתו achos
zkukaso, and therefore but then we say if she's אחות זקוקתו achos
zkukaso. she's צרות אחות זקוקתו tzaros achos zekukaso
there's no difference. So we're saying fine, there's no זיקה *zika*. Okay,
there's no זיקה *zika* what's the problem? Okay for God's sake if
there's no זיקה *zika* just go ahead and do יבום *yibum*. I
mean maybe it's אסור לבטל מצוות יבומין assur l'vatel mitzvas yibumin, but
what how does that make one woman even if it's אסור לבטל
מצוות יבומין, it's not about one woman being more problematic than the
other, it's just don't do certain things because then you won't have
the opportunity for יבום *yibum*. So if that's true that there's no
זיקה *zika*, well why should there be any difference in terms of
the type of חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* you're doing? So let's take a
look. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: אי הכי
חלץ לאחיות אמאי לא נפטרו צרות? tzaros, בשלמא צרה דרחל לא תיפטר,
Bishlama tzarah d'Rachel lo tiftar, I get why Rachel's
צרה tzara *tzarah* doesn't get off the actually I keep on doing,
using the different nomenclature than the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Just the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* assumes that Leah is the one that actually becomes available
first. Okay,
presumably—I don't know, maybe because לאה Leah is the one that was
married first in the תורה. Torah. Okay, so anyway, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this, "I get why רחל's Rachel צרה, tzara okay,
let's read this—oh, let's read this, hold
on—בשלמא צרה דרחל לא תיפטר,
Bishlama tzara
deRochel lo tipter, I get why רחל's Rachel צרה tzara doesn't get
off the hook with the חליצה chalitza of רחל, Rachel, דכיון דחלץ
לה ללאה והדר חלץ לה לרחל הויא לה חליצה דרחל חליצה פסולה.
dekivan dechaltz la leLeah vehadar chaltz la leRochel havya lah chalitza deRochel
chalitza pesula.
Okay, so what happened? This was the order it happened.
And ראובן Reuven first went ahead, and let's assume he did חליצה
chalitza with לאה Leah first, okay? And then now זבולון Zevulun dies,
okay? So, if he were to do, what's רחל Rachel to him
right now? אחות חלוצתו. Achos Chalitzaso. So in this scenario, even if
you hold אין זיקה, there is still a reality of חליצה chalitza
here, and therefore רחל Rachel is אחות חלוצתו, achos chalitzaso, and נעמי
Naomi is a little bit better, okay? So therefore, she's not a
package deal, and even if you hold אין זיקה... well, okay, so
that's the question.
Why not also ask צרת אחות זקוקתו?
tzaras achos zekukaso? Fine, whatever. But that's a question that the גמרא
could get to. But let's hold off for that for right now,
okay? Anyway, here I can at least understand why רחל Rachel is
אחות חלוצתו achos chalitzaso and more problematic than נעמי. Naomi. But at
this stage, even if these guys have both died at the same
time and certainly if they die sequentially, right? What's לאה Leah to
him? Nothing. So why doesn't the חליצה chalitza. of לאה Leah get
דבורה Devorah off the hook, right? If you hold—if you hold אין
זיקה, then before any act has been done, everybody is on an
equal footing, okay? So the גמרא says like this:
'So אלא צרה דלאה תיפטר, ela tzara deLeah tipter, so let לאה's
Leah. צרה tzara get off the hook if you say אין זיקה.'
The גמרא says, 'No, מאי לא נפטרו צרות נמי דקאמר צרה דרחל.
mai lo nifteru tzaros nami dekamar tzara deRochel. He didn't mean that
the צרות tzarot. don't get off the hook; he meant the second
צרה tzara doesn't get off the hook, רחל's Rachel צרה tzara doesn't
get off the hook.' The גמרא
says,
'והצרות
קאמר, vehatzaros kamar, he says the צרות tzarot in plural don't get
off the hook.' So, okay, no, no. So it says, 'והצרות קאמר.'
vehatzaros kamar. So it says, 'צרות דעלמא, tzaros dealma, it means צרות
in these types of cases don't get off the hook, but only
the second one, the first one
is fine. אי הכי חלצה לה צרה נפטרה אחות—one ei hachi chaltza
la tzara nifterah achos minute. It says if you do חליצה chalitza,
on the צרות, the אחות achos get off the hook, והצרות דרחל
מי מיפטרא—but vehatzaros deRochel mi miftera one minute, how is—ah, but how
does the צרה tzara of רחל Rachel get off the hook? So
why—והתנן, vehatnan, we taught in the משנה, mishna, אסור אדם בצרת קרובת
חלוצתו.' asur adam betzaras krovat chalitzaso. Okay, so a person—we're not even
going to try to understand why this is true right now, we'll
just accept it. A person is not allowed to—a man is not
allowed to marry the צרה tzara of his חלוצה's chalutza relatives. So
what does this mean?
I have to remind myself.
So רש"י says, one minute, yeah, yeah, one minute, one minute. One
minute, so says—right, so the גמרא's saying like this. So, okay, so
in this case here, so you're saying in this case, go ahead
and ראובן Reuven do חליצה chalitza, now with נעמי, Naomi, okay, because
רחל Rachel is אחות חלוצתו, achos chalitzaso, that's how we've explained it.
Do חליצה chalitza. with נעמי, Naomi, and רחל Rachel will get off
the hook, okay? But, but that's what we're saying, okay? Because רחל
Rachel is more problematic, אחות חלוצתו, achos chalitzaso, do with נעמי. Naomi.
But we've got a problem. What's the problem? אסור אדם בצרת קרובת
חלוצתו. asur adam betzaras krovat chalitzaso. Let's read the רש"י together, second
wide line here, or middle-sized line. רש"י says, 'ואפילו לא היתה צרתה
מאחיו אלא מנכרי.' veafilu lo haysah tzaratah meachiv ela menochri. So even
if she wasn't a צרה tzara from his brother, but from a
נכרי.
nochri.
רש"י actually has it מנכרי. menochri.
רש"י says מנכרי. menochri. Yeah, I know.
It doesn't mean non-Jew. It means—it means somebody who's not related to
you.
Oh, unrelated Jew.
נכרי nochri in ninety-five percent of this גמרא means not related to
you, not your brother. Okay, so—okay, ואפילו היתה צרתה מנכרי. veafilu haysah
tzaratah menochri. So you have a co-wife, so you have your קרובת
חלוצתו. krovat chalitzaso. You did חליצה chalitza to—okay, I don't even know
where to go.
You did חליצה chalitza to לאה.
Leah. Can you marry her mother? You did חליצה—right, chalitza, forget—right, exactly.
So let's forget right now, thank you, we'll use this scenario. We'll
ignore right now what happened to זבולון, Zevulun, okay? He did חליצה
chalitza to לאה. Leah Now you have somebody else here, ברק, Barak,
okay, is married to—is married to—no, is married to
לאה's Leah
mother, let's say רבקה, Rivka, we'll make רבקה Rivka לאה's Leah? mother.
He's married to רבקה *Rifkah*, לאה Leah, *Leah*'s mother, okay? ראובן *Reuven*,
so who's רבקה *Rifkah* to him? ראובן *Reuven*'s רבקה *Rifkah* to him
is קרובת חליצתו *krovat chalitzato*. Okay. Now
ברק *Barak* also happens to be married to דבורה Devorah *Devorah*. And
then ברק *Barak* dies. Now his brother, he is not allowed to
marry דבורה Devorah *Devorah* because דבורה Devorah *Devorah* is צרת tzaras קרובת
חלוצה *tzorat krovat chalutzah*. Okay, I'm not even going to begin to
explain why that should be a problem, but that's the problem. So
if we say that's a problem, how can we say here that
all he's got to do is do חליצה chalitza *chalitzah* to נעמי
*Naomi* and then he's מותר *mutar* to רחל *Rachel*? רחל *Rachel* is...
נעמי
*Naomi* is... wait a minute...
נעמי *Naomi* is...
צרת קרובת חלוצה *tzorat krovat chalutzah*,
right? רחל *Rachel* is קרובת חלוצה *krovat chalutzah*, that's צרת קרובת חלוצה
*tzorat krovat chalutzah*. Oh, so נעמי *Naomi* is just as problematic to
him as רחל *Rachel* is. Why do we say רחל *Rachel* is
אחות חלוצה *achot chalutzah*? יישר כח *Shkoach*. נעמי *Naomi* is קרובת אחות
חלוצה *krovat achot chalutzah*, which is just generally problematic.
In the third-rate problem.
Ah, no. No. When she was צרת חלוצה *tzorat chalutzah* here, she
was one degree less than רחל *Rachel*, but here it's seen as
an independent issue
and therefore an equal issue. It's not because of the ייבום yibum
*yibum* aspect.
All right, so the גמרא *Gemara* says like this, דתנן detnan, *hatnan*,
אסור אדם בצרת קרובת חלוצו *asur adam betzorat krovat chalutzo*. All right.
שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* נמי *nami* התחיל ולא התחיל קאמר *hitchil velo hitchil
kamar*. Fine. שמואל Shmuel *Shmuel* isn't really saying that when you do
it with נעמי *Naomi*, when you do... that in this case the
חליצה chalitzah, *chalitzah* to נעמי *Naomi* is preferable to the חליצה chalitzah,
*chalitzah* to רחל *Rachel*. He's talking about when you begin the process
one way, how you end it. We're going to completely re-read שמואל
Shmuel. *Shmuel*. Okay,
let's continue this. You'll see what the גמרא *Gemara* says. Here's what
he says. התחיל ולא התחיל קאמר *hitchil velo hitchil kamar*.
התחיל באחיות *hitchil beachayot*,
if he began, if he did, okay, before זבולון *Zevulun* died, okay,
or before, let's say they both died, before he did anything, all
these
women were equal because he holds אין זיקה *ein zikah*. Okay, so
now actually if he's smart, he'll focus on דבורה Devorah *Devorah* because
then רחל *Rachel* won't be אחות חלוצה *achot chalutzah*. Okay, but if
he went and he started with לאה Leah *Leah* and turned her
into... and turns רחל *Rachel* into אחות חלוצה *achot chalutzah*, so in
that case התחיל באחיות לא יגמור בצרות *hitchil beachayot
lo yigmor betzarot*. דתנן *hatnan*, אסור אדם בצרת קרובת חלוצו *asur adam
betzorat krovat chalutzo*. In that case, if he began with לאה Leah
*Leah*, then he should not finish with נעמי *Naomi* because נעמי *Naomi*
is this problem, צרת קרובת חלוצו *tzorat krovat chalutzo*. So in that
type of a case, he should finish with רחל *Rachel*. I don't
get exactly why רחל *Rachel*'s any better, it's the exact same, okay,
but it's, you know, it's אחות חלוצה *achot chalutzah*, who knows. But
so רש"י *Rashi* says it doesn't mean it's better. רש"י *Rashi* says
it means that it's like no... I think רש"י *Rashi* says it
means it's no different. Hold on...
basically. Hold on, let me check the רש"י *Rashi*.
Oh, right. רש"י *Rashi* says it doesn't mean he shouldn't finish, it
means that by doing נעמי *Naomi* he won't get רחל *Rachel* off
the hook. Okay, when it says לא יגמור בצרות *lo yigmor betzarot*,
it means normally we're saying you do the צרה tzara *tzara*, you
get the other wife off the hook. לא יגמור בצרות *lo yigmor
betzarot* means doing it with the צרה tzara *tzara* won't get the
other wife off the hook. So if you started with לאה Leah
*Leah*,
this won't help. You still need to do רחל *Rachel*.
He has to do both because one won't get the other off
the hook because they're both problematic, okay? So if he begins with
לאה Leah *Leah*, then both of these are now problematic: אחות חלוצה
*achot chalutzah*, צרת אחות חלוצה *tzorat achot
chalutzah*, finishing with נעמי *Naomi* won't help you.
You have to do it with both. התחיל באחיות לא יגמור בצרות
*hitchil beachayot lo yigmor betzarot*, דתנן *hatnan*, אסור אדם בצרת קרובת חלוצו
*asur adam betzorat krovat chalutzo*. התחיל בצרות יגמור אף באחיות *hitchil betzarot
yigmor af beachayot*, דתנן *hatnan*, מותר אדם בקרובת
צרת חלוצו *mutar adam bekrovat tzorat chalutzo*. But if he's smart and
he starts with דבורה Devorah *Devorah*,
okay, so then רחל *Rachel* is not אחות חלוצה *achot chalutzah*, nobody
is related to anybody. In this case, either one can work. He
can do it with רחל *Rachel* and that's a totally good חליצה
chalitzah *chalitzah* to get נעמי *Naomi* off the hook. And he can
do it with נעמי *Naomi* and that'll get רחל *Rachel* off the
hook. Why? Now isn't... Okay, so and why? And because we say...
and let's just read these words, because here מותר אדם *mutar adam*,
because a person is allowed, בקרובת צרת חלוצו *bekrovat tzorat chalutzo*, in
the relative... so he's allowed to finish with רחל *Rachel* because רחל
*Rachel* is... this is the mirror image of the other case. רחל
*Rachel* is the relative of the צרה tzara *tzara*. This is צרת
חלוצה *tzorat chalutzah* and that's קרובת צרת חלוצה *krovat tzorat chalutzah*. So
it's like the mirror image of the other case. But that's not
problematic. You might have thought it's like this, don't worry, it's not
like that. So in this case, both of the women are totally
מותר *mutar* to him, so doing it with either woman will get
the other one off. Okay, that was a... Super complicated complete reread
of what שמואל Shmuel had said, okay, all because the גמרא wanted
to understand if it's יש זיקה, yesh zika, why is דבורה Devorah
better than לאה? Leah And it couldn't just have said because דבורה
Devorah is one degree removed? Yes, she's
צרת אחות זקוקתו, tzaras achos zkukaso, but it's one degree removed. So
the גמרא had this total reread of
שמואל. Shmuel Okay, now the גמרא finally gives the simple explanation of
שמואל. Shmuel רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi
says, לעולם כדקאמרית, leolam kidekamris, don't bother me with all this. It's
שמואל Shmuel like you thought he said. Okay, it's better to do
it with דבורה Devorah. than with לאה, Leah even though דבורה Devorah
is like a צרת quasi-ערווה, tzaras erva, that's one degree removed from
being a quasi-ערווה. erva, כדקאמרית ומשום דלא אלימא זיקה, kidekamris umishum delo
alima zika, the זיקה too is not strong enough לשווייה לצרה כערווה
lishveiye litzara ke'erva to make the צרה as much of an ערווה
erva. as לאה Leah is. So in this case שמואל Shmuel holds
יש זיקה, yesh zika? לאה Leah? is אחות זקוקתו, which makes her-
and they didn't die בבת אחת?
bevas achas? What?
They're both אחות זקוקתו.
Okay, they both died at the same time.
Yeah, whatever, exactly. They all died at the same time. Okay, they're
both אחות זקוקתו. So they're both quasi-ערווה. erva So דבורה Devorah is
a quasi-צרת ערווה, tzaras erva. but that's not as close to being
an ערווה erva. because לאה Leah, isn't a real ערווה. erva So
since לאה Leah. isn't a real ערווה, erva. normally there's already a
חידוש chidush that a צרה becomes like the ערווה. erva, Okay, so
she's not going to be enough like an ערווה erva. in this
case because already לאה Leah isn't even a full ערווה. erva And
therefore, maybe none
of them is a סוג א׳, sug aleph, none of them is
a grade A, but at least דבורה Devorah is a grade B,
whereas לאה Leah might be a grade C.
So therefore, you do it to דבורה Devorah and you get לאה
Leah off the hook. It is the better חליצה. chalitzah Alright. Phew.
תניא כוותיה דרב אשי. Tanya kevasei deRav Ashi. We taught like רב
אשי, Rav Ashi, thank God. So, חלץ לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות. chalatz
laachayot lo nifteru tzarot.
If you did חליצה chalitzah with the sisters, the co-wives didn't get
off the hook. חלץ לצרה, chalatz litzara, if you do it to
the co-wives, נפטרו אחיות, nifteru achayot, the sisters do get off the
hook. מאי טעמא? Mai taama? What's the reason? משום דקסבר יש זיקה
mishum dekasavar yesh zika ולא אלומי זיקה לשווייה לצרה כערווה. velo alumi
zika lishveiye litzara ke'erva. It must be exactly like רב אשי Rav
Ashi said. There is a זיקה, and therefore the sisters are אחות
זקוקתו, but that's not strong enough to create a serious enough problem
with the co-wife. So therefore the חליצה chalitzah with the co-wife still
works for the sisters fine.
Wait, so שמואל's שיטה shita יש זיקה?
I thought we said אין זיקה. No, that's when we were trying
to reread שמואל. Now we're back to the normal read of שמואל
and the problem is אחות זקוקתו. אמר רבי אבא בר ממל, Amar
Rabbi Abba bar Mamul, הא מני בית שמאי היא? ha mani Beis
Shammai hi? דתנן,
he's going to come up with a different answer why the צרה
is not a problem, why it's better to do חליצה with דבורה.
Devorah Isn't she a צרת quasi-ערווה? erva. So he says, no, we're
not holding like there's an issue of צרה altogether. הא מני בית
שמאי היא? ha mani Beis Shammai hi? דתנן בית שמאי מתירין הצרות
לאחים. detnan Beis Shammai matirin hatzarot leachim. Okay, well that's pretty radical,
right? So he says, why is שמואל saying do חליצה to דבורה
Devorah and not to לאה? Leah Isn't דבורה Devorah. a צרה of
לאה, who's also problematic?
Answer: He is the שיטה shita of בית שמאי Beis Shammai who
doesn't believe in צרות. Okay?
It's like that other משנה? mishnah? Yeah, and שמואל is just סתם
stam incorporating that. So the גמרא says, אי הכי, ייבמו נמי ליתייבמו.
yivmu nami lityabmu. So go ahead and do ייבום yibum with דבורה
Devorah in that case. So the גמרא says, כרבי יוחנן בן נורי,
keRabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, דאמר, de'amar, like רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri says, בואו ונתקן להם לצרה שיהו חולצות ולא מתייבמות,
bo'u unetaken lahem latzarot sheyihyu choltzot velo mityabmot,
that even according to- let's just play it safe and have everybody,
we'll cover both בית שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל, Beis Hillel,
do חליצה. So בית הלל Beis Hillel will say it's not necessary
but at least it doesn't hurt, and בית שמאי Beis Shammai will
say you have to do ייבום yibum, or חליצה, so we won't
do ייבום, yibum, we'll do חליצה, we'll make everybody happy. So therefore
we're פוסק paskening like him. So דבורה Devorah is not really an
ערווה, erva? 'cause basically we're assuming like בית שמאי Beis Shammai that
צרות are okay, but we have a דרבנן derabbanan demand to do
חליצה. So we're saying, better to do חליצה with דבורה Devorah? than,
you know, than with לאה. The חליצה with דבורה Devorah will still
get לאה off the hook by the way, right?
Because he still has a מצווה mitzvah of ייבום, yibum according to
בית שמאי Beis Shammai there's a מצווה mitzvah of ייבום yibum with
דבורה. Devorah, Okay, all we're saying is that according to בית שמאי
Beis Shammai you're allowed to do ייבום yibum with דבורה and we're
insisting you do חליצה, but not that דבורה's out of the picture.
Okay, so therefore he's saying, why do it with דבורה? 'Cause we're
like בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, there's no idea of צרת ערווה. erva,
Okay, and in theory you could do ייבום yibum but we want
to be nice to בית הלל Beis Hillel so we're going to
do חליצה and that'll get לאה off the hook. Of course why
we should assume that שמואל's talking like that I have no idea.
Okay, so the גמרא says, והא אמר מר לא הספיקו לגמור את
הדבר עד שנפטרה השעה. veha amar Mar lo hispiku ligmor et hadavar
ad shenifterah hasha'ah. They never made that ruling that they said that
everybody needs חליצה and not ייבום according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אחריהן חזרו
ותקנו. achareihen chazaru vetiknu. Nah, even though they didn't get a chance...
Okay, the
easier explanation is like we said, we're back to the basic idea
that you assume that even though שמואל has that you even if
it's a second-rate חליצה, we should say rate as opposed to grade
as if we're in grade school or something. A second, even if
it's a second-rate חליצה, even though you only need one, and even
though you'll allow a second-rate you don't need it from all the
brothers, and allow a second-rate חליצה to get the woman off the
hook, you don't need the first-rate to get her off the hook,
but if you have a co-wife, then the other, then you need
the better חליצה that will get the other wife off the hook.
And in this case, the better חליצה is the one to דבורה
because לאה is אחות זיקתו achos zikkuso and דבורה, even though she's
צרת אחות זיקתו, tzaras achos zikkuso, she's one degree removed and therefore
it's the better חליצה and it will get לאה off the hook.
All right.