Okay, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody.
Today's דף, Daf, well officially today's דף Daf is דף ל. Daf
Lamed. We are on כט עמוד ב. Chaf Tet Amud Bet. I'm
going to start us back very quickly, I know this is a
little, it's not smart given that we're behind, but from the bottom
of כט עמוד א, Chaf Tet Amud Aleph, just because I read
the גמרא Gemara yesterday slightly incorrectly, I want to correct that and
also we need to anyway reframe what we're talking about. So if
we go to כט עמוד א, Chaf Tet Amud Aleph, we'll pick
up with אמר רבי אלעזר לא תימא, Amar Rabbi Elazar Lo Teima,
it's five lines from the bottom. The משנה Mishna basically said that
ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon died, leaving two sisters, you know, as
two sister-in-laws, רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. So לוי, Levi, but before
שמעון Shimon died, ראובן Reuven died, excuse me, then לוי Levi did
מאמר Maamar with רחל. Rachel. And that's already pretty close to doing
יבום. Yibum. And then שמעון Shimon died. So בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says well, you already basically are married to רחל, Rachel, לאה Leah
walks away, which is fascinating, which basically says that מאמר Maamar according
to בית שמאי Beit Shammai counts as יבום; Yibum; it not only
gets rid of the problem of אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zikukato, which is
דרבנן, derabbanan, but it lets לאה Leah walk away completely as a,
you know, as a יבמה Yevamah who's an ערווה. Erva. So that
seems like there's a real דאורייתא de-Oraita status to that,
and whereas בית הלל Beit Hillel says I'm sorry, now they're both
אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zikukato, you gotta do חליצה Chalitzah with לאה Leah
and a גט Get and חליצה Chalitzah with רחל, Rachel, a גט
Get to counteract the מאמר. Maamar. So we have here the idea
that בית שמאי Beit Shammai really says that the מאמר Maamar is
quite powerful, and the גמרא Gemara wants to figure out exactly how
powerful. So let's pick up five lines from the bottom of כט
עמוד א: Chaf Tet Amud Aleph: אמר רבי אלעזר לא תימא מאמר
לבית שמאי קונה קניין גמור, Amar Rabbi Elazar Lo Teima Maamar l'Beit
Shammai Koneh Kinyan Gamur,
don't say מאמר Maamar for בית שמאי Beit Shammai is a full
קניין, Kinyan, it's like actually the exact same as יבום. Yibum. דאי
בעי לאפוקי סגי לה בגיטא, De-ee Ba-ee l'apukei sagi lah b'gita, and
what would be the evidence of this? Or what would be a
full קניין? Kinyan? That after, if he wanted to now divorce from
רחל, Rachel, he would only have to give her a גט, Get,
right? After יבום, Yibum, then it's like they're totally married, there's no
remnant of the יבום Yibum component left, and if they want to
get divorced it's not חליצה, Chalitzah, it's a גט. Get. Would that
be true according to בית שמאי? Beit Shammai? He says no. Even
after the מאמר Maamar and even if it sort of frees רחל,
Rachel, even if it frees לאה Leah to walk away without יבום
Yibum or חליצה, Chalitzah, it's not a hundred percent done. If he
wanted to get divorced at this stage from רחל, Rachel, it would
need both a גט Get and חליצה. Chalitzah. אלא מאמר לבית שמאי
אינו קונה אלא לדחות בצרה בלבד. Ela Maamar l'Beit Shammai eino koneh
ela lidechot bi-tzarah bilvad. What it does is it pushes off לאה;
Leah; it says לאה Leah is enough of a, you know, of
an ערווה Erva
even on a דאורייתא de-Oraita level, but it does not mean that
the יבום Yibum status has completely gone away vis-a-vis רחל. Rachel. It's
still a little bit left in terms of solidifying that. Interesting exactly
how you'd exactly frame that, but nevertheless it hasn't completely finished with
רחל, Rachel, but it's enough to free לאה Leah from any obligation.
Is it stronger than קידושין Kiddushin in a way?
No, it's not stronger. Oh, what do you mean it's not stronger?
If he was married to רחל, Rachel, whatever, it's not stronger. Not
stronger. Anyway, you need more, but it's not because it's stronger, it's
because it hasn't gotten rid of the יבום Yibum obligation. Okay. אמר
רב
אבין אף אנן נמי תנינא, Amar Rav Avin, Af Anan Nami Tanina,
that's implicit in the משנה. Mishna. Why? Because two days ago we
learned that in a case not here
where they died sequentially, but in a similar case of they died
let's say at the same time or whatever, or you didn't do
anything until they had both died, that it says here that לוי
Levi and יהודה Yehuda when, you know, cannot go ahead and do
יבום Yibum with רחל Rachel and לאה Leah because each one is
אחות זקוקתו Achot Zikukato when no מאמר Maamar had been done. Okay,
but בית שמאי Beit Shammai says if they went ahead and did
יבום, Yibum, יקיימו, Yekayemu, they can stay married to רחל Rachel and
לאה. Leah. יקיימו Yekayemu בדיעבד, b'di-avad, אין, in, לכתחילה l'chatchilah לא, lo,
only בדיעבד, b'di-avad, not לכתחילה. l'chatchilah. But he's going to say one
minute, if מאמר Maamar really, here's a proof that מאמר Maamar is
not a hundred percent, because if מאמר Maamar was a hundred percent,
there would be a solution here for בית שמאי Beit Shammai in
this second case even if nobody had done anything yet to allow
them to get married לכתחילה. l'chatchilah. What would be the solution? ואי
סלקא דעתך מאמר לבית שמאי קונה קניין גמור, V'ee salka da-atach Maamar
l'Beit Shammai koneh kinyan gamur, if it was a hundred percent, so
יעשה מאמר ויקנה וזה יעשה מאמר ויקנה וזה יעשה מאמר ויקנה. yaaseh
Maamar v'yikneh v'zeh yaaseh Maamar v'yikneh v'zeh yaaseh Maamar v'yikneh. So he
says I got a perfect idea. So they can't do יבום, Yibum,
it's אחות זקוקתו, Achot Zikukato, but nobody says you can't do מאמר;
Maamar; it's only you can't have sex with אחות זקוקתו. Achot Zikukato.
So go ahead and do מאמר, Maamar, okay, and then that was
allowed, nobody said it was אסור. assur. Go ahead and do מאמר,
Maamar, if this was really a hundred percent, so then now רחל
Rachel is a hundred percent married to לוי. Levi. So לאה Leah
is now irrelevant, no longer a זיקה. Zikah. So now that לאה
Leah is no longer a זיקה, Zikah, now he can consummate it
with רחל. Rachel. And then יהודה Yehuda will do the same with
לאה. Leah. So if מאמר Maamar really worked a hundred percent, there'd
be a solution here: do מאמר Maamar which is allowed, get לאה
Leah off, and then go ahead and finish it. So the גמרא
Gemara says, Look, that's a question if מאמר ma'amar is 100% or
not 100%. אלא מאי? Ela mai? So what, you think that this
makes sense if you say דוחה? doche? That מאמר ma'amar just pushes
לאה Leah off, and it's not a 100% with רחל? Rachel? So
דחייה גמורה? dechiya gemura?
If it fully pushes לאה Leah off, you have the same question.
It's not any better according to you. זה יעשה מאמר ויכנוס וזה
יעשה מאמר ויכנוס. Ze ya'aseh ma'amar ve-yiknas ve-ze ya'aseh ma'amar ve-yiknas. Either
way it's the same question. What we see from בית שמאי Beit
Shammai up here is that once there's מאמר, ma'amar, however you understand
whether the relationship with רחל Rachel is 100%, לאה Leah is free.
So whether it's 100% or not, לאה Leah is free. So it's
the same question down here. Let him do מאמר ma'amar and get
לאה Leah out of the picture, and then finish. It doesn't, this
doesn't prove whether it's 100% or not, that's a, either way it's
a question. Why can't you do מאמר ma'amar and get לאה Leah
out of the picture? אלא מאי אית לך למימר, Ela mai itlach
le-meimar,
what's the explanation? What's the only way of explaining why the top
works and the bottom doesn't work? מאמר דהיתרא דחי דאיסורא לא דחי.
Ma'amar de-heteira dachi de-issura lo dachi.
Because you'll say that up here, when לוי Levi did מאמר ma'amar
with רחל, Rachel, שמעון Shimon hadn't died yet. So a מאמר ma'amar
done when he could have done יבום, yibbum, that'll define it as
a full relationship or strong relationship so that when לאה Leah becomes
a widow, she's out of the picture. Whereas here, where there's already
a problem of אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato and he can't do יבום,
yibbum, the מאמר ma'amar does not have an effect. So הכא נמי
hacha nami even if you say מאמר ma'amar works 100%, that's only
when it comes in an uncomplicated scenario. So הכא נמי מאמר אפילו
למאן דאמר מאמר קונה קניין גמור, hacha nami ma'amar afilu le-man de-amar
ma'amar koneh kinyan gamur,
even if I were to claim that מאמר ma'amar was 100%, so
what would that be? מאמר דהיתרא קני דאיסורא לא קני. Ma'amar de-heteira
kanei de-issura lo kanei.
Only if it's היתרא heteira not if it's איסורא. issura. Okay, so
the basic point is that the difference down here is that the
מאמר ma'amar here you can't do a מאמר ma'amar to solve the
problem. Once everything is אסור, assur, מאמר ma'amar isn't going to work.
But here the מאמר ma'amar came in before לאה Leah became a
widow, created a relationship with רחל, Rachel, and then לאה Leah and
then לאה's Leah the widow, then she's out of the picture, she
can walk away. So the question we have right now is: is
מאמר ma'amar 100% with רחל, Rachel, קניין גמור, kinyan gamur, and that
it's only therefore needs a גט, get, or although מאמר ma'amar gets
לאה Leah off and lets him consummate with רחל, Rachel, it's not
yet 100% and there's still a remnant of the יבום yibbum aspect
there, and if he wanted to divorce her he would need a
גט get and חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, so that's the question, whether it's
קניין גמור, kinyan gamur, okay,
which is all of this is with רחל, Rachel, לאה's Leah off
either way, קניין גמור kinyan gamur and therefore you just have a
גט get if you wanted to get divorced, or it's דחייה גמורה.
dechiya gemura. דחייה גמורה dechiya gemura means that לאה's Leah out of
the picture, but the relationship here is not complete, and therefore with
רחל, Rachel, if you wanted to get divorced, you would need a
גט get plus חליצה chalitzah because there's still some remnant
of the יבום yibbum still around.
All
right, know interesting, we're going further. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: רב אשי מתני הכי. Rav Ashi matni hachi. Here's how
רב אשי Rav Ashi teaches, and it's not a question of קניין
גמור kinyan gamur versus דחייה גמורה, dechiya gemura, but a different one,
a different way of understanding בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. אמר רבי אלעזר,
Amar Rabbi Elazar, לא תימר מאמר לבית שמאי דחי דחייה גמורה. lo
teimar ma'amar le-Beit Shammai dachi dechiya gemura. Don't say like was just
said before by who was it, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, that it's
דחייה גמורה, dechiya gemura, that לאה Leah is pushed off but this
is not yet complete. Don't say this, we're not going to go
back to this, we're going one even less than this. Don't say
it's a דחייה גמורה dechiya gemura that pushes לאה Leah fully off
and וצרתה חליצה נמי לא בעיא. ve-tzarata chalitzah nami lo ba'ya. לאה
Leah doesn't even need חליצה. chalitzah.
אלא דוחה ומשייר הוא. Ela doche u-meshayyer hu. Yes, it pushes לאה
Leah off, but there's some remnant even vis-à-vis לאה, Leah, which basically
means, very different than the משנה Mishnah sounds and the גמרא's Gemara
going to ask from the משנה, Mishnah, it's strong enough to let
him consummate with רחל, Rachel, so that there is not a problem
of אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. There's like not enough of a זיקה
zika to make לאה Leah a problem, so he can finish with
רחל, Rachel, it's not אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. But maybe it's only
דרבנן, de-rabbanan, maybe it's not דאורייתא. de-Oraita. Remember אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato
problem is all דרבנן de-rabbanan anyway. So there still is some connection
to לאה, Leah, and therefore he would still need to do חליצה
chalitzah with לאה. Leah. Now the משנה Mishnah doesn't sound like that,
the משנה Mishnah sounds like לאה Leah just walks away. So the
גמרא's Gemara going to pretty much reject this. Let's take a look.
אמר Amar right,
okay, אמר רב אבין, Amar Rav Avin, אף אנן נמי תנינא. af
anan nami tanina. So first we're going to try to prove it
like we did before. בית שמאי אומרים יקיימו, Beit Shammai omrim yekayemu,
that they can בדיעבד bidi'avad if in the bottom case they can
stay married if they did it after when they weren't supposed to.
יקיימו אם לכתחילה לא. yekayemu im le-chatechila lo. Only בדיעבד bidi'avad not
לכתחילה. le-chatechila. ואי סלקא דעתך מאמר לבית שמאי דחי דחייה גמורה, ve-is
salka da'atach ma'amar le-Beit Shammai dachi dechiya gemura, and now this is
a better, a better point of why we're trying to prove it.
If here according to, if once you did מאמר ma'amar לאה Leah
was completely pushed away and it removed the problem of אחות זקוקתו,
achot zekukato, so זה יעשה מאמר ויכנוס וזה יעשה מאמר ויכנוס. Ze
ya'aseh ma'amar ve-yiknas ve-ze ya'aseh ma'amar ve-yiknas. Why don't we solve this
problem by doing מאמר ma'amar and getting rid of the. sort of
pushing the other wife out of the picture and then finishing it?
So the גמרא Gemara says again similar type of an answer והא
קתני veha katani no you can't say that says the גמרא. Gemara.
That's not a proof. Just because you couldn't solve the problem down
here doesn't mean that there's still some remnant of a relationship. Because
our משנה mishna is very clear that there is no remnant of
a relationship with לאה. Leah. והא קתני Veha katani our
משנה mishna says בית שמאי אומרים Beis Shammai omrim אשתו עמו והלזו
תצא משום אחות אשה ishto imo vehalazu teitzei mishum achos isha his
wife רחל Rachel is with him and I'm sorry I skipped a
line. אשתו עמו והלזו תצא משום אחות אשה Ishto imo vehalazu teitzei
mishum achos isha his wife רחל Rachel is with
him and לאה Leah walks away. She's his wife's sister. So you
see that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says that לאה Leah walks away.
There's no new חליצה chalitza any חליצה chalitza needing to be done
with לאה. Leah. מאמר Maamar actually has a דאורייתא De'oraisa status and
לאה Leah really walks away. So
אלא ella what's the explanation of why it works here and not
down here? So the same thing it said before about מאמר דהיתרא
Maamar de'heisera except using a different language. אלא Ella says the גמרא
Gemara
יבמה דחזיא לכולהו חזיא למקצתה yevama dechazya lekulhu chazya lemiktzasa
this sister-in-law that could have had יבום yibum for her a partial
מאמר Maamar is meaningful okay? יבמה דלא חזיא לכולהו לא חזיא למקצתה
yevama delo chazya lekulhu lo chazya lemiktzasa the sister-in-laws down here that
could not have had יבום yibum because it was אחות זיקתו achos
zikuso so לא חזיא למקצתה lo chazya lemiktzasa then even the מאמר
Maamar is not meaningful which is another way of saying a מאמר
דהיתרא Maamar de'heisera works a מאמר דאיסורא Maamar de'issura does not work.
So the גמרא Gemara tried to suggest maybe it's קנין גמור kinyan
gamur okay did not have a reason not to say it but
nevertheless רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya preferred this idea okay רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yirmeya preferred the idea that it's partial okay although you could in
theory have said it's קנין גמור. kinyan gamur. Then רב אשי Rav
Ashi tried to say that you still have to do חליצה chalitza
with לאה Leah but that clearly was against the משנה mishna that
that was משייר meshayer that he still had some relationship with לאה
Leah but that clearly is against the משנה. mishna. So the one
we're sort of most focusing on is the possibility that it is
לאה Leah is completely out of the picture but his relationship with
רחל Rachel is not yet a hundred percent. However the גמרא Gemara
now is going to seem it's going to look like go back
to the possibility we passed over before and say maybe his relationship
with רחל Rachel really is ממש mamash a hundred percent and he
would only have to do a גט get not a גט get
and חליצה. chalitza. So those are the two possibilities within בית שמאי
Beis Shammai we're contemplating. By the way how do we understand that
how this מאמר Maamar could have a biblical implication and get לאה
Leah off? Right I mean until now we've all been saying that
מאמר Maamar is דרבנן. derabbanan. So the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says gives a
פסוק pasuk for בית שמאי Beis Shammai and here's the ירושלמי'ס Yerushalmi's
פסוק pasuk for בית שמאי Beis Shammai it's יבמה יבא עליה ולקחה
לו לאשה ויבמה.
yevama yavo aleha velakacha
lo le'isha veyibmah.
I think
that's the
פסוק. pasuk. Guess what it says? ויבמה Veyibmah is יבום yibum and
ולקחה לו לאשה velakacha lo le'isha is מאמר Maamar קידושין. kiddushin. Wow.
And that actually קידושין kiddushin is also a way of if not
doing a hundred percent you know that's the question you hear some
things that are not exactly the same in terms of the impact
of it but basically sees that קידושין kiddushin is part of the
is a דאורייתא De'oraisa component or could be a דאורייתא De'oraisa component
of יבום. yibum. So that is בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. What?
It's a good דרשה? drasha?
It's a good דרשה drasha not bad right?
Certainly better than a lot of other דרשות. drashos. Alright so now
the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say like this. בעי רבא Ba'ei Rava
רבא Rava so רבא Rava asked. מאמר לבית שמאי Maamar le'Beis Shammai
assuming for בית שמאי Beis Shammai מאמר Maamar is a real type
of a קנין kinyan maybe even a קנין גמור. kinyan gamur. Now
we're going to push it even further. Maybe not only is it
קנין גמור kinyan gamur which we said the implication would be that
it would just be a גט get with רחל Rachel not even
חליצה chalitza but maybe it's even more than קידושין. kiddushin. What's more
than קידושין? kiddushin? נישואין. nisu'in. So let's take a look. בעי רבא
Ba'ei Rava רבא Rava asked מאמר לבית
שמאי נישואין עושה או אירוסין עושה. Maamar le'Beis Shammai nisu'in oseh o
eirusin oseh. Does it do נישואין nisu'in is it like even with
חופה chuppah or is it just like קידושין? kiddushin? Okay which is
pretty funny all you're doing is you do קידושין kiddushin הרי את
מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshes li you haven't done יבום yibum which
is the act of sex which is like נישואין. nisu'in.
So why
would you think that it would be? Yes so let's take a
look. Well this isn't rabbinic according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai remember
okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר ליה אביי Amar
lei Abaye so אביי Abaye said למהי הלכתא le'mai hilchasa what's the
implication? What do you want to suggest to say that it's like
נישואין? nisu'in? אילימא ליורשה ולטמא לה ולהפר נדריה ilima leyorshah uletamei lah
ulehafer nedareha here's what happens between you know that נישואין nisu'in adds
to קידושין. kiddushin. After נישואין nisu'in the husband
inherits
his wife if he's a כהן kohen he can become טמא tamei
to her and he can annul her vows even without her father's
participation. Okay there's a lot of other things also some דאורייתא De'oraisa
some דרבנן derabbanan we'll worry about that in a few weeks but
okay here's a handful of things
that
נישואין nisu'in adds. One minute רבא Rava says, רבא Rava says. Why
would this be more weightier than a bit than a standard קידושין?
kiddushin? השתא ארוסה בעלמא, Hashta arusa be'alma, standard ארוסה arusa who had
קידושין, kiddushin, תני בי חייא, Tani bei Chiyya, ארוסה arusa אשתו ארוסה,
ishto arusa, if his wife's an ארוסה arusa and there's not been
yet נשואין, nisu'in, לא אונן, lo onen, if she dies then he
does not have an אונן onen status to her, ולא מטמא לה,
ve-lo metamei-lah, and if he's a כהן kohen he doesn't become טמא
tamei to her. וכן היא, ve-chen hi, and she, לא אוננת, lo
onenet, if he dies she's not an אוננת onenet to him, ולא
מטמא לו, ve-lo metamei-lo, she doesn't become טמא tamei to him. Now
people say that's just רש"י Rashi says it's just thrown in because
she is never would be a כהן, kohen, I mean she'd be
a בת כהן, bat kohen, she would never have any restrictions of
becoming טמא. tamei. All right, other ראשונים rishonim try to say maybe
it's ברגל, be-regel, you're not supposed to be טמא ברגל. tamei be-regel.
Anyway, okay, but it's just קידושין, kiddushin, yet you don't have yet
these laws
of אבילות avelut and אנינות. aninut.
מתה אינו יורשה, meta eino yorshah, if she dies he does not
inherit her. מת הוא, met hu, if however he dies, גובה כתובתה,
govah ketuvatah, she can still collect her כתובה ketuvah in a case
when a כתובה ketuvah was written from the קידושין. kiddushin. So anyway,
the point is is that all of these sort of זכויות, zechuyot,
you know, sort of rights and changes of status happen at נשואין,
nisu'in, even when we're telling in a standard case of קידושין kiddushin
and נשואין. nisu'in. So if that's true by a classic קידושין kiddushin
she doesn't, those rights don't yet, haven't yet changed, those statuses haven't
changed, so
מאמר מיבעיא, maamar miba'aya, is there any question that with מאמר maamar
you don't have those? Now what is the קל וחומר, kal vachomer,
why should, why is it obvious that if you don't have it
by אירוסין eirusin you won't have it by מאמר? maamar? So רש"י
Rashi says, if you look at
רש"י, Rashi,
רש"י Rashi says
השתא ארוסה, hashta arusa, it's like three lines over where it says
כ"ה chof hey in that margin on the left between the גמרא
Gemara and
רש"י. Rashi. השתא ארוסה דקידושין דידה דאורייתא, Hashta arusa de-kiddushin didah de-oraita,
even when it's biblical, תני בי חייא אינה יורשה ואינו מטמא לה.
Tani bei Chiyya eina yorshah ve-eino metamei lah. מאמר יבמי מדרבנן הוא
דמדאורייתא יבמה יבא עליה רחמנא, Maamar yavmi mi-drabbanan hu de-me-oraita yevamah yavo
aleha rachmana, מיבעיא? miba'aya? So how could מאמר maamar which is only
rabbinic give you those things if קידושין kiddushin which is דאורייתא de-oraita
does not? Now the ראשונים rishonim ask, what is רש"י Rashi talking
about? We're dealing here according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, and according
to בית שמאי Beit Shammai he thinks that מאמר maamar has to
be biblical because it lets לאה Leah walk away without חליצה. chalitzah.
So they, so for example the ריטב"א Ritva says he doesn't like
רש"י's Rashi פשט, pshat, we're assuming מאמר maamar like בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is biblical, that's what lets לאה Leah walk away, but nevertheless
it's not as weighty as קידושין. kiddushin. Now in what way is
it not as weighty as קידושין? kiddushin? It demands a גט. get.
So he says there's another גמרא Gemara that says what would be
the consequence if the woman would actually sleep with another man after
this מאמר maamar before the act of יבום. yibum. So another גמרא
Gemara says that she would, it would not be considered the you
know adultery that you're חייב מיתה chayav mitah for, okay? It would
still be a לאו lav that she couldn't marry another man like
you know while she's waiting for יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitzah, but
even if this creates a status of אשתו, ishto, it's not with
the full weight of אשת איש. eishet ish. So we, we're taking
that for granted even if it's a דאורייתא, de-oraita, even if maybe
now you know it's only a גט get without חליצה chalitzah or
maybe we're assuming חליצה chalitzah would be needed so it's not a
hundred percent, but even if it's דאורייתא de-oraita and it lets לאה
Leah walk away, it's not the full weight as if it were
a classic case of קידושין. kiddushin. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says
if a normal קידושין kiddushin is not נשואין, nisu'in, you don't have
those rights or you don't have those changes of status, so why
should this which is not yet the same, has not yet gotten
to the same level, even if it is דאורייתא, de-oraita, why should
this count as נשואין? nisu'in? So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. Okay, you can't, what does this mean that it should count
as נשואין? nisu'in? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר ליה,
amar lei, so he said to him, השתא לא עבד בה מאמר—I'm
Hashta lo avad bah maamar sorry, I skipped a
line. ואלא בענין מסירה לחופה מאי? Ve-ella be-inyan mesirah la-chuppah mai? The
question is about the need, not about those rights. Those rights don't
kick in after מאמר maamar or whatever, those different statuses. The question
is about whether you're going to need an act of an act
of נשואין nisu'in later. אלא ענין מסירה לחופה מאי נשואין עושה? Ela
inyan mesirah la-chuppah mai nisu'in osah? Does this count as a חופה
chuppah ולא בעיא מסירה לחופה, ve-lo baya mesirah la-chuppah, and then you
won't later need to have a חופה? chuppah? או דילמא אירוסין עושה
בעיא מסירה לחופה? O dilma eirusin osah baya mesirah la-chuppah? Or maybe
it's only אירוסין eirusin and you will need—now what does this mean?
Does this mean that we think that a normal case of יבום
yibum after they do יבום yibum they have to do some act
of of going under the חופה chuppah and do some act of
נשואין? nisu'in? Like we never heard of anything like that. But maybe
he thinks that and maybe who knows. So anyway, so here his
question is or maybe as we're going to see that you basically
think that once you start down the קידושין kiddushin path by doing
מאמר, maamar, you didn't go straight to יבום, yibum, you did מאמר
maamar which is essentially קידושין, kiddushin, maybe now. because you started down
the path and דרבנן drabbanan you're supposed to do that before you
do ייבום, yibbum, maybe now דרבנן drabbanan we're going to demand for
there to be a נישואין nisuin as well. So here's רבא's Rava
question. Now they did they did אירוסין, eirusin, they did מאמר, ma'amar,
and now they're going to have sex and do ייבום. yibbum. Do
they also need a חופה? chuppah? Do they need a נישואין nisuin
or can they just go straight and do the ייבום yibbum or
do they also need a נישואין, nisuin, which is a reasonable question,
you could ask it even not according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai,
right, at the דרבנן drabbanan level. You do מאמר, ma'amar, do they
also want me to do a נישואין? nisuin? Okay, but here we're
asking that question according to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So let's take
a look. או דילמא אירוסין עושה בה נישואין בעי. o dilma eirusin
oseh bah nisuin ba'i. אמר ליה, Amar leih, השתא לא עבד בה
מאמר כתיב. hashta lo avad bah ma'amar ketiv.
So I sort of just told you a little bit of the
גמרא Gemara ahead. If he did not do מאמר, ma'amar, the verse
says the classic forget the whole מאמר ma'amar thing. Even בית שמאי
Beit Shammai admits that you don't have to do מאמר ma'amar even
if it works at a דאורייתא d'oraita level. So if you don't
do מאמר ma'amar it says יבמה יבא עליה, yevamah yavo aleha, that
the that the
brother-in-law shall have shall have sex with her, enter into her בעל
כרחה be'al korchah
even against her will. So now why it says בעל כרחה be'al
korchah here is not clear why it's emphasizing. This is always a
very obviously you know difficult הלכה halacha to deal with. But it
seems to be saying that if they're doing it sort of willingly
and consensually then that maybe itself is חופה. chuppah. So why isn't
every act of sex, it gets the whole question of what חופה
chuppah is. But like every act of once they're actually having sex
as a married couple that itself should be a חופה chuppah even
like in a forget a ייבום yibbum case, in normal cases, right?
They do the קידושין kiddushin and then they start living together as
husband and wife that counts as חופה. chuppah. Okay,
so how here would you ever have a case of an act
of ייבום yibbum that wouldn't itself already be an act of חופה?
chuppah? Only if she wasn't really agreeing to it. Okay, again very
difficult that that... קידושין Kiddushin can't be...
Yeah,
I understand, you shouldn't and we're going to see that the בית
דין Beit Din is going to try to compel him to do
חליצה. chalitzah. But הלכתית halachically if he went ahead and and did
it, it would still it would still work even if he shouldn't.
Nobody's saying he should, but if he did it would be effective
and it's very you know difficult, right.
You know, I'd like to understand at least some of the בעל
כרחהs be'al korchah are not like literal literal rapes, but you know
she you know somewhat like she doesn't want to but she's going
along type of a thing. But nevertheless you know it's still very
very difficult. You know, I I really can't make it better, yeah.
קידושין Kiddushin can't be בעל כרחה. be'al korchah.
Right, but the but the sex can be. Okay, so if there
was a case of a normal couple had קידושין kiddushin and then
they started living together as husband and wife, that's נישואין. nisuin. But
in this case what if they it was a case that was
not consensual sex? It wouldn't count as נישואין. nisuin. Here he says
what about this case? Okay, so here he says look, if the
normal act of ייבום yibbum non-consensual sex still works, so how and
that's full then with all the changed statuses, how here could you
say that you need an idea of מסירה לחופה? mesirah l'chuppah? Any
sex automatically makes her נשואה, nesuah, you know gives her full status.
So the גמרא Gemara says, alright, so the גמרא Gemara says, עבד
בה מאמר מיבעיא? avad bah ma'amar mibaya? So if there's מאמר ma'amar
why should you ask, of course once they have sex that that's
going to count however that sex took place. So אמר ליה amar
leih he said back to him yes, שאני אומר sh'ani omer because
I say כל העושה מאמר ביבמתו, kol ha'oseh ma'amar b'yevamto, anybody who
does מאמר ma'amar with his sister-in-law,
פרחה הימנו זיקת יבמין. parcha mimenu zikat yevamin. It actually again and
now תוספות Tosafot says שאני אומר sh'ani omer because still presumably we're
working within בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. But I say once you according
at least going to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, once you do מאמר
ma'amar the whole aspect of ייבום yibbum goes away. Like maybe again
like we said before, not even חליצה chalitzah would be needed, וחל
עליו זיקת אירוסין. v'chal alav zikat eirusin. You're totally within the קידושין
kiddushin track. So again bracketing the very difficult גמרא Gemara about sex
בעל כרחה, be'al korchah, you know this is a fascinating type of
of a model that once we say מאמר ma'amar works דאורייתא d'oraita
for בית שמאי Beit Shammai and sort of makes לאה Leah אחות
אשתו achot ishto etc., right, maybe it completely shifts the whole track.
If you go ahead and you do ייבום yibbum that works one
way, that's about the act of sex and maybe you know again
doesn't even it'll even work even בעל כרחה. be'al korchah. But once
however he puts himself on a different track, he does the לקיחה
לו לאשה lekicha lo l'ishah not the יבמה, yibamah, he starts on
that track, then maybe that works according to the normal type of
of קידושין kiddushin model. And therefore you would need a normal type
of a מסירה לחופה. mesirah l'chuppah. Okay, so that then becomes the
question. And according to that presumably if that's true that you're on
a different track and there's no more זיקה, zikah, then presumably here
again it would be up here you wouldn't even need חליצה, chalitzah,
it would only be a גט. get. Okay, so that's his question
whether there's going to have to be a חופה chuppah here as
well. If you put yourself on a different track the answer is
yes, if you're still on the ייבום yibbum track the answer is
no.
Okay, so מאי mai what's הלכה? halacha? תא שמע, Ta shema, שומרת
יבם, shomeret yavam, a woman waiting for ייבום, yibbum, בין יבם אחד
בין שני יבמים, bein yavam echad bein shenei yevamin, whether there are
two brother-in-laws or one brother-in-law, so they both there's some זיקה zikah
with this woman. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר יפר *Rabbi Eliezer
omer yafer*. And now what happens if she goes and makes a
נדר *neder*? Can these men be מפר *mefer* her נדר *neder*, okay,
these men that are her quasi-husband? Now, remember the הלכה halacha. *halacha*
that if there's קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* without נישואין *nissuim*, the הפרת נדרים
hafarat nedarim? *hafarat nedarim* takes place as with a combination of the
husband, the ארוס *arus*, and the father. Okay, so here, for them
to be able to do it alone, you would have to sort
of give her almost like a נישואין *nissuim* status, okay? And there's
also the question, what if there are two of them? Then it's
not even clear who's going to be the one that's going to
sort of actualize the זיקה zika *zika*. So let's take a look.
So this woman who's waiting for יבום yibbum, *yibum*, רבי אליעזר אומר
יפר *Rabbi Eliezer omer yafer*, that the man, the brother-in-law, can do
a, can annul the vows. רבי יהושע אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua omer*, well,
we'll see what that means, okay. רבי יהושע אומר *Rabbi Yehoshua omer*,
let's say, let's say it means either one can do it. רבי
יהושע אומר לאחד ולא לשנים *Rabbi Yehoshua omer leachad velo lishnayim*, only
if there's one brother-in-law can he annul the vows, but if there
are two, they cannot because neither of them have a strong enough
relationship with her. רבי עקיבא אומר לא לאחד ולא לשנים *Rabbi Akiva
omer lo leachad velo lishnayim*, not even two, but even one cannot
annul the
vows; the זיקה *zika* is not strong enough. ובעינן בה *vabainan bah*,
and then we asked on this. בשלמא לרבי עקיבא *bishlama leRabbi Akiva*,
I get Rabbi Akiva, סבר אין זיקה אפילו לאחד *savar ain zika
afilu leachad*, that the זיקה *zika* even with one doesn't exist or
is not significant enough to allow him to annul the vows. רבי
יהושע לאחד יש זיקה לתרי אין זיקה *Rabbi Yehoshua leachad yesh zika
letrei ain zika*, and Rabbi Yehoshua also makes sense, that there is
with one, there's a זיקה *zika* because and it's clearly about him,
so he can annul the vows, and not with two. Again, we're
sort of ignoring the נישואין *nissuim* question, but we'll get back to
that. אלא לרבי אליעזר *ela leRabbi Eliezer*, but Rabbi Eliezer, that doesn't
distinguish, הנה נמי דקסבר יש זיקה *hinei nami dekasavar yesh zika*, let
him hold that there is זיקה *zika*. בשלמא לאחד מפר *bishlama leachad
mefer*,
I get that if there's one he can be מפר *mefer*. אלא
לתרי אמאי *ela letrei amai*, how can you do it with two?
Meaning how can, you know, how can one of them, A, you'd
have to say that each person, even though it's not clear who's
going to do the יבום yibbum. *yibum*, each person
has a strong enough זיקה *zika*. But even if that's true, how
can you say one of them does הפרה *hafara*? Wouldn't you need
both of them to do הפרה *hafara*? So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, so
that's our question. ואמר רבי אמי בר אבא *ve'amar Rabbi Ami bar
Abba* or whoever, said Rabbi Ami, הכא Hacha, במאי עסקינן *hacha bemai
askinan*,
here's the case what we're talking about, כגון שעשה בה מאמר maamar
*kegon she'asah bah ma'amar*, that
it's not just a simple case of a woman waiting for יבום
yibbum *yibum*, an act of מאמר Maamar, *ma'amar* was already done with
this woman by one of the guys. ובית שמאי היא דאמרי מאמר
maamar קונה koneh קנין גמור kinyan gamur. *uVeit Shammai hi de'amri ma'amar
koneh kinyan gamur*, and it's Beit Shammai, and that's why he can
go ahead and do the הפרת נדרים hafarat nedarim. *hafarat nedarim*. So
we
have said that this case is talking with מאמר maamar *ma'amar*. So
now that we're talking with מאמר maamar *ma'amar*, we see our answer.
אי אמרת בשלמא נישואין עושה *ei amart bishlama nissuim osah*, if
מאמר maamar *ma'amar* makes her like נישואין *nissuim*, משום הכי מפר *mishum
hachi mefer*. Now, now we under... by the way, so that explains
Rabbi Eliezer, why does Rabbi Eliezer say one guy? Because only one
guy did מאמר maamar, *ma'amar* and it takes, focuses on that one
guy and takes out the other. But now that we've introduced מאמר
maamar *ma'amar* to this scenario, we see that with מאמר maamar *ma'amar*
you're like, she's like a נישואין *nissuim* and there could be הפרת
נדרים hafarat nedarim? *hafarat nedarim*. So
that shows that מאמר maamar *ma'amar* works to create her like a
נישואין *nissuim*. Now by the way, this is going back to the
original way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* framed it. If you remember, the
גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* said no no no, הפרת נדרים hafarat nedarim *hafarat
nedarim* whatever, that wouldn't work, we're only talking about whether she needs
חופה *chuppah*. Now we're going back to what the easier way of
framing the question, which is no, maybe really מאמר maamar *ma'amar* jumps
her automatically to a נישואין *nissuim* status and you can do הפרת
נדרים hafarat nedarim *hafarat nedarim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying
that's clearly how we're explaining this issue of הפרת נדרים hafarat nedarim?
*hafarat nedarim*, that there was מאמר maamar *ma'amar* and she has a
נישואין *nissuim* status. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי אמרת בשלמא
נישואין עושה *ei amart bishlama nissuim osah*, if it's like a נישואין
*nissuim*, משום הכי מפר *mishum hachi mefer*, that's why they can be
מפר *mefer* and there's only a question one or two or whatever.
אלא אי אמרת אירוסין eirusin, עושה *ela ei amart eirusin osah*, but
if it only is at the אירוסין *eirusin* level, היכי מצי מפר
*heichi matzi mefer*? How can he do הפרה *hafara*? It needs to
be done together with the father. דתנן נערה מאורסה אביה ובעלה מפירין
נדריה *detnan na'arah me'orasah aviha u'ba'alah mefirin nedareha*. So it should have
had to say together with the father. Now, somebody's going to say
wait wait, what if the father's dead? Maybe that scenario? Okay, so
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* has already thought about that. So look at תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot*, he says אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה *aviha u'ba'alah mefirin nedareha*,
ואם אין לה אב או שאינה ברשות האב לא מצי מפר *ve'im
ain lah av o she'einah birshut ha'av lo matzi mefer*, כדאמרינן בנדרים
*keda'amrin beNedarim*. Okay, so the husband, the ארוס *arus* cannot do it
without a father even if there is no father. Now by the
way, even if the father's alive, he's irrelevant now. Why? Because she
got married to another man. So although the father is irrelevant, right,
so you know, or might be around depends if she was ארוסה
arusah *arusah* to the other man or נשואה nesuah. *nesuah* to the
other man. Anyway, so it's still he shouldn't be able to do
it as an, if it's just an ארוס *arus* and an ארוסה
arusah *arusah* status. So one minute, אלא אי אמרת אירוסין היכי מצי
מפר והתנן נערה מאורסה אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה *ela ei amart eirusin
heichi matzi mefer vehatnan na'arah me'orasah aviha u'ba'alah mefirin nedareha*? So אמר
רב Rav נחמן בר יצחק *amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, so you
see it's
a pretty good proof that
there's מאמר *ma'amar* and we're assuming it allows for הפרת נדרים hafarat
nedarim *hafarat nedarim*. So according to Beit Shammai, מאמר נישואין עושה *ma'amar
nissuim osah*. אמר רב Rav נחמן בר יצחק מאי מפר מפר בשותפות
*amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak mai mefer mefer beshutfut*. Okay, it doesn't
mean by himself, it means together with the יפר ויפירו *yafer veyaperu*.
Yeah, I understood the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* going to say that. It
means together with the father and we're still going to insist that
it's אירוסין *eirusin*.
So the גמרא Gemara says ולאלעזר דאמר מאמר לבית שמאי אינו קונה
אלא לדחות בצרה בלבד.
U'l'Elazar d'amar maamar l'Beit Shammai
eino koneh ela lidchot b'tzarah bilvad.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, צא. tzei. All
of this discussion was assuming מאמר could be קנין גמור. kinyan gamur.
Okay, but according to what we said earlier, רבי אליעזר said that
it's not קונה koneh. even and it only sort of pushes the
צרה tzarah off, but it's not really קונה. So according to that,
right, and he even said it's משייר. meshayer. So אמאי מיפר בשותפות?
amai meifer b'shutfut? How, how does any of this work? We're back
to the problem. All of the possibility that something was working here
was assuming that it was קנין גמור. kinyan gamur And therefore it
either made her an ארוסה arusah, and therefore he could do it
together with the father, which was a weak answer but okay, or
it made her a נשואה. nesuah. Okay, but both of those assumed
at least that you were in the קנין גמור kinyan gamur, category.
So now you're down here with the משייר.
meshayer. So if it according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai
it's not even full, so how does any of this work? Even
at the ארוסה arusah level it doesn't work because it's not even
full, it's not full. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמאי מיפר בשותפות?
amai meifer b'shutfut? אמר לך רב אלעזר, Amar lach Rav Elazar, אימא
דאמרי אנא אינו קונה אלא לדחות לצרה. eima d'amri ana eino koneh
ela lidchot l'tzarah. When did I say that his relationship with רחל
Rachel is not strong enough except to push off צרה, tzarah, לאה,
Leah, but it's not really full with רחל? Rachel? בלבד דלא סגי
לה בגיטא. bilvad d'lo sagi lah b'gita. That a גט get won't
be enough, you need a גט get and חליצה. chalitzah. He hasn't
so... okay, but if that's true, how still how did you do
הפרת נדרים? hafarat nedarim I mean that requires to be an ארוסה,
arusah if not a נשואה. nesuah אלא בעי נמי חליצה. Ela ba'ei
nami chalitzah. But הפרת נדרים מי אמר? hafarat nedarim mi amar? But
maybe he can still do הפרת נדרים. So which is again quite
a strange story. So I don't get it. So what does... so
why? I mean it still begs the question why? I mean if
she's still going to need a חליצה chalitzah and it's not complete,
why can he do הפרת נדרים? Maybe he really says that you've
got two things going on here. She's both an ארוסה arusah. and
at the ארוסה arusah level he can do הפרת נדרים with the
father, but she still has it left being a יבמה. yevamah. And
from that perspective she needs חליצה. chalitzah. So we're not saying she's
not an ארוסה. arusah, The קידושין kiddushin, is a hundred percent, but
it hasn't yet removed the יבמה yevamah status. Even by בית שמאי?
Beit Shammai? Yeah, well that's what we're saying, that's what he was
saying his thing according to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Okay. So that's
one answer. ואי בעית אימא, V'ei ba'it eima, and if you want
you could say, אמר לך רב אלעזר, Amar lach Rav Elazar, Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak, מי ניחא? mi nicha? I don't get it. Even
if you say קנין גמור, this is not a good answer just
to say he's doing it with the father. מי קתני יפירו? Mi
katani yafeiru? It doesn't say they will annul. יפר קתני. Yeifer katani.
One. So it's not a good answer. Don't tell me he's doing
it with the father. So even if it's אירוסין, this doesn't make
sense. So then why are they annulling it? אלא הכא במאי עסקינן,
Ela hacha b'mai askinan, what's the case? שעמדה בדין ופסקו לה מזונות
משלו. She'amda b'din u'pasku lah mezonot mishelo. Basically it was a case
where all of the brothers were refusing to do anything about it.
I don't want to do יבום, yibbum, I don't want to do
חליצה, chalitzah, don't bother me about it. So what they did is
she took him to a court case. You gotta do something buddy.
And the בית דין beis din basically said until you act on
this, you are not... we're going to treat her like your wife
and you're going to have to support her. You're going to have
to pay for her, you know, for her upkeep, מזונות. mezonot. And
in a pre-nuptial... so yeah, and then hopefully then that'll get him
to act one way or the other way. There you go. So
in that case, once he's already supporting her and he has a
financial sort of relationship and responsibility towards her, even though הלכתית, halachically,
the גמרא's Gemara. going to say she's not an ארוסה or נשואה
yet, but we can assume that her vows are going to be
done, you know, implicitly assuming the husband agrees. Assuming not the husband,
the brother-in-law, because she wants to sort of, you know, she wants
the relationship to work. וכהא דרב פנחס משמיה דרבא. U'kh'ha d'Rav Pinchas
mishmei d'Rava. דאמר רב פנחס משמיה דרבא. D'amar Rav Pinchas mishmei d'Rava.
כל הנודרת על דעת בעלה היא נודרת. Kol ha'noderet al da'at ba'ala
hi noderet. So it's not the classic הפרת נדרים that he has
to hear within twenty-four hours or whatever, it's just an assumption that
she's going to do it, you know, pending his agreement. Of course
if that's true, who needs the תורה's Torah's category of הפרת נדרים?
You'll just always say that the wife does it pending the husband's
agreement. But the גמרא Gemara makes it a not a technical הפרת
נדרים like an implicit stipulation and תנאי tnai because of a unique
type of a relationship. Okay, so that's sort of how it deals
with it. But for us, I want to remind us we have
some amazing possibilities in בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. First of all, it
sounds like if לאה Leah walks away without חליצה chalitzah it's דאורייתא.
d'Oraita. מאמר, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi learned it from לקיחה לאישה. lekicha l'ishah.
How complete is it? We have the possibility that it's full קידושין,
kiddushin. all they need now is a גט, get, wouldn't need חליצה.
chalitzah. Even further, maybe it's נשואין, nisuin, that he has הפרת נדרים
and all those types of things. Or we have things that are
a little bit less than full קידושין. Both need a גט get
and חליצה. chalitzah. Although even there, the גמרא Gemara suggested that that
might not be because it's not a hundred percent. It might be
a hundred percent in terms of she's his wife, it's a full
ארוסה, but she also still retains a status of a יבמה yevamah
until he actually does the act of יבום. yibbum. That's a way
of understanding like a double status, not a partial status. Okay, but
again as I told you, another גמרא says it would still not
have the consequence of like אשת איש, eishet ish, you know, so...
So it still is an interesting type of a status here and
the idea that once you put yourself on a
track of מאמר *ma'amar*, you might now
be on a complete different track that like רבא *Rava* said it
really removes זיקת יבמים *zikat yevamim*. You switched the whole dynamic and
the relationship. Okay, quite fascinating according to בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*. Now
we finally turn to today's דף *daf*, top of ל"א עמוד א'
*lamed aleph amud aleph*. Okay, it'll go quicker, but we only have
about 22 minutes, so let's see how far we can go. I'm
sure if I just read it and don't explain it, we can
get caught up. Okay, שלושה אחים *shlosha achim*. This most of this
will be pretty straightforward. Ha ha ha. שלושה אחים, שניים מהם נשואים
שתי אחיות *shlosha achim, shnayim meihem nesuim shtei achayot*, three brothers, two
married to two sisters like our classic case, ואחד נשוי נכרית V'echad
nasui nochrit. *ve'echad nasui nochrit*, and one is married to a unrelated
woman. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות Met echad miba'alei ha'achayot, *meit echad miba'alei
ha'achayot*, so these are going to be all different, these are going
to be all different permutations of the case. Okay, you've got ראובן
Reuven *Reuven* and שמעון Shimon *Shimon* married again to our רחל Rachel,
*Rachel* and לאה Leah *Leah*, and you've got לוי Levi *Levi* here
married to דבורה Devorah. *Devorah*, okay, not related. Okay, and the whole
question is going to be who is going to die and who
is going to marry whom and in what order? Okay, let's go
through them. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות *meit echad miba'alei ha'achayot*, one of
the ones married to the sister died, שמעון Shimon *Shimon* died, וכנס
נשוי נכרית nochrit, את אשתו *vechanas nasui nochrit et ishto*, okay, so
ראובן Reuven, *Reuven* died, לאה Leah *Leah* did יבום yibbum *yibum*, okay,
וכנס נשוי נכרית את אשתו ומת u-met, *vechanas nasui nochrit et ishto
umeit*. And then לוי Levi *Levi* died. הראשונה *harishona*, the first woman,
רחל Rachel. *Rachel*, she was the one that first became the widow,
okay, הראשונה יוצאה משום אחות אשה achot isha *harishona yotza mishum achot
isha*. רחל Rachel *Rachel* walks away because of his wife's sister. והשנייה
*vehashniya*, and דבורה Devorah *Devorah* walks away משום צרתה *mishum tzarata*. עשה
בה מאמר ומת Asa bah maamar u-met, *asa bah ma'amar umeit*, now
if שמעון Shimon *Shimon* went ahead and, I'm sorry,
if לוי Levi *Levi* instead of doing
יבום yibbum *yibum* did מאמר *ma'amar*, back to that, and then he
died, now we're dealing with בית הלל *Beit Hillel* not בית שמאי
*Beit Shammai*. So רחל Rachel *Rachel* isn't really his what,
it it well,
רחל Rachel *Rachel* is his wife's sister, but she's only an ערוה
ervah, *erva* in the יבום yibbum *yibum* category because she's sort of
quasi married to לוי Levi *Levi*, right? Right? So so this only
sort of affects it's going to affect דבורה's Devorah. *Devorah's* status because
she's quasi married to לוי Levi *Levi*. So דבורה Devorah *Devorah* is
not really צרת ערוה ervah, *tzarat erva*, דבורה Devorah *Devorah* is sort
of צרת quasi ערוה ervah *tzarat quasi erva*. Okay, I've got to
stop thinking בית שמאי *Beit Shammai* now. No longer בית שמאי *Beit
Shammai*. Okay, so in that case, ומת, u'met, נכרית חולצת ולא מתייבמת
*umeit, nochrit choletzet velo mityabemet*. So so רחל Rachel, *Rachel* obviously walks
away, because if she were fully married to לוי Levi *Levi*, she'd
be an ערוה erva *erva*, so if she's quasi married, she's an
ערוה erva. *erva*, she walks away. But דבורה Devorah *Devorah* needs חליצה
chalitza, *chalitza*, can't have יבום yibbum *yibum* because רבנן *rabanan* she's a
צרת quasi ערוה erva *tzarat quasi erva*. Okay, but at least but
at least does need חליצה chalitza *chalitza* because because רחל Rachel *Rachel*
was not really married to לוי Levi *Levi*. So דאורייתא de'oraita *de'oraita*
חליצה chalitza. *chalitza* as it were? Yeah. טעמא דעבד בה מאמר *ta'ama
de'avad bah ma'amar*, so the only reason says the גמרא *Gemara* that
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* has to that you know that דבורה Devorah, *Devorah*
is in a problematic status is because לוי Levi *Levi* did מאמר
*ma'amar* and made רחל Rachel *Rachel* his quasi wife. Okay, and that
now makes דבורה Devorah. *Devorah* quasi צרת ערוה ervah *tzarat erva*. הא
לא עבד בה מאמר, נכרית יבומי נמי מייתבמא *ha lo avad bah
ma'amar, nochrit yibumi nami mityabma*. If he had not done מאמר *ma'amar*,
the implication of the משנה mishna, *mishna* is ראובן Reuven? *Reuven* dies,
okay, לוי Levi *Levi* did nothing, and then לוי Levi *Levi* died.
So שמעון Shimon *Shimon* here, obviously he's nothing with רחל Rachel *Rachel*
because it's his wife's sister, but he could go ahead and do
יבום yibbum *yibum* with דבורה Devorah. *Devorah*. Why not? That's the implication
of the משנה mishna *mishna*. If there was no מאמר *ma'amar*, there'd
be no relationship here and he'd be free to do יבום yibum.
*yibum* with דבורה Devorah. *Devorah*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, so what
does that show you? אמר רב Rav נחמן, זאת אומרת אין זיקה
ואפילו בחד אחא *amar Rav Nachman, zot omeret ein zika va'afilu bechad
acha*. There's no זיקה *zika* even with one brother as opposed to
before we were all talking about אחות achos זקוקתו *achot zekukato* whatever.
He's saying this משנה mishna *mishna* at least holds there's no זיקה
*zika*. Why? Because לוי Levi *Levi* might not have done מאמר *ma'amar*
with רחל Rachel. *Rachel*, but guess what he has with רחל Rachel
*Rachel*? א זיקה *a zika*, right? Even if he did nothing, he
had a זיקה *zika*. So after לוי Levi. *Levi* died, and שמעון
Shimon *Shimon* didn't have a זיקה *zika*, right? Because it was his
wife's sister. So there was only one relevant brother that could do
יבום yibum *yibum*, there was one brother and there was a זיקה
*zika*, then he died. Why doesn't שמעון Shimon *Shimon* say, oh, we're
back to being a type of a צרת ערוה ervah *tzarat erva*
because רחל Rachel *Rachel* was a quasi wife based on the זיקה
*zika*. We don't say that. So you see that the זיקה *zika*
is not meaningful and אין זיקה *ein zika*. Okay, and therefore if
he didn't do יבום yibum. *yibum*, רחל Rachel *Rachel* is irrelevant and
he can go if he didn't do מאמר *ma'amar*, רחל Rachel *Rachel*
is irrelevant and he can go ahead and do יבום yibum. *yibum*
with דבורה Devorah *Devorah*. All right, we're going to reassess that later,
but that's what we're saying now. Next משנה mishna *mishna*. שלושה אחים
*shlosha achim*, same case except different order of dying and יבום yibum
*yibum*. שלשה אחים שנים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות, two married to two
sisters, ואחד מהם נשוי נכרית, ve-echad mehem nasuy nochrit, מת הנשוי נכרית.
met ha-nasuy nochrit. Now what happened is not that ראובן Reuven died
first, but לוי Levi. died first. Okay. So step number one is
that לוי Levi died. מת הנשוי נכרית. Met ha-nasuy nochrit. וביכנס אחד
מבעלי האחיות את אשתו, U-vikhenas echad mi-ba'alei ha-achayot et ishto, and then
step number two is, here ראובן, Reuven right, who is married to
רחל, Rachel now he also does יבום yibum with דבורה. Devorah. Okay,
that's step number two. Then guess what's going to happen to ראובן?
Reuven Okay, ומת, and then ראובן Reuven died. Okay, so now we've
got שמעון Shimon. again. Now we've got שמעון Shimon with two wives,
right, with one is ערווה erva and one is צרת ערווה. tzarat
erva. So that's the same הלכה. halacha? Okay, so in that case,
ומת הראשונה יוצאה משום אחות אשה והשנייה משום צרתה. u-met ha-rishona yotzei'a
mishum achot isha ve-ha-sheniya mishum tzaratah. עשה בה מאמר ומת, let's say
instead of doing יבום, yibum he had done מאמר with דבורה Devorah
and then he died. So what's the הלכה? halacha הנכרית חולצת ולא
מתייבמת. Ha-nochrit choletzet ve-lo mityabemet. Same story that he does חליצה, chalitza
not יבום. yibum Now this is like the flip, right? Case number
one was that he had done מאמר with, again, that you know
לוי Levi had done מאמר with רחל. Rachel So רחל Rochel was
sort of like the, was the ערווה erva who was quasi the
wife, who was the quasi wife. Right? That was the case, right?
And לאה Leah was the צרה. tzara. Okay, in this case, A
and B, in this case, the מאמר was with דבורה. Devorah Right?
And then he died. So in this case, right, the ערווה erva
is the wife, right, the real wife here is רחל Rochel and
that's the real ערווה. erva. The ערווה erva is the wife and
דבורה Devorah is the quasi-צרת ערווה. tzarat erva. You got that? Okay.
So that's, it's the flip of the other case. Okay here the
ערווה erva is the actual relationship, רחל Rachel walks away and she's
like the quasi-צרת ערווה, tzarat erva, but according to מדאורייתא mi-de'oraita though,
right, שמעון Shimon, would have to do יבום yibum; with דבורה Devorah
because מדאורייתא, mi-de'oraita, when לוי Levi. died, שמעון Shimon also could have
done יבום yibum with דבורה Devorah and that doesn't go away. So
even though now he's done מאמר, okay, and made her a quasi-צרת
ערווה, tzarat erva, right, she still, he still needs to do חליצה
chalitza? to get דבורה, Devorah to free דבורה. Devorah Okay, so in
this case though, this case was a quasi, the ערווה erva was
the quasi wife, here the ערווה erva is the definite wife and
she, the צרה tzara is the quasi-צרת ערווה. tzarat erva. You got
that? Okay. So that's, it's the flip of the other case. The
גמרא says, הא תו למה לי? ha tu lama li? Why
do I need this
second case? היינו הך. Hainu hach. It's essentially the same, that the
מאמר sort of pulls the other woman into the, into the picture
and then it's not דאורייתא so you still need to do חליצה.
chalitzah. So the גמרא says no. השתא, Hashta, not only is it
the same, it's like a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה התם דאחות
אשה הויה צרה לנכרית, U-ma hatam de-achot isha havaya tzara le-nochrit, when
the wife's sister was the צרה tzara to the נכרית, right? In
the first case, the real wife was דבורה. Devorah The wife's sister,
she was quasi-married, that was the one that was being connected through
the מאמר and nevertheless that was enough to problematize יבום yibum with
דבורה. Devorah. ומה התם דאחות אשה הויה צרה לנכרית U-ma hatam de-achot
isha havaya tzara le-nochrit and אחות אשה achos isha was the one
that
through the מאמר got connected to דבורה Devorah, where there was a
real
obligation of יבום yibum, and nevertheless it's enough to problematize the דבורה.
Devorah, ואמרת נכרית אסורה, Ve-amarta nochrit asura, and nevertheless you have to
do חליצה chalitzah. with דבורה Devorah even though that was the real
obligation and the ערווה erva was only quasi-brought in. הכא, here the
real wife is רחל, Rachel so it starts with being fundamentally problematic.
הכא דנכרית הויה צרה לאחות אשה, Hacha de-nochrit havaya tzara le-achot isha,
the wife's sister, the ערווה erva is the real wife and it's
דבורה Devorah, that's being quasi-pulled in. So לא כל שכן, lo kol
she-ken, how much more so are you not going to be able
to do יבום yibum, with דבורה Devorah and going to have to
do חליצה? chalitza So the second case, it's the same הלכה halacha.
and if anything it's more obvious than the first משנה, Mishna okay?
Because here the basic obligation to דבורה Devorah was already, you know,
דבורה Devorah wasn't even the real wife. So the גמרא says, תנא
הכא תנא ברישא. Tana hacha tana bereisha. You know what, you're right.
This second משנה Mishna is much more obvious and therefore this משנה
Mishna was the first משנה Mishna that was taught when these הלכות
halachot were learned. והא חזיא להיתרא ושריא. Ve-ha chazya le-heitera ve-sharya. And
he actually initially actually there was a thinking that the, that I'm
sorry, I'm sorry, תנא הכא תנא ברישא. Tana hacha tana bereisha. No,
first he taught the one above, right? Um, wait a minute, I'm
sorry, no no no, I was right the first way. Okay, first
he taught this one, the one where דבורה Devora. is only being
brought in in a quasi way in a quasi way. And this
is the one that's more obvious that she's going to need. chalitzah
that you're not going to be able to do יבום. yibum. והכא
חזי להיתירא ושריא. Vehacha chazi lehiteira vesharia. And he actually initially the
תנא Tanna thought that the first משנה Mishna would be allowed. In
the first משנה Mishna where דבורה Devora. was the real wife and
רחל Rachel was the one that was quasi brought in, he figured
well look, דבורה Devora, is the real wife, well maybe we should
even allow you to do יבום yibum, since רחל is being brought
in through this מאמר and the real obligation is with דבורה. Devora?
So he maybe even thought that in the first משנה Mishna, to
allow יבום. yibum Okay? והדר חזי לאיסורא. Vehadar chazi leisura. And then
he thought no, we should actually make that case forbidden as well.
Okay? So really you're right. The first one is the second משנה
Mishna is much more obvious. The first משנה Mishna. was like a
later move to make even that case forbidden. ואיידי דחביבא ליה אקדמה.
Ve'aidi dechaviva lei akdema. And because that second משנה Mishna. was like
a dear to him, the author, because he realized like, oh, this
is a חידוש, chiddush, we're even going to make this case forbidden.
So he said it first. ומשנה לא זזה ממקומה. Umishna lo zazah
mimekomah. But then he didn't take out the second משנה, Mishna even
though the second משנה mishna now became superfluous and obvious. Okay?
So it's basically saying
you're right, the first one is more obvious, but the first one,
I'm sorry, once you say the first one, the second one is
obvious, but nevertheless we taught both. The first one actually was the
next move, the bigger חידוש. chiddush. By the way, תוספות just says
why was that very complicated? Why don't you just say what you
normally say which is, you know, זו ואין צריך לומר זו, Zu
ve'ein tzarich lomar zu, X and it goes without saying, you know,
the next one.
תוספות says that you can say if you throw in two extra
words or an extra line in order to which is really superfluous,
you can say it goes without saying this other case. Here you
have a whole extra משנה. mishna You've redescribed the whole scenario, so
you're not going to just say that that was done like, you
know, just and by the way, it goes without saying. So we
have this whole explanation that it was a move to go from
one to the other. Okay, but now we're saying whether the זיקה
brings in the, whether the basic obligation is here, the basic obligation
is to דבורה, Devora okay, and the מאמר that brings in a
quasi ערוה, there you really could have thought who cares? The basic
obligation is to דבורה, Devora. do יבום. yibum Nevertheless, we say even
in this case do חליצה. And then it goes without saying when
the basic obligation was to the when the wife was basically the
ערוה, so it started out without any יבום yibum, and דבורה Devora
was brought in in this quasi way that there's not going to
be יבום yibum, with דבורה, Devora. there's only going to be חליצה.
Okay. Next משנה. mishna, Third scenario.
שלושה אחים שניים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות ואחד נשוי נכרית.
Shlosha achin shnayim mehem
nesuim shtei achayot ve'echad nasui nochrit. Same start-off. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות
וכנס נשוי נכרית את אשתו. Met echad miba'alei ha'achayot vechanas nasui nochrit
et ishto. So sounds like we said before. What else is like
this that can be done? We've had we've had the one married
to דבורה dying and we've had the one married to רחל dying.
The one married to לאה Leah is just the case is just
the parallel of the one married to רחל. What's the other possibility?
So the other possibility is not who gets married but who then
dies after the marriage. Okay. So מת אחד מבעלי האחיות, ראובן Reuven
dies. Then לוי Levi. of course does יבום yibum because he's the
only one that can do יבום yibum here. But then instead of
לוי Levi, dying, here's what happens. וכנס נשוי נכרית את אשתו ומתה
אשתו של שני. Vechanas nasui nochrit et ishto umeta ishto shel sheni.
Okay, ואחר כך מת נשוי נכרית. Ve'achar kach met nasui nochrit. Then
לאה Leah dies. Okay? So this happened: one, ראובן Reuven dies; I
guess two, יבום; yibum. three, לאה Leah, dies; and now finally, okay,
what's going to happen? And now שמעון Shimon. dies. Okay? So now
did I get that right? No, no, שמעון Shimon didn't die and
there's nothing left to happen. Excuse me. Excuse me. Then there's nothing
left to happen. Then לוי Levi dies. Right. Then לוי Levi dies.
Okay, thank you. Then לוי Levi dies. So now שמעון Shimon has
רחל and דבורה before him. Okay? Is רחל אחות אשתו? achot ishto?
No, he's no right. לאה Leah has died. If he only divorced
לאה, Leah right it would be because אחות אשתו achot ishto is
even while she's divorced or whatever but we'll talk about that but
okay, I mean, but right now לאה Leah has died, so רחל
is no longer אחות אשתו. achot ishto. And now when רחל and
דבורה fall before him, there's no ערוה anymore because לאה Leah had
died before that event occurred. Okay, so in that case, נשוי נכרית
ומת נשוי נכרית, Nasui nochrit umet nasui nochrit, right and then לוי
dies. הרי זו אסורה עליו עולמית הואיל ונאסרה עליו שעה אחת. Harei
zu asurah alav olamit ho'il venesrah alav sha'ah achat. So what the
משנה mishna. says actually is not that way, that actually that רחל
remains forbidden to him עולמית olamit because she was אסורה עליו שעה
אחת. asurah alav sha'ah achat. What was the שעה אחת? sha'ah achat?
The שעה אחת sha'ah achat was that ראובן Reuven died, at that
stage לאה Leah hadn't died yet, right? So רחל became here at
stage one אחות אשתו. achot ishto. So then even though by stage
three she stopped being אחות אשתו achos ishto and that by stage
four now there's a מצוה יבום, mitzva yibum, that status of אחות
אשתו achos ishto that happened at stage one still remains. All right?
Yes, have I lost everybody by now? Let's take a look at
the גמרא. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav:
כל יבמה שאינה נקראת בה בשעת נפילה יבמה יבוא עליה הרי היא
כאשת אח שיש לה בנים ואסורה. Kol yevama she'eina nikreis bah besha'as
nefilla yevama yavo aleha harei hi ke'eshis ach sheyesh la banim va'asura.
Any sister-in-law that was not able to do יבום yibum? at the
time that she became a widow, then she remains a brother's wife,
an ערוה of אשת אח, eshis ach, and she remains forbidden. Okay,
which basically is this case. ראובן Reuven died, he couldn't do יבום
yibum at this moment, she's אחות אשתו, achos ishto, okay? So even
though that status is going to change and לאה Leah is going
to die later on, all right, nevertheless she is going to remain
forbidden. You know why? Because even if she doesn't remain אחות אשתו,
achos ishto, the moment that she ראובן Reuven died and he couldn't
do יבום, yibum. she became not only אחות אשתו achos ishto but
what else did she become? She became another ערוה. If she can't
do יבום, yibum, what does she become? אשת אח, eshis ach, right?
So if at the moment of this death, you know, that's בשעת
מיתה besha'as misa you cannot say יבמה יבוא עליה, yevama yavo aleha,
then what this to add to whatever ערוה status is she also
becomes אשת אח, eshis ach, right? Because that's what she is, brother's
wife without a מצוה mitzva of יבום. yibum So that even when
the אחות אשה goes away because לאה Leah dies, she's going to
remain forbidden as their brother's wife. Yes? Sort of? You are going
to be tested on this tomorrow. Okay. So, okay, so הרי היא
כאשת אח שיש לה בנים. harei hi ke'eshis ach sheyesh la banim.
Once she was forbidden, she remains like a brother's wife with children,
meaning a brother's wife for whom there is no מצוה mitzva of
יבום, yibum ואסורה va'asura and she remains forbidden even when she stops
being the wife's sister. So מאי קמ"ל? mai kamashma lan? Why is
that a חידוש? chiddush? תנינא, tenina, that's what our משנה mishna. says.
הרי זו אסורה לו עולמית הואיל ונאסרה עליו שעה אחת.
harei zu asura lo
olamis ho'il venesra alav sha'a achas. It's exactly what our משנה mishna.
says, that even when she stops being wife sister, she continues to
be forbidden to שמעון. Shimon So the גמרא says מהו? mahu? I
might have thought רב רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is taking it one
step further. מהו דתימא הני מילי היכא דלא חזיא ליה בנפילה ראשונה.
mahu detaima hani mili heicha dela chazya lei benefilla rishona. That is,
in this case, in the case in the משנה, mishna? she remained
אחות אשתו achos ishto the entire period while she had the status
of being a יבמה. yevama. And then לוי
did יבום yibum to her,
right? But her status vis-a-vis שמעון Shimon did not change the entire
time that she was free. It only changed after she was married
to לוי. So that's a more enduring status where when he had
her יבום yibum relationship to her, she was always אחות אשתו achos
ishto and then she got married to לוי. And her status only
changes later. לאה Leah only died later. That's one thing to say,
that if during that entire period she was אסורה, asura, she always
remains forbidden. That's the משנה. mishna. אבל היכא דחזיא ליה בנפילה ראשונה,
aval heicha dechazya lei benefilla rishona, אימא תשתרי, eima tisharei, קמ"ל. kamashma
lan. Let's say you had a different case. Let's say you had
that ראובן Reuven died and then before לוי did יבום, yibum לאה
Leah died, okay? Right? What if ראובן Reuven died and then before
לוי did יבום, yibum nothing happened yet, ראובן Reuven died and then
לאה Leah, died. Okay? So then while she was in a potential
יבום yibum relationship with שמעון, Shimon. right? Because nobody had acted yet
on her יבום yibum status, her status changed. She stopped being his
wife's sister. Maybe that would allow us to reassess if a change
of status occurred while she was still in that first period. And
that's what רב is saying that it does not. It all goes
by the moment of death. Okay, so גמרא says הא נמי תנינא,
ha nami tenina, but that's also something we teach in a משנה.
שני אחים נשואים שתי אחיות, sheni achim nesu'im shtei achayos, two brothers
married to two sisters. מת אחד מהן ואחר כך מתה אשתו של
שני. meis echad mehen ve'achar kach meisa ishto shel sheni. One died,
okay, ראובן Reuven died and so now you have רחל who is
שמעון's Shimon wife's sister, okay, can't do יבום. yibum, And then what
happens? Nobody's done anything obviously. There's only one brother, there's only שמעון.
Shimon. Okay, he can't do anything. And then ואחר כך מתה אשתו
של שני, ve'achar kach meisa ishto shel sheni, and then לאה Leah.
dies. So now רחל stops being his wife sister. Okay, maybe do
יבום? yibum, No. הרי זו אסורה עליו עולמית הואיל ונאסרה עליו שעה
אחת.
harei zu asura alav olamis ho'il venesra
alav sha'a achas. Exact same הלכה. So here's a case where her
status changes before יבום yibum is done and it doesn't matter. So
why is רב a חידוש? chiddush? That's a משנה. It says, no,
that's a little different. התם הוא דאידחי לה מהאי ביתא לגמרי. hasam
hu de'idchi lah mehai beisa legamrei. That case where there's only one
brother, ראובן Reuven, dies and it's שמעון's Shimon wife's sister and he
can't do anything, there's nobody around that could do יבום. yibum So
we might say שמעון Shimon can't do יבום, yibum no other brother...
End of story. She's אסור assur period, we've finished the whole process.
אבל הכא לא אידחי מהאי ביתא לגמרי. Aval hacha lo idchei me-hai
beisa l'gamrei. Here when ראובן Reuven dies it's not the end of
the story with רחל because רחל could still have יבום yibum with
לוי. So she's still in process, we're still figuring out what her
status is going to be. It's not the end of the story.
If there's only שמעון Shimon and שמעון Shimon can't do יבום with
her, we're done. Here we're not done. She still is waiting for
יבום or חליצה with לוי. So since we're not done, maybe her
status changes, maybe she'll be permissible even to שמעון. Shimon Okay? אבל
הכא דלא אידחייא מהאי ביתא לגמרי, Aval hacha d'lo idchaya me-hai beisa
l'gamrei, אימא מיגו דחזיא להאי חזיא נמי להאי. eima migo d'chazya l'hai
chazya nami l'hai. Maybe now as she's permissible to לוי, now maybe
that שמעון's Shimon wife dies, maybe she'll become permissible to שמעון. קמשמע
לן Kamaschma lan that we don't say that, that it all goes
by the moment of death, and the reason is for what I
said,
that since when ראובן dies she's
אסור assur to שמעון because אחות אשתו, achos ishto, so she also
becomes אסור assur as אשת אחיו, eshes achiv, and that even when
אחות אשתו achos ishto goes away, the dead brother's wife's איסור issur
is still going to remain, that's not going to change. Okay? Do
we have time to do one more משנה? I have 8:28, what
time do you have? So far? Okay, we have 8:29. Now, we'll
just read the משנה. Okay, שלושה אחים שנים מהם נשואים שתי אחיות.
Shlosha achim shnayim mehem nesuim shtei achayot. Sound familiar? ואחד נשוי נכרית.
Now, no death, divorce. גירש אחד מבעלי האחיות את אשתו. Gerash echad
miba'alei ha'achayot et ishto. Okay, so here we go. ראובן, שמעון married
to רחל and לאה, Leah
לוי married to דבורה. Now what happened? גירש אחד מבעלי
האחיות את אשתו. Gerash echad miba'alei ha'achayot et ishto. שמעון now divorces
לאה. Leah. Okay, so he didn't, לאה Leah, didn't die, he divorced
לאה. Leah ומת נשוי נכרית. U'met nasui nochrit. And now לוי dies.
וכנס המגרש. V'chinsa hamgaresh. And now שמעון can go ahead and do
יבום with דבורה. Okay, because this is why? Because this is not,
she's not אחות אשתו, achos ishto, she's אחות his ex-wife. Okay, it's
interesting, if she was אחות אשתו, achos ishto, כל זמן שהאחיות קיימות,
kol zman sheha'achayot kayamot, oh you're right, I'm sorry, you're right, you're
right, right, for אחות אשתו achos ishto is אסור assur as long
as the woman is alive. Right, it's only בחייה. bechayeha. So I'm
sorry, right, so that wouldn't have mattered. Thank you. Thank you. Okay,
so he goes ahead and does יבום with דבורה, which is totally
fine. Okay, thank you, right. וכנס המגרש ומת. V'chinsa hamgaresh u'met. And
then שמעון dies. Okay, so now, is there any problem for ראובן
to do יבום with דבורה? No, it's שמעון's ex-wife and he has
no מצוה mitzvah of יבום with לוי because they got divorced. So
there's no ערוה over there. I mean, there's an ערוה but he
can't marry לאה, but she's not in the category of יבום because
they were divorced. So since she's out of יבום, right, so since
she's out of יבום, his only relationship is with דבורה and he
can go ahead and do יבום with דבורה. זו היא שאמרו. Zu
hi she'amru. So ומת, זו היא שאמרו, zu hi she'amru, כולן שמתו
או שנתגרשו צרותיהן מותרות. kulan shemetu o shenitgareshu tzaroteihen mutarot. So if
they die, we won't worry about the die right now, that was
sort of some of the cases from before, but anyway, if they
got divorced, right, if לאה had died, right, then also she'd be
out of the picture and he could do יבום with דבורה or
if she was divorced. Now he can go ahead and do יבום
with דבורה. She's out of the picture, she's not part of the
יבום equation. Okay, so to see more about this tomorrow.