Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is, officially it's נט,
nun-tet, but we are דף-bound, daf so it's נח nun-chet for us.
And we pick up to the bottom of נז עמוד ב, nun-zayin
amud-bet, two lines from the bottom. אמר רמי בר חמא. Amar Rami
bar Chama. So we've been introduced to a debate of רב Rav
and שמואל Shmuel
whether יש חופה לפסולות, yesh chuppah li-psulot, whether חופה chuppah is meaningful
for women who are פסולות. psulot. I already mentioned there's an interesting
debate whether חופה chuppah counts as the מצוה mitzvah of חופה chuppah
for שבע ברכות sheva brachot and whatnot if a woman is a
נדה. niddah. So that's different in two respects. Number one is that's
asking the question whether you're יוצא yotzei חופה chuppah and can you
make שבע ברכות. sheva brachot. And number two, it's about a woman
who's only in a temporary status; she's a נדה. niddah. Obviously, this
is a woman that the man can marry. Here we're talking about
whether the woman is a פסולה, psulah, a גרושה grushah to a
כהן kohen for example. And the question is not "Are you יוצא
yotzei the מצוה mitzvah of חופה?" chuppah? but whether the act of
חופה chuppah has meaning. What would be the meaning of the act
of חופה? chuppah? So the גמרא Gemara made it clear that the
act would be whether it would be considered like a ביאה, biah,
because it said yesterday that we're only talking about בת שלוש שנים
ויום אחד, bat shalosh shanim v'yom echad, which halachically is the age
in which it's considered to be a ביאה. biah. And would it
be an act of ביאה, biah, for example, to make this woman
now considered פסול לכהונה? pasul l'kehunah? Now, for example, the case of
a גרושה, grushah, she's already פסולה לכהונה, psulah l'kehunah, but as we've
been saying, the relevance is not for her to marry a כהן,
kohen, the relevance is that if she's the daughter of a כהן,
kohen, can she go back to eating תרומה? trumah? If she has
an act of sex that is forbidden, particularly forbidden from a כהונה
kehuna perspective, then she becomes a חללה chalalah and cannot even eat
תרומה trumah from her father's house. So is the act of חופה
chuppah like the act of ביאה? biah? We had the discussion in
the גמרא Gemara whether marriage, קידושין, kiddushin, without נישואין, nissuin, to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, somehow invalidated her. But now we're talking about, forget
קידושין, kiddushin, let's go to the חופה chuppah itself. Would that be
like the act of ביאה biah or not? So that's the debate.
רב Rav says yes and שמואל Shmuel says no. Let's take a
look now where the גמרא Gemara goes with it. אמר רמי בר
חמא, Amar Rami bar Chama, יש חופה לפסולות. yesh chuppah li-psulot. There
is חופה chuppah for women that are פסולות. psulot.
That question, באו למחלוקת ba'u l'machloket רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir ורבי אליעזר
ורבי שמעון. v'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon. That essentially is a debate of
in our משנה, mishna, or not it is a debate,
but it would be, it's an application of the debate in our
משנה mishna between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון.
v'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon. Ah, good to see you, Saf. Hi, thank
you, doubly good to see you. Okay, thanks. פשיטא היא מחלוקת. Peshi-ta
hi machloket.
רבי מאיר דאמר Rabbi Meir d'amar קידושין פסלי, kiddushin pasli, according to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says that when a כהן kohen has
just קידושין kiddushin with a woman, he invalidates her and she can't
eat תרומה trumah from her father's house.
So חופה נמי פסלה, chuppah nami pasla, חופה chuppah also would do
that. לרבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון דאמרי L'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon d'amri קידושין
לא פסלי, kiddushin lo pasli, according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that said קידושין kiddushin doesn't do it, חופה
נמי לא פסלה, chuppah nami lo pasla, חופה chuppah wouldn't do it.
Now obviously you can make a distinction, which the גמרא Gemara says.
וממאי, U-mima'i, who says it's the same debate? דילמא עד כאן לא
קאמר רבי מאיר Dilma ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Meir התם hatam
אלא בקידושין דקנה לה, ela b'kiddushin d'kana lah, when did רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir say קידושין kiddushin created a problem?
אלא בקידושין ela b'kiddushin where there was already a קנין. kinyan. Okay,
so already there was a meaningful קנין kinyan and then the next
what was around the bend was ביאה. biah. אבל חופה דלא קנה
לה, Aval chuppah d'lo kana lah, but חופה chuppah that he's not
קונה koneh her, לא, lo, not. Now I'm going to get back
and unpack that because your obvious question should be what the heck
are you talking about? חופה chuppah comes after קידושין, kiddushin, so if
she's already invalid as a result of קידושין, kiddushin, she should obviously
remain invalid as a result of חופה. chuppah. I'm going to come
back to that in a second. Let's read the next line first.
אבל חופה דלא קנה לה—so Aval chuppah d'lo kana lah that. And
רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון, v'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon, the difference is obvious.
ואינמי עד כאן לא קאמרי רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון V'einami ad kan
lo ka'amri Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon התם hatam אלא בקידושין דלא קריבה
לביאה, ela b'kiddushin d'lo kriba l'biah, and for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, they only said it when it's only קידושין,
kiddushin, when you're not yet up to the context of having sex.
אבל חופה דקריבה לביאה, Aval chuppah d'kriba l'biah, but חופה chuppah which
is in the context of having sex, that's the whole thing that's
about them living together, הכי נמי דפסלה, hachi nami d'pasla, then they
would admit that she's פסולה. psulah. So that's the obvious point, that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, there's a reason
to say that if you've already got to the stage of חופה,
chuppah, that should be like sex and that should invalidate her. The
question is why the גמרא Gemara thinks that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
might agree by חופה chuppah that it's not a problem. I mean,
you don't have חופה chuppah without קידושין. kiddushin. So that has to
do with what this large תוספות Tosafot is doing with back here.
And basically what רש"י Rashi says and then תוספות Tosafot elaborates on
is that the גמרא Gemara is suggesting that we're talking about חופה
chuppah even without קידושין. kiddushin. There was no קידושין kiddushin and they
just stood under a חופה. chuppah. I don't know what he said
there; they made שבע ברכות. sheva brachot. Who knows what? But you
had חופה chuppah without קידושין kiddushin and that's the question. So is
חופה chuppah even when it comes without קידושין, kiddushin,
that has a power, that has a power to it is that
חופה chuppah symbolizes living together and symbolizes sex. So therefore that could
be a problem even according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who say קידושין kiddushin isn't a problem. They could
agree חופה chuppah is a problem because it's all about sex. On
the other hand, you have the opposite argument, that even according to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says קידושין kiddushin is a problem, חופה
chuppah by itself... might be nothing, because חופה chupah, *chupa* without קידושין
kiddushin *kiddushin* maybe means absolutely nothing. Okay, so that's the way רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* explains this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that we are talking about
חופה chupah, *chupa*, but חופה chupah. *chupa* that comes without קידושין kiddushin
*kiddushin*. Now תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, in order to make it a little
bit more understandable, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* says that there's a debate in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* whether חופה chupah. *chupa*
can be used as one of the acts of קידושין kiddushin? *kiddushin*.
We normally say קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* is כסף שטר ביאה biah. *kesef
shtar biah*. There's a debate in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in קידושין
kiddushin *kiddushin* whether you can do חופה chupah, *chupa* as an act
of קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*. And תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* says maybe, because it's
crazy, תוספות *Tosafot*, that's what he says, crazy, how could we think
that חופה chupah *chupa* by itself would be meaningful? You know, you
know, I mean, I don't know, let's say they rented a room
in a hotel, but they never did anything. Would you say, oh
well, that's about sex so therefore, I mean, you know, if it
doesn't have halachic meaning, how is it a reasonable conversation?
So
therefore, okay, but so therefore תוספות *Tosafot* says we can only be
talking according to the idea that חופה chupah *chupa* by itself is
an act of קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin* and therefore that's the question. Of
course that a little bit creates a certain circular problem because if
חופה chupah. *chupa* is an act of קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin* you're back
to square one. Then according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir*
then obviously it should be a problem, if קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin* is
a problem then חופה chupah *chupa* should be a problem. Anyways, that's
רש"י's Rashi *Rashi's* approach. רש"י's Rashi *Rashi's* approach is that we are
talking with חופה chupah *chupa* that did not precede, that that קידושין
Kiddushin *kiddushin* did not precede it, חופה chupah *chupa* by itself. So
one argument to say that it is worse than קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin*,
it makes it more like they've had sex even according to רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* because that's
what חופה's chupah *chupa's* about. On the other hand, the argument is
the opposite, even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* would say it's
not a problem because it's not קידושין Kiddushin *kiddushin* and it's not
coming with קידושין Kiddushin, *kiddushin*. That's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. תוספות *Tosafot* has another read of the גמרא
Gemara, *Gemara* which I'll just mention briefly not to confuse you but
I'll just mention, and he says that the question here in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is that we are talking, yes, חופה chupah *chupa*
came after קידושין Kiddushin. *kiddushin*. So if חופה chupah *chupa* came after
קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*, how could it be according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* she's not already, if קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* is a
problem חופה chupah *chupa* should all obviously be a problem, I mean
it's coming after the קידושין kidushin, *kiddushin*. So תוספות *Tosafot* says yes,
but חופה chupah *chupa* came after קידושין kidushin *kiddushin*, they didn't have
sex and now they're divorced. So the question is, having been in
the state of חופה chupah. *chupa*, will that permanently mark the woman
as a חללה chalalah, *chalala*? Because you might remember the משנה Mishnah.
*mishna* says even according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* if
they had קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* she can't eat תרומה terumah? *teruma*. If
they got divorced or he died and they never consummated she can
go back to eating תרומה terumah. *teruma*. That according to רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* the problem is only while they're still in
that state of קידושין kidushin *kiddushin* as opposed to if they actually
had sex she's permanently marked and then she remains invalid. So according
to תוספות *Tosafot* the question in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is, well
let's say there was קידושין kidushin *kiddushin* and חופה chupah *chupa* but
no sex, and then he died, would that have permanently would that
have
permanently
changed, no, that's the question. What's the status of חופה chupah *chupa*
without the sex? Would that have permanently changed the status? So that's
how תוספות *Tosafot* reads it. We're going to work with also רש"י
Rashi *Rashi*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* understands we're talking about חופה chupah *chupa*,
חופה chupah *chupa* without קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*. And the question is on
the one hand again it could be worse because it could be
like they've had sex because it's about חופה chupah *chupa*. On the
other hand, it could be less bad because there hasn't been קידושין
kiddushin *kiddushin* and therefore maybe even רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
would agree that it's not a problem. Yes.
I thought there was a פשט *pshat* that חופה chupah *chupa* was
not a canopy the way we associate it, but that it was
actually a closed room that made sex viable or possible.
Possibly. There's a whole range of opinions what חופה chupah *chupa* is.
Okay so that's one of them, but, right, but yes, but that's
either way it's clear, either way
it's
clear that חופה chupah, *chupa* is about, is normally about נישואין nisuin
*nisuim* and it's about the context of them having sex. That certainly
is clear. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. So that's
the issue.
So maybe it's part of the debate רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi
Meir* versus ר' אלעזר *Rebbi Elazar* ור' שמעון *ve-Rebbi Shimon*. The גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says no, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* could be
lenient because again we'll read it רש"י's Rashi *Rashi's* way, there's only
חופה chupah, *chupa*, there's no קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*, and ר' אלעזר *Rebbi
Elazar* ור' שמעון *ve-Rebbi Shimon* maybe would be strict because חופה's chupah,
*chupa's* about having sex. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this. אי איכא למימר בפלוגתא דתנאי *ee eecha lemeimar b'pelugta d'tana'ei*, if
you want to say it's dependent on a debate of תנאים *tana'im*,
בפלוגתא דהני תנאי *b'pelugta d'hanei tana'ei*, it's dependent on the following תנאים
*tana'im*, דתניא De'tanya, *detanya*, תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan* in a ברייתא Baraisa
*beraita*. ניסו nisu זו וזו *nisu zu bezu*, if women who were
פסולות psulos, *pesulot* or כשרות *kesherot* got married, כשרות ופסולות ksheros upesulos,
*kesherot u-fesulot*, meaning זו וזו *zu bezu* is כשרות ופסולות *kesherot u-fesulot*,
to כהנים kohanim *kohanim*, או שנכנסו לחופה ולא נבעלו *o she-nichnesu le-chupa
ve-lo niv'alu*, or they went into a חופה chupah *chupa* and they
didn't have sex. So whether it's נישואין nissuin? *nisuim* or just חופה
chupah. *chupa*, the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* going to say, well what's נישואין
nissuin. *nisuim* different than חופה Chuppah? *chupa*? Okay, but let's take a
look. So maybe it means they actually did have sex or they
had the חופה Chuppah, *chupa* without having had sex. These women, whether
they were כשרות *kesherot* or פסולות psulos, *pesulot*, obviously the only one
that's going to be interesting is the פסולות *pesulot*. אוכלות משלו ואוכלות
בתרומה *ochlot mishelo ve-ochlot bi-teruma*. They eat, the כהן kohen. *kohen* has
to feed them because once there's נישואין nissuin *nisuim* you have an
obligation of support, not just a כהן kohen *kohen*, any man. And
they would eat תרומה terumah *teruma* because after נישואין nissuin, *nisuim* is
when they eat תרומה terumah, *teruma*. Of course the amazing thing is
they're eating תרומה terumah. *teruma* even though they're פסולות *pesulot*, right? Our
משנה Mishnah. *mishna* at most had ר' אלעזר *Rebbi Elazar* ורבי שמעון
*ve-Rebbi Shimon* say that they could continue to eat תרומה terumah, *teruma*
if they were only קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*, and even that, the פשט
*pshat* of רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafot* might only be if they
were a בת כהן bat kohen, *bat kohen* and were eating by
virtue of the father.
Here... How are they eating תרומה? terumah. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says, now, ואוכלת פי תרומה, ve'ocheles pei trumah,
נכנסו, nichnesu,
so it says they went into the חופה, Chuppah מכלל דניסו, michlal
denisu, ניסו ממש. nisu mamash. So when it says they got married,
presumably it means literally married, meaning that they've had sex. אלא לאו,
ella lav, is that possible? How could we be talking that they
literally have had sex and nevertheless they could be eating תרומה? terumah,
אלא לאו, ella lav, you can, so you can't read that mean,
because then there would be no way of understanding that they're eating
תרומה. terumah, So what are these two categories, ניסו nisu versus נכנסו
לחופה? nichnesu lachupa? כגון שנכנסו לחופה ולא נבעלו. kagon shenichnesu lachupa velo
nivalu.
It must mean that they went into the חופה, Chuppah, they did
not have sex, and that ניסו nisu is not really, the way
רש"י reads this, a separate category, it's really explaining it. The same
way אלו ואלו elu ve'elu is being explained as כשרות ופסולות, ניסו
is being explained as נכנסו לחופה ולא נבעלו. nichnesu lachupa velo nivalu.
I know, I don't know what to tell you about that.
Okay, so I don't know what to tell you about that. Anyway,
so basically we're trying to say the only way this can begin
to make sense is if they haven't had sex yet, but there's
been a חופה. Chuppah And you see that they're eating תרומה terumah.
even though there's been a חופה. Chuppah, So the גמרא Gemara says,
מכלל דניסו ניסו ממש אלא לאו כגון שנכנסו לחופה ולא נבעלו, michlal
denisu nisu mamash ella lav kagon shenichnesu lachupa velo nivalu, דתני אוכלת
פי שלו ואוכלת פי תרומה. detani ocheles pei shelo ve'ocheles pei trumah.
So you see they're eating תרומה, terumah. so here's a woman that's
had חופה, Chuppah case of פסולות, and they're eating תרומה. terumah, That
would be a clear example that חופה Chuppah is not like ביאה.
biah חופה דאין חופה לפסולות, chupah de'ein chupah l'psulos, it does not
make them like they've had sex. And then the ברייתא Braita, continues.
רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר, Rabbi Yishmael beno
shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka omer, כל שביאתה מאכילתה חופתה מאכילתה. kol
shebi'asah ma'achilasah chupasah ma'achilasah. Any
time that if she had sex she could be eating תרומה, terumah,
so the חופה Chuppah, she can eat תרומה. terumah וכל שאין ביאתה
מאכילתה, vechol she'ein bi'asah ma'achilasah,
but if the sex would not entitle her to eat תרומה, terumah.
like in this case that they're פסולות, so the sex would make
her a חללה, chalalah. אין חופתה מאכילתה, ein chupasah ma'achilasah, she cannot
be eating by virtue of the חופה. Chuppah, And the way רש"י
wants to understand the strong identity here of חופה Chuppah to ביאה
biah is not just saying that she's not entitled to eat תרומה,
Truma but that the implication would be that he would say the
חופה Chuppah would be like ביאה biah and she would be permanently
invalidated of eating תרומה. truma, Disagreeing, but not just disagreeing that she's
not entitled, going further to say that she's invalidated. Right, there's three
possibilities. One is she's not allowed in this current state, but at
once they get divorced or whatever she'll go back to being allowed.
The other is that she is allowed in this current state, the
other is that she's not allowed and she'll never be allowed again
because she's been invalidated, she's become a חללה. chalalah So the גמרא
Gemara wants to frame it, the first תניא tanya says she's ממש
mamash allowed, even though she's נשואה nesua and it's a פסולה, psula,
she's allowed, which is a pretty extreme position. Even though it's a
case that if there's ביאה biah she'd be permanently a חללה chalalah
and there's already חופה Chuppah and all that, she can still eat
תרומה. truma. That's a strong position of אין חופה לפסולות, ein chupah
l'psulos, that not only is קידושין kiddushin not a problem, even חופה
Chuppah is not a problem without having had sex. And then רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yishmael beno shel Rabbi
Yochanan ben Broka is going the opposite extreme, the way the גמרא,
Gemara רש"י is reading the גמרא, Gemara to say that no, חופה
chuppah is like ביאה biah. and she's permanently פסול pasul and it's
like she's a חללה chalalah and that's יש חופה לפסולות. yesh chupah
l'psulos. Okay, so that's the debate the גמרא Gemara wants to say.
So the גמרא Gemara says ממאי, mimai, who says that's his debate?
דילמא, dilma, maybe רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi
Yishmael beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka כרבי מאיר סבירא ליה, k'Rabbi
Meir s'vira lei, maybe he holds like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, דאמר
קידושין לא אכלה, de'amar kiddushin lo achla, that it's not because of
the חופה chuppah that there's a problem, and maybe he's not saying
that she's permanently פסולה, psula, maybe he's just saying that once there's
even a קידושין kiddushin to a woman who is פסולה, psula, then
she cannot eat תרומה, truma but not that the חופה chuppah makes
it worse and that the חופה chuppah permanently invalidates her. So the
גמרא Gemara says הא, ha, and so the גמרא Gemara says no,
if that's true, האי כל שאין ביאתה מאכילתה אין חופתה מאכילתה, hai
kol she'ein bi'asah ma'achilasah ein chupasah ma'achilasah,
then it shouldn't have been comparing it to ביאה. biah, It shouldn't
have said, oh, since she can't eat as a virtue of ביאה,
biah. she can't eat as a virtue of חופה. chuppah That makes
it sound like the problem is the חופה chuppah and חופה chuppah,
is like ביאה. Biah If it was just רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
issue and it was just about of not currently being able to
eat, not being invalidated, it should have said כל שאין ביאתה מאכילתה
אין כספה מאכילתה. kol she'ein bi'asah ma'achilasah ein ksafah ma'achilasah.
He should have said look, since the sex is going to be
problematic, the קידושין kiddushin is already problematic. Why is he emphasizing חופה
chuppah and not קידושין? kiddushin, It must be that it's not just
that the קידושין kiddushin is the problem and it's not just a
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir problem. It must be that the חופה chuppah,
is the problem and that the חופה chuppah invalidates her. ואיבעי ליה,
v'ibai leh, that's what he should have said. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, that doesn't prove anything. דילמא, dilma, maybe איידי דאמר תנא
קמא חופה אמר איהו נמי חופה. ayidi de'amar tanna kamma chupah amar
ihu nami chupah. No,
the תנא קמא tanna kamma was going to one extreme saying חופה
chuppah wasn't a problem at all, והא היא, v'ha hi, that's an
extreme position, right? I mean that's a real חידוש. chiddush. A חופה
chuppah that follows קידושין kiddushin presumably, not just רש"י's case where it
came by itself. You had קידושין kiddushin and חופה, chuppah you just
haven't had sex and she can still eat תרומה, truma. even though
she's a גרושה grusha who has had a חופה, chuppah נישואין nissuin
with a כהן. kohen, She can still eat תרומה truma. because they
haven't yet had sex. Okay, up to the last minute she can
eat תרומה. truma So comes רבי אלעזר בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא Rabbi Elazar beno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka and says no,
the חופה, chuppah I'm sorry she can't eat, חופה chuppah, she can't
eat as a result of the חופה. chuppah? Now. Really they think
personally I hold even because of אירוסין Erusin she can't eat. You're
going so far as to say she can eat even with חופה?
chuppah. Forget that, she certainly can't eat because of חופה, but not
only that, maybe you would say even according to רבי מאיר, even
at the קידושין kiddushin stage she can't eat. You don't know for
him it's particularly a חופה problem, it might already have been a
קידושין kiddushin, problem. Okay, so we don't know. So we still have
this debate which is, when you have חופה, does would רבי אלעזר
Rebbi Elazar and רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon still say that she can
eat, even though she's literally one step away from having had sex
and becoming a פסולה? Psulah? And at the other hand, so maybe
they'll admit she can't eat, or maybe according to like this ברייתא,
Braita, you have a תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that says she can
eat. Very extreme position. And the other side is maybe רבי מאיר
would say, would say that חופה at least without קידושין, kiddushin, maybe
also isn't a problem. With קידושין kiddushin it's certainly a problem, but
maybe without קידושין kiddushin even a חופה, even חופה isn't a problem.
So that's the debate. Okay, so let's take a look. So אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, so is חופה make it like ביאה Biah, or
not? And that could be either רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar or רבי
שמעון could say, you know, maybe they'd be more strict by ביאה,
Biah. maybe רבי מאיר would be more strict by חופה, maybe רבי
מאיר without קידושין kiddushin, would be less strict by חופה, but we
have this possibility, this reasonable possibility that חופה should be considered like
ביאה. Biah. Okay, and invalidate her permanently. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, הא מילתא אמר רב
ששת, Ha milsa Amar Rav Sheshet, so this issue that we're about
to say about this question around whether יש חופה לפסולות, Yesh Chuppah
Li'Psulot, רב ששת Rav Sheshet said to us, ונהרינהו לעינין ממתניתין, Ve'naharineihu
le'einayn mi'matnitin, and he lit up our eyes from a משנה. Mishnah,
Okay, he told us a פסק Psak and then he showed us
how that this פסק, Psak, this idea was already hinted embedded in
a משנה. Mishnah Here's what he said to us:
יש חופה לפסולות, Yesh Chuppah Li'Psulot, חופה for a woman who's פסולה
Psulah is meaningful and basically counts like ביאה. bi'ah. Okay, and would
invalidate her, at least in this תרומה trumah, discussion. Okay, but now
we're going to look at it not in the case like רש"י
was talking about about חופה by itself without קידושין, kiddushin. we're going
to look at a classic case of חופה with קידושין. kiddushin דתנא
תונא, De'tana tuna, and our תנא Tanna taught a משנה, Mishnah, תונא
tuna means our תנא. Tanna. אמן, Amen, so this is actually not
our תנא Tanna in the sense of this מסכת, Masechet, but our
תנא Tanna in the sense as opposed to like the ברייתא, Braita,
it's from the corpus of משניות. Mishnayot. So anyway, here's what we
taught and this is in about the woman who is suspected of
being a סוטה Sotah and it says in the פסוקים Psukim ואמרה
האשה אמן אמן. Ve'Amra Ha'Isha Amen Amen. He says that you did
not, you know, you did not go wayward with any other
man and so on, and the woman will say אמן אמן. Amen
Amen. So what's the double אמן? Amen? So the משנה mishna. explains:
what's the אמן אמן? Amen Amen?
אמן שלא שטיתי ארוסה ונשואה, Amen Shelo Saititi Arusa Ve'Nissua, שומרת יבם
וכנוסה. Shomeret Yavam Ve'Khenusa. I did not go wayward, I did not
stray whether I was an ארוסה Arusa or נשואה, Nissua, whether I
was a שומרת יבם, Shomeret Yavam, so apparently the brother-in-law while he's
waiting this whole idea of זיקה Zikka to have to do יבום
Yibum is in a position where he can also do קינוי וסתירה,
Kinuy Ve'Stirah, can like tell her don't I don't want to see
you go private with another man and if she does, make her
drink the סוטה Sotah water, we'll discuss that. So she says אמן
Amen that I did not do it when I was a שומרת
יבם Shomeret Yavam or כנוסה Kenusa or after the יבום Yibum took
place. So now so that's the idea that he can actually do
קינוי וסתירה Kinuy Ve'Stirah in those scenarios, even a case of ארוסה,
Arusa, even a case of שומרת יבם. Shomeret Yavam.
So the גמרא Gemara says: okay, but she didn't. So the גמרא
Gemara says: האי ארוסה היכי דמי? Hai Arusa Hechi Dami? First let's
understand the case of
ארוסה. Arusa. אי נימא דקני לה כשהיא ארוסה וקמשקי לה כשהיא ארוסה,
Iy nima de'kani lah keshe'hi arusa ve'kamashke lah keshe'hi arusa, if he
did the whole process when she was an ארוסה, Arusa, ארוסה בת
משתייה? Arusa Bat Mishtaya? Can you make an ארוסה Arusa drink the
סוטה Sotah water? דתנן, De'Tnan, we taught in the
משנה, mishna ארוסה ושומרת יבם לא שותות ולא נוטלות כתובה, Arusa Ve'Shomeret
Yavam Lo Shotot Ve'Lo Notlot Ktuvah, that a woman who is an
ארוסה Arusa or שומרת יבם Shomeret Yavam who is being suspected and
the guy went through this whole process, so on the one hand
they cannot be made to drink the water, the water is only
by a woman who is
a נשואה Nissua because it says תחת אישך, Tachat Ishech, under your
husband, and husband there is understood like in the full status, so
that means that you're already fully married, it's נשואין, Nissuin, so a
going wayward when it's your ארוס Arus but not your איש Ish
is not considered to be in the category of סוטה. Sotah. On
the other hand, because they went into private with this man after
being warned, they are now seen as at fault and can be
divorced without the כתובה. Ktuvah. So they are divorced without the כתובה,
Ktuvah, but they cannot be made to drink the סוטה Sotah water.
אלא, Ella, so it can't be that that's the scenario because there
would never be a drinking of the סוטה Sotah water in that
case.
אלא, Ella, דקני לה כשהיא ארוסה ונסתרה, De'Kani Lah Keshe'Hi Arusa Ve'Istatra,
so it must be that he warned her when she was an
ארוסה, Arusa, then she went into private, וקמשקי לה כשהיא נשואה, Ve'Kamashke
Lah Keshe'Hi Nissua, and now after they went through with the נשואין,
Nissuin, now he's making her drink the סוטה Sotah water for an
event that occurred during the אירוסין Erusin period. So the גמרא gemara
says: no, one minute, מי בדקי לה מיא? Mi Badki Lah Maya?
Would the water work in that case? דתניא, we taught the ברייתא,
Braisa ונקה האיש מעון, Ve'Nikah Ish Me'Avon, the man would be clean
from sin and that woman will bear her sin is what the
פסוקים Psukim says,
בזמן שהאיש מנוקה מעון. Bazman She'Ish Menukeh Me'Avon. When he is clean
from sin, the water works. אין האיש מנוקה מעון, Ein ha'ish minuka
me'avon, if he's not clean from sexual sin, אין המים בודקין את
אשתו. ein hamayim bodkin et ishto. It won't work on her. Now
why is he not clean from sexual sin? Because if she was
a סוטה sotah at the stage of an ארוסה, arusa, how they
ever get around to having נישואין? nisuin Right? Not allowed to have
sex with your wife who is a סוטה. sotah.
So it was even for פסול לכהונה psul l'kehunah then, I mean
he's not allowed to marry her either. What? Then all right,
he married between קינוי kinuy and סתירה. stira.
No, he married after סתירה. stira. When she was already between קינוי
kinuy he was allowed to marry her, but after סתירה stira he
wasn't. He wasn't allowed to have sex with her when she went
into private with this man after being warned, she had a הלכה
halakha of a סוטה, sotah, he was אסור asur to have sex
with her, and then he did the נישואין. nisuin, So that can't
be the case. אלא, Ella, it must
be דקניה כשהיא ארוסה ונסתתרה ונכנסה לחופה ולא נבעלה. d'kanya k'shehi arusa
v'nistatra v'nichnesa l'chuppah v'lo niv'ala. It must be, now of course you
and I would say exactly what Joe just said, which is why
don't you say the קינוי kinuy was when she was an ארוסה
arusa and then they got married and then the סתירה, stira, going
into private, was when she was a נשואה. nesua. But presumably you
can't say that because it says, she says לא שטיתי כשהיא ארוסה,
lo satisi k'shehi arusa, I did not go wayward. So the going
wayward was the being in private and what she did when she
was in private. So if that happened when she was an ארוסה,
arusa, how they ever get around to being a נשואה? nesua? So
it must be that they had חופה but they didn't have ביאה.
bi'ah, And because they had חופה not ביאה, bi'ah he's still מנוקה
מעון. minuka me'avon. Nobody says you're not allowed to have חופה with
your wife who's a סוטה, sotah, you just can't have ביאה bi'ah
with your wife who's a סוטה. sotah. Okay, so that ונכנסה לחופה
ולא נבעלה v'nichnesa l'chuppah v'lo niv'ala ושמע מינה יש חופה לפסולות. v'shma
mina yesh chuppah l'psulot. So you see that since he is considered
enough that the that he is now considered נשואה nesua and he
can still make her drink the סוטה sotah water, even though the
נישואין nisuin, happened under the context when she was אסורה asura to
him. Now this question of יש חופה לפסולות yesh chuppah l'psulot is
different than the earlier question, right? The earlier question is, is it
like they've had sex so that so that she becomes like I
don't know, פסול לכהונה. psul l'kehunah. That was a very limited type
of a פסול כהונה pasul kehuna question. We've now broadened it to
a very general question. Is there a חופה when the woman is
אסור asur to the husband? This is almost like the case of
a נידה, niddah, right? Is there such a thing as חופת נידה?
chuppat niddah? So again, נידה niddah you could say is sort of
regularly the status that goes off, it's not the same. But here
she's a סוטה, sotah, that status might go off after they drink
the water or whatever. And nevertheless, the question is not is it
like she's had sex to invalidate her, the question is are they
considered like they're married, like the חופה was meaningful and like they're
נשואות nesuot or not, so that now he's in a position to
make her drink the סוטה sotah water because the סוטה sotah water
you can only do in a context of נישואין, nisuin? you can't
do in a context of אירוסין. erusin. So now it's become a
in a way a much broader and I would even argue in
some ways a more interesting question. Is the act of נישואין nisuin?
when the woman is אסורה asura to the husband a meaningful act
and have they now entered into a status of being נשואות nesuot
or not?
How about the ביאה biah itself ממש? mamash? That maybe this this
act of זנות...
znut... well you could ask, you could ask that, right. So the
גמרא gemara says ושמע מינה יש חופה לפסולות.
v'shma mina yesh
chuppah l'psulot. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, and says Rava, ותסברא, v'tisbora, does
that make sense? דמיתרצתא היא da-mitarsti that you've that ברייתא Braisa has
been like is
is correct text? מיתרצתא Mitarsta sort of means like it's a correct
text and that you've explained it properly. דהא כי אתא רב אחא
בר חנינא מדרומא, De-ha ki ata Rav Acha bar Chanina midaroma, when
רב אחא בר חנינא Rav Acha bar Chanina came from the south,
אתא, ata, he came, ואייתי מתניתא בידיה, v'ayti matnita biyadei, and he
brought the following ברייתא Braisa in his hand. מבלעדי אישך, Mibal'adei ishech,
it says ואת שטית טומאה מבלעדי אישך, v'at satisi tum'ah mibal'adei ishech,
right? And you if you have like you know, by the way
I want to point out that exactly in the same location in
yesterday's דף, daf, the exact bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב', nun zayin
amud bet, it had כי אתא רב אחא בר חנינא מדרומא אתא
ואייתי מתניתא בידיה. ki ata Rav Acha bar Chanina midaroma ata v'ayti
matnita biyadei. So I don't know what it means that exactly one
דף daf before at the exact same location we have this very
unusual thing of this רב אחא בר חנינא Rav Acha bar Chanina
coming from the south and bringing a ברייתא Braisa in his hand.
But anyway, somebody up center had a sense of humor.
Exactly. Anyway, okay. Anyway, he brought the following ברייתא Beraita in his
hand. מבלעדי אישך, Mibal'adei ishech, had sex with a man other than
your husband, so מי שקדמה שכבת בעל לבועל. mi shekadma shkhivat ba'al
l'bo'el. You could only do the סוטה sotah if your husband has
had sex, the husband has had sex with the woman before the
suspected adulterer. מבלעדי אישך Mibal'adei ishech means your husband has already been
with you and now somebody other than your husband has also been
having sex with
you. Okay, ולא שקדמה שכבת בועל לבעל. v'lo shekadma shkhivat bo'el l'ba'al.
But if the first person she had sex with or suspected of
having sex with is the adulterer, then that would not be the
context of the סוטה sotah water, okay, which is quite fascinating. Either
way it's adultery, okay, but nevertheless there's a whole idea about the
husband and his הקפדה hakpada וקינוי את אשתו v'kinuy et ishto and
all these types of things. So somehow it's specifically that they've already
been intimate, they've already had sex and now she's had sex with
another man. So the whole context has to be that they've already
had sex but we've But we've got a problem. We've just constructed
the case that she committed adultery when she or suspected of committing
adultery when she was an ארוסה. arusa. He's not allowed now to
have sex with her because otherwise he would not be מנוקה מעון.
menuka me'avon. So they had חופה without having had sex. But now
but there's also a context that the woman won't have to drink
the סוטה Sotah water because the husband never had sex with her.
The whole context has to be that the husband has had sex
with her prior to her being suspected of having committed adultery or
prior to the
act. Exactly. Now of course you could because you could have had
sex while she was an ארוסה arusa before the whole קינוי וסתירה
kinei v'stira case, which is what the גמרא's gemara going to say.
So let's take a look. אמר רמי בר חמא Amar Rami bar
Chama משכחת לה mashkachat lah oh here's how you could get it.
You could have the case שבא עליה ארוס בבית אביה she'ba aleha
arus b'veit aviha her ארוס, arus, ארוסה arusa right, her ארוס arus
anyway the ארוס arus had sex with her when she was still
in her father's house when she was an ארוסה arusa before she
was a נשואה. nesua. And therefore so here's the scenario here's the
case. Gives her קידושין, kiddushin. has sex with her, then suspects her
of spending too much time with another man, does קינוי, kinei, she
goes into hiding she goes into private with this other man, then
he decides to anyway go through with it and have the חופה,
but he hasn't had sex now because now he's also to have
sex with her because she's a סוטה. Sotah. Now he wants to
make her drink for that suspected thing when she went into that
hotel room with that guy when she was an ארוסה arusa and
in this case number one he's מנוקה מעון menuka me'avon because he
hasn't had sex with her since she's been in private with this
other man. And number two he's already had sex with her because
he had sex while she was still an ארוסה arusa and that's
the scenario. Okay so the גמרא gemara, says one minute that works
fine in the case of ארוסה arusa but how about the other
case in the ברייתא baraita שומרת יבם? shomeret yavam? Right once you've
had sex you're no longer a שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. So the
גמרא gemara, says so so the גמרא gemara says דקתני סיפא גבי
שומרת יבם d'katni seifa gabei shomeret yavam שבא עליה יבם בבית חמיה
she'ba aleha yavam b'veit chamia if they've had sex even while she's
still in her brother-in-law's house whatever that would mean but if once
they've had sex so שומרת יבם קרית לה? shomeret yavam karit lah?
אשתו מעליא היא. ishto ma'alya hi. How could you call her שומרת
יבם? shomeret yavam? She's his wife. So how are you going to
get the case where he's making her swear about not having committed
adultery or slept with another man when she was a שומרת יבם?
shomeret yavam? How do you have a case of קדמה שכיבת בעל
לבועל? kadma shechivat ba'al l'boel? If there was ever קדמה שכיבת בעל
kadma shechivat ba'al she's no longer a שומרת יבם. shomeret yavam. Yes
Charlie.
So this is implying that it is not a prohibited sin to
sleep with your ארוסה arusa for the purposes...
well it's not whether it's a sin or not. Oh you mean
would it be the case of מנוקה מעון? menuka me'avon? Exactly yeah.
Yeah so the question is exactly what constitutes the מנוקה מעון menuka
me'avon scenario in that but okay look we know that there was
a whole issue of יהודה וגליל Yehuda v'Galil about sleeping so anyway
right. Okay so anyway but that's a good point.
So the גמרא gemara says like this
דאמר רב קנאה לכל d'amar Rav kanah l'chol that you're considered fully
to be a wife.
You might remember that weeks before if an act of
sex was done because remember we
could be talking about the fact that they were doing it just
to have sex they weren't doing it for the sake of יבום.
yibum. But that was a debate earlier of רב Rav and שמואל.
Shmuel. An act of sex that was done just for the sake
of having sex just for fornication and so on would that make
her fully his wife? On the one hand Rav says yes it
would make her fully his wife. Shmuel says no. It makes her
his wife because normally what's the reason not? Right this was what
covered when I wasn't here. Because normally an act of sex would
not be a meaningful act of you know of changing status unless
it was specifically done in a particular context it was done as
קידושי ביאה kiddushei biah right or maybe it came after קידושין kiddushin
so it's a type of נשואין nisuin or whatever. But if an
act of sex is just done you know for having sex not
in a particular type of a status creating a status context normally
it's not meaningful. The only place it is meaningful you know the
שוגג מזיד shogeg mezid type of a thing is by יבום yibum
because the זיקה zika preceded and all those reasons. So Rav says
I don't care yes that's the חידוש chiddush because the זיקה zika
preceded once you had sex I don't care what was in your
mind it's fully אשתו. ishto. Shmuel says no it's like half and
half the aspects of יבום yibum are binding so it's exempts the
co-wives it exempts the other brothers you inherit all those types of
things. But for the full status of wife that we normally talk
about הלכתית halachit that does not come without דעת da'at to to
effect that status. Okay so that's the debate of רב Rav and
שמואל. Shmuel. Whether קנאה לכל מילי kanah l'chol mili or just for
דברים הכתובים בפרשה. devarim haktuvim b'parshah. So the גמרא Gemara says once
you've had sex here you know then obviously she's no longer שומרת
יבם. shomeret yavam. So the גמרא Gemara says wait it could work
according to שמואל. Shmuel. According to שמואל Shmuel you could still call
her שומרת יבם shomeret yavam because to some degree she's not really
fully his wife and therefore we could be talking about that status.
But she isn't enough of his wife for סוטה Sotah purposes?
For סוטה Sotah purposes right. So the גמרא Gemara says so אמר
רב קנאה לכל. amar Rav kanah l'chol. So the גמרא gemara says
fine כשמואל k'Shmuel דאמר לא קנאה לדברים המפורשים בפרשה. d'amar lo kanah
l'devarim hamforashim b'parshah. So how could we be talking about a שומרת
יבם shomeret yavam that's already had sex with the brother-in-law? Okay like
שמואל Shmuel that it was done for the sake of sex not
for the sake of יבום yibum and it's not fully אשתו. ishto.
The גמרא gemara. says מכדי הוי טעמיה אלא לרב, michdi havei taamei
ela lerav, this whole discussion is according to רב. rav. Why is
this whole discussion going to רב? rav?
Because רב rav is the one that says יש חופה לפסולות, yeish
chuppah lepsulot,
right רב, rav, and we tried to say, oh this ברייתא baraita
proves like רב, rav, חופה is binding because the whole point was
that you have a חופה, this woman is a פסולה, psula, she's
a סוטה, sota, the husband still is in a position to do
the whole סוטה sota process. So we said this supports רב. rav.
And then we're saying, oh it doesn't support רב rav because you
can't explain the יבום yibum case, the whole ברייתא baraita doesn't make
sense. Oh, we can explain the יבום yibum case like שמואל. shmuel.
But the whole point is that you're trying to support רב, rav,
okay? So you can't support רב rav with this ברייתא baraita because
the יבום yibum case doesn't make sense according to רב. rav. Okay,
אלא לרב הא אמר רב קנה לכל. ela lerav ha amar rav
kana lechol. So we got the problem. This whole ברייתא Baraita: is
supposed to be a support to רב, rav, but the יבום yibum
doesn't make any sense. How do you have a case that the
guy had sex with her and she's still a שומרת יבם? shomeres
yabam? So the גמרא gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שעשה בה
מאמר ובית שמאי היא דאמרי מאמר קונה קנין גמור. hacha bemai askinan
kigon sheasah bah maamar uveit shamai hi deamri maamar koneh kinyan gamur.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, here's the way. Now again, there's
a whole big two versions in רש״י, rashi, but I'll lead the
simpler version which is just radical conceptually, but it's a simpler read
of the גמרא, Gemara which is: here's how the יבם yabam can
have sex with his sister-in-law and she still not be אשתו. ishto.
You know how? According to בית שמאי beit shamai that he does
מאמר. maamar. Now you might remember according to בית שמאי, beit shamai,
מאמר maamar by a יבמה yevama works דאורייתא, deoraita, like if it
ends up exempting the צרה tzara and all these other things if
it's wife's sister and all those scenarios. So we're talking he did
מאמר. maamar. Now not only does it work to exempt the צרה,
tzara, according to this read of the גמרא, Gemara what it would
also mean would be if he did מאמר maamar followed by sex,
then the sex would be like having had sex with a woman
who was just his ארוסה, arusa, not a woman who was a
שומרת יבם. shomeres yabam. So that sex would not be meaningful from
a הלכות יבום hilchos yibum context. Okay, so did מאמר, maamar, so
that puts her in the category of an ארוסה, arusa, takes her
out of the יבום yibum category. And now therefore if you did
חופה whatever, fine, she's a נשואה. nesua. But if you basically went
ahead and did sex and it was sex not for the purposes
of נישואין nisuin, or יבום, yibum, just sex for sex, then she
would still be in an ארוסה arusa status. It would not do
the normal thing that sex does in a יבום yibum context, which
is automatically makes her a נשואה, nesua, because according to בית שמאי
beit shamai once you did מאמר, maamar, she's basically out of the
יבום yibum category and into a classic ארוסה arusa category. Very radical
understanding.
Wait, but you don't have a—she's still—you haven't clarified how she's a
שומרת יבם. shomeres yabam.
Yes, he's just
taken her out of that.
She becomes like an ארוסה. arusa. Right. The basic point is that
according to בית שמאי, beit shamai, the גמרא Gemara says you had
ארוסה arusa and נשואה, nesua, שומרת יבם shomeres yabam and כנוסה. knusa.
So the גמרא Gemara says, I understand how you could have an
ארוסה arusa that has had sex and still just an ארוסה. arusa.
She had sex בבית חמיה. beveit chameha. How do you have a
שומרת יבם shomeres yabam that has had sex and still only in
that category? It says, well according to בית שמאי, beit shamai, if
you first did קידושין, kiddushin, you did מאמר, maamar, and then you
had sex, right, she would still be like an ארוסה arusa who
has had sex. The קידושין kiddushin. put her in an ארוסה arusa
category, took her out of the יבום yibum category, and therefore even
the act of sex that follows, if it's not done as for
the purposes of creating נישואין, nisuin. it's just done for the purposes
of sex, she remains in the type of ארוסה arusa type of
a category. She does not—it's not like sex with a sister—with a—in
a יבום yibum context which automatically makes her a
נשואה. nesua. This is according to בית שמאי. beit shamai.
So the answer essentially is, how can you have a שומרת יבם
shomeres yabam like this? You can't. She has to leave the category
of שומרת יבם. shomeres yabam.
Right. But the חידוש chiddush is that according to בית שמאי beit
shamai by doing a מאמר maamar you basically are able to completely—until
now we've assumed for בית שמאי beit shamai that מאמר maamar counted
like יבום, yibum, but it did not completely supplant, right, the realities
of יבום. yibum. I mean, here we're actually saying that it completely
removes it from the יבום yibum category and now means that they
could have sex and she would still be in the ארוסה arusa
status as it were without going up to the נשואה nesua status.
Okay. Is she—is it prohibited?
Is she prohibited at that point?
To sleep with another man?
He's sleeping with his brother's...
No, she's permitted because that—the מאמר maamar works. You know, yeah, it
works. Yeah. But it just doesn't—but the sex now doesn't make her
automatically like a נשואה nesua according to בית שמאי. beit shamai.
Then how do you ever מקיים mekayem the מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum that way if you do מאמר? maamar?
You do it with the intention of creating
for the purpose not of just sex, for the purpose of making
her a נשואה, nesua, for the purpose of יבום. yibum. בית שמאי
beit shamai would say that
מאמר maamar requires the כוונה...
kavana... yeah. Okay.
So,
all
right, this is a pretty radical idea. Okay, I mean let's look
at רש״י, rashi, see it inside. רש״י rashi says ובית שמאי היא
דאמרי, uveit shamai hi deamri, it's the second narrow line, פרק ארבעה
אחין, perek arbaah achin, מאמר קונה קנין גמור לעשות ארוסה גמורה והפריח
את זיקת היבום, maamar koneh kinyan gamur laasot arusa gmura vehefriach et
zikat hayibum, it completely blew away the זיקת יבום, zikat yibum, ותו
לא מקניא לה בביאה מזיד, vetu lo maknya lah beviah mzid, and
sex—ביאה מזיד beviah mzid meaning sex for the purpose of sex—would no
longer be meaningful in this context. It would be like ארוסה בבית
אביה. arusa beveit aviha. And the מציאות חופה metziut chuppah כאישה דעלמא
k’ishah d’alma דתנן בארבעה אחין detnan beArba’ah Achin ומשום הכי איקרי לה
שומרת יבם umishum hacha ikarei lah shomeret yavam אפילו אחר ביאה afilu
achar biah דאי בי בית הלל de’ibei Beit Hillel לא אמרי מאמר
להפריח זיקת יבם lo amri ma’amar lehafriach zikat yavam ולשווי זיקת ארוסין
ונשואין ulshavei zikat arusin unisuin והויא לה ביאת זנות גביה. vehaveiah lah
biat zenut gabeih. So according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, now it
is not—this ביאת יבום biat yibum doesn't mean anything coming after—a ביאה
biah of some sex doesn't mean anything coming after מאמר. ma’amar. It
would only be a ביאה biah. now in the context of a
type of נשואין nisuin ביאה. bia Okay, so that's how you could
get—that's how you could get it according to שומרת יבם shomeret yavam
that he's already had sex with her brother-in-law and she's still in
the שומרת יבם shomeret yavam category. So the גמרא Gemara says: One
minute. אי הכי Ei hachi היינו ארוסה. hainu arusah. So then we're
basically talking about a variation of an ארוסה. arusah. So why is
it being—because you're basically saying you did קידושין, kiddushin it was binding,
it put her in an ארוסה arusah category. Why is it being
listed separately? So the גמרא Gemara says: ולטעמך נשואה וכנוסה לאו חדא
מילתא היא? Ultamecha nesuah ukhnusah lav chada milta hi? It says: Okay,
big deal. We also spoke about ארוסה arusah and נשואה, nesuah, שומרת
יבם shomeret yavam and כנוסה. kenusah. So when you get to stage
two, is there any halakhic difference between a נשואה nesuah and a
כנוסה—a kenusah woman who was a שומרת יבם shomeret yavam and now
they have performed יבום? yibum? No. Nevertheless, we talk about them as
parallel scenarios, even though they're not substantively different.
אלא נשואה דידיה וכנוסה דחבריה. Ela nesuah didey ukhnusah dechavre. נשואה nesuah
means a woman that he himself chose to marry, and כנוסה kenusah
is a woman that he married via his brother—that's his friend, his
brother. הכי נמי ארוסה דידיה ושומרת יבם דחבריה. Hacha nami arusah didey
veshomeret yavam dechavre. Okay,
so they're not really—they're basically more or less the same, but that's
the scenario. So what have we said about all this? We have
said that we've constructed a case where he's had sex with her
first, even before ארוסין, arusin, so he can—or whatever, before נשואין, nisuin,
so he can—and she can have strayed as an ארוסה arusah even
though they've already had sex. And we've figured out how we can
have that even in a שומרת יבם shomeret yavam case. And now
they are נשואות, nisuot, but he hasn't had sex after she has
been suspected, because then he would not be מנוקה מעון. menukah me’avon.
So that shows you, in the end, all of this is to
show you, like רב, Rav, that a חופה that occurs with a
woman who is a פסולה psulah still is meaningful and is binding
and they're considered to be נשואות. nisuot. Okay, and what's significant now
is that we've broadened the conversation, we're no longer talking about just
her status as it—like she's had sex and is she אסורה לתרומה
asurah letrumah and so on. It's a general question of חופה with
a woman who he is forbidden to. Here we've got a case
of סוטה, Sotah, we've had a case of איסור כהונה—I've issur kehunah
mentioned to you a more—a narrower case of נידה, Niddah, which is
very temporary and so on, but it's once we've broadened it like
this, it's worth thinking about that too. And in those cases, one
way to ask it is, is it like they've had sex in
terms of her status? But now the question is, is it like
the חופה was meaningful and are they considered to be נשואות? nisuot?
And here is a נפקא מינה nafka mina completely unrelated to the
question about making her drink in terms of the סוטה Sotah water.
Okay, so now the גמרא says like this: רב פפא אמר האי
תנא הוא דתניא. Rav Pappa amar hai tanna hu detanya. That question
that you've had about how can you make her drink if she's
an ארוסה arusah and you can only make her drink as a
נשואה, nesuah, you know, as a נשואה, nesuah, because it says תחת
אישך tachat ishech etc. No, he's going back to the older, earlier
question. It's a different תנא. Tanna. We taught in a ברייתא: braita
אין מקנא לה לארוסה להשקותה כשהיא ארוסה אבל מקנא לה להשקותה כשהיא
נשואה—that Ein mekana lah l'arusah l'hashkotah k'shehi arusah aval mekana lah l'hashkotah
k'shehi nesuah you do not
warn a woman who is an ארוסה arusah to make her drink
when she's an ארוסה, arusah, but you can warn her to make
her drink when she's a נשואה. nesuah. So what does that—what does
that solve?
So one minute.
Right, so רש״י Rashi says what that means is, is that—רש״י Rashi
says that somehow that means that the קינוי kinui happened when she
was an ארוסה, arusah, but the concern of going into private, when
it says להשקותה כשהיא נשואה, l'hashkotah k'shehi nesuah, it means that she
went into private when she was a נשואה. nesuah. So as opposed
to the way we were reading before, which is לא שטיתי כשהיא
ארוסה, lo satisi k'shehi arusah, which sounds like the suspicious behavior happened
as an ארוסה, arusah, he's saying that's not what we're talking about.
We're talking about that the suspicious behavior—the קינוי kinui happened when she
was an ארוסה, arusah, but the suspicious behavior happened when she was
a נשואה, nesuah, and therefore the whole proof goes off. רב נחמן
בר יצחק אמר על ידי גלגול. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar al
yedei gilgul. A totally different answer. Normally he's saying you're right. These
types of things you could never make a woman swear to. She
can only—you would only make her swear about a case of suspected
adultery when she was a נשואה, nesuah, not when she was an
ארוסה. arusah. And there's all these other questions about that they've had
to—only if the husband has had sex with her first, right? These
were all the questions we had. How did he have sex with
her first? If she possibly committed adultery as an ארוסה, arusah, how
did he go ahead and have חופה with her and have sex
with her afterwards? And we had all these questions, we constructed this
very bizarre case.
So now we're giving two easier answers. Easy answer number one is
that the קינוי kinui happened when she was an ארוסה, arusah, but
everything else happened when she was a נשואה. nesuah. It didn't sound
that way, but that's how we're explaining. And the second easy answer
is that you're right. As the foundational case to make her drink,
you cannot make her drink without satisfying all of those
criteria—that first they've had sex, she was suspected when she was a
נשואה, nesuah, etc. all those types of things. But once you're in
the process of making her drink, you can lump onto her any
type of suspicions, okay? And this is called גלגול שבועה. gilgul shvua.
From this we learn a general principle not limited to סוטה, Sota,
that once you get somebody on the stand and are able to
start getting them to make an oath about certain something that they're
obligated to make an oath on, you can throw everything else in
the kitchen sink in and have them swear about anything you want
them to swear by, okay? So this is a concept called גלגול
שבועה. gilgul shvua. So here what he's saying is, you're right. This
was a problematic case. They didn't have sex first, normally she would
only be a case of נשואה, nesua, not an
ארוסה. arusa. There you go. Right, once you give the power to
the special prosecutor, he can do whatever he wants, okay? You know,
all of those questions you had. They've had to have had sex
first, it had to be a נשואה nesua not an ארוסה, arusa,
etc., fine. That's not what we're talking about. We're talking about that
the basic basis for drinking and making this oath you had, it
was a classic case of סוטה. Sota. Once you're making her take
that oath, then you can make her swear about any other types
of
suspicions, okay? על ידי גלגול, al yedei gilgul, fine. And now we're
done with that. Okay, so we are, that is the end of
where we are up to now. So that was a fascinating little
digression about סוטה, Sota, about where we are with יש חופה לפסולות.
yesh chupa lifsulot. We've had a narrow question of is it like
ביאה biah to invalidate this woman for eating תרומה, trumah and now
a broader question of are they considered to be married in general,
even for a הלכה halacha like סוטה. Sota. Now we're not done.
Let's, we have one final act in this play. Yes?
I don't understand this ברייתא רב פפא Rav Papa brought. In other
words, he did קינוי kinuy when she was an ארוסה, arusa, then
he had sex with her and then she, there was סתירה stira
and he made her drink? Yep.
So he had sex with her even after the קינוי. kinuy. Right.
Which would have been, which is אסור assur thing to do but.
No, it's אסור assur to have sex after the סתירה, stira, not
after the קינוי. kinuy.
Oh, oh, it's not אסור assur after the קינוי. kinuy.
No, the קינוי kinuy is he's just jealous. He hasn't done anything
after that.
Okay, okay. So he does a קינוי, kinuy, he has sex with
her, she's now a נשואה, nesua, if he obligated, if she, oh
I see, then she does the act of סתירה stira and then
he drinks, then she drinks?
Right. Okay. So now the גמרא says like this. שלח
ליה רב חנינא משמיה דרב יוחנן, Shalach leh Rav Chanina mishmei deRav
Yochanan, רב חנינא Rav Chanina sent in the name of רב יוחנן.
Rav Yochanan. עשה מאמר ביבמתו, Asa maamar beyevamto, a man does מאמר
maamar with his sister-in-law, ויש לו אח, veyesh lo ach, and he's
got a brother, אפילו הוא כהן והיא כהנת, afilu hu kohen vehi
kohenet, even if he is a כהן kohen and she is a
כהנת, kohenet, פסלה מן התרומה, pasla min hatruma, he has invalidated her
from תרומה. trumah. So what does this mean? So, let me just
double-check רש״י Rashi again. Oh, meaning until they actually consummate, okay? Because,
and here's why, because, well let's take a look.
Because the brother,
ironically, although everything seems to be wonderful. Look, she's a בת כהן,
bat kohen, she can eat תרומה terumah because of her father. Yes,
he's a kosher woman, she's not a, to a כהן, kohen she's
not a גרושה, grusha, she's not an אלמנה, almana, she's not a
whatever, nothing. Okay, this brother who's a כהן kohen does מאמר. maamar.
Wonderful, everything is great. Either as a result of the father or
as a result of the pending נישואין, nisuin she should be able
to eat תרומה. terumah? Except because he's done מאמר, maamar, the other
brother, the other guy who didn't do מאמר, maamar, is not allowed
to do יבום yibum with her, right? Right, because one brother did
מאמר, maamar, the other brother is, is excluded from doing יבום. yibum.
But the other brother still has a זיקה, zika, okay? It's in
this very weird middle stage. He's got a זיקה, zika, but he's
אסור assur to do to act on it. So he is saying
that that would be like רבי מאיר's case of a woman who
is שומרת לביאה פסולה. shomeret lebia psula. It's like he also still
has a little bit of a קידושין kiddushin with the other brother,
and if that were ever consummate with the other brother, then that
would be a ביאה אסורה bia assura because this brother did מאמר
maamar with her. So that fact makes her at this stage אסור
assur to eat תרומה. terumah. Even though everything was done exactly the
way it should have done, but because there's this weird stage that
one brother has still a present זיקה zika which could still, you
know,
which if you were to act on it would be invalid.
So she's in a condition of freeze-dried adultery?
I wouldn't say that, but anyway, yes.
Just by nature of her having relationships in her life that are
אסור, assur, she's,
she could be awaiting an אסור.
assur.
Yeah, but that's not, there's no הלכתי halachic meaning to that. You
mean let's say she has a boyfriend?
Right, but there's an actual brother here, right?
Right, so the point is that there's a זיקה zika here. The
זיקה, zika, the point is that the זיקה zika to this other
brother, even though he's the brother that didn't do מאמר, maamar, is
like a quasi-הלכתי קידושין. halachic kidushin. That's his idea. Okay, let's read
in the גמרא.
He drinks תרומה terumah, wine for the brother...
All right, let's, let's go ahead and look at it. The גמרא
says like this.
למן, Leman, who does this go like? אילימא כרבי מאיר, Ilima keRabbi
Meir, if it's like רבי מאיר, אימא דאמר רבי מאיר, eima d'amar
Rabbi Meir, שומרת לביאה פסולה לא אכלה. shomeret lebia psula lo achla.
When does רבי מאיר say a woman who is awaiting ביאה פסולה,
bia psula, like a קידושין that if it were to be consummated
would be a ביאה פסולה, bia psula, that she can't
eat? אימא דאמר רבי מאיר Eima d'amar Rabbi Meir שומרת לביאה פסולה
לא אכלה. shomeret lebia psula lo achla. מדאורייתא? mideoraita? When the forbidden
act of sex is a biblically forbidden act of sex. דרבנן Derabbanan
מי אמר? mi amar? Here, even if she were to consummate with
the other brother that would not be biblically forbidden, this whole מאמר
maamar thing is only rabbinic. סבר לה כרבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון, Savar
lah k'Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon, which is crazy, they're the ones that
are more lenient.
התם Hatam משמשת ביאה פסולה דאורייתא אכלה. mishameshet biah psulah deoraita achlah.
Even a woman who is awaiting an invalid biblical ביאה biah, can
still eat, meaning awaiting meaning like she's in a קידושין that were
to consummate would be that, דרבנן מבעיא? derabbanan mibaya? So this doesn't
make any sense. Even רבי מאיר wouldn't go that far. אלא כי
אתא רבין אמר
Ela
ki
ata Ravin amar when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
he said, עשה בה מאמר ביבמתו asah bah maamar biyevamto דברי הכל
אכלה. divrei hakol achlah. If no, you're right, forget what we said
before. If הכהן hakohen did מאמר, maamar, she can eat, even though
there's another brother who were to act on his זיקה zikah would
create problems, but okay, he that's only rabbinic and he's on the
outs, so fine, no problem. However, יש לו אח חלל, yesh lo
ach chalal, let's say the other brother who did not do מאמר
maamar is a חלל, chalal, okay? So in that case, now a
חלל chalal that has has sex with a woman makes her a
חללה chalalah, and invalidates her from eating תרומה, okay? So here you
have, this is a woman who is a בת כהן, bat kohen,
she's eating תרומה from her father's house. She is now has had
מאמר maamar with her husband died, מאמר maamar with one of the
brothers, they're going to consummate it, שאר ישראל, she'ar Yisrael, everybody is
כשר, kasher, would be a wonderful marriage. But the brother who didn't
do מאמר maamar is a חלל chalal
and he's got a half-brother right, he'd have to be a half-brother
right. And he has a זיקה, zikah, and what even though he
hasn't done מאמר maamar and he should be considered ignored, nevertheless there
is still a זיקה zikah and were he to act on it
it would be a ביאה פסולה דאורייתא. biah psulah deoraita.
Okay, so he had a wife who was a
גרושה?
grushah? Yeah, but then the other one would also be a חלל,
chalal, so he's half, רש"י is correct, for one to be a
חלל chalal and the other not, they'd have to have different mothers.
Really? Because if one כהן kohen,
marries a גרושה grushah his brother becomes a חלל chalal also? No,
that's why he'd be the half-brother. Two כהנים Kohanim are brothers, how
could one be a חלל chalal and the other not? One one's
mother was a גרושה grushah and the other was not, so they're
half-brothers, they have the same father, different mother. Okay, so you'll figure
it out. דברי הכל אין Divrei hakol ein so in that case,
דברי הכל אינה אוכלת. divrei hakol einah ochelet. Everybody would agree that
she would not eat. לא נחלקו אלא שנתן לה גט. Lo nechelku
ela shenatan lah get.
So the question is, now the question is why is it
דברי
הכל? divrei hakol? So,
why is it דברי הכל divrei hakol a minute?
Yeah, oh, okay, so רש"י says why is it דברי הכל, divrei
hakol, why is it even רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון? Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi
Shimon? רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon normally say that
let's say a case of a גרושה grushah to a כהן kohen
she can eat תרומה. So why here can she not? Because they
say remember in this case, right, of a גרושה grushah married to
a כהן, kohen. right, רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon
say she can eat because this כהן kohen although normally קידושין would
take her away from the father, here it is קידושין to a
כהן. kohen Now even though it's a problematic because she's a גרושה,
grushah, but the כהן kohen, if he's married to another woman could
allow that other woman to eat, יש לו להאכיל במקום אחר, yesh
lo lehachil b'makom acher, you might remember that, right? But in this
case she's not a גרושה, grushah, okay? And he did here מאמר,
maamar,
okay? But here you've got a חלל chalal brother who's got a
זיקה, zikah, okay? In this case even רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi
Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon would agree it's a problem, why? Because if we
acknowledge the זיקה, zikah, the quasi-קידושין,
this case is worse. You know why this case is worse than
the other case of the גרושה? grushah? Because this חלל chalal no
woman can ever eat on behalf of him, right? Because he's a
חלל, chalal, his so the זיקה zikah takes her away from her
father's house like a קידושין takes her away, and she doesn't stay
in the פרשה parashah because she's married to a כהן kohen because
this although this is good, but because this also exists and this
is a type of thing which she can never
eat on this חלל chalal can never have a woman eat on
his behalf. Okay? So therefore even רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer
v'Rabbi Shimon would say that that is a problem.
But מאמר maamar is not stronger than the זיקה. zikah.
Correct, or it doesn't remove the זיקה, zikah, correct, remove all consideration
of that. Okay, so דברי הכל אינה אוכלת. divrei hakol einah ochelet.
לא נחלקו, Lo nechelku, the whole debate is, אלא שנתן לה גט.
ela shenatan lah get. Okay, so he went ahead, the guy who
did the מאמר, maamar, after doing the מאמר, maamar,
went ahead and gave her a גט. get. Let me just check
something.
Right. So רבי
יוחנן אמר אוכלת. Rabbi Yochanan amar ochelet. No, so there's no אח
חלל. ach chalal. Okay, I think there's no אח חלל, ach chalal,
I'm trying to remember this. Okay? First he did a מאמר maamar
and then he cancelled the מאמר maamar by giving a גט. get.
Okay? Okay? And
then he cancelled. After having given a גט, get, rabbinically he's not
allowed to go ahead and to do יבום, yibum, right? And so
but there's still biblically is a זיקה. zika. Okay, so we're back
to this case where there's still biblically this זיקה, zika, okay, but
it if he were to act on it, it would be a
rabbinically forbidden. So that's משמרת mishmeret would be a פסולה דרבנן. psula
d'rabbanan.
Rabbinically he cannot do ביאה, biah okay. So why don't we say,
we just got through saying that if it's only a rabbinic problem
then it should not be a problem. So let's see what the
issue is. לא נחלקו אלא שנתן לה גט. lo nechleku ella shenatan
lah get. רבי יוחנן אומר אוכלת וריש לקיש אומר אינה אוכלת. Rabbi
Yochanan omer ochelet v'Resh Lakish omer einah ochelet. Let's see what this
is about. רבי יוחנן אומר אוכלת, Rabbi Yochanan omer ochelet, אפילו רבי
מאיר דאמר אינה אוכלת, afilu Rabbi Meir d'amar einah ochelet, הני מילי
משמרת וביאה פסולה דאורייתא. hani milei mishmeret u'biah psulah d'oraita. Even Rabbi
Meir that says there's a problem by קידושין if the ביאה biah
were to cause because of the ביאה biah that when it would
be a ביאה biah that would be biblically invalid. אבל דרבנן אוכלת,
aval d'rabbanan ochelet, this is after a גט, get, in this case
it's only a rabbinic problem, right? Because the גט, get, I mean
she's not a real גרושה דאורייתא, grusha d'oraita, this is a גט
get in a יבום yibum context, so doing יבום yibum after a
גט, get, even for a כהן, kohen? is only a rabbinic problem
and therefore he says even Rabbi Meir would say she could eat
in this case.
She could eat חליצה chalitzah in this case?
Yes. וריש לקיש אומר אינה אוכלת, v'Resh Lakish omer einah ochelet, אפילו
רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון דאמרי אוכלת, afilu Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Shimon d'amri
ochelet, הני מילי יש לה להאכיל במקום אחר. hani milei yesh lah
l'haachil bemakom acher. אבל הכא כיון דאין לה להאכיל במקום אחר לא.
aval hacha keivan d'ein lah l'haachil bemakom acher lo.
That's only because he could normally have somebody else eat on his
behalf. But here he could not have somebody else eat on his
behalf. Why not? Hold on, I'm trying to remember this case.
Oh, because here any other woman he would have given a גט
get to, he could never have, that no other woman he could
have given a גט get to could ever eat on his behalf.
Okay, so here
even though it's even Rabbi Elazar and Rabbi Shimon normally they say
it's because the כהן kohen if he were married to another woman
in a similar type of circumstance, she could eat on his behalf
if she weren't a גרושה. grusha. But here his relationship with any
other woman after having given that woman a גט get would never
be able to have that other woman eat on his behalf. So
therefore even in this case she cannot eat, okay?
She goes back to her father.
What? So that's the point. The point is is that because once
there's קידושין or זיקה, zika, which is like קידושין, it takes her
away from the father. The question is, is she still eating on
behalf of the כהן? kohen, So what Rabbi Elazar and Rabbi Shimon
have normally said is even though were they to have ביאה biah
it would be a problem, they haven't had ביאה yet, and since
it's a type of relationship that in another circumstance where she not
a גרושה grusha or whatever, the woman could eat, we'll allow her
to continue to eat. But here the argument of ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish is, but if it's another woman that he had given a
גט get to, this defines the relationship, it's not just she happens
to be a גרושה, grusha, this is what defines the relationship, then
that type of a case she could not eat.
If he marries an unrelated other woman, that other woman can't eat
תרומה from him because he had given this woman a גט? get?
No. But if it were a similar relationship defined by a גט,
get, another woman couldn't eat. Okay. כיון דאין לה להאכיל במקום אחר
לא. keivan d'ein lah l'haachil bemakom acher lo. וכי תימא הכא נמי
יש לה להאכיל בחוזרת. v'ki teima hacha nami yesh lah l'haachil bechozeret.
Ab, one minute. If there's a case where he could give a
גט get to a woman and a woman could go back eating
eating תרומה? How? He was married to a woman who is a
בת כהן, Kohen, he gave her a גט, get, and then she
went back and she's to her father's house and she ate by
virtue of her father. So there could be a woman who got
a גט get from a כהן Kohen who eats
תרומה. So גמרא says, yeah, but חוזרת פסיקא מיניה וקרובה לבי נשא,
chozeret psika minei u'krova l'vei nasha, when it's חוזרת chozeret that relationship
stops and she's now eating by virtue of the father. אבל הכא
אגידה ביה, aval hacha agida beih, here she's not going back to
the father, there's still the זיקה zika and the גט. get. So
any woman who is related to him through a גט, get, she
could never eat by virtue of him, and therefore even Rabbi Elazar
and Rabbi Shimon would agree in this case. Let's finish to the
next משנה. mishna. נתאלמנה או נתגרשה, nitalmenah o nitgarshah,
if they were divorced or גרושין geirushin after this אירוסין eirusin then
they could to a person that's like a case of a גרושה
grusha to a כהן, Kohen, then they could go back to eating
תרומה, okay. So the גמרא says like this. בעי מיניה רב חייא
בר יוסף משמואל. baei minei Rav Chiyya bar Yosef mi'Shmuel. So Rav
Chiyya bar Yosef asked from Shmuel. כהן גדול שקידש את הקטנה ובגרה
תחתיו. kohen gadol shekiddesh et haktanah u'bagrah tachtav.
Great, great. A כהן גדול kohen gadol we're going to read in
the next משנה Mishnah. has to marry a woman as a נערה,
naarah, okay, or a קטנה, ktanah, but not as a בוגרת, bogeret,
okay, or that'll be a debate, that's the next משנה. Let's say
he goes and he marries this young girl when she's a קטנה
ktanah and then נבאך nebach he waited so long before the חופה
she's now already an old maid of thirteen years old and she's
a בוגרת, bogeret, okay. So when the when we say that he
has that he has to marry a woman who is not a
בוגרת, bogeret, is that קידושין or is that נישואין? nisuin So let's
take a
look. So, מהו, mahu, what's the הלכה? halacha? Top of נט עמוד
א. nun tet amud aleph. בתר נישואין אזלינן או בתר אירוסין אזלינן.
batar nisuin azlinan o batar eirusin azlinan. What do we go to
define that he has to marry a woman who... is not a
בוגרת. bogeres. A כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, is it defined by קידושין
or defined by נישואין? nisuin? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to
him, תניתוה, tanitua, we taught in our משנה. נתאלמנה או נתגרשה מן
הנישואין, nis-almana o nis-garsha min ha-nisuin, these women that are אסור assur
to a כהן, kohen, if they got divorced after נישואין, nisuin. פסול,
pasul, then they're פסול pasul because it's like they've had sex, we
assume they've had sex, it's like they've had sex and they remain
forbidden and they remain invalidated, the act of sex invalidated them. So
מן האירוסין, min ha-eirusin, כשרה, kesheira, but if it's after אירוסין, eirusin,
they are כשרה. kesheira. Now exactly what that exactly proves is not
clear. It seems like he's saying you see that what matters for
כהנים Kohanim is the נישואין. nisuin So if that's what matters for
כהנים for the נישואין nisuin, in order to define her as a
חללה, chalalah, the sex to define her as a חללה, chalalah. presumably
that's what also matters in terms of defining her status in terms
of being a נערה na'arah when she is married. So the גמרא
says אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, לשוויה חללה
לא קמיבעיא לי. leshavyah chalalah lo kamibaya li. I didn't have a
question of what act makes her a חללה. chalalah? ביאה היא דמשויא
חללה. biah hi de-mshavya chalalah. Obviously sex changes the status of the
woman. Okay, that's in general. It's a normal case we know, it's
אסור, assur, blah blah blah. What act makes her a חללה? It's
the act of sex. כי קמיבעיא לי, ki kamibaya li, I'm asking
a narrow question about the דין din of marrying a woman as
a קטנה ketanah or not as a בוגרת. bogeres. והוא אשה בבתוליה
יקח. ve-hu isha vi-vsuleha yikach. He should take a woman who's a
virgin that we're going to read later according to some mean that
she's even before she's a בוגרת. bogeres. So מאי, mai, what does
that mean? קיחה דקידושין בעינן? kichah de-kiddushin bainan? The act of קידושין
is at that stage? Okay, או קיחה דנישואין בעינן? o kichah de-nisuin
bainan? Or even the נישואין nisuin. has to be at that stage?
It's a very simple question. When we say that he has to
marry a woman in this way, are we talking about a woman
who's not a בוגרת, bogeres, is it קידושין or נישואין? nisuin. So
בעינן. bainan. אמר ליה, amar lei, he said הא נמי תניתוה, ha
nami tanisua, we taught that. אירס את האלמנה. eiras es ha-almana. A
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, a כהן did אירוסין eirusin with a widow
who is מותרת mutteres to a כהן, אסורה assura to a כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, ונתמנה להיות כהן גדול, ve-nismana li-hyos Kohen Gadol, and
then before the חופה, he was appointed a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Can he go through with the חופה? Okay, so יכנוס, yichnos, he
can go through with the חופה. So you see that that's if
the idea of אלמנה almana applies only to the act of קידושין,
presumably all of these special things about a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
apply only to the moment of קידושין, not the moment of נישואין.
nisuin. So it says no. שאני התם, shani hasam, there it's different.
דכתיב, de-chsiv, the פסוק pasuk says יקח אשה. yikach isha. Who, you
know, אשה, isha, he shall take as a wife, and therefore we
learn from יקח אשה, yikach isha, כי אם בתולה מעמיו יקח אשה.
ki im bsulah me-amav yikach isha. So from that extra verse of
יקח אשה, yikach isha, because it said יקח, yikach, we learn
an extra case that he can marry a woman. Even in this
type of a scenario where the קידושין was okay and now it's
נישואין nisuin that's problematic, he can go through with it because the
קידושין was okay when she was an אלמנה. almana. So we have
a special פסוק. pasuk. So the גמרא says okay, if you have
a special פסוק pasuk to allow by אלמנה, almana, then you should
have the same thing by this case of a בוגרת. bogeres. So
the גמרא says הכא נמי כתיב
אשה. hacha nami ksiv isha. So say the same thing here, that
if your פסוק pasuk says the special הלכות halachos of a כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol that it has to be a non-אלמנה, almana, a
virgin, you know, a what do you call it, a non-בוגרת, bogeres,
so if we learn by אלמנה almana from the extra word אשה
isha that that goes only by קידושין, not by נישואין, nisuin let's
say the same thing about not being a בוגרת bogeres only goes
by קידושין. So the גמרא says no. אשה אחת ולא שתים. isha
achas ve-lo shtayim. And it only says one אשה, isha, not two.
So we can only include one case. We can't include all the
cases. So מאי חזית, mai chazis, what motivates you to include the
case by אלמנה almana and not to include the case of בוגרת?
bogeres? So the גמרא says הא אשתני גופא והא לא אשתני גופא.
ha ishtani gufa ve-ha lo ishtani gufa. Did her body change or
not? When a woman goes from being a קטנה ketanah to a
בוגרת, bogeres, it's a more significant change and therefore when she's an
אלמנה almana and her non-אלמנה, almana, it's not a significant change. Now
again, it's very hard to understand what the heck difference does that
mean. Make up your mind. Either these הלכות halachos go by קידושין
defining which women he can marry or they go by נישואין. nisuin?
Why by an אלמנה almana who physically there's no change to her
body, oh, no change to her body, that we'll say just goes
by קידושין. By בוגרת, bogeres, oh her body has changed, she's changed
from being a minor to an adult, that's problematic even at the
נישואין. nisuin. Like it's not clear at all what the logic is
there. So תוספות says the following thing. תוספות says it's not so
much that her body changed, it's about who did the change occur
to. He says in one case the קידושין was, her status was
defined. The change in status came to him. He became a כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, right, after קידושין, right? In the other case, the
change of status came to her. He started as a כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, she became
a
בוגרת. bogeres. בוגרת bogeres and he was a normal כהן, and then
he became a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So it says it could
be in that case he's allowed to marry her. As long as
her status remains the same and it's his status that changed, you
can go by the virtue of the קידושין. And if the קידושין
was okay, you can go through with the נישואין. nisuin. But when
it's her status that changed, then you have to reassess and then
you can't do the נישואין if the נישואין if she's not in
that status. So in terms of the question of do the do
the special requirements of a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, that she be
a virgin, that she be a non-בוגרת, bogeres, that she not be
an אלמנה, almanah, do they apply at קידושין or נישואין? According to
the way תוספות understands the answer, it's basically it applies when in
terms of that if he married her when she was not in
that status and then and then her status changed, then it's a
problem at נישואין. If he married her when in when she was
in that status and his status changed, then you can still go
on the original status and still go through with the נישואין. All
right, so not exactly clear what the logic is for all that.
We will continue looking at כהן גדול kohen gadol and his special
statuses tomorrow.