Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is מ"א. mem aleph.
We pick up in the middle of מ"א עמוד ב' mem amud
bais and we are up to we had done the משנה mishna
which spoke about the whole idea that a חלוצה chalutza is considered
like a excuse me חלוצה chalutza is considered like a גרושה gerusha
with the implications about the relatives and then a weird הלכה halacha
at the end about צרת קרובת חלוצתו tzaras krovos chalutsaso which we'll
get to. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. איבעיא להו
Iba'aya lehu so we're on the top of מ"א עמוד ב'. mem
amud bais. We are definitely a little behind. איבעיא להו, Iba'aya lehu,
they asked a fun question: גזרו שניות בחלוצה או לא? gazru shniyos
b'chalutza o lo?
So when the חלוצה chalutza is treated as a גרושה gerusha and
you're not allowed with one another's relatives as if this was a
woman that the man was married to and then divorced, would that
would we also apply not just basic עריות arayos but even the
rabbinic עריות? arayos? Right. So the משנה mishna sounds like it did.
It does, but we'll discuss it in the
גמרא. Gemara. דאורייתא D'oraisa gazru ברבנן שניות, brabbanan shniyos, בחלוצה לא גזרו
רבנן שניות. b'chalutza lo gazru rabbanan shniyos. By biblical relationships when the
man really was married to the woman that's where there'll be an
idea of שניות לעריות shniyos l'arayos but not in חלוצה chalutza which
is only rabbinically considered as if he's wife. By the way I
should point out that there is you know we've discussed before that
חלוצה chalutza is considered a גרושה gerusha for a כהן kohen and
there's some evidence that in the tannaic literature that was even considered
to be that status דאורייתא d'oraisa she's considered like a גרושה gerusha
although the גמרא Gemara insists it's דרבנן d'rabbanan but her status as
a כהן kohen is not the same as this issue in terms
of the עריות arayos right it's one thing to say since you
had an act of חליצה chalitza done she's a חלוצה chalutza and
her status has changed to a כהן kohen and it's another thing
to say that because he did this act of חליצה chalitza this
if the two of them were married and had formed this relationship
between the two of them and that implicates or whatever you know
pulls in all of the עריות arayos that's clearly דרבנן. d'rabbanan. So
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. So by a woman the man
was really married to that's דאורייתא d'oraisa and there's שניות, shniyos, בחלוצה
לא גזרו רבנן שניות b'chalutza lo gazru rabbanan shniyos but not by
the חלוצה chalutza which is rabbinic. או דלמא לא שנא O dilma
lo shana or maybe it doesn't matter. תא שמע Ta shma come
in here. הוא אסור באמה ובאם אמה. Hu assur b'ima u'b'eim ima.
So when it says that he he cannot now marry that he
did חליצה chalitza with this woman it's her mother and her grandmother
which all would be a biblical עריות. arayos. ואילו אם אם אמה
לא תניא V'ilu eim eim ima lo tanya and it doesn't say
her great-grandmother.
So the fact that it stops as grandmother is stopping at the
biblical עריות arayos it's not going on to the rabbinic ones. So
that seems to be a proof. So the גמרא Gemara says no
דילמא היינו טעמא דלא תניא משום דקבעי למתני סיפא ואחין מותרין. dilma
hainu ta'ama d'lo tanya mishum d'ka'ba'i misni seifa v'achin mutarin. No maybe
the reason it didn't speak about great-grandmothers because then it wants to
say that even though he is forbidden the brothers are permissible because
they don't have a relationship with this woman. דוקא באם אם אמה
Davka b'eim eim ima
and if it would have said that he is forbidden in the
great-grandmother and then it said but the brothers are permissible so I
would have הוה אמינא hava amina I would have interpreted it to
mean אחין תהא מותרין דוקא באם אם אמה achin t'hi mutarim davka
b'eim eim ima that they're permitted only with the great-grandmother אבל באם
אמה ואמה לא aval b'eim ima v'ima lo but I might not
have I might have said oh well maybe only permitted with the
great-grandmother not with the grandmother and the mother. So therefore it stops
so you wouldn't misinterpret what the היתר heter was for the brothers.
So the גמרא Gemara says ולתני אם אם אמה v'lisni eim eim
ima why
I don't understand how hard would it have been to say both?
Say he's forbidden in the great-grandmother ולתני אחין מותרין בכולם v'lisni achin
mutarin b'kulam and say the brothers are permitted in all of these
women. Alright קשיא kashya that's difficult. So you got a good point
that it stopped by grandmother and should have gone on to great-grandmother
if שניות shniyos were included. תא שמע Ta shma let's try it
again. היא אסורה באביו ובאבי אביו. Hi asura b'aviv u'b'avi aviv. Now
here's where it starts getting to be more interesting because here the
simple sense of the משנה mishna really is only talking about שניות.
shniyos. Let's take a look. היא אסורה באביו ובאבי אביו Hi asura
b'aviv u'b'avi aviv
she is forbidden with his father and his grandfather. קתני מיהא אבי
אביו Katani miha avi aviv the grandfather now again עריות arayos are
defined from the man's perspective. So grandfather is his the grandfather so
let's take a look at father. Why can't she marry the father?
Because from the man's perspective it is his daughter-in-law right is that
clear right? If it's her husband's father it's the guy's daughter-in-law that's
in the תורה. Torah. But grandfather that's the guy's son's daughter-in-law. So
that's not a biblical עריות. arayos. So קתני מיהא אבי אביו מאי
לאו משום חולץ? katani miha avi aviv mai lav mishum cholets?
It seems that it's because of this man she did חליצה chalitza
with דהוה ליה כלת בנו d'hava lei kallas bno
and therefore it is the grandfather's it is you know the man's
son's daughter-in-law and which is rabbinic. So it says לא משום מת
lo mishum misna it's not because of him it's because of the
dead guy דהוה ליה כלת בנו d'hava lei kallas bno
and there it is yes it's the same thing it's his son's
son-in-law but it is a biblical not a rabbinic one. What does
that mean? This is going to be what we're going to be
doing here. with
what we're going to be doing here. I'm sorry, I'm just going
to use a sort of quadrant because I don't want to erase
this, but anyway, I hope this will be enough space. If not,
I'll erase it. Anyway, we're going to be doing this throughout these
cases in the משנה, mishna, which we're going to actually be saying
you're right, you got the relationship right, and the relationship is only
a שנייה לעריות, shniya l'arayot, but it's not a proof that the
חלוצה chaluza status is relevant because not only is she a חלוצה
chaluza to one brother, she's also a brother's wife, no זיקה zika
to the others. Yes, but to the dead guy, she actually is
the dead brother's wife, you know, widow. Okay, so yes you'll have
a case of שניות, shniyot, but it's not שניות shniyot from the
חלוצה chaluza side, it's a שניות shniyot on the biblical side of
the guy she was married to. Okay, so if you've got ראובן
Reuven
and
שמעון. Shimon. Okay, ראובן Reuven dies. He does חליצה chalitza with רחל.
Rachel. Now it says he cannot marry his, who's שמעון's Shimon father?
יעקב Yaakov and then יצחק. Yitzchak. Okay. She can't marry יצחק. Yitzchak.
Why? To say oh because יצחק Yitzchak because that for יצחק Yitzchak
it's יעקב's Yaakov daughter-in-law.
Right? So that's okay but that's a שנייה, shniya, a father's son's
daughter-in-law is a שנייה shniya and so you see you give the
חלוצה chalitza status to a שנייה. shniya. Gemara says oh no, because
יעקב Yaakov guess what is also ראובן's Reuven father. So yes it's
a שנייה, shniya, but it's not because of the חלוצה chalitza status,
it's the
it's יצחק's Yitzchak son's daughter-in-law based on the דאורייתא de'oraisa relationship. So
it's a שנייה shniya for a דאורייתא de'oraisa relationship, not a שנייה
shniya for rabbinic relationship. And that's how we're going to go through
the משנה, mishna, that all of these things are not because of
שמעון, Shimon, all of these things are because of ראובן Reuven which
is the דאורייתא de'oraisa relationship.
The purpose of the גזירה gzaira of שניות shniyot for the חלוצה
chaluza is what? It's not
גזירה. gzaira. It says...
yeah but basically it means like what we give her status of
a חלוצה chaluza and then we the it's the same way שנייה
shniya is a גזירה gzaira for the biblical. but it's just an
expansion. I'm not going to get into the idea of גזירה gzaira
as a safeguard, it's just an expansion. Okay, so Gemara says like
this: לא משום משנה דהויא
ליה כלת בנו.
lo mishum mishna dahavya
leh kallas beno. Yeah, sure, it's his son's daughter-in-law, but the daughter-in-law
is through ראובן. Reuven. It's יעקב's Yaakov daughter-in-law through ראובן Reuven and
that's biblical so that allows us to make a שנייה לעריות. shniya
l'arayot.
Okay, תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear: ובן בנו, u'ven beno,
she also cannot marry שמעון's Shimon grandson. So מאי לאו דמשום
mai lav de'mishum חלוצה, chaluza, it must be because of שמעון, Shimon,
דהויא ליה אשת אבי אביו. dahavya leh eshes avi aviv. So what's
שמעון's Shimon grandson? Okay, so שמעון's Shimon grandson is, I don't know
who שמעון's Shimon grandson is, but anyway we'll just draw it like
this. Okay, okay well I guess son and we'll do son and
grandson. Okay, so שמעון's Shimon grandson to רחל Rachel who is so
she can't marry שמעון's Shimon grandson. שמעון's Shimon grandson is from the
grandson's perspective, his grandfather's wife. Now his father's wife is biblical, but
his grandfather's wife is rabbinic. So here you have a שנייה לעריות
shniya l'arayot due to the status of חלוצה. chalitza. So the Gemara
says מאי לאו משום חלוצה דהויא ליה אשת אבי אביו mai lav
mishum chaluza dahavya leh eshes avi aviv isn't it because of שמעון's
Shimon status to her and that's therefore the grandfather's wife, אשת אבי
אביו? eshes avi aviv? So the Gemara
says לא משום משנה דהויא ליה אשת אחי אבי אביו. lo mishum
mishna dahavya leh eshes achi avi aviv. So no because ראובן Reuven
is the דאורייתא de'oraisa relationship. So who's רחל Rachel to the grandson?
It's his great uncle's wife. Okay, you got that? Now biblically the
man's uncle's wife is biblical, right?
Father's brother's wife. So great uncle's wife is rabbinic, but it's rabbinic
from the perspective of ראובן. Reuven. We're ignoring שמעון. Shimon. So since,
is that clear? Since this would be biblical, right? I'm sorry, you
know if it was you know if it was here if it
was father's brother's wife, right? That's biblical, right? So grandfather's brother's wife,
that's a שנייה לעריות. shniya l'arayot. So it's not because of שמעון's
Shimon relationship to רחל, Rachel, it's because of ראובן, Reuven, but it's
a שנייה shniya based on the biblical idea of father's brother's wife.
So it's grandfather's brother's wife. Okay, so it says לא משום lo
mishum where was he? Okay,
so the Gemara says לא משום משנה lo mishum mishna the dead
guy, דהויא ליה אשת dahavya leh eshes the wife of, אחי אבי
אביו achi avi aviv the grandfather's brother. Okay, but we're ignoring שמעון.
Shimon. Even based on ראובן, Reuven, it's a problem and that's a
שנייה לעריות. shniya l'arayot. Okay, Gemara says one minute, אמימר מכשר באשת
אחי אבי אביו. Ameimar machshir b'eshes achi avi aviv. אמימר Ameimar says
that your grand uncle your great uncle's wife is not a שנייה
לעריות. shniya l'arayot. So there's no way that this could be based
on ראובן Reuven because your great uncle's wife is not a problem.
So the Gemara says אמימר מוקי לה
בבר ברא דסבא. Ameimar moki lah be'var bra de'sabba. No, because what
המימר Amemar says when it says she cannot marry the son and
the grandson, okay, it's a very hard read, because first it says
that רחל Rachel cannot marry, you know, שמעון'ס Shimon's father and grandson,
right? And then it says she can't marry the son and grandson,
this is a very hard read of the ברייתא. Braita. It doesn't
mean שמעון'ס Shimon's son and grandson. It means she can't marry יעקב'ס
Yaakov's son and grandson, okay? So it's a little trick to get
out of the problem. We're not talking about שמעון'ס Shimon's son and
grandson, we push it all up a generation. All right, which is
a weak answer, but anyway, אי הכי היינו אחיו ובן אחיו. ei
hachi, hainu achiv u'ven achiv. One minute. If it's she can't marry
יעקב'ס Yaakov's son or יעקב'ס Yaakov's grandson, so why, that's שמעון'ס Shimon's
brother, right? Yeah and and שמעון'ס Shimon's brother's son, well, that's already
in the משנה. Mishna. תנא אחיו מן האב וקתני אחיו מן האם?
Tanna achiv min ha'av uk'tani achiv min ha'em? So why do you
say it again? היינו אחיו ובן אחיו, Hainu achiv u'ven achiv, that's
already in the משנה. Mishna. So no, תנא אחיו מן האב וקתני
אחיו מן האם. Tanna achiv min ha'av uk'tani achiv min ha'em. No,
because it wants to tell you both forms of of brothers, a
paternal brother and a maternal brother. Okay, moving on. So we basically
have that רחל Rachel can't marry going up these generations and down
these generations. It sounds like a שני לעריות sheni l'arayot because even
at a biblical thing, two two, you know, you know, that would
be considered, you know, that that these two generations would be a
second degree, would be a שני. sheni. And the גמרא'ס Gemara's basic
answer is yes, it's a שני לעריות, sheni l'arayot, but from ראובן'ס
Reuven's perspective, not שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so it's not based on this
דרבנן derabbanan relationship, it's based on this דאורייתא de'oraisa relationship. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this: תא שמע, ta shema, come in
here, דתני רבי חייא ארבע מדברי תורה וארבע מדברי סופרים. d'tani Rabbi
Chiya arba midivrei Torah v'arba midivrei Sofrim. רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya says
the people that the that are forbidden due to the חליצה chalitza
status, four are based on biblical relationships and four are are based
on rabbinic, meaning the חלוצה'ס chalutza's always rabbinic, but we are importing
four types of biblical עריות arayot and four types of rabbinic. Okay,
what are these? אב ובנו אחיו ובן אחיו מדברי תורה. av u'vno
achiv u'ven achiv midivrei Torah. So that she cannot marry the father,
the son, the brother, and the brother's son, right? Because a brother's
son from the perspective of the man is your, right, brother's son
is your father's your father's brother's wife, right? Wait. So I'm
sorry, I got that right. All right. ראובן, Reuven, okay, so if
if רחל Rachel can't marry שמעון'ס Shimon's brother's son, right? שמעון'ס Shimon's
brother's son, right? So what is that from the perspective of the
son? It's father's brother's wife. Okay, so that's aunt. So that's biblical.
So those are the four she's not allowed to marry based on
her relationship to שמעון Shimon that would have been biblical עריות. arayot.
So those are the four. And what are the ones that are
based on rabbinic עריות, arayot, which is basically saying שני לעריות sheni
l'arayot applies here? אבי אביו, avi aviv, grandfather, ואבי אמו, v'avi imo,
grandfather from the mother side, בן בנו, ben bno, grandson, ובן בתו,
u'ven bito, and grandson through a daughter, מדברי סופרים. midivrei Sofrim. So
okay, it's very clear that there are four rabbinic עריות arayot that
are אסור assur to this חלוצה, chalutza, so that's an idea of
שני לעריות. sheni l'arayot. תנא מיהא, tanna miha, we taught nonetheless, אבי
אביו, avi aviv, so grandfather. We're going to go through the same
thing. מאי לאו משום חולץ, mai lav mishum choleitz, it must be
because of her relationship to שמעון, Shimon, והויא ליה כלת בנו, v'havya
leh kallas bno, and this is a שני לעריות, sheni l'arayot, right,
the grandfather's son's daughter-in-law? לא משום מגרש דהויא ליה כלת בנו. lo
mishum migareish d'havya leh kallas bno. So we're saying the same thing.
Yes. So again, you see ah, if יצחק Yitzchak is אסור assur
to רחל, Rachel, it's a שני לעריות sheni l'arayot through שמעון, Shimon,
and it says no, it's a שני לעריות sheni l'arayot through ראובן.
Reuven. Okay, same answer. And the relationship with ראובן Reuven is a
biblical relationship. Okay, so תא שמע, ta shema, אבי אמו, avi imo,
grandfather through the mother's side. מאי לאו משום חולץ mai lav mishum
choleitz דהויא ליה כלת בתו? d'havya leh kallas bito? So if it's
now
אבי אמו, avi imo, so mother's father, לאה Leah and לבן.
Lavan. Okay? So same idea, grandfather. But here though, who is רחל
Rachel to לבן? Lavan?
His daughter's son-in-law. Now, if you remember שני לעריות, sheni l'arayot, when
you switch sexes, it's not as obvious we do it, right? If
your son-in-law is forbidden, then the שני לעריות sheni l'arayot is your
son's son-in-law. Okay, so that's this, right, son's son-in-law. This, if you
look at this, right, is your daughter's son-in-law is not as obvious.
Okay, so let's take a look what the just the way it
works, a normal natural extension is to keep within the same gender
but just extend it a generation. Okay, so let's take a look.
תא שמע, ta shema,
where are we?
אבי אמו, avi imo, okay, mother's father, לבן. Lavan. מאי לאו משום
חולץ? mai lav mishum choleitz? It must be because of the relationship
to שמעון Shimon דהויא ליה כלת בתו, d'havya leh kallas bito, his
daughter's daughter-in-law? לא משום מגרש דהויא ליה כלת בתו. lo mishum migareish
d'havya leh kallas bito.
Now, back to the same idea. It is because of because of
through,
it's the same thing, but it's through ראובן. Reuven. Yes, it's his
daughter's son-in-law, but through ראובן, Reuven, not through שמעון. Shimon. So yes,
it's a שני לעריות, Sheni L'Arayot, but through the ראובן Reuven relationship,
which is the biblical, not the שמעון Shimon relationship, which is the
rabbinic. תא שמע. Ta Shma. So let's now go the other way.
ובן בנו, U'ven Beno, grandson. We're back to here. מאי לאו Mai
Lav משום mishum חולץ Choletz דהויא ליה De-Haviya Lei אשת אבי אביו?
Eishes Avi Aviv? Isn't it because of the relationship to שמעון? Shimon?
So it's grandfather's wife, which is rabbinic. לא Lo משום mishum מפנא
Mifna דהויא ליה De-Haviya Lei אשת אחי אבי אביו. Eishes Achi Avi
Aviv. No, because of the of ראובן'ס Reuven's relationship, because it's grand-uncle's
wife. All right, basically the exact same thing, except doing it on
the ברייתא Braisa of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiyah. The only reason or
one of the reasons רבי חייא'ס Rabbi Chiyah's more interesting is he
said explicitly there are four rabbinic. Okay, but what the גמרא'ס Gemara's
doing is it's making it rabbinic on ראובן'ס Reuven's side, not on
שמעון'ס Shimon's side. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והא אמימר מכשיר
באשת אחי אבי אביו. Ve'ha Amemar machshir b'Eishes Achi Avi Aviv. But
אמימר Amemar allows the case of, you know, of even as a
שני לעריות Sheni L'Arayot of great-uncle's wife, and you can't do the
trick you did before of applying it one generation up. It doesn't
work in the language of רבי חייא'ס Rabbi Chiyah's ברייתא. Braisa. So
the גמרא Gemara says אמימר מוקים לה משום חולץ. Amemar mokim lah
mishum Choletz.
Yes, you're right, you got me into a corner. There's no way
here that it can make any sense unless you do it from
the perspective of שמעון, Shimon, not ראובן. Reuven. וקסבר גזרו שניות בחלוצה.
Ve'kasavar gazru shniyos be'chalutzah. And אמימר Amemar would have to concede, at
least for אמימר Amemar you've proven your point. There's no way to
make it based on the relationship to ראובן. Reuven. It can only
be based on the relationship to שמעון, Shimon, and you see there's
an idea of שני לעריות Sheni L'Arayot that applies to to
the חלוצה Chalutzah relationship. Okay, but we've only proven it for אמימר.
Amemar. תא שמע. Ta Shma. We're going to try again. ובבן בתו,
U've'ven Bito, his daughter's son. מאי לאו Mai Lav משום mishum חולץ
Choletz דהויא ליה De-Haviya Lei אשת אבי אמו? Eishes Avi Imo? So
if this was his daughter's son, okay, so what's now the relationship?
His mother's father's wife. Okay, that would be like a שני לעריות.
Sheni L'Arayot. If you can't do it with your mother or your
father's wife, you can't do it with your mother's father's wife. Okay,
so מאי לאו Mai Lav משום mishum חולץ Choletz דהויא ליה De-Haviya
Lei אשת Eishes the wife of אבי אמו, Avi Imo, his mother's
father? לא Lo משום mishum מפנא Mifna דהויא ליה De-Haviya Lei אשת
אחי אבי אמו. Eishes Achi Avi Imo. Now,
this is going to be trickier. What's the relationship if we wanted
to do it through רחל? Rachel? So it is your mother's
father's brother's wife. That's not a שני לעריות, Sheni L'Arayot, okay? That's
too many degrees. Even if you're not אמימר, Amemar, if it's father's
father's brother's wife, that's like okay, a natural extension. The father's brother's
wife, so father's father's brother's wife. But this is mother's father's brother's
wife, nobody is going to say that's שני לעריות. Sheni L'Arayot. Okay,
so ה- ha- the גמרא Gemara wait one minute. דהויא ליה De-Haviya
Lei אשת Eishes the wife of אחי אבי אמו, Achi Avi Imo,
mother's father's brother's wife. So the גמרא Gemara says אהכי שניות דערבה
לא גזרו. Ah bei Sheniyos de'ervah lo gazru.
That's never a שני לערוה, Sheni L'Arayot, that relationship. So if you
need to do it through ראובן, Reuven, it doesn't work. אלא לאו
Ela lav משום mishum חולץ? Choletz? It only works if you do
it through שמעון. Shimon. שמע מינה גזרו שניות בחלוצה שמע מינה. Shema
mina gazru shniyos be'chalutzah shema mina. So you've proven your point that
it is there's a problem of שני לעריות Sheni L'Arayot even for
a חלוצה. Chalutzah. So not only did they make the עריות Arayot
forbidden, they even made the שניות Shniyot forbidden. Okay. מותר אדם. Mutar
adam. Now the last line of the משנה Mishnah was, a man
is permissible, let's read it, מותר אדם, Mutar adam, what does it
say? מותר אדם בקרובות צרת חלוצתו. Mutar adam be'krovos tzaras chalutzaso.
Who's קרובות צרת חלוצתו? krovos tzaras chalutzaso?
So here, okay, you've got ראובן Reuven again and שמעון, Shimon, okay,
and ראובן Reuven dies and he does חליצה Chalitzah to רחל. Rachel.
So the קרובה krovah of רחל Rachel is לאה, Leah, sister. He's
forbidden in לאה, Leah, that's what the משנה Mishnah first taught, right?
He's אסור assur in the עריות. Arayot. Now, קרובות, krovos, I'm sorry,
I'm sorry, קרובות צרת חלוצתו, krovos tzaras chalutzaso, excuse me. ראובן Reuven
was married to רחל Rachel and דבורה, Devorah, okay? Okay, and דבורה
Devorah has and דבורה Devorah has a sister. Okay, so can שמעון,
Shimon, now שמעון Shimon does חליצה Chalitzah to רחל. Rachel. Can he
go ahead and marry דבורה? Devorah? No, because דבורה Devorah was is
his brother's ex-wife, or his brother's whatever, his brother's widow's wife, right?
Can he go marry דבורה'ס Devorah's sister? Yes. Okay, he can't marry
רחל'ס Rachel's sister because since he did חליצה Chalitzah to רחל, Rachel,
she's like his ex-wife, and that's the whole issue, her קרובים, krovim,
her relatives are forbidden to him. But since he never did חליצה
Chalitzah to דבורה, Devorah, although he freed himself from his relationship to
דבורה Devorah by doing the act to רחל, Rachel, so he does
דבורה Devorah is not treated as his ex-wife. So therefore he is
allowed to go ahead and marry דבורה'ס Devorah's sister. Okay, so מותר
אדם בקרובות צרת חלוצתו. mutar adam be'krovos tzaras chalutzaso. He can marry
the sister of the צרה tzarah of the woman he did חליצה
chalitzah to. But it says, but it says,
you know what, we'll get to the second line in a minute.
Let's just focus on the first line.
אמר רב טובי בר קיסנא amar Rav Tuvi bar Kisna אמר שמואל
amar Shmuel הבא על צרת חלוצה, haba al tzarat chalutza, let’s say
Shimon went ahead, had sex with דבורה. Dvora. Okay, so what is
the status of דבורה Dvora to him? Is the fact that she,
is she basically like אשת אחיו? eshet achiv? Right? There is no
longer a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum and the child therefore after
doing חליצה chalitza or no, since he did חליצה chalitza that somehow
transforms her status. Okay. So let’s take a look. הבא על צרת
חלוצה haba al tzarat chalutza הולד ממזר. havlad mamzer. Okay. The child’s
a ממזר. mamzer. מאי טעמא mai ta’ama באיסורה קיימא. be’issura kaima. She
retains her original forbidden status. She was brother’s wife. She would only
have been allowed in the context of יבום. yibum. No act of
יבום yibum was done, so she remains forbidden as brother’s wife. אמר
רב יוסף amar Rav Yosef אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami
tanina. We taught that מותר אדם בקרובת צרת חלוצתו. mutar adam b’krovat
tzarat chalutzato. A person is permitted to marry the relative of the
דבורה Dvora here, of the co-wife. Okay, אי אמרת בשלמא צרה אבראי,
ee amrat bishlama tzara abarai, if you say the co-wife is considered
completely unrelated to the act of חליצה, chalitza, so משום הכי מותר
באחותה. mishum hachi mutar b’achota. That’s why you can marry her sister.
It’s because she’s not like part of the process of חליצה chalitza
at all. Because what you have to understand is, if Shimon after
doing חליצה chalitza to רחל Rachel goes ahead and has sex with
רחל, Rachel, everybody agrees that’s אסור. assur. Okay, based on a פסוק
pasuk that once לא יבנה שוב לא יבנה. lo yivneh shuv lo
yivneh. But her status has transformed enough because she underwent חליצה chalitza
that it would no longer be the ערוות אשת אח, arvayas eshet
ach, right, so there’s no longer a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum
after doing חליצה, chalitza, it would still be forbidden, but not the
ערוות אשת אח, arvayas eshet ach, brother’s wife. And you might remember
before the question that he asked is, when he does חליצה chalitza
to רחל, Rachel, is it like he’s also doing חליצה chalitza to
דבורה? Dvora? Okay. So what he’s saying with this, it’s not עריות
arayot if he goes ahead and has sex. With this it is,
means that the act of חליצה chalitza focuses on רחל Rachel and
completely is not related to דבורה. Dvora. So that his relationship to
רחל, Rachel, this is no longer ערוות, arvayas, but that remains ערוות.
arvayas. So he says, well that’s consistent with the idea that he’s
allowed to marry דבורה Dvora’s relatives. It shows you that the status
of חלוצה chalutza applies only to רחל. Rachel. Okay. So since there’s
no חלוצה chalutza status to דבורה, Dvora, she’s the חלוצה, chalutza, she’s
not the חלוצה. chalutza. That’s why he can marry דבורה Dvora’s sister.
But once that’s true, her status changes and she’s no longer an
ערוות, arvayas, but her status doesn’t change and she’s still an ערוות.
arvayas. Okay. So he says like this. אי אמרת בשלמא צרה אבראי,
ee amrat bishlama tzara abarai, right,
if you say that the צרה tzara דבורה Dvora is on the
outside, not related to the act of חליצה, chalitza, משום הכי מותר
באחותה, mishum hachi mutar b’achota, that’s why he can marry the sister.
And therefore, but her status will not be as a חלוצה chalutza
and she’ll still be brother’s wife. אלא אי אמרת צרה כחלוצה דמיא,
ella ee amrat tzara k’chalutza damya, if she’s like a חלוצה, chalutza,
so her status changed, so she’s no longer אשת אחיו, eshet achiv,
okay, forbidden, but not ערוות אשת אח, arvayas eshet ach, brother’s wife.
אמאי מותר? amai mutar? Why can he go ahead and marry דבורה
Dvora’s sister? So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרבי יוחנן?
leima tehavi tyuvta d’Rabbi Yochanan? So this seems to be a contradiction.
So that’s a good proof. But this seems to be a contradiction
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, because רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says דאמר
בין הוא בין אחין אין חייבין לא על החלוצה כרת ולא על
צרתה כרת. d’amar bein hu bein achin ein chayavin lo al hachalutza
karet v’lo al tzarata karet.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says not only after the act of חליצה
chalitza are you not חייב chayav if you have sex with רחל,
Rachel, okay, because she’s no longer, her status has changed, you’re not
even חייב כרת chayav karet if you have sex with דבורה. Dvora.
So both of their status changes. So now we’ve got a great
question. If דבורה Dvora’s status changes through the act of חליצה chalitza
to רחל Rachel enough that she’s no longer considered brother’s wife and
the act of sex is no longer considered ערווה, arvah, why doesn’t
she have a status of חלוצה chalutza to make her relatives forbidden?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר לך רבי יוחנן, amar lach Rabbi
Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan would say back to you, וכי תיסברא?
v’chi tisbara? Does this make sense? אחות חלוצה דאורייתא? achot chalutza d’oraita?
Is the anyway, is the whole status of a relative of a
חלוצה chalutza דאורייתא? d’oraita? והאמר ריש לקיש, v’ha’amar Reish Lakish, כאן שנה
רבי, kan shana Rabbi,
אחות גרושה מדברי תורה, achot gerusha midivrei Torah, the sister of a
divorced wife is biblical obviously, אחות חלוצה מדברי סופרים, achot chalutza midivrei
soferim, the relative of a חלוצה chalutza is rabbinic. So we already
knew the whole status of forbidding relatives is a rabbinic idea. So
basically what his answer is, is like look, biblically speaking, she’s enough
of a חלוצה chalutza and her status has enough changed, has enough
transformed, right, that now if שמעון Shimon has sex with her, it’s
not an איסור כרת. issur karet. On the תורה Torah level, even
though he only did the act to רחל, Rachel, it transformed both
of their statuses and they’re no longer looked of as brother’s wife
and it would not be an איסור כרת. issur karet. But at
the rabbinic level, we’re going to forbid the relatives of a חלוצה.
chalutza. That’s a rabbinic idea. So for that idea, we’ll do it
with the woman he did the act with and not with the
woman he didn’t do the act with. So basically it’s saying there’s
a difference between the דאורייתא d’oraita and the דרבנן. d’rabbanan. Everybody agrees
the act is done with רחל, Rachel, the change of status occurs
to both, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says דבורה Dvora’s status also changes
regarding ערווה, arvah, but in terms
of... Or the
other
way
around. Yeah,
but not... but there's no הלכה halacha that קרובים krovim of ערווה
ervah are אסור, assur, so I don't know, anyway. All right, let's...
all right, I hear the point. I want to move on. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara has the following question. מאי שנא האי
ומאי שנא האי? Mai shna hai u-mai shna hai? Now it's going
to the last line of the ברייתא. Beraita. The last line of
the ברייתא Beraita said Shimon is מותר mutar with
צרת קרובת חלוצתו. tzaras krovat chalutzato. So this is מותר. mutar. Okay,
you know who he's אסור assur with? The last line of the
משנה Mishna says ואסור, v'assur, I'm sorry, he's
מותר mutar בקרובת צרת חלוצתו, bikrovat tzaras chalutzato, ואסור, v'assur, he's אסור
assur with צרה tzara the co-wife of קרובת חלוצתו. krovat chalutzato. So
who's קרובת חלוצתו? krovat chalutzato? Okay, לאה Leah here is his חלוצת
קרובה. chalutzas krova. Okay, so he's right, so he's אסור assur with
לאה. Leah. Not only is he אסור assur with לאה, Leah, לאה
Leah is married to ברק Barak who also has a wife דבורה.
Devorah. Okay, so here's ברק Barak and he also has דבורה. Devorah.
Okay, so he's אסור assur with רחל, Rachel, אסור assur with לאה,
Leah, I need my red marker to show אסור. assur. Anyway, okay,
so anyway, whatever it is, I'll use orange for now. He's אסור
assur with רחל, Rachel, אסור assur with דבורה Devorah because that's the
קרובה krova of the חלוצה. chalutza. But how about ברק Barak was
married to לאה Leah and דבורה? Devorah? ברק Barak died. What's about
דבורה? Devorah? So that should be totally okay, right? This is even
if this is my wife's sister, since when can I not marry
my wife's sister's co-wife? It makes no sense. Okay, so the first
thing you have to know, so that's the way רש"י Rashi reads
it. But I'm going to tell you that תוספות Tosfos explains it.
תוספות Tosfos says yeah there's absolutely no logic to that. Even the
גמרא's Gemara answer doesn't work. And תוספות Tosfos says we're not dealing
with ברק. Barak. You know who we're dealing with? לוי. Levi.
שמעון's Shimon brother. Okay, so that's what תוספות Tosfos says. All right,
just to confuse you all a little bit more. So then, if
this becomes שמעון's Shimon quasi ערווה, ervah,
basically two brothers married to two sisters.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So right, you can figure out all the math.
But if this is now שמעון's Shimon ex-wife's sister as it were,
ex-wife, ex
חלוצה chalutza sister, she's a rabbinic ערווה ervah to him, right? So
therefore דבורה Devorah is a צרה tzara to a rabbinic ערווה. ervah.
Okay? Right? צרת ערווה tzaras ervah is אסור, assur, so this is
also a quasi צרת ערווה. tzaras ervah. That's the way תוספות Tosfos
reads it. Okay? So that's why this is okay and this is
not okay. All right, it's very simple. Once she's חלוצה, chalutza, like
an ex-wife, she's אחות חלוצה achos chalutza which is like an ערווה,
ervah, a quasi ערווה. ervah.
And therefore if לוי Levi now dies, he can't do ייבום yibbum
with לאה Leah because she's a quasi ערווה ervah and he can't
do ייבום yibbum with דבורה Devorah because she's a צרת ערווה. tzaras
ervah. Yeah, the פטור petur of צרת ערווה. tzaras ervah. Yes.
Why are you so hesitant? It makes a lot of sense.
לוי Levi and שמעון Shimon are brothers?
Yes.
So the two brothers married two sisters. That's what we've been talking
about the whole time. Okay, so if that's the explanation, if that's
the read of the משנה, Mishna, then the explanation is obvious. That's
just a logical derivation of the idea that you call this an
ערווה, ervah, so you're going to call her a צרת ערווה. tzaras
ervah.
And they're talking about ייבום yibbum not ordinary marriage.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, a case of ייבום. yibbum. Right, so I know,
so with רש"י's Rashi read, you don't understand the answer. With תוספות'
Tosfos read, you don't understand the question. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says:
מאי שנא האי ומאי שנא האי? Mai shna ha u-mai shna ha?
What difference does one make or the other?
הך דאזלא בהדאי Hach d'azla behadei or בהדא. behada. תוספות' Tosfos גרסא
girsa reads it בהדא. behada. הך דאזלא בהדא לבי דינא גזרו בה
רבנן. Hach d'azla behada l'vei dina gezru bah rabbanan. רחל, Rachel, who
he schlepped to court, this is the way תוספות Tosfos reads it,
and did חליצה chalitza to רחל. Rachel. So she's the one that
has all the status. She's the one that לאה Leah becomes forbidden
to and that דבורה Devorah becomes a צרת ערווה tzaras ervah etc.
והך דלא אזלא בהדא לבי דינא V'hach d'lo azla behada l'vei dina
and דבורה, Devorah, who never came with her to court, although she's
a co-wife and even though the status change occurred to דבורה, Devorah,
she has no status, so לא גזרו בה רבנן, lo gazru bah
rabbanan, she's off for free. Okay, which should also explain the idea
of what we said before that דבורה's Devorah status changes so it's
no longer an ערווה, ervah, but her relatives are still permissible. Why?
Because at the end of the day, the act was done to
רחל. Rachel. So since the act was done to רחל, Rachel, her
status changes which affects לאה Leah and דבורה, Devorah, but this דבורה,
Devorah, whatever, a different דבורה, Devorah, is off for free. Okay, that
was that. Moving on now. Next משנה. Mishna. Still remaining only an
עמוד amud behind. Okay, top of מ"א עמוד א'. mem-aleph amud-aleph. החולץ
ליבמתו, Hacholeitz liyvimto, a guy did חליצה. chalitza. ונשא אחיו את אחותה.
V'nasa achiv es achosa. And his brother married the sister. Okay, so
we're back to he did חליצה chalitza with רחל Rachel and then
comes along לוי, Levi, just sort of like we were just talking
about. showing, according to the way תוספות Tosafot read it, this is
exactly the way תוספות Tosafot read that last line of the משנה,
Mishnah, this is the scenario. Comes along לוי Levi and marries לאה,
Leah, okay, and לאה Leah to him is obviously אסור assur because
that's, you know, that's his חלוצה'ס chalutza's sister. Okay, so שמעון Shimon
comes ahead and marries לאה, Leah, which she would be אסור assur
to. לוי Levi comes and marries לאה. Leah. Right, thank you. Okay,
so, and again, remember also the interesting part that even though לוי
Levi had an obligation to רחל Rachel as well and לוי Levi
could have done חליצה chalitza to רחל, Rachel, the status of חלוצה
chalutza only applies between the people who did the act, not between
דבורה Devorah over here who was affected by the act but didn't
do it, and not between לוי Levi who was also needed to
do something or is part of the group of brothers. Nevertheless, the
status only relates to the two people who are involved in the
act, okay? So שמעון Shimon can't marry לאה Leah but לוי Levi
can, okay? ונשא אחיו את אחותה ומת. V'nasa achiv et achoto umet.
Okay, and then of course לוי Levi dies. Always a bad business
to be getting married here in these משניות. Mishnayot. Okay, ומת. umet.
So חולצת ולא מתייבמת. Choletzet v'lo mityabemet. So now what does שמעון
Shimon have to do with לאה? Leah? So biblically he's חייב chayav
in ייבום, yibbum, right? Brother's wife. But rabbinically, it's an ערווה, erva,
a rabbinic ערווה. erva. So what do you do in a case
of a rabbinic ערווה? erva? You got to deal with it but
you can't do ייבום, yibbum, so you do חליצה chalitza and not
ייבום. yibbum. וכן המגרש את אשתו ונשא אחיו את אחותה. V'chen hamgaresh
et ishto v'nasa achiv et achoto.
Or let's say it was a case of not just חליצה, chalitza,
but let's say it was a real case of a גרושה. grusha.
So in the same, so the same thing is true. Now of
course, first of all it's not true. If this if רחל Rachel
was really a גרושה, grusha, then לאה Leah would really be an
ערווה erva and you wouldn't even have to do חליצה. chalitza. Is
that clear? Right, if רחל'ס Rachel's really the ex-wife, not just a,
not just a חלוצה, chalutza, so then this is wife's sister, so
then she's totally פטורה. pturah. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to say
it doesn't really mean וכן. v'chen. It really means ואפילו, v'afilu, and
even more, even more so in the case of a real גרושה,
grusha, then you don't even have to do חליצה. chalitza. Okay. הרי
זו פטורה, Harei zu pturah, she's completely exempt. You don't even need
חליצה. chalitza. שומרת יבם שקידש אחיו את אחותה. Shomeret yavam shekidesh achiv
et achoto. So now you've got a woman waiting for ייבום yibbum
and his brother married her sister. So basically it's the same story
except except
nobody
has, so you've got, right, רחל Rachel here, right, ראובן Reuven has
died.
Okay, you've got רחל Rachel as a שומרת יבם, shomeret yavam, okay?
So she's waiting for ייבום yibbum from one of these brothers. And
comes along לוי, Levi, so for some reason let's say שמעון'ס Shimon's
the older brother and he's the one expected to do it. While
they're waiting to do whatever they're going to do here, whether חליצה
chalitza or ייבום, yibbum, comes along לוי Levi and he marries לאה.
Leah. All right? ונשא אחיו את אחותה. V'nasa achiv et achoto. Okay,
so what do you do? So משום רבי יהודה בן בתירה אמרו
אומרים לו המתן עד שיעשה אחיך מעשה. Mishum Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira
amru omrim lo hamten ad sheya'aseh achicha ma'aseh. Now what will happen
if לוי Levi not only does קידושין kidushin but consummates with לאה?
Leah? He'll be having sex with אחות זקוקתו. achot zikukato. So,
right, remember the old זקוקה, zikuka, אחות זקוקתו. achot zikukato. So he
cannot do that because he has a זיקה zika to רחל, Rachel,
the sister. So you say to לוי, Levi, wait for שמעון Shimon
to do something. שמעון Shimon will do either ייבום yibbum or חליצה.
chalitza. That'll change, then רחל Rachel will have no relationship to you
after שמעון Shimon does something, and then you can go ahead and
consummate with לאה, Leah, okay? אומרים לו המתן, Omrim lo hamten, wait,
עד שיעשה אחיך מעשה, ad sheya'aseh achicha ma'aseh, let your brother do
something. חלץ לאחיו או כנסה. Chalatz l'achiv o kinsah. Now once ראובן
Reuven goes ahead and does חליצה chalitza or ייבום, yibbum, then יכנוס
את אשתו, yichnos et ishto, then he can go ahead and consummate
with לאה. Leah. מתה היבמה יכנוס
את אשתו.
Metah hayevama
yichnos et ishto. Now let's say רחל Rachel dies. That's also a
scenario. רחל'ס Rachel's out of the picture. Even if he was married
to רחל, Rachel, once she dies he can now marry לאה, Leah,
okay? So if שמעון Shimon does something with רחל Rachel and removes
her from the picture, or if רחל Rachel dies, he can now
consummate with לאה, Leah, okay? However, מת היבם. Met hayavam. What happens
if, here's the worst scenario from לוי'ס Levi's perspective, שמעון Shimon dies.
שמעון Shimon dies, he's stuck. Now she's his זקוקתו zikukato and what
what can he do? Oh, do חליצה. chalitza. שקויח, Shkoyach, he do
חליצה, chalitza, now she's חלוצתו chalutzato and that's אחות חלוצתו. achot chalutzato.
Do ייבום. yibbum. No, because then he's having sex with his wife's
sister. So he's completely stuck. He has no options here, right? So
what do you do? So in that case יוציא את אשתו בגט
ואשת אחיו בחליצה. yotzi et ishto b'get v'eshet achiv b'chalitza. He's got
to divorce, he's got to separate the relationship with both of them
and he even after he divorces לאה, Leah, he can't do ייבום
yibbum here because then it's his ex-wife's sister.
So he can only, so he's got to sort of just divorce
both of them. He has to divorce his wife, which is pretty
tragic. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי וכן?
Mai v'chen? Why when it switched from the case of a חלוצה
chalutza to the case of a גרושה grusha it said וכן? v'chen?
A גרושה grusha is דאורייתא de'oraita and you don't even have to
do חליצה chalitza in that case. She's totally exempt. ערווה. ervah. So
אימא אבל, eima aval, so don't read it וכן, v'chen, read it
אבל. aval. אבל! Aval! אבל המגרש. Aval ha-megaresh. Okay. אמר ריש לקיש,
Amar Reish Lakish, כאן שנה רבי, kan shana Rabbi, אחת גרושה מדברי
תורה, achas gerusha midivrei Torah, אחת חלוצה מדברי סופרים. achas chalutza midivrei
soferim. Here it's clear, the sister of a חלוצה chalutza you still
need to do חליצה chalitza to because it's not a דאורייתא d'oraissa
ערווה. ervah. The sister of a גרושה gerusha is a דאורייתא d'oraissa
ערווה, ervah, so you don't even have to do חליצה chalitza to.
All right, so that's how we explain the משנה. Mishnah. שומרת יבם
שקידש. Shomeres yavam she-kidesh. Now getting to this whole case here, לוי
Levi going ahead and marrying לאה. Leah. So, אמר שמואל, amar Shmuel,
הלכה כדברי רבי יהודה בן בתירה, halacha k'divrei Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira,
we rule like רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira that
he has to wait and something has to happen with רחל Rachel
and if ראובן Reuven goes ahead and if שמעון Shimon goes ahead
and dies, then everybody has a real big problem. So, איבעיא להו,
ibayahu, now they ask the question, מתה אשתו מהו? mesa ishto mahu?
מהו ביבמתו? Mahu b'yevimto? Let's say the case of
מתה אשתו. mesa ishto. Yes, that's exactly it. I don't know why
I erased it. Okay, so we've dealt with everybody dying except what
happens if לאה Leah dies? Okay, now if לאה Leah dies, here's
the story. When did he marry לאה? Leah? If you read the
משנה Mishnah closely, it said that he married לאה Leah after רחל
Rachel was already a שומרת יבם. shomeres yavam. So
שומרת יבם, shomeres yavam, so that was stage number one. Was she
מותר mutar to לוי? Levi? Yes, she was מותר. mutar. Then stage
number two is he married לאה. Leah. All right, then at that
stage when he married לאה, Leah, right, רחל Rachel became forbidden. Okay,
so that makes her forbidden at stage number two. Okay, then stage
number three, right, is לאה Leah dies. So if לאה Leah dies,
now the relationship goes off and she becomes permitted again. Permitted, forbidden,
permitted. Okay, I don't know if I illustrated that well, but I
think you get the idea. As long as רחל Rachel was available
first, marrying לאה Leah made her first permitted, then forbidden, then לאה
Leah dies, she'll become permitted again. Okay, so let's take a look.
מתה אשתו מותר ביבמתו, Mesa ishto mutar b'yevimto,
if לאה Leah dies, now he can go ahead and consummate and
do יבום yibum with רחל. Rachel. Okay,
איבעיא להו, ibayahu, מתה אשתו מה ביבמתו, mesa ishto mah b'yevimto, I'm
sorry, what's the הלכה? halacha? רב ורבי חנינא דאמרי תרווייהו, Rav v'Rabbi
Chanina d'amri tarvaihu, Rav and Rabbi Chanina both say מתה אשתו מותר
ביבמתו, mesa ishto mutar b'yevimto, now she reverts back to being מותר.
mutar. שמואל ורב אסי דאמרי תרווייהו, Shmuel v'Rav Assi d'amri tarvaihu, they
say no, מתה אשתו אסור ביבמתו. mesa ishto assur b'yevimto. Once אסור,
assur, always אסור, assur, even though she started being permitted and it
came happened only later, once אסור assur always אסור. assur. אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, מאי טעמא דרב, mai ta'ama d'Rav, what's the reason of
רב Rav that says that she goes back to becoming permissible? משום
דהוה יבמה שהותרה, Mishum d'hava yevama she-hutra, it was a sister-in-law that
first was permissible, רחל Rachel was permissible, ונאסרה, v'ne'esra, she became forbidden
when לוי Levi went ahead and married לאה, Leah, וחזרה והותרה, v'chozra
v'hutra, and then she went back to being permitted. תחזור להיתירה הראשון,
Tachzor l'heiteira harishon, she goes back to the first status because her
basic identity is defined when the guy died, when ראובן Reuven died.
When ראובן Reuven died, she was not an ערווה ervah vis-a-vis שמעון
Shimon and vis-a-vis לוי. Levi. So as long as that so she
can go back to that original status. So מתיב רב המנונא, masiv
Rav Hamnuna, רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna asks, this will remind you of
stuff we've done before. ג' אחים, Gimmel achim, three brothers, נשואים שתי
אחיות, nesu'im shtei achayot, married to two sisters, ואחד מופנה, v'echad mufne,
and one is single. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות, Mes echad miba'alei ha-achayot,
one of the ones married to a sister dies, ועשה בה מופנה
מאמר, v'asah bah mufne ma'amar, okay, so this we're going to have
to illustrate. Okay, another case. ראובן שמעון
ולוי, Reuven, Shimon, v'Levi, why do I start with שמעון? Shimon? ראובן
שמעון ולוי. Reuven, Shimon, v'Levi. These two guys are married to sisters,
רחל ולאה, Rachel v'Leah, okay, and לוי Levi is single. Okay, so
what happens?
מת אחד מבעלי האחיות, Mes echad miba'alei ha-achayot, so ראובן Reuven dies,
always ראובן Reuven who dies. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות ועשה בה מופנה
מאמר, Mes echad miba'alei ha-achayot v'asah bah mufne ma'amar, he did a
מאמר, ma'amar, so he's quasi-married to
רחל. Rachel. Okay, ואחר כך מת אחיו השני, v'achar kach mes achiv
hasheini, and then שמעון Shimon dies. So now he's in a similar
status, right? He's got a זיקה zika to לאה, Leah, it's pretty
similar, he's got a זיקה zika to לאה Leah and he's pretty
much married to רחל. Rachel. He can't consummate either way, it's the
wife's sister, one of the wife's sister as it were. Okay, so
what does it say? So it says ואחר כך מת אחיו השני
ואחר כך מתה אשתו אחריו, v'achar kach mes achiv hasheini v'achar kach
mesa ishto acharav, but then his wife dies. Not לאה, Leah, I'm
sorry, who dies? מתה אשתו אחריו. Mesa ishto acharav.
Right, I think אשתו ishto just means רחל. Rachel. Right, then רחל
Rachel dies. Okay, so now רחל Rachel dies, oh, now maybe he
can consummate with לאה. Leah. Okay, right is that clear? Now לאה
Leah became permitted, right? The problem was רחל. Rachel. But here's the
issue. Was לאה Leah ever permitted? At this stage, first what was
the order? First he did מאמר ma'amar with רחל, Rachel, right? It
says עשה מאמר asah ma'amar and then שמעון Shimon died. So when
שמעון Shimon died, he was already quasi-married to רחל, Rachel, yes? So
לאה Leah was never permitted. As soon as לאה Leah became a
widow, she was already the wife's
sister. So this case even after רחל Rachel dies, לאה Leah remains
forbidden because she started forbidden, okay? So it says ואחר כך מתה
אחותה של זו, אותה יבמה חולצת ולא מתייבמת, ve-achar kach metah achotah
shel zo, otah yevamah choletzet ve-lo mityabemet, you can't be, you can
only do חליצה. chalitzah.
ואמאי? ve-amai? תהוי כיבמה שהותרה. tehavi ke-yevamah she-hutrah. When was she הותרה?
hutrah? Oh, did he marry רחל Rachel after?
Did he marry רחל Rachel after שמעון Shimon dies? One minute, let
me get this straight. מת אחד מבעלי האחיות ועשה במופנת מאמר. met
echad mi-ba'alei ha-achayot ve-asah ba-mufnet ma'amar.
Why was she הותרה? hutrah? One minute.
Oh,
because I
got it wrong. I'm sorry. I apologize. It wasn't רחל Rachel who
died. אשתו ishto meant לאה Leah died, the אשתו ishto of שמעון.
Shimon. My mistake. Okay? So first he goes ahead and רחל, Rachel,
he has a זיקה zika to רחל Rachel and he does a
מאמר. ma'amar. Then שמעון Shimon dies. Then לאה Leah becomes available. Now
he's אסור asur to both of them, okay? He started being מותר
mutar to רחל. Rachel. Now לאה Leah became available, רחל Rachel became
forbidden. Okay? Then לאה Leah dies, okay? And that then says he
can't do ייבום, yibbum, he can only do חליצה. chalitzah. Now that
seems an exact parallel. He started to be okay with רחל, Rachel,
became forbidden because of לאה, Leah, and then לאה Leah dies, gets
out of the picture, and now he remains forbidden to רחל, Rachel,
he can only do חליצה. chalitzah. So that's a proof that you
don't say you go back to being originally permitted? So the גמרא
Gemara says
ואמאי? ve-amai? תהוי כיבמתו שהותרה ונאסרה. tehavi ke-yevamto she-hutrah ve-neasrah.
רחל Rachel first was permitted, became forbidden because of לאה, Leah, וחזרה
והותרה, ve-chazrah ve-hutrah, and then לאה Leah dies, she goes back to
being permissible. תחזור להיתרה הראשון. tachzor le-heterah ha-rishon. So this is a
proof that you don't say that, she doesn't go back to being
permitted. אישתיק, ishtik, he was silenced. He didn't have any answer. סבירא
ליה הכי svira leh hachi it is, it's the same case and
it's אסור. asur. לבתר דנפק, le-vatar de-nafak, after he left, אמר, amar,
oh, you know, it's always like after you have the exchange, then
you realize what you should have said, right? Oh, I had that
zinger, I should have
said it. לבתר דנפק אמר, le-vatar de-nafak amar, he said,
אמאי לא אמרת ליה רבי אלעזר היא, amai lo amart leh Rabi
Elazar hi, why didn't I say to him רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar
he, דאמר כיוון שעמדה עליו שעה אחת באיסור נאסרה עליו לעולם. de-amar
keivan she-amdah alav sha'ah achat be-issur ne-esrah alav le-olam. Yes, I'm talking
about the general approach. The general approach is you can go back
to your original state of being permitted. But there's a position of
רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar that's more strict. So you've got a משנה
mishna against me? That משנה mishna is רבי אלעזר. Rabi Elazar. רבי
אלעזר Rabi Elazar says that once a woman is forbidden once, she
remains forbidden. I'm not going like רבי אלעזר, Rabi Elazar, okay? But
there is a רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar position that says it. הדר
אמר, hadar amar, then he said wait, wait, I couldn't have said
it was רבי אלעזר. Rabi Elazar. Why not? אימת דאמר רבי אלעזר,
eimat de-amar Rabi Elazar, when does רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar say once
forbidden always forbidden? היכא דלא חזיא בשעת נפילה, heicha de-lo chazya bi-she'at
nefilah, when she was never permitted when she died. What's the case?
The case of
רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar is that—I went downstairs—the case of רבי אלעזר
Rabi Elazar is that ראובן Reuven goes ahead
and marries, no, I've got to read רש"י Rashi to remind myself.
Yes, okay, so ראובן Reuven is married to רחל, Rachel, okay? And
then he divorces, he divorces רחל. Rachel. So what, now can שמעון
Shimon marry רחל Rachel right now? No, it's your brother's ex-wife, even
though they're divorced, okay? So she's an ערווה ervah to שמעון. Shimon.
Then ראובן Reuven remarries רחל. Rachel. Okay? And then ראובן Reuven dies.
So does רחל Rachel remain to שמעון Shimon brother's wife? Because at
a stage when she was available, when she was divorced, she was
an עריות arayot to him, right? So without any context of ייבום.
yibbum. She had been a divorced ex-brother's wife without any context of
ייבום. yibbum. Then she gets remarried to the brother, and then ראובן
Reuven dies, to the original husband, and then ראובן Reuven dies. So
does she remain that עריות arayot status? And רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar
says yes, once she was an עריות, arayot, always an עריות. arayot.
So that, I should have said it was רבי אלעזר, Rabi Elazar,
he says once אסור, asur, always אסור. asur. Then he says no,
maybe I couldn't have said it was רבי אלעזר. Rabi Elazar. He
says, אימת דאמר רבי אלעזר, eimat de-amar Rabi Elazar,
when does רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar say once forbidden always forbidden? היכא
דלא חזיא בשעת נפילה, heicha de-lo chazya bi-she'at nefilah, that when she
became a יבמה yevama she was never permitted. She was forbidden when
she was a divorced wife, but when she was a widow she
had never had a state of being permitted. אבל היכא דחזיא בשעת
נפילה, aval heicha de-chazya bi-she'at nefilah, these scenarios we're talking about, where
when actually רחל Rachel became a יבמה yevama she was permitted, and
then she only became forbidden because of לאה, Leah, מי אמר? mi
amar? I don't know that he would say that she would remain
forbidden. Maybe she could go back to being permitted. So we have
a good logic to say that even רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar who's
strict over there should say once permitted, you can go back to
that state, okay? If even if she became forbidden, go back to
that state. But the problem is this ברייתא braita here
sounds
like— That sounds like a proof against him. So הדר אמר, hadar
amar, then he said, no, אין, in, yes, actually רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer would say it even in this case, that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says once forbidden, always forbidden, even for a woman who was
initially permitted when she was a יבמה. yevama. ותניא v'tanya and we
teach this in a ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר אומר עד מתה יבמתו
מותר באשתו, Rabbi Eliezer omer ad mesa yevamto mutar b'ishto, מתה... okay,
if his sister-in-law dies then in this case of our משנה, mishna
right, this case of our משנה mishna. here, okay, he married Leah
and he's got this זיקה zika with Rachel. So מתה יבמתו, mesa
yevamto, if Rachel dies he can go ahead and finish and consummate
with Leah. Okay,
מתה יבמתו מותר באשתו. mesa yevamto mutar b'ishto. מתה אשתו, mesa ishto,
if Leah dies, okay, אותה יבמה, osa yevama, then Rachel, חולצת ולא
מתייבמת, choletzet v'lo misyabemet, she remains forbidden. But that's exactly our discussion,
right? What happens if Leah dies? Rachel was originally permitted, he married
Leah, he became forbidden, what happens if Leah dies? Does she go
back to being permitted? And we have a ברייתא braita that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no, she does not go back to being
permitted. Once forbidden, always forbidden. Okay, so this is the debate. You've
got רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel on one side. Who was on
the other side?
רב Rav and רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina on one side, שמואל Shmuel
and רב אסי Rav Assi on the other. Do you say that
if she started by being permitted when she became a יבמה yevama
that and then she became forbidden, can she go back or not?
Okay. Do you say once forbidden, always forbidden, or do you say
if initially she was permitted, then even if she was forbidden she
can go back? So now the גמרא Gemara says, we're almost done
to with this discussion,
לימא שמואל ורב אסי דאמרי כרבי אליעזר, leima Shmuel v'Rav Assi d'amri
k'Rabbi Eliezer,
so שמואל Shmuel and רב אסי Rav Assi that say she remains
forbidden, yeah, I'm sorry, she remains forbidden, that sounds like רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, same idea, she remains forbidden. So the גמרא Gemara says,
and maybe it's the same רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer about the case
of the divorced twice? No, there, by the divorced wife they could
hold like the רבנן. rabbanan. אפילו תימא כרבנן, afillu teima k'rabbanan, by
the case of the divorced wife they could say she becomes permitted.
עד כאן לא קמיפלגי רבנן עליה דרבי אליעזר אלא משום דמן נפילה
ואילך לא מצר להו. ad kan lo kamifligi rabbanan alei d'Rabbi Eliezer
ella mishum d'min nifila v'ailech lo mitzra lei. There, her problematic status
was before she became a יבמה. yevama. And by the time, remember
he divorced her and then he remarried her. So when she became
actually a יבמה, yevama, she was never forbidden. Her status had now
become just a normal brother's wife. Okay, that case they could say
totally okay. What happened before the brother died is completely irrelevant to
us. אבל הכא, aval hacha, here, after people are in a יבמה
yevama status, once you're in the יבמה yevama status and a problem
crops up, then you get excluded from the possibility of
ייבום. yibum. דאיסור אפילו רבנן מודו, de-issur afillu rabbanan modei, even the
רבנן rabbanan would agree. So you can go both ways, right? You
can say if you started okay when you became a יבמה, yevama,
you can go back to being okay even if you become אסור
assur in the middle. Or you can say no, that case is
worse. If you once you're in the יבמה yevama status and a
problem crops up, then that you know excludes you from ייבום yibum
from that point onwards even if that status changes. Okay, so we
have these different opinions about a woman who starts okay and then
becomes אסור, assur, can she go back to being okay? Phew, next
משנה. Mishna היבמה, ha-yevama, are we doing enough different topics in one
day? היבמה לא תחלוץ ולא תתייבם, ha-yevama lo tachlot v'lo tisyabem, now
actually this is a significant shift, okay? New topic. We've sort of
alluded to it before but brand new topic: wait three months so
you know who the father is. That's the new topic, okay, if
you don't have pregnancy tests. היבמה, ha-yevama, the sister-in-law, לא תחלוץ ולא
תתייבם, lo tachlot v'lo tisyabem, don't do חליצה chalitza or ייבום, yibum,
now why not חליצה chalitza we'll have to discuss, but don't do
חליצה chalitza or ייבום yibum עד שיהיה לה שלשה חדשים, ad she-yeish
la shlosha chodashim, wait three months so there's no question who the
father is. וכן כל שאר נשים, v'chen kol sh'ar nashim, all women
who are left, you know, whose husband is no longer around, whether
they are divorcees or widows, they have to wait three months. לא
יארסו ולא ינשאו עד שיהיה להם שלשה חדשים. lo ye'arsu v'lo yinas'u
ad she-yeish lahem shlosha chodashim.
Don't have קידושין kiddushin or נישואין nisuin until three months. Now קידושין
kiddushin does not really make so much sense. It's just like a
type of a לא פלוג lo plug because קידושין kiddushin without נישואין
nisuin they're not having sex yet, okay? But the first position is
all women, we're not distinguishing, if you were married wait three months
even before קידושין. kiddushin. And it says explicitly, we're not distinguishing, אחד
בתולות ואחד בעולות, echad betulot v'echad beulot, whether a virgin, meaning a
woman who never had sex, just had קידושין, kiddushin, her first husband
she had קידושין kiddushin with and then he died, okay, and she's
clearly still a virgin, nevertheless don't get married to the next man.
Don't even do קידושין kiddushin with the next man, so it's like
a לא פלוג lo plug on both sides, right? Do you understand
the real concern is she had sex with her first husband don't
have sex with the second husband. We're extending it to even if
you were married to the first guy with קידושין kiddushin without נישואין,
nisuin, no possibility of sex, and now you can't even do קידושין
kiddushin with the second husband. Okay even if there's like no possibility
with sex on both ends, it's a type of a לא פלוג.
lo plug. אחד בתולות. echad betulot. אחד בתולות אחד בעולות, echad betulos
echad be'ulos, whether virgins or non-virgins, אחד גרושות אחד אלמנות, echad grushas
echad almanas, whether divorcees or widows, that's the most obvious point, why
should there be a difference? אחד נשואות אחד ארוסות, echad nesuas echad
arusas, whether originally it was נישואין nissuin which would have allowed for
the possibility of sex, that sort of sounds like בעולות, be'ulos, or
whether it was only אירוסין. eirusin. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the logical thing. הנשואות יתארסו, hanesuas ye'arasu,
it's also nice, the sort of the language here, the parallel, הנשואות—like
it's
ABBA—הנשואות יתארסו, women who had been נשואות, nesuas, so might have had
sex with their first husbands, they can at least have קידושין kiddushin
with the second husbands as long as they don't move on to
נישואין, nissuin, okay? Because then there's no sex at that stage. והארוסות,
veha'arusas, and women that were only אירוסין eirusin with the first husband
and didn't have sex, ינשאו, yinaseu, they can actually have נישואין nissuin
with the second guy and start having sex, because in those cases
there's no concern. He doesn't buy into the לא פלוג. lo plug.
חוץ, Chutz, the one case he would exclude is מן הארוסה שביהודה,
min ha'arusa shebiyehudah, in the women who are ארוסות arusos but in
יהודה Yehuda as opposed to the הגליל, haGalil, מפני שלבו גס בה,
mipnei shelibo gas bah, because he's a little bit too comfortable with
her. Because basically what they would do is before the נישואין, nissuin,
you know, it's like they would actually be—the ארוס arus and the
ארוסה—would arusa spend private time together in order that they would start
feeling comfortable with one another before they actually started living together. Of
course if you give them some private time with one another, sometimes
it might actually lead to them having sex. So ארוסות arusos in
יהודה, Yehuda, we have to be concerned that they've had sex. All
right. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, כל הנשים יתארסו. kol hanashim
ye'arasu. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi agrees with רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. I
completely agree with you and therefore אירוסין eirusin is allowed for all
women, because they're not yet having sex with the second guy. חוץ,
Chutz, one exception for a completely different reason is מן האלמנה מפני
האיבול. min ha'almana mipnei ha'eivul. And now we understand why it mentioned
widows and as—in addition to divorcees. A widow has to wait—has to
wait until her אבילות aveilus is over. So even though I agree
that any woman could have אירוסין eirusin because they're not yet having
sex, but if the woman's a widow, she's got to wait a
month till her—till her אבילות aveilus is over. Okay, which is like
interesting, like why would you disagree with that? Okay, maybe so we'll
see in the גמרא. Gemara. So גמרא Gemara says like
this. בשלמא לא תתייבם, bishlama lo tityabem, I understand why not to
do יבום, yibbum, שמא יהא הולד בן קיימא וקפגע באיסור אשת אח.
shema yehei havlad ben kayama vekapaga be'issur eshes ach. Maybe, like, there's
this one issue of not the יבום yibbum case, who's the father?
Okay, we'll get to that. But in the יבום yibbum case, it's
even more weighty. If the woman is pregnant and if the child
is viable, there's no מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibbum and you're doing
an איסור issur of brother's wife. וקפגע באיסור אשת אח דאורייתא. vekapaga
be'issur eshes ach de'oraisa.
אלא חליצה אמאי? ella chalitza amai? Why not do חליצה? chalitza? And
this you might remember. We had a whole discussion of doing חליצה
chalitza with a pregnant woman. So the משנה Mishna says don't do
חליצה chalitza in the first three months. Why not? Okay, it must
say that חליצה chalitza with a pregnant woman doesn't work, which is
a discussion we had before. לימא תהוי תיובתא דרבי יוחנן? Leima tehei
tiyuvesa d'Rabbi Yochanan? Is this a contradiction to רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan?
דאמר חליצת מעוברת שמה חליצה, d'amar chalitzas me'uberes shema chalitza, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says חליצה chalitza with a pregnant woman counts, and our
משנה Mishna says don't do it.
ולאו אותיבניה לרבי יוחנן חדא זימנא? Velav osivneih l'Rabbi Yochanan chada zimna?
Okay, but we already disproved רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. All right. So
the גמרא Gemara says, לימא מהא נמי תהוי תיובתא? Leima meha nami
tehei tiyuvesa? I know, but let's also use this as a proof
again. So
רש״י Rashi says, like, if for some way you were able to
answer up the previous proof, we're going to pile on the proofs.
This משנה also proves against רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא, Lo, no, not necessarily. הכא היינו טעמא, Hacha hainu
ta'ama, I could tell you that if you did חליצה chalitza with
a pregnant woman it would work. Why though are you not—why there
does it say not to do חליצה? chalitza? שמא יהא ולד בן
קיימא, shema yehei velad ben kayama, because if she actually does have
a viable child, then she wouldn't have needed חליצה, chalitza, and you
would have already done חליצה. chalitza. ונמצאת אתה מצריכה כרוז לכהונה, Venimtzesa
ata matzricha karoz l'kehuna, and then you're going to have to make
an announcement and say, oh, this woman who חליצה chalitza was done
two months ago, everybody should know she's really not a חלוצה chalutza
because she had a viable child. So the גמרא Gemara said, וניצרכה,
Venitzrecha, so what? Make the announcement. לא, Lo, דילמא איכא דהוי בחליצה,
dilma ika dehavai bachalitza, there were people that were present at the
חליצה, chalitza, ולא הוי בהכרזה, velo havai behachraza, they weren't at the
retraction,
ומפסלו לה מן הכהונה, umafslu lah min hakehuna, and they'll go around
saying she can't marry a כהן kohen because they never heard the
retraction. Right, it's like the newspaper prints a retraction in small little
print on the—on the next day, nobody knows about it. Okay. So
therefore for practical reasons we don't want to do it even if
it would work. So the גמרא Gemara says, תינח אלמנה, Teinach almana,
fine, that's a case where she's a
אלמנה—I almana mean, let's say she—but גרושה מאי איכא למימר? grusha mai
ika leima? If this woman were גרושה grusha before she married the
brother—okay, before she married the first guy, ראובן—she Reuven had already been
divorced from her previous relationship. So why should we care about doing
an act of חליצה chalitza to her? She's already אסורה asura to
a כהן, kohen, right? Is that clear? She was divorced from some
other guy, married ראובן, Reuven, ראובן Reuven died. So why can't שמעון
Shimon go ahead and do a חליצה? chalitza? Right, she's already אסורה
asura to a כהן kohen because she's a גרושה grusha from her
earlier marriage. So the גמרא Gemara says—so מאי איכא למימר? mai ika
leima? משום דמפסלו לה ממזונות, Mishum demapslu lah memezonos, because once the
act Once the act of חליצה chalitza is done, we're gonna find
out that before the act of חליצה chalitza is done, she is
supported from the from the estate, okay? Once the act of the
dead guy's estate. Once the act of חליצה chalitza is done, she
stops being supported. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, we don't, we
don't want to let you do חליצה chalitza too soon. She deserves
to be supported for those three months, let her first anyway find
out if she's got a kid from the guy or not, okay?
And let's figure out if she needs חליצה chalitza or not, and
and don't do חליצה chalitza early because then you are, you are
depriving her of the מזונות. mezonos. The גמרא Gemara says תינח נשואה,
teinach nesua, that's fine if she was נשואה nesua to ראובן, Reuven,
then she's entitled to מזונות. mezonos.
ארוסה, arusa, גרושה, grusha, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? If she
was a גרושה grusha from a previous marriage and then only an
ארוסה arusa to ראובן, Reuven, so A, she's already פסול passul to
a כהן Kohen because a גרושה grusha from a previous marriage, and
B, she's only an ארוסה arusa to ראובן Reuven and then ראובן
Reuven dies, not entitled to מזונות. mezonos. Why not do חליצה? chalitza?
So the גמרא Gemara says fine, here's why we're not doing
חליצה. chalitza. אלא משום דרבי יוסי, ella mishum deRabbi Yosi, from רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. דתניא, detanya, מעשה באחד שבא לפני רבי יוסי. maaseh
be'echad sheba lifnei Rabbi Yosi. אמר ליה, amar lei, מהו לחלוץ בתוך
ג'? mahu lachlotz besoch gimmel? Can I do חליצה chalitza while it's
still within three months? אמר ליה, amar lei, לא תחלוץ. lo tachlotz.
No. ותחלוץ ומה בכך? vesachlotz umah bekach? Why not? So here we
have exactly our question was in this discussion. So קרא עליה מקרא
זה, kara aleih mikra zeh, he read this פסוק: pasuk: אם לא
יחפוץ, im lo yachpotz, you know, if you don't want to, then
you do חליצה. chalitza. So הא אם חפץ יבם, ha im chafetz
yabam, it has to be that you, if you wanted to, you'd
be allowed to do יבום. yibum. We're only going to allow חליצה
chalitza in a context where יבום yibum is an option.
כל העולה ליבום עולה לחליצה וכל שאינו עולה ליבום אינו עולה לחליצה.
kol ha'oleh leyibum oleh lechalitza vekol she'eino oleh leyibum eino oleh lechalitza.
So his basic answer is, now we know that rabbinically it's not
true, why? We know there are all these women that רש"י Rashi
points out that are rabbinically forbidden that we have חליצה chalitza with
and not יבום yibum with. But nevertheless, as a לכתחילה lechatchila approach,
we don't want to allow חליצה chalitza when יבום yibum isn't possible.
And since we can do the חליצה chalitza three months from now
when יבום yibum is possible, we
prefer to limit חליצה chalitza to a time when you have an
option of doing יבום. yibum. Okay, so we will, I guess we'll
end there for now.
Since he asked, where's the idea of some sort of סמיכות smichus
across with the גמרא? Gemara?
Yeah, and that is that we're concerned that the original...