After hearing some fascinating ideas about what happened to the twelve... to
the ten שבטים shevatim and the ideas that matrilineal and patrilineal descent
by themselves with one non-Jewish parent would be ממזר mamzer in both
ways and Jewish, of course it's not the way we rule. Anyway,
that was fascinating end of last פרק, perek, we began this פרק
perek with once again revisiting the issue about אשת אחיו שלא היה
בעולמו eshes achiv shelo haya b'olamo and we have now looked at
the דרשות drashos of where we know the idea that ייבום yibum
only applies when both brothers are alive at the same time at
the and one of them dies from the פסוק pasuk of יחדו.
yachdav. And we looked at יחדו yachdav to tell us other things
about patrilineal brothers on the father's side, and even if it's only
patrilineal, even if it's not by both parents, and so on. And
we had a fascinating line in the גמרא Gemara that ייבום yibum
is בנחלה תלה רחמנא. b'nachala tala rachmana. ייבום yibum is somehow directly
connected to an idea of inheritance and that is something to keep
in mind that we'll get back to. Now we pick up on
a new topic, I mean not fully new, but anyway that we
are going to see is going to circle back to the end
of the משנה Mishna that dealt with the issue of זיקה, zika,
of מאמר maamar and זיקה. zika. So let's take a look. הגמרא
hagemara says like this, אמר רב הונא אמר רב. amar Rav Huna
amar Rav. So the line starts with the word רב, Rav, it's
about twenty lines from the bottom. אמר רב הונא אמר רב amar
Rav Huna amar Rav
שומרת יבם שמתה מותרת באמה. shomeres yavam shemeisa muteres b'ima. So ראובן
Reuven is married to רחל, Rachel, ראובן Reuven dies,
so now שמעון Shimon is waiting to do
ייבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, ייבום או חליצה. yibum o chalitza. רחל's
Rachel status, a woman who is awaiting the act of ייבום או
חליצה yibum o chalitza is called a שומרת יבם. shomeres yavam. A
woman who is wait like sort of watching, you know, for this,
you know, waiting for this act to take place, watching her status
until something can happen, until either she'll have ייבום או חליצה. yibum
o chalitza. So here we are, רחל Rachel is שומרת יבם, shomeres
yavam, and then she dies. So שמתה, shemeisa, מותר, mutar, so שמעון
Shimon who was the person who would have done ייבום yibum is
now מותר באמה. mutar b'ima. Now can go ahead and marry רחל's
Rachel mother.
Why not? Well, if he had already been married to רחל Rachel
and רחל Rachel died, why couldn't he marry her mother?
Because that would be
אשה ואמה
isha
v'ima and that applies even after one's wife passes away, one still
cannot marry one's ex-wife, dead wife, lives wife's mother. So the point,
thank you so much, so the question is that רחל Rachel who
was not his wife but was his זקוקה, zekuka, was a woman
he had a זיקה zika to, a quasi-marital connection inherited from his
dead brother ראובן, Reuven, is that make her enough like his wife
that even if nothing went happened to sort of to concretize that
and to actualize that, nevertheless she always remains even after death his
זקוקה zekuka and the mother would be forbidden as, as the mother
of not אשתו ishto but the mother of זקוקתו. zekukaso.
Assumedly דאורייתא, d'oraysa, right?
Well, that's actually interesting, it does sound very rabbinic. Look, the whole
idea of זיקה, zika, it's worth saying, you know,
is fascinating, I find the idea of זיקה zika because there's nothing
in the פסוקים psukim that talk about that. Like the פסוקים psukim
just talk about the מצוה mitzvah of ייבום. yibum. And throughout the
גמרא Gemara you find the discussion of this concept called זיקה, zika,
this connection, what I've been describing as a sort of inherited quasi-marital
relationship. And חז"ל chazal understand that that actually is the biblical mechanism,
like that's part of the metaphysical, you know, or legal reality that
is at play here even though there's nothing in the פסוקים psukim
that talks about that. And that's not a דרבנן, derabbanan, that concept
of זיקה zika is fundamentally not. Now Michael is saying okay, I
might accept that the concept of זיקה zika is fundamentally not, that's
some mechanism, but the implications of it to treat this woman as
a wife so that her mother becomes forbidden, that sounds very rabbinic.
But we're actually going to find out, maybe in some cases yes,
but we're actually going to find out that there are some broad
possible implications of זיקה zika even at the דאורייתא d'oraysa level, both
לחומרא l'chumra and possibly even לקולא. l'kula.
Okay, but the פסק psak of רב Rav is it's not a
problem. The אם זקוקתו aim zekukaso is not a problem. Okay,
so קסבר kasavar מותר באמה. mutar b'ima. אלמא קסבר, alma kasavar, we
see that רב Rav holds, רב הונא Rav Huna in the name
of רב Rav holds, אין זיקה, ein zika, that there's no זיקה.
zika. Now does that mean he completely denies a concept of זיקה
zika altogether, right? Or does it mean that whatever the concept of
זיקה zika is, it's not enough to be seen as a quasi-marriage
for these types of implications, like for the implication about then relatives
of the woman he had a זיקה zika to are also considered
ערוה, erva, like for that we're not going to say זיקה. zika.
But the pretty categorical statement of אין זיקה, ein zika, but again
one wonders if הגמרא hagemara means it completely categorically. Okay, but... whatever
it is, if it exists, it's certainly not significant enough to make
the mother forbidden. Okay, now, I should also point out another obvious
reason why you might generally hold יש זיקה yeish zika and hold
it's not a problem here, because here the woman died, right? It's
one thing to say that while she's still alive and that there's
this potential and מצוה mitzvah and this thing to actualize about the
act of יבום, yibbum, that that reality of the obligation of יבום
yibbum and it could be actualized, that creates a זיקה zika which
maybe even has biblical implications for her sister and her mother and
all these other types of things. But as soon as she dies,
there's no longer a מצוה mitzvah of יבום. yibbum. So while it's
true that somebody's dead wife there are עריות arayos related to a
dead wife, here the whole idea of זיקה zika was connected to
the מצוה mitzvah that needed to be actualized and maybe after she
died we no longer see any significance to that after she has
died. That the גמרא Gemara is going to get to, whether you
could hold יש זיקה yeish zika but death makes it disappear. But
the גמרא Gemara here does, well חליצה chalitzah would remove it, but
one of the other had to be acted upon to be transformed.
But the גמרא Gemara here is interpreting if it's not a problem,
it's not saying because death did anything, it's saying fundamentally you would
not really hold of the concept of זיקה zika or certainly not
in any significant way for these הלכות. halachos. Yes, Jonathan's question.
Like זיקה zika was just a designation like a to be determined.
What's the difference between זיקה zika and מאמר? maamar?
And מאמר maamar is, so to understand that זיקה zika is, I
mean okay here it says an opinion אין זיקה, ein zika, but
assuming יש זיקה. yeish zika.
Does זיקה zika have some sort of.
Yes, זיקה zika is a, מאמר maamar is דרבנן. drabbanan. מאמר maamar
is to get some type of an act of קידושין kiddushin to
precede יבום yibbum to make it a little bit more like classic
marriage as a formal act of קידושין kiddushin and then there's the
act of sex and the act of living together that actualizes the
מצוה. mitzvah. That's מאמר. maamar. מאמר maamar is purely דרבנן. drabbanan. Although
we will see some interesting things about מאמר, maamar, but for now
let's just assume purely דרבנן. drabbanan. זיקה zika is their understanding of
the legal
or I might even say metaphysical mechanisms that are at play in
terms of יבום. yibbum. The brother dies, now the living brothers have
some type of a quasi-marital
relationship with this woman that they've inherited from their dead brother. That
has now somehow transferred to them and that thing can be like
actualized once the act of יבום yibbum is done and therefore that's
why the act of יבום yibbum is not like something new and
it's not an איסור issur of אשת אחיו, eishet achiv, but in
a way it's a continuation of the previous relationship, but that starts
with a זיקה zika which is a connection like
which is somewhat inherited from the dead brother. So that's the concept
behind it. So if it does create a connection, maybe it has
implications for like you know the woman's mother or the woman's sister.
Yes, I understand this statement אין זיקה ein zika in this context
like the first משנה mishna in קידושין Kiddushin in which death releases
the
woman.
Right, so it could be אין זיקה ein zika in a case
of death, but that but we'll see as we continue that the
גמרא Gemara is not limiting it to that type of a statement.
Okay, so let's continue.
למימר הלכה כדברי האומר אין זיקה. leima halacha k'divrei ha'omer ein zika.
So why do you give a case of מוטר ואימא? mutar v'ima?
Why don't you just say we rule like the opinion who says
אין זיקה? ein zika? Now who is the opinion that says אין
זיקה? ein zika?
So רש"י, Rashi, it's a little debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot but רש"י Rashi points us to a case we're going to
see on like a little bit like on י"ח עמוד ב', yud
chet amud bet, which is the following issue of the תנאים. Tannaim.
Basically a person, ראובן Reuven dies, he's married to two sisters, רחל
Rachel and לאה. Leah. Come along לוי, Levi, לוי Levi and לאה
Leah that work out. Come along לוי.
Levi. Did he marry two sisters?
Oh I'm sorry, sorry, you're right. He's not married to two sisters.
Thank you very much.
Okay, sorry. He
is married to, he is married to רחל. Rachel. Thank you very
much. Okay, he is, wait wait, let me get this right. He
is married to רחל. Rachel. Thank you very much. ראובן Reuven is
married to רחל. Rachel. לוי Levi is married to לאה. Leah. Okay,
ראובן Reuven dies. So now לוי Levi just did קידושין kiddushin with
לאה. Leah. He hasn't yet done נשואין nisuin with לאה. Leah. He
hasn't yet slept with לאה, Leah, he's just in קידושין. kiddushin.
רחל Rachel and ראובן Reuven were married. ראובן Reuven dies. So now
what do we say to לוי Levi as לוי? Levi? Don't do
נשואין nisuin yet with לאה. Leah. If you were to do נשואין
nisuin with לאה Leah then you would be having sex
with אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. Right, רחל Rachel is the woman who's
זקוקה zekukah to him, quasi-married,
and לאה Leah is the sister. So if you were to consummate
that marriage and do נשואין nisuin it would be a problem about
אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. What you should do rather לוי Levi is
wait before your wedding and get your brother שמעון Shimon to do
either יבום yibbum or חליצה chalitzah with רחל. Rachel. That'll take רחל
Rachel off of the picture, she'll no longer have a זיקה zika
to you. Either she'll be married to שמעון Shimon or she'll be
completely out of the picture. And then you could go ahead and
do your and have your wedding with לאה. Leah. Okay, so that's
the position that we're going to see later. That's a
position assumed as we'll see that's the position in the name I
think of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda and it yes רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda and it seems like that there's an opposing position.
זיקה zika or not. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says יש זיקה yesh
zika again it's a problem about אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso and those
that would disagree with him would say אין זיקה ein zika go
ahead consummate the marriage there's no problem of אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso.
So similar to us we're talking about a question of אין זקוקתו
ein zekukaso and there's a question about אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. There's
two differences though of that case and ours both of which the
גמרא Gemara is going to point to. Difference number one is in
that case Rachel was still alive. So the idea that there's a
זיקה zika and it's meaningful makes a lot more sense when the
woman is alive than when she's dead. Number two that makes the
reason to have זיקה zika there there's more of a reason to
think זיקה zika in that case. However number two there's a little
less of a reason to think זיקה zika because there are two
brothers שמעון Shimon and לוי. Levi. So it's not like it has
to be Rachel with לוי Levi it could be Rachel with שמעון
Shimon right? So in a case where there's not only one person
that could be consummating the relationship or doing ייבום yibum or חליצה
chalitza it might be harder to say יש זיקה yesh zika because
you don't know who this woman is ultimately going to do either
ייבום yibum or חליצה chalitza with so it's more like you know
it's more indeterminate. You had a question.
So yes is there no difference between the status of שמעון Shimon
and לוי Levi in terms of their
obligation wasn't שמעון Shimon like first...
Oh so that's also a good question meaning it adds to the
point I just made which is we say מצוה בגדול לייבם mitzvah
begadol leyabaim the older brother. So you could say if it matters
that there are two maybe it's even more of a reason to
say אין זיקה ein zika if we're dealing with the younger brother
rather than the older brother. Right absolutely absolutely. The whether you say
like מצוה בגדול mitzvah begadol at a דאורייתא deoraisa level or דרבנן
derabanan level but yes if it's fundamentally שמעון's Shimon obligation then not
only is it indeterminate but it's but more is on שמעון Shimon
and that's even more of a reason to say אין זיקה ein
zika in that case.
And the idea that he would have to put off marriage because
of the possibility that his next brother will die and then he'll
have an additional obligation.
Right but the way to be framing it wouldn't be the
possibility would be as long as ייבום yibum or חליצה chalitza hasn't
been done there's remains a connection with him so meaning you want
to think if it's מצוה בגדול mitzvah begadol it means it's not
his relationship at all nobody says that no it means it might
be primarily his obligation but there's still some type of a זיקה
zika but you are right the fact that there's more than one
brother is an argument more in that case to say whatever exists
is not so meaningful אין זיקה ein zika and that's why these
cases can be distinguished. Yes.
One question does it make a difference if the marriage of the
one preceded the קידושין kiddushin of the other or not I mean
אירוסין erusin of the other.
Oh so the גמרא Gemara has the case where the אירוסין erusin
yes so that's discussed and that might make a difference but let's
bracket that for now. Okay so let's take a look. Okay so
the גמרא Gemara says ולימא uleima why not just say
הלכה כדברי האומר אין זיקה halacha kedivrei haomer ein zika that we
rule like that position over there of אין זיקה ein zika and
he can go ahead and consummate his marriage with לאה. Leah. So
why do you have to give this case about the mother and
so on create a new case? גמרא Gemara says no. אי הוי
אמר הכי iy havai amar hachi if he had just given a
פסק psak about that case of אין זיקה ein zika הוה אמינא
הני מילי בתרי hava amina hanei milei bitrei that's because there are
two brothers you know and therefore לוי Levi and Rachel don't have
such a you know as a clear relationship and that's why לוי
Levi can consummate his marriage with לאה. Leah. אבל בחד aval bechad
maybe in the case where there is only one brother and he
has the full obligation יש זיקה yesh zika maybe it would be
זיקה zika so he had to tell you even in a case
of only one live brother he can go ahead and marry the
mother and there's not a problem of זיקה. zika. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולימא הלכה כדברי האומר אין זיקה אפילו בחד. uleima halacha
kedivrei haomer ein zika afilu bechad. Okay so why not say we
rule אין זיקה אפילו בחד ein zika afilu bechad even in the
case of one and make it clear? Okay so now אי אמר
הכי iy amar hachi if you'd said that הוה אמינא אפילו מחיים
hava amina afilu mechayaim then I might think that there's no זיקה
zika even if you know even in a case where the woman
is alive. קא משמע לן לאחר מיתה אין מחיים לא kamashma lan
leachar misa in mechayaim lo that after she died yes not
from alive let me just make sure I'm explaining this right one
second let me just check one second.
No I'm sorry I knew I was explaining it wrong. So I
would have thought that when he if you were to say אין
זיקה ein zika I'm sorry let me get this right one second.
ולימא uleima right if you were to say אין זיקה אפילו בחד
ein zika afilu bechad so maybe I would have said here's שמעון
Shimon he has to do this מצוה mitzvah of ייבום yibum with
Rachel we have said that if Rachel dies שמעון Shimon can marry
Rachel's mother because of אין זיקה ein zika but had I just
said אין זיקה אפילו בחד ein zika afilu bechad you might have
said שמעון Shimon can marry Rachel's mother even when Rachel is still
alive. Okay so therefore he didn't just want to say אין זיקה
ein zika אפילו בחד afilu bechad he wanted specifically say a case
of Rachel died now you can marry the mother. So after she
died you don't have to worry about it. If Rachel's still alive
you can't marry the mother. Okay so he said אי הוי אמר
הכי הוה אמינא אפילו מחיים
iy havai amar
hachi hava amina afilu mechayaim even if Rachel is still alive he
could have he could go ahead and marry the mother קא משמע
לן לאחר מיתה אין מחיים לא kamashma lan leachar misa in mechayaim
lo after death yes not from alive. Now, I would have thought
the reason is for what we said. After there is a זיקה,
zika, but when she dies, it goes away. But that's not what
the גמרא Gemara is saying. Look at what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say. There is a difference between marrying the mother if
Rachel is alive or dead. משום דאסור לבטל מצות יבמין Mishum de'assur
levatel mitzvos yevamin because you cannot be מבטל mevatel the מצות mitzvos
of יבום. yibum.
What does that mean? Meaning, really I hold the גמרא's Gemara saying
אין זיקה ein zika even when Rachel is alive. So if I
marry the mother, I'm not doing any איסור. issur. It's not אין
זקוקתו. ein zikukoso. There's no זיקה zika even when Rachel's alive. But
what's going to happen if I do the mother? I do the
mother and I haven't yet done anything with Rachel, יבום yibum or
חליצה. chalitza. Now I've married her mother. So what's my—what now do
I do with Rachel? Well, I certainly can't do יבום, yibum, right?
Because now it would be אשה ובתה. ishah u'vitah. So now, can
I do חליצה? chalitza? So here's, by the way, a fascinating case
which we haven't had yet, which is what happens if the sister-in-law
becomes an ערווה ervah after the guy died. Okay?
So when the guy died, there was a מצוה mitzvah of יבום
yibum or חליצה. chalitza. Now I'm married to her mother. Do I
still—is there still some remainder of a מצוה mitzvah that I still
maybe still have to do חליצה chalitza even though I obviously can't
do יבום? yibum? So the גמרא Gemara here assumes and רש"י Rashi
says this explicitly, that no, even if she becomes an ערווה ervah
after, you know, it started with a מצוה mitzvah to her, the
guy died and there was a מצוה, mitzvah, now she's an ערווה,
ervah, now you don't do יבום yibum or חליצה, chalitza, completely like
when she started as an ערווה, ervah, completely no מצוה mitzvah at
all. And that's why the גמרא Gemara says אסור לבטל מצות יבמין.
assur levatel mitzvos yevamin. In principle, I would hold אין זיקה ein
zika
even when Rachel's alive. And when I marry Rachel's mother, I didn't
do anything wrong. I was not marrying אין זקוקתו ein zikukoso because
there's no concept of זקוקה. zikukah. Okay? Certainly not to make the
mother forbidden. But we're not going to let me do that because
that's going to take a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum or חליצה,
chalitza, one or the other, and completely make it go away. And
that's seen as a problem. If there's an idea of doing יבום
yibum or חליצה, chalitza, then I should do one form of that
מצוה mitzvah rather than make it disappear. And that's אסור לבטל מצות
יבמין.
assur levatel mitzvos yevamin.
I assume
that's a לכתחילה lechatchila and בדיעבד. bediavad. Yeah, בדיעבד bediavad it would
be חל. chal. Exactly. And it would not be an איסור issur
of אין זקוקתו. ein zikukoso. It would just be that I negated
the מצוה mitzvah of יבום.
yibum. What's the rationale behind that?
About not negating the מצוה mitzvah of יבום? yibum? So
it's—yeah,
I don't know. I mean, it's something like, you know, that there's
a מצוה mitzvah to be done and you made it disappear. But
I don't know. I don't know if there's more to it than
that.
Okay, she's free to marry anybody.
And then she's free to marry anybody she wants.
I mean, it seems like it's
so—I don't want to trivialize this concept. I mean, it's like סוכות
Sukkos is coming. Is it the same as saying, like, it would
be אסור לכתחילה assur lechatchila to take a vacation in a place
where you know there's not going to be a סוכה?
sukkah? Yeah, something like—I mean, maybe. If there's more to it than
that, then I can't say what it is. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so basically the גמרא's Gemara saying
that the—in principle here, אין זיקה ein zika even מחיים, mechayim, but
don't act on it in a way that's going to get out
of the—that's going to make the מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum disappear.
תנן. Tenan.
Now we're going to try to analyze this position. יבמתו שמתה מותר
באחותה. Yevamto shemesa mutar be'achosa.
We have a משנה Mishnah later that says that again, this woman
who is יבמתו, yevamto, שומרת יבם, shomeres yavam, waiting to do יבום
yibum or חליצה, chalitza, she dies, the brother can marry her sister.
באחותה. be'achosa. Now, if even if a wife dies, you can marry
the sister, right? ואשה אל אחותה לא תקח לצרור לגלות ערותה עליה
בחייה, ve'ishah el achosah lo sikach litzror legalos ervasah aleha bechayeha, right?
So here, if the שומרת יבם shomeres yavam dies, of course you
can marry the sister. באחותה אין באמו לא. Be'achosa in be'imo lo.
So it only says sister,
presumably can't marry the mother, because if a wife dies, you couldn't
marry the mother. So the implication here is, is if the שומרת
יבם shomeres yavam dies, you also can't marry the mother. Sounds like
יש זיקה. yesh zika. גמרא Gemara says, no, הוא הדין דאפילו באמו.
hu hadin de'afilu be'imo. No, really, in that case, could marry the
mother like we've been
saying. ואיידי דתנא רישא, ve'aidi detana reisha, because the beginning of the
משנה Mishnah starts by saying אשתו שמתה מותר באחותה, ishto shemesa mutar
be'achosa,
that when a real wife dies, actual wife dies, he can marry
his sister. באחותה אין אבל באמו לא, be'achosa in aval be'imo lo,
only the sister he can marry, not the mother, דהוי ליה איסור
דאורייתא, dehava leh issur d'oraisa, because biblically there's obviously a prohibition of
marrying a mother even after the wife has died. תנא נמי סיפא
מותר באחותה. tana nami seifa mutar be'achosa. So when it talks about
the case of שומרת יבם, shomeres yavam, it also says sister, which—but
the real הלכה halacha would be that—of course it's funny because it's
such a חידוש, chiddush, once you have this difference by wife, you
should have said that if the difference doesn't hold by יבמה. yevamah.
But the גמרא Gemara here says, no, it was לאו דוקא. lav
davka. And really you could even marry the mother, אין זיקה. ein
zika. Okay, so that's one version. רב יהודה אמר, Rav Yehuda amar,
that's a version in the name of רב. Rav. רב הונא אמר
רב. Rav Huna amar Rav. רב יהודה אמר, Rav Yehuda amar, now
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says שומרת יבם שמתה אסור באמה. shomeres yavam
shemesa assur be'imah.
Even after she dies, you cannot marry the mother, which is אלמא
קסבר יש זיקה. alma kasavar yesh zika. So you see that there
is זיקה zika and the mother is forbidden even after the woman
has died, יש זיקה. yesh zika. ולימא הלכה כדברי האומר יש זיקה.
veleima halacha kedivrei ha'omer yesh zika.
Why not rule like יש זיקה yesh zika like that case about
lazy not consummating the marriage with לאה Leah because of because of
because of רחל? Rachel? So why not say יש זיקה yesh zika
in general? אי אמר הכי, Ee amar hachi, had he said יש
זיקה, yesh zika, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would have said הני
מילי בחד, hani mili b-chad, maybe only יש זיקה yesh zika in
a case of one brother, אבל בתרי אין זיקה, aval b-trei ein
zika, but maybe with two there's not, which the גמרא Gemara says
what? The whole other case of אין זיקה יש זיקה ein zika
yesh zika as I've been talking about,
לוי Levi with שמעון Shimon and לוי, Levi, is a case where
there's two brothers. דהא כי פליגי בתרי פליגי. D-ha ki peligi b-trei
peligi. What do you mean? The case about לוי Levi not consummating
the marriage is because there's also שמעון Shimon in the picture. So
why not just rule in that case, that's another case that we
know, a Tannaidic debate about whether does לוי Levi have to wait
to consummate the marriage? Just say you rule in that case יש
זיקה, yesh zika, and if there's יש זיקה yesh zika by case
of two brothers, certainly there'll be יש זיקה yesh zika by one
brother. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אלא אי אמר הכי, Ella
ee amar hachi, no. Had you just said יש זיקה yesh zika
in that case of לוי Levi waiting to consummate the marriage, I
would have said הוה אמינא, hava amina, top of 41a, I would
have
said מחיים me-chayim that's because רחל's Rachel alive and that's why he
can't consummate his marriage with לאה. Leah. אבל לאחר מיתה, Aval l-achar
mita, if the woman died, פקעה לה זיקה, paka la zika, which
to me makes an enormous amount of sense. Once the woman has
died, it's no longer meaningful. You could talk about a woman who
has died as still his dead wife and therefore you don't marry
the mother. But after she's died, to call her זקוקתו zikukaso after
she's died something still remains, that there's some lasting meaning to that,
maybe I would say that in that case it wouldn't be a
problem and then he could marry the mother. So maybe יש זיקה
מחיים yesh zika me-chayim but not זיקה לאחר מיתה. zika l-achar mita.
קמשמע לן דזיקה בכדי לא פקעה. Kamashma lan d-zika b-chadi lo paka.
So he's explicitly telling you זיקה zika doesn't disappear by itself, it
doesn't just disappear. So if there's a concept of זיקה zika which
is a quasi-marriage concept, that idea would continue status, continued to remain
even after death. And therefore could not marry the mother. Okay. So
we are פוסקן-ing paskin יש זיקה yesh zika in the most broad
way, presumably even in a case of two brothers, where it's not
specifically relating to him, and even לאחר מיתה יש זיקה. l-achar mita
yesh zika. Okay. Now we're going to, so we have this debate,
יש זיקה yesh zika או o אין זיקה. ein zika. לימא מסייע
ליה, Leima msayei lei, certainly
with regarding the question of whether it creates an issue of עריות.
arayot. לימא מסייע ליה, Leima msayei lei, let's try to support this
idea. יבמתו שמתה מותר באחותה. Yevimto she-meita mutar b-achotah.
So we're going to go through the same thing that before was
a disproof, now it's going to be a proof. We have the
משנה Mishna that says when the sister-in-law dies, he can marry the
sister. באחותה אין באמה לא. B-achotah in b-imah lo. So it sounds
like only the sister, not the mother, because of a זיקה zika
problem. No, הוא הדין דאפילו באמה, Hu ha-din d-afilu b-imah, it could
even marry the mother. ואיידי דתנא רישא V-aidi d-tana reisha אשתו שמתה
מותר באחותה, ishto she-meita mutar b-achotah, since initially it said when the
wife dies, he can marry the sister, דוקא באחותה davka b-achotah only
the sister, אבל באמה לא aval b-imah lo but not the mother,
דהויא איסור דאורייתא d-havei issur d-oraita because that's mother of one's wife
even after death is forbidden. תנא נמי סיפא Tana nami seifa מותר
באחותה. mutar b-achotah. So it says in the end by the יבמה
yevama that also מותר באחותה, mutar b-achotah, but that's because it spoke,
but that's because it was paralleling the language about wife. But maybe
the real הלכה halakha here, maybe you could read it that it
would also be מותר באמה, mutar b-imah, maybe the end is לאו
דוקא. lav davka. Okay. So the simple sense of that משנה Mishna
certainly seems to say that it's אסור באמה, assur b-imah, יש זיקה,
yesh zika, which is what here we have רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
saying, but it's not absolutely dispositive. So now it says like this,
מתיב Metiv רב הונא Rav Huna בר פחייא. bar Phiah. So now
we're going to keep on trying to prove it or disprove it.
עשה בה מאמר, Assa bah maamar, and now we're going to turn
to our משנה. Mishna. Okay. So עשה בה מאמר, assa bah maamar,
if the one of the surviving brothers did מאמר. maamar. So
I'm going to remind you about what this case was because I've
properly forgotten it as well. Let me run and remember this all
right up here.
Okay, so I'm going to turn this. Aha.
Okay.
So anyway we had the case about אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו.
eshet achiv she-lo haya b-olamo. So we had ראובן Reuven married to
רחל Rachel and שמעון Shimon was
around. שמעון Shimon was around,
okay, and שמעון Shimon was married to שרה. Sarah. Fine. Okay. And
then, and then, so this
is stage one. Stage two, ראובן Reuven dies. Okay. Stage three, לוי
Levi is born. לוי Levi is born now, רחל Rachel is אשת
אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, eshet achiv she-lo haya b-olamo, no מצות יבום.
mitzva yibum. Okay. And now שמעון Shimon does יבום yibum with רחל.
Rachel. Okay. And in that case, if שמעון Shimon were to die,
then she would be an ערווה erva to him and that would
be a צרת ערווה, tzarat erva, right? And that's the case of,
now let's say he did not do יבום yibum with רחל. Rachel.
Let's say he only did
מאמר. maamar. Okay. right? Okay, because she's not really Shimon's wife. But
דאורייתא, de-Oraisa, he should really be doing יבום yibbum with Sarah, but
דרבנן, de-rabbanan, she's quasi his wife, so this is quasi a case
of ערוה ervah for יבום, yibbum, so this is sort of a
צרת ערוה, tzaras ervah, because the יבום yibbum מאמר ma'amar makes it
almost as if Rachel is Shimon's wife. So because of that, so
if we look at it as if she's the wife, he can't
do יבום yibbum with—so Rachel is the ערוה, ervah, Sarah is צרת
ערוה, tzaras ervah, but he can't just not do anything because דאורייתא,
de-Oraisa, Sarah is the real חיוב יבום. chiyuv yibbum. So the משנה
Mishna says you do חליצה chalitzah with Sarah, don't do יבום, yibbum,
that's what you do in that case. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara
is going to ask is why is this the scenario only after
Shimon did מאמר? ma'amar? Let's say Shimon did not do מאמר. ma'amar.
He's still got a זיקה zika relationship with Rachel. He's got a
זיקה zika relationship even if he does absolutely nothing. So why don't
we say that even in that case he can't go ahead and
do יבום yibbum with Sarah, because then that will be a case
of about—Sarah will be—is right is is
Sarah צרת זיקתו? tzaras zikkusako? No, not צרת זיקתו. tzaras zikkusako. It'll
be what? Something like that. It'll be a case of צרת ערוה
על
ידי זיקה.
tzaras ervah
al
yedei zika.
Okay? That would sort of be the thing.
Who's got the זיקה?
zika? You're talking about Shimon, at the moment Reuven dies, Shimon and
Levi is born, right? Shimon has a זיקה zika to Rachel, okay?
So she's like quasi אשתו, ishto, okay? Then Shimon dies, so now
Levi should be אסור assur דאורייתא de-Oraisa to Sarah even without מאמר,
ma'amar, he should be אסור assur to Sarah because because Rachel because
Sarah is צרת, tzaras, you know, I don't know, צרת זיקת שמעון.
tzaras zikkusas Shimon. So the same way צרת אשת שמעון tzaras eshas
Shimon is a problem, צרת זיקת שמעון tzaras zikkusas Shimon is. Now
this is of course different because here the זיקה zika is not
with the person himself, it's another man's זיקה zika is defining a
relationship. Levi is not the יבם yavam because he wouldn't born
yet, because he wasn't born yet. Right.
Well then and then he gets born, so he was not the
יבם yavam here but he is the יבם yavam after Shimon dies.
After Shimon dies, so he's a יבם yavam to Sarah. To Sarah.
But but Rachel, Rachel is an ערוה ervah to him. So so
the same way as if Shimon had been מאמר ma'amar or יבום
yibbum with Rachel, he couldn't do anything with Sarah because then it
would be צרת, tzaras, you know, צרת ערוה. tzaras ervah. So here
it's צרת ערוה על ידי זיקה, tzaras ervah al yedei zika, okay?
Not that Shimon really married Shimon but she sort of was על
ידי זיקה. al yedei zika. So it's a little bit different because
the זיקה zika is not with the person himself, it was another
man's זיקה zika is defining a relationship. But the גמרא Gemara assumes
it should be the same. So the question, so if we פוסקן
pasken יש זיקה yesh zika even after death, so even after Shimon
has died, we still see Rachel as quasi-connected to Shimon and therefore
Levi's מצות יבום mitzvat yibbum should be defined by Rachel's presence. Okay.
So why did the משנה Mishna say only after מאמר? ma'amar? It
should have said in all cases Levi cannot go ahead and do
יבום yibbum with Sarah. Alright, let's take a look. Okay. עשה בה
מאמר ומת, asa bah ma'amar u-met, so Shimon did a מאמר ma'amar
with Rachel and died. I think somebody even asked this question when
we read the משנה Mishna yesterday. עשה בה מאמר ומת שניה חולצת
ולא מתיבמת,
asa bah ma'amar u-met shniyah choletzet
v'lo mityabemet, so with Sarah, he does חליצה chalitzah not יבום. yibbum.
Yes? Wait, the basic basics. Shimon is married to Sarah, and when
Reuven died, Shimon can be the יבם yavam of Rachel? Right, they're
not related. But he can do it even though he is married.
Yes, well we're dealing with a polygamous society. Yes, right.
I mean that's all the cases
of the משנה Mishna about צרת אשתו, tzaras ishto, right, is multiple
wives, right? But I should say right upfront that we're going to
find a debate and we've already indicated it like I think on
the first דף daf about whether we first say מצוה לחלוץ mitzvah
lachlot or מצוה ליבם, mitzvah lyabem, which one do we sort of
say is preferable? And it winds up being a debate between בבלי
Bavli וירושלמי v'Yerushalmi which translates into a debate between אשכנז Ashkenaz וספרד,
u-Sefarad, and you might be able to guess which is which. בבלי
Bavli וספרד u-Sefarad which had polygamous society said מצוה ליבם תחלה mitzvah
lyabem techila and and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael ואשכנז v'Ashkenaz which had
a monogamous society said מצוה לחלוץ, mitzvah lachlot, not מצוה ליבם. mitzvah
lyabem. So but assuming a polygamous society, that's all what we've been
talking about, right? So okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: So עשה בה מאמר ומת, asa bah ma'amar u-met, טעמא דעשה
בה מאמר. ta'ama d'asa bah ma'amar. The reason is is because Shimon
did מאמר ma'amar with Rachel which made it quasi his wife. טעמא
דעשה בה מאמר. Ta'ama d'asa bah ma'amar. הא לא עשה בה מאמר,
Ha lo asa bah ma'amar, if he did not do מאמר, ma'amar,
שניה נמי יבום מיבמת, shniya nami yibbum meyabemet, then Levi could even
do יבום yibbum with Sarah. So why is that? ואי אמרת יש
זיקה, ve-i amart yesh zika, if there's זיקה, zika, הויא לה havya
lah Sarah should be צרת אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו בזיקה. tzaras
eshas achiv shelo haya beolamo bezika. Now you don't have to feel
bad that we couldn't say it in a nice concise way. So
Sarah should be So because so anyway so if so it should
be like a case of צרת ערווה tzoras erva if זיקה zika
is meaningful. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so okay so why did
it have to be מאמר ma'amar in the משנה mishna if יש
זיקה yesh zika even after death? So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, הוא
הדין דאף על גב דלא עבד בה מאמר, שניה מחלץ חלצה יבומי
לא מיבמה. hu hadin de'af al gav delo avad ba ma'amar, shniya
mechlatz chaltza yibumi lo meyabma. You know what? You're right. Big shock,
it's a שקלא וטריא shakla v'tarya when the משנה mishna says מאמר,
ma'amar, it didn't have to happen. Even if שמעון Shimon did nothing,
the זיקה zika is enough to make שרה Sarah a problem to
לוי. Levi. Okay, so you could only do חליצה chalitza not יבום.
yibum. Now obviously זיקה zika is not enough to say you don't
have to do חליצה, chalitza, okay at least you would have to
do חליצה. chalitza. There's still some, it's not a full, but it
is enough to say you can't do יבום. yibum. והא דקתני מאמר,
V'ha diktani ma'amar, so why did it say in the case when
שמעון Shimon did מאמר ma'amar with רחל? Rachel? לאפוקי מבית שמאי דאמר
מאמר קונה קנין גמור. Le'apoke mi-Beis Shammai de'amar ma'amar koneh kinyan gamur.
Okay, here the גמרא Gemara is going back to you. I said
מאמר ma'amar is totally דרבנן derabbanan except for בית שמאי Beis Shammai
who thinks that מאמר ma'amar is really like real יבום. yibum. Okay,
so קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, so it's telling you not that you
did מאמר ma'amar to make שרה Sarah a problem; even without doing
מאמר, ma'amar, even with זיקה, zika, this is a quasi-relationship and therefore
רחל Rachel is a problem to לוי Levi and שרה Sarah is
a problem to לוי Levi even with just זיקה. zika. But I
might have thought that if you did מאמר ma'amar according to בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, if you did מאמר, ma'amar, maybe according to בית
שמאי Beis Shammai that equals, for בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, יבום. yibum.
And if he had done יבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, what would
be לוי's Levi's story? He wouldn't even have to do חליצה. chalitza.
That would be a straight case of צרת ערווה. tzoras erva. So
it says לוי Levi has to do חליצה chalitza with שרה Sarah
even without מאמר. ma'amar. The משנה mishna said מאמר ma'amar because I
might have thought like בית שמאי Beis Shammai that with מאמר ma'amar
לוי Levi is, שרה Sarah is completely off, it's a real צרת
ערווה. tzoras erva. Why would you think like בית שמאי? Beis Shammai?
I don't know, but that's the way the גמרא Gemara gets out
of it. Okay.
מאמר Ma'amar
we assume that there were also sexual relations? No, דווקא davka not.
That would be יבום. yibum. It's a קידושין kiddushin in a case
of יבום yibum
and whether does that
have any דאורייתא de'oraisa meaning. Okay, so קמשמע לן kamashma lan that
that's not so.
איתיביה אביי, Eisivei Abaye, so now אביי. Abaye. שני אחים בעולם אחד,
ומת אחד מהם בלא ולד. Shnei achim b'olam echad, u-meis echad mei-hem
b'lo valad. Okay, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon are alive. ראובן Reuven
dies, no kids, ואמר השני הזה לעשות מאמר ביבמתו v'amar ha-sheini hazeh
la'asos ma'amar b'yivamto and שמעון Shimon gets already to do מאמר ma'amar
with רחל, Rachel, ולא הספיק לעשות בה מאמר עד שנולד לו אח,
v'lo hispik la'asos ba ma'amar ad she-nolad lo ach, he didn't get
a chance he was about to do מאמר ma'amar and then לוי
Levi was born, ומת u-meis and then שמעון Shimon died. So meaning,
it's a very dramatic way of describing it, but meaning it's just
like we described. It's the case of exactly the case of the
משנה mishna except the case of זיקה zika and not מאמר. ma'amar.
Okay, שמעון Shimon had a זיקה zika to רחל, Rachel, he died,
and now what's the story with לוי? Levi? לוי Levi was born
before שמעון Shimon did the מאמר. ma'amar. Yes. So the זיקה, zika,
it's a case of זיקה, zika, not a case of מאמר. ma'amar.
So if we, this is exactly our case. So let's take a
look what the story with לוי Levi is. Okay, so ומת, u-meis,
הראשונה יוצאה משום אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו, ha-rishona yotza mishum eshes
achiv shelo haya baolamo, so obviously לוי Levi can't do יבום yibum
or חליצה chalitza with רחל, Rachel, that's ערווה, erva, אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו. eshes achiv shelo haya baolamo. But והשנייה, v'ha-shniya, שרה, Sarah,
או חולצת או מתיבמת. o choletzes o misyabemes. Look at that, לוי
Levi can do יבום yibum or חליצה chalitza with שרה. Sarah. שרה
Sarah is not a problem. So
this
is very clear. שרה Sarah only becomes a problem if שמעון Shimon
had done מאמר ma'amar to רחל. Rachel. מאמר Ma'amar to רחל Rachel
makes it a type of an ערווה erva case. That's enough of
a real quasi as if he's married. But without מאמר, ma'amar, just
זיקה, zika, then שמעון Shimon is, then if there's just a זיקה
zika here and שמעון Shimon dies, רחל Rachel is into the picture
and לוי Levi can do יבום yibum with שרה. Sarah. Okay so
the גמרא, Gemara, so that's a pretty good proof אין זיקה ein
zika at least after death. So let's
take a look. ואי אמרת יש זיקה, V'ee amart yesh zika, if
you said יש זיקה, yesh zika, הויא לה צרת אשת אחיו שלא
היה בעולמו בזיקה.
havya la tzoras eshes achiv
shelo haya baolamo b'zika. Okay, that's a real good way to see
if like this anyone's been paying attention in the דף. daf. What's
the, explain these words: צרת אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו בזיקה. tzoras
eshes achiv shelo haya baolamo b'zika. How many different sort of הלכות
halachos are embedded in each one of those words? Okay, anyway, so
if so you see if זיקה zika was a real issue, then
רחל, Rachel,
who's an ערווה erva to him, would create a problem for שרה.
Sarah. Since רחל Rachel isn't creating a problem for שרה, Sarah, you
see that the זיקה zika is not meaningful, at least after death.
So the גמרא Gemara has to concede that. It says fine, that's
true, that is a position of אין זיקה ein zika at least
after death. But הא מני רבי מאיר היא דאמר אין זיקה. Ha
mani Rabbi Meir hi d'amar ein zika. That's a רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir position that we're going to see later that actually says אין
זיקה. ein zika. So I can see that ברייתא braisa does say
אין זיקה. ein zika. But that's not, it's not necessarily דברי הכל.
Divrei HaKol.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, ומי סבר ליה
לרבי מאיר אין זיקה? U'mi savar lei leRabbi Meir ein Zika? Is
that really true that you can ascribe to Rabbi Meir the position
of אין זיקה? ein Zika? והתנן, V'hatnan, we have a משנה Mishna
and a סתם משנה stam Mishna we're going to assume is רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. ארבעה אחים, Arba'a achin, four brothers. שנים מהם נושאים
שתי אחיות. Shenayim mehem nosim shtei achayot. So ראובן Reuven and שמעון
Shimon are married to רחל Rachel and שרה. Sarah. No, that's not
good because they're not married. So ראובן Reuven and לוי Levi are
married to רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. Okay, שתי אחיות. shtei achayot.
ומתו, u'metu, הנשואים האחיות. hanesuim ha'achayot. So now ראובן Reuven and לוי
Levi died. So רחל Rachel and לאה Leah are sisters. הרי אלו
חולצות ולא מתייבמות. Harei elu chotzot v'lo mityabmot. So now what is
the story of רחל Rachel and לאה Leah vis-a-vis the two other
brothers, okay, יששכר Yissachar and זבולון? Zevulun? So can יששכר Yissachar and
זבולון Zevulun do ייבום yibum like maybe יששכר Yissachar should do ייבום
yibum with רחל Rachel and זבולון Zevulun should do ייבום yibum with
לאה? Leah? Problem is as soon as יששכר Yissachar does ייבום yibum
with רחל, Rachel, what has he just now done? He has had
sex
with אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, right? He does ייבום yibum with רחל,
Rachel, but he has a זיקה Zika to לאה. Leah.
A זיקה Zika to both of them.
Because he has a זיקה Zika to both of them and זבולון
Zevulun has a זיקה Zika to both of them. So if he
goes ahead and he does ייבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, then he
is having sex with לאה's Leah sister, לאה Leah his זקוקה. zekuka.
So אחות זקוקתו. achot zekukato. So if זיקה Zika is like אשתו,
ishto, it's sort of like אחות אשתו. achot ishto. So therefore what
the משנה Mishna says is, therefore since that would be a problem,
חולצות ולא מתייבמות. chotzot v'lo mityabmot. You have to do חליצה chalitza
and not ייבום. yibum. So this is a סתם משנה, stam Mishna,
we're assuming it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and it has a problem
with זיקה, Zika, right? Because it won't let them do ייבום yibum
because of the other, because of the sister. So you see here's
a סתם משנה stam Mishna of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
יש זיקה yesh Zika and you're telling me that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir holds אין זיקה. ein Zika.
Right, the two of the brothers, both those two brothers died. Right.
So now you see the זיקה Zika in effect has יששכר Yissachar
and זבולון Zevulun both married to the same women.
There's a זיקה Zika to two sisters.
Each of them have a זיקה Zika to each of those two
sisters. Yes. So you basically have a case in which before they
do anything more than that, זיקה Zika is already defining them in
an ערוה erva position.
Exactly. To don't make it more problematic and actually then go ahead
and have sex and then go have sex with אחות זקוקתו. achot
zekukato.
So חליצה chalitza with one and the other does חליצה chalitza with
the other?
Does that work? Yes, exactly. Okay, because the חליצה chalitza with one
doesn't work for the other because they're coming from different husbands. Okay,
so here you see it says יש זיקה yesh Zika
and how could you say רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and this is
a סתם משנה, stam Mishna, so how could you say רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says אין זיקה? ein Zika? So the גמרא Gemara says
like this, ואי סלקא דעתך סבר רבי מאיר אין זיקה, v'ei salka
da'atach savar Rabbi Meir ein Zika, if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds
אין זיקה, ein Zika, הני מתרי בתי קאתין. hani mitrei batei ka'atyan.
They come from two different households, right? Meaning two different husbands. So
why not just each one do ייבום yibum with the other one?
It's not a case of צרת ערוה tzarat erva or whatever. There's
two different, two different husbands. So each one, so each one could
do ייבום yibum with a different brother. והאי ליבם חדא והאי ליבם
חדא. v'hai liyabem chada v'hai liyabem chada. Let one brother do ייבום
yibum with one, let the other brother do ייבום yibum with the
other. So you see here's this משנה Mishna that holds יש זיקה.
yesh Zika. So and how did that work with the ברייתא Braita
that you were saying was רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that held אין
זיקה ein Zika and there was no problem in the case of
אשת אחיו שלא היה בעולמו? eshet achiv she'lo haya b'olamo? So the
גמרא Gemara says לעולם אין זיקה. le'olam ein Zika. Now I'm going
to stick by my guns, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds אין זיקה
ein Zika and even in this case about רחל Rachel and לאה
Leah he would hold אין זיקה. ein Zika. So if אין זיקה,
ein Zika, why can't יששכר Yissachar and זבולון Zevulun do ייבום? yibum?
So, אבל משום דקסבר אסור לבטל מצות יבמין,
aval mishum de'kasavar
assur levatel mitzvat yevamin, because if they do ייבום, yibum, it might
lead to a ביטול bitul of the מצוה mitzvah of ייבום. yibum.
How is it a ביטול bitul of the מצוה? mitzvah? Each one
of them is doing ייבום yibum with a different one of the
wives. So here's how that would lead to the case. דדילמא אדמיבם
חד. de'dilma ad'miyabem chad. So goes יששכר Yissachar and he does ייבום
yibum with רחל. Rachel. And while he's, that's what he did first.
ומת אידך. u'met idach. And then what's going to happen? זבולון Zevulun
חס ושלום chas v'shalom he goes and he dies. So now, why
would he die? I don't know, he's making problems. He goes and
he dies. So now in that scenario what is now the story
with לאה? Leah? She doesn't get ייבום yibum or חליצה. chalitza. Because
now she is an ערוה, erva, right, to יששכר. Yissachar. You got
יששכר Yissachar did ייבום yibum with רחל. Rachel. So לאה Leah to
him is now an ערוה. erva. That's אחות אשתו. achot ishto. So
no problem, let זבולון Zevulun do ייבום. yibum. But let's say זבולון
Zevulun would now die, then לאה Leah who before this could have
had חליצה chalitza or ייבום, yibum, now goes without anything. That's ביטול
מצות יבמין. bitul mitzvat yevamin.
The problem is that the human being wasn't מבטל, mevatel, הקדוש ברוך
הוא! HaKadosh Baruch Hu!
I understand, but we don't want to create a scenario where that's
going to happen. So rather than a, you gotta point out the
irony, especially since we assume that there's a real importance of doing
ייבום. yibum. So rather than telling each brother to do ייבום yibum
because and not worry about the one scenario where one will do
it and the other will die before he gets a chance to
do it, you know, just go ahead do ייבום. yibum. No, we're
going to worry about that one scenario and therefore both of you
are going to do חליצה. chalitza. If you ask me, that's more
of a case of ביטול מצות יבמים bitul mitzvas yevamim than the
other, but somehow the גמרא Gemara feels יבום yibbum or חליצה, chalitzah,
at least you're doing something, and better to make sure you've done
something than to create a scenario where nothing happens for one of
the women. I don't understand it. Okay, so really אין זיקה ein
zika and it's a very different type of a problem. Okay, so
משום אל תבטל מצות יבמים, mishum al tevatel mitzvas yevamim, דילמא אדמיבם
חד, dilma ad-meyabbem chad, so Issachar does יבום yibbum with Rachel, מאי
אידך, mai idach, Zebulun dies, וקא מבטל מצות יבמים, ve-ka mevatel mitzvas
yevamim,
and now Leah has no nothing done to her, no יבום yibbum
or חליצה. chalitzah. So in order not to have that happen, we
say both of you do חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says one minute.
So we're not worried that someone's going to die
between before getting around to doing חליצה, chalitzah, that you're also מבטל
מצות יבמים? mevatel mitzvas yevamim?
No, then he could do no no because then he could do
חליצה chalitzah to Leah as well. He did חליצה chalitzah to Rachel
so then he could do חליצה chalitzah to Leah because then Leah
is Rachel there's no ערווה erva case because he did חליצה chalitzah
with Rachel and he broke the זיקה. zika. Okay, but good question
though. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, ואי אין זיקה, ve-ee ein zika, one minute. If Rabbi Meir
holds אין זיקה, ein zika, תיבטל. tibatul. So here we're getting maybe
a little clearer understanding of what משום אל תבטל מצות יבמים mishum
al tevatel mitzvas yevamim is. If he holds אין זיקה, ein zika,
why should I care that the מצוה mitzvah goes away? Meaning the
גמרא Gemara thinks that they might be logically connected. If you hold
יש זיקה, yesh zika, remember I described זיקה zika as some like
a quasi קידושין, kiddushin, a transfer, a potential that has to be
like actualized. Something has to be done with it. It has to
either be, you know, transformed into יבום yibbum or released through חליצה.
chalitzah. So if you hold יש זיקה, yesh zika, I can understand
that you sort of feel there's this thing here that something had
to be done to transform it from some potential to some actual,
to do something with this זיקה. zika. But if there is no
זיקה, ein zika, so who cares if there's a מצוה mitzvah and
due to circumstances outside of your control, something happened, it rained and
you couldn't go in your סוכה, sukkah, my brother died and this
woman couldn't have יבום, yibbum, okay, so you weren't able to do
a מצוה, mitzvah, something happened out of your control. Meaning the גמרא
Gemara thinks that maybe that logic of ביטול מצות יבמים bitul mitzvas
yevamim makes more sense only if there's some thing there that needed
to be transformed or affected and something wasn't done to it. So
that's what it's saying. We're now saying that Rabbi Meir holds אין
זיקה, ein zika, and the whole problem with the four brothers was
that the מצוה mitzvah on Leah might disappear, but if he holds
אין זיקה, ein zika, what do I care that the מצוה mitzvah
disappeared? ואי אין זיקה תיבטל. ve-ee ein zika tibatul. Now I'm going
to even demonstrate to you that these two ideas are linked, דהא
רבן גמליאל אמר אין זיקה. de-ha Rabban Gamliel amar ein zika. We're
going to have quoted in a minute a position of Rabban Gamliel
who says אין זיקה, ein zika, and we're also going to see
he's going to hold ומוטב לבטל מצות יבמים. u-mutav levatel mitzvas yevamim.
And at the same now he's not necessarily going to say they're
logically connected, but it just so happens he holds both אין זיקה
ein zika and you don't have to worry that the מצוה mitzvah
of יבום yibbum might disappear. What's the case? דתנן, de-tenan, we taught
in a משנה. Mishnah. רבן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Gamliel omer, אם מיאנה
מיאנה, im miana miana, if she did מיאון mi'un good, ואם לאו
תמתין עד שתגדיל ותצא הלזו משום אחות אשה. ve-im lav tamtin ad
she-tagdil ve-teitzei halazu mishum achos isha. And if she didn't do מיאון,
mi'un, wait until she grows up and that the other one get
be exempt because of אחות אשה. achos isha. So that's clear enough.
So what does that mean? It means like Reuben is married to
Rachel. Levi is married to Leah, the sister, except that Leah is
under age and Leah was married off by brother and mother, so
there's a case about מיאון, mi'un,
it's not a דאורייתא d'oraisa yet קידושין. kiddushin. Okay, and Leah's under
age, and then Reuben dies. So now what do we tell Levi
to do with Rachel? Do you say go ahead and do יבום?
yibbum? Okay, if he does יבום, yibbum, then he's married דאורייתא d'oraisa
to Rachel and then he's also has this דרבנן קידושין derabbanan kiddushin
with Leah which is אחות אשתו, achos ishto, right?
So what do we say you're supposed to do? Do you say
like, you know, have that, well maybe you do חליצה, chalitzah, but
A, maybe that's not giving the opportunity to do יבום, yibbum, and
B, there's already like you can flip it, you can say there's
like a quasi ערווה erva case around here, he's already quasi married
to Leah, so maybe Rachel should be looked at as ערווה erva
and he should be, right, and he should, I mean, not דאורייתא
d'oraisa but at least דרבנן. derabbanan. So how do you best deal
with this situation? So what Rabban Gamliel says is here's what he
says. First of all, if she does מיאון, mi'un, that's great. If
Leah decides, you know what, I'm going to do מיאון, mi'un, reject
the קידושין kiddushin retroactively, so there's a whole question about do we
advise her to do it? Okay, some say you דווקא davka advise
her. But if she does מיאון, mi'un, then retroactively he was never
married to Leah, he's free to go ahead and do יבום yibbum
with Rachel. Perfect. אם מיאנה מיאנה. im miana miana. ואם לאו, ve-im
lav, if she didn't, what do you do? He says, don't do
anything, don't, and תמתין עד שתגדיל, tamtin ad she-tagdil, wait until Leah
becomes an adult and then continue living with Leah, and he continues
living with Leah now it's קידושין דאורייתא, kiddushin d'oraisa, now they've had
sex with Leah of an adult it's קידושין דאורייתא, kiddushin d'oraisa, and
now Rachel turns into, once he's now married to Leah דאורייתא, d'oraisa,
Rachel becomes... ערווה, Erva, and now and then ערווה, Erva, you don't
have to do ייבום Yibum or חליצה, Chalitza, ותצא הלזו משום אחות
אשה, V'tetzei halazo mishum achos isha,
and then you know and then רחל Rachel can go free without
ייבום Yibum or חליצה Chalitza because she's now אחות אשתו. Achot Ishto.
Okay, why did the young underage one get precedence over the other
one?
You mean why isn't it do divorce her and then I mean
what are you asking?
No I'm saying that we say specifically if we wait around and
you know especially then somebody might be מבטל, mevatel, someone might die
meanwhile.
Well that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So let's
take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, okay? So this is what
he says.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so anyway so what do you see? But you see that רבן
גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds אין זיקה. Ein Zika. Now how do you
see רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds אין זיקה? Ein Zika? Because tell
me how you hold he holds אין זיקה. Ein Zika. Because while
you're waiting around for לאה Leah to grow up, okay, they are
still presumably okay sadly whatever they're having sex underage with underage girls
but he's still living with his wife לאה Leah there, his דרבנן
d'Rabbanan wife לאה Leah having sex with her while he hasn't done
anything with רחל Rachel while רחל Rachel is his זקוקתו, zikukaso, right?
So רחל Rachel is his זקוקתו zikukaso and he's still living with
לאה Leah waiting for לאה Leah to grow up. Why isn't that
a problem? Why isn't that an issue about אחות Achot you know
about about אחות זקוקתו? achot zikukaso? So you see that רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel holds אין זיקה. Ein Zika. He's not bothered by that.
At the same and what he also holds is as Michael just
said: Wait why do we let this relationship continue? That's going to
make the מצווה mitzvah with רחל Rachel go away. Well that's exactly
מבטל מצוות יבמין. mevatel mitzvas yabmin. Okay so what you're seeing is
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds two things. By allowing him to remain
married to לאה Leah he's not bothered by אחות זקוקתו, achot zikukaso,
he's not bothered with זיקה zika and he's not bothered that the
מצווה mitzvah of ייבום yibum with רחל Rachel will disappear. So you
see אין זיקה Ein Zika and logically should logically not be bothered
with מבטל מצוות
יבמין.
mevatel
mitzvas yabmin.
Are we waiting for לאה Leah to grow up to see whether
she's going to be ממאנת?
me'anes? No. No. No. Not waiting for it to be ממאנת. me'anes.
If at any time she decides to be ממאנת me'anes fine, she'll
go out of the picture and he can go ahead and do
and do ייבום yibum with רחל. Rachel. And if she grows up
and she's not ממאנת me'anes then they become married דאורייתא d'Oraisa and
then he doesn't have to do anything with רחל. Rachel.
But why did you throw in there that they're having relations already
while she's a קטנה? ketana?
To prove אין זיקה. Ein Zika. Because that's to show you that
we're not concerned about his relationship with רחל Rachel because he can
continue having sex with לאה Leah and we're not concerned about אחות
זקוקתו. achot zikukaso.
Is
the assumption here that is it the assumption here that they could
already be having relations?
Yes, I'm sorry to tell you but yes that is the assumption.
I'm sorry that you're sorry.
I just didn't see it in the words. Yes those are those
are not in the words, those are the assumptions. Okay, so anyway
the גמרא Gemara says like this: So you see רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel holds אין זיקה Ein Zika and similarly he's not bothered that
the מצווה ייבום mitzvah yibum goes away. It's like he doesn't give
weight to the potential and to what's going to happen if the
potential disappears. He just doesn't גורס goresh the whole thing so by
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir we should say the same thing. So גמרא
Gemara says, so אמר ליה, Amar lei, רבן גמליאל אדרבי מאיר קרמית?
Rabban Gamliel ad Rabbi Meir ka ramit? He said back, what are
you doing comparing רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel to רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir?
So what? So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel holds of those two things,
אין זיקה Ein Zika and we're not concerned of ביטול מצוות יבמין,
bittul mitzvas yabmin, but maybe those are not logically connected. Maybe רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir holds אין זיקה Ein Zika but it's אסור לבטל
מצוות יבמין. assur l'vatel mitzvas yabmin. So גמרא Gemara says: No. הכי
קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what I'm saying. Rabbi how does it
go from one extreme to the other? רבי מאיר חייש אפילו לספיקא.
Rabbi Meir chayish afilu l'sfeika. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is so concerned
of ביטול מצוות יבמין bittul mitzvas yabmin even in this you know
maybe maybe יששכר Yisachar will do ייבום yibum and then זבולון Zevulun
will die, you know it's not even a definite מצוות יבמין mitzvas
yabmin and he's still concerned about it. And רבן גמליאל אפילו לודאי
לא חייש. Rabban Gamliel afilu l'vadai lo chayish. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
isn't concerned even if it's definitely going to happen. לאה Leah is
going to grow up and the thing with רחל Rachel is definitely
going to go away and he's not concerned at all. So גמרא
Gemara says: Why not? דילמא מאן דלא חייש אפילו לודאי לא חייש?
Dilma man d'lo chayish afilu l'vadai lo chayish?
If you're not bothered with it you're not bothered with it at
all even if it's definitely going to happen like the case where
לאה's Leah going to grow up and it's going to disappear with
רחל. Rachel. ומאן דחייש, U'man d'chayish, and if you're concerned about it
like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, he doesn't like the מצווה mitzvah of
ייבום yibum to disappear, אפילו לספיקא חייש, afilu l'sfeika chayish, he'd even
be concerned in the יששכר זבולון Yisachar-Zevulun case: maybe he'll do this
and he'll die and whatever. So big deal, one person is concerned
with it and one person in even doubtful case the other is
not concerned at all. But what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
there's not necessarily a logical relationship with אין זיקה Ein Zika and
whether אסור assur or מותר לבטל מצוות יבמין. mutar l'vatel mitzvas yabmin.
But it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara thought they were related.
To the degree that זיקה zika is some type of a quasi-existing
relationship, אסור לבטל מצוות יבמין assur l'vatel mitzvas yabmin is you can't
take this existing relationship and just have it like you know not
do something to translate it, either translate it to ייבום yibum or
translate it to חליצה, chalitza, that that's the problem and therefore that's
connected to אסור לבטל מצוות יבמין. assur l'vatel mitzvas yabmin. And the
גמרא Gemara says it's not connected. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir might hold
אין זיקה Ein Zika but still not want the מצווה mitzvah of
ייבום yibum to disappear. Okay, so now we've dealt with different ברייתות.
braitot. that go one way or the other whether יש זיקה yeish
zika or אין זיקה, ein zika, clearly it is a debate in
the תנאים Tannaim and we clearly have a רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
who holds אין זיקה. ein zika. But we still have this debate
in the אמוראים Amoraim which way to go and the whole case
about marrying the mother when the שומרת יבם shomeres yavam dies. Okay
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר ליה אביי לרב
יוסף. Amar lei Abaye le-Rav Yosef. So אביי Abaye says to רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, הא דרב יהודה דשמואל היא. ha de-Rav Yehuda de-Shmuel
hi. This thing that he said about רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that
you can't marry the mother because of יש זיקה yeish zika when
the שומרת יבם shomeres yavam dies, that's really שמואל's Shmuel position. דתנן.
De-tenan. And now we're going to see the thing that we were
referring to before that I paraphrased for you. שומרת יבם שקידש אחיו
את אחותה, Shomeres yavam she-kiddesh achiv es achosah, top of י"ח עמוד
ב. Yud-Ches Amud Beis.
So this woman שומרת יבם shomeres yavam that now
so again ראובן Reuven was married to רחל, Rachel, ראובן Reuven dies.
Okay.
לוי Levi marries לאה. Leah. That's קידושין, kiddushin, not נישואין. nisu'in. Okay.
Now what's the story? So can he go ahead and do נישואין?
nisu'in? If he does נישואין nisu'in with לאה, Leah, he's going to
be having sex with אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. So משום רבי יהודה
בן בתירה אמרו, mishum Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira amru, in the name
of רבי יהודה בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira they said אומרים
לו, omrim lo, they say to לוי, Levi, המתן, hamtein, wait, don't
yet have sex with לאה, Leah, עד שיעשה אחיך מעשה, ad she-ya'aseh
achicha ma'aseh, let שמעון Shimon do יבום yibbum or חליצה chalitzah and
then you'll be free to go ahead and consummate the marriage. But
as long as שמעון Shimon is not, that would be a problem
of אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. Okay, so you see that's the position
right of two brothers, that was the case of two, even when
it's not זיקה zika was one and we're still saying יש זיקה
yeish zika and don't go ahead and do this, it'll be a
case of אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso. So ואמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יהודה
בן בתירה ve-amar Shmuel halacha ke-Rabbi Yehuda ben Beseira and שמואל Shmuel
says we rule like that. So when we were dealing with the
case about the woman dying and and and going ahead and marrying
the mother, here's another case about the sister and so on, but
you see your so your פסק psak about marrying the mother that
you gave that פסק psak in the name of רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda that it's אסור assur to marry the mother, that's really a
שמואל Shmuel position because שמואל Shmuel says in this case he can't
consummate the marriage with לאה Leah because of the זיקה. zika. Okay,
so that idea you רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said is really a
שמואל Shmuel position. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר ליה דאי דרב
המאי. amar lei de-ei de-Rav hamai. So big deal, so meaning when
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda normally says something, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda was
a תלמיד talmid of רב Rav and of שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, so
if you remember what we did is we started this whole issue
about marrying the mother, right if the שומרת יבם shomeres yavam died,
it started with a statement of I think it was רב הונא
אמר רב, Rav Huna amar Rav, I forgot who it was, רב
הונא אמר רב Rav Huna amar Rav that said it's מותר. muttar.
Then we had רב יהודה Rav Yehuda saying it's אסור. assur. Now
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda presumably got it either from רב Rav or
שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, so but רב יהודה Rav Yehuda said אסור. assur.
If he was saying in the name of רב Rav then it's
two, then it's a debate what was רב's Rav position. Okay, it's
a מחלוקת machlokes of the תלמידים talmidim what was רב's Rav position.
So what we're saying now is that thing that רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda said אסור, assur, that was actually שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav said
מותר, muttar, שמואל Shmuel said אסור assur and here you see that
שמואל Shmuel holds יש זיקה. yeish zika. Okay, so that's what he
says. The גמרא Gemara says so what do I care? I mean
let it be a different tradition in the name of רב. Rav.
What do I care if it's two traditions in the name of
רב Rav or one tradition in the name of רב Rav and
one in the name of
שמואל? Shmuel? Says דאי דרב מאי. de-ei de-Rav mai. So קשיא דרב
אדרב. kashya de-Rav a-de-Rav. You don't want רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda to
be a tradition in the name of רב Rav because then we'll
have competing statements of רב. Rav. So big deal. דתרי אמוראי נינהו
ואליבא דרב. de-trei amora'ei ninhu ve-aliba de-Rav. No, so what? So maybe
it's a debate what רב Rav held. So we had an initial
statement that said מותר muttar to marry the mother, another one אסור
assur to marry the mother. You're telling me the אסור assur is
a שמואל Shmuel position of יש זיקה. yeish zika. Let it be
a רב Rav tradition position, let it be a debate what רב
Rav said. So the גמרא Gemara said no, כיון דאיתמר משמיה דשמואל.
keivan de-is'mar mishmeih de-Shmuel. We don't like to say there are competing
traditions. So כיון דאיתמר משמיה דשמואל בהדיא, keivan de-is'mar mishmeih de-Shmuel ba-hadya,
since we have an explicit ruling in the name of שמואל Shmuel
that יש זיקה, yeish zika, so ומשמיה דרב כתרי אמוראי. u-mishmeih de-Rav
ke-trei amora'ei. An alternate to that we could say it's a debate
either it's a debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel or it's
a debate of what רב Rav two versions of what רב Rav
said. So לא שבקינן משמיה דשמואל בהדיא. lo shavkinan mishmeih de-Shmuel ba-hadya.
We don't abandon the position of saying that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
got it from שמואל Shmuel who we know that that's שמואל's Shmuel
position. So it's a debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel ומוקמינן
כתרי אמוראי אליבא דרב. ve-mokeiminan ke-trei amora'ei aliba de-Rav. We don't abandon
that to say that there's a debate about what רב Rav actually
said. Debates between different אמוראים Amoraim we know, but we'd rather that
that be than an actual sort of you know corruption of the
tradition or a loss of the tradition which is a debate of
what רב Rav actually said. So we have the two statements whether
you can or can't marry the mother. It could have been two
versions of what רב Rav says. We're saying it's a debate between
רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav says you can marry the
mother. שמואל Shmuel says you can't. שמואל Shmuel says יש זיקה yeish
zika and that's why you tell לוי Levi wait to consummate your
marriage with לאה Leah until we get רחל Rachel sort of dealt
with. Okay, and now we'll just wrap
this up, just do one more minute to get to the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay. אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, אמריתי לשמעתא Amrisi Lishmaysta
קמיה דרב זביד Kamei D'Rav Zvid מנהרדעא, Min Nahardea, I told over
this discussion in front of רב זביד Rav Zvid from נהרדעא. Nahardea.
אמר, Amar, he
said, אתון הכי מתניתו לה, Atun Hachi Masnisu Lah, that's how
you tell over this
discussion. אנן בהדיא
מתניתו לה, Anan Behedya Masnisu Lah, you
mean you said that there was a question whether רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda was saying it in the name of רב Rav or שמואל.
Shmuel. We have an explicit version that רב יהודה Rav Yehuda explicitly
said it in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, שומרת יבם שמתה אסור באמה, Shomeres
Yavam Shemesa Asur B'imah, that if she died you can't marry the
mother. אלמא קסבר יש זיקה, Alma Kasavar Yesh Zika, he holds יש
זיקה. Yesh Zika. ואזדא שמואל לטעמיה, V'asra Shmuel L'taimei, and he's consistent,
שמואל Shmuel with another position we know, another statement he knows he
says that says יש זיקה, Yesh Zika, דאמר שמואל הלכה כרב יהודה
בן בתירה. D'amar Shmuel Halacha K'Rav Yehuda Ben Beseira. We rule like
רב יהודה בן בתירה Rav Yehuda Ben Beseira that we tell לוי
Levi don't consummate it with לאה Leah until until your brother deals
with רחל. Rachel. וצריכי, V'tzrichi, and שמואל Shmuel had to say both
positions. אי אשמעינן יש זיקה, Ei Ashmeinan Yesh Zika, if he had
said יש זיקה Yesh Zika in the case of when she dies
and not marry the
mother, הני מילי בחד, Hani Mili B'chad, that's because there's only one
person around, so it's that's why don't marry the mother because there's
a real זיקה. Zika. אבל בתרי, Aval B'trei, in the case of
שמעון Shimon and לוי, Levi, לא, Lo, maybe it wouldn't be a
problem because maybe the זיקה Zika is with שמעון Shimon and let
לוי Levi consummate his marriage. קא משמע לן, Kamashma Lan, so it's
telling you we rule even in the שמעון Shimon and לוי Levi
case, don't consummate the marriage, there's זיקה Zika even when there are
two brothers
around. ואי אשמעינן הלכה כרב יהודה בן בתירה, V'ei Ashmeinan Halacha K'Rav
Yehuda Ben Beseira, had we just said that
פסק, Psak, so הני מילי בחיים, Hani Mili B'chaim, fine, there there's
זיקה Zika because רחל Rachel is still alive, so there's a live
זיקה, Zika, so therefore don't consummate the marriage with לאה. Leah. אבל
אחר מיתה, Aval Achar Misa, if the woman's dead and then פקע
ליה זיקה, Paka Lay Zika, then I would say there's no זיקה,
Zika, marry the mother. קא משמע לן דזיקה בכדי לא פקע, Kamashma
Lan D'zika Bichdi Lo Paka, זיקה Zika doesn't go away by itself.
So in the end we conclude, and this seems to be the
position of the גמרא, Gemara, that we say יש זיקה Yesh Zika
even in the most extreme cases. Meaning even after the woman has
died, זיקה Zika is still around, and even if there's multiple brothers
and only one of them is going to do יבום Yibum or
חליצה, Chalitzah, we still say there's זיקה Zika with all of the
brothers. Okay. Phew.