Good morning. Okay, so today's דף daf is כ"ז. Chaf Zayin. We
are very short, we are an עמוד amud behind, but a very
short עמוד. amud. So here's hoping we catch up. We pick up
at the very bottom of כ"ו עמוד א'. Chaf Vav Amud Aleph.
And we are discussing this משנה Mishnah here about the four brothers
and neither brother can do ייבום yibum because it's אחות זקוקתו, achot
zekukato, משנה Mishnah we've had a couple times. Each one does חליצה.
chalitzah. But then we had the alternative explanation of the משנה, Mishnah,
which is that the real problem is אסור לבטל מצות יבם. assur
levatel mitzvat yabam. That if לוי Levi goes ahead and does ייבום
yibum with רחל, Rachel, then we're afraid that יהודה Yehuda will die.
לאה Leah will wind up being אחות אשתו. achot ishto. She can't
get either חליצה chalitzah or ייבום, yibum, and therefore we have לוי
Levi do חליצה chalitzah so that even if יהודה Yehuda dies, לוי
Levi would still be able to go ahead and do חליצה chalitzah
with לאה. Leah. All right, so let's take a look now as
the גמרא Gemara picks up with that on the bottom of כ"ו
עמוד א'. Chaf Vav Amud Aleph. The גמרא Gemara says like this:
Two lines from the bottom. אי הכי I hachi if that's true,
says the גמרא, Gemara, that the concern is אסור לבטל מצות יבם,
assur levatel mitzvat yabam, תלתא נמי. telata nami. Why did it have
to give a case of four brothers? Why not give a case
of three brothers? If the issue was the issue problem of אחות
זקוקתו, achot zekukato, so we understand, yes, it's true with three brothers
as well, sure. לוי Levi can't do ייבום yibum with either woman
because of אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, he has to do חליצה chalitzah
with both women. Fine. But there's a חידוש chiddush of talking about
four brothers, because the זיקה zikah is weaker if there are two
brothers left behind. If both לוי Levi and יהודה Yehuda have a
זיקה, zikah, there's more of a reason to argue that it's not
a problem of אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato because it's not necessarily לוי's
Levi זיקה, zikah, not necessarily יהודה's Yehuda זיקה. zikah. So there's a
חידוש chiddush of four brothers that there's a problem of אחות זקוקתו
achot zekukato even with two brothers... even with two remaining brothers. But
if it's the idea of אסור לבטל מצות יבם, assur levatel mitzvat
yabam, then even with three it's a problem. Because let's say... because
then what will happen, then you don't even need the possibility that
יהודה Yehuda will die. Then לוי Levi shouldn't go ahead and do
ייבום yibum with רחל Rachel because he leaves לאה Leah out cold.
If he does ייבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, לאה Leah becomes אחות
אשתו achot ishto and no ייבום, yibum, no חליצה. chalitzah. So even
with three brothers the הלכה halakhah should be לוי Levi can't do
ייבום yibum because he'll be מבטל מצות יבם mevatel mitzvat yabam with
the other sister. So the גמרא Gemara says: אי הכי תלתא נמי?
I hachi telata nami? So the גמרא Gemara says: לא מבעיא קתני.
Lo miba'aya katan. You're right, but that's more obvious. לא מבעיא תלתא
דברי בטיל מצות יבם. Lo miba'aya telata de-bari batel mitzvat yabam. If
there are three and לוי's Levi the only one left behind, of
course he can't do ייבום yibum with רחל Rachel because לאה Leah
is left out. אלא אבל ארבע, Ella aval arba, but four, even
if לוי Levi does ייבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, most likely יהודה
Yehuda will still be alive to do either ייבום yibum or חליצה
chalitzah with לאה. Leah. So that's a חידוש chiddush that I'm concerned
that יהודה's Yehuda going to
drop dead.
אי הכי I hachi says the גמרא, Gemara, that's what's going on,
it's about אסור לבטל מצות יבם, assur levatel mitzvat yabam,
חמישה נמי? chamisha nami? So why don't you tell me, where's my
pen?
We got here יששכר. Yissachar. Okay, so why don't I say, what
about this case? Three are left behind. Can לוי Levi do ייבום?
yibum? לוי Levi will do ייבום yibum with רחל, Rachel, maybe יהודה
Yehuda and יששכר Yissachar will die. Okay, how far am I going
to go with it? So the גמרא Gemara finally says: No, you
know what, we're not going to go that far. למיתה דתרי לא
חיישינן. Lemita de-trei lo chayshinan. We're not going to be afraid that
two people will die.
Think of the odds, two people will drop dead at the same
time.
Exactly. So before any one of them gets a chance to do
ייבום yibum or חליצה. chalitzah. So yes, it's pretty far-fetched, it's concerned
that one of them will drop dead and then and then... I
mean, how big a deal is it that לאה Leah won't get
ייבום yibum or חליצה chalitzah if she winds up being freed from
the obligation anyway? But... exactly,
but anyway, we're only concerned that one will drop dead, not two.
So yes, it's obvious if there's only לוי, Levi, then לוי Levi
immediately loses the מצות יבם... mitzvat yabam... you know, the מצות יבם
mitzvat yabam goes away. Even if there's one around, we're afraid he'll
drop dead and then we'll lose that opportunity. But with two already
we won't be afraid. Okay.
I guess the גמרא Gemara is more concerned with men dropping dead
than women going free.
I just... Okay. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבה בר אבוה Rava
bar Avuna אמר רב: amar Rav: שלש אחיות יבמות שנפלו לפני שני
אחים יבמים. Shalosh achayot yevamot shenafelu lifnei shenei achim yevamim. Okay, so
back to two surviving brothers, except we have now three sisters. Okay,
I don't know who we're going to call רחל Rachel and לאה's
Leah sister.
בלהה? Bilhah? No, that's confusing.
Okay, anyway, whatever, we'll just call her שרה. Sarah. You okay? Fine.
Then you have... fine. Then you have down here יששכר Yissachar and
זבולון. Zebulun. Okay,
so we'll just for... Just pretend that all these three are sisters,
okay? שרה, Sarah, רחל Rachel and לאה's Leah sister.
Now, three, I'm sorry, so yes,
three sisters and right, so now they, and all of these guys
died and now you have two brothers and they have three sisters,
each of which they have a מצוה mitzvah to a זיקה zika
to a מצוה יבום mitzvah yibum to, right? And there's no ערוה
ervah because they were they're sisters to be sisters and they were
married to different men but to them none of them is אסור,
asur, okay? But any act of יבום yibum if you hold יש
זיקה yesh zika any act of יבום yibum is אחות זקוקתו. achos
zekukaso. So it's just a bigger case of אחות זקוקתו achos zekukaso
but that there's three women to deal with. So the question is
when there are two women we know what you do. One does
חליצה chalitzah with one, right, and one does חליצה chalitzah with the
other. Now let me just remind you why did when there were
two women why didn't
יששכר Issachar go ahead and do, actually it doesn't say that he
can't. Wait, what did it say? Hold on. It says הרי אלו
חולצות, harei elu chotzos, right? It doesn't say that they have to
do with who. הרי חולצות. harei chotzos. We haven't even discussed, that's
what we're going to get into, but in the case of let's
say two could יששכר Issachar do חליצה chalitzah with both? We don't
see why not, right? Why not let יששכר Issachar do חליצה chalitzah
with both? Okay, so
therefore, so but now we're going to see what the story is
going to be with this case and how it's going to divide.
Hold on, let me just make sure I'm getting this right. One
second. Give me one second. Why
can't
he do חליצה? chalitzah? Wait,
one second.
In principle,
right, one minute. In principle, now I'm getting confused. Actually we had
this, we had this, right? In principle in this case,
hold on a second.
One second. Remind, help me remember guys. In principle in this case
where you had two, right? Okay, we'll do יששכר Issachar and זבולון
Zebulun again. Okay.
Okay, so
יששכר Issachar does חליצה chalitzah with רחל, Rachel, right? So he cannot
do יבום yibum with לאה Leah because that would be אחות חלוצתו.
achos chalitzaso. And he can't do, and he can't do, and he
can't, so he does חליצה chalitzah with לאה. Leah. But why can't
זבולון Zebulun do יבום yibum with לאה? Leah? Right?
We talked about it.
Oh, he can. Oh, actually the point is is that if actually
רחל Rachel had חליצה chalitzah done first and then שמעון Shimon died,
then he can. Then it's not זיקתו zikaso or חלוצתו. chalitzaso. The
point is is that if both of them were around, well actually
anyway.
Except that he did at one point have
a זיקה, zika, but then the זיקה zika went away. Anyway we're
going to get back to that, okay? About that case that maybe
that you know to what degree maybe should לאה Leah be able
to do it with זבולון? Zebulun? Yeah, we actually had that, that
they flip over and they do it with the other ones. Right,
we actually had that. Okay, but so it's interesting therefore that our
משנה Mishnah says חולצות ולא מתייבמות chotzos velo mityabmos
because in theory there could be a way we actually had that,
that one does חליצה chalitzah and the other winds up doing יבום.
yibum. We've got to have that. Alright for some reason that's not
in the משנה, Mishnah, it just occurred to me that that's not
in the משנה. Mishnah.
Anyway, now we're dealing with it that you've got three.
Okay, so what's going to happen? So let's take a look. Alright,
so until now we don't know that it matters who's doing the
חליצה chalitzah and as I said it's even possible that if one
does the חליצה chalitzah the other might be able to do the
יבום, yibum, but let's take a look. Okay, אמר רבה בר אבונה
אמר רב amar Rabba bar Avuna amar Rav שלוש אחיות יבמות שנפלו
לפני שני אחים יבמים shalosh achayos yevamot shenafelu lifnei shnei achim yevamim
זה חולץ לאחת וזה חולץ לאחת ואמצעית צריכה חליצה משניהם.
zeh choletz leachas vezeh
choletz leachas ve'emtza'it tzericha chalitzah mishneihem.
So one gets חליצה chalitzah from one, one gets חליצה chalitzah from
the other and the middle one, which really means the last one,
not the middle one, gets the חליצה chalitzah from both of them.
Now the way we'll spell out our cases in the גמרא, Gemara,
the case is going to be that we're talking about that they
did it sort of before as they were dying, so whatever, I
don't mean literally as they were dying. Okay.
And the reason it's going to be sort of called, so here's
what happened, okay, and here's יששכר Issachar and זבולון. Zebulun.
So the גמרא Gemara will say as ראובן Reuven dies, so ראובן
Reuven dies, יששכר Issachar does חליצה chalitzah with רחל. Rachel.
Then שמעון Shimon dies and זבולון Zebulun does חליצה chalitzah with לאה.
Leah.
Or he could do the יבום.
yibum. Well yeah, that's what we were just discussing,
but for now those
were brothers, all five of them were brothers, okay?
Right, okay and they've
and then לוי Levi dies and then שרה Sarah needs חליצה chalitzah
from both of them. The reason she's called middle, תוספות Tosafot says
even though she's last, is in a way she's like in the
middle of יששכר. Issachar. And זבולון, Zebulun, okay? So she's like caught
between them and she gets חליצה chalitzah from both. So the question
is, why does she need חליצה chalitzah from both, and why is
there a preference that זבולון Zebulun does חליצה chalitzah to לאה Leia
and not יששכר? Issachar?
Why does she need חליצה? chalitzah?
We'll discuss, what do you mean why does she need חליצה chalitzah
at all?
Because they're all sisters.
You mean why can't she get יבום?
yibbum? No, why shouldn't she be פטורה peturah everything? Because it's... No,
because of אחות חלוצתו? achot chalutzato?
That's only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. No, they all
did חליצה chalitzah here. Okay, but anyway, so it's אחות חלוצתו, achot
chalutzato, but anyway the point is, why is there a preference for
זבולון Zebulun to do חליצה chalitzah to לאה Leia and why rather
than יששכר, Issachar, and why do both of them get... and why
does Sarah need חליצה chalitzah from both of them?
Wait, you just said that they do חליצה chalitzah to her, not
she does...
All right, all right, because that's because we're talking about who needs
to do it. All right, let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. So it's going to spell out what the logic is between
this. אמר ליה רבא. Amar lei Rava. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei
Rava, מדיקאמרת אמצעית צריכה חליצה משניהם, mideka'amret emtzait tzrichah chalitzah mishneihem, since
you're saying the middle, the last one, needs חליצה chalitzah from both
of them, קסבר יש זיקה, kasavar yesh zikah, presumably you hold the
problem here is יש זיקה. yesh zikah. Now the תוספות Tosafot are
saying, how do you know, maybe this could work within the idea
of מצווה לבטל מצות יבמין? mitzvah levatel mitzvat yevamin? We're not going
to unpack that. But this is working within the assumption of יש
זיקה. yesh zikah. והויא לה חליצה פסולה. Vahaveia lah chalitzah pesulah. And
now I understand what's bothering you. What's bothering you is that it's
an invalid חליצה, chalitzah, which doesn't mean invalid, it means like a
less than full חליצה, chalitzah, דחליצה פסולה צריך לחזור על כל האחים.
dechalitzah pesulah tzarich lachzor al kol ha'achim. And a less than full
חליצה chalitzah you need to get it from all the brothers, not
just one brother. So this is a new principle that you have
to know that's going to guide us throughout today's דף daf and
also we'll encounter in an ongoing way, which is an idea that
we know if there are six wives, right? Guy dies, six wives,
you do יבום yibbum or חליצה chalitzah with one of them, then
you're done. All of the other ones are free, right? Don't need
חליצה, chalitzah, don't need יבום, yibbum, you're not allowed to do יבום
yibbum with them. It's done once you do it with one wife.
Okay, but let's say for some reason there is a weaker זיקה
zikah with one of the women. Why would that be? So let's
take a scenario. Here's like a... here are some possible scenarios. One
is one of the wives of these six wives is אחות זיקתו.
achot zikkato. If she was really your wife's אחות אשתו, achot ishto,
then she'd be an ערוה ervah and everybody would be פטורה, peturah,
you'd go home. But she's not אחות אשתו, achot ishto, it's a
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. She's אחות זיקתו. achot zikkato. So with this one of
these six wives, you have a slightly weaker connection because דרבנן d'rabbananly
that's... it's problematic. In that type of a case, okay, if you
go ahead and do the חליצה chalitzah with that woman,
then she actually needs חליצה chalitzah from all the brothers because the
relationship with her... since the relationship is weaker... I shouldn't have introduced
the co-wives, I'm jumping into another case. But let's just take one
woman. ראובן Reuven dies here, take another woman.
Let's... we'll get back to the top of the board in a
minute. ראובן Reuven here is married to רחל. Rachel.
Okay, and there's לוי Levi and יהודה. Yehuda.
ראובן Reuven dies. If for some reason the זיקה zikah here is
a weaker זיקה, zikah, okay, then we say the act of חליצה
chalitzah from one brother doesn't totally free her. It... because the act
is weaker because the rel... it's a little ironic... because the relationship
is weaker, the חליצה chalitzah is also weaker and less meaningful, and
it has to be gotten from all the brothers. So what would
be a case that that relationship is weaker? So תוספות Tosafot summarizes
it nicely, if you look at the end of this תוספות Tosafot
here. דחליצה פסולה צריך לחזור. Dechalitzah pesulah tzarich lachzor. You see there's
a little ב bet about two-thirds down in that תוספות, Tosafot, a
little ב bet in square brackets. Do you see that?
Yep. Okay, אלא נראה לרי דלא חשיבא חליצה
פסולה אלא אחות זיקתו למאן דאמר יש זיקה.
Ella nira leRi
d'lo chashiva chalitzah pesulah ella achot zikkato leman d'amar yesh zikah. Okay,
either רחל Rachel here is an אחות זיקתו, achot zikkato, so for
some reason they've got some other woman here that... that you know
they've got לאה Leia here that they also have a זיקה zikah
to, so that makes רחל Rachel into an אחות זיקתו, achot zikkato,
not a real ערוה, ervah, but a
quasi-ערוה, ervah, quasi-אחות אשתו. achot ishto.
למאן דאמר יש זיקה. Leman d'amar yesh zikah. או אחות חלוצתו O
achot chalutzato or they did חליצה chalitzah to לאה, Leia, so רחל
Rachel is אחות חלוצתו achot chalutzato לכולי עלמא. lecholay alma. ובעלת
הגט ובעלת מאמר, U'ba'alat haget u'ba'alat ma'amar, and we'll see that in
a minute. Let's say for some reason, ironically, you already started the
process
of doing חליצה chalitzah with רחל. Rachel. Now, what does that mean,
started the process? You gave רחל Rachel a גט. get. Now, what
does a גט get mean? You're supposed to do חליצה. chalitzah. גט
Get isn't meaningful. But we're going to find out that if you
give a woman a גט get in the, you know, a woman
that you're supposed to do חליצה chalitzah and instead you give her
a גט, get, you make it impossible now to do יבום. yibbum.
It wasn't needed, nobody demanded it, but it has enough weight that
it... that it makes it impossible to do יבום. yibbum. You've gone
and you do חליצה chalitzah because חליצה chalitzah is the... דאורייתא, d'oraita,
גט get in this case is only rabbinic and wasn't even asked
for, but if you did it, so if they gave a גט
get to רחל, Rachel, right? Now the act, ironically the relationship is
weaker, they can't do ייבום. yibbum. Because the relationship is weaker, the
act of חליצה chalitza is now less meaningful. So in all those
cases, and we'll see more of them later, if there's a weaker
זיקה, zika, the act of חליצה chalitza is now less meaningful and
therefore she has to get it from all the existing brothers. Okay,
so that is the principle of
חליצה פסולה צריכה לחזור על כל האחין. chalitza psula tzarich lachzor al
kol ha'achin.
Okay, so now here's what we're going to say. So that's going
to explain why שרה Sarah needs a חליצה chalitza from both, because
what is שרה Sarah to each of them?
אחות חלוצתו. achot chalutzaso. Each one did חליצה chalitza with a different
woman. שרה Sarah is אחות
חלוצתו, achot chalutzaso, וחלוץ v'chalutz of זבולון Zevulun is לאה, Leah, so
she's אחות לאה. achot Leah. The חלוצה chalutzah of יששכר Yissachar is
רחל, Rachel, she's אחות רחל. achot Rachel. So she's אחות חלוצתו, achot
chalutzaso, she needs a חליצה chalitza from both. But then the גמרא's
Gemara question is: but why does רחל Rachel need a חליצה chalitza
from both? Because רחל Rachel is אחות זיקוקתו, achot zikukaso, right? So
she also has a weaker relationship and should need a חליצה chalitza
from both. So let's take a look. Okay, wait, no, no, we're
going to read it and then I'm just going to read two
more lines and then you'll ask your questions. Okay. אי
הכי, ei hachi, says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true, קמייתא נמי.
kamaisa nami. So רחל Rachel and לאה Leah should also need two
חליצות, chalitzas, because it's אחות זיקוקתו achot zikukaso for for all the
brothers. The גמרא Gemara says you know what? אי נפלה בבת אחת
הכי נמי. id naphal b'vas achas hacha nami. If ראובן, Reuven, שמעון,
Shimon, and לוי Levi all died at the same time, you're right,
then every woman is אחות זיקוקתו achot zikukaso and they each need
two חליצות. chalitzas. אבל הכא במאי עסקינן, aval hacha b'mai askinan, what
are we talking about, הכי נמי. hacha nami. לא צריכא דנפלה זו
אחר זו. lo tzricha d'naphal zo achar zo. So that's why I
laid it out for you, they died sequentially. So נפלה חדא חלץ
לה ראובן. naphla chada chalatz lah Reuven. So when... it's talking about
these here as ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, so I'm sorry about
that, let's keep the גמרא's Gemara nomenclature, we'll do that this is
יששכר, Yissachar, זבולון, Zevulun, and who? And נפתלי. Naphtali. Okay, fine. So,
okay, and this is ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so, חלץ...
chalatz... so the first guy died, so רחל, Rachel, total total obligation,
no other sister, full זיקה, zika, so that's a total חליצה, chalitza,
it's not a חליצה פסולה, chalitza psula, it's a complete חליצה. chalitza.
Now after that happened, then זבולון Zevulun died. So what's לאה? Leah?
So can ראובן... Reuven... what's לאה Leah to
ראובן? Reuven? אחות חלוצתו. achot chalutzaso. So vis-a-vis ראובן, Reuven, if ראובן
Reuven were to do חליצה, chalitza, it would be a חליצה פסולה.
chalitza psula. But what's she to שמעון? Shimon? Not אחות חלוצתו achot
chalutzaso and not אחות זיקוקתו, achot zikukaso, because the זיקה zika has
been removed. So therefore שמעון Shimon does it and she only needs
one because it's a completely acceptable חליצה chalitza that she got from
שמעון. Shimon. Okay, but then by the time now that נפתלי Naphtali
dies, שרה Sarah is אחות חלוצתו achot chalutzaso of both of them
and therefore any חליצה chalitza done to her is a חליצה פסולה
chalitza psula and therefore she needs to get it from all the
brothers. Okay,
so, לא צריכא דנפלה זו אחר זו. lo tzricha d'naphal zo achar
zo. נפלה חדא חלץ לה ראובן. naphla chada chalatz lah Reuven. נפלה
אידך, naphla idach, then the next one died, חלץ לה שמעון. chalatz
lah Shimon. So שמעון Shimon did חליצה chalitza with לאה, Leah, so
that was also completely okay. לאה Leah was not אחות חלוצתו, achot
chalutzaso, not אחות זיקוקתו, achot zikukaso, because רחל Rachel had already been
taken care of and so that was a total 100% חליצה. chalitza.
He could have even done ייבום, yibbum, we discussed, right? If he
wanted to, he could have done ייבום yibbum in that case. So
נפלה אידך, naphla idach, then finally the third one becomes available, whatever.
Then
חלץ להאי מפקע זיקתו חלץ להאי מפקע זיקתו. chalatz l'hai mapka zikaso
chalatz l'hai mapka zikaso. Each one has to do a חליצה chalitza
to remove the זיקה, zika, but each חליצה chalitza is a weaker
חליצה chalitza because it is a case of אחות חלוצתו achot chalutzaso
and that's why she needs it from both of them. Now, what
were the questions? Yeah, Isaac.
Did you mention a גט get from a זיקה zika bond?
Yeah, a גט get has a דרבנן d'rabanan effect that it prevents...
it doesn't free the woman, but it prevents... it prevents doing ייבום.
yibbum. So...
so for whatever reason if a man wanted to, I don't know
why, maybe the woman was anxious that he was going to do
ייבום yibbum and whatever he was, but decides to give a גט,
get, he locks out his possibility of doing ייבום. yibbum.
And then rather than doing חליצה... chalitza...
then he has to do חליצה, chalitza, right.
Oh then he does?
Yes, exactly, yeah. Yeah.
Just I want a restatement of זיקה. zika. So in other words
a זיקה, zika, she's אחות זיקוקתו achot zikukaso is a type of
ערווה, ervah, correct? דרבנן. d'rabanan. דרבנן, d'rabanan, yeah. So in normal cases
of ייבום yibbum or חליצה, chalitza, the wife normally would have been
an ערווה, ervah, the husband dies, the brother marries her.
You mean a standard אשת אח, eshet ach, yeah. Correct.
So just remind me why isn't the same principle operative?
Because that's the first משנה, mishna, the what the גמרא Gemara said,
which is although we're מתיר matir the איסור issur of... ערות אח,
ervas ach, all the other ערוות ervas create our obstacles, and that's
the first משנה, mishna, and that's why any other ערוה, ervah, she's
פטור patur and the צרות tzaros are פטור. patur.
So this is a spin-off
דרבנן d'rabonon of אחות אשה. achos isha.
The paradigm is still being developed.
Exactly. It's a type of an אחות אשה. achos isha. It's a
different ערוה. ervah. The ערוה ervah of אחות אשתו achos ishto is
the only one that יבום yibum takes care of. You had a
question.
You had to define חליצה פסולה chalitza pesula as
a
חליצה chalitza that takes place in a situation where there could not
be יבום. yibum.
So that is what רשי Rashi says. So if you look at
רשי, Rashi, רשי Rashi says, תוספות Tosafos is a little bit more
precise. רשי Rashi says
about eight lines, ten lines down in the narrow lines, the line
starting with the word
כלומר, klomar, רשי Rashi says: כלומר גרועה, ההוא פשוטה דמי פסולה, אבל
היא פירושו סקנד רייט, שאם רצה לייבם אינו יכול. Klomar gru'a, ha'u
pshuta de'mi psula, aval hi perusho second rate, she'im ratza l'yabem eino
yachol. Okay, so it's exactly what you said, Jonathan, that it means
in a case where יבום yibum is not possible. תוספות Tosafos says
that that's a little bit too broad of a definition. It's sort
of like, you know, what was it when Einstein came and corrected
Newton? Like it wasn't that Newton was wrong, it was just he
didn't, it was a little imprecise, okay? So, so yes, it's true
that all the cases of חליצה פסולה chalitza pesula is when יבום
yibum is impossible. But תוספות Tosafos says there are cases where יבום
yibum is impossible that we wouldn't call חליצה פסולה. chalitza pesula. So
it has to be a specific scenario that the reason יבום yibum
is impossible is because there's something weaker or that's been problematized about
the זיקה. zika. In that there could be a scenario where you
don't do it for other reasons and that wouldn't fall in this
category. Okay, but if it's easier to think about רשי'ס Rashi's reason,
that's a general, that's a general way to cover it, okay, but
it's a little imprecise. All right, so let's take a look now
as the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: והאמר רב v'ha'amar Rav and doesn't רב Rav say אין זיקה?
ein zika? How could this whole thing is explained now because of
this idea of חליצה פסולה צריך לחזור על כל האחין? chalitza pesula
tzarich lachzor al kol ha'achin? It must have to do with an
issue of זיקה zika and אחות זקוקתו ואחות חלוצתו. achos zekukaso v'achos
chalutzaso. But רב Rav is the one who says it and רב
Rav says אין זיקה, ein zika, that we're not afraid, we don't
worry about זיקה zika and we don't worry about, meaning obviously there
is, but we don't call, create problems like אחות זקוקתו. achos zekukaso.
So he wouldn't have any of those issues. So the גמרא Gemara
says: פשיטא לדידי אמר יש זיקה קאמר. Pshita l'didi amar yesh zika
ka'amar. Okay, he was saying according to the person who says יש
זיקה, yesh zika, maybe this is not his personal approach, but according
to that approach, that would be the הלכה halacha here. Fine, that's
רב'ס Rav's position. ושמואל אמר, u'Shmuel amar, now what does שמואל Shmuel
say you do in this scenario?
אחד חולץ לכולן. echad choleitz l'kulan. שמואל Shmuel says I don't buy
any of this, let ראובן Reuven go ahead and do חליצה chalitza
to all three women. Okay? So he presumably does not hold of
the problem of חליצה פסולה, chalitza pesula, right? Because ראובן, Reuven, as
soon as זבולון Zevulun dies, לאה Leah is אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzaso.
He says: who cares? Let him do it. Then נפתלי Naftali dies,
שרה Sarah is אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzaso. Let ראובן Reuven do it.
You don't prefer, a) you don't have to go to all the
other brothers, and b) you don't prefer the stronger חליצה, chalitza, you
can even do the weaker חליצה. chalitza. You okay? You understand? It's
weaker because it's, it's been problematized for ראובן Reuven and not for
שמעון. Shimon. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, that's שמואל. Shmuel. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this: מכדי, Michdi, one minute, let's take
a look. שמעינן ליה לשמואל דאמר חליצה מעליא בעינן. Shami'inan lei l'Shmuel
d'amar chalitza ma'alya ba'inan. We know that שמואל Shmuel normally says you
need a good חליצה. chalitza. Now of course everybody says you need
a good חליצה, chalitza, but again it means a, you need a
higher rate חליצה. chalitza. If you can choose between a, what רשי
Rashi called a גרועה, gru'a, a second-rate חליצה, chalitza, or a first-rate
חליצה, chalitza, you'll always prefer the first rate, okay? And here, as
soon as זבולון Zevulun dies, even forget the idea of צריך לחזור
על כל האחין. tzarich lachzor al kol ha'achin. Forget צריך לחזור. tzarich
lachzor. Let's assume only one חליצה. chalitza. Whose חליצה chalitza would you
rather לאה Leah get? ראובן'ס Reuven's חליצה chalitza or שמעון'ס Shimon's חליצה?
chalitza? שמעון'ס Shimon's חליצה chalitza is first rate because שמעון'ס Shimon's relationship
is a full, he could do יבום. yibum. So, whereas ראובן Reuven
couldn't do יבום, yibum, it's אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzaso. So even forgetting
how many חליצות chalitzos you need, shouldn't we prefer a first-rate חליצה
chalitza over a second-rate? And we know that שמואל Shmuel holds that.
How do you know that שמואל Shmuel holds that?
דאמר שמואל d'amar Shmuel ת"ב ע"א. Taf-Beis Amud Alef. See that? Only
those three lines only took half an hour. דאמר שמואל חלץ לאחיות
לא נפטרו צרות. d'amar Shmuel chalatz l'achayos lo nifteru tzaros. Okay, so
you have a case of, okay, this is what I was getting
a little bit confused with before. You have a case of,
okay,
again let's use ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon as the surviving brothers,
okay? So you have a case of, he's married to רחל Rachel
and he's married to לאה, Leah, and רחל Rachel also has a
co-wife called דבורה, Devorah, and she has a co-wife called, what should
she be called? נעמי. Naomi. Thank you. Somebody from a different section
of תנך. Tanakh. Okay. So, okay, so basically, so those two,
and there's only one other guy left, ראובן. Reuven. Okay, we don't
have to worry about two brothers. These two guys die. Okay, so
here's the הלכה. Halakha.
חלץ לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות. halotz la'achayot lo nifteru tzarot. If Reuven,
can Reuven do, let's start this way, these four women that are
in front of Reuven, can he do יבום yibbum with Rachel?
No, because Rachel is אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, right? And he can't
do יבום yibbum with Leah. Now, can he do יבום yibbum with
Devorah? Well, it's a little bit better, but if we're going to
call אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato sort of like אחות אשתו, achot ishto,
then she's going to be like sort of like צרה... tzara... no,
צרת ערווה, tzarat ervah, right? Okay, but it is one degree removed.
This is already a quasi, you know, ערווה, ervah, and this is
one degree removed. So even though he can't do יבום yibbum with
Devorah, his relationship with Devorah is stronger than his relationship with Rachel.
Okay, so in this case, if he were to do חליצה chalitzah
with Rachel, which is the weaker חליצה, chalitzah, that's the סוג ב,
sug bet, okay, second rate חליצה, chalitzah, Devorah doesn't get off the
hook. But because it was only a second rate חליצה. chalitzah. But
if he did the חליצה chalitzah with Devorah, which is a relatively
first rate, not א-א, alef-alef, okay, it's a better חליצה, chalitzah, then
Rachel does get off the hook. So that shows that there's a
preference for a first rate over a second rate and a first
rate is more powerful. A first rate will get the co-wife off
the hook whereas a second rate will not. And therefore, we should
assume that he was here, Reuven should not, we should not allow
the second rate חליצה, chalitzah, we should demand the first rate.
So חליצה chalitzah with Devorah would be stronger because Reuven's connection to
Devorah is weaker.
No, because the איסור issur to Devorah is weaker.
Right, the איסור issur is weaker.
Right. So the connection is stronger. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
דאורייתא De-Oraita makes its sense.
דאורייתא De-Oraita makes its sense. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says חלץ
לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות. halotz la'achayot lo nifteru tzarot. So therefore, but
the reverse would be if it was חלץ לצרות נפטרו אחיות. chalatz
litzrot nifteru achayot. So the weaker חליצה chalitzah is less powerful. And
if the weaker חליצה chalitzah is less powerful, here Shimon should be
the one doing חליצה chalitzah to Leah. We shouldn't let Reuven do
חליצה chalitzah to Leah.
That's a weaker חליצה. chalitzah. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
היכא דקיימא חליצה דשמעון חליצה כשרה חליץ ליה ראובן חליצה פסולה? Heicha
de-kaima chalitzah de-Shimon chalitzah kesherah chalitz leh Reuven chalitzah pesulah? So if
Shimon could do a top rate חליצה, chalitzah, we're going to let
Reuven do a second rate חליצה? chalitzah? So the גמרא Gemara says
alright, that was a pretty good question. So when שמואל Shmuel said
we're going to reread שמואל Shmuel radically and then we're going to
go back to the original reading. Okay, but here's first the radical
reread of שמואל. Shmuel. When שמואל Shmuel said one brother does חליצה
chalitzah to all of them, when he said מאי אחד חולץ לכולן
נמי דקאמר אהן צד, mai echad choletz lekulan nami dekamar a-han tzad,
he didn't really mean one brother does it to all, does it
with all of them. What he meant was that he was just
arguing on the idea that צרה tzara needed two חליצות. chalitzot. Okay,
so he agrees, Reuven did it with Rachel, Shimon did חליצה chalitzah
with Leah. But when he says one brother does it with all,
he didn't mean all-all. He meant by the time you get to
Sarah, one brother is enough, you don't need it from both brothers.
Okay, so he's just arguing on the idea that you could ever,
that you would ever need it from multiple brothers. Okay, so he
was saying yes, here you prefer the higher level חליצה, chalitzah, but
by the time you get to Sarah and either brother is going
to give her a סוג ב sug bet חליצה, chalitzah, she doesn't
need it from both, one brother is enough. Okay, so that's all
he was arguing on. You don't need it from both, one brother
is enough. So the, that's not what he said and that's what
the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay. והא כולן קאמר? Ve-ha
kulan ka'amar? It says one brother does it for all of them,
and you're just saying Shimon just did it for the last two.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, כיון דרובא גביה, keivan deruba gabeih,
since Shimon did it for two out of the three, קרי ליה
כולן. kari leh kulan. Okay, fine. Okay. Now that's a weak answer,
but at least what it has you doing is saying that שמואל
Shmuel might be debating the idea that if you get a סוג
ב sug bet חליצה chalitzah you need it from all the brothers,
and maybe he's just saying no, you know, maybe just one brother
is enough. That's one reread of שמואל. Shmuel. But now we're going
to go back to the original read, that Reuven can do it
with all of them. איבעית אימא, Iba'it eima, if I want I'll
say, כי קאמר שמואל חליצה מעליא בעינן, ki ka'amar Shmuel chalitzah ma'alya
beinun, when does שמואל Shmuel say in this case that you need
the, you know, top grade חליצה chalitzah in order to get Devorah
off the hook? Right, this is a סוג ב sug bet חליצה
chalitzah and this is a סוג א sug alef חליצה, chalitzah, and
you need the סוג א sug alef חליצה chalitzah here. The סוג
א sug alef חליצה chalitzah gets Rachel off the hook, the סוג
ב sug bet does not get Devorah off the hook. So he
clearly prefers the סוג א sug alef חליצה. chalitzah. So when is
that true? כי קאמר שמואל חליצה מעליא בעינן הני מילי למפטר צרתה.
Ki ka'amar Shmuel chalitzah ma'alya beinun hanei mili limftar tzartah. Yes, if
you need to get a co-wife off the hook, then top grade
חליצה chalitzah is needed. אבל למפטר נפשה פטרה, Aval limftar nafshah patrah,
for it to be effective for the woman
herself, that's enough to have even a second grade חליצה. chalitzah.
So שמואל Shmuel does not get
the top grade, so שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel does not say that
you always must do the top-grade חליצה. chalitzah. שמואל Shmuel says a
lower-grade חליצה chalitzah doesn't get the co-wife off the hook. The top-grade
חליצה chalitzah gets the co-wife off the hook. But here שמואל Shmuel
says, you know what? שמעון Shimon can go ahead and do all
three. Okay? Yes. Is this a- is this a second-grade חליצה chalitzah
to לאה? Leah? Sure. But לאה Leah doesn't have any co-wives. Okay?
So שמואל Shmuel actually says, I don't have a problem with a
second-grade חליצה chalitzah as long as there are no co-wives. So he
can do it here and then yes you could have had a
better חליצה chalitzah here but let him do the second-grade חליצה chalitzah
and everybody's fine. We have him saying two things. A, you can
use the second-grade חליצה chalitzah even if you have a- you can-
you can allow for that even if you have the option of
a top-grade. And B, he doesn't hold חליצה פסולה צריך להחזיר על
כל האחים. chalitzah psulah tzarich lehachazir al kol ha'achim. That's even the
bigger חידוש, chidush, right? Which is that even though he's doing weaker
חליצות, chalitzas, it's enough to get it from one brother, you don't
have this idea of getting it from all the brothers. Okay? So
that's the major debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav
says, you need it from all brothers.
Okay? And שמואל Shmuel says, you just need it from one. What
do you do about the second-grade חליצה? chalitzah? Second-grade, not- not like
as opposed to third-grade. Okay, second-grade חליצה.
chalitzah. Okay.
רב Rav says you need it from all brothers and שמואל Shmuel
says you just need it from one. And because- and שמואל Shmuel
goes so far to say, I'll- I'll allow you to do a
second-grade even if you have a first-grade available.
And שמואל Shmuel is the bigger
חידוש, chidush, but I mean the whole- okay, רב Rav is the
bigger חידוש. chidush. We started with רב, Rav, so שמואל Shmuel is
the חידוש chidush now that he's rejecting that. Fine.
Okay. Fine. I agree with you. רב Rav is really the חידוש.
chidush. Okay. Now. גופא. Gufa. Yes.
There's a note here that- that רש"י Rashi says רב Rav stated
this just- right? And there's the note from ברטנורא Bartinura says רב
Rav himself, however, he holds אין זיקה. ain zika.
Oh yeah, yeah. The גמרא Gemara says that we know that רב
Rav in another place holds אין זיקה. ain zika. So if you
hold אין זיקה, ain zika, then all of the assumptions here are
different because you don't even start with a case of אחות זקוקתו.
achos zekukaso. Okay, so alright, whatever. That's why it's a footnote. Let's
not let that bother us. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay. גופא. Gufa. Let's go back to what we said.
אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, חלץ לאחיות לא נפטרו צרות.
chalatz leachayot lo
niftru tzarot. Okay? לצרות נפטרו אחיות. Letzarot niftru achayot. So we're back
to this case. You do it with רחל, Rachel, doesn't get דבורה
Devorah off the hook. You do it with דבורה, Devorah, gets רחל
Rachel off the hook. And the same is true with זבולון's Zevulun's
wives. Okay.
Okay. חלץ לבעלת הגט לא נפטרה צרה.
chalatz lebaalas haget lo
niftra tzara. לצרה נפטרה בעלת הגט. Letzara niftra baalas haget. Let's say
it were not a case- the reason this was problematic was not
because רחל Rachel was- and here's where we're getting other scenarios of
חליצה פסולה, chalitzah psulah, other scenarios of second-grade חליצות. chalitzas. Okay? One
was it was רחל Rachel was weaker because it was אחות זקוקתו.
achos zekukaso. The other case is that ראובן- Reuven and I really
need color markers- that ראובן, Reuven, this was the case, and ראובן
Reuven went ahead and before any this, he gave her a גט.
get. I'm a little dyslexic today. He gave her a גט. get.
Okay? Which means that now רחל's- Rachel's his relationship to רחל Rachel
is weaker, ironically, because he's already started the process as it were,
but he has to do חליצה chalitzah with רחל, Rachel, he can't
do יבום. yibum. So it's the same idea. If she's a בעלת
הגט, baalas haget, then it's a second-grade חליצה chalitzah to her, so
it won't get דבורה Devorah off the hook, but with דבורה Devorah
he has a totally fine relationship with, or full relationship with, so
the חליצה chalitzah with דבורה Devorah will get רחל Rachel off the
hook. Same idea, except in- as opposed to אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukaso,
it's a case of בעלת הגט. baalas haget. חלץ לבעלת הגט chalatz
lebaalas haget lo niftra tzara. לצרה נפטרה בעלת הגט. Letzara niftra baalas
haget. Now, how about a third case? How about חלץ לבעלת מאמר?
chalatz lebaalas maamar? As opposed to a גט get here, ironically, he
did something that you would say would strengthen the relationship. He did
מאמר. maamar. מאמר maamar is קידושין. kiddushin. He actually gave her a
ring, he said הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li. הרי
את מומרת לי?
Harei at mumeret li?
Yeah, I don't know what he said. Okay. Whatever he said. Okay.
Anyway. Okay. But she's still not his wife because he hasn't done
יבום. yibum. It- with a normal woman it would have worked, in
this case it doesn't, but it's the first stage, it's the דרבנן
de-rabbanan קידושין kiddushin that precedes the דאורייתא, de-oraisa, you know, נישואין nissuin
if you want, יבום. yibum. Okay, so it's a stronger relationship with
רחל. Rachel. But ironically, anytime you sort of move off the center,
you, you know, change the parameters. Because רחל Rachel is now more
his wife, חליצה's chalitzah's less relevant. Right? Do you understand that logic?
No, he can do חליצה, chalitzah, but he actually now has to
do both חליצה chalitzah and a גט. get. Once you do מאמר,
maamar, you even need a גט get to- to negate the מאמר
maamar and חליצה chalitzah to negate the זיקה. zika. But the point
is, because he is now seen as quasi his wife, because he
strengthened the זיקה, zika, חליצה chalitzah is less relevant because if she
were fully his wife, you can't do חליצה chalitzah to your wife,
you only do חליצה, chalitzah, right? So whenever the sister-in-law moves off
the center, right, either because she becomes more distant to him, so
חליצה chalitzah is like she's quasi an ערווה, ervah, חליצה's chalitzah's not
relevant by an ערווה, ervah, or she becomes more close to him
and therefore she's quasi his wife, while חליצה's chalitzah's now less relevant.
for a wife. So anytime the זיקה zika changes, interestingly, either when
it gets weaker or even gets stronger, but it makes חליצה chalitza
less relevant, we get to a case of considering a second grade
חליצה, chalitza, a חליצה פסולה, chalitza pesula, okay? So let's just read
this.
Do you need to get and...
so right, Rachel in this case would need a גט get and
חליצה, chalitza, and even if she basically did that, gave her גט
get and... well actually it's interesting too, if he gave her the
גט get first and then the חליצה, chalitza, would at that stage
the חליצה chalitza have moved up to a first grade? Probably not,
because then it would be she would be sort of like גרושתו
gerushato and whatever, I don't think that matters, okay? So in this
case again, because the because her status has shifted and it's not
the classic one, it's a weaker חליצה, chalitza, and this חליצה chalitza
doesn't exempt the צרה. tzara.
Do you need to do גט get and חליצה chalitza all the
time now?
I don't know, whatever. Okay, so it says like this, let's read
that. חלץ לבעלת המאמר לא נפטרה צרה לצרה נפטרה בעלת המאמר. Chalatz
le-ba’alat ha-ma’amar lo niftra tzara לצרה נפטרה בעלת המאמר le-tzara niftra ba’alat
ha-ma’amar. Okay, so let's just read the גמרא Gemara so there was
some questions, but let's have the גמרא Gemara clarify this for us
a little bit. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
one moment, I just want to check רש"י Rashi for one second.
Yeah, so רש"י Rashi says,
by the way, to answer Michael's question, that the case was you
did חליצה chalitza to Rachel, רש"י Rashi describes it before you gave
the גט. get. So רש"י Rashi doesn't spell out the exact thing,
I'd have to check, but רש"י Rashi implies that if he had
already given the גט get to Rachel things might... except no, actually
not, because then it's going to become... then she'll be a בעלת
הגט. ba’alat ha-get. Okay, anyway, so I don't know, it could... probably
it doesn't matter, probably if he did it before then she's more
as his wife, if he did it after the גט get then
she's a בעלת הגט. ba’alat ha-get. But anyway רש"י Rashi describes the
scenario here when there has not been a גט get given. There
was a מאמר ma’amar and then a חליצה chalitza immediately followed. Okay,
so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי שנא לאחיות,
Mai shena le-achyot, what's the difference when the case you had sisters
and Rachel's problem was it was אחות זקוקתו achot zekukato דלא נפטרו
צרות de-lo niftru tzarot דהוו להו אחות אשה בזיקה, de-havu lehu achot
isha be-zika, interesting. Before we had the phrase אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato,
here framing it a little differently. But when there was the whole
other case about you know the other sister, so it was a
weaker, it was a weaker חליצה chalitza because it was אחות זקוקתו,
achot zekukato, so חלץ לצרות נמי לא יפטרו אחיות chalatz le-tzarot nami
lo yiftru achiyot דהוו להו צרת אחות אשה בזיקה. de-havu lehu tzarat
achot isha be-zika. So the גמרא Gemara says he can't do יבום
yibum with Deborah, right? Whatever problem he had with Rachel because now
she's like a quasi ערווה, ervah, אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, okay, so
Deborah is צרת אחות זקוקתו, tzarat achot zekukato, she's צרת ערווה, tzarat
ervah, okay point is okay but it's one degree removed. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says קסבר שמואל אין זיקה.
kasavar Shmuel ein zika. So
now
everything we've been explaining has been assuming that שמואל Shmuel holds יש
זיקה, yesh zika, right? And that's why all these cases of אחות
זקוקתו achot zekukato and blah blah blah blah blah and it's a
סוג ב, sug bet, etc. Now we're saying שמואל Shmuel holds אין
זיקה. ein zika. Of course if שמואל Shmuel holds אין זיקה, ein
zika, then go ahead and do יבום yibum with Rachel, okay? So
let's take a look. קסבר שמואל אין זיקה והאמר שמואל יש זיקה?
Kasavar Shmuel ein zika ve-ha-amar Shmuel yesh zika? Yeah, okay, לדידיה הוא
דאמר אין זיקה. le-dideih hu de-amar ein zika. Oh, this is within
the idea of אין זיקה. ein zika. Of course, אי הכי חלץ
לאחיות אמאי לא נפטרו צרות? ei hachi chalatz le-achyot amai lo niftru
tzarot? So if that's true, okay, so now we're getting back not
to the case of מאמר ma’amar and גט get but to the
case of sisters.
Okay, and this case Rachel we were saying was אחות זקוקתו achot
zekukato and therefore, but then we said if she's אחות זקוקתו, achot
zekukato, she's צרת אחות זקוקתו, tzarat achot zekukato, there's no difference. So
we're saying fine, there's no זיקה. zika. Okay, there's no זיקה, zika,
what's the problem? For God's sake, if there's no זיקה, zika, just
go ahead and do יבום. yibum. I mean maybe it's אסור לבטל
מצות יבמין, assur le-vatel mitzvat yevamin, but what how does that make
one woman even if it's אסור לבטל מצות יבמין, assur le-vatel mitzvat
yevamin, it's not about one woman being more problematic than the other,
just don't do certain things because then you won't have the opportunity
for יבום. yibum. So if that's true that there's no זיקה, zika,
why should there be any difference in terms of the type of
חליצה chalitza you're doing? So let's take a look. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
So אי הכי חלץ לאחיות אמאי לא נפטרו צרות?
ei hachi chalatz le-achyot amai
lo niftru tzarot? בשלמא צרה דרחל לא תפטר, Bishlama tzara de-Rachel lo
tiftar, I get why Rachel's צרה tzara doesn't get off... actually I
keep on doing using the different nomenclature than the גמרא Gemara just...
the גמרא Gemara assumes that Leah... is the one that actually becomes
available first. Okay?
Presumably, I don't know, maybe because לאה Leah was the one that
was married first in the תורה. Torah. Okay, so anyway, the גמרא
Gemara says like that: I get why רחל's Rachel צרה, tzara, okay
let's read this, oh let's read this, hold on.
בשלמא Bishlama where am I?
צרה דרחל לא תפטר. Tzara d'Rachel lo tiftar. I get why רחל's
Rachel צרה tzara doesn't get off the hook with the חליצה chalitza
of
רחל, Rachel, דכיון דחלץ ללאה והדר חלץ לרחל הויא ליה חליצה דרחל
חליצה פסולה. Dechivan dechalatz l'Leah v'hadar chalatz l'Rachel hava lei chalitza d'Rachel
chalitza psula.
Okay, so what happened? This was the order it happened.
And ראובן Reuven first went ahead and let's assume he did חליצה
chalitza with לאה Leah first, okay, and then now זבולון Zevulun dies,
okay. So, if he were to do what's רחל Rachel to him
right now?
אחות חלוצתו. Achos chalutzaso. So in this scenario, even if you hold
אין זיקה, ein zika, there is still a reality of חליצה chalitza
here. And therefore רחל Rachel is אחות חלוצתו achos chalutzaso and נעמי
Naomi is a little bit better, okay.
So therefore she's not a package deal and even if you hold
אין זיקה
ein zika well okay, so that's the question: why not also ask
this? צרת אחות זקוקתו? Tzaras achos zekukaso? Fine, whatever. But it's a
question that the גמרא Gemara could get to. But let's hold off
for that right now, okay? Anyway, here I can at least understand
why רחל Rachel is אחות חלוצתו achos chalutzaso and more problematic than
נעמי. Naomi. But at this stage, even if these guys have both
died at the same time and certainly if they died sequentially, right?
What's לאה Leah to him? Nothing. So why doesn't the חליצה chalitza
of לאה Leah get דבורה Devorah off the hook, right? If you
don't if you hold אין זיקה, ein zika, then at before any
act has been done, everybody is on an equal footing. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So אלא צרה דלאה תפטר. ela tzara deLeah tiftar. So let לאה's
Leah צרה tzara get off the hook if you say
אין זיקה. ein zika. גמרא Gemara says no. מאי לא נפטרו צרות
נמי דקאמר צרה דרחל.
Mai lo nifteru tzaros
nami deka’amar tzara d'Rachel. He didn't mean that the צרות tzaros don't
get off the hook. He meant the second צרה tzara doesn't get
off the hook. רחל's Rachel צרה tzara doesn't get off the hook.
גמרא Gemara says והא צרות קאמר. V’ha tzaros ka’amar. He says the
צרות tzarot in plural don't get off the hook. So okay, another
one. No. So he says והא צרות קאמר. V’ha tzaros ka’amar. So
it says צרות דעלמא, Tzaros d’alma, it means צרות tzaros in these
types of cases don't get off the hook, but only the second
one. The first one is fine. אי הכי חלץ לצרות נפטרו אחיות?
Ei hachi chalatz l’tzaros nifteru achayos?
One minute. It says if you do חליצה chalitza on the צרות
tzaros the אחיות achayos get off the hook.
וצרת רחל
מי מפטרא? V'tzaras Rachel mi miftera? But one minute, how
is
ah but how does the צרה tzara of רחל Rachel get off
the hook? So why והתנן, v’hasnan, we taught
in the משנה, Mishna, אסור אדם בצרת קרובת חלוצתו. Assur adam b'tzaras
krovos chalutzaso. Okay. So a person, we're not even going to try
to understand why this is true right now, we'll just accept it.
A person is not allowed to marry a man is not allowed
to marry the צרה tzara of his חלוצה's chalutza relative. So what
does this mean? I have to remind myself. So רש"י Rashi says,
one minute, yeah, yeah, one minute, one minute,
one minute.
So רש"י Rashi says, one minute. So okay, so in this case
here, so you're saying in this case, go ahead and ראובן Reuven
do חליצה chalitza now with נעמי, Naomi, okay, because רחל Rachel is
אחות חלוצתו, achos chalutzaso, that's how we've explained it. Do חליצה chalitza
with נעמי, Naomi, and רחל Rachel will get off the hook, okay?
But but that's what we're saying. Okay, because רחל Rachel is more
problematic, אחות חלוצתו, achos chalutzaso, do it with נעמי. Naomi. But we've
got a problem. What's the problem? אסור אדם בצרת קרובת חלוצתו. Assur
adam b'tzaras krovos chalutzaso. Let's read the רש"י Rashi together. Second wide
line here or middle-sized line. רש"י Rashi says: ואפילו לא היתה צרתה
מאחיו אלא מנכרי. v'afilu lo haysa tzartah me'achiv ela minachri. So some
other guy is married
to your
קרובת חלוצתו. krovos chalutzaso. You did חליצה chalitza to I don't even
know where it goes.
Use it for לאה. Leah. You married her mother?
You did חליצה chalitza okay, right, exactly. זבולון, Zevulun, right, forget right,
exactly. So let's forget right now, let's ignore, thank you, we'll use
this scenario. We'll ignore right now what happened to זבולון, Zevulun, okay?
He did חליצה chalitza to לאה. Leah. Now you have somebody else
here, ברק, Barak, okay, is married to is married to
no,
is married to לאה's Leah mother, okay? Let's say רבקה, Rivka, we'll
make רבקה Rivka לאה's Leah mother. He's married to רבקה, Rifka, לאה's
Leah mother, okay. ראובן, Reuven, so who's רבקה Rifka to him? רבקה
Rifka to him is קרובת חליצתו. krovat chalitzato.
Okay,
now, ברק Barack also happens to be married to דבורה. Devora. And
then ברק Barack dies. Now his brother, he is not allowed to
marry דבורה, Devora, because דבורה Devora is צרת קרובת חליצתו. tsoras krovat
chalitzato. Okay, I'm not even going to begin to explain why that
should be a problem, but that's the problem. So if we say
that's the problem, how can we say here that all he's got
to do is do חליצה chalitza to נעמי Naomi and then he's
מותר mutar to רחל? Rachel? רחל Rachel is... נעמי Naomi is... wait
a minute...
נעמי Naomi is צרת קרובת חליצתו,
tsoras
krovat chalitzato, right? רחל Rachel is קרובת חליצתו, krovat chalitzato, that's צרת
קרובת חליצתו. tsoras krovat chalitzato. Oh, so נעמי Naomi is just as
problematic to him as רחל Rachel is. Why do we say רחל?
Rachel? רחל Rachel is אחות חליצה, achos chalitza, שכח, shkoyach, נעמי Naomi
is קרובת אחות חליצה, krovat achos chalitza, which is just generally problematic.
It's a third-way problem. No, no. When she was צרת חליצתו tsoras
chalitzato here, she was one degree less than רחל, Rachel, but here
it's seen as an independent issue
and therefore an equal issue, it's not because of the יבום yibbum
aspect.
Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like this, דתנן אסור אדם בצרת
קרובת חליצתו.
datnan asur adam bitzoras
krovat chalitzato. Alright, שמואל Shmuel נמי nami התחיל ולא התחיל קאמר. hitchil
velo hitchil ka'amar. Fine, שמואל Shmuel isn't really saying that when you
do it with נעמי, Naomi, when you do, that in this case,
the חליצה chalitza to נעמי Naomi is preferable to the חליצה chalitza
to רחל. Rachel. He's talking about when you begin the process one
way, how you end it. We're going to completely re-read שמואל, Shmuel,
okay?
Let's continue this. You'll see what the גמרא Gemara says. Here's what
he says.
התחיל ולא התחיל קאמר. hitchil velo hitchil ka'amar.
התחיל באחיות, hitchil ba'achayos,
if he began, if he did, okay, before זבולון Zvulun died, okay,
or before, let's say they both died. Before he did anything, all
these
women were equal,
because he holds אין זיקה. ein zika. Okay, so now, actually if
he's smart, he'll focus on דבורה, Devora, because then רחל Rachel won't
be אחות חליצה, achos chalitza, okay. But if he went ahead and
he started with לאה Leah and turned her into, and turned רחל
Rachel into אחות חליצה, achos chalitza, so in that case, התחיל
באחיות לא יגמור
בצרות.
hitchil ba'achayos lo yigmor
bitzoros. דתנן אסור אדם בצרת קרובת חליצתו. de-tnan asur adam bitzoras krovat
chalitzato.
In that case, if he began with לאה, Leah, then he should
not finish with נעמי, Naomi, because נעמי Naomi has this problem, צרת
קרובת חליצתו. tsoras krovat chalitzato. So in that type of a case,
he should finish with רחל. Rachel. Now, I don't get exactly why
רחל's Rachel any better, it's the exact same, okay, but it's אחות
חליצה, achos chalitza, who knows. But רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean
it's better. רש"י Rashi says it means that it's like no, I
think רש"י Rashi says it means it's no different. Hold on.
Basically. Hold on, let me check the רש"י. Rashi.
Oh, right, רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean he shouldn't finish. It
means that by doing נעמי Naomi he won't get רחל Rachel off
the hook, okay. When it says לא יגמור בצרות, lo yigmor bitzoros,
it means normally we say you do the צרה tzora you get
the other wife off the hook. לא יגמור בצרות lo yigmor bitzoros
means doing it with the צרה tzora won't get the other wife
off the hook. So if you started with לאה, Leah,
this won't help. You still need to do רחל. Rachel. You need
to do both. He has to do both, because one won't get
the other off the hook because they're both problematic, okay. So if
he begins with לאה, Leah, then both of these are now problematic,
אחות חליצה, achos chalitza, צרת אחות חליצה, tsoras achos
chalitza, finishing with נעמי Naomi won't help you.
You have to do it with both. התחיל באחיות לא יגמור בצרות.
hitchil ba'achayos lo yigmor bitzoros. דתנן אסור אדם בצרת קרובת חליצתו. de-tnan
asur adam bitzoras krovat chalitzato. התחיל בצרות יגמור אף באחיות. hitchil bitzoros
yigmor af ba'achayos. דתנן מותר אדם בקרובת צרת חליצתו. de-tnan mutar adam
bikrovas tsoras chalitzato.
But if he's smart and he starts with
דבורה, Devora, okay, so then רחל Rachel is not אחות חליצה, achos
chalitza, nobody is related to anybody. In this case, either one can
work. He can do it with רחל Rachel and that's a totally
good חליצה chalitza to get נעמי Naomi off the hook, and he
can do it with נעמי Naomi and that'll get רחל Rachel off
the hook.
Why? And because we say, and this is the... let's just read
these words,
because מותר אדם, mutar adam, for the person
is allowed, בקרובת צרת חליצתו. bikrovas tsoras chalitzato. In the relative, so
he's allowed to finish with רחל, Rachel, because רחל Rachel is... this
is the mirror image of the other case. רחל Rachel is the
relative of the צרה. tzora. This is צרת חליצתו tsoras chalitzato and
that's קרובת צרת חליצתו. krovat tsoras chalitzato. So it's like the mirror
image of the other case. But that's not problematic. You might have
thought it's like this, don't worry, it's not like that. So in
this case, both of the women are totally מותר mutar to him,
so doing it with either woman will get the other one off.
Okay, that was a... Super complicated complete reread of what שמואל *Shmuel*
has said, okay, all because the גמרא *Gemara* wanted to understand if
it's יש זיקה *yesh zika*, why is דבורה *Devorah* better than לאה
*Leah*? And it couldn't just have said because דבורה *Devorah* is one
degree removed? Yes, she's צרת זקוקתו *tzaras zkukaso*, אחות זקוקתו *achos zkukaso*,
it's one degree removed. So the שמואל *Shmuel* גמרא *Gemara* had this
total reread of שמואל *Shmuel*. Okay, now the גמרא *Gemara*, now the
גמרא *Gemara* finally gives the simple explanation of שמואל *Shmuel*. רב אשי
אמר *Rav Ashi amar*, רב אשי *Rav Ashi* says לעולם כדקאמרת *le’olam
ked’kamris*, don't bother me with all this. It's שמואל *Shmuel* like you
thought he said. Okay, it's better to do it with דבורה *Devorah*
than with לאה *Leah*, even though דבורה *Devorah* is like a צרת
*tzaras* quasi ערווה *erva*, that's one degree removed from being a quasi
ערווה *erva*, כדקאמרת *ked’kamris*. ומשום דלא אלימא זיקה *umishum d’lo alima zika*,
the זיקה *zika* too is not strong enough לשוייה לצרה כערווה *l’shavyei
l’tzara k’erva* to make the צרה *tzara* as much of an ערווה
*erva* as לאה *Leah* is. So in this case שמואל *Shmuel* holds
יש זיקה *yesh zika*. לאה *Leah* is אחות זקוקתו *achos zkukaso*, אחות
זקוקתו *achos
zkukaso*, which makes her, wait,
they're both אחות זקוקתו *achos zkukaso*.
They both died at the same time.
Yeah exactly, they all died at the same time. Okay, they're both
אחות זקוקתו *achos zkukaso*. So they're both quasi ערווה *erva*. So דבורה
*Devorah* is a quasi צרת ערווה *tzaras erva*, but that's not as
close to being an ערווה *erva*
because לאה *Leah* isn't a real ערווה *erva*. So since לאה *Leah*
isn't a real ערווה *erva*, normally there's already a חידוש *chiddush* that
the צרה *tzara* becomes like the ערווה *erva*. Okay, so she's not
gonna be enough like an ערווה *erva* in this case because already
לאה *Leah* isn't even a full ערווה *erva*. And therefore maybe they're
not, none of
them is a סוג א *sug aleph*, none of them is a
grade A, but at least דבורה *Devorah* is a grade B whereas
לאה *Leah* might be a grade C.
So therefore you do it to דבורה *Devorah* and you get לאה
*Leah* off the hook. It is the better חליצה *chalitza*. All right,
whew. תניא כוותיה דרב אשי *tanya k’vosei d’Rav Ashi*, we taught like
רב אשי *Rav Ashi*, thank God. So, חלץ לאחיות לא נפטרו
צרות *chalatz l’achayos lo nivtru tzaros*. If you did חליצה *chalitza* with
the sisters, the co-wives didn't get off the hook. חלץ לצרות *chalatz
l’tzaros*, if you do it to the co-wives, נפטרו אחיות *nivtru achayos*,
the sisters do get off the hook. מאי טעמא *mai ta’ama*, what's
the reason? לאו משום דקסבר יש זיקה *lav mishum d’kasavar yesh zika*
ולא אלמי זיקה לשוייה לצרה כערווה *v’lo almi zika l’shavyei l’tzara k’erva*?
It must be exactly like רב אשי *Rav Ashi* said, there's a
זיקה *zika* and therefore the sisters are אחות זקוקתו *achos zkukaso*, but
that's not strong enough to create a serious enough problem with the
co-wives. So therefore the חליצה *chalitza* with the co-wife still works for
the sisters fine.
Wait, so שמואל *Shmuel* says יש זיקה *yesh zika*? I thought we
said אין זיקה *ein zika*?
That's when we were trying to reread שמואל *Shmuel*. Now we're back
to the normal read of שמואל *Shmuel*, as the problem is אחות
זקוקתו *achos zkukaso*. אמר רבי אבא בר ממל *amar Rabbi Abba bar
Mammel*, הא מני בית שמאי היא *ha mani Beis Shammai hi*, דתנן
*d’tnan*, he's gonna come up with a different answer why the צרה
*tzara* is not a problem. Why it's better to do חליצה *chalitza*
with דבורה *Devorah*. Isn't she a צרת *tzaras* quasi ערווה *erva*? So
he says nah, we're not holding like that there's an issue of
צרות *tzaros* altogether. הא מני בית שמאי היא דתנן בית שמאי מתירין
הצרות לאחים *ha mani Beis Shammai hi d’tnan Beis Shammai matirin hatzaros
l’achin*. Okay well that's pretty radical, right? So he says why is
שמואל *Shmuel* saying do חליצה *chalitza* to דבורה *Devorah* and not to
לאה *Leah*? Isn't דבורה *Devorah* a צרה *tzara* of לאה *Leah* and
therefore also problematic?
Answer, it's the שיטת בית שמאי *shitas Beis Shammai* who doesn't believe
in צרות *tzaros*.
Okay, it's like against the משנה *mishna*? Yeah, and שמואל *Shmuel* is
just somehow incorporating that. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אי הכי יבומי
נמי תתייבם *ei hachi yibumi nami tisyabem*. So go ahead and do
יבום *yibum* with דבורה *Devorah* in that case. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says כרבי יוחנן בן נורי *k’Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri*, דאמר *d’amar*, like
רבי יוחנן בן נורי *Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri*, he says בואו ונתקן
להם לצרות שיהיו חולצות ולא מתייבמות *bo’u venisaken lahem l’tzaros sheyehu choltzos
v’lo misyabmos*, that even according, that let's just play it safe and
have everybody like you know, we'll cover both בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*
and בית הלל *Beis Hillel* and do חליצה *chalitza*. So בית הלל
*Beis Hillel* will say it's not necessary, but at least it doesn't
hurt. And בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* will say you have to do,
you have to do יבום *yibum* or חליצה *chalitza*, so that we
won't do יבום *yibum*, we'll do חליצה *chalitza*, we'll make everybody happy.
So therefore we're פוסקנינג *paskening* like him. So דבורה *Devorah* is not
really an ערווה *erva* because basically we're assuming like בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai* that צרות *tzaros* are okay, but we have a דרבנן *d’rabbanan*
demand to do חליצה *chalitza*. So we're saying better to do חליצה
*chalitza* with דבורה *Devorah* than you know than with לאה *Leah*. And
the חליצה *chalitza* with דבורה *Devorah* will still get לאה *Leah* off
the hook by the way, right?
Because because he still has a מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibum* according
to בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* he has a מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום
*yibum* with דבורה *Devorah*. Okay, all we're saying is that according to
בית שמאי *Beis Shammai* you're allowed to do יבום *yibum* with דבורה
*Devorah* and we're insisting you do חליצה *chalitza*. But not that דבורה
*Devorah* is out of the picture. Okay, so therefore he's saying why
do it with דבורה *Devorah*? Because we're like בית שמאי *Beis Shammai*,
there's no idea of צרת ערווה *tzaras erva*. Okay, and in theory
you could do יבום *yibum*, but we want to be nice to
בית הלל *Beis Hillel* so we're going to do חליצה *chalitza* and
that'll get לאה *Leah* off the hook. Of course, why we should
assume that שמואל *Shmuel* is talking like that I have no idea.
Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says והאמר מר לא הספיקו לגמור את
הדבר עד שנפטרה השעה *v’ha’amar mar lo sispiku ligmor es hadavar ad
sheniftra hasha’ah*, they never made that ruling that they said that everybody
needs חליצה *chalitza* and not יבום *yibum* according to בית שמאי *Beis
Shammai*. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק *amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak*, אחר
כך חזרו ותקנו *achar kach chazru v’tiknu*. Nah, even though they didn't
get a chance to. And they made that ruling, the power of
חומרא *chumrah* ultimately won out, so at some later time they wound
up making that תקנה *takanah*. Again, very bizarre explanation why שמואל *Shmuel*
would be working within בית שמאי *Beit Shamai*. Okay, the easier explanation
is like we said, we're back to the basic idea that you
assume that even though שמואל *Shmuel* has that even if it's a
second-rate חליצה *chalitzah*—we should say rate as opposed to grace, lest we're
in grade school or something—even if it's a second-rate חליצה *chalitzah*, even
though you only need one, and even though you allow a second-rate,
you don't need it from all the brothers, and allow a second-rate
חליצה *chalitzah* to get the woman off the hook, you don't need
the first-rate to get her off the hook, but if you have
a co-wife, then you need the better חליצה *chalitzah* that gets the
other wife off the hook. And in this case, the better חליצה
*chalitzah* is the one to דבורה *Dvorah* because לאה *Leah* is אחות
זיקתו *achot zikuto* and דבורה *Dvorah*, even though she's צרת אחות זיקתו
*tzarat achot zikuto*, she's one degree removed, and therefore it's the better
חליצה *chalitzah*, and it will get לאה *Leah* off the hook. All
right.