Today's דף Daf. *daf* is דף daf. ד *daf dalet*, and we
pick up on the very top line, first line of דף daf
ד *daf dalet*, and what we are dealing with is different bases,
different sources for why you separate the כהן Kohen *kohen* for seven
days, and also there's analogous discussion of the פרה Parah *parah* of
the כהן kohen *kohen* who's going to do the פרה אדומה para
aduma. *parah adumah*. To remind you, the most dominant source until now
has been that of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*, although two
traditions in the name of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan*
that the source from the מלואים Miluim. *miluim*, כאשר עשה ביום הזה
kaasher asah bayom hazeh צוה ה׳ לעשות tziva Hashem la'asos לכפר עליכם
*ka'asher asa bayom hazeh tzivah Hashem la'asot lechaper aleichem*. And on the
one hand, it is very comparable to the מלואים Miluim. *miluim*, it
is preparation to do a certain type of an עבודה avoda *avodah*
in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*, as the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, it's תחלה במקום *techilah bamakom*, almost an initiating of the
space or the עבודה Avoda *avodah* in the space. Of course by
the קדש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim* after the first time and it's stopping
the first time, but nevertheless, there's a sense of the space that's
being entered. It's a special, they're associated with the קרבן korban *korban*
that the כהן גדול kohen gadol. *Kohen Gadol* brings,
and it very much focuses on the person who is preparing that
person to do the עבודה Avoda. *avodah*. That is one source that's
very, the comparison is weaker relating to the פרה אדומה para aduma.
*parah adumah*, and we have another tradition in the name of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* that the פרה אדומה para aduma *parah
adumah* is not included. The פרה אדומה para aduma *parah adumah* is
only a rabbinic issue relating to טומאה וטהרה tumah vetahara. *tumah and
taharah*, and the stringencies about טומאה וטהרה tumah vetahara *tumah and taharah*,
and it's not really part of this model. The other version that
includes it in the model, it's harder to see the common denominator,
but anyways, that's one source of the מלואים Miluim. *miluim*. ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Resh Lakish* disagrees. He says if that was really the
basis, if you didn't do it, it wouldn't be good, and we
know that the stand-in כהן *kohen*, the understudy, בדיעבד bedieved *bedi'avad* would
not require this. So therefore, he feels it cannot be based on
the מלואים Miluim? *miluim*, and he bases it rather on משה Moshe
*Moshe* and הר סיני Har Sinai, *Har Sinai*, on the verse that
says that he reads to understand that משה Moshe. *Moshe* was in
the cloud six days before he went up to הר סיני Har
Sinai. *Har Sinai*, so as a preparation, and here too, it is
required that type of a preparation. Of course according to that as
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it really should only be a six-day
preparation. Seven days are just a טומאה tumah *tumah* concern, and are
not really based on that fundamental model. Similarly, presumably, פרה Parah. *parah*
would not be based on that model. פרה *parah* would be a
טומאה *tumah* concern, but at least the core here is about משה
Moshe *Moshe* at הר סיני Har Sinai. *Har Sinai*. And that is
very significant conceptually because it points us not to the act of
the עבודה Avoda *avodah* and what's needed in order to enable the
עבודה Avoda *avodah*, it points us to the sense of the encounter
with God and focusing on the fact that משה Moshe. *Moshe* is
going to have this encounter and he needs this preparation. And the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *Kohen Gadol* focuses not on all the עבודה
avodah *avodah* he's doing on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, but
essentially the going into the קדש הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim* and that encounter,
מחנה שכינה machaneh Shechinah, *Machaneh Shechinah* is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
said before, but מחנה שכינה machaneh Shechinah. *Machaneh Shechinah* in the very
specific sense here, not the general sense of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, but the more limited sense of the קדש הקדשים
*Kodesh Hakodashim* and a sense of the preparation for that immediate encounter
with God, and particularly also thinking about how that relates to us
and our preparing for יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, it definitely
puts the attention in a different aspect and not about the עבודה
avodah *avodah*. But that would be six days. So that is the
debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* and ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish *Resh Lakish*, and now we continue in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
Top of דף ד עמוד א *daf dalet amud aleph*. אמר ליה
amar lei, רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan. לריש לקיש *Amar leh Rabbi Yochanan
le-Resh Lakish*, so רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan* said to ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish *Resh Lakish*, בשלמא לדידי *bishlama lidi*,
it works well according to me, דאלפינא ממלואים *d'alfina m'miluim*, that I
learn it out from מלואים Miluim. *miluim*, היינו דתניא d'tanya, *hainu de-tanya*,
that fits in with the ברייתא braita, *baraita* that we're going to
quote a little bit later and we quote in a few דפים
*dafim* from now, זה וזה מזין עליו כל שבעה מכל חטאות שהיו
שם Mazin Alav Kol Shivah Mi-Kol Chattat She-Hayu Sham. *zeh v'zeh mazzin
alav kol shiva mikol chatatot shehayu sham*. Okay, that this and this,
whether it's the case of preparing the כהן *kohen* for the פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah *parah adumah* or whether it's preparing the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol *Kohen Gadol* for the עבודה avodah *avodah* on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, they would sprinkle on him the ashes from
all of the חטאות *chatatot*, all the red heifers that they had
there. What does it mean all the red heifers? רש״י Rashi *Rashi*
says that they would always store up, they wouldn't wait to completely
use up all of the ashes of one פרה אדומה Parah Adumah.
*parah adumah* before they did another פרה אדומה parah adumah, *parah adumah*.
They'd always have some of the old stuff around. רש״י *Rashi* actually
also quotes an idea that the ashes of the פרה *parah* that
was done in the time of משה Moshe? *Moshe*, by a miracle,
never ran out. So when they did the sprinkling to prepare the
כהן *kohen* for the פרה אדומה parah adumah. *parah adumah* or the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, *kohen gadol* for the עבודה avodah, *avodah* on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, they didn't just want to make
him טהור tahor. *tahor*. As we've been seeing, there's a whole big
ritual associated. Look, if they just wanted to make him טהור *tahor*,
they would just do it on day three and day seven, but
they wind up doing it every single day. So clearly there is
more here than just the act of making טהור *tahor*. So one
of the things that they would do is they'd take some ashes
from all of the different פרות אדומות *parot adumot* that they had
ever burned if they still had the ashes of. That's מכל חטאות
אמורות *mikol chatatot amurot*. I understand why we don't know which certain
seven day it would be, we'll see about that later, but that
might be an aspect, but it's more, not fundamentally, at least not
here the focus. Okay, so I understand why... They would do every
single day. Why would they do every single day? דהוי נמי הזאה
hazaa במילואים. Because there was also sprinkling every day in מילואים. miluim.
That was a different sprinkling; it was with the blood of the
קרבנות, korbanot, but the whole seven days there was some act of
sprinkling being done, and this is being done analogous to that. אלא
לדידך, ela ledidach, but according to you, דילפת מסיני, dyalpat misinai, your
basis is סיני, Sinai, הזאה בסיני מי הוי, haza b’Sinai mi havi,
where was this ever existed at הר סיני, Har Sinai. this preparatory
sprinkling and the whole you know every single day? So clearly this
indicates the מילואים miluim model and not the סיני Sinai model. אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said back to him, ולטעמיך מי ניחא, ultamich
mi nicha, wait a minute, according to you, why is it good?
במילואים דם, הכא מים. bemiluim dam, hacha mayim. It wasn't the same
sprinkling; in the מילואים miluim they did blood with the קרבנות, korbanot,
here you did water, you know פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah, So the
גמרא Gemara says no, הא לא קשיא, ha lo kashya,
that wouldn't bother me, דתני רב חייא, detani Rav Chiyya, because רב
חייא Rav Chiyya teaches in a ברייתא, Braita נכנסו מים תחת דם.
nichnesu mayim tachat dam. Fine, so, you know, you use water instead
of blood, which means we admit that it's not identical, but at
least it's built on that model and it would be obviously you're
not going to do blood because number one, there are no fixed
קרבנות korbanot to be bringing in the days leading up to יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur and number two, there's no basis to use you
can't use the blood of a קרבן korban. right to do sprinkling
unless the תורה Torah mandates it, else it's obviously a misuse of
the קרבן. korban, So therefore the only type of sprinkling that we
have available to us that's a meaningful sprinkling is that of the
פרה אדומה. So yes, we use that model, we translate it in
a way that works, but still it's fundamentally based on that model.
So that to me still works. אלא לדידך, ela ledidach, but according
to you, הזאה בסיני מי הוי, haza b’Sinai mi havi, you don't
have the model at all for הזאה on הר סיני. Har Sinai,
Now of course תוספות Tosafot points out that you did have the
sprinkling that was done with the דם הברית, dam habrit, you know,
at the foot of הר סיני. Har Sinai, But first of all
that was only right after they got the תורה, Torah, the end
of משפטים, Mishpatim, משה Moshe, takes חצי הדם וישם באגנות chatzi hadam
vayasem baaganot and he sprinkles on the people הנה דם הברית hinei
dam habrit etcetera. But תוספות Tosafot points out that it cannot serve
as the model. Number one, that was fundamentally on the people. We're
talking about משה'ס Moshe's preparation to go into מחנה שכינה, machaneh Shechinah.
to go up to הר סיני. Har Sinai That was not part
of a process of blood. Number one. Number two, that was only
one day, it was not seven days. So clearly that cannot be
the model. So according to you, what is all this sprinkling about?
אמר ליה, so he said back to him, מעלה בעלמא, maala bealma,
alright, like we said before about why seven rather than six, you
know, or
why פרה אדומה if it's really all about the כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol And the answer is, yeah, you're right, that's not the basic
idea. The basic idea would not require sprinkling, but once we're the
same way the basic idea only requires six days, but this is
רבי יוחנן speaking who learns out from הר סיני, Har Sinai but
once we're doing it, we do other things to make it important.
So why do we go from six to seven? To cover טומאה
purposes, because if he’s away from his house seven days, it’ll be
he’ll be safer meantime. Why do we go why do we add
sprinkling to part of the process? It’s to show as רש"י Rashi
says, you could say for טהרה tahara purposes, but again the גמרא
Gemara מעלה maala is not exactly the same word as טהרה, tahara,
so רש"י Rashi here says we do it as a way of
sort of also preparing for this event of going into מחנה שכינה.
machaneh Shechinah. So the more ritual you create in the process, it's
not just you’re not living at home and you’re living here in
the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. But if you create a ritual every
day, that more creates that whole idea of building up, of preparing,
of you know of getting ready for that standing before that entering
into the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, that encounter with you know of
מחנה שכינה. Machaneh Shechinah, So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, would admit that
there are parts of this that don't fit into his model. There
are parts of this that have to do with טומאה וטהרה. There
are parts of this that are added on later. But at the
core he says, conceptually, this is about standing before God and preparing
yourself to enter into מחנה שכינה. Machaneh Shechinah? It is not some
type of a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash ritual right that is about
preparing for the עבודה avodah or preparing for פרה אדומה like רבי
יוחנן would
have
it. Yes Michael. Yeah, that’s not the same. It’s not just the
physical space, it’s the meaning of that entering into that space. Okay,
to what degree is that defined as an as a you know
encountering of of the שכינה? Shechinah? So it’s not obviously it’s not
just the physical space. Okay, so anyway תוספות Tosafot does ask the
question that Michael sort of asked before about the גמרא Gemara later
tries to explain the seven days sprinkling relating to obviously טומאה וטהרה
purposes. Why did you need it every day and not just three
and seven? Well we don’t know which days are three and seven,
and even though בדיעבד it would work regardless da da da da
da and the גמרא Gemara goes through a whole חשבון. cheshbon. But
nevertheless תוספות Tosafot says that’s you know that’s
here the גמרא Gemara that’s that seems like secondary reasons and here
the גמרא Gemara understands that the prime the primary model it would
be based on would not would not be that issue of just
covering your bases and making sure he’s טהור. There seems here to
be a much more primary model, at least according to רב יוחנן,
Rav Yochanan, of the מלואים. Miluim. Okay, so let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara now continues. תניא כוותיה דרב יוחנן, Tanya Kevatei De-Rav
Yochanan, תניא כוותיה דריש לקיש. Tanya Kevatei De-Resh Lakish. We have a
ברייתא Braita that supports each approach. תניא כוותיה דרב יוחנן. Tanya Kevatei
De-Rav Yochanan. We have a ברייתא Braita that supports רב יוחנן. Rav
Yochanan. ובזאת יבא אהרן אל הקדש. U-Be-Zot Yavo Aharon El Ha-Kodesh.
With this Aaron shall come into the sanctuary. מה שאמור בענין. Mah
She-Amur Be-Inyan. What it said in another context. Now what's the other
context? מהי בענין? Mah Hi Be-Inyan? בענין
מלואים. Be-Inyan Miluim. What it says by the
בזאת. Be-Zot. So the way רש"י Rashi explains right what the question
is, is פר בן בקר לחטאת ואיל לעולה Par Ben Bakar Le-Chatat
Ve-Ayil Le-Olah is not feminine. פר Par and an איל Ayil is
masculine and it should be באלו Be-Elu or whatever, בזה. Be-Zeh. What's
בזאת Be-Zot in the feminine? So זאת Zot in the feminine has
to could relate to the פרישה Prisha of the מלואים. Miluim פרישה
Prisha is a feminine word I guess. Anyway, whatever, somehow the דרשה
Drasha is that with this includes some other process that is necessary
for the עבודה avodah, on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur And what is
that other process? בענין דמלואים. Be-Inyan De-Miluim. What we find by the
מלואים. Miluim. ומה אמור בענין דמלואים? U-Mah Amur Be-Inyan De-Miluim? What do
we find by the מלואים? Miluim, אהרן פירש שבעה ושימש יום אחד.
Aharon Piresh Shivah Ve-Shimmesh Yom Echad. Aaron separated seven and served one
day and משה. Moshe Now it's interesting, we add to this more
of the whole ritual of separation once we're using this as a
model. ומשה מסר לו כל שבעה. U-Moshe Masar Lo Kol Shivah. משה
Moshe. was effectively the כהן for the seven days of the מלואים.
miluim כדי לחנכו בעבודה, Kedei Le-Chanecho Ba-Avoda, to prepare him to do
the עבודה. Avodah, So not just to do the עבודה Avodah, then,
but part of it was getting Aaron prepared. ואף לדורות, Ve-Af Le-Dorot,
and similarly לדורות. Le-Dorot. כהן גדול פירש שבעה ומשמש יום אחד. Kohen
Gadol Piresh Shivah U-Meshamesh Yom Echad. He separates seven days and he
serves the one day of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur, ושני תלמידי חכמים
מתלמידיו של משה, U-Shene Talmidei Chachamim Mi-Talmidav Shel Moshe, two תלמידי חכמים
Talmidei Chachamim who now represent משה. Moshe, Okay, now what does it
mean specifically they represent משה? Moshe So here we get another dig
at the צדוקים. Tzedukim. לאפוקי צדוקים, Le-Afokei Tzedukim, right, to exclude the
צדוקים, Tzedukim, meaning they're דוקא Davka representatives of משה, Moshe. of the
true tradition, not of the perverted tradition or the false tradition. They're
the true מסורה, Mesorah, and they serve as representatives of משה Moshe
and תורה. Torah. מוסרין לו כל שבעה, Mosrin Lo Kol Shivah, they're
given to him all seven days, כדי לחנכו בעבודה Kedei Le-Chanecho Ba-Avoda
to prepare him for the עבודה Avodah because we're going to learn
that they each day they would walk the animals before the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, they would prepare him, they would teach him, and
that was done by two sages, two people from the rabbinic class
who represented משה. Moshe, So it's exactly sort of parallel to what
you have by the מלואים. miluim, ומכאן אמרו, U-Mi-Kan Amru, שבעת ימים
קודם יום הכפורים מפרישים כהן גדול מביתו ללשכת פרהדרין. Shiv'at Yamim Kodem
Yom Ha-Kippurim Mafrishim Kohen Gadol Mi-Beito Le-Lishkat Parhedrin. And this is the
basis of the משנה Mishnah that seven days before—it's interesting when a
מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha refers to a משנה. Mishnah. Right, there's always
a question about which came first, מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha or משנה,
Mishnah, you know, they were edited over time. Anyway, from here this
מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha refers to the line in our משנה. Mishnah.
This is the basis of what we teach, that the כהן גדול
kohen gadol they would separate out from his house seven days to
this special chamber. וכשם U-Ke-Shem and then the תוספתא Tosefta ends, וכשם
שמפרישים כהן גדול כך מפרישים כהן השורף את הפרה ללשכה שעל פני
הבירה. U-Ke-Shem She-Mafrishim Kohen Gadol Kach Mafrishim Kohen Ha-Soref Et Ha-Parah Le-Lishkah
She-Al Penei Ha-Birah. The same way you do it for the כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, you would do it for the כהן השורף את
הפרה, Kohen Ha-Soref Et Ha-Parah, he'd be in this special chamber, צפונה
מזרחה, Tzafonah Mizrachah, northeast, northeast. Now רש"י Rashi says obviously that doesn't
fit the pattern because it was such a beautiful model that fit
exactly מלואים miluim analogous to יום כיפור Yom Kippur, and doesn't fit
the שורף את הפרה, Soref Et Ha-Parah, right, which is why we
had one tradition that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan did not include that.
So according to רש"י Rashi says yes, according to this ברייתא baraisa
that's like an add-on and that clearly is not the—not understood as
the עיקר Ikkar you know sort of teaching here. That would be
like rabbinic, that would not be the real you—that's just
a—that's just a rabbinic type of an issue. It is not what
fundamentally we learn from the פסוק. Pasuk. Fundamentally what we learn from
the פסוק Pasuk is the כהן גדול kohen gadol. on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. which is directly analogous to the
מלואים. What's the problem with putting it here as one of... yeah
but anyway but we don't have that
whole
process. ואחד זה ואחד זה, Ve-Echad Zeh Ve-Echad Zeh,
whether it is
the
פרה or the
כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, מזין עליו כל שבעה מכל חטאות שהיו שם.
They would do from the פרה אדומה that they would they would
sprinkle them from the פרה אדומה. This is what we quoted at
the top of the דף. ואם תאמר במלואים דם הכא מים. Ve-Im
Tomar Bi-Miluim Dam Hacha Mayim.
And if you say what about the problem about the difference between
blood and water? Blood was in the מלואים, here we're using the
water of the פרה. פרה אדומה, אמרת נכנסו מים תחת
דם. amarta nichnesu mayim tachat dam. All right, so use a substitute.
Okay, ואומר, ve'omer, so that's the whole basis, learn that from בזאת
יבוא, bezot yavo, not כאשר עשה. ka'asher asa. So fundamentally it's about
the עבודה avodah. on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and all of these
ways of comparison of of you know linked analogous acts of preparation.
Now ואומר, ve'omer, and finally a פסוק pasuk says כאשר עשה ביום
הזה צוה ה' לעשות לכפר עליכם. ka'asher asa bayom hazeh tsiva Hashem
la'asot lechaper aleichem. לעשות אלו מעשה פרה, la'asot eilu ma'aseh parah, לכפר
אלו מעשה יום הכיפורים, lechaper eilu ma'aseh Yom HaKippurim, like we saw
before, that rather than learning it on the פסוק pasuk by יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur which focuses us just on the עבודה avodah, of
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur learning it from the פסוק pasuk of מילואים
milu'im that also allows us to drag in פרה אדומה. So גמרא
Gemara says והאי בזאת מיבעי ליה לגופיה? ve'hai bezot mibaye lei legufeih?
So
what גמרא Gemara says, one minute, how can you use בזאת bezot
to tell you there's another act of preparation, the whole seven days?
בזאת bezot is telling you what the פסוק pasuk says, פר בן
בקר לחטאת ואיל לעולה. par ben bakar lechatat ve'ayil le'olah. So
yeah, you need it to teach, you know, for basic פשט peshat
of the פסוק. pasuk. How do you use it to say, oh,
there's some other act of preparation? אמרי, amri, no, you could say,
אי לקרבן לחודיה, ei lekorban lechudeih, if it was just about the
קרבן, korban, לימא קרא בזה או באלה. leima kra bezeh o be'eileh.
מאי בזאת? mai bezot?
What's בזאת? bezot? Now רש"י Rashi again points out because בזאת bezot
is feminine and פר בן בקר par ben bakar and איל ayil
is masculine. משמע מינה תרתי. mashma mi'na tarti.
The difference of language is to tell you there's another part of
the process that you need to be ready for יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur, מאי ואומר? mai ve'omer? And why then if you did something
so convincing, בזאת bezot would mean... all right, we say what we
want to say, what's the reason at the end we have to
quote another פסוק, pasuk, which is the פסוק pasuk we've known until
now? וכי תימא יום הכיפורים קמא הוא דבעי פרישה כדאשכחן במילואים? vechitema
Yom HaKippurim kama hu dibaye perishah kedashcham bemilu'im?
No,
because there's a way that you could have limited it. You could
have said בזאת יבוא אהרן, bezot yavo Aharon, that in the first
time, because you do realize and the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon points
this out that the entire פרשה parshah of אחרי מות Acharei Mot
of the עבודה avodah, is all about אהרן. Aharon. בזאת יבוא אהרן
אל הקודש. bezot yavo Aharon el hakodesh. הגר"א ha'Gra even says that
the entire פרשה parshah doesn't even mention יום כיפור Yom Kippur till
the very end. It's like when אהרן Aharon would ever want to
go in, right to the קודש הקודשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, if he would
ever want to enter, right, so then this is what he would
have to do. I mean, also remember that you had the death
of the שני בני אהרן, shenei benei Aharon, right, because they drew
near in a way that was inappropriate. So God is saying, oh,
if you want to have this encounter, בזאת יבוא, bezot yavo, you
have to go through this entire process in order to enter into
the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. At the very end of the whole
thing it says, oh, you should do this every year on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur and you should do this לדורותיכם. ledoroteichem. But it
starts fundamentally about a focus on אהרן, Aharon, which by the way,
although here we're within רבי יוחנן who learns from the מילואים, milu'im,
is a very important point to underscore for ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
that sees that the whole idea is about the God encounter, right.
The whole idea of the preparation is not so much the עבודה,
avodah right, it's like learn from משה, Moshe it's about the God
encounter and in a way that's how the whole עבודה avodah, is
introduced. Here's how you have that God encounter, here's how you enter
in doing this whole process. And that's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
focuses on. But anyways for now it's saying that if I just
had this בזאת יבוא, bezot yavo, maybe I would have thought the
first time if you want to do it and we can learn
that would be analogous to the מילואים. milu'im. It would not be
a regular יום כיפור Yom Kippur. thing, but the same way מילואים
milu'im was a way of being מחנך mechanech the כהנים kohanim and
the first use of the מזבח mizbe'ach like we said yesterday, maybe
this too would be the first time to establish this practice and
to establish אהרן, Aharon, you know the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, in
this role and to establish and to allow you to enter the
קודש הקודשים, Kodesh Hakodashim, the first use of the קודש הקודשים. Kodesh
Hakodashim. There'd be a God encounter between God and אהרן, Aharon, not
God and... Well, okay, but now I've digressed a little bit because
that God encounter is ריש לקיש, here we're רבי יוחנן. But here
anyway it's more echoing or the גמרא Gemara before was echoing this,
whatever anyway the idea that it was if you the context if
you really compare it to the מילואים, milu'im, the מילואים milu'im is
initiating in the עבודה, avodah initiating the כהנים, kohanim, initiating the בית
המקדש. It's the first use
of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so here too maybe it would only be
required once in history. You don't do a מילואים milu'im multiple times,
so maybe you only do this once in history to initiate this
role of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol this use of the קודש
הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. So that's the focus on מילואים, milu'im, maybe it
would only be
once. So in the last rabbinic way of using the you know
inclusions and exclusions it's all making sense. Very true. Okay, so something
that comes along, so גמרא Gemara says but says... so וכי תימא
יום הכיפורים קמא הוא דבעי פרישה כדאשכחן במילואים אבל ביום הכיפורים דעלמא
לא. vechitema Yom HaKippurim kama hu dibaye perishah kedashcham bemilu'im aval beYom
HaKippurim de'alma lo. It's not part of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur it's
part of an initiation process. אי נמי, i nami, so then I
wouldn't so maybe I would have limited the verse. אי נמי כהן
גדול קמא הוא דבעי פרישה אבל כהן גדול דעלמא לא, i nami
kohen gadol kama hu dibaye perishah aval kohen gadol de'alma lo, maybe
the first כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol תא שמע כאשר עשה ביום הזה,
tashma ka'asher asa bayom hazeh, which tells me לעשות la'asot in future
generations. I want to again point out that the two things
the גמרא said here are exactly parallel to what we learned at
the bottom of yesterday's דף. The bottom of yesterday's דף said, right...
when it was talking about, why not apply it to, why not
apply it to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah קרבן, korban, how do you
know it’s the יום כיפור Yom Kippur קרבן, and it wanted to
underscore what was similar about the יום כיפור Yom Kippur, to the
מילואים. Miluim. And it gave two answers. One answer was that they
both require a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol right? The מילואים Miluim was
focused on אהרן Aaron and יום כיפור. And the other one was
it was the first use of the space, the first use of
the מזבח, Mizbeach, or at least the, the first יום כיפור was
the first use of the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So those two
ideas are exactly echoed here, right? Maybe I would have limited it
to the first כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol emphasizing him as a person
and preparing and initiating him as a person and the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol in that role. Or maybe I would have limited it
to the first time that אהרן Aaron entered into the קדש קדשים
Kodesh Kodashim and the initiation of that space. So there’s an exact
echoing here and an acknowledgment that the idea of the מילואים Miluim
drawing from that relates to this idea of initiation of initiation. Preparing,
sort of
establishing the כהן גדול in this role, establishing the space as the
space to be used for this עבודה, avodah. and therefore, I might
have said just once. So we say no, you do it every
year, but presumably it still has echoes of that or source in
that concept of initiation. And that, I think, is an important idea
behind רבי יוחנן. Yes. So maybe we'll talk more about this. And
according to ריש לקיש though, it’s a matter of encountering the divine,
and you know, משה Moshe didn’t have to go through this every
time. Did he always go into the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim when
meeting? He didn’t go into the קדש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, we’re going
to discuss that later. Okay? Because the קול kol came from בין
הכרובים. bein hakeruvim. Right, but he didn’t enter in. No, it never
says משה. Moshe ויכל משה לבוא אל תוך הענן. Vayachol Moshe lavo
el toch he’anan. No, but no, we never find that משה Moshe
went into the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Now I want to say
one thing before we move on. All of this has been sounding
very much like it’s taking this very seriously and that this is
a דאורייתא, d’Oraisa, right? Certainly according to now the דרשה drasha of
זאת, zos, כאשר עשה, kaasher asah, and so on. Take a look
at the תוספות נכנסו מים תחת דם. Tosafos nichnesu mayim tachas dam.
תוספות Tosafos says,
how could we do this? How could we substitute water for blood?
דלאו לגמרי דרשה גמורה היא. delav legamrei drasha gemura hi. We can
substitute it because it’s not really a דאורייתא d’Oraisa to do this.
הא דגמיר ממילואים אלא אסמכתא בעלמא. ha d'gamir mi'miluim ela asmachata b'alma.
עיקר קרא ikkar kra דכאשר עשה ביום הזה, d'kaasher asah bayom hazeh,
יש לפרש yesh leforesh ביום ראשון של שבעת ימי מילואים. beyom rishon
shel shivas yemei miluim. אמר להם amar lahem that that פסוק pasuk
of כאשר עשה kaasher asah was not about day eight of the
מילואים, miluim, it was about day one of the מילואים. miluim. אמר
להם amar lahem כאשר עשה kaasher asah, ביום הזה on day one,
צוה ה׳ לעשות כל שבעת ימי המילואים. kol shivas yemei hamiluim. Continue
this for the next seven days. It doesn’t mean like we did
today on day eight, or like we prepared seven days for day
eight, you should do this in the future. וכן פירש רש״י פשוטו
בפירוש החומש. v’chein pirish Rashi peshuto b’feirush hachomesh. Interesting, quoting רש״י on
the חומש. Chomesh. וכיון דאסמכתא בעלמא הוא אין לחוש אם אמרינן נכנסו
מים תחת דם. v’keivan d’asmachata b’alma hu ein lachush im amrinan nichnesu
mayim tachas dam. So at the end of the day, it’s just
a model. It’s not really a דאורייתא. d’Oraisa. If it’s a model,
we can say we’re basically following the model but we’re tweaking it.
Okay, now of course you could say it’s a דאורייתא, d’Oraisa, but
nevertheless, since we’re not, that we have to apply it as it’s
appropriate. The דאורייתא d’Oraisa is use the model but apply it as
appropriate. But at the end of the day, whether you call it
a דאורייתא d’Oraisa or not, the more interesting conceptual question is what
is the reason for this and what is the conceptual model? And
for רבי יוחנן, the conceptual model is that of מילואים, miluim, of
preparing the כהן גדול or
initiating, preparing him to serve,
initiating him into that service on a yearly basis, or particularly because
it’s going to be a special use of a particular space, the
other idea focusing on space. But it’s that sense of initiation that
is the focus, and that’s very different than ריש לקיש where the
focus is the God encounter as opposed to the initiation in the
עבודה, and it’s much more type of a בית המקדש process and
ritual
to allow the עבודה to take place. Yes, Charlie.
How can they use a verse from פרשת אחרי מות Parshas Achrei
Mos when אחרי מות Achrei Mos was given specifically says אחרי מות,
Achrei Mos,
אחרי מות שני בני אהרן. Achrei Mos Shenei Benei Aharon. I mean,
the order is wrong. What’s the order wrong? What do you mean?
So there’s this about the מילואים, miluim, but they would have already
taken place before these commands in. No, the only question is how,
no, the use of the פסוק pasuk אחרי מות Achrei Mos is
better because it comes after the מילואים, miluim, so you could say
בזאת, bezos, with what we did in the מילואים miluim which came
earlier. The problem is more when you learn from the מילואים miluim
that says כאשר עשה צוה ה׳ לעשות kaasher asah tziva Hashem la’asos
and the other things about פר par and the יום כיפור haven’t
been mentioned. They’re not mentioned. But okay, נו, nu, that’s okay, it
all
pre-existed. הסתכל באורייתא וברא עלמא. Histakel b’Oraisa b’ra alma. How did you
explain
והאומר? v'haomer? Why did you need another פסוק pasuk of כאשר עשה,
why wasn't בזאת bezos sufficient? Because if it had just
been בזאת, bezos, והאומר v'haomer means why did you need the other
פסוק? pasuk? Yes, because the end of the ברייתא said והאומר, v'haomer,
and by the way, it also
says... By the way, I think I a little bit misquoted תוספות
*Tosfos* before because how does this גמרא *Gemara* relate to the idea
that the הזיה *haza'ah* was for טהרה *taharah* purposes? So I said
yeah that's like a secondary reason. תוספות *Tosfos* actually at the bottom
of the next תוספות *Tosfos* says once you accept that all of
this is an אסמכתא *asmachta* you could say the opposite that the
seven days is for טהרה *taharah* purposes is the real reason and
this is sort of layered on top of this but that's not
the way the גמרא *Gemara* is presenting it. The גמרא *Gemara* here
is presenting it as that this is the real model and even
the הזיה *haza'ah* is not fundamentally certainly for doing it for all
seven days is not fundamentally about טהרה *taharah* the הזיה *haza'ah* is
about this ritual which is based on the מילואים *miluim*. So that's
what רבי יוחנן *Rebbi Yochanan* says. Now let's take a look at
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*.
תניא כוותיה דריש לקיש *Tanya k'vasei d'Reish Lakish* we learned like ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish* משה Moshe עלה בענן ונתכסה בענן *Moshe alah be'anan
veniskaseh be'anan* משה Moshe, *Moshe* went up in the cloud and was
covered with the cloud ונתקדש בענן *veniskadesh be'anan* and therefore sanctified in
the cloud כדי לקבל תורה Torah לישראל בקדושה *kedai lekabel Torah l'Yisrael
bikdusha* in order that he should be in a holy state when
he was then going to receive the תורה Torah *Torah* from God.
שנאמר וישכון כבוד ה' על הר סיני Har Sinai. *shene'emar vayishkon kevod
Hashem al Har Sinai*
the cloud of God rested on הר סיני Har Sinai *Har Sinai*
זה היה מעשה אחר עשרת הדברות *zeh hayah ma'aseh achar aseres hadibros*
this occurred after the Ten Commandments שהיו תחילה לארבעים יום *shehayu techilah
l'arba'im yom* which began the forty days דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose ha-Gelili *divrei Rebbi Yosi HaGelili*. Now that of course is totally
פשט pshat *peshat* in the פסוקים pesukim *pesukim*. People what don't people
do not appreciate is ואלה המשפטים *ve'eileh hamishpatim* is a continuation of
the עשרת הדברות *aseres hadibros*. Right God first says here's the Ten
Commandments and then he says okay now let's talk about some more
details laws and some civil laws ואלה המשפטים אשר תשים לפניהם *ve'eileh
hamishpatim asher tasim lifneihem* and as you read through all of פרשת
משפטים Mishpatim, *Parashas Mishpatim* משה Moshe *Moshe* is still up there on
הר סיני Har Sinai. *Har Sinai* and it's still the same event
of the עשרת הדברות *aseres hadibros*. And then you get to the
very end of משפטים Mishpatim *Mishpatim* and what do you find out?
And at the very end of משפטים Mishpatim *Mishpatim* it says okay
ואל משה Moshe, אמר עלה אל ה' אתה ואהרן נדב ואביהוא ושבעים
מזקני ישראל *ve'el Moshe amar aleh el Hashem atah ve'Aharon Nadav
va'Avihu v'shiv'im miziknei Yisrael* so משה Moshe *Moshe* has not gone down
yet or whatever maybe he's midpoint in the mountain and God says
come up to me. ויגש משה Moshe, לבדו *vayigash Moshe levado* okay
so then but before משה Moshe *Moshe* goes up God says okay
you and the זקנים *zekenim* are going to come up but what
does משה Moshe *Moshe* do now that the עשרת הדברות *aseres hadibros*
and all of משפטים Mishpatim, *Mishpatim* has been given? ויבא משה Moshe
ויספר לעם את כל דברי ה' ואת כל המשפטים *vayavo Moshe vayisaper
la'am es kol divrei Hashem v'es kol hamishpatim*. Now את כל דברי
ה' ואת כל המשפטים *es kol divrei Hashem v'es kol hamishpatim* is
אלה הדברים אשר תדבר אל בני ישראל *eileh hadevarim asher tedaber el
b'nei Yisrael* עשרת הדברים *aseres hadevarim*.
So דברי ה' *divrei Hashem* is the עשרת הדברים *aseres hadevarim* ואת
כל המשפטים *v'es kol hamishpatim* is all of פרשת משפטים *Parashas Mishpatim*.
So משה Moshe *Moshe*'s up there he gets the דברי ה' *divrei
Hashem* he gets the משפטים *mishpatim* he comes down he reports it
to the people and then they say כל הדברים אשר דבר ה'
נעשה *kol hadevarim asher diber Hashem na'aseh* ויכתב משה Moshe את כל
דברי ה' *vayichtov Moshe es kol divrei Hashem* he gets up in
the morning and then he does the whole he does the קרבנות
*korbanos* ויקח ספר הברית ויאמרו כל אשר דבר ה' נעשה ונשמע *vayikach
sefer habris vayomeru kol asher diber Hashem na'aseh venishma*. So against the
classic rabbinic that נעשה ונשמע *na'aseh venishma* preceded הר סיני Har Sinai
*Har Sinai* פשט *peshat* of the פסוקים pesukim, *pesukim* is they heard
it all they got it all it was all written down and
they said נעשה ונשמע *na'aseh venishma* to all of it. And then
ויקח את הדם ויזרק על העם *vayikach es hadam vayizrok al ha'am*
this is the דם הברית *dam habris* okay and that's what happened
at the end of the events of הר סיני *Har Sinai* משה
Moshe *Moshe* comes down tells them all of that tells them all
משפטים *mishpatim* they agree they enter into a ברית *bris*. And then
remember how the first פסוק pasuk *pasuk* I read to you was
come back up with the זקנים *zekenim*? So then he does it.
ויעל משה ואהרן נדב ואביהוא ושבעים מזקני ישראל ויראו את אלהי ישראל
*vaya'al Moshe ve'Aharon Nadav va'Avihu v'shiv'im miziknei Yisrael vayiru es Elohei Yisrael*
and that sort of very anthropomorphic פסוק pasuk *pasuk* okay. So that
is all right after הר סיני *Har Sinai*. Then what is the
next פסוק *pasuk* here at the very end of משפטים *Mishpatim*? ויאמר
ה' אל משה עלה אלי ההרה והיה שם ואתנה לך את לחת
האבן והתורה והמצוה אשר כתבתי להורותם *vayomer Hashem el Moshe aleh elai
haharah veheyeh sham v'esnah lecha es luchos ha'even vehaTorah vehamitzvah asher kasavti
lehorosam*. So then he says come up and we'll spend forty days
together and I'll tell you even more. Presumably that's after הר סיני
*Har Sinai* came down told it to them they did the ספר
הברית *sefer habris* they had this vision of God משה *Moshe* and
the זקנים *zekenim* then says now you come up and we'll spend
forty days together.
ויקם משה ויהושע משרתו ויעל אל הר האלקים *vayakom Moshe viYehoshua mesharto
vaya'al el Har HaElokim*. ואל הזקנים אמר *v'el hazekenim amar* and then
he says to the זקנים *zekenim* you guys stay down you got
one you got one opportunity to have that vision but you guys
now stay down שבו לנו בזה *shevu lanu bazeh*. ויעל משה אל
ההר ויכס הענן את ההר וישכן כבוד ה' על הר סיני ויכסהו
הענן ששת ימים ויקרא אל משה ביום השביעי Vayikra el Moshe bayom
ha-shevi'i מתוך הענן ומראה כבוד ה' וגו' ויבא משה בתוך b'soch הענן
ויעל אל ההר ויהי משה בהר ארבעים יום וארבעים לילה *vaya'al Moshe
el hahar vayichas he'anan es hahar vayishkon kevod Hashem al Har Sinai
vayichaseihu he'anan sheishes yamim vayikra el Moshe bayom hashvi'i mitoch he'anan umareh
kevod Hashem v'go' vayavo Moshe besoch he'anan vaya'al el hahar vayehi Moshe
bahar arba'im yom ve'arba'im lailah*. So it's very clear the פשט *peshat*
of the פסוקים psukim *pesukim* is he tells them all משפטים *mishpatim*
they have the ספר הברית *sefer habris* there was this one vision
with the זקנים *zekenim* משה *Moshe* goes up six days under the
six days in the cloud seventh day God calls him and then
that's the forty days that משה *Moshe* spends on the mountain and
that's exactly what ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* says. And what רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose ha-Gelili *Rabbi Yose HaGelili* say here is that this
was all preparing משה *Moshe* for going up and for being with
God for those forty days. Now what you're going to see, it's
obviously the פשט *peshat* of the פסוקים *pesukim*, but there's going to
be a different opinion because there's one פסוק *pasuk* that's a little
bit echoed. Because here you have right before the עשרת הדברות *Aseret
Hadibrot*, right, what does God say? God says to משה *Moshe* right
before the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot*, he says, ויקרא Vayikra. ה' למשה
ראש ההר ויעל משה *Vayikra Hashem l'Moshe rosh hahar vaya'al Moshe*. Right?
And then he says, רד העד בעם *Red ha-ed ba'am*, ויאמר משה
לא יוכל העם לעלות אל הר סיני *Vayomer Moshe lo yuchal ha'am
la'alot Har Sinai*, but you have ויקרא אל משה vayikra el Moshe,
ויעל משה *Vayikra el Moshe vaya'al Moshe*, and here on the day
on the seventh day it says ויקרא אל משה ביום השביעי Vayikra
el Moshe bayom ha-shevi'i מתוך הענן *Vayikra el Moshe bayom hashvi'i mitoch
he'anan*. So we're going to see an opinion that takes this entire
last paragraph, six days of the cloud and calling to משה *Moshe*
on the seventh day and says that didn't happen here. That actually
happened way back before the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot* were given and
that's when משה *Moshe* was being called and not afterwards. And now
let's see why that matters and why that's linked to ריש לקיש
*Resh Lakish*'s position. Okay, so let's take a look. Let's do this
again. Okay, תניא כוותיה דריש לקיש *Tanya k'vatah d'Resh Lakish*. משה עלה
בענן ונתכסה בענן ונתקדש בענן כדי לקבל תורה Torah. לישראל בקדושה *Moshe
ala be'anan veniskasa be'anan veniskadesh be'anan kedai l'kabel Torah l'Yisrael bikdusha*. שנאמר
וישכון כבוד ה' על הר סיני *Shene'emar vayishkon kvod Hashem al Har
Sinai*. זה היה מעשה אחר עשרת הדברות *Ze haya ma'aseh achar Aseret
Hadibrot*. This was actually the end of the משפטים *Mishpatim*. שהוא תחילה
לארבעים יום *Sheu tichla l'arba'im yom* and that began even the six-day
preparation as we'll see was included in the forty days and that
began the forty days that משה *Moshe* was at the top of
הר סיני *Har Sinai* after after the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot*. דברי
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose ha-Gelili *Divrei Rabbi Yose HaGelili*. That's what
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGelili* says. And משה *Moshe*
was therefore covered in the ענן anan. *anan* and that was his
preparing for that event. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר *Rabbi Akiva omer*,
וישכון כבוד ה' מראש חודש *Vayishkon kvod Hashem
merosh chodesh*. No, the last פרשה Parsha *parsha* paragraph of משפטים *Mishpatim*,
God's cloud was resting for six days, that wasn't after the עשרת
הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot*, that was six days earlier. That was on ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh*. And the six days were the six
days leading up to the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot*. ויכסהו הענן להר
vayichasehu he-anan la-har, *Vayichasehu he'anan le'har*. And when it says the cloud
covered it, it didn't cover משה *Moshe*, it covered the mountain. Now
why is he forced to say that? Because as Michael just signified,
משה *Moshe* was going back and forth the entire time. So you
can't say משה *Moshe* was in the cloud and in the separate
zone and preparing himself, right, because משה *Moshe* was running up and
down. So if this פרשה parsha *parsha* took place before מתן תורה
Torah *Matan Torah*,
then משה *Moshe*, there was none of this ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish*'s
idea of a six-day preparation to stand before God. And the cloud
did not cover משה *Moshe*, the cloud covered the mountain. One minute.
It says here. וישכון כבוד ה' על הר סיני ויכסהו הענן ששת
ימים *Vayishkon kvod Hashem al Har Sinai vayichasehu he'anan sheshet yamim*. That's
the question. What's the ויכסהו *vayichasehu*? No no, but like if you
look at it, you know. Okay, fine. One thing to mention the
פסוק *pasuk*. All right, fine. ויקרא Vayikra. אל משה *Vayikra el Moshe*.
Now we have to do why is God calling to משה *Moshe*?
Because according to the other approach, God calls משה *Moshe* so משה
*Moshe* can stand up there and be with God for the forty
days. But here, why is God calling משה *Moshe*? Because it's actually,
you know, now I read you right before the עשרת הדברות *Aseret
Hadibrot*, it says God called משה *Moshe*. ויקרא ה' למשה ויעל משה
*Vayikra Hashem l'Moshe vaya'al Moshe*. But God calls משה *Moshe* right before
the עשרת הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot* why? To say לך רד העד בעם
פן יהרסו אל ה' לראות *Lech red ha-ed ba'am pen yeher'su el
Hashem lirot*. Go back and tell them guys, keep away. And משה
*Moshe* says, hey you don't have to tell them, you know בני
ישראל *B'nei Yisrael*, you tell them once they listen.
And God says no, לך רד *lech red*. Trust me on this
one, משה *Moshe*, go back and tell them. Okay, so anyway, so
that ויקרא *vayikra*, right, is to call him up to have him
go down. So it seems like it's a little different than this
ויקרא *vayikra* at the end of משפטים *Mishpatim*, which is just He
called משה *Moshe* for what purpose? And it's not and so here
the he says now you could have said like Michael, I mean
it's an interesting question. Where was משה *Moshe* standing when the עשרת
הדברות *Aseret Hadibrot* were being given? Was he at the bottom of
the mountain with the people? Was he at the top of the
mountain with God? Right, I think we tend to think he was
at the top of the mountain. But the פסוקים *pesukim* are not
so clear. If you look in יתרו *Yitro*, right, after God says
go back again, he says ויאמר ה' לך רד ועלית אתה ואהרן
עמך והכהנים והעם אל יהרסו *Vayomer Hashem lech red ve'alita ata ve'Aharon
imach vehakohanim veha'am al yeher'su*. וירד משה ויאמר *Vayered Moshe vayomer*. So
first of all it never says that משה *Moshe* and אהרן *Aharon*
went back up like they were supposed to. Okay, but somewhere משה
*Moshe* is somewhere presumably midpoint in the mountain there. Because משה *Moshe*
also says in דברים *Devarim*, he says אנכי עומד בין ה' וביניכם
להגיד לכם את דבר ה' *Anochi omed bein Hashem uveinechem lehagid lachem
et dvar Hashem*. I was sort of between the two of you.
So anyway, so but we don't have what you have at the
end of משפטים *Mishpatim*, which is God just calling to משה *Moshe*
without then you know you know
without a clear what the purpose was. What you have in יתרו
*Yitro* is God calls משה *Moshe* and tells him go back down
and presumably then משה *Moshe* and אהרן *Aharon* go up by themselves.
And what you have in the end of משפטים *Mishpatim* if we're
to believe if we're to take the approach that that happened before
מתן תורה Torah *Matan Torah* is God just calling to משה *Moshe*
with no explanation about what that was about. So that's why right
now we try to understand what that ויקרא *vayikra* was about. Okay
we could have linked it to the ויקרא *Vayikra* and יתרו *Yisro*
but let's see what we do. ויקרא אל משה *Vayikra el Moshe*:
משה וכל ישראל עומדים *Moshe v'chol Yisroel omdim*. So משה *Moshe* and
כל ישראל *kol Yisroel* were standing there. It was not for משה
*Moshe* to go up into the cloud. משה *Moshe* was already where
he should have been, maybe it was halfway on the mountain, but
he was there with ישראל *Yisrael* and the ויקרא *Vayikra* was not
to go into the cloud. So what was the ויקרא *Vayikra*? ולא
בא הכתוב אלא לחלק כבוד למשה *Velo ba hakasuv ella lechalek kavod
leMoshe*, it just called משה *Moshe* to say, to tell everybody, משה
*Moshe* and בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael*, I'm about to tell you this,
so called משה *Moshe* to single him out, to give him special
recognition or special honor, but it was really that was the whole
purpose of the ויקרא *Vayikra*. Okay, and we're going to make a
little אגדתא *aggadeta* based on that a little bit later in a
little bit of a discussion. So it's quite fascinating, not only right
does רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* take this פרשה *parsha* at the end
of משפטים *Mishpatim* and say it's covering the mountain and it's all
taking place before הר סיני *Har Sinai*, but also the פסוק *pasuk*
that says ויקרא אל משה ביום השביעי מתוך הענן *Vayikra el Moshe
bayom hashvii mitoch heanan*, right, it doesn't then it says גמרא *gemara*
that would just be God called, okay, he was about to give
the תורה Torah. *Torah* and he calls משה *Moshe* and then he
gives the תורה *Torah*, משה *Moshe*, אנכי ה' אלקיך *Anochi Hashem Elokecha*
or something like that. And then it says ומראה כבוד ה' כאש
אכלת *Umareh kvod Hashem ke-esh ochelet* and then the last פסוק *pasuk*
ויבא משה בתוך b'soch הענן ויעל אל ההר ויהי שם ארבעים יום
וארבעים לילה *Vayavo Moshe betoch he-anan vaya'al el hahar vayehi sham arbaim
yom ve-arbaim layla*, that was after the עשרת הדברות *aseret hadibrot*. Okay,
so this entire פרשה *parsha* took place is a summary as you
would, the end of משפטים *Mishpatim*, the way רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
is reading it, is a little summary of everything of the two
פרשיות *parshiot* that preceded. So there was an ענן anan. *anan* there,
God called משה *Moshe*, parenthesis there was עשרת הדברות *aseret hadibrot*, and
then afterwards משה *Moshe* went up for forty days, and that whole
little paragraph at the end is not an event that took place
after הר סיני *Har Sinai*, it's summarizing everything from ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh*. And that's where the question is what's the ויקרא
*Vayikra* about? Okay, because it just says ויקרא *Vayikra* it doesn't say
for what purpose. And says oh, it's just לחלק כבוד למשה *lachlok
kavod leMoshe*. And the reason רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* is doing this
as opposed to the פשט *pshat* that this is I don't know
what motivated him, I don't. Okay, but that's how he's reading it.
רבי נתן אומר *Rabbi Nasan omer*, now רבי נתן *Rabbi Nasan* says,
ולא בא הכתוב אלא למרק אכילה ושתיה שבמעיו לשומו כמלאכי השרת *Velo
ba hakasuv ella lemorek achila veshistia shebim'av leasomo kemalachei hasharet*. So רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says this is specifically connected to the idea that he
was in the ענן anan *anan* for six days. But why being
in the ענן anan *anan*? Is it just an idea of separation,
sanctified? No, actually it was a process of making him more angelic,
making him less, you know, the same way for forty days he
didn't eat or drink, לחם לא אכל ומים לא שתיתי *lechem lo
achal umayim lo
shatati*, thank you, right, so in the period preceding, in the period
preceding to allow him to be there, he first had to cleanse
himself from as much physicality as possible and that was what being
in the ענן anan *anan* was about. So רש"י *Rashi* reads this
connected to the idea of being in the ענן anan *anan*, but
it's not about the this sort of general sense of קדושה *kedusha*
that can be applied to the כהן גדול *kohen gadol* on יום
כיפור *Yom Kippur*, because it was just for him because the כהן
גדול *kohen gadol* we don't say stop eating for six days. רבי
מתיא בן חרש אומר *Rabbi Matya ben Cheresh omer*, ולא בא הכתוב
אלא לאיים עליו *lo ba hakasuv ella le'ayem alav*. The reason again
the way רש"י *Rashi* reads it is the reason he was in
the ענן anan *anan* for six days was to strike fear in
his heart. כדי שתהא תורה ניתנת באימה ברת ובזיע *Kedei shetehei torah
nitenet be-eima beret uveze-a*. The תורה *Torah* should be given with fear
and trembling and sweat, שנאמר עבדו את ה' ביראה וגילו ברעדה *shene'emar
ivdu et Hashem beyira vegilu birada*,
serve God with fear and rejoice in trembling. מאי וגילו ברעדה *Mai
vegilu birada*, what does it mean rejoice in trembling? אמר רב אדא
בר מתנא אמר רב במקום גילה שם תהא רעדה *Amar Rav Adda
bar Matna amar Rav bimkom gila sham tehei ra'ada*. At the place
of rejoicing when you get the תורה *Torah*, on the one hand
it's a tremendous high, but on the other hand there has to
be the awe of this God encounter, the God encounter combining with
it the sense
of transcendence and high and so on with this profound sense of
awe and trembling. You know in a way that sort of the
balance of what happened to בני אהרן *Bnei Aaron*, if you want
to go back to the whole יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* story, right
בזאת יבא *bezot yavo*, there have to be a process, you don't
just go encounter God, there have to be that awe as well
and there have to be the וגילו ברעדה *gilu birada*. Now so
as I said רש"י *Rashi* says this is all explaining the approach
of רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili* of six days. מהרש"א *The
Maharsha* says it's a little bizarre because it comes right after רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. And מהרש"א *the Maharsha* says this could even be
fitting with רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. According to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
you still have to deal with the question of what's ויקרא אל
משה *Vayikra el Moshe*? What's the point ויקרא אל משה *Vayikra el
Moshe*? So one answer is to give him כבוד *kavod*. Another answer
is that that act of ויקרא אל משה *Vayikra el Moshe* basically
somehow that one act of calling
משה *Moshe* cleansed him out completely. And the third idea is it
struck fear in his heart. So these are three explanations the way
מהרש"א *the Maharsha* reads it of ויקרא אל משה *Vayikra el Moshe*.
We don need an explanation of the six days according to רבי
יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose HaGlili*, that's clearly a preparing him and putting
him in a state of קדושה *kedusha*. Now of course it is
pretty funny that of all the people who needed fear struck in
their heart, probably משה *Moshe* was
was the least of them unless you say אדרבה *adaraba* sort of
like the story of what was it חוני המעגל *Choni HaMa'agel* like
you're a בני בית *bnei bayit*, maybe you דוקא *davka* משה *Moshe*
because he felt so comfortable, the people believe me they had plenty
of awe and fear, they refused to get right they stepped away
from the mountain, they didn't want to get close, so anyway but
it is quite fascinating that it focus on משה *Moshe*. Now before
we go on now we're going to go to sort of unpack
these but you see these two models of רב יוסי *Rav Yossi*
of ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. I wanted
to mention that there is this book put out it must be
by 20 years now by רב *Rav* Aharon Lichtenstein which is a
דף *daf* by דף *daf* you know commentary sort of well like
a חידושים *chiddushim* of הרב *HaRav* of רב סולובייצ'יק *Rav Soloveitchik* on
מסכת יומא *Maseches Yoma*. Now it's not like דף *daf* by דף
*daf* like every דף *daf* he has you know he has a
paragraph. He basically takes like a topic that occurs and develops a
topic. So his first piece which basically context you know the second
piece is on דף י"ב *daf yud-bet*. But the first piece is
on our סוגיה *sugya* on about this debate of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* which he really develops at length
these two approaches and just to say very briefly what he says
I mean he just sharpens the ideas that we've been talking about
the themes that are there. He says that if it's based on
you know clearly he says ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* is in a
way easy to understand. It's about not about the עבודת יום הכיפורים
*avodas Yom HaKippurim* it's about that God encounter entering into the קודש
הקודשים *Kodesh Hakodashim* and it's about having that prepare you know creating
that sense of קדושה *kedusha* to prepare for the God encounter. But
he has a lot to say about רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*'s approach
about the מילואים *Miluim* and he has a very you know interesting
idea about it. He says you know on the one hand you
say yes it's about the עבודה *avoda* and a special act that's
needed to allow for the עבודה *avoda* to take place and prepare
the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* for the עבודה *avoda*. But then he
says more he says maybe what it's doing is if you really
base it on the מילואים *Miluim* maybe it is in a way
sort of giving him a special כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* status that
allows him to do the עבודה *avoda* on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*.
Almost like re-establishing him reaffirming him as the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*.
And that and that in that way you know it is you
know really sort of similar to that process of מילואים *Miluim* that
established the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim* as כהנים *Kohanim*. And then he tweaks
it a little bit and says and this is the whole idea
of like the הגר"א *HaGra* that it was a special הכשר *hechsher*
for אהרן *Aharon* to go in and then it became generalized. He
says maybe דווקא *davka* here you need the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*
to serve as a representative of אהרן *Aharon*. Very interesting idea. To
enter into the קודש הקודשים *Kodesh Hakodashim* maybe you have to דווקא
*davka* do it as a type of בזאת יבוא אהרן *Bezot Yavo
Aharon*. And that's why you had to sort of do this whole
process similar to the מילואים *Miluim* to give him this status and
then he speaks to the גמרא *Gemara* that we just did about
the שני תלמידי חכמים shenei talmidei chachamim *shnei talmidei chachamim* similar to
the sort of sense of משה *Moshe*. That the whole idea of
sort of recreating the process of the מילואים *Miluim* you know is
you have a substitute משה רבינו *Moshe Rabbeinu* which is the שני
תלמידי חכמים *shnei talmidei chachamim* and a substitute so this כהן גדול
*Kohen Gadol* becomes the substitute of אהרן *Aharon*. And that so it's
very powerful also thinking about you know what it would require to
enter into the קודש הקודשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*. He very much focuses on
this process of defining the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* status and this
idea of being a תלמיד *talmid* of being a representative of אהרן
*Aharon*. He also says Zev you'll appreciate this that the because I
think you mentioned something like this yesterday that some of the things
so first of all he says well why isn't it מעכב *me'akev*
you know what about the standing guy? Okay so בדיעבד *b'diavad* it's
not מעכב *me'akev* but then he gives a good reason why we
can't do it for the standing guy. Why not just do it
for the standing guy? What's the big problem? Okay so have him
wait seven days as well. He says no he says if the
idea is to raise his status as כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* you
need for that the foundation of him to start as כהן גדול
*Kohen Gadol* right? If you start as the כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*
then we can do this process that makes you the special כהן
גדול *Kohen Gadol* for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* or the כהן גדול
*Kohen Gadol* who's the representative of אהרן *Aharon*. But if you start
if you're the standing guy and you're not you don't even have
the basic identity of כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* we can't add the
various layers to you. Okay so בדיעבד *b'diavad* you'd have to actually
use this guy that didn't have the whole preparation but there's no
way to do the preparation for him. Interesting idea. But then he
sort of says this other point like Zev I think you said
which is that part of the whole thing of of preparing the
backups and so on is part of the ritual. It's not and
let me just try to find sort of the line that he
says that one minute.
He
says
alright I'll have to find it.
We have the nice idea of how to explain that a lot
of these rituals here were not just secondary things but they were
part of this whole process of preparing him and making him ראוי
rauy לעבודה *ra'uy la'avoda*.
Let me just give me one more second here.
Oh
yeah, yeah.
here it is. ויתקין שאף מה שמתקין לו כהן אחר הוא חלק
ממערך ההפרשה של הכהן הראשון
בהכשר עבודתו.
Okay,
he says like this, הרי, Harei, so
yeah,
I mean he just says... all right, he doesn't add too much
more than that, but what he does say is, he says that
if the whole idea is of this of the basis of the
מלואים is to allow him to sort of serve as כהן גדול
on יום כיפור, all the attendant things we do, the you know
making sure he doesn't become טמא, tamei, sprinkling the ashes of the
פרה אדומה, having a כהן as a backup, all of those are,
if you get down to it, what's all that about? To ensure
that he will be able to do the עבודה. So once you
base it on the מלואים, his point, then that's all about preparing
him for the עבודה, then you could look at everything we do
around that as ultimately being derived from it. And the שני תלמידי
חכמים who were standing in for משה, they're teaching him the עבודה,
right? So that is all part of this concept of the מלואים
of preparing and enabling the עבודה to take place. So anyway, the
bottom line is that he has a very nice thing if you
want to see more of it, but I think that
the sharpest point was that it basically raises his level to a
כהן גדול ראוי for the עבודה, and even this idea of sort
of like a substitute of אהרון Aharon and explaining why we could
not do it for the other כהנים. This is the גמרא אכילה
ושתייה שבמעי עובר achilah v'shtiyah she-b'mei ubar part, you know... No, he's
not the עובר. ubar. I'm saying what do we do there? So
that's why רש"י says that's not our basis, that's what's... Okay, so
let's get a little bit further. גמרא says like this: במאי קמיפלגי?
B'mai kamiflagi? What is the debate based on? רבי יוסי הגלילי and
רבי עקיבא בפלוגתא דהני תנאי, b'plugta d'hanei tanna'ei, the debate of the
following תנאים, Tanna'im, דתניא, as it is taught in a בריתא: Baraita:
בשישה בחודש ניתנה תורה לישראל. B'shishah b'chodesh nitnah Torah l'Yisrael.
The תורה was given on the sixth of סיון. Sivan. רבי יוסי
אומר בשיבעה בו, omer b'shivah bo, on the seventh. מאן דאמר
בשישה, Man d'amar b'shishah, if it was given on the sixth, so
we got the עשרת הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot on the sixth. משה went
up on the seventh and spent forty days on הר סיני, and
that ends in שבעה עשר בתמוז Shivah Asar b'Tammuz when he broke
the לוחות. luchos. מאן דאמר בשיבעה, Man d'amar b'shivah, if it was
given on the seventh, so בשיבעה ניתנה, b'shivah nitnah, so the עשרת
הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot on the seventh, but בשיבעה עלה, b'shivah alah, you
also have to say that משה went and began the forty days
on the seventh because nobody can deny that the forty days have
to begin on the seventh cause that will only that will get
us שבעה עשר בתמוז Shivah Asar b'Tammuz as the day he came
down. דכתיב ויקרא אל משה ביום השביעי. Dichktiv Vayikra el Moshe bayom
ha-shevi'i. So then he went up on the seventh day to begin
the forty days. So we have this debate, sixth or seventh. Now
how to fit in the פסוקים might be affected by the sixth
or seventh because we know they came to הר סיני on ראש
חודש. רבי יוסי הגלילי סבר לה כתנא קמא. savar lah k'Tanna Kamma.
רבי יוסי הגלילי holds like the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, that the
תורה was given on the sixth: דאמר בשישה בחודש ניתנה תורה. d'amar
b'shisha b'chodesh nitnah Torah. הילכך זה המעשה אחר עשרת הדיברות. Hilkach zeh
ha-ma'aseh achar Aseret HaDibrot. When God calls משה on day seven, which
we say at the end of משפטים, that can't be a story
of the beginning of the giving of the תורה. Right? You understand?
Since תורה was given on the sixth, and the פרשה at the
end of משפטים says God called משה on the seventh day, right,
so that can't be referring to the seventh day from them coming
to הר סיני because the תורה was given on the sixth, not
on the seventh. Okay, so therefore he has to push, say that
that whole story is occurring after הר סיני. Why doesn't he just
say because that's פשט of the פסוקים, I don't know, but anyway,
if day seven is when God called משה and was then gave
the עשרת הדיברות, Aseret HaDibrot, then that you need to say that
the עשרת הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot were given on the seventh of סיון,
Sivan, not the sixth. הילכך זה המעשה אחר עשרת הדיברות. Hilkach zeh
ha-ma'aseh achar Aseret HaDibrot. וישכון כבוד ה' על הר סיני ויכסהו הענן
ששת ימים למשה. Vayishkon kvod Hashem al Har Sinai vayichasehu he-anan sheshet
yamim l'Moshe. So that whole process was after, after the עשרת הדיברות
Aseret HaDibrot the cloud covered משה, ויקרא אל משה ביום השביעי לקבולי
שאר תורה. l'kabulei shear Torah. And then משה goes up on the
seventh day after the עשרת הדיברות Aseret HaDibrot to get the rest
of the תורה. ואי סלקא דעתך וישכון כבוד ה' מראש חודש, V'ei
salka daitach vayishkon kvod Hashem me-Rosh Chodesh, if we're going to read
that last פרשה in משפטים to be recapping everything starting at ראש
חודש, ויכסהו הענן להר, and it's covering the mountain, not משה, ויקרא
אל משה ביום השביעי לקבולי עשרת הדיברות. l'kabulei Aseret HaDibrot. According to
you got the עשרת הדברות *Aseres Hadibros* on the sixth. Okay, so
it's very simply: if you believe the עשרת הדברות *Aseres Hadibros* was
given on the sixth, of course you could say where do you
get that from? But all right, if you accept that the עשרת
הדברות *Aseres Hadibros* were given on the sixth, that whole פרשה *parsha*
at the end of משפטים *Mishpatim* can't be a recap because that
פרשה *parsha* emphasizes day seven. And according to this, the emphasis needs
to be day six. Does this whole מחלוקת *machlokes* of six or
seven have to do with פסח *Pesach* and counting? Yeah, but I'm
not getting into—let's just deal with what we have here. Okay, so
רבי עקיבא סבר לה *Rabbi Akiva savra lah* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva* says, והאי אסתלק עננא משישה *ve-hai istalak anana meshisha*, and the
עננא *anana* would have anyway been, you know, lifted up on the
sixth day after the תורה *Torah* was given and it wouldn't have
been there on day seven. רבי עקיבא סבר לה כרבי יוסי *Rabbi
Akiva savra lah ke-Rabbi Yosi*, דאמר בשבעה בחדש ניתנה תורה לישראל *d'amar
b'shiva be-chodesh nitna Torah l'Yisrael*. רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* would hold it
was on the seventh, which allows us to read the last פרשה
*parsha* in משפטים *Mishpatim* as a recap of the entire story. בשלמא
*Bishlama*—and therefore ויקרא משה *Vayikra Moshe* is on day seven to give
the עשרת הדברות *Aseres Hadibros*. Now בשלמא דרבי עקיבא *bishlama d'Rabbi Akiva*,
היינו דמשכחת לה בשבעה עשר בתמוז נשתברו לוחות *hainu d'meshachas lah b'shiva
asar b'Tamuz nishtabru luchos*. We get that it happened on שבעה עשר
בתמוז *Shiva Asar B'Tamuz*, the breaking of the לוחות *luchos*. עשרין וארבעה
דסיון *Esrin v'arba d'Sivan*, okay, you start counting the forty days from
day seven, which is, right, which is when משה *Moshe* went up
for the to for the forty days. The תורה *Torah* was given
on day—I'm sorry, the, yeah, he says the תורה *Torah* was given
on day seven and the forty days began on day seven and
משה *Moshe* began his forty days back then. So counting forty days
from day seven of סיון *Sivan*, you have twenty-four days remaining of
סיון *Sivan*, ושיתסר דתמוז *v'shissar d'Tamuz*, sixteen of תמוז *Tamuz*, is for
forty. מלו ארבעין יומין *Milu arbaiyn yomin*, that's your forty days דהוו
בטורא *d'havu b'tura*, ובשבעה עשר בתמוז נחית *u'v'shiva asar b'Tamuz nachis*, he
came down on the seventeenth of תמוז *Tamuz*, ואתבר בהו לוחות *v'atbar
behu luchos*, he broke the לוחות *luchos*. אלא לרבי יוסי הגלילי *Ela
l'Rabbi Yosi HaGelili*, דאמר ששה דפרישה וארבעין דטורא *d'amar shisha d'prisha v'arbaiyn
d'tura*, according to רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi HaGelili* you got a
problem. There's much more than forty days after the עשרת הדברות *Aseres
Hadibros* were given. Six days of separation, called on the seventh day,
and then forty days. You're not going to get שבעה עשר בתמוז
*Shiva Asar B'Tamuz* that way. Okay, well that's what they're going to
say. Okay, so ששה דפרישה וארבעין דטורא *shisha d'prisha v'arbaiyn d'tura*, עד
עשרין ותלת בתמוז לא אתו לוחות *ad esrin v'slas b'Tamuz lo asu
luchos*, it wouldn't have happened until the twenty-third of תמוז *Tamuz*. אמר
לך רבי יוסי *Amar lach Rabbi Yosi*, רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* gets
back to you, הגלילי *HaGelili*, ארבעין דטורא בהדי ששה דפרישה *arbaiyn d'tura
behadi shisha d'prisha*. No, the forty days included the six days of
preparation. So that's a fascinating—we never think about that, right? We think
he's up there with God for the forty straight days of getting
the תורה *Torah*, right? And he says no, actually, six of those
forty days was the preparatory process. He only was with God from
day seven on. Okay, I'm sure there's some nice מוסר *mussar* in
that about how, you know, about the journey and not also the
destination, part of that being with God was the process of preparing
to be with God. All right, so let's look a little bit
more. אמר מר ויקרא משה *Amar Mar Vayikra Moshe*. So משה וכולן
עומדין *Moshe v'chulan omdin*. So משה *Moshe* was there and every—and everybody
heard and it was just to give כבוד *kavod* to משה *Moshe*,
according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*. הגמרא *The Gemara* says מסייע ליה
לרבי אלעזר *misayei leih l'Rabbi Elazar*. This supports רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*.
דאמר רבי אלעזר *D'amar Rabbi Elazar*, ויקרא משה *Vayikra Moshe*, משה וכולן
עומדין ולא בא הכתוב אלא לחלק לו כבוד למשה *Moshe v'chulan omdin
v'lo ba haksav ela l'chalek lo kavod l'Moshe*. Okay, basically saying exactly
what רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* said. That it was not to call
him up to the mountain, this was, according to רבי עקיבא *Rabbi
Akiva*, at the moment of מתן תורה *Matan Torah*, and it was
to give him honor. מיתיבי *Meseivei*, I'll ask you on this because
that means the only way it gives honor to משה *Moshe* is
everybody else heard God's voice calling משה *Moshe*. So is that really
true that everybody else would have heard that voice? Here's a here's
a famous דרשה *drasha* we have. קול לו קול אליהם *Kol lo
kol eleihem*. It says, you know, that it says by by the
כרובים *keruvim*, it says ובבוא משה אל אהל מועד Ohel Moed לדבר
אתו וישמע את הקול מדבר אליו מבין שני הכרבים *U'v'vo Moshe el
ohel moed l'daber ito vayeishma es hakol midaber eilav mibein shnei hakeruvim*.
He heard the voice of God speaking to him from between the
two כרובים *keruvim*. The problem is why does it say מדבר אליו
*midaber eilav*? It should have been מדבר לו *midaber lo*. Right? What's
מדבר אליו *midaber eilav*? It should have said קולו *kolo*, it should
have said not קול אליו *kol eilav*. So to tell you the
following. משה שמע וכולן לא שמעו *Moshe shama v'chulan lo shamu*. The
voice was only—meaning if I'm מדבר לו *midaber lo*, it means who
are my words directed towards. Okay, but if it's מדבר אליו *midaber
eilav*, it means that only he was the one who heard it.
Not only they were directed to him, only he heard it. So
look, when God calls משה *Moshe* and speaks to משה *Moshe*, only
משה *Moshe* hears. So how could you say that calling משה *Moshe*
was לחלק לו כבוד *l'chalek lo kavod* if only משה *Moshe* was
the one who heard? So הגמרא *the Gemara* says, לא קשיא *lo
kashya*, הא בסיני הא באהל מועד *ha b'Sinai ha b'ohel moed*. Okay,
it was a one-time event at הר סיני *Har Sinai* that everybody
heard when God called משה *Moshe*. From there on in, God spoke
to משה *Moshe* and nobody heard. ואי בעית אימא *V'iy ba'is eima*,
if you want you could say, לא קשיא *lo kashya*, הא בקריאה
הא בדיבור *ha b'kriya ha b'dibur*. When God just says משה *Moshe*,
everybody hears. When then you get to the content of the speech,
what God needs to say, that's only משה *Moshe* is hearing. Be
fascinating to think that that occurred even after הר סיני *Har Sinai*.
Okay. רב זריקא רמי *Rav Zrika rami* קראי *krayi* קמיה דרבי אלעזר
*kamei d'Rabbi Elazar*. He showed a contradiction of פסוקים *psukim* to רבי
אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. ואמרי לה אמר רב זריקא אמר רבי אלעזר *v'amrei
lah amar Rav Zrika amar Rabbi Elazar*. Some say רב זריקא *Rav
Zrika* said in the name of רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar*. רבי אלעזר
רמי *Rabbi Elazar rami*, that רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* was the one
who showed the contradiction. כתיב *Ksiv*, ולא יכול משה לבוא אל אהל
מועד Ohel Moed. *v'lo yachol Moshe lavo el ohel moed*. ולא יכול
משה לבוא אל אהל מועד Ohel Moed. and he couldn't even go
into the אהל מועד Ohel Moed because of the ענן. anan Now
what's often not realized is that that and that's how שמות Shemos
ends. What's often not realized is that that connects to the first
פסוק in ויקרא. ויקרא אל משה מאהל מועד לאמר. Vayikra el Moshe
me-Ohel Moed l'mor. So משה couldn't go in, but here you're talking
about God calling to משה, but God calls משה from the אהל
מועד. Now does God, does he go in after he's called? Or
does he stay out and he hears God's voice? But those two
פסוקים have to be juxtaposed. Anyway, he can't penetrate the ענן. anan
Yeah, I mean not maybe physically, but certainly in terms of the
holiness of it. Okay, so here משה could not enter in. Okay,
וכתיב, v'chsiv, another פסוק says, ויבוא משה בתוך הענן. vayavo Moshe b'soch
he-anan. That by הר סיני he went into the ענן anan. for
the forty days. So what was it? Is he able to go
into the ענן anan of God's presence or not? So you could
say he needs to be called. He was called at the end
of משפטים, ויקרא אל משה, and he was called at the beginning
of ויקרא. But let's see what his answer is. So מלמד שתפסו
הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה והביאו בענן. melamed she-tefasa Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Moshe
v'hivio be-anan. משה himself couldn't go into the ענן anan or he
wouldn't go into the ענן where God was. But God forced him
into the ענן at the time of הר סיני. Beautiful imagery. דבי
רבי ישמעאל תנא D'vei Rebbi Yishmael tana and the house of ישמעאל
Yishmael they teach, נאמר כאן בתוך, ne'emar kan b'soch, ונאמר להלן בתוך.
v'ne'emar le-halan b'soch. There it says he couldn't go, here it says
by הר סיני he went בתוך ענן. b'soch anan. Okay, so what
does בתוך mean? It says בתוך somewhere else. ויבאו בני ישראל בתוך
הים. vayavo'u bnei Yisrael b'soch hayam. מה להלן שביל, ma le-halan shvil,
the same way there there was a path, אף כאן שביל, af
kan shvil, here I'm sorry, דכתיב המים להם חומה, d'chsiv hamayim lahem
chomah, אף כאן שביל. af kan shvil. So משה can't go into
the ענן on on אהל מועד. Why was he able to go
up into the ענן where God was? God made a path for
him. He allowed him to go into the ענן. But obviously what
the גמרא is dealing with is the again the impossibility of the
divine human encounter, right? God goes up, he's in, משה goes up,
he's in מחנה שכינה, is it really possible to be there with
God? You know, so the first answer is, yeah, God can make
it happen. The other answer is, not fully. It was a path,
the cloud was around him, he wasn't really in the cloud. By
the way, how did anybody go into the אהל מועד to do
the עבודה if if משה couldn't go in? So that another מדרש
medrash says the ענן would lift up and then you could go
in to do the עבודה. But when the ענן was there, you
couldn't go in. So that's the end question dealing with: is it
really possible to go into מחנה שכינה? Okay, so.