Okay בוקר טוב *boker tov*, today's דף daf *daf* is ג *gimmel*.
We pick up with the second line, we'll read the first line
again. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is dealing with the fact that our
משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* speaks about a seven-day preparation of the כהן גדול
kohen gadol *Kohen Gadol* to do the עבודה avodah *Avodah* on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur? *Yom Kippur*. He would be separated out of his
house. Similarly, a seven-day preparation for the כהן Kohen *Kohen*, we learn
in a משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* from פרה Parah *Parah*, that would do
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *Parah Adumah*. And the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's*
question is, where is this from? And the first answer that we've
been focusing on bases it on the verse of מילואים Miluim *Miluim*
where it was also seven days' preparation before the כהנים kohanim. *Kohanim*
began doing the עבודה avodah *Avodah* in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beit Hamikdash*. And the verse says there, כאשר עשה ביום הזה צוה
ה׳ לעשת לכפר עליכם *kaasher asah bayom hazeh tsivah Hashem la'asot lekaper
alechem*, where the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* interprets to mean God commanded to
do like this for future events. Which events? So one event is
פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *Parah Adumah*, which is based on a גזירה
שוה *gezerah shavah* of צוה צוה *tsivah tsivah*. And the other event
is יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*. And the question is, how
do we know יום כיפור Yom Kippur? *Yom Kippur*? So because it
links it to the word לכפר *lekaper*. But לכפר *lekaper* is a
very generic word; it could refer to קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* as well.
But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, but it has to be
something similar to יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*. It can't be
like a regular thing; it has to be a special event. So
it says, and it has to be an event that's a one-day
event. So it can't be the רגלים *regalim*, but maybe, says the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it's שמיני עצרת Shmini Atzeret, *Shmini Atzeret*, that's a
one-day event. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, we would
not do a preparation for שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres *Shmini Atzeret* and
not do a preparation for סוכות *Sukkot*. And even though we say
שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres, *Shmini Atzeret* is somewhat independent of סוכות *Sukkot*,
and we'll pick up with that, it says הני מילי לענין פז״ר
קש״ב *hanei mili le'inyan Pezer Keshev*, top of ג עמוד א *gimmel
amud aleph*. Yes, it is independent for the idea of פז״ר קש״ב
*Pezer Keshev*: פייס *Payis*, its own lottery to determine a new cycle
of קרבנות korbanos *korbanot*; זמן *Zman*, a new שהחיינו *Shehecheyanu* as opposed
to the last day of חג chag. המצות *Chag Hamatzot*; רגל בפני
עצמו *Regel bifnei atzmo*, which is not clear what that means, let's
say it means that you don't have the same חג *chag*, you
don't sit in the סוכה *sukkah*, take the לולב *lulav*; קרבן korban
בפני עצמו *Korban bifnei atzmo*, an independent קרבן korban *korban*, not part
of the regular cycle; שיר *Shir*, we do not do the same
שיר של יום yom *shir shel yom* on the קרבנות *korbanot*. רש״י
Rashi *Rashi* says the שיר של יום *shir shel yom* on the
קרבנות *korbanot*, or the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, would be on סוכות
*Sukkot* based on מתנות עניים *matanot aniyim*, on שמיני Shmini. עצרת Atzeret
*Shmini Atzeret* it would be something distinct. And ברכה בפני עצמו *Bracha
bifnei atzmo*, רש״י *Rashi* says might be a special blessing to the
king, or it means that in the שמנה עשרה *Shmoneh Esrei* we
refer to it by a different name, and in ברכת המזון *Birkat
Hamazon* we refer to it יום השמיני yom hashmini: חג העצרת הזה
*Yom Hashmini Chag Ha'atzeret hazeh*. Yes, it has all these ways it's
independent, but nevertheless, it's clearly the eighth day of סוכות *Sukkot* and
it clearly is linked to סוכות *Sukkot*. אבל לענין תשלומין *Aval le'inyan
tashlumin*, but when it comes to making up missed קרבנות *korbanot*, תשלומין
דראשון הוא *tashlumin derishon hu*. It still is a day that you
make it up for missing the קרבן korban *korban* of the first
day of יום טוב yom tov *Yom Tov*, דתנן *dehatnan*, we taught
in the משנה *Mishnah*: מי שלא חג ביום טוב ראשון של חג
*mi shelo chag beyom tov rishon shel chag*, if you do not
bring your קרבן korban חגיגה *korban chagigah* on the first day of
יום טוב *Yom Tov*, חוגג והולך כל הרגל כולו *chogeg veholech kol
haregel kulo*, you can make up your קרבן korban, חגיגה *korban chagigah*
and bring it any day of the רגל *regel*. ביום טוב אחרון
של חג *beyom tov acharon shel chag*, you can even bring it
on the last day, even on שמיני Shmini, עצרת Atzeret *Shmini Atzeret*.
And the רמב״ם *Rambam* says it's also about the עולת ראיה *olat
re'iah*, not just about the שלמי חגיגה *shalmei chagigah*. Question about the
שלמי שמחה *shalmei simcha*, but that's a more bigger question about whether
the מצוה *mitzvah* of שלמים *shlamim* is every day, is one day,
and so on. But anyway, the last day, שמיני Shmini, עצרת Atzeret
*Shmini Atzeret*, is a makeup day for the קרבנות *korbanot* that you
should have brought on סוכות *Sukkot* itself. So clearly שמיני Shmini, עצרת
*Shmini Atzeret* is related, is part of סוכות *Sukkot*, and it would
not make sense to say you need a preparation, a seven-day separation,
for שמיני Shmini עצרת *Shmini Atzeret* and not need it for the
חג *chag* which it is the culmination of, and not need it
for סוכות *Sukkot* itself. So it cannot be that the seven-day preparation
is just for שמיני Shemini עצרת *Shmini Atzeret*, and therefore we are
going to say this goes to be for יום כיפור Yom Kippur?
*Yom Kippur*. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* now turns to the next
obvious candidate. If you've ruled out פסח *Pesach* and סוכות *Sukkot* and
שמיני עצרת *Shmini Atzeret*, and you're looking for a one-day יום טוב
*Yom Tov*, well, there seems to be one obvious one that is
left which the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* about to turn to. But first
we have to answer אוצי׳ס *Otsi's* question. Yeah?
I'm surprised they don't mention second day יום טוב *Yom Tov* and
how if the second day was really the first day, the eighth
day would really be the seventh.
Yeah, but that's not relevant. We're trying to understand the פסוקים *psukim*.
So the whole later practice of second day יום טוב *Yom Tov*...
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ואימא ve'eima... עצרת *ve'eima Atzeret*. So
ironically it's called עצרת *Atzeret* here, which we know חז״ל׳ס *Chazal's* term
for שבועות Shavuot? *Shavuot*, but it's a switch from שמיני עצרת *Shmini
Atzeret* to עצרת *Atzeret*, which is שבועות Shavuot *Shavuot*. How about שבועות
Shavuot *Shavuot*? That's a one-day יום טוב *Yom Tov*, so that's perfect.
It's a perfect analogy to the מילואים Miluim, *Miluim*, seven days' preparation
for a one-day event, for the one day of שבועות Shavuot. *Shavuot*.
דפרישה שבעה ליומא חד *deparisha shiva leyoma chad*, who went to a
seven-day separation for a one-day event? So אמר ליה amar lei, רבא
*amar lei Rava*: דנין פר par אחד ואיל v'ayil. אחד מפר אחד
ואיל אחד mi'par echad v'ayil echad, *danin par echad ve'ayil echad mipar
echad ve'ayil echad*, לאפוקי עצרת la'apukei Atzeret דשני אילים eilim, נינהו *leafukei
Atzeret dishnei eilim ninhu*. So he says, if you take a look
at the, can I have that חומש *Chumash*? Yeah. At the פסוקים
*psukim*. So by the מילואים Miluim.
*Miluim*, you have it was a seven-day preparation for one day, and
that one day, what did they bring? They brought פר par, אחד
ואיל אחד *par echad ve'ayil echad*. If you look at ויקרא Vayikra
ח *Vayikra Chet*.
This isn't the seven-day preparation before שבועות Shavuot? though is it?
That's what it's suggesting, why not? If it's going to be one
day, why pick the one day as יום כיפור? Yom Kippur How
about picking it as שבועות? Shavuot, That's a one-day חג. So it
says, no, listen to what they would do when it's in terms
of that, in terms of that, what do you call it, in
terms of the מלואים. Miluim. It says the following. It says,
hold on, it says like
this, it says,
yeah, it says like this: ויהי ביום השמיני, Vayehi bayom hashmini, not
in פרק ח, perek chet, פרק ט, perek tet, beginning of שמיני.
קרא משה לאהרן ולבניו ולזקני ישראל. Kara Moshe le'Aharon ule'vanav uleziknei Yisrael.
ויאמר להם, ויאמר אל אהרן: קח לך עגל בן בקר לחטאת ואיל
לעלה תמימים והקרב לפני השם. kach lecha egel ben bakar lechatat ve'ayil
le'olah tmimim vehakrev lifnei Hashem.
So what is the culmination? Day eight? One עגל, egel, one calf
for חטאת chatat and one ram for an עולה. olah. And that's
for אהרן. Aharon. ולבני ישראל תדבר לאמר: קחו שעיר עזים לחטאת ועגל
וכבש בני שנה תמימים לעלה. Ule'vnei Yisrael tedaber leimor: kchu se'ir izim
lechatat ve'egel vakeves bnei shana tmimim le'olah. And בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
takes a goat for a חטאת chatat and an עגל egel and
a כבש. keves. Now compare that to יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. What
do we know happens on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur So on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur
we
have... so remember what we said here on יום השמיני: yom hashmini.
עגל בן בקר לחטאת ואיל אחד לעולה egel ben bakar lechatat ve'ayil
echad le'olah for אהרן. Aharon. What is יום כיפור? Yom Kippur יום
כיפור Yom Kippur is, right? בזאת יבא אהרן אל הקדש בפר בן
בקר לחטאת ואיל לעלה. Bezot yavo Aharon el hakodesh bepar ben bakar
lechatat ve'ayil le'olah. Exact same. It's a פר par, versus איל ayil
but basically cow, calf for a חטאת chatat and an איל ayil
for an עולה. olah. That was for אהרן. Aharon. That was also
for אהרן Aharon on יום השמיני. And בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, by
the way, parenthetically, is also somewhat similar. Right? Because here it says:
ומאת עדת בני ישראל יקח שני שעירי עזים לחטאת ואיל אחד לעלה.
ume'et adat bnei Yisrael yikach shnei se'irei izim lechatat ve'ayil echad le'olah.
And here was: קחו שעיר עזים לחטאת ועגל וכבש בני שנה תמימים
לעלה. kchu se'ir izim lechatat ve'egel vakeves bnei shana tmimim le'olah. So
not exactly the same but a very similar structure. But there is
in terms of אהרן, Aharon, which is by the way the whole
separation here is for the כהן kohen and is for אהרן, Aharon,
there is an exact parallel of a cow, a calf, you know,
a bull or a calf or anyway from the cow family for
a חטאת chatas and an איל לעולה. ayil le'olah. So it says
that's why we want to apply the מלואים Miluim to יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur And we don't want to apply it to שבועות Shavuot?
because שבועות Shavuot? we have two אילים, not one איל, ayil, and
therefore we do not want to apply it to שבועות. Shavuot What
do we have by שבועות?
Shavuot But the idea of the מלואים Miluim where there's a preparatory
time, a separation seven and then one, eight? Because the מלואים Miluim
happened at a certain time of year.
Yeah, so based on the פסוק, pasuk, no, but based on the
פסוק: pasuk: כאשר עשה ביום הזה צוה השם לעשות לכפר עליכם, ka'asher
asa bayom hazeh tziva Hashem la'asot lachaper aleichem, we learn that the
מלואים Miluim is a model for doing similar paradigm and but it
has to be similar to the מלואים. Miluim. Okay. Now if you
look at שבועות, Shavuot, what does it say by שבועות? Shavuot, So
you have to understand that the גמרא's Gemara focusing not on the
מוסף Musaf because there was a מוסף Musaf on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur as well. We're ignoring the מוסף Musaf and there was a
מוסף Musaf on the eighth day of the מלואים Miluim because it
happened to be ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. So we're not looking at
the מוסף, Musaf, we're talking about what is unique to that day
for the special עבודה avodah of the day. So special עבודה avodah
of the מלואים Miluim which is the פר לחטאת par lechatat and
איל לעולה ayil le'olah for אהרן. Aharon. There's a special עבודה avodah
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur which is a פר, par, an איל,
ayil, you know which is an עגל לחטאת egel lechatat and an
איל לעולה. ayil le'olah. Now how about on שבועות? Shavuot, Well שבועות
Shavuot, had a מוסף Musaf but let's bracket the מוסף. Musaf. The
difference is the מוסף, Musaf, שבועות Shavuot. have the special עבודה avodah
for the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. What does it say there for
the שתי הלחם? shtei halechem? So that's the פסוק pasuk in אמור
Emor and אמור Emor the פסוק pasuk says the following. Thank you.
It
says: והקרבתם על הלחם, vehikravtem al halechem, this is כג יח: chaf
gimmel yod chet: שבעת כבשים תמימים בני שנה, shivat kvasim tmimim bnei
shana, so already we're doing seven sheep. ופר בן בקר אחד ואילם
שנים יהיו עלה להשם. Ufar ben bakar echad ve'eilim shnayim yihyu olah
l'Hashem. So first of all, it's not a פר לחטאת. par lechatat.
It's a פר, par, yes it is a פר, par but it's
a פר לעולה par l'olah and שנים אילים לעולה. shnayim eilim l'olah.
And there's also six sheep as well. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this: for יום כיפור Yom Kippur, ignoring the מוסף, Musaf, the
special עבודה avodah of the יום for אהרן Aharon was a פר
לחטאת, par lechatat, איל לעולה. ayil le'olah. For the מלואים Miluim it
was a פר לחטאת, par lechatat, איל לעולה ayil le'olah for אהרן.
Aharon. For שבועות, Shavuot. first of all, there were six sheep, but
let's even bracket that. Okay, this is for the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem not for the מוסף. Musaf. There was one
פר, par parenthetically it was an עולה olah not a חטאת, chatat,
already that's a difference, we'll get back to that. And there were
שנים אילים shnayim eilim not one איל. ayil. So therefore that is
less similar and we would rather make it apply to יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. which is identical rather than to the מלואים. Miluim. So
let's read that again. So it says: אמר רבי אבא דני פר
אחד. Amar Rabi Abba dani par echad. איל אחד, ayil echad, which
is what you have by the מילואים Miluim, on the eighth day
that אהרן Aharon brought, or no, that's what you also have by
יום כיפור Yom Kippur. that אהרן Aharon brought, מפר אחד ואיל אחד,
you learn it out from the one פר par, and the one
איל, ayil, פר לחטאת ואיל לעולה par l'chatas v'ayil l'olah of the
מילואים, Miluim. לאפוקי le'apukei, עצרת and you would not apply it to
עצרת to שני אילים נינהו. shnei eilim ninhu. Yes, it's one cow,
and by the way, I'm telling you because a little bit of
a foreshadowing, that one cow anyway is an עולה olah not a
חטאת, chatas, so already that's a difference, and it's שני אילים, shnei
eilim, not one איל. ayil. הגמרא Gemara says one minute. הני ניחא
למאן דאמר יום הכפורים איל אחד הוא. hani nicha leman de'amar Yom
Hakippurim ayil echad hu. That's good if you say on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur there was only one איל. ayil. אלא למאן דאמר שני
אילים נינהו, ela leman de'amar shnei eilim ninhu, but there's an opinion
that says on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. you would bring not one
ram but two rams. Although the פסוק pasuk says like עגל בן
בקר לחטאת ואיל אחד לעולה, eigel ben bakar lechatas ve'ayil echad le'olah,
where would you get two rams? מאי איכא למימר, mai ika lemeimar,
so we'll see in a minute. What can you say? It's not
similar. דתניא, detanya, and here's where we taught that. רבי אומר, Rabbi
omer, איל אחד הוא האמור כאן הוא האמור בחומש פקודים. ayil echad
hu ha'amur kan hu ha'amur be'chumash pekodim.
The איל אחד ayil echad that it says by יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur? by the, you know, by אחרי מות, Acharei Mos, עגל בן
בקר לחטאת ואיל אחד לעולה, eigel ben bakar lechatas ve'ayil echad le'olah,
right? That's what you have by אחרי מות. Acharei Mos. So you
have another thing you have to reconcile, which is that in במדבר,
Bamidbar, in פנחס, Pinchas, it speaks about the מוסף musaf of יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur Right? In
פנחס Pinchas talks about all the מוספים. musafim. And there within the
מוסף musaf it also mentions an איל. ayil. If you take a
look at פנחס Pinchas it says in the מוסף musaf it says,
ובעשור לחדש השביעי הזה מקרא קדש יהיה לכם ועניתם את נפשתיכם כל
מלאכה לא תעשו והקרבתם עלה לה' ריח ניחוח פר בן בקר אחד
איל אחד כבשים בני שנה שבעה תמימים
יהיו לכם ומנחתם סלת בלולה בשמן שלשה עשרנים לפר שני עשרנים לאיל
האחד עשרון עשרון לכבש האחד לשבעת הכבשים מלבד חטאת הכפרים ועלת התמיד
ומנחתה ונסכיהם. uve'asor lachodesh hashvi'i hazeh mikra kodesh yihyeh lachem ve'inisem es
nafshoseichem kol melacha lo sa'asu vehikravtem olah la-Shem reiach nichoach par ben
bakar echad ayil echad kevasim bnei shana shiva tmimim yihyu lachem u'minchatam
solet belula va'shemen shlosha esronim la'par sheni esronim la'ayil ha'echad isaron isaron
la'keves ha'echad l'shivat ha'kevasim milvad chatas hakippurim v'olat ha'tamid u'minchatah v'niskeihem. So
it seems very clear that this is completely independent. This is a
מוסף. musaf. It has nothing to do with אחרי מות Acharei Mos
which is the whole special עבודת יום הכפורים. avodas Yom Hakippurim. This
is the מוסף. musaf. And the only thing is that there's one
animal that does overlap. פר בן בקר אחד par ben bakar echad
is not the same פר par, that we have by יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur יום כיפור Yom Kippur, it's עגל בן בקר לחטאת. eigel
ben bakar lechatas. Here it's an עולה. olah. Okay, the seven כבשים
kevasim we don't have by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur But there is
one thing that is similar. In פנחס Pinchas it mentions a ram
for an עולה olah for a מוסף musaf and in אחרי מות
Acharei Mos it mentions a ram for an עולה. olah. So are
those the same ram or not the same ram?
So comes along and he also differs.
Everything else is different, so of course the complete logic is to
say it's different. But רבי Rabbi for some reason says it's the
same. Why רבי Rabbi wants to say it's the same is not
clear at all. But let's, by the way, let me just talk
about this anyway, it's useful to have this. You have אחרי מות,
Acharei Mos, right? What does it say? It says קח
לך,
kach
lecha, this is for אהרן, Aharon, עגל בן בקר לחטאת eigel ben
bakar lechatas and איל אחד לעולה. ayil echad le'olah.
Now and by the way for בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael it says
יקחו
שני שעירי
עזים לחטאת
yikchu shnei se'irei izim le'chatas
and איל אחד לעולה. ayil echad le'olah. Okay.
Now by the way, just so you remember how this stuff is
used, okay? This is the one that he does the וידויה viduya
on, right? וכפר בעדו ובעד
ביתו, ve'chiper ba'ado uve'ad beiso, right? And then he goes in, right?
And he sprinkles the blood of that one, remember that? He goes,
he slaughters his פר, par, he does the whole sprinkle, the seven,
the אחת ושבע achas ve'sheva etc. This is, one goes לעזאזל, la'Azazel,
right? לעזאזל la'Azazel and one, one, what was
the, anyway,
okay?
And one basically parallels this פר, par right? One goes and one
goes, you know, into gets the whole one plus seven treatment, gets
the blood sprinkled on the inside, right? This is וכפר בעד, ve'chiper
ba'ad, no, no, וכיפר בעד
כל עדת בני
ישראל,
ve'chiper ba'ad
kol adas Bnei Yisrael, no,
this is the one he says the וידויה viduya on actually. Okay,
anyway, so this is, so anyway, so this is the שני שעירים,
shnei se'irim, right? So this is the focus of the יום הכפורים.
Yom Hakippurim. You see this one עגל eigel and these שני שעירים.
shnei se'irim. Okay, this, the איל אחד לעולה ayil echad le'olah basically,
after the, just as, oh yeah, go ahead and do the איל
ayil after you're done with everything, just bring the איל עולה. ayil
olah. And these two איל עולות ayil olot are not so, don't
play a very central role. These parts that play the central role.
And then this is what you have at אחרי מות. Acharei Mos.
And then in פנחס Pinchas you have it basically saying, what's the
מוסף musaf of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur It says that the מוסף
musaf of יום
כיפור
Yom
Kippur is איל אחד, ayil echad, פר בן
בקר אחד, par ben bakar echad, פר, par right? ואיל. עולה olah
and seven כבשים, kvasim, right?
Okay. ושבעה כבשים. veshivah kvasim.
Okay. And all of those are an עולה. olah. So this obviously
isn't the same, because here's a חטאת. chatas. This obviously looks... here's
an איל לעולה. ayil le'olah. Okay. So it obviously makes sense to
assume that this is something completely different than this, right? But for
some reason, רבי Rebbi says, no, this איל ayil here is the
same as the איל ayil over there. Okay. So according to him,
there's only one total איל. ayil. Okay. But let's go back and
take a look... Well, you still have the one for
בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael.
If יהודה Yehuda said it's the same,
you would say it's the same? Really? Even everything else is different?
It was like the defining link.
All right, anyway, fine.
What? Yes, that's true too. I was going to say that. If
I had to say it was the same, I would have said
it's the same as the one for בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, not
the one for אהרן, Aharon, right? Because a מוסף mussaf is for
all of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, so that's also very strange. Okay,
anyway, let's take a look. Hold on one second.
I just want to see one thing.
Did
we stop before seeing where רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer berabbi
Shimon was the one who says שנים?
shnayim? Wait a minute, wait a minute.
Yeah, it says ויצא, veyatza, after he's done with the whole thing
of sending the שעיר לעזאזל, sa'ir la'azazel, ויצא ועשה את עולתו ואת
עולת העם וכפר בעדו ובעד העם, veyatza ve'asah es olaso ve'es olas
ha'am vechiper ba'ado uve'ad ha'am, like just dispatched with the עולה olah
very quickly. But right, if you're going to link them, you would
have linked it at least to the one of בני ישראל. Bnei
Yisrael. Anyway, let's take a look. Because the גמרא Gemara says,
אלא מאן דאמר שנים נינהו מאי איכא למימר? ella man de'amar shnayim
ninu mai ikka lemeimar? דתניא, detanya, רבי Rebbi אומר, omer, איל אחד
הוא האמור כאן הוא האמור בחומש פקודים. ayil echad hu ha'amur kan
hu ha'amur beChumash Pikudim. רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon
אומר, omer, שני אילים הם האמור כאן והאמור בחומש פקודים. shnei eilim
hem ha'amur kan veha'amur beChumash Pikudim. So according to him, it's two
rams, so even יום כיפור Yom Kippur. is not like the מילואים.
Miluim So the answer seems pretty obvious. Let's see what the answer
is. גמרא Gemara says, אפילו תימא afilu teima רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון,
Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon, התם חד דחובת היום וחד דמוספים. hasam chad
dechovas hayom vechad demussafim. No, there the other ram is for the
מוסף. mussaf. Where... and you know, as תוספות Tosafot points out, there
was even a מוסף mussaf on the eighth day of the מילואים,
Miluim which we're ignoring. It was the מוסף mussaf of ראש חודש.
Rosh Chodesh. We're not talking about the מוסף. mussaf. We're talking about
the special קרבן korban. that was for the special עבודה avodah of
the day. And as far as that's and as far as that's
concerned, right, this which was for אהרן Aharon would be exactly the
same as what we have for the מילואים. Miluim The מילואים Miluim
we have is the פר לחטאת par lechatas and an איל לעולה.
ayil le'olah. So the special thing, not the מוסף, mussaf, but the
special עבודה avodah of the day, was exactly the same. לאפוקי, le'apukei
to exclude, עצרת by שמיני עצרת, I mean by שבועות, Shavuos, דתרוייהו
חובת היום נינהו, detarvaihu chovas hayom ninu, both rams are the חובת
היום. chovas hayom. Because in ויקרא where it mentions not the מוסף
mussaf of שבועות, but what is brought על הלחם, al halachem, הקרבתם
על הלחם, hikravtem al halachem, so it's very different than that, right?
So what we have by what we have by מילואים Miluim in
the beginning of
שמיני, by מילואים Miluim is פר לחטאת par lechatas
and איל לעולה. ayil le'olah. That's in the beginning of פרשת שמיני.
Parshas Shmini. And by שבועות, which we have in אמור, Emor, which
is not the מוסף mussaf but the הקרבתם על הלחם, hikravtem al
halachem, the special עבודה avodah of the day, we have first of
all שבעה כבשים. shivah kvasim. So that's already one way in which
it's different, right? And then we have פר par and פר par
and we have שני אילים. shnei eilim. Okay? So we actually have
two major differences. It's even bracketing this. But anyway, it's saying ignore
the מוסף, mussaf, if you look at the חובת היום, chovas hayom,
it's two and this is only one. As I'm pointing
out, even the פר par, is different. This is an עולה olah
and here it's a חטאת. chatas.
Okay? So that's what you would bring on the שתי הלחם shtei
halachem on שבועות. So we therefore cannot link it to that.
Is it just that the מילואים Miluim just had to be described
in
פשט?
pshat? It says second... Yeah, yeah, yeah, but שמיני, we're only talking
about the eighth day. We're talking about the culmination. Okay.
ואימא... ve'eima Okay, fine, so forget שבועות. But hey, there's another one-dayer
that we forgotten. ואימא ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. How about ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashanah? דאית פרישה שבעה ימים ליום אחד הוא, de'it prishah shivah
yamim leyom echad hu, to the seven-day separation for one day. אמר
רבי אבהו... amar Rabbi Abbahu...
I'm sorry, how do you get a seven-day separation?
Well, you'll start seven days before, meaning we're looking for one special
day that we can, you know, have the preparation for. So אמר
רבי אבהו, amar Rabbi Abbahu, דונין פר ואיל שלו מפר ואיל שלו.
donin par ve'ayil shelo mipar ve'ayil shelo. לאפוקי עצרת ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah דציבור נינהו. detzibbur ninu. Here's another difference. Yes, on ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah it would be... Now, what would be the קרבן korban.
on ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? So first of all, one of the
differences is now in order to find a קרבן korban on ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah you have to go back to... מוסף, Musaf, we've
been bracketing מוסף, Musaf, right? There's nothing on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
other than the מוסף. Musaf. What would be the קרבן korban on
ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah? What is the קרבן מוסף? korban Musaf? So
it says in פנחס: Pinchas: ובחודש השביעי באחד לחודש מקרא קודש יהיה
לכם כל מלאכת עבודה לא תעשו יום תרועה יהיה לכם ועשיתם עולה
לריח ניחוח לה' פר בן בקר אחד איל אחד. uvachodesh hashvii be'echad
lachodesh mikra kodesh yihyeh lachem kol melechet avodah lo taasun yom teruah
yihyeh lachem vaasitem olah lereach nichoach la-Hashem par ben bakar echad ayil
echad. So we have the פר par and the איל. ayil. But
of course כבשים בני שנה שבעה תמימים. kevasim bnei shanah shivah tmimim.
We do have a still difference. But at least by מוסף, Musaf,
okay, by ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah now we are going to deal
with the מוסף Musaf קרבן, korban, not some unique thing for איל,
ayil, we have פר, par איל, ayil, and שבעה כבשים. shivah kevasim.
And I mean you see the basic structure of actually that kind
of מוסף Musaf anyway, שבעה כבשים. shivah kevasim. So we do have
the one פר par and the one איל ayil is the same,
but there's two differences. Number one is the שבעה כבשים, shivah kevasim,
and number two is that these are all עולות, olot, here it's
פר לחטאת. par lachatat. But the גמרא Gemara is ignoring that and
saying, "Oh, you want a פר par and an איל? ayil? I've
got a פר par and an איל ayil for a one day
יום טוב just like the מילואים Miluim where you had a פר
par and an איל." ayil.
What's the מוסף Musaf for שבת? Shabbat? The regular שבת?
Shabbat? שני כבשים. shnei kevasim. Right. Okay, so, so
the גמרא's Gemara answer before it points out to the difference of
the שבעה כבשים shivah kevasim and the עולה olah is: This is
a קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur. This is קח לך, kach lecha, this
is אהרן's Aharon קרבן. korban, This is קח לך, kach lecha, this
is אהרן's Aharon קרבן. korban. And by the way, that's very significant
because the separation is a separation for אהרן. Aharon. Right? So it
says, and there we have אהרן's Aharon קרבן korban which is the
same as opposed to here.
Any כהן kohen, can bring the מוסף. Musaf.
Right. ואמר, ve'amar, okay, and also where would, who would pay for
it? Which funds would it come from?
שקלים. shekalim. Don't go back.
No, but that's what we're going to discuss. אמר רבי אבהו: Amar
Rabbi Abahu: דנין פר ואיל שלו, danin par ve'ayilo shelo, which you
had by the מילואים Miluim... and by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, מפר
ואיל שלו. mipar ve'ayilo shelo. So you learn out the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur from the מילואים Miluim לאפוקי עצרת וראש השנה, le'apukei Atzeret
ve-Rosh Hashanah, now we'll have an easy answer for both of them,
דציבור נינהו. detzibur ninhu. Those are of the קרבן ציבור. korban tzibur.
The גמרא Gemara says: One minute. הני ניחא למאן דאמר קח לך
משלך. hani nicha leman de'amar kach lecha mishelcha. That's good if the
phrase קח לך kach lecha normally means "take from your own funds,
you pay for it." And both by the מילואים Miluim; and by
יום כיפור Yom Kippur it says קח לך. kach lecha. Okay, right?
I'll just do it again. By שמיני, שמיני begins by saying:
ויאמר אל אהרן קח לך עגל בן בקר. vayomer el Aharon kach
lecha egel ben bakar. Right? By יום כיפור Yom Kippur, begins with
saying:
קח לך עגל בן בקר לחטאת. kach lecha egel ben bakar lachatat.
Right? בזאת יבוא אהרן, bezot yavo Aharon, it says בזאת יבוא אהרן,
bezot yavo Aharon, it doesn't say קח לך, kach lecha, but it
does say אהרן. Aharon. So anyway, all right, so it's also going
to the קרבנות of מילואים... Miluim
I understand. Okay, let's take a look. So if קח לך kach
lecha means "you pay for it", then you have that similarity of
the מילואים Miluim and of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur אלא למאן דאמר
משל ציבור, ela leman de'amar mishel tzibur, but according to the opinion
that says even when it says קח לך, kach lecha, it means
communal funds, מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? What can you say?
There's not, that's not a basis for distinction. Now where do you
see this debate? דתניא: detanya: We taught in the ברייתא. Braita. קח
לך משלך ועשה לך משלך. kach lecha mishelcha va'aseh lecha mishelcha. When
the תורה Torah says קח לך, kach lecha, it means your own
money. When it says עשה לך, aseh lecha, it means your own
money. Now that doesn't necessarily mean by the eighth day of the
מילואים; miluim there's other places that say that, like עשה לך שתי
חצוצרות כסף. aseh lecha shtei chatzotzrot kesef. Okay, there's other places. But
wherever it says קח לך kach lecha or עשה לך, aseh lecha,
it means your own funds.
ויקחו אליך, vyikchu eleicha, like ויקחו אליך שמן זית זך, vyikchu eleicha
shemen zayit zach, right? Although it says אליך, eleicha, but "they will
take" אליך, eleicha, not "you will take" for yourself. So that already
is different. That's משל ציבור. mishel tzibur. דברי רבי יאשיה. Divrei Rabbi
Yoshiyah. So רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiyah says as opposed to ויקחו אליך,
vyikchu eleicha, when it says קח לך kach lecha and it's in
the singular and it says לך lecha or עשה לך, aseh lecha,
it means out of your own funds. רבי יונתן אומר: Rabbi Yonatan
omer: Now רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan disagrees. בין קח לך בין ויקחו
אליך משל ציבור. bein kach lecha bein vyikchu eleicha mishel tzibur. It
always is communal funds. So according to רבי יונתן, Rabbi Yonatan, even
the קרבן korban that was brought on the eighth day of the
מילואים miluim was coming from communal funds. So you don't have this
difference of, you know, private funds of אהרן Aharon as opposed to
communal funds of ראש השנה...
Rosh Hashanah... terminology. I don't know.
So let's take a look. We'll see in the גמרא. Gemara So
ומה תלמוד לומר umah talmud lomar (you see it asks exactly what
you asked, Michael) ומה תלמוד לומר קח לך? umah talmud lomar kach
lecha? So why say קח לך kach lecha if it's communal funds?
כביכול, kevayachol, as if God is
saying, משלך אני רוצה יותר משלהם. mishelcha ani rotzeh yoter mishelahem. I
would rather it be yours than it be theirs. So, "as if".
Meaning, now what's the "as if"? So רש"י Rashi says two "as
ifs". One "as if" is like: Okay, if it were permissible (of
course God is the one making the rules), but if I would
be okay with the idea of it being a private קרבן, korban:
I'd actually prefer it אהרן Aharon to be your private קרבן, korban,
let's say this eighth day of מילואים miluim. or the חצוצרות, chatzotzrot,
I'd rather they come from your private funds, God says to משה,
Moshe, rather than communal funds. But we have to make it a
communal thing, so it's going to be communal, but I'd rather rather
it be yours. That's the כביכול, kevayachol, the first one. It's a
kind of weird, one כביכול kevayachol is כביכול kevayachol if it would
be acceptable to be private. The other כביכול kevayachol רש"י Rashi says
is not this idea... to a bizarre idea God's making the rules.
What do you mean if it would be acceptable to be private?
But what the כביכול ke-vayakhol means is that the גמרא Gemara doesn't
really want to say it because to say such a thing, I'd
rather it be yours than it be the ציבור'ס tzibbur's is basically
suggesting, you know, that God has
favors and doesn't want something from all of כל ישראל, Klal Yisrael,
right? So to prefer something from a יחיד yachid over from all
of כל ישראל Klal Yisrael was a very harsh thing to say,
even if that יחיד yachid is משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu or אהרן.
Aharon. So it sort of says it as a כביכול. ke-vayakhol. It
suggests this idea we would never really say such a thing. Of
course, something from the ציבור tzibbur so significant, but it suggests how
important like אהרן Aharon and משה Moshe is to suggest this kind
of possible idea. Of course, God sort of said it to משה,
Moshe, I'll wipe them all out and make an עם am out
of you. So it suggests that idea but we don't want to
say it. That's what the כביכול ke-vayakhol says. It's for midrashic purpose,
not for halakhic purpose. Now we're going to have this little midrashic
derivation. אבא חנן אומר משום רבי אליעזר: Abba Chanan omer mishum Rabbi
Eliezer: כתוב אחד אומר ועשית לך ארון עץ, katuv echad omer v'asita
lekha aron etz, which is God talking to משה Moshe after the
breaking of the לוחות, luchot,
right? That's after the breaking of the לוחות, luchot, right? דברים י.
Devarim Yud. It's funny because that's משה Moshe quoting it anyway.
Well, נו נו. nu nu.
Suggests this kind of metaphysical aspect of כפרה kapparah that needs to
work in a certain way. It's like if God said, well, I
would like if the moon, you know, would come out in the
day, but it doesn't.
Right. But there's this reality that this interpretation deals with that, you
know, this is how כפרה kapparah
works is that it's ציבור tzibbur based. Right. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer,
right, exactly,
ועשית לך ארון עץ.
v'asita lekha aron etz. Okay. ועשית לך ארון עץ. v'asita lekha aron
etz. So that's after משה Moshe had broken them. Okay. So that
is and then it says, what do you do? It says וכתבתי
על הלוחות אשר היו על הלוחות הראשונים אשר שברת ושמתם בארון. ve-khitavti
al ha-luchot asher hayu al ha-luchot ha-rishonim asher shibarta ve-samtam ba-aron. The
new לוחות luchot are going to go in the ארון. aron. Now
the simple sense of that is that that is not the ארון
aron that בצלאל Bezalel made. That's like a temporary holding ארון aron
until they can make the whole משכן. mishkan. But
the גמרא Gemara is going to make a contrast. One פסוק pasuk
says ועשית לך ארון עץ. v'asita lekha aron etz. One כתוב אחד
אומר ועשו ארון עצי שטים katuv echad omer v'asu aron atzei shitim
in the plural. And all of כל
ישראל. Klal Yisrael.
הכיצד? ha-keitzad? כאן בזמן שישראל עושים רצונו של מקום, kan bi-zman she-Yisrael
osim retzono shel makom, when כל ישראל Klal Yisrael does God's will,
then it's like it comes from all of כל ישראל. Klal Yisrael.
כאן בזמן שאין ישראל עושים רצונו של מקום, kan bi-zman she-ein Yisrael
osim retzono shel makom, when they don't do all of God's will,
then God focuses on the צדיקים, tzaddikim, let's say, and on the
fact that oh, this is משה'ס Moshe's ארון. aron.
I don't want it to take care of the מחצית השקל. machatzit
ha-shekel.
Something like that. Right, exactly. So it's interesting having this coming after
שקלים, Shekalim, you know. It's and but it's playing off of a
similar theme. You know, of course, the idea is that it comes
from כל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, but sometimes the המון עם hamon am
is off the דרך derekh and God would rather focus on the
צדיקים. tzaddikim. Okay. Back to the point though. We have the idea
that it says it comes from, according to some, it comes from
the ציבור, tzibbur, according to רבי יונתן. Rabbi Yonatan. So you don't
have this difference of these two coming only from אהרן'ס Aharon's funds.
So the גמרא Gemara says no. עד כאן לא פליגי אלא בקיחות
דעלמא ועשיות דעלמא. ad kan lo peligi ela be-kikhot de-alma ve-asiyot de-alma.
This debate of whether לך lekha means you אהרן Aharon or משה,
Moshe, whoever the person being spoken to is, your personal funds or
communal funds, that's generally when it talks about it in other contexts.
Like making the חצוצרות chatzotzrot and other times it says, like it
says קח לך סמים, kakh lekha samim,
like when it speaks about the קטורת, ketoret, right? It says קח
לך סמים נטף ושחלת וחלבנה. kakh lekha samim nataf u-shekhelet ve-khelbenah. When
it talks about the שמן המשחה, shemen ha-mishchah, right? What's the קח
לך סמים? kakh lekha samim? קח לך סמים נטף ושחלת וחלבנה סמים
ולבונה זכה בד בבד יהיה ועשית אותה קטורת רוקח מעשה רוקח ממולח
טהור קדש. kakh lekha samim nataf u-shekhelet ve-khelbenah samim u-levonah zakkah bad
be-vad yihyeh ve-asita otah ketoret rokach ma'aseh rokach memulach tahor kodesh. Anyway,
that's the קטורת. ketoret. That's the קטורת, ketoret, that's not the שמן
המשחה.
shemen
ha-mishchah.
Anyway, so when it normally says קח לך סמים...
kakh lekha samim...
I was going to do קח
לך סמים ואתה קח לך בשמים ראש מר דרור חמש
מאות וקנמון בשם מחציתו חמשים ומאתים.
kakh lekha samim ve-atah kakh lekha besamim rosh mor dror chamesh
me'ot
ve-kinman besem machatzito chamishim u-matayim. No, that is the שמן המשחה, shemen
ha-mishchah, isn't it?
Right. No, you said קטורת. ketoret.
Yeah, no, but I was correcting myself, it's the שמן המשחה. shemen
ha-mishchah. No no no, you start with all of these things, but
it's for the שמן המשחה. shemen ha-mishchah. Okay. So when is it
אלא בקיחות דעלמא ועשיות דעלמא? ela be-kikhot de-alma ve-asiyot de-alma?
Only by other cases, קיחות דעלמא קח לך סמים. kikhot de-alma kakh
lekha samim. Okay. So where was the שמן המשחה shemen ha-mishchah made?
So according on that was the debate, is it made from משה'ס
Moshe's personal, you know, contributions,
and or is it made from the ציבור'ס? tzibbur's? ועשיות דעלמא עשה
לך שתי חצוצרות כסף ve-asiyot de-alma aseh lekha shtei chatzotzrot kesef
by the trumpets. That's where we could debate, was it private or
was it communal? אבל הנך, aval hanakh,
by the ones about the eighth day of the מילואים miluim and
אהרן Aharon in bringing in, you know, doing the עבודה avoda, on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, פרישי קמי פרש דמשלו הוא. perishi kime-farash de-mishelo
hu. It's quite clear that was אהרן'ס Aharon's private קרבן. Nobody debates
that neither that both the מילואים miluim and the and the what
do you call it and the עבודה avoda, of יום כיפור Yom
Kippur? that אהרן'ס Aharon's קרבן came from his own funds. Right. And
nobody had a debate. No, we said there's a general debate of
whether לך lekha means private funds. So it's saying there might be
a general debate, but not by יום כיפור Yom Kippur. and שמיני
and the מילואים. miluim מכדי כתיב mikhdi ketiv אל בני ישראל תדבר
לאמר el benei Yisrael tedabber lemor by the מילואים miluim it says
after it says קח לך, kakh lekha, this is what your... say
why did you say tell to אהרן Aaron *Aharon*, קח עגל בן
בקר *Kach eigel ben bakar*, ובני ישראל Yisrael תדבר *U'bnei Yisrael tedabeir*?
So the contrast of
אהרן Aaron *Aharon* to בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* and underscoring not only
was it said to אהרן Aaron *Aharon*, but it was קח לך
kach lecha. *Kach lecha*, שמע מינה קח לך משלך הוא *Shma mina
kach lecha mishelcha hu*. Nobody would disagree with the idea that on
the מלואים milu'im *Miluim* it was אהרן Aaron *Aharon*'s own private funds
that paid for the קרבן *Korban*.
And you don't think that it has to do with the people
with greater authority have greater and weightier responsibility to shoulder, let's say,
the well-being, the metaphysical well-being and the כפרה kappara *Kapara* of the
עם *Am*?
Yeah, but still this is אהרן Aharon *Aharon*'s קרבן *Korban*.
It's about צדיקים *Tzaddikim* and רשעים *Reshaim*.
Oh, you're going back to my previous thing about משלו הוא *Mishelo
hu*, that it's an issue about leadership. Exactly. Yeah, that's possible of
course but once you raise the issue of leadership, you raise the
problem that if the ציבור *Tzibur* is not worthy, then that undermines
also then that's a stain on the leadership as well. So anyway,
all right, but anyway I hear the point that the previous point
might be about leadership and not about righteousness. Anyway, back to this.
So by, so normally we could debate by the שמן המשחה *Shemen
Hamishcha*, by the קטורת *Ketores*, excuse me, by the שמן המשחה *Shemen
Hamishcha*, by the חצוצרות *Chatzotzros*, it says לך *Lecha*, does it mean
private, does it mean communal? But here clearly it means private. אהרן
*Aharon*'s קרבן *Korban* on the eighth day of מלואים *Miluim* is contrasted
to the ציבור *Tzibur*'s and it says לך *Lecha*, which means your
private one. שמע מינה קח לך משלך הוא *Shma mina kach lecha
mishelcha hu*. ביום הכיפורים מכדי Michti, כתיב ובזאת יבוא אהרן אל הקודש
בפר בן בקר לחטאת lachatas ואיל לעולה le'ola. *Byom hakippurim michdi ksiv
bezose yavo Aharon el hakodesh b'par ben bakar l'chatas v'ayil l'olah*, and
then the next פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* contrasts: ומאת עדת בני ישראל יקח
*U'me'eis adas Bnei Yisrael yikach*. So that from, and then it says
from the community you should take שני שעירי עיזים לחטאת ואיל אחד
לעולה והקריב אהרן את פר par החטאת אשר לו *Shnei se'irei izim
l'chatas v'ayil echad l'olah v'hikriv Aharon es par hachatas asher lo*. למה
לי *Lama li*? So it already contrasts אהרן *Aharon*'s versus the ציבור
*Tzibur*'s. Why does it once again underscore he should take his פר
*Par*? שמע מינה האי לו משלו הוא *Shma mina hai lo mishelo
hu*, that it's his private one. So it basically says look, if
the פסוק pasuk. *Pasuk* drops in one word of לך *Lecha*, קח
לך סמים *Kach lecha samim*, עשה לך שתי חצוצרות כסף *Aseh lecha
shtei chatzotzros kesef*, we could say the לך *Lecha* doesn't really mean
your private funds. But by the מלואים *Miluim* and by יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, it's very clear the תורה Torah *Torah* is
underscoring this is אהרן *Aharon*'s קרבן *Korban* as opposed to this is
the ציבור *Tzibur*'s קרבן *Korban*. And if those places after it's underscored
that fundamental difference it also throws in the word לו *Lo* or
לך *Lecha*, that it's to tell you it's your private קרבן *Korban*.
Now, by the way, תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* points out I don't know
why the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* cared about all of this. Because who
cares the issue of whose funds it comes from? It could have
just pointed out that in both of those cases it's coming for
to be מכפר *Mechaper* for אהרן *Aharon*. Who by the קרבן *Korban*,
how much do we care who paid for it? What we care
about the קרבן *Korban* is who is it coming for, for whom
is it coming, not from which funds. So what, so תוספות Tosfos
*Tosafos* says I really don't understand what bothered the גמרא *Gemara*. But
at the end of the idea the question is why do we
compare מלואים *Miluim* to, to יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*? Why
we compare it? Because doesn't it have a similar thing on ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashana*? You have a פר *Par* and an
איל ayil, *Ayil*. So besides that there are other differences, עולה *Olah*,
שבעת כבשים *Shivas kevasim*, etc. That was the question. Why go to
יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* not ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh
Hashana*? And the answer is this is אהרן *Aharon*'s קרבן *Korban*, this
is אהרן *Aharon*'s קרבן *Korban*, this is the ציבור *Tzibur*'s קרבן *Korban*.
Now what the גמרא *Gemara* sort of, sort of got focused on
is who's paying for it. Oh, how do you know אהרן *Aharon*
pays for it? Maybe this comes from communal funds. Maybe this comes
from communal funds. Just because it says לך *Lecha* how do you
know he paid for it? And the answer is no, no, no,
everybody agrees here לך *Lecha* means he paid for it because here
it really underscores the difference of his קרבן *Korban* and the עם
*Am* and we have this idea that this is paid for אהרן
*Aharon* rather than paid for communally. But תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* again says
why did I need all of that? Right, he just leaves it
as a question. Who cares who paid for it? This is coming
for the sake of the ציבור *Tzibur*, this is a מוסף *Musaf*,
and this is coming for the sake of אהרן *Aharon*. When we
say whose קרבן *Korban* it is, we don't mean who paid for
it, we mean for whom is it coming. And this is coming
for אהרן *Aharon* and that's coming for אהרן *Aharon*. So there clearly
is a much greater parallel here than here. And again remember, it's
אהרן הכהן הגדול *Aharon Hakohen Hagadol* who's being separated out and we're
focusing on the similarity of a special קרבן *Korban* coming for the
כהן גדול kohen gadol, *Kohen Gadol*. Yes, there was one thing you
said that for the שמן המשחה *Shemen Hamishcha* and the קטורת *Ketores*
or whatever it is or the חצוצרות *Chatzotzros* that משה Moshe. *Moshe*
or somebody, right, individual had to pay for it himself. משה Moshe
*Moshe*, yeah. Right, and then what do you
do, how do you deal with the fact that in the נשיאים
הביאו את אבני השהם *Nesi'im heviu es avnei hashoham* it says והבשם
ולשמן המשחה ולקטורת הסמים *V'habosem u'lshemen hamishcha u'lketores hasamim*? If משה Moshe
*Moshe* had to pay for it, how would they be able to
do it?
Good question, maybe he had to buy it off of them. I
don't know, that's a good question. It's a good question, I don't
know. Okay, so now let's see, the גמרא *Gemara* continues. Now, okay,
so that's why we don't learn it out from ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah, *Rosh
Hashana*. רב אשי
אמר amar, *Rav Ashi amar*, and now רב אשי *Rav Ashi* says
forget all of that headache about who paid for it, there's a
much better answer. דני פר לחטאת ואיל לעולה, par lachatas ve'ayil le'ola,
פר לחטאת ואיל לעולה, par lachatas ve'ayil le'ola. like I've been saying
all along, it's true that by ראש השנה you do have a
פר and an איל, ayil but they're both עולות olas as opposed
to by the מילואים miluim and by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the
פר is לחטאת and the איל ayil? is לעולה. מפוקי ראש השנה
ושמיני עצרת דתרוייהו עולות נינהו. Mafukei Rosh Hashanah ve'shemini atzeres d'taryahu olas
ninhu. Who cares by שמיני עצרת and ראש השנה you found a
פר and an איל? Those are all עולות, olas, it's not a
פר לחטאת par lachatas and an איל לעולה. ayil le'ola. רבינא אמר
דני עבודה בכהן גדול מעבודה בכהן גדול לאפוקי כולהו קושיאתין דלאו עבודה
בכהן גדול נינהו, Ravina amar danni avoda be'kohen gadol me'avoda be'kohen gadol
lapukei kulu kushyasen d'lav avoda be'kohen gadol ninhu, which is a very
nice elegant answer. All of your questions before, שמיני עצרת, שבועות, ראש
השנה, anybody could do the עבודה, avoda and we'd rather compare it
against the מילואים miluim, where it was אהרן doing the עבודה, avoda.
right? אהרן did the עבודה avoda on the eighth day of the
מילואים miluim. and therefore we'd like to compare it to יום כיפור
Yom Kippur where אהרן does the עבודה. avoda And again underscoring the
idea, you separate out the כהן גדול kohen gadol because it is
a special day, not just generic special day, but it's a special
day for the כהן גדול, kohen gadol and that's why you separate
him out and that's why we make that comparison, and underscoring the
idea that we've also been saying that there's a special קרבן for
the כהן גדול kohen gadol, which is the same, the פר לחטאת
ואיל לעולה. Par l’chatas v’ayil l’olah. Okay,
אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, ואיכא דאמרי אמר רבינא דני עבודה תחילה מעבודה
תחילה. ve'ika d'amri amar Ravina danni avoda techila me'avoda techila. You learn
out an initial עבודה avoda. from an initial עבודה avoda which is
both the case
on the מילואים miluim and on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, לאפוקי הני דלאו תחילה נינהו, lapukei hani d'lav
techila ninhu, there was no initial עבודה. avoda The גמרא asks מאי
תחילה? mai techila? What do you mean initial? אילימא תחילה בכהן גדול,
ileima techila be'kohen gadol, the first time a כהן גדול kohen gadol
functioned. Now what does that mean? By the מילואים, miluim, the first
time אהרן actually played the role as the כהן גדול, kohen gadol.
played anybody played the role as כהן גדול kohen gadol was the
מילואים. miluim. So that's תחילה techila for the כהן גדול. kohen gadol
What do you mean by יום כיפור? Yom Kippur, So the רש"י
Rashi says the first time the כהן גדול kohen gadol had an
opportunity to do a קרבן ציבור korban tzibbur would have been, or
that uniquely required a כהן גדול kohen gadol. would have been on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur So the גמרא says, okay, then it just
boils down to the כהן גדול kohen gadol. point. So היינו קמייתא,
hainu kamaisa, that's the first point that it was specifically about a
כהן גדול. kohen gadol, אלא Ella no, here's what we mean that
it was the first initial. אלא אלו עבודה תחילה במקום מעבודה תחילה
במקום. Ella eila avoda techila bemakom me'avoda techila bemakom. The first initiation
of a place, the first time a place had an עבודה avoda,
done in it, which is what? On the מילואים Miluim it was
the first time the עבודה avoda was done in on the מזבח
החיצון. mizbeach hachitzon. Now רש"י Rashi says, what about the whole seven
days that led up to it? But that's not an official עבודה,
avoda that wasn't with כהנים. kohanim But the first time it was
an official עבודה Avodah with כהנים kohanim was on the eighth day
of the מילואים, Miluim and the first time an עבודה Avodah? was
done in the היכל, heichal, right, in the actual קודש וקודש קדשים
kodesh v'kodesh kodashim was on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So that's the
similarity and therefore we learn those out. Now it's worth taking a
moment to appreciate the difference here because okay, you could just say,
yeah, fine, we're just trying to find similarities, but think by the
way about all the different things that we are saying here in
terms of what this what it might be the significance of the
seven day preparation. Right? One is saying the significance is it requires
you as the כהן גדול. Kohein Gadol Both of these things are
unique to a כהן גדול, Kohein Gadol, so the seven day preparation
is essentially to get me ready, to get me to prepare me,
to get me sort of like at that level because this is
something that's about my unique position and status and so on. Okay,
that's a little bit different than saying עבודה תחילה במקום. avoda techila
bemakom. I mean ultimately I have to be ready yes, but I
have to be ready because we are doing something sort of you
know we're this space is being consecrated or is being initiated is
you know in a very special way. It's not something that, oh
I it's all about me and I have to be ready. Yes
it requires me, but I am getting ready in order that I
can properly approach this place, and if you think about it בזאת
יבא אהרן אל הקדש. bezot yavo Aaron el hakodesh. So it's right,
so it's not necessarily about about sort of you know focusing on
me being at the it's all about me being at the right
מדריגה, madrega, but I still think there's a difference between whether the
focus is all about me and whether the focus is about I
have to get at that right מדריגה madrega because I have to
be entering into this space in the right type of way.
Yes that's not a me in the sense like we would say
it's modern ego-centricity. The כהן, kohen...
his בגדי שרד bigdei serad and the ratios of geometric ratios of
the structure of the משכן Mishkan were all proportional to each other.
The חושן Choshen and the different selections of beads providing there. In
other words they were coterminous. He was a walking משכן.
Mishkan. Well that's an interesting point as well which is speaking about
is it a process of consecrating the same way you consecrate the
משכן Mishkan you consecrate the כהנים Kohanim which is certainly what is
happening in the פרשה parsha of the מילואים. Miluim It's hard to
say that that's being paralleled. It is true that on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur. you are cleansing the משכן Mishkan but if you need
seven days to sort of consecrate the כהן... Kohein, consecrate the כהן,
Kohein
you don't need seven days to consecrate the משכן, Mishkan, you're not
doing עבודה avodah, on the seven days in the משכן Mishkan or
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, to consecrate it. But I do
think that although these are, you know, these are similar, there's a
subtle difference which is, is this a process of needed in order
to lead to entering into that space in a particular way, right,
or is this a process that is needed because you need to
get the כהן Kohen. at a certain level because it requires a
כהן גדול Kohein Gadol. and he has to be at a certain
level in order to do the עבודה? avodah Or is it that
he needs to be that way to prepare him to enter into
the space, which is I think the way אחרונים Achronim opens this:
זאת יבא אהרן אל הקדש. Zos Tavo Aharon el Hakodesh. Okay, so
now the גמרא continues.
כי אתא רב דימי אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki asa Rav Dimi amar
Rabbi Yochanan, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael he said in the name of רבי יוחנן, מתני חדא. Rabbi
Yochanan matni chada. He only taught רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, said one
of the two things, not פרה Parah. and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur
just one. רבי יהושע בן לוי מתני תרתין Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi
matni tartein was רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi who
taught, or some say ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, who taught two things.
רבי יוחנן מתני חדא לעשות לכפר אלו מעשי יום הכיפורים, Rabbi Yochanan
matni chada, la’asos lachaper eilu ma’asei Yom Hakippurim, that all he learns
out from the מילואים Miluim is יום כיפור, Yom Kippur? not the
פרה. Parah. And you understand why the גמרא introduces that now. Because
at this stage we have just gone through a whole דף that
has underscored the way in which the מילואים Miluim, and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur are extremely similar. Think about it. Both of them have
the exact same קרבן: פר לחטאת ואיל לעולה. par l’chatas v’ayil l’olah,
Those are קרבנות that are uniquely for the כהן גדול, Kohein Gadol.
קח לך. A is from his funds, B as תוספות points out
who cares whose funds it is, it's for the sake of the
כהן גדול. Kohein Gadol, Number three is they’re all עבודות avodos that
require the כהן גדול. Kohein Gadol Number four is they’re all initiations
of particular places. So we have now shown, oh my god, מילואים
Miluim, and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. that's ממש mamash like it's all
really analogous, it's really כמעט k’imat the same thing. Which now sticks
out as a sore thumb? What we talked about yesterday, the פרה.
Parah פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah You don't need a כהן גדול, Kohein
Gadol it doesn't get done in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you
don't bring a פר לחטאת ואיל לעולה, none of these things applies
to the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. So now we introduce the idea,
you know what? There's actually a teaching in the name of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that doesn't, that says פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is
not part of this. The real, the real, the real sort of
application of this seven-day preparation from the מילואים Miluim, is to יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur not the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah.
But that's the one missing piece that you have to fill in.
Yeah, we've done such a great job equating יום כיפור Yom Kippur
to the eighth day of מילואים, Miluim we've left פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah, off by the wayside. So אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami,
that's a version now we have of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan so
חדא, chada, last
thing about the פרה אדומה.
Parah Adumah Well,
hold on, we'll take a look where that's coming from, but it's
not coming from this פסוק. רבי יהושע בן לוי מתני תרתין. Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi matni tartein. רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi teaches like we taught yesterday. לעשות אלו מעשי פרה לכפר אלו
מעשי יום הכיפורים. La’asos eilu ma’asei parah, lachaper eilu ma’asei Yom Hakippurim.
So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, מתני חדא. Matni Chada. So now רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan only learns out one, only he learns out יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur? ותנן שבעת ימים קודם יום הכיפורים ושבעת ימים קודם
שריפת הפרה. V’anan tenan shivas yamim kodem Yom Hakippurim v’shivas yamim kodem
sraifas haparah. Don't we say that both of them have seven-day preparation
presumably based on the same reason?
מעלה בעלמא. Ma’ala b’alma. That was just a nice thing to do
for the פרה אדומה, Parah Adumah it wasn't really required. And as
תוספות again points out, okay, because remember, we did so many things,
we had this one leniency by the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah that
we did it by the guy that went to the מקוה, mikvah,
the טבול יום, Tevul Yom, that we want to do a million
things that are crazy מחמיר. machmir. So yeah, we did this too.
Now, by the way, this also gets to the question about why
did we do this, right? Michael yesterday assumed that we were doing
seven days to ensure that the כהן גדול Kohein Gadol. was טהור.
tahor. But that's not what the גמרא said. The גמרא said we're
doing it in order because we learn it out from the מילואים,
Milu'im. it's part of a process of preparation. Forget preparing, protecting him
from being טמא. tamei. But when the גמרא now says according to
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that for the פרה Parah? it was מעלה
בעלמא, ma’ala b’alma, it's putting it in a completely different category. כהן
גדול Kohein Gadol is like the מילואים, Milu'im, it's a whole preparatory
process of being ready to do that special עבודה, avodah preparing yourself,
transforming yourself and so on. That's what we get by מילואים Milu'im,
and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur? What about פרה? Parah. Eh, that was
טומאה וטהרה. tumah v’taharah. That was since we had that little קולא
kulo we're going crazy to be מחמיר, machmir, and it's all, now
seven days you understand is relevant for טומאה וטהרה, tumah v’taharah, right?
Because seven days is the maximum period and so on. Okay, so
that's what it is by פרה. Parah Don't confuse that with כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol, It's nothing to do with our כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol, discussion. Okay, that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said. והא אמר
רבי מניומי בר חלקיה אמר רבי מחסיא בר אידי אמר רבי יוחנן,
Veha amar Rabbi Minyumi bar Chelkiya amar Rabbi Machasya bar Idia amar
Rabbi Yochanan, but we have another statement in the name of רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, כאשר עשה ביום הזה צוה ה' לעשות לכפר עליכם,
Ka'asher asa bayom hazeh tziva Hashem la’asos lachaper aleichem, לעשות אלו מעשי
פרה לכפר אלו מעשי יום הכיפורים, la’asos eilu ma’asei parah lachaper eilu
ma’asei Yom Hakippurim,
that exactly this to learn out both פרה Parah and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur? we have that in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi
Yochanan. So how could you say in the name of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan it's only יום כיפור? Yom Kippur. So ההיא דרביה. hahi
d’Rabbay. No, that's not רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying it in his
own name, that's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan saying it in his רבי's
Rebbe name. דכי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Dechi asa Ravin amar
Rabbi Yochanan, because when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
he said in the name of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan משום רבי ישמעאל mishum Rabbi Yishmael that it
was ultimately a chain of tradition that went back through of רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, לעשות אלו מעשה פרה
לכפר אלו מעשה יום הכיפורים. la'asot eleh ma'aseh parah l'chaper eleh ma'aseh
Yom HaKippurim. Okay,
so what we have is different statements in the name of רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. תוספות says he could've just said it's a מחלוקת
אמוראים machlokes amora'im about what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, which the
גמרא elsewhere says, but at the end of the day, you have
two basic approaches now. Everybody agrees you learn from the מילואים. Milu'im.
One says you learn both פרה Parah and יום כיפור Yom Kippur.
from the מילואים, Milu'im and the other says only יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur, פרה Parah is its own thing, it's rabbinic, it's a whole
special thing just to be more מחמיר machmir and so on. Now,
it's very attractive now that idea that פרה parah is less is
left by the wayside, you could you really focuses you on this
idea of preparing the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol a special עבודה avodah
of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol a special entering into the מקום,
Makom, you really understand, you know, this the similarity. The challenge is,
if you say you both learn פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. and יום
כיפור Yom Kippur from it, what's the common denominator? What, you know,
okay, both of them were very special events, but sort of the,
you know, more concretely, more specifically, you lose the power of the
you know, it's hard to see what the common denominator is. Yes,
Charlie.
Question, who is this רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that the תנא? Tanna?
The
תנא. Tanna. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was the first generation
אמורא. Amora.
His רבי rebbe was רבי.
Rebbe. Yeah, yeah. Okay.
Did you explain what רש"י Rashi means when he explains the מעלה
בעלמא מפני הקל
שהכירו?
ma'aleh b'alma mipnei hakal
shehikiru?
Yes, I said that before. Because since we thought that they did
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah with a טבול יום tevul yom in
order to in order to, you know, to to show defiance of
the צדוקים's Tzaddukim interpretation, so once they had that one leniency, they
threw on a million stringencies. And this is one of the stringencies.
Wait, why is that I guess that's what's confusing me.
Why is that seven days of
why is that a leniency?
A טבול יום, tevul yom, that somebody who was טמא tamei and
it hasn't hasn't become totally טהור, tahor, it hasn't been nightfall yet?
טבול יום tevul yom means he only went to the מקוה mikveh
today. They made sure he would do it. They wanted it with
a טבול יום.
tevul yom. אף על פי שאמרו, af al pi she-amru,
right, exactly, להוציא מלבן של צדוקים. l'hotzi mi-liban shel Tzaddukim. Okay, so
now we have this this issue about learning from the מילואים, Milu'im
but one that really focuses on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and really
underscores the similarity and one that makes it a little more generic
and includes פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Now, אמר ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן:
amar Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan: So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says to
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מהכא קיילפת, mehacha kayalphat, where are you learning
this idea out about יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? We're now ignoring the
פרה אדומה part of the question. Where are you learning out this
idea of יום כיפור? Yom Kippur From מילואים. Milu'im, Okay, you say
מילואים Milu'im, is your basis. One minute.
אם ממילואים כל הכתוב בהם מעכב בהם im me-Milu'im kol ha-katuv ba-hem
me'akev ba-hem one minute. We know by the מילואים Milu'im. that anything
that was written in the מילואים, Milu'im,
the גמרא will say later in like two days, that if any
one thing was not done by the מילואים, Milu'im, it would have
been invalid. Anything written is
מעכב. me'akev. So, for example, the seven-day separation. It would not have
been an acceptable process of מילואים. Milu'im, אף הכא נמי כל הכתוב
בהם מעכב בהם af hacha nami kol ha-katuv ba-hem me'akev ba-hem so
would you say the same here that if you don't do the
seven-day separation, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol can't do the עבודה avoda
on יום כיפור? וכי תימא הכא נמי, ve-chi teima hacha nami, why
not? Let's say that, that's a nice idea, that he has to
go through this preparatory process and maybe it's מעכב. me'akev. No, דתנן
ומתקינין לו כהן אחר, de-tenan u-matkinin lo kohen acher, you prepare another
כהן. Kohen. So you designate a backup כהן. Kohen Now, people were
asking, does this backup כהן Kohen. need the seven-day preparation as well?
So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is going to assume no, we never
say it. We say we separate the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol for
seven days, we never say it about the about the stand-in, the
understudy. ולא תני מפרישין, ve-lo tani mafrishin, it didn't say מפרישין, mafrishin,
you separate this backup כהן. Kohen, Clearly, he doesn't need that preparation.
And if you wind up using the backup כהן, you do it
without the seven-day preparation.
That's a good question. Maybe to the same way an understudy has
to use time to learn the lines, he's got to know what
עבודה avoda, he's got to do, but not for a seven-day preparation.
וכי תימא מאי מתקינין מפרישין, ve-chi teima mai matkinin mafrishin, so maybe
it says, no, maybe מתקינין matkinin means exactly that, that he also
goes through seven days of separation. No, ליתני או אידי ואידי מתקינין,
lisni o idi ve-idi matkinin, so use the same phrase, either both
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol: and the backup say מתקינין, matkinin, או
אידי ואידי מפרישין o idi ve-idi mafrishin or both of them say
מפרישין. mafrishin. If you use a different phrase, a different verb, clearly
it indicates that you see them differently. We never see that the
backup is seven days. So you see the seven-day preparation is not
a מעכב. me'akev. And therefore, says ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, I can't
believe that you learn it from the מילואים, Milu'im? because if you
really learn it from מילואים, it was great to point out all
of those comparisons, but if you really learn it from the מילואים,
it should be מעכב. me'akev. אמר ליה, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said back to him, אלא מר מהכא יליף לה ela mar mehacha
yalif lah fine, you have a better answer? So
where do you learn it out from if you don't like מילואים?
אמר, so he says yes, actually I do have a better answer.
אמר מסיני, amar mi-Sinai, I learn it out from הר סיני. Har
Sinai. Not that he has it straight from God from סיני, Sinai,
but I learn it out from what happened in הר סיני. Har
Sinai. דכתיב וישכן כבוד ה' על הר סיני
ויכסהו הענן ששת ימים, de-chtiv vayishkon kvod Hashem al Har Sinai vayichasehu
he'anan sheshet yamim, that God's presence dwelt on הר סיני Har Sinai
and it covered him, the cloud, six days. ever did it. Now
it could mean הר סיני, Har Sinai, רש״י says it means משה.
Moshe
ויקרא אל משה ביום השביעי, Vayikra el Moshe bayom hashvi'i, ויעל משה,
Vaya'al Moshe, and called משה on the seventh day. So משה was
covered in the ענן, anan, he was like in the presence of
God but in the ambient, right? Not in the right at the
at the top of the mountain. But he was in that sort
of divine presence for six days prior to going up to the
mountain. So it's like I know, so we're gonna ask that obviously.
So similar to the כהן גדול is in the presence, he goes
to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash he lives in the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash, and on the finally on the eighth day he's ready
to go into the עזרה azara and to go into the קודש
kodesh and the קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. A very nice whole comparison
about entering into that encounter with God on יום כיפור. So he
says, "Okay, but we have a little problem." He says, מכדי, פשיטא,
Pshita, no first he's going to explain how he learns this from
the פסוק. Let's take a look. It says, ויקרא אל משה ביום
השביעי, Vayikra el Moshe bayom hashvi'i, called משה on the seventh day.
מאי ששת ימים? Mai sheshet yamim? Why did it have to say
that it was there for six days prior? You know, just say
seventh day, I could have figured out how many days came before.
So at why did it underscore six days? זה בני אב, Ze
b'nai av, this is a telling you a general principle, שכל הנכנס
במחנה שכינה, shekol hanichnas bemachaneh shechina,
anybody who's going to go into the divine presence, מחנה שכינה, machaneh
shechina, טעון פרישת ששה, teun perishat shisha,
has to have a six-day preparation. Now it's worth noting that the
technical halachic term מחנה שכינה machaneh shechina refers to the קדושה kedusha
of the בית המקדש, of the עזרה. azara. Now, anybody who goes
into the עזרה azara does not need six days' preparation, right? The
כהנים Kohanim regularly went into the עזרה azara without any preparation. And
a ישראל could go into the עזרה azara without any preparation. You
had to be טהור, tahor, but you didn't need a preparatory process.
So although מחנה שכינה machaneh shechina in the technical sense means the
עזרה, azara, here it means the קודש kodesh and the קודש קדשים.
kodesh kodashim. Maybe not even the קודש, kodesh, because כהנים also went
to light the מנורה menorah and put the bread on the שולחן
shulchan without any preparation. So here it has a much more limited
sense of you're going to go into the קודש קדשים, kodesh kodashim,
you're going to go to be right with God. That requires preparation.
So the גמרא says, אנן שבעה תנן? Anan shiv'a tnan? One minute,
but okay, very beautiful, but our משנה says seven days. מתניתין דלא
כרבי יהודה בן בתירא היא דחייש לטומאת ביתו. Matnitin d'lo ke-Rabbi Yehuda
ben Beteira hi d'chaish letumat beito. You know what, says the גמרא,
the seven days in our משנה is not the biblical basis of
it. The biblical basis is six days and really you could get
six days is really what it's about. Why does it say seven
days? That's like we were saying by the פרה אדומה. That's for
טומאה tumah purposes. That's only a rabbinic concern. That's not the biblical
idea. Now what does טומאת ביתו tumat beito mean? It means we're
afraid that he'll have sex with his wife and his wife will
become a נדה niddah while they're having sex, and we're not now
afraid of the sin involved but of the טומאה tumah involved. If
he winds up having sex with his wife and she's a נדה,
niddah, even if she became a נדה niddah during the act, he
wouldn't obviously do it consciously, he would be טמא tamei for seven
days the same way she's טמא tamei for seven days. That's what
the תורה says. A man who has sex with a woman who's
a נדה, niddah, he's טמא tamei seven days. So we have to
make sure he's out of his house for seven days in advance
because we don't want him to have that טומאה, tumah, possible טומאה,
tumah, that will be in present on יום כיפור. But that's completely
a rabbinic concern, ביתו beito here being an allusion to his wife,
טומאת ביתו. tumat beito. That's completely a rabbinic concern. That's the seven
days. The real idea, the biblical idea, is six days. Now I
want to again underscore the interesting difference of the models. One model
of the מלואים is more of a model of yes, you have
to be prepared but it's, you know, it's somehow you have to
be sanctified, you have to be prepared, but you are going to
do a special עבודה avoda, and so on. Speaking about going to
an encounter with God, מחנה שכינה, machaneh shechina, right, is very different
than focusing on the עבודה, avoda of the מקום. makom. בזאת יבא
אהרן אל הקדש Bezot yavo Aharon el hakodesh is not just you're
entering into the קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim but it's really about this
encounter with God. And thinking about that as יום כיפור, you know,
the לוחות שניות luchot shniyot were given on יום כיפור and thinking
about יום כיפור not just, you know, in terms of this preparation
of the עשרת ימי תשובה aseret yemei teshuvah leading up to this
profound encounter with God, the same way אהרן went into the קודש
קדשים. kodesh kodashim. Right, I think that's the power when we think
about the עבודה, you know, how do you relate to the עבודה
on יום כיפור? But if you emphasize the idea not just of
the כפרה he achieves for כלל ישראל, klal Yisrael, but all of
the preparation he needed to enter into this profound encounter with God
in the קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. So here that is what is
being underscored by this idea, that would be six days not seven
days, but that's what's being underscored. So both of them do talk
about if you put פרה to the side, about the focus on
the כהן גדול: His קרבן, his day, his initiation into that מקום,
makom, into that new space. But one is more, you know, a
sort of I would say more of a technical type of מקדש
mikdash process of sanctifying things, preparing things that are going to be
used in a particular way. The other is I think much more
personal, that you are encountering God and so to encounter God and
to enter into מחנה שכינה machaneh shechina requires this preparation that you
start maybe distant, then you use אלול Elul to get closer, then
you use עשרת ימי תשובה aseret yemei teshuvah to be in the
cloud and then finally on יום כיפור you finally go up to
the top of the mountain.