Good morning. Today's דף daf is מ. Mem. We pick up at
the bottom of לט עמוד ב. lamed tet amud bet. I should
mention, by the way, that I double-checked the תוספות Tosafot or whatever
he calls the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, this whole issue about שמעון הצדיק's, Shimon
HaTzadik that this person dressed in white would walk in with him.
The ירושלמי Yerushalmi says, well, how could it be an angel that
doesn't answer the question? Because it understands כל אדם לא יהיה באהל
מועד kol adam lo yihiye b'ohel moed includes even an angel. So
the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi answer is, well, maybe it was the שכינה. Shechinah.
So it's actually interesting this whole story because, you know, it identified
this person in white as some image of God actually or God's
presence, so it's very anthropomorphic, I think, for our tastes, but it's
definitely worth mentioning. What?
Could it be a vision?
Could be. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, but
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi obviously did not interpret it that way.
All right, so we pick up on the bottom, we pick up
on the bottom
of לט עמוד ב, lamed tet amud bet, and we had had
this question about the whether the הגרלה, hagralah, the actually act of
drawing lots, is מעכב me'akev or not.
And this was a debate between, so let's take a look. רבי
ינאי Rabbi Yannai says that עליות גורל מתוך הקלפי מעכבת, aliyot goral
mitoch hakalpi me'akevet, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it's not מעכב,
me'akev, the actual drawing of the lot and putting them on the
animals. And the גמרא Gemara asks whether this to what degree is
this based on the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי
נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in general is not
says that things that are done outside of the קדש קדשים, Kodesh
Kodashim, the order is not מעכב. me'akev. And the גמרא Gemara understands
that might mean that certain things are not מעכב me'akev at all
outside the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Obviously that cannot be said too
broadly, but nevertheless that's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda where רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemia more insists that the order is מעכב me'akev even out of
the קדש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, maybe
there's a lineup between these opinions, that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda that things aren't מעכב, me'akev, maybe the drawing of the lots
are not מעכב. me'akev. And the גמרא Gemara gave arguments to be
more strict or more lenient. It could be that even according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda there's a position would argue this is more
strict because the Torah repeats אשר עלה, asher ala, אשר עלה. asher
ala. And the other argument is that even according to רבי נחמיה,
Rabbi Nechemia, maybe this isn't מעכב me'akev because this isn't an עבודה.
avodah. And we pointed out the, you know, the point that a
non-כהן Kohen can do it, you can do it with your left
hand, I mean a non-כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and so on. So
two ways to go about the drawing of the lots. So the
גמרא Gemara picks up now at the bottom and says like this.
Two lines from the bottom on
לט עמוד ב. lamed tet amud bet. מתיבי: Meitivei: מצוה להגריל ואם
לא הגריל כשר. mitzvah l'hagril, v'im lo higril kasher. We have a
ברייתא braita that says it's a מצוה mitzvah to draw lots, and
if you don't do it, it's כשר, kasher, which seems to be
a straight support to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that says בדיעבד b'di'eved
without drawing the lots it's still good.
Yes, you have to understand the word מצוה mitzvah there not in
its technical term as a מצוה mitzvah but that it's a good
or preferable,
yeah, like the best, the proper way to do it. I mean
look, it gets to a larger question of when we talk about
עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you're no longer talking
about individual מצוות, mitzvot, like whose מצוה mitzvah is it? The כהן
גדול's? Kohen Gadol In general, you know, we normally when we talk
about the breakdown of מצוות, mitzvot, the normal categorization we assume is
like עשה asei and לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. But you know like
when you have lists of the 613 מצוות, mitzvot, but the גאונים
Geonim actually had three categories: there's עשה, asei, לא תעשה, lo ta'asei,
and מצוות ציבוריות. mitzvot tzibburiot. Like you know community, like where do
you put the מצוה mitzvah of כי יגח שור איש את שור
רעהו ומת? ki yigach shor ish et shor re'ehu va'met? You know,
where do you put that? It's a civil law, what מצוה mitzvah
is it? Is it a מצוה עשה? mitzvah asei? So they said
you know no, that's like one of the laws of the house.
So it's sort of it's in a different category when it speaks
about at a communal level. So you know it's also when you
think about מצוה mitzvah in the context of the מקדש, Mikdash, it's
like how the מקדש Mikdash is supposed to operate, we're not talking
about like a private מצוה mitzvah obligation. But yes, in this context
in particular it means that this is the right way to do
it, but בדיעבד b'di'eved if you don't do it it's כשר. kasher.
So the גמרא Gemara says, so that seems to be strong evidence
for רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that בדיעבד b'di'eved it's not מעכב. me'akev.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא bishlama it works להך
לישנא דאמרת אליבא דרבי יהודה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דלא מעכבא, l'hach
lishna de'amart aleiba d'Rabbi Yehuda kuli alma lo peligi d'lo ma'akva, according
to the approach that even that both רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and
רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai would say that according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda it's not מעכב, me'akev, the only question was
whether even רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia would agree it's not מעכב me'akev
here because it's not an עבודה. avodah. So that works.
הא מני? רבי יהודה היא. Ha mani Rabbi Yehuda hi. Because then
everybody agrees that according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, who generally says
certain things might not be מעכב, me'akev, he would say this isn't
מעכב, me'akev, so that ברייתא braita works. Everybody could agree it's רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אלא, Ela, top of מ עמוד א, mem amud
aleph, להך לישנא דאמרת פליגי, l'hach lishna de'amart peligi, according to the
version that the debate of whether the drawing of the lots is
מעכב me'akev is a debate not within רבי נחמיה's Rabbi Nechemia position
but within רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position, and that according to רבי
ינאי Rabbi Yannai even רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, everybody says the drawing
of the lots is מעכב. me'akev. So, how does this ברייתא Braitah
say it's not מעכב? me'akev? בשלמא למאן דאמר לא מעכב, Bishlama leman
d'amar lo me'akev, of course it's fine according to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan who says it's not מעכב, me'akev, הא מני ha manni? רבי
יהודה היא. Rabbi Yehuda hi. It's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. אלא למאן
דאמר מעקבא, Ella leman d'amar me'akva, but according to the one that
says it is מעקבא, me'akva, הא מני? ha mani? Who is it
going like? So again, it's a little complicated because there's two debates
going on. There's רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai
who are debating whether the drawing of the lot is מעכב, me'akev,
and then there's two versions: are they debating it within רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, the generally more lenient position, or within רבי נחמיה? Rabbi
Nechemia? So what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, assuming they're debating
it within רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, and רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai who
says it's מעכב me'akev is saying that even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says it's מעכב, me'akev, everybody says it's מעכב, me'akev, what do you
do with the ברייתא Braitah that says it's not מעכב? me'akev? There's
nobody to attribute that ברייתא Braitah to. That's the גמרא's Gemara question.
Says the גמרא, Gemara, תני מצוה להניח. Tani mitzvah lehaniach. So alright,
we do what we do sometimes, we switch the text. When it
says it's a מצוה mitzvah to draw the lot, it doesn't really
mean it's, but בדיעבד bedi'avad it's not מעכב, me'akev, it doesn't mean
it's a מצוה mitzvah to draw the lot, it means it's a
מצוה mitzvah to put the lot on the head of the animal.
But if you drew, but if you didn't put it on the
head, you're still יוצא. yotzei. So להגריל, lehagril, we switch the word
להגריל lehagril to mean להניח. lehaniach. Now תוספות Tosfos actually points out
that הא דקאמר, had de-kamar, the second תוספות Tosfos on מ' עמוד
א', Mem Amud Aleph, תני מצוה להניח, Tani mitzvah lehaniach, אינו מגיה
ברייתא. eino magiah Braitah. I mean, you know, we've all been learning
the דף daf long enough to know that the גמרא Gemara will
not hesitate sometimes to make radical emendations to the text. But here
תוספות Tosfos is saying, and we'll see why because the way it
plays out in a minute, that it's not literally, it's not literally
changing the text. אלא פירושי קמפרש, Ella perushei kamefaresh, מאי לא הגריל
לא הניח הגורל. mai lo higril lo hiniach hagoral. When it says
didn't do the lot, it means didn't do the end of the
process of the lot. Okay? So it's a little vague what that
means didn't draw, didn't do the lot. Okay, so we have a
ברייתא Braitah that says בדיעבד bedi'avad if you didn't do the lot,
you're יוצא. yotzei. Who, how does that work if the one that
says you have to do the lot בדיעבד? bedi'avad? So the answer
is when it means if you didn't put the lot on the
head of the animal, then בדיעבד bedi'avad you're יוצא. yotzei. But certainly
you would have to draw the lot. תא שמע, Ta shema, let's
try again. Another ברייתא, Braitah, four lines from the top. מצוה להגריל,
Mitzvah lehagril, same idea, it's a מצוה mitzvah to draw the lot,
ולהתוודות, u'lehitvadot, and to say the וידוי, viduy, the confession, right? אנא
השם כפר נא Ana Hashem kaper na etc. לא הגריל ולא התודה,
Lo higril v'lo hitvadah, בדיעבד bedi'avad if you did it without drawing
the lot and without the וידוי viduy even, כשר, kasher, it's כשר.
kasher. The וידוי viduy is not מעכב. me'akev. So that's another interesting
question which we haven't addressed yet. That's, so here again we have
this ברייתא Braitah that says if you didn't draw the lot. So
the גמרא Gemara says, now obviously we now have an answer in
our back pocket, להגריל lehagril means להניח. lehaniach. So the גמרא Gemara
says no, I'm not going to let you say that. וכי תימא
הכי נמי להניח, V'chi teima hacha nami lehaniach, when it says if
you didn't do the lot, it means if you didn't place the
lot on the head of the animal, and that's when בדיעבד bedi'avad
it's not מעכב, me'akev,
אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the end of this ברייתא.
Braitah. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, לא הגריל כשר, lo higril
kasher, לא התודה פסול. lo hitvadah pasul. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says, I don't agree with you fully. I agree that if you
didn't do the lot it's כשר, kasher, but if you didn't do
the וידוי, viduy, the confession, it's לא כשר, lo kasher, it's פסול.
pasul. So there's a debate, one minute, there's a debate between רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים Chachamim whether the confession is מעכב.
me'akev. But everybody agrees that the הגרלה hagralah is not מעכב. me'akev.
Now, how does that prove whether the הגרלה hagralah refers to the
drawing of the lot or the placing of the lot? So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי לא הגריל, Mai lo higril,
what does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon mean when he's conceding that if
you didn't do the lot you're still יוצא? yotzei? אילימא לא הניח,
Ileiima lo hiniach, if it means like you've been trying to claim
that we're not talking about drawing the lot but placing the lot,
that's where we are saying it's not מעכב. me'akev. So מכלל דרבי
שמעון סבר הגרלה מעקבא. mikhlal de-Rabbi Shimon savar hagralah me'akva. Now I've
got a challenge for you, because if the word לא הגריל lo
higril is amended or translated to mean not to place the lot,
so they're saying if you didn't place the lot you're still יוצא.
yotzei. So the implication of that would be that if you didn't
draw the lot, then what? If I say if you don't place
the lot you're יוצא, yotzei, the implication would be that if you
don't draw it altogether you're not יוצא, yotzei, right? So if we've
now reframed the statements of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, they're debating whether בדיעבד bedi'avad if you didn't do
the וידוי, viduy, but they're agreeing about this issue of the lot
that that's not מעכב. me'akev. So if we are saying that they're
saying their statements about the placing of the lot, we now have
both of them saying, including רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that if you
didn't draw the lot you're not יוצא. yotzei. But you can't say
that. We actually know that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you are
יוצא yotzei without drawing the lot. How do we know? Let's take
a look. מכלל דרבי שמעון סבר הגרלה מעקבא. mikhlal de-Rabbi Shimon savar
hagralah me'akva. So to have them be talking about the placing of
the lot would imply that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say that
the drawing of the lot is מעכב, me'akev, that everybody agrees to
that. והתניא, V'ha tanya, I'll show you that's not true. מת אחד
מהם, Met ech mehem, let's say after the drawing of the lot
and after שחיטה shachting for example, the goat that goes on the
inside, the one that's לחטאת, l'chatat, the the שעיר seir
you're supposed to send off to the desert drops dead on you.
So what do you do? So one answer is, well get another
goat. There's a problem though, what's the problem? Yeah, first of all
the identical isn't מעכב, me'akev, but there's no process of the גורל,
goral, of the lot, of all the whole thing, right? You just
start with an independent, you don't start with them as a pair.
So there's a lot of things there that you could argue you
can't just grab another goat. And there is the opinions that you
can, you have to start the whole process again. But רב שמעון
Rav Shimon says no, in that case you can just take another
goat and just have that be the לעזאזל. l'Azazel. So that is
a pretty radical position of רב שמעון Rav Shimon which בדיעבד b'diavad
not only is the not drawing of the lots not מעכב, me'akeiv,
the whole process of starting as a pair, you know, and sort
of designating them differently and so on, even that is not מעכב.
me'akeiv.
No, but you're saying once the lot's been
drawn, already a lot's been drawn. But then not on the one
that's going לעזאזל. l'Azazel.
The lot's still been drawn.
Okay, but nobody is thinking about this as
מעכב me'akeiv somehow in the generic עבודת יום כיפור avodas Yom Kippur
and it's part about what makes מכשיר machshir this קרבן. korban. That
nobody says you're not יוצא yotzei the other קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says so let's take a look. מת אחד מהן
מביא חברו שלא בהגרלה. Meis echad meihen meivi chaveiro shelo behagra'ah. Okay,
so bring the other one without doing the drawing of the lot.
דברי רבי שמעון, Divrei Rebbe Shimon, that's what רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
said.
So you see that רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says that בדיעבד b'diavad
the drawing of the lot isn't מעכב. me'akeiv. So it's quite interesting
actually just take a moment and take a step back. We have
this whole debate of רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan and רבי ינאי Rebbe
Yannai is drawing of the lot מעכב? me'akeiv? We're trying to figure
out is it according to רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, is it according
to רבי נחמיה. Rebbe Nechemia. Now we find out that there's a
תנא Tanna that very clearly holds it's not מעכב. me'akeiv. But that
position is sort of seen as a very sort of exceptional position.
We're bracketing רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon is pretty
radical. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says not only is not drawing of
the lot מעכב me'akeiv like the whole process isn't מעכב. me'akeiv. So
we're going to bracket רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. We're talking about everybody
else that thinks in general this process is מעכב me'akeiv would the
drawing of the lot be? So one is to appreciate that there
is a position that clearly states it's not but that's being bracketed.
We're talking because that's like a somewhat radical position and we're talking
within the general assumption that the process is מעכב. me'akeiv. But in
context of what the גמרא Gemara is saying right now so we
have a ברייתא brayta that says בדיעבד b'diavad if you don't draw
the lot it's good. So it says you want to reframe that
if because you think you have to draw the lot says בדיעבד
b'diavad if you didn't place the lot on the head. But then
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon is saying that okay בדיעבד b'diavad not placing
the lot is okay but implicitly saying that you have to draw
the lot? But we know that's not רבי שמעון's Rebbe Shimon position.
So clearly they're talking about the drawing they're not talking about the
placing. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Let me just
finish this thought, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי
שמעון לא ידע מאי קאמרי רבנן. Rebbe Shimon lo yada mai kamri
rabanan. No, רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon wasn't sure what the רבנן rabanan
meant when the רבנן rabanan said בדיעבד b'diavad you don't have to
draw the lot, you don't have to do the lot. והכי קאמר
להו, V'hachi kamar lehu, this is what he's saying back to the
רבנן: rabanan: Listen guys, אי הגרלה הגרלה ממש i hagra'ah hagra'ah mamash
when you say you don't have to do the lot that you're
יוצא yotzei if you literally mean you don't have to draw the
lot altogether קאמריתו, kamrisu, that that's what you're saying, פליגנא עליכו בחדא.
pligina alaichu bachada. Then great, I totally agree בדיעבד b'diavad you don't
have to do the lot. You're not going to get any argument
from me about that. But I disagree with you about saying the
וידוי. viduy. There I think that if you don't do it you're
not יוצא. yotzei. So then that's why I'm going to focus on
the וידוי viduy because maybe we're in agreement about the lot. Maybe
you mean that בדיעבד b'diavad you don't have to do the lot.
But אי הגרלה דקאמריתו היינו הנחה i hagra'ah d'kamrisu haynu hanachah on
the other hand if when you said בדיעבד b'diavad you don't have
to do the lot what you meant is you don't have to
place the lot on the top of the animal but you really
are of the position that you have to draw the lot, if
that's what you're saying then פליגנא עליכו בתרתי pligina alaichu betarti you
should know by the way I argue on both of the things
you said. Okay. So basically what we're saying is is that it's
clearly the simple sense of the ברייתא brayta is that both according
to the רבנן rabanan and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon the drawing of
the lot is not מעכב. me'akeiv. The גמרא Gemara how does that
work with רבי ינאי Rebbe Yannai that says it is מעכב? me'akeiv?
So the גמרא Gemara rereads it and says you know רבי שמעון
Rebbe Shimon yes says it is, and when רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon
says the lot's not I mean it's not, when רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon says the drawing of the lot is not מעכב me'akeiv he
literally means the drawing of the lot is not מעכב. me'akeiv. But
the רבנן's rabanan position they're only talking about placing the lot. They're
not talking about drawing. Okay. So again many of the ברייתות braytas
seem to indicate that the drawing is not מעכב me'akeiv but the
גמרא Gemara reframes it to be that the placing is and we
have the position of רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon that is more radical
that even the whole process is not מעכב. me'akeiv. First though you
had a question before.
I just want to make sure that I'm keeping sight of the
foundation of the whole thing. רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon would claim that
it's not מעכב me'akeiv
fundamentally because he doesn't believe that this entire process is an עבודה?
avodah?
Oh so that's an interesting question. So there are things there are
things that are עבודות avodos that are מעכב, me'akeiv, right, you know.
So right you know we are going to see what we haven't
seen yet is a systematic approach to how do we know what
is מעכב. me'akeiv. Now you know normally in anything outside the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash you don't have to ask the question. The תורה
Torah says ולקחתם לכם פרי עץ הדר כפת תמרים וענף עץ עבת.
u'lakachtem lachem pri eitz hadar v'kapos tmarim v'anaf eitz avos. Well that's
למצוה l'mitzvah but if I only took two I would still be
יוצא. yotzei. Nobody would suggest such a thing. The תורה Torah says
do it, if you don't do it you're not יוצא. yotzei. But
when it comes to the קרבנות korbanos חז"ל Chazal have a start
with a basic assumption not just עבודת יום כיפור avodas Yom Kippur
in general there are so many details so many particulars that now
you could say fine but you got to do them all. Normally
that's what הלכה halacha is. You look up in שלחן ערוך Shulchan
Aruch in the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah you have a thousand details
if you're not doing it you're not יוצא. yotzei. But חז"ל Chazal
understand that no that actually the assumption is that nothing is מעכב
me'akeiv unless the תורה Torah somehow repeats it or underscores it. A
general principle is either
Or the language of חוק. chok. If it uses the language of
חוק, chok, and חוק chok does come up by יום כיפור Yom
Kippur as well, that means it's מעכב. me'akeiv. So what you have
to realize is that the general assumption is that details in the
קרבנות korbanot are often not מעכב me'akeiv unless you have a פסוק
pasuk or reason or some indication that they are. So we have
not seen why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows him to take this
position particularly, we're actually going to see something to that degree in
a minute, but I want to just basically respond to your question,
it is not, you know, it should not be seen as bizarre
that the statement that a major thing is not מעכב me'akeiv because
very often
there's an assumption that a
lot of details are not מעכב. me'akeiv.
Suppose I take a goat, I take a sheep, it's not...
No, that not. I know, so the question is where to draw
the line. Right. So that's actually interesting because that issue
about like the species of animal is not...
You know,
that's an interesting point that some of the assumptions like how much
wine, how much flour, what age of the animal, there the גמרא
Gemara never feels a need to prove it's מעכב, me'akeiv, it's more
of a question of, you know, how the עבודה avodah is done,
you know, with the details of the עבודה, avodah, that there you
need some repetition. But it's a good point that why that is
assumed to definitely be required. Michael, you had a hand up?
Yeah, I mean what I was going to say was, this is
very interesting, the point about רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon against the viewpoint
of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, for us I feel like the whole
point, right?
Right, then it becomes more formulaic, you know.
Okay, so we'll talk about that too, but actually that was a
discussion I was having with Norm beforehand which is, you know, it
gets to the issue we discussed yesterday about the focus of the
תורה Torah and so much of the עבודה avodah is the stuff
that's done בפנים bifnim about being מטהר metaher המקדש haMikdash that we
don't relate to at all, what we primarily relate to is the
וידוי viduy because that we can relate to. And then the וידוי
viduy by the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach and that's our personal atonement,
but that's not the primary focus in the תורה Torah about the
עבודה. avodah. And similarly, the high emphasis on וידוי viduy which for
us is central to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, תשובה teshuvah and וידוי
viduy is not central to the תורה. Torah. The תורה Torah doesn't
really talk about תשובה teshuvah in the context of, I mean תשובה
teshuvah you sort of get it at the end of דברים, Devarim,
but in that context of אחרי מות Acharei Mot you don't get
a discussion of תשובה, teshuvah, you don't get a discussion of personal
וידוי, viduy, all you get is this ritual וידוי. viduy. So much
more in the תורה Torah it is the ritual of קרבנות korbanot
that effects a metaphysical cleansing and much less the personal process of
וידוי viduy and תשובה. teshuvah. But so that's just something we have
to accept as a very different type of a framework. But yes,
that being said, וידוי viduy is something that we would think is,
you know, is a necessary component, so we'll have to see what
that debate is about later. We're not done with this issue, okay.
Rifka, you had a question?
No it was basically
those points.
It takes away from the randomness if you view that whole thing
with the goat as symbolic of the randomness of life with those
two identical animals that have a completely different fate. So
without the הגרלה... hagralah... Right.
So it's sort of like Michael, it's like don't take away the
things of the עבודה avodah that we can relate to. Like all
you're leaving is the שחיטה shechitah and the blood! We want the
וידוי, viduy, we want the הגרלה, hagralah, that's at least the part
we can relate to, yes, it's true. Yeah.
Can you clarify when you said that nothing is מעכב me'akeiv unless
it's repeated or as the word חוק chok was used, was that
specifically about the קרבנות korbanot and was it only inside or outside?
No, that's like by all קרבנות, korbanot, like even not יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, like even when you learn like about the חטאת, chatat,
right, if you put one placement of דם dam on the corner
and not all four corners בדיעבד bedi'avad you're יוצא. yotzei. So a
lot of details of קרבנות korbanot in general, there's an assumption that
the details are not מעכב me'akeiv unless you have an indication that
they are.
It seems it should be the opposite because with קרבנות korbanot and
the עבודה avodah במקדש, baMikdash, it's almost explicit that there's a metaphysical
component here of כפרה. kaparah. So you would think that if you
don't do it exactly right, the assumption should be that it's מעכב,
me'akeiv, right? And with other things, you know, with things outside the
מקדש, Mikdash, you know, so we have like common sense and things,
but you know, the fact the תורה Torah tells you to do
this doesn't say why you take a לולב. lulav. So you would
think it's the opposite.
Yeah, I agree, meaning you know why is it that the stuff
that is sort of most central to the, you know, sort of
to connecting to God as sort of seeing you know the centrality
of the מקדש Mikdash as the עבודה, avodah, why is it that
some details like don't matter as much, you know, as outside they
do. So again my assumption had always been, as I said, that
it has to do with just the vast amount of details that
there's some like going into it assumption that like you can't tell
me all of this is מעכב, me'akeiv, but I don't know. You
know, you could make an interesting argument the other way, sort of
like if you're like a בן בית, ben bayit, you're right there
in the home, when you're a little bit further away you've got
to be more careful. I don't know, there's probably a good דרשה
drasha in there, but yes, it certainly is ironic. Okay, so now
let's see the גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, תא
שמע, ta shema, so middle of מ"ד mem dalet עמוד א' amud
aleph by the little א'. aleph. Come and hear. ארבעה מעכבין בדאורייתא,
arba'ah me'akvin b'de'oraisa, now we're going to get to some of the
question of how do we know... how they're מעכב. me'akev. But this
is going to, these types of discussions will be very confusing, so,
and that's going to be coming up, so a lot of places
like, wait, wait, if you didn't do this, how does this affect
that? But we're going to try to keep it simple for now,
okay. פר מעכב את השעירה. Par me'akev et ha'seira. Not doing, now
the פר par and the שעירה, seira, remember, the פר par is
the כהן גדול's Kohen Gadol פר par that he brings and does
the sprinkles. The goat here is not the שעיר המשתלח, Seira HaMishtaleach,
it's the one that's the להשם חטאת L'Hashem Chatat and it's the
one that represents, right, the people's, the עם Am and their sins,
but again in the cleansing of the מקדש Mikdash process. Okay, so
פר, par, if you do something wrong with the, with the cow,
with the bull, מעכב את השעירה, me'akev et ha'seira, that prevents the
goat from being valid. The שעירה seira comes earlier, meaning if you
did it out of order, okay. So, so שעירה, seira, but if
the goat, doing it out of order, אין מעכב את הפר, ein
me'akev et ha'par, does not prevent the,
the bull from being good. So what does it mean? So, so
פר מעכב את השעירה par me'akev et ha'seira means if you did
the, if you did one of the עבודות avodot of the שעירה
seira
earlier than it should have been done, you sort of, it bumped
ahead of the פר, par, it jumped in the order, then the
fact that it was trying to sort of de-seat the פר, par,
that prevents the שעירה seira from being good. But if the פר
par bumped in the line and did, you did something with the
פר par before the goat, then, then the goat will still be
good. That's basically what it's saying. So let me remind, it's very,
though, I know, it is confusing, which is why I'm telling it
to you. What, you know, how, how the גמרא Gemara understands it.
Now there's a very nice רש"י Rashi here that gives you a
summary of the entire order of the עבודות, avodot, which you need
to know in order to understand this. So take a look at
רש"י Rashi where רש"י Rashi says,
here let's just read the רש"י, Rashi, פר מעכב את השעירה, par
me'akev et ha'seira, like eight lines before the lines get wide. אם
הקדים אחת מעבודות של שעירה המאוחרות לשל פר ועשה קודם לפר, Im
hikdim achat mei'avodot shel seira hamu'acharot leshel par v'asa kodem lapar, so
means if the goat sort of like bumped in in, ahead of
the line, so הפר שראוי להקדם לה, hapar sheraui l'hakadem lah, the
פר par which should have been first ahead of it in the
line, מעכבא me'akva prevents it from being good ופוסלה u'posla and invalidates.
So the פר par invalidates the goat if the goat bumps in
the, ahead of it in the line. ואין לה עוד אלא וצריך
לחזור ולעשות לאחר הפר. V'ein lah od elah v'tzarich lachzor v'la'asot l'achar
hapar. And then you have to go back and do the goat.
Now, here's רש"י's Rashi very nice little summary of how the order
of all the עבודות avodot with the, with the פר par and
the
שעירה. seira. וסדר עבודתם כך היא בפרשה. V'seder avodatam kach hi b'parsha.
בתחילה מתוודה על הפר וידוי ראשון, Batichilah mitvadeh al hapar vidui rishon,
ואחר מגריל על השעירה, v'achar magrial al ha'seira, ואחר מתוודה על הפר
וידוי שני, v'achar mitvadeh al hapar vidui sheini, ושחטו ומכניס כף. v'shachto
u'machnis kaf. So can somebody read this for me so I'm going
to write this down. So first you do the וידוי פר, vidui
par, right? That, that we've had in an earlier משנה, mishna, okay.
Then you do what? Then you go ahead and do the הגרלה,
hagrala, right?
מגריל על השעירים.
Magrial al ha'seirim. Then what do you do?
מתוודה על הפר. Mitvadeh al hapar. וידוי פר שני. Vidui par sheini.
וידוי שני, Vidui sheini, right, this is about, this is for him
and this is for the כהנים, Kohanim, okay, right. Go ahead. ושחטו.
U'shachto. Okay, שחיטת פר, shechitah par, yep.
ומכניס כף. U'machnis kaf.
Okay, so now this is, right, הכנסת כף, hachnasat kaf, this is
the
קטורת, ktoret, yeah. ומחתה. U'machtah.
כף ומחתה, Kaf u'machtah, right, and then.
נותן את הקטורת על האש. Notein et haktoret al ha'esh.
Right, the whole קטורת ktoret process, yeah. Keep going.
נותן מדם הפר על הכפורת. Notein midam hapar al hakaporet. דם הפר
על הכפורת, Dam hapar al hakaporet, right.
ואחר כך שוחט את
השעירה.
V'achach shocheit
et ha'seira. נותן ממנו על הכפורת. Notein mimeno al hakaporet.
שעירה, seira,
דם השעירה על הכפורת, dam haseira al hakaporet, yeah.
ואחר כך נותן מדם הפר על הפרוכת. V'achach notein midam hapar al
haparochet.
דם הפר על הפרוכת. Dam hapar al haparochet. Is everybody getting this?
Yeah.
ואחר כך מדם השעירה. V'achach midam ha'seira.
דם השעירה על הפרוכת. Dam ha'seira al haparochet.
I'll get a new whiteboard. ואחר כך
מערב דמים.
V'achach
me'arev damim.
Okay.
ונותן על המזבח הפנימי. V'notein al hamizbe'ach hapnimi.
דמים Damim על, and this is already on the מזבח mizbe'ach הפנימי.
Okay, so that's,
that's a lot in terms of order. So what if you, so
now let's identify which is the פר par and which is the
שעירה. seira. פר, Par, וידוי פר שני, vidui par sheini, right, שחיטת
פר, shechitah par, דם הפר
על הכפורת, dam hapar al hakaporet, דם הפר על הפרוכת. dam hapar
al haparochet. Okay, that's פר. par.
And then רש"י Rashi went through all the סוגיות sugyot and then
gleaned the information and wrote that comment? Yep.
He could have just looked at the עבודה avodah in the מחזור.
Machzor. Okay.
Oh, he got the מראה מקומות mar'eh mekomot which is green address.
Yeah, I know, I was thinking about that. Okay, so this is
the order, okay. These in terms of פר par and שעירה, seira,
right, different עבודות, avodot, these are, this is the order, alright. So
the question is, so the basic statement is if at some place
where the שעירה seira was supposed to be later it's bumped in
the line... Let's say you שחט shachted the שעיר seir earlier here,
okay? Or you, you know, or I guess you put the blood
of the שעיר seir on the פרוכת Paroches before the blood of
the פר Par on the פרוכת. Paroches. If it, if it got,
you know, moved ahead in the line, the fact that the פר
Par was supposed to be first prevents you from being יוצא. yotze.
But if it's the reverse, if the פר Par bumped ahead of
the line, let's say you did the וידוי viduy of the פר
Par before the שעיר, seir, or the שחיטת shchitas of the פר
Par before the שעיר, seir, so if it, it bumped earlier in
the line, then the שעיר seir does not prevent it. That's what
the language says. Let's see how the גמרא Gemara now goes ahead
and reads it. All right, so it says like this. So אין
מעכבין את הפר. ein meakvin es hapar. Now, that's only true במתנות
שבפנים, be-matanos shebifnim, the things that are done inside the קודש קודשים,
Kodesh Kodashim, because if you remember, we mentioned before by רבי יהודה
ורבי נחמיה, Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Nechemiah, there's a general debate whether
order is מעכב meakev out of the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So
this issue about the פר Par preventing the שעיר seir but not
the reverse is only about things that are inside the קודש קודשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. Now, what things are inside the קודש קודשים? Kodesh Kodashim?
I need a third, a third, whatever. So let's star the things
that are inside the קודש קודשים: Kodesh Kodashim: דם הפר על הכפורת,
dam hapar al hakapores, not the שחיטת השעיר, shchitas haseir, דם השעיר
על הכפורת, dam haseir al hakapores, and that's what, that's basically it,
right? I mean, this is the פרוכת, Paroches, that's already, is already
not the קודש קודשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Okay, what, and the קטורת. ketores.
So it could have been, right, so for the שעיר, seir, what
would that mean, but the שעיר... seir... okay, whatever, let's, we'll see,
we'll see how that would play out. Okay, so let's take a
look. So how is it going to be we can get how
the שעיר seir would come before, would jump the line, but where
is the פר Par going to jump the line? Okay, so let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Well, what
if you did the וידוי פר שני viduy par sheini before the
הגרלה hagralah on... yeah, but that's not, that's not בעבודות שבפנים. be-avodos
shebifnim. Okay, במתנות שבפנים. be-matanos shebifnim. Let's take a look. בשלמא פר
מעכב את השעיר, bislama par meakev es haseir, I get the idea
that if the שעיר seir jumps the line, the פר Par prevents
it from being יוצא. yotze. דאקדמיה לשעיר מקמי פר לא עביד ולא
כלום. de-akdeimei laseir mikmei par lo avid velo klum. That if you
basically did the דם dam of the שעיר seir before the דם
dam of the פר Par on the כפורת, kapores, it doesn't count.
Fine. Okay. אלא שעיר אין מעכב את הפר מנייהו? ela seir ein
meakev es hapar mainihu? What's the case that the שעיר seir does
not prevent the פר Par from being good if the פר Par
jumps the line? So אילימא דאקדי מתנות דפר בהיכל מקמי מתנות דשעיר
בפנים. ileima de-akdi matanos depar beheichal mikmei matanos daseir bifnim. So what
you did was, let's say the פר Par jumping the line is
the פר Par on the פרוכת, Paroches, right, which is in the
היכל, Heichal, not in the קודש קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, jumps before the
שעיר seir on the כפורת. kapores. Okay, that's where the פר Par
would jump the line. But the problem is, חוק כתיב בו. chok
kesiv bo. So then how could you not, could you, how, how
says the גמרא Gemara could it not prevent you from being יוצא
yotze if you have the language of חוק, chok, which is... that
because basically now, here's going to be the funny thing that the
גמרא Gemara does. That while the ברייתא braisa focuses us on which
one is out of line, the פר Par or the שעיר, seir,
the גמרא Gemara is going to reframe it that it's really not
about the פר Par and the שעיר. seir. Why should one have
more power to invalidate than the other? If one of them bumps
the line, it should be the same. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's really
going to make it more about the details of which עבודה avodah
was it that we're talking about? So that's what the גמרא Gemara
says. What would be the case that the פר Par jumped the
line right before the שעיר? seir? The only meaningful jumping of the
line is doing it here before the כפורת, kapores, but then it
says it shouldn't invalidate. Then you've done something wrong about the עבודת
פנים. avodas pnim. So let's keep on going, one minute. So it
says, אלא
לאו, ela lav, so the case must
be, דאקדי מתנות דפר בפנים מקמי הגרלה. de-akdi matanos depar bifnim mikmei
hagralah. Okay, and so says like it can't be about פר Par
and שעיר. seir. The real thing is if it changes the order
of things that are done on the inside, it should prevent. So
it really has to be about not whether it's a פר Par
or שעיר, seir, but about what's the עבודה avodah that is affected.
So what it says it must really mean therefore is that what
you did is, what is it?
אלא מה,
ela
ma, it says, דאקדי מתנות דפר...
de-akdi
matanos depar...
one
minute... דאקדי מתנות דפר בפנים מקמי הגרלה. de-akdi matanos depar bifnim mikmei
hagralah. That what you did was you did this blood before having
done... you did this I guess all the way up here and...
And that's a better way to think about it is that you
didn't do the הגרלה. hagrolah. You did the הגרלה, hagrolah, you waited
and you did not do the הגרלה hagrolah at all. You did
the הגרלה hagrolah after. Okay. And the גמרא Gemara says if that's
true then the reason that would not be מעכב me'akeis is because
ultimately not that the שעיר se'ir isn't important but that the הגרלה
hagrolah isn't important. Okay. And see so if you did a wrong
order about the הגרלה hagrolah I have a sincere feeling I might
be losing people. So the ברייתא baraysa says that if you did
the פר par early, okay, the שעיר se'ir does not prevent the
פר par for you from being יוצא. yotzei. So the גמרא Gemara
says what's the case? If it just means you did the דם
dam of the פר par before the דם dam of the שעיר,
se'ir, then it should prevent it because you've actually postponed
the עבודה avoda of the כפרה. kapparah. You've actually postponed it. And
that's a חוק. chok. זה חוק. zeh chok. So rather the only
way it shouldn't prevent you from being יוצא yotzei is really what
it means is you just didn't do the הגרלה. hagrolah. You did
the whole thing with the פר par without doing the הגרלה. hagrolah.
And therefore the reason it's not a problem in that case is
because really the הגרלה hagrolah is not so important. That's what
now I realize there is a little bit of a problem here
because if you didn't do the הגרלה, hagrolah, it also means that
you didn't do this stuff, right? Which also means that you did
have it come before the שעיר. se'ir. And so let's just bracket
that for now.
You know there's a difference between it's a difference between being מקדים
makdim with the פר par with the שעיר se'ir being מוגרל mugral
or not being מוגרל. mugral. Right. So that conceptually seems to make
a difference, right? Because the הגרלה hagrolah is really giving the identity
to the שעיר. se'ir. If you haven't done that, then it's nothing.
Right. See what you're saying. No? One more time what did you
say?
In other words, if the הגרלה hagrolah was not done at all,
the שעיר se'ir that's not מוגרל mugral is just an animal. Right.
So you could say you did all this without the הגרלה, hagrolah,
but the גמרא Gemara is just saying and that's where you did
this order correct. Right. But the גמרא Gemara is saying that you
actually did the order wrong. So anyway let's read the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אלא לאו דאקדים מתנות דפר בפנים מקמי הגרלה. ela lav de'akdim
matnos depar bifnim mikmi hagrolah. You did all that stuff without doing
the הגרלה. hagrolah. ומידי דסדרא לא מעכב, umidei desidra lo me'akeis, since
the order is not מעכב, me'akeis, you can do the הגרלה hagrolah
later. So איכא דהגרלה נמי לא מעכבא, ika dehagrolah nami lo me'akva,
so maybe the whole idea of הגרלה hagrolah isn't מעכב me'akeis because
that's sort of what we've been assuming that if you're not מקפיד
makpid on the order maybe you're not מקפיד makpid on doing the
thing itself. So now the next two lines some take out, but
the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no wait a minute, לא. lo.
Maybe that's not the case. What it means is דאקדים מתנות דפר
במזבח מקמי מתנות דשעיר בהיכל. de'akdim matnos depar bamizbe'ach mikmi matnos deshe'ir
beheichal. Maybe what we're talking about here is not that this jumped
the line, but that this, the מתנות matnos of the פר par
on the מזבח here was before the שעיר se'ir on the היכל.
heichal. Maybe we're talking about this going here and that's what we're
talking about, okay? And that's why it's not מעכב. me'akeis. It's not
מעכב me'akeis because this isn't in the קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. So
you did maybe that's what you did wrong. That's the explanation.
So it's not the order...
רבי יהודה היא. Rabbi Yehudah hi. The place...
the order in that place, right?
Right, right.
Because it's necessarily... right, right, right. Oh, I mean the קודש קדשים
kodesh kodashim where order really is מעכב. me'akeis. רבי יהודה היא דאמר
דברים הנעשים בבגדי לבן מבחוץ לא מעכבי. Rabbi Yehudah hi de'omar devarim
hana'asim bevigdei lavan mibachutz lo me'akvei. And the reason that would not
be מעכב me'akeis is because it's out of the קודש קדשים. kodesh
kodashim. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, that was a nice try,
but והא מתנות שבפנים קתני. veha matnos shebifnim katani. The ברייתא baraysa
explicitly said if you went out of order relating to the stuff
בפנים, bifnim, relating to the stuff in the קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim.
Okay. So basically again what we have is a ברייתא baraysa that
says if you go out of order with the stuff that's in
the קודש קדשים, kodesh kodashim, which is really only these two, right?
These are the only two that are in the קודש קדשים. kodesh
kodashim. If you go out of order, so it's a problem if
the goat goes out of order, if the goat goes earlier. But
it's not a problem if the פר par goes out of order.
So the question is how would the פר par go out of
order? How would the פר בפנים par bifnim right, go earlier? It
anyway is earlier. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara says we have to
be talking about these. So maybe the case of the פר par
going earlier means this is the part... I mean they don't both
have to be talking about בפנים. bifnim. So the פר par going
earlier is something that occurs goes down here goes earlier. And the
גמרא Gemara says but no, but if that were true, it should
be no good. So rather the גמרא Gemara says okay, so the
פר par going earlier meant that this happened before... oh, that's the
explanation for what I was saying before. The פר par going earlier
means this happened before the הגרלה. hagrolah. So you came down and
you did the הגרלה hagrolah down here. Okay. So it says if
you did... talking about the stuff that's on the inside, if you
did it earlier... now yeah, now my explanation. If you did it
earlier, it's a problem for the goat, not a problem for the
cow. So doing the goat earlier we understand, that's a problem and
this is stuff done on the inside and הסדר מעכב. haseder me'akeis.
Doing the פר par earlier on the inside would mean what? It
would mean waiting to do the הגרלה hagrolah until you're done with
the פר. par. Okay, and so why isn't it מעכב? me'akeis? It's
something done on the inside, there is a problem with it, why
isn't it a problem? The only reason it's not a problem is
because ultimately the הגרלה hagrolah itself is not so important. That's what
the גמרא... Gemara... that's what... That's what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay,
that was a little clearer. So let's keep on going. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא הא מני רבי שמעון. Ella Ha
Mani Rabbi Shimon. Fine, you proved that according to that ברייתא Braisa
order doesn't matter about the הגרלה. Hagralah. Fine, who's that ברייתא Braisa
going like? It's going like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, like we already
saw, there's a רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that says the whole process
isn't so important, isn't so מעכב. Maakev. דאמר הגרלה לא מעכבא, De'amar
Hagralah lo ma'akva, הגרלה Hagralah doesn't prevent it. ואיבעית אימא לעולם רבי
יהודה היא. Ve'iba'is eima le'olam Rabbi Yehudah hi. And you know what,
I'll give you another thing, I can tell you that it is
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehudah, cause we know רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah generally
says order isn't מעכב Maakev out of the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
But there's a difference between order and doing the thing
itself. דנהי דסידרא לא מעכב, De'nehi de'sidra lo me'akev, he might say
that order isn't מעכב, Maakev, הגרלה מיהא מעכבא, Hagralah miha me'akva, but
the הגרלה Hagralah is מעכב, Maakev, okay? So again, I know this
is confusing and this is just a foretaste of it, but again
to repeat what the ברייתא Braisa said, I'll just say one last
time. It's talking about the פר ושעיר Par ve'Sayir that is done
בפנים, Bifnim, those only two עבודות. Avodos. If you did the שעיר
Sayir earlier and the בפנים Bifnim is where everything is מעכב. Maakev.
If you did the שעיר Sayir earlier you are not יוצא Yotzei
with the שעיר. Sayir. If you did the פר Par earlier you
are יוצא. Yotzei. So what does it mean to do the פר
Par earlier than the שעיר Sayir here? The only thing it could
mean is did you did it before you did the הגרלה. Hagralah.
So why isn't it מעכב Maakev if it's בפנים? Bifnim? It must
be evidence that the הגרלה Hagralah is not important or is not
מעכב Maakev in general. And the גמרא Gemara answers no, not necessarily,
maybe it's just evidence that the הגרלה, Hagralah, the order isn't מעכב.
Maakev. But we would say, but you would still need to do
the הגרלה Hagralah in order to be יוצא. Yotzei.
I don't understand the difference between the סדר Seder and the act
itself.
Really? You don't understand the difference?
Well are they talking about שבע ברכות?
Sheva Brachos? For example שבע ברכות, Sheva Brachos, if you do them
out of order you're still יוצא. Yotzei. You can't understand that doing
things as long as you do it, בדיעבד Bedi'eved the order doesn't
matter?
Of course I understand that, of course the distinction the גמרא Gemara
is now making to say no, the order is not מעכב, Maakev,
the thing itself is מעכב. Maakev.
Right, if you don't do the הגרלה Hagralah at all,
you don't do it at all. Right, don't do it at all.
Exactly, that
is מעכב. Maakev. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואזדו
לטעמייהו, V'azdu l'ta'amayhu, and it gets a little easier now. And they
go according to their reasoning. So רש"י Rashi says this goes back
to the earlier debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים, Chachamim, like where is this idea coming
from from רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that the whole process isn't מעכב,
Maakev, you know, that if you don't do the הגרלה Hagralah and
anything it's not מעכב. Maakev. But let's take a look. דתניא, Detanya,
we learn in a ברייתא: Braisa: יעמד חי לפני ה' לכפר עליו.
Ya'amad chai lifnei Hashem lechaper alav. I have to say it's plainly
God forbid תוספות סימני יומא. Tosafos Simanei Yoma. יעמד חי לפני ה'
לכפר עליו. Ya'amad chai lifnei Hashem lechaper alav. So here it says
by the שעיר, Sayir, it says you know by השעיר אשר עלה
עליו הגורל לעזאזל. Ha'sayir asher ala alav ha'goral l'Azazel. So the one
that is for לעזאזל L'Azazel should stand alive לכפר עליו Lechaper alav
to atone for it, לשלח אותו לעזאזל המדברה. L'shalach oso l'Azazel ha'midbarah.
That's the פסוק. Pasuk. So they want to know what is this
what you know what is the emphasis of יעמד חי. Ya'amad chai.
So let's take a look. עד מתי יהיה זקוק לעמוד חי? Ad
masai yiheye zakuk la'amod chai? Until what time does the שעיר Sayir
have to still be alive? What בדיעבד Bedi'eved is מעכב Maakev about
the שעיר המשתלח? Sayir ha'Mishtale'ach? Okay, before we were shocked like that
the וידוי Viduy would not be מעכב Maakev by the שעיר לה'.
Sayir L'Hashem. Let's take a look. At what point am I יוצא
Yotzei the שעיר לעזאזל? Sayir l'Azazel? Let's say I didn't do everything
by the שעיר לעזאזל. Sayir l'Azazel. What point am I יוצא? Yotzei?
So עד שעת מתן דמו של חבירו דברי רבי יהודה. Ad she'as
matan damo shel chaveiro divrei Rabbi Yehudah. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
says until you bring the שעיר לה'. Sayir L'Hashem. Once you bring
the שעיר לה', Sayir L'Hashem, if the שעיר לעזאזל Sayir l'Azazel drops
dead, you're still יוצא. Yotzei. That's amazing, it could drop dead afterwards
and you be יוצא. Yotzei. יעמד חי לפני ה' לכפר עליו Ya'amad
chai lifnei Hashem lechaper alav says רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that לכפר
עליו Lechaper alav means
when the דם Dam of the שעיר Sayir is מכפר עליו. Mechaper
alav. This has to remain alive as long as that is still
atoning. But once that atones, you don't have to send it לעזאזל.
L'Azazel. Okay, that's his position. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehudah. That's
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehudah. רבי שמעון אומר עד שעת וידוי דברים. Rabbi
Shimon omer ad she'as viduy devarim. No, לכפר עליו Lechaper alav means
you're doing the כפרה Kaparah on the one that's going לעזאזל. L'Azazel.
So it has to be alive until you do the וידוי. Viduy.
The shocking thing is that according to both of them, if it
drops dead after the וידוי, Viduy, you're יוצא. Yotzei. It doesn't have
to go over the cliff. Okay, the only question is at what
point, you know, whether you have to do the וידוי Viduy or
not, but everybody agrees once the וידוי Viduy is done, you know,
even if it didn't go over the cliff, you're יוצא. Yotzei.
So it goes over the cliff?
The וידוי, Viduy, no, on the שעיר
לעזאזל Sayir l'Azazel that goes over the cliff. Actually on this year
we don't have where you did the וידוי Viduy and the שעיר
לעזאזל. Sayir l'Azazel. That's coming up. We don't have the וידוי Viduy
on the שעירים Se'irim either, so we sort of shortchanged it.
Doesn't have to take the
דם Dam into the קודש? Kodesh? No, the שעיר לעזאזל Sayir l'Azazel
never has the דם Dam go in.
No, the other one.
No, the other one does. But no, the order is that first
the other one has the דם Dam taken in and then you
do the וידוי Viduy on
the שעיר לעזאזל. Sayir l'Azazel.
So right, could be ten
minutes difference.
Yeah, exactly. In that interval it dropped dead even before you did
the וידוי. Viduy. That's the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah and
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
But is it the וידוי Viduy or the זריקה Zrika that has
to be?
No, no, the וידוי Viduy on the שעיר לעזאזל. Sayir l'Azazel. Basically
what you have is you have, I
see, okay,
you have you have וידוי, Viduy, now everything is working.
We need a new
set. Okay, anyway, you have וידוי Viduy of the שעיר להשם, Se'ir
Lahashem,
שחיטה, Shechita, right, of the שעיר להשם, Se'ir Lahashem, then you have
מתן דמים Matan Damim together with of course all of the פר,
Par, right? Then you have וידוי Viduy on the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir
La'azazel. שעיר
לעזאזל,
Se'ir La'azazel,
how do I spell it? And then you have like דחיקה, Dechika,
מצוק, Mitzok, pushing it over the cliff. Okay? So the point is
this is the שעיר להשם, Se'ir Lahashem, this is the שעיר לעזאזל.
Se'ir La'azazel. So when it says this is יעמד חי לכפר עליו,
Ya'amad Chai Lechaper Alav, does it, you have to have this alive
until this is done with its כפרה Kapara and then you're יוצא
Yotzei even if it drops dead? So לכפר עליו Lechaper Alav goes
on this, this דם, Dam, right? Or is it יעמד חי Ya'amad
Chai until you do, oh, it says לכפר עליו Lechaper Alav until
you do the וידוי? Viduy? Okay? And then, but if it dies
after the וידוי Viduy before you push it off the cliff, then
everybody would agree you're יוצא. Yotzei.
So that's the question, meaning the meaning of pushing it off.
Exactly. Okay, but let's, so let's mull on that, but let's see
what the גמרא Gemara is doing right
now. Okay, במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai Kamiflagi? What do they
debate? דתניא: Detanya: לכפר עליו, Lechaper Alav, לכפר, Lechaper, בכפרת דמים הכתוב
מדבר. Bechaparat Damim Hakatuv Medaber. So here, this is what you were,
you were saying, Jonathan, that לכפר Lechaper means the normal word of
the word כפרה, Kapara, the putting of blood. So לכפר עליו Lechaper
Alav means until that the עזאזל Azazel has to be alive until
the דם Dam כפרה Kapara of the שעיר להשם Se'ir Lahashem is
done, and then you're יוצא. Yotzei. וכן הוא אומר: Vechen Hu Omer:
וכלה מכפר את הקודש. Vechila Mechaper Et Hakodesh. That's what it says
in the context of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. כיפר Kipper means the
blood
ritual in the sanctuary. מה להלן בכפרת דמים אף כאן בכפרת דמים.
Ma Lehalan Bechaparat Damim Af Kan Bechaparat Damim. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei
Reb Yehuda. That's what רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda says. רבי שמעון Reb
Shimon אומר: Omer: No, לכפר עליו, Lechaper Alav, בכפרת דברים הכתוב מדבר.
Bechaparat Devarim Hakatuv Medaber. It means until you say the וידוי, Viduy,
okay? So, and that's, you know, so you do the act of
atonement, the more verbal atonement. And it's interesting, he doesn't say where
what's the strength of his argument, right? I mean, the strength of
the word לכפר Lechaper meaning blood is a powerful one. So רש"י
Rashi says the strength of his argument is that the simple sense
of עליו Alav means the one לעזאזל, La'azazel, the one we're talking
about. If you say יעמד חי לפני השם לכפר עליו, Ya'amad Chai
Lifnei Hashem Lechaper Alav, so
the עליו, Alav, the, what's the thing that precedes the pronoun? The
antecedent seems clearly to be the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir La'azazel. So if
it means לכפר עליו, Lechaper Alav, it means until you do the
וידוי. Viduy. Okay? So again, the debate is this thing has to
remain alive until לכפר עליו, Lechaper Alav, until this has done the
כפרה, Kapara, which he has the idea of כפרה Kapara being דמים,
Damim, or לכפר עליו, Lechaper Alav, עליו Alav means the שעיר לעזאזל
Se'ir La'azazel until you've done the atonement. Okay, that's the debate. Now,
what does the... You've done the וידוי. Viduy. I mean, yeah.
So they're drawing a distinction between וידוי Viduy and כפרה. Kapara.
Right, well, the question is does the word...
After the וידוי Viduy we haven't received כפרה Kapara yet, that maybe
okay enough.
Well, well, what it's saying is is that the שעיר לעזאזל, Se'ir
La'azazel, the כפרה Kapara can be achieved with just by the וידוי
Viduy because there is not a classic מתן דמים Matan Damim by
the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir La'azazel. So what achieves the כפרה Kapara of
the שעיר לעזאזל? Se'ir La'azazel? That's basically exactly what that's saying. Now,
I do want to say what is this debate demonstrating? What is
this אזל לטעמיה? Azal Letameih? So רש"י Rashi says this is going
back to the question we had before, like Rebecca you asked, which
is where does רבי שמעון Reb Shimon get this idea that the
וידוי Viduy is not מעכב? Me'akeiv? Okay, so רש"י Rashi says oh,
he gets the idea that the וידוי Viduy is not מעכב Me'akeiv
from here, because he says if the שעיר Se'ir drops dead, after,
after you're done with the שעיר להשם, Se'ir Lahashem, you're
יוצא Yotzei the שעיר לעזאזל. Se'ir La'azazel. That's how רש"י Rashi explains
it. רבינו חננאל: Rabbeinu Chananel: לכפר עליו, Lechaper Alav, you need to
do the וידוי. Viduy. So the debate before whether וידוי Viduy is
מעכב Me'akeiv is based on this פסוק, Pasuk, very simple. Of course,
this is about שעיר לעזאזל, Se'ir La'azazel, maybe it's different if you're
dealing with the other animals, but that's where they're debating whether this
issue of whether it requires you to do the וידוי Viduy to
be יוצא. Yotzei. תוספות Tosafot says, and I'm not going to because
it's late and complicated, I'm not going to get into the details,
but תוספות Tosafot says that no, what this is showing you is
not just the debate of whether the כפרה Kapara is מעכב. Me'akeiv.
What this is showing you is why in general רבי שמעון Reb
Shimon thinks that the whole process of הגרלה Hagrala is not מעכב.
Me'akeiv. Why he thinks that that is not so critical. Because תוספות,
Tosafot, I'll just try to tell it to you simply if I
can reconstruct it. Okay, what תוספות Tosafot says is like this, according
to רבי שמעון, Reb Shimon, רבי שמעון Reb Shimon says that when
this says, hold on, let me just make sure I've got
this, right, שמעון Shimon is the one that says וידוי Viduy is
מעכב. Me'akeiv. I'm sorry. רבי שמעון Reb Shimon is the one that
says וידוי Viduy is מעכב. Me'akeiv. So רבי שמעון Reb Shimon says
that לכפר עליו Lechaper Alav means until you're done doing the כפרה
Kapara on this, right? רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda who says וידוי Viduy
is, all right, I lost people, I make a what. Okay, doing
the כפרה. Kapara.
Okay,
רבי שמעון Reb Shimon says that לכפר... Lechaper... Okay,
רבי שמעון Reb Shimon says that לכפר עליו Lechaper Alav means until
you've done the וידוי, Viduy, of this, and that means that וידוי
Viduy is מעכב. Me'akeiv. So that's what רש״י Rashi says, that's where
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon gets his idea וידוי viduy is מעכב. me'akeiv.
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says no, לכפר עליו lachaper alav means here,
and therefore וידוי viduy is not מעכב. me'akeiv. But תוספות Tosfos says
it's something, it goes further. Says look, the question is to what
degree is the
שעיר להשם, sa'ir la-Hashem, שעיר לעזאזל sa'ir la'azazel linked to the שעיר
להשם. sa'ir la-Hashem. That's also what's going on in this debate. So
when רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon says, when if you have to wait
to be יוצא, yotzei, you have to wait to do the וידוי,
viduy, on the one hand it's making you wait till a later
point to do the וידוי, viduy, but on the other hand what
it's telling you is, this שעיר sa'ir is not at all dependent
on this. What it's dependent on to be יוצא yotzei is whether
you did the וידוי. viduy. Whether you finished the דמים damin here
or not is irrelevant. לכפר עליו lachaper alav means what are you
doing about the שעיר לעזאזל? sa'ir la'azazel? Whereas רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
says no, for this to be יוצא yotzei you need this. So
that's the debate. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda links the two and רבי
שמעון Rebbe Shimon unlinks the two. And therefore that translates into the
question of whether בדיעבד b'diavad the whole process of the lot is
מעכב. me'akeiv. According to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda that this depends on
this, the whole process of drawing up the lots and starting with
them together as a pair is necessary. According to רבי שמעון Rebbe
Shimon that this is independent, then בדיעבד b'diavad even if this one
drops dead, if this drops dead, you can bring a new one
here and you don't have to do the whole process again.
And this is huge theologically. In other words, if they're dependent, right,
your
וידוי viduy as an independent human being is linked inextricably with the
cleansing of הקדוש ברוך הוא's Hakadosh Baruch Hu house.
That's a very good point.
And if they're independent, I'm taking care of הקדוש ברוך הוא Hakadosh
Baruch Hu and the משכן, mishkan, I'm cleaning the house, but I
have my own existential problem.
That's a very beautiful point, meaning to be thinking that the question
of is the הגרלה hagralah מעכב me'akeiv is not just the question
as Rifka said like the symbolism of the randomness and the lot.
The other point that comes out from תוספות's Tosfos explanation is that
the question is to what degree does the personal atonement connect or
the atonement of עוונות avonot connect to the cleansing of the מקדש.
mikdash. Cosmic. Right. Okay, so that's תוספות's Tosfos explanation, that's very nice.
That's the question. See פני משה Pnei Moshe תוספות. Tosfos. Alright, so
it's a huge one, it's the one that starts on the previous
עמוד amud and it's over to the תמיד. tamid. Yeah, okay. Okay,
so that's how תוספות Tosfos understands that this question of what לכפר
lachaper means is whether you are linking the שעיר לעזאזל sa'ir la'azazel
to the שעיר להשם. sa'ir la-Hashem. According to רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
לכפר lachaper means כפרת דמים, kaparas damim, you're linking them, and according
to רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon who demands the וידוי, viduy, fundamentally the
word לכפר lachaper is not linking them. Okay, let's do a little
bit more, try to get one more proof in. תא שמע, Ta
shma, come in here. שאל תלמידו את רבי עקיבא. Sha'al talmido es
Rebbe Akiva. So the student asks רבי עקיבא: Rebbe Akiva: עלה בשמאל,
ala b'smol, מה שיחזיר לימין? mah she'yachazir l'yamin? So before we talked
about not rigging the lottery, they said maybe even after the fact,
if you drew the one that said להשם חטאת la-Hashem chatas in
your left hand, can you put it over into your right hand?
Can you switch the lot after you drew them? You can't rig
it though. Exactly. אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them: אל
תתנו מקום לצדוקים לרדות. al titnu makom l'tzedukim lirdos. Don't give the
צדוקים tzedukim some basis to rebel, meaning some basis to show that
like, oh, we do whatever the heck we want. So which is
an interesting answer, which means fundamentally you could do it. So the
גמרא Gemara says: טעמא ta'ama דאל תתנו מקום לצדוקים לרדות, d'al titnu
makom l'tzedukim lirdos, that's the only reason why you can't switch hands.
הא לאו הכי, Ha lav hachi, if it were not for that,
מהדרינן ליה, mahadrinan lei, so you could go back and you could
reverse it. Okay, so how could you reverse it? והא אמרת הגרלה
מעכבא? Ve-ha amarta hagralah me'aksa? If the drawing of the lot is
מעכב me'akeiv according to that opinion, then you have to go by
what the lot said. If you say בדיעבד b'diavad you don't have
to draw the lot, you can designate them yourself and be יוצא,
yotzei, so fine, you could also ignore the results of the drawing
of the lot. But if the drawing of the lot is מעכב,
me'akeiv, how could you ignore the result?
It's like the voting machines in Florida.
אמר רבא, Amar Rava, says רבא: Rava: הכי קאמרי ליה. hachi kamari
lei. הכי קאמרי: hachi kamari: עלה הגורל בשמאל, ala ha-goral b'smol, מה
שיחזירו לו ולשעירו לימין? mah she'yachaziru lo u-l'se'iro l'yamin? No, we don't
want to actually just reverse the lot, what we're going to do
is, if this says להשם la-Hashem and this says לעזאזל, la'azazel, right,
and the one that says לעזאזל, la'azazel, this is my left hand.
If this says לעזאזל la'azazel and this is in my left hand—no,
did I say it right? I didn't. Okay. This is my left—yeah,
I'm a lefty. Yeah, I'm a lefty. This says להשם la-Hashem and
this is in my left hand, and I want the one להשם
la-Hashem to be in my right hand. So I'm not just going
to do this. What I'm going to do is, I'm going to
do this and I'm also going to switch the goats. So I
will still have the one that said להשם la-Hashem going on—I'm still
going by the results of the lottery. I'm just reversing both the
lot and the goat so that it works out nicer symbolically that
it's all in the right. Okay. So מה שיחזירו לו ולשעירו לימין?
mah she'yachaziru lo u-l'se'iro l'yamin? אמר
להם: Amar lahem: אל תתנו מקום לצדוקים
לרדות. al titnu makom l'tzedukim lirdos. Don't give them some reason to
complain. תא שמע, Ta shma, let's hear another again.
Because it looks
like you're messing with the results. It looks like you're doing whatever
you want and you're tricking it and how are we supposed to
trust the integrity of the פרושים perushim and their interpretation of the
עבודה avodah if they can go ahead and just—you're really random. Not
only random, but if they can—it's not random, but they can manipulate
things. Exactly. תא שמע, Ta shma, come in here. it's really random.
Right. Not only no, but if they can—it's not random, but they
can manipulate things, exactly. תא שמע. Ta shma. Come and hear. אילו
נאמר Ilu ne'emar את השעיר אשר עליו et hasair asher alav not
אשר עלה עליו. asher ala alav. הייתי אומר Hayiti omer יניח עליו
yani'ach alav I might think literally you have to put it on
the goat. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar עלה ala that was raised over
it or that fell on it. כיון שעלה Keivan sheala once it
was drawn, שוב אינו צריך. shuv eino tzarich. Then you don't have
to put it on. So basically the פשט pshat of this being,
הנחה hanachah is not מעכב. me'akeiv. Once you drew it, you don't
actually have to put it on בדיעבד. bediavad. So the גמרא Gemara
says, למאי? lemai? So what does it mean you don't have to
put it on? אילימא למצוה, Ilima lemitzvah, if it's just saying that
you don't have to put it on even לכתחילה, lechatchila, you don't
place it on the top on the animal. מכלל דהנחה מצוה נמי
לא? Michlal dehanachah mitzvah nami lo? Could anybody say that you don't
have to actually put the lot at least as a לכתחילה? lechatchila?
So you know, maybe the answer is yes, but the גמרא Gemara
thinks that's unthinkable. So
how could that be that you don't have to put it on,
that you don't have to even לכתחילה lechatchila put it on? אלא
לאו לעכב. Ela lav le'akeiv. What the ברייתא braita must mean is
that בדיעבד bediavad if you didn't put it on, you're still יוצא.
yotzei. Okay, so בדיעבד bediavad if you didn't put it on, you're
יוצא. yotzei. ושמע מינה הגרלה מעכבת הנחה לא מעכבת. Ushma mina hagralah
me'akevet hanachah lo me'akevet. So the implication is clear. בדיעבד bediavad you
don't have to put it on, but you have to draw the
lots, it has to be אשר עלה. asher ala. So אמר רבא
הכי קאמר. Amar Rava hachi ka'amar. רבא Rava says no, this is
what it means. אילו נאמר אשר עליו, Ilu ne'emar asher alav, הייתי
אומר יניחנו עליו עד שעת שחיטה. hayiti omer yanichenu alav ad sheat
shechitah. Yes, it's—he—it's not talking about putting it on. It's talking about
you do have to leave it on until you שחט. shacht. If
it had said עליו, alav, then I would say you have to
leave it on the whole time. תלמוד לומר אשר עלה, Talmud lomar
asher ala, כיון שעלה שוב אינו צריך, keivan sheala shuv eino tzarich,
that you don't לכתחילה lechatchila have to put it on that whole
time. לכתחילה lechatchila you only have to put it on, you know,
at one moment.
So meaning what רבא Rava does—but
you don't have to keep it there. So what רבא Rava does
is again, you know, there's a lot of rereading here, but the
ברייתא braita says that, you know, that you don't have to put
it on. The גמרא Gemara can't imagine it means לכתחילה lechatchila you
don't have to put it on, so it must mean בדיעבד bediavad
you don't have to put it on, which means בדיעבד bediavad you
have to draw the lots. So here's evidence that בדיעבד bediavad you
have to draw the lots. And רבא's Rava response is no, what
it means is לכתחילה lechatchila you don't have to put it on,
but not you don't have to put it on at all, לכתחילה
lechatchila you don't have to put it on until you שחט shacht
it. That's actually not the מצוה. mitzvah. The מצוה mitzvah is only
to put it on for one moment, okay? And again, there's no
discussion of the implications for the drawing of the lots, we're just
talking about the מצוה mitzvah of putting it on, how long that
מצוה mitzvah is. It's only for a moment, it's not until you
do the שחיטה. shechitah. So just to review what we did today
was this issue about is the drawing of the lots מעכב? me'akeiv?
We definitely saw a lot of ברייתות braitot that seem to indicate
that it was not מעכב. me'akeiv. We reread them to say that
it's not talking about the drawing, it's talking about the placing, so
we still haven't like resolved that question. This last ברייתא braita actually
seemed to indicate that it was מעכב. me'akeiv. We reread that. So
there's different evidence. But the other interesting thing we've seen is number
one, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon clearly holds the drawing of the lot
is מעכב. me'akeiv. He even holds that the whole linking of the
two is not מעכב me'akeiv and if one dies you just get
another one, you can skip the whole process. That is a definitely
a radical position. And what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon also though says
is that וידוי vidui is מעכב, me'akeiv, but there's a position that
says that even וידוי vidui is not מעכב. me'akeiv. Another radical position
in terms of our focus on what is like significant about this
whole process. And as תוספות Tosafot points out that this debate here
of do you—is it focus on the וידוי vidui of the שעיר
sair or on the כפרה kaparah of the other one, actually is
not just a question of the focus on וידוי, vidui, but it's
also a question on the way in which שעיר לעזאזל sair laazazel
links or does not link to the שעיר להשם. sair lahashem. Okay.