Okay
בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is כ"ט, chaf tet, זבחים
Zevachim 29. We pick up at the bottom part of כ"ח עמוד
ב', chaf chet amud bet, we are up to... אלא אמר רבא.
ela amar Rava. It is 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
8 9 10 11 lines from the bottom. Line starts with word
וקמיה מאי? vekamei mai? And we're in the middle of trying to
figure out how... where we learn from the פסוקים psukim the idea
of פיגול piggul of a מחשבה machshava of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano
and that that you get כרת karet for that. And in addition,
what's less clear in the פסוקים psukim is the idea of חוץ
למקומו, chutz limkomo, a thought to eat it in the wrong place
where it's a לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, it's a negative prohibition to
eat from that, but... you do not get כרת. karet. And we're
dealing with two פסוקים. psukim. One which the גמרא Gemara calls the
long פסוק pasuk in צו, Tzav, and the פסוק pasuk there says
just to read that again, this is ויקרא ז' י"ח. Vayikra zayin
yud chet. ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו ביום השלישי. Ve'im he'achol
ye'achel mibsar zevach shelamav bayom hashlishi. If you eat from the flesh
of the שלמים shelamim on the third day, לא ירצה, lo yeratzeh,
it will not be... accepted. The word ריצוי ritzui is the key
word by קרבנות. korbanot. המקריב אתו, Hamakriv oto,
the one who offers it, לא יחשב לו, lo yechashev lo, it
will not be considered on his account, פיגול יהיה, piggul yihyeh, it
will be פיגול, piggul, abomination, let's translate it like that. ונפש האכלת
ממנו עונה תשא. Venefesh ha'ochelet mimenu avonah tisa. If you eat from
it, you carry your... your sin. Okay, so that is what the
גמרא Gemara calls the long פסוק pasuk in צו. Tzav. And again,
the simple sense of the פסוקים psukim is talking about נותר, notar,
but as we know, the גמרא Gemara reads it that the idea
of פיגול piggul is about a מחשבה, machshava, a thought, because you
cannot retroactively make a קרבן korban unacceptable if you eat from the
נותר notar three days... two days later. And then the short פסוק
pasuk in the beginning of קדושים Kedoshim and it's interesting the prominence
it gets in the beginning of קדושים Kedoshim is פרק י"ט פסוק
ז'. perek yud tet pasuk zayin. ואם האכל יאכל ביום השלישי, Ve'im
he'achol ye'achel bayom hashlishi, if it is also talking again about
the שלמים, shelamim, ביום זבחכם השלמים, bayom zivchechem hashelamim, if it is
eaten on the third day, פיגול הוא לא ירצה. piggul hu lo
yeratzeh. It will be פיגול, piggul, it will not be accepted. Same
key words: האכל יאכל, he'achol ye'achel, יום שלישי, yom shlishi, פיגול לא
ירצה. piggul lo yeratzeh. And then it just adds the idea of
כרת. karet. ואכליו עונו ישא כי את קדש ה' חלל ונכרתה הנפש
ההיא מעמיה. Ve'ochlav avono yisa ki et kodesh Hashem chillel venichreta hanefesh
hahi me'ameha. Okay, and the soul will be cut off. So you
have very similar except there in קדושים Kedoshim it mentions כרת. karet.
And the גמרא Gemara yesterday was trying to... go through a whole...
figuring out one פסוק pasuk talks about חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, one
חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. How do you know which one כרת karet
applies to? And in the end, it felt that it could not
really resolve it. So now we are going to try one more
time. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather רבא Rava says, again
כ"ח עמוד ב', chaf chet amud bet, 11 lines from the bottom.
אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather רבא Rava says, כולו מקרא
אריכתא אתי kulu mikra arichta ati and all the ideas come from
this one פסוק pasuk in the long פסוק pasuk in צו. Tzav.
Okay, דכתיב, dechtiv, let's take a look. The פסוק pasuk says: האכל
יאכל, he'achol ye'achel, if it will be eaten from it. So the
double language, בשתי אכילות הכתוב מדבר, bishtei achilot hakatuv medaber, it's talking
about two types of eatings. אחד אכילת אדם ואחד אכילת מזבח. Echad
achilat adam ve'echad achilat mizbe'ach. Eating of humans, eating of the altar.
Meaning that a פיגול piggul thought is to eat from it in
the wrong... in the wrong time or across the related idea of
the wrong place, for you the human to eat from the meat
in the wrong time or for you to offer up the... the
entrails, the אימורים emurim on the altar in the wrong time. That's
אכילת מזבח. achilat mizbe'ach. There's also the thinking about זורק הדם, zorek
hadam, okay, דם dam has... is both the thing that is the
act on which you're... during which you're having the פיגול piggul thought
and also the... could be the subject and the object of the
פיגול piggul thought. But now we'll focus on the meat and on
the flesh. So it's
the meat and on the אימורים, emurim, two types of אכילות achilot
are relevant for the פיגול piggul thought.
מבשר זבח שלמיו, Mibsar zevach shelamav, from the flesh of the sacrifice
of the שלמים. shelamim. מה שלמים, Ma shelamim, so why is שלמים
shelamim used as the paradigm for פיגול? piggul? מה שלמים מפלגין ומתפלגין,
Ma shelamim maphalgin umitpalgin, אף כל מפלגין ומתפלגין. af kol maphalgin umitpalgin.
The same way שלמים shelamim you have the thing that you do
the פיגול piggul on when you're doing the עבודה avoda of the
blood, the שחיטה, shechting, the catching of the blood, the... the transferring,
the throwing of it etc. So and it also has something that
the פיגול piggul is... takes effect on that would become permitted through
the throwing of the blood, which would be the meat. Okay, מפלגין
ומתפלגין. maphalgin umitpalgin. So similarly anything that has both of those things.
What is that excluding? It's excluding something like the מנחה mincha of
a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol which is totally burnt. And that type
of thing you don't have that one act is done with the
מתיר matir and the remainder becomes permissible. It's all just offered up
at once. So every other thing pretty much you throw the blood
and that allows the meat to be eaten and that allows
the... All right, so there you learned that הלכה. halacha. So here's
where we're going to get all of the key הלכות halachas about
פיגול. pigul.
שלישי shlishi on the third day, זה חוץ לזמנו. zeh chutz lizmano.
Okay, it says ביום השלישי bayom hashlishi the third day. So that's
the concept of חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. לא ירצה lo yeratze it
will not be accepted. כהרצאת כשר כן הרצאת פסול. k'hartzat kasher ken
hartzat pasul. The same way a כשר kasher sacrifice has to be,
you have to have הרצאה, hartza'ah, you have to go through all
the processes to make it acceptable by God, you know, pleasing, acceptable
to God, which is you throw the blood, you do all the
right processes, etc. The same is true even by a case of
פיגול. pigul. It only becomes פיגול pigul if, you know, if you
are, if you did כל מתיריו. kol matirav. Okay,
so as it says מה הרצאת כשר עד שיקריבו כל מתיריו, mah
hartzat kasher ad she'yakrivu kol matirav, the same way מתיריו, matirav, the
same way to make something כשר kasher you have to finish the
process of the things that make it מותר. mutar. So you throw
the blood and that makes, you know, the, that both is מרצה,
meratze, that makes the sacrifice acceptable, now the sacrifice is basically, you
know, you're יוצא yotzei your obligation, it's accepted by God, and that
also makes the rest of the stuff מותר. mutar. You can now
eat the meat and burn the אימורים. emurim. Okay, so
but the הרצאה hartza'ah only comes after you do all of the
מתיר matir acts. Okay, and it says כל מתיריו kol matirav like
you could imagine something that has two of them, like for example
the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim has the two בזיכים. bazichim. Okay, you
know, a מנחה mincha has the קומץ kometz and the לבונה. levona.
Okay, but you have to do all of the stages to make
it מותר. mutar. אף הרצאת פסול עד שיקריבו כל מתיריו. af hartzat
pasul ad she'yakrivu kol matirav. So the same way when you're dealing
with a פסול, pasul, with a פיגול, pigul, this is the irony
of פיגול. pigul. You could have a פיגול pigul thought and then
you spill the blood. It's not פיגול. pigul. It's only פיגול pigul
if you then are זורק zorek the blood, you know, בכשרות, b'kashrut,
that the whole rest of the process is done exactly in the
normal acceptable way. If you were and you were זורק zorek the
blood, you know, שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it wouldn't be פיגול. pigul.
Everything has to be perfect except for the פיגול pigul thought. That's
one of the ironies of the הלכה halacha of פיגול. pigul. עד
שיקריבו כל מתיריו. ad she'yakrivu kol matirav. Okay, so there cannot,
not just that the blood is thrown, but everything is done properly
and the only improper thing is the thought of פיגול. pigul. Okay,
עד שיקריבו כל מתיריו. ad she'yakrivu kol matirav. המקריב, hamakriv, the one
who offers it, בהקרבה הוא נפסל ואינו נפסל בשלישי. b'hakrava hu nifsal
v'eino nifsal bashlishi. Okay, it's only at the time of being offered
when the, you know, the עבודה avoda is being done, the slaughtering,
the blood, etc., and not, you know, as the פסוק pasuk sounds
like, on the third day itself. It won't retroactively become פסול. pasul.
המקריב אותו, hamakriv oto, it's at the time of הקרבה hakrava that
the מחשבה machshava of פיגול pigul matters, ואינו נפסל בשלישי. v'eino nifsal
bashlishi.
אותו, oto, okay, המקריב אותו, hamakriv oto, who brings it, the sacrifice,
בזבח הכתוב מדבר ואינו מדבר בכהן bazevach hakatuv medaber v'eino medaber b'kohen
or some have the גרסא girsa בזובח. b'zove'ach. It's talking that the
sacrifice becomes invalid, המקריב אותו, hamakriv oto, the one offering it, not
the מקריב makriv himself becomes invalid, not that because you had a
bad thought as a כהן, kohen, you are now פסול pasul as
a כהן. kohen. לא יחשב, lo yeichashev, it will not be accounted
to him. Okay, top of כ"ט עמוד
א'. chaf-tet amud aleph. לא יערב בו מחשבות אחרות. lo ye'arev bo
machshavot acherot. Other thoughts, bad thoughts, that get mixed up will make
it no longer פיגול. pigul. So it's not, it shall not be
considered on his account, but he may not have already if, this
is only when there are no other thoughts. So if you have
a thought of חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo that in addition to your
חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought, then that makes it no longer פיגול.
pigul. That's similar to the principle of עד שיקריבו כל מתיריו. ad
she'yakrivu kol matirav. Okay, so because a thought of חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo would make it invalid, then by itself, then you have something
about this. that is not done correctly. פיגול piggul is everything is
done correctly except for the פיגול piggul thought. If you have another
thought of חוץ למקומו, chootz limkomo, it's no longer פיגול piggul because
there's something else that makes it invalid. Okay, but that's learned specifically
that that other thinking can be even a thought by לא יחשב,
lo yechaisev, okay, לא יערב בו מחשבה אחרת. lo ye'arev bo machshava
acheres. Other thoughts that invalidate it make it no longer פיגול. piggul.
It's still פסול passul but makes it no longer פיגול piggul and
therefore there's no כרת kareis for eating it. Okay, so לא יחשב
לו, פיגול
יהיה, lo yechaisev lo piggul yihyeh, זה חוץ למקומו, zeh chootz limkomo,
I'm sorry, so now it just explained. Okay, so that other thought
would be a חוץ למקומו chootz limkomo thought. לא יחשב לו lo
yechaisev lo, פיגול יהיה, piggul yihyeh, it shall be. What does the
יהיה yihyeh teach you? מלמד שמצטרפין זה עם זה, melamed shemitztarfin zeh
im zeh, that if you have a thought of a half of
a כזית kezayis of פיגול piggul to eat in the wrong, a
half כזית kezayis to eat in the wrong place and a half
כזית kezayis to eat in the wrong time. So even though it
is not a פיגול piggul because you don't have a whole כזית
kezayis of פיגול piggul there and you have another thought of חוץ
למקומו, chootz limkomo, nevertheless חוץ למקומו chootz limkomo and חוץ לזמנו chootz
lizmano are enough in the same category that since you had a
thought about a כזית, kezayis, even though you split the כזית, kezayis,
half חוץ למקומו chootz limkomo and half חוץ לזמנו, chootz lizmano, still
bad thoughts about a כזית kezayis is enough to make it פסול,
passul, not פיגול, piggul, but פסול. passul. Okay,
מלמד שמצטרפין זה עם זה. melamed shemitztarfin zeh im zeh. והנפש האוכלת
ממנו, vehanefesh haocheles mimenu, back to the פסוק, passuk, ממנו, mimenu, and
the soul that eats from it. So ממנו, mimenu, from it, singular,
אחד ולא שנים, echad velo shnayim, only one of it. So because
לא יחשב lo yechaisev allowed us to introduce the idea of what
do you call it,
of חוץ למקומו, chootz limkomo, and יהיה yihyeh that חוץ למקומו chootz
limkomo and חוץ לזמנו chootz lizmano combined for כזית kezayis to invalidate,
but now the האוכלת ממנו, haocheles mimenu, from it, it, singular, is
telling us only one of them עוונו ישא, avono yisa, which will
mean ultimately כרת. kareis. Okay, so only for one of them do
you get כרת. kareis. אחד ולא שנים. echad velo shnayim. ואיזה, ve'eizeh,
now back to the question that bothered us yesterday, how do you
get to decide which is the one that you get כרת kareis
for? זה חוץ לזמנו, zeh chootz lizmano, that is חוץ לזמנו. chootz
lizmano. Why? דגמר עון עון מנותר, degmar avon avon minosar, because we
learn from נותר, nosar, that's the פסוק passuk over there in צו
Tzav that says, you know, ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה. venichresa hanefesh hahi
me'ameha. What's the פסוק? passuk? The פסוק passuk again, excuse me, not
in צו, Tzav, in קדושים, Kedoshim, the next פסוק, passuk, ואכליו עוונו
ישא, ve'ochlav avono yisa, that's again עוונו, avono, then ישא, yisa, כי
את קדש ה' חילל ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה. ki es kodesh Hashem
chillel venichresa hanefesh hahi me'ameha. Okay, so that we understand is talking
about נותר, nosar, and that we allow, we make a גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah
of עון עון, avon avon, right, עוונו ישא avono yisa to tell
us כרת. kareis. And how do we know that it is חוץ
לזמנו chootz lizmano and not חוץ למקומו? chootz limkomo? דדמי ליה בזמן
dedami lei
biazman because חוץ לזמנו chootz lizmano and נותר nosar are similar because
they're both about זמן, zman, time. I mean, the whole פשט pshat
of the פסוק passuk is about נותר. nosar. So we translated it
and it's all about the wrong time, and we say that's talking
about a thought about the wrong time, but obviously thought about the
wrong time, eating wrong time are fundamentally in the same category. And
the ב' beis is במה, bamah, neither of, you know, both of
them apply by במה, bamah, חוץ למקומו chootz limkomo doesn't apply by
a במה bamah because there's no מקום makom once you're having a
במה. bamah. Okay, anyway, so now we have it very nice, all
the הלכות halachos we learn from this one פסוק passuk in צו
Tzav and the connection of חוץ לזמנו chootz lizmano and נותר nosar
and the obvious close connection there teaches us that it's only חוץ
לזמנו chootz lizmano that you get כרת kareis for.
Okay, אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא, amar lei Rav Pappa leRava, so
Rav Pappa said to Rava,
we're not done yet.
לדידך שלישי דפרשת קדושים
תיהוי מאי דרשת ביה?
ledidach shelishi deparshas Kedoshim
tihvei mai darshas beih? Oh, you did brilliant, you learned it all
out from the פסוק passuk in צו. Tzav. What do you do
by the פסוק passuk in קדושים Kedoshim where it says, you know,
a similar פסוק, passuk, ואם האכל יאכל ביום השלישי? ve'im he'achol ye'achel
bayom hashelishi?
So what's that פסוק passuk going to teach you? הוא מיבעי ליה
למקום שמשולש בדם בבשר ובאימורים. hu mibei lei lemakom shemeshulash bedam bebasar
uve'imurim.
No, that's telling you a different הלכה, halachah, that when it comes
to the thought of פיגול, piggul, it only applies to a place
which is a three, a tripartite place, a place that is equal
when it comes to meat, blood, and the אימורים imurim and the
entrails. Now, what does that mean? Big debate of the ראשונים, Rishonim,
no answer is really totally perfect. רש"י Rashi says it means that
if you had a thought to eat it in the
actual היכל, Heichal, that it would not be a פיגול piggul thought
because that is not a, is not a place that is invalid,
not valid, but invalid for blood, בשר, basar, and אימורים. imurim. So
outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you cannot, you know, sprinkle
the blood, you cannot eat the בשר, basar, at least the בשר
basar of
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, and, you
know. So if you have a thought to eat קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim
in ירושלים Yerushalayim let's say, that's an invalid place for בשר, basar,
דם, dam, and אימורים. emurim. And if you have a thought to
eat קדשי קלים kodshim kalim out of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that's an invalid
place for בשר, basar, דם, dam, and אימורים. emurim. Whereas if you
have a thought to eat the meat in the היכל, Heichal, okay,
although that is a legitimate place, you know, for the blood, it
is not a place where you eat the meat and it's not
a place where you offer up the אימורים. emurim. Now, תוספות Tosafot
actually points out that if you if, you know, if there were
like the enemies surround were at the- barbarians were at the gate
that you and you weren't able to eat in the עזרה Azara
you could eat the meat in the היכל, Heichal, but you still
couldn't offer up the אימורים emurim in the היכל. Heichal. Anyway, so
that's the way רש"י Rashi says it that if you have a
thought to eat it in the היכל, Heichal, it's since it's not
invalid for all three, it's only, you know, invalid for let's just
say at least, you know, the blood, and the blood can be
there also, for the blood you know when like יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and inner חטאות, chatos, but you know, so it is not
invalid for all three and therefore it is not a thought of
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo if you have a plan to do it
inside the היכל. Heichal. Okay, that's how רש"י Rashi reads it. It
has to be a place that is invalid for all three, and
the היכל Heichal is not invalid for the blood and might not
even also be invalid for the meat. תוספות Tosafot has other explanations,
I'll just give you two of them. One of them is that
it's only if you have a thought in terms of the מזבח.
mizbeach. So, meaning only if it's a קרבן korban that is offered
on the outer מזבח, mizbeach, because the outer מזבח mizbeach is a
place for meat of the עולה, olah, blood, obviously, and the אימורים,
emurim, but if it's a type of a קרבן korban that is
offered on the inner, you know, מזבח, mizbeach, like it's a- you
know, it's an inner חטאות chatos or something, since that is not
a place for blood, meat, and אימורים, emurim, you can't have פיגול.
piggul. Problem with- only problem with this תוספות Tosafot says is that
the evidence is against this, that you can have פיגול piggul for
קרבנות korbanot that are like the inner חטאות. chatos. So another explanation
is is that the person thinking the פיגול piggul has to be
in this tripartite place, meaning he has to be in the עזרה,
Azara, because the עזרה Azara is a place where you can have
the blood, you know, meat, and the אימורים emurim on the- on
the מזבח. mizbeach. But if you were doing a שחיטה shechita and
standing outside the עזרה, Azara, which we're going to learn is כשר,
kasher, we've already discussed that, if you have a long knife you
can be standing outside of the עזרה Azara and doing a שחיטה
shechita and you have your פיגול piggul thought, that is not invalid
because you are not standing in a place which is כשר kasher
for the meat, בשר, basar, and the אימורים. emurim. Okay, so that
is a- so that's another explanation. So anyway, we have, so we
have, so- so we have multiple different ways of explaining this, but
that is what the פסוק pasuk is doing to tell you that
one aspect of פיגול piggul requires a certain type of place which
is equal for בשר, basar, אימורים, emurim, and blood, whether it is
the place where the person is standing, whether it is about a
type of a קרבן korban that's brought on the outer מזבח, mizbeach,
or whether it's like רש"י Rashi about having a thought to eat
it in the wrong place, and it has to be the wrong
place in terms of all three of those. Okay, so let's keep
on going. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this, בדם בשר ואימורים, bedam basar
ve'emurim, שתיפוק ליה מקרא קמא. sheteipok lei mikra kama. So why not
learn it from the first פסוק? pasuk? You know, the first פסוק
pasuk said יום השלישי, yom hashelishi, it could have been talked- we
decided it's talking about a שלמים shelamim and a third day, you
know, it could have- you know, it could have been talking about
something on the second day, it still says third, three in the-
in the first פסוק. pasuk. So why not learn this tripartite place
from the first פסוק pasuk as well? So it says,
because אימא הכי יאכל, eima hachi yei'achel, מדאפקי רחמנא בלשון שלישי, mide'afkei
rachmana belashon shelishi, since it bothered to give the example of the
תורה Torah of שלישי, shelishi, that should tell us this tripartite place
and then you will not need the פסוק pasuk in קדושים. Kedoshim.
So אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, so said רב אשי, Rav
Ashi, אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב מתנא, amritah lishmeita kamie deRav Masna, I
said this in front of רב מתנא. Rav Masna. אמר לי, amar
li, he said to me, אם מהתם הוה אמינא im mehatam hava
amina שלישי shelishi פרט prat פיגול piggul כלל klal ונעשה כלל מוסיף
על הפרט. venasa klal mosif al haprat. Okay, no, because it says
ואם האכל יאכל ביום השלישי פיגול יהיה. ve'im haiachol yei'achel beyom hashelishi
piggul yihyeh. So- so- so שלישי shelishi would have told me it
has to be a tripartite place, פרט, prat, it would have narrowed
the scope of פיגול, piggul, but then the word פיגול piggul afterwards,
because if you remember the דרשה drasha before we jumped over the
word פיגול, piggul, we- we focused on the word שלישי shelishi and
on the word יהיה. yihyeh. So the word- so then the פיגול
piggul would have been a more expansive word and said you don't
need a tripartite place, okay,
ונעשה כלל מוסיף על הפרט וישרבו שאר מקומות, venasa klal mosif al
haprat veyisrebu shear mekomot, and it would not have limited us to
a tripartite place. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, that's why you
needed the פסוק pasuk in קדושים. Kedoshim. Okay, so the פסוק pasuk
in קדושים, Kedoshim, the whole purpose of the פסוק pasuk in קדושים
Kedoshim is to tell us that you need a tripartite place for
דם בשר ואימורים dam basar ve'emurim for פיגול. piggul. What exactly that
means is a whole debate, whether it's where the guy is standing,
what type of קרבן korban that's brought on the מזבח, mizbeach, what
type of thought of חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, but that's what the
whole point of the פסוק pasuk in קדושים Kedoshim and the reason
you couldn't learn it out from the פסוק pasuk in צו Tzav
is because since the word שלישי shelishi is followed by the word
פיגול piggul I would have said it would be
the- and it would not have limited it to this tripartite place.
All right, so ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, we are now done figuring
out where we get the laws of פיגול pigul from the פסוקים,
pesukim, where we know חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and how we know
that it's only חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano that you get כרת. kares.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught:
ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו. V'im He-achol Yei-achel Mibasar Zevach Shelamav.
אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, so we're now going to once
again engage this פסוק, pasuk, but we've established fundamentally where we learn
things from. Said רבי אליעזר: Rabbi Eliezer: כוף אזנך לשמוע, Kof oznecha
lishmoa, bend your ear to listen, meaning this פסוק pasuk is a
difficult פסוק, pasuk, so come give a listen and I will explain
to you how that the what this פסוק pasuk is talking about.
במחשב לאכול מזבחו ביום השלישי הכתוב מדבר. Bemachshev leechol mizivcho bayom hashelishi
hakatuv medaber. It's not like the פשט pshat that it sounds like
it's talking about eating נותר, nosar, it's talking that you have an
intent to eat from it on the third
day. או אינו אלא באוכל מזבחו ליום השלישי? O eino ela be-ochel
mizivcho leyom hashelishi? Maybe it's actually when you eat like the simple
sense of the פסוק, pasuk, literally you ate from the meat on
the third
day? אמרת, Amarta, אחר שוכשר יחזור ויפסל? achar shehuchshar yachzor viyepasel? So
no, that's not possible because it says לא ירצה, lo yeiratze, the
קרבן korban won't be accepted. And it can't be that retroactively after
you eat from it the נותר nosar on the third day, retroactively
you go back two days and you say we thought it was
a good קרבן korban but now retroactively we see it wasn't. So
because we clearly have that principle that makes no sense to say
retroactively it becomes invalid, we are going to interpret the פסוק pasuk
to be talking about a thought of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano about
פיגול. pigul. All right, אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi Akiva,
it shows you how much like working from certain like principles, you
know, makes us drives חז"ל Chazal to read a פסוק pasuk even
not according to פשוטו. peshuto. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi
Akiva, said רבי עקיבא: Rabbi Akiva: הן, Hen, yes, it's not impossible
that things retroactively get ruined. מצינו בזב וזבה ושומרת יום כנגד יום.
Matzinu b'zav v'zavah v'shomeret yom kineged yom. I'll give you an example:
a זב zav and a זבה. zavah. You know, a זב zav
has three penile emissions; a זבה, zavah, you know, has on three
consecutive days not during her menstrual period sees blood. The הלכה halacha
for both of them, they have to count seven days for the
זב zav of no appropriate of no
penile emission, of the זבה zavah of no blood. Seven days and
then they can go to the מקוה. mikvah. Now the הלכה halacha
is that they can actually go to the מקוה mikvah on the
morning of day seven.
But if late because of the principle of מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat
hayom k'kulo, part of the day counts like the whole day. But
if later on day seven they do have this emission, you know,
problematic emission, it retroactively means that all of their seven days were
no good. You know, the fact that they went in the morning
at the anticipation that the rest of the day would be good,
מקצת היום ככולו miktzat hayom k'kulo was proven to be false and
they have to start their counting all over again. The same is
true about a שומרת יום כנגד יום. shomeret yom kineged yom. That's
a woman who bleeds one or two days not during her menstrual
period that she needs to observe one day that there is no
bleeding, and similarly she can go to the מקוה mikvah once a
part of that day begins with no bleeding the next day, but
if later she sees blood, it retroactively ruins her going to the
מקוה mikvah and she has to start the count all over again.
So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says אהא, aha, you see we have
cases where retroactively it can become destroyed. Now, that's not necessarily the
greatest proof because those as I've explained are based on the principle
of מקצת היום ככולו, miktzat hayom k'kulo, which means we're allowing you
to go to the מקוה mikvah in the morning at the anticipation
of how the rest of the day will end, that it will
end just like it started without there being blood. That's very different
than a קרבן korban focuses on the blood then you do something
later wrong with the meat two days afterwards and it's going to
ruin it. But anyway, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says we do have
the idea of retroactively invalidating. אמר לו רבי עקיבא: Amar lo Rabbi
Akiva: הן, Hen, yes, מצינו בזב וזבה ושומרת יום כנגד יום matzinu
b'zav v'zavah v'shomeret yom kineged yom שהן בחזקת טהרה. shehein b'chezkat tahara.
We assume that they're טהור tahor on their last day, וכיון שראו
סתרו, v'keivan she-rau satru, and then when they see, even if they
see after having gone to the מקוה, mikvah, it destroys all their
previous count. So אף אתה אל תתמה על זה. af ata al
titma al zeh. So, you know, if it was just based on
the idea, oh this can't be retroactive, no, you shouldn't be astounded
about this. שאף על פי שהוכשר יחזור ויפסל, she-af al pi shehuchshar
yachzor viyepasel, even if it became כשר, kasher, yes, maybe it could
retroactively be destroyed. All right, אמר לו, amar lo, so רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer said back to רבי עקיבא: Rabbi Akiva: הרי הוא אומר,
harei hu omer, fine, I can't prove it logically, but let's look
at the פסוק. pasuk. It says המקריב אותו, hamakriv oto, the one
who offers it. So בשעת הקרבה, bish-at hakravah, it focuses us on
the moment of it being offered at the time that the blood
work is being done. הוא נפסל ואינו נפסל בשלישי. hu nifsal v'eino
nifsal bashlishi. So that's back to we're going to learn it not
from the logic but from, although the logic clearly a driver here,
but from the word המקריב hamakriv that tells us at the time
of it being offered, so it's an issue of the thought, not
that it actually was eaten at the third day. או אינו אומר
המקריב אלא זה כהן המקריב? o eino omer hamakriv ela zeh kohen
hamakriv? Maybe המקריב אותו hamakriv oto means that the כהן kohen himself
is becomes invalid when it is eaten eaten on the third day?
The מקריב makriv is becomes invalidated. כשהוא אומר אותו, keshehu omer oto,
no, המקריב אותו, hamakriv oto, it. בזבח הוא מדבר, bezevach hu medaber,
we're focusing, that's just again. what we just said earlier, that focuses
us on that it is the קרבן korban that becomes invalid ואינו
מדבר בכהן ve'eino medaber bakohein and not on the כהן. kohein. Okay,
so because it says המקריב hamakriv and that is telling us that
it becomes invalid at the time of הקרבה. hakravah. That's what we
said earlier. בן עזאי אומר, Ben Azzai omer, Ben Azzai says: אותו
מה תלמוד לומר? Oto mah talmud lomar?
No, אותו oto is telling you something different.
What is אותו oto telling you? מה תלמוד לומר? Mah talmud lomar?
לפי שנאמר: Lefi shene'emar: לא תאחר לשלמו, Lo te'acher leshalmo, that if
you make a vow you cannot delay bringing it. יכול אף מאחר
נדרו בלא ירצה? Yachol af me'acher nidro belo yeratzeh? Maybe if you
bring it too late, and what exactly is considered בל תאחר bal
te'acher is a debate, one רגל, regel, three רגלים, regalim, but whatever
it is, when if you violate בל תאחר, bal te'acher, maybe the
קרבן korban itself becomes invalid? תלמוד
לומר: Talmud lomar: אותו. oto. No, this thing that the קרבן korban
is invalid only applies to this or this case of חוץ לזמנו
chutz lizmano or חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, but this type of being
wrong time.
Okay, אותו בלא ירצה ואין מאחר נדרו בלא ירצה. Oto belo yeratzeh
ve'ein me'acher nidro belo yeratzeh. Okay, so that's where you learn it
from. And he presumably is not bothered by telling you that it's
talking about the קרבן, korban, not the כהן. kohein. We'll see about
that in the גמרא. Gemara. So this is just telling you: no,
אותו oto is telling you a separate הלכה halachah that בל תאחר
bal te'acher the קרבן korban is not invalid, it only applies to
this
קרבן. korban. Okay, ואין בלא ירצה. ve'ein belo yeratzeh. אחרים אומרים, Acherim
omrim, others
say: לא יחשב, Lo yeichashev, it shall not be thought, במחשבה הוא
נפסל ואינו נפסל בשלישי. bemachshavah hu nifsal ve'eino nifsal bashlishi. It's the
thought that invalidates. So rather than learning it out from המקריב, hamakriv,
he learns it out from לא יחשב, lo yeichashev, which admittedly is
the best פסוק pasuk to anchor it on because the whole focus
here is on thought and מחשבה. machshavah. If you remember before we
used that to teach you that a different thought of חוץ למקומו
chutz limkomo would take it out of פיגול. piggul. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this: ובן עזאי דבזבח כתב מדבר ואינו
בזובח מנא ליה? U'ven Azzai d'bezavach ketav medaber ve'eino bazoveiach m'nala lei?
So Ben Azzai who uses אותו oto to tell me that it's
not, it's only talking about this and not בל תאחר, bal te'acher,
where does he learn this idea that it's only the קרבן korban
that we're talking about that becomes invalid and not the כהן? kohein?
מנא ליה? M'nala lei? אי בעית אימא נפקא ליה מאחרים. I ba'it
eima nafka lei me'acherim. Either he learns it out from אחרים, Acherim,
because אחרים Acherim said, what did אחרים Acherim say? אחרים Acherim said
לא יחשב, lo yeichashev,
that it only becomes invalid through מחשבה machshavah and it does not
become invalid on the third day. So the fact that you need
a פסוק pasuk to tell you that it's only מחשבה machshavah and
not the third day shows you that you're talking about the קרבן.
korban. Because if you were talking about the כהן, kohein, obviously there
would not be an idea that on the third day the כהן
kohein becomes invalid. That's how רש"י Rashi explained it. So either from
אחרים, Acherim, from the לא יחשב, lo yeichashev, that tells us that
we're talking about the קרבן korban and not the כהן. kohein. ואי
בעית אימא מדכתיב לא ירצה. Ve'i ba'it eima mideketiv lo yeratzeh. It
will not be acceptable. ולא ירצה, Velo yeratzeh, זבחה הוא. zivcha hu.
The idea right, that's obviously the פשט. pshat. Wonder why the גמרא
Gemara didn't say that before? Any, you know, the idea
of לרצון, leratzon, ירצה, yeratzeh, that is the key פסוק, pasuk, word
that the תורה Torah uses throughout the discussion of קרבנות. korbanot. So
that is talking about the קרבן, korban, it is not talking about
the כהן. kohein. So Ben Azzai does not need אותו oto to
talk about the כהן, kohein, clearly the פסוק pasuk is talking about
the קרבן: korban: לא ירצה. lo yeratzeh. And אותו oto teaches you
it does not apply to בל תאחר. bal te'acher.
Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ובן עזאי אותו בלא ירצה ואחר נדרו בלא ירצה מהכא נפקא?
U'ven Azzai oto belo yeratzeh ve'acher nidro belo yeratzeh meihacha nafka? One
minute, does Ben Azzai learn this idea that somebody who is over
on בל תאחר, bal te'acher, the קרבן korban does not become invalid,
does he really learn it out from this פסוק pasuk of אותו?
oto? מאחרינא נפקא. Me'acharina nafka. He learns it out from an אחרינא,
acharina, a different אחרינא. acharina. Where's the אחרינא? acharina? דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: braita: אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, others say: יכול
יהא בכור שעבר שנתו. Yachol yehei bechor she'avar shenato. Perhaps a בכור
bechor that was over one year, you're supposed to bring the בכור
bechor in the first year. Top of כט עמוד ב. kaf tet
amud bet. כפסולי המוקדשין ויפסל. Kipsulei hamukdashin veyipasel. Maybe that will be
like, you know, like other קרבנות. korbanot. Like if you, you know,
a פסח Pesach has to be a one-year-old. If it's more than
one year, it's פסול. pasul. You know, other קרבנות korbanot the תורה
Torah gives an age to some of them, and if they're too
old or too young they're invalid. So maybe a בכור, bechor, it's
not exactly the problem of בל תאחר, bal te'acher, but you know,
maybe, I mean, you know, it's also the fact that the תורה
Torah frames it as, you know, as being in the first year.
So maybe if it's more than that, it should be considered too
old and no longer valid.
תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך מעשר דגנך תרשך ויצהרך
ובכרות בקרך וצאנך. Ve'achalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha ma'asar deganecha tiroshcha veyitzharecha u'vechorot
bekarcha vetzonecha. So it has בכור bechor there. מקיש בכור למעשר. Makish
bechor lema'asar. It's connecting בכור bechor to מעשר. ma'asar. מה מעשר אינו
נפסל משנה לחברתה. Mah ma'asar eino nifsal mishanah lachaverta. Just the same
way the מעשר ma'asar you can eat at a different year, the
whole point of the פסוק pasuk is talking about like every three
years you clean out your מעשר. ma'asar. So obviously you can eat
it at a different year. אף בכור אינו נפסל משנה לחברתה. Af
bechor eino nifsal mishanah lachaverta. So even a בכור bechor is not
invalid from one year to the next. Okay, so even though it
says by the בכור bechor תאכלנו שנה בשנה, tochlenu shanah beshanah, that's
not saying that the בכור bechor itself has to be one year
old. The eating should be every year, okay, but the animal itself
is not נפסל nifsal and being late in your... obligations does not
make the קרבן korban פסול. pasul. So, why does בן עזאי Ben
Azzai need to learn it out from אותו, oto, can't he learn
it out from this idea that a בכור bechor is linked to
מעשר? ma'aser? So the גמרא Gemara says איצטריך. itztarech. No you need
both. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salcka daitach amina, I would have thought הני
מילי בכור דלאו בר הרצאה הוא. hani mili bechor d'lav bar hartza'ah
hu. Sure, a בכור bechor can be, you can have, you know,
be delayed in bringing it more than a year, but you're not—it's
not coming, you know, to like it's not something that you vowed
out of free will and, you know, it's about your relationship with
God, it's like, you know, normal קרבנות, korbanot, if you look at
רש״י, Rashi, let's look at רש״י. Rashi. דלאו בר הרצאה הוא, d'lav
bar hartza'ah hu, last last line of the wide lines at the
top, אינו בא לכפר, eino ba l'chaper, it's not coming to atone,
אבל קדשים כגון עולה שמכפרת על עשה ושלמים שמביאים לדורון ליתן שלום
בין ישראל לאביהם שבשמים. Aval kodashim kegon olah shemechaperet al asei u'shelamim
shemevi'im l'doron litein shalom bein yisrael l'avihem shebashamayim. So it's not that
all קרבנות korbanot are לכפר, l'chaper, right? Some of them are a
gift, some of them are, but somehow they're seen as about cult-
like תפילה, tefillah, like about cultivating your relationship with God, about being
in communication with God. So בכור bechor is recognizing, you know, that
everything is from God and you're giving the firstborn to God, it
could also be seen as giving it to the כהן, kohen, okay,
but it's not about an act of אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן,
adam ki yakriv mikem korban, it's not an act of, you know,
relationship with God. So therefore that, okay, you got it a year
late, fine, it's not about the whole relationship, so that's okay, okay.
So הני מילי בכור דלאו בר הרצאה הוא, hani mili bechor d'lav
bar hartza'ah hu, אבל קדשים דבני הרצאה נינהו, aval kodashim d'vnei hartza'ah
ninhu, normal קרבנות korbanot which are about הרצאה, hartza'ah, about a your
relationship with God, we'll we'll define it that way, אימא לא לירצו,
eima lo lirtzu, maybe they won't be acceptable, קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan that it is, okay. So you need the פסוק pasuk
אותו oto to tell you even when you're delayed with your obligation
by other קרבנות korbanot which are really much more about הרצאה, hartza'ah,
not just about בכור, bechor,
nevertheless, you know, even though you were over on בל תאחר, bal
tacher, the קרבן korban is still כשר. kasher. Now why not just
tell me that and I don't have to tell me בכור? bechor?
Okay,
well the גמרא Gemara doesn't actually say that.
Yeah, I don't know exactly, normally the גמרא Gemara says why you
needed both פסוקים. psukim. Here it explains to me why you needed
it by the other קרבנות, korbanot, but why you—but does not tell
me why you needed it by בכור. bechor. But who knows? Maybe
if we had not had a clear פסוק pasuk by בכור, bechor,
we would have explained our פסוק pasuk אותו oto to refer only
to בכור. bechor. Now that we know by בכור bechor even if
you're late it's כשר, kosher, now we can explain the אותו oto
of our פסוק pasuk to say even other קרבנות korbanot שבאים לרצון,
sheba'im l'ratzon, even if you are over on בל תאחר, bal tacher,
they still remain כשר. kosher. Okay. והכתי ve'hakati says the גמרא, Gemara,
מהתם נפקא? meihatam nafka? Still, is that really where from—where you learn
it from? Don't we learn it from another פסוק? pasuk? והיה בך
חטא ולא בקרבנך חטא? v'haya becha cheit v'lo b'korbanacha cheit? Right,
it says that לא תאחר לשלמו, lo tacher l'shalmo, do not be
delay in bringing it, you know, and if you do, you know,
והיה בך חטא v'haya becha cheit that if you are delayed then
the—you will be sinning. So the דרשה drasha is you will have
the sin, but your קרבן korban won't have the sin. So why
do you need the אותו oto by our פסוק pasuk by פיגול
piggul to tell you that the קרבן korban isn't invalid when you're
over on בל תאחר? bal tacher? We learn it out from והיה
בך חטא ולא בקרבנך חטא. v'haya becha cheit v'lo b'korbanacha cheit. The
חטא cheit is only in you, it doesn't invalidate the קרבן. korban.
That's a good question. So the גמרא Gemara says בן עזאי ההוא
מיבעי ליה והיה בך חטא ולא באשתך חטא. Ben Azzai hahu mibaei
leh v'haya becha cheit v'lo b'ishtecha cheit. No, no, no, בן עזאי
Ben Azzai uses that for a different דרשה. drasha. You're the only
one who suffers, your wife won't suffer. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salcka daitach
amina, הוה אמר רבי אליעזר ואיתימא רבי יוחנן אין אשתו של אדם
מתה אלא אם כן מבקשים ממנו ממון ואין לו. hava amar Rabbi
Eliezer v'itima Rabbi Yochanan ein ishto shel adam meta ela im kein
mevakshim mimeno mamon v'ein lo. Since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and some
it say—say רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that a person's wife—of course
it's all focused on the man—a man's wife will only die, I
guess for somebody else's sins, if, you know, if he owes money—if
they ask something from him up in heaven as it were, you
know, for—for—he has some monetary obligation and he's not paying it up,
which תוספות Tosafot says means exactly this case of בל תאחר, bal
tacher, that you had a נדר neder and a vow to give
something to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you're being over on
בל תאחר bal tacher and that is, you know, and that would
be a reason why, you know—it's a funny, you know, obviously the
פסוקים psukim say לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים לא יומתו על
אבות איש בחטאו יומתו, lo yumtu avot al banim u'vanim lo yumtu
al avot ish b'cheit'o yumatu, but there are other פסוקים psukim that
re—that reference
an idea that there is some sense of collective punishment, you know,
ונתתי את פני באיש ההוא ובמשפחתו. v'natati et panai ba'ish hahu u'v'mishpachto.
And so, and there is some idea sometimes that like, you know,
people's—I mean, whatever, we have to acknowledge it even though it's disturbing
for our, you know, in terms of our own sort of understanding
that the— there are some פסוקים psukim in the תורה Torah and
there are some, you know, may—stated in the גמרא Gemara as well,
that some types of sins particularly, it's interesting when it does deal
with the idea of debts, you know, of צדקה tzedakah that's not
being paid or of a נדר neder or whatever, that a person's
wife or children, a man's wife or children might be taken from
him because he is not giving to God what is God's due.
So אין אשתו של אדם מתה אלא אם כן מבקשים ממנו ממון
ואין לו. ein ishto shel adam meta ela im kein mevakshim mimeno
mamon v'ein lo. שנאמר אם אין לך לשלם, shene'emar im ein lecha
l'shalem, if you do not have to pay. the money what to
pay up למה יקח משכבך מתחתיך lama yikach mishkavcha mitachtecha why shall
that thing that you sleep on or with why should your wife
be taken from you so if you so since there's a teaching
some others teach that if a person you know owes this קרבן
korban to God and doesn't pay it his wife will suffer as
a result so therefore בן עזאי Ben Azzai would interpret the פסוק
pasuk בהאי עוון דבל תאחר נמי
מיתה behai avon debal te'acher nami mita so you might have thought
בהאי עוון דבל תאחר נמי מיתה behai avon debal te'acher nami mita
maybe that would apply even in case of בל תאחר bal te'acher
קא משמע לן kamashmalan that it doesn't by בל תאחר bal te'acher
it's בחטאך ולא באשתך חטאך bechetecha velo be'ishtecha chetecha so the way
the גמרא Gemara frames it it sounds like we're not denying this
principle altogether we're just saying that it doesn't apply to בל תאחר
bal te'acher
so you know תוספות Tosafot says that it applies to like other
types of vows you could there's other רש"י Rashi says it applies
to cases of
גזל gezel where somebody stole something and isn't paying it back so
the גמרא Gemara is not totally rejecting that idea but rejecting it
by בל תאחר bal te'acher okay so phew we basically have now
covered you know the פסוקים pesukim we learned that the key דרשות
drashot of פיגול pigul are learned out from צו Tzav we learned
that in קדושים Kedoshim that's telling you this idea of מקום משולש
makom meshulash whatever that means then we had another ברייתא braita about
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva בן עזאי Ben Azzai
that they all pretty much you know wanted to make it clear
that the problem was reading it כפשוטו kipshuto was the idea of
retroactive okay but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says well we have retroactive
invalidation in other places okay but still and then in the end
we learned it out either from the word יחשב yechashev or המקריב
hamakriv you know pretty similar to what we've done before and we
just had a little digression here where בן עזאי Ben Azzai said
אותו oto is teaching you the idea that it just does not
apply to בל תאחר bal te'acher
and that's true not just about you know about בכור bechor which
we learned from a different פסוק pasuk it's also true about other
קרבנות korbanot that even if you're over on בל תאחר bal te'acher
it does not affect your קרבן korban and as we're also learning
it does not mean for a man that his wife will die
even if that's a concept that the גמרא Gemara does have in
other places okay last piece of that ברייתא braita אחרים אומרים במחשבה
הוא נפסל ואינו נפסל בשלישי Acheim omrim bemachshavah hu nifsal ve'eino nifsal
bishlishi so the last דרשה drasha was not from המקריב אותו hamakriv
oto but לא יחשב lo yechashev that the invalidation occurs through מחשבה
machshavah and not on the third day so רבי אלעזר לא יחשב
מאי עביד ליה Rabbi Elazar lo yechashev mai avid leh so רבי
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar that learns it out from המקריב אותו hamakriv oto
what does he do with לא יחשב lo yechashev מבעי ליה לכדרבי
ינאי meba'ei leh lechiderabi Yannai to what רבי ינאי Rabbi Yannai teaches
דאמר רבי ינאי מנין למחשבות שמוציאות זו מזו de'amar Rabi Yannai minayin
lemachshavot shemotzi'ot zo mizo how do you know this is what we
said you know earlier that if you have a thought of חוץ
למקומו chutz limkomo it takes it out of the פיגול pigul status
that it's another source of invalidation and it makes it no longer
פיגול pigul even if you had a חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought
שנאמר לא יחשב לא יערב בו מחשבות אחרות shene'emar lo yechashev lo
ye'arev bo machshavot acherot okay other thoughts cannot be mixed up if
they are it won't be פיגול pigul ורב מרי מתני אמר רב
ינאי מנין למחשב בקדשים שהוא לוקה veRav Mari matni amar Rabi Yannai
minayin lemachashev bekodashim shehu lokeh now we have a new דרשה drasha
how do you know that if you have a פיגול pigul thought
that you actually get מלקות malkot that you transgress meaning not only
the קרבן korban is invalid but you transgress that's a good question
how do we know that it's not valid to do this so
שהוא
לוקה shehu lokeh תלמוד לומר לא יחשב talmud lomar lo yechashev you
may not have that thought so that's actually a very new point
and something that I think we would have liked you know is
good that it's said that it's not only that it invalidates but
it's prohibited but now we didn't just say prohibited we said you
get מלקות malkot אמר ליה רב אשי לרב מרי amar leh Rav
Ashi leRav Mari so רב אשי Rav Ashi said to רב מרי
Rav Mari לאו שאין בו מעשה הוא וכל לאו שאין בו מעשה
אין לוקין עליו lav she'ein bo ma'aseh hu vechol lav she'ein bo
ma'aseh ein lokin alav what do you mean it's a negative prohibition
that there's no act you know it's only thought you know maybe
verbalized thought that's a separate question but it's no physical act and
you don't get lashes so he says אמר ליה רבי יהודה היא
דאמר לאו שאין בו מעשה לוקין עליו amar leh Rabi Yehuda hi
de'amar lav she'ein bo ma'aseh lokin alav no this follows רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah who says that even without a physical act you can
get מלקות malkot okay so that's a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda in
a different context phew so that was a lot of stuff about
just דרשנינג darshoning from the פסוק pasuk the basic principles of פיגול
pigul but now we know the basic principles of פיגול pigul let's
take a look at the משנה mishnah זה הכלל zeh haklal now
we get a little bit more to the פיגול pigul this is
the general rule כל השוחט kol hashochet here's the acts in which
you can have a פיגול pigul thought you שוחט shochet it המקבל
hamakabel you catch the blood המהלך hamehalech you walk it to the
מזבח mizbe'ach והזורק vehazorek and you throw it on the מזבח mizbe'ach
okay so at any of those four stages of blood if you
have a thought לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול le'echol davar shedarcho le'echol to
eat something that's normally eaten meaning to eat the meat of the
קרבן korban ולהקטיר דבר שדרכו להקטיר ule'haktir davar shedarcho le'haktir or to
offer up something that is normally offered meaning the entrails כזית kezayit
if it's so if it's a thought about a כזית kezayit it
has to be a minimum amount that's another principle it has to
be doing the four עבודות avodot of blood it has to be
a minimum amount it has to be about something that is eaten
by either humans or the מזבח mizbe'ach if it is a thought
to be done חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo in the wrong place פסול
ואין בו כרת pasul ve'ein bo karet the animal becomes the קרבן
korban becomes פסול pasul but if you eat it you do not
get כרת karet חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano if it's eaten at the
wrong time פיגול pigul the animal becomes פיגול pigul the קרבן korban
becomes פיגול pigul וחייבין עליו כרת vechayavin alav karet you get כרת
karet if you eat now from the קרבן. korban. Okay? And the
idea by the way of דבר שדרכו לאכול davar shedarko leachol is
that if you had intention to eat from the entrails or to
burn the meat that was supposed to be eaten, then that would
not be a problem. That would not invalidate. Okay. ובלבד שיקריב המתיר
כמצותו. Uvilvad sheyakriv hamatir kemitzvato. And
now
like we said before, as long as the remaining the מתיר, matir,
the blood, or you know maybe if it's a מנחה mincha it's
the קומץ kometz and the לבונה, levonah, but the thing that makes
it permissible, the thing that validates the קרבן, korban, as long as
you finish that properly. כמצותו kemitzvato being the key thing. Not only
do you throw the blood at the end, but you don't have
another type of a thought that would invalidate it from another direction.
Okay, כיצד, keitzad, how is this?
כיצד קרב המתיר כמצותו? keitzad karav hamatir kemitzvato? שחט בשחיטה, shachat bishchitah,
you slaughtered it without any thought. קיבל והלך וזרק חוץ לזמנו, kibel
vehilach vezarak chutz lizmano, and then you caught and you walked and
you threw the blood with a חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought.
זהו שמקריב המתיר כמצותו. zehu shemakriv hamatir kemitzvato. That would be saying
that everything else was done properly, meaning additional thoughts of פיגול, piggul,
of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano do not make do not take it
out of פיגול. piggul. So if you had one totally כשר kosher
thought and three חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thoughts, then it still is
פיגול piggul and that's מקריב, makriv, that's the case of הקריב המתיר
כמצותו hikriv hamatir kemitzvato and it's
פיגול. piggul. כיצד לא קרב המתיר כמצותו? keitzad lo karav hamatir kemitzvato?
What's an example where it was not done properly, the rest of
it, and therefore it's not פיגול? piggul? שחט חוץ למקומו. shachat chutz
limkomo. I think I skipped a line. כיצד קרב המתיר כמצותו, keitzad
karav hamatir kemitzvato, שחט בשחיטה וקיבל והלך וזרק חוץ לזמנו, shachat bishchitah
vekibel vehilach vezarak chutz lizmano, oh, yeah I skipped. או ששחט חוץ
לזמנו, o sheshachat chutz lizmano, or the שחיטה shchitah was done
חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano וקיבל והלך וזרק בשתיקה, vekibel vehilach vezarak bishtikah,
and the rest of it was done with silence. או ששחט וקיבל
והלך וזרק חוץ לזמנו, o sheshachat vekibel vehilach vezarak chutz lizmano, or
everything was done with the חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano thought. זהו שמקריב
המתיר כמצותו. zehu shemakriv hamatir kemitzvato. So anywhere between one and four
of the four acts were done with a פיגול piggul thought and
the rest with no other thoughts. That is a case of הקריב
המתיר כמצותו. hikriv hamatir kemitzvato. כיצד לא קרב המתיר כמצותו? keitzad lo
karav hamatir kemitzvato? What's an example where something where was not done
properly, the rest of it, and therefore it's not פיגול? piggul? שחט
חוץ למקומו. shachat chutz limkomo. You had a שחיטה shchitah which was
a חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, which invalidates but is not פיגול. piggul.
קיבל והלך וזרק חוץ לזמנו, kibel vehilach vezarak chutz lizmano, and then
you had a פיגול piggul thought in one of the three remaining
ones. או ששחט חוץ לזמנו, o sheshachat chutz lizmano, or the שחיטה
shchitah was a even if the first thought, this is important, even
if the first thought was a פיגול, piggul, that does not finish
it off as פיגול piggul if the rest if something later on
is done with another way that invalidates it. So even if the
שחיטה shchitah was done with a חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, קיבל והלך
וזרק חוץ למקומו, kibel vehilach vezarak chutz limkomo, and one of the
later things was חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, that different type of invalidating
thought, okay, prevents it from being פיגול. piggul. או ששחט וקיבל והלך
וזרק חוץ למקומו, o sheshachat vekibel vehilach vezarak chutz limkomo, or obviously
if you did all of them
חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. הפסח והחטאת ששחטן שלא לשמן, hapesach vehachatat sheshachtan
shelo lishman, and it's not only a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo type
of a thing that makes it that makes it not פיגול. piggul.
Another type of invalid thought could also make it not פיגול. piggul.
It was a חטאת chatat or פסח pesach that you did שלא
לשמו. shelo lishmo. That makes it that makes it, you know, not
כשר kosher like we learned in the first משנה. mishnah. That also
would take it out. So if the שחיטה shchitah was חוץ לזמנו,
chutz lizmano, פיגול piggul was the very first thought, and then later
the זריקה zrikah was שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and it was a
פסח pesach or חטאת, chatat, that's לא קרב המתיר כמצותו. lo karav
hamatir kemitzvato. Something else came and invalidated it and it's no longer
פיגול. piggul. Okay. הפסח והחטאת ששחטן שלא לשמן וקיבל והלך וזרק חוץ
לזמנו. hapesach vehachatat sheshachtan shelo lishman vekibel vehilach vezarak chutz lizmano. So
if the שחיטה shchitah of the פסח pesach was שלא לשמן shelo
lishman and then the rest was was חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. Or
the other case, which is the bigger חידוש, chidush, או ששחט חוץ
לזמנו, o sheshachat chutz lizmano, you started it with פיגול, piggul, you
slaughtered it with a פיגול piggul thought, והלך וזרק שלא לשמו, vehilach
vezarak shelo lishmo, and then a later עבודה avodah of this פסח
pesach and חטאת chatat was שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. או ששחט וקיבל
והלך וזרק דמן שלא לשמו, o sheshachat vekibel vehilach vezarak daman shelo
lishmo, or all of them were שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. That's obvious,
זהו, zehu, you know, I guess together with a חוץ לזמנו chutz
lizmano somewhere there. זהו שלא קרב המתיר כמצותו. zehu shelo karav hamatir
kemitzvato. Okay. So very clear. And obviously if there was something else
like the blood got spilled, you know, wasn't, you know, that really
it did not the עבודה avodah didn't get done at all, that
would obviously also be a לא קרב כמצותו. lo karav kemitzvato. So
everything has to be done perfect except for the פיגול piggul thought
or thoughts that you had.
Now, let's say different point. לאכול כזית בחוץ כזית למחר, lechol kezayit
bachutz kezayit lemachar, not really so different because this is, you know,
essentially the same point as before. If you had a thought to
eat a כזית kezayit outside of the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and
a כזית kezayit tomorrow, so that's חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and חוץ
לזמנו. chutz lizmano. Now this could be in two different עבודות. avodahs.
Could be exactly like the point before. When you were doing the
שחיטה shchitah it was the wrong place, when you're doing the זריקה
zrikah it was the wrong time. Or it could be both thoughts
during the same act. As you're doing the שחיטה, shchitah, we'll see
the גמרא gemara tomorrow will sort of assume that, as you're doing
the שחיטה, shchitah, at the beginning you're thinking of the שחיטה shchitah
as you're cutting it that you're going to eat it in the
wrong place and by the time you finish and as you're finishing
the שחיטה shchitah you're thinking that you'll also eat a כזית kezayit
at. A different כזית kezayit at the wrong time. Okay, so as
you're doing the שחיטה, shechita, you're thinking to eat one כזית kezayit
in the wrong place and one כזית kezayit in the wrong time,
or כזית למחר כזית בחוץ kezayit l'machar kezayit bachutz or the reverse,
first you're thinking wrong time, then you're thinking wrong place, or כחצי
זית בחוץ כחצי זית למחר, kechatzi zayit bachutz kechatzi zayit l'machar, כחצי
זית למחר כחצי זית בחוץ, kechatzi zayit l'machar kechatzi zayit bachutz, let's
say you thought half of a כזית, kezayit, you know, today, half
of a כזית kezayit I'm going to eat in the wrong place,
half in the wrong time or in the reverse order, פסול ואין
בו כרת, pasul v'ein bo kares, it's invalid and there's no כרת.
kares. So we basically have already taught all of that because that's
a case of some other thing was done improperly, and the only
new חידוש chiddush is half a כזית kezayit and half of a
כזית, kezayit, one of חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zmano and one of חוץ
למקומו, chutz limkomo, they combine to be a כזית kezayit to invalidate,
but they do not make it פיגול piggul because you do not
have a פיגול piggul thought on a whole כזית. kezayit. And now
we have just one different opinion. אמר רבי יהודה Amar Rabbi Yehuda
says Rabbi Yehuda זה הכלל, zeh haklal, he disagrees. No, here's the
rule: כל שמחשבת זמן קדמה למחשבת המקום פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. Kol
she'machshavat zman kadma l'machshavat hamakom, piggul v'chayavin alav kares. I don't believe
that a thought later on takes it out of פיגול. piggul. If
your first thought was חוץ לזמנו, chutz l'zmano, a later thought of
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo does not take it out of פיגול. piggul.
Okay,
now that could be two scenarios. As I'm doing שחיטה, shechita, I'm
thinking חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zmano and then as I'm continuing I'm thinking
another כזית kezayit חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, okay, or I do שחיטה
shechita חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zmano and I do זריקה zerika חוץ למקומו.
chutz limkomo. It seems that either way Rabbi Yehuda is saying once
it's פיגול, piggul, it's פיגול. piggul, Even if in the same act
later you had a thought of חוץ למקומו, it doesn't matter. Once
you've made it פיגול, piggul. you've made it פיגול, piggul, and that
does not change. וחייבין עליו כרת. kares. אם מחשבת המקום קדמה למחשבת
הזמן, Im machshavat hamakom kadma l'machshavat hazman, but if the first thing
you had was thinking about the wrong place and then you had
the wrong time, so then you've already made it invalid and it
can't become פיגול. piggul, פסול ואין בו כרת, pasul v'ein bo kares,
it's פסול pasul and not כרת. kares וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim and
the חכמים Chachamim say זה וזה פסול ואין בו כרת, zeh v'zeh
pasul v'ein bo kares, no, either way it's invalid and no כרת
like we've been teaching. Okay, so what we might have introduced here
at the end is the idea of during one act of שחיטה,
shechita, having a thought of one כזית kezayit here, one כזית kezayit
there, and also this idea and a half a כזית, kezayit, half
a כזית kezayit combine but to make it invalid but not to
make it פיגול, piggul and Rabbi Yehuda's principle that once it's פיגול,
piggul it doesn't get to be un-פיגול'd piggul. by a later thought,
and presumably even if that later thought is during the very same
act. Last point. לאכול כחצי זית להקטיר כחצי זית, Le'echol kechatzi zayit
lehaktir kechatzi zayit, let's say you have a thought to eat a
כזית, kezayit, you know, כלל שאין אכילה והקטרה מצטרפין. klal she'ein achila
vehaktara mitztarvin. So before we said you don't combine a half of
a כזית kezayit of the wrong place with the wrong time. What
if they're both thoughts of the wrong time but different ways of
consuming them?
I'm going to eat a half of a כזית kezayit at the
wrong time and I'll also burn a half of a כזית kezayit
of entrails at the wrong time. So even though those are both
פיגול thoughts, since one is about human consumption and one is about
the consumption of the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, so אכילה achila and הקטרה haktara
do not מצטרף mitztarev since you do not have a thought of
a כזית, kezayit, of a full כזית kezayit of חוץ לזמנו chutz
l'zmano in one type of an act, it is not פיגול. Okay,
we will end here.