Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is ל"ז Lamed Zayin
זבחים Zvachim 37. We have just begun the fourth פרק perek and
we will pick up at the גמרא Gemara two lines from the
bottom on ל"ו עמוד ב'. Lamed Vav Amud Bet. We are still
in the middle of פיגול, pigul, but in order to deal with
interesting cases of פיגול pigul we introduced the debate of בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. What are the minimum number
of זריקות zrikot or of applications of blood that are required for
a קרבן? korban? And
it's when it's all קרבנות korbanot other than חטאת, chatat, even though
the תורה Torah says that you should be זורק סביב zorek saviv
all around, which חז"ל Chazal understand to mean two diagonally opposite corners
on all four walls; each corner you get two walls; that בדיעבד
bedi'eved even only one is sufficient and you know, one זריקה zrika
even presumably one wall. And for a חטאת chatas that the תורה
Torah says you should put it on the four corners with the
finger, not a throwing but application, here בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
it has to be a minimum of two בדיעבד bedi'eved and בית
הלל Beit Hillel says one is sufficient בדיעבד bedi'eved here as well.
And when it comes to the inner חטאות chata'ot on the inner
מזבח, mizbe'ach, everybody agrees you need all four. And because there is
this reality that the כפרה, kapara, the קרבן korban is valid at
the immediate application of one of the applications of blood, then the
remainder applications have no relevance for פיגול. pigul. Once the קרבן korban
is good, it's good, even though the remainder is still part of
the
required לכתחילה lechatchila required עבודה. avoda. Nevertheless once the קרבן korban is
good, it's פיגול pigul status cannot change. It all has to do
with the first application or for בית שמאי Beit Shammai the first
two if it's a חטאת. chatas. So let's take a look at
what the גמרא Gemara says. Today is going to be a lot
of דרשות. drashot. Where do we know when the תורה Torah says,
you know, סביב saviv or when it says four corners, how do
we know to say even less would be sufficient בדיעבד? bedi'eved? So
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabanan, two lines from the bottom on ל"ו עמוד
ב': Lamed Vav Amud Bet:
Our rabbis taught, מנין לניתנים על המזבח החיצון שנתנם במתנה אחת שכיפר?
minayin l'nitanim al hamizbe'ach hachitzon shenetanam b'matana achat shekiper? How do you
know the ones that are to be placed on the outer מזבח
mizbe'ach if you only did one application it's good? According to בית
הלל Beit Hillel that's true about all קרבנות; korbanot; according to בית
שמאי Beit Shammai for all קרבנות korbanot except for the חטאת. chatas.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the פסוק pasuk teaches: ודם זבחיך ישפך על
יסוד מזבח העולה,
v'dam zvacheicha yishafech
al yesod mizbach ha'olah, you should pour the blood of your sacrifices
on the base of the עולה olah מזבח, mizbe'ach, which is the
outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. So it's a very general פסוק: pasuk: spill the
blood of your sacrifices. It could be referring to the שיריים, shirayim,
but it doesn't say
that. It sounds like it's talking about the fundamental act of כפרה.
kapara. So from that we learn that even one application, even one
spilling, now it doesn't seem like it would matter, throwing, spilling, when
you place it on one corner for the חטאת, chatat, that's not
exactly spilling. Okay, but nevertheless from this we learn even one application
suffices. ודם זבחיך ישפך. v'dam zvacheicha yishafech. So now the גמרא Gemara
says: והאי להכי הוא דאתא? v'hai l'hachi hu de'ata? Is that really
what it's coming to teach you?
המיבעי ליה לכדתניא, ha miba'ei lei l'chidi tanya, we need it for
which we teach in the ברייתא: braita: מנין לכל הדמים שטעונין מתן
דם ליסוד? minayin l'chol hadamim shet'unin mattan dam l'yesod? How about that
point?
The actual spilling out on the יסוד, yesod, not the putting of
the blood that is the basic act of כפרה, kapara, but after
you put it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the remainder of the blood
you pour on the base. And the תורה Torah actually only says
this by a חטאת; chatas; only by a חטאת chatat does it
say that you pour the remainder on the base. It does not
say it by any of the other קרבנות, korbanot, which is fascinating.
So
where do we learn that from? מנין מתן דם ליסוד? minayin mattan
dam l'yesod? תלמוד לומר ודם זבחיך ישפך: Talmud lomar v'dam zvacheicha yishafech:
pour the blood of your sacrifices, which means it's referring to the
blood after you're done with the fundamental placing of the blood; all
the remainder blood you pour on the base. The שיריים shirayim go
to the יסוד. yesod. You know my actually, I'll say my father-in-law
יצחק
אהרן זצ"ל, Yitzchak Aaron zatzal, he actually suggested that the reason the
תורה Torah does not mention it by the other קרבנות korbanot is
when the other קרבנות, korbanot, the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim
is that it says you should put it על המזבח סביב, al
hamizbe'ach saviv, וזרקו בני אהרן את הדם על המזבח סביב. v'zarku bnei
aharon et hadam al hamizbe'ach saviv. And there the simple sense is
all of the blood gets put all around the מזבח, mizbe'ach, so
then there's no שיריים. shirayim. It's only the חטאת chatat where you
only put four applications with your finger that there's obviously going to
be שיריים, shirayim, right? But the גמרא Gemara wants to know once
the גמרא Gemara understands... it's really only two corners and it could
be you used up all the blood that you caught in a
כלי שרת, kli shares, but if you didn't, how do we know
that you pour at the base? ודם זבחיך ישפך. v'dam zvachecha yishapech.
So how so how can you learn this out to tell you
only one application? If you learn it out to tell you only
one application, where would you learn this הלכה halacha that all blood,
the שיריים shirayim of all קרבנות korbanos has to be poured at
the base? נפקא ליה, nafka lei, he could learn it out from
a different פסוק. pasuk. מדרבי, mid'Rabbi,
from from where Rabbi learns it out from. דתניא, detanya, we taught
in the ברייתא. Baraisa.
רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, Rabbi says, והנשאר בדם ימצא, v'hanishar badam yimatze,
and what remains of the blood you shall squeeze out, this is
by you know, by by by a חטאת העוף, chatas ha'of, a
bird that's a חטאת, chatas, where you sort of squeeze out the
blood and it you know against the wall and it runs to
the base. שאין תלמוד לומר בדם. she'ein talmud lomar badam. It didn't
have to say what's left of the blood, it could have just
said
והנשאר. v'hanishar. Alright? So what does it say בדם? badam? ומה תלמוד
לומר בדם? u'mah talmud lomar badam? לפי שלא למדנו אלא לניתנים מתן
ארבע שטעונין מתן דמים ויסוד. lefi shelo lamadnu ela l'nitanim matan arba
shete'unin matan damim v'yesod. שאר דמים מנין? sha'ar damim minayin? Because the
תורה Torah only says, here it says explicit, only by the things
that are placed at the four corners, meaning only a חטאת, chatas,
does the תורה Torah say that the remainder gets poured out on
the base. שאר דמים מנין? sha'ar damim minayin? How do you know
it's true about all other קרבנות? korbanos? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, והנשאר
בדם, v'hanishar badam, what is left in the blood, ימצא, yimatze, you
shall squeeze out. So even though it's talking about just the bird,
it's telling you that what's left has to get, you know, find
its way to the base of the altar and the extra word
בדם badam tells you to generalize this beyond just the case of
the bird. This concept is true about all קרבנות. korbanos.
So שאין תלמוד לומר בדם, she'ein talmud lomar badam, ומה תלמוד לומר
בדם, u'mah talmud lomar badam, why did the תורה Torah add the
word בדם? badam? לימד על כל הדמים שטעונין מתן דמים ליסוד. limed
al kol hadamim shete'unin matan damim l'yesod. All קרבנות, korbanos, like the
bird and like the חטאת, chatas, the blood has to get to
the base, any leftover blood is poured at the base.
ואכתי, v'akti, says the גמרא, Gemara, still I'll tell you... Okay, so
that's how you have it free to learn ודם זבחיך ישפך v'dam
zvachecha yishapech that one נתינה netina suffices and we don't have to
learn it that the general הלכה halacha of pouring the שיריים shirayim
to the יסוד, yesod, because we can learn that from the case
of חטאת העוף. chatas ha'of. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, but
we still need that ודם זבחיך v'dam zvachecha for another לימוד. limud.
ואכתי להכי הוא דאתא? v'akti l'hachi hu d'ata? Is that what it's
coming to teach you? מבעי ליה, miba'ei lei, you need it, כדתניא,
k'detanya, what we taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa. מנין לניתנים בזריקה שנתנן
בשפיכה יצא? minayin l'nitanim b'zrika shenetanan b'shficha yatza? תלמוד לומר ודם זבחיך
ישפך. talmud lomar v'dam zvachecha yishapech.
How do you know all the things that are supposed to be,
you know, thrown on the altar, meaning everything other than a חטאת,
chatas, okay? How do you know that if the way they get
to the wall, you know, if you don't actually throw it at
the wall of the altar, but you actually just do שפיכה, shficha,
you pour it to the base, how do you know that you
are יצא? yotzei? And that's a pretty big חידוש chiddush that you're
יצא. yotzei. But of course, you know, if you think about it,
the blood that you throw is at the bottom half of the
altar, the base is part of the altar, so if you're sort
of pouring it on the base, you're also in a way, you
know, similar place where the blood is going. But here's the הלכה,
halacha, if you actually pour a blood, you do a pouring for
every normal קרבן korban that requires זריקה, zrika, you're יצא. yotzei. Where
do you learn that out from? תלמוד לומר ודם זבחיך ישפך. talmud
lomar v'dam zvachecha yishapech. So that ודם זבחיך ישפך, v'dam zvachecha yishapech,
you're right, says the גמרא, Gemara, it is teaching you in general
you can do שפיכה shficha for קרבנות, korbanos, but not to teach
you that one application suffices, but to teach you that שפיכה shficha
is an alternative way of putting the blood on the מזבח. mizbeach.
If you're going to do זריקה, zrika, it has to be at
maybe, you know, two things at two opposite, two diagonal corners. But
you could also do שפיכה, shficha, so it is about the עיקר
כפרה, ikar kapara, but to tell you that there's an alternative path
of שפיכה. shficha. So that's what it's telling you. So the גמרא
Gemara says סבר לה, savar lah, no, they would hold and the
סבר לה savar lah presumably is both בית שמאי Beis Shammai and
בית הלל, Beis Hillel, because remember for both בית שמאי Beis Shammai
and בית הלל Beis Hillel we have to ask how do you
know only one application is good enough? Okay, so no, they could
hold כרבי עקיבא k'Rabbi Akiva like Rabbi
Akiva. דאמר, d'amar, לא זריקה בכלל שפיכה ולא שפיכה בכלל זריקה. lo
zrika bikhlal shficha v'lo shficha bikhlal zrika. Rabbi Akiva disagrees with this
הלכה. halacha. When you're supposed to throw, you gotta throw. And if
you pour, it doesn't count. And when you have to pour the
blood, and we'll see in a minute that there are some קרבנות
korbanos that you pour the blood and don't throw it, then throwing
doesn't count. So they are mutually exclusive. It is not true that
one of them can count for the other, that you have two
paths for certain קרבנות. korbanos. Now where do we know, so that,
so we don't need the פסוק pasuk to teach me that because
we don't agree with that. Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara says
probably one of the things you're thinking about, all these תנאים Tanna'im
that use the פסוק pasuk of ודם זבחיך v'dam zvachecha to learn
out these other things, where do they know the הלכה halacha of
בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, you know, that
only one application is good enough? So we'll get to that in
the גמרא. Gemara. But for now we're saying at least if you're
going to learn it out we can learn it out from ודם
זבחיך v'dam zvachecha and we don't need to have the other לימודים,
limudim, either because we learn them from other פסוקים pesukim or because
we don't agree with them. disagree with that. So the idea that
שפיכה shvicha works as an alternative to זריקה, zrika, we don't hold
like that. We hold like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that says they're
mutually exclusive. Now, where do we see that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says this?
דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה mishna in פסחים, Psachim, the
very last משנה mishna in פסחים, Psachim, after you get through all
of the tenth פרק perek and all the הלכות halachot of the
סדר Seder and קידוש Kiddush and all of that fun stuff, you
have this last משנה mishna that's about קרבנות. korbanot. And here's what
the משנה mishna says: בירך ברכת הפסח פטר את של זבח של
זבח לא פטר את הפסח. Birach birchat hapesach patar et shel zevach,
shel zevach lo patar et hapesach. If you make the ברכה bracha
for the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, okay,
which is the ברכה bracha about at the time of the eating,
אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לאכול הפסח, asher kidshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu l'echol hapesach,
and the זבח, zevach, the other thing that you sacrifice, which is
the חגיגה Chagiga of the fourteenth that you bring if there's a
lot of people in your group and you don't want people to
be eating the פסח Pesach ravenously, so you want them to get
a little meat in their stomach ahead of time. So that's the
חגיגה Chagiga of the fourteenth. And when you're going to eat that,
you say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לאכול את הזבח. asher kidshanu b'mitzvotav
v'tzivanu l'echol et hazevach.
Now, what, can one of the ברכות brachot count for both of
the קרבנות? korbanot? Okay, so the first opinion in the משנה mishna
says: בירך ברכת הפסח פטר של זבח של זבח לא פטר את
הפסח. Birach birchat hapesach patar shel zevach, shel zevach lo patar et
hapesach. The ברכה bracha on eating the פסח, Pesach, you don't have
to make a separate ברכה bracha for the חגיגה. Chagiga. But if
you made the ברכה bracha on the חגיגה, Chagiga, that doesn't count
for the פסח. Pesach. You have to make a separate one for
the פסח. Pesach. דברי רבי ישמעאל, divrei Rabbi Yishmael, that's what רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says: לא זו פוטרת זו ולא זו פוטרת זו. lo
zo poteret zo v'lo zo poteret zo. No, one of them, either
one does not exempt the other. Now, who says this has anything
to do with זריקה zrika and
שפיכה? shvicha? Especially the way רש"י Rashi understands that it's about eating
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and eating the חגיגה, Chagiga, why should
whether one exempts the other have anything to do with how you
put the blood on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? And you very reasonably could
have understood that the debate is that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael holds,
and eventually רש"י Rashi says that this is a version of the
debate, that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael holds, look, the עיקר ikar is
the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. I mean, come on, it's סדר Seder
night. The עיקר ikar is the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. The other
קרבן korban is טפל, tafel, it's secondary. So if you make the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, it's the פסח Pesach plus the stuff that
goes with it, the חגיגה, Chagiga, and so on. All right? So
that's why it exempts it. But obviously if you make a ברכה
bracha on the טפל tafel thing, it doesn't exempt the main show,
it doesn't exempt the פסח. Pesach. That would be רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi
Yishmael opinion. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say,
I don't buy into this טפל tafel and עיקר, ikar, or the
ברכה bracha on the פסח Pesach is too specific. Whatever reason, each
one has to get its own ברכה. bracha. All right? That would
be one way to explain it having nothing to do with our
discussion about זריקה zrika and שפיכה. shvicha. However, the interpretation that the
גמרא gemara is assuming here and that it adopts in פסחים Psachim
is that their debate is exactly this question of whether you could
do the same עבודה avoda for both קרבנות. korbanot. Okay? And the
assumption is the תורה Torah never tells you what you do with
the blood of the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, interestingly, because the פסח
Pesach is fundamentally brought to be eaten. So it doesn't focus on
what you do with the blood, although of course we know what
they did with the blood in מצרים. Mitzrayim. And therefore, the assumption
here is that you pour the blood and you don't throw it,
and we'll see in a minute where we learn that from. Okay?
Whereas the חגיגה, Chagiga, that's a classic sacrifice and you throw the
blood. So the גמרא's gemara understanding that according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, since you could do שפיכה shvicha for the חגיגה Chagiga because
anything that's with זריקה zrika has an alternative of שפיכה, shvicha, then
the ברכה bracha on the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach which is a
שפיכה shvicha קרבן korban counts for the חגיגה Chagiga which also could
be done through שפיכה. shvicha. And that's why the פסח Pesach exempts
the חגיגה. Chagiga. But the ברכה bracha on the חגיגה Chagiga which
is a זריקה zrika קרבן korban fundamentally cannot exempt the פסח Pesach
because פסח Pesach can only be done by שפיכה, shvicha, it cannot
be done by זריקה. zrika. That's רבי ישמעאל's Rabbi Yishmael position. So
that the פסח Pesach exempts because the חגיגה Chagiga could be done
by שפיכה shvicha as well. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds they
don't exempt one another, the פסח Pesach is only שפיכה shvicha and
the חגיגה Chagiga is only זריקה. zrika. Okay? So given that read
of their debate, where there's a position of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that each one is in its own lane and therefore the פסוק
pasuk ודם זבחיך ישפך v'dam zvacheicha yishafech is not teaching you that
שפיכה shvicha is a legitimate alternative. All right? So that's that.
So now the גמרא gemara says, אכתי להכי הוא דאתא, akati l'hachi
hu d'ata, wait a minute, I'm still going to question whether you
can use ודם זבחיך v'dam zvacheicha to teach you that one application
of blood suffices. I'll show you yet another thing that you learn
from it.
מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, mibaya lei l'chidi tanya, we need it for what
we teach in the ברייתא, braita, רבי ישמעאל רבי
ישמעאל
Rabbi
Yishmael אומר omer מתוך שנאמר mitoch shene'emar אך בכור שור או בכור
כשב או בכור עז. ach bechor shor o bechor kesev o bechor
ez.
So this is in the end of קרח Korach where there's a
list of all of the מתנות כהונה, matnot kehunah, all these types
of things that the כהנים kohanim are זוכה zocheh in, get from
the rest of the people. And here's the פסוק, pasuk, it's י״ח
י״ז, yud chet yud zayin, אך בכור שור או בכור כשב או
בכור עז ach bechor shor o bechor kesev o bechor ez לא
תפדה, lo tipadeh, they cannot be redeemed, קודש הם kodesh hem they're
holy, את דמם תזרק על המזבח ואת חלבם תקטיר אשה לריח ניחח
לה׳. et damam tizrok al hamizbe'ach ve'et chelbam taktir isheh lere'ach nichoach
l'Hashem. You have to throw the blood on the מזבח mizbe'ach and
burn up this sort of קרבן, korban, but you the כהנים kohanim
get to eat from the meat. Other פסוקים psukim just talk about
giving the בכור bechor to the כהן, kohen, do not mention the
fact that it's a קרבן, korban, this says it's a קרבן korban
and you throw the blood on the מזבח mizbe'ach and the אימורים
emurim on the altar. And the אימורים emurim similarly you burn. Okay,
so let's read that again. מתוך שנאמר mitoch shene'emar אך בכור שור
או בכור כשב או בכור עז ach bechor shor o bechor kesev
o bechor ez etc. למדנו לבכור שטעון דמים ואימורים לגבי מזבח. lamadnu
labechor sheta'un damim ve'emurim legabei mizbe'ach. Good. That teaches us about a
בכור bechor which the תורה Torah had not said until now what
you do with the blood, that it's a normal קרבן korban and
you put the blood, you throw it and you burn the אימורים
emurim like any other normal קרבן. korban. Okay, but מעשר פסח מנין?
ma'aser pesach minayin? How do you know that you do similarly, you
know, what you do with the blood for the מעשר ma'aser and
פסח? pesach? Two other things where the מעשר ma'aser the focus is
again a gift to the כהן, kohen, the תורה Torah doesn't talk
about what you do with the blood, doesn't focus on it as
a קרבן, korban, the פסח pesach the focus is on eating the
meat, so the תורה Torah also doesn't talk about what you do
with the blood. So how do we know what you should do
with them? ואימורים לגבי מזבח מנין? ve'emurim legabei mizbe'ach minayin? תלמוד לומר
talmud lomar ודם זבחיך ישפך. vedam zivchecha yishapech. So ודם זבחיך ישפך
vedam zivchecha yishapech is telling you there are קרבנות korbanot which the
תורה Torah has not specified what to do with their blood and
now it's telling you pour it at the base. Okay, so this
would be the basis for what we were assuming before that the
קרבן פסח korban pesach the blood gets poured, פסח pesach and מעשר
ma'aser where the תורה Torah doesn't say what to do with the
blood, we learn from this פסוק pasuk it gets poured. So how
can you use this פסוק pasuk to teach you one application? We
need this פסוק pasuk to teach you what you do with the
blood of the פסח pesach and מעשר. ma'aser. So the גמרא Gemara
says סבר לה כרבי יוסי הגלילי. savor lah keRabbi Yosi HaGelili. No,
the author of our משנה Mishnah would hold like רבי יוסי הגלילי
Rabbi Yosi HaGelili דתניא detanya רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGelili אומר
omer דמו לא נאמר אלא דמם. damo lo ne'emar ela damam. When
it speaks about the blood of the בכור, bechor, the פסוק pasuk
I just read, it doesn't say את דמו תזרק אל המזבח, et
damo tizrok el hamizbe'ach, it says דמם damam their blood. Now the
simple פשט pshat is because it mentioned three types of animals: אך
בכור שור או בכור כשב או בכור עז לא תפדה קודש הם
ach bechor shor o bechor kesev o bechor ez lo tipadeh kodesh
hem etc. they are holy, all of these types of בכורות bechors
את דמם et damam their blood of whether it is a goat,
a sheep or a calf. But we're going to say no, the
תורה Torah should have said its blood because they're all one type
of a קרבן בכור korban bechor and it said their blood, that's
including other קרבנות korbanot as well. All right, so את דמו לא
נאמר אלא דמם, et damo lo ne'emar ela damam, it says their
blood plural.
חלבו chelbo its fat לא נאמר אלא חלבם lo ne'emar ela chelbam
their fat.
לימד הבכור מעשר ופסח, limed abechor ma'aser upesach, it teaches you that
not only בכור bechor which is explicit in the פסוק, pasuk, but
two other things where the תורה Torah never tells you what to
do with their blood, מעשר ma'aser and פסח pesach as well, that
they're all the same. You're being told in this פסוק pasuk what
to do with them. לימד הבכור מעשר ופסח שטעון דמים ואימורים לגבי
מזבח. limed abechor ma'aser upesach shete'un damim ve'emurim legabei mizbe'ach. You throw
the blood and you burn the אימורים. emurim. So this פסוק pasuk
tells you זריקה zrika by the blood of a בכור bechor and
the plural tells you the same is true by מעשר ma'aser and
פסח. pesach. Actually there's a debate: Do you... are you שופך shofech
the blood of מעשר ma'aser and פסח pesach based on דם זבחיך
ישפך dam zivchecha yishapech or are you זורק zorek the דם dam
of מעשר ma'aser and פסח pesach like the תורה Torah says to
do by בכור bechor based on the plural דמם damam and חלבם?
chelbam? Okay, so that's how come if you say you're זורק zorek
and you learn it from בכור, bechor, again we have דם זבחיך
ישפך dam zivchecha yishapech free to teach me one application on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach.
So now the גמרא Gemara has finally a question which is: We
got a lot of things we're learning out from this and what
are they like mutually exclusive? You know? And particularly רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. We heard a minute before that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said
about, you know, that the ברכה bracha of the פסח pesach exempts
the זבח zevach and we assumed that that meant that it was
because, you know, the פסח pesach is בשפיכה bishvicha and the זבח
zevach is בשפיכה... bishvicha... excuse me, זבח zevach is זריקה zrika but
שפיכה shvicha would be an alternative path, it would work. And here
from the same פסוק pasuk he's learning that the קרבן פסח, korban
pesach, right, is בשפיכה. bishvicha. Meaning the way the גמרא Gemara understood
the position of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, why the ברכה bracha of
the פסח pesach exempts the חגיגה, chagiga, because the פסח pesach is
שפיכה. shvicha. point number one, assumption number one, זבח Zevach is זריקה,
Zrika, and number two, שפיכה Shvicha can work for זריקה. Zrika. Or
the גמרא Gemara says both those points you learn from the same
פסוק. Pasuk. דם זבחיך ישפך Dam zvachecha yishafech tells you that the
פסח Pesach is בשפיכה, bishvicha, that’s this teaching of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael that we just said. And דם זבחיך ישפך Dam zvachecha yishafech
is the other teaching that שפיכה shvicha works for זריקה. zrika. So
and we assumed that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael holds both of those
and that was his position about the ברכה bracha exempting. So how
can he learn both of those things from the same פסוק? pasuk?
Good question. So let’s see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאפיק ליה
להכי ומאפיק ליה להכי? mafke lei l'hachi umafke lei l'hachi? So the
גמרא Gemara says, תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי ישמעאל. trei tanna'ei aliba d'Rabbi
Yishmael. There are two different תנאים Tanna'im for רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael.
There’s the תנא Tanna of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says the
one we just said that the פסח Pesach is בשפיכה. bishvicha. And
then there’s another תנא Tanna of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael about the
ברכה. bracha. Now that is really not a satisfying answer because the
תנא Tanna of the ברכה bracha still assumes two things. It assumes
the פסח Pesach is בשפיכה, bishvicha, one of the things you learn
from the פסוק, pasuk, and it assumes that the חגיגה chagiga which
is בזריקה bizrika can also work בשפיכה, bishvicha, another thing you learn
from the פסוק. pasuk. So in that תנא tanna himself, both of
those things are assumed. So that basically pushes רש"י Rashi to say,
you know what, according to what the גמרא Gemara is really saying
is that the debate about the ברכה bracha has nothing to do
with שפיכה shvicha and זריקה. zrika. The debate about the ברכה bracha
is really the question of טפל tofel and עיקר ikkar and it’s
completely irrelevant to this question of שפיכה shvicha and זריקה. zrika. Doesn’t
exactly fit the words תרי תנאי, trei tanna'ei, but that is, that
is at least רש"י Rashi recognized the problem and that’s how he
explains it. Bottom line is there’s a lot of things we learn
from this פסוק pasuk and it’s hard to assume that they are
all mutually exclusive, but that sort of seems to be what the
גמרא Gemara is assuming right now. תוספות Tosafot works on figuring out
how they, you know, you could learn the same הלכות halachot from
other פסוקים. psukim. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
בשלמא לרבי ישמעאל דמוקי לה כולה בבכור היינו דכתיב ובשרם יהיה לך.
Bishlama l'Rabbi Yishmael d'muki lah kullah b'vechor haynu d'chtiv u'vsaram yiyeh lach.
So for רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, so now we’re just going to
look at this פסוק pasuk we just read about בכור שור. bechor
shor. Okay, so רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says that the entire
פסוק pasuk is talking about בכור, bechor, right? את דמם תזרק על
המזבח ואת חלבם תקטיר. et damam tizrok al hamizbe'ach v'et chelbam taktiv.
It’s just talking about בכור. bechor. פסח Pesach and מעשר ma'aser is
שפיכה shvicha and we learn that from דם זבחיך ישפך. dam zvachecha
yishafech. So according to him, the בכור bechor פסוק pasuk here in
קרח Korach is just בכור bechor פשט. peshat. So the next פסוק
pasuk ובשרם יהיה לך, u'vsaram yiyeh lach, and you the כהנים Kohanim
get the flesh because the point of mentioning this in this section
in קרח Korach is to say that the כהנים Kohanim get, you
know, it’s one of the מתנות כהונה. matnot kehuna. So that makes
sense, we’re just talking about בכור bechor and it’s saying the כהנים
Kohanim get the meat of the בכור. bechor. היינו דכתיב ובשרם יהיה
לך. Haynu d'chtiv u'vsaram yiyeh lach. אלא לרבי יוסי דמוקי לה נמי
במעשר ופסח. Ella l'Rabbi Yossi d'muki lah nami b'ma'aser u'vpesach. To רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi that says את דמם et damam in plural תזרק
על המזבח ואת חלבם tizrok al hamizbe'ach v'et chelbam in plural תקטיר
taktir is telling you that not only בכור bechor do you throw
the blood and offer the אימורים, imurim, but also פסח pesach and
מעשר, ma'aser, which it never says elsewhere in the תורה Torah what
do you do with it? So now the תורה Torah is talking
in this פסוק pasuk את דמם חלבם et damam chelbam about בכור,
bechor, מעשר ma'aser and פסח, pesach, all three of them. So according
to that,
so the next פסוק pasuk ובשרם יהיה לך, u'vsaram yiyeh lach, their
flesh is for you to eat the כהנים, Kohanim, that’s not true
about פסח pesach and מעשר. ma'aser. So the גמרא Gemara says,
דמוקי לה נמי במעשר ופסח, מעשר ופסח בעלים אכלי ליה. d'muki lah
nami b'ma'aser u'vpesach, ma'aser v'pesach be'alim achli lei. מעשר Ma'aser and פסח
Pesach is eaten by the owners, not by the כהנים. kohanim. I
actually think I might have misspoke before when I was mentioning מעשר,
Ma'aser, it’s not a מתנת כהונה, matnas kehuna, you have to be
מפריש mafresh it from your flock but ultimately the owners themselves eat
it. Okay, so how does רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi read the next
פסוק pasuk ובשרם יהיה לך? u'vsaram yiyeh lach? The כהנים kohanim eat
their flesh. Obviously that’s only talking about בכור. bechor. But he says
the previous פסוק pasuk is talking about בכור, bechor, מעשר ma'aser and
פסח. pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says no. מאי ובשרם יהיה לך
אחד תם ואחד בעל מום. Mai u'vsaram yiyeh lach? Echad tam v'echad
ba'al mum. You’re right. The plural means something different. In the first
פסוק pasuk דמם תזרק על המזבח חלבם תקטיר, damam tizrok al hamizbe'ach
chelbam taktir, the plural is telling you what do you do with
the blood and the אימורים imurim of not only בכור bechor but
also מעשר ma'aser and פסח. pesach. And when you get to the
next פסוק pasuk ובשרם יהיה לך, u'vsaram yiyeh lach, that plural is
telling you a different plural. Two types of בכור, bechor, whether it’s
a בכור bechor that is בעל מום ba'al mum or whether it’s
a בכור bechor that is תם, tam, either way the כהנים Kohanim
get the
meat. Okay. לימד על בכור בעל מום שניתן לכהן. Limed al bechor
ba'al mum shenitan l'kohen. Let’s turn to the top of ל"ז ע"ב.
lamed zayin amud bet. This is telling you that a בכור bechor
that has a בעל מום ba'al mum you give it to a
כהן kohen and it’s not brought as a קרבן. korban. The כהנים
kohanim just straight eat it, which is bizarre. Here it’s קדוש, kadosh,
it’s sanctified But if it can't be brought as a קרבן, korban,
what do you do? You would think you would have to redeem
it, but you're not allowed to redeem it. So what do you
actually do? So what you do is the כהן Kohein is allowed
to eat this קדוש kadosh animal with a מום, mum, with a
blemish, without redeeming it. Okay, and the גמרא Gemara says שלא מצינו
לו בכל התורה כולה, shelo matzinu lo bechol haTorah kullah, so which
we didn't find in the entire תורה. Torah. So רש"י Rashi says
we never found a פסוק pasuk anywhere else that tells us what
you do with a בכור בעל מום, bechor ba'al mum, but תוספות
Tosafot says it's actually making a sharper point. Yes, that's true, but
we also have never found this phenomenon in the תורה, Torah, that
something that is קדוש kadosh can be eaten with a מום mum
without redeeming it. Okay, so that's a very bizarre phenomenon, so you
need the plural to tell you yes, the כהן Kohein gets to
eat the meat both of a תם tam that's brought as a
קרבן korban and of a בעל מום ba'al mum even though it
is קדוש. kadosh. Okay, but bottom line is he's conceding that the
plural means something different. In the first פסוק pasuk the plural means
בכור, bechor, מעשר, ma'aser, and פסח, Pesach, what you do with the
blood and the אימורין, imurin, and they're all the same, and the
next פסוק pasuk about eating the meat for the כהנים Kohanim is
two types of
בכור. bechor. Okay. ורבי ישמעאל, veRabbi Yishmael, now רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
where does he learn since he says the plural דמם תזרוק חלבם
damam tizrok chelbam is talking about a בכור bechor of שור כשב
ועז, shor kesev ve-ez, פשט בבי פסוקים, pshat be-vei psukim, רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael in general is a פשט pshat man, he reads, you
know, the פסוקים דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם, psukim dibra Torah kileishon
benei adam, so בשרם יהיה לך besaram yihyeh lecha also means whether
it is a sheep, goat, or cow בכור, bechor, where is he
going to learn the הלכה halacha that the כהן Kohein eats a
בכור בעל מום bechor ba'al mum without bringing it as a
קרבן? korban? רבי ישמעאל נפקא ליה מלך יהיה דסיפא, Rabbi Yishmael nafka
leih milach yihyeh desifa, because the פסוק pasuk says ובשרם יהיה לך
כחזה התנופה וכשוק הימין, u-vesaram yihyeh lecha kachazeh hatenufah u-cheshok hayamin, and
it could have put a period, and it says לך יהיה. lacha
yihyeh. So the extra לך יהיה lacha yihyeh is telling you an
extra thing you get. You even get the בעל מום. ba'al mum.
Okay. Now so now we've learned how to deal with those פסוקים
psukim about בכור bechor and what they teach us about פסח Pesach
and מעשר ma'aser and בעל מום ba'al mum and תם tam and
we have many דרשות drashot that we have learned from, you know,
what do you call it, from דם זבחיך ישפך. dam zivcheicha yishapeich.
Let's just review what they are. Number one, the reason it was
brought in, to teach you מתנה אחת matanah achat suffices. Okay. Number
two, to teach you that even קרבנות korbanot that are not חטאת,
chatat, you spill the remainder of the blood on the יסוד. yesod.
Number three, the idea that, and these you might not, some of
these might be debated, like number three, the idea that something that
has that should be done בזריקה bizrika can be done also בשפיכה,
bishfichah, בדיעבד bedi'avad it works בשפיכה, bishfichah, that might be debated. Number
four,
that what do you call it, number four, that קרבן פסח korban
Pesach and מעשר, ma'aser, the תורה Torah doesn't tell you what to
do with their blood, so you do it בשפיכה, bishfichah, again that's
debated and others would say it would be בזריקה. bizrika. So that's
a lot of things we've learned from that פסוק. pasuk. Let's keep
on going. So the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא לרבי יוסי הגלילי דמוקי
לה נמי במעשר ופסח, bishlama leRabbi Yosi HaGlili demokei lah nami bema'aser
u-Pesach, ah we're not done yet with this פסוק pasuk about בכור.
bechor. So according to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGlili that says
דמם תזרוק חלבם תקטיר damam tizrok chelbam taktir is talking about all
three: בכור, bechor, מעשר, ma'aser, and פסח, Pesach, היינו דכתיב לא תפדה
קודש הם. hainu dechtiv lo tifdeh kodesh hem. Okay, that's why it
says אך בכור שור או בכור כשב או בכור עז לא תפדה
קודש הם, ach bechor shor o bechor kesev o bechor ez lo
tifdeh kodesh hem, okay, and why? And because that teaches you the
following הלכה, halacha, not just that they can't be redeemed, but that
only they can be brought. הם קריבים, hem kreivim, they are holy,
they can be brought as a קרבן: korban: בכור, bechor, מעשר, ma'aser,
and פסח, Pesach, ואין תמורתן קריבה. ve-ein tmuratan kreivah. But the תמורה
tmurah of בכור, bechor, sometimes a תמורה tmurah can be offered up,
sometimes it cannot, the תמורה tmurah of בכור, bechor, מעשר, ma'aser, and
פסח Pesach cannot be offered. Now בכור bechor and מעשר ma'aser you
understand to some degree, to some degree בכור bechor is totally natural,
it wasn't sort of created by humans, that puts it in a
separate category. מעשר, ma'aser, yes you counted it as the tenth, but
still to some degree you're not making something out of nothing קדוש,
kadosh, so it's somewhat similar to בכור. bechor. פסח Pesach is harder
to understand. I mean פסח Pesach is also distinctive that it's fundamentally
brought for the meat, but anyway, hard to understand what the common
denominator is here, but the הלכה halacha is all three of these
cannot, you cannot offer up a תמורה. tmurah. And we, according to
רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yosi HaGlili, that would be based on the
word קודש הם. kodesh hem. They are holy and only they can
be brought up, not the תמורה. tmurah. How do we know this
הלכה, halacha, where do we see this הלכה halacha that they cannot
be offered, that their תמורה tmurah cannot be offered? דתנן, detnan, we
taught in the משנה: mishna: תמורת בכור ומעשר, tmurat bechor u-ma'aser, so
first we'll do with בכור bechor and מעשר, ma'aser, if you do
a תמורה tmurah for בכור bechor and מעשר, ma'aser, you say this
will be in exchange for this, הן וולדיהן וולד ולדיהן עד סוף
כל העולם, hein u-valdeihen ve-velad valdeihen ad sof kol ha'olam, they and
if their children and grandchildren, if the animals give birth, the תמורה
tmurah gives birth, הרי הן כבכור ומעשר. harei hen ke-bechor u-ma'aser. On
the one hand they have the קדושה kedushah of בכור bechor and
מעשר, ma'aser, but in the following way: ויאכלו במומם לבעלים, ve-ye'achlu bemumam
labe'alim, that they can never be offered up. They're like a בכור
bechor and מעשר ma'aser that when they get a מום, mum, you
can't redeem them, but you... And you eat them with their מום
mum even though they're still קדוש. kadosh. Right? That was the חידוש
chiddush that the Torah that we learned before about בכור בעל מום.
bechor ba'al mum. But they can't be offered as a קרבן. korban.
Only can be eaten with a מום, mum, okay, but not as
a קרבן korban in themselves. That's בכור ומעשר. bechor u'ma'aser. דתנן, d'tnan,
and when it comes to פסח, Pesach, אמר רבי יהושע, amar Rabbi
Yehoshua, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says, שמעתי שתמורת הפסח קריבה ותמורת הפסח
אינה קריבה. shamati she'tmurat ha'Pesach kreiva u'tmurat ha'Pesach eina kreiva. I heard
there are some types of a תמורה tmura of a פסח Pesach
that can be offered and some cannot be offered, ואין לי לפרש,
v'ein li l'faraish, but I don't know the difference. And the גמרא
Gemara there, whatever, concludes that the difference is that the תמורה tmura
of a פסח Pesach before פסח Pesach or on the 14th, when
it's really a תמורה tmura of a פסח, Pesach, cannot be offered,
whereas the תמורה tmura of a פסח Pesach after פסח, Pesach, when
a פסח Pesach is effectively a שלמים, shlamim, can be offered. Okay,
so we have a הלכה, halacha, no, you cannot offer up a
תמורה tmura of פסח, בכור ומעשר. Pesach, bechor u'ma'aser. So according to
רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili, we learn it from קודש הם
kodesh haim because the פסוק pasuk is talking about all three. אלא
רבי ישמעאל דמוקי לה כולה בבכור, ella Rabbi Yishmael d'muki la kullah
b'bechor, but according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that the whole פסוק
pasuk is talking about בכור, bechor, מעשר ופסח דלא קרבה תמורתן מנלן,
ma'aser u'Pesach d'lo kreiva tmuratan minalan, where does he learn the הלכה
halacha that מעשר ופסח ma'aser u'Pesach are not offered up? So, different
פסוקים. psukim. מעשר גמר עברה עברה ma'aser gmar avara avara because it
says by מעשר, ma'aser, כל אשר יעבור תחת השבט, kol asher ya'avor
tachat ha'shavet, and by בכור bechor it says והעברת כל פטר רחם.
v'ha'avarta kol peter rechem. So they both say pass over, העברת. ha'avarta.
So that גזירה שוה gzaira shava teaches us this הלכה halacha of
no תמורה. tmura. Why of all the possible things to learn out,
it specifically teaches this, I don't know, but that's what the גזירה
שוה gzaira shava teaches.
It's interesting, right? Because this is the position of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael that says that the what you do with the blood is
different. So the גזירה שוה gzaira shava would teach us this הלכה
halacha that the תמורה tmura isn't offered, but it doesn't teach us
to do the same thing with the blood. Anyway, עברה עברה מבכור.
avara avara m'bechor. פסח
בהדיא כתיב ביה כשב. Pesach b'hadya ktiv bei kesev. מה תלמוד לומר
אם כשב ma talmud lomar im kesev לרבות תמורת הפסח אחר הפסח
שתקרב שלמים. l'rabot tmurat ha'Pesach achar ha'Pesach she'tikarev shlamim. Okay, so פסח
Pesach there's a different דרשה. drasha. Okay, because the תורה Torah says,
you know, by a שלמים, shlamim, it says אם כשב הוא מקריב,
im kesev hu makriv, if he's going to bring a כשב, kesev,
a sheep. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מה תלמוד לומר,
ma talmud lomar, it could have said כשב, kesev, you're bringing a
sheep, מה תלמוד לומר אם כשב, ma talmud lomar im kesev, what's
the extra word אם? im? I mean, grammatically not so clear that
it's extra, but okay. To tell you לרבות תמורת הפסח אחר הפסח
שתקרב שלמים l'rabot tmurat ha'Pesach achar ha'Pesach she'tikarev shlamim that there's, we're
talking about a שלמים, shlamim, and we know a פסח Pesach is
a sheep, goat, so to tell you that if it is that
there's something else in addition to a normal שלמים shlamim that's also
brought as a שלמים, shlamim, not just a פסח Pesach after פסח
Pesach that we all already know, but even a תמורה tmura of
a פסח Pesach after פסח Pesach can be brought as a שלמים.
shlamim. יכול אף לפני פסח כן, yachol af lifnei Pesach kein, maybe
even before פסח Pesach we could offer up the תמורה tmura as
a שלמים shlamim or as a פסח. Pesach. תלמוד לומר הוא. talmud
lomar hu. So it says הוא, hu, זבח פסח הוא, zevach Pesach
hu, only it is a פסח Pesach and nothing else. So while
this פסח Pesach still has a status of a פסח, Pesach, it's
before פסח, Pesach, it's, you know, the 14th or earlier, while it
still has a status of a פסח Pesach and not a status
of a שלמים, shlamim, then we read it as פסח הוא, Pesach
hu, only it can be brought up and nothing else. Okay, so
that's how we learn מעשר ma'aser and פסח Pesach from different פסוקים
psukim that their תמורה tmura cannot be offered up. All right, so
that was a whole big
digression, fascinating the range of different things we learn from דם זבחיך
ישפך. dam zvachecha yishapech. Okay, but basically if you say that that's
the basis of בית הלל ובית שמאי, Beit Hillel u'Beit Shammai, you'd
have to say that they either have a different פסוק pasuk for
all the things we just taught or they disagree with some of
the things we just taught, you know, which is hard to sort
of support that position. But you could also ask in reverse, and
all the people that learned something from this פסוק, pasuk, where do
they know the הלכה halacha that one נתינה סתם netina stam suffices?
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. Exactly the question the
גמרא Gemara asks.
וכל הנהו תנאי דמפקי ליה להאי דם זבחיך ישפך dam zvachecha yishapech,
לדרשה אחרינא האי כל הניתנים על המזבח החיצון שנתן מתנה אחת שכיפר
מנא להו? All of the תנאים Tannaim that we just quoted that
have a different thing to learn from דם זבחיך ישפך, where do
they learn the הלכה halacha they, you know, if we're going, it's
so funny, sometimes the גמרא Gemara is happy to learn five things
from a פסוק. pasuk. Here, you know, only the one thing. So
if they learn whatever they're learning from this פסוק, pasuk, where do
they know this basic הלכה halacha that one נתינה netina suffices? So
the גמרא Gemara says,
סבירא להו כבית הלל דאמרי אף חטאת שניתנה מתנה אחת כיפר וילפינן
כולהו מחטאת. savira lahu k'Beit Hillel d'amri af chatat she'nitna matana achat
kiper v'yalfinan kuleihu m'chatat. So they could hold like בית הלל, Beit
Hillel, you know, and say that בית הלל Beit Hillel learns that
a חטאת, chatat, we're going to see in a minute, that'll be
the next discussion, where בית הלל Beit Hillel learns that a חטאת
chatat one נתינה netina suffices. And since one נתינה netina suffices by
a חטאת, chatat, even though there are four נתינות, netinot, right, four
separate נתינות netinot and one suffices. so you could sort of make
like a קל וחומר kal vachomer or at least a בנין אב
binyan av and you know and say that if that's true by
a חטאת Chatas that one suffices, which we'll learn about in a
minute, it's true about all the other קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, so you
could learn it all from a חטאת Chatas and that's a cliffhanger
which we'll now see about where you learn it from a חטאת.
Chatas. But בית שמאי Beis Shammai that says a חטאת Chatas has
to be two, the חטאת Chatas cannot be the paradigm for the
other קרבנות. korbanos. So it was for בית שמאי Beis Shammai that
we had to actually say that it was, what do you call
it, that it was learned out from ודם זבחיך ישפך. v'dam zvachecha
yishapech. Okay, so that presumably sounds now like the whole previous discussion
was according to בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. By the way, תוספות Tosfos
actually has a point that there's a סברא sevara to say that
a חטאת Chatas one is good, one or two is good, but
by all other קרבנות korbanos it has to be, it has to
be exactly what the תורה Torah says, you know, both corners. Why?
Because really by the other קרבנות korbanos the תורה Torah says תזרק
על המזבח סביב, tizrok al hamizbeach saviv, all around. And we say
that you're יוצא yotzei סביב saviv by two opposite corners, each one
hitting two walls. But you could have said that's not just a
number, that is conceptually making it as if the blood went all
around the מזבח. mizbeach. So anything less than having it hit all
four walls isn't סביב, saviv, it's zero. It's not one out of
two, it's zero. Okay, whereas by the חטאת, Chatas, if it says
four corners, one is at least one of the four, you know,
you actually did something. So maybe you don't, so maybe the extra
three are like, you know, the ideal and one suffices. So that's
actually conceptually an excellent point, but the גמרא Gemara is not saying
that here. It is saying that if by a חטאת Chatas one
suffices, we can assume it's true by all other קרבנות korbanos as
well. Okay, so let's just now take a look, get to the
bottom of the דף daf and take a look at where do
we know this by a חטאת Chatas that one suffices. Okay, וחטאת
שתי מתנות, v'chatas shtei matanos, so בית שמאי Beis Shammai two and
בית הלל Beis Hillel one. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, מאי
טעמא דבית שמאי? mai taama d'Beis Shammai? What's the reason of בית
שמאי? Beis Shammai? קרנות קרנות קרנות. karnos, karnos, karnos. Because it says
you know in the תורה Torah where it's talking about the at
the end of פרשת ויקרא, Parshas Vayikra, the different קרבנות korbanos of
חטאת Chatas that are brought by individuals, whether it's the נשיא nasi
or whether it's an individual, that are brought on the outer מזבח,
mizbeach, it says you shall put the blood on the קרנות המזבח,
karnos hamizbeach, the corners. So we're going to do a thing that
the גמרא Gemara sometimes does, which is if you have multiple words,
we're going to count it up and that's going to give us
the number that we need. Okay, and קרנות karnos is plural, so
it says קרנות karnos three times, you know, somehow we're able to
put all the פסוקים psukim together, presumably if it said it by
one we could have learned it out to the others, so if
it's repeating it, it allows us to add them all together, and
that gets you two, two, and two, that gets you six corners.
הרי כאן שש. harei kan shesh. ארבע למצוה ושתים לעכב. arba l'mitzvah
u'shtayim l'akev. Four is like the לכתחילה, lechatchila,
and then the two, I mean four is the ideal, the מצוה,
mitzvah, what you're supposed to do, not just לכתחילה, lechatchila, that's what
the תורה Torah is to do, but it's telling you there's another
two to teach you a different הלכה. halacha. There's one הלכה halacha
about four, four is
what's the basic requirement, but there's another הלכה halacha about two that
בדיעבד bedieved two suffices. Okay, now I should make a point here
that there's a general principle by קדשים Kodshim that you need שנה
לאו הכתוב לעכב, shina lav hakasuv l'akev, that if even when the
תורה Torah describes a procedure, if it's not said twice or it's
not said חק chok or it's not somehow repeated, then you say
בדיעבד bedieved you're יוצא yotzei even without it. It's fascinating, like you
would never say that by anything that wasn't קדשים, Kodshim, right? ולקחתם
לכם ביום הראשון. ul'kachtem lachem bayom harishon. Well, it didn't say twice,
it only said once, so בדיעבד bedieved I'm יוצא yotzei without doing
it. I mean, you know, the תורה Torah tells you this is
the מצוה. mitzvah. But here, because it's you know, it's not like
each thing is a separate מצוה, mitzvah, it's like a procedure of
the קרבן korban and there are so many details about what makes
the קרבן korban the process, that it's the גמרא Gemara sort of
works with the assumption that we can't say every single one of
them is absolutely required unless it's repeated. We don't say it's מעכב.
maakev. So that knowing that lets us from the get-go start with
an attitude that like all four are not necessarily required בדיעבד bedieved
and בית שמאי Beis Shammai learns it out from six, you get
the four and the two. That, excuse me, בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
That's where בית שמאי Beis Shammai learns it from.
ובית הלל, u'Beis Hillel, קרנת קרנת קרנות. karnas, karnas, karnos. So בית
הלל Beis Hillel says it's actually two of the times, right, we
read it קרנות karnos in the plural, that's יש אם למקרא yesh
em l'mikra you focus on how it's read, but the way it's
written, יש אם למסורת yesh em l'masores is without a ו, vav,
קרנת, karnas, which would be in the singular,
I mean singular סמיכות smichus but singular. So בית הלל Beis Hillel
is going to focus on how it's written, not how it's read,
and that would give you one, one, and two. קרנת קרנת קרנות.
karnas, karnas, karnos. So הרי כאן ארבע. harei kan arba. That gives
you four.
שלש למצוה ואחת. shalosh l'mitzvah v'achas. Four, three of them, of the
four, three are a מצוה, mitzvah, meaning the way it should be
done, but one is מעכב. me'akev. So the גמרא Gemara asks the
obvious question, ואימא כולהו למצוה? v'eima kuleihu l'mitzvah? Why not just say
all of them are just the לכתחילה lechatchila מצוה, mitzvah, and nothing
is מעכב? me'akev? As I said, if the תורה Torah doesn't repeat
it, then it's not מעכב. me'akev. So say nothing is מעכב. me'akev.
So the גמרא Gemara says, כפרה בכדי לא אשכחן. kapara b'chidi lo
ashkechan. No, there's no, you don't get a כפרה, kapara, it doesn't
count if you didn't do anything for nothing. Now there's other things
you did, you burnt the entrails, the אימורים, imurim, but the גמרא
Gemara all assumes of course that everything is based on the blood.
So it's impossible that, you know, none of the blood is required
בדיעבד. bedi'avad.
But since we don't have that the תורה Torah repeated it and
all we have is the number four, so we're going to say,
you know, that only one is מעכב. me'akev.
Based on the rule that if the תורה Torah didn't repeat it,
it's not מעכב, me'akev, we'd say nothing is מעכב, me'akev, but that
can't be our conclusion. So we're going to say the minimum, one
is מעכב, me'akev, and the other three are for the מצוה. mitzvah.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ואי בעית אימא היינו
טעמא דבית הלל. v'i ba'it eima hainu ta'ama d'Beit Hillel. So the
גמרא Gemara wasn't so satisfied with that. So here's the reasoning of
בית הלל, Beit Hillel, הני מקרא והני מסורת. hani mikra v'hani masoret.
The we're going to play focus both on how it's read, that's
what in this context מקרא mikra means, and the מסורת masoret of
how it's written. Okay, we're going to look at both of them,
not just one or the other. הני מקרא לטפויי חדא, hani mikra
l'itfuyei chada, the way it's read gives you six, that makes you
add one to the four, והני מסורת לבצורי חדא, v'hani masoret l'vatzurei
chada, but the way it's written is קרנת, קרנת, קרנות, karnat, karnat,
karnot, four, that makes you subtract one from the six. It gets
you to five. Basically what the גמרא Gemara is saying is you
take both and you divide by two. Okay? The way it's read
gets you קרנות, קרנות, קרנות, karnot, karnot, karnot, six. The way it's
written is קרנת, קרנת, קרנות, karnat, karnat, karnot, four.
So so if you have to account for both of them, you
add them together, 10, you divide by two, five. And it basically
tells you that the right number here is five. And once the
right number here is five, we can do similar to what we
did with בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Okay? That now that you have
five, we'll say four is the מצוה mitzvah and one is מעכב.
me'akev. So it's certainly more elegant to say that with five, but
of course it's pretty interesting how we got to the number five.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to say, oh, so there's
other places where we learn numbers based on multiple words, and are
you going to say the same thing, like add the two readings
and divide by two? So let's take a look at that.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, if
you say that, לטטפת, לטטפת, לטוטפת, l'totafot, l'totafot, l'totafot, הרי כאן ארבע.
harei kan arba. So when the תורה Torah says it should be
לטטפת בין עיניך, l'totafot bein einecha, okay, so two of the words
לטטפת l'totafot are written without a ו. vav. So if you read
it the way it's written,
לטטפת, לטטפת, לטוטפת—I l'totafet, l'totafet, l'totafot guess לטטפת, l'totafet, לטטפת—you l'totafet get
four. But if you read it the way that it's read, לטטפת,
לטטפת, לטוטפת, l'totafot, l'totafot, l'totafot, two, two, two, you get six. So
we should say the same thing. Let's add them together, divide by
two, and we'll get five compartments for תפילין. tefillin.
Okay? So should we say הני קרא והני מסורת? hani kra v'hani
masoret?
You both look at the way it's read and the way it's
written, that will lead to the conclusion חמישה בתי בעי למעבד, chamisha
batei ba'ei l'me'avad, that you have to have five compartments for your
תפילין. tefillin. So, and we learn טטפת, טטפת, טטפת, totafet, totafet, totafot,
we learn four. So the גמרא Gemara says, סבר לה כרבי עקיבא.
savar lah k'Rabbi Akiva. That's not a problem. בית הלל Beit Hillel
could hold like רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, דאמר, d'amar, טט בכתפי שתים
פת באפריקי שתים. tat b'Katfi shtayim pat b'Afriki shtayim. The word טוטפת
totafet itself means four, טט tat like tetragram- whatever, anyway
means four, and and פת pat in you know, in this language
כתפי Katfi and פת pat in this language and African, whatever means
two—excuse me, טט tat means, oh yeah, actually טט tat like tetra
is four, so forget what I just said. Anyway he says טט
tat in one language means two, פת pat in another language means
two, and therefore the word טוטפת totafet itself or לטוטפות l'totafot itself
is a word that says four compartments. And we don't do it
by adding the words together. Okay? You'd have to say that according
to בית שמאי Beit Shammai also. So that's how we got out
of that one. But we're not done. אלא מעתה, ela me'ata, says
the גמרא, Gemara, if you say that, בסכת, בסכת, בסכות. basukat, basukat,
basukot. So again, we learn an idea from the fact that it
says בסכות תשבו שבעת ימים basukot tishvu shivat yamim and it says
the word בסכות basukot three times, but very, all this is very
similar, three times, two of which are written without the ו. vav.
So if you read it the way it's written,
excuse me, the way it's written you get בסכת, בסכת, בסכות, basukat,
basukat, basukot, four, which will tell you maybe one for the סכך
sechach and three for the walls. But according to the what you're
going to do now, we should do six and four, because בסכות,
בסכות, בסכות basukot, basukot, basukot is the way it's read, and we
should come with the number five, and that should translate into demanding
more walls than we know is required. So would you say הני
מקרא והני מסורת? hani mikra v'hani masoret? It it, you know, it
it helps, like it contributes, both the way that it's read... and
the way that it's written. So חמישה דפנות בעי למבני chamisha defanot
be'ei lemivnei and now you have to make five walls. I was
subtracting one for the סכך sechach because that's what the גמרא Gemara
said, you know, elsewhere, but anyway, just focusing straight on the walls.
But you ain't, I mean are you going to say five walls?
Even if you say one for the סכך, sechach, are you going
to say four walls? That's not the הלכה halacha for סוכות. Succot.
סוכה Succa three walls is enough. So top, so let's just do
this and we'll end with this for now. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. התם
חד קרא כולה לגופיה. hatam chad kra kuleh legufeh. No, no, no.
Here's how we get out of it. One of the words סוכות
Succot we need just to tell you the basic מצוה. mitzvah. בסוכות
תשבו, basuccot teshvu, you're sitting in a
סוכה. succa. Okay. וחד לסככה ואתאי הלכתא וגרעתה לשלישית ואוקמתה אטפח. vechad
lescacha ve'atai hilchta vegaratah lishlishit ve'okmata atephach.
So now we have one סוכות Succot being used to just for
the פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. So now we're left with
סוכת succat and סוכות, succot, okay? And we're going to read that
סוכות succot and סוכת succat and have four and say one of
those is going to teach you the what do you call it,
one of them is going to teach you סכך, sechach, okay, now
that we have four, and the other three are going to teach
you three walls and of the three walls הלכה למשה מסיני halacha
l'moshe mi'sinai tells us one of the walls suffices to be even
a טפח. tephach. Now, why don't we say the same thing? Why
don't we say let's add both and divide by two? Well you
can't do that because once you're left with, once you use one
word סוכות Succot to tell you just פשט pshat of the פסוקים,
psukim, and you're left with סוכת succat and סוכות, succot, so the
way it's read is four, the way it's written is three. So
you add them together and you divide by two, three and a
half. You know, you know,
you can't deal with a half. And in some degree that even
works nicely. Great, three and a half. One for the סכך sechach
and two and a half for the walls. So that's how the
גמרא Gemara gets out of it. It says the first סוכות Succot
you need for the פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. The question
is, well why not say that about with טוטפות, totafot, you need
the first one for the פשט? pshat?
Or קרנות, karnot, you need the first one for the פשט? pshat?
So תוספות Tosafot asks that question. He points out it's hard to
know exactly when the גמרא Gemara feels that the first one you
need for the פשט pshat and when it feels you can start
counting already with the first one. Okay, but anyway let's just do
one more thing to end this point about adding the words. So
the גמרא Gemara says
אלא מעתה וטמאה שבועים ela me'ata vetame'ah shevu'ayim by a woman who
gives birth to a girl it says she will be טמאה tame'ah
for two weeks. Okay, but it's written without a ו. vav. So
written without a ו vav it would be שבעים, shiv'im, she's טמאה
tame'ah for seventy days. So if we do our same thing, you
have fourteen one way of reading it, seventy the other way, eighty-four
divide by two. אהני קרא ואהני מסורת, ahni kra ve'ahni mesoret, we'll
pay attention both to how it's written and how it's read. ארבעים
ותרתי בעי למיסב. arba'im vetarti be'ei lemesav. So this woman would have
to sit forty-two days. She'd be טמאה tame'ah for forty-two days according
to this methodology. So גמרא Gemara says no. שאני התם דכתיב כנדתה.
shani hatam d'chtiv kenidatah. It says וטמאה שבועים כנדתה, vetame'ah shevu'ayim kenidatah,
like her נדה. niddah. So her נדה niddah is a week. So
the way תוספות Tosafot understands it, it means שבועים, shevu'ayim, she's a
week more than if she gave a boy just like her נדה
niddah period. So כנדתה kenidatah tells us that it means two weeks,
we're counting in weeks and we're not counting seven days. Okay, so
right now we have two ways of understanding. For בית שמאי Beit
Shammai it's six, which divides into four and two. For that's בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. For בית הלל Beit Hillel either it's just a
number four and really we would say בדיעבד bedi'avad you don't need
anything but that's not possible so we wind up saying בדיעבד bedi'avad
one suffices, excuse me
one is מעכב. me'akev. Or we do some, you know, creative math
and get five and that teaches you four plus one. Okay, we
will pick up with this tomorrow.