Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is the last דף
daf of זבחים, Zevachim, ק"כ kuf-chaf 120. We will start with the
very last line of קי"ט עמוד ב', kuf-yud-tet amud bet, and we
are finishing up the משנה mishna that's discussing, you know, the transition
of the מקדש Mikdash from the משכן Mishkan to the מקדש, Mikdash,
גלגל, Gilgal, שילה, Shilo, נוב Nob and גבעון, Gibeon, finally the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and also the different types of things that were
practiced whether you were in a even at the time of the
היתר במות heter bamos by a במה גדולה bama gedola as opposed
to a במה קטנה bama ktana by the sort of central במה
bama even if it didn't have a status of מקדש Mikdash like
נוב Nob and גבעון Gibeon or גלגל Gilgal as opposed to the
במה קטנה, bama ktana, the במה bama in people's backyards, and one
of the whole cases in the משנה mishna is things like the
waving of the, giving of the חזה chazeh and the שוק shok
to the כהן. Kohen. There was no status of the כהן, Kohen,
the waving of the חזה chazeh and שוק shok and so on.
So let's take a look now, last line of קי"ט עמוד ב'.
kuf-yud-tet amud bet. בעי רב זירא, Ba'i Rav Zeira, רב זירא Rav
Zeira asked, עולת במת יחיד שהכניסה לפנים והוציאה לחוץ מהו. olas bamas
yachid she'hechnisa lifnim ve'hotzia lachutz mahu. So if you had an עולה
olah for on a private במה bama and then you went ahead
and you brought it into the area of the במה גדולה, bama
gedola, all right, there's no
איסור issur of something being outside of the environs
because of or of שחיטה shechting it outside because it's a time
of היתר במות, heter bamos, and you went ahead though and you
brought it into the במה גדולה bama gedola and
and then you took it back out, okay, מהו, mahu, what's the
story? מי אמרינן כיון דעייל קטלה מחיצה, Mi amrinan keivan de'ayal katla
mechitza, do we say since you brought it in, the מחיצה mechitza
absorbed it and once it was brought into the environs of the
במה גדולה, bama gedola, it now has the status of an עולה
olah that was offered up on the במה גדולה, bama gedola, או
דילמא כיון דהדר הדר, o dilma keivan de'hadar hadar, or do we
say that no, once you brought it back out, it now just
goes back to the status of a במת יחיד? bamas yachid? Now
the גמרא Gemara doesn't exactly spell out what the נפקא מינה nafka
mina is. If you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says שהכניסה
לפנים אחר ששחטה בחוץ וחזר והוציאה מהו, she'hechnisa lifnim achar she'shachata bachutz
vehazar ve'hotzia mahu, מנהג בדין קדשי במה גדולה ליטען תרומת חזה ושוק.
minhag bedin kodshei bama gedola lit'on terumas chazeh veshok. Okay, whether to
give the חזה chazeh and the שוק shok to the כהן Kohen
and to wave the חזה chazeh and the שוק. shok. The only
problem with that is that the case in the גמרא Gemara is
by an עולה olah and an עולה olah doesn't have a חזה
chazeh and a שוק. shok.
תוספות Tosafot says that we could also be talking about a case
where it wasn't שחט shachted and then brought inside, it was sanctified
for the purpose of a במה קטנה bama ktana
and then it was brought into a במה גדולה, bama gedola, the
environs of a במה גדולה bama gedola and it was שחט shachted
there and then there are a lot of questions about the נפקא
מינה, nafka minas, right, like does it require כהן Kohen and בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehuna and סמיכה semicha and צפון tzafon and all those
other types of issues that are listed in the משנה, mishna, you
know, that apply sort of prior to the actual or שחיטה shechita
or during the קבלת הדם. kabbalas hadam. So for רש"י Rashi it's
not exactly clear. רש"י Rashi focuses in just on a case of
a שלמים. shlamim. Okay, but that's the question. It was sanctified for
a במה קטנה, bama ktana, maybe you
even שחט shachted it
according to רש"י, Rashi, you brought it in the
environs, you
took it
out, וצריך להחזירה לפנים או לא, ve'tzarich lehachazira lifnim o lo,
that if it got that status and the status stuck, you'd have
to then bring it back in. Okay, so this is the question.
It was sanctified for a במה קטנה, bama ktana, maybe you even
שחט shachted it according to רש"י, Rashi, you brought it in the
environs, you took it out, does having brought it in the environs
give it the status of a קרבן korban for במה גדולה bama
gedola for all of what those requirements would be? So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says לאו היינו פלוגתא דרבה ורב יוסף, lav
hainu plugta de'Rabba ve'Rav Yosef, isn't this the debate of רבה Rabba
and רב יוסף? Rav Yosef? דתנן, Detnan, it's in מעילה, Me'ila, קדשי
קדשים ששחטן בדרום מועלין בהן. kodshei kodashim she'shachtan bedarom mo'alin bahen.
If you שחט shacht קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim in the south, right,
they're normally are supposed to be the north, there still is מעילה,
me'ila, it's not as if, you know, you just shot the animal
in the head and it died in a in a way that
would completely take it out of the context of the מקדש Mikdash
context, it still is in the מקדש Mikdash context and therefore there
is still מעילה. me'ila. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara continues,
where were we? Now here there's a whole major question about what
the גרסא girsa is. Some have the גרסא girsa of אם עלו
לא ירדו, im alu lo yerdu, if they were put up on
the מזבח mizbe'ach even though they were שחט shachted in the south,
you would not bring them off the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Let's read it with that. ואיבעיא להו Ve'iba'ya lehu and we asked
the question, ירדו מהו שיעלו? yerdu mahu she'ya'alu?
If you did bring them back down, can you go ahead and
put them up again on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? Once they were שחט
shachted in the south, are they still enough in the environs that
לכתחילה lechatchila you could put them up on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? All
right, there's a whole range of different readings of the... of this
case anyway let's see what's the text that we have here. רבא
Rava אמר amar לא יעלו. lo ya'alu. רבא Rava says you cannot
put them up on the מזבח mizbeach and רב יוסף Rav Yosef
אמר amar יעלו. ya'alu. They can be put up. Now, what does
this have to do with anything? I mean, you know, we've dealt
a lot with פסולים psulim about the מזבח mizbeach and the הלכה
halacha is that if something is פסול, pasul, you know, if it's
פסולו בקודש, psulo b'kodesh, we say if you put it up, you
don't have to take it down, but once it's taken down, you're
not allowed to put it back up.
And how is this really, this seems like it belongs in that
debate. What does it have to do at all with like our
debate? So,
major debate as I said about what the גרסא girsa is. רש"י'ס
Rashi's גרסא girsa is not can you put them on the מזבח,
mizbeach, but if they're on the מזבח, mizbeach, can you take them
off? And then the question is, oh, once they got into the
environs of the מזבח, mizbeach, does that redefine them and now they
cannot be removed? Now again, that sounds like the just whole general
question about, you know, the מזבח מקדש, mizbeach mekadesh, which we had
a whole פרק perek devoted to. What does this exactly have to
deal with this issue? But it seems like there's the analogy has
something to do with the question about location and space. Part of
the problem here was it was in the wrong space, it was
in the south. Now that it's brought into the right space, the
מזבח, mizbeach, maybe that goes ahead and that defines it as belonging
to the מזבח mizbeach and you would not have to take them
down. Again, though, very strange what the comparison is. We've had a
whole פרק perek devoted to this issue of עלו ירדו alu yerdu
or not ירדו. yerdu. But let's just go with it. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. תיבעי לרבא תיבעי לרב יוסף. Tibei
l'Rava tibei l'Rav Yosef. No, you could ask the question and רש"י'ס
Rashi's גרסא girsa was that רבא Rava would say ירדו, yerdu, you
have to bring it down. Okay, so therefore for רבא Rava the
location doesn't redefine it and for רב יוסף Rav Yosef the location
does redefine it. So the גמרא Gemara says תיבעי לרבא תיבעי
לרב יוסף.
tibei l'Rava tibei
l'Rav Yosef. The question no, it's not a direct debate. It could
go either way our question regardless of רבא Rava and רב יוסף.
Rav Yosef. The question could be asked according to either of them.
תיבעי לרבא, Tibei l'Rava, you can ask to רבא Rava who says
again with רש"י'ס Rashi's גרסא girsa ירדו yerdu by the case of
something שחט shechted in the north that goes up to the מזבח.
mizbeach. תיבעי לרבא, Tibei l'Rava,
עד כאן לא קאמר רבא אלא במזבח, ad kan lo ka'amar Rava
ela b'mizbeach, when does רבא Rava say that the מזבח mizbeach does
not redefine the thing's status and allow it to stay there? דחזי
ליה מקדש דלא חזי ליה לא מקדש, d'chazi leh mekadesh d'lo chazi
leh lo mekadesh, because we've had a whole principle, something only something
that's fit for the מזבח mizbeach is sanctified for the מזבח, mizbeach,
not something that isn't, פסולו בקודש psulo b'kodesh and so on, although
again this would seem to be a case of פסולו בקודש. psulo
b'kodesh. But whatever. Okay, but there there's criteria what types of things
are fit for the מזבח, mizbeach, and if it's not fit, the
מזבח mizbeach won't redefine its status. That's for the case of שחט
shechting it in the south. אבל מחיצה
אף על גב דלא חזי ליה קלטה, aval mechitza af al gav
d'lo chazi leh kalta, but we could say that when it comes
to the actual, you know, מחיצה mechitza of the מקדש, Mikdash, even
maybe something there that's not about the מזבח, mizbeach, that's about a
time, you know, the מזבח, mizbeach, some things are really not fit
for the מזבח. mizbeach. Here it's a little bit different. Here it's
the opposite. Here it's the time of היתר במות heter bamot and
things could be brought anywhere. And this is something that was for
a במת יחיד bamah yachid that you chose to bring it into
the במת ציבור. bamah tzibbur. So maybe that redefines it. This isn't
something that's problematic. This is something that's totally fine and you just
brought it into a holier precincts and maybe that redefines it. אבל
מחיצה אף על גב דלא חזי ליה קלטה, aval mechitza af al
gav d'lo chazi leh kalta, again doesn't literally mean לא חזי ליה,
lo chazi leh, but it just means it wasn't sanctified for it,
but it's not something that's fundamentally not fit. You know the way
the גמרא Gemara makes it sound more it's more about somehow מזבח
mizbeach functions different than the מחיצה, mechitza, but I would more emphasize
the idea that this is not something that's fundamentally not fit for
the environs of the במה גדולה. bamah gedolah.
That's according to
רבא. Rava. או דילמא o dilma okay, או דילמא אפילו רב יוסף,
o dilma afilu Rav Yosef, go the other way. Even according to
רב יוסף Rav Yosef who says it gets to stay on the
מזבח, mizbeach, עד כאן לא קאמר רב יוסף התם אלא דחד מקום
הוא. ad kan lo ka'amar Rav Yosef hatam ela d'chad makom hu.
That's only when it's one place. You're basically already in the environs
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so we say if it gets
on the מזבח, mizbeach, it stays on the מזבח. mizbeach. אבל הכא
דתרי מקומות נינהו, aval hacha d'trei mekomot nin-hu, here it's fundamentally two
places. It's חוץ, chutz, it's on your private במה, bamah, or it's
in the environs of the במה גדולה. bamah gedolah.
So לא, lo, okay then maybe in that case no, it would
not get redefined. או דילמא לא שנא o dilma lo shena or
do we say it doesn't make a difference? תיקו. teiku. And the
גמרא Gemara leaves it as a question mark. All right, so as
I said, very difficult גמרא Gemara to know what the גרסא girsa
is, why this is not just exactly all the questions we had
before about מזבח מקדש. mizbeach mekadesh.
But anyway, the גמרא Gemara is saying that the questions of מזבח
מקדש mizbeach mekadesh are not necessarily the same as whether the environs
of the במה גדולה bamah gedolah will redefine something. Now the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
מילתא דפשיטא ליה לרבה בחד גיסא ולרב יוסף בחד גיסא. Milta depshita
leih leRabbah bechad gisa ulerav Yosef bechad gisa. That issue that רבה
Rabbah knew was clear one way and רב יוסף Rav Yosef the
other way about this thing that was shechted in the south, you
know, whether it goes off the מזבח Mizbeach or not or whether
you could put it on the מזבח Mizbeach based on your גרסא,
Girsah, but they had a clear debate, they each one knew exactly
their position. מיבעיא ליה לרב ינאי, Mibaya lei leRav Yannai, that was
actually רב ינאי Rav Yannai had the question which רבה Rabbah and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef came down on different sides of. דבעי רב
ינאי Debaya Rav Yannai because רב ינאי Rav Yannai asked the following
question:
אברי עולת במת יחיד שעלו למזבח וירדו מהו? Evrei olat bamas yachid
shealu lamizbeach veyardu mahu? If you have the limbs of an עולה,
Olah, you know, the limbs, the things that were going to be
burnt on the מזבח, Mizbeach, of a במה Bamah of a, you
know,
of a במה Bamah in your backyard and
you put them on the מזבח Mizbeach of the במה גדולה, Bamah
Gedolah, what is the story? Okay?
וירדו, Veyardu, and then they came down. מהו? Mahu? What's the whole
story? And then again, this is our גרסא Girsah of they came
down, can you put it back up? So that would sort of
seem to be, you know, the similar question by the case of
something shechted in the south, if it came down can you put
it back up? But again, depending on your גרסא Girsah the question
might be are you allowed to put it up? Now רש"י Rashi
here spells out a little bit more what the analogy is to
the case of the south, which is רש"י Rashi says that, you
know, something shechted on a private במה Bamah is considered חוץ למקומו
chutz limkomo of the במה גדולה. Bamah Gedolah. Because even though it's
true, you know, that you are allowed to shecht things for a
במה Bamah for a במת יחיד, bamas yachid, but for the במת
ציבור bamas tzibur itself, the במת ציבור bamas tzibur does have its
environs, right, something shechted in the environs of the במת ציבור bamas
tzibur has to be eaten, something קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim has to
be like, you know, eaten לפנים מן החומה. lifnim min hachomah.
So maybe, you know, there it is easier to understand some degree
the analogy to the case of the south, right? The south of
the מזבח Mizbeach is a fit place for קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim,
not a fit place for קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. You shecht קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim there in the south and then you bring it
to the מזבח Mizbeach which is the fit place for קדשי קדשים.
kodshei kodashim. So somewhat by analogy you have something that you shechted
at a במת יחיד bamas yachid which is an okay place
for קרבנות korbanos for a במת יחיד bamas yachid but not for
a קרבן korban that was brought by a, in, at a במה
גדולה. Bamah Gedolah. Then you brought it into the environs of the
במה גדולה, Bamah Gedolah, here according to this case you put the
limbs on the altar of a במה גדולה, Bamah Gedolah, you know,
is this considered enough to be defined by the space of the
במה גדולה Bamah Gedolah that it gets to stay there? Or do
we say no, from the perspective of the במה גדולה Bamah Gedolah
this was in the wrong place and therefore it would have to
be removed? Okay, so you sort of see the question. Although again
it's still different because here when you shechted it by the במת
יחיד bamas yachid it was totally כשר. kosher. When you shechted the
עולה Olah in the south it was פסול. pasul. But anyway in
both cases it was like the wrong place from the perspective of
the מזבח, Mizbeach, you know, the central מזבח. Mizbeach. Now it's on
the מזבח, Mizbeach, now do you have to remove it or not?
Okay, or can you even if it's on the ground, can you
even put it up? מהו? Mahu?
היכא דלא משלה בהן האור לא תיבעי לך. Heicha delo mashla bahen
haur lo tiba'ei lach. What if the fire has not completely seized
it? Then, you know, that's not a question, presumably that would mean
that again, not clear whether you're talking about bringing it up, putting
it down, but presumably היכא דלא משלה בהן האור heicha delo mashla
bahen haur would be more obvious that it was not yet לחמו
של מזבח lachmo shel mizbeach so you should not restore it or
you should actively bring it down. But כי תיבעי לך היכא דמשלה
בהן האור, ki tiba'ei lach heicha demashla bahen haur, if it caught,
if the fire has already seized it, then that's when we want
to know can it be redefined, can you leave it up on
the מזבח Mizbeach or can you even bring it up? And that's
the question, and that is the question. מה תיקו? ma takei?
And we leave it as a תיקו. takei. All right, so I
have to say as you can already hear from me that I
really struggle to understand how the גמרא Gemara is making all of
these analogies, but be that as it may, the גמרא Gemara wants
to understand when you take something from a במת יחיד bamas yachid
and you put it up on a במה גדולה, Bamah Gedolah, how
much does that במה גדולה Bamah Gedolah redefine it? And that could
go in two ways. One way רש"י Rashi said is to create
new requirements that you have to do the חזה ושוק, chazeh veshok,
you might need כהונה kehunah if you brought the animal in when
it was alive. You could also say it in a different way
which makes it more similar to the מעילה me'ilah case, which is
is this considered now that it's on the on the במה גדולה
Bamah Gedolah as something that was actually from חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo
from the perspective of the במה גדולה Bamah Gedolah and would have
to be removed or not? And that's more similar to the case
of something that was shechted... שחט shechted in the south. Okay, now
we are going to continue. By the way, shouldn't surprise you, there's
a different גרסה girsa in our גמרא Gemara as well about whether
it's talking about the case of whether they're debating the case of
משלה בהן האור mushla bahen ha'or or לא משלה בהן האור. lo
mushla bahen ha'or.
Okay. אתמר. Itmar. Let's try something a little easier now. שחיטת יחיד
לילה בבמת יחיד. Shechitas Yachid Laila b'Bamas Yachid. You שחט shechted it
at night in a private במה. Bama. Forget במת יחיד Bamas Yachid
and a במה גדולה, Bama Gedolah, just a simple question of the
story of a במת יחיד. Bamas Yachid. Is it a problem to
שחט shecht something at night? It doesn't seem to, shouldn't be, like
there seems to be almost no rules, but the key word is
almost, so what's the story about night?
בבמת יחיד. b'Bamas Yachid. רב ושמואל. Rav and Shmuel. It's a debate
of רב ושמואל. Rav and Shmuel. חד אמר כשר וחד אמר פסול.
chad amar kasher ve'chad amar pasul. One says it's כשר, kasher, one
says it's פסול. pasul. וקמיפלגי בדרבי אלעזר ve'kamiflagi b'de'Rabbi Elazar and they
debate they're debating this regarding the statement of רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar.
דרבי אלעזר רמי. de'Rabbi Elazar rami. רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar raised a
contradiction by two פסוקים. psukim. קראי אהדדי. kraya ahaddi. Two פסוקים. psukim.
כתיב. ksiv. It says ויאמר בגדתם. vayomer begadetem. Okay so he says
בגדתם begadetem that you have rebelled. This was a story that they
were running after the פלשתים Plishtim and they had a victory over
the פלשתים Plishtim and it says the people took from the booty
and from the cattle and they slaughtered it ויאכלו על הדם. vayochlu
al hadam. They ate over the blood. Not exactly clear, there's a
prohibition in the תורה, Torah, אל תאכלו על הדם, al tochlu al
hadam, don't eat over the blood. What exactly that means, does it
mean that they sanctified it and you know didn't, well we'll see
from how the גמרא Gemara interprets. Anyway, and שאול Shaul says that
you have rebelled by eating over the blood. בגדתם. begadetem. גולו אלי
היום אבן גדולה. golu elai hayom even gedolah. Roll to me a
big stone that they were going to use actually it seems like
as an altar. Okay and what does it say? וכתיב u-chsiv and
it says ויאמר שאול פוצו בעם. vayomer Shaul putzu ba'am. Spread out
amongst the people ואמרתם להם הגישו אלי איש שורו ואיש שיה ושחטתם
בזה ואכלתם ולא תחטאו להשם לאכול אל הדם. ve'amartem lahem higishu elai
ish shoro ve'ish seyo ushchattem bazeh va'achaltem velo techte'u l'Hashem le'echol el
hadam. Bring to me each person his ox and his sheep ושחטתם
בזה ushchattem bazeh slaughter
it and ואכלתם va'achaltem and you won't sin to God by eating
over the blood. So we'll see exactly what that means, what they
had been doing and what now they're doing correctly. ויגישו כל העם
איש שורו בידו הלילה וישחטו שם vayagishu kol ha'am ish shoro beyado
halailah vayishchatu sham and each brought their ox that
night and they slaughtered it. So what is the problem? The problem
is that initially it says
גולו אלי היום golu elai hayom today presumably with an emphasis that
it has to still be daytime. And then it says that they
did it at night. So what's the story? Okay so let's take
a look.
So that's the question that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar asked and רב
ושמואל Rav and Shmuel debate how to answer it. מר משני כאן
בחולין כאן בקדשים. mar mishani kan b'chullin kan b'kodshim. So one answers
that no what they שחט shechted at night was that they שחט
shechted the non-sanctified stuff you know just to eat what they שחט
shechted during the day was קדשים. kodshim. It was במת יחיד bamas
yachid it's true it's outside of a central במה bamah but they
had to do it during the day because even a במת יחיד
bamas yachid requires daytime.
ומר משני u-mar mishani and the other one answers כאן בקדשי במה
גדולה כאן בקדשי במה קטנה. kan b'kodshei bama gedolah kan b'kodshei bama
ktana. They had sanctified all of the flock some they had sanctified
to bring to the במה גדולה bama gedolah some to the במה
קטנה. bama ktana. So the stuff they did at night was for
the במת יחיד bamas yachid and the stuff they did for the
day although again I don't know exactly where they're bringing it maybe
because they had sanctified it for the במה גדולה bama gedolah even
though at which was the discussion we had before even though they're
now going to be שחט shechting it by a במת יחיד bamas
yachid because they had sanctified it for במה גדולה bama gedolah that
they were מקפיד makpid to do specifically during the day. As to
what eating over the blood means well the גמרא Gemara here doesn't
discuss it but רש"י Rashi on that פסוק pasuk in תנ"ך Tanach
says you know quotes a חז"ל Chazal that basically says that it
means that it was again in this context of קרבנות korbanos that
they eat from it before זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Okay but anyway
the distinction between לילה lailah day and night is a question about
whether you say that's במה קטנה bama ktana במה גדולה bama gedolah
and that you are conceding that במה קטנה bama ktana does not
can be done at night or not only חולין chullin could be
done at night even במה קטנה bama ktana requires day. Okay.
אתמר. itmar. Now it was taught עולת במת יחיד. olath bamas yachid.
Now so that's one debate. Do you need night in a במת
יחיד? bamas yachid? Now another question of what you need in a
במת יחיד. bamas yachid. You have an עולה. olah. רב אמר אין
טעונה הפשט וניתוח. rav amar ein te'una hafshait ve'nituach. You do not
need to if you're bringing you don't need to flay it and
chop it up into limbs you can just put the whole animal
with its skin on right on the fire even in a במת
יחיד. bamas yachid. ורבי יוחנן אמר. ve'Rabbi Yochanan amar. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says טעונה הפשט וניתוח. te'una hafshait ve'nituach. No it needs flaying
and dismembering. וקמיפלגי בדרבי יוסי הגלילי ve'kamiflagi b'de'Rabbi Yose HaGlili they debate
based on the statement of רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili. דתניא
בברייתא. de'tanya b'braisa. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר עולה. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer
olah. עולה שהקריבו ישראל במדבר אין טעונה הפשט וניתוח. olah she'hikrivu Yisrael
b'midbar ein te'una hafshait ve'nituach. Okay the עולה olah that they brought
in the מדבר midbar you know before ויקרא Vayikra when it you
know where all the laws. it's in only פרשת ויקרא parshat Vayikra
where it says that you should flay it and dismember it. So
when they brought the עולה olah beforehand, like at מעמד הר סיני
Ma'amad Har Sinai which we alluded to before, ויגשו שלמים ויזבחו, va-yigshu
shelamim va-yizbechu, ויגשו שלמים va-yigshu shelamim and so on, זבחים פרים לה'
שלמים. zevachim parim la-Hashem shelamim. Anyway, there it was, it did not
have to be dismembered because it wasn't yet commanded, you know, in
אהל מועד Ohel Moed in פרשת ויקרא. parshat Vayikra.
שאין הפשט וניתוח אלא מאהל מועד ואילך. She-ein hafsheit ve-nituach ela me-Ohel
Moed va-eilech. It only was from the time, you know, of פרשת
ויקרא parshat Vayikra was given starting in אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. מר
סבר מאהל מועד ואילך לא שנא בבמה גדולה ולא שנא בבמה קטנה.
Mar savar me-Ohel Moed va-eilech lo shna be-bama gedola ve-lo shna be-bama
ketana. So one opinion, the opinion that says that it has to,
requires flaying and dismemberment says, fine, but once ויקרא Vayikra was given,
that now applies to all קרבנות, korbanot, even קרבנות korbanot of a
במת יחיד. bamat yachid. ומר סבר בבמה גדולה אין בבמה קטנה לא.
U-mar savar be-bama gedola in be-bama ketana lo. No, you know, the
stuff that's given in ויקרא Vayikra is only specifically around קרבנות korbanot
that are in a central place like the משכן. Mishkan. That should
not be assumed to apply to even private קרבנות korbanot in a
case of a במת יחיד. bamat yachid. You know, you could also
say that a במת יחיד bamat yachid the model is pre-מתן תורה,
mattan Torah, is, you know, בני נח, Bnei Noach, you know, and
so on and that's also if this only came after מתן תורה
mattan Torah it should not be assumed to apply to a במת
יחיד. bamat yachid. Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תניא כוותיה דרבי
יוחנן. Tanya kevasei de-Rabbi Yochanan. We taught like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
who says that it does require flaying, that even this new stuff
that's given in ויקרא Vayikra could apply to a case of a
במת יחיד. bamat yachid. What do, what does the ברייתא braisa teach?
דברים שבין במה גדולה לבמה קטנה. Devarim she-bein bama gedola le-bama ketana.
Here are the things that are difference between the private במה bama
and the public במה. bama. קרן, Keren, whether they need for the
horn on the מזבח, mizbeiach, כבש, kevesh, the ramp, יסוד, yesod, the
base, ריבוע, ribu'a, that it has to be a square. בבמה גדולה,
Be-bama gedola, all those apply in a central במה, bama, ואין קרן
ויסוד וכבש וריבוע בבמה קטנה, ve-ein keren ve-yesod ve-kevesh ve-ribu'a be-bama ketana,
not in a minor one. כיור וכנו בבמה גדולה. Kiyyor ve-kanno be-bama
gedola. The need for a washbasin and you know and the base.
That's also central one. ואין כיור וכנו בבמה קטנה, Ve-ein kiyyor ve-kanno
be-bama ketana, not in a private one. By the way, the difference
between all of these is mostly whether it says, you know, it
uses the word like לפני השם lifnei Hashem or something of that
nature. Okay,
בבמה
קטנה. be-bama ketana. חזה ושוק בבמה גדולה ואין חזה ושוק בבמה קטנה.
Chazeh ve-shok be-bama gedola ve-ein chazeh ve-shok be-bama ketana. Same by the
חזה ושוק. chazeh ve-shok. Right there רש"י Rashi emphasizes it says לפני
השם, lifnei Hashem, so that's only by a במה גדולה. bama gedola.
Again, this is an interesting conceptual point. It's not only whether it
was private or public, but the sense of is God's presence there,
is it לפני השם, lifnei Hashem, is a major difference between במה
קטנה bama ketana and
במה גדולה. bama gedola. Okay. דברים ששוו בבמה גדולה ובמה קטנה. Devarim
she-shavsa be-bama gedola u-vama ketana. But here are the things that they
are the same with. שחיטה בבמה גדולה וקטנה. Shchita be-bama gedola ve-ketana.
You have to שחט shecht the קרבן, korban, you can't just strangle
it. הפשט וניתוח בגדולה וקטנה. Hafsheit ve-nituach be-gedola ve-ketana. You have to
flay it and dismember it. So there, exactly, explicitly like רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. דם מתיר ומפגל בגדולה וקטנה. Dam matir u-mifagel be-gedola ve-ketana.
The blood is the thing that it's only the putting of the
blood on the מזבח mizbeiach that allows it to now be the
member, you know, the the the limbs to be burnt for an
עולה olah or the meat to be eaten for other קרבנות. korbanot.
It also has the ability of making the animal פיגול pigul because
you still have an idea of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano by a
במה, bama, even by a במה קטנה. bama ketana. You don't have
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo but you have חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano
וקטנה. ve-ketana. מומים וזמן בגדולה וקטנה. Mumim ve-zman be-gedola ve-ketana. And similarly
blemishes are פסול pasul for both. Again, some of this was in
our משנה Mishnah as well as a time to eat it. If
you're going to have פיגול pigul that also means there's going to
be a time to eat it. Okay, now back to our משנה
Mishnah which a little bit continues the previous discussion. אבל נותר והזמן
והטמא שווים בזה ובזה. Aval nosar ve-hazman ve-hatamei shavim be-zeh u-ve-zeh. The
idea that meat could be considered to be left over and be
נותר notar and have to then be destroyed and can't be eaten,
and a time limit which is similar to נותר notar but also
could refer to aspects of פיגול, pigul, as well as the idea
that טומאה tumah is a problem, that is true for both of
them. Okay, that's a part of the משנה. Mishnah. תנו רבנן מנין
לעשות זמן בבמה קטנה כבמה גדולה? Tano Rabbanan minalan la'asot zman be-bama
ketana ke-bama gedola? How do you know that time should be an
issue by a minor במה, bama, when that's a very reasonable question
because since space is not an issue, it could be in any
place, maybe time shouldn't be an issue. Very reasonable question. So let's
take a look. We'll read the parentheses. אמר תורה לן ישרף פיגול
ישרף, Amar Torah lan yisaref pigul yisaref, מה פיגול פסול בבמה אף
לן פסול בבמה. mah pigul pasul be-bama af lan pasul be-bama. So
you could say look, you know, the same way פיגול pigul is
obviously invalid in a במה, bama, so also something that sleeps over,
לן, lan, is invalid. Of course that sort of begs the question,
how do you know פיגול pigul is a problem until you've determined
that time is an issue on a במה קטנה, bama ketana, you
don't know that פיגול pigul is an issue, which might be why
some people take out that phrase. So anyway, but let's אוכלך לדהו
ochlach le-dehu and now to just continue after the
parentheses, דהא אמר תורה. de-ha amar Torah. You, what do you have,
what are the two basic problems that can happen if you crossover
a boundary as it were? It could be a boundary of time
or a boundary of space. You have to burn something if it
gets sleeps over, if it becomes נותר, notar, if it goes beyond
the time, and you have to burn something if it goes out
of the right precincts. So מה יוצא כשר בבמה, mah yotze kasher
bevama, so the same way by a minor במה bamah there are
no precincts, it could be anywhere, there's no issue of space, אף
לן כשר בבמה, af lan kasher bevama, the same should be true
about sleeping, there should be no issue of time. That is a
very reasonable argument. ולאו קל וחומר היא מעופות—one velav kal vachomer hi
meofot minute, maybe we can make a קל וחומר kal vachomer from
birds in the opposite direction. What's that קל וחומר? kal vachomer? מה
עופות שאין מום פוסל בהן זמן פוסל בהן. mah ofot she'ein mum
posel bahen zman posel bahen. By birds, when you're talking about, let's
say, the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, blemishes aren't a problem, and nevertheless
time is an issue.
Okay. So קדשי במה קטנה שמום פוסל בהן אינו דין שזמן פוסל
בהן? kodshei bamah ketanah shemum posel bahen eino din shezman posel bahen?
So we see from that that time is a bigger concern than
blemishes, at least by birds. So when you're dealing therefore with a
במת יחיד, bamas yachid, so there we know that blemishes are a
problem. So if it's just a universal truth that time is a
bigger deal than blemishes, which we can see from birds, so if
blemishes are going to be a problem by a במה קטנה, bamah
ketanah, then we should certainly say that time is a problem. Of
course, who knows, maybe the bird thing has—maybe the blemish thing has
specifically to do with birds. But that's the argument in the opposite
direction. Okay. מה לעופות שכן אין זר כשר בהן תאמר במה קטנה
שזר כשר בה? mah le'ofot sheken ein zar kasher bahen tomar bamah
ketanah shezar kasher bah? So the גמרא Gemara says no, you can't
prove that because birds,
they have—time might be an issue, but birds are, in a normal
case of the מקדש, Mikdash, have more demands. What are the more
demands by a bird? You need a כהן. kohen. In a
במה, bamah, במת יחיד, bamas yachid, you don't need a כהן. kohen.
So who knows? Maybe all bets are off in a במת יחיד.
bamas yachid. You can't go ahead and prove me something about a
bird in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. We're talking about a במת
יחיד bamas yachid where כהן kohen doesn't matter, space doesn't matter, why
should you think that time matters? Okay. תאמר במה קטנה שזר כשר
בה. tomar bamah ketanah shezar kasher bah. לא יהא זמן פסול. lo
yehei zman pasul. So maybe time is not an issue. תלמוד לומר
זאת תורת זבח השלמים. talmud lomar zos toras zevach hashelamim. This is
the תורה Torah of זבח השלמים zevach hashelamim and there it lists
all the problems of פיגול pigul and time and so on. And
the word תורה Torah is a inclusive word. So to tell you
לעשות זמן בבמה קטנה כזמן בבמה גדולה, laasot zman bevama ketanah kezman
bevama gedolah, that the same way time is an issue by a
במה גדולה, bamah gedolah, it is still an issue by a במה
קטנה. bamah ketanah. So and with that we end the פרק. perek.
הדרן עלך פרק חטאת וסליקא לך מסכת זבחים. hadran alach perek chatas
uslika lach masechet zvachim. And מסכת זבחים, masechet zvachim, it's a pretty,
I don't know if I would say anticlimactic, but it seems like
a pretty mundane thing to end the פרק perek on and the
מסכת masechet on. But maybe what I will say is, that it
speaks in general to the prior—to the greater significance of the sanctity
or of the significance of time over space. You know the קדושה
kedushah of שבת Shabbos
precedes chronologically the קדושה kedushah of the מקדש. Mikdash. You know שבת
Shabbos comes in the six days of creation, מקדש Mikdash only comes
later obviously. And it also is—supersedes, you know, it. You
don't, the תורה Torah consistently juxtaposes שבת Shabbos and מקדש Mikdash to
say that you don't violate שבת Shabbos for the sake of building
the מקדש. Mikdash. And שבת, Shabbos, the קדושה kedushah of time is
accessible to all. The קדושה kedushah of space has limited accessibility.
So it's—there's something maybe nice about saying that here we are ending
this מסכת masechet and talking about a case
where במת יחיד bamas yachid and sort of saying that even in
the case of במת יחיד, bamas yachid, even in times where space
doesn't matter, time still matters. The significance of time is the more
sort of dominant one than that of the קדושה kedushah and the
significance of space. So we will end with that and looking forward
to tomorrow when we start מנחות. Menachot.