Today's דף *Daf* is קט"ו *Kuf Tet Vav*, 115. The end is
nigh. So anyway, and we pick up למ"מ *Lameid Mem* מסייעי *Mesayayei*,
three lines down. So basically you had a pretty what I would
consider radical statement from רב חילקיה *Rav Chilkiya* who said that
if you שחט shacht *shacht* an אשם Asham *asham* on a במה
bama *bama* outside
and it's before its time, so this is not yet fit for
אהל מועד ohel moed *Ohel Moed* if you were to if you
were to bring it like you know in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* לשמו lishmo, *lishmo* you wouldn't be יוצא yotzei *yotzei*,
you שחט shachting *shacht* it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo, *shelo lishmo*, you're
חייב chayav *chayav* for שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz? *shechutei chutz*. Why? Because
his argument is and this is so interesting that right now at
the very end of a מסכת *masechet* we're going back to the
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo *shelo lishmo* ideas at the beginning and introducing
a completely what I think is new idea. Normally we assume that
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo *shelo lishmo* invalidates something but doesn't invalidate it
totally, like okay, you're not יוצא *yotzei* but the קרבן korban, *korban*
is still כשר kasher *kosher*. What he seems to be saying is
that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo. *shelo lishmo* can change to some degree
the identity of the קרבן korban *korban*. So an אשם Asham, *asham*
before its time is invalid. You would assume an אשם שלא לשמו
asham shelo lishmo *asham shelo lishmo* before its time would be worse,
would be would always also be invalid, would be more invalid, but
he says no, an אשם Asham *asham* if you were to שחט
shacht *shacht* this in the בית המקדש שלא לשמו Beis Hamikdash shelo
lishmo? *Beis HaMikdash shelo lishmo* before its time, you would make it
somehow less than not a full אשם Asham? *asham*, I don't know
what you would make it, an עולה Olah. *olah*, a שלמים shelamim.
*shelamim*, who knows what you would make it, and anyway and therefore
it would not be invalid. You wouldn't have to burn it like
a קרבן korban פסול pasul *korban pasul* like you know, it would
still again what would you use it למה עולה Olah. *lemah olah*,
you wouldn't get to burn the meat on the מזבח *mizbeach*, but
anyway, so he doesn't fully sort of spin that out and spell
that out, but somehow you somewhat changed its identity. Can it be
older than the other ones? Is that any do with it or
no? Let's not worry about the age. The before its time here
I mean that we're going to get to that later, but before
its time here is just because you the person who's חייב chayav
*chayav* an אשם Asham, *asham* like you're a נזיר *nazir* whatever the
time hasn't come, okay, right, that would be the reason. So had
it been any other קרבן korban. *korban*, had it not been about
its אשם Asham *asham* identity, right we're not talking about the physical
age of the animal, we're talking specifically because you're not ready yet
to bring it as an אשם Asham, *asham* in terms of what
your status is. And therefore if you שחט shacht *shacht* it outside
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash? *Beis HaMikdash*, if you שחט shacht, *shacht*
it as an אשם Asham *asham* you're going to be פטור patur.
*patur*, if you שחט shachting *shacht* it as something else you make
it the time of the thing, it's not fully an אשם Asham
*asham* and therefore as a different קרבן korban *korban* you could bring
it and therefore somehow you're going to be חייב chayav, *chayav*. So
that's that pretty radical idea. So let's take a look and Rav
Huna challenged it. How does doing it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo. *shelo
lishmo* make it better? Okay, so let's take a look now. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues three lines down, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
all of the evidence is actually going to seem to back up
this statement of רב חילקיה *Rav Chilkiya*. למ"מ מסייעי ליה *Lameid Mem
Mesayayei Leih*, let's try to support רב חילקיה *Rav Chilkiya*'s statement.
So here we're going to have a series of ברייתות braitos *beraitot*
that are going to try to figure out what is included and
excluded in the transgression of שחוטי חוץ shichutei chutz. *shechutei chutz*. יכול
שאני מוציא אף עולה Olah. מחוסרת זמן בבעלים *Yachol she'ani motzi af
olah mechuseret zman be-ba'alim*, maybe I would exclude from your liability a
case of an עולה Olah *olah* that the time has not yet
come, okay, so that would be let's say a woman who's a
יולדת Yoledes, *yoledet* and she's going to be obligated as an עולה
Olah. *olah* when her forty or eighty days are up and she
brings her עולה Olah *olah* before the forty or eighty days. Now
that case you're חייב chayav *chayav* when you do it outside because
even though the time for the obligation of an עולה Olah *olah*
hasn't come, an עולה Olah *olah* is really valid at any time.
So therefore you would be חייב chayav *chayav* before its time has
arrived. So maybe I should פוטר *poter* you. The answer is I'm
not going to פוטר *poter* you. Maybe I should exempt you for
שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz *shechutei chutz* for an עולה ola. *olah* whose
time has not yet come ואשם נזיר ואשם מצורע *ve-asham nazir ve-asham
metzora* or an אשם Asham *asham* presumably whose time has not yet
come, but we'll see about that. תלמוד לומר שור מכל מקום כשב
מכל מקום shor mikol makom kesev mikol makom. *Talmud lomar shor mikol
makom kesev mikol makom* when it says אשר ישחט *asher yishchat* שור
או כשב במחנה
*shor o kesev bamachaneh*, why did it have to say שור או
כשב *shor o kesev*, why didn't it just say אשר ישחט *asher
yishchat*? So that's coming to be more including. So it's including now.
So again, to include an עולה olah *olah* whose time has not
yet come because the woman isn't ready yet to bring it, it's
not day forty or eighty-five, an עולה olah *olah*'s כשר kasher *kosher*
at any time. The חידוש chiddush *chiddush* here is the אשם Asham
*asham*. So what's the case of the אשם Asham *asham* that we're
coming to include?
Because an אשם Asham *asham* whose time hasn't come should be invalid
and you should be פטור patur. *patur*, so why are we saying
you're חייב chayav *chayav*? ואילו חטאת chatas. שיירה *Ve-ilu chatat shiyra* and
the implication is you're חייב chayav, *chayav* for an אשם Asham *asham*,
you'd be exempt for חטאת chatas, *chatat*. So what's the scenario that
you're חייב chayav *chayav* for an אשם Asham *asham* out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and you're exempt for חטאת chatas
*chatat*? במאי עסקינן bemai askinan? *Bemai askinan*, what's the case? אילימא בזמנו
bizmano. *Ilema bizmano*, the time has come, it's time for you as
a נזיר *nazir* or מצורע *metzora* to bring your אשם Asham *asham*
and it's the time to bring a חטאת chatas *chatat*. So if
that's true, מאי איריא אשם Asham אפילו חטאת chatas נמי *mai irya
asham afilu chatat nami*, so then you're חייב chayav, *chayav* for an
אשם Asham *asham* out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*,
you're חייב chayav. *chayav* for a חטאת chatas *chatat* out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. Anyway, why would you even need
a פסוק? pasuk If it's the right time for the קרבן, korban.
of course you're חייב chayav out of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
So obviously we're not talking that it's the right time to bring
these קרבנות. korbanos. Then of course you're חייב chayav and an אשם
Asham isn't special, the same would be true by a חטאת. chatas.
אלא שלא בזמנו, Ela shelo bizmano, it must be that it's not
yet the time. And therefore, what the ברייתא Braisa is telling you
is exactly this point of רב חילקיא, Rav Chilkiya, that if it's
not yet the time for an אשם, Asham you're going to be
חייב, chayav but not yet the time for חטאת, chatas you're going
to be פטור. patur. The only, and presumably because it's שלא לשמו,
shelo lishmo and that makes an אשם Asham considered to be somehow
fit, but a חטאת chatas? not
fit. Okay, ובמאי? ubimai? אילימא לשמו? Eileima lishmo? If it is a
case of לשמו, lishmo, אשם אמאי חייב? Asham amai chayav? Then it
still doesn't work. Why are you חייב chayav for an אשם? Asham.
An אשם לשמו, Asham lishmo, it's not yet the time. Why are
you חייב chayav out of the
בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash. אלא שלא לשמו. Ela shelo lishmo. אלא לאו
שלא לשמו. Ela lav shelo lishmo. So that is a very reasonable
read of the ברייתא. Braisa. It has you're חייב chayav. for an
אשם, Asham not for a חטאת chatas. implicitly. You needed a פסוק
pasuk to tell you you're חייב, chayav so it's not, it can't
be the case of בזמנו. bizmano The only logical case is שלא
בזמנו שלא לשמו. shelo bizmano shelo lishmo. And therefore you're exempt for
a חטאת chatas because שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is פסול pasul, or
whatever and it's שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, and you're חייב chayav. for
an אשם Asham because it must be this idea that שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo makes it a little bit more kosher when it's שלא
בזמנו. shelo bizmano.
Okay, that's a very reasonable read of this ברייתא Braisa supporting רב
חילקיא. Rav Chilkiya. גמרא Gemara says, no. לעולם בזמנו ושלא לשמו. Le'olam
bizmano v'shelo lishmo. No, no, no. We'll say it's talking about בזמנו
bizmano, and it's שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo Now, one minute. So now
if it's, if it were בזמנו ולשמו, bizmano v'lishmo, yes you'd be
חייב, chayav but it wouldn't be a חידוש chiddush that you're חייב.
chayav. Here it's בזמנו, bizmano like then you wouldn't need this ברייתא
Braisa to teach you you're חייב chayav? if it's a case of
a חטאת chatas or an אשם בזמנו. Asham bizmano. But if it's
בזמנו שלא לשמו, bizmano shelo lishmo, what would you think? Let's say
we're talking about not an אשם, Asham let's say we're talking about
a חטאת. chatas. What would you think if you brought a חטאת
chatas when it was the time to bring a חטאת? chatas. Forget
this case of נזיר, אשם, Nazir, Asham, whatever, יולדת, yoledes you're just
ate חלב cheilev and you bring this separate off this חטאת. chatas
It's always the time to bring as soon as you did your
sin. And you שחט shachting it outside the בית המקדש שלא לשמו.
Beis Hamikdash shelo lishmo, Now what's the story if you bring a
חטאת chatas, in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash שלא לשמו? shelo lishmo.
It doesn't count at all. It's פסול, pasul, right? The whole קרבן
korban is פסול, pasul. okay. When you bring it outside the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash. שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo are you חייב chayav for
שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz What do you think?
You got the case? Yeah, look, I mean at some point it
was ראוי. ra'uy. Right, right? So
the point is I'm שחט shacht it out of the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash it's also פסול. psul Okay, so, so that's the חידוש
chiddush here. The חידוש chiddush here is that if you bring, if
you שחט shecht a חטאת שלא לשמו chatas shelo lishmo outside the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash now this is not so פשוט pashut because
you know we've had cases before. What if you שחט shecht it
לשם פיגול, lesheim piggul, נותר, nosar, whatever? You know, what type of
פסול pasul, and so on. Of course, if you think about it,
if you שחט על מנת shacht al menas to be אוכלו חוץ
למקומו ochlo chutz limkomo or something, it's already חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo.
So that's always the funny thing. At this moment it's פסול, pasul,
you're פוסל pasuling it anyway because you're doing it outside. So that's
the point. If you שחט שלא לשמו, shacht shelo lishmo, you're still
going to be חייב chayav, even though after it's שלא לשמו shelo
lishmo it's no longer a kosher קרבן in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash At the moment you were ready, you had it there and
you were bringing the knife to its neck and ready to שחט,
shecht this was ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'uy l'pesach ha'ohel moed. So
the fact that when you did the שחיטה shchita you had a
thought which would have invalidated it, guess what? You're invalidating it anyway
because you're שחט shecht it outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash Okay,
so that's the חידוש chiddush what we're saying of this ברייתא. Braisa.
This ברייתא Braisa is not talking about a case of אשם Asham?
before its time שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and that's why it's ראוי,
ra'uy, that the שלא לשמו shelo lishmo. makes it more fit. No,
no, no. The חידוש chiddush? of this ברייתא Braisa is you're חייב
chayav for an אשם Asham and by the way also a חטאת
שלא לשמו chatas shelo lishmo once it's its time. And don't tell
me that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidated it. No, I mean it
did, but nevertheless you're still חייב chayav because until that moment of
שחיטה shchita this was fit for אהל מועד ohel moed because it
was זמנו. zmano. Okay, so that's the case.
So now wait, so wait, hold on, let me just read one
more sentence to deal with the אשם, חטאת Asham, chatas issue. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no. לעולם בזמנו, Le'olam bizmano, it is the
time. ושלא לשמו. V'shelo lishmo. Now if it's the time, what's the
חידוש? chiddush Of course you're חייב. chayav The חידוש chiddush is you're
שחט shecht it שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo And I might have thought
that invalidated it and I would have thought it invalidated a חטאת
Chatas and I would have thought it invalidated an אשם Asham according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer היא דאמר מקשינן אשם לחטאת. hi d'amar
makshinan Asham l'chatas. Okay, it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says an
אשם Asham is like a חטאת. Chatas. Because our whole question was,
it sounds from this ברייתא Braisa that an אשם Asham you're חייב
chayav and a חטאת Chatas you're פטור. patur, Right? And that pushes
us to say it supports רב חילקיא Rav Chilkiya that an אשם
שלא בזמנו שלא לשמו Asham shelo bizmano shelo lishmo is valid. And
what we're answering now is, we don't mean to single out
אשם Asham in contradistinction from a חטאת. Chatas What we mean to
say is אשם, חטאת Asham, chatas it's the same thing. And this
is a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer approach. It looks at אשם Asham
and חטאת Chatas as one package. So what the ברייתא Braisa is
saying is whether you שחט shecht an עולה שלא בזמנו Olah shelo
bizmano or an אשם Asham? in parentheses, and of course a חטאת,
Chatas. they're all the same thing, בזמנו שלא לשמו. bizmano shelo lishmo.
In all those cases you're going to be
חייב. chayav. Okay רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer היא דאמרינן hi d'amarkinan אשם
לחטאת Asham l'Chatas ותנא תפס v'Tanna tafas we talked about an אשם
Asham but הוא הדין hu hadin it's the same would be true
about the חטאת Chatas. itself. Okay, so this ברייתא Braisa we're going
to do one or two more that are just going to be
like this. So basically what you have here is is עולה שלא
בזמנו, Olah shelo bizmano, right like it's a case of like you
know יולדת yoledes let's say something like that. Okay you're going to
be חייב chayav because actually שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano doesn't matter because
it's always the time of an עולה. olah That was the first
part of the ברייתא Braisa like ignore that but that was the
first part of the ברייתא. Braisa. Okay and then it had a
case of basically אשם asham you're going to be חייב. chayav. So
what was the scenario of אשם asham and you're going to be
חייב? chayav So the first assumption we had was אשם asham and
not a חטאת. Chatas Okay so that the case would be scenario
number one would be שלא בזמנו
שלא לשמו. shelo bizmano shelo lishmo. Okay and in that case the
אשם asham, becomes a little bit like something שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
makes it a little bit like somehow changes its identity, changes its
identity. So even so so it's no longer really שלא בזמנו shelo
bizmano because it's no longer really an אשם asham and therefore you're
going to be חייב chayav whereas had it been a חטאת Chatas
the שלא לשמו shelo lishmo would have made it פסול, pasul right
that's what שלא לשמו shelo lishmo does and therefore you're going to
be פטור. patur That's the way we read it, only an אשם.
asham Okay an אשם asham you're חייב, chayav? a חטאת Chatas you're
פטור, patur I mean חייב chayav means you're חייב chayav but whatever.
Okay that's our first read. Okay when it says אשם asham. you're
חייב chayav it means only an אשם asham not a חטאת Chatas
and the חידוש chiddush? is when are you חייב chayav by an
אשם? asham, If it's בזמנו bizmano. you're obviously חייב. chayav If it's
שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano so it must be שלא בזמנו שלא לשמו
shelo bizmano shelo lishmo which makes you חייב chayav for an אשם
asham? and פטור patur. for a חטאת. Chatas Okay the second read
was that we're talking about בזמנו. bizmano
So of course you're חייב. chayav What's the חידוש? chiddush The חידוש
chiddush is that it's שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo Okay and it's like
and we mean
אשם asham. plus חטאת. chatas Okay and we're going according to רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that says שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidates. And the
חידוש chiddush is that even though שלא לשמו shelo lishmo. should mean
even though שלא לשמו shelo lishmo should normally mean פסול pasul. okay
had you done it inside nevertheless you're going to be חייב chayav.
okay because at the time you were ready to שחט it it
was ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. raui l'petach ohel moed. Alright so what
do we mean when we're saying that an אשם asham. you're חייב
chayav. outside I don't know if this helped at all anyway but
it already looks way too complicated there's got to be a better
way to represent this but anyway what do we mean when we
say you're going to be חייב? chayav One scenario is you're חייב
שלא בזמנו שלא לשמו chayav shelo bizmano shelo lishmo and only an
אשם asham and not a חטאת chatas and why? because the שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo sort of makes it something else so therefore it
doesn't make it fully it's no longer שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano because
it's no longer fully its אשם asham identity and the other approach
is we're talking about בזמנו b'zmano. and then of course you're חייב
chayav but the חידוש chiddush. is שלא לשמו shelo lishmo. and you
might think שלא לשמו shelo lishmo invalidates it but no because we're
talking according to רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that an אשם asham and
a חטאת chatas are basically the same thing okay and nevertheless the
this is about רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer that basically says that they're
the same and שלא לשמו shelo lishmo. invalidates okay and nevertheless you're
going to be חייב chayav because the moment before שחיטה shechita it
was ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. raui l'petach ohel moed. Alright so that's
two different reads of this, yes. So
you're saying you parenthesized the עולה שלא לשמו בזמנו Olah shelo lishmo
bizmano because it's
always yeah because it's always being you might not be חייב chayav
in it now but it's always fit שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano so
it's always an עולה. olah Right because you can bring it for
something else. Exactly. But you know and we'd say the same thing
for an עוף? of? Do we? That what? That you can always
bring a קרבן עוף korban of because usually yeah because the יולדת
yoledes brings a קרבן עוף korban of doesn't she? Does that change
anything? Because it's an עולה. olah. Yeah I don't
see good question. I don't know I'll let me check on that.
Okay so let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara says.
Okay yeah is this חטאת chatas also able to become an עולה
olah. or not? It's it can't right? I mean is that in
comparison to an אשם? asham The אשם asham could become an עולה.
olah. Correct we're actually going to get to that. Okay תא שמע
ta shma
here's another ברייתא Braisa יכול שאני מרבה yakhol she'ani marbe עולה מחוסר
זמן בגופה Olah mechusar zman begufa
so we included an עולה olah, that the time hadn't arrived because
the owner wasn't yet חייב chayav but now we're going to get
to an עולה ola whose time has not arrived because it's too
young it's less than eight days old let's say okay okay so
if less than eight days old you're going to be פטור patur
for that type of an עולה ola obviously it's not ראוי לפתח
אהל מועד. raui l'petach ohel moed. Okay רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon would
say right? Yeah let's not worry about that but that's true. וחטאת
v'Chatas
yeah let's not worry about that but that's true. וחטאת v'Chatas בין
בגופה בין בבעלים bein begufa bein beba'alim and maybe you'll be חייב
chayav, for חטאת chatas. if it's a too early for in because
it's let's say less than eight days old or it's too early
for a חטאת chatas even if it's too early because the time
for the owner to bring it hasn't come. It's like the יולדת
forty days isn't up yet. Okay, תלמוד לומר ואל פתח אהל מועד
לא הביאו כל שאינו ראוי לבוא פתח אהל מועד אין חייבין עליו.
talmud lomar v'el petach ohel moed lo hevio kol she'eino ra'uy lavo
petach ohel moed ein chayavin alav. Okay, no, it's not fit for
אהל מועד Ohel Moed. so you're פטור. patur Now of course we
get the idea less than eight days old. But here the simple
sense if you juxtapose these two ברייתות braitos seems to be a
very strong proof to רב חלקיא Rav Hilkiya because the previous ברייתא
braita said you're חייב chayav for an אשם asham and this ברייתא
braita says you're פטור patur. for a חטאת chatas that the time
has not yet arrived, right? So if you read them juxtaposed, it
sounds like an אשם asham, you're חייב chayav, the time hasn't arrived
and a חטאת chatas you're פטור patur the time hasn't arrived and
it's exactly what רב חלקיא Rav Hilkiya was saying. Okay, but here
again this ברייתא, braita, so it seems to be only a חטאת
chatas. are you exempt when the time has not yet arrived, presumably
an אשם asham you would be חייב. chayav. Okay, so and again
the time here I don't mean less than eight days old, that's
true even in an עולה. ola But when it got to חטאת
chatas it mentioned the time hasn't arrived even because the owners weren't
yet obligated. Okay, and that seems again to be unique to a
חטאת. chatas So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, במאי עסקינן?
bemai askinan? What's the case when we talk about a חטאת chatas?
that the owners are not yet obligated? I'm sorry, I skipped a
line. ואילו אשם שיירי, v'ilu asham shayrei, but it didn't mention an
אשם, asham presumably an אשם asham in this scenario you would be
חייב. chayav, Okay, it's only a חטאת chatas whose owners are not
yet obligated that you're פטור. patur, במאי עסקינן? What's the case? אילימא
לשמו, eileima lishmo, if the case is that you brought it before
its time לשמו, lishmo so אשם נמי ליפטרי, asham nami liftrei, so
an אשם asham also you're exempt. An אשם asham brought before its
time לשמו lishmo is clearly invalid and you're not חייב chayav, when
you do it outside, when you do שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. Okay,
אלא לאו שלא לשמו, ela lav shelo lishmo, it must be we're
talking that even when you do it שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo So
a חטאת chatas before its time, before the owners are
obligated שלא לשמו shelo lishmo, you're פטור patur because for לשמו lishmo.
you'd be פטור, patur it wouldn't be its time, and for שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo. you're פטור patur because you invalidate it. But an
אשם asham שלא לשמו shelo lishmo, you'd be חייב chayav? because you've
changed its identity even before its time. So again, the one ברייתא
braita that says you're חייב chayav says an אשם. asham The ברייתא
braita that says you're פטור patur says a חטאת. chatas It seems
very clear that we're saying that there's this difference between חטאת chatas
and אשם asham. and the only logic is this case of before
its
time שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says אלא לאו שלא לשמו, ela lav shelo lishmo,
you see it's שלא לשמו shelo lishmo before its time and therefore
you're פטור patur. for a חטאת chatas, but you'd be חייב chayav
for an אשם, asham. which is a proof to רב חלקיא. Rav
Hilkiya. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לעולם שלא לשמו, l'olam shelo
lishmo, no, no, no, I will tell you that it's you're right
that it's שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo Okay, so then why is it
only invalidating a
חטאת? chatas Why is it implying why is it implying that you'd
be חייב chayav. for an אשם? asham? So it says no, no,
no, you're also פטור patur, for an אשם. asham רבי אליעזר היא
דמקיש אשם לחטאת, Rabbi Eliezer hi d'makish asham l'chatas, okay, and it's
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who links a חטאת chatas, to an אשם.
asham ותני עיקר וכל שכן טפל, v'tani ikkar v'chol shekein tafel, and
you know what they're both invalid. Okay, yes, it mentions a חטאת
chatas is invalid but it also means an אשם asham is invalid.
So what we have is we have a ברייתא braita that says
an אשם asham you're חייב, chayav okay, and we have another ברייתא
braita that says a חטאת קודם זמנו chatas kodem zemano you are
going to be פטור. patur, So the simplest read of these two
ברייתות braitos is that here you're חייב chayav because it's קודם זמנו
שלא לשמו, kodem zemano shelo lishmo, that changed its identity, but that
doesn't help you with a חטאת chatas, because שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
makes it invalid. And this is קודם זמנו kodem zemano also שלא
לשמו, shelo lishmo, you're פטור, patur and the implication being here that
for an אשם asham, you would be
חייב, chayav the same way the implication here being that for a
חטאת chatas you would be פטור, patur. and the explanation and presumably
that would be a case of קודם זמנו kodem zemano and שלא
לשמו. shelo lishmo. Okay, and that if it's שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo,
קודם זמנו, kodem zemano, okay, קודם זמנו kodem zemano you're going to
be פטור patur? here because it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, ra'uy
l'petach ohel moed, but the אשם asham you're going to be חייב.
chayav Okay, so it very much seems by these two ברייתות braisos
that there's a difference between אשם asham and חטאת, chatas and the
only explanation would be before its time שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo, But
the גמרא Gemara basically says, like it said here, which is a
very weak read, that we really don't mean אשם חייב, asham chayav,
we mean a חטאת chatas plus an אשם asham you're going to
be פטור. patur. Okay, and why are you going to be פטור?
patur, Because it is קודם זמנו שלא לשמו, kodem zemano shelo lishmo,
that you're right about, but שלא לשמו shelo lishmo, doesn't help. שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo actually just means again, it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and the שלא לשמו shelo lishmo even by an אשם, asham whether
it's an אשם asham, and a חטאת, chatas basically invalidates, okay. So,
that's why you are going to be so that's this case. So
this case says an אשם asham you're חייב, chayav this case says
a חטאת chatas you're פטור. patur. Rather than actually say it's a
difference between אשם asham and חטאת, chatas which would be a support
for רב חלקיא, Rav Hilkiya, which clearly the פשט pshat is, we're
actually saying this though, this actually means an אשם asham plus a
חטאת chatas you're חייב, chayav okay, and what's the case of an
אשם asham plus a חטאת chatas you're חייב? chayav, It's going to
be the
case— Since a second before that act it was fit for חול
המועד, chol hamoed, in that case you're actually going to be חייב
chayav. because that was fit a second before you took the knife
to the animal. That's בזמנו. b'zmano, Here what says a חטאת chatas
you're פטור, patur it actually means a חטאת chatas and other קדשים
kodashim you're פטור. patur The same thing as this except this is
שלא בזמנו. shelo b'zmano. Okay? When this is שלא בזמנו shelo b'zmano
and שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo they're both not ראוי לפסח חול המועד
ra'uy l'pesach chol hamoed and therefore you're going to be פטור in
both of those cases. Yes. I know the גמרא Gemara does this
all the time when it gets backed into a corner, but how
often do we really have a סתם stam that goes by a
minority opinion?
Oh, you mean of רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? I don't know who
it is, you know. Yeah. I mean that's often enough. I don't
think that that's, yeah, that's quite often. I don't think it's just,
I don't think that makes it a דוחק dochak by any means.
Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Okay. Now, תא שמע. ta shma. That's
all a very weak answer because the implication of these two ברייתות
braisos is there's a difference between a חטאת chatas and an אשם
asham and we're basically saying one of them says אשם asham, and
means חטאת chatas and one says חטאת chatas and also means אשם.
asham It's very weak. We're radically, we're eliminating the difference that's implicit
in the ברייתא braisa between חטאת chatas. and אשם. asham So here's
going to be a more explicit ברייתא braisa to support רב חלקיה.
Rav Chilkiya. תא שמע. ta shma. כי אתא רב דימי אמר, ki
ata Rav Dimi amar, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael he said, תנא דבי רב לוי, tana d'vei Rav
Levi, we taught from the house of רב לוי, Rav Levi, יכול
שאני מוציא אף עולת מחוסר זמן בבעלים, yachol she'ani motzi af olas
mechusar zman b'va'alim,
maybe I would say that you would be exempt from שחוטי חוץ
shechutei chutz if the עולה ola was not yet the owner's time
had not yet arrived, okay? And again by an עולה ola, it
doesn't matter that the owner's time hadn't arrived because an עולה ola
is always כשר kosher as a קרבן. And maybe I'll also exclude
אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע. asham nazir v'asham metzora. And then it said
no, those you're חייב chayav for. Okay? Meaning אשם נזיר אשם מצורע
asham nazir asham metzora whose also time doesn't, well, we haven't spelled
it out but we're going to get to it in a minute.
But presumably whose time hasn't arrived, maybe I would exempt you. So
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי תלמודא? mai talmuda? And then it quoted
a פסוק pasuk to say you're חייב. chayav So parenthetically we're saying,
I'm skipping the parentheses but the next line is also somewhat parenthetical.
What's the פסוק pasuk that you're חייב chayav for this עולה ola
before its time and the אשם? asham, So אמר רבינא, amar Ravina,
שור מכל מקום כשב מכל מקום. Like we said before, עז מכל
מקום, ez mikol makom, okay? Whatever. Okay.
Now, now, so the גמרא Gemara says, now the point is, again,
we're presuming אשם you're going to be חייב chayav for, חטאת chatas
not. And the only scenario is this case again of שלא בזמנו
שלא לשמו. shelo b'zmano shelo lishmo. Okay? Again אשם yes, חטאת not.
But now the גמרא Gemara says, well why is that again a
proof to רב חלקיה? Rav Chilkiya? We just gave, I mean they
might have been דוחק dochak answers but we just gave these answers.
Nah, it says אשם and it also means חטאת and we're actually
talking about בזמנו, bizmano, etc., etc. Why is this more of a
proof than anything else which was, we got out of even though
it sounds like it's אשם yes and חטאת no? So the גמרא
Gemara says, היי מאי רומיא? hai mai rumya? What is this a
contradiction to? Why, כדי אמרת k'di amras like you can answer like
you did before. כדי אמרת. k'di amras. Exactly.
You know, so the גמרא Gemara says, it's like we said above,
what's the question here? So the גמרא Gemara says no, אמר רב
נחמן משום דרמי דתנא דבי רב לוי אדתני לוי. amar Rav Nachman
mishum d'rami d'tana d'vei Rav Levi ad'tani Levi. So רב לוי Rav
Levi and לוי. Levi. Because here's the reason. Because it's clear that
the מסורה mesorah that רב דימי Rav Dimi had was that this
was talking about אשם שלא לשמו שלא בזמנו. asham shelo lishmo shelo
b'zmano. How do you know that? Because he asked a question that
he said, oh wait, this seems to contradict something else. And from
the question it's implicit that he understood that when we say you're
חייב chayav. for an אשם, we meant חייב שלא בזמנו שלא לשמו.
chayav shelo b'zmano shelo lishmo. Let's see how that question makes that
implicit. Okay? Because here's what לוי Levi taught. אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע
ששחטן שלא לשמן. asham nazir v'asham metzora she'shachtan shelo lishmon. Yeah, שלא
בזמנו שלא
לשמו. shelo b'zmano shelo lishmo. Yeah, yeah. אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע ששחטן
שלא לשמן. asham nazir v'asham metzora she'shachtan shelo lishmon. Now we're not
going to talk about שחוטי חוץ here. In the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and you שחט like I said, this is the real חידוש.
chiddush The real חידוש chiddush here isn't about שחוטי חוץ. The real
חידוש is what's its status in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash? In
the בית המקדש you שחט an אשם נזיר asham nazir and an
אשם מצורע שלא לשמן, asham metzora shelo lishmon, כשרים ולא עלו לבעלים
לשום חובה. ksherim v'lo alu l'ba'alim l'shum chova. Okay, if you שחט
them it's still כשר kosher. even though it's not לשמן. lishmon. And
presumably yes, but presumably, okay,
שחטן מחוסר זמן בבעלים. shachtan mechusar zman b'va'alim.
Now if you שחט them when it is before the owner's time
had arrived,
או שהיו בני שתי שנים, o she'hayu b'nei shtei shanim, there you
go Michael, or the animals are two years old as opposed to
too young, ושחטן v'shachtan and you
שחט them, פסולים psulim they're פסול. pasul.
So he said wait, these ברייתות seem to contradict. Why? Because this
ברייתא braisa seems to say that when it's שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano,
right, when it's שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, an אשם is פסול. pasul,
You can't make an אשם כשר kosher. שלא בזמנו. shelo bizmano. That's
what this second ברייתא braita said. The earlier ברייתא braita that said
you're חייב for an אשם out of the בית המקדש makes it
sound like שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano it's כשר. kosher Okay? So this
ברייתא braita sounds שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano it's פסול, pasul that ברייתא
braita sounds like שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano it's כשר. kosher And he
answered, and what was his answer? ומשני, Umeshani, and his answer was
Rav Dimi, לא קשיא כאן לשמו כאן שלא לשמו. lo kashya kan
lishmo kan shelo lishmo. No, this ברייתא braita that says שלא בזמנו
shelo bizmano it's פסול pasul. is when you did it לשמו. lishmo,
The ברייתא braita of שחוטי חוץ that said שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano
is כשר kosher and you're חייב is when you did it שלא
לשמו. shelo lishmo. Okay, so basically Rav Dimi came back and he
had a ברייתא braita that said just like this. That said that
an אשם you're going to be חייב for. That was Rav Dimi's
ברייתא. braita. So he said alright, that doesn't prove anything, maybe we're
talking about like בזמנו, bizmano who knows what we're talking about, maybe
we mean אשם והוא הדין חטאת. asham vehu hadin chatas. But we
said no, from the question he asked, he said wait, if this
says חייב, his question said that implies that שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano
is כשר kosher. for an אשם, okay, because otherwise you wouldn't be
חייב. And he said we've got another ברייתא braita that says אשם
שלא בזמנו בבעלים asham shelo bizmano bebealim we said was פסול. pasul.
Which is number two over there. Right, right. So we said so
wait a minute, how could you be חייב when it's בחוץ, bachutz,
okay, which means that it's כשר kosher שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, if
this says that when you do it שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano in
the בית המקדש it's פסול. pasul And his answer was, this is
לשמו, lishmo so לשמו lishmo in שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano is פסול
pasul, because it's not yet the time, and this where you're חייב
outside is שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo which is what we thought all
along, that שלא לשמו שלא בזמנו shelo lishmo shelo bizmano is going
to be כשר. kosher, So the fact that yes, if you just
had this you could've given some דחוי dachui answer that we're talking
about בזמנו and it's the same with a חטאת whatever. But the
fact that he says this implication that שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano was
כשר kosher, contradicts this statement that שלא בזמנו shelo bizmano is פסול,
pasul, and the difference is when it's לשמו lishmo and שלא לשמו,
shelo lishmo shows that his understanding of this ברייתא braita was the
simple reading we had before. Was that when it says an אשם
you're חייב בחוץ, chayav bachutz, it's a case of שלא בזמנו shelo
bizmano and שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo and somehow the שלא לשמו shelo
lishmo actually makes it more valid. And therefore the same way if
it was שלא לשמו shelo lishmo inside the בית המקדש it wouldn't
be פסול, pasul, even though when it's לשמו lishmo before its time
it is פסול, pasul if it was שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it
would be כשר, kosher. you wouldn't be יוצא but it would be
כשר, kosher. that's why you're going to be חייב outside as well.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Alright, don't worry, the עמוד ב amud beis here gets a lot
easier. Okay, I know, okay so now, Rav Ashi, okay, Rav Ashi
רמי מתניתין אברייתא rami masnisin abraita ומשני כאן לשמו וכאן שלא לשמו.
umeshani kan lishmo vekan shelo lishmo. Okay so now Rav Ashi did
basically the same thing. He said our משנה Mishna says that by
an אשם you're going to be פטור when it's בחוץ, bachutz, and
the ברייתא braita we quoted here says an אשם you're going to
be חייב בחוץ, chayav bachutz, and he gave the same answer. Not
זמנו zmano and לא זמנו lo zmano but לשמו and שלא לשמו.
shelo lishmo. So all this evidence supports רב חלקיה. Rav Chilkiya. And
this is like I said shocking, like we went a hundred דפים
dapim and now we're finding out that שלא לשמו shelo lishmo, can
make something actually a different type of an identity and even more
כשר. kosher Okay, and that this אשם which its time is not
yet arrived, when you do it שלא לשמו you make it something
of a different קרבן and more כשר. kosher. And therefore you're, it's
more כשר kosher in the בית המקדש and you're חייב outside. So
now the גמרא Gemara says okay all this evidence is against Rav
Huna who rejected all of this. לימא תיהוי תיובתא דרב הונא, Leima
tehe tuvta deRav Huna, this should be a contradiction to Rav Huna
because Rav Huna said wait שלא לשמו doesn't make it more כשר.
And here all the evidence is that שלא לשמו makes it more
כשר and you'd be חייב. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר לך
רב הונא, amar lach Rav Huna, Rav Huna can say to you
הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan what are we talking about? כגון
שהפריש שתי אשמות לאחריות. Kegon shehifrash shtei ashamot leachrayot. Here you go
David, your case. It's a case where actually Rav Huna admits there
is a case that שלא לשמו can make it better. What's Rav
Huna's case that שלא לשמו can make it better? From the very
outset, it's not like I had my one אשם and it's before
my time. Then he says if this is פסול pasul it's going
to be even more פסול שלא לשמו. I start by separating out
two animals, and I say one of these is going to be
the אשם, the other is a backup in case I lose it.
Okay, and I separate both of them out. Now I'm separating both
of them out, that means that inevitably one is going to be
an אשם and the other is going to be, David, an עולה.
ola Because if you separate out an אשם as a backup, okay,
and you know, and then you use one, the other one it
becomes like נתכפר באחר niskaper beacher by an אשם, it means the
other one becomes an עולה. ola... So since
you can't do this by חטאת. You can't do this by חטאת
because then it's מיתה. misa. But so one of these inevitably is
going to be an עולה. ola And in that scenario when it's
before זמנו zmano and I do it שלא לשמו, I've designated this
one as the עולה, ola okay, because That yes, אין הכי נמי
*ein hachi nami*, that's where it's not necessarily an אשם *asham*, one
is going to be an עולה olah *olah*, so your שלא לשמו
*shelo lishmo* makes it an עולה olah *olah* and that's why you're
going to be חייב *chayav*. Okay, דחד מינייהו מעיקרא עולה olah היא
*d'chad mineihu meikara olah hi*, one of them inevitably is going to
be an עולה olah *olah*, כדרב הונא *k'd'Rav Huna*, top of עמוד
ב׳ *amud beis*, like רב הונא Rav Huna *Rav Huna* says, אמר
רב דאמר רב הונא Rav Huna אמר רב *amar Rav d'amar Rav
Huna amar Rav*, אשם שניתק לרעייה *asham shenitak lireiah*, if you have
an אשם *asham* separated off for grazing because it can't be brought
for its own reason because another one was brought, ושחטו סתם *v'sh'chato
stam*, and you slaughtered it without once it was clear that it
wasn't going to be the אשם *asham* because the other one was,
then even if you slaughtered it סתם *stam*, כשר לעולה *kasher l'olah*,
it's kosher for an עולה olah, *olah*. So here, even though both
animals are still around and it's קודם זמנו *kodem zemano*, since one
will be an עולה olah *olah*, if you slaughtered it לשם עולה
olah *l'shem olah*, you've made it an עולה olah? *olah* and therefore
you made it kosher in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* and you're
חייב *chayav* outside the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. Okay, so that was
all very complicated about but there's a tremendous חידוש *chiddush* that אשם
קודם זמנו שלא לשמו *asham kodem zemano shelo lishmo* is actually כשר
*kasher*. Yes. Is the reason the חטאת *chata'as* can't become עולה olah.
*olah* because it has to be specific to the sin? No, it's
because there's a הלכה halacha. *halacha* that if a חטאת *chata'as* can't
be used, it's a חטאת המתה *chata'as hameisah*, so it has to
die, basically. Yeah. But actually I shouldn't rush to say that because
the case of when you לכתחילה הפרשתיהם לאחריות *l'chatchilah hifrash'tehem l'achrayus* is
actually could be different even by a חטאת *chata'as*. So it might
actually be when you from the very outset, I have to double
check from the very outset you designate both of them, that even
by a חטאת *chata'as* you might actually it might actually be possible,
this scenario. But you're right, all the evidence before sounded like just
an אשם *asham*, not a חטאת *chata'as*. So I have to check.
I think it might be debated. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. Now we finally get to move on to
a different point of the משנה Mishna, *Mishnah*. המעלה מבשר חטאת *ham'aleh
mibesar chata'as*, so now it says that we've talked about before, that
if you burn stuff on the altar that is not normally burned,
you're going to be פטור *patur* as העלאת חוץ *ha'alas chutz*. So
the meat that's normally eaten or the מנחה *mincha* that's normally eaten,
if you burn it on an altar outside the בית המקדש *Beis
Hamikdash*, you're פטור *patur* because that's not what you would do in
אהל מועד Ohel Moed. *Ohel Moed*. Okay, תנו רבנן *tanu rabanan*, מנין
למעלה מבשר חטאת *minayin lam'aleh mibesar chata'as*, how do I know that
if you put up on the fire outside of the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash* the meat of a חטאת *chata'as*, ומבשר אשם *v'mibesar asham*,
or the אשם *asham*, ומבשר קדשי קדשים *v'mibesar kodshei kodashim*. It's funny,
what's קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim*? That's not a חטאת *chata'as* and an
אשם *asham*. I guess it's זבחי שלמי ציבור *zivchei shalmei tzibur* or
something. Okay. ומבשר קדשים קלים *v'mibesar kodashim kalim*, the meat of קדשים
קלים *kodashim kalim*, וממותר העומר *v'mimosar ha'omer*, leftover from the עומר *omer*,
which is like leftover of מנחה *mincha* that be eaten, ושתי הלחם
*v'shetei halechem*, ולחם הפנים *v'lechem hapanim*, all these things which should be
eaten, ושירי מנחה *v'shiyarei mincha*, or just normal מנחה *mincha* that be
eaten, שפטור *shepotur*, how do I know you're פטור *patur* if you
burn it outside the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* on an altar? תלמוד
לומר עולה olah *talmud lomar olah*. It says, right, it says what's
the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*? It says אשר יעלה עלה או זבח ואל
פתח אהל מועד Ohel Moed. לא הביאו *asher ya'aleh olah o zavach
v'el pesach ohel moed lo hevi'o*. So מה עולה olah, שראויה להעלאה
*mah olah sh'reuyah l'ha'alah*,
the same way an עולה *olah* is a type of a thing
that in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* you burn on the fire,
אף כל שראוי להעלאה *af kol sh'rauy l'ha'alah*, anything that you would
normally burn on the fire in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* is
exposed to these. מנין... so that's in terms of burning the wrong
thing. Now how do I know about different types of activities that
are also temple rituals, you know, קרבן *korban* rituals? How do I
know that those you're also פטור *patur* for, that it's only שחיטה
*shchita* and העלאה *ha'alah* and we've also included זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam*.
And by the way, I'll just remind you what we've also included
is like הקטרה *haktara* of the קטרת *ketores*, which is sort of
like העלאה *ha'alah*, burning something on a fire, but also we've talked
about like יציקה *yetzika*, right, like pouring a
libation? No, יציקה *yetzika* here is I didn't mean יציקה *yetzika*, I
mean what do I call ניסוך *nisuch*. יציקה *yetzika* is pouring the
oil onto the מנחה *mincha*. Okay, but you are חייב *chayav* if
you do ניסוך היין *nisuch hayayin*. So you're חייב *chayav* for a
broader scope of עבודה avoda, *avoda*. Yeah, but no, you don't burn
it, you just pour it on the altar, it doesn't burn, it
goes down like the whatever. You mean it gets consumed so to
speak? All right, fine. But how do you know to include certain
עבודות *avodos* that aren't in the תורה Torah *Torah* and others to
exclude? So we're going to now discuss that. מנין שאף היוצק *minayin
she'af hayotzek*, pouring of the oil on the מנחה *mincha*, והבולל *v'habolel*
and mixing it, והפוטת *v'hapotes* and breaking it up after it was
baked into pieces, והמולח *v'hamole'ach* putting salt on a קרבן *korban*, והמניף
*v'hamenif* waving like the pieces of the קרבן *korban*, והמגיש *v'hamagish* touching
it to the altar by מנחה *mincha*, והמסדר השלחן *v'hamesader hashulchan* putting
the bread on the שלחן *shulchan*, והמטיב את המנורות *v'hametiv es hamenoros*
and cleaning out the מנורה *menorah*, והקומץ *v'hakometz* taking the קומץ *kometz*,
which actually is interesting because that's the most like שחיטה *shchita*, והמקבל
בחוץ *v'hamekabel bachutz* and if you catch the blood, if you do
any of those things outside שפטור *shepotur*, you're פטור *patur*. All of
these are עבודות *avodos*. How do I know you're פטור *patur*? תלמוד
לומר אשר יעלה עלה או זבח *talmud lomar asher ya'aleh olah o
zavach*. מה העולה שגמר עבודה avoda. *mah ha'olah sheg'mar avodah*, because it
has to be like העלאה *ha'alah*, like the burning, which means that
it's the end of a process, or it's the entire process. It's
not a stage in an earlier stage in a process. אף כל
שגמר עבודה avoda. *af kol sheg'mar avodah*. All of these things are
earlier stages in a process, as opposed to זריקת הדם *zrikas hadam*,
which is not the earlier stage of a process, that's the end
of a process, so you're חייב *chayav*, or the ניסוך *nisuch*, right,
that's also the end of a process, or you know, it's not
a middle stage. But the rest of these are middle stage. Now
of course שחיטה *shchita* is also a middle stage if you think
about it that way, you know, but nevertheless that's explicit in the
פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. Okay, something like קמיצה *kmitzah* which is similar to
שחיטה *shchita* isn't explicit in the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk*. So basically, when
we're going to include things that aren't explicit in the פסוקים, pesukim
they're going to be things that are not middle stages.
Fine. Now we get to what I consider to be a really
fun part, which is the whole question about the history of, you
know, of when were במות bamot permitted, when were they forbidden. Okay,
עד שלא הוקם המשכן, ad shelo hukam hamishkan, before the המשכן hamishkan
was erected, says the משנה, Mishna the עבודה, avoda. before we get
to במות, bamos, we're going to ask about who got to do
the עבודה. avoda. So the משנה Mishna says until the המשכן hamishkan
was erected it was the בכור, bechor, the firstborn that got to
do the עבודה. avoda Now, where do we get this idea? I
mean, okay, you could have implicitly from earlier narratives in the תורה
you get the idea that a בכור bechor has a special status.
But where do you get this idea, you know,
that Christians still have it, the Catholic Church, you know, the idea
that they used to have their firstborn go off and be the
priests or whatever. But where do you get—but where do you—but where
do you see in the פסוקים pesukim: that the idea that I
mean, no, בכור bechor died in מצרים, Mitzrayim, but where do you
see that they had this idea of being like כהנים, kohanim, right?
So we're actually going to get it, it seems from the פסוק
pasuk, by הר סיני Har Sinai where it says, וישלח את נערי
בני ישראל Vayishlach et na'arei Bnei Yisrael ויזבחו זבחים שלמים להשם פרים.
vayizbechu zevachim shelamim l'Hashem parim. Now נערי na'arei doesn't mean that they
were the בכור bechor either. But obviously, again, there was this very
powerful idea that, you know, בכור bechor had this elevated status. So
that's going to be the assumption that until the time when, you
know, the המשכן hamishkan was erected, אהרן Aharon and his sons, right,
you went through the whole process of anointing them and whatever, the
same way you anointed the המשכן, hamishkan, that's when the כהנים kohanim
were chosen and that's when they had their status. But until that
moment of, like, the first day of ניסן Nissan of when the
המשכן hamishkan was put up, until that moment the בכור bechor were
doing the עבודה. avoda That's what the משנה Mishna, claims. Let's take
a look if that's really agreed upon by everyone, because let's take
a look at this story. Okay, עד שלא הוקם
המשכן. ad shelo hukam hamishkan. So יתיב רב הונא בר רב קטינא,
yativ Rav Huna bar Rav Ketina, רב הונא Rav Huna, the son
of רב קטינא Rav Ketina was sitting קמיה דרב חסדא kamei d'Rav
Chisda in the front of רב חסדא Rav Chisda וקא קרי. v'ka
kari. Now, it's a question between רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot who
was reading this פסוק, pasuk, but it sounds like רב הונא Rav
Huna, was reading the פסוק. pasuk וישלח את נערי בני ישראל, Vayishlach
et na'arei Bnei Yisrael, he sent the נערי בני ישראל na'arei Bnei
Yisrael and they brought sacrifices. אמר ליה, amar lei, so we'll read
it תוספות's Tosafot way, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רב
הונא, הכי אמר רב אסי ופסקו. hachi amar Rav Assi upasku. But
after this they stopped doing it. Yes, at הר סיני Har Sinai
the בכור bechor brought it, but after הר סיני Har Sinai they
didn't. Now, it sounds like that's our משנה, Mishna. but not exactly,
because there was a gap from הר סיני, Har Sinai, which was,
you know, which was what, you know, whatever it was, it was,
right, you know, סיון Sivan until, you know, a good almost a
year until the המשכן hamishkan was put up. So to say they
stopped means that only at הר סיני, Har Sinai, but that there
was a good ten months where it was no longer the בכור,
bechor, it already shifted to the כהנים. kohanim. So that's different from
our משנה. Mishna Okay, now by the way, רש"י Rashi has another
version of this. It's not ופסקו, upasku, they stopped bringing after הר
סיני, Har Sinai, but it's ופסקי. upaskei. He had him, like, end
the פסוק, pasuk, you know, he had him, like, interrupt the פסוק,
meaning it's וישלח את נערי בני ישראל Vayishlach et na'arei Bnei Yisrael
period. Okay, he sent the נערי בני ישראל na'arei Bnei Yisrael to,
I don't know, fetch the animals. And then it's ויזבחו זבחים שלמים
להשם פרים Vayizbechu zevachim shelamim l'Hashem parim is not going on נערי
בני ישראל. na'arei Bnei Yisrael. Meaning put like a big period. So
who did it? The כהנים? kohanim? Yeah, the כהנים kohanim were doing
it, even then. Right, that's right, exactly. That's another way of reading
it. So one way either reads: I'll concede at הר סיני Har
Sinai was the בכור bechor but after that it was different even
before המשכן. hamishkan. Or: No, even at הר סיני, Har Sinai, the
נערים ne'arim were not the ones who were bringing the קרבנות. korbanot.
He sent them to go assist, but they weren't the ones bringing
the קרבנות. korbanot. Now, סבר לאותביה ממתניתין, savar l'otveih mimatnitin, so whoever
was the one who said, like, maybe function as like לויים Leviim
or something? Yeah, I guess, right. So he said: Wait a minute,
how can you say that? Our משנה Mishna says that until the
המשכן, hamishkan, it was the firstborn, not—it didn't end at הר סיני.
Har Sinai. שמעיה דאמר משמיה דרב אדא בר אהבה, shameih d'amar mishmeih
d'Rav Adda bar Ahava, before he got a chance to ask him
that the משנה Mishna. contradicts this, he, the other one said—it's a
little unclear who's saying what—the other one says another statement which also
seems to go against, you know, our משנה. Mishna Because what? He
said another thing in the name of רב אדא בר אהבה Rav
Adda bar Ahava in addition to the idea that it switched at
הר סיני. Har Sinai. He said the following: עולה שהקריבו ישראל במדבר,
Ola shehikrivu Yisrael bamidbar, the עולה that they brought at the foot
of הר סיני—okay, Har Sinai now by the way, it's worth noting
that it's very interesting when it speaks about bringing the קרבן תמיד,
korban tamid, right, because it says what does it say by the
קרבן תמיד? korban tamid? העשויה בהר סיני. Ha'asuya b'Har Sinai. So somehow
there's some idea which is not clear in the
פסוקים: ויזבחו זבחים פרים להשם, Vayizbechu zevachim parim l'Hashem, מה פסוק mah
pasuk Michael?
Right, ויעלו עולות. Vaya'alu olot. Thank you. ויזבחו זבחים שלמים להשם פרים.
Vayizbechu zevachim shelamim l'Hashem parim. So there are עולות, olot, but somehow
the fact that עולה is identified with העשויה בהר סיני Ha'asuya b'Har
Sinai is fascinating and presumably it's this פסוק, although anyway. So רש"י—so
Rashi therefore, those עולות olot that they brought at הר סיני, Har
Sinai, so אינה טעונה הפשט וניתוח. eina teuna hafshat v'nituach. The laws
of עולה did not yet fully apply to it. They didn't have
to flay it and chop it up. I mean, they put the
whole carcass on the fire. Like they did in the בית המקדש?
I mean, it would still be okay, right?
Maybe, but anyway, but that's—we're not questioning about בדיעבד. bediavad. We're questioning,
like, the הלכה. halakha. the detailed הלכות halakhas of עולה didn't apply
to it. That only came—where does it say you flay it and
you cut it up? At the beginning of ויקרא. Vayikra. So that
only began... what? That only began once the משכן Mishkan was put
up. At הר סיני, Har Sinai, okay, those details didn't apply and
they just put the whole thing up. So now what you have
is, you've got these two statements, both of which by the way
are pointing in different directions. One statement seems to say that the
כהנים Kohanim thing started right away, okay, right, doesn't want to accept
the... and the other says, but the details of the עולה, that
didn't start right away. Those are the two statements that are being
made. Got it? Okay. Our משנה says until the משכן Mishkan it
was the בכור. Bechor. Here he's saying no, no, no, right after
הר סיני Har Sinai we started immediately with the כהנים. Kohanim. But
by the way, here's another הלכה. halakha Even though the כהנים Kohanim
thing started right away, the details of the עולה didn't start until
הר Har until until the משכן. Mishkan. Okay. So then he said,
אותביה ברייתא, osvei baraysa, so he challenged these two statements from a
ברייתא baraysa דשויה בכולהו, de-shavya be-khulu, that this ברייתא baraysa equally challenges
both of these statements. Okay. The statement that כהנים Kohanim started right
after הר סיני Har Sinai and that the details of an עולה
only started at the time of the משכן. Mishkan. Here's the ברייתא
baraysa that challenges both of those. Okay.
דתניא, de-tanya, we learned a ברייתא. baraysa. עד שלא הוקם המשכן, ad
shelo hukam ha-mishkan, before the משכן Mishkan had been put was put
up, הבמות מותרות, ha-bamot mutarot, you could bring on your private altars,
ועבודה בבכורות. ve-avoda bi-vchorot. So all the way even from הר סיני
Har Sinai all the way till the next ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh
Chodesh Nissan, you could still do it was the firstborn who would
do the עבודה. avoda Okay. Which by the way,
does that mean even on your private altar you had to get
your firstborn son to do it, right? Or does this mean no,
like if you're doing it in some central location, you know, you're
getting the בכורות bechorot to do it, you know, some communal thing
you're getting the בכורות bechorot to do it? Because now because the
הלכה halakha is, the הלכה is that on a במה bama when
it's a time of היתר במות, heter bamot, you don't need a
כהן. Kohen. So presumably in the there also before the משכן Mishkan
in your private backyard במה bama. everybody could bring their own קרבן.
But some type of a communal עבודה avoda that would be the
firstborn. Okay. והכל כשירים להקריב. ve-hakol k'sherim le-hakriv. Doesn't mean all people,
it means all animals, you could bring all things for קרבנות. korbanot.
בהמה חיה ועוף, behema chaya ve-of, זכר ונקבה, zachar u-nekeva, you know,
it was all types of בהמה behema and חיה chaya and עוף,
of, so you could bring a deer, okay, you could bring a
what's another type of חיה, chaya, a buffalo or something like that,
we talked about the other day, well that was a בהמה behema
we decided. Okay. Anyway, males and females, תמימים ובעלי מומים, temimim u-va'alei
mumim, even if they had a blemish. טהורים אבל לא טמאים, tehorim
aval lo tmei'im, but they had to be kosher animals, you couldn't
bring a non-kosher animal. והכל קרבו עולות, ve-hakol kirvu olot, and everything
was brought as an עולה as opposed to as other types of
קרבנות. korbanot. That's what it sounds like it's saying. We're going to
question that later because the פסוק says by הר סיני Har Sinai
שלמים. So we're going to question that. Okay. The עולה... so number
one is the עבודה avoda was with the firstborn until... so it
sounds so far it sounds like all the details don't apply yet
until the משכן. Mishkan. The עבודה avoda was with the firstborn, you
can bring any animals, but ironically the one details that do apply
even at this early stage is ועולה שהקריבו ישראל במדבר טעונה הפשט
וניתוח, ve-ola she-hikrivu Yisrael ba-midbar te'una hefshet ve-nituach,
but the one detail that did apply is you have to flay
the עולה and chop it up. When we say במדבר ba-midbar we
mean before the משכן. Mishkan. Yeah, exactly, exactly,
yes, that's correct, you know, you could say otherwise but yes, that
is correct. Okay. So now one minute right.
Yeah,
רש"י Rashi says קודם מתן תורה, kodem matan torah, right. Okay. ונכרים
בזמן הזה, ve-nochrim bi-zman ha-zeh, by the way, another interesting parenthetical part
of this ברייתא baraysa is non-Jews
nowadays רשאים לעשות כן, rasha'in la'asot ken, there's no איסור במות issur
bamot for non-Jews, so if a non-Jew wants to go ahead and
bring a קרבן like before to God, that's totally acceptable on their
private במה. Anyway, so what do you have? Right? So it's very
it's fascinating that I think like this issue about the details of
an עולה is like the odd man out. Okay? Because this ברייתא
baraysa basically says, okay, what do we have? We have here's this
period, here's הר סיני, Har Sinai, okay, and then here's the משכן,
Mishkan, okay, right? And this is like I don't know ו' סיון
vav Sivan or whatever it is and this is וישלח נערי בני
ישראל. va-yishlach na'arei bnei Yisrael. Well it'd be beforehand too, right? Even
before הר סיני. Har Sinai. נערי, na'arei, right. Yeah, yeah, okay. Anyway,
correct. Anyway, so the first ברייתא baraysa basically says from this point
on you had בכורות, bechorot,
the עבודה was with the בכורות, bechorot, right? You had all animals,
all kosher animals,
animals, right, even בעלי מומים, ba'alei mumim, even בעלי מומים, ba'alei mumim,
so none of the details applied, right? All of this was sort
of true until you got to the משכן Mishkan right here where
it's the beginning of like ויקרא, Vayikra, okay, here's where it basically
becomes the כהנים Kohanim and it becomes only you know and here's
זכר ונקבה, zachar u-nekeva, זכר ונקבה, zachar u-nekeva, and here you basically
have and here you basically have all the different types of things,
right? Only you know certain animals, שור כשב עז, shor kesev ez,
whatever, you know,
תמימים, temimim, etc., you know, only
some are זכר, zachar, some are נקבה, nekeva, the details as we
know them now. With the interesting exception of
עולה requires הפשט וניתוח. hefshet v'nituach. That began here. Okay. That's this
statement. Okay, and that is as opposed to the statement that was
made by רב חסדא Rav Chisda or רב הונא, whatever, in that
exchange of the פסוק, which was the exact opposite, which was basically
that was after הר סיני Har Sinai already the עבודה was בכוהנים,
bikohanim,
but ironically,
עולה was not הפשט וניתוח. hefshet v'nituach. So it's very strange that
the details of the עולה are the inverse of all the other
things, whether they begin the normal way or not. Okay. The flaying
and the chopping up. Rabbi? Yes. This the seven Noahide laws, does
that include idolatry?
Yes. So the במות bamot here are to God? They... yes, they
could bring to God, but not to idolatry. Exactly. Exactly. Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
so what do you do? This here, this statement that you were
saying, oh, the עבודה started with the כוהנים kohanim right after הר
סיני Har Sinai and the עולה doesn't require הפשט וניתוח, hefshet v'nituach,
that is the exact opposite of this ברייתא. braita. So how do
you defend that? So the גמרא Gemara says, תנאי
היא, tannai hi, it's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, דתניא בברייתא: detanya
b'braita: וגם הכהנים הניגשים אל ה' יתקדשו. V'gam hakohanim hanigashim el Hashem
yitkadashu. So this is by הר סיני. Har Sinai. The כוהנים kohanim
who get close to God should sanctify themselves and should stay off-limits
because they don't want to get sort of in trouble by getting
too close to God at הר סיני. Har Sinai. So who are
these כוהנים kohanim at הר סיני? Har Sinai? רבי יהושע בן קרחה
אומר: Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omer: זו פרישות בכורות. zu prishus bechorot.
That's telling the firstborn to keep their distance. So that's the approach
that of this ברייתא, braita, that it was the firstborn had their
status and presumably kept it all the way until the משכן. Mishkan.
Okay. So רבי אומר: Rabbi omer: זו פרישות נדב ואביהו. zu prishus
Nadav v'Avihu.
No, already at the time of הר סיני Har Sinai it was
no... it was not the בכורות, bechorot, it was the כוהנים. kohanim.
So that's this approach, the approach that said that even at הר
סיני Har Sinai it was already the כוהנים. kohanim. Okay. And it
was נדב ואביהו Nadav v'Avihu that were sort of said, they are
designated off. Now, בשלמא למאן דאמר bishlama leman d'amar זו פרישות נדב
ואביהו, zu prishus Nadav v'Avihu, if it's נדב ואביהו Nadav v'Avihu who
were told like, hey guys, keep your distance at הר סיני, Har
Sinai, you're the כוהנים, kohanim, so היינו דכתיב, hainu d'chtiv, הוא אשר
דבר ה', hu asher diber Hashem, that's when in נדב ואביהו Nadav
v'Avihu died, when the משכן Mishkan is erected, and משה Moshe says
to אהרן, Aharon, this is what God said: בקרובי אקדש. bikrovai ekadesh.
לאמור, lemor, בקרובי אקדש, bikrovai ekadesh, I will be sanctified by those
that are close to me. So where did he say that? What
did God say? Okay, what do you mean, this is what God
said? Because what God said was, at הר סיני Har Sinai God
said, hey guys, keep your distance, and if you don't keep your
distance, פן יפרץ בם ה', pen yifrotz bam Hashem, God is going
to come burst out at you against you and you'll die. So
משה Moshe said to אהרן Aharon when נדב ואביהו Nadav v'Avihu died,
he said, this is what God told you at הר סיני, Har
Sinai, like be careful, don't get too close, okay, which is not
very comforting, but okay, that's what he said to him. אלא למאן
דאמר ela leman d'amar זו פרישות בכורות, zu prishus bechorot, but if
at הר סיני Har Sinai the directive was given to the בכורות,
bechorot, so where did God say by נדב ואביהו, Nadav v'Avihu, what
does משה Moshe mean God said this already? Where did God say
it already? Okay, by נדב ואביהו, Nadav v'Avihu, היכא רמיזא? heicha remiza?
Where is it hinted? דכתיב: d'chtiv: ונועדתי שמה לבני ישראל ונקדש בכבודי.
v'noadeti shama livnei Yisrael v'nikdash bichvodi.
When God gives the command to build the משכן, Mishkan, he says,
I will encounter there בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and I will be
sanctified in my glory. So אל תקרי בכבודי, al tikrei bichvodi, don't
read sanctified in my glory, אלא במכובדיי, ela bimchubadai, I will be
sanctified by those who honor me. So when God says we're going
to build the משכן Mishkan and I'm going to dwell in it,
it means that, okay, but those who actually come to honor me,
those who draw close, I will be sanctified through them, but sanctified
through them in an ironic way means if they get too close,
they're going to die as a result, but that'll give a message
to everybody else. And that's the way in which God is being
sanctified here. דבר זה אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה. davar zeh amar
Hakadosh Baruch Hu l'Moshe. God said this to משה. Moshe. ולא ידעו,
v'lo yadu, and they didn't know who was going to be the
people that were who would be sacrificed in order that everybody else
would learn this lesson. ולא ידעו v'lo yadu עד שמתו בני אהרן,
ad shemetu bnei Aharon, until בני אהרן Bnei Aharon died. כיוון שמתו
בני אהרן, keivan shemetu bnei Aharon,
once בני אהרן Bnei Aharon died, sorry, once בני אהרן Bnei Aharon
died, okay, כיוון שמתו, keivan shemetu, where were we, בני אהרן, Bnei
Aharon, אמר לו, amar lo, he משה Moshe said to him, אהרן
אחי, Aharon achi, אהרן Aharon my brother, לא מתו בניך אלא להקדיש
שמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. lo metu banecha ela l'hakdish shemo shel
Hakadosh Baruch Hu. You should know that this sanctified God's name, because
it makes everybody else realize how holy God is that if even
your sons, you know, this is what happened to them. And that's
ונקדש בכבודי. v'nikdash bichvodi. כיוון שידע אהרן שבניו ידועי המקום הן, keivan
sheyada Aharon shebanav yidu'ei hamakom hen,
that's, you know, and know, you know, that they are known to
God, you know, בקרובי אקדש, bikrovai ekadesh, they were the ones that
were somehow, you know, dearest to God and therefore their death sort
of is a lesson to everybody else, שתק, shatak, he didn't like...
it's interesting, it doesn't say like, oh, okay, that makes sense, I
got it, good. No, it's like, it was a good enough answer
that it allowed him to accept it in silence. Not to really
embrace the answer, but allowed him to accept God's judgment in silence.
שתק. shatak. וקיבל שכר v'kibel sachar and he received reward for accepting
this judgment in silence. שנאמר she'ne'emar וידם אהרן. vaydome aharon. וכן בדוד
הוא אומר vechein bedavid hu omer דום לה' והתחולל לו, dome la'Hashem
v'hitcholeil lo,
be silent to God and long to Him, and we're going to
read התחולל לו, hitcholeil lo, אף על פי שמפיל לך חללים חללים,
af al pi shemapil lach chalalim chalalim, even if it seems like
God is calling all of these corpses to fall down, all these
deaths to occur to you,
אשתוק, ashtok, nevertheless accept God's judgment. So it's quite what I really
like about this is Moshe's explanation, oh, don't worry, God is getting
honors through your sons and that's what God said, בכבודי אקדש, bichvodi
ekadesh, it doesn't say like Aharon fully bought into that and he
was able to sort of submit and accept it in silence or
not protest, but it wasn't, but it's still the גמרא Gemara allows
us to understand that there's still questioning going on, there's still not
just difficulty, obviously your children died, but there's not a
full
understanding of it. You still don't, doesn't really still make sense,
but there's still struggles, there's still questioning, but nevertheless,
he allowed himself to at least accept it in silence. Rabbi, do
you see any parallels to the Christian idea of Jesus and the
crucifixion, a sacrifice, he's dying for
them? Yeah, no, that's more of an issue of vicarious atonement, which
you do have in a different גמרא about like about מיתת צדיקים
mitas tzaddikim is מכפר, mechaper, but that's not the point here. The
point here is not their suffering atones for us. It's not that
Christian idea. The point here is that it's a lesson to all
of us that about how careful we have to be in terms
of our sins and don't think we're so privileged that we can
get close to God and it's more sort of it serves as
a lesson rather than it's their actual death and suffering which is
an atonement, which is a different idea. Okay. וכן בשלמה הוא אומר
vechein b'Shlomo hu omer עת לחשות ועת לדבר. eis lachashos v'eis l'dabber.
There's a time to be silent and a time to speak. פעמים
ששותק ומקבל שכר על השתיקה, pe'amim she'shosek u'mekabel sachar al ha'shtika, sometimes
your job is just be silent and you get your reward for
your silence. Maybe you don't understand, maybe you want to challenge or
whatever. Your job is not to necessarily give
verbal acceptance. Your reward will be just your silence, that is suffices.
פעמים מדבר ומקבל שכר על הדיבור pe'amim m'dabber u'mekabel sachar al ha'dibbur
and times you're supposed to speak and that's what you're rewarded for.
Okay. והיינו דאמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן v'hainu d'amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan מאי דכתיב, mai de'chsiv, what's
meant נורא אלהים ממקדשיך, nora elohim mimikdashecha, God You are awesome from
Your holy
place. אל תקרי ממקדשיך אלא ממקודשיך, al tikri mimikdashecha ela mimikudashecha, from
those who sanctify You. בשעה שהקדוש ברוך הוא עושה דין בקדושיו, besha'ah
she'hakadosh baruch hu oseh din bikdoshav, when God actually does judgment even
against those that are close to Him, the holy ones, so מתיירא
ומתעלה ומתהלל, misyarei u'misaleh u'mishalel, here it's spelling it out, then He
is feared and glorified and raised up, raised up.
Okay. So now we've answered how was it בכורות bechorot or was
it כהנים? kohanim? So this is a debate. When God said keep
the כהנים kohanim off of הר סיני, Har Sinai, according to one
we're talking about the בכורות bechorot and that's this ברייתא, baraita, and
according to the other we're talking about נדב ואביהוא, Nadav v'Avihu, and
that's where נדב ואביהוא Nadav v'Avihu were warned. Now how do you
get though this issue about whether the עולה, the details of the
עולה applied at הר סיני Har Sinai or did the details of
the עולה only apply at the משכן? mishkan? So the גמרא says
let's just read that. אלא
קשיא עולה, ela kashya olah, what do you do about the contradiction
by the עולה? תרי תנאי היא, trei tannai hi, it's another debate
of תנאים. tannaim. דתניא רבי ישמעאל אומר detanya Rabbi Yishmael omer כללות
נאמרו בסיני, klalos ne'emru b'Sinai, the general principles were said at הר
סיני, Har Sinai, like at הר סיני Har Sinai it says bring
קרבנות, korbanot, ופרטות באהל מועד, u'pratos b'Ohel Moed, but the details in
אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So it wasn't until you got to ויקרא
Vayikra where you got all of the details and that's where you're
told what to do by the עולה. So according to that, you
don't have to flay and cut up the עולה until you get
to the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra, until you get to אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. Until then the details didn't apply yet. Okay. רבי עקיבא
אומר Rabbi Akiva omer כללות ופרטות נאמרו בסיני. klalos u'pratos ne'emru b'Sinai.
No, no, no. Even at הר סיני Har Sinai all the details
were said already ונשנו באהל מועד, v'nishnu b'Ohel Moed, and then they
were repeated at אהל מועד. So even though they appear for us
only in ויקרא, Vayikra, they were already said earlier ושלשו בערבות מואב,
v'shilshu b'Arvos Moav, and then in ערבות מואב Arvos Moav before they
entered in, they were said a third time. Okay. Now, by the
way, this is very ironic because what we're saying here is that
the explanation that the הפשט וניתוח hafshet v'nituach did not apply yet
is basically because the
פרטות, pratos, the details are only at אהל מועד. And the one
here that says הפשט וניתוח hafshet v'nituach did apply is because the
פרטות, pratos, the details already applied at הר סיני. Har Sinai. But
as I said, it's bizarre because that's about the עולה, but these
details, all of this stuff,
that didn't apply until אהל מועד. So I don't really get
why we can sort of say this detail applied here because this
is following the approach that all the details applied at הר סיני,
Har Sinai, but we're going to say all of this didn't apply
yet. And here we're going to say oh no no this... Already
began, you know, this does not require flame because the details didn't
start later. But if this one holds that the details already started
here, why didn't these? Why did all of this stuff, right, the
kosher animals, the בעלי מומין, baalei mumin, why did that, that the
גמרא doesn't really explain. Okay, so anyway we are going to pick
up with this tomorrow, this idea that at הר סיני, Har Sinai,
for you know, for whatever reason all of this detail applies, these
other details don't go until the משכן. Mishkan. How we know that
until the משכן Mishkan you can do all types of animals and
they can have blemishes and all that type of stuff. So we'll
pick up with that tomorrow.