Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. We are in the penultimate daf
דף daf קי"ט, kuf yud tet, Zvachim זבחים, Zvachim, four lines down.
I have to
make corrections of the day before. So I have to make two
arrows or slash corrections. One is, when we were discussing this lovely
here map, and you know, about Binyamin בנימין Binyamin and Yehuda יהודה
Yehuda and Ephraim אפרים Ephraim and being between them, I mentioned about
how the Beis Hamikdash בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was in Yehuda יהודה
Yehuda and you know, David דוד David was from Yehuda יהודה Yehuda
and then in the earlier stage the Beis Hamikdash בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash or the Shilo שילה, Shilo, whatever, you know, was like in
Ephraim אפרים. Ephraim. So anyway, I think I might have said at
that stage, if so I'm correcting it, that Shaul שאול Shaul was
from Ephraim אפרים. Ephraim. It's not true, Shaul שאול Shaul was from
Binyamin בנימין. Binyamin. But it's obviously very interesting how the way the
kingship and the Mikdash מקדש Mikdash and whatever are all sort of
being navigated among, you know, the children of Yosef יוסף Yosef and,
you know, and that's the question, right? Who's the bechor בכור, bechor,
right? You know, children of Yosef יוסף Yosef or Yehuda יהודה. Yehuda.
I mean Reuven's ראובן Reuven totally cut out, but he at least
gets Ever Hayardein עבר הירדן. Ever Hayardein. Anyway, so that's one point.
The other point is that we've been emphasizing that the reason that
Nob נוב Nob and Givon גבעון, Givon, you know, are do not
have a status of Mikdash מקדש, Mikdash, let's just call it that
for short, you know, it's because it's not a place of like
Makom Hashchina מקום השכינה Makom Hashchina and therefore it's not a singular
place of avoda עבודה, avoda, we're going to sort of emphasize that
again. And that's why there's a heter bamot היתר במות heter bamot
elsewhere, right, because it's not like a singular place, even though it's
the central place and it's the bama gedola במה גדולה, bama gedola,
it's not the a sense of like God's presence and therefore, you
know, God if God is equally present everywhere, you can offer to
God everywhere and so on. Anyway, just to be clear about this,
that's true about about Nob נוב Nob and Givon גבעון. Givon. Gilgal
גלגל, Gilgal, they had the aron ארון aron there. But it so
there was a different reason like for Gilgal גלגל, Gilgal, those first
fourteen years, though we have a whole timeline. Those first fourteen years,
you know, that doesn't have a sense of Mikdash מקדש, Mikdash, it's
not as clear why, presumably because they're still in like transition, you
know, they just came into the land, they're not yet conquered and
settled it. So everything is very tentative as it were, which is
a little ironic, because here they're in the midbar מדבר midbar and
they're wandering around, right? You don't need a fixed place and you
have that that sense, but nevertheless here there wasn't you weren't I
mean, you know, after after the chet hameraglim חטא המרגלים, chet hameraglim,
you weren't heading anywhere. So your goal was to be wandering around,
right? Here your point is you entered into the land and you're
on the cusp of settling it and getting everything in place. You
know, it's like you just moved into an apartment and you're still
getting all the furniture, you're still getting everything in place, so like
it's this unsettled state, you know. Anyway, it's different. It's a little
interesting why Gilgal גלגל Gilgal does not have that same sense of,
you know, the Mishkan משכן Mishkan and the central place and the
issur bamot איסור במות. issur bamot. Everything is a bit in disarray
during this transition period. So everybody is off doing their own thing,
you know. Anyway, I just wanted to point out that it's a
different issue why there's a heter bamot היתר במות heter bamot here
as opposed to why there's a heter bamot היתר במות heter bamot
here. Okay, anyway, now the Gemara גמרא Gemara continues, five lines down.
So Nob נוב Nob and Givon גבעון Givon you said there wasn't
the aron ארון, aron, is that what you said? What? Nob נוב
Nob and Givon גבעון, Givon, the aron ארון aron had been taken
captive, right? This whole time? And yeah, that's when Shilo שילה Shilo
was destroyed, was when the aron ארון aron was taken captive. And
then once it was returned, it was in Kiryat Yearim קרית יערים,
Kiryat Yearim, and then it was moved, you know, to like Beit
David בית דוד Beit David or whatever, I mean whatever, David דוד
David moved it, you know, but it was it wasn't together with
the central mizbeach מזבח. mizbeach. So the central altar and the aron
ארון aron weren't in the same place. Okay, so five lines down
on קי"ט. kuf yud tet. Bo l'Nob v'Givon באו לנוב וגבעון. Bo
l'Nob v'Givon. Minan hani mili מנלן הני מילי, Minan hani mili, where's
this from? Detanu rabanan דתנו רבנן. Detanu rabanan. What? I wonder how
they did the avoda עבודה avoda like Yom Kippur יום כיפור Yom
Kippur or whatever. Yeah, well they didn't. Okay,
right, that's what we had, like you know, in the central altar,
whatever, you know, without Shilo שילה Shilo they did not do right
I mean, you know, well that was the question. Did they do
a chatas חטאת? chatas? Right, those years in the city you did
everything. Well, you did the avoda עבודה avoda without the aron ארון
aron in the second Beis Hamikdash בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, right? Yeah.
But they went to the rock there though, right? That's true. Okay.
Minan hani mili מנלן הני מילי. Minan hani mili. All right, moving.
Now, minan hani mili מנלן הני מילי? Minan hani mili? How do
you know that there's a heter bamot היתר במות heter bamot here?
We know there's a heter bamot היתר במות heter bamot here because
of the pasuk פסוק pasuk of ki lo basem ad ata, ki
lo basem ad ata el hamenucha v'el hanachala כי לא באתם עד
עתה, כי לא באתם עד עתה אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה. ki lo
basem ad ata, ki lo basem ad ata el hamenucha v'el hanachala.
Okay, so which is read as during the el hanachala אל הנחלה,
el hanachala, during this period when you're entering in the land, it's
ish hayashar be'einav איש הישר בעיניו, ish hayashar be'einav, you can go
ahead and actually I discussed that in my parsha פרשה parsha sheet
today. Ish hayashar be'einav איש הישר בעיניו, ish hayashar be'einav, you can
go ahead and offer on the bamot במות bamot once you enter
the land. Why? Because ki lo basem ad ata כי לא באתם
עד עתה ki lo basem ad ata because you will not have
yet come to the menucha מנוחה menucha and the nachala נחלה, nachala,
and since we're in that state of like I said, of disarray
or whatever not disarray, that's a little harsh, but whatever, of transition,
you know, you have you have the right to go ahead and
be makriv מקריב makriv on the bamot במות. bamot. But once you
get to Shilo שילה, Shilo, that's the menucha מנוחה. menucha. Okay? So
once you get to Shilo שילה Shilo and you're at the menucha
מנוחה menucha here, el hamenucha v'el hanachala אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה, el
hamenucha v'el hanachala, here you're at the menucha מנוחה, menucha, where do
you know that during this, and here's the Beis Hamikdash בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, right? Where do you know that during this interim period
once again bamot במות bamot are permissible? Okay, got it? You know
bamot במות bamot are permissible here because it's lo basem el hamenucha
v'el hanachala לא באתם אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה. lo basem el hamenucha
v'el hanachala. How do you know bamot במות bamot are permissible in
the interim between Shilo שילה Shilo and the Mikdash מקדש? Mikdash? Detanu
rabanan דתנו רבנן, Detanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: ki lo basem ad
ata el hamenucha v'el hanachala, el hamenucha zo Shilo כי לא באתם
עד עתה אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה, אל המנוחה זו שילה. ki lo
basem ad ata el hamenucha v'el hanachala, el hamenucha zo Shilo. נחלה
זו ירושלים, nachala zu yerushalayim, fine. How do you know it's permissible
in between? למה חילקן, lama chilkan, why were they divided? כדי ליתן
היתר בין זה לזה, kedai litten heter bein zeh lazeh, to say
that it's permissible between one and the other. Now what does it
mean why was it divided? Right? Because it says אל המנוחה ואל
הנחלה. el hamenuchah v'el hanachalah. Exactly. That is exactly what I think.
Bizarrely, רש"י Rashi does not say that. רש"י Rashi just said, you
know, could have said אל המנוחה. el hamenuchah. Why did רש"י Rashi
more let- reads it למה חילקן lama chilkan as sort of why
did it also have to mention ירושלים? Yerushalayim? If the איסור במות
issur bamot began at שילה Shiloh and went from that point on
in Jewish history, it could have just said כי לא באתם אל
המנוחה. ki lo batem el hamenuchah. And then once you come to
שילה, Shiloh, the במות bamot are אסור. assur. So the fact that
it also mentions ירושלים Yerushalayim tells you there's a היתר heter between
the two. But I completely thought what- you know, agree with what
Michael said, which is why didn't it say אל המנוחה והנחלה, el
hamenuchah v'hanachalah,
ואל הנחלה, v'el hanachalah, right? Sort of says that there's like these
two separate units and there's a space in between them. So that's
what I really think it's saying. The extra ואל v'el is telling
you there's a space in between them of Nov and Gibeon where
the במות bamot become permissible again.
Okay, אמר ליה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן. ama lei Reish Lakish le-Rabbi
Yochanan. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מעשר
שני נמי ליתני. ma'aser sheni nami lisni. Now the משנה mishna says
that when they came to Nov and Gibeon, קדשים קלים kodshim kalim
were eaten בכל ערי ישראל. bechol arei Yisrael. Okay? There's always the
question: what is sort of the pseudo-ירושלים? Yerushalayim? When you're in שילה,
Shiloh, where could you eat קדשים קלים? kodshim kalim? Let's see if
anybody can remember from yesterday. If you could see שילה. Shiloh. How
about when you're in Nov and Gibeon? Where do you eat קדשים
קלים? kodshim kalim? So the משנה mishna says anywhere. Why anywhere? Because
you can bring your- you can bring your קדשים קלים kodshim kalim
anywhere. You can bring your שלמים shlamim anywhere. So if I can
bring my שלמים shlamim in my backyard, even if I bring my
שלמים shlamim in Nov and Gibeon, right, fundamentally, קדשים kodshim are eaten
everywhere.
Now קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodshim, like a חטאת chatas or whatever, assuming
you have קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim in Nov and Gibeon, whatever that
whole debate about קבוע להם זמן kavua lahem zman or whatever, but
when- anyway, when- if you had a חטאת chatas there okay, that
would be eaten only within the space of the actual, like, you
know, courtyard, whatever that would be defined, the courtyard. But קדשים קלים,
kodshim kalim, if I could bring a שלמים shlamim in my backyard
and eat it there, if I brought a שלמים shlamim in Nov
and Gibeon I eat it there. So שלמים shlamim are eaten everywhere.
Now, what about מעשר שני? ma'aser sheni? So here you have a
really big question about the גירסא girsa of the משנה mishna and
how to read this next גמרא. gemara. Our גירסא girsa doesn't mention
מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. And the implication is that you would not
bring- you're not eat מעשר שני ma'aser sheni at all during the
Nov and Gibeon period. Okay? Which is, which makes a certain sense.
If you don't have a place of- you might have a central
במה, bamah, but if you don't have a pseudo-ירושלים Yerushalayim during this
period, I mean, if you don't have that place of the city
surrounding where God's presence is residing, right, you get how you don't
have that during Nov and Gibeon, that's the point we've been making.
Then you don't have a place to bring מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
to. Okay? So קדשים, kodshim, you can eat קדשים, kodshim, you know,
בכל מקום אשר אזכיר את שמי, bechol makom asher azkir et shemi,
that's the thing in this period. You can sacrifice everywhere. But if
the concept of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni is eating לפני ה', lifnei
Hashem, then you're not going to do that during the Nov and
Gibeon period. And our משנה mishna doesn't mention מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni.
So that's one way of reading this גמרא gemara and I'm going
to read the גמרא gemara that way because it's the simplest read.
But I need to inform you that רש"י Rashi has a different
גירסא girsa in our משנה. mishna. רש"י's Rashi גירסא girsa in our
משנה mishna is קדשים קלים kodshim kalim and מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
are eaten everywhere. So you do eat מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, right?
It's sort of
it's two sides of the coin. You don't have that central place
of God's presence. So what does that mean for מעשר שני? ma'aser
sheni? Two possibilities: eat it nowhere or you eat it everywhere. Right?
You got it? So by קרבנות korbanos you eat it everywhere. But
by קרבנות korbanos it's not that sense of לפני ה'. lifnei Hashem.
מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, what do you do? So based on different
גירסות girsas of the משנה, mishna, the answer is either eat it
nowhere or eat it everywhere. So for רש"י Rashi the question in
the גמרא gemara is, okay, why- why, you know, which is like
why are you eating מעשר שני ma'aser sheni everywhere, why aren't you
bringing מעשר שני ma'aser sheni to Nov and Gibeon? So either way
the question is why not מעשר שני ma'aser sheni in Nov and
Gibeon, but the question is when the answer is you can't because
it's not לפני ה', lifnei Hashem, which is essentially going to be
the answer, is it and therefore you can eat it everywhere or
therefore you can eat it nowhere? That's the question. Yes, Charlie. So
by רש"י's Rashi גירסא girsa there might be a question of whether
you would even bring- bring מעשר שני ma'aser sheni to שילה Shiloh
because the language of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni really is referring to
the ultimate resting place of ה'. Hashem. Oh, what language are you
thinking about? I- I have to look it up. It's like המקום
אשר יבחר, hamakom asher yivchar, you're saying? Yeah. But I'm not sure-
that's an interesting one whether that's emphasized. And it will also resolve
the issue of you have to use actual money. I know, Charlie,
that's your favorite issue. All right, let's take a look at the
גמרא. gemara. Okay? So the גמרא gemara says, okay, אמר ליה ריש
לקיש לרבי יוחנן. ama lei Reish Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish said to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, מעשר שני נמי ליתני. ma'aser
sheni nami lisni.
Now
our גירסא girsa is why isn't it mentioned in the משנה, mishna,
which sort of reinforces the idea that the משנה mishna isn't saying
it and maybe presume and you wouldn't eat it anyway. But רש"י
Rashi is- but the other way of reading it is, why Why
isn't it listed in the things that you would do in נוב
וגבעון? Nov and Givon? Why don't you bring your מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni to נוב וגבעון? Nov and Givon? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he
said, מעשר שם שם מארון קא ילפי. Maaser sham sham me-aron ka-yalfi.
By מעשר Maaser it says
ואכלתם שם, ve-achaltem sham, and by the ארון aron it says, you
know, ונסעת שם את הארון, ve-nasata sham et ha-aron,
which is a way of saying that the concept of מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni again is eating it לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. That's the
phrase I'm going to use, okay? And therefore that's not a relevant
concept in נוב וגבעון, Nov and Givon, and you would not and
therefore, again, I would say the consequence would be you wouldn't eat
it anyway, okay? Or you could say there's no uniqueness to נוב
וגבעון Nov and Givon and you can eat it everywhere. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara says, כיון דארון לא הוה מעשר נמי לא הוה.
Keivan de-aron lo hava, Maaser nami lo hava. Since the ארון aron
wasn't there, you would not there would be no special role of
eating מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in נוב וגבעון. Nov and Givon. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, פסח
וקדשים נמי, Pesach ve-kodashim nami, דשם שם מארון ילפי. de-sham sham me-aron
yalfi.
If that's true, by all קרבנות korbanot it says, you know, וזבחת
שלמים ואכלת שם, ve-zavachta shelamim ve-achalta sham,
all קרבנות, korbanot, it says שם. sham. So why don't we say
that all קרבנות, korbanot, you know, since there's no מקום השראת השכינה,
makom hashra'at ha-Shechina, no ארון aron or whatever,
you can't bring any קרבנות? korbanot? Or maybe you certainly can't bring
communal קרבנות. korbanot. You can't bring the פסח, Pesach, you can't bring
other קרבנות, korbanot, right? Why don't we just say, okay, if you're
going to look at the word שם, sham, then everything goes off.
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says... Wait, when he says מעשר שני,
Maaser Sheni, are we also including בכור? bechor? Because it's in the
same פסוק. pasuk. Yeah, what
we'll see about that in a second. Okay, so you'll see it's
coming up. Anyway, so the point is that if מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni has no special place in נוב וגבעון, Nov and Givon, right,
then say by פסח Pesach and maybe all communal קרבנות, korbanot, they
have no special place in נוב וגבעון Nov and Givon and you
shouldn't be bringing them at
all, or alternatively bring them everywhere, whatever. But anyway, it's all the
same פסוק pasuk of שם. sham. So the גמרא Gemara says, דכיון
דארון לא הוה אינהו נמי לא הוה. de-keivan de-aron lo hava, inhu
nami lo hava. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
he said back to him, דאמר לך המני רבי שמעון היא. da-amar
lach ha-mani Rabbi Shimon hi. Fine,
forget the שם שם. sham sham. Forget that, that's that will get
us into that problem. Why does מעשר שני Maaser Sheni more need
לפני השם lifnei Hashem than these other things? Although you ask me,
it makes a lot of sense, but okay, fine. You know, because
קרבנות korbanot are קרבנות, korbanot, so wherever they are, you know, but
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, the power is you bring it to a
you carry it and it's a pilgrimage, right? And you're bringing it
like the same way like there wouldn't be עולת ראיה olat re'iah
to נוב וגבעון, Nov and Givon, you know, even if you could
be like there's no sense of that pilgrimage in that place. But
to me that answer makes a lot of sense, but the גמרא
Gemara says no, once you start focusing on שם sham and the
ארון aron or whatever, you want everything logically should be included. Fine.
So the reason מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is not in נוב וגבעון
Nov and Givon is a completely different perspective. Here's why. Does he
just say you eat it in Jerusalem? No, it says מקום אשר
יבחר, makom asher yivchar, right. התורה ha-Torah never, even though a lot
of דברים Devarim speaks about the single place that God will choose,
it never mentions ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
המני רבי שמעון היא דאמר אף ציבור לא הקריבו אלא פסח וחובות
שקבוע להם זמן. ha-mani Rabbi Shimon hi, de-amar af tzibbur lo hikrivu
ela Pesach ve-chovot she-kavu'a la-hem zman. Here's why. The reason you don't
do מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in נוב וגבעון Nov and Givon is
because this is following a רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon approach that says
that what you do in נוב וגבעון Nov and Givon is very
restrictive. It's only פסח Pesach and fixed obligations. Now תוספות Tosafot really
points out this is not so much רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, because
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is brought by individuals. This is really, I
mean it works with רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, but it's really more
the point of I forget who it was, of רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir and the חכמים Chachamim who argue on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and who say that even when an individual goes to the במה
גדולה, bama gedola, you only bring your free-will sacrifices. You remember that?
Right? When you actually go to that central במה, bama, do you
now get to bring obligatory sacrifices or are you just like you're
on your rooftop? So if we follow the approach that even in
the central במה bama you're just like you're on your rooftop and
it's only free-will, so מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is a well we're
going to start with מעשר בהמה. Maaser beheima. מעשר בהמה Maaser beheima
is obligatory, and you're not going to bring מעשר בהמה Maaser beheima
even in נוב וגבעון. Nov and Givon. And if you're not going
to bring מעשר בהמה, Maaser beheima, you're not going to bring מעשר
שני. Maaser Sheni. That's the argument. So let's take a look. So
it has nothing to do with eating לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. It
has to do with this is part of a whole system of
obligation and that system doesn't apply in the context of נוב וגבעון.
Nov and Givon. Okay.
אבל חובות שאין קבוע להם זמן הכא והכא לא קרב. Aval chovot
she-ein kavu'a la-hem zman, hacha ve-hacha lo karev. But if it's not
fixed they wouldn't bring it like even, you know, what a minute?
דאמר אף ציבור
וכו׳, de-amar af tzibbur etc., but you know, but they would not
bring it in either place. So מעשר בהמה חובת שאין קבוע להם
זמן. Maaser beheima, chovat she-ein kavu'a la-hem zman. Again, it's funny the
emphasis of קבוע זמן, kavu'a zman, לא קבוע זמן lo kavu'a zman
which has to do with communal sacrifices. But the real point is
מעשר בהמה, Maaser beheima, I mean תוספות Tosafot says this, מעשר בהמה
Maaser beheima is not an obligation and since it's not an obligation...
wait, it is an obligation. Excuse me, it is an obligation. It
is an obligation, but it's not a communal fixed obligation. So it's
an individual obligation and therefore according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים, Chachamim, it doesn't belong in
the במה גדולה bama gedola because it's an obligation but not a
communal fixed obligation. Okay, so therefore you're not going to bring your
מעשר בהמה Maaser beheima to the
במה גדולה. bama gedola. ואיתקיש מעשר דגן למעשר בהמה, Ve-itkish ma'aser dagan
le-ma'aser beheima, and therefore the two מעשרות ma'asrot are connected, the grain
and the animal, and therefore the reason you don't do מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni in נוב וגבעון Nov and Givon has nothing to do
with the sense of... It's a visit לפני השם Lifnei Hashem or
not לפני השם, Lifnei Hashem, it has to do with the sense
that in the period of the במות Bamot we do not work
with a system relating to individual obligation. So therefore the same way
as we've been pointing out, if you sinned, you don't get the
opportunity of bringing a חטאת, Chatat, right? And if you are טמא,
tamei, you can't bring a חטאת Chatat to become טהור tahor in
a certain type of טומאה. tumah. If you have מעשר שני, Maaser
Sheni, you also you don't get to operate in that system of
obligation. Now, again, the question is and therefore what do you do?
By a קרבן, korban, if there's no place to bring the קרבן,
korban, you don't bring it, right? And therefore yes, you're not going
to bring your חטאת. Chatat. But by the מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni,
this is the question, this is this long תוספות Tosafot discussing this
position of רש״י, Rashi, is the consequence don't bring your מעשר Maaser
and let it rot? Okay, or is the consequence that no, we're
not talking about a קרבן korban here, we're talking about מעשר, Maaser,
so if there's no sense of bringing it to a central location,
I can eat it in my private backyard? So that's still the
open question what you do with מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Yes. But
מסכת מעשר שני Masechet Maaser Sheni talks about this a lot, although
I don't think they mention נוב וגבעון. Nov u-Givon. I don't remember
it ever being mentioned. Right, that it gets discussed here, exactly. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: מכלל דלרבי יהודה קריב, Michlal de-Rabbi Yehuda
kareiv, does that mean for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, notice we skip
it's specifically about רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda versus everyone else, for רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says an individual does
obligatory stuff at נוב וגבעון, Nov u-Givon, would he also say that
it's מעשר שני? Maaser Sheni? Is it really just about the obligatory
point or as opposed to again the לפני השם Lifnei Hashem point?
In yes, for him you would eat מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in
נוב וגבעון. Nov u-Givon. דאמר רבה בר בר חנה מעשר שני ומעשר
בהמה נאכלים בנוב וגבעון לדברי רבי יהודה. d'amar Rabba bar bar Chana
Maaser Sheni u-Maaser Behemah ne'echalin be-Nov u-Givon le-divrei Rabbi Yehuda. We teach
that explicitly, that for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda the same way, and
that also shows that the logic is because they're linked, that for
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says you do obligations in נוב וגבעון
Nov u-Givon and in the במה גדולה, Bamah Gedolah, he would say
you bring מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. Which we still need to get
the בכור bechor because he links both of those.
Yeah, but the point is that the assumption would be the בכור
bechor is exactly the same as all of this. So according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you do בכור, bechor, I'm sorry, I said
it was going to be mentioned it wasn't but it's implicit in
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and מעשר בהמה. Maaser Behemah. So you would
do בכור bechor and I think תוספות Tosafot mentions it explicitly. And
the other one, I mean because בכור bechor isn't even the כהן
kohen gets to eat it, right? Right, I understand, but nevertheless it's
a חובה, chovah, right? So the גמרא Gemara says, so yes, that
would be the exact same thing. והא בעיא בירה? Ve-ha ba'ya birah?
Doesn't it require the בירה? birah? Now בירה birah is a phrase
sometimes that refers to ירושלים Yerushalayim or לפני הבירה, Lifnei ha-Birah, it
has some, it's basically, that's I think a way of communicating this
idea of לפני השם. Lifnei Hashem. It's all very nice, it's an
obligation, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you can bring obligations, but what
about that idea of לפני השם? Lifnei Hashem? If you look at
רש״י, Rashi, right, והא בעיא בירה, ve-ha ba'ya birah, רש״י Rashi says
דכתיב לפני השם אלקיכם. de-chtiv Lifnei Hashem Elokeichem. So רש״י Rashi actually
says it. So that idea which the גמרא Gemara introduced initially by
שם שם sham sham from ארון Aron and then sidelined, it's bringing
up again. It's all very nice that the obligation issue is not
relevant, but doesn't מעשר שני Maaser Sheni need a concept of לפני
השם Lifnei Hashem which again the גמרא Gemara assumes you don't need
by other קרבנות, korbanot, right? קרבנות korbanot when there's no when you're
in נוב וגבעון, Nov u-Givon, right בכל מקום אשר אזכיר את שמי,
be-chol makom asher azkir et shmi, you don't need some central לפני
השם, Lifnei Hashem, you don't need a more concentrated sense of God's
presence, okay, but don't for מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, isn't there some
idea of bringing it to this place of where there's a more
concentrated place of God's presence, okay, that בירה, birah, don't you need
that? So the גמרא Gemara says,
ותניא רב יוסף שלש בירות הן, ve-tanya Rav Yosef shalosh birut hen,
okay, but רב יוסף Rav Yosef taught that there are three places
that are considered to be בירה, birah, that לפני השם. Lifnei Hashem.
What are they? שילה ונוב וגבעון, Shilo ve-Nov ve-Givon, נוב וגבעון Nov
ve-Givon two places but we always count them as if they're one,
okay, ובית עולמים. u-veit olamim. הוא תני לה והוא אמר לה, Hu
tani lah ve-hu amar lah, he taught and he explained, what does
it mean to call it a בירה? birah? It means לאכילת מעשר
שני ואליבא דרבי יהודה, le-achilat Maaser Sheni ve-aliba de-Rabbi Yehuda, for מעשר
שני Maaser Sheni for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So if you can
bring מעשר שני Maaser Sheni because we don't care about the חובה
chovah element, you can even bring it to נוב וגבעון. Nov u-Givon.
So here we have a fascinating idea, right? And I don't know,
are we saying this more by נוב וגבעון Nov u-Givon than by
גלגל? Gilgal? I mean maybe גלגל Gilgal no, I think רש״י Rashi
points out גלגל Gilgal you didn't have מעשר שני Maaser Sheni because
because the land was before the land was conquered and settled. No,
not only we didn't have land, but before the whole land, the
whole land was conquered and settled, the מצות התלויות בארץ mitzvot ha-teluyot
ba-aretz didn't apply yet. Okay, so now it's an interesting thing. Until
now I've been saying that the whole nice explanation of why the
במות bamot are permissible here is because even though it was a
central communal במה, bamah, since it didn't have a place of the
ארון Aron and the שכינה Shechinah and a central sense of God's
presence, there's no logic to restrict offering outside because every place is
equal access to God, there's no central location of God's presence. But
now we're saying at least for the purpose of מעשר שני, Maaser
Sheni, it is enough of a sense of לפני השם. Lifnei Hashem.
Okay, so it's a very weird type and in a minute we're
back to actually say all the things you don't do in נוב
וגבעון Nov u-Givon because נוב וגבעון Nov u-Givon are not called לפני
השם. Lifnei Hashem. We're about to list a whole range of things
that are not done in נוב וגבעון Nov u-Givon because it's not
לפני השם. Lifnei Hashem. But somehow the answer is for מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni it was enough. So I don't exactly get it. But
the question was בירה, birah, don't we need בירה? birah? The answer
is yes, it is, it counts as בירה. birah. It doesn't say
why, it doesn't explain the logic, there was no ארון, Aron, and
it's also not going to be consistent. Because we're not going to
call it לפני השם Lifnei Hashem in a second where we're going
to say a million, a dozen things at once that weren't done
in נוב Nov and גבעון Gibeon because it wasn't considered to be
לפני השם. Lifnei Hashem. So I don't really get how by מעשר
שני Maaser Sheini we can assert that it is, yes. So this
thing that נוב Nov and גבעון Gibeon is the בירה, Birah, that
works for רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but it wouldn't seem to work
according to... Well, according to the others they wouldn't disagree with that
concept necessarily, but they would just say you're not allowed to do
חובות. Chovot. So you can't do חובות Chovot and of course we
agree with רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was the final answer. And
there's two points: רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the others is whether
you're allowed to do חובות. Chovot. Even if you check off you're
allowed to do חובות Chovot in נוב Nov and גבעון, Gibeon, what
about the לפני השם? Lifnei Hashem? So that check, which is also
considered the בירה Birah and לפני השם, Lifnei Hashem, which doesn't mean
that those that say you don't do חובות Chovot disagree with this
בירה Birah concept, they just say you can't bring it because it's
a חובה. Chovah. Okay, but anyway, but this is very strange that
that's considered that, A, that there wasn't an ארון Aron and why
should it be considered that and we just said the whole היתר
במות Heter Bamot presumably is rests on the idea that that's not
considered a central place of God's presence and now we're going to
have a whole list of things that after we get through ירושלים
Yerushalayim but when we turn the page a whole list of things
that you don't do in נוב Nov and גבעון Gibeon because it's
not considered לפני השם. Lifnei Hashem. Doing סמיכה Semicha on the קרבנות,
Korbanot, waving them, a whole כהן, Kohen, בגדי כהונה, Bigdei Kehunah, a
lot of things that require this לפני השם Lifnei Hashem concept. Okay,
let's take a look. באו לירושלים. Bau L'Yerushalayim. Then they came to
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and from this point on no
longer going to be a היתר במות. Heter Bamot. Okay. תנו רבנן.
Tanu Rabbanan. כי לא באתם עד עתה אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה. Ki
lo batem ad atah el hamenuchah v'el hanachalah. That פסוק Pasuk again.
מנוחה זו שילה. Menuchah zo Shiloh. נחלה זו ירושלים. Nachalah zo Yerushalayim.
ואומר, V'omer, and the verse says the concept of ירושלים Yerushalayim as
the נחלה Nachala makes sense because a נחלה Nachala has a sense
of perpetuity. So once they inherit, the inheritance then it remained that
way forever and no other place, even when there was בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash was destroyed, no other place you had a במה, Bamah,
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash would never be in another place, that
was the permanent inheritance. And the funny thing is though is that
נחלה, Nachalah, isn't there an opinion that ירושלים לא נתחלקה לשבטים? Yerushalayim
lo nitchalkah l'shvatim? Yeah, it's true, it's true, it's like the... it's
like that's an excellent point, it is, it's like the national נחלה,
Nachalah, this is a national heritage, so nobody individually can have it.
Okay. ואומר, V'omer, and the verse says: היתה לי נחלתי כאריה ביער,
Haysah li nachalasi k'aryeh baya'ar,
my inheritance was like a lion in the in the desert, right,
obviously this is ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, this is when ירושלים Yerushalayim is in
the anticipating it about to be destroyed, but anyway, but it's being
associated with נחלה Nachalah even in this negative context. ואומר: V'omer: העיט
צבוע נחלתי לי העיט סביב עליה. H'ayit tzavua nachalasi li h'ayit saviv
aleha. Like a like a speckled or
whatever, עיט, Ayit, עיט Ayit is like a raven, right? What are
they, jackal? Eagle? Bird of prey? Bird of prey.
העיט על הפגרים. H'ayit al hapgarim. Yeah, vulture, right, vulture, anyway, circling
around, anyway it calls ירושלים Yerushalayim my נחלה. Nachalah. Okay. דברי רבי
יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, מנוחה זו ירושלים נחלה זו שילה. Menuchah
zo Yerushalayim nachalah zo Shiloh. Doesn't sound like there's any halachic debate,
just says no no no, he reverses the order, which is not
chronological, which is what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask, but anyway,
מנוחה זו ירושלים נחלה זו שילה. Menuchah zo Yerushalayim nachalah zo Shiloh.
Okay. ואומר זאת מנוחתי עדי עד. V'omer zos menuchasi adei ad. This
is my final resting place. So I... maybe it's a question of
whether you perspective of the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael or of God.
From בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, they rested in שילה, Shiloh, but it
was only a final נחלה Nachalah when they got to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
From God's perspective, my resting place is maybe talking about it, that's
like where I'm finally going to rest, and that's so that's ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. זאת מנוחתי עדי עד פה אשב כי איויתיה. Zos menuchasi adei
ad po eshev ki ivisiha. This is where I will dwell because
I desired it. ואומר כי בחר השם בציון אווה למושב לו. Ki
bachar Hashem b'Tzion ivah l'moshav lo. So that פסוק Pasuk doesn't say
מנוחה, Menuchah, but it connects איויתיה Ivisiha desired it with ציון, Tzion,
with Zion, which is ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay. בשלמא, Bishlama, it doesn't explain
why שילה Shiloh should be called a נחלה. Nachala. בשלמא למאן דאמר,
Bishlama l'man d'amar, maybe like Michael said. Zion is always ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
not just ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? Fundamentally, I mean I haven't looked
at everything, but fundamentally it's ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
Go tell people that that's what being a Zionist really means. Okay,
בשלמא למאן דאמר מנוחה זו שילה, Bishlama l'man d'amar menuchah zo Shiloh,
היינו דכתיב אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה. Hainu d'chtiv el hamenuchah v'el hanachalah.
So the verse makes sequential sense, first שילה Shiloh then ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
אלא למאן דאמר מנוחה זו ירושלים נחלה זו שילה, Ella l'man d'amar
menuchah zo Yerushalayim nachalah zo Shiloh, אל הנחלה ואל המנוחה מיבעי ליה.
el hanachalah v'el hamenuchah mibei lei. It should have said, the order
should have been reversed because first it was שילה Shiloh then it
was ירושלים. Yerushalayim. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this is what the verse
says: לא מיבעי מנוחה דלא מטיסו, lo mibei menuchah d'lo matisu, כי
לא באתם עד עתה אל המנוחה. ki lo batem ad atah el
hamenuchah. You haven't come during this interim period, you haven't come to
the final resting place, you haven't come to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, אלא אפילו
נחלה נמי לא באתם. ella afilu nachalah nami lo basem. You wouldn't
have even come to a temporary resting place. So okay, it's out
of order, fine. Okay, anyway, but that's how they read the verse.
Okay. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל. Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael. So now you
think we covered both possibilities, but no, there are two more possibilities.
Okay, תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael teaches: זו וזו
שילה. zo v'zo Shiloh. The פסוק Pasuk isn't referring to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
You haven't come until שילה Shiloh and after שילה Shiloh there would
be presumably היתר במות Heter Bamot and according to... and now the
question is one minute, really? So if it's not mentioning ירושלים Yerushalayim
and it's not creating a gap, how do we know there was
a היתר במות Heter Bamot in נוב Nov and גבעון? Gibeon? And
תוספות Tosafot plays... with the idea maybe there was an איסור במות,
Issur Bamot, whatever, but it's like not possible. So how do we
know there was a היתר במות Heter Bamot in נוב Nov and
גבעון, Givon, right, if the פסוק Pasuk is only talking about שילה?
Shilo? So רש"י Rashi says, why is it repeating itself? Why? Well,
okay, the Torah sometimes uses poetic words, but also why is it
saying the word אל, el, right? The אל el really emphasizes that
it's a different place. Right, you haven't come to this or, you
know, nor to this or to this, you know, to A or
to B. Like I sometimes, you know, when I'm writing, ask myself
whether to like repeat the, you know, what's it called, the preposition,
right? I haven't spoken to Charlie or to David or to Michael
or do I say I haven't spoken to Charlie, David, or Michael,
right? It creates a greater gap when you add the preposition. So
the question is if this really, the fact that it's saying a
second word, you know, אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה, el hamenucha veel hanachala,
you know, that could be a nice poetic way of describing it.
But the אל el really suggests it's separate. So I don't know
the answer to that. And the question of what do you call
it, about how do you know that there's a היתר במות? Heter
Bamot? So רש"י Rashi basically says this opinion would have to say
that there's a היתר במות Heter Bamot even after ירושלים Yerushalayim is
destroyed. So that, so that, and therefore, it's only mentioning שילה, Shilo,
and after שילה Shilo it's destroyed, היתר במות, Heter Bamot, and then
you build ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and then, you know, and then fine, have
like a קל וחומר kal vachomer ירושלים Yerushalayim has the same status
as שילה, Shilo, but it's no different. And then afterwards there also
would be היתר במות, Heter Bamot, which is pretty radical. One minute,
let's just do that. Exactly. Okay. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says, תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל זו וזו שילה רבי שמעון בר יוחאי
אומר, Tana devei Rabbi Yishmael zo vezo Shilo Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai
omer, and here's the fourth possibility, זו וזו ירושלים. zo vezo Yerushalayim.
It's both ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So according to that, it's ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That
suggests that there's a היתר במות Heter Bamot through the entire שילה
Shilo period. And lo and behold, look at רש"י, Rashi, זו וזו
ירושלים ועד שיבנה הבית לא נאסרו הבמות. zo vezo Yerushalayim vead sheyibaneh
habayit lo neesru habamot. Okay. So these ideas, these last two are
really radical. They either come with it the implication the way רש"י
Rashi reads the first one that there's a היתר במות Heter Bamot
after ירושלים Yerushalayim is destroyed, right? Because ירושלים Yerushalayim is no different
than שילה. Shilo. Or the or if the פסוק Pasuk is only
mentioning ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that there was a היתר במות Heter Bamot even
during the period of שילה. Shilo. Okay. Michael, you had a... what's
your name? Charlie, you had a question. Yeah. So there has to
be a היתר במות Heter Bamot during the period of נוב וגבעון
Nov veGivon because in ספר שמואל, Sefer Shmuel, people are offering קרבנות
על במות korbanot al bamot all over the place with no objection.
Right, exactly, which is what forces רש"י Rashi to say that if
there's a היתר במות Heter Bamot after שילה Shilo and the פסוק
Pasuk is only mentioning שילה, Shilo, then there would be a היתר
במות Heter Bamot after ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: בשלמא למאן דאמר מנוחה זו שילה נחלה זו ירושלים,
Bishlama leman damar menucha zo Shilo nachala zo Yerushalayim, אי נמי איפכא,
ei nami ipcha, at least the reverse. In the end, they're not
really disagreeing, it's just like which word is which. But they basically
agree that the פסוק Pasuk is mentioning both. היינו דכתיב אל המנוחה
ואל הנחלה. hainu dechtiv el hamenucha veel hanachala. Okay, which is exactly
the question we were asking. You understand the ואל, veel, which separates
them as two separate locations. אלא למאן דאמר זו וזו שילה או
זו וזו ירושלים, ela leman damar zo vezo Shilo o zo vezo
Yerushalayim, it's basically two words to describe the same place. Okay, מנוחה
ונחלה מיבעי ליה. menucha venachala mibei lei. It shouldn't have the ואל.
veel. Right? So the גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. Okay, you're right,
that's a problem, I don't have an answer. But move on. Okay.
בשלמא למאן דאמר זו וזו שילה, Bishlama leman damar zo vezo Shilo,
if it's both, if it's referring to שילה, Shilo, מנוחה, menucha, so
I understand how both terms, now the גמרא's Gemara going to get
very like I don't know, you know, almost like just, I mean
it's not even הלכה halacha now, just like okay how do these
words work as descriptors? Okay, so זו וזו שילה, zo vezo Shilo,
so מנוחה, menucha, what does מנוחה menucha mean? דנחו מכיבוש, denachu mikibush,
that they the בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael rested from the process of
conquering. נחלה, Nachala, דפלגו התם נחלות, depalgu hatam nachalot, because actually in
שילה Shilo is where they divided up the land after the period
of conquering. So that's why it's called the נחלה. nachala. It's the
place where the נחלה nachala took place, not נחלה nachala in reference
to God's presence there, because obviously the it was going to move
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but נחלה nachala in the place of נחלה. nachala.
Okay. דכתיב ויחלק להם יהושע ויפל להם גורל בשילה על פי השם.
Dechtiv vayechalek lahem Yehoshua vayapel lahem goral beShilo al pi Hashem. So
both of those descriptors work for שילה. Shilo. אלא למאן דאמר זו
וזו ירושלים, Ela leman damar zo vezo Yerushalayim, בשלמא נחלה, bishlama nachala,
נחלת עולמים, nachalat olamim, that's perpetuity. אלא מנוחה, Ela menucha, מאי מנוחה?
mai menucha? What does מנוחה menucha mean? Now, if you remember a
few lines ago, we quoted a פסוק Pasuk that said זאת מנוחתי
עדי עד. zot menuchati adei ad. So the גמרא's Gemara question isn't
like how do you justify calling it מנוחה? menucha? Fine, a פסוק
Pasuk says it even, זאת מנוחתי. zot menuchati. But what does the
word מנוחה menucha mean in this context? What's the, you know, how
is this a meaningful descriptor? So why are you calling it מנוחה?
menucha? So it says מנוחת ארון, menuchat aron, because that's where the
ארון aron finally came to rest. After this point, I mean, of
course, the ארון aron was taken captive, Raiders of the Lost Ark,
go find out all the movings of the ארון, aron, how where
it went. But anyway, but okay, but this is the final, you
know, intended resting place of the ארון. aron. Actually, we don't know
where it is today. I know, it's buried in Washington, D.C. somewhere.
דכתיב ויהי בנוח הארון. Dechtiv vayehi benoach haaron. And it was when
the ארון, aron, when the ארון, aron, you know, took rest. Now,
of course, רש"י Rashi again like before, great רש"י, Rashi, top of
the page, רש"י Rashi says, ויהי בנוח הארון, vayehi benoach haaron, חיפשתי
ולא מצאתי. chipasti velo matzati. I've looked for this and I haven't
found it. You know, so you know, יגעתי ולא מצאתי אל תאמין
yagati velo matzati al taamin is supposed to be but you know
what? I'm going to trust רש"י Rashi here. רש"י Rashi says this
is not... a פסוק pasuk anywhere. Okay, ואם אינו בכתובים יש לי
מקרא אחר בדברי הימים בשלמה קומה ה' אלוהים לנוחך אתה וארון עוזך.
v'im einu biktuvim yesh li mikra acher b'divrei hayamim bishlomo kuma Hashem
elokim l'nochacha atta va'aron uzecha. So there are פסוקים psukim about the
ארון aron resting, okay, ובנוחו יאמר. uvnucho yomar. How about that פסוק?
pasuk? Okay, but anyway, but it's not this... these words are not
exactly a פסוק. pasuk. Anyway. בשלמא למאן דאמר זו וזו ירושלים, bishlama
l'man d'amar zu v'zu Yerushalayim, if they're both descriptors of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
אבל שילה הוי שרי בבמות, aval Shilo havay shari b'bamot, and here
the גמרא Gemara says explicitly what רש"י Rashi said a minute ago,
במות bamot were permissible during the שילה Shilo period. היינו דכתיב ויקח
מנוח גדי עזים ואת המנחה ויעל על הצור. hainu d'chtiv vayikach Manoach
gdi izim v'et hamincha vaya'al al hatzur. That's why he was able
to offer when he had the visitation from the angel about... and
we had this one פסוק pasuk that also... אמר כמה כביי. amar
k'ma k'vei. I know, we had this פסוק pasuk about what they
did בשעת היתר במות. b'sha'at heter bamot. But now we're actually pointing
out, wait, it wasn't שעת היתר במות, sha'at heter bamot, it was
שילה. Shilo. Okay, if you say במות bamot were permissible in שילה
Shilo it works. אלא למאן דאמר זו וזו שילה, ובמות הוי אסירי.
ela l'man d'amar zu v'zu Shilo, u'bamot havay asiri. But if במות
bamot were forbidden... or if one is שילה Shilo and one ירושלים
Yerushalayim and במות bamot are forbidden, doesn't matter, this was during the
period of שילה. Shilo. So if במות bamot were forbidden during שילה,
Shilo, which is what we've always been assuming, מאי ויקח מנוח? mai
vayikach Manoach? How could he do this? הוראת שעה היתה. hora'at sha'ah
hayta. It was a special, you know, exceptional ruling. It doesn't seem
like he got a הוראת שעה, hora'at sha'ah, he did it and...
No, because the angel said ואם תעלה עולה לה' תעלנה. v'im ta'aleh
olah l'Hashem ta'alenu. But why didn't he do it there, bring it
to, you know... Yeah, that's true, bring it to שילה. Shilo. Yeah,
but it sounds like he wanted to do it right there. But
also the context sounds like the angel wasn't sort of telling him,
I'm going to give you a special היתר heter to be מקריב
makriv a קרבן, korban, he was actually saying, oh, don't be מקריב
makriv to me, right? I understand. Okay, anyway. הוראת שעה היתה. hora'at
sha'ah hayta. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל כרבי שמעון בן יוחאי. tana d'vei
Rabbi Yishmael k'Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. In the house of רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael they follow the position of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. Rabbi
Shimon ben Yochai. דאמר זו וזו ירושלים. d'amar zu v'zu Yerushalayim. That
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which actually means שעת היתר במות sha'at heter bamot during
שילה, Shilo, again, shocking. You know, we always assume מנוחה ונחלה, menucha
v'nachala, I always assume whatever, איסור במות. issur bamot. Actually here now
there is a position that the גמרא Gemara is treating seriously that
through the entire 369 years of שילה Shilo it was actually a
time of היתר במות. heter bamot. וסימנך... v'simanach... what? More shock is
זו וזו שילה, zu v'zu Shilo, which then means after ירושלים Yerushalayim
is destroyed that's even more... That depends which way you go. Could
be, that's true too. But anyway, but anyway, according to this anyway
that it's ירושלים Yerushalayim and then during שילה Shilo was a שעת
היתר במות. sha'at heter bamot. וסימנך v'simanach and the way to remember
that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
follow רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, משכי גברא לגברי.
mashkei gavra l'gavri. The one man, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, schlepped the
whole house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael to follow his opinions. Not
exactly sure what that helps us remember, but okay. Now moving on.
So that is fascinating, it's not just a parsing of the פסוקים,
psukim, but it's if you read it in certain ways you come
out that either היתר במות heter bamot during שילה, Shilo, or היתר
במות heter bamot after ירושלים Yerushalayim is destroyed. Yes, Charlie. So even
while ירושלים Yerushalayim in בית ראשון Bayit Rishon were there, people were
still doing במות bamot all the time. But there was an איסור
במות. issur bamot. Right. עוד העם מזבחים ומקטרים בבמות, od ha'am m'zavchim
u'maktirim b'bamot, right, is what they talk about during the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash period. Right. It's not during the שילה Shilo period. Exactly.
So which is a good point, the fact that you never hear
of any criticism of במות bamot and I think we would have
to assume that whether it was היתר במות heter bamot or איסור
במות issur bamot during שילה Shilo people were probably still doing it
on the במות, bamot, right? So that's the silence about that which
suggests possibly היתר במות heter bamot even during שילה. Shilo. Okay, now
we start... now, okay, now we talk about this back to שחוטי
חוץ, shchutei chutz, okay, this הלכה halacha that if you go ahead
and you sanctify something at the time of היתר במות. heter bamot.
Like say you were doing גלגל Gilgal and you or whatever, you're
in נוב וגבעון Nov u'Givon and you sanctified it and then the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash got built and you figured out, okay, but
I already sanctified this, I'm not going to schlepp it to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I'm going to bring it in my backyard.
So since it was sanctified at the time of היתר במות, heter
bamot, even though it's שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, you're not חייב כרת.
chayav karet. You transgress, but you're not חייב כרת. chayav karet. That's
what the משנה Mishna teaches. Okay, so let's take a look at
this גמרא, Gemara, we're back to שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. אמר רב
כהנא לא שנו אלא בשחיטה. amar Rav Kahana lo shanu ela b'shchita.
That's only if you slaughtered this thing you sanctified בשעת היתר במות,
b'sha'at heter bamot, you slaughtered it now outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אבל
העלאה, aval ha'ala'ah, if you actually put it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
okay, then I don't care that you sanctified it earlier. כרת נמי
מחייב. karet nami mechayev. You get כרת. karet. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
What's the reason? דאמר קרא ועליהם תאמר, על הסמוכים תאמר. d'amar kra
va'aleihem tomar, al hasmuchim tomar. So the פסוק pasuk that we learned
a distinction between whether it was sanctified בשעת היתר במות b'sha'at heter
bamot or איסור במות, issur bamot, okay, we learned that earlier, comes
before... is in the context of שחיטה. shchita. And then after that
פסוק pasuk it says ועליהם תאמר, va'aleihem tomar, tell to בני ישראל,
Bnei Yisrael, okay, and talking about העלאה. ha'ala'ah. So the way it's
being read is ועליהם תאמר, va'aleihem tomar, that thing that I told
you, that distinction between whether it was sanctified בשעת היתר במות b'sha'at
heter bamot or איסור במות issur bamot is only עליהם, aleihem, it's
only on that earlier stuff, that discussion about שחיטה. shchita. It's not
on this stuff we're about to talk about, which is the discussion
of העלאה. ha'ala'ah. Okay, so he reads it sort of dividing the
two sections in the תורה Torah between שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz and
העלאת חוץ, ha'alat chutz, and this distinction only holds by שחוטי חוץ.
shchutei chutz. Okay. מתקיף לה רבה, matkif lah Rava, רבה Rava challenges.
מי כתיב ועליהם תאמר? אליהם כתיב. mi ktiv va'aleihem tomar? aleihem ktiv.
It says to them. to בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, you can't read
it to create this separation. ועוד, ve'od, תניא, tanya, ארבעה כללות היה
רבי שמעון אומר arba'ah klalot haya Rebbi Shimon omer בקדשים, bekodshim, he
gave four categories: הקדישן בשעת איסור במות ושחט והעלה בשעת איסור במות,
hikdishan b'sha'at issur bamot v'shachat v'he'elah b'sha'at issur bamot, if you did
it all at the time of איסור במות issur bamot during the
period of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash let's say, בחוץ הרי הן
בעשה ולא תעשה ויש בהם כרת. bachutz harei hen ba'aseh v'lo sa'aseh
v'yesh bahem kares. That's of course the full prohibition, you transgress the
positive and the negative and you get כרת. kares. הקדישן בשעת היתר
במות ושחט והעלה בשעת איסור במות. hikdishan b'sha'at heter bamot v'shachat v'he'elah
b'sha'at issur bamot. Let's say you sanctified them during the נוב וגבעון
Nov v'Givon period, at the היתר במות. heter bamot. And then you
שחט shachted or, here it's explicitly challenging what was said before, or
you offered it up at the time of the איסור במות, issur
bamot, now at the time of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. הרי
הן בעשה ולא תעשה ואין בהם כרת. harei hen ba'aseh v'lo sa'aseh
v'ein bahem kares. So that's a positive and a negative, but there
is no כרת. kares. Okay, so there you have explicit that even
when it comes to העלאה, ha'alah, if they were sanctified at the
time of היתר במות, heter bamot, you do not get כרת kares
even for העלאה. ha'alah. הקדישן בשעת איסור במות ושחט והעלה בחוץ בשעת
היתר במות. hikdishan b'sha'at issur bamot v'shachat v'he'elah bachutz b'sha'at heter bamot.
You sanctified it during the period of שילה. Shilo. And then שילה
Shilo was destroyed, so you offered it in your backyard in נוב
וגבעון. Nov v'Givon. So what are you doing wrong? It's a time
of היתר במות heter bamot now. So הרי הן בעשה, harei hen
ba'aseh, you transgress an עשה. aseh. What עשה? aseh? I sanctified it
at שילה, Shilo, שילה Shilo was destroyed, I'm offering it in my
backyard. The עשה aseh is the פסוק pasuk that says והבאתם שמה,
v'havaysem shammah, since you sanctified it at a time when there was
a central location, when there was שילה, Shilo, and you had an
opportunity to bring it to שילה, Shilo, and you didn't, even though
the destruction of שילה Shilo wasn't your fault, nobody is blaming you
for that, but what we are blaming you for is it was
sanctified when שילה Shilo was around, and you didn't see to it
that you were able to bring it, and now שילה Shilo is
no longer around, so at least you violated the עשה aseh of
והבאתם שמה. v'havaysem shammah. Okay, ואין בהם בלא תעשה, v'ein bahem b'lo
sa'aseh, but you obviously don't transgress any negative thing, you know, you
only transgress the positive passively anyway, and now of course bring it
in your backyard. הקדישן בשעת היתר במות ושחט והעלה בשעת היתר במות,
hikdishan b'sha'at heter bamot v'shachat v'he'elah b'sha'at heter bamot, if you did
everything at a time of היתר במות, heter bamot, פטור מכלום, patur
miklum, you're completely exempt. It's funny, פטור. patur. Yeah, well because until
now the whole discussion has been what do you violate. So you
don't violate anything. But right, you could have said מותר. muttar. Okay,
but of course which raises an interesting question, right? You know, I
mean it's an interesting question in general. How do we look at
the period of שעת היתר במות? sha'at heter bamot? Do we look
at it as like, at that time it was a good thing?
Yeah, that's how you, the same way right now, everybody has their
own שול shul and we דאוון davven in our own homes, right?
It's a positive phenomenon, as long as there's no איסור במות, issur
bamot, it's all positive. Or do you look at the שעת היתר
במות sha'at heter bamot as like a concession? You know, and even
at the time of היתר במות, heter bamot, ideally you really should
be going to a central location. I don't know, we've never said
that, but I do agree the word פטור patur is a little
strange. Anyway, תיובתא דרב כהנא תיובתא. tiyuvta d'Rav Kahana tiyuvta. This is
a total contradiction of רב כהנא Rav Kahana because it shows that
at the time, if you sanctified it at the time of היתר
במות, heter bamot, even if you offered it up on the מזבח
mizbe'ach at the time of איסור במות, issur bamot, you do not
get כרת. kares. Okay, אלו קדשים, eilu kodshim, then it goes on,
now, now we have the list of all the things that did
not apply, okay, in, you know, in a private במה. bamah. And
I think it's also implicitly, I was saying before, in נוב וגבעון,
Nov v'Givon, but now it occurs to me, I don't know if
it said that explicitly. Hold on, let me just check what the
משנה mishna said. It says ומה בין במת יחיד לבמת ציבור. u'mah
bein bamas yachid l'bamas tzibur. So actually, I think I now have
to go back and edit my whole tape because I think I
actually way misspoke because actually, oh man, I have to completely edit
my whole tape because I was misremembering the משנה. mishna. I was
remembering that the differences we're going to list about things like סמיכה
smicha and תנופה tnufa and בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, etc., the משנה
mishna says all of those applied in a private במה bamah but
not the public במה. bamah. I was thinking that they applied only
in שילה Shilo and ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But actually the משנה mishna says
that no, they all of those things like the כהונה kehuna and
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna and all those things also applied in נוב
וגבעון. Nov v'Givon. Okay, it's a difference between the private במה bamah
and the public. So actually, this actually is consistent with what we
said before about מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, because we're going to see
that all of these things are connected to a concept of לפני
השם. lifnei Hashem. So this is actually maybe that's why I was
sort of blocking it, but this is actually a little shocking that
we're going to say even in נוב וגבעון, Nov v'Givon, you're going
to have not just public and communal, you're going to have a
sense of לפני השם lifnei Hashem and you're going to have כהנים.
kohanim. Well, I guess, you know, well I don't know. Well yes,
because נוב Nov was עיר כהנים, Ir Kohanim, that's partly how we
sort of know that it was there. So that's quite interesting that
even though you don't have an ארון aron and even though you
have a היתר במות, heter bamot, you're still maintaining this idea that
a central במה bamah and the communal במה bamah is לפני השם.
lifnei Hashem. So number one we said it for מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni and now we're going to say it for all these other
rituals that require a sense of לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. Okay, so,
so all the קשיות kashyas I had before are actually now תירוצים.
terutzim. Okay, it's like you do תשובה מאהבה, teshuva me'ahava, so your
עבירות aveiros become... Okay, anyway, סמיכה דכתיב... smicha d'ksiv... How do we
know סמיכה *semichah* was only in the place of a central במה
bama *bamah*, of a במה גדולה bama gedola, *bamah gedolah*? לפני השם
וסמך *Lifnei Hashem v'samach*. Okay, so סמיכה *semichah* is connected to לפני
השם *Lifnei Hashem*. שחיטת צפונה דכתיב *Shechitas tzafona d'chesiv*, צפונה לפני השם
*tzafona Lifnei Hashem*. Okay, so the idea of north by an עולה
ola *olah* would be whatever, לפני השם *Lifnei Hashem*. מתנות סביב *Matanos
saviv*, the idea that it’s there's a specific way you put the
blood, it’s not just any application of blood but it’s like all
around the altar or two opposite corners, דכתיב וזרק על המזבח סביב
*d'chesiv v'zarak al hamizbeiach saviv*. Now that doesn’t say לפני השם *Lifnei
Hashem* and but a פסוק *pasuk* right nearby says לפני השם *Lifnei
Hashem*, רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* quotes a פסוק *pasuk* that says לפני השם
*Lifnei Hashem*, but also we’re gonna see that the word המזבח *hamizbeiach*,
the מזבח *mizbeiach*, could mean like the central communal מזבח *mizbeiach*. Okay,
okay, תנופה דכתיב *tenufah d'chesiv*, the waving, והניף הכהן לפני השם *v'henif
hakohen Lifnei Hashem* by the מנחה *minchah*. So there’s לפני השם *Lifnei
Hashem*. הגשה דכתיב הגישה אל המזבח *Hagashah d'chesiv higishah el hamizbeiach*. So
again it doesn’t say לפני השם *Lifnei Hashem*, it says לפני השם
*Lifnei Hashem* in a nearby nearby like nearby, but it also says
המזבח *hamizbeiach*. So the idea of המזבח *hamizbeiach* and לפני השם *Lifnei
Hashem*, that does not apply in a private במה bama *bamah*, but
again it actually does apply in a public במה bama *bamah* even
in נוב Nov וגבעון *Nov v'Givon*. So even though there’s no ארון
*aron* and even though I keep on repeating myself but I’m just
trying to undo everything I said before, anyway even though there’s no
ארון *aron* and there’s a היתר במות *heter bamot*, it is considered
לפני השם *Lifnei Hashem*. So before we discussed that in the concept
of מעשר שני *Ma'aser Sheni* and here we’re saying all of these
rituals of סמיכה *semichah*, תנופה *tenufah*, הגשה *hagashah*, the way the blood
was done, which require לפני השם *Lifnei Hashem*, you all did even
in נוב Nov וגבעון *Nov v'Givon*. Let’s keep on going. רבי יהודה
אומר אין מנחה בבמה *Rebbi Yehuda omer ein minchah b'bamah*. Okay, so
now we’re now we’re moving up now so that’s done, that was
that whole list of things that you did in oh actually we’re
going to get back to no no he’s just interrupting for a
second because we mentioned the waving of the מנחה *minchah*, right, there’s
still a whole other remainder of the list that we’re going to
say about things that were done in the central במה bama... *bamah*
and not on the private, but first we interrupt for this commercial
message that רבי יהודה *Rebbi Yehuda* says I disagree I don’t you
that I disagree I think that there was you have to say
there was no waving or whatever etc. of the מנחה *minchah* in
a private במה bama *bamah* because there was no מנחות *minchos* altogether
in a private במה bama, *bamah*. אין מנחה בבמה *Ein minchah b'bamah*.
אמר רב ששת לדיבי אומר יש מנחה בבמה יש עופות בבמה *Amar
Rav Sheshes l'dibei omer yesh minchah b'bamah yesh ofos b'bamah*. If there
was a מנחה *minchah* there were also bird sacrifices in your private
במה bama, *bamah*, לדיבי אומר אין מנחה בבמה אין עופות בבמה *l'dibei
omer ein minchah b'bamah ein ofos b'bamah*, and if it and if
there wasn’t a מנחה *minchah* there weren’t bird sacrifices. How do you
know? Because when it speaks about the slaughtering by a במה bama
*bamah*, it says you know וזבחת *v'zavachta*, what’s the פסוק *pasuk* what’s
the פסוק *pasuk* Rashi quotes it says וזבחו זבחי שלמים להשם la-Hashem
אותם *v'zivchu zivchei shelamim l'Hashem osam*. So זבחים ולא מנחות *zevachim v'lo
menachos*, slaughtered things and not מנחות *menachos*. זבחים *Zevachim* and even though
you and no עופות *ofos* because an עוף *of* you don’t you’re
not זובח *zoveiach*, you do מליקה *melikah* to it. Okay, so fine,
so that’s the discussion which we’ve been referencing for a long time,
would you bring a מנחה *minchah* on a private במה bama. *bamah*
or is it only limited to like you know sheep and cattle
and so on. Okay, back to things that you do in a
public במה bama, *bamah* not in a private במה bama, *bamah*. כהן
דכתיב וזרק הכהן *Kohen d'chesiv v'zarak hakohen*. Okay, על מזבח השם *al
mizbach Hashem* I think it says is the end of the פסוק
*pasuk*, את הדם על מזבח השם *es hadam al mizbach Hashem*, right.
So again you have מזבח השם *mizbach Hashem*. בגדי שרת *Bigdei shares*,
לשרת בקודש *l'shares bakodesh*, the sense that it’s a special holy place.
וכלי שרת אשר ישרתו בם בקודש *U'klei shares asher yesharsu bam bakodesh*.
So we have now three concepts that apply in a public במה
*bamah* and not in a private: לפני השם *Lifnei Hashem*, well המזבח
*hamizbeiach* I guess, the central מזבח *mizbeiach*, and the idea of בקודש
*bakodesh*. Okay, those are things that apply in a central במה *bamah*
even נוב Nov וגבעון *Nov v'Givon* but not in a private במה
*bamah*, and that’s why you can do all those rituals in נוב
Nov וגבעון *Nov v'Givon* but not in a private במה *bamah*. ולריח
ניחוח *U'l'reiach nichoach*, it’s not considered to be offered up לריח ניחוח
*l'reiach nichoach*, דכתיב לריח ניחוח להשם *d'chesiv l'reiach nichoach l'Hashem*, which is
a little ironic because you would think wherever you’re offering your קרבן
korban, *korban* you’re offering it to God, it might not be לפני
השם *Lifnei Hashem* but it’s still להשם *l'Hashem*, right. So that I
think that’s quite fascinating. So the בקודש *bakodesh* is not referring as
much to the קרבן korban *korban* because you know the קרבן korban
*korban* is also קודש *kodesh*. It was the place. Yeah, the place,
exactly. מחיצה בדמים *Mechitza bedamim*, the idea that there’s a line on
the מזבח *mizbeiach* and some bloods go above and some go below,
דכתיב ועשה הרשת עד חצי המזבח *d'chesiv v'asah hareshesh ad chatzi hamizbeiach*.
It’s only by the central altar. רחיצת ידיים *Richutz yadayim*, the washing
of hands that precedes the עבודה *avodah*, דכתיב ובקרבם אל המזבח ירחצו
*d'chesiv u'v'korvam el hamizbeiach yirchatzu*, only the central מזבח *mizbeiach*. אמר רמי
בר חמא לא שנו אלא בקדשי במה קטנה bama ktana. והקריבום בבמה
קטנה *Amar Rami bar Chama lo shanu ela b'kodshei bamah ketanah v'hikrivum
b'bamah ketanah*. אבל בקדשי במה קטנה דהקריבום בבמה גדולה יש רחיצה *Aval
b'kodshei bamah ketanah d'hikrivum b'bamah gedolah yesh richutz*. This idea that the
line doesn’t matter okay when when you do it on your private
במה *bamah*, that’s only if it is sanctified for your on your
private במה *bamah* and offered, but let’s say you sanctified it for
your private במה *bamah*, when you sanctified it you plan to bring
it in your backyard, but you happen that day to be traveling
to נוב Nov וגבעון *Nov v'Givon*, so you decided heck I’ll bring
it in נוב Nov וגבעון *Nov v'Givon*. So this is an interesting
question, the distinctions, he’s focusing specifically on the blood because presumably the
other distinctions like the place, what are the כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim* going
to do, right, in נוב Nov וגבעון *Nov v'Givon* they’re going to
They're going to be כהנים, Kohanim they're going to be wearing כלי
שרת, klei sharet, they're going to be washing their hands, right? So
like that's like standard operating procedure. But when you get to the
קרבן, korban if the identity of this קרבן korban? is a private
במה קרבן korban being brought in נוב Nov and גבעון, Givon, what
do you do with its blood? Is its blood treated as a
private במה קרבן korban or as a נוב Nov and גבעון Givon
קרבן? korban So he says if it was sanctified for private and
brought in נוב Nov and גבעון, Givon, then you would go by
the נוב and גבעון Givon rules and you would put the blood
would be based on above or below the line. Okay, it doesn't
matter how it was sanctified. I'm sorry, wait, how does the ריח
ניחוח reiach nichoach which is just getting back to something before prove
anything? So so it says להשם so what? So it has to
mean in that particular spot? I have that question. I don't know
the answer. Okay. מתיב רבא, Motiv Rava, רבא Rava challenges this: חזה
ושוק תרומת לחמי תודה נוהג בקדשי במה גדולה ואינו נוהג בקדשי במה
קטנה. Chaze v’shoke trumat lachmei todah noheig b’kodshei bama gedola v’eino noheig
b’kodshei bama ktana. The idea that you would do the חזה chaze
and the שוק shoke that you would give to the כהנים, Kohanim,
again, there's only כהנים Kohanim in a במה גדולה, bama gedola okay,
the giving of the of the breads of the of the תודה
todah to the כהנים, that applied in the במה גדולה bama gedola.
because that's where you would have כהנים anyway and didn't apply in
a במה קטנה. Okay. So why is that a question? Because it
says קדשי במה גדולה kodshei bama gedola and קדשי במה קטנה. kodshei
bama ktana. So it sounds like the emphasis is what context was
it sanctified? Was it sanctified for a private or a public? It
doesn't matter where it was done, it matters how it was sanctified.
So the language of this ברייתא braita suggests that if you sanctify
something for your backyard במה and bring it in נוב and גבעון,
Givon, at least for the things that relate to the קרבן itself,
you know, not the larger operations, okay, it would go by the
way it was sanctified, not by the fact that it was brought
in נוב and גבעון. Givon. That was confusing. Yes, total. So the
גמרא's Gemara answer is אימא נוהג בבמה גדולה ואינו נוהג בבמה קטנה.
eima noheig b’vama gedola v’eino noheig b’vama ktana. No, take out the
word קדשי. kodshei. It doesn't mean how it was sanctified, it means
where it was brought. Okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika d’amri, some say. אמר
רבי בר חמא: Amar Rabbi Bar Chama: לא שנו אלא בקדשי במה
גדולה והקריב בבמה גדולה. lo shanu ela b’kodshei bama gedola v’hikriv b’vama
gedola. When is there this divide? When it was sanctified and brought
in the במה גדולה. אבל בקדשי במה קטנה אף על גב דקרבינה
בבמה גדולה אין חיצוי. Aval b’kodshei bama ktana af al gav d’karvina
b’vama gedola, ein chitzuy. So now he's saying the opposite. He's saying
actually it would follow the... it would follow the way in which
it was sanctified, okay, not where it was brought. לימא מסייע ליה.
Leima misayei lei. Okay, now I can support you. חזה ושוק ותרומת
לחמי תודה נוהג בקדשי במה גדולה ואינו נוהג בקדשי במה קטנה. Chaze
v’shoke u’trumat lachmei todah noheig b’kodshei bama gedola v’eino noheig b’kodshei bama
ktana. This ברייתא braita speaks about whether they sanctified for the private
or they sanctified for the public. So that seems to support you.
You say it goes by the way it was sanctified. At least
again the stuff that pertains to the actual קרבן itself. So אימא
נוהג בבמה גדולה ואינו נוהג בבמה קטנה. eima noheig b’vama gedola v’eino
noheig b’vama ktana. No, you can't really prove it. Yes, the language
sounds that way but the language could be imprecise. So of course
I totally agree with David, you know, give me a break. You
bring something to the central place you're going to do it like
the central... you know, they're going to do everything as they would
do normal. But I guess the question would be, let's say they
accidentally did it the wrong way. Is the fact that it was
sanctified for a private במה... you know, what they would actually do
in practice would be one thing. They could do everything treat everything
the same. But what would actually be required if it was sanctified
for a private במה might be different. Okay. So that's the question.
And now the גמרא Gemara says: ופליגא דרבי אלעזר דאמר רבי אלעזר
עולת במת יחיד שהכניסה בפנים קלטו המחיצות. u’pliga d’Rabbi Elazar, d’amar Rabbi
Elazar olat bamas yachid she’hichnisa bifnim kaltu hamchitzot. If you have an
עולה that you brought on a private... on a private במה, okay,
and then you went ahead and you brought it inside into נוב
and גבעון, Givon, okay? So you have the meat and you brought
it to נוב and גבעון, Givon, so now it basically follows the...
you know, like it gets defined by being in נוב and גבעון.
Givon. Like you don't get to take it back out and bring
it back to your private במה, you have to offer it, you
know, in the central במה and so on. So that again shows
the power of the place, right, even though this was sanctified for
your private במה. Okay, so wait, this disagrees... Well, it disagrees with
the second version of it, right? The second version was that it
goes by how it was sanctified. And here we're saying או אלא
אימא, o ela eima, we did re-reading the ברייתא braita as a
possible support. But the statement of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, the second
version of רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is that it goes how it
was sanctified. Okay, okay, okay, fine. I'm just checking רש"י, okay. Okay,
now, okay now, בעי רבי זירא. ba'i Rabbi Zeira. רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira asked: עולת במת יחיד שהכניסה בפנים והוציאה לחוץ. olat bamas yachid
she’hichnisa bifnim v’hotzia lachutz. So this is exactly this question of like
קלטו המחיצות. kaltu hamchitzot. Okay, you sanctified it for your private במה,
you brought it into נוב and גבעון Givon and you took it
outside. מאי, Mai, what do we say? מי אמרינן, Mi amrinan, do
we say כיון דעיילה קלטה למחיצתה, kivan d’ayela kalta l’mechitzta, which is
what we would... sounded like we said a minute ago. Since you
brought it in, the מחיצות mechitzot absorbed it, and now if you
bring it out, you invalidate it. או דלמא, Odilma, כיון דהדר הדר.
kivan d’hadar hadar. Okay, or maybe do we say that, you know,
once you took it back out, it now reverts to, you know,
being considered an external במה, a במת יחיד bamas yachid type of
a קרבן and the other הלכות halachot would apply. So we're going
to... I'm going to leave you with this cliffhanger and we will
finish up the מסכת masechet tomorrow. You said 20 minutes before? Yeah,
maybe half hour.