Okay, today's דף daf, *daf* is דף ק"י *Daf Kuf Yud*, 110
and we start at the top of the דף *daf*. And we
were just in the middle of a debate in the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* about the case of whether you're the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer* and the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* about if you offer up
a כזית kezayis *kezayis* of קטורת Ketores *ketores* outside of בית המקדש
Beis ha-Mikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* and it's not the full שיעור shiur *shiur*
and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of tried to figure out exactly
what the parameters of the debate were and the most recent explanation
was was that it was two זיתים *zeisim* in one כלי
kli *kli* and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* would agree with
the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* that normally one כזית kezayis. *kezayis* would be
enough for הקטרה haktara *haktara* for offering up the incense on the
מזבח mizbeach. הזהב *Mizbeach Hazahav* and you should be חייב chayiv *chayav*
for that outside. The only difference, the only time it would be
more than that for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* would require
more would be ביום כיפור *byom Kippur*. But the issue, but the
case was that you put two כזיתים Kezaysim, *kezaisim* in a כלי
kli *kli* and does that now change the שיעור shiur *shiur*? And
now for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* because the כלי kli
*kli* establishes that they're both now combined as one unit, now a
כזית kezayis *kezayis* is not enough if you took it from this.
Now you would not be חייב chayiv *chayav* if you took it
outside unless you did the full amount. Okay, so that's the top
of ק"י עמוד א' *Kuf Yud Amud Aleph* and now we're going
to continue. מר סבר קביעותא דמנא מילתא היא *Mar savar kviusa demana
milta hi*, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? *Rabbi Eliezer* is of the opinion
that establishing them in the like sort of fixing them in the
vessel is significant and makes this now the new unit and now
a כזית kezayis *kezayis* is not enough if you take it from
this. ומר סבר לאו מילתא היא *Umar savar lav milta hi*, no,
that doesn't change the facts that a כזית kezayis *kezayis* is enough.
אמר רבא Rava *Amar Rava*, says רבא *Rava*, השתא למאן דאמר קביעותא
דמנא לאו כלום היא *hashta leman d'amar kviusa demana lav klum hi*,
according to the approach of the חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* that say that
the putting it in the כלי שרת kli shares *kli shares* doesn't
change what the actual minimum is, קבע שישה לפר *keva shisha lepar*,
let's say we're dealing with יין *yayin*, with wine that would be
you know יין *yayin* that you would pour on the altar and
now you pour six לוג log *log* for a for the cow,
right? That's a half of a הין *hin* which is 12 לוג
log *log*. So you did six לוג log. *log* for a cow
but what you did now according to the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan*, according
to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? *Rabbi Eliezer* that would mean this is
the שיעור shiur, *shiur* six לוג log. *log* and anything less than
this is not the full amount. But we know that normally you're
חייב chayiv *chayav* for three לוג log *log* outside of the בית
המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash *Beis Hamikdash* because that's the amount that could work
for you know for a sheep. So if you hold like the
חכמים Chachamim *Chachamim* then it would still be the same even if
you took three לוג log, *log* out of this. You don't view
this as one unit of six that now anything less is not
the minimum amount. So השתא *hashta*, so קבע שישה לפר ומשך מהן
ארבעה והקריבן בחוץ *keva shisha lepar umashach mehen arba'a vehikrivan bachutz*, you
took four out of the six, could have said three, חייב chayiv
*chayav*, you're still חייב chayiv. *chayav*, ראויין לאיל *reuyin l'ayil*, that four
is still meaningful because it could be brought with a ram and
the fact again that you put six in one vessel doesn't establish
that as a as the fixed unit. ארבעה לאיל *Arba'a l'ayil*, similarly
if you did four for the ram, four לוג log. *log*, ומשך
מהן שלושה והקריב בחוץ *umashach mehen shlosha vehikriv bachutz*, and you took
three and you put it outside, so similarly in that case חייב
chayiv *chayav*, ראויין לכבש *reuyin lakeves*, that you're also חייב chayiv *chayav*
because three works for a lamb. You could have said if you
did six and you took three. Anyway, the point being that it
does not re-, it doesn't change what the actual minimum was even
for this object. That's wrapping up that opinion. Now חסר chasar כל
שהוא kol shehu. והקריבן בחוץ
*Chasar kol shehu vehikrivan bachutz*, excuse me one more line, if however
this full amount this amount was lacking meaning it wasn't just you
took some of them but that actually the minimum amount was lacking
and in that case we're going to get to the issue of
חסר chasar *chasar* in a minute, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that
this means not again a little lacking from the six but a
little lacking from the three. Anything less than the minimum three amount
in that case you'd be פטור patur. *patur*. Fine, that's pretty obvious,
less than three you'd be פטור patur *patur*. רב Rav, אשי אמר
ניסוך nisuch מהקטורת לא ילפי lo yalfee, רבנן Rabbanan *Rav Ashi amar
nisuch mehaketores lo yalpi rabbanan*. Now if you remember yesterday the point
was was the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tried to have one way of
explaining the debate that everybody would agree that you are חייב chayiv
*chayav* for one כזית kezayis *kezayis* of the normal קטורת Ketores *ketores*
and the question outside, the question is are you כזית kezayis *kezayis*
חייב chayiv *chayav* for one כזית kezayis *kezayis* of the קטורת Ketores
*ketores* on יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* where there's the amount
is מלא חפניו *melo chofnav*? So and the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
no, that can, and the reason to say you're חייב chayiv *chayav*
is not because it works inside the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash *Beis
Hamikdash* which it doesn't, but because if a כזית kezayis *kezayis* you're
חייב chayiv *chayav* for outside of the normal קטורת Ketores. *ketores* the
same should be true of the קטורת ketoret. *ketores* of יום כיפור
Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*. Okay and then that was challenged and said
one minute, how can you apply an outside קטורת ketores *ketores*, you
know, and apply that to the יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*
קטורת *ketores* if we don't even apply two things from the outside
to the other? We don't, you know, less than three לוג log
*log* of wine isn't going to work even though if you were
dealing with other things you would say a כזית kezayis. *kezayis*. So
you're not going to apply the שיעור shiur *shiur* from meat or
from you know or from קטורת *ketores* to wine. So why would
you apply the שיעור *shiur* from קטורת *ketores* that was outside קטורת
*ketores*, קטורת *ketores* of the היכל Heichal *heichal*, to קטורת *ketores* of
the קודש kodesh הקדשים *Kodesh Hakodashim*? Of course the answer is pretty
obvious, that that's קטורת *ketores* and קטורת *ketores*, which is what now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say. רב Rav אשי אמר
ניסוך nisuch מהקטורת לא Lo. ילפי רבנן Rabbanan *Rav Ashi amar nisuch
mehaketores lo yalpi rabbanan*, they're not going to learn ניסוך nisuch *nisuch*
from הקטרה *haktara* and say... maybe because כזית kezayit is enough to
be חייב chayiv for the wine outside. אף על גב Af al
gav דחוץ מחוץ de-chutz mi-chutz לא ילפי, and even though that's true
that that's two things on the outside, you know, that they're both
sort of what a שיעור of the ניסוך nisuch on the outside
and a שיעור of the קטורת on the outside and you don't
say since the קטורת on the outside is a כזית kezayit. the
ניסוך nisuch. on the outside is a כזית. kezayis. Nevertheless, הקטורת מהקטורת
ילפי ha-Ketores me-ha-Ketores yalfee אף על גב דחוץ מפנים, af al gav
de-chutz mi-pnim, but they would be prepared to learn the minimum amount
to be חייב chayiv for the for יום כיפור Yom Kippur. from
the minimum amount that you're חייב chayiv for the other even though
one is a different type of a קרבן, korban, it's a one
that's brought in the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kadashim. Nevertheless, at least it's
קטורת and קטורת. Fine, that was just sort of saying that the
answer we gave yesterday is still a viable answer. Now the גמרא
Gemara continues. Okay, וכולן שחסרו. ve-chulan she-chasru. Now going back to our
משנה Mishna where our משנה Mishna says that even though the רבנן
Rabbanan say that it's כזית kezayis. is enough, remember רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says to be חייב chayiv you need the entire מתיר. matir.
If you're dealing with the meat of an עולה olah whatever fine
כזית kezayis. is enough to be חייב. chayav But if you're dealing
with the but if you're dealing with a מתיר matir like the
קומץ komets or something of that nature, then it's the full amount
because less than that it's not meaningful. It doesn't actually have the
effect. Okay, so that's רבי אליעזר's Rebbe Eliezer position. וחכמים אומרים va-Chachamim
omrim even a כזית kezayis. of the קומץ komets is fine. Outside,
fine, it's enough to be חייב chayav for outside. But now the
חכמים Chachamim agree that the כזית Kezayis of the קומץ komets but
the קומץ komets is whole. If actually a little bit of that
קומץ komets were to go missing, were it to be burnt or
destroyed, then they actually would agree that you're not חייב chayav for
the כזית because then there's no the מתיר matir doesn't exist anymore.
So it's not a so that loses sort of its meaning as
the מתיר. matir. Now I have to tell you that I find
this a little bit funny because trying to figure out why חסר
chaser, is different than some of the other פסולים. psulim. We said
before that anything that was פסולו בקודש psulo ba-Kodesh since אם עלו
לא ירדו, im alu lo yerdu, you know, you would, you know,
it you'd be חייב בחוץ. chayiv ba-chutz. So this certainly seems to
fall in that category of פסולו בקודש. psulo ba-Kodesh. I'm not exactly
sure why חסר chaser, is worse than let's say קבלת הדם, kabbalas
ha-dam, you know, by in a without a כלי שרת kli sharet.
or something. Oh, there we
go.
That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying in terms of that if
it's חסר, chasar? if it's not whole, the מתיר matir then even
the רבנן Rabanan agree that you're not חייב chayav for a כזית
of it. Okay, or similarly the way רש"י Rashi says even if
the remnant of the מנחה mincha is חסר, chaser, since under that
circumstances you're not allowed to be מקריב makriv the מתיר, matir, you're
not חייב chayav for doing the מתיר matir not חייב chayav for
doing the קומץ komets outside the בית המקדש. Beis ha-Mikdash Okay so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, איבעיא להו, ibaia lehu, they
raised the following question: חיסרון דחוץ שמי חיסרון או לא שמי חיסרון.
chisaron de-chutz shme chisaron o lo shme chisaron. What happens if it's
not that a little bit of the קומץ komets went missing in
the בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash and then you brought the rest outside,
or a little bit of the of the remnant of the מנחה?
mincha? But no, you brought the whole קומץ komets outside and then
a little went missing. Are you חייב chayav for doing a כזית
of what remains? Is that considered חסר? chasar. Okay, so what's the
issue? מי אמרינן כיון דנפיק איפסלו להו, mi amrinan keivan de-nafik ipsalu
lehu, this is similar to an issue we've had way way before
which is if you start in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
you brought it out, it also's a פסול, psul, it's a פסול
psul of יוצא. yotzei. So since anyway the קומץ komets becomes invalid
by being brought out and nevertheless you're חייב chayav for העלאת חוץ,
ha'alas chutz, that's exactly what the חיוב chiyuv is, okay? So we
don't care once it's brought out that it became פסול, pussul, you're
still going to be חייב chayav if you put it on the
מזבח. mizbeach, So if that's true, מה לי חסר מה לי יתר
mah lee chasar mah lee yeser or the better גירסא girsa is
מה לי יוצא. mah lee yotzei. What do I care what the
פסול psul is, whether it's because it went out of the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash? or because it's lacking? But lacking in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash. would then sort of, you know, label it as
a פסול קומץ pussul komets and then you're not חייב chayav, if
you bring it outside. But if you brought it outside when it
was כשר kasher and then something happened afterwards, who cares? It's already
פסול pussul anyway. That's one way of looking at it. או דילמא
o dilma would you say יוצא דאיתיה בעיניה אין דליתיה בעיניה לא.
yotzei de-isaya be-einaya in de-laisaya be-einaya lo. No, יוצא yotzei the whole
thing is still there and therefore it's like a פסול psul which
is like a label on it, but the entity exists. Whereas if
something is so maybe another פסול psul wouldn't be a problem, let's
say it would become טמא tamei or something. It's an interesting question.
But but if it's חסר, chasar. that changes the actual entity and
maybe that's considered to be now you can't be חייב chayav for
bringing part of this קומץ. komets. That's the question. So what's the
story? אמר אביי amar Abaye תא שמע ta shema come hear, רבי
אליעזר פוטר עד שיקריב את כולן. Rabbi Eliezer poter ad she-yakriv es
kulan. So רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer, says that, you know, we know
this, that רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer says you need the whole מתיר.
matir. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to of course say what relevance
is רבי אליעזר? Rebbe Eliezer We're asking for the חכמים Chachamim that
generally you only need a כזית. And the point is that even
for them if something is missing it's different. So that's what the
גמרא Gemara says back, very funny what the גמרא Gemara thought to
prove. אמר ליה רבה בר בר חנה. amar lei Rabbah bar bar
Chana. אמר ליה רבה בר בר חנה לאביי, Amar lei Rabba bar
Bar Chana l'Abaye, מידי רבי אליעזר פשיט מר? Midi Rabbi Eliezer pashit
mar? You want to try to learn something out from רבי אליעזר?
אמר Rabbi Eliezer Amar. ליה, so אביי Abaye says back yes, בפירוש
שמיע לי מיניה דרב, B'feirush shmia li minei d'Rav, I heard, I
have a tradition from רב, Rav עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה
דרבי אליעזר אלא דאיתיה בעיניה. Ad kan lo pligi rabbanan alei d'Rabbi
Eliezer ela d'isya b'inei. So it's not really what רבי אליעזר Rebbe
Eliezer says in the משנה, Mishnah, it's just a tradition I have
from רב that until now the חכמים Chachamim are only agreeing that...
disagreeing and saying you're חייב chayav. for כזית when the whole קומץ
kometz is still present, okay? דאיתיה בעיניה. d'isya b'inei. אבל בחסרון, Aval
b'chisaron,
but if some of that קומץ kometz went missing and then it
became not a legitimate מתיר matir anymore, in that case, מודה ליה
דלאו, modei lei d'lav, מודה ליה, modei lei, they would agree to
him that you would not be חייב chayav because because you would
not have the whole קומץ. kometz. So now that just says they
agree in a case of חסר. chasar? The משנה Mishnah says that
the רבנן Rabanan agree in a case of חסר. chasar That's not
asking answering our question, when did it where did it become חסר?
chasar
So the גמרא Gemara says so even this tradition of רב which
to some degree תוספות Tosfos already says is somewhat implicit in the
משנה. Mishnah. Anyway, it doesn't answer the question, are we talking about
when it's only when it's חסר chasar in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash. and then you know and then it already got labeled as
an invalid קומץ kometz or even if it's חסר chasar outside? Once
it's outside we've already pointed out it's already פסול. pasul. So the
גמרא Gemara says לאו דחסר בחוץ? lav d'chasar b'chutz? Isn't this talking
about even if it got if it became lacking outside the בית
המקדש? Beis HaMikdash. לא. No. Who says it? דחסר בפנים. d'chasar b'pnim.
We're talking about that it became חסר chasar in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash But if it became חסר after you took it out,
maybe that would not you know compromise it anymore and therefore you
would be חייב chayav? in that case. And now the גמרא Gemara
tries to just prove it from the line of the
משנה. Mishnah. תא שמע וכולן שחסרו והקריבן בחוץ פטור. Ta shma v'chullan
shechasru v'hikrivan b'chutz patur. Again the line in our משנה, Mishnah, funny
it didn't start there. If you're lacking a little bit you're going
to be
פטור. patur? So לאו דחסר בחוץ? lav d'chasar b'chutz? Aren't we talking
about that it became חסר even outside? לא דחסר בפנים. lo d'chasar
b'pnim. Again you can't prove where the חסרון chisaron took place. So
minimally of course the משנה's Mishnah talking about it was lacking inside
and therefore that somehow different from other פסולים psulim and you're not
חייב chayav. for the רבנן Rabanan if you do a כזית. If
it became lacking outside, that was the question which we have not
resolved. Okay. Next
משנה. Mishnah. מנחה שלא נקמצה והקריבה בחוץ פטור. Mincha shelo nikmetza v'hikriva
b'chutz patur. So now let's say you have the מנחה mincha that
you did not do a קומץ kometz of and you have your
whole מנחה mincha and you put your whole מנחה mincha on the
fire outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, And this is not a
מנחת כהן minchas kohen that that would be okay. This is a
normal מנחה. mincha. I mean not okay, whatever you'd be חייב chayav.
for that. But a normal מנחה. mincha. So since this normal מנחה
mincha is not yet ראוי לפתח אהל מועד rauy l'pesach ohel moed
an unkomtzed מנחה, mincha, this type of a thing is not fit
for הקרבה. hakrava. So in that type of a case you would
be exempt. Now what the משנה Mishnah doesn't say is and I
imagine this is the case,
you took this whole מנחה mincha outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash
Until now I guess we've been imagining you took the קומץ kometz
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or some כהן kohen did and
then you brought it outside and you were מקריב makriv it. Let's
say you took the whole מנחה mincha outside the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you did the קומץ kometz outside and you were מקריב makriv
the קומץ kometz outside. So you're not חייב chayav for the קומץ
kometz because we've learned that before that the special הלכה. halacha. Okay.
Are you חייב chayav for being מקריב makriv for taking the קומץ?
kometz? Are you חייב chayav. for being מעלה ma'aleh the קומץ? kometz?
So there maybe you would say no, you know a קומץ kometz
taken outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is invalid. So on the
other hand how's that different from שחיטה? shchita? If you שחט shcheted
outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. that's invalid and you're חייב chayav.
then for העלאה. ha'alah. So anyway that's not addressed in the משנה.
Mishnah. I would imagine if you took the קומץ kometz outside and
were מקריב makriv it as a separate קומץ kometz you'd be חייב,
chayav but the משנה Mishnah is talking maybe not. Anyway the simple
case of the משנה Mishnah is you put the whole מנחה mincha
and therefore that's not ראוי rauy for אהל מועד. ohel moed. קמצה
וחזרה ונתערבה בתוכה והקריבה בחוץ חייב. Kamtza v'chazra v'nisarva b'socha v'hikriva b'chutz
chayav. Now let's say you took a קומץ kometz let's for argument's
sake assume in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash? you took a קומץ
kometz and then you dropped the קומץ kometz back in the מנחה
mincha and mixed it all up. Oh wait, I'm sorry. I ran
to the משנה. Mishnah.
Bracket that. Go back. We didn't do the last three lines of
the גמרא Gemara. before on the on the end of the previous
משנה. Mishnah.
המקריב קדשים. Hamakriv kodashim. We'll get back to this in a second.
Okay. So the משנה Mishnah is if you go ahead and you
put the אימורין imurin wrapped up in the meat on the on
the altar outside the outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. you're פטור
patur. because you're not directly putting the... I'm sorry. The משנה Mishnah
says you're חייב chayav. because you're חייב. Chayav, The גמרא's Gemara going
to ask why are you not פטור? You're not directly putting the
אימורין imurin on the fire and that would not be considered a
legitimate הקרבה hakrava in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash, So why are
you חייב chayav for that outside of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash
So the גמרא Gemara says אמאי? Amai? Why are you חייב? chayav
והאיכא חציצה? V'ha'ika chatzitza? Isn't the meat a חציצה chatzitza between the
אימורין imurin and the fire? אמר שמואל כשהפכן. Amar Shmuel k'she'hafechan. No,
we're talking that you turned it over and that the אימורין imurin
directly came into contact with the fire. In which case תוספות Tosfos
says what's the חידוש? chiddush? But okay. ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו תימא
שלא הפכן. V'Rabbi Yochanan amar afilu teima shelo hafechan. You didn't turn
it over. ומאן ר' שמעון היא דאמר אפילו העלה על הסלע חייב.
U'man Rabbi Shimon hi d'amar afilu he'ela al hasela chayav. This is
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you don't need
the act of הקרבה hakrava although the object has to be ראוי
לפתח אהל מועד, rauy l'pesach ohel moed, the act of הקרבה hakrava
does not have to be like you do the הקרבה hakrava in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash It's sufficient that you do a הקרבה
hakrava that's a הקרבה hakrava on a במה. bama. So since he
says that on a במה bama you could be מקריב... makriv... something
just by putting it on a rock, and we’ve discussed this, presumably
not even burning it, just placing it on a rock. So therefore
out, so therefore as well, that’s when במות bamos are kosher, that
would be a legitimate הקרבה hakrava on a במה. bama. So here
too, it's true, this wouldn't come directly in contact with the fire.
But we're not measuring it by the act of the ritual in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash we're saying if it's a העלאה haala'ah
of a במה bama you're חייב. chayav. And for a במה bama
it's not about putting it on the fire, so even putting it
on the rock. So therefore you'd be חייב. Chayav רבא אמר מין
במינו אינו חוצץ. Rava amar min bemino eino chotetz. רבא says it's
meat and meat, and there’s no חציצה, chatzitza, and you would presumably
be יוצא yotzei in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. and therefore you're
חייב Chayav outside. Okay, now back to the משנה. mishna. Okay, מנחה
שלא נקמצה והקריבה בחוץ פטור. Mincha shelo nikmetza v'hikriva bachutz patur. You
didn't take the קומץ, komets, so you have the whole thing and
you put it on the fire. That's not חייב Chayav because that
would not be ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. rauy l'pesach ohel moed.
קמצה וחזר וקמצה לתוכה והקריבה בחוץ חייב. Kimtza v'chozer kimtza l'tocha v'hikriva
bachutz chayav. But if, however, you took the קומץ komets and then
you dropped it back in and mixed it in, and that you
did outside, you would be חייב. Chayav. Why? Because even though that
type of a קרבן korban you're not supposed to put on the
מזבח, mizbeach, if you do put it on the מזבח, mizbeach. you
don't take it down. Once the קומץ komets was taken, even if
now it's mixed up with the rest of the מנחה, mincha, if
the whole מנחה mincha is put on, it's like you put the
קומץ komets on and you're יוצא. yotzei. And therefore, out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, you're חייב. Chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says
ואמאי ליבטלו שיריים לקומץ? V’amai livatlu shirayim l’komets? Why? Why when you
drop the קומץ komets back in, why don't we say the rest
of the מנחה, mincha, which is a majority, nullifies the קומץ? komets?
And then you wouldn't be יוצא yotzei in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and not חייב chayav. outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash אמר
רבי זירא נאמר הקטרה בקומץ ונאמר הקטרה בשיריים. Amar Rebbe Zeira ne'emar
haktara b'komets v'ne'emar haktara b'shirayim. It speaks about the קומץ, komets, it
says you're מכתיר maktir it, burn it on the מזבח. mizbeach, And
by the שיריים shirayim it says don't be מכתיר maktir them, or
the way חז"ל Chazal read the פסוק, pasuk, don't be מכתיר maktir
the שיריים shirayim on the altar. So they're linked.
מה הקטרה דקומץ אין קומץ מבטל חבירו. Ma haktara d'komets ein komets
mevatel chaveiro. When you're putting the קומץ komets on the מזבח, mizbeach.
let's say you mixed up two קומצות kometzos from two different מנחות
minchos and put them on. Even if one was bigger, there would
not be ביטול. bittul. Why would there not be ביטול? bittul? Because
of the principle of אין עולין מבטלין זה את זה. ein olin
mevatlin zeh es zeh. Things that go on the altar don't negate
one another, they don't nullify one another. So if you mixed up
a קומץ komets with a קומץ, komets, it doesn't get negated. So
similarly, if you mix up a קומץ komets with the שיריים, shirayim,
even though the שיריים shirayim is not an עולה, oleh, it also
doesn't get negated because the word הקטרה is used by the שיריים
shirayim as well. אף הקטרת שיריים אין שיריים מבטלין קומץ. Af haktaras
shirayim ein shirayim mevatlin komets. Okay, and that's all the גמרא Gemara
has to say about that משנה. mishna. Next משנה. mishna. הקומץ והלבונה
שהקריב את אחד מהן בחוץ חייב. Hakomets v'halevona shehikriv es echad mehen
bachutz chayav.
So now you've got two מתירין. matirin. This is a classic case
of חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. You've got your מנחה mincha and the
thing that makes the מנחה mincha valid is
the
קומץ komets and the לבונה, levona, the frankincense, that is on the
מנחה. mincha. And without both of those, the מנחה mincha is invalid.
You go and you just take one of those and you do
it outside. So the answer should be obvious. For the חכמים you
don't need the whole מתיר, matir, so they would say you'd be
חייב. chayav רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer needs the whole מתיר matir and
he'd say you'd be פטור. So let's take a look. חייב, chayav
that's exactly what happened. רבי אליעזר פוטר עד שיקריב את השני. Rebbe
Eliezer poter ad sheyakriv es hasheini. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's good
to know that the world still spins and everything still works the
way it's supposed to be. He says you need the full, the
full מתיר. matir. Now, אחד בפנים ואחד בחוץ חייב. Echad bifnim v'echad
bachutz chayav. Now this is just like what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
said before about the קטורת. If you did the קומץ komets inside
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash since all you're left with now is
the לבונה, levona, or the reverse, you did the לבונה, levona, all
you're left with now is the קומץ, komets, and you did the
second one outside, you are חייב chayav because that is the whole
מתיר. matir. Now, שני בזיכי לבונה שהקריב את אחד מהן בחוץ חייב.
Shnei bezichei levona shehikriv es echad mehen bachutz chayav. Now, for the
לחם הפנים, Lechem Hapanim, in order for the כהנים kohanim to be
able to eat the לחם הפנים Lechem Hapanim on שבת, Shabbos, what
you do is there are two little like spoons that have לבונה,
levona, frankincense, in them, and you burn them on the altar and
then it allows the bread to be eaten. So here again, you're
going to burn these spoons of frankincense outside. Are you חייב chayav
by just doing one? So the חכמים say yes, you don't need
the full amount. רבי אליעזר פוטר עד שיקריב את השני. Rebbe Eliezer
poter ad sheyakriv es hasheini. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you need
both. But אחד בפנים ואחד בחוץ חייב. Echad bifnim v'echad bachutz chayav.
If you already brought one in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
now the second one is what's left, and that's the remainder of
the מתיר, matir, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would agree you're חייב. chayav
It's interesting because I don't know the exact שיעור, but I always
imagine that these are less than a כזית. Maybe I'm wrong, maybe
they are a כזית. But normally you presumably need a minimum of
a כזית. Maybe not. Maybe if these are בזיכין bezichin that gives
each one an independent meaningful identity that it's a full spoonful or
whatever and therefore maybe you don't need a כזית. Okay, let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara בעא רב יצחק נפחא. Baia Rebbe
Yitzchak Nafcha. רב יצחק בר נפחא Rebbe Yitzchak bar Nafcha asked the
following question. קומץ מהו שיתיר כנגדו בשיריים? Komets mahu sheyatir k'negdo b'shirayim?
This is a great conceptual question. You've got these two מתירין. matirin.
I'm going to read this like תוספות. Tosfos. You've got these two
מתירין. matirin. You've got the קומץ komets and the לבונה. levona. You
just did one on the מזבח. mizbeach. Let's not worry about חוץ
chutz just yet. You just did one on the מזבח. What is
the current status of the מנחה? mincha? Is the מנחה mincha 50%
of it is 50%... be eaten, and 50 percent is not fit
to be eaten. You don't know which is which, but, you know,
if you were to let's say eat the מנחה, Mincha, maybe you'd
have to eat two כזיתים, I don't know, maybe we had to
eat the whole מנחה Mincha because you don't know which, which 50
percent is which. But there still is, it's still not totally מותר,
Mutar, half of it is מותר, Mutar, half isn't, and therefore you
could be חייב מלקות Chayav Malkos for eating it. That's one possibility.
Each one works on a half, you just don't know which half.
Do you say that? או כחלושי מקלש? O Kechilushi Miklash?
Or maybe each one, they don't, you know, they don't cut it
this way, they cut it that way. Meaning, the first one lowers
the איסור, Issur, and the second one fully removes it. But it
relates to the whole מנחה. Mincha. What would be the נפקא מינה?
Nafka Mina? The נפקא מינה Nafka Mina might be you wouldn't get
מלקות Malkos maybe if you ate it after the first one. Maybe
it's not as forbidden because one of the מתירים Matirim are already
brought. Or maybe there's no מעילה. Me'ila. Okay, so it's a great
conceptual question. Obviously logically, I think we would all say the second
one. But anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אליבא דמאן?
Aliba Deman? Who is this according to whom is this question being
asked? אי אליבא דרבי מאיר דאמר מפגלין בחצי מתיר? Ei Aliba De'rabbi
Meir De'amar Mapiglin Bechatzi Matir? So hopefully you'll all remember that fun
phrase מפגלין בחצי מתיר. Mapiglin Bechatzi Matir. You have two things that
are מתיר. Matir. This is a perfect case of that, the לבונה
Levona and the קומץ. Kometz. And you had a פיגול Pigul thought
for one of those two. Half of the מתיר. Matir. Okay. Does
that make the קרבן פיגול? Korban Pigul? So for רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, he says it does make the קרבן פיגול. Korban Pigul. So
if it makes the קרבן פיגול, Korban Pigul, it must be that
that מתיר Matir actually made some part of that קרבן Korban you
were planning on eating, why would that be meaningful if that מתיר,
Matir, you know, did not actually change the status of that קרבן?
Korban? So for he would therefore say that it must be that
it actually does have an effect on half of the, half of
the מנחה. Mincha. I have to say I don't fully understand this
because, you know, you can have a פיגול Pigul thought when you're
doing שחיטה Shechita or catching the blood, and I mean the meat
still isn't מותר Mutar at that stage. It's just an עבודה. Avoda.
It's a פיגול Pigul thought at an עבודה. Avoda. It doesn't have
to be that that עבודה Avoda is making everything permissible. Anyway, that's
what the גמרא Gemara. is saying. According to רבי מאיר מפגלין בחצי
מתיר, Rabbi Meir Mapiglin Bechatzi Matir, if you can have פיגול Pigul
by half, משרא שרי. Mishra Shari. It must mean that that half
is effective, and that half makes half of the מנחה Mincha מותר.
Mutar. Oh, אי אליבא דרבנן דאמרי אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר? Ei Aliba
De'rabanan De'amri Ein Mapiglin Bechatzi Matir? And according to the רבנן that
you can't have a פיגול Pigul thought, לא משרא שרי ולא מכלוש
קליש. Lo Mishra Shari Velo Michlush Kalish. How do you know it
does anything? Maybe one of it does no effect, and only when
both of them, they have the full effect. That really is the
פשט. Pshat. Meaning, if you had a חדוש, Chiddush, you would presumably
say it weakens and then removes rather than half and half. But
if you really had a חדוש, Chiddush, you might say, who says
it's either of those? Until both are brought, nothing has, no change
has been effected. So the גמרא Gemara. says for the רבנן who
say אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, Ein Mapiglin Bechatzi Matir, you have no
evidence that anything is accomplished with less than both. And for רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir presumably it works that, that there is פיגול, Pigul,
presumably it works on half. Again, I, I would say for רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir it's either half or it's קלוש. Kalush. Like maybe
it has some effect, but anyway, it's not clear to me why
for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it has to be that it actually
had an effect. But anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara. is saying.
So one way or the other, your question is answered. Okay, גמרא
Gemara says, אי אליבא דרבנן דאמרי אין מפגלין או לא משרא ולא
מכלוש קליש. Ei Aliba De'rabanan De'amri Ein Mapiglin O Lo Mishra Velo
Michlush Kalish. אלא אליבא דרבי אליעזר. Ella Aliba De'rabbi Eliezer.
Maybe it's like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says you're not חייב
chayav until you do both מתירים Matirim outside. So the גמרא Gemara
says, wait, that's again, that's like you need them both combined and
there's no evidence that one of them has any meaning. So רבי
אליעזר כרבנן סבירא ליה דאמר אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר. Rabbi Eliezer Kerabanan
Sevira Lei De'amar Ein Mapiglin Bechatzi Matir. רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer you
know, the same way the rabbis say you don't have פיגול Pigul
with a half of מתיר, Matir, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you're
not חייב בחוץ Chayav Bachutz with half of a מתיר. Matir. So
there's no evidence that one of those two does anything. אלא אליבא
דרבנן דהכא מאי? Ella Aliba De'rabanan Dehacha Mai? So the question is
according to the rabbis that say you're חייב chayav with just the
קומץ Kometz outside or just the לבונה Levona outside. So for them,
it seems like one of those things has, does actually have an
effect. So according to them, what is, what is that effect? משרא
שרי או מכלוש קליש? Mishra Shari O Michlush Kalish? Is it that
it makes half permissible or that it weakens? תיקו. Tayku. And it
says תיקו. Tayku. Again, I don't understand this because for רבנן you're
also חייב chayav for כזית of the קומץ. Kometz. א כזית A
Kezayis of the קומץ Kometz doesn't have an effect. They don't need
a whole מתיר. Matir. So who's to prove to them that half
of a, that according to them, half of a מתיר Matir is
meaningful? I don't really understand this, but anyway, the question is an
interesting one. Okay, משנה. Mishna. Last משנה Mishna on the page. הזורק
מקצת דם בחוץ חייב. Hazorek Miktzas Dam Bachutz Chayav.
If somebody does not all of the blood, just part of the
blood, he's חייב. chayav Now that doesn't all mean all the blood
of the animal, but like doesn't even do all the applications of
the blood, just puts it on one corner of the altar, then
you're חייב. chayav Now that's pretty obvious even according to רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't argue here because that
is, you know, even by a חטאת Chatas that there's four applications,
we פוסקין Pasken that any one application of blood actually is a
מתיר. Matir. So even for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that needs a
whole מתיר, Matir, since בדיעבד Bediavad one application is a מתיר, Matir,
that he would agree and that's why he does not argue on
this משנה. Mishna. Now רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אמר. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says a different point. אף Af אף המנסך מהחג בחג בחוץ
חייב. af hamenasech mehachag bachag bachutz chayav. Okay, we had a ברייתא
braita before that said this, but here רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer saying
it in the משנה, Mishnah, that if you do ניסוך nisuch of
the water that you would use for ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim on
סוכות, Succos, you're חייב. hayyav Now the question would be: what's the
חידוש? chiddush? If you're חייב hayyav for the wine, you're חייב hayyav
for the water. Once you introduce the idea that ניסוך you're חייב
hayyav for outside, why is the water any different? So we'll see
in the גמרא. Gemara רבי נחמיה אומר שירי הדם שהקריבן בחוץ חייב,
Rabbi Nechemiah omer sheyarei hadam shehikrivan bachutz chayav, that רבי נחמיה Rabbi
Nechemiah says,
since he feels that that the pouring of the שיריים shirayim is
מעכב, meakev,
okay, this is... so therefore he says that if you pour the
שיריים shirayim outside you are חייב hayyav as well, that's a form
of הקרבה. hakravah. Okay, now we're going to have to see exactly
about that, why, anyway, we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara
You could have said that at that stage it's not exactly, since
it's no longer sort of a part of, it's only the remnant,
you already מקריב makriv the thing, you already put the דם dam
on the altar, you already put the meat on the altar, and
this is just some wrap-up stuff with the blood, maybe you would
think that you are not חייב hayyav for being מקריב makriv it,
and he says you are, and that... and we'll see whether that's
connected to an idea of that the spilling is מעכב, meakev, and
therefore it is still a necessary עבודה, avodah, and therefore it's ראוי
לפתח אהל מועד. rauy l'pesach ohel moed. Okay, that'll be tomorrow. Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara אמר
רבא ומודה רבי אליעזר בדמים. Amar Rava u'modeh Rabbi Eliezer bedamim. Now
this is explicit in the משנה Mishnah or implicit in the משנה.
Mishnah. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't argue on this idea of even
a little blood, so he's just making it explicit that that means
that he agrees that as opposed to needing the קומץ kometz and
the לבונה, levonah, the full amount of the קטורת and so on,
here he says even one application of blood, you don't need the
full applications of blood. Why? Because one is enough to be יוצא.
yotzei. Okay, דתניא רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים ממקום שפסק הוא מתחיל.
detanya Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon omrim mimakom shepasak hu matchil. Now this
is תוספות Tosafos sort of says this is really what רבא'ס Rava's
חידוש chiddush is, because the first point was implicit in the משנה.
Mishnah. The חידוש chiddush is even one application of the blood, let's
say from יום כיפור, of the blood that was done inside. And
the blood that was done inside, you know, the היכל or whatever
on יום כיפור, every single application is מעכב. meakev.
Okay, so if you need all of the applications to be מעכב,
meakev, for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer why are you חייב hayyav for
one application outside? He says you need the full amount. That is
a big חידוש. chiddush. And what's the answer? The answer is because
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that if some of the blood spilled,
you don't have to start the whole thing over again on יום
כיפור. So even though it is at the one hand you're not
יוצא yotzei yet, it's not the full מתיר matir in that sense,
but on the other hand it accomplished something. You don't have to,
you know, start again from scratch. So it did accomplish its own
thing, it accomplished this part of the עבודה. avodah. Okay, and therefore
that's evidence that it's meaningful even though it's not the whole מתיר
matir and you'd be חייב hayyav outside. That already is a חידוש.
chiddush. Okay, let's continue. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר אף המנסך מהחג בחוץ.
Rabbi Eliezer omer af hamenasech mehachag bachutz. Now we get to this
idea of ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim and we're going to figure out
what the חידוש chiddush is. If you're חייב hayyav for ניסוך היין,
nisuch hayayin, you're חייב hayyav for ניסוך המים. nisuch hamayim. So let's
take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי מנחם יודפאה. Amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Menachem Yudfaya. רבי אליעזר בשיטת רבי עקיבא רבו אמר.
Rabbi Eliezer beshitas Rabbi Akiva rabbo amar. Here's the חידוש: chiddush: he's
following רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva his רבי. rebbe. What's רבי עקיבא'ס... Rabbi
Akiva's... what's רבי עקיבא'ס רבו? Rabbi Akiva's rabbo? דתניא תנא ברייתא, detanya
tana braita, רבי עקיבא אומר ונסכיה בשנים. Rabbi Akiva omer u'nesacheha bishnayim.
This is by, you know, by the ניסוך היין, nisuch hayayin, by
the נסכים nesachim that come with the sacrifices on סוכות, Succos, on
the sixth day it says ונסכיה u'nesacheha and not ונסכו, v'nisko, and
ונסכיה u'nesacheha is in the plural. So that plural, its libations,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says בשני ניסוכים הכתוב מדבר. bishnai nesuchim hakasuv
medaber. He uses that to learn that the idea of ניסוך המים
nisuch hamayim is דאורייתא. d'oraysa.
Okay, and it's referring to two types of ניסוך. שני ניסוכים הכתוב
מדבר אחד ניסוך המים ואחד ניסוך היין. Shnai nesuchim hakasuv medaber echad
nisuch hamayim v'echad nisuch hayayin. So the חידוש chiddush is that ניסוך
המים nisuch hamayim is דאורייתא d'oraysa and because it's דאורייתא, d'oraysa, that's
why you're חייב hayyav outside. Now let's just pause here for a
second. תוספות Tosafos says this is wild. This suggests that there's an
opinion that ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim is Rabbinic. So תוספות Tosafos says,
I mean first of all what about the problem of חולין בעזרה?
chullin ba'azarah? Even if we bracket חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah and say
it's לאו דאורייתא, lav d'oraysa, that the Rabbis would come along and
establish a whole major ritual לכתחילה lechatchilah to do when it's not
something warranted by the תורה Torah is pretty shocking. And תוספות Tosafos
says, well, you know, maybe they did it because the idea of
water and the theme of water was so central on סוכות Succos
and they were in such need of water that they were prepared
to establish a special ritual in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, even
though it wasn't warranted by the תורה. Torah. So first of all
that's like a shocking thing. Okay, I mean if you take a
look at תוספות, Tosafos, he says it's תוספות אשתמיטתיה. Tosafos Ishtamitetei. It's,
but if it's in the wide lines of תוספות, Tosafos, let's say
where the lines get light, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, if you
look down six lines where it says מנחות Menachos in the half
paren in the half parenthesis at the end of the line, תוספות
Tosafos says: וזהו תימה דאפילו מאן דאמר חולין בעזרה לאו דאורייתא, v'zehu
teima d'afilu man d'amar chullin ba'azarah lav d'oraysa, even if it's not
a biblical violation to bring חולין בעזרה, chullin ba'azarah, it's still
astounding שתקנו חכמים לנסך חולין בעזרה, shetiknu chachamim lenasech chullin ba'azarah, that
the Rabbis would actually establish to... לכתחילה l'khathillah to do this ritual
which is not something that the Torah had recognized, and if you
want to frame it, not only the ritual isn't but the water
isn't really קודש for a קרבן, korban, you know, if it's not
something, so it's חולין. hullin. So then he says ושמא לפי שהוא
זמן גשמים כדי שיזכרו לפני המקום להתברך בימי גשמים. V'shema le-fi shehu
z'man geshamim kedei she-yizkeru lifnei ha-Makom le-hisbarekh bimei geshamim. Maybe, no, somehow
it was so important to be remembered before God. The funny thing
is, it's one thing to say like it's important symbolically for the
people, but you know, whether it's important to be remembered before God,
the idea that you're doing a ritual in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and that somehow means God will pay more attention even though
this isn't the ritual that God has asked for, I think like
there's a fascinating sort of theology going on there. Anyway, that's what
the גמרא Gemara says. That for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the חידוש
hiddush is that ניסוך המים nisukh ha-mayim is from the תורה Torah
and therefore you're חייב hayyav outside. So comes along the גמרא and
says like this: אמר ריש לקיש Amar Reish Lakish where were we?
אמר ליה ריש לקיש לרבי
יוחנן. Amar leh Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yohanan. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said
to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yohanan, אם על הלן שלושה לוגין אף כאן
שלושה לוגין. im al hallan shloshah lugin af kan shloshah lugin. One
minute, if he's basing himself on רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so he
should say רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learned it from the link to
wine. Well, the wine is שלושה לוגין, shloshah lugin, that's the minimum
amount of wine, so presumably the minimum amount of water for ניסוך
המים nisukh ha-mayim inside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is שלושה לוגין,
shloshah lugin, and therefore that should be the minimum you should be
חייב hayyav outside. Now you might remember the ברייתא braita yesterday actually
said that you're חייב hayyav for three... there is a minimum of
שלושה לוגין shloshah lugin to be חייב hayyav. outside. But here it
seems that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't say that. Why? והרי רבי
אליעזר כל שהוא קאמר. V'harei Rabbi Eliezer kol shehu ka'amar. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer didn't say a minimum amount and you know, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer has been big at talking about what the minimum amount
is. So it sounds like for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer even the
smallest amount you'd be חייב chayav outside, which means that you're יוצא
yotzei even the smallest amount inside and there is a position like
this. There's a position that ניסוך המים nisukh ha-mayim on סוכות, Succos,
it's not שלושה לוגין, shloshah lugin, it's לוג אחד log ehad or
maybe it's even a כל שהוא. kol-she-hu. So that's... so it's implicit
that רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer holding even a small amount, but that
can't be following רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because if you follow רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it would have to be שלושה לוגין. shloshah lugin.
That's question number one. Question number two: ואם על הלן בשאר ימות
השנה אף כאן בשאר ימות השנה. V'im al hallan bish'ar yemot ha-shanah
af kan bish'ar yemot ha-shanah. If you're basing yourself on רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, well that applies the rest of the year, so here
why are you only חייב chayav on סוכות? Succos? והרי רבי אליעזר
בחג קאמר. V'harei Rabbi Eliezer be-hag ka'amar. You're only חייב chayav on
סוכות. Succos. Now one minute, says תוספות Tosafos like this: since when
did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva say that you do ניסוך המים nisukh
ha-mayim the rest of the year? Like we never heard of such
a thing. So of course even רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says it's
only on סוכות. Succos. And if what the גמרא means is well
if you're חייב chayav on סוכות, Succos, if it's a מצוה mitzvah
of סוכות Succos in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash you're חייב chayav
the rest of the year outside, maybe, but it's not based on
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and תוספות Tosafos sort of thinks that that's
not really possible either. So תוספות Tosafos has a very interesting other
גירסא. girsa. תוספות's Tosafos גירסא girsa is that the evidence in the
גמרא is that for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who learns it from
ונסכיה u-nesakheha which is written on day six of סוכות, Succos, the
ניסוך המים nisukh ha-mayim only start... was only on day six, only...
and therefore only started on day six, I think. So therefore the
גמרא's question is not שאר ימות השנה, sh'ar yemot ha-shanah, it's שאר
ימות החג, sh'ar yemot ha-hag, that if it's based on רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, you'd only be חייב chayav on day six or maybe
six and seven. But according to what רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer, says,
you're חייב chayav any of סוכות. Succos. So since רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer implies (it's a great גירסא), girsa since רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
implies that you're חייב chayav on all the days of סוכות Succos
and even for a small amount, it can't be modeled after רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay. So now the גמרא says אשתמיטתיה, ishtamitayh, so
הא דאמר רבי אסי. ha d'amar Rabbi Assi. So you know, he,
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, when he asked this question (this is one
way of reading it), he forgot the other statement of רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yohanan. Meaning, and it's not like really a question why Reish
Lakish forgot this, but anyway. But the point is that there's another
non-רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva model of ניסוך המים nisukh ha-mayim that רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer could be going like, which would allow even a
small amount and would allow all the days of סוכות. Succos. What's
the other ניסוך המים nisukh ha-mayim model that's דאורייתא de-oraita but not
a רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva model? הא דאמר רבי אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן משום רבי נחוניא איש בקעת בית חורתן עשר נטיעות ערבה וניסוך
המים הלכה למשה מסיני. Ha d'amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yohanan mishum
Rabbi Nehunia ish Bik'at Beit Hortan esser nityot aravah v'nisukh ha-mayim halakhah
l'Moshe mi-Sinai. That this is actually not based on ונסכיה, u-nesakheha, it's
הלכה למשה מסיני halakhah l'Moshe mi-Sinai together with the ערבה aravah ritual
you would do on סוכות Succos and together with a special הלכה
halakhah about plantings in a field which we're not going to talk
about. So therefore, yes, he holds it's דאורייתא, de-oraita, a better treatment
may be אשתמיטתיה דרבי יוחנן. ishtamitayh d'Rabbi Yohanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yohanan
when he said, you know, that רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer follows רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, okay, he forgot, I mean it's funny because he
even taught this idea of הלכה למשה מסיני, halakhah l'Moshe mi-Sinai, but
he didn't think to say wait, no, it's דאורייתא de-oraita but not
the דאורייתא de-oraita of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, it's the דאורייתא de-oraita
of the הלכה למשה מסיני. halakhah l'Moshe mi-Sinai. And now it all
makes sense. Now you could be חייב chayav even a small amount
because that הלכה למשה מסיני halakhah l'Moshe mi-Sinai could hold you don't
need שלושה לוגין, shloshah lugin, and you could be חייב chayav on
any of the days of סוכות Succos because you would do it
all the days of סוכות. Succos. Okay, let's do the next piece.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught: המנסך שלושה לוגין מים בחג
בחוץ חייב. Ha-menasekh shloshah lugin mayim be-hag ba-hutz hayyav. Three log
you're חייב. Now רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon
omer because this is a little... little tricky, because we just said
a minute ago that רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer said even a כל
שהוא. kol-she-hu, But anyway, אם לן לשם חג חייב. im la'an l'sheim
chag chayav. So תוספות Tosafot has the גרסא girsa רבי אליעזר, Rebbi
Eliezer we'll read this like תוספות's Tosafot גרסאות. girsas. I will concede
you need three לוג log, if you filled it up for the
sake of the חג. chag. Normally I would say a כל שהוא,
kol-she-hu. but I would agree three לוג if you filled it up
for the sake of the חג. chag. What does this mean? So
מאי בינייהו, mai beinai-u, what's their debate about? אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, בישיר במים קמיפלגי. b'yesher b'mayim kamiflegi.
So he says look, the חכמים say like we just said a
minute ago, very nice, they hold maybe like רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
that you need a minimum of three לוג. And therefore they say
you're not חייב outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, unless you have
three לוג. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer we know says a כל שהוא.
kol-she-hu But remember רבי אליעזר said, we just read it at the
beginning of today's דף, רבי אליעזר says that if you put a
larger amount in a כלי kli and you that establishes that is
the amount for הקרבה. hakrava. So he says look, if you just
took a כל שהוא kol-she-hu and had כל שהוא kol-she-hu in a
כלי and brought it outside you'd be חייב because I say a
כל שהוא kol-she-hu, is enough for ניסוך המים. nisuch hamayim. But אם
מלן לשם חג, im mil'an l'sheim chag, if you decided your ניסוך
המים nisuch hamayim is going to be three לוג and you filled
up your כלי and you intended to use it in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash? as three לוג, then you won't be חייב for
any less than three לוג. That establishes three לוג as the שיעור
for the water. So that's beautiful. Everything fits. חכמים hold there's three
לוג, רבי אליעזר holds כל שהוא, kol-she-hu but he holds that a
כלי can change the amount. רב פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, רב
פפא Rav Pappa says, top of ק"ד עמוד ד', kuf yud daled
amud daled, בקרבו נסכים במדבר פליגי. b'kirbu nesachim bamidbar pligi. They're debating
whether you brought נסכים nesachim in the, you know, in the מדבר.
midbar. Now that has got to be one of the most cryptic
statements. What does that have to do with this debate? So here's
how רש"י connects the dots. The תורה Torah says when it commands
the נסכים nesachim that goes with the קרבנות, korbanot, it says כי
תבואו אל הארץ, ki tavo'u el ha'aretz, when you come to the
land. Which sounds like they didn't bring the נסכים nesachim in the
מדבר, midbar, which is the simple read. Fine. And if that's true,
it's telling you wait till you get to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and then you'll bring it when you have like a central בית
המקדש and the implication would be because you don't have any special
פסוק pasuk to tell you otherwise that they wouldn't be brought on
a במה. bama. Fine.
If you say however that they brought the נסכים nesachim in the
מדבר, midbar, what does it mean כי תבואו אל הארץ? ki tavo'u
el ha'aretz? So according to that approach כי תבואו אל הארץ ki
tavo'u el ha'aretz is telling them that when you come into the
land, even when you no longer have a central משכן Mishkan like
you have here and even when you have private במות, bamot, bring
נסכים nesachim on your private במה. bama. So ultimately this question did
they bring it in the מדבר midbar turns into a debate of
were there נסכים nesachim on private במות. bamot. Now you'll remember something
that works on a private במה, bama, even if it doesn't work
like in the בית המקדש, okay, something that works on a private
במה, bama, you're חייב for out as for bringing it when in
a time of איסור במות. issur bamot. So we're talking here that
you have the wine and you have the water or whatever and
you did not sanctify it in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. Okay
and you didn't sanctify it in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. Are
you חייב outside the בית המקדש? So normally you would say no,
it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, ra-uy l'petach ohel mo'ed, okay, and
that's what רבי אליעזר says. רבי אליעזר says you have to be
מלען לשם חג לחייב mil'an l'sheim chag l'chayeiv means you need to
fill it in a כלי שרת. kli sharet Without a כלי שרת
kli sharet. it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד ra-uy l'petach ohel mo'ed
and you're going to be exempt. And the rabbis say no, since
it was קרבו נסכים במדבר, karvu nesachim bamidbar, that means that נסכים
nesachim were also brought on a private במה bama and on a
private במה bama there's no כלי שרת. kli sharet And since there's
no כלי שרת kli sharet. on a private במה, bama, therefore you're
going to be חייב even without a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So
according to that the debate isn't three versus a כל שהוא kol-she-hu
but the כל שהוא kol-she-hu could become three if you put it
in a כלי שרת. kli sharet Here maybe both sides agree even
a כל שהוא that's not even what they're discussing and the question
is do you need a כלי שרת kli sharet. to be חייב
because did does a במה bama did you have נסכים nesachim on
a במה bama and if you did it wouldn't have needed a
כלי שרת. kli sharet. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, בלמידין ניסוך המים מניסוך
היין פליגי. b'limadim nisuch hamayim mi-nisuch hayayin pligi. No, here's the debate.
Everybody agrees that ניסוך היין nisuch hayayin they did on their private
במות bamot without a כלי שרת. kli sharet. And ניסוך היין nisuch
hayayin you're חייב on a במה bama when their במות bamot are
forbidden without a כלי שרת. kli sharet Okay, but the question is
how about מים? mayim? The ניסוך of מים mayim never occurred on
a private במה, bama, that's a communal sacrifice. And therefore the question
is if you can if you're חייב with ניסוך היין nisuch hayayin
without a כלי שרת kli sharet, are you also חייב with ניסוך
המים? nisuch hamayim? So again the basic same way that the rabbis
don't need a כלי שרת, kli sharet, רבי אליעזר does, but rather
than the debate of about whether you had a כלי שרת, kli
sharet, whether you had wine on a במה bama without a כלי
שרת, kli sharet, the question is you certainly had wine without a
במה bama on a במה bama without a כלי שרת, would the
same be true about water and that is the debate. Okay, we'll
pick up with here tomorrow.