Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף Daf is מ"ג, Mem Gimmel,
זבחים Zevachim 43. We left off in the middle of the משנה.
Mishna. We are picking up on the top of מ"ג עמוד א'
Mem Gimmel Amud Aleph and the משנה Mishna is talking about what
types of things, if you consume them when an animal becomes פיגול,
Pigul, if you consume it that you get כרת. Kares. So by
which things does this apply? And the basic principle is it is
something that is made permissible whether for human consumption or for being
burned on the מזבח Mizbeach through something else. All right, so maybe
we'll just take the משנה Mishna again from the beginning to see
that and the things that do not work in that מתיר Matir
and הניתר, Nittar,
the status of פיגול Pigul would not apply to the object itself.
So let's take a look. We'll start again from the beginning of
the משנה. Mishna. ואלו דברים שאין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול. Ve'elu Devarim
She'ein Chayavin Aleihem Mishum Pigul. This is the bottom of מ"ב עמוד
ב'. Mem Bet Amud Bet. The following things are not obligated because
of פיגול Pigul meaning that if you eat them you have not
considered to have eaten פיגול. Pigul.
הקומץ, Hakometz, the hand breadth that you take that you put not
handful I should say that you take from the מנחה Mincha and
that you burn it on the מזבח. Mizbeach. So that is מתיר
Matir the מנחה. Mincha. So the שיריים, Shirayim, the remnant of the
מנחה Mincha has פיגול, Pigul, but this the מתיר Matir itself and
it doesn't make anything else permissible, it itself just gets burned. So
there's no פיגול Pigul that applies to that even if the מנחה
Mincha becomes פיגול. Pigul. If you ate the remainder of the מנחה
Mincha you would get כרת. Kares. If you ate the הקטורת Haketoress
you would not get
כרת Kares at least for פיגול. Pigul. והקטורת, Vehaketoress, similarly the burning
of the קטורת, Ketoress, that's just something you burn straight, it's not
מתיר Matir something else so to speak. It's not something that is
made מותר Mutar by something else. והלבונה Vehalvonah and the frankincense also
same
point, something that would be burned straight and not made permissible by
something else. ומנחת כוהנים Uminchat Kohanim the מנחה Mincha that any כוהן
Kohen brings. Anytime a כוהן Kohen brings a מנחה Mincha the whole
מנחה Mincha is burned. So it again when the whole thing is
burned it doesn't have a מתיר Matir and הניתר. Nittar.
ומנחת כוהן משיח Uminchat Kohen Mashiach and also the כוהן גדול Kohen
Gadol would bring a standard מנחה Mincha every day, half in the
morning, half in the evening, also followed the הלכה Halacha that the
whole thing would be burned. והדם, Vehadam, the blood of a קרבן.
Korban. That again is the מתיר, Matir, but the blood never becomes
מותר Mutar through something else. So even if by throwing the blood
you made the קרבן Korban פיגול Pigul and you get כרת Kares
for eating the meat, you would not get כרת Kares for eating
the blood. Again, for פיגול. Pigul. And there is כרת Kares for
eating blood. והנסכים הבאים בפני עצמן דברי רבי מאיר. Vehanesachim Haba'im Bifnei
Atzman Divrei Rabbi Meir. And when you bring נסכים Nesachim wine libations
independently. So somebody could just make a נדר Neder to bring wine
and it would get poured on the מזבח Mizbeach and so that
obviously again there's no two
stages, but the reason it says דברי רבי מאיר Divrei Rabbi Meir
is because what's implicit is that however wine libations that come together
with a קרבן, Korban, right when you bring the מנחה Mincha and
the נסכים Nesachim that you bring with the קרבנות, Korbanot,
then that according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would be פיגול Pigul
because by throwing the blood of the קרבן Korban the blood is
the מתיר. Matir. What becomes permissible? What becomes permissible is the meat
for consumption and the wine and the נסכים Nesachim that came with
it to be put on the מזבח. Mizbeach. Okay, so therefore he
says that does follow the מתיר Matir and הניתר Nittar category. וחכמים
אומרים אף הבאים עם
הבהמה. Vachachamim Omrim Af Haba'im Im Habehemah.
No, even when it comes with the בהמה Behemah it is not
conceived of as the מתיר Matir and הניתר. Nittar. Why? Because even
the נסכים Nesachim that come together with an animal, the הלכה Halacha
is that you could bring them on a later day after bringing
the קרבן. Korban. So therefore the חכמים Chachamim say the קרבן Korban
is not מתיר Matir the נסכים Nesachim and therefore certainly not when
it's on a different day. You never have something that yesterday because
of what you did is מתיר Matir something today and therefore even
when you bring them on the same day the mechanism is the
same, the קרבן Korban is not מתיר Matir the נסכים Nesachim and
they remain independent and therefore it's just the נסכים Nesachim being brought
by themselves. You're obligated to bring it because of the קרבן Korban
but it's not being made permissible because of the קרבן Korban and
therefore it doesn't fall into פיגול. Pigul. Now we have a similar
debate about another case.
לוג שמן של מצורע. Log Shemen Shel Metzora. You bring a מצורע
Metzora when he goes through the טהרה Tahara process on the eighth
day brings an אשם Asham and with it a לוג Log of
שמן. Shemen. A לוג Log is about 12 ounces
and that לוג Log of שמן Shemen is used to put on
his ear and to put on his thumb, etc. and it's part
of the purification process. And later the גמרא Gemara learns out elsewhere
that the remainder of the לוג Log is eaten by the כוהנים.
Kohanim. Okay, so it definitely only operates together with the אשם. Asham.
You need the blood of the אשם Asham being. put on the
מצורע Metzora first in order to put the לוג log of the
שמן, shemen, but is the דם dam of the אשם asham a
מתיר mattir for the לוג log or not? So, the first position
says, לוג שמן של מצורע. Log Shemen Shel Metzora. The לוג שמן
של מצורע Log Shemen Shel Metzora regarding the לוג שמן Log Shemen
of the מצורע, Metzora, רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer אין חייבין
עליו משום פיגול. ein chayavin alav mishum piggul.
You're not חייב chayav because of פיגול, piggul, the blood is not
a מתיר. mattir. And very similar to the נסכים, nesachim, what's the
evidence of it? That you can,
because you can go ahead and bring the לוג שמן Log Shemen
on the day on a later day after you have already brought
the אשם. asham. And therefore clearly when you bring it on a
later day, this is just like the נסכים, nesachim, the mechanism in
that case is not that the קרבן korban was a מתיר mattir
for it. So therefore even when you bring it on the same
day, the קרבן korban is not a מתיר mattir for it. So
therefore that is just like the חכמים Chachamim when it comes to
the נסכים. nesachim. רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer but רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir
says חייבין עליו משום פיגול שדם האשם מתירו. chayavin alav mishum piggul
shedahm ha'asham matiro.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, you are חייב chayav for פיגול
piggul because when you bring it on the same day, the mechanism
is different. When you bring it on the same day with the
אשם, asham, the blood of the אשם asham actually is a מתיר.
mattir. Just like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says when you bring the
נסכים nesachim with the בהמה behemah on the same day, the blood
of the קרבן korban is a מתיר. mattir.
Okay, וכל שיש לו מתירין בין לאדם בין למזבח חייבין עליו משום
פיגול. vechol sheyesh lo matirin bein leadam bein lemizbe'ach chayavin alav mishum
piggul. So those are the things that don't have פיגול, piggul, and
now the flip side. Anything that does become מותר mutar that something
else is מתיר mattir it, there is פיגול, piggul, whether it is
become מותר mutar through the other thing for human consumption or whether
it becomes מותר mutar to be burnt or placed on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. So now we're going to expose that out. העולה, Ha'olah, so
when it comes to an עולה, olah, burnt offering, דמה מתיר את
בשרה למזבח ועורה לכהנים. damah mattir et besarah lemizbe'ach ve'orah lakohanim. The
blood makes the meat fit for being, even though the meat is
not eaten by people, to put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. You can't
put the meat on the מזבח mizbe'ach until you sprinkle the blood.
So the blood makes the meat, is מתיר mattir the meat to
be put on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And therefore were you to eat
from that meat in a case of a פיגול קרבן, pigul korban,
you a קרבן korban, that became פיגול, piggul you would be חייב
chayav in פיגול. piggul, And it also makes the skin permissible for
the לכהנים, Kohanim, that makes it allowed for them to benefit from
the leather, the hide of the animal. Okay, not like you that
would be ראוי אכילה ra'uy achilah but that is how it the
mechanism from the פיגול piggul. perspective, but that is the mechanism of
how it works. עולת העוף Olah HaOf דמה מתיר את בשרה למזבח.
damah mattir et besarah lemizbe'ach. By an עולת העוף, Olah HaOf, it's
similar, you burn the whole thing, and the blood makes the meat
of the bird fit for the מזבח. mizbe'ach. There is no hide
that goes to the לכהנים Kohanim and if it was it became
a פיגול piggul קרבן korban and you ate the meat, you would
be חייב chayav because the meat was made מותר mutar through the
blood. חטאת העוף Chatat HaOf דמה מתיר את בשרה לכהנים. damah mattir
et besarah lakohanim. A חטאת העוף, Chatat HaOf, the blood makes the,
did I skip, hold on, yeah
it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara it does not talk about a
straight חטאת. Chatat. Okay, it went straight to the birds. Anyway, חטאת
העוף Chatat HaOf דמה מתיר את בשרה לכהנים. damah mattir et besarah
lakohanim. So a חטאת העוף Chatat HaOf the לכהנים Kohanim eat the
meat of it like they eat a meat of a normal חטאת
Chatat and the blood makes the meat permissible to the לכהנים. Kohanim.
Could have said a normal חטאת Chatat of a בהמה behemah as
well. Okay, פרים הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim veSeirim HaNisrafim, how about
the things that you sprinkle the blood inside the היכל Heichal and
that they the meat gets taken out and gets burnt out outside?
So it would seem there there's nothing that's being made מותר. mutar.
So no, דמן מתיר את אימוריהם לקרב. daman mattir et emureihem lekarev.
It even by those types of חטאות, Chata'ot, the meat isn't מותר
mutar for human consumption or for the consumption of the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
but the innards,
the fat and the entrails of that חטאת Chatat are burnt on
the מזבח mizbe'ach and they can only be burnt on the מזבח
mizbe'ach when the blood is thrown. So the even the blood of
a חטאת הנשרפות Chatat HaNisrafos where everything is burnt outside, it's not
everything. The אימורים emurim are put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, the blood
makes that permissible for the מזבח mizbe'ach to consume it. And if
you were to eat those אימורים emurim by a פיגול piggul קרבן,
korban you would be חייב chayav כרת. kares. רבי
שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer כל שאינו מזבח החיצון כשלמים אין חייבין
עליו משום פיגול. kol she'eino mizbe'ach hachitzon kishlamim ein chayavin alav mishum
piggul. Position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we've seen before that he
says there's another no, I don't agree by these things that you
sprinkle the blood on the inside in the היכל Heichal because not
because they're נשרפים, nisrafim, but because the תורה Torah speaks about פיגול
piggul multiple times in the context of שלמים. Shelamim. And from that
I learn out that only something that is placed on the outer
מזבח mizbe'ach can become פיגול, piggul just as a categorically excludes things
that are only done on the inner מזבח, mizbe'ach, or at least
the blood is done on the inner מזבח. mizbe'ach. You burn the
entrails of the even of the פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim on the
outer one, but the fundamental מתיר mattir of the blood is done
on the inner מזבח. mizbe'ach. from the inner מזבח, mizbeach, so for
רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that excludes it from the category of פיגול.
piggul, Okay, let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
עולא Amar Ulla said. אמר עולא: Amar Ulla: קומץ פיגול שהעלו על
גבי מזבח פקע פיגולו ממנו. Komitz pigul she-he'alo al gabei mizbeach paka
pigulo mimenu. If you take a קומץ kometz of the, you know,
the handful of
a
מנחה mincha and you had a פיגול pigul. thought and the מנחה
mincha became פיגול pigul and you put it on the מזבח, mizbeach,
because it's being put on the מזבח, mizbeach, its status of פיגול
pigul gets removed. פקע פיגולו ממנו Paka pigulo mimenu the פיגול pigul
status got flies away from it. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to try to ask like for what הלכה halacha are you saying
this? But before you even get to that, here's his explanation. אם
אחרים מביא לידי פיגול הוא עצמו לא כל שכן? Im acherim meivi
lidei pigul, hu atzmo lo kol shekein?
If it can bring other things to פיגול, pigul because we will
remember that something only becomes פיגול pigul, once הקריבו כל מתיריו, hikrivu
kol matirav, or only once all of the things that make the
קרבן מותר, korban mutar, you know, only once the מתיר matir is
offered up, does the animal become פיגול. pigul If you stopped in
mid-process, even if you had a פיגול pigul. thought, the animal wouldn't
be פיגול. pigul So what he's saying is when you burn the
קומץ kometz on the מזבח, mizbeach, okay, of the מנחה mincha of
a פיגול pigul. קרבן, korban, so it's מביא אחרים לידי פיגול. mevi
acherim lidei pigul. It makes the שיריים shirayim into פיגול. pigul. And
you needed it to be burned in order to make the שיריים
shirayim into פיגול. pigul. So if it can do that, make the
שיריים shirayim into פיגול, pigul,
so הוא עצמו לא כל שכן? hu atzmo lo kol shekein? Can't
it do the same for itself? Now, that's a bizarre point because
your claim is that it loses its פיגול pigul status and it
sounds like you're trying to make a קל וחומר kal vachomer if
it can make the שיריים shirayim פיגול, pigul, it should make itself
פיגול. pigul. So that's what the גמרא Gemara wants to first figure
out the logic and then we'll figure out the ramifications of the
הלכה. halacha. So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי קאמר? mai qamaar? What
is what does he mean to say? הכי קאמר, Hachi qamaar, here's
what he means to say: אם אינו מתקבל
היכי מביא אחרים לידי פיגול? Im eino mitkabel, heich mevi acherim lidei
pigul? I will prove to you that the קומץ kometz is seen
as not itself פיגול. pigul. Why?
Because if it were seen as פיגול, pigul, the קומץ, kometz, it
would not be like the קרבן korban was done properly and it
would not have made the שיריים shirayim into פיגול. pigul. So the
fact that it makes the שיריים shirayim into פיגול pigul shows that
we look at it as if the קרבן korban was offered properly
and as if that קומץ kometz itself was not פיגול. pigul. All
right, so that's already an interesting point and it's really true, right?
We say the whole rest of the קרבן korban has to be
done properly, bracketing the fact that the דם dam or the קומץ
kometz is פיגול. pigul. So he says, well, that shows you that
at some level we're looking at it as though the קומץ kometz
itself is not פיגול. pigul.
So the way to read that into his statement is: אם אחרים
מביא לידי פיגול הוא עצמו לא כל שכן? Im acherim meivi lidei
pigul, hu atzmo lo kol shekein? If it makes the שיריים shirayim
into פיגול, pigul, isn't it a קל וחומר kal vachomer that it
itself must be seen of as not פיגול pigul or else how
could it make the קרבן- korban how could it be considered that
הקריבו כל מתיריו? Okay, so that's his argument. So now we have
to figure out, okay, for what הלכה halacha exactly are you saying
this? So גמרא Gemara says, מאי קמשמע לן? mai kamashmalan? What are
you trying to teach us? אי דאין חייבין עליו משום פיגול Ee
dee-ein chayavin alav mishum pigul if you're trying to say that if
you eat from the קומץ, kometz, you're not חייב פיגול chayav pigul
because at some level it's the thing that you're offering that makes
it a good קרבן korban is is looked at as if that
מתיר matir is not
פיגול. pigul. תנינא Tanina that's already in our משנה mishna that you're
not חייב chayav on פיגול pigul for the
for the קומץ. kometz. אלו דברים שאין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול הקומץ
והקטורת והלבונה מנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח ומנחת נסכים והדם. Eilu devarim
she-ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul: hakometz ve-haktoret ve-halevona minchat kohanim ve-minchat kohen
mashiach ve-minchat nesachim ve-hadam. All the things. Now, the interesting point to
point out is also not only did we already teach it, but
the logic is different. The logic of the משנה mishna is that
פיגול pigul only doesn't apply to the מתיר, matir, it only applies
to the thing that is ניתר. nitar. עולא's Ulla logic is that
it's as if there's no פיגול pigul on the מתיר matir itself.
Maybe that would be the explanation of the משנה. mishna. The reason
פיגול pigul doesn't apply to a מתיר matir is because at some
level we look at the מתיר matir as if it weren't פיגול.
pigul. But anyway the גמרא Gemara is saying that that's already being
taught in our משנה. mishna. אלא Ela so if עולא's Ulla trying
to be מחדש mechadesh something, so אלא דאם עלו לא ירדו. ela
de-im alu lo yardu. Maybe what he's telling us is that if
this קומץ kometz was put up on the מזבח, mizbeach, this פיגול
קומץ, pigul kometz, we look at it as if it's not פיגול.
pigul. It's for the הלכה halacha that you don't have to now
take it off the מזבח mizbeach once you realize what you have
done. So the גמרא Gemara says, תנינא, tanina, but we already taught
that as well. הלן והיוצא והטמא ושנשחט חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו אם
עלו לא ירדו. Halan vehayotzei vehatamei veshenishchat chutz lizmano vechutz limkomo im
alu lo yardu. Right? So a משנה mishna we're going to say
later on teaches us that a lot of things that are פסול
pasul and are not allowed to be put on the מזבח, mizbeach,
once you put them on the מזבח, mizbeach, you don't take them
off. Something that is לן, lan, that's a case of לן, lan,
something meat that was taken out or blood that was taken out-
out or whatever outside the environs, and something that became טמא, tamei,
and a case of חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו, chutz l'zmano v'chutz limkomo,
meaning פיגול pigul and חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. All those types of
things, don't put them on the מזבח, Mizbeach, but if you did
put them on, you don't take them off. And by the way,
that has nothing to do with it's as if it's not פיגול,
pigul, because it applies to a wide range of invalid things that
are פסול, pasul, and it's a different הלכה, halacha, if something is
on the מזבח, Mizbeach, you don't remove it. So the גמרא Gemara
says, so that can't be what עולא Ula is teaching us. ואיבעית
אימא
דאם ירדו יעלו. v'iba'is eima d'im yardu ya'alu. So maybe what he's
telling us is, and maybe specifically for פיגול, pigul, no, by the
קומץ komets of- by the קומץ komets that's פיגול, pigul, at some
level we're looking at it as if the קומץ komets itself is
not פיגול. pigul. Oh, well if that's true, maybe the חידוש chiddush
would be that even if you took it off the מזבח, Mizbeach,
you now should put it back on, because it's not just to
leave it up there, but we're really looking at it as if
it's not פיגול, pigul, so now you should proactively put it back
on. But the גמרא Gemara says, but that's not true. הא
נמי תנינא. ha nami tanina. Now here הא נמי תנינא ha nami
tanina doesn't mean we taught the same thing in a משנה, Mishnah,
but we taught a משנה Mishnah that actually shows that that's wrong.
Okay? כשם שאם עלו לא ירדו, keshem she'im alu lo yardu, the
same way if they got put on the מזבח Mizbeach they don't
get taken off, כך אם ירדו לא יעלו, kach im yardu lo
ya'alu, similarly if they were taken off, you don't put them back
on. And that list explicitly included פיגול. pigul. So conceptually that was
a nice point, oh, we look at it as if the קומץ
komets itself, the מנחה minchah is פיגול, pigul, but as if the
קומץ komets itself is not, that- okay, but if you really want
to go by that, that would say, put it back up on
the מזבח, Mizbeach, but that's not the הלכה. halacha. So clearly that
can't be your point.
So the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא שמשלה בהן האור. lo tzericha
shemashlah bahen ha'ur. No, no, עולא's Ula point is that when it's
a case where yes, it would be a case where it would
get taken down and put back up, but it would be an
exception to the rule we talked before, it would be a case
where the majority of it had already been burnt on the מזבח.
Mizbeach. And once, well, you know, once the thing had actually been
burnt by the fire of the מזבח, Mizbeach, I mean the fire
משלה בהן, mashlah bahen, like had, you know, sovereignty over them, the
fire really took hold of it. So once that's true, רש"י Rashi
sort of says it נעשה לחמו של מזבח. na'aseh lachmo shel Mizbeach.
Now it's like transformed. Now it's already seen as, you know, as
belonging to the מזבח, Mizbeach, and once that's true, you know, the
מזבח Mizbeach consumed it. So once that's true, the הלכה halacha is
even when it's taken down, you put it back up. So maybe
that's what שמואל Shmuel is telling us. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הא נמי אמרה עולא חדא זימנא. ha nami amrah Ula chada zimna.
Well, עולא Ula already told that הלכה halacha at a previous time.
דאמר עולא, d'amar Ula, עולא Ula said, לא שנו אלא שלא משלה
בהן האור. lo shanu ela shelo mashlah bahen ha'ur. When does the
later משנה Mishnah say that when פסול pasul things are taken down,
you don't put them back up? That's only before the fire of
the מזבח Mizbeach has, you know, consumed it, has taken sovereignty over
it, has taken hold of it. אבל משלה בהן האור יעלו, aval
mashlah bahen ha'ur ya'alu, once it's- it's taken hold of it, then
you would put it back up even if it was brought down
because then it's transformed and it's like part of the מזבח. Mizbeach.
So besides the idea that עולא Ula already said it, again like
we were saying before, it's also clearly a different principle here. עולא's
Ula statement was specifically about פיגול, pigul, it's as if the מתיר
mattir itself is not פיגול, pigul, only the remainder is פיגול. pigul.
Okay, but here, this idea that משלה בהן האור mashlah bahen ha'ur
applies to all the פסולים psulim and it's a completely different mechanism.
So what is עולא Ula saying that he has not- that we
don't already know or that he has not already told us? So
the גמרא Gemara is going to go with the last answer, surprisingly.
The גמרא Gemara says like this, no, לא צריכא שמשלה בהן האור.
lo tzericha shemashlah bahen ha'ur. No, he is telling us this הלכה
halacha that if the fire takes hold you can put it back
up. And he still wanted to make the point specifically about the
קומץ komets of the מנחה minchah that is פיגול. pigul. מהו דתימא
mahu d'teima because I might have thought הני מילי hani mili that's
only true top of מ"ג ע"ב mem gimmel amud bet הני מילי
אבר hani mili aver if you have a limb of a קרבן
korban and the fire, you know, took hold of most of it,
then you would go- then it got- and it was a פסול
קרבן, pasul korban, even if it got brought back down, you would
put it back up. That was the first teaching of עולא. Ula.
But that's true about something that's a like a whole unit. אבל
קומץ דמפרת aval komets d'mifrat but a case of the handful of
the מנחה minchah that it sort of can be broken into pieces,
so what the fire does for part of it won't define the
remainder of it. אימא לא, eima lo, because the הלכה halacha as
I said before is even if it's only משלה בהן האור ברובו,
mashlah bahen ha'ur berubo, the גמרא Gemara should have said that here
about- that's the point. Even if the fire only sort of took
hold of the majority of it. So, you know, if you have
a big drumstick up there, so once it took hold of the
majority of it, the whole drumstick now has transformed and even if
it gets brought brought down, you bring it back up. But if
it's like just
a big chunk of a מנחה, mincha, flour and oil, and the
majority the fire took hold of, so it's not so obvious if
it's brought down, bring it back up, because that you could just,
you know, what makes that still one unit? Maybe it actually even
did shatter into multiple units. So the חידוש chidush is, so then,
you know, the part that the fire didn't take hold of, we
should look at as a separate unit and say that even if
that got taken back, taken down, you wouldn't put it back up.
So עולא's Ulla telling you, no, since it's put up as one
unit, we always conceptually look at it as one unit, and even
if it's broken into pieces, once the fire has taken over the
majority of it, then it's like that whole unit has now become
transformed into the לחמו של מזבח, lachmo shel mizbeach, the food of
the מזבח, mizbeach, and if it's taken down, even though it's פיגול,
pigul, you would put it back up. Okay, so that's at least
explaining an implication of it, but again, I do need to emphasize
that it has nothing to do with עולא's Ulla logic of like
it's as if the מתיר matir itself is itself not פיגול pigul
because it's being מתיר matir the rest. This is now just a
הלכה halacha that applies to all פסולין. psulin. Okay, he could have
said if you have a מנחה mincha that's טמא, tamei, you know,
if you could have a
מנחה mincha that was יוצא, yotzei, any type of פסול, psul, the
חידוש chidush is just משלבא ביה mashlaba beih or ברובו, berubo, once
the fire takes hold of most of it, it transforms it, even
if it's something like flour and oil, and even if it's something
that's in different parts, and if part of it got brought down,
you would bring it back up. Alright, so it doesn't really fit
with עולא's Ulla previous logic. It's probably nicer to say that עולא
Ulla was explaining, giving a level of explanation for the logic of
the משנה. mishna. The reason פיגול pigul doesn't apply to the מתיר
matir is because at some level the מתיר, matir, we're framing it,
you know, we're seeing it as if it's not פיגול, pigul, so
we can say that the מתיר matir of the קרבן korban, was
brought. But anyway, this is where the גמרא Gemara lands. אמר רב
אחאי, Amar Rav Achai, so רב אחאי Rav Achai said, often אמר
רב אחאי Amar Rav Achai is sometimes understood to be גאוני, Geonic,
but anyway, אמר רב אחאי Amar Rav Achai here, הלכך, hilkach, therefore,
האי קומץ פיגול דפלגיה מחית ארעא ופלגיה אסקיה אמערכה, hai kometz pigul
depalgei machis ara upalgei askei amaaracha, let's say what you did was
you actually broke it into two halves, or let's say on a
60% and 40%, and you kept
half of it on the floor of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
you did not put it on the מזבח, mizbeach, and the other
bigger half, 60%, you put on the מזבח mizbeach of this פיגול
pigul קומץ. kometz. Okay, and then משלבא ביה אור. mashlaba beih or.
Now the fire has burned it. So, says רב אחאי, Rav Achai,
once we're willing to say that even when it's in different pieces,
you know, the fire transforms the whole thing and you would take
even the other part, you would bring back up, so even if
from the very get-go it was in two halves, we should say
the same thing. ומשלבא ביה אור מסקינן ליה לכוליה לכתחילה, umashlaba beih
or maskinei lei lekulei lechatchila, we would bring the whole, the remainder
of it, we would put the remainder of it up on the
מזבח, mizbeach, even though it had never been on the מזבח. mizbeach.
Now that is a little bizarre for a few reasons. Number one
is it's one thing to say when the קומץ kometz is put
as a unit on the מזבח, mizbeach, then we continue to look
at it as a unit, and then we say when part of
it is transformed, it's all transformed even if it got broken up
into different pieces. If the whole thing was never put on the
מזבח, mizbeach, why should we be looking at the part at the
bottom as part of the unit on the thing on the top?
You know, another obvious question here is why should you be putting
it on the מזבח? mizbeach? If you haven't offered up the whole
קומץ, kometz, then you haven't actually offered the מתיר matir of the
קרבן, korban and then the קרבן korban actually didn't become פיגול. pigul.
So wouldn't you be smarter to just not offer up the other
half? So it's a little bit hard to understand this line. Sometimes
with these רב אחאיs, Rav Achai they're understood, like I said, that
they might be גאוני Geonic and they sometimes don't fit so much
the logic of the סוגיא. sugya. Okay, now we're moving on to
a, to like continuing this issue, not in the context of עולא's
Ulla statement, but about putting stuff on the מזבח mizbeach and what
the consequences are.
So אמר רבי יצחק אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, הפיגול והנותר והטמא שהעלו לגבי מזבח פקע איסור מהן. hapigul vehanotar
vehatamei sheheelo legabei mizbeach paka isur meihen. So he makes a statement
that sounds very similar to עולא, Ulla, except he says it not
just about פיגול. pigul. He says whether it is פיגול pigul or
even נותר, notar, you know, meat that's left over, or the entrails
left over, or something that became טמא, tamei, once you put it
on the מזבח, mizbeach, maybe again the case that the fire took
hold, that's not clear, their status goes away from them. So what's
he talking about? You know, same type of question that we asked
in regarding regarding עולא. Ulla.
So let's, and so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So
and this is again is not something unique about פיגול, pigul, that
oh פיגול... pigul... So this is again not something unique about פיגול,
pigul, that oh, פיגול pigul we look at it as if it's
the מתיר matir as if it's not really פיגול. pigul. We're saying
this about לן lan and טמא tamei as well. So how could
it be because I put it up on the מזבח mizbeach if
now somebody went let's say and ate from the meat? It would
not be like they ate טמא tamei meat because it was put
on the מזבח mizbeach so their status flew away from them. And
how does that work? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, Rav Chisda said, מרי דהאי, Mari
De-hai, the master of this teaching, meaning, you know, it's another way
of saying like what the what are you talking about? Okay, מזבח
מקוה טהרה? Mizbeach mikveh tahara? Is the מזבח mizbeach a מקוה? mikveh?
Like you put the you put טמא tamei meat on a מזבח
mizbeach and it stops being טמא? tamei? How did that happen exactly?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, שמשה
בהן האור. She-mashlah bahen ha-or. Oh, back to what we were saying
before. No, no, no, it's again because the fire took hold of
them, and because the fire took hold of them, that transformed them,
and they're not looked at as what they were before, which is
טמאי אימורים tamei eimurim or טמא tamei meat. It's just looked at
now as something that has been consumed by the מזבח. mizbeach. So
for the same reason if it came brought down you put it
back up, because we just don't look at it anymore as טמא
tamei meat, we look at it as something else. So the same
is true, that's what he means that their איסור issur flies away,
and if you were to eat from it you would not be
חייב chayav for eating טמא tamei meat in the case of טומאה.
tumah. Okay.
So, מתיב רב יצחק בר ביסנא, Metiv Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna, so
Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna challenged this הלכה. halacha. אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim,
we have a ברייתא braita which we'll quote later, others say, meaning
an opinion of תנאים tannaim says,
וטומאתו עליו, מי שטומאה פורחת ממנו. v'tumaso alav mi shetumah porachas mimenu.
The טומאה tumah is on it, to exclude a case of meaning
somebody where the טומאה tumah can leave the person. יצא בשר שאין
טומאה פורחת ממנו, yatza basar she-ein tumah porachat mimenu, to exclude meat
where the טומאה tumah does not leave. Now what is that talking
about? It's talking about an ambiguous פסוק pasuk in צו. Tzav. Here's
what the פסוק pasuk says in צו. Tzav. It says,
so this is right after the פסוק pasuk of פיגול, pigul, פיגול
יהיה הנפש האוכלת ממנו עונה תשא. pigul yihyeh ha-nefesh ha-ochelet mimenu avonah
tisa. And the next פסוק, pasuk, פרק ז' הלכה י"ט perek zayin
halacha yud tet says the following
thing: והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא, v'habasar asher yiga b'chol tamei, if
meat touches something
טמא, tamei, לא יאכל באש ישרף. lo yei'achel ba-esh yisaref. והבשר כל
טהור יאכל בשר, v'habasar kol tahor yochal basar, only somebody טהור tahor
can eat
בשר. basar. והנפש אשר תאכל בשר v'ha-nefesh asher tochal basar and a
person who eats the meat מזבח השלמים אשר לה' mizevach ha-shelamim asher
l'Hashem of a
קרבן korban, שלמים, shelamim, וטומאתו עליו v'tumato alav, and the טומאה tumah
is on it or him, ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה, v'nichretah ha-nefesh ha-hi
mei-ameha, that soul shall be cut off from his people. So it
first said if the meat is טמא, tamei, it's forbidden. Then this
פסוק pasuk says you get כרת. karet. And the question is, is
this פסוק pasuk talking about the same case, the meat is טמא,
tamei, or is it talking that the person is טמא? tamei? I'll
read the and only when the person is טמא tamei you get
כרת, karet, but when the meat is טמא, tamei, it's a לאו
lav without כרת. karet. And that I should say is the הלכה.
halacha. But the question is, how do you know? I'll read the
פסוק pasuk again. והנפש אשר תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים אשר לה', v'ha-nefesh
asher tochal basar mizevach ha-shelamim asher l'Hashem, the soul that eats the
meat of the שלמים shelamim that is to God, וטומאתו עליו v'tumato
alav and the טומאה tumah is on what? Him, the eater, or
it, the meat of the שלמים? shelamim? ונכרתה הנפש ההיא, v'nichretah ha-nefesh
ha-hi, how do you know that it's talking about the person and
it's not, which is the הלכה, halacha, and not talking about the
meat? And the גמרא Gemara actually subtly sharpens the question and רש"י
Rashi spells it out, that there's even a grammatical reason to say
that it's talking about the meat. Because נפש nefesh is feminine. It
says והנפש אשר תאכל בשר, v'ha-nefesh asher tochal basar, not יאכל בשר,
yochal basar, תאכל בשר. tochal basar. Okay. And then it says ונכרתה
הנפש, v'nichretah ha-nefesh, not ונכרת הנפש. v'nichrat ha-nefesh. So נפש nefesh is
feminine. So if it wanted to say the person was טמא, tamei,
it should have said וטומאתה עליה, v'tumatah aleha, its טומאה tumah of
the soul is on it. וטומאתו עליו v'tumato alav grammatically can only
be talking about the בשר, basar, which is masculine. So the גמרא
Gemara says how do we know that's not true? How do we
know וטומאתו עליו v'tumato alav means that the person is טמא? tamei?
So אחרים אומרים, Acherim omrim, so we're going to see a couple
of answers to that in a ברייתא, braita, but here we're quoting
the position of אחרים. Acherim. אחרים Acherim say וטומאתו עליו, v'tumato alav
the טומאה tumah is on him, so on it means that it's
a temporary status. It's not a permanent identity of the thing. It
happens to be that it is טמא tamei right now. So that
can only be talking about a human being. מי שטומאה פורחת ממנו,
mi she-tumah porachat mimenu. that is somebody who a טומאה tumah can
leave them. A human that you can go to the מקוה mikveh
and become טהור. tahor. יצא בשר Yatza basar would exclude the case
that the meat is, if the meat were טמא, tamei, then when
food is טמא tamei you cannot make it טהור. tahor. People can
become טהור, tahor, כלים keilim can become טהור, tahor, food cannot become
טהור tahor if it became טמא. tamei. יצא בשר שאין טומאה פורחת
ממנו, yatza basar she-ein tumah porachat mimenu, to exclude meat where the
טומאה tumah does not leave. Okay, so that's how they learn that
out. Now, fine, what does that have to do with this question
about once the fire burns it, you know, then it's permissible, then
it's like it stops being considered, you know, פיגול, piggul, טמא, tamei,
etc. Well, he says like this: אי איתא, I isa, what you
said was correct, that the status changes and it's no longer like
בשר טמא, basar tamei, הרי
טומאה פורחת ממנו על ידי האור. harei tumah porachas mimenu al yedei
ha'ohr. The fire actually does make the טומאה tumah leave it. So
this דרשה drasha wouldn't make sense. The fact that they're saying that
it can't be meat because meat, the טומאה tumah never leaves it,
according to you, טומאה tumah does leave it. So what are you
going to do, how are you going to explain your position?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, על ידי מקוה
קאמינאן. al yedei mikvah ka'aminan. So no, it means only somebody, you
know, this is talking about somebody whose טומאה tumah can leave them
through going to a מקוה mikvah and wouldn't include meat that the
טומאה tumah won't leave it by putting it in a מקוה. mikvah.
So the גמרא Gemara gives the obvious response to that: מידי מקוה
כתיב? Midi mikvah ksiv? Where does it say מקוה? mikvah? The דרשה
drasha was עליו, alav, that it's a temporary status that could be
removed. So it doesn't say how it could be removed. So according
to you, that can apply to the meat as well, that could
be removed by it being consumed by the מזבח. mizbeach. Now I
should say that I don't really understand this question, because if the
logic is, yes, the language used was that the איסור issur leaves
it, but if the logic is that the thing transforms, it's no
longer טמא tamei meat, it's now
just things that have been consumed by the מזבח. mizbeach. It has
a different identity. So then, and that's why even if it comes
down you can bring it back up, it's not just that the
טומאה, tumah, you know, there's no mechanism that the טומאה tumah leaves
it, the thing has transformed its identity. So the טומאה tumah never
left it, it just became something else. You know, if you burnt
it to ashes, you wouldn't say, "Oh look, the טומאה tumah left
it." No, it transformed. So I don't really totally understand the question,
but that's the question that the גמרא Gemara is asking. So אמר
רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, so here's the answer to that. אלא
אמר רב פפא, Ela amar Rav Pappa, rather רב פפא Rav Pappa
said, בבשר שלמים עסקינן, be-basar shelamim askinan, first wide line, we're talking
about the case of meat of שלמים, shelamim, right? That's the context
of the תורה, Torah, מבשר זבח השלמים אשר לה', mi-basar zevach ha-shelamim
asher la-Shem,
דלא חזי להקרבה. de-lo chazi le-hakrava. And meat of שלמים shelamim is
eaten by the owners, it's not put on the מזבח. mizbeach. So
the scenario of something put on the מזבח mizbeach that it changes
its status is talking either about the meat of an עולה olah
or the אימורים emurim of another sacrifice.
But the פסוק pasuk is talking about the meat of שלמים. shelamim.
And if it is saying the טומאה tumah is on it, well,
if the meat was טמא, tamei, that טומאה tumah is not going
away. And the טומאה tumah might go away if it's on the
אימורים emurim and you put the אימורים emurim on the מזבח, mizbeach,
but it's not going away on the meat of the שלמים. shelamim.
So טומאתו עליו tumato alav must refer to the person and not
the meat. רבינא אמר, Ravina amar, which is a very nice answer,
טומאתו עליו, tumato alav, מי שטומאה פורחת ממנו כשהוא שלם. mi she-tumah
porachas mimenu keshu shalem.
So instead of giving a מקוה mikvah answer, he's giving an answer
of no, the עליו alav means that the טומאה tumah is on
this person, on this thing, and the טומאה tumah can leave and
the thing can still be the same thing, right? So it's on
him, it's on him, but he could exist without the טומאה. tumah.
So the טומאה tumah could be removed and the person or the
thing would remain the same. That's what's implied in the פסוק. pasuk.
Okay. כשהוא שלם, Ke-she-hu shalem, יצא בשר, yatza basar, דבר
שאין טומאה פורחת כשהוא שלם, davar she-ein tumah porachas ke-she-hu shalem, אלא
כשהוא חסר. ela ke-she-hu chaseir. But in the case of meat, this
is maybe similar to what I was saying before, although I think
it's a little different, in the case of meat, the טומאה tumah
doesn't depart from the meat as it is when it became טמא,
tamei, it only departs from the meat when the meat has changed.
And so the טומאתו עליו tumato alav means the טומאה tumah is
a temporary status for this thing as it is now. So there
can only be talking to about a person because for the meat
it would only get removed if the meat actually transformed. Okay, so
that was another similar statement that once it's put on the מזבח,
mizbeach, somehow its status changes, but again the גמרא, Gemara, you know,
sort of makes sense of it because those are radical statements to
be talking about cases where the fire has sort of seized the
object. Now that we have quoted
these—this ברייתא baraita about how do we know this פסוק pasuk here
is talking that you get כרת kares is talking about the person
is טמא tamei and not the meat, now the גמרא Gemara is
going to quote the whole ברייתא. baraita. And we're going to spend
the rest of the דף daf figuring it out. Let's take a
look. גופא, Gufa, let's go back to the thing we quoted a
selection about before and now let's quote the whole thing.
טומאתו עליו, Tumato alav, quoting the פסוק, pasuk, you know, if a
person—again, I'll read the פסוק pasuk one more time, והבשר, v-habasar, והנפש
אשר תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים אשר לה', v-hanefesh asher tochal basar mi-zevech
ha-shelamim asher la-Shem, a person who eats from the שלמים, shelamim, וטומאתו
עליו, v'tumato alav, and the טומאה tumah is on him. or it,
ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה. V’nichrasa hanefesh hahi me’ameha.
So where do you have כרת? Kares? When he is טמא Tamei
or when the meat is טמא? Tamei? And the answer is when
he is טמא, Tamei, but how do we know that that’s what
it means? וטומאתו עליו, ve-tumato alav, בטומאת הגוף הכתוב מדבר, bitumas haguf
hakatuv medaber, talking about when he’s טמא. Tamei. אתה אומר בטומאת הגוף,
Ata omer bitumas haguf, או אינו אלא בטומאת בשר? o eino ela
bitumas basar?
You say it's he's טמא, Tamei, but maybe it means the meat
is טמא Tamei and again as רש״י Rashi said, the grammar supports
that because נפש nefesh here is feminine. So נאמר כאן טומאתו ונאמר
להלן טומאתו, ne'emar kan tumaso v'ne'emar lehalan tumaso, מה להלן בטומאת הגוף
הכתוב מדבר אף כאן בטומאת הגוף הכתוב מדבר. ma lehalan bitumas haguf
hakatuv medaber af kan bitumas haguf hakatuv medaber. No,
because in another case it says טומאתו tumaso and רש״י Rashi says,
the question in תוספות Tosafot רש״י Rashi what it’s talking about, but
רש״י Rashi says it’s when a person goes into the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and they’re טמא, Tamei, and it says או טומאתו בו
o tumaso bo and clearly there the person is טמא, Tamei, so
the טומאתו tumaso here also is a case where the person is
טמא Tamei and not where the meat is טמא. Tamei. So that’s
one answer: גזירה שווה. gezeira shava. רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer,
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says, הואיל ונאמרו קדשים בלשון רבים ונאמר טומאה
בלשון יחיד, בטומאת הגוף הכתוב מדבר. ho'il v'ne'emru kodashim bilshon rabim v'ne'emar
tumah bilshon yachid, bitumas haguf hakatuv medaber. Okay,
so he says this is a hard to understand explanation. He says
since it says אשר תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים asher tochal basar mizevach
hashelamim that the שלמים shelamim is a plural I mean it does
have a
יוד yud מ mem ending, but it is referring to a single
sacrifice. And so there but he says שלמים shelamim is a plural
and if it meant that the שלמים shelamim was טמא, Tamei, it
should have said וטומאתם עליהם. v'tumosam aleihem. All right, so since it’s
not in the plural it must be talking about the person. Very
hard to understand explanation. Number one, is שלמים shelamim really a plural?
And number two, it says the meat from the שלמים, shelamim, so
the subject would be the meat not the שלמים. shelamim. That’s his
answer.
Okay. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, רבי Rabbi says, ואכל בטומאת הגוף הכתוב
מדבר. v'achal bitumas haguf hakatuv medaber. No,
the next פסוק pasuk says ואכל v'achal and that’s talking that the
person is טמא Tamei so the same is true here. So we’ll
hold off on that because the גמרא Gemara is going to ask
what that means. And then we say what we said before. אחרים
אומרים, Acherim omrim, וטומאתו עליו V’tumaso alav, מי שטומאה פורחת ממנו. mi
she-tumah porachat mimenu,
No, the עליו alav shows you that the טומאה tumah is a
temporary status and that applies to a human. יצא בשר שאין טומאה
פורחת ממנו yatza basar she'ein tumah porachas mimenu as opposed to the
case of meat. Okay. So we’re going to hone in on רבי
Rabbi's statement because that’s the only one that was not very clear.
אמר מר, Amar mar, so let’s go back to what we just
said. By the way, I should point out that we here we
have in exactly
back-to-back the word גופא gufa and אמר מר. amar mar. And both
of those are when we’re referring to a previous text, but they
function differently. גופא Gufa is when we quoted a selection from a
larger text and then we want to quote the whole thing. Let’s
see the body of the thing. So we had quoted the אחרים
אומרים acherim omrim before and then we wanted to bring in the
body and we saw the whole ברייתא braisa now. Now we want
to zoom in on one line. So when you have the whole
body of something and you want to zoom in on one line
then it’s אמר מר. amar mar. So here we actually have both.
גופא Gufa allowed us to bring in the whole text from a
previous excerpt and then אמר מר amar mar allows us to zoom
in onto one line that we want to now look at, different
than the line before. And that is the line of רבי. Rabbi.
רבי אומר ואכל בטומאת הגוף הכתוב מדבר. Rabbi omer v'achal bitumas haguf
hakatuv medaber. מאי משמע? Mai mashma? What does that mean? ואכל v'achal
shows you that he’s he’s טמא. Tamei. So let’s first say what
the פסוק pasuk says. Okay, the פסוק pasuk after the one I’ve
been reading says the following. Right, the one I’ve been reading: וטומאתו
עליו ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה. v'tumaso alav v'nichrasa hanefesh hahi me'ameha. Then
it says like this: ונפש כי תגע בכל טמא, v'nefesh ki tiga
bechol tamei, if a person touches anything טמא, tamei, בטומאת אדם או
בבהמה טמאה, bitumas adam o biveheima temei'a, a person who’s טמא Tamei
or an animal that’s טמא, Tamei, או בכל שקץ טמא, o bechol
sheketz tamei, ואכל מבשר זבח השלמים אשר להשם ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה.
v'achal mibasar zevach hashelamim asher la'Hashem v'nichrasa hanefesh hahi me'ameha. And he
eats from the שלמים shelamim he’ll get כרת. kares. So that’s an
explicit פסוק pasuk that he is טמא Tamei and he eats from
the שלמים shelamim and he gets כרת. kares. So by the way,
that might make you think that the previous פסוק pasuk is not
that case. Why would you need two פסוקים? pesukim? The גמרא Gemara
is going to get to that later. It’s actually going to say
we have multiple פסוקים pesukim about a טמא tamei person eating getting
כרת kares and they’re all needed. Okay, so but this פסוק pasuk
clearly says he’s טמא, Tamei, he eats from it, he gets כרת.
kares. And רבי Rabbi says ah, because it says that he eats
from it, ואכל, v'achal, in the second פסוק, pasuk, so that means
that the previous פסוק pasuk was also talking that it was the
person that was טמא. Tamei. So the גמרא Gemara is like what
do you mean? Like what does one have to do with the
other? And why are you focusing on the word ואכל? v'achal? So
let’s see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי משמע? Mai mashma? So
what is this talking about? אמר רבא, Amar Rava, כל קרא דלא
מפרש ליה רב יצחק בר אבדימי, kol kra d'lo mefaresh lei Rav
Yitzchak bar Avdimi, any פסוק pasuk that you have not heard explained
by רב יצחק בר אבדימי, Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, וכל מתניתא דלא
מפרש לה רבי זירא, v'kol masnisa d'lo mefaresh lah Rabbi Zeira, and
any ברייתא braisa that you have yet to have here heard explained
by רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, לא מפרשא, lo mefarsha, is never going
to it won’t be fully explained. So it’s a nice little hyperbolic
statement. Because we're going to see that רב זירא Rav Zeira on
this פסוק pasuk and רב... excuse me, רב יצחק בר אבדומי Rav
Yitzchak bar Avdimi on this פסוק pasuk and רב זירא Rav Zeira
on a ברייתא braisa also talking about טומאה tumah and כרת, kares,
are dealing with things that are very, you know, like, like, opaque
and hard to understand and and they and they gave beautiful explanations
to it. So רבא Rava is saying if you haven't heard the
פסוק pasuk explained by רב יצחק בר אבדומי Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi,
or you haven't heard the ברייתא braisa explained by רב זירא, Rav
Zeira, you never really heard it explained properly. Okay, although he doesn't
just say this ברייתא braisa and this פסוק, pasuk, he says any
ברייתא, braisa, any פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so now let's take a look
what they said. So הכי קאמר hachi ka'amar רב יצחק בר אבדומי,
Rav Yitzchak bar Avdimi this is what רב יצחק בר אבדומי says
regarding the פסוק pasuk we just read, so he actually is explaining
a ברייתא braisa about רבי, Rebbi, but he's going to help us
understand the פסוק pasuk better and the point that רבי Rebbi is
making. So he says הואיל ופתח הכתוב בלשון נקבה וסיים בלשון נקבה
ולשון זכר באמצע בטומאת הגוף הכתוב מדבר. ho'il upatach hakatuv bilshon nekeva
v'siyem bilshon nekeva ulshon zachar be'emtza b'tum'as haguf hakatuv medaber. So he
says that pattern that we had in the פסוק pasuk we're struggling
with is the exact same grammatical pattern that we have in the
next פסוק. pasuk. In the פסוק pasuk we're struggling with it's והנפש
אשר תאכל v'hanefesh asher tochal feminine, and then you know וטומאתו עליו
v'tumo'so alav when we're trying to figure out what וטומאתו עליו v'tumo'so
alav means, ונכרתה v'nichrasa feminine. Feminine, masculine, feminine. He says let's look
at the next פסוק. pasuk. ונפש כי תגע בכל טמא. v'nefesh ki
siga bechol tamei. So again feminine, תגע, tiga, not יגע, yiga, נפש
nefesh is feminine. It's... you know אדם או בבהמה טמאה או בכל
שרץ טמא adam o b'vehema tmeia o b'chol sheretz tamei ואכל מבשר
זבח השלמים אשר לה'. v'achal mibsar zevach hashlamim asher l'Hashem. And there's
only one subject here, it is the נפש, nefesh, and it says
and it eats or he eats in the masculine, not ואכלה. v'achla.
And then it goes back to the feminine, ונכרתה הנפש ההיא. v'nichrasa
hanefesh hahi. So it's brilliant. He says it's exactly the same pattern.
It's talking about נפש, nefesh, it opens with an action in the
feminine, it opens with ונכרתה v'nichrasa in the feminine, and the keyword
in the middle is masculine. But since in the second
פסוק pasuk that's obviously talking about the person, there's no other subject,
the same is true in our פסוק. pasuk. Once you see that,
it truly is a brilliant read. Okay, so now that's... so now
we've understood that... that ברייתא braisa and that פסוק. pasuk. But now
that we have this lovely statement here about... about רבא, Rava, that
you've... you know, if you haven't heard a ברייתא braisa explained by
רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, you never heard it explained, now we want
to know what that's talking about. מתניתא, masnisa, the ברייתא braisa דתניא,
detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, and this is again in the
context of being טמא tamei and eating, although not being טמא tamei
and eating from a קרבן, but it is being טמא tamei and
eating from הקדש. hekdesh. And this is about the פסוק pasuk that
is in אמור. Emor. And I'll just read that פסוק. pasuk. So
this is a section in... in פרק כ"ב Perek Chaf Beis of
ויקרא, Vayikra, and I'll just sort of jump to the most relevant
פסוק, pasuk, which is פסוק ו'. pasuk vav. It says... or... let's
start with פסוק ה': pasuk hei: או איש אשר יגע בכל שרץ
אשר יטמא לו,
o ish asher yiga bechol sheretz
asher yitma lo, or let's see even earlier, it says איש איש
מזרע אהרן, ish ish mizera Aharon, this is פסוק ד', pasuk daled,
והוא צרוע או זב בקדשים לא יאכל עד אשר יטהר והנגע בכל
טמא נפש או איש אשר תצא ממנו שכבת זרע. vehu tzarua o
zav bakodashim lo yochal ad asher yit'har vehanogei'a bechol tmei nefesh o
ish asher teitzei mimenu shichvas zara. So if he's a צרוע, tzarua,
or he touches somebody טמא, tamei, or he's טמא tamei because he
had a nocturnal emission. או איש אשר יגע בכל שרץ אשר יטמא
לו, o ish asher yiga bechol sheretz asher yitma lo, or he's
טמא tamei because of he touched a שרץ, sheretz, או באדם אשר
יטמא לו לכל טומאתו, o b'adam asher yitma lo lechol tumaso, or
a person, maybe a dead body. נפש אשר תגע בו וטמאה עד
הערב. nefesh asher tiga bo v'tam'a ad ha'erev. So... the... this now
person is טמא tamei until the evening. ולא יאכל מן הקדשים כי
אם רחץ בשרו במים. v'lo yochal min hakodashim ki im rachatz besaro
bamayim. Can't eat unless he has gone to the מקוה. mikveh. ובא
השמש וטהר ואחר יאכל מן הקדשים כי לחמו הוא. uva hashemesh v'taher
v'achar yochal min hakodashim ki lachmo hu. The sun will set, he'll
be טהור, tahor, then he may eat from it. So you can't
eat from קדשים kodshim if you're טמא. tamei. And by the way,
what is the consequence? That was the opening פסוק pasuk which I
skipped, which is: אמור אליהם לדרתיכם כל איש אשר יקרב מכל זרעכם
אל הקדשים אשר יקדישו בני ישראל לה' וטומאתו עליו, emor aleihem l'doroseichem
kol ish asher yikrav mikol zar'achem el hakodashim asher yakdishu bnei Yisrael
l'Hashem v'tumaso alav, here again is וטומאתו עליו, v'tumo'so alav, ונכרתה הנפש
ההיא מלפני אני ה'. v'nichrasa hanefesh hahi milfanai ani Hashem. So if
you're טמא tamei and you eat from the קדשים, kodshim, you get
כרת. kores. Okay, very sort of similar... to what we've been talking
about before. The only difference is that חז"ל Chazal understand, and I...
I won't go into why right now, that the פסוקים psukim are
not talking about just meat of the קרבנות, korbanos, but they're talking
about מעשר ma'aser and תרומה, trumah, or like מעשר שני ma'aser sheni
and תרומה, trumah, that's also what they are talking about. Okay, so
let's take a look at what this גמרא... Gemara... at this ברייתא
braisa that is hard to understand. Here's the ברייתא. braisa. דתניא, detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא: braisa: אם נאמרו קלים, im ne'emru kalim,
if by these פסוקים psukim light cases were stated... said, למה נאמרו
חמורות, lama ne'emru chamuros, why did the תורה Torah have to say
the weighty cases? ואם נאמרו חמורות למה נאמרו קלות, Ve-im ne'emru chamuros
lama ne'emru kalos, if it told us the weighty cases why did
it have to tell us the light cases? אם נאמרו קלות ולא
חמורות, Im ne'emru kalos velo chamuros, had it just said the light
cases and not the weighty cases, הייתי אומר על הקלות בלאו ועל
החמורות במיתה, haiseti omar al hakalos belav ve-al hachamuros be-misa, that I
would have said, let's read that over again, אם נאמרו קלות ולא
נאמרו חמורות, im ne'emru kalos velo ne'emru chamuros, had it just said
the light ones and not the heavy ones, הייתי אומר על הקלות
בלאו ועל החמורות במיתה, haiseti omar al hakalos belav ve-al hachamuros be-misa,
I would have said that you get, you know, for the light
ones you get just a negative prohibition and for the more weighty
ones you would actually get מיתה. misa. If it had not said
the חמורות, chamuros, I would have guessed that חמורות chamuros would have
been weightier and you would get מיתה. misa. לכך נאמרו חמורות, Lekach
ne'emru chamuros, that's why it said the חמורות chamuros to teach you
that the חמורות chamuros are only a negative prohibition and they're not
going to get you מיתה. misa. So then just tell me חמורות.
chamuros. ואם נאמרו חמורות ולא נאמרו קלות, Ve-im ne'emru chamuros velo ne'emru
kalos, if it just said the weighty and not the light ones,
הייתי אומר על החמורות יהא חייב ועל הקלות יהא פטור, haiseti omar
al hachamuros yehei chayav ve-al hakalos yehei patur, maybe the yes, the
weighty ones are a negative prohibition, no מיתה, misa, but the light
ones maybe are no prohibition at all. לכך נאמרו קלות, Lekach ne'emru
kalos, therefore it said the light ones. So meaning we're talking about,
we don't know what is light and what is heavy, it's a
very opaque ברייתא, Braita, but clearly we're talking about whether it's light
or heavy, you get a negative prohibition but you don't get מיתה.
misa. And it had to say both because if it only said
light I would have said the weightier one is מיתה, misa, and
if it only said the weightier one is a לאו lav I
would have said light is nothing. Okay, but what's light, what's heavy,
what are we talking about? So let's take a look. מאי קלות
ומאי חמורות, Mai kalos u-mai chamuros, what's light and what's heavy? אילימא
קלות Ileima kalos מעשר, maaser, meaning if you are טמא tamei and
you eat מעשר, maaser, חמורות תרומה, chamuros terumah, and חמורות chamuros is
that you eat תרומה, terumah, so הייתי אומר haiseti omar I would
have said, הייתי אומר במיתה, haiseti omar be-misa, so the ברייתא Braita
remember says that the conclusion is whether it's קלות kalos or חמורות
chamuros it's only a לאו, lav, it's not מיתה, misa, but the
הלכה halacha is when you're טמא tamei and you eat תרומה, terumah,
you actually are חייב מיתה בידי שמים, chayav misa bi-yedei shamayim, so
that can't be the explanation of the ברייתא. Braita. The ברייתא Braita
says I would have said you would have gotten מיתה. misa. הא
נמי במיתה, Ha nami be-misa, but that is the הלכה. halacha. So
if the weighty ones mean תרומה, terumah, the הלכה halacha is you
do get מיתה, misa, but the ברייתא Braita is saying it's only
a לאו. lav. ותו, Ve-tu, and in addition, ואילו לא נאמר הייתי
אומר במיתה, ve-ilu lo ne-emar haiseti omar be-misa, דיו לבוא מן הדין
להיות כנדון, dayo lavo min ha-din lihyos ke-nadon, and if it had
not said it I would have thought that you would get מיתה,
misa, what's even the logic of that? Oh, if it had just
said the light ones with a לאו lav I would have thought
the heavier ones were מיתה. misa. How can you go from לאו
lav to מיתה? misa? If you're learning it out with a קל
וחומר kal va-chomer you can't go beyond your original case. So how
could I have even thought to get to מיתה misa if I
had just started with a לאו? lav? But besides which it can't
be talking about תרומה terumah because תרומה terumah you actually do get
מיתה misa and the ברייתא Braita here is saying that in the
end it's just a לאו. lav. Okay, אלא, ela, so let's try
it this way. קלות טומאת שרץ, Kalos tumas sheretz, חמורות טומאת מת,
chamuros tumas meis, maybe the weighty is not about what you're eating,
but the weightiness of the טומאה. tumah. The light is that you
got טמא tamei through touching a שרץ sheretz and the weighty is
you got טמא tamei through a טומאה tumah coming from a corpse.
Okay, and therefore maybe the weightier טומאה tumah you should get a
weightier punishment, that maybe is what I would have thought and it's
teaching you no it's just an equal לאו lav for both, assuming
you're not eating תרומה, terumah, okay. So let's take a look. חמורות
טומאת מת. Chamuros tumas meis. ובמאי, U-vemai, now what are we talking
about that you would be eating with this טומאה? tumah? אי בתרומה,
I be-terumah, if we're talking that with this טומאה tumah you ate
תרומה, terumah, האידי והאידי במיתה, haidi ve-haidi be-misa, so that doesn't fit
the ברייתא. Braita. The ברייתא Braita says I would have thought you
got מיתה misa but no you get a לאו. lav. But the
הלכה halacha by תרומה terumah is you actually get מיתה. misa. ותו
לכך נאמרו חמורות דבלאו הכי במיתה היא, Ve-tu lekach ne'emru chamuros de-belav
hachi be-misa hi, and again same point basically that the ברייתא Braita
says no it's telling you to tell you you only get a
לאו lav but that's not true. You actually get מיתה misa here
whether you have a light טומאה tumah or a weighty טומאה tumah
if you eat תרומה terumah you get מיתה misa either way. So
it's clearly not what the ברייתא Braita's saying because the ברייתא Braita's
saying no מיתה misa just a לאו. lav. ואי בחיות מעשר, Ve-i
be-chiyus maaser, and if we're talking about eating מעשר maaser which is
just a לאו lav regardless of how טמא tamei you are, okay
top of מ"ד עמוד א', mem daled amud aleph, אם לא נאמרו
חמורות הייתי אומר על החמורות
במיתה,
im
lo
ne'emru
chamuros
haiseti
omar
al
hachamuros
be-misa,
okay so now actually the
ברייתא Braita would make sense. If it were weightier I might think
you get מיתה misa because it's a weightier טומאה tumah and it's
telling me no it's just a simple לאו lav because you're only
eating מעשר maaser even if it's a weighty טומאה. tumah. Fine, but
what was how could I have thought you would get מיתה, misa,
right? Where would I ha- I only started with a לאו lav
from שרץ, sheretz, how could I have made a קל וחומר kal
vachomer and had a reason to think you would get מיתה? misa?
So הא מטומאת שרץ קאתיא. ha mitumas sheretz ka'asya. You know, your
point of departure would be somebody with טמא שרץ tamei sheretz eats
מעשר maaser gets a לאו. lav. And but I would have thought
that if it's actually corpse impurity, you'd get מיתה. misa. How could
I get there from שרץ? sheretz? שרץ sheretz is just a לאו.
lav. The דיו לבא מן הדין להיות כנדון. dayo lavo min hadin
lihyos kanidon. It's sufficient if the thing we learn out from a
קל וחומר kal vachomer doesn't go beyond the original case. So if
it had just said שרץ, sheretz, I would have said קל וחומר
kal vachomer if you touch a dead body. But I wouldn't have
said you get מיתה misa if you touch a dead body, it's
a לאו. lav. So how could I have had a reason to
think you would get מיתה? misa? So it's right, it's a very
difficult ברייתא beraisa to understand. Here comes זעירי's Zeiri magic answer. אמר
זעירי Amar Zeiri says זעירי: Zeiri: קלות טומאת שרץ, kalos tumas sheretz,
חמורות טומאת מת, chamuras tumas meis, like you thought. The קלות kalos
and חמורות chamuros of the ברייתא beraisa are degrees of טומאה. tuma.
And regardless of the degree of טומאה, tuma, if you eat מעשר,
maaser, you only get a לאו. lav. והכי קאמר, ve-hachi ka'amar, but
here's how I would have thought it could have been worse. אילו
נאמר טומאת שרץ ונאמר מעשר ותרומה ולא נאמר טומאת מת. illu ne'emar
tumas sheretz ve-ne'emar maaser ve-terumah velo ne'emar tumas meis. Had the Torah
just said the case of טומאת שרץ, tumas sheretz, the lighter טומאה,
tuma, and that you get a לאו lav whether you eat מעשר
maaser or תרומה, terumah, no מיתה—I'm misa sorry, you get a לאו
lav when you're טמא שרץ, tamei sheretz, excuse me, when you're טמא
שרץ, tamei sheretz, the lighter טומאה, tuma, you cannot eat מעשר maaser
and you cannot eat תרומה, terumah, but there's different punishments. Okay? והייתי
אומר, v'hayisi omer, here's what I would have said, because if you
have טומאת שרץ, tumas sheretz, even a light טומאה, tuma, if you
eat מעשר maaser it's a לאו, lav, if you eat תרומה terumah
it's מיתה. misa. So here's what I could have said, הייתי אומר,
hayisi omer, קלות על הקלות בלאו. kalos al hakalos belav. If you're
טמא tamei with מעשר, maaser, if you're טמא tamei with שרץ sheretz
and you eat מעשר, maaser, you get a לאו. lav. That's a
light טומאה tuma and a light eating, מעשר, maaser, and that's a
לאו. lav. ועל החמורות במיתה. ve'al hachamuros bemisa. Light טומאה, tuma, שרץ,
sheretz, eating תרומה terumah gets מיתה. misa. Okay, that would have been
my point of departure, if it had just spoken about שרץ sheretz
with מעשר maaser and תרומה. terumah. So here's what I would have
said. So I would have said, ומדיקלות על החמורות במיתה, u-mi'de-kalos al
hachamuros bemisa, but if with a light טומאה tuma doing a weighty
eating, טומאת שרץ tumas sheretz eating תרומה terumah is going to get
me מיתה, misa, I might have thought by analogy, חמורות נמי על
הקלות במיתה, chamuros nami al hakalos bemisa, that if you would have
a weighty טומאה tuma and a light eating, טומאת מת tumas meis
and eating מעשר, maaser, maybe you should also get מיתה. misa. לכך
נאמר חמורות. lakach ne'emar chamuros. It has to tell me also the
case of טומאת מת. tumas meis. Okay, brilliant read. Right? The ברייתא
beraisa is if it had just told me טומאת שרץ, tumas sheretz,
so קלות kalos is שרץ, sheretz, חמורות chamuros is טומאת מת. tumas
meis. If it had just told me שרץ, sheretz, I would have
thought טומאת מת tumas meis would get you מיתה. misa. Why would
I have thought טומאת מת tumas meis would have gotten you מיתה?
misa? Because since, you know, a light טומאה, tuma, שרץ, sheretz, and
a heavy eating, תרומה, terumah, gets you מיתה, misa, I would have
thought that a heavy טומאה, tuma, מת, meis, and a light eating,
מעשר, maaser, also gets you מיתה. misa. So the Torah had to
therefore also say טומאת מת, tumas meis, so you should know that
even in a case of טומאת מת, tumas meis, when we're talking
about מעשר, maaser, it is only a לאו lav and not מיתה.
misa. Okay, we will end here.