Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף daf is ק"ו Kaf Vav
106, we pick up on ק"ה עמוד ב' Kaf Hey Amud Bet
about 15 lines from the bottom, יצאו אלו ואלו Yatzu elu v'elu
by the two dots,
and the גמרא Gemara is going back to the משנה Mishnah where
it's speaking about we're dealing with פרים הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim
v'se'irim hanisrafim,
the קרבנות korbanot that would be burned outside of the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash, and it says that the תורה Torah says that the
person who burns them, they and their garments become טמא, tamei, and
the משנה Mishnah taught that it was when they leave the עזרה
azarah that you become טמא, tamei, and so it's spoke about some
people were carrying the front and some the back so only the
ones that were carrying the front became טמא, tamei, and then the
משנה Mishnah comes on and says that when you know when they
fully left the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash everybody comes טמא tamei obviously
the people in the front and the back, and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says no the טומאה tumah only exists once they actually are
involved in the burning of it, not from the moment that they
bring it out. Okay, so let's take a look now at the
גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says the following: יצאו אלו
ואלו מטמאין בגדים. Yatzu elu v'elu metamin begadim. מנא הני
מילי? Mina hani mili? Where do you get this from? דתנו רבנן
Detanu rabanan that you know the טומאה tumah comes when the minute
you leave and when you leave the עזרה azarah because we taught
in a ברייתא: braita: להלן הוא אומר חוץ לשלוש מחנות. Lehalan hu
omer chutz l'shalosh machanot. Over there it says outside of
three camps. Now what does the להלן lehalan mean? So as רש"י
Rashi points out, this is a ברייתא braita that is taught in
reference to the פר ושעיר par v'se'ir on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and the להלן lehalan what it's referring to that's not in the
locus that it's focused on is the discussion in the beginning of
ויקרא Vayikra of the פר כהן גדול par kohen gadol and of
the you know פר העלם דבר של ציבור par helam davar shel
tzibur when the בית דין Beit Din rules incorrectly also are burned
outside of the camp. So it says over there by the פר
העלם דבר של ציבור par helam davar shel tzibur and the פר
כהן גדול, par kohen gadol, the חטאות chataot that are burned outside
of the camp, it says outside of all three camps. Now where
we get that from we'll see in a minute, but that's being
assumed, okay? That's what it says over there in the beginning of
ויקרא. Vayikra. כאן למחנה אחת. Kan l'machaneh achat. But here where it's
talking about the פר ושעיר par v'se'ir of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
it says it only references one camp. Why? Because it says you
know that you shall take it out אל מחוץ למחנה ושרפו el
michutz lamachaneh v'sharafu outside of the camp, which means only one. Now
there's actually a similar language used also by the פר par by
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and by the העלם דבר של ציבור helam
davar shel tzibur but okay we'll get to that. But anyway here
by the by יום כיפור Yom Kippur when it only says אל
מחוץ למחנה, el michutz lamachaneh, only one camp. So להלן אומר חוץ
לשלוש מחנות וכאן למחנה אחת, Lehalan omer chutz l'shalosh machanot v'kan l'machaneh
achat, למה לך? lama lach? To tell you כיון שיצא חוץ למחנה
אחת מטמא בגדים, keivan sheyatza chutz l'machaneh achat metamei begadim, that really
as long as even though the burning takes place outside all of
three camps, meaning outside of מחנה שכינה machaneh shechinah which is the
בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, מחנה לויה machaneh leviyah which is the הר
הבית, Har Habayit, and מחנה ישראל machaneh yisrael which is ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
right? And in the תורה Torah it would be outside of the
actual encampment, right? So the burning is outside of all three camps,
that's why it says three camps when it talks in the beginning
of ויקרא. Vayikra. But here by by יום כיפור Yom Kippur when
it only says מחוץ למחנה, m'chutz lamachaneh, one camp, it's to tell
you that it's true the burning is outside of three camps, but
the טומאה tumah occurs as soon as you take it outside of
the first camp, as soon as you take it outside of the
עזרה. azarah. Okay, so that's why it says both the three and
the one. והיא גופא מנא לן? V'hi gufa mina lan? So where
do you actually know this itself, that the three camps from the
case of the beginning of ויקרא? Vayikra? מנא לן דתנו רבנן? Mina
lan detanu rabanan? Because we taught over there: והוציא את כל הפר
אל מחוץ למחנה. V'hotzi et kol hapar el michutz lamachaneh. So this
is talking again by you know in the beginning of ויקרא: Vayikra:
והוציא את כל הפר אל מחוץ למחנה אל מקום טהור אל שפך
הדשן ושרף אתו על עצים באש על שפך הדשן ישרף. v'hotzi et
kol hapar el michutz lamachaneh el makom tahor el shefech hadeshen v'saraf
oto al etzim ba'esh al shefech hadeshen yisaref. Okay, so what does
that tell you?
So והוציא
את כל הפר אל מחוץ למחנה, v'hotzi et kol hapar el michutz
lamachaneh, חוץ לשלוש מחנות. chutz l'shalosh machanot. So that really means all
three. Now how do you know that? אתה אומר חוץ לשלוש מחנות
או אינו אלא חוץ למחנה אחת? Atah omer chutz l'shalosh machanot o
eino ela chutz l'machaneh achat? Maybe it just means right outside the
עזרה azarah is where you do the burning? כשהוא אומר בפר העדה.
Keshehu omer b'par ha'edah. No, that was because that was talking about
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. It says מחוץ למחנה. m'chutz lamachaneh. But
then it talks about the פר par from the you know העלם
דבר של ציבור helam davar shel tzibur when the בית דין Beit
Din ruled incorrectly and it also says מחוץ למחנה m'chutz lamachaneh there.
There the פסוק pasuk is והוציא את הפר אל מחוץ למחנה ושרף
אתו כאשר שרף את הפר הראשון חטאת הקהל הוא. v'hotzi et hapar
el michutz lamachaneh v'saraf oto ka'asher saraf et hapar harishon chatat hakahal
hu. So it's very parallel language and there it also says מחוץ
למחנה, m'chutz lamachaneh, שאין צריך לומר. she'ein tzarich lomar. It doesn't have
to say because it already says כאשר שרף את הפר הראשון. ka'asher
saraf et hapar harishon. The פר העלם דבר של ציבור par helam
davar shel tzibur is explicitly being connected to the פר כהן גדול.
par kohen gadol. So it just should have said you burned it
where you burned the first פר. par. Why does it have to
repeat אל מחוץ למחנה el michutz lamachaneh again here? ליתן לו מחנה
שניה. Liten lo machaneh sheniyah. To tell you, so you're right, from
the case of כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, אל מחוץ למחנה el michutz
lamachaneh it's outside of one camp. Then it says אל מחוץ למחנה
el michutz lamachaneh again and it was redundant by פר העלם דבר
של ציבור, par helam davar shel tzibur, that says outside of two
camps. Now where we going to get to three?
כשהוא אומר מחוץ למחנה בדשן. Keshehu omer m'chutz lamachaneh b'deshen. But then
it says by the תרומת הדשן terumat hadeshen that you should take
it מחוץ למחנה. m'chutz lamachaneh. Okay, and it already said by these
פרים parim that where they're burnt they're burnt אל שפך הדשן el
shefech hadeshen where the ashes are, so we know that these פרים
parim are burnt where the ashes are. So it just could have
said by the דשן deshen you shall bring it out. And we
know that it's brought out where you're going to be burning the
פרים, parim, those are all put in the same place. But it
again repeats מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachane to tell you get one camp
further, outside of all three ג' מחנות. gimel machanot.
כשהוא אומר מחוץ למחנה בדשן שאין צריך לומר שהרי כבר נאמר על
שפך הדשן ישרף. keshehu omer michutz lamachane badeshen she'ein tzorach lomar sheharei
kvar ne'emar al shefech hadeshen yisaref. Right, we're already told that the
פרים parim are brought where you pour out the ashes. So why
when it speaks in צו Tzav about bringing out the ashes does
it have to say מחוץ למחנה? michutz lamachane? It should have just
said you bring it out. Right, you bring it and you pour
it out. So why again מחוץ למחנה? michutz lamachane? ליתן לו מחנה
שלישית. leiten lo machane shlishit. Okay, so you have three מחוץ למחנה.
michutz lamachanes. They're in the beginning, the end of ויקרא, Vayikra, the
beginning of צו, Tzav, and that tells you outside of all three
מחנות. machanot. And then when you get to יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and it says מחוץ למחנה, michutz lamachane, that's to tell you there
can't be a fourth מחנה machane you're taking it out of. So
that is to tell you it's burnt outside of three camps, but
the טומאה tumah occurs even as soon as you take it out
of the עזרה. azarah. Okay, for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, האי מחוץ
למחנה מאי עביד ליה? hai michutz lamachane mai avid lei? And רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, who focuses on that the טומאה tumah exists when
you actually burn it, והשורף אותה יכבס בגדיו, vehasoref otah yichabes begadav,
which is what the פסוקים pesukim are more explicit about. So what
does he say that it repeats מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachane by יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur, by יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? It's not to tell
you one camp for him. There's no significance of one camp, three
camps for the burning, and טומאה tumah is also by the burning.
So why does it say מחוץ למחנה? michutz lamachane? האי מחוץ למחנה
מאי עביד ליה מיבעי ליה כדתניא. hai michutz lamachane mai avid lei
mibei lei kidtanya. Like we taught in a ברייתא, braita, רבי אליעזר
אומר נאמר כאן
חוץ
למחנה. Rabbi Eliezer omer ne'emar kan chutz lamachane. It says here חוץ
למחנה chutz lamachane ונאמר להלן חוץ למחנה vene'emar lehalan chutz lamachane and
it says over there חוץ למחנה. chutz lamachane. What's the over there?
So it says ונתתם אותה אל אלעזר הכהן והוציא אותה אל מחוץ
למחנה ושחט אותה לפניו. unatatem otah el elazar hakohen vehotzi otah el
michutz lamachane veshachat otah lefanav. There is the פרה אדומה parah adumah
and the פסוק pasuk is ונתתם אותה אל אלעזר הכהן והוציא אותה
אל מחוץ למחנה ושחט אותה לפניו. unatatem otah el elazar hakohen vehotzi
otah el michutz lamachane veshachat otah lefanav. Okay, so the place where
now the פר ושעיר של יום כיפור par vesa'ir shel Yom Kippur
are being taken is also according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer the
purpose of מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachane is to link it to the
פרה אדומה. parah adumah. Not everybody agrees with this, but he is
linking the place of burning of the פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim to
the place where the ritual of the פרה אדומה parah adumah is
being done and that's what the מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachane is teaching
you. ונאמר להלן חוץ למחנה מה להלן חוץ לג' מחנות אף כאן
חוץ לג' מחנות. vene'emar lehalan chutz lamachane mah lehalan chutz legimel machanot
af kan chutz legimel machanot. Okay, so the same way we have
learned that by the burning that's outside of three מחנות, machanot, so
the פרה אדומה parah adumah is also outside of three מחנות machanot
outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. מה להלן ממזרחה של ירושלים mah lehalan mimizrachah
shel Yerushalayim and now here becomes, nobody disagrees with that, but here
becomes the real חידוש. chiddush. פרה אדומה parah adumah is to the
east of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Why? Because it says that you sprinkle the
blood towards פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel moed. So פתח אהל מועד
petach ohel moed is in the east, so you have to be
further east than that to be facing the opening of אהל מועד.
ohel moed. So we know פרה אדומה parah adumah is to the
east of ירושלים Yerushalayim and this מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachane linking it
to the burning, the things that you burn, is going to tell
you that that also happens in the east of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. אף
כאן. af kan. So top of כ"ד עמוד א', chaf dalet amud
aleph, here as well למזרחה של ירושלים, lemizrachah shel Yerushalayim, to the
east of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So that's what he does with מחוץ למחנה
michutz lamachane to link it to פרה אדומה parah adumah to tell
you
that
the burning here of these פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim is to the
east of ירושלים Yerushalayim just like the פרה אדומה. parah adumah.
אלא לרבנן היכי שרפו להו? ela lerabanan heichi sarfu lehu? Okay, so
if that's true for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, according to the rabbis
who use מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachane to tell you that the טומאה
tumah occurs immediately when it leaves the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, where
do they, they don't link it to the פרה אדומה, parah adumah,
so where do they think that you do the burning of these
cows and where do you pour out the ashes?
היכי שרפו כדתניא היכן נשרפין לצפון ירושלים חוץ לשלש מחנות. heichi sarfu
kidtanya heichan nisraphein litzfon Yerushalayim chutz leshalosh machanot. To the north of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And רש"י Rashi says, and the גמרא Gemara doesn't say
but רש"י Rashi says it's pretty obvious once רש"י Rashi says it
because it's a חטאת chatat and a חטאת chatat is done in
the north. So since this is connected to a חטאת, chatat, this
is the burning of a חטאת chatat outside the מקדש, Mikdash, but
if you had to pick a place you're going to pick it
to the north of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not to the east. Okay, רבי
יוסי הגלילי אומר אל בית הדשן נשרפין. Rabbi Yossi HaGlili omer el
beit hadeshen nisraphin. They're burnt where you pour the ashes. Now that's
pretty obvious. The תורה Torah says על שפך הדשן ישרף. al shefech
hadeshen yisaref. So what is he coming to add? So the גמרא
Gemara asks that. אמר רבא מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי יוסי הגלילי?
amar Rava man tanna dephalig alei deRabbi Yossi HaGlili? Who argues on
רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili, which is also a way of
saying what exactly is רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili saying? So
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov היא. hi. It's רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov. דתניא, detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, על שפך הדשן ישרף. al shefech hadeshen yisaref. So
this is explicitly where it says that you burn these things by
where the ashes are spilled, these פרים הנשרפים. parim hanisrafim.
שיהיה שם דשן. sheyehei sham deshen. So what it means על שפך
הדשן, al shefech hadeshen, the ashes actually have to already be there.
Okay, there has to actually be the ashes that you removed from
the מזבח mizbe'ach when you are going now burn these cows that
have to be burnt outside
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer.
Yaakov says שיהא מקומו משופך. shehei mekomo meshupach. No, it doesn't actually
literally have to be where there are ashes, it just has to
be at an incline so ashes could be spilled there. So the
גמרא's Gemara understanding that when רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yossi HaGlili says
אל בית הדשן, el beit hadeshen, he's underscoring ashes that literally have
to be there. And then it's saying, oh well that's a debate:
you literally need ashes or is it enough that it just be
at an
incline? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, Abaye said back, דילמא במקומו משופך פליגי.
dilma bimekomo meshupach pligi. Maybe no, maybe nobody disagrees that there have
to be ashes, maybe the second תנא Tanna is adding and saying
in addition to having to be ashes, it has to be at
an incline. Okay, so and the גמרא Gemara doesn't really respond to
אביי, Abaye, but it's possible to read it, so there's two points:
one, there has to be ashes; the other, it has to be
an incline; and it's a question: are they rejecting one another, or
is the one who says at an incline saying I agree there
has to be ashes but in addition it has to be an
incline. Okay, fine. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues. So that's anyway interesting details about where it was
burned, to the north or to the east and or excuse me,
yes, to the north or to the east and also what שפך
הדשן shefach hadeshen means and what that requires. Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan,
our Rabbis taught: השורף מטמא בגדים ולא המצית את האור. Hasoref metamei
vegadim velo hamatzit et ha'or.
So this is according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, it is only
the one who is, excuse me, it's not limited to רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Oh, רש״י Rashi says it is like רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. רש״י Rashi says, oh I'm sorry. Okay, so let me
just pull back.
Yeah, so רש״י Rashi says that this is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
who says that the טומאה tumah occurs at the time of שריפה
sreifah and not when it's being brought out from the מקדש. Mikdash.
It's not clear to me that those necessarily have to be arguing
and why you can't hold of both because why you can't hold
that both when it's brought out, the people that are bringing it
out are מטמא, metamei, and then if somebody joins in after it's
been brought out, then his that he will become טמא tamei when
he actually is involved in burning it. So anyway רש״י Rashi says
this is according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who focuses on the
burning, but I'm not sure that the חכמים Chachamim disagree with רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that that is a point of creating טומאה, tumah,
but they do say that just bringing it out creates טומאה tumah
and that's what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagrees with. But okay, so
here this ברייתא braita says certainly it's going at least like רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. השורף מטמא בגדים ולא המצית את האור. Hasoref metamei
vegadim velo hamatzit et ha'or. And it's only when you're, it's actually
being burned and you're involved in it burning, not in the preparatory
work. So if you're the one who lights the fire, you do
not your you do not become טמא tamei and your garments do
not become טמא. tamei. Only if you're involved in the burning of
it itself. ולא המסדר המערכה מטמא בגדים. Velo hamasader hama'arachah metamei vegadim.
That's even more obvious, not the person who just lays the wood.
Okay, you have to actually directly be involved. ואיזו הוא השורף? Ve'eizehu
hasoref? What's considered the one who's burning it? המסייע בשעת שריפה. Hamisayei
bish'at sreifah. You actually are participating while it's on the fire. Maybe
the fire is going and you put it on the fire or
you stir the fire while it's on there. That causes טומאת בגדים.
tumat begadim. יכול אף משנעשו אפר מטמא בגדים? Yachol af mishena'asu efer
metamei vegadim?
Maybe even once it turns into full ashes, that there'd still be
טומאה בגדים tumah begadim if you're involved in the burning of it?
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar אותם. otam. It says השורף אותם, Hasoref otam,
them. אותם מטמא בגדים, Otam metamei vegadim, only when it's still a
cow, ומשנעשו אפר אין מטמא בגדים. umishena'asu efer ein metamei vegadim.
Once it's ashes, it's no longer אותם, otam, it's no longer the
same thing, so you're not burning it; now it's already doesn't exist
anymore and there's no more טומאת בגדים. tumat begadim. Okay. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, now here's רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, אותם
מטמאים בגדים ניתך הבשר אין מטמאים בגדים. otam metameim begadim nitach habasar
ein metameim begadim.
So no, only once the once the flesh has become hardened like,
you know, and charred, then it no longer is מטמא בגדים. metamei
vegadim. Only when it's like the original thing. So that sounds pretty
similar. Before it says משנעשה אפר mishena'asa efer and here it says
ניתך הבשר אין מטמאים בגדים. nitach habasar ein metameim begadim. So what's
the difference? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו? mai beineihu? אמר
רבא, Amar Rava, איכא בינייהו דשוויי חרוכא. ika beineihu deshavyei charucha. You
made it like a piece of charcoal. Okay, it no longer is
the thing itself, but it's not yet ashes. So the more you
emphasize that it has to be אותם, otam, the thing itself, then
once it's a piece of charcoal, it's no longer טומאת בגדים. tumat
begadim. If you say it has to be completely something different, ashes,
okay, then it will still be טומאת בגדים tumat begadim until it
turns to ashes. הדרן עלך פרים הנשרפים. Hadran alach Parim HaNisrafim. So
that is a question of until when is it מטמא בגדים, metamei
vegadim, but it again it is interesting that רש״י Rashi thinks that
the חכמים Chachamim would disagree and say טומאת בגדים tumas begadim is
only when you bring it out, you know, what's somebody, it could
be that they agree both points cause טומאת בגדים. tumat begadim. Okay,
so that is the end of פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim and all
of that. Now we get onto a totally different הלכה, halacha, complete
shift. We're now sort of finished up all of the bringing of
animal sacrifices, and now we talk about the איסורים issurim of bringing
sacrifices to God outside of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. שחוטי חוץ
והעלאת חוץ. Shechutei chutz veha'ala'at chutz. Okay,
and it's very properly named new פרק. perek. השוחט והמעלה בחוץ. Hashocheit
vehama'aleh bachutz.
Somebody who שוחט shochets or offers up meaning burns on
the... When there is a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so חייב על
השחיטה וחייב על ההעלאה. chayav al ha-sh'chita v'chayav al ha-ha'ala. You're חייב
chayav for שחטינג shachting it and you're חייב chayav for burning it,
and this is a חיוב כרת. chiuv kares. The פסוקים pesukim here
say are the following. This is in ויקרא Vayikra 17. So ויקרא
Vayikra 17:3 says the following: איש איש מבית ישראל אשר ישחט שור
או כשב או עז במחנה או אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה, Ish ish
m'beis Yisrael asher yishchat shor o khesev o ez bamachaneh o asher
yishchat michutz lamachaneh, whether in the camp or out of the camp,
okay. In the camp is funny, but it obviously doesn't mean the
בית המקדש; Beis HaMikdash; it means somehow in מחנה ישראל Machaneh Yisrael
but not in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay. ואל פתח אהל
מועד לא הביאו, V'el pesach Ohel Mo'ed lo hevi'o, but you didn't
bring it to the אהל מועד Ohel Mo'ed להקריב קרבן לה' l'hakriv
korban l'Hashem לפני משכן ה'. lifnei Mishkan Hashem. You didn't bring it
as a קרבן. korban. So and the assumption חז"ל Chazal have means
that it was sanctified as a קרבן, korban, but you שחטד shachted
it outside. So דם יחשב לאיש ההוא דם שפך ונכרת האיש ההוא
מקרב עמו. Dam yeichashev la-ish hahu dam shafach v'nichras ha-ish hahu mikerev
amo. It's like he spilled blood and he's חייב כרת. chayav kares.
Okay, so that is שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. Alright, and then it
says, and then some more פסוקים. pesukim. One פסוק pasuk it actually
says ולא יזבחו עוד את זבחיהם לשעירם אשר הם זונים אחריהם חוקת
עולם תהיה זאת להם לדורותם. V'lo yizbechu od es zivcheihem l'se'irim asher
hem zonim achareihem chukas olam tihyeh zos lahem l'dorosam. That the reason
is that they should not be bringing קרבנות korbanos to gods out
in the fields, the goats or whatever,
those types of godheads, but there's an איסור שחוטי חוץ issur shchutei
chutz even when it's שחטד shachted to God. And that's שחיטה. sh'chita.
And then it says פסוק ח': pasuk ches: ואליהם תאמר איש איש
מבית ישראל ומן הגר אשר יגור בתוכם אשר יעלה עולה או זבח
ואל פתח אהל מועד לא יביאנו לעשות אותו לה' ונכרת האיש ההוא
מעמיו. Va'aleihem tomar ish ish m'beis Yisrael u'min hager asher yagur b'socham
asher ya'aleh olah o zavach v'el pesach Ohel Mo'ed lo yavi'ennu la'asos
oso l'Hashem v'nichras ha-ish hahu me'ammav. So again, כרת, kares, and how
is this different? Because it doesn't say אשר ישחט, asher yishchat, but
it says אשר יעלה. asher ya'aleh. So it's to offer up, meaning
to burn on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So either one of those is
חייב כרת. chayav kares. השוחט והמעלה בחוץ חייב. HaShochet v'HaMa'aleh ba-chutz chayav.
חייב על השחיטה וחייב על ההעלאה. Chayav al ha-sh'chita v'chayav al ha-ha'ala.
And if you do them both in one state of forgetfulness, you're
doing it בשוגג. b'shogeg. You forgot that it was אסור assur to
do. Maybe you thought that there was, you know, that it was
still before the period of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, nobody ever
told you there was an איסור issur of bringing things outside the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Since they are separate איסורים, issurim, you bring
two separate קרבנות korbanos even though it was one state of forgetfulness.
רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר: Rabbi Yose Haglili omer, שחט בפנים והעלה בחוץ
חייב, Shachat bifnim v'he'ela bachutz chayav, it should say.
Now there's a new point. Nobody disagrees with the former first point.
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGelili says if you, when are you
חייב chayav for burning the meat on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? If you
שחטד shachted it in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then let's
say an עולה olah or whatever, you burned the meat on an
altar outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, because in that case, the
meat was fit to go on the מזבח mizbe'ach in the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That's when you're חייב. chayav. However, שחט בחוץ והעלה
בחוץ פטור. shachat bachutz v'he'ela bachutz patur. If you שחטד shachted it
out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so you're חייב chayav for
שחיטה, sh'chita, but you're not now going to be חייב chayav for
העלאה, ha'ala, for burning it on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, because once you
שחטד shachted it out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, the meat
was never fit to go on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So according to
him, you could never be חייב chayav for שחיטה sh'chita and העלאה
ha'ala of the same animal. If you're חייב chayav for שחיטה sh'chita
of that animal, you won't be חייב chayav for העלאה ha'ala because
it's no longer fit for going on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And if
you're חייב chayav for העלאה, ha'ala, it means because you שחטד shachted
it in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So he could still have
somebody be doing both at the same state of forgetfulness, but not
with the same animal. Okay, so רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGelili
says you're only חייב chayav for העלאה ha'ala if you שחטד shachted
it in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. בשלא העלה אלא דבר הפסול,
B'shelo he'ela ella davar ha-pasul,
because if you שחטד shachted it out then the thing you're burning
on the מזבח mizbe'ach is something that was never fit for the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, and here the whole point is this was a
קרבן korban that should have been brought in the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. Well, that meat by an animal that was שחטד shachted outside,
a קרבן korban שחטד shachted outside, never could have been brought in
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. אמרו לו, Amru lo, the חכמים Chachamim
say back to him, אף השוחט בפנים ומעלה בחוץ. af ha-shochet bifnim
u'ma'aleh bachutz. No, he says I don't understand. Let's take your scenario.
You שחטד shachted it in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then
you took the meat and you brought it outside and you're going
to offer it on an altar outside. That's your scenario where you're
חייב chayav for העלאת חוץ. ha'alat chutz. So they say in that
case, כיון שהוציאו פסול, keivan she-hotzi'o pasul, as soon as you took
the meat out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you invalidated it.
So you're anyway only going to be חייב chayav on burning meat
that cannot be burned in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because once
it's taken out, whether it was שחטד shachted out or שחטד shachted
in and brought out, it's no longer fit for the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
So once that's true, what do I care if it was שחטד
shachted in and brought out and what do I care if it
was שחטד shachted out? You're חייב chayav even though it's not fit
for the מזבח mizbe'ach because the animal started as a קרבן. korban.
And because of that debate about like do we look at the
alternative case, you know, to prove this case, we're going to have
a similar debate not relating to קרבנות, korbanos, sorry, not relating to
bringing קרבנות. korbanos. הטמא שאכל בין קודש טמא בין קודש טהור חייב.
Ha-tamei she-achal bein kodesh tamei bein kodesh tahor chayav. The Torah says
that if you are טמא tamei and you eat קרבנות, korbanos, you're
חייב כרת. chayav kares. However, if the קרבן korban is טמא tamei
and you eat it, it's a לאו lav but it's not כרת.
kares. So what this משנה Mishnah is saying, the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma is, if you're טמא, tamei, then whether the קרבן korban is
טהור tahor or the קרבן korban is טמא, tamei, you're חייב. chayav.
Once we're dealing with the reality of you being טמא, tamei, you're
חייב כרת. chayav kareis. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGelili אומר, omer:
no. טמא שאכל טהור חייב tamei she'achal tahor chayav וטמא שאכל טמא
פטור. vetamei she'achal tamei patur.
If you were טמא tamei and you ate a קרבן korban that
was טהור, tahor, that's why you're חייב כרת, chayav kareis, because then
the thing was in its pristine state and you ruined it by,
you know, your טמא tamei and you ate it. However, if you're
טמא tamei and you ate something טמא, tamei, you're not חייב כרת.
chayav kareis. Why? שלא אכל אלא דבר טמא, shelo achal ela davar
tamei, because in that case the thing you ate was already defiled,
it was already טמא, tamei, so what you did was not as
big of a defilement. Okay, similar to the idea, what you brought
on the מזבח mizbeiach was already something that was פסול, pasul, what
you brought outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was already פסול,
pasul, you can't be as חייב. chayav. So אמרו לו, amru lo,
so they said back to him, אף טמא שאכל את הטהור, af
tamei she'achal es hatahor, but I don't understand, even in the case
of the classic case, a טמא tamei person who eats something that
is טהור, tahor, כיון שנגע בו טמאו, keivan shenaga bo tim'o, as
soon as you touched it, you made it טמא. tamei. So you
touched it, you're bringing it into your mouth, so until every scenario
of חייב כרת, chayav kareis, even if you start with you being
טמא tamei and the meat being טהור, tahor, it's going to end
with the meat being טמא tamei and you're eating something טמא. tamei.
So once that's true in the classic scenario, what do I care
if it became טמא tamei in the process of you picking it
up and eating it, and what if it was טמא tamei before?
Either way you're going to be חייב כרת. chayav kareis. Okay. כיון
שנגע בו טמאו keivan shenaga bo tim'o וטהור שאכל טמא פטור, vetahor
she'achal tamei patur, and then it just ends, everybody agrees that if
you're טהור tahor and the meat is טמא, tamei, then you are
exempt from כרת, kareis, שאינו חייב אלא על טומאת הגוף, she'eino chayav
ela al tumas haguf, the only time you're חייב כרת chayav kareis
is if you are טמא. tamei. Okay, so that's two very interesting
debates, but our focus of course is the beginning part is about
the העלאה ha'alah and שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. And now we're going
to look at the פסוקים. pesukim. בשלמא Bishlama העלאה ha'alah כתיב kesiv
עונש onesh ואזהרה. ve'azhara.
I get when it speaks about burning the fats and the meat
on the מזבח mizbeiach outside of the, on a במה bamah outside
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash that you're חייב כרת. chayav kareis.
It tells you both that you get כרת kareis and it tells
you that you're prohibited against doing it. עונש דכתיב, onesh diche'siv, where
does it say that you're punished? The פסוקים pesukim I read before.
ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו, Ve'el pesach ohel moed lo hevi'o,
right, he did not bring it to אהל מועד, ohel moed, דם
יחשב לאיש ההוא דם שפך Dam yeichashev la'ish hahu dam shafach and
then it ends by saying ונכרת האיש ההוא מעמיו. ve'nichras ha'ish hahu
mei'amav.
The person will be cut off, you know, from his nation. אזהרה
דכתיב, Azhara de'chasiv, השמר לך פן תעלה עלתיך בכל מקום אשר תראה.
hishamer lecha pen ta'aleh oloscha bechol makom asher tireh.
This is now in דברים, Devarim, guard yourself lest you are עולה
oleh your עולות, olos, you offer them up wherever you choose. Very
clearly you cannot burn them outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
But those פסוקים pesukim about telling you you're not allowed to in
דברים Devarim only mention the burning, the העלאה, ha'alah, they don't mention
the שחיטה. shechita. Okay, so by העלאה ha'alah we get both. Okay,
וכי הא דאמר רבי אבין אמר רבי אלעזר vechi had amar Rabi
Avin amar Rabi Elazar like what Avin says in the name of
רבי אלעזר, Rabi Elazar, כל מקום שנאמר השמר פן ואל אינו אלא
לא תעשה. kol makom shene'emar hishamer pen ve'al eino ela lo sa'aseh.
When it says השמר, hishamer, guard yourself, and פן pen and אל,
al, it means do not, it means a negative prohibition. So we
get that you have both, the כרת kareis in ויקרא Vayikra and
the איסור, issur, the לאו lav in דברים. Devarim. אלא Ela שחיטה,
shechita,
but when it comes to שחטינג shechting outside for a קרבן, korban,
בשלמא Bishlama עונש דכתיב. onesh diche'siv. So the עונש onesh it says
by again in ויקרא Vayikra here, ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו,
Ve'el pesach ohel moed lo hevi'o, right, he did not bring it
to אהל מועד, ohel moed, it says דם יחשב לאיש ההוא דם
שפך ונכרת האיש ההוא מקרב עמו. dam yeichashev la'ish hahu dam shafach
venichras ha'ish hahu mikerev amo. So there it's explicit. אלא אזהרה מנלן?
Ela azhara minalan?
But how about where it says you're not allowed, how about where
it prohibits you from doing it? Right, and we have a principle,
you know, you can't get punished unless you're warned, unless there's a
prohibition. And רש"י Rashi also says you can't bring a קרבן korban
unless there's a לאו. lav. So there's a whole interesting question in
תוספות Tosafos does actually a קרבן korban require a לאו lav or
not, or is the לאו lav only for the מלקות. malkos. But
either way, right, we're going to work with an assumption that if
you're going to get כרת kareis there's gotta be a לאו. lav.
I mean, there's two cases you get כרת kareis which is an
עשה, aseh, which is פסח Pesach and מילה, milah, which is non-performance
of something. But anyway, but certainly if you're going to get a
קרבן, korban, רש"י Rashi assumes you need a לאו, lav, the גמרא
Gemara assumes if there's כרת kareis you're going to get מלקות, malkos,
you need a לאו. lav. Where is the לאו lav for שחוטי
חוץ? shechutei chutz? Very good question. אלא Ela אזהרה מנלן? azhara minalan?
So אמר קרא amar kra ולא יזבחו עוד את זבחיהם. velo yizbechu
od es zivcheihem. So this is as I read before, after it
says you get כרת kareis for שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, it says
ולא יזבחו velo yizbechu which I sort of, I think I read
it as so that they shall not offer their sacrifices to the
gods, but you know very simply it could be read and the
גמרא Gemara will soon think it and you shall not. Of course
it's not just לשעירם, lase'irim, ולא יזבחו עוד את זבחיהם velo yizbechu
od es zivcheihem is being read now, do not bring these קרבנות
korbanot outside, it will be like offerings to the gods, even if
you do it for G-d, for the one G-d. Okay, but the
ולא יזבחו, velo yizbechu, you shall not, that is the shall not
of שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. That's what we're saying now, that's the
אזהרה. azhara.
So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, האי מיבעי ליה לרבי אלעזר,
hai miba'ei lei leRabi Elazar, but you use that פסוק ולא יזבחו
pasuk v’lo yizbechu. to really talk about a form of עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, not about
שחוטי חוץ, shechutei chutz, like
רבי אלעזר Rabi Elazar teaches. it by throwing the stone at this
little pyramid. So how do you know, so that’s your חייב chayav
for any עבודה avodah that is the classic עבודה avodah of that
god. But there’s also a principle that you’re חייב chayav for standard
עבודות avodot even if it is not the normal way this god
is worshipped. So that’s the question. How do I know that if
somebody worships מרקוליס merkulis through שחיטה shechting an animal to it, even
though it’s not the classic way it’s worshipped, that you’re חייב? chayav?
דכתיב d’chtiv ולא יזבחו עוד את זבחיהם, v’lo yizbechu od et zivcheihem,
you shall not bring your sacrifices to the gods. אם אינו ענין
לכדרכה, im eino inyan l’chedarkah, you don’t need that to tell me
when that’s the normal way the god is worshipped, דכתיב d’chtiv איכה
יעבדו הגוים האלה
את אלהיהם ואעשה כן גם אני. eichah ya’avdu hagoyim ha’eileh et eloheihem
v’e’eseh chein gam ani.
So that tells you you can’t worship their gods like the gods
are naturally worshipped. So you don’t need it for that case because
I already know that the way it’s naturally worshipped is prohibited. תנהו
ענין לשלא כדרכה, t’nehu inyan l’shelo chedarkah, so ולא יזבחו עוד את
זבחיהם v’lo yizbechu od et zivcheihem is telling you even if it’s
not the normal way the god is worshipped, you are חייב עבודה
זרה chayav avodah zarah if you bring, if you are שוחט shochet
an animal to a god even if it’s not the classic way
it is worshipped. Okay, so that’s what you need ולא יזבחו velo
yizbechu and not to tell you an איסור issur of שחוטי חוץ
sh’chutei chutz when it is being done on a במה bamah to
the one true God. So we’re back to our question: where do
you know שחוטי חוץ? sh’chutei chutz? אמר רבה, amar rabba, so רבה
rabba says, קרי ביה ולא יזבחו וקרי ביה ולא עוד. krei beih
v’lo yizbechu u’krei beih v’lo od. No,
so you should read it twice. ולא יזבחו v’lo yizbechu is שחוטי
חוץ. sh’chutei chutz. ולא יזבחו, v’lo yizbechu don’t שוחט shochet the way
I the Torah have just been describing שחיטה sh’chitah by bringing an
animal outside the מקדש. mikdash. Oh, and by the way, also ולא
עוד את זבחיהם v’lo od et zivcheihem לשעירם, l’se’irim, don’t bring sacrifices
to the gods. Okay, so ולא יזבחו v’lo yizbechu, put a period
because obviously the rest of the פסוק pasuk is about עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. So you’re right, part of the פסוק pasuk is learned
to teach you something about עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, but the first
words ולא יזבחו v’lo yizbechu just tells you there’s an איסור issur
of שחוטי חוץ. sh’chutei chutz.
So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אכתי מבעי ליה לכדתניא, achati
mibaei lei l’chid’tanya, no, we still need the ולא יזבחו v’lo yizbechu
for another teaching like we teach in a ברייתא. braita. עד כאן
הוא מדבר בקדשים שהקדישם בשעת איסור במות והקריבם בשעת איסור במות. ad
kan hu m’daber b’kodashim she’hikdisham b’sha’at issur bamot v’hikrivam b’sha’at issur bamot.
Okay, when the Torah starts by saying don’t bring שחוטי חוץ, sh’chutei
chutz, the simple sense is
we’re talking about animals that you sanctified when
במות bamot were not permitted, when the only place to worship was
the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because it says ואל פתח אהל מועד לא
הביאו, v’el petach ohel mo’ed lo hevi’o, the sin is that you
did not bring it to the פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel mo’ed.
So the simple sense is that these are animals that were sanctified
when there was a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and when you had
to bring it to the אהל מועד ohel mo’ed and then you
chose to bring it outside. That’s the simple sense of the פסוק.
pasuk That’s what I would have known. However,
אזהרה, azharah, דכתיב d’chtiv השמר לך פן תעלה עלתיך, hishamer lecha pen
ta’aleh olotecha, and the prohibition against שחוטי חוץ sh’chutei chutz is it
says השמר לך פן תעלה עלתיך, hishamer lecha pen ta’aleh olotecha,
don’t offer up your עולות olot anywhere you choose. Now that you
should note is a problem because we were saying that’s about העלאת
חוץ, ha’alat chutz, it’s not about שחוטי חוץ. sh’chutei chutz. Okay, so
we’re not going to focus on that line now, we’re going to
get to that later on, that’s going to be about the idea
that we actually learn out שחוטי חוץ sh’chutei chutz from העלאת חוץ,
ha’alat chutz, but we’re not up to that yet. Okay, right now
we’re just talking about what we do with the פסוק pasuk. ולא
יזבחו. v’lo yizbechu But within this ברייתא, braita, they’re learning the prohibition
based on the פסוק pasuk by העלאה, ha’ala’ah, the פסוק pasuk in
דברים Devarim of פן תעלה עלתיך. pen ta’aleh olotecha. We’ll get back
to that. All right, back to our point. The simple sense of
the פסוקים psukim is when it was sanctified when there was a
מקדש. mikdash. מכאן ואילך בזבחים שהקדישם בשעת היתר במות והקריבם בשעת איסור
במות. mikan v’eilach bizvachim she’hikdisham b’sha’at heter bamot v’hikrivam b’sha’at issur bamot.
Okay, now, but going forward, where it says אשר הם זבחים על
פני השדה, asher heim zovchim al pnei hasadeh, the second פסוק ולא
יזבחו עוד את זבחיהם אשר הם זבחים, pasuk v’lo yizbechu od et
zivcheihem asher heim zovchim, it sounds like right now they’re in the
process of bringing קרבנות korbanot outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So it’s a very interesting reading. The first פסוקים psukim say פתח
אהל מועד לא הביאו, petach ohel mo’ed lo hevi’o, that’s when there
was a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you sanctified it when there was
a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you had to bring it into the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and not outside. Then it says ולא יזבחו
עוד את זבחיהם אשר הם זבחים על פני השדה. v’lo yizbechu od
et zivcheihem asher heim zovchim al pnei hasadeh. Now, when they’re bringing
קרבנות korbanot outside in the field, meaning this is a different time
when there was no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash initially and you sanctified
it when there was no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you were
bringing your קרבנות korbanot out in the fields. And even so, before
you had a chance to bring it, you sanctified it when it
was okay to bring on a במה, bamah, אשר הם זבחים על
פני השדה, asher heim zovchim al pnei hasadeh, that’s what you were
doing. But now there’s a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and now even
though you sanctified it when there was a היתר במה, heter bamah,
now that there’s a בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it’s still prohibited to
be brought
outside. have to bring it in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You
do not get grandfathered in. Okay. So תנן ואילך בזבחים שהקדישו בשעת
היתר במות והקריבם tan ve-ilech bizvachim shehikdishu beshas heter bamos ve-hikrivam בשעת
איסור הבמות, beshas issur habamos, שנאמר אשר יביאו בני ישראל את זבחיהם
אשר הם זובחים, shenemar asher yaviu bnei Yisrael es zivcheihem asher hem
zovchim, זבחים שהותרת לך כבר, zvachim shehutartu lach kvar, I think, things
that
right now it's okay that you're slaughtering על פני השדה al pnei
hasadeh and nevertheless once a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash gets built, even
if you sanctified them when there was a היתר במות, heter bamos,
you have to bring them now into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
You do not get grandfathered in. So that's a very nice reading
of the shift which seems to describe a scenario that right now
people are bringing outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It's saying that
is a different scenario than the initial פסוקים. psukim. Initial פסוקים psukim
is when you walk, when you started out when there was a
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that's clear, that's when you get כרת, kareis,
that's ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו. ve-el pesach ohel moed lo
hevyo. Scenario two: it started out that אשר הם זובחים על פני
השדה, asher hem zovchim al pnei hasadeh, you had it was okay
to bring, there were במות, bamos, there was no yet בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. Now there's a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, this also you
have to now bring, you don't get grandfathered in. Okay. בשעת איסור
במות, bishas issur bamos, מהו עונשו? mahu onsho?
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: כבר kvar על פני
השדה, al pnei hasadeh, now you've brought them על פני השדה, al
pnei hasadeh, לומר לך הזובח בשעת איסור במות lomar lach hazoveach bishas
issur bamos מעלה עליו הכתוב כאילו הקריב על פני השדה maaleh alav
hakatuv ke-ilu hikriv al pnei hasadeh
that if you go ahead and you do it now that the
במות bamos are forbidden, it is like you did it על פני
השדה al pnei hasadeh which רש"י Rashi says basically means as if
you did it לעבודה זרה, le-avodah zarah, לשעירים. laseirim. Okay,
it's all very nice. Until this moment you were allowed to do
it out in the fields and אשר הם זובחים על פני השדה.
asher hem zovchim al pnei hasadeh. But now that there's a בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, if you continue that way even if you already
sanctified it, it's כאילו ke-ilu you were מקריב makriv it at the
time of איסור במות issur bamos and maybe even at the time
like as if it were לעבודה זרה. le-avodah zarah. Now והביאום לה',
ve-hevium la-Hashem, so what do you do again with these things that
you started off sanctifying with היתר במות heter bamos but now the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was built? You have to bring it to
God. זו מצוות עשה. zo mitzvas aseh. לא תעשה מנין? lo saaseh
minayin? How do I know that it's a negative prohibition to bring
it on the במה? bamah? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar ולא יזבחו עוד.
velo yizbechu od. ולא יזבחו עוד, velo yizbechu od,
now here's the point. So ולא יזבחו עוד velo yizbechu od is
telling me the איסור issur of something that was sanctified when there
was a היתר במות heter bamos and it's still nevertheless it is
still prohibited to שחט shacht now that there's a בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash and that prohibition is learned from ולא יזבחו עוד. velo yizbechu
od. And the עוד od works out very nicely here. Until this
moment it was okay to bring this קרבן korban on a במה,
bamah, but now there's a בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, no more. There's
a negative prohibition, ולא יזבחו עוד. velo yizbechu od. And now יכול
יהא ענוש כרת? yachol yehe anosh kareis? Now this case where when
you started it was okay, when you sanctified it there was a
היתר במות, heter bamos, it's not going to be as weighty. If
you went ahead and you שחטed shacht it outside the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash since you could have done that earlier with this animal
before the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash was built, so you transgress the
עשה aseh and the לא תעשה lo saaseh but you don't get
כרת. kareis. That's only the earlier פסוקים psukim when it says ואל
פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו. ve-el pesach ohel moed lo hevyo.
תלמוד לומר חוקת עולם תהיה זאת להם לדורותם, talmud lomar chukas olam
tihyeh zos lahem ledorosam, this will be an eternal edict for all
generations. זאת להם ולא אחרת להם. zos lahem velo acheres lahem. This
is for them, meaning עשה aseh and the לא תעשה lo saaseh
is what you get in this scenario but you do not get
כרת. kareis. So what the גמרא Gemara has said is is that
the we don't still know where the לא תעשה lo saaseh comes
from but we have introduced the idea that the second פסוקים psukim
of ולא יזבחו עוד velo yizbechu od are talking A about עבודה
זרה avodah zarah or B even a more interesting scenario: sanctified בשעת
היתר במות, beshas heter bamos, then there was a בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. Those cases it's true until now אשר הם זובחים על פני
השדה asher hem zovchim al pnei hasadeh it was allowed, היתר במות,
heter bamos, but still now that there's a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
there's an איסור עשה issur aseh and there's an איסור לא תעשה,
issur lo saaseh, ולא יזבחו עוד, velo yizbechu od, don't keep on
doing it. But no כרת. kareis. Anyway what do you see? You
see that ולא יזבחו עוד velo yizbechu od is about this special
scenario of היתר במות heter bamos איסור במות. issur bamos. We still
don't have the לא תעשה lo saaseh for the case of when
the whole thing was בשעת איסור במות beshas issur bamos and the
לא תעשה lo saaseh to get כרת. kareis. That we don't have.
So we will pick up with this and we'll leave you with
that cliffhanger, pick up with this tomorrow.