בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is דף עין Daf Ayin
70. And we pick up in the middle of a discussion of
a debate between, a three-way debate in the משנה Mishnah but רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir will focus on about
whether מליקה Melikah of a bird that is a נבילה, Neveilah, that
is a טריפה, Treifah, מליקה Melikah of a קרבן, Korban, does it
become a נבילה Neveilah or not? So, since the תורה Torah sort
of accepts מליקה Melikah and מליקה Melikah itself doesn't become נבילה, Neveilah,
what if the מליקה Melikah doesn't work because the bird is a
טריפה? Treifah? Which is sort of similar to these other questions about
other ways you can invalidate the מליקה. Melikah. Anyway, so רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says that the bird is not a טריפה, Treifah, is
not a נבילה. Neveilah. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that it
is a נבילה. Neveilah. And actually, there are really three opinions. רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda actually would say that even the שחיטה, Shechitah, and
this is what we're going to focus on, the שחיטה Shechitah of
a bird that is a טריפה Treifah is a נבילה. Neveilah. Okay,
everybody agrees that by a בהמה, Behemah, right, there's two completely separate
categories. נבילה Neveilah didn't have a שחיטה Shechitah and טריפה Treifah it
had a kosher שחיטה. Shechitah. And the difference basically is that a
נבילה Neveilah is טמא Tamei and a טריפה Treifah is not. But
by a bird, logically you would assume it's the same thing. Once
you're distinguishing these two categories, נבילה Neveilah and טריפה. Treifah. So for
by a cow if you שחט shechted and it's a טריפה, Treifah,
it's a טריפה Treifah not a נבילה Neveilah and it doesn't have
טומאה. Tumah. You would assume the same is true about a bird.
Okay, before you even get so it would seem the most you
would want to debate is מליקה Melikah because מליקה Melikah is something
that under normal circumstances of a sacrifice of a bird that's a
sacrifice because מליקה Melikah under normal circumstances would make something a נבילה.
Neveilah. So that's where we could have an interesting debate. But רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda goes so far, and we're really going to focus
on רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda here, to say that even the שחיטה
Shechitah of a bird that's a טריפה, Treifah, it's טמא Tamei like
a נבילה. Neveilah. Where
does he get it from? He gets it from a פסוק Pasuk
because a פסוק Pasuk says, אשר תאכל נבילה וטריפה וטמא עד הערב.
asher tochal neveilah u'treifah v'tamei ad ha'erev. Okay,
and the חז"ל Chazal say it's talking about a טומאה Tumah that
comes through eating. So they say it's talking about a bird that's
not explicit in the verse. And he says, look, it says you
eat a טריפה Treifah you're טמא. Tamei. What do you want from
me? It's this פסוק. Pasuk. So a bird is different than other
things, which is a very reasonable position. Okay. Which leads the גמרא
Gemara to then say, but wait a minute, it says נבילה Neveilah
and טריפה Treifah elsewhere and we don't always interpret that to mean
literally a טריפה, Treifah, we interpret it for other purposes. Okay, where
do we see that elsewhere that we interpret it for other purposes?
So for example, the פסוק Pasuk says, וחלב נבילה וחלב טריפה יעשה
לכל מלאכה ואכל לא תאכלו. v'chelev neveilah v'chelev treifah ye'aseh l'chol melachah
v'achol lo tochelu. So that now, it is true that לא תאכלו.
lo tochelu. It is true that both of these are that this
is true. You're not allowed to eat the חלב chelev of a
נבילה Neveilah and a טריפה. Treifah. And the idea of יעשה לכל
מלאכה ye'aseh l'chol melachah means that it's טהור. Tahor. You can use
it for even for קדשים Kodshim types of purposes. So the פסוק
Pasuk is literally true.
Right, how does that mean for קדשים?
Kodshim? Because that's the way חז"ל Chazal interpret it. That's the way
that יעשה לכל מלאכה ye'aseh l'chol melachah means it's טהור. Tahor. That's
the way you could also say it means it's not אסור בהנאה.
Assur b'hana'ah.
That's talking about an animal, right?
An animal. Okay. 'Cause birds don't have right, right. The only question
is whether the word טריפה Treifah in the context of נבילה וטריפה
Neveilah v'Treifah literally means טריפה Treifah or is coming to teach something
else. So it could literally mean טריפה Treifah here because it's true.
You're allowed to you're not allowed to
eat the חלב chelev of a נבילה Neveilah and a טריפה. Treifah.
You can't even eat the חלב chelev of a שחוטה. Shechutah. Okay.
But they but the problem is, חז"ל Chazal say the גמרא Gemara
says, is that if it literally means טריפה, Treifah, it suggests that
only the fat is טהור Tahor and the animal itself is טמא.
Tamei. Which is not true when you're talking about a cow. Okay.
By a cow,
a טריפה, Treifah, as we said, is not טמא. Tamei. So the
word טריפה Treifah here cannot literally mean טריפה Treifah because the implication
is wrong. Okay, so therefore they say what does the word what
does the word טריפה Treifah mean over here? The word טריפה Treifah
over here means to exclude animals that have a category of טריפה,
Treifah, which excludes the case of non-kosher animals. טריפה Treifah teaches you
kosher animals, because מי שיש במינו טריפה. mi sheyeish bemino treifah.
Exactly.
Okay. And therefore, and because the idea
that the חלב chelev is טהור Tahor is only true about kosher
animals. Non-kosher animals, even the fat is טמא. Tamei. Okay, so that's
basically what the גמרא Gemara says. So since sometimes this word טריפה
Treifah means not literally טריפה, Treifah, it's coming to teach you something
else, it's questioning רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda's use of the word טריפה
Treifah in this פסוק. Pasuk. It's so fascinating that the גמרא Gemara's
like upset that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is reading the verse literally.
Okay. 'Cause at the end of the day, that's what רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is doing. He's saying the verse says a טריפה Treifah
causes טומאה. Tumah. All right, but the גמרא Gemara says, no, טריפה
Treifah sometimes means something else and therefore how are you so certain
that's what it means there? Okay.
Was that a matter of debate if I I thought or maybe
I'm mistaken that if I שחט shecht a cow that's a טריפה
Treifah it now was no longer נבילה Neveilah the meat?
No, that is not debated. Everybody agrees by a cow that it
is a טריפה, Treifah, not a נבילה. Neveilah. Okay, so now let's
pick up at the top of עין עמוד א. Ayin Amud Aleph.
That's sort of some of the background, reviewing some of the background
of yesterday. What about the birds? It's all about the bird. So
the גמרא Gemara says now, האי נמי תיפוק ליה מחלב נבילה ומי
שאסור משום בל תאכל חלב נבילה יצאה זו שאין איסור משום בל
תאכל חלב נבילה. Hai nami teipoke lei mivecheilev neveila umi she'asur mishum
bal tochal cheilev neveila yatsah zo she'ein isur mishum bal tochal cheilev
neveila. So the גמרא Gemara says now, האי נמי תיפוק ליה מחלב
נבילה ומי שאסור משום בל תאכל חלב נבילה יצאה זו שאין איסור
משום בל תאכל חלב נבילה משום טמא. Hai nami teipoke lei mivecheilev
neveila umi she'asur mishum bal tochal cheilev neveila yatsah zo she'ein isur
mishum bal tochal cheilev neveila mishum tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says
you don't need the word טרפה treifa in this case to come
and teach you that we're only talking about kosher animals because the
very fact that it says חלב נבילה, cheilev neveila, okay, tells you
only talking about kosher animals because נבילה neveila means a type of
animal that the status of נבילה neveila is meaningful. And a נבילה
neveila status is only meaningful for kosher animals. For non-kosher animals, the
status of נבילה, neveila, you know, it doesn't matter. Yes נבילה, neveila,
no נבילה. neveila. It's always אסור assur anyway. Okay, so it's basically,
again, we're not debating the law, we're just saying don't tell me
you use the word טרפה treifa to tell me kosher animals, יש
במינו טרפה. yeish bimino treifa. You could say essentially the same thing
about נבילה, neveila, יש במינו נבילה. yeish bimino neveila. The concept of
נבילה neveila is only relevant by kosher animals. Okay. יצאה זו שאין
איסור משום בל תאכל חלב נבילה אלא משום טמא. yatsah zo she'ein
isur mishum bal tochal cheilev neveila ela mishum tamei. Okay,
so when it says וחלב נבלה לא תאכלוהו, vecheilev neveila lo tocheiluhu,
don't eat it, it says don't eat it because it's חלב. cheilev.
Okay, it doesn't... so obviously we're talking about a kosher animal because
a non-kosher animal, right, you couldn't eat it anyway. It has nothing
to do with the fact that it's חלב. cheilev. So, אלא משום
טמא. ela mishum tamei. So the גמרא Gemara says fine. אלא האי
טרפה מיבעי ליה לאתויי חיה. Ela hai treifa miba'ei lei le'atuyei chaya.
So you know what the word טרפה treifa here is coming to
do? We already know it's kosher animals, not from טרפה treifa but
from the fact that it says if it's חלב נבלה לא תאכלוהו.
cheilev neveila lo tocheiluhu. Don't eat it because it is, you know,
it is coming from a נבילה neveila or whatever means that if
it was coming, that if it's as opposed to a non-kosher animal
where the conversation wouldn't even start. So we already know that we're
talking about kosher animals from the word נבילה. neveila. It suggests that
נבילה neveila is the prime problem and that would not be true
if it was a non-kosher animal. So what does טרפה treifa come
to teach you? טרפה treifa is extra word comes to teach you
that this applies even to the case of a חיה. chaya. Remember
by a חיה chaya like a deer, the חלב cheilev actually is
you're allowed to eat the חלב. cheilev. So here's an interesting question.
You've got a dead deer, deer drive, you know, was hit in
the street by a
car. Okay. Take the חלב. cheilev. Okay. The deer itself, the meat
of the deer is טמא, tamei, it's a נבילה. neveila. What's the
story about the חלב? cheilev? So the גמרא Gemara is going to
say I would very could very reasonably have thought that the חלב
cheilev is also טמא. tamei. The חלב cheilev of a חיה chaya
is different than the חלב cheilev of a cow. Why? Because since
you're not allowed to eat the חלב cheilev of a cow, it's
conceptually distinct from the meat. So the meat is טמא tamei and
the חלב cheilev is not. By a deer, you're allowed to eat
the חלב. cheilev. Maybe the חלב cheilev should also be טמא, tamei,
it should just be like meat. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
says. אלא האי טרפה מיבעי ליה לאתויי חיה, Ela hai treifa miba'ei
lei le'atuyei chaya, that this fact that it's not טמא tamei applies
even to a חיה. chaya. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salaka daitach amina, I
would have had a very good הוה אמינא, hava amina, I would
have thought to say, מי שחלבו אסור בשרו מותר. mi shechelbo assur
besaro mutar.
That when is it that the חלב cheilev is not טמא? tamei?
That's by when the חלב cheilev is distinct, when you're not allowed
to eat it. יצאה זו שחלבה ובשרה מותר. yatsah zo shechelba uvesara
mutar. By a deer where you're allowed to eat the חלב, cheilev,
so I would think that if you have a deer that's a
נבילה, neveila, the חלב cheilev is טמא. tamei. קא משמע לן. Ka
mashma lan. So the word טרפה treifa comes to teach you anything
that has a טרפה, treifa, meaning on the one hand we're excluding
non-kosher animals where טרפה treifa is not meaningful, and on the other
hand we're including חיה. chaya. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה
מאי שנא טמאה דאין חלבה חלוק מבשרה. amar lei mai shna tmeiah
de'ein chelba chaluk mibesara. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what,
that would be a very nice thing that the word might be
teaching you, but it's such a good הוה אמינא hava amina that
actually the הוה אמינא hava amina is right. Okay. It's such a
good הוה אמינא hava amina that because the חלב cheilev of a
deer is just like the meat, that actually then should be the
הלכה halacha that the חלב cheilev actually should be טמא. tamei. Okay,
I, you know, your הוה אמינא hava amina was so good that
it actually is not just a הוה אמינא. hava amina. ועוד הא
כתיב ולא תאכלוהו. Ve'od ha ketiv velo tocheiluhu. At the end the
verse says don't eat the חלב. cheilev. So it can't be talking
about a deer because a deer you're allowed to eat the חלב.
cheilev. This verse that says it's not טמא tamei is also saying
that don't eat it, which isn't true by a deer. So it
says you can't tell me the word טרפה treifa is coming to
include deer because actually you're wrong. A deer is not included in
this verse. The חלב cheilev of a deer that's a נבילה neveila
actually is טמא. tamei. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר אביי
אלא אמר אביי amar Abaye ela amar Abaye fine, but I'm going
to tell you the word טרפה treifa is coming to tell you
something else.
טרפה לגופיה איצטריך. Treifa ligufeih itztarich. Actually it's coming to tell you.
its own thing, meaning it is literal, it does mean a טריפה,
treifa, but the problem we had was if it's literal in this
verse, then why don't we imply oh, only the חלב chelev is
טהור? tahor? That means that the meat is טמא, tamei, which isn't
true about a טריפה. treifa. So Abaye is going to say don't
worry about the implication. טריפה Treifa is here to tell you for
the purpose of it itself. What does that mean? טריפה לגופא איצטריך,
Treifa legufa itzreich, שלא תאמר, shelo tomar, הוא וטמא אסור מחיים וטריפה
אסור מחיים. ho utamei assur m'chayim v'treifa assur m'chayim. I might have
thought
that the חלב chelev of a טריפה treifa is worse, is more
טמא tamei than the חלב chelev of a נבלה. neveilah. Why? Because
a טריפה treifa is אסור, assur, the problems with a טריפה treifa
start even while it's still alive, right? Even before you שחט shecht
it, it’s already a טריפה. treifa. What other animal is אסור assur
even before it's שחט, shecht, like you know it's going to be
אסור, assur, is a טמאה, tmeiah, a non-kosher animal? So I might
have thought the following, it's parallel to a טמאה. tmeiah. So therefore,
מה טמאה חלבה טמא, ma tmeiah chelba tamei, so the same way
by a pig, the fat is טמא tamei because and maybe the
defining characteristic here is that it's something that its status began even
while it was alive. So אף טריפה חלבה טמא, af treifa chelba
tamei, I might have thought that a טריפה, treifa, the fat is
טמא. tamei. So the reason it said here is that a טריפה,
treifa, the fat is טהור, tahor, does not say oh don't now
go have a conniption and say oh that means that the meat
is טמא. tamei. It's not true, the meat isn't טמא tamei by
a טריפה. treifa. So why did it say here that the fat
is טהור? tahor? So you shouldn't think that a טריפה treifa is
like a non-kosher animal, and a non-kosher animal is טמא, tamei, don't
think that a טריפה treifa is טמא tamei as well. Okay, got
it? People with me here? So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי
האי נמי מיבעי ei hachi hai nami mibaya שלא תאמר הוא ועוף
טמא אסור באכילה וטריפה אסורה באכילה מה עוף טמא אינו מטמא אף
טריפה אינו מטמא. shelo tomar ho v'of tamei assur b'achilah v'treifa asura
b'achilah ma of tamei eino m'tamei af treifa eino m'tamei. So the
גמרא Gemara says so then one minute, so then you needed it
even in this פסוק, passuk, right, אשר תאכל נבלה וטריפה וטמאה עד
הערב, asher tachal neveilah utreifa utm'eia ad ha-erev, right, why don't you
say the same thing? Why don't you say that since a non-kosher
bird is forbidden while it's
alive and a טריפה treifa is forbidden while it's alive to be
eaten? So the same way a non-kosher bird
does not cause טומאה tumah when you swallow it, a טריפה treifa
does not cause טומאה tumah when you swallow it. Okay, which is
like not a good point which is like okay, so meaning the
גמרא Gemara is saying that maybe that's the same purpose that the
word טריפה treifa serves here. You would have thought what this פסוק,
passuk, okay, well actually here's a point, right? What is your remember
the גמרא Gemara says back here that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
that the word טריפה treifa is coming to tell you when you
swallow the טריפה treifa of a bird you're טמא, tamei, right? He
reads טריפה treifa literally. What is the other way of reading טריפה?
treifa? Does anybody remember the other way of reading טריפה treifa by
bird here, by the case of it doesn't literally mean the טריפה
treifa of a bird causes טומאה? tumah?
Were they talking about נבלה neveilah rather?
מי שיש במינו. Mi sheyesh be-mino. So what the גמרא Gemara says
is the other way of reading this if it is coming to
say that this idea that a bird causes טומאה tumah when you
swallow it is only going to be kosher bird. A non-kosher bird
will not cause טומאה tumah when you swallow it. That's what the
word טריפה treifa is coming to tell you. You see it could
be worse if you're with me. Yeah. Fine. Now what the גמרא
Gemara is saying is though is one minute, but based on your
logic, we could say that actually the word טריפה treifa here is
coming not to tell me we're only talking about kosher birds, but
to come and tell me basically what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks
it's telling you. The same
way you would have thought look, a non-kosher bird doesn't cause טומאה
tumah when I swallow it, so a טריפה treifa shouldn't cause טומאה
tumah when I swallow it because we're saying a טריפה treifa is
like non-kosher, the status starts while it's alive. So the פסוק passuk
is coming to tell me no, a טריפה treifa also causes טומאה
tumah when you swallow it. So basically what the גמרא Gemara is
coming to say here is if you read טריפה treifa literally here
because I would have had a הוה אמינא hava amina to say
that the חלב chelev of a טריפה treifa is טמא tamei and
compared it to non-kosher animals, then read טריפה treifa literally here, gets
you to a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position. Okay? So the גמרא
Gemara says
שלא תאמר shelo tomar הוא ועוף טמא אסור באכילה וטריפה אסורה באכילה
ho v'of tamei assur b'achilah v'treifa asura b'achilah מה עוף טמא אינו
מטמא אף טריפה אינו מטמא. ma of tamei eino m'tamei af treifa
eino m'tamei. So okay very nice, if you're going to say that
the word טריפה treifa here is literal because I had some הוה
אמינא hava amina that this wouldn't apply, then you're going to be
back to a רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda position here and טריפה treifa
should be literal and a swallowing a bird טריפה treifa should cause
טומאה. tumah. ועוד מי קא דמי טריפה מטמאה Ve-od mi ka dami
treifa mi-tmeia and anyway says the גמרא, Gemara, you don't need the
פסוק passuk to tell you oh, the חלב chelev of a טריפה
treifa is better than the חלב chelev of a pig, and I
would have thought it's like a pig because they're both אסור assur
when they're alive. The גמרא Gemara says it's not a good comparison.
טמאה לא היתה לה שעת הכושר, Tmeia lo hayta lah sha'at hacher,
a pig never started life being kosher. טריפה היתה לה שעת הכושר
Treifa hayta lah sha'at hacher and a טריפה treifa did, so I
never would have compared it to a pig. Okay, וכי תימא טריפה
מבטן. v'chi teima treifa mibeten. And what about an animal that was
born as a טרפה? treifa? But fine, מאי איכא למימר, mai ika
l'meimar, but סוף סוף sof sof במינה מיהא איכא, bemina miha ika,
but okay, at least cows general don't start their lives as a
טרפה. treifa. So I don't need, again, what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is I don't need the verse to tell me that the
fat of a טרפה treifa is טהור tahor because I know that
the טרפה treifa itself is טהור. tahor. I don't need it to
tell me the fat is טהור. tahor. And don't tell me I
need it to tell me it because I would have compared a
טרפה treifa to a non-kosher animal. There's not a real good basis
to compare to a non-kosher animal. It doesn't start off life as
a general rule being forbidden. Okay, so therefore we're back to the
question: what is the word טרפה treifa teaching me? All right, what
am I learning from טרפה? treifa? I can't take it literally because
that would imply that the meat is טמא, tamei, which is not
true. I can't tell me I need it because I would have
thought to compare it to a non-kosher animal, that's also not true.
So what is that word טרפה treifa coming to teach me? אלא
אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, so רבא Rava rather says,
התורה אמרה. haTorah amrah. So you know what רבא Rava says? It's
not about the fat. It's about the fact that a, well, it
is about the fat but it's not about the fact that it's
טמא tamei or not טמא. tamei. It's about the fact that the
fat of a טרפה treifa has both איסורים issurim applying to it.
If it says חלב טרפה אכול לא תאכלוהו, cheilev treifa achol lo
sochlehu, okay, don't eat it as חלב, cheilev, but presumably also don't
eat it as a טרפה. treifa. And it's coming to tell you
that both statuses apply. It is literal, it does mean טרפה. treifa.
Don't infer from here that the meat is טמא. tamei. The emphasis
here is not on the טמא tamei thing. It's true. By a
טרפה treifa the meat is טהור. tahor. By a נבלה neveila the
meat is טמא tamei and the חלב cheilev is טהור. tahor. But
the key of what the פסוק pasuk is teaching you and why
it threw in טרפה, treifa, even though by טרפה treifa even the
meat is טהור, tahor, is to tell you אכול לא תאכלוהו. achol
lo sochlehu. אלא אמר רבא, Ella amar Rava, התורה אמרה, haTorah amrah,
יבא איסור נבלה ויחול על איסור חלב. yavo issur neveila v’yachul al
issur cheilev. That
yes,
this is חלב cheilev and it was חלב cheilev from the moment
the animal was born, so it starts as an איסור חלב. issur
cheilev. But now it died and it was not shechted. It also
has an איסור נבלה. issur neveila.
Exactly, about time you say איסור חלב. issur cheilev.
Exactly. יבא איסור טרפה ויחול על איסור חלב
Yavo issur treifa v'yachul
al issur cheilev וצריכא.
v'tzricha.
It needs to tell you both. Because obviously this doesn't seem to
actually fit. Generally you would say אין איסור חל על איסור. ein
issur chal al issur. Maybe this is the source for the position,
you know, it's not so, okay. וצריכא, v'tzricha, you need both. דאי
אשמעינן נבלה De'ee ashmeinan neveila משום דמטמא. mishum de'mitama.
So נבלה neveila is maybe a weighty איסור issur because there's also
טומאה tumah that comes with נבלה. neveila. So maybe that's weighty enough
to come on top of חלב. cheilev. אבל טרפה אימא לא, Aval
treifa eima lo, but טרפה treifa maybe doesn't come on top of
חלב. cheilev. ואי אשמעינן טרפה V'ee ashmeinan treifa משום דאיסורה מחיים. mishum
de’issurah mechayim.
If it says טרפה, treifa, that's because טרפה treifa has more weight
in a different way. It starts while the animal is still alive.
אבל נבלה אימא לא, Aval neveila eima lo, צריכא. tzricha. But maybe
not נבלה, neveila, it has to tell you both. So what have
we said? It doesn't say why because it really doesn't, it shouldn't
work because of the אין איסור חל על איסור ein issur chal
al issur principle. But anyway what we're saying is the following.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda again says that טרפה treifa in this verse
by birds is literal. And therefore if you swallow a bird that's
a טרפה treifa that you slaughtered, it causes טומאה.
tumah. And that's only by birds.
Right. The חז"ל Chazal just tells us. Right. Now, רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda and the response is no, טרפה treifa can sometimes mean something
else, not literal. It can mean we're talking about kosher birds, not
non-kosher birds, etc. Now we're saying okay, let's actually ask that question:
what does טרפה treifa. mean? Is it literal in some of these
פסוקים? psukim? So this פסוק pasuk חלב נבלה וחלב טרפה cheilev neveila
v'cheilev treifa we're saying it can't really be literal because that suggests
that the meat is טמא. tamei. And that's not true by a
טרפה. treifa. So the גמרא Gemara goes around, thrashes around with a
couple of possibilities, and in the end it says it is literal.
But don't worry yourself about, oh, it implies the meat is טמא.
tamei. The meat is טהור tahor by a טרפה. treifa So why
is טרפה treifa. being mentioned if even the meat is טהור? tahor?
To tell you the end of the פסוק. pasuk. To tell you
that even though this is חלב, cheilev, it also is אסור assur
as a טרפה. treifa Even though it's חלב, cheilev, it's also אסור
assur as a נבלה. neveila. Okay, and that's why טרפה treifa here
is literal for the end of the פסוק. pasuk. And that's the,
and the question here by the bird, the debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and his interlocutor, like that, is whether טרפה treifa here
by the bird is literal or not literal.
And how do we know that we can differentiate between מליקה melika
and שחיטה? shechita? Maybe for the bird even if you shechted it
would be the same.
Right. That was that we discussed yesterday about about whether how you
move from שחיטה shechita to מליקה. melika. That's based on a מה
מצינו mah matzinu or a פסוק pasuk and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi
challenges that. Okay, but now we're at the earlier stage.
Okay, but that would still apply.
Yeah. Okay. רבי
מאיר האי טרפה מאי עביד ליה? Rabbi Meir hai treifa mai avid
lei? Finally. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that this,
wait a minute, let me just make sure I'm knowing which טרפה
treifa, we're talking about. Yeah, it's this one by the bird. One
minute.
Yes. Yes, this טרפה, treifa which is why we're having this whole
discussion that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says is literal, okay, and therefore
the bird that's a טרפה treifa causes טומאה. tumah. רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir who says that a bird that's a טרפה treifa? does not
cause טומאה tumah by comparison to the large animals, what does he
do with this word טרפה? treifa Okay now again, we've already suggested
this word טרפה treifa is to tell you it's limited to כשר
kosher birds, not non-כשר kosher birds, okay, but anyway we'll get back
to that, okay. So what does he do with the word טרפה
treifa if he doesn't read it literally by birds? For רבי מאיר
האי טרפה מאי עביד ליה? Rebbi Meir hai treifa mai avid lei?
מיבעי ליה למיעוטי שחיטה שהיא בפנים. Mi-bai-ei lei l'mi'utei shechita she-hi bifnim.
Okay to tell you that remember of these things, right? Oh did
I erase some of it? Unfortunately I erased it. Okay but if
you remember,
right, let me rewrite this.
Right what are the cases where of מליקה, melika, right, where you
know remember what a מליקה melika when it when it is טהור,
tahor, when it is not a נבלה, neveila, right, it has to
be you did a מליקה, melika, you did the right act.
Yeah yeah.
Right it could be פסולין, psulin, that's true, that could be the
exception, but it was the right act of קדשים, kodshim, okay,
which is the right object as it were בפנים, bifnim, in the
right place. Okay that's what that's when it's not it's not. Now
now
what if similarly if it is שחיטה shechita of חולין
בפנים
chullin
bifnim.
or of קדשים kodshim whatever בחוץ bachutz or בפנים, bifnim all of
those cases is not a נבלה neveila because basically here because it's
שחיטה, shechita, it's not מליקה. melika. Okay what is a נבלה? neveila?
What is a נבלה neveila is if it's not מליקה, melika, let's
say it's מליקת סכין, melikat sakin, so that's the wrong act,
or if it is
חולין, chullin מליקת חולין, melikat chullin, okay, wrong object,
or if it is מליקת קדשים בחוץ, melikat kodshim bachutz, wrong place.
Okay that okay plus what else is what else makes it a
נבלה? neveila? The other thing that makes it a נבלה neveila is
if it is
מליקת קדשים melikat kodshim
or whatever even חולין chullin, but even קדשים, kodshim, well I guess
that's implicit here, okay, מליקת קדשים בחוץ. melikat kodshim bachutz. Okay fine
anyway fine. Okay we did that. Well we did that right that's
implicit here. No we did בחוץ bachutz I thought right sorry. Am
I forgetting anything here? It goes here I'm not sure. Okay anyway
so that's it. Now of course the question becomes and this is
important to remember this because what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda because what
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir comes to do. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is
a חידוש. chiddush. It's one thing to say שחיטה shechita of a
bird that's a טרפה treifa is not מטמא. metamei. But רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda says even מליקה melika of a bird that is a
טרפה treifa is not
מטמא. metamei. For example the גמרא gemara had a ברייתא, braisa, it
doesn't seem like this is going according to רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir,
but
the גמרא gemara had a ברייתא, braisa, you know what's also included
in the wrong object? Included in the wrong object the גמרא gemara
said was מחוסר אבר, mechusar eiver, okay,
or פקין pikin obviously or something that is like too old or
too young, you remember that? Yeah. Okay so you would think, right,
that a טרפה treifa. would fall in the wrong object category, right?
So well no because it's the מחוסר mechusar well I guess so.
But no but a chicken is edible, you know.
I understand I'm not saying not necessarily but if these types of
things right make it make it considered like a מליקה melika and
a not like a נבלה, neveila, so anyway that's what you would
be inclined to think. Anyway רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says no it
doesn't matter at all internal it's not a בעל מום, ba'al mum,
it's whatever and it's not so it's not like a קדשים kodshim
problem whatever it is anyway רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says it's not
a רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says it's not a נבלה neveila רבי
and whatever and רבי יוסי says it is a נבלה neveila certainly
the מליקה melika case is a נבלה neveila even if in general
he agrees by the שחיטה shechita of a טרפה. treifa Okay so
now the גמרא gemara says okay let's get back to the גמרא.
gemara. So the גמרא gemara says so what do you do with
the word רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir who disagrees
with רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and says that that it is not
טמא tamei even מליקה melika is not טמא tamei האי טרפה מאי
עביד ליה hai treifa mai avid lei what does he do by
the טרפה treifa. word by over there by the bird?
So the גמרא gemara says מאי
עביד ליה למיעוטי שחיטה שהיא בפנים. mai avid lei l'mi'utei shechita she-hi
bifnim. Okay so remember we said this so the fact that it
says נבלה וטרפה neveila u-treifa what we learned to tell if you
remember is how did we learn that שחיטת חולין בפנים shechitas chullin
bifnim how did we learn that that is not not טמא? tamei?
Because we said it compares it because of the word טרפה. treifa
Do you remember this from yesterday? That the same way something that
has to be equal inside and outside causes טומאה. tumah. But שחיטת
חולין בחוץ shechitas chullin bachutz is acceptable. So therefore since it's not
the same inside and outside שחיטה shechita it doesn't. not fall into
this טמא tamei category. And therefore שחיטת חולין בפנים shchitas chullin bifnim
does not cause טומאה. tumah. So the word טרפה treifa is not
coming to tell me literally a טרפה treifa bird, that's not true,
according to רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, it's coming to tell me inside
and outside have to be the same, which is where I learned
that שחיטת חולין בפנים shchitas chullin bifnim is actually going to be
טהור tahor and not טמא. tamei. Yes.
חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah is a rabbinic prohibition? Yeah. So it shouldn't
affect?
That's true. I mean, based on how you think about חולין בעזרה
chullin ba'azarah is a question why you even need a פסוק pasuk
for this, because if חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah is rabbinic, that's true.
Okay. רבי יהודה טרפה אחרינא כתיב. Rebbe Yehuda treifa achrina ksiv. Now
where does רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda learn this principle? That שחיטה בפנים
shechita bifnim is okay, that it has to be the same inside
and outside of your problem, because it says נבלה וטרפה neveila ve'treifa
twice. Once it says אשר תאכל נבלה וטרפה וטמא עד הערב, asher
tochal neveila ve'treifa ve'tamei ad ha'erev, and another פסוק pasuk says נבלה
וטרפה לא יאכל לטמאה בה. neveila ve'treifa lo yochal le'tam'ah vah. Okay.
So therefore it says טרפה treifa, twice, once to teach me we're
talking about literally טרפה, treifa and once to teach me this הלכה
halacha of inside and outside. So the
גמרא Gemara says רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, חד למעוטי שחיטה שבפנים וחד
למעוטי עוף טמא. chad le'moutei shechita she'bifnim ve'chad le'moutei of tamei. Okay,
that gets back to what we said before. So one טרפה treifa
is coming to tell me this הלכה halacha that a נבלה neveila
causes טומאה tumah when you swallow it, a bird נבלה, neveila, it's
only by kosher birds. Okay, only by something that טרפה treifa is
relevant. The other טרפה treifa, teaches me this הלכה halacha that טומאה
tumah is only when it's the same inside and outside, and that
שחיטת חולין בפנים shchitas chullin bifnim does not cause טומאה. tumah. Okay,
so for רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir you learn two things from the
word טרפה, treifa. neither of which are the literal meaning of טרפה.
treifa One thing is that we're only talking about kosher birds, and
the other thing is that the טומאה tumah is only when it's
the same inside and outside as opposed to חולין chullin בפנים. bifnim,
Okay, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda, says at least one of those טרפהs
treifa. I'm going to use literally to tell you that this טומאה
tumah is caused by a bird that's a טרפה. treifa Your sympathies
got to be with רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda I got to tell
you. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, רבי יהודה מנבלה נפקא ליה. Rebbe Yehuda mi'neveila nafa lei. This
is what we said before. רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda knows to exclude
a non-kosher bird from the word נבלה. neveila. Also נבלה neveila is
something that's only relevant to kosher birds, not to non-kosher birds. So
I already know we're only talking about kosher birds. רבי מאיר, Rebbe
Meir, האי נבלה מאי עביד ליה? hai neveila mai avid lei? So
what does רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir do with the נבלה? neveila? לשיעור
אכילה. le'shiur achila. To tell you how much of a bird causes
טומאה. tumah. The amount that would be אסור assur for eating it
as a נבלה, neveila, which is a כזית. kezayis. So when you
swallow a כזית kezayis of the bird, you're טמא, tamei, and we
learned that from the word נבלה neveila because that's the amount the
size that's meaningful for a נבלה. neveila. ותיפוק
ליה מקרא קמא מדאפקיה רחמנא בלשון אכילה. ve'teipokei mikra kama mid'afchei rachmana
bilshon achila. So it says but wait a minute, it says, you
know, it says don't eat, אשר תאכל asher tochal it says נבלה
וטרפה לא יאכל לטמאה בה. neveila ve'treifa lo yochal le'tam'ah vah. So
since it
just says אשר תאכל וטמא asher tochal ve'tamei or it says לא
יאכל לטמאה בה, lo yochal le'tam'ah vah, so that should tell you
that the amount that causes טומאה, tumah, the same way it's the
act of eating that causes טומאה, tumah, that should tell you the
amount that causes טומאה tumah is the normal amount of eating is
a
כזית. kezayis. Okay. מדאפקיה בלשון אכילה. mid'afchei bilshon achila. No. חד לשיעור
אכילה בכזית וחד לשיעור אכילה בכדי אכילת פרס. chad leshiur achila bikezayis
ve'chad leshiur achila bichtei achilas pras. You need to tell me twice
the idea that it's like אכילה. achila. Once from the word נבלה
neveila and once from the word אכילה. achila. Once to tell you
the minimum amount, which is a כזית kezayis causes טומאה, tumah, and
the other is to tell you it only causes טומאה tumah if
you eat it in the normal way הלכה halacha defines eating, which
is eating the כזית kezayis within the amount of time it takes
to eat half a loaf of bread. Okay. Why would I have
thought this is different?
Because סלקא דעתך אמינא הוא וחידושו, salka daiteich amina ho ve'chidushu, since
it's a חידוש chidush that טומאה tumah is caused by eating, so
maybe it's eating is defined in different ways. Maybe as long as
that amount goes down your throat it doesn't matter how long it
takes you. דיוצא מכדי אכילת פרס נמי לטמא, de'yotzei michdei achilas pras
nami letamei, maybe even if it
takes you too long.
But maybe that's the point, maybe the point is טומאה tumah is
caused by this going down your throat, not by a מעשה אכילה,
ma'aseh achila, that's what I would have thought.
Even though it says יאכל. yochal.
I know. Okay, what can I tell you, Michael. קא משמע לן.
kamashma lan. Okay, so anyway, so the point is all these different
things and the bottom line is רבי יהודה reserves one use of
the word טרפה treifa to tell you it's literal, and that a
even a bird that's a טרפה treifa, causes טומאה, tumah, and רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir says I'm just going to learn a lot of
other stuff from it. I'm going to learn we're only talking about
kosher birds, I'm going to learn it has to be the same
inside and outside, I'm going to learn from the word נבלה neveila
I'm going to learn that it has to be the size of
a כזית kezayis or כזית בכדי אכילת פרס kezayis bichtei achilas pras
etc. etc. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תנו רבנן וחלב נבלה וחלב טרפה. Tenu rabbanan vecheilev neveila vecheilev treifa.
בחלב becheilev finally now we're shifting back to this פסוק pasuk but
now we're starting a little bit fresh. Okay, don't eat the חלב
cheilev of a נבלה neveila and a טרפה, treifa, but they do
not cause
טומאה. tumah. בחלב בהמה טהורה הכתוב מדבר. becheilev beheima tehora hakasuv medaber.
We're talking about חלב cheilev of a kosher animal.
אתה אומר בחלב בהמה טהורה הכתוב מדבר, ata omer becheilev beheima tehora
hakasuv medaber, the חלב cheilev of a kosher animal, או אינו אלא
בחלב בהמה טמאה, o eino ela becheilev beheima t'meia, maybe it's the
חלב cheilev of a non-kosher animal.
אמרת. Amarta.
Okay, so here we're saying that חלב chelev is טהור tahor and
we also know that if you שחט shacht an animal it is
טהור, tahor, the meat is טהור, tahor, right? So we have two
we know two things about we know that there are two ways
in which the in which something is טהור tahor of an animal.
The חלב chelev is טהור tahor and if you שחט shacht it
it's טהור. tahor. Okay, so תיהר מכלל tihar miklal where are we?
תיהר מכלל שחיטה שחוטה ותיהר מכלל חלב. tihar miklal shechitah shechutah vetihar
miklal chelev. מה כשתיאר מכלל שחוטה, mah keshetihar miklal shechutah, we know
when you what is the case when you שחט shacht an animal
that it's טהור? tahor? That's בטהורה ולא בטמאה. betehorah velo betmei'ah. We
know that the only meat of an animal that's טהור tahor is
a meat of a כשר kosher animal, okay? So if that's true,
אף כשתיאר מכלל חלב בטהורה ולא בטמאה. af keshetihar miklal chelev betehorah
velo betmei'ah. So similarly when we're talking about the חלב chelev of
an animal being טהור, tahor, we're talking about that of a כשר
kosher animal, okay? So meaning the point is here it says חלב
chelev is טהור. tahor. Remember we said before that it's only the
חלב chelev of a כשר kosher animal that's טהור. tahor. The חלב
chelev of a non-כשר kosher animal is טמא, tamei, okay? Logically the
reason is because the חלב chelev because since you're not allowed equally
eat both the meat and the חלב, chelev, it's all like the
same thing, the meat and the חלב chelev is all the same.
So the fact that the חלב chelev is טהור tahor is only
by a כשר kosher animal, not by a non-כשר kosher animal. But
this ברייתא's braita's questioning that. How do we know that? And the
answer is, well look, when it comes to the meat being טהור,
tahor, when is the meat of an animal טהור? tahor? The meat
of an animal is טהור tahor only by a כשר kosher animal,
not by a non-כשר kosher when you שחט shacht it. So here,
even though we're not talking about שחיטה, shechitah, when we're going to
say a piece of it is טהור, tahor, we're only talking about
כשר kosher animals, not about non-כשר kosher animals, okay? So that's how
we know the חלב chelev here is only talking about כשר kosher
animals. That would be one argument. But you can make another argument,
okay? We could say like this: או כלך לדרך זו, o kalech
lederech zo, or go this way, follow this path. תיהר מכלל נבלה
ותיהר מכלל חלב, tihar miklal neveilah vetihar miklal chelev, okay, that there
are some types of things that are כשר kosher that are not
טמא tamei as a נבלה. neveilah. What types of things are not
טמא tamei as a נבלה? neveilah? We just said it before, you
said it, we all said it was ironic. Anybody know what animal
is not טמא tamei as a נבלה? neveilah?
A כשר kosher a כשר kosher cow is טמא tamei as a
נבלה. neveilah.
A non-כשר kosher pig is טמא tamei as a נבלה. neveilah. There's
one animal that's not טמא tamei as a נבלה, neveilah, we just
said it a minute ago, a non-כשר kosher bird. This strange הלכה
halachah that a bird causes טומאה, tumah, right? Remember one of the
things we learned from this whole thing, this whole הלכה halachah that
a bird causes טומאה tumah when you swallow it is only כשר
kosher birds. So you actually have an irony that normally non-כשר kosher
animals cause more טומאה, tumah, right? Even if you שחט shacht a
non-כשר kosher animal it causes טומאה, tumah, even if the חלב chelev
of a non-כשר kosher animal causes טומאה, tumah, that's what we're sort
of saying. But you have one case where a non-כשר kosher animal
doesn't cause טומאה: tumah: a non-כשר kosher bird. If you swallow it,
it does not cause טומאה. tumah. This is only by כשר kosher
birds, okay? So the גמרא's gemara's saying if we're going to say
חלב chelev is טהור, tahor, does that apply even to non-כשר kosher
animals? So the first argument is: no, that doesn't make sense, non-כשר
kosher animals are always more טמא. tamei. Even if you שחט shacht
a non-כשר kosher animal it's טמא. tamei. So therefore certainly the חלב
chelev should be טמא. tamei. This doesn't apply to non-כשר kosher animals.
The other argument: wait, there's a case where non-כשר kosher animals actually
are better, are טהור, tahor, the case of birds. So therefore maybe
the idea that the חלב chelev is טהור tahor should apply to
non-כשר kosher animals as well, okay?
But what's חלב chelev for a bird?
I know it's not, but just the general concept that non-כשר kosher
animals. You're right, you could say what do birds have to do
with these things, that's true. But it doesn't matter, general concept. So
we don't know when the תורה's Torah's saying חלב chelev is okay,
whatever, not טמא, tamei, does it also mean non-כשר kosher animals? Logic
would say no, only כשר, kosher, because non-כשר kosher animals are always
more טמא. tamei. You שחט shacht a pig, it's טמא. tamei. Okay,
but גמרא gemara says: wait, the bird case has non-כשר kosher animals
being less טמא, tamei, okay? או כלך לדרך זו, o kalech lederech
zo, or go this way. תיהר מכלל נבלה ותיהר מכלל חלב. tihar
miklal neveilah vetihar miklal chelev. There's some non-כשר kosher animals that are
טהור tahor as a נבלה, neveilah, okay, and the תורה Torah here
is saying חלב chelev is טהור. tahor. So why don't I say
מה כשתיאר מכלל נבלה בטמאה ולא בטהורה? mah keshetihar miklal neveilah betmei'ah
velo betehorah? The same way when it's saying that certain dead animals
are טהור, tahor, which means dead birds are טהור, tahor, is non-כשר
kosher animals, אף כשתיאר מכלל חלב בטמאה ולא בטהורה. af keshetihar miklal
chelev betmei'ah velo betehorah. Maybe I'll say this verse is only talking
about non-כשר kosher animals. The same way only non-כשר kosher birds are
טהור, tahor, maybe it's only חלב chelev of non-כשר kosher animals are
טהור. tahor. Maybe I'll come with a position that non-כשר kosher animals
are less of a טומאה tumah problem, okay? So you've got the
world of
you've got the world of let's say, you know, whatever, mammals, right?
You've got the world of like, you know, cows and sheep
and
whatever. Anyway, so in this world, okay, in this world, if you
do if you have a שחיטה shechitah *shechita*, if you שחט shecht
*shecht* an animal,
right, this is טמא tamei. *tamei* and this is טהור tahor. *tahor*.
And it's only by נבלה neveilah *neveila*, right, that they're both טמא
tamei, *tamei*. So if you would look at this chart and you
would say okay, and we have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* here that
says חלב cheilev. *chelev* is going to be טהור tahor. *tahor*, you'd
assume that the חלב cheilev *chelev* goes into the kosher column, not
into the non-kosher column, right? So that's חלב cheilev *chelev*. But if
you look at this world, the world of birds, so you've got
a pigeon here and a chicken and a duck, that's in the
kosher column. What do you have in the non-kosher column? What's a
non-kosher bird? A vulture,
eagle. Okay. Here you have the הלכה *halacha* that if you
eat eat it when it's dead, bizarrely this is טמא tamei *tamei*
and that's טהור tahor. *tahor*. Weird. So here when the Torah says
חלב cheilev *chelev* although it's true it's talking about a חלב cheilev
*chelev* of a mammal, but if I don't know is the Torah
talking here about kosher animals or non-kosher animals when it's telling me
טהור tahor? *tahor*, if I look at the top if I look
here I'm going to say it's talking about kosher animals because those
are more טהור tahor? *tahor*, right? But if I look down here
I'm going to say it's talking about non-kosher animals because in the
bird world non-kosher animals are more טהור tahor, *tahor*.
So, alright. So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says אף כשתהא מכלל חלב cheilev בטמא ולא בטהור *af keshetehei
mikhlal chelev betamei velo betahor*, so maybe here where it's saying חלב
chelev *chelev* is טהור tahor. *tahor* I should say that we're talking
about טמא tamei. *tamei* animals because at least in the world of
birds טמא tamei? *tamei* animals are more טהור tahor? *tahor* בלא בטהור
*velo betahor*. אמרת *Amarta*, so now you said כשבא בדרך זו היא
בטהורה *kesheba bederech zo hi betehora*. I like the it keeps this
imagery of go on this path. If you go on this path
you'll come to the conclusion that we're talking about kosher animals. If
you go on this path you'll come to the conclusion we're talking
about non-kosher. כשבא בדרך זו היא בטהורה *Kesheba bederech zo hi betehora*,
when you go on this path it's טהורה tehorah, *tehora*. כשבא בדרך
זו היא בטמאה *Kesheba bederech zo hi betemeia*, when you go on
the other path you talking you learn out that you're talking about
non-kosher animals. This case of חלב chelev *chelev*. It sort of brings
up that classic case in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* about there's two
paths, you know, and one of them has טומאה tumah. *tumah* under
it and
one of them doesn't and you don't know which path you went
on, right? So anyway, so here you have two paths you can
go. Do you go on this this path and say the חלב
chelev *chelev* is talking about kosher animals or do you go on
the bird path and again we're not talking about birds when we're
talking about חלב chelev *chelev*, but at least learn from the bird
paths and say that the חלב chelev *chelev* is talking about non-kosher
animals? So which way? So you don't know which way if you
were just doing logic. So תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar *talmud lomar*, so
the verse teaches טריפה treifah, *treifa*. That's what the word טריפה *treifa*
why the word טריפה *treifa* is needed. This gets back to the
idea here. You need the word טריפה *treifa* to teach you not
literally טריפה *treifa* but that we're only talking about kosher birds. מי
שיש במינה טריפה *mi sheyesh beminah treifa*, we're talking about things that
טריפה *treifa* is relevant to. Okay. הוציא את הטמאה שאין במינה טריפה
*hotzi et hatemeia she'ein beminah treifa*, I'll exclude a טמאה *temeia* that
does not have טריפה *treifa*. ולא הוציא את החיה שיש במינה טריפה
*velo hotzi et hachayah sheyesh beminah treifa*. Oh wait a minute. Not
this טריפה *treifa*. Excuse me. I jumped back to the birds. The
טריפה *treifa* here we're talking about חלב chelev *chelev*. So what does
the טריפה *treifa* here coming to tell me, this we said this
point also. This טריפה *treifa* is coming to tell me that that
we're only talking about kosher animals, only animals that have that have
a type of a טריפה *treifa*. So this חלב chelev *chelev* is
coming to genuinely say yes, we're in this category, we're only talking
about kosher animals, not non-kosher because of the word טריפה *treifa* tells
me go on this path. Go on the path, you know, not
the pig path, whatever, go on this path, go on the path
of animals that have that have a concept of טריפה *treifa*. Okay,
so that's how I know that. תלמוד לומר טריפה
מי שיש במינה טריפה *talmud lomar treifa mi sheyesh beminah treifa*. Period.
Now the now the ברייתא braita *braita* continues, three lines from the
top. הוציא את הטמאה שאין במינה טריפה ולא הוציא את החיה שיש
במינה טריפה *hotzi et hatemeia she'ein beminah treifa velo hotzi et hachayah
sheyesh beminah treifa*, maybe I should only exclude pigs, maybe I shouldn't
exclude deer because deer actually do have טריפה *treifa* relevant, okay, but
we know that deer are excluded because deer the חלב chelev *chelev*
is the same because the like to the meat because you can
eat the meat חלב chelev *chelev*. תלמוד לומר ואכול לא lo, תאכלוהו
מי שחלבו אסור ובשרו מותר יצא חיה שחלבה ובשרה מותר *talmud lomar
ve'achol lo tachaluhu mi shechelbo asur uvesaro mutar yatza chayah shechelba uvesara
mutar*. So ואכול לא תאכלוהו *ve'achol lo tachaluhu* tells you you're only
talking about things animals in which the meat the fat cannot be
eaten. The חלב chelev is the same 'cause they're linked to the
meat because you can eat the meat חלב. chelev תלמוד לומר וכל
לא תאכלו vechol lo tochlu מי שחלבו אסור בשרו מותר mi shechelvo
asur besaro mutar יצא חלב חיה yatza cheilev chayah שחלבו
ובשרו
מותר. shechelvo uvesaro mutar. So וכל לא תאכלו vechol lo tochlu tells
you you're only talking about animals in which the fat cannot be
eaten. If the fat can be eaten like a deer, then the
then the fat is not treated as distinct from the meat and
the
fat does cause טומאה. tumah. So you got it? So here we
have חלב chelev does not cause טומאה. tumah. What are we talking
about? Are we going to learn from birds, or are we going
to learn from the larger animals? We're going to learn from the
larger animals because of the word טרפה, treifa something that טרפה treifa
is relevant. So the חלב of a of a kosher animal does
not cause טומאה. tumah. But it's only of a בהמה. behemah. The
חלב of a deer does cause טומאה. tumah. Why? Because the חלב
can be eaten. It's like the meat. That's not only logic, it's
because the verse says וכל לא תאכלו. vechol lo tochlu. The verse
is telling you that we're only talking about animals whose fat is
forbidden. A deer whose fat is permissible, the חלב actually does cause
טומאה. Okay, now what we're going to do is, remember, I spelled
out the meaning of the ברייתא braita, that was talking about birds
when it says there's some type of an animal that the נבלה
neveilah is actually of a non-kosher animal is actually טהור. tahor So
I told you that's talking about birds, but that wasn't explicit in
the ברייתא, braita it was a very bizarre line in the ברייתא
braita until I explained it. It's not because I'm a genius, it's
because I read the end of the גמרא. Gemara Okay, or actually
because I read רש"י Rashi who told me what the end of
the גמרא Gemara was going to say. But now the גמרא Gemara
is going to try to figure that out. What did that ברייתא
braita mean when it said, wait, there's some type of non-kosher animals
that the נבלה neveilah is טהור. tahor Really? So the גמרא Gemara
says like
this: אמר ליה רב יעקב בר אבא לרבא. Amar lei Rav Yaakov
bar Abba le-Rava. So רב יעקב בר אבא Rav Yaakov bar Abba
said to רבא, Rava, אלא
מעתה נבלת בהמה טהורה הוא דמטמאה נבלת בהמה טמאה לא מטמאה?
ela me-ata nevilat behemah
tehorah hu de-metameiah nevilat behemah tmeiah lo metameiah? So he says, I
don't understand when the ברייתא braita said that a נבלה neveilah of
a non-kosher animal is טהור. tahor. What the heck do you mean
a נבלה neveilah of a non-kosher animal is טהור? tahor? The נבלה
neveilah of a pig is טהור? tahor. Are you kidding me? What
does that mean? So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to
him, כמה סבי שבישתו. kama savei shavishtu. How many elders have, you
know, confused things? Like you're such a great and senior rabbi, I'm
surprised you couldn't understand what that ברייתא braita meant. סיפא אתאן לנבלת
עוף טמא. Seifa atan le-nevilat of tamei. The end where it's saying
that there's a נבלה neveilah of a non-kosher animal that's טהור, tahor
it means in the bird world. And the bird world, ironically, נבלה
neveilah. of a non-kosher bird is טהור. tahor, Okay, phew, we are
done with that. Now, what we get to spend the end time
doing is of this ברייתא braita is looking back at רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir basic position. רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir basic position is even
the מליקה melikah of a bird that is a טרפה treifa is
not going to make it טמא. tamei, Okay, right? That was רבי
מאיר's Rabbi Meir position, right? Going back to that basic point. So
even though you did מליקה. melikah. Now looking back here, there's a
lot of ways if you do מליקה melikah wrong it is טמא,
tamei, it does become a נבלה. neveilah. And what's most relevant for
us are things like if you do it on חולין chullin or
you do it on missing a limb or a chicken or too
young or whatever it is. So there's a good reason to think
that if it was a טרפה treifa and not kosher as a
sacrifice, that would also make—even if normally שחיטה of a טרפה treifa
bird is not טמא—to tamei. think that מליקה melikah of a טרפה
treifa bird is טמא. tamei? And nevertheless רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
no. So now we want to know how far is רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir going to push it that if you do מליקה melikah
on the wrong type of bird, it's still not going to be
טמא? tamei? All right? It's not going to be a נבלה. neveilah.
So let's take a look. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, לא שנו רבי מאיר אלא בתמימים. lo
shanu Rabbi Meir ela bi-tmimim. It was only by animals that did
not have a blemish. So at least externally or whatever it looked
like it would be a kosher קרבן korban and you only found
out afterwards that it wasn't. So that enough put it in the
category of right object that the מליקה melikah does not make it
a
נבלה. neveilah. אבל בבעלי מומין, Aval be-baalei mumin, if it has a
physical blemish, which presumably by a bird means like it's missing a
limb, לא, he would not say it. We had a ברייתא braita
that explicitly said, we don't know if the ברייתא braisa was רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but like if it's has a missing a limb,
it's out of the קרבן korban category, it's out of the right
object category, and in that case it actually is a נבלה. neveilah,
All right? ורבי אלעזר אמר, Ve-Rabbi Elazar amar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
says, אפילו בבעלי מומין. afilu be-baalei mumin. Nope! Once רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says even a טרפה treifa is considered the right object and
it's not a נבלה, neveilah. even a בעל מום baal mum is
considered the right object and it's not a נבלה. neveilah. Makes sense.
Well, it makes sense that they're compared, but it's getting a little
bit extreme. And now the גמרא Gemara is going to make it
even more extreme.
איתמר נמי, Itmar nami, it was also taught, אמר רב ביבי אמר
רבי אלעזר, amar Rav Bibi amar Rabbi Elazar, מטהר היה רבי מאיר
בבעלי מומין. metaher hayah Rabbi Meir be-baalei mumin. He would say even
if it's got a blemish, it's not a
נבלה. neveilah, ואפילו באווזים ותרנגולים, ve-afilu be-avazim ve-tarnegolim, even by ducks and
chicken. Now that already doesn't make so much sense, right? So basically
what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is learning from his principle that according
to this, that a מליקה melikah on a טרפה is not a
נבלה, neveilah, is that מליקה melikah even on the wrong object is
not a נבלה, neveilah, is not a נבלה, meaning it has to
probably be sanctified. You know, when you sanctify your chicken as a
קרבן, korban, it really doesn't have a real, like, you know, obviously
it can't ever be brought as a קרבן. korban.
Presumably he still agrees to this principle of חולין, chullin, if you
did a מליקה melikah on a non-sanctified bird, but he seems to
be saying once you sanctify... sanctify it as a קרבן, korban, no
matter how messed up it is, it's a טריפה, it's a בעל
מום, baal mum, it's a chicken, whatever it is, okay, it's still
the מליקה melikah is not going to make it a נבילה. neveilah.
Yes.
A sanctified bird that's not able to be brought on the altar,
wouldn't that be בדק הבית? bedek habayit?
Yes, it would be. Or, you know, you transfer the קדושה, kedusha,
whatever. But yes. I mean, yes. Okay. But anyway, but that's surprising,
right, that even that קדושה kedusha that was never fit to be
קדושת קרבן kedushas korban because you sanctified a chicken, nevertheless, for him,
that's enough to, what do you call it, to say to say
that מליקה melikah is not a נבילה. neveilah. Okay.
Now, בעי רב ירמיה, ba'ei Rav Yermiah, רב ירמיה Rav Yermiah asks
the following question. Once we're talking about this, that it could be
way off and still not be a נבילה neveilah for רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, he wants to know about another case where you break
something's neck from behind. What thing do you break its neck from
behind?
The עגלה ערופה.
eglah arufah. Exactly. So, בעי רב ירמיה, ba'ei Rav Yermiah, רב ירמיה
Rav Yermiah asks: ערף עז מהו? araf ez mahu? Instead of using
an עגלה, eglah, a calf, the young cow, let's say you took
like a, you know, a ram, right?
So what would be the story? That עז? ez? Yeah. A ram,
right? How's it translated? Ram?
Isn't it a goat?
עז, ez, right, right, I'm sorry. I'm thinking of איל, ayil, excuse
me, goat. I'm sorry, goat. Right. עזים, izim, of course, עזים את
העם, izim at ha'am, okay, I don't know. Okay, sorry. If you
go ahead and you and you break the neck of a goat,
so what is the story? Okay. Now, it means that he presumably
assumes, which the גמרא Gemara is going to reveal in a moment,
that he presumably presumes that when you break the neck of an
עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, it's not a נבילה. neveilah. That's a fascinating
question. When I break the neck of an עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah,
does it have טומאת נבילה? tumas neveilah? Do we say similar to
מליקה, melikah, that when you kill it in the way the תורה
Torah tells me to kill it, that takes it out of the
נבילה neveilah category? Even though, right, as opposed to the bird sacrifice,
the breaking of the neck makes it usable, usable to put on
the מזבח, mizbeiach, usable to be eaten, so there's a logic to
say the breaking of the neck makes it not a נבילה. neveilah.
By an עגלה ערופה, eglah arufah, the point is you break it
in the neck and you do you use it for a ritual,
but it doesn't make it usable for anything, usable for anything, you
leave it there, right? So we have no evidence that the breaking
of the neck makes it somehow fit to be used. But nevertheless,
we're going to assume that since the תורה Torah mandates the breaking
of the neck, that it is going to be a not a
נבילה. neveilah. And now we want to know, so according to רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, if you do מליקה melikah on a chicken that
you sanctified, it's not a נבילה. neveilah. What if for the עגלה
ערופה eglah arufah you used a goat and you broke the neck
of a goat? Right? What would be that story? Would that be
a נבילה neveilah or not?
Okay. So, of course there's a little bit of a difference because
even in the chicken case, you sanctified it, you brought it to
the... well, here you brought it to the wadi, but the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash is a defined place. Which wadi you're going to
use for עגלה ערופה eglah arufah is not a defined place. So
what's to define that what I did with my goat was not
just some like animal torture in a wadi? What's to define it
as an act of עגלה ערופה? eglah arufah? Here at least you
have the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it is sanctified, you know, it's
being done by a כהן, kohen, right, the מליקה melikah has to
be done by a כהן, kohen, right, so there you could say
you have all of that, even though it's a chicken, it's still
a מליקה melikah and it's still not a נבילה. neveilah. But what
he says: what about if you used a goat for עגלה ערופה
eglah arufah where you don't have the same defined... I mean, yeah,
you do have a ritual, you have all the זקנים zekeinim coming
down, but nevertheless, it's not exactly the same as a fully defining
context. Okay. What would be the story there? Would that be a
נבילה neveilah or not?
So, יתיב רב דימי וקאמר לה להא שמעתא, yaseiv Rav Dimi veka'amar
lah l'ha shmaysa, so what does it say? So, let's go to
the end. So,
בעי רב ירמיה, ba'ei Rav Yermiah, so רב ירמיה Rav Yermiah who
always asks these types of questions, right, he always wants to know
one leg inside חמשים אמה, chamishim amah, one leg outside חמשים אמה.
chamishim amah. So בעי רב ירמיה, ba'ei Rav Yermiah, רב ירמיה Rav
Yermiah asks: ערף עז מהו? araf ez mahu? What about if you
did an עגלה ערופה eglah arufah and you used a goat?
אווז ותרנגול אמתינא מאי דמינו דעופות נינהו? avaz vetarnigol amtaina mai demino
de'ofos ninhu? Why by chickens does it work to say that it's
still not a נבילה? neveilah? Because at least they're birds. It's the...
אבל עז לאו מיניה הוא. aval ez lav minei hu. But a
goat and a cow are completely different types of animals. Okay. לאו
מיניה דעגלה נינהו. lav minei d'eglah ninhu. או דלמא, od dilma, or
do we say, מיניה דבהמה הוא? minei debeheimah hu? It might not
be a type of a cow, but it's still a type of
a mammal, you know, the same way... right. So anyway, so that's
what we want to know. What would be that story? So he
wants to know is it significantly similar or different? I want to
say, to me the bigger question is is that you don't have
the same defining context as you do by the case of the
bird. But the גמרא Gemara first wants to uncover the hidden assumption
here. The hidden assumption that an עגלה ערופה eglah arufah is not
a נבילה, neveilah, which is fascinating in itself. יתיב רב דימי וקאמר
לה להא שמעתא, yaseiv Rav Dimi veka'amar lah l'ha shmaysa, רב דימי
Rav Dimi was telling this over. אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye,
אביי Abaye said to him: one minute, מכלל דעגלה ערופה טהורה היא?
miklal d'eglah arufah tehorah hee? Is the assumption here that an עגלה
ערופה eglah arufah is טהורה, is not a נבילה? neveilah? Again, even
though... So the Torah says break its neck, as opposed to the
מליקה melikah of a bird, it doesn't say that it makes the
bird the calf usable for something. So אמר ליה אין, Amar leih
in, yes. אמרי דבי רבי ינאי, Amrei devei Rabbi Yannai, they say
in the house of Rabbi Yannai, כפרה כתיב בה כקדשים. kaparah ketiv
bah kekodashim.
By the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah it says כפר לעמך ישראל, kaper
le'amcha Yisrael, atone for your people Israel. So since it treats it
as an act of atonement, we're looking at it as a pseudo-קרבן,
korban, right? So that's fascinating. How do you look at the עגלה
ערופה? Eglah Arufah? Do you sort of say, you know, we're killing
this because it's sort of like in place of executing the murderer,
or we're killing this to remind us of the innocently spilled blood,
right? Or do you say, you know, I mean it uses the
elders, it does not use כהנים, kohanim, so it seems like it's
more of a judicial thing of like blood is on our hands,
right? That seems to be the idea and you atone for us
because by owning our responsibility that the bloodshed was our, you know,
negligence, you know, that just should bring about a form of atonement.
On the other hand, you're doing a ritual killing of an animal
which sounds an awful lot like a קרבן. korban. So how much
do you think of עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah as a type of
a קרבן, korban, even though it's outside the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
So the גמרא Gemara is here saying since it says atone and
כפר, kaper, it's enough like a קרבן korban to basically say the
same way the מליקה melikah of a bird in a קרבן korban
context is not a נבילה, neveilah, the breaking of the neck of
an עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah is also not a נבילה, neveilah, yes.
Is the שעיר לעזאזל Seir L'Azazel tamei?
Right. Right, that's a good question too. Okay, I don't know. מיתיבי
Meisivei it's a good question when you throw the שעיר Seir off
the cliff, whatever. מיתיבי רב נתן אבוה דרב הונא בר נתן, Meisivei
Rav Nasan avuha deRav Huna bar Nasan, whatever. וחלבם לא תאכלו. Vechlevam
lo socheilu. אין לי אלא חלב שאסור באכילה ומותר בהנאה, חלב של
שור הנסקל ועגלה ערופה. Ein li ela chelev she'asur ba'achilah umutar behana'ah,
chelev shel Shor Haniskal ve'Eglah Arufah.
I'm going to challenge this idea that an עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah
is not a נבילה. neveilah. Because what is the story when, okay,
about this thing that is טהור? tahor. So the ברייתא braisa says
like
this:
I only know that the חלב of a נבילה neveilah that's טהור
tahor. is the type of a חלב that you're allowed to get
benefit from. You can't eat, but you can get benefit from. Because
that's the פסוק pasuk about ייעשה לכל מלאכה, ye'aseh lechol melachah, which
is it's טהור tahor. and you can get benefit from it. חלב
של שור הנסקל ועגלה ערופה, Chelev shel Shor Haniskal ve'Eglah Arufah, how
about the fat of a שור הנסקל Shor Haniskal and עגלה ערופה,
Eglah Arufah, which the assumption here is that it's a נבילה? neveilah?
But not only is it a נבילה, neveilah, because it's an עגלה
ערופה Eglah Arufah or a שור הנסקל, Shor Haniskal, okay, you can't
derive benefit from it. So since this פסוק pasuk of ייעשה לכל
מלאכה ye'aseh lechol melachah does not apply to it, which tells you
you can derive benefit, maybe I should say that the חלב actually
should be טמא, tamei. not טהור. tahor How do I know that
that's also טהור? tahor? תלמוד לומר כל חלב. Talmud lomar kol chelev.
Okay, so because of the word of כל חלב, kol chelev, you
treat it all the same, even the חלב of an עגלה ערופה
Eglah Arufah is טהור. tahor. Okay, but now we've got a problem.
The fact that you have to tell me the חלב of an
עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah is טהור tahor. implies what about the meat?
That the meat is טמא, tamei. right? If you have to tell
me the חלב is טהור, tahor? which is what this ברייתא braisa
is telling me, presumably the meat is טמא. tamei. But you just
got through telling me that the meat of an עגלה ערופה Eglah
Arufah is טהור. tahor. Okay, וכי תימא, vechi teima, עגלה ערופה טהורה
היא, Eglah Arufah tehorah hee, if עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah because you
did the right ritual and it's like a קרבן korban or whatever
it is, the meat is טהור. tahor. היא טהורה וחלבה טמא? Hee
tehorah vechelba tamei?
So why would I never have thought that the fat would be
טמא? tamei. Of course the fat is טהור. tahor. Why do you
need a פסוק pasuk to tell me why do you need this
ברייתא to teach me the fat is טהור tahor, if the meat
itself is טהור? tahor. So the גמרא Gemara says look, היכא דעריף
מעריף לא איצטריכא ליה. Heicha de'arif me'arif lo itztricha leih. If you
did the right ritual, you don't need the פסוק pasuk to tell
me this. If you did the right ritual and broke the neck,
even the meat is טהור. tahor, And then of course the חלב
is טהור. tahor. Okay, כי איצטריך, ki itztrich, why do you need
the when do you need the פסוק pasuk to tell me the
חלב is טהור? tahor Meaning when would the meat be טמא? tamei.
היכא דשחטה משחט. Heicha deshachata meshachat. You took this עגלה ערופה Eglah
Arufah and instead of breaking the neck, you שחט-ed shecht it, okay?
So in that case, since you did the wrong ritual, so there
I might think that the חלב is טמא. tamei. The גמרא Gemara
says wait, even if you did the wrong ritual, since you שחט-ed
shecht it, the meat is still טהור. The גמרא says wait a
minute, ודהני ליה שחיטה לטהרו מידי נבלה? vede'hanei leih shechitah leta'aro midei
neveilah? That doesn't make sense because that's not a case where the
meat is טמא. No, לא צריכא שמתה. lo tzricha shemesah. Okay, no,
here's the case. If you took this down and you broke its
neck because you did the right ritual, it's all טהור. If you
שחט-ed shecht it because you שחט-ed it, it's all טהור. But there's
a case by the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah where the meat is
טמא. What is it? You brought it down into the wadi, you
were going to break the neck, and before you got a chance
to break the neck, it dropped dead on you. So there it's
a נבילה, neveilah, and there it's טמא. And there I might have
thought that even though a normal נבילה neveilah the חלב is טהור,
maybe this נבילה neveilah of an עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah the חלב
is טמא. And therefore it has to tell you even here the
חלב is טהור. So the גמרא says מכלל דמחיים אסורה... mikal demichayim
asurah... wait a minute, if you're saying that if it died it
has a status of an עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah that's forbidden in
הנאה hana'ah even if it dropped dead on its own, I would
have normally thought when does the status
of
עגלה ערופה... Eglah Arufah... אין, In, yes, there’s a moment before you
break the neck where it already becomes forbidden in benefit, okay? אמר
רב ינאי Amar Rav Yannai גבו שמעתי ושכחתי. Gvu shamati v’shachachti. I
heard that there was a moment in time where it becomes an
עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah and forbidden in benefit even before you break
the neck. I forgot what that moment in time was. ונסבין חברייא
למימר V’nasvin chavrayah l’meimar but the חברייא, chavrayah, you know, the students
in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash sort of have, you know, have
concluded or came to a consensus to say, ירידתו לנחל איתן היא
אוסרתה, Yeridato l’nachal eitan hi osarta, when you bring it down into
the wadi, that gives it the status. So actually, yes, by coming
with the בית דין Beis Din and doing the whole ritual, that
gives it the status and by the way, that makes it easier
to understand why the breaking of the neck of a goat even,
because if there’s something that precedes the breaking of the neck that
gives it that status, you know, the בית דין Beis Din bringing
it down, so then we’re sort of saying that therefore that’s an
עגלה ערופה. Eglah Arufah. If you do the right ritual and break
the neck, the whole thing is טהור, but if it dies, it’s
a נבילה neveilah and it’s טמא. But it’s also an עגלה ערופה
Eglah Arufah because you brought it into the wadi and therefore I
need a פסוק to tell me even that נבילה neveilah the fat
is going to be טהור. Okay? And the question of רב ירמיה
Rav Yirmeya was once you say that by an עגלה ערופה Eglah
Arufah if you do the right ritual it is טהור even if
you break its neck, what is the story if I use a
goat for the עגלה ערופה Eglah Arufah according to רבי מאיר? Rabbi
Meir? And we’re going to have to go to bed tonight not
knowing the answer to that question. Okay, הדרן עלך חטאת העוף. Hadran
Alach Chatas HaOf.