Boker tov (בוקר טוב). Boker tov Today's daf (דף) daf is kuf-zayin
(ק"ז), kuf-zayin 107, but we're a little behind. We pick up on
kuf-vav amud-bet (ק"ו עמוד ב), kuf-vav amud-bet
ela amar Rav Avin (אלא אמר רב אבין), ela amar Rav Avin
which is about 10 lines down. The words Rav Avin is in
the parentheses. So some versions have ela amar Abaye (אלא אמר אביי).
ela amar Abaye And the question of the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara is
how do you know that, we're dealing with the issue of shechutei
ve-haalot chutz (שחוטי והעלאות חוץ) shechutei ve-haalot chutz that you can't shecht
(שחט) shecht something outside the Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש) Beis Hamikdash as
a korban (קרבן) korban or offer it up, burn it on an
altar as a korban (קרבן). korban This is an issue of a
bamah (במה) bamah of a private altar, and if you do so,
you're chayav kares (חייב כרת), chayav kares you're deserving of excision. This
is even if it's being offered to God. And the Gemara's (גמרא's)
Gemara question is that the verses make it clear what the punishment
is, but they never, but when it comes to offering, it says
explicitly that you're not allowed to: lo tishamer lecha pen ta'aleh olotecha
(לא תשמר לך פן תעלה עלתיך), lo tishamer lecha pen ta'aleh olotecha
be careful lest you offer up your olot (עלות). olot But when
it comes to the issue about slaughtering a korban (קרבן) korban outside
the Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש), Beis Hamikdash it never explicitly says that
it's prohibited. And we have a principle that in order to get
a punishment, you need for it to be prohibited, and not only
that, the implication of our Mishnah (משנה) Mishnah when it says 'you
are chayav (חייב), chayav when are you chayav (חייב), chayav when are
you chayav (חייב)' chayav means when would you have to bring a
korban (קרבן)? korban If you did it beshogeg (בשוגג), beshogeg unintentionally, then
you bring a korban (קרבן). korban Now you only bring a korban
(קרבן) korban for something that is actually, there's a negative prohibition and
the punishment is kares (כרת) kares when you do it willingly. So
the Gemara's (גמרא's) Gemara question is where is the negative prohibition of
slaughtering a sacrifice outside of the Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש)? Beis Hamikdash
And we tried various arguments and none of them worked. So now
let's see what the answer is, or what the answers we sort
of settle on. Ela amar Rav Avin (אלא אמר רב אבין) ela
amar Rav Avin or ela amar Abaye (אלא אמר אביי): ela amar
Abaye kal vachomer (קל וחומר). kal vachomer
We're going to learn out the prohibition from a kal vachomer (קל
וחומר). kal vachomer Mah bimkom shelo anash hizhir (מה במקום שלא ענש
הזהיר), mah bimkom shelo anash hizhir
in a place where you don't have a weighty punishment, nevertheless you
get a prohibition. Okay, what's the case where you don't have a
weighty punishment? When it comes to slaughtering, we had just said that
if an animal was sanctified as a korban (קרבן) korban when private
altars were still allowed, there was the period before the building of
the Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש), Beis Hamikdash before the building of the
Mishkan (משכן). Mishkan So it was sanctified when those altars were allowed,
and then the Mishkan (משכן) Mishkan was built, or then the Beis
Hamikdash (בית המקדש) Beis Hamikdash was built, so even though that's also
prohibited now, because since now there's a central place you're not allowed
to offer it. Since it was sanctified when there wasn't a central
place, so although you violate a prohibition, you don't get kares (כרת).
kares Okay, so that was the discussion yesterday that it was sanctified
before the Mishkan (משכן) Mishkan or the Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש) Beis
Hamikdash was built and now it's built. You're still not allowed to
slaughter it, but you don't get kares (כרת). kares So now it's
a kal vachomer (קל וחומר). kal vachomer If you're prohibited even without
kares (כרת) kares in that case, so in a case where everything,
where we know it was sanctified afterwards and everything was after there
was a Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש) Beis Hamikdash and you get kares
(כרת), kares it's implicit that it's prohibited, right? Makes a lot of
sense. Mah bimkom shelo anash hizhir (מה במקום שלא ענש הזהיר), mah
bimkom shelo anash hizhir when if there's when there's no punishment of
kares (כרת), kares nevertheless it's prohibited when it was sanctified before the
Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש) Beis Hamikdash and then the Beis Hamikdash (בית
המקדש) Beis Hamikdash was built. Makom she-anash einu din she-yizhir (מקום שענש
אינו דין שיזהיר)? makom she-anash einu din she-yizhir When we know you
get kares (כרת) kares for slaughtering, it's explicit if you slaughter an
animal that you sanctified after there was a Beis Hamikdash (בית המקדש)
Beis Hamikdash and you slaughter it out of the Beis Hamikdash (בית
המקדש), Beis Hamikdash that's when you get kares (כרת). kares So it
certainly should be assumed that it's prohibited. That's our kal vachomer (קל
וחומר). kal vachomer So amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi (אמר ליה רבינא
לרב אשי). amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi So now what we're basically
doing is we're saying that you can infer a prohibition, you can
learn out a prohibition from a kal vachomer (קל וחומר). kal vachomer
Now we're going to challenge that in a minute because the general
principle is ein mazhirin min hadin (אין מזהירין מן הדין), ein mazhirin
min hadin you can't learn that something is prohibited based on a
kal vachomer (קל וחומר). kal vachomer It needs to be explicit. But
that's our argument now, okay? If there's a prohibition without a punishment
in this type of case, then certainly when there is a punishment
there should be a prohibition. That's our kal vachomer (קל וחומר). kal
vachomer So amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi (אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי),
amar leh Ravina le-Rav Ashi so Ravina said to Rav Ashi: im
ken (אם כן), im ken lo yomar lav bechelev (לא יאמר לאו
בחלב). lo yomar lav bechelev
If you can learn out a prohibition from a kal vachomer (קל
וחומר), kal vachomer why did the Torah have to ever tell me
that it was prohibited to eat this forbidden fat of an animal
and which is, by the way, the punishment is kares (כרת). kares
Just tell me you get kares (כרת) kares and I'll be able
to infer that it's prohibited based on comparing it to other issues
of kashrus (כשרות). kashrus Why? Tesei be-kal vachomer (תיתי בקל וחומר), tesei
be-kal vachomer learn it from a kal vachomer (קל וחומר). kal vachomer
Mi-neveilah (מנבלה), mi-neveilah from an animal that wasn't shechted properly, there you
don't get kares (כרת). kares It's a negative prohibition, but you don't
get kares (כרת). kares So I should say, if in areas of
kashrus (כשרות) kashrus sometimes it's prohibited without kares (כרת), kares then if
chelev (חלב) chelev gets kares (כרת), kares certainly it should be prohibited.
Okay, that's why why did the Torah have to tell me not
to eat chelev (חלב)? chelev So mah neveilah shelo anash hizhir (מה
נבלה שלא ענש הזהיר)... mah neveilah shelo anash hizhir נבלה neveilah that
there's no כרת, kareth, it's prohibited, חלב שענש לא דין שהזהיר, chelev
she-anash lo din she-hizhir, חלב chelev that you get כרת, kareth, certainly
it should be prohibited.
So also, so you know, come on, you can't just make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer to learn something is out, out is prohibited.
So אתא לקמיה דרבא, ata lekamei de-Rava, so this question came to
רבא. אמר Rava amar ליה, no,
it's possible you can't learn out prohibitions from a קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, and here's why I'm not bothered by your question about חלב.
chelev. אמר ליה, amar lei, מנבלה נמי לא אתיא. mi-neveilah nami lo
atya.
No,
you can't learn out חלב chelev from נבלה. neveilah. דאיכא למפרך, de-ika
lemifrach, you could challenge it. מה לנבלה שכן מטמאה? mah le-neveilah sheken
mitama? Okay,
maybe נבלה neveilah is prohibited because it's weightier, it causes טומאה. tumah.
So just because we normally say נבלה neveilah is lighter, there's no
כרת, kareth, and if there's a prohibition by נבלה, neveilah, certainly it
should be by חלב. chelev. That was the question. So why do
you need the prohibition by חלב? chelev? So now we're saying, wait,
נבלה neveilah isn't lighter, maybe it's true there's no כרת, kareth, but
it causes טומאה, tumah, so you can't make a קל וחומר kal
vachomer from נבלה. neveilah. Okay, משרצים טמאים? mi-shratzim temeim? How about dead
rodents that cause טומאה? tumah? And so let's make a קל וחומר,
kal vachomer, they're also no כרת kareth prohibited, קל וחומר kal vachomer
to חלב? chelev? No. מה לשרצים טמאים שמטמאין במשהו? mah le-shratzim temeim
she-metamin be-mashahu? They're also they cause טומאה. tumah. Okay, משרצים טהורים? mi-shratzim
tehorim?
Okay, let's make a קל וחומר kal vachomer from forbidden rodents, things
that are forbidden to be eaten but that don't cause טומאה, tumah,
like a frog, for example. Okay, so why don't we say, so
if a frog is prohibited without כרת, kareth, חלב chelev which gets
כרת kareth certainly should be prohibited? No. מה לשרצים טהורים שאסורים במשהו?
mah le-shratzim tehorim she-asurim be-mashahu? There you because there
the because it's a שרץ sheretz and other שרצים shratzim cause טומאה
tumah in a little bit, a little bit is like the size
of a כעדשה ke-adasha like a bean, not literally a tiniest amount.
So here too, even though they don't cause טומאה, tumah, the prohibition
for eating them is not the normal כזית ke-zayit size, but a
much smaller size. So you can't say just because this is prohibited
חלב chelev should be prohibited. This is weightier, at least in one
area, that even if you eat a tiny amount, you still would
get lashes. So the גמרא Gemara says fine. How about מערלה וכלאי
הכרם? me-orlah ve-kilay ha-kerem? Let's make a קל וחומר kal vachomer from
ערלה orlah and כלאים, kilayim, those are prohibited no כרת, kareth, so
certainly חלב? chelev? No. מה לערלה וכלאי הכרם שכן אסורים בהנאה? mah
le-orlah ve-kilay ha-kerem sheken asurim be-hana'ah? Those things are forbidden in benefit,
so you can't apply that to חלב. chelev. Again, every one of
these things has something weightier, so the קל וחומר kal vachomer fails.
משביעית? mi-shevi'it? How about a קל וחומר kal vachomer from שביעית? shevi'it?
No. מה לשביעית שכן תופסת דמיה? mah le-shevi'it sheken tofesset dameha? That
has a weighty thing that when you buy שביעית shevi'it the status
transfers to the money you bought it with. מתרומה? mi-truma? How about
תרומה? truma? No. שכן לא הותרה מכללה. sheken lo hutra miklala. Okay,
no no, so תרומה truma has you know and it's funny, there's
other things you could say about תרומה, truma, but anyway the גמרא
Gemara here points out תרומה truma is weightier because there's never a
case תרומה truma is permitted to a non-כהן. kohen. Now where's חלב
chelev permitted? וחלב ve-chelev isn't exactly permitted, the חלב chelev of a
בהמה, behemah, but the חלב chelev of a חיה chayah is permitted,
right? So חלב chelev is only something, the fat is only prohibited
when it's an animal that could be in theory brought as a
קרבן korban like a בהמה. behemah. It is not the fat of
a deer, for example, is not prohibited. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says so therefore you really can't make a קל וחומר kal vachomer
from anything to חלב chelev because חלב chelev has a way in
which it's more lenient than all other prohibited food items, that the
existence of חלב chelev in a in a deer, for example, is
permitted. Okay, מכולהו נמי שכן לא הותרה מכללו. mi-kulehu nami sheken lo
hutra miklalo. And that's really a way why you can't make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer from anything because חלב chelev actually has a
way in which in which it's less weighty even though it gets
כרת. kareth. Okay,
so we're trying to say, don't tell me it's prohibited based on
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If you can make קל וחומר kal
vachomer then to then I'll make קל וחומר kal vachomer elsewhere and
you know and that'll raise questions and up till now the גמרא's
Gemara answer is very local. No no no, you can't make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer for this or this reason, but in general
you know in this case of חלב. chelev. But in general maybe
you should be able to use a קל וחומר kal vachomer to
learn that something is prohibited. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר
רבא, amar Rava, says רבא, Rava. אי קשיא לי הא קשיא לי.
ei kashya li ha kashya li. If you want to know what
bothers me about this idea that you can learn something is prohibited
from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, here's what bothers me. הדתנן פסח
ומילה מצות עשה. ha-di-tenan Pesach u-milah mitzvat aseh. That פסח Pesach and
מילה milah you get כרת kareth but you don't you don't transgress
a negative prohibition, it's just lack of doing a positive מצווה. mitzvah.
But now רבא Rava, says, I got a good קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. If there's כרת kareth then you should get it should be
negatively prohibited. Okay?
תיתי בקל וחומר. teiti be-kal vachomer.
With your logic that if something you get כרת kareth for you
can make a קל וחומר kal vachomer that it's prohibited from something
that you don't get כרת kareth for, say that about bringing a
קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Let me say that it's actually a transgression,
a negative prohibition. Okay, so מנותר, mi-notar, leaving the food over from
the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Not eating נותר notar but leaving it
over. So that's prohibited, no כרת. kareth. So the פסח Pesach itself
where you do get כרת kareth certainly it should be a negative
prohibition. No. מה נותר שלא ענש הזהיר. mah notar shelo onash hizhir.
פסח ומילה שענש אינו דין שהזהיר. Pesach u'milah she'onash eino din shehizhir.
Okay, so again, if you can learn a negative prohibition from a
קל וחומר, kal vachomer, it's going to be a very disruptive idea.
So אמר רב אשי אמריתיה לשמעתא קמי דרב כהנא, amar Rav Ashi
amritai l'shemata kamei d'Rav Kahana, I said this over to רב כהנא,
Rav Kahana, ואמר לי v'amar li and רב כהנא Rav Kahana said
to me, ממותיר לא אתיא. mimotir lo atya. No, no, no, you
can't learn it out from מותיר. motir. Why? דאיכא למפרך מה למותיר
שכן אין לו תקנה? d'ika l'mifrach ma l'motir sheken ein lo takana?
When you leave something over and you make it נותר, nosar, it's
ruined, there's no way to fix it. תאמר בפתח שיש לו תקנה,
tomar b'Pesach sheyesh lo takana, but by פסח Pesach you can fix
it, you can bring a second פסח. Pesach. So for a technical
reason you can't make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. But anyway what
the גמרא's Gemara doing here, it's saying is
maybe like it's trying to challenge the idea of using a קל
וחומר kal vachomer to learn something is prohibited by local counterexamples. And
it's managed to respond to all the local counterexamples. But now the
גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute, we have a principle that you're
not allowed to do this. Fine, forget the local example. But you
have a principle that you do not learn a prohibition based on
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, וכי מזהירין מן הדין? v'chi mazhirin
min hadin? Do you learn that something is prohibited based on a
קל וחומר? kal vachomer? Okay, אפילו למאן דאמר עונשין מן הדין, afilu
l'man d'amar onshin min hadin, even if you say you can get
punished from a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, you can learn out once
you know something is prohibited, you can figure out what the punishment
is based on a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, but מזהירין מן הדין?
mazhirin min hadin? But the basic fact that something is prohibited, you
can't learn out from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, there's something
nice about this idea
because, if the idea of something being prohibited, right, it's all like
divine command, right, the sense of prohibition is because God said don't
do it. So the whole use of a קל וחומר kal vachomer
is like the human component in deriving and so on, and it's
human logic, and like don't use your logic to tell me, as
if God were saying like what's okay and not okay, you know
what I mean? So it's like if to define the basic issue
of what you, what you can and can't do, in terms of
the תורה מצות, Torah mitzvot, that has to come straight from God.
Like we can sort of infer the detail, we might even be
able to infer what the consequence, what the punishment is, but the
basic
commandedness, which is, that has to be like without, it's not something
you just figure out on your own logic. Okay, so anyway, so
therefore we're back to square one. How do you know that it's
prohibited to slaughter a sacrifice outside the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? אלא
כרבי יוחנן. ela k'Rabbi Yochanan.
Fine, we'll learn it from רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan דאמר אתיא הויה
הויה. d'amar atya havayah havayah.
It's based on a link. Because the תורה Torah speaks about don't
offer up outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and don't slaughter or
whatever tells you the consequence. And we learned it is a פסוק
pasuk that you're not allowed to offer up. השמר לך פן תעלה
עלותיך. hishamer lecha pen ta'aleh olotecha. Okay, so since the and in
the
so therefore
now we're going to just link the words. Okay, the words that,
right, is in ויקרא יז. Vayikra Yud-Zayin. Here's what it says, right,
it says we'll see the linked words we're going to use to
say if it's forbidden in the case of offering up, then it's
forbidden in the case of slaughtering. Okay, it says זה הדבר אשר
צוה ה' לאמר איש איש מבית ישראל אשר ישחט שור כשב או
עז או אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה, zeh hadavar asher tzivah Hashem lemor
ish ish mibeit Yisrael asher yishchat shor kesev o ez o asher
yishchat michutz lamachaneh, if you slaughter it, if you're in the camp
or out of the camp, ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו, v'el
petach ohel moed lo hevi'o,
but you don't bring it to the tent of meeting להקריב קרבן
לה' לפני משכן ה' דם יחשב לאיש ההוא, l'hakriv korban l'Hashem lifnei
mishkan Hashem dam yeichashev la'ish hahu,
it's considered like he spilled blood, דם שפך ונכרת האיש ההוא מקרב
עמו, dam shafach v'nichrat ha'ish hahu mikerev amo,
and he gets כרת. karet. So there's the כרת. karet. But it
never said you're not allowed to do it, it just says כרת.
karet. למען אשר יביאו, l'ma'an asher yavi'u, and there's הויה, havayah, בני
ישראל את זבחיהם אשר הם זובחים על פני השדה והביאום לה' אל
פתח אהל מועד אל הכהן וזבחו זבחי שלמים לה' אותם, bnei Yisrael
et zivcheihem asher hem zovchim al pnei hasadeh v'hevi'um l'Hashem el petach
ohel moed el hakohen v'zavchu zivchei shelamim l'Hashem otam,
in order that they should bring their קרבן korban to God. So
that's where it speaks about the punishment for שחיטה. shchita. Then it
speaks about offering up. ואליהם תאמר איש איש מבית ישראל ומן הגר
אשר יגור בתוכם אשר יעלה עלה או זבח, va'aleichem tomar ish ish
mibeit Yisrael u'min hager asher yagur betocham asher ya'aleh olah o zavach,
if you offer it up, ואל פתח מועד לא יביאנו, v'el petach
moed lo yavi'ennu,
so there again, you did not bring it to אהל מועד ohel
moed לעשות אותו לה' ונכרת האיש ההוא מעמיו. la'asot oto l'Hashem v'nichrat
ha'ish hahu me'amav.
So since we know that the עולה olah is forbidden because it's
bringing it up is forbidden because it says השמר לך פן תעלה
עלותיך, hishamer lecha pen ta'aleh olotecha, which
we can use the link of יביאנו yavi'ennu and הביאו, hevi'o, הויה
הויה havayah havayah
to say the same thing applies to the case of the case
of the שחיטה. shchita. אתיא הויה הויה, atya havayah havayah, מה להלן
לא ענש אלא אם כן הזהיר אף כאן לא ענש אלא אם
כן הזהיר. ma lehalan lo onash ela im ken hizhir af kan
lo onash ela im ken hizhir.
The same way by עולה, olah, by bringing it up, there's a
negative prohibition, by the שחיטה shchita there's a negative prohibition. Now the
point I made before, if you want something to be forbidden that
has to come from God, and here you are using a hermeneutic
principle. There's still a difference of a hermeneutic principle of a גזירה
שוה, gezeirah shavah, which our understanding is that fundamentally that's like encoded
in
the text to tell us to link these two and to say
that the same prohibition applies, as opposed to a קל וחומר kal
vachomer which is just my pure logical speculation, but I'm not like
saying that it's actually already encoded in the text. So this you're
allowed to do. Okay, רבא Rava דף קז עמוד א. daf kuf-zayin
amud aleph. Okay, רבא Rava אמר כרבי יונה. k'Rabbi Yonah. I'll learn
that שחיטה... shchita... עולתך. olatecha. Okay, so another גזירה שוה. gezerah shavah.
מה להלן לא ענש אלא אם כן הזהיר אף כאן לא ענש
אלא אם כן הזהיר. ma lehalan lo anash ela im ken hizhir
af kan lo anash ela im ken hizhir.
So fine, the basic answer is we get it from a גזירה
שוה gezerah shavah based on the idea of עולה, olah, of... not
עולה, olah, whatever, an עולה olah קרבן, korban, based on the idea
of העלאה ha'ala'ah of offering them up on the fire, which we
know there is a negative prohibition, so we use that גזירה שוה
gezerah shavah to tell me that there's also a negative prohibition for
what do you call it, or for... for שחיטה shechitah outside the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay,
now we move on. So now we're done with that discussion, okay,
about where you know that שחיטה shechitah is negatively prohibited. Now, new
topic.
אשכחן ashkechan מוקטרי פנים muktarei pnim שהעלה בחוץ. shehe'elah bachutz. Now this
is sort of getting to the debate in the משנה. Mishnah. We
can... we can infer or we assume that we're talking about things
let's say that you are... מוקטרי פנים muktarei pnim means things that
are fit to be offered up inside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Means if you שחט-ed shacht it in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and then you burnt it outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, because
remember a key principle here is, okay, ואל פתח אהל מועד לא
יביאנו. v'el pesach ohel moed lo yavi'enu. You're חייב chayav because you
didn't bring it as a קרבן korban into the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. All right, so it has to be something that is ראוי
לפנים. ra'uy lifnim. It is something that is fit to be brought
inside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. All right, so the question is,
and this was the debate in the משנה Mishnah with רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, what about something, so when you שחט shacht something outside
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it was fit to be brought in,
you're חייב. chayav. But if you're not talking about שחיטה, shechitah, we're
talking about burning on the fire, if you שחט-ed shacht it inside
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and burnt it outside, then you're burning
something outside that was fit to be burnt inside. Why was it
fit to be burnt inside? Because it was שחט-ed shacht inside. But
if you שחט shacht something outside and burn it outside, by the
time you get to the burning part on the altar, this is
not something that's fit for the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So why
are you חייב? chayav? Okay, that was and actually רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon in the משנה Mishnah says you're not חייב. chayav. Okay, so
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. אשכחן ashkechan מוקטרי פנים, muktarei pnim, we
found things that are fit to be burnt on the inside, שהעלה
בחוץ, shehe'elah bachutz, and if you burnt them on the outside you're
חייב chayav because that was at least fit to be burnt on
the
inside. מוקטרי חוץ שהעלה בחוץ מנין? muktarei chutz shehe'elah bachutz minayin? How
do you know something that was only fit for the outside? Meaning
how do you know something that was שחט-ed shacht on the outside,
that you're חייב chayav when you burn it? That you should say
that's not fit for the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and that's what
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually says, he actually says you're פטור. patur.
So אמר רב כהנא אמר קרא, amar Rav Kahana amar kra, the
verse says, ואליהם תאמר, v'aleihem tomar, על הסמוכים תאמר. al hasmookhim tomar.
So you have the whole פסוק pasuk right that sort of says,
you know, here it says, you know, here it says about שחוטי...
שחיטה, shechutei... shechitah, right? It says אשר ישחט במחנה, asher yishchat bamachaneh,
okay, you know, אשר ישחט במחנה במחנה או אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה,
asher yishchat bamachaneh bamachaneh o asher yishchat michutz lamachaneh, okay, ואל פתח
אהל מועד לא הביאו v'el pesach ohel moed lo hevi'o I think,
לא הביאו. lo hevi'o. ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו, v'el pesach
ohel moed lo hevi'o, okay, then it says like לא הביאו ונכרת.
lo hevi'o v'nichras. You get כרת, kareis, okay? So that's שחיטה. shechitah.
Okay, and then it says... why? Pens are ruining, or getting rid
of... then it says, okay, ואליהם תאמר, v'aleihem tomar, and to them
you should say, to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael you should say, right,
איש איש מבית ישראל ומן הגר אשר יגור בתוכם אשר יעלה, ish
ish mibeis Yisrael umin hager asher yagur besocham asher ya'aleh, אשר יעלה
עולה או זבח. asher ya'aleh olah o zavach. Okay, so here it's
יעלה, ya'aleh, it's burning. Here it's אשר ישחט. asher yishchat. And then
it says אשר יעלה עולה או זבח, asher ya'aleh olah o zavach,
ואל פתח אהל מועד לא יביאנו, v'el pesach ohel moed lo yavi'enu,
okay, ונכרת. v'nichras. Same idea. ואל פתח אהל מועד לא יביאנו ונכרת.
v'el pesach ohel moed lo yavi'enu v'nichras. Okay, and that's about שחוטי
חוץ shechutei chutz and this is about העלאת חוץ. ha'ala'as chutz. Okay,
so now we want to know what happens when you שחט, shacht,
how do you know if you שחט-ed shacht outside you're חייב chayav
if you burn it outside? Maybe you're only חייב chayav if you
שחט-ed shacht in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and then you burnt
it outside because that's fit for being offered in the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. But once you שחט-ed shacht it inside, it's no longer
fit for being offered in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, maybe it
should be פטור. patur. So the first answer is how we know
is the ואליהם תאמר. v'aleihem tomar. We're reading ואליהם *V'aleihem* as it
says ועליהם *V'aleihem*, not ואליהם *V'aleihem* to בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael *Bnei
Yisroel*, but regarding those things, on those things we mentioned above, things
you slaughtered outside, the following also applies: don't offer them outside. So
if we're reading אליהם *aleihem* to them as עליהם *aleihem* regarding those,
regarding those earlier things, it's also prohibited. And that's how the first
דרשה drasha *drasha* of how we learn that even if they're שחט
shacht *shechted* outside and not fit for inside, you're חייב chayav *chayav*
for offering them on the outside. ועליהם תאמר, על הסמוכים תאמר *V'aleihem
Tomar, Al HaSmuchim Tomar*, regarding the things just said above, this prohibition
of המעלה *ha'alah* also applies. משקיף ליה רבא Rava *Maskif lei Rava*,
so רבא Rava, *Rava* challenged this. מי כתיב ועליהם? ואליהם כתיב *Mi
ksiv V'aleihem? V'aleihem ksiv*. Okay, that's fine, but that's not what the
word is. אלא כדתניא דבי רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael *Ela kedisanya d'bei
Rabbi Yishmael*, like we taught in the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael *Rabbi Yishmael*, ואליהם תאמר *V'aleihem Tomar*, לערב פרשיות *l'arev parshiyos*. You're
right to focus on this word, but it's not the literal meaning
of the word, it's the ו *vav*. The ו *vav* connects them.
And by connecting them it's saying this prohibition of offering the, burning
the sacrifice applies even, not only to sacrifices that were slaughtered in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, but even to sacrifices that
were slaughtered out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. לערב
פרשיות *L'arev parshiyos*. רבי יוחנן אמר אתיא הבאה הבאה *Rabbi Yochanan amar:
asya hava hava*. No, similar to how we connected the פרשיות *parshiyos*
to learn out the sense of a prohibition, we're connecting it here
through the idea that it applies to things slaughtered outside by a
similar link. It says לא יביאנו lo yevienu *lo yevieno*, לא הביאו
*lo hevio*, so that teaches us. מה להלן מוקטרי חוץ chutz, *Ma
hallan muktarei chutz*, the same way the first פרשה parsha, *parsha* is
about שחט shacht *shecht* outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis
HaMikdash*, אף כאן מוקטרי חוץ *af kan muktarei chutz*, the second פרשה
*parsha* about burning it is also about a case, also includes a
case where it was slaughtered outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis
HaMikdash*. משקיף ליה רב ביבי *Maskif lei Rav Bibi*, now רב ביבי
*Rav Bibi* challenged this idea that there is a, that there are
these two separate prohibitions, as it were, one for when it was
slaughtered in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* and one for
when it was slaughtered out. הא דתנן *Ha ditnan*, we taught: שלושים
ושש כריתות בתורה *Shloshim v'shesh krisos baTorah*, there are 36 separate categories
in the תורה Torah. *Torah* where you get כרת *kares* for it,
negative prohibitions you get כרת *kares* for. Now according to you, תלתין
ושבעה הוין *tlatzin v'shiva haviyan*, they should be 37. דאיכא המעלה והמעלה
*D'ika ha'ma'aleh v'ha'ma'aleh*, because since you're saying that the prohibition of, when
it was slaughtered on the, the simple meaning of the verse was
when it was slaughtered inside, because that's פתח אהל מועד לא יביאנו
Pesach Ohel Moed
lo yevienu, *pesach Ohel Moed lo
yevieno*. But now based on another דרשה drasha *drasha* from the ו
*vav* that connects it, or from הבאה הבאה *hava hava*, whatever, we
learn that there's also a prohibition of when it was slaughtered on
the outside, that should make it a separate prohibition and a separate
כרת *kares*. Okay, now you say what difference does it make whether
you call it separate or not? Well, the difference is if you
do all of them at one time, forgetting that
any of these are prohibited, you would bring 36 קרבנות Korbanos. *korbanot*.
That's why, but that's why saying everything. Now let's say you forgot
that it was prohibited to offer קרבנות korbanos. *korbanot* outside the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and you brought one קרבן Korban *korban*
that
you had, you burnt one קרבן Korban, *korban* that you had slaughtered
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and one קרבן korban.
*korban* that you had slaughtered out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
*Beis HaMikdash*. If we consider it to be one prohibition, then you
only bring one חטאת chatas? *chatas* for that because it's doing twice
the same sin in one state of forgetfulness. But if we consider
two separate prohibitions, you would bring two sin offerings. So the point
is, according to this, right, this we need to list this as
a separate prohibition. Alright, so and why do we not? So that's
the question. אם *im* if you're distinguishing here
between when it was slaughtered in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis
HaMikdash* and slaughtered out and that we learn it from a different
place, then it needs to be a different prohibition and there's הלכתי
*halachic* ramifications about this. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says קשיא *kashya*,
fine, that's a difficulty. Alright, I'm not sure why it's such a
difficulty, since at the end of the day what we're saying is
that based on this ו *vav* and based on whatever it is,
we're saying that this פרשה *parsha* includes both cases. So if this
פרשה *parsha* includes both cases, why don't we just say it's one
prohibition? I don't really understand the force of the question why we
should assume that it's a separate prohibition. But anyway, now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay, but that's actually the issue in the משנה
*Mishna*. רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* says that the burning it only applies
to when it was שחט shacht *shecht* in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. And here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* saying is he's
got a point that would be the default, but based on this
דרשה *drasha*, that's why the רבנן *Rabbanan* assume that it applies even
if you שחט shacht *shecht* out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, והא דתנן *veha ditnan*, now that which we taught:
הזורק מקצת דמים בחוץ *hazorek miktzas damim bachutz*, we're about to teach
right this משנה *Mishna* that it applies not only to שחט shacht
*shechting* and burning, but even to sprinkling of the blood. Okay, if
you sprinkle some of the blood outside, חייב chayav *chayav*. מנא לן
*Mina lan*? So now here's a, here is a real new category.
How do you know you're חייב chayav *chayav* not just for שחט
shacht *shechting* and burning, but even for sprinkling blood? So מנא לן
*mina lan*? נפקא ליה מדיתניא *Nafkha lei mideisanya*, from what we taught
in the ברייתא Baraita *Braisah*. דם יחשב dam yeichashev. *Dam yeichashev*. Okay,
so here it says when you שחט shacht *shecht* it, לא יביאנו
yevienu *lo yevieno*, then it says דם Dam; יחשב לאיש ההוא דם
dam, שפך *Dam yeichashev la'ish hahu dam shafach*. Because basically it's like
you spilled blood, because I mean לאיש ההוא דם dam, שפך *la'ish
hahu dam shafach*, this is a whole issue about what justifies. What
justifies the taking of an animal life. So the simple sense of
this verse is well it's justified when it's being brought as a
קרבן; korban it's not when you bring it outside. Maybe there'll be
an allowance if you're doing it for the meat, but here you're
doing it, which comes later in the תורה. But here if you're
doing it not as a קרבן Korban out of the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash. besides that there's this problem of one central location, there's
a problem that it's the spilling of blood, the unjustified spilling of
blood. Okay, but now what we're going to learn from this is
the דם; dam. the focus on blood is going to tell us
that also what is prohibited is doing one of the sacrificial rituals
with the blood outside. Okay, so דם יחשב לרבות הזורק, Dam yeichashev
lerabbos hazorek, דברי רבי ישמעאל. divrei Rabbi Yishmael. That's what רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael says. רבי עקיבא אומר: Rabbi Akiva omer: או זבח o
zevach אשר יעלה עולה או זבח. asher ya'aleh olah o zevach. Okay,
here he focuses not on a פסוק pasuk by שחיטה; shechita; he
focuses on the פסוק pasuk by העלאה ha'ala'ah and it says עולה
או זבח. olah o zevach. So somehow the או o is, or
the זבח, zevach, or somehow which is slaughtering which maybe evokes the
idea of blood I mean this is a much nicer דרשה I
think, explicitly it's about blood okay, but he's going to say the
sort of mentioning an עולה olah or a זבח zevach is coming
to include an idea of sprinkling of the blood, לרבות את הזורק.
lerabbos es hazorek. ורבי ישמעאל האי או זבח מאי עביד ליה, Ve'Rabbi
Yishmael hai o zevach mai avid lei, what does he do with
it? לחלק. Lechalek. The או o is coming to tell you- what
do you mean? Of course you need to know, if it said
עולה וזבח olah vezevach you'd think you'd only be חייב chayav if
you brought both an עולה olah and a שלמים; Shelamim; we're going
to assume זבח zevach means a שלמים. Shelamim. So the או o
is telling you you're חייב chayav one or the other. Of course
you need the או; o; what do you mean? The או o
isn't extra; the או o is doing its normal grammatical function in
the verse. Okay. I lost my place. Okay, ורבי עקיבא לחלק מנא
ליה? Ve'Rabbi Akiva lechalek mena lei? Now how does he- if he
says the word או o is extra to teach you about זורק,
zorek, how does he- what do you mean? Doesn't it need to
do the function to tell you either an עולה olah or a
זבח, zevach, not both? So מנא ליה, mena lei, where does he
know that from? נפקא ליה מלא יביאנו. Nafka lei milo yevienu. Okay,
it says פתח אהל מועד pesach Ohel Moed. לא יביאנו, yevienu not
לא יביאם, lo yeviam, but יביאנו yevienu is singular. So that tells
you that even if it's only one קרבן, Korban. not two קרבנות.
korbanos Okay, ורבי ישמעאל ההוא מיבעי ליה; Ve'Rabbi Yishmael hahu mibaei lei;
no, the singular of לא יביאנו yavianu is telling you something else.
על השלם הוא חייב ואינו חייב על החסר. Al hashalem hu chayav
ve'eino chayav al hachaser. You're only חייב chayav if you burn something
whole, not something lacking. We'll see later what that means. Do you
have to burn up the whole animal? Does it mean that if
the animal is lacking a limb? Okay, but we'll see in a
minute the יביאנו doesn't mean one rather than two; it means the
complete thing. Okay, so that's what we're going to learn from it.
ורבי עקיבא נפקא ליה מלעשות אותו, Ve'Rabbi Akiva nafka lei mila'asos oso,
and to make it, so that means the sense that it's complete.
ורבי ישמעאל חד במוקטרי פנים שחיסרו והעלו בחוץ וחד במוקטרי חוץ שחיסרו
והעלו בחוץ. Ve'Rabbi Yishmael chad bemuktrei pnim shechisru vehe'elu bachutz vechad bemuktrei
chutz shechisru vehe'elu bachutz. No, no, no, the יביאנו and לעשות אותו,
la'asos oso, which are two verses that say that it means the
full thing, it's for two different scenarios. The two scenarios we talked
about: one that it was שחט shacht it in the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash. one that it was שחט shacht it out of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash And either way you're only חייב chayav if
you offer up the whole thing. Okay, דתניא detanya because we taught
in a ברייתא that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael makes this point, that
whether it's שחט shechted, in or out of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, you're only חייב chayav, if you offer up the whole thing.
רבי ישמעאל אומר: Rabbi Yishmael omer: יכול מוקטרי פנים שחיסרו והעלו בחוץ
חייב, Yachol muktrei pnim shechisru vehe'elu bachutz chayav, maybe if it was
שחט shechted. in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash Now let me explain
why שחט shechted in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. you think more
that you'd be חייב chayav, if it wasn't whole. Because רש''י Rashi
makes the point that when something is let's say in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash and you took the animal, the עולה, olah, you
put it all up on the fire, so it was whole, you
put it all up on the fire. Okay, and now though it's
been burning and most of it is consumed and there's one piece
of it that comes off. So what do you do? You put
it back up, right? So therefore in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
there's a principle that you put something even partial back on the
fire. So therefore maybe if I שחט shechted this in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash, and I burn it outside, maybe since it already
had that בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash context I'd be חייב chayav even
if I only burnt even on a partial thing, not on a
whole thing. So that's why he says I have to tell you
that you are פטור patur if it's partial, whether it was שחט
shecht outside and even if it was שחט shecht inside you're not
going to transgress if you're only burning something partial, only if you
burn the whole thing. Okay, so that's what he says. יכול מוקטרי
פנים, Yachol muktrei pnim, maybe if it was fit for the inside,
שחט shecht on the inside, שחיסרו והעלו בחוץ, shechisru vehe'elu bachutz, that
it was incomplete and you brought on the outside, חייב, chayav. maybe
you'd be חייב, chayav תלמוד לומר לעשות אותו, talmud lomar la'asos oso,
על השלם חייב ואינו חייב. al hashalem chayav ve'eino chayav. לעשות אותו
la'asot oto also tells you it has to be whole. So do
these two things tell you it has to be whole to tell
you that you're exempt, you know, not only if it was if
it was incomplete and it was shechted outside, but even if it
was shechted inside and you offered up incomplete you're also exempt. Okay,
and that's why he has both of those tell you it needs
to be whole in those two scenarios in order to transgress. רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the או o is coming to tell you
about the blood, the יביאנו is coming to tell you one or
the other, and there's only one thing to tell you that it
has to be whole. And what do we say from that is,
because he actually says, he disagrees for the הלכה, halakha, and he
would say, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would tell you, מוקטרי פנים שחסרו
והעלו בחוץ חייב. muktarei p'nim shechasru v'he'elu bakhutz chayav. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva would disagree and he would say there's only one verse that
tells you it has to be whole, and actually you know what?
If it was shechted in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, and burnt
outside, you'd be חייב chayav even if it was only partial. Okay,
so that's exactly what they debate. Fine. So that was a lot
sort of doing all of the accounting to figure out how you
deal with all the rest of the פסוק. pasuk. But bottom line
is, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael learns from the word דם, dam, the
idea that it is, that it is it is what you call
it, about זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns
from the word או o that it's זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Okay,
and now because one of them categorizes it together with שחיטה, shechita,
and one categorizes it together with burning, that's going to lead to
some practical implication. I gotta tell you, the רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
דרשה makes a lot more sense. Not only is it does it
focus on the word דם, but if you had to talk about
which of these two would you put the idea of זריקה zrika
together with, שחיטה shechita or burning, because I would put it with
שחיטה, shechita, you know? So anyway. All right, so let's take a
look. רבי עקיבא האי דם יחשב מאי עביד ליה? Rabbi Akiva hai
dam yeichashev mai avid leh? So what does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
do with the verse about blood? Oh, we didn't finish the accounting
yet. What does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva do with the verse about
blood? לרבות שחיטת העוף L'rabos shechitas ha'of to tell to include a
case of when you shecht a bird outside the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash, Because since birds are normally done by מליקה, melika, you might
think that if you shecht a bird sacrifice outside, you'd be exempt,
because that's not what you do in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
In the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? you do מליקה. melika. So the
extra emphasis of blood comes to tell me even if you shecht
a bird sacrifice you're חייב. chayav Okay, רבי ישמעאל נפקא ליה מאו
אשר ישחט. Rabbi Yishmael nafka leh mi'o asher yishchat. Okay, from or
if you slaughter, coming to tell you a separate type of שחיטה
shechita even by birds. רבי עקיבא למיכתב הוא מיבעי ליה על השוחט
הוא חייב ולא על המולק. Rabbi Akiva l'michtav hu mibayei leh al
hashocheit hu chayav v'lo al hamoleik. That no, it's coming to tell
you not only are you חייב chayav for birds for shechting them
out of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash? but ironically if you do
מליקה melika on birds outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. you'd be
exempt, only for שחיטה. shechita. רבי ישמעאל נפקא ליה מזה הדבר. Rabbi
Yishmael nafka leh mi'zeh hadavar. This is the matter, it says in
או אשר ישחט. o asher yishchat. So this and then it mentions
שחיטה, shechita, only שחיטה shechita not מליקה. melika. Fine, דתניא. detanya. אשר
ישחט. Asher yishchat. If somebody slaughters out of the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash אין לי אלא שוחט בהמה ששוחט בהמה. Ein li ela shocheit
beheima sheshocheit beheima. Only maybe that's about like a cow or sheep.
שוחט עוף מנין? Shocheit of minayan? How do you know by shechting
a bird since in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, a bird is
מליקה melika maybe you're not חייב chayav. for shechting in outside. תלמוד
לומר או אשר ישחט. Talmud lomar o asher yishchat. You know, it
says אשר ישחט במחנה או אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה. asher yishchat bamachaneh
o asher yishchat michutz lamachaneh. So that's talking about where you're doing
the שחיטה, shechita, how close to the Temple, but we'll get to
that in a minute. But now we're something the fact that it
repeats the word ישחט, yishchat, it could have said אשר ישחט במחנה
או מחוץ למחנה. asher yishchat bamachaneh o michutz lamachaneh. It didn't have
to repeat the verb או אשר ישחט, o asher yishchat, right? It
could have just said אשר ישחט במחנה או מחוץ למחנה. asher yishchat
bamachaneh o michutz lamachaneh. So the extra ישחט yishchat is coming to
tell me even שחיטה shechita of birds even though you would think
that that's not relevant to birds, no, you're חייב chayav. even for
שחיטה shechita of birds. יכול אף המולק? Yakhol af hamoleik? Maybe it
should apply even to מליקה melika of birds you're חייב chayav outside.
ובדין הוא מה שחיטה שאין דרך הכשרה בפנים חייב. U'badin hu mah
shechita she'ein derekh hachshira bifnim chayav. שחיטה Shechita which is not what
you do with them in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, you're חייב.
chayav מליקה שדרך הכשרה בפנים אינו דין שיהא חייב? Melika she'derekh hachshira
bifnim eino din sheyei chayav? But as מליקה melika which is how
you do it in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash you would think
that if you did it out of the בית המקדש you would
be חייב. chayav תלמוד לומר זה הדבר. Talmud lomar zeh hadavar. This
is the matter אשר ישחט asher yishchat meaning the זה zeh only
שחיטה shechita nothing other than שחיטה. shechita. So the זה zeh tells
you only שחיטה shechita and the extra ישחט yishchat tells you even
שחיטה shechita by birds. Fine. But anyway but רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
learns out birds from דם יחשב. And that's why they're debating how
to use that verse about the דם. So now the גמרא Gemara.
tells me this says this. ורבי עקיבא אמר לך הוא מיבעי ליה
לגזירה שוה. V'Rabbi Akiva amar lakh hu mibayei leh ligzeira shava. The
extra זה הדבר zeh hadavar is needed for some גזירה שוה gzeira
shava which thankfully we are not getting to go into right now
what that is. Okay. Okay, so now we go so now the
גמרא Gemara. says the following. Okay. Now. והא דתנן *veha d'tnan* הקומץ
והמקבל דמים בחוץ פטור Patur. *hakometz vehamikabel damim bachutz patur*. So now
we've got how do you know, we know שחיטה shchita *shechita*, we
know העלאה ha'ala? *ha'alah*, we know זריקה zrika *zerika*. זריקה zrika *zerika*
is either going to be learned either from דם *dam* or from,
from whatever, from the אזובא *azovah*, okay, so we know these three,
you're חייב chayav. *chayav*. But there are some things that you can
do out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* and be פטור Patur
*patur*, okay, not שחיטה shchita, *shechita*, זריקה zrika *zerika*, and העלאה ha'ala
*ha'alah*, so by the way, what's missing here? Okay, of the classic
עבודות *avodos*, שחיטה shchita *shechita*, זריקה zrika *zerika*, burning it, what's one
of the עבודות *avodos*? הולכה *holacha*. הולכה *holacha*, okay, although הולכה *holacha*
always is like the, the one that's seen as not central because
it's not necessary, but also קבלה *kabala*, catching the blood, right? So
what about that? So let's take a look. והא תנן *veha tnan*
הקומץ *hakometz* or if it's a מנחה mincha, *mincha* we included birds,
okay, but what about מנחה mincha, *mincha*? So we've got, so if
you do the קמיצה *kmitza* of a מנחה mincha. *mincha*, now if
you actually burnt the, the flour of a מנחה mincha *mincha*, that's
being מעלה *ma'aleh*, that's burning it up on the fire, okay, but
what about if you did the קמיצה *kmitza* of a מנחה *mincha*?
Or what if by, what if you did, if you caught the
blood, okay? והא תנן *veha tnan* הקומץ והמקבל דמים בחוץ פטור Patur.
*hakometz vehamikabel damim bachutz patur*, you're actually פטור *patur* for those, okay.
מנלן *menalan*, how do you know you're פטור *patur*? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says ומהיכא תיתי דחייב *umeheicha taisi dechayav*? What do you
mean how do you know you're פטור *patur*, why should you think
you're חייב chayav *chayav*? Okay, we start with שחיטה shchita *shechita* and
העלאה ha'ala. *ha'alah*, we included זריקה zrika. *zerika*, anything that's not these
three you should be פטור *patur*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
once I got these three, why don't I start to look at
a common denominator and why don't I include something like קמיצה *kmitza*
or קבלת הדם kabbalas hadam, *kabalas hadam*? Okay? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ומהיכא תיתי *umeheicha taisi*, תיתי משחיטה *taisi mishchita*, well let's
learn it, let's imply it, maybe I can infer it from שחיטה
shchita, *shechita*. No, מה לשחיטה שכן נפסלה שלא לאוכליו בפסח *ma lishchita
shekein nifsela shelo l'ochlav b'Pesach*, שחיטה shchita *shechita* is more weighty and
therefore why is שחיטה shchita *shechita* more weighty than like קבלת הדם
*kabalas hadam*? Because by at least by קרבן Korban פסח pesach, *Korban
Pesach*, if you שחט shecht *shacht* it and some of the people
that are part of the קרבן Korban, פסח *Korban Pesach* are not
able to eat the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*, right, that's like שלא
לאוכליו *shelo l'ochlav*, right, that's an invalidity. So that's a very narrow
type of a scenario with the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*, but anyway
there's some type of an invalidity that applies to שחיטה shchita *shechita*
that doesn't apply to other things. So just because you're חייב chayav
*chayav* for שחיטה shchita, *shechita* doesn't mean you're חייב chayav *chayav*, right,
to these other things are on the other side of the line
are, you know, קומץ kometz *kometz* of a מנחה *mincha*, right, which
is sort of parallel to שחיטה shchita? *shechita*, and קבלה *kabala* which
normally occurs before the, the זריקה zrika *zerika*, קבלת הדם *kabalas hadam*.
Okay. So those things you're פטור *patur* on. So let's infer from
these. Well, this at least is weightier than everything else, okay, in
this special הלכה *halacha* of שלא לאוכליו *shelo l'ochlav* by פסח *Pesach*.
So just because you're חייב chayav *chayav* on this, you can't infer
you're חייב chayav *chayav* on that. How about if you're חייב chayav
*chayav* on זריקה zrika, *zerika*, you should be חייב chayav. *chayav* on
this? No, מה לזריקה שכן זר חייב chayav? עליה מיתה *ma lizerika
shekein zar chayav aleha misa*. By זריקה zrika. *zerika* a non-כהן *Kohen*
gets מיתה *misa*. Now why does a non-כהן *Kohen* not get מיתה
*misa* by these things? Because these two, קומץ *kometz* and קבלת הדם
*kabalas hadam*, are considered to be incomplete עבודות *avodos*. The קומץ *kometz*
is, is part of a process and the process isn't over, the
process is burning it. The קבלה *kabala* is a part of a
process, the end of the process is the זריקה zrika. *zerika*. So
a זר *zar* is only חייב Chayav *chayav* by זריקת הדם *zerikas
hadam* or העלאה ha'ala, *ha'alah* which are like ends of processes or
you know a complete thing, not, not a middle stage. So don't
you can't learn it out from זריקה zrika. *zerika* to these things
because זריקה zrika *zerika* a non-כהן *Kohen* is חייב Chayav? מיתה *chayav
misa*, מיתה בידי שמים *misa bidei Shamayim* whatever, but you know and
therefore it's much weightier than these things. Okay. תיתי מבינייהו *taisi mibeineiyahu*,
why not try to learn it from the common denominator? That's like
usually the way to go, right? To learn from one thing you
can always find a point of distinction, but why don't we try
to say the common denominator of these things should allow me to
include the other two? No, אם כן לא יאמר בזריקה im kein
lo yomar bizrika, ותיתי מבינייהו *im kein lo yomar bizerika v'taisi mibeineiyahu*,
ותיתי משחיטה veteisi meshchita, *v'taisi mishchita*. Okay, it says so this is
very interesting. In principle, really, okay, if you're חייב Chayav *chayav* on
these three, the common denominator should tell you these are עבודות *avodos*
etc., we should also say you're חייב Chayav *chayav* on these. Logically
you're right, that from here if we were to use a common
denominator we would include these. But now we're going to say this:
the fact that we needed a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to teach me
זריקה zrika *zerika* shows me that we're not going to make logical
expansions because if we were going to make a logical expansion we
wouldn't have needed a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to teach me זריקה zrika,
*zerika*. I could have just inferred זריקה zrika *zerika* from the common
denominator of these two, and the fact that I didn't just infer
it from the common denominator, I needed a פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*, tells
me that the rule here is don't use the common denominator, don't
abstract, just do the explicit things that are mentioned in the verse,
okay, and because of that even though you're right if I were
to abstract I would include this, but I've learned my lesson from
the fact that there's a verse about זריקה zrika *zerika* to tell
me not to. the only things that get to be included are
things that are directly able to be linked to the verse. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. So the גמרא Gemara says: No,
אם כן לא יאמר בזריקה, it shouldn't, it wouldn't have had to
say it by זריקה zrika ותיתי מביניא veteisi mibeinaya I could have,
why wouldn't I just infer זריקה zrika from the common denominator of
שחיטה shchita and העלאה? ha'ala. ותיתי משחיטה, מה שחיטה שכן נפסלה שלא
לשם אוכלין בפסח, ma shchita shekein nifsela shelo lesheim ochlin bepesach, תיתי
מהעלאה. teisi meha'ala. So I'd start by saying learn from שחיטה, shchita
no שחיטה shchita, is weightier by פסח, learn it from the burning,
no מה העלאה שכן ישנה במנחה, ma ha'ala shekein yeshna bemincha, העלאה
ha'ala, applies to a מנחה, זריקה zrika doesn't apply to a מנחה,
you don't have blood by a מנחה. ותיתי מביניא veteisi mibeinaya and
I could have learned זריקה zrika from the common denominator of שחיטה
shechitah and העלאה. ha'ala And nevertheless, there was a verse to teach
me זריקה. zrika להכי כתב קרא lehachi kesav kra so that's why
there's the verse teaches me זריקה zrika למימרא דלא אתי מביניא lameimra
delo asi mibeinaya to teach me the rule that when it comes
to figuring out what you're חייב Chayav. for here, it's only things
that are in the verse or that can be derived from the
verse, not things that can be figured out logically, expanded by abstracting.
So yes, once we have שחיטה, Shechitah חוץ, זריקה, zrika, and העלאה,
ha'ala, logically you should include the קומץ for the מנחה and the
קבלת הדם, but we're saying no. At the end of the day,
it's only things that are in the verse and we're not going
to sort of abstract and include other things. Okay. Now so now
we've got that. We figured out how you know it's prohibited. We
figured out how you know זריקה. zrika We've sort of figured out
why things that are not זריקה. We've included birds here. We got
all the basic parameters. Now we're going to move on. Next thing.
אמר רבי אבהו: amar Rabbi Abahu: שחט וזרק לדברי רבי ישמעאל חייב
אחת לדברי רבי עקיבא חייב שתיים. shachat vezarak ledivrei Rabbi Yishmael chayav
achas ledivrei Rabbi Akiva chayav shtayim. So now that we've got these
three, he's going to say a very logical thing. Okay, if you
did it again, a way of testing is something considered to be
a separate prohibition is if you did it in one state of
forgetfulness, do you bring two sacrifices or you know two חטאות chataos
or one חטאת? So somebody in a state of forgetfulness that it
was forbidden to offer things outside of the בית המקדש, he did
שחיטה Shechitah, and זריקה. Are those two, is that one sin twice
or two separate sins? So that depends. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael. put
זריקה with the category of שחיטה Shechitah from the דם, from that
פרשה, right? So he would say that's one sin twice, so you
only bring one קרבן. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says זריקה comes from
the category of העלאה. ha'ala, So if you did שחיטה Shechitah and
זריקה, that's two sins and two קרבנות. korbanos Okay. So he says
שחט וזרק shachat vezarak so you did those two in one state
of forgetfulness, לדברי רבי ישמעאל חייב אחת ledivrei Rabbi Yishmael chayav achas
for רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael you bring one sacrifice, ולדברי רבי עקיבא
חייב שתיים uledivrei Rabbi Akiva chayav shtayim for רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
you bring two sacrifices, it's two separate sins. אביי אמר אפילו לדברי
רבי עקיבא אינו חייב אלא אחת. Abaye amar afilu ledivrei Rabbi Akiva
eino chayav ela achas. No no no. אביי Abaye wants to say
there's not a big difference between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. Even though רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva learns it from
the verse of העלאה, ha'ala, in the end he agrees that זריקה
gets categorized together with שחיטה, Shechitah which makes a lot of sense.
Where does he learn that you sort of group it together with
שחיטה? אפילו לדברי רבי עקיבא אינו חייב אלא אחת דאמר קרא שם
תעשה ושם תעלה.
afilu ledivrei Rabbi Akiva eino chayav ela achas de'amar kra
sham ta'aseh visham ta'aleh. When the פסוק pasuk. talks about bringing your
קרבנות korbanos in the בית המקדש, it says שם תעשה ושם תעלה.
sham ta'aseh visham ta'aleh. Okay, שם תעשה sham ta'aseh there you should
do your קרבנות korbanos ושם תעלה. visham ta'aleh. So basically what he
says is תעשה ta'aseh is generic, העלאה ha'ala is specifically about burning
it. So that means there's one category for burning it and all
other עשיות, asiyos, all other parts of rituals of the קרבן are
in their own category. So שחיטה and זריקה are in its, are
in its one category and burning it is in a separate category.
So therefore even though he learns it from a verse about העלאה,
ha'ala he agrees that conceptually all the rituals are in one category
and burning is in a separate category. Okay. שם תעשה ושם תעלה,
sham ta'aseh visham ta'aleh, כתב עשיה לכולהו עבודה אחת. kasav asiya lechulhu
avoda achas. It makes the זריקה and the שחיטה one עבודה avoda
even though it's learned from a different verse. Okay, now we're going
to say essentially the same thing in reverse. זרק והעלה. zarak vehe'ela.
Let's say a guy did the sprinkling and the burning with one
state of forgetfulness. לדברי רבי ישמעאל חייב שתיים ledivrei Rabbi Yishmael chayav
shtayim for רבי ישמעאל you're חייב Chayav, two, okay, because זריקה is
a separate sin than העלאה, ha'ala'ah זריקה is learned from the verses
of שחיטה, so it's a
separate sin. ולדברי רבי עקיבא אינו חייב אלא אחת. uledivrei Rabbi Akiva
eino chayav ela achas. So
this is not אביי, Abaye, this is the first approach that says
it's based on where you learned it from. So for רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, since you learned זריקה from the פסוקים psukim of העלאה,
ha'ala'ah if you did זריקה and העלאה in the same state of
forgetfulness, it's the same sin twice and you're only a חייב Chayav
one קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. Okay. אביי Abaye again is going to
say no. Okay. אמר אביי אפילו לדברי רבי עקיבא חייב שתיים. Abaye
amar afilu ledivrei Rabbi Akiva chayav shtayim. Even רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
again there's no practical difference between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי
ישמעאל. Okay. He might learn it from a different verse, but he
agrees that conceptually the way you categorize is העלאה is in one
category, burning is one category... category and
everything else is in the other. Okay, and therefore in this case
זריקה העלאה that's two sins. אפילו דברי רבי עקיבא חייב שתיים והכי
פלגינהו קרא. afilu divrei Rabbi Akiva chayav shtayim vehachi pelaginhu kra. That's
why it was split. שם תעלה ושם תעשה. sham ta'aleh vesham ta'aseh.
That burning is its own category, unique category and everything else is
a different one. Okay. Now, ושחט וזרק והעלה, veshachat vezarak vehe'ela, let's
say he did all three in one state of forgetfulness, so לדברי
הכל חייב שתיים. ledivrei hakol chayav shtayim. Everybody would agree that there's
two קרבנות korbanos because wherever you categorize זריקה, it's in one of
the two categories. So if you did all three, you're going to
be, you're going to have two distinct sins. One sin you'll have
done twice and you'll have one other sin. Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu
Rabbanan. So that was the end of this שחיטה זריקה העלאה category.
Now we're going to deal with this question about the where. Where
is this taking place? Okay? Because the פסוק pasuk says אשר ישחט
במחנה או אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה. asher yishchat bamachaneh o asher yishchat
michutz lamachaneh. But meaning, it might be in the camp, it might
be in where, you know, where בני ישראל is camped around the
משכן, Mishkan, but it's not actually the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, right?
It's not, it's not the temple. Okay? So that's the, that's the
פסוק. Pasuk That it's, you're, it's in the camp. It could be
you're in the, you know, where everybody is camped. In the context
of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you know, maybe that's הר הבית Har HaBayis or
maybe it's ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but it's not the בית המקדש. And therefore
you're חייב. Chayav, Okay? So that's the, that's the פסוק. Pasuk. So
now let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Okay? So it says like this: תנו רבנן,
tanu Rabbanan, אשר ישחט, asher yishchat, I'm going to read the גרסא
girsa on the side is אשר ישחט מחוץ למחנה. asher yishchat michutz
lamachaneh. יכול חוץ לשלוש מחנות? yachol chutz leshalosh machanos? Maybe you're only
חייב Chayav. if you do it outside of all three מחנות, machanos,
where the contemporary or the translation would be, let's say, outside of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, fully outside the camp? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, או, o,
what's או'ס? O's? או אשר ישחט או במחנה. o asher yishchat o
bamachaneh. Okay? או אשר ישחט או, o asher yishchat o, you know,
אי במחנה. i bamachaneh. יכול השוחט עולה בדרום? yachol hashochet olah badarom?
So basically that's what it says. אשר ישחט במחנה או אשר ישחט
מחוץ למחנה. asher yishchat bamachaneh o asher yishchat michutz lamachaneh. So מחוץ
למחנה michutz lamachaneh normally means outside of all three מחנות. machanos. Okay?
So this מחוץ, michutz, but you're, but the whole point is of
saying במחנה bamachaneh is you don't have to go outside of all
three מחנות. machanos. Even if you're, you know, even if you're in
ירושלים Yerushalayim and you שחט, shecht even if you're on הר הבית
Har HaBayis and you שחט. shecht Okay, but now we're saying wait,
but maybe במחנה, bamachaneh, if it says במחנה, bamachaneh, maybe I could
be חייב Chayav, even if I שחט shecht in the בית המקדש?
Well, how would I be חייב Chayav, if I שחט shecht in
the בית המקדש? That's the right place. So no, but you could
do it in the wrong place in the בית המקדש. You could
do an עולה olah in the south. Okay? So מחוץ למחנה michutz
lamachaneh the implication is outside of all three מחנות. machanos. That's usually
what מחוץ למחנה michutz lamachaneh means, like when you go ahead and
do the פרה, parah, you know what, actually, when you do the
פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim and you burn them outside the camp, means
outside of all three מחנות, machanos, which means like outside of ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. Okay? אשר ישחט במחנה, asher yishchat bamachaneh, probably the simple meaning
means in, right in the camp, presumably... presumably means even if it's,
you know, in מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah or מחנה ישראל, Machaneh Yisrael,
which would mean הר הבית Har HaBayis or ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Even if
it's that close, you're still going to be חייב Chayav because it's
not פתח אהל מועד. pesach Ohel Moed. Okay? That's the point. It
could be close, but it's not פתח אהל מועד. Petach Ohel Moed.
Or it could be far away, don't say oh it's so far
it's not relevant. Right, it's funny you could think that there's more
of an offense if you're closer than if you're further away. Right,
if you're right there and you're doing it outside, maybe... so the
פסוק Pasuk is saying if you're closer or if you're far, you're
חייב Chayav. if it's not אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. But now the
גמרא is going to say, so this tells me it doesn't have
to be outside of three מחנות. machanos. But maybe I'm חייב Chayav
even in the בית המקדש if it's not in the right place
in the בית המקדש, once it's telling me even in the camp
I'm going to be חייב. Chayav. Okay? So let's take a look.
אי במחנה, i bamachaneh, יכול השוחט עולה בדרום יהא חייב? yachol hashochet
olah badarom yei chayav? Maybe if you do the עולה olah in
the south you'd be חייב? Chayav תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, או אשר
ישחט מחוץ למחנה. o asher yishchat michutz lamachaneh. מחוץ למחנה מיוחד שאין
ראוי לשחיטת קדשים ולשחיטת כל זבח, michutz lamachaneh meyuchad she'ein ra'uy lishchitas
kodshim ulemishchitas kol zevach, so the same way out of the camp,
you know, is not a place where you can't bring sac... is
a place where you can't bring sacrifices or any זבח, zevach, not
only can you not bring עולות. olos. Out of the camp you're
not allowed to bring any sacrifice. So יצא דרום שאף על פי
שאין ראוי לשחיטת קדשי קדשים, yatza darom she'af al pi she'ein ra'uy
lishchitas kodshei kodshim, so the south of the, you know, of the
altar in the בית המקדש, even though it's not fit for like
an עולה olah and, you know, קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim and so
on, but ראוי לשחיטת קדשים קלים, ra'uy lishchitas kodshim kalim, it's fit
for like a שלמים, shelamim, okay? So the link of out of
the camp and in the camp is, no, no, we're talking about
places where no קרבנות Korbanot are allowed to be brought. In the
בית המקדש there are places where certain קרבנות Korbanot are allowed to
be brought. yes certain no, but the fact is you're not going
to be חייב for שחוטי חוץ. Shchutei Chutz. You invalidated the קרבן
if you slaughtered it in the wrong place, but the linking of
these two is to tell you only in a place that you're
not allowed to bring any sacrifices. Okay, so אמר עולא Amar Ulla
השוחט על גגו של היכל חייב. Hashochet al gago shel Heichal chayav.
Let's say somebody gets to the roof of the היכל, Heichal, okay,
and he שחטs shecht up there. Okay, now that's not a valid
place to שחט shecht a קרבן. No קרבן is allowed to be
שחטed shecht on the roof of the היכל. Heichal. Are you חייב?
Is that שחוטי חוץ? Shchutei Chutz? Is your whole criteria a place
where no קרבנות are allowed to be שחטed? So he says I'll
give you a place where no קרבנות are allowed to be שחטed,
the roof of the היכל. Heichal. Am I, you're going to be
חייב for שחוטי חוץ? Shchutei Chutz? So he says השוחט על גגו
של היכל חייב הואיל וראוי לשחיטת כל זבח. Hashochet al gago shel
Heichal chayav ho'il v'rau'i l'shechitat kol zevach. So מתקיף לה רבא, Matkif
lah Rava, רבא challenged this. אם כן נכתוב קרא מחוץ למחנה ולא
בעי פתח אהל מועד. Im ken nichtov kra michutz lamachaneh v'lo ba'ei
Petach Ohel Moed. No, because the verse doesn't just say you're outside
the camp, it says you didn't bring it to the opening of
the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. This animal that's on the roof of
the היכל Heichal was brought to the opening of the אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. It's in the airspace of the zone of the אהל
מועד. Ohel Moed. So it's not just about a place where שחיטה
is allowed, where שחיטת קרבנות Shechitat Korbanot is allowed. If you're if
you brought it into the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, you're not going
to be חייב for שחוטי חוץ. Shchutei Chutz. Okay, פתח אהל מועד
למה לי? Petach Ohel Moed lamah li? לאו למיעוטי גגות. Lav l'mi'utei
gagot. It excludes the roof. I don't care that you know, again,
it's not a כשר Kasher קרבן, but you're not חייב. You're in
the פתח אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. Okay. ולרבא אם כן נכתוב פתח
אהל מועד במחנה ומחוץ למחנה למה לי? U'l'Rava im ken nichtov Petach
Ohel Moed bamachaneh u'michutz lamachaneh lamah li? So now the גמרא says
one minute, just say if somebody who שחטs something and doesn't bring
it to the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. This is actually a good
question. Why did the פסוק Pasuk, have to say במחנה מחוץ למחנה
Bamachaneh michutz lamachaneh and you didn't bring it? Just say אשר ישחט
ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו. Asher yishchat v'el Petach Ohel Moed
lo hevi'o. That covers it all. You שחטed it anywhere and you
didn't bring it to אהל מועד. Ohel Moed And once you brought
it to אהל מועד Ohel Moed, you're not חייב, even if you
did it on the roof of the היכל. Heichal. לאו לאתויי גגו?
Lav l'atuyei gago? Isn't, shouldn't we say that the fact that it
emphasizes במחנה Bamachaneh and חוץ למחנה Chutz lamachaneh etc. is to tell
me that it's not all about the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed that
there could be something that's brought to the אהל מועד Ohel Moed,
and you're still חייב if it's on the roof? Okay, because if
it's all about אהל מועד, Ohel Moed. just say אהל מועד. Ohel
Moed, So אמר רב מרי, Amar Rav Mari, no, לאתויי כולה בפנים
וצוארה בחוץ. L'atuyei kullah bifnim v'tzavarah bachutz. No, here's why for רבא,
you're right. If it just said אהל מועד, Ohel Moed you would
have said, okay, you would have said you would have learned to
exclude everything and to and I I mean to say everything outside
of אהל מועד Ohel Moed, you're חייב, but on the roof of
the היכל Heichal you're going to be פטור. And that would have
done the job. Why do you need מחנה Machaneh and חוץ למחנה
Chutz lamachaneh to tell you more complicated scenarios? Let's say you've got
an animal that's standing in the עזרה Azarah and the neck is
sticking out and you're going to שחט it there. Okay, so there,
that was sort of brought to אהל מועד, Ohel Moed right? Because
it's in the space of אהל מועד Ohel Moed the animal is
standing, but you're still going to be חייב. And therefore אהל מועד
Ohel Moed. would not have would not have been enough to learn
that you're חייב, because that was at least brought into the אהל
מועד. Ohel Moed, But the fact that it's שחטed במחנה ומחוץ למחנה,
Bamachaneh u'michutz lamachaneh, even though the animal is standing in אהל מועד,
Ohel Moed that you learn from that פסוק. Okay, לאתויי כולה בפנים
וצוארה בחוץ. L'atuyei kullah bifnim v'tzavarah bachutz. So the גמרא says צוארה
בחוץ פשיטא אמאי קפיד רחמנא אשחיטה? Tzavarah bachutz pshita amai kapid Rachmana
ashechitah? No, no, no, you don't need a פסוק to tell you
that scenario. Even if you just had the אהל מועד Ohel Moed
פסוק, I would have known that if the neck is outside the
אהל מועד Ohel Moed, you're going to be חייב, because it's all
about the act of שחיטה, and שחיטה בחוץ היא. Shechitah bachutz hi.
The גמרא says fine, אלא לאתויי Ella l'atuyei to include the case
of כולה בחוץ וצוארה בפנים. Kullah bachutz v'tzavarah bifnim. The reverse. The
neck is on the inside. So if it were just for the
verse of and the animal standing on the outside, if it were
just for the verse of ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו, V'el
Petach Ohel Moed lo hevi'o, I'd say you'd be פטור because at
least the שחיטה occurred in the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed. that's where
the neck is and that's where you maybe are. But because it
says במחנה ומחוץ למחנה, Bamachaneh u'michutz lamachaneh, I learn that in that
case you're also חייב because at least the animal is in the
מחנה Machaneh even if the שחיטה and part of it is in
the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed, So bottom line is, okay, the במחנה
ומחוץ למחנה, Bamachaneh u'michutz lamachaneh, the גמרא really just did the straight
meaning of those פסוקים. Psukim. Whether it's close, it could be on
הר הבית, Har Habayit, ירושלים, Yerushalayim, don't say, oh, it's at least
in the temple environs so I shouldn't be חייב. You're חייב there.
And if it's far, don't say, oh, it's so far away it's
not a challenge to the temple. Whether it's close or far you're
going to be חייב. But if it's in the space of אהל
מועד, Ohel Moed. okay, if it actually is שחטed in the south,
you know, it's an עולה Olah שחטed in the south, you're going
to be פטור. It's only when it's outside of the אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed, And then the גמרא says what if it's actually on
the roof of the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed? which is not fit
for שחיטה but it's in the zone of the אהל מועד? And
there there was a debate whether or not you'd be חייב for
שחוטי חוץ Shchutei Chutz if you did it on the roof of
the היכל. Heichal. Okay, so we will end with that, we will
pick up with the איתמר itmar tomorrow.