בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is דף י. Daf Yud.
It is the April 23rd and the 23rd day of the עומר,
Omer, and we pick up two lines from the bottom, or four
lines from the bottom on ט עמוד ב, Tet Amud Bet, and
we're in the middle of, you know, different variations about what constitutes
שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, particularly at the end of yesterday, playing off
the issue about in some times if you do something that's too
different, you have intent for a different person and the person isn't
obligated a חטאת, chatas, he's obligated an עולה, olah, then it's so
irrelevant it doesn't invalidate. And the question of the גמרא Gemara about
what about a חטאת chatas that's not really related to חטא, cheit,
is that like a חטאת chatas or like an עולה? olah? And
sometimes you need it to be if it's if it's very close
it's not a problem, and only if it's very different or significantly
different is a problem from one חטאת chatas to another חטאת, chatas,
there's a debate in the גמרא Gemara but anyway in general we
assume that that would be valid. From a חטאת chatas to an
עולה, olah, that would be invalid. So we are sort of exploring
those different degrees of שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah. Now we turn to
a different question about the sort of the moment, if you would,
of the intent. So let's take a look, four lines from the
bottom. איתמר Itmar was taught, שחטה לשמו לזרוק דמו שלא לשמו. shachata
lishmo lizarok damo shelo lishmo. You slaughtered the animal with intent that
I'm doing I'm slaughtering this חטאת, chatas, now we're sort of assuming
a חטאת chatas because our focus is what would invalidate. Presumably you
could have the same debate if it's a question about what would,
you know, make it לא לשמו לבעלים, lo lishmo l'ba'alim, but we're
talking about a חטאת. chatas. I'm slaughtering this חטאת chatas for the
sake of a חטאת, chatas, but my intent is that when I
get around to throwing the blood, I'm going to do it with
with with the intent of making this an עולה, olah, of of
thinking of this as an עולה, olah, that this should count as
an עולה. olah. Okay, so you're just planning something, but you're planning
this at the time you do the שחיטה shchitah of the חטאת.
chatas. Okay, so what's the story? רבי יוחנן אמר פסולה, Rabbi Yochanan
amar psulah, it's invalid. ריש לקיש אמר כשרה, Resh Lakish amar kesherah,
says it's kosher. I've noticed something in general with רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan and ריש לקיש, Resh Lakish, that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan tends
to be takes the strict position and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish the
more lenient. I mean not just here, it seems to be a
general rule. Pay attention if you see if you think it's correct.
Anyway, so רבי יוחנן אמר פסולה, Rabbi Yochanan amar psulah, רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says it's invalid. מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה. machshavin me'avodah l'avodah. If
you have a מחשבה machshavah during one עבודה, avodah, it is, you
know, it can be meaningful, you know, even if it's a מחשבה
machshavah about a different עבודה. avodah. So therefore, so so if you're
have an intent about the עבודה avodah of שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah,
it's valid and it sort of it is about the זריקת הדם,
zrikas hadam, which is a different עבודה, avodah, that is enough to
invalidate it even when you're doing this עבודה avodah of the שחיטה.
shchitah. All right, somehow that מחשבה machshavah about a different עבודה avodah
works for this עבודה. avodah.
That's רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, works to invalidate. ואפינן ממחשבת פיגול, v'afinan
mimachsheves pigul, and we learn out, רש"י Rashi says the vav is
not a different point, it's like and that we learn out because
we learn this out from פיגול. pigul. Classic פיגול pigul in the
תורה, Torah, well the way חז"ל Chazal understand פיגול, pigul, classic פיגול
pigul in the תורה Torah is that you ate the meat at
the wrong time. But חז"ל Chazal say it's not about eating the
meat, what makes an animal a פיגול, pigul, you know, invalidate is
that when you do the עבודה avodah you're planning on eating it
at the wrong time. And the classic thing is you have to
be planning to either be doing some form of אכילה, achilah, either
the human eating, you're consuming it, or the altar eating, you're going
to burn the entrails or the meat on the altar at the
wrong time, or the throwing of the blood on the altar is
a type of like of a consumption of the altar. So because,
you know, the verse by פיגול pigul emphasizes thought, it says, לא
יחשב לו פיגול הוא, lo yeichashev lo pigul hu, it should not
be considered for him, but the חז"ל Chazal read it you should
not be thinking. So if the problem is שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano,
if you think about it, doing it at the wrong time, right,
חז"ל Chazal said it's not just that you did the act at
the wrong time because then it's not about thought, then it's about
doing the act at the wrong time. And anyway if you waited
to the wrong time, you likely waited to the next day to
throw the blood, it's already invalid, it's already נותר. nosar. So חז"ל
Chazal understand that classic פיגול pigul is you're doing it at the
right time, but your thought is to do the אכילה achilah part
of the process, either the throwing of the blood or the burning
of the stuff on the altar or the human consumption, at the
wrong time. That's classic פיגול. pigul. When you're doing one of the
earlier עבודות, avodos, let's say שחיטה, shchitah, you're planning on doing an
אכילה achilah part of the process, like the זריקת הדם zrikas hadam
or the burning of it and so on, at the wrong time.
So classic פיגול, pigul, the only way you get פיגול, pigul, you
can't get פיגול pigul if you do if you're doing the act
at the wrong time. You only get if you're doing this act
at the right time with intending to do another act at the
wrong time. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that's our model. So
if that works, therefore I mean if that invalidates, so here too,
when you're thinking about doing this עבודה avodah שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah,
it invalidates this act right now. Okay, that's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says. ואפינן ממחשבת פיגול, v'afinan mimachsheves pigul, we learn this out
from the thought of פיגול. pigul. ריש לקיש אמר כשרה, Resh Lakish
amar kesherah, it's kosher. אין מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה, ein machshavin me'avodah l'avodah,
no,
a thought about one עבודה avodah does not invalidate the current עבודה.
avodah. לא אפינן ממחשבת פיגול, lo afinan mimachsheves pigul, and
we do not use פיגול pigul as a model. Now why do
we not use פיגול pigul as a model? as a model, it
seems like a pretty good model. So רש"י Rashi makes a very
important point. רש"י Rashi says because if you
think first of all if you think about it, the type of
thought you have by פיגול, piggul, I mean first of all you
could just say which the גמרא Gemara will sort of say in
a minute, that's exactly how פיגול piggul is defined and it's a
different type of an animal than this. But besides that,
the thought about פיגול piggul is about a type of a thing
that would not be relevant by שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. You could
have a thought of a פיגול piggul about when you're going to
burn the the limbs on the altar, when you're going to eat
it. Okay, שלא לשמו shelo lishmo does not invalidate when you're burning
the limbs on the altar. שלא לשמו shelo lishmo does not invalidate
when you are eating it. So the nature of פיגול, piggul, it's
not really exactly comparable. It's not like oh, since a שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo would have invalidated there, we're going to import it and
say you thought about act B where שלא לשמו shelo lishmo would
have invalidated and now we're going to import it and make it
work on act A. Like that's what you want to say here,
you're playing on doing the זריקה, zerikah, which would have invalidated שלא
לשמו, shelo lishmo, but you're thinking about it at the שחיטה, shechitah,
so we're going to import it and say it invalidates right here.
But that's not the way פיגול piggul works. פיגול piggul the second
act is not like a central act to make the קרבן כשר.
korban kasher. So פיגול piggul is like a very different type of
a thing. פיגול piggul is when you're doing a critical act now
you can't be thinking about the אכילה achilah at the wrong time.
That's just the way it's defined. But it's not that that later
מחשבה machshavah comes how and invalidates you know this current act. A,
that later מחשבה machshavah is not about a critical עבודה, avodah, right,
it can be about a non-critical עבודה avodah like the eating of
the meat. And number two as we're going to see in a
minute, if you actually have the thought right now to do it
שלא בזמנו, shelo bizmano, it doesn't make it פיגול. piggul. It doesn't
make it פיגול piggul even during this act itself, that מחשבה. machshavah.
It only is a מחשבה machshavah about what you're going to do
in the future by a different act. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says פיגול piggul is
a, and you're missing up the very act of doing because I'm
at the end of the day I'm not messing it up because
I am throwing the blood at the right time. Is that, is
that what you're saying for פיגול? piggul? Meaning if like what was
that last point you're making?
That if I שחט shacht it to do the שחיטה שלא בזמנו,
shchita shelo bizmano. I don't invalidate.
Right, because you're doing it בזמנו, bizmano, right, yeah, yeah, right.
So that's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, you can't learn from
פיגול. piggul. פיגול piggul is a very is a unique type of
a thing where the bad thought doesn't work for the thing you're
doing, it only works for a later thing and that later thing
is can be even a non-central עבודה. avodah. It's not relevant to
our case about where it's a thought about זריקה zerikah which would
itself invalidate and trying to import it right now and sort of
say the fact that you're having it at the time of שחיטה
shechitah invalidates. Okay, ואזדו לטעמייהו, v'azdu l'ta'ameihu, now they follow their reasoning
that they adopt the similar debate that they have in a in
a related case, דאיתמר, d'itmar, was taught and we had this in
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah briefly very briefly.
השוחט את הבהמה על מנת להזריק דמה לעבודת כוכבים ולהקטיר חלבה לעבודת
כוכבים, Ha'shochet et ha'beheimah al menat l'hazrik damah l'avodat kochavim u'lehaktir chelba
l'avodat kochavim, you שחט shacht an animal and when you're שחט shachting
it you're not saying through this שחט shachting I am offering up
this animal to Zeus. No, what you're saying is through this שחט
shachting I am going to offer this animal to Zeus when I
get the blood and then I'll throw the blood on the altar
or when I get the you know the entrails and I'll burn
the entrails to Zeus. That'll be my then I'll offer it up
to Zeus, right now I'm just שחט shachting it. Okay, so have
you made this animal תקרובת עבודה זרה tikrovet avodah zarah if you
if you never wind up actually throwing the blood or burning the
entrails? Is this act of שחיטה shechitah with this plan enough to
make it a type of an offering to עבודה זרה avodah zarah
to make it forbidden in benefit? תוספות Tosafot points out you could
be that right now you did עבודה זרה avodah zarah and you'd
be חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, right שחט shachting it with this plan
could be a sufficient act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But since
the act itself is not yet with the כוונה kavanah to do
this as an offering now, it's only an intention to do it
as an offering later, okay, does it define the animal right now?
Okay, ר' יוחנן אמר אסורה, Rebbi Yochanan amar asurah, the animal is
forbidden, it's a type of an offering to עבודה זרה avodah zarah
even though you have not yet thrown the blood or whatever, מחשבין
מעבודה לעבודה, m'chashvin me'avodah l'avodah, your מחשבה machshavah from one עבודה, avodah,
the עבודה avodah of the you know burning of the entrails, you
know it sort of has you know is imported here with this
עבודה avodah and defines this as an act of תקרובת עבודה זרה,
tikrovet avodah zarah, וילפינן חוץ מפנים. v'yalfinan chutz mi'pnim. Now we learn
this from פיגול, piggul, okay, פיגול piggul so even though פיגול piggul
is something that works in the מקדש Mikdash and worshipping something to
עבודה זרה avodah zarah is not an act you're supposed to be
doing in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, not act you meaning you're
not supposed to be doing at any time but anyway but it's
not considered an act of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, wherever you're
doing it it's not related to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you
can learn use a model from the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and
apply it to a non-מקדש Mikdash context to an עבודה זרה avodah
zarah context and say that that plan later on redefines the nature
of this act right now. Okay, ר' יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is
a more strict, yeah
he's he's always more strict. ריש לקיש אמר מותרת, Reish Lakish amar
muteret, it's permissible. אין מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה, ein machshavin me'avodah l'avodah, you
do not you cannot you don't import from one thought about one
act to another, ולא ילפינן חוץ מפנים, v'lo yalfinan chutz mi'pnim, and
you don't learn something relating to עבודה זרה avodah zarah from the
way it was done in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay. Okay
now, so it's a very parallel debate, now the גמרא Gemara says
וצריכי, u'tzrichi, you need both. דאשמעינן בהא, de'ashmian b'ha, if you had
just said the debate by עבודה זרה, avoda zara, בהא קאמר ריש
לקיש, b'ha ka'amar Reish Lakish, that's where ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says
your thought about doing a later act of עבודה זרה avoda zara
isn't relevant now. Right? Why? Because that's a non-בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
act, so you're not going to learn it from בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. אבל פנים פנים, aval pnim pnim, but when you're talking about
שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and learning שלא לשמו shelo lishmo from פיגול,
pigul, those are two בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash acts. So אימא מודי
ליה לרבי יוחנן eima modi leh l'Rabbi Yochanan maybe he would agree
to רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that you would use פיגול pigul as
a model. ואישמעינן הא, ve'ashmian ha, and if we had just said
the case of פיגול, pigul, בהא קאמר רבי יוחנן, b'ha ka'amar Rabbi
Yochanan, that's where רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says you learn from the
פיגול pigul model and apply it to שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. I
mean if we just had the שלא לשמו shelo lishmo case. אבל
בההיא aval b'hahi by עבודה זרה avoda zara אימא מודי ליה לריש
לקיש eima modi leh l'Reish Lakish maybe he'd agree to ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish you don't use a פיגול pigul model for עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. צריכי tzrichi so you need to tell me that they
argue on both cases. And רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan basically says what
you're planning now to do at a later stage of an עבודה
avoda defines the character of the act that you're doing right now.
Okay? Whereas ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no, you know, only how
you're defining the current act can define its character. It cannot be
defined based on what you're doing now with an intention to do
something during a different עבודה. avoda.
I'm sorry, I don't understand this חוץ מפנים chutz mipnim part. Why
do we say this specifically עבודה זרה avoda zara is חוץ, chutz,
I mean you could be doing it in the בית המקדש? Beis
Hamikdash?
Because it's not an עבודת המקדש. avodas Hamikdash. It's not defined as
something that's defined how you do the עבודה avoda in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, doesn't matter where you do it. Whereas the other
two are the criteria of בית המקדש עבודה: Beis Hamikdash avoda: לשמו
lishmo and בזמנו. bizmano. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this.
Okay. כי אתא רב דימי, ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי
Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan are both in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
When רב דימי Rav Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר,
amar, he reported the following story about how this debate continued. מתיב
רב ירמיה לסיועיה לרבי יוחנן ורב אילא לסיועיה לריש לקיש. masiv Rav
Yirmiya l'siyu'ei l'Rabbi Yochanan v'Rav Ila l'siyu'ei l'Reish Lakish. Back in ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael we sort of took sides on this debate. We
had a little debating team. And anyway, and רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiya
brought a proof to defend רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position or to
support רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan position and רב אילא Rav Ila brought
a proof to support ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish position. And now we're
going to show the proofs. רב ירמיה לסיועיה לרבי יוחנן, Rav Yirmiya
l'siyu'ei l'Rabbi Yochanan, רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiya brought a proof to support
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. ומה במקום שאם אמר הריני שוחט חוץ מזמנו
שהוא כשר שחט על מנת לזרוק דמו חוץ מזמנו פסול. u'ma bimkom
she'im amar hareni shocheit chutz lizmano shehu kasher shachat al mnat lizrok
damo chutz lizmano pasul. So exactly what I was saying before for
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that sort of shows that פיגול pigul is
unique and a model you really can't learn from, we're using it
here to make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer.
By פיגול, pigul, if you do the שחיטה shechitah and you're שוחט-ing
shocht it and you're שוחט-ing shocht it and you're saying I am
שוחט-ing shocheit it with the intent that this שחיטה shchita should be
a שחיטה shchita שלא בזמנו. shelo bizmano, And of course it's absurd.
It's a שחיטה בזמנו. shchita bizmano. Who cares what you're saying? Right
now I'm שוחט-ing—first shocheit of all, how do you have a שלא
בזמנו? shelo bizmano? I guess you could say I'm שוחט-ing shocheit it
with the intent that it should be a night שחיטה. shchita. Of
course night doesn't work by קרבנות. korbanos. Okay, and it's a day
שחיטה. shchita. So that doesn't invalidate. א, Aleph, that's not the הלכה
halacha of פיגול. pigul. פיגול pigul is a מחשבה machshava relating to
a future eating. Number one, eating in quote marks. And number two,
it's not—it doesn't invalidate because it's it's absurd. You're שוחט-ing shocht it
at day, what do you mean I'm—right now I'm שוחט-ing shocht at
day with כוונה kavana that it should be a night שחיטה? shchita?
It's not a night שחיטה. shchita. Okay, but anyway, so he says
look, so there, your מחשבה machshava on the act itself doesn't invalidate,
but your מחשבה machshava on a future act invalidates. ומה במקום שאם
אמר הריני שוחט חוץ מזמנו שהוא כשר שחט על מנת לזרוק דמו
חוץ מזמנו פסול. u'ma bimkom she'im amar hareni shocheit chutz lizmano shehu
kasher shachat al mnat lizrok damo chutz lizmano pasul. When you שחט
shachat it to do the זריקה zrika at the wrong time—I'm going
to do a זריקה zrika day later—that invalidates. מקום שאם אמר הריני
שוחט שלא לשמו פסול. makom she'im amar hareni shocheit shelo lishmo pasul.
So when the כוונה kavana works on the act itself, when you
have כוונה kavana to do it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, שחט על
מנת לזרוק דמו שלא לשמו אינו דין שיהא פסול? shachat al mnat
lizrok damo shelo lishmo eino din sheyehei pasul? So certainly if my
כוונה kavana is to do the זריקה שלא לשמו, zrika shelo lishmo,
if, you know, if that כוונה kavana about another act, you know,
works even when the כוונה kavana of the act itself doesn't work,
how much more so should it work when the כוונה kavana of
the act itself does work? Okay, that's his proof. So the גמרא,
Gemara, let's see how the גמרא Gemara responds. Obviously that's so—but the
absurdity within פיגול pigul that that's true, shows that פיגול pigul really
should be thought of as a different type of a thing. But
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מתקיף
לה רבא בר אהילאי. maskif lah Rava bar Ahilai. רבא בר אהילאי
Rava bar Ahilai challenged this support of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. מה
לחוץ מזמנו שכן כרת. ma l'chutz lizmano sheken kares. So he doesn't
say that it's a unique thing. He just says חוץ מזמנו chutz
lizmano is weightier than שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
invalidates the קרבן. korban. But if you have a כוונה kavana to
do the זריקת הדם שלא בזמנו, zrikas hadam shelo bizmano, make it
פיגול, pigul, so your act of making it פיגול pigul you don't
get כרת kares for. But once the animal becomes פיגול, pigul, if
you eat the meat, you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. Okay, you get
it? So I'm שוחט-ing shocht this animal to do it שלא לשמו.
shelo lishmo. I invalidate the קרבן, korban, but eating it you don't
get כרת kares for it.
But so you just over the לאו lav of making something פיגול?
pigul?
Well I didn't make it פיגול. pigul. First I said שלא לשמו.
shelo lishmo. Eating it you do not get כרת kares for it.
I mean you ate sort of קדשים פסולים kodshim psulim or whatever
but you don't get כרת kares for it. Okay. If however I
שחט shachat it with the intent to be זורק הדם שלא בזמנו,
zoreik hadam shelo bizmano, so א Aleph I do not get... get
כרת kares for. I'm over on a לאו lav for having the
מחשבה machshava's פיגול. pigul. So that I want that to be clear.
But if I eat the meat because it's פיגול, pigul, I get
כרת. kares. So in the world of פיגול, pigul, פיגול pigul is
weightier. There's כרת. kares. So even though by פיגול pigul a מחשבה
machshava of a different עבודה avoda can invalidate, you can't bring that
as relevance to שלא לשמה shelo lishma which is not as weighty
of a category because פיגול pigul is weightier, maybe the laws are
stricter. That's the basic idea. Okay. So no, it's not relevant. There's
כרת. kares. Okay,
so now the גמרא gemara says like this: שכן
כרת. shechen kares. אלא
אמר רבא בר עילאי הכי קאמר. ela amar rava bar ilai hachi
kamar. Here's the way to make the קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה
במקום שאם אמר הריני שוחט חוץ למקומו, uma bemakom she'im amar hareini
shochet chutz limkomo, parallel to פיגול pigul is doing the exact same
thing, שחט shechting it with the intent although not to be do
the אכילה achila act, אכילה achila get in quote marks at the
wrong time but in the wrong place. Okay. I'm going to be
זורק zorek the דם dam חוץ למקדש. chutz lamikdash. I'm going to
eat the meat outside of the בית המקדש beis hamikdash or outside
of ירושלים yerushalayim wherever the meat is supposed to be eaten. Okay.
That's a מחשבה חוץ למקומו. machshava chutz limkomo. It has the exact
same הלכות halachos that it invalidates the קרבן. korban. It follows the
same rules when you're doing let's say an earlier act you have
a כוונה kavana to do the אכילה achila at the wrong place.
But the only difference is it doesn't make the קרבן korban פיגול.
pigul. It makes the קרבן korban פסול. pasul. And if you eat
the קרבן korban you don't get כרת. kares. Got it? So it's
חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano and חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. They follow the
exact same rules except חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo makes it פסול pasul
and not פיגול pigul and you don't get כרת kares for eating
the meat. So now you're not going to be able to push
it away by saying it's a special case, it's כרת. kares. Let's
take a look. Okay. ומה מקום שאם אמר הריני שוחט חוץ למקומו
שהוא כשר. uma makom she'im amar hareini shochet chutz limkomo shehu kasher.
If you actually said the שחיטה, shechita, right now I'm שחט shechting
it in the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, but I'm saying I'm doing
the שחיטה shechita in the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, I'm treating it
like I'm שחט shechting it in Tel Aviv. So that's כשר. kasher.
Okay. Because that's obviously an absurd כוונה. kavana. Okay. שחט על מנת
לזרוק דמו חוץ למקומו פסול. shachat al menas lizrok damo chutz limkomo
pasul. But if you שחט shechted it with the intent to be
sprinkling the blood in Tel Aviv, okay, then that is invalid. מקום,
makom, so there
an act that doesn't, a thought that doesn't invalidate on this act
invalidates if it's a thought to do about a different act. That's
by חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo. מקום שאם אמר הריני שוחט שלא לשמה
שהוא פסול. makom she'im amar hareini shochet shelo lishma shehu pasul. So
when you have a כוונה, kavana, but so when you do שלא
לשמה shelo lishma which invalidates the act you're itself you're doing,
שחט על מנת לזרוק דמו שלא לשמה אינו דין שיפסול? shachat al
menas lizrok damo shelo lishma eino din sheyifsol? So if you're שחט
shechting it with the intent to do the זריקה שלא לשמה, zrika
shelo lishma, certainly it should invalidate. We should learn from פיגול pigul
or from חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo that a מחשבה machshava about a
later act should have more power to invalidate than the מחשבה machshava
of the act you're doing itself. That's what we see by פיגול
pigul or חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo that a מחשבה machshava about a
later act is more powerful than a מחשבה machshava about the current
act. So let's say the same here. Okay. מתקיף לה רב אשי.
maskif la rav ashi. So
רב אשי rav ashi challenges and says no. מה לחוץ למקומו שכן
נוהג בכל הזבחים. ma lechutz limkomo sheken noheg bechol hazvachim. תאמר בשלא
לשמה שאינו נוהג אלא בפסח וחטאת. tomar beshelo lishma she'eino noheg ela
bepesach vechatas. No. חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo maybe this idea that a
מחשבה machshava about a later act invalidates, maybe that's because חוץ למקומו
chutz limkomo is again some degree a weightier category. Why is it
weightier? Because it invalidates all sacrifices. עולה, olah, שלמים, shlamim, I mean
the whole פרשה parsha of פיגול pigul is by שלמים. shlamim. Okay.
So that because it's weightier that has the power to invalidate all
sacrifices, it also applies if you have a מחשבה machshava about a
later act. שלא לשמה shelo lishma only has the power to invalidate
חטאת chatas and פסח. pesach. So because it's not as powerful, you
might not have this special rule that a מחשבה machshava about a
later act works. Okay. So the קל וחומר kal vachomer is look,
by פיגול pigul or חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo מחשבה machshava about a
later act works even if about the מחשבה machshava the act itself
doesn't work. And the answer, so certainly here the מחשבה machshava about
a later act should work by שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. And the
answer is no, שלא לשמה shelo lishma isn't as weighty of a
category and therefore it does not necessarily work. Does פיגול pigul always
involve זריקה? zrika? No. It could be that you're שוחט על מנת
לאכול. shochet al menat le'echol. That's what I said.
Any מחשבה machshava about an אכילה. achila. אכילה achila is either זריקה,
zrika, אכילת בשר achilas basar or הקטרת אימורים. haktaras emurim. Okay, so
now the גמרא gemara says like this: אלא אמר רב אשי הכי
קאמר. ela amar rav ashi hachi kamar. Here's how to make your
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. ומה במקום שאם אמר הריני שוחט לשם פלוני
שהוא כשר. uma bemakom she'im amar hareini shochet leshem ploni shehu kasher.
Now this is a much better קל וחומר. kal vachomer. It doesn't
pick up focus on the unique character of פיגול pigul which besides
the גמרא gemara's point about כרת kares or בכל הזבחים, bechol hazvachim,
also the point is like as I said, the מחשבה machshava about
the act itself is absurd, like the nature of פיגול pigul because
it's obviously wrong. The nature of פיגול pigul is about a future
intent. But let's now look at something that's much more in our
שלא לשמה shelo lishma world. Okay, although before it sounded like we
were saying פיגול pigul is a model, here we're
going to
And here what you have to know is the following: we've been
talking about two types of מחשבות machshavos that invalidate, שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah and שלא לשם בעלים. shelo lishmah baalim. But if you remember
all those דרשות, drashos, which was a sort of tough גמרא Gemara
to get through, but the פסוקים psukim that we learned שלא לשם
בעלים shelo lishmah baalim always came from a פסוק pasuk that said
לכפר עליו, l'chaper alav, to atone for him. And the word כפרה,
kapara, the atonement for the person comes with the זריקת הדם, zrikas
hadam, okay? So therefore, even though we say, you might remember, we
learned out that מחשבת בעלים machshavas baalim works by all the other
עבודות, avodos, invalidates by the other עבודות, avodos, since the verse is
לכפר עליו, l'chaper alav, לכפר עליו, l'chaper alav, okay, עליו alav is
בעלים, baalim, לכפר l'chaper is זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. So therefore, when
we learned that it applied by the other עבודות, avodos, right? שחיטה,
shechita, קבלה, kabala, הולכה, holacha, okay, and זריקה, zrika, all of those
cases of שלא לשם בעלים shelo lishmah baalim was when I'm being
שוחט, shochet, I'm thinking, here I'll draw a guy being שוחט, shochet,
here's his knife,
okay, I don't know, here's the cow, whatever, fine. Anyway, when he's
being שוחט, shochet, his thought bubble is about זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam.
Okay, so when we say the עבודות שלא לשם בעלים avodos shelo
lishmah baalim invalidate, that's only when you're doing those עבודות avodos and
planning for the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Okay, that's different than the
normal שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah. לשמה lishmah means I'm שוחט shocheting it
and I'm thinking it's an עולה. olah. I'm catching the blood and
thinking it's an עולה. olah. I'm walking the blood for well, not
thinking, intending for it to work as an עולה, olah, etc. Here,
שלא לשם בעלים shelo lishmah baalim doesn't mean I'm שוחט shocheting it
for the sake of שמעון. Shimon. That would not invalidate if it's
ראובן's Reuven קרבן. korban. The שחיטה שלא לשם בעלים shechita shelo lishmah
baalim of a חטאת chatas that invalidates is I'm שוחט shocheting ראובן's
Reuven קרבן korban with the intent to do the זריקה לשם שמעון,
zrika l'shem Shimon, which is exactly the question we're asking about שלא
לשמה. shelo lishmah. And this is the only way that it works
לשם בעלים lishmah baalim is you do these עבודות avodos not to
do the thing itself לשם שמעון, lishmah Shimon, but to plan to
do the זריקה לשם שמעון. zrika l'shem Shimon. Okay, so now, now
that's a good model to say if that's what you have by
שלא לשם בעלים, shelo lishmah baalim, it should be the same by
שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah. Yeah, everybody get that? Yes.
What happens if you have if you do that, but when you
get to the זריקה zrika you remember and then you you do
it for the right guy?
You've still invalidated it from the moment of שחיטה, shechita, correct. Okay,
so now that is a good model that if that's how שלא
לשם בעלים shelo lishmah baalim works, that should be how שלא לשמה
shelo lishmah works as well, at least as well. Okay, so let's
take a look. הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: ומה במקום שאמר הריני שוחט
לשם פלוני שהוא כשר, uma bemakom she'amar hareni shochet l'shem ploni shehu
kasher, I'm שוחט shocheting it for שמעון, Shimon, it's ראובן's Reuven sacrifice,
it's so כשר. kasher. אם תאמר לזרוק דמו לשם פלוני פסול, im
tomar lizrok damo l'shem ploni pasul,
but the שלא לשם בעלים shelo lishmah baalim that works is when
you שוחט shochet it, you plan to do the זריקה לשם פלוני.
zrika l'shem ploni. במקום שאמר הריני שוחט שלא לשמה שהוא פסול. bemakom
she'amar hareni shochet shelo lishmah shehu pasul. So when it comes to
שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, if you say I'm doing the שחיטה shechita
of this חטאת chatas and I'm intending that it should be as
an עולה, olah, that invalidates. שחטו על מנת לזרוק דמו שלא לשמה
אינו דין שיהא פסול? shachto al mnat lizrok damo shelo lishmah eino
din sheyehe pasul? Certainly it should be when you're doing the שחיטה
shechita with the intent to do the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Okay,
so that's a pretty darn good proof. Okay, here שחיטה שלא לשם
בעלים shechita shelo lishmah baalim doesn't invalidate, but שחיטה shechita with the
intent of זריקה שלא לשם בעלים zrika shelo lishmah baalim does invalidate.
So when שחיטה שלא לשמה shechita shelo lishmah invalidates, שחיטה shechita to
be זורק שלא לשמה zorek shelo lishmah should also invalidate. Okay, pretty
good proof. So so that's it. Okay, and we do not have
an answer. That is a pretty darn good קל וחומר kal vachomer
and a pretty darn good model that a כוונה kavana even in
the שלא לשמה shelo lishmah world for a later act as long
as the later act is זריקה, zrika, right? This is particularly about
זריקה. zrika. If you do the שחיטה shechita to do קבלה שלא
לשם בעלים, kabala shelo lishmah baalim, it doesn't work, or to do
the הולכה שלא לשם בעלים. holacha shelo lishmah baalim. It's all about
לכפר עליו, l'chaper alav, all about זריקה. zrika. So this is specifically
a point, not just that a כוונה kavana about a later act
works for now, this is specifically a point that a כוונה kavana
about זריקה zrika invalidates at any of the earlier stages. Okay, and
we see that by שלא לשם בעלים, shelo lishmah baalim, and we
want to say the same about שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah.
Let me just make sure I got the one rule right. So
you see the פיגול pigul what we said, that was the quote-unquote
broader expansive eating חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. But if it's חוץ למקומו,
chutz limkomo, what is it called? Just חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo, not
פיגול? pigul? Yep. And then it's not and then if you eat
it, that's not כרת? kares?
לאו, lav, it's not it's not כרת. kares.
And doing it in both cases is always a לאו? lav? Correct.
Yes, כרת kares is only by eating on a פיגול pigul which
is חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano.
Yes, all that's going to be second פרק perek in זבחים. Zevachim.
Okay, now. מתיב רב אילא. mesiv Rav Ila. So that's a pretty
darn good point. So now let's see the support of ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. רב אילא לסיועיה לריש לקיש. Rav Ila l'siyu'ei le'Reish Lakish.
רב אילא Rav Ila has the following argument to support ריש לקיש.
Reish Lakish. לא תאמר בזריקה, lo tomar bizrika, but So that’s a
pretty darn good point. So now let's see the support of ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish. רבי אלעזר לשיטתיה דריש לקיש. Rebbi Elazar leshitateh de'Reish
Lakish. רבי אלעזר Rebbi Elazar has the following argument to support ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish. לא תאמר בזריקה ותצא מקל וחומר מבניינה. lo tomar
bizrika veteitzei mikal vachomer mibinyana. Why did the תורה Torah have to
tell me that לא לשמה? lo lishma? Remember we had a פסוק
pasuk to tell me לא לשמה lo lishma by שחיטה, shchita, לא
לשמה lo lishma by קבלה, kabala, by הולכה, holacha, by זריקה? zrika?
Why? At least הולכה holacha was always sort of one unit with
קבלה. kabala. Why does it have to tell me לא לשמה lo
lishma by זריקה, zrika, the פסוקים? psukim? Why didn't it just tell
me—we're not talking about שלא לשם בעלים, shelo lshem be'alim, just straight
שלא לשמה—just shelo lishma tell me שלא לשמה shelo lishma is a
problem by שחיטה shchita and שלא לשמה shelo lishma is a problem
by קבלה? kabala? And I could have inferred זריקה. zrika. Why? If
I just say שחיטה, shchita, I wouldn't have inferred זריקה zrika because
שחיטה shchita has a unique הלכה halacha of שלא לשמה shelo lishma
because of קרבן פסח, korban pesach, right? It has to be לאוכליו,
le'ochlav, etc. If it had just said by קבלה, kabala, I wouldn't
have been able to infer זריקה zrika because I would have said—and
now I'm forgetting what I would have said by קבלה... kabala... one
minute...
I'm forgetting what I would have—how I would have limited קבלה. kabala.
But anyway, okay, so anyway,
why did it tell me—why did it tell me two? Okay? By
telling me שחיטה shchita and קבלה, kabala, why did it have to
also tell me זריקה? zrika? שחיטה shchita now doesn't—you know, it's not
unique to שחיטה shchita that has שלא לשמה shelo lishma because of
קרבן פסח korban pesach because it also applies by קבלה kabala שלא
לשמה. shelo lishma. So between שחיטה shchita and קבלה, kabala, I would
have learned that שלא לשמה shelo lishma applies by all עבודות. avodot.
Why did it have to also tell me by זריקה? zrika? Okay,
so let's take a look.
Where were we?
לא תאמר בזריקה, lo tomar bizrika, don't tell me בזריקה bizrika ותצא
מקל וחומר מביניה. veteitzei mikal vachomer mibeineiya. I will learn it out
from the two of them, from שחיטה shchita and קבלה. kabala. If
שלא לשמה shelo lishma invalidates by שחיטה shchita and it invalidates by
קבלה, kabala, it should certainly invalidate by זריקה. zrika. זריקה's zrika always
obviously much more weighty. You know, it has the פסול psul of
שלא לשם בעלים shelo lshem be'alim and all those types of things.
So למה הלכתא כתב רחמנא? lemai hilchata katav Rachmana? Why did the
תורה Torah have to write שלא לשמה shelo lishma is an issue
by זריקה? zrika? I could have learned it out.
לומר שאין מחשבין מעבודה לעבודה. lomar she'ein me'chashvin me'avoda le'avoda. The reason
it says שלא לשמה shelo lishma is a זריקה zrika issue is
to tell me זריקה zrika also the same שלא לשמה shelo lishma
applies, meaning you have to have שלא לשמה shelo lishma by the
act itself, and it can't be a different thing, you know, thinking
about זריקה zrika when you're doing a different act. So the reason
the תורה Torah told me שחיטה, shchita, זריקה zrika of שלא לשמה
shelo lishma is to tell me that thinking about זריקה zrika at
a different act does not invalidate. So the גמרא Gemara says, how
do you know that that's how you read the extra word? מתקיף
לה רב פפא. matkif lah Rav Pappa. Maybe it's coming to tell
me the exact opposite.
ודילמא דמחשבין מעבודה לעבודה כן. v'dilma d'mechashvin me'avoda le'avoda ken. Maybe I'll
say the opposite. The reason the תורה Torah said—added the word—told me
that זריקה zrika has to be שלא לשמה shelo lishma was not
to limit the שלא לשמה shelo lishma by זריקה zrika but to
expand the שלא לשמה shelo lishma by זריקה zrika and tell me
by זריקה שלא לשמה zrika shelo lishmo works even if you had
that thought at an earlier עבודה. avoda. Okay? So the argument is,
since the תורה Torah said שלא לשמה shelo lishma by זריקה zrika
and it didn't have to say it, it's coming to limit and
saying you need the thought only during the זריקה zrika itself, not
at an earlier time for the sake of the זריקה. zrika The
גמרא Gemara says, how do you know to read it that way?
Maybe I should say that the שלא לשמה shelo lishma is coming
to tell me—the extra word זריקה zrika. is coming to tell me
that when you have a thought about זריקה, zrika it works even
many times—even at an earlier stage, right? Maybe it's expanding the scope
of when שלא לשמה shelo lishma works.
So the גמרא Gemara says no.
אם כן לשתוק קרא מיניה ותיתי מקל וחומר דרב אשי. im ken
lishtok kra mineih veteiti mikal vachomer de'Rav Ashi. No, because based on
the whole great קל וחומר kal vachomer רב אשי Rav Ashi made
about זריקה zrika, and שלא לשם בעלים, shelo lshem be'alim, without any
extra פסוק, pasuk, the גמרא Gemara says, you know what? You're right.
The natural thing would have been to think that שחיטה על מנת
לזרוק דמו שלא לשמה shchita al mnat lizrok damo shelo lishma does
invalidate. רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is the more natural thing to think,
that it does invalidate. Why? Because that's the הלכה halacha by שלא
לשם בעלים, shelo lshem be'alim, שחיטה על מנת לזרוק את הדם. shchita
al mnat lizrok et hadam. So you're right, that's a very powerful
model, the שלא לשם בעלים, shelo lshem be'alim, and therefore we should
have said the same by a normal שלא לשמה. shelo lishma So
I would have said this without a special פסוק. pasuk. I would
have agreed with רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that שחיטה על מנת להיות
זורק הדם shchita al mnat lihyot zorek hadam
invalidates the same way it invalidates by שלא לשם בעלים. shelo lshem
be'alim. That would have been my natural position. Since the תורה Torah
even with that went out of its way to say explicitly זריקה
zrika is an issue of שלא לשמה, shelo lishma. the only thing
it's coming to do is to limit the פסול psul and say
only when I have that מחשבה machshava during זריקה zrika itself, not
when I have that מחשבה machshava at an earlier stage for the
sake of what I'm going to do at זריקה. zrika Okay?
So אם כן, im ken, if the תורה Torah wanted to invalidate
שחיטה shchita with the intent of זריקה, zrika. לשתוק קרא מיניה. lishtok
kra mineih. You didn't need to tell me the issue of שלא
לשמה shelo lishma, by זריקה. zrika, Just be quiet. ותיתי מקל וחומר
דרב אשי. veteiti mikal vachomer de'Rav Ashi. I would have learned it
from the קל וחומר kal vachomer of שלא לשם בעלים. shelo lshem
be'alim. The fact that the תורה Torah tells me an issue of
שלא לשמה shelo lishma by זריקה zrika. is telling me only. Only
if the שלא לשמה shelo lishma is during the act itself, not
during an earlier stage with the intent of the act. ואידך, V'idach,
the other one would say back, פריך
הכי, parich hachi, מה להני ma l'hani שכן טעונים צפון shekein te'unim
tzafon וישנן בחטאות הפנימיות. v'yeshnan b'chataos hapenimiyos. No, don't tell me the
word of זריקה zrika is extra. If it had just told me
שחיטה shechita and קבלה, kabala, I would have said that these things
are weightier than זריקה. zrika Why? Because these things when you're dealing
with a חטאת, chatas, they have to be done at the north
of the מזבח. mizbeiach. Okay, and therefore that's טעון צפון te'un tzafon
וישנן בחטאות הפנימיות, v'yeshnan b'chataos hapenimiyos, and these two apply by even
when you're doing a חטאת chatas that's brought in the inner, you
know, that the blood is sprinkled on the inner מזבח, mizbeiach, whereas
זריקה, zrika. it never has to be in the north and זריקה,
zrika, you don't do זריקה zrika, on the outer מזבח mizbeiach for
a חטאת chatas that's brought in to the innermost sanctuary. So therefore
the answer back, ah, זריקה zrika is extra, that's tell me only
during זריקה zrika not at an earlier stage and the answer is
זריקה zrika isn't extra because these I could not have gotten זריקה
zrika from these cases. These cases in some ways are weightier than
זריקה zrika that when you're dealing with a חטאת chatas it has
to be at the north and therefore I would not have been
able to infer that you need לשמה lishma by זריקה. zrika Okay,
and that's why don't tell me זריקה zrika. is extra. ואידך, V'idach,
and the answer back is השתא מיהא בשלמים קיימינן. hashta meiha b'shlamim
kayminan. Now we're talking about שלמים, shlamim, right? The פסוקים psukim about
שלא לשמה shelo lishmo are about שלמים, shlamim, and in the world
of שלמים, shlamim, if I would have just had שחיטה shechita and
קבלה, kabala, I could have inferred זריקה. zrika Yes, there are ways
these are weightier in the world of חטאת, chatas, but we're not
dealing with חטאת. chatas. We're dealing with a שלמים. shlamim. And therefore
since we're dealing with שלמים shlamim the תורה Torah just had to
say שחיטה shechita and קבלה kabala and I could have inferred זריקה.
zrika. Why did the תורה Torah have to tell me זריקה? zrika.
Says ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, to tell me don't learn this out
from the idea of, you know, שלא לשם בעלים shelo l'shem ba'alin
that an earlier מחשבה machshava works. זריקה zrika? is telling me when
it comes to שלא לשמה, shelo lishmo only the מחשבה machshava during
the act itself works. א מחשבה A machshava from one stage for
a later stage does not work. Okay, so at the end of
the day what have we said? We've said that even though we
started by saying that the model is פיגול, pigul, פיגול pigul is
really a unique type of a model and we're not going to
learn out from it. But a much more relevant one is the
שלא לשם בעלים shelo l'shem ba'alin where there it is true that
at an earlier stage מחשבת זריקה machsheves zrika invalidates even when the
מחשבה machshava for the act itself doesn't. So why not say the
same about שלא לשמה? shelo lishmo, And the basic response of ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish is you're right. The logic would have said we
should have said the same by שלא לשמה shelo lishmo? that a
מחשבה machshava at an earlier stage to do the זריקה שלא לשמה
zrika shelo lishmo, invalidates the same way that's true by שלא לשם
בעלים. shelo l'shem ba'alin. But the extra, the fact that the תורה
Torah went out of its way to say explicitly זריקה, zrika says
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, I'm going to interpret that to say that
it's telling me דווקא davka not that way. It's telling me that
the זריקה zrika, only the thought at the זריקה zrika itself invalidates,
not the thought of the זריקה zrika at an earlier stage. All
right, איתמר. itmar. Now שחטה לשמו לזרוק דמו שלא לשמו. shachtah lishmo
lizrok damo shelo lishmo. So this exact debate, רב נחמן אמר פסולה.
Rav Nachman amar psula. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says it's invalid like
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבא אמר כשרה, Rava amar kesheira, כשר kosher
like ריש לקיש. Reish Lakish. והדר ביה רבא לגבי רב נחמן, V'hadar
beih Rava legabi Rav Nachman, in the end רבא Rava retracted and
went like רב נחמן Rav Nachman and said it's invalid מקל וחומר
דרב אשי mikol v'chomer d'Rav Ashi from רב אשי'ס Rav Ashi's קל
וחומר, kol v'chomer, right? Which is very straight, which is the basic
point. Hey, if we see this by שלא לשם בעלים shelo l'shem
ba'alin that a מחשבת זריקה machsheves zrika at an earlier stage invalidates
even when the מחשבה machshava for the act itself doesn't, so it
should be true by שלא לשמה shelo lishmo as well. It should
certainly be true. If the מחשבה machshava for שחיטה shechita invalidates, then
a מחשבה machshava for planning to do the זריקה zrika should also
invalidate at the time of שחיטה. shechita. Okay, so certainly if you
use the לשם בעלים l'shem ba'alin as a model without quoting some
extra פסוק, pasuk, you're going to come to this conclusion that if
you have a כוונה kavana to do the זריקה zrika שלא לשמה,
shelo lishmo it invalidates even at an earlier stage. But that's only
זריקה. zrika. That's a unique characteristic of זריקה, zrika, the power of
זריקה לכפר, zrika l'chaper, and we learn that out from שלא לשם
בעלים. shelo l'shem ba'alin. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. Now we
move on from those fun explorations of the extent of שלא לשמה
shelo lishmo and we get on to the position of רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer. You might remember in the משנה, Mishna, רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says an אשם asham is like a חטאת. chatas. The פסוק
pasuk says כחטאת כאשם, kachatas ka'asham, they're both coming על חטא. al
cheit. So the same way שלא לשמה shelo lishmo invalidates by a
חטאת, שלא לשמה Chatat shelo lishma invalidates by an אשם. asham. Let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. תניא, Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא. braisa. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer, חטאת בא על חטא
ואשם בא על חטא. chatas ba al cheit v'asham ba al cheit.
מה חטאת שלא לשמה פסולה אף אשם שלא לשמה פסולה. Ma chatas
shelo lishmo psula af asham shelo lishmo psula. Okay,
it's a nice obvious point. If it's about sin and שלא לשמה
shelo lishmo invalidates, and as we sort of said, it makes a
lot of sense. A חטאת'ס chatas's whole identity is wrapped up about
the atonement and is connected to this person and so on. Once
it's disconnected from the person, which is the effect of שלא לשמה,
shelo lishmo right, it's invalid. So the same is true by an
אשם. asham. Okay, אף אשם שלא לשמו פסול. af asham shelo lishmo
pasul. אמר ליה רבי יהושע, amar leh Rabi Yehoshua, Rabbi Yehoshua said
back to him, לא. אם אמרת בחטאת שכן דמה למעלה. lo im
amarta b'chatas sheken dama l'ma'la. By a חטאת, chatas,
now this seems to be a relatively arbitrary and not related point,
but we're just saying there's something distinctive about it, okay? And maybe
it's a distinctive thing that points out that it's weightier, okay? Which
is that you have your altar here, okay? Let's see how good
my drawings are, whatever,
whatever, doesn't matter.
Okay, whatever. Anyway, you've got your altar. Okay, there we go, whatever,
whatever, it doesn't matter. Anyway, here we'll make it like this, actually,
that's, that's actually more correct. Okay, anyway. Okay.
Okay,
so
anyway, there's this thing in the middle called a חוט הסיקרא, chut
hasikra, which is the mid-line of the, of the, of the altar.
So, when you are sprinkling the blood of sacrifices, the blood of
a חטאת chattas, goes at the corners, at the four corners. Okay,
that's חטאת. chattas Okay, עולת העוף olas haof goes like above this
middle line, and I guess I should draw it like this, that's
the middle line. So the עולת העוף olas haof blood goes, well,
whatever, it goes here, let's say. Okay, that's עולת העוף. olas haof.
And all the other sacrifices go here, below the line, okay? שלמים,
shelmim,
אשם. asham. Okay, so, he says look, you can't learn out which
includes an אשם. asham. So he says, no, you can't say oh,
an אשם asham should be like a חטאת chattas. and שלא לשמה
shelo lishmo, would invalidate. A חטאת chattas is different, a חטאת chattas
is above the line and an אשם asham is below the line
and somehow that should tell you they're different. What below and above
the line has to do, I don't know, I mean I know
it matters in bridge, contract bridge, but anyway, anybody know how to
do contract bridge? Anyway, so, alright, anyway, what that has to do
with this but it shows you they're different. Okay, לא, lo. אם
אמרת בחטאת שכן דמה למעלה. im amarta bechattas sheken dama lemala. אמר
ליה רבי אליעזר, amar leh Rabi Eliezer, פסח יוכיח, pesach yochiach, שדמה
למטה. shedama lemata.
One minute, we have another thing that's invalid שלא לשמה, shelo lishma
קרבן פסח, korban pesach, and that blood is below the line. So
you see it's not about above or below the line, you can
be פסול שלא לשמה pasul shelo lishma even below the line. ושחטו
שלא לשמה פסול. vshachato shelo lishma pasul. אמר ליה רבי יהושע, amar
leh Rabi Yehoshua, Rabbi Yehoshua said back to him, מה לפסח שכן
זמנו קבוע. ma lpesach sheken zmano kavoa. פסח pesach is only at
a fixed time. So, therefore, so, you know, each one has a
unique characteristic, right? A חטאת chattas you can bring it any time,
but it's above the line. A פסח pesach only has a fixed
time, so maybe one or those are necessary by שלא לשמה, shelo
lishma, but you can't apply that to an אשם asham that has
neither of those characteristics. אמר ליה רבי אליעזר, amar leh Rabi Eliezer,
חטאת תוכיח. chattas tochiach. Go back to חטאת, chattas right, meaning he
wants to sort of do חוזר הדין. chozer hadin. Right, okay, but
don't blame it on above the line, you see by פסח. pesach.
Don't blame it on a fixed time, you see by חטאת. chattas,
It's not about being above or below the line, it's not about
being a fixed time or non-fixed time, so you can have שלא
לשמה shelo lishma, in a wider range of things, alright? I mean
that it invalidates. אמר ליה רבי יהושע, amar leh Rabi Yehoshua, as
Rabbi Yehoshua said back to him, חזרני chozrani or חזרנו, chozanu, חלילה.
chalila. Now you've got made us go all around in a circle.
Okay, which means what? Which basically means like, no, you're just now
going in circles. You're going to tell me חטאת, chattas. I'm going
to tell you that it's above the line. You're going to tell
me פסח, pesach, I'm going to tell you שלא בזמנו. shelo bizmano.
You're going to go back to חטאת, chattas, I'm going to tell
you it's above the line. The funny thing is, as the גמרא
Gemara is going to say, what type of response is that? What
Rabbi Eliezer is saying is the classic צד השווה. tzad hashaveh. You
can't blame it on this characteristic of a חטאת chattas, or that
characteristic of a פסח, pesach, because the other one proves that that's
not relevant. So we see that above or below the line isn't
relevant, we see that a fixed time isn't relevant, that means that
we can apply it more broadly. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to say what Rabbi Yehoshua's response was to Rabbi Eliezer. It's not
clear what his response was. Okay, but that's one critique. One critique
is, חטאת chattas is different, it's above the line. חזר רבי אליעזר
ודן דין אחר. chazar Rabi Eliezer vdan din acher. Rabbi Eliezer went
and made another קל וחומר, kal vachomer, another argument. חטאת נאמר בה
היא. chattas neemar ba hi.
It says חטאת היא, chattas hi, okay? And that's how we learn
that it has to be לשמה lishma בשחיטה. beshchita. היא לשמה כשרה
שלא לשמה פסולה, hi lishma kshira shelo lishma psula,
only when it's done לשמה lishma is it kosher, not when it's
done שלא לשמה. shelo lishma ופסח נאמר בו הוא, upesach neemar bo
hu, כי זבח פסח הוא. ki zevach pesach hu. So הוא hu
says that it has to be done exactly this way. בזביחה, bezvicha,
by the שחיטה, shchita, הוא לשמה כשר שלא לשמה פסול. hu lishma
kasher shelo lishma pasul. אף אשם נאמר בו הוא, af asham neemar
bo hu, אשם הוא, asham hu, אשם אשם לה'. asham asham lHashem.
הוא לשמה כשר שלא לשמה פסול. hu lishma kasher shelo lishma pasul.
So I'm not going to do it by a connection to חטאת,
chattas by an analogy, I'm going to say the keyword הוא hu
or היא, hi, which it applies by חטאת chattas, and פסח, pesach,
is used by אשם asham as well. That seems like a pretty
good argument. אמר ליה רבי יהושע, amar leh Rabi Yehoshua, Rabbi Yehoshua
said back to him, חטאת נאמר בה היא בשחיטה. chattas neemar ba
hi beshchita. No, no, here's the difference Rabbi Eliezer. The היא hi
that appears by חטאת chattas appears at the moment of שחיטה. shchita.
ושחט אותה לחטאת, vshachato osa lchattas, חטאת היא. chattas hi. Okay, actually
is it אותה, osa, is it היא, hi, sometimes we do one,
the other, anyway, היא לשמה כשרה שלא לשמה פסולה. hi lishma kshira
shelo lishma psula. פסח נאמר בו הוא בזביחה. pesach neemar bo hu
bezvicha. קרבן פסח הוא לה', korban pesach hu lHashem, זבח פסח הוא
לה', zevach pesach hu lHashem, זבח. zevach. The שחיטה Shechita has to
be לשם פסח. lshem Pesach. לשמה כשר
שלא לשמה פסול. lishma kasher shelo lishma pasul. But אשם, asham, and
we quoted this line earlier, לא נאמר בו הוא אלא אחר הקטרת
אימורים. lo nemar bo hu ela achar haktaras emurim. But
when the Torah says by אשם, asham, אשם הוא אשם אשם לה׳,
asham hu asham asham lHashem, it says it in the Torah after
it describes the entrails being burned. Okay, and at that stage that's
not the four classic עבודות. avodos. It's too late to invalidate the
קרבן. korban. Once you get done with the זריקה, zrika, right, you
can't invalidate the קרבן. korban. והוא עצמו שלא הוקטרו אימורים vehu atzmo
shelo huktru emurim כשר, kasher, and even if you didn't do the
אימורים emurim it's כשר. kasher. So the הוא hu by the אשם
asham does not tell you to not be a basis of שלא
לשמו shelo lishmo invalidate because it's written in in a place where
obviously שלא לשמו shelo lishmo could not have an impact. Okay, אמר
לו רבי אליעזר, amar lo Rebbi Eliezer, Rebbi Eliezer tries a third
time. הרי הוא אומר כחטאת כאשם. harei hu omer kachatas ka'asham. The
verse explicitly links them. כי כחטאת כאשם, ki kachatas ka'asham, I forget
the end of the פסוק. pasuk.
Anyway,
okay, the פסוק pasuk explicitly links the two. מה חטאת שלא לשמה
פסול אף אשם שלא לשמה פסול. ma chatas shelo lishma pasul af
asham shelo lishma pasul. Okay, I got an explicit link and Rebbi
Yehoshua does not have a response back. Okay, that's the ברייתא, beraisa,
three different proofs, the first two Rebbi Yehoshua has a response, the
third one he doesn't. Now we're going to unpack it. אמר מר.
amar mar. אמר לו רבי יהושע, amar lo Rebbi Yehoshua, חזרני חלילה,
chozarni chalila,
now you've made me go in circles. So the גמרא Gemara says
what type of response is that? He said don't try to push
away חטאת chattas by saying it's above the line, I'll show you
פסח. Pesach. Don't tell me פסח Pesach is a fixed time, I'll
show you חטאת. chatas So what do you mean you're going in
circles? I'm not going in circles. Learn it out, the common denominator
should tell you that you that it's not based on above or
below the line or a fixed or a non-fixed time. ולימהדר דינא,
v'leihadar dina, so go around, go back in a circle, ולייתי במה
הצד, v'leisei b'ma hatzad, learn it out from the common denominator that
you can't base it on above or below the line.
No,
because here's really what Rebbi Yehoshua was saying back, משום דאיכא למיפרך,
mishum deika lemifrach, you can challenge it the following way. מה לצד
השוה שבהן שכן יש בהן צד כרת. ma l'tzad hashaveh shebahen sheken
yesh bahen tzad kares. Now that wasn't clear in Rebbi Yehoshua's word
at all, but okay, חטאת chatas. and פסח Pesach are both linked
to a world of כרת, kares, right? Because a חטאת chatas comes
to atone for a sin that you're deserving כרת, kares, and if
you don't bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach you get כרת. kares.
Okay, so because they're both connected to כרת, kares, they're weightier. But
an אשם, asham, you can't apply that to an אשם. asham. אמר
לו רבי יהושע, amar lo Rebbi Yehoshua, so Rebbi Yehoshua would say
back, לא lo, אם אמרת בחטאת שכן דמה למעלה. im amarta bechattas
sheken dama lemala. Okay, fine. אם אמרת בחטאת שכן דמה למעלה im
amarta b'chatas sheken dama l'ma'la ולימא ליה לא. veleima lei lo.
Okay, okay, fine. So that's what his response back. So we're done
with that. His response back was they're connected to כרת, kares, and
that's why Rebbi Yehoshua said don't learn it out from the combination
of חטאת chatas and פסח. Pesach. So now we understand Rebbi Yehoshua's
response to Rebbi Eliezer. Now let's go back to another point of
when Rebbi Yehoshua, so that was why you don't learn out from
a צד השוה. tzad hashaveh. Now let's learn out from why Rebbi
Yehoshua tries to say that חטאת chatas is different because the blood
is above. That was the one point he made. You can't learn
it, before we got to the כרת kares point, you can't learn
it out from a חטאת chatas because the blood is above and
an אשם asham the blood is below. So he says why is
that what we focused on? אמר לו רבי יהושע לא אם אמרת
בחטאת שכן דמה למעלה. amar lo Rebbi Yehoshua lo im amarta b'chatas
sheken dama l'ma'la. ולימא ליה, veleima lei,
there's more things you could point out about the unique nature of
חטאת chatas and why you can't apply it to an אשם. asham.
Why didn't he say לא אם אמרת בחטאת שכן נכנס דמה לפני
ולפנים? lo im amarta b'chatas sheken nichnas dama lifnai v'lifnim?
חטאת chatas is very weighty. You know, some types of קרבנות, korbanos,
on a יום כיפור Yom Kippur you bring it all the way
into the inner sanctum and to the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. בחטאת
החיצונה קאמרינן. b'chatas hachitzona ka'amrinan.
No, we're talking about the the outer חטאות, chata'os, the one that
are brought on the outer altar. So those don't have that weightiness.
So he couldn't make that point that that's why חטאת chatas has
a special שלא לשמה shelo lishma. because that's not relevant to a
normal חטאת. chatas Okay, how about how about this comparison? Why didn't
he say here's how חטאת chatas. is weightier, שכן נכנס דמה לפני
ולפנים פסולה. sheken nichnas dama lifnai v'lifnim psula. The הלכה halacha is
כל חטאת אשר יובא מדמה אל אהל מועד לכפר בקדש לא תאכל
באש תשרף. kol chatas asher yuva midama el ohel mo'ed lachaper bakodesh
lo te'achel ba'esh tisaref.
If you bring the blood of a חטאת chatas that the blood
should have been on the outer altar, you bring it into the,
you know, to the to the קודש Kodesh or the קודש קדשים,
Kodesh Kodashim, you invalidate the sacrifice. And that is only true about
the blood of a חטאת. chatas If you bring the blood of
the עולה Olah into the, you know, the היכל, Heichal, you do
not invalidate the sacrifice. So the fact that the blood of a
חטאת chatas. is more easy to invalidate if it's just brought
in to the היכל Heichal and you invalidate it shows you that
a חטאת chatas is weightier. This above and below the line, you
know, does not really so much signify that a חטאת chatas is
weightier. But if you want to say here's why I know a
חטאת chatas is weightier and שלא לשמו shelo lishmo is a special
חטאת chatas הלכה halacha and not an אשם, asham, make the point
that the blood of a חטאת chatas is more easy to invalidate,
you just bring it in
to the היכל Heichal and you invalidate
it. So the גמרא Gemara says no, אית ליה לרבי אליעזר אף
אשם, is lei lRebbi Eliezer af asham, because Rebbi Eliezer. because he
links חטאת chatas and אשם, Asham, he actually is going to say,
as we'll see tomorrow,
that the same הלכה halacha applies to an אשם. Asham. If you
bring the blood of an אשם Asham into the היכל heichal you
invalidate. So then don't prove to me that a חטאת Chatas is
weightier, I'll tell you the same הלכה halacha should apply to an
אשם. Asham. Okay, why don't we say a חטאת Chatas is weightier
the following way? שכן מחברת החייבי כריתות. shekein mechaveres hachayvei krisos. Here's
why חטאת Chatas is weightier and maybe it's more invalid by שלא
לשמו, shelo lishmo, because חטאת Chatas atones for sins of כריתות. krisos.
An אשם Asham doesn't atone for sins of כריתות, krisos, an אשם
Asham atones for lighter sins. No, מחטאת דשמיעת הקול, meichatas deshmiah hakol,
there's the חטאת Chatas of, you know, of an oath of giving
עדות edus is not a case of כרת. kares. Okay, so
therefore רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, since חטאת שלא לשמו Chatas shelo
lishmo invalidates, even a חטאת Chatas that's not about a weighty כרת
kares sin, don't tell me a חטאת Chatas is different because it's
only by weighty sins. Okay, why didn't he say חטאת Chatas was
weightier in the following way? שכן טעונה ארבע מתנות. shekein teuna arba
matanos. So not just above or below the line, the fact is
here you have four separate applications of blood. All other sacrifices that
are down here, you do what's called שתים שהן ארבע, shtayim shehein
arba, like you sprinkle the blood at two kitty corners and you
throw it here and then at the other corner over here you
throw it like that. So it hits all four walls, but it's
by two throwings of blood. Okay, so that is more than above
and below the line, this shows a חטאת Chatas is weightier, it
gets four separate applications, this only gets two applications. Why didn't he
use that as an example of חטאת Chatas being weightier? Why didn't
he say
כרבי ישמעאל דאמר כל הדמים טעונים ארבע מתנות? ki'rabbi yishmael d'amar kol
hadamim teunim arba matanos? No, because maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would
hold like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that would say you don't do
it like that, by the other קרבנות korbanos you actually do separate
זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam, you don't do, you know, two that's four,
you do four that's four. You know what I mean? So you
do some here and then some there and then some there and
then some there. So therefore this is four and that's four,
so there's no חטאת Chatas being weightier according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi
Yishmael, everything gets four, either four corners or four sides at the
bottom.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
why didn't it say שכן טעונה על ארבע קרנות? shekein teuna al
arba kranos? Okay, but why didn't it say that this is still
four different corners? And that's still four different, you know, sides of
the altar. Here it's this and here, but you never get this
corner or that corner. So even though this is four and that's
four, this is still obviously more in the sense that it hits
all the corners of the altar. So there's other ways to show
that a חטאת Chatas is weightier. So the גמרא Gemara says look,
there are plenty of ways to show that a חטאת Chatas is
weightier, says the גמרא, Gemara, ולטעמיך, ul'taameich, I'll give you other ways
he could have said a חטאת Chatas is weightier. איכא אצבע, ika
etzba, by חטאת Chatas you apply with your finger, these you just
throw the blood. So that's obviously a special ritual by a חטאת.
Chatas איכא קרן, ika keren, you put it on the horn, on
the actual what's called here the horns, not just on the wall.
ואיכא חודה, ve'ika huda, and you put it like at the edge
of the קרן. keren. It's just a more details about how you
put it at those horns. אלא, ella, so of course there's other
ways a חטאת Chatas. is weightier. חדא מתרי תלת טעמי נקט, chada
mi'trei tlas ta'ami nakat, he gives one out of two or three
reasons. He could have given a lot of ways חטאת Chatas is
weightier, he chose the fact that חטאת Chatas is above the line
and this is below the line. You know, that was רבי יהושע's
Rabbi Joshua response, don't learn it out from חטאת, Chatas חטאת Chatas,
is weightier. There are many details of the certainly of the blood
of whatever of a חטאת Chatas that he could have pointed to
that would have shown that חטאת Chatas is weightier. He just gave
one out of many examples. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר מר, amar mar, let's go back to another part
of this ברייתא. braita. אמר לו לרבי יהושע, amar lo le'rabbi yehoshua,
look, אם אמרת im amarta etc. You know, he says no, that's
only by a חטאת, Chatas a חטאת Chatas, is, so again, we're
going to the point that he says a חטאת Chatas is weightier
because the blood is above the line. That was רבי יהושע's Rabbi
Joshua pushback to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, you can't learn from a
חטאת. Chatas So the גמרא Gemara says why did רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer concede the point? If רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer always links a
חטאת Chatas. to an אשם, Asham, maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer should
have said you know what I'm going to say? I'm going to
say an אשם's Asham blood should also be above the line, right?
Since רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is always linking an אשם Asham to
a חטאת. Chatas So לימליה רבי אליעזר, leimalieh rabbi eliezer, why doesn't
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say back אשם נמי דמו למעלה? asham nami
damo l'maala? Hey, I'll say the blood for an אשם Asham should
be above the line. אמר אביי, amar abbaye, so says אביי, Abbaye,
אשם דמו למעלה לא מצית אמרת. asham damo l'maala lo matzis amart.
No, that you can't say. Why? קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, even רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would have to admit that from a קל וחומר
kal v'chomer that the blood of an אשם Asham is not above
the line. מעולה, me'olah, from an עולה. olah. ומה עולה שהיא כליל,
u'mah olah shehi kalil, an עולה olah that you burn the entire
thing דמה למטה, damah l'mata, and even though it's that weighty that
you burn the entire thing the blood is below the line, אשם
שאינו כליל, asham she'eino kalil, an אשם Asham that's not all burnt
up כל שכן, kol shekein, certainly it should be below. Obviously there's
some assumption that below the line is worse than above the line.
ומה לעולה, mah le'olah, no, said the גמרא, Gemara, that you can't
say that, שכן אינה מכפרת, shekein einah mechaperes, an עולה olah doesn't
atone. Maybe something as weighty as an אשם Asham should be above
the line and maybe above the line has to do with the
fact that it atones. חטאת העוף תוכיח. Chatat ha-of tochiach. Ah, but
a חטאת העוף Chatat ha-of is also below the line, a bird
חטאת. Chatas. So you see something can atone and can be below
the line. So no. מה לחטאת העוף שכן אינה מן זבח, Mah
l'chatat ha-of she-ken eina min zevach, but that's not something that's slaughtered.
That's not, you know, that's something that the כהן Kohen sort of
kills it by using his fingernail, not by שחיטה, shechita, not by
שחט-ing shacht it. Okay, so you don't have like any large animal
that atones that's below the line. So therefore you could have said
an אשם Asham should be above the line. It's a large animal,
it's שחט-ed, shacht it atones. So לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא
ראי זה כראי זה. lo rei zeh k'rei zeh v'lo rei zeh
k'rei zeh. So the חטאת העוף Chatat ha-of is not like the
עולה Olah and vice versa. But הצד השוה שבהן, hatzad hashavah she-bahen,
the common denominator is, okay, it's true that a חטאת העוף Chatat
ha-of isn't a large animal but an עולה Olah is. So if
you look at the common denominator between an עולה Olah and a
חטאת העוף, Chatat ha-of, you see it can be a large animal
and it can atone and it can still be below the line.
שכן קדשי קדשים, she-ken kodshei kodashim, things that are holy of holies,
not a שלמים, Shelamim, ודמן למטה, v'daman l'mata, you can do them
below the line. Okay. And it's not relating to atoning because you
have the עולה. Olah. It's not relating to being a large animal,
you got the bird. Anyway, so the common denominator is is that
these things go below the line. אף אני אביא אשם שהוא קדשי
קדשים ודמו
למטה. af ani avi asham she-hu kodesh kodashim v'damo l'mata. Okay, so
therefore we had no basis to argue that an אשם Asham should
be above the line. If these other things are weighty and whatever
and are below the line, an אשם Asham should also be. אמר
ליה רבא מפיזקא לרב אשי. amar leh Rava mi-Pizka l'Rav Ashi. Okay,
one minute, that shouldn't prove it. ולפרוך, u'lifroch, one minute, what's common
about the חטאת, Chatat. bird חטאת, Chatat, and the עולה? Olah? שכן
אין להם קצבה. she-ken ein lahem kitzvah. There's no minimum amount that
the sacrifice has to be worth. So therefore they're not so weighty.
תאמר באשם שיש לו קצבה. tomar b'asham she-yesh lo kitzvah. The תורה
Torah actually says אשם בכסף שקלים, Asham b'kesef shekalim, that there's a
minimum value of cost of the אשם. Asham. So if that's true,
again, so why didn't he say an אשם Asham follows a חטאת?
Chatat, It should be above the line. Don't tell me there are
weighty things below the line, those things in some ways aren't as
weighty as an אשם. Asham. An אשם Asham atones, has a minimum
value, etc. Why didn't רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who wants to make
an אשם Asham always like a חטאת, Chatat? why didn't he say
the blood of an אשם Asham goes above the line? So אלא
היינו טעמא דרבי אליעזר. ela hainu ta'ama d'Rabbi Eliezer. Here's why רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer could not say that. דאמר קרא, d'amar kra, the
verse says הכהן המחטא אותה. ha-Kohen ha-mechateh osah. The כהן Kohen who
makes it a חטאת. Chatat, Okay, and the אותה, osah, דמה למעלה.
dama l'ma'ala. So that talks about putting the blood at the corners.
It, a חטאת, Chatat. goes above the line, ואין דמו של אחר
למעלה, v'ein damo shel acher l'ma'ala, no blood of no other. So
yes, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer might have been inclined to say an
אשם Asham goes above the line, but he had to concede this
point because of the word of אותה. osah. אי הכי, I hachi,
says the גמרא, Gemara, חטאת נמי נימא אותה לשמה כשר שלא לשמה
פסול. Chatat nami neima osah lishma kasher shelo lishma pasul. One minute,
but if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer isn't isn't usually persuaded by the
word אותה osah by a חטאת. Chatat, Because if he were to
be persuaded by that word, he would have said that you can't
say שלא לשמה shelo lishma by an אשם, Asham, because אותה osah
tells me this הלכה halacha applies only to a חטאת. Chatat. No,
הא שאר כל הזבחים בין לשמן בין שלא לשמן כשרים. ha shear
kol hazvachim bein lishman bein shelo lishman ksherim. גמרא Gemara says no,
הוא אותה לאו דוקא. hu osah lav davka. That אותה osah by
חטאת Chatat. that a חטאת Chatat שלא לשמה shelo lishma is פסול
pasul cannot mean the only thing שלא לשמה shelo lishma is פסול
pasul is a חטאת. Chatat. דהא איכא פסח. d'ha ika pesach. Okay,
because פסח Pesach is also שלא לשמה פסול. shelo lishma pasul. So
when it says אותה osah by לשמה lishma that it has to
be for the right reason, it's not meant to exclude everything else.
It doesn't exclude פסח. Pesach. So it also doesn't exclude אשם. Asham.
But when it talks about putting the blood here and it says
אותה osah by the חטאת, Chatat, it does exclude everything else. There's
nothing else that gets put above the line. And therefore from there
we learn that an אשם Asham does not go above the line
because it says אותה osah by the חטאת. Chatat. But the גמרא
Gemara says one minute, that's not true. חטאת Chatat is not the
only thing that's above the line. הכא נמי לאו דוקא. hacha nami
lav davka. אותה Osah doesn't fully exclude everything else דהא איכא עולת
העוף, d'ha ika olas ha-of, because עולת העוף olas ha-of also goes
above the line. So אותה osah doesn't mean חטאת Chatat is the
only thing above the line. No, בזביחה מיא לא שייר מידי. bizvicha
maya lo shayer midi. Okay, when it comes to like things that
you slaughter with a knife, not a bird, like the larger animals,
the only thing that's above the line is a חטאת. Chatat. So
אותה osah tells you that of those larger animals, only a חטאת
Chatat is above the line, birds are different. Only a חטאת Chatat
is above the line, everything else is below. So even though רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wants an אשם Asham to always be like a
חטאת, Chatat, the word אותה osah here prevents him. And the word
אותה osah is telling you the blood of a חטאת Chatat is
the only thing that goes above the line. Okay. When it comes
to שלא לשמה, shelo lishma,
אותה osah isn't as limiting because it also doesn't exclude פסח. Pesach.
One last line. ואיבעית אימא הא מני רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון היא.
v'iba'is eima ha mani Rabbi Eliezer b'rebi Shimon hi. The reason I
don't exclude חטאת, Chatat, you know, I can't say an אשם Asham
goes above the line, is based on רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi
Eliezer b'rebi Shimon. דאמר היי מקום לחוד והיי מקום לחוד. d'amar hai
makom l'chud v'hai makom l'chud. That רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer
b'rebi Shimon emphasizes the idea... That basically each קרבן korban needs its
separate place. Okay? דתניא, De-tanya, we turn a ברייתא. braisa. דמי חטאות
ניתנין מחוט לסיקרא ולמטה, Dami chataos nitanin michut lasikra u-le-mata, the lower
bloods are below the line, that's called the red line, והעליונים מחוט
הסיקרא ולמעלה, ve-ha-alyonim michut ha-sikra u-le-ma'ala, and the other ones above. אמר
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון במה דברים אמורים בעולת העוף. Amar Rebbe Elazar
be-Rebbe Shimon be-meh devarim amurim be-olas ha-of. אבל בחטאת בהמה, Aval be-chatas
behemah, when is that true? That's by an עולת העוף, olas ha-of,
that goes like above the line, okay, but it's in a different
like place. But when it comes to a חטאת, chatas, היא עצמה
אין נעשית אלא על גופה של קרן. hi atzma ein ne'asah ela
al gufa shel keren. We have to be careful, and I don't
want to get into the details of what it means, but it
just means it's not enough to say that these things go above
the line. Each one has its separate place. The עולת העוף olas
ha-of is here, חטאת chatas is at the corners, they each have
their separate place. So basically things that are above the line have
to have their separate place. So therefore there's nowhere for an אשם
asham to do anything above the line. The עולה ola's got this,
the חטאת chatas has got this, the עולת העוף olas ha-of has
that, so you can't place the אשם asham above the line because
everything has to be in its own place. All right? So one
way or another we know that רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, although he
likes an אשם asham to be like a חטאת, chatas, can't have
the אשם asham blood above the line. He concedes the אשם asham
blood is below the line, and therefore רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua uses
that as a way of critiquing him and saying the חטאת chatas
is different, only חטאת chatas is above the line and therefore only
חטאת chatas is שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Okay, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer at the end of the day is not convinced. We will
continue with this tomorrow.