Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's daf דף daf is kuf-tet
ק"ט, kuf-tet, we pick up at the top of kuf-tet ק"ט. kuf-tet.
We're continuing in the discussion of when a person is obligated for
shechting שחיטה shechting korbanot קרבנות korbanot or I should say for offering
korbanot קרבנות korbanot outside of the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash,
offering them to God. So we've been mentioning questions about, well just
yesterday, you know the question, first of all the question which avodah
עבודה, avodah, shechitah שחיטה, shechitah, zrikat hadam זריקת הדם, zrikat hadam, the
ones explicit in the verse are shechitah שחיטה shechitah and the putting
it up on the altar, which we've assumed meant putting it up
on a fire on the altar, although we had a discussion yesterday
whether it had to be an altar or not and I raised
the question whether it even had to be a fire.
And the Gemara גמרא Gemara added in also throwing of the blood,
and you know different types of questions about shechting שחיטה shechting a
korban קרבן korban even for the sake of the meat, there was
a chidush חידוש chidush that that was chayav חייב chayav even though
that wasn't an actual offering of that korban קרבן korban as opposed
to the burning, the burning has to be to God and so
on. So now we talk about starting with the Mishnah משנה Mishnah
on the top of kuf-tet ק"ט, kuf-tet, we talk about what type
more specifics about the type of korbanot קרבנות. korbanot. So echad kodshim
ksheirim ve'echad kodshim psulim אחד קדשים כשרים ואחד קדשים פסולים. echad kodshim
ksheirim ve'echad kodshim psulim. So Michael you had asked the other day
about what if it has a baal mum בעל מום. baal mum.
So this is saying whether it's kosher whether it's pasul פסול, pasul,
but not everything that is pasul פסול, pasul, okay? Shehayah, I mean
first of all let's just remind ourselves there's a principle about about
el petach ohel moed lo hevi'o אל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו,
el petach ohel moed lo hevi'o, so it has to be ra'ui
lipetach ohel moed ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'ui lipetach ohel moed. If
somebody wants to sanctify a, you know, like a
duck or wants to sanctify what would it be a deer or
something like that, obviously you wouldn't be chayav חייב, chayav, and you
would not be chayav חייב chayav because that's not ra'ui lipetach ohel
moed ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'ui lipetach ohel moed.
Okay so for shechitah שחיטה shechitah or what about or not even
ha'ala'ah העלאה? ha'ala'ah?
Not even ha'ala'ah העלאה, ha'ala'ah, again you're doing something wrong like maybe
you're over on the lav לאו lav of hishamer lecha pen ta'aleh
olotecha bechol makom asher tireh השמר לך פן תעלה עלתיך בכל מקום
אשר תראה, hishamer lecha pen ta'aleh olotecha bechol makom asher tireh, that's
a question about how broad is the scope of that lav לאו,
lav, right? Because right that's the question you mean to tell me
people can go ahead and have their private bamot במות bamot and
be bringing these things to God and as long as they don't
fall within these parameters about ra'ui lipetach ohel moed ראוי לפתח אהל
מועד ra'ui lipetach ohel moed they're not transgressing? So look, the issur
איסור issur I haven't looked into it, but the issur איסור issur
about pen ta'aleh olotecha פן תעלה עלתיך pen ta'aleh olotecha might be
a much broader issur איסור. issur. But in terms of this and
the certainly the chiyuv kares חיוב כרת chiyuv kares it has to
be ra'ui lipetach ohel moed ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'ui lipetach ohel
moed.
Meaning let's say I was molek מולק molek a behemah בהמה, behemah,
you know
I did something other than shechitah שחיטה. shechitah. Exactly, exactly, or even
melikah מליקה melikah of a bird now, which is ironic but okay
it's only shechitah שחיטה shechitah anyway. But so why pasul פסול pasul
is okay? Because the next line is shehayah or not okay why
are you chayav חייב? chayav? Shehayah psulan bakodesh שהיה פסולן בקודש. shehayah
psulan bakodesh. If it was one of these, it was something that
was psulan bakodesh פסולן בקודש, psulan bakodesh, meaning the parameters which you
know is that if it was put up on the altar it
stays on the altar even though it was pasul פסול pasul and
you're not allowed to put it on the altar, if you did
it stays up on there, so that's enough considered ra'ui lipetach ohel
moed ראוי לפתח אהל מועד ra'ui lipetach ohel moed that it would
be allowed to stay on the altar. Okay so psulan bakodesh פסולן
בקודש psulan bakodesh we're going to illustrate that in the Gemara גמרא,
Gemara, you know something like but basically the easiest way to understand
that is as the phrase indicates that the psul פסול psul happened
after it was brought into the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
It was shechted נשחטה shechted shelo lishmah שלא לשמה, shelo lishmah, the
blood was caught by a zar זר, zar, it was taken, the
blood was taken out of the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
after, you know, and so on as opposed to a baal mum
בעל מום, baal mum, a baal mum בעל מום baal mum now
by the way I should say even if somehow it got in
the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and somebody scratched it or
whatever made it a baal mum בעל מום baal mum in the
Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash that's still not considered psulan bakodesh
פסולן בקודש psulan bakodesh because that's the type of a psul פסול,
psul, you know, and that is basically precedes it sort of, it's
not about it having been brought into the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש,
Beit HaMikdash, that was completely circumstantial. It's not a psul פסול psul
that was generated by the fact of something went wrong in the
rituals within the Beit HaMikdash בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay so baal
mum בעל מום baal mum actually you would not be chayav חייב.
chayav. So if somebody's makriv מקריב makriv a baal mum בעל מום
baal mum outside he is not chayav kares חייב כרת chayav kares
for shichutei chutz שחוטי חוץ shichutei chutz or ha'ala'as chutz העלאת חוץ.
ha'ala'as chutz. But if zarut זרות zarut has nothing to do with
it because zarut זרות zarut was hutra bebamah הותרה בבמה hutra bebamah
anyway right? So if I'm a zar זר zar meaning I can,
either I can't do the avodah עבודה avodah in the Beit HaMikdash
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, can I do it on my bamah במה
bamah in my?
Sure,
that's I mean that's part of the whole question about ha'ala'as chutz
העלאת חוץ ha'ala'as chutz because you already were paskened פסקנו paskened it
by shichutei chutz שחוטי חוץ shichutei chutz and so on. So you
know you're sort of saying is that ha'ala'as chutz העלאת חוץ ha'ala'as
chutz you also was nishchata נשחטה nishchata by a zar זר zar
or something like that. But actually shechitah שחיטה shechitah by a zar
זר zar is okay. So the actual act of ha'ala'ah העלאה ha'ala'ah
though, yes the whole thing here is talking about a zar זר,
zar, so that's not part of, that doesn't create a prior psul
פסול psul to raise this question. Okay hamaleh hikrivan bachutz chayav המעלה
והקריבן בחוץ חייב. hamaleh vehikrivan bachutz chayav. So psulan bakodesh פסולן בקודש
psulan bakodesh hikrivan bachutz chayav הקריבן בחוץ חייב. hikrivan bachutz chayav. Hamaleh
kezayit min ha'olah umin ha'imurin bachutz chayav המעלה כזית מן העולה ומן
האימורין בחוץ חייב. hamaleh kezayit min ha'olah umin ha'imurin bachutz chayav. Now
how much? So we've been assuming the amount is a kezayit כזית
kezayit although yesterday we discussed the issue about that it has to
be shalem שלם shalem which again based on Tosafot תוספות Tosafot just
meant that it has to be coming from something that is complete,
okay, not that the actual have to offer the complete thing which
is what Rashi רש"י Rashi made it sound like. But anyway but
let's say so now it says let's say you have a half
of a kezayit כזית kezayit from the meat of the olah עולה
olah and half from the imurin אימורין imurin they combine to a
whole kezayit כזית kezayit because both of them would be burnt. But
that obviously suggests that if it was like a half a kezayit
כזית kezayit from a shelamim שלמים shelamim and a half a kezayit
כזית kezayit of the meat of a shelamim שלמים shelamim and half
kezayit כזית kezayit of the imurin אימורין imurin they would not combine
because as is implicit in the Mishnah משנה Mishnah but hasn't been
said you're only chayav חייב chayav on— Doing העלאה ha'alah on those
things that based on the קרבן korban you're dealing with you would
do העלאה ha'alah in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, so therefore,
if you put the meat of a שלמים shlamim on the fire,
you would actually be exempt. Okay? So another way you could go
ahead and be מקריב makriv on your private במה. bamah. Just make
things into שלמים shlamims and then put the meat on the altar
and you're exempt, again probably over still on the לאו lav and
then you'd at least be over on the שחיטה. shchita. Anyway, תניא
רבנן, Tanya Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: אשר יעלה עולה או זבח, asher
ya'aleh ola o zavach, a person who offers an עולה olah or
a sacrifice. אין לי אלא עולה מנין לרבות אימורי אשם ואימורי חטאת
ואימורי קדשי קדשים ואימורי קדשים קלים. Ein li ela ola minayin l'rabos
imurei asham v'imurei chatas v'imurei kodshei kodashim v'imurei kodashim kalim. How do
you know the אימורים imurim of all the other sacrifices? Notice it
mentions אימורים imurim because you're not חייב chayav on the meat of
the other sacrifices, you're only חייב chayav on the אימורים imurim of
the other sacrifices. How do you know that's included in the איסור
issur of העלאה? ha'alah? So it says תלמוד לומר זבח, talmud lomar
zavach, so that's the whole point. עולה או זבח, ola o zavach,
it's not limited to an עולה. olah. But of course what's implicitly
being read into this is that the זבח zevach just like the
עולה, olah, which is the part that normally, an עולה olah is
paradigmatic that the whole thing is put up on the altar. So
when you're dealing with a זבח, zevach, it's only that part of
it that would normally go up on the altar. Only that you're
חייב chayav for, you're not חייב chayav for the part that wouldn't
go up on the altar. Okay. Now, מנין לרבות הקומץ והלבונה. minayin
l'rabos hakometz v'halivona. How about things that are not even meat? Okay?
How do you know to include the קומץ kometz which is normally
burnt on the fire, the handbreadth from the מנחה, mincha, and the
לבונה, levona, the frankincense, okay, that comes, you know, with the with
the what do you call it, you know, with the מנחה. mincha.
והקטרת v'haktoret and the קטרת ketores which is burnt daily, half in
the morning and half in the afternoon on the מזבח של זהב
mizbeach shel zahav in the, you know, the golden altar inside of
the היכל. heichal. ומנחת כהנים u'minchas kohanim and the מנחה mincha of
a כהן kohen which is fully burnt. ומנחת כהן משיח u'minchas kohen
mashiach and the מנחה mincha of a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol which
is daily brought and also fully burnt. והמנסך שלשת לוגין יין ושלשת
לוגין מים. v'hamenasach sheloshet lugin yayin v'sheloshet lugin mayim. So those are
things that are burnt, so that's just expanding the scope of the
types of sacrifices. But now this next line is a חידוש. chiddush.
והמנסך שלשת לוגין יין ושלשת לוגין מים, v'hamenasach sheloshet lugin yayin v'sheloshet
lugin mayim, that it's not even like putting on the fire, right?
It's a libation. So it's a type of העלאה, ha'alah, okay, but
it's ניסוך, nisuch, and you would pour wine on, three לוג, log,
you would do that, would be the smallest amount of wine you
would bring together with a קרבן, korban, or three לוג log of
water which you would do if it was water that was part
of the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchas Beis HaShoeivah. And by the way,
רש"י Rashi says by all of these, the same way you're not
חייב chayav if you שוחט shecht a חולין chullin animal, let's say
outside of your house, outside בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you just go
to your backyard, you take your cow or your sheep and you
don't sanctify it, you just שוחט shecht it to God. Okay? You're
not חייב. chayav. Again, it has to be something that is sanctified.
So here too, by the wine, by the מנחה, mincha, and by
the wine and even by the water, it has to be sanctified.
So the water...
Wait, so if I שוחט shecht my cow and I do everything
wrong but I don't say הרי זה להשם...
harei zeh l'hashem...
Right. I've made my מזבח, mizbeach, I שוחט shecht it, I put
everything, you know, I didn't put the parts that shouldn't go, I'm
not over on anything?
You might be over on פן תעלה עולותיך pen ta'aleh olotecha
again, but עולותיך olotecha is, you know, is הקדש. hekdesh.
I don't know the scope of פן תעלה עולותיך. pen ta'aleh olotecha.
I have to check that out. Like maybe is that maybe a
general איסור במה issur bamah whatever the context is, you know what
I mean? Not about the animal being sanctified. I don't know the
answer. Okay, so anyway, by the way, but if you look at
the מים, mayim, רש"י Rashi says ושלשת לוגין מים, v'sheloshet lugin mayim,
רש"י Rashi says בחג קאמר ובמקדשים לחג. be-chag kaamur u-mekudashim l'chag. That
it's only, again, it has to be ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'uy
l'pesach ohel moed. You have to be talking about on סוכות Sukkos
and water that's been sanctified for the for the actual, you know,
ניסוך המים בחג. nisuch hamayim be-chag. All right? So it has to
be again, we have to remember that context that the sanctity is
appropriate and it's ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. ra'uy l'pesach ohel moed. Anyway,
how do you know that? תלמוד לומר ואל פתח אהל מועד לא
יביאנו. Talmud lomar v'el pesach ohel moed lo yevienu. It was not
brought. כל הבא לפתח אהל מועד חייבין עליו בחוץ. Kol haba l'pesach
ohel moed chayavin alav bachutz. Okay, anything that would be brought. But
again, it's still limited to העלאה, ha'alah, right? It's still limited to
being placed on the altar, right? If you remember, like, the types
of עבודות avodas you're פטור pattur for: קבלת הדם, kabbalas hadam, you're
פטור pattur for, the act of קומץ komatz you're פטור pattur for.
It's still within the context of העלאה, ha'alah, just not limiting itself
to animals. But I should mention by the wine and the water,
it's also not limiting itself to the idea of being burnt. Okay,
but again, that's because that's what is done on the altar. Certain
things are burnt and other things there's libations. You know, it gets
back to my question about when we talk about putting it on
a rock, okay, would you have to burn it on the rock?
You know, or whatever. Anyway, so at least here, it sounds like,
you know, you gotta burn the things that are burnt and do
a libation for the things that are libations, but it's all העלאה,
ha'alah, it's all stuff that goes on the altar, just not limited
to animals. Okay, now, ואין לי אלא קדשים כשרים מנין לרבות פסולים.
v'ein li ela kodashim kesherim minayin l'rabos psulim. That's only if everything
is כשר. kosher. How do I know a certain category of
פסולים, psulim, which we see in the משנה mishna means not something
like a בעל מום, ba'al mum, but something that if it were
put on the מזבח, mizbeach, stays on the מזבח. mizbeach. כגון הלן
kegon halan that you שוחט shecht it and everything was כשר kosher
and then it became
נותר, nosar, the אימורים imurim became נותר. nosar. והיוצא, v'hayotzei, it was
taken out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. All this outside of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Right. Okay. It's still going through its
normal list. Okay, but you know, well, anyway,
והטמא v'hatamei Anyway, inside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, anyway, all of
these thoughts of פיגול, pigul, ושקיבלו פסולים וזרקו את דמו, veshekiblu p'sulim
vezarku es damo, or you had a זר zar involved in it,
והניתנים למטה שנתן למעלה והניתנים למעלה שנתן למטה, vehanitannim lemata shenassan lemala
vehanitannim lemala shenassan lemata, or that you know this blood was thrown
in the
wrong place, והניתנים בחוץ שנתן בפנים, vehanitannim bachutz shenassan bifnim, something that
goes on
the outer altar, the blood was put on the inner altar, והניתנים
בפנים שנתן בחוץ, vehanitannim bifnim shenassan bachutz, or the reverse, ופסח וחטאת
ששחטן בשלישי שלא לשמן, vepesach vechatas sheshachtan bashlishi shelo lishmon, a שחיטה
שלא לשמו, shechita shelo lishmo,
all these types of things that the פסול psul was that it
was a ritual associated with the עבודה avoda in the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, and those are the types of things that if you
put it on the altar stays on the altar. So how do
you know that those things if you put on an outer במה,
bama, on a במה, bama, that you're חייב chayav for even though
it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד? ra'uy lepesach ohel moed? תלמוד לומר,
talmud lomar, לא יביאנו לעשות. lo yeviennu la'asos. So כל המתקבל בפתח
אהל מועד חייבין עליו בחוץ. kol hamiskabel bepesach ohel moed chayavin alav
bachutz.
So לא יביאנו lo yeviennu it just mean cannot be brought, and
these things cannot be brought, I mean they were already sort of
brought into פתח אהל מועד, pesach ohel moed, but they can't be
brought because they are not acceptable, they're not allowed to be on
the altar. But by emphasizing the word לעשות, la'asos,
it means that they can be done on the altar. So even
though to some degree these cannot be brought to the altar, if
they were put on the altar, they are allowed to be done
on the altar. And רש"י Rashi even points out, it's not just
you don't do anything, let's say these things were left on top
of the altar or whatever on the ramp, but not on the
fire, what would you do with them? You'd actually put them on
the fire. It's not just you let the status quo, once they're
on the altar you actually actively offer them. Okay, or if they're
burning on the fire, you turn them over. So these are still
in the category of לעשות, la'asos, even though they're not in the
category of what's the לשון הפסוק leshon hapassuk about פתח אהל מועד
לא יביאנו. pesach ohel moed lo yeviennu. You're still not allowed to
bring them as it were to פתח אהל מועד, pesach ohel moed,
they're in פתח אהל מועד, pesach ohel moed, but you're not allowed
to bring them closer, but if you did, they're still in the
category of לעשות la'asos and therefore you are going to be חייב
chayav if you do them outside.
But in terms of my actual thought though, like I mean I
can use the same קרבן korban that would, you know, something went
wrong in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but I don't have to
be thinking on my במה, bama, oh I'm going to eat this
is a שלמים shlamim which I'm going to eat in the next
two days or whatever it is, I
don't have to be thinking that. Well no, because that's what we
just said, that even if you had all those פסולים. psulim.
No, no meaning like I don't have to have any specific thought
other than this is my קרבן להשם, korban lashem, right? סתמן לשמו
חייב.
staman lishmo
chayav.
Okay. המעלה כזית מן העולה, hama'aleh kezayis min ha'olah, now we get
to what do you offer up? So the implicit point of the
משנה mishna is that you're or made explicit in the ברייתא brayta
we started with, is that you're only חייב chayav a כזית. kezayis.
B, you're only חייב chayav for the type of thing you would
put on the מזבח mizbeach in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay,
so that is so that's not just ראוי לפתח אהל מועד ra'uy
lepesach ohel moed in terms of the whole animal, but that's like
the עבודה, avoda, the thing you're doing is the thing you would
do in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so it would only
be it would be אימורים emurim and the meat from an עולה
olah and the אימורים emurim for other קרבנות. korbanos. So עולה ואימוריה
אין, olah ve'emureha in, שלמים ואימוריהם לא. shlamim ve'emureihem lo. Right, as
clear as in the משנה, mishna, you're חייב chayav for the עולה
olah and the אימורים, emurim, but for the שלמים shlamim you're not
חייב chayav for the half a כזית kezayis of meat combined with
half כזית kezayis of אימורים emurim because you're not חייב chayav for
the meat of a שלמים. shlamim. תנינא להא דתנו רבנן, tanina lehad
detanu rabbanan, we taught in our משנה mishna and that which was
taught in the
ברייתא, brayta, עולה ואימוריה מצטרפין לכזית להעלותן בחוץ. olah ve'emureha mitztarfin lekezayis
leha'alosam bachutz. So an עולה olah and its אימורים emurim since both
of those are burnt, the meat and the אימורים, emurim, so they
make a full כזית kezayis which you're חייב chayav for if you
burn it outside
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash ולחייב עליהן משום פיגול נותר וטמא, ulechayev
aleihen mishum pigul notar vetamei, and to be חייב chayav for פיגול
נותר וטמא. pigul notar vetamei. Presumably what that means is is that
if the עולה olah was פיגול pigul and you ate a half
a כזית kezayis of the meat and a half a כזית kezayis
of the אימורים, emurim, or it was נותר notar and you ate
a half a כזית kezayis of each, or it was טמא tamei
and you were טמא tamei excuse me because we're all talking about
these three are normally about the חיוב כרת, chiyuv kares, you were
טמא tamei and you ate a half a כזית kezayis of each,
then you're חייב chayav because it's all considered essentially the same category.
Okay, good. That's as opposed to a שלמים shlamim you're not חייב
chayav because it's not stuff that's burnt on the מזבח. mizbeach. So
now the גמרא gemara says like this: one minute. בשלמא העלאת עולה
דכליל אין שלמים לא. bishlama ha'alos olah dekalil in shlamim lo. I
get העלאה, ha'alos, okay, that makes sense. You're not חייב chayav on
the meat of a שלמים shlamim combined with אימורים emurim because you're
not חייב chayav for the meat of a שלמים shlamim for העלאה
ha'alos because the meat isn't what's put on the מזבח. mizbeach. אלא
פיגול ונותר וטמא מאי טעמא? ella pigul venotar vetamei mai ta'ama? One
minute though, by פיגול נותר וטמא pigul notar vetamei you know if
the שלמים shlamim is פיגול pigul then the meat and the אימורים
emurim are פיגול, pigul, if it's נותר notar the meat and the
אימורים emurim are נותר. notar. So why aren't you חייב chayav for
eating a half a כזית kezayis of each? Right? You got it?
I mean that makes a lot of sense. If the חיוב chiyuv
is burning on the fire העלאה ha'alos then by a שלמים shlamim
it's only by the אימורים emurim and not by the meat. But
when we get to פיגול נותר וטמא pigul notar vetamei and we're
talking about an איסור issur of eating and an איסור issur that
applies to the entire קרבן korban then you should be able to
combine a half of a כזית kezayis of each.
I'm sorry, wait, where were we saying in our משנה? mishna?
Our משנה mishna doesn't talk... no, but the ברייתא, brayta, עולה ואימוריה
מצטרפין לכזית ולחייב עליהן משום פיגול נותר וטמא. olah ve'emureha mitztarfin lekezayis
ulechayev aleihen mishum pigul notar vetamei. Oh, I guess the implication here
is עולה ואימוריה olah ve'emureha as implicitly not שלמים ואימוריהם. shlamim ve'emureihem.
Okay, right, it wasn't... It wasn't said explicitly, it was implicit. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says why, so we get why by
the עולה, Ola, it's only the meat of the עולה Ola with
the אימורים emurim and not by שלמים. Shelamim. By שלמים Shelamim you're
not חייב chayav on the meat of the עולה, Ola, but why
do you not combine these when it comes to these other things
of פיגול, pigul, נותר, nosar, and טמא? tamei? והתנן v'hasnan one minute,
we even taught in a משנה, Mishna, כל הפיגולין מצטרפין וכל הנותרין
מצטרפין, kol hapigulin mitztarfin v'chol hanosarin mitztarfin, that פיגול pigul and נותר
nosar combine. Okay,
I mean, it could even be half a כזית kezayis of עולה
פיגול Ola pigul and half a כזית kezayis of שלמים פיגול Shelamim
pigul or half a כזית kezayis of שלמים Shelamim of the meat
and half a כזית kezayis of שלמים Shelamim of the אימורין. emurin.
And the same is true by נותר. nosar. So how do you
make sense of this? Why does the first ברייתא Braisa say you
don't combine פיגול pigul and נותר nosar and this says you do?
קשיא פיגול אפיגול קשיא נותר אנותר. Kashya pigul apigul kashya nosar anosar.
So פיגול אפיגול לא קשיא, pigul apigul lo kashya, כאן בפיגול כאן
במחשבת פיגול. kan b'pigul kan b'machsheves pigul. This is a nice answer.
So the point is like this. What does it mean when we
say it combines? Does it mean I already made the thing פיגול
pigul because as I was שוחט shachting it I was thinking I'm
going to בזרוק bizrok the דם dam חוץ לזמנו? chutz l'zmano? In
that case, the whole thing is פיגול, pigul, and then if I
eat half a כזית kezayis of meat of the שלמים Shelamim and
half a כזית kezayis of the אימורין, emurin, everything here is פיגול,
pigul, I'm חייב, chayav, I ate a full כזית kezayis of פיגול.
pigul. That's one case, that's when it is מצטרף. mitztaref. The ברייתא
Braisa that implies that it's not מצטרף mitztaref is the following: I'm
שוחט shachting it and I am planning on eating half a כזית
kezayis of the שלמים Shelamim tomorrow, or whatever in three days, and
being מעלה ma'aleh half a כזית kezayis of the
אימורין emurin in three days. That doesn't combine because those are two
completely separate things,
אכילת אדם achilas adam and אכילת מזבח. achilas mizbeiach. But let's say
it were an עולה, Ola, and I שוחט shachted the עולה Ola
and I said I am going to burn tomorrow half a כזית
kezayis of the meat and half a כזית kezayis of the אימורין.
emurin. I would be חייב chayav because I had a מחשבה machshava
about a כזית kezayis of אכילת מזבח. achilas mizbeiach. So that makes
a lot of sense, and that's exactly parallel to the issue of
being חייב chayav for העלאת חוץ. haalos chutz. Okay, so by a
thought of פיגול pigul that it's only עולה Ola and אימורין emurin
combine whereas opposed to שלמים Shelamim and אימורין, emurin, that makes sense
because by a thought of פיגול, pigul, עולה Ola and אימורין emurin
you're doing the same thing with them.
Since that's not teaching you a הלכה halacha of שחוטי חוץ, shchutei
chutz, it's teaching you a הלכה halacha of just פיגול pigul essentially.
Yeah, well this is a ברייתא Braisa says עולה Ola and אימורין
emurin are מצטרף mitztaref for העלאה, haala, העלאת חוץ, haalos chutz, because
they both are on the מזבח, mizbeiach, and for מחשבת פיגול machsheves
pigul because they're both on the מזבח. mizbeiach. It's like almost the
exact same point. Since they're both on the מזבח mizbeiach they מצטרף
mitztaref for מחשבת פיגול, machsheves pigul, they מצטרף mitztaref for העלאת חוץ,
haalos chutz, whereas by a שלמים Shelamim since they're not both on
the מזבח mizbeiach there's no way they combine for העלאת חוץ haalos
chutz and there's no way they combine for מחשבת פיגול. machsheves pigul.
That's very elegant. Once the thing is פיגול pigul and you eat
it, they do combine. But the problem is the נותר. nosar. Okay,
because נותר nosar doesn't fit the same way, right? How is it
that we suggest that נותר nosar applies to the עולה Ola and
the אימורין emurin in a way it doesn't apply to the שלמים
Shelamim and the אימורין? emurin? That's hard to understand. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, נותר אנותר לא קשיא. nosar anosar lo kashya. Here's
how we're going to solve the נותר nosar issue.
What does it mean that by נותר nosar שלמים Shelamim and the
אימורין emurin do not combine? כאן בנותר. kan b'nosar. So when they
do combine is, yeah, the whole animal is נותר nosar and you
ate half a כזית kezayis of the שלמים Shelamim and half a
כזית kezayis of its אימורין. emurin. Then they combine, you ate a
כזית kezayis of נותר nosar meat, doesn't matter whether it's the meat
or the אימורין. emurin. Okay. So what does it mean when they
don't combine? כאן בשניתותרו עד שלא נזרק הדם. kan b'shenisosru ad shelo
nizrak hadam. It's when it was left over before the blood was
thrown. How do you leave it over before the blood is thrown?
נותר nosar is only after the blood is thrown. So what it
means is no, here's what happened. You שוחט shachted this animal, this
עולה Ola let's say. And something happened to the עולה Ola and
the אימורין, emurin, somebody accidentally dumped them, threw them in the incinerator,
there's nothing left of them. You haven't thrown the blood yet.
Wait, so the blood is left but
the rest of the animal's not. And now but what was left
over was half a כזית kezayis of the meat and half a
כזית kezayis of the
אימורין emurin for your whole קרבן. korban. Now we're going to go
like ורבי יהושע ומני רבי יהושע היא דתניא רבי יהושע אומר כל
הזבחים שבתורה
שנשתייר בהן כזית בשר או כזית חלב ואו כזית חלב זורק את
הדם. v'Rabbi Yehoshua u'manni Rabbi Yehoshua hi d'tanya Rabbi Yehoshua omer kol
hazvachim shebatorah shenishtayir bahen kezayis basar o kezayis chelev v'o kezayis chelev
zorek es hadam. Okay, that if you have all of the meat
and the אימורין emurin were lost, he says, since it says ועשית
עולותיך הבשר והדם v'asisah olosyecha habasar v'hadam whatever, I think that's where
you learn it from, anyway, or וזרק הכהן את הדם והקטיר את
החלב המזבחה v'zarak hakohen es hadam v'hiktir es hachelev hamizbeacha anyway, that
he understands that you don't do, even though the כשרות kashrus of
the whole קרבנות korbanos is only about the blood, at least he
says let's not forget the meat of the קרבן korban which is
a pretty important emphasis, and the אימורין. emurin. And if the blood
is not going to allow, if there's no meat left and it's
not going to allow the meat to be eaten, and there's no
אימורין emurin left and it's not going to allow אימורין emurin to
be burnt on the מזבח, mizbeiach, you would not be זורק את
הדם. zorek es hadam. You would only be זורק את הדם zorek
es hadam if there is either a כזית kezayis of meat to
be eaten or a כזית kezayis of חלב chelev to be burnt.
Okay.
So that should be
או כזית חלב o kezayis chelev then זורק את הדם.
zorek es hadam. Right. חצי זית בשר וחצי זית חלב, chatzi zayis
basar vechatzi zayis chelev, אינו זורק את הדם. eino zorek es hadam.
However, if it was this שלמים shlamim in the scenario we gave
and a half of a כזית kezayis of meat, you're not זורק
את הדם zorek es hadam because you don't have a כזית's kezayis
worth of meat to do anything with. But באולה, be'olah, חצי זית
בשר chatzi zayis basar וחצי זית חלב, vechatzi zayis chelev, זורק את
הדם, zorek es hadam, מפני שכולו כליל. mipnei shekulo kalil. But by
an עולה olah you would be זורק את הדם zorek es hadam
because it's all burnt up. So now it is exactly parallel. The
ברייתא baraisa that says that by עולה olah only an עולה olah
and אימורים eimurim combine are by three categories where we're talking about,
you know, burning it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, so there's העלאת
חוץ, ha'alas chutz, they combine. A thought of פיגול, piggul, because both
their thoughts combine because it's both about putting on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
And if those are if only a half a כזית kezayis of
the בשר basar and a half a כזית kezayis of אימורים eimurim
the only thing left over before you get to זריקת הדם, zrikas
hadam, then by an עולה olah you're allowed to be זורק את
הדם. zorek es hadam. Whereas by a שלמים, shlamim, you're not חייב
chayav for half a כזית kezayis of each by העלאה ha'ala because
you don't burn the meat, so that's not you're not you don't
burn it in the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, you're not חייב בחוץ.
chayav bechutz. You're not חייב chayav for מחשבת פיגול machsheves piggul because
they're two different acts, eating it and burning it. And you're not
allowed to be זורק את הדם zorek es hadam if you have
a כזית kezayis left of each, because there's not enough of a
full כזית, kezayis, half a כזית kezayis of each, because there's not
a full כזית kezayis that you can do something together with. Now
that doesn't exactly fit the language of the ברייתא baraisa which I'll
get back to, but let's just finish reading this. Okay.
ומנחה אפילו כולה קיימת לא יזרוק. umincha afilu kula kayemes lo yizrok.
By a מנחה mincha even if it's all there, don't throw the
blood. So the גמרא gemara says מנחה מאי עבידתיה, mincha mai avidethei,
since when does a מנחה mincha have blood? So אמר רב פפא,
amar Rav Pappa, מנחת נסכים הבאה עם הזבח. minchas nesachim haba'ah im
hazevach. No, no, it means if you have the מנחה mincha that
came with the sacrifice and you lost all the meat of the
sacrifice and all the אימורים, eimurim, don't say, oh, I'll still be
זורק את הדם zorek es hadam because it'll let me eat the
מנחה. mincha. No, even though there's something left over to be doing
something with, the eating of the מנחה, mincha, that's not the actual
sacrifice itself. So if the blood is being put on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, it has to still be connected to some of the animal
that you're doing something with. Okay? It still has to be a
מתיר matir for the meat of the animal, either to eat it
or to burn it. Now the only hanging question with this, it's
a beautiful, it's an elegant answer because now all the ways the
עולה olah combines are things that have to do with burning on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. The only problem is that it sort of said
that the עולה olah and the אימורים eimurim are מצטרפים, mitztarfim, actually,
you know, this isn't a problem because it said אימור ואימור מצטרפין
לכזית, eimur ve'eimur mitztarfin lechezayis, no, it says yes, it says מצטרפין
ולחייב עליהם משום פיגול נותר וטמא. mitztarfin ulechayev aleihem mishum piggul nosar
vetamei. So the problem was what does it mean that לחייב עליהם
משום נותר? lechayev aleihem mishum nosar? What we said is that when
it applies only an עולה olah is מצטרף, mitztaref, then it means
it allows you to throw the blood if that's what's left over,
right? It's not that you're חייב chayav on it. So what רש״י
Rashi says is the following. What רש״י Rashi says is,
let's say you went ahead and you had a half of a
כזית kezayis of each left over and you threw the blood. Okay?
You were throwing it and then this stuff became טמא tamei or
the stuff became נותר nosar and then you ate it. Okay? So
after you threw the blood on a half a כזית kezayis of
each. So by an עולה olah since the throwing of the blood
was allowed, so then it brought that meat to the next status,
and then the meat can become נותר nosar and then you're חייב
chayav on the meat. Whereas by a שלמים, shlamim, since the throwing
of the blood wasn't allowed, even if you're יוצא בדיעבד yotze bidi'avad
if you throw the blood, which might actually be the case even
according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, but since you weren't supposed to
do it and it wasn't really connected anymore to the meat, it
didn't change the status of the meat. So now, although it's a
little ironic, but now because the blood wasn't meaningful for the meat,
you're not going to be חייב chayav on the meat if it
got left over and it became נותר. nosar. Okay? So the principle
is when are you allowed to throw the blood if it's a
half a כזית kezayis of each, but a נפקא מינה nafka mina
it is if you're allowed to throw the blood it changes the
status of the meat so that you could be חייב chayav on
it if something goes wrong.
We were saying before with those kind of things that you shouldn't
have done or whatever then you are חייב. chayav. Like didn't we
say that
before if you, you know, פסולי בקודש, psulei bakodesh, the פיגול piggul
and נותר nosar and טמא. tamei. Yeah, yeah.
We were saying before, yeah, if you did it
then you can put it on the מזבח.
mizbe'ach. Probably, but we're not talking about העלאה ha'ala when I just
talked about חייב. chayav. I'm talking about everything now I was bracketing
the העלאה, ha'ala, not of the העלאה. ha'ala. You're totally in the
בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, you have a half a כזית kezayis of
each left over, you throw the blood, and now these חצי כזיתים
chatzi kezaysim become נותר nosar or you become טמא tamei and you
eat it. Are you חייב chayav on eating it? Okay. משנה. mishnah.
Okay, since a lot of this משנה mishnah was already anticipated by
the ברייתא baraisa we read. הקומץ והלבונה והקטורת ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן
משיח, hakometz vehalevonah vehaketores uminchas kohanim uminchas kohen mashiach,
so all these things that are burnt on the fire that are
not animals. מנחה, mincha,
you know, the hand breadth, and the לבונה, levonah, the frankincense that
comes with the מנחה, mincha, and the קטורת ketores that's burnt on
the inner מזבח, mizbe'ach, and the מנחות minchos of כהנים kohanim that
are totally burnt, משיח, mashiach, ומנחת נסכים, uminchas nesachim, and the מנחה
mincha that comes with the קרבן korban that that is totally burnt
a free-will קרבן korban שהקריב מאחת מהן כזית בחוץ חייב. shehikriv me'achas
meihen kezayis bechutz chayav. So now we're going to back now we're
going to focus on the שיעור. shiur. We implicitly mentioned before a
כזית kezayis when we talked about the meat, and here again we're
talking about a כזית, kezayis, although before even though there wasn't a
debate about the כזית kezayis of the meat, here there is going
to be a debate about the כזית. kezayis. רבי אליעזר פוטר עד
שיקריב. Rabbi Eliezer poter ad sheyakriv. עד שיקריב את כולן. ad sheyakriv
es kulan. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says no you're exempt until you've
offered up the entire קומץ kometz you're exempt until you offer up
the entire מנחה. mincha. Now why is this? Let's see Michael, here's
a little pop quiz. Can you think why this would be different
than the meat? Why would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agree that by
the meat you're only you're חייב chayav as soon as you do
a כזית? kezayis?
Does it say מנחת כהנים שתהיה כליל תקטיר? minchas kohanim shetehei kalil
taktir?
But okay let's just focus contrast it to the קומץ. kometz. Why
by the meat are you חייב chayav as soon as you do
a כזית kezayis but by the קומץ kometz of a מנחה mincha
you're only חייב chayav if you do the whole קומץ kometz not
just a כזית? kezayis?
Because the whole קומץ kometz is supposed to go on the מזבח
mizbeach whereas like all the meat is you know some of the
well all the meat is supposed to go on the מזבח mizbeach
all the meat of the עולה olah of an עולה. olah. So
you're close here's the difference. The קומץ kometz is the מתיר. matir.
So there the תורה Torah doesn't just it's not just a מצוה
mitzvah you're supposed to put it all on there its function is
only meaningful it only does its function when it's the full קומץ
kometz right? These other things don't have a מתיר matir so they're
seen as being מתיר matir themselves. So by these types of things
it's seen as since there's not something else that is מתיר matir
them they are the מתיר. matir. So then he says then we're
going to focus on
and by מתיר matir you mean specifically that it what?
It validates the קרבן. korban. Okay. Now some of that is not
exactly the same point because like you know by a מנחת כהן
minchas kohen if you just put half if you did half of
it on the מזבח mizbeach was he not יוצא yotzei at all?
You know maybe that's true like again you know it's an interesting
question. By the קטורת ketores if you don't have so the גאנצע
gantze could be yeah you're not יוצא. yotzei. It's like there's this
is the מתיר matir and it has to be the full amount.
So so that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is saying. If you
already made it a valid קרבן korban or whatever we're dealing with
something that's not about validating the קרבן korban just about an act
of putting it on the altar okay some type of an act
of putting it on the altar putting a כזית kezayis is a
meaningful act. Okay and yes in the תורה Torah you'd have a
מצוה mitzvah to do it all but for every כזית kezayis that
you burnt you're still doing a meaningful act. Or here's another way
to look at it. Let's say a זר zar were to offer
up on the מזבח mizbeach in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash right
a כזית kezayis of the עולה. olah. He'd be presumably חייב chayav
even though he didn't do the מצוה mitzvah oh but all the
meat is supposed to go up. Okay because there every כזית kezayis
is a meaningful act. But here the only meaningful act is it's
a מתיר matir and you're supposed to do the whole thing to
make it a valid קרבן. korban. So the only meaningful act is
the whole thing. So that's a nice distinction. Okay by the meat
I agree with you but here פוטר עד שיקריב את כולן. poter
ad sheyakriv es kulan. You have to do the entire amount. Okay
וכולן שהקריב בפנים ושייר מהם כזית והקריבן בחוץ חייב. vechulan shehikriv bifnim
veshayar mehem kezayis vehikrivan bechutz chayav. Now however all these things if
you if even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would agree that if you
did the entire מנחת כהן minchas kohen inside and you left over
a כזית kezayis or all of the קומץ kometz inside and you
left over a כזית kezayis and you did the כזית kezayis outside
you're חייב. chayav. Why?
Because obviously the remaining כזית kezayis now had you done it inside
would have been meaningful that was the only thing that was left
that was the finishing of the whole amount. Okay so he says
look you have to do something that basically functions as a מתיר.
matir. So if you're doing it all outside you've got to do
the whole amount. If you're doing you know when you're dealing with
a מתיר matir it has to function as a מתיר. matir. If
you if you did most of it inside then if you do
the remainder outside and it's at least a כזית kezayis you're also
going to be חייב.
chayav. So even though you weren't יוצא yotzei because you left some
some of it off over right
but this is the amount that's ראוי לפתח אהל מועד rauy lepesach
ohel moed as it were. This is the amount that would validate
the קרבן korban inside. Okay וכולן שחסרו כל שהוא והקריבן בחוץ פטור.
vechulan shechasru kol shehu vehikrivan bechutz patur. All of these that were
a little bit lacking okay like the same way like if you
do a מנחה mincha for example and you don't have the whole
all of the שיריים shirayim there okay then it's then it's not
good. So the same way here too if it wasn't all
present okay you're going to be פטור patur because that would not
have been valid as an הקרבה hakrava of the קומץ kometz had
you done this inside.
Okay so where were we?
Okay right. Okay okay or if the קומץ kometz wasn't whole or
whatever. Okay פטור. patur.
Meaning this is different than leaving it over because here we've just
it's gone right?
Either the שיריים shirayim aren't there or correct or like you know
or that some of the actual קומץ kometz itself got destroyed. It
just as not that just you haven't got it. So in that
case since the קרבן korban would not be valid inside it's not
valid out you're not חייב chayav outside. המעלה קדשים ואימורים בחוץ חייב.
hama'aleh kodashim ve'imurim bechutz chayav. Now that's weird. Yeah right. So so
the basic so if you look at רש״י Rashi I mean it's
not look
רש״י Rashi המעלה קדשים ואימוריהם hama'aleh kodashim ve'imureihem שהקריב הבשר והאימורים מחוברים
בו חייב משום אימורים shehikriv habasar veha'imurim mechubarim bo chayav mishum imurim
even if it's not an עולה olah but the question's like what's
the חידוש? chiddush? Like why would I think the extra meat would
be different? We've already said you're not you don't combine a half
of a כזית kezayis of each. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to say no you have a full כזית kezayis of אימורים imurim
but it's attached to the meat and don't think that the meat
is like a חציצה chatzitza that if you bring it on your
במה bamah outside you shouldn't be חייב chayav because there was the
other meat was like surrounding the אימורים. imurim. I mean if you
imagine let's say the אימורים imurim were inside of the meat. So
I didn't somebody will say I didn't put the אימורים imurim directly
on the
fire. Okay, you've got to go go. תנו רבנן. tano rabanan. המקטיר
כזית בחוץ חייב. hamaktir kezayis bachutz chayiv. חצי פרס בפנים פטור. chatzi
pras bifnim patur. So if you bring a כזית kezayis outside you're
חייב. chayiv. Let's say it's half of the amount, okay,
חצי פרס בפנים פטור. chatzi pras bifnim patur. If it's half of
the amount, so which
is... as רש״י Rashi says we don't literally mean half of a
פרס, pras, the point is it's a כזית, kezayis, okay, but it's
less than the full amount. So if you do it inside you're
פטור. patur. So what do you mean if you do it inside
you're פטור? patur? You should say if you do it inside you're
not יוצא, yotze, you're חיוב. chiyuv. We're talking here about the קטורת,
ketores, okay? So קטורת ketores was פרס, pras, half of the amount
in the morning and half of the amount in the afternoon. And
you went ahead and in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash you brought
less than the full amount, okay? So what does he mean פטור?
patur? It should say... so the גמרא Gemara says, קא סלקא דעתך
מאי פטור פטור זר. kasalka daatach mai patur patur zar. So presumably
what we mean is if a non-כהן kohen did, right, did it
he is פטור. patur. So that would actually mean that what? That
in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash this is that you are exempt
unless you do the full... you're not יוצא yotze unless you do
the full amount, and therefore anything less than a full amount a
non-כהן kohen is exempt for. Okay, so this is the basic idea
that sort of seems to be reflecting רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer position,
that you need the full amount. So since you need the full
amount to be יוצא yotze in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a
זר zar is exempt if it's less than the full amount. But
then the גמרא Gemara says, then why are you חייב chayiv for
a כזית kezayis outside? If the full amount that you need to
make a non-כהן kohen חייב chayiv and not a כזית, kezayis, then
you should need the full amount to be meaningful outside as well.
We go with the full מתיר. mattir. So what's the split? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמאי הקטרה היא? amai haktara hi? Why is
a זר zar exempt if if the first part of this ברייתא
braisa said that you're חייב chayiv by a כזית kezayis outside, then
a זר zar should be חייב chayiv *chayiv* for a כזית kezayis
inside. So אמר רבי זירא אמר רב חסדא אמר רבי ירמיה בר
אבא אמר רב מאי פטור פטור ציבור. amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav
Chisda amar Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba amar Rav mai patur patur tzibur.
So that's a pretty interesting read. פטור Patur means you're not יוצא,
yotze, okay, it doesn't really mean you're exempt. Okay, so now what
we have is a... excuse me, I'm sorry, I misread that. Means
you you you discharge your obligation. פטור Patur actually means you were
יוצא. yotze. All right, and now it's a very strange read, okay,
you know, it's almost like saying don't say פטור, patur, read יצא.
yatza. But that's what we're saying now is that if you do
it a כזית kezayis inside you are יוצא. yotze. So now we're
saying something strange and there's a תוספות Tosafos that tries to figure
this out. Because the question is what is the position of the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that disagrees with רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer and
says that you're חייב chayiv outside even if it's not the whole
קומץ, kometz, even if it's only a כזית kezayis of the קומץ?
kometz? Or you're חייב chayiv outside even if it's not the full
amount of the קטורת ketores or the whole, you know, handbreadth or
whatever it is, it's only a כזית kezayis of the קטורת. ketores.
There's two ways of understanding him. He could most logically he would
say to רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, listen, I agree with you, I
agree that you're not יוצא yotze in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash,
it's not doesn't function as a מתיר mattir unless you do the
full amount. Nevertheless, I say that if it's a כזית kezayis it's
meaningful enough to be חייב chayiv outside even though it doesn't operate
the way it's supposed to inside unless it's the full amount. That's
the simple thing to say. And as תוספות Tosafos points out, you
know, we would certainly say that by something like the קומץ kometz
of the מנחה. mincha. Because by a קומץ kometz of a מנחה
mincha nobody disagrees
that
anything... if you do less than the קומץ, kometz, you're יוצא. yotze.
Everybody agrees you need the full קומץ kometz on the inside. And
nevertheless the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says that you're חייב chayiv for
a כזית kezayis. outside. So even though it's not... so for רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer says it has to be the whole מתיר, mattir,
you know, it has to function correctly, and the חכמים Chachamim would
say it doesn't have to function correctly just has to be a
כזית. kezayis Fine. But for some reason when the גמרא Gemara gets
to the קטורת ketores and תוספות Tosafos discusses why this would be,
but for some reason when the גמרא Gemara gets to the קטורת
ketores it shifts gears. And the גמרא Gemara understands that by the
קטורת, ketores, when the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says you're חייב chayiv
for a כזית kezayis outside, that would reflect the idea that they
would say that by the קטורת ketores a כזית kezayis inside would
suffice. That even though we normally do a larger amount, since the
Torah never says exactly how much you do by the קטורת ketores
inside, we're not talking about יום כיפור Yom Kippur where it says
מלא חפניו, mlo chofnav, we're talking about the daily קטורת, ketores, since
the Torah never says how much, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would
say that the same way you're חייב chayiv for a כזית kezayis
outside, you're יוצא yotze if you do a כזית kezayis inside. Again,
not clear why he doesn't say that by a מנחה. mincha. By
a מנחה mincha you need to do the full קומץ kometz inside
but you're חייב chayiv even for a כזית kezayis outside, but for
the קטורת ketores it's understanding that if you're חייב chayiv for a
כזית kezayis outside you're יוצא yotze for a כזית kezayis inside. Okay,
so now that's how the גמרא Gemara has just read this. So
by re-reading פטור patur to mean פטור ציבור, patur tzibur, not פטור
זר, patur zar, we said you're חייב chayav for a כזית kezayis
outside and if you did just a כזית kezayis. inside the ציבור
tzibur discharged its obligation. Okay, so now that's a pretty radical idea
that you're יוצא yotze for in the קטורת ketores inside even if
it's... It's not the standard amount, the פרס, pras, even if it's
only a כזית. kezayis? So let's take a look where the גמרא
Gemara goes with this. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, אי קשיא
לי הא קשיא לי. ee kashya li ha kashya li. You know
what? If I've got a problem, this is my problem. Not that
language of פטור, patur, here's my problem. הא דאמר רב Hadamar Rav
עלה, ala, what רב Rav said, בהא אפילו רבי אליעזר מודה. beha
afilu Rabbi Eliezer modeh. That on this issue that, you know, even
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would agree. Hold on, let me just check
רש"י. Rashi.
Yeah, this idea that the ציבור tzibur fulfills its obligation, even רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, if we're reading פטור patur as פטור ציבור, patur
tzibur, the ציבור tzibur fulfills its obligation, even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
would agree. Now that's bizarre. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you need
the full amount. So how could he say the ציבור tzibur fulfills
its obligation with just a כזית? kezayis Okay. דהא רבי אליעזר לאו
הקטרה היא קאמר. Deha Rabbi Eliezer lav haktara hi ka’amar. So that
doesn't make sense, because רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's one thing to
say for the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, if you're חייב chayav for
כזית kezayis outside, then you're יוצא yotzei for כזית kezayis inside. But
for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, he says that you only need, you
need the full amount outside. So how could he say you're יוצא
yotzei for כזית kezayis inside? That makes absolute no sense. So if
the thing when it says that פטור patur means פטור ציבור patur
tzibur that you're יוצא yotzei for כזית kezayis. inside, there's no way
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer could say that because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
requires the full amount outside. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא דאמר
רבי אליעזר לאו הקטרה היא קאמר. veha d’amar Rabbi Eliezer lav haktara
hi ka’amar. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that's not considered a הקטרה.
haktara. אמר רבה. Amar Raba. רבה. Raba. Okay, let's get this straight.
בהקטרה דהיכל דכולי עלמא לא פליגי. behaktara deheichal d’chulei alma lo peligi.
When you're talking about the הקטרה haktara that was done in the
עזרה, Azarah, in the היכל, Heichal, you know, in the קודש, Kodesh,
not the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, the normal one that was done
twice a day, everybody agrees that you're יוצא yotzei with a כזית.
kezayis. Again, radical stuff. Why? Because even though the חכמים Chachamim told
us what the שיעור shiur was, a פרס pras in the morning,
פרס pras in the afternoon, it's not in the תורה. Torah. And
מדיאורייתא m’de’oraisa you're יוצא yotzei with a כזית. kezayis Okay, so everybody
would agree with the הקטרה, haktara, the twice a week, the twice
a day הקטרה haktara that was done in the היכל, Heichal, that
you're יוצא yotzei with a כזית kezayis. and therefore everybody would agree
that you're חייב בחוץ chayav bachutz in a כזית. kezayis So that's
not what was being discussed in the משנה Mishnah because everybody would
say you're חייב בחוץ chayav bachutz כזית kezayis. because you're יוצא yotzei
inside with a
כזית. kezayis כי פליגי בהקטרה דפנים. Ki peligi behaktara d’fnim. When you're
talking about the הקטרה haktara that was done לפני ולפנים lifnai v’lifnim
in the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And
there it says מלא חפניו. melo chofnav. Okay, דמר סבר מלא חפניו
דווקא. demar savar melo chofnav davka. That's where רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says it has to be, it literally has to be the fill
of your hands and therefore only then are you יוצא yotzei inside
and only then, imagine that on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, somebody's doing
a special עבודה avodah on their private במה, bamah, only then are
you יוצא yotzei inside with the full amount and only with the
full amount are you חייב chayav outside.
ומר סבר מלא חפניו לאו דווקא. U’mar savar melo chofnav lav davka.
No, you don't need, even a כזית kezayis you'd be יוצא yotzei
inside on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and therefore you're חייב chayav outside.
So of course that's pretty radical, radical enough to tell us every
day on יום כיפור Yom Kippur also doesn't literally have to be
מלא חפניו? melo chofnav? So אביי Abaye immediately rejects this. אמר ליה
אביי, Amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said back to this,
והא כי כתיבה חוקה בהקטרה דפנים הוא דכתיבה. veha ki ksiva chukka
behaktara d’fnim hu d’chsiva. What do you mean? The תורה Torah says
when it says that it's a חוק chok by יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, okay, והייתה זאת לכם לחקת עולם, v’hayesa zos lachem l’chukas olam,
it's the emphasis is the הקטרה haktara inside the מקדש, Mikdash, inside
the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. So clearly that requires a literal מלא
חפניו. melo chofnav. So if again, if we're assuming that when it
comes to the קטורת ktores for whatever reason as contrasted to the
מנחה, mincha, that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma when they say you're
חייב chayav for כזית kezayis outside, must mean that at least for
the קטורת, ktores, it means you're יוצא yotzei for כזית kezayis. inside,
we cannot be talking about יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Everybody agrees on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur you need מלא חפניו. melo chofnav. Okay. אלא,
Ella, so אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says here's the debate.
בהקטרה בפנים כולי עלמא לא פליגי. behaktara bifnim chulei alma lo peligi.
When it comes to, or דפנים, d’fnim, when it comes to the
הקטרה haktara on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, everybody agrees you need מלא
חפניו melo chofnav inside and you would need מלא חפניו melo chofnav
to be חייב chayav outside.
כי פליגי בהקטרה דחוץ. Ki peligi behaktara d’chutz. The question is the
הקטרה haktara that we do outside, you know, the הקטרה haktara every
day that we do in the היכל. Heichal. And here's the debate.
Now again, what we're also going to say is, is that nobody
is going to debate that, again this is a little bit shocking,
that you're
יוצא yotzei your daily הקטרה, haktara, your daily קטורת ktores with כזית.
kezayis. Everybody agrees on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you need מלא חפניו
melo chofnav and because you need it you're not חייב chayav until
you do מלא חפניו. melo chofnav. Again we're assuming by קטורת, ktores,
contrasted to the מנחה, mincha, that you're only חייב chayav outside if
it's the full amount inside, or if it's the minimum required amount
inside. When it comes to the daily קטורת, ktores, we're now saying
everybody agrees you're יוצא yotzei with a כזית. kezayis,
The question is, here's the question, you're יוצא yotzei with כזית, kezayis?
the question is, are you חייב chayav outside with a כזית? kezayis
Okay, and let's take a look. כי פליגי בקטורת. Ki peligi bi'Ketores.
מר סבר ילפינן פנים מחוץ ומר סבר לא ילפינן. Mar savar yalfinan
pnim m'chutz u'mar savar lo yalfinan.
So let me just make sure I'm saying this right, let me
just double-check
רש״י. Rashi. Oh no, I said it wrong. One minute.
Okay, I'm sorry, I said it wrong. Here's what we're saying.
We'll do a visual aid.
Okay,
here we go. Little thing.
Okay, we got this. So, inside here on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
you need מלוא חפניו. melo chofnav. We'll draw your two hands.
You need מלוא חפניו. melo chofnav. That's what you need to be
יוצא. yotzei. Everybody agrees to that. I was saying it wrong though
because we'll get back, we'll get back to what you need to
be חייב chayav outside. So, here's ירושלים, Yerushalayim, here's your private במה
bamah outside. Okay, so everybody agrees here you need מלוא חפניו melo
chofnav to be יוצא, yotzei, and everybody agrees here you need just
a כזית kezayis to be יוצא yotzei for your daily, for your
daily. Now the question is, what are you חייב chayav for outside?
Since everybody agrees that you need just a כזית kezayis. to be
יוצא yotzei here, everybody agrees that if you're burning this outside, you're
חייב chayav for a כזית. kezayis But here, this is the question.
So when we said רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agrees that, you know,
that he agrees that the daily you're יוצא yotzei with a כזית
kezayis. and he agrees that the daily you're חייב chayav? for כזית.
kezayis, So what's the debate? The debate is on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur you went ahead and you were מקריב makriv somehow, I don't
know how you managed to do this, on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
you got a hold of some of the קטורת Ketores that was
going to go to the inside and you were מקריב makriv it
outside. Okay, it was going to go to the קודש קדשים. Kodesh
Kodashim. So on יום כיפור Yom Kippur you took some of this
stuff and you were מקריב makriv it on your private במה. bamah.
How much do you need to be חייב? chayav So here, here
the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you're going
to need the full amount, because again, we're assuming by the קטורת,
Ketores, contrasted to the מנחה, Mincha, that you're only חייב chayav outside
if it's the full amount. So therefore by the קטורת Ketores you're
going to need the full amount outside, that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says no, even though I
agree that by the קטורת Ketores you need the full amount, in
general I would agree to that, at least by the קטורת, Ketores,
here I'm going to say since by the קטורת Ketores of the,
since by the קטורת Ketores of the קודש Kodesh you're חייב chayav
on a כזית, kezayis. by the קטורת Ketores of the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur you're also חייב chayav on a כזית. kezayis. So the
debate in the משנה Mishna is about the קטורת Ketores of יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says since you need a
מלוא חפניו, melo chofnav, you're only חייב chayav for מלוא חפניו, melo
chofnav,
and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says even though you need a
מלוא חפניו, melo chofnav, and even though I agree with you that
when it comes to the קטורת Ketores you need the minimum amount
to be חייב chayav on the outside to be יוצא, yotzei, but
here we're going to link it to this קטורת Ketores and say
that you're חייב chayav on a כזית. kezayis, Okay, so let's read
that again. אלא אמר אביי בקטורת שבפנים כולי עלמא לא פליגי. Ella
amar Abaye bi'Ketores she'bifnim kulei alma lo peligi. Nobody disagrees what you
need to be יוצא yotzei inside. You need to be יוצא yotzei
is
מלוא חפניו. melo chofnav. כי פליגי Ki peligi when did they debate?
בקטורת דחוץ. Bi'Ketores di'chutz. Okay, when you are going to take this
stuff that was coming from קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and be מקריב
makriv it outside. מר סבר ילפינן פנים מחוץ Mar savar yalfinan pnim
m'chutz that we learn, you know, this from outside, that since by
this you're חייב chayav on a כזית, kezayis. this also you're going
to be חייב chayav on a כזית. kezayis, Okay, and that would
be the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. ומר סבר לא ילפינן. u'mar savar
lo yalfinan. Okay, so רבא Rava does not like this. אמר רבא
השתא חוץ מחוץ לא ילפי רבנן פנים מחוץ מבעיא. Amar Rava hashta
chutz m'chutz lo yalfe rabbanan pnim m'chutz mibei'ei. I don't get it.
We don't learn how can you say that if you need a
מלוא חפניו, melo chofnav,
nevertheless because this is a כזית, kezayis. this is also going to
be a כזית. kezayis, In other places we don't apply different שיעורים
shiurim from one to the other by things that you're חייב chayav?
outside on a במה. bamah. מאי היא? Mai hi? דתניא יכול המעלה
פחות מכזית קומץ ופחות מכזית אימורין והמנחה פחות משלושה לוגין יין ופחות
משלושה לוגין מים יהא חייב? De'tanya: yachol ha'ma'aleh pachos mi'kezayis kometz u'pachos
mi'kezayis emurim v'ha'menachah pachos mi'shlosha lugin yayin u'pachos mi'shlosha lugin mayim yehei
chayav?
Maybe if you do less than the minimum amount of all these
various things, three לוג, log, כזית, kezayis etc., you'd be חייב? chayav
תלמוד לומר לעשות: Talmud lomar la'asos: על השלם הוא חייב ואינו חייב
על החסר. al ha'shalem hu chayav v'eino chayav al ha'chaser. So that's
our basic principle that you're only חייב chayav on the minimum amount
of what would be done in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
now רבא Rava says the question: one minute, why are you חייב
chayav on, why are you not חייב chayav unless three לוג log
of wine? ופחות משלושה לוגין דאית בהו כמה זיתים. U'pachos mi'shlosha lugin
d'is behu kama zeisim. Why don't we say, you know, when it
comes to wine and, you know, here I've got my, here I've
got my wine. wine
and
I'm going to do a ניסוך nisuch and it's less than three
לוג. log. It's only like two לוג. log. Okay, but that two
לוג log is more than a couple of זיתים, zeisim, so why
don't they say, well look, if you're חייב chayav on a כזית
kezayis of meat on the outside, you should be חייב chayav on
a כזית kezayis of wine. I don't say that. I say each
thing has its own שיעור. shiur. So then why should I say
just because you're חייב chayav on a כזית kezayis of the of
the קטורת ketores of the היכל, Heichal, you should be חייב chayav
on a כזית kezayis, of the קטורת ketores of the קודש קדשים.
Kodesh Kadashim. No, each thing has its own שיעור. shiur. For the
היכל Heichal you're חייב chayav. on a כזית, kezayis for the קודש
קדשים Kodesh Kadashim you're required a full שיעור. shiur. Okay, now of
course this is קטורת ketores and קטורת, ketores, but רבא Rava just
says you do not apply שיעורים shiurim from different
categories. Okay, so we still don't really
get a handle on what exactly is the nature of this debate.
If רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agrees that as we've chosen to read
it, there's no compelling text, but we've chosen to read it that
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agrees that there's a כזית kezayis that you're
יוצא yotzei for inside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash by the קטורת,
ketores, what's the debate of whether of outside whether it's a כזית
kezayis, or the full amount? So that's the question. אלא אמר רבא,
ella amar Rava, רבא Rava says I'm going to tell you how
this works. כגון דקבעינהו שני חצי פרס במנא. kegon dikav'inhu shenei chatzei
pras bemana. You've got here, it's true, you're יוצא yotzei here with
a כזית, kezayis, forget יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, we're going to
get rid of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that's too confusing, forget it.
Okay, also totally bizarre to think that the משנה's Mishnah talking about
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. We're going to talk about your normal daily
קטורת. ketores. Now we said רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer agrees that you're
יוצא yotzei if it's not the if it's just a כזית, kezayis
even if it's not the full פרס. pras. That's true, you are
יוצא. yotzei. But how did you sort of like start the process?
Here's your כלי שרת kli shareis and you're bringing in your stuff,
right, here you're the כהן, kohen, you're bringing it in to offer
it up, okay, here's your כלי שרת kli shareis that you're going
to bring in for the קטורת. ketores. If you only had a
כזית kezayis in there, everybody would agree that you'd be יוצא. yotzei.
And if you took that כזית kezayis outside the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, everybody would agree you'd be חייב. chayav But what you have
in here is you actually have two כזיתים. kezeisim.
Okay, or two half פרס, pras, but each of those is let's
say let's say a כזית kezayis. or minimally a כזית. kezayis So
because you put it in the כלי שרת kli shareis together to
bring it in, even though had you just had a כזית kezayis
you'd be יוצא, yotzei, because you have two כזיתים kezeisim and they're
in the same כלי שרת, kli shareis, so that's the debate. חכמים
Chachamim say you'd still be יוצא yotzei even if you just did
a כזית kezayis even though you had more in the כלי שרת,
kli shareis, and since you'd still be יוצא yotzei you're still חייב
chayav for it outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says even though a כזית kezayis is enough to be
יוצא, yotzei, but once you put them in the כלי שרת kli
shareis you need the full amount to be יוצא. yotzei. And since
you need the full amount to be יוצא, yotzei, you need the
full amount outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. מר סבר קביעותא דמנא
מילתא היא, mar savar keviusa demana milsa hi, putting them in the
same vessel is meaningful and that creates what the minimum amount is,
ומר סבר לאו מילתא היא, umar savar lav milsa hi, it's not
meaningful. Okay, and we'll end with that, and again just to repeat
that this is very strange as תוספות Tosafos notes, here the assumption
is
you
would not be חייב chayav outside for a כזית kezayis according to
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma unless you're יוצא yotzei for a כזית
kezayis inside. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer always says the amount you need
to be יוצא yotzei inside is the amount you need to be
חייב chayav outside. But for the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma by מנחה
minchah that's certainly not true, or מנחת כהן minchas kohen you need
the full amount, or a normal מנחה minchah you need the full
קומץ, kometz, and nevertheless he says you're חייב chayav for a כזית
kezayis, outside. But for some reason by the קטורת ketores we assume
that they would agree to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that the outside
is linked to what you're יוצא yotzei with inside. And therefore we're
saying that the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says you're חייב chayav for
a כזית, kezayis you're יוצא yotzei for a כזית kezayis, inside, and
that's why you're חייב chayav. outside. And then we're also saying רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer actually agrees to that, but nevertheless he says that
because you put more than that in one כלי שרת, kli shareis,
that's when you have to do more than the full amount out
that's when you have to do the full amount, more than a
כזית, but the full amount you put in the כלי שרת kli
shareis outside in order to be חייב. Okay, we will end here
for today.