Hey, good מוצאי שבת. Motzei Shabbos. Today's דף daf is ק''א, Kuf
Aleph, 101. We pick up at the bottom of ק' עמוד ב'
Kuf Amud Beis and we pick up with the following, about five
lines from the bottom,
אמרו קמיה דרבא. Amru kamei de-Rava.
So the גמרא Gemara has introduced a debate of רבי Rebbi and
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose about whether the אנינות Aninus is just that
day or until נקבר המת. nikvar hames. רבי Rebbi said it's until
נקבר, nikvar, which could have been a קולא kula or could have
been a חומרא. chumra. The גמרא Gemara reads it as a חומרא
chumra until not only the day but until the day of burial,
not only the day of death but the day of burial. And
then the גמרא Gemara went further to say that what they really
were debating
was
whether it applies at the night as well;
that רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose said it just applies the day and
רבי Rebbi said it applies even the night, even if it's just
יום קבורה, Yom Kvura, not the day of death. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
five lines from the bottom,
אמרו קמיה דרבא. Amru kamei de-Rava. So they said this in front
of רבא, Rava, מכדי קאמר רבי יוסי קבורה תופס לילה מדרבנן. mi-de-ka-amar
Rebbi Yose kvura tofes layla mi-drabbanan. Since רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose is
saying, I guess the way I'm reading here that that's רבי יוסי
Rebbi Yose saying that יום קבורה Yom Kvura even that
the night following יום קבורה Yom Kvura also has a status of
אנינות, Aninus, so תופס לילה מדרבנן, tofes layla mi-drabbanan, מכלל דיום מיתה
תופס לילה מדאורייתא. miklal de-yom misa tofes layla mi-doraisa. So from there
we can infer that because presumably we wouldn't make the דרבנן drabbanan
יום קבורה Yom Kvura without יום מיתה Yom Misa is just a
דרבנן. drabbanan. So if the דרבנן drabbanan of יום קבורה Yom Kvura
includes the night, presumably that's only because the דאורייתא doraisa of יום
מיתה Yom Misa also would include the night following. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara asks that: וסבר רבי אנינות לילה דאורייתא? Ve-savar Rebbi
Aninus layla doraisa? Now does רבי Rebbi really hold that אנינות לילה
Aninus layla is מן התורה? min ha-Torah? Because according to this, right,
this would have רבי Rebbi and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose here saying
essentially the same thing, right? So that would make you have them
saying that if יום קבורה Yom Kvura includes the night מדרבנן mi-drabbanan
then and יום קבורה Yom Kvura itself is דרבנן drabbanan and it's
going to include the night, so יום מיתה Yom Misa must include
the night מדאורייתא. mi-doraisa. So is that really true that that's what
רבי Rebbi says? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Braisa: הן
היום. Hen hayom. אני היום אסור ולילה מותר. Ani hayom asur velayla
mutar. So now we're going to get into one of the whole
bases for learning out that an אונן onen is אסור assur in
קרבנות korbanos and that the discussion of whether it applies at night,
which is the whole discussion by אהרן Aharon and the death of
נדב ואביהוא Nadav ve-Avihu where משה Moshe tells him you should have
eaten the חטאת היום chatas hayom and he said if I would
have eaten this today הייטב בעיני ה'? hayitav be'einei Hashem? So presumably
one way to understand that is the reason אהרן Aharon didn't eat
it is because he was an אונן. onen. So let's take a
look. הן היום. Hen hayom. אני היום אסור ולילה מותר. Ani hayom
asur velayla mutar. So the way it's being read is: Today, I
was permitted, it was היום, hayom, I wasn't allowed to eat it
because I was an אונן, onen, but that night I would have
been allowed to eat. ולדורות, U-le-doros, but in future generations, בין ביום
בין בלילה אסור דברי רבי יהודה. bein bayom bein balayla assur divrei
Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda would say that even night is
forbidden this we already know from earlier, that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
is of the position that the night of אנינות Aninus is דאורייתא.
doraisa. Maybe that wasn't true by אהרן Aharon but in general the
night following the אנינות Aninus is דאורייתא. doraisa. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer,
now רבי Rebbi says what we've known before that רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon said, we had this before in the discussion of eating the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach if somebody was an אונן onen that day:
אנינות לילה אין מדברי תורה אלא מדברי סופרים. Aninus layla ein mi-divrei
Torah ela mi-divrei sofrim. It's only rabbinic. So now we've got a
problem. If רבי Rebbi holds that the night even by יום מיתה
Yom Misa is only דרבנן, drabbanan, so why by יום קבורה Yom
Kvura would he also hold that it applies to the night? Okay,
presumably if even by יום מיתה Yom Misa if in the תורה
Torah it is only the day itself by יום מיתה Yom Misa
not the night, that's from the תורה Torah law. So מדרבנן mi-drabbanan
when we apply say it also applies יום קבורה, Yom Kvura, we
should pattern it after the תורה Torah and say it's only the
יום קבורה Yom Kvura not the following night.
לעולם דרבנן היא. Le-olam drabbanan hi. You know what, you're right. Fine,
that it is true that the night following יום מיתה Yom Misa
is דרבנן. drabbanan. And even though that's true and even though מן
התורה min ha-Torah it's only the day and not the night, when
we extend that from not only יום מיתה Yom Misa but to
יום קבורה, Yom Kvura, we're going to go even further than the
תורה. Torah. For the תורה Torah it only applies to the day
and not the night we are going to add on the night
for the תורה's Torah יום מיתה. Yom Misa. Now when we're going
to create a יום קבורה, Yom Kvura, you could say that's just
make it just the יום קבורה Yom Kvura let's pattern it after
the תורה. Torah. But no we're going to go further. וחכמים Ve-chachamim
top of ק''א ע''א, Kuf Aleph Amud Aleph, וחכמים עשו חיזוק לדבריהם
יותר משל תורה. Ve-chachamim asu chizuk le-divreihem yoser mi-shel Torah.
They made it even more than the תורה Torah הלכה. halacha. Fine,
so that is this discussion about whether
two discussions: number one is whether יום מיתה Yom Misa which everybody
says is מן התורה min ha-Torah does that apply at night as
well? According to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose it applies according to רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda it applies at night, according to רבי Rebbi and
רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose it does not apply at night. And then
there's a separate discussion יום קבורה Yom Kvura that isn't יום מיתה
Yom Misa that we all agree is דרבנן drabbanan are we going
to extend that into the night as well? But now we're going
to focus on the דאורייתא doraisa and on יום מיתה Yom Misa
and whether... on the day of death
does
אנינות aninus *Aninus* extend into the night. So now we have the
following: תנו רבנן Rabbanan *Tanna Rabbanan*, our rabbis taught, כי כן צויתי
*Ki chen tzuveisi*, כאשר צויתי *Kaasher tziveisi*, כאשר צוה השם *Kaasher tziva
Hashem*. Three times it says as I have been commanded, when משה
Moshe *Moshe* talks to אהרן Aharon *Aharon* and he should have eaten
these קרבנות korbanot *Korbanos* even though it was the death of נדב
ואביהו Nadav v'Avihu *Nadav and Avihu*. So what does each one of
these כי כן צויתי *Ki chen tzuveisi* mean? כי כן צויתי באנינות
יאכלוה *Ki chen tzuveisi baaninus yochluha*, so the first one was you
should have eaten it even though you are אונן onen, *Onen*, I
told you that you were supposed to eat this even though נדב
ואביהו *Nadav and Avihu* died. So why did you not eat it?
Okay, I have commanded you to eat it even as אונן onen.
*Onen*. Okay, כי כן צויתי באנינות יאכלוה *Ki chen tzuveisi baaninus yochluha*.
כאשר צויתי *Kaasher tziveisi*, I've been commanded, בשעת מעשה *Beshaas maaseh*, at
the time, okay. So he says that, so the way רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says, if you look at רש"י *Rashi*, so רש"י *Rashi* says
בשעת מעשה *Beshaas maaseh*, so, one minute, כי כן צויתי *Ki chen
tzuveisi*, כאשר צויתי *Kaasher tziveisi*, כאשר צויתי *Kaasher tziveisi*, כי כן צויתי
באנינות יאכלוה *Ki chen tzuveisi baaninus yochluha*, כאשר צויתי בשעת מעשה *Kaasher
tziveisi beshaas maaseh* רש"י *Rashi* says, four lines from the top, כשארע
להם אנינותם אמר להם שלא ימנעו מאכילת קדשים היום hayom, ששמע מפי
הגבורה שחלוק אנינות aninus היום בקדשים משאר ימים *Keshearua lahem aninusam amar
lahem shelo yimnou meachilas kodashim hayom sheshama mipi hagevurah shechalok aninus hayom
bekodashim mishar yamim*. Right, this day was special, here I'm telling you
you should eat it even though you're אונן onen. *Onen*, משאר ימים
*Mishar yamim*, וכשראה שנשרפה אמר להם אכול תאכלו אותה לכם לא היה
לכם לאכלה כאשר צויתי אתכם בשעת מעשה *Ucheshara'ah shenisrefah amar lahem achol
sochalosa lahem lo haya lachem leachlah kaasher tziveisi eschem beshaas maaseh*. So
this is sort of to say when he first gave it to
them he said eat this, כי כן צויתי *Ki chen tzuveisi*, I've
been commanded to tell you to eat this even though you are
אונן onen, *Onen*, that's when he, after the death before then he
told them go ahead and eat it anyway. And then he says
כאשר צויתי *Kaasher tziveisi*, when he found out they burned it, he
says you should have eaten it like I told you, like I
had been commanded, and I told you you were commanded to eat
it even though you were going to be אונן onen? *Onen*. So
I told you that בשעת מעשה *Beshaas maaseh* why did you not
do that? אמר להן כאשר צוה השם *Amar lahen kaasher tziva Hashem*,
and then he said as God had commanded, לא מאלי אני אומר
*Lo meailai ani omer*, I didn't say it on my own, God
had said it, reiterating that this was from God. So anyway, you
should have eaten it when you were אונן onen, *Onen*, I told
you that at the time, why did you not do it? Okay,
okay. ורמינהי *Verminei*, now, מפני אנינות aninus נשרפה *Mipnei aninus nisrefah*.
So here, here he's saying you should have eaten it, I told
you to eat it as אונן onen *Onen*. So presumably the reason
they didn't eat it must have been for some other reason other
than the fact that they were אונן onen. *Onen*. So now we're
going to get to the question why did they not eat it?
Why did they burn it? Okay, so here the ברייתא brayisa. *Braisa*
says, מפני אנינות aninus שרפוה לכך נאמר כאלה *Mipnei aninus serafuha lachach
ne'emar ka'eileh*. So אהרן Aharon *Aharon* says to משה Moshe, *Moshe*, ותקראנה
אותי כאלה vatikrena oti ka'ele, *Vatikreinosi ka'eileh*,
if a death like this had happened you expect me to eat
from it? So pointing to his dead sons נדב ואביהו *Nadav and
Avihu* he's saying I shouldn't have eaten from it. So he's saying
I didn't eat that as an אונן onen? *Onen*. So how do
you reconcile this? One ברייתא braisa *Braisa* says משה Moshe *Moshe* explicitly
told them eat them, eat it even though you're אונן onen *Onen*,
that's what God has told me. And then it says the reason
they didn't eat it was because they were אונן onen *Onen*. So
how can you reconcile this? So, let's take a look. אמר שמואל
לא קשיא הא רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda הא רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia
*Amar Shmuel lo kashya ha Rebbe Yehuda ha Rebbe Nechemia*. It's a
debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* and רבי נחמיה *Rebbe
Nechemia*. דתניא de'tanya, *Detanya*, מפני אנינות aninus שרפוה לכך נאמר כאלה דברי
רבי נחמיה *Mipnei aninus serafuha lachach ne'emar ka'eileh divrei Rebbe Nechemia*. רבי
נחמיה *Rebbe Nechemia* says they didn't eat it because they were אונן
onen. *Onen*. So presumably משה Moshe *Moshe* had not given them explicit
license to eat it as אונן onen. *Onen*. We'll see about that,
but that's at least right now at the face of it is
against the idea that they ate it because משה Moshe *Moshe* explicitly
told them that they had license to eat it as אונן onen
*Onen*. No, he didn't tell them that, and they didn't eat it
because they were אונן onen *Onen*, and that's that. רבי יהודה ורבי
שמעון אומרים *Rebbe Yehuda veRebbe Shimon omrim*, although we know they debate
about whether אנינות לילה aninus lailah *Aninus layla* anyway, but they both
say מפני טומאה mipnei tuma. נשרפה *Mipnei tumah nisrefah*. No, he had
license to eat it. That was כי כן צויתי *Ki chen tzuveisi*
and צויתי *Tzuveisi*.
And why did they not eat it?
That was for some completely different reason, it became טמא tamei? *Tamei*,
nothing having to do per se with the death of אהרן Aharon
*Aharon*'s children. So now let's take a look as we're going to
play this out in the פסוקים psukim *Psukim*.
שנאמר she-ne'emar *Shenemar*, here's רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rebbe Shimon*'s proof that it was because of something else like
טומאה tumah? *Tumah* and not because of
אנינות aninus, *Aninus*. שאם אתה אומר מפני אנינות aninus נשרפה היו לשלשתן
שישרפוה *She'im atah omer mipnei aninus nisrefah hayu lishloshan sheyisrefuha*.
So they should have burned all three of the חטאות chata'ot *Chatas*.
We're going to find out there were three חטאות *Chatas*, one because
it was ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh*, it was ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh. ניסן *Rosh Chodesh Nissan*, one because it was the eighth
day of the מילואים miluim. *Miluim*, and one because of נחשון Nachshon
*Nachshon*, the first day of the dedication of the משכן mishkan? *Mishkan*,
נחשון Nachshon *Nachshon* brought a קרבן korban *Korban* and it had a
שעיר se'ir לחטאת *Seir lachatat*. So there were three חטאות *Chatas*. But
they only burned one of them. Okay, so therefore they say look,
if it was אנינות aninus. *Aninus*, if it was something like טומאה
tumah. *Tumah* that could have happened to one and not the others.
But if it was אנינות aninus, *Aninus*, that excludes them from all
of them. So it couldn't have been אנינות aninus? *Aninus*, then they
would have burned all three. Number one. Number two, דבר אחר Davar
acher, *Davar acher*, היו ראוי לאכלה לערב *Hayu ra'uy leachlah laerev*. If
it was just an אנינות aninus *Aninus* problem they could have eaten
it at night. Now of course רש"י *Rashi* points out that works
better for רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon* who says that אנינות aninus, לילה
*Aninus layla* is not מן התורה *Min hatorah*, so then if it
were אנינות aninus, *Aninus* they would have just eaten it that night.
For רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* that's not exactly, and now רבי יהודה
*Rebbe Yehuda* but רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* And רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*
are both saying that it couldn't have been אנינות aninus *aninus* and
one of the reasons it couldn't have been אנינות aninus *aninus* was
because if it were אנינות aninus *aninus* just eat it at night.
So רש"י *Rashi* says okay look even though רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*
normally holds like we should have just alluded to this a second
ago, even though רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* normally holds אנינות aninus, לילה
*aninus layla* is דאורייתא d'Oraisa, *d'oraysa*, he agrees that in this case
they would have had an exception and they would have been allowed
to eat it at night. But okay, but number—so with two reasons
it couldn't have been אנינות aninus? *aninus*. Number one is if it
was אנינות *aninus* they shouldn't have burnt all three. Number two is
if it was אנינות *aninus* at least for רבי שמעון *Rebbe Shimon*
and maybe for רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* there would have been a
special exception, they could have eaten it at night. That's number two.
דבר אחר *davar acheir*, number three, ולא פנחס היה עמהן v'lo Pinchas
haya imahen? *v'lo Pinchas haya imahen*? Hey, if it was just אנינות
*aninus*, פנחס Pinchas *Pinchas* wasn't an immediate relative, right? It was—you know—it
was פנחס Pinchas? *Pinchas*'s uncle, so he wasn't—he wasn't an immediate relative,
he wasn't an אונן onen. *onein*. So he could have—it would not
have been אבילות *aveilus* for his uncles. He could have eaten it.
So three reasons why it couldn't have been אנינות *aninus*, it must
have been some extra special issue that that became טמא tamei. *tamei*
and that's why they burnt it. Okay. So, now רבא אמר *Rava
amar*, so according to that, the one that says they had a
license to eat it because of אנינות *aninus* is—cannot say that it
was burnt because of אנינות *aninus*. So the position of רבי נחמיה
*Rebbe Nechemia* that it was burnt because of אנינות *aninus* obviously understands
that they didn't have a special license. Okay, that's one explanation. But
now we're going to see there's another explanation. It could be they
have a—had a license and they burnt it because they were אוננים
onanim *oneinim*. Let's take a look. רבא אמר *Rava amar*, רבא *Rava*
said, אידי ואידי דרבי נחמיה *idei v'idei d'Rebbe Nechemia*, no, it could
be רבי נחמיה *Rebbe Nechemia*. רבי נחמיה *Rebbe Nechemia* could hold both
they had a license to eat it as אוננים onanim *oneinim* and
they burnt it because they were אוננים *oneinim*. Why? ולא קשיא
*v'lo kashya*, it's not difficult. כאן בקדשי שעה כאן בקדשי דורות *kan
b'kodshei sha'ah kan b'kodshei doros*. It depends—it depends which קרבן korban, *korban*
you're talking about and this answers the first of the three questions:
why didn't they burn all three? Because the license to go ahead
and eat it even though they were אוננים *oneinim* applied only to
the things that were themselves exceptions, the special קרבנות korbanot, *korbanos* that
were only brought for that period of time. What were those? The
חטאת chatat, *chatas* of the מלואים *milluim* and the חטאת chatat *chatas*
of נחשון *Nachshon*. But the third חטאת chatat *chatas* of ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, that was for all generations. We're not going
to make any special rules for that. We could make special rules
for special קרבנות korbanot? *korbanos*. So now it all makes sense. They
had a license to eat it, but they had a license to
eat the special חטאות *chataos*, but they burnt the חטאת chatat *chatas*
of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh* because that they didn't have
a license. And that's why it was because both כי כן צויתי
*ki chein tziveisi* that you could eat it as אונן onen. *onein*
and it was burnt because of אנינות *aninus* because they were talking
about different קרבנות korbanot. *korbanos*. Okay, let's take a look. So now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: רבי נחמיה היכי מתרץ הני
קראי ורבנן היכי מתרצי להני קראי *Rebbe Nechemia heichi mitaretz hani kray
v'rabbanan heichi mitartzei l'hani kray*. How did they each approach whether it's
because of אנינות *aninus* they burnt it or whether it's because of
טומאה tumah *tuma*, how did they read the פסוקים *psukim*? רבי נחמיה
מתרץ להו הכי *Rebbe Nechemia mitaretz l'hu hachi*, here's how רבי נחמיה
*Rebbe Nechemia* explains it. מדוע לא אכלתם *madua lo achaltem*, why didn't
you eat it? אמר לו משה amar lo Moshe, לאהרן *amar lo
Moshe l'Aharon*, so now what we're going to do is we're going
to explain what the back—what the story behind it must have been
so—and then we're going to hear that echoed and reflected in what
the verse actually says. So אמר לו משה amar lo Moshe, לאהרן
*amar lo Moshe l'Aharon*, משה Moshe *Moshe* said to אהרן Aharon. *Aharon*:
שמא נכנס דמה לפני ולפנים *shema nichnas dama lifnai v'lifnim*? Look, I'm
trying to understand, אהרן Aharon, *Aharon*, help me out here, like why'd
you burn it? Maybe accidentally you brought the blood of this חטאת
chatat. *chatas* into the, you know, inner sanctum and then you have
to burn the חטאת chatat *chatas*? אמר לו amar lo, הן לא
הובא דמה hen lo huva dama. *amar lo: hein lo huva dama*.
No, the blood wasn't brought inside. Okay, so שמא חוץ למחיצתה יצאה
shema chutz limchitzata yatza'ah? *shema chutz l'mechitzata yatza*? Okay, maybe the opposite.
Maybe you brought it outside the משכן *Mishkan*? אמר לו amar lo,
בקדש *amar lo: bakodesh*. So הן לא הובא דמה אל הקדש פנימה
*hein lo huva dama ela kodesh penima*. So הן לא הובא דמה
*hein lo huva dama*, it wasn't brought inside, אל הקדש *ela kodesh*,
it remained in the
קדש *kodesh*, so בקדש היה *bakodesh haya*. ודלמא באנינות אקריבתיה ופסלתיה *v'dilma
b'aninus akrivtuha u'pessaltuha*, maybe you brought it as an אונן onen *onein*
and—and—and it's פסול passul *passul*? אמר לו amar lo, *amar lo*, so
he said back to him: משה Moshe. *Moshe*, וכי הם הקריבו *v'chi
heim hikrivu*? Do you think my sons brought the קרבן korban *korban*
after נדב ואביהוא Nadav ve-Avihu *Nadav v'Avihu* died? אני הקרבתי Ani hikravti
*ani hikravti*. I'm the one who brought it. Okay, so I brought
it and a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol. *Kohen Gadol* is עובד אונן
onen *oveid onein*. So therefore none of those are the reason why
it was burnt. So now we're going to see how that whole
conversation they had beforehand
is echoed and reflected in now what משה Moshe *Moshe* says to
אהרן Aharon *Aharon*. So אמר ליה הן לא הובא דמה *amar leh:
hein lo huva dama*, so listen אהרן *Aharon*, based on what you
just told me, number one, the blood wasn't brought inside. Number two,
הן לא הובא דמה ובקדש היה אל הקדש פנימה *hein lo huva
dama u'bakodesh haya ela kodesh penima*,
and you're telling me it remained in the קדש *kodesh*. Okay, אכול
תאכלו אותה כאשר צויתי באנינות יאכלו *achol tochlu osa ka'asher tziveisi b'aninus
yochlu*.
You know, you should have eaten it as I commanded you, eat
it in your אנינות *aninus*. Okay, as long as it wasn't נפסל
nifsal? *nifsal*, even though you're אונן onen *onein* you should have eaten
it. Now, by the way, the—what we didn't so—say explicitly here, but
the אהרן *Aharon*'s response they weren't מקריב *makriv* it I was מקריב
*makriv* it was—was הן היום hen hayom. הקריבו את קרבנם ואת חטאתם
לפני ה' *hein hayom hikrivu es korbanam v'es chatasam lifnei Hashem*. What,
you think they brought the קרבן korban, *korban*? They didn't bring it,
I brought it! So we got now all of that back and
forth in the פסוקים *psukim*. I brought it, it remained in the
קדש *kodesh*, it didn't go into the קדש *kodesh*—it didn't go into
the inner sanctum. inside, it didn't go פנימה. So all those reasons
it should be good. So משה Moshe said, "Great, it should have
been good, why'd you burn it?" Okay, and don't tell me you
were אונן, onen I told you you were allowed to eat it
as אונן. onen אמר לו, Amar lo אהרן said back, "הן היום
הקריבו את קרבנם ואת חטאתם לפני השם ותקראנה אותי כאלה ואכלתי חטאת
היום הייטב בעיני השם?" hen hayom hikrivu et korbanam ve'et chatatam lifnei
Hashem vatikrena oti ka'ele ve'achalti chatat hayom hayitav be'einei Hashem? Look משה,
Moshe, I just suffered a death. You think I should have eaten
the חטאת, chatat meaning I didn't eat it cause I was אונן.
onen So now we get to the loggerheads, right? משה Moshe. said,
"I gave you license to eat it as an אונן," onen and
אהרן says, "What, you think I'm going to eat it as an
אונן?" onen. So,
and now here's why אהרן said, "I didn't follow your היתר." heter.
שמא לא שמעת אלא בקדשי שעה? shema lo shamata ela bekodshei sha'ah?
Maybe when you had a special היתר heter to eat it as
אונן, onen it applied to the two חטאות that were special for
this time, the חטאת chatat of נחשון and the חטאת chatat of
the מילואים. miluim. Okay, but הרי בקדשי דורות, harei bekodshei dorot, but
as a general rule, an אונן obviously can't eat a קרבן korban
as a general rule. How do I know that? קל וחומר ממעשר
הקל. kal vachomer mima'aser hakal. I can make a קל וחומר kal
vachomer from מעשר. ma'aser. ומה מעשר הקל אמרה תורה לא אכלתי באוני
ממנו, uma ma'aser hakal amra Torah lo achalti be'oni mimenu, by
מעשר ma'aser which is much less weightier than a קרבן, korban you
say you didn't eat it as an אונן. So, בקדשי דורות לא
כל שכן? bekodshei dorot lo kol sheken?
How much more so by a קרבן korban that has, you know,
that applies for all generations, should you not be able to eat
it as an אונן? So if you gave me a היתר, heter,
I assumed that the היתר heter was for the special קרבנות korbanot.
that are only for this time, but for anything that's like part
of a general process and a general rule and a general type
of a קרבן, korban you would not make an exception. Obviously there
אוננים are not allowed to eat. So that's why, so that answers
one of the three questions. If it was אוננים why didn't they
burn all three? Because two of them he had a license for,
but he said, "I don't I don't believe this license applies to
the third one." It doesn't apply to the קרבן korban of ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Okay.
So, מיד וישמע משה וייטב בעיניו. miyad vayishma Moshe vayitav be'einav. משה
Moshe heard and it was good in his eyes. הודה ולא בוש
משה לומר לא שמעתי. hoda velo bosh Moshe lomar lo shamati. He
wasn't embarrassed to say that I didn't hear, okay, and try to
claim oh God never told me that. אלא אמר, ela amar, "You
know what? שמעתי ושכחתי. shamati veshachachti. You're right, טאקע, take, you did
the right thing, and I got it mixed up. I forgot the
היתר heter was only for the two קרבנות, korbanos. not the third
one. You were right to burn the third one." That's the approach
of רב נחמיה. Rav Nechemya. Now we don't know how he answers
the other two questions, get פנחס Pinchas to eat it, eat it
at night, we'll see about that. But anyway,
now, רב יהודה ורב שמעון היכי מתרצי להו? Rav Yehuda ve'Rav Shimon
heichi mitartzei lehu? How do they explain the פסוקים since for them
it's about טומאה? tuma. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכי מתרצי להו. heichi mitartzei lehu. Here's how they explain it. מדוע
לא אכלתם את החטאת במקום הקודש? madua lo achaltem et hachatat bimkom
hakodesh? So it's going to be pretty much the exact same thing,
except the אפשאט, apshat, the final answer, is going to be different.
שמא נכנס דמה לפנים ולפנים? shema nichnas dama lifnim velifnim? Maybe you
brought it into the אהל מועד Ohel Moed and therefore became נפסל?
So אמר לו, "הן לא הובא דמה. It wasn't brought inside. שמא
חוץ למחיצתה יצאה? Maybe it was brought outside the משכן?" אמר לו,
"הן בקודש היתה. hen bakodesh hayta. It was in the קודש. kodesh.
ודילמא באנינות הקרבתם ופסלתם אותה? udilma be'aninut hikravtem ufsaltem ota? Maybe you
brought it as an אונן and פסול-ed pasul? her?" אמר לו משה,
Moshe "הן הקריבו? hen hikrivu? Did they bring it? הן הקריבו היום
חטאתם דפסלוה באנינות? hen hikrivu hayom chatatam depasluha be'aninut? That אוננות onenut
would פסול? No, אני הקרבתיה. ani hikravtiha. I'm the one who brought
it." Okay. So now that far we got. Now משה Moshe, goes
on. ודילמא אגב מריראיכו פשעתם בהו ואיתמו? udilma agav meriraichu pashatem behu
ve'itmu? Maybe because you were so bitter and, you know, overwhelmed by
your grief you were negligent and it became טמא? tamei. אמר לו
משה, Moshe "כך אני בעיניך? kach ani be'einecha? Is that
what you see how I'm seen in your eyes? שאני מבזה קדשי
שמים? she'ani mevaze kodshei shamayim? That I would
be denigrate, like, not pay due respect to the קרבנות? korbanos. So
ותקראנה אותי כאלה, vatikrena oti ka'ele
אפילו אלה וכאלה איני מבזה קדשי שמים. afilu ele vecha'ele eini mevaze
kodshei shamayim. Even if
tragedies beyond this occur to me, I would not lose sight of
the sanctity and of the protection of the קרבנות." korbanos So as
opposed to before ותקראנה אותי כאלה vatikrena oti ka'ele is hey it
isn't about אוננות, onenut, here he's saying hey it isn't about טומאה.
tuma In the end it's a little ironic. In one case he
said hey it wasn't about
אוננות, onenut, but in the end,
in the first one it was. In the first one it was
ותקראנה אותי כאלה vatikrena oti ka'ele because of this tragedy should I
be eating it, meaning it was because אוננות. onenut. So the first
answer ותקראנה אותי כאלה vatikrena oti ka'ele because of this tragedy that's
why I didn't eat it. And that's the answer that it wasn't
eaten because of אוננות. onenut. This explanation that it wasn't eaten because
of טומאה tuma it's going to be a little ironic because he's
saying even had terrible tragedies happened to me I would not have
let it become טמא. tamei, And that's my defense against saying that
I ate it because it was טמא. tamei. In the end we're
going to find out it did become טמא, tamei but not because
of any negligence of אהרן. משה Moshe says it was not because
we weren't careful. No matter what had happened to us we would
have been careful. Okay. So here's
the
ותקראנה אותי כאלה vatikrena oti ka'ele before the
ותקראנה אותי כאלה
was like. אמר לו Aaron said back to him שמא לא שמעת
אלא בלילה Shemma lo shamata ela balaila דביום קל וחומר ממעשר הקל.
De'bayom kal v'chomer mimaser hakal.
Maybe when you gave us a heter to eat it as אונן
maybe that heter was only for night. Okay, but maybe in the
day we shouldn't be eating it as אונן. Okay, so it's a
same type of a dynamic, right? They're pushing back on משה. Moshe
Of course, the answer's going to be, if fine, why did you
wait till night to eat it at night? We'll see about that
in a minute. But here again משה Moshe thinks there's a blanket
heter to eat it as אונן. In the first version they said
only for the קדשי שעה kodshei sha'ah not for the קרבן korban
of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh Here they're saying there might have been
a heter to eat as אונן maybe it applied to everything, but
presumably we would have waited at least till
night. Okay. דביום קל וחומר ממעשר הקל De'bayom kal v'chomer mimaser hakal
מה מעשר הקל אמרה תורה לא אכלתי באוני ממנו Ma maser hakal
amara Torah lo achalti be'oni mimenu קודש חמור לא כל שכן? Kodesh
chamur lo kol sheken? מיד וישמע משה וייטב בעיניו. Miyad vayishma Moshe
vayitav be'einav. לא בושת משה לומר לא שמעתי אלא שמעתי ושכחתי. Lo
boshet Moshe lomar lo shamati ela shamati v'shachachti. Okay fine so it
says you're right תגר taka I forgot. Now according to this it
doesn't sound like it's מפני טומאה. It sounds like they burnt it
because they couldn't eat it during the day they had to wait
till night. Now the גמרא Gemara of course asks the obvious follow-up
question. What do you mean? Just wait till night.
Okay. איבעי להו לשוייה ולמיכליה באורתא Ibayalu lishuay u'leimichla be'orsah then they
should have waited and eaten it at night according to this. No.
טומאה באונס באתה. Tuma be'ones basta. It wasn't because they were negligent.
Now we introduce the טומאה. Okay. Yes, you're right some accidental טומאה
occurred nothing they could have done anything about and that's why they
didn't eat it and therefore it was only one specific קרבן korban
not all three. Again if it was the night issue and for
some reason that was an issue whatever it would have applied to
everything. So the אנינות here within רבי יהודה and רבי שמעון is
a completely bracketed point. Okay you didn't even need that back and
forth. Okay but what it is sort of saying is that according
to רבי יהודה that normally you weren't allowed to eat by אונן
at night here they got a special license at night they didn't
want to interpret the license to be during the day. Fine. But
anyway what we basically have is the following. According to one version
they had a license or according to both versions they had a
license to eat it as אונן. According to one version they pushed
back and said yes but that didn't apply to the קרבן korban
of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. and that's why we burnt the קרבן
korban of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh And according to the other version
they said fine but we chose to understand that that would only
allow us at night not during the day and by the time
it took us to wait to night at least a טומאה happened
to one of the קרבנות. And that's why it got burnt. Okay.
איבעי The גמרא says like this. בשלמא לרבנן היינו דכתיב היום. Bi'shlama
le'rabanan hainu dichsiv hayom.
According to the רבנן Rabbanan that say that they wanted to wait
till night that's why they said ואכלתי חטאת היום. v'achalti chatat hayom.
That part of the back and forth although not the full explanation
why they burnt it but part of the back and forth was
we didn't want to eat it at the daytime we wanted to
wait till the night. אלא
רבי נחמיה מאי היום? Ela Rabbi Nechemia mai hayom? חובת
היום. Chovas hayom. Says very smart, very ingenious. It says אכלתי חטאת
achalti chatat
not had I eaten the חטאת chatat today. Had I eaten חטאת
היום. chatat hayom. Had I eaten the day's חטאת. chatat The day's
חטאת chatat means the regular חטאת chatas, of the day the חטאת
chatas of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It's the day's חטאת chatas the
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, חטאת chatas that I'm not allowed to eat
because of an אונן. Okay so according to one the push back
was we can't be eating it as אונן in the day we
have to wait till the night. Okay at least even if there's
a heter the heter should only wait till the night. And the
other explanation was I can't eat the חטאת היום. chatat hayom. I
can't eat the heter doesn't apply to the regular חטאת chatas of
the day. Now. בשלמא לרבי נחמיה היינו דכתיב הן היום.
Bi'shlama le'Rabbi Nechemia hainu dichsiv
hen hayom. אלא לרבנן מאי הן היום? Ela rabanan mai hen hayom?
So according to רבי נחמיה you understand what it means הן היום.
hen hayom? Okay
because that's the same point. This is the קרבן korban. of the
day that's why we're not doing it. But for the רבנן what's
the underscoring of הן היום? hen hayom So
הכי קאמר. hachi kamar. הן הקריבו? Hen hikrivu? So it's like we
said before did הן הקריבו היום את חטאתם hen hikrivu hayom et
chatatam not הן היום the קרבן korban. of the day. No did
they do it? If they did it as אונן they would have
invalidated it. No. אני הקרבתי I'm the one who did it. Fine.
Okay great so we have the whole back and forth. The הן
לא הובא את דמה Hen lo huva et dama it wasn't brought
inside ובקודש היתה u'bakodesh hayisa and it remained in the קודש kodesh
אכול תאכלו אותה בקודש כאשר צויתי achol tochlu osa bakodesh ka'asher tziveiti
you should have eaten it why did you not eat it but
אנינות she'yochlu אונן I've told you you can eat it as אונן
and clearly they did were prepared to eat as אונן this is
the approach that they did eat it as אונן so why didn't
you eat it? So either because of אנינות and it's חטאת היום
chatat hayom and the חטאת chatas of the
day that the special heter of אנינות does not override that I
couldn't eat because of. or it's היום, we had to wait till
the night, and by the time we waited till the night, it
became טמא. tamei Okay.
אמר מר, Amar mar, היו לשלשתן שישרפו. hayu lishloshan sheyisrafu. They should
have burned all three of them. Okay, this is their pushback to
רב נחמיה. Reb Nechemia. We already have an answer, because they only
burned the one that was the regular חטאת, but anyway this was
their pushback.
Okay, מאי שלשתן? mai shloshan? What three? דתניא, we
taught in a ברייתא. Excuse
me. ואת שעיר החטאת דרוש דרש משה. V'es se'ir hachatas darosh darash
Moshe. The שעיר se'ir of the חטאת Moshe searched out to find
out. שעיר, זו שעיר נחשון. Se'ir, zu se'ir Nachshon. Okay, that's the
שעיר se'ir of נחשון because he was the first of the נשיאים
nesi'im to dedicate.
חטאת, זו חטאת שמיני. Chatat, zu chatat shemini. That's the חטאת of
the eighth of the מילואים. miluim, דרוש,
זה שעיר של ראש חודש. Darosh, zeh se'ir shel Rosh Chodesh. Okay,
so there are three שעירים. se'irim. יכול שלשתן נשרפו, Yachol shloshan nisrafu,
maybe all three were burned? תלמוד לומר והנה שורף. Talmud lomar v'hinei
soraf. אחד נשרף, Echad nisraf, it was burned, ולא שלשתן נשרפו. v'lo
shloshan nisrafu. And now we find out why was it only one?
Either because it was טמא tamei. and only happened to one, or
because of the אנינות where the היתר heter didn't apply to the
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh, Now, דרוש דרש, darosh darash, שתי דרישות. shtei
drishos. Two explorations. Number one,
מפני מה חטאת זו נשרפה? mipnei mah chatat zu nisrefah? Question number
one, why did you burn this one? That's obviously the focus. ואלו
מונחות? V'eilu munachos? Number two is, why did you wait for the
other two, why didn't you eat them now, why are you waiting
till night? And that's what we sort of said according to the
approach that they said we get that there was a היתר heter
for אנינות, but we wanted to wait till night. So now he
has two questions: why'd you burn one and why'd you wait for
night for the other two? And the answer is: one becomes טמא
and the other because the היתר heter of אנינות we are going
to assume does not apply during the day. Now, ואיני יודע איזהו.
v'eini yodeia eizeh hu. Now he says I don't know which one
is the one that was burned. כשהוא אומר ואותה נתן לכם לשאת
את עון העדה, K'shehu omer v'osah natan lachem laseis es avon ha'eidah,
this חטאת was given to you for you to carry the sin
of the people, הוי אומר זה שעיר של ראש חודש, Hevei omer
zeh se'ir shel Rosh Chodesh, because שעיר of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh.
it says that it's
לחטאת להשם. l'chatat l'Hashem. Okay, now, שפיר קאמרי ליה לרב נחמיה. shapir
ka'amlei l'Reb Nechemia. Now the גמרא says they actually challenged רב נחמיה
Reb Nechemia well. Okay, they, why weren't all three of them burned?
So now, if it was אנינות. Now we already know the answer
to that. רב נחמיה לטעמיה, Reb Nechemia l'taimei, דאמר קדשי שעה פסלה
בו אנינות. d'amar kadshei sha'ah paslah bo aninus. No, he says I,
two of them wasn't a problem with, the ones that were קדשי
שעה. kadshei sha'ah. So that's his answer. Yes, it was אנינות, and
only one, only the ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Okay, but now we
have two other questions for רב נחמיה. Reb Nechemia. Why not wait
till night? And why not פנחס? Pinchas אמר מר, Amar mar, so
let's take a look. היה לו לאכלו לערב? Haya lo l'ochlo la'erev?
Why not wait till night if it was just אנינות? שפיר קאמרי
ליה, Shapir ka'amlei, so that's a good challenge. קסבר אנינות לילה דאורייתא.
Kasavar aninus lailah d'Oraisa. No, because רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia holds אנינות
לילה is דאורייתא, that's a very easy answer, so does רב יהודה.
Reb Yehuda. Okay, so רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia holds it was a
total היתר, heter, but it only applied to the קרבן of to
the קדשי שעה. kadshei sha'ah. Okay,
but so that's why they couldn't wait till night for the because
for the one, excuse me, for the ראש חודש, there was no
היתר heter at all and night was still אסור. assur. So they
so for him, אנינות applies day and night, and since the היתר
heter didn't apply to ראש חודש, they had to burn the ראש
חודש. Okay, so that's why he says they didn't wait till night
and that's why it was only one of the three. Now we're
going to have another one. דבר אחר, ולא פנחס Pinchas היה עמהן?
Okay, if it was אנינות, just get פנחס Pinchas to eat it.
So now we're going to have an interesting discussion about פנחס's Pinchas
status as a כהן. kohen. שפיר קאמרי ליה, Shapir ka'amlei,
that's a good challenge. סבר לה כרב אליעזר, Savar lah k'Reb Eliezer,
he holds like רב אליעזר. Reb Eliezer. דאמר רב אליעזר אמר רב
חנינא לא נתכהן פנחס עד שהרגו לזמרי. D'amar Reb Eliezer amar Reb
Chanina lo niskahin Pinchas ad she'harag l'Zimri. פנחס Pinchas was not a
כהן kohen until he killed זמרי. Zimri. Now that's very bizarre, he's
obviously a direct descendant of אהרן, but since the תורה Torah only
says that who became anointed as כהנים, kohanim, it says אהרן, אלעזר,
איתמר, נדב ואביהו. Aharon, Elazar, Isamar, Nadav v'Avihu. Now they what but
if פנחס Pinchas was already born to אלעזר, Elazar, so when his
father became a כהן, kohen, he wasn't becoming a כהן kohen and
he wasn't a כהן kohen by birth. Okay, any children that that
אהרן's kids would have had afterwards would have been כהנים kohanim because
they would have been born to כהנים. kohanim. But פנחס Pinchas was
already born and his father became a כהן kohen and he didn't
become a כהן. kohen. So he only became a כהן kohen at
the story of זמרי. Zimri. Okay, and therefore at the time when
נדב ואביהו died, he could not have been eating from the קרבנות.
So now we got the idea that it was אנינות, משה Moshe
said you should have eaten it, I gave you a היתר, heter,
they said that היתר heter only applied to קדשי שעה, kadshei sha'ah,
it didn't apply to the ראש חודש. Why didn't you wait till
night? Sorry משה, Moshe אנינות applies at night as well. Oh, that
wasn't the exchange but anyway, okay, his position אנינות applies night. Why
didn't פנחס Pinchas eat? פנחס Pinchas wasn't a כהן. kohen. קסבר, Kasavar,
okay, where were we? דאמר רב אליעזר אמר רב חנינא לא נתכהן
פנחס עד שהרגו לזמרי, D'amar Reb Eliezer amar Reb Chanina lo niskahin
Pinchas ad she'harag l'Zimri, until he killed זמרי. Zimri. דכתיב והיתה לו
ולזרעו אחריו ברית כהנת עולם. Dichsiv v'haysah lo ul'zar'o acharov bris kehunas
olam.
So what is this ברית כהנת עולם bris kehunas olam that God
gives him? So according to this, God made him a כהן, kohen,
before that he wasn't a כהן. kohen. רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi
amar עד ששם שלום ad she-sam shalom
בין שבטים. bein shvatim. No, פנחס Pinchas even surprisingly even later did
not also because your part of the whole question is how did
פנחס Pinchas kill זמרי? Zimri? He was a כהן, Kohen, he wasn't
allowed to become טמא. According to this that wasn't a problem yet.
But anyway, so פנחס Pinchas. even though he gets this ברית כהונת
עולם, bris kehunas olam, he didn't really become a כהן Kohen until
much later in his career, not through this act of violence, right?
It's very nice, ברית שלום bris shalom after this act of violence.
But at the end of his career when he is the sort
of warrior turned diplomat and he goes makes peace with בני גד
ובני ראובן Bnei Gad u-Bnei Reuven when they're when there's about to
be a civil war because, you know, the other tribes think בני
גד ובני ראובן Bnei Gad u-Bnei Reuven are about to break off.
This is after they go into the land and whatever and and
so on and they think that there's about to be then and
they want to go against them in civil war, and they send
פנחס Pinchas. on a diplomatic mission and פנחס Pinchas. makes peace. So
that's a real fulfillment of the ברית כהונת עולם. bris kehunas olam.
It's starting with violence and ending with שלום. shalom. Anyway, so this
says that's when he became a כהן, Kohen, not when he showed
his violent zealous side, but when he showed his peace-loving side. Okay,
עד ששם שלום בין השבטים ad she-sam shalom bein ha-shvatim שנאמר she-ne'emar
וישמע פנחס הכהן ונשיאי העדה וראשי אלפי ישראל. va-yishma Pinchas ha-kohen u-nesi'ei
ha-eidah ve-roshei alfei Yisrael.
They heard this about what happened and then they went whatever, they
went there and they made peace and they did a diplomatic mission.
So the point is that here it actually identifies him as פנחס
הכהן. Pinchas ha-kohen. Before this it's always פנחס בן אלעזר בן אהרן
הכהן. Pinchas ben Elazar ben Aharon ha-kohen. It doesn't have the כהן
Kohen referring to פנחס. Pinchas Here it has the כהן Kohen referring
to פנחס. Pinchas? ואידך נמי האי כתיב והייתה לו ולזרעו אחריו, Ve-idach
nami hai ksiv ve-haysah lo u-le-zaro acharo, wait a minute, but doesn't
it say ברית כהונת עולם bris kehunas olam way back in the
זמרי Zimri story? No, כי כתיב ההוא בברכה הוא דכתיב. Ki ksiv
hahu be-vrakhah hu de-chsiv. That's a blessing that it will be a
ברית כהונת עולם, bris kehunas olam, but it was only fulfilled at
this story much later at the time when they made you know,
when they were in the land and they made peace. ואידך נמי
הכתיב וישמע פנחס הכהן, Ve-idach nami ha-ksiv va-yishma Pinchas ha-kohen, why does
it call him הכהן? ha-kohen? Why does it directly identify כהונה kehunah
with him only here? So it says ההוא ליחס זרעו אחריו Hahu
le-yacheis zaro acharo to give him a יחוס. yichus. What's the point
of the יחוס? yichus?
רש"י said this is primarily to indicate that the כהנים גדולים kohanim
gedolim are now going to descend from פנחס. Pinchas Okay, אמר רב.
Amar Rav. Now that we are discussing this issue about נדב ואביהוא
and פנחס and so on, okay, let's take a look and this
whole אנינות question also and who else could have eaten from the
קרבנות. We're going to bring in משה. Moshe, אמר רב משה רבינו
כהן גדול. Amar Rav Moshe Rabbeinu Kohen Gadol. משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu
was a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol, He served during the period of
the מילואים, miluim so he presumably retained a status of כהן. Kohen.
I don't know why כהן Kohen גדול, but anyway, maybe because he
could also go into the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Anyway, משה Moshe
was also a כהן Kohen. וחולק בקדשי שמים היה, ve-choleik be-kodshei shamayim
hayah, and he would get a חלק chelek in all the קרבנות
שנאמר מאיל המלואים למשה היה למנה. me-eil ha-miluim le-Moshe hayah le-manah.
Okay,
so this from the איל מלואים eil miluim משה Moshe had a
portion, and he's reading this not just that one קרבן during the
מילואים miluim. period, but that he had this status now of a
כהן. Kohen. Pretty wild. מיתיבי, Meisivi, I'll ask you, ולאו פנחס עמהם
היה? va-lav Pinchas imahem hayah? The challenge was to how can you
say it was אנינות, what about פנחס? And the answer was that
פנחס wasn't a כהן. Kohen, According to you, how could you say
it was אנינות? משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu was with them. Okay, you
so there was somebody to eat the קרבן. So ואי איתא לימא
ולאו משה רבינו היה עמהם? ve-i issa leima va-lav Moshe Rabbeinu hayah
imahem? This dismisses משה, Moshe, דיומא דשאני
משה דטריד בשכינה. yuma de-shani Moshe de-tarid be-shchinah. No, no, no, even
though משה Moshe was a כהן, Kohen they could not have said,
"Hey, we're all אונן-im, but don't worry we don't have to burn
the meat, we'll get משה Moshe to eat the meat because he's
not an אונן." No, because משה Moshe would have been way too
busy. So since they were אונן-im and משה Moshe was way too
busy, they had to burn the meat. Why was משה Moshe way
too busy? Because he was spending all his time with God. דאמר
מר משה בהשכמה עלה בהשכמה ירד. De-amar mar Moshe be-hashkamah alah be-hashkamah
yarad. He went up first thing in the morning to הר סיני,
Har Sinai, went down first thing in the morning. Now that was
הר סיני, Har Sinai, here it was after the at least that
immediate event, but nevertheless he was totally busy with God. They could
not have held the meat for משה Moshe to eat. מיתיבי, Meisivi,
okay. That's why we brought in the story of משה, Moshe but
now we're going to challenge it. לחם אלוהיו מקדשי הקדשים ומן הקדשים
יאכל. Lechem elohav mi-kodshei ha-kodashim u-min ha-kodashim yokhal. Okay,
so this is בעל מום. ba'al mum. A בעל מום ba'al mum
can eat from the קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim and from the קדשים
קלים. kodashim kalim. He just can't be bring the קרבן. So now
the ברייתא says the following: אם נאמר קדשי קדשים למה נאמר קדשים
קלים, אם נאמר קדשים קלים למה נאמר קדשי קדשים? Im ne'emar kodshei
kodashim lamah ne'emar kodashim kalim, im ne'emar kodashim kalim lamah ne'emar kodshei
kodashim? I mean, you know, why does it have to say that
a בעל מום ba'al mum can eat both from קדשים קלים kodashim
kalim and קדשי קדשים? kodshei kodashim? I mean, you know, just say
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and קדשים קלים kodashim kalim should be obvious.
So it says like this: אילו לא נאמר קדשים קלים הייתי אומר
קדשי קדשים הוא
דאכיל. Ilu lo ne'emar kodashim kalim hayisi omer kodshei kodashim hu de-akhil.
Fine, I get that a בעל מום ba'al mum can eat from
קודש קדשים. kodesh kodashim. Why? שהותרו לזר. she-hutru le-zar. There was a
non-כהן Kohen that was allowed to eat קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. What
non-כהן Kohen. was allowed to eat קדשי קדשים? kodshei kodashim? The only
one could have been משה Moshe. during the period of the מילואים.
Okay, so that shows that משה Moshe was a זר, zar, he
wasn't a כהן. Kohen, Okay, הותרו לזר. hutru le-zar. והלכך Ve-hilkach and
therefore, so that's why it's permitted also to the בעל מום. ba'al
mum. קדשים קלים לא יאכלו, Kodashim kalim lo yokhelu, but not קדשים
קלים. kodashim kalim. ואילו לא נאמר קדשי קדשים, Ve-ilu lo ne'emar kodshei
kodashim,
so that's why it had to say קדשים קלים kodashim kalim because
I would have thought קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim we know were allowed
to a non-כהן, Kohen, משה, but קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim, משה never
ate קדשים קלים kodashim kalim as a כהן, kohen, I
mean קדשים קלים kodashim kalim the שלמים shlamim that the owners eat.
Okay, you. Now obviously that in fact he can eat. But the
meat of the קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim that only the כהנים kohanim
eat, that's the question. So משה never ate the meat of the
קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim that only כהנים kohanim eat even though he
ate the sort of something from the שלמים, shlamim, it was a
שלמי צבור shalmei tzibur which is קדשי קדשים. kadshei kadashim. Anyway, משה
only ate from קדשי קדשים. kadshei kadashim. So had it just said
קדשי קדשים, kadshei kadashim, fine, because משה ate from קדשי קדשים, kadshei
kadashim, a non-כהן, kohen's but קדשים קלים, Kodashim Kalim, the כהן's kohen?
part of קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim maybe not. ואילו נאמר קדשי קדשים
ve-ilu ne'emar kadshei kadashim and if it had just said קדשים קלים,
Kodashim Kalim, ואילו לא נאמר קדשים קלים, ve-ilu lo ne'emar kodashim kalim,
הייתי אומר קדשים קלים hayiti omer kodashim kalim יהא אוכל yehe ochel
fine, if it had just said קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim I say
fine, a בעל מום ba'al mum can eat קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim
שכן קלים she-ken kalim that they're קל, kal, but בקדשי קדשים bekadshei
kadashim לא יהא אוכל lo yehe ochel but not קדשי קדשים kadshei
kadashim which are weightier. ולכך נאמר קדשי קדשים ולכך נאמר קדשים קלים.
ul-chach ne'emar kadshei kadashim ul-chach ne'emar kodashim kalim. That's why it had
to say both. Fine. Okay. Obviously if it had just said קדשים
קלים Kodashim Kalim you had to also say קדשי קדשים. kadshei kadashim.
That's clear. But the point is that if it said קדשי קדשים
kadshei kadashim I wouldn't have limited it to that because we know
that a זר zar eats from it. So that makes it pretty
clear that משה was a זר. zar. קתני מיהת שהרי הותר לזר
ולהם. katani mi-hat she-harei hutar le-zar velahem. לאו משה? lav Moshe? Doesn't
this mean משה that משה was a זר zar not a כהן?
kohen אמר רב ששת: amar Rav Sheshet: לא, בבמה לזר. lo, bebamah
le-zar. No, we mean that it was brought at a במה bamah
and that was eaten by a זר. zar. וכדברי האומר יש מנחה
בבמה. uch-divrei ha-omer yesh minchah bebamah. And like the one who says
there's a מנחה minchah at a במה. bamah. Now what does that
mean? Why do you have to say a מנחה minchah at a
במה? bamah? Because what are the קדשי קדשים? kadshei kadashim? So the
normal קדשי קדשים kadshei kadashim is עולה. olah. Well, nobody's eating an
עולה. olah. חטאת and an אשם, asham, but חטאת and אשם asham
are obligations, those you don't bring at a במה. bamah. So where
would you ever get קדשי קדשים kadshei kadashim that a זר zar
could eat at a במה? bamah? So the only קדשי קדשים kadshei
kadashim would be a מנחה. minchah. מנחה minchah is something that normally
is only eaten by the זכרי כהנים zacharei kohanim in the בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. If that's brought at a במה bamah and you
can understand why that could be brought because that's a נדבה, nedavah,
free will, and then it would be eaten by a non-כהן kohen's
because that would be the הלכה halachah at במה. bamah. So that's
how you would have קדשי קדשים kadshei kadashim eaten at a במה.
bamah. Okay. And but not the כהן's kohen's portion of קדשים קלים
Kodashim Kalim because there is no כהן's kohen's portion of קדשים קלים.
Kodashim Kalim. So therefore we're using the example of במה bamah not
the example of משה. Had it just said קדשי קדשים kadshei kadashim
I would have said there you have a זר zar eating קדשי
קדשים, kadshei kadashim, but you never have a זר zar eating the
כהן's kohen portion of the קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim and that's why
it had to say both. Okay. And we will pick up with
this tomorrow or whenever on Tuesday to continue this question of whether
משה was a כהן kohen. or not a כהן.