מזל טוב, Mazel tov, today's דף daf is מ"ד, mem daled, 44.
We pick up on דף מ"ד עמוד א, daf mem daled amud
aleph, about 10 lines down at the two dots, and we're continuing
to look at the משנה mishna which was identifying those parts of
the different types of animals and the different types of the קרבנות
korbanot and the different parts of the קרבנות korbanot that פיגול piggul
does or does not apply to. So it says like this: כל
שיש לו מתירים בין לאדם בין למזבח חייבין עליו משום פיגול. kol
sheyesh lo matirin bein leadam bein lemizbeiach chayavin alav mishum piggul. Anything
that has something else that serves as a מתיר, matir, meaning the
meat or the entrails is the simple example in an animal sacrifice,
that it itself, that the blood is what is done to make
the קרבן korban valid, and once the blood is put on the
מזבח, mizbeiach, then the meat and the entrails are permissible, either to
be eaten by humans or
to be burnt on the מזבח. mizbeiach. So therefore the blood is
the מתיר, matir, and פיגול piggul doesn't apply to the blood, meaning
now we're talking here by the way when applied not at what
stage in the process, but when an animal is פיגול, piggul, the
blood itself is not פיגול. piggul. You know, even when the קרבן
korban is פיגול, piggul, if one were to eat the blood, one
would not get כרת. kares. But the parts of the קרבן korban
which have a מתיר, matir, the meat and the entrails, there פיגול
piggul does apply. Okay, so that's the meaning of the phrase כל
שיש לו מתירים, kol sheyesh lo matirin, any type of part of
that קרבן korban that something else serves as its מתיר, matir, and
that thing that serves as its מתיר, matir, the thing that validates
it, makes it permissible, whether to people or to the altar, בין
לאדם בין למזבח, bein leadam bein lemizbeiach, that type of a thing
חייבין עליו משום פיגול. chayavin alav mishum piggul. So גמרא Gemara says
like this: תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabanan: או אינו מביא אלא כיוצא בשלמים. o eino meivi
ela kiyotzei beshlamim.
So here's a ברייתא braita that focuses on how we derive this
from the פסוקים psukim about פיגול, piggul, because the פסוקים psukim about
פיגול piggul are talking about a שלמים. shlamim. So the ברייתא braita
says maybe the פסוקים psukim are only talking about שלמים, shlamim, maybe
פיגול piggul only applies by
שלמים. shlamim. מה שלמים מיוחדים נאכלים לשני ימים ולילה אחד, ma shlamim
meyuchadim ne'echalim lishnei yamim velaila echad, that
the same way שלמים shlamim are eaten for two days and the
intervening night, אף כל נאכל לשני ימים ולילה אחד. af kol ne'echal
lishnei yamim velaila echad.
So maybe also פיגול piggul would only apply to קרבנות korbanot that
are eaten for two days and the intervening night, which is a
very small category of קרבנות korbanot as we'll see in a minute.
נאכל ליום ולילה מנין? ne'echal leyom valaila minayin?
How about your standard קרבן korban that's eaten for a day and
a night? How do you know that פיגול piggul goes beyond the
scope of שלמים-like shlamim קרבנות? korbanot? תלמוד לומר: מבשר. Talmud lomar mibasar,
Okay,
that it says in the פסוק pasuk about פיגול piggul which is
ויקרא Vayikra 7 here, I think, yes, 7:18.
Thank you. ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו ביום השלישי לא ירצה
המקריב אתו לא יחשב לו פגול יהיה והנפש האכלת
ממנו עונה תשא.
ve'im he'achol yei'achel mibasar zevach shlamav bayom hashlishi
lo yeiratzeh
hamakriv oto lo yeichashev lo piggul yihyeh vehanefesh haochelet
mimenu avonah tisa. So it's מבשר זבח שלמיו. mibasar zevach shlamav.
So the idea of meat is a broadening word, it's being read
any sort of קרבן, korban, you know, the eating of the meat
of any קרבן. korban. Okay, so תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: מבשר, mibasar.
כל שיש לו שיירים נאכלים. kol sheyeish lo she'ayarim ne'echalim.
So anything that basically has like meat that can be eaten is
included in this prohibition. עולה שאין שיירים נאכלים מנין? ohlah she'ein she'ayarim
ne'echalim minayin? How about the עולה, ohlah, which is the קרבן korban
that does not have anything that can be eaten? So that's not
in the category of מבשר. mibasar. תלמוד לומר זבח. Talmud lomar zevach.
מבשר זבח שלמיו. mibasar zevach shlamav. Now why did it just say
מבשר שלמיו? mibasar shlamav?
So זבח zevach is any sacrifice. Of course the irony is that
זבח zevach classically in the פסוקים psukim refers to a שלמים, shlamim,
refers to something that is eaten, whatever. But okay, so the מבשר
basar and the זבח zevach allows us to include all sacrifices. Now
that's all maybe animal sacrifices. מנין לרבות העופות והמנחות עד שאני מרבה
לוג שמן של מצורע?
minayin lerabot ha'ofot vehamenachot ad she'ani marbeh log
shemen shel mitzora?
How do you know to include even much broader, even include birds,
even include המנחות, hamenachot, even include the לוג שמן log shemen of
the מצורע? metzora? We'll discuss the לוג שמן log shemen of the
מצורע metzora in a little bit. תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: אשר הם
מקדישים לי. asher hem makdishim li. Okay, now this is not this
פסוק pasuk here, it's a different פסוק pasuk in אמור Emor 22
which is talks about טומאה. tumah. Okay, it says דבר אל אהרן
ואל בניו וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל ולא יחללו את שם קדשי אשר
הם מקדישים לי אני ה'.
daber el aharon ve'el banav veyinazru mikodeshei bnei yisrael velo yechalelu et
shem kodshi asher
hem makdishim li ani Hashem.
So anything that they sanctify to me. The problem is that that
is talking about טומאה. tumah. How do I know that פסוק pasuk
about טומאה tumah to apply it to פיגול? piggul? ואתי נותר חילול
חילול מטומאה. ve'ati notar chilul chilul mitumah. So
it's a two-way jump. Okay, by נותר notar it says, by טומאה
tumah it says ולא יחללו, velo yechalelu, and by נותר notar it
says ולא תחלל velo techalel I think or ולא יחללו. velo yechalelu.
So therefore this scope by טומאה tumah of all קרבנות korbanot by
this חילול חילול chilul chilul link applies to פיגול. piggul. And once
we apply it to נותר, nosar, ואתיא ve'atya פיגול pigul עון עון
avon avon מנותר. minosar. So there's a link by פיגול pigul and
נותר, nosar, both use the word עון avon to say ונשא עוונו
v'nasa avono etc.
that that allows us now to say that since קדשים kodashim is
all קרבנות, korbanot, נותר nosar is all קרבנות, korbanot, and פיגול pigul
is all קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. Now מאחר שסופו לרבות כל דבר למה
נאמר שלמים? me'achar shesofo l'rabot kol davar lamah ne'emar shelamim? Okay,
so if you're going to include everything, why does the Torah emphasize
שלמים? shelamim? So מאחר שסופו לרבות כל דבר למה נאמר שלמים מעתה,
me'achar shesofo l'rabot kol davar lamah ne'emar shelamim me'atah, לומר לך, lomar
lecha, to tell you, מה שלמים מיוחדים שיש להם מתירים בין לאדם
ובין למזבח,
mah shelamim meyuchadim sheyesh lahem mattirim bein la'adam
uvein lamizbe'ach, to tell you that there is one limit, and the
one limit is that it has to function like שלמים, shelamim, that
there is something that is done that is a מתיר mattir and
what's left over now becomes permissible to a person or to the
altar. אף כל שיש לו מתירים בין לאדם ובין למזבח חייבין עליו
משום פיגול. af kol sheyesh lo mattirim bein la'adam uvein lamizbe'ach chayavin
alav mishum pigul. So therefore that is the limit and as we
saw in the משנה, mishnah, things that basically don't have two parts
to them like a מנחה mincha of a כהן kohen that you
all burn all up, right, and other types of examples that we
had, the קומץ, kometz, the לבונה, levonah, the דם dam itself, those
things that they themselves are the מתיר, mattir, for that is what
we learn from שלמים shelamim that פיגול pigul does not apply, but
not to limit it to the scope of the קרבנות. korbanot. Now
we're going to continue down, now this actually is going to sound
very much like our משנה mishnah but this is really a continuation
of the ברייתא, braita, okay? So it's actually interesting here because you
get to see the משנה mishnah is sort of like the codified
you know דין din and being quoted parallel is like the מדרש
הלכה midrash halachah which sort of derives it all out and sometimes
actually the lines in the מדרש הלכה midrash halachah are either borrowed
from or copied to the משנה. mishnah. Interesting question like which came
first, right? Sometimes מדרש הלכה midrash halachah seems to be quoting a
משנה, mishnah, maybe sometimes a משנה mishnah is constructed from a מדרש
הלכה. midrash halachah. Anyway, so here it
continues: העולה
דמה מתיר את בשרה למזבח, ha'olah damah mattir et besarah lamizbe'ach, so
even an עולה olah as we said is included, even though there's
no meat to be eaten but the meat can be put on
the altar, so that's considered
יש לו מתירים, yesh lo mattirim, והעור לכהנים, veha'or lakohanim, does this
really say that you transgress פיגול pigul if you eat the leather
of an עולה, olah, I don't know, anyway: עולת העוף דמה מתיר
את בשרה למזבח, olat ha'of damah mattir et besarah lamizbe'ach, a bird
עולה olah similarly although it's not a you know not a cow
or sheep or whatever, but okay, the blood now allows the bird
to be put on the altar, so פיגול pigul applies to the
meat of the bird. חטאת העוף דמה מתיר את בשרה לכהנים, chatat
ha'of damah mattir et besarah lakohanim, a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of the
blood may allow the meat to be eaten by the
כהנים. kohanim. ופרים הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים, uparim hanisrafim use'irim hanisrafim, which we're
going to see is a debate, but according to this approach, דמם
מתיר אימוריהם ליקרב, damam mattir emureihem likarev, okay yes because even there
the blood, even though the actual meat is burnt outside and it's
not considered to be allowing the meat to be eaten or to
be put on the altar, but at least it allows the you
know entrails to be put on the altar. Okay, so all of
that is included based on the בשר זבח שלמיו אשר הם מקדישים
basar zevach shelamav asher hem makdishim that we include all these קרבנות.
korbanot. What is excluded from this idea of יש לו מתירים? yesh
lo mattirim? ומוציא אני את הקומץ ואת הלבונה והקטורת, umotzi ani et
hakometz ve'et halevonah vehaketoret,
so here it actually has the right order: קומץ kometz and לבונה,
levonah, what's excluded are the components that actually are the מתירים mattirim
themselves, okay, the קטורת, ketoret, the קומץ, kometz, the handful, the לבונה,
levonah, the frankincense, both of which are the מתיר mattir for the
מנחה. mincha. תוספות Tosafot has an interesting question, is the קומץ kometz
a מתיר mattir for the לבונה, levonah, like can you do the
לבונה levonah before you do the קומץ kometz and you know would
you sort of see it that way, but anyway, קטורת ketoret is
the incense that's burnt on the inner altar. ומנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן
משיח, uminchat kohanim uminchat kohen mashiach, whether the free-will מנחה mincha of
any כהן kohen who chooses to give a מנחה, mincha, the whole
מנחה mincha is burnt, or the obligatory מנחה mincha of the כהן
גדול. kohen gadol.
All these things they either they're the מתיר mattir of something else
or they're the מתיר mattir of themselves, but if they're the מתיר
mattir then they are not a פיגול. pigul. ומנחת נסכים והדם. uminchat
nesachim vehadam. מנחת נסכים, minchat nesachim, right, the flour and oil plus
the wine that comes with a קרבן, korban, also you can sort
of obligate yourself separately, so according to this approach, since it can
come after you brought the קרבן korban not on the same day,
so there's nothing to מתיר mattir it, it might have even been
separated out after you brought your קרבן, korban, so therefore that is
מתיר mattir itself. So when it comes by itself it's certainly מתיר
mattir itself, and in the משנה mishnah there was a debate about
what happens when it's coming with the קרבן korban and the דם,
dam, the דם dam is the obvious thing that is the מתיר.
mattir. So even though that's during the act of the דם dam
is exactly when you make פיגול, pigul, that's the whole point because
it's the מתיר, mattir, but it itself does not become
פיגול. pigul. רבי שמעון אומר: מה שלמים מיוחדים Rabbi Shimon omer mah
shelamim meyuchadim שיש she-yesh בהן מזבח mizbeach? החיצון וחייבין עליו. No no
no, so this is the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon of our משנה.
mishnah. He says I'm going to use שלמים shelamim to exclude something
else, and yes I agree with you it excludes something that's a
מתיר, mattir, but it also excludes קרבנות korbanot that the that are
not put on the outer altar, that the דם, dam, the מתיר
mattir is not put on the outer altar. So a inner חטאת,
chatat, the מתיר, mattir, the דם, dam, I mean yes the אימורים
emurim are on the outer altar... did I say inner before? I
meant outer... anyway, it has to be like a שלמים shelamim that
the מתיר mattir is put on the outer altar, so by a
these inner חטאות chataot although the אימורים emurim are put on the
outer altar, the... the blood is put on the inner altar, so
for him that's just categorically excluded from פיגול. piggul. רבי שמעון אומר
Rabbi Shimon omer: מה שלמים shelamim מיוחדים oh my God שיש I
really do need a nomo over here
to be talking for me. מה שלמים מיוחדים שישנם על מזבח החיצון
וחייבין עליו אף כל שישנם על מזבח החיצון חייבין עליו. mah shelamim
meyuchadim she-yeshnam al mizbe'ach ha-chizon ve-chayavin alav af kol she-yeshnam al mizbe'ach
ha-chizon chayavin alav. It has to have that the מתיר matir is
put on the outer altar משום פיגול. mishum piggul. יצאו פרים הנשרפים
ושעירים הנשרפים הואיל ואין על מזבח החיצון כשלמים אין חייבין עליו משום
פיגול.
yatz'u parim ha-nisrafim ve-se'irim ha-nisrafim
ho'il ve-ein al mizbe'ach ha-chizon ke-shelamim ein chayavin alav mishum piggul. Okay,
so that's the end of the ברייתא braita and the whole end
of that ברייתא braita is
very almost word-for-word our משנה, mishna, a little bit different but pretty
much identical. But the beginning is showing how you get it from
the פסוק. pasuk.
אמר מר, amar mar, now let's go back and analyze this more
line by line. כי יוצא בשלמים, ke-yotzei be-shelamim, so it says I
might have thought maybe it's only just right now things that are
very similar to a שלמים shelamim that are eaten for two days
and the intervening night. Now how many קרבנות korbanot are there like
that? Can you name any קרבן korban that's like a שלמים shelamim
and not a שלמים shelamim that's eaten for two days and the
intervening night? Don't feel bad if you can't, it's very hard to
find one. Okay, so here's what the גמרא gemara says. מאי ניהו?
mai nihu? There's one one thing that fits that category. בכור. bechor.
The only thing is the בכור, bechor, which we tend to think
of as like a type of a שלמים shelamim. for exactly that
reason, but it's not technically speaking. מאי ניהו בכור דנאכל לשני ימים
ולילה אחד. mai nihu bechor de-ne'echal li-shnei yamim ve-laila echad. So maybe
I would have limited פיגול piggul to just that because that's the
thing that's most similar to a שלמים. shelamim Now במאי אתי? be-mai
ati? Now how would I have extended if I'm going to broaden
שלמים shelamim, to things like שלמים, shelamim what principle am I going
to use to broaden it? אי במה מצינו, ei be-ma mazinu, if
it's like a type of במה מצינו, be-ma mazinu, like you know
an analogy, just like it applies to שלמים shelamim it should apply
to similar things. So that type of an argument, it has to
be really pretty identical.
So איכא למפרך. ika le-mifrach. מה לשלמים שכן טעונים סמיכה ונסכים
ותנופת חזה ושוק.
mah le-shelamim she-ken te'unim semicha
ve-nesachim u-tenufat chaze ve-shok. שלמים shelamim, have other demands: you put your
hands on it, you bring the נסכים, nesachim, you wave the you
know the breast and the thigh. So it's not exactly similar. If
it's not exactly similar, you can't just go ahead and apply it
to something else. אלא מאם האכל יאכל, ela me-im he-achol ye-achel, so
it's basically based on the principle of כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat
u-klal. Okay, it says אם האכל יאכל im he-achol ye-achel מבשר זבח
שלמיו. mi-bsar zevach shelamav. So זבח שלמיו zevach shelamav is only a
שלמים, shelamim. that's a פרט. prat. האכל יאכל he-achol ye-achel is a
כלל, klal, anything you eat. Of course the problem is כלל ופרט,
klal u-prat, you have only the פרט, prat, you don't have anything
similar to the פרט. prat. In order to broaden it, it needs
to be כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat u-klal. So where are you
going to get your כלל ופרט וכלל? klal u-prat u-klal? גמרא gemara
maybe always could have said this was a ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u-mi'ut
but anyway. So it's going to say the double language of האכל
יאכל he-achol ye-achel gets to count as the two כללים. klalim. So
האכל he-achol is כלל, klal, שלמיו shelamav is פרט, prat, יאכל ye-achel
is another כלל, klal, and that would have allowed us to broaden
it. אם האכל יאכל. im he-achol ye-achel. So גמרא gemara says הני
תרי כללי דסמיכי אהדדי. hani terei klalei de-smichi ahadadi. You know one
minute, but those two כללים klalim are juxtaposed, it's not that the
פרט prat appears between them. אמר רבא amar Rava כדאמרי במערבא ke-damrei
be-maarava like they say in ארץ ישראל, eretz yisrael, כל
מקום שאתה מוצא שני כללים הסמוכים זה לזה הטל פרט ביניהם ודונהו
בכלל ופרט וכלל.
kol makom she-ata moza sheni klalim ha-smuchim ze la-ze hatel
prat beineihem ve-donehu be-klal u-prat u-klal. Yes, we're allowed to do this.
If you have two כללים klalim that are right next to each
other and then the פרט prat comes right after, you can rearrange
it to get your כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat u-klal.
Okay, it doesn't
well right maybe it's better that it's not a separate פסוק pasuk
because therefore you know it allows us to do a little bit
manipulate within the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, anyway. So that's what I would
have said. But no, זבח שלמיו אשר הם מקדישים zevach shelamav asher
hem makdishim tells me expand it to all קרבנות, korbanot, including even,
seems to say this ברייתא, braita, the שמן, shemen, the לוג log
of the שמן shemen that comes with a מצורע. metzora. So with
the לוג log of the שמן shemen with the מצורע metzora what
happens is you know the מצורע metzora is outside the camp, first
you do this ritual with the birds to like get rid of
the most severe טומאה tumah as it were and allow him to
come into the camp. Then he waits seven days
and then on the eighth day you do the special קרבן korban
of the מצורע. metzora. With the special קרבן korban of the מצורע
metzora to purify him is an אשם asham and you use the
blood of the אשם asham to put you know on his thumb
and his earlobe and whatever, and then you take a לוג שמן
log shemen and the לוג שמן log shemen is also which comes
with the אשם asham and it's almost like a little bit of
its own קרבן korban because you sprinkle seven times from the oil
of the לוג שמן log shemen
you know towards the קודש. kodesh. And then you use the you
do with the oil the remainder of the oil like you put
from it on the ear on the lobe and on the thumb
just like you did by you know the blood of the אשם.
asham.
So how do we think of this לוג שמן? log shemen? Do
we think of it as something that has a מתיר? matir? And
what's the מתיר? matir? The מתיר matir is the blood of the
קרבן. korban. Or do we think about it something that's מתיר matir
itself? That it doesn't have a מתיר, matir, it just comes by
itself? Okay, because and part of that argument would be like the
נסכים nesachim that you could bring it on a different day and
you can bring it on a different day. So let's take a
look. עד שאני מרבה לוג שמן של מצורע. ad she-ani marbe log
shemen shel metzora.
So גמרא gemara says הא מני רבי מאיר היא. ha mani Rabbi
Meir hi. דתניא de-tanya this is רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. לוג שמן
של מצורע שחייבין עליו משום פיגול דברי רבי מאיר. log shemen shel
metzora she-chayavin alav mishum piggul divrei Rabbi Meir. That's רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says you're חייב chayav for פיגול. piggul. אימא סיפא eima seifa
but wait at the end it says ומוציא אני מנחת נסכים והדם
u-mozi ani minchat nesachim ve-hadam that מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim is not
included okay because presumably Probably that is a מתיר matir, את עצמו
*matir es atzmo*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, that is—where were
we—אזלא לרבנן *azla lerabbanan*, that goes like the rabbis, דתניא Detanya *detanya*:
נסכי בהמה חייבין עליהם משום פיגול piggul. מפני שדם הזבח מתירן ליקרב
דברי רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *nischei behemah chayavin aleihem mishum pigul mipne
she-dam ha-zevach matiran likarev divrei Rabbi Meir*. So it seems like the
נסכים nesachim *nesachim* and the לוג שמן Log Shemen. *log shemen* are
the same. They're these types of liquids or whatever they are, things
separate from the קרבן korban. *korban* that certainly when they come with
the קרבן korban *korban*, you can conceive of it as though the
blood of the קרבן korban *korban* is the מתיר matir *matir* for
them. And that's what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says by
both of these. He says this by the לוג log, שמן shemen
*log shemen* and he says it by
the
נסכים nesachim.
*nesachim*. But the rabbis say, since we know these can come separate,
and then they're מתיר matir את עצמן *matir es atzman*, even when
they come together with the קרבן korban *korban*, they're seen as being
מתיר matir את עצמן *matir es atzman* and they're excluded from פיגול
piggul. *pigul*. אמרו לו *amru lo*, they said back to him, ולא
אדם מביא את זבחו היום ונסכיו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים *ve-lo adam
mevi es zivcho hayom u-nesachav mikan ve-ad asarah yamim*? I'll prove to
you the blood of the קרבן korban *korban* isn't מתיר matir. *matir*
them—they're מתיר matir את עצמן *matir es atzman* because in theory you
could bring them after the קרבן korban *korban*. אמר amar, להם *amar
lahem*, אף אני לא אמרתי אלא בבאים עם הזבח *af ani lo
amarti ela be-ba'im im ha-zevach*. Right, so when you do bring it
separate, I agree with you, but when you bring it with the
קרבן korban? *korban*, then I think the blood is מתיר matir *matir*.
And they say no, that's only one mechanism, they're מתיר matir את
עצמן *matir es atzman*. So the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* say the לוג
log. שמן shemen *log shemen* presumably and the נסכים nesachim *nesachim* are
excluded from פיגול piggul *pigul*. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says
when they come with the קרבן korban? *korban* they're included with פיגול
piggul *pigul*. So now we got a problem. This ברייתא Braisa: *beraisa*
seems to say that the לוג log *log* is included in פיגול
piggul *pigul* and the נסכים nesachim *nesachim* are excluded, so presumably they
go together. How do you explain that? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. אמר
רבי Rebbi יוסף *amar Rabbi
Yosef*, הא מני רבי Rebbi היא *ha mani Rabbi hi*, דאמר לוג
log שמן shemen של מצורע metzora מתנותיו שרו ליה *de-amar log shemen
shel metzora matnosav sharu leih*. So this is a position of רבי
Rebbi *Rabbi* which we'll introduce in a minute, and רבי Rebbi *Rabbi*
says the following: actually, the לוג log, שמן shemen *log shemen* of
מצורע metzora. *metzora* could be that even the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* agree
that this
is—that this has a מתיר matir. *matir*. Why? Because what do you
do with the לוג log שמן shemen *log shemen* of the מצורע
Metzora *metzora*? The לוג log שמן shemen *log shemen* of the מצורע
Metzora. *metzora* you take it, let's say you brought it after the
קרבן korban? *korban*. The חכמים chachamim, *Chachamim* proof that this is מתיר
matir את עצמו *matir es atzmo*, it doesn't have two components, is
that you can bring it separate from the קרבן korban *korban*. Okay,
so if you bring the נסכים nesachim. *nesachim* separate from the קרבן
korban *korban*, what do you do with them? You just put them
all on the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbeach*. So there's no מתיר matir, *matir*,
you just put it all on the מזבח Mizbe'ach. *mizbeach*. But with
the לוג log. שמן shemen. *log shemen*, what do you do?
So first you sprinkle it, then you use it for the ears,
and then the כהנים kohanim *kohanim* eat it. So you can say,
wait a minute, there is a מתיר matir. *matir* here, not blood,
not something that's on the altar, but oil. This is the מתיר
mattir *matir* because it's going like in the direction, you know, of
the altar or of the מקדש *Mikdash*. So that's an expansion of
the idea of מתיר *matir* because until now, you know, מתיר *matir*
required something physically put on the altar, whether it was blood or
whether it was the לבונה *levonah* or whatever. But nevertheless, you could
view this as saying generally, I think, נסכים nesachim, *nesachim* because they
can come separate are מתיר את עצמן *matir es atzman* even when
they're with the קרבן korban *korban*. But שמן *shemen*, even when it
comes separate, is not one whole—is not—it does have two components, has
a מתיר *matir* and has the remainder of the שמן *shemen*. So
therefore,
it's true that the חכמים chachamim *Chachamim* say they're all the same,
but here we're going to claim רבי Rebbi *Rabbi* would actually say
that you can פסקן *pasken* the נסכים nesachim,
*nesachim*—does not have two components and is excluded from פיגול piggul. *pigul*,
שמן *shemen* does have two components as in included in פיגול piggul
*pigul*.
So basically what he's saying is when we had on the list
above that even לוג log שמן *log shemen*
is included, so it's either
the position of רבי *Rabbi* or the position of רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir*?
It's not the position of רבי מאיר rabbi meir, *Rabbi Meir* because
at the end of the ברייתא Braisa *beraisa* it says that the
נסכים nesachim *nesachim* are excluded.
I mean it's following the חכמים *Chachamim*?
No, that's the גמרא's gemara *Gemara's* point, it can't be anybody. It
can't be רבי מאיר rabbi meir, *Rabbi Meir*. רבי מאיר rabbi meir
*Rabbi Meir* said that both לוג log שמן *log shemen* and מנחת
נסכים minchas nesachim. *minchas nesachim* have פיגול piggul *pigul*. It can't be
the חכמים *Chachamim* because the חכמים *Chachamim* say both לוג log שמן
*log shemen* and מנחת נסכים nesachim *minchas nesachim* don't have פיגול piggul
*pigul*, and the ברייתא braita *beraisa* splits its vote. So the only
way we can split the vote is not to choose between
רבי מאיר rabbi meir *Rabbi Meir* and the חכמים *Chachamim* but to
choose a third opinion of רבי *Rabbi*. So רבי *Rabbi* basically is
like the חכמים *Chachamim* that נסכים nesachim. *nesachim* don't have פיגול piggul
*pigul*, but he says but לוג Log, שמן *log shemen* that's a
different story. Okay, so רבי היא דאמר לוג שמן של מצורע מתנותיו
שרו ליה *Rabbi hi de-amar log shemen shel metzora matnosav sharu leih*.
וכיון דמתנותיו שרו ליה מתנותיו מפגלי ליה *ve-cheivan de-matnosav sharu leih matnosav
mefagli leih*. You can actually do פיגול piggul *pigul* during the act
of sprinkling. Okay, דתניא *detanya*: לוג שמן של מצורע מועלין בו עד
שיזרק הדם *log shemen shel metzora mo'alin bo ad she-yizarek ha-dam*, that
there's מעילה meilah *meilah* that's sanctified until the blood is put on
the—you know, on the altar, of the blood of the אשם asham
*asham*. נזרק הדם לא נהנין ולא מועלין *nizrak ha-dam lo nehenin ve-lo
mo'alin*. Once the blood is on the altar, you're not allowed לכתחילה
lechatchilah *le-chatchilah* to get benefit but there's no מעילה meilah *meilah*. Okay,
so that is
the חכמים's *Chachamim's* position, that when it comes with the קרבן korban
*korban*, the only thing that's
מתיר *matir* it is the blood. רבי אומר מועלין עד שיתן מתנותיו
*Rabbi omer mo'alin ad she-yiten matnosav*, that no, there is מעילה meilah
*meilah* even on this, even when it came with a קרבן korban
*korban*, until the sprinkling occurred of the oil itself. So since the
sprinkling of the oil is a מתיר *matir* of the status of
מעילה meilah. *meilah*, meaning in the end what can be done with
the oil by the way once after it's placed on the מצורע
*metzora*, the remainder... The remainder of the oil can be eaten by
כהנים, kohanim so it's just like anything else that's sanctified, you do
something, it's now permitted to be eaten. So רבי says, ah, but
here it's not just the blood that permits it to be eaten,
it is forbidden, there's still מעילה meilah until the sprinkling of the
oil. So part of the sprinkling of the oil itself permits the
rest to be eaten. So now we can say within the oil
itself, there's a מתיר, the oil is the מתיר for itself. Okay.
ושוין Veshavin but they agree שאסור באכילה עד שיתן מתן שבע ומתן
בהונות. she'asur be'achilah ad sheyiten matan sheva ve'matan behonot. Okay,
even the חכמים who say that there's no מעילה meilah agree that
you're not allowed to eat it until actually you finish all of
the applications. You know that's at least like לכתחילה and even רבי
presumably says that you're not allowed to eat it until you not
only do the sprinkling, but you also put it on the מצורע
and you change the status of the מצורע. Okay, but anyway, so
that's a nice answer. The answer is that even according to the
general approach like the חכמים that there's no מעילה meilah by נסכים
nesachim because since they come by themselves, they're not two components, you
could still argue that שמן is two components and therefore by שמן
it is included in מעילה. Okay? So it seems to be a
nice answer, but let's take a look. Conceptually, it's a nice
answer. אמרו קמיה דרבי ירמיה. Amru kamei d'Rebbi Yirmiah. So they say,
the
students said this answer of
what was רב יוסף's Rav Yosef answer in
front of רבי ירמיה. Rebbi Yirmiah. So אמר, so רבי ירמיה Rebbi
Yirmiah said
גברא רבה כרב יוסף לימא כי האי מילתא? gavra rabba k'Rav Yosef
leima ki hai milta?
Such a great person as like רב יוסף Rav Yosef would give
such an answer? It seems to us like a very good answer,
but let's take a look why the גמרא Gemara doesn't like it.
Oh, God. הרי לוג הבא בפני עצמו דלכולי עלמא מתנותיו שרו ליה
ולא מפגלין ליה.
Harey log haba bifnei atzmo d'le'chulei alma matnotav
sharu lei velo mepaglin lei.
One minute he said, we could have a debate between רבי and
the debate of רבי and the חכמים, I mentioned this parenthetically before,
about when does the oil become permissible to be consumed, was when
you were bringing it with the קרבן. korban The חכמים say that
the blood removes the מעילה status and רבי says, no, the blood
plus the oil removes the מעילה status. But what happens when you
bring the oil by itself? Presumably everybody would agree there that it's
the oil, that the oil removes the מעילה status. There is no
blood there in that case. Right? I mean, you brought it by
itself after. You brought the אשם asham. today and you're bringing the
oil three days later. So in that case, what's going to allow
the oil to be consumed? You can't say the blood of the
אשם. asham You didn't even designate the oil until after the אשם
asham was brought. So in that case, everybody is going to agree
that the oil, the sprinkling of the oil is מתיר the remainder
to be eaten and they will still say that there is no
פיגול. piggul Okay, let's take a look. הרי לוג הבא בפני עצמו
דלכולי עלמא מתנותיו שרו ליה ואמאי לא מפגלין ליה.
Harey log haba bifnei
atzmo d'le'chulei alma matnotav sharu lei ve'amai lo mepaglin lei. And even
though that's true that it makes it permissible to be eaten, there
still would not be פיגול. Pigul. Okay. דתניא we taught a ברייתא:
braita לא שמן של מצורע חייבין עליו משום פיגול מפני שדם
מתירו לבהונות דברי רבי מאיר.
lo shemen shel metzora chayavin alav mishum piggul mipnei she'dam matiro
lebehonot divrei Rebbi Meir. So רבי מאיר says when it comes with
the קרבן korban. there's פיגול Pigul, because you have the blood of
the קרבן korban. like רבי מאיר said by the נסכים. אמרו לו
לרבי מאיר ולא אדם מביא אשמו עכשיו ולוגו מכאן עד עשרה
ימים?
Amru lo leRebbi Meir ve'lo adam meivi ashamo achshav
velogo mikan ad asarah yamim? But you can bring your אשם Asham
today and your לוג, you know, a week later. So therefore clearly
it's not the blood that's מתיר the לוג. And he says as
we now know אמר להם אפילו לא אמרתי אלא בבאים עם האשם.
amar lahem afilu lo amarti ela bevaim im ha'asham. Fine, in that
case I agree there's no פיגול Pigul but when it comes with
the קרבן korban then there is פיגול Pigul because the blood is
מתיר. Okay, but now what do we see? That רבי מאיר says
that when the לוג comes after the קרבן korban. comes by itself
there's no פיגול. Pigul. But everybody agrees in that case that the
oil, the sprinkling of the oil is מתיר the remainder to be
eaten. So it's so just because the sprinkling of the oil is
מתיר the remainder to be eaten, nobody says that that makes it
that פיגול pigul. applies here. Presumably because this is something that why
not actually by the way? It makes a lot of sense. How
is this any different than a מנחה minchah or than a קרבן
korban, and so on. Well the difference is two parts. Number one
is, is this really a קרבן? Korban? Is number one type of
an interesting question. Do you identify the whole thing as a קרבן?
Korban It's something that you need to use to ritual blah blah
blah, but is it a קרבן? Korban And number two is and
maybe they're interrelated, do you put any of this thing on the
מזבח? Mizbe'ach, Since you don't put any of this thing directly on
the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, so therefore the גמרא Gemara says that's not a
good answer. You can't say the reason the ברייתא braita. said that
there was פיגול pigul by שמן is because שמן has a מתיר
the sprinkling. Because actually we know that even רבי מאיר agrees that
there's no פיגול pigul, by שמן when it comes by itself. So
there's just no פיגול pigul. so therefore that is so clearly it
is not because of the sprinkling that is not sufficient to say
that that applies. The only reason there would be פיגול pigul by
the שמן is if you link it to the קרבן Korban, and
you speak about the דם dam as a מתיר. But then we've
got a problem because the משנה Mishnah said there's פיגול pigul by
the שמן. And which means when it comes with the קרבן Korban,
because of the blood, the משנה mishnah the ברייתא Baraisa. excuse me,
and it says that there's no פגול pigul by the מנחת נסכים.
Well, so why not? How are you splitting your vote? So the
גמרא Gemara says,
okay, אלא אמר רבי ירמיה לעולם רבי מאיר היא וסמי מכאן נסכים.
ela amar rabbi yirmiah leolam rabbi
meir hi vesami mikan nesachim. So one answer is just get out
your eraser. Fine, it's רבי מאיר, there's פגול pigul because of the
blood of the קרבן and it's come coming with the קרבן and
take out that line of נסכים in the list of things that
there's no פגול. pigul. אמר אביי לעולם לא תסמי, amar abaye leolam
lo tismi, no, no, don't erase that. Okay, ותנא לוג הבא עם
האשם והוא הדין לנסכים הבאים עם הזבח.
vetana log habah im haasham vehu hadin lenesachim
habaim im hazevach. אביי's abaye going to say actually you're right. The
difference is not, no, no, the difference is not
לוג yes פגול, pigul, נסכים no פגול. pigul. The difference is for
רבי מאיר, with קרבן yes פגול, pigul, without קרבן no פגול. pigul.
So when it said there's פגול pigul by the לוג, it did
not mean the לוג and not the נסכים. It meant the לוג
and also the נסכים, anything that comes with a קרבן. And when
it says there's no פגול pigul by the נסכים, it didn't mean
the נסכים as opposed to the לוג. It meant there's no פגול
pigul whether נסכים or לוג when it comes without, not together with
the קרבן. So it's a little difficult read, why should we assume
one of them means with and one means without, but okay. That's
what he says. ותנא לוג הבא עם האשם והוא הדין לנסכים הבאים
עם הזבח. vetana log habah im haasham vehu hadin lenesachim habaim im
hazevach. It's not splitting the vote between לוג and נסכים. It's splitting
the vote and this isn't a splitting, it's רבי מאיר's position of
coming with the קרבן and not coming with the קרבן. When these
things come with the קרבן, the blood is מתיר and there's פגול.
pigul. והדר תנא נסכים הבאים בפני עצמן, vehadar tana nesachim habaim bifnei
atzman, and then when נסכים comes by themselves, והוא הדין ללוג הבא
בפני עצמו, vehu hadin lelog habah bifnei atzmo, the לוג comes by
itself, then there is no מתיר, there's no two components, and then
רבי מאיר concedes that there is no פגול. pigul.
Okay. חטאת העוף דמה מתיר בשרה לכהנים. chatas haof damah matir besarah
lekohanim. Okay, continuing here, it's not
clear if now we're continuing in the ברייתא Baraisa, or continuing in
our משנה. mishnah. But anyway, the חטאת העוף, chatas haof, so that's
included, because even though it's a bird, you have a מתיר. So
now that the fact that that fits into פגול pigul is pretty
obvious, once we say an עולת העוף olas haof fits into פגול
pigul and so on. But what we're actually going to use this
as an opportunity to do
is to say
how do we know the כהנים kohanim get to eat the meat
of the חטאת העוף? chatas haof? Because actually there's a couple of
things that it's not explicit who gets to eat them.
So we're now going to use this as an opportunity to list
things that the כהנים kohanim are entitled to eat
that it's not explicit elsewhere that they're entitled to eat and we're
going to explain where we learn that from. Okay. חטאת העוף דמה
מתיר בשרה לכהנים. chatas haof damah matir besarah lekohanim. מנלן הני מילי?
minan hani mili? How do you know the כהנים kohanim get to
eat it? דתני לוי, detani levi, לוי levi taught the ברייתא. כל
קרבנם. kol korbanam. Now this is at the end of פרשת קרח
parshas korach
where you know, קרח korach challenged the כהונה kehunah
and therefore at the end of פרשת קרח, parshas korach, it lists
all, it reinforces and lists all the things that the כהנים kohanim
are entitled to. רש"י rashi throws in just for you know, just
סתם stam רש"י rashi says, 'Oh yeah, this is like a משל
mashal that we have, which is like, oh it's good, you know,
it's a good thing the leg of my cow broke.' Like you
know, I guess you know, it made me realize that I don't
know, I needed to, it's a good thing my car broke down,
it made me realize I needed to do an overhaul and otherwise
I might have gotten into a big accident or whatever. So you
know, it's a good thing קרח korach challenged the
כהונה. kehunah. Now I'm going to reinforce to you everything you as
the כהנים Kohanim are entitled to. So that's the end of פרשת
קרח. parshas korach. So he says, so here's the פסוק, pasuk, it
says,
so it lists like everything, even things that we knew from before
you're entitled to, but there's some things that use the word כל.
kol. It says like this: זה יהיה לך מקדש הקדשים
מן האש.
zeh yihyeh lecha mikodesh
hakodashim min
haesh. This is
י"ח... yud-ches... nine, ten...
ט', tes,
right? ט', tes, right. כל קרבנם לכל מנחתם. kol korbanam lechol minchasam.
And a lot of our דרשות drashas is going to be on
the words
כל. kol. לכל מנחתם ולכל חטאתם ולכל אשמם. lechol minchasam ulechol chatasam
ulechol ashamam. I mean this just begging for a מדרש הלכה, midrash
halakhah, you know.
ולכל אשמם. ulechol ashamam.
And then the end of it, אשר ישיבו לי קדש קדשים לך
הוא ולבניך. asher yashivu li kodesh kodashim lecha hu ulevanecha.
אשר ישיבו לי, asher yashivu li, and then it's קדש קדשים לך
הוא,
kodesh kodashim
lecha hu,
so that means that the כהנים Kohanim are entitled to eat it,
right, ולבניך, ulevanecha, fine. Okay. So now we're just going to go
through this whole
part, this whole פסוק. pasuk. Okay. חטאת העוף מנלן הני מילי? chatas
haof minan hani mili? דתני לוי. detani levi. לוי levi taught, כל
קרבנם kol korbanam
לרבות
לוג שמן של מצורע. lerabbos log shemen shel metzora. So כל קרבנם...
kol korbanam... That gets to our question of is that really a
קרבן? You know, it's sanctified, it's brought in, it's used in a
ritual, but it's not like it's offered and it's not like it
goes on the מזבח. Mizbeach, So סלקא דעתך אמינא מן האש, Salka
Deitach Amina Min Ha'esh, קודשי קודשים מן האש. Kodshei Kodashim Min Ha'esh.
So something that doesn't go on the מזבח, Mizbeach, you know, so,
or you know, that none of it goes on the מזבח, Mizbeach
maybe it would not apply. כתב רחמנא והיי לאו מותר מן האש
הוא, Kasav Rachamana Vehei Lav Mutar Min Ha'esh Hu, not מותר, Mutar,
מותר Mutar leftover, קא משמע לן לכל קרבנם, Ka Mashma Lan Lechol
Korbanam, anything that is brought close, anything that is נקרב. Nikrav. Okay,
so,
and רש״י Rashi points out that it says by the לוג, והקריב
אותו לאשם ואת לוג השמן. Vehikriv Oso L'asham V'es Log Hashemen. So
the word קרבן is להקריב, Lehakriv, to bring close. So it actually
uses the word והקריב Vehikriv by the oil. Okay. ולכל מנחתם, U'lechol
Minchasam, we're going to get to the חטאת העוף, Chatas Ha'of, that's
where we started, we're getting there.
ולכל מנחתם לרבות מנחת העומר ומנחת הקנאות, U'lechol Minchasam L'rabos Minchas Ha'omer
U'minchas Hakena'os, that's last week's פרשה. Parsha. Okay, the מנחת העומר Minchas
Ha'omer and the מנחה Mincha by the, by the סוטה. Sotah. סלקא
דעתך אמינא ואכלו אותם אשר כופר בהם, Salka Deitach Amina V'achlu Osam
Asher Kuper Bahem, that you know, the thing that, that the eating
is like the whole idea of a קרבן is that it achieves
כפרה. Kapara. ומנחת העומר להתיר, U'minchas Ha'omer L'hatir, מנחת העומר Minchas Ha'omer
is brought not to achieve anybody's כפרה, Kapara, you know, not to
atone or change anybody's הלכה Halacha status, but it's come to allow
you to, to eat the new grain. ומנחת קנאות לברר עוון קאתיא,
U'minchas Kena'os L'varer Avon Kasya, מנחת עוון Minchas Avon also is coming
to clarify whether she sinned or not. קא משמע לן לכל מנחתם.
Ka Mashma Lan Lechol Minchasam. Okay. So כל קרבנם Kol Korbanam is,
כל Kol here is לוג שמן.
And רש״י Rashi says because it says like
והקריב. Vehikriv. Okay. לכל מנחתם Lechol Minchasam is עומר Omer and
סוטה. Sotah. I guess I'll say
קנאות, Kena'os, קנאות. Kena'os. Okay next. לכל חטאתם. Lechol Chatasam. ולכל חטאתם.
U'lechol Chatasam. Okay,
can you guess what we're going to include in לכל חטאתם? Lechol
Chatasam? This חטאת העוף Chatas Ha'of what we started with. ולכל חטאתם
לרבות חטאת העוף. U'lechol Chatasam L'rabos Chatas Ha'of. Now why would I
think not? But by the way it's interesting, the תורה Torah never
says that the כהנים Kohanim eat a חטאת העוף. Chatas Ha'of. So
that's actually, you know, anyway. סלקא דעתך אמינא נבילה היא Salka Deitach
Amina Neveila Hi because you break it through the back of the
neck. So maybe since it's not שחוטה Shechuta properly, maybe nobody gets
to eat it. You know, maybe you burn it outside or something.
Nope.
You get to. But the תורה Torah doesn't say to do that
either.
Right. Okay, I understand. But anyway now we know what to do.
ולכל אשמם. U'lechol Ashamam.
לרבות
אשם נזיר ואשם מצורע.
L'rabos Asham Nazir
V'asham Metzora. The אשם Asham brought by a נזיר Nazir when he
became טמא Tamei to start his נזירות Nezirus again and the אשם
brought by a מצורע that we've been referring to, סלקא דעתך אמינא
Salka Deitach Amina to purify himself, להכשיר קא אתו, Lehachshir Ka Asu,
those things are coming to start new, like you know, to not
for כפרה, Kapara, but for like, now it's interesting.
Well for a נזיר Nazir he became טמא, Tamei, so you know,
doesn't it say?
Yeah, but this is not to be מטהר Metahar him, this is
to start the new נזירות, Nezirus, מטהר Metahar him you do the
פרה אדומה Para Aduma whatever. Okay, but it's coming to like, you
know, to change his halachic status, you know, to reinstate his נזירות
Nezirus or to purify him from being a מצורע. קא משמע לן,
Ka Mashma Lan, so it teaches you. Now by the way, there
are other חטאות Chata'os that are coming to change your status, like
a חטאת Chatas of a יולדת Yoledes that is not מכפר, Mechaper,
but the assumption is that we already know, you don't need a
ריבוי. Ribbuy. Okay here, you know, are stuff that we otherwise wouldn't
have known. So maybe I would have thought since it never says
explicitly what to do here and these aren't a classic קרבן, maybe
they don't get to eat the meat. So it tells you they
do get to eat the meat. So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute. אשם מצורע בהדיא כתיב ביה. Asham Metzora Behedya Kesiv Bei. It
says explicitly by the אשם מצורע Asham Metzora that the כהנים Kohanim
eat it. אלא לרבות אשם נזיר כאשם מצורע. Ela L'rabos Asham Nazir
K'asham Metzora. Fine. To tell you an אשם נזיר Asham Nazir is
just like an אשם מצורע. Asham Metzora. Now you understand by the
way, because אשם נזיר, Asham Nazir, אשם מצורע Asham Metzora is a
little more classic. You do have a חטאת Chatas which is about
changing somebody's טומאה וטהרה Tumah V'tahara status. But אשם נזיר Asham Nazir
is not about טומאה וטהרה, Tumah V'tahara, the, he becomes טהור Tahor
by the אפר Eifer of the פרה אדומה. Para Aduma. The אשם
נזיר Asham Nazir is to actually allow the נזירות Nezirus to begin
again. So anyway, it's a little different, and it never says explicitly
that the כהנים Kohanim, eat it, so this is telling you that
the כהנים Kohanim get to eat it. Okay.
So now we're left with אשר ישיבו לי. Asher Yashivu Li. Now
that's not a כל. Kol. So this all is telling you something
you otherwise did not know. This is going to tell us something
we did know, but we're still going to identify, because as רש״י
Rashi says, a lot of the things in the list there in
קרח Korach are things that we already know and the תורה Torah
is just reinforcing it. Okay. So the next line is not going
to tell us something we didn't already know, but we're just going
to explain what it's including. Okay. אשר ישיבו לי זה גזל הגר.
Asher Yashivu Li Ze Gezel Hager. So if somebody steals and then
takes an oath and lies, they bring an אשם אשם גזילות Asham
Asham Gzeilos and they return the principal plus a fifth, which is
actually a fourth, to the owners. But the תורה Torah says if
there's nobody to return it to, it goes to the כהנים, Kohanim.
the principal plus the, the fine. So who has somebody that doesn't
have a relative to inherit him? Only a גר, Ger, okay, who
then doesn't have children after they convert. Okay. So that's גזל הגר.
Gezel HaGer. לכהן הוא שיהא אפילו כרישבתא אשה. L'chohen hu sheyehei afilu
karishbasa isha. This money that's given back, okay, so this is גזל
הגר. Gezel HaGer.
And you fully owned that money and it's not considered like somehow
sanctified money, you fully own it and you could go ahead and
marry a woman with it, that's usually an example of whether it's
considered totally yours. Okay, so for example, this is only going, this,
even to use for like for קידושין Kiddushin is only going on
the גזל הגר. Gezel HaGer. You go ahead and you try to
marry a woman with the meat of a חטאת, Chatas, which is
actually a משנה קידושין, Mishnah Kiddushin, and it doesn't take effect. Even
though you have a right to eat the meat of a חטאת,
Chatas, you don't own it. The phrase that the גמרא Gemara uses
is משלחן גבוה קזכו. Mishulchan Gavoa Kazchu. When you're eating the meat
of a חטאת, Chatas, you're sitting at God's table. Like when I
come to חנן'ס Chanan's house there and he invites me for שבת
Shabbos and I say, oh, you know what, I really don't have
time to stay, but I'm just going to take all the food
here and walk out. No, like he hasn't given me the food,
I mean I might ask if I take some home with me,
but he's allowing me to eat from his food. So when the
כהנים Kohanim, eat from this stuff, they're eating from God's food. Okay,
it's not theirs. And if they were to use that meat to
buy something with, to marry a woman, it would not take effect.
That's called משלחן גבוה קזכו. Mishulchan Gavoa Kazchu. But when you get
the money that was being returned, okay, that's money, that's not a
קרבן, and therefore that you can use to, you know, for your
own purposes.
Okay, תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
Yeah,
the end of the פסוק, Pasuk, קודש קודשים תאכלו כל זכר יאכל
אותו. Kodesh Kodashim tochlu kol zachar yochal oso.
I think that's the next פסוק, Pasuk, right?
Yeah.
Is that broadening it up?
Yeah, well no, not broadening it, but the קודש קודשים תאכלו Kodesh
Kodashim tochlu is going back on all of this as opposed to
the, it's sort of like this is like bracketed, the way חז"ל
Chazal are reading it. The גזל הגר Gezel HaGer you get to
use for everything you want, and then the next פסוק Pasuk is,
you know, but all the things that are really the sacrifices, that
has to be eaten in the temple. Okay, כל זכר. Kol zachar.
Oh, well the כל זכר kol zachar is even בעלי מום. ba'alei
mum. That's what כל זכר kol zachar includes. But still
male כהנים. Yeah, yeah, male כהנים, but even בעלי מום. ba'alei mum.
All right, תניא, Tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, רבי אליעזר אומר משום רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Eliezer omer
mishum Rabbi Yose HaGlili or רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, some have the
גרסה. girsa. פיגול בדבר הנעשה בחוץ. Pigul b'davar hane'aseh b'chutz. Now this
is going to be back to פיגול. pigul This is going to
be similar to the discussion of what do you call it, of
excluding
the פרים הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim, but this isn't going to be about
the פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim categorically excluded. It's going to be certain
acts of the פרים הנשרפים. Parim HaNisrafim. And as opposed to saying,
since the פרים הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim, the blood is not on the
מזבח, Mizbeach outer מזבח, mizbe'ach, it's, there's no פיגול, pigul, that's רבי
שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's position. This position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is
going to say, the only aspect of פיגול pigul, that applies to
פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim is עבודה avoda when you're doing an עבודה
avoda on the outer מזבח and it's about something that is going
to be eaten out in the temple courtyard, not in the היכל.
Heichal. Okay, so what is it that is done by the פרים
הנשרפים? Parim HaNisrafim? Okay, again, right? Here's you go, you know.
I'm sorry, wait, what was your statement? Because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
said that...
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says they're completely excluded. Okay, this is not
going to say they're completely excluded. There's, what is excluded is in
order, a פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim there is an element that פיגול
pigul applies to, but only when you do an עבודה, avoda, it's
going to refer...
first spilling the blood is done outside, right?
Yeah, so it's going to refer to, by the way, חוץ chutz
often means outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Here חוץ chutz
is going to mean in the עזרה. Azara. Okay, so this is
חוץ chutz and this is פנים. pnim. Okay, so only something that
an עבודה avoda is done out here and it only applies to
something which will, you know, which will be eaten or consumed by
the מזבח out here. So what's the one עבודה avoda that is
done out here for, until Michael said, what?
Just spilling the rest of the blood.
Spilling of the שיריים. shirayim. Okay, so and what is the one
thing that is eaten or consumed out here?
The אימורים, emurim, the אימורים.
emurim. The אימורים. emurim.
Okay, let's take a look at what he says. Okay,
רבי אליעזר
אומר
משום רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Eliezer omer
mishum Rabbi Yose, פיגול בדבר הנעשה בחוץ פיגל בדבר הנעשה בפנים לא
פיגל. Pigul b'davar hane'aseh b'chutz pigel b'davar hane'aseh b'pnim lo pigel.
If it's all about stuff, you know, in the עזרה, Azara, it's
פיגול. If it's stuff that's only in the היכל, Heichal, it's not.
כיצד? Keitzad? היה עומד בחוץ ואמר הריני שוחט להזות מדמו למחר, Haya
omed b'chutz v'amar hareni shocheit l'hazos midamo l'machar,
I'm shechting this פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim and I'm going to sprinkle
the blood on the inner altar tomorrow, tomorrow, לא פיגל, lo pigel,
שהמחשבה בחוץ, shehamachshava b'chutz,
the act, the עבודה avoda you were doing was on the outside
in the עזרה, Azara, בדבר הנעשה בפנים, b'davar hane'aseh b'pnim, but it
was about doing it about something that the עבודה avoda was going
to be done
on the inside. לא פיגל. Lo pigel. היה עומד בפנים ואמר הריני
מזה על מנת להקטיר אימורים ולשפוך שיריים למחר,
Haya omed b'pnim v'amar hareni mazei al m'nas l'haktir emurim v'lishpoch
shirayim l'machar, now let's say you were doing the עבודה... avoda... So
in that case, even though the part two is on the outside,
the עבודה avoda you're doing is on the inside. לא פיגול. Lo
Pigul. That's also not פיגול. שמחשבה בפנים, Shemachshava bifnim, you're thinking about
it when you're doing an עבודה avoda on the inside בדבר נעשה
בחוץ bidavar na'aseh bachutz about something done on the outside. You have
to be thinking about it when you're on the outside regarding an
עבודה avoda on the outside. So אבל, aval, היה עומד בחוץ ואמר
הריני שוחט לשפוך שיריים למחר.
haya omeid bachutz ve'amar hareini
shocheit lishpoch shiyarayim lemachar. Ah, so that the
שיריים shiyarayim actually because that part, the שיריים, shiyarayim, by the way
Michael, whether שיריים shiyarayim can count for this has to do whether
שיריים shiyarayim are מעכב me'akeiv for חטאת הפנימיות. chatas hapnimiyos. If שיריים
shiyarayim are not מעכב, me'akeiv, then they're not an עבודה avoda for
which פיגול thought matters. But you know which one act that is
done out here that is? It's the שחיטה. shechita. Okay, so now
actually it's interesting because it actually could have also included other things,
right? קבלה, kabbalah, הולכה. holacha. Okay, actually three of the עבודות, avodos,
I mean, that's an interesting question whether the הולכה holacha here or
the הולכה holacha here, but that actually got to be a discussion.
Okay, but at least two out of the four עבודות avodos are
done out here. Right, let's not forget פיגול,
do we have that פסוק passuk that says, according to the, you
know, it was not applied at all remember like, you
know, even if it was done on the, yeah, so that's, yeah,
that's relevant to this, let's not go there. Anyway, two out of
the four עבודות avodos apply out here. So you, if you do
it during these עבודות הדם avodos hadam regarding a second part of
the process that normally goes on the מזבח, the burning of אימורים
eimurim or this, then you have actually
אשכחיה ashkaicha accomplished פיגול.
Okay,
so you've done that outside and you did
the other part and because this is not Rabbi Shimon who categorically
excludes it, it's just that you need both components to be on
the outside. Okay. אבל, aval,
היה עומד בחוץ ואמר הריני שוחט לשפוך שיריים למחר להקטיר אימורים למחר,
haya omeid bachutz ve'amar hareini shocheit lishpoch shiyarayim lemachar lehaktir eimurim lemachar,
פיגל. pigel. שמחשבה בחוץ בדבר נעשה בחוץ. Shemachshava bachutz bidavar na'aseh bachutz.
Okay. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי מאי קרא? Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi: Mai krah? Where do you get this from? Where does he
get like limiting it this way? Because it's all a question about
what's the scope of it has to be like שלמים. shelamim Everybody
agrees like שלמים shelamim it has to have two components, a מתיר
and a remainder. Rabbi Shimon says it has to be like שלמים
shelamim and it has to be the blood is on the outer
altar. Rabbi Eliezer is saying here: It has to be like שלמים
shelamim. that you need the עבודה avoda and the thing that the
עבודה avoda is being done if the thought is about to be
stuff on the outside. So where does he get it? כאשר יורם
משור זבח השלמים. Ka'asher yuram mishor zevach hashelamim. This is what it
says by the פר הכהן המשיח. par hakohen hamashiach. It says: Do
to the entrails like you did to the entrails of a
שלמים. shelamim? That's, now that פר הכהן המשיח par hakohen hamashiach is
one of these פרים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, one of these things that
the blood is on the inside and it's burnt. So why is
a פסוק passuk by פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim connecting it to a
שלמים? shelamim. Okay, and it's not really to tell you a הלכה
halacha about the אימורים eimurim because if you read the פסוקים, pesukim,
all of the אימורים eimurim are listed. And after it lists all
the אימורים, eimurim, it says, "Oh, just like you do by a
שלמים." shelamim? So what the heck is the point to connect one
of these פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim to a שלמים? shelamim? וכי מה
למדנו משור זבח השלמים מעתה? Vechimah lamadnu mishor zevach hashelamim me'atah? What
do we, what do we have left to learn from a שלמים?
shelamim, We know about all of the אימורים, eimurim, it says it
right here. אלא מקיש פר כהן המשיח לשור זבח השלמים מה שור
זבח השלמים עד שיהיה מעשיו ומחשבותיו על המזבח החיצון,
Ela makish par kohen hamashiach leshor zevach hashelamim.
Mah shor zevach hashelamim ad sheyehei ma'asav umachshevosav al hamizbe'ach hachitzon, the
same way a שלמים, shelamim now of course now it's completely arbitrary,
now whatever, but completely the discretion of the דרשן darshen to decide
which features of a שלמים shelamim to emphasize, okay, but for Rabbi
Eliezer, he's emphasizing these features. Okay, so the same way a שלמים
shelamim both the act, the עבודה, avoda, and the thing that the,
the thought about what you're planning to do tomorrow relates to things
that are on the outside, אף פר כהן המשיח עד שיהיה מחשבותיו
ומעשיו על המזבח החיצון. af par kohen hamashiach ad sheyehei machshevosav uma'asav
al hamizbe'ach hachitzon. And only then is it like the שלמים that
laws of פיגול would apply to it. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה אמר רב: Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha amar
Rav: הלכה כרבי אליעזר שאמרו משום רבי יוסי. Halacha keRabbi Eliezer she'amru
mishum Rabbi Yose. We rule like Rabbi Eliezer that פרים הנשרפים, parim
hanisrafim, that, that פיגול does apply to פרים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, not
like Rabbi Shimon, but only when both the עבודה avoda that you're
doing it to during and the plan of what you're going to
do later relates to things on the outside. So אמר רבא, amar
Rava, so Rava said: הלכתא למשיחא? Hilchesa lemashiacha? You mean passing the
הלכה? halacha? This is a הלכה halacha that's never going to apply
until ימות המשיח. yemot hamashiach. So what, what do you mean, "Oh,
this is the הלכה"? halacha אמר ליה אביי, amlei Abaye, and we've
been
doing this entire time, אמר ליה אביי:
amlei Abaye: אלא מעתה כל שחיטת קדשים לא ליתני? Ela me'atah kol
shechitas kodashim lo lisni? So let's forget learning about, let's forget learning
זבחים. Zevachim.
By the way, it's
interesting that they call it שחיטת קדשים shechitas kodashim because חולין Chullin
is actually the technical term for מסכת חולין Masechet Chullin is שחיטת
חולין. shechitas chullin. And the technical term for מסכת זבחים, Masechet Zevachim,
although the Mishnah, although they began to call it זבחים, Zevachim, okay,
but apparently you see here that it's also called שחיטת קדשים. shechitas
kodashim. Okay, so let's not learn all of זבחים. Zevachim. Okay, לא
ליתני הלכתא למשיחא הוא? lo lisni hilchesa lemashiacha hu? אלא דרוש וקבל
שכר. Ela derosh vekabeil sachar. Okay, it's part of תלמוד תורה. Talmud
Torah. We want to learn what is it that these מצוות mitzvos
that God has given us, it's not about practical application. הכא נמי
דרוש וקבל שכר. hacha nami derosh vekabeil sachar. So what's bothering you?
So אמר הכי קאמינא, amar Hachi kamina, no, this is what bothers
me: הלכתא למה לי? Hilchesa lamah li? I understand discussing the theoretical
issues but... How but what does it mean to פסק pasken bottom
line? פסק paskening bottom line suggests that there's some relevance, okay, and
the only reason that there's relevance is if you've פסול pasuled me
so I'm going to know when there's a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Now maybe אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, I want to know
when there's a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash what the הלכה Halacha is
going to be, you know, but apparently that's like, you know what,
we'll worry about it then, maybe we'll have different things to consider
then. How are you going to lock in a פסק psak now,
you'd actually say like what does it mean to פסק pasken in
absence of a relevant context? Anyway so that's what bothers me. ושינוייא
v'shinuiya אמר ליה amar lei הלכה קאמינא, Halacha kamina, it's not clear
how these two answers are different. What bothers me is why are
we talking הלכה Halacha as opposed to talking the theoretical positions. Now
תוספות Tosafot says by the way, he goes through a number of
places that the גמרא Gemara פסק paskens הלכה, Halacha, which seem to
be completely theoretical and completely—like בן סורר ומורה?
Ben Sorer u-Moreh? Right.
Well no, but the question is do they use the language of
הלכה? Halacha? Again, we say we don't have a problem discussing the
positions. Are we going to use הלכה? Halacha? But תוספות Tosafot gives
a list of cases where the גמרא Gemara seems to פסק pasken
הלכה Halacha by something that's only relevant in a time of בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Most of them, you'll read it, most of them
he's able to explain that we're really only פסק paskening it because
it does have a practical relevance nowadays. There's a handful that he
can't explain that way, and then he just tries to say well
maybe what bothers the גמרא in particular here is that this situation
only comes if you've transgressed. If you had a פיגול thought you're
not supposed to have. So if you just wanted to tell me
a הלכה Halacha in general, how do we פסק pasken בית הלל
בית שמאי, Beis Hillel Beis Shammai, do you do four which is
מעכב me'akev one of the מתנות matanos or two of the מתנות,
matanos, you know, fine you'll tell me what the הלכה Halacha is.
But to tell me a הלכה Halacha that's relevant if somebody does
something wrong, like that's slight—so all that is
you mean all פיגול, right?
Yeah like פיגול, right, any הלכה Halacha about פיגול is a הלכה
Halacha that we sort of say like you know what, it's like
A, it assumes somebody's doing something wrong, and B, it's not relevant
nowadays, let's not talk about it. So that's how תוספות Tosafot explains
because there are times גמרא says הלכה Halacha by something that relates
to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and it's not bothered by this
question.
Yeah, when you say פסק pasken you mean using the word הלכתא,
Hilchesa, yeah?
הלכתא, Hilchesa, yeah, הלכתא.
Hilchesa. So if you just don't use that word then you're not
פסק? paskening?
Well I don't know if that's the two לשונות lishonos here. הלכתא
למאי Hilchesa l'mai or הלכה קאמינא. Halacha kamina. I mean if it
said הלכה כרבי יוסי, Halacha k'Rabbi Yosi, I don't know, to me
it's not clear what the difference of those two final answers are,
רש"י, Rashi, it's hard for me to see if רש"י Rashi is
saying that there is a difference. So but maybe you're right. Maybe
somehow the word הלכתא Hilchesa has a particular force, you know, that
just saying הלכה Halacha kid doesn't, but תוספות Tosafot doesn't seem to
read it that way. תוספות Tosafot is bothered just other cases where
the גמרא פסק paskens the הלכה Halacha is like X even if
it's a just a you know a future or a בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash oriented type of an issue.