Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף Daf is נ"ז Nun Zayin
57, the last דף Daf of the fifth פרק. Perek. We pick
up on נ"ז Nun Zayin עמוד א Amud Alef about ten lines
down, הבכור נאכל לכהנים. Habechor Ne'echal Lakohanim. We're dealing with the last
type of category of קדשים, Kodashim, which is בכור, Bechor, מעשר, Ma'aser,
and פסח, Pesach, which are קדשים קלים, Kodashim Kalim, but they're they
share the idea that it's one application of blood כנגד היסוד Keneged
HaYesod and then different ways in which they are eaten and by
whom they are eaten. So let's take a look but they're and
also for how long. בכור Bechor and מעשר Ma'aser are for two
days and the intervening night and פסח Pesach is only, בכור Bechor
is for כהנים, Kohanim, מעשר Ma'aser is for anybody for the owners,
it's all within ירושלים Yerushalayim and פסח Pesach is only eaten until
חצות Chatzot and it's only eaten roasted and only those that have
been a part of the group למנויו, Limnuyav, those that were counted
as a part of it. So הבכור נאכל לכהנים, Habechor Ne'echal Lakohanim,
the בכור Bechor is eaten for the כהנים. Kohanim. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, מנלן לבכור שנאכל לשני ימים ולילה? Minalan Labechor Shene'echal Lishnei Yamim
Velaila? Okay, so we're not dealing with the distinction about the כהנים
Kohanim and the בעלים, Ba'alim, כהנים Kohanim is actually anyway explicit, that
בשרם יהיה לך, Besaram Yihye Lach,
but we're dealing with the with the issue about two days and
the intervening night. שנאמר, Shene'emar, ובשרם יהיה לך כחזה התנופה וכשוק הימין
לך יהיה. Uvisharam Yihye Lach Kachazeh HaTenufa Ukhshok HaYamin Lach Yihye. Okay,
so there the flesh of the בכור Bechor will be to you
the כהנים, Kohanim, like the
like the breast that was waved and the thigh that was the
right thigh of the שלמים Shelamim for you it will be. הקישו
הכתוב לחזה ושוק של שלמים. Hekishu Hakatuv Lechazeh Veshok Shel Shelamim. So
the flesh of a בכור Bechor is linked to the breast and
of the thigh of the שלמים. Shelamim. So or the whatever the
calf. מה שלמים נאכלים לשני ימים ולילה אחד, Ma Shelamim Ne'echalim Lishnei
Yamim Velaila Echad, so the same way שלמים Shelamim is two days
and one night, אף בכור נאכל לשני ימים ולילה אחד. Af Bechor
Ne'echal Lishnei Yamim Velaila Echad. So the same by בכור, Bechor, okay,
so that's why the תורה Torah doesn't just say it's yours the
כהנים Kohanim you get the בכור, Bechor, but it links it to
the חזה ושוק Chazeh Veshok to learn out the idea of two
days and the intervening night. וזו שאלה נשאלה לפני חכמים בכרם ביבנה
Vezo She'ela Nish'ala Lifnei Chachamim Bekarem BeYavneh and this question was raised
to the sages in the literally vineyard of יבנה Yavneh when the
ישיבה, Yeshiva, the ישיבה Yeshiva of יבנה Yavneh where the learning was
after the destruction of the
בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. וזו נשאלה לפני חכמים ביבנה. Vezo Nish'ala Lifnei
Chachamim BeYavneh. בכמה נאכל Bekama Ne'echal for how long can you eat
the בכור Bechor the תורה Torah never spells out what the period
of eating it is. נענה רבי טרפון Na'ana Rabbi Tarfon ואמר לו
Ve'amar Lo לשני ימים ולילה אחד. Lishnei Yamim Velaila Echad. So רבי
טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said two days and the intervening night, didn't say
how he knew it.
היה שם תלמיד אחד Haya Sham Talmid Echad שבא לבית המדרש Sheba
Leveit HaMidrash לפני חכמים תחילה Lifnei Chachamim Techila there was there one
student that was the first time they were actually coming to the
study house to study. There was their first time of coming to
כרם ביבנה. Kerem BeYavneh.
And what was his name? רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili שמו
Shemo the future רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, okay, if it
was, ואמר לו Ve'amar Lo and so he said to רבי טרפון,
Rabbi Tarfon, רבי Rebbe מנלן לך? Minalan Lach? Where do you know
this from that a בכור Bechor is only is two days and
the intervening night? אמר לו Amar Lo בני Beni מה מצינו Ma
Matzinu שלמים קדשים קלים ובכור קדשים קלים. Shelamim Kodashim Kalim Uvechor Kodashim
Kalim. It's basically a מה מצינו, Ma Matzinu, we learn it out
from the paradigm of שלמים, Shelamim, שלמים Shelamim is light sacrifices, it
can be, you know ירושלים Yerushalayim
and בכור Bechor is קדשים קלים. Kodashim Kalim. מה שלמים נאכלים לשני
ימים ולילה אחד Ma Shelamim Ne'echalim Lishnei Yamim Velaila Echad so the
same way שלמים Shelamim is two days and the intervening night which
is explicit in the פסוק, Pasuk,
אף בכור נאכל לשני ימים ולילה אחד Af Bechor Ne'echal Lishnei Yamim
Velaila Echad the same is true by בכור. Bechor. אמר לו Amar
Lo רבי, Rebbe, so רבי יוסי
הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili said back to רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon but
my my teacher רבי Rebbe בכור מתנה לכהן וחטאת ואשם מתנה לכהן.
Bechor Matana LaKohen Vechatat Ve'asham Matana LaKohen. You know, that's one category
you could put it in is the שלמים Shelamim because they're קדשים
קלים Kodashim Kalim to be eaten all of ירושלים Yerushalayim but you
could put it in another category of things that are specifically קרבנות
Korbanot specifically for the כהנים. Kohanim. So בכור Bechor is given to
the כהן Kohen and a חטאת Chatat and אשם Asham are given
to the כהן. Kohen. מה חטאת ואשם ליום ולילה Ma Chatat Ve'asham
Leyom Velaila so maybe it should be in that category in the
same way חטאת Chatat and אשם Asham is only a day is
only a day and the following night, אף בכור ליום ולילה Af
Bechor Leyom Velaila so בכור Bechor also only be one and the
following night. אמר לו, Amar Lo, so רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said
back to him, נידון דבר מדבר ונמו דבר מדבר. Nidon Davar MiDavar
VeNimo Davar MiDavar. Let no no let's let's compare things to what
they are more similar to now that's exactly the question which is
it more similar to but he's now going to give him an
argument that בכור Bechor another reason בכור Bechor is more similar to
שלמים Shelamim and not to בכור Bechor and מעשר Ma'aser בכור Bechor
and not to excuse me חטאת Chatat and an אשם. Asham.
שלמים אין באין על חטא אף בכור אינו בא על חטא. Shelamim
Ein Ba'in Al Cheit Af Bechor Eino Ba Al Cheit. So both
שלמים Shelamim and a בכור Bechor are not coming for any sin.
So therefore and as we've said they're both
קדשים קלים. Kodashim Kalim. מה שלמים נאכלים לשני ימים ולילה אחד אף
בכור נאכל לשני ימים ולילה אחד ma shelamim ne'echalim lishnei yamim v'layla
echad af bechor ne'echal lishnei yamim v'layla echad. hence we should put
it the בכור Bechor in the same category of שלמים Shelamim and
say that it is two days and the intervening night. אמר
לו Amar Lo רבי, Rebbe, so so רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose
HaGlili said Rabbi Yosi ha-Glili said back to Rabbi Tarfon my teacher,
נידון דבר מדבר וילמוד דבר מדבר. nidun davar mi-davar v'yilmod davar mi-davar.
I agree to you you should learn something from what it's similar
to, but here's why I'm going to tell you again that it
is more similar or at least as similar to a חטאת chatas
and an
אשם. asham. וילמוד דבר מדבר, v'yilmod davar mi-davar, חטאת ואשם מתנה לכהן
בכור מתנה לכהן. chatas v'asham matana la-kohen bechor matana la-kohen. Number one
as I said, they're both a gift to a כהן. kohen. And
number two, מה חטאת ואשם אין באים בנדר ונדבה, ma chatas v'asham
ein ba'im b'neder u-nedava, it's true that there's a difference whether they're
coming for חטא cheit or not, but here's a similarity: a חטאת
chatas and an אשם asham is an obligation, you don't give it
as a free will offering. אף בכור אינו בא בנדר ונדבה, af
bechor eino ba b'neder u-nedava, בכור bechor is אינו בא בנדר ונדבה,
eino ba b'neder u-nedava, בכור bechor is you're obligated, it's automatically קדוש,
kadosh, it's the first animal, the פטר רחם. peter rechem.
So therefore it should be similar to a חטאת chatas and an
אשם. asham. מה חטאת ואשם נאכלים ליום אחד ולילה אחד אף בכור
נאכל ליום אחד ולילה אחד. ma chatas v'asham ne'echalin l'yom echad v'layla
echad af bechor ne'echal l'yom echad v'layla echad. So therefore it should
be again like a חטאת chatas and an אשם. asham. So just
based on a מה מצינו, ma matzinu, I'm going to argue there's
just as much reason to compare it to a חטאת chatas and
an אשם asham as there is to a
שלמים. shelamim. Okay. קפץ רבי עקיבא ונסתלק רבי טרפון. kafatz Rebbi Akiva
v'nistalek Rebbi Tarfon. Rabbi Akiva jumped up and Rabbi Tarfon was sort
of removed. Rabbi Akiva said, okay let me try here, let me
step in okay and answer and answer this new תלמיד, talmid, this
רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yosi ha-Glili. So אמר
לו, amar lo, so Rabbi Akiva said to Rabbi Yosi ha-Glili, הרי
הוא אומר ובשרם יהיה לך. harei hu omer u-vesaram yihye lach. So
like the ברייתא braita opened up, it's an explicit פסוק pasuk that
links a בכור bechor to the חזה chaze and the שוק shok
of a שלמים. shelamim. הקישו הכתוב לחזה ושוק של שלמים. hikisho ha-kasuv
l'chaze v'shok shel shelamim. מה שלמים נאכלים לשני ימים ולילה אחד Ma
Shelamim Ne'echalim Lishnei Yamim Velaila Echad אף בכור נאכל לשני ימים ולילה
אחד. Af Bechor Ne'echal Lishnei Yamim Velaila Echad It's explicitly linked to
the חזה chaze and a שוק shok of presumably a שלמים shelamim
and therefore the same way that's two days and a night, the
same is true for a בכור. bechor. אמר לו, amar lo, so
Rabbi Yosi ha-Glili was not ready to give up. Rabbi Yosi said,
הוקש לחזה ושוק של שלמים, hukash l'chaze v'shok shel shelamim, אתה הקישו
לחזה ושוק של שלמים. ata hikisho l'chaze v'shok shel shelamim. You,
yes it's true the פסוק pasuk links it to the חזה chaze
and the שוק. shok. You assume that it was the חזה chaze
and the שוק shok of a standard
שלמים, shelamim, ואני מקישו לחזה ושוק של תודה. va'ani mekisho l'chaze v'shok
shel toda. But I'll say no, it's what it's linked to is
the חזה chaze and the שוק shok of a תודה, toda, not
of a שלמים. shelamim. מה תודה נאכלת ליום ולילה אחד אף בכור
נאכל ליום ולילה אחד. ma toda ne'echeles l'yom v'layla echad af bechor
ne'echal l'yom v'layla echad.
And the same way a תודה toda is only one day and
night, the same true is about a בכור. bechor. Yes it's linked
to a חזה chaze and שוק, shok, but how do you know
חזה chaze and שוק shok of a שלמים? shelamim? Maybe it's חזה
chaze and שוק shok of a תודה? toda? Okay, good question. אמר
לו, amar lo, so Rabbi Akiva said back to him, הרי הוא
אומר ובשרם יהיה לך. harei
hu omer
u-vesaram yihye lach. So the beginning of the פסוק pasuk said ובשרם
יהיה לך כחזה התנופה וכשוק התרומה. u-vesaram yihye lach k'chaze ha-tenufa u-ch'shok
ha-teruma. And there maybe you would be right, maybe it would be
limited to a תודה toda and it would be the day and
the night. שאין תלמוד
לומר לך יהיה. she'ein talmud lomar lach yihye. The פסוק pasuk didn't
have to go and repeat afterwards and say לך יהיה. lach yihye.
It already said יהיה לך. yihye lach. So מה תלמוד לומר יהיה
לך? ma talmud lomar yihye lach? Why does the פסוק pasuk end
by repeating יהיה לך? yihye lach? הוסיף הכתוב
הוויה אחרת בבכור.
hosif ha-kasuv havaya acheres
b'bechor. It's giving you another way that it's yours, like it's לך
יהיה יהיה לך. lach yihye yihye lach. It's even more yours. So
even more yours meaning you have it for the longer period of
time, not the shorter period of time.
הוויה אחרת בבכור. havaya acheres b'bechor. So that's how we know it
from יהיה לך yihye lach and לך יהיה lach yihye tells us
that it's the larger period of time, the שלמים shelamim חוק chok
and the חזה chaze and the שוק shok of the שלמים, shelamim,
not of the תודה. toda. וכשנאמרו דברים לפני רבי ישמעאל, u-ch'she-ne'emru devarim
lifnei Rebbi Yishmael, now when this whole discussion was reported to Rabbi
Yishmael, אמר להן, amar lahen, he said to Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi
Tarfon,
לכו ואמרו לו, lechu v'imru lo, or he said to those excuse
me who reported to him, go back and say to Rabbi Akiva,
טעית, ta'ita, you made a mistake when you basically conceded the point
that yes from the first part of the פסוק pasuk maybe it
was just linked to a תודה, toda, but what then was said
לך
יהיה, lach yihye,
that that went and gave it and even to the larger category
of the שלמים. shelamim. But by the beginning of the פסוק, pasuk,
ובשרם יהיה לך, u-vesaram yihye lach, that could've, you're right, you could've
been linked
to the שוק shok and the
חזה chaze of the תודה. toda. So he says tell Rabbi Akiva,
טעית, ta'ita, you made an error when you conceded that point.
קודם מהיכן למדו משלמים? kodem me-heichan lamdu mi-shelamim? How do you know
that there is a חזה chaze and a שוק shok by a
תודה? toda? The תודה toda never says there's a חזה chaze and
a שוק shok by a תודה. toda. It only says you know
it sort of connects a תודה toda to a שלמים shelamim or
it says a תודה toda is a type of שלמים, shelamim, but
it never explicitly says that there's a חזה chaze and a שוק
shok of a תודה. toda. So you only know that that exists
by a תודה toda from a שלמים. shelamim. And you probably anticipate
what's about to come. וכי דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? v'chi
davar ha-lamad b'heikesh chozer u-melamed b'heikesh?
So you only know that a תודה toda has a חזה chaze
and a שוק shok from a שלמים. shelamim. So now when the
פסוק... pasuk... The פסוק pasuk says by the בכור bechor it is
like the חזה chazeh and שוק, shoke, you can't say it's like
the חזה chazeh and שוק shoke of a תודה todah which then
is only one day because that you only know that it exists
by a תודה todah from a שלמים. shlamim. So something that you're
learning from a היקש, hekkesh, a תודה's todah linked to a שלמים
shlamim and therefore you know it has a חזה chazeh and שוק,
shoke, you can't go and again learn, apply another היקש hekkesh and
get it to tell you that the בכור bechor is like the
חזה chazeh and the שוק shoke of a תודה todah and it's
one day. You can't do a two-step process like that, דבר הלמד
בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש. davar halamad behekkesh chozer umelamed behekkesh. So if
the בכור bechor is being linked to a חזה chazeh and שוק,
shoke, it must be being linked to a direct חזה chazeh and
שוק shoke of the שלמים shlamim itself, not one that was itself
derived, not that of the תודה. todah. So your first answer, you
should have stuck by your first answer, just from the beginning of
the פסוק pasuk we know that it is being linked to the
שלמים shlamim and not to the תודה. todah. היקש הא אין לך
אלא למידו מן האחרון, Hekkesh ha ein lach ela lemido min ha'acharon,
you should not go by your second answer that yes, it was
linked by a תודה todah but the extra לך תהיה lecha tihyeh
is coming to tell you even more, even a שלמים. shlamim. No,
don't go by that answer. אלא בלשון ראשון, Ela belashon rishon, you
should have gone by your first answer that it's being linked directly
to a שלמים. shlamim. It can't be linked to a תודה todah
because that itself was only learned from a שלמים. shlamim. Okay, that
seems like a very good answer. So now we're going to have
to explain why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva did retract, but we also
want to understand what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael does with the extra
פסוק pasuk of לך תהיה. lecha tihyeh. ורבי ישמעאל האי לך תהיה
מאי עביד ליה? VeRabbi Yishmael hai lecha tihyeh mai avid lei? Since
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael does not need לך תהיה lecha tihyeh to
tell you two days, what does he do with the לך תהיה
lecha tihyeh of the link of the בכור bechor to the חזה
chazeh and the שוק shoke of the שלמים? shlamim? מאי עביד ליה?
Mai avid lei? לימד על בכור בעל מום שהוא מתנה לכהן. Limad
al bechor ba'al mum shehu matanah lekohen.
You're right, the לך תהיה lecha tihyeh is giving the כהנים kohanim
something more by a בכור, bechor, but not more to teach you
not one day, two days, that we know anyway. The more it's
giving you by the בכור bechor is to teach you that even
if a בכור bechor has a מום, mum, it goes to the
כהן kohen and the כהן kohen eats it without bringing it as
a קרבן. korban. Okay, שלא מצינו בכל התורה. shelo matzinu bechol haTorah.
You never found that in the entire תורה. Torah. רש"י Rashi says
it means nowhere else in the תורה Torah does it say that
when it has a מום mum it goes to the כהן, kohen,
but תוספות Tosafos elsewhere says it means that nowhere in the תורה
Torah do you have anything like this, that you don't have to
redeem it and you eat something that otherwise would have been brought
as a קרבן korban and you straight eat it with its מום
mum without redeeming it and without bringing it as a קרבן. korban.
But anyway, either way, from the extra לך תהיה lecha tihyeh you
learn from here that with a מום mum it still goes to
the כהן kohen and he eats it without bringing it as a
קרבן. korban. Okay, now for רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, now we're going
to ask the question that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael sort of asked
on רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. ורבי עקיבא יליף ליה מבשרם. VeRabbi Akiva
yalif lei mibesaram. Okay, but
first we have to explain where does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva know
this הלכה halacha that a בכור בעל מום bechor ba'al mum goes
to a כהן? kohen? ורבי עקיבא יליף ליה מבשרם. VeRabbi Akiva yalif
lei mibesaram.
It says בשרם besaram in the plural, יהיה לך. yihyeh lach. What's
their in the plural? חד תם וחד בעל מום. Chad tam vechad
ba'al mum. Their flesh of the בכורות bechorot whether it be a
תם tam or a בעל מום. ba'al mum. So from the plural
בשרם besaram is where he learns and not from the לך תהיה.
lecha tihyeh. From the plural בשרם besaram is where you learn that
a בכור בעל מום bechor ba'al mum also goes to a
כהן. kohen. ורבי ישמעאל ורבי ישמעאל אמר מבשרם דהני בכורות קאמר. VeRabbi
Yishmael veRabbi Yishmael amar mibesaram dehanei bechorot ka'amar. No, בשרם besaram plural
doesn't mean תם tam and a בעל מום. ba'al mum. בשרם besaram
in the plural means of all the בכורות bechorot we've been mentioning,
whether it's a שור shor or עז ez or כשב, kesev, whatever
type of animal it is. But it is not coming to include
that of a בעל מום. ba'al mum. That you learn from לך
תהיה. lecha tihyeh. Fine, so that's how both רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael learn out that a בכור בעל מום
bechor ba'al mum goes to a כהן. kohen. Now back to the
other question.
Now במאי קמיפלגי? bemai kamiflagi? What does רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael debate? Why did רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva indeed
retract his position?
Why was he bothered by the fact that רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yose HaGelili said, "Oh, why don't we link it to a חזה
chazeh and a שוק shoke of a תודה?" todah? You can't do
that. It's דבר הלמד בהיקש אינו חוזר ומלמד בהיקש. davar halamad behekkesh
ein chozer umelamed behekkesh. So the גמרא Gemara
says here, no, here's why רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thought that רבי
יוסי הגלילי's Rabbi Yose HaGelili challenge was a good one. מר סבר
הימנו ודבר אחר הוי היקש ומר סבר לא הוי היקש. Mar savar
heimenu vedavar acher havei hekkesh umar savar lo havei hekkesh. Because whether
this principle of something you learned from a היקש hekkesh you can't
go and apply elsewhere, the question is does that apply when half
of it was already in the פסוק pasuk and half of it
was learned from a היקש? hekkesh? So the way that works is
you have categories A, B, and C. Okay? Now in category A,
you're מחדש mechadesh new הלכה halacha X. Because B is linked to
A, X now applies to B. Because C is linked to B,
you want to go, you want to apply X not only to
B but also to C. That's דבר הלמד בהיקש אינו חוזר ומלמד
בהיקש. davar halamad behekkesh ein chozer umelamed behekkesh. But what if
actually in category B you already knew half of X and the
link to A was telling you the other half of X? And
then maybe if B is linked to C, then maybe if... Maybe
you can then, since you're learning it both from something that's already
in ב B to ג, C, you can carry with it the
part that you also learned from א. A. So how does that
apply here? Because here, the basic point we're trying to learn from
ב B to ג, C, from תודה Toda to שלמים, Shelamim, from
תודה Toda to בכור Bechor is one day,
not two days. Well the idea that a תודה Toda is only
eaten for one day is explicitly written by a תודה. Toda. What
we are learning from א, A, from the case of שלמים, Shelamim,
is that there's a thing called the חזה ושוק, Chaze vehaShok, the
חזה ושוק Chaze vehaShok is given to the כהן Cohen from the
תודה. Toda. So then, when we're now moving that from ב B
to ג, C, the חזה Chaze and the שוק Shok sort of
is what links ב B to ג, C, but the הלכה Halacha
that we're applying to ג C is actually something we already knew
in ב B itself. It's already the idea of a day was
already something that was explicit by תודה Toda as well. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says since the idea of a day and that's
the point of the link of ב B to ג C is
already in ב, B, even though what makes us allows us to
make the link is we learned from א A that there's a
חזה ושוק, Chaze vehaShok, that to me is not the issue of
דבר הלמד בהקיש davar halamad behekesh is now חוזר ומלמד בהקיש. chozer
umelamed behekesh. And that's why I thought it was a good point
and I had to go ahead and learn it out from ליצחק
יהיה. Leitzchak Yihiyeh. Okay. הא מן דאמר חביב בשר ולא הוי היקש,
Ha mandamar chaviv basar velo havei hekesh, בשלמא למאן דאמר לא הוי
היקש bishlama lemandamar lo havei hekesh according to the one that says
that this is not considered a היקש, hekesh, so it allows you
to go apply from ב B to ג C when it's partly
already in ב B itself. היינו
דכתיב וכן יעשה לאהל מועד Hainu dichtiv vechen yaaseh lOhel Moed and
now we're going to do a totally different הלכה. Halacha.
The idea of the sprinkling of the blood on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur
of the פר par and the שעיר, seir, of the ox and
the goat. So by the פר, par, it says explicitly
that there are seven sprinkles below, but it doesn't tell you how
many sprinkles above. Okay, by the פר par it says והזה באצבעו
על פני הכפורת
קדמה ולפני הכפורת
יזה שבע פעמים מן הדם באצבעו. vehizah beetzbao al pnei hakaporet kedma
vlifnei hakaporet yazeh sheva peamim min hadam beetzbao. So it doesn't tell
you how many times above, but it says seven below. When it
speaks about the
שעיר, seir, it says והזה אותו על הכפורת ולפני הכפורת. vehizah oto
al hakaporet vlifnei hakaporet. So אותו oto is singular. So by the
שעיר seir you learn the one above, but it's not explicit the
seven below. And the two of them are
linked by the פסוק. passuk. It says ועשיתם כאשר עשה לדם הפר.
veasatam kaasher asa ldam hapar. Okay, so
from one of them one says seven, one says one, and because
they're linked you learn both of them have one above and seven
below. And then how much sprinkling do you do outside of the
קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim onto the פרוכת? Parochet? So there it says,
so let's take a look.
דכתיב וכן
יעשה לאהל מועד. dichtiv vechen yaaseh lOhel Moed. כשם שמזה לפנים אחת
למעלה ושבע למטה מדם הפר כך מזה בהיכל. kshem shemizah lifnim achat
lemaala vsheva lemata midam hapar kach mazeh baheichal. The
same way one above and seven below by the פר par in
the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, the same in the היכל. Heichal. וכשם
שלפני ולפנים אחת למעלה ושבע למטה מדם השעיר כך מזה בהיכל. ukshem
shelifnei vlifnim achat lemaala vsheva lemata midam haseir kach mazeh baheichal. The
same way it's one and seven by the
שעיר, seir, it's the same by the היכל. Heichal. Okay, so now
how do you do that? Right? You only learned
by the ox you only learned that it had one above from
the שעיר. seir. And now you're learning from the שעיר seir to
the פר par one above and now that's א A to ב
B and now you're going ב B to ג C and you're
saying also out of the היכל Heichal you're going to be doing
one above and seven below, but you only knew the one above
because you were already linking you already did the א A to
ב, B, you linked the פר par to the שעיר. seir. So
if you say הימנו ודבר אחר himenu vedavar acher you can do
it, it makes sense. You already knew the seven by the פר,
par, you're just adding the one, but part of it is in
the פר par itself. So then when the פר par inside the
קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim is linked to the פר par in the
היכל, Heichal, the same way you can go from ב B to
ג C and you can take the seven, you can also take
that extra thing that was learned with the היקש hekesh and you
can also do the one. Okay, ב B to ג C are
linked by the seven on the inside, seven on the outside, that's
the link inside to outside, and therefore you can transport with it
the extra one when you learn from the שעיר seir to the
פר par about the one above, and say the same for the
שעיר. seir. So that works because you have an anchor in the
thing itself and that lets you transport. Okay, כך
מזה בהיכל. kach mazeh baheichal. אלא למאן דאמר דהוה היקש מאי איכא
למימר? ella lemandamar dehavei hekesh mai ika lemimar? But if even that
is
considered a דבר הלמד בהקיש שחזר ומלמד בהקיש, davar halamad behekesh shechozer
umelamed behekesh, how do you manage to link פר par and the
שעיר seir to do one and seven on the inside and then
do another link to get them both on the outside? So the
גמרא Gemara says מקומות הוא דגמירי מהדדי. mekomos hu dgemiri mehadadi. No,
no, no. There we're not linking the same thing. The first thing
links the פר par to the שעיר. seir. and that gets you
the one and the seven. Then we're not saying this פר par
is linked to some other animal. We're saying the inside of the
היכל Heichal is linked to the outside of or the inside of
the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kadashim is linked to the outside of the
קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kadashim. So because the things that are being linked
are something different, that doesn't count like a דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר
ומלמד בהיקש. davar halamad b'hekesh chozer u'melamed b'hekesh.
Top of נז עמוד ב. Nun Zayin amud Bet.
ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'it eima, if you want I can tell you, חוץ
מפנים בחד זימנא גמיר. chutz mi'pnim b'chad zimna gamir. No, you're learning
it all out at one time. What does this mean? So there's
a whole discussion רש"י תוספות, Rashi Tosafot, but basically what רש"י Rashi
says is as follows: that in this case, even if it wasn't
for דבר הלמד בהיקש, davar halamad b'hekesh,
you know, you would there would already be something to learn out
from B to C. Okay, the פר par is seven on the
inside, so the link of the inside to the outside would tell
you seven on the outside. So once you're and that's straight, there's
no so there's nothing being transported. You're straight learning seven on the
inside, seven on the outside. Once you're doing that, you're able also
to learn what you learned from the פר par to the שעיר
se'ir of one above. Okay, now that's not the same as we
said before about הימנו ודבר אחר. himenu v'davar acher. Because הימנו ודבר
אחר, himenu v'davar acher, there was nothing you were learning first, right?
The הימנו ודבר אחר himenu v'davar acher was, you know, the whole
thing we only wanted to learn one thing from the בכור. bechor.
We wanted to learn that it was for one day. How were
we going to do that? Because it was linked to the חזה
ושוק chazeh v'shok of a תודה. todah. Okay, there was only one
הלכה. halacha. Without but there is no חזה ושוק chazeh v'shok of
a תודה todah unless we learn A to B, unless we apply
שלמים shelamim to תודה. todah. Okay, so so that says that you
can't do. That's דבר הלמד בהיקש אין חוזר ומלמד בהיקש. davar halamad
b'hekesh ein chozer u'melamed b'hekesh. I know the idea of one day
is already said by תודה, todah, but there's nothing to be learnt
out until you link it and say that there's a חזה ושוק.
chazeh v'shok. So that's דבר הלמד בהיקש אין חוזר ומלמד בהיקש. davar
halamad b'hekesh ein chozer u'melamed b'hekesh. And I'm not persuaded by the
fact that okay, but you have the idea of one day by
a תודה. todah. There's nothing is happening until you are מלמד בהיקש.
melamed b'hekesh. And therefore you can't be חוזר ומלמד בהיקש. chozer u'melamed
b'hekesh. Here, even without any double היקש, hekesh, you're applying seven of
the פר par on the inside to seven of the פר par
on the outside. And once you're able to do that, you can
piggyback with it and also get what you learned with the היקש,
hekesh, which is one of the שעיר se'ir above. Okay, fine. Now
the גמרא Gemara goes on.
בשלמא למאן דאמר דהוה היקש, Bishlama l'man d'amar d'havei hekesh, according to
the one that says that when you have הימנו ודבר אחר himenu
v'davar acher it counts as a היקש, hekesh, when part of it
already existed there, it still counts as a היקש hekesh and you
can't apply it onwards.
היינו דכתיב ממושבתיכם תביאו לחם תנופה. Hainu d'chtiv mi'moshvoteichem tavi'u lechem tnupha.
Okay, so this is talking about the you know, the what do
you call it? the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem on שבועות Shavuot and
it says שתים שני עשרונים. shtayim shnei esronim. So those are two
loaves and each one is an עישרון. issaron. And from there we
learn out that when the תורה Torah tells you to bring ten
loaves by the or tells you bringing loaves of חמץ chametz by
תודה, todah, and we learn out that that's ten, ten of חמץ
chametz and thirty of מצה, matzah, that those ten loaves of חמץ,
chametz, each loaf is an עישרון. issaron. So the ten loaves are
ten עשרונות. isronot. Why? Because by the תודה, todah, which also has
חמץ, chametz, each loaf is an עישרון. issaron. Okay, so that's how
we're going to learn out how much are the loaves by the
תודה. todah. ממושבתיכם תביאו לחם תנופה שאין תלמוד לומר תביאו. Mi'moshvoteichem tavi'u
lechem tnupha she'ein talmud lomar tavi'u. Why does it say
תביאו? tavi'u? ממושבתיכם לחם תנופה, Mi'moshvoteichem lechem tnupha, מה תלמוד לומר תביאו?
mah talmud lomar tavi'u? כל שאתם מביאים ממקום אחר הרי הוא כזה.
Kol she'atem mevi'im mi'makom acher harei hu kaze. Anytime you are bringing
חמץ, chametz, it will be like the חמץ chametz that you are
bringing by the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. מה להלן עישרון לחלה, Mah
lehalan issaron l'challah, the same way by the by the שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem for each of the two חלות challot it is a
full עישרון issaron of flour, אף כאן עישרון לחלה, aph kan issaron
l'challah, the same by a תודה todah for each one of the
ten loaves of חמץ, chametz, it is a full עישרון issaron of
flour. אי מה להלן שני עשרונים אף כאן שני עשרונים, Ei mah
lehalan shnei esronim aph kan shnei esronim, why don't we say differently?
By the by the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem it is two עשרונים
esronim for all of the חמץ, chametz, all two loaves. So here
too for all of the חמץ, chametz, all ten loaves, it'll be
just two עשרונים. esronim. אף כאן שני עשרונים, Aph kan shnei esronim,
תלמוד לומר תהיינה. talmud lomar tihyena. No, תהיינה tihyena tells you each
loaf is one עישרון. issaron. Okay, it's another גמרא Gemara learns out
how we exactly get it from there. Okay, so anyway that tells
us one עישרון issaron per חמץ chametz loaf in the תודה todah
of the ten loaves of חמץ chametz in the תודה. todah.
ולמדנו, V'lamadnu, the ברייתא braita continues,
עשרה לחמץ. asara l'chametz. Period. That tells you for the ten loaves
of חמץ, chametz, one עישרון issaron per loaf. עשרה למצה מניין? Asara
l'matzah minayin? How do you know for the מצה? matzah? תלמוד לומר
על חלת לחם חמץ, Talmud lomar al challat lechem chametz, נגד חמץ
הוי מצה. neged chametz havei matzah. So there's a total of ten
עשרונות isronot for the חמץ, chametz, one עישרון issaron per loaf. ten
עשרונות *issronot* for the חמץ *chametz*, how do you know ten עשרונות
*issronot* for the מצה *matza*, and there are thirty loaves of מצה
*matza*? So how do you know? So it's each loaf is only
a third the size. But how do you know the total amount
of weight, ten the ten עשרונות *issronot* for חמץ *chametz*, similarly ten
עשרונות *issronot* for the thirty loaves of מצה *matza* for a תודה
todah *toda*? So it says, על חלת לחם חמץ *al challat lechem
chametz*, on the, you know, on the loaves of the חמץ *chametz*,
you know, you should bring the מצה *matza*. So נגד חמץ הביא
מצה *neged chametz havi matza* equal to the חמץ *chametz*, all of
the מצה *matza* loaves equal all of the חמץ *chametz* loaves. Fine,
that's the דרשה *drasha*. So now what the, how is this relevant
for our issue? Because we are learning the idea of ten עשרונות
*issronot* or an עישרון *issaron* per loaf. We are learning from, you
know, A to B, we are learning from שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*
to the חמץ *chametz* of the תודה *toda*, and then we are
learning the ten עשרונות *issronot* of the חמץ *chametz* to ten עשרונות
*issronot* for the מצה *matza* from the תודה *toda* from B to
C. Okay, so that's a straight now. So that's a היקש חוזר
ומלמד בהיקש *hekesh chozer umelamed be'hekesh*.
But it is הימנו בדבר אחר *himenu bedavar acher* because the idea
of ten loaves was already there in the case of the חמץ
*chametz*. What we just, we just learned one piece of it, the
idea of an עישרון *issaron* per loaf to apply to the חמץ
*chametz* of the תודה *toda*. That was the היקש *hekesh*. But the,
but the הימנו *himenu* was ten loaves, and that got us to
ten עשרונות *issronot*. And then we're going to take what we already
knew there, the ten loaves plus the thing we learned, the one
עישרון *issaron* per loaf, and apply it from the חמץ *chametz* to
the מצה *matza*. So we understand you can do that if you
say that doesn't count as a היקש *hekesh*. But if you say
it does count as a היקש *hekesh* and it's not a special
category, how can you make this double step, דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר
ומלמד בהיקש *davar halamad be'hekesh chozer umelamed be'hekesh*?
So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says, אלא מן דאמר *ela man de'amar*
הוי היקש *havei hekesh*, but if it counts as a היקש *hekesh*,
how, so what can you do, מאי איכא למימרא *mai ika l'meimra*,
what can you do, how can you do the double step? So
the גמרא *gemara* says, תביאו יתירה הוא *taviu yeseira hu*. No, when
it says תביאו לחם תנופה *taviu lechem tenufa*, that is like it
is explicitly telling you, it's not a היקש *hekesh*. The פסוק *pasuk*
is telling you one עישרון *issaron* per loaf whenever you bring חמץ
*chametz*. So it's not a היקש *hekesh*, it's directly telling you, here's
the rule, and it applies whether you're dealing with שתי הלחם *shtei
halechem* or whether you're dealing with a תודה *toda*. Okay, that is
the end of that. Last piece now of the משנה mishna *mishna*
of the פרק perek, *perek*, הפסח אינו נאכל *hapesach eino ne'echal*, the
פסח Pesach *pesach* is only eaten, you know, until חצות chatzot *chatzot*.
So מאן תנא *man tanna*, who is the תנא *tanna* that says
only until חצות chatzot *chatzot*? אמר רב יוסף רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
היא *amar Rav Yosef Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya hi*. Rabbi Elazar ben
Azarya everybody should know this because also, you know, eating the אפיקומן
*afikoman* until חצות *chatzot* פסח *pesach* night. So Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya.
דתניא *detanya*, we learned in a ברייתא *braita*, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה
אומר נאמר כאן בלילה הזה *Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya omer ne'emar kan
balayla hazeh*, you shall eat this the meat on this night, the
פסח *pesach* night, ונאמר להלן ועברתי בארץ מצרים בלילה הזה *vene'emar lehalan
ve'avarti be'eretz mitzrayim balayla hazeh*. מה להלן עד חצות ad chatzot *ma
lehalan ad chatzot*, the same way that God passes through it's at
חצות *chatzot*, until חצות *chatzot*, at חצות *chatzot*, אף כאן עד חצות
*af kan ad chatzot*, here too the פסח *pesach* is only eaten
until the moment of מכת בכורות *maka bechorot* because it was there
basically also the blood was, you know, to save them from מכת
בכורות *maka bechorot*, so the event was only until that moment of
מכת בכורות *maka bechorot* occurred. Okay, אמר ליה רבי עקיבא *amar lei
Rabbi Akiva*, Rabbi Akiva said back to him, והלא כבר נאמר ואכלתם
אותו בחיפזון *vahalo kvar ne'emar va'achaltem oto bechipazon*, you shall eat it
in haste, עד שעת חיפזון *ad she'at chipazon*, which he says means
until you actually are hasting out, until you actually are leaving, which
was in the morning. So therefore it's eaten the whole night. So
אם כן מה תלמוד לומר בלילה הזה *im kein ma talmud lomar
balayla hazeh*, so why does it say this night, why is that
linked, you know? So שיכול יהא ככל קדשים הנאכלים ביום *sheyachol yehei
kechol kodashim hane'echalim bayom*, maybe like all קדשים *kodashim*, you know, you
start eating it the day that it's brought, you know, פסח *pesach*
is very bizarre, you bring it on the fourteenth but you only
begin eating it on the fifteenth. תלמוד לומר בלילה *talmud lomar balayla*.
That's why it had to say בלילה *balayla*, not to the, to
have the הלילה הזה *halayla hazeh* linked הלילה הזה *halayla hazeh* by
the מכת בכורות *maka bechorot*, but to tell you you don't start
eating it until the night. בלילה יהא נאכל ואינו נאכל ביום *balayla
yehei ne'echal ve'eino ne'echal bayom*. Okay fine. So our משנה *mishna* that
says until חצות *chatzot* is רבי אלעזר בן עזריה *Rabbi Elazar ben
Azarya*. So אמר ליה אביי *amar lei Abaye*, so Abaye said back,
למאי רבי אלעזר בן עזריה היא ומדאורייתא *l'mai Rabbi Elazar ben Azarya
hi umide'oraisa*, what made you say that our משנה *mishna* is Rabbi
Elazar ben Azarya and it's talking מדאורייתא *mide'oraisa* it's only eaten until
חצות *chatzot*? דילמא דרבנן derabbanan *dilma derabbanan* ולהרחיק את האדם מן העבירה
*ul'harchik es ha'adam min ha'aveira*, maybe מדאורייתא *mide'oraisa* it's eaten the whole
night like Rabbi Akiva, but maybe still the ברייתא *braita* said until
חצות *chatzot* because it's, you know, because it's it's the general principle
that אמרו חכמים עד חצות *amru chachamim ad chatzot* ולהרחיק את האדם
מן העבירה *ul'harchik es ha'adam min ha'aveira*, they told you to finish
it by חצות *chatzot* in order to get you to not lead
it should not lead you to be sloppy and and and not
finish it in time like the first משנה ברכות *mishna brachot* teaches,
you know, that the קדשים *kodashim* are eaten all night but חכמים
*chachamim* said until חצות *chatzot*. Now there's an obvious answer here because
all of the other משניות mishnayot, *mishnayot* that are talking about קדשים
*kodashim* being eaten at night like חטאת *chatas* and אשם *asham* or
whatever, it didn't say until חצות *chatzot*, it said that they're eaten,
you know, at night. So by פסח *pesach* as well when it
says חצות *chatzot*, it doesn't mean דרבנן derabbanan. *derabbanan*, we're not talking
דרבנן derabbanan, *derabbanan* here, we're talking מדאורייתא *mide'oraisa*, but let's see what
the גמרא *gemara* says.
Oh, excuse me, I don't know, I misspoke there. At the opposite,
I don't know what I was saying. I just double-checked, it actually
does say that, right? If you take a look for example on
ד עמוד ב, it says, it says by the זבחי שלמי ציבור
ואשמות, zivchei shalmei tzibur veashamot, it says נאכל ליום ולילה עד חצות,
neechal leyom valayla ad chatzot, דווקא davka
it does say that, okay? And same by the תודה and איל
נזיר, ail nazir, so I completely misspoke. All right, so actually, it's
actually is a very strong question. We're always saying עד חצות by
the things that are eaten all night, so why here by פסח
did you interpret it to be a דאורייתא? deoraita? In all the
other משניות, it's the דרבנן להרחיק את האדם מן העבירה leharchik et
ha-adam min ha-aveira even though דאורייתא deoraita it's the whole night. So
maybe the same thing is true here by the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. So let's see what the גמרא says. Excellent question. No,
אם כן מאי אלא עד חצות? im ken mai ella ad chatzot?
Then why does it say it's, so why does the משנה say
ואינו נאכל אלא עד חצות? ve'eino ne'echal ella ad chatzot? אלא למנוייו
ואלא צלוי. ella limnuyav ve'ella tzaloi. It should have said ונאכל עד
חצות, ve'ne'echal ad chatzot, you know, it should have said just like
the other cases that it's נאכל עד חצות. ne'echal ad chatzot. So
when it says ואינו נאכל אלא עד חצות, ve'eino ne'echal ella ad
chatzot, it sounds like there's absolutely cannot be any further than this.
This is the absolute line, so it sounds like it's a דאורייתא,
deoraita, not just that that's the לכתחילה lechatchila of the
דרבנן. כי התם, ki hatam, אלא למנוייו ואלא צלוי ella limnuyav ve'ella
tzaloi means it has to be that way, אלא עד חצות ella
ad chatzot means it has to be that way. So he although
by the other cases the חצות was a דרבנן, here the חצות
is a דאורייתא. deoraita. Okay, we will stop here at the end
of the פרק, הדרן עלך איזהו מקומן. Hadran Alach Eizehu Mekoman.