Okay בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is קי"ד, Kuf Yud
Daled, 114, and we pick up with the two dots, we're about
10 lines down or 12 lines down, and this is the last
פרק, perek, and it's all about continuing the discussion of שחוטי חוץ,
shchutei chutz, but it's going to move into the question about relating
to the issue of במות, bamot, how when במות bamot were permissible,
when they were forbidden at different stages within Jewish history. But right
now, or, you know, Torah history. But right now we are, anyway,
in the continuing discussions about what types of things you are transgress
and don't transgress for when you שחט shacht outside the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. So we basically did the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah and
the שעיר המשתלח, Seir Hamishtaleach, although even if you שחט shachted in
the wrong place outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, its place is
outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, and therefore it's not חוץ,
chutz, it's not פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו. Petach Ohel Moed Lo
Heviao. So you're פטור patur for those. I should say that תוספות
Tosafos points out that based on another גמרא, Gemara, actually, if you
שחט shacht the שעיר המשתלח Seir Hamishtaleach before the lottery is drawn,
before the lots are drawn, you actually are חייב chayav because at
that stage it's not specifically the שעיר המשתלח, Seir Hamishtaleach, it's one
of the goats and could just as easily wind up being the
one that gets used,
you know, on יום כיפור Yom Kippur as the one that goes
להשם. Lashem. But anyway, so that's interesting. But anyway, you're פטור patur
for those, those are not פתח אהל מועד. Petach Ohel Moed. And
now the משנה mishna goes on to talk about other types of
invalidities; it mentions things like animals used in bestiality, animals used in
idolatry, animals with blemishes, and so on. But רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
comes, and you're פטור patur for all of those. But comes along
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says, actually, if
it's something that right now can't be brought as a קרבן korban
but in the future has the ability will be able to be
brought, you transgress a negative prohibition. You don't get כרת, kares, which
is the punishment for שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, because right now it
can't be brought, but if it's able to be brought in the
future, you will transgress a לאו, lav, a negative prohibition, and the
רבנן Rabbanan disagree, they say, no, there's no כרת, kares, there's no
לאו, lav, you don't transgress, at least in this case they're linked,
if you don't get כרת kares you don't get anything, if it's
not fit now to be brought. What's an example of things that
are not fit now to be brought that will be fit later?
A passing blemish, something that is an issue of אותו ואת בנו,
oso v'es bno, its mother was שחט shachted today or, you know,
or it was שחט shachted today, its mother or its child was
שחט shachted today and therefore this thing cannot be שחט shachted today.
So that's a type of מחוסר זמן, mechussar zman, it's lacking the
right time, or there's other ways of מחוסר זמן: mechussar zman: it's
not yet eight days old, it is too young, it's a bird
that's too young, something that it's going—it's not yet the right time
for it. You know, when I was young, there was an ad
about a certain wine: 'We will sell no wine before its time.'
Do you remember that? Anyway, so anyway, we will be מקריב makriv
no קרבן korban before its time. Anyway, so there's מחוסר זמן. mechussar
zman. And then the last example is something that the problem is
it's not the right time, not because the animal isn't yet at
the right stage, but that the owners are not yet at the
right stage to be able to bring it, like a חטאת chattas
for a יולדת yoledes or a זב zav or whatever. All of
those are things that are not yet the time, and רבי שמעון—the
Rabbi Shimon חכמים Chachamim say since you can't bring them now and
they—you are פטור, patur, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no, you
transgress a negative prohibition. You don't get כרת, kares, but you transgress
a prohibition. So let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, the
two dots. בעלי
מומין, baalei mumin, אותו ואת בנו, oso v'es bno, etc. וצריכי, u-tzrichi,
you need to tell me the debate in all three cases. דאי
תנא בעלי מומין, de-i tana baalei mumin, had we just said they
debated the case of an animal with a blemish that is transitory,
so I would say משום דמאיסי, mishum de-meeisay, that's why the רבנן
Rabbanan say that you're not חייב, chayav, because since it has a
physical blemish that somehow seen as more, you know, repugnant,
and therefore it's more fully rejected, and that's why, because it's more
fully, like, rejected and not appropriate for, for, you know, for the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, even though it's transitory, you're not חייב chayav
when you שחט shacht it outside, or you don't transgress anything.
אבל תורין, aval torin, but if it's birds that are just they're
too young, there's nothing repugnant about them, אימא מודי ליה לרבי שמעון,
eima modi lei le-Rabbi Shimon, maybe the רבנן Rabbanan agree to רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that at least, again, you don't get כרת kares
because you can't bring it now, but at least you would transgress
a negative prohibition. ואי תנא תורין, ve-i tana torin, if it said
that, משום דלא חזי ואידחי, mishum de-lo chazi ve-idchi, that's because they
were never fit and pushed away. אבל בעלי מומין דחזי ואידחי, aval
baalei mumin de-chazi ve-idchi, but בעלי מומין baalei mumin that were fit
and pushed away, so אימא—now eima it's an interesting question what your
גירסא girsa here is—אימא מודי להו רבי שמעון לרבנן, eima modi lehu
Rabbi Shimon le-Rabbanan, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree to the
רבנן Rabbanan that you would be that you would be פטור. patur.
So it's funny because now it's introducing a new reason. If it's
just reversing the point, maybe רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would agree to
the
רבנן Rabbanan that for a בעל מום baal mum which is repugnant,
מאיסי, meeisay, maybe he would agree that it's so pushed away that
it is, you know, that you don't even transgress a negative prohibition
even for רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. It's funny that it introduces another
reason why בעלי מומין baalei mumin there's more of a reason to
be פטור patur because they were fit and rejected and something fit
and rejected is seen as more rejected. Of course, you know, the
גירסא girsa here is a little funny and you could have made
the opposite argument. בעלי מומין baalei mumin at least
Anyway, there's an argument to be made why you both have to
say the case of a blemish and the case of a young
bird. A blemish has the more negative in that it's a blemish
and it's also a possible more negative that it was fit and
rejected, or you could see that as a possible more positive that
there was time it was fit.
ואי תנא הני תרתי ve-is tana hani tarte
משום דפסולה דגופייהו mishum de-psula de-gufaihu that's some intrinsic problem in the
animal itself. אבל אותו ואת בנו דפסולה מעלמא קאתי aval oto ve-et
beno de-psula me-alma ka ati but if it's an issue like it's
not that the bird is too young but that the mother was
נשחטה shechted today, so the problem came from something external to it,
okay? It's now it's not ready, but it's not because it isn't
developed enough or it's not, you know, unblemished enough, something external
happened. So therefore maybe אימא מודי ליה רבנן לרבי שמעון eima modei
lei rabanan le-rabbi Shimon again, here's another reason the rabbis should agree
with Rabbi Shimon and say it's enough in the פרשה parsha that
you actually maybe will transgress a negative prohibition, again, not get כרת
karet because it can't be brought, but at least transgress a negative
prohibition. צריכי. tzrichi. So that's why you needed to tell me all
these cases, no matter how much rejected it is or not rejected
it is, the rabbis say if for whatever reason it can't be
brought today, you don't transgress anything, and Rabbi Shimon says even if
you can't bring it today, if it can be brought later, at
least you transgress a negative prohibition. שהיה רבי שמעון אומר she-hayah Rabbi
Shimon omer and now it's in the משנה mishna itself spells out
for us the principle of Rabbi Shimon because Rabbi Shimon used to
say anything that can't be brought today but can be brought another
day, you don't get כרת karet but you transgress a negative prohibition.
Now we want to say that's a very nice principle and it's
a nice sort of way of splitting your vote, you know, it's
close enough in the פרשה parsha but it's not fully ראוי, rauy,
but the question is okay, but where do you get this idea
other than pure logic that there should be this middle ground? So
מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון mai ta’ama d’Rabbi Shimon what's his reasoning? אמר
רבי אילעאי אמר ריש לקיש דאמר קרא amar Rabbi Ilai amar Reish
Lakish de-amar kra because the verse says
לא תעשון ככל אשר אנחנו עושים פה היום איש כל הישר בעיניו.
lo taasun ke-chol asher anachnu osim po hayom ish kol hayashar be-einav.
Okay, so this is a cryptic verse where Moshe says to Bnei
Yisrael, don't do like you're doing now, everybody what you seems right
in your
eyes כי לא באתם עד עתה אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה ki lo
vatem ad atah el hamenucha ve’el hanachala that God has given you.
והיה כאשר תעברו את הירדן vehaya ka’asher tavoru et hayarden whatever, Michael
what's the end of the פסוק pasuk actually it's coming up, right?
ועברתם את הירדן וישבתם בארץ אשר ה' אלהיכם מנחיל אתכם והניח לכם
מכל אויביכם מסביב וישבתם
בטח והיה המקום אשר יבחר ה' אלהיכם בו,
ve-avartem et hayarden vishavtem ba’aretz asher Hashem Elokeichem manchil etchem vehiniach lachem
mikol oyveichem misaviv vishavtem betach vehaya hamakom
asher
yivchar Hashem Elokeichem bo, right שם תביאו, sham tavi’u, right? So the
simple sense of the verse is don't do like you're doing now
where you're bringing your קרבנות korbanot in every place, but in when
you cross the Jordan you're going to bring it in a central
place. And the funny thing is that what do you mean and
the time of the מדבר midbar there was a משכן mishkan and
they were bringing it in a central place. And by the way
that איש כל הישר בעיניו ish kol hayashar be-einav echoes or foreshadows
or whatever pre-echoes whatever the word is of פסוקים משופטים psukim mi-Shoftim
they repeatedly theme in שופטים Shoftim is בימים ההם אין מלך בישראל
איש הישר בעיניו יעשה, bayomim haheim ein melech be-Yisrael ish hayashar be-einav
yaaseh, right? So
which is basically the idea like everybody doing their own thing, right?
And, you know, so anyway, and is it ever explicitly tied into
the במות bamot that's another repeating theme, right? רק הבמות לא סרו
עוד העם מזבחים ומקטרים בבמות. rak habamot lo saru od ha-am mezabchim
u-mektirim ba-bamot. But I don't know if it's tied because the Torah
doesn't really get to be angry about sort of focusing on the
במות bamot until there's a בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash even though according
to חז"ל Chazal right, sort of the period of שילה Shilo there
was an איסור במות. issur bamot. But anyway, the idea is everybody's
doing their own thing certainly suggests the world of במות. bamot. So
the simple read of that verse is don't do like you're doing
now where everybody bringing on their own במות, bamot, you're going to
cross the Jordan there's going to be a central place and it's
only going to be one place to bring it. The problem is
that there was only one place to bring it in the time
of the משכן Mishkan as well. So how do you read the
פסוק? pasuk? So here's the way we're going to read the פסוק,
pasuk, okay? So דאמר קרא d’amar kra the verse says לא תעשון
ככל אשר אנחנו עושים פה היום lo taasun ke-chol asher anachnu osim
po hayom אמר משה לישראל amar Moshe le-Yisrael so Moshe said to
the Jewish people
כי עיילתון לארץ ki ayeltun la-aretz when you get to the land
ישרות תקריבו חובות לא תקריבו. yashrus takrivu chovos lo takrivu. Do the
stuff that's right in your eyes, not the stuff that you're obligated
to do, meaning the do the נדר neder and the נדבה nedava
the freewill sacrifices which are שלמים shlamim and עולות. olot. Do not
do the obligatory ones, that's not you're doing it because it seems
right in your eyes, that's because you're doing because you're obligated. So
don't do the like the אשם asham and the חטאת. chatas. Okay,
so now the way we're reading it is so לא תעשון lo
taasun when you pass the Jordan now you're doing both הישר בעיניו
hayashar be-einav not you're not only doing ישר בעיניו, yashar be-einav, you're
not only doing, you know נדרים ונדבות nedarim u-nedavot you're also doing
חובות chovos because you're doing it in the משכן. Mishkan. והיה כאשר
vehaya ka’asher you know לא תעשון ככל אשר אנחנו עושים פה היום
lo taasun ke-chol asher anachnu osim po hayom don't do, it's very
like a big wall in the פסוק, pasuk, don't do like you're
doing today which is both הישר בעיניו hayashar be-einav and חובות, chovos,
but rather, okay, once you cross the Jordan only do, you know
איש כל הישר בעיניו. ish kol hayashar be-einav. Then once you pass
the Jordan only do the נדרים ונדבות nedarim u-nedavot when there's a
time of היתר במות. heter bamot. היתר במות heter bamos *heter bamos*
you're only allowed to do נדרים *nedarim* and נדבות *nedavos*, you're not
allowed to do חובות *chovos*. Okay? And then when you get to
build a בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beis HaMikdash* or שילה *Shilo*, then
you'll go back to be able to be bringing חובות *chovot*. Okay,
so that's how we read it, which is the basic הלכה halacha
*halakha* that only נדר *nedar* and נדבה *nedavah* is קרב בבמה *karev
b'bamah*, only נדרים *nedarim* and נדבות *nedavos* are brought on a במה
bamah, *bamah*. Fine. How's that relevant for our purpose? It's relevant in
the following way. Okay, כי עלו לארץ יש ותקריבו חובות לא תקריבו
*ki alizu l'aretz yasos takrivu chovos lo takrivu*, וגלגל *v'Gilgal* לגבי שילה
מחוסר זמן mechusar zman, הוא *v'Gilgal legabei
Shilo mechusar zman hu*. Now, we're assuming this is not פשט pshat
*pshat* of the משנה mishna *mishna*. The פשט pshat *pshat* in the
משנה Mishna *mishna*, you might remember, spoke about bringing קדשי קדשים *kodshei
kodashim* in גלגל Gilgal. *Gilgal*, which קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* are basically
can be eaten are basically חובות *chovot* or חטאת chatas *chatas* and
אשם asham *asham*. But this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* right now is assuming
that when it says you're only going to be able to bring
חובות *chovot* when there's a central location, it means only in שילה
*Shilo* and the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. Even in a
place like גלגל Gilgal, *Gilgal* and נוב *Nov* and גבעון *Givon*, where
there is a large במה bamah *bamah* and a communal במה bamah
*bamah*, at that time also there you're only going to be able
to bring נדרים *nedarim* and נדבות *nedavos*. There is going to be
no חובות *chovot*, no חטאת chatas *chatas* and no אשם asham *asham*,
okay, during the period until except at the time of שילה *Shilo*
and the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. So even if you
wanted to bring it at גלגל Gilgal. *Gilgal*, you would not be
able to bring a חטאת chatas *chatas* or an אשם asham.
*asham*. So what do you do? Let's say you committed a sin.
Yep, yes, what do you do nowadays when you commit a sin?
Okay, but back then there actually were קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot*.
איי *I*, what can I tell you? That's this read. Now that's
not at all our משנה Mishna *mishna*. Our משנה Mishna *mishna* assumes
that of course you could bring חובות *chovot* at the central במה
bamah *bamah*, at the במה גדולה bamah gedolah *bamah gedolah*, okay, but
here not.
So now, what's impelling them to read it that way?
We're trying to come up with the explanation for רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*. Okay, it's not going to be the only read
for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*. This is a רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* approach, not a חכמים Chachamim *chachamim* approach. What
is this going to lead? How's this going to lead to מחוסר
זמן mechusar zman *mechusar zman*? We'll see in a minute. Let's read
the next
line. Okay, וגלגל לגבי שילה *v'Gilgal legabei Shilo*, so let's say you
were you had a חטאת chatas, *chatas* you had to bring, and
it was only גלגל Gilgal, *Gilgal*, it was the time of גלגל
Gilgal, *Gilgal*. So that חטאת chatas *chatas* would have been a מחוסר
זמן mechusar zman. *mechusar zman*. It was not yet the time to
bring that חטאת chatas, *chatas* because there was no
yet it wasn't yet the time of שילה *Shilo*, wasn't yet the
time of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*.
But it's not just אסור assur *asur*, it's totally different.
I know, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* wants to imagine this as
מחוסר זמן mechusar zman, *mechusar zman*. You're obligated in a חטאת chatas
*chatas*, and you can't bring it because it's not yet לא באתם
עד עתה *lo basam ad ata*. And I agree with you. What
do you mean it's מחוסר זמן mechusar zman *mechusar zman*? It's more
like מחוסר מקום makom, *mechusar makom*, as it were,
somehow you need a certain type of a structure, you need a
central בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beis HaMikdash*, it's not just the time
hasn't arrived. Anyway, so it's a very it is a very complicated
way to get to this idea, and you're right, it seems to
be mixing things
up. Okay, it's not a context of a time of an איסור
במות issur bamos. *issur bamos* and what are the parameters of an
איסור במות issur bamos, *issur bamos*. Here it's a time of a
היתר במות heter bamos, *heter bamos* where within the whole universe of
היתר במות heter bamos *heter bamot*, even in גלגל Gilgal *Gilgal*, you're
not allowed to bring certain things. Okay? And therefore, וקאמר להו משה
לא תעשון lo sa'asun *v'ka amar lehu Moshe lo taasun*, don't do
this. So basically what we're doing is like this: we're taking a
verse that we're reading to say don't bring חובות *chovos* on a
במה bamah, *bamah*, and what we're saying is rather than looking at
that as a violation of what are the restrictions of what you
can do when there's a היתר במות heter bamos, *heter bamot*, and
if you bring an obligatory קרבן korban *korban* on a היתר במה
bamah. *heter bamah* maybe you violate, we're going to translate that into
bringing
an obligatory קרבן korban *korban* on a במה bamah *bamah* is a
problem of מחוסר זמן mechusar zman, *mechusar zman* because this would be
the time to bring it if there was שילה *Shilo* or the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. And from here we learn out
that מחוסר זמן mechusar zman, *mechusar zman* you are actually you do
transgress the negative prohibition even though it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד
ra'uy l'pesach ohel moed. *re'uy la-pesach ohel mo'ed* because there's no אהל
מועד *ohel mo'ed* right now. So it's very weird. We get this
prohibition, A, we get these huge periods now where they couldn't bring
חטאת chatat. *chatas* and אשמות *ashamot* so they couldn't bring חובות *chovot*,
right now they can't even bring it during גלגל Gilgal, *Gilgal* and
נוב *Nov* and גבעון *Givon*. And number two, we turn something which
is a restriction of what you're allowed to bring at the time
of היתר במות heter bamot, *heter bamos* to translate that into an
issue about the scope of the restriction of איסור במות issur bamos
*issur bamos*, that מחוסר זמן mechusar zman *mechusar zman* is a prohibition.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רבי Rebbi ירמיה
*amar Rabbi Yirmya*, this is not the only source we're going to
give for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*. It's a very complicated
way of explaining רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*. אמר רבי ירמיה
לרבי זירא *amar Rabbi Yirmya le-Rabbi Zeira*, so רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmya*
says to רבי זירא *Rabbi Zeira*, אי הכי Ee hachi *i hachi*,
if that's true, מלקי נמי לילקי *milka nami lilki*, you should get
lashes because you transgress this issue of לא תעשון lo sa'asun, *lo
taasun*. Okay? And אלא מה אמר רבי זירא הכתוב נתקו לעשה *al-ama
amar Rabbi Zeira hakasuv nitko l'asei*, that the verse transformed it into
an עשה aseh *aseh*. Now normally ניתק לעשה *nitak l'asei* means it's
a negative prohibition which is linked to an עשה aseh. *aseh* and
if you do the עשה aseh *aseh* you don't get lashes. But
here הכתוב נתקו לעשה *hakasuv nitko l'asei* means it converted it to
an עשה aseh. *aseh*, it's only an עשה aseh, *aseh*. What's the
it? So there's a whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in
חולין *Chullin*, okay, which is that what happens when you שחט shechted
*shecht*, let's forget the time of במות bamos, *bamot*, you bring inside
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* an animal that its mother
was שחט shechted *shechted* today, okay,
and it's מחוסר זמן mechusar zman, *mechusar zman* because it can't be
brought today, right? And you שחט shechting *shechted* in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. So first of all... You're going to get
lashes for transgressing the prohibition of אותו ואת בנו. You שחט shechted
the child of something whose mother was שחט shecht today. Will you
also get lashes for violating the prohibition of שחט shecht a פסול
pasul קרבן korban in the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash. Apparently there is
a prohibition of like לא ירצו, lo yiratzu, okay, that that you
would actually, you know, transgress if you שחט shechted a קרבן korban,
that was פסול pasul in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, If you
knew it was פסול? pasul? Yeah, if you knew it was פסול.
pasul. So the גמרא Gemara says no, when it comes to מחוסר
זמן, mechusar zman, that's only an עשה asei. prohibition, okay, and it
is not is
and you do not actually get lashes for slaughtering something מחוסר זמן
mechusar zman, in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, Okay? מחוסר יום והלאה?
Mechusar yom v'halah?
Yeah, I think so.
Well, no,
that's your standard מחוסר זמן. mechusar zman, Yeah. So anyway, so for
us what we have to know is, because the basic point that
we're making is, we're confusing things. We're talking about something that's a
restriction for how you bring a קרבן korban. in the proper in
this context, transforming it into like a הלכה halacha about חוץ, chutz,
about about an issue about איסור במות. issur bamos But so that's
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, wait a minute, according to
you, לא תעשון lo sa'asun, is telling you don't bring an obligatory
קרבן, korban, you know, at the, you know, during the period of
גלגל. Gilgal, Okay, so if you're bringing it, so we're not only
saying don't bring it on a במה, bamah, don't even bring it
in גלגל, Gilgal an obligatory קרבן. korban Okay, and you're saying that
that's where רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon. gets his idea that there's a
negative prohibition. Okay, so that means that if you do bring this
obligatory קרבן, korban right, which you're calling a type of a מחוסר
זמן, mechusar zman, okay, you get lashes. So you would get lashes
even if you brought it at גלגל. Gilgal. But wait a minute,
we have a principle that if you bring a מחוסר זמן mechusar
zman. if in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. you don't get lashes.
And according to your argument that you want to create this whole
idea that this is a פסוק pasuk about מחוסר זמן, mechusar zman,
you know, being brought, whether it's on a במה bamah? or whether
it's in גלגל, Gilgal. then at least you should get lashes, at
least if you bring it in גלגל, Gilgal, at least you bring
it in the, you know, central מקום, right? Because according to you
I mean, excuse me, then you should, excuse me, based on you
that it's a separate פסוק, pasuk, you should get lashes, okay? But
we know that you don't get lashes. We know when you slaughter
a מחוסר זמן, mechusar zman okay, you only it's only an עשה.
asei So what's the answer?
Is he saying that you can't only bring your own חטאת chatat
but you can bring a communal חטאת chatat, though?
No, I mean, according to this it would sound like, yeah, you
wouldn't bring any communal.
So like so the you know, מוספים musafim or whatever?
Yeah, I don't know, that's a good question. What's the point of
a במה גדולה bamah gedolah like would they bring any communal sacrifices?
Would they bring, yeah, I don't know, it's a very bizarre idea
that they could
have brought any.
You can bring the תמיד tamid though, but like, you know.
Yeah, I don't know, I haven't figured out exactly the implications of
that for רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon So the גמרא Gemara says הני
מילי לרבנן. hani mili l'rabbanan. You know what? That's true for the
רבנן, Rabbanan, that it's only an עשה asei. if you שחט shecht
a מחוסר זמן mechusar zman in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or
you שחט shechting this like חטאת chatas in גלגל Gilgal or something.
But לרבי שמעון, l'Rabbi Shimon, for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that we're
saying that he learns from this פסוק pasuk of לא תעשון, don't
bring a חטאת, chatas, you know, at the time of גלגל, Gilgal
whether in your own במה bama, or in גלגל, Gilgal, so according
to him, אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, if you שחט shacht
a חטאת chatas, in גלגל which is basically a מחוסר זמן, mechusar
zman? you would get מלקות, malkus, not like we said in that
other גמרא Gemara that it's only עשה. asei Okay, לרבי שמעון, l'Rabbi
Shimon, הכי נמי, hachi nami, you would get מלקות. malkus. Okay, so
it's all very complicated. We're confusing all these different categories. רב נחמן
בר יצחק אמר פנים דגלגל לגבי שילה כחוץ דמי. Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar panim d'Gilgal l'gabbei Shiloh k'chutz dami. No, no, no. He
says it's not relevant, okay? Because here, right, the case where, and
maybe I'll draw a picture to help you
sort of, I don't know, pictures help me. Okay, so here's your
בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash, You have a בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. I just erased it. I know, you're right, what can
I tell you? All right, anyway, here's your בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash.
we'll draw it in the whole normal way. Okay, fine, whatever. Okay.
Now, if you have here and you שחט shacht your animal, right?
And it's like day seven, okay? So that's מחוסר זמן, mechussar zman
okay, for example. Then we say that that's only an עשה, asei
that's not a לא תעשה lo ta'aseh for שחט shacht that when
there is a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash Now, here we are in
the world of pre-בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash okay? Here's גלגל. I don't
know why I'm imagining it up on a mountain. Okay, I don't
know. That's your במה bama גדולה in גלגל. And here's your private
little במה bama. in your backyard, okay? Now, what we're saying here
is that if you bring your little animal that's like a חטאת,
chatas which is now מחוסר זמן, mechussar zman. because חטאת chatas are
not supposed to be brought during this period, okay, because there's no
central בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash okay, so we're going to say here
that you bring this thing which equals מחוסר זמן, mechussar zman,
and you bring it on your במה, bama, we're going to say
that's לא תעשון, and that's your negative prohibition. And from there we
learn out that he's, now it's bizarre because the basic problem here
is not איסור במות, issur bamos. the basic problem here is איסור
issur obligatory קרבנות, korbanos, but... And this is going to be our
basis of saying that בזמן איסור במות, bizman issur bamos, if something
is מחוסר זמן, mechussar zman. you get lashes. You don't, you're not
חייב כרת, chayav kares, but you get lashes from this scenario where
it's really זמן היתר במות. zman heter bamos. And the real problem
is that you're just bringing something that you're not allowed to bring
that happens to be identified as מחוסר זמן. mechussar zman So then
the question is, so if that's true, but we know that over
here, when you שחט shacht something מחוסר זמן, mechussar zman it's only
an עשה. asei If you're telling me this, that's telling me that
this is a לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. So then here logically, which
is the sort of the שחיטת מחוסר זמן shechitas mechusar zman in
the inner like in the inside, right, in the inner place, okay,
this should only
be an עשה asei. based on that. But based on this, it's
a לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. So how do you resolve it? So
right, because based on this, it's a לא תעשה, lo ta'asei, but
based on this comparison, it should be an עשה. asei So answer
number one is it is an עשה asei for רבי for for
I'm sorry answer number one is that for רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon,
who says לא תעשה, lo ta'asei, it's a לא תעשה. lo ta'asei.
Okay, he disagrees and he would say that's a לא תעשה. lo
ta'asei. Okay. רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon רבי שמעון. Rebbi Shimon, רבי שמעון
Rebbi Shimon, would disagree with this. Okay.
So רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon, would sort of say that's a לא
תעשה. lo ta'asei. That's answer number one. Okay. Answer number two is
that
the reason this is an עשה only an עשה and not a
לא תעשה lo ta'asei is because it's in the inner space. It's
inside the עזרה. azarah. Okay. So here because there is no inner
space, right, even though you're in גלגל, גלגל is as you guys
were saying is not really that different than your private backyard במה.
bama. Okay. So when you take a מחוסר זמן mechussar zman and
you put it in the inner space, you're only going to do
an עשה. When you do it in these like outside במות, bamos
okay, so one reason it's going to be a לא תעשה lo
ta'asei is because that's a לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. The other reason
it's going to be this is going to be a לא תעשה
lo ta'asei here is because this is considered to be חוץ. chutz.
And the עשה is only when it's a מחוסר זמן mechusar zman
that's שחט shacht בפנים. bifnim. Okay. So that's the lashes for the
לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. Yeah. And you'll get lashes. Okay. The only
question is why you're getting lashes if here you don't get lashes.
And the answer is either here you do get lashes according to
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon or this is considered to be outside and
when is it that you're free from lashes when you do it
inside. Okay. So הגמרא haGemara says like this. רב נחמן בר יצחק
אמר Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar פנים דגלגל, panim deGilgal, no, the
inner space of גלגל לגבי שילה כחוץ דמי. legabei Shiloh k’chutz dami.
That's like outside. So therefore when do we say you only get
an עשה when you שחט shacht a מחוסר זמן? mechusar zman, When
you're inside the like מקדש. Mikdash. Here there's no מקדש. Mikdash. So
therefore it's a לא תעשה. lo ta'asei. רבא אמר. Rava amar. Okay,
so those are very complicated answers, right, because it got us all
mixed up in a whole other set of categories and the real
problem there was not the problem of שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. Okay.
So now we get to move on to something a little more
understandable. רבא אמר טעמא דרבי שמעון כדתניא. Rava amar ta'ama deRebbi Shimon
k’detanya. No, no, here's what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon is based on.
רבי שמעון אומר מנין לזובח פסח בבמת יחיד בשעת איסור במות שהוא
בלא תעשה. Rebbi Shimon omer minayin l’zove’ach Pesach bevamas yachid b’shas issur
bamos shehu b’lo ta'asei.
How do you know if you שחט shachted a פסח Pesach on
your private במה bama. at the time of איסור במות issur bamos.
that it's a לא תעשה? lo ta'asei? Now why would you need
a פסוק pasuk to tell me that? If it's time of איסור
במות issur bamos
and you שחט shachted your קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, then that's a
classic case of a חיוב כרת. chiyav kares. You're bringing a קרבן
korbon, at a time of an איסור במות. issur bamos, So we're
going to have to see. Anyway, תלמוד לומר לא תוכל לזבוח את
הפסח באחד שעריך. Talmud lomar lo suchal lizbo’ach es haPesach b’achad she'arecha.
Okay, you can't sort of שחט shachted your פסח Pesach in any
one of your gates; you have to do it in a central
location. יכול אף בשעת היתר במות כן? Yachol af b’shas heter bamos
kein? Maybe when במות bamos are permissible even so maybe לא תוכל
לזבוח את הפסח lo suchal lizbo’ach es haPesach tells me a פסח
Pesach can never be brought at your private במה, bama. which makes
sense because it's it's sort of obligatory, it's not communal but it's
obligatory, right? So maybe even in the time of היתר במות heter
bamot, you're not allowed to bring your קרבן פסח korban Pesach at
your private location. תלמוד לומר באחד שעריך לומר לך לא אמרתי לך
אלא בשעה שכל ישראל נכנסים בשער אחד. Talmud lomar b’achad she'arecha lomar
lach lo amarti lach ela b’sha'ah shekol Yisrael nichnasim b’sha'ar echad. Although
באחד שעריך b’achad she'arecha means in each one of your private towns
you can't bring it, but we're sort of reading it the reverse.
When is it that you're not allowed to bring your קרבן פסח
korban Pesach in your private town? When there's a central location. So
according to רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon you can actually bring your פסח.
Pesach. Well this first of all we haven't said that this is
רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon right? Oh yeah, it is רבי שמעון, I'm
sorry. אמר רבי שמעון, Amar Rebbi Shimon, sorry. So right, so first
of all, this is interesting. This sounds like בשעת היתר במות, b’shas
heter bamos, you know, you can bring everybody can bring their private
קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, which is fascinating. Okay, but for right now
we're going to focus on the fact that he says that בשעת
איסור במות b’shas issur bamos you're not. Now why do you need
a special פסוק pasuk to tell me בשעת איסור במות b’shas issur
bamos you're not allowed to bring a קרבן פסח korban Pesach on
your במה? bama? Why is it different than anything
else?
Well because it has this quasi קרבן יחיד korban yachid status.
So what? It's an איסור במות. issur bamos, שעת איסור במות. Shas
issur bamos. So of course שעת איסור במות shas issur bamos you
can't bring a קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Why do you need a
separate פסוק? pasuk?
But it's also a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur to an extent so.
Okay, so what? You can't bring any קרבן korbon at a time
of איסור במות issur bamos as a בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash? Why
do you need a פסוק pasuk to tell me specially can't bring
the קרבן פסח. korbon Pesach. Okay, so let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, why don't we see what the
גמרא Gemara says? So the גמרא Gemara, says like this: okay, אימת?
Eimas? Now what are we talking about? אי נימא אחר חצות, Eineima
achar chatzos, if we're talking about אחר חצות achar chatzos when it's
the time for bringing the קרבן פסח, korbon Pesach, so כרת נמי
מיחייב, kares nami mechayev, so it's another way of saying why do
you need a special פסוק? posuk? It's not a special פסוק posuk
about קרבן פסח, korbon Pesach, it's your classic שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz
and by quoting a פסוק posuk by לא תוכל לזבוח את הפסח
lo suchal lizboach es hapesach it sounds like it's a simple negative
prohibition. No, this is the classic שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. If there's
a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you're bringing your קרבן פסח korbon
Pesach in your private במה, bamah you're חייב כרת, chayav kares, okay?
So clearly we're not talking about that scenario. That scenario is a
much more central פסוק posuk and you're חייב כרת, chayav kares, okay?
אלא לאו, קודם חצות, ella lav kodem chatzos, it must be before
חצות. chatzos. Now and therefore it's מחוסר זמן mechusar zman and this
is רבי שמעון's basis, so that's a nice basis. Now at least
we're talking in a parameters we recognize. It's a time of איסור
במות, issur bamos, okay? You obviously get כרת kares if you bring
your קרבן פסח korbon Pesach after חצות chatzos because it's ראוי לפתח
אהל מועד. ra'uy lepetach ohel moed, What do you get if you
bring your קרבן פסח korbon Pesach that morning? It's מחוסר זמן. mechusar
zman, So the חכמים would say you're off the hook, and רבי
שמעון says no, I got a פסוק, posuk, לא תוכל לזבוח את
הפסח lo suchal lizboach es hapesach and that says you at least
transgress a negative prohibition even if it's not yet the right time
for the קרבן פסח. korbon Pesach. And from there רבי שמעון learns
that at the time of איסור במות, issur bamos if you bring
something before the right time, you still get a negative prohibition. That
at least is a very straightforward learning because we're dealing with the
issue of איסור במות issur bamos. and we're telling us even at
not the right time there still is a negative prohibition. Okay, that
would be very nice, but the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to accept
it. I mean it's a good learning but the גמרא Gemara says
there's ways to say he's talking about another scenario. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says no, אלא לאו Ella lav, קודם חצות, kodem chatzos,
לעולם אחר חצות. l'olam achar chatzos. Says the גמרא, gemara no, you
know what? I could say we're talking after חצות. chatzos. After חצות,
chatzos, why do you need a special פסוק? posuk? It's basically your
classic שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. ובשעת היתר במות קאי. Ub'shas heter bamos
kai. Now we're going to get confusing again. Okay, it's after חצות,
chatzos, even though it said בשעת איסור במות, b'shas issur bamos, we
mean שעת- we're talking about שעת היתר במות. shas heter bamos So
שעת היתר במות heter bamot, after חצות, chatzos, so what's the problem
with it? So the problem is, so the problem is is that
it actually is now the problem we said before, that it's an
obligatory קרבן, korban. okay? So
the גמרא gemara says what are you talking about? והא בשעת איסור
במות קאמר. V'ha b'shas issur bamos ka'amar. It says how do you
know you're not allowed to do it on במות are forbidden. So
the גמרא gemara says no, איסור במה לו היתר במה לחבירו. issur
bama lo heter bama l'chaveiro. No, it's אסור assur for the קרבן
פסח, korbon Pesach, it's a time- it's מותר muttar for your for
other קרבנות, korbanos like your נדר ונדבה, neder u'nedava, okay? So meaning,
it's a very bizarre read of this ברייתא. braisa. But as opposed
to the way we read it before, which it actually was sounded
was a shocking idea, the simple way we read it before was,
was that, you know, that at a time of היתר במות, heter
bamot. everybody could bring their private קרבן פסח, korbon Pesach, even though
the whole idea of a קרבן פסח korbon Pesach is a קרבן
ציבור, korbon tzibur, okay? It sounded like, you know, maybe it meant
that they all bring it in Gilgal or not, whatever, anyway, didn't
sound like...
and you rebuild a מזבח mizbeach somewhere around Gilgal.
I mean maybe, right, well that's what they did.
Right, what what? I mean they brought קרבן פסח korbon Pesach in
Gilgal, by יהושע. Yehoshua. Yes, by יהושע, Yehoshua, yeah.
That's a good point.
And they make a big deal about it, you know, but meaning
everyone could put their make their own little במה bamah in Gilgal
as opposed to being like the central במה.
Right, right, correct, meaning, meaning that's what my point is incorrect. The
פשט of our משנה Mishna, is is that when you have a
place like Gilgal and Nov and Givon then you have communal and
obligatory sacrifices are brought at like in the central במה, okay, or
at least obligatory ones, whatever, anyway they're brought at the central במה.
So the fact that יהושע Yehoshua brings a קרבן פסח korbon Pesach
at Gilgal is fine. The simple reading of רבי שמעון's statement is
at the time of היתר במות heter bamot everybody could bring it
in their private backyard, okay? That's what's very strange. But so the
גמרא Gemara never really addresses that. The first read of this ברייתא
braisa is it ignores that fact that he seems to be saying
at the time of Gilgal bring it in your backyard and it
basically says he's telling you that there's an איסור issur of of
bringing it even before חצות. chatzos. And from there we learn that
at the time of איסור במות, issur bamos it's forbidden even קודם
זמנו. kodem zmano. That would be a relatively simple read ignoring the
idea that he says you get to bring your קרבן פסח korbon
Pesach in your backyard at the time of Gilgal. Now we're reading
it very differently. Now we're reading it that when he says at
the time of איסור במות issur bamot he doesn't really mean איסור
במות. issur bamot. He really means at the time when you're not
allowed to bring your obligatory קרבנות korbanos on a במה. That's all
איסור במות issur bamot, means. Okay, yes, it's a time of היתר
במות, heter bamot, you can bring your שלמים shlamim and your עולה
olah and whatever, but it's a time when you're not allowed to
bring your obligatory קרבנות on a במה. So how do you know
that you actually transgress, like we said before, how do you know
you were transgressed if you brought an obligatory קרבן korban on a
במה? Because it says by the פסח Pesach לא תוכל לזבוח את
הפסח. lo suchal lizboach es hapesach. So לא תוכל לזבוח את הפסח
lo suchal lizboach es hapesach is now according to this read coming
to tell you not that there is a negative prohibition at the
time of איסור במות issur bamot to be bringing it קודם זמנו,
kodem zmano, that's one read, but we're trying to say לא תוכל
לזבוח את הפסח lo tuchal lizboach et hapesach is telling you at
a time of היתר במות, heter bamot, okay, you are still not
allowed to bring an obligatory קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
Okay, so how do you get מה זה חוץ מזמנו ma zeh
chutz mizmano out of this?
What? No. So you got, okay, yeah. So לא תוכל לזבוח את
הפסח. lo tuchal lizboach et
hapesach.
Okay, באחד שעריך.
be'achad she'arecha. Okay, that's כולם נכנסים לשעריך.
kulam nichnasim lish'arecha.
So we'll get to that in a
minute.
Okay. So
what
is this saying? So he says, so the simple reading is of
this is at a time of איסור במות. issur bamot, So if
it's איסור במות, issur bamot, of course you're not allowed to bring
your קרבן פסח. korban pesach. So then the חידוש chiddush is that
even though it's מחוסר זמן, mechusar zman. there still is a לאו,
lav, even if it's קודם חצות. kodem chatzot. Okay, that was the
first read. At the time of איסור במות issur bamot, and okay,
and so why do you need a separate פסוק? pasuk? You need
a פסוק pasuk to tell you even if it's מחוסר זמן. mechusar
zman. Okay. Then the גמרא Gemara suggests, okay, and then this is
what it would be saying. So this is read number one. And
then according to read number one, what this would be saying is
at a time of היתר במות, heter bamot,
you can bring presumably a private קרבן פסח, korban pesach, which is
wild and we don't and we don't stop to figure that one
out. Okay. That's what it sounds like, unless you read it to
mean that you can bring it at a central במה or something.
But that's at least what it sounds like. Okay, we'll just leave
this with a question mark. Okay, but that's what he says. At
a time of איסור במות, issur bamot, there's still a problem of
מחוסר זמן mechusar zman, and at the time of היתר במות, heter
bamot, go ahead and bring your קרבן פסח, korban pesach, maybe every
individual, maybe in a central location.
Wouldn't that be a contradiction of ideologically to bring it your own?
Yes, yes, yes, which is why I keep on pointing it out.
It's bizarre. The גמרא Gemara doesn't bother to deal with it. Now
the second read of this is we're actually talking about, even though
he says איסור במות, we're really talking about a time of היתר
במות.
heter bamot Okay,
it's היתר במות for your like עולה olah and your
שלמים. shelamim. And it's a time of איסור במות, what we mean
by that is that even at a time of היתר במות, it
still remains אסור for a קרבן חובה. korban chovah. Okay, and what
this is telling you is that even at a time of היתר
במות, you can't bring your קרבן פסח korban pesach on a במה
because that's an obligatory sacrifice. Okay, and what we would learn from
this is that the not a הלכה halacha of מחוסר זמן בבמה,
mechussar zman bebamah, what we learn from this is at the time
of היתר במות, you still you transgress if you bring an obligatory
קרבן.
korban Right, but then there's a, then to follow up with what
I said before, then you wouldn't know Rabbi Shimon's הלכה halacha of
מחוסר זמן mechusar zman, as it gets from one of those other
two.
Right, right, so that's what he's just saying,
which results in a difficulty.
Right, alright. So this was the best learning for Rabbi Shimon and
the גמרא Gemara then should then says it's not מוכרח. muchrach. Okay,
there's another possible way of reading this. But of course the first
way of reading it is the simplest way. Why not read it
that way and it's a good basis for Rabbi Shimon. Okay. What
it also doesn't explain if we're talking about היתר במות, what does
this
mean? What what's the second part of it mean? So let me
remind myself what רש״י Rashi says the second part of that means.
One minute. Oh,
so
he says that this means, ah, whatever. He says this would mean
even before the פסח, pesach, קודם זמנו, kodem zmano, it's a שלמים.
shelamim. It's a very weak read of the whole ברייתא, braita, okay.
It is much better to read the ברייתא braita the first way
and that gives you the basis for Rabbi Shimon. It's the פשט
of the ברייתא. braita. We don't know what it's saying here. We
don't know if it's actually saying that at a time of היתר
במות you can bring your private קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Maybe it
means you can bring a קרבן פסח korban pesach at the central
location in גלגל, as Charlie said as well יהושע Yehoshua did. But
anyway, at least at least this, the simple read would be at
the time of איסור במות, there's a time you don't get כרת
karet and you still got a לאו lav and that would be
a very straightforward basis for Rabbi Shimon. Okay, let's move on. Okay.
So now it says like this. It gives other examples of something
that's מחוסר זמן because of the owners, בבעלים. be'be'alim. So for example,
the owner is a זב zav or a זבה, zavah, יולדת, yoledet,
and they haven't waited their requisite number of days till they bring
a חטאת. chatas So therefore the קרבן korban. is ready but the
owners aren't ready and therefore
the קרבן can't be brought. You can bring
an עולה olah or שלמים, shelamim,
even if somebody like a יולדת yoledet brings an עולה, olah, okay,
so if she brought it before her right time, it's still ראוי
לפתח אהל מועד, ra'uy lepetach ohel moed. you can because you can
bring an עולה olah for something else. But her חטאת chatas before
the right time is not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. roy l'pesach ohel
moed. So if the יולדת's yoledet חטאת, chatas if her עולה olah
is brought בחוץ, bachutz, even before her period of childbirth, whatever her
seven days or fourteen days or whatever, or you know, actually no,
forty days, eighty days, whatever, before that period. It still is ראויה
לפתח אהל מועד reuyah lepesach ohel moed because you can bring an
עולה olah for something else. But her חטאת chatas, before it's the
right time is not ראויה לפתח אהל מועד. reuyah lepesach ohel moed.
So if the יולדת'ס yoledes's חטאת, if her עולה olah is brought
בחוץ bachutz even before her period of childbirth, whatever her seven days
or fourteen days or whatever, or you know, actually no, forty days,
eighty days, whatever, before that period is up, okay, if it's brought
בחוץ, bachutz, her חטאת, she's, whoever brings it is פטור patur because
a חטאת before its time, before you're obligated, then you're not able
to bring it. A חטאת only works within the parameters of obligation.
But her עולה olah brought before that time outside the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, you'd be חייב chayav because that could be brought inside
and for another קרבן. All right, so that's what the משנה Mishna
said. Except the משנה was a little bizarre because it said these
people, if they bring their חטאת and אשם asham outside before their
right time,
they're פטור. patur. Their עולה olah and שלמים, shelamim, they're חייב. chayav.
Because is what אשם asham. are you talking about? A זב, zov,
a זבה, zovah, a יולדת, yoledes, there's no אשם. asham, Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, והני בני אשמות נינהו? ve-hani bnei ashamot ninhu?
What's the scenario of an אשם asham, by the people you listed?
So מצורע. Metzora. So our משנה didn't originally have the גרסא girsa
of מצורע. Metzora. אמר זעירי תני מצורע בהדייהו. Amar Zeiri tani Metzora
behadayhu.
Throw in מצורע. Metzora. Okay, a מצורע Metzora does have an אשם.
asham In our משנה, it's in there already. Okay, then it says,
okay, but if you bring their עולה olah or שלמים shelamim before
the right time, you're חייב chayav because those could be brought in
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, So the גמרא Gemara says, עולותיהם ושלמיהם,
הני בני שלמים נינהו? oloseihem ushalmeihem, hani bnei shelamim ninhu? Who here
brings a שלמים? shelamim? That's not part of their טומאה tumah and
coming out of their טומאה. tumah. So אמר רב ששת תני נזיר
בהדייהו. Amar Rav Sheshet tani Nazir behadayhu. Throw in נזיר Nazir in
the list because a נזיר Nazir brings a שלמים shelamim and also
his שלמים shelamim is not, he also has חטאות. chata'os. There's a
חטאת for a נזיר Nazir and there's a שלמים. shelamim. So it's
also one of these people that the time hasn't come yet. Their
חטאת too soon would not be ראויה לפתח אהל מועד, reuyah lepesach
ohel moed, the שלמים shelamim would.
So why is מצורע Metzora in the list and not נזיר? Nazir?
So now the גמרא Gemara says, דזעירי קבעוה תנאי. de-Zeiri keva'uha Tannai.
The addition, emendation of זעירי Zeiri of מצורע Metzora was incorporated by
the תנאים. Tannaim. Now, does the תנאים Tannaim mean, does this mean
that like the early תנאים Tannaim and זעירי'ס Zeiri's just reporting another
text that existed from the time of the תנאים? Tannaim? Or does
he mean the תנאים Tannaim here are not like the early תנאים
Tannaim but means that the people that would memorize and teach over
the משניות Mishnayot and whatever, they incorporated this and this became the
new text? Okay, but דרב ששת לא קבעוה תנאי. de-Rav Sheshet lo
keva'uha Tannai. רב ששת'ס Rav Sheshet's addition of נזיר Nazir was not
incorporated. Why not? תוספות Tosafot points out because one of these things
is not like the other. Okay, מצורע Metzora is טמא. tamei. Everybody
else on the list is טמא. tamei. Okay,
so therefore מצורע Metzora belongs much more on that list than a
נזיר Nazir does. All right, so that's why מצורע Metzora was incorporated
and why it appears in our משנה and נזיר Nazir does not.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, אמר
רבי חלקיא דבי רבי טובי Amar Rabbi Chilkiya de-bei Rabbi Tuvi or
whatever, לא שנו אלא לשמו, אבל שלא לשמו חייב, הואיל וראוי לשלא
לשמו בפנים. lo shanu ela lishmo, aval shelo lishmo chayav, ho'il v'rauy
l'shelo lishmo bifnim.
If you're talking about an אשם, asham this only works by an
אשם, asham so it's the one case of the אשם asham that
we're talking about, about like the what do you call it, about
the מצורע. Metzora. Okay, you have this אשם asham that the time
has not yet arrived and you שחט shachted it outside of the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, So you're פטור, patur, it's not ראויה לפתח
אהל מועד. reuyah lepesach ohel moed. But let's say you שחט shacht
it outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. as an עולה. olah. You
got me, you got it? So what's the הלכה halacha? if you
שחט shachted an אשם asham, in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, as
an עולה? olah? What's the הלכה?
halacha Well, isn't that a מחלוקת, machlokes, what is it, אף אשמות?
af ashamot? Okay, but if you don't say an אשם asham, is
like a חטאת, the general approach is if you שחט shacht an
אשם שלא לשמו, asham shelo lishmo, it's כשר בלא עלה לבעלים לשם
חובה. kasher belo ala labe'alim leshem chova. So is the אשם ראויה
לפתח אהל מועד? asham reuyah lepesach ohel moed? Because you could שחט
shachted it inside.
Now here, but you can't say it's מצורע Metzora because you could
do something wrong.
Well, maybe you could, but here's the bigger question. Here's the bigger
question. When we say when you שחט shachted an אשם לשם עולה,
asham leshem olah, it's כשר בלא עלה לבעלים לשם חובה. kasher belo
ala labe'alim leshem chova. Is it basically an אשם asham, that you
didn't ruin too much or is it now something else? Since you
called it an עולה, olah, it's sort of like a quasi עולה,
olah, it's a little bit like you redefined it. Normally we assume
א, Aleph, we assume it's an אשם, asham. but you did it
שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, but that didn't ruin it too much, it
only ruined it a little bit. Okay, but if that's true, then
this אשם, asham it's still not yet its time to be brought.
So an אשם שלא לשמו, asham shelo lishmo, here's a question. I'm
a מצורע, Metzora, I'm obligated in my אשם, asham. it's not yet
the time to bring it. I bring it in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and they שחט shachted it שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. Are
the כהנים Kohanim allowed to eat the meat? Or is the whole
thing, it's like, it's this, the same way if they שחט shachted
it לשמו, lishmo, it would be מחוסר זמן and it would be
פסול. passul. When you שחט shacht it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, it's
מחוסר זמן, it's פסול. passul. שלא לשמו Shelo lishmo doesn't stop it
from being an אשם. asham That's the natural thing to say. So
what he's saying here is a bizarre idea. Forget the fact you
could and you haven't done it yet. What he's saying here is,
no, if you שחט shachted this אשם asham, in the בית המקדש
מחוסר זמן Beis Hamikdash mechusar zman and you called it an עולה,
olah, it would be כשר kasher because then we'd stop looking at
it as an אשם. asham Okay, and therefore if you שחט shachted
it out of the בית המקדש שלא לשמו, Beis Hamikdash shelo lishmo,
you're also going to be חייב. chayav. So let's read that. Okay,
לא שנו אלא לשמו. lo shanu ela lishmo. When are you פטור
patur when you שחט shacht this אשם asham out of the בית
המקדש? When you שחט shacht it לשמו lishmo or
סתם. stam. אבל שלא לשמו, Aval shelo lishmo, if you שחט shacht
it out of the בית המקדש as an עולה, olah, חייב. chayav.
You're חייב. chayav. Why? הואיל וראוי לשלא לשמו בפנים ho'il v'rauy l'shelo
lishmo bifnim because if you would have... Cause if you were to
שחט shacht it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo in the בית המקדש, it
would be כשר, kasher, which is a huge חידוש, chiddush, which we're
going to get to in a second. So therefore, when you שחט
shacht it שלא לשמו shelo lishmo out of the בית המקדש, you're
חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי לשמו נמי נחייב.
lishmo nami nechayiv.
If that's true be חייב chayav when you שחט shacht it לשמו
lishmo outside, cause even if I'm שחטing shacht it לשמו lishmo and
it's פסול pasul this way, had I שחטed shacht it שלא לשמו,
shelo lishmo, it would have been ראוי, roy, so let me be
חייב, chayav, you know, cause it could have been ראוי לפתח אהל
מועד. roy l'pesach ohel moed. גמרא says: No. בעי עקירה. Ba'i akira.
No, no, no,
cause until you do it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, you haven't changed
its identity. So when you שחט shacht it לשמו lishmo outside the
בית המקדש, you're פטור, patur, cause its identity is as an אשם,
asham and as an אשם asham, it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד.
You don't say, you know what they say, like if grandma had
wheels she'd be a trolley car. You don't say that if this
אשם asham was an עולה, olah, you'd be חייב. chayav. Right now
it's an... you never heard that phrase? Okay,
anyway. So right now this אשם asham is still an אשם, asham
and as an אשם asham it's מחוסר זמן and you're פטור. patur.
Okay. You don't say, oh, but I could have made it something
else. As an אשם asham, you're פטור. patur. But if you did
make it something else, if you שחטed shacht it as an עולה,
olah, you're חייב, chayav, cause then it would be כשר kasher in
the בית המקדש. Alright, you know, all that makes sense assuming that
you would actually be כשר kasher in the בית המקדש, but that
is a bizarre idea. You bring an אשם asham that's מחוסר זמן,
you שחט shacht and you call it an עולה, olah, and not
only do we say it's not totally פסול, pasul, we actually say
you made it a little bit like an עולה, olah, and therefore
now it's actually going to be כשר, kasher, even though as an
אשם asham it's מחוסר זמן. So that's the question the גמרא asks.
We'll ask that question and then we'll work to answer it tomorrow.
So the גמרא says: מתקיף לה רב הונא Matkif leh Rav Huna
וכי יש לך דבר שאינו כשר לשמו וכשר שלא לשמו? v'chi yesh
l'cha davar she'eino kasher lishmo v'kasher shelo lishmo? I don't get it.
When you שחט shacht in the בית המקדש as an אשם, asham.
it's פסול pasul cause it's מחוסר זמן. You שחט shacht as an
עולה, olah, you now make it כשר? kasher? Okay. So an אשם
asham שחטed shacht as an עולה olah is... the שחטing it as
an עולה olah doesn't totally פסול pasul it, but it doesn't make
it something else. Okay. Apparently he held otherwise. He held when you
שחט an אשם asham, as an עולה, olah, you a little bit
change its identity, okay? And so that's where... and therefore he says
it makes it כשר kasher cause it's no longer מחוסר זמן, you
no longer look at it as an אשם. Okay. So we'll read
one sentence, I know we're all over, but let's read one answer
cause this is the obvious retort where something שלא לשמו shelo lishmo
is more כשר kasher than לשמו. lishmo. ולא? והרי פסח בשאר ימות
השנה. V'lo? Ve'harei Pesach b'sha'ar yemos hashanah. What do you mean? A
פסח Pesach what we just mentioned then when it's not... when it's
not פסח, Pesach, דאינו כשר לשמו, d'eino kasher lishmo, when you do
it לשם פסח leshem Pesach it's פסול, pasul, וכשר
שלא לשמו, v'kasher shelo lishmo, but when you do it for something
else it's כשר. kasher. So there when you do it שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo it gets better. גמרא says: No. פסח בשאר ימות השנה
שלמים נינהו. Pesach b'sha'ar yemos hashanah shelamim ninhu. There's a special הלכה
that when it's not פסח, Pesach, it's considered a שלמים. shelamim. So
when you do it שלא לשם פסח, shelo leshem Pesach, you're not
really doing it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, its identity has already changed.
Okay. So that is what we're going to explore tomorrow if you
שחט all along. We're going back way to the beginning of the
מסכת masechet of שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo. We've always assumed שלא לשמו
shelo lishmo is a פסול psul but not a totally destructive פסול.
psul. And what here he's trying to say is actually it might
change its identity, and שלא לשמו shelo lishmo could take something that's
an אשם that's מחוסר זמן, and by calling it something else, you
actually could make it כשר kasher cause you make it a little
bit not an אשם, you make it something else. Okay, so we
will continue with this tomorrow.