Good morning. Sorry for the delay. I'm filling in for Rabbi Linzer
while he's unavailable. Today is August 3rd, it's the 22nd of אב.
Av. Today's דף Daf is זבחים קייב. Zevachim Kof Yud Bet. Today
is also the last day of one of the various ירושלמי Yerushalmi
דף יומי Daf Yomi cycles. So if anyone wants to start learning
ירושלמי Yerushalmi tomorrow, you start with a new cycle, which is very
nice. Start from the beginning of ברכות. Berakhot.
Our גמרא Gemara at the top of קייב Kof Yud Bet wraps
up the or wraps up the end of the 13th chapter השוחט
והמעלה, Hashochet Veha'aleh,
the discussion from the previous משנה. Mishnah. The גמרא Gemara says בשלמא
בחוץ, bishlama bachutz, let's get back into the משנה Mishnah a little
bit. The משנה Mishnah said חטאת שקיבל דמה בכוס אחד ונתן בחוץ
וחזר ונתן בפנים. Chatat shekibel dama bekhos echad venatan bachutz vehazar venatan
biphinim. What if you had collected the blood of a קרבן חטאת
korban chatat in a single jar, a single cup, and then you
took some of the blood and did the זריקה zeriko outside and
you did some of the זריקה zeriko inside? That is in the
whole discussion of שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz and העלאה בחוץ ha'alah bachutz
and זריקה בחוץ zeriko bachutz etc etc. So the גמרא Gemara says
בשלמא בחוץ וחזר ונתן בפנים. bishlama bachutz vehazar venatan biphinim. It makes
sense to say in such a case that you're חייב chayav if
you first did it בחוץ, bachutz, and then you took the remaining
blood and brought it inside the temple and put the blood on
the מזבח mizbe'ach inside, שכולו ראוי להיות בפנים, shekulo ra'uy lihyot biphinim,
because it had been suitable to be brought inside and when you
did it outside it became disqualified. You violated the prohibition of bringing
the sacrifice outside. אבל בפנים והעלה בחוץ, aval biphinim vehalan bachutz, but
what if you did it inside and then you take the remainder
of the blood and take it outside as the משנה's Mishnah next
case? שירים נינהו, shi'arim ninhu,
but those are just
שירים shi'arim of the blood. Those are just the leftover blood, שיריים
shi'arayim of the blood, and therefore it shouldn't be a problem because
you've already fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah of the זריקה zeriko of the
קרבן חטאת korban chatat and now you just have the leftover blood
which has to be put on the יסוד yesod of the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, but it's not an עבודה avodah of the same weight or
of the same significance. So we have to say הא מני רבי
נחמיה היא, ha mani Rabbi Nechemya hi, that's the opinion of רבי
נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemya, דאמר שירי דם שהקריבן בחוץ חייב. de'amar she'arey dam
she'hikrivan bachutz chayav.
רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya extends the prohibition of הקרבה בחוץ hakrava bachutz
even to the שירי הדם, she'arey hadam, the leftover blood, that is
not even the blood that effects the כפרה, kaparah, that does the
first stage of the זריקה, zeriko, but even the remainder. He has
a more expansive view of the prohibition. אי ei רבי נחמיה, Rabbi
Nechemya, but if you say that the משנה Mishnah is the opinion
of רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemya, אימא סיפא: eima seifa: קיבל דמה בשני
כוסות, kibel dama bishnei khosot, נתן שניהם בפנים פטור. natan shneihem biphinim
patur.
But we said that the later case in the משנה Mishnah is
if you collected the blood in two cups and you took both
of them inside,
then you're פטור. patur. נתן שניהם בפנים פטור, natan shneihem biphinim patur,
שניהם בחוץ חייב. shneihem bachutz chayav. And if you
took both of them outside then you're חייב. chayav. אחד בפנים ואחד
בחוץ פטור. echad biphinim ve'echad bachutz patur. And if you took one
of them inside, one of them outside then you're פטור. patur. That
is the opinion of רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya seems not to fit
with this later case in the משנה Mishnah which says that if
the blood had been divided into two separate cups and you only
took one of them outside and you did the זריקה zeriko inside
with the one that was left inside and you did זריקה zeriko
outside with the one that was brought outside then you're פטור, patur,
והאמר רבי נחמיה שירי דם שהקריבן בחוץ חייב. veha'amar Rabbi Nechemya she'arey
dam she'hikrivan bachutz chayav. And רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemya would say that
the remaining blood, the leftover blood that was brought outside you'll still
be חייב chayav for. So סיפא אתא לתנא קמא דרבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון. seifa ata l'Tana Kama d'Rabbi Elazar be'Rabbi Shimon. So no,
we have to say that the סיפא seifa of the משנה Mishnah
is the opinion of רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar be'Rabbi Shimon
even though the רישא reisha of the משנה Mishnah is the opinion
of רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemya. דאמר כוס עושה דחוי לחבירו, de'amar kos
oseh dichei lechavero, and we can attribute it to רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון Rabbi Elazar be'Rabbi Shimon because he says a general principle about
if the blood was put into two containers, כוס עושה דחוי לחבירו,
kos oseh dichei lechavero, if one of the cups becomes disqualified then
it invalidates the partner cup as well. Okay, so and the רמב"ם
Rambam points out in his commentary on פירוש המשניות Perush ha-Mishnayot that
it's clear from this סוגיא sugya that רבי נחמיה's Rabbi Nechemya position
is rejected one and that's why so we're trying to attribute רבי
נחמיה's Rabbi Nechemya position to our משנה Mishnah to try to tie
up some of the loose ends. The משנה Mishnah had then said
למה הדבר דומה, l'ma hadavar domeh, and compared the first case of
the blood in two different cups to the following case: למפריש חטאתו
ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה. l'mafrish chatato ve'avdah ve'hifrish acheret tachteha. You separated
out, you designated a קרבן חטאת korban chatat for a particular sin
and then it got lost, it ran away, and then you separated
designated a second animal.
So the משנה Mishnah says למה הדבר דומה, l'ma hadavar domeh, in
what case is in what way is this similar? למפריש חטאתו ואבדה
והפריש אחרת תחתיה ואחר כך נמצאת הראשונה. l'mafrish chatato ve'avdah ve'hifrish acheret
tachteha ve'achar kach nimtzet harishonah. And then the first animal was found.
הרי שתיהן עומדות. harei shteihen omdot. And now two of them stand
in their in their place in their designated status as קרבן חטאת.
korban chatat. שחט שתיהן בפנים פטור. shechat shteihen biphinim patur. If you
slaughter both of them inside the בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash you're פטור.
patur. שתיהן בחוץ חייב. shteihen bachutz chayav. And if you slaughter both
of them outside you're חייב. chayav. אחד בפנים ואחד בחוץ פטור. echad
biphinim ve'echad bachutz patur. But if you slaughter... But if you slaughter
one inside and one outside, then you're exempt from the prohibition of
שחיטת חוץ. Shechitas chutz. אחד בחוץ ואחד בפנים חייב על החיצונה והפנימית
מכפרת. Echad bachutz ve-echad bifnim chayav al hachitzonah ve-hapenimis mechaperes. But if
you slaughter first the one that's outside and then the one that's
inside, that is you do it in the opposite order, so you
did the outside one first then you're then you're חייב chayav for
slaughtering that one first and then והפנימית מכפרת ve-hapenimis mechaperes and the
second one is still good enough is because the first one was
brought outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it's disqualified and then the
second one can be מכפר mechaper can serve as a קרבן חטאת.
Korban Chatas. כשם שדמה פוטר את בשרה כך היא פוטרת את בשר
חברתה. Keshem shedama poter es besara kach hi poteres es besar chaverta.
And therefore just like the blood of שדמה פוטר את בשרה shedama
poter es besara just like the blood fulfills the requirement of the
meat, that is if you slaughter the animal outside... no, if you
sorry, if you had
the
blood of the קרבן Korban in two cups and you brought one
outside and then you brought the second one inside and that works
to fulfill the זריקה zrikah the requirement זריקה zrikah for the קרבן,
Korban, כך היא פוטרת את בשר חברתה kach hi poteres es besar
chaverta so too the זריקה zrikah of the second cup. Okay, so
our גמרא Gemara says now למה דבר דומה למפריש חטאתו ואבדה והפריש
אחרת תחתיה ואחר כך נמצאת הראשונה. Lema davar domeh le-mafrish chataso ve-avda
ve-hifrish acheres tachteha ve-achar kach nimses harishonah. The גמרא Gemara says למה
דבר דומה lema davar domeh למה לי? lama li? Why do I
have this whole comparison of our case of two different cups to
a case of two different animals? Why does the משנה Mishnah introduce
a למה דבר דומה? lema davar domeh? So למה לי? lama li?
הא מני רבי היא, Ha mani Rebbi hi, it must be Rebbi's
opinion דאמר אבודה בשעת הפרשה מתה. d'amar avuda beshas hafrasha meisa. Because
Rebbi's opinion is that if it was lost at the time when
you had designated another animal in its place מתה, meisa, then that
animal has to die. That קרבן חטאת Korban Chatas is besides the
five חטאות מתות chatas meisos that we know about from the from
in general, this one would be a sixth one.
והכי קאמר טעמא דאבדה. Ve-hachi ka-amar taama de-avda. The reason why is
because the animal got lost. The first one was lost in the
in the interim. So הא פריש שתי חטאות לאחריות חדא מיניהו מעיקרא
עולה היא. Ha hifrish shte chatas le-achrayus chada mineihu me-ikara olah hi.
But if you tried to designate two קרבנות Korbanos at once for
the same liability for the same sin, then one of them will
automatically revert to being a קרבן עולה. Korban Olah. כדרב הונא דאמר
רב K'de-Rav Huna de-amar Rav because רב הונא Rav Huna quoted רב
Rav saying דאמר רב הונא אמר רב de-amar Rav Huna amar Rav
אשם שניתק לרעייה ושחטו סתם Asham shenitak l'reia u-shechato stam if I
had an אשם Asham that was disqualified and had been left out
to graze until you can exchange it, it develops some מום mum
and you can sell it to bring a קרבן אשם... Korban Asham...
קרבן עולה... Korban Olah... ושחטו סתם u-shechato stam and then you שחט'ד
shachted it just סתם stam without anything in mind כשר לעולה kasher
le-olah
then it becomes a כשר עולה. kosher olah. So מי דמי התם
אשם זכר ועולה זכר. mi dami hatam asham zachar ve-olah zachar. But
that's because they're both male animals. אבל חטאת נקבה היא. Aval Chatas
nekeva hi. But a קרבן חטאת Korban Chatas is a female animal
and you don't bring a קרבן Korban female animal as a קרבן
עולה Korban Olah which is only allowed to be brought from male
animal. אמר רבי חייא מבסטיניא בשעיר נשיא. Amar Rebbi Chiya me-Vastinya be-seir
nasi. It must be specifically referring only to the case of a
very limited case of the שעיר נשיא seir nasi which by the
time of the בית שני Beis Sheni may not have even applied
to very much maybe it applied to the Hasmonean kings I don't
know. But so for that is אבודה בשעת הפרשה מתה. avuda beshas
hafrasha meisa. So Rebbi's designation that if it gets lost in the
interim between when it was designated, in fact according to the אמוראים
Amoraim ends up being limited to very specific case because otherwise it
doesn't make any sense how can you say that the female animal
could be designated for a קרבן עולה Korban Olah which is only
allowed to be brought from male animal. הדרן עלך השוחט והמעלה. Hadran
alach Hashachat Ve-hamaaleh. We now start the next פרק perek and the
rest of today's דף daf is just going to be learning the
משניות. mishnayos. Big משנה. Mishnah. Well it's the whole פרק perek of
משנה. Mishnah. So we'll read the we'll read the פרק perek of
משנה Mishnah and get started on the fourteenth chapter פרת חטאת. Paras
Chatas. Okay, the משנה Mishnah says פרת חטאת ששרפה חוץ מגתה. Paras
Chatas she-serafa chutz mi-gita. What if the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah was
burned outside of the designated place on הר הזיתים Har Hazaysim where
it's supposed to be burned in its גת gas in its place?
Why do they call it פרה חטאת? para chatas? It's called פרת
חטאת. paras chatas. No, I know but it's always called חטאת, chatas,
I don't know, or just say פרה... para...
פרת חטאת ששרפה חוץ מגתה.
paras chatas she-serafah
chutz mi-gita. פרה, para, but a lot of
times it says that.
Here it's called פרת חטאת, paras chatas, that's why.
Okay. רש"י Rashi says למקום עמוק le-makom amok in a pit.
So it was there
was some hole
or pit designated for the burning of
the
פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. וכן שעיר המשתלח שהקריב בחוץ. Ve-chein seir hamishtaleach
she-hikriv bachutz. Or what if you took the שעיר המשתלח seir hamishtaleach
which is supposed to be pushed off of a cliff and instead
brought it as a sacrifice outside the temple פטור. patur. Then you're
exempt from the prohibition of prohibitions of שחיטת חוץ. shechitas chutz. שנאמר
ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו. Shene'emar ve-el pesach ohel moed lo
hevi'o. Because the violation is incurred when you do not bring it
to the entrance of the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. And the משנה
Mishnah says כל שאין ראוי לבוא אל פתח אהל מועד אין חייבין
עליו. kol she-ein raui lavo el pesach ohel moed ein chayavin alav.
For anything which you're not liable for... for
anything which has no obligation to bring it into the temple, bring
it to the entrance of
the.
Okay. The next משנה: Mishnah: הרובע והנרבע, Harove'ah ve-hanirba, an animal which
was involved in an act of bestiality, והמוקצה והנעבד, ve-hamuktzeh ve-hane'evad, or
animals which were designated or worshipped for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, והאתנן
והמחיר, ve-ha'etnan ve-hamichir, and animals which were used either for אתנן זונה
etnan zonah for payment for prostitution or מחיר michir or were exchanged
in payment for a dog, והכלאים, ve-hakilayim, or a crossbred animal, והטרפה,
ve-hatreifah, or an animal with a physical injury that's going to result
in its death, היוצא דופן, hayotzei dofen, or an animal which is
born by a sort of Caesarean section—it emerges through the wall of
the animal's abdominal wall rather than being born
vaginally—שהקריבן בחוץ, she-hikrivan bachutz, those animals which were slaughtered outside the temple,
פטור, patur, because all of these animals are disqualified בגופן begufan as
the גמרא Gemara will clarify; they have an inherent bodily disqualification. So
if they're brought outside the temple, then you're פטור patur from the
prohibition of שחיטת חוץ, sh'chitat chutz, שנאמר: she-ne'emar: לפני משכן ה'. Lifnei
mishkan Hashem. כל שאינו ראוי לבוא אל משכן ה' אין חייבין עליו.
Kol she-eino ra-uy lavo el mishkan Hashem ein chayavin alav. It's interesting
to note that the משנה Mishnah derives this exemption from a slightly
different part of the description of the מצוה mitzvah than from the
previous part of the משנה. Mishnah. The first משנה Mishnah had said
because it's אל פתח אהל מועד לא יביאנו, al petach ohel moed
lo yevienu, and this one says לפני משכן ה'. lifnei mishkan Hashem.
So perhaps these are more about being abhorrent to God and therefore
that's why they're not brought as sacrifices, rather than the other ones
which are sacrificial or quasi-sacrificial animals which are meant to be done
outside. Okay.
בעלי מומין, Ba'alei mumim, so animals which have a physical deformity, physical
injury, which either is permanent or could be temporary. So בין בעלי
מומין קבועים, bein ba'alei mumim kevu'im, if it's a permanent deformity, בין
בעלי מומין עוברים, bein ba'alei mumim overim, or whether it's a temporary
deformity, שהקריבן בחוץ, she-hikrivan bachutz, which were slaughtered outside the temple, פטור,
patur, then you're exempt from the prohibition of שחיטת חוץ. sh'chitat chutz.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says: בעלי
מומין קבועים פטור, ba'alei mumim kevu'im patur, if it's a permanent deformity
then you're exempt, בעלי מומין עוברים בלא תעשה. ba'alei mumim overim belo
ta'aseh. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going to introduce now in a
number of cases an intermediate status. That is, on the one hand,
the prohibition of שחיטת חוץ sh'chitat chutz will apply to the extent
that a person incurs the punishment of כרת; karet; those are the
cases which the משנה Mishnah and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma say
חייב. chayav. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon introduces an intermediate category between
חייב chayav and פטור patur which he calls לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh.
It's clear that this does not mean that you receive lashes for
this; this is that you have violated the prohibition which if you
had done it in a more substantive way you would incur כרת,
karet, but because there's a certain defect in the way you've done
the violation, you don't receive the punishment, but it's still a violation
of the לא תעשה. lo ta'aseh. So you violate the מצוה mitzvah
but without incurring the punishment. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says if
it's a permanent deformity then you're פטור, patur, but if it's בעלי
מומין עוברים בלא תעשה, ba'alei mumim overim belo ta'aseh, but if it's
a temporary deformity that you brought the animal as a sacrifice outside
the temple, then you've violated the prohibition but you do not incur
כרת. karet. Okay. תורין שלא הגיע זמנן, Torin shelo higi'a zemanam, what
about turtledoves that were not reached their proper age yet, ובני
יונה שעבר זמנן, u-vnei yonah she-avar zemanam, or regular doves, pigeons that
have aged out? That is, when we bring bird sacrifices, the תורין,
torim, the turtledoves have to be old birds, and the בני יונה
bnei yonah have to be young birds, and you can't bring old
בני יונה bnei yonah and you can't bring young תורין. torim. So
if you brought
תורין שלא הגיע זמנן, torin shelo higi'a zemanam, if you have תורין,
torim, turtledoves which are too young, or you have בני יונה שעבר
זמנן, bnei yonah she-avar zemanam, or you have pigeons which have gotten
too old, שהקריבן בחוץ, she-hikrivan bachutz, which were brought outside the temple,
פטור, patur, because they have an inherent bodily problem; they're the wrong
age and therefore they're considered
invalid to be brought for these sacrifices, then you're פטור. patur. רבי
שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: בני יונה שעבר זמנן פטור, bnei yonah
she-avar zemanam patur, if they are the doves that have gotten too
old you are פטור, patur, ותורין שלא הגיע זמנן בלא תעשה. ve-torin
shelo higi'a zemanam belo ta'aseh. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that if
it's the case of turtledoves which are too young, then you still
violate the prohibition but you do not incur כרת. karet. And this
is because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon has a different view of the
disqualifications that are brought about by time—that those which the time is
going to come in sometime in the future, that is, it's too
early, then you still violate the prohibition. It's only if the deadline
has already passed in the past that you're פטור. patur. So that's
רבי שמעון'ס Rabbi Shimon's position. And now the משנה Mishnah continues: אותו
ואת בנו, Oto ve-et beno, what about the prohibition to sacrifice or
kill, slaughter an animal and its child on the same day, ומחוסר
זמן, u-mechusar zman, or an animal which is too young, it hasn't
yet reached the eighth day of its life—שבעת
ימים יהיה תחת אמו, shivat yamim yihyeh tachat imo, the מצוה mitzvah
in the תורה Torah that has to remain with, that is not
be brought as sacrifice the first seven days of life. So אותו
ואת בנו oto ve-et beno and מחוסר זמן, mechussar zeman, רבי שמעון
אומר הרי זה בלא תעשה. Rabbi Shimon omer ha-rei zeh be-lo ta’aseh.
Rabbi Shimon says that those are part of the prohibition בלא תעשה
be-lo ta’aseh
because, because like I said, the prohibition, the deadline will come in
the future. So אותו ואת בנו, oto ve-et beno, you could just
sacrifice this animal tomorrow, or מחוסר זמן, mechussar zeman, you could wait
until next week, and therefore it’s still included in the prohibition. שהיה
רבי שמעון אומר, she-hayah Rabbi Shimon omer, general articulation of Rabbi Shimon's
position: כל שהוא ראוי לבוא לאחר זמן הרי זה בלא תעשה ואין
בו כרת. kol she-hu ra-uy lavo le-acher zeman ha-rei zeh be-lo ta’aseh
ve-ein bo karet. Anything which can be brought at a future time,
it’s part of the prohibition, it’s included in the prohibition of בלא
תעשה, be-lo ta’aseh, but you do not receive כרת. karet. חכמים אומרים,
Chachamim omrim, the majority opinion responds to Rabbi Shimon and says: כל
שאין בו כרת אין בו בלא תעשה. kol she-ein bo karet ein
bo be-lo ta’aseh. No, there's no such intermediate category, Rabbi Shimon. Either
you’re חייב כרת chayav karet or it’s totally פטור. patur. And therefore
you do not, we don’t consider it to be part of the
prohibition. Now, does that mean that you’re allowed to take an animal
and do these other—no, there may be other prohibitions involved. So saying
that you’re outside of the prohibition of שחיטת חוץ shechitat chutz just
tells me that you’re not part of this מצוה, mitzvah, but there
may be other prohibitions involved.
Okay. מחוסר זמן. mechussar zeman. What about an animal which is מחוסר
זמן, mechussar zeman, which is too young? בין בגופו בין בבעליו. bein
be-gufo bein bi-ve’alav. So whether it’s a problem of the animal itself
or whether it’s a problem of the owners. So what does it
mean that the problem is of the owners?
One second.
Okay.
Fine. מחוסר זמן בין בגופו בין בבעליו. mechussar zeman bein be-gufo bein
bi-ve’alav. So איזהו מחוסר זמן בבעליו? eizehu mechussar zeman bi-ve’alav? What does
it mean that it’s מחוסר זמן בבעליו? mechussar zeman bi-ve’alav? What the
משנה Mishnah says: what does it mean that the animal
is too soon, is brought at the wrong time for its owners?
הזב והזבה והיולדת והמצורע. ha-zav ve-ha-zavah ve-ha-yoledet ve-ha-metzora. So
the four cases of מחוסרי כפרה mechussarei kapparah will be discussed in
the משנה Mishnah in כריתות: Keritot: a male זב, zav, a female
זבה, zavah, a יולדת, yoledet, a woman who gave birth, and מצורע,
metzora, either male or female person who’s recovered from צרעת tzara’at have
to bring a קרבן korban before they can eat other קרבנות. korbanot.
It’s part of effecting their full purification. שהקריבו חטאתן ואשמן בחוץ פטורין.
she-hikrivu chattatam ve-ashamam ba-chutz peturin.
So in those cases if the owners brought their קרבן חטאת korban
chattat or their קרבנות korbanot for their מחוסרי כפרה mechussarei kapparah קרבנות,
korbanot, שהקריבו חטאתן ואשמן, she-hikrivu chattatam ve-ashamam, either קרבן חטאת korban chattat
or אשם asham בחוץ ba-chutz outside the temple, פטורין. peturin. They
are exempt from the prohibition. However, עולותיהן ושלמיהן בחוץ חייבין. olotaihen ve-shalmeihan
ba-chutz chayavin. But if they brought their קרבן עולה korban olah and
קרבן שלמים korban shelamim outside, then they are חייב. chayav. The גמרא
Gemara will discuss all of these. והמעלה מבשר חטאת מבשר קדשי קדשים,
ve-ha-ma’aleh mi-vesar chattat mi-vesar kodshei kodashim, and if you burn the meat
of a קרבן חטאת, korban chattat, מבשר קדשי קדשים mi-vesar kodshei kodashim
from any of the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, that is of the
holiest of sacrifices like the קרבן חטאת korban chattat or קרבן אשם
korban asham or מבשר אשם, mi-vesar asham, for example, as the משנה
Mishnah says. מבשר קדשים קלים mi-vesar kodashim kalim or from the meat
of קדשים קלים kodashim kalim like שלמים shelamim and בכור bechor and
מעשר ma’aser and things like that, that is things that should be
eaten. מותר העומר motar ha-omer or the leftover part, the remainder of
the קרבן העומר, korban ha-omer, the barley that’s brought on פסח. Pesach.
שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem or the wheat breads which are brought on
שבועות. Shavuot. ולחם הפנים ve-lechem ha-panim or the wheat breads which we
bring every prepared every שבת. Shabbat. שיריי מנחות shirei menachot or the
part of the קרבן מנחה korban minchah which is left for the
כהנים kohanim to eat.
והיוצק והבולל ve-ha-yotzek ve-ha-bolel or someone who sprinkles
oil onto the מנחות menachot or בולל bolel or mixes the flour
with the oil.
והפותת ve-ha-potet or crumbles the מנחה minchah breads into crumbles when they’re
which is part of the processing of how they’re going to be
put onto the מזבח. mizbe’ach. והנמלח ve-ha-nimlach or putting salt onto things.
והמניף ve-ha-menif and doing the wavings, various sacrifices need to be waved.
והמגיש ve-ha-magish and someone who brings things toward which which is part
of the process of the תנופה tenufah which will be discussed in
the fifth chapter of מנחות. Menachot. So we’re getting a little taste
here now of many of the steps of the קרבן מנחה korban
minchah which we’ll learn about soon. והמסדר את השולחן ve-ha-mesader et ha-shulchan
or arranging the breads onto the שולחן. shulchan. והמיטיב את הנרות ve-ha-metiv
et ha-nerot or cleaning out and relighting the lamps of the מנורה.
menorah. והקומץ ve-ha-kometz or doing the קמיצה kemitzah of the קרבן מנחה.
korban minchah.
והמקבל דמים בחוץ ve-ha-mekabel damim ba-chutz or catching the blood in a
receptacle in outside the temple, פטור. patur. All of these are not
because they're not slaughtering and they’re not burning a sacrifice. So they’re
all because especially the first examples are most clear, even burning the
meat. the meat which is meant to be eaten, that is you
took a part which would not normally be brought on the altar
and burned it outside the Temple, so that does not, you may
be bringing a sacrifice outside the Temple or something like that, but
at least for that action you've not violated the prohibition of העלה
בחוץ. Ha'alah Bachutz. And אין חייבין עליו לא משום זרות ולא משום
טומאה, Ein chayavin alav lo mishum zarut v'lo mishum tumah, and there's
no violation incurred either if a non-כהן Kohen does these things or
because of טומאה tumah if a טמא tamei person does them, that
is if they're outside, ולא משום מחוסר בגדים, v'lo mishum mechusar bgadim,
and not because you're not wearing the בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehunah, ולא
משום רחוץ ידים ורגלים, v'lo mishum rechutz yadayim v'raglayim, and not because
the hands and feet are not washed. That is all of these
things because they're not fully considered full or most central or most
important of the עבודות, avodot, so they're of a lower rank and
therefore you don't incur the same punishments for these kinds of activities.
So these are all temple עבודות, avodot, but at the same time
they're not violated in that way. The interesting example is המטיב את
הנרות. Hametiv et hanerot. Wait a second, המטיב את הנרות, Hametiv et
hanerot, and also המסדר את השלחן Hamessader et hashulchan perhaps as well.
Putting the breads onto the שלחן, shulchan, which was in the היכל,
Heichal, and lighting the lamps of the מנורה. menorah. Also is in
the, the מנורה menorah is in the היכל. Heichal. So how can
it be that you're not חייב משום זרות? chayav mishum zarut? No
ישראל Yisrael is ever allowed to go into the היכל. Heichal. There's
no way to even approach to the היכל. Heichal. You're not allowed
בין האולם ולמזבח bein ha'ulam v'lamizbeach even you know other places even
farther out are prohibited to ישראלי. Yisraeli. So there's at least one
suggestion which I've heard, I forget now who says this, who says
perhaps there's a possibility that a ישראל Yisrael with a very long
match could light the מנורה menorah all the way through the door.
You could imagine the difficulties involved in such an activity, but at
least the point is that the activity itself is not off limits
to non-כהנים. kohanim. It may be circumstantial that in order to get
to the place where you normally do this, do this מצוה, mitzvah,
you have to be a כהן, kohen, but there's no actual requirement
that it be done by a כהן. kohen. Or somewhat differently, or
if a non-כהן kohen does it you've not incurred the punishment or
you don't violate the prohibition to the fullest extent. המשנה Hamishnah continues.
עד שלא הוקם המשכן. Ad shelo hukam hamishkan. Now we get into
the discussion, the last, the end of זבחים Zevachim deals with a
bit of history. The questions of the period of היתר במות. heter
bamot. That is, if we've been talking about the prohibition of שחיטת
חוץ shechitat chutz and העלה בחוץ, ha'alah bachutz, prohibition to bring sacrifices
outside of the משכן Mishkan or outside of the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, but wait a second, we know that there were at least
isolated periods in Jewish history when there was a היתר במות, heter
bamot, there was a permission to use outside altars. So the משנה
mishnah now discusses this and this is somewhat
very anachronistic in that there's no future applicability of this הלכה. halacha.
It only applied back in history. So the משנה mishnah says: עד
שלא הוקם המשכן, Ad shelo hukam hamishkan, before the משכן Mishkan was
ever even built, היו הבמות מותרות, hayu habamot mutarot, there was permission
to use במות, bamot, ועבודה בבכורות, v'avodah bibchorot, and the service, the
sacrificial service was generally, you could assume, was performed by the firstborn
son in every family or something like that. A little bit strange
to consider because we know also for example, I mean, this gets
into other kinds of questions, but אברהם Avraham brought קרבנות, korbanot, יעקב
Yaakov brought קרבנות, korbanot, משה Moshe brings various קרבנות, korbanot, none of
them perhaps are the firstborn son.
This seems to be reference particular to the number one, to the
קרבן פסח korban Pesach which was done in מצרים, Mitzrayim, and number
two to the קרבנות korbanot which were brought at הר סיני Har
Sinai before the תורה Torah was commanded or during the period of
time even before the משכן Mishkan was commanded. It may have been
actually a number of months there, so we don't really know what
exactly was happening. משהוקם המשכן נאסרו הבמות. Mishehukam hamishkan ne'esru habamot. And
when the משכן Mishkan was erected, then the period of במות, bamot,
of outside altars were prohibited, ועבודה בכהנים, v'avodah bkohanim, and the worship,
the service transferred to the כהנים. kohanim. And that's exactly why in
the תורה Torah in the beginning of ספר במדבר Sefer Bamidbar there
are all of these designations about how to exchange the לוים Leviyim
for the tribe of לוי Levi for all of the בכורים bechorim
in the whole בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, that the service had been
transferred to the כהנים kohanim and other parts of it were transferred
to the לוים, Leviyim, and in that regard, the בכור bechor were
taken away of their right to do the עבודה. avodah.
Some have suggested, right, רש"י Rashi suggests that part of why יעקב
Yaakov was so interested in the בכורה bechorah from עשו Esav is
because he didn't want עשו Esav to be serving in the celestial
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash or in the future בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
in some way. So a little bit something there as well about
the בכורה. bechorah. קדשי קדשים נאכלים לפנים מן הקלעים. Kodshei kodashim ne'echalim
lifnim min hakla'im. And the permission to eat קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim,
to eat קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, to eat קרבן אשם, korban asham,
for the כהנים kohanim to eat the זבחי שלמי ציבור zivchei shalmei
tzibur on שבועות, Shavuot, those sacrifices were all eaten לפנים מן הקלעים,
lifnim min hakla'im, within the curtains, which is the phrase that we've
seen many times actually throughout our משניות, mishnayot, which was always anachronistic
because our משניות mishnayot were talking about the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
which didn't have fabric curtains, but here we're talking about the משכן
Mishkan which actually did, so it may be that that was borrowed
from these משניות mishnayot
as an overlay, anachronistic overlay on the temple structure. קדשים קלים בכל
מחנה ישראל. Kodashim kalim b'chol machaneh Yisrael. And קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim,
the קרבן שלמים korban shelamim and other kinds of קדשים קלים kodashim
kalim were eaten throughout the entire camp. As we know that the
designation of the camps, this came up a few, maybe a few
weeks ago, the innermost camp, the מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shekhinah, מחנה לויה,
Machaneh Leviyah, and then מחנה ישראל, Machaneh Yisrael, the sections of of
the מחנה שכינה Machaneh Shekhinah which was just the משכן. Mishkan. The
Levites' camp which surrounded the משכן Mishkan and then all of the
Jewish people's camp, each of those sort of are parallel to the
holiness of the city of Jerusalem, the מחנה שכינה Machaneh Shekhinah is
the temple itself, the מחנה לויה Machaneh Leviyah is the הר הבית,
Har HaBayit, the Temple Mount, and then the entirety of the designated,
halakhically designated city of Jerusalem is what's considered to be the
מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael. What's interesting also is the ספר יחזקאל Sefer
Yechezkel towards the end seems to imply that the city of Jerusalem
will have much expanded borders in the future time. The גמרא Gemara
discusses this in other places as well that perhaps it may be
the city of Jerusalem, the boundaries of Jerusalem will be extended very
far. So permission to eat קדשים קלים Kodshim Kalim throughout the city
of Jerusalem may extend much beyond even what's currently considered to be
the city of Jerusalem boundaries. באו לגלגל
הותרו הבמות. Ba'u le-Gilgal hutteru ha-bamot. When the משכן Mishkan was brought
to Gilgal, that is in the period of יהושע, Yehoshua,
then the במות bamot were permitted at that point. קדשי קדשים נאכלים
לפנים מן הקלעים Kodshei kodashim ne'ehalim lifnim min ha-kelaim and you could
eat קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim there. קדשים קלים בכל מקום Kodshim kalim
bekhol makom and you could eat קדשים קלים kodshim kalim anywhere, that
is not only within the camp because now the Jewish people were
in the land of Israel, the משכן Mishkan was in Gilgal, there's
no boundary for what consider- what's considered to be מחנה ישראל Machaneh
Yisrael
associated with the משכן. Mishkan. So there's only a designation of what
counts as the מחנה שכינה, Machaneh Shekhinah, the place where you can
eat קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, that is inside the משכן, Mishkan, within
the curtain. But there's no designation for what counts for קדשים קלים
kodshim kalim and that's exactly the point, the היתר במות hetter bamot
allows you to bring a קרבן שלמים korban shelamim at your local
במה bamah and eat it there. So that's exactly the point. באו
לשילה, Ba'u le-Shilo, when the משכן Mishkan was brought to Shiloh, that
is when the ארון Aron and the מזבח Mizbe'ach were reunited and
they actually built some kind of a physical stone structure to support
the משכן. Mishkan. It was still the משכן Mishkan but it had
stone walls now. It wasn't just the wooden beams. באו לשילה נאסרו
הבמות, Ba'u le-Shilo ne'esru ha-bamot, then the period of במות bamot ended
when it went on pause again. ולא היה שם תקרה, Velo hayah
sham tikrah, but there was no roof over the structure. It was
just the curtains. אלא בית של אבנים מלמטן, Ella bayit shel avanim
mil-mattan, it was a stone
walls, יריעות מלמעלן yeri'ot mil-ma'alan with the curtains on top. That is,
in the משכן, Mishkan, the walls were made of wooden beams and
there was fabric and leather on top, and then in Shiloh, instead
of the wooden beams of the משכן, Mishkan, they built stone walls,
but they still kept the curtains and the leather roof and in
that way it was a more substantial structure, but it still, so
it retained a more permanent structure and more permanent status and
therefore, מלמעלן, mil-ma'alan, והיא היתה מנוחה. ve-hi hayetah menuchah. Once the משכן
Mishkan reached the place of Shiloh, that fulfills the requirement in the
פסוק, pasuk, a number of requirements in the פסוק. pasuk.
That is, first of all, it's called בית השם. Beit Hashem. So
the פסוק pasuk says, כי לא באתם עד עתה אל המנוחה. ki
lo vatem ad attah el ha-menuchah. That's the פסוק pasuk in דברים
Devarim 12, פסוק pasuk 9, which sounds like that once there's the,
once you've reached quote-unquote מנוחה, menuchah, you've reached a stable, settled place
in the land of Israel with a designated central worship, even if
it's not בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but it's still the משכן, Mishkan,
and it's, but it's built in a more permanent way, it's not
like it was in Gilgal where it was more temporary. So in
that sense, באתם אל המנוחה, batem el ha-menuchah, once you came into
the מנוחה, menuchah, then that becomes the איסור במות issur bamot period.
So that's when, once the משכן Mishkan was in Shiloh, there was
no longer permission to use
במות. bamot. קדשי קדשים נאכלים לפנים מן הקלעים, Kodshei kodashim ne'ehalim lifnim
min ha-kelaim, you can eat קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim within the curtains
of the משכן Mishkan still, and קדשים קלים ומעשר שני בכל הרואה.
kodshim kalim u-ma'aser sheni bekhol ha-ro'eh. You can eat them anywhere within
sight of the משכן Mishkan in Shiloh. That is, there's no boundary
to the city of Shiloh in the same sense that there's a
boundary to the city of Jerusalem or there's a boundary to מחנה
ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael. It goes by the visual lines of sight. באו
לנוב, Ba'u le-Nov, when the משכן Mishkan was brought to Nob, that
is when the, when everything except the ארון Aron was brought to
Nob, ולגבעון, u-le-Giv'on, and then into Gibeon, הותרו הבמות, hutteru ha-bamot, there
was a period of היתר במות hetter bamot again. So that is,
since, since the משכן Mishkan was erected, there was איסור במות, issur
bamot, היתר במות, hetter bamot, איסור במות, issur bamot, now היתר במות
hetter bamot again. באו לנוב ולגבעון הותרו הבמות, Ba'u le-Nov u-le-Giv'on hutteru
ha-bamot, קדשי קדשים נאכלים לפנים מן הקלעים. kodshei kodashim ne'ehalim lifnim min
ha-kelaim. You can eat קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim within the curtains. קדשים
קלים בכל ערי ישראל, Kodshim kalim bekhol arei Yisrael, and you can
eat קדשים קלים kodshim kalim in any city. So now it sounds
like it has to be within a city. The previous משנה, mishnah,
the previous period of היתר במות hetter bamot said בכל מקום, bekhol
makom, and now the משנה mishnah says בכל ערי ישראל. bekhol arei
Yisrael. באו לירושלים נאסרו הבמות. Ba'u li-Yerushalayim ne'esru ha-bamot. Once the, everything
was brought to the city of Jerusalem and that is the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was built, the
period of במות bamot ended, ולא היה להם עוד היתר. velo hayah
lahem od hetter. There was no further period of permission. והיא היתה
נחלה. V'hi hayata nachalah. That is, the פסוק pasuk says, כי לא
באתם אל המנוחה ואל הנחלה. ki lo vatem el hamenuchah v'el hanachalah.
So the מנוחה menuchah was שילה, Shiloh, that is the period of
time when there was איסור במות issur bamot before there was a
מקום אשר יבחר השם, makom asher yivchar Hashem, it wasn't the actual
sense of a permanent location, but it was a it was in
a substantive and substantial and and no longer temporary structure. So שילה
Shiloh was somewhere in the middle. שילה Shiloh was the משכן. Mishkan.
It had both the ארון Aron and the מזבח. mizbe'ach. It was
a place where there was a real designated sense of of having
a central shrine rather than when the משכן Mishkan was in גלגל
Gilgal or נוב Nov or גבעון. Givon. But once the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash was built, that's נחלה. nachalah. That's now the next stage.
And once we've reached נחלה, nachalah, there's no more היתר במות hetter
bamot anymore. It's so the entirety of this interesting period of of
היתר במות hetter bamot basically reaches from you know from before מתן
תורה, Matan Torah, a little bit before we'll consider יציאת מצרים, Yetzat
Mitzrayim, the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, but maybe not even that. Maybe
we'll just go from הר סיני Har Sinai and then until the
building of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. So really only several hundred
years of of this kind of on-again off-again איסור במות, issur bamot,
היתר במות. hetter bamot. קדשי קדשים נאכלין לפנים מן הקלעים. Kodshei kodashim
ne'echalin lifnim min hakla'im. You can eat קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim now
within the curtains, but really within the the walls of the temple.
קדשים קלים Kodashim kalim and you can eat קדשים קלים kodashim kalim
ומעשר שני u'ma'aser sheni לפנים מן החומה. lifnim min hachomah. They have
to be eaten within the wall of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and we understand
why then that in the book of נחמיה Nechemiah at least part
of the concern for actually building the wall around the city of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, obviously for physical security in the sense of of the
stature of the city, but also for halachic reasons as well. כל
הקדשים שהקדישן בשעת איסור הבמות והקריבן בשעת איסור הבמות בחוץ. Kol hakodashim
she'hikdishan b'sha'at issur habamot v'hikrivan b'sha'at issur habamot bachutz. So now we
go back to our topic, which is the question of again, this
is an incredibly
out-of-date הלכה halachah in a certain sense because we're discussing what happens
if there was an animal which was alive and had been sanctified
at one period and then the prohibition flipped. So none of this
happens anymore since the first בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was built, but
it's an interesting question nonetheless for the history of הלכה. halachah. So
כל הקדשים שהקדישן בשעת איסור הבמות. kol hakodashim she'hikdishan b'sha'at issur habamot.
If the animal was sanctified during a period when there was a
prohibition of במות, bamot, והקריבן בשעת איסור הבמות בחוץ, v'hikrivan b'sha'at issur
habamot bachutz, and it was brought so this applies today, that is
it was sanctified and brought as a sacrifice outside the temple, both
during a period of איסור במות, issur bamot, הרי אלו בעשה ולא
תעשה וחייבין עליהם כרת. harei elu b'aseh v'lo ta'aseh v'chayavin aleihem karet.
There's a מצות עשה mitzvat aseh that you've violated, there's a מצות
לא תעשה, mitzvat lo ta'aseh, a prohibition that you violated, and you
violated the punishment of כרת. karet. But what if הקדישן בשעת היתר
במות? hikdishan b'sha'at hetter bamot? What if I sanctified the animal when
במות bamot were permissible
והקריבן בשעת איסור הבמות, v'hikrivan b'sha'at issur habamot, and then I actually
brought the sacrifice only after the that is I sanctified this animal
in one year, and then they built the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and now I'm still out in the countryside in
ישראל Yisrael somewhere and now I decide to bring the sacrifice? So
הרי אלו בעשה ולא תעשה ואין חייבין עליהם כרת. harei elu b'aseh
v'lo ta'aseh v'ein chayavin aleihem karet. So that for that I violate
an עשה aseh and a לא תעשה, lo ta'aseh, but not I
do not receive כרת karet for that. So actually this seems either
it seems to accord with רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position that there's
an intermediate position or it even means that even the חכמים Chachamim
agree to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about these cases in the past,
that there is such an intermediate position just not not for the
kinds of cases that were addressed in the beginning of the פרק.
perek. הקדישן בשעת איסור הבמות והקריבן בשעת היתר במות. Hikdishan b'sha'at issur
habamot v'hikrivan b'sha'at hetter bamot. What about the opposite? If I sanctified
the animal during a period of איסור במות, issur bamot, that is
during the time of שילה Shiloh let's say, והקריבן בשעת היתר במות,
v'hikrivan b'sha'at hetter bamot, and then שילה Shiloh was destroyed and then
right now the מזבח mizbe'ach is in נוב Nov and I still
have my animal, הרי אלו בעשה ואין בהם לא תעשה. harei elu
b'aseh v'ein bahem lo ta'aseh. If I bring that animal as a
sacrifice now, I still violated an עשה, aseh, I violated a מצות
עשה, mitzvat aseh, but I don't violate any לא תעשה lo ta'aseh
because I'm currently in a period of היתר במות. hetter bamot. So
אלו קדשים קרבין במשכן. elu kodashim krevin b'Mishkan. These
sorry, one
sec.
Okay, so the משנה Mishnah says אלו קדשים קרבין במשכן. elu kodashim
krevin b'Mishkan. Which kind of sacrifices have to be brought in the
משכן? Mishkan? קדשים שהוקדשו למשכן. Kodashim she'hukdeshu l'Mishkan.
Those sacrifices which were sanctified for the משכן. Mishkan. That sounds like
that's sort of part of what's this discussion of איסור במות issur
bamot and היתר במות. hetter bamot. קרבנות הציבור קרבין במשכן. Korbanot hatzibur
krevin b'Mishkan. And public sacrifices, that is sacrifices brought on behalf of
the ציבור tzibur have to be brought in the משכן, Mishkan, have
to be brought in the the central shrine. קרבנות היחיד בבמה. Korbanot
hayachid b'bamah. But individual sacrifices are permitted to be brought on a
במה. bamah. קרבנות היחיד שהוקדשו למשכן, Korbanot hayachid she'hukdeshu l'Mishkan, but if
an individual sanctified his animal specifically to bring them to the משכן,
Mishkan, יקרבו במשכן, yikrevu b'Mishkan,
then they have to be brought to the משכן. Mishkan. ואם הקריבן
בבמה פטור. V'im hikrivan b'bamah patur. But if you decided בדיעבד be-diavad
to bring them to a במה, bamah, then you are פטור. patur.
You haven't violated any prohibition, it's just that you have a לכתחילה
le-chatchilah requirement to fulfill what you said you were going to do,
which was bring them to the משכן. mishkan. מה בין במת היחיד
לבמת הציבור? Mah bein bamat hayachid levamat hatzibur? What's the difference between
במת היחיד bamat hayachid and במת הציבור? bamat hatzibur? That is, even
the Mishkan during the time of the היתר במות heter bamot is
called a במה, bamah, במה גדולה, bamah gedolah, במת הציבור. bamat hatzibur.
So what is the difference, in what ways is the במה bamah
different from the central central במה, bamah, the central משכן? mishkan? So,
סמיכה ושחיטת צפון ומתן סביב ותנופה והגשה. Smicha ushchitat tzafon umatan saviv
utnufah vehagashah. So these requirements: Number one, סמיכה. smicha. We don't do
סמיכה smicha on a קרבנות korbanot outside of the outside of the
במה, bamah, outside of the central משכן, mishkan, let's say. ושחיטת צפון,
Ushchitat tzafon, and that the קרבנות korbanot קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, like
a חטאת, chatat, for example, or אשם, asham, have to be brought
on the north side, or עולה, olah, have to be brought on
the
north side. ומתן סביב, Umatan saviv, and putting the blood around, that
is actually going around and doing the זריקות zerikot on the four
corners.
ותנופה, Utnufah, and the waving of the various parts of the קרבן
שלמים korban shelamim when you bring a שלמים, shelamim, the waving and
the והגשה, vehagashah, the various acts involved in the bringing of the
of the קרבן מנחה. korban minchah. רבי יהודה אומר אין מנחה בבמה.
Rabbi Yehudah omer ein minchah babamah. Rabbi Yehuda says actually you can't
bring a מנחה minchah in a במה. bamah. And further, וכהון. ve-kehun.
He says
that there's no requirement for כהנים kohanim at a במה, bamah, actually
a זר zar could even bring קרבנות korbanot on a במה. bamah.
ובגדי שרת, Uvigdei sharet, and there's no requirement for בגדי שרת vigdei
sharet and כלי שרת. klei sharet. So there's no requirement for בגדי
כהונה. bigdei kehunah. Interesting, they're called בגדי שרת bigdei sharet here rather
than בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. And כלי שרת, klei sharet, there's no
requirement to use actually sanctified containers for catching the blood, for example,
or for what he says there is no מנחה, minchah, but for
the blood. וריח ניחוח, Vereiach nichoach, and there's no actual fulfillment of
what what is the ריח ניחוח, reiach nichoach, that it doesn't bring
the same smell on behalf of God. But as well as Rashi
points out here: ריח ניחוח כדאמרינן בפרק בית שמאי לשם ששה דברים
הזבח נזבח. reiach nichoach ke-da'amrinan be-perek Beit Shammai leshem shishah devarim hazavach
nizbach. You have to have in mind,
mental awareness, that what your sacrifice is bringing is to bring ריח
ניחוח, reiach nichoach, and there's actually no requirement to have that mental
awareness in a במה, bamah, because it doesn't bring the same ריח
ניחוח. reiach nichoach. ומחצה לדמים, Umechetza ledamim,
and that the
halfway line of the מזבח, mizbeach, the upper half is for the
upper blood and the lower half is for the lower blood, the
חוט הסיקרא chut hasikra divides the מזבח, mizbeach, there's no such requirement
in the במה. bamah. ורחיצת ידים ורגלים, Urchitzat yadayim veraglayim, and the
washing of hands and feet. So Rabbi Yehuda actually has a much
longer list of things which do not apply to the במה. bamah.
We can see in what ways is a במה bamah sort of
like actually doing something totally different than working in the in the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash or in the central משכן. mishkan. How much
is it really just a miniaturized or more permissive, more, you know,
more minor scale version of what's going on? So is it something
totally different or is it something very similar? אבל הזמן והנותר, Aval
hazman vehanotar, the requirement to eat things in the correct time and
the requirements of נותר, notar, that things left over past their time.
והטמא, Vehatamei, and that if things become טמא, tamei, they're disqualified. שוים
בזה ובזה. Shavim baze uvaze. With that, we've completed the משניות mishnayot
of מסכת זבחים, Masechet Zevachim, and we'll pick up tomorrow with the
גמרא Gemara of the fourteenth פרק, perek, which we have only about
a week and a half, a week left until דף קב. Daf
Kuf Beis. Hope everyone has a wonderful day. Bye bye.