Okay
אוקיי בוקר טוב, Okay boker tov, today's דף daf is נ', nun,
זבחים Zevachim 50. We pick up at the very last line of
מ''ט עמוד ב' mem tet amud bet and we are in the
middle of a relatively technical section of the גמרא Gemara about how
do you, what are the parameters of doing derivations of learning various
הלכות halachos by קדשים. kodshim. There are certain unusual rules by קדשים
kodshim in terms
of, you know, the י''ג מדות yud gimmel midos and how we
דרשן darshen פסוקים. pesukim. The first is is that we assume that
a detail on how a sacrifice is supposed to be brought is
not מעכב, me'akev, it's only למצוה lemitzvah unless you have שנה לו
הכתוב לעכב, shina lo hakatuv le'akeiv, or perhaps the פסוק pasuk says
it twice or uses some other word to tell you it's מעכב,
me'akeiv, which is very strange, normally by any מצוה mitzvah even if
the תורה Torah gives details we assume all the details are essential,
but that is the מסורה חז''ל mesora chazal had, probably because there
are just so many details that we assume that they can't all
be essential, so we need שנה לו הכתוב לעכב. shina lo hakatuv
le'akeiv.
The other thing is is that, you know, not all of the
details in any particular קרבן korban are always fully spelled out. There's
a lot of קרבנות korbanot in the תורה Torah and sometimes some
details will be spelled out by, you know, a subset of a
חטאת, chatas, but not by the חטאת chatas itself, and so on.
And how do we exactly learn and apply and there's also a
pressure to learn and apply from one case to the next because
if you need שנה לו הכתוב לעכב, shina lo hakatuv le'akeiv, you're
not always going to get that it's going to be repeated unless
you can make some connections and learn it out from some other
source. So that's the principle that so then so then we start,
you know, doing a lot of derivations in order to apply one
category to the next by קדשים, kodshim, but then there are some
limits. And the basic principle of the limit is, you know, is
and that's we said at the end of yesterday רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said בכל התורה כולה, bechol hatorah kulo, there's about five lines
from the bottom, למדים למד מלמד. lemadim lamad milamad. You can go
ahead and make a derivation from a derivation. So you learn A
from B in a certain way and then you go from B
to C transitive axiom of equality or of למדים lamads in the
גמרא. Gemara. However by קרבנות korbanot there are limits. Okay and the
first limit the גמרא Gemara said is as I said yesterday דבר
הלמד בהיקש אין חוזר ומלמד בהיקש, davar halamad behekkesh ein chozer umelamed
behekkesh, that if something is learned out from a היקש hekkesh from
two things being connected to one another, like you know the תורה
Torah explicitly will say that כחטאת כאשם kechatas ka'asham or something of
that nature, so it's linking the two together, a link, then you
can't go ahead and then go from from that to the next
one. So the fact you know for example that can you have
applied the idea that a חטאת chatas is in the צפון north
of the מזבח mizbeiach from the עולה, olah, and then from there
you go from and since that's true of the חטאת chatas and
then the חטאת chatas is linked to the אשם asham then you
apply it to the אשם, asham, that would be היקש מן ההיקש
hekkesh min hahekkesh and that we do not do. Okay that's one
thing and then the next thing the גמרא Gemara said is how
about starting with the link a היקש hekkesh and then going to
a גזירה שוה? gezeirah shavah? And the גמרא Gemara says that we
don't do that either and the principle was at the end of
yesterday's דף daf
that it could have just said צפון north by a חטאת chatas
and that was again learned from the עולה olah so that's the
היקש, hekkesh, and then could have gone from the חטאת chatas to
the אשם asham not by a היקש hekkesh but from a גזירה
שוה gezeirah shavah of קדש קדשים kodesh kodashim which it says both
by the חטאת chatas and the אשם. asham. And we don't do
it. We had to say explicitly צפון north by the אשם. asham.
Okay so now we know that you don't do היקש מן ההיקש
hekkesh min hahekkesh and you don't do גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah built
on a היקש. hekkesh. So now what we're going to do is
we're going to look at two more things about that
opinion of אב av and a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. And then
we're going to look through all of the 16 possibilities in the
chart if you can imagine. On one side of the chart you
have היקש, hekkesh, גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, בנין אב, binyan av, קל
וחומר kal vachomer and then on the other direction היקש, hekkesh, בנין
אב, binyan av, גזירה שוה, קל וחומר. gezeira shava kal vachomer. And
now we're going to go through all 16 possibilities about whether you
are able to do this by קדשים kodshim or not. So let's
take a look bottom of מ''ט עמוד ב'. mem tet amud bet.
דבר הלמד מהיקש, davar halamad mehekkesh, so we now did starting with
a היקש hekkesh and going to a היקש hekkesh no, starting with
a היקש hekkesh and going to a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah, no.
דבר הלמד מהיקש חוזר ומלמד בקל וחומר, davar halamad mehekkesh chozer umelamed
bekal vachomer, but you can do a היקש hekkesh and then a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. How do you know that? מדתנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל, Midetana d'bei Rabi Yishmael, well we taught by the name of
רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael we did this in the previous פרק perek
and this was about applying the principles of something that we know
from one of the inner חטאות, chatasot, הש בדמו ובטבילה, as bedam
ubitvilah, certain הלכות halachos about an inner that we learned from an
inner חטאת, chatas, and that we apply it to the חטאת chatas
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and the mechanism used were a starting
with a היקש hekkesh and then connecting the פר העלם דבר par
he'elam davar and the פר par of the כהן משיח, kohen mashiach,
that was the היקש, hekkesh, and then a קל וחומר kal vachomer.
from that פר par to the פר par of יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. Okay, so that showed. Now again, all we're doing is we're
bringing evidence from Tannaitic material, right? We're not going to prove it
for a פסוק, pasuk, this is a question of our traditions of
these דרשות. drashot. Okay, but from that תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tanna
D'vei Rabbi Yishmael, that's what they did. They did היקש hekesh and
then קל וחומר kal vachomer and that worked. דבר הלמד בהיקש מהו
למד בבניין אב. Davar Lamed B'Hekesh Mah Shehu Lamed B'Binyan Av. How
about doing היקש hekesh and בניין אב, binyan av, the fourth of
the four possibilities within היקש? hekesh?
So בניין אב binyan av is when you use something as a
paradigm. It's not explicitly linked, it's not גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah which
is because of the same word. It's not a קל וחומר, kal
vachomer which is, you know, this is a weaker case, that's a
stronger case. It's a בניין אב, binyan av, which is, it's a
paradigm. If this is true by this, it should logically be true
by everything that is, is, you know, fundamentally in the same category.
Okay, so what's that story? היקש hekesh and then building on it
with
a בניין אב. binyan av. אמר רבי ירמיה, Amar Rabbi Yirmiah, so
back to our major theme here where we got onto this whole
discussion, which was the idea that all of the קרבנות, korbanos, well
the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim have to be in the north. The
Torah didn't need to say north by the
אשם. asham. ותיתי מבניין אב מחטאת, Veteisei m'binyan av m'chatas, from a
חטאת. chatas. Okay, חטאת chatas we learn חטאת chatas is the north
because it's linked to an עולה, olah, that's explicit in the Torah,
במקום אשר תשחט העולה תשחט החטאת, bimkom asher tishachat ha'olah tishachat hachatat,
so it's explicitly linking it. All right, and that makes the חטאת
chatas in the north from a היקש. hekesh. And now, why didn't
you go ahead and apply that to an אשם asham from a
בניין אב? binyan av? You know, they're קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and
just apply it to an אשם. asham. And the fact that we
didn't, and we needed an
explicit—the Torah to explicitly say—say it should show you you cannot do
build a בניין אב binyan av on a היקש. hekesh. Okay, לכתוב
צפון באשם ותיתי בניין אב מחטאת. lichtov tzafun b'asham veteisei binyan av
m'chatas. למאי הלכתא כתביה, L'mai hilchasa kasvei,
so why does the Torah go ahead and still write north by
an אשם? asham? לאו למימר, Le'av l'meimar, it must be to tell
you that דבר הלמד בהיקש אין חוזר ולמד בבניין אב, davar lamed
b'hekesh ein chozer u'lamed b'binyan av, that something that's learned from a
היקש hekesh you cannot go ahead and make it into a paradigm.
So that's the proof that we needed to say it explicitly by
an אשם. asham. But the Gemara isn't happy. ואימא, V'eima, according to
you, says the Gemara, תיתי מבניין אב מעולה. teisei m'binyan av m'olah.
If you really have a בניין אב, binyan av, who needs the
חטאת? chatas? Why not just start from the עולה? olah? The עולה
olah is explicitly in the north and that should be a בניין
אב binyan av that anything that's קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim is a
north. So why did it have to say it by חטאת? chatas?
Why did it have to say it by אשם? asham? There must
be some problem here with the בניין אב. binyan av. Okay, so
מאי טעמא לא אתי? mai ta'ama lo asi? Why are you not
learning it? משום דאיכא למפרך, mishum d'ika l'mifrach, because it's not a
paradigm, it's not a בניין אב. binyan av. There are things that
make the categories not exactly the same.
מה לעולה שכן כליל, mah l'olah she'ken kalil, an עולה olah is
completely burned, so you can't apply that to a חטאת chatas and
an אשם. asham. Okay, חטאת נמי איכא למפרך, chatas nami ika l'mifrach,
and if it had just said by a חטאת, chatas, so that's
why we didn't say it by an עולה. olah. So that's why
we're also not going to say it by a חטאת. chatas. And
it's not because of a היקש hekesh and then a בניין אב.
binyan av. The בניין אב binyan av is intrinsically problematic. Why couldn't
you have learned it from a חטאת? chatas? מה
לחטאת שכן מכפרת על חייבי כריתות, mah l'chatas she'ken mechaperet al chayavei
krisos, חטאת chatas is very weighty, חטאת chatas is מכפר mechaper on
things that you get כריתות krisos for and אשם asham is for—for
things that are usually of a lighter nature. So each one of
those is weighty, so you would not have been able to apply
it to an אשם, asham, an אשם asham is a weaker category.
Okay, so that's why you don't do a בניין אב binyan av
here and it has nothing to do with the fact that it
started with a היקש. hekesh. All right, now the Gemara is going
to turn its focus on this בניין אב binyan av thing. Okay,
which is טאקע taka why don't you do a בניין אב binyan
av here? And why don't you—maybe you could have done the צד
השווה tzad hashaveh of two of them to apply it to the
third. So now the Gemara says like this:
חדא מחדא לא אתי, chada m'chada lo asi, fine, I get that
you could not have learned עולה olah to a חטאת, chatas, you
couldn't have learned any one from—from the next. But תיתי חדא מתרתי,
teisei chada m'tartei, why not have said two and then you could
have maybe that created a common category and applied it to the
third. מהי תיתי? Mei-heicha teisei? So from which ones should you learn?
לא נכתוב רחמנא בעולה lo niktov rachmana b'olah ותיתי מחטאת ואשם, veteisei
m'chatas v'asham, and learn from a חטאת chatas and אשם. asham. Why
didn't the Torah explicitly say they need north and then you could
apply it to an עולה? olah? No, מה להנך שכן מכפרים, mah
l'hanei she'ken mechaperin, both of those achieve atonement.
לא נכתוב רחמנא בחטאת lo niktov rachmana b'chatas ותיתי מהנך, veteisei m'hanach,
learn it from an עולה olah and an אשם. asham. מה להנך
שכן זכרים, mah l'hanei she'ken zecharim, those are male animals. Now that's
not a חומרא—that's chumra not more מחמיר, machmir, but again, a בניין
אב binyan av means you want to do a pattern matching. Well
the pattern matching is, is that both an עולה olah and an
אשם asham are male and a חטאת chatas is a female. So
maybe for whatever reason the Torah demands north by males.
לא נכתוב באשם lo niktov b'asham ותיתי מהנך, veteisei m'hanach, learn it
from an—an עולה olah and a חטאת, chatas, okay, which are one's
male, one's female. No, מה להנך שכן ישנן בציבור כביחיד, mah l'hanei
she'ken yeshnan b'tzibur k'byachid, both of those you can have an עולה
ציבור, olah tzibur, like the normal תמיד, tamid, and you can have
a חטאת ציבור, chatas tzibur, which is like the case of, you
know, פר העלם דבר par helem davar and יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
and maybe that's why they get north. So—so okay, so therefore there
was no way that we could have
made. had to say it by all three and therefore we don't
know the answer of can you do a בניין אב binyan av
building on a היקש. hekesh. Now if you ask me, if you
can do, I will say this. The fact that you can do
a קל וחומר kal vachomer, building on a היקש, hekesh, so קל
וחומר kal vachomer is stronger. קל וחומר kal vachomer isn't just its
pattern matching, it's similar, it's like no, if it applies to a
strong case, certainly it applies to a weak case. So therefore that
makes sense that you might be able to do that building on
a היקש hekesh and not a בניין אב binyan av which is
weaker, which is just more a pattern matching paradigm and analogy. Okay,
so that's where we are. So, yes a קל וחומר, kal vachomer
בניין אב binyan av we don't know. That's in terms of starting
with a היקש. hekesh. Now as I said we're going to go
through
all 16 possibilities. So we started starting with a היקש, hekesh, now
we're going to start with the next thing. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay.
דבר הלמד בגזירה
שווה. Davar halamed bigzeirah shavah. Okay,
so the order is that we've done here is היקש, גזירה שווה,
hekesh gzeirah shavah, קל וחומר, kal vachomer, and בניין אב. binyan av.
So we did היקש hekesh, and we looked at היקש היקש, hekesh
hekesh, היקש hekesh גזירה שווה, היקש gzeirah shavah hekesh, קל וחומר, kal
vachomer, היקש בניין אב. hekesh binyan av. Now we're doing גזירה שווה,
gzeirah shavah, imagine it's like I said it's a square. So we're
going to do גזירה שווה היקש, gezeirah shavah hekesh, גזירה שווה גזירה
שווה, gzeirah shavah gzeirah shavah, גזירה שווה קל וחומר, gzeirah shavah kal
vachomer, גזירה שווה בניין אב. gzeirah shavah binyan av. Alright, that's going
to be the pattern. Let's take a look.
דבר הלמד בגזירה שווה מהו שילמד בהיקש. Davar halamed bigzeirah shavah mahu
sheyilamed behekesh. Something that you start with a גזירה שווה, gzeirah shavah,
you get from A to B with a גזירה שווה, gzeirah shavah,
can you get from B to C with a היקש. hekesh. אמר
רב
פפא Amar Rav Pappa says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, וזאת תורת זבח
השלמים אם על תודה יקריבנו. Vezot torat zevach hashlamim im al todah
yakrivennu. This is the הלכה halacha of a שלמים, shlamim, if you're
bringing it for a thanksgiving and then it tells you the הלכות
halachot of a תודה. todah. So, למדנו לתודה שבאה מן המעשר. Lamadnu
letodah sheba'ah min hama'aser. Now we can learn out that a
תודה todah comes from
מעשר. ma'aser. Somebody has their מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah,
excuse me, not מעשר בהמה, ma'aser behemah, you have your מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni of your fruit and you go ahead
and redeem it on money and then you're going to go use
that money in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And one of the things you can
use that money in ירושלים Yerushalayim for is to bring a קרבן
korban that you can eat the meat, is to bring like a
שלמים shlamim and eat the meat. Okay,
so the same is, even if you have an obligation to bring
a תודה, todah, you can go ahead and use your money of
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni to bring your תודה. todah. Now that is
specifically if you say when you make the נדר neder that you're
going to bring a תודה todah from the money of מעשר שני.
ma'aser sheni. If you just said that you're going to bring a
תודה todah and you had a standing obligation, then you cannot bring
it from money of מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. But anyway, that is
the הלכה. halacha. So let's take a look at what the גמרא
Gemara does with this. וזאת תורת זבח השלמים אם על תודה. למדנו
לתודה שבאה מן המעשר. Vezot torat zevach hashlamim im al todah. Lamadnu
letodah sheba'ah min hama'aser. A תודה todah can come from money of
מעשר שני. ma'aser sheni. How do you know that? מדאשכחן שלמים דאתו
ממעשר. Mid'ashkechan shlamim d'atu mima'aser. We know that שלמים shlamim can come
from מעשר. ma'aser. שלמים, shlamim,
and therefore since a תודה todah is being linked to a שלמים,
shlamim, I'll get back to that point in a minute,
we can apply what we know from שלמים shlamim to a תודה.
todah. Now how do you know about a שלמים? shlamim? שלמים גופייהו
מנלן? Shlamim gufayhu minalan? And where do you know שלמים shlamim themselves?
דכתיב שם שם. Dechtiv sham sham. That it's a גזירה שווה gzeirah
shavah, of שם שם. sham sham. By שלמים shlamim it says וזבחת
שלמים ואכלת שם. Vezavachta shlamim ve'achalta sham. And by מעשר ma'aser it
says ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך במקום אשר יבחר לשכן שמו שם. Ve'achalta
lifnei Hashem Elokecha bamakom asher yivchar leshaken shemo sham. So the שם
sham of מעשר שני ma'aser sheni and the שם sham of שלמים,
shlamim, so that is a גזירה שווה gzeirah shavah that gets us
to שלמים, shlamim, A to B through a גזירה שווה, gzeirah shavah
שם sham from מעשר ma'aser to שם sham of שלמים, shlamim, and
from שלמים shlamim to תודה todah is a היקש. hekesh. So something
from a גזירה שווה gzeirah shavah, can go the A to B,
can go the next step B to C through a היקש. hekesh.
Now the problem with this is that the גמרא Gemara doesn't really
distinguish when it talks about a היקש hekesh between something that is
explicitly stated, this is the הלכה, halacha, and something that is just
linked and we're inferring therefore you can go from B to C.
When the תורה Torah says וזאת תורת זבח השלמים אם על תודה
יקריבנו, Vezot torat vzevach hashlamim im al todah yakrivennu, it seems to
be saying that a תודה todah is a שלמים, shlamim, is a
type of a שלמים. shlamim. So to call it, it's a little
funny to call it a היקש, hekesh, but okay, it's not a
paradigm שלמים. shlamim. Anyway, so that's what the גמרא Gemara said. It's
similar when the תורה Torah sort of said במקום אשר תשחט העולה
תשחט החטאת. Bimakom asher tishachat ha'olah tishachat hachatat. You wouldn't think that
that's a היקש. hekesh. You think that the תורה Torah is explicitly
telling you, shecht it in this place. It's not a לימוד, limud,
that's explicitly what the תורה Torah is saying. But nevertheless, however we're
moving from A to B even if it's pretty explicit is considered
to be a, or B to C is considered to be a
היקש. hekesh. Okay, so if your A to B is a גזירה
שווה, gzeirah shavah you can go from B to C with a
היקש. hekesh.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like this, but we're not done.
The גמרא Gemara is not convinced about that. אמר ליה מר זוטרא
בריה דרב מרי לרבינא. Amar lei Mar Zutra bereih deRav Mari leRavina.
The son of רב מרי *Rav Mari* said to אבינא *Avina*, מעשר
maaser. דגן חולין chullin. בעלמא הוא *Maaser dagan chullin b'alma hu*, but
I don't understand, your A is חולין chullin *chullin*. Your מעשר שני
maaser sheni. *Maaser Sheini*, you know, there's a ר' מאיר *Rebbi Meir*
position that it's like קודש *kodesh*, but anyway fundamentally certainly compared to
קרבנות *korbanot* it's חולין chullin. *chullin*. So that's why you can do
this. These are laws that govern that limit the למד מן הלמד
*lamed min ha-lamed* by קדשים kodshim, *kodshim*. Here you're starting with חולין
chullin. *chullin*.
So אמר ליה *amar lei*, so רב פפא Rav Pappa *Rav Pappa*
said back to him, אמר אמר למה קודש ומלמד קודש *amar amra
lamed kodesh u'melamed kodesh*? Did anybody ever say that both the application
has to be קודש *kodesh* and the מלמד melamed. *melamed*, the one
you're coming it from has to be קודש *kodesh*? Both the A
and the B have to be קודש *kodesh*? No, the restrictions are
based on what you're applying it to, not where you're coming from.
So since what you're applying it to, your B and then your
C are קודש *kodesh*, that's where the restrictions would apply and nevertheless,
it's okay to go גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah, *gezeirah shavah* and then
היקש heikesh, *heikesh*. Now the implicit point of מר זוטרא בריה דרב
מרי *Mar Zutra brei d'Rav Mari* to אבינא *Avina* is that no,
it's not enough that the למד *lamed* is קודש *kodesh* for these
restrictions to apply, even if the מלמד *melamed*... sorry, let me say
that again,
just because the למד *lamed* is קודש *kodesh* doesn't mean that the
restrictions apply, only if the מלמד *melamed* is קודש *kodesh* do the
restrictions apply. Okay, so that is the debate, when these restrictions apply,
does... is it only when you know, does it have to be
that the application is קודש *kodesh* for the restrictions to apply or
does it have to be that the original הלכה halacha *halacha* has
to be קודש *kodesh* for the restrictions to apply? If you take
a look at רש"י *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* says,
the middle of רש"י *Rashi* אמר אמר *amar amra*, רש"י *Rashi* says
like this,
okay so he says דבתר למד אזלינן ומר זוטרא סבר בתר מלמד
אזלינן *d'batar lamed azlinan u'Mar Zutra savar batar melamed azlinan*, והיינו דאמרינן
בעלמא הניח למאן דאמר בתר למד אזלינן ומהו דאי בתר מלמד אזלינן
*v'hainu d'amrinan b'alma hanich l'man d'amar batar lamed azlinan u'mahu d'ei batar
melamed azlinan*. So this is implicit in this is the source of
the debate that with these restrictions of למד מן הלמד *lamed min
ha-lamed*, that you don't say them by... you know, there're restrictions about
it by קדשים kodshim. *kodshim*. Does it go by the A or
does it go by the B? Does it go by the source
or does it go by the application? But at least for רב
פפא Rav Pappa *Rav Pappa* we have proved that you can do
גזירה שוה gezeira shava *gezeirah shavah* A to B and then a
היקש hekesh *heikesh* B to C. Okay, so that's גזירה שוה gezeira
shava *gezeirah shavah* and היקש hekesh, *heikesh*. Now we're going to do,
for those keeping score at home, גזירה שוה gezeira shava. *gezeirah shavah*
גזירה שוה gezeira shava. *gezeirah shavah*. Let's take a look.
Okay, דבר הלמד בגזירה שוה מהו שילמד בגזירה שוה *Davar ha-lamed b'gezeirah
shavah mahu she-yilamed b'gezeirah shavah*? Can you go גזירה שוה gezeira shava
*gezeirah shavah* גזירה שוה gezeira shava *gezeirah shavah*? אמר רמי בר חמא
Rami bar Chama, תניא *Amar Rami bar Chama tanya*, we taught in
a ברייתא braita. *braita*, סולת מורבכת *soles murbeches*. Okay, so this is
by... this gives us a whole overview of קדשים *kodshim*. Okay, this
is by actually you know the חלות *chalos* that are brought by
the different types of things that are brought with the תודה todah
*Todah*. So one of them is סולת מורבכת *soles murbeches*, which is
a way that it is making... made, that first you cook it
in water, you know, and then you use... you do it with
the oil. So למדנו לרבוכה *lamadnu l'revuchah* that's the type of one
of the types of loaves is called a רבוכה *revuchah*, שבה סולת
*she-bah soles* that it's coming from fine flour. חלות מניין *chalos minayin*?
How do you know that even the חלות *chalos*, which is a
second type of the חלות *chalos* of the breads in the תודה
*Todah*, has to come from fine flour? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar, חלות
חלות *Talmud lomar chalos chalos*, because it says חלות *chalos* by רבוכה
*revuchah* and it says חלות *chalos* by the standard חלות *chalos*. רקיקין
מניין *rekikin minayin*? How about רקיקין *rekikin*, which is the third type
of bread that comes with a תודה *Todah*—I mean it's מצה *matzah*
whatever—but the third type of loaf, how do you know that has
to be fine flour? רקיקין מניין תלמוד לומר מצות מצות *rekikin minayin
Talmud lomar matzos matzos*. Okay, it says מצות *matzos* by the רקיקין
*rekikin* and it says מצות *matzos* by the חלות *chalos*. So therefore,
so this is a perfect example: you got from רבוכה *revuchah* to
חלות *chalos* from A to B by גזירה שוה gezeira shava *gezeirah
shavah*, okay, that גזירה שוה gezeira shava, *gezeirah shavah* was חלות חלות
*chalos chalos*. And then you got from B to C by גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* which was מצות מצות *matzos matzos*. Okay, so therefore
you can go from A to B and B to C, גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* built on גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. Perfect. Except let's
take a look. אמר ליה רבינא Ravina, *Amar lei Ravina*, so רבינא
Ravina *Ravina* challenged back, ממאי דמצות מצות מחלות גמר *mimai d'matzos matzos
me-chalos gmar*? Yes you have a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* מצות *matzos*,
but how do you know it is going from the חלות *chalos*
case of the תודה *Todah*, which itself was learned from a גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah*? דילמא ממאפה תנור גמר *dilma mi-maafeh tanur gmar*? Maybe
it's just from the מנחה *mincha* done by a תודה *Todah*, the
standard מנחה *mincha* that's a נדבה *nedavah* that's baked in an oven,
that there the תורה *Torah* explicitly calls it מצות *matzos* and explicitly
says סולת *soles*. So that's just a straight גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*,
not גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* based on גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. Okay,
so you don't know, you can't prove it from that. אלא ela,
אמר רבא Rabba *Ela amar Rava*, so we don't know based on
that, גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* because we don't
know that's what was going on there. אלא ela, אמר רבא Rabba
תניא *Ela amar Rava tanya*, we taught in a ברייתא *braita*, וקרבו
פרשו והוציא v'hotzi, *v'kirbo pirsho v'hotzi*. Okay, this is talking about taking
out the inner חטאת chatas *chatas* of a... you know, brought by
a כהן משיח kohen mashiach *Kohen Mashiach*, and that you take all
of the stuff, you take the inner... words and the refuse, you
know, and you bring it outside of the camp and the meat
and the skin and you burn it outside of the camp. Okay,
that's what it says by the חטאות chataos פנימיות of the פר
כהן משיח. par kohen mashiach. So let's take a look. וקרבו ופרשו
והוציא. v'kirbo u'firsho v'hotzi. מלמד שמוציאו שלם. Melamed she'motzio shalem. Now, so
you take it all out as one. Okay, so it doesn't say
that
you know, it says one act והוציא, v'hotzi so there's no way
you can take all the parts of the animal outside in like
one act unless you have not yet chopped, unless, if you have
chopped it up, there's no way you can take them all out
in one thing. But to take out everything, you know, the meat
and whatever and the innards as one thing, as one act, it
has to still be whole. Okay, so מלמד שמוציאו שלם. melamed she'motzio
shalem. יכול ישרפנו שלם, yachol yisrefenu shalem, maybe you burn it all,
you know, without having chopped it up first. תלמוד לומר, נאמר כאן
ne'emar kan ראשו וכרעיו. rosho u'chrao. It says here its head and
its legs. ונאמר להלן v'ne'emar l'halan ראשו וכרעיו rosho u'chrao and it
says later, you know, by an עולה olah that you, you know,
that you burn on the altar its head and its legs. מה
להלן על ידי נתוח, ma l'halan al yedei nitoach, in the same
way there it is, you know, through chopping it up as it's
clear, it says explicitly that you're מנתח, menateach, you chop it up
into pieces, into these various sections I should say, אף כאן על
ידי נתוח. af kan al yedei nitoach. Here too. So it is
a גזירה שוה that teaches you by the חטאת הפנימית chatas ha'pnimis
that you cut it up into sections before burning it. The פסוק
pasuk tells you you take it out fully, and the גזירה שוה
says you cut it up into sections before burning it. Okay. אי
מה להלן בהפשט אף כאן נמי בהפשט. ei ma l'halan b'hefshet af
kan nami b'hefshet. Maybe I should say, well, the same way by
an עולה olah you first flay it, you remove the leather, the
skin. Here too, maybe you should flay it before burning it.
תלמוד לומר וקרבו ופרשו. Talmud lomar v'kirbo u'firsho. No, וקרבו ופרשו v'kirbo
u'firsho says that you do not flay it. So what does "its
innards and its refuse" tell you that you don't remove the skin?
מה תלמודו? ma talmudo? What is the teaching?
אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa, כשם שפירשו בקרבו כך בשרו בעורו.
keshem she'pirsho b'kirbo kach besaro b'oro. The same way clearly you're not
going to remove, you know, the digested food, the פירשו pirsho from
the
intestines. וקרבו ופרשו v'kirbo u'firsho means, you know, as one unit, you
leave the digested foods in the intestines. So the same way what
the previous פסוק pasuk says because the previous פסוק pasuk says ואת
עור הפר ואת כל בשרו על ראשו ועל כרעיו וקרבו ופרשו והוציא.
v'es or ha'par v'es kol besaro al rosho v'al kera-av v'kirbo u'firsho
v'hotzi. So that's all this stuff והוציא in one taking out, you
don't chop it up initially. You chop it up when you get
there, but it connects עור הפר וכל בשרו or ha'par v'chol besaro
to וקרבו ופרשו. v'kirbo u'firsho. So the same way וקרבו ופרשו v'kirbo
u'firsho is one unit, which is just intuitive and obvious, the same
is true by the meat and the skin.
Okay. ותניא. v'tanya. So that gets us to how you treat an
inner חטאת chatas from a גזירה שוה. We learn that you cut
it into sections before you burn it outside of the camp, but
after you have brought it out whole. ותניא, v'tanya, we find a
ברייתא. רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, Rebbi says, נאמר כאן עור ובשר ופרש.
ne'emar kan or u'vasar u'feresh. Here it says, you know, the skin,
the meat, and the refuse. ונאמר להלן v'ne'emar l'halan and it says
over there, I mean, actually, excuse me, the כאן kan here is
Rebbi's case. The כאן kan here was the פר ושעיר par v'seir
of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the other cases of inner חטאות that
we've been talking about. So it says here by יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, you know, the עור ובשר ופרש. or u'vasar u'feresh. ונאמר להלן
v'ne'emar l'halan and it says over there, coming back to our case,
עור ובשר ופרש or u'vasar u'feresh by the inner חטאת chatas of
the פר כהן משיח. par kohen mashiach. מה להלן על ידי נתוח,
ma l'halan al yedei nitoach, and the same way there you cut
it up into sections, שלא בהפשט, she'lo b'hefshet, but you don't flay
it, אף כאן על ידי נתוח שלא בהפשט. af kan al yedei
nitoach she'lo b'hefshet. Here too, you cut it up into sections by
יום כיפור Yom Kippur without flaying it. So perfect, you go from
A to B and B to C by גזירה שוה. You went
from A to B from the עולה olah to the חטאת chatas
of פר כהן משיח par kohen mashiach by גזירה שוה to say
you cut it up before you burn it, and then you go
from there to יום כיפור Yom Kippur by גזירה שוה to say
the same is true by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so when
you start with a גזירה שוה and you then do a היקש,
hekesh רב פפא Rav Pappa says you can do that, but that
was debated whether you start, you know, based on למיד lamid or
מלמד. And גזירה שוה גזירה שוה, gezeira shava gezeira shava, that is
clear that you can do. Next,
גזירה שוה וקל
וחומר.
gezeira shava v'kal vachomer.
Okay. דבר הלמד בגזירה שוה מהו שילמד בקל וחומר. Davar ha'lamed b'gezeira
shava mahu she'yilamed b'kal vachomer. When you,
if you start with a גזירה שוה, can you build on it
a קל וחומר? קל וחומר. kal vachomer kal vachomer? So now the
גמרא, Gemara, pretty high funny, the גמרא Gemara now is going to
try to use logic to prove whether these rules apply, which all,
it also seems pretty arbitrary, but the גמרא Gemara is going to
try to use logic, and it's going to try to use קל
וחומר kal vachomer? to determine whether the rules can apply or not.
So it's a קל וחומר kal vachomer. that you should be able
to do גזירה שוה קל וחומר. kal vachomer Why? ומה היקש שאינו
מלמד בהיקש... u'ma heikesh she'eino melamed b'heikesh... מדרבא מדרבא מדרבינא מדרבינא, mi'de'Rabba
mi'de'Rabba mi'de'Ravina mi'de'Ravina, a היקש hekesh doesn't go to another היקש, hekesh,
that was the very first thing we did either based on רבא
or רבינא, you know, based on the idea of north by the
חטאת chatas and the
אשם. asham. So מלמד בקל וחומר, melamed be'kal vachomer, so even though
a היקש hekesh can't build, you can't build on a היקש hekesh
to do a היקש, hekesh you can build on a היקש hekesh,
to do a קל וחומר. kal vachomer Okay, בקל וחומר מדתנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל be'kal vachomer mi'de'tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael from תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael about applying you know some of the
stuff about a חטאת chatas.
by פר העלם דבר par he'elam davar to what do you call
it to יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Okay, so you see that a
קל וחומר kal vachomer. that a קל וחומר kal vachomer is strong.
It can build on a היקש hekesh. which is comparatively weak cause
you can't do a היקש hekesh on a היקש, hekesh. but you
can do a קל וחומר kal vachomer on a היקש. hekesh, Okay,
so גזירה שווה המלמדת בהיקש, gezeirah shavah ha'melamedes be'hekesh, a גזירה שווה
gzeirah shavah, is stronger a foundation because when you start with a
גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah you can then build a היקש hekesh on
it, which you could not do when you started with a היקש.
hekesh. How do you know that? מדרב פפא mi'de'Rav Pappa from what
רב פפא Rav Pappa said about the whole case about שלמים shelamim
and תודה and מעשר maaser שני. So אינו דין שתלמד בקל וחומר?
eino din she'tilamed be'kal vachomer? So that clearly is a stronger foundation,
a גזירה שווה. gezeirah shavah So if it's a stronger foundation than
היקש, hekesh certainly you should be able to build a קל וחומר
kal vachomer on it, which is actually a very good argument. Okay,
אינו דין שתלמד בקל וחומר. eino din she'tilamed be'kal vachomer. So therefore
you should be able to say גזירה שווה קל וחומר. gezeirah shavah
kal vachomer. If you can do גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah. היקש, hekesh
you can certainly do גזירה שווה קל וחומר. gezeirah shavah kal vachomer.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, הניחא למאן דאית ליה דרב פפא,
hani nicha le'man d'is lei de'Rav Pappa, that's if you agree to
רב פפא Rav Pappa that you can do גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah
and היקש hekesh and you were able to learn from מעשר. אלא
למאן דלית ליה דרב פפא, ela le'man d'lais lei de'Rav Pappa, but
if you don't agree with רב פפא because there the case started
with מעשר which wasn't קדשים, so the whole thing isn't relevant. אלא
למאן דלית ליה דרב פפא מאי איכא למימר? ela le'man d'lais lei
de'Rav Pappa mai ika le'meimar? What can you say? So you have
not proved yet that outside of רב פפא that you can do
גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah and then היקש. hekesh אלא, okay, we'll try
to prove it with another
קל וחומר. kal vachomer אלא קל וחומר ומה היקש שאין מלמד בהיקש,
ela kal vachomer uma hekesh she'ein melamed be'hekesh, we'll start with the
fact that you can't do a היקש hekesh on a היקש hekesh
like we did before, either רבא or רבינא by אשם asham and
עולה olah and חטאת. chatas. מלמד בקל וחומר, melamed be'kal vachomer, but
everybody agrees that you can do היקש hekesh and then
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מדתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל mi'de'tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael
from what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael taught about you know learning out
to פר יום כיפור. par Yom Kippur.
So therefore it's a weak foundation but you can still build on
it a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Okay, מלמד בקל וחומר מדתנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל גזירה שווה המלמדת בגזירה שווה חברתה. melamed be'kal vachomer mi'de'tana
d'bei Rabbi Yishmael gezeirah shavah ha'melamedes be'gezeirah shavah chavertah.
Now a גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah it can be learned, can build
on a גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah חברתה, chavertah, that we've learned, גזירה
שווה גזירה שווה. gezeirah shavah gezeirah shavah. Okay, we have it, so
how do you know that? מרמי בר חמא mi'Rami bar Chama from
רמי בר חמא, the whole thing we did here about cutting up
the you know going from עולה olah to what do you call
it to a פר par of the כהן משיח to cutting it
up before you burn it and from there to יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. So אינו דין שתלמד בקל
וחומר? eino din she'tilamed be'kal vachomer?
Certainly you should be able to be learning it from a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. Certainly you should be able to build a קל
וחומר kal vachomer. on it. So what is the גמרא Gemara saying?
It's saying you're right,
you cannot necessarily go, it's the same basic you know it's the
same basic thing that we did before, that היקש hekesh on היקש
hekesh, doesn't work so היקש hekesh is a weak foundation,
and קל וחומר kal vachomer on היקש hekesh does work. So now
what's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer So first we tried to say
well
גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah is a stronger foundation cause you can't do
היקש hekesh built on a היקש, hekesh but you can do a
היקש hekesh, built on a גזירה שווה. gezeirah shavah. So that was
going to allow us to make a קל וחומר, kal vachomer? you're
starting from a stronger foundation. But the גמרא Gemara says no, not
everybody agrees you can do a היקש hekesh. built on a גזירה
שווה. gezeirah shavah. So now we're doing the same thing except we're
saying okay fine I can't say היקש hekesh built on גזירה שווה,
gezeirah shavah, but I can say גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah built on
a גזירה שווה. gezeirah shavah. So היקש hekesh. on a היקש, hekesh
one thing on itself, that's weak and you can't do, and nevertheless
you can do a קל וחומר kal vachomer, on a היקש. heikesh
גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah on a גזירה שווה, gezeirah shavah, the thing
on itself, everybody agrees you can do, so that's starting off as
something conceptually stronger than היקש heikesh on היקש. heikesh Okay, because you
can do it on itself. So if you can do גזירה שווה
gezeirah shavah on גזירה שווה, gezeirah shavah, then you should certainly be
able to do גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah excuse me קל וחומר kal
vachomer on גזירה שווה. gezeirah shavah.
Okay, so bottom line,
if you can do a קל וחומר kal vachomer built on a
היקש heikesh which is weaker, you can do a קל וחומר kal
vachomer built on a גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah which is stronger. And
the evidence that גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah is stronger. is that you
can do a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* on a גזירה שוה *gezeirah
shavah*, but you cannot do a היקש hekesh. *hekesh* on a היקש
*hekesh*. Okay, good. So where are we now? As we have, we
did גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* on built on a היקש *hekesh*. That
was debate, that was רב פפא *Rav Pappa* says yes, others question
it.
Excuse me, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
Start again. We starting with a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and then
going to a היקש *hekesh*. Okay, that רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said
yes, others debate it. Starting from a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* then
going to a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, everybody says yes. גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* going to קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*, everybody says
yes, because גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* is stronger than היקש *hekesh*, and
you can do היקש *hekesh* to קל וחומר kal vachomer, *kal vachomer*,
so you can do גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* to a קל וחומר
kal vachomer *kal vachomer*. Now we're left with the final case, which
is גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* בנין אב binyan av? *binyan av*. Let's
take a look. דבר הלמד בגזירה שוה מהו שילמד בבנין אב *davar
halamed b'gezeirah shavah mahu sheyilamed b'binyan av*. Excuse me, did I skip
a line?
Yeah, no, דבר הלמד בגזירה שוה מהו שילמד בבנין אב *davar halamed
b'gezeirah shavah mahu sheyilamed b'binyan av*. You start with a גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* and you do בנין אב binyan av *binyan av*. What's
the story? תיקו *teiku*, we don't know. Okay, so that's גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah*. The first three are pretty much yes: גזירה שוה *gezeirah
shavah* then היקש *hekesh*, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* says yes, others question.
גזירה שוה גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah gezeirah shavah*, yes. גזירה שוה קל
וחומר kal vachomer *gezeirah shavah kal vachomer*, yes. גזירה שוה בנין אב
binyan av. *gezeirah shavah binyan av*, which is weaker than a קל
וחומר kal vachomer, *kal vachomer*, we don't know. Fine. Now we are
going to the column of קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*. So
again, the order is היקש *hekesh*, גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, קל וחומר
kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*, בנין אב binyan av *binyan av*. So now
we're going to start with a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*
to get us from A to B and then try to go
from B to C through these various things. Okay. דבר הלמד בקל
וחומר מהו שילמד בהיקש be-heikesh *davar halamed b'kal vachomer mahu sheyilamed b'hekesh*.
So first, היקש *hekesh*. Can you do קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal
vachomer* A to B, קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*, B to
C, היקש *hekesh*? קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*. We'll try to
argue you can do it from a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal
vachomer*. ומה גזירה שוה שאינה למדה בהיקשה מדבי רבי יוחנן מלמד בהיקש
מדבי רב פפא *u'mah gezeirah shavah she'einah lamedah b'hekaysha mid'vei Rabbi Yochanan
melamed b'hekesh mid'vei Rav Pappa*. So when it comes to a גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah*, you cannot build a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* on
a היקש *hekesh*. That was Rabbi Yochanan's point before about, let's say,
by חטאת *chatas*, and חטאת *chatas* will link to אשם *asham* based
on the גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* of קדש קדשים *kodesh kodashim*. So
you can't do that. If you start with a היקש *hekesh*, you
cannot do a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* built on it. Okay. So
גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* in a way as the second step is
weak in that it cannot build on a היקש *hekesh*. ומה גזירה
שוה שאינה למדה בהיקשה מדבי רבי יוחנן מלמד בהיקש מדבי רב פפא
*u'mah gezeirah shavah she'einah lamedah b'hekaysha mid'vei Rabbi Yochanan melamed b'hekesh mid'vei
Rav Pappa*.
So even though it's weak that it cannot build on a היקש
*hekesh*, it has the strength that it can be that it can
do the reverse. You can start with a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*
and then do a היקש *hekesh*, like רב פפא *Rav Pappa*.
You can do the reverse order. That was the case of שם
שם
*sham sham* by, you know, by מעשר שני *maaser sheni* and שלמים
*shlamim*. Okay. קל וחומר kal vachomer? הלמד מהיקש מדבי תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל *kal vachomer halamed me'hekesh mid'tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael*. קל וחומר kal
vachomer *kal
vachomer*, however,
is stronger than a גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. A קל וחומר kal
vachomer *kal vachomer* can build on a היקש *hekesh* from תנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל *tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael* about יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. So
if a קל וחומר kal vachomer, *kal vachomer* is stronger that it
can build on a היקש *hekesh* and גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* cannot,
אינו דין שילמד בהיקש *eino din sheyilamed b'hekesh*. So logically, therefore, it
can certainly then do the reverse, and you can do קל וחומר
kal vachomer *kal vachomer* and then היקש *hekesh*. Okay. So if you
can do גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and היקש *hekesh*, and גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* is weaker, you can certainly do קל וחומר kal vachomer.
*kal vachomer* and then היקש *hekesh*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
הניחא למאן דאית ליה דרב פפא *ha nicha l'man d'is lei d'Rav
Pappa*. That's if you hold of רב פפא *Rav Pappa* that you
can do that you can do גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and then
a היקש *hekesh*, learning from מעשר *maaser*. אלא למאן דלית ליה דרב
פפא מאי איכא למימר *ela l'man d'leis lei d'Rav Pappa mai ika
l'meimar*? If you don't hold like רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, what can
you say? תיקו *teiku*. All right. So then we don't have any
way to learn it out. Okay. So step number one here, which
we are in terms of קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* and
then היקש *hekesh*, we are saying that based on what we know
by רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, if you hold of רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* and you can do גזירה שוה היקש *gezeirah shavah hekesh*, then
you can do קל וחומר kal vachomer, היקש *kal vachomer hekesh*. But
if you don't hold like רב פפא *Rav Pappa*, we don't know
what the story is with קל וחומר kal vachomer היקש *kal vachomer
hekesh*. Okay. So that's starting with קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*
and then going to היקש *hekesh*. Next is going to be קל
וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*, דבר הלמד בקל וחומר מהו שילמד בגזירה
שוה *davar halamed b'kal vachomer mahu sheyilamed b'gezeirah shavah*. Okay. גזירה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* comes next in the list. All right. So if you
start with a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer* to a קל
וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*, can you build on it a גזירה
שוה *gezeirah shavah*? קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*. We're learning from
a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*. ומה גזירה שוה שאינה למדה
מהיקשה מדבי רבי יוחנן *u'mah gezeirah shavah she'einah lamedah me'hekaysha mid'vei Rabbi
Yochanan*. A גזירה שוה *gezeirah shavah* cannot build on a היקש *hekesh*.
That's what we learned from רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, right? The היקש
*hekesh* was The היקש *hekkesh* was that it was north about a
חטאת *chatas* and we don't build a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* on
it to get you to an אשם *asham*, so גזרה שוה *gezeirah
shavah* is weak that it cannot build on a היקש *hekkesh*, מלמד
בגזרה שוה *melamed be-gezeirah shavah*, but you can do גזרה שוה גזרה
שוה *gezeirah shavah gezeirah shavah* מרמי בר חמא *mi-Rami bar Chama*. That's
מרמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama*'s case, right? גזרה שוה גזרה שוה
*Gezeirah shavah gezeirah shavah* was the whole case of the chopping up
of the, what do you call it, of the animal and of
the and burning it, you know, outside. קל וחומר kal vachomer הלמד
בהיקש
מתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *Kal vachomer halomed be-hekkesh mi-Tanna de-Vei Rabbi Yishmael*.
So now a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer* is stronger than
a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* because a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal
vachomer* can build on a היקש *hekkesh*. How do you know? That's
תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *Tanna de-Vei Rabbi Yishmael*. That's the whole case
of יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* learning out from, you know, the פר
העלם דבר *par helam davar*. So now a קל וחומר kal vachomer
*kal vachomer* which is stronger than a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, אינו
דין שתלמד בגזרה שוה *eino din she-tilamed be-gezeirah shavah*. So that certainly
you can go ahead and go from a קל וחומר kal vachomer
*kal vachomer* to a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*. Okay, so let's say
that again. גזרה שוה
*Gezeirah shavah* when גזרה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* is the, you know, the second step, so so
that is
so when גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* is weaker as a second step
than a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* because you can't build
a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* on a היקש *hekkesh* but you can
build a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* on a היקש *hekkesh*.
Okay, so גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* makes that weaker at least as
a second step than a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*. Now
that we've established it's weaker, we'll assume it's true even as a
first step. So if a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* can build on
a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, so even though גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*
is weaker than a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*, then certainly
a קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* when you start with a
קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer*, if you can start with a
גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and add a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, then
certainly when you start with a קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*
which is stronger, you can then add a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*.
Okay, so that is how we are proving that. So starting with
a קל וחומר kal vachomer? *kal vachomer* and then doing a גזרה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* does work. Okay. דבר הלמד בקל וחומר מהו שילמד
בקל וחומר *Davar lamed be-kal vachomer mahu she-yilamed be-kal vachomer*. Now they're
up now they're up to the third of the of the four
with the קל וחומר kal vachomer *kal vachomer* starting with a קל
וחומר *kal vachomer* and then going to a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*
build a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* of a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*.
So let's take a look. קל וחומר *Kal vachomer* we're going to
try to use a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* to prove this question.
ומה גזרה שוה שאינה למידה בהיקש מדרבי יוחנן *U-mah gezeirah shavah she-einah
lemeidah be-hekkesh mi-deRabbi Yochanan*, a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* is is weak.
Okay that you cannot go ahead and build it on a היקש
*hekkesh* from רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, that was the whole thing about
the חטאת *chatas* and the עולה *olah*. Okay so גזרה שוה *gezeirah
shavah* is weak that you can't build it on a היקש *hekkesh*,
מלמדת בקל וחומר *melamedes be-kal vachomer*.
However a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* can go ahead and build itself
on a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* so you can do
you
can start from a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* and then do a
גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* כדאמרן *kede-amaran* like we said before, we learned
that out actually using a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. Okay so קל
וחומר הלמד מהיקש מתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *kal vachomer halomed me-hekkesh mi-Tanna
de-Vei Rabbi Yishmael*. So קל וחומר *kal vachomer* that you can actually
go ahead and build on a היקש *hekkesh* like we learned from
רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*, אינו דין שתלמד בקל וחומר *eino din she-tilamed
be-kal vachomer*. Certainly you can go ahead and do a קל וחומר
*kal vachomer* built on a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. So how does
that work? So it works as follows. We are first going to
prove that a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* is stronger than a גזרה
שוה *gezeirah shavah*. How are we going to prove that a קל
וחומר *kal vachomer* is stronger than a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*?
Because you go you can't do היקש *hekkesh* and then גזרה שוה
*gezeirah shavah*. Okay, that you can't do, that was the whole discussion
before about, you know, חטאת *chatas* and אשם *asham*. But you can
do היקש *hekkesh* and then קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. So it shows
that קל וחומר *kal vachomer* is stronger. That's the beginning, that's the
basic קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. Now what you can do is גזרה
שוה *gezeirah shavah* and then קל וחומר *kal vachomer* that we proved
earlier. We actually used a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* to prove earlier
that you can do גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah* and קל וחומר *kal
vachomer*. So now that we've proved that you can do גזרה שוה
*gezeirah shavah* and then a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, then you can
now and we've proven that a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* is stronger
than a גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, then you should certainly be able
to do a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* and then a קל וחומר
*kal vachomer*. Okay, I hope you're following this. So that is that,
that is the proof. Basically קל וחומר *kal vachomer* is stronger than
גזרה שוה *gezeirah shavah*, so if you can do גזרה שוה *gezeirah
shavah* and קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, you can do קל וחומר *kal
vachomer* and קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. All right, so let's see what
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. וזהו קל וחומר בן קל וחומר ve-zehu
kal vachomer ben kal vachomer. בן קל וחומר *Ve-zehu kal vachomer ben
kal vachomer ben kal vachomer*.
That's a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* derivative of a קל וחומר *kal
vachomer*. Why is that? Because the you know the the we use
a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* to teach you that you can make
a derive a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* from a קל וחומר *kal
vachomer*. So it's a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* that is learned out,
the קל וחומר *kal vachomer* that we're learning from the קל וחומר
*kal vachomer* is learned out itself, we learned the law from a
קל וחומר *kal vachomer* showing that a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*... was
stronger than a גזירה שווה. gezera shava. So then the גמרא Gemara
challenges this and the גמרא Gemara, says, what are you talking about?
בן בנו של קל וחומר הוא. ben beno shel kal vachomer hu.
It’s actually the grandson of a קל וחומר, meaning the whole way
we use a קל וחומר to show that a קל וחומר was
stronger than a גזירה שווה. gezera shava But the basis that we
were learning from was that you can do from גזירה שווה gezera
shava קל וחומר, you should be able to do קל וחומר קל
וחומר. kal vachomer kal vachomer. But the only way we know you
can do גזירה שווה gezera shava, קל וחומר is itself a קל
וחומר from the earlier discussion. So this is itself, as it were,
a קל וחומר based on a קל וחומר. So it's pretty like,
you know, meta. Okay, the question is, can you do a קל
וחומר based on a קל וחומר? And we sort of, you know,
can you go קל וחומר A to B and then קל וחומר
B to C? And we're learning it using the קל וחומר, but
the גמרא Gemara, is saying, but you're only using it using a
קל וחומר based on another קל וחומר. So that's already like, you
know, it's almost the same question. How do you know that you
can do a קל וחומר בן בנו של קל וחומר? kal vachomer
ben beno shel kal vachomer? Now I should say that in parlance
in the ישיבה yeshiva world, you know, when you say this is
a קל וחומר בן בנו של קל וחומר, kal vachomer ben beno
shel kal vachomer, it's a way of saying this is such an
obvious thing. It's like the granddaddy of all קל וחומרים. kal vachomerim.
But in the גמרא, gemara it really means it's derivative. It's a
קל וחומר based on a קל וחומר, so it's not so clear
you should be able to do it. So our whole question is
can you go A to B, B to C, קל וחומר קל
וחומר? kal vachomer kal vachomer. We're learning that out from a קל
וחומר based on the fact that קל וחומר is stronger than גזירה
שווה, but that itself we only know based on a קל וחומר.
אלא, says the גמרא, gemara קל וחומר. We'll try this קל וחומר.
ומה היקש שאינו למד מהיקש אם ידרב אם ידרב אם ידרב ורבינא,
uma heikesh she-eino lamed me-heikesh im yidrav im yidrav im yidrav veravina,
you can't go היקש היקש, heikesh heikesh, מלמד בקל וחומר מדתנא דבי
רבי ישמעאל, melamed be-kal vachomer mi-detanya devei Rebbi Yishmael, but you can
go היקש קל וחומר. hekesh kal vachomer,
So that's not using any קל וחומרים, kal vachomerim, it's just straight.
היקש is weak but you can still do היקש קל וחומר. heikesh
kal vachomer. קל וחומר הלמד מהיקש מדתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, kal vachomer
halamad me-heikesh mi-detanya devei Rebbi Yishmael, קל וחומר is stronger. You can't
do היקש היקש, heikesh heikesh, but you do היקש קל וחומר. heikesh
kal vachomer. So if קל וחומר is stronger than היקש and בהיקש
you can do היקש קל וחומר, heikesh kal vachomer. אינו דין שילמד
בקל וחומר קל וחומר. eino din she-yilamed be-kal vachomer kal vachomer. Certainly
you do קל וחומר קל וחומר. וזהו קל וחומר בן קל וחומר.
That's a simple קל וחומר based on a קל וחומר. Okay, so
basically היקש is weak and the laws of היקש we know without
any קל וחומרים. kal vachomerim. היקש היקש heikesh heikesh no, היקש קל
וחומר heikesh kal vachomer, yes. So קל וחומר that is stronger, you
can certainly do קל וחומר קל וחומר. Okay, and that is using
a קל וחומר argument to learn out that you can make a
קל וחומר argument.
Last case: דבר הלמד בקל וחומר מהו שילמד בבנין אב. davar halamad
be-kal vachomer mahu she-yilamed be-binyan av. Okay, last of the קל וחומר
column. Can you start with a קל וחומר and then do a
בנין אב? So אמר רב ירמיה תא שמע, amar Rav Yirmiya ta
shema, come in here. מלק ונמצא טרפה. malak ve-nimtza tereifa. You did
a מליקה melika on a bird
and then it was a טרפה. tereifa. Now the basic הלכה is
like this. If you שחט shachat an animal and it's a טרפה,
tereifa, there's no טומאה. tumah. If it dies without שחיטה, shechita, it's
a נבלה, nevela, there is טומאה. tumah. A bird that is a
נבלה nevela also there's טומאה, tumah, but only when you swallow it.
So the question is the following: if you go ahead and you
שחט... shacht... so if you do a מליקה melika on a bird
and it's a טרפה, tereifa, do you treat it like a טרפה
tereifa and no טומאה, tumah, or do you treat it like a
נבלה nevela and yes טומאה? tumah? And there actually are three debates.
There is a position... well let's take a look. מלק ונמצא טרפה.
malak ve-nimtza tereifa. רבי מאיר אומר אינו מטמא בבית הבליעה. Rebbi Meir
omer eino metamei be-veit ha-beli'ah. You treat it like a טרפה tereifa
and there's no טומאה tumah when you swallow it. רבי יהודה אומר
מטמא בבית הבליעה. Rebbi Yehuda omer metamei be-veit ha-beli'ah. No, there is
טומאה tumah when you swallow it. And actually רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says when it comes to birds, even if you שחט shacht it
and it was a טרפה, tereifa, there's טומאה. tumah. Okay, so אמר
רבי מאיר קל וחומר. amar Rebbi Meir kal vachomer. So רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir is going to make a קל וחומר that there should
be no
טומאה. tumah. ומה נבלת בהמה שמטמא במגע ובמשא, u-mah neveilat behema she-metamei
be-maga u-ve-massa, when it comes to an animal that it's טמא tamei
if you touch it or carry it... and it's a real serious
טומאה, tumah, nevertheless, שחיטתה מטהרת טרפתה מטומאתה, shechitatah metaheret tereifatah mi-tum'atah, when
you שחט shacht it and it's a טרפה, tereifa, there's no טומאה.
tumah. נבלת העוף שאין מטמא במגע ובמשא neveilat ha-of she-ein metamei be-maga
u-ve-massa when you deal with a נבלה nevela of a bird that
there's no טומאה tumah when you touch it or carry it, only
when you swallow it, so it's a much lighter... אינו דין שתהא
שחיטתה מטהרת טרפתה מטומאתה. eino din she-tehei shechitatah metaheret tereifatah mi-tum'atah. Certainly
שחיטה shechita should say... a שחיטה shechita of a bird should say
that it is not a נבלה. nevela. And once we accept that,
which is pretty logical, even though רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda argues on
that, so that's a קל וחומר to say שחיטה shechita of a
bird is not a טרפה. tereifa. And now we're going to do
a בנין אב to say the same as about
מליקה. melika. מה מצינו בשחיטה שמכשרת באכילתה מטהרת טרפתה... mah matzinu bi-shechita
she-makhsheret be-akhilatah metaheret tereifatah... so the same way שחיטה shechita that makes
it fit for eating gets it out of, you know, its טרפה...
tereifa... you know, if it's a טרפה tereifa it's still
טהור... tahor... מטהרת טרפתה מטומאתה. metaheret tereifatah mi-tum'atah. The טרפה tereifa it
still removes it from its טומאה tumah status. So שחיטה shechita of
a bird is
טהור. tahor. אף מליקה שמכשרת מאכילה תטהר טרפתה. af melika she-makhsheret me-akhila
tetaher tereifatah. Even מליקה, melika, which normally would make something a נבלה,
nevela, but when it's a קרבן korban is what. makes it kosher
and makes it able to be eaten if it's a חטאת. So
if it's true by שחיטה shechita of a bird, of a טרפה
traifa bird, that it's טהור, tahor, מליקה melika should be as well.
So it's a קל וחומר that שחיטה shechita of a טרפה traifa
bird is טהור, tahor, and building on that קל וחומר you do
a מה מצינו ma matzinu to say the same is true about
מליקה. melika. So that seems to be a pretty good proof that
you can do a מה מצינו ma matzinu built on a קל
וחומר. So the גמרא says שמעת מינה דכלי שרת מטהר טרפתה מטומאתה.
shamas mina d'kli shares metaher traifasa mitumasa. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi
omer דיה כנבלת בהמה טהורה dai k'nevelas beheima tehora ששחיטתה מטהרתה she'shechitasa
mitaherasa ולא מליקתה. v'lo melikasa. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says no,
no, no, you can't go from a, you know, from שחיטה shechita
to מליקה. melika. מליקה melika is fundamentally a different act. You can't
use a בנין אב. Okay, but anyway, isn't this a proof that
you can build a בנין אב on a קל וחומר? So the
גמרא says ולא היא. v'lo hi. That's not a proof. התם תיהוי
היא משחיטה דחולין קא חזינן. hasam tehavi hi mishechita d'chullin k'chazinan. There
it makes sense because there you're learning it from חולין. You start
from the bird of, you know, you start from an animal that's
חולין and a bird that's חולין. So the A and the bird
are חולין. It's only the C that's קדשים. So in that case,
you know, definitely the restrictions do not apply. So we do not
know about start, about קל וחומר and then a היקש. Okay, that
is three of the four columns. We will do the last one
tomorrow.