Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ח, chet, זבחים
Zvachim 8. We pick up at the bottom of ז: עמוד ב,
Zayin Amud Bet, two lines from the bottom. We are going through
the different parts of the משנה mishnah and we had a whole
discussion how do you know that normal all קרבנות korbanot other than
חטאת chatas and
פסח, pesach, though you're supposed to שחט shecht them לשמה, lishmah, do
all the עבודות avodos לשמה lishmah and לשם בעלים, l'shem ba'alim, but
if you don't, then they are כשר kosher and you offer them
up on the מזבח, mizbeach, but they don't count for the לשם
חובה, l'shem chovah, they, the owners, don't fulfill their obligation. So we
learned all the פסוקים psukim about that, and now we're shifting to
the next part of the משנה mishnah where it says that the
exception is חטאת chatas and פסח. pesach. חטאת chatas and פסח, pesach,
if you do it שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo, you know thinking of
that it's a different קרבן korban or for different owners, then it
is פסול, pasul, and the קרבן korban is completely invalid and you
cannot bring it on the מזבח. mizbeach. So we're going to see
where we learn that from. Okay, חטאת מנלן, chatas minalan, two lines
from the bottom ז: עמוד ב. Zayin Amud Bet. Where do you
learn the חטאת chatas from?
So first the גמרא gemara is going to try to say where
do you learn that you're supposed to do it even למצוה לכתחילה,
l'mitzva l'chatchila, then it's going to ask where do you learn that
it's מעכב me'akev that if you don't do it the whole קרבן
korban is פסול. pasul. And as רש"י Rashi points out, the גמרא
gemara before already sort of said you learn all the קרבנות korbanot
that are לכתחילה l'chatchila from the פסוק pasuk that sort
of categorized them all together, grouped them all together, זאת התורה לעולה
למנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמילואים ולזבח השלמים, zos hatorah la'olah u'laminchah v'lachatat v'la'asham
v'lamiluim u'lizevach hashelamim, okay, which puts them all in the same category.
But and we're going to get back to that, but first we're
going to try to see if we can learn it out from
the פסוקים psukim by חטאת chatas itself that number one it's a
מצוה mitzva that you're supposed to do it and number two that
if you don't it's מעכב me'akev the קרבן korban is invalid. So
חטאת מנלן, chatas minalan, where do you know this from a חטאת?
chatas? דכתיב dechsiv the פסוק pasuk says ושחט אתה לחטאת v'shachat osah
l'chatat
and he should שחט shecht it, this is talking about the normal
חטאת chatas that's brought for a normal sin what the גמרא gemara
calls a חטאת חלב, chatas chelev, a חטאת chatas of forbidden fat
because that's like a way of a classic type of an עבירה
aveira that you get כרת kares for, okay, and he shall שחט
shecht it לחטאת l'chatat for a חטאת, chatas, which we understand to
mean for the purpose of being a חטאת. chatas. שתהא שחיטה לשם
חטאת she'te'hei shechitah l'shem chatat that teaches you the שחיטה shechitah has
to be for the sake of it being a חטאת. chatas. אשכחן
שחיטה, ashken shechitah, that's good for שחיטה. shechitah. Now we have to
go through all the
עבודות. avodos. קבלה מנלן, kabala minalan, how do you know about catching
the blood? דכתיב dechsiv as it says top of ח. עמוד א
Chet Amud Aleph ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת v'lakach hakohen midam hachatat
the כהן kohen shall take from the blood of the חטאת. chatas.
It could have said מדמו midamo or מדמאי midamai I guess so
why does it say החטאת hachatat again? שתהא קבלה לשם חטאת she'te'hei
kabala l'shem chatat that the receiving of the blood the catching of
it in a vessel should be for the sake of חטאת. chatas.
לקח lakach is classically understood to refer to the קבלה, kabala, okay,
and the קבלה kabala plus also the הולכה. holacha. ואשכחן שחיטה וקבלה.
v'ashken shechitah v'kabala.
So now you see שחיטה shechitah and קבלה. kabala. זריקה מנלן, zerika
minalan, how do you know that even the throwing of the blood
on the מזבח? mizbeach? דאמר קרא וכפר עליו הכהן מחטאתו de'amar kra
v'chiper alav hakohen michatato and
the כהן kohen shall atone for him from his sin. So the
atoning is the blood on
the
מזבח. mizbeach. שתהא כפרה לשם חטאת she'te'hei kapara l'shem chatat the atoning
the blood also has to be for the sake of a חטאת.
chatas. Great, okay, so that's how you know all the עבודות avodos
at least לכתחילה l'chatchila have to be for the sake of a
חטאת. chatas. אשכחן שינוי קודש, ashken shinui kodesh, that teaches you when
you are to switch it and have in mind a different קרבן
korban what the גמרא gemara calls שינוי קודש. shinui kodesh. שינוי בעלים
מנלן, shinui ba'alim minalan,
how do you know that you also can't switch it and have
in mind לכתחילה l'chatchila you're supposed to have in mind at least
לכתחילה l'chatchila the right owner as well and that switching it would
be a problem? דאמר
קרא עליו de'amar kra alav וכפר עליו הכהן v'chiper alav hakohen for
him. עליו ולא לחבירו alav v'lo l'chavero it has to be for
him for the owner and not for another person. Okay, and that
אשכחן
למצוה. ashken l'mitzva. לעכב מנלן? l'akev minalan? So all of that tells
you that that's what you're supposed to do. How do you know
that if you don't do it, if you do שינוי קודש shinui
kodesh or שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, how do you know the קרבן
korban is invalid by a חטאת chatas as opposed you know and
makes it and in this way it's different from the other קרבנות?
korbanot? לעכב מנלן? l'akev minalan? כדאמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע חטאת
חטאתו kedamar Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua chatat chataso like we're going
to see in a minute that רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua makes a דרשה drasha from the extra ו
vav חטאתו chatato
חטאתו chataso to teach you something. הכא נמי חטאת חטאתו. hacha nami
chatat chataso. Here too it says וכפר עליו הכהן מחטאתו v'chiper alav
hakohen michatato his חטאת, chatas, okay, so
that extra ו vav is somehow underscoring that it has to דווקא
davka be that way, and that's לעכב. l'akev. So the גמרא gemara
understands that it's not just a ו vav generally tells us that
what's said in this פסוק pasuk is לעכב, l'akev, but that it's
the ownership aspect is לעכב. l'akev. The extra ו vav we already
know from the fact that it says עליו alav that it has
to be for the owner so the fact that it repeats... his
חטאת, chatat, it's like twice saying it has to be for the
owner, so that when you do the זריקה zrika not for the
sake of the owner, it's invalid. So that's at least where you
learn that the owner part has to be even
בדיעבד bedi'avad it is necessary. Or if you don't do it the
קרבן korban is פסול. pasul. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: אשכחן מצוה בשינוי קודש וזריקה בשינוי בעלים בין למצוה בין לעכב.
ashkachan mitzvah b'shinui kodesh v'zrika b'shinui ba'alim bein l'mitzvah bein l'akeiv. So
what you've done is you've shown from the פסוק pasuk like all
the פסוקים psukim we said ושחט אותה לחטאת, v'shachat ota l'chatat, ולקח
מדם החטאת. v'lakach midam hachatat. You understand that it has to be
that לכתחילה lechatchila you need it for the sake of the for
the sake of the right קרבן. korban. Okay. That there's a problem
with שינוי קודש. shinui kodesh. We also learned that the fact that
it says וכפר עליו מחטאתו v'chiper alav meichatato
tells you that שינוי בעלים shinui ba'alim is מעכב. m'akeiv.
Okay. It said it twice. שינוי קודש לכתחילה, shinui kodesh lechatchila,
שינוי בעלים shinui ba'alim is מעכב. m'akeiv. אשכחן ashkachan
let's do that again: למצוה. l'mitzvah. Oh I'm sorry I just did
that. Say אשכחן מצוה בשינוי קודש וזריקה בשינוי בעלים. ashkachan mitzvah b'shinui
kodesh v'zrika b'shinui ba'alim. You see that מצוה mitzvah all the עבודות
avodot you need when it comes to for the sake of the
חטאת. chatat. And that when it comes וכפר עליו מחטאתו v'chiper alav
meichatato
for שינוי בעלים shinui ba'alim when it comes to לכפר l'chaper זריקה
zrika that's even מעכב. m'akeiv. וזריקה בשינוי בעלים בין למצוה בין לעכב.
v'zrika b'shinui ba'alim bein l'mitzvah bein l'akeiv. Okay
but we haven't finished. לעכב בכל עבודות בשינוי קודש. l'akeiv b'chol_avodot b'shinui
kodesh. How would we know that when it comes to the idea
of switching it from a חטאת chatat to something else that that's
מעכב? m'akeiv? That if you don't do it the קרבן korban is
actually פסול? pasul? We only had one set of פסוקים psukim for
the idea לחטאת. l'chatat. That you know that all the עבודות avodot
have to be for the sake of a חטאת. chatat. How do
we know if it's not it's
פסול? pasul? ובשאר עבודות בשינוי בעלים. uv'sh'ar avodot b'shinui ba'alim. And when
it comes to שינוי בעלים shinui ba'alim we were only talking about
זריקה. zrika. וכפר עליו הכהן מחטאתו. v'chiper alav hakohein meichatato. So by
זריקה zrika it said it twice and we know that it's מעכב.
m'akeiv. But what we don't know is שינוי קודש shinui kodesh we
needed something else to tell us that if you don't do it
the right way it's מעכב m'akeiv it's invalid. And by שינוי בעלים
shinui ba'alim we need to know that it goes beyond וכפר. v'chaper.
It goes beyond just the idea of זריקה. zrika. So where do
you get that from? אמר רב יונה אתיא מחטאת נזיר. amar Rav
Yona atya m'chatat nazir. You learn it out from the חטאת chatat
of a נזיר. nazir. Okay and we're going to assume that you
can apply one חטאת chatat to the other. We'll get to that
in a minute. דכתיב dichtiv it says by the חטאת chatat of
the נזיר: nazir: והקריב הכהן לפני ה' ועשה את חטאתו ואת עולתו.
v'hikriv hakohein lifnei Hashem v'asa et chatato v'et olato. שיעשה כל עשיותיו
לשם חטאת. sheya'aseh kol asiyotav l'shem chatat. So it's very nice when
you have the word
ועשה. v'asa. ועשה v'asa is generic. So all of the עבודות. avodot.
So you don't have to go looking for separate פסוקים psukim for
each one. So it says ועשה את חטאתו. v'asa et chatato. Now
it's not exactly clear what else it could have said. Maybe ועשה
קרבנו? v'asa korbano? Anyway from ועשה חטאתו v'asa chatato we learn all
of the עבודות avodot have to be for the sake of a
חטאת. chatat. Okay. לשם חטאת. l'shem chatat. אשכחן שינוי קודש. ashkachan shinui
kodesh. Now that tells you about שינוי קודש shinui kodesh that it
has to be that way. שינוי בעלים מנלן? shinui ba'alim minalan? How
do you know that there's an idea of שינוי בעלים shinui ba'alim
as also that it applies to all the עבודות? avodot? So now
there's a question here of
גרסאות. girsa'ot. The גרסא girsa that's in the parentheses is: אם אינו
ענין לשינוי קודש תנהו ענין לשינוי בעלים אשכחן למצוה לעכב מנלן. im
eino inyan l'shinui kodesh tneihu inyan l'shinui ba'alim ashkachan l'mitzvah l'akeiv minalan.
Okay so and we'll go with that גרסא girsa that's תוספות's Tosafot
גרסא girsa which is in some ways easier than רש"י's Rashi גרסא
girsa who takes it out. So that says
ועשה v'asa by the קרבן korban of the נזיר nazir ועשה את
חטאתו. v'asa et chatato. All the עשיות asiyot have to be for
a חטאת. chatat. Now you don't need it to tell us that
you need it לכתחילה lechatchila for everything for a חטאת. chatat. We
know that already. Those were the פסוקים psukim we just cited. So
what we're going to use it to teach us is that all
the עבודות avodot have to be לשם בעלים. l'shem ba'alim. So now
we've covered the לכתחילה lechatchila
that all the עבודות avodot have to be for a חטאת chatat
and we've covered that לשם בעלים l'shem ba'alim also that לכתחילה lechatchila
all the עבודות avodot have to be לשם בעלים l'shem ba'alim because
ועשה את חטאתו v'asa et chatato by the נזיר nazir is extra.
But we only know לעכב l'akeiv still just by the זריקה לשם
בעלים. zrika l'shem ba'alim. We still don't have the answer of how
do we know that it's מעכב. m'akeiv. So למצוה לעכב מנלן? l'mitzvah
l'akeiv minalan? אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע חטאת חטאתו. amar Rav
Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua chatat chatato. The fact that it says חטאתו
chatato that extra ו vav is somehow
saying that reiterating it and saying that everything is מעכב. m'akeiv. Okay.
So basically individual פסוקים psukim by the four עבודות avodot by the
חטאת chatat or three of the עבודות: avodot: ולקח מדם החטאת, v'lakach
midam hachatat, ושחטה החטאת. v'shachata hachatat. That tells us לכתחילה lechatchila for
שינוי קודש. shinui kodesh. וכפר עליו הכהן מחטאתו. v'chiper alav hakohein meichatato.
That tells us שינוי בעלים shinui ba'alim and even מעכב. m'akeiv. And
then this general פסוק pasuk ועשה v'asa by חטאת נזיר chatat nazir
is telling us all the עבודות avodot have to be for the
sake of the בעלים, ba'alim, the מצוה. mitzvah. And now we've got
everything covered. covered למצוה, lemitzvah, and now the extra ו vav מחטאתו
mechata'to tells us it's all מעכב. me'akev. That's where the גמרא's Gemara
holding right now. Okay, מתקיף לה רבינא, matkif lah Ravina, רבינא Ravina
challenges this. אלא מעתה, ella me'atta, עולת עולתו olas olaso מאי דרשת
ביה? mai darshet beh? So what do you do with the extra
ו vav by עולתו olaso that you also have there by the,
you know, because the נזיר nazir brings not only a חטאת chatas
but an עולה olah and it says עולתו. olaso. So what are
you going to do with that ו vav because it's not מעכב
me'akev by an עולה? olah? It's only מעכב me'akev by a חטאת.
chatas. אמר
ליה רבינא—so amar leh Ravina now the גמרא Gemara says before answering
רבינא's Ravina question—מנחה מנחתו נסך נסכו minchah minchaso nesech nisko מאי דרשת
בהו? mai darshet behu? Why did he only ask and challenge about
עולתו? olaso? There's וs vav all over the place there by the
נזיר. nazir. It also says מנחתו, minchaso, his מנחה, minchah, and נסכו,
nisko, the wine libation. So why didn't he—why wasn't he bothered with
challenge, you know, from those extra וs vav as well? So the
גמרא Gemara says: No, that—there he knew what the answer was. ההוא
מיבעי ליה hahu mibai leh מנחתם ונסכיהם minchasam veniskeihem בלילה balaylah מנחתם
ונסכיהם minchasam veniskeihem אפילו למחר. afilu lemachar. That there's a דרשה drasha
we make by—by סוכות. Sukkos. By—it says,
you know, מנחתם ונסכיהם, minchasam veniskeihem, that, you know, with all the—with
the קרבנות korbanos you can—you know, you bring a—with the עולה olah
you bring a מנחה minchah and a נסך, nesach, you bring a—like
a—flour and oil and you also bring wine libation. And what happens
if you bring those—you know, you bring the קרבן korban on day
one and then you didn't get around to bringing the מנחה minchah
and the נסך? nesach? Can you bring it the following night? Can
you bring it the following day? So somehow the fact it says
מנחתם ונסכיהם, minchasam veniskeihem, it says the possessive, now you might think
the possessive is telling you דווקא davka it has to be together
with the קרבן korban on the same day. But somehow no, from
the possessive we learn out that whenever you bring it, it will
be considered the מנחה minchah and the נסך nesach of this קרבן.
korban. And you can even bring it at night. It's like finishing
up the קרבן korban at night because normally a קרבן korban לכתחילה
lechatchilah can't be brought in the day. But because it's seen as
sub—you know, as a subsidiary, as an extension of the קרבן korban
and the עיקר ikkar קרבן korban was brought during the day, and
these are connected to it, it could be brought even at night,
even the following day. So therefore we would learn that out from
the נזיר nazir from the קרבנות korbanos of the נזיר nazir as
well, מנחתו ונסכו, minchaso venisko, that it could be brought on a
night and on a following day. So that ו vav he understood.
But his challenge was: if you're going to use the ו vav
of מחטאתו mechata'to by the נזיר nazir to say it's מעכב, me'akev,
what are you going to do with the ו vav of עולתו
olaso by the נזיר? nazir? Because there it's not מעכב. me'akev. So
the גמרא Gemara says: that's question number one. אלא עולת עולתו ella
olas olaso מאי דרשת ביה? mai darshet beh? What are you going
to do with the extra ו vav of
עולתו? olaso? וסו—and vesu in
addition—מגמרי מהדדי? migmari mehadedi? חטאת חלב chatas chelev מחטאת נזיר? chatas nazir?
לא גמרי. lo gamri. Okay, מגמרי מהדדי—excuse migmari mehadedi me—how can you
learn them from one another? You're assuming: oh look, we have an
extra פסוק pasuk by the חטאת chatas of a נזיר nazir and
that'll tell us—we're assuming all חטאות chatasos are the same, so that'll
help—we'll apply that to שינוי בעלים shinui be'alim and we'll apply the
ו vav to say it's מעכב me'akev and we're just going to
apply one to the next, okay? But the גמרא Gemara says: how
can you put them in the same
category? חטאת חלב chatas chelev מחטאת נזיר chatas nazir לא גמרי. lo
gamri. You can't learn a
חטאת חלב, chatas chelev, the standard חטאת chatas of a sin,
from the חטאת chatas of a נזיר, nazir, you know, and
say—hold on—חטאת חלב chatas chelev מחטאת נזיר chatas nazir לא גמרי. lo
gamri. You can't apply what we have this extra פסוק pasuk by
חטאת נזיר chatas nazir to a normal חטאת chatas of a sin
and say that, you know, apply it that you say that we
need שינוי בעלים shinui be'alim is an issue with all the עבודות.
avodos. שכן יש עמה דמים אחרים. sheken yesh immah damim acherim. Because
a חטאת נזיר chatas nazir comes also with an עולה. olah. And
therefore you can't go ahead and apply this קרבן, korban, you know,
maybe there's extra requirements here. It's also coming with other קרבנות. korbanos.
So you can't just apply this idea of—you know, that—that emphasizes it
has to be לשם חטאת. leshem chatas. You can't just go ahead
and apply it to a normal חטאת chatas of a sin
offering. חטאת נזיר chatas nazir מחטאת חלב chatas chelev לא גמרי. lo
gamri. And you also can't do the reverse and say the פסוקים
pesukim that tell us by a normal sin
offering, for a חטאת חלב, chatas chelev, for a sin, that you
need, you know, שינוי קודש shinui kodesh is an issue, let's apply
that to the case of the נזיר. nazir. No, you can't assume
that either. לא גמרי lo gamri שכן כרת. sheken kares. You know,
חטאת חלב chatas chelev is a חטאת chatas you bring for something
that you get כרת kares for. And therefore it has extra requirements.
So each thing you can't apply one to the other. Each one
has its own aspect that's weighty that the other doesn't have. And
therefore you need to learn each חטאת chatas separately. You can't just
join them together and now have a lot of פסוקים pesukim that's
going to help you cover all your bases.
אלא אמר רבא: ella amar Rava: so fine. So רבא Rava says:
אתיא מחטאת מצורע. atya mechatas metzora. Don't learn it from the חטאת
chatas of a נזיר, nazir, learn it from the חטאת chatas of
a מצורע. metzora. And obviously you're going to anticipate the same question:
חטאת מצורע chatas metzora is distinct from a normal חטאת chatas of
a sin. But let's first see what he says. דכתיב, dechassiv, it
says by the מצורע: metzora: ועשה הכהן את החטאת. ve'asah hakohen es
hachatas. ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, it's another ועשה ve'asah which allows us
to cover all the עבודות. avodos. The כהן Kohen will do the
חטאת, Chatas, שיהיו כל עשיותיו לשם חטאת. Sheyehu kol asiyosav leshem chatas.
All of it has to be for the sake of the חטאת.
Chatas. Okay, so that’s what it says, so we have another פסוק
posuk here that everything has to be for the sake of a
חטאת, chatas, and assuming we can apply all the חטאות chataos to
one another, so now ואשכחן שינוי קודש שינוי בעלים מנלן? ve’ashkechan shinui
kodesh shinui be’alim menalan? So that’s in terms of, you know, that
you have to do it for the sake of that it has
to be for the sake of the חטאת. chatas. How do you
know that there’s even an issue that it has to be for
the right owner? So אמר קרא וכיפר על המיטהר, amar kra vechiper
al hamitaher, that he should atone for the מיטהר, mitaher, the one
becoming purified. על המיטהר זה ולא על מיטהר חבירו, Al hamitaher zeh
velo al hamitaher chaveiro, on this one, not on somebody else. Okay,
and therefore you have by the מצורע metzora that it has to
be שינוי קודש shinui kodesh and you have שינוי בעלים, shinui be’alim,
and somehow if you combine that we would just have said that
that was למצוה, lemitzvah, but somehow if you combine it now with
what we already know by a normal חטאת, chatas, the doubling is
going to tell you that it’s going to be מעכב. me’akev. Okay,
so that’s how you do, because you have a whole set of
פסוקים psukim by a normal חטאת chatas and a set of פסוקים
psukim by a מצורע, metzora, so if you’re able to combine them
you learn that you’re obligated to do it and it’s מעכב. me’akev.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: One minute, the גמרא Gemara
says ואכתי מהדדי יליף? ve’achti mehadadi yalif? How can you learn one,
how can you apply them to one another? חטאת חלב מחטאת מצורע
לא ילפי, Chatas chelev mechatas metzora lo yalfei, you can’t learn a
חטאת chatas of sin offering from that of a מצורע, metzora, that
what’s true by a מצורע, metzora, the demands of a מצורע metzora
should apply to a normal sin offering. שכן יש עמם דמים אחרים.
Sheken yesh imom damim acherim. Again, a מצורע metzora you bring an
עולה olah and an אשם, asham, there’s a lot of קרבנות korbanos
you bring, so maybe there are heavier demands. So a demand of
לשמה, lishmah, לשמה lishmah would not necessarily apply from a חטאת chatas
from a חטאת chatas of a מצורע metzora to a חטאת chatas
of a normal חטאת חלב. chatas chelev. חטאת מצורע מחטאת חלב לא
גמר, Chatas metzora mechatas chelev lo gamar, and also the reverse, the
demands of a חטאת chatas for sin offering you can’t apply to
the case of a מצורע. metzora. Why not? שכן כרת, Sheken kares,
because a normal חטאת chatas of sin is כרת, kares, so maybe
there the demands are heavier. So each one you need the פסוקים
psukim to tell you the thing itself. You can’t combine the פסוקים
psukim because you can’t learn one from the other.
So the גמרא Gemara says, okay fine, חדא מחדא לא אתיא. chada
mechada lo asya. You can’t learn one from the other because each
one has its own strengths and therefore might have distinct requirements. But
לא אתיא. lo asya. תיתי חדא מתרתי. Teisi chada mitartei. But why
not learn one from two? Okay, basically it’s going to say we
now have three פסוקים, psukim, all of them demand לשמה, lishmah, לשמה.
lishmah. Okay,
a normal חטאת, chatas, חטאת חלב, chatas chelev, a חטאת נזיר, chatas
nazir, and a חטאת מצורע. chatas metzora. So if, as long as
we could have, two would have sufficed and we could have applied
it to the third, then the פסוקים psukim by the third are
redundant and therefore that can come and teach you that not only
is it required לכתחילה, lechatchila, but it’s מעכב. me’akev. All right,
so that’s what we’re going to say, that in two you could
have had the basis for applying to the third and you do
apply to the third, so the extra פסוקים psukim are now going
to tell you that it’s מעכב me’akev by all of them. Okay,
so let’s take a look. How can we do this? תיתי חדא
מתרתי. Teisi chada mitartei. בהאי לא ליכתוב. Behai lo lichtov. Which one
do you want it not to write the idea that you require
לשמה lishmah and that we could learn out from the other two?
לא ליכתוב רחמנא בחטאת חלב ותיתי מהנך, Lo lichtov rachmana bechatas chelev
veteisi mehanach, don’t say by the sin
offering and learn out from מצורע metzora and נזיר. nazir. Well, that’s
obviously they’re different. Those are there as part of the purification process,
not relating to sin. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מה להנך
שכן יש עמם דמים אחרים. mah lehanach sheken yesh imom damim acherim.
The
גמרא Gemara is going to say in terms of like the weightiness,
both of those are קרבנות korbanos that come in a cluster with
other קרבנות, korbanos, so the demands thereof לשמה, lishmah, לשמה lishmah cannot
be assumed to apply to a normal חטאת chatas that comes as
a standalone. Maybe it has lower demands. Okay, שכן יש עמם דמים
אחרים. sheken yesh imom damim acherim. לא ליכתוב רחמנא בחטאת נזיר ותיתי
מהנך. Lo lichtov rachmana bechatas nazir veteisi mehanach. Okay fine, but let’s
say just by
חטאת חלב chatas chelev and by מצורע metzora and then apply those
two and say then we can infer the לשמה lishmah requirements by
נזיר. nazir. Okay, let’s see if that’s going to work. לא ליכתוב
רחמנא בחטאת נזיר ותיתי מהנך. Lo lichtov rachmana bechatas nazir veteisi mehanach.
No, מה להנך שכן אין להם שאילה. mah lehanach sheken ein lahem
she’eilah. No, because you know נזיר nazir is something that the נזיר
nazir can go ahead and can ask a חכם, chochom, you know,
it ultimately comes through a נדר neder and get the whole נזירות
nezirus uprooted. So therefore, if you require לשמה lishmah by a sin
offering for sin and for מצורע, metzora, maybe those it’s more required
because those are things that you can’t back out of, you’re stuck
with. But נזיר nazir where in theory you could undo it, maybe
you wouldn’t require לשמה, lishmah, so you could not have applied from
those two to נזיר. nazir. So לא ליכתוב רחמנא בחטאת מצורע ותיתי
מהנך. lo lichtov rachmana bechatas metzora veteisi mehanach. Fine, let’s try this
way. Don’t say it by מצורע metzora and- say it by חלב
Chelev and by נזיר Nazir then apply it to מצורע. Metzora. No,
מה להנך שכן אין בהם בדלות? Mah la-hanach she-ken ein bam bedalut?
No, because a מצורע, Metzora, if you're poor, you're able to bring
a lesser קרבן Korban with a bird, okay, whereas a נזיר Nazir
and a חטאת חלב Chatas Chelev is only the קרבנות, Korbanos, you
know, that the Torah explicitly mandates. So therefore, maybe those where you
don't have an option to bring less if you're poor are weightier
and require לשמה, Lishma, but מצורע Metzora which has an option to
bring less if you're poor maybe doesn't require לשמה. Lishma. So therefore,
you could not have learned the third a third out from the
other two, you know, you could not have, yes, you could not
have learned the third from the other two no matter how you
configure it, and therefore each one you needed the פסוקים Psukim to
say it by the thing itself. So we have no extra פסוקים,
Psukim, you know, in each one of those it says you need
לשמה, Lishma, but all of that is לכתחילה. Lichatchila.
How do we know that it's מעכב? Me-akeiv? אלא
אמר קרא, Ela amar Kra, okay
fine, the פסוק Pasuk says, going back to what we quoted earlier,
זאת התורה לעולה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמלואים ולזבח השלמים, Zos hatorah la'olah
u-lamincha ve-la-chatas ve-la-asham ve-la-miluim u-lezeivach hashelamim, הקישו הכתוב לשלמים. Hikishu hakasuv leshelamim.
חטאת Chatas is compared to a שלמים. Shelamim. מה שלמים בין שינוי
קודש בין שינוי בעלים בעינן לשמן למצוה אף חטאת בין שינוי קודש
בין שינוי בעלים בעינן לשמן למצוה. Mah shelamim bein shinuy kodesh bein
shinuy ba'alim ba'inan lishmon lemitzva af chatas bein shinuy kodesh bein shinuy
ba'alim ba'inan lishmon lemitzva.
So we already learned in the previous דפים Dappim for שלמים Shelamim
that you need to do it לכתחילה Lichatchila for the right sake
and you need to do it for the right owners, and therefore
that לכתחילה Lichatchila problem of שינוי קודש Shinuy kodesh and שינוי בעלים.
Shinuy ba'alim. So therefore that applies to all קרבנות. Korbanos. We just
know it from the connection to שלמים. Shelamim. That's our starting point.
All קרבנות Korbanos need to be לשמה Lishma and for the sake
of the בעלים Ba'alim at least לכתחילה. Lichatchila.
Once that's true and now we have an extra set of לשמה
Lishma by חטאת חלב Chatas Chelev and an extra set of לשמה
Lishma by נזיר Nazir and by מצורע, Metzora, what it is telling
us is that in each of those categories which each one is
distinct and you can't learn them from one another, not only is
it required לכתחילה, Lichatchila, it's also required בדיעבד. Bedieved. Okay, so אף
חטאת בין שינוי בין שינוי בעלים בעינן לשמן למצוה, Af chatas bein
shinuy bein shinuy ba'alim ba'inan lishmon lemitzva, הלכך מצוה משלמים, Hilkach mitzva
mi-shelamim, the מצוה Mitzva idea you learn from שלמים, Shelamim, that's the
point of departure for all קרבנות, Korbanos, והנך קראי לעכב, Ve-hanach kra'ei
le-akeiv, and the fact that it says לחטאת, Le-chatas, you know, ועשית
את החטאת, Ve-asata es ha-chatas, all those extra פסוקים Psukim that we've
been saying, that is telling you the doubling is telling you that
it's מעכב. Me-akeiv. If you don't do it, it's invalid. All right,
חטאת Chatas now. חטאת חלב דכתיב בה לחטאת. Chatas Chelev de-chativ ba
le-chatas. So that's and you needed in all three because as we
said you can't learn one from the other. Okay, חטאת חלב דכתיב
בה לחטאת. Chatas Chelev de-chativ ba le-chatas. I skipped a line. Okay,
לעכב. Le-akeiv. ואשכחן חטאת חלב. V'ashkachan Chatas Chelev.
Now,
when it comes to sin, not נזיר Nazir and מצורע Metzora which
we said are separate categories and we already have פסוקים Psukim for
it, but when it comes to the sin category, let's see if
we now can cover all of the cases. So we have the
normal חטאת Chatas that's brought for חלב Chelev meaning for any sin
that you get כרת, Kares, דכתיב בה לחטאת, De-chativ ba le-chatas, it
says ושחט אותה לחטאת. ve-shachat osa le-chatas.
We already had the פסוקים Psukim that we learned out to tell
you that it's מעכב. Me-akeiv. Top of ח עמוד ב. Chet amud
bet. חטאת עבודת כוכבים ודשמיעת קול הקול וביטוי שפתים וטומאת מקדש וקדשיו
דלא כתיב בהו מנלן. Chatas Avodat Kochavim u-de-shmias kol hakol u-vituy sfasayim
ve-tum'as mikdash ve-kodshav de-lo ketiv behu minalan.
So the special חטאת Chatas for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah that is
in פרשת שלח לך Parshas Shlach Lecha and it doesn't say לחטאת.
Le-chatas. So, you know, how are we going to learn from, how
are we going to say that they're מעכב? Me-akeiv? And also the
חטאת Chatas at the end of פרשת ויקרא Parshas Vayikra where somebody
is sworn to come and give testimony
and then they lie and they say they don't have testimony, or
they just, you know, violate their שבועה, Shvua, or they are טמא
Tamei and they enter into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or eat
קרבנות, Korbanos, you know. There the פסוקים Psukim at the end of
ויקרא Vayikra assign a special חטאת Chatas and it's, you know, very
based on how wealthy you are, it's עולה ויורד Oleh ve-yored as
we've, you know, as we alluded to before in another case. So
there, how do you know those two
חטאת, Chatas, חטאת עולה ויורד Chatas Oleh ve-yored and a חטאת עבודה
זרה, Chatas Avodah Zarah, how do you know those the לשמה Lishma
is
מעכב? Me-akeiv? דלא כתיב בהו מנלן, De-lo ketiv behu minalan, how do
you know there that the לשמה Lishma is מעכב? Me-akeiv?
So Gemara says, here's how we're going to do it. חטאת עבודת
כוכבים אתי מחטאת חלב שכן כרת. Chatas Avodat Kochavim atei mi-chatat chelev
she-ken kares. The one of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, that's easy. Okay,
that's pretty much the same as a normal חטאת Chatas for sin
offering, it's something you would get כרת Kares for. The only difference
is that when it's עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah it's a different type
of a קרבן. Korban. But fundamentally that's in the same category. So
if it's מעכב Me-akeiv by חטאת חלב, Chatas Chelev, it's מעכב Me-akeiv
by a חטאת עבודה זרה. Chatas Avodah Zarah. שכן כרת She-ken kares
and the others, you know, which aren't כרת, Kares, then
So
the other things that you know, the עולה ויורד oleh v'yored that
has things in it that is not כרת, kares, מנא לן, minalan,
how do I know that that's מעכב? meakev? Maybe it's lighter because
it's not כרת, kares, and maybe it's not מעכב? meakev? So the
גמרא gemara says, כלהו אתיין במה הצד. kulu asyan b'ma hatzad. Now
we can do a צד השוה, tzad hashaveh, now that we know,
you know, we couldn't get one from two, but now we have
three or four that we know is מעכב, meakev, so we can
apply it to the fifth by doing a צד השוה tzad hashaveh
and saying that if in all these cases of חטאות chatasos לשמה
lishmah is מעכב, meakev, it's also going to be מעכב meakev by
a קרבן עולה ויורד. korban oleh v'yored. All right, excellent. That's how
we know that it's מעכב meakev by a חטאת. chatas. There's also
of course the logic that it's מעכב meakev by a חטאת, chatas,
which is that a חטאת, chatas, you know, is connected to the
owner and to their sin, and therefore the phenomenon of לא עלה
לבעלים לשם חובה lo olah l'baalim l'shem chovah doesn't really work by
a חטאת. chatas. What sense does it mean to bring a חטאת
chatas if it's not connected to the owner anymore? And that's why
we have a whole category of חטאות מתו chatasos meisos that when
the owner gets atonement through another קרבן korban or other types of
cases that you have to let the חטאת chatas die. So that
also explains why the way when it not עולה לבעלים, oleh l'baalim,
you know, which would be the case of a normal שלא לשמה,
shelo lishmah, why was a חטאת chatas that also comes with it
being completely פסול. pasul. Okay. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Now we're going
to move on to the פסח pesach because the פסח pesach is
the other thing that when you do it not for the sake
of פסח, pesach, it's going to be פסול. pasul. תנו
רבנן, tanu rabbanan, פסח בזמנו לשמו כשר שלא לשמו פסול. pesach bizmano
lishmo kasher shelo lishmo pasul. That's what we teach in the משנה.
mishnah. When it's שחט shachted for the sake of a פסח pesach
and it's the time of bringing it, it's the 14th of ניסן
nissan from חצות chatzos on, when it's לשמו lishmo it's כשר kasher
and when it's שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it's פסול. pasul.
That's what we said, the שלא לשמו shelo lishmo by פסח pesach
is also invalid, completely. ובשאר ימות השנה, uv'shaar yemos hashanah, but now
we're going to add something. When it's not פסח, pesach, when it's
not I should say the 14th from חצות chatzos on. Any other
time, even the 14th in the day before חצות, chatzos, when it
is not the time of bringing the קרבן פסח korban pesach
or it's after פסח, pesach,
ובשאר ימות השנה לשמו פסול שלא לשמו כשר. uv'shaar yemos hashanah lishmo
pasul shelo lishmo kasher. It's the reverse. If you שחט shachted it
as a פסח, pesach, it's פסול, pasul, and if you שחט shachted
it for something else, it's כשר. kasher. Now the reason if you
שחט shachted it for a פסח pesach it's פסול pasul is רש״י
rashi says, you know, the תורה torah repeats time and again, ושחטו
אותו כל קהל עדת ישראל בין הערבים, v'shachatu oso kol kehal adas
yisrael bein haarbayim, that it must be שחט shachted multiple times it
says on the 14th after חצות. chatzos. So if you're taking something
that was sanctified as a קרבן פסח korban pesach and שחט shachting
it as a קרבן פסח, korban pesach, so it's totally a קרבן
פסח korban pesach and you're doing it at the wrong time, then
it's פסול. pasul. The תורה torah repeated that multiple times. That we
get. What we don't know is how do you know when it
is the right time שלא לשמו shelo lishmo it's פסול pasul like
a חטאת? chatas? And also what we're going to start by focusing
on is how do you know this other thing, that when it's
not the right time and you שחט shachted it for something else,
that it's going to be כשר? kasher? Then it becomes a שלמים.
shelamim. Okay, so but if you שחט shachted it as a פסח,
pesach, then as I said, it's פסח שלא בזמנו pesach shelo bizmano
and it's פסול. pasul. But if you שחט shachted it as something
else, you make it not a פסח, pesach, it's called you're being
עוקר השם, oker hashem, and if you're making it not a פסח
pesach when it's not the 14th after חצות, chatzos, then it is
going to be כשר kasher as a שלמים. shelamim. שלא לשמו כשר
לשמו shelo lishmo kasher lishmo as a פסח, pesach, it's פסח שלא
בזמנו pesach shelo bizmano and it's פסול. pasul. שלא לשמו, shelo lishmo,
it's something other than a פסח, pesach, it becomes a שלמים shelamim
and it's כשר. kosher. Where do we learn that from? Okay, so
the גמרא gemara says like this, מנא הני מילי? minalan hanei mili?
Where do we learn this idea, the second part, that פסח שלא
בזמנו שלא לשמו pesach shelo bizmano shelo lishmo is כשר? kosher? So
אמר אבוה דשמואל אמר קרא, amar avuh d'shmuel amar kra, the פסוק
pasuk says ואם מן הצאן קרבנו לזבח שלמים לה׳. v'im min hatzon
korbano l'zevach shelamim l'hashem. This is right at the beginning of ויקרא
vayikra that you could bring a שלמים shelamim from all types of
animals, male or female, and it says if from the sheep is
your קרבן korban as a זבח שלמים. zevach shelamim. So from there
we're going to say the following דרשה. drasha. דבר הבא מן הצאן,
davar haba min hatzon, a type of a קרבן korban that only
comes from sheep. What is that? A פסח, pesach, you know, צאן
tzon includes sheep and goats. A type of קרבן korban that only
comes from צאן, tzon, a פסח, pesach, יהא לזבח שלמים. yehei l'zevach
shelamim. So אם מן הצאן קרבנו לזבח שלמים, im min hatzon korbano
l'zevach shelamim, if it's a type of a קרבן korban that's a
sheep, if it's a פסח, pesach, then it should be a שלמים.
shelamim. Now obviously a פסח pesach isn't a שלמים shelamim on the
14th after חצות. chatzos. So it's going to mean a פסח pesach
any other time of the year will be a שלמים. shelamim.
Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says fine, I get that דרשה,
drasha, but אימא שלמים מידי דאחריני לא, eima shelamim midi dachrini lo,
maybe that's only if you שחט shachted it for the sake of
a שלמים, shelamim, it's a שלמים. shelamim. Maybe if you שחט shachted
it for an עולה olah or a חטאת, chatas, it should be
פסול, pasul, right? Because you say any שלא לשמו... shelo lishmo... how
when it's שלא בזמנו *shelo bizmano* makes it כשר *kosher* as a
שלמים Shelamim, *shlomim*. That's a little bizarre idea; you could think that
any שלא לשמה *shelo lishma* maybe transforms it to that type of
a thing, or maybe if in its very nature it's fundamentally like
a שלמים Shelamim *shlomim*, it can all be eaten by the owners,
it could be eaten in all of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so you understand
why it's sort of being drawn to its שלמים Shelamim *shlomim* identity,
but maybe you need דווקא *davka* כוונה kavana *kavana* for a שלמים
*shlomim*. How should כוונה *kavana* for an עולה *olah*, that's a pretty,
I mean, you know, you can understand the mechanism. כוונה *kavana* for
an עולה *olah* uproots the name of the status of פסח Pesach
*Pesach* and then because of its fundamental קדושה kedusha, *kedusha* of something
that can be eaten by the owners in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, it becomes
a שלמים *shlomim*. But that's not obvious. Maybe only if you had
כוונה *kavana* for a שלמים *shlomim* it becomes a שלמים *shlomim* and
for everything else it should be פסול *pasul*. אימא שלמים אין מידי
אחריני לא *Eima shlomim in, midei achrinei lo*, maybe only if you
had כוונה *kavana* for שלמים *shlomim* will it work? So אמר רב
אילא אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rav Ila amar Rabbi Yochanan*, לזבח לרבות
כל זבח *lezavach lerabot kol zavach*. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is saying no, no, this is how we're going to read it.
ואם מן הצאן קרבנו *ve'im min hatzon korbano*, if it's a קרבן
*korban* that comes only from the sheep, it's a קרבן פסח korban
Pesach *korban Pesach* שלא בזמנו *shelo bizmano*, לזבח *lezavach*, if you שחטת
*shachtet* for the sake of any זבח *zavach* that's not פסח Pesach
*Pesach*, okay, then שלמים *shlomim*, it's going to be a שלמים *shlomim*.
So that's a pretty cool read. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, so
אימא *eima*, but why don't we say כל דשחיט ליה הוי כוותיה
*kol deshachit leh havei kevateih*? Why don't we say it's לזבח *lezavach*
and שלמים *shlomim*? If it's a פסח *Pesach*, you can turn it
into any זבח *zavach* or a שלמים *shlomim*. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says no, no, no,
the grammar doesn't
work. אי הוי כתיב לשלמים וזבח כדקאמרת *Ei havei ketiv leshlomim vezavach
kideka'amart*, if it would have said ואם מן הצאן קרבנו לשלמים וזבח
*ve'im min hatzon korbano leshlomim vezavach*, then you're right; it would have
said you could make it any קרבן *korban* you want. But that's
not what it said. השתא דכתיב לזבח שלמים *Hashta dechtiv lezavach shlomim*,
but the grammar now is if you do it לזבח *lezavach* for
any זבח *zavach*, it becomes a שלמים *shlomim*. לזבח שלמים לכל דשחט
ליה שלמים ליהוי *Lezavach shlomim lechol deshachat leh shlomim lehevei*, anything you
שחטת *shachtet* it for, שלמים *shlomim* it will be. So that's a
nice elegant דרשה *drasha*. But the גמרא *Gemara* is still not satisfied.
אימא *Eima*, says the גמרא *Gemara*, why don't I say וזבח כלל
*vezavach klal*, if for a זבח *zavach* is a general, you know,
like you're saying any זבח *zavach*, שלמים פרט *shlomim prat*, שלמים *shlomim*
is a specific, is a specific. כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה
שבפרט *Klal uprat ein baklal ela mah shebaprat*. So a כלל *klal*
and a פרט *prat* is only something that it, you know, when
you have a general and specific, then the rule is that the
specific defines the entire scope. שלמים אין מידי אחריני לא *Shlomim in,
midei achrinei lo*, so at the end of the day you can't
דארשן *darshan* לזבח *lezavach*, you should see לזבח *lezavach* as a broadening
and שלמים *shlomim* as a narrowing and saying only with כוונה *kavana*
of a שלמים *shlomim* can you make it into a שלמים *shlomim*.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says לה' הדר וכלל *Lashem hadar veklal*. It
says לזבח שלמים לה' *lezavach shlomim lashem*,
so that's broadening it again and therefore it's saying that any כוונה
*kavana* works. Somehow שלמים *shlomim* is still telling you it will revert
to a שלמים *shlomim*, but the לזבח *lezavach* and the לה' *lashem*
is telling you that any כוונה *kavana* works. So the גמרא *Gemara*
is not happy. גמרא *Gemara* says like this, מתקיף לה רב יעקב
מנהר פקוד *Matkif lah Rav Yaakov miNehar Pekod*, Rav Yaakov from Nehar
Pekod challenged this, הא לא דמי כללא בתרא לכללא קמא *Ha lo
dami klala batra leklala kama*. No, the general statement of לה' *lashem*
is not similar in scope to the earlier one of לזבח *lezavach*.
Okay, why not?
כללא קמא *Klala kama*, the first כלל *klal*, מרבי זבחים *marbi zvachim*.
לזבח *Lezavach* is things that are זבחים *zvachim*, which refers specifically to
like animals, like mammals that are slaughtered, cows and sheep and goats.
Okay, ותו לא *Veto lo*, and nothing else. כללא בתרא לה' *Klala
batra lashem*, when it says לה' *lashem*, כל דלה' *kol delashem*, that's
anything that would be going to God, ואפילו לעופות ואפילו למנחות *ve'afilu
le'ofot ve'afilu lemenachot*,
even something that is being brought as a מנחה *mincha*, meaning לה'
*lashem* is any type of a קרבן *korban*. So maybe it means
that you know if you have כוונה *kavana*, maybe even if you
have כוונה *kavana* to שחט *shacht* a פסח *Pesach* and you have
כוונה *kavana* to treat it as an עולת העוף *olat ha'of* or
as a מנחה *mincha*, which is a bizarre type of a כוונה
*kavana*, but you know that that it should be כשר *kosher* as
a שלמים *shlomim*, right? So what's, what's the story? Like though you
cannot make a כלל ופרט וכלל *klal uprat u'klal* if the כללים
*klalim* are of different scope.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says הא תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל הוא *Ha
Tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael hu*. No, our תנא *Tanna* is according to
the house of Rabbi Yishmael. בכלל ופרט דריש כי האי גוונא *Be'klal
uprat darish ki hai gavna*. So, so the גמרא *Gemara* says yeah,
Rabbi Yishmael as we know has a looser approach than Rabbi Akiva,
so even if he can do a כלל ופרט *klal uprat* even
if they are a little bit, you know, not precise. The כללים
*klalim* are not exactly the same and we'll do, so even though
they are broader, we're still going to allow us to abstract any
כוונה *kavana* similar to a שלמים *shlomim*. So the גמרא *Gemara* goes
from this. So the גמרא *Gemara* says כלל ופרט וכלל *Klall u'Prat
u'Klall*, אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט *ee ata dan elo k'ein
haprat*. גמרא *Gemara* says
okay,
let me give you that it's a כלל ופרט וכלל *Klall u'Prat
u'Klall*. לזבח *L'zevach* is a כלל *Klall*, שלמים *Shelamim* פרט *Prat*, לה׳
*L'Hashem* כלל *Klall*.
But still, it has to be similar to the פרט *Prat*. So
מה פרט מפורש דבר הבא בנדר ונדבה אף כל דבר הבא בנדר
ונדבה *ma prat meforash davar habah b'neder u'nidavah af kol davar habah
b'neder u'nidavah*. עולה ושלמים *Olah u'Shelamim* אין *in*, חטאת Chatas ואשם *Chatas
v'Asham* לא *lo*. Okay, but it would have to be כוונה *kavana*
like a שלמים *Shelamim*. Like a שלמים *Shelamim* is some type of
a thing that you can bring as a, you know, as a
נדר *neder*. So that would be like an עולה *Olah*, but, you
know, and שלמים *Shelamim* obviously, that's what we're starting. But if you
had כוונה *kavana* for a חטאת *Chatas* and an אשם Asham, *Asham*,
which is not similar to a שלמים *Shelamim*, maybe that כוונה *kavana*
would not work. So if you're going to say כלל ופרט וכלל
*Klall Prat u'Klall* is telling you כוונה *kavana* of a different קרבן
*korban* helps transform this into a שלמים *Shelamim*, but שלמים *Shelamim* being
your anchor word there, then maybe it only is a כוונה *kavana*
of a שלמים *Shelamim* or an עולה *Olah* that would work and
not of a חטאת *Chatas* and an אשם *Asham*. אלא *Ela* says
the גמרא *Gemara* fine, לזבח ריבויא הוא *L'zevach ribuya hu*.
We're not going to do the כלל ופרט וכלל *Klall u'Prat u'Klall*
דרשה *drasha*, which will get us sort of anchored, first a problem
are the כללים *klallim* the same, second it'll get us anchored too
much in the שלמים *Shelamim*. We're going to sort of go back
to what we were doing before and say לזבח *L'zevach* is a
ריבוי *ribuy*. Now, ריבוי *ribuy* is a different type of a דרשה
*drasha* than a כלל *klall* and a פרט *prat*. Sometimes it has
to do with what your methodology is. רש״י *Rashi* here says it
has to do with the language of the פסוקים *psukim* whether we
feel we can דרשן *darshen* them as a ריבוי *ribuy* or as
a כלל ופרט *klall u'prat*. But either way, if it's not general
and specific, it's specifically seen as ריבוי *ribuy* as coming to expand.
And since it's coming to expand, it is coming to tell us
that any כוונה *kavana* can work for any זבח *zevach*. And שלמים
*Shelamim* is then telling us and it becomes a שלמים *Shelamim*. Okay,
so we're sort of back to what we said before, but we're
responding to כלל ופרט *Klall u'Prat* by saying we're going to use
the word as a ריבוי *ribuy*, not as a כלל ופרט *Klall
u'Prat*, as something that broadens and expands. אימא לכל דשחיט ליה ליהוי
כוותיה *Eima l'chol d'shachit lei lehavei k'vatai*, but the גמרא *Gemara* is
still not happy because now that we are somehow reading it as
a ריבוי *ribuy*, we can't read it like just as פשט *p'shat*.
You know, פשט *p'shat* is or quote unquote פשט *p'shat* the way
we were reading it as like a full sentence. You know, ואם
מן הצאן קרבנו *v'im min hatzon korbano*, if it's a קרבן פסח
*korban Pesach*, לזבח *L'zevach*, any זבח *zevach* you שחט *shecht* it for,
שלמים *Shelamim*, it becomes a שלמים *Shelamim*. But now we're not reading
it as a sentence. The word לזבח *L'zevach* is just a ריבוי
*ribuy*. So if the word לזבח *L'zevach* is just a ריבוי *ribuy*,
then the גמרא *Gemara* says maybe we're back to where we started
before. Okay good, you could have any כוונה *kavana*, but any כוונה
*kavana*, it becomes that קרבן *korban*. How do you still know that
ultimately it becomes a שלמים *Shelamim*? So אמר ר׳ אבין *amar Rebbi
Avin*, says ר׳ אבין *Rebbi Avin* top of ט׳ ע״א *Tes amud
Aleph*, דוחין קדשים הנאכלים אצל קדשים הנאכלים ואין דוחין קדשים הנאכלים אצל
קדשים שאינם נאכלים *dochin kodshim ne'echalim etzel kodshim ne'echalim v'ein dochin kodshim
ne'echalim etzel kodshim she'einam ne'echalim*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no look,
a קרבן פסח *korban Pesach* is eaten by the owners, it's eaten
everywhere in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So if it's going to change its status,
then it's not going to turn into a different type of a
קרבן *korban* that can't be eaten, you know, that's an עולה *Olah*,
or that, you know, can't be eaten by everybody or is a
קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodshim*. That won't happen. It's going to דוחין *dochin*,
it's sort of like it's going to be pushed, its natural gravitation,
you know, its natural way of inclination is towards a שלמים *Shelamim*,
and that's where it's going to be. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
אטו חטאת ואשם מי לא מיתאכלי *atu Chatas v'Asham mi lo misachlei*?
One minute, what do you mean it's only things that are eaten?
Fine, but שלמים *Shelamim* isn't the only thing that's eaten. A חטאת
*Chatas* and an אשם *Asham* are also eaten by the כהנים *kohanim*
in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says אלא
דוחין קדשים הנאכלים לכל אדם אצל קדשים הנאכלים לכל אדם *ela dochin
kodshim ne'echalim l'chol adam etzel kodshim ne'echalim l'chol adam*. Right, right, right.
What we meant is, you know, פסח *Pesach* is eaten by all
people, by all people, you know, by the owners, by everybody, and
שלמים *Shelamim* is eaten by everybody. And I would also add and
in all of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So if it's not going to be
a פסח *Pesach*, it's going to become a שלמים *Shelamim*. Okay. ואין
דוחין קדשים הנאכלים לכל אדם אצל קדשים שאינם נאכלים לכל אדם *v'ein
dochin kodshim ne'echalim l'chol adam etzel kodshim she'einam ne'echalim l'chol adam*. And
you don't turn something that's a פסח *Pesach* into a חטאת *Chatas*
that can't be eaten by all people. So if it stopped and
going to not be a פסח *Pesach*, it's going to revert to
being a שלמים *Shelamim*. All right let's just read one more line.
מתקיף לה ר׳ יצחק ברבי סוורוף *maskif lah Rebbi Yitzchak berebi Svarof*,
so ר׳ יצחק ברבי סוורוף *Rebbi Yitzchak berebi Svarof* asked a question.
Oh I'm sorry, I skipped a line. אצל הנאכלים לכל אדם *etzel
hane'echalim l'chol adam*. ר׳ יוסי ברבי אבין אמר דוחין קדשים קלים kodshim
kalim, אצל קדשים קלים kodshim kalim ואין דוחין קדשים קלים אצל קדשי
קדשים *Rebbi Yose berebi Avin amar dochin kodshim kalim etzel kodshim kalim
v'ein dochin kodshim kalim etzel kodshei kodshim*. Okay,
that's sort of what I was saying. פסח *Pesach* and שלמים *Shelamim*
are קדשים קלים *kodshim kalim*, meaning they can be eaten in all
ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, and therefore a פסח *Pesach* is going to become a
שלמים *Shelamim*. It's not going to become a חטאת *Chatas* or an
אשם *Asham* even if that was your כוונה *kavana*, that's קדשי קדשים
*kodshei kodshim*. קדשי קדשים. Okay, מתקיף לה רבי יצחק ברבי סברא maskif
la Rabbi Yitzchak bar Rabbi Svara אימא שחטיה לשם מעשר להוי מעשר.
eima shachatei l'sheim Maaser l'havei Maaser. Okay, one minute, but I get
that. I get that a פסח can't, you know, be a חטאת
or an אשם, but maybe if you had כוונה for מעשר, Maaser,
maybe it could be treated as a מעשר. Maaser. That's eaten by
the owners, that's קדשים קלים, that could be eaten by anybody. Now,
you'll say what difference does it make? מעשר, Maaser, שלמים, it's all
the same קדושה, you know, who cares which one you call it?
So the גמרא says no. להוי מעשר? l'havei Maaser? למאי הלכתא? l'mai
hilchata? דלא לבעי נסכים. d'lo libaei nesachim. If we treat it as
מעשר, Maaser, מעשר Maaser you don't do נסכים nesachim with it, the
wine libations. ולמילקי עליה בלא יגאל, u'l'milkei alei b'lo yige'el, and you'll
get מלקות malkus if you sell, try to sell it because that's
a special לאו lav by מעשר. Maaser. So maybe, okay, I get
פסח is gonna be something
that's קדשים קלים and eaten by the owners, but that שלמים isn't
your only option. שלמים is your most generic option, but it's not
your only option. Why not treat it as a מעשר? Maaser? So
אמר קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says, העשירי יהיה קדש. ha'asiri
yihiyeh kodesh. Now the tenth one is sanctified. זה מעשר ואין אחר
מעשר. zeh Maaser v'ein acher Maaser. Only this has the status of
מעשר, Maaser, the one that is tenth, not something like a קרבן
פסח does not magically become מעשר. Maaser. Okay, we'll end with that
here.