Boker tov בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is ק"יא, Kuf
Yud Aleph, 111. We are really the end is near. So we
pick up at the top of ק"יא עמוד א Kuf Yud Aleph
Amud Aleph and we had been discussing a debate in the about
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the חכמים Chachamim when it says if
you do three לוג log of water are you חייב chayav outside
and different ways of explaining the debate and one of them and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer sort of said only if you fill it
up in a כלי. kli. What does that mean? So anyway one
way of defining it is do you need a כלי שרת kli
shares to sanctify the water in order to be חייב? chayav? And
that's a function of you certainly need it in the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash but did you need it in a במה? bamah? Because
if you didn't need it in a private במה bamah now
that's one of the ways you could be חייב chayav in your
private במה bamah outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is would it
have been legitimate in a private במה bamah at the time that
במות bamos were permissible? It doesn't always have to be the way
it was done in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash like the whole
issue about the possibility of putting it on a rock without burning
it on a fire. So anyway so that's part of the debate
here about whether you could have done wine without a כלי שרת
kli shares on a במה bamah and therefore can you do water
without a כלי שרת kli shares on a במה. bamah. Regarding water
wait let's just get a little further because that's going to be
we're going to continue that discussion right now. So we'll get back
to your question I just want to get a little further. תנו
רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Two lines from the top. המנסך שלושה לוגין יין
בחוץ. Hamenaseach shlosha lugin yayin bachutz. So exactly what we talked about
except now it's about wine. רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer berabbi
Shimon אומר omer חייב. chayav. You're חייב. chayav. Okay. Three לוג log
is the minimum that's what we've been saying. רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון
אומר והוא שקידשן בכלי. Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon omer vehu shekidshen bikli.
Only if you sanctified it in a vessel. Sounds very similar to
what we said before. There was a מלאם לשם חייב. miloam leshem
chayav. Here it emphasizes the vessel but again an emphasis of a
vessel which is why before some switched the גירסא girsa to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer כלי שרת. kli shares. Well you don't sanctify with
a vessel without a כלי שרת kli shares which is why before
some read רבי Rabbi there was a question whether before it was
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer or רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Eliezer berabbi
Shimon. Anyway so it's very parallel to the earlier debate but here
it's about wine. So מאי בינייהו? mai beinayhu? What is their debate
about? Sometimes מאי בינייהו mai beinayhu means like what is the practical
ramifications of their debate? למאי נפקא מינה? L'mai nafkamine? But here what
comes out of it? But here it actually sounds like what is
the core of what they're really arguing about? אמר רב אדא בר
אבא בר יצחק Amar Rav Adda bar Abba bar Yitzchak ביירוצי מידות
beirutzay midos איכא בינייהו. ika beinayhu. They're talking about whether the wine
you know there's what's that called? The meniscus. The when the surface
tension holds like a mound you know goes where a liquid can
go over the you know the the plane of the top of
the vessel because of the surface tension. So that's called ביירוצי מידות
beirutzay midos the heaping of the quantity. So when you need something
to be sanctified in a כלי שרת kli shares does it sanctify
only the things only what's in the walls or would it even
sanctify the overflow?
And therefore so the חכמים chachamim just say three לוג log anyway
you got three לוג log meaning however that was in your כלי
שרת. kli shares. כלי שרת kli shares is now being assumed. Whereas
רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon is saying no sanctified
in the vessel means I'm not prepared to say everything only that
that's exactly within the walls of the vessel. It's obviously reading a
lot into that.
Okay. Wait would it be the
same for מנחה mincha too like if you have yeah
yeah yeah same thing for מנחה. mincha. Correct. You're right. It's not
about specifically wine and ניסוך. nisuch. רבא בריה דרבה אמר Rava brei
de-Rabbah amar קירבו נסכים בבמה kirvu nesachim babamah איכא בינייהו. ika beinayhu.
Before we said במדבר bamidbar and here we said בבמה babamah but
as the גמרא Gemara it's sort of like the same debate whether
you're allowed to whether people brought נסכים nesachim you know wine libations
when the time that במות bamos were permissible. And if they did
there was no כלי שרת kli shares in a במה. bamah. So
therefore implicitly is that you had libations on a במה bamah without
a כלי שרת. kli shares. And if you had that at the
time when במות bamos were permissible then you're חייב chayav for it
now even though it's not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד ra'uy le-pesach ohel
mo'ed without a כלי שרת. kli shares. So the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma just says any three לוג log presumably you still need קדושת
פה kedushas peh you have to sanctify the wine as a you
know to be brought as a קרבן korban but you don't need
a כלי שרת. kli shares. And רבי אליעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer
berabbi Shimon is saying no even in the במות bamos excuse me
they didn't have them in the במות. bamos. במות bamos never didn't
have כלי שרת. kli shares. That's true. But they didn't have them
in the במות bamos and therefore you're only חייב chayav in a
כלי שרת kli shares because only then is it ראוי לפתח אהל
מועד. ra'uy le-pesach ohel mo'ed. Okay. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי. Ub-pulgta d'hanei tannai.
And it's tied into this debate. דתניא D'tanya we taught in the
ברייתא. braisa. במת יחיד אינה צריכה נסכים Bamas yachid einah tzericha nesachim
דברי רבי. divrei Rabbi. So now we're sort of not only saying
is it allowed but is it required. But it's all the same
debate. So if you bring a private sacrifice on a private במה
bamah in a time when במות bamos were permissible before the first
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was built so רבי Rabbi said you don't
have to bring the נסכים nesachim with it. Do you have to
or can you? Well it says you're not חייב chayav אינה צריכה
נסכים. einah tzericha nesachim. Okay but yes as I said it's really
it's the same. If it doesn't require it's also
not allowed. All right so you don't have נסכים nesachim in a
private במה. bamah. וחכמים אומרים טעונה נסכים. Vachachamim omrim te'unah nesachim. It
is required and so that is the debate of do you have
it in a private במה bamah again. In a private במה bamah
you would not have כלי שרת. kli shares. So therefore are you
חייב chayav When you do it on your במה bamah at a
time when במות bamos are forbidden without a כלי שרת klei shareis
is a function of whether such a phenomenon ever existed at the
time when במות bamos were permissible. Because certainly it's not ראוי לפתח
אהל מועד rauy l'pesach ohel moed without a כלי שרת, klei shareis,
but whether it's fit for a במה, bamah, that would be the
question: did you ever have במות bamos that had נסכים, nesachim, and
if you did then you had them without a כלי שרת? klei
shareis? Michael, you had a question from before.
Yeah, so I was trying to understand this in terms of the
ניסוך המים, nisuch hamayim, because they went out from the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, didn't they have a צלוחית? tzlochit? So was it not
a כלי שרת? keli shareis?
And then when they poured it down... Right, that would be the
question. Well no, but in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, forget that,
bracket that. All this stuff had a כלי שרת keli shareis in
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. The only question was is that did
you have... so therefore if if if you only had the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash model you'd be פטור pattur if you didn't use
a כלי שרת. keli shareis. The question is is can you be
מחייב mechayev somebody not because of ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, rauy l'pesach
ohel moed, but now we're seeing that there's another model to which
to be מחייב mechayev somebody, which is is that this is a
a legitimate worship in a במה bamah when במות bamos are permissible.
No, no, I understand that, but I guess I'm trying to envision
like the process. So they went because they have to fill the
the this whatever.
Yeah, yeah,
I have to check the משניות mishnayos in סוכה Sukkah again. I
think that they poured it in a כלי שרת keli shareis in
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, but I don't remember. I have
to check the משניות mishnayos in סוכה. Sukkah. Okay. Now והני תנאי
כהני תנאי. v'hani tannai k'hani tannai. Now this this debate of רבי
Rebbi and the חכמים chachamim did did were נסכים nesachim required on
a במה, bamah, which also means were they permitted on a במה,
bamah, ties into the following debate of תנאים tannaim because as we've
already alluded or said or alluded that whether נסכים nesachim were on
a במה bamah is also a function of whether they were in
the מדבר. midbar. Okay, and we're going to see how that ties
in. It doesn't like necessarily logically tie in because in the מדבר
midbar it was a משכן, mishkan, it was a central location, but
it ties in based on the פסוק. pasuk. So let's take a
look. דתניא, D'tanya,
we taught in a ברייתא. beraisa. כי תבאו, Ki tavo, when you
come to the land, that's what it says at the end of
פרשת קרח, parshas Korach, כי תבאו... Ki tavo... or is it שלח?
Shlach? The end of שלח. Shlach. כי תבאו אל ארץ מושבותיכם אשר
אני נותן לכם. Ki tavo el eretz moshvoseichem asher ani nosen lachem.
Anyway, and you shall go ahead and you bring a קרבן korban
and then you should bring these wine and flour and oil together
with your קרבן. korban. Okay. So הלטינו נסכים בבמה גדולה הכתוב מדבר.
halatinu nesachim b'bamah gedolah haksav medaber. So it says you're going to
come to your land, so presumably we're going to presume that the
basic default is to be talking about a case of קרבנות korbanot
brought in a central location. So we're going to be talking about
a במה גדולה. bamah gedolah. You're only חייב chayav when you enter
the land to bring נסכים, nesachim, you're not חייב chayav now in
the מדבר. midbar. You're only going to be חייב chayav when you
enter the land and it's going to be in a central location.
Okay. הכתוב מדבר. Haksav medaber. אתה אומר בבמה גדולה או אינו אלא
אפילו בבמה קטנה? Atah omer b'bamah gedolah o eino ela afilu b'bamah
ketanah? Maybe you'll bring it when you enter the land even in
your private במות? bamos? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar אל ארץ מושבותיכם אשר
אני נותן לכם. el eretz moshvoseichem asher ani nosen lachem. The land
of your inheritance that I will give you. הרי בבמה הנוהגת לכולכם
הכתוב מדבר. harei b'bamah hanoheges l'chulchem haksav medaber. We're talking about a
collective. You all as a collective. It's not every individual I'm going
to give the land. You as a collective I'm going to give
the land. It's going to be the land of your dwelling as
a people as a collective. So therefore it means when you bring
קרבנות korbanot as a collective or when you bring, not קרבנות ציבור
korbanos tzibbur necessarily, but anyway, a central type of a location, a
single
location. Okay. דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabi Yishmael. That's רבי ישמעאל Rabi
Yishmael says. So you didn't bring it in the מדבר, midbar, you'll
bring it when you go in, but you'll only bring it in
a במה גדולה, bamah gedolah, no במה יחיד. bamah yachid. Okay. רבי
עקיבא אומר. Rabi Akiva omer. רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva says, כי תבאו,
Ki tavo, when you come. הלטינו נסכים בבמה קטנה הכתוב מדבר. halatinu
nesachim b'bamah ketanah haksav medaber. No, when they enter the land even
on their private במות. bamos. אתה אומר בבמה קטנה או אינו אלא
בבמה גדולה? Atah omer b'bamah ketanah o eino ela b'bamah gedolah? Maybe
it means a central במה? bamah? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar אל ארץ
מושבותיכם. el eretz moshvoseichem. הרי בבמה הנוהגת בכל מושבות הכתוב מדבר. harei
b'bamah hanoheges b'chol moshvos haksav medaber. I'm going to emphasize not מושבותיכם
moshvoseichem you as a collective, I'm going to emphasize מושבות, moshvos, your
dwellings, so means wherever you all the different places that you dwell.
And that's one of the obviously the thing about
במות, bamos, right? רק הבמות לא סרו עוד העם מזבחים ומקטרים בבמות.
rak habamos lo saru od ha'am m'zavchim umkattrim babamos. All the private
במות, bamos, everybody gets their own little private במה. bamah. Okay, so
a phrase that my wife likes is everybody's making their own Shabbos,
like you know, everybody has their own little private במה, bamah, everybody
gets to decide which day of the week you want Shabbos to
be. Okay, anyway. הכתוב מדבר. Haksav medaber. Now so therefore he says
that they would in the private במות, bamos, and he emphasizes that
part of the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, and therefore that's the debate. Now
that by the way that's not a debate that says that it's
dependent on whether they did it in the מדבר. midbar. That's just
a debate how do you read the פסוק pasuk when it says
when you go into the land. Does it mean when you go
into the land and have a central location or when you go
into the land and everybody is worshipping in their private location? But
now the גמרא Gemara says כשתמצי לומר, keshtimtzai lomar, like if you
want you could say, לדברי רבי ישמעאל לא קרבו נסכים במדבר לדברי
רבי עקיבא קרבו נסכים במדבר. l'divrei Rabi Yishmael lo karvu nesachim b'midbar
l'divrei Rabi Akiva karvu nesachim b'midbar. That actually רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael
would say they didn't bring it and רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva would
say they did. Why? How did that tie in exactly? Not totally
clear, but basically the way is is that if you think that
they're already bringing it in, you know, in the משכן, mishkan, then
when it says when you come then there's like somehow, you know,
I mean there's a whole long רש"י Rashi to explain it. But
basically if they already bring it in in the משכן, mishkan, then
it's, you know, it's pretty implicit you're going to bring it in
a central location when you enter into the land. So what's the
חידוש chiddush that says when you enter into the land you're going
to bring it? You're already bringing it. What do you mean when
you enter? So the only real leftover חידוש chiddush to be saying
is you can bring it in your private במה bamah everywhere, whereas
if you're not yet bringing it, then the first thing you want
to say is when you enter the land, you'll be bringing it
in your central location, right? And therefore you never get around to
saying that you bring it in your private במה. bamah. Okay, good.
And therefore that debate will determine whether or not you'll be חייב
chayav when you bring it in the period when במות bamot are
not permissible without a כלי שרת kli sharet because when you do
things in private במות bamot it's without a כלי שרת. kli sharet.
נחמיה אומר, Nechemya Omer, Rabbi נחמיה Nechemya said, שירי הדם שהקריב בחוץ
חייב. shearei hadam shehikriv bachutz chayav. So this was the end of
the משנה, mishna, that the משנה mishna said that even one application
of blood, because one application of blood is meaningful and is מכפר,
mechaper,
but Rabbi נחמיה Nechemya says even the remnant of blood that you
go ahead and you do. Now the question is why is that
ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, raui l'petach ohel moed, the spilling of the
remnant of blood, you know, is not an important part of a
כפרה kapara in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, I mean it's sort
of, you know, it's not a necessary part of the כפרה. kapara.
Do you need that to be considered ראוי לפתח אהל מועד raui
l'petach ohel moed to be a necessary part of the כפרה? kapara?
So let's take a look. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, תנא דרבי נחמיה כדברי האומר שיריים מעכבים.
Tana d'Rabbi Nechemya k'divrei haomer shearayim meakvim. Rabbi
נחמיה Nechemya actually is saying that you need to spill the remainder
of the blood to be יוצא yotze the קרבן. korban. It really
is מעכב, meakev, which is, I mean we've heard that idea by
a חטאת, chatas, an inner חטאת, chatas, it's a much stranger idea,
rarer idea by an outer קרבן, korban, but he's understanding that you
would not be חייב chayav outside in a במה bamah unless this
was something that was necessary for כפרה, kapara, you know, for the
act of כפרה kapara in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, okay? And
so he actually holds that even the spilling of the remnant of
the blood maybe by a standard sacrifice seems to be is מעכב.
meakev. But did you really need to say that for Rabbi נחמיה?
Nechemya? Couldn't you just say that this is still a ritual, you
know, a sacrificial rite outside? Why do you have to say that
it's מעכב? meakev? It's still ראוי לפתח אהל מועד. raui l'petach ohel
moed. So let's take a look. That's what the גמרא's gemara going
to ask. מתיב רבי נחמיה, Meisiv Rabbi Nechemya, מתיב, Meisiv, I'll ask
you on your claim, your implicit point that it needs to be
מעכב. meakev. רבי נחמיה אומר, Rabbi Nechemya omer, here we have a
ברייתא, braisa, Rabbi נחמיה Nechemya says, שירי הדם שהקריב בחוץ חייב. shearei
hadam shehikriv bachutz chayav. You're חייב chayav if you use the remnant
of the blood, remainder of the blood. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar
lo Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi עקיבא Akiva said to him, והלא שירי הדם
שירי מצוה הן. v'halo shearei hadam shearei mitzvah hein. But what do
you mean, it's just like wrap-up stuff, it's not central to the
rites of the blood. אמר לו, Amar lo, איברים ופדרים יוכיחו. evarim
u'fedarim yochichu. Okay, but who says you need something that is central
to the כפרה kapara of the קרבן? korban? How about the fats,
you know, and the, you know, and the inner organs, okay, the
entrails. If you didn't bring that, you're still
יוצא, yotze, and nevertheless that's an explicit פסוק pasuk that you're חייב
בחוץ. chayav bachutz. So since when do you need something that's a
מכפר, mechaper, you know? שאין
שירי
מצוה, sheein shearei mitzvah, they're just wrapping up, you've already done the
כפרה kapara of the blood, והמקריבן בחוץ חייב, v'hamakrivan bachutz chayav, and
you're חייב. chayav So that's a pretty reasonable position. So if you're
חייב chayav. for the burning of the entrails, you should be חייב
chayav for a final blood rite, you know, sacrificial rite. So let's
see what Rabbi עקיבא Akiva says back. אמר לו, Amar lo, he
said back to him, lo, no, it's not a good comparison.
אם אמרת באיברים ופדרים שהם תחלת עבודה. Im amarta b'evarim u'fedarim sheheim
techilat avoda. There they're not like the end of and the wrap-up
work of some other thing which is primary. For they're not מעכב
כפרה, meakev kapara, that's true, but there is a separate act that
is called the offering up of the fats and the
entrails. And there that's the whole act, okay? So within that special
ritual of offering the entrails, okay, nobody, you're right, not מעכב כפרה,
meakev kapara, but
it is, it has its own significance. Whereas the blood is not
the, you know, its own ritual of spilling the remainder of the
blood. That's like a footnote to the ritual of זריקת הדם. zrikas
hadam. And therefore it's not central enough to be חייב
בחוץ.
chayav
bachutz?
Don't we also have אם בשר אין דם, im basar ein dam,
like let's say
there's that opinion, okay?
So then it's not just like, you know, and it was the
end of the blood, okay, but like, you know, but the איברים
evarim can be central because if you don't something happen to it
you may not be even able to make right.
That's I mean that's true, but that's a debate, so you don't
need and you know you might not hold that specific position. But
you're right, the entrails is also important in its in the you
know plays a role in the legitimacy of the דם, dam, at
least according to that opinion. But we're focusing here on the act
of right that's true but anyway we're focusing here on the act
of offering them up. And that point was actually debated. So anyway
he says שכן תחלת עבודה, shechein techilat avoda, תאמר בשירי דם שאינם
תחלת עבודה. tomar b'shearei dam sheeinam techilat avoda. Okay, so that's the
debate. So now you could understand that debate, right, which is is
that, you know, everybody agrees and that's a reasonable debate. Everybody agrees
that the spilling of the blood is not מעכב, meakev, and
Rabbi נחמיה Nechemya says I don't care, you have these three things,
שחיטה, shechita, blood, and העלאה, haalaah, and as long as the blood
is still ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, raui l'petach ohel moed, you're חייב.
chayav It's a very reasonable position. Nobody says you need something that's
מעכב. me'akev. It's רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva that's coming and introducing a
distinction. I mean it's a logical
distinction but... sorry. You still understand רב נחמיה's Reb Nechemia position. Okay,
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva just says no, there's a big difference between
איברים ופדרים eivarim upedarim and the שיריים shirayim and the blood.
Sorry.
All right. So anyway, so that's the simple reading of their debate.
That you don't need that... רב נחמיה's Reb Nechemia not claiming that
it's מעכב. me'akev. So the גמרא Gemara says, sorry,
allergies, who knows?
All
right,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So ואם איתא לימא ליה,
ve'im isa leima leh, sorry,
ואם איתא, ve'im isa, if what you're saying is correct רבי יוחנן,
Rebbi Yochanan, that it's about whether it's מעכב me'akev or not,
לימא
ליה, leima leh, הני נמי מעכבי. hani nami me'akvei. Why didn't רב
נחמיה Reb Nechemia say back to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, what are
you talking about? I think the blood is מעכב. me'akev. תיובתא. tiuvta.
So you're right. So that ברייתא braita is a clear
contradiction
to רבי יוחנן's Rebbi Yochanan claim that רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia is
about it being מעכב. me'akev. It seems like רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia
does not need the idea of it being מעכב. me'akev. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, והשתא דאמר רב אדא בר אהבה, vehashta de'amar
Rav Ada bar Ahava, sorry, oy. Now that רב אדא בר אהבה
Rav Ada bar Ahava says מחלוקת בשיריים פנימיים אבל בשיריים חיצוניים דברי
הכל לא מעכבי, machlokes beshirayim pnimiyim aval beshirayim chitzoniyim divrei hakol lo
me'akvei, that actually the whole debate of whether the blood is מעכב,
me'akev, the spilling of the שיריים shirayim of the blood is מעכב,
me'akev, is only by the inner חטאת. chatas. By the outer חטאת
chatas or by the outer קרבנות, korbanos, nobody says it's מעכב, me'akev,
which totally makes sense. We've never heard anybody
say
that the outer... by that the outer קרבן, korban, the spilling of
the blood is מעכב. me'akev. By the inner חטאת chatas maybe it
makes sense because there everything is מעכב. me'akev. Anyway, now that he
says that that's the debate,
כי קאמר רב נחמיה בשיריים הפנימיים. ki ka'amar Reb Nechemia beshirayim hapnimiyim.
Now we have a way to defend רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. Okay,
how could we defend רבי יוחנן? Rebbi Yochanan? Because we could say,
sorry, sorry, we could say that רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is right.
רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia is only saying his position because he believes
it's מעכב. me'akev. And he's only saying it by an inner חטאת,
chatas, although again, there's no evidence... oh my gosh, I'm sorry.
Even though again, there's no evidence of that in the משנה. Mishna.
He's only saying it by an inner חטאת chatas and the debate
of him and רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva was by an outer חטאת.
chatas. Okay, but it doesn't explain the question. That
explains how he could say it's מעכב, me'akev, but if they're talking
about an outer קרבן, korban, then why is he... oh, I'm sorry.
And he's talking about an outer קרבן korban and therefore
that's why he couldn't say back to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, it's
מעכב, me'akev, because they're talking about an outer one, it's not מעכב.
me'akev. Of course, it still begs the question because let him say
to רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva you misunderstood me,
an outer... an outer קרבן korban I'm not... I agree with you,
it's not... you're חייב. chayav. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. כי קאמר רב נחמיה בשיריים הפנימיים. ki ka'amar Reb Nechemia beshirayim
hapnimiyim.
When did he say to make this work with רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan that you're חייב chayav. by an inner... an inner חטאת chatas
and the remainder of an inner חטאת. chatas. כי תניא היא... ki
tanya hee... and the debate of him and רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
is בשיריים החיצוניים, beshirayim hachitzoniyim, the outer one. Okay, which explains why
he didn't say back, hey it's מעכב, me'akev, that's why I'm saying
this. But why didn't he say back, you're misunderstanding me, we're not
disagreeing about an inner חטאת. chatas. So now the גמרא Gemara says
and we should read the parentheses, אי הכי, ei hachi, the גמרא
Gemara says, רבי עקיבא לא ידע מאי קאמר רב נחמיה. Rebbi Akiva
lo yada mai ka'amar Reb Nechemia. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva misunderstood רב
נחמיה. Reb Nechemia. כסבור רב נחמיה שיריים חיצוניים קאמר. kasbar Reb Nechemia
shirayim chitzoniyim ka'amar. He thought רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia was saying it
by the outer חטאת. chatas. וקא מהדר ליה שיריים חיצוניים veka mahdar
leh shirayim chitzoniyim and therefore he was giving him a counter proof
of שיריים חיצוניים. shirayim chitzoniyim. So why didn't רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia
correct רבי עקיבא's Rebbi Akiva misunderstanding? Because רב נחמיה לדבריו דרבי עקיבא
קאמר.
Reb Nechemia lidvarav deRebbi
Akiva ka'amar. He was just saying, hey רבי עקיבא, Rebbi Akiva, look,
for the fun of it, you know, I really am only talking
about an inner חטאת, chatas, but for the fun of it let's
argue about an outer חטאת. chatas. I'm going to push back on
you and try to say that an argument could be made even
by an outer קרבן korban that a שיריים shirayim should be חייב.
chayav And רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva says no, I'd make a distinction.
So again, the simple reading is that רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia says
it even by an outer קרבן korban and he's saying since when
do you need it to be מעכב me'akev and therefore anything about
the blood, as long as the blood is still ראוי לפתח אהל
מועד ra'ui lepetach ohel moed you're חייב. chayav. And רבי עקיבא Rebbi
Akiva makes a distinction between the remainder of the blood and the
איברים ופדרים. eivarim upedarim. But according to רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan, they
only... רב נחמיה Reb Nechemia only said it because it's מעכב me'akev
and therefore he would only be talking about an inner חטאת. chatas.
Okay, next.
So it ends with a logical question and you know. Whoever it
is, let's say he over here אביי ורבא Abaye ve-Rava says מחלוקת
machlokes in this and the other one says מחלוקת machlokes in that,
is that just their opinion or they actually, like, have a מסורה,
mesorah, like you know based on some sort of source?
No way of knowing.
No way of knowing. I mean, since he doesn't quote a מסורה
mesorah whatever, it sounds like he's just saying that logically, which you
certainly understand the logic here. Okay. Next משנה. Mishnah. המולק את העוף
בפנים והעלה בחוץ חייב. Hamolek es ha-of bifnim ve-he'ela bachutz chayav. Back
to מליקת העוף melikas ha-of which is a, like a nice fascinating
example, because there it's the counter of what you of what you
do inside. Okay, if you do מליקה melika inside, that's makes a
כשר kosher עבודה avoda and therefore if you do העלאה ha'ala'ah outside
you're going to be חייב. chayav. מלק בחוץ והעלה בחוץ Malak bachutz
ve-he'ela bachutz how about if you started with מליקה melika outside and
then you did העלאה, ha'ala'ah, you're פטור patur on the מליקה melika
because we learned that it's only a הלכה halacha of שחוטי חוץ,
shchutei chutz, so even though the מליקה melika is what you would
do inside, it's not meaningful outside. And B, you're פטור patur on
the העלאה ha'ala'ah because that's considered like not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד.
ra'uy le-pesach ohel mo'ed. Of course it's a little ironic, we all
know, because if you do the שחיטה shechita of a בהמה behema
it's also not ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, ra'uy le-pesach ohel mo'ed, you
brought it outside the בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash. But it's sort of
like פיגול, piggul, like within the world of the fact that you're
doing this עבודה, avoda, we sort of bracket the fact that you
did it outside and therefore when you שחט shacht the בהמה behema
and then you do העלאה ha'ala'ah you're חייב. chayav. Okay, but here,
the fact that you did
a מליקה melika outside, so מליקה melika outside the בית המקדש Beis
Ha-Mikdash is, you know, again, it's not, it's somehow not, it's sort
of like it's not like a meaningful עבודה avoda at all. It's
not like the שחיטה shechita outside which is still sort of fits
the parameters of שחיטה. shechita. So therefore since מליקה melika outside
invalidates, and therefore the העלאה ha'ala'ah that follows is also going to
be פטור. patur. So again, it's a little ironic. שחיטה Shechita of
the bird which is not meaningful at all inside, but that's the
meaningful act outside, therefore the next stage you'd also be חייב chayav.
by the העלאה. ha'ala'ah. מליקה Melika which דוקא davka is meaningful inside,
but because it's not meaningful outside, the next stage you're going to
be פטור. patur. Okay, מלק בחוץ והעלה בחוץ פטור. malak bachutz ve-he'ela
bachutz patur. So it's quite fascinating. השוחט את העוף בפנים והעלה בחוץ.
Ha-shochet es ha-of bifnim ve-he'ela bachutz. Now let's say you did the,
now let's say you started the process in the בית המקדש. Beis
Ha-Mikdash. So there it's the reverse. Everything is defined by its context,
right? Is שחיטה shechita meaningful or מליקה melika meaningful? It's all defined
by its context.
So if it took place in the בית המקדש Beis Ha-Mikdash and
you did
שחיטה, shechita, that was a meaningless act and it's like you know
you shot it in the head. Okay, והעלה בחוץ פטור. ve-he'ela bachutz
patur. So therefore the second stage of העלאה ha'ala'ah you're going to
be פטור patur because it's like no longer ראוי לפתח אהל מועד.
ra'uy le-pesach ohel mo'ed. שחט
בחוץ והעלה בחוץ. Shachat bachutz ve-he'ela bachutz. How about if you did
שחט בחוץ והעלה בחוץ חייב? shachat bachutz ve-he'ela bachutz chayav? If
you did a שחיטה shechita outside...
yeah I know. המולק את העוף בפנים והעלה בחוץ חייב. Hamolek es
ha-of bifnim ve-he'ela bachutz chayav. מלק בחוץ והעלה בחוץ. Malak bachutz ve-he'ela
bachutz. Okay, so if you, yeah I'm fine I just think I...
anyway, שחט בחוץ והעלה בחוץ shachat bachutz ve-he'ela bachutz you're going to
be, I think I just introduced that before and I confused myself.
Anyway if you did the שחיטה shechita outside and the העלאה ha'ala'ah
outside you're going to be חייב, chayav okay? So let's sort of
draw the pictures, okay.
Yeah, if you did what's valid
in each context
you're חייב chayav, basically or whatever.
Okay, here's the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, okay fine, and here you
are outside the בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash. So whatever, here's your little
bird.
Draw them with wings. Okay, anyway, so okay, if you basically do
מליקה...
melika... I can't draw מליקה, melika,
I'm going to sort of kind of do... I'm going to draw
a fingernail for my hand... I'm bad at drawing hands... okay anyway...
ach that looks awful.
Oh I see, it's the back of the head.
Back of the head. If you do מליקה melika there, okay, then
that's a meaningful act. So then if you follow it with stage
two of העלאה, ha'ala'ah, here's your little מזבח mizbeach and here's your
poor bird on the מזבח, mizbeach, okay, if you follow that with
stage two you're going to be חייב chayav because that was a
meaningful act. If however you did שחיטה... shechita...
okay, okay, at stage one, that's not a mean... whatever, that's like
shooting it in the head, so then if you do stage two
here you're going to be פטור, patur, okay, because if you ruined
it here, you're פטור patur on stage two. If however you started
everything on this side, let's see if we get the black working...
this is where you can really use more colors... okay, if however
you started it here,
okay,
you started מליקה melika here, okay, then that is meaning... that's a,
you know, a wrong act outside the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash, it
doesn't have any meaning, it's like you shot it in the head,
and then for stage two you're going to be
פטור. patur. Whereas I guess we'll use orange again, if you did
שחיטה, shechita, that's meaningful, so then for stage number two you're going
to be חייב.
chayav And if you did מליקה בחוץ melika bachutz and then העלאה
בפנים... ha'ala'ah bifnim...
oh well, מליקה בחוץ והעלאה... melika bachutz ve-ha'ala'ah... that's just bringing something
פסול pasul בפנים... bifnim... and בחוץ ובפנים מה זו...
bachutz
u'bifnim ma zu...
that's not... yeah, exactly, it's not our discussion. Okay, so נמצא
דרך הכשרו בפנים פטורו בחוץ. Nimtza derech hechshero bifnim paturo bachutz. Now
the גמרא Gemara is going to change the word הכשרו hechshero here
to mean חיובו. chiyuvo. Okay? But דרך חיובו בפנים, derech chiyuvo bifnim,
פטורו בחוץ. paturo bachutz. The way in which, and now I've got
to read this whole רש״י Rashi I've read it like three times
last night. Hold on. Hold on. דרך שחט
בפנים והעלה בחוץ פטור. derech shachat bifnim vehela bachutz patur.
דרך, derech, one minute, דרך... derech...
Okay, so דרך חיובו, derech chiyuvo, so let's try this, let's see
if I can get this. דרך, derech, let's, we'll read הכשרו hechsheiro
as חיובו, chiyuvo, the גמרא Gemara is going to amend it. דרך
חיובו בחוץ, derech chiyuvo bachutz, the way you're חייב בחוץ chayav bachutz
by מליקה, melikah, okay, if you start the
מליקה melikah inside...
No, in- no,
instead of הכשרו hechsheiro read it חיובו. chiyuvo. חיובו בפנים. chiyuvo bifnim.
Oh, I'm sorry, skip to the second line. דרך חיובו בפנים, derech
chiyuvo bifnim, the way you're חייב chayav. if you do it בפנים,
bifnim, meaning, meaning,
מליקה. melikah.
But he's not פטור. patur. פטורו בחוץ, paturo bachutz, you did it
outside, right?
Yeah, you would think it means, hold on, רש״י Rashi is reading
the בחוץ, bachutz. hold on, let me just get this one more,
I have read this. Hold on... I had this before. Hold on.
דרך שחט בפנים והעלה בחוץ פטור. derech shachat bifnim vehela bachutz patur.
בפנים... bifnim... Right.
So דרך, derech, דרך חיובו בפנים, derech chiyuvo bifnim, the way you're
חייב chayav is if you start something, this is how you have
to, this is how you read it. Again, the simple read of
this I think says something else, but we won't worry about that,
we're going to go with רש״י. Rashi. The way you're חייב chayav
if you started it בפנים. bifnim. What's the way you are חייב
chayav if you start it בפנים? bifnim? So it doesn't mean the
whole thing is בפנים. bifnim. You started it בפנים. bifnim. The way
you're חייב chayav is מליקה, melikah, which could also mean הכשרו hechsheiro
because it's because this is כשר kosher בפנים, bifnim, that's you're חייב
chayav when you start it בפנים. bifnim. Okay? So the way you,
in this case, you started it בפנים bifnim and you're going to
be חייב. chayav This is this case. So it's דרך חיובו בפנים
derech chiyuvo bifnim because it's מחייב mechayev you when you start it
בפנים. bifnim. You could also read it הכשרו בפנים hechsheiro bifnim because
the מליקה melikah is meaningful inside. So דרך הכשרו derech hechsheiro slash
חיובו בפנים, chiyuvo bifnim, if you do that בחוץ, bachutz if you
do מליקה, melikah, you're going to be פטור. patur. Okay? פטור. patur.
דרך הכשרו מבחוץ, derech hechsheiro mibachutz, the way you're חייב chayav if,
because the word here הכשר hechsheir doesn't work, הכשר hechsheir works for
when you're talking about this, it doesn't work. The way you're חייב
chayav. when you start outside, which is שחיטה, shechitah, is פטורו מבפנים,
paturo mibifnim, is when you start שחיטה shechitah inside you're going to
be פטור. patur. So it's actually
fine. Okay? דרך הכשרו מבחוץ פטורה מבפנים. derech hechsheiro mibachutz patura mibifnim.
רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer,
כל שחייבין עליו בחוץ חייבין על כיוצא בו בפנים. kol shechayavin alav
bachutz chayavin al kayotzei bo bifnim. He seems to be arguing on
something, but the גמרא Gemara is going to try to figure out
what. Anything that if you'd be חייב chayav if you did the
stages inside, you'll be חייב chayav when you did the stages outside.
Okay? כיוצא בו בפנים שהעלה בחוץ kayotzei bo bifnim shehela bachutz and
then you finish it outside. So it sounds like he would be
saying, okay, in what case are you חייב chayav בחוץ? bachutz, The
case you're חייב chayav בחוץ bachutz, is when you start with שחיטה,
shechitah, right? And then you do העלאה. ha-ala. Yes, Michael? So that's
כל שחייבין עליו בחוץ. kol shechayavin alav bachutz. You started with שחיטה.
shechitah. So חייבין עליו כיוצא בו בפנים שהעלה בחוץ. chayavin alav kayotzei
bo bifnim shehela bachutz. It sounds like he's saying the same way
outside you're חייב chayav by שחיטה shechitah and then העלאה, ha-ala, if
you did שחיטה shechitah inside and you finished it with העלאה ha-ala
you're also חייב. chayav. Okay? חוץ מן השוחט בפנים ומעלה בחוץ. chutz
min hashochet bifnim umaaleh bachutz. But then he says with the exception
of exactly what we think he's talking about. If you שחט shecht
inside and finish outside. So this is going to be a cryptic
statement, okay? He's saying if you're חייב chayav on it outside you're
also חייב chayav when you start inside. So it sounds like he's
talking about when you're חייב chayav with starting with שחיטה shechitah outside,
you're חייב chayav when you start with שחיטה shechitah inside, but then
he says except for the case when you started with שחיטה shechitah
inside. So the גמרא Gemara is going to figure out so what
case are you leaving us exactly? Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. האי הכשרו חיובו. hai hechsheiro chiyuvo. What do you mean
it's הכשר? hechsheir? I mean we could talk about it's הכשר בפנים,
hechsheir bifnim, but we can't talk about it's הכשר בחוץ, hechsheir bachutz,
בחוץ bachutz is when you're חייב chayav when you start with שחיטה.
shechitah. Fine. תני חיובו, tani chiyuvo, have it say חיובו. chiyuvo. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, now we're going to have to unpack
this, this, this statement of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. אהי קאי? ahi
kai? What is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon disagreeing with and what case
is he referring to?
אילימא רישא קאי, ee lima reisha kai, if he's talking about the
case of המולק, hamoleik, המולק עוף בפנים והעלה בחוץ חייב. hamoleik of
bifnim vehela bachutz chayav. If you do it inside and finish outside
you're
חייב. chayav. מולק בחוץ והעלה בחוץ פטור. moleik bachutz vehela bachutz patur.
ואמר ליה veamar lei רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon כי היכי דבפנים מחייב,
ki heichi debifnim mechayev, the same way מליקה melikah you're חייב chayav
when you start it inside, בחוץ נמי מחייב, bachutz nami mechayev, then
if you start מליקה melikah outside you should be חייב. chayav. Okay,
maybe that's what he's doing. If you're חייב chayav inside you should
be חייב chayav outside. So then he should have said it in
the reverse. האי כל שחייבין עליו בחוץ, hai kol shechayavin alav bachutz,
he shouldn't have said if you're חייב chayav outside you're חייב chayav
inside, he should have said כל שחייבין עליו בפנים איבעי ליה, kol
shechayavin alav bifnim ibaya lei, right? If he's talking about מליקה, melikah,
he wants you to be חייב chayav for מליקה melikah outside. He
shouldn't have said what you're חייב chayav *chayav* on outside you're חייב
chayav *chayav* on inside. He should have done the opposite, what you're
חייב chayav *chayav* on inside, מליקה melika, *Melika*, you're חייב chayav *chayav*
on outside. So that he can't be talking about מליקה melika. *Melika*
outside, he should have said the reverse. אלא *Ela*, maybe he's trying
to פטור patur *patter* you when you by מליקה melika. *Melika*. כי
היכי דבחוץ לא מחייב *Ki haichei d'bechutz lo mechayev*, the same way
by מליקה *Melika* when you start מליקה *Melika* outside you're not חייב
chayav *chayav*, בפנים bifnim נמי לא מחייב *bifnim nami lo mechayev*. Maybe
he wants to say, hey, if you even if you start it
with מליקה *Melika* inside you're פטור patur. *patter* the same way when
you started it with מליקה *Melika* outside you're פטור Patur, *patter*. No,
because then he shouldn't have said whatever you're חייב chayav, *chayav* on,
you know outside you're חייב chayav. *chayav* inside. האי כל שאין חייבין
עליה בחוץ bachutz, מיבעי ליה *Hai kol she'ein chayavin aleha bechutz miba'ei
lei*. He should have said what you're פטור patur *patter* on outside
by מליקה *Melika* you're פטור patur. *patter* on inside. So by מליקה
*Melika* it doesn't work. Okay, it sounds like he's saying because you're
חייב chayav, *chayav* outside you're חייב chayav. *chayav* inside. But by מליקה
*Melika*, okay, you know, it would the linking of the outside and
inside would come to an opposite sort of, you know, would come
to an opposite conclusion. So כי היכי דלא מחייב בפנים bifnim מחייב
בפנים bifnim, נמי לא מחייב *ki haichei d'lo mechayev bifnim mechayev bifnim
nami lo mechayev* wait, wait, wait. אלא אסיפא קאי *Ela
aseifa ka'ei*. So we're talking not about the מליקה *Melika* case because
the מליקה *Melika* case doesn't yield fit his words, but we're talking
about the שחיטה *Shechita* case. השוחט עוף בפנים bifnim, והעלה בחוץ Vehe'elah
bachutz. פטור patur. *Hashocheit of bifnim v'he'ela bechutz pattur*. שחט shachat בחוץ
bachutz, והעלה בחוץ bachutz חייב chayav *Shachat bechutz v'he'ela bechutz chayav*. Okay,
אמר ליה רב שמן *amar lei Rav Shemen*, רב שמן *Rav Shemen*
says one minute, כי היכי דבפנים לא מחייב בחוץ bachutz נמי לא
מחייב *ki haichei d'bifnim lo mechayev bechutz nami lo mechayev*, when you
so it the same way maybe he's sort of trying to פטור
patur, *patter* you and say the same way when you start with
שחיטה *Shechita* of a bird inside you're פטור patur, *patter*, even when
you do שחיטה *Shechita* of a bird outside you're פטור patur. *patter*.
Okay, if he's trying to פטור patur *patter* you, he shouldn't have
said what you're חייב chayav *chayav* on, you know, in you know,
outside you're חייב chayav *chayav* inside, he should have said האי כל
שאין חייבין מיבעי ליה *ha kol she'ein chayavin miba'ei lei*. He should
have said what you're פטור *patter* on. If you're פטור *patter* on
שחיטה *Shechita* inside you should be פטור *patter* on שחיטה *Shechita* outside.
אלא *Ela*, so the only thing he logically can be saying is,
and this we said when we read the משנה mishna, *Mishnah*, the
following: כי היכי דבחוץ מחייב *ki haichei d'bechutz mechayev*, the same way
when you start with שחיטה *Shechita* outside you're חייב chayav *chayav*, בפנים
bifnim, נמי מחייב *bifnim nami mechayev*. So when you start with שחיטה
*Shechita* inside you're חייב chayav. *chayav*. That exactly fits his language. Whatever
you're חייב chayav, *chayav* on outside, you're חייב chayav *chayav* on inside.
So what's the one case he would be saying? The שחיטה *Shechita*
of a bird that you're חייב chayav *chayav* on outside, you're חייב
chayav *chayav* when you start with a שחיטה *Shechita* inside. That's perfectly
fits those words. But that's exactly what he says I'm not talking
about. הכי קתני חוץ Chutz, מן השוחט בפנים והעלה בחוץ *Hak tani
chutz min hashocheit bifnim v'he'ela bechutz*. Now by the way, the fact
that he says except for this proves that that is what he's
talking about. Meaning it proves that that's what the words mean. If
you're חייב chayav *chayav* you know, if you're חייב chayav *chayav* when
you start outside you're חייב chayav *chayav* when you start inside. It's
just now that you've excluded the one obvious case for that of
שחיטה *Shechita* of a bird, right? The fact that he had to
exclude it shows that that's exactly what he's talking about. Now that
you've excluded that one obvious case of שחיטה *Shechita* of a bird
inside, what case are you talking about that you're חייב chayav, *chayav*
on outside and therefore you're חייב chayav? *chayav* on inside?
So אמר זעירי *amar Zeiri*, says זעירי *Zeiri*, שחיטת בהמה בלילה איכא
בינייהו *shechitas behemah balaylah ika beinaihu*. Okay, there's other cases that he
could be talking about.
Yeah, but they're introducing something that's that's not even being talked about.
So he's kind of going Right! Right, but he's actually saying here
but you could understand. He says here by birds we've got an
exception to some general rule. This is an interesting phenomenon this whole
birds case, but it's a little, you know, reverse of what you
would expect and it's a little bizarre. And I want to point
out that it's an exception to something I I want to tell
you is a general rule by שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz. *shechutei chutz*,
okay? And the general rule by שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz *shechutei chutz*
is, if you're חייב chayav? *chayav* on something when you started it
outside, you're also חייב chayav, *chayav* on it when you started it
inside. What would be an example? שחיטת לילה Layla. *Shechitas laylah*, okay?
והכי קאמר Vehachi ka'amar: *v'hachi ka'amar*, וכן vechein, השוחט בהמה בפנים בלילה
והעלה בחוץ פטור *v'chen hashocheit behemah bifnim balaylah v'he'ela bechutz pattur*. The
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* would maybe implicitly be saying it,
I mean תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* isn't saying it, but if we
were to use the same model of the bird, this is the
conclusion we would get. If you שחט shachat *shechted* inside בלילה *balaylah*
that would be that would and did it outside you'd be פטור
*pattur*. Now that's not so clear because remember when you start something
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*, right? The question of
is it ראוי לפתח אהל מועד ra'uy lepetach ohel mo'ed, *ra'uy l'pesach
ohel mo'ed* is a question about when you said if you put
it on the מזבח mizbe'ach. *Mizbei'ach* אם עלה תרד *im alah teired*
or not. So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* throughout all of this reads that
what they're really debating is whether you say אם עלה תרד *im
alah teired* in these scenarios which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not
saying. But רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is saying that ultimately determines whether you're
חייב chayav בחוץ *chayav bachutz*. How bad of a פסול pasul *psul*
was it? Do you say אם עלה תרד *im alah teired*? But
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not directly addressing that. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says like this, okay? So you started it inside and you
did it and you did and you did it בלילה *balaylah*, that's
פסול pasul *pasul*, you're פטור *patter* outside. שחט בחוץ בלילה והעלה בחוץ
חייב chayav *Shachat bechutz balaylah v'he'ela bechutz chayav*. But if you did
it outside since the same way you've got שחוטי חוץ chutz *shechutei
chutz* you're ignoring, you could also ignore שחוטי לילה Layla *shechutei laylah*.
And for this רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer*, no,
כל שחייבין עליה בחוץ חייבין על כיוצא בו בפנים והעלה בחוץ *kol
she'chayavin aleha bechutz chayavim al kayotzei bo bifnim v'he'ela bechutz*. No, you
know, the general principle is if you'd be חייב chayav. *chayav* on
it outside, the case of לילה *laylah*, שחוטי לילה *shechutei laylah*, you're
חייב Chayav, *chayav* if you started it inside and the bird case
is an exception. Don't use birds as your model. The bird case
is an exception. חוץ מן השוחט העוף בפנים והעלה בחוץ Min hashochait
ha'of bifnim vehe'elah bachutz. *Chutz min hashocheit ha'of bifnim v'he'ela bechutz*. Okay,
so it isn't totally off-topic because the question is and it's not
a bad read at all. The הרב implicitly, the question is, are
you going to use this bird scenario as a model? And implicitly,
the Rabbis maybe are prepared to, and רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying like, look, the bird case is its
own case. But in general, if there's something you're חייב chayav on
when you started outside, you'd be equally חייב chayav on when you
started it inside. Okay, רבא אמר, Rava amar, so now we're going
to have just another example like the case of לילה. קבלה בכלי
חול אית בינייהו. Kabala bichli chol it bainaihu. You didn't use a
כלי שרת kli sharet for the קבלת הדם. kabalas hadam. והכי קאמר:
וכן,
so implicitly the תנא קמא would be saying parallel to the bird
that it would matter whether you started inside or outside. המקבל בכלי
חול בפנים והעלה בחוץ פטור. Hamikabel bichli chol bifnim vehe'elah bachutz patur.
If you did it with a כלי חול kli chol inside, you
would be פטור if you started, ended outside. Again, רש"י Rashi says
כדי שאם עלה תרד, kedei im olah taired, the גמרא isn't saying
that. והמקבל בכלי חול בחוץ והעלה בחוץ חייב. Vehamikabel bichli chol bachutz
vehe'elah bachutz chayav. But if you did it בחוץ, you're חייב chayav.
because of course once you're doing it בחוץ, we ignore those parameters.
You know, it sort of lives within its own little bubble.
Okay. ורבי שמעון אומר לא. VeRabbi Shimon omer lo. כל שחייב עליו
בחוץ חייב על כיוצא בו בפנים. Kol shechayav alav bachutz chayav al
kayotzeh bo bifnim. No, if you're חייב chayav. outside when you started
in a certain way, you're חייב chayav. inside when you started in
the same way. והעלה בחוץ. חוץ, and the one exception is the
bird case, that I'll concede. מן השוחט העוף בפנים והעלה בחוץ. Okay.
השתא דתניא אבוה דשמואל בר רב יצחק: Hashta detanya avua deShmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak: המולק עוף בפנים והעלה בחוץ חייב. hamolik of bifnim vehe'elah
bachutz chayav. He teaches
that
actually they are discussing a bird case. Okay. And he teaches the
following, that we're talking about the following case: you did מליקה בפנים
melika bifnim and then you did it outside, you're חייב, chayav, that
we know. מלק בחוץ והעלה בחוץ פטור. Malak bachutz vehe'elah bachutz patur.
If you did it outside, if you started outside with מליקה, then
you're פטור. ורבי שמעון מחייב. VeRabbi Shimon mechayev. And רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says you're חייב. So the same רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon of
our משנה, mishna. according to אבוה דשמואל, avua deShmuel, is learning it
in the opposite direction. He's saying since מליקה בפנים melika bifnim is
חייב, מליקה בחוץ melika bachutz is also חייב. So not if you're
חייב outside you're חייב when you start inside, but if you're חייב
when you start inside you're חייב when you start outside. מליקה בחוץ
Melika bachutz is going to be חייב. לרבי שמעון. LeRabbi Shimon. Okay.
So now we see that actually according to him at least we
have to like reread a little bit the words of רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon in the משנה. mishna, רבי שמעון התם קאי ותני, Rabbi
Shimon hatam kai vetani, and what you have to reread the words
of רבי שמעון is reverse them, like he meant the mirror image
of what he said. כל שחייב עליו בפנים והעלה בחוץ חייב עליו
בחוץ. Kol shechayav alav bifnim vehe'elah bachutz chayav alav bachutz. If you
start something inside you're חייב, then you're also חייב when you started
it outside by מליקה. Okay, doesn't exactly explain why he said the
חוץ in our משנה, mishna, but anyway that's a different way of
learning, not you learn not if you're חייב outside you're חייב inside
and has to do with לילה and כלי חול kli chol etc.,
but if you're חייב inside are you חייב outside and the question
is מליקה. Okay.
Next משנה, mishna last משנה of the פרק. perek. חטאת שקיבל דמה
בכוס אחד. Chatas shekibel dama bekos echad.
So let's say you caught all the blood of a חטאת chatas
in one cup. They always say cup and I'm always thinking bowl.
Anyway,
I imagine trying to put a cup right there with the blood
squirting out of the cow. Anyway, נתן בחוץ, nasan bachutz, now from
this one bowl, from this one collection of blood, which was all
when it was caught was ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, ra'uy lepetach ohel
mo'ed, you put some of it outside and you did, you know,
זריקה בחוץ. zerika bachutz. וחזר ונתן בפנים. Vechazar venasan bifnim. And then
you used the remainder of the blood inside. בפנים וחזר ונתן בחוץ,
Bifnim vechazar venasan bachutz, or the reverse. Okay, חייב in either case
you're חייב, שכולו ראוי בפנים, shekulo ra'uy bifnim, because when it, because
because it's all fit for פתח אהל מועד. petach ohel mo'ed. If
you started outside, obviously it's ראוי לפתח אהל מועד, ra'uy lepetach ohel
mo'ed. okay, right, because then it's not yet hasn't been thrown. But
why if you were נתן בפנים, nasan bifnim, wait a minute, בפנים
and then you were נתן בחוץ nasan bachutz are you חייב? So
that if you were already נתן בפנים, nasan bifnim, then this should
be like the שירי הדם, shirei hadam, right? So why should you
be חייב? So רש"י says, wait one minute,
וסתמא כרבי נחמיה. vestama k'Rabbi Nechemia. Okay, so רש"י says yeah that
this idea that if you started בפנים and you finish it בחוץ
you're חייב, we're going like רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia who says you're
חייב even for the שירי הדם shirei hadam because you could still
be using it for the spilling of the remainder of the blood.
Okay so that's the first position, okay, the first case, where it's
all in one כוס kos and therefore either way you're חייב and
even if you started בפנים, according to רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, you
ended בחוץ you're going to be חייב.
Now, קיבל דמה בשתי כוסות, kibel dama bishtai kosot, this is the
more interesting case. You caught in two separate vessels. Now, נתן שניהם
בפנים. nasan shenaiahem bifnim. Now you use from both of those vessels
you sprinkle the blood on the מזבח. פטור, obviously you're פטור because
it's not well, the first one is מכפר mechaper and the second
one was meaningless. Okay, right. שניהם בחוץ. Shenaiahem bachutz. Now you went
ahead and you threw from both of these bloods outside. חייב, you're
חייב for each one. Why? Because each one is theoretically ראוי לפתח
אהל מועד. rauy le-pesach ohel moed. If you spilled one of them
you would use the other. So just because you used one to
do this זריקה בחוץ, zerika bachutz, then okay, if the other one
at least in theory, if it hadn't been פסול pasul because of
יוצא, yotzai, could be used בפנים, so therefore you're חייב for each
each, you know, bowl of blood. אחד בפנים ואחד בחוץ. Echad bifnim
ve'echad bachutz. Now let's say one bowl you used inside and one
outside, okay, so פטור. So if you started inside, then you're פטור.
Why? Because the blood in the... The second bowl is not usable
for anything. If you started בפנים, the remainder of the blood in
the first bowl is ראוי rauy for שפיכת הדם, shvichas hadam, okay,
but the second bowl was not part of the זריקה. zrika.
So you can't say that remainder?
No, it's not remainder, it's only the stuff left over from the
כלי שרת, kli shares, you know, it's the remainder of the same
blood that was used in the זריקה. zrika. So since the second
bowl at that stage is דחוי, dichuy, okay, that's what we're going
to sort of say in the גמרא that using one כוס kos
puts דחוי dichuy on the second כוס. kos. So that blood is
now not usable and therefore you're פטור בחוץ. patur bachutz.
אחד בחוץ ואחד בפנים, Echad bachutz ve-echad bifnim, if you started outside
and then did inside, now this is the fascinating case. חייבין על
החיצונה והפנימי מכפר. Chayavin al hachitzonah ve-hapnimis mechaper. Okay. The same blood
of a קרבן, korban, you would think the fact that you used
the blood outside of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash, basically like invalidates
the קרבן, korban, but it doesn't. That was some of the blood.
You used some of it outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash,
okay, it doesn't relate to the other blood you caught in the
other vessel. So this blood when you started outside, had this blood
been inside it could have been used, okay, so it's ראוי לפתח
אהל מועד. rauy le-pesach ohel moed So you're חייב. Now you used
it, but it's like you spilled it. You have blood in a
different vessel. The fact that you spilled one vessel, fine. We could
have used that, we didn't, we spilled it. And now we have
the second one, we're going to use the second one and that
will be מכפר. mechaper. למה הדבר דומה, Lama hadavar domeh, what is
this like?
למפריש חטאתו ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה. Lemafresh chataso ve-avdah ve-hifrish acheres tachteah.
You separated out your חטאת, chatas, it got lost, you separated out
another little sheep.
It should be מתה. meisah.
Right. Well, once you bring one of them, the other one is
מתה. meisah. ונמצאת הראשונה, Venimtzais harishonah, okay, and then you found the
first. והרי שתיהן עומדות Ve-harei shteihen omdos and they're both presenting themselves
like the two cups of blood. They're both presenting themselves. שחט שתיהן
בפנים, Shachat shteihen bifnim, if you slaughtered both of them inside,
פטור, obviously it's not שחוטי חוץ. The first one you שחט you
were יוצא, yotze, the second one you שחט a קרבן korban that
was supposed to be מתה, meisah, so I don't know, maybe it
was like מזיק קדשים, mazik kodshim, well he's going to die anyway,
okay, but זלזול קדשים, zilzul kodshim, who knows what it is, but
it's certainly not a חיוב. chiyuv. Okay. שתיהן בחוץ חייב, Shteihen bachutz
chayav, if you slaughtered both outside, you're חייב. You slaughter the first
one, that's ראוי לקרבן, rauy le-korban, fine, you slaughter it outside. Now
the second one, if the owners would say, "Hey, what are you
doing with my sheep?" and bring it back to the בית המקדש,
right, they would be able to bring it. Just cause you slaughtered
one of them, they can still bring the second. So now when
you slaughter the second, that's also ראוי לפתח אהל מועד rauy le-pesach
ohel moed and you're חייב. אחת בפנים ואחת בחוץ, Achas bifnim ve-achas
bachutz, let's say you did one inside and one outside, פטור, then
you're פטור. Why? Because when you did the one inside, it turns
the second one
into חטאת המתה, chatas hameisah, חטאת שכיפרו בעליה, chatas she-kiperu ba'aleha, so
the same way by the blood, I mean well that's the analogy,
similar to that one, when you do one blood, the other blood
becomes now not usable. When you do one sheep, the other sheep
is not usable as a קרבן korban and therefore you're פטור outside.
אחת בחוץ ואחת בפנים, Achas bachutz ve-achas bifnim, however if you started
outside and you ended inside, so the one you did outside you
were חייב, it was ראוי לפתח אהל מועד when you brought it.
Once it was brought, it doesn't make the other one חטאת המתה.
chatas hameisah. That's like somebody, you know, shot the first one in
the head. Fine. The owners can still bring the second one. Okay.
חייב על החיצונה והפנימית מכפרת Chayav al hachitzonah ve-hapnimis mechaperes and the
second one works. Now the only problem with the analogy is is
that since it's two separate animals, there's no הוה אמינא hava amina
that when you bring a שחוטי חוץ for one it should פסול
the second one, whereas if it's all the blood from the same
קרבן korban you might want to think, even if it's caught in
two separate vessels, you know, you might want to think
that when you bring the blood from the קרבן korban and use
that blood in a זריקת חוץ zrikas chutz ritual, it might פסול
the קרבן. korban. We have no basis to say that. Okay. כשם
שדמה פוטרת בשרה כך היא פוטרת את בשר חברתה. Keshem she-damah poteres
basarah, kach hi poteres es basar chavertah. So this is a little
bit of a cryptic statement, but the basic point is the same
way when you do the blood for the, you know, and you
throw the blood, it basically means that the meat is no longer
חייב במעילה. chayav be-meilah. So therefore the same is true by its
other one. So what exactly that means, it's very cryptic, we'll leave
unpacking that till tomorrow. Okay, we'll end with here for today. What?
Yep.