Hello today's דף *Daf* is מ"ה *Mem Hey*, 45. We pick up
on the משנה mishna *Mishna* and we're still obviously somewhat dealing with
issues of פיגול piggul *Pigul*, but we're actually having an interesting pivot
right now, so we're broadening it to the other things. נותר notar
*Nosar*, טמא tamei, *Tamei*, and actually the focus here is on the
same way the last משנה mishna. *Mishna* about פיגול piggul *Pigul*, the
focus was on what are the types of קרבנות korbanos *Korbanot* to
which פיגול pigul, *Pigul* applies, here it's a similar question about a
specific type of קרבן korban *Korban*, a fascinating type of קרבן korban,
*Korban*, and whether certain הלכה Halacha *Halacha* apply to it. So let's
take a look. משנה mishna. *Mishna* says as following: קדשי עובדי כוכבים
Ovdei kochavim *Kodshei Ovdei Kochavim*, a non-Jew sanctifies an animal, wants to
bring a קרבן korban *Korban*, okay, and we know and we have
a principle that we accept קרבנות korbanos. *Korbanot* of non-Jews in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. So what is their status? Do
they have a full status of a קרבן korban. *Korban*? I mean
on the one hand if you're going to bring it on the
מזבח mizbei'ach *Mizbe'ach*, you know, then you should then you would think
that you would have to look at this thing as fully sanctified,
fully appropriate for the מזבח Mizbeach *Mizbe'ach*. All right, so what's the
story? So the משנה mishna *Mishna* says אין חייבין עליהן משום פיגול
pigul, נותר notar וטמא *Ein Chayavin Aleihen Mishum Pigul Nosar VeTamei*. So
something about them is, you know, which one wonders must presumably speak
to the question of their קדושה Kedushah, *Kedusha*, their sanctity, but who
knows, maybe it's seen as some technical point, that if the כהן
*Kohen* has a פיגול pigul, *Pigul* thought, if the meat is left
over נותר nosar *Nosar*, if the person is טמא tamei. *Tamei* and
eats it or the meat is טמא tamei *Tamei*, anyway you do
not transgress those prohibitions. So it's acceptable as a קרבן korban *Korban*
to be brought, but these types of prohibitions will not be transgressed
if these things happen. והשוחט בחוץ פטור
*VeHaShochet BaChutz Patur*, and similarly if somebody brings them outside the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*, they're exempt. So one gets a sense
according to the דברי רבי שמעון Divrei Rabbi Shimon. *Divrei Rabbi Shimon*,
the words of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon*. So one gets
a sense according to this approach that, excuse me, that like
okay there's like a concession. We can accept the קרבנות korbanos? *Korbanot*
of a non-Jew here, you know we really, they really don't belong
here so much but obviously you want the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beit HaMikdash*, I mean it's an interesting question, ביתי ביתי יקרא לכל
העמים *Beiti Beiti Yikarei LeChol HaAmim*, you know, but certainly in the
time when it was around it was like and you know I
mean I wonder how many סתם *Stam* non-Jews sent, we certainly have
stories about like the Roman government sending, you know, and the authorities
wanting to know that in your temple you're bringing their sacrifices and
you're recognizing their power etc. So one wonders how much this is
being conceived of as a type of a, you know, an allowance.
We permit it. Yeah, I mean obviously look everybody agrees to the
דרשה drasha *Drasha* that we accept קרבנות korbanos. *Korbanot* of non-Jews, but
I think the question is how do you understand what that, you
know, nobody is framing it as like some רבני *Rabbinic* thing like
something is really being violated, everybody understands that that's allowed according to
the תורה *Torah*, but the question is sort of like הותרה hutrah
*Hutra* versus דחויה *Dechuya* type of like how much is the תורה
*Torah* giving allowance for this or how much is like fundamentally, anyway
you know that's one way of thinking about it, to what degree
we're thinking that the קרבנות korbanos. *Korbanot* really belong here.
And that fits with also the idea about חייב hayav *Chayav* when
you שחט *Shecht* it outside of חוץ *Chutz* because חוץ *Chutz* you're
only חייב hayav *Chayav* for something that really belongs inside the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. So one way of framing it is
how much does a קרבן korban *Korban* of a non-Jew belong in
our בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash*, you know which is how
we relate to God, which is not saying about how a non-Jew
can relate to God but it's a question about like how much
it belongs you know here, right. This is our, this is the
Jewish temple. The other question way to raise it is the idea
of קדושה Kedushah *Kedusha*, right, how much if the way in which
you sanctify an animal you know is a halachic construct, right, so
I mean there's just the reality of human experience, קין והבל *Kayin
VeHevel* bring sacrifices, you know wonderful, but to think about the animal
as something sanctified with all of these statuses that apply to it,
מעילה meilah. *Me'ilah* which we didn't mention, פיגול pigul *Pigul* etc. etc.,
right, so that's not just the human experience of bringing a sacrifice,
that's its status. And since all that status is sort of defined
according to הלכה *Halacha* from within the Jewish context, so you know
how obvious is it that a non-Jew can create that status of
קדושה Kedushah *Kedusha* that has all of those types
of you know of consequences. Okay, so again I would not want
to say it like oh Jews are holy non-Jews aren't holy, therefore
whatever, no, but it's like this is a halachic, you know a
halachic status, and how much can it be created by somebody outside.
Now one could actually ask a fascinating question which I do not
think is being asked here
but just occurs to me which is let's say I can normally,
here I am I'm a wealthy farmer and my good friend David
here feels terrible because he's never had a chance to bring, he
rarely has a chance to bring a קרבן korban. *Korban* to the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, so I'm going to be מקדיש
makdish *Makdish* my sheep as an עולה Olah, *Olah* for David and
now David will be able to bring it to the בית המקדש
Beit Hamikdash? *Beit HaMikdash*. So let's say I want to do the
same thing with my friend Christopher. I'm מקדיש it, so it has
a Jew is did the הקדשה, hakdasha, but it's a non-Jew's קרבן
korban. and the non-Jew's bringing it. Would that say that these statuses
don't apply or they do apply because I was מקדיש it? So
it's an interesting way of thinking of exactly what the nature of
the problem is. Anyway. So that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon. says all these statuses do not apply. All right. And
רבי יוסי מחייב. Rabbi Yose mechayev. But רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says
no they have the full status. I am really sorry I thought
my voice was going to be back enough for me to give,
but I didn't know till I woke up this morning. Hold on.
I don't know if sucking candies help but they just taste good.
Anyway. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. קדשי עובדי כוכבים לא נהנין ולא
מועלין. Kadshei ovdei kochavim lo nehenin velo moalin.
So here we have a ברייתא, braisa, a תוספתא, Tosefta, and
this is just basically the same thing in our משנה mishna except
it's a little bit more expanded. So it starts with the position
of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon So there's no prohibition, you are not
allowed to get הנאה hana'ah but you don't actually transgress מעילה. meilah.
ואין חייבין עליהם משום פגול נותר וטמא. Ve'ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul
nosar vetamei. You don't have those transgressions if there was a פגול
pigul thought, it was left over, it became טמא, Tamei, you're טמא.
Tamei, ואין עושין
תמורה.
Ve'ein osin temurah.
Something not mentioned in the משנה. If it's sanctified and you try
to exchange it with another animal, תמורה, temurah,
it doesn't become the other animal doesn't become sanctified. ואין מביאין נסכים.
Ve'ein mevi'in nesachim.
We also do not let non-Jews bring נסכים nesachim by themselves. אבל
קרבנם טעון נסכים. Aval korbanam ta'un nesachim. דברי רבי שמעון. Divrei Rabbi
Shimon.
But when we bring their קרבן, Korban the קרבן Korban itself has
to be brought with נסכים nesachim like a Jewish קרבן. Korban
So if they send an animal and they sent money for the
נסכים, nesachim, for the wine and the flour and the oil, we
bring it. If they didn't send money, we provide it with public
funds. But the basic point is any קרבן Korban, that's brought on
the מזבח Mizbeach that's like not a חטאת chatas basically, we bring
with נסכים nesachim and it doesn't matter whose קרבן Korban it is.
What we don't allow them to do is bring נסכים nesachim separate
from a קרבן. Korban Okay.
And this is all going to be linked to verses. I mean
I can't think of any once we start making distinctions, if it's
a general principle this רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. holds it has none
of the full status and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose has it all
the full status, you can try to sort of give some broader
framing of how do you think of קרבנות korbanos of non-Jews. Some
of these distinctions is harder to understand exactly and in the end
the גמרא's Gemara going to link them to פסוקים. pesukim. דברי רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. The word of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon
אמר רבי יוסי. Amar Rabbi Yose. Said רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose. רוני
בכולם להחמיר. Roni bechulam
lehachmir.
To
me
it seems that all of these I would rule strictly that all
of these statuses do apply. שנאמר בהן לה'. Shene'emar bahen Lashem.
It says לה'. Lashem. Now where does it say לה'? Lashem? So
רש"י Rashi quotes the פסוק pasuk
and this is quite ironic from the that the דרשה drasha I
mentioned before the דרשה drasha that non-Jews could bring קרבנות. Korbanot.
Where's the דרשה drashah that non-Jews could bring קרבנות? Korbanot. So it's
from the following פסוק. pasuk. This probably would have been the last
פסוק pasuk you would have thought to say that non-Jews could bring
קרבנות. Korbanot It says... Right. דבר
אל אהרן
ואל בניו ואל
כל בני ישראל ואמרת אליהם.
Daber el Aharon ve'el banav ve'el kol
bnei Yisrael ve'amarta aleihem. איש איש מבית ישראל ומן הגר בישראל אשר
יקריב קרבנו לכל נדריהם ולכל נדבותם אשר יקריבו לה' לעולה.
Ish ish mibeis Yisrael umin hager beYisrael asher
yakriv korbano lechol nidreihem ulechol nidvosam asher yakrivu Lashem le'olah.
Any person from the Jew from from the Israelites or from the
sojourner or the convert of the Israelites. Oh well, it says Israelite
and Israelite but it does say איש איש ish ish any person.
So איש איש ish ish means even a non-Jew. So that's quite
ironic.
The end of that פסוק pasuk is אשר יקריבו לה'. asher yakrivu
Lashem.
So איש איש ish ish tells you non-Jews can bring a נדר
neder or can bring a free will sacrifice obviously not an obligatory
one. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says here בכולן אני רואה בהן
להחמיר שנאמר בהן לה'. Bechulan ani ro'eh bahen lehachmir shene'emar bahen Lashem.
אשר יקריבו לה'. Asher yakrivu Lashem.
Once we can agree that they're being included by the פסוק pasuk
of אשר יקריבו asher yakrivu that איש איש ish ish is לרבות
lerabos non-Jews,
so then if it says that it's לה' Lashem it means that
it's fully sanctified. And if it's fully sanctified then it should have
all these statuses. Okay, how can you how can you argue that
it shouldn't have a full status? Now במה דברים אמורים בקדשי מזבח.
Bameh devarim amorim bekadshei mizbei'ach. אבל בקדשי בדק הבית מועלין בהן. Aval
bekadshei bedek habayis moalin bahen.
Now this is true about things that have been sanctified as קרבנות.
Korbanot? But things that have been sanctified to be owned by the
Temple treasury there is מעילה. meilah. Now what does what does that
who is saying this?
It's strange that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is saying this because רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose says I'm strict by all these things and one
of these things was מעילה. meilah So it would seem that רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose would be saying that there would be מעילה Me'ilah,
by קרבנות Korbanot as well. So רש"י... Rashi... reads that this is
going back to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, is
saying by the way even though I said, says רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon that there's no מעילה, Me'ilah I only said there's no מעילה
Me'ilah. by קרבנות. Korbanot But when it comes to something sanctified to
the temple treasury, there I agree that there is מעילה. Me'ilah And
this, by the way, makes a lot of sense, right? Because
this
is a principle that I
keep
coming back to, which is when something is owned by the temple
treasury, it's
there's מעילה Me'ilah because I've transferred my property to the temple.
It's now owned by the temple, so you know, it fully just
belongs to to the בית המקדש and it's type of a stealing
or whatever it is. And the מעילה Me'ilah comes, yes it comes
from the קדושה, kedushah but the קדושה kedushah emerges from ownership.
So if a non-Jew transfers ownership of his car to the בית
המקדש, then they're fully holding the title, then the קדושה comes from
the fact that the בית המקדש holds the title to his car.
And of course there's going to be מעילה Me'ilah. on it. But
if the non-Jew comes and sanctifies his sheep for an עולה, it's
not really that it's the בית המקדש's sheep; it's my sheep that
has this sanctity. So then we can discuss how much sanctity was
I able to imbue it with, right? If I'm from outside the
system, if I'm a non-Jew, how much does it really belong fully
on the מזבח Mizbeach, so that it has that full sanctity? So
that's like a different world, and there you can say if you're
a non-Jew and it's fundamentally not your temple, etc., etc., it doesn't
have you can't give it that full sanctity. But if I just
transfer my property to the בית המקדש, then there ownership makes it
sanctified,
and
therefore there is מעילה. Me'ilah. So even רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon. who
excludes non-Jews, he would not do it, I mean or says it
doesn't have the full status, that's only by קרבנות. Korbanot Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara is going to unpack this. Wow.
I really did not realize
how
bad my voice was going to be.
Okay.
לא נהנין ולא
מועלין. Lo nehenin velo moalin. לא נהנין מדרבנן, Lo nehenin mi-Derabbanan, so
rabbinically you're not allowed to derive הנאה. hana'ah. This is now going
with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. that these קרבנות Korbanot don't have full
status.
ולא מועלין, Velo moalin, but there's no מעילה. Me'ilah, דגמר מעילה חטא
חטא מתרומה De-gamar Me'ilah cheit cheit mi-terumah because the category of מעילה,
Me'ilah. it speaks about חטא cheit and חטא cheit is learned out
from תרומה terumah and תרומה terumah we know only applies to Jews.
דבתרומה כתיב בני ישראל ולא עובדי כוכבים
De-vi-terumah ketiv Bnei Yisrael
velo ovdei kochavim because by תרומה terumah it uses the phrase ולא
ישאו עליו חטא, velo yisu alav cheit, that's the חטא cheit word,
and in תרומה terumah it says ולא יחללו את קדשי בני ישראל.
velo yechalelu et kodshei Bnei Yisrael. Okay, so since by תרומה terumah
it's clearly about בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, here too by מעילה. Me'ilah
That's all this is רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon
ואין חייבין עליו משום
פיגול
נותר וטמא. Ve-ein chayavin alav mishum piggul notar v'tamei. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? דאתי
פיגול עון עון מנותר. De-ati
piggul avon
avon mi-notar. ואתי נותר חילול חילול מטומאה. Ve-ati notar chillul chillul mi-tumah.
So we've seen this before. טומאה Tumah we've already,
and how do you know טומאה tumah is only by the Jewish
קרבנות? Korbanot Because it says בני ישראל ולא עובדי כוכבים. Bnei Yisrael
velo ovdei kochavim. By טומאה tumah it says
וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל. vayinazeru mi-kodshei Bnei Yisrael. Okay, that's the פסוק
pasuk that says be careful when you're טמא Tamei, don't touch it,
separate yourself מקדשי
בני ישראל. mi-kodshei Bnei Yisrael. So תרומה terumah we know is only
by קרבנות Korbanot. of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael,
and once that's about תרומה, terumah, then based on these various גזירות
שוות gezeirot shavot we can apply it to
נותר notar, and פיגול pigul, as well. Okay, so all of this
is רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon
We find certain things that say explicitly בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and
then we link them to these other things. Okay, so תרומה terumah
says בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, so similarly מעילה is only בני ישראל.
Bnei Yisrael. טומאה Tumah says בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, so similarly נותר
notar, and פיגול pigul is also only בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael.
Yes. Sort of ironic because we're דרשן-ing darshan these verses to say
they're excluded, but we דרשן-ed darshan the verse before to say that
they could bring them.
Right, so that's the way he reads it. איש איש Ish ish
comes
to tell you,
I mean even the initial דרשה drasha. is ironic. It says איש
איש מבית ישראל ish ish mi-beit Yisrael and איש איש ish ish
includes non-Jews. So that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon approach. Fine, they're included,
but included sort of like a סוג ב' sug bet because I
have all this other stuff that says בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So
I'm not going to just say, oh, we erase all the distinctions,
right? We'll include them but with distinctions. That's exactly it. Okay.
ואין עושין תמורה, Ve-ein osin temurah, you can't make a תמורה temurah
with their קרבן. Korban Again, you're not supposed to be making תמורות,
temurot, but it doesn't work.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דאיתקש תמורה למעשר בהמה De-itkash temurah le-maaser behema
because in the פרשה parsha of תמורה temurah it starts with talking
about מעשר בהמה. maaser behema. ומעשר בהמה איתקש למעשר דגן U-maaser behema
itkash le-maaser dagan and the, you know, and the מעשר בהמה maaser
behema it says
עשר תעשר aser te-aser and the גמרא Gemara says that that means
both מעשר בהמה maaser behema and מעשר דגן, maaser dagan, the מעשר
maaser of the grain, not that and the מעשר maaser of the
flock. במעשר דגן כתיב בני ישראל Bi-maaser dagan ketiv Bnei Yisrael
and since we've got בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael by מעשר דגן, maaser
dagan, okay,
so therefore. It's now going to teach you to מעשר בהמה Maaser
Behema which is going to now teach you to תמורה. Temurah. So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute. אם בלא עובדי כוכבים. Im belo
ovdei kochavim.
So the גמרא Gemara says וכי דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש,
Vechi davar halamed be-hekesh chozer u-melamed be-hekesh,
one minute. How can something that's learned out by a היקש hekesh
go back and apply through another היקש? hekesh? Now we sort of
did it before but before we were doing a גזירה שוה. gezeira
shava.
גזירה שוה Gezeira shava apparently if you have a גזירה שוה gezeira
shava link A to B and then B to C you can
do it two steps. But here it's a היקש, hekesh, it's just
עשר תעשר aser te-aser that's talking about מעשר בהמה maaser behema and
מעשר דגן, maaser dagan, so they're like juxtaposed and they're linked to
one another, that's היקש hekesh but it's not a גזירה שוה. gezeira
shava. It's not like the same word allows you to just transport
everything.
So since it's only a היקש, hekesh, are you really allowed to
go ahead and apply, A to B and B to C? Normally
we're only allowed one jump, not two jumps. We just had a
double
though didn't we just...
That's what I said before so you mean עוון עוון avon avon
and
what the גמרא Gemara just said a minute ago, חילול חילול, chilul
chilul, עוון עוון. avon avon. So yes, so that is, so that's
גזירה שוה. gezeira shava.
גזירה שוה Gezeira shava is you have two separate different פרשיות, parshiot,
right? You got נותר notar. and טומאה tumah and one of them
says עוון avon and one of them says עוון avon and the
keyword sort of lets you link everything. Okay, that's actually, we might
think that's weaker but because of the power of גזירה שוה gezeira
shava that you're allowed to do and you're allowed to keep on
then going and do multiple steps.
You're linking A to C...
well A to B and then B to C but you do
it through גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, through keywords. When you do it
through keywords you're allowed. When you do it through a היקש, hekesh,
a היקש hekesh comes by, היקש hekesh is by a more
a natural relationship that exists in the פסוקים. psukim. It's not this
magic.
So when it says עשר תעשר aser te-aser take מעשר maaser and
we say that means מעשר בהמה maaser behema and מעשר דגן, maaser
dagan, that's a היקש. hekesh. They're just being packaged together in the
פסוקים. psukim. When it talks about תמורה temurah and it starts by
talking about מעשר בהמה maaser behema and then it talks about תמורה,
temurah, they're just being packaged together and that's a היקש. hekesh. So
for us it seems more natural but for whatever reason גזירה שוה
gezeira shava has this power when they're separate and they're keywords that
you're allowed to go A to B and B to C,
whereas היקש hekesh you can't go A to B and B to
C when it's just a question about like how they're naturally packaged
together.
It's more thematic connections as opposed to a word specifically.
Exactly. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says וכי דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר
ומלמד בהיקש?
vechi davar halamed be-hekesh
chozer u-melamed be-hekesh? The גמרא Gemara says yes, מעשר דגן חולין הוא.
maaser dagan chullin hu. That idea that you can't go A to
B and B to C when you're dealing with a היקש hekesh
is only by קדשים. kodshim. But when you're dealing with חולין chullin
you're allowed to do those A to B and B to C.
There are more limits by what you can do by קדשים. kodshim.
So, so the גמרא Gemara says so since we start with מעשר
maaser of grain, that's where it says בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael and
that goes to מעשר בהמה maaser behema and that goes to תמורה.
temurah. Since the initial starting point is non-קדשים kodshim you're allowed to
do A to B and B to C.
So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר בתר מלמד אזלינן. hanicha
le-man d'amar batar melamed azinan. That's good if you go by the
thing that does the teaching, by the original source. It's by מעשר
דגן maaser dagan where it says בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, so that
teaches that these other things require בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. אלא למאן
דאמר בתר למד אזלינן, Ella le-man d'amar batar lamed azinan, but if
you go by the thing that's learning, so since the thing you're
applying it to is קדשים, kodshim, therefore according to this approach, since
you're applying it to קדשים kodshim you're not allowed to do A
to B and B to C. So if we have a rule
about you're allowed to do double jumps by חולין chullin but not
by קדשים, kodshim, how do you define whether? Because a double jump
involves three objects. How do you decide whether it's קדשים kodshim or
חולין? chullin? Do you go by the initial thing or do you
go by the applications? So if you go by the applications and
it's קדשים kodshim we're still stuck.
So the גמרא Gemara says how are you allowed to do this
double jump? אלא מעשר בהמה חובה שאין קבוע לה זמן. Ella maaser
behema chovah she-ein kavua la-zman. Fine forget מעשר, maaser, or forget that.
We don't need to learn it out from מעשר דגן maaser dagan
where it says בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael.
We can learn it straight from מעשר בהמה. maaser behema. מעשר בהמה
Maaser behema and תמורה temurah are in the same פרשה. parsha. How
do I know non-Jews מעשר בהמה maaser behema does not apply to
non-Jews? Because מעשר בהמה maaser behema is a non-fixed time obligation. And
רש"י Rashi actually says like the opposite of מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמה.
mitzvot asei
she-hazman grama. But רש"י Rashi says that the point really here, it's
funny that it mentions fixed time because it's really not about fixed
time or not fixed time. It's really that non-Jews were only included
in free-will sacrifices נדרים ונדבות. nedarim u-nedavot.
Non-Jews are never included in obligatory sacrifices. So since מעשר בהמה maaser
behema is an obligatory sacrifice, clearly non-Jews are not included.
So we can say that you don't do תמורה temurah because מעשר
בהמה maaser behema and תמורה temurah are connected. Non-Jews aren't in מעשר
בהמה maaser behema by definition because it's obligatory, so therefore they're not
in תמורה. temurah. וחובה שאין לה זמן קבוע ישראל מעשרו עובדי כוכבים
לא מעשרו. ve-chovah she-ein la-zman kavua Yisrael maasiru ovdei kochavim lo maasiru.
It's brought by Jews not by non-Jews. Okay, so what we have
now is... For
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, as was said, איש איש מבית
ישראל *Ish Ish mi-Beis Yisrael* includes non-Jews, but then all these other
areas it says בית ישראל *Beis Yisrael* or בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael.
*Bnei Yisrael* or whatever, and that's going to say so all these,
all these הלכות Halachos *halachos* though, you know, maybe technically you bring
it but all these הלכות halachot. *halachos* don't apply. And so by
מעילה *Meilah* it's because we learn it from תמורה *Temurah*, from תרומה
*Trumah* where it says בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael *Bnei Yisrael*. From פיגול
pigul *Pigul* and נותר notar *Notar* we learn it from טמא Tamei,
*Tamei* where it says וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael. *ve-hinnazru mi-kadshei
Bnei Yisrael*. And from תמורה *Temurah* we learn it from מעשר בהמה
*Maaser Behemah* just by the assumption that מעשר בהמה *Maaser Behemah* because
it's an obligation, clearly non-Jews are excluded. All right. ואין מביאים נסכים
*Ve-ein
mevi'im nesachim*, so their קרבנות korbanot. *korbanos* come with נסכים *nesachim*, okay,
because that's a דין *din* in the קרבן Korban *korban*. Because it
says
but
they don't donate נסכים *nesachim* separately. תנו רבנן *Tana Rabbanan*, אזרח *Ezrach*,
this is by the פרשה *parsha* where it speaks about, about the
נסכים *nesachim*, במדבר ט"ו *Bamidbar Tet-Vav*, here I'll read it to you.
פנחס
*Pinchas*, right? No,
no, no, not פנחס *Pinchas*. שלח
*Shlach*, right, it's right after the חטא המרגלים *chet hamiraglim*. כי תבאו
אל ארץ משבתיכם
אשר אני נתן לכם *Ki tavo'u el eretz moshvoteichem
asher ani noten lachem* ועשיתם אשה לה' עלה או זבח לפלא נדר
או בנדבה *va'asitem isheh la-Hashem olah o zavach li-nedor o bi-nedavah* etc.
etc. Okay, and then it goes through the whole thing about what
you bring,
about the different נסכים *nesachim*. וכי יגור אתכם גר או אשר בתוככם
לדרתיכם ועשה אשה ריח ניחח לה' כאשר תעשו כן יעשה *Ve-chi yagur
itchem ger o asher betochechem ledoroteichem va'asah isheh reach nichoach la-Hashem ka'asher
ta'asu ken ya'aseh*. הקהל חקה אחת לכם ולגר הגר חקת עולם לדרתיכם
ככם כגר *Hakkahal chukkah achat lachem velagger haggar chukkat olam ledoroteichem kachem
kagger*. תורה אחת ומשפט אחד יהיה לכם ולגר הגר *Torah achat umishpat
echad yihyeh lachem velagger haggar*... oh where's אזרח *Ezrach*? Oh, right before
that. כל האזרח יעשה ככה את אלה להקריב אשה ריח ניחח לה'
*Kol ha-ezrach ya'aseh kachah et elleh le-hakriv isheh reach nichoach la-Hashem*. So
it says אזרח *Ezrach*, you, the גר *ger*, so all those things
are אזרח *Ezrach*, you and the גר *ger*, it seems to be,
but not the non-Jew. Okay. So, תנו רבנן *Tana Rabbanan*, אזרח *Ezrach*,
אזרח מביא נסכים ואין עובד
כוכבים מביא נסכים *Ezrach mevi nesachim ve-ein oved kokhavim mevi nesachim*.
Now that means now we're reading that to mean by itself. יכול
לא תהא עולתו טעונה נסכים תלמוד לומר ככה *Yakhol lo te'eh olato
te'unah nesachim, talmud lomar kachah*. Maybe though that means that even when
he brings a קרבן Korban? *korban*, the קרבן Korban *korban* itself, not
that he's bringing the נסכים *nesachim*, but the קרבן korban *korban* itself
comes naked, comes without the נסכים *nesachim*? No, it says ככה *kachah*.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that ככה *kachah* is for like, you know,
ככה יעשה לפר האחד *kachah ye'aseh lapar ha-echad* o etc. Meaning no,
ככה *kachah* is telling you a קרבן korban *korban* has to have
נסכים *nesachim*. A non-Jew doesn't bring it as a separate thing, but
if he's bringing a קרבן korban *korban*, the קרבן korban *korban* itself
requires the נסכים *nesachim*.
He cannot bring נסכים *nesachim* as a separate קרבן korban, *korban*. If
he brings an animal קרבן korban *korban*, then he, then it has
to have נסכים *nesachim* coming with it. Either he's going to pay
for it or we're going to pay for it, but it has
to have נסכים *nesachim* coming with it.
All right. Okay, אמר
רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yosi, *Amar Rabbi Yose*,
רואה
אני את כולן להחמיר *ra'ani et
hakullan le-hachmir*. במה דברים אמורים B'meh devarim amurim בקדשי
מזבח Mizbeach. *Be-meh devarim amurim bekadshei mizbe'ach*.
Now again, this is a little vague, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads
this to be going back to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just completely jumps over רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi, *Rabbi Yose*, it's quite fascinating. But רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rabbi
Yose* says I give them full status. Okay, you give them full
status, that's fine. You know, well,
apparently you start with the idea that if we say, you know,
איש איש *Ish Ish* including non-Jews, so if it's including non-Jews, it's
including it across the board, he doesn't have to make all these
other דרשות *drashos*. I mean, his is a simple thing, if you're
going to include them, you're going to include them.
So, it jumps to this distinction which רש"י Rashi. *Rashi* says is
going according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*. That when רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon* says that there's no מעילה *Meilah*, it's
only no מעילה *Meilah* by קדשי מזבח mizbeiach *kadshei mizbe'ach*. But קדשי
בדק הבית *kadshei bedek habayis* there is מעילה *Meilah*. So let's see
why. I already sort of explained that, but let's see. מאי טעמא
*Mai ta'ama*? קסבר כי גמר מעילה חטא חטא מתרומה דומיא דתרומה דקדיש
קדושת הגוף *Kasavar ki gamar Meilah chet chet mitrumah dumya de-trumah dekadish
kedushas haguf*. Because remember, it's from תרומה *trumah* that we learned that
only בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael. *Bnei Yisrael*, that only something that is,
you know,
sanctified by בני ישראל *Bnei Yisrael* like תרומה *trumah* has מעילה *Meilah*.
But that's true when we're comparing it to something that's like תרומה
*trumah*, like a קרבן korban *korban* that has an interior sanctity, a
קדושת הגוף *kedushas haguf*, like it's sanctified for a purpose. It's not
about its ownership, it's about what sort of status and purpose you've
given it. You know, so that type of a thing, like תרומה
*trumah* is eaten by כהנים kohanim *Kohanim*, קרבנות *korbanos* goes on the
מזבח mizbeiach *mizbe'ach*, it sort of, you know, defines its entire identity
and status and so on. So that type of a thing, that's
where מעילה *Meilah* is limited to sanctified by Jews according to רבי
שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*. אבל קדושת בדק הבית קדושת דמים לא *Aval kedushas
bedek habayis kedushas damim lo*. But קדושה *kedushah* of the temple, of
the temple, which is a question about monetary ownership, right? So that,
that's not limited to only Jews. That basically is by dint of
the fact that the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* owns it. So once
you've transferred ownership to the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, they own it.
So their ownership gives it קדושה *kedushah*, and therefore it doesn't matter
how they got ownership over it. תנו רבנן *Tana Rabbanan*, דם dam
שנטמא *Dam shenitma*. So now we'd so דם dam שנטמא וזרקו בשוגג
הורצה, במזיד לא הורצה. So if you have blood that became טמא,
tamei, so you're not supposed to you're supposed to stop there but
if you went ahead and you put it on the altar, the
קרבן korban, is good,
because that's the idea of רצוי ציץ, Ritzuy Tzitz, that the ציץ
Tzitz makes it acceptable even though the Torah says that the ציץ
Tzitz is מטומאות בני ישראל, mi'tumot Bnei Yisrael, so
even though the blood is טמא, tamei it makes it acceptable. However,
if it was knowingly put on the מזבח mizbeiach? when it was
טמא, tamei the ציץ Tzitz does not make it acceptable. Now the
גמרא Gemara says that this is not really the הלכה in the
sense of it's not the power of the ציץ Tzitz really is
that it actually would make the קרבן korban acceptable even if it
was knowingly put בטומאה B'tumah on the מזבח, mizbeiach, but the חזל
Chazal said that we cannot allow that, you know as a קנס
Knas we're not going to let that work. So רשי Rashi explains
what that קנס Knas means. That's not going to mean that you're
going to have to bring another קרבן korban because then it's going
to be a חולין בעזרה Chulin Ba'azarah consideration if it really did
work. But what it's going to mean is we're not going to
let you eat the meat. Okay, you got it? So the blood
is
טמא, tamei,
don't put it on the מזבח. mizbe'ach, If you do, the ציץ
Tzitz is מרצה. Meratze. If you do it knowingly, then
מעיקר הדין M'ikar Hadin the ציץ Tzitz is מרצה Meratze and you
don't have to bring another קרבן, korban. but we're going to say
you're not allowed to eat the meat because מדרבנן Mid'rabbanan we're going
to say it doesn't work. Now במה דברים אמורים when is this
true ביחיד B'yachid by an individual. אבל בציבור Aval b'tzibur by a
community בין בשוגג בין במזיד הורצה, Bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid hurtza, whether
it is knowing or unknowing we're going to say it works. ובעובדי
כוכבים Uve'ovdei kochavim and this is why we're bringing it in because
it's another question about Jew non-Jew distinction, if it's a קרבן of
a non-Jew בין בשוגג בין במזיד לא הורצה, Bein b'shogeg bein b'meizid
lo hurtza, it doesn't work. Now why is that? Is that rabbinic,
is that דאורייתא, D'oraysa, why is that? So אמרו רבנן קמי דרב
פפא, Amru rabbanan kamei d'Rav Pappa, the Rabbis said this before רב
פפא, Rav Pappa, כמאן דלא כרבי יוסי. K'man d'lo k'Rabbi Yosi. This
is going against רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi right, this maybe fits with
רבי שמעון who basically says all these הלכות don't apply to it,
so presumably he would also say the ציץ Tzitz doesn't apply to
it. But according to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, דרבי יוסי האמר בחולין
אני מורה להחמיר, D'Rabbi Yosi ha'amar b'chulin ani moreh l'hachmir, רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yossi says that a קרבן of a non-Jew has full status.
So full status, the רצוי ציץ Ritzuy Tzitz should work. Of course,
the irony is that this isn't a חומרא, Chumra, this is a
קולא, Kula, but the point is that we assume that what רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yossi means is it has full status. So אמר להו
רב פפא, Amar lehu Rav Pappa, so רב פפא Rav Pappa said
to them, אפילו תימא רבי יוסי, Afilu teima Rabbi Yosi, even רבי
יוסי, שאני התם דאמר קרא להם. Shani hasam d'amar kra lahem. It
says לרצון להם לפני ה L'ratzon lahem lifnei Hashem that the ציץ
Tzitz is to be מרצה Meratze for them, for בני ישראל. That
it works because of the unique relationship that בני ישראל have with
God and that's the whole idea of the ציץ Tzitz etc. to
express that, so it only works for the קרבנות of בני ישראל.
So אלא מעתה, Ela me'ata, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this:
להם ולא לעובדי כוכבים. Lahem v'lo l'ovdei kochavim. אמר ליה רב הונא
בריה דרב נתן לרב פפא Amar lei Rav Huna brei d'Rav Nosson
l'Rav Pappa אלא מעתה Ela me'ata אשר הם מקדישים לי, Asher hem
makdishim li, the פסוק Pasuk that we know that non-Jews bring sacrifices
is it says איש איש מבית ישראל ומן הגר בארץ
ישראל Ish ish mibeis Yisrael umin hager b'eretz Yisrael whatever אשר יקריב
קרבנו אשר הם מקדישים לי אני ה. Asher yakriv korbano asher hem
makdishim li ani Hashem. So
that פסוק Pasuk therefore that very פסוק Pasuk says הם מקדישים לי.
Hem makdishim li. So why don't we similarly exclude non-Jews? If הם
Hem excludes non-Jews, that's the whole פסוק Pasuk that we learn out
that non-Jews bring קרבנות from. הכא נמי
הם ולא עובדי כוכבים?
Hacha nami hem v'lo ovdei kochavim?
So you can't just say the word הם Hem has the power
of excluding non-Jews because that's in the פסוק Pasuk where we include
non-Jews. אלא אמר רב אשי אמר קרא לרצון להם, Ela amar Rav
Ashi amar kra l'ratzon lahem,
yes we are going to base it on the verse לרצון להם,
L'ratzon lahem, but here's the point. Now this is very of course
up until now I've been managing to keep this whole thing very
neutral in terms of attitude towards non-Jews, but here anyway ועובדי כוכבים
לאו בני הרצאה נינהו. V'ovdei kochavim lav bnei hartzah ninhu. So עובדי
כוכבים are not
בני הרצאה. Bnei hartzah. So what does that mean? Like רצוי Ritzuy
means that the קרבן is accepted לרצון. L'ratzon. Does that mean that
we think that when a non-Jew brings a קרבן in the בית
המקדש it doesn't like he doesn't develop it's not God doesn't desire
the קרבן? You know, so if you take I mean here's what
רשי says, בני הרצאה להקדוש ברוך הוא הם שאינו מתרצה להם. Bnei
hartzah l'Hakadosh Baruch Hu heim she'eino mitratzeh lahem. Like God will tolerate
their קרבנות but it really does not you know it's really not
something that cultivates that relationship, you know, desired by God. So since
it's a concept of here of לרצון, L'ratzon, so that's a concept
only שייך Shayach for בני ישראל. You know, I'd rather not say
that to read it that way. I think one could also talk
about the fact that the whole idea is you know I mean
if you think about though this isn't the ציץ, Tzitz, this is
the חושן, Choshen, you know, it sort of says ונשא אהרן את
שמות בני ישראל על לבו לפני ה Venasa Aharon et shmot Bnei
Yisrael al libo lifnei Hashem etc. Right? That the point is not
in principle a non-Jew can't pray or bring a קרבן and be
נרצה, Nisratzeh, that would be deeply disturbing, right? I mean you know
נח Noach brings קרבנות and whatever you know everybody brings קרבנות. You
could say well that's before מתן תורה Matan Torah or something but
anyway I would rather say it means that this specific point of
the רצוי ציץ, Ritzuy Tzitz, you know the things that are part
of בגדי כהונה, Bigdei kehunah, we know that בגדי כהונה Bigdei kehunah
are very much
about... So I would rather read it to mean that they're not
included in this רצוי ritzuy that's achieved by the בגדי כהונה, bigdei
kehunah, but the phrase, I do have to admit that the phrase
does seem broader than that. Does your English say anything that makes
it, that addresses this issue, David?
Probably not, if I have the Soloveitchik, he just says a lot.
I'm sure it does. Okay, alright, let's keep on going. I want
to yes, it discusses השם'ס Hashem's not favorably inclined towards idolaters. Yeah,
it makes it about them being idolaters rather than about non-Jews. The
problem is that it's not limited to idolaters, it's always a way
to get out of it, but yeah. Yeah, what were you going
to say Hanan?
Is there some distinction between רבי יוסי and רבי שמעון about like
focusing on the animal like and the חפצא chepza and גברא gavra
or something like that? Like רבי שמעון is focusing on the person
who is bringing it or offering it and רבי יוסי is maybe
just focusing on its the animal itself?
Yes, I
think I think that is true. I think that if you want
to say
that we're not going to make distinction, one way of saying it
is, and that's an excellent point, I think I was mentioning before
now that I was reading this academic book called Blood For Thought
that deals with sort of how חז"ל, Chazal, you know, focused on
what they focused on, what they didn't focus on in terms of
the קרבנות. And the point that the author makes is that she
says that you know, classic קרבן in the narratives in the Torah
is basically about I'm bringing and God is accepting. Okay, but in
ויקרא, Vayikra, it focuses on what the כהנים kohanim doing and she
says even more so in the גמרא, Gemara. it basically like it
ignores the offerer, it ignores God, and it totally focuses on like
just the כהנים kohanim and did they do the technical activity correct.
So you're right that, you know, to the way to exclude, I
mean I was maybe automatically interpreting it via the קרבן and saying
if you're non-Jew can you create the same level of sanctity, if
you're non-Jew does your קרבן fully belong in our בית המקדש? So
I was sort of focusing it more on like the קרבן of
a non-Jew. Is it fully sanctified? Does it fully belong here? But
what you're saying could be more correct, that what רבי שמעון is
saying is, I'm not talking about the קדושה being problematic somehow, I'm
talking about the person behind the animal, right? And to what degree
does that person, you know, belong sort of here or not, or
you know, if you focused on the offerer, right, so then it
could actually be more of a reason to say there are separate
הלכות. Whereas if you focus on the קרבן, like the קרבן at
all looks the same, we're just going to focus on the קרבן
here. It could be, it could be. But you know at the
end of the day things like פיגול, pigul נותר, notar? טמא, tamei
etc. are functions of the קדושה of the קרבן, you know, not
of just the act like of הקרבה. hakravah. So it's an interesting
question. Alright, let's take a look at the משנה. דברים שאין חייבין
עליהם משום פיגול חייבין עליהם משום נותר משום טמא.
Devarim she’ein hayavin aleihem mishum pigul, hayavin aleihem mishum notar
mishum tamei.
So all the things that we've excluded from פיגול, pigul like the
דם dam, and the קומץ kometz because they're a מתיר, mattir, even
though that's an exclusion from פיגול, pigul, if somebody were to eat
the קומץ kometz or the לבונה levonah or something of that nature,
something that's a מתיר mattir after and they were טמא tamei, or
that it had been left over and it was נותר, nosar then
that person would actually transgress those prohibitions. So the idea that פיגול
pigul is excluded from the מתיר, mattir, that's only פיגול, pigul not
these other statuses. חוץ
מן הדם, chutz min hadam, but the blood, which is your classic
מתיר, mattir, that you're not חייב hayav on because of טומאה tumah
and because of what do you call it, of נותר. nosar Why
not? We don't know. We'll see in the גמרא. gemara רבי שמעון
מחייב בדבר שדרכן לאכול. Rabbi Shimon mechayev bedavar shedarkan leechol. Now רבי
שמעון says even when you say so he's not arguing on the
דם dam, thing he's saying let's go back to the previous thing
that טומאה tumah and נותר nosar apply to things
that פיגול pigul don't apply to, so other than דם, what are
the things that פיגול pigul? doesn't apply to? Well you have מנחת
כהנים, Minchat Kohanim, you have קומץ, kometz, but you also have something
like the לבונה levonah and the קטורת. ketoret. So would you say
that basically you're טמא tamei, and you eat the לבונה? levonah? You
eat frankincense. Okay, or you're or the לבונה levonah was left over
and you eat it? So you're going to say you're חייב hayav
because of eating בטומאה, betumah, you're חייב chayav for נותר? nosar רבי
שמעון says no, you're only חייב chayav on something that's edible, not
on something that's not
edible. רבי שמעון מחייב בדבר שדרכו לאכול אבל עצים ולבונה וקטורת אין
חייבין עליהם משום טומאה.
Rabbi Shimon mechayev bedavar shedarko leechol, aval etzim velevonah
veketoret ein hayavin aleihem mishum tumah. Alright? So you got it? So
the basic point of the משנה is we have a couple of
things that פיגול pigul does not apply to. What are the things
that פיגול pigul does not apply to?
We have
all the מתירים, mattirs, קומץ, kometz, but we start with דם, okay,
and then we have, you know, קומץ... kometz... מנחת כוהנים *minchas kohanim*,
מנחת
כוהן משיח *minchas
kohen mashiach*, מנחת כוהן גדול *minchas kohen gadol*.
Okay,
all of those things. Oh, נסכים *nesachim* maybe and whatever are debated.
So all those things. So we're saying, okay, דם *dam* for whatever
reason is excluded, but all these, even though there's no פיגול pigul.
*pigul*, there is טמא tamei *tamei* and there is נותר nosar *nosar*.
And comes along רבי שמעון *Rabbi Shimon* and he says, uh-uh, there
ain't טמא tamei. *tamei* and נותר nosar *nosar* for these two. Okay,
those are not edible. There's only טמא *tamei* and נותר nosar *nosar*
for the rest of the list.
All right, what's the actual case? That the כהן *kohen* had a
פיגול pigul. *pigul* thought about one of those things? Is that?
Yeah. No, he had a פיגול pigul *pigul* thought about the קרבן
*korban* and even though the rest of the קרבן *korban* is פיגול
pigul *pigul*, it doesn't apply like in here, it could be that
the rest of the קרבן *korban* is פיגול pigul. *pigul* if this
is the whole קרבן *korban*. But yeah, he had a פיגול Pigul
*pigul* thought and those things do not become פיגול pigul. *pigul*. Okay.
All right, let's look at the גמרא gemara *Gemara*.
תנו רבנן *tanu rabbanan*. יכול לא
יהיו חייבין משום טומא אלא דבר שיש לו מתירין matirin. בין לאדם
בין למזבח *yachol lo yiheyu chayavin mishum tuma ella davar sheyesh lo
matirin bein leadam bein lemizbeach*. Maybe טומאה tumah, *tuma* the same way
פיגול pigul *pigul* only applies to something that has a מתיר matir
*matir*, maybe טומאה tumah *tuma* should also only apply to something that
has a מתיר matir. *matir*. ודין הוא *vedin hu*, and it's a
קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. ומה פיגול pigul. שהוא בקביעה *uma pigul shehu
bekvia*, פיגול pigul.
*pigul* is something that when you do פיגול pigul *pigul*, you bring
a קרבן חטאת קבועה *korban chatas kavuah*, it's very weighty, a fixed
value חטאת *chatas*. ובידיעה אחת *uvyedia achat*, and you only need to
just be aware of it after you sinned. It's not like you
need to know before and after. This is if you ate פיגול
*pigul*. ולא הותר hutar, מכללו *velo hutar miklalo*, and there's never any
exceptions to it, so even though it's very weighty, אין חייבין עליו
אלא דבר שיש לו מתירין matirin. בין לאדם בין למזבח *ein chayavin
alav ella davar sheyesh lo matirin bein leadam bein lemizbeach*. Nevertheless, it
only applies to something that has a מתיר matir? *matir*, not to,
you know, that has these two components, a מתיר matir *matir* and
something left over.
So if that's true about פיגול *pigul*, so טומאה tumah *tuma*, טומאה
tumah. *tuma* which is much lighter, okay, why is that? Number one,
שהיא בעולה ויורד *shehi beola veyored*, if you're טמא *tamei* and you
eat a קרבן *korban*, you don't bring a fixed value חטאת *chatas*,
it's a variable cost based on your ability to afford it. So
that's lighter. ובשתי
ידיעות *uvishtei yedios*, and to be חייב chayav *chayav* for טומאה tumah
*tuma* you have to know you were טמא *tamei*, forget, eat the
thing, and then know again, so it's harder to be חייב chayav
*chayav* for טומאה tumah *tuma* because you need to know beforehand, forget,
and then realize again. והותרה מכללה *vehotra miklala*, and also when like
טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutrah b'tzibur. *tuma hutra betzibur*. Now, although that's
when the, so therefore,
given that that's true, okay, that there's these exceptions, so טומאה tumah.
*tuma*'s lighter. So אינו דין שאינו חייב chayav אלא דבר שיש לו
מתירין בין לאדם בין למזבח *eino din sheaino chayav ella davar sheyesh
lo matirin bein leadam bein lemizbeach*? Maybe similarly therefore, if פיגול *pigul*
has such a limited scope and it's weighty, טומאה tumah *tuma* which
is less weighty should certainly have such a limited scope. תלמוד לומר
*talmud lomar*, אשר הם מקדישים asher hem makdishim לי *asher hem makdishim
li*. This is the פרשה *parsha* by טומאה tumah. *tuma*. וינזרו מקדשי
בני ישראל אשר הם מקדישים לי *veyinazru mikodeshei bnei yisrael asher hem
makdishim li*. Separate yourself, you know, from the קדשים *kodashim* that they
sanctify to me and don't encounter them when you're טמא *tamei*. So
that, so therefore, אשר הם מקדישים *asher hem makdishim* is coming to
include anything that they sanctify. So logically you would have said that
טומאה tumah *tuma* has the same scope of פיגול *pigul*, it's even
lighter than פיגול *pigul*, so certainly it shouldn't be broader, but אשר
הם מקדישים *asher hem makdishim* comes to tell me no, it has
a broader thing. Anything that's sanctified to me, the prohibition of being
טמא *tamei* and eating it applies. יכול מיד yachol miyad
*yachol miyad*, maybe it would apply as soon as you sanctify it.
When at what stage if I eat it when I'm טמא *tamei*
am I חייב כרת chayav kares *chayav kares*? So it's not the
moment that it's sanctified. Okay. Now if you think about an animal,
I'm not going to chop into a live leg of an animal.
But if you think about a מנחה mincha *mincha*, I mix the
flour and the oil or whatever and I sanctify it. So right
now I'm at home, I sanctified it, I mixed my flour and
my oil. If I eat it right now and I'm טמא *tamei*,
am I חייב כרת chayav kares, *chayav kares*? Reasonably you might think
yes. So it tells me no. It says, it says, איש איש
מבית ישראל אשר יקרב asher yikrav *ish ish mibeis yisrael asher yikrav*.
I think, what's let me read the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*... ויקרא *Vayikra* 22... Right.
It says, אמור אליהם לדרותיכם כל
איש אשר יקרב asher yikrav מכל זרעכם אל הקדשים el hakodoshim אשר
יקדישו asher yakdishu בני ישראל לה' וטומאתו עליו *emor aleihem ledoroseichem kol
ish asher yikrav mikol zarachem el hakodeshim asher yakdishu bnei yisrael la'Hashem
vetumaso alav*. So when it speaks about, that's not the וינזרו *veyinazru*.
That's the earlier פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. So first it says, the earlier
פסוק *pasuk* says וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל אשר הם מקדישים לי *veyinazru
mikodeshei bnei yisrael asher
hem makdishim li*.
ולא יחללו V'lo yechalelu. את שם קדשי אשר הם מקדישים לי *velo
yechalelu es shem kodshai asher hem makdishim li*. Thank you. Right. Let's
see. Dot dot dot, okay. ולא יחללו V'lo yechalelu *velo yechalelu* whatever.
אשר הם מקדישים לי *asher hem makdishim li*. Okay. אשר הם מקדישים
לי *asher hem makdishim li*. So this is telling me all things
that they sanctify not just these that are פיגול *pigul*. And then
the next פסוק *pasuk* says כל איש אשר יקרב asher yikrav *kol
ish asher yikrav*, אשר יקרב yikrav מכל זרעכם
*asher yikrav mikol zarachem*... אל הקדשים
אשר יקדישו okay אל הקדשים okay ונכרתה. venichretah. Now the problem here
is this gets you כרת kares okay but it says אשר יקרב
and not that you eat. Okay, but we know that you only
חייב כרת chayav kares, if you eat when you're טמא, not if
you just touch it or something. So we're going to read אשר
יקרב not to tell me that the act of touching makes you
חייב chayav? כרת, but אשר יקרב you're only חייב chayav once the
sacrifice is in a state that it's fit, that's like, you know,
fit to be offered, okay.
יכול מיד maybe I'm חייב chayav if I'm טמא and I eat
it as soon as I sanctify it. תלמוד לומר יקרב, talmud lomar
yikrav, okay, only when it's fit to be offered. אמר רבי אלעזר,
amar Rabbi Elazar, so אמר רבי אלעזר amar Rabbi Elazar explains what
this means. וכי יש נוגע שהוא חייב? vechi yesh nogeia shehu chayav?
יקרב can't mean touch. If you touch it and you're טמא, we
never heard that you're חייב chayav כרת, okay.
אלא מה תלמוד לומר יקרב? ela mah talmud lomar yikrav? במוכשר בשר
ליקרב הכתוב מדבר. bemuchshar basar likrav hakatuv midaber. Once the stuff is
fit to be offered, that's when you're חייב if you're טמא, because
then it's ready for the מזבח and you diverted it and you
ate it for yourself, and you ate it בטומאה. betumah. Okay. הכיצד?
ha keitzad? יש
לו מתירים. yesh lo matirim. If there's something that has a מתיר
matir. like the blood, okay,
so then the meat is only fit for human consumption or מזבח
after the blood is put on the altar.
So then משיקרבו מתיריו. misheyikrevu matirav. So when am I חייב if
I'm טמא and I eat the meat? After the blood has been
thrown. Or if I eat the entrails, because then that's when the
thing that I ate was fit for the altar. The blood or
fit for human consumption,
only when that thing is fit am I חייב when I eat
it בטומאה. betumah. All right? So that's that case.
But that's a classic case of a קרבן in the meat and
the entrails, okay? Or if I eat a מנחה mincha and I'm
טמא. If I eat the מנחה mincha before the קומץ kometz was
taken, I do not transgress. If I eat the מנחה mincha after
the קומץ kometz was put on the altar, I do transgress. That's
when the מנחה became fit. That's something that has a מתיר. matir.
דבר שאין לו מתירים, davar she'ein lo matirim, now how about this
type of stuff that doesn't have a מתיר? matir When I eat
the קומץ kometz itself, when am I חייב? When I eat the
לבונה, levonah, the קטורת, ketoret, and the מנחת כהנים, minchat kohanim, מנחת
כהן גדול, minchat kohen gadol, when am I חייב here? Right? Because
this doesn't have an act that makes it fit. So it says,
no, משיקדש בכלי. misheyikdash bekli. No,
it does. Because this מנחת כהנים minchat kohanim for example,
when can it be offered up on the מזבח? After it's put
in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, right? When can these things be
offered? After they're put in a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So the
putting of it in a כלי שרת kli sharet is what makes
them fit to be offered. And therefore I'm חייב when I eat
it בטומאה betumah only when it's fit. So I'm חייב בטומאה, chayav
betumah, it's not limited to
things that are מתירים matirim are not excluded the same way they
are by פיגול, but I'm only חייב when the thing itself is
fit for being offered, fit for being put on the מזבח, fit
for being eaten by כהנים or the owners, only when it's at
that stage of being fit. Which either means the מתיר was done
or it means it was put in a כלי שרת. kli sharet.
All right? Now אשכחן טומאה. ashkachan tumah.
That's true by טומאה, tumah. that that applies to that larger scope.
נותר מנלן? nosar minalan? How do you know נותר notar applies to
a larger scope and even things that are even the things that
are the מתירים? matirim? אתיא חילול חילול מטומאה. atya chilul chilul mitumah.
Again this גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. So now the גמרא Gemara says
one minute though, we got a problem. ולילף עון עון מפיגול? veleilef
avon avon mipigul?
Until now we've been putting everything in the same category. Okay, so
פיגול it says
עון. avon.
טומאה tumah it says
חילול. chilul. Okay. And נותר notar... it says both חילול chilul and
עון. avon. So טומאה tumah we know is a broader scope, right?
That's broad. It applies even to the מתיר. פיגול is narrow. It
does not include the מתיר. So we said that נותר notar is
like טומאה. tumah Why is נותר notar like טומאה tumah. and it's
going to be broad? Because of חילול. chilul. But says wait, we
should make it like פיגול because of the עון. avon. How do
you know which one to link it to, right? Okay. So our
משנה says that נותר notar and טומאה tumah have this broad scope,
but we've only so far shown that that's true by טומאה. tumah
So what lets you put נותר notar with טומאה tumah rather than
putting it with פיגול? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. אשכחן טומאה, ashkachan tumah, נותר מנלן? nosar
minalan? אתיא חילול חילול מטומאה. atya chilul chilul mitumah. So it says
ולילף עון עון מפיגול? veleilef avon avon mipigul? מסתברא מטומאה הוי ליה
למילף mistabra mitumah hava lei lemeilaf שכן גז"ל. sheken gezel.
No, the following ways is it like טומאה. גז"ל gezel is that
it is... now I got to look at רש"י. This is obviously
ראשי תיבות roshei teivot of points of comparison. Okay, נותר notar. and
טומאה are פסול הגוף, psul haguf, they're basically the thing is something
happened to the thing itself, you or to the food, as opposed
to פיגול is a thought. Wait, that's ג. gimel. ז zayin is
that they are... one minute.
זריקת הדם. Zrikat Hadam. Right. שכן גזל. Shechein gezel.
ז Zayin is זריקת הדם. Zrikat Hadam. So פיגול you need זריקת
הדם Zrikat Hadam to make it פיגול. נותר וטומאה notar v'tumah you
don't need זריקת הדם Zrikat Hadam to make it פיגול. Okay. And
the ל, lamed, so רש"י says the ל lamed means חילו חילו,
chillo chillo, the just the דרשה. תוספות Tosafot says the ל lamed
there means
כולו, kulo,
that פיגול is a status that applies to the whole קרבן whereas
נותר וטומאה notar v'tumah could apply to only a part. It's possible
for only a part of the קרבן. Okay, so anyway, there are
these ways that נותר וטומאה notar v'tumah are similar, so we should
learn it from there. So the גמרא says no, there's more ways
in which נותר notar. is similar to פיגול than in which it's
similar to טומאה. So the גמרא says אדרבה מפיגול הוה ליה למילף
שכן נותר. adaraba mipigul havei lei lemeilaf shechein notar. First of all,
הותר, meaning that they're... נותר... notar. טומאה is הותרה when you say
טומאה הותרה בציבור. hutrah b'tzibur. That doesn't apply to נותר and פיגול.
So they're similar to one another that you don't say הותרה בציבור.
ציץ. Tzitz. Neither of them the ציץ tzitz works for. The ציץ
tzitz works for טומאה but it doesn't work for those two. טהור.
Tahor.
Both of them, I guess, apply even if you're טהור, tahor, which
is sort of
self-explanatory. Okay. בזמן. Bizman. Both of them are time-related. פיגול is a
thought about time, נותר is a fact about
time. קרב. Karev. And what's
קרב? karev?
Oh, both of these apply to the object whereas טומאה applies to
the person. Okay. והני נפישן. V'hanei nefishen. So the points of comparison
are greater between נותר and פיגול.
So why don't
we link נותר with פיגול and say it has a narrow
scope? אלא מדאמר לוי. Ela mid'amar Levi. Fine. We get it from
what לוי Levi teaches. דאמר לוי מנין שאף בפסול זמן הכתוב מדבר
תלמוד לומר ולא יחללו. D'amar Levi minayin she'af b'psul zman hakatuv medaber
talmud lomar v'lo yechalelu. Fine. Okay, we're going to go back to
here. ולא יחללו. The double ל lamed tells me a double חילול.
chilul. Right. This is the פסוק by טומאה. ולא יחללו etc. אשר
הם מקדישים is a broad scope. And the double ל lamed tells
two types of חילול. chilul. Not only the חילול chilul of טומאה
but even of נותר. Okay. How do you know that that פסוק
בפסול זמן הכתוב מדבר תלמוד לומר ולא יחללו בשני חילולין הכתוב מדבר
אחד פסול
נותר
ואחד פסול טומאה? pasuk b'psul zman hakatuv medaber talmud lomar v'lo yechalelu
bishnei chilulin hakatuv medaber echad psul notar v'echad psul tumah? Right. We
don't learn it just from the גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah of חילו
חילו chillo chillo because then it would have a competing thing over
in terms of פיגול. We learn it because the פסוק by טומאה
itself has a double ל lamed and that tells us that we
include another thing that's called חילול. chilul. We're also going to include
נותר. Okay, so bottom line is the scope of טומאה is broader
than פיגול. It includes the מתירין. It only applies once the thing
is fit for the מזבח, for the person etc., which is either
the מתיר or כלי שרת. kli sharet. And similarly that's true about
נותר. It has this broader scope. פיגול is the one that has
that very narrow scope and does not apply to the מתירין. Okay.
We will end here. Hopefully my voice will be in better shape
tomorrow.