We should say today because it's יום טוב שני של גלויות Yom
Tov Sheni shel Galuyot or something like that.
No, you shouldn't say הלל Hallel every day. You say the other...
Happy Abe Karas. Anyway, good morning. Today is April 20th, it's the
20th day of the עומר, Omer, it's the 5th of אייר, Iyar,
and today's דף Daf is זבחים דף ז, Zevachim Daf Zayin, and
we're picking up somewhere around the top of דף ז, Daf Zayin,
is that right?
I don't know because we didn't record yesterday.
I didn't record yesterday.
No, no, no, it was pre-recorded. It was pre-recorded.
The end, the end of דף ו, Daf Vav, the end of
דף ו. Daf Vav. I'll try to catch us in. It's kind
of a complex issue at the end here. So if we go
back to the end of דף ו Daf Vav
where
it says,
okay,
we're in the discussion of the two different שעירים se'irim that are
brought on שבועות. Shavuot. There's one שעיר חטאת se'ir chatat which is
brought with the regular קרבן מוסף korban musaf and there's another שעיר
חטאת se'ir chatat or two more? One more, two more? One more,
I think, that's brought with the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. So you
have two different קרבנות חטאת korbanot chatat on שבועות. Shavuot. So the
question was why did you need them? And maybe the reason why
was because you need for כפרה kapparah for the עבירות averot that
happened between the period of הפרשה hafrashah of designating the קרבן korban
and the time of the שחיטה. shechitah.
Okay, so like from a few lines from the bottom of ו
עמוד ב, Vav Amud Bet, דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל קרבנות ציבור
צריכין משכתן למה שהן. de'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel korbanot tzibbur tzrichin
moshachtan lema shehen.
The claim at least is that by קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibbur for
public sacrifices, the act of שחיטה shechitah is actually what finally designates
them to their status, so you wouldn't necessarily make that conclusion that
there would be this kind of lag period between the designation and
the שחיטה. shechitah. אמר ליה רב יוסף בריה דרב שמואל לרב פפא,
Amar leh Rav Yosef breih deRav Shmuel leRav Pappa, ומי אית ליה
לרבי שמעון לב בית דין מתנה עליהם? u'mi it leh leRabbi Shimon
lev Beit Din matneh aleihem? Does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon really hold
of the principle that the בית דין Beit Din can make a
conditional designation for the sacrifices that only takes effect once they're actually
slaughtered? והאמר רב אידי בר אבין אמר רב עמרם אמר רב יצחק
אמר רבי יוחנן. Veha'amar Rav Iddi bar Abin amar Rav Amram amar
Rav Yitzchak amar Rabbi Yochanan. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan taught תמידין
שלא הוצרכו לציבור. temidin shelo hutzrechu latzibbur. We had this back in
שבועות Shavuot in the what, second פרק? perek? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
taught that if you have תמידין, temidin, you have the sheep which
are designated to be the קרבן תמיד korban tamid which were bought
already for the year, let's say תשע"ח, Taf Shin Ayin Chet, they
already bought all of the כבשים kevassim for the תמיד tamid and
then it's getting to be late אדר Adar and we have a
few extra sheep left over. So what happens? Those are תמידין שלא
הוצרכו לציבור. temidin shelo hutzrechu latzibbur. They're not needed for the ציבור
tzibbur because starting with the new month of ניסן, Nisan, from ראש
חודש ניסן Rosh Chodesh Nisan we'll have to buy the קרבן תמיד
korban tamid using the funds from the שקלים shekalim which were collected
for the coming year. So the leftover leftover קרבנות, korbanot, what are
we supposed to do with them? So according to רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, תמידין שלא הוצרכו לציבור לדברי רבי שמעון אין נפדין תמימים, temidin
shelo hutzrechu latzibbur ledivrei Rabbi Shimon ein nifdin temimim, sorry. So according
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon they could not be exchanged or redeemed
for their value while they're in a state of the תמימים, temimim,
that they don't have any מום. mum. לדברי חכמים נפדין תמימים. Ledivrei
Chachamim nifdin temimim. According to the חכמים Chachamim and according to the
majority position, you could do that. That is, the debate between רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים Chachamim is whether the leftover sheep
from the previous year, you have to let them get a מום
mum first before you can be פודה podeh or whether you can
be פודה podeh immediately.
So we still saying though that the reason we have three תמידין,
temidin, I mean two
שעירים se'irim
on שבועות Shavuot is because like there's a possible טומאה tumah between
the...
That has to be what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say because
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does not is not of the opinion לב
בית דין מתנה עליהם lev Beit Din matneh aleihem that the הפרשה
hafrashah is delayed until the time of until the time of שחיטה.
shechitah. So he sees there is this gap time window between during
the time when the קרבן korban was designated and the time the
קרבן korban is shechted. And then the question is, okay, so if
you שחט shecht one here and one here, then what happens during
this time period? You could have another עבירה averah and the question
would have to revert back to...
Right, and the point is therefore
that's really what it's coming for.
Right, as opposed to like it's just part of like the regular
מוסף musaf structure, that's just like what you did.
Right. Right, that's the obvious answer. The obvious answer is the תורה
Torah says so, and there are all sorts of strange קרבנות korbanot
that we bring for all sorts of reasons and we could try
to figure out exactly what each one is for, but at the
end of the day there's a list of קרבנות korbanot and we
bring those קרבנות. korbanot. We don't have to worry about why is
this חטאת chatat and this עולה. olah. If they're communal קרבנות, korbanot,
they're just sort of coming in... I was actually just thinking about
this earlier while I was walking the dog. The idea, every קרבן
מוסף korban musaf except on שבת, Shabbat, שבת Shabbat is the exception,
every קרבן מוסף korban musaf comes with a חטאת. chatat. There's almost
this idea of like maybe the חטאת chatat is not for some
other חטא, cheit, maybe the חטאת chatat is somehow about the audacity
of bringing the קרבנות korbanot or for the somehow we... feel trepidatious
about bringing these קרבנות Korbanot and these holidays. אלה מועדי ה׳
אשר תקראו אתם במועדם.
Eileh Moadei Hashem
Asher Tikre'u Otam BeMo'adam. We have some responsibility in the designation of
the holidays. So maybe there's a fear around the bringing of קרבנות
Korbanot on holidays, we got the day wrong or something like that,
maybe that's part of it as well, I'm not sure.
Also חטאת Hattat can mean to purify,
to purify as well, right? At the beginning of מסכת שבועות Masechet
Shevuot there's this extensive discussion, of course on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
especially, the חטאות Hatta'ot that we bring on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
are for חטאת, Hattat, for חטא, Het, but they're also to cleanse
the מזבח, Mizbe'ah, to cleanse the מקדש. Mikdash. So there's a lot
more to be unpacked there. Let's keep going. ועוד הא דבעי רבי
ירמיה מרבי זירא. Ve'od Ha Deba'i Rabbi Yirmeyah MeRabbi Zeira. So רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah asked רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, שעירי עצרת שקיבל דמן
בשני כוסות ונזרק דמן של ראשון, שני למה הוא בא?
Se'irei Atzeret SheKibel Daman BiShnei Kosot VeNizrak Daman Shel Rishon, Sheni
Lama Hu Ba? So what about שעירי עצרת, Se'irei Atzeret, the same
kind of case, the קרבן חטאת Korban Hattat that's brought on שבועות,
Shavuot, that the blood was collected in two different containers. That is,
and if you look
here where רש״י Rashi explains, שני כוסות נשחטין כאחד, Shnei Kosot Nishhatin
Ke'ehad, the two goats were both slaughtered sort of simultaneously, ואין שהות
לערויי טומאה בין שחיטתן, Ve'ein Shahut Le'aruyei Tum'ah Bein Shehitatan, and there's
no opportunity for there to have been a chance impurity or some
sin that would have occurred in between the שחיטה Shehitah of the
first one and the second one because they were done very proximally
to each other. ונזרק דמו של ראשון, שני למה קרב? VeNizrak Damo
Shel Rishon, Sheni Lama Karev? So if you already sprinkled the blood
of the first קרבן, Korban, then why do you even need the
second one? Because there was no opportunity for טומאת מקדש Tum'at Mikdash
in between the first and second קרבן. Korban. So he says, למה
הוא בא? על טומאה שאירעה בין זריקה של זה לזה. Lama Hu
Ba? Al Tum'ah She'ire'ah Bein Zerikah Shel Zeh LaZeh. So no, it's
possible even to consider that the second זריקת הדם, Zerikat HaDam, even
though the שחיטה Shehitah took place more or less simultaneously, now the
time gap we're looking at is between זריקת הדם Zerikat HaDam of
the first חטאת Hattat and זריקת הדם Zerikat HaDam of the second
חטאת. Hattat. So what's interesting here is that it's a
little obsessive.
It's a little bit obsessive, but the point is everything really, like
100%. Like then we're going to wait four months until, or we're
going to wait one month until ראש חודש תמוז Rosh Hodesh Tammuz
before we bring another חטאת, Hattat, right?
And why would you need it here and then why would you
not need it every time you bring it?
Right, so the point at the end of the day, the real
answer is the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLehem gets a קרבן חטאת Korban
Hattat and the קרבן מוסף Korban Musaf gets a קרבן חטאת Korban
Hattat and that's just how it is. But what they're trying to
do here is sort of flesh, they're trying to provide a rationale.
Why did the תורה Torah command us to bring these, why did
God tell us bring these קרבנות Korbanot if they seem redundant? There
are more dangerous answers than that to this question as well, but
the question that they're getting at here is at least the point
here to say is that the זריקה, Zerikah, even though the זריקה
Zerikah actually happens after the שחיטה, Shehitah, and so therefore we would
think okay, the הפרשה, Hafrashah, the שחיטה Shehitah are important time points
for determining the כפרה, Kapparah, here the זריקת הדם Zerikat HaDam actually
is connected to the כפרה Kapparah of the קרבן, Korban, and that's
what's interesting also to think about. The זריקת הדם, Zerikat HaDam, the
whole point is that the blood has the spiritual power of the
קרבן Korban or whatever it is, the animal's life force. That's what's
bringing about the כפרה, Kapparah, and that's what's being described here. So
actually that the זריקת הדם Zerikat HaDam between the two time points
for the first קרבן Korban and the second קרבן, Korban, that that
would work as well. אבל עשה דלאחר שחיטה אבל עשה דלאחר הפרשה
לא
קא מיבעיא ליה.
Aval Asay DeLe'ahar Shehitah Aval Asay DeLe'ahar
Hafrashah Lo Ka Miba'aya Leh. Okay, עד כאן לא מיבעיא ליה. Ad
Kan Lo Miba'aya Leh.
So that's not a problem, because we still have an answer for
that. אלא עשה דלאחר שחיטה אבל עשה דלאחר הפרשה לא קא מיבעיא
ליה. Ela Asay DeLe'ahar Shehitah Aval Asay DeLe'ahar Hafrashah Lo Ka Miba'aya
Leh.
So the question, so on the one hand, they're sort of saying
okay, that makes sense for things that you did after the שחיטה
Shehitah because you שחט Shaht both animals and now we have to
say okay, so there was one זריקת הדם Zerikat HaDam and then
I had waited fifteen minutes and then there was another זריקת הדם.
Zerikat HaDam. And then what about if it was לאחר הפרשה, Le'ahar
Hafrashah, it really doesn't leave the question so well answered.
לא קא מיבעיא ליה. Lo Ka Miba'aya Leh. דילמא אם תמצי לומר
קאמר. Dilma Im Timtzi Lomar Ka'amar. So we're sort of left with
an unresolved סוגיא. Sugya. It doesn't seem particularly of great practical relevance
either, but it gives us some tools for thinking about which are
the important time points in the קרבן. Korban. Obviously the הפרשה Hafrashah
is important for designating it for its future life, the שחיטה Shehitah
of course, and זריקת הדם Zerikat HaDam actually a very important step
for effecting the כפרה. Kapparah. Okay, now we get into a new
topic.
The bulk of this עמוד Amud is going to be about the
קרבן תודה. Korban Todah. The קרבן תודה Korban Todah is a subcategory
of קרבן שלמים, Korban Shelamim, but unique about the קרבן תודה Korban
Todah unlike a regular שלמים Shelamim is it has a much shorter
time to be eaten. A regular שלמים Shelamim you get to eat
it the day you bring it, the night after, and then the
next day. So close to two days or, you know, 24 hours
plus for a regular שלמים. Shelamim. And קרבן תודה Korban Todah you
only get until midnight of the night after you bring the קרבן.
Korban. So you get a very short window of time.
They didn't have refrigeration.
They didn't have refrigeration, certainly. Part of the other piece is a
קרבן תודה Korban Todah is a cow, a large... animal and it's
brought along with forty loaves of bread. Thirty loaves of מצה matzah
of three different kinds of מצה matzah and one kind of חמץ,
chametz, actually one of the only two kinds of קרבנות korbanos that's
brought with חמץ, chametz, yeah.
The midnight is a rabbinic stringency?
Yeah, really off the top of my head, I think right, that's
the first משנה mishna in ש"ס, Shas, רבן גמליאל'ס Rabban Gamliel's position
is everything that חכמים chachamim told you the קרבן korban has to
be eaten by midnight, really you get until עלות השחר, alot hashachar,
but they were מחמיר machmir for midnight. So if יבנה בית המקדש
במהרה בימינו, yibaneh Beit HaMikdash bimeheira v'yameinu, and שמי Shami actually, actually
פוסק paskens that way.
Right, but we're still going to say that until midnight, all the
משניות mishnayos say until midnight. Okay.
So, it's good to eat meat so early in the morning.
Right. Well, it's late at night, right? You're eating the whole night.
Okay. So the question we have here based on our משנה mishna
is going to be what about what's the interplay between the designation
of a קרבן שלמים korban shelamim and קרבן תודה. korban todah. If
תודה todah is a subcategory of שלמים, shelamim, is there going to
be a problem of overlapping statuses, שינוי קודש, shinui kodesh, שינוי השם,
shinui hashem, of if we're going to see exactly this case. So
איתמר. itmar. This was the אמוראי amoraic teaching. תודה ששחטה לשם תודת
חבירו. todah sheshachatah leshem todat chaveiro. Okay, what if one person, two
different people show up and they have a, they're bringing קרבן תודה
korban todah and the כהן kohen when he does the שחיטה shechitah
for one person's תודה, todah, has in mind the other person's תודה.
todah. If you look at what רש"י Rashi says about this, it's
a little bit of a tricky case to try to parse exactly
what's going on. It was a שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, they'd say.
So you would think it's שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, but רש"י Rashi
doesn't say that.
רש"י Rashi says: תודה ששחטה לשם תודת חבירו, לא ששחטה על מנת
שיתכפר בה מי שאינו בעליה, todah sheshachatah leshem todat chaveiro, lo sheshachatah
al menat sheyitkaper bah mi she'eino ba'aleha, that is not שינוי בעלים.
shinui ba'alim.
But he says, well, we'll get to that also. אלא שינוי קודש,
ela shinui kodesh, okay? He says it's שינוי קודש, shinui kodesh, it's
a change of the designation of the קרבן korban שהיתה לראובן תודה
לשמעון תודה אחרת, ושחט תודתו של זה לשם תודתו של זה. shehayata
l'Reuven todah l'Shimon todah acheret, v'shachatah todato shel zeh leshem todato shel
zeh.
I understand, so it's שינוי קודש.
shinui kodesh.
That you had in mind, it's like what and רש"י Rashi concludes
והוא הדין בשוחט חטאת חלב לשם חטאת דם, vehu hadin beshocheit chatat
cheilev leshem chatat dam,
that is that two different people show up with their קרבנות, korbanot,
and the כהן kohen has in mind not that it's the wrong
person, but that I'm doing this קרבן, korban, I thought the קרבן
korban was שמעון'ס Shimon's תודה todah that I'm doing for שמעון Shimon
and instead had in mind I'm doing ראובן'ס Reuven's תודה todah for
שמעון. Shimon. There's not שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, it's a change of
the... it's a change of status, I understand it is שינוי בעלים.
shinui ba'alim. Okay, but רש"י Rashi doesn't think that it's שינוי בעלים.
shinui ba'alim. I think that the main פשט pshat is that it
should be שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, but it's going to get caught
up in this.
Even when you describe it שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, I don't understand.
See, he says לא שינוי בעלים. lo shinui ba'alim. He's saying it's
not oranges and an apple, although it's orange and it's orange and
it tastes...
yeah, David has a footnote just one second, exports.
He intended ראובן'ס Reuven's תודה todah should assume the sacred qualities of
שמעון'ס Shimon's תודה, todah, though it should remain ראובן'ס Reuven's offering.
Right, that it's still designated according to the owner, but that it
somehow has the status of the other animal, it's a little bit
of a finer case. I'm not... anyway. Okay. The point is this
is a kind of a strange case, we're going to see some
of the דרשות drashos are a little bit strange as well. And
do you understand רש"י? Rashi? No. Okay. I just wanted to read
the רש"י Rashi so you could get the sense that the main
פשט pshat is that it should be שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, but
that רש"י Rashi obviously doesn't feel comfortable with that. Okay. איתמר: itmar:
תודה ששחטה לשם תודת חבירו. todah sheshachatah leshem todat chaveiro. רבה Rabba
אמר: amar: כשירה. kesheira. So רבה Rabba says that that's okay, that
that is כשירה kesheira for us here still means actually that it
was עלו לבעלים לשם חובה. alu labalim leshem chovah. It actually counts
for your obligation. You took a נדר, neder, I'm going to bring
a קרבן תודה, korban todah, and then you brought your קרבן תודה,
korban todah, you fulfilled that obligation. Okay. And רב חסדא Rav Chisda
אמר: amar: פסולה. psula. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says it's פסולה, psula,
that is the קרבן korban is kosher but that it didn't fulfill
your obligation. So רבה Rabba אמר: amar: כשירה kesheira תודה לשם תודה
נשחטה. todah leshem todah nishchatah. It was brought לשם תודה, leshem todah,
it was designated the same level of קרבן. korban. רב חסדא Rav
Chisda אמר: amar: פסולה. psula. לשם שלמים דידיה נשחטה בעינן. leshem shelamim
didei nishchatah bayinan. You need to have the שחיטה shechitah actually for
your own שלמים. shelamim. So again, it sounds like it's talking about
שינוי בעלים, shinui ba'alim, but that's why רש"י Rashi is a difficult
רש"י. Rashi. Okay. אמר amar רבה, Rabba, so רבה Rabba has to
respond to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. So מנא מילי? mina milei? דתניא:
detanya: ובשר זבח תודת שלמיו ביום קרבנו יאכל, uvesar zevach todat shelamov
beyom korbano yachachal, ואומר. v'omer.
So it says: הקריב את זבחו, hakrivo et zivcho, your קרבן. korban.
So אבא חנין Abba Chanin אמר amar משום mishum רבי אליעזר: Rabbi
Eliezer: בא ללמד ba lelamed תודה ששחטה לשם שלמים, כשירה. todah sheshachatah
leshem shelamim, kesheira. So the תנאים Tannaim are discussing what
about the exchange not a case of two different קרבנות תודה, korbanos
todah, but a תודה todah with a שלמים. shelamim. So that interchange.
So if I brought תודה ששחטה לשם שלמים, todah sheshachatah leshem shelamim,
I had in mind I'm bringing a קרבן שלמים korban shelamim instead,
כשירה. kesheira. Because תודה todah is a subcategory of שלמים, shelamim, so
שלמים shelamim is a more inclusive category, you're able to therefore it
still counts as the correct מחשבה. machshavah. שלמים שנשחטו לשם תודה, shelamim
shenishchatu leshem todah, but if I brought a regular קרבן שלמים korban
shelamim and had in mind that it was a קרבן תודה, korban
todah, פסולים. psulim. Those are disqualified because in that case you've designated
it for a more specific type of קרבן, korban, which it actually
isn't.
So what happened to our משנה mishna though, that כל הזבחים ששחטן
שלא לשמן כשירים?
kol hazvachim
sheshachtan shelo lishmam kesherim? Yeah. So why are we asking this question?
So here we're talking about, was it עולה לבעל לשם חולין? olah
l'ba'al l'shem chullin? That's what we're talking about.
But we know that already. That's what our משנה mishna says.
So but here we're talking about it's some kind of שלמים shelamim
and it's some kind of שלמים. shelamim. So now within a primary
category, now we're talking about finer distinction. Maybe that's not even going
to reach the level of disqualification, even to not count for fulfillment,
because you still had in mind some kind of שלמים. shelamim. You
still had in mind some kind of שלמים. shelamim. So the point
is that the תודה ששחטה לשם שלמים כשרה, todah she'shachtah l'shem shelamim
kesherah, 100% כשרה, kesherah, totally fulfilled. And שלמים שנשחטו לשם תודה shelamim
she'nishchatu l'shem todah is פסולים psulim because that's a disqualified מחשבה. machshava.
ומה הפריש בין זה לזה? u'mah hifrish bein zeh l'zeh? So תודה
קרויה שלמים. todah kruyah shelamim. The תודה todah is considered a קרבן
שלמים korban shelamim ואין שלמים קרויין תודה, v'ein shelamim kruyin todah, but
regular קרבן שלמים korban shelamim is never called תודה, todah, which makes
sense. Okay, so שלמים לשם תודה פסולה. shelamim l'shem todah psulah. If
I bring a שלמים לשם תודה, shelamim l'shem todah, then I've disqualified
it. הא תודה לשם תודה כשרה. ha todah l'shem todah kesherah. So
from here, רבא Rava can infer from this whole תנאיתי Tannaitic discussion
about interchanging שלמים shelamim and תודה. todah. He says, oh, so תודה
לשם תודה כשרה. todah l'shem todah kesherah. That means even if I
had in mind the wrong קרבן תודה, korban todah, whether it was
a שינוי בעלים shinuy ba'alim or that it was just, that's why
שינוי בעלים shinuy ba'alim doesn't, that's why רש״י Rashi doesn't like it
is because what we're talking about here is שינוי קודש. shinuy kodesh.
I had in mind a different קרבן. korban. So the point is
ראובן׳ס Reuven's קרבן korban was designated for crossing the Atlantic Ocean and
שמעון׳ס Shimon's קרבן תודה korban todah was for getting better from, you
know, hypertension or something. So then they each had a different קרבן,
korban, and then the כהן kohen had in mind that ראובן Reuven
is ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon is שמעון, Shimon, but he interchanged
which קרבן korban was for what, perhaps, or something like that, the
designation of the קרבן. korban. Okay, so מאי לאו דחבריה? mai lav
d'chavrei? So does that really mean that it refers specifically to someone
else's קרבן? korban? לא, דידיה. lo, didey. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda
can defend himself against רבא׳ס Rava's point and say, no, it really
just means about one person, about one person who brought two different
קרבנות תודה korbanot todah and they were interchanged, that would be allowed,
but not for two different people. אבל דחבריה, aval d'chavrei, so we
say מאי פסולה? mai psulah? עד דתני שלמים לשם תודה פסולה, ad
d'tani shelamim l'shem todah psulah, once we've said that שלמים לשם תודה
shelamim l'shem todah is disqualified, ליתני תודה לשם תודה. litni todah l'shem
todah.
The מדרש midrash could have included a mention of תודה לשם תודה
todah l'shem todah as well because if we're going to teach that
שלמים לשם תודה shelamim l'shem todah is disqualified and it left this
excluded middle case ambiguous, כל שכן שלמים לשם תודה. kol she'ken shelamim
l'shem todah. If it would have said תודה לשם תודה, todah l'shem
todah, then I could have obviously inferred that if I had a
שלמים לשם תודה, shelamim l'shem todah, it would be disqualified because I
actually had a totally different קרבן korban in mind. שלמים לשם תודה
לדידיה איצטריכא ליה.
shelamim l'shem todah l'didey
itztricha leh. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka da'atach amina, I could have thought
מדאורייתא קרויה שלמים, mide'oraita kruyah shelamim, שלמים נמי קרויה תודה. shelamim nami
kruyah todah. I have to use that לימוד limud to undermine the
possibility of understanding that just like a תודה todah is called שלמים,
shelamim, maybe we would have thought that שלמים shelamim is also called
קרבן תודה korban todah and they would be totally interchangeable.
How would you thought that?
Because maybe once, I mean, that's the way the גמרא Gemara says
it. So מדאורייתא קרויה שלמים, mide'oraita kruyah shelamim, once the תורה Torah
already calls a תודה todah a קרבן שלמים, korban shelamim, so maybe
I would just think the terms are interchangeable, right? Maybe I would
think, oh, so the תורה Torah calls it sometimes שלמים, shelamim, sometimes
תודה, todah, and there's certain circumstances where you're supposed to bring this
קרבן, korban, but not that there's any real legally meaningful distinction between
the two types of קרבנות korbanot besides, okay, so this one you
have a shorter length of time to eat and this one you
have to bring more bread with it or whatever, but basically they're
the same thing. And what's the purpose of the שלמים? shelamim? The
purpose of any regular קרבן שלמים korban shelamim usually is just I
wanted to bring a קרבן korban or I decided to bring a
קרבן. korban.
So just a free will,
just a free will offering. Usually translated in English "free will offering."
א קרבן שלמים. a korban shelamim. The only times we have
a mandatory קרבן שלמים, korban shelamim, we have a communal קרבן שלמים
korban shelamim on שבועות. Shavuot. We have the קרבן תודה korban todah
which is a bit of a debate how mandatory it is, but
under certain circumstances the גמרא Gemara seems to say that you have
some kind of an obligation to bring a קרבן תודה. korban todah.
Not for cheesecake. Not for cheesecake.
Cheesecake, then you can't have, if you have the קרבן תודה, korban
todah, you can't have any more cheesecake. That's the problem. Okay, וכי
שחטו לשם תודה? v'chi shachato l'shem todah? Yeah.
So הא תודה לשם תודה כשרה
ha todah l'shem
todah kesherah means it's דחבריה d'chavrei because otherwise we'd be going out
of our way, which is why then, according to this opinion, is
not redundant or superfluous given the משנה mishna that said it's already
כשר. kasher. Right. But we may have thought תודה todah is different.
We may have thought תודה todah is different and what רב חסדא
Rav Chisda can come back and say is, no, the point is
you may have had this spurious assumption that תודה todah and שלמים
shelamim are totally equivalent terms and that's what this לימוד limud is
coming to teach, but don't come to think that actually if you
interchange two different תודות todot that you've gotten yourself off the hook.
So it's easier to, it seems to exchange תודה todah and שלמים
shelamim than two different תודות. todot.
No, the point, not that far. That is, right, we still have
the הלכה halacha that if you שחט shacht a regular שלמים לשם
תודה, shelamim l'shem todah, it's disqualified to the extent that it doesn't
count for the obligation to have brought the קרבן, korban, you have
to bring another one. another שלמים. Shelamim. So the point רבא Rava
and רב חסדא Rav Chisda's debate is does the designation between two
different תודות, Todot, is that problematic or not? And the point of
this לימוד limud here is to say what was the, what would
have been the rationale one way or the other why we would
have said that was disqualified. Okay. אמר רבא. Amar Rava. Now we
have numerous statements, short little teachings of רבא, Rava, in quick succession.
Okay. אמר רבא חטאת ששחטה לשם חטאת כשרה ולשם עולה פסולה. Amar
Rava: Chatat she-shechatah l'shem Chatat, keshera; u-l'shem olah, psula.
So this seems like a bit of a redundant teaching seeing we've
read the משנה Mishnah already and we saw that חטאת Chatat was
the one that is the exception to the rule, but nonetheless if
you brought a קרבן חטאת Korban Chatat on,
with חטאת Chatat in mind, it's כשר, kosher, and לשם עולה פסולה.
l'shem olah psula. If you had in mind that it was a
קרבן עולה, Korban Olah, you've disqualified it. So מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
ושחט אותה לחטאת. v'shachat otah l'Chatat. So you have to שחט shecht
the קרבן חטאת, Korban Chatat, לחטאת, l'Chatat, it has to be a
חטאת, Chatat, אמר רחמנא. amar Rachmana. והרי חטאת לשם חטאת נשחטה לשם
עולה פסולה. v'harei Chatat l'shem Chatat nishchatah l'shem olah psula. Okay, fine.
ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, another teaching of רבא. Rava. ואמר חטאת ששחטה
על מי שמחויב חטאת פסולה. v'amar Chatat she-shechatah al mi she-mechuyav Chatat
psula. If I brought a קרבן חטאת Korban Chatat for another person
who was obligated to bring חטאת, Chatat, it's become disqualified. על מי
שמחויב עולה כשרה. Al mi she-mechuyav olah keshera. So if the, right,
that is, the person, some other person, I had someone else in
mind for this קרבן Korban instead, and I had in mind a
person who is מחויב חטאת, mechuyav Chatat, that is they had to
bring their own חטאת Chatat and I brought somebody else's חטאת Chatat
for them, it becomes disqualified because I had in mind the wrong
owner. This is kind of like a מינה מחריב לה mina machriv
la that we had early in the early in the מסכת, Masechet,
the notion that they're very close, close to each other in their
obligation so that that's why it disqualifies. But a person who is
מחויב עולה, mechuyav olah, who's מחויב עולה? mechuyav olah?
So, oh
yeah, you
wouldn't normally think that you are מחויב עולה mechuyav olah because an
עולה olah is usually not brought as a, an obligation, obligatory. But
in this case, but for an individual, so the notion that's going
to come up on today's דף daf it would be ביטול עשה.
bitul aseh. Right, we say ביטול עשה bitul aseh or לאו הניתק
לעשה. lav hanitak l'aseh. There are certain עבירות aveirot that you would
bring a קרבן עולה Korban Olah in some sense but it's not
exactly a חיוב chiyuv to bring it. So it's a little bit
of a strange way of putting it. משום מחויב חטאת פסולה משום
מחויב עולה כשרה. mishum mechuyav Chatat psula mishum mechuyav olah keshera. So
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? וכיפר עליו עליו v'chipper alav, alav
ולא חברו. v'lo chavero. Your קרבן Korban that you designated for a
certain sin, you can't have it transferred to someone else for their
sin. חברו דמיא דידיה. Chavero damya didei. So another, your friend is
comparable to you במחויב כפרה כמותו. b'mechuyav kapara k'moto. So that is,
the kind of חברו chavero that's disqualified is the type of חברו
chavero who is equivalent to you in his need to bring a
קרבן חטאת. Korban Chatat. But some other person who didn't do any
איסור כרת issur kareth and doesn't have to bring חטאת, Chatat, then
they're not considered חברו chavero to be excluded. We saw these דרשות
drashot already. Okay. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, this is now number three,
right? ואמר רבא חטאת ששחטה על מי שאינו מחויב כלום פסולה. V'amar
Rava Chatat she-shechatah al mi she-aino mechuyav klum psula. What if I
had in mind someone who's not obligated to bring any קרבן? Korban?
We said if you're מחויב עולה, mechuyav olah, if you're someone who
had a ביטול עשה bitul aseh that he was trying to get
כפרה kapara for and you accidentally brought the קרבן חטאת Korban Chatat
for him, that it would be okay. But if you're אינו מחויב
כלום, aino mechuyav klum, it's פסולה, psula, then it's disqualified. שאין לך
אדם בישראל שאין מחויב עשה. she-ain lecha adam b'Yisrael she-ain mechuyav aseh.
But there's no such person because every person in ישראל Yisrael has
to bring קרבן עולה Korban Olah anyway, so it's not really a
problem. ואמר רבא חטאת מכפרת על חייבי עשה. V'amar Rava Chatat mechaperet
al chayavei aseh. רבא Rava teaches that a חטאת Chatat can even
be מכפר mechaper on חייבי עשה, chayavei aseh, that is if, right,
if the חטאת Chatat was accidentally brought on behalf of not the
owner who designated it for his חיוב כרת, chiyuv kareth, but for
some other person who brought a קרבן Korban for a חיוב עשה,
chiyuv aseh, it sort of can fill in for that role as
well. That is, normally we would think the עולה olah is the
קרבן Korban that you're supposed to bring for a מצות עשה, mitzvot
aseh, but in this case חטאת מכפרת על חייבי עשה מקל וחומר.
Chatat mechaperet al chayavei aseh mi-kal v'chomer. Yeah.
So when רבא Rava said the second teaching, I'm still trying to
understand this, that if I שחט shecht a חטאת Chatat for someone
who's מחויב mechuyav an עולה, olah, it's כשרה. keshera. So he interprets
our משנה Mishnah to say חוץ מן החטאת chutz min ha-Chatat only
in case of שינוי בעלים?
shinui ba'alim? Is that, not the wrong person, sorry, that, that you
had in mind, yeah, wrong person. Right.
He's saying שינוי
משנה shinui Mishnah says
no because the משנה Mishnah is talking about שינוי קודש, shinui kodesh,
I designate the wrong, right, שלא לשמן, shelo lishmam, I brought it
for the wrong, the wrong קרבן. Korban. So if I brought, you
brought me your קרבן חטאת Korban Chatat and I said oh this
is a beautiful עולה olah and I brought it as an עולה
olah instead, that's why it doesn't מכפר mechaper your קרבנות, korbanot, your
כרת, kareth, because it's the wrong, it's the wrong sort. Say it
again? That the משנה Mishnah is talking about שינוי השם. shinui ha-shem.
I brought it for the wrong, the wrong, the wrong קרבן. Korban.
Okay, but רבא Rava says that if I...
this is שינוי בעלים. shinui ba'alim.
But he
says אמר רבא חטאת ששחטה על מי שמחויב חטאת פסולה על מי
שמחויב
עולה כשרה.
amar Rava Chatat she-shechatah al mi she-mechuyav Chatat psula al mi
she-mechuyav olah keshera.
So it's also... I brought
a, you know, I bring ראובן'ס Reuven's קרבן korban
on behalf of שמעון, Shimon, and שמעון Shimon doesn't have any חטאות
chata'ot in his scorecard, but he's מחויב עולה mechuyav olah because he
broke a מצות עשה. mitzvah asei.
So I use this, so I, this is a חטאת, chatat, I
thought it was an עולה, olah, I sacrificed as an עולה. olah.
That's what we're saying?
That's what the משנה Mishna is saying. That's where it would be,
it would be פסול pasul because there you change, because חוץ מן
החטאת, chutz min hachatat, because חטאת chatat has to be associated with
the...
And רבא'ס Rava's case is what?
רבא'ס Rava's case, so רש"י Rashi says is the second one, was
that רבא'ס Rava's case is
חטאת ששחטה על מי שמחויב חטאת פסולה. chatat sheshchatah al mi shemechuyav
chatat pesulah. If I bring a קרבן חטאת korban chatat for some
other another person who is מחויב חטאת, mechuyav chatat, it's disqualified. על
מי שמחויב עולה כשרה. Al mi shemechuyav olah kesherah. For if it's
someone who's not מחויב mechuyav in a, if I did a שינוי
בעלים shinui be'alim but into a person who is not חייב chayav
in a קרבן חטאת... korban chatat...
Meaning it's a חטאת, chatat, but I'm thinking it's my חטאת, chatat,
but I'm thinking it's
שמעון'ס Shimon's חטאת, chatat, and it turns out שמעון Shimon doesn't have
any
עבירות aveirot that he would have to bring a קרבן חטאת. korban
chatat.
But he did bring, but he did bring in קרבן, korban, שמעון?
Shimon?
No, he's just, he happens to, he lives wherever. Your name is
Michael Axman, I thought your name was Michael Greenstein, and Michael Greenstein
is some other guy who doesn't have to bring a קרבן חטאת.
korban chatat. That's the kind of thing with what's going on. So
the כהן Kohen has in mind a different person, right?
That should, that be invalid?
So if it was a person who's מחויב חטאת, mechuyav chatat, who
had also had to bring a קרבן חטאת, korban chatat, it's disqualified
because that's what the תורה Torah calls חברו. chavero. That is, well,
the תורה Torah doesn't say חברו, chavero, the מדרש Midrash says חברו,
chavero, right? It says וכיפר עליו. vechiper alav. The תורה Torah says
it has to come to atone for your sin. So עליו alav
comes to exclude other people, but only which type of people? Only
חברו הדומה לו לדידי, chavero hadomeh lo ledidi, that is another person
comparable to me. That is another person who should be also bringing
a קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. The problem is mixing up two different
people are waiting online to bring their קרבן חטאת korban chatat and
I brought it on behalf of the wrong person. But if there's
some person who's not חייב chayav in a קרבן חטאת korban chatat
at all, he's totally outside the פרשה, parsha, then it's fine because
it's not going to interfere. That מינא מחריב בה, mina machriv bah,
the closer it is, the more interference there is.
So sacrificed it for somebody else?
I sacrificed it on behalf of Michael Greenstein.
But it's still, but it's still a חטאת?
chatat? Right, but as a חטאת. chatat. They didn't have last names
in those days. But as a חטאת, chatat, as a, I brought
a קרבן חטאת korban chatat as a קרבן חטאת korban chatat on
behalf of a person who's not required to bring קרבן חטאת, korban
chatat, it's fine. And רבא Rava adds מכפר על חייבי עשה, mechaper
al chayavei asei, that is retroactively, he will be מכפר mechaper on
מצוות עשה mitzvot asei that such a person brought. When we say
he's מחויב עולה, mechuyav olah, let's say he's not חייב chayav anything,
would that be better or worse? Well, no, that's what רבא Rava
says is that אין לך אדם מישראל, ein lecha adam mi'Yisrael, right?
What was the line? אין לך אדם מישראל שאינו מחויב עשה. Ein
lecha adam mi'Yisrael she'eino mechuyav asei.
Everyone violates מצוות עשה mitzvot asei all the time, we know that.
That's why as soon as the הלכה halacha is as soon as
you do תשובה teshuva for it,
you're forgiven for it because מצות עשה
ביטול עשה, mitzvah asei bitul asei, relatively low level violation.
So מי שחייב עולה mi shechayav olah then is not, is not
literal
because you're not חייב chayav to bring the קרבן. korban.
Right, because no, but I mean like, even like, you know, he
bought one a second before, right? It still works.
What do you mean?
Like Greenstein and Greenstein, he bought it again, עולה עולה, olah olah,
whatever, right? It still works. This חטאת chatat and this עולה. olah.
Because on behalf of some other person, but it's a person who's
מחויב עולה, mechuyav olah, yeah. Okay, והאמר רבא, veha'amar Rava, let's second
to last line. והאמר רבא חטאת ששחטה על מי שמחויב חטאת פסולה.
veha'amar Rava chatat sheshchatah al mi shemechuyav chatat pesulah. If I brought
a חטאת chatat on behalf of another person who is חייב chayav
in a חטאת, chatat, it's disqualified. על מי שמחויב עולה כשרה. Al
mi shemechuyav olah kesherah. The same principle. So כמאן דבעי למימר מכפרה
מקופיא מכפרה. keman debaye lemeimar mechaperah mikupya mechaperah. So the point is
that it doesn't atone fully for the violation, but מקופיא מכפרה. mikupya
mechaperah. רש"י Rashi says, right, חטאת עשה. chatat asei. The קרבן חטאת
korban chatat can still partially atone for the מצות עשה. mitzvah asei.
Okay, fine. Yeah.
That's just weird.
Well, that's sort of the point. The חטאת, chatat, the purifying atoning
powers of the קרבן חטאת korban chatat are more powerful than the
קרבן עולה, korban olah, so it's a kind of a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Okay.
Yeah, that I get, but the idea that it's
I would think the קל וחומר kal vachomer would be that it
completely atones for without any...
No, but the point is just that the partial is to say
that bringing, bringing an what is it? אילו
הוא מתחייב חטאת מכפר
עשה מקופיא. Ilu
hu hitchayav chatat mechaper
asei mikupya.
What's קופיא? kupya?
קופיא Kupya is like a residue, no?
Like partial basically. I
what I thought this is saying is מכפר מקופיא מכפר mechaper mikupya
mechaper that it's partial atonement for for the person who's מחוייב עולה
mechuyav ola who has the קרבן חטאת korban chatas brought for him
still gets a partial atonement. Not- but meaning that you don't get
a full atonement from קרבן עולה korban ola anyway, right? Because this
is what רבא's Rava next teaching, right? דאמר רבא עולה ששחטה שלא
לשמה אסור לזרוק דמה שלא לשמה.
de'amar Rava ola sheshachata shelo lishmah
asur lizrok dama shelo lishmah. Fine. The next point is that if
you- if you did the שחיטה שלא לשמה, shchita shelo lishmah, then
the later עבודה avodah like the זריקה zrika you also can't do
not לשמה, lishmah, you have to do it לשמה lishmah as best
as possible. So אי בעית אימא קרא אי בעית אימא סברא. iba'it
eima kra iba'it eima svara. There are two different reasons for this,
one based on a פסוק pasuk and one based on logic. So
אי בעית אימא קרא, iba'it eima kra, the one based on the
פסוק, pasuk, it says מוצא שפתיך תשמור ועשית, motza sefatecha tishmor ve'asita,
right? We had this already. The אי בעית אימא סברא משום דשני
בה. iba'it eima svara mishum deshanya bah. So you have to do
as best as possible what you're trying to do and you have
to do as best as possible what you're trying to do, both
based on the פסוק pasuk and based on the סברא. svara. So
here the סברא svara and the פסוק pasuk are aligned. Sometimes we
say קרא למה לי סברא הוא, kra lama li svara hu, why
do we need a פסוק pasuk if it's based on סברא? svara?
That's what we have two times I think in the גמרא, Gemara,
only very extreme cases, and both times they're rejected, but interesting suggestion.
Okay, וכדריש פירקא, uchidreish pirka, like what appears early in our מסכת.
masechet. Usually you don't see this וכדריש פירקא, uchidreish pirka, it's interesting,
it's like a very self-aware גמרא. Gemara. They know they already wrote
about it. ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava, another teaching of רבא, Rava, עולה
הבאה לאחר מיתה ששחטה בשינוי קודש פסולה. ola haba'ah le'achar mita shechata
beshinuy kodesh pesula. So עולה ola that was brought after the owner
died, okay,
so it doesn't count for the if it was brought with בשינוי
קודש, beshinuy kodesh, then the heirs have to bring another one, doesn't
fulfill the requirement.
בשינוי בעלים כשירה דאין בעלים לאחר מיתה. beshinuy be'alim ksheira de'ein be'alim
le'achar mita. But if it was brought with בשינוי בעלים beshinuy be'alim
after the owner had died, then it's fine because there's no such
thing as the owner, that is the owner, the owner himself no
longer is alive, the heirs have a responsibility to bring the קרבן
korban that was already designated, but so there's no need for the
קרבן korban to be associated with the owner after he's passed away.
Yeah.
Well, that brings up the issue, if I pointed at a sheep
and say זו עולה. zu ola. Yeah,
in a certain sense that's not really my sheep anymore.
But yet this is really saying that it is my sheep.
It is your sheep. This is a point which is developed already
in תוספות Tosafot and really רב חיים Rav Chaim brought it to
the fore, the difference between two different types of הקדש. hekdesh. There's
הקדש hekdesh which is a designation בדק הבית, bedek habayit, which means
that it becomes the corporate financial property of the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. I take this table and I make it הקדש, hekdesh, then
it's going to be sold by the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and
they'll use the money for בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash things. If I
take an animal which could be brought as a קרבן korban or
even some other things, flour and oil and things like that, and
I designate them for the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, then because they
could be brought on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, they're designated as קדושת הגוף.
kedushat haguf. They're actually meant to be brought as קרבנות korbanot and
the point is there's a difference between קדושת דמים kedushat damim and
קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf and קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf means actually and
there's סוגיות sugyot in בבא קמא Bava Kamma about this, it's very
interesting, but basically that קדושת הגוף kedushat haguf still belongs to the
owner, but the owner has a responsibility to bring it as a
קרבן. korban. Things that are קדושת דמים kedushat damim belong to the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash will sell
them and use the money for other things. So those are two
totally different types of הקדש. hekdesh. One is it belongs to me
but I have responsibility to bring the קרבן korban and one is
it no longer belongs to me, I gave it as a gift
to the corporate entity of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay, so
that sounds like רבא Rava thinks אין בעלים לאחר מיתה. ein be'alim
le'achar mita. ורב פנחס בריה דרב אמי אמר יש בעלים לאחר מיתה.
veRav Pinchas berei deRav Ami amar yesh be'alim le'achar mita. So רב
פנחס בריה דרב אמי Rav Pinchas berei deRav Ami disagrees and he
thinks that there's actually the designation of the owner is still in
effect even after the owner has died. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב
פנחס בריה דרב אמי, amar leh Rav Ashi leRav Pinchas berei deRav
Ami, so רב אשי Rav Ashi says to him, דווקא קאמר מר
יש בעלים לאחר מיתה ובעי לאתויי עולה אחריתי.
davka qamar mar yesh
be'alim le'achar mita uva la'atuyei ola achriti.
So when you say יש בעלים לאחר מיתה, yesh be'alim le'achar mita,
that the designation of who is the owner still is meaningful after
the owner has died, what do you mean by that? Do you
mean ובעי לאתויי עולה אחריתי? uva la'atuyei ola achriti? Do they- do
the heirs have to bring another עולה ola on their father's behalf
after he's died because the first one got messed up? או דילמא
דאיכא כמה עשה גביה מכפר? o dilma de'ika kama asei gabei mechaper?
Or is it just what you're saying that if- if the owner,
the original owner who had died had had multiple חיובי עשה chiyuvey
asei and he wanted to bring extra עולות olot that they could
do that. That is how far are you willing to say that
יש בעלים לאחר מיתה yesh be'alim le'achar mita means that the original
קרבן korban was disqualified and needs to be repaired a second time
around? אמר ליה. amar leh.
What keeps someone's- it's for expressing thanksgiving posthumously.
Well,
it's not about expressing thanksgiving, it's about bringing the קרבן עולה. korban
ola. So here the assumption at least is the קרבן עולה korban
ola is being brought brought for a מצוות עשה mitzvah aseh violation.
Of course, in our mind we read ספר ויקרא Sefer Vayikra and
we think, oh, a קרבן עולה korban olah is also if you
just decide you want to bring a קרבן עולה, korban olah, you
bring one. But
so that's at least the orientation that they have, as assumption that
it's about being brought for a מצוות עשה. mitzvah aseh. אמר ליה
Amar lei דוקא davka קאמינה. kamina. He says I really think it's
דוקא. davka. דוקא Davka meaning the first one. So בעי לאתויי עולה
אחריתי, ba'ei le'atuyei olah achriti, that is if it was messed up
by שינוי בעלים shinui be'alim in the first time, then the heirs
have to bring another קרבן עולה. korban olah. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar Rava,
another teaching of רבא, Rava, עולה דורון היא. olah doron hi.
The עולה olah is actually considered to be a דורון, doron, a
present. Okay, and look at the top תוספות: Tosafot: אף על גב
דעשה מכפר יותר מחטאת דהא מכפרא קא בעיא. af al gav de'asei
mechaper yoter mechattat de'ha mechappera kam ba'i.
The designation of the עולה olah as a דורון doron is even
though the עולה olah has sort of some power to be מכפר
mechapper for מצוות עשה, mitzvah aseh, really it's not really about כפרה.
kapparah. Really the קרבן עולה korban olah is a דורון, doron, it's
giving a present to God. So this is exactly kind of that
distinction which is that you sort of have both elements of the
role of the קרבן עולה. korban olah.
And where did he get forgiveness? How? What was? Who? If the
person, it says here if עולה olah is a gift offered to
השם, Hashem, this is a note from
רש"י, Rashi, as
offered to השם Hashem after the person has been forgiven for his
transgression.
Well,
I don't know about after, it's just, it's just a gift. Meaning
look what רש"י Rashi says. רש"י Rashi says: עולה דורון היא אינה
באה לכפר על עשה כפרה ממש אלא אחר שכפרה תשובה על עשה.
olah doron hi eina ba'a lechapper al aseh kappara mamash ela achar
shekapparatchuva al aseh.
Once you did תשובה teshuva for your מצוות עשה, mitzvah aseh, but
even there still the association is with the קרבן, korban, with the
מצוות עשה. mitzvah aseh. I don't think רבא Rava is actually saying
that. At some point רבא Rava is just saying you want to
bring קרבן עולה, korban olah, great, bring קרבן עולה. korban olah. He
said: אין לך אדם מישראל שאינו מחויב עשה, ein lecha adam miyisrael
she'eino mechuyav aseh, right?
Every person has violated a מצוות עשה. mitzvah aseh. So you sort
of have the freedom to bring this קרבן korban when you want
to. Okay.
So when do we know when תשובה teshuva achieves the atonement and
when do we know that we need to bring...
Well,
every sin that you do you need to do תשובה teshuva for
it and sometimes you have an obligation to bring a קרבן korban
for it as well. But the קרבן חטאת korban chattat is never
going to work unless you do תשובה teshuva also, right? Like you
do וידוי viduy on the קרבן. korban. So all of these kind
of things, תשובה teshuva is the most important element. I mean, learn
you know the end of יומא Yoma and the רמב"ם הלכות תשובה,
Rambam Hilchot Teshuva, he discusses there at the beginning like the first
or second פרק perek he talks about the role that the קרבן
korban plays in the atonement and certain things.
But the קרבן korban itself usually, actually bringing the קרבן korban in
some metaphysical sense maybe affects some additional level of atonement, but generally
the תשובה teshuva is really the most important thing. So we say
here ואמר רבא עולה דורון היא היכי דמי? ve'amar Rava olah doron
hi heichei dami? Like what case are we talking about? אי דלא
איכא תשובה? ei delo ika teshuva? So are we talking about a
case where you didn't do תשובה? teshuva? So זבח רשעים תועבה, zevach
reshaim to'eva, then a wicked person who brings a קרבן korban is
considered תועבה, to'eva, it's considered abominable.
ואי דאיכא תשובה? ve'ei de'ika teshuva? If you did תשובה, teshuva, הא
תניא עבר על מצוות עשה ושב לא זז משם עד שמוחלין לו.
ha tanya avar al mitzvat aseh veshav lo zaz misham ad shemochalin
lo. So if you did a מצוות עשה, mitzvah aseh, you violated
a מצוות עשה, mitzvah aseh, that is you didn't wear תפילין, tefillin,
you didn't put up a מזוזה mezuzah on your door, whatever, so
you do תשובה teshuva for it, say God, I'm so sorry, I
didn't mean to, I'm going to do better next time. So
then לא זז משם עד שמוחלין לו. lo zaz misham ad shemochalin
lo. God immediately forgives you before you even take a step, that
is when you're right there, immediately you've been forgiven. אלא שמע מינה
דורון הוא, Ela shema mina doron hu, and therefore the קרבן עולה
korban olah actually never needs to affect כפרה kappara in any real
sense for מצוות עשה, mitzvah aseh, because מצוות עשה mitzvah aseh you've
already been forgiven for and therefore it's just being given as a
gift. Okay. So תני נמי הכי, tani nami hachi, it was taught
similarly in a ברייתא: braita: אמר רבי שמעון חטאת למה באה? amar
Rabbi Shimon chattat lama ba'a? So why do you bring קרבן חטאת?
korban chattat? למה באה? Lama ba'a? לכפר. Lechapper. The whole purpose of
a קרבן חטאת korban chattat is to atone for your sins. אלא
למה באה לפני עולה? Ela lama ba'a lifnei olah? So why do
you bring קרבן חטאת korban chattat before your קרבן עולה? korban olah?
That is this week's פרשה parsha especially. Have lots of people who
have to bring both a חטאת chattat and an עולה. olah. A
מצורע, metzora, יולדת, yoledet, all sorts of, right? אחד לחטאת ואחד לעולה,
echad lechattat ve'echad le'olah, right? You bring the חטאת chattat first. So
why? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says: לפרקליט שנכנס, leparaklit shenichnas, that is
one of the king's courtiers goes to visit the king, so ריצה
פרקליט נכנס דורון אחריו. ritza paraklit nichnas doron acharav. So first you
have to appease the king for what you did wrong and then
once you've been forgiven and you're allowed to enter in, then you
can bring a gift as well to say, oh I love you
so much, thank you. So you say please forgive me before you
say your gratitude and your thanks and your appreciation. So you bring
the קרבן חטאת korban chattat before the קרבן עולה. korban olah. And
that's often why you see them paired together, that is they're sort
of different sides of the same coin. חטאת chattat is taking away
something bad, עולה olah is adding something good, and they very often
come together.
And the חטאת chattat is always brought first. Okay. The next part,
the next clause in our משנה mishnah is the discussion about the
פסח pesach and the חטאת chattat and the קרבן. korban. Pesach it
will be the next discussion. We'll get as far as we can
now and the rest we'll try to do tomorrow as well. Like
I said, this was a long דף. Daf. Okay, פסח. Pesach. So
the משנה Mishna had said חוץ מן הפסח והחטאת, chutz min haPesach
vehaChatat, that is, every קרבן, korban, the משנה Mishna had said,
sorry,
כל הזבחים שנזבחו שלא לשמן כשרים, אלא שלא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה,
חוץ מן הפסח והחטאת. הפסח בזמנו והחטאת בכל זמן.
Kol hazvachim shenizbechu shelo lishmam kshairim, ela shelo alu l'baalim l'shem chova,
chutz min haPesach vehaChatat. HaPesach bizmano vehaChatat bechol zman. That is, the
פסח Pesach at בזמנו, bizmano, whether that's on the 14th of ניסן,
Nisan, whether it's only in the afternoon of the 14th, whether even
the morning of the 14th, but if I brought a קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach with some other קרבן korban in mind, then it's totally
disqualified. It's not just that it was a kosher קרבן korban and
retroactively
didn't fulfill my obligation, but actually becomes totally disqualified. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says, פסח מנלן? Pesach minalan? Where do I learn this
rule about the קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? דכתיב, Dichtiv, שמור את חודש
האביב ועשית פסח. Shamor es chodesh ha'Aviv ve'asisa Pesach. So the month
of אביב Aviv you have to do the פסח, Pesach, שיהיו כל
עשיותיו לשם פסח. sheyihyu kol asiyosav l'shem Pesach. Every action for this
קרבן korban has to be done with a positive לשמה, lishma, not
just
and certainly if it was then disqualified with a different קרבן korban
in mind, then you have violated that requirement. So there's a special
requirement by the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, ועשית פסח. ve'asisa Pesach. You
have to do the פסח, Pesach, every action has to be done
with the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach in mind. So אשכחן שינוי קודש.
ashkachan shinuy kodesh. That makes sense in terms of designating for a
different קרבן, korban, for for a קרבן שלמים Korban Shelamim or קרבן
חטאת Korban Chatat or something. שינוי בעלים מנלן? Shinuy baalim minalan? What
about if I brought the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach for the wrong
owner? דכתיב ואמרתם זבח פסח הוא, Dichtiv va'amartem zevach Pesach hu, שתהא
זביחה לשם פסח. shetehei zvicha l'shem Pesach. So the פסוק pasuk says
you have to say this is the זבח פסח, zevach Pesach, this
is the פסח Pesach sacrifice. So does that mean there has to
be זביחה לשם פסח? zvicha l'shem Pesach? אימא אינו עניין לשינוי קודש,
Ima eino inyan l'shinuy kodesh, so if I already learned שינוי קודש
shinuy kodesh from ועשית פסח, ve'asisa Pesach, so זבח פסח תניהו עניין
לשינוי בעלים. zevach Pesach t'naihu inyan l'shinuy baalim. So then I use
that to learn that it has to be designated only for its
owner. קרבן פסח Korban Pesach also has an interesting unique rule about
the בעלים baalim as opposed to other קרבנות, korbanos, which is that
it has to be the people who are going to be eating
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach have to be in mind as well,
not just the person who owns it, but all of the חבורה
chaburah who will be eating it that evening have to have been
in mind for the the person who bought it has them in
mind that he's bringing the קרבן korban on their behalf. That is,
it's one קרבן korban brought for a large group and and therefore
it's a little bit unique. So אשכחן למצוה, לעכב מנלן? Ashkachan l'mitzvah,
l'akeiv minalan? So I understand that that's a positive requirement, but how
do I know that it's מעכב? ma'akeiv? We know that in קדשים
Kodashim we have this general rule that שינה הכתוב לעכב, shina hakasuv
l'akeiv, that everything that's repeated now twice, duplicated, is because it creates
a
that if you don't do it then it was disqualified. So it
creates a higher level of threshold to prove that something is actually
necessary, not just mandatory, but necessary. אמר קרא וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך.
Amar kra vezavachta Pesach l'Hashem Elokecha.
So וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך Vezavachta Pesach l'Hashem Elokecha also means you
have to וזבחת, vezavachta, you have to bring the קרבן korban and
it has to be brought as a פסח, Pesach, that is you
have to have in mind that it's for the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. So מתקיף לה רב ספרא, Matkif lah Rav Safra, רב ספרא
Rav Safra
challenges this based on based on a logical question. So האי וזבחת
להכי הוא
דאתא? Hai vezavachta l'hachi hu de'asa? Is that what you're using the
word וזבחת vezavachta to mean? האי מיבעי ליה לכדרב נחמן. Hai mibai
lei l'chiderav Nachman. You need it to teach what רב נחמן Rav
Nachman taught, דאמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה מנין למותר פסח
שקרב שלמים? d'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha minal l'mosar Pesach
shekarev shelamim? How do I know that leftover קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach?
That is, the sheep was meant to be a קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, it was bought to be a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and
it's hanging out, 14th of ניסן Nisan comes, 14th of ניסן Nisan
goes, it's the end of פסח Pesach now, whatever, it's חול המועד.
Chol HaMoed. So now, how do I know that the animal which
had been designated as a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach could be brought
as a שלמים? Shelamim? שנאמר וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך צאן ובקר. Shene'emar
vezavachta Pesach l'Hashem Elokecha tzon uvakar. You can bring the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach
as a sheep or a cow. והלא אין פסח בא אלא מן
הכבשים ומן העזים. Vahalo ein Pesach ba ela min hakesavim umin haizim.
But I know the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach can only be a
sheep, not a cow. מכאן למותר הפסח שיהיו לדבר הבא מן הצאן
ומן הבקר. Mikan l'mosar haPesach sheyihyu l'davar haba min hatzon umin habakar.
That leftover קרבן פסח Korban Pesach animals could be redesignated as something
which could be either sheep or cattle, therefore קרבן שלמים. Korban Shelamim.
ומאי ניהו? שלמים. Umai nihu? Shelamim. So that's רב נחמן'ס Rav Nachman's
teaching. That is, וזבחת פסח לה' אלוהיך צאן ובקר Vezavachta Pesach l'Hashem
Elokecha tzon uvakar comes to teach me that the leftover animals from
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach could be used as a שלמים, Shelamim,
and therefore I don't have that as a שינה הכתוב לעכב, shina
hakasuv l'akeiv, a second verse teaching me about שינוי בעלים. shinuy baalim.
אלא אמר רב ספרא, Ela amar Rav Safra, רב ספרא Rav Safra
has to say instead, וזבחת פסח vezavachta Pesach לכדרב נחמן l'chiderav Nachman
comes to teach what רב נחמן Rav Nachman taught, that it could
be brought as a שלמים, Shelamim, שמור את חודש האביב Shamor es
chodesh ha'Aviv למצוה, l'mitzvah, and the פסוק pasuk שמור את חודש האביב
ועשית פסח Shamor es chodesh ha'Aviv ve'asisa Pesach comes to teach. Teach
me the מצוה, mitzvah, the requirement that it has to be לשם
פסח, l'shem pesach, בשינוי קודש, be'shinui kodesh, ואמרתם זבח פסח, ve'amartem zevach
pesach, בשינוי בעלים be'shinui be'alim למצוה, l'mitzvah, and the ואמרתם זבח פסח
ve'amartem zevach pesach is about שינוי בעלים shinui be'alim למצוה. l'mitzvah. Who?
לעכב. le'akeiv. בין הכא והכא אשכחן זביחה. bein hacha ve'hacha ashkechan zvicha.
So how do I learn לעכב? le'akeiv? So because both of these
בין הכא להכא ואשכחן זביחה. bein hacha l'hacha v'ashkechan zvicha. All of
them mention זביחה, zvicha, the שחיטה. shechita. שאר עבודות מנלן? sha'ar avodot
minalan? How do I know all of the other עבודות avodot of
the קרבן? korban? הואיל וגלי גלי, ho'il v'galli galli, once the תורה
Torah has revealed this principle about the שחיטה, shechita, so apply the
same principle across the board for the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Oh,
I saw the recorder here, I'm recording it on YouTube so I'll
have to hold the thing. Okay.
רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב אשי Rav Ashi said הואיל
וגלי גלי לא אמרינן. ho'il v'galli galli lo amrinan. We don't say
that once it's been made clear in one context we can extend
it to the other three עבודות. avodot. לא אמרינן. lo amrinan. אלא
עבודות מנלן? ella avodot minalan? Where do I learn the other three
עבודות avodot from? That they have to be לשם פסח l'shem pesach
for the קרבן פסח? korban pesach? דכתיב, dichtiv, זאת התורה לעולה ולמנחה
ולחטאת ולאשם ולמילואים
ולזבח השלמים,
zot ha'Torah
l'olah v'l'minchah v'l'chatat v'la'asham v'l'miluim v'l'zevach hashelamim, right?
So it doesn't mention פסח, pesach, but anyway. ותניא, v'tanya, ביום צוותו
בני ישראל להקריב את קרבניהם. beyom tzavoto b'nei Yisrael l'hakriv et korbeneihem.
So at the day that God commanded the Jewish people to bring
their sacrifices, זה
בכור ומעשר ופסח. ze bechor u'ma'aser v'pesach. So that, right, ביום צוותו
בני ישראל להקריב את קרבניהם, beyom tzavoto b'nei Yisrael l'hakriv et korbeneihem,
their קרבנות. korbanot. So the קרבנות korbanot that really belong to you
more than any other are the בכור, מעשר, ופסח. bechor, ma'aser, v'pesach.
The three lowest level קדושה kedushah קרבנות, korbanot, right? If you have
in mind your, everyone should learn קרבנות korbanot in the morning, you
learn פרק ה perek heh of זבחים Zevachim very well. So the
משנה Mishnah איזהו מקומן, eizehu mekoman, starting from the most holiest קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim and then going the חטאת chatat and then
עולה, אשם, שלמים. olah, asham, shelamim. And then after שלמים shelamim we
have תודה todah and איל נזיר eil nazir which are sort of
second level kind of like a שלמים shelamim level. And then the
last משנה Mishnah dealing with the בכור, מעשר, ופסח. bechor, ma'aser, v'pesach.
בכור, מעשר, ופסח bechor, ma'aser, v'pesach are the lowest level קדושה kedushah
קרבנות. korbanot. So those three, and because they're most associated with the
owner. The בכור bechor it belongs to me and I have to
give it to the כהן. kohen. The מעשר ma'aser I get to
eat myself. There's a strange ריטב״א Ritva in מסכת שבת, Masechet Shabbat,
and פסח pesach also. It's mine, I have to eat it myself,
I share it with my whole family, whatever, the sense that it
belongs to you even more so. That's why it's called קרבניהם. korbeneihem.
So היקישה הכתוב לשלמים. hikishah hakatuv l'shelamim. So that פסוק pasuk connects
the idea of those three, the קדשים קלים kodashim kalim with the
שלמים. shelamim. So מה שלמים בין שינוי קודש בין שינוי בעלים בעינן
למצוה, mah shelamim bein shinui kodesh bein shinui be'alim ba'inan l'mitzvah, אף
כל
בין שינוי קודש בין שינוי בעלים למצוה. af kol bein shinui kodesh
bein shinui be'alim l'mitzvah. So we have set up the first part,
which is that there's a requirement that they have to be done
לשמה. lishmah. וקשלמים, u'k'shelamim, and they're comparable to שלמים shelamim in what
way? מה שלמים בין זביחה בין שאר עבודות לא חלק בהם למצוה.
mah shelamim bein zvicha bein sha'ar avodot lo chailak bahem l'mitzvah. So
there's no distinction by the קרבן שלמים korban shelamim whether it has
to be done לשמה lishmah between the זביחה zvicha and the other
three עבודות, avodot, קבלה, הולכה, וזריקה. kabalah, holachah, v'zrikah. So אף פסח
לא תחלוק בו בין זביחה
לשאר עבודות. af pesach lo tachlok bo bein zvicha l'sha'ar avodot. You
shouldn't distinguish between the שחיטה shechita and the other three עבודות. avodot.
לעכב, le'akeiv, so where do I learn that it's לעכב, le'akeiv, that
it's actually if I didn't do it לשמה lishmah the קרבן korban
is
disqualified? אלא הוא למה לי? ella hu lamah li? So why does
it say הוא? hu?
So if it's תניא v'tanya נאמר בפסח הוא בשחיטה לעכב. ne'emar b'pesach
hu b'shechita le'akeiv. So it says the word הוא, hu, that פסח
הוא. pesach hu. So בשחיטה לעכב. b'shechita le'akeiv. So that tells me
that the שחיטה, shechita, if I don't have in mind that it's
a פסח pesach when I'm doing the שחיטה, shechita, that it's לעכב,
le'akeiv, actually disqualify. אבל אשם לא נאמר בו הוא. aval asham lo
ne'emar bo hu. קרבן אשם korban asham interestingly enough doesn't use the
word הוא. hu. אלא לאחר הקטרת אימורין. ella le'achar haktarat imurin. והוא
עצמו
שלא הוקטרו
אימוריו כשר.
ve'hu atzmo
shelo hukteru imurav kasher. So it actually comes to teach that the
קרבן אשם korban asham as well, if the קרבן אשם korban asham
afterward, one of the steps which is not one of the four
עבודות avodot is burning the fats on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So a
קרבן אשם korban asham that you post facto didn't burn the fats
on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, actually it's totally kosher and you didn't disqualify
the קרבן אשם korban asham in that case. So on the one
hand the word הוא hu by the קרבן פסח korban pesach comes
to teach me that it's מעכב me'akeiv to have קרבן פסח korban
pesach done לשמה, lishmah, and on the other hand the absence of
the word הוא hu in the context of the קרבן אשם korban
asham comes to teach if the קרבן אשם korban asham you didn't
bring the אימורים imurim to the מזבח mizbe'ach that retroactively it's still
okay. Yeah, Charlie, take the question.
The פסח pesach doesn't have the portions that are burned on the
altar?
No, קרבן פסח korban pesach the only thing, certain קרבן פסח korban
pesach no, the חלב, chelev, the real inner חלב chelev has to
still go on the מזבח mizbe'ach pretty sure,
but but none of the, it doesn't have any big pieces of
meat that go on the מזבח mizbe'ach
and it doesn't have the gifts that are separate for the כהן.
kohen.
No, there's nothing that goes to the כהן. kohen. The owner gets
everything with his
friends and family.
The normal rule for a קרבן שלמים korban shelamim is the שוק
shok and the חזה. chazeh. And the חזה chazeh go to the
כהן. kohen. But with the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, there's no parts
that go to the כהן. kohen. Actually, I heard one interpretation—I forget
who said this—one interpretation of the word שלמים, shelamim, why is it
called a קרבן שלמים? korban shelamim? Because it brings שלום. shalom. Why?
Because everyone gets a piece as it were, right? Part of it
goes to the מזבח, mizbeach, part of it goes to the כהן,
kohen, and part of it goes to the owner. Every other קרבן,
korban, right? קרבן חטאת korban chatas goes to the מזבח mizbeach and
goes to the כהן, kohen, but the owner doesn't get to eat
any because it's—you're atoning for your sin, you did something wrong, so
you have to give it for somebody else. קרבן עולה, korban olah,
nobody eats it, right? And
so the קרבן חטאת—השם eats it! Right, but that's my point, meaning
that it doesn't go to any human to eat it. So a
קרבן שלמים, korban shelamim, there's a part that goes to the מזבח,
mizbeach, part that goes to the כהן, kohen, and part that goes
to the owner. It's like one happy family. All right, wonderful. Everyone
had a piece. יישר כוח! Yasher koach! It's a long דף, daf,
but we got through it.
Yeah, we did!
Oh yes, we did!