Boker tov. Today's דף Daf is דף ה, Daf He, five, and
it is also the 18th day in the עומר. Omer. We pick
up in the middle of יום הזכרון, Yom HaZikaron, and
we pick up in the middle of ד' עמוד ב' Dalet amud
bet where it says if you look at the תוספות Tosafot שקולין
הן Shkulin Heim and go across from that תוספות Tosafot about three
lines down it says רבינא אמר. Ravina Amar. Okay, so we're in
the middle of discussing how you know this idea that you require
לכתחילה L'chatchila to have לשמה Lishmah when you slaughter and do all
the various עבודות Avodot by קדשים, Kadshim, and then how did we
sort of establish that the other day? זבח שלמים, Zevach Shlamim, the
זביחה Zevicha should be לשם שלמים, L'shem Shlamim, the slaughtering should be
for the sake of it being a שלמים, Shlamim, and then we
sort of had other ways of expanding it to the other עבודות,
Avodot, and then we wanted to say how do you know it
has to be לשם בעלים L'shem be'alim for the sake of the
owners. So to some degree that answer was because it repeats this
idea of זבח שלמים, Zevach Shlamim, so since it's redundant or זבח
תודה, Zevach todah, whatever, תודה שלמיו, Todah shlamav, we say not only
for the sake of the sacrifice, for the sake of the owners.
The one פסוק Pasuk that we had that a little bit sort
of like was more specific about the idea of the owners was
the פסוק Pasuk about ונרצה לו לכפר עליו. Ve-nirtzah lo l'chaper alav.
So לכפר עליו, L'chaper alav, the כפרה Kappara is with the דם,
Dam, so that's about the זריקה Zerika but עליו Alav for the
owner. And I should remind you that the idea that it has
to be for the sake of the owner is because the idea
of the owner is really only specifically about who the כפרה Kappara
is for, and that's the זריקת הדם. Zerikas hadam. Even when we
say the other עבודות Avodot have to be for the sake of
the owner, what we mean is that when you שחט Shecht it,
you have to, meaning it's also סתמא Stama works. But the issue
is having in mind when I'm שחט Shechting it, who am I
planning on doing the זריקת הדם Zerikas hadam for? On behalf of
whom am I doing this זריקת הדם? Zerikas hadam? Ultimately it's all
rooted in the זריקת הדם. Zerikas hadam. If somebody שחט Shechts it
and isn't thinking about the זריקת הדם Zerikas hadam and is thinking
about the wrong owner, it's not a problem. So there it's important
to remember that difference that while all four עבודות Avodot have to
be לשם L'shem the right קרבן, Korban, and again when we're saying
לשם L'shem it really means it can't be actively for a different
קרבן, Korban, that's the issue of סתמא Stama whatever. But when we
say it has to be for the sake of the right owner,
we really only mean that the זריקה Zerika has to be for
the sake of the right owner. And if you're doing the שחיטה
Shechita and the קבלה Kabbalah or whatever, if as long as you're,
you know, there you could invalidate it if you're planning on how,
who you're going to do the זריקה Zerika for. For whom you're
going to do the זריקה, Zerika, but the act intrinsically there's not
an issue of owners. Owners are rooted in the זריקת הדם, Zerikas
hadam, לכפר עליו. L'chaper alav. Okay, so that's where we sort of
were yesterday. Okay, so but now the גמרא Gemara has a question
about how we know the other עבודות. Avodot. All right, and one
of the ways it wanted to learn it out was sort of
like from another פסוק, Pasuk, את האיל יעשה זבח שלמים לה', Es
ha-ayil ya'aseh zevach shlamim l'Hashem, and that's again it talks about זבח,
Zevach, זביחה, Zevicha, but we want to sort of expand it to
include all types of עבודות. Avodot. The גמרא Gemara had a problem
that it was a כלל ופרט, Klal u'prat, and now we're going
to see רבינא's Ravina answer. רבינא אמר Ravina amar after the word
ופרט: U'prat: לעולם דנין. L'olam donim. Actually זבח שלמים לה', Zevach shlamim
l'Hashem, you know, would have been a case of a כלל ופרט,
Klal u'prat, excuse me, את האיל יעשה זבח שלמים לה', Es ha-ayil
ya'aseh zevach shlamim l'Hashem, so יעשה Ya'aseh and שלמים Shlamim are like
the כלל Klal and זבח Zevach is the פרט, Prat, and we
could have said that was a כלל ופרט Klal u'prat and limited
it to זביחה. Zevicha. But לעולם דנין L'olam donim ולה' חוזר וכלל.
V'l'Hashem chozer v'klal. But it says when it says יעשה זבח שלמים
לה', Ya'aseh zevach shlamim l'Hashem, so יעשה Ya'aseh is the כלל, Klal,
any type of the עבודה, Avodah, זבח Zevach is the פרט, Prat,
זביחה, Zevicha, and לה' L'Hashem is again seen as another כלל, Klal,
any type of עבודה. Avodah. So it's a כלל פרט וכלל Klal
prat u'klal and that allows us to expand beyond זביחה Zevicha to
include the other עבודות. Avodos. Okay, אמר ליה רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא,
Amar leh Rav Achai mi-Difti l'Ravina, Rav Achai mi-Difti said to Ravina:
והלא לא דמי כללא קמא לכללא בתרא. V'halo lo dami klala kama
l'klala basra. But the כללים Klalim are not the same. Why is
that? כללא קמא מר בעשיות, Klala kama mar b'asiyos,
יעשה Ya'aseh which is all the things that really are central in
making it a קרבן, Korban, which are the classic four עבודות: Avodot:
שחיטה, Shechita, קבלה, Kabbalah, הולכה, Holacha, and זריקה. Zerika. Okay, so the
יעשה Ya'aseh would have included all the עבודות Avodos which is exactly
where we want to get to. Okay, but that would, but wait
a minute, ותו לא כללא בתרא V'sulo klala basra nothing more. The
last כלל Klal לה' L'Hashem is כולו לה', Kulo l'Hashem, what would
mean any part of the עבודת הקרבן Avodas hakorban that is לה'.
L'Hashem. It's not just the things that make it a קרבן. Korban.
So what other עבודות Avodot does that include? So ואפילו שפיכת שיריים,
V'afillu shefichas shirayim, even the stuff that after it's a כשר קרבן
Kosher korban you've already thrown the blood, there's still other things to
be done, spilling out the remainder of the blood on the base,
והקטרת אמורים, V'haktaras emurim, burning
the innerds on the altar. Okay, so therefore it's not a classic
כלל פרט וכלל. Klal prat u'klal. So again what we're trying to
do is know how do you know the other עבודות Avodot have
to be לשם בעלים? L'shem be'alim? So we have the פסוק Pasuk
of ונרצה לו לכפר עליו.
Ve-nirtzah
lo l'chaper alav. So עליו Alav means בעלים, Be'alim,
and לכפר L'chaper is דם, Dam, is זריקת הדם. Zerikas hadam. Okay,
that's classically what לכפר L'chaper is. So that's one פסוק, Pasuk, but
that's זריקה. Zerika. How do you know the other things? Okay. Okay,
so we have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk* about ייעשה זבח שלמים zevach
shelamim להשם *ye'aseh zevach
shelamim l'Hashem*. So that's extra, so we're going to interpret it for
the בעלים ba'alim. *be'alim*. זבח *zevach* here is, okay, זביחה *zevicha*, obviously,
שחיטה shechitah *shechita*. Okay. Okay,
but we still don't know the other two עבודות avodos, *avodot*. So
we want to say כלל ופרט וכלל *klal u-prat u-klal* and we're
going to expand this idea of שחיטה *shechita* to include other things.
So ייעשה *ye'aseh* is a כלל *klal*, anything, and להשם *l'Hashem* is
another כלל *klal* for any type of עבודה *avodah*. Okay, but the
problem is is that ייעשה *ye'aseh* is what makes it a קרבן
korban *korban*, the four classic עבודות avodot *avodot*, which is where we're
trying to go to. But the extra להשם *l'Hashem*, anything you're doing
להשם *l'Hashem* would include all the עבודות avodot *avodot* and therefore even
the stuff after it was a kosher קרבן korban *korban* and therefore
it's not a classic כלל ופרט וכלל *klal u-prat u-klal* because the
two כללים *klalim* are not the same. That's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s
question. So let's see what it says.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s answer is, האי תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל
*hai tanna d'vei Rabbi Yishmael*, this is the תנא *tanna* from the
house of רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael*, בכללו ופרטו דריש כי האי גוונא
*b'chlalu u-prati darish ki hai gavna* that he does a כלל ופרט
*klal u-prat* that type of a way. He doesn't matter, he's not
so, you know, again רבי ישמעאל *Rabbi Yishmael* is sort of דיברה
תורה Torah כלשון בני אדם *dibra Torah k'lashon bnei adam*, he's a
little looser and he's willing to consider that a כלל ופרט וכלל
*klal u-prat u-klal* even though the last כלל *klal* is a broader
כלל *klal* than the first one. So what is the כלל ופרט
וכלל *klal u-prat u-klal*? So how are we going to get here
to the other עבודות *avodot*? Let's take a look. כלל ופרט וכלל
*klal u-prat u-klal*, יצא דנא כעין הפרט *yatza dana k'ein haprat*, it
has to be similar to the פרט *prat* in the middle. מה
הפרט מפורש עבודה ובעינן לשמה l'shma *mah haprat meforash avodah u-vinan lishma*?
So the פרט *prat* is זבח *zevach*, is שחיטה *shechita*, that's an
עבודה *avodah* and it needs to be לשמה lishma. *lishma*. Here we
mean לשם בעלים l'shem ba'alim *l'sheim be'alim*. אף כל עבודה בעינן לשמן
*af kol avodah beinan lishman*. It's true by all the עבודות *avodot*.
One minute says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. You can't necessarily go from
שחיטה *shechita* to all the עבודות *avodot*, the four classic עבודות *avodot*.
אם מה הפרט מפורש עבודה וחייבין עליה בחוץ *im mah haprat meforash
avodah vechayavin aleha bachutz*, I might say שחיטה *shechita* has a unique
characteristic. שחיטה *shechita* is one of the four עבודות *avodot* that you're
חייב *chayav* if you bring a קרבן korban *korban* outside the בית
המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. אף כל עבודה וחייבין עליה בחוץ *af kol avodah
vechayavin aleha bachutz*. I'll expand it, כלל ופרט וכלל *klal u-prat u-klal*
means expand, but it doesn't mean go overboard. So I'll expand it
to other עבודות *avodot* that are so powerful that even if you
do them out of the בית המקדש, that those are the ones
that are forbidden out of the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*. What is
that? שחיטה וזריקה *shechita u-zrika*, slaughtering and sprinkling of the blood or
throwing of the blood. Those are the two. אין *in*, yes, קבלה
kabalah. והולכה לא *kabbala v'holacha lo*, I'm not going to be able
to expand that to get me to קבלה kabalah *kabbala* and הולכה
holacha, *holacha*. And by the way we don't even need זריקה zrikah
*zrika* because we have זריקה zrikah *zrika* from up here. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says even with your כלל ופרט וכלל *klal u-prat
u-klal* how do you get beyond שחיטה *shechita* and זריקה zrikah, *zrika*?
If something similar to שחיטה *shechita* is זריקה zrikah, *zrika*, not necessarily
the other two. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says אינמי *inami*, or
maybe I'll expand it but go in a different direction but still
not be all inclusive. מה הפרט מפורש דבר טעון צפון *mah haprat
meforash davar taun tzafun*, שחיטה *shechita* is something that you have to
do at the צפון *tzafun* of the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*. וישנו בחטאת
הפנימיות *v'yeshno b'chatat hapnimiyot* and even in an inner חטאת chatas, *chatat*
based on what? Okay, fine, but at some times and even in
an inner חטאת chatas *chatat* you have to, even a חטאת chatas,
*chatat* that the blood is sprinkled on the inside. As long as
it doesn't, right? I understand, yes, yes, yes. And even, well that
too, okay anyway, and even but it has that quality. And even
for an inner חטאת chatas *chatat*, a חטאת chatat *chatat* that's blood
is sprinkled on the inside, you know, inside the היכל *heichal*, okay,
which is not זריקה zrikah. *zrika*, it's sort of applied with the
finger on the altar, on the inner altar, the incense altar. Okay,
so so that doesn't have זריקה *zrika*. But what does, but שחיטה
*shechita* is always applies by all the קרבנות korbanos, *korbanot* and it
has this unique characteristic that sometimes it needs to be at the
צפון *tzafun* of the altar. So I'll limit it to things that
are like שחיטה *shechita*. אף כל הטעון צפון וישנו בחטאת הפנימיות *af
kol hataun tzafun v'yeshno b'chatat hapnimiyot*, I'll include other things that sometimes
demand צפון *tzafun* of the altar and that apply to the חטאות
פנימיות *chataot pnimiyot*. What are they? שחיטה וקבלה *shechita v'kabbala*. Everything you
slaughter, everything you slaughter at the צפון *tzafun*, well not everything on
the צפון *tzafun*, but anyway those that you slaughter at the צפון
*tzafun* you also catch the blood at the צפון *tzafun*. Okay, but
the reason but this excludes זריקה *zrika*. Why does this exclude זריקה
*zrika*? זריקה *zrika* isn't limited to the צפון *tzafun* of the מזבח
mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* obviously. זריקה *zrika*'s like all around the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach*
and so on. And זריקה *zrika* is not for the חטאות פנימיות
*chataot pnimiyot*, the חטאות פנימיות *chataot pnimiyot* the blood is placed with
the finger on the incense altar, it's not זריקה *zrika*. So if
I'm going to expand שחיטה *shechita*, I could expand it two ways.
I could expand it to include זריקה *zrika* because of the principle
of ישנו בחוץ *yeshno bachutz*, things that apply even in the prohibition
of שחוטי חוץ *shechutei chutz*. Or I could expand it to include
קבלה kabalah. *kabbala* because it has the similar characteristics of צפון *tzafun*
and חטאות פנימיות *chataot pnimiyot*.
Okay, but that doesn't apply but ישנו בחוץ
*yeshno bachutz* doesn't apply to קבלה kabalah, *kabbala*, that's not prohibited outside
the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* for a קרבן korban. *korban* or at
least you don't get כרת *kares* or whatever. And the idea of
doing it in the צפון *tzafun* and the חטאות פנימיות *chataot pnimiyot*
don't apply to זריקה *zrika*. So how do I know to have
this expand to include everything? I could based on which characteristic I
emphasize I could get a little bit of an expansion, but I'm
not going to have it include all four עבודות *avodot*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says let's take a look. Take
a look. אף כל התם שיש בחטאות הפנימיות שחיטה וקבלה אין זריקה
לא. So the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is fine you answered your question
already. איכא למימר הכי ואיכא למימר הכי. Ika lemaimar hachi ve'ika lemaimar
hachi. Since you can expand it either way, and there's no way
to determine which way is the right way to go, so שקולים
הם, shkulim hem, so they're both equivalent. ויבואו שניהם, veyavo'u shneihem, and
we'll go we'll interpret it both ways. Since there's no way to
say whether the logical expansion is in this way or in that
direction, so that tells us that actually it should be expanded to
include both. That's like type of a principle that the גמרא Gemara
uses sometimes. Since you don't know which way to go and they're
both equivalent ways you could go with the דרשה, drasha, the דרשה
drasha applies equally to both. Now
the question is what about הולכה, holacha right, what about carrying the
blood? And the answer is הולכה holacha, always is sort of a
sort of like the you know the sort of like the the
black sheep or whatever, the one anyway the one that doesn't get
enough attention anyway. So it gets wrapped up in קבלה. Okay, קבלה
is assumed to include הולכה, holacha. and therefore since we've got that,
we've now expanded it to include all the עבודות לשם בעלים. avodos
l'shem ba'alim. Okay, לשנא אחרינא, lishna achrina, another way, which is not
another approach, but another way of another terminology to use to this
idea that they're equivalent and just include both, is חדא
וחדא תקי במילתא, chada vechada teki bemilsa, so each one, which is
another way of saying שקולים הם, shkulim hem, each one since you
can go each way, each one gets established, we do it each
way, we do both. Okay, אי בעית אימא, I bayit eima, now
okay, so that's how we expand it to include all four. אי
בעית אימא, I bayit eima, or I could say the following. זריקה
מדרב אשי נפקא. Zrikah mid'Rav Ashi nafka. We don't we would know
not to do the זריקה approach because זריקה we get from this
פסוק ונרצה לו לכפר עליו. pasuk v'nirtzah lo l'chaper alav. So since
we've already included זריקה, we obviously that's not where we should be
expanding, we've already covered that. That tells us to expand and include
קבלה. And once we include קבלה, we also get הולכה. Okay, so
the combination of these פסוקים psukim you get זריקה, you get שחיטה
and then because of כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal you expand
it and now you have all the עבודות לשם בעלים. avodos l'shem
ba'alim. אשכחן איל נזיר. Ashkachan eil nazir. Okay, now this is the
question that Michael asked I think at the beginning of yesterday when
I was in here briefly, which is all of these דרשות drashos
of לשם l'shem you know for the sake of the קרבן korban.
and for the sake of the owners are all by שלמים shlamim
cases. How do you know to expand it? Now you could say
שלמים shlamim is like the weakest of the קרבנות, korbanos. it's קדשים
קלים kodashim kalim or whatever, certainly it would apply to the more
weighted ones, but we will see that there's ways in which שלמים
shlamim have more components and more demands, so it's not obvious you
can go from שלמים shlamim to all the other קרבנות. korbanos? So
let's take a look. So now we're so that's our next move.
To not expand to the עבודות, we've got the idea that all
four עבודות לשמה, avodos l'shma, all four of the עבודות לשם בעלים,
avodos l'shem ba'alim, although again לשם בעלים leshein ba'alim is a focus
on the זריקה. And now we want to know how to apply
it beyond the קרבן korban that we started with.
Elazar asks that question. Answer it.
Fine, okay, all right good.
אשכחן איל נזיר. Ashkachan eil nazir. That is the איל נזיר. eil
nazir. שאר שלמים מנלן? Sha'ar shlamim minalan? This anyway all of this
just starts with the איל נזיר. eil nazir. How do you go
to other שלמים? shlamim? Even get to שלמים shlamim in general. So
וכי תימא נילף מאיל נזיר, vechi teima neilef me'eil nazir, let's apply
it from איל נזיר. eil nazir. לא מה לאיל נזיר שכן יש
עמו דמים אחרים. Lo mah l'eil nazir sheken yesh imo damim acherim.
איל נזיר Eil nazir comes with an עולה olah and a חטאת,
chatat so maybe there are particular heavy requirements by that. So no,
אם כן נכתוב רחמנא נכתוב שלמי, im ken nichtov rachmana nichtov shalmei,
okay, which is a funny thing because the word is שלמים shlamim
but זבח שלמי, zevach shalmei, why didn't it say זבח שלמי, zevach
shalmei, it's שלמי shalmei or whatever. So מאי שלמים, mai shlamim, why
in the plural? לרבות כל השלמים, lerabos kol hashlamim, all שלמים shlamim
have this requirement. Fine, okay, so these requirements are by שלמים shlamim
in general but still how do you get by שלמים shlamim to
all the other קרבנות? korbanos. אשכחן שלמים שאר כל קדשים מנלן? Ashkachan
shlamim sh'ar kol kodashim minalan? How do you know the other קדשים?
kodashim? So the גמרא Gemara says וכי תימא נילף משלמים vechi teima
neilef mishlamim let's apply from שלמים shlamim which makes sense, שלמים shlamim
is like at the bottom of the level of hierarchy of קרבנות.
korbanos: No, מה לשלמים שכן טעונים סמיכה ונסכים ותנופה חזה ושוק. Mah
lishlamim sheken te'unim smichah unesachim utnuphah chazeh vashok. שלמים Shlamim have a
lot of things you do, extra components. Okay, you put your hands
on the קרבן korban. that's a סמיכה smichah on the head of
the קרבן. korban Okay, you bring the flour and the wine together
with it and the you do you know you do a waving
of the and a waving of the breast and of the thigh.
So you don't do all three of those with any other קרבן.
korban, A lot of most basically almost all קרבן korban you do
סמיכה, smichah, the hands on the head, with the exception of like
בכור מעשר פסח. bechor ma'aser pesach. Okay, סמיכה smichah fine is pretty
much by all קרבן. korban, But the נסכים nesachim is only by
a קרבן korban that is basically a free will קרבן, korban, a
שלמים shlamim or an עולה. olah. You do not bring the נסכים
nesachim by a חטאת chatas and an אשם. asham. Okay, and the
waving of the חזה ושוק chazeh vashok that's only the שלמים. shlamim.
So the שלמים shlamim is certainly the only one that has all
of these components, okay? So now the גמרא Gemara says so maybe
that's why it has the לשמה lishma? requirement. אלא אמר קרא, Ella
amar kra, here's how we get once you get it for one
קרבן korban, we're going to be able to expand it. זאת התורה.
Zot haTorah. זאת התורה לעולה ולמנחה ולחטאת ולאשם ולמלואים ולזבח השלמים. Zos
hatorah la'olah lamincha ulechattas vela'asham velamiluim ulzevach hashelamim. This is the law,
and it lists all the קרבנות: korbanos. the עולה, olah, the מנחה,
mincha, the חטאת, chatas, the אשם, asham, and the זבח שלמים shelamim,
and the מלואים miluim which is not
לדורות. le'doros. הקישנו כתוב לשלמים, Hikishanu kasuv leshlamim, everything is connected to
שלמים, shelamim and it works well here because שלמים shelamim is at
the end. So that actually emphasizes an idea that we're taking שלמים
shelamim, and expanding it to everything else. Okay? מה שלמים בין שינוי
קודש בין שינוי בעלים בעינן לשמה, Ma shelamim bein shinuy kodesh bein
shinuy ba'alim ba'inu lishma, the same way קדשים kodshim שלמים, shelamim there's
an issue of doing it לשם בעלים leshein ba'alim, and לשם leshein
the right קרבן, korban אף כל בין שינוי קודש בין שינוי בעלים
בעינן לשמה. af kol bein shinuy kodesh bein shinuy ba'alim ba'inu lishma.
Okay, fine, that's how we know it, and now, that was sort
of like the end of yesterday, we have פסוקים pesukim that tell
me you need it to be לשם קרבן, leshein korban, לשם בעלים,
l'shem ba'alim. again, סתם stam also works, and it's basically by שלמים
shlamim and we've expanded it to all the קרבנות. korbanot. So now
we've established point number one, that you need לשמה. lishma Now we
have to move on to point number two. What happens when you
don't have לשמה? lishma The משנה Mishna tells you, other than a
חטאת chatas and a פסח, pesach, the קרבן korban, is כשר kasher
but it doesn't count for the owners. Where do you know that
idea? How do you move on to that idea? So that's the
next thing, that's what we're going to focus on today. Okay, so
let's take a look. So גמרא Gemara says like this, אימא, ema,
now why don't I say, four lines from the bottom,
היכא
דשחטיה שלא לשמה ליפסלו? heicha deshachatei shelo lishma lifselu? If you need
לשמה lishma when you do it שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, it should
be invalid. Now before we go on I want to say an
important point, which is that, which is that, I guess here, I'm
sorry, remind me name again? Fred. Fred was using your גמרא, Gemara
so it's, I'm sorry, okay. We'll have to bring up, if you
can find, yeah, I mean that'd be great, I haven't brought them
up yet. Oh, coming, yeah, I
don't know.
Here, I'll give you this.
It'll open the door at the other end. Okay, tell you the
code offline.
Okay, anyway, okay, so first of all, here's an important principle. The
important principle is that by קדשים, kodshim, normally if the תורה Torah
says you need something, if you don't have it it's invalid. The
תורה Torah says I don't know, by a לולב, lulav, it has
to be or an אתרוג, esrog, פרי עץ הדר. pri eitz hadar.
So if it's not הדר, hadar, if it's not beautiful, it's פסול,
pasul, okay? It has ערבי נחל arvei nachal and we learn out,
you know, the question about, you know, we learn out certain things,
and if it doesn't have those criteria it's פסול. pasul. Like whenever
we learn a requirement in the תורה Torah we assume if the
thing doesn't have that requirement it's invalid. Okay? So by קדשים, kodshim,
it's because there are so many, this is my interpretation of it.
I'll tell you about the rule. The rule is, something is not
a requirement, is not assumed, the absence of satisfying a requirement by
קדשים kodshim is not assumed to make the thing invalid unless the
תורה Torah repeats the requirement twice. Until it שנה עליו הכתוב לעכב.
shina alav hakatuv le'akeiv. Okay, my interpretation of that is that since
there are שנה עליו הכתוב לעכב.
shina alav
hakatuv le'akeiv. It has to repeat it twice in order to say
that without doing that requirement it's invalid. Again, we'd never say this
for anything else, right? תפילין, tefillin, you know, if you had three
פרשיות parshiyos it's invalid, it doesn't have to say that twice, okay?
But by קדשים, kodshim, my read is, since there are so many
requirements, okay, the presumption is that they're not all מעכב, me'akeiv, and
that the תורה Torah has to say it twice to tell you
that it is. So the question is, say that again. What? I
did say that again, right, exactly. So anyway, so good, so the
point is the גמרא Gemara says, well if it's not לשמה lishma
it should be invalid. So why does the גמרא Gemara assume if
it's not לשמה lishmah it should be invalid even if it's a
requirement? So I just want to show you that תוספות Tosafos asks
that question. If you look at the תוספות, Tosafos, אימא היכא דשחטיה
שלא לשמה ליפסלו. Eima heicha deshachatei shelo lishma lifselu. תימא הא בכל
דוכתא בעניין קדשים, Teima habochu duchtei be'inyan kodshim, every place when we're
dealing with קדשים, kodshim, בעינן בקדשים, be'ainan bekodshim, excuse me, we require
by קדשים, kodshim, שנה לעכב. shina le'akeiv. It has to repeat it
to tell you that if you don't do it it's invalid. והכא
לא שנה, Ve'hacha lo shina, it didn't repeat it, so why is
the גמרא Gemara asking "Oh it should be invalid if you don't
do לשמה"? lishmah, So I wanted you more to see the question,
we'll do one part of the answer. ויש לומר דפרכינן משינוי קודש
דאיכא תרי קראי. Veyesh lomar deparkeih mishinuy kodesh de'ika trei krei. Okay,
by the idea of doing it לשם הקרבן, lesheim hakorban, there were
multiple פסוקים pesukim about that, and therefore the גמרא Gemara is saying
maybe if you don't do it it should be invalid. So whatever
the answer is, I wanted you to be aware of this principle,
that just because you require something by a קרבן, korban, the actual
initial assumption is it's not מעכב me'akeiv unless the תורה repeated twice.
But anyway, here's the גמרא's Gemara question. Okay, אימא, ema, why don't
we say, four lines from the bottom, היכא דשחטיה שלא לשמה ליפסלו?
heicha deshachatei shelo lishma lifselu? If it's שחטיה שלא לשמה shachatei shelo
lishma it should be invalid. So אמר קרא, amar kra, so how
do you know שלא לשמה shelo lishma בדיעבד bidi'avad is okay? But
it doesn't work for the owners, that's like part two of the
question. How do you know it's okay, and then how do you
know but it still doesn't, is it עולה oleh for the sake
of the owners? So אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says, מוצא
שפתיך תשמור ועשית, motza sefasecha tishmor ve'asisa, we had this at the
beginning of the first דף, daf, what comes out of your mouth
you should observe, כאשר נדרת לה' אלקיך נדבה, ka'asher nadarta l'Hashem Elokecha
nedavah, like you vowed to God a נדבה. nedavah. So the גמרא
Gemara says, what do you mean a נדבה? nedavah? You called it
a נדר. neder. האי נדבה? Hai nedavah? האי נדבה נדר הוא. hai
nedavah neder hu. Again נדר neder is when you say it's my
obligation, נדבה nedavah is when you just sanctify the animal. So what's
the פסוק pasuk: equating them? אלא ella here's how to read the
פסוק: pasuk אם כאשר נדרת עשית, im ka'asher nadarta asita, if it's
כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta, if you did it exactly as you vowed,
you said to bring an עולה olah and all the עבודות were
done for the sake of an עולה, olah, then יהי נדר, yehei
neder, then it counts as a נדר neder and you satisfy your
obligation. ואם לאו, v'im lav, but if you did it in a
different way than you vowed, you said you were going to make
an עולה olah and then you sanctified it as an עולה olah
but you שחטת shachtat it for שלמים shlamim, let's say or you
threw the blood for שלמים, shlamim so it wasn't exactly as the
sanctity dictated, then יהי נדבה, yehei nedavah, it still counts as a
קרבן, korban it's like you sanctified the animal, but it doesn't count
as a נדר, neder, it doesn't count to satisfy your personal obligation.
Again, a נדר neder is when you accept on yourself a personal
obligation. So that's the פסוק pasuk that we learn that you can
have a קרבן korban, that because you didn't do it the right
way, it's not כאשר נדרת, ka'asher nadarta, somehow it's what you were
reading not just that you somehow did one of the עבודות physically
wrong but somehow for the wrong sake, then therefore it counts as
a נדבה. nedavah. It still is a legitimate קרבן, korban. but it
does not work for the owners. Okay, so that's how we learn
out the double stage. It still works, but it doesn't work for
the owners. It works as a נדבה. nedavah. One minute. ואיצטריך מוצא
שפתיך, v'itztirich motza sefatecha, you need the פסוק pasuk, of מוצא שפתיך
motza sefatecha to tell you what happens when it's not done right,
that
it's in this middle stage. ואיצטריך זאת התורה, v'itztirich zot hatorah, you
need the זאת התורה, zot hatorah, this is pretty obvious. דאי כתב
רחמנא מוצא, de'i katav rachmana motza, if it just said this idea
that if something's not right it's in this middle stage, לא ידע
במה כתב רחמנא, lo yada bemai katav rachmana, I wouldn't know what
criteria, what problem it's talking about, what types of things have to
be done and if they're not done right, they're in this middle
stage.
במה, bemai, excuse me, I wouldn't have known במה, bemai, what's it
talking about? כתב רחמנא זאת התורה. katav rachmana zot hatorah. It says
זאת התורה לעולה ולמנחה zot hatorah l'olah v'l'minchah to tell you those
special requirements by שלמים shlamim, that all of this לשמה lishmah that
we learned by שלמים, shlamim that applies by
all קרבנות. korbanot. No, לכתחילה, lechatchilah, those demands that by שלמים shlamim
it all needs לשמה, lishmah so זאת התורה zot hatorah tells you
you need it by all קרבנות. korbanot. So that obviously you needed
the זאת התורה zot hatorah to tell you the demand of לשמה
lishmah by all קרבנות. korbanot. ואי כתב רחמנא זאת התורה, v'i katav
rachmana zot hatorah, and if it had just said that, הוי אמינא
לפסלו, hava amina lifsulo, so then I would have said okay, if
you don't have לשמה lishmah it's invalid. כתב רחמנא מוצא שפתיך. katav
rachmana motza sefatecha. Okay, that's pretty obvious. We learn out from שלמים
shlamim all the לשמה lishmah. requirements. זאת התורה zot hatorah we learn
out לעולה ולמנחה ולחטאת, l'olah v'l'minchah v'l'chatat, we learn out that those
לשמה lishmah requirements apply to all קרבנות. korbanot. And then the third
פסוק, pasuk the kicker is מוצא שפתיך תשמור ועשית motza sefatecha tishmor
ve'asita that if you don't do it correctly, it's still a כשר
kosher קרבן, korban it's a נדבה, nedavah, but it's a נדבה nedavah
meaning it's not a נדר neder so it was not עולה לבעלים
לשם חובה. oleh l'ba'alim l'shem chovah. So the combination of those three
get us where we want. By the שלמים shlamim, we have multiple
פסוקים psukim that tell us
לשמה. lishmah. Then we have זאת התורה zot hatorah and לשמה lishmah,
and לשם בעלים. l'shem ba'alim?
Whoops, בעלים. ba'alim. Then we have זאת התורה zot hatorah which tells
us
all קרבנות. korbanot That's פסוק pasuk number two or whatever group. I
mean this is a group of פסוקים. psukim. And then number three
is מוצא שפתיך motza sefatecha which tells you that it is כשר
kosher but לא עלו לבעלים. lo alu l'ba'alim. So
it's the combination of these three tell us the principles of our
משנה. mishnah.
But if we had a פסוק pasuk, that says זאת התורה zot
hatorah and says there everything is together but didn't we say it's
different that חטאת chatas, is in?
Okay, that we're going to have to learn out. How do you
know חטאת chatas has a special הלכה? halachah? It still is true
that it has the requirement of לשמה. lishmah This is telling you
that they all קרבנות korbanot. require לשמה, lishmah that the לשמה lishmah
here is required by all
קרבנות. korbanos. Okay. Alright, now let's go on. Today's דף, daf, דף
ה. daf hey. Alright. And this is going to be to some
degree, look, we're in an area,
the גמרא Gemara will move beyond all these פסוקים. psukim. We're in
the forest of the פסוקים psukim right now. We will move beyond
it. But today's דף, daf, the remainder of דף ה daf hey
will have פסוקים, psukim, but at least we're going to start right
now with an important conceptual question which is where do you get
this idea that something can count as a קרבן korban, but not
count לשם בעלים? leshem ba'alim, Like maybe such an animal doesn't
exist. Either it's a good קרבן, korban. that means it works for
the owners, or if it's not going to work for the owners
maybe it's totally a פסול pasul קרבן. korban How do you know
that you can have, I mean yes you have this פסוק, pasuk
but conceptually where do you get this from? So that's what the
גמרא Gemara is now going to shift to. Okay, and it starts
with a great little visual story. It says like this: רמי ריש
לקיש. rami Reish Lakish. So normally when you say רמי rami it
means you're going to throw a... to, you know, ברייתות braisos together
and show a contradiction. Okay, but here ריש לקיש Reish Lakish is
not throwing two Tannaitic sources. רמי ריש לקיש אל מעוהי, Rami Reish
Lakish al me'ohi, he threw himself on his stomach, okay, and בבי
מדרשא, bei midrasha, in the beis medrash, he threw himself on the
floor of the beis medrash. It's almost like a kid having a
tantrum, you know, you throw yourself on the ground, okay, ומקשי, u'makshi,
and this is his question. Okay, so his question is, it's almost
like the problem is a conceptual one, it's not throwing two different
sources together, it's, you know, logically trying to work them together. And
here's what's bothering him. I mean, I get, I didn't... the גמרא
Gemara never does anything with, with that image, there he is on
the floor of the beis medrash and he's asking this question. Okay,
does he regularly do that?
Is that explained?
Yeah, there's other places where he does that. Does it say anything
interesting about that? No, just...
they just refer to Keren Orah, or they have a further explanation.
Okay. Anyway, I, so... Right. I think I... I would like to
interpret at least here, I have to check the other places, that
the רמי rami is not a contradiction of text, it's a logical
problem that's sort of bothering him, and he's throwing himself on the
floor. But anyway, ומקשי, u'makshi, and he asks the following question: אם
כשרים הם ירצו. im kesherim heim yirtzu. If they are kosher, then
they should work for the owners. It should be like all or
nothing. Okay. ואם אינם מרצים, ve'im einam mirtzim, and if they're not
going to work for the owners, so למה באים, lama ba'im, why
do they come at all? Like, either the whole package or not
the whole package. אמר ליה רבי אלעזר, amar lei Rebbi Elazar, so
Rebbi Elazar said to him, מצינו בבא לאחר מיתה שהן כשרים ואין
מרצים. matzinu be-va le-achar misa she-hein kesherim ve-ein mirtzim. It's not an
unusual phenomenon. I'll give you another case where you have a קרבן
korban that work, that is a kosher as a קרבן, korban the
blood could be thrown, the meat could be eaten and so on,
it could be offered on the מזבח, mizbe'ach but it doesn't help
the owners. What would be a case like that? The owners are
dead. Okay, somebody sanctified an עולה olah and dropped dead. What do
you do? You bring the עולה, olah, even though the person is
dead. How do you know it doesn't help them in some sort
of...? All right, so fine, we're going to assume not, we can
worry about that later. דתנן, de-tenan, we taught a משנה: Mishnah: האישה
שהביאה חטאתה ומתה. ha-isha she-hevia chatasa u-mesa. Now, actually, this week's פרשה
parsha is תזריע, Tazria, a woman who has a, who gives childbirth,
and then you have to bring a קרבן. korban So we're talking
here about the חטאת chatas, that a woman would bring after childbirth.
Okay, so she brought her חטאת, chatas, because a חטאת chatas, you
can't bring after death. Okay, and then she dies. But the thing
is, she doesn't just bring a חטאת, chatas okay, she also brings
an עולה. olah. So האישה שהביאה חטאתה ומתה, ha-isha she-hevia chatasa u-mesa,
now she died, יביאו יורשים עולתה, yaviu yorshim olasa, her heirs will...
should bring her עולה. olah. If she had designated it, if she
had sanctified it. Okay, if she had sanctified it. If she didn't
sanctify it, no. Okay. עולתה ומתה, olasa u-mesa, now she brought her
עולה olah before the חטאת chatas. and she sanctified the חטאת, chatas,
לא יביאו יורשים חטאתה, lo yaviu yorshim chatasa, they don't bring the
חטאת, chatas חטאת לאחר מיתה chatas le-achar misa is a principle that
you basically let it die. Okay. But an עולה, olah, she sanctified
an עולה, olah, she died, now it could be anybody sanctified an
עולה, olah, but this is the scenario that we're starting with, this
is a משנה, Mishnah, and it's brought even though the owners are
dead. Okay, so אמר ליה, amar lei, so look, the phenomenon exists.
What's bothering you? You can have an animal that is sanctified, that
is somehow detached from the owners and still operates as an animal,
as a sacrifice to be brought. It doesn't bother him also? Okay,
well, let's take a look. Let me read...
Yeah, there's a note saying also that the death was a greater
atonement, so they didn't need...
That might be, but anyway, I'm not... That could be, but
I don't want to get into that. Can you generalize then? No,
no, no, that's distracting. Let's bracket that. Okay, אמר ליה, amar lei,
I... at this stage I think the גמרא Gemara is basically just
assuming that it doesn't make sense to speak about an atonement for
somebody who's dead. I don't want to introduce that whole idea. Okay.
אמר ליה מודה אני לך בעולה דאתיא לאחר מיתה. amar lei modeh
ani lach be-olah de-asya le-achar misa. Fine, you know what? I'll concede
the point. In the case of an עולה, olah, case of a
שלמים, shlamim, that those come and those work for the... those work
but don't work for the בעלים. Anything that's a נדבה, nedava, by
the way, both because of this לאחר מיתה le-achar misa point, or
you could also say, look, if I make a נדבה, nedava, I
sanctify this animal as an עולה, olah, I sanctify this animal as
a שלמים, shlamim okay, it doesn't satisfy a personal obligation. I don't
have a personal obligation. But you could still say, even if it
doesn't satisfy a personal obligation, it still is counted, I get brownie
points up in heaven, you know, it still somehow is מכפר, mechaper,
counts to my merit. Okay, but at least those things are less
connected to the owners by necessity, because they're not coming in the
context of an obligation. And the לאחר מיתה le-achar misa allows them
to happen even after... let's say somebody sanctifies a שלמים shlamim. and
drops dead. You'll bring the שלמים. shlamim, Okay, so ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says, you know what? There I agree, that phenomenon is possible,
the קרבן korban, without the owner. Okay, but what bothers me is
the idea of an אשם, asham, because an אשם asham is all
about sin. Right? A חטאת, chatas because it's all about sin, it...
you don't get to bring it if it's not... it doesn't work
if it's לשם בעלים, if you... you know, if you do it
שלא לשמו, she-lo lishmo, it's invalid. So the one that stands out,
it works by עולה olah and שלמים, shelamim those can work without
an owner, it, by חטאת chatas. we know that if שלא לשמו
she-lo lishmo because it doesn't connect to the owner, it's invalid. The
standout is אשם. asham. אשם asham requires a connection to the owner
normally, you would assume. If somebody sanctifies an אשם... asham... אשם asham.
*asham* and die, you do not bring the אשם asham *asham* לאחר
מיתה l'acharei misa, *le’achar misah*. An אשם asham. *asham* does not work
without a connection to the owner in general, okay, and nevertheless, here
the אשם asham, *asham* will be valid but it won't work for
the owners. So that ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* is saying
doesn't make conceptual sense. So that's what רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar* says.
So that's what the answer's going to be back. Let's take a
look. Okay, he says, אמרי ליה *amlei* מודינא לך בעולה *modinu lach
be'olah* concede the point of an עולה olah *olah* דאתי לאחר מיתה
l'acharei misa. *de'asi le’achar misah*. אשם asham *asham* but an אשם asham
*asham* דלא אתי לאחר מיתה l'acharei misa. *de-lo asi le’achar misah*, so
if somebody sanctifies an אשם asham *asham* and dies, מנא לן *mina
lan* where do you have an idea that that could at all
ever work without being connected to the owners? אמרי ליה *amlei* הרי
מחלוקתך בצדו *harei machlokascha be'tzido* look, you're right, that dissenting opinion that
you're expressing is right there in the משנה *Mishnah*. רבי אליעזר אומר
*Rabbi Eliezer omer* אף אשם asham *af asham* רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
says an אשם asham *asham*'s also invalid. So your thinking is just
like רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*'s thinking. So there you go. So get
up off the floor. So אמר *amar* so he said, so he
said to this רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar*, let's not get confused, it's
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* in the משנה *Mishnah* and רב אלעזר *Rav
Elazar* the אמורא *Amora* who's answering him. אמר *amar* so he said
about this רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar*, זו שאומרים עליו אדם גדול הוא
hu *zo she'omrim alav adam gadol hu*, this is the person that
people are talking about he's such a big תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham*
this רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar* who thinks he's answering my problem? קאמינא
אנא משנה שלמה *ka amina ana mishnah shelemah* I'm bothered with the
סתם משנה *stam mishnah*, with the הלכה halacha *halacha* as we פוסקין
*paskin* it. Okay, and it's I'm saying it doesn't make any sense.
ואת אמרת לי *ve'at amrat li* oh רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar* רבי
אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. Okay, fine, you know, your problem is רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer*'s problem. I don't care that it's רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*'s
problem. I care about the הלכה halacha *halacha*, the הלכה *halacha* rejects
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. Okay, so what sense does it make that
you can have an אשם asham *asham* that works without being connected
to the owner? אלא אמר *ella amar* ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish
Lakish*, so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* did not get any
satisfying answer so he said אפתח אנא פתחא לנפשאי *eftecha ana pitcha
lenafshai*, you know what, nobody's here to help me, I'll open the
door for myself. Okay, what door am I going to open for
myself? מוצא שפתיך motza sefasecha *motza sefasecha* היא hia נדבה נדר neder,
הוא hu, כלא *hi nedavah neder hu k-lo*. We get this idea
that it could exist in a middle state from this אם כאשר
נדרת להשם אלוקיך נדבה *im ka-asher nadarta lashem elokecha nedavah* that something
could function like a נדבה *nedavah* in the sense you know that
you started it off it was connected to the owner, it was
a נדר neder. *neder*, but in the end because it wasn't done
properly it worked even though it wasn't connected to the owner like
a נדבה *nedavah*. Now the interesting thing is I don't understand didn't
he read the earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara*? So רש"י *Rashi* basically says
no they had not yet figured out this basis and if you
look at the earlier גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that quoted this פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* it was and made this דרשה *d'rasha* it was quoted by
the סתם *stam* of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it wasn't attributed to
anybody. So probably historically what happened was is that this story came
first, ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* came up with this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*,
once this פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* was said ah that's a great פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* now to establish this idea the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* brought
it in for you know earlier already twice. But when you read
it you say ah what's the matter ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* you
should have known the answer. But the reality is he's the one
that figured out the answer and then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* incorporated
it. Okay so that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* it seems was the read
of that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that way comes from ריש לקיש *Reish
Lakish*. Okay and that's how you know that even though normally we
don't have something like an אשם asham. *asham* that can exist without
an owner, here you can have an אשם asham *asham* without an
owner. Okay so let's see but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s not done.
Okay יתיב רב זירא ורב יצחק בר אבא *yasiv Rav Zeira veRav
Yitzchak bar Abba* so רב זירא *Rav Zeira* and רב יצחק בר
אבא *Rav Yitzchak bar Abba* were sitting ויתיב אביי גבייהו *ve'yasiv Abaye
gabeihu* and אביי *Abaye* was with them ויתבי וקא אמרי *ve'yasvi veka
amri* and they were sitting and saying קשלי לריש לקיש אשם asham
*kashlei leReish Lakish asham* ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* was bothered with this
story about the אשם asham *asham* דלא אתי לאחר מיתה l'acharei misa?
*de-lo asi le'achar misah* that it couldn't come after death and that
for him meant so therefore how can you have it שלא לשמה
shelo lishmah. *shelo lishmo* ונסיב לתלמודא *ve'nasiv le-talmuda* and he learned it
out from the תלמוד *talmud* here doesn't mean the Talmud, the תלמוד
*talmud* meaning he made his derivation from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of
מוצא שפתיך motza sefatecha *motza sefasecha* okay so that's what that's the
story so אימא *eima* הבא בנדר ובנדבה ליתו ולא לירצו *haba beneder
uvindavah laysu velo liyrtzu* אשם asham לא ליתי כלל *asham lo laysi
klal* he says you know what ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* I'm sorry
your פסוק pasuk *pasuk* didn't solve your problem because the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* is talking about נדר *neder* versus נדבה *nedavah*. That is in
the world of עולה ושלמים olah ushelamim, *olah ushlamim* where you can
have a נדר *neder* and you can have a נדבה *nedavah* and
there you could say something could sort of like switch. It could
start as a personal obligation and then exist as a קרבן korban
*korban* without connected to the person. Okay but that's in a world
of נדר ונדבה neder unedavah. *neder unedavah* in a world of עולה
ושלמים olah ushelamim, *olah ushlamim* where those can come through a נדר
*neder* and a נדבה *nedavah* but an אשם asham *asham* which only
comes through an obligation that the תורה *Torah* puts on you isn't
in that world of נדר ונדבה neder unedavah. *neder unedavah*, your problem
still exists. How do you know you can have this middle state?
Okay it was a great פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* but if you're bothered
with the fact that אשם asham *asham* is different then you still
got your problem. How do you know to apply this פסוק *pasuk*
to the case of an אשם asham *asham*? אשם asham לא ליתי
כלל *asham lo laysi klal* so that's a good question. So אמר
ליה אביי *amar leh Abaye* so אביי *Abaye* said back ריש לקיש
מהכא פתח *Reish Lakish me'hacha pasach* fine you know what he didn't
get it from the פסוק *pasuk* of מוצא שפתיך *motza sefasecha* he
actually got it from a different פסוק *pasuk* ושחט אותה לחטאת otah
lechatas *veshachat osa lechatas* you should slaughter it לחטאת lechatas *lechatas* for
the sake of a חטאת chatas *chatas*. So this answers the question
about how do you know חטאת chatas שלא לשמה shelo lishmah *chatas
shelo lishmo* doesn't work. אותה otah. לשמה lishmah כשירה שלא לשמה shelo
lishmah, פסולה *osa lishmo kesherah shelo lishmo pesulah* אותה otah. *osa* means
it, it has to be לחטאת *lechatas* and לחטאת *lechatas* is telling
you לשמה lishmah *lishmo* and אותה *osa* is telling you that this
requirement of לשמה lishmah. is unique to a חטאת. chatas. Now we
know that the requirement of לשמה lishma is not unique to a
חטאת, chatas all the קרבנות. korbanot So what it's telling you must
be unique is that it's בדיעבד bedieved it doesn't work. That even
if you don't do it, בדיעבד bedieved the קרבן is invalid. That's
the אותה. לחטאת otah lechatas is לשמה lishma, and there's something that's
unique to a חטאת chatat that בדיעבד bedieved it makes the קרבן
is invalid if it's done
שלא לשמה. shelo lishmah. So okay, we'll worry about that. But now
the same פסוק that you learned that it's מעכב meakev by a
חטאת chatat, tells you that this is only a הלכה by חטאת.
chatat Tells you that it works by an אשם. asham Now we
have not still conceptually explained the idea that what does it mean
for an אשם asham to be unrelated to the owners? But at
least we're saying we have a פסוק to base it on. Okay,
we're not just making it up, we needed a פסוק to ground
it because it's a new idea, we can't say it without it
being grounded and learned from a פסוק. Okay. One minute let me
just finish. אותה לשמה כשרה שלא לשמה פסולה. Otah lishmah kesherah shelo
lishmah pesulah. Only by the חטאת chatat. do we say that if
it's not done לשמה it's invalid. השאר קדשים Hashar kodashim all other
קדשים kodashim שלא לשמן כשרים, shelo lishman kesherim, שלא לשמן כשר shelo
lishman kasher and that would include an אשם. asham Okay, now so
from there we get the idea that it's כשר שלא לשמו. kasher
shelo lishmo. Now the only question I have left is יכול ירצו,
yachol yeratzu, maybe if it's כשר, kasher, maybe it should even count
for the sake of the owners? Okay, that's sort of the other
logic. Fine, you want to say it's כשר, kasher, let it be
כשר, kasher, let it count for the owners. No. תלמוד לומר מוצא
שפתיך. Talmud lomar motza sefasecha. So that's what the מוצא שפתיך teaches
you, that it doesn't count for the owners. Okay, so we're still
not haven't we still haven't really answered our question, right?
Because אותה לחטאת otah l'chatat tells you, okay, tells you חטאת chatat.
its לשמה is מעכב meakev
and everything else, all else, which includes אשם, asham okay,
לשמה שלא לשמה lishmah shelo lishmah it's still כשר. kasher. Okay, so
that's how you know that even an אשם asham could be כשר
שלא לשמן kasher shelo lishman and why it's different than a חטאת.
chatat? But then the question is maybe it's כשר kasher and it
should count, you know, and it should even be מרצה. meratze. So
then we have to go back to the פסוק of
כאשר
נדרת נדבה,
kaasher nadarta
nedavah, you know, that this כאשר נדרת נדבה kaasher nadarta nedavah tells
you it's a middle state, that it's כשר ואינו עולה. kasher veino
oleh. Okay, now the problem that we said is that this these
words are talking in a context of עולה oleh, ושלמים, in a
context of things that work with נדר ונדבה. So now we're going
to sort of have to combine these two things and say the
logic is the following: if an אשם asham is כשר, kasher, okay,
if an עולה olah and a שלמים shelamim are
כשר ואינו עולה, kasher veino oleh, what are you going to say?
But an אשם asham it's כשר kasher and it is עולה, olah
it does count? I mean an אשם asham is more problematic when
it's not attached to the owners. So if even an עולה olah
and a שלמים shelamim aren't going to count for their owners, certainly
a חטאת chatat, won't count for the owners. That's how we're going
to combine it. Okay, but let's but the גמרא is not going
to be satisfied. Let's take a look. Okay, I'm not forgetting about
you, David. Okay, so it says like this, it says, okay, so
תלמוד לומר מוצא שפתיך. Talmud lomar motza sefasecha. ואימא Veima the גמרא
says I'm still not satisfied. I can say הבא בנדר ונדבה לאו
ובלאו ירצו, haba beneder unedavah lav ubelav yeratzu, אשם ירצו נמי לירצה.
asham yeratzu nami leiratze. If an אשם asham were weighty yes, but
an אשם asham is something that only makes sense connected to the
owners. So I am still going to tell you you cannot use
this פסוק for an אשם. asham You're telling me, oh but an
אשם asham is already כשר, kasher, I know from this פסוק an
אשם asham? is כשר. kasher. So what are you going to tell
me? That an עולה olah doesn't count for the owners and an
אשם asham does? And the answer is yes, I am going to
tell you that because an עולה olah is not tightly connected to
the owners. So even if you say it's כשר, kasher, I can
live with the idea that it doesn't work for the owners. But
if you're going to tell me an אשם asham is כשר, kasher,
then I'm going to tell you the only way an אשם asham,
is going to be כשר kasher is if it counts for the
owners and you this פסוק is not going to help you. This
פסוק works in a world of עולה olah ושלמים, of נדר ונדבה.
I am still going to insist by an אשם asham, it's all
or nothing, it's one package. Okay, so you still have not proven
your point. So the גמרא says,
okay,
מה לעולה שכן באה בנדר ונדבה. mah leolah sheken baah beneder unedavah.
I'm
sorry, אמר אביי, amar Abaye, אשם דמירצי לא מצית אמרת. asham demirtzei
lo matzit amart. No, here's why you can't say that once we've
established from פסוק number one אותה לחטאת that an אשם asham works,
here's how you can here's how I'm going to tell you that
that it you cannot say that it's מרצה. meratze. Why not?
Okay, אשם דמירצי לא מצית אמרת. asham demirtzei lo matzit amart. קל
וחומר Kal vachomer מעולה meolah because again I'll make the קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. ומה עולה שאינה מכפרת אינה מרצה Umah olah sheienah mechaperes
einah meratzah an עולה olah which doesn't serve to, now so he's
not, here's the logic is not that an עולה olah is weaker,
the logic is the following: an עולה olah normally never brings atonement.
Now, is it really true doesn't bring atonement? Actually, an עולה olah,
brings atonement—we normally say—I mean the פסוקים psukim just talk about an
עולה olah as a gift, okay? But the חז"ל Chazal say that
an עולה olah works to atone for the things that other קרבנות
korbanot don't work for, which basically is an עשה, aseh, מצות עשה
mitzvot aseh that you didn't do or לא תעשה lo taaseh that
is combined to an עשה aseh or whatever. The thing though that
we're going to say is that that's maybe a normal עולה, olah
but an עולה olah that a woman brings as a for for
childbirth is part of the process of טהרה taharah for childbirth and
is not connected to ריצוי ritzuy and to כפרה. kaparah. But we'll
get to that in a minute. So it says like this: Here's
going to be the argument. The argument is not going to be,
'Oh, if a weak עולה olah doesn't count for a for the
owner's, how do you expect a weighty אשם asham to count for
the owners?' That's not the argument. The argument is going to be
an עולה olah in general does not work to achieve כפרה. kaparah.
That's not normally its function. And therefore and when it's שלא לשמה
shelo lishma it also doesn't work to achieve כפרה kaparah like it
doesn't work for the owners, okay? Therefore an אשם asham which is
well, let's let's finish it, okay? So here's a here's a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. What's the קל וחומר? kal vachomer? מה עולה שאינה
מכפרת? ma olah she’eina mechaperet? An עולה olah normally doesn't serve the
function of כפרה, kaparah, אינה מרצה, eina mirtzah, and we say that
somehow you know, it doesn't count for the owners. Not counting for
the owners can mean more than just whether it achieves atonement. Like
if the owners made a נדר, exactly like the גמרא said, they
didn't satisfy their obligation of a נדר. Okay, so אשם שמכפר, asham
shemechaper, an אשם asham is normally its function is to bring כפרה.
kaparah. So and here it's done wrong, אינו דין שאינו מרצה? eino
din she’eino mirtzah? Certainly it should not be מרצה. mirtzah. Now,
yeah, I'm trying to figure out how the קל וחומר kal vachomer
works because it's still the logic the גמרא said before is that
let's still say that an אשם asham is like an all or
nothing. But I guess it's it's going beyond the all or nothing
argument and it's basically saying like if its whole function...
yeah,
the the direct connection between the person bringing the קרבן and and
the purpose of the קרבן, right? עולה olah has no כפרה kaparah
aspect, therefore it would make sense that it wouldn't be
if an עולה olah that has no כפרה kaparah reason isn't מרצה
mirtzah when it's שלא לשמה, shelo lishma. it can't it wouldn't make
sense for an אשם asham that does have a כפרה kaparah reason
to be מרצה mirtzah שלא לשמה. אשם asham seems to be more
personally connected to the person being...
Yeah, but that's a sort of a Abaye's point, but that was
the point. You're right, it shouldn't be in a middle position. So
therefore, because it's all connected, it should be that it's מכפר mechaper
it's it's כשר kasher and מכפר. mechaper.
So we're shifting from פסוקים psukim to logic. פסוקים psukim you could
say that, but in logic, if if we see that even קרבנות
korbanot, that don't have a direct connection to the person can't be
מכפר mechaper can't fulfill their purpose, can't be מרצה, mirtzah, a קרבן
that has a direct connection because it needs to be מכפר mechaper
cannot be מרצה mirtzah when there's no לשמה. It just doesn't make...
it still a little begs the question. It's still like a little
bit that you have to assume that it's like... yeah, I'm still
I'm still a little bothered because what bothered the גמרא until this
point was how do you know that you can
like that the אשם asham can work without connection to the person?
Well, the question was...
yeah, Jed, what what do you want to say?
From logic-wise I would almost think the opposite, right?
Well, that's what the גמרא has been saying, like how do you
know that if it's כשר, kasher, maybe the only way for an
אשם asham to be כשר kasher is for it to be for
it to be מרצה mirtzah because an אשם asham doesn't you know
only works together with... I'm anyway. I think the answer is is
that it basically yeah, it is ignoring that sense that like it
all has to come as a package. And if you ignore that
sense that it comes as a package and it just focuses on
the power to be מרצה, mirtzah, so you know so then it
sort of you know says...
you just responding to the fact that we said before that it
should be מרצה, mirtzah, and now you're saying it doesn't?
I know, but the problem is that Abaye's point was that it
should all come as a package. Anyway, let's keep on reading. Okay,
so the גמרא understands it some קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So the
קל וחומר kal vachomer is מה עולה שכן כליל, ma olah shekein
kalil, no, maybe an עולה olah is because it's all burnt up,
that's why it's a a weightier type of a thing. And a
חטאת chatat. which is somehow or an אשם asham, which is somehow
less weighty, maybe it actually can be מרצה. mirtzah. שלמים יוכיחו. shelamim
yochichu.
Okay, but שלמים shelamim are also not מרצה. mirtzah. So if an
עולה olah is not מרצה mirtzah and a שלמים shelamim is not
מרצה, mirtzah, an אשם asham also shouldn't be מרצה. mirtzah. No, מה
לשלמים שכן טעונים נסכים תנופה וחזה ושוק? ma leshelamim shekein te’unim nesechim
tnufah vechazeh vashok?
שלמים shelamim have a greater weightiness in these other things that are
brought with them. So just because עולה olah and שלמים shelamim are
not מרצה mirtzah doesn't prove that an אשם asham is not מרצה.
mirtzah. עולה תוכיח. olah tochiah.
Okay, but that's not but those are not the things that an
עולה ola. has. וחזר הדין. vechazar hadin. And you go back and
forth like you know, don't point out, oh עולה ola. is weightier
this way, שלמים shelamim, is weightier that way. We have to look
for the common denominator. לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה
כראי זה, lo rei zeh kerei zeh velo rei zeh kerei zeh,
each one's distinctive characteristics are not like the other. הצד השוה שבהן,
hatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator is שהן קדשים, shehen kodashim, that
they're קרבנות, korbanot ושחטן שלא לשמן כשרים, veshachtan shelo lishaman ksheirim, and
שלא לשמה they're כשר, kasher, ואינם מרצים. ve’einam mirtzim.
So that's the common denominator by everything else, by עולה ola. and
שלמים, shelamim, so אף אני אביא אשם. af ani avi asham. אף
אני אביא אשם asham שהוא קדש וחטאת שלא לשמה כשר kasher, *af
ani avi asham shehu kodesh v'chatat shelo lishmah kasher*, I'll say the
same is true by an אשם asham *asham*. So it's pretty much
saying the same thing, let's learn it out from the others. Again,
I still don't understand how it answers אביי *Abaye*'s conceptual question. But
anyway, if the other things are not מרצה *mirtze*, the אשם *asham*
should be מרצה *mirtze*. ואינו מרצה *v'eino mirtze*. No? מה לצד השווה
שבהן שכן ישנו בציבור *ma latzad hashaveh shebahen shekein yeshno b'tzibur*. No,
an עולה ola *olah* and a שלמים shelamim *shelamim* can exist as
a קרבן ציבור *korban tzibur*.
You know, an אשם *asham* never exists as a קרבן ציבור *korban
tzibur*. So therefore since it's not exactly like, there's something that makes
it distinct, you can't apply the rule of עולה ola. *olah* and
שלמים *shelamim* to an אשם *asham*. No, תודה תוכיח *todah tochchiach*. Ah,
but a תודה *todah* also can't exist as a קרבן ציבור *korban
tzibur*. And there the same principle of אינו מרצה *eino mirtze* applies
by a תודה *todah*. מה לתודה שכן טעונה לחם *ma latodah shekein
teuna lechem*. No, but a תודה *todah* is weightier because it demands
the, a תודה *todah* you bring loaves of לחם *lechem* with it.
עולה ola, ושלמים יוכיח *olah v'shelamim yochchiach*. But that's not unique by
עולה ola *olah* and שלמים *shelamim*. וחזר הדין *v'chazar hadin*. לא ראי
זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה *lo reize k'reize v'lo
reize k'reize*. So each one has its unique things. It's sort of
like a Venn diagram,
right?
You have like, you've
got עולה *olah*, שלמים
*shelamim*, and תודה *todah*. And each one has some unique things. A
תודה *todah* has bread, which you don't have by the others. עולה
*olah* is כליל *kalil*, it's all burnt up, which you don't have
by the others. This has חזה ושוק *chaze v'shok*, which you don't
have by the others. So since none of these exist by the
others, you can't say that's the determining factor. The intersection of all
of these is, you know, they're all קרבנות *korbanos*. So the rule
is any קרבן *korban* that is, you know, it... the הלכה *halacha*
should be that it is עולה ואינו מרצה *oleh v'eino mirtze*, you
know, it's כשר kasher ואינו מרצה *kasher v'eino mirtze*. And therefore through
the intersection of this, we're going to come ahead and include also
what do you call it, also the אשם *asham*. Again, ignoring the
fact that by the אשם *asham* it is more tightly connected to
the owner. Okay. לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי
זה *lo reize k'reize v'lo reize k'reize*. הצד השווה שבהן *hatzad hashaveh
shebahen*, the common denominator, שהן קדשים ושחטן שלא לשמה כשרים ואינם מרצים
*shehein kodshim v'shachtan shelo lishmah k'sheirim v'einam mirtzim*, אף אני אביא אשם
שהוא קדש ושחטו שלא לשמו כשר ואינו מרצה *af ani avi asham
shehu kodesh v'shachto shelo lishmo kasher v'eino mirtze*. Okay. So I'm going
to include it because I'm going to say I'm going to learn
out a principle here and again ignore the fact that all of
these can exist even when the owner is dead and all of
these have a unique connection to the owners. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says no, so finally now the גמרא *Gemara* gets back essentially to
אביי *Abaye*'s question, okay? So גמרא *Gemara* says מה לצד השווה שבהן
שהן באין בנדר ונדבה *ma latzad hashaveh shebahen shehein ba'in b'neder u'vindavah*.
But these are all similar, going back to essentially what was אביי
*Abaye*'s question before, that these all are from a world of נדר
ונדבה *neder u'vindavah* and not from a world of obligation and they're
all from a world in which קרבנות *korbanot* can exist with a
less tight connection to the owner. So we are really back to
our earlier question. We know, we did not answer it. That's why
we were pausing before because we already...
אלא אמר רבא *ello amar Rava*...
whatever, we haven't said it yet in this case. So you've anticipated
the next line of the גמרא *Gemara*. אלא אמר רבא זאת התורה
*ello amar Rava zot hatorah*. Okay, that we haven't said it yet.
We said זאת התורה *zot hatorah* over here to tell you you
need לשמה *lishmah*. Now we're going to say זאת התורה *zot hatorah*
to tell you this principle of we're going to introduce זאת התורה
*zot hatorah* here as well. זאת התורה *zot hatorah* to tell me
that even though this is by נדר ונדבה *neder u'vindavah*, okay, זאת
התורה *zot hatorah* is going to tell me plus אשם *asham*.
Okay, the only problem is in חוץ חטאת chatat *chutz chatat*.
Okay, we'll get to that. Okay, yes, you're right. This whole idea
of this middle status makes more sense by נדר ונדבה *neder u'vindavah*.
זאת התורה *zot hatorah*'s gonna let me now include אשם *asham*. Okay.
הקישו הכתוב לשלמים *hekisho hakatuv l'shelamim*, מה שלמים שהן קדשים ושחטן שלא
לשמה כשרים ואינם מרצים *ma shelamim shehein kodshim v'shachtan shelo lishmah k'sheirim
v'einam mirtzim*, אף אף אני אביא אשם שהוא קדש *af af ani
avi asham shehu kodesh* etc. etc. Okay. מאי חזית *mai chazis*? Now
this is Michael's question. דאקיש לשלמים *d'akish l'shelamim*? You connected it to
a שלמים *shelamim* to say that it has this middle status. אקיש
לחטאת *akish l'chatat*. Connect it to a חטאת chatat *chatat* and say
that it's connected to a חטאת chatat *chatat* and it's אינו כשר
*eino kasher*. הא מיעט רחמנא אותה *ha mi'eit rachmana osah*. No,
because אותה *osah* up here tells me that the only thing that
has this הלכה *halacha* that it is not כשר *kasher* at all
is a חטאת chatat, *chatat*. So since I can't connect it to
a חטאת chatat. *chatat*, I'm forced to connect it to the נדר
נדבה *neder nedavah* etc. which tells me a middle state. And I
don't have the third option. There are three options: not כשר *kasher*
at all, כשר ואינו מרצה *kasher v'eino mirtze*, כשר ומרצה *kasher u'mirtze*.
Our argument had been let's say כשר ומרצה *kasher u'mirtze* by an
אשם *asham* because it's so tightly connected. So the point is no,
it has to connect either to a שלמים *shelamim* or to a
חטאת *chatat*. It can't connect to a חטאת *chatat*, a חטאת *chatat*
is the only thing that's פסול pasul *pasul*, so it has to
connect to the category of עולה ושלמים *olah v'shelamim* to tell me
it's in this middle state of כשר ואינו מרצה *kasher v'eino mirtze*.
So what's the חטאת *chatat* doing in the פסוק *posuk*
of זאת התורה *zot hatorah*? I don't know, for this הלכה *halacha*
that לכתחילה *l'chat'chilah* requires לשמה *lishmah*. Okay. So now the גמרא *Gemara*
says like this: Alright, that we got through that. יתיב רב הונא
רב נחמן ויתיב רב ששת Rav Sheshet גבייהו ויתבי ואמרי *yasiv Rav
Huna Rav Nachman v'yasiv Rav Sheshet gabayei v'yasiv v'amrei*. They were all
sitting and saying. קשיא ליה לריש לקיש *kasha lei l'Resh Lakish*. Similar
scenario: three rabbis sitting and reflecting on ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish*'s... throwing
himself on the floor. You know, I guess it captured their attention,
a rabbi throws himself on the floor. Okay, says קשיא ליה לריש
לקיש. ריש לקיש was puzzled אשם דלא אתי לאחר מיתה. asham delo
ati l'acharei misa.
אשם doesn't happen לאחר מיתה, l'acharei misa. so how could it have
this middle state of כשר ואינו
מרוצה? kasher ve'eino merutza? לימא ליה רבי אלעזר, leima lei Rebbi Elazar,
who tried to answer back ריש לקיש, and he's let him say
אשם נמי אתי לאחר מיתה. asham nami ati l'acharei misa. רבי אלעזר
Rebbi Elazar wanted to bring a proof from like the קרבנות that
came לאחר מיתה. l'acharei misa And ריש לקיש said, what about אשם?
He should have said there's a type of an אשם that does
come לאחר מיתה. l'acharei misa What type of אשם comes לאחר
מיתה? l'acharei misa? לימא ליה. leima lei. Now what does that mean?
So an אשם, so the גמרא doesn't say, but it's implied and
it'll say it in a minute. If the person dies and leaves
behind a חטאת, what do you do? You let the חטאת die.
If a person dies and leaves behind an אשם, do you know
what you do?
Do
you, well, we're saying you bring it לאחר מיתה.
l'acharei misa, No, no, no. What do you do? Okay, don't focus
on the words the גמרא just said. What do you do by
an אשם that the owner's died? You let it graze till it
gets a
מום, mum, you transfer the קדושה kedusha to money, you use the
money to buy an עולה. So the קדושה kedusha of an אשם
לאחר מיתה le'achar misa, is ultimately realized by being brought on the
מזבח mizbe'ach in the form of an עולה. So therefore you could
have still said, you know what? אשם is not 100% like a
חטאת. In some new reincarnated form, its נשמה neshama goes to the
money and then there's a גלגול נשמה gilgul neshama and it goes
to the עולה. In some reincarnated form, the אשם comes לאחר מיתה
as an עולה on the מזבח. And that's why אשם we can
allow for it to have the status of being brought without connecting
to the owners.
Okay. אמר ליה רב ששת, Amar lei Rav Sheshet, רב ששת said,
אשם למאי קרב? asham lemai karev? In what sense is an אשם
brought on the מזבח לאחר מיתה? למותרו. lemotaro. For the remainder, meaning
what was left over, the money is transferred and the transfer of
the money is used to bring an עולה. That's what the word
מותר motar means. Okay. It can sometimes mean excess funds, but anyway
here that's what it means. So חטאת נמי מקרב קרבה מותרה? chatat
nami mikrav karva motara? So one minute, this also applies by a
חטאת. Now what does it mean it applies by a חטאת? So
let me just check רש״י Rashi one minute.
One minute.
Yeah. Oh
right. So it's only a specific case. It's not a classic case.
If you look at רש״י, Rashi, the first narrow line, חטאת נמי,
chatat nami, רש״י Rashi says מותרו נדבה הוא כגון הפריש שתי חטאות
לאחריות מתכפר באחת מהן. motaro nedava hu kegon hifrish shtei chatatot l'achrayot
mitkaper be'achat mehen. So this is a complicated case, which is I
know that I'm terrible at losing things. So when I go ahead
and sanctify my animal as a חטאת, what I actually say is
both of these sheep are a חטאת. If I lose one, the
other one will stand in place of it. That's הפריש שתי חטאות
לאחריות. hifrish shtei chatatot l'achrayot. So since from the very outset I've
designated some type of a leftover one, if then the owner brings
one and then the owner dies, the other one which was always
a backup, that one can still be also brought, you know, on
the מזבח and so on. Okay. So that's a very unusual type
of a case. A classic חטאת doesn't
come afterward, it's just let to die. So let's take a look.
חטאת נמי מקרב קרבה מותרה. chatat nami mikrav karva motara. No, חטאת
אע״ג דקרבה מותרה, chatat af al gav dekarva motara, מיעט רחמנא הוא.
mi'et rachmana hu. No, even though maybe there is some way in
which a חטאת in a very special case can come לאחר מיתה,
that we know from the הוא that a חטאת is פסול pasul
when it's שלא לשמה. Okay, אשם נמי כתיב. asham nami ketiv. Okay,
so basically what we've said now is, and now we're going to
get to words of הוא והיא, hu vehia, but the basic new
point that we've made is to help you deal conceptually with this
idea that an אשם can come without an owner, like okay, we
did it with all these פסוקים, pesukim, fine. But what about the
conceptual question of an אשם without an owner, right? Where do we
ever else have that? And the גמרא actually has now given a
little bit of an answer to that. We have that idea because
in the end, even when the owner dies, the אשם in a
reincarnated form, at least as an עולה, is brought. So therefore, even
though here the אשם itself is brought without an owner, it's not
like it's completely unprecedented. Okay, so let's just now read a little
bit more with the הוא והיא, hu vehia, because now we're saying
the אותה לחטאת or חטאת היא, chatat hia, actually not הוא, היא
tells me, you know, that a חטאת, you know what? Let's end
here. Okay, it's 8:30 and we'll have to still, we're not still
totally out of the woods about the פסוקים, pesukim, but we definitely
have, we've accomplished a lot. We know that you require לשמה from
שלמים, that says basically
everything requires לשמה, and מוצא שפתיך tells me, but if it's done
incorrectly, it's כשר ולא עלו לבעלים. kasher velo alu leba'alim. That's not
true by a חטאת. A חטאת בדיעבד chatat bedi'avad is not good
because of the word of אותה. Okay, how do we know that
an אשם, you know,
בדיעבד, bedi'avad, you know, can be in this middle state? So this
פסוק, this middle state applies by like שלמים and עולה whatever. How
do we know the middle... State also applies to an אשם and
that's וזאת התורה. v'zos hatorah. וזאת התורה v'zos hatorah which equates things,
say yes, conceptually אשם maybe should not exist in a middle state.
It should either be completely פסול or completely כשר, but we link
it to the other things and we say it can exist in
a middle state. And the גמרא ended by actually telling us a
little bit of a סברא sevara that sometimes an אשם can exist
in a reincarnated way לאחר מיתה, so that helps us understand why
this הלכה can apply to an אשם as well, that it can
have this middle state of being כשר and not עולה לבעלים. oleh
l'be'alim. All right, פסיק ופלא. pasik u'fela. We'll end here.