Good morning. Today is July 10th, the 27th of תמוז, Tammuz, and
today's Tuesday. Today's דף Daf is פ"ט. Pei Tet. We're starting the
10th פרק, Perek, פרק כל התדיר, Perek Kol Hatadir, right at the
top of the דף, Daf, and we'll aim to get through much
of the discussion. The second עמוד ב' Amud Bet is rather long,
but we'll see where we get up to. I hope we'll be
able to cover what I anticipated.
The משנה Mishna begins: כל התדיר מחברו קודם את חברו. Kol hatadir
mechavero kodem et chavero. A general rule: whichever of the קרבנות korbanot
are more
frequent—as רש"י Rashi gives us an example right at the top: שבת
תדירה מראש חודש. Shabbat tadira meRosh Chodesh. שבת Shabbat happens once a
week, and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh happens once a month. So whichever
happens more
frequently—with a greater frequency. You could wonder why רש"י Rashi chooses שבת
Shabbat and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh as the examples. But whichever is
more frequent than its friend—that is, whichever one is more frequent than
another—קודם את חברו, kodem et chavero, comes first, is given priority. התמידים.
HaTmidim. So the משנה's Mishna
example—seemingly a better example than רש"י's—I'm Rashi wondering about this רש"י Rashi
now. התמידים קודמים למוספים. HaTmidim kodmim lamusafim. The קרבן תמיד, korban Tamid,
the daily sacrifice which is brought literally every single day, has priority
over the מוספים. musafim. And we know that
both—well we'll see where it's learned out from, but just in the
order of the day in בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, we—at least our
basic conception is that the קרבן תמיד korban Tamid of the morning
is the first קרבן korban offered every morning, and the קרבן תמיד
korban Tamid of the afternoon is always the last קרבן korban done
in the afternoon except for the קרבן פסח korban Pesach which has
to be done after that. But except on פסח, Pesach,
every other קרבן korban which is brought in the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash is tried to be—at least לכתחילה—to lechatchila be sandwiched between those
two. Did you have a question?
Did you bring this over to our prayers and
the readings of the תורה? Torah? Yes, so we do מוסף Musaf
after שחרית, Shacharit, for example. Right.
No, but I mean also the one that's most frequent—Right, is mentioned
first.
So when it's שבת Shabbat and ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, we first
mention שבת Shabbat in the מוסף Musaf and then we mention ראש
חודש, Rosh Chodesh, right.
And now the משנה Mishna continues: מוספי שבת קודמין למוספי ראש חודש.
Musfei Shabbat kodmin lemusfei Rosh Chodesh. שבת Shabbat precedes ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh. מוספי ראש חודש קודמין למוספי ראש השנה. Musfei Rosh Chodesh kodmin
lemusfei Rosh Hashanah. And ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh precedes ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah because ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh happens every month and ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah only happens once a year. שנאמר מלבד עולת הבוקר אשר
לעולת התמיד תעשו את אלה. Shene'emar: Milvad olat haboker asher le'olat hatamid
ta'asu et eleh. Because the פסוק pasuk describing
the
קרבן מוסף korban Musaf for פסח—for Pesach חג המצות—says: Chag HaMatzot מלבד
עולת הבוקר, Milvad olat haboker, besides the morning עולה, olah, אשר לעולת
התמיד, asher le'olat hatamid, which is the תמיד, tamid, the daily continual
sacrifice, תעשו את אלה, ta'asu et eleh, you should do these. That
is, besides the קרבן תמיד, korban Tamid, you also have to do
the מוסף. Musaf. So the מוסף—I Musaf mean, we call it מוסף
Musaf because חז"ל Chazal told us that word, but it means additional;
it's added on to the קרבן תמיד. korban Tamid. So that's the
general notion of this משנה. Mishna. So the גמרא Gemara asks a
following question: מנלן? Menalan? Where do we learn this from?
We know in
פנחס—פנחס, yeah.
We just read
this: מלבד עולת החודש ומנחתה ועולת התמיד ומנחתה. Milvad olat hachodesh uminchatah
ve'olat hatamid uminchatah. So, right, so the פסוק pasuk should have mentioned
תמיד tamid first then: ועולת התמיד ועולת החודש ומנחתה. Ve'olat hatamid ve'olat
hachodesh uminchatah.
Well, so—but we have a general rule of כל התדיר מחברו קודם
את חברו, kol hatadir mechavero kodem et chavero, and there'll be specific
examples where it's learned out. The גמרא Gemara asks the following
question: מנלן? Menalan? Where do we learn this from? But wait a
second, the משנה Mishna quotes a פסוק! pasuk! So the גמרא Gemara
says: מנלן כדקאמר. Menalan kedekamar. So you already quoted me the פסוק,
pasuk, why do you have to even ask this question? So the
גמרא Gemara says: טעמא מלבד עולת הבוקר. Ta'ama milvad olat haboker. If
I would have—I would have thought from the words מלבד עולת הבוקר,
milvad olat haboker, that is sort of alongside or despite the daily
sacrifice, דילמא תמידין הם דקדמו למוספים. dilma tmidin hem dekadmu lamusafim. Maybe
I would have thought only the rule should be that the קרבן
תמיד korban Tamid precedes every קרבן מוסף, korban Musaf, משום דתדירי, mishum
detadiri, because it happens every single day. מוספים למוספים מנא לן? Musafim
lemusafim mena lan? How do I know that on a day which
has multiple קרבן מוסף, korban Musaf, like שבת חול המועד Shabbat Chol
HaMoed or שבת ראש חודש Shabbat Rosh Chodesh or ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, how do I know which of the קרבנות מוסף korbanot Musaf
should be given primacy? So אמר רבי אילא. Amar Rabbi Ila. רבי
אילא Rabbi Ila says: דאמר קרא כאלה. De'amar kra: Ka'eleh. The most
despised word in the תורה Torah for בעלי קריאה, ba'alei kriya, sadly.
The community often joins in... The most despised word in the תורה
Torah *Torah* for בעלי קריאה *Ba'alei Keriah* sadly, the community often joins
in with the chanting this word, כאלה תעשו ליום שבעת ימים yamim?
*ka'eleh ta'asu layom shivat yamim*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* of the קרבן
korban מוסף *korban Musaf* of the seven days of פסח *Pesach*. So
unlike סוכות *Sukkot*, on פסח *Pesach* the קרבן korban מוסף *korban Musaf*
is the same every single day of the holiday. And so we're
given the instructions for the day first day, the fifteenth of ניסן
*Nisan*, and then the תורה Torah *Torah* says כאלה תעשו ליום שבעת
ימים yamim, *ka'eleh ta'asu layom shivat yamim*. You should do like this
for seven days. And therefore we're learning out from the word כאלה
*ka'eleh* like this to understand that the same principle of תמידים *temidim*
coming before מוספים *Musafim* because of כל התדיר מחבירו קודם kodem, מחבירו
*kol hatadir m'chavero kodem m'chavero* should apply as well within the category
of מוספים *Musafim* as well. That is, any קרבן korban. מוסף *korban
Musaf* we'll assess based on how תדיר *tadir* it is which one
should go first.
So אלה *eleh*, כאלה *ka'eleh*. I could have, it could have said
אלה תעשו ליום *eleh ta'asu layom*, כאלה *ka'eleh*. So the fact that
the extra letter כ *kaf* comes to teach me this. והא מבעי
ליה לגופיה *V'ha mibayei leh l'gufeh*? Don't I need this to teach
me what it teaches me itself? That is to teach me that
the קרבן korban מוסף *korban Musaf* of every day of פסח *Pesach*
should be equal to the קרבן korban מוסף *korban Musaf* of the
first day?
So
one
second. So אם כן נכתוב אלה תעשו ליום *im ken nichtov eleh
ta'asu layom*. So you would have learned that. So אי כתב אלה
תעשו ליום שבעת ימים *i katav eleh ta'asu layom shivat yamim*, if
I would have, if it would have said אלה תעשו ליום שבעת
ימים *eleh ta'asu layom shivat yamim*, these you do every day for
seven days, הוה אמינא hava amina *hava amina* I might have thought
אלה לשבעת הימים *eleh l'shivat hayamim*.
So I might have thought that those קרבנות korbanot *korbanot* for פסח
*Pesach* would be divided up to be sacrificed throughout all seven days
of the holiday. They don't have to be brought on a specific
day. Some of the, you know, הכבשים *hakevasim* could be brought one
day and some a different day and you could split them up.
How does this say אלה תעשו ליום? No, that would have said
אלה תעשו שבעת ימים. אלה תעשו ליום שבעת ימים.
Okay, so I'm just telling you what the דרשה drasha *drasha* says.
It makes no sense. I agree, it's not such a great דרשה
derasha. *drasha*. Okay. אלה לשבעת הימים ליום כתיב *eleh l'shivat hayamim layom
ktiv*. So it says ליום *layom*.
So והא כתיב אימא אלה ליום *v'ha ktiv eima eleh layom*. So
you could, if that was what you were trying to preempt, then
you would have just said אלה ליום *eleh layom*. You have to
do these for every day. אבל שאר יומי לא ידעינן כמה *Aval
shear yomei lo yadinan kama*. So I might have thought that those
are only for the first day of פסח *Pesach* and the other
six days of פסח *Pesach* I have no idea what קרבן korban
*korban* to bring. I know there's a קרבן korban *korban*, but I
don't know what it's supposed to be. אמר קרא תעשו *Amar Kra
ta'asu*. So then you learn that you have to bring, bring them.
תעשו *ta'asu*. שיהיו כל העשיות שוות *she'yihyu kol ha'asiyot shavot*. Every action
has to be equivalent. That is all seven days of פסח *Pesach*
are equal. The fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going through
so much work to דרש *darsh* this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is I
think points to the fact that the discomfort or the oddity of
the holiday of פסח *Pesach* in comparison to סוכות *Sukkot*. And the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in ערכין *Arachin* and other places points this out
in a variety of contexts that פסח *Pesach*, the nature of the
day of פסח *Pesach* is that the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* of every
day is more or less equivalent. Each day of חול המועד *Chol
HaMoed* and even the last days of יום טוב *Yom Tov* of
פסח *Pesach* sort of all an outgrowth of the first day of
פסח *Pesach*. They're just sort of a residual continuation of really what
happened the first day. We of course make a big deal, oh
the seventh day of פסח *Pesach* was the day we crossed the
sea, but at least in the תורה *Torah*, the first day of
פסח *Pesach* is the day we left מצרים *Mitzrayim*. That's the celebration.
And there's six more days added on to make it a week-long
vacation, the week-long holiday, but not that there's any specific character to
the individual days of פסח *Pesach*. And on סוכות *Sukkot*, the individual
days each have their own character, their own קרבן korban, *korban*, each
one is different. Already in the תורה *Torah*, you just see in
פרשת פנחס Pinchas *Parshat Pinchas* that פסח *Pesach* gets one paragraph and
סוכות *Sukkot* gets seven, eight paragraphs. It's much more substantial in that
regard. And there are some הלכתיות *halachic* differences. Obviously it's a bit
debated, but at least the practice in many אשכנזי *Ashkenazi* communities is
that on חול המועד סוכות *Chol HaMoed Sukkot*, the ברכה *bracha* said
over the הפטרה *Haftarah*, even on שבת חול המועד *Shabbat Chol HaMoed*,
mentions קדושת היום *kedushat hayom* of סוכות *Sukkot* because the days of
חול המועד סוכות *Chol HaMoed Sukkot* are considered to be more יום
טוב *Yom Tov*-like or more individual. And on חול המועד פסח *Chol
HaMoed Pesach*, many communities the שבת חול המועד פסח *Shabbat Chol HaMoed
Pesach*, the ברכה *bracha* in the הפטרה *Haftarah* does not mention פסח
*Pesach*. So it's kind of an interesting split there. It's a debate
in the אחרונים *Acharonim*, but it's an interesting discussion. Okay,
fine. So that was the opinion of רבי אילא *Rabbi Ila*. אביי
Abaye *Abaye* אמר *amar*, אביי Abaye *Abaye* disagrees. מגופא דקרא migufeh dekra
*Migufeh d'kra*. No, you just learn it from the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*.
אם כן לימא קרא מלבד עולת הבוקר milvad olat haboker? *im ken
leima Kra milvad olat haboker*. So that is you could learn it
from the גופא דקרא *gufa d'kra*, but then what you might have
said. So אם כן לימא קרא *im ken leima Kra*, the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* could have said מלבד עולת הבוקר *milvad olat haboker*. It
wouldn't have to have the second clause אשר לעולת התמיד asher le'olat
hatamid *asher l'olat hatamid*, right? מלבד עולת הבוקר ומנחתה מלבד
*Milvad olat haboker u'minchatah milvad*. No, no, they're all so similar, I'm
mixing them up in my head. One second.
Where is this? This is in פרק perek. כ"ח *Perek Kaf Chet*
towards the end, right? Just going to look.
Sorry, מלבד כאלה תעשו ליום שבעת ימים *milvad ka'eleh ta'asu layom shivat
yamim*. So before that it
says. Yeah, פסוק כ"ג Pasuk Kaf-Gimel. is מלבד עלת הבקר אשר לעלת
התמיד תעשו את אלה. Milvad olat haboker asher le'olat hatamid ta'asu et
eleh. Do these on top of or in addition to the קרבן
תמיד. Korban Tamid. And then כאלה תעשו לימים שבעת ימים לחם אשי
ריח ניחוח לה' על עולת התמיד יעשה ונסכו. kaeleh ta'asu layamim shivat
yamim lechem isheh reiach nichoach l'Adonai al olat hatamid ye'aseh venisko. So
the requirement to do them in addition is mentioned twice. So אביי
says מגופא דקרא if so, למה לי קרא lama li kra מלבד
עולת הבוקר? Should only have פסוק pasuk כ"ג. So what do I
need פסוק כ"ד Pasuk Kaf-Daled for? ושתוק veshtok אשר לעולת התמיד למה
לי lama li למימר דהא דתדירא תקדם. lemeimar deha detadira tikdam. So
אביי learns it from the same פרשה parsha in the תורה but
from a slightly different, maybe less convoluted דרשה that we learn this
general rule of primacy. You could have also just said, I mean
it's interesting that they don't take this avenue. You could have said
this sort of is just sort of a reasonable procedural rule. They're
trying to actually get it from the פסוקים. pesukim. They don't want
to just say, oh, this is a סברא, sevara, oh, this is
just the way we do things in בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but
that actually it has a scriptural basis as well, which is interesting.
We get to the next משנה mishna which proposes seemingly a competing
rule for primacy, and part of the debate in especially when this
comes up הלכה למעשה halacha lema'aseh in various contexts is, well, which
one of these rules is more important or which one of these
rules takes primacy? We had כל התדיר מחברו קודם לחברו kol hatadir
mechaveiro kodem lachaveiro that primacy is afforded according to frequency. And now
we have the rule in the משנה mishna כל המקודש מחברו קודם
לחברו, kol hamikudash mechaveiro kodem lachaveiro, whichever one is holier, whichever one
has a higher level of קדושה kedusha. should precede the other. So
the big question is, do you put on your טלית tallit first
or your תפילין tefillin first? טלית Tallit is worn seven days a
week for every day of the year, and but it's also of
a lower level קדושה. kedusha. The תפילין tefillin have שם השם, Shem
Hashem, they're really an object of קדושה. kedusha So are you supposed
to put your תפילין tefillin on before your טלית tallit because they're
מקודש מחברו, mikudash mechaveiro, or are you supposed to put the טלית
tallit on before the תפילין tefillin because they're כל התדיר מחברו? kol
hatadir mechaveiro? So that's a question which gets discussed, and as far
as I understand it, most people just put on their טלית tallit
first, though there are some people who put on טלית קטן, tallit
katan, then put on the תפילין, tefillin, and then put on the
טלית גדול tallit gadol later in different kind of permutations they're much
discussed at the beginning of אורח חיים. Orach Chayim. So the משנה
mishna says כל המקודש מחברו קודם לחברו, kol hamikudash mechaveiro kodem lachaveiro,
whichever is holier comes first. And now we have many examples. The
גמרא Gemara is going to go through various הוה אמינא hava amina,
why we would have thought otherwise. So the משנה mishna says דם
החטאת קודם לדם העולה, dam hachattat kodem ledam ha'olah, the blood of
a קרבן חטאת korban chattat precedes the blood of the קרבן עולה
korban olah מפני שהוא מרצה, mipnei shehu meratzeh, because the דם dam
of the קרבן חטאת korban chattat serves the כפרה kaparah process of
the קרבן korban and with the חטאת chattat as we already know,
we're more focused on the blood. With קרבן עולה, korban olah, the
blood is sort of there just to permit me then to bring
the איברים eivarim onto the מזבח. mizbeiach.
איברי עולה קודמים לאימורי חטאת. eivarei olah kodmim le'imurei chattat. On the
flip side, however, the limbs, the body,
sectioned-up limbs of the קרבן עולה korban olah precede אימורי חטאת, imurei
chattat, the portions of the קרבן חטאת, korban chattat, the fats and
the חלב chelev and everything which go on the מזבח mizbeiach מפני
שהוא כליל לאישים mipnei shehu kalil la'ishim because the קרבן עולה korban
olah will be entirely burnt. So now I want to try to
make a chart. I hope it will be clear.
So doesn't the עולה olah also affect atonement? Not really.
No? We sort of say that it does. We sort of say
that it does. Do you get atonement or not? Not really. I
mean, you could. We say that a קרבן עולה korban olah is
מכפר mechaper for מצות עשה mitzvat aseh that you forgot to do
or something like that. But it's generally not really focused on. So
the goal is, we could say מכפר, mechaper,
and then we, you know, the עולה olah is called always דורון.
doron. We have what do you, how, who eats it? We'll call
it אכליו. ochlav.
And we'll have כליל. kalil. We'll have the כהנים. kohanim. And we'll
have the בעלים. be'alim. We'll say, which we could also call this
is קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim,
that's a terrible abbreviation because now
קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. Okay.
What was the word you're using for עולה? olah?
The כליל, kalil, that it's fully burnt.
No, no, but for the עולה, olah, what's that word? דורון. Doron.
Which means?
Which means a gift. The גמרא Gemara calls the עולה olah a
דורון. doron. Ah, okay. So at least for now, we could sort
of see that the קרבן עולה korban olah in terms of who
eats it or what you do with the meat is of a
higher level קדושה kedusha, because the קרבן חטאת korban chattat is eaten
by the כהנים kohanim but the קרבן עולה korban olah is fully
burnt on the מזבח. mizbeiach. However, the קרבן עולה, korban olah, the
goal of the קרבן עולה korban olah is lower. The purpose of
bringing קרבן חטאת korban chattat is to be מכפר mechaper and that's
really equated with the דם, dam, which is given to a higher
status. So we see that the blood of the קרבן חטאת korban
chattat is of a higher sanctity and the meat of the קרבן
עולה korban olah is of a higher sanctity. So if you had
to choose between which one, the משנה mishna has given me two
different things. The גמרא Gemara. will then raise the possibility: what if
I'm talking about the blood of a חטאת chattat versus the limbs
of the עולה? olah? And vice versa. That is, at what point
does this typology start to break down and we try to see
sort of more interesting permutations? Okay. מפני שהוא כליל לאישים. Mipnei shehu
kalil la'ishim. חטאת קודמת לאשם Chattat kodemet le'asham מפני שדמה ניתן לארבע
קרנות על היסוד mipnei shedama nittan le'arba karnot al hayesod and it
should be ועל היסוד. ve'al hayesod.
That is now מתנות. matanot.
Okay. So we have four. We have
ב ד. And we have מתנה אחת. matana achat. Right, so we
have our קרבן חטאת korban chatat gets four מתנות. matanot. We have
קרבן אשם korban asham and קרבן עולה, korban olah, קרבן שלמים korban
shelamim get two which are really four and we get בכור bechor
and מעשר maaser really only get one מתנה על היסוד. matana al
hayesod. So we'll see that there's קדושה, kedusha that is there's multiple
different categories that we could be using to determine the קדושה kedusha.
of the קרבן korban, and different קרבנות korbanot are going to break
down different ways.
You know it also could be simple as the other principle that's
not mentioned here is אין מעבירין על המצוות. ein maavirin al hamitzvot.
Let's say for whatever reason they brought you the other one first,
you do that one first. Right. So it sounds here like לכתחילה
l'chatchila the rule will be the כהנים kohanim have to have a
working list of whatever's ready to go and then they'll see, okay,
well if this one, which one is the most מקודש mekudash and
I'll take that one first. And then the... oh that's a nice
bird.
Okay, fine. So the next one, so I'm going to call this
one עמו, imo, what comes along with it?
We're going to get to that in a second. Okay, so now
we say אשם קודם לתודה. asham kodem l'toda. קרבן אשם korban asham
precedes a קרבן תודה korban toda ואיל נזיר, v'eyl nazir, and the
איל נזיר, eyl nazir, the ram which is brought by a נזיר
nazir when he finishes his נזירות nezirut מפני שהיא קדשי קדשים mipne
shehi kodshei kodashim because the קרבן אשם korban asham is eaten only
by the כהנים kohanim and the איל נזיר eyl nazir and the
קרבן תודה korban toda could be eaten by the owners or by
ישראלים yisraelim or whomever. Okay, so תודה ואיל נזיר קודמים לשלמים toda
v'eyl nazir kodmim l'shelamim and the תודה toda and the איל נזיר
eyl nazir precede the שלמים shelamim because they get לחם. lechem. So
what I'm going to put here for now, we're going to get
back to it דמים אחרים. damim acherim.
You skipped a word because they're eaten only one day.
Oh did I?
And then לחם. lechem. מפני ש...
oh sorry, איל נזיר Eil Nazir קודמים לשלמים מפני שנאכלין ליום אחד,
right. Oh so I have to make another list which is how
many ימים? Right, you get one is more מקודש mekudash than two.
Or the ones that you don't eat at all, presumably, right, the
קרבן עולה korban olah which you don't eat at all is also
more מקודש. mekudash. Okay,
וטעונים לחם v'te'unim lechem and they need bread that comes along with
them. השלמים קודמים לבכור מפני שטעונים מתן ארבע. hashelamim kodmim labechor mipne
shete'unim matan arba. So the שלמים shelamim precede the בכור bechor because
the שלמים shelamim gets
מתנות matanot on the two opposite diagonal corners of the מזבח, mizbeach,
שתים שהן ארבע, shtayim shehen arba, וסמיכה usmichah and you have to
do סמיכה smichah on a קרבן שלמים korban shelamim unlike for בכור
bechor which doesn't get סמיכה, smichah, ונסכים. unesachim. So we could put
נסכים nesachim on the עמו imo category as well, the מנחה mincha
and the wine that comes along with קרבן שלמים, korban shelamim, ותנופות
חזה ושוק utnufot chaze v'shok and the כהן kohen has to take
the brisket and the foreleg of the שלמים shelamim and wave them
and the בכור bechor does not. הבכור קודם למעשר habechor kodem l'maaser
and בכור bechor precedes מעשר maaser מפני שקדושתו מרחם. mipne shekdushato merechem.
So בכור bechor precedes מעשר maaser because it has inherent sanctity which
we sort of just I don't know, קדושתו, kedushato, so there's מרחם
merechem and there's...
Do it, based on that you can say
that בכור bechor is more קדוש kadosh than everything. That is that's
the point is that we're in many different categories of what you
could choose. So now we could rank these, which of these is
the most important if two things are relatively equal in קדושה. kedusha.
If we would be otherwise confused or otherwise compare them, the גמרא
Gemara has now identified for us specific elements which distinguish them. So
this one applies mostly for בכור, bechor, this one will apply you
know in comparison of the different kinds of קדשים קלים kodshim kalim
etc. Who eats the בכור? bechor? Right,
so the who eats the בכור bechor is also that כהנים kohanim
eat it even though it's קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. So it's another
point.
That's the next word. Right, ונאכל לכהנים.
v'ne'echal lakohanim. ונאכל לכהנים v'ne'echal lakohanim exactly. So David is anticipating the
גמרא. Gemara I'm in it for the sanctity maybe. Yeah exactly right
so the fact that it's eaten by כהנים kohanim indicates that. So
here we get another chance to revisit all of the different קרבנות
korbanos and to compare which ones are holier than the others because
of which qualities. Okay,
ונאכל לכהנים. v'ne'echal lakohanim. המעשר קודם לעופות hamaser kodem l'ofot and מעשר
maaser precedes birds מפני שהוא זבח. mipne shehu zavach. So or מפני
שהוא מין זבח. mipne shehu min zavach. Right mammals have a higher
holiness than fowl and העופות קודמים למנחות ha'ofot kodmim l'minachot and birds
are better than מנחות minachot מפני שהן מיני דמים mipne shehen minei
damim because they have blood. The quality of the blood of the
animal being the מכפר, mechaper, so קרבן מנחה korban mincha is sort
of yes you can bring a קרבן מנחה korban mincha for a
חטא chet in various circumstances but it somehow lacks the same quality
as bringing a living being.
נדבה מפני שהיא בעל חטא... nedavah mipne shehi ba'al chet... so sorry,
מנחת חוטא קודמת למנחת נדבה. minchat chote kodemet l'minchat nedavah. You had
two different types of מנחה mincha that you could bring on a
normal circumstance let's say, a מנחה mincha that you bring as a
קרבן חטאת korban chatat or a מנחה mincha that you just bring
because you want to be מתנדב, mitnadev, you're donating the קרבן. korban.
So קרבן חוטא korban chote is better מפני שהוא בעל חטא. mipne
shehu ba'al chet. So now we've come full circle back to the
question of goal. Is it מכפר mechaper or is it just as
a gift?
So that's also used to distinguish them here.
מפני שהוא בעל חטא. mipne shehu ba'al chet. חטאת העוף קודמת לעולת
העוף chatat ha'of kodemet l'olat ha'of וכן בהקדשה. v'chen behakdesha. And חטאת
chatat of a bird precedes the עולה olah of birds for the
same reason that a חטאת chatat of a mammal precedes the עולה
olah of a mammal which is that it's מכפר mechaper or anything
else וכן בהקדשה v'chen behakdesha and also this applies to the order
in which they are sanctified. Which that is presumably when you separate
the two birds out you're supposed to designate which one will be
for the קרבן חטאת korban chatas and the second bird that goes
along with it will automatically be designated as a קרבן עולה korban
olah because the חטאת chatas has that primacy. Now we turn the
page, we'll get into the גמרא Gemara on this משנה. mishnah.
If a person does not and the כהן kohen
does it, the person could have... the whole מסכת קינים masechet kinnim
is all about what if you gave the כהן kohen many different
birds and now he doesn't know which ones are which or he
has to designate them or they were given סתם stam or unspecified
in various ways and all the complicated probabilities and math that comes
out of that. The גמרא Gemara says from the top of עמוד
ב', amud beis, פ"ט עמוד ב'. Pei Tes Amud Beis. מנא הני
מילי? Mina hanei mili? Where do we learn the rule that כל
המקודש מחברו קודם את חברו, kol ha-mekudash me-chavero kodem es chavero, that
whatever is holier has primacy in the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? So
the גמרא Gemara says דתנו רבנן, detanu rabanan, this is the ברייתא
beraisa that brings proof for that based on the פסוק pasuk, in
the beginning of פרשת בהעלותך. parshas Behaaloscha. פר שני בן בקר תקח
לחטאת. Par sheni ben bakar tikach l'chatas. When the לויים Leviyim were
being designated for their specific role, there were certain special קרבנות korbanos
that the לויים Leviyim had to bring which are basically without much
parallel in certain ways similar to the מלואים miluim which were used
to inaugurate the כהנים. kohanim. The לויים Leviyim have certain sacrifices and
they have to bring two bulls. One is designated as a קרבן
עולה korban olah and one is designated as a קרבן חטאת. korban
chatas. And the פסוק says פר שני בן בקר תקח לחטאת, par
sheni ben bakar tikach l'chatas, you take the second bull as a
חטאת. chatas. So the
ברייתא beraisa says: אם בא ללמד שהם שנים הרי כבר נאמר ועשה
את האחד חטאת ואת האחד עולה. im ba l'lamed she-heim shnayim harei
kvar ne'emar v'asah es ha-echad chatas v'es ha-echad olah. Then I already
knew that they were two bulls because you told me one is
for a חטאת chatas and one is for an עולה. olah. So
מה תלמוד לומר ופר שני בן בקר תקח לחטאת? mah talmud lomar
u-far sheni ben bakar tikach l'chatas? So what does it teach me
that the second bull is brought as a חטאת? chatas? שיכול שיהא
חטאת קודמת לכל מעשה עולה. she-yachol she-yehei chatas kodemes l'chol ma'aseh olah.
You might have thought that the חטאת chatas precedes the עולה olah
in every regard. That is, from the previous פסוק it mentioned חטאת
chatas first, so I already learned that the חטאת chatas in certain
ways precedes the עולה. olah. But it now calls the חטאת chatas
פר שני, par sheni, the second bull. So תלמוד לומר ופר שני
בן בקר תקח לחטאת, talmud lomar u-far sheni ben bakar tikach l'chatas,
you have to bring the second bull as a חטאת. chatas. אי
פר שני יכול תהא עולה קודמת לחטאת לכל מעשיה? ei par sheni
yachol tehei olah kodemes l'chatas l'chol ma'aseha?
So then I might have learned the opposite, that the עולה olah
should precede the חטאת chatas in every regard because it says פר
שני, par sheni, but the other פסוק calls the first one האחד
חטאת והאחד עולה. ha-echad chatas v'ha-echad olah. So the point here is
like we said, that in certain regards the עולה olah is of
a greater sanctity than a חטאת, chatas, specifically in the treatment of
its meat because the meat is fully burned. But in other regards
the blood of the חטאת chatas is of a higher sanctity than
the עולה. olah. So that is עולה olah and חטאת chatas compete
for first rank depends on which category we're comparing them. ועשה את
האחד חטאת והאחד עולה הכיצד? v'asah es ha-echad chatas v'ha-echad olah ha-keitzad?
So therefore what conclusion can we draw? We have different verses each
indicating that either the חטאת chatas or the עולה olah are of
higher sanctity or have to be done first. So how do we
reconcile them? דם חטאת קודם לדם עולה מפני שמרצה. Dam chatas kodem
l'dam olah mipnei she-meratzeh. The blood of the חטאת chatas precedes the
blood of the עולה olah because it's מרצה, meratzeh, because it brings
כפרה. kaparah. But vice versa, the אימורים. imurim. And by the way
the משנה, mishnah, I love this, the משנה mishnah has a very
precise language. The משנה mishnah uses the word איברים eivarim to refer
to the limbs of the עולה olah and only uses the word
אימורים imurim for the חטאת chatas because the עולה, olah, the real
meat of the animal, the whole body cut up into parts is
burned on the מזבח, mizbeiach, and the אימורים imurim is a reference
only to the חלב chelev and the various offal.
We never asked that
the דם dam comes first. דם dam comes first. The מתנות matanos
of the דם dam are put first onto the מזבח. mizbeiach.
So why didn't it just
say... then I would think...
Oh, but then it makes perfect sense. The first פסוק in the
תורה says את האחד חטאת והאחד עולה. es ha-echad chatas v'ha-echad olah.
No, it doesn't. No.
ועשה האחד חטאת והאחד עולה ופר שני בן בקר תקח
לחטאת.
v'asah ha-echad chatas v'ha-echad olah u-far sheni ben bakar tikach
l'chatas.
That comes first.
That comes first. That would have done it the other way around.
Exactly what you were... that's exactly what I questioned.
Anyway, we have the דרשה. We know. The principle is in certain
regards, that is, we know certain ways the חטאת chatas come before
the עולה, olah, we know certain ways the עולה olah comes before
the חטאת. chatas. And now the question is, well, which ways? Which
ways are unique to them or which ways indicate their higher sanctity?
The עולה olah is of higher sanctity because it's כליל, kalil, so
we apply that specifically to the meat of the animal and the
reverse, the חטאת, chatas, what's most specific about the חטאת chatas rather
than the עולה? olah? It has ארבע מתנות. arba matanos. It has
that the דם dam is מרצה meratzeh for חטא. chet. So all
of those reasons make it that the דם dam of the חטאת
chatas is central and the איברים eivarim of the עולה olah are
central for the עולה olah and they each have primacy in that
regard. So now the גמרא Gemara says איברי עולה וכולי. eivarei olah
v'chulu.
So now we have the rule. So אמאי מתנה קמייתא דמכפר תקדם?
amai matana kamaisa d'mechaper tikdam?
Why not, we could solve this whole problem, do it a different
way, instead of saying... All of the blood of the חטאת chatat
should come first, say wait a second, the blood of the חטאת
chatat is מכפר, michaper, yeah? But really only the first מתנה matana
of blood is what really affects the כפרה kapara and the rest
are just לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So why not do one מתנה matana of
blood from the חטאת, chatat, just one קרן, keren, the southeast corner,
then do the עולה olah because it's really inherently higher sanctity because
we know that because it's burned on the מזבח, mizbeiach, so do
the blood for the עולה olah then and then do the other
three for the חטאת? chatat?
Because that's just too
confusing. Okay.
You think like the ירושלמי אמוראים, Yerushalmi Amoraim, but we're going to
see two different answers to this question. Okay. So אמאי מתנה קמייתא
דמכפרא תקדם והנך לא? amai matana kamaita demichapra tikdom v'hanach lo? So
אמר רבינא, amar Ravina, רבינא Ravina says הכא בחטאת הלוים עסקינן. hacha
b'chatat haleviim askinan.
The proof was brought from a very exceptional or sui generis kind
of חטאת chatat which is not brought for any sin, and nonetheless
ואף על גב דכי עולה דמי. v'af al gav dechi olah dami.
So even though that it is not brought for a sin, it
still is given primacy over the עולה, olah, so that should teach
me a blanket rule no matter what, everything from the קרבן חטאת
korban chatat has to come before the עולה olah for the blood
because it's sort of a general rule for קרבן חטאת, korban chatat,
it doesn't have anything to do with whether this actual... what do
you mean ואף על גב דכי עולה דמי? v'af al gav dechi
olah dami? What does that mean? Because that is even though this
קרבן korban. is not בעל חטא, baal cheit, it still is treated
with the primacy of the קרבן חטאת korban chatat before the עולה.
olah. Therefore, the other three מתנות, matanot, the numbers two, three, and
four of the קרבן חטאת korban chatat that come after the קרבן
korban has already been מרוצה merutze should also still take primacy over
the קרבן עולה. korban olah.
That doesn't explain why.
No, it's what it's saying is... is a kind of a... what?
The first... okay. Right, but since we're learning it from a קרבן
חטאת korban chatat that has no atonement involved, or no sin really
involved, the לוים Leviim are מכפר michaper in sort of a general
sense, right? But not in a real specific sense. By the way,
what does it even mean like 22,000 לוים Leviim or whatever bringing
a... or whatever, however more... no, yeah, like 22,000 לוים Leviim bringing...
bringing one קרבן חטאת korban chatat together. I don't understand, is that
a communal קרבן korban or is that an individual קרבן korban that
they're all partners in? And how can partners have a קרבן חטאת?
korban chatat? So it's also a very strange notion. It's a very
exceptional קרבן, korban which is sort of the point. So רבינא's Ravina
proof is because it's an exceptional קרבן Korban that's not really a
normal קרבן חטאת korban chatat and we're learning this rule anyway, you
should just say this is the blanket rule, חטאת chatat comes before
עולה. olah. Don't try to, as Michael said, it gets too confusing.
One... one מתנה matana and then go back and get the עולה
olah and then come back and do the other three. It's too
confusing. So ואף על גב v'af al gav okay, so דכי עולה
דמי קאמר רחמנא היא תקדם. dechi olah dami ka'amar Rachmana hi tikdom.
So
nonetheless it should come first. That is, even though it's sort of
different than a normal קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. במערבא אמרי b'maarava amrei
and the ארץ ישראל אמוראים Eretz Yisrael Amoraim explained in a much
more simplistic way, הואיל והתחיל במתנות גומר. hoiel vehitchil bematanot gomeir. Once
you've started one קרבן, you have the מזרק mizrak in your hand,
you have it or... you're ready to go, right? Just do the...
do the מתנות, matanot, do one, two, three, four, you're done, and
then and then go get the blood of the עולה. olah. You'd
get way too confused. Okay. Very often we see the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi
answers to certain questions are much more sort of practical and straightforward
rather than getting too convoluted.
They were doing it. But I mean... yeah. They weren't doing it.
No, but I mean it's more practical there probably you know in
terms of...
they're going to... no, it's just the thinking. The thinking was more
a practical kind of thinking to have less convoluted proofs. Anyway.
I guess that's related to... I don't know.
I'm not sure. In בבל Bavel they were also hoping that the
בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash would be rebuilt and they would be returning
to do it. Okay, the גמרא Gemara now asks a number of
possible questions, some of which are left unanswered and some of which
are answered with interesting answers. Now we're sort of testing this paradigm,
in which ways are there cases which kind of push the limits
of the paradigm? So the גמרא gemara asks: איבעיא להו דם חטאת
ואיברי עולה. ibaia lehu dam chatat ve'evarei olah. What about the blood
of a חטאת chatat versus the limbs of the עולה? olah? That
is the two holiest aspects of each קרבן. איזה מהן קודם? eizeh
meihen kodem? Which one of them should come first? דם חטאת קודם
מפני שמרוצה, dam chatat kodem mipnei shemerutze, should the blood of the
חטאת chatat take precedence because it is מכפר michaper for a sin?
או דילמא איברי עולה קודם מפני שהן כליל לאישים, o dilma evarei
olah kodem mipnei shehein kalil la'ishim, or the limbs of the עולה
olah because they're fully burned on the מזבח? mizbeiach? That is, each
one has a defining trait. So תא שמע דם חטאת קודם לדם
עולה. ta shema dam chatat kodem l'dam olah. So it sounds from
the משנה Mishna that the blood of a חטאת chatat precedes the
blood of the עולה. olah. So we could say לדם עולה הוא
דקדים. l'dam olah hu dekadim. It only precedes the blood of the
עולה, olah, which is less important regarding the עולה olah because the
thing that's special about the עולה olah are the איברים. evarim. לאיברי
עולה לא קדים. l'evarei olah lo kadim. It
should not precede the limbs of the עולה. olah. So you could
infer that from the משנה Mishna and therefore you would say that
actually the limbs of an עולה olah take precedence even before the
blood of a קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. So now the גמרא gemara
says back, אדרבה מסיפא, aderaba m'seifa, from the end of the משנה
Mishna we can read איברי עולה קודמין לאימורי חטאת. evarei olah kodmin
l'emurei chatat. The limbs of the עולה olah precede the fats of
the קרבן חטאת. korban chatat. לאימורי חטאת הוא דקדים. l'emurei chatat hu
dekadim. So it's only for the fats of the קרבן חטאת... korban
chatat... that actually the limbs of an עולה ola take precedence even
before the blood of a קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. So now the
גמרא gemara says back, אדרבה מסיפא, adaraba meseifa, from the end of
the משנה mishna we can read, איברי עולה קודמים לאימורי חטאת, evarei
ola kodmim le'emorei chatas, the limbs of the עולה ola precede the
fats of the קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. לאימורי חטאת הוא דקדים, le'emorei
chatas hu dekadim, so it's only for the fats of the קרבן
חטאת korban chatas that the limbs of the עולה ola are able
to precede, לדם חטאת לא קדים, ledam chatas lo kadim, but they
could not precede the blood of the קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. So
we are stuck. אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה. ela me'ha lekka lemishma
mina. We can't actually infer anything about this case from our משנה,
mishna, sort of left somewhat unresolved. I didn't get a chance to
check in the רמב"ם Rambam how the רמב"ם Rambam פוסק, paskens, my
sense is that it should be the blood of the חטאת chatas
should precede but I'm not a hundred percent sure I didn't check
in.
Isn't that what we just stated?
No, remember the משנה mishna said blood of the חטאת chatas comes
before the blood of the עולה ola and the limbs of the
עולה ola come before the limbs of the חטאת. chatas. And now
the גמרא Gemara has asked which comes first, blood of a חטאת
chatas or the limbs of an עולה? ola? So we're sort of
doing a mix and match. That is each one is special in
its own way, now how do I know which one is more,
more קדוש kadosh than the other? The גמרא Gemara now asks the
opposite question. איבעיא להו, ibayeil'hu, the third to last of the skinny
lines. איבעיא להו: ibayeil'hu: דם עולה ואימורי חטאת. dam ola ve'emorei chatas.
What about the blood of the עולה ola and the fats of
the קרבן חטאת? korban chatas? איזה מהן קודם? eizu mehen kodem? Which
one should come first? דם עולה קודם דקאתי מכוח כליל. dam ola
kodem deka'ati mikoach kalil. Should we say that it should be the
blood of the קרבן עולה korban ola because it comes from מכוח
כליל, mikoach kalil, it comes from it's a derivative, it comes out,
outgrowth of the sacrifice which is fully
burned? או דילמא אימורי חטאת קודמין דקאתי מכוח מכפר, odilma emorei chatas
kodmin deka'ati mikoach mechaper, or because they're then outgrowth or derivative of
the sacrifice which is actually מכפר mechaper for a sin? So תא
שמע: tashma: דם חטאת קודם לדם עולה. dam chatas kodem ledam ola.
We try to make the same kind of inference from our משנה.
mishna. The blood of the חטאת chatas comes before the blood of
the עולה. ola. דם חטאת הוא דקדמי לדם עולה. dam chatas hu
dekadmei ledam ola. It's only the blood of the חטאת chatas which
should precede the blood of the עולה, ola, אבל אימורי חטאת לא,
aval emorei chatas lo, maybe you would not say that the fats
of the קרבן חטאת korban chatas should precede the blood of the
עולה, ola, that is עולה ola blood is still holier than חטאת
chatas fat. לא אדרבה, lo adaraba, you could infer the opposite מסיפא,
meseifa, from the end of the משנה. mishna. איברי עולה קודמין לאימורי
חטאת. evarei ola kodmim le'emorei chatas. Only the limbs of the עולה
ola are of higher sanctity than the fats of the חטאת. chatas.
איברי עולה הוא דמקדמי לאימורי חטאת, evarei ola hu demakde- makdemai le'emorei
chatas,
so the limbs of the עולה ola are of higher sanctity than
the fats of the חטאת, chatas, אבל דם עולה לא, aval dam
ola lo, but not the blood of the עולה. ola. So you
can't draw this inference, אלא מהא ליכא למשמע מינה, ela me'ha lekka
lemishma mina, and again we cannot draw a conclusive inference from our
משנה mishna regarding this question. So we're sort of left hanging and
in this regard it sounds like again like the הלכה halacha in
my mind should be that we should sort of give just the,
give the primacy to the blood itself. The blood is given a
higher sanctity than the burning of the limbs. So that's a different
kind of a paradigm which is seeing which part of the עבודה
avoda is of a higher קדושה. Kedushah We sort of have this
intuitive sense that the blood is of holier status, but at least
with the קרבן עולה korban ola it's kind of pushing that boundary.
Okay, next question. איבעיא להו. ibayeil'hu. Following question: דם עולה ודם אשם,
איזה מהן קודם? dam ola vedam asham eizu mehen kodem?
Now the משנה mishna was explicit comparing the blood of the חטאת
chatas and the blood of the עולה, ola, that blood of a
חטאת chatas is of a higher sanctity than the blood of the
עולה. ola. But what about קרבן אשם? korban asham? קרבן אשם korban
asham in certain regard is similar to a חטאת chatas in that
the blood is מכפר mechaper for the sin. On the other hand
it's more similar to the blood of a קרבן עולה korban ola
because it is only put on two of the four corners of
the מזבח mizbeach on a diagonal. So you might say, well which
one? And this is the question which permeates the entire מסכת masechet
is what is actually the nature of a קרבן אשם? korban asham?
Is קרבן אשם korban asham something similar, more similar to a קרבן
עולה korban ola or is it something really more similar to a
קרבן חטאת? korban chatas? Is it an עולה ola that the כהנים
kohanim get to eat and that comes for a sin? Or is
it a קרבן חטאת korban chatas that only gets two corners of
the מזבח mizbeach and it is of a lower level sanctity? So
that's sort of the question and there are other qualities of the
קרבן אשם korban asham as well that kind of butt heads against
some of this. So we'll see. איבעיא להו: ibayeil'hu: דם עולה ודם
אשם dam ola vedam asham, איזה מהן קודם? eizu mehen kodem? Which
one comes first? דם עולה קודם. dam ola kodem. Maybe you should
say that the עולה ola blood is higher דקאתי מכוח כליל deka'ati
mikoach kalil because it is a derivative of a sacrifice which is
fully burned unlike the אשם asham which will be eaten by the
כהנים. kohanim. או דילמא דם אשם קודם דמכפר? odilma dam asham kodem
demichaper? Maybe you should say that the blood of the אשם asham
is of a higher sanctity because it's מכפר. mechaper. That is if
we said the whole thing, the reason why the blood of the
חטאת chatas was more special and more קדוש kadosh than the blood
of the עולה ola because it's מכפר mechaper so the same should
be true for קרבן אשם korban asham as well. So תא שמע,
tashma, we learn the following way: דם חטאת קודם לדם עולה. dam
chatas kodem ledam ola. Our משנה mishna says that the blood of
the חטאת chatas comes before the blood of the עולה, ola, אבל
דם אשם לא, aval dam asham lo, it doesn't mention the blood
of the אשם. asham. בדין הוא, badin hu, no you could say
that you learn it out logically. דאיבעי למיתני דם אשם ואיידי דאיבעי
למיתני סיפא, de'iba lemisni dam asham ve'aydi de'iba lemisni seifa, because the
only reason the משנה mishna left off the, if it had mentioned
blood of the אשם asham ואיידי דאיבעי למיתני סיפא ve'aydi de'iba lemisni
seifa because when the משנה mishna comes to teach the end of
the משנה, mishna, איברי עולה קודמין לאימורי חטאת. evarei ola kodmim le'emorei
chatas. Because it says that the limbs of the קרבן עולה korban
ola precede the fats of the קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. דאי תנא
לאימורי אשם, de'i tana le'emorei asham, if you would have said לאימורי
אשם, emorei asham, so if if the parallelism in the משנה mishna
had been comparing עולה ola to אשם asham rather than חטאת chatas
to עולה, ola, then we would have had the following problem. That
is what? הוה אמינא, havah amina, I would have thought לאימורי אשם
הוא דקדמי le'emorei asham hu dekadmei that the limbs of the עולה
olah *Olah* can precede the fats of the קרבן אשם Korban Asham.
*Korban Asham*, חטאת Chatat לא קדמי *Chatas lo kadmei* but that they
would not precede the fats of the חטאת Chatat *Chatat* and actually
the highest level in terms of the fats and limbs would actually
still be the חטאת chatas? *Chatat* as well. So משום הכי *mishum
hachi* that's why the תנא תנא חטאת chatas, *tana tana Chatat*, the
תנא *tana* was discussing the laws of חטאת chatas *Chatat* and not
אשם *Asham* and left אשם *Asham* out of the list, but we
could still draw the inference. So חטאת Chatas קודם kodem לאשם *Chatas
kodem le'Asham*, so תא שמע *ta shema* חטאת Chatas קודם לאשם *Chatas
kodem le'Asham*, we can learn חטאת Chatas *Chatat* precedes אשם *Asham* because
חטאת Chatas *Chatat* is of a higher level קדושה Kedushah *kedusha* than
the קרבן אשם Korban Asham, *Korban Asham* because of the מתנות matanos,
*matanos* etc. חטאת Chatas הוא דקדמי ליה לאשם *Chatas hu de'kadmei lei
le'Asham* that חטאת *Chatat* precedes אשם *Asham* אבל עולה olah לא *aval
Olah lo* but עולה olah *Olah* should come after the אשם *Asham*.
That is the quality of being מכפר *mechaper* for a sin bumps
the אשם *Asham* up to a higher level sanctity than the עולה
Olah *Olah*.
So מאי לאו *mai lav* דם *dam*? Are we, so that reference,
is that a reference to the blood of the sacrifice and that
we should say oh well that makes perfect sense because we're talking
about מכפר *mechaper*? לא, אימורין *lo, emurin*, we're talking about the limbs
and the fats. So דיקא נמי דקתני *deika nami de'kasni* and that's
why it makes sense in the language of the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
that says מפני שדמה ניתן *mipnei she'doma nitan*. The quality of the
חטאת *Chatat* in reference to the אשם *Asham* is specifically regarding it
says דמה *doma*, its blood. That is we're talking actually about the
meat and the body of the animal. So in that regard we
see that the limbs and the meat of the of the קרבן
חטאת Korban Chatas, *Korban Chatat* are of higher primacy than the אשם
*Asham*, so the ranking in terms of אימורין *emurin*
should
be עולה Olah. *Olah*, חטאת *Chatat*, and then אשם *Asham*. And in
terms of the blood should be חטאת *Chatat*, אשם
*Asham*, and then עולה Olah, *Olah*. So really אשם *Asham* just always
goes with חטאת *Chatat*, but it's sort of one notch down.
It's a lower קדושה Kedushah, *kedusha* version of a חטאת *Chatat*, at
least the conclusion from here.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues חטאת קודמת
*Chatas
kodemes*.
I just want to check the משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah*. So now we're up to the next part which is again
discussing the קרבן אשם *Korban Asham*. The משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* had said
חטאת קודם לאשם מפני שדמה ניתן על ארבע קרנות ועל היסוד *Chatas
kodem le'Asham mipnei she'doma nitan al arba karnos ve'al ha'yesod* because the
blood is put on the four corners of the מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbeiach*
and also is put on the יסוד *yesod* of the מזבח Mizbe'ach,
*mizbeiach*. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks אדרבה adrabba, *aderaba*, maybe
you should say אשם *Asham* still has a quality which makes it
of a higher קדושה Kedushah *kedusha* than the חטאת *Chatat*? That is,
all these are sort of suggestions which test the qualities that we've
already outlined in the משנה *Mishnah*. So this is now, so we
had three questions of איבעיא להו ibaya lehu, *ibaia lehu*, no, we
had three questions, איבעיא להו *ibaia lehu*, איבעיא להו *ibaia lehu*, two
that were opposites of each other and then we introduced אשם *Asham*
to the equation as well. Now we ask אדרבה אשם קדים *aderaba
Asham kadim*, maybe you should say אשם *Asham* should be before חטאת
*Chatat* שכן יש לו קצבה *she'ken yesh lo kitzva* because the אשם
*Asham* has to be of a fixed price. קרבן אשם *Korban Asham*,
at least for certain kinds of אשמות *ashamos*, has to be specifically
by one שקל *shekel* to buy the animal, which is an expensive
animal. אפילו הכי Afilu hachi *afillu hachi* ריבוי דמזבח עדיף *ribui de'mizbeiach
adif*. So nonetheless we say no, because the מזבח *mizbeiach* gets more
מתנות matanos *matanos*, the חטאת *Chatat* has all four corners, we say
that's really the defining quality of the קדושה Kedushah *kedusha* of the
קרבן חטאת Korban Chatat *Korban Chatat* even more than the קרבן אשם
*Korban Asham*. So even though the קרבן אשם *Korban Asham* could be
more expensive, it's a male animal, it's sort of somehow more higher
quality, nonetheless we say the defining quality is still the nature of
the מתנות *matanos*. אשם קודם לתודה *Asham kodem le'Todah*. The משנה *Mishnah*
had said that the אשם *Asham* precedes a תודה Todah *Todah* because
it's קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim, *kodshei kodashim*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אדרבה התודה ואיל נזיר nazir קדמי שכן טעונין לחם lechem *aderaba
ha'Todah ve'ayil nazir kadmei she'ken te'unin lechem*. Maybe you should say, that
is we still said there's nothing that goes along with a קרבן
אשם *Korban Asham*. These קרבנות korbanos, *korbanos* get a breads that come
along with them, so the איל נזיר Eil Nazir, *ayil nazir* and
the תודה Todah *Todah*. So maybe you should say they have a
higher קדושה Kedushah *kedusha* because they have something that comes along with.
So we say אפילו הכי קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim, עדיפי *afillu hachi
kodshei kodashim adifei*. It's better, more primary classification is who eats the
קרבן *korban*. If it's קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* that the כהנים Kohanim,
*kohanim* eat, that's a more important classification and then the question of
what comes along with it will only be a classification within קדשים
קלים *kodashim kalim*. That is we have primary classification and we have
secondary classification. We're going to end up with the kind of ranking
that we're, the issue here is is this list where עולה Olah
*Olah* has switched order but then you're going to end up with
תודה Todah, *Todah*, איל נזיר Eil Nazir, *ayil nazir*, שלמים Shelamim. *shelamim*,
בכור bechor *bechor*, מעשר ma'aser.
*ma'aser*,
עוף Of *of*,
and מנחה *mincha*. That's that's our list. That is we're basically in
a good place here and now we're sort of testing the water.
So we said wait a second, why is אשם *Asham* of a
higher קדושה Kedushah *kedusha* than תודה Todah *Todah* and איל נזיר Eil
Nazir *ayil nazir* because they have bread? We say no, because these
are קדשי קדשים *kodshei kodashim* and these are קדשים קלים *kodashim kalim*.
So that's why you draw a big bold line across the middle
here and say well this is of a different class than these.
Okay, גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, תודה ואיל נזיר. Todah ve'Eil Nazir. So we said that תודה
Todah and איל נזיר Eil Nazir. are of a higher level קדושה
Kedushah. than the שלמים. Shelamim So the גמרא again asks, אדרבא, adaraba,
maybe you should say instead שלמים קדמי, Shelamim kadmi, maybe שלמים Shelamim
should be of a higher קדושה Kedushah than the תודה Todah and
the איל נזיר, Eil Nazir? שכן ישנן בציבור כביחיד, sheken yeshnan b'tzibbur
k'b'yachid,
because there is such a thing as a שלמים Shelamim which is
brought by the ציבור. tzibbur. By the way though, the שלמים Shelamim
which is brought by the ציבור tzibbur is actually קדשי קדשים, it's
very similar to the קרבן אשם.
It's eaten only by the כהנים, Kohanim, it has two מתנות, we
learn that in the fifth פרק. Perek
So but because there exists such a thing of a שלמים Shelamim
associated with the ציבור, tzibbur, that means that even an individual's שלמים
Shelamim you might have said has a higher level of קדושה, Kedushah.
and we reject this הוה אמינא, we say instead אפילו הכי נאכלין
ליום אחד עדיפי. afillu hachi ne'echalin l'yom echad adifei. It's better to
define how many days you get to eat the קרבן. קרבן חטאת,
Korban Chatat. קרבן אשם, תודה, Todah איל נזיר, Eil Nazir you only
can eat for one day. שלמים Shelamim you can eat for two
days. So if you can eat it for two days, it means
it's of a lower level of קדושה Kedushah automatically. Don't give me
this alternative suggestion, I'll say the more primary notion of קדושה Kedushah
should be the number of ימים, and but we could also say
who are the בעלים, be'alim, you could say ציבור tzibbur is of
a better
קדושה kedusha. than an individual, better than the יחיד. yachid. So we
have many different aspects of each קרבן that are associated what makes
them holier than the others, but we still know there's certain characteristics
which are most primary: who gets to eat it, how many מתנות
are there on the מזבח, how many days do you get to
eat it, the things that we're more familiar with and the things
which we're less familiar with. The reason why we're less familiar with
them is because they come up less often or they're less important
in this classification. Okay.
In earlier when we used the example of the לויים Levi'im being
consecrated, we used that as a as our point of reasoning, but
here we're not using the communal aspect of the שלמים Shelamim which
is high on a higher level. Of which?
About the לויים. Levi'im. The לויים Levi'im point is that that קרבן
is sort of sui generis, it was a specific sort of one-time-in-history
special קרבן חטאת Korban Chatas. that was a unique aspect. I'm not
sure it's because it was a communal חטאת necessarily, sort of just
totally sui generis. And רבינא's Ravina point was because it's sui generis,
you learn that the rule applies not specifically to the act of
כפרה kaparah but to defining the class of קרבן חטאת. So that
was רבינא's Ravina argument about that. Okay.
Right here, right here we're not using the special quality of the
שבועות Shevuos aspect of the שלמים Shelamim. in the same way.
We say it's a very minor quality like, by the way, the
vast majority of קרבן שלמים Korban Shelamim will be individual שלמים. Shelamim
And only twice two כבשים kvasim on שבועות Shevuos are going to
be שלמים Shelamim for the community. They're very you know a few
times other times in history where there were שלמים Shelamim brought on
a ציבור tzibbur level, but basically it's very rare.
It's the same with the חטאת I'm saying of the לויים. Levi'im.
That was only once, but it's I mean the general...
I'm having a hard time seeing the association there. I see what
you're doing but I'm not sure there's much connection. That's fine. Okay.
גמרא asks a follow-up question to what we just said, that is
we rejected the possibility that the שלמים shlamim should be considered of
a higher קדושה kedusha. than תודה and איל נזיר Eil Nazir because
it has a communal aspect, because we said נאכלין ליום אחד עדיפי.
ne'echalin l'yom echad adifei. If they're only eaten for one day, that
indicates that they have a higher level of קדושה. kedusha גמרא said,
איבעיא להו, so fine, we can question the ranking in in the
list of תודה and איל נזיר. Eil Nazir תודה ואיל נזיר איזה
מהם קודם? Todah ve'Eil Nazir eizeh mehem kodem? Which one should be
first, תודה or איל נזיר? Eil Nazir, תודה קדמה שכן טעונה ארבעה
מיני לחם, Todah kadma sheken te'una arba'ah minei lechem,
maybe the קרבן תודה Korban Todah is of a higher level קדושה
kedusha because it gets four different types of bread, three of which
are made of מצה, matzah, ten loaves each, one of which are
חמץ chametz breads, ten of which. או דילמא איל נזיר קודם שכן
יש עמו דמים אחרים, odilma Eil Nazir kodem sheken yesh imo damim
acherim,
maybe you should say the איל נזיר Eil Nazir, is קודם, שכן
יש עמו דמים אחרים. sheken yesh imo damim acherim. That is,
when we talk about what comes along with it, which is sort
of the defining characteristic of each of these, the תודה gets לחם
and we could say they're four and two different kinds of bread,
the איל נזיר eil nazir only gets two different kinds of bread,
but it also gets דמים אחרים. damim acherim. Along with the איל
נזיר eil nazir? you also bring a קרבן עולה Korban Olah and
a קרבן חטאת. And so the question of, well, it gets actually
other קרבנות korbanos which come along with it for the איל eil
נזיר, so maybe that's a higher level of קדושה. kedusha And we
say no,
sorry, I lost the spot.
So תא שמע זו קודמת לזו. ta shema zu kodemes l'zo. So
the משנה says this one is of a higher level קדושה kedusha
than this one. שזו טעונה ארבעה מיני לחם וזו אינה טעונה אלא
שני מיני לחם. shezu te'una arba'ah minei lechem v'zu eina te'una ela
shnei minei lechem.
The defining quality of both of them should be the breads, how
many different types of bread come with it, and therefore a קרבן
תודה Korban Todah is of a higher קדושה kedusha than the איל
נזיר, and we don't bring into the equation this דמים אחרים, damim
acherim, other קרבנות, korbanot because guess what, the other קרבנות korbanos, that
come along with
it... How much do you see it as a package deal? All
three קרבנות Korbanos. of the נזיר and how much are they individual
in מסכת נזיר? Masechet Nazir? The question is when can he get
his haircut? There's מחלוקת תנאים: machloket Tannaim: is it dependent specifically on
the איל or could it even be with of the other קרבנות,
the עולה Olah and the חטאת? So that's part of this question
as well. What is it? Is it that the איל נזיר is
attended to by this עולה and חטאת, or are the עולה and
חטאת sort of their own thing separate from the איל נזיר? Okay.
The גמרא has a following question: השלמים קודמים לבכור. hashlamim kodmim labechor.
The גמרא had said that שלמים shlamim is קודם to בכור bechor,
because שלמים shlamim. have many different qualities: you have סמיכה, smeicha, they
need four corners, you have to bring נסכים, neisachim, they have to
have the תנופה, tenufah, all these different specific nature of the קרבן
שלמים korban shlamim different than the קרבן בכור. korban bechor. The גמרא
asks: אדרבה בכור קודם שכן קדושתו מרחם. adrabba bechor kodem sheken kedushato
m'rechem. If we're talking about בכור, bechor, the most defining quality of
a בכור, bechor unlike every other קרבן basically except ולד חטאת vlad
chatas or something which you can't
bring—I'm trying to think if a ולד עולה, vlad olah, what you
do with a ולד עולה, vlad olah, I forget—but
so the basic quality of the בכור bechor is that it's קדוש
מרחם, kadosh m'rechem, it's born into its קדושה. kedusha Every other קרבן
is designated by a human being to have its קדושה. Kedushah So
maybe we should say בכור bechor is of a higher level קדושה
Kedushah than the שלמים. shlamim ונאכל לכוהנים, v'ne'echal lakohanim, and it's eaten
by the כוהנים kohanim and the שלמים shlamim is only eaten by
is eaten mostly by the owners. So אפילו הכי מצוות יתירות עדיפי.
afillu hachi mitzvos yeteros adifei. It's better, the שלמים shlamim. is better
because it has many מצוות, mitzvos, many different things. You do סמיכה,
smeicha, you do נסכים, neisachim, you do תנופה, tenufah, you do, right,
so many of those different qualities are what define the שלמים. There
are many different ways in which it's better than the בכור bechor.
or a higher קדושה Kedushah. than the בכור. bechor Okay.
הבכור קודם, habechor kodem, so בכור bechor. precedes מעשר. ma'aser And again
we said the main reason was because it's קדוש מרחם. kadosh m'rechem.
So now we say אדרבה מעשר קודם שכן מקדש לפניו ולאחריו. adrabba
ma'aser kodem sheken mikadesh lifanav v'l'acharyav.
So maybe you should say that מעשר ma'aser is of a higher
level קדושה than the בכור. bechor For what this phrase actually means,
take a look in the רש"י Rashi one second.
Find the spot in
רש"י. Rashi.
לפניו ולאחריו. lifanav v'l'acharyav. So רש"י Rashi says דתנן קרא לתשיעי עשירי
ולעשירי תשיעי. detnan kra litshi'i asiri v'la'asiri tshi'i. What if you messed
up when you were counting the מעשר ma'aser. animals? That is, the
animals walking through the דיר, dir, walking through the sheepfold, and you
count them: one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten,
and the tenth one becomes מעשר. ma'aser, So what if by accident
I mixed up and I called the ninth one number ten, or
I called the tenth one number nine, or I called the eleventh
one number ten or whatever? ולאחר עשר עשירי שלושתן מקודשים. v'l'achar asar
asiri shloshtan mekudashim. So all three of them attain the status of
the בכור—that bechor, is, if I have number nine, number ten, and
number eleven, and I call this one, right, I make a speech
balloon here and I called it number ten, I called this one
number nine, and I called this one
number
ten, right? So either being the tenth one gives it קדושה בכור,
bechor right?
So this one is בכור bechor because it actually is the tenth
one, and these ones are בכור bechor. because you called them בכור.
bechor. Okay. So that actually can all three of them, we say
שלושתן
מקודשים. shloshtan mekudashim.
Okay. All three become the בכור. bechor, So מעשר, ma'aser. sorry, I
said בכור, bechor, I mean מעשר. ma'aser That is, מעשר ma'aser is
entirely dependent on your designation, but and the counting. So the point
is because I made a mistake in the counting, so the tenth
one, which really is supposed to be מעשר ma'aser from God's perspective,
is also מעשר ma'aser. and the ones which I called the tenth
one are מעשר. ma'aser There are questions to what extent can you
designate more than ten percent of your flock to be מעשר ma'aser
and things like that, but at least in the abstract, in this
kind of a case where you messed up, the משנה says, as
רש"י Rashi quotes, לפניו ולאחריו דתנן קרא, lifanav v'l'acharyav detnan kra, right,
דתנן קרא לתשיעי עשירי. detnan kra litshi'i asiri. You called the ninth
one ten. ולעשירי תשיעי, v'la'asiri tshi'i, and you called the tenth one
number
nine. ולאחר עשר עשירי שלושתן מקודשים. v'l'achar asar asiri shloshtan mekudashim. Okay.
And it's learned out from a פסוק, so it's actually an intrinsic
quality of how מעשר ma'aser works. So you might have said מעשר
קודם. ma'aser kodem. מעשר ma'aser has a higher level קדושה than בכור,
bechor why? שכן מקדש לפניו ולאחריו. sheken mikadesh lifanav v'l'acharyav.
It can even make the ones that come before it number nine
or the number that comes after it number eleven also make them
קדוש. kadosh. אפילו הכי קדושה מרחם עדיפא. afillu hachi kedusha m'rechem adifa.
Even still, it's better to have קדושה מרחם; kedusha m'rechem; בכור being
born קדוש kadosh is a better quality than even this fancy sort
of double-counting system where we care both about what you said and
which number it actually was. Okay. מעשר קודם לעופות. ma'aser kodem l'ofos.
And the משנה had concluded that the מעשר Ma'aser, precedes the bird
sacrifices, that is, we think all mammal sacrifices should have a higher
level קדושה than birds. So אדרבה, maybe we could say עופות קדמי
שכן קודשי. ofos kadmi sheken kodshei. Maybe you should say that birds
precede the מעשר, and maybe we should really put the birds up
here with the חטאת and the עולה because guess what? Birds are
חטאת and עולה. The חטאת העוף Chatas Ha'of is eaten by the
כהנים, the עולת העוף Olas Ha'of is burned entirely on the מזבח,
so they're קדשי קדשים, they're of the holiest sanctity. So maybe we
should say that אפילו הכי מן זבח עדיף. Min zvach adif. Nonetheless,
our notion of those which are slaughtered using a knife, that is
the mammalian sacrifices, are of an intrinsically higher level קדושה than foul,
just because. That is the species matters more than what type of
קרבן it is. It's actually very interesting to then think, so then
that's really what we're saying here is that this עוף Of here,
right? We have עוף Of which is חטאת
and
עולה, and actually the חטאת and עולה of the עוף are of
very low קדושה in comparison to many of the other קרבנות. So
they have things which are in common to the חטאת and עולה
up here, but they're actually very different. So we had a whole
פרק almost about עופות, Ofos, but it's very interesting to be thinking
about that. Okay.
It sort of didn't come up in context there that they're of
such a low קדושה. It's sort of fascinating, kind of pushes the
limits there a little bit. Okay, so אמר רבינא. Amar Ravina. So
let's stop here actually because it's a good place to stop for
sort of the next continuation of the סוגיא. Sugya. It goes on
to the next דף. Daf. I'll leave for Rabbi Linder for tomorrow.
Hope everyone has a wonderful day and happy learning.