Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is ק' Kuf 100,
we are in triple digits, we pick up at the bottom of
צ"ט עמוד ב' Tzadi Tet Amud Bet and we are רב מרי
אמר, Rav Mari Amar, the last three words on צ"ט עמוד ב'.
Tzadi Tet Amud Bet. The discussion is whether an אונן onen can
eat קרבנות korbanot at night. The גמרא Gemara inferred from our משנה
mishna that he only can't eat קרבנות korbanot during the day, but
the night following the day of death he can, and the גמרא
Gemara challenged this, that seemed to be a rule only by פסח,
Pesach, not by other קרבנות, korbanot, and the גמרא Gemara said that
one answer of the גמרא Gemara was the difference between יום מיתה
yom misa and יום קבורה, yom kvura, that on the day of
death, the night is forbidden, and on the day our משנה, mishna,
which suggested that you could eat it that night, if you're an
אונן, onen, was the day of burial but not the day of
death, the day of burial was separated from the day of death.
So whether the night is a problem or not depends on whether
it's the day of death or not the day of death. That
was one important distinction that the גמרא Gemara made,
and then the גמרא Gemara went on to discussing the position of
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that he states that אנינות לילה aninus layla
is not דאורייתא, de'oraita, and his proof is that you can eat
the קרבן פסח korban Pesach at night if you were an אונן
onen during the day. And this goes against another teaching of רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon where he said that כשהוא שלם הוא מביא keshu
shalem hu meivi from the word שלמים, shelamim, that somebody who's an
אונן onen cannot have a קרבן korban brought on their behalf because
they are not in a state of שלמות, shlemut, and including in
that he mentioned the פסח. Pesach. So in one place you have
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon saying that you can bring a פסח Pesach
on behalf of an אונן onen in the day and eat it
at night, and another place saying that he cannot because he is
not שלם. shalem. And the גמרא's Gemara answer, first answer was פסח
Pesach doesn't mean פסח, Pesach, it was just thrown in for nothing.
Now we're going to see some other answers. Okay, but we have
those various questions. Number one, does the night follow the day? Is
it the same if it's יום מיתה, yom misa, maybe yes for
יום מיתה, yom misa, maybe no for יום קבורה? yom kvura? And
the number question, question number two, can you bring a קרבן korban
on behalf of an אונן? onen? רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon teaching that
you have to be שלם, shalem, it cannot be brought on behalf
of them, on behalf of an אונן onen altogether, because of this
idea of being שלם, shalem, and how does that work with his
teaching that a קרבן פסח korban Pesach could be brought on behalf
of an אונן? onen? Okay, so let's take a look at where
the גמרא Gemara goes with this. רב מרי אמר, Rav Mari Amar,
רב מרי Rav Mari says, top of ק' עמוד א', Kuf Amud
Alef, לא קשיא, lo kashya, this contradiction of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
about whether you bring a פסח Pesach on behalf of an אונן
onen is not difficult: כאן שמת לו מתו בי"ד וקברו בי"ד כאן
שמת לו מתו בי"ג וקברו בי"ד. kan shemeis lo meiso be-yud daled
ve-kivro be-yud daled, kan shemeis lo meiso be-yud gimmel ve-kivro be-yud daled.
So exactly the distinction that we made earlier with trying to deal
with our משנה, mishna, the difference between when it's יום מיתה yom
misa and יום קבורה yom kvura are the same day, and when
it's just a יום קבורה. yom kvura. And now the גמרא Gemara
spells it out. מת לו מתו בי"ד וקברו בי"ד, meis lo meiso
be-yud daled ve-kivro be-yud daled, if the guy is an אונן onen
and it is the day of death itself, so it's the 14th,
that's the day you're bringing קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, so he's like
an אונן דאורייתא onen de'oraita on that day. In that case, יום
מיתה תופס לילו מדאורייתא, yom misa tofes leilo mi-de'oraita, then because it's
a real אנינות דאורייתא, aninus de'oraita, the night is included, you won't
be able to eat the קרבן פסח korban Pesach at night, and
since you won't be able to eat the קרבן פסח korban Pesach
at night, you don't bring the פסח Pesach on behalf of this
person. And that's where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you do not
bring the פסח Pesach on behalf of the אונן. onen. מת לו
מתו בי"ג וקברו בי"ד, meis lo meiso be-yud gimmel ve-kivro be-yud daled,
however, if the 14th was only the day of קבורה kvura and
not the day of מיתה, misa, so you're only the guy's only
an אונן מדרבנן, onen mi-derabbanan,
in that case, אינו תופס לילו, eino tofes leilo, it does not
grab the following night, אלא מדרבנן. ela mi-derabbanan. So if it's יום
קבורה, yom kvura, then the night following is only rabbinic, so we
would override that to eat the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, so therefore
we let you bring the קרבן פסח korban Pesach on behalf of
this person during the day. Whereas if it is יום מיתה, yom
misa, the night is דאורייתא, de'oraita, you won't be able to eat
the קרבן פסח korban Pesach at night, so we also do not
let you bring the קרבן פסח korban Pesach on your behalf, on
this person's behalf during the day. Now, I should note that here
the גמרא Gemara seems to say the whole question of whether you're
bringing the פסח Pesach on behalf of this person is whether they'll
be able to eat it at night. That elides over the fact
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon in the ברייתא braita quoted at the
bottom of the דף daf yesterday seemed to create a whole other
issue, not about an אונן onen eating קרבנות, korbanot, this idea that
you have to be in a state of שלמות shlemut and you
can't bring a קרבן korban for somebody who's not in a state
of שלמות, shlemut, and that has nothing to do with whether they
can eat it at night or not eat it at night. So
תוספות Tosafos raises that question and it might get reconciled based on
the other answers of this גמרא, Gemara, but right now we are
sort of pretending as if that reason wasn't given, we're totally focusing
on the question of whether you can eat it at night. You
can bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach for somebody and they can
eat it at night, that's when it's only אנינות דרבנן, aninus derabbanan,
it's יום קבורה. yom kvura. You can't bring a קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach on behalf of somebody because they can't eat it at night,
that's when it's אנינות דאורייתא, aninus de'oraisa, יום מיתה, yom misa, and
therefore night is also דאורייתא de'oraisa and he can't eat it at
night, so we won't bring it to him on his account during
the day. Okay. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב מרי, Amar lei Rav
Ashi le-Rav Mari, so רב אשי Rav Ashi said to רב מרי,
Rav Mari, who was the one who just gave this answer, ואלא
הא דתני אמר ליה רבי שמעון תדע שאמרו אונן טובל ואוכל את
פסחו אבל לא בקדשים. vela-hade-tani amar lei Rabbi Shimon, teda she-amru onen
tovel ve-ochel es picho aval lo bekodashim. So רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's
proof to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that אנינות לילה aninus layla is
not דאורייתא de'oraisa is that you can eat your קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach at night. Now, we are just saying that that's talking about
only יום קבורה, yom kvura, that is the case where it's not
דאורייתא de'oraisa and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows you to eat the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at night. Okay, and he said, תדע שאמרו
אונן טובל ואוכל את פסחו אבל לא בקדשים, teda she-amru onen tovel
ve-ochel es picho aval lo bekodashim, but you can't eat קדשים kodashim
because at least אנינות aninus is night would still be דרבנן derabbanan
even for יום קבורה. yom kvura. So the גמרא Gemara says, נימא
ליה, neima lei, why doesn't רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say back to
him, קאמינא לך אנא יום מיתה דאורייתא ואמרת לי את יום קבורה
דרבנן? kamina lach ana yom misa de'oraisa ve-amarta li at yom kvura
derabbanan? So he says, I don't understand, the debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about whether אנינות לילה aninus
layla is דאורייתא de'oraisa is when it's יום מיתה, yom misa, the
day of death. How do we know this? Because it's going to
be based on the story
of נדב ואביהוא's Nadav and Avihu's death, which we're going to get
to tomorrow. And that is when it was the day of death.
So when רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the night of אנינות לילה
aninus layla is דאורייתא, de'oraisa, he's talking about the night following the
day of death. And you now have said that according to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he agrees with that. He's only talking about the
night following יום קבורה. yom kvura. Well, who said רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda disagreed with that? Right, so the focus of their debate is
יום מיתה, yom misa, how can you say that רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon was talking only about יום קבורה yom kvura when he said
that night is not דאורייתא? de'oraisa? So the גמרא Gemara says, קשיא.
kashya. All right, you're right, that's a difficulty. It's funny it just
says קשיא kashya not תיובתא tiyuvta because it really seems that רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda's debate is about יום
מיתה, yom misa, and even there רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying
that the night is not דאורייתא de'oraisa and you could eat the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at night. So if we, if that is
indeed the case, we have to reconcile that with this other statement
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that you can't bring a קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach on behalf, you can't be מקריב makriv it on behalf
of an אונן. onen. So let's see the other answers we're going
to come up with. אביי אמר, Abbaye amar, אביי Abbaye says, לא
קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
כאן שמת קודם חצות כאן שמת לאחר חצות. Kan she-mes kodem chatzos,
kan she-mes le-achar chatzos. It depends, yes, yes, it is יום מיתה,
yom misa, okay,
but whether the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach overrides or not depends on
whether the death occurred, which did you hit the person first? Was
he first an אונן onen and then he had an obligation of
קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? That would be if the person died before
חצות, chatzos, the obligation of קרבן פסח Korban Pesach only hits on
at midday on the fourteenth. So in that case, the אונן onen
status dictates and in that case, you do not bring, that's when
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you do not bring on behalf of
him because he's not שלם, shalem, or at least the אונן onen
status dominates and therefore pushes off the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and
he's not going to eat his and he won't eat his קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach at night even though that's only דרבנן derabbanan for
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about אנינות לילה. aninus layla. Okay, but regardless,
the אנינות aninus took came first so that takes precedence. Whereas if
first it got to be חצות chatzos and then this relative died,
well he already had the obligation of קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, so
in that case, that obligation is not going to get pushed off
by the אנינות, aninus, we'll be able to bring it on his
account and he eats at night again because night will only be
דרבנן. derabbanan. All right, so that's אביי's Abbaye's answer.
Okay. Now, let's
spell it
out. So, כאן קודם חצות. kan kodem chatzos.
קודם חצות דלא איחזי לפסח, kodem chatzos she-lo echazi le-Pesach,
before חצות chatzos when he's not yet fit for the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach and not obligated, חיילי עליה אנינות, chailei alei aninus, the
status of אנינות aninus takes effect on him and then he can't
bring on his
behalf. כשהוא שלם הוא מביא keshe-hu shalem hu meivi and not when
he's an אונן. onen. חיילי עליה אנינות. chailei alei aninus. לאחר חצות
דאיחזי לפסח, achar chatzos de-ichazi le-Pesach, if after חצות chatzos that he
was fit for פסח... Pesach... If the person died after חצות, Chatzos,
so this this person was already fit and obligated in the פסח,
Pesach, לא חלה עליה אנינות, lo chayla alei aninus, the אנינות aninus
does not take hold. Now that doesn't mean the אנינות aninus doesn't
take hold, he still is an אונן, onen, but his relationship to
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach doesn't change and you can still bring
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on his behalf even though he is
an אונן. onen. And at night he can eat it because that's
only אנינות לילה. aninus layla. ומנא תימא, Uminatema, now Abbaye goes on.
Where do I get this from דשאני ליה בין קודם חצות ובין
אחר חצות? de'shani lei bein Kodem Chatzos u'vein achar Chatzos? That we
can make a that whether the obligation hit before or after changes
in terms of competing statuses, you know, regarding the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach and טומאה tumah and so on, or אנינות. aninus. דתניא, Detanya,
we taught in a ברייתא. Baraita. לא יטמא, Lo yitama, this is
by the נזיר, nazir, right? It says, you know, by the נזיר
nazir it says, oh, excuse me, I jumped ahead. We're going to
get to the נזיר nazir in a minute. This is just by
a normal כהן. kohen. It says לאחותו הבתולה הקרובה אליו אשר לא
היתה לאיש לה יטמא. l'achoso habetula hakerova elav asher lo haysa l'ish
lah yitama. That
a normal כהן kohen can become טמא tamei to his immediate relatives
including his sister who is not married to another man, who's not
married to a man. Okay, מצוה, mitzvah, that's an obligation. The כהן
kohen has an obligation to make himself טמא tamei or to involve
himself in the burial of his relatives. לא רצה מטמאין אותו על
כרחו. Lo ratza metamin oto al korcho. And if he doesn't want
to, oh I'm going to protect my כהונה, kehuna, I'm going to
not you know involve myself in the burial of a relative, then
you forcibly obligate him. He's you know to become טמא. tamei. You
force him to involve himself and it even says a little more.
Not just he has an obligation to bury, but לה יטמא, lah
yitama, to actually be מטמא metamei his כהונה kehuna for the sake
of his relatives. That to put sort of like that to it's
almost like a statement that my obligation to my relative is so
great that it is willing and it has to come even at
the cost of the קדושה kedusha of the כהונה. kehuna. So he
has a מצוה mitzvah to do it and if he doesn't want
to you do it against his will. ומעשה ביוסף הכהן Umaaseh b'Yosef
hakohen is the story with a כהן kohen יוסף הכהן Yosef hakohen
שמתה אשתו בערב פסח, she'mesa ishto b'erev Pesach,
his wife died on ערב פסח Erev Pesach and לא רצה להטמא
lo ratza l'hitamei and he didn't want to be טמא tamei because
a) his כהונה kehuna and b) it would mean that he wouldn't
be able to bring the פסח Pesach like we're talking about. Okay,
ונמנו אחיו הכהנים וטמאו אותו על כרחו, v'nimnu echav hakohanim v'tim'u al
korcho, and they took a vote, his fellow כהנים, kohanim, and they
forced him to become טמא, tamei, and then he couldn't bring the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, but he had an obligation to become טמא
tamei to bury his wife. It's actually interesting because the sense that
a wife is a קרוב karov is not explicit in the פסוק.
pasuk. חז"ל Chazal learn it from the פסוק pasuk of לא יטמא
בעל בעמיו להחלו lo yitama baal b'amav l'heichalo which is very hard
to see where they learn it from. According to Rambam it's actually
only דברי סופרים מדרבנן. d'ivrei soferim m'drabbanan. So how they exactly allowed
that to override the קדושה kedusha of כהונה, kehuna, Rambam says well
they made it that nobody else had an obligation to bury other
than he did so it sort of became a מת מצוה. meis
mitzvah. But anyway, okay, so that's a separate conversation about the obligation
of wife and is that דאורייתא d'oraysa or not in terms of
burial for a for a כהן kohen to be מטמא metamei himself.
But anyway there's an obligation to be מטמא metamei yourself for relatives
and even overrides the קדושה kedusha of כהונה kehuna and even overrides
the obligation of bringing the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. That's one ברייתא.
Baraita. ורמינהי, Ureminei, but I'll ask you we got another ברייתא. Baraita.
ולאחותו, V'la'achoso, now this is going about the נזיר nazir and this
is saying that a נזיר nazir like a כהן גדול kohen gadol
cannot become טמא tamei even to his immediate relative. לאביו ולאמו לאחיו
ולאחותו לא יטמא להם במותם. L'aviv u'leimo l'achiv u'le'achoso lo yitama lahem
b'mosam. Okay, that whether father, mother, brother, sister, he cannot become טמא.
tamei. So why do you have to say all those people: father,
brother, mother, sister? You know, once you say father, mother, obviously brother
and sister or whatever. So that's what this ברייתא Baraita does. Why
is it listing all these things that a נזיר nazir all these
relatives a נזיר nazir cannot become טמא tamei for? So ולאחותו מה
תלמוד לומר? V'la'achoso mah talmud lomar? What does it teach? הרי שהלך
לשחוט את פסחו ולמול את בנו. Harei shehalach lishchot et pishcho v'lamol
et bno.
So
let's say you had this נזיר nazir who was also let's say
a כהן kohen and he was going to שחט shecht his קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach and to give a ברית מילה bris milah to
his kid. Why ברית מילה? bris milah? Either because it's necessary for
the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, you
know, that he can't have kids obligated in מילה milah for the
קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, or just telling you this other important מצוה
mitzvah of חיוב כרת. chiyuv kares. He's got all these important things
he's got to do that he's got to stay focused and stay
טהור. tahor. Okay, and heard that שמת לו מת she'meis lo meis
and he heard that a relative died. יכול יטמא? Yachol yitama? Maybe
he should become
טמא? tamei? אמרת Amarta לא יטמא. lo yitama. No, the general לא
יטמא lo yitama that it says by a נזיר. nazir. So certainly
with you know if a נזיר nazir can't become סתם טמא stam
tamei to a relative, how much more so when he's a נזיר,
nazir, כהן גדול, kohen gadol, פסח, Pesach, etc. etc. The reason it
layered all those things on was not to say it was אסור.
assur. Any one of those would have made it אסור. assur. It's
to say that there's a case that overrides all of them. יכול
כשם שאינו מטמא לאחותו כך אינו מטמא למת מצוה? Yachol kesheim she'lo
yitama l'achoso kach eino metamei l'meis mitzvah? Maybe if there was a
מת מצוה, meis mitzvah, a dead body that there was nobody to
bury, maybe... Maybe he would not be מטמא mitame to that for
מת מצווה. meis mitzvah. תלמוד לומר ולאחותו. Talmud lomar uleachoto. That's why
it says the extra word ולאחותו. uleachoto. We'll see in a minute
the ברייתא braitah that from each word לאביו לאמו לאחיו לאחותו leaviv
leimo leachiv leachoto it learns out even if you had another status
and even another status and even another status, not just a נזיר,
nazir, also a כהן, kohen, also a קרבן פסח, korban pesach, also
ברית מילה. bris milah. Even with all those statuses, it's to these
people he can't become טמא: tame: אביו אמו אחיו ואחותו. aviv imo
achiv veachoso. But for a מת מצווה, meis mitzvah, even with all
of those things going on, you're מטמא mitame to a מת מצווה.
meis mitzvah. Okay, so that's a very powerful statement about טומאה tumah
for מת מצווה. meis mitzvah. Okay,
where are we? כך אינו מטמא תלמוד לומר לאחותו. kach eino mitame
Talmud lomar leachoto. לאחותו הוא דאינו מטמא ומטמא הוא למת מצווה. leachoto
hu deino mitama umitama hu lemeis mitzvah. Now, so that's a very
powerful statement about מת מצווה. meis mitzvah. How is this relevant to
us? The way it's relevant is the following: is the גמרא Gemara
is assuming, and תוספות Tosafot discusses why the גמרא's Gemara making this
assumption, that all these additional statuses that are being added are ones
that if it weren't a מת מצווה, meis mitzvah, you would not
be מטמא mitame for them. Okay, so even not only if you're
a נזיר, nazir, but even if you are going to bring a
קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Okay, if you're going to bring a קרבן
פסח korban pesach and somebody's sister dies—they're not a נזיר, nazir, they're
not a כהן גדול kohen gadol or whatever—no, they don't become טמא.
tame. The obligation of the קרבן פסח korban pesach takes precedence. All
right, that's a very powerful statement, not what we would have expected.
It's also, we have to admit, and תוספות Tosafot is bothered with
this, not פשט pshat in this ברייתא braitah because, you know, not
everything here had the power to take precedence over טומאה. tumah. It
was layering a lot of things on top of one another. Giving
a ברית מילה bris milah to your kid does not take precedence
over an obligation
of an immediate relative dies. But okay, we're just going to bracket
that, for whatever reason in the גמרא Gemara assumes that the fact
that it mentioned פסח Pesach means that if it were—if that פסח
Pesach by itself would be a reason not to become טמא tame
if it were not a מת מצווה, meis mitzvah, if it was
just an immediate relative. So now we have a contradiction: by יוסף
Yosef the כהן, kohen, it says it was ערב פסח erev Pesach
and they forced him to become טמא. tame. Here it says that
the way the גמרא's Gemara reading it, that if it's ערב פסח,
erev Pesach, you don't become טמא, tame, you bring your קרבן פסח.
korban pesach. So which one is it? How do you reconcile this?
So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אלא לאו, ela lav, so this is אביי's Abaye proof. How do
you deal with this contradiction? אלא לאו שמע מינה כאן קודם חצות
כאן אחר חצות. ela lav shma mina kan kodem chatzos kan achar
chatzos. It must be this is the difference: when they were מטמא
mitame יוסף, Yosef, that was when it was ערב פסח erev Pesach
in the morning, and there his obligation to become טמא tame to
bury his sister, that took precedence. Okay, and then become טמא. tame.
For the case of this דרשה drasha of ולאחותו, uleachoto, it was
when it was post-חצות, chatzos, he became obligated in the פסח, Pesach,
and then a relative died, and in that case we would say:
don't become טמא, tame, focus on your obligation of the קרבן פסח.
korban pesach. So you see which of those two competing things—your חיוב
chiyuv to become טמא tame and to bury your relative or your
חיוב chiyuv to bring the קרבן פסח—which korban pesach one takes precedence
is dependent on which one hit you first. And if that's true
here, then it could also be true about whether your אונן onen
status prevents you from bringing the קרבן פסח, korban pesach, which status,
similar to which obligation, which status came on you first? Okay, that's
אביי's Abaye proof. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, ממאי? mimai?
Who tells you that's the way to reconcile this issue of the
קרבן פסח? korban pesach? דילמא לעולם אימא לך dilma leolam eima lach
אידי ואידי אחר חצות. aidi veaidi achar chatzos. That both of them
are talking about after חצות. chatzos. You know, you are already obligated
in the פסח. Pesach. And nevertheless, the story with
יוסף Yosef the כהן, kohen, that they were מטמא mitame him even
though the פסח Pesach obligation came first, is because the טומאה tumah
obligation of burying your sister, your relative overrides. All right, so then
why would it not override in this ברייתא braitah of ולאחותו? uleachoto?
So the גמרא Gemara says, אידי ואידי אחר חצות והא רבי ישמעאל
והא רבי עקיבא.
aidi veaidi achar chatzos veha
Rabbi Yishmael veha Rabbi Akiva. Maybe it's a debate—the debate of רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל—whether Rabbi Yishmael how much is there
a real obligation to become טמא tame to a relative? What's this
debate? דתניא, detanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braitah, לה יטמא. la
yitama. This is again by a normal כהן. kohen. He should become
טמא tame to a sister: רשות, reshus, that's you have the permission,
דברי רבי ישמעאל, divrei Rabbi Yishmael, what רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says.
But you don't have an obligation to become טמא tame to your
sister, to your relative when they die. רבי עקיבא אומר חובה, Rabbi
Akiva omer chova, it's an obligation. So, it was clear in the
first ברייתא braitah about יוסף Yosef that they forced him and they
made him טמא tame that it was saying it's an obligation, and
that would override even if you first became obligated in the פסח,
Pesach, whereas this ברייתא braitah about the guy going to bring his
פסח Pesach and to give his son ברית מילה bris milah etc.,
etc., that it says that you would not interrupt the קרבן פסח
korban pesach for טומאה, tumah, okay, that is רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
that you do not have an obligation. you're allowed to but you
don't have an obligation. Okay so maybe that's the way to reconcile
it? So the גמרא Gemara says לא סלקא דעתך, lo salka daiteich,
no, that doesn't make sense. The רישא reisha דהיא dehi רבי עקיבא
קתני לה, Rabbi Akiva kitani lah, because actually that very ברייתא braisa
of ולאחותו v'lachoso and the guy going to bring his קרבן פסח
korban pesach and give ברית מילה bris milah to a son, the
beginning of that ברייתא braisa is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, explicitly says
there's an obligation to become טמא tamei to a relative. דתניא, Detanya,
okay now we're going to quote the whole ברייתא. braisa. רבי עקיבא
אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says: נפש אתא סוסי,
nefesh etsasosei, על נפש מת לא יבוא, al nefesh meis lo yavo,
the נזיר nazir cannot come to contact with a dead body. אלו
הקרובים, elu hakerovim, that means your relatives. מת, meis, נפש מת, nefesh
meis, dead, אלו הרחוקים, elu harechokim, those are even people that are
not your relatives. So already by על נפש מת לא יבוא, al
nefesh meis lo yavo, that double language says already that a נזיר
nazir can't become טמא tamei to a relative.
לאביו, l'aviv, okay, so now why does it have to say your
father, you've already said you don't become טמא? tamei? So אינו מטמא
אבל מטמא הוא למת מצוה. eino mitamei, aval mitamei hu l'meis mitzvah.
So the extra word לאביו l'aviv tells us the override of מת
מצוה, meis mitzvah, for your father not, מת מצוה meis mitzvah yes.
This whole ברייתא braisa is telling you how much you can do
for a מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. לאמו, l'imo, now so why does
it then also add לאמו? l'imo? And now we're going to start
layering it. היה כהן והוא נזיר, haya kohein v'hu nazir, let's say
he was both a כהן kohein and a נזיר, nazir, an extra
reason not to become טמא tamei because he's also a כהן. kohein.
Okay, לאמו הוא דאינו מטמא אבל מטמא הוא למת מצוה. l'imo hu
deino mitamei, aval mitamei hu l'meis mitzvah. He can't become טמא tamei
for his mother, now a normal כהן kohein by the way does
מטמא mitamei for his mother, the only real thing stopping him right
here is a נזיר. nazir. But okay, for his mother he can't
be מטמא, mitamei, but even with all these layers he can be
מטמא mitamei for a מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. לאחיו, l'achiv, why does
it then after mother and father and mother add brother? To add
even another layer. שאם היה כהן גדול והוא נזיר, she'im haya kohein
gadol v'hu nazir, let's say he was a כהן גדול kohein gadol
and a נזיר. nazir. So כהן גדול kohein gadol by itself would
say you do not become טמא tamei to a relative, okay, and
נזיר nazir by itself you're not טמא tamei to a relative. Nevertheless,
even with those two combined, it's only לאחיו הוא דאינו מטמא אבל
מטמא הוא למת מצוה. l'achiv hu deino mitamei, aval mitamei hu l'meis
mitzvah. Only not for the brother but yes for מת מצוה. meis
mitzvah. So even with two statuses of the highest status of protecting
their קדושה, kedusha, כהן גדול kohein gadol and a נזיר, nazir, it
would be overridden for a מת מצוה. meis mitzvah. ולאחותו
מה תלמוד לומר?
v'lachoso mah
talmud lomar? So now why do we need that last word of
ולאחותו v'lachoso and this is the part we quoted before.
תלמוד לומר הרי שהלך לשחוט את פסחו ולמול את בנו
ושמע שמת לו מת יכול יטמא? אמרת לא יטמא. talmud lomar, harei
shehalach lishchot es pesacho v'lamol es beno v'shamah shemeis lo meis, yachol
yitamei? amarta, lo yitamei. No, you do not. And again, the way
the גמרא's Gemara reading this, is the פסח pesach itself you would
not, even if you're not כהן גדול kohein gadol and a נזיר,
nazir, you would not become
טמא. tamei. יכול כשם שאינו מטמא לאחותו כך אינו מטמא למת מצוה?
תלמוד לומר ולאחותו, לאחותו הוא דלא יטמא אבל מטמא הוא למת מצוה.
yachol k'sheim she'eino mitamei l'achoso kach eino mitamei l'meis mitzvah? talmud lomar,
v'lachoso, l'achoso hu delo yitamei, aval mitamei hu l'meis mitzvah. So again,
all these extra words are telling you even with all this layering,
it's only to a relative you can't be טמא, tamei, but even
somebody with all these layers is מטמא mitamei for a מת מצוה.
meis mitzvah. Anyway, what do you see? You see that the ברייתא
braisa is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, that there's an obligation to be
טמא tamei to a relative. So we now have one ברייתא braisa
which is רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, obligation to be טמא tamei and
it overrides פסח, pesach, and there's another ברייתא, braisa, obligation to be
טמא tamei does not override פסח, pesach, you keep to the קרבן
פסח. korban pesach. How do you reconcile it? So אביי Abaye says,
must be before חצות chatzos and after חצות. chatzos. And if that's
true about this טומאה, tumah, it would also be true about the
אנינות aninus status. Okay, top of קמ"ב. kuf mem bais. So that's
one nice answer to reconcile the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about whether
you bring a... for an אונן onein a קרבן... korban... whether you
bring a קרבן פסח korban pesach or not, it matters before חצות
chatzos or after חצות. chatzos. רבה אמר, Rava amar, now רבה Rava
is going to shift gears a little bit. Top of
קמ"ב. kuf mem bais. אידי ואידי idi v'idi אחר חצות. achar chatzos.
No no, we're talking after חצות. chatzos.
Okay, and normally even after חצות chatzos if the guy became an
אונן, onein, that overrides קרבן פסח, korban pesach, even if it's after
חצות, chatzos, and you would not bring it for him. That is
the statement of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that only when he is
שלים shaleim you bring, once he's an אונן onein you do not
bring it, even if he became an אונן onein after חצות. chatzos.
So what is רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon case where he says you
can eat the קרבן פסח korban pesach at night? ולא קשיא. כאן
קודם ששחטו וזרקו עליו, כאן לאחר ששחטו וזרקו עליו. v'lo kashya. kan
kodem sheshachtu v'zarku alav, kan l'achar sheshachtu v'zarku alav.
It's actually a beautiful reconciliation because it focuses on the two different
things those ברייתות braisas were talking about. When the question is, do
I שחט shecht the קרבן פסח korban pesach and זורק zoreik the
דם dam for an אונן? onein? The answer is no. He's not
שלים. shaleim. That's where רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you do not
bring a קרבן korban on behalf of an אונן. onein. That was
the ברייתא, braisa, and even a פסח pesach you don't bring on
his behalf. When Wait, when did רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say you
eat a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach that night? That's if nobody asked
and they went ahead and brought it already, they שחט shechted it
and they were זורק zoreik the דם. dam. Okay? So then the
question is not can you bring it on his behalf, it already
was brought and presumably it's כשר kosher even though you're not supposed
to presumably it's כשר. kosher. And then the only question is can
you eat it? And the answer is yes, you can eat it
at night. So it's actually quite beautiful. One place רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says don't bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach on behalf of
an אונן onen and you don't. You do not שחט shecht and
זורק zoreik the דם. dam. And in another place he says, oh,
but if it was brought, then he can eat it that night
because לילה layla is only דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Okay, very elegant answer. So
אמר ליה רב אדא בר מתנה לרבא, amar lei Rav Adda bar
Matna l'Rava, so רב אדא בר מתנה Rav Adda bar Matna said
to רבא, Rava, אך ששחטו וזרקו את הדם מה דהוה הוה. ach
sheshachtu v'zarku et hadam, mah d'hava hava. He says I don't get
it. If you already sprinkled the blood and שחט shechted it, so
why do you have to permit him to eat? This is the
way רש"י Rashi explains the question, to eat the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach at night. What was, was. You weren't supposed to, you did
it, fine. You're יוצא yotzei the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, you know,
but don't keep on continuing in this wrong path. Get back to
the אנינות, aninus, don't eat it at night. Okay? So why would
you allow him to eat it at night once he already brought
it and maybe even once he already brought it and he shouldn't
have brought it? Okay, so that's the question. So
אמר ליה רבינא, amar lei Ravina, so רבינא Ravina said to him,
אכילת פסחים מעכב. achilat pesachim m'akeiv. No, eating the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach is
מעכב. m'akeiv. You're not יוצא קרבן פסח yotzei Korban Pesach by just
sprinkling the blood, you have to actually
eat from it, מדרבה בר רב הונא, m'drabba bar Rav Huna, from
the teaching of רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna which
we'll see in a minute. And אמר ליה, amar lei, so רבא
Rava said back to רב אדא בר מתנה Rav Adda bar Matna
that challenged him, ציית מה דקאמר לך רבך. tzayis mah d'kamar lach
rabach. Pay attention to what your רבי רב הונא Rebbe Rav Huna
is saying in defending my position, that that is the key difference
that you have to eat a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So this
is very interesting about a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. In
all קרבנות korbanot the focus is on the זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam.
You know, the eating and the burning of the entrails or whatever,
that's all seen as secondary. A קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is fundamentally
brought because there's a מצוה mitzvah of eating the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach that night. And that is one good way of seeing this
is that, you know, the הלכה halacha is טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah
hutra b'tzibur when you bring a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibur you bring
it even if everybody is טמא, tamei, but you don't eat it.
It only allows it to be brought. The one exception to that
is a קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Since a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
is brought for the sake of being eaten, when you say טומאה
הותרה בציבור tumah hutra b'tzibur by the פסח, Pesach, you would also
allow for the eating of the פסח. Pesach. Okay, and now within
that, so everybody agrees the eating of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
is the focus. Within that there's a debate of if you didn't
do the eating, בדיעבד b'dieved could you still be יוצא yotzei just
from the fact it was brought? Alright, so that's the question. And
here we're saying no, you would not be יוצא, yotzei, you would
need to do the eating. Now תוספות Tosfos says maybe it's לאו
דוקא, lav davka, it just means the eating is real important, but
one way or another we'll take the גמרא Gemara כפשוטה, k'pshuta, you
have to do it to be יוצא. yotzei. So if you didn't
bring the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach for this אונן, onen, don't bring
it, he's an אונן. onen. If you sprinkled the blood, then we're
going to let him eat it at night even though there's אנינות
דרבנן aninus d'rabbanan because the eating now is necessary for the קיום
המצוה kiyum hamitzvah and it was already brought on his behalf. Okay,
so now the only issue is אכילת לילה achilas layla and that's
only דרבנן, d'rabbanan, that we will allow. Okay, so now we have
a very elegant answer. Don't bring something on behalf of an אונן.
onen. If it was brought, can you eat it at night? At
least for a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach we will say
yes because אנינות לילה aninus layla is דרבנן d'rabbanan and because eating
is מעכב m'akeiv by a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, so then we
will let you do it. Okay, מאי דרבה בר רב הונא? mah
d'Rabba bar Rav Huna? Where did רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar
Rav Huna make this point that eating a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
is מעכב? m'akeiv? דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא: braita: יום שמועה כיום קבורה למצות שבעה ושלושים. Yom shmua
k'yom kvura l'mitzvot shiva u'shloshim. The day if somebody did not was
not did not hear that their relative died and they heard about
it, you know, like two weeks later, as long as it's still
within the שלושים, shloshim, that day of hearing that the relative died
is like the day of that's when שבעה shiva begins for that
person. It's like the day of קבורה, kvura, which is what it
says: יום שמועה כיום קבורה. Yom shmua k'yom kvura. He's not an
אונן, onen, the person's already buried, okay, but it's like the day
of burial, which means now the obligation of שבעה shiva and שלושים
shloshim begin today when this person heard that the relative died.
ולאכילת פסחים כיום ליקוט עצמות. v'leachilat pesachim k'yom likut atzamot. But when
it comes to can you eat a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach the
night following יום שמועה, yom shmua, the answer is if it was
the day of burial, the answer would be no. Before we were
saying yes, if it was day of burial and not the day
of death, but whatever, different opinions. So the implicit point of this
ברייתא braita is if it was the day of burial, can you
eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at night? The answer would be
no. But since this is not actually the day of burial, it's
just the day of hearing of the death, then it is of
a lighter weight, and it's like the day of ליקוט עצמות. Likut
Atzamot. ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamot they would do is after the body
decomposed, they would disinter it, take the bones, and put the bones
in a little niche in a, you know, in a cave.
And so, so and that day because, you know, it would be
like a reburial, has like a secondary יום קבורה Yom Kvura status.
Okay, so what it is saying is the day of hearing is
like יום קבורה Yom Kvura that that's when שבעה Shiva and שלושים
Shloshim begins, but it's lighter than יום קבורה, Yom Kvura, it's more
like, it's like the lighter status of the day of gathering of
the bones of ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamot that it allows you to
eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach at night. All right, so the
basic point here is you can't eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
the night of יום קבורה, Yom Kvura, you can eat it the
night of יום שמועה Yom Shmuah and יום ליקוט עצמות. Yom Likut
Atzamot. That's the beginning of the
ברייתא. Braita. ליקוט עצמות מכלל Likut Atzamot miklal דיום קבורה, de'Yom Kvura,
now the גמרא Gemara spells it out, first wide line, from this
we can see that יום קבורה Yom Kvura אפילו ערב נמי לא
אכיל, afillu erev nami lo achil, you can't eat the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach the night of יום קבורה Yom Kvura even if it
isn't יום מיתה. Yom Mita. Okay, different than we said before, but
that's a debate.
והדר תני, Ve'hadar tani, and then the ברייתא Braita goes on and
says, אחד זה ואחד זה טובל ואוכל בקדשים לערב. Echad ze ve'echad
ze tovel ve'ochel bekodashim la'erev. And then it says, but whether this
or that, whether you're talking about יום קבורה Yom Kvura or יום
ליקוט עצמות, Yom Likut Atzamot, okay, you can go ahead and go
to the מקווה mikvah and that night you can eat קדשים. kodashim.
So that's crazy, קדשים kodashim are even more are even less overriding
than קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So
okay, so this ברייתא, Braita, the first half of it suggests that
יום קבורה Yom Kvura you can't even eat a קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach at night, and the second half sounds like יום קבורה Yom
Kvura and יום שמועה, Yom Shmuah, excuse me, יום קבורה Yom Kvura
and ליקוט עצמות, Likut Atzamot, you can eat even general קרבנות korbanot
at night. So what's the story?
So אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, תנאי היא. tannai hi. So
רב חסדא Rav Chisda said it's a debate of תנאים, tannaim, this
ברייתא Braita is really two different תנאים tannaim that were stuck together.
Okay, and this what is it? תנאי היא. Tannai hi.
So that's answer number one, two different תנאים tannaim that were stuck
together, one thinks the night of יום קבורה Yom Kvura you can
eat קרבנות korbanot in general and the other says no, you can't
even eat קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. רבה בר רב הונא, Rabbah bar
Rav Huna, now רבה בר רב הונא, Rabbah bar Rav Huna, that
was the one that we were interested in, okay, רבה בר רב
הונא אמר לא קשיא כאן ששמע שמועה על מתו סמוך לשקיעת החמה
וכן שלקטו לו עצמות סמוך לשקיעת החמה. Rabbah bar Rav Huna amar
lo kashya kan sheshama shmuah al meto samuch leshkiat hachamma vechen sheliktu
lo atzamot samuch leshkiat hachamma.
החמה, Hachamma, wait hold on, let me do that again. אמר לא
קשיא כאן ששמע שמועה על מתו סמוך לשקיעת החמה וכן Amar lo
kashya kan sheshama shmuah al meto samuch leshkiat hachamma vechen excuse me
שלקטו לו עצמות סמוך לשקיעת החמה. sheliktu lo atzamot samuch leshkiat hachamma.
So the part, part number one is that the burial, the פסח
Pesach is the fourteenth, okay? So the first case is that the
שמועה shmuah of the dead or the ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamot happened
on the fourteenth itself. וכן שמת לו מת וקברו סמוך לשקיעת החמה,
Vechen shemet lo met u'kvaro samuch leshkiat hachamma, right there are three
things looked at here. יום קבורה, Yom Kvura, ליקוט עצמות, Likut Atzamot,
and the question is יום שמועה Yom Shmuah whether you categorize it
as יום קבורה Yom Kvura or as ליקוט עצמות. Likut Atzamot. But
the ברייתא Braita seems to say, so here's the difference he says,
and the סמוך לשקיעת החמה samuch leshkiat hachamma is not really relevant.
What's relevant is while it was still the day. So the first
case where we don't allow יום קבורה Yom Kvura at night, that's
when the יום קבורה Yom Kvura occurred on the fourteenth itself. Wait,
excuse me, I got that wrong. Let's say that the other way.
Where it says the end of the ברייתא, Braita, that where it
says that you can eat the קדשים kodashim at night, that is
when it's a normal case. The burial or the יום שמועה Yom
Shmuah or the ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamot happened on the fourteenth and
then you can go ahead and do the burial and then you
can eat קדשים kodashim that night because it's the night after, and
the night after, you know, is does not follow the day of
אנינות aninnut according to this. So that's the second part of the
ברייתא Braita that says that you can eat קדשים kodashim at night
when it happened on
the fourteenth. Okay, וכאן לאחר שקיעת החמה, Vekan le'acher shkiat hachamma,
and the case where it says that you cannot eat it is
when actually the burial or the ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamot or the
יום שמועה Yom Shmuah happened actually when it was already night. Okay,
so when it was already night, now you're a real אונן, onen,
and now you're a real אונן, onen, so can you eat the
קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? Well, let's discuss. If it was יום קבורה,
Yom Kvura, right, was on the night of the fourteenth, then no,
that's even if it's only דרבנן, de'rabbanan, but that's the day of
the אנינות aninnut itself, the burial was already after it was night,
so you can't eat פסח, Pesach, sorry, okay, and similarly but if
it's ליקוט עצמות, Likut Atzamos, then we do let you eat the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. קרבן פסח Korban Pesach overrides, okay, because it's
only ליקוט עצמות, Likut Atzamos, and we'll also be lenient by שמועה,
Shemuah, and קרבן פסח Korban Pesach will also override, and we will
let you eat because it's only because because it is a דרבנן,
DeRabbanan, it's not יום מיתה, Yom Misah, and it's only יום שמועה,
Yom Shemuah, it's not even יום קבורה, Yom Kevurah, so we'll let
you eat the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Okay, so let's just say
that again. So when the ברייתא Braitah says טובל ואוכל קדשים בערב
Tovel VeOchel Kodashim BaErev for an אונן, Onen, that's a classic case.
All these things happened: קבורה, Kevurah, שמועה, Shemuah, ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamos
happened on the 14th night. Go, you know, go for it. It's
night does not follow the day. Have all קרבנות. Korbanos. When there
are issues of eating your קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, that's when these
things happened when it was already the night of the 14th. So
in that case, יום שמועה Yom Shemuah would be, excuse me, יום
קבורה, Yom Kevurah, even though יום קבורה Yom Kevurah by itself is
only דרבנן, DeRabbanan, but יום קבורה Yom Kevurah would override פסח, Pesach,
and יום שמועה Yom Shemuah and ליקוט עצמות, Likut Atzamos, you know,
would not, פסח Pesach would override them, okay, and you would eat
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach if it was just יום שמועה Yom
Shemuah and יום ליקוט עצמות. Yom Likut Atzamos. Alright, that's a resolution.
It's actually, you know, can reads very can read very well because
because one it speaks about doing it לערב LaErev and the other
might be referring to when it actually happened at the time itself.
So how is this relevant to us? So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says לאחר שיצתה חמה LeAkhar SheItsta Khama מאי
דהוה הוה. Mai DeHava Hava. I don't get it, says
the גמרא. Gemara. Why would if the ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamos or
the יום שמועה Yom Shemuah happened and it was already the night
of the 14th and you already brought the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
in the day of the 14th, so why would we let, you
know, eating the פסח Pesach override your
אנינות Aninus status, even if it's only אנינות דרבנן, Aninus DeRabbanan, even
if it's only ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamos or יום שמועה? Yom Shemuah?
Why would we let it override? You already brought the קרבן Korban
on the 14th and you were יוצא Yotsei the קרבן. Korban. So
why should we be lenient here and let it override? אלא שמע
מינה Ela Shema Mina אכילת פסחים מעכבת. Akhilas Pesakhim Me'akvas. So you
see that אכילת פסחים Akhilas Pesakhim are מעכב, Me'akeiv, are necessary and
at least are weighty enough to allow us to override אנינות. Aninus.
Okay, so that was a little complicated. But the ברייתא Braitah was
hard to read and one reconciliation
was that when יום קבורה Yom Kevurah is on the night of
the 14th,
then we do not override for eating the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
but we do override for שמועה Shemuah and ליקוט עצמות, Likut Atzamos,
and that shows you how important אכילת פסחים Akhilas Pesakhim is that
it overrides אכילה מעכבת, Akhila Me'akva, overrides that sort of lighter אנינות
Aninus status. And once that's true, we could say the same about
reconciling רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that when the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
was already brought for you in the day when you're an אונן,
Onen, we're going to let you eat the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
at night. It will override the status of אנינות לילה. Aninus Layla.
Okay, so one more answer to this ברייתא. Braitah. So the גמרא
Gemara says רב אשי אמר Rav Ashi Amar מאי אחד זה ואחד
זה Mai Echad Zeh VeEchad Zeh הכי קאמר Hachi KaAmar אחד יום
שמועה ואחד יום ליקוט Echad Yom Shemuah VeEchad Yom Likut טובל ואוכל
בקדשים בערב. Tovel VeOchel BeKodashim BaErev. Okay, so we were bothered because
the end of the ברייתא Braitah sounded like whether it's שמועה, Shemuah,
whether it's קבורה Kevurah or ליקוט, Likut, you can eat קדשים Kodshim
at night, even though the first part of the ברייתא Braitah sounded
like the night of יום קבורה Yom Kevurah you cannot even eat
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. רב אשי Rav Ashi says, no, no, no,
you misunderstood. When it says אחד זה ואחד זה, Echad Zeh VeEchad
Zeh, it wasn't saying whether קבורה Kevurah or ליקוט עצמות Likut Atzamos
you can eat קדשים Kodshim at night. No, קבורה Kevurah you can't
eat even פסח Pesach at night. It was saying whether it's יום
שמועה Yom Shemuah or יום ליקוט עצמות Yom Likut Atzamos you can
eat קדשים Kodshim at night. So the גמרא, Gemara, that seems like
a very reasonable answer. We're saying that שמועה Shemuah is like ליקוט
עצמות Likut Atzamos for the פסח. Pesach. So אחד זה ואחד זה
Echad Zeh VeEchad Zeh means whether שמועה Shemuah or ליקוט עצמות Likut
Atzamos you can eat קדשים Kodshim at night. So the גמרא Gemara
doesn't like it. והא דרב אשי בדידותא היא. V'ha D'Rav Ashi Bidusi
Hi. That that רב אשי Rav Ashi said is like rejected or
foolish maybe. מכדי, Mikdi, let's take a look. אלא קאי, Ala Kai,
we were just talking about how יום שמועה Yom Shemuah was like
יום ליקוט עצמות Yom Likut Atzamos for פסח. Pesach. If you wanted
to say that those two things that we have already equated are
also the same for eating קדשים Kodshim at night, זה וזה מיבעי
ליה. Zeh VeZeh MiBaya Lei. It should have said and both of
them you can eat קדשים Kodshim at night. When it says אחד
זה ואחד זה, Echad Zeh VeEchad Zeh, it's being totally inclusive of
all the cases we mentioned. Whether all the way back to קבורה
Kevurah or whether we're talking about שמועה Shemuah or ליקוט עצמות, Likut
Atzamos, regardless, all those things you can go ahead and eat קדשים
Kodshim at night. And that's a problem. That's why we had to
reconcile it because you had just said that you can't eat פסח
Pesach the night of יום קבורה. Yom Kevurah. אלא שמע מינה בדידותא
היא. Ela Shema Mina Biduta Hi. Okay, so therefore what have we
said? This is how to reconcile this complicated ברייתא Braitah about שמועה
Shemuah and קבורה Kevurah and ליקוט עצמות. Likut Atzamos. The reconciliation was
that we will allow the lighter sort of statuses of אונן. Onen.
to be overridden at night even though the קרבן Korban was already
brought earlier in the day and that shows you אכילת פסחים Achilas
Pesachim is מעכבא, Meakeva, that eating the פסח Pesach can override a
lighter אנינות Oninus status, and that allows us also to explain רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Even though the קרבן Korban was brought for the
אונן Onain in the day, he can eat it at night, אנינות
לילה Oninus Layla is דרבנן, DeRabbanan, and אכילת פסחים Achilas Pesachim can
override that status. Okay, I hope you got all that. That was
good.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומאי תנאי, Umai Tanai, what
are the debates of תנאים Tannaim because we said before that it
was a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Remember according to the way רב
חסדא Rav Chisda reconciled the ברייתא Braisa about can you eat the
פסח Pesach the night of יום קבורה Yom Kevura was to say
that there's a debate of תנאים Tannaim about whether the night follows
the day of יום קבורה Yom Kevura or not for eating קדשים.
Kodshim. So where is this debate of תנאים? Tannaim? דתניא, DeTanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, עד מתי מתאונן עליו, Ad Masai Miasonnin
Alav, until how long are
you מתאונן Misonain for a relative who died?
כל היום, Kol Hayom, the whole day you're in a status of
an אונן. Onain. רבי אומר, כל זמן שלא נקבר, Rebbi omer kol
zman shelo nikvar, no, only until the person has not been buried.
So it sounds like רבי Rebbi would say that the אנינות Aninus
status ends even on the day of מיתה Misa once burial takes
place. So the גמרא Gemara says במאי עסקינן, Bimay Iskinan, what are
we talking about? אילימא ביום מיתה, Ilima Beyom Misa, if it's the
day of
מיתה, Misa, מי איכא דלית ליה דיום מיתה תפיס לילה מדרבנן, Mi
Ika Delis Lei DeYom Misa Itofis Leila DeRabbanan, first of all, how
could anybody say that it doesn't extend into the night? Everybody agrees
that אנינות Aninus extends into the night at least rabbinically, and the
first opinion just said just the day itself.
So everybody though should say night. ותו, VeTu, רבי אומר, כל זמן
שלא נקבר, Rebbi omer kol zman shelo nikvar. and also it's even
harder, רבי Rebbi says until he hasn't been buried, הכי קברו אישתרי
ליה, HaKivro Ishtari Lei, it sounds like if he was buried on
the day of מיתה Misa now the person is no longer an
אונן. Onain. ומי איכא דלית ליה ואחריתה כיום מר, Umi Ika Delis
Lei VeAchriso KeYom Mar, nobody says that the אונן Onain does not
apply the whole first day. The פסוק Pasuk says that what follows
death is like the bitterness of like a bitter day, the whole
day is bitter. So everybody holds that the first day, full day
you're an אונן Onain and everybody holds the night is at least
rabbinic. So how do you fit in this debate here between רבי
Rabbi and the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, how do you make sense
of it? אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshes, איום קבורה קאי, A
Yom Kevura Kai, they're not talking about the day of מיתה. Misa.
They're talking about the day of קבורה, Kevura, which is not the
day of מיתה. Misa. So in that case, the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma would say it's the day but not the night, and רבי
Rebbi would say the אונן Onain status even ends at the קבורה
Kevura itself. So the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב יוסף, Maskif
Lei Rav Yosef, which is by the way how we פוסק, Pasken,
right, when somebody I mean אונן Onain here by the way we're
not talking I should pause about אונן Onain like for our practical
purpose, the way אונן Onain plays out for us, it's about making
certain things forbidden, you know, certain sort of acts of like יין
Yayin or
בשר, Basar, other question about marital sex, other things and also not
doing מצוות. Mitzvos. Okay, that's how and for that definitely ends even
if it's the day of מיתה Misa once the קבורה Kevura takes
place. That's not what we're talking about here. Here we're talking about
אונן Onain as this status of bitterness which means you can't eat
קדשים. Kodshim. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says so now we're reading
it that when the day of קבורה Kevura is not the day
of מיתה, Misa, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says the whole day
and not the night, and רבי Rebbi says it ends at the
קבורה. Kevura.
So, מתקיף
לה רב יוסף, Maskif Lei Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef
challenged it, אלא הא דתניא, Ela Ha DeTanya, השומע על מתו כמלקט
עצמות, HaShomea Al Meso KeMelakket Atzamos, that when somebody hears about a
death, you know, within the first thirty days, it's like the day
of gathering of the bones, we said this, טובל ואוכל בקדשים לערב,
Tovel VeOchel BeKodshim LaErev, and you can eat קרבנות Korbanos that night,
right, that was that variance of the ברייתא Braisa we said before,
okay, that יום שמועה Yom Shemua and ליקוט עצמות Likkut Atzamos you
can eat קרבנות Korbanos at night. מכלל, MiKlal, since it only said
that for the day of hearing and ליקוט עצמות, Likkut Atzamos, but
not the day of קבורה Kevura itself, you can infer דיום קבורה
אפילו לערב נמי לא אכיל, DeYom Kevura Afilu LaErev Nami Lo Achil,
that on the day of קבורה, Kevura, even if it's not the
day of מיתה, Misa, you can't eat at night. Okay, so from
the previous ברייתא, Braisa, right, which limited it to the day of
hearing and ליקוט עצמות, Likkut Atzamos, the implication was that the day
of קבורה Kevura you can not eat קדשים Kodshim at night. Here
we're saying that רבי Rebbi and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma are
debating the status of the day of קבורה, Kevura, and everybody allows
at night. And we don't want it to be a three-way debate.
So הא מני, HaManni, so who's that going to be that position
that's going to say it's permissible at excuse me, it's forbidden at
night if according to you both רבי Rebbi and the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma say it's permissible at night. אלא תריץ הכי, Ela Teritz
Hachi, so here's how you have to read it. עד מתי מתאונן
עליו, Ad Masai Miasonnin Alav, okay, it is the day of קבורה
Kevura not the day of מיתה. Misa. How long does אנינות Aninus
last? כל אותו היום ולילו, Kol Oso HaYom VeLeilo, the entire day
and its night. A little missing... from the ברייתא. Braisa. We're going
to stick into the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and its night. So
now the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says יום קבורה, Yom Kvurah, that's
not the day of death, includes the night for the prohibition of
קדשים. Kodshim. רבי אומר Rebbi Omer, כל זמן שלא נקבר, Kol Zeman
Shelo Nikbar, but that's only until it's been buried, אבל נקבר aval
nikvar once he's been buried בלא לילה belo layla it would not
include the night. Okay, so now it really does not sound that
way in the ברייתא, Braisa, maybe it is a three-way debate, but
the גמרא Gemara is interpreting that ברייתא Braisa as that it is
a debate whether יום קבורה Yom Kvurah includes the night for the
איסור issur of קדשים. Kodshim. All right. All right, so where are
we? We reconciled רבי שמעון, Rebbi Shimon, wait remember רבי שמעון Rebbi
Shimon about whether you can eat the פסח Pesach at night or
not and to say he forbids bringing קרבן korban on behalf of
the אונן, onen, he's not שלם, shalem, but the פסח Pesach can
be eaten at night, that overrides אנינות לילה aninus layla which is
דרבנן derabbanan for the sake of פסח. Pesach. Okay, and because the
אכילת פסחים מעכבא. achilas pesachim me'akva. In terms of general קדשים, Kodshim,
that's where everybody says the night follows the day, the night is
off-limits, at least maybe
דאורייתא, de'oraisa, at least דרבנן. derabbanan.
And then whether, however, we would say that by the יום קבורה
Yom Kvurah does the night follow the day, that we now said
for קדשים Kodshim in general, that we now said is a debate,
is a מחלוקת תנאים. machlokes tanna'im. Okay, אמרו קמיה דרב ירמיה, Amru
kamei d'Rav Yirmiyah, they said this to רב ירמיה. Rav Yirmiyah. So
אמר amar and he said גברא רבה כרב יוסף לימא הכי, Gavra
raba k'Rav Yosef leima hachi, would a great personage like
רב יוסף Rav Yosef say this, say this is the explanation of
the debate of רבי Rebbi and the תנא קמא? Tanna Kamma? So
לימא דרבי לקולא, leima d'Rebbi lekula, so that means that רבי Rebbi
is being lenient? רבי Rebbi is saying it doesn't extend into the
night, once you buried him it ends there. That's how we said
the debate. Does יום קבורה Yom Kvurah extend into the night and
רבי Rebbi said no. והתניא Ve'hatanya it taught in a ברייתא, Braisa,
עד מתי מתאונן עליו ad masai misonen alav until how long does
the אנינות aninus status last for a relative? כל זמן שאינו נקבר
אפילו מכאן ועד עשרה ימים דברי רבי. Kol zman she'eino nikvar afilu
mikan v'ad asara yamim divrei Rebbi. So רבי Rebbi said it extends
well beyond the first day, as long as this person has not
been buried, this אנינות aninus status continues and that is by the
way how we actually practice even for our sense of אונן. onen.
וחכמים אומרים אין מתאונן עליו אלא אותו יום בלבד. Vachachamim omrim ein
misonen alav ela oso yom bilvad. Nope, only the very day itself.
Okay, so it's actually a very different debate. אלא תריץ הכי, Ella
taritz hachi, here's how you have to read their debate. עד מתי
הוא מתאונן עליו כל אותו היום בלא לילו. Ad masai hu misonen
alav kol oso hayom belo leilo. How long is the אנינות, aninus,
that day, the day of קבורה kvurah without the night? Okay.
So the opposite of what we said before because now we're structuring
it to get רבי Rebbi to be the מחמיר. machmir. So the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma didn't say
לילו, leilo, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma just said כל אותו היום.
kol oso hayom. Okay, so how long is the אנינות, aninus, that
entire day which would be יום מיתה yom misa or
now we're
saying including יום קבורה, Yom Kvurah, so from יום מיתה yom misa
until קבורה kvurah but not the night. רבי אומר Rebbi Omer, כל
זמן שלא נקבר. Kol Zeman Shelo Nikbar, No, no, no, the אנינות
aninus status goes until he's buried which presumably the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma agree to, ואם נקבר תופס לילו, ve'im nikvar tofes leilo, but
once he's been buried then it even includes the night. Now that
part isn't said, רבי Rebbi just says until he's buried. So you
could have really more simply understood the debate that the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma was saying just יום מיתה yom misa and רבי Rebbi
was saying nope it extends even ten days until he's buried. But
the גמרא Gemara does not want to say everybody agrees the אנינות
aninus status extends at least rabbinically until he's buried, so it turned
it into a debate where the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was saying
not the night and רבי Rebbi was the מחמיר machmir and רבי
Rebbi was saying yes the night. But one way or another we
have the debate about whether יום קבורה Yom Kvurah includes the night
for קרבן. korban. So again, רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says you don't
bring a קרבן פסח korban Pesach on behalf of an אונן, onen,
he's not שלם, shalem, if you did bring it you can eat
it at night because אנינות לילה aninus layla is דרבנן derabbanan and
פסח Pesach overrides. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda disagreed, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says אנינות לילה aninus layla is דאורייתא. de'oraisa. That is for יום
מיתה. yom misa. What about יום קבורה? Yom Kvurah? So here we
have a debate. יום קבורה Yom Kvurah we now said some say
that you can eat קדשים Kodshim at night, it's not תופס לילו
tofes leilo when יום קבורה Yom Kvurah is not יום מיתה, yom
misa, and others say רבי Rebbi now we're saying says it is
תופס לילו tofes leilo and you can't eat קדשים. Kodshim. Okay, when
it comes to ליקוט עצמות likut atzamos and שמועה, shmua,
there we do allow אכילת פסח achilas pesach even if it's the
day of ליקוט עצמות likut atzamos and שמועה shmua and it would
not be תופס לילו tofes leilo for קדשים. Kodshim. Okay, we will
end with that here.