Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is ל"ו lamed vav
36 and with this we will be finishing the third פרק perek
with its focus on פיגול pigul and we take a look at
the משנה mishna bottom of ל"ה עמוד ב'. lamed hey amud bet.
שחט על מנת להניח את דמו או אימוריו למחר shachat al menat
l'haniach et damo o emurav l'machar או להוציא לחוץ. o l'hotzi l'chutz.
So we know that classic פיגול pigul or חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo
is that you are going to be זורק zorek the דם dam
in the wrong time or eat the meat or offer up the
אימורים emurim in the wrong time or do all of those things
in the wrong place. What happens if you're thinking about the blood
and the אימורים emurim and the meat but you're not thinking about
eating them or offering them on the מזבח mizbeach in the wrong
time or place but you're just planning on leaving them there? Okay
so you שחטת shachted it with the intent to להניח l'haniach to
leave the blood or the אימורים emurim for the next day. You're
not going to eat them the next day you're just going to
leave them over for the next day. You're going to do the
sin of נותר. nosar. Or you're
not going to be זורק zorek the דם dam outside of the
precincts of the בית המקדש beis hamikdash or eat the meat you're
just going to bring it outside but both of those things are
violations and they impact the status of the blood and of the
meat but they are not the case of אכילה achila האכל יאכל
he'achol ye'achel it is just a מחשבה להניח. machshava l'haniach.
So what's the הלכה? halacha? So רבי יהודה פוסל וחכמים מכשירים. Rabbi
Yehuda posel v'chachamim machshirim. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's פסול pasul
it's not פיגול pigul again that's that middle space so even if
it's a thought of הינוח חוץ לזמנו hinuach chutz l'zmano it's not
פיגול pigul because it's not האכל יאכל he'achol ye'achel it's not the
אכילת אדם achilat adam or אכילת מזבח achilat mizbeach but it is
פסול pasul and the חכמים chachamim say it's כשר kosher because the
חכמים chachamim say if you don't have something that specifically qualifies as
חוץ לזמנו או חוץ למקומו chutz l'zmano o chutz limkomo in terms
of a type of אכילה achila then it's neither פיגול pigul or
the חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and it's totally כשר kasher there is
not this middle state of פסול. pasul. Okay I mean פסול pasul
is for חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo but not for מחשבה להניח. machshava
l'haniach. Okay על מנת ליתנם את אגב הכבש שלא כנגד היסוד al
menat l'nitnam et agav hakevesh shelo kineged hayesod
now let's say you had a מחשבה machshava that was not related
at all to מקום makom or to זמן zman it was to
put it in the to be זורק zorek the דם dam in
the wrong place on the מזבח mizbeach so that's a type of
a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo but not exactly. It's in the בית
המקדש beis hamikdash but it's the wrong place to be זורק zorek
the דם dam on the כבש kevesh on the ramp or not
כנגד היסוד kineged hayesod at the corner of the מזבח mizbeach which
is the
south-east corner which does not have a יסוד yesod underneath it והניתנים
למעלה למטה והניתנים למטה למעלה v'hanitnim lemala lemata v'hanitnim lemata lemala
or to put the blood that normally goes above the דם dam
of the חטאת chatas on the corners to put it below on
the מזבח mizbeach in the lower half or the stuff that goes
on the lower half to put it on the upper half והניתנים
בפנים בחוץ והניתנים בחוץ בפנים v'hanitnim bifnim bachutz v'hanitnim bachutz bifnim top
of ל"ו עמוד א' lamed vav amud aleph the blood that normally
goes on the in the inside meaning on the מזבח הזהב mizbeach
hazahav for חטאת הפנימית chatos hapnimis
you're going to put it on the outside on the on the
מזבח הנחושת mizbeach hanechoshet on the outer מזבח mizbeach or those that
go on the outside to put them on the inside והניתנים בחוץ
בפנים v'hanitnim bachutz bifnim
so all of this is being זורק zorek the דם dam in
a type of a wrong place but it is not the wrong
place of outside of the בית המקדש beis hamikdash it's just in
a way that it's not מכפר. mechaper. Okay שיאכלוהו טמאים שיקריבוהו טמאים
sheyachilut t'mayim sheyakrivut t'mayim
that טמאים t'mayim people will eat it or that they'll be מקריב
makriv it up שיאכלוהו ערלים ושיקריבוהו ערלים sheyachilu arelim v'sheyakrivu arelim or
ערלים arelim will be eating it or
be מקריב makriv all these things could have would have the effect
or not all eating it would not פסול pasul the קרבן korban
but being מקריב makriv it by an ערל arel or a טמא
tamei would פסול pasul the קרבן korban and nevertheless שיקריבוהו טמאים שיאכלוהו
ערלים ושיקריבוהו לשבר עצמות הפסח sheyakrivut t'mayim sheyachilu arelim v'sheyakrivu l'shaber atzmot
hapesach לאכול ממנו נא l'echol mimenu na לערב דמו בדם הפסולים l'arev
damo b'dam hapsulim
or let's say you wanted to you were going to do an
עבירה aveira it was a קרבן פסח korban pesach and it's called
ועצם לא תשברו בו etzem lo tishbru bo and you were going
to break one of the bones or you were going to eat
from it when it was לא תאכלו ממנו נא lo t'ochlu mimenu
na you were going to eat from it raw so all of
those are things that you're not allowed to do that might even
invalidate the קרבן korban but depending on the specific things obviously not
breaking a bone of a פסח pesach but some of those things
might and nevertheless it's not a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and it's
not a חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zmano and it's not even doing those
things להניח l'haniach okay or לערב דמו בדם
הפסולים l'arev damo b'dam hapsulim to mix this blood with דם dam
of פסול pasul blood which presumably would make the blood unusable כשר
kasher all of those things are כשר kasher and even רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda agrees so a מחשבה machshava to do something wrong with
it that is not even in the category of חוץ לזמנו או
חוץ למקומו chutz l'zmano o chutz limkomo this is at least the
way the משנה mishna sounds like everybody would agree it's כשר kasher
if it's חוץ לזמנו או חוץ למקומו chutz l'zmano o chutz limkomo
but it's not to be זורק zorek or to offer up or
to eat it's just להניח l'haniach that's the debate of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים chachamim שאין מחשבה פוסלת אלא בחוץ לזמנו
ובחוץ למקומו she'ein machshava poselet ela b'chutz l'zmano u'b'chutz limkomo
the only type of מחשבה machshava that can invalidate is a חוץ
לזמנו chutz l'zmano which is פיגול pigul or a חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo and and.
And finally going back to the first משנה mishnah of a פסח
וחטאת שלא לשמן pesach vechatas shelo lishmon or פסח וחטאת שלא לשמן
pesach vechatas shelo lishmon that also is a type of a מחשבה
machshava that can invalidate. Okay so anything that is not חוץ לזמנו
וחוץ למקומו chutz lizmano v'chutz limkomo is not even part of the
discussion. If it's חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו chutz lizmano v'chutz limkomo but
it's להניח, lehaniach, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says פסול pasul and the
חכמים Chachamim say כשר. kasher. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's the
reason of Rabbi Yehuda? Good question. Once it's not in the פסוק
pasuk of האכל יאכל, he-achel ye-achel, where does he get this middle
ground that it's פסול? pasul? So אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar,
says Rabbi Elazar, תרי קראי כתיבי. Trei kraei kesivi. He learns it
out from a פסוק. pasuk. There's an extra פסוק pasuk by נותר.
nosar. Okay, בנותר, B'nosar, regarding נותר, nosar, actually leaving the meat over.
כתוב אחד אומר, Kasuv echad omer, one פסוק pasuk says לא תותירו
ממנו עד בוקר, Lo sosiru mimenu ad boker, do not leave it
over until the next morning. וכתוב אחד אומר, V'kasuv echad omer, לא
יניח ממנו עד בוקר, Lo yaniach mimenu ad boker, do not also
leave it till the next morning. That's להניח, lehaniach, to leave it,
but it's not the word נותר, notar, to leave over, like leftovers.
It's just the word להניח, lehaniach, don't leave it till the next
morning. And it assumes that you could have learned one from the
other even though תוספות Tosafot points out they're about different קרבנות. korbanot.
Nevertheless, presumably we could have applied one to the other. So why
did the תורה Torah have to repeat it? אם אינו עניין להניח
תנהו עניין למחשבת הינוח. Im eino inyan lehaniach tnahu inyan l'machsheves hinuach.
If you don't need it to tell you the איסור issur of
actually leaving over of נותר, nosar, we learned that from one of
the פסוקים, psukim, so why does it say it in a second
place? To tell you even a thought about leaving over, מחשבת הינוח.
machsheves hinuach. Okay, that's interesting. Basing it on a פסוק. pasuk. So
now the גמרא Gemara is going to question this. רבי יהודה האי
קרא להכי הוא דאתא? Rabbi Yehuda hai kra l'hacha hu d'asa? Is
that really true that Rabbi Yehuda would use the פסוק pasuk to
tell you this about מחשבת הינוח? machsheves hinuach? האי מיבעי ליה לכדתניא.
Hai mibaei lei l'chid'sanya. He needs it for what we taught in
a ברייתא. Baraisa.
ובשר זבח תודת שלמיו, U'vesar zevach todah shelamav, and this is the
classic פסוק pasuk from one of the classic פסוקים psukim of
פיגול, pigul, right, ובשר זבח תודת שלמיו ביום הקרבנו זבחו יאכל U'vesar
zevach todah shelamav b'yom hokravno zivcho ye-achel etc.
Excuse me, this is the פסוק pasuk about נותר. nosar. The פסוק
pasuk about פיגול pigul comes right here two פסוקים psukim later, but
this is the specific פסוק pasuk by נותר nosar by a שלמים
shlamim and it is you know the end of it is the
beginning of the פסוק pasuk of לא יניח ממנו עד בוקר lo
yaniach mimenu ad boker that we quoted above. So let's see what
the ברייתא Baraisa says. ובשר זבח תודת שלמיו, U'vesar zevach todah shelamav,
and I'll read the whole פסוק. pasuk. This is ויקרא ז' ט"ז.
Vayikra Zayin Tes Zayin. ואם
נדר או נדבה זבח קרבנו ביום הקריבו את זבחו יאכל V'im neder
o nedavah zevach korbano b'yom hakrivo es zivcho ye-achel etc.
Excuse me, that was the next פסוק, pasuk, one פסוק pasuk before
that. This is ויקרא ז' ט"ו. Vayikra Zayin Tes Vav. ובשר זבח
תודת שלמיו ביום קרבנו יאכל, U'vesar zevach todah shelamav b'yom korbano ye-achel,
and the meat of the זבח zevach of your תודה שלמים, todah
shlamim, so a תודה todah ביום קרבנו יאכל, b'yom korbano ye-achel, excuse
me, you eat it on the day that it was brought. A
normal שלמים shlamim is eaten two days and the intervening night, but
this because it's a תודה todah would only be eaten the day
itself. לא יניח ממנו עד בוקר, Lo yaniach mimenu ad boker, do
not leave over for the next day. And then the next פסוק
pasuk says just to flesh this out, haha, ואם נדר או נדבה
זבח קרבנו, V'im neder o nedavah zevach korbano, if it's a normal
type of a שלמים, shlamim, נדר או נדבה, neder o nedavah, it's
not a תודה, todah, ביום הקריבו את זבחו יאכל וממחרת והנותר ממנו
יאכל. b'yom hakrivo es zivcho ye-achel u'mimochoras v'hanosar mimenu ye-achel. That you
can eat on the next day. והנותר מבשר הזבח ביום השלישי באש
ישרף. V'hanosar mib'sar hazevach bayom hashlishi ba-esh yisaref. And then the third
day you burn it. And then comes our famous פיגול pigul פסוק,
pasuk, ואם האכל יאכל מבשר זבח שלמיו ביום השלישי לא ירצה. V'im
he-achel ye-achel mib'sar zevach shlamav bayom hashlishi lo yeratze.
So now we're going to look about why the different words are
needed in the פסוק pasuk going back to the first פסוק pasuk
about the תודה. todah. Let's take a look again. ובשר זבח תודת
שלמיו, U'vesar zevach todah shelamav, and the meat of the זבח zevach
of your תודה שלמים. todah shlamim. למדנו לתודה שנאכל ליום ולילה. Lamadnu
l'todah shene-echeles l'yom valaylah.
So that's the straight meaning of the פסוק, pasuk, a תודה, todah,
ביום הקרבנו זבחו יאכל. b'yom hokravno zivcho ye-achel. Okay, you eat it
on the day that it was brought. ביום קרבנו יאכל, B'yom korbano
ye-achel, excuse me. You eat it on the day it was brought.
חליפין, Chalifin, how about something that's not the תודה todah but that's
an exchange for the תודה? todah? Now what's an exchange? So תמורה
tmurah that comes next, so רש"י Rashi says it means that you
had your תודה todah and then you lost it, so you separated
out another קרבן korban for your תודה, todah, and then you found
the first one. So something that you had sort of designated not
as a תמורה. tmurah. תמורה Tmurah is where you try to transfer
the קדושה, kedushah, but something that you designated as a substitute because
you had lost the original one. Okay, so that's a חליפין. chalifin.
ולדות, Velados, שלמים shlamim can be a female, so if it gave
birth. תמורות, Tmuros, if that's actually תמורה, tmurah, you tried to transfer
the קדושה kedushah and the תורה Torah says the second animal gets
קדוש kadosh and the first one remains קדוש. kadosh. מנין? Mina-yin? So
how do you know even things that aren't the תודה todah itself
but are in some way derivative from the תודה? todah? How do
you know those also have only one day of eating? They're all
can be offered up. How do you know they can only be
eaten for one day? תלמוד לומר ובשר. Talmud lomar u'vesar. So it
could have just said וזבח תודת שלמיו. v'zevach todah shelamav. Why did
it have the extra word "the flesh of" זבח תודת שלמיו? zevach
todah shelamav? That's to tell you even something that is derivative from
a תודה todah is like a תודה todah and it can only
be eaten for one day. Now חטאת ואשם מנין? Chatas v'asham minayin?
How about a חטאת chatas and an אשם? asham? Fascinating thing in
the תורה Torah that the תורה Torah only speaks about how long
do you eat to eat a שלמים Shlamim for. A תודה Toda
is one day and a שלמים Shlamim is two days. The תורה
Torah never says how much time the כהנים Kohanim have to eat,
you know, the meat of a חטאת, Chatat, okay, which is or
of an אשם, Asham, which is fascinating. Maybe the תורה Torah just
assumes that since it's כהנים Kohanim and כהנים Kohanim are זריזים, zerizim,
you know, they're going to obviously eat the meat on the day
itself. I don't know, but it's fascinating that it never says in
the תורה Torah how long they have to eat the meat. So
מנין? minayin? So we learn it out from this פסוק pasuk about
a תודה. Toda. How do you know a חטאת Chatat and אשם
Asham also only have one day of eating? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
זבח. zevach. So the word זבח zevach is inclusive, any sacrifice. So
even though it's talking about a תודה, Toda, it could have said
ותודת שלמיו. Ve-todat Shlamav. It could have just said תודה. Toda. Why
does it have the word בשר? basar? Even things that derive from
a תודה. Toda. Why the word זבח? zevach? All other קרבנות korbanot
that are not a שלמים Shlamim and that are not a תודה
Toda also only one day. ומנין לרבות שלמי נזיר ושלמי פסח? U'minayin
l'rabot shlomei nazir u'shlomei pesach? Now, the one thing that is two
days is a שלמים, Shlamim, but not including a תודה, Toda, which
is a type of a שלמים, Shlamim, a generic שלמים. Shlamim. And
now we're going to exclude even certain other types of שלמים Shlamim
that also are only one day. What are they? שלמי נזיר ושלמי
פסח. Shlomei nazir u'shlomei pesach. So שלמי נזיר shlomei nazir is the
of a נזיר nazir brings a ram as a שלמים, Shlamim, okay,
when, you know, when he finishes his נזירות. nezirut. And שלמי פסח,
shlomei pesach, רש"י Rashi says that means the חגיגה Chagiga that's brought
on the 14th together with the פסח. Pesach. תוספות Tosafos has a
lot of evidence against that. תוספות Tosafos says it's a derivative of
the פסח. Pesach. It basically means, let's say, or the פסח Pesach
itself. Let's say you didn't bring the פסח, Pesach, you sanctified it
as a פסח, Pesach, and then you wind up you didn't bring
it on the 14th of ניסן. Nissan. Now what is the הלכה?
halacha? As you remember from the first פרק, perek, the הלכה halacha
is that a פסח בשאר ימות השנה Pesach b'shaar yemot hashanah is
שלמים. Shlamim. So תוספות Tosafos says שלמי פסח shlomei pesach is a
פסח Pesach that became a שלמים Shlamim because you missed פסח Pesach
or it's not on פסח Pesach itself. So how do you know
that these two types of שלמים Shlamim that are not generic שלמים,
Shlamim, they're special, one is an obligatory one of a נזיר, nazir,
the other is something that comes from a פסח, Pesach, and פסח
Pesach also can only be eaten, you know, that night? So how
do you know that those are limited to the day? It's not
exactly like a פסח, Pesach, it has the whole day, but how
do you know that those are limited to the day, to one
day? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, שלמיו. Shlamav. So the extra word שלמיו,
Shlamav, it could have said ותודה ביום הקריבו יאכל. Ve-toda b'yom hikrivo
ya'achel. So each extra word teaches you something. בשר basar tells you
things that are derivative from a תודה, Toda, like a child or
a חליפין chalifin or תמורה. tmura. זבח zevach tells you other קרבנות
korbanot that are not שלמים, Shlamim, and שלמיו, Shlamav, which is by
the way plural, you know, I believe it's plural, anyway tells you
other types of שלמים Shlamim that are not generic שלמים, Shlamim, שלמי
נזיר ושלמי פסח, shlomei nazir u'shlomei pesach, also are only one day.
Okay, we're not done yet.
לחמי תודה וחלות ורקיקין שבנזיר מנין? Lachmei toda v'chalot u'rekikin she-be-nazir minayin?
How about things that are not meat but accompany some of these
sacrifices that are one-day sacrifices? Like the bread that comes with a
תודה, Toda, or the חלות chalot and רקיקין, rekikin, other types of,
you know, wafers and so on, that come with the that the
נזיר nazir brings together with the שלמים. Shlamim. How do you know
these things that accompany the one-day קרבנות korbanot also are only one
day? מנין? minayin? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, קרבנו. korbano. So it says,
you know, ביום, b'yom, it
says ובשר זבח תודת שלמיו ביום קרבנו יאכל. U'besar zevach todat shalamav
b'yom korbano ya'achel. So קרבנו korbano is more inclusive than the word
בשר basar or זבח, zevach, which are things that are slaughtered or
meat, and that comes to include even these things that are eaten
together with these קרבנות. korbanot. כולן קורא אני בהן לא יניח ממנו
עד בקר. Kulan korei bihen lo yaniach mimenu ad boker. All of
them you only have the day to eat, not the next day.
So you learn a lot from this פסוק. pasuk. From this פסוק
pasuk about a תודה, Toda, you pretty much learn that everything other
than a generic שלמים Shlamim has only one day to be eaten.
Okay, and maybe that is also what the תורה, Torah, you know,
one way to read the פשט peshat of the תורה Torah is
maybe it's just working with an assumption that everything is eaten at
the day and it has to point out that a שלמים Shlamim
you have two days. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara learns it out
from this פסוק. pasuk. So clearly you cannot say this פסוק pasuk
is extra to teach you מחשבת הינוח. machshevet hinuach. You need this
פסוק pasuk to teach you pretty much all other קרבנות. korbanot.
So how can you say he uses it, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
uses his idea for a מחשבה machsheva for leaving something over?
So the גמרא Gemara says yes, you could say it, אם כן
לימא קרא לא תותירו. Im ken leima kra lo totiru. If the
פסוק pasuk wanted to just expand and include all of these other
קרבנות korbanot for one day, it would have just said לא תותירו,
lo totiru, it would have used the classic word of נותר notar
to leave over. מאי לא יניח? Mai lo yaniach? Why did it
switch the language and say don't leave it, in other words? But
it's not the word of נותר. notar. אם אינו עניין להינוח תנהו
עניין למחשבת הינוח. Im eino inyan l'hinuach, tnehinu l'machshevet hinuach. That change
of words is telling you that there's something that's not only about
actually leaving it, but another category, and that is the category of
planning on leaving it over. Okay, so that is how רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar claims it's based on an extra word of a פסוק
pasuk or the terminology used to teach you this other idea of
מחשבת הינוח. machshevet hinuach.
So the גמרא Gemara now says fine, maybe you get it from
a פסוק, pasuk, but we're still not satisfied.
התינח להניח, Hatenech lehaniach, that's good explaining where ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
gets his idea that if you plan on leaving it over till
the next day, like a type of a נותר notar except a
מחשבת נותר, machshevet notar, leaving it over. התינח להניח, Hatenech lehaniach, להוציא
מאי איכא למימר? lehotzi mai ika lemimar? But what about the other
case of the משנה, Mishna, which was a חוץ למקומו? chutz limkomo?
You planned on bringing it outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, not
eating it outside, not being זורק הדם, zorek hadam, just bringing it
outside. Where do you get that from? So you don't have a
פסוק, pasuk, that's problem number one. ועוד, Ve'od, and number two, טעמיה
דר' יהודה סברא הוא. taameh d'Rebbe Yehuda sevara hu. There's
ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda actually just knows it from logic. He's not
basing himself on a פסוק. pasuk. How do I know that? Because
we have a ברייתא Braisa that tells us דתניא, detanya, we taught
in a ברייתא. Braisa. You wonder if the גמרא Gemara knew the
ברייתא, Braisa, why did it have to have the whole discussion beforehand?
But presumably ר' אלעזר Rebbe Elazar didn't know the ברייתא Braisa or
didn't hold of the ברייתא Braisa and he believed it was a
פסוק, pasuk, but the גמרא's Gemara saying that's not sufficient, that does
not explain all the cases. From a ברייתא Braisa it is clear
that it's just based on straight logic. Okay, so let's see the
ברייתא. Braisa. דתניא, detanya,
אמר להם ר' יהודה, amar lahem Rebbe Yehuda, ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
said to the חכמים, Chachamim, אי אתם מודים שאם הניחו למחר שהוא
פסול? ee atem modim she'im hinicho lemachar shehu pasul? Wouldn't you agree
to me that if you actually left it over till the next
day it's פסול? pasul? Now left what? If you leave the meat
over till the next day sure, the meat is פסול, pasul, it's
נותר, notar, but the קרבן korban isn't פסול. pasul. But if you
left, notice the משנה, Mishna, let's look back at the משנה, Mishna,
שחטו על מנת להניח את דמו, shachto al mnat lehaniach es damo,
right, או אמר למחר. o emar lemachar. So if you leave the
blood over till the next day, then it's פסול, pasul, okay, because
then you can't be זורק הדם. zorek hadam. Once it becomes nightfall
you cannot be זורק הדם. zorek hadam. So let's at least focus
for now just on the blood. Okay, so his argument is look,
you would agree to me that if you leave the blood over,
the קרבן korban becomes פסול, pasul, correct? אי אתם
מודים שאם הניחו למחר שהוא פסול אף חישב להניח למחר פסול.
ee atem modim
she'im hinicho lemachar shehu pasul af chishev lehaniach lemachar pasul. So therefore
say if he planned on leaving it over till the next day
it's פסול, pasul, and now we understand why it applies to חוץ
למקומו. chutz limkomo. Because if you brought the blood out of the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it becomes פסול ביוצא, pasul beyotzei, you can't
use it, the קרבן korban is פסול. pasul. So planning on bringing
it outside also becomes פסול. pasul. Now, if that's his logic, that
basically something that if you actually did it in actuality would invalidate
the קרבן, korban, the thought to do it also invalidates, which seems
to sort of be what we've been saying by פיגול. pigul. But
he makes it very generic, any act that would invalidate, the thought
to do it also invalidates. He's abstracting now. It doesn't make it
פיגול pigul but it invalidates. Okay, if that's true, it's not because
it's just about חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano and חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo.
The cases of the משנה Mishna were bringing the blood outside, חוץ
למקומו, chutz limkomo, leaving the blood over, חוץ לזמנו. chutz lizmano. But
if this is the logic, there's a lot of other things that
can invalidate a קרבן, korban, so why doesn't ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
also say the thinking about doing those would make it פסול? pasul?
And the rest of the משנה Mishna sounded like thinking about other
types of things everybody would agree that it's still כשר. kasher. So
how do you explain that? So let's take a look.
אלא, Ella, you're right. טעמיה דר' יהודה סברא הוא. taameh d'Rebbe Yehuda
sevara hu. So now you've shown that ר' יהודה's Rebbe Yehuda a
סברא, sevara, and it's basically if the act invalidates, the מחשבה machshava
invalidates.
If that's true, says the גמרא, Gemara, ונפלוג נמי ר' יהודה בכולהו.
veniflog nami Rebbe Yehuda bechulhu. Let ר' יהודה Rebbe Yehuda argue with
all the other cases of the משנה. Mishna. It's not just based
on the model of חוץ לזמנו chutz lizmano and חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo like we explained the משנה, Mishna, פשט pshat of the משנה
Mishna sounded like. It's based on this much more general idea, so
he should argue on all the other cases of the משנה. Mishna.
So let's take a look.
בהיי נפלו? behai niflo? Which one do you want him to argue
about? בשבירת עצמות הפסח, beshvirat atzmot hapesach, so we're going to take
the low-hanging fruit first.
In the case of breaking the bones of the פסח, Pesach, ולאכול
ממנו נא, ule'echol mimenu na, or to eat from it raw, זבחה
גופיה מי מיפסל? zivcha gufeh mi mipsal? Fine, you're doing an איסור,
issur, but that doesn't invalidate the קרבן, korban, so planning on doing
it also doesn't invalidate the
קרבן. korban. על מנת שיאכלוהו טמאים, al mnat she'yochluhu tme'im, how about
the case of that tamei people will eat it?
ושיקריבוהו טמאים, v'sheyakrivuhu tme'im, and that tamei people will offer it up,
זבחה גופיה מי מיפסל? zivcha gufeh mi mipsal? How does the קרבן
korban become פסול? pasul? Now, or let's read one more sentence and
then I'll sort of make the point. Similarly, says the גמרא, Gemara,
שיאכלוהו ערלים ושיקריבוהו ערלים, sheyochluhu arelim v'sheyakrivuhu arelim, if ערלים arelim will
eat from it or ערלים arelim will offer it up, זבחה גופיה
מי מיפסל? zivcha gufeh mi mipsal? How it won't become פסול pasul
just based on that? Now, let's pause for a minute. Okay, so
that's true, if a טמא tamei or an ערל arel person eats
it, it won't become פסול, pasul, but if a טמא tamei or
an ערל arel person is מקריב makriv it, is זורק הדם, zorek
hadam, it will become פסול. pasul. So why is that not an
issue? So רש"י Rashi says no, we're talking here about the אימורים.
eimurim. The fact that it says יקריבוהו yakrivuhu and doesn't say like
יזרקו את דמו, yizreku es damo, יקריבוהו yakrivuhu here's understood to mean
במקטיר. bemaktir. the אימורים imurim. *emurim*. If you take a look earlier
in the משנה Mishnah *mishna* it said, well actually here it didn't
say, it says אימוריו למזבח *emurav lamizbei'ach*, but it does often talk
about להקריב אימוריו למזבח *lehakriv emurav lamizbei'ach*. So יקריבוהו *yakrivuhu*, רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* says, is about the אימורים imurim *emurim*. So being having a
טמא tamei *tamei* person be מקריב makriv *makriv* the אימורים imurim *emurim*
or a טמא tamei *tamei* person being or an ערל *arel* being
מקריב *makriv* the אימורים imurim *emurim* doesn't invalidate. Only the דם dam
*dam* can invalidate. So a טמא tamei, *tamei* person eating or טמא
tamei *tamei* ערל *arel* eating or being מקריב *makriv* the אימורים imurim
*emurim* would not invalidate. That's what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says. A little
bit of a problem is that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*'s
case is also thought about being מניח *meni'ach* the אימורים imurim *emurim*,
right? It says שחטו מנת להניח את דמו או אימוריו למזבח או
להוציאם לחוץ *shachato m'nas lehani'ach et damo o emurav lamizbei'ach o l'hotzi'am
lachutz*. So why does that פסול pasul *pasul* it? That's also about
the אימורים *emurim* and that shouldn't פסול pasul? *pasul* the קרבן korban
*korban*. So תוספות Tosafos, *Tosfos* says, well, in that case, if you
at least the first case where the אימורים *emurim* are being left
over till the next day, you sort of effectively פסול pasul *pasul*
the קרבן korban. *korban* because you can't be
זורק Zorek *zorek* the דם Dam, *dam*, excuse me, you can't eat
the
meat if the אימורים *emurim* are around and you have not been
offered them up. So if you're leaving the אימורים *emurim* till the
next day, right, then you are effectively invalidating the קרבן korban *korban*
because you are preventing the meat from being eaten. Now, number one,
that's not really invalidating the קרבן korban *korban* because the owners are
still יוצאי ידי חובתו *yotzei yedei chovaso*. Number two, it doesn't explain
the case about being מוציא *motzi* the אימורים *emurim* לחוץ *lachutz*. Being
מוציא *motzi* the אימורים *emurim* לחוץ *lachutz* actually invalidates the אימורים *emurim*
and then you could go ahead and eat the meat, the אימורים
*emurim* aren't around ready to be offered, they're פסול Pasul *pasul*. How
is it any different, the case of a טמא tamei *tamei* or
an ערל *arel* being מקריב *makriv* the אימורים *emurim* and the case
of being מוציא *motzi* the אימורים *emurim* לחוץ *lachutz*? So it's really
a little unclear what the full answer here is. But anyway, this
is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, that the case of
ערל *arel* or טמא tamei, *tamei* would affect the meat or the
אימורים *emurim*, but it would not invalidate the קרבן korban, *korban*, which
seems to say that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* would only
say his idea about דם Dam *dam*, which does make the משנה
Mishnah, *mishna* problematic. But let's keep on going.
Okay. לישנא אחרינא *lishna
achrina*,
or another way of explaining why that's not why the case of
ערלים *arelim* is not a problem: כה כמיני *ko k'minei*?
Who's going to listen to you? Okay,
you're saying I will get a טמא tamei *tamei* person to eat
it, I will get an ערל *arel* to eat it or to
offer it up. So that's not under your control. Now you could
say I'll make myself טמא tamei. *tamei*, all right, but that since
it involves another person or a completely different reality than we have
now, that's an irrelevant thought. So that works better. All right, yes,
מחשבה machshava *machshava* will work by the אימורים *emurim*, okay, but the
reason ערלים *arelim* and טמאים tmeim, *tmei'im* is not a it does
not invalidate is that's not under your control. Okay, so once more,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is now being generalized to say
a מחשבה machshava. *machshava* of doing something that will invalidate according to
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* will itself invalidate, the מחשבה machshava
*machshava* itself will invalidate. The קרבן פסח korban Pesach *korban Pesach* things
do not invalidate the קרבן korban. *korban*, the אימורים *emurim* and the
אכילה *achila* by a טמא tamei *tamei* or an ערל *arel* do
not invalidate the קרבן korban, *korban*, or said another way, even if
somehow there is a problem when it gets to the אימורים *emurim*,
it's not under your control and therefore the thought is not a
meaningful thought.
Okay, let's keep on going. לערב דם Dam דמן בדם הפסולים *l'arev
dam daman b'dam hapsulim*, how about the other cases in the משנה
mishna *mishna*? You're going to mix the blood with דם Dam *dam*
with invalid blood and that will make the blood unusable. So why
shouldn't the מחשבה machshava *machshava* of doing that also invalidate? רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda לטעמיה דאמר אין דם Dam מבטל דם Dam *Rabbi Yehuda
l'taimei d'amar ein dam m'vatel dam*. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
goes according to his reasoning that he says that when blood of
קרבנות korbanos *korbanot* get mixed up with other blood, it's not בטל
*batel*. מין במינו *min b'mino* is not בטל *batel*, other reasons for
that according to רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, and therefore it
does not invalidate the blood. So he actually would say that case
would be כשר kasher. *kasher* and that's why your מחשבה machshava *machshava*
is not a problem. Okay, ליתן את הניתנים למעלה למטה למטה למעלה
*liten et hanitnim l'ma'ala l'mata, l'mata l'ma'ala*, how about being זורק Zorek
*zorek* it in the wrong place of the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbei'ach*? That
would invalidate. So why doesn't the thought for that invalidate? רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda לטעמיה דאמר שלא למקומו כמקומו נמי מקומו קרינן ביה *Rabbi
Yehuda l'taimei d'amar shelo limkomo k'bimkomo nami mkomo korinan bei*. If you
remember there's a whole discussion earlier in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that
if you be זורק Zorek *zorek* it, but in the מזבח mizbeiach
*mizbei'ach* but in the wrong place on the מזבח mizbeiach *mizbei'ach*, it's
according to at least one approach it still counts. So therefore that
also doesn't invalidate, so the thought of doing it doesn't invalidate. Okay
again, the תנא tanna קמא *tanna kamma* might hold it does invalidate,
and mixing the blood invalidates, but fundamentally disagrees with רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. Thought of doing things that are פסול Pasul, *pasul*
does not make the קרבן korban פסול Pasul *korban pasul*. רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*, who says thought of doing things that are
פסול pasul. *pasul* does invalidate, will say that those cases actually the
קרבן korban. *korban* is כשר Kasher. *kasher*. Mixing the blood, still throw
the blood. You threw the blood in the wrong place, it's still
כשר Kasher. *kasher*. Okay, that's why he doesn't argue by that.
Now, וליפלוג בניתנים בפנים שנתנן בחוץ וניתנים בחוץ שנתנן בפנים *v'liflog b'nitanim
bifnim shenatnan bachutz v'nitanim bachutz shenatnan bifnim*. Okay, but how about the
cases of being ניתנים בפנים שנתנן בחוץ *nitanim bifnim shenatnan bachutz* and
ניתנים בחוץ שנתנן בפנים *nitanim bachutz shenatnan bifnim*? Yes, when it talks
about being זורק zorek the דם Dam, that goes on the outside
outer מזבח mizbeiach, on the inner מזבח mizbe'ach, or vice versa? That
certainly is considered a שלא במקומו shelo bimkomo and it doesn't count
and when you bring the blood of an outer חטאת chatas or
any outer קרבן Korban, inside, you and it clearly invalidate it. So
that's clearly going to invalidate it. So why doesn't a מחשבה Machshava
for רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda invalidate invalidate in that case? Good question.
So the גמרא Gemara says, קסבר רבי יהודה, kasavar Rebbi Yehuda, רבי
יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda of the opinion, בעינן מקום שמשולש בדם בבשר באימורים.
beinan makom shemeshulash bedam bebasar ba'imurim. You need a place that is
threefold meat, blood, and the אימורים. Okay, so you'll remember there was
a whole range of different interpretations of what this meant earlier, but
the simplest interpretation is that it excludes the inner מזבח
mizbe'ach. because the inner מזבח, mizbe'ach, you bring, you're not
מקריב אימורים makriv imurim and you don't eat
בשר, basar, the תוספות, Tosafos in the inside of in the actually
the in the היכל Heichal itself. There's a debate whether בדיעבד bedieved
you could eat בשר basar the היכל Heichal itself, minimally you don't,
you're not מקריב the אימורים there. Alright, so therefore a thought about
that is outside of the category of מחשבה. Machshava Even though before
we were you might have when you were dealing with like the
narrow parameters of פיגול, pigul, you might have said we that
we understand this extra criterion and put that like outside of the
category. Here that we're making a much more generic point that a
מחשבה Machshava of something that invalidates, the מחשבה Machshava also invalidates, it's
a little surprising that we have, oh, but there's this one criteria
about מקום משולש. makom meshulash. Alright, but that is what the גמרא
Gemara is saying and therefore, yes, it's a thought about doing something
פסול pasul? but it's not effective because it has to do with
the outer courtyard and the inner היכל Heichal and that type of
מחשבה Machshava from one to the other does not invalidate. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ומי סבירא ליה לרבי
יהודה האי סברא? umi sivreh Rebbi Yehuda hai sevara? Now does רבי
יהודה Rebbi Yehuda really hold this that the idea of מקום משולש
makom meshulash means it can't become פסול? pasul, Why not?
דתניא רבי יהודה אומר דבר רע. ve-tanya Rebbi Yehuda omer davar ra.
It says לא תזבח לה' אלוקיך שור ושה אשר יהיה בו מום
כל דבר רע, lo tizbach l'Adoshem Elokecha shor vaseh asher yihiyeh bo
mum kol davar ra, any bad thing. So what's כל דבר רע
kol davar ra coming to include? So,
כל דבר רע ריבה כאן חטאת ששחטה בדרום. kol davar ra riba
kan chatas sheshachata badarom. So he says that includes other things you
did wrong with the קרבן. Korban Okay, and he's paskin לא תזבח
lo tizbach at the time of שחיטה. shechita. So what other thing
you could do wrong with the קרבן Korban is שחט shecht a
קרבן Korban that's supposed to be in the north, you שחט shechted
in the south. Okay, number one, וחטאת שנכנסה לפנים פסולה. vechatas shenichnasah
lifnim pesulah. Or a חטאת chatas that you brought the blood inside
into the היכל, Heichal, it's invalid. Now רש"י says of course a
חטאת chatas you bring the blood inside it's invalid, that's a מפורש
פסוק, m'furash pasuk, וכל חטאת אשר יובא מדמה אל הקודש פנימה vechol
chatas asher yuva midamah el hakodesh panima etc. But what it means
is just thinking about it will invalidate. So רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
learns from the פסוק pasuk כל דבר רע kol davar ra other
types of things can also invalidate a קרבן, Korban not just a
מום. mum. שחיטה Shechting it in the wrong place invalidates it and
planning on bringing the blood into the קודש kodesh can also invalidate
it. How do we know it's about a thought? So רש"י says
because it says לא תזבח lo tizbach we're talking about something at
the time of שחיטה. shechita. תוספות Tosfos says the דרשה drasha might
also be from the word דבר davar like דיבור, dibur, sometimes we
use that for thought or speech and not act. Okay, so here
we have a ברייתא braisa that at least the way we're interpreting
it, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, is clearly saying that a thought about
bringing the blood into the into the היכל Heichal actually does invalidate
the קרבן. Korban So in a way you should just say so
forget our whole explanation of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. before this. If
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. says a thought of bringing it into the
into the היכל Heichal does invalidate the קרבן, Korban then how come
in the משנה mishna he doesn't argue about that case? Okay, so
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So that shows you that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. actually says that
it does invalidate, but the גמרא Gemara then pushes back in the
other direction. ולית ליה לרבי יהודה שלישי? velais leh l'Rebbi Yehuda shelishi?
Are you telling me רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda does not hold of
this principle of the tripart of the tri-fold
space, meaning that does not hold that you're exempt when it comes
to inside the היכל Heichal or not exempt or whatever that the
קרבן Korban doesn't become
פסול pasul, when it relates to the inside of the היכל Heichal
a thought about the inside of the היכל? Heichal? I'll show you
that he says that a thought about bringing it to the inside
of the היכל Heichal does not invalidate the קרבן. korban דתנן ve-t'nan
we taught in the משנה, mishnah אמר רבי יהודה, amar Rebbi Yehuda,
הכניס בשוגג כשר. hechnis bishogeg kasher.
If you brought the blood of a חטאת בשוגג chatas bishogeg inside
the היכל, Heichal, the חטאת chatas remains כשר. kasher, Okay, הא במזיד
פסול, ha b'meizid pasul, the obvious implication is that when you bring
the blood of a חטאת chatas inside the היכל, Heichal, it does
become invalid. וקיימא לן בשחיטה. vekayma lan beshechita.
And we know, we over there when we get to that פרק
perek. *perek*, we explained that according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, when
does the blood of an outer חטאת chatas *chatas* that's brought inside
the היכל *heichal*, when does it invalidate the קרבן korban *korban*? Not
just when you bring it into the היכל *heichal*, but when you
actually are זורק הדם zorek hadam *zorek hadam*. Okay, so what does
that show? It shows that just bringing in does not invalidate. All
right, so and now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to make a
קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. השתא ומה התם אילו עייליה אי כיפר kiper,
אין אי לא כיפר לא *Hashta uma hatam ilu ayeilei i kiper
in i lo kiper lo*, when you actually bring the blood in
from an outer חטאת chatas *chatas* into the היכל *heichal*, it only,
it will only invalidate if you actually were זורק הדם zorek hadam
*zorek hadam* and not if you weren't זורק הדם zorek hadam *zorek
hadam*. הכא דחשיב חישובי לא כל שכן *Hacha dechashiv chishuvey lo kol
shekein*? Here where you just thought about bringing it in, so certainly
it would not... if bringing it in doesn't have the power to
invalidate, then thinking to bringing it in certainly does not have the
power to invalidate. Okay, and therefore you see that yes, רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* does exempt from this category when it relates to this
idea, you know, he has this idea of מקום משולש *makom meshulash*
and he does exempt a מחשבה machshava *machshava* when it relates to
bringing it into the היכל *heichal*. So, you probably,
there's a lot of questions to ask about that, which I'll get
to in a second, but let's just review what we said. Okay,
in the משנה *mishna*, it sounds like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* basically
is limiting himself to חוץ לזמנו Chutz L'Zmano, וחוץ למקומו *chutz lizmano
v'chutz limkomo*, but he says that if you plan on just leaving
it חוץ לזמנו Chutz L'Zmano, וחוץ למקומו *chutz lizmano v'chutz limkomo*, it's
פסול pasul, *pasul*. But anything that's not about חוץ לזמנו Chutz L'Zmano.
וחוץ למקומו *chutz lizmano v'chutz limkomo* obviously is כשר kasher *kasher*. From
the ברייתא Braisa *baraita* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it seems that
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* is making a much broader statement, that any
act that you do that invalidates, if you have the מחשבה machshava
*machshava* about that act, it also invalidates. Then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, well, if that's true, he should argue on all the cases
of the משנה *mishna*. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* goes through all
the cases of the משנה *mishna* to explain why those are not
acts that invalidate the קרבן korban *korban* or they're not under your
control, it would require somebody else. But then we're left with, okay,
but bringing the blood inside the היכל *heichal* would invalidate the קרבן
korban *korban*, so why doesn't he say that the מחשבה machshava *machshava*
invalidates? And the גמרא *Gemara* says, well, no, things that relate to
inside the היכל *heichal* it's not a מקום משולש *makom meshulash*, things
that relate to inside the היכל *heichal*, those are out of the
category of מחשבה machshava *machshava*. All right, but then the גמרא *Gemara*
pushes back, but no, it sounds like רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says
that a מחשבה machshava, *machshava* of bringing the blood on the inside
does invalidate, כל דבר רע Kol Davar Ra *kol davar ra*. And
then it pushes back the other way. No, I'll show you that
he says it doesn't invalidate, because he says even bringing it inside
doesn't invalidate, so thinking about bringing it inside also won't invalidate. So
therefore the גמרא *Gemara* says, תרי תנאי ואליבא דרבי יהודה *Trei Tannai
v'aliba deRabbi Yehuda*. Fine, you're right. One תנא *Tanna*, the תנא *Tanna*
of כל דבר רע *kol davar ra*, says thinking about bringing the
blood on the inside will invalidate, and that actually will fit into
this general pattern of a מחשבה machshava *machshava* about doing something that
invalidates, the מחשבה machshava *machshava* also invalidates. And the other תנא *Tanna*,
our תנא *Tanna* of the משנה *mishna*, where רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*
does not argue, will say that planning on bringing it inside does
not invalidate, and that is because of this requirement of מקום משולש
*makom meshulash*. So even though bringing it inside, yes, will invalidate, thinking
about bringing it inside will not invalidate because of this requirement of
מקום משולש *makom meshulash*, and that's why he does not argue. Now,
just to pause for a second and say something about the גמרא
*Gemara*'s קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. It's a bizarre קל וחומר *kal vachomer*
because as תוספות *Tosafot* points out, that קל וחומר *kal vachomer* should
undermine all the laws
of פיגול Piggul. *pigul*, because, well, you know, if פיגול Piggul *pigul*
is like I plan on eating it in the wrong time, well,
that doesn't invalidate the קרבן *korban*, so thinking about eating it in
the wrong time shouldn't invalidate. Like, why is this making any sense,
this קל וחומר *kal vachomer*? But so תוספות *Tosafot* tries to answer
that question.
It's not really a satisfactory answer, we're just going to leave it
as it is. But that's what the גמרא *Gemara* says. Okay. So
now the גמרא *Gemara* says like
this: וסבר רבי יהודה חטאת chatas ששחטה בדרום יחייב *visavar Rabbi Yehuda
chatas sheshachtah bedarom yechayev*, going back to
the
other
דרשה *d'rasha* of
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*, where he says
כל דבר רע *kol davar ra*, that if you שחט *shachted* it
in the south, a חטאת chatas, *chatas* in the south, that does
he really say that you would be חייב chayav. *chayav*, meaning מלקות
*malkus*? He says, you know, it says because first of all, I
mean, it means the קרבן *korban* is פסול pasul *pasul*, and B,
it's based on a פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* that says לא תזבח לה'
אלהיך *lo tizbach l'Hashem Elokecha*, so presumably you get מלקות *malkus*. Is
that really true? והתניא *V'hatanya*, did we not teach in a ברייתא
Braisa *baraita*, דף ל"ו עמוד ב' *daf lamed vav amud bet*: רבי
יהודה אומר יכול חטאת ששחטה בדרום יהא חייב chayav *Rabbi Yehuda omer
yakol chatas sheshachtah badarom yehei chayav*, maybe ex- exactly rejecting what the
other ברייתא Braisa said רבי יהודה said. This ברייתא braisa has רבי
יהודה saying maybe if you slaughtered it in the south you would
transgress, תלמוד לומר לא תזבח לה' אלהיך שור ושה אשר יהיה בו
מום כל דבר רע. Talmud Lomar Lo Tizbach Lashem Elokecha Shor Ve-Seh
Asher Yiheyeh Bo Mum Kol Davar Ra. על דבר רע Al Davar
Ra את מחייבו At Mechayvo ואי אתה מחייבו חטאת
ששחט בדרום. Ve-Ee Atah Mechayvo Chatas She-Shacht Be-Darom. It has to be
something that's intrinsically bad with the animal, it has a מום, Mum,
and not something that the act was in the wrong place. That's
not something intrinsically bad of the animal. כל דבר רע does not
include slaughtering it in the wrong place, or one might say slaughtering
it with the wrong thought. Okay? So you have a direct contradiction.
One ברייתא braisa has רבי יהודה saying it is included in the
פסוק pasuk and one has him saying it's not included. So the
גמרא here says תרי תנאי אליבא דרבי יהודה. Trei Tannai Aliba De-Rebbi
Yehuda. This is clearly two different תנאים Tannaim about what רבי יהודה's
position is. Okay. So now let's move on. Now we move on
to a series of sort of you know building of
statements building on
the concepts that we've already laid down. So let's take a look.
אמר רבי אבא Amar Rebbi Abba מודה רבי יהודה Modeh Rebbi Yehuda
says רבי אבא Rebbi Abba רבי יהודה agrees שחוזר וקובעו לפיגול. She-Chozer
Ve-Kovo Le-Piggul. Okay? That even though this מחשבת הינוח Machshavas Hinuach
invalidates the קרבן, if you after the מחשבת הינוח Machshavas Hinuach you
had a thought of חוץ לזמנו, Chutz L'Zmano, you will make the
קרבן into פיגול. Piggul. Now that's a big חידוש. Chiddush. Normally we
say that if your קרבן is פסול pasul for a different reason,
either you didn't go through the process, you weren't מקריב כל מתיריו,
Makriv Kol Mattireh, or you had another מחשבה machshava that invalidated, a
מחשבה machshava of חוץ למקומו, Chutz L'Makomo, that the פיגול Piggul. would
not become פיגול. Piggul And here he's saying that not clear why
he's saying it but he's saying this idea of רבי יהודה, this
generic idea, it's not the concrete cases of the תורה Torah of
חוץ לזמנו, Chutz L'Zmano חוץ למקומו. Chutz L'Makomo. It's some broad generic
idea that if you plan on doing something that invalidates the קרבן
also is invalid, that does not take the קרבן out of the
ability to become פיגול. Piggul All right? That's his claim. אמר רבא
Amar Rava רבא Rava
said תדע Teda I'll show you that that's the case. דפיגול לפני
זריקה לאו כלום היא. De-Piggul Lifnei Zerika Lav Klum Hi. פיגול Piggul.
before you throw the דם, dam you know, you can't eat the
meat. The you know any animal, any קרבן you can't eat the
meat before the דם dam is thrown. And nevertheless even though the
meat isn't edible,
throwing the דם dam for פיגול Piggul. makes it פיגול. Piggul. So
ואתיא זריקה וקבעה לה בפיגול Ve-Asya Zerika Ve-Kavah Lah Be-Piggul and comes
the זריקה Zerika and says even this דם dam, that until even
though before the זריקה Zerika you couldn't eat it, so in one
way it was already not edible, you could still turn it into
פיגול. Piggul So once that's true then here too when your מחשבה
machshava makes it inedible, makes it פסול, pasul you'll still be able
to go ahead and make it into פיגול. Piggul. Now that is
a crazy comparison to which the גמרא gives the immediate response. ולא
היא. Ve-Lo Hi. Those are not comparable. התם הוא חד מחשבה היא.
Hasam Hu Chad Machshava Hi. there you don't have some other מחשבה
machshava invalidating for some other reason. That's the whole way פיגול Piggul.
works. You know that when you're זורק zorek the דם dam in
a certain way the meat becomes פיגול. Piggul Oh yes you couldn't
eat it because of the law of קדשים. Kodshim. It couldn't be
eaten until the דם dam was being נזרק Nizrak but there was
not another מחשבה machshava that invalidated. There was not something that was
invalidating, there was just it wasn't yet ready to be eaten. Okay?
That's and therefore it can become פיגול. Piggul. הכא תרי מחשבות. Hacha
Trei Machshavos.
Here it's two thoughts. Okay? The thought of, you know, the
מחשבת הינוח Machshavas Hinuach actually actively invalidates, so it can't become פיגול
Piggul. after it has been invalidated. Okay? Makes a lot of sense.
You wonder what רבא Rava was thinking. So רבא's Rava analogy is
not good but we still have the claim that that's true, that
this somehow doesn't have the power to take it out of פיגול.
Piggul, All right? So let's take a look. איתיבי רב הונא לרבי
אבא. Eisevei Rav Huna Le-Rebbi Abba. So רב הונא Rav Huna challenged
רבי אבא's Rebbi Abba claim that it could become
פיגול. Piggul נתנה למעלה למטה למטה למעלה. Nitna Lemala Lemata Lemata Lemala.
So now we had a ברייתא braisa, that says the following: if
you planned on putting the things above below or below above, so
you know doing it in the wrong place, so לאלתר כשר. La'altar
Kasher. So if you had the plan to do it
right away, so that's a thought of, you know, of doing something
that invalidates but it's not a חוץ למקומו Chutz L'Makomo and it's
not a חוץ לזמנו. chutz l'zmano. So the קרבן is כשר. kasher,
Okay? That's a thought of doing something wrong but it's not פיגול,
pigul. it's not חוץ למקומו, Chutz L'Makomo, the קרבן is כשר. kasher
חזר וחישב חוץ למקומו פסול ואין בו כרת. Chozar Ve-Chishev Chutz L'Makomo
Pasul Ve-Ein Bo Kares. Then you had a thought I'm going to
actually be זורק zorek the דם, you know, חוץ למקומו. Chutz L'Makomo.
It's פסול pasul and there's no כרת. Kares. That's your classic חוץ
למקומו. Chutz L'Makomo. חוץ לזמנו פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. Chutz L'Zmano Piggul
Ve-Chayavin Alav Kares. If you instead if after this thought of being
זורק in the wrong place you had the thought about doing it
חוץ לזמנו, chutz l'zmano, since your first thought did absolutely nothing, okay,
then the second thought about חוץ לזמנו chutz l'zmano now can make
it פיגול pigul. and if you eat it you'll get כרת. Kares.
למחר פסול. lamachar pasul. Now, if if that's when your thought about
being זורק הדם zorek hadam was to be זורק הדם zorek hadam
right away in the wrong place, that did zero, and then afterwards
you can come in with a חוץ למקומו chutz l'mikomo or חוץ
לזמנו. chutz l'zmano, Let's say however you had a plan to be
זורק הדם zorek hadam in the wrong place tomorrow. So what effectively
is that? זורק הדם zorek hadam in the wrong place tomorrow. That
is effectively a מחשבת הינוח. machshavas hinuach. Because it's not a מחשבת
פיגול. machshavas pigul. מחשבת פיגול machshavas pigul is מחשבה machshava to be
זורק הדם zorek hadam in the right place tomorrow. So a מחשבה
machshava to be זורק הדם zorek hadam in the wrong place tomorrow
is basically a מחשבה machshava to leave the דם over and to
not use the דם the way it's supposed to be. That's a
מחשבת הינוח. machshavas hinuach. Okay, so what will happen in that case?
פסול. pasul So now it's invalid. Okay, so who says that's פסול?
pasul. That's רבי יהודה. מחשבת הינוח machshavas hinuach by זורק הדם zorek
hadam in the wrong place tomorrow, which is effectively just leaving the
דם over for tomorrow is invalid. So this is רבי יהודה. חוזר
וחישב בין חוץ לזמנו בין חוץ למקומו פסול ואין בו כרת. chozar
v'chishev bein chutz l'zmano bein chutz l'mikomo pasul v'ein bo kores. After
you had this מחשבת הינוח machshavas hinuach to be זורק הדם zorek
hadam in the wrong place tomorrow, you then had a thought of
חוץ למקומו chutz l'mikomo or חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, even a חוץ
לזמנו chutz lizmano, thought, it's only פסול, it does not become פיגול.
pigul פסול ואין בו כרת. pasul v'ein bo kores. You could why?
Because you have already invalidated it. So this ברייתא is very clear.
You plan on leaving it over until the next day, effectively that's
what זורק in the wrong place is like. So it's פסול, that's
רבי יהודה. And once it's פסול, it can't become פיגול. pigul. Okay,
which is what we would totally have expected. תיובתא דרבי אבא תיובתא.
tyuvta d'Rebbi Abba tyuvta. That's a complete contradiction of רבי אבא. Rebbi
Abba. So רבי אבא Rebbi Abba wants to understand that this generic
מחשבה machshava for רבי יהודה is yes it invalidates, but the קרבן
can still become פיגול pigul, and we have a ברייתא that makes
it clear that that is not true. For if it becomes פסול
even for this generic מחשבה, machshava then it is out of the
category of פיגול. pigul.
Okay, אמר רב חסדא, amar Rav Chisda, says רב חסדא, Rav Chisda,
אמר רבינא בר שילא, amar Ravina bar Shila, חישב שיאכלו טמאים למחר
חייב. chishev sheyachalu tmeim lamachar chayav. If you planned on טמא tamei
people would eat it tomorrow, you're חייב. chayav Okay, that's a type
of a meaning that's פיגול, pigul. that's real פיגול. pigul Alright, that's
just like planning that you're going to eat it tomorrow. Now, that's
a little strange cause number one it's, you know, we said before
it's if it relates to other people you can't necessarily control that.
But okay, that's what he says. It's also strange because you would
have said if other people, טמא tamei, people are going to eat
it, they're going to make it פסול and therefore, you know, it's
going to be פסול for a different reason. But again, this is
just your thought. Okay, so since it's just your thought and a
מחשבת אכילה machshavas achila for for the next day, even if it's
a type of a פסול אכילה, pasul achila, that still counts as
a מחשבת אכילה. machshavas achila. So it's interesting also because a מחשבה
machshavah to be זורק הדם in a way that doesn't make the
קרבן כשר, kasher like to be זורק it in the wrong place,
is not a מחשבה machshavah about זריקת הדם. zrikas hadam. Okay, but
a way of eating it in a way that's not a כשר
eating it is a מחשבת אכילה, machshavas achila, which shouldn't totally surprise
us, you know, cause we had before even a discussion of a
dog eating it or a fire eating it. Okay, so that's a
מחשבת אכילה machshavas achila and it's invalid.
אמר רבא, amar Rava, says רבא, Rava, תדע teida you should know
that this is true, דבשר לפני זריקה לא חזי. d'basar lifnei zrika
lo chazi. So רבא Rava again is trying to try to argue
this by analogy. Meat before you're זורק הדם is not fit to
be eaten, similar to what he said before. Okay, וכי מחשב ביה
מיפסל v'chi mchashev bei mipsal and nevertheless, when you have a מחשבה
machshavah about that meat, okay, this meat that's not fit to be
eaten and now you're, you know, planning you have a מחשבה machshava
you're זורק הדם with a מחשבה about חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, you
make the meat, you know, you make the meat פיגול. pigul So
you can make the meat פיגול pigul, even at a time when
the meat is not fit to be eaten. So the same is
true if your thought of פיגול pigul. is to eat it in
a way that's not fit to be eaten. Now, of course it's
a little different. In the normal case, right now the meat isn't
fit to be eaten, but your מחשבה is to eat it in
a way that is normally eaten, you know, eaten by טהור tahor
people. Here your מחשבה is to eat it in a way that's
not normally eaten, which is what the גמרא responds. ולא היא, v'lo
hi, that's not a good comparison. התם זריקה זורק ומיחזי. hasam zrika
zorek u'michzi. There,
in the normal case, you'll be זורק the דם, the meat will
become fit. And the thing that is, you know, the only thing
that is problematic is your plan of tomorrow. הכא לא מיחזי כלל.
hacha lo michzi klal. Here, with your plan to eat it by
טמאים, it's not fit at all. So therefore, you know, that's not
a good analogy, you could easily see that this is not an
acceptable eating, not a type of an eating that is considered the
eating of פיגול, pigul. you know, that would actually make it a
problem. Alright, now תוספות says you'd have to distinguish if you would
say this wasn't a problem. You'd have to distinguish this from the
case of let's say the dogs or the fire, but here the
difference is clear, here because you make it טמא, tamei there it
might not be eating by a טהור tahor person the way meat
of קרבנות korbanos, is supposed to be eaten, but it's still the
meat is being eaten. Here, without it being פסול for another reason.
Here, if it's being eaten by a טמא tamei. person, it's becoming
פסול because it's being handled by the טמא tamei. person before it's
being eaten, and for that reason it is not, one could claim,
this is the question, that it is not a מחשבה that could
make it into פיגול. pigul. All right, by the way, it occurs
to me that if רבא Rava was going to make an analogy,
he'd had a better analogy. He could have say any מחשבה to
eat the meat חוץ לזמנו, the meat is already invalid because of
נותר. nosar. So that's what he should have said. That's a case
where the meat is actually invalid at the time of eating. If
you think about it, every מחשבה of אכילה חוץ לזמנו achila chutz
lizmano is מחשבה of eating meat that's already invalid because of נותר.
nosar. Again, that's the natural case, here it's invalid for an external
reason. All right, so that's the question whether מחשבה of אכילת טמאים
achilas tmeiyim would make it invalid. אמר רב
חסדא, Amar Rav Chisda, מרגלא בפומי' דרב דימי, Margla befumei de-Rav Dimi,
it was a pearl in the mouth of רב דימי. Rav Dimi.
רב דימי Rav Dimi used to like saying רב חנינא, Rav Chanina,
רבינא בר חנינא, Ravina bar Chanina, בשר פסח שלא הוצלה ולחמי תודה
שלא הורמו חייבין עליהם משום טומאה. Bassar Pesach shelo hutzla v'lachmei todah
shelo hurmu chayavin aleihem mishum tumah. Okay, we're bringing now the only
reason this is relevant is because רבא Rava is again going to
say a תדע, teda, you should know this is true. Okay, and
then we reject רבא's Rava's analogies or רבא's Rava's proofs. Okay, so
he said the הלכה halacha is is that a if somebody is
טמא, tamei we had this just a few days ago and eats
the meat of קרבנות, you're חייב כרת. chayav kares. Okay, but that's
only after the זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam, the כרת, kares, only once
the meat is considered fit to be eaten. Let's say there was
זריקת הדם, zrikas hadam, but the meat still wasn't fit to be
eaten. Would a טמא person be חייב כרת? chayav kares? Why would
it not be fit to be eaten? For some external reason. What
would that external reason be? So בשר פסח שלא הוצלה. bassar Pesach
shelo hutzla. You have the meat of a פסח, Pesach, the דם
was being נזרק, nizrak, but it hasn't been roasted. So it's אסור
assur to eat because of the לאו lav of לא תאכלו ממנו
נא. lo sochlu mimenu na. And this person is טמא. So does
he get כרת kares for eating בשר קדשים bassar kodashim and he's
טמא and it's קדשים kodashim that's fit to be eaten from their
זריקת דם קדשים zrikas dam kodashim perspective, but not fit to be
eaten from their קרבן פסח Pesach perspective? That's one case. And the
other is ולחמי
תודה שלא הורמו. u-lachmei todah shelo hurmu. You have the breads of
the תודה todah and you give one out of each ten to
a כהן, kohen, and it's sort of like תרומה, terumah, and before
you do it, you're not allowed to eat the bread. But before
the blood of the קרבן of the תודה todah was thrown, you
couldn't eat the bread for a קדשים kodashim reason. It was seen
as one with the קרבן and it wasn't like the מתיר matir
wasn't offered up yet. So here the מתיר matir was offered up,
the bread is fit to be eaten from a קדשים kodashim perspective,
but not fit to be eaten from a תרומה terumah perspective. Okay,
so in that case are you חייב כרת chayav kares or not?
And he said חייבין עליהם משום טומאה. chayavin aleihem mishum tumah. Yes,
you are חייב chayav since they're fit to be eaten from a
קדשים kodashim perspective. This other thing that makes it אסור assur does
not take it out of the category
of a טמא person eating קדשים kodashim that is fit to be
eaten. Okay, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רבא Rava said תדע teda you
should know this is true, דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
אשר לה'. asher la-Hashem. Okay, so the פסוק pasuk says והנפש אשר
תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים אשר לה' וטומאתו עליו ונכרתה. ve-hanefesh asher tochal
bassar mizevach hashelamim asher la-Hashem v'tumaso alav venichrasa. Okay,
so if you eat the meat and your טומאה tumah is on
you, you will be cut off. אשר לה' לרבות אימורי קדשי קלים
לטומאה. Asher la-Hashem lerabos imurei kodshi kalim l'tumah. That that אשר לה'
asher la-Hashem is that not only the meat, but even if you
eat the אימורים after the blood was נזרק nizrak and you're טמא,
the אימורים that go on the מזבח, mizbeiach you also are חייב
כרת chayav kares for eating it בטומאה. be-tumah. Okay, so what do
you see from that? אלמא אף על גב דלאו בני אכילה נינהו,
Alama af al gav delav bnei achila ninhu, אימורים are not stuff
that's fit to be eaten, it's not only not fit because it's
mostly disgusting, but also it's אסור assur to be eaten, it has
to be offered on to the מזבח. mizbeiach, חייבין עליה משום טומאה.
chayavin aleha mishum tumah. You're חייב chayav for טומאה tumah because once
the מתיר matir and the blood was thrown, you're now חייב chayav
for כרת kares if you're טמא when you eat it. So הכא
נמי אף על גב דלאו בני אכילה נינהו. hacha nami af al
gav delav bnei achila ninhu. Here too, even though they're not fit
to be eaten, the meat of the פסח pesach and the bread,
חייבין עליה משום טומאה. chayavin aleha mishum tumah. Once the blood has
been thrown, you're still חייב if you're טמא. So that's another analogy
that רבא Rava makes, and the גמרא once again rejects it. ולא
היא, V'lo hi, it's not a good comparison. התם אימורי קדשי קלים
חזו לגבוה. Hasam imurei kodshi kalim chazu legavoah.
There once נזרק הדם, nizrak hadam, the אימורים are now totally fit
for what they were intended. They're fit to be put on to
the מזבח, mizbeiach, even though they're not fit for you. But they've
reached their final state. And therefore you're חייב if you're טמא. לאפוקי
בשר פסח שלא נצלה L'afukei basar pesach shelo nitzla ולחמי תודה שלא
הורמו, v'lachmei todah shelo hurmu,
as opposed to the פסח meat that hasn't been roasted or the
breads that have not, you know, one thing has not been given,
in those cases, yes, the blood has been thrown and as a
קורבן korban it's, you know, in the state as from קדשים kodshim
perspective it's fit to be eaten. But nevertheless, דלא חזו לא לגבוה
ולא להדיוט, delo chazu lo legavoah velo lehediot, in their current state,
even though their קורבן korban state קדושה kedusha sort of has transformed
somewhat, in their current state they are not fit to be eaten
either for the מזבח mizbeiach. or for human, and since it's not
yet fit for human consumption, you could say it is not included
in the חיוב כרת chiyuv kares for being טמא when you consume
it. Okay, הדרן עלך כל הפסולים, Hadran alach Kol Hapsulim, so that
is the end of the פרק כל הפסולים, Perek Kol Hapsulim, which
is pretty much all about פיגול. pigul, Let's just begin the start
with the משנה of the next פרק. Okay, and we're not yet
out of פיגול. pigul. So, בית שמאי אומרים, Beis Shammai omrim, בית
שמאי Beis Shammai says, כל הניתנים על מזבח החיצון שנתן במתנה אחת
כיפר. kol hanitannim al mizbeiach hachitzon shenasan b'matanah achas kiper. Now, so
this looks like we're now talking about the general עבודה avodah of
קורבנות korbanot and we're out of פיגול, pigul, but don't get your
hopes up too soon. So בית שמאי Beis Shammai says, anything that
is the blood that is thrown on the outside מזבח, mizbeiach meaning
all the קורבנות, korbanot, you're supposed to throw, the תורה Torah says
סביב, saviv, וזרקו בני אהרן את הדם סביב, v'zarku benei Aharon es
hadam saviv, you know, את דמו סביב, es damo saviv, you throw
the blood, it sounds like a ring around the whole מזבח, mizbeiach,
but חז"ל Chazal understand that it is two, you know, diagonal corners,
so it hits all four walls by throwing it at two, call
two corners that are diagonal from one another. So let's say you
threw it only at one corner, not at two. Let's say you
only put it on one side, on one wall, you didn't even
have it hit both both walls on the one corner. Nevertheless, as
long as you did one placement of blood, כיפר, then בדיעבד bedieved
the קורבן korban is okay. Okay, we'll learn from we'll learn in
the גמרא what פסוק you learn it from, but that's the teaching.
בדיעבד Bedieved even one, even one placement is okay. ובחטאת, Uvechatas, now
a חטאת is supposed to be four corners, you know, by placing
with blood with your finger, not throwing the blood. שתי מתנות, Shtei
matanos, there בדיעבד bedieved since it's four things, בדיעבד bedieved you need
two to be בדיעבד כשר. bedieved kasher. That's בית שמאי's Beis Shammai
position. ובית הלל אומרים, Uveis Hillel omrim, and בית הלל Beis Hillel
says, אף חטאת שניתנה במתנה אחת כיפר, af chatas shenitnah b'matanah achas
kiper, even a חטאת just putting one, you know, one corner suffices.
Okay, so this is a general debate, בדיעבד, bedieved, what counts as
putting the blood on the מזבח. mizbeach But as I said, we're
being introducing it in this משנה not for its own sake, but
to talk about its implications for פיגול. pigul, לפיכך, L'fichach, therefore, אם
נתן את הראשונה כתיקנה והשנייה חוץ לזמנה כיפר.
im nasan es
harishonah ketiknah vehashniyah chutz lizmanah kiper. If you put the first application
of blood, you know, by all the קורבנות korbanot according to בית
הלל Beis Hillel or by anything other than a חטאת according to
בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, where one application suffices. So the first application
you did in the right way, כתיקנה, ketiknah, as it was supposed
to. Then if the rest of the throwing of the blood or
the putting on the corners you did with a thought of פיגול,
pigul. the
והשנייה חוץ לזמנה כיפר, vehashniyah chutz lizmanah kiper, the קורבן korban is
still כשר, okay, and it doesn't become פיגול, pigul because as soon
as you did the one placement, now the קורבן korban is כשר
and after the קורבן korban is כשר you cannot retroactively make it
פסול. Even though the remaining placement is still part of the זריקת
הדם zrikas hadam or the נתינת הדם nesinas hadam and you could
say that when you keep on doing it, it still defines the
קורבן, korban, no, once you did what was minimally required, everything that
comes afterwards is a מצווה mitzvah to do but does not define
the nature of the קורבן. korban. You were already the קורבן korban
was already valid. ואם נתן את הראשונה חוץ לזמנה והשנייה חוץ למקומה,
V'im nasan es harishonah chutz lizmanah vehashniyah chutz limkomah, now let's say
the first application of blood was חוץ לזמנה, chutz lizmanah, it became
פיגול. pigul. And the next one was חוץ למקומה, chutz limkomah, so
normally, if in the process of blood you had a חוץ לזמנה
chutz lizmanah thought and then a חוץ למקומה chutz limkomah thought, the
second מחשבה takes it out of פיגול pigul because it's another מחשבה
that invalidates. But here, it doesn't do that. פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת.
Pigul vechayavin alav kares. It is it remains פיגול. pigul Why? Because
after that first application of blood, it's done. It's not like שחיטה
shechitah it, catching the blood, walking it, throwing it where you're still
in process. There a later מחשבה of חוץ למקומה chutz limkomah can
take it out of the פיגול pigul. category. But here, once you
got to the מזבח mizbeach, and you did one מתנה, matanah, the
קורבן korban is done and anything afterwards is now extra credit, is
no longer affects the status of the קורבן. korban. So it cannot
get it out of פיגול pigul? either. Okay, כל הניתנים על מזבח
הפנימי, Kol hanitannim al mizbeiach hapnimy, now, כל הניתנים על מזבח הפנימי,
Kol hanitannim al mizbeiach hapnimy,
all of the blood that is put on the inner מזבח, an
inner חטאת, שאם חיסר אחת מן המתנות כאילו לא כיפר. she'im chisar
achas min hamatanos k'ilu lo kiper. There the הלכה halacha is everybody
agrees that if you're missing even one of the four corners, it's
not good. Every one of the four corners is essential for the
קורבן korban to be good. Okay, לפיכך, L'fichach, therefore, נתן כולן כתיקנה
ואחת שלא כתיקנה פסולה ואין בו כרת. nasan kullan ketiknah v'achas shelo
ketiknah psulah v'ein bo kares. If you did three of them the
right way and one of them חוץ לזמנה chutz lizmanah or חוץ
למקומה, chutz limkomah, you have invalidated. Even if it's the last one,
the כפרה kaparah is not done, so you've invalidated it, but it's
not פיגול. pigul. It says אין בו כרת. ein bo kares. Why
is it not פיגול? pigul Let's say you did three of the
corners of the inner מזבח right and the fourth one
חוץ לזמנו, with the thought of חוץ לזמנו, it's not פיגול. pigul?
Why? Because since all four are part of one act, okay, this
is if you remember the גמרא discussed before whether מפגלין בחצי מתיר.
mifaglin bechatzi matir. So there was a discussion of when you're שוחט
shochet the animal, you know, and you cut the windpipe and the
trachea and is a מחשבה of פיגול pigul on part of an
act enough to make it פיגול? pigul And the תנא of this
משנה says no. Since yes, it was a פיגול pigul. thought, but
it was only on a quarter of the four, you know, one
of the four acts that is considered the זריקה, zrika, the putting
of the דם on the מזבח, and therefore a פיגול pigul. thought
for part of a מכפר mechaper does not make it פיגול. Part
of a מתיר matir does not make it פיגול. Okay, we will
continue with this tomorrow.