בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף י״ז, daf Yud-Zayin,
30th day in the עומר, Omer, 30th day in
March, April, whatever, oh my god, months just fly, don't they?
True. All right, 30th day in April. We pick up two lines
from the top of י״ז עמוד א׳ Yud-Zayin Amud Aleph where we're
going through all of the various people and their states that when
you're in a particular state or their status that when that would
invalidate the קרבנות korbanot if they're, you know, when they're in that
state. So we went through the beginning of the משנה, Mishnah, the
non-כהן, Kohen,
somebody who is an אונן, Onein, somebody who immediately suffered a death,
and now we move over to a טבול יום, Tevul Yom, somebody
who has been טמא, Tamei, gone to the מקווה Mikvah and is
waiting for nightfall to become totally טהור. Tahor. Okay, טבול יום, Tevul
Yom, and I should mention that from the פסוק pasuk וינזרו מקדשי
בני ישראל ולא יחללו Veyinazru mikodeshei benei Yisrael velo yehallelu we say
that that's talking about a normal טמא Tamei person, that if he
does the עבודה avoda he violates, he desecrates it. And now we
want to know about a טבול יום. Tevul Yom. So two lines
from the top of י״ז עמוד
א׳, Yud-Zayin Amud Aleph, טבול יום מנלן, Tevul yom minalan, where do
you know this from? דתניא רבי סימאי אומר, De-tanya Rabbi Simai omer,
רמז לטבול יום שאם עבד חילל מנלן? Remez le-tevul yom she-im avad
hillel minalan? Where's a hint to the idea that if a טבול
יום, Tevul Yom, somebody who's gone to the מקווה Mikvah that day
and is waiting for nightfall, that if he did the עבודה avoda
he desecrated it? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, the verse says, excuse
me, קדשים יהיו לאלהיהם ולא
יחללו שם אלהיהם כי את אשי ה׳ הם מקריבים והיו קדש.
Kedoshim yihyu leloheihem velo
yehallelu shem eloheihem ki et ishei Hashem hem makrivim vehayu kodesh.
So
they should be holy to their Gods and they should not desecrate,
you know, the bread of God, so to their Gods. So therefore
it shows, so what does it show you about a טבול יום?
Tevul Yom? I mean that shows that, you know, if you're in
a certain state that's not fully holy you can violate the עבודה,
avoda, but how does that tell you the idea of a טבול
יום? Tevul Yom? So it says אם אינו ענין לטמא, im eino
inyan le-Tamei, so we don't need it to, so normally
presumably the thing that's most obviously contradicts the idea of קדושה, kedushah,
holiness, is טומאה, tumah, but if somebody is a, so maybe that's
suggested by the verse that if they're טמא Tamei they desecrate it.
But טמא Tamei itself we know from the פסוק pasuk דנפיק מוינזרו,
de-nafik mi-veyinazru,
we learned it from the פסוק pasuk וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל, Veyinazru
mikodeshei benei Yisrael, okay, ולא יחללו. velo yehallelu. So
from there we learn, separate when you're טמא. Tamei. So this פסוק
pasuk that's pretty generic and it can't be talking about full טמא
Tamei because we already know full טמא, Tamei, what's it coming to
teach me? תנהו ענין לטבול יום, Tena-u inyan le-tevul yom, talk about
somebody who was טמא Tamei and it's not totally done with the
טומאה, tumah, has gone to the מקווה Mikvah and it's not nightfall.
So again, not a very clear פסוק, pasuk, an extra פסוק pasuk
and therefore we are coming to add this case of somebody who
has still a little bit of טומאה tumah left. What's the moral
point? קדשים יהיו. Kedoshim yihyu. Okay, well not clear what the קדושה
kedushah means, but the גמרא Gemara does say if you want to
know what the קדושה kedushah means, why not look at the פסוק
pasuk right before it? So the גמרא Gemara says אימא תנהו ענין
לקורח קרחה ולמשחית פאת זקן. eima tena-u inyan le-kore-ach korchah u-mash-chis pa-as
zakan. So
it says לא יקרחו קרחה בראשם ופאת זקנם לא יגלחו ובבשרם לא
ישרטו שרטת, lo yikrechu korchah berosham u-feas zakanam lo yegalechu u-vivesaram lo
yisretu saretet, right?
Do not make a bald spot, do not make an incision in
the flesh,
do not cut, you know, the corners of the beard, and then
it says קדשים יהיו ולא יחללו. Kedoshim yihyu velo yehallelu. Okay, you
should be holy and should not desecrate. Now that is very strange,
of course, because we normally assume that if somebody who does that,
they violate an obligation of the כהונה, kehunah, some of these are
not also just limited to כהונה, kehunah, but we never have seen
this to create a lasting status on the person that after having
done this, you know, it would cause them to desecrate the sacrifice
if they have now made some incision on the flesh let's say.
But the גמרא Gemara says as long as you're reading the פסוק,
pasuk, that's what's juxtaposed. So let's say that a כהן Kohen who
made, I don't know, an incision on the flesh or a bald
spot on the head and now does the עבודה avoda desecrates it.
So the גמרא Gemara says no,
because here's the answer how we know it's not what it's talking
about. Because טבול יום דאם עבד במיתה מנלן? Tevul yom de-im avad
be-misah minalan? How do you know, says the גמרא, Gemara, because I'll
tell you we know to read טבול יום Tevul Yom into the
פסוק pasuk based on a different sort of דרשה. drasha. How do
you know that if somebody does the עבודה avoda because there's always
two different questions: how do you know they're prohibited to do it
in this state? And how do you know that they actually desecrate
the עבודה? avoda? And within the category of how do you know
they're prohibited, what is the weight of the prohibition? What is the
weight of the transgression? So גמרא Gemara says let's put aside for
a moment the idea that if they do it they desecrate it.
How do you know this הלכה halakhah that if somebody is a
טבול יום Tevul Yom and they do the עבודה avoda that they're
deserving of death? Now it does not mean death by the court,
most of the deaths in the context of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash is like מיתה בידי שמים. misa bidei Shamayim. But how do
you know that that's a punishment that's deserving of that? So טבול
יום
דאם עבד עבודה במיתה מנלן, Tevul yom de-im avad avodah be-misah minalan,
where do you know it? דגמיר חילול חילול מתרומה. de-gamir hillul hillul
mi-terumah. Okay, we learn it from תרומה terumah because by תרומה terumah
the פסוק pasuk says, it says what's the פסוק? pasuk? It says
ומתו בו כי יחללהו u-masu vo ki yehallelu-hu that they will die
by the תרומה terumah if they desecrate it and from that somehow
not being explicated
here.
ומתו בו כי יחללהו u'meisu vo ki y'chalaluhu and that's how we
know and now we're just going to assume, not show how we
know, that this is talking about a case of a תבול יום
t'vul yom among other things. Okay, so a תבול יום t'vul yom
who eats תרומה, terumah, okay, this is תרומה terumah and this is
קדשים. kodshim.
Okay, so we know, I should be using different colors. Anyway, a
תבול יום t'vul yom that eats תרומה terumah is deserving of death.
So therefore we say, ah, so since we have יחללו יחללו, y'chalalu
y'chalalu, we're going to say, whoops, that a תבול יום t'vul yom
that does the עבודה avodah is also deserving of
מיתה בידי שמים.
misah bi'yedei shamayim. What?
קדושים יהיו, kedoshim yihyu, ולא יחללו, v'lo y'chalalu, thank you. Okay, so
anyway, so now we know that a תבול יום t'vul yom who
eats תרומה terumah is חייב מיתה בידי שמים chayav misah bi'yedei shamayim
and a תבול יום t'vul yom who does the עבודה avodah is
חייב מיתה בידי שמים, chayav misah bi'yedei shamayim, but once this פסוק
pasuk here is getting us a תבול יום t'vul yom up into
this פסוק pasuk from תרומה terumah up into this פסוק pasuk by
קדשים, kodshim, we're also going to learn that if he does the
עבודה avodah he violates it, then, then not only is he חייב
מיתה בידי שמים chayav misah bi'yedei shamayim based on this link, but
once we've sort of imported תבול יום t'vul yom up here, we're
also going to learn that he, that he invalidates the עבודה. avodah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
One minute, let's read it. Okay, so דגמר חילול חילול מתרומה. d'gamar
chillul chillul mi'trumah. So therefore we're going to conclude דפסול בתרומה מחל
עבודה. d'pasul bi'trumah mechal avodah. Somebody who invalidates תרומה, terumah, you know,
also, you know,
who invalidates the עבודה. avodah. דלא פסול בתרומה, d'lo pasul bi'trumah, somebody
who's not invalidate תרומה, terumah, לא מחל עבודה lo mechal avodah does
not invalidate the עבודה. avodah. Now it's not exactly a complete identity.
Somebody for example sitting is not פסול בתרומה pasul bi'trumah and does
invalidate the עבודה. avodah. Whatever, but the basic point being and you
know the שיטה מקובצת Shittah Mekubetzet even asks a stronger question. The
שיטה מקובצת Shittah Mekubetzet says that a תבול יום t'vul yom actually
himself does not פוסל בתרומה, posel bi'trumah, which is like, which is
seems to be the exact opposite of what we're saying. But we're
just going to sort of say bracket that and basically say that
through this link we're going to import תבול יום t'vul yom here
and therefore, yes, this פסוק pasuk is a little bit vague but
through the link of תרומה terumah we're going to read תבול יום
t'vul yom in and say that that's how we know that a
תבול יום t'vul yom invalidates the עבודה. avodah. Yes Michael.
It seems to me clear that it's just a more general point.
Like, you know, we just had קדושים kedoshim before, קדושים תהיו, kedoshim
tihyu, קדוש אני השם אלוקיכם. kadosh ani Hashem Elokeichem. It doesn't say
that it means בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael can't be תבולי יום, t'vulei
yom, you know, so it's like, it's like, you know, you do
all these sorts of things.
I understand, but the חז"ל Chazal want to read the פסוקים pesukim
as about הלכה. halacha. What does יחללו y'chalalu mean? So I don't
understand. If you don't act in a lofty way you're מחלל mechalel
the עבודה? avodah?
It's ולא יחללו שם אלוהיהם. v'lo y'chalalu shem Elokeihem. That's what it's
saying, like don't desecrate God's name through your actions, through bad way
of living, which entails like a bunch of these things.
Okay, that is correct that ולא יחללו v'lo y'chalalu is more about
the name of God than the קרבנות. korbanos. You are correct. The
גמרא Gemara is reading this in a very specific, concrete הלכתי halachic
way. You are correct that that's not the פשט pshat of the
פסוק. pasuk. Okay, so anyway, that's how we get תבול יום. t'vul
yom. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. As you can
see there's a very long תוספות Tosafos because it's not exactly clear
how we read תבול יום t'vul yom into these פסוקים pesukim exactly
but anyway, we're going to move on. Okay, אמר רבא למה לי
דכתב רחמנא טמא ותבול יום ומחוסר כפורים? Amar Rava lama li d'chtav
Rachmana tamei u't'vul yom u'mechussar kippurim? So we have three people that
are invalidated from, that if they do the עבודה, avodah, they invalidate
it. A טמא tamei which we learned out from וינזרו, v'yinazzru, a
תבול יום t'vul yom that we learn out from קדושים יהיו, kedoshim
yihyu, and a מחוסר כפורים, mechussar kippurim, somebody who has not brought
the קרבן korban the next day, like somebody let's say a זב
zav went through a process of טהרה tahara that took seven days
and he's supposed to bring the קרבן korban on the eighth day
and before he brought the קרבן. korban. So why did the תורה
Torah have to tell me that all three of these people invalidate
the עבודה? avodah? Just tell me one and I could learn out
the other two. Especially if you tell me like it would seem
like the weakest is the מחוסר כפורים. mechussar kippurim. He had his,
you know, he went through a process, he went through the מקוה,
mikveh, the only thing missing is the קרבן, korban, he has the
weakest level of טומאה. tumah. Just tell me he invalidates the קרבנות
korbanos and I'll figure out the other guys. Now רש"י Rashi by
the way points out that that the question is really not, not
exactly the way it's framed because the תורה Torah could not have
not said the case of טמא. tamei. Because since the תורה Torah
doesn't explicitly label תבול יום, t'vul yom, it doesn't explicitly say מחוסר
כפורים mechussar kippurim like we just did above. Well since we already
know that a טמא tamei is פסול, pasul, the extra פסוק pasuk
is coming to teach me that even a תבול יום t'vul yom
is פסול. pasul. So therefore if the תורה Torah had just said
one of them, right, I would have automatically assumed it was talking
about a טמא. tamei. Okay so obviously the תורה Torah sort of
had to get the idea of a pure טמא tamei person out
of the way, okay, and then I would have, and then the
extra פסוקים pesukim are coming to teach me even a תבול יום,
t'vul yom, even a מחוסר כפורים. mechussar kippurim. But anyway, but once
I know, why couldn't it have just said, excuse me, once I
could have just said we were talking about a תבול יום, t'vul
yom, I mean about a real טמא, tamei, which I needed to
start labeling. as the baseline, you know, obviously because I wouldn't have,
you know I had to start with real טמא tameh and tell
me one of the others. Why did I need all three? Just
tell me two, is the question. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. מה הצד. Ma hatzad. Well, basically. Okay. But the real question
is מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim because מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim is a
guy that the טומאה tumah is very, is very, is very, you
know, just a vestige of it. So why if I already, you
know, just tell me מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim and I could have
figured out טבול יום. tvul yom. So let's take a look. Okay.
למה לי דכתב רחמנא טמא טבול יום ומחוסר כיפורים? Lama li d'katav
rachmana tameh tvul yom u'mechusar kippurim? צריכי, Tzrichi, you need all three.
דכתב רחמנא טמא, D'katav rachmana tameh, had it just sent טמא, tameh,
obviously I wouldn't have gotten to the weaker cases. I would have
said, דכתב רחמנא טמא, d'katav rachmana tameh, שכן מטמא, she'ken metameh, that
that he causes טומאה tumah to other people. It's a higher level
of טומאה. tumah. Okay, בטבול יום, b'tvul yom, so בטבול יום, b'tvul
yom, מחוסר כיפורים לא אתי מיניה. mechusar kippurim lo ati minei. Now
if it had just said the case of the טבול יום, tvul
yom, I couldn't have inferred
a מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kippurim, why? שכן פוסל בתרומה. She'ken posel b'trumah.
A טבול יום tvul yom like we just said a minute ago,
a טבול יום tvul yom effectively has the status of a שני.
sheni. Okay, you know, a person who is originally טמא tameh has
a status depending on how he got טמא, tameh, an אב av
or a ראשון. rishon. A טבול יום tvul yom has the level
of a שני, sheni, two degrees removed, and a טבול יום tvul
yom ability is only to be מטמא תרומה. metameh trumah. He can't
be מטמא metameh normal non-sanctified things. Okay, so basically you have, here,
just so you sort of, okay, here you've got the guy who's
the אב הטומאה. av hatumah. The אב הטומאה av hatumah is I
don't know let's say he's like a זב. zav. Okay, he's somebody
that experienced טומאה tumah himself. Okay, he touches something, okay he touches
food or whatever, that food is a ראשון. rishon. Okay, now that
food which is one degree removed, okay or it's a, whatever it
is, or it's a כלי kli or whatever it is, or it's
a person, okay, those things are all one degree removed. Now they,
if they touch something, the only thing they can be מטמא metameh
now is food, okay, שני, sheni, it's two degrees removed. That's חולין.
chulin. Okay, and this is all חולין chulin even if it's non-sanctified.
After it's two degrees removed, okay, the only thing now it can
be מטמא metameh is תרומה. trumah. תרומה Trumah can become a שלישי.
shelishi. Well, yes. And then תרומה trumah and all of these are
only food can only be מטמא קדשים. metameh kodshim. Okay, so the
holier something is, the more it could become, the more removed it
can become and still become טמא. tameh. Now if this זב zav
himself, okay, basically
goes through a process of the זב zav of the seven days,
let's say he goes through a טהרה taharah process, he waits his
seven days, okay, and now he's, you know, goes to the מקוה,
mikvah, here, here are some nice מקוה mikvah waters, okay, here he
is floating in the מקוה, mikvah, okay, anyway, okay, then after he
goes to the מקוה, mikvah, he now is a טבול יום. tvul
yom. He's a טבול יום tvul yom and he's like which is
basically like a שני. sheni. Okay, okay, means that he can now
be מטמא תרומה. metameh trumah. Okay, that's on day seven. On day
eight,
here day eight,
he's going to bring his קרבן. korban. That's his that's my idea
of a קרבן. korban. Okay here he is in the בית המקדש
beis hamikdash with his with his with his קרבן, korban, whatever. Okay
anyway he's bringing his קרבן. korban. Before he brings his קרבן, korban,
okay, after nightfall, okay, after night, this is the night, after night
he stops being a טבול יום tvul yom and he now goes
to be a
מחוסר כיפורים. mechusar kippurim. Until he brings his קרבן, korban, he he
מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim means he's lacking his קרבן. korban. And his
status there, okay, as a טבול יום tvul yom his status is
approximately that of a שני. sheni. As a מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim
his status is approximately that of a שלישי. shelishi. He can only
be like מטמא קדשים metameh kodshim he can't be מטמא תרומה. metameh
trumah. Okay so that's basically how he progresses. So the גמרא Gemara
says that had I,
so what did the גמרא Gemara say, if לא לכתוב רחמנא, lo
lichtov rachmana, so, so לא, lo, so if it had written,
where were we, מחוסר כיפורים לא אתי מיניה שכן פוסל בתרומה. mechusar
kippurim lo ati minei she'ken posel b'trumah. If it had just said
that this guy is invalidates when he's after the מקוה mikvah when
he's waiting for nightfall when he's a טבול יום, tvul yom, you
couldn't have said this guy because he is effectively a שני, sheni,
he invalidates תרומה. trumah. After nightfall when he's just a מחוסר כיפורים
mechusar kippurim he doesn't invalidate תרומה. trumah. He's like a שלישי. shelishi.
He only invalidates קדשים. kodshim. So if it just said this guy
was טמא tameh what invalidated a a קרבן, korban, I couldn't have
assumed that by after nightfall he would invalidate a קרבן, korban, that's
even a weaker טומאה. tumah. The real question is tell me this
guy invalidates and then certainly this guy. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: במחוסר כיפורים טבול יום לא אתי מיניה b'mechusar kippurim
tvul yom lo ati minei had it just written it by the
guy who has yet to bring his קרבן korban on day eight,
I couldn't have learned out the טבול יום, tvul yom, why not?
שכן מחוסר מעשה. she'ken mechusar ma'aseh. Because this guy, although his טומאה
tumah is weaker, the thing standing between him and becoming totally טהור
tahor is bringing And that's like a bigger obstacle, whereas if you've
gone to the מקוה mikvah now, not everybody needs a קרבן korban
the next day, right? This is a guy who was
a בעל קרי. Ba'al Keri. This is a guy
who was a זב, Zav, right? Let's say the guy wasn't a
זב, Zav, let's say well בעל קרי Ba'al Keri actually also is
a what do you call it? Is a ראשון, Rishon, but okay.
Anyway, let's say the guy rather than being a זב, Zav, a
זב, Zav, let's say the guy here... what... okay, if the guy's
בעל קרי Ba'al Keri down here, okay, so if he's a בעל
קרי, Ba'al Keri, he saw a seminal emission, he starts his טומאה
tumah as a ראשון, Rishon, okay, or I don't know, let's say
he touched a נבלה, neveilah, whatever he did, okay, and then he
goes, he doesn't wait seven days, he goes that day, he goes
to the מקוה, mikvah, okay, here he is in the מקוה mikvah
that day, okay, and then this is all on day one,
and then before while he's waiting for nightfall after going to the
מקוה, mikvah, this is the night, right? He's a טבול יום, Tevul
Yom, and then as soon as the night happens, he is totally
טהור. tahor. Okay, so this guy, when he doesn't have a seven-day
process, he's never going to have to bring a קרבן, korban, when
he's in the status of טבול יום Tevul Yom waiting for the
nightfall, the only thing standing between him and being totally טהור tahor
is the sun setting, it'll happen all by itself. So even though
his level of טומאה tumah is higher than this guy's, if you
had just told me this guy was פסול, pasul, invalidated the קרבנות,
korbanot, I wouldn't have known this guy invalidated the קרבנות, korbanot, because
this guy needs a קרבן korban to change his status. This guy
just needs to wait. So I might have thought he invalidates the
קרבנות, korbanot, and obviously if he's in this process and he's this
guy, he's going to need both nighttime and a קרבן. korban. So
anyway, this guy invalidates because you've got the obstacle of a קרבן,
korban, but this guy maybe doesn't because all you need is nightfall.
So therefore, you had to tell me both this guy and this
guy invalidate a קרבן. korban. Okay, so,
now,
now, שכן מחוסר מעשה, sheken mechusar ma'aseh, מחדא לא אתי. michada lo
ati. You couldn't have gotten it from one of them. Either, now,
תיתי מחדא מתרתי, teisi michada mitarti, learn it out from two, from
but one, you know, you have three, just say two and figure
out the third. ובהאי לא ליכתוב רחמנא, uvhai lo lichtov rachmana, which
should it not write? לא ליכתוב במחוסר כיפורים ותיתי מהנך, lo lichtov
bimechusar kippurim veteisi mehannach,
don't write it for מחוסר כיפורים mechusar kippurim and learn it from
טבול יום Tevul Yom and normal טמא. tamei. No. מה להנך שכן
פסולים בתרומה? mah lehannach sheken psulim biterumah?
Those two have a higher level, a normal טמא tamei and a
טבול יום Tevul Yom are still invalidate תרומה. terumah. מחוסר כיפורים Mechusar
kippurim is the weakest level. אלא לא ליכתוב רחמנא בטבול יום ותיתי
מהנך. ela lo lichtov rachmana betevul yom veteisi mehannach. So
don't write it by טבול יום, Tevul Yom, write it by a
normal טמא tamei and by a מחוסר כיפורים. mechusar kippurim. דמאי פרכת?
demai parchat? What are you going to say? מה להנך שכן מחוסר
מעשה? mah lehannach sheken mechusar ma'aseh? So you're going to say, ah,
if you had just said טמא, tamei, the case of טמא, tamei,
a טמא tamei and the case of מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kippurim, I
would have said well, those two both need a מעשה. ma'aseh. This
guy's מעשה ma'aseh is dunking in the מקוה, mikvah, and this guy's
מעשה ma'aseh is bringing a קרבן. korban. So I can't from those
two know the case of a טבול יום Tevul Yom that just
needs to wait. Okay, so maybe I couldn't have learned it from
those two. Right, this is the טמא tamei guy, he still needs
to dunk in the מקוה. mikvah. This is the מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar
kippurim, he still needs to bring a קרבן. korban. So I can't
infer from those the case of the טבול יום Tevul Yom that
just needs to wait till nightfall. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
no, סוף סוף קלישות טומאתן. sof sof klishus tumasan. No, nevertheless you
could have learned it from these two, because this guy's טומאה tumah
is weaker. So even though he needs a מעשה, ma'aseh, his טומאה
tumah has gotten to a weaker state. Now of course, you understand
the point? Like I could have learned it out
from
טמא tamei and טבול יום, Tevul Yom, I would have said this
guy's פסול, pasul, this guy's פסול, pasul, so certainly the guy in
the middle, the טבול יום, Tevul Yom, should be פסול. pasul. Of
course, the problem is that these two guys are פסול, pasul, but
they, you know, but they need an act to change the status.
He has to dunk in the מקוה mikvah and he has to
bring a קרבן. korban. So how do I learn out the טבול
יום Tevul Yom that doesn't need an act? Well the גמרא Gemara
says okay, but even though he needs an act, he doesn't need
an act, this guy has a weaker טומאה, tumah, it's much more
residual. But once that's true, just learn straight from this guy, right?
Say this guy has the weakest טומאה, tumah, if he's invalid, certainly
this guy whose טומאה tumah is stronger. So again, it's not exactly
clear why the גמרא Gemara thinks that because you threw this guy
in, that it's now you're more able to learn out the טבול
יום Tevul Yom case. The way שיטה מקובצת Shitu Mekubetzis explains it
is he says the following: he says the following, he says the
act here is not the same meaning of the act here. Act
here is just going to the
מקוה. mikvah. That's just a weakening of the טומאה. tumah. Okay, the
act here is a bringing of a קרבן, korban, that's actually like
getting atonement, getting כפרה, kaparah, that's seen as a bigger act. Okay,
so therefore when you put both of these in the equation, you
can't say they both need an act, because this act of dunking
is not the same as this act of bringing in the קרבן.
korban. The only thing that... so you should say שכיחא מעשה רבא
shecheicha ma'aseh rabba or something. Whatever,
yeah.
So his basic point is that the act here, its significance is
to weaken the טומאה, tumah, as opposed to this, the significance is
כפרה. kaparah. If the significance is to weaken the טומאה, tumah, so
then this guy, his טומאה tumah is already
weak.
Okay, anyway, some... I
don't know, we're saying that it's a less significant, but we're saying
that the כפרה kapparah that he has, the...
he needs a קרבן korban which this guy doesn't,
so it's more significant.
Right, so that's exactly the גמרא's Gemara point. The טומאה, tumah, the
residual טומאה tumah is weaker, but the obstacle to finish the process
requires a bigger thing. Since he was in a weightier sort of
process, he was a זב, zav, he wasn't just touched a נבלה
neveilah or בעל קרי, baal keri, to end that weightier process you
need a bigger act. You're now you're at a much more residual
level, but you need a bigger thing to bring it to a
conclusion. Whereas here the level is higher, but you don't need as
big of a thing to bring it to a conclusion.
It's like גמרא Gemara saying you need all three.
Right, so anyway somehow therefore I couldn't have gone from here to
here, because this needs a big act, even though it's weaker. But
somehow the גמרא Gemara is assuming that if I had this and
this I could have inferred the middle case. Again, not totally clear
why, because this and this both need an act, but anyway that's
what the גמרא's Gemara saying. Since this case is weaker, and these
acts are different, I should have been able to infer that this
case which is... which is a stronger טומאה tumah should certainly be
invalid. So, anyway, so why did you need the middle case? So
the גמרא Gemara says, here's why you need the middle case, turn
the page, קסבר
מחוסר
כיפורים דזב כזב דמי. kasavar mechusar kippurim dezav kezav dami. No, this
is not weaker. Okay, don't say that I could have inferred this
because this is weaker. Since this derives from a זב, zav, if
you're lacking the fine... even though it's weak, it's residual, it's residual
of something that is very potent. It is residual of a זב.
zav. So on the one hand, it's true. The only thing he
can invalidate is touching קדשים. kodshim. He won't invalidate this, he won't
invalidate this, he won't invalidate this... it's very residual. But, it's residual
of like something like radioactive. Okay? So therefore a little... a little
like, you know,
a little contamination, right, a little like, you know, a little radioactivity
is still pretty bad. As opposed to this, you know, this is
just I don't know, like a little germs. Okay? It's more germs
and this is only a little bit of radioactivity. So this, it
might be true that he's sort of only can be מטמא קדשים,
metamei kodshim, but to some degree, he still has a status of
a
זב. zav. What does that... in what...
what does this to some degree?
Does it mean... I'm going to tell you what that means in
a minute, okay? But let's just conceptually establish it. This guy is
a leftover... is a residual זב. zav. And therefore it's very weighty.
This guy, okay, he can be מטמא תרומה. metamei terumah. He's... he...
you know, he's somewhat higher up here. But all he's got, he's
got something stronger but it's a stronger germs. It's not stronger radioactivity.
It's just leftover from being a נבלה neveilah or בעל קרי. baal
keri. So therefore just because this guy is invalid doesn't tell me
that this guy is invalid. Okay? That's why I needed all three
because at the end of the day even though it's weaker it's
weaker from something that's much more... much stronger. Now, what is the
נפקא מינה nafka mina of saying that this guy is like a
זב? zav? Okay, for what הלכה? halacha? So רש"י Rashi says two
things, תוספות Tosafot rejects one of them. The one thing that actually
I'll tell you has an interesting נפקא מינה nafka mina is the
question about going into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. תוספות Tosafot actually
says everybody agrees to what I'm about to say, but רש"י Rashi
says it depends whether you say that מחוסר כיפורים דזב כזב דמי.
mechusar kippurim dezav kezav dami. This is a general question when the
guy's at this low level and you're waiting for it to get
rid of the residual stuff, does he still have some of that
earlier identity? So what רש"י Rashi says this debate is about is,
let's say a guy was a...
I'll give you a classic example, okay? This happens because I love
doing this example because people who go to these tours on the
Temple Mount. Okay? And therefore what they tell people is, they say,
now the problem is that on the Temple Mount, which is מחנה
לויה, Machaneh Leviyah, somebody who is a בעל קרי baal keri or
a woman who's a נדה niddah is not allowed on the Temple
Mount. So even if you avoid the place where actually is מקום
המקדש, makom hamikdash, you're not allowed anywhere on the Temple Mount. So
what do people say? They say, well, you know, they say go
to... they say to the men, like go to the מקוה mikvah
in the morning. And therefore if you go to the מקוה mikvah
in the morning, even if you're a בעל קרי baal keri you're
allowed on the Temple Mount. The only problem is if somebody had
a seminal emission the night before and went to מקוה mikvah in
the morning, what is their... or a נדה niddah who went to
מקוה mikvah the night before, what's their status now? They are a
טבול יום. tvul yom. Okay? So here's the point. It's only... it's
weak, it's only like a שני, sheni, but it's residual of being
a בעל קרי baal keri or a נדה. niddah. So, therefore, it
doesn't have the הלכה halacha for example of a נדה niddah she's
allowed to have sex with her husband or whatever. If you were
to touch קדשים, kodshim, you know, you would invalidate קדשים kodshim or
whatnot. It would be like this, okay, it would be like a
שני. sheni. Is this the הלכה halacha of somebody who is a
זב zav or בעל קרי baal keri or a נדה niddah that's
not allowed on the Temple Mount? So if you say מחוסר כיפורים
mechusar kippurim that this would be טבול יום tvul yom of
a
בעל קרי baal keri is like a
בעל קרי baal keri or...
Meaning they need to have gone to מקוה Mikveh, *mikvah* the day
before is what you're saying.
Yeah, and not have had- and not have had a seminal emission
the night after. So if you go ahead and when these tour
guides arrange their trips, right, they have to tell everybody, okay, the
trip is on Monday, go to the מקוה Mikveh *mikvah* on Sunday,
oh, and by the way, you know, for all you men out
there, don't be having sex with your wives, and if you happen
to have a seminal emission the night before, I'll understand if you
have to cancel the next morning. Okay, nobody obviously says that, okay,
but it's very interesting because if they even if they went to
the מקוה Mikveh, *mikvah* that morning, they're still a טבול יום Tevul
yom *tvul yom*. And if you say that טבול יום Tevul yom
*tvul yom* or מחוסר כפורים *mechusar kippurim* is like has a status
of, you know, personal status, maybe what you touch, you know, is
weak or what you can invalidate, but if your personal status is
still, like we would say in Brisker language, בגברא *b'gavra*, if your
personal identity is still בעל קרי Ba'al keri, *ba'al keri*, זב Zav,
*zav*, whatever it is, because that residual טומאה Tumah, *tumah* has not
wiped away, you're still not allowed on הר הבית Har HaBayit. *Har
HaBayit*. So that's a very important נפקא מינא *nafka mina*. תוספות *Tosafos*
even thinks everybody agrees to that. רש״י *Rashi* says it's based on
this debate. תוספות *Tosafos* says the other question about מחוסר כפורים *mechusar
kippurim* is whether it's כזב דמי Ke-zav dami *kezav dami* or not
is that let's say you have a קרבן Korban, פסח *korban pesach*
that is brought בטומאה *betumah*. We mentioned the other day the question
about טומאה Tumah, הותרה בציבור *tumah hutrah betzibur*. So when everybody is
טמא Tame טמאי מתים *tamei tumei meys*, you know who can't bring
the קרבן Korban, פסח *korban pesach* even if it's being brought בטומאה
*betumah*? A זב Zav, *zav*. Somebody who is טמא Tame. *tamei* because
of טומאה Tumah, היוצאה מגופו *tumah hayotzei migufa*. So let's say this
guy was א זב Zav *a zav*, but he had gone to
the מקוה Mikveh, *mikvah* whatever and he was still waiting to bring
his קרבן Korban. *korban*, and everybody else was totally טמאי מתים *tamei
meys* and bringing a קרבן Korban פסח *korban pesach*. Could he bring
a קרבן Korban *korban* together with them? If you say מחוסר כפורים
כזב דמי *mechusar kippurim
kezav dami*, then his personal status even though it's only residual is
still in the זב Zav *zav* category. He's not like he touched
a dead body, like he's just a normal טמא Tame *tamei* person.
No, he still is, I mean not that it's a good thing,
but he still is א זב Zav. *a zav* who hasn't finished
his טהרה *tahara* process. Okay, so because even though it's only the
slight, you know, vestiges, but since it started from this full thing,
he still has that as a personal status.
So טבול יום Tevul yom. של זב Zav, *tvul yom shel zav*
will be אסור *assur* in this קרבן Korban פסח *korban pesach* case,
is what you're saying.
Yeah. So what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying is you could
not have learned it even though it's very residual and the level
is weak, the personal status is very high. He still is- he
still hasn't left the status of א זב Zav, *a zav*. And
therefore just because this guy is פסול pasul *pasul*, doesn't mean that
this guy is פסול *pasul*. Okay, because this guy only has the
residual status of like a בעל קרי Ba'al Keri *ba'al keri* or
something of that nature. Okay, so that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. קסבר מחוסר כפורים כזב דמי *kasavar mechusar kippurim kezav dami*. מחוסר
*Mechusar*- now, the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says מחוסר כפורים כזב דמי תנאי
*mechusar kippurim kezav dami tannai*, it's a debate of תנאים *Tannaim*. Once
you're down to that residual level, are you still seen as א
זב Zav, *a zav* who has not yet totally been cleansed? Or
are you now seen- you went to the מקוה Mikveh, *mikvah*, whatever,
you're now seen as some person with some light טומאה Tumah *tumah*,
but we don't still transfer the person- or sustain the personal status
from the past. That's the question.
Like the reason that we just said?
Yeah, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying that argument that
we made that we do sustain the personal status and that's why
just because this guy's פסול *pasul* you can't infer that that guy's
פסול *pasul*, that question whether we sustain the personal status until you're
totally done is a debate of תנאים *Tannaim*. Okay, so now we're
going to see that debate. Okay. מחוסר כפורים כזב דמי תנאי *Mechusar
kippurim kezav dami tannai*. It's a debate of תנאים *Tannaim*. דתניא d'tanya
*Detanya*, we learn
a ברייתא *braisa*. שרפה אונן Onen, ומחוסר כפורים כשירה
*srefah onen umechusar kippurim kesherah*. Let's say the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah?
*parah adumah* was burnt by somebody who is an אונן onen *onen*,
a כהן kohen *kohen* who is an אונן onen, *onen*, who we
know is פסול *pasul* for עבודה Avodah, *avoda*, but remember פרה אדומה
Parah Adumah *parah adumah* is not an עבודה Avodah *avoda*, it's not
brought in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*, it's קדשי בדק
הבית *kodshei bedek habayis*, or an אונן onen *onen* or a כהן
kohen *kohen* who was מחוסר כפורים *mechusar kippurim*. If he basically burnt
the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *parah adumah*, it's כשר *kasher*. It's fine.
יוסף הבבלי אומר אונן onen כשר *Yosef HaBavli omer onen kasher*, an
אונן *onen* ultimately is כשר *kasher* because an אונן *onen* is, again,
this is not a real עבודה Avodah *avoda*, so an אונן *onen*
is כשר *kasher* to burn the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *parah adumah*,
but מחוסר כפורים פסולה *mechusar kippurim pesulah*, מחוסר כפורים *mechusar kippurim* who
burns the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah, *parah adumah* is invalid. So what's
the debate? So מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי *mai lav behak mifligi*, let's
say this is the debate. מר סבר Mar savar מחוסר כפורים כזב
דמי ומר סבר Umar savar, לאו כזב דמי *mar savar mechusar kippurim
kezav dami umar savar lav kezav dami*. This is the debate, are
you seen like א זב Zav *a zav* or not? Meaning we'll
assume that if it's just an issue of a tiny amount of
residual טומאה Tumah *tumah*, so at the end of the day, okay,
this is not an עבודה Avodah *avoda* in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash. *Beis HaMikdash* and that wouldn't be a problem. But if your
personal status is that of א זב Zav *a zav*,
okay, then obviously, I don't know how we know obviously, but we're
going to assume obviously if your personal status is that of א
זב Zav *a zav*, even for פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *parah adumah*
you would be invalid. Okay, because the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* says ושרף
*vesaraf*- because when the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* describes it, it says ושרף
איש טהור Tahor, את *vesaraf ish tahor ais*- what's the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*? It says והזה הטהור על הטמא Ve-hizah hatahor al hatame, *vehizah
hatahor al hatamei*. Okay, so it describes the person who was doing
the act of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. *parah adumah* It's not
a קרבן, korban. so you don't have to follow the same rules
of the קרבן, korban. but it does refer to the person as
הטהור, Hatahor, okay? So a guy with a tiny residue amount of
טומאה, Tumah we would say if it was just because of this
residual טומאה, tumah like the tiny amount that would not be enough
to say that you're not defined as a person who is טהור,
Tahor, okay? But if you still have an identity of a זב,
Zav, then you don't fall into the category of הטהור. Hatahor. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, look, it's not a קרבן, korban. so
somebody like an אונן, everybody agrees is okay, but it does say
you have to be טהור, Tahor. a person who as a personal
status is טהור. Tahor So presumably that's a debate. At your level
of טומאה, tumah you know, it's only a tiny amount would not
put you out of this category, but if your identity is that
as a זב, Zav you're still a זב Zav? that has not
left the זב Zav identity, then that would invalidate you. So that
seems to be the debate of whether מחוסר כיפורים דזב Mechusar kippurim
de-zav is כזב דמי or not. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
isn't that what the debate is about?
לא, Lo, says the גמרא, Gemara not necessarily. דכולי עלמא כזב דמי,
De-chulei alma ke-zav dami, everybody might say that you're like a זב.
Zav. So you're like a זב, Zav. so then how could you
go ahead and do the and do the burning of the פרה
אדומה? Parah Adumah, והכא בהא קמיפלגי, Ve-hacha be-ha kamiflegi, this is the
debate, דכתיב, De-chtiv, the פסוק pasuk says, והזה הטהור Ve-hizah hatahor על
הטמא, the טהור Tahor person should sprinkle the ashes. מכלל שהוא טמא,
Michlal she-hu tame, this teaches you that the person, this is the
you gotta love this דרשה Derashah of the rabbis. He's טהור Tahor
means you don't have to say he is טהור Tahor. unless he
was once טמא Tame. and now he became טהור. Tahor. So the
person the תורה Torah is saying can do the עבודה, Avodah, can
do the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah? is somebody that
had just recently been טמא. Tame Now, לימד על טבול יום שכשר
בפרה. Limed al tevul yom she-kasher be-farah. And that tells you that
if he had gone to, he had been טמא Tame, and he'd
gone to the מקוה, Mikveh, he can do the עבודה avodah. of
the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah That's quite ironic that it says הטהור
Hatahor tells you that he had recently been טמא. Tame, Now, the
גמרא Gemara does say that this actually was something the rabbis used
to do, right, to annoy the צדוקים, Tzedukim, because the צדוקים, Tzedukim,
you know, would say that, oh, somebody who had been to the
מקוה mikvah? and was a טבול יום Tevul yom could not do
the עבודה avodah of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah So the גמרא
Gemara describes or the משנה Mishnah describes how they would go crazy
to make sure that everything would be super טהור. Tahor, They would
raise kids from infancy to do the עבודה avodah, of the פרה
אדומה, making sure that they were a hundred a thousand percent טהור,
Tahor. and then the day of the thing they would put, they
would get them טמא Tame and put them into the מקוה, so
that they would be a טבול יום Tevul yom just to spite
the צדוקים Tzedukim to show you that the פרה עבודה avodah of
the פרה אדומה could be done by a טבול יום. Tevul yom
So הטהור Hatahor shows that the person was once טמא, tamei okay,
and that says a טבול יום Tevul yom, is okay. And the
question is, that's like a טבול יום Tevul yom by somebody who
touched a שרץ. Sheretz. What would we say once we have that
idea that a טבול יום Tevul yom is okay, what would we
say about a מחוסר כיפורים? Mechusar kippurim? Would this also allow for
that case? Okay, לימד על טבול
יום שכשר בפרה. Limed al tevul yom she-kasher be-farah. מר סבר טומאה
דכל התורה כולה. Mar savar tumah de-chol ha-torah kullah. Now, when it
says הטהור, Hatahor, okay, so the context here is somebody that came,
came in touch with a dead body, alright. So somebody who comes
in touch with a dead body, right, what's the process, right? Somebody
who comes in touch with a dead body, here you are, you're
a person, you came in touch with a dead body, here's a
guy, whatever. Okay, so you touched a dead body, now you're, now
you're טמא מת. Tame met. You have טומאה tumah of a dead
body. You wait seven days, on day three you have the ashes,
and on day, you know, seven you've got the ashes, and then
you're, you go to the מקוה, okay, there's the
מקוה, okay, during the מקוה, and then you are a טבול יום,
Tevul yom,
and then come the night of day eight, you're totally טהור. Tahor
Okay, so that's a case, it took seven days, but you're not
מחוסר כיפורים. Mechusar kippurim.
If you touch a dead body you don't need to bring a
קרבן.
korban, Okay, so when the גמרא Gemara's says והזה הטהור
which implies that he was טמא, the context here is טומאת מת.
Tumat met. So who was somebody who had just been טמא and
now is mostly טהור tahor, but not a hundred percent? This guy
who's a
טבול יום Tevul yom of a טמא מת. Tame met. So if
that's the context, this is including somebody who is a טבול יום
Tevul yom, of a טמא מת, Tame met, and obviously it would
include all other types of טומאה tumah. that are like it, touching
a dead corpse of an animal, a בעל קרי, Ba'al Keri, all
other types of טומאה tuma like it that you're a טבול יום,
Tevul Yom then you would still be okay to do the ashes
of the פרה אדומה. The one thing that's not implicitly included even
though טמא מת Tame met is very weighty, the one thing that's
not implicitly included is something like a זב, something that needs a
קרבן korban, at the end, okay? Something, remember, קרבן korban is a
bigger thing, you need an actual to bring a קרבן korban. to
change your status. So yes, we know that somebody's a טבול יום
Tevul Yom can do the thing because the context here is טומאת
מת, Tumat met, so somebody who just got finished with טומאת מת
Tumat met as a טבול יום, Tevul Yom but what's not clear
is, can somebody who's a מחוסר כיפורים Mechusar kippurim do the עבודה,
avodah do the ashes? Because that person there's a bigger obstacle before
that person
is. can do the
ashes. Can a מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim do the ashes? So let's
take a look.
Okay, now, מר סבר Mar savar,
distinctions of
אב
הטומאה, Av HaTumah, right? In other words, the most extreme type...
Yes, but this is a... this is very weighty. This is an
אב. av. This is just as weighty as this.
That's what I'm saying.
Right, the difference is that this doesn't need a קרבן. korban So
that person, it's going to go away by itself. That, that we
learn out that person can do the ashes. Somebody who it sticks,
right? מחוסר כיפורים, Mechussar Kippurim, you need something to change it. You
know, that person maybe the status still sticks with him and cannot
do the עבודה. avodah. Okay. So מר סבר, טומאה דכל התורה כולה,
tumah dechol haTorah kullah, okay, that any טומאה tuma that you had
once been, that's now done with, even if it's not totally done
with, including זב, including מחוסר כיפורים. Mechussar Kippurim. That type of a
person can do the עבודה avodah of the, of the פרה אדומה.
ומר סבר, and the other one holds, no, טומאה דהך פרשה. tumah
de'hach parshah. We're only talking within the פרשה parshah of טומאת מת,
tumat meit, and you can't extend it to an idea of a
מחוסר כיפורים. Mechussar Kippurim. הלכך, Hilkach, אונן וטבול יום דטמא שרץ, ve'Tevul
Yom de'tamei sheretz, אונן, everybody agrees because this isn't about a קדשים,
kodashim, so אונן is not a problem to begin with. And טבול
יום דטמא שרץ, Tevul Yom de'tamei sheretz, or a טבול יום Tevul
Yom. of somebody who touched a שרץ, sheretz, a dead rodent or
a dead carcass of an animal, or even of a dead body,
of a
מת, meit, דקילי... dekillei... those are weaker, like those only start off
as like a ראשון. rishon. אתו בקל וחומר Atu be'kal vachomer מטבול
יום דמת. mi'Tevul Yom demet. So since the תורה Torah is talking
about a טבול יום Tevul Yom. of a מת, meit, you obviously
would include if a טבול יום Tevul Yom of a מת meit
can do the עבודה, avodah. certainly you would include שרץ sheretz and,
you know, בעל קרי Ba'al Keri
and all those other people, right? All of those are just טבול
יום. Tevul Yom, So if this guy can do the stuff with
the ashes, certainly those can. You get it by a קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Okay, אתו בקל וחומר atu be'kal vachomer מטבול יום
דמת. mi'Tevul Yom demet. אבל מחוסר כיפורים דזב, Aval Mechussar Kippurim de'Zav,
דחמיר, dechameir, but a
מחוסר
כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim of a זב that's weightier. Now, I said the
reason it's weightier is because it sticks more, because you need to
bring a קרבן. korban The גמרא Gemara says it's weightier for a
different reason, שכן טומאה יוצא עליו מגופו. sheken tumah yotzei alav migufo.
It came from your very body, and that's important. The גמרא Gemara
in general describes that in certain ways a מת meit is more
weighty, you need the whole ashes of the פרה אדומה, you're considered
an אב הטומאה, Av HaTumah, whatever. But the זב is weightier because
it actually is something that happened directly to your body. A way
that you know that a זב is weightier than a טמא מת
tamei meit is exactly the point I said before. We all consider
ourselves טמאי מת temei meit and we're allowed to go up to
הר הבית. Har HaBayit Just because you're dead with טומאה for a
bit... מת, meit, you're not allowed in the מקום המקדש, makom HaMikdash,
where the actual temple stood, but you're allowed on the Temple Mount.
But if you have a טומאה that came from your body, you're
a בעל קרי, Ba'al Keri? you're a זב, you're a נדה, Niddah,
whatever, you're not allowed on the Temple Mount. Okay, so those things
are weightier. So therefore, and also I would throw in you have
to bring a קרבן. korban So therefore it's not clear that that
person can do the stuff with the ashes. Okay, so לא, lo,
no. So therefore what did the גמרא Gemara say? This was a
whole fascinating digression
about the status of מחוסר כיפורים. Mechussar Kippurim. So basically we have
the following issue: is somebody who is waiting a קרבן, מחוסר כיפורים,
Mechussar Kippurim, still have the personal status of that previous state? And
in theory you could ask that also by a טבול יום. tevul
yom Is a טבול יום tvul yom of a בעל קרי like
a בעל קרי? Is a מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim of a זב
like a זב? מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim is maybe even more so
because that requires a bigger hurdle to get over to change your
status. So to what degree does your personal status still remain? What
is a נפקא מינה? nafka mina? So one נפקא מינה nafka mina
we mentioned was like קרבן פסח בטומאה, Korban Pesach be'tumah, which is
a little obscure. Another interesting נפקא מינה nafka mina I thought of
a very relevant one is can you go up on הר הבית
after you've been to the מקוה? That's more about טבול יום, tvul
yom not מחוסר כיפורים. Mechussar Kippurim. Okay, and the גמרא's Gemara נפקא
מינה nafka mina is can you do the עבודה avodah? of פרה...
can you do the עבודה avoda of פרה אדומה? Because on the
one hand פרה אדומה is not an עבודה avoda, in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so an אונן can do it. On the other
hand you have to be described as a טהור, tahor. as a
person who is טהור. tahor, So can you do it? So the
גמרא Gemara thinks that maybe the actual, right, debate is, excuse me,
is if you're missing this קרבן, is are you now... still... do
you have the personal status still as a זב and then you're
not טהור, tahor or have you lost that personal status and you
do fall into this category? That would be a nice way to
explain it. In the end the גמרא Gemara said, whatever you think
in general about מחוסר כיפורים, Mechussar Kippurim, that's not the issue here.
In general you could say מחוסר כיפורים Mechussar Kippurim is always still
like a זב. Maybe you could always say he's not like a
זב. Doesn't matter. Whatever you say in general about let's say going
on Temple Mount tours, that's a separate discussion. Here there's a special
פסוק pasuk that tells you that the guy could have just been
טמא a minute ago and you could still... and now he's טהור
enough to do the עבודה. avoda, And we know that applies to
טמא מת tamei meis and we know to a טבול יום and
we know it applies to all these טבולי יום. tevulei yom. This
special פסוק pasuk. is coming to tell you the implication of what
the תורה Torah is telling you all those people are okay, and
the only question is does we read the פסוק pasuk to go
so far to also include מחוסר כיפורים? mechusar kippurim? Okay, so that's
a special debate by פרה אדומה where the פסוק pasuk allows it,
and we want to know how far does that allowance go. That
doesn't tell you the general debate of the status of a מחוסר
כיפורים. mechusar kippurim. Okay. All right? Is that? So that's where that
is. Now, we move on to מחוסר בגדים. mechusar begadim. We talked
about מחוסר כיפורים, mechusar kippurim, now we go to מחוסר בגדים. mechusar
begadim. So those are different levels of טומאה. Now we go to
a כהן kohen that is not wearing all the בגדי כהונה. bigdei
kehunah. So let's take a look. Okay,
so now,
so
like this, take a look.
Okay, מחוסר בגדים, mechusar begadim, מנלן, menalan, where do you know this
from? אמר רב אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav Abbahu Amar Rabbi
Yochanan ומתני בה משמיה דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון u'matni bah mishmei d'Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon דאמר קרא, d'amar kra, the verse says וחגרת אתם
אבנט v'chagarta osam avnet you shall gird them with the belt אהרן
ובניו Aharon u'banav Aaron and his children וחבשת להם מגבעות v'chavashta lahem
migbaos put on them the miters, the hats והיתה להם כהנה לחקת
עולם v'hayesa lahem kehunah l'chukas olam the kehunah will be for an
eternal edict בזמן שבגדיהם עליהם כהונתם עליהם bizman she'bigdeihem aleihem kehunasam aleihem
when their garments are on them then they really have a full
status of כהונה kehunah because that was the whole point right? The
whole ritual of putting on the garments was a way of, you
know, initiating them into the כהונה, kehunah, in, you know, imbuing them
with their כהונה kehunah status. Let's also not forget that you know
remember with the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, I don't know if you
remember this from הוריות, Horayos, when there's no שמן המשחה, shemen hamishchah,
how does he get his status of כהן גדול? kohen gadol? It's
called מרובה בגדים merubeh begadim by wearing the garments. Okay, so the
garments is what gives them their full כהונה kehunah status. אין בגדיהם
עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם ein bigdeihem aleihem ein kehunasam aleihem when they're
not wearing their clothes they're not really have a full כהונה kehunah
status and therefore it's like a זר zar did the עבודה avoda
in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now I have to tell you
that some people latched onto this גמרא Gemara and says oh, this
solves all of our problems of all these issues nowadays of כהנים,
kohanim, you know, כהן kohen can't marry a גרושה gerushah or a
כהן kohen wants to be a doctor. The גמרא Gemara says oh,
if they're not wearing their בגדים begadim they're not כהנים kohanim so
therefore don't wear your בגדים begadim and then it's all free for
all. Okay, obviously the גמרא Gemara did not mean that, you know,
it's clear throughout the entire ש"ס Shas that the גמרא treats all
the restrictions of כהנים kohanim when they were not כהנים kohanim walking
around with בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah. What it means particularly is the
כהונה kehunah of working in the temple and that makes sense, right?
The whole emphasis of the תורה Torah in פרשת שמיני, Parshas Shemini,
right, you know is about or whatever צו Tzav is at you
know and then also in שמות Shemos that the way you sort
of make them part of the apparatus of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash. you know you do the, you put the clothes on each
day, you know the seven day process, right? And you sprinkle the
oil the same way you would put the oil on the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash All of this is part of their like identity
as like כלי המקדש klei hamikdash as part of the apparatus of
the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash So when they're not wearing the בגדים
begadim vis-a-vis the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. they're no longer part of
that apparatus. It doesn't mean that they're not כהנים kohanim at all.
Okay, an interesting though like נפקא מינה nafka mina was
there was a great story that the מרדכי Mordechai brings down a
story that רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam once asked a כהן kohen to
like, I don't know, do something for him I forget what it
was, pour, pour him a glass of water or something, and one
of the students said to him, how are you allowed to do
that? The גמרא says, the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says המשתמש בכהן כאילו מעל
hamishtamesh b'kohen k'ilu maal that somebody who makes personal use of a
כהן kohen is like they transgress the איסור issur of מעילה. me'ilah.
מעילה Me'ilah is like you know trespass on the sanctified things of
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash. like you drank from a כלי שרת,
kli shares, you know you drank from one of the holy vessels
of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, So it says you can't have
a כהן kohen do some personal service for you. So רבינו תם
Rabbeinu Tam said oh אין בגדיהם עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם. ein bigdeihem
aleihem ein kehunasam aleihem. They're not wearing their בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah.
So some people say ah, you see if you're not wearing your
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah it's a free for all which is obviously
not the point. The point of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam seems to
have very clearly been the language of that ירושלמי Yerushalmi is כאילו
מעל. k'ilu maal. מעל Maal is a language used for things that
are part of the כלים keilim of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash
So that idea that I can't have a כהן kohen, do some
service for me, it's like I misused an object of the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash. that's when a כהן Kohen, has his status as
an object of the בית המקדש when he's wearing his בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehunah. When he's not wearing his בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah it's
a completely different story. So the idea of אין בגדיהם עליהם אין
כהונתם עליהם ein bigdeihem aleihem ein kehunasam aleihem is specifically in terms
of their connection to the בית המקדש. Okay, but when they're not
wearing it they're like a זר zar and therefore they invalidate the
עבודה. avoda והא מהכא נפקא מהתם נפקא? v'ha me'hacha nafka me'hasam nafka?
What do you mean? We don't learn it from here, we learn
it from over there from a different place, דתניא מנין לשתויי יין
שאם עבד חילל? minayin l'shisuyei yayin she'im avad chillel?
How do you know if somebody, a כהן, Kohen. is drunk that
he violates, that he desecrates the עבודה? avoda תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar
יין ושכר אל תשת אתה ובניך אתך בבאכם אל אהל מועד ולא
תמתו yayin v'shichar al tesht atah u'vanecha itacha b'vo'achem el ohel mo'ed
v'lo samusu and then it says ולהבדיל בין הקדש ובין החל u'lehavdil
bein hakodesh u'vein hachol that by keeping this you separate between the
holy and the profane which means when you are drunk you profane
that which is holy. Okay, so now that tells you if you're
drunk, you profane. מחוסר בגדים ושלא רחוץ ידים ורגלים מניין? Mechusar begadim
veshelo rachutz yadayim veraglayim minayin? Now that tells you if you're drunk.
How do you know if you're not wearing the בגדי כהונה, bigdei
kehuna, you haven't washed your hands? By the way, this is covering
other cases in our משנה mishna as well. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar,
the verse teaches, okay, חוקה חוקה חוקה, chuka chuka chuka, חוקה חוקה
לגזירה שוה. chuka chuka legezeira shava.
It says by being drunk חוקת עולם chukat olam and by the
garments it says ועשית להם כהונה לחוקת עולם, ve'asita lahem kehuna lechukat
olam, we just quoted that, and by washing the hands and the
feet it says ועשית להם לחוקת עולם. ve'asita lahem lechukat olam. So
by all of them it says חוק. chok. So since by drunk
you invalidate, by not washing your hands or not wearing the בגדים
begadim you also invalidate. So which is it? Do we learn it
from the idea that you're like a זר, zar, like a non-כהן,
Kohen, and that's how you invalidate, or do we learn it from
the link to being drunk that you invalidate? Which one is it?
So the גמרא says, no, אי מהתם, ei mehatam, had it just
been from the case about being drunk and that I learn that
not wearing the בגדים begadim you
invalidate, הוה אמינא hava amina I would have thought הני מילי עבודה
דזר חייב עליה מיתה. hanei milei avoda dezar chayav aleha misa. Right,
there it says that you're חייב מיתה, chayav misa, right, ולא תמותו,
velo tamutu, don't be drunk and don't die. So which עבודה avoda
is a זר zar חייב מיתה chayav misa for? If a זר
zar does an עבודה, they're deserving of the death penalty. So surprisingly,
when we say if a זר zar does עבודה, it is the
four classic עבודות. avodot. What are the four classic עבודות avodot that
you invalidate a קרבן if you have שלא לשמה shelo lishma or
that if a זר zar does it? Well שחיטה, shechita, שחיטה shechita
is כשרה בזר. keshera bezar.
קבלה, Kabala, הולכה, holacha, and זריקה. zerika. Those are the עבודות הדם
avodot hadam that make a קרבן כשר korban kasher and that if
it's done incorrectly invalidate a קרבן. But in the חייב מיתה chayav
misa these are the things that are part of, that are like,
you know, מכשיר machshir a קרבן or can פסול a קרבן if
done incorrectly. Okay, what are the ones that are however that you're
חייב מיתה chayav misa if a זר zar did it or if
it was done because remember all of these things have two הלכות:
halachot: you're not allowed to and if you do it you invalidate?
Okay, and sometimes when you're not allowed to and you do the
עבודה in a way you're not allowed to you're חייב מיתה, chayav
misa, מיתה בידי שמים, misa bidei shamayim, we discussed that before, right,
about how do you know this person is חייב מיתה, chayav misa,
etc. Okay, טבול יום and זר. zar. So the חייב מיתה chayav
misa though we learn out from a different פסוק. We learn out
from
ועבדתם. va'avadetem.
So and we learn out that that is עבודה תמה. avoda tama.
It has to be a full עבודה meaning something that is not
in the middle of a process. These things are in the middle
of a process. Okay, what are the things that are considered to
be an עבודה תמה avoda tama that you're חייב מיתה chayav misa
for? So those are things that are like the end of a
process. Those are things like זריקה, zerika,
הקטרה, haktara, you're burning the stuff. And now I got to remind
myself, רש"י Rashi lists them. Okay, ניסוך המים והיין, nisuch hamayim vehayayin,
ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim
and
ניסוך היין. nisuch hayayin. Okay, those are things which are not like
a whole process. These are the last things that are putting it
on the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, so those are the only things that
you're חייב מיתה. chayav misa. These are the things that are part
of the דם. dam. All right, very different list. So the גמרא
is saying when you say don't do the עבודה when you're drunk
ולא תמותו velo tamutu then you're only talking about ולא תמותו velo
tamutu something that's of this list. The only one of this list
that could invalidate the קרבן is the זריקה, zerika, right? Everything here
happens, doesn't invalidate. This is the only thing that can invalidate. So
I would have only known that it's a problem on the זריקה
zerika because it says ולא תמותו. velo tamutu. How do I know
that by these other things as well it's a problem? Okay, yeah,
you with me? All right, so it says like this, it says
אי מהתם, ei mehatam, how do you learn it out from being
drunk that it invalidates? Okay,
so I would have said הני מילי עבודה דזר חייב עליה מיתה.
hanei milei avoda dezar chayav aleha misa. That's only by a type
of a thing like ולא תמותו velo tamutu which it's talking about
by being drunk so it's like זריקה. zerika. אבל עבודה שאין זר
חייב עליה מיתה אימא לא, aval avoda she'ein zar chayav aleha misa
eima lo, an עבודה that a זר zar is not חייב מיתה
chayav misa for, these things, קבלה kabala and הולכה, holacha, I might
have said that it does not invalidate, אימא לא. eima lo. So
therefore קמשמע לן, kama mashma lan, and therefore it says אין בגדיהם
עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם. ein bigdeihem aleihem ein kehunatam aleihem. That's why
I learn from the פסוק that when you're not wearing the בגדים
begadim it's like you're not a כהן. Kohen, And therefore now שחיטה
shechita of course is okay without being a כהן, Kohen. but these
are the things that you know it's only a כהן, Kohen from
קבלה kabala ואילך ve'eilach is כהן. Okay. And therefore the פסוק tells
me if you're not wearing the בגדים begadim you're not a כהן
and you invalidate. All right then it doesn't explain why you needed
the חוקה chuka once I learn it out from here but okay.
All right, so that's how we learn the idea of מחוסר בגדים.
mechusar begadim. Everybody good? So most of today was figuring out the
idea of the difference between טבול יום which is weightier than מחוסר
כיפורים mechusar kipurim in the sense that there's more of a presence
of the טומאה but the טומאה itself is weaker, it's dirt, it's
not radioactivity. This is a
more residual. Okay, and therefore אין בגדיהם עליהם אין כהונתם עליהם, ein
bigdeihem aleihem ein kehunatam aleihem, and therefore, and that's why it invalidates,
okay, and that there's a different list between the עבודות avodot that
can validate and invalidate and the עבודות avodot that a
זר zar would be חייב מיתה. chayav misa. All right, we will
bring it to—we will end today. Next time we start a new
משנה mishna about how—how we learned about the זר zar and the
difference between the זר zar and the בעל מום. ba'al mum. Have
a wonderful night, everybody. Enjoy the beautiful evening.