So today's דף daf is מ"ח, Mem-Chet, 48. We pick up at
the very first line. We're going through
the, working through the משנה. Mishnah. I mean we're in the גמרא,
Gemara, working through the משנה Mishnah about the different ways in which
the different procedures for the different קרבנות. korbanos. משנה Mishnah starts with
קדשי קדשים ששחטן בצפון kodshei kodshim she-shachtan ba-tzafon and you and then
every single one of them you catch the blood, also you have
to be in the צפון, tzafon, but it didn't mention that as
a global statement. It mentioned that with each one in particular. So
yesterday the גמרא Gemara just discussed why because in the אשם asham
there's a separate procedure where some of the blood is accepted caught
directly in the hand. Now we turn to the specifics and the
first sort of one of the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodshim that it
mentions is the פרים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, the things that the blood
is brought on the into the inner sanctuary and that
the meat is burnt outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
starting with them in particular it starts first with the פר ושעיר
par v-sair of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So let's take a look.
Top of מ"ח עמוד א. Mem-Chet amud aleph. פר ושעיר של יום
הכפורים. Par v-sair shel Yom HaKippurim. מכדי, Michdi, let's take a look.
צפון בעולה כתיב. Tzafon ba-olah ksiv.
The Torah when it first mentions צפון tzafon mentions about the עולה
olah and as we're going to see momentarily even when it references
that the other animals are שחט-ed shacht in the צפון tzafon it
always says you should שחט shacht it in the place where you
שחט shacht the עולה. olah. Okay so and it's very interesting in
general the way the עולה olah sort of is referenced as the
primary קרבן. korban. A, it's just an interesting question in general right
why when the Torah opens the קרבנות korbanos in ויקרא Vayikra does
it speak about an עולה? olah? You know it's not about the
sin fundamentally it's about presumably more about like this connecting to God.
I mean if you think about the earlier קרבנות korbanot in the
Torah they're not about sin right they're about just somebody wanting to
bring a קרבן korban to connect to God and so on. Also
you know the Torah often mentions by like the עולת תמיד העשויה
בהר סיני olas tamid ha-asuya be-har Sinai like there's some sense that
this is like the paradigm in the original one. So anyway it
says the following. מכדי, Michdi, צפון בעולה
כתיב. tzafon ba-olah ksiv. It's written by the עולה. olah. ניתני עולה
ברישא. Nisni olah ba-reicha. Why not say עולה olah first? We'll see
in a minute where it's written by the עולה. olah. Why did
our list in our משנה Mishnah start with a חטאת? chatas? So
the גמרא Gemara says חטאת איידי דאתי מדרשא חביבא ליה. chatas idi
d'asi midrasha chaviva lei. No because a חטאת chatas we learn it
from a דרשה, derasha, it's not I mean it's not such a
דרשה, derasha, the פסוק pasuk says במקום אשר תשחט העולה תשחט החטאת,
bimkom asher tishchat ha'olah tishchat hachattat,
but nevertheless since it's somehow part of the rabbinic enterprise it's not
totally explicit so therefore we wanted to mention it first. It's not
totally explicit in the פסוקים. pesukim. That's a general principle the גמרא
Gemara has or uses when it's needed to explain something. וניתני חטאת
החיצוניות. V'nisni chatas hachitzoniyot.
Why not start with the outer חטאות chataos which are also mentioned
earlier in the Torah before the inner חטאות? chataos? איידי דנכנס דמן
לפני ולפנים חביבא ליה. Idi d'nichnas daman lifnai v'lifnim chaviva lei. Oh
we'd rather mention the inner one because their blood goes into the
inner Holy of Holies and particularly לפני ולפנים lifnai v'lifnim references not
just a normal inner חטאת chatas but the חטאת chatas of יום
כיפור Yom Kippur where it goes into the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim
so therefore that was wanted to give it
priority. So and that is interesting right how maybe that informs in
general why the חטאת chatas was mentioned first in order to mention
the inner חטאות chataos and in order to mention the fact that
you know the blood does go into the קדש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim
so it has a certain power that an עולה olah does not.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. וצפונה בעולה היכא כתיב.
V'tzafona ba-olah heicha ksiv. So where does it say צפון tzafon by
the עולה? olah? Now that we've sort of explained just the order
of the משנה Mishnah let's get to the פסוקים. pesukim. ושחט אתו
על ירך המזבח צפנה לפני ה'. V'shachat oso al yerech hamizbeach tzafona
lifnei Hashem. That's what it says by the עולה. olah. אשכחן בן
צאן, בן בקר מנלן. Ashchan ben tzon, ben bakar minan. Now if
you look in the Torah right at the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra
so the beginning of ויקרא Vayikra starts with the עולה. olah. It
says אדם כי יקריב מכם קרבן לה' מן הבהמה מן הבקר ומן
הצאן תקריבו את קרבנכם. Adam ki yakriv mikem korban la-Hashem min habeheima
min habakar u-min hatzon takrivu es korbanchem. And then the first קרבן
korban it mentions is אם עלה קרבנו מן הבקר. im olah korbano
min habakar. If it's an עולה olah from the בקר bakar right?
So then it says from the cattle. זכר תמים יקריבנו אל פתח
אהל מועד יקריב אתו לרצנו לפני ה'. Zachar tamim yakrivenu el pesach
ohel moed yakriv oso l'retzono lifnei Hashem. And then where does it
say you שחט shacht the בקר? bakar? It says וסמך ידו על
ראש העלה ונרצה לו ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה'. v'samach yado
al rosh ha'olah v'nirtzah lo v'shachat es ben habakar lifnei Hashem. It
just says לפני ה'. lifnei Hashem. And then when you get to
פסוק י, pasuk yud, ואם מן הצאן קרבנו מן הכשבים או מן
העזים לעלה זכר תמים יקריבנו ושחט אתו על ירך המזבח צפנה לפני
ה'.
v'im min hatzon korbano min hakvasim o min ha'izim l'olah zachar tamim
yakrivenu v'shachat oso al yerech
hamizbeach tzafona lifnei Hashem. So when it
gets to the צאן tzon it says צפון. tzafon. But when it
started with the בקר bakar it just said שחט shachted לפני ה',
lifnei Hashem, did not say צפון. tzafon. So the גמרא Gemara says
okay אשכחן בן צאן. ashchan ben tzon. We see where the צאן
tzon is שחט-ed shacht in the צפון tzafon of an עולה. olah.
בן בקר מנלן. Ben bakar minan. And where do you get it
that it's the בקר? bakar? אמר קרא ואם מן הצאן. Amar kra
v'im min hatzon. So it says because when it introduces the צאן
tzon it says and if the עולה olah comes from the צאן.
tzon. So since it says and
if, ו' מוסיף על עניין ראשון vav mosif al inyan rishon it's
an addition to what we've said above. Now here's the trick. If
what we wanted to say by the בקר bakar by what the
first thing we wanted apply to the second thing and you said
here's the law by the בקר. bakar. Oh and if it's the
צאן tzon here's the law you would assume... Since it says and
if and it's a ו vav and it's connecting them, anything we
said by the בקר bakar would also be true by the sheep
unless explicitly stated otherwise. But here we have to do the reverse.
We have to say something we're now going to say about the
sheep is we're going to say is because it's linked to the
above, we're going to apply it to what preceded it. That's not
so פשוט pashut just in terms of פשט, pshat, many might be
פשוט pashut in terms of a דרשה, drasha, but it's not פשוט
pashut in terms of פשט, pshat, right that it comes second and
you add something in the second thing you didn't say in the
first and they're going to say ah but because of this ו
vav connecting it, it really is true about the first thing as
well. So that's the issue
here. ו מוסיף על עניין ראשון, vav mosif al inyan rishon, the
ו vav adds to what we said
above. וילמד עליון מתחתון velamed elyon mitachton and here becomes the key
and we're going to learn what was said earlier from what was
said below. So since by the sheep it says on the north,
we're going to assume it's true by the cattle as well. So
now the גמרא Gemara says, הניחא למאן דאמר מלמדים, hanicha lemandamar melamdim,
that's good if you take the approach that you can learn the
above from the below when they're linked with a ו. vav. אלא
למאן דאמר אין מלמדים, ela mandamar ein melamdim, but if the below
can't literally teach the thing above, so then
מאי איכא למימר, mai ikka lemeimar, where do you learn this from?
דתניא, detanya, how do we know there's a debate of whether you
can learn when they're connected with a ו vav the thing above
from the thing below, whether the thing below can teach more literally
the thing above. דתניא, detanya, ואם נפש. ve'im nefesh. So now we're
going to do to another aspect of קרבנות, korbanot, about the אשם.
asham. Okay, so here's the point. The Torah says at the end
of ויקרא Vayikra it mentions the אשם asham some cases of an
אשם. asham. And it says the
following.
Okay, so first we have the following. This is in ה יד.
Hay Yod-Dalet. נפש כי תמעול מעל וחטאה בשגגה מקדשי ה', nefesh ki
timal ma'al vechata bishgaga mikadshei Hashem, this is אשם מעילות, asham meilot,
if you did a מעילה, meila, you trespassed. והביא את אשמו לה'
איל תמים מן הצאן בערכך כסף שקלים בשקל הקדש לאשם. vehevi et
ashamo l'Hashem ayil tamim min hatzon beerkecha kesef shekalim beshekel hakodesh l'asham.
Okay, so going to write
this.
Here's my blue, blue is the best marker here. Okay.
So
here it says this is ה טו. Hay Tet-Vav. נפש כי תמעול
מעל. nefesh ki timal ma'al. וחטאה בשגגה מקדשי ה' והביא את אשמו
לה' איל תמים מן הצאן בערכך כסף שקלים
בשקל הקדש לאשם.
vechata bishgaga mikadshei Hashem vehevi et ashamo l'Hashem
ayil tamim min hatzon beerkecha kesef shekalim beshekel
hakodesh
l'asham. I'm doing the words that are going to be relevant to
us. כסף שקלים בשקל הקדש
לאשם.
kesef shekalim beshekel
hakodesh l'asham. So we're going to see in a little bit that
כסף שקלים kesef shekalim is a minimum cost of an אשם. asham.
This is אשם מעילות. asham meilot. Okay, etc. etc. Okay, so that's
that. That's the אשם מעילות. asham meilot. And
then right afterwards it says here in ה יז. Hay Yod-Zayin. ואם
נפש כי תחטא ועשתה אחת
מכל מצות ה' אשר לא תעשינה ולא ידע ואשם. ve'im nefesh ki
techeta
ve'asta achat
mikol mitzvot Hashem asher lo te'asina velo yada ve'ashem. ואם נפש כי
תחטא
ולא ידע
ואשם.
ve'im nefesh ki techeta velo yada
ve'ashem.
So this is אשם ספקות, asham sfeikot, you don't know if you've
done a sin that you have to bring a חטאת. chatat. והביא
איל תמים מן הצאן בערכך לאשם אל הכהן. vehevi ayil tamim min
hatzon beerkecha l'asham el hacohen. והביא איל תמים מן הצאן בערכך. vehevi
ayil tamim min hatzon beerkecha. Okay, etc.
etc. Okay, so
this is אשם ספק. asham safek.
So this is an אשם asham you bring if you don't know
if you've done a sin. Now normally we assume that you bring
the אשם asham if you think you might have sinned and only
in specific concrete examples where there's reason that you think that you
did an act and you don't know the nature of the act
and so on. So not just to stop anxiety, but certain cases
where you might have sinned and you don't know, you bring an
אשם ספקות, asham sfeikot, an אשם ספק. asham safek.
So the question is, like if you went down a path, one
might have a dead body there, the other might
not, not exactly but okay maybe, but more like you ate a
piece of meat and you don't know if it was חלב chelev
or kosher meat. Now normally the case is that if what you
might have done was something that you would otherwise bring a חטאת
chatat for. What if what you might have done was something that
you otherwise would have brought an אשם asham for? What if the
sin that you don't know that you did was you don't know
if you did מעילה? meila?
Will
you bring an אשם ספק asham safek for something that had you
known for certain wouldn't have been a חטאת chatat but would have
been an אשם? asham? And more specifically in our case, an אשם
מעילה? asham meila? So are we going to learn from the ו
vav to say that this is actually teaching above and teaching that
in the above case for מעילה meila as well you can bring
an אשם ספק asham safek if you don't know? So let's take
a look. It says like
this. דתניא, detanya, ואם נפש, ve'im nefesh, that's our פסוק pasuk by
אשם ספק, asham safek, לחייב על הספק מעילות אשם תלוי, lechayev al
hasafek meilot asham taluy, that teaches you that even if you have
doubt about if you did מעילה meila you bring an אשם תלוי,
asham taluy, אשם, asham, it's another word for אשם ספק asham safek
or אשם ספקות. asham sfeikot. דברי רבי עקיבא, divrei Rabbi Akiva, that's
what Rabbi Akiva said. וחכמים פוטרים, Vachachamim potrim, and the חכמים Chachamim
exempt. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? Mai lav beha kamiflagi? This is the
debate. מר סבר למדים, Mar savar lemadim, that you can learn from
the ו vov can allow you to learn the above from the
below, you don't only learn down, you learn up. ומר סבר אין
למדים, Umar savar ein lemadim, you don't. Okay, that's a reasonable explanation
of the debate. And if that's the debate, then we have to
figure out how do we know by the case that a cow
עולה olah is slaughtered in the north if according to some opinions
you can't learn with a ו vov from below to above. So
אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa no. דכולי עלמא למדים. Dechulei alma
lemadim. Everybody says the ו vov you can learn from below to
above, and that'll let us say that everybody says that's how you
learn that a cattle gets slaughtered in the north as well. והיינו
טעמא דרבנן, Vehaynu taama deRabanan, here's the reason of the רבנן. Rabanan.
נאמר כאן מצות Ne'emar kan mitzvot ונאמר בחטאת חלב מצות. Vene'emar bechatas
chelev mitzvot. Because here it says מצות mitzvot from כי תחטא בשגגה
מכל מצות השם Ki techeta bishgaga mikol mitzvot Hashem אשר לא תעשינה,
Asher lo te'asenah, okay, אשר לא תעשינה. Asher lo te'asenah. Anyway,
מצות. mitzvot. Okay, and it says ונאמר חטאת מצות. Vene'emar chatas mitzvot.
So this links you and this tells you the basic principle that
אשם תלוי, asham taluy, אשם ספקות asham svekos is only by a
normal sin that you would otherwise bring a חטאת chatat for.
Other than רבי עקיבא, Rabi Akiva, okay, wait a minute.
So really in principle the ו vov would tell you to learn
up. Okay, and that's why everybody can say that by the cattle
you slaughtered on the north. But here there's a very specific reason
the rabbis want to limit it, because the מצות mitzvot limit it
to a חטאת, chatat, a normal חטאת, chatat, what we call חטאת
חלב, chatas chelev, a normal חטאת chatat for which you bring a
fixed, you know, חטאת chatat for, it's a חטאת, chatat, it's not
an אשם, asham, it's fixed, it's not like עולה ויורד. oleh veyored.
So the classic example of that that is חלב, chelev, forbidden fat.
So that's what מצות mitzvot does. So normally you would learn up
and you can learn up by the case of slaughtering cattle in
the north, but the word מצות mitzvot here tells you no, it's
only going to be for a normal חטאת. chatat. מה להלן דבר
שחייבין על זדונו כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת, Ma lehalan davar shechayavin al
zedono kares veal shigagato chatat,
the same way there it's something that you get כרת kares for
and otherwise you bring a חטאת, chatat, אף כאן שחייבין על זדונו
כרת ועל שגגתו חטאת, af kan shechayavin al zedono kares veal shigagato
chatat, an אשם asham is only for something that's just like that,
that you'd bring a fixed חטאת chatat for, an אשם ספק, asham
safek, אשם תלוי. asham taluy. ורבי עקיבא, Verabi Akiva,
רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva would say back, so if that's true, how
does, what does רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva do? If this is linked
to a normal חטאת, chatat, how does he override that link? So
he would tell you מה להלן בקבועה אף כאן בקבועה. Ma lehalan
bikvuah af kan bikvuah. I'll admit to you that the link of
מצות mitzvot to link it to a normal חטאת chatat is to
tell you that it can't be a variable cost קרבן. korban. You
would not bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy for a, for עולה
ויורד, oleh veyored, okay, for חטאת chatat that's עולה ויורד. oleh veyored.
But you could bring it for an אשם asham if it's not
something that you basically, you know, that the nature of the קרבן
korban shifts based
on your wealth. You know, a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh veyored,
if you're wealthy you bring an animal, if not you bring a
bird, if not you bring a
מנחה, mincha, that you don't bring an אשם תלוי asham taluy for.
Okay, an אשם תלוי asham taluy you're only going to bring for
something that's a fixed, sort of regular, you know, the type of
קרבן korban is always the same, which is a normal חטאת, chatat,
but for רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva also a normal אשם. asham. So
מצות mitzvot limits you to fixed types of קרבנות, korbanot, but it
does not limit you just to חטאת chatat and exclude אשם. asham.
So it'd be the same thing for אשם שפחה חרופה asham shifcha
charufa
and all those other yellow ones, right? In principle, yeah, although we'll
get to that in a minute. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this, ורבי עקיבא מה להלן בקבועה אף כאן בקבועה, Verabi Akiva
ma lehalan bikvuah af kan bikvuah, לאפוקי חטאת דטומאת מקדש וקדשיו דעולה
ויורד, la'afukei chatas detumas mikdash vekodashav de'oleh veyored,
as opposed to that type of a חטאת chatat of when you're
טמא tamei going into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that what type
of קרבן korban you bring depends on your ability to afford.
And what do the rabbis say? In that case would you also
be bringing?
No, of course not. The rabbis have a narrower scope than רבי
עקיבא. Rabi Akiva. ורבנן, Verabanan,
and the rabbis would say back, אין גזרה שוה למחצה. ein gezera
shava lemechetza. No, once you're linking it to a חטאת, chatat, you
can't say I'm just going to link it to this idea fixed
value. Once the אשם תלוי asham taluy is linked to a חטאת,
chatat, it has to be, you don't do halfways. So it's fully
linked to a חטאת, chatat, which basically means that not only fixed
value, but only a חטאת. chatat. And you're not going to bring
an אשם תלוי asham taluy for a, another אשם, asham, for אשם
מעילות. asham me'ilot. ורבי עקיבא נמי אין גזרה שוה למחצה. Verabi Akiva
nami ein gezera shava lemechetza. So the גמרא Gemara considers that to
be a pretty powerful argument. If the word מצות mitzvot is going
to link it to a חטאת, chatat, then yeah, you really are
linked to a חטאת. chatat. And how are you now going to
say that it expands and applies even to an אשם? asham? אין
הכי נמי, Ein hachi nami, that's true. והכא בהא קמיפלגי. Vehacha beha
kamiflagi. רבי עקיבא סבר Rabi Akiva savar ואם נפש כתיב, Ve'im nefesh
kesiv, ו מוסיף על ענין ראשון. vov mosif al inyan rishon.
Okay, so it's not exactly clear that sort of what we were
just saying before. It sounds like the גמרא Gemara is going to
say like this: In principle I'm right. מצות mitzvot doesn't just tell
you קבועה. kvuah. We can all agree, we רבי עקיבא Rabi Akiva
and רבנן, Rabanan, that מצות mitzvot tells you that an אשם תלוי
asham taluy applies
to
a חטאת. chatat. But that's what the word says. But it doesn't
חטאת קבועה. chatas kvuah. But it doesn't tell you only a חטאת
קבועה. chatas kvuah. It tells you it does apply to a חטאת
קבועה. chatas kvuah. What now the ו vov though says, oh, link
it to the above and it also applies to an אשם מעילות.
asham me'ilot. So we're back to where we started. רבי עקיבא Rabi
Akiva says you're going to use the ו vov to go back
up here and to say it applies to the אשם. asham. this
tells you חטאת קבועה Chatas Kevuah and then we're going to say
plus אשם מעילות. Asham Meilos. So what are the רבנן Rabbanan saying?
It seems like we've come full circle. The Rabbis say you don't
use the ו vav to apply above. So let's see what the
רבנן Rabbanan say here. ורבנן נמי הכתיב ואם נפש Verabbanan nami haksiv
ve'im nefesh
and you're trying to claim that everybody says you do use the
ו vav to apply above and that's how we know that a
cattle is slaughtered in the north. The גמרא Gemara says, לימא בהא
קמיפלגי. Leima be'ha kamifligi. Ah, maybe here's the debate. דמר סבר היקש
עדיף ומר סבר גזירה שוה עדיף. Demar savar heikesh adif umar savar
gezeirah shavah adif. This thing is linked in two ways. It's linked
here by a היקש, heikesh, okay, and it's linked by מצות, mitzvos,
it says מצות mitzvos by חטאת חלב, Chatas Cheilev, by חטאת קבועה,
Chatas Kevuah, okay, and it's got that's a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah,
okay. So
the
question is, right, are you going which one is more powerful? Now
of course the funny thing is is that Rabbi Akiva if you
were to say this is more powerful and we're going to focus
on this and not this then maybe it would only be for
that, maybe it wouldn't be for חטאת חלב. Chatas Cheilev. So it's
not really like which one is more powerful like one wins and
the other doesn't but somehow for Rabbi Akiva the היקש heikesh is
enough to say even though there's a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, the
היקש heikesh can add to the גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Whereas the
Rabbis are going to say no the היקש heikesh can't add, it's
totally defined by the גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. So in general, we
can all agree that the ו vav allows you to apply it
above. And that's again how we get the idea that a cattle
is slaughtered in the north. But here we have this limited or
linked in this way and once it's already linked in this way
can the ו vav also do its work? Rabbi Akiva says yes
and the Rabbis say no. Okay, so let's say that's the debate.
דמר סבר היקש עדיף ומר סבר גזירה שוה עדיף. Demar savar heikesh
adif umar savar gezeirah shavah adif. לא דכולי עלמא
היקש עדיף. Lo dechuli alma heikesh adif. Everybody would agree you go
by the היקש. heikesh. Okay, so we're back by square one. So
why not bring it by אשם מעילות, Asham Meilos, why not bring
an אשם תלוי? Asham Talui? ואמרי לך רבנן Ve'amri lach Rabbanan תחתון
הוא דגמר מעליון tachton hu degamar me'elyon לאשם בכסף שקלים le'asham bechessef
shekalim שלא תאמר לא יהא ספקו shelo tomar lo yehei sefeko, חמור
מודאו chamur mivado מה ודאו חטאת בדנקא mah vado chatas bedanka אף
ספקו נמי אשם בדנקא. af sefeko nami asham bedanka. So what we're
going to say is we agree to the היקש heikesh but we're
going to learn in the opposite direction. Do you remember here what
I circled was כסף שקלים. chessef shekalim. כסף שקלים Chessef shekalim means
that an אשם asham has to cost at least two שקל. shekel.
Okay, the Torah gives a minimum cost for an אשם. asham. Now
a חטאת, chatas, the גמרא Gemara says בדנקא, bedanka,
you can even buy it with a דנקא danka which is like
a sixth of a שקל. shekel. There's no minimum it means like,
you know, for pennies. Of course go try to buy a sheep
for pennies but whatever. There's no minimum cost for a חטאת. chatas.
So if there's no minimum cost for a חטאת, chatas, there's a
minimum cost for this
אשם, asham, what about an אשם תלוי? Asham Talui? So logically you
could say look if I actually did the sin I would have
to bring a חטאת chatas which I could spend pennies
on. So if I don't even know if I did the sin,
it's an אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, maybe certainly there would be no
minimum cost. That's a good הוה אמינא. hava amina. So it says
no, actually this link and now what we're saying is the היקש
heikesh goes in the opposite direction. Okay, this link is telling you
apply this principle of כסף שקלים chessef shekalim and apply it down
here and say that even an אשם תלוי Asham Talui you have
to spend a minimum amount on. Some of the, you know, מוסר
mussar thinkers I think it's Rabbeinu Yonah makes a big deal about
this. He says, you know, when we know that we've sinned then
we can, you know, more concretely own our responsibility and do תשובה
teshuvah easier and so on. When we're not sure we have ways
of rationalizing it and not really engaging, you know, whatever. So actually
the Torah's actually telling you you're like no it's actually forcing you
more to like pony up, you know, and put forth if you
have a ספק safek you have to spend this minimum amount. But
I would have had a הוה אמינא hava amina not that way.
So in the end what we're saying is the Rabbi Akiva is
saying use the היקש heikesh go up and the רבנן Rabbanan are
saying no use the היקש heikesh go down and use the היקש
heikesh to tell you that this הלכה halachah that you have to
spend a minimum amount on the אשם ספק, Asham Safek, on the
אשם תלוי. Asham Talui. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Let's
read that again. לא דכולי עלמא היקש עדיף. Lo dechuli alma heikesh
adif. Everybody agrees that the היקש heikesh again I don't know if
it's עדיף adif but we also say the היקש. heikesh. ואמרי לך
רבנן Ve'amri lach Rabbanan but the Rabbis will say maybe in principle
when it comes to שחיטה shechitah in the north and that issue
the ו vav can we can say apply
up, you know, you don't you are allowed to apply up. But
in this case we're not going to apply up. In this case
what we'd rather do is apply down, apply the היקש heikesh in
the opposite way. תחתון הוא דגמר מעליון, Tachton hu degamar me'elyon, the
bottom one we'll learn from the top. לאשם בכסף שקלים Le'asham bechessef
shekalim שלא תאמר shelo tomar לא יהא ספקו, lo yehei sefeko
a ספק safek that you bring by an אשם תלוי Asham Talui
should the cost should not be weightier weightier חמור מודאו chamur mivado
when you do a definite sin. מה ודאו חטאת בדנקא Mah vado
chatas bedanka when you definite sin you bring a חטאת chatas and
that can even be for pennies. אף ספקו נמי אשם בדנקא. Af
sefeko nami asham bedanka.
So when you have a ספק, safek, when you have an אשם
תלוי, Asham Talui, maybe also it's also for pennies. So therefore the
היקש heikesh tells you no, an אשם תלוי Asham Talui even though
it's only for a ספק, safek, you also have to spend a
minimum amount you have to spend a minimum two שקל. shekel. So
in principle going back to our point, everybody says that the ו
vav So אף ספיקו, af sfeiko, אף ספיקו אשם בת דנקא, af
sfeiko asham bat danka, בר דנקא. bar danka. So when you have
a ספק, safeik, when you have an אשם תלוי, asham taluy, maybe
also it's also for pennies. So therefore the היקש hekesh tells you
no, an אשם תלוי asham taluy even though it's only for a
ספק, safeik, you also have to spend a minimum amount, you have
to spend a minimum two שקל. shekel. So in principle, going back
to our point, everybody says that with a ו vav you can
learn up and that teaches you that a cattle you שחט shecht
in the north, but in this case they're debating do you learn
up or do you learn down? Wait, let's just finish this point.
Okay, now, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, הסברא מנליה, hasvara minalei, where does
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva know the minimum cost of an אשם? asham?
נפקא ליה מזאת תורת האשם, nafka lei mizot Torat haAsham, this is
the law of the אשם, asham, תורה אחת לכל האשמות. Torat achat
lechol haashamot.
That teaches you that to treat all אשמות ashamot the same, and
therefore that allows you to globalize and say if this is the
minimum for one אשם, asham, it's the minimum for other. תינח מאן
דאית ליה תורת, teinach man de'it lei Toras, that's good if you
דרש darshan תורת Toras to allow you to sort of globally apply
those. מאן דלית ליה תורת מהיכא גמר, man deleit lei Toras meheicha
gamar, where do you learn it from? גמר בערכך בערכך, gamar b'erkecha
b'erkecha, like that's why I had it says בערכך, b'erkecha, I think
I missed out, בערכך, b'erkecha, כסף שקלים, kesef shekalim, and here it
says בערכך, b'erkecha, I had בערכך b'erkecha here, בערכך. b'erkecha. So that
tells you to link that actually is
in the value, the value of כסף שקלים. kesef shekalim. So that
allows us to learn out that amount and the היקש hekesh I
was still saying to tell me that you bring an אשם תלוי
asham taluy for a ספק מעילה. safek me'ilah. Okay, so גמר בערכך
בערכך. gamar b'erkecha b'erkecha. תינח היכא דכתיב בערכך. teinach heicha d'chtiv b'erkecha.
Now now this is similar to Michael's question, although Michael was asking
I think for the other issue, but anyway, that is good where
it says בערכך b'erkecha to tell you that you have to spend
two שקל, shekel, okay, which is what's but אשם שפחה חרופה asham
shifchah charufah דלא כתיב ביה בערכך מהיכא למימר? delo ktiv bei b'erkecha
meheicha leimeimar? How about an אשם שפחה חרופה? asham shifchah charufah? It
doesn't say בערכך, b'erkecha, where do we know there that you have
to spend, because now we're saying this idea that you have to
spend two שקל shekel on an אשם asham is not just here
and not just here, it's true about all the אשמות. ashamot. So
if you learned it from זאת תורת האשם, zot Torat haAsham, fine,
but if you learned it only because of, I mean the גמרא
Gemara could have asked this according to the idea that you learned
it based on the ו vav too, how do you know to
globalize it more? But okay, anyway here we're learning if you learn
it based on בערכך, b'erkecha, how do you globalize it to other,
apply it to other אשמות? ashamot? So גמר באיל באיל, gamar b'ayil
b'ayil, because of the same word איל, ayil, איל ayil allows you
to apply it more broadly. Okay, now there's other cases also, there's
an אשם. asham. I think רש"י, Rashi, if you look at רש"י,
Rashi, בערכך בערכך, b'erkecha b'erkecha, באשם תלוי ובאשם גזילות כתיב בערכך לאשם.
b'asham taluy u'v'asham gezeilot ktiv b'erkecha l'asham. Okay, both of them it
says
בערכך. b'erkecha. Okay, one minute, and now אשם נזיר, asham nazir, אשם
מצורע, asham metzora, there, because actually it's not the הלכה halachah of
two שקלים, shekalim, אשם נזיר, asham nazir, אשם מצורע asham metzora you
don't bring an איל, ayil, you bring a sheep, which is a
baby איל ayil or whatever, and therefore actually there the הלכה halachah
is it's only one שקל, shekel, as we somehow assume if an
איל ayil which is two years old or whatever is two שקל,
shekel, a sheep is one שקל. shekel. So actually it's not true
about all אשמות, ashamot, but it's true about the אשמות ashamot that
we that we buy a subset of the אשמות. ashamot. Okay, so
anyway, so this is what we have. Upshot of all of this
is this teaches us these various links about certain things about the
אשמות, ashamot, debated whether you have an אשם תלוי asham taluy by
a אשם asham for the sake of אשם מעילה, asham me'ilah, but
anyway everybody agrees a ו vav when היקש hekesh can in principle
apply up and that's how we learn the idea that a what
do you call it? That a cattle is שחט shecht in the
north. Yes, Michael, cattle עולה. olah.
In terms of חטאת טומאת מקדש וקדשיו, chatat tumat mikdash v'kodashav, so
I think we were saying that both רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
the רבנן Rabbanan agree that if you're not sure then you don't
bring an אשם asham for it. Correct. So then what do you
do? I guess that's what the ציץ tzitz is for, to מכפר
mechaper on that?
No, the ציץ tzitz is more to be מכפר mechaper for for
like
טומאה. tumah. No, that's for like יום כיפור Yom Kippur and תשובה
teshuvah is for and that's what I mean no, it is also
what the קרבנות korbanot of oh if it's specifically טומאת מקדש וקדשיו,
tumat mikdash v'kodshav, no no but that's not the sin of טומאה,
tumah, that's like טומאה סתם tumah stam and to be מרצה meratzeh
the קרבנות. korbanot. No, the sin of טומאת מקדש וקדשיו tumat mikdash
v'kodshav according to the גמרא Gemara is what all the חטאות chataot
on the רגלים regalim are for and what the חטאות chataot on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur are for. But there are sins that you
might not know that are that you know you have to just
do תשובה teshuvah for, that you don't get a קרבן korban
for. Alright, so let's continue. Now, חטאת מנלן דבעיא צפון? chatat minalan
d'ba'ya tzafon?
So that is how we know the עולה. olah. We started with
the עולה olah and then we digressed. But now we got basically
whether it's a sheep עולה olah or a cow עולה olah we
know the עולה olah is the north. How do you know now
for חטאת? chatat? And this is really פסוקים, psukim, all the פסוקים
psukim when they talk about a חטאת chatat say במקום אשר תשחט
העולה תשחט החטאת...
bimkom asher tishchat ha'olah tishchat
hachatat... whatever. So חטאת מנלן דבעיא צפון? chatat minalan d'ba'ya tzafon? דכתיב,
d'chtiv, so we're not even going to although our משנה mishna started
with the inner חטאת chatat we're going to just start about a
חטאת chatat in general, okay? So it says ושחט את החטאת במקום
העולה. v'shachata et hachatat bimkom ha'olah. Now it speaks about this in
a few places. So let's get back our let's open back our
חומש. Chumash.
So it
says like this,
it
says
in ויקרא ד'
כ"ז: Vayikra
daled chaf zayin:
ונפש כי תחטא בשגגה מעם הארץ, v'nefesh ki techeta bishgagah me'am ha'aretz,
okay. And then it says da da da da da וסמך ידו
וסמך ידו על ראש החטאת
Vesamach yado,
vesamach yado al rosh hachatat וסמך ידו על
ראש החטאת
Vesamach yado al rosh hachatat
ושחט את החטאת במקום
העולה.
Veshachat et hachatat
bimkom haolah.
Okay so that's what it says by a normal חטאת. hachatat. That's
a case of חטאת יחיד. hachatat yachid. Okay, במקום העולה bimkom haolah
pretty explicit. Now earlier when it talks about a חטאת נשיא, hachatat
nasi, it says the following. This is earlier. Okay, so earlier when
it talks about a חטאת נשיא hachatat nasi it says אשר נשיא
יחטא. Asher nasi yecheta.
This is in ד כב.
Daled Chaf Bet.
It says
אשר לא תעשינה asher lo teasena da da da da da וסמך
ידו על ראש השעיר vesamach yado al rosh haseir so he brings
a שעיר seir וסמך ידו על ראש השעיר vesamach yado al rosh
haseir ושחט אותו במקום אשר ישחט את
העולה.
veshachat oto bimkom
asher yishchat et
haolah.
So that seems pretty clear, right? All right. So let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara has to say about all of this.
חטאת מנלן דבעי צפון? Chatat minalan deba'ei tzafon?
How do you know it's north? דכתיב ושחט את החטאת במקום העולה.
Dechtiv veshachat et hachatat bimkom haolah. Okay so that is the one
about the normal חטאת יחיד. hachatat yachid. We're starting with that. So,
אשכחן שחיטה קבלה
מנלן? Ashkchan shechita kabala minalan?
How do you know it has to be caught in the north?
דכתיב ולקח הכהן מדם החטאת. Dechtiv velakach hacohen midam hachatat.
Okay that's the next פסוק pasuk afterwards. מקבל עצמו מנלן? Mikabel atzmo
minalan? How do you know the... so he takes מדם החטאת midam
hachatat is somehow read as from where the חטאת hachatat is being
slaughtered that's where he has to be, the blood has to be
caught. מקבל עצמו מנלן? Mikabel atzmo minalan? How do you know the
person catching the blood has to be standing in the north? And
here's an interesting הלכה. halacha. The person doing the שחיטה shechita doesn't
have to be standing in the north. You might remember that the
person doing the שחיטה shechita doesn't even have to be standing in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash if you get a long enough knife.
Okay? But the person catching the blood because once you get to
the blood it's a כהן cohen issue, the כהן cohen has to
be standing in the north when he's catching the blood. So how
do you know that the person catching the blood has to be
standing in the north? Okay מקבל עצמו מנלן? mikabel atzmo minalan? אמר
קרא ולקח. Amar kra velakach. So ולקח מדם
החטאת velakach midam hachatat which we mean to mean catching the blood,
we're going to play this word in the ולקח velakach we mean
לו יקח. lo yikach. Like take the words ו' ל' vav lamed
and reverse the letters as opposed to ולקח velakach it's לו יקח.
lo yikach. Take himself, place himself where the blood is being caught.
All right. Anyway, that's how you get the idea that this is
in the north. Now, אשכחן למצוה לעכב מנלן? Ashkchan lemitzvah leakeiv minalan?
Now the גמרא Gemara could have asked us about an עולה, olah,
we'll get back to an עולה olah in a minute. But this
is now this general principle that by all these laws of קרבנות
korbanot for whatever reason the גמרא Gemara assumes, it never assumes this
anywhere else, it doesn't say like it says ולקחתם לכם פרי עץ
הדר כפות תמרים velakachtem lachem pri etz hadar kapot temarim etc. אשכחן
למצוה לעכב מנלן? Ashkchan lemitzvah leakeiv minalan?
You know, you know it doesn't say like וקשרתם אותם על ידך
ukashtam otam al yadecha you know, אשכחן למצוה. ashkchan lemitzvah.
Now every time the normally says you do something, you assume you
gotta do it this way, if you don't do it, it's not
good. Some reason when it comes to קרבנות, korbanot, maybe because there
are so many details, the גמרא Gemara assumes that we're not going
to assume any particular one is מעכב meakeiv unless it's repeated. Fascinating
approach, assumption. So how do we know that that is this is
מעכב? meakeiv? We learned that it has to be in the north,
how do we know that if you don't do it, it prevents
it from being good? אשכחן למצוה לעכב מנלן? Ashkchan lemitzvah leakeiv minalan?
קרא אחרינא כתיב. Kra achrina ktiv.
There's another verse. ושחט אותו במקום אשר ישחט את העולה. Veshachat oto
bimkom asher yishchat et haolah. So that's this verse. ושחט אותו במקום
אשר ישחט את העולה. Veshachat oto bimkom asher yishchat et haolah. That's
by חטאת נשיא. hachatat nasi. So somehow that repeats it and that
tells you it's got we're more serious about it. Okay. So, דתניא
detanya היכן עולה נשחטת? heichan olah nishchetet? בצפון. Batzafon.
Now, where what is the מקום אשר ישחט עולה? makom asher yishchat
olah? Obviously the north. אצלו בצפון. Etzlo batzafon. Okay good. וכי Vechie
page דף מ"ח עמוד ב' Daf Mem Chet Amud Bet וכי מהיכא
תיתי Vechie meheicha teiti
is this where you learn that the idea that a חטאת chatat
is in the north from? והלא כבר נאמר במקום אשר תשחט העולה
תשחט החטאת. Vhalo kvar ne'emar bimkom asher tishchat haolah tishchat hachatat.
So that is a different פסוק. pasuk. That is a פסוק pasuk
of where's that פסוק? pasuk? Hold on.
424 is that it right there? Yeah, במקום אשר תשחט העולה לפני
ה'.
bimkom asher
tishchat
haolah
lifnei Hashem.
No, that's what we just had. The next פסוק. pasuk.
429 it's in ויקרא ו'. Vayikra Vav. פרק ו'.
Perek Vav. Okay.
All right. It's in it's in the beginning of צו. Tzav. 6:18.
Right, 'cause צו *Tzav* repeats the קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*. So right, דבר
אל אהרן ואל בניו לאמר זאת תורת החטאת במקום אשר תשחט העלה
תשחט החטאת לפני השם קדש קדשים היא *daber el aharon v'el banav
lemor zot torat ha-chatat bimkom asher tishachat ha-olah tishachat ha-chatat lifnei Hashem
kodesh kodashim hi*.
So that's in צו *Tzav*, so this is in ויקרא *Vayikra*, okay,
but over here in צו *Tzav* it gives a very nice, okay,
this is ויקרא *Vayikra*, in צו *Tzav* it gives a very nice
global statement. And it says, במקום אשר תשחט העלה תשחט החטאת *bimkom
asher tishachat ha-olah tishachat ha-chatat*. And that's just general, זאת תורת *zot
torat*, right? It's זאת תורת החטאת *zot torat ha-chatat*. So it's clearly
sort of saying it's a general principle, okay, זאת תורת החטאת במקום
אשר תשחט העלה תשחט החטאת *zot torat ha-chatat bimkom asher tishachat ha-olah
tishachat
ha-chatat*. So this is a general principle. So here you've got a
general principle that it's always in the north. So why is it
repeated here? It's repeated here לעכב l'akev, *le-akev*. Okay, and then you
could say the same thing, it's repeated here לעכב *le-akev*. So we'll
see in that. Okay, והלא כבר נאמר במקום אשר תשחט עולה olah,
תשחט החטאת הלמה יצא לקבוע לו מקום *v'halo kvar ne'emar bimkom asher
tishachat olah tishachat ha-chatat halama yatza likvo'a lo makom*. Why is this
singled out here by the חטאת chatas. נשיא *chatat nasi* for whatever
reason this דרשה drasha. *drasha* is starting on the חטאת chatas. נשיא
*chatat nasi*, to fix its place. שאם לא שחטה בצפון פסול pasul.
*she-im lo shachatah b'tzafon pasul*, to say that if you didn't do
it, it's invalid. אמרת לומר לכך יצא או אינו אלא ella שזה
טעון צפון ואין אחר טעון צפון *amarta lomar lekach yatza o eino
ela she-zeh ta'un tzafon v'ein acher ta'un tzafon*, maybe when it says
ושחט אתו *v'shachat oto*, אתו *oto* is coming to say, oh by
the way, this is the only one that needs north, nothing else
needs a north, okay, תלמוד לומר ושחט את החטאת במקום העלה *talmud
lomar v'shachat et ha-chatat bimkom ha-olah*.
So here it says no, this also needs north, okay, so don't
read the אתו *oto* to mean only this. This is repeated to
say it's מעכב m'akev *me-akev*, what we're going to do with the
אתו *oto* we'll talk about in a minute, okay, and there this
is repeated here to tell you don't read the אתו *oto* to
limit it here, you need it here, you need it here, you
need it by all חטאות *chataot* and it's מעכב m'akev, *me-akev*. תלמוד
לומר ושחט במקום העלה *talmud lomar v'shachat bimkom ha-olah*. זה בני אב
לכל חטאות שיהו טעונות צפון *zeh bnei av l'chol chataot she-yehu te'unot
tzafon*. Okay, אשכחן שעיר נשיא בין למצוה בין לעכב שאר חטאות נמי
אשכחן למצוה לעכב מנלן *ashkan se'ir nasi bein l'mitzvah bein l'akev shear
chataot nami ashkan l'mitzvah l'akev minalan*. Okay, now this is a funny
question. It says okay, this is repeated, so this is מעכב m'akev.
*me-akev*. Other חטאות *chataot*, how do you know that they're מעכב me'akev
*me-akev*? So the funny point is, what do you mean how do
you know they're מעכב me'akev *me-akev*? You have it repeated here as
well, right? Why assume that here it's repeated and here it's מעכב
*me-akev* and here we don't say the same thing that it's repeated
and it should be מעכב *me-akev* there is a little strange. רש״י
*Rashi* tries to sort of figure that whole thing out. Hold on,
let me just check רש״י *Rashi* again if I could figure out
what רש״י *Rashi*
is
saying.
Minute. I guess what the point is, I think the point is
that somehow since we're reading these two together, right, rather than seeing
this as a global, I think this is רש״י *Rashi*'s point, rather
than seeing this as a global and then it's a global plus
this or it's מעכב *me-akev* here plus this, it's מעכב *me-akev* here,
we're somehow reading these two, I don't know why exactly, combined, okay,
to be talking about this type of a חטאת chatas *chatat*, maybe
because this one appears first even though I wrote it here second.
So how do we know this is not just a special like
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* here? How do we know that this also is
something that is doubled, okay, and that is מעכב *me-akev*?
I think רש״י *Rashi* kind of understands it.
How do you explain this?
I think רש״י *Rashi* was saying it says ושחט אתו *v'shachat oto*
regarding שעיר נשיא *se'ir nasi*, right, and then you need another פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* to clarify that ושחט אתו *v'shachat oto* doesn't למעט *l'ma'et*
the other חטאת chatas, *chatat* completely from תורת החטאת *torat ha-chatat*.
Correct. But then the point is that even though this is saying
that this goes beyond just שעיר נשיא *se'ir nasi* and applies to
other חטאות *chataot*, we don't have, we're not able to use this
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* to say that this also, that this now applies
here and you have two פסוקים psukim *p'sukim*, that's the only thing
that's bothering me. Right. Somehow we start by assuming that these are
the two, that these are both talking about שעיר נשיא *se'ir nasi*
and this broadens and says no, it's not only שעיר נשיא *se'ir
nasi* that needs north, but somehow we're still not entitled to use
this as a doubling. So we only have this as a single
and therefore we want to know how is it מעכב *me-akev* by
the other ones? Okay, אלא ella, אי הכי *ela i hachi* the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אשכחן שעיר נשיא בין למצוה בין לעכב שאר
חטאות נמי אשכחן למצוה לעכב מנלן דכתיב בכשבה וכתיב בשעירה *ashkan se'ir
nasi bein l'mitzvah bein l'akev shear chataot nami ashkan l'mitzvah l'akev minalan
d'chtiv b'chesevah v'chtiv b'se'irah*, 'cause it says it twice. It says both
by, you know, by the, if it's a, if it's a כשבה
*chesevah*, it says במקום העלה *bimkom ha-olah*, and if it's a, and
if it's a שעירה *se'irah*, it says במקום העלה *bimkom ha-olah*. So
the doubling that appears here tells you that this also is מעכב
*me-akev*. So it's מעכב *me-akev* by שעיר נשיא *se'ir nasi* because of
this doubling and it's מעכב *me-akev* by the שאר חטאות *shear chataot*
because it's doubled within. that פרשה *parsha* itself when it talks about
the sheep and it talks about the goat. Okay, אלא ella אותו
oso למה לי *ela oso lama li* so fine so then what's
the אותו oso, *oso* doing if all of this is מעכב *me'akeiv*
and אותו oso, *oso* isn't limiting the scope of some of these
to just the שעיר נשיא *se'ir nasi*, what is the אותו oso,
*oso* doing? מיבעיא ליה לכדתניא *mibaya lei l'chidi tanya*: אותו oso. בצפון
ואין שעיר נחשון בצפון *oso batzafon v'ein se'ir nachshon batzafon*.
This goat that's a חטאת chatat. *chatas* is in the north. But
another חטאת chatat, *chatas* goat is not in the north. What other
חטאת chatat. *chatas* male goat? Because usually a חטאת chatat *chatas* is
a female.
What
other חטאת chatat *chatas* male goat? The חטאת chatat *chatas* that נחשון
*nachshon* and the- not just נחשון *nachshon*, but it's called him because
he was the first, the goats that the נשיאים *nesi'im* brought. We
just read that at the end of last week's פרשה *parsha*. Right?
What did it say at the end of last week's פרשה *parsha*?
It said- no, not excuse me. Yeah, hold on. Right? It
says: ויהי המקריב ביום הראשון
את קרבנו נחשון בן עמינדב למטה יהודה
פר אחד בן בקר איל
אחד כבש אחד בן שנתו לעלה שעיר עזים אחד לחטאת *vayehi hamakriv
bayom harishon es korbano nachshon ben amminadav l'matei yehuda par echad ben
bakar ayil echad keves echad ben shenaso l'ola se'ir izim echad l'chatas*.
A male שעיר לחטאת *se'ir l'chatas*.
Okay, so that's also what you bring on like the רגלים *regalim*,
שעיר עזים אחד לחטאת *se'ir izim echad l'chatas*. But here it was
brought as an individual חטאת chatat *chatas*, and it's very rare. The
only time you have an individual חטאת Chatas, *chatas* that's a שעיר
*se'ir* is the נשיא *nasi*. Okay, it's actually interesting. This is a
נשיא *nasi*, right? These are the נשיאים *nesi'im*. Okay, but this is
a נשיא *nasi* for a חטא *chet*, this is obligatory. This was
a נשיא *nasi* as a free-will חטאת *chatas*, which is bizarre. What's
a free-will חטאת *chatas* or whatever. Anyway, okay, so what are the
הלכות halachos *halachos* of that חטאת *chatas* that נחשון *nachshon* brought and
that the other נשיאים *nesi'im* brought? So here we're saying that because
it's a special category, it does not have to be shechted in
the north. אותו oso *oso* this שעיר נשיא *se'ir nasi*, this נשיא
*nasi* which is a real חטא נשיא *chet nasi* is in the
north, but not the שעיר נשיאים *se'ir nesi'im* that was a free-will
and that was a special circumstance in the מדבר midbar *midbar*, that
does not have the same הלכה halacha, *halacha*. Okay, ואין שעיר נחשון
בצפון *v'ein se'ir nachshon batzafon*. ותניא *v'tanya*: וסמך ידו על ראש השעיר
*v'samach yado al rosh hase'ir*. לרבות שעיר נחשון לסמיכה *l'rabos se'ir nachshon
l'smicha*, דברי רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, *divrei rabbi yehuda*. רבי שמעון אומר
*rabbi shimon omer*: לרבות שעיר עבודת כוכבים לסמיכה *l'rabos se'ir avodas kochavim
l'smicha*. So why does it say וסמך ידו על ראש השעיר *v'samach
yado al rosh hase'ir* not וסמך ידו על ראשו *v'samach yado al
rosho*? So the extra השעיר *hase'ir* is to tell you there's some
other שעירים *se'irim* that don't explicitly talk about סמיכה smicha *smicha* that
you need סמיכה smicha, *smicha*. So what are they? רבי יהודה *rabbi
yehuda* says the שעיר *se'ir* of נחשון *nachshon*, that did need סמיכה
smicha, *smicha*. We're saying it doesn't need north, but it does need
סמיכה *smicha*. And רבי שמעון *rabbi shimon* says no, שעיר *se'ir* of
עבודה זרה *avoda zara* which is brought by the ציבור *tzibbur* when
they rule incorrectly and so on when the בית דין *beis din*
rules incorrectly. Okay. So that's that debate. But now that we see
that the שעיר נחשון *se'ir nachshon* to some degree for רבי יהודה
*rabbi yehuda*'s being brought into the normal procedure of normal שעירים *se'irim*,
so סלקא דעתך אמינא *salka daitach amina*, I would have thought הואיל
ואישתרבו לסמיכה *ho'il v'israbu l'smicha*, since the שעירים *se'irim* of the נשיאים
*nesi'im* in the מדבר *midbar* are included for סמיכה *smicha*, that normal
procedure, אישתרבו נמי לצפון *israbu nami l'tzafon*, they also should be included
for the צפון *tzafon*, קא משמע לן *kamashma lan* not that way.
Okay, קא משמע לן *kamashma lan* that that's why it says אותו
oso, *oso* that only this שעיר *se'ir* of a נשיא *nasi* is
the north, not the special ones that happened in the מדבר *midbar*.
Now מתיב לה רבינא *maskif lah ravina*, so רבינא *ravina* challenged this.
I get why you need that אותו oso *oso*, הניחא לרבי יהודה
*hanicha l'rabbi yehuda*, I get why you need it for רבי יהודה
*rabbi yehuda* because רבי יהודה *rabbi yehuda* already brought the שעיר נחשון
*se'ir nachshon* to some degree into the normal procedure, so you need
the אותו oso *oso* to say not the north. אלא ella, לרבי
שמעון מאי איכא למימר *ela l'rabbi shimon mai ika l'meimar*? For רבי
שמעון *rabbi shimon*, he never brings the שעירים *se'irim* of the נשיאים
*nesi'im* in the מדבר *midbar* into any normal procedure, so you won't
need the אותו oso *oso* to exclude it from the north. אמר
ליה מר זוטרא בריה דרב טבי לרבינא *amar lei mar zutra brei
de-rav tavi l'ravina*: ולרבי יהודה מי ניחא *u'l'rabbi yehuda mi nicha*? Ah,
you think so I'm going to like make your question even bigger.
Since you think it's good for רבי יהודה *rabbi yehuda*, it's just
not good for רבי שמעון *rabbi shimon*, I say why is it
even good for רבי יהודה *rabbi yehuda*? למאי דאישתרבו אישתרבו ולמאי דלא
אישתרבו לא אישתרבו *l'mai d'israbu israbu v'l'mai d'lo israbu lo israbu*. Even
with רבי יהודה *rabbi yehuda*, it's just a special inclusion for סמיכה
*smicha*, right? But since this whole- the whole שעירים *se'irim* of the
נשיאים *nesi'im* here, this free-will חטאות *chataos* of the נשיאים *nesi'im* are
a whole special category, if it's not explicitly included I'm going to
assume it doesn't apply. So you don't need the אותו oso. *oso*
to exclude it; there's no basis to include it even if I've
already included it for סמיכה *smicha*. וכי תימא אי לא מיעטיה קרא
הוה אמינא hava amina תיתי בבנין אב *v'chi teima ee lo mi'atei
kra hava amina tesei binyan av*, no, because you'll say, well, if
it wasn't for the אותו oto *oso*, I would have learned it
out from like a comparison, you know, the same way this gets-
this gets צפון *tzafon*, this should get צפון *tzafon*. No, אם כן
סמיכה גופא תיתי בבנין אב *im kein smicha gufah tesei binyan av*.
The fact that it's similar to another שעיר וחטאת *se'ir v'chatas* that
we don't say that, because this is a special one, it's the
one brought only in the מדבר *midbar*, and if we were really
going to learn it out from the general שעירי חטאת *se'irei chatas*,
חטאות *chataos*, then we wouldn't have needed a special פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
to teach סמיכה *smicha*. So clearly, the fact that we need a
special פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* for רבי יהודה *rabbi yehuda* to teach סמיכה
*smicha* by the שעיר *se'ir* of נחשון *nachshon* shows us that we're
treating this as its own category that we can't assume the normal
rules apply. The only thing that we're going to apply are things
that are stated explicitly. So if that's true, I don't need אותו
oto to exclude it, just the absence of being included means that
I'm not going to say that it requires the north. So the
גמרא Gemara says
אלא מדורות לא גמרינן. ella madoros lo gamrinan. The reason we'd need
a special פסוק pasuk by סמיכה is because we say this is
a unique קרבן korban that was brought at the time of the
מדבר and we're not going to learn it from קרבנות that apply
throughout the generations. הכא נמי מדורות לא גמרינן. hacha nami madoros lo
gamrinan. So the same would be true about the north. So because
it's a special קרבן, korban, a type of הוראת שעה, hora'as sha'ah,
therefore, right, a special thing that was an exception for that time,
we're going to start with the assumption that nothing applies to it
unless we know otherwise. And therefore, okay, you got a פסוק about
סמיכה, you got a פסוק about סמיכה, but we're still not going
to assume north unless you got a פסוק, we're not going to
assume anything applies to
it. So
the
גמרא Gemara says אלא ella, where are we? What? Question mark. Right.
So therefore what do you need the אותו oto for? אלא אותו
בצפון ואין שוחט בצפון. ella oso batzafon v'ein shochet batzafon. Ah, what
it's coming to tell you is אותו, oto אותו, oto the animal
has to be in the north. When it comes to the catching
of the blood as we mentioned earlier, the person doing the catching
has to be in the north as well because that requires a
כהן. kohen. But here only the אותו, oto only the animal has
to be in the north. You the שוחט shochet can be standing
in the south and שוחט shechting over the line. אותו בצפון ואין
שוחט בצפון. oso batzafon v'ein shochet batzafon. Okay. אלא, so the גמרא
Gemara says fine, that's a nice דרשה. drasha, אלא אותו בצפון ואין
בן עוף בצפון. ella oso batzafon v'ein ben ohf batzafon. I'm sorry,
I skipped a line. Wait a minute. ואין שוחט בצפון. v'ein shochet
batzafon. So the גמרא Gemara, says, but מדרבי חייא נפקא. m'deRebbi Chiya
nafkha. No, you don't learn it from this אותו. You learn it
from a different דרשה, drasha דרשה drasha of רבי חייא. Rebbi Chiya.
דתניא רבי חייא אומר, de-tanya Rebbi Chiya omer, ושחט אתו על ירך
המזבח צפנה. v'shachat oso al yerech hamizbe'ach tzafonah. That's going back to
the עולה, olah? not the חטאת. מה תלמוד לומר, mah talmud lomar,
why does it, what's the אותו by the עולה? olah, לפי שראינו
עומד בצפון ומקבל בצפון. lefi sheratzinu omed batzafon u-mekabel batzafon. Since we
know that when you catch the blood you have to be standing
in the north, ואם עמד בדרום וקיבל בצפון פסול. v'im amad badarom
v'kibel batzafon pasul. If the כהן kohen stood in the south and
caught in the north, it's פסול. יכול אף זה כן, yachol af
zeh ken, maybe by the שחיטה shechita it's the same. תלמוד לומר
אותו. talmud lomar oso. By the שחיטה shechita it says it, the
animal. אותו בצפון ואין שוחט בצפון. oso batzafon v'ein shochet batzafon.
So same הלכה, halacha. same דרשה drasha? of the word אותו, but
an אותו by an עולה, olah not by a חטאת. So we
know this idea that the שוחט shochet doesn't have to be standing
in the north by the עולה olah already. And so if it's
true by the עולה olah, and this is all linked to the
עולה, olah of course it's true to a חטאת as well. So
still what do you need the אותו to teach you over here?
אלא says the גמרא, Gemara אותו בצפון ואין בן עוף בצפון. oso
batzafon v'ein ben ohf batzafon. Okay. This is in the north, but
the מליקה melika that you do by a bird sacrifice, that does
not have to be in the north. דתניא יכול יהא בן עוף
טעון צפון. de-tanya yachol yehei ben ohf taun tzafon. Maybe a bird
sacrifice has to be in the north. ודין הוא, v'din hu,
it
makes
sense. ומה בן צאן שלא קיבל לו כהן קיבל לו צפון. u-mah
ben tzon shelo kibel lo kohen kibel lo tzafon. Sheep that doesn't
require to use the body of the כהן, kohen, you use a
knife, you don't use the כהן's kohen finger, nevertheless has to be
in the
north. בן עוף שקיבל לו כהן אינו דין שיהא צפון. ben ohf
she-kibel lo kohen eino din sheyehei tzafon. Certainly the north, I don't
exactly get these קל וחומרים kal v'chomers but okay. תלמוד לומר אותו.
talmud lomar oso. No, only this חטאת, not a bird. מה, mah,
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, why would I have
made that דרשה? drasha, I could have said, why is it so
obvious that I would have had a הוה אמינא hava amina. of
the north? מה לבן צאן שכן קיבל לו כלי. mah l'ben tzon
shekein kibel lo keli. אלא, say the opposite. A בן צאן ben
tzon requires a כלי שרת. kli shares. Meaning, why is using the
body of a כהן kohen more of a reason to think that
it's more מחמיר machmir and needs the north? I can say the
opposite. A sheep needs a knife, so that needs a north. A
בן עוף ben ohf that doesn't... a bird that doesn't need a
knife shouldn't need the north. Meaning, it's not make more sense to
think whether it needs the כהן kohen or needs a knife is
a better proof whether or not it needs the north. Okay, so
I wouldn't have had a הוה אמינא. hava amina I don't need
אותו to tell me a bird isn't the north because I wouldn't
have had a basis to think that a bird does need the
north. אלא, fine, you're
right. אותו בצפון ואין פסח בצפון. oso batzafon v'ein pesach batzafon. This
is in the north and not the קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Now
what's the הוה אמינא of a קרבן פסח? korban pesach? קרבן פסח
korban pesach is like a שלמים, shelamim, it's קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim.
Why would I have thought a קרבן פסח korban pesach would need
the
north? דתניא, de-tanya, we learned a ברייתא. braisa. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
אומר יכול יהא פסח טעון צפון. Rebbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer yachol
yehei pesach taun tzafon. Here's why. Maybe it should need the north.
ודין הוא, v'din hu, it stands to
reason. ומה עולה שכן לא קיבל לו זמן לשחיטתו קיבל לו צפון.
u-mah olah shekein lo kibel lo zman l'shchitaso kibel lo tzafon. An
עולה olah doesn't have a fixed time, you bring an עולה ola
whenever you want, it has to be the north. פסח, pesach, it's
true פסח pesach is a שלמים, shelamim, but as opposed to all
other types of שלמים, shelamim, they can be brought whenever you want.
פסח pesach is obligatory at a fixed time. שקיבל לו זמן לשחיטתו
אינו דין שיהא צפון. she-kibel lo zman l'shchitaso eino din sheyehei tzafon.
So because of the fixed nature of פסח, pesach, that would have
been a reason to think north. תלמוד לומר אותו. talmud lomar oso.
Okay, so that's why I need the אותו. So the גמרא Gemara
is still not convinced. That would not have been a strong enough
reason to make me think you need a north that you need
a פסוק to tell me you don't. Why? מה לעולה שכן כליל?
ma l'ola sheken kalil? Because then I could have said an עולה
ola. is more reason to need a north. It's fully burnt, so
I can't learn it out from a פסח. Pesach. There would have
been no basis to think that פסח Pesach would have needed a
north. I couldn't have learned it out from עולה. ola, Okay, מחטאת,
mechatat, I'll learn it out from a חטאת. That's not all burnt.
מה לחטאת שכן מכפרת? ma l'chatat sheken mechaperet?
Oh, but that has the greater weightiness that it atones על חייבי
כריתות. al chayavei kiritot. מאשם, me'asham, how about an אשם? asham? מה
לאשם שכן קדשי קדשים. ma l'asham sheken kodshei kodashim. Okay, but so
fine, learn it out from an אשם. asham. No, even an אשם,
asham, even it's קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. And the גמרא Gemara says
מכולן נמי שכן קדשי קדשים. mikulan nami sheken kodshei kodashim. That's the
הלכה. halacha קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim are in the north. So you,
no, I would have had no basis to think that פסח Pesach
would have been in the north. Even though פסח Pesach is a
fixed time, all of the all of the times the תורה Torah
says in the north is by things that are holy of holies.
Now it is a little wonder, you know, you wonder if it's
a little circular, what makes it holy of holies? But the simple
rule is קדשים קלים kodashim kalim can be eaten by the owners
in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim can only be
eaten by the כהנים kohanim in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That
is the basic dividing line. So all the things that are in
the north are either eaten, burnt on the מזבח mizbeach or eaten
by the כהנים kohanim in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash are קדשי
קדשים. kodshei kodashim. So even though פסח Pesach has the idea of
fixed time, there would have been no basis to think that I
could learn from עולה, ola? חטאת, and אשם asham that are in
the north to think that a פסח Pesach was in the north.
So I don't need אותו to exclude פסח. Pesach. I don't have
a basis to learn out פסח. Pesach.
It's strange that the, they're quoting a ברייתא. Baraisa.
I know, the ברייתא Baraisa does learn it out, but the גמרא
Gemara still says, come on, that's not a real that's not a
real need. It is interesting. I know. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says לעולם כדאמרן מעיקרא אותו בצפון ואין שוחט בצפון. le'olam k'de'amran me'ikara
oto b'tzafon v'ein shochet b'tzafon.
Go back to the previous thing. You're fine. You don't know what
אותו is telling you? That only the animal in the north and
not the שוחט shochet in the north. אה, ah, didn't we already
learn that out from an עולה? ola. אבל ואין שוחט בצפון ודקשיא
לך בדרבי אחא נפקא לן. aval v'ein shochet b'tzafon v'dikashya lach bid'Rabbi
Acha nafka lan. We learned it out from Rabbi Acha. לאו למיעוטי
שוחט בצפון. lav l'mi'utei shochet b'tzafon.
You're right. Well, we're not we're not learning out here that the
שוחט shochet doesn't have to be standing in the north. That we
already learned from an עולה. ola What are we learning out here?
אלא אין שוחט בצפון אבל מקבל בצפון. ela ein shochet b'tzafon aval
mekabel b'tzafon. אה, ah, the אותו is coming to tell you like
a double negative. Okay, meaning we know that already from an עולה
ola, that you don't have to be standing in the north, you,
the שוחט, shochet, be standing in the south. אותו is telling you
here that it's telling you this הלכה halacha that you don't have
to be standing in the north that you already know from an
עולה, ola that only applies to the act of שחיטה. shechita. When
it comes to catching the blood, you do have to be standing
in the north. Okay? So by the עולה ola you had a
single negative, as it were, it was telling you, oh, only the
animal, not the stander. And here it's a double negative. That הלכה
halacha of not the stander is not true by something else. It's
not true, so the stander does have to be in the north
by the קבלה. kabala. Okay,
מקבל, mekabel,
the גמרא Gemara says מולקח ולקח נפקא. mi'velakach velakach nafka. The we
learned it out from the word ולקח, velakach, לא יקח. lo yikach.
That was what we said earlier. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
that ולקח ולקח לא משמע ליה. velakach velakach lo mashma lei. Eh,
he doesn't buy that דרשה, the moving around of the ו vav
and the ל lamed or whatever. All right, so finally we've satisfied
ourselves. The extra אותו here teaches you, we already know that you
don't have to be standing in the north for שחיטה, shechita, and
the אותו tells you by catching of the blood, you do have
to be standing in the north. Now, one last point before we
end for today. The גמרא Gemara says like this. אשכחן שחיטה בעולה
למצוה קבלה נמי למצוה אשכחן. ashkechan
shechita b'ola l'mitzvah kabala
nami l'mitzvah ashkechan.
So by the עולה ola? we, this all we had a doubling
of the פסוקים by the שחיטה shechita and so on by the
חטאת. How about by the עולה? ola Okay, by the עולה ola
we found שחיטה shechita for a מצוה mitzvah. and we found קבלה
kabala for a מצוה. Where is the doubling by an עולה ola,
to say that those things have to be in the north even
לעכב, even and if you don't do it, it's no good? So
the גמרא Gemara says קבלה לעכב אשכחן שחיטה וקבלה לעכב מנלן. kabala
l'akev ashkechan shechita v'kabala l'akev minalan. אמר אבא בר אבא ואי תימא
רבא בר שילא קל וחומר. amar Abba bar Abba v'isei ma Rava
bar Shila kal vachomer. ומה חטאת הבאה מכח עולה מעכבת עולה שבא
חטאת מכחה אינו דין שמעכבת? uma chatat haba'ah mikach ola m'akevet ola
sheba chatat mikocha einu din shem'akevet?
Pretty good argument. If the חטאת is saying, do it like you
did the עולה, ola and by a חטאת we learn that it's
מעכב the north, and the תורה Torah is constantly telling you שחט
החטאת shachat hachatat where you שחט shachat the עולה ola in the
north, and now we've learned that by the חטאת north is מעכב,
so certainly the עולה ola which is its paradigm from which it's
being learned, certainly by the עולה ola. it would be מעכב. Pretty
reasonable argument.
So
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, maybe not. מה לחטאת שכן מכפרת
על חייבי כריתות? ma l'chatat sheken mechaperet al chayavei kiritot?
But one minute, a חטאת might be weightier than an עולה. Olah,
Now the funny thing is, it's not a question of weightier or
not weightier. It's a question if it's a derived הלכה halacha, by
the nature sort of of just, you know, something derived can't be.
weightier than the thing it's coming from. It's not like a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. A is weightier than B so A must have
the same הלכות as B. It's by its nature of being derived.
It only inherits the properties of the thing it's derived from. Okay.
אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, so Ravina says, הא קשיא ליה לרב אדא
בר אהבה. ha kashya lei l'Rav Adda bar Ahava. Now this is
really what רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava was saying.
He wasn't just saying סתם stam a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. He
was saying, כלום מצינו טפל חמור מן העיקר. klum matzinu tafel chamur
min ha'ikar. It's not חמור chamur and קל, kal, weighty and light,
that you can then start pointing out, oh, this is weightier in
this way and this is weightier in that way. It's talking about
a derivative. Is something that is derived, could it ever be weightier
than the source of where it comes from? You never get a
copy of something sharper than the original. Okay? So, אמר ליה מר
זוטרא בריה דרב מרי לרבינא, amar leh Mar Zutra brei de'Rav Mari
l'Ravina, בלא? belo? I'll show you a case of a derivative which
is weightier. Now this is a little funny the way that this
is a derivative, it's a different type of
a derivative. ברא מעשר Brai Ma'aser דהוא נפדה. de'hu nifdeh. I have
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, okay, if the stuff became
טמא tamei I can redeem it. ואילו לקוח בכסף מעשר, V'ilu lakuach
b'chesef Ma'aser, if I redeemed my מעשר Ma'aser on money and then
I bought something with my מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni money in ירושלים
Yerushalayim and that became טמא, tamei, אינו נפדה, eino nifdeh, I can't
redeem it. So that's a stricter הלכה, okay? So it's weightier even
though this is a derived קדושה, kedusha, it has more limits. דתנן,
D'tenan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, הלקוח בכסף מעשר שנטמא יפדה.
halakuach b'chesef Ma'aser shenitma yipadeh. רבי יהודה אומר יקבר. Rabbi Yehuda omer
yikaver.
So at least according to רבי יהודה, you can't redeem it even
though it's a derivative קדושה, kedusha, it has more limits. So the
גמרא says no, התם hasam that's not a stringency. It's, it is,
you are more limited, but you're more limited because the קדושה kedusha
is weak. Okay? It's not, so it's not like a weightier status,
it's more limit of what you can do because of the weakness
of the קדושה. kedusha. התם לא אלימא קדושתיה למיתפס פדיונה. hasam lo
alima kedushateh l'mitfas pidyonah.
The קדושה kedusha is because it's a derived קדושה, kedusha, it can't
transfer on to yet another thing. It's not strong enough to transfer
to the next thing. Okay? So there the weakness of it is
like, it's like if we use my loose example of a copy,
okay, you can make, you know, you can make a relatively high
quality copy from the original, but you can't make a relatively high
quality copy from the copy. Okay, that's not a חומרא chumra of
the copy. Okay? It's a weakness of the copy that it doesn't
have the power to do that. So don't read just the limit
here as saying that somehow indicates a weightiness to it. Okay? But
yes, by the עולה, Olah, it is the where it has to
be שחט, shechted, that that limit is reflecting the weightiness of the
קדושה kedusha and the חטאת, and therefore if it's derived from the
עולה, Olah it's not going to be weightier and if it has
to be מעכב in the north, an עולה as well is מעכב
in the north. Okay.