Hi everybody! Today's דף daf is ס"ט, Samech Tet, and we pick
up at the top. And what we have is, we had a
משנה mishnah which basically said, when you do מליקה—right? melikah This is
there's this like bizarre ironic sort of reality, that the way you
slaughter the bird for the bird sacrifice, מליקה melikah through the back
of the neck, under any other sort of circumstances would be considered
like a not even a שחיטה, shechitah, would be like just making
it into a נבלה neveilah and so on. But because it's in
the context of the sacrifice, that's what makes it כשר. kosher. So
then the question becomes, the גמרא Gemara wants to sort of look
at, when would it be a נבלה? neveilah? And the, as I
said the other day, the way to look for this is not
to ask when is it אסור asur to eat, because this might
be אסור asur to eat because it's an עולה, olah, but when
does it cause טומאה tumah when you swallow it, which is the
sign of a bird that's a נבלה? neveilah? Okay? And so it
basically said, if you have the right act—the מליקה—if melikah you have
it on the right object—a sanctified bird—and if you have it in
the right place—in the בית המקדש—then Beit HaMikdash it will not be
a נבלה, neveilah, even if the wrong people do it: you do
it with your left hand, you do it at night. And the
גמרא—we're Gemara going to discuss how wrong is the person. Okay? But
anyway, but even if there's something פסול pasul about the way it's
done, it's not going to be a נבלה. neveilah. If, however, any
one of those components is missing: okay, it was done with a
knife, so it wasn't done מליקה melikah with the fingernail of the
כהן, kohen, so it's the wrong act; or it was done on
the wrong object, it was done on something not sanctified, it was
done on something that wasn't even, as we saw in a ברייתא
baraita in the גמרא, Gemara, that wasn't even a pigeon or turtle
dove, okay, it was too young, or it was missing a limb;
okay, or it was done in the wrong place, it was done
on outside of the בית המקדש—any Beit HaMikdash of those things, it
will be a נבלה. neveilah. Okay? Because ultimately, ultimately you're doing a
מליקה. melikah. However, one minute, if you did an act of שחיטה,
shechitah, not an act of מליקה, melikah, even if it's a שחיטה
shechitah that you shouldn't be doing because it's on a bird sacrifice
or some other type of a reason why you shouldn't be doing
שחיטה shechitah when the normal thing this would demand is מליקה, melikah,
if it's a שחיטה shechitah it's also not a נבלה. neveilah. So
it's a נבלה neveilah if it's a non-שחיטה, shechitah, a מליקה melikah
but somehow the wrong act, on the wrong object or in the
wrong place. One minute, that was the basic point of the משנה.
mishnah. And the גמרא Gemara introduced a debate of רב Rav and
רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: what if a זר zar does it—a non-כהן
kohen does it? Now, one way to conceptualize that is, and because
the language in the גמרא Gemara in the משנה mishnah at the
end was not what I said—act, object, place—the language in the משנה
mishnah at the end was, is it פסולה בקודש pesulah bakodesh or
not פסולה בקודש. pesulah bakodesh. How much is this something that sort
of like is the problem is relevant to this world of the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash versus something that somehow precedes it, which is
a little bigger abstract and sometimes hard to get your exact handle
on. But anyway, so one way to conceptualize the debate of רב
Rav and רבי Rabbi... יוחנן—רב says a זר zar does make it
a נבלה, neveilah, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it does not—is like
how out of base is a זר? zar? Like it's not like
פסולה בקודש. pesulah bakodesh. How much is it completely not relevant to
the world
of קרבנות korbanot that therefore it's considered completely פסול, pasul, it's like
it was out of bounds. Okay? And then that had to do
with some type of a question about a זר zar on a
במה bamah and other types of questions and a זר zar doing
שחיטה shechitah and how out of bounds is a זר? zar? But
the other way, which I think is even the simpler way is,
because we know that מליקה melikah is done with the finger of
the כהן, kohen, the thumb of the כהן, kohen, maybe a זר,
zar, the problem isn't that he's a זר zar as much as
the problem is that it was the wrong object—the wrong act, meaning
the act is with, the same way if you do it with
a knife you did the wrong act, if you did it with
the thumb of a non-כהן, kohen, that's like doing it with a
knife. It's like doing it's doing the wrong act. It's using the
wrong thing to do
the
to do the מליקה. melikah. Another way of testing this question of
right how out of bounds something is, which always gets sort of
interwoven with this, or you know is the question about if you
put it on the altar do you have to take it down?
And there similar was that type of an issue that some types
things are invalid but not so out of bounds that, you know,
that you would have to take them off the altar. Only things
that are like completely irrelevant to this world, completely out of bounds,
you know, are things that you would have to take them off
of the altar and in בריסק Brisk terminology, and this is the
last thing I'll say for review, for בריסק Brisk terminology, you know,
they often the way they talk it is, is it that it's
not the thing itself or is it the פסול pasul thing? Like
is it not a מליקה melikah at all or is it a
מליקה פסולה? melikah pesulah? You know, if it's not a מליקה melikah
at all, right, if you start to talk about let's say using
the knife or whatever, then it's completely obviously a different thing and
out of bounds. Yes, Mike?
And what of the aspect of it being the wrong place as
in בחוץ? bachutz? So could we infer from there that there were
never any קרבנות העוף korbanot ha-of on a במה? bamah?
Because I know the גמרא—we're Gemara going to discuss that. We're going
to discuss that, we're going to discuss that in one minute. So
now let's resume with the top of ס"ט, samech tet, ס"ט. samech
tet. Top of ס"ט עמוד א', samech tet amud aleph, four lines
from the top. תניא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן. Tanya k'vattei d'Rabbi Yochanan. We
taught like Rabbi Yochanan. מליק זר, malik zar, if a non-kohen did
it, מליקה פסולה, melikah psulah, if a פסול pasul kohen did it,
which
by the way we haven't expanded on פסול, pasul, right? אונן, onen,
you know, what about יושב, yoshev, what about a kohen who's a
בעל מום? ba'al mum? Presumably all of that's included in פסול, pasul,
okay? הפיגול והנותר והטמא, ha'piggul v'ha'notar v'ha'tamei, or let's say you had
a פיגול piggul thought, okay? So the korban became פסול pasul because
you had a פיגול piggul thought, or you left it over, or
it became טמא. tamei. Now that's obviously you would think this because
you left it over it's not retroactively going to change its status.
So אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami, that's the הלכה. halacha. אין
מטמאין בבית הבליעה, ein mtam'in b'veit ha'bli'ah, those things are not נבילה.
nevelah.
Wait so then how so what? טמא tamei would be when you
touch it?
I mean, if it's טמא tamei you do become טמא. tamei. Oh,
no but that's a second degree. טמא tamei means something טמא tamei
touched it so it's not a source of טומאה tumah so whatever.
Okay, but it's a good point. Anyway, so this is like Rabbi
Yochanan. It says that a זר zar makes it, it's not it's
not it's not נבילה. nevelah. We also added in פיגול piggul and
also we should understand that the word פסול pasul also includes a
whole other category of כהנים kohanim who are פסולים psulim not because
it's a זר. zar. Okay, so that's a nice ברייתא braita like
Rabbi Yochanan. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak,
שמעתי, shamati, I heard, שתים, shtayim, הלכות halachot about two different things.
אחת קמיצת זר ואחת מליקת זר. achat kmitzot zar v'achat melikat zar.
One was a הלכה halacha about whether קמיצת זר kmitzot zar and
the other about a מליקה melikah of a זר. zar. And so
the question isn't about נבילה, nevelah, the only thing we could be
looking at compared to those two is this other thing which is
related which is if I put it on the altar do I
have to take it down? That's another way of measuring, right, or
another symptom of, right, how much is this completely out of bounds
or not completely out of bounds. So I heard a different ruling
between whether the קמיצה kmitzah was done by a non-kohen or the
מליקה melikah was done by a non-kohen.
אחת תרד ואחת לא תרד. achat tered v'achat lo tered. One of
them if you put it on the altar afterwards you have to
take it down and the other not. ולא ידענא v'lo yadana and
I don't know which is the one that's more problematic and that
you have to take it down. Now if you ask me based
on what we just said, I would have said the מליקה's melikah
more problematic, okay, it's debated Rav and Rabbi Yochanan, but ultimately the
מליקה melikah of a זר zar as I said you're using the
wrong implement to do the שחיטה, shechitah, you're using the thumb of
a non-kohen whereas קמיצה's kmitzah just a normal זר zar problem. That's
what I would have said. The גמרא's Gemara going to say the
opposite, that the קמיצה kmitzah of a זר zar is worse than
the מליקה melikah of a זר. zar. Let's take a look.
אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiyah, מסתברא mistavra it makes sense קמיצה תרד מליקה
לא תרד. kmitzah tered melikah lo tered. מליקה melikah doesn't go down,
that's like Rabbi Yochanan like we said, but קמיצה kmitzah does. All
of a sudden why would a קמיצה kmitzah by a מנחה minchah
of a זר zar be more off-base than the מליקה melikah of
a זר? zar? So מאי שנא מליקה דישנה בבמה? mai shna melikah
d'yeshnah b'bamah? So the גמרא Gemara asks that question, what makes מליקה
melikah not totally off-base if it's done by a non-kohen a זר?
zar? Because a זר zar can operate on a במה, bamah, right?
So we had that discussion yesterday and is somebody who can do
it on a במה, bamah, is that relevant for the בית המקדש?
Beit HaMikdash? But if you're going to say a זר zar is
in bounds, you're going to use the במה bamah as an example
that he's in bounds to demonstrate that. So that's true about a
מליקה. melikah. So קמיצה נמי ישנה בבמה. kmitzah nami yeshnah b'bamah. So
okay, you do a קמיצה kmitzah on a במה bamah with a
non-kohen. The זר zar is כשר kosher on a במה bamah with
anything. So why again is קמיצה kmitzah worse?
וכי תימא אין מנחה בבמה? v'chi teima ein minchah b'bamah?
Now you'll say no, you don't have קמיצת זר kmitzot zar by
a במה bamah because there's an opinion that says they wouldn't bring
a מנחה minchah on a במה. bamah. You know what? עוף נמי
אין בבמה. of nami ein b'bamah. But that opinion, they go together.
If there's no מנחה, minchah, there's no עוף of because the only
thing that we would sort of say is larger, you know, is
mammals. דאמר רב ששת d'amar Rav Sheshet because רב ששת Rav Sheshet
says לדברי האומר יש מנחה בבמה יש עוף בבמה l'divrei ha'omer yesh
minchah b'bamah yesh of b'bamah לדברי האומר אין מנחה אין עוף. l'divrei
ha'omer ein minchah ein of. Whatever you're going to say by the
מנחה minchah you're going to say by the birds.
So again, why is a קמיצה kmitzah worse? You can't say that
there's no קמיצת זר kmitzot zar on a במה bamah because if
that's your opinion then there's no מליקה melikah of a bird on
a במה bamah of a זר zar on a במה. bamah. So
what makes the קמיצה kmitzah of a זר zar more out of
bounds than the מליקה melikah of a זר? zar? So the גמרא
Gemara
says מאי טעמא mai ta'ama excuse me, I didn't finish the קושיא
koshya before, זבחים ולא מנחות זבחים ולא עופות. zvachim v'lo menachot zvachim
v'lo ofot. When it speaks about outside of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash and here we're using it, it's fascinating, מעמד הר סיני Ma'amad
Har Sinai is the example of a במה, bamah, as the example
of שחיטה shechting things outside the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Okay, because
it says and it says that they brought their זבחים פרים להשם
שלמים. zvachim parim l'Hashem shelamim. Okay, so if you want to read
זבחים zvachim as narrow, right, like the name of our מסכת masechet
זבחים, zvachim, it's things that are זבוח, zavuach, that are slaughtered, so
bird is not זבוח, zavuach, it's מלוך, maloch, מליקה, melikah, you do
מליקה. melikah. מלאכה malacha right anyway מלאכה. malacha. Anyway, so if that's
the way you read the verse, so fine they're going to go
together. So we're back to our question, why is קמיצה kmitzah of
a זר zar more out of bounds than מליקה melikah of a
זר? zar? So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא אין קידוש בכלי.
ella eima ein kiddush b'kli.
No,
here's the reason. Because when you bring a מנחה Mincha outside the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you don't sanctify it in a כלי שרת,
Kli sharet, okay? You're just bringing on your local במה, bama, whatever.
You don't have a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So where, so that's
true. The actual now that is a necessary part of making the
מנחה Mincha fit to be brought. Okay? So therefore, or putting it
in, let me reframe that. That is a necessary part of bringing
the מנחה Mincha into the sanctified context. So therefore, if a זר
zar is כשר kasher by a מנחה Mincha on a במה, bama,
it's even, it's not only because it's a במה bama that's not
a relevant example to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it's not even
in the full קדושה Kedusha context because the מנחה Mincha itself wasn't
even sanctified in a כלי שרת. Kli sharet. So therefore, sure that
works, but that's like completely irrelevant. That's not a discussion that you
can use: "Ah, you see, what you do in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash with a זר zar is not so bad because you
do the same thing by a במה." bama. Anyway, סתם stam we
said before, like, why should you prove anything about a במה? bama?
But even if a במה bama is relevant, okay, something like this,
which is not only in a במה bama but also the thing
hasn't even been sanctified, okay, that's obviously a completely different phenomenon. And
you can't use it to demonstrate something about the meaning of the
קמיצה Kemitzah of a זר zar in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
Whereas by when it comes to the bird, okay, a bird never
gets sanctified in a כלי שרת. Kli sharet. It only gets sanctified
verbally. So what you're doing in a במה bama is not as
different. And since what you're doing in a במה bama is not
as different, and the fact that a זר zar works in a
במה bama means that a זר zar actually is not totally out
of bounds in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay? So it's basically
the same point. We're using the logic of how out of bounds
is it and based on whether you can demonstrate that the thing
is ever good in a different context. So the זר zar is
not fully out of bounds because it works on a במה, bama,
but
מליקה Melikah of a זר zar but קמיצה Kemitzah of a זר
zar is fully out of bounds. Don't tell me it works in
a במה. bama. What goes on in a במה bama what stays
in, exactly, exactly. It happens in Vegas, stay. What goes on in
a במה, bama, that context is really not, it's a completely different
phenomenon. And you can't connect the dots to that in the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash because even the מנחה Mincha is not fully sanctified
in that context, okay? Well, then we don't even know.
That's a debate, right, if it can or can't?
Yeah, but that's right.
But was there certain like, like in other words like a חטאת
Chatat or an אשם Asham or an עולה, Olah, like you know,
were there certain things that were categorically excluded from a במה? bama?
Yeah, I mean, it has to be דבר הנידר והנידב. davar haniddar
v'haniddav. It has to be basically free-will. Okay, and then there's other
things.
So you can never do even if you can do a מליקה,
Melikah, it could be an עולה Olah but not a חטאת Chatat
then. Right.
And we'll discuss all this later. מלק בשמאלו בלילה. Malak b'smolo balailah.
So we got through the case about the פסולים psulim or at
least does פסולים psulim include זר? zar? Interestingly, again we did not
discuss the question about אונן onen and יושב yoshav and so on.
Okay, but anyway, presumably those are also being included. And now we're
getting to the line in the משנה Mishna that says it's funny
to see שמאל smol and לילה lailah as an example or, you
know, of פסולים, psulim, which is what the גמרא Gemara said before,
because לילה lailah is not the פסול pasul person, you know, and
שמאל smol he also בגברא b'gavra is פסול, pasul, if he did
it with the left.
That's the line in the משנה Mishna we weren't sure about. Right,
exactly.
But the גמרא Gemara at least the way it read it, said,
yeah. Anyway, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Anyway,
but now we're going to move on to this whole part.
A פסול pasul would also be like a woman then, right?
Yeah. I mean, but that's a זר zar though. Even a בת
כהן bas kohen is a זר zar for this purpose. Anyway, now
we get to the שחיטה shechitah issues, you know, and the פנים
pnim and the חוץ chutz issues. We're sort of done with the
act and the knife and so on and then we get to
all of this part. Okay? The wrong place issues. Let's take a
look. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. יכול תהא מליקה שהיא לפני לפנים תטמא
בגדים בבית הבליעה. Yachol tehei melikah she'hi liphnim t'tamei b'gadim b'veis hablia.
Maybe, meaning this is a ברייתא braisa that's working in stages. First,
how do we know even if the קרבן korban is done properly,
maybe it's a נבילה, neveilah, right? Because look, at the end of
the day, you did a מליקה. melikah. So maybe the תורה, Torah,
you know, allows a כהן kohen to eat from it, but maybe
in terms of it shouldn't lose its status of a נבילה. neveilah.
You didn't שחט shacht it properly.
How does, how can you possibly be eating a נבילה? neveilah?
Well, רש''י Rashi says also, maybe we're talking about an עולה. olah.
Okay, but anyway.
You can't eat an עולה. olah. I understand.
So we're not saying, so we're saying is, maybe a normal bird
sacrifice should always be seen as a נבילה. neveilah. Okay? So you
want to say, oh but then how would the כהנים kohanim be
allowed to eat it? So okay, maybe it's an exception. You know,
כהנים kohanim also get to wear שעטנז. sha'atnez. Or you could say
that, you know, at least the עולה, olah, which isn't being eaten,
maybe that should be seen of as a נבילה neveilah because at
the end of the day, you didn't do a proper שחיטה. shechitah.
How do we know it's
not שחטed shacht the same way.
I understand, not the same way. This is יבדיל, yavdil, this is
לא יבדיל. lo yavdil. Anyway, how do we know not to give
it a status of a נבילה neveilah at least for טומאה וטהרה?
tumah v'taharah? Okay, that's the question. At the end of the day,
this logically should be a נבילה. neveilah. So even if it's allowed
to be eaten if it's a חטאת chatas whatever the case may
be, how do you know it's not a נבילה neveilah for טומאה
tumah purposes? Okay? תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. יכול תהא מליקה שהיא לפני
לפנים תטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה. Yachol tehei melikah she'hi liphnim t'tamei b'gadim
b'veis hablia. תלמוד
לומר: Talmud lomar: נבילה. neveilah. So the פסוק pasuk says, the פסוק
pasuk says, what's the פסוק? pasuk? רש''י Rashi what's the פסוק? pasuk?
I'm not looking for the רש''י. Rashi. ונפש אשר תאכל נבלה וטרפה.
V'nefesh asher tochal neveilah u'treifah.
This is talking about an נבלה neveilah about a bird. So this
is the exact
sacrifice point that
we're.
ט"ו, Tet-Vav, thank you. ובכל
נפש אשר תאכל
נבלה וטרפה באזרח ובגר וכיבס בגדיו ורחץ במים וטמא עד הערב וטהר.
U'v'chol nefesh asher tochal neveilah utreifiah ba'ezrach u'vager v'chibes
begadav v'rachatz bamayim v'tamei ad ha'erev v'taher. So it doesn't say it's
a bird. I mean this is a very strange פסוק. pasuk. It
says if you eat a נבלה neveilah or a טרפה treifah you
are טמא. tamei. So first of all it makes you טמא tamei
by eating. But it says טרפה. treifah. But we hold the other
evidence is that a טרפה treifah doesn't cause טומאה. tumah. So how
do you make any sense of this? So the rabbis say it's
talking about eating a bird that's a נבלה. neveilah. So number one,
it's limited to a bird. And number two, okay, and the bird
only causes טומאה tumah when you eat it. But we still have
to deal with the word טרפה treifah because they say that only
applies to a נבלת עוף, nevelat of, not a טרפת עוף. treifat
of. So let's take a look. Oh well we'll see it in
just a second.
If I eat a regular נבלה neveilah
and you don't touch it, then you're not טמא. tamei. If you
manage not to touch it, it only touches the inside of your
mouth, that's like נגיעת בית הסתרים negiat beit hasetarim or whatever, so
yes, you would not be טמא. tamei.
But normally, I mean in order, you know,
exactly, exactly.
But this only causes טומאה tumah when you swallow it. Okay, and
that's this פסוק. pasuk. But it says, so A, what we're not
going to discuss is how we know to limit it to a
bird, but B, it says נבלה neveilah and טרפה. treifah. יכול תטמא
לי כשהיא לפנים מטמא וגורם בבית הבליעה, תלמוד לומר נבלה. Yachol titamei
l'kashilei panim metamei v'gorem b'veit habli'ah, talmud lomar neveilah. No,
only a real נבלה, neveilah, not this thing that you did מליקה
melikah to. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, הא נמי נבלה
היא. ha nami neveilah hi. What do you mean? That was exactly
your question. Logically you would put a bird that you did מליקה
melikah to, even a קרבן, korban, in the נבלה neveilah category. How
do you know not to put it in that? אלא תלמוד לומר
טרפה. Ella talmud lomar treifah. It says אשר יאכל נבלה וטרפה. asher
yochal neveilah u'treifah.
So what's the link since טרפה treifah doesn't literally mean a טרפה?
treifah? A bird that's a טרפה treifah does not cause טומאה. tumah.
So what is the link? The link is to tell you the
following thing. מה טרפה שאין מתרת את האיסור, אף כל שאין מתרת
האיסור. Ma treifah she'ein materet et ha'issur, af kol she'ein materet ha'issur.
It has to be like a טרפה. treifah. And the same way
a טרפה treifah when you שחט shacht a טרפה treifah you can't
eat the meat. So the only type of a נבלה neveilah that
is in the נבלה neveilah category and causes טומאה tumah is a
נבלה neveilah that the act of sort of slaughtering it or whatever
did not make it permissible. יצא מליקה שהיא לפנים והיא מתרת את
האיסור, אין מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה. Yatza melikah shehi lifnim v'hi materet
et ha'issur, ein metamei begadim b'veit habli'ah. But the מליקה melikah of
a bird lets you go ahead and burn it on the מזבח,
mizbeiach, right, lets the כהנים Kohanim eat it if it's a חטאת.
chatat. So since the מליקה melikah actually makes it כשר kosher in
a certain way, that מליקה melikah cannot make it a נבלה, neveilah,
which is a logical thing to say anyway, which is why Michael's
having such a hard time about the question. If the תורה Torah
tells you to do it, it's hard to say that it makes
it a נבלה, neveilah, but the גמרא Gemara is saying logically that's
because it's linked to טרפה. treifah. So טרפה treifah has to be
something that actually when you שחט shacht it does not make it
permissible. Here, the act makes it permissible for the מזבח, mizbeiach, for
the כהנים. Kohanim. It's not going to be a נבלה. neveilah.
Is there any הוה אמינא hava amina to say נבלה טרפה neveilah
treifah that is like kind
of both, that like somehow makes it worse? We'll see about that
at the end of the דף. daf. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, הבי המולק. Hevi hamolek. Now that includes מולק. molek.
קדשים Kodashim ah נו. nu. הבי המולק קדשים בחוץ ומולק חולין בין
מבפנים בין מבחוץ הואיל ואין מתירין את האיסור מטמאי בגדים בבית הבליעה.
Hevi hamolek kodashim bachutz u'molek chullin bein mibifnim bein mibachutz ho'il v'ein
matirin et ha'issur metamei begadim b'veit habli'ah. Okay, one minute. Or
it should be not הבי hevi like אבי. avi. Should I now
say that המולק קדשים בחוץ? hamolek kodashim bachutz? Let me just see
what's the... here there's זיין, Zayin, sorry.
אבי, Avi, right. אבי, Avi, should I now include maybe המולק קדשים
בחוץ ומולק חולין בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ? hamolek kodashim bachutz u'molek chullin
bein mibifnim bein mibachutz?
Let's say you do the מליקה melikah but you do it קדשים
בחוץ kodashim bachutz or you do it חולין chullin but you do
it בפנים. bifnim. Once I said מליקה melikah doesn't make it a
נבלה, neveilah, what about when you do a מליקה melikah in the
wrong place or on the wrong object? So there, הואיל ואין מתירין
את האיסור, ho'il v'ein matirin et ha'issur, using my same logic of
is it like a טרפה, treifah, here the answer is yes, it
is like a טרפה. treifah. When I do מליקה melikah of קדשים
kodashim out of the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, I don't make it
permissible. כהנים Kohanim can't eat it, I can't burn it as a
קרבן. korban. When I do מליקה melikah of חולין chullin in the
בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, I haven't done anything to make it permissible.
So only when I do מליקה melikah of קדשים kodashim in the
בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, because I've made it permissible, does it go
out of the category of נבלה. neveilah. But when I do it
on חולין chullin in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash or קדשים kodashim
outside, since the act of מליקה melikah in no way made this
bird any more permissible, it is going to still be in the
category of נבלה. neveilah. הואיל ואין מתירין את האיסור מטמא בגדים בבית
הבליעה. Ho'il v'ein matirin et ha'issur metamei begadim b'veit habli'ah. Okay, so
that's that ברייתא. braita. And that basically tells us normal מליקה melikah
isn't a נבלה, neveilah, but מליקה melikah in the wrong place or
on the wrong object is a נבלה. neveilah. תניא אידך, Tanya idach,
we taught in another ברייתא. braita. יכול תהא שחיטה. Yachol tehei shechitah.
Now we've sort of done this. Now we're going to look at
the שחיטה. shechitah. How do we know שחיטה, shechitah, even if it's
חולין בפנים chullin bifnim or קדשים בחוץ, kodashim bachutz, alright,
is כשר? kosher? Now the biggest חידוש chiddush probably here would be
שחיטת חולין בפנים shechitat chullin bifnim is not such a חידוש, chiddush,
okay. But שחיטה shechitah of a bird קרבן korban outside, there you
might say since the תורה Torah mandates that you do מליקה melikah
by a bird קרבן, korban, maybe שחיטה shechitah for it would make
it a נבלה. neveilah. So let's take a look. תניא אידך *Tanya
idach*: יכול דשחיטת חולין בפנים chullin b'pnim *yakhol deshchitas chullin bifnim*, okay,
וקדשים בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ *vekodshim bein mibifnim bein mibachutz*, מטמא בית
הבליעה *metamei beis habli'ah*, maybe that would cause טומאה tumah. *tuma*, תלמוד
לומר *Talmud lomar*: נבילה neveila *neveila*. No, only a real נבילה neveila,
*neveila*. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says: הנמי נבילה neveila היא *hanami
neveila hi*. But that was your question. Maybe we should call this
a נבילה neveila. *neveila* because maybe the שחיטה shechita. *shchita* is the
wrong thing to do by a bird קרבן korban, *korban* and makes
it a נבילה neveila, *neveila*. אלא ela, תלמוד לומר *ella Talmud lomar*:
טריפה treifa *treifa*. Okay fine, we know the meaning of נבילה neveila.
*neveila* by the juxtaposition to טריפה treifa, *treifa*. What are we going
to learn from there? מה טריפה treifa שוה בפנים b'fnim כבחוץ אף
כל שוה בפנים b'fnim כבחוץ *mah treifa shaveh bifnim kevachutz, af kol
shaveh bifnim kevachutz*. It has to be like a טריפה treifa *treifa*.
The same way an animal that's a טריפה treifa. *treifa*, you can't
eat it when you שחט shachted *shecht* it out of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* and you can't bring it as a
קרבן korban *korban* in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. So
therefore the only thing that's a נבילה neveila *neveila* is something that
the status is the same inside and outside of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*. What does this mean? יצא שחיטת חולין בפנים
shechitas chullin b'pnim. וקדשים בין מבפנים בין מבחוץ *yatza shchitas chullin bifnim
vekodshim bein mibifnim bein mibachutz*. הואיל ולא v'lo? שוו בפנים כבחוץ אין
מטמאין בית הבליעה *ho'il velo shavu bifnim kevachutz, ein metamin beis habli'ah*.
As opposed to these cases. Now what do you mean as opposed
to these cases? Well let's, the easiest one to see is as
opposed to חולין בפנים chullin b'pnim, *chullin bifnim*. When you do a
חולין chullin *chullin* out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*,
that's the way you're supposed to do it, right? So it's כשר
Kosher שחיטה shechita, *kosher shchita*... I mean שחיטת חולין *shchitas chullin*. If
you שחט shechted *shecht* חולין *chullin* out of the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*, that's the way you're supposed to do it. So
that's good. So inside, okay, it's the wrong place. So you got
right place and wrong place, but like a טריפה treifa *treifa*, the
status of a טריפה treifa, *treifa*, it equally פסל *passuls* inside and
out. That we know. So something that's going to be a נבילה
neveila *neveila* has to be equally פסול posul *passul* inside and out
of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. So don't tell me
oh, a שחיטה shechita, *shchita* in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis
HaMikdash* should פסל *passul* it. No, if you want it to פסל
*passul* it, it has to equally פסל *passul* it out of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*. And we know that a שחיטת
חולין *shchitas chullin* out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash*
is not a problem. So therefore שחיטת חולין *shchitas chullin* in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis HaMikdash* is not going to make it
a נבילה neveila. *neveila*.
But you still can't eat it though, right?
Right, because it's a קרבן korban *korban* that hasn't been brought properly.
Okay, but it won't make it a נבילה neveila *neveila*. So you
got it? If you want something to make it a נבילה neveila
*neveila*, it has to operate... it has to be able to make
it a נבילה Neveila, *neveila* both in and out of the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beis HaMikdash*. So since שחיטת חולין *shchitas chullin* out
of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* doesn't make it a נבילה Neveila
*neveila*, it's not going to make it a נבילה *neveila* in the
בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, now the question is: what about שחיטת
קדשים בחוץ shechitas kodshim bachutz *shchitas kodshim bachutz*, right? And בין מבפנים
בין מבחוץ *bein mibifnim bein mibachutz*. So there you should say, well,
a bird sacrifice is wrong to do שחיטה shechita *shchita* inside or
outside. So that doesn't explain why there's a difference there. So maybe
that should make it a נבילה *neveila*. So let's see what the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says. Let's take a look. בשלמא חולין לא שוו
בפנים כבחוץ *bishlama chullin, lo shavu bifnim kevachutz*. חולין *chullin* I get.
The שחיטת חולין *shchitas chullin* inside isn't going to make it a
נבילה *neveila* because שחיטת חולין *shchitas chullin* outside is totally fine. Okay,
אלא קדשים kodshim. *ella kodshim*, but שחיטה shechita, *shchita* of a bird
קרבן korban *korban*, אידי ואידי פסולים נינהו *idi ve'idi psulim ninhu*, in
and out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* it's the wrong thing
to be doing. So that should be making it a נבילה *neveila*.
That's a good question. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*: So רבא *Rava* says:
you know what, you're right. All we learned from this inside-outside thing
is the חולין *chullin*. The idea of a שחיטת קדשים kodshim, *shchitas
kodshim*, how we know that's not a נבילה *neveila* is learned from
a different place. אמר רבא *Amar Rava*: רבא *Rava* says like this:
אם הועילו לו שחיטת חוץ לחייבו כרת לא תועיל לו לטהרו מידי
נבילה *im ho'ilu lo shchitas chutz lachayev kareis, lo so'ilu lo letaharu
midei neveila*? So רבא *Rava* says like this: you're right. שחיטת חולין
*shchitas chullin*... שחיטת חולין בפנים Chullin B'fnim, *shchitas chullin bifnim* is not
a נבילה *neveila* because שחיטת חולין בחוץ chullin bachutz *shchitas chullin bachutz*
is the right thing to do. שחיטת קדשים kodshim, *shchitas kodshim* is
not a נבילה *neveila*, not because בחוץ bachutz, *bachutz* it's the right
thing to do, but it's effective בחוץ *bachutz*. How do you know
שחיטת קדשים *shchitas kodshim* is effective בחוץ *bachutz*? Because even though in
the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* the only thing that's כשר Kosher *kosher*
by a bird sacrifice is מליקה melika. *melika*, the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
learns from another way that to be עובר *over* and חייב chayav.
*chayav* for bringing a קרבן korban *korban* out of the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash*, if you did שחיטה shechitah *shchita* on a bird that
was a קרבן korban *korban*, you'd also be חייב *chayav* for bringing
a קרבן *korban* out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*. Okay, got
it? So שחיטה shechitah, *shchita* on a bird קרבן *korban* in the
בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, meaningless. שחיטה shechitah *shchita* on a bird קרבן
*korban* out of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, bam, you're חייב *chayav*.
Okay, whatever, it's a different גמרא gemara *Gemara*, you know, we learn
it from a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. So what the גמרא gemara *Gemara*'s
saying is like: so why therefore is שחיטה shechitah, *shchita* of a
bird קרבן *korban* not going to make it not a נבילה *neveila*?
Because it's a meaningful thing. If it's a meaningful enough שחיטה shechitah
*shchita* to say you brought a קרבן *korban* out of the בית
המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, then therefore it's going to be meaningful enough to
say you can't... you're not going to consider the animal a נבילה
*neveila*. Okay, because obviously it has to be some... it's sort of
like the idea before that it כשר Kosher *kashered* it. If it
כשר Kosher *kashered* it, it didn't make it a נבילה *neveila*. This
didn't כשר Kosher *kasher* it, but it gave... but it was recognized
as a meaningful act, and therefore it's not going to make it
a נבילה *neveila*. Okay, so he says: אשכחן חוץ
*ashchan chutz*. Now that's when you did a שחיטה shechitah. *shchita* on
a bird בחוץ *bachutz*, it's not going to be a נבילה *neveila*
because the שחיטה shechitah, *shchita* gave it weight and meaning, meaning enough
to make you חייב *chayav*. פנים מנלן *pnim minalan*? How do you
know about a שחיטה shechitah *shchita* of a bird inside isn't going
to be a נבילה *neveila*? Okay, so: הואיל ולא שוו פנים כבחוץ
*ho'il velo shavu pnim kevachutz*. No, because now we got the link
like we said before, that's stage two. Once you said שחיטה shechitah
*shchita* of a bird on the outside is a meaningful act, now
you can't make it
a נבילה *neveila* inside.
Right. It's a roundabout way to go there.
Well, you had to first prove that it was חייב כרת. chiyuv
kares?
And we know that.
All right. Fine. הגמרא gemara says like
this: אי הכי מה לעוף קדשים בחוץ נמי לא דלא שוו פנים
כבחוץ?
ee hachi ma l'of kodshim bachutz nami lo d'lo shavu pnim
k'vachutz?
'Cause of חייב כרת?
Yeah. Is that the question? Hold on.
דיתני דם מה טעמא על שום דהתם בפנים הכשיר במליקה. d'isani dam
ma ta'ama al shum d'hasam b'pnim hichshir b'melika. No, no. This is
קדשים. This is, wait, מליקה. melika. No, we're now switching to מליקה.
melika. We're moving off of שחיטה. shechitah Fine. Okay. So, by שחיטה,
shechitah okay, let's say שחיטה, shechitah
חולין בפנים is not going to be נבלה neveilah because חולין בחוץ
Chullin Bachutz works. So, it's not going to install if it's good
on the outside it's not going to make it נבלה neveilah on
the inside. קדשים, if it's מליקת קדשים, melikas kodshim, I'm sorry, שחיטת
קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz is a meaningful act because it makes you
חייב. And therefore once it's a meaningful act on the outside and
it's not נבלה neveilah on the outside it's not going to be
נבלה neveilah on the inside. Good. Now we move back to מליקה.
melika Okay, מליקת קדשים בחוץ, melikas kodshim bachutz, okay, which actually does
make it, okay, why don't we say it doesn't make it? Because
the outside is bad, the inside is good. מליקת קדשים בפנים melikas
kodshim b'pnim is good. So even saying if the inside and the
outside aren't the same it should not be a נבלה. neveilah. Okay.
So how come here מליקת קדשים בחוץ melikas kodshim bachutz is a
נבלה? neveilah? So the גמרא Gemara's says like this: אי הכי מה
לעוף קדשים בחוץ נמי לא דלא שוו פנים כבחוץ? ee hachi ma
l'of kodshim bachutz nami lo d'lo shavu pnim k'vachutz? אמר רב שימי
בר אשי דנים דבר שלא בהכשירו מדבר שלא בהכשירו ואין דנים דבר
שלא בהכשירו מדבר שבהכשירו. amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi danim davar shelo
b'hechsheiro midavar shelo b'hechsheiro v'ein danim davar shelo b'hechsheiro midavar shebehechsheiro. Okay.
That you can compare two things that are being done like improperly,
okay? So meaning what? That here you can compare
קדשים בחוץ kodshim bachutz and קדשים בפנים, kodshim b'pnim, okay? And those
are both being done improperly and you can sort of say, okay
even though it's improper, here it doesn't totally פסול it, so it's
not going to make it a נבלה neveilah here. Whereas in this
case, okay, we're not going to take a look at קדשים בחוץ
kodshim bachutz, and say it's not a נבלה neveilah when you do
it in the wrong way because it's not a נבלה neveilah when
you do it in the right way, right? When you do קדשים
בפנים kodshim b'pnim you're doing it in the right way. So the
link, the link of פנים בחוץ, pnim bachutz, we're not going to
start from a case that's being done right. Well, meaning because of
the שחיטה shechitah right? Let's just finish this, okay? So the גמרא
Gemara says, one minute...
so the גמרא Gemara says, ולא? But do we not? והתניא מנין
ליוצא שאם עלה לא ירד שהרי יוצא כשר בבמה. v'hatanya minayin l'yotzei
she'im ala lo yeired sheharei yotzei kasher b'vama. So, oh, this is
a classic thing the גמרא Gemara likes throwing out. But don't we
learn that something that was taken out of the environment of the
בית המקדש and put in the... on the altar you don't have
to take down because it's good... because it's good on a במה?
vama? So that's learning the status of something inside the בית המקדש
from the status of something out of the בית המקדש. So that,
you just said you're not allowed to do that. So the גמרא
Gemara says, no, תנא זאת תורת העולה ריבה סמיך ליה. tanna zos
toras ha'olah riba samich lei. That's not really learning from the הלכה
halacha of a במה, vama, that's just learning because we have a
פסוק pasuk. and so on and we said that before. Now, so
the point is that you're not going to learn to say something
done the right way or in the בית המקדש is going to
be... wait a minute. What are we saying?
Hold on one second.
Well, no, I forget which direction. You're not going to learn from
something done the right way in the בית המקדש that that is
not a נבלה, neveilah, שחיטת קדשים בפנים, shechitas kodshim b'pnim, to say
something done out of the בית המקדש and the wrong way is
a נבלה, neveilah, okay? So you're not going to go from the
right way in the בית המקדש to change the status... you're not
going to use this to make something that is
wrong, right? But the problem is, is that, and I think this
is what's bothering you Mike, I'm just sort of processing it myself,
is that that seems to be what we did by the case
of חולין בפנים, right? That we said since חולין out of the
בית המקדש is good, we're going to say that in the בית
המקדש it'll also be good.
But I thought we were trying to, like you know, figure out
to begin with whether מליקה melikah in עוף of in the בית
המקדש makes a נבלה neveilah or not.
Yeah but we said, we addressed that, we proved that.
Anyway, look, here's the point, okay? קדשים, here you've got your קדשים
בחוץ, okay, and that's in a way it's a check because it's
good to be מחייב mechayev you for שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, so
it's meaningful, okay? And once that's okay, then your קדשים בפנים kodshim
b'pnim is also going to be a check because of the link.
Okay, similarly, you have here, this is all שחיטה, shechitah okay? You
have שחיטת
חולין בפנים. חולין בחוץ and here's חולין בפנים,
okay? So since this is a check because that makes it kosher,
this is going to be a check and also not in the
נבלה. neveilah. Okay, so if it's good on the outside, it's going
to be, you know, we first establish it's good on the outside,
then it's going to be good on the inside, okay? תוכו כברו.
Tocho K'varo. Whereas here you've got, right,
מליקת קדשים Melikas Kodashim
בפנים
and here it's בחוץ, right? So בפנים we know it's good and
here it's no good. And what we want to say is, why
don't we say here inside is like the outside? If the inside
is good, the outside should be good, okay? And the גמרא's Gemara
answer, what I think, what I want the גמרא Gemara to be
saying, although it's not in the language of the גמרא Gemara because
it just makes it more simple, is the answer is not בהכשרה
b'hachshara or לא בהכשרה. lo b'hachshara. Maybe this is what the גמרא
Gemara means, okay, but it doesn't seem that way from the end
question is, you don't use the fact that something is kosher on
the inside to kosher something on the outside. In these cases, it
was kosher on the outside, so we're going to say it's kosher
on the inside. Here it's kosher on the inside, you don't want
to say it's kosher on the outside. Okay, that's at least how
I'd like to frame it. The גמרא Gemara seems to be saying
it a little bit differently, seems to be saying דבר בהכשרה davar
b'hachshara and לא בהכשרה, lo b'hachshara, but to me that's a little
complicated. Let's get onto the next משנה. mishna. מלק ונמצאת טרפה. Malak
v'nimtzet tereifah. רבי... yes?
I'm just questioning why the outside should validate something on the inside.
It doesn't validate it. It's based on the link to טרפה tereifah
that it shows that the status is going to be the same,
okay? That the only thing that's a נבלה neveilah is something whose
status is the same on the inside and the outside. So it
doesn't, like, it's not validating, it's just demonstrating whether it falls into
this category or not. Okay, מלק ונמצאת טרפה. Malak v'nimtzet tereifah. Now
we get to actually the טרפה tereifah issue that we were discussing.
Now here's the question in general, okay? When you do a
שחיטה shechitah
on an animal and you find that it's a טרפה. tereifah. Logically
you could say, well isn't that like a נבלה? neveilah? Why? Because
a נבלה neveilah is... what is the הלכה'ic halachic definition of a
נבלה? neveilah?
In the תורה Torah a נבלה neveilah is like an animal that
drops dead because, you know, out of disease or illness or whatever.
But the הלכה'ic halachic definition of a טרפה, tereifah, like we learned
that מליקה melikah. normally should be a טרפה... tereifah... a נבלה, neveilah,
the הלכה'ic halachic definition of a נבלה neveilah is an animal that
did not have a proper שחיטה, shechitah. okay?
So if I did a שחיטה shechitah and there was a little
nick in the knife and it made it an improper שחיטה, shechitah
it's a נבלה. neveilah. If you need a Jew to do a
שחיטה shechitah and a non-Jew does it, it's a נבלה, neveilah, okay?
A נבלה neveilah is an animal that died through an improper שחיטה.
shechitah If that's true, logically you should say, well if there was
a... if the animal was a טרפה tereifah and I שחט shecht
it, maybe it should also be a נבלה, neveilah, because even though
I did the physical act of שחיטה, shechitah the שחיטה shechitah didn't
make it permissible because it was a טרפה. tereifah. Okay, so the
answer is no. Normally if you do a שחיטה shechitah on an
animal, since the act of שחיטה shechitah was done properly, even if
the animal is a טרפה, tereifah, the animal is not a נבלה
neveilah and it doesn't cause טומאה. tumah. Only a נבלה neveilah causes
טומאה. tumah. Okay, but what's the story by a bird? Here you
have a debate both by שחיטה shechitah and by מליקה. melikah All
right? There's the opinion of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says basically a bird is like a... an animal and
if you do a שחיטה shechitah on a bird and it's a
טרפה, tereifah, it's not a נבלה, neveilah, it's a טרפה. tereifah. If
you do a מליקה melikah on a bird and it's a טרפה.
tereifah. Now, here you could say, one minute, he did a מליקה
melikah on a bird that's a טרפה. tereifah. That's like our earlier
discussion.
Maybe the same way if you did a מליקה melikah on a
chicken or on a bird that's too young or on a מחוסר
אבר mechusar eivar or you did it with a knife. So if
you did a מליקה melikah in a way that the animal didn't
become kosher because of something physical about the animal because it was
a טרפה, tereifah, maybe that should be... it's not a מליקה melikah
of a קרבן, it's not in this קרבן category and therefore the
מליקה melikah. makes it a נבלה. neveilah. Because at the end of
the day you are doing a מליקה. melikah So maybe like our
whole previous discussion, when does a מליקה melikah make something a נבלה?
neveilah? You could say, well if it's a טרפה, tereifah, then the
מליקה melikah never was really in a valid context and it makes
it a נבלה. neveilah. You could say that, right? רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says no, whether you do a שחיטה shechitah on a bird
that's a טרפה tereifah or מליקה melikah that's on a קרבן that's
a... that's a טרפה, tereifah, it does not make it a נבלה.
neveilah. Okay, that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is
going to say, not only does מליקה melikah, on a bird that's
a קרבן on a טרפה tereifah bird make it a נבלה, neveilah,
and that makes sense because at the end of the day you
did מליקה, melikah okay? But even שחיטה shechitah on a normal bird
that's a טרפה tereifah makes it a נבלה. neveilah. All right, so
you have they sort of argue both extremes. A logical position is
a middle one, which we're not going to explore, which is a
middle position of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says
שחיטה shechitah, of a bird טרפה tereifah is not a נבלה neveilah
because you did a שחיטה. shechitah, מליקה melikah of a bird טרפה
tereifah is a נבלה neveilah because it's a מליקה melikah that didn't
work. Okay, so let's take a look. מלק ונמצאת טרפה. Malak v'nimtzet
tereifah. You did מליקה melikah. and it was a טרפה. tereifah. רבי
מאיר אומר אינו מטמא בית הבליעה. Rabbi Meir omer eino metamei beit
habliah. It's not a נבלה. neveilah.
Even though you did a מליקה. melikah. רבי יהודה אומר מטמא. Rabbi
Yehuda omer metamei. It is... it does cause טומאה. tumah. Not... so
far רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is only saying this by a... by
מליקה. melikah אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, said רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, קל וחומר! kal vechomer! אם נבלה Im neve... I'll make a
קל וחומר kal vechomer from a, from a large animal. From a
mammal. אם נבלת בהמה שמטמא במגע ובמשא, Im nevelas beheima shemetamei bemaga
uvemasa, the נבלה neveilah which is weightier נבלה? neveilah? The נבלה neveilah
of a mammal, because that even if you touch it, even if
you carry it, it's not this very narrowly defined thing of when
you swallow. So that's like a weighty טומאה. tumah Nevertheless, שחיטתה מטהרת
טרפתה מטומאתה. shechitasa metaheras treifasa mitumasa. A
שחיטה shechitah of a cow that's a טרפה treifah is not a
נבלה. neveilah. We can all agree on that. If that's true, נבלת
עוף שאינה מטמאה במגע ובמשא, nevelas of she'eino metamei bemaga uvemasa, נבלת
העוף nevelas ha'of that if you touch it and carry it doesn't
cause טומאה—the tumah טומאה tumah. is much
narrower—אינו דין שתהא שחיטתה מטהרת טרפתה מטומאתה? eino din shetehei shechitasa metaheras
treifasa mitumasa? So certainly the שחיטה shechitah of a bird טרפה, treifah,
which we haven't discussed yet, now we're introducing it, the שחיטה shechitah
of a bird טרפה treifah should make it a non-נבלה. neveilah. Now,
if you will concede to me that point, that the שחיטה shechitah
of a bird טרפה treifah makes it a non-נבלה, neveilah, I'm going
now build from that to say even the מליקה melikah of a
bird טרפה, treifah, of a קודש, kodash, of a sacrifice bird טרפה
treifah is a non-נבלה. neveilah. Okay, and that I'm going to do
by a מה מצינו. mah matzinu. So מה מצינו בשחיטה שהיא מכשירתה
לאכילה ומטהרת טרפתה מטומאתה, mah matzinu bishchitah shehi machshartah leachilah umetaheras treifasa
mitumasa, so I've just sort of proven to you by a קל
וחומר kal vechomer that the שחיטה shechitah, of a bird טרפה treifah
is, makes it a not טמא, tamei, not a נבלה. neveilah. And
why is that? Because שחיטה shechitah, was the right act to be
done with it.
Okay, so אף מליקתו שהיא מכשירתו לאכילה—so af melikaso shehi machshiraso leachilah
even the מליקה melikah which is normally what you do by a
bird sacrifice to make it fit to be eaten or fit to
be on the
מזבח—תטהר טרפתה מטומאתה. Since מליקה melikah was what you were supposed to
do, the same way שחיטה Shechita on a טרפה treifah is not
a נבלה, neveilah, מליקה melikah on a טרפה treifah for a קרבן
is not a נבלה. neveilah. That's his argument. Okay. But רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehudah does not respond. Okay, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah actually
disagrees with his basic assumption. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah actually feels that
even שחיטה shechita of a bird טרפה treifah is a נבלה. neveilah.
All right. Now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is like a middle position.
Okay, so you've
got שחיטת בהמה טרפה.
shechitas beheima
treifah. There we can all agree that that is טהור. tahor. I'll
just call it טהור, tahor, not a נבלה. neveilah. Okay, so comes,
comes
along
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir makes a קל
וחומר. kal vechomer. Okay. This is a weighty טומאה. tumah. So, you
know, בהמה beheima is weighty טומאה. tumah. בהמה beheima is weighty,
weighty טומאה. tumah Okay. So if this is true that it's טהור,
tahor, even though generally the טומאה tumah. here is weighty, קל וחומר
kal vechomer that
שחיטת עוף
טרפה
shechitas of
treifah is טהור. tahor. That's stage number one. Okay, because this is
obviously an עוף נבלה of neveilah is less weighty. Then מה מצינו,
mah matzinu, we're going to go from שחיטת עוף shechitas of to
מליקת עוף. melikas of. Because שחיטה's the right act, so מליקת עוף
melikas of which is a קרבן also of a טרפה treifah is
also going to be טהור. tahor. So this is the weak link,
because you could say give me a break. Even though מליקה's melikah
the right thing, it's not a מה מצינו mah matzinu because a
מליקה melikah is an act that normally makes something a נבלה. neveilah.
Okay, which is, which is sort of what רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
is going to say. But what is not explicit in the משנה
mishnah is that this is, okay, so this is רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah
basically disagrees with this. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah actually says no,
I say you're wrong here, I don't buy that, and I'm actually
going to say that שחיטת עוף טרפה shechitas of treifah
is a נבלה. neveilah. Okay, I disagree with point one. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose is going to sort of challenge point two. Okay, so
let's take a look at what the משנה mishnah says about רבי
יוסי. Rabbi Yose. רבי יוסי אומר דיי לבוא מן הדין להיות כנבלת
בהמה שחיטתה מטהרת ולא מליקתה. Rabbi Yose omer dayo lavo min hadin
lihyos kenevelas beheima shechitasa metaheras velo melikasa.
You had a קל וחומר kal vechomer here, okay? So this whole
thing rests, the basis of all your thing is the שחיטה of
a בהמה. beheima. And since by the שחיטה of a בהמה, beheima,
מליקה melikah. would always make it a נבלה—by neveilah a בהמה beheima
there is nothing to get it out of a נבלה neveilah other
than שחיטה—so since that's true, you can't go שחיטה, שחיטה, and now
you're going to go to מליקה. melika, You know they have this
thing, what's it called, like a word chain? You change one letter
at a time and then you get to a completely, you know,
each time it's a different word and then you get to a
completely different word. You're not allowed to do that. At the end
of the day, this all rests back on the שחיטה of a
בהמה, beheima, and since by a בהמה beheima only שחיטה
saves it, by a bird only שחיטה's going to save it. So
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says I disagree with your מה מצינו. mah
matzinu. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehudah says I disagree with your stage two,
even שחיטה makes it a נבלה. neveilah. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
says, we'll use a different color.
And רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* says, no, מליקה *melikah*, no, only שחיטה
*shechitah*. Only שחיטה *shechitah* saves you and therefore מליקה *melikah* is going
to be a נבילה *neveilah*. Okay, so those are the two debates.
רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehuda*, which is not explicit, debate point
one, and רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose* the point debate point two. Let's
take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
לא דריש דיו *lo darish dayyo*? How could רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*
not agree to this דיו *dayyo* point of רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yose*?
ודיו דאורייתא *V'dayyo d'Oraita*, that idea that you can't exceed based on
a קל וחומר kal v'chomer. *kal vachomer* your original source, okay, is
a דאורייתא *d'Oraita* principle. דתניא *D'tanya*, מדין קל וחומר kal v'chomer, כיצד
*mi-din kal vachomer keitzad*? This is like a listing of the hermeneutic
principles. What does it mean to like what's an how do you
do a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*?
And where do you see that in the תורה *Torah* here? ויאמר
ה' אל משה ואביה ירק ירק בפניה *Vayomer Hashem el Moshe v'avih
yarok yarak b'paneha*, you know, just recently in the פרשה *parshah*, right?
If her father were to spit in her face by מרים *Miriam*,
wouldn't she be wouldn't she be embarrassed? So now she'd have to
be she'd be closed up for seven days? Here too she has
to wait out of the camp for seven days. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says wait, if her father spitting would embarrass her seven days,
if God's going to show displeasure, obviously that's got to be more
than seven days. Okay, so the גמרא *Gemara* says, קל וחומר לשכינה
ארבעה עשר יום *kal vachomer l'Shechinah arba'ah asar yom*. So logically God
being displeased, God showing displeasure should be 14 days. אלא דיו לבוא
מן הדין להיות כנדון *Ella dayyo lavo min hadin lihyot k'nidon*. Yes,
it's a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, but you don't go beyond, the
whole point of a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* is you're not if
you don't have license to go beyond the original because then you
know you can't prove anything beyond the original case. So therefore you're
limited to the original seven days. So anyway, so here too if
it all started from a קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, shouldn't you be
limited to שחיטה *shechitah* and not מליקה *melikah*? The funny thing is,
is that you could say yes, the original קל וחומר *kal vachomer*
you're only limited to שחיטה *shechitah*, but who says then like you
know that's how the גמרא *Gemara* does, right? חוזר ומלמד בהיקש *Chozer
v'melamed b'heikesh*, חוזר ומלמד במה מצינו *chozer v'melamed b'ma matzinu*, but the
גמרא *Gemara* somehow feels that no, since it's a מה מצינו mah
matzinu. *ma matzinu*, it's not one of these formal things like a
היקש *heikesh* or a קל וחומר *kal vachomer* or גזירה שוה *gezirah
shavah*, that at the end it is ultimately has to find its
justification in the original קל וחומר *kal vachomer*. And therefore you should
be limited to that. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, אמר רבי יוסי
ברבי אבין *amar Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Avin*, רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* קרא
אשכח ודריש *kra ashkhach v'darish*. You're right. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* didn't
really fully do it from this קל וחומר *kal vachomer*, he based
himself on a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. What's the פסוק pasuk: *pasuk*? זאת
תורת הבהמה והעוף *Zot torat habehemah v'ha'of*. This is the law of
the בהמה behemah, *behemah* and the עוף *of*. Okay, וכי באיזה תורה
שוה בהמה behemah לעוף *v'khi b'eizeh torah shavah behemah l'of*? What do
you mean the בהמה behemah *behemah* and עוף *of*, like it's all
the same category? What do you mean? ועוף לבהמה *v'ha'of l'behemah*, בהמה
Behema, אשוה על הדיבשי *behemah asho'u al hadivshei*. בהמה Behema מטמאה metameh.
במגע ובמשא *Behemah metamei b'massa u'v'maga*. If you want to talk about
טומאה tumah. *tumah*, a בהמה *behemah* when it's dead a נבילה *neveilah*,
that's by touch and by carrying. עוף אינו מטמא במגע ובמשא *Of
eino metamei b'massa u'v'maga*. עוף *of* is only doesn't have טומאה tumah
*tumah* that way. And they're like they're not even there's not even
an overlap. They're mutually exclusive. עוף מטמא בבגדים בבית הבליעה *Of metamei
b'vigdei b'veit habli'ah*. עוף *of* is when you swallow it and then
it's not only you it's the clothes you're wearing. בהמה אינה מטמאה
metameh. בבגדים בבית הבליעה *Behemah eino metamei b'vigdei b'veit habli'ah*. An animal
if you were to stick a נבילה *neveilah* in somebody's throat wouldn't
cause that טומאה tumah. *tumah*. אלא *Ella* so what do you mean
how this is the same תורה *torah*? They're not the same תורה
*torah*, they're completely distinct. אלא לומר לך מה בהמה דבר שמכשירה לאכילה
מטהר טרפתה מטומאתה *Ella lomar lekha mah behemah davar shemakhshirah l'akhilah metahar
tereifasoh mitumatah*. The whole point of that פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* is to
tell you our הלכה halacha *halakhah*, that they're similar in this way:
the act that makes a בהמה *behemah* כשר Kosher לאכילה *kosher l'akhilah*
will say that even if it's a טרפה treifa *tereifah* it's not
an it doesn't become a נבילה *neveilah*. So if you did a
שחיטה *shechitah*, אף עוף דבר שמכשיר באכילתו מטהר טרפתו מטומאתו *af of
davar shemakhshir b'akhilasoh metahar tereifasoh mitumatah*. So by a bird if you
did the act that under normal circumstances would have made it kosher,
so you did a מליקה *melikah* by a קרבן *korban* bird, so
if you did a מליקה *melikah* by a קרבן *korban* bird it's
that also makes it not a נבילה *neveilah*. So you're right. Meaning
it's the same מה מצינו *ma matzinu* here, but it's not a
מה מצינו *ma matzinu* just based on logic, it's a מה מצינו
*ma matzinu* that's supported by a פסוק pasuk. *pasuk*. Okay, so this
מה מצינו *ma matzinu* is actually based on זאת תורת הבהמה והעוף
*zot torat habehemah v'ha'of*. You're right. Logically logically the מה מצינו *ma
matzinu* should fail because it's limited it's all based on a קל
וחומר *kal vachomer* and limited to the original קל וחומר *kal vachomer*.
But because it's not a מה מצינו *ma matzinu*, it's a פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*, we're allowed to take that next step. Okay, so that's
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. So now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this:
ורבי יהודה מאי טעמא *v'Rabbi Yehuda mai ta'ama*? How about רבי יהודה
Reb Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*? Where does he get his idea? And again
not just that he doesn't like מליקה *melikah*, but that even the
שחיטה *shechitah* of an עוף *of* is going to be a מליקה
*melikah*, is going to be שחיטה *shechitah* of an עוף *of* is
going to be a נבילה *neveilah* of an עוף טרפה treifa *of
tereifah*. Where does he get that from? קרא אשכח ודריש *Kra ashkhach
v'darish*. He also has got himself a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. נבילה טרפה
treifa *Neveilah tereifah*. Remember that פסוק pasuk *pasuk* we quoted on the
עמוד א' *amud alef* about the טומאה tumah *tumah*? It says if
you eat a נבילה *neveilah* and a טרפה treifa *tereifah* you're טמא
tamei. *tamei*. Okay, so he's going to learn this, let's see how
he's going to learn that. אמר רבי יהודה Amar Reb Yehuda: *amar
Rabbi Yehuda*, טרפה treifa? למה נאמרה *tereifah lamah ne'emrah*? Why does it
say טרפה treifa *tereifah*? Because we know that well let's start. So
what's the scenario of טרפה treifa *tereifah* that it says if you
eat it's going to be טמא tamei, *tamei*? This actually works very
nice for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. Let's just pause for
a moment because take where he's going, right? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* says if even if you שחט shecht *shecht* a bird
and it's a טרפה treifa. *tereifah* it's טמא tamei, *tamei* like a
נבילה *neveilah*. So he actually is the one that's able to read
the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* like... Like normally. It says if you eat
a נבילה or a טריפה treifa? you're טמא. tamei. And he says
yes, even if you eat a bird that's a טריפה, treifa, you're
טמא, tamei. even if you שחט shecht it. It's different than a
בהמה, בהמה that you שחט shechted, that's טריפה treifa is not טמא,
tamei. a bird that you שחט shechted. that's טריפה treifa, is טמא.
tamei So actually, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda like that is the פסוק.
Pasuk The פסוק Pasuk says נבילה and a טריפה. treifa Okay, let's
see how he gets there. Okay. So here the reason רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says שחיטת עוף shechitas of טריפות treifas is נבילה, because
it says in the
פסוק: Pasuk. נבילה וטריפה, neveila u'treifa, what is it? לא יאכל לטמאה
בה. lo yochal l'tama bah. Is that what it is?
Is that, am I quoting it or am I making that up?
What was it?
Let me find it.
No, אשר תאכל נבילה, asher tochal neveila, I'm thinking of a different
פסוק, Pasuk וטמא עד הערב. v'tamei ad ha'erev.
Okay. אשר תאכל נבילה וטריפה וטמא עד הערב. asher tochal neveila u'treifa
v'tamei ad ha'erev. So he says, what are you talking about? It
says נבילה and טריפה treifa causes טומאה. Tumah, I don't buy your
קל וחומר. I think even if you שחט shechted a bird that's
a טריפה, treifa it's going to cause טומאה. Tumah. That's a פסוק.
pasuk. Okay, it's hard to argue with that. Let's see what he
says.
Okay. רבי יהודה מאי טעמא קרא אשכח ודרש. Reb Yehuda mai taama
kra ashchach v'darash. נבילה וטריפה. neveila u'treifa. אמר רבי יהודה: Rabbi Yehuda
טריפה למה נאמר? treifa lama ne'emar? Why טריפה? treifa So אם טריפה
חיה הרי נבילה אמורה. im treifa chaya harei neveila amura. Now this
is a funny phrase. Here's the way רש"י Rashi says it means.
If normally there's a whole debate whether an animal that's a טריפה,
treifa. will it normally, will it be able to like live out
its life, you know, normally it's defined as like live for 12
months. If you normally assume that a טריפה treifa could live, so
then even while it was a טריפה, treifa it was considered to
be a totally living animal. Fine. How did it die? If then
it did die as a result of its wounds or it died,
then it's a נבילה. So you don't need a פסוק pasuk to
tell me if a טריפה treifa. died naturally without being שחט, shechted
that it's a נבילה, cause it is a נבילה. It just died
without being
שחט. shechted אם טריפה אינה חיה, im treifa eina chaya, let's say
you say a טריפה treifa. as soon as it becomes a טריפה
treifa we see it as the walking dead. It's like, it's not
going to live out its life. הרי היא בכלל נבילה, harei hi
bichlal neveila, then I might even want to consider it a נבילה
while it's still walking around. So if so, אלא, it's like a
little funny with the הוה אמינה, hava amina, let's get to the
punchline. להביא טריפה ששחטה, l'havi treifa she'shachtah, which is the פשט. pshat.
If we're going to think that נבילה is an animal that died
without שחיטה, so טריפה treifa, is an animal that was שחט shechted
and was nevertheless a טריפה. treifa Okay? So he says, it says:
נבילה וטריפה. neveila u'treifa. The טריפה treifa cannot mean an animal that
died naturally without שחיטה, cause then it would have been a נבילה.
So a טריפה treifa. has to be an animal that you שחט
shechted and that was found to be a טריפה. treifa Okay. And
there you stay, it's a פסוק pasuk that tells you! I don't
care what, that's not true by a cow and a sheep and
a goat or whatever. It tells you by a bird, it's a
bizarre הלכה Halacha by a bird's weird anyway, that when you swallow
it you're טמא. tamei. So you know what? That's true also in
terms of if it's a טריפה. treifa
So what is it? למה נאמר? lama ne'emar? אם טריפה חיה אלא
להביא טריפה ששחטה שמטמאה. im treifa chaya ela havi treifa she'shachtah she'metameh.
Okay. אמר ליה רב שיזבי: Amar lei Rav Shizbi: אלא מעתה, ela
mei'atah, based on this, דכתיב, d'ksiv, if you're going to link נבילה
and
טריפה treifa based on טומאה Tumah laws, let me ask you a
question. It says: וחלב נבילה וחלב טריפה יעשה לכל מלאכה ואכל לא
תאכלהו. v'cheilev neveila v'cheilev treifa yei'aseh l'chol melacha v'achol lo sochelehu.
It says don't eat the fat of a נבילה and טריפה, treifa
but you can use it for any labor. And the דרשה drasha
of the Rabbis of use it for any labor means you can
even use it in the בית המקדש, means that it's not טמא.
tamei. So basically the פשט pshat of this is only the meat
is טמא tamei. and not the fat. You got it? Because since
it says do the fat and anything you want with the fat,
just don't eat it, it means that the fat is not טמא.
Tamei, התם נמי
נימא, hasam nami neimar, so let's use this logic. אם טריפה חיה
הרי נבילה אמורה. im treifa chaya harei neveila amura. אם טריפה אינה
חיה הרי היא בכלל נבילה. im treifa eina chaya harei hi bichlal
neveila. אלא להביא טריפה ששחטה שחלבה טהור. ela havi treifa she'shachtah she'chelbah
tahor. So again, we're going to say that the word טריפה Treifa
here means, basically what we normally say טריפה Treifa means, is not
an animal that died of its wounds, but an animal that you
שחט that was found to be a טריפה. Treifa Fine. So it's
telling you the fat of a טריפה Treifa, is not טמא. Tamei.
But now we've got a problem. מכלל דהיא מטמאה? miklal d'hi metameh?
That sounds like the meat of a טריפה Treifa is מטמאה. But
that's not true. We all agreed at point one that a normal
בהמה that you שחט that's a טריפה Treifa is not מטמאה. That
everybody agrees to. Okay. והאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, v'ha'amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav, ואמרי לה במתניתא תנא: v'amri lei b'masnisa tana: וכי ימות
מן הבהמה. v'chi yamuso min habehemah. If an animal dies, okay, and
then it says it causes טומאה. Tumah? מקצת בהמה מטמאה ומקצת אינה
מטמאה. miktzas behemah metameh miktzas eina metameh. Some dead animals cause טומאה
Tumah. and some do not. ואיזו זו? v'eizo zu? זו טריפה ששחטה.
zu treifa she'shachtah.
Okay, we all agree at point one. Everybody agrees that a normal
animal that is שחט that is a טריפה Treifa is not טמא.
Tamei. So now we've got a problem though, if you're doing all
your learnings from the words
נבילה וטריפה neveila u'treifa etcetera etcetera, so you've got a פסוק that
says, right,
וחלב
נבילה וחלב טריפה
יעשה לכל מלאכה,
v'cheilev neveila v'cheilev treifa yei'aseh
l'chol melacha, so which basically means יעשה לכל מלאכה yei'aseh l'chol melacha
means, means what? Means that the חלב... cheilev...
is
טהור. Tahor. Okay, that's what it means. So now, and the, but
implicitly the בשר Basar is טמא, Tamei, but the בשר Basar of
a טריפה Treifa is not טמא. Tamei. So, right? So what do
you do—I mean it's a סתם Stam question—what do you do with
this word טריפה Treifa here? If you literally say it means טריפה
Treifa the same way רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said literally by the
bird it's טריפה, Treifa it's a טריפה Treifa that was שחוטה Shechted
and that's how we knew a bird that was a טריפה Treifa
that was שחוטה Shechted is טמא. Tamei, So say טריפה Treifa here
also means an animal that was שחוטה. Shechted. And then you're going
to say that it's טמא, Tamei but that's not true.
But what did רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda intend originally, right, when we
said אלא להוציא טרפה ששחטה שמטמא.
Ella l'hotzi treifa she'shachata
she'mitamei.
What טריפה Treifa was he talking about there? A bird?
A bird? Yeah, yeah, yeah. This bird אשר תאכל נבילה וטרפה וטמא
עד הערב, Asher tochal neveila v'treifa v'tamei ad ha'arev, right? That's what
I said. Everybody agrees that a בהמה טריפה Behema treifa is טהור.
Tahor. רבי יהודה says I don't agree that a bird טריפה Treifa.
is טהור Tahor because this פסוק by bird נבילה וטרפה וטמא עד
הערב Neveila v'treifa v'tamei ad ha'arev is about bird and that says
a טריפה Treifa is טמא. Tamei.
How about the פסוק of using the same logic to a פסוק
about חלב Chelev in בהמה, it doesn't just emerge.
Right. So since רבי יהודה chooses to read טריפה Treifa here not
as נבילה, as literally a טריפה Treifa that was שחוטה, Shechted, and
that tells him a bird טריפה Treifa that was שחוטה Shechted is
טמא, Tamei? so tell me also that an animal טריפה Treifa שחוטה
Shechted is טמא tamei? based on the חלב Chelev פסוק. Okay. So
the גמרא says מכלל
דמטמא ואמר רב יוסף בסין אצטריך—but Michlal d'mitamei v'amar Rav Yosef B'sin
itztarich it's not—so the גמרא says מיבעי ליה למעוטי טמאה מי שיש
במינה טריפה יצאה זו שאין במינה טריפה. Mibei lei l'ma'utei tmeia mi
she'yesh b'mina treifa yatza zo she'ein b'mina treifa. So the גמרא says
okay, no, you're right. Here we're not going to say טריפה Treifa
means literally an animal that was שחוטה Shechted that was a טריפה.
Treifa What we're going to use טריפה Treifa to tell me is
an animal that is a כשר Kosher animal. Okay, meaning let me
just look it in.
Right, מי שיש במינה—a Mi she'yesh b'mina type of animal that it
matters if it's a טריפה Treifa or not. My cow, it matters
if it's a טריפה Treifa or not. If it's a טריפה Treifa,
I can't eat it. My pig, it doesn't matter if it's a
טריפה Treifa because what a טריפה Treifa is fundamentally about is not
טומאה, Tumah? a טריפה Treifa is fundamentally about eating. So therefore טריפה
Treifa. only matters by כשר Kosher animals. טריפה Treifa? doesn't matter by
non-כשר Kosher animals. So טריפה Treifa here doesn't mean טריפה, Treifa because
then you're right, then it would lead you to say that an
animal that's a טריפה Treifa is—causes טומאה. tumah. טריפה Treifa here means
we're talking about, bracket this whole thing, and this tells you we're
talking about כשר Kosher animals. Non-כשר Kosher animals, okay, okay,
that's what it's coming to tell you. Okay, they're only by כשר
Kosher animals. But non-כשר Kosher animals, okay, one minute... tell you the
חלב Chelev of the
טמאה Tmeia is...
one minute...
right, when do we say that the fat is טהור? Tahor? By
כשר Kosher animals. But by non-כשר Kosher animals, my pig, my dead
pig, the fat is טמא. tamei. Okay. So anyway, that's what the
word טריפה Treifa is here to do. This הלכה Halacha that the
fat is טהור Tahor doesn't mean a literal טריפה. Treifa, This הלכה
Halacha that the fat is טהור Tahor is to tell you כשר
Kosher animals. So if that's true and presumably רבי יהודה has to
agree to that. So if that's true, we're going to go back
here and challenge: how does רבי יהודה read this פסוק about birds
and טומאה whatever to be literally a טריפה? Treifa The word טריפה
Treifa should really just signifies that we're talking about כשר Kosher animals
and not non-כשר Kosher animals. So the גמרא says if that's true
there, okay. So the גמרא says הכא נמי ליתי למעוטי עוף טמא
שאין במינו טריפה. Hacha nami leitei l'ma'utei of tamei she'ein b'mino treifa.
So how do you learn טריפה Treifa here to mean literally a
טריפה Treifa. and a literal bird טריפה Treifa doesn't cause—causes טומאה? No.
טריפה is a way of telling you we're talking about כשר Kosher
birds. So the גמרא says עוף טמא לרבי
יהודה מנבלה נפקא ליה.
Of tamei
l'Rabbi Yehuda m'neveila nafka lei.
No, רבי יהודה already knows that non-כשר birds are not included. How
does he know this? דתניא רבי יהודה אומר יכול תהא נבלת עוף
טמא מטמא בגדים בבית הבליעה. D'tanya Rabbi Yehuda omer yachol tehe nevelat
of tamei m'tamei b'gadim b'veit hablia. Here's a bizarre הלכה Halacha that
if it's a non-כשר bird it doesn't cause טומאה. Maybe a dead
non-כשר bird that you swallow causes טומאה? תלמוד לומר נבילה וטרפה לא
יאכל—מי שהאיסור משום בל תאכל נבילה יצא זה שאין איסורו משום בל
תאכל נבילה אלא משום בל תאכל טמא. tamei.
So we've got נבילה and טריפה, okay. That's I think לא יאכל
לטמא בה. Lo yochal l'tamei bah. So here, let me just say
this. Sometimes, let me try to pull this together.
Everybody concedes that the שחיטה of a בהמה that's a טריפה is
טהור. Tahor.
So what does this mean, this חלב נבילה וחלב טריפה, Chelev neveila
v'chelev treifa, which I could infer that the meat of a טריפה
is טמא? No. The word טריפה here doesn't mean טריפה. The word
טריפה here means כשר animals, okay, that this הלכה halacha applies only
to כשר animals. The fat of non-כשר animals
So sometimes the word טרפה treifa means, or here means, kosher animals.
So why don't I say, so what's רב יהודה's Reb Yehuda argument
that the שחיטה of a טרפה bird is טמא? Because it says
נבלה וטרפה neveila u'treifa is טמא. He reads טרפה literally. So we
say, but why not say טרפה just means we're talking only about
kosher animals? And he says no. How do I know we're talking
about kosher animals? I get that already from the word נבלה. neveila.
נבלה neveila means an animal that is forbidden to eat to be
eaten only by virtue of it being a נבלה, neveila, as opposed
to non-kosher birds, they're already forbidden.
The next question is obvious, right?
Well, let's not worry about the next question, let's just finish here
for today. Okay, so this tells you that this הלכה applies only
to kosher animals. Somehow the word okay, only kosher animals is from
the word נבלה. neveila. And therefore, what do you left to learn
from טרפה? טרפה can't be telling you kosher animals. So for him
טרפה is literally טרפה. And a שחיטת טרפה shechitas treifa of a
bird—sorry, a שחיטת טרפה shechitas treifa of a bird actually is טמא.
Okay, a שחיטת בהמה טרפה shechitas beheima treifa is טהור. tahor. But
here it says נבלה וטרפה. neveila u'treifa. Bottom line is רב יהודה
Reb Yehuda is just reading the פסוק. It says נבלה וטרפה, neveila
u'treifa, once you read it to be referring to a bird, he's
saying the פסוק is explicitly telling you that even a bird that's
שחט'ד shechted that's a טרפה does cause טומאה. So רב יהודה Reb
Yehuda disagrees with this. This might be a nice קל וחומר, but
the פסוק tells you otherwise. And רב יוסי Reb Yossi tells you
no, I agree to this, I just say you can't get to
מליקה, I don't buy your מה מצינו. So it's a three-way debate.
Okay, we'll end here
for today.