Okay בוקר טוב boker tov today's דף daf is ל"ח. lamed chet.
We pick up
about one two three four five six five lines down from the
top of ל"ח עמוד א lamed chet amud aleph and we are
in the middle of a discussion of the debate of בית הלל
Beis Hillel בית שמאי Beis Shammai that even though the Torah speaks
about putting you know the חטאת chatas putting it on all four
corners
that according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai two suffices בדיעבד bedieved and
according to בית הלל Beis Hillel one suffices. בית שמאי Beis Shammai
learns it out from קרנות karnos קרנות karnos קרנות karnos gives us
six and divides to four לכתחילה lechat'chilah two בדיעבד. bedieved. בית הלל
Beis Hillel we're a little bit struggling to where we know this
idea four לכתחילה lechat'chilah one בדיעבד. bedieved. So now we tried to
learn it out from קרנת karnat קרנת karnat קרנת karnat קרנות karnos
which gives us starts us off with four and the גמרא Gemara
had different ways of dealing with that. Now we're going to introduce
a new a new approach. So again five lines from the top
ל"ח עמוד א. lamed chet amud aleph. ותנא מייתי לה מהכא. Vetana
meiti lah mehacha. The תנא tanna following you know we have a
תנא tanna from a ברייתא baraita that learns בית שמאי Beis Shammai
בית הלל's Beis Hillel position from the following פסוק pasuk וכיפר וכיפר
וכיפר. vechiper vechiper vechiper. Okay it says this by
you know by again by the קרבנות korbanot of the at the
end of פרשת ויקרא Parshat Vayikra that are brought by individuals whether
of the נשיא nasi or by individuals each time it says you
know you should put it on the corners of the מזבח mizbe'ach
and it says and it will atone for him. Okay מפני הדין.
mipnei hadin. So this is you know it is necessary that the
Torah repeats these words וכיפר vechiper to teach us
that
as we're going to see we're going to learn from the וכיפר
vechiper that בדיעבד bedieved you don't need all four corners of the
placement of the blood of the חטאת. chatas. Okay so there's a
reason we need these words. שיכול sheyachol now you might have said
this is a classic מדרש הלכה midrash halacha that it introduces you
why we need to learn it from the particular formulation of the
פסוק pasuk and we can't just learn it out from logic. Okay
so maybe I could have said this הלכה halacha based on
logic. שיכול ולא דין הוא sheyachol velo din hu I could say
that it's a logical derivation. נאמרו דמים למטה ונאמרו דמים למעלה. neemru
damim lemata veneemru damim lemala. It speaks about blood that's at the
bottom half of the מזבח mizbe'ach all קרבנות korbanot other than a
חטאת chatas and it speaks about blood that's at the top half
of the מזבח mizbe'ach the
חטאת. chatas. Okay ונאמרו דמים למעלה. veneemru damim lemala. מה מתן דמים
אמורים למטה שנתן במתנה אחת כיפר mah matan damim amurim lemata shenatan
bematana achas kiper the same way all other קרבנות korbanot that isn't
a חטאת chatas one application of blood suffices. Now we don't know
where we know that from or let's say that yesterday you know
we learned it from ודם זבחיך ישפך. vedam zevachecha yishapech. Presumably according
to this argument we have a separate source to teach us that
by all the other קרבנות korbanot that are not a חטאת chatas
that one application of blood suffices. So if that's true about all
the other
קרבנות korbanot שנתן במתנה אחת כיפר shenatan bematana achas kiper אף דמים
אמורים למעלה שנתן במתנה אחת כיפר. af damim amurim lemala shenatan bematana
achas kiper. I could make an analogy. If all the other קרבנות
korbanot that are on the bottom half of the מזבח mizbe'ach one
מתנה matana is enough let's say from ודם זבחיך ישפך vedam zevachecha
yishapech I'll say the same by a חטאת. chatas. So who needs
a פסוק? pasuk? I'll just learn it out from all the other
קרבנות. korbanot. או כלך לדרך זו o klach lederech zu but no
if we're making a logical argument you could go you could go
this other path. What's this other path? נאמרו דמים בפנים ונאמרו דמים
בחוץ. neemru damim bifnim veneemru damim bachutz. It says putting on the
four corners by a חטאת chatas on the inner altar by an
inner חטאת chatas חטאת פנימית chatas pnimis and it says four corners
of a חטאת chatas on the outer altar when it's that type
of a חטאת. chatas. מה דמים אמורים בפנים חיסר אחת מן המתנות
לא עשה ולא כלום mah damim amurim bifnim chiser achas min hamatanos
lo asa velo klum the same way when it comes to the
inner חטאת chatas all four are מעכב me'akev as we taught in
the משנה mishna we don't yet know where we know that from
but now it's just again take that as an assumption okay so
the same way they're all מעכב me'akev on the inner מזבח mizbe'ach
לא עשה
ולא כלום
lo asa
velo klum אף דמים אמורים בחוץ חיסר אחת מן המתנות לא עשה
ולא כלום. af damim amurim בחוץ chiser achas min hamatanos lo asa
velo klum. So I'll say the same by a חטאת chatas on
the outer מזבח mizbe'ach that every one of them is מעכב. me'akev.
So since you could analogize it the חטאת chatas on the outer
מזבח mizbe'ach on the one hand to the other קרבנות korbanot on
the outer מזבח mizbe'ach that they're on the outer מזבח mizbe'ach but
they're not חטאת chatas and they're the lower half but they're you
could analogize it to them because they're the outer מזבח mizbe'ach that
would teach you only one is מעכב me'akev or you could analogize
it to the חטאת בפנים chatas bifnim which is different that it's
the inner altar but it's similar that it's a חטאת chatas and
four מתנות matanos and you could say that all of them are
מעכב. me'akev. So since you could go either way you needed the
words וכיפר vechiper to teach us that only one is
מעכב. me'akev.
נלמד ממי דומה nilamed mimi domeh but let's keep on arguing and
saying maybe is there more reason to argue to compare and analogize
it to one rather than the
other. דנים חוץ מחוץ ואין דנים חוץ מבפנים. danim chutz michutz ve'ein
danim chutz mibifnim. You'd say no let's analogize it to the other
קרבנות korbanot because they're both on... the outer altar. So that's where
the more logical thing to learn it from. או כלך לדרך זו?
o kalakh l'derekh zu? Or no, let's go the opposite path. There's
a reason to make it an analogize it to the inner חטאת.
chatas. דנים חטאת וארבע קרנות מחטאת וארבע קרנות. danim chatas v'arba kranot
michatas v'arba kranot. Let's both compare a חטאת chatas and all four
corners, which is in the inner altar, to a חטאת chatas and
all four corners, which is the outer altar. ואל יוכיח חוץ שאין
חטאת וארבע קרנות. v'al yokhiach chutz she'ein chatas v'arba kranot. And we
won't analogize it to the other קרבנות, korbanot, even though they're the
outer altar, they're not a חטאת chatas and they're not four corners.
So since you could go
both
ways, logic won't suffice. We need a פסוק pasuk to teach us.
Okay. So תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar, so that's why the פסוק pasuk
teaches וכיפר וכיפר וכיפר. vechiper vechiper vechiper. It says three times. Not
only you put the blood on the מזבח, mizbeiach, but it will
atone for him. Okay. וכיפר. vechiper. And each one is
saying and don't worry, you'll get atonement. So it's underscoring the atonement
will happen. So that's to tell you even if you don't do
it perfectly, it'll be atoned. And it tells it to us three
times. וכיפר אף על פי שלא נתן אלא שלש. vechiper af al
pi shelo natan ela shalosh. You'll be atoned even if you didn't
do it perfectly, even if you only did three times. That's what
the first וכיפר vechiper says. וכיפר אף על פי שלא נתן אלא
שתים. vechiper af al pi shelo natan ela shtayim. The second וכיפר,
vechiper, even if you did less perfectly than that and you only
did two. וכיפר אף על פי שלא נתן אלא אחת. vechiper af
al pi shelo natan ela achat. And even if you did less
perfectly than that, only one. So the three וכיפרs vechiper that tell
you, promise you the end result is you'll get atonement, all of
those, each one of those knocks down the requirement, says בדיעבד, bedi'avad,
you know, goes down one level, so בדיעבד bedi'avad only
one suffices. So that's where this תנא tanna learns it from. That
to me is a little more satisfying than the counting of the
numbers of קרנות. kranot. Okay. So now the גמרא gemara says one
minute. והמיבעי ליה לגופיה? vehami'ba'ei lei legufei? How do you start learning
וכיפר vechiper to start teaching you you know even if you didn't
do it perfectly, you're still going to be atoned? Maybe you just
need it for פשט pshat to tell me that you'll be atoned?
Like that's פשט. pshat. It's not to tell me that it doesn't
have to be perfect. First it has to just tell me this
achieves כפרה. kapara. So the גמרא gemara says אמר רב אדא בר
אהבה מארי אספר לי. amar rav adda bar ahava mari aspar li.
So Rav Adda bar Ahava said
Mari explain to me אמר קרא, amar krah, the פסוק pasuk says
וכיפר ונסלח. vechiper venislach. It uses two words. It'll be atoned and
he'll be forgiven. זו היא כפרה זו היא סליחה. zo hi kapara
zo hi slicha. So that's basically communicating the same point. You bring
your קרבן korban and it cleans your sin. Why does it have
to say both וכיפר vechiper and ונסלח? venislach? אימא וכיפר אף על
פי שלא נתן אלא שלש למה? eima vechiper af al pi shelo
natan ela shalosh lama? Okay fine. So therefore because it already says
ונסלח, venislach, we can use וכיפר vechiper to start saying even if
it's not perfect. And three וכיפרs vechiper get you down to one
מתנה. matana. Very good. Okay now the גמרא gemara is going to
ask a question about maybe I could have used וכיפר vechiper to
tell you not perfect, but not perfect in a different way. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא gemara says אימא, eima, but
why not say the following? וכיפר אף על פי שלא נתן אלא
שלש למעלה ואחת למטה. vechiper af al pi shelo natan ela shalosh
lemala v'achat למטה lemata. Even if you didn't do it perfectly, even
if you only did three above and one below. Not just did
three, you did four, but one of the four you did on
the bottom half of the מזבח. mizbeiach. And then the next וכיפר
vechiper would tell you וכיפר אף על פי שלא נתן אלא שתים
למטה ושתים למעלה. vechiper af al pi shelo natan ela shtayim lemata
u'shtayim lemala. Even if you didn't do even if you did only
two above and two below, meaning I'm with you, it's saying even
if it's not perfect that you didn't do them on the corners,
but maybe it still would be assuming but you did them on
the lower half of the מזבח. mizbeiach. וכיפר אף על פי שלא
נתן למעלה אלא למטה. vechiper af al pi shelo natan lemala ela
lemata.
And the third one would tell you even if you did none
above, even if you did you know all four below. Now it's
a little interesting that the גמרא gemara jumps. The גמרא gemara should
have said one above and three below. So תוספות tosafot asks this
question.
And at least one of the answers that he gives is that
you know we could have understood the model that the top of
the מזבח mizbeiach is the majority. It's like three or two, at
least it's 50 percent.
And we could understand the model that you just skipped the top
of the מזבח mizbeiach and you did the bottom because then you're
going on a different path, doing the bottom. But to say but
to say one above and three below is a little נישט אהין
נישט אהער nisht ahin nisht aher that the גמרא gemara didn't see
as a possible landing point. Anyway, that's what תוספות tosafot says. Not
exactly clear. Okay, but the גמרא gemara says why not learn it
to tell me not that בדיעבד bedi'avad if you don't do them
at all, but בדיעבד bedi'avad if you do them below it counts.
Okay, and do the rest above. So the גמרא gemara says אמר
רב אדא בר יצחק אם כן ביטלת תורת ארבע קרנות.
amar rav adda bar yitzchak
im ken bitalta torat arba kranot.
Okay,
what no, because if that's true, then you're ending that you don't
need it on any of the corners. You know, you could have
it all below. Again, this raises the question why the גמרא gemara
didn't suggest one above and three below, but again let's just assume
that it cannot it's you know. it must either have the weight
above, or it has to have everything below. All right, so then
he says no, that wouldn't, that's not a possible read of the
פסוק *pasuk* because then you will have totally eliminated the idea of
the four corners. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ורחמנא אמר ליבטלו
*ve-rachmana amar livtelun*. But so what? If the תורה *Torah* says that's
an option, let it be בטל *batel*. You know, sort of like
we said yesterday. If you don't do זריקה zrika *zerika*, you know,
okay, you do שפיכה *shfika*. Maybe there's a different path here. Who
cares that you don't get anything on the corner? That's the way
we're going to read the פסוק *pasuk*. So אמר רבא *amar Rava*
no, איזהו דרוש שצריך שלוש הוי אומר אלו קרנות *eizu drush she-tzarich
shalosh havei omer elu kranos*. So I'll read this way רש"י *Rashi*
reads it. רש"י *Rashi* says what thing דרשה *drasha* does three וכפר
*ve-chiper*s work for? Three וכפר *ve-chiper*s work to go from four קרנות
*kranos* to one קרן *keren*. But if you want to end by
saying everything below, then you would have needed four וכפר *ve-chiper*s. Three
וכפר *ve-chiper*s is not enough. Okay, again, why not say one above
and three below? But for some reason, that's not being perceived of
as an option. So if you're going to end up with four
below, you would have needed four וכפר *ve-chiper*s.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one minute, let's try another
way of reading the פסוק *pasuk*. אימא וכפר אף על פי שלא
נתן אלא אחת למעלה ושלוש למטה *eima ve-chiper af al pi she-lo
nasan ela achas l-ma'alah ve-shalosh l-mata*. So now finally the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says wait, wait, what about the option we skipped over? Okay,
let's read for three and come to the conclusion one above and
three below. So now it's the same idea. One above suffices. We're
just saying not that you didn't do any of the three but
you did the other three but you did them all below. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
now we're going to understand why it was resisting it before. לא
lo, מצינו דמים שחצים למעלה וחצים למטה *lo matzinu damim she-chetzyan l-ma'alah
ve-chetzyan l-mata*. You know, we haven't found blood that's half above and
half below. Now this is a little strange because you know by
the second וכפר *ve-chiper* we were two and two. So that was
also half above and half below. But it seems what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is saying is no, no, that was a midpoint. The
question is where are we going to land? Okay? So in our
first version, we landed you don't need anything above, you can do
it all below. And that was rejected because then we would have
needed four וכפר *ve-chiper*s. In this version, forget the middle steps. Where
we land is one above and three below. That's not an acceptable
end result because you are splitting the מתן דמים *matan damim* above
and below. And so now we have better insight to why the
גמרא Gemara? *Gemara* didn't want to do it before. We can accept
בדיעבד *be-di'avad* one is enough above. We can accept בדיעבד *be-di'avad* nothing
above all below. Okay? We cannot accept בדיעבד *be-di'avad* half above half
below. There is no קרבן korban *korban* that you split the blood
like that, that that could be a requirement that requires both above
and below. Okay? So that's not an acceptable conclusion. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says ולא *ve-lo*? Is that not true?
והתנן *ve-ha-tenan*, we taught in a משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* about יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*, הזה ממנו אחת למעלה ושבע למטה *hizah mimenu achas l-ma'alah
ve-sheva l-mata*. So if you did, you know, when he's sprinkling towards
the ארון *Aron*, one above and seven below. Now of course we
all know, you know, what that means. You're not supposed to hit
the ארון *Aron*. It means the way you're moving your finger. But
the גמרא *Gemara* understands at least you know playing dumb maybe that
it means one at the top half of the ארון *Aron* and
seven at the bottom half. So you're splitting where the blood is.
So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, it means כמצליף *k-matzlif*. It means
that you're flicking your hand. Are you flicking your hand up, your
finger up, or are you flicking your finger down? But you're not
hitting the ארון *Aron*. Okay? And the ארון *Aron* isn't functioning like
a מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbe'ach* here. מאי כמצליף *mai k-matzlif*? What does that
mean like flogging or whatever? מחוי ליה רב יהודה *machvei lei Rav
Yehuda*. רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* demonstrated with his finger כמנגדא *ke-menagda* like
somebody sort of flogging. Okay? So you know, your finger moves up
to down, that's the seven below, or down to up, that's the
one above. But it's not being split on the ארון *Aron*. So
now the גמרא *Gemara* continues. הזה על טהרו של מזבח mizbeach. *hizah
al taharo shel mizbe'ach*. So after you're done with you know the
קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kadashim* and then you're done with the פרוכת *paroches*
and then you go to the מזבח הזהב mizbeach hazahav *mizbe'ach ha-zahav*.
This is on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* and you sprinkle on the
טהרו *taharo* of the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. So what does this word
the טהרו *taharo* of the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach* mean, the מזבח mizbeach.
הזהב *mizbe'ach ha-zahav*? שבע פעמים *sheva pe'amim*, seven times. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says top of ל"ח עמוד ב *lamed chet amud beis*, מאי
לאו *mai lav* אפלגיה דמזבח *a-palgei d-mizbe'ach*. So at the טהרו *taharo*
of the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*, that must mean you know in the
middle of the מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*. Like you know on the side
of the מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach* halfway up. Why? כדאמרי אינשי *k-d-amrei inshi*
טיהרא טיהרא דיומא *tiahra tiahra de-yoma*. People talk about like the you
know the purity of the day means midday, it means when noon
when the sun is in the middle. So טהרו של מזבח *taharo
shel mizbe'ach* the גמרא *Gemara* thinks means at the wall of the
מזבח *mizbe'ach* at the midpoint. Okay? And that would be splitting the
blood. Why? The way תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* explains because you have it
you put it on the four corners and it says after the
four corners you put on טהרו של מזבח *taharo shel mizbe'ach*. So
it would be a combination of the corners which are above and
like the middle of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*. which is also, you know,
some of it is below, or whatever, but they're clearly very separate
places. Okay, so you see it can work to have separate places.
So גמרא says no. אמר רבה בר שילא Amar Ravva bar Shila
לא, that's not what סתירה stira means, it means אגלוייא agiluya on
the exposed part, but it's still the roof of the מזבח. So
if it's on the corners and it's on the roof, that's all
in the same place. Okay, כדכתיב וכעצם השמים לטהר, kichsiv u'ke-etzem hashamayim
latohar, the purity of the heaven, so that means what is above.
Okay, or means what is exposed.
So now the גמרא says, okay, but in any קרבן korban, ואיכא
שיריים, ve'ika shirayim, don't isn't there the spilling of the remainder of
the blood? So any קרבן, korban like let's even start with a
חטאת, chatas, four on the four corners plus the spilling at the
יסוד. yesod. So that's blood in two places. So שיריים לא מעכבי.
shirayim lo ma'akvei. No, the שיריים shirayim are not מעכב, ma'akve, and
here we're talking about what is מעכב, ma'akve, what will prevent the
קרבן korban, from being כשר. kosher. So
the גמרא says ואיכא שיריים פנימיים, ve'ika shirayim pnimiyim, there's an opinion
you pour and you after you do the four corners of the
מזבח הזהב in the inner חטאת, chatas, you pour the remainder of
the blood at the יסוד yesod of the outer מזבח. So and
there's an opinion that that's מעכב. ma'akve. So there you have two
placements of blood and not just in different places in the מזבח
but on different מזבחות mizbeachos and they're both מעכב. ma'akve.
So גמרא says בחד מקום קאמינא. bechad makom kamina. No, in one
place on one מזבח you don't have that you need two separate
places on the מזבח. Okay, it's a little funny. You say קל
וחומר kal vachomer you shouldn't be good, should require one thing one
מזבח and one the other? But maybe not. Each מזבח does its
own thing, but the עבודה avoda of blood on a particular מזבח,
you know, cannot be that it has to be fundamentally in two
places. So now what do we have? We have one way of
learning the idea of one only is מעכב ma'akve from קרנות קרנת
קרנת קרנת karnot karnat karnat karnat what we did yesterday. And the
other is by וכיפר וכיפר וכיפר vechifer vechifer vechifer gets you down
from four to three to two to one, again also remembering a
general idea of that, you know, when it comes to קרבנות korbanot
unless it's repeated we don't assume that it's מעכב. ma'akve. And the
גמרא here just said we land at one suffices and we don't
land by reading it, you know, all below because then you would
have needed four וכיפר. vechifers. And we don't land at reading it
one above and three below because that would not make sense that
what is מעכב ma'akve is blood in two separate places. Okay, that
is where we learn, you know, according to בית הלל Beis Hillel
and בית שמאי. Beis Shammai.
Now, now we are going to speak about the ramifications of it,
what the משנה did particularly in terms of פיגול. pigul. Let's take
a look.
תניא תנא ברייתא Tanya tana Baraisa רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov omer בית שמאי אומרים שתי מתנות שבחטאת ואחת שבכל
הזבחים Beis Shammai omrim shtei matanot shebachatat ve'achat shebechol hazevachim מתירות, mtirot,
they are מתיר matir the קרבן, korban meaning that makes you יוצא
yotzei the קרבן korban and now you can eat the meat and
burn the אימורים emurim ומפגלות. umefaglot. And during this period and for
those two עבודות avodot by the חטאת chatas and the one act
by the other קרבנות, korbanot, right, that is your only opportunity for
פיגול. pigul. After the קרבן korban is good, the rest of the
stuff you're doing with the blood, even the זריקה or whatever, does
not have relevance for פיגול. pigul. בית הלל אומרים Beis Hillel omrim
and בית הלל Beis Hillel says אחת שבחטאת ואחת שבכל הזבחים. achat
shebachatat ve'achat shebechol hazevachim. No, no, no, whether it's even by a
חטאת chatas it's only one placement and also agreeing with בית שמאי
Beis Shammai one for all other קרבנות. korbanot. So for all קרבן
korban, including a חטאת chatas it's only the first placement of blood
that matters, מתרת, mteret, that first placement makes the animal the קרבן,
korban? you know, it's good, you're יוצא yotzei ומפגלת umefagelet and only
and פיגול pigul can only occur during that one placement of blood.
Okay,
so
מתקיף לה רב אושעיא maskif lah Rav Oshaya asked on this, אם
כן ליתני קולי בית שמאי וחומרי בית הלל. im kein lisnei kulei
Beis Shammai ve'chumrei Beis Hillel. So actually בית שמאי Beis Shammai is
being מיקל. meikel. Now why is בית שמאי Beis Shammai being מיקל?
meikel? Well, it depends what perspective you're looking for. In terms of
if the blood spilled, was I יוצא yotzei the קרבן? korban So
בית שמאי Beis Shammai is מחמיר machmir after you did the first
מתנה matana by a חטאת, chatas, חטאת chatas is the only place
they disagree, two versus one. So there, you know, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai is his classic מחמיר, machmir, you have to do both before
you're יוצא yotzei the קרבן korban? if it spills after one you're
not יוצא. yotzei. And בית הלל Beis Hillel says one you're יוצא.
yotzei. So there בית שמאי Beis Shammai is his classic מחמיר. machmir.
But when it comes to פיגול, pigul, you know, בית שמאי Beis
Shammai is a מיקל. meikel. Why? Because בית שמאי Beis Shammai would
say if you had פיגול pigul thought on the first מתנה matana
of blood but not on the second, it's not פיגול. pigul. You
need it at both מתנות matanot assuming אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר. ein
mefaglin bechatzi matir. I'll get back to that in a second. So
בית שמאי Beis Shammai actually is מיקל meikel because he says פיגול
pigul requires both מתנות matanot by the חטאת chatas and for בית
הלל Beis Hillel only the first מתנה matana is what matters. matter.
So the גמרא says, אמר ליה רבא כי אצטריך להיתרא אצטריך דהוי
בית שמאי לחומרא. Amar lei Rava ki itztarich l'heitera itztarich d'havei Beit
Shammai l'chumra. No, when it was decided, you know, in the place
where we're listing the debate because in, you know, in עדיות Edyos
is where it says, you know, things that are קולי בית שמאי
וחומרי בית הלל, kulei Beit Shammai v'chumrei Beit Hillel, places where בית
שמאי Beit Shammai is מקל, meikel, it lists the places. So it
says, you know, that when that was being decided, oh, should we
incorporate this debate about, you know, two מתנות matanot for a חטאת
chatat or one, it was framed as, what do you need to
מתיר matir the קרבן? korban So in that context, right, it was,
you know, להיתרא אצטריך, l'heitera itztarich, what will make the קרבן korban.
מותר, muttar, what will make you יוצא. yotzei. And in that context,
בית שמאי Beit Shammai is מחמיר. machmir. So even though when you
look at it from a פיגול pigul lens, בית שמאי Beit Shammai
is מקל, meikel, you know, when we were deciding whether to list
this as קולי בית שמאי וחומרי בית הלל, kulei Beit Shammai v'chumrei
Beit Hillel, we were approaching it from the perspective of what do
you need to be יוצא yotzei the קרבן. korban. Now, I just
want to say one thing about this assumption that בית שמאי Beit
Shammai is מחמיר machmir because, you know, you need a פיגול pigul
thought at both מתנות. matanot. So תוספות asks how do we know
this is true? You know, maybe בית שמאי Beit Shammai says מפגלין
בחצי מתיר. mefaglin b'chatzi matir.
Maybe בית שמאי Beit Shammai says either the first or the second
can create פיגול. pigul. How do you know that he says that
both, you need both to create פיגול? pigul? Then בית שמאי Beit
Shammai will again be מחמיר. machmir. So what's the question of the
גמרא? So on the one hand, he tries to say that the
parallel to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, the same way בית הלל Beit
Hillel said one is מפגל mefagel and they say two, means both
of them, not either of them, and you need both and אין
מפגלין בחצי מתיר. ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir. And the other point he
says is even when it comes to פיגול, pigul, even if that
were true, that בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say either the first
or the second can create פיגול, pigul, and so they're also מחמיר
machmir by פיגול, pigul, but at least there's a scenario where they're
מקל meikel by פיגול. pigul. What's a scenario where they're מקל meikel
by פיגול? pigul? Which is you put on one corner with the
כוונה kavana of פיגול, pigul, and then you spilled the blood. So
you didn't do the second corner. So in that case, בית הלל
Beit Hillel would say it's פיגול, pigul, and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
would say, you know, no, it's not פיגול, pigul, you didn't finish
doing the placement of the blood.
So according to both, you're not יוצא yotzei the קרבן. korban. So
in that case, בית הלל Beit Hillel is more מחמיר machmir because
he says not only are you not יוצא, yotzei, it's פיגול, pigul,
and בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say you did not קרב כל
מתיריו. karev kol matirav. I'll give you another way in which בית
שמאי Beit Shammai is מקל meikel by פיגול, pigul, even if either
one suffices, and that would be you had a פיגול pigul thought
for number one and a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo thought for number
two. So according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, the חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo thought is irrelevant, you're done with the מתיר matir of the
קרבן. So according to בית הלל, Beit Hillel, it is פיגול. pigul.
But according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, the first thought made it
פיגול, pigul, but the second thought made it חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo,
and that takes it out of פיגול. pigul. So there are ways
even if it's not clear if according to בית שמאי Beit Shammai
you need a פיגול pigul thought in both of the מתנות, matanot,
אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir, and then he's obviously
מקל meikel by פיגול. pigul. Or even if he says מפגלין בחצי
מתיר mefaglin b'chatzi matir and either מתנה matana can make it פיגול,
pigul, there are scenarios in which בית שמאי Beit Shammai will be
לכולא. lekula. But when the question was asked, it was asked from
the perspective not of פיגול, pigul, but of what makes the קרבן
כשר. korban kasher. Okay, we will end with this here.