So, today's דף daf is כ"ג chaf gimmel 23, but we're going
to start on כ"ב עמוד ב' chaf beis amud beis and where
I was told that we should be resuming there, and we have
spent a good amount of time talking about the washing of the
hands and the feet and not just about if a כהן kohen
does not do it, the עבודה avodah is פסול, pasul, but also
how the hands and feet were washed and all of those details.
And now we're turning to the next—we did briefly—and now we're turning
to the next case of the משנה, mishnah, which is טמא. tamei.
An impure person, an impure כהן, kohen, the עבודה avodah is פסול,
pasul, is invalid. We've actually spoken about lesser degrees of impurity, about
מחוסרי כיפורים mechusrei kippurim and טבול יום, tevul yom, and now we
talk about the case of טמא tamei itself. So let's take a
look, middle of כ"ב עמוד ב': chaf beis amud beis: טמא פסול.
tamei pasul. So אמרו זקני דרום, Amru Ziknei Darom, the elders of
the South say: לא שנו אלא טמא שרץ אבל טמא מת הואיל
ומרצה בציבור מרצה נמי ביחיד. Lo shanu ela tamei sheretz, aval tamei
meis ho'il umiratzeh betzibur, miratzeh nami beyachid. So when is a כהן
kohen who is טמא tamei invalidates the עבודה? avodah? That's only if
he's טמא tamei by touching a שרץ, sheretz, like a dead rodent,
or other types of טומאה tuma through contact, but
or certainly טומאה tuma through bodily secretions. But if he's טמא tamei
because of contact with a dead body, then actually although that's more
severe than touching a dead animal, ironically nevertheless
the עבודה avodah is כשר. kasher. Why?
Because since it is accepted בציבור, betzibur, מרצה נמי ביחיד meratzeh nami
beyachid is also accepted as an individual. Now I want to say
something that I've been meaning to say something, so that you know
the constant term we use about a sacrifice being valid is ריצוי,
ritzuy, מרצה, miratzeh, and I just wanted to note how the one
of the תפילות, tefillos, one of the ברכות brachos of the שמונה
עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, which says רצה ה' אלוהינו, Retzei Hashem Elokeinu, right,
is the only one actually, it's interesting, the whole idea to which
תפילה כנגד קרבנות, tefillah keneged korbanos, but on the other hand קרבנות
korbanos are really absent from שמונה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So the only
place that קרבנות korbanos are alluded to is in the רצה, Retzei,
and even there it only says אשי ישראל ותפילתם, ishei Yisrael u'tefillatam,
you know, their fire offerings. So it's interesting, but that why are
קרבנות korbanos so hidden from the שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? What?
And that's why we say מוסף mussaf definitely, and that's why you
say יעלה ויבא Yaaleh v'Yavo in רצה Retzei because it's כנגד הקרבנות.
keneged hakorbanos. Anyway, I just wanted to note that the ריצוי ritzuy
and רצה, Retzei, that is the key verb for קרבנות. korbanos. Anyway,
back to this point. So the principle is טומאה הותרה בציבור. tuma
hutra b'tzibur. Interesting principle for חנוכה, Chanukah, the question people ask is:
why did they need the שמן טהור? shemen tahor? Now תוספות Tosafos
points out and the רמב"ם Rambam points out that it's really טומאה
הותרה בציבור tuma hutra b'tzibur is really a misnomer, because it's not
about it being a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, it's about it being
a קרבן korban that has a fixed time. So most of the
time that's קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, right, because what's a קרבן ציבור?
korban tzibur? קרבן תמיד, korban tamid, a קרבן korban of יום טוב,
Yom Tov, the מוספים, musafim, those are the קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur
and they have a fixed time. You can have a קרבן יחיד
korban yachid that has a fixed time—one of them פסח, Pesach, right?
פסח Pesach comes at a very specific time, can come at no
other time, so in their ways it's like a קרבן ציבור korban
tzibur that everybody brings it at the same time, but technically it's
a קרבן יחיד. korban yachid. And you could have a קרבן ציבור
korban tzibur that does not have a fixed time, for example like
the טומאת הוריות, tumat horayos, the קרבנות korbanos of הוריות. horayos. Okay,
so the real point is that at the fixed time, because of
the fixed time it has to come, it overrides טומאה, tuma, but
interestingly not all טומאה, tuma, only טומאה tuma of טמא מת. tamei
meis. Certain טומאות tumaot that are more severe it doesn't override, like
a זב, zav, נדה, niddah, מצורע, metzora, and so on, it would
not override
זבה zavah etc. Those does not override because those are considered טומאה
יוצא מגופו, tuma yotzei m'gufo, and it also does not override even
interestingly less severe ones, contact טומאות tumaot which are less than מת,
meis, שרץ, sheretz, for some reason the principle is it only overrides
טמא מת. tamei meis. I want to say one other thing about
when it overrides טמא מת tamei meis and where this misnomer of
ציבור tzibur comes, so it only overrides when either the entire—the רוב
rov of the ציבור tzibur is טמא. tamei. So
and that really is mostly a problem by קרבן פסח, korban Pesach,
because most of the time why do you care the רוב rov
of the ציבור tzibur is טמא? tamei? Like if it's a תמיד
tamid or מוסף, mussaf, let the כהנים kohanim bring it, who cares
that the ציבור tzibur is טמא? tamei? So that really only comes
up by קרבן פסח korban Pesach where the people have to eat,
so if one or two people or half is טמא tamei so
they bring a פסח שני, Pesach Sheni, when רוב rov are טמא
tamei they can bring it now. Okay, so most of the time
outside of קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, טומאה הותרה בציבור tuma hutra b'tzibur
is when the כהנים kohanim are טמא. tamei. Now there's a discussion
in the גמרא Gemara whether טומאה הותרה בציבור tuma hutra b'tzibur or
טומאה דחויה בציבור, tuma dchuya b'tzibur, whether it totally is like there's
no problem of it in these contexts, when it's a קרבן ציבור
korban tzibur we don't care about טומאה, tuma, that's הותרה, hutra, or
no, it's a problem but the need to bring it overrides, that's
דחויה. dchuya. If you say overrides, overrides is only a concept when
there aren't alternatives. So therefore if there are טהור כהנים, Tahor Kohanim,
you have the טהור כהנים Tahor Kohanim, bring it. Interestingly, even if
the כהנים kohanim, whose whose week to work is not this week,
but if there's in another sort of shift, you have טהור tahor
כהנים, kohanim you get rid of the כהנים Kohanim from this shift
that are טמא Tamei and you bring in the other shift. But
if there are no available טהור tahor כהנים, Kohanim then you do
it בטומאה. Be-Tuma. So it's a concept of דחויה Dechuya being overridden
when there are no alternatives. So again the basic principles is it's
a קרבן Korban of a fixed time, it's only for טמי מת,
Tmei Meis, and it is דחויה, Dechuya, so if you have alternatives
you go by the alternatives.
Why don't they make a קל וחומר? Kal Vachomer?
Why? Because it's all הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai, so you
don't use logic, you don't use קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, you have
these fixed rules.
So therefore the argument that it's only טמי מת Tmei Meis meaning
all other טומאות Tumot
would not be הותרה בציבור, Hutra Be-Tzibur, you would not bring the
קרבן. Korban. Okay.
So that's although it's a little ironic that we understand maybe more
severe but not less severe, but anyway because of that we say
if a כהן Kohen is טמי מת Tmei Meis and he does
the—gezundheit—עבודה, Avoda, then it is כשר בדיעבד, Kasher B'diavad, meaning whether he
violated, that's not the point, the point is the עבודה Avoda is
כשר, Kasher, since were it a case of ציבור, Tzibur, all the
כהנים Kohanim would be טמא, Tamei, then it would go ahead and
allow it to be brought. So therefore even if it was only
a case of the individual, בדיעבד, B'diavad, since sometimes we tolerate טומאה,
Tuma, or at least טומאת מת, Tumat Meis, the קרבן Korban is
כשר. Kasher. But if it was a lower טומאה Tuma or a
higher one, but even if it was a טמי שרץ, Tmei Sheretz,
since we never tolerate that even in a ציבור Tzibur case, therefore
בדיעבד B'diavad it's invalid. Okay. So they said the exception to the
rule of טמי מת Tmei Meis of כהן Kohen that he invalidated
is when he's טמי מת, Tmei Meis, because since there are times
when we tolerate it, therefore בדיעבד, B'diavad, post facto, will always be
valid. Okay. Is that clear? Okay. Well let's take a look at
that. Okay. מתוך שמרצה בציבור, Mitoch She-Miratze Be-Tzibur, since it would be
accepted if it was a case of a קרבן ציבור, Korban Tzibur,
מרצה נמי ביחיד, Miratze Nami Be-Yachid, it's acceptable even when it is
not a קרבן ציבור, Korban Tzibur, even when it is a private
קרבן, Korban, because since sometimes טמי מת Tmei Meis is tolerated. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי טמי שרץ נמי ניתי בקל וחומר
מטמי מת, Ei Hachi Tmei Sheretz Nami Nesei Be-Kal Vachomer Mi-Tmei Meis,
so let's make a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer from a טמי שרץ,
Tmei Sheretz, somebody who touched a dead rodent. What's the קל וחומר?
Kal Vachomer? מה טמי מת שטוען הזיה שלישי ושביעי מרצה, Ma Tmei
Meis She-Taun Hazaya Shlishi Ve-Shevii Miratze, טמי מת Tmei Meis which is
much more severe, you need to sprinkle the ashes on the third
and the seventh day, and בדיעבד B'diavad it's okay when he brings
a קרבן, Korban, טמי שרץ שאינו טוען הזיה שלישי ושביעי, Tmei Sheretz
She-Eino Taun Hazaya Shlishi Ve-Shevii, a טמי שרץ Tmei Sheretz that you
don't need to go through a seven-day process, you just go to
the מקוה, Mikvah, אינו דין שמרצה, Eino Din She-Miratze, certainly it should,
it should be good. So I understand that you don't have the
principle of טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma Hutra Be-Tzibur, but at the end
of the day you're saying a כהן Kohen who's a טמי מת,
Tmei Meis, the קרבן's Korban's good, so say a כהן Kohen who's
a טמי שרץ, Tmei Sheretz, certainly the קרבן Korban should be good,
it's a lesser טומאה. Tuma. You could say that for a זב
Zav also.
No, a זב Zav is more severe. But he doesn't need שלישי
ושביעי. Shlishi Ve-Shevii.
He doesn't need שלישי ושביעי, Shlishi Ve-Shevii, but the גמרא Gemara always
assumes that a זב, Zav, that anything that's טמא Tamei because of
something that's happening to your body is different than a טומאה Tuma
that comes from the outside because of contact. טומאה יוצא מגופו Tuma
Yotzei Mi-Gufo was always considered more severe even though there's no הזיה
שלישי ושביעי. Hazaya Shlishi Ve-Shevii. Okay. That's just, I mean, you know,
they're apples and oranges a little bit, but that's the way the
גמרא Gemara thinks. Okay. So, so the גמרא Gemara says okay, it's
very nice where you got it from, but at the end of
the day you make a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer. So קסברי זקני
דרום, Kasavari Ziknei Darom, זקני דרום Ziknei Darom are of the opinion,
מכפרים כמתכפרים, Mechapprim K'mi-S-chapprim, that those that atone are like those that
are atoned for. כהנים Kohanim are like the people who are atoned
for. So what does that mean? מה מתכפרים טמי מת אין טמי
שרץ לא, Ma Mis-chapprim Tmei Meis In Tmei Sheretz Lo, the same
way those that are atoned for, ישראל, Yisrael, if a ישראל Yisrael
is טמי מת, Tmei Meis, he is and most of the ציבור
Tzibur is טמי מת, Tmei Meis, they bring the קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, you know, they don't push it off, they bring it on
the day. So therefore, and not if it's their טמי שרץ, Tmei
Sheretz, even though that's less severe. So that's what I told you,
that's the irony of טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma Hutra Be-Tzibur, that it's
for טמי מת Tmei Meis not for טמי שרץ. Tmei Sheretz. So
the same way that's true for ישראל Yisrael that we know that
by a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and that presumably is agreed upon,
so if that's true for the ישראל Yisrael that it's only by
טמי מת, Tmei Meis, אף מכפרים טמי מת אין טמי שרץ לא.
Af Mechapprim Tmei Meis In Tmei Sheretz Lo.
So therefore they say, so this is a question about the parameters,
right, of טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tuma Hutra Be-Tzibur, that we know that
for the ישראלים, Yisraelim, ישראל Yisrael is only, can only bring the
קרבן פסח בטומאה Korban Pesach Be-Tuma when it's טמי מת, Tmei Meis,
not when it's other טומאות. Tumot. So they're saying if that's true
for the ישראלים, Yisraelim, it's true for the כהנים Kohanim as well.
So the כהנים Kohanim also when the טומאה Tuma is allowed for
them, it's only allowed when they're טמי מת, Tmei Meis, it's not
allowed for them when they're טמי שרץ. Tmei Sheretz. So at the
end of the day it's true, טמי מת Tmei Meis is more
severe, but because according to זקני דרום Ziknei Darom the principle of
טומאה הותרה בציבור Tuma Hutra Be-Tzibur applies whether ישראל, Yisrael, whether כהנים
Kohanim only for טמי מת, Tmei Meis, then even though it's a
more severe טומאה Tuma when it's a case of an individual כהן
Kohen who's טמא, Tamei, we're willing more to tolerate טמי מת Tmei
Meis than we are a טמי שרץ. Tmei Sheretz. Yes.
You understand why it's more severe?
טמי מת, Tmei Meis, you mean why in the תורה? Torah? I
mean, the evidence that it's more severe... seven days and so on.
Well the evidence seems to be, I mean, you know, if it's
coming through the contact טומאות tumos are all through different sources.
Why? Why the source?
Why the תורה, Torah, why
the תורה Torah treats,
why the source of a dead human is more severe than a
dead animal? I mean, the assumption generally is is that, you know,
is that if the loss of life, the change between living and
dead is greater, the, you know, in general טומאה, tuma, the best
way to understand, you know, טומאה tuma in general is having some
relationship with death. Right.
But it seems, it seems like that's שרץ.
sheretz. No. No, no. טמאי שרץ Tmei sheretz does not have the
override of הותרה בציבור. hutra betzibur. Right. Oh, so that's what you
mean. So you mean why does the overriding principle of הותרה בציבור
hutra betzibur only by טמאי מת tmei meis and not by שרץ.
sheretz. Yes. So that's correct. That's very, that is definitely ironic. That
it's exactly just one סוג sug of מת, meis, not something that's
more severe the cases of, you know, of a מצורע metzora and
a זב, zav, and not something less severe like a שרץ. sheretz.
Only this. So, yeah, I don't know. You know, the דרשה drasha
that טומאה הותרה בציבור tuma hutra betzibur is learned from קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, and it's learned from the people that were טמאי מת,
tmei meis, and it's, you know, and it says איש כי יהיה
טמא לנפש או בדרך רחוקה ish ki yihye tamei lanefesh o bederech
rechoka then he brings a פסח שני. Pesach Sheini. And the גמרא's
Gemara דרשה drasha is when an איש ish is טמא, tamei, when
an individual is טמא, tamei, then he brings a פסח שני. Pesach
Sheini. When הציבור hatzibur is טמא, tamei, you don't bring a פסח
שני. Pesach Sheini. And the טומאה tuma the תורה Torah happened to
be talking about there, because that was the case that original, you
know, was the origin of it, was טמאי מת. tmei meis. So
it says איש איש כי יהיה טמא לנפש. ish ish ki yihye
tamei lanefesh. So טמא לנפש tamei lanefesh means טומאת מת. tumas meis.
So that at least is a source. It's not an explanation, but
that's how come we identify טומאת מת tumas meis as the thing
that overrides. As far as an explanation, I can't help you.
Because there were so many things that were done at the time
in response to death that we were forbidden from,
that the idea of having a, of having the opportunity to bring
קרבנות korbanos after death is perhaps a kind of a, an override
in
itself.
Affirm the sense of life when there's so much death. That's an
interesting approach. Right.
There are all these things we're told we're not allowed to do
in grief.
Right. Right. It's a good point. I mean, you know, the cases
in the תורה Torah where it's being אסור, assur, the few cases
which are all about human death. You know, you got נדב ואביהוא,
Nadav v'Avihu, you've got the people that can't bring the קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, and it's all because of encountering death. I mean, the
other side of that what I sort of would have said is
that the, you know, is that dealing with people that are dead
is also a tremendous מצוה. mitzvah. You know, so you got
נדב ואביהוא Nadav v'Avihu and according to חז"ל, Chazal, the people that
were טמא לנפש tamei lanefesh were the people that had buried נדב
ואביהוא, Nadav v'Avihu, right? So you have and you have the brothers
of נדב ואביהוא, Nadav v'Avihu, so maybe there's that sense that if
there's so much death going around in הציבור hatzibur that most of
הציבור hatzibur is טמא, tamei, it has to do with the fact
that everybody is somehow dealing with, like
you know, also at some level engaged in a profound מצוה. mitzvah.
So, but I don't know. Yeah. Right. אהרון Aharon doesn't want to
do עבודה. avoda.
He's not allowed as an individual. Well, no, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
is allowed. Moses says to him, and he... Right, so the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol is allowed.
But what has happened to me?
Right, right, right. I understand. So a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is
allowed and that creates that problem about playing a public role versus
being allowed your private grief in the way the תורה Torah sort
of says a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not allowed at a
certain level that private grieving. He has to, he has to maintain
his public role. That's very difficult. So, but I think that the
aspect here that's coming to the surface is that טמאי מת, tmei
meis, you know, has this, at the same time it's a severe
טומאה tuma has this sort of sense of profound human engagement with,
you know, with the needs of the dead. And so to some
degree maybe at a ציבור tzibur level we can override the same
way...
Right, and go back to film a little bit. It isn't only
the dead, it's the dying.
That this, if there wasn't an override you would think that people
might hesitate or, or
abandon the dying person.
That's an interesting point. That's an interesting point. Wow. Yeah. Okay. יישר
כוח. Yashar koach. All right. So, so let's get back to the
גמרא Gemara where what the גמרא Gemara says. So קסבר... Kasavar... okay.
טמאי מת ולא טמאי שרץ אף מכפרין טמאי מת ולא טמאי שרץ.
Tmei meis v'lo tmei sheretz af mechapperin tmei meis v'lo tmei sheretz.
So similarly for the כוהנים, Kohanim, their היתר heter is only when
they're טמאי מת, tmei meis, not טמאי שרץ. tmei sheretz. So since
the override is only for טמאי מת, tmei meis, the בדיעבד bedi'avad
allowance is also only for טמאי מת. tmei meis. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי קסבר? Mai kasavar? One minute, what are they exactly
of the opinion
of? אי קסבר אין שוחטין וזורקין על טמאי שרץ אמאי לא עבדי
ציבור בטומאה? Ei kasavar ein shochtin v'zorkin al tmei sheretz amai lo
avdi tzibur betuma? So here's another question. קרבן פסח Korban Pesach as
we have said is the unique קרבן korban that there's a demand
for it to be eaten.
What happens if it can be eaten that night, cause it's eaten
at night, but the person could not in theory eat it and
come into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash the day that it's being
brought? So a person here is טמאי שרץ, tmei sheretz, they went
to the מקוה, mikvah, they're טבול יום tvul yom or they're gonna
go to the מקוה, mikvah, he'll be able... able to eat the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach that night, but right now they're טמא Tamei
and they can't go into the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Can I
as a כהן Kohen bring a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach for somebody
who is right now טמא Tamei but will be able to eat
it
tonight? Any קרבן, Korban, but any קרבן Korban eating it doesn't matter
so much, קרבן פסח Korban Pesach it really matters. And here we're
saying and you will be able to even eat it tonight. So
logically you should, what's the big problem? I bring the פסח Pesach
for him, he'll eat it tonight, what's the problem? And that's the
general position. But there are some that say no, if you are
right now טמא, Tamei, the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach can't be brought
for you even if there's nothing to stop you from eating it
tonight. Okay, so that's the question. So let's see how this is
relevant. אי קסבר, Ei kasavar, if they're of the opinion אין שוחטין
וזורקין על טמא שרץ, Ein shochtin vezorkin al tamei sheretz, you cannot
שחט Shecht and זרוק, Zrok, you cannot bring the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach for somebody who's טמא שרץ Tamei Sheretz even though he can
eat it tonight, so אמאי לא עבדי ציבור בטומאה? Amai lo avdi
tzibbur betumah? What do you mean that if the ציבור Tzibbur is
טמא Tamei by טומאת שרץ, Tumah Sheretz, they can't, it doesn't, there's
no allowance for them to bring a קרבן פסח? Korban Pesach? There's
an allowance. Imagine the whole ציבור Tzibbur is טמא טומאת שרץ, Tamei
Tumah Sheretz, let the כהנים Kohanim go ahead and bring it for
them. The ציבור Tzibbur will be able to eat it that night.
So it's not like טומאה Tumah is הותרה, Hutrah, but there's not
even an obstacle for them to have a קרבן Korban brought when
they're טמא שרץ. Tamei Sheretz. הכל שביחיד נדחה, בציבור עבדי בטומאה. Hakol
shebeyachid nidcheh, betzibbur avdi betumah. And so, one minute,
אמאי לא עבדי ציבור בטומאה, Amai lo avdi tzibbur betumah, הכל שביחיד
נדחה ציבור עבדי בטומאה. Hakol shebeyachid nidcheh, tzibbur avdi betumah. One minute.
No, I'm sorry, I misread that. Okay, whoops, I'm sorry. Rewind. Okay,
I skipped the אין. Ein. מה קסבר, Ma kasavar, let's do that
again.
מה קסבר, Ma kasavar, I'm sorry, אי קסבר, Ei kasavar, let's do
that again. מה קסבר, Ma kasavar, I'm sorry. אי קסבר אין שוחטין
וזורקין על טמא שרץ. Ei kasavar ein shochtin vezorkin al tamei sheretz.
Somebody should have stopped me there. Okay, if I read, I misread
the אין. Ein. If you say that you cannot bring a קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach for somebody who's טמא שרץ, Tamei Sheretz, so the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach cannot be brought, so אמאי לא עבדי ציבור
בטומאה? Amai lo avdi tzibbur betumah? Why can't the ציבור Tzibbur bring
the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach if the, if it's, why isn't it
הותרה? Hutrah? הכל שביחיד נדחה. Hakol shebeyachid nidcheh. Since the individual who's
טמא שרץ Tamei Sheretz would be forced to wait until פסח שני,
Pesach Sheni, ציבור עבדי בטומאה. Tzibbur avdi betumah. When the ציבור Tzibbur
has the situation, they are allowed to do it בטומאה, Betumah, meaning
if as an individual I can't bring it, when you're going to
have to tell the whole majority of the ציבור Tzibbur wait till
next month, so rather than have the whole ציבור Tzibbur wait till
next month, you would never push off an entire ציבור, Tzibbur, you
would do it now. So why shouldn't טומאת שרץ Tumah Sheretz override
for a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach if as individuals you can't bring?
So,
אלא קסבר שוחטין וזורקין על טמא שרץ. Ella kasavar shochtin vezorkin al
tamei sheretz. So they must say you can bring it for somebody
who is טמא שרץ. Tamei Sheretz. So here actually the גמרא Gemara
steps back from what we've been saying a minute ago, which is
just a formal rule only טמא מת. Tamei Meis. And the גמרא
Gemara is actually saying no, actually if the logic would dictate that
this is a real obstacle for bringing the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
then when it happens at a ציבור Tzibbur level you're allowed to
bring it. So if טומאת שרץ, Tumah Sheretz, a contact טומאה Tumah
really would not allow the ציבור Tzibbur to bring the קרבן, Korban,
they could not bring it, have the כהנים Kohanim bring it for
them and they would eat it that night, if that was not
an option, then you would not make a ציבור Tzibbur wait until
פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. It would override. So the only argument that
the ציבור, Tzibbur, the טומאה Tumah does not override for a ציבור
Tzibbur is because it's not really an obstacle because the כהנים Kohanim
can bring it for you now even though you're טמא. Tamei. So
here is what we are...
the זקני דרום Ziknei Darom then...
Well, I'm going to... So here's what the זקני דרום Ziknei Darom
are saying. They're saying look, this idea of טומאה הותרה בציבור Tumah
hutrah betzibbur applies by a טמא מת. Tamei Meis. If the ציבור
Tzibbur is טמא מת, Tamei Meis, they can't bring... it would be
overridden. So of course if the כהנים Kohanim are טמא מת, Tamei
Meis, they're also allowed to bring it בטומאה. Betumah. Okay, but what's
the story by טומאת שרץ? Tumah Sheretz? If the ציבור Tzibbur is
טמא שרץ, Tamei Sheretz, so nothing prevents the קרבנות Korbanos from being
brought. Let the כהנים Kohanim go ahead and bring it now. The
ציבור Tzibbur will be not in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but
they'll eat it that night. So since nothing prevents the קרבנות Korbanos
from being brought right now, so טומאת שרץ Tumah Sheretz was never
allowed for the ציבור, Tzibbur, was never overridden because it was never
a problem. So it never needed to be overridden. So therefore it's
never overridden for כהנים. Kohanim. So if all the כהנים Kohanim are
טמא שרץ, Tamei Sheretz, even though for the כהנים Kohanim it is
a problem, because if the כהנים Kohanim are טמא שרץ Tamei Sheretz
they can't go into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they can't do
the עבודה, Avodah, nevertheless since it was never had the principle of
being overridden for the ציבור, Tzibbur, it's never overridden for the כהנים.
Kohanim. So
therefore that's the הלכה Halacha that טומאה הותרה בציבור, Tumah hutrah betzibbur,
whether for the ציבור Tzibbur or the כהנים Kohanim by מת. Meis.
It's not הותרה Hutrah by שרץ Sheretz because it's not needed for
the ציבור. Tzibbur. So therefore to be הותרה. Hutrah. So therefore it's
not overridden for the כהנים. Kohanim. And therefore if it was not
a ציבור Tzibbur case but a private קרבן Korban and a כהן
Kohen brought it, בדיעבד Bidi'avad it's okay because sometimes that's allowed by
טמא מת. Tamei Meis. But by a שרץ, Sheretz, בדיעבד Bidi'avad it's
no good because we never tolerate a כהן Kohen with טומאת שרץ.
Tumah Sheretz. Okay, so that's the position of זקני דרום. Ziknei Darom.
That more or less clear?
Yes? Is that true if all of the כהנים Kohanim are...
Yes, so even if all the כהנים Kohanim are טמא שרץ, Tamei
Sheretz, meaning this is sort of, you know, this is the linking
of it to the ציבור. Tzibbur. By the ציבור Tzibbur you didn't
need the היתר, Heter, but once you don't have the היתר Heter
by the ציבור, Tzibbur, you don't have... you can't avail yourself of
it at the כהנים. Kohanim. So if all the כהנים Kohanim are
טמא שרץ... Tamei Sheretz... You're not going to bring the קרבן. Korban.
Okay? Because we never have the היתר heter by the ציבור. tzibur.
So once we know this, that the היתר heter only flies to
טמאי מת tmei meit and not to טמאי שרץ, tmei sheretz, because
that's true by ציבור tzibur so it's true by כהנים. Kohanim. So
what is the case בדיעבד? bedi'avad? If a כהן Kohen brings it
בדיעבד bedi'avad and a private קרבן, Korban, not a ציבור tzibur קרבן,
Korban, by טמאי מת tmei meit we tolerate that more than we
do by טמאי שרץ. tmei sheretz.
But wait, if we say, if all ציבור tzibur is טמא, tamei,
we bring the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. If טמאי מת, tmei meit,
we bring the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. Right. If all the ציבור
tzibur is טמאי שרץ. tmei sheretz.
We bring the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach.
Okay, so then say the same thing then.
No, but the גמרא Gemara is saying is you never have the
principle of override by טומאה. tumah.
You're saying it's not... you're saying it's really a problem that's overwritten,
whereas there's really no problem.
שרץ Sheretz was no problem. You don't come to the בית המקדש,
Beis HaMikdash, I'll bring your קרבן Korban for you.
It's not that it's overwritten, it's just no problem by שרץ.
sheretz. Right. Right. So טמאי מת tmei meit by the ציבור tzibur
is overwritten. טמאי שרץ tmei sheretz wasn't a problem. So since טמאי
שרץ tmei sheretz was never overwritten by the ציבור, tzibur, we never
have a principle to override it by כהנים. Kohanim. Okay? So that's
what we're saying in the end. So David, going back to your
question, it's not, you know, the way the גמרא Gemara is dealing
with it, it's not somehow there's something distinctive about מת, meit, but
what since it wasn't a problem by the ציבור tzibur we never
developed a principle, you know, or articulated a principle of being overwritten.
All right? So that's... so that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying
now, and that's why if it's not even when the principle wasn't
true, but since we tolerate טומאת מת tumat meit a little bit
more under some circumstances, when a כהן Kohen brings it even as
a private קרבן, Korban, the קרבן Korban is still good. So let's
take a look as the גמרא Gemara continues.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so תקלהו ריש לקיש לדרומאי. Taklehu Reish Lakish le-Droma'ei. So ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish like challenged, literally like, you know,
pounded or something for the חכמי דרום. chachmei Darom. Yeah, right, he
lies on the floor, he pounds, right, exactly. He takes off his
shoe and he bangs it. Right, like Khrushchev. What? Yeah. Passionate. Yeah,
exactly. So he said like this: וכי איזה כוח מרובה, כוח מכפרים
או כוח מתכפרים Vechi eizeh koach merubah? Koach mechapprim o koach mitchapprim?
Who has more power to override טומאה? tumah? Those who do the
atoning or those that are atoned for? הוי אומר כוח מתכפרים. Hevei
omer koach mitchapprim.
So those that are atoned for, meaning, you know, for the... for
the Jews that are atoned for, he's going to say that since
you are allowed to bring, meaning it's going to be the same
problem. טומאת שרץ Tumat sheretz is less of an issue. You can
bring it when the people are טמאי שרץ tmei sheretz because it's
בכלל be-chlal not a problem. So he's not going to accept this
difference. ומה במקום שנטמאו בעלים בשרץ, U-mah bi-mkom she-nitme'u be'alim be-sheretz, when
the owners are טמאי שרץ, tmei sheretz, משלחים קרבנותיהם, meshallchim korbanoteihem, their...
you don't need it to even be overwritten, their קרבן Korban can
be brought for them even they're טמאי שרץ. tmei sheretz. כהן שנטמא
בשרץ אינו מרצה, Kohen she-nitma be-sheretz eino mirtzeh, but if a כהן
Kohen is טמאי שרץ tamei sheretz he can't come into the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So when a ישראל Yisrael is טמאי שרץ tmei
sheretz it's less of an issue, right? It has more... you know,
so therefore,
מקום שנטמאו בעלים במת, makom she-nitme'u be'alim be-meit, שאין משלחים קרבנותיהם. she-ein
meshallchim korbanoteihem. So when the owner as an individual, as a private
person, is טמא מת tamei meit and his קרבן Korban can't be
brought for him, כהן שנטמא במת אינו דין שאינו מרצה? Kohen she-nitma
be-meit eino din she-eino mirtzeh? So he is basically saying, okay, I
want to go the other way, right. I'm not going to argue
that it should both be good בדיעבד, bedi'avad, because actually that would
go against our משנה mishnah that says a טמא tamei is not
good בדיעבד. bedi'avad. But at the end of the day, remember זקני
דרום, Ziknei Darom, their חידוש chiddush was to say בדיעבד bedi'avad that
post facto it works for a כהן Kohen who's טמא מת. tamei
meit. Their חידוש chiddush was to be lenient. Since sometimes we tolerate
טומאת מת, tumat meit, even when a כהן Kohen is a טמא
מת tamei meit and is an individual קרבן, Korban, it'll be good
בדיעבד. bedi'avad. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said, one minute. You know,
by ישראל Yisrael we're more tolerant for his טומאה tumah than a
כהן's Kohen טומאה. tumah. If a ישראל Yisrael is טמא tamei and
he can't come to the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a כהן Kohen
can still bring his קרבן. Korban. So we more tolerate טומאה tumah
of a ישראל Yisrael than of a כהן. Kohen.
טומאת שרץ Tumat sheretz or טומאת מת?
tumat meit? טומאת שרץ.
Tumat
sheretz.
We'll start with שרץ. sheretz. That's our first example. So we more
tolerate that at the ישראל Yisrael level than at the כהן Kohen
level, right? If a כהן Kohen is טמאי שרץ, tamei sheretz, he
can't come into the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. ישראל's Yisrael טמאי שרץ,
tmei sheretz, we'll bring his קרבן Korban for him.
But you have an alternative.
If a ישראל Yisrael is... if the ישראל Yisrael is טומאת שרץ
tumat sheretz and he's sending his קרבן, Korban, any כהן Kohen can
do it.
Right. But even if you have no... even if you have all
כהנים Kohanim that are טמאי שרץ, tmei sheretz, he just got... first
of all, it's this is a קרבן יחיד Korban yachid and not
a
קרבן ציבור, Korban tzibur, and זקני דרום Ziknei Darom are of the
opinion that you don't say הותר בציבור hutar be-tzibur by טומאת שרץ
tumat sheretz anyway. So even if you don't have an alternative, right,
by... טומאת שרץ tumat sheretz we never allow by כהנים. Kohanim.
I understand. But one... one can presume
it's the exceptional circumstance where where the entire... right... group of כהנים
Kohanim are going to be... טמאי שרץ. tmei sheretz. Right. So the
כהן Kohen is just an agent. Right. Right. So take a different
agent. This... this one's not available for this.
Right.
So again, so your question is...
so one minute. The גמרא's Gemara saying that when a ישראל Yisrael
is טמאי שרץ, tmei sheretz, it's... we don't tolerate... you
know...
But that's true also if the כהן kohen is a טמא מת.
tameh met. Meaning, what we're trying to—that's fine, because all we're trying
to do is challenge זקני דרום's Ziknei Darom assertion that when a
כהן kohen is a טמא מת, tameh met, the קרבן korban is
בדיעבד bedieved okay. And they say, here's the scenario: You have a
כהן, kohen, a ישראל Yisrael who is a טמא שרץ tameh sheretz
sending his קרבן, korban, fine. If he's, if the כהן kohen is
a טמא שרץ tameh sheretz bringing the קרבן, korban, no good. So
if a ישראל Yisrael is a טמא מת tameh met and he
can't even send his קרבן, korban, so certainly if the כהן kohen
is a טמא מת, tameh met, he shouldn't be בדיעבד—the bedieved קרבן
korban should be no good. Okay, so that's all he's saying. So
it's the same—you're right. The logic might be exactly that: Get a
different כהן kohen to do it. It's not a קרבן ציבור, korban
tzibbur, there are other כהנים, kohanim, get a different כהן kohen to
do it. But that's basically what he's saying. It's all very nice
that you figured this out, that we sometimes tolerate טומאת מת tumat
met more, but at the end of the day, we don't tolerate
טומאה tumah of שרץ sheretz by a כהן, kohen, so we shouldn't
tolerate טומאת מת tumat met at the יחיד yachid level. You want
to learn out from the ציבור tzibbur level, I want to learn
out from the individual level. At the individual level, we tolerate טומאה
tumah more by ישראל Yisrael than by a כהן. kohen. We don't
tolerate it by מת met by ישראל, Yisrael, we shouldn't tolerate it
by מת met by a כהן. kohen. That's what he's saying. Yeah.
I find this extremely appealing. It is?
Good. I was not expecting that adjective.
And
the reason I find this appealing—yes—is because it's really all about ישראל.
Yisrael. It's about the people. And the people should never ever suspect
for one moment that כהן kohen are—is השם. Hashem. That they have
the power of השם. Hashem. That they are השם. Hashem. Interesting. It
is the כהן kohen reduced to humanity because of these laws, and
so it empowers the people to believe in this power beyond all
is ultimately השם. Hashem. And that's the reason, I believe, it breaks
my heart every year that אהרן Aharon continues to stand for the
community when his two sons have just been destroyed. So I find
it extraordinarily appealing.
Great. Thank you. Okay.
Wait, I have a side question. Who are זקני דרום? Ziknei Darom?
That is a good question. I don't know. I'll have to—I was
waiting for somebody to ask that. Is in, right? You imagine they've
got to be somewhere in ישראל, Yisrael, and ריש לקיש Resh Lakish
is in ישראל, Yisrael, right? And you would not refer—דרום Darom seems
to be referring to an ישראל Yisrael geography, not a בבל Bavel
geography. Yes. So, but I don't know, I have to find out
if there's any discussion about this. Okay. What? All right, so let's
go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: Okay.
So that's what ריש לקיש Resh Lakish said. דאמר ריש לקיש משום
זקני דרום כהן טמא מת אינו נושא את כפיו.
De'amar Resh Lakish mishum Ziknei Darom
kohen tameh
met eino noseh et kapav. קסברי זקני דרום, Kasavri Ziknei Darom,
so how do זקני דרום Ziknei Darom respond to that? You know,
they could have just said, well, who cares? I mean, we're still
going by this principle of ציבור. tzibbur. But no, let's see what
their response is. טמא מת נמי משלח קרבנותיו. Tameh met nami meshaleach
korbanotav. They say, you know what? You don't have that—you know, you
said, 'Oh, טומאת שרץ tumat sheretz we tolerate more, you know, and
we allow by—when the individual is טמא שרץ. tameh sheretz. We don't
tolerate it by טומאת מת, tumat met, so we shouldn't tolerate it
by the כהן.' kohen. So they say, 'Guess what? We actually think
that we do tolerate טומאת מת tumat met by the individual who
sends his קרבן. korban. You can send your קרבן, korban, even your
קרבן פסח, korban pesach, when you're טמא מת, tameh met, and have
the כהן kohen bring it for you, even though you can't eat
it that night.' Okay, now that's wild. So then how does פסח
שני
Pesach Sheni happen?
Right, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
So, והכתיב, Ve'haktiv, what?
That's what the גמרא Gemara asks.
והכתיב איש איש כי יהיה טמא וגו' ועשה פסח בחדש השני. Ve'haktiv
ish ish ki yiheyeh tameh etc. ve'asah pesach bachodesh hasheni. So the
גמרא Gemara says, למצוה. L'mitzvah.
Okay, so ideally, if you're טמא מת, tameh met, you should wait
until פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. But actually, if you had a כהן
kohen bring it for you, even though you couldn't eat it, you
were יוצא yotzeh your obligation of קרבן פסח. korban pesach. Ideally do
it at a time when you can eat it, פסח שני, Pesach
Sheni, but you really—of course, what why were the people complaining?
אשר יהיו טמאים לנפש אדם וגו' ולא יכלו לעשות הפסח ביום ההוא?
Asher hayu temeim lenefesh adam etc. velo yachlu la'asot hapesach bayom hahu?
They could have just asked זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, they would have
told them okay. Maybe they felt, but they couldn't eat from the
קרבן פסח, korban pesach, so better to wait. So that's the problem.
So okay, better to wait. והכתיב, Ve'haktiv, doesn't it say איש לפי
אכלו, ish lefi ochlo, that you have to שחט shacht it according
to the eaters, and you're not going to be an eater if
you have טומאת מת? tumat met? למצוה. L'mitzvah. That's ideally, but בדיעבד
bedieved even if you can't eat it tonight. ולעכובי לא, U'le'ikuvi lo,
that it does not prevent you fulfilling your obligation. והתניא, Ve'hatanya, במכסות
נפשות, bemichsat nefashot, according to the number of people that are counted
on the קרבן פסח—well, korban pesach we're not saying eaters yet, hold
on—במכסות נפשות, bemichsat nefashot, מלמד שאין הפסח נשחט אלא למנויו, melamed she'ein
hapesach nishchat ela limnu'av, it's only can be שחט-ed shacht for those
that have been counted as part of the group.
שחטו—what Shachto if they're only counted through Facebook? Okay, anyway—שחטו שלא למנויו,
shachto shelo limnu'av, if you שחט-ed shacht it for people that were
not appointed, were not part of
it, יכול יהא כעובר. yachol yehei k'over. maybe, okay, you transgress the
obligation, but nevertheless the פסח Pesach is still kosher. תלמוד לומר תכוסו.
Talmud lomar tachossu. It says again you shall slaughter it. הכתוב שנו
לאו לעכב. Hakasu v'shino lav l'akeiv. It repeated it to say that
if you don't slaughter it for the people counted, it's no good.
And now that means that you have to be part of the
appointed group. But we also say that it is איש לפי אכלו,
ish lefi achlo, איש לפי אכלו תכוסו על השה. ish lefi achlo
tachossu al haseh. That's not only the people מכסת נפשות michsas nefashot
who were counted, but the people who could be eaters of the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So the גמרא Gemara says והקיש אוכלים למנויים,
v'hikish ochlim limnuim, presumably the requirement for you to be an eater
is similar to the requirement for you to be counted on the
קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. And if you cannot be a person that
can eat from it that night, then בדיעבד b'dieved it's no good.
So how does זקני דרום Ziknei Darom deal with this? So זקני
דרום Ziknei Darom לא מקשי, lo makshi, they don't connect eaters to
those that were counted. You're counted on the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
you're not going to eat from it tonight, ideally you should not
be doing this, you should be part of a פסח Pesach that
you'll be able to eat from, wait for פסח שני, Pesach Sheni,
but בדיעבד b'dieved it's good. So to get out of this problem
of ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, which you would have thought they would
have another way, they just would
have said okay, כח מכפרין koach m'kaprin is better.
Yeah, who knows? Anyway, but since ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says bottom
line I can't accept that we tolerate, you know, if we don't
tolerate a כהן kohen who's טמא שרץ, t'mei sheretz, how do we
tolerate a כהן kohen who's טמא מת? t'mei meis? Since by the
owners we tolerate שרץ sheretz more than מת. meis. So in order
to get out of it they said oh, even by the owners
if they're טמא מת t'mei meis you can bring your קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, בדיעבד b'dieved it's okay. Okay, so now we've introduced... you're
counted part of the group you can't eat it and then we
introduce this radical concept now that people can be part of the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach and יוצא yotzei even though they can't eat
it according to the
no according to זקני דרום.
Ziknei Darom.
What? They just keep making it up as they go.
Right. Oh well, we'll change this. Right. Okay, exactly. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this: וכי לא מקשי נמי מהני נמי אית
להו פירכא. v'chi lo makshi nami mehani nami ishu pircha. So okay,
even if they don't connect the eaters to those that are counted,
and they get out of it that way, here's another question on
זקני דרום. Ziknei Darom. ומה במקום שנטמאו בעלים בשרץ שמשלחים קרבנותיהם לכתחילה,
Uma bemakom she'nitmu ba'alim b'sheretz shemeshalechin korbanosaihem l'chatchila, so at least you
can make a לכתחילה l'chatchila difference, at least they admit that טמא
מת t'mei meis לכתחילה l'chatchila cannot have a קרבן korban brought for
him. So we can still prove that טמא מת t'mei meis is
worse than טמא שרץ. t'mei sheretz. When the כהנים kohanim are טומאת
שרץ, tumas sheretz, לכתחילה l'chatchila you can bring their קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach for them. Okay, מקום שנטמאו בעלים ב... makom she'nitmu ba'alim b...
לכתחילה l'chatchila כהן שנטמא בשרץ kohen she'nitma b'sheretz אינו מרצה, eino meratzeh,
the כהן kohen is still not good when he's טמא שרץ, t'mei
sheretz, מקום שנטמאו בעלים במת makom she'nitmu ba'alim b'meis when the owners
are טמא מת t'mei meis and at least זקני דרום Ziknei Darom
have to admit שאין משלחים קרבנותיהם לכתחילה she'ein meshalechin korbanosaihem l'chatchila that
at least לכתחילה l'chatchila they can't send their קרבנות, korbanos, they wait
until פסח שני. Pesach Sheni. כהן שנטמא במת אינו דין שאינו מרצה,
Kohen she'nitma b'meis eino din she'eino meratzeh, certainly the כהן kohen who's
טמא מת t'mei meis should be no good. So in the end,
and we don't answer that question. So in the end what we
say is זקני דרום Ziknei Darom say because we make an exception
by טומאת מת tumas meis for a כהן kohen by טומאת ציבור,
tumas tzibur, we'll make an exception for him for טומאת יחיד. tumas
yachid. And we'll say that as an individual, when not definitely as
an individual, even a private קרבן korban a כהן kohen brings it
as a טמא מת t'mei meis בדיעבד b'dieved it'll be okay. But
we only find this override by טומאת שרץ. tumas sheretz. And ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish says why should I compare it to what in
theory would happen if it was a קרבן ציבור? korban tzibur? Let
me better compare it to what the status is as a כהן
kohen who's bringing a private קרבן. korban. And as a כהן kohen
who's bringing a private קרבן korban and as the person who's sending
a private קרבן, korban, we know טומאת מת tumas meis is worse.
We know at a person's level טומאת מת tumas meis prevents him
from sending a קרבן korban or at least לכתחילה l'chatchila means he
can't send the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach because he can't eat it
that night or at least לכתחילה. l'chatchila. So if that's true that
it's worse at the person sending it, it should be worse for
the כהן. kohen. And the כהן kohen bringing it as a טמא
מת t'mei meis should not it should not be good בדיעבד. b'dieved.
Okay so that's the debate now between ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and
זקני דרום Ziknei Darom when the כהן kohen is טמא מת t'mei
meis is it בדיעבד b'dieved okay. So let's now continue in the
גמרא. Gemara.
מיתיבי, Meisvei, the גמרא Gemara says I'll ask you on this:
מפני שאמרו נזיר ועושה פסח הציץ מרצה על טומאת דם ואין הציץ
מרצה על טומאת הגוף. mipnei she'omru nazir v'oseh pesach hatzitz m'ratzeh al
tumas dam v'ein hatzitz m'ratzeh al tumas haguf. So as if that
weren't difficult enough talking about טומאה הותרה בציבור, tumah hutra b'tzibur, we're
now going to have to talk about a principle of the ריצוי
ritzuy of the ציץ. tzitz. The Torah says that you know the
כהן kohen wears the ציץ tzitz ונשא כהן את עון הקדשים אשר
יקדישו בני ישראל לה'. v'nasa kohen et avon hakodashim asher yakdishu b'nei
Yisrael l'Hashem. So the כהן kohen will carry, will forgive for the
sin of the sacrifices. And we learn that it means that the
wearing of the ציץ tzitz somehow makes better the fact that certain
things were done בטומאה. b'tumah. The גמרא Gemara will have a דרשה
drasha pretty soon that how we know it's specifically talking about טומאה
tumah what? The ציץ tzitz headband. The ציץ, tzitz, yeah, I'm sorry,
it's that gold headband on the forehead that says קודש לה' Kodesh
L'Hashem on it. Okay that he wears, right? We talked before the
תפילין tefillin can fit right between the end of the hat and
the beginning of the ציץ. tzitz. Anyway, so that headband. So the
גמרא, Gemara, what?
How do you want to translate מרצה? m'ratzeh?
Literally atones for, but you know sort of forgive. It's the sin
of, so the key word by all the components is רצוי, ritzuy,
it makes the קרבן korban acceptable. So like רצה. retzei. But okay
so, okay so we say that that's talking about טומאה. tumah. Now
the question is what type of טומאה tumah does it atone for?
The general principle is it's something called טומת התהום. tumat hatehom. טומת
התהום Tumat hatehom literally
means the טומאה tumah of the depths, which really means a question
that there's some doubt of the טומאה, tumah, some ספק safek טומאה.
tumah. Somebody did not know if they were טמא tamei exactly, if
they walked over a grave, whatever the case might be, it's not
clear if they were טמא, tamei, they brought their קרבן, korban, בדיעבד
bdiavad the ציץ tzitz makes it okay. So now we're going to
say what exactly but then but there's all these questions about exactly
how the ציץ tzitz works and for which קרבנות. korbanot. So let's
take a look at this ברייתא. braita. מפני שאמרו נזיר ועושה פסח.
mipnei she'amru nazir v'oseh pesach. Now a נזיר nazir and the person
bringing a קרבן פסח korban Pesach are two people that have to
be able to be טהור tahor why? ועושה פסח v'oseh Pesach we
said because he has to be able to eat from the קרבן
פסח. korban Pesach. זקני דרום Ziknei Darom aside.
The נזיר, nazir, why does he have to be טהור? tahor? Because
a
נזיר nazir who's טמא tamei brings his קרבן korban because he became
טמא, tamei, so therefore it's not like oh as טמא tamei you
can't eat from the קרבן, korban, that's not. The whole purpose of
bringing the קרבן korban is to end the טומאה tumah to start
the טהרה tahara again. So until you're טהור tahor you can't bring
it. Okay, so when will the ציץ tzitz work for it? So
it says for a for עושה פסח oseh Pesach and the נזיר,
nazir, הציץ מרצה על טומאת דם, hatzitz mirtzeh al tumat dam, if
the issue is that the דם dam had become טמא tamei and
the קרבן korban was brought, the ציץ tzitz will make it okay.
But ואין הציץ מרצה, v'ein hatzitz mirtzeh, it does not atone for,
it does not make acceptable, על טומאת הגוף, al tumat haguf, when
the when the person became טמא tamei for the reason I said
that they they need to be טהור tahor and the ציץ tzitz
won't work for them if they're not טהור. tahor. So let's see
what the גמרא Gemara does with this.
וקתני—did v'katani I skip a line?
I skipped two lines. Okay,
במה? b'meh? אילימא בטומאה כששרץ, eilima b'tumah k'sheretz, how is this person
טמא tamei or the דם dam טמא? tamei? If it's through contact
with a שרץ, sheretz, הא מר סבירא ליה שוחטים וזורקים על טמאי
שרץ. ha mar savira leh shochtin v'zorkin al t'mayei sheretz. So why
do I even need the ציץ? tzitz? Right? Let the נזיר nazir
or let the guy bringing the קרבן פסח korban Pesach be טמא.
tamei. זקני דרום Ziknei Darom said that, you know, you can bring
a קרבן korban for that type of a person. So why do
I even need the ציץ tzitz in that case? אלא טומאת מת,
ela tumat meit, it must be they're טמאי מת t'mayei meit and
there is a real problem and therefore I would have thought you
needed the ציץ tzitz and therefore I would have needed the ציץ.
tzitz. וקתני אין הציץ מרצה v'katani ein hatzitz mirtzeh and it tells
you the ציץ tzitz doesn't help. אלמא alma we see from this,
נטמאו בעלים במת אין משלחים קרבנותיהן. nitm'u b'alim b'meit ein m'shalchin korbanoteihen.
So this proves against זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, not their direct point
of what happens if the כהן kohen brings it when he's טמא,
tamei, but about the background to their position. What's the background to
their position is they said that if a person is טמא מת
t'mei meit a קרבן פסח korban Pesach can be brought for
him בדיעבד. bdiavad. בדיעבד. Bdiavad. But here you see that בדיעבד bdiavad
it didn't work and even the ציץ tzitz doesn't help and if
the person was טמא, tamei, right, the קרבן פסח korban Pesach is
no good. So this is a proof against that one of the
assumptions of זקני דרום. Ziknei Darom.
We're knocking them down here.
Yes, we are
definitely beating them when they're down.
Well okay, we you know we're trying to make our we're trying
to absolutely prove the position. אלמא alma you see that נטמאו בעלים
במת אין משלחים קרבנותיהן nitm'u b'alim b'meit ein m'shalchin korbanoteihen because that's
exactly the point here, that when the owners are טמא tamei the
ציץ tzitz does not work. So the גמרא Gemara says לא, lo,
that's not how to read it. אי דנטמאו בעלים במת הכי נמי,
ei d'nitm'u b'alim b'meit hachi nami, if the owners were טמא מת
t'mei meit you'd be right, the ציץ tzitz would work or you
wouldn't need the ציץ, tzitz, you could bring a קרבן פסח korban
Pesach for somebody who's טמא מת. t'mei meit.
Wait is this for the owner of the קרבן korban or for
the כהן? kohen?
No, the כהן גדול kohen gadol wears the ציץ tzitz and because
he's wearing the ציץ tzitz it allows קרבנות korbanot that are brought
בטומאה b'tumah to count.
טומאה Tumah of the?
Well that's the whole question. Whose טומאה? tumah? What טומאה? tumah? So
that's like whole major discussions in ש"ס Shas what exactly are the
parameters. So what we're saying here is the טומאה tumah when the
קרבן korban becomes טמא tamei not when the owners are טמא. tamei.
Okay so that was exactly that statement, טומאת דם ולא טומאת בעלים.
tumat dam v'lo tumat b'alim. Now what about the טומאה tumah of
the כהנים? kohanim? That's not being discussed here. I mean so you
know that's a whole major discussions, I know. So it's a whole
separate issue, right, when is טומאה הותרה בציבור, tumah hutra b'tzibbur, what
does the ציץ tzitz do, how does the ציץ tzitz interact with
the principle of טומאה הותרה בציבור? tumah hutra b'tzibbur?
I feel like we're coming in at halftime.
Yeah we keep popping up.
All of ש"ס Shas is coming in at halftime. Okay so so
alright so yes but all we're focusing on now is that it
doesn't work for the owners. So it doesn't work for the owners
means that it was a problem for the owners. Means if the
owners were טמאי מת t'mayei meit their קרבן פסח korban Pesach was
no good. So how did זקני דרום? Ziknei Darom?
Thank you. Okay so the
גמרא Gemara says alright אימא סיפא—did eima seifa I skip a line?
לא אי דנטמאו בעלים במת הכי נמי, lo ei d'nitm'u b'alim b'meit
hachi nami, if the owners
were— So it was exactly what David said. So here we're talking
that the כהן Kohen was טמא שרץ, tameh sheretz, not the owners.
Okay. So therefore it's saying that the ציץ Tzitz works if the
קרבן Korban becomes טמא, tameh, it doesn't work if the כהן Kohen
is טמא. tameh. David, exactly what you asked. It says, you see,
it says if the כהן Kohen is טמא, tameh, the ציץ Tzitz
works if the קרבן Korban is טמא. tameh. If the owners are
טמא, tameh, we don't need the ציץ, Tzitz, right? You can bring
the קרבן Korban when the owners are טמא tameh even a קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. And when the כהן Kohen is טמא, tameh, the
ציץ Tzitz does not work for that when the כהן Kohen is
טמא. tameh. Okay, now it can't be when the כהן Kohen is
טמא מת tameh meis because זקני דרום Ziknei Darom said that then
it works בדיעבד. bedieved. So it means when a כהן Kohen is
טמא שרץ, tameh sheretz, which they said doesn't work בדיעבד, bedieved, there
the ציץ Tzitz doesn't help you either. Okay, so it says, let's
just read that.
הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שנטמא כהן בשרץ. Hacha b'mai askinan k'gon shenitma
Kohen b'sheretz. So when the owners are טמא, tameh, it doesn't matter.
When the קרבן Korban is טמא, tameh, the ציץ Tzitz works. When
the כהן Kohen is טמא tameh with a שרץ, sheretz, that's where
the ציץ Tzitz does not work. אי הכי אימה סיפא, Ei hachi
eima seifa, let's look at the end of that ברייתא. braisa.
נטמא טומאת התהום, Nitma tumas hatehom, when it is a טומאת התהום,
tumas hatehom, which means a questionable טומאה, tumah, there's exactly questions about
what are the parameters of טומאת התהום. tumas hatehom. The קרבן Korban
or the person? Well, that's the question. הציץ מרצה, Hatzitz mertzeh, and
it does work. So that seems to say
that it so and והתני רבי
חייא, v'hatni Rebbe Chiya, one minute,
לא אמרו טומאת התהום אלא למת בלבד. lo amru tumas hatehom ela
l'meis bilvad. And this principle of טומאת התהום tumas hatehom only applies
to a dead to טומאת מת, tumas meis, not to other טומאה.
tumah. So טומאת התהום tumas hatehom is again means like a questionable
טומאה. tumah. It's learned from a.
It's the way they explain it here.
It's you're walking over ground and there's maybe something buried underneath. But
from that we analogize it to be other cases of ספק. safek.
So for example the גמרא Gemara says there could be a טומאת
התהום tumas hatehom of a זב. zav. What's a טומאת התהום tumas
hatehom of a זב? zav? What type of thing did he walk
over? So a טומאת התהום tumas hatehom of a זב zav is
that he had a flow all through בין השמשות bein hashmashos and
he doesn't know if it was on one day a one day
flow or a two day flow because when did the day actually
start? So it gets it gets abstracted to the idea of a
ספק, safek, but the actual paradigm of טומאת התהום tumas hatehom is
walking over a walking on a, you know, valley and there may
be somebody buried deep underground and you don't know. Okay, so we
say that the ציץ Tzitz works when the קרבן Korban becomes טמא,
tameh, not when the individual. And now we're saying the individual means
the כהן Kohen is טמא. tameh. But it does work even in
a case when the individual, i.e., the כהן Kohen is טמא tameh
if it was this טומאת התהום. tumas hatehom. So and we're going
to say what's a טומאת התהום, tumas hatehom, presumably that's only about
a dead body. So you see that if a כהן, Kohen, if
you want to say we're talking about a כהן, Kohen, when a
כהן Kohen is טמא מת, tameh meis, it is a problem. Right,
זקני דרום Ziknei Darom said when a כהן Kohen is טמא מת
tameh meis בדיעבד bedieved it's good. But now we're saying when a
כהן Kohen is טמא מת tameh meis it's not good.
It's טומאת שרץ tumas sheretz then.
What? But we said לא אמרו טומאת התהום אלא למת בלבד. lo
amru tumas hatehom ela l'meis bilvad. Okay, so that's the question. So
מאי לאו למעוטי? Mai lav l'ma'utei? So let's read that again. אימא
סיפא נטמא טומאת התהום, Eima seifa nitma tumas hatehom, if the individual
was טמא tameh through טומאת התהום, tumas hatehom, then הציץ מרצה, hatzitz
mertzeh, the ציץ Tzitz does work. And we're saying the individual is
the
כהן. Kohen. So and והתני רבי חייא v'hatni Rebbe Chiya and רבי
חייא Rebbe Chiya taught לא אמרו טומאת התהום אלא למת בלבד, lo
amru tumas hatehom ela l'meis bilvad, that it only applies for a
מת. meis. So that sounds like when a כהן Kohen is a
טמא מת tameh meis it generally is a problem. So the גמרא
Gemara says למת למעוטי מאי? L'meis l'ma'utei mai? What does למת l'meis
excluding? לאו למעוטי טומאת התהום דשרץ? Lav l'ma'utei tumas hatehom d'sheretz? Is
it not excluding the case of שרץ? sheretz? Now again we don't
need literally טומאת התהום tumas hatehom because שרץ sheretz is not מטמא
metameh unless you touch it, not by walking over. Okay, but we
still mean a case of ספק. safek. טומאת התהום Tumas hatehom now
just becomes abstracted to ספק. safek. So לא למעוטי טומאת התהום דזיבה.
Lo l'ma'utei tumas hatehom d'zivah. No, we mean a טומאת התהום tumas
hatehom of a worse case of a זב, zav, like I said
to you, he had a flow, he didn't know whether it was
a one day flow or a two day flow. Okay, so now
what have we said? Okay, since I'm sure we're all, you know,
it's all very easy to bring all this together. Basically bottom line
what we're saying is that זקני דרום Ziknei Darom says if a
כהן Kohen is טמא מת tameh meis בדיעבד bedieved it's okay. Now
we have some discussion about which cases are בדיעבד bedieved okay by
מת meis because that's the whole principle of the ציץ, Tzitz, that
the ציץ Tzitz says בדיעבד bedieved things you shouldn't be doing with
טומאה tumah sometimes can be okay. So when does the ציץ Tzitz
say בדיעבד bedieved they're okay? It says בדיעבד bedieved it's okay if.
Why are you saying the ציץ Tzitz is related to בדיעבד? bedieved?
Why isn't the ציץ Tzitz another force that cleans it up, is
מרצה?
mertzeh? Well, because the תורה Torah does call it עון הקדשים. avon
hakodashim. It says ונשא אהרן את עון הקדשים אשר יקדישו בני ישראל
לה'. v'nasa Aharon es avon hakodashim asher yakdishu bnei Yisrael l'Hashem. So
there's some type of a sin, but somehow by wearing the ציץ
Tzitz it lift, it carries the sin, it forgives for the sin
and it makes things acceptable.
That's how חז"ל Chazal understand. Now you could say it just atones
for their sin but the קרבן Korban was still no good. חז"ל
Chazal do understand that the ציץ Tzitz actually validates the קרבן Korban
בדיעבד bedieved when brought incorrectly.
It's
the בדיעבד. bedieved. נשיאת עון nisiat avon is always in the
Torah.
God is נושא עון ופשע. noseh avon vafesha.
נשיאת עון nisiat avon always means that a sin was done but
it's being overlooked.
We have a concept in philosophy of the end justifying the means.
Yes, but we don't in הלכה, Halacha, except for the few exceptions
of עבירה לשמה. aveira lishmah. Okay, so that's essentially what rabbinic concept
of ציץ tzitz is that it atones, it makes the קרבן korban
acceptable בדיעבד bediavad if something was wrong and that thing we're assuming
is טומאה. tumah. And we're going to explain that and get to
that in a minute. So זקני דרום Ziknei Darom say, actually some
ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. Yeah, it makes the קרבן נרצה. korban nirtzeh. Right. רצוי
Ritzui קרבן. korban.
Exactly, makes it acceptable. So that's essentially the same conversation as זקני
דרום, Ziknei Darom, when בדיעבד bediavad is טומאה tumah okay? So זקני
דרום Ziknei Darom said, oh there's a special הלכה Halacha כהן טמא
מת, Kohen tamei mes, בדיעבד bediavad it's okay because טמאי מת tamei
mes sometimes we overrule. So let's look at what we say by
the ציץ. tzitz. That tells us when בדיעבד bediavad things are okay
and it says the ציץ tzitz says that the קרבן korban if
it became טמא, tamei, בדיעבד bediavad is alright. But at the individual
level only for this טומאת התהום. tumat hatehom. So since the, since
זקני דרום Ziknei Darom said that individual level is talking about a
כהן, Kohen, not the אונס onus because they say the אונס onus
it's always okay if they are טמא. tamei. So it's talking at
the כהן. Kohen. So it says okay, but it's limited to טומאת
התהום. tumat hatehom. They say okay, it's limited to טומאת התהום, tumat
hatehom, that's talking about things like a שרץ. sheretz. Okay. טומאת שרץ,
tumat sheretz, the ציץ tzitz works only for doubtful טומאה. tumah. But
טומאת מת, tumat mes, you don't even need the ציץ. tzitz. טומאת
מת tumat mes since we allow it בציבור, betzibbur, בדיעבד bediavad is
okay. So what do we have now? So listen to, listen to,
listen to what we have in terms of when טומאה tumah is
okay. According to זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, pretty much every time בדיעבד.
bediavad. If the אונס onus are טמא, tamei, even טמאי מת, tamei
mes, fine בדיעבד. bediavad. Okay, even for קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, even
though they can't eat from it. If the קרבן korban is טמא,
tamei, the ציץ tzitz is מרצה meratzeh בדיעבד. bediavad. Now there's a
question, does the כהן Kohen have to be wearing the ציץ tzitz
for it to work? Okay, so maybe it doesn't work all the
time. But anyway, assuming he's there and he's wearing the ציץ, tzitz,
okay, good reason for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to be on
the job
and not take a day off, then the קרבן korban is טמא,
tamei, it's okay בדיעבד. bediavad. How about if the כהן Kohen is
טמא? tamei? Well, if it's טומאת מת, tumat mes, okay בדיעבד bediavad
because טומאת מת tumat mes is okay for ציבור. tzibbur. If it's
טומאת שרץ, tumat sheretz, the ציץ tzitz works for טומאת התהום tumat
hatehom if it's a doubtful טומאה, tumah, not if it's a ודאי
טומאה. vaday tumah, And if the only case where you don't have
ציץ tzitz and you don't have anything else is like if he's
a זב. zav. Wait, wait, wait, if he's טמא שרץ. tamei sheretz.
So if it's a ודאי טומאה, vadai tumah, ציץ tzitz won't work.
But if it's a טומאת התהום, tumat hatehom, ציץ tzitz will work.
טמאי מת, tamei mes, you don't need the ציץ. tzitz. So all
we're left with is like טומאת שרץ ודאי tumat sheretz vaday and
טומאת זב. tumat zav. Those are the cases.
So what about רב חייא? Rav Chia? How do they explain רב
חייא? Rav Chia? רב חייא Rav Chia said it doesn't work, only
when, what was רב חייא's? Rav Chia רב חייא Rav Chia said
לא אמרו טומאת התהום אלא למת בלבד. lo amru tumat hatehom ela
le-mes bilvad.
So אלא למת ela le-mes meaning not, meaning nothing's worse than a
מת, mes, not זב. zav. But it does work for טומאת שרץ.
tumat sheretz. Because that's how זקני דרום. Ziknei Darom.
And טומאת התהום tumat hatehom is sort of some unless proven innocent.
You
walk along, you walk along...
No, we don't say anytime somebody takes a walk on a street
it's טומאת התהום. tumat hatehom. There's a very concrete reason why we
think that there's, we know there's a grave buried in this field,
somewhere we don't know where in the field. There's a specific reason,
what we call a לידת הספק, leidat hasafek, like a concrete reason
why we assume there could be a problem.
So let me ask you, let's say the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
has pneumonia. Right.
And he's not in that day and he's not wearing his ציץ.
tzitz.
Not in for not one day, but a few weeks. Right. Is
there somebody who's the second in
command who wears the ציץ? tzitz? Well, that's a good, that's a
good question. I mean, we do have a concept of a כהן
Kohen standing in, right, which we had in הוריות. Horayos. I thought,
yeah, but that only, that only is discussed for יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. So, I mean, it's an excellent point, you know, why don't
we have an idea of a substitute כהן Kohen because of the
importance of wearing the ציץ. tzitz. But as far as I know,
that's not discussed. But we do have it on a כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol. We do have it on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
Wait, I want to make sure I understand. לא אמרו טומאת התהום
lo amru tumat hatehom that what? רב חייא Rav Chia said לא
אמרו טומאת התהום
אלא למת בלבד.
lo amru
tumat hatehom ela le-mes bilvad. No, לא אמרו טומאת התהום lo amru
tumat hatehom that what? That it's a problem?
No, that the ציץ tzitz works for טומאת התהום tumat hatehom only
for מת, mes, but it doesn't work for טומאת התהום tumat hatehom
of something worse than a מת. mes.
So now does זקני דרום Ziknei Darom say you don't need,
you don't need it by a מת. mes. So of course, right.
That's, right. It's bizarre because according to that you don't even need,
you're right, the גמרא Gemara should ask that. That saying טומאת התהום
tumat hatehom by מת mes is actually not correct because according to
them by מת mes it's not limited to טומאת התהום tumat hatehom
and you don't even need the ציץ. tzitz. Exactly. Good question. Okay.
Can we go back to רב? Rav? Yes. איזהו מרובה. Eizehu m'rubah.
That's,
did we answer that? No! No!
We, that's an unanswered question.
But that's, right.
It's still a logical question which we haven't addressed and now we're
still and we're trying to now, you know, like nail a hammer,
you know, hammer the nail in. Right. We're not, no, we're not
going to defend זקני דרום. Ziknei Darom. They're constantly getting knocked down.
We're attacking them from another place.
Right. Yeah, we're just loading up the problem.
He has
like...
Those are the best questions. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ואלא הא דבעי רמי בר חמא, Ve-ela ha d'ba'ei
Rami bar Chama, רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asks a question:
כהן המרצה בקרבנותיהם, Kohen ha-mirtzeh be-korbenoteihem, when a כהן Kohen is bringing
a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, right, for a נזיר Nazir or an
עושה פסח. oseh Pesach. These are the people for whom if they're
טמא מת, tamei meis, if they're טמא, tamei, then the ציץ tzitz
does not work because the ציץ tzitz only works for
them, right, if they are, I mean they can only, they're only
good if they're טהור, tahor, they can eat from the פסח Pesach
or they can start their זבה, zavah, their, what do you call
it,
their נזירות nezirus again. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: דבעי רמי בר חמא, d'ba'ei Rami bar Chama, כהן המרצה בקרבנותיהם,
Kohen ha-mirtzeh be-korbenoteihem, if the כהן Kohen is doing the קרבנות korbanos
for the guy, for the עושה פסח oseh Pesach or the נזיר,
Nazir, הותרה לו טומאת התהום או לא הותרה לו טומאת התהום? hutra
lo tumas ha-tehom o lo hutra lo tumas ha-tehom? So
he's obviously assuming that the טומאת התהום tumas ha-tehom
works for the guy, not for the כהן, Kohen, but for the
guy bringing the קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, and wants to know: in
the same way the ציץ tzitz works for the guy bringing the
קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, does it work for the כהן Kohen who's
bringing his קרבן פסח? korban Pesach? Okay, meaning as opposed to זקני
דרום, Ziknei Darom, we generally assume when we say the ציץ tzitz
works if the person is טמא, tamei, the person we're referring to
is not the כהן, Kohen, the person we're referring to is the
owner. So if the owner of the קרבן פסח korban Pesach is
טמא tamei or the נזיר Nazir is טמא, tamei, if it's a
ודאי vaday טומאה, tumah. it doesn't work, if it's a טומאת התהום,
tumas ha-tehom, it does work. That's our general assumption, not like זקני
דרום Ziknei Darom who were talking about a כהן. Kohen. And then
רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama says: okay, I get that it
works for the טומאת התהום tumas ha-tehom of the guy bringing the
קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. I want to know if it works also
for the כהן Kohen who's bringing this guy's קרבן פסח. korban Pesach.
If he has a טומאת התהום, tumas ha-tehom, will the ציץ tzitz
work for him? So that proves not like זקני דרום Ziknei Darom
that the basic statement is said about the person bringing the קרבן,
korban, not about the כהן. Kohen. Okay, so you see that's against
זקני דרום. Ziknei Darom. תיפשוט
דטומאת התהום הותרה לו דהכא בכהן קיימינא. Tipshot d'tumas ha-tehom hutra lo
d'hacha be-Kohen kaymina. According to זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, the whole discussion
is about the כהן, Kohen, not about the guy bringing it, and
according to them we're saying that טומאת התהום tumas ha-tehom works for
a כהן. Kohen. So the גמרא Gemara says: all right, דרמי בר
חמא ודאי פליגי. de-Rami bar Chama vadai pligi. You're right. רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama clearly assumes not like זקני דרום. Ziknei Darom.
So again, the simple sense is, just to give you the context
of זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, if the כהנים Kohanim are טמא, tamei,
it's always off the table. ציץ tzitz doesn't work, you know, טומאת
מת tumas meis doesn't work, you know, it's off the table. The
ציץ tzitz is working for when the owners are טמא. tamei. So,
you know, if you want to just keep it clear because, you
know, back and forth is a little complicated, זקני דרום Ziknei Darom
are much more liberal at בדיעבד bedi'avad allowing טומאה. tumah. Okay, they
say if the owners are טמא מת, tamei meis, you can even
בדיעבד bedi'avad participate in a קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. If the כהן
Kohen is טמא, tamei,
בדיעבד bedi'avad it's good. If he's טמא טומאת התהום tamei tumas ha-tehom
of a שרץ, sharetz, the ציץ tzitz works. The other approach is
much stricter about
טומאה. tumah. Says if the owners are טמא מת, tamei meis, can't
bring the קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. If the כהן Kohen is טמא,
tamei, it is not good בדיעבד. bedi'avad. The only thing that might
be that's good sometimes is that a ציץ tzitz could work for
the owner who's טומאת התהום. tumas ha-tehom. So it's much more limited
according to the standard approach. The זקני דרום Ziknei Darom are much
more sort of liberal, allowing things to work בדיעבד. bedi'avad.
You know what would help me is three seconds, like just say
שרץ, sharetz, מת, meis, and תהום, tehom, you know, meaning like the
categories and זקני דרום Ziknei Darom and what we say.
Fine. So according to זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, by let's say taking
a קרבן פסח, korban Pesach, right, שרץ sharetz is not a problem
at all because they can eat at night, מת meis בדיעבד bedi'avad
is good, you don't have to, בדיעבד bedi'avad if you don't bring
a פסח שני Pesach Sheni you're okay, and טומאת התהום tumas ha-tehom
is not even necessary because all the other two are good. The
only discussion is by the כהן. Kohen. So a כהן Kohen for
זקני דרום, Ziknei Darom, שרץ sharetz is no good, מת meis is
fine because we allowed in cases of ציבור, tzibur, and טומאת התהום
tumas ha-tehom we're going to allow even for a שרץ sharetz because
of the ציץ. tzitz. Right. Does that clarify it? Right. And then,
and now the חכמים Chachamim would say, שרץ sharetz by the owner
is okay because he can eat at night.
Same thing as זקני...
Ziknei... מת meis is no good. But מת meis of טומאת התהום,
tumas ha-tehom, the ציץ tzitz works for the owner. Okay, that's where
the ציץ tzitz is working for the owner, מת טומאת התהום. meis
tumas ha-tehom. And for the כהן, Kohen, שרץ sharetz is no good,
מת meis is no good, and טומאת התהום, tumas ha-tehom, will it
work for the כהן Kohen when it works for the owner? That's
the question for the ציץ. tzitz. How
is it all totally clear? Great. You, yeah. Good. Thank you, Michael.
All right.
We need, we need a whiteboard and charts. All right, there's going
to be a quiz tomorrow. All right. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay. Yeah, right,
exactly. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. Oh my god, let's
get to the two dots. ונשא אהרן את עון הקדשים. Ve-nasa Aharon
et avon ha-kodashim. Here is the idea of the ציץ. tzitz. אהרן
Aharon will carry the sin of the sacrifices. וכי איזה עון נושא,
Ki eizeh avon nosei, which sin is he bearing? carrying. אם עון
פיגול *Im avon pigul*, if it's the sin of פיגול *pigul*. Now,
פיגול *pigul* here means, ironically, not פיגול *pigul*, which is when you're
thinking to eat it at the wrong time, but the pseudo פיגול
*pigul* when you're thinking to eat it at the wrong place. הרי
כבר נאמר לא יחשב *Harei kvar ne'emar lo yeichashev*, that will not
be counted for the owners, presumably under any circumstances. אם עון נותר
*Im avon notar*, now we do not mean, I'm reading this like
רש"י *Rashi*, we do not mean literally נותר *notar*, the sacrifice was
left over because once the blood was sprinkled obviously if you don't
eat the meat it doesn't affect the legitimacy of the sacrifice. So
נותר *notar* here means, according to רש"י *Rashi*, the פיגול *pigul* that
you're planning on eating it at the wrong time. Real פיגול *pigul*.
So if you're planning on eating it at the wrong time, הרי
כבר נאמר לא ירצה *harei kvar ne'emar lo yeiratzeh*, it won't be
accepted. So what it atones for cannot be forms of פיגול *pigul*,
planning to eat it at the wrong time or the wrong place.
הא אינו נושא *Ha eino nosei*, so what other thing could invalidate
a קרבן korban, *korban*? אלא עון טומאה tumah, *Ela avon tumah*, and
now why do we leap on טומאה tumah, *tumah*? Maybe it's a
זר *zar*, maybe it's אונן *onen*, there are other types of invalidities
that we've been learning about, שהותרה מכללה בציבור *she'hutra miklala betzibur*, because
we know sometimes we override טומאה tumah *tumah*, we override טומאה tumah
*tumah* when it's a communal קרבן korban, *korban*. So therefore since sometimes
we override טומאה tumah *tumah* and the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* also atones
for certain sins of קרבנות *korbanot*, we'll assume it is טומאה tumah?
*tumah* problems that it is going to atone for. So מאי טומאה
Mai tumah, *mai tumah*, what's the טומאה tumah. *tumah* that the ציץ
tzitz *tzitz* is working for? Right? And remember for זקני דרום *Ziknei
Darom*, the only טומאה tumah. *tumah* it works for is when a
כהן *kohen* is טמא שרץ tamei sheretz, *tmei sheretz*. You don't need
it for a כהן *kohen* who's טמא tamei. מת *tmei meit*. For
a כהן *kohen* who's a זב *zav* it doesn't work. So the
only thing you need it for is a, you know, כהן טומאת
שרץ tumas sheretz *kohen tumat sheretz*. That's the only case for זקני
דרום *Ziknei Darom*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: מאי
טומאה tumah *Mai tumah*? אילימא מטומאת שרץ sheretz *Ileima mitumat sheretz*? So
if it's the case that the owner are טמא שרץ *tmei sheretz*,
היכי אישתרי *heichi ishtrei*, or the כהן *kohen* even is טמא שרץ
*tmei sheretz*, if it's טומאת שרץ tumas sheretz. *tumat sheretz*, היכי אישתרי
*heichi ishtrei*? We never say טומאת שרץ *tumat sheretz* is הותרה בציבור
*hutra betzibur*, right? We never override טומאת שרץ *tumat sheretz* בציבור *betzibur*.
So that's it can't be the idea that טומאה tumah, *tumah* was
overwritten. אלא טומאת מת tumas mes. *Ela tumat meit*, the only טומאה
tumah *tumah* that we override בציבור *betzibur* is טומאת מת tumas mes.
*tumat meit*. ולא כגון שנטמאו בעלים במת *Velav kegon shenitme'u ba'alim bemeit*,
and again it is presumably the owners are טמא מת *tmei meit*.
אלמא נטמאו בעלים במת משלחים קרבנותיהם *Alma nitme'u ba'alim bemeit meshalechin korbanoteihem*,
so you see when the owners are טמא מת *tmei meit* you
can bring their קרבן korban. *korban*, it's overwritten. ובמאי *Ubemai*? What's the
case?
So that's a force for זקני דרום *Ziknei Darom*, no?
One minute. One minute. אי בנזיר וכי ימות מת עליו אמר רחמנא
*Ibe'nazir v'chi amut meit alav amar rachmana*. אלא לעושה פסח *Ela la'oseh
pesach*. Hold on, let me just check רש"י *Rashi* and make sure
I'm saying this right.
Oh right, so רש"י *Rashi*, right, right, I'm sorry, so this is
actually initially, in the end the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
read it as a קשיא *kashya* to זקני דרום *Ziknei Darom*. But
here it's actually reading it as a קשיא *kashya* to רמי בר
חמא Rami bar Chama *Rami bar Chama* who says that the owners
cannot bring when they're טמא מת *tmei meit*. Okay, it's a little
bizarre because it says הותרה בציבור *hutra betzibur*, but anyway so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s reading it like this. So if, so we're talking
obviously that it's טמא מת *tmei meit*. So and it's showing you
that you can bring your קרבן korban, *korban* when you are טמא
מת
*tmei meit*, which is exactly what זקני דרום *Ziknei Darom* said.
Right. But the problem is that it says it's בציבור *betzibur*. So
זקני דרום *Ziknei Darom* were saying it ביחיד *beyachid*, so it's not
exactly clear. Okay, but anyway the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* maybe so, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s saying so what? If it's
by a נזיר *nazir*, וכי ימות מת עליו אמר רחמנא *v'chi amut
meit alav amar rachmana*, so the תורה Torah *Torah* is saying
that you know when he becomes טמא *tamei* and he can't bring
his קרבן korban *korban* until he's fit to become טהור *tahor*. So
clearly, again it's a little unclear how it gets it from that
פסוק *pasuk*, but anyway clearly he would not be able to bring
his קרבן korban *korban* when he's טמא *tamei*. אלא לעושה פסח *Ela
la'oseh pesach*. Unless it's talking about the people doing the פסח *pesach*
and they can bring their קרבן korban *korban* even when they are
טמאים *tmeim*. Now again it's very questionable. I mean it's a hard
read of this גמרא *Gemara* because it strongly seems to be that
we allow it בציבור *betzibur*. זקני דרום *Ziknei Darom*'s position was that
we allow the owners to bring their קרבן korban פסח *Korban Pesach*
even as individuals when they're טמאים *tmeim*. But so let's see what
the answer is. לעולם בשרץ *Le'olam besheretz*. No, we're not talking about
about טומאת מת tumas mes *tumas meit*, we're talking about טומאת שרץ
*tumat sheretz*. ושם טומאה tumah? בעולם *V'shem tumah ba'olam*. And what we're
just saying is טומאה *tumah*'s sometimes allowed. We don't mean the exact
same טומאה *tumah* is allowed, טומאת מת tumas mes, *tumat meit*, we
mean since טומאה *tumah* is sometimes allowed, some טומאה *tumah*, therefore we
allow it even in the case, therefore the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* works
for טומאה *tumah*. So what the משנה *mishnah* the ברייתא braisa *braisa*
says the following: What does the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* work for? It
has to work for טומאה *tumah* because טומאה *tumah* is something we
find that sometimes the תורה *Torah* allows. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
well when do we find that the תורה *Torah* allows the טומאה
*tumah*? Where is there an exception made to טומאה *tumah*? It must
be when the תורה *Torah* allows somebody who's טמא מת *tmei meit*
to bring the קרבן korban פסח *Korban Pesach*. So you see that
זקני דרום *Ziknei Darom* are correct. So but and because we know
that the ציץ tzitz *tzitz* works for טומאת מת tumas mes, *tumas
meit*. When it says the תורה allows טומאה, it means when the
owners are טמא שרץ, they can bring their קרבן, korban
and but since we find sometimes the תורה allows טומאה, we therefore
the ציץ tzitz could work for other types of טומאה for טומאת
מת. tumas mes, It's a very difficult גמרא you can see there
are these huge תוספות Tosafos in, especially because the principle here seems
to be about ציבור tzibbur and not יחיד. yachid. But let's just
finish to the two dots, we're basically done with this so we
can start something totally new tomorrow. ואיכא דדייקי ומייתי הכי, Ve-ika d'dayki
u-mayti hachi, some ask the other way and ask it as a
support of רמי בר חמא and a question on זקני דרומא. Ziknei
Daroma. עון קדשים אין, Avon kodashim in, it only atones for the
טומאה of the sacrifices, עון מקדישים לא, avon makdishim lo, not for
the טומאה of those that are bringing the sacrifices. מאי טומאה, and
what type of טומאה? אילימא טומאת שרץ מי אישתרי בציבור, Ileima tumas
sheretz mi ishtari b'tzibbur, if it's טומאת שרץ there was never an
override of that. אלא לאו טומאת מת, Ella lav tumas mes, it
must be talking about טומאת מת. ועון קדשים אין עון מקדישים לא,
Ve-avon kodashim in avon makdishim lo, and the ציץ tzitz only works
for the sacrifices, not for the individuals. So you see that even
when the individuals are טמאי מת, tamei mes, they can't bring their
קרבן, and that is against the זקני דרומא Ziknei Daroma who said
that טמאי מת tamei mes can bring their קרבן. So the גמרא
says לעולם טומאת שרץ ושאין טומאה בעולם. Le'olam tumas sheretz v'she'ein tumah
ba'olam. Okay, so we're only talking about שרץ and talking just that
it sometimes allows some טומאה. I think we probably were a little
lost there, but I think it's time to start a new discussion.
So just to try to summarize that last point though and maybe
a way that would be a little clearer, I'm trying to do
it in one sentence is:
the
גמרא here at the end, and I think I might have misexplained
this a minute ago, so let me try again. The גמרא here
at the end seems to understand that when the זקני דרומא Ziknei
Daroma say that the owners can bring it when they're טמאי מת,
tamei mes, that that also is something of a function of the
ציץ tzitz as opposed to what it was assuming before. So here
this ברייתא said that the ציץ tzitz works, the ציץ tzitz is
מרצה. meratzeh. The ציץ tzitz works because we override טומאה. So the
גמרא says, okay one minute, what טומאה do we override? We override
טומאת מת בציבור. tumas mes b'tzibbur. So what is the ציץ being
מרצה? meratzeh? Something analogous when it happens at an individual level, which
means that the ציץ works when the owners are טמאי מת, tamei
mes, which is the position of זקני דרומא Ziknei Daroma that when
the owners are טמאי מת tamei mes they can bring their קרבן,
because it's not mentioning טומאת התהום tumas hatehom here, so it's just
the general principle that the owners can bring their קרבן when they're
טמאי מת. tamei mes. So that seems to be a support for
the זקני דרומא. Ziknei Daroma. The גמרא says no, we're not comparing
the same types of טומאה, the טומאה הותרה בציבור tumah hutra b'tzibbur
is טומאת מת but the טומאה it works for is טומאת שרץ.
The other approach was different, the ציץ isn't working for the owners,
it's working for the בשר basar for the קרבן for the blood.
So the ציץ works for the blood when it's טומאת מת, but
it doesn't work for the owners when they're טמאי מת, tamei mes,
and that proves against זקני דרומא Ziknei Daroma that when the owners
are טמאי מת tamei mes the קרבן doesn't work.
So let's see, it works for blood.
If the blood is טומאת מת, the ציץ means בדיעבד b'di'eved it's
okay.
If the blood is טומאת מת, doesn't the קרבן—I think that does
the קרבן also bring טומאה?
No, no, a קרבן that is שחט, shachted, an animal that's שחט
shachted correctly is not טמא.
Oh, any animal שחט shachted correctly?
Any כשר kosher animal.
Okay, to be continued tomorrow.