Okay boker tov, today's daf is Pe
Menachos 80. We pick up in the
mishnah on the bottom of עין טית
עמוד בית and we are in the
middle of dealing with aspects of the
todah, which is a korban which requires
bread, so hence its connection to Menachos.
And here's the mishnah: bottom of עין
טית עמוד בית. vlad todah utemurasah הפריש
תודה ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה ein hatemurah
lechem. So we're dealing with the todah,
of course, needs the 40 loaves of
bread, 30 matzah, 10 chametz. But here
are things that are connected to derived
from a todah that do not require
bread because they're not the todah itself.
So one is if a todah gives
birth, a todah is brought for, it
can be female, and therefore if it
has a child, that child has the
kedushah of a todah but it is
not the todah itself. temurasah, if you
basically say I'm going to exchange this
animal for that one, this animal that
I already sanctified. The Torah says you're
not allowed to, but nevertheless והיה הוא
ותמורתו קודש. If you try, the second
one gets the kedushah as well even
though the first one does not lose
it. הפריש תודה ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה.
You designated out your todah korban and
then it got lost. And then, so
you had to create, to get a
substitute because you're obligated in a todah.
So you then designated, sanctified another animal
in its stead, and then you found
the first one. Okay, so one of
them is going to be the todah,
the other is going to sort of
be, have the kedushah to fill the
place of the todah, but it is
not the todah itself. So in all
those cases, einah teunah lechem. shene'emar הקריב
על זבח התודה. התודה טעונה לחם ולא
ולדה ולא חליפתיה ולא תמורתה טעונה לחם.
Only the todah itself, not its child,
not the thing that was done to
substitute for it, and not the temurah,
the exchange. Okay, so very straightforward, let's
see the gemara. tanu rabanan utano babraisa:
מה הוא אומר תודה יקריב. ה-pasuk omer
זאת תורת זבח השלמים אם על תודה
יקריבנו והקריב על זבח התודה חלות מצות
בלולת בשמן כרקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן. So
we're going to bracket out the 'nu',
'it', 'bring it', for a second, and
just treat אם על תודה יקריב. מניין
למפריש תודתו ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה ונמצאת
הראשונה והשניה עומדות. How do you know
if you separated out a todah and
it got lost, and then you've sanctified
another one in its stead and then
you found the first one, and both
of them are now in front of
you? מניין שאיזה מהן שירצה יקריב? How
do you know that either one you
can bring to fulfill your obligation? This
is a general principle of sanctifying an
animal if one got lost, and how
do you know it satisfies your obligation?
velachmah imah, and not only that, though,
that you also will bring the bread
with it, even if it's the second
one that you sanctified as a substitute
for the first. And even though the
first one is right here in front
of you, how do you know you
can bring the second one and bring
the bread, or the matzah? talmud lomar,
or the matzah, talmud lomar, hatodah yakriv.
im al todah so, whichever is the
todah, you know, or either one is
the todah, and therefore either one you
can bring. יכול שתהא שניה טעונה לחם,
maybe after you bring one of them,
so you, because then the... I should
say, hatodah yakriv, it says אם על
תודה יקריבנו והקריב על זבח התודה חלות
מצות. So you todah yakriv, you bring
the one you want and then you
bring the bread with it. How do
you know though that the second one,
the one you're bringing second, whether it
was the first one you sanctified or
the second one you sanctified, how do
you know the one you're bringing second
you don't bring bread? מניין ש... יכול
שתהא שניה טעונה לחם? talmud lomar, yakrivenu,
you should bring it. והקריב על זבח
התודה חלות מצות. So you should bring
one of them, one of them is
a todah with the bread, and the
other one has the kedushah of the
todah, but it is not the single
one that gets the bread. echad velo
shenayim. עכשיו ריבה הכתוב ומיעט. So now
after the verse, you know, it's expansive
then it limits, מניין לרבות ולדות וחליפות
ותמורות להקרבה? So we have a broader
verse, im al todah, but then you
have yakrivenu. How do I know so
we're going to first say that that
pasuk is talking about something that is
effectively a todah itself, something that you
directly sanctified to be a todah instead,
in the stead of the first one
that got lost. But how do I
know that you can even bring a
korban if it is not the todah
itself and not sanctified to serve as
a todah, but it is a type
of a derivative? It is a temurah
or it is a vlad. מניין לרבות
ולדות וחליפות... והא דתניא ולדותיהן ותמורותיהן להקרבה
talmud lomar im al toda יכול כשירות
להקרבת talmud lomar והקריב על זבח תודה.
So what we're doing here is we're
focusing on the extra word al. If
you noticed before, even though the pasuk
is אם על תודה יקריבנו, we sort
of bracketed the word al. We read
im toda yakrivenu, whichever you pick one
as a toda and then you bring
it with the bread. But the al
toda, im al toda means even something
that is not serving as the toda
itself but like on top of the
toda derived from the toda. It is
the vlad of the toda, the child
or it is the tmura of the
toda. Okay. In that case even though
it's not there to serve as the
toda itself, nevertheless, אם על תודה יקריבנו,
you could still bring it. Yachol yetun
lechem, maybe these should bring bread, maybe
in the first case where they were
both there to serve the same purpose,
so only one has bread. Maybe here
where they're not in the same way
competing, so this derivative thing maybe you
would bring its bread since it has
the kdusha that derives from a toda.
הקריב על זבח התודה. So that's the
next pasuk al zevach hatoda, only the
one חלות מצות בלולות בשמן. Only the
one that is actually serving as a
toda itself. תודה טעונה לחם ולא ולדה
ולא חלופה ולא תמורתה טעונה לחם. Okay.
So from the extra word ואם על
תודה יקריבנו is to sort of tell
you that if two of them are
both trying to serve as a toda,
you can pick one and that one
gets the bread. Yakrivenu, only one of
them will get the bread, the one
that you bring first. And al toda
and then al zevach hatoda. Al toda
tells you even derivative things you bring
as a toda. But al zevach hatoda
is telling you that only the one
that's but that a derivative thing doesn't
get bread, only something that's actually serving
as a toda gets bread. Okay. שלח
רב חנינא משמיה דשמואל, three lines up
from the bottom. שלח רב חנינא משמיה
דרבי יוחנן, לא שנו אלא לאחר כפרה
אבל לפני כפרה טעונה לחם. So now
we're going to spend like the whole
rest of the next amud unpacking this
statement. This idea that you don't bring
bread is only after kapara has been
made, meaning after the sacrifice has been
legitimately offered. But before kapara has been
made, then you would bring bread. So
the gemara's going to try to figure
out what this means. הוי בה רבי
עמרם. Rabbi Abin questioned this. Ahai, on
which case are you referring to distinguish
before kapara and after kapara? אילמא אחליפי
תודה חובה, let's say the type that
we were the first primary case we
were talking about, that you really designated
something as a substitute and the type
of chova we're talking about is an
obligatory chova that the person says harei
alai. They take a neder that they've
vowed that they're obligated themselves or according
to one version of Rashi, the obligation
is based on what chazal understood based
on the perek of tehillim, the people
that are obligated to bring a toda,
people that cross a desert, cross a
sea, etc. But you have a personal
obligation to bring, okay, and then you
designate a toda, it gets lost and
now you designate another one. Okay, so
that's pretty much the case we were
talking about. But then his point is
well then you're not saying anything, we've
already said it. So אי לפני כפרה
תנינא אי לאחר כפרה תנינא. So both
of those cases, before kapara you bring
the bread, after kapara you don't, both
of those we taught that was exactly
the braita that you pick one, as
soon as you bring one, it's le'achar
kapara, you satisfied your obligation. So before
you've brought either is lifnei kapara, you
haven't satisfied your obligation, so the one
that you're going to bring gets bread.
And then the second one, now that
you've satisfied your obligation, is le'achar kapara
and it doesn't get bread. So that's
exactly what we taught. If you substitute
one, one is lost and then you
sanctify one in its stead, the first
one gets bread, the second one does
not. So that would not have been
the point of Rabbi Yochanan. Ela, so
rather, top of peh amud aleph, achalifei
toda nedava. We're talking about it is
a free-will toda, meaning there's no harei
alai, there's no circumstances that obligated you,
you just said I'm sanctifying this animal
as a toda. Now in that case
if the toda gets lost, you have
no obligation. You sanctified the animal but
you have not accepted a personal obligation.
So it gets lost and then you
sanctify another one and say ah, that
first animal got lost, fine, I'm sanctifying
this next one. Okay, in that case
says the gemara, בין לפני כפרה בין
לאחר כפרה טעונה לחם. Then regardless of
whether you brought one or you didn't
bring one yet, you bring bread on
the second. Why? מר בר תודה הוא.
Because you're just bringing another toda. Right.
So this might sound a little ironic
that if there's no You're just giving
another toda. Okay, that's a nice point.
So ela, so rather, so what is
the case where lifnei v'achar kapara matter
and it's not the case we already
taught? avlad toda nidava. So it is
the vlad of a toda of a
nidava. Again, I don't have any obligation,
I sanctify this sheep and I ask
for a toda and then it gives
birth. Okay, so in that case, בין
לפני כפרה בין לאחר כפרה אין טעונה
לחם, motar de-toda hu. So then in
that case, whether I before bring the
vlad toda before or after I bring
the mother, there's not going to be
bread. This is derivative kedusha, okay, and
derivative kedusha doesn't require bread. The only
question that something might logically require the
bread is when I sanctified it to
take the stead, you know, of the
one that was lost, or in the
case of nidava, it was lost, I
essentially I sanctified it directly as a
toda. But something that is derivative like
a vlad toda, who cares if you
were makriv the mother yet, not makriv
the mother yet, it's not a real
toda, it doesn't get bread. בין לפני
כפרה בין לאחר כפרה אין טעונה לחם,
motar de-toda hu, it is the remnant
of the toda he. אלא אולד תודה
חובה, okay, so it is a toda
I was obligated, I said harei alai,
or according to the other language in
Rashi, you know, somebody who crossed an
ocean, crossed a desert, separated out a
toda, and then the toda gave birth.
Okay, avlad toda chova. So לפני כפרה
טעון לחם. Before kapara it requires bread.
לאחר כפרה אין טעון לחם. After kapara
it does not. Now we know why
after kapara it does not, it's just
derivative kedusha, so it should never require
bread. So why would it require bread
if I have not yet brought the
mother? Okay, so mai kamashma lan, what
is this teaching us? דקסבר רבי יוחנן
אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש, that a person
can get atonement through the increase of
hekdesh. So in a way this animal
was sanctified, it then increased, so it
increased through giving birth. So basically this
is this like derivative, but it's a
derivative it's not temura, it's a derivative
that's sort of a natural increase of
hekdesh, so it's a way of saying
a vlad of a hekdesh. And Rebi
Yochanan actually says that you can use
that for a, like the scenario of
sanctifying something in something's stead, okay, when
something got lost. You can use that
to satisfy the obligation. So if you
had an obligation of a toda or
you said harei alai shelamim or you
said harei alai olah, well olah is
a male so forget that, but anyway,
and then it gave birth, that thing,
if you bring that thing you satisfy
your obligation. It's a type of like
an ubar yerech imo, it's an extension
of the thing itself. So because it
gets kedusha from the thing, and Tosafot
by the way says it doesn't matter
if it became pregnant before you sanctified
it or after you sanctified it, through
that you satisfy your obligation. So if
you are satisfying your obligation through that,
so if you bring the mother then
you're not going to satisfy your obligation,
if you bring the thing itself you
will satisfy your obligation and you will
bring, and you will bring the bread.
Okay, so that's what he is saying,
that even though it is derivative, if
it is an obligatory toda, because it
has the power to make you satisfy
your obligation, that is considered to be
like the toda itself and you bring
bread. What's not clear is in that
case, would you also bring the bread
for the mother? Okay, because maybe the
mother is the actual original, this is
just derivative. Or would we say it
seems like since Rashi and Tosafot don't
comment that the answer would be no,
that it would sort of just be
like losing and another one in its
stead. But you could see why you
might distinguish, because here it's basically there
is the mother and then the thing
that derived. Okay, but that's why he
said it, and it would only work
in a case where it was obligatory
because this thing that's derived and that's
a shevach hekdesh. satisfies the obligation. Okay,
but if you do the mother first
it's not satisfying then no. But if
it's a free will since it's not
satisfying any obligation and it's just derivative,
it's not really a todah so it
does not get bread. Okay. הוי בני
אביי כהאי גוונא and Abaye also wanted
understand what was the context of Rabbi
Yochanan's statement before kappara and after kappara
and he came basically to the same
conclusion that we were talking about a
vlad of a of a of a
of a todah chova. Okay, itmar nami
was also taught. אמר רבי יצחק בר
רב יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן, chilufei todah
nedava a substitute for a free will
todah, okay, so if it gets lost
and you sanctify another one but there's
no obligation, בין לפני כפרה בין לאחר
כפרה טעונה לחם, whether before or after
you brought the first one, it doesn't
matter, you bring bread on the second.
Marbeh betodot hu, you're just bringing extra
todot, okay, since there's no obligation you're
satisfying each one is a todah on
its own accord. Marbeh betodot hu. Vlad
todah chova, however if you're dealing with
the child of a todah and it
is an obligatory todah, לפני כפרה טעונה
לחם לאחר כפרה אין טעונה לחם. If
you bring it before you brought the
mother, it gets bread, after you do
not. So again in the name of
Rabbi Yochanan but very clearly identifying the
case as vlad todah chova. Okay, amar
Shmuel, says Shmuel, חמש בחטאת מתה בתודה
אין טעונה לחם חמש בחטאת רועה בתודה
טעונה לחם. Anytime you would have a
sin offering that you would let die,
there are five types of sin offerings
you let die, I'll explain in a
minute, the parallel case in a todah
would not get bread. However, if it
was a type of sin offering that
you would let graze until it got
a blemish and then redeem it, then
you would bring bread. So what are
the chatot that you let die? This
is a specific halacha by chatot which
are very sin connected and therefore you
don't have like an option to bring
like a derivative or a substitute or
those types of things. Interestingly it's not
true by an asham, asham is also
sin derivative, but there you wait for
it to get a blemish, but by
a chatas it's specifically the halacha is
you have to let it die. What
are those five cases? The acronym is
vitimna. Okay, Vitimna hayesa pilegesh. Vav is
vlad chatas, a child of a chatas.
It's derivative, it's not the chatas itself,
you can't bring it on a sin
because only the mother could be brought
on the sin, so and therefore you
have to let it die. Tet is
temuras chatas, you try to exchange it,
again doesn't work but the second one
gets kedusha but cannot be brought for
the sin, you have to let it
die. Mem, mesu ba'aleha, the owners died.
In that case, you know, it's no
longer meaningful to be bringing it for
a sin, so you would not, so
you let it die. Nun is nevda,
which is the case we've been talking
about, it gets lost and you create
and you bring and you sanctify a
substitute and then you find it. So
one of them you bring, the other
one you let die. And ayin is
avar shnaso, it's no longer a year
old, a chatas has to be a
year old. So the ayin isn't relevant
cause a todah does not have to
be a year old. Vlad is what
we've been talking about, vlad so okay
we'll have to see if that works
out, niskapru b'acher we've been talking about,
so we'll have to see if that
works with Shmuel's statement. Temura we've been
talking about, all those three work. And
mesu ba'alov, interestingly the Gemara is not
going to discuss, you could that actually
seems to on the face of it
possibly violate Rabbi Yochanan because why just
because the owners died should you not
bring the bread for a todah? But
let's see what the Gemara says. The
Gemara's going to bracket the mesa we'll
get back to that in a minute,
the mes ba'alov. Okay, so let's see
the Gemara. Okay. Masiv Rav Amram, Rav
Amram asked on Shmuel's statement. Mahu omer?
So you know, he's going back to
the baraita we quoted at the beginning
of today's daf. התודה יקריב מנין למפריש
תודתו ואבדה והפריש אחרת תחתיה ונמצאת הראשונה
והרי שתיהם עומדות מנין שאיזה מהם שירצה
יקריב ולחמו עמו? How do you know
that when you you know separate one
and then have another one that you
bring the one you want and with
its bread? תלמוד לומר התודה יקריב יכול
תהא שניה טעונה לחם, maybe you bring
bread with the second one? תלמוד לומר
יקריבנו אחד ולא שנים. Okay, ve'ilu so
why is that a question that seems
perfect? The second one you would let
die by a chatas and here you
don't bring bread. Okay, niskapru alav b'acher.
Ah because it actually is not necessarily
true that there's a debate or the
circumstances matter whether you let it die
by a chatas. ואילו גבי חטאת כהאי
גוונא when it comes to a chatas...
chatas in that case, ro'eh, you let
it graze, d’tnan, הפריש חטאתו ואבדה והפריש
אחר תחתיו ונמצא הראשון והרי שניהם עומדות,
נתכפר באחת מהן והשנייה תמות דברי רבי.
So Rebbe says exactly this scenario that
if one got lost and you do
another, sanctify another one, you find the
first, you bring the one you want
and the second one you have to
let die. That's exactly how that works
well, that's like our case. The second
Toda, the one you didn't offer, the
one that wasn't for your obligation, that
you don't bring the bread. However, that's
just Rebbe. Vachachamim omrim, but the Chachamim
say, אין חטאת מתה אלא שנמצאת לאחר
שנתכפרו הבעלים. No, no, no. When do
we say if it's niskaper b'acher it
dies? If the first one was found
after you brought the second. So you
brought the second, you're yotzei, and then
you found the first one. In that
case, the first one comes onto the
scene late, then it's totally pushed away,
it's let die. Okay? But the Gemara
spells out the implication. What are they
saying? Kodem sheniskapru haba'alim if you found
the second one, if you found the
first one before either were offered and
you have both of them in front
of you, which was our case, right?
Since both of them potentially could be
brought, according to the Chachamim, you don't
let the other one die. Ro'eh, you
let it graze. So that is a
case where clearly when they're both in
front of you and you pick one,
by a Toda the second one doesn't
get bread, but Shmuel said that if
it doesn't get bread, it means it
dies by a chatas, or let's say
it the other way, in that case
by a chatas it grazes and waits
for a blemish, and according to Shmuel
that means it should get bread, but
we don't get bread when you have
two in front of you and bring
one for the second one. So the
Gemara says, שמואל כרבי סבירא ליה דאמר
אבודה בשעת הפרשה מתה. Fine, okay, you're
right, but Shmuel holds like Rebbe. Shmuel
says, I don't care by the chatas
if it gets found after you were
makriv the second one or before and
both of them were in front of
you. Whatever the scenario is by a
chatas, if you used one and you
didn't use the other, the second one
dies and that's exactly the same by
a tmura or what in our case,
that the second one doesn't bring bread.
Okay. So now the Gemara says like
this: אלא רועה לרבי היכי משכחת לה?
Okay, so fine. So now you've got
for Shmuel the case where it's going
to die by a chatas you won't
bring bread by a Toda because all
the cases of one as a substitute
it's going to die by a chatas,
the second one. But Shmuel also said
a second part of his statement where
it grazes by a chatas you do
bring bread. What is that scenario? Okay.
First of all, what's a scenario that
it even grazes for chatas according to
Rebbe? It sounds like Rebbe all the
cases you're going to, unusual cases you're
going to let die. אלא רועה לרבי
היכי משכחת לה? K’Rav Oshaya, like Rav
Oshaya. D’amar Rav Oshaya, הפריש שתי חטאות
לאחריות מתכפר באיזו מהן שירצה והשנייה תרעה.
So here's a third scenario of having
the case of two animals that could
serve as a chatas. The first one
is it gets lost, you separate one,
and then you bring it and then
the first one gets found. The second
one is that everybody agrees mesa. The
second one is you separate one then
you find the first one, you bring
one of them and there there's a
debate whether the second one is mesa
or not. But here's a third case.
From the very beginning you say: These
two animals are going to, I have
an obligation of a chatas, I'm separating
out these two animals, one of them
I will and I'll decide which one
will use or one will be a
backup for the other but from the
very get-go you sanctified or separated out
both of those. In that case he
says that you bring from one of
them and the other one, because as
opposed to the case where one was
lost that the one that was lost
for a time being it couldn't be
used and so on, here each one
was from the very beginning set to
be brought as a chatas. Okay? So
in that case v'hashnia tir’eh, that it
wouldn’t die. So the Gemara says: אבל
גבי תודה כי האי גוונא אין טעונה
לחם, but that doesn't work. So great,
we found a case where it could
be that it's ro'eh by a chatas
of niskaper ba'al b’acher, but nevertheless in
that case, we learn from the pasuk
HaToda that whatever the scenario is, the
second one that's coming for the same
obligation does not get bread. Alright, so
Shmuel’s principle doesn't work. So the Gemara
says: אלא שמואל כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה
דאמר חמש חטאות מתות. So fine, Shmuel
holds like Rabbi Shimon that says five
chatas die, we generally say five chatas
die, although there's some question maybe it's
four or whatever, but anyway, and he
would say it in any case, as
Rashi spells out, of niskaper ba'aleha b’acher.
So since he would say it in
any case of niskaper ba'aleha b’acher... it
works perfectly with our Mishnah. There are
two, there's a toda, there's something there
that was coming because one was lost,
whatever, they're both trying to satisfy the
obligation, the one that you don't use,
you don't bring bread. Here too by
Chatas, any scenario where they're both trying
to satisfy the same obligation, according to
Rabbi Shimon the other one you let
die. So that works for Shmuel. Great.
But it doesn't tell us what Shmuel's
chiddush is, that's basically just our Mishnah
or Baraysa. And also doesn't tell us
the case of Ro'eh for Shmuel. So
the Gemara says, והרועה לרבי שמעון לית
ליה כלל so, okay, so Rabbi Shimon
never has a case of Ro'eh. So
why did Shmuel say if it's Ro'eh
you do bring bread? What's the case
of Ro'eh? They're always Meisos. So the
Gemara says, שמואל נמי חדא קאמר You're
right, Shmuel didn't say the second part
of this statement. He just said the
first part of his statement: כל שבחטאת
מתה בתודה אינה טעונה לחם Anytime it
dies by Chatas, no bread by a
toda. Okay. So the Gemara says, מאי
קא משמע לן So what are you
teaching me? We already know by a
toda that any case where the two
are competing for the same obligation, that
you don't bring bread for the second
one. Those are all the cases of
it got lost and so on. So
Shmuel wasn't mechadesh anything by a toda.
And even to make Shmuel work, we
had to say a chiddush about what
he's saying by a Chatas, that he
holds like Rabbi Shimon that any case
of Niskaper be'acher you're going to say
is going to be Mesa. Fine, but
it's not a chiddush by a Chatas.
So what's the point of this statement?
So the Gemara says, Leafukei miDeRabbi Yochanan
Ah, to, do you remember Rabbi Yochanan?
To reject the position of Rabbi Yochanan,
דאמר אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש קא משמע
לן דלא. Ah, because Rabbi Yochanan says
that if you have a case of
the vlad of a toda, you can
use of an obligatory toda, you can
use that child of the obligatory toda
to satisfy your obligation. Okay, so Rabbi
Yochanan would say 'a' you can use
it to satisfy your obligation and 'b'
it would get bread. Okay, that's what
he says. If you bring that first.
It's a vlad toda. But remember the
first v'simnah, the first vov there is
the vov of a vlad chatas. So
Shmuel says I reject Rabbi Yochanan. Since
a vlad chatas you always let die,
even though you would bring a vlad
of a Shelamim, okay, a vlad of
a toda, you would not bring bread.
All right, so that's basically the point
of Shmuel. קא משמע לן דלא. So
now what is shocking about all of
this is that the Gemara does not
explore the category of Mesu be'aleha. It's
not really, that's a case where a
Chatas dies. What's the story by the
toda? And it's not really explicit anywhere
in the Bavli about that. There's Yerushalmi
that says in that case that you
do bring the bread, which stands to
reason. It's not a case like a
sin. So if a toda gets bread,
it gets bread whether the owners are
around or not, it's not linked to
the circumstances of the owner. There's such
a thing as a todas nedavah which
is not based on crossing a sea
or and so on. So it makes
sense that it gets bread. So that
is a contradiction to Shmuel. That would
be a case of where a Chatas,
it would die, and where a by
a toda you would bring the bread.
So it's fascinating I could not find
any of the Rishonim or whatever that
asked this question. One of the commentators
on the Yerushalmi asks this question. It
is interesting that it does not get
discussed. Okay, so now the Gemara says
like this. Amar Rabbi Abba, said Rabbi
Abba, זו תודה וזו לחמה If somebody
separates out an animal and says this
is the toda and then separates out
bread or flour and says and this
is for the bread, אבד הלחם מביא
לחם אחר If the bread is lost,
you can bring substitute bread for the
toda. Avda toda, but if you lose
the toda, אינו מביא תודה אחרת You
cannot bring another toda. I mean, you
would bring another toda maybe for your
obligation but it would require its own
bread. This bread would have to be
redeemed or whatever, it could not be
used for this other toda. Okay. Why
not? Mai ta'ama, לחם לגבי תודה ואין
תודה לגבי לחם Because it's its bread.
Which is the owner and which is
the, which is the possessor and which
is the possessed? Okay, so the bread
is linked to the toda. The toda
isn't linked to the bread. So if
you lose the bread, so if you
lose the bread you can bring other
bread. The toda is not, other bread
can be added to the toda. The
toda is the possessor. Okay. But if
the toda's lost, then the bread doesn't
mean anything. The bread is specifically linked
to the toda. Okay. And amar Rava,
that makes a lot of sense, obviously.
Ve'amar Rava, says Rava: Hifrish ma'os letodaso,
if somebody set aside money for his
toda, and Venisosru, and then there was
leftover. You said I'm going to set
this to buy the lamb for my
toda. And you sanctified it, and there
was leftover money. Mevi bahen lechem, you
can use the leftover to buy the
the bread, which comes with it. Lelachmei
toda, if you set aside money to
bring the buy the bread for your
toda and v'nitosru and leftover, אין מביא
בהן תודה, you can't use the leftover
money for the toda. Same idea basically.
Mai ta'ama, what's the reason? אילימא משום
דרב כהנא, de'amar Rav Kahana, how do
you know the bread of the toda
is called the toda itself? Shenne'emar, וקריב
על זבח התודה חלות מצות. You should
bring on the toda sacrifice the challah.
Now, on the peshat, that's not calling
the challah the toda. But the way
he's reading it is hatoda challot matzot.
The challah matzot are also considered part
of the toda. אי הכי איפכא נמי?
So if that's true, if the bread
is called toda, so if you set
aside money for the bread, since it's
called toda, you should also be able
to use it to buy a toda.
So again the Gemara says basically the
same answer here, it's even a little
sharper than before. לחם איקרי תודה תודה
לא איקרי לחם. No, the bread can
be called toda because it's part of
the toda. So this is money for
a toda, includes not only the animal
but also the bread, because the bread
is part of the toda. This is
money for bread, okay, so the animal
is not bread. Same basic idea. The
lechem is like an appurtenance, like an
extension of the, the bread is an
extension of the animal, not in the
reverse. Okay, ve'amar Rava, and says Rava,
hifrish todaso ve'avda, וחזר והפריש אחרת תחתיה,
this sounds familiar. Okay, you know you
set aside your toda, it got lost,
now you set aside another one, we
know the halacha is whichever one you
bring first gets the bread. But now,
ve'avda, and then the second one got
lost. וחזר והפריש אחרת תחתיה, now you
set aside a third one as a
substitute for the second one. Ve'nimtze'u harishonot,
and then so and then you have
three now, number three that was set
aside, but now number one and two
both get found. Ve'harei sheloshtan omdot, and
you have all three of them standing
in front of you and you could
decide which one to bring. Okay, נתכפר
בראשונה שנייה אינה טעונה לחם שלישית טעונה
לחם. If you use number one for
the toda, then number two doesn't get
bread, and number three does get bread.
Why? Because number two was a substitute
for number one. So one got brought,
both of them were competing for that
same box, if you would, the number
one box, you know, the obligation. Number
one filled it, it gets the bread,
number two is not the actual toda
itself, you know, and it doesn't get
the bread. But number three was substituting
for number two. Now at the time
we might have thought that they were
still trying to fit into that one
box called the obligation. But now we
see that two was never going to
be an obligation. So three as a
substitute for number two, okay, it's not
satisfying an obligation, so you're basically just
sanctifying a toda, marbe betodos. You didn't
need number two, two wasn't an obligation,
now you sanctified three to be a
substitute for number two, we're all saying
this with the benefit of hindsight, you
basically are just sanctifying a toda. It's
pretty interesting that something that's a substitute,
derivative, has bread when the thing itself
does not have bread. But okay, that's
what he says. נתכפר בשלישית שנייה אינה
טעונה לחם ראשונה טעונה לחם. Same in
the reverse. If you use number three,
שנייה אינה טעונה לחם, you don't bring
for number two, because three and two
were competing for the same box and
three got the box, obligation, so two
doesn't get the bread. Rishona te'una lechem,
but the first one does get the
bread because the first one is, you
know, is by itself, it's just a
toda and it's not competing with anything
else and therefore it's not competing with
anything else, it goes ahead and it
gets the bread. Okay, be'emtza'ita, be'emtza'i, if
you use number two for your obligation,
שתיהן אינן טעונות לחם, neither of them
gets bread, because, because then three and
two were competing for the same box,
and two and one was competing for
the same box, two got it, so
one and three both are not the
real toda and therefore don't get bread.
Abaye amar, Abaye says, Abaye says that's
very ingenious, but Abaye says the simpler
thing. אפילו נתכפר באחת מהן שתיהן אינן
טעונות לחם. I don't care which one
you use, the other two don't get
bread. כולהו חליפי דהדדי נינהו. They're all
basically substitutes of one another. Even though
two got lost and you separated three
as a substitute, all of them were
competing for the same box of your
obligation, and therefore whichever one satisfies, gets
in that box, the other two are
not the actual toda per se and
therefore do not get bread.