Yes, it is Ayin-Tet, starting with some
things on the bottom of Ayin-Tet Amud
Bet. Okay. Now we are moving a
little bit back into, you know, things
that sound a little more like Zevachim.
We're talking about the actual slaughtering of
the Korban, but again the Torah presents
a very interesting hybrid because it has
a Korban element and the Mincha, as
it were, the bread element, although as
I said, questionably, I mean obviously the
Gemara's treating it as a Mincha, but
it's Kodshim Kalim not Kodshei Kodshim, it's
not brought on its own, so, you
know, it's not exactly a Mincha. Anyway,
and that's what we're focusing on is
how the Toda relates to the bread.
So last day, yesterday we saw that
the slaughtering of the Korban is what
gives Kedusha to the bread. And now
we are going to continue on that
discussion. So let's take a look. Shachata
Chutz Lizmano Ve-Chutz Limkomo, if the Toda
was slaughtered, now again, this Chutz Lizmano
Ve-Chutz Limkomo, as you probably remember from
Zevachim, does not literally mean in the
wrong place or at the wrong time,
actually hard to imagine what the wrong
time would be, I guess it could
be at night. Anyway, but it means
with a thought of the wrong place
or the wrong time. So it's a
Pigul thought or a Chutz Limkomo thought,
which is analogous to a Pigul thought.
So basically we said that the slaughtering
of the Toda sanctifies the bread. What
happens if the Toda is slaughtered incorrectly
with a Psul? So here, interestingly, Kadesh
Halechem, the bread does become Kadosh. Kadosh
Venifsal. Kadosh Venifsal, okay, which is the
worst of the scenarios, which means that
it's sanctified, now the Korban is no
good, if the Korban is no good,
the bread is no good and you
can't use it for anything else. Okay,
so that's Kadesh Halechem. Shachata Venimtzeit Treifa,
but this is in contrast to if
the Korban was slaughtered and it was
a Treifa, which also means it's Pasul,
Lo Kadesh Halechem, the bread is not
sanctified. What is the difference? The difference
is actually obvious, pretty obvious, which the
Gemara will say explicitly, if the Shechita
was never Kasher to begin with, the
Psul occurred before the Shechita, so the
Shechita was meaningless from the get-go, it
was already a Treifa, then the Shechita
did not sanctify the bread. If it
didn't sanctify the bread, that's better, now
you could use the bread for some
other Korban. If, however, the Shechita was
Kasher, or you know, the Psul didn't
predate the Shechita, the Psul was somehow
in the Shechita, it was this Psul
of Pigul, a wrong thought or whatever,
but the Shechita was considered an act
of Shechita, so in that type of
a case, the Shechita did sanctify the
bread and now everything became Pasul and
now you have the worst scenario. Now,
yes. That bothers you because? I don't
know if it's a matter of predating,
I think it's sort of like, you
know, you didn't have mind for this
so it's not even considered. Mind doesn't
matter so much. Let's say you do
Hagrama and you invalidate through the act
of Shechita. That would also Lo Kadesh
Halechem because it wasn't a Maaseh Shechita.
So if it's a Treifa or let's
say the Shechita itself is technically Pasul
just in terms of the physical act,
that's you're right, the case of Treifa
is an easy case because it's not
a Kasher Shechita. Or if it's a,
or if it's let's say, you know,
like Michael says, you know, you put
pressure on it, you did something that
would have made it Treif, you know,
in normal Kashrut laws, it's not a
Kasher Shechita, obviously Lo Kadesh Halechem. The
more interesting case we're going to see
in a minute will be a Mum
case where it's a Kasher Shechita, but
it's a Korban problem. Okay, so let's
look at the next case and that'll
help maybe clarify. Wouldn't you think it's
a Treifa? Well, let's take a look.
Let's take a look. Okay, Shachata Venimtzeit
Baalat Mum, you slaughtered it and then
you realized that it had a Mum.
Now this Mum predated the Shechita, but
you weren't aware of it. Rabbi Eliezer
Omer Kadesh, you did sanctify the bread,
Ve-Chachamim Omerim Lo Kadesh, you did not
sanctify. So what is this debate about?
So it could be like along the
lines, you know, that Michael and I
were just discussing a minute ago, it
could be exactly this. The Shechita as
an act of Shechita, like if you
were to judge it through a Kashrut
lens, was Kasher. The problem was a
Korban problem, it had a Mum, or
like the other problem, it was with
a wrong Machshava. So but the act
of Shechita is Kasher, it's Kadesh Halechem.
There was a Korban problem, that adds
a Psul to it. So it's Kadosh
but now it's Pasul, like as I
said, the worst of both cases. That
makes a lot of sense in terms
of the position that Baal Mum is
Kadesh Halechem. What we're going to see
in the Gemara is that the position
that a Baal Mum is Lo Kadesh
Halechem basically does this issue of time,
predating or not predating. If the problem
predated, then when you get to the
Shechita you say at this moment the
Shechita's meaningless. It already has a Mum.
I don't care whether you know, what
whether it's a Korban problem or another
problem, the Shechita's meaningless, it already has
a Mum. So therefore the Shechita can't
be Mekadesh. But if when you got
to the Shechita everything was okay and
then your thought invalidated it, so the
Shechita is a meaningful Shechita, it's just
you had a problem with your thought,
therefore that gets you into the worst-case
scenario where because the Shechita was okay
it's Kadesh, but you introduced a Psul
so it's Kadosh and it's Pasul. Can
you just clarify the difference between Treifa
and Mum? Yeah, Treifa is like a
Kashrut issue, Treifa means like it has
a hole in the lung. A Mum
is an external blemish. That well, right,
that's one of the ways of defining
it, but yes, it's some type of
an internal injury that will let's say
make it die within a year. But
a Mum they could see before they
They might have missed it. It was
under this under the thigh where the
flap of the skin was covering it
up, they weren't paying close attention. Okay?
The Gemara actually is going to talk
about a cataract of the eye, like
some mum that's not blatant. Why should
there be a difference between a treifa
and a mum? Because a treifa, so
like I said, one way to explain
it, which is not the way the
Gemara is going to, but I think
is the simpler explanation, is that a
treifa because it's a normal kashrus problem.
A treifa means it wasn't a kosher
shechita. The shechita didn't do anything, it
didn't make the meat permissible. Whereas a
mum, the shechita was kosher, it's just
that it was a korban problem. A
mum is about it as a korban.
It's not a general problem of an
animal. It's not acceptable, but if we
want to say was there an act
of a shechita? Outside the Mikdash it
would have been okay. So if the
question is was there an act of
shechita that sanctified the bread, obviously the
korban is pasul, but what we want
to know is did the bread become
kadosh? To answer if the bread became
kadosh, we don't want to just know
if the bread can become kadosh even
if the korban is pasul, like in
the case of the machshava. The question
is you need the shechita to sanctify
the bread. Did we have a shechita?
So that's how I would frame the
mum issue. That's not how the Gemara
is going to frame the mum issue.
Okay, let's finish the mishna and then
we'll see what the Gemara does. Okay.
Shelo lishma. Now if it is did
I skip a line? No. Shelo lishma.
Let's say you slaughtered it without the
right intention to be a toda. So
what do we normally say? Actually there
we say the korban is kasher, but
lo alu l'ba'alim l'shem chova. Nevertheless, v'chein
ayil milu'im v'shnei kavsei atzeres, we're going
to do two other cases where there's
bread that is coming as a result
of the animal korban. The ayil milu'im,
which is interesting, the recent mishnayos have
been interested in that, that was like
the first case where the Torah had
a shlamim brought with bread coming along.
And the shnei kavsei atzeres which actually
also are shlamim together with bread. So
these are all very linked phenomena. They
are shlamim with bread where the bread
somehow is being that the bringing of
the korban somehow sanctifies the bread. So
in all of those cases, sheshachatan shelo
lishmon, if you do it shelo lishmo,
lo kidesh halechem, the bread does not
become kadosh. Not because the korban is
pasul, but we learned out yesterday it
says al zevach todah shlamav, it has
to be slaughtered as a toda and
only then kidesh halechem. One could say
the reason is because what links the
bread to the animal, what defines them
as somehow units, so the slaughtering of
the animal sanctifies the bread is its
identity as a toda or its identity
as the kavsei atzeres, right? If it
was some other korban, the bread would
be irrelevant. So if you are not
slaughtering it with that lishma, then the
bread cannot be linked and the bread
cannot be sanctified. Well, yeah, but you're
saying it would be different than let's
say I do it lishma but instead
of thinking having you in mind, having
him in mind? Excellent question. Yeah, shelo
l'shem ba'alim. I think shelo l'shem ba'alim,
it would be kidesh halechem. I'd have
to check that up, but that's a
great question. I would say it would
be kidesh. And remember the pasuk is
al zevach todah, lishmon, shlamav, it means
your shlamav. Okay. It's a good question.
I would have to look it up,
but I would think I would incline
to say, I'm inclined to say yes.
I think you could just say it's
gezeiras hakatuv, it has to be lishma
for the kidesh, but I really think
it's because that the lechem only relates
to it because of its particular identity.
So your case of lo l'shem ba'alim
is a good question. Okay, so now
let's take a look at the Gemara,
how the Gemara explains what type of
shechita is mikadesh the bread and what
type is not. Masnisin mani? Who is
our mishna? Rebbi Meir. It's Rebbi Meir.
Detanya. And now we're going to have
a braisa that will say that it's
the position of Rebbi Meir and also
clarifies the logic behind our mishna. Ze
haklal. This is the principle. Kol shepisulo
kodem shechita. Now you see what I'm
getting at Michael. Any invalidity that predated
the shechita, lo kidesh halechem. The bread
does not become kadosh because by the
time you got up to the shechita
it was already pasul, so the shechita
cannot be meaningful to sanctify the bread.
Achar shechita. After the shechita. After really
doesn't mean after, it really sort of
means not predating because obviously there's a
psul that comes during the shechita. But
if it does not, not predating, if
it does not predate the shechita, kidesh
halechem. Then when you got to the
shechita everything was okay, so the shechita
sanctified the bread. And now we're going
to give the examples. Actually now we're
going to go in the reverse order
of the way we just presented it.
Shachata chutz l'zmano v'chutz l'mkomo. If you
shechted it with the wrong thought in
mind, a wrong time or wrong place,
kidesh halechem. The bread does become kadosh
because there the psul did not predate.
The psul came at the moment, but
it's not predated, and therefore it is
considered that the shechita was a meaningful
shechita. By the way, but to just
clarify the point Michael raised, if the
shechita really was a bad shechita in
terms of just a kashrus bad shechita,
like you applied pressure or something, obviously
lo kidesh because then it wasn't even
an act of a shechita. But if
it was the korban was kasher and
it was an act of a shechita
and then a psul was introduced even
if it was during the shechita, the
shechita is still considered a ma'aseh shechita
and it's kidesh halechem. Okay, or a
sufficient shechita to be mikadesh halechem. Shachata
v'nimtzas treifa. If the shechita was while
it was a treifa, lo kidesh halechem.
The bread does not become sanctified because
it predated the shechita. Now we look
at the top of ayin ches amud
aleph. Now, and this is the issue
in our mishnah, the debate, shachat venimtza
baalas mum, one who slaughtered and it
was found it had a mum, Rabbi
Eliezer omer kidesh, Rabbi Yehoshua omer lo
kidesh. So that's the debate of Rabbi
Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua. And now if
we're framing the issue as predating or
not predating, it's hard to understand why
Rabbi Eliezer says kidesh because the mum
predated the shechita. So we'll discuss that
in a minute. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's
how Rabbi Meir understood. Rabbi Meir understood,
we're going to see, that everybody knew
there was a debate of Rabbi Eliezer
and Rabbi Yehoshua about the parameters here,
and Rabbi Meir understood that their debate
was local, was about the issue of
the baalas mum, which is our mishnah.
But now we're going to see that
there's another version of what the debate
was. Amar Rabbi Yehuda, so Rabbi Yehuda
said back to Rabbi Meir, lo necheleku
Rabbi Eliezer veRabbi Yehoshua al sheshachat venimtza
treifa. First of all, you're right, nobody
debated the case of a treifa, shelo
kidesh, everybody agrees the bread is not
sanctified because it wasn't a good shechita,
it was treifa already before you got
there. Veal chutz lizmano shekidesh, and nobody
disagrees that if the problem was a
thought of a pigul, that it was
kidesh halechem. Okay, that everybody also agrees
to because the psul is only introduced
at the moment of the shechita. But
not only that, those are the two
points you Rabbi Meir already said, but
even the baalas mum case, veal baalas
mum shelo kidesh, everybody agrees with the
baalas mum lo kidesh. Why? Because based
on the way the Gemara's framing it,
a baalas mum is the same as
a treifa because the issue is predating
the shechita. So you're wrong, they did
not debate baalas mum. That predated the
shechita and everybody agrees it's no good.
Veal ma necheleku, what was the debate?
Al chutz limkomo, a thought problem but
not a pigul thought chutz lizmano but
a chutz limkomo. And this is quite
fascinating. We learned the entire Masechet Zevachim
and chutz lizmano and chutz limkomo were
like Siamese twins, right? One was D'Oraita,
the other was D'Rabbanan. No, it wasn't
D'Oraita D'Rabbanan. One was kares and the
other was not kares. One was pigul
and kares, the other was not kares.
But in terms other than the kares
issue, the punishment, the severity, the ways
in which they invalidated were always the
exact same. We are finally, you know
you had to get through all of
Zevachim and three-quarters of Menachot to find
this discussion about, funny again the way
you know things are not always in
their place, the possibility that chutz limkomo
in some cases can have a different
scope than chutz lizmano. So let's take
a look. That's what he says they
debated. Al ma necheleku, al chutz limkomo.
When his thought is to eat in
the wrong place. SheRabbi Eliezer omer kidesh,
Rabbi Yehoshua omer lo kidesh. There Rabbi
Eliezer says it is the bread is
kadosh just like chutz lizmano, just like
a pigul thought, and Rabbi Yehoshua said
no, that's different than pigul, the bread
is not kadosh. So that's pretty interesting.
Why is that different? So let's take
a look. And here he had, this
is fascinating, Rabbi Yehuda had a whole
version of their debate not just with
opinions but with a whole back and
forth. Okay, and again this is an
interesting question in general about mesorah. It's
not only that like Rabbi Yehuda remembers
their debate to be about this topic
and Rabbi Meir remembers it about baalas
mum. I remember their debate they were
debating baalas mum. No, I remember they
were debating chutz limkomo. No, we're going
to see that Rabbi Yehuda has a
whole, a whole like narrative of their
debate with a whole series of proofs
back and forth. So it raises like
interesting questions about where these different traditions
developed from. Okay, so let's take a
look. So amar Rabbi Yehoshua, so here's
still within Rabbi Yehuda, his version of
their debate. Rabbi Yehoshua said to Rabbi
Eliezer, okay, hoil vechutz limkomo pasul ubaalas
mum pasul. Look, did I skip a
line? I skipped a line. Amar Rabbi
Eliezer, here's Rabbi Eliezer explaining his argument
why chutz lizmano and chutz limkomo should
be the same. Hoil vechutz lizmano pasul,
chutz lizmano is a psul, that's pigul,
vechutz limkomo pasul, and chutz limkomo is
a psul also very analogous about a
wrong thought. So therefore they're both about
wrong thoughts. Ma chutz lizmano kidesh af
chutz limkomo kidesh. So the same way
chutz lizmano the bread is sanctified, so
the same with the psul of chutz
limkomo. So okay, so amar Rabbi Yehoshua,
so Rabbi Yehoshua said back, no, I'll
compare it to another thing. Hoil vechutz
limkomo pasul, so chutz limkomo is an
invalidity, ubaalas mum pasul, and a blemish
is an invalidity. Ma baalas mum lo
kidesh, the same way a blemish does
not, if you shachted the animal with
a blemish the bread is not sanctified,
af chutz limkomo lo kidesh. The same
is true with chutz limkomo. Now that's
a really bad comparison, right? How are
they similar? One predated the other didn't
predate, one is a thought, one is
physical. Compare the thought to the thought.
All right, so that's where we're going
to get. Okay, so let's keep on
going. Obviously here the weight of the
argument seems to be on Rabbi Eliezer's
side, right? Chutz lizmano chutz limkomo are
a pair. But let's keep on going.
It gets, it gets more interesting. Okay,
so amar lo Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Eliezer
said back to him, what are you
talking about? Ani dimitiu lachutz lizmano veata
dimiso lbaalas mum. I've compared it to
a chutz lizmano, you compared it to
a baalas mum. Neire lemi dome, let's
see which one is it more similar
to. Im dome lachutz lizmano nidunennu michutz.
we'll learn it out from chutz zemano.
Im domeh l'baal mum, if it's more
similar to a baal mum, nidunenu m'baal
mum, then we can derive it from
a baal mum. So let's have the
debate now. Let's shift the debate to
the question of which is it more
similar to, and that'll determine what the
halacha is. So hischil Rabbi Eliezer ladun.
So Rabbi Eliezer started making, analyzing or
arguing. Donim p'sul machshava mip'sul machshava. You
derive a case where it's an invalidity
based on thought from an invalidity based
on thought. V'ein donim p'sul machshava mip'sul
haguf. You don't derive an invalidity of
thought, chutz limkomo, from a blemish which
is a physical invalidity. That's reasonable. So
hischil Rabbi Yehoshua ladun. So Rabbi Yehoshua
had, he derived it his way. Donim
p'sul she'ein bo kares mip'sul she'ein bo
kares. Chutz limkomo doesn't have kares, that's
the one way it's different from chutz
zemano, and you learn it out from
a mum, which is also a problem
that doesn't have kares ever attached to
it. V'ein donim and you don't learn
out, I lost my place. V'al yochiach,
that's why, I just lost my place.
Okay, where am I? Oh, v'al yochiach
chutz zemano shep'sul sheyeish bo kares. And
let's not learn it out from chutz
zemano which has kares. Now, of course,
who cares? That's a trivial point. I
mean, the severity of it is not
really speaking to the character of it.
So that does not seem to be
so relevant. But here comes his better
argument. V'od nidunenu mishelo lishmo. You know
what? I'll concede to you that mum
is a bad model, but I have
a better model to learn it from.
Let's learn it from the case of
shelo lishmo. Why should we learn it
from shelo lishmo? Shep'sul machshava v'ein bo
kares. That is another example of a
machshava p'sul and there's no kares. So
why are you going to learn it
from chutz zemano? I have another machshava
p'sul that the bread is not sanctified.
What does the mishna say? If you
shecht it shelo lishmo, everybody agrees the
bread is not sanctified. So let's learn
chutz limkomo from shelo lishmo. A machshava
problem that also does not predate, it
comes at the time of shechita, and
therefore, and that should be like chutz
limkomo. Now, he says that's reasonable, but
it's chutz zemano then. Why? Right, but
at least then, okay, so now the
arguments are pretty much equal, right? You
have in both cases you have a
machshava p'sul, one has kares, one doesn't,
but chutz zemano is in general more
similar to chutz limkomo. In one case
by shelo lishmo the bread is not
sanctified, chutz zemano it is. It seems
like a pretty even, evenly weighted, which
one. If anything, our intuition would be
more to say chutz limkomo goes with
chutz zemano. Right, exactly, and they're both
the same parsha in the Torah, etc.
So although now it still seems that
Rabbi Yehoshua is making an improved argument,
for us I think it would still
seem that Rabbi Eliezer has the better
position. But surprisingly, let's look at the
next line of this braisa. V'shatak Rabbi
Eliezer. Rabbi Eliezer had no response. And
the Gemara is going to say not
only did he have no response to
say like, okay, it's a draw, the
Gemara is going to interpret his silence
to mean that in the end he
admitted to Rabbi Yehoshua that you're right,
that actually we should learn it out
that way, and we should say that
actually it does not kadesh halechem. Now
what is the logic here? Right? What
is the logic, okay, there are two
models, they're both machshava, one is kidesh,
one is lo kidesh. Again, why should
I learn it more from shelo lishmo
than from chutz zemano? So Tosafos says,
and this is sort of, it's a
long Tosafos, he deals with other problems,
but one thing he says which is
also what I was sort of thinking,
is let me also reframe the question.
Forget just like why learn it more
from one than the other. What is
the logic to say that chutz zemano
which is a greater p'sul, it's yeish
bo kares, right, that that should still
have the power to be m'kadesh halechem,
but chutz limkomo which in our mind
is just like a weaker version of
piggul, right, and is not kares, that
somehow doesn't sanctify the bread? It's ironic.
So the one thing that I think
you can say to this is, if
you remember one of the funny things
about piggul is we say a phrase
of meratzeh l'piggulo. That the idea of
piggul is it says lo yeiratzeh, which
means that somehow other than the piggul
it has to be considered like it's
fit for ritzu'i, it's fit for being
received. And that basically when we deal
with piggul we look at, we're able
to bracket the piggul element to say
that if it weren't for the piggul,
it would be meratzeh and that's what
allows it to be piggul. It's potential
to be meratzeh if you were to
bracket the piggul. So when it comes
to piggul we actually are able to
suspend the idea of piggul to evaluate
it as whether it's still meratzeh. Meratzeh
l'piggulo. So that's basically what Tosafos says.
That's why piggul could be kadesh halechem
but not chutz limkomo. Because within piggul
we say is it meratzeh l'piggulo? Would
it be meratzeh without, so we look
at it, we're able to look at
it by bracketing the piggul and saying,
oh, bracketing the piggul it was a
good shechita. And chutz limkomo is not
really piggul. So chutz zemano we'd say
oh, bracketing the piggul it was a
good shechita, it was kadosh, it would
have been meratzeh. Oh, so if that's
true, the lechem is kadosh because we're
able to suspend disbelief or suspend the
psul for that moment. Whereas by everything
else, shelo lishma, chutz l’komo, the other
psulim we never look at it through
that lens. And therefore we just say
it was a pasul shechita, lo kidesh
halechem. So that’s the best way to
explain it. But again, if you just
look at what the Gemara says, it’s
crazy. Rabbi Yehuda... I know, we never...
and that’s what Tosafot tries to figure
out, we’ve never seen these split even
in these questions about whether kidesh or
lo kidesh. Tosafot says basically as far
as the korban is concerned, the shechita
would be equally kadosh, but the whole
issue here is the bread which is
one degree removed, so that’s maybe where
the difference plays out. So that’s what
Tosafot also says why we didn’t see
this... right, there’s the whole debate with
the bread and not... right, well that’s
the question, kidesh halechem. So Tosafot also
says the reason we never saw this
in Zevachim and we don’t see this
in other Gemaras is because this is
a slight difference and it only has
impact when it comes to its ability
to affect something else, but not in
terms of the thing itself. Anyway, that’s
what you have, that this, the way,
without having Tosafot’s part, the way the
Gemara sounds, it sounds like pretty much
equal positions, if anything, our intuition would
have gone to say with Rabbi Yehoshua
to say that it’s like chutz l’zmano
and it’s pasul, and it’s lo kidesh
halechem. Rabbi Eliezer, and nevertheless the Gemara
says that this says Rabbi Eliezer was
silent, which presumably means he agreed to
Rabbi Yehoshua. Now, this is all Rabbi
Yehuda’s version. According to Rabbi Yehuda’s version,
the end of the story is chutz
l’komo is different than chutz l’zmano. But
according to Rabbi Meir’s version, they’re the
same. Chutz l’zmano and chutz l’komo is
both kidesh halechem. So at least with
Rabbi Meir we could say the world
gets restored to its normal tilt, now
we understand, because that’s back to piggul
and chutz l’komo being the same thing.
Okay, so now we see that our
Mishna is Rabbi Meir because according to
our Mishna, chutz l’zmano and chutz l’komo
are the same, and the whole debate
is about the ba’al mum. Let’s take
a look now at the Gemara. So
now the Gemara says like this: Ve’Rabbi
Meir mai shna shachta venimtza terefa de’havi
psulo kodem shechita? What is the difference
between the terefa where the psul predated
and therefore lo kidesh halechem? U’mai shna
shachta venimtza ba’al mum, and how is
it different from the case of the
mum, which also predated the... de’lo havi
psulo kodem shechita? And it’s now, it
doesn’t mean de’lo havi psul, meaning why
should we not consider it to be
a case of psulo kodem shechita? Should
it not be the same thing? Should
it not fit into that category or
why is it not fitting into that
category and therefore you should say lo
kidesh halechem? Why is ba’al mum any
different than terefa? Very good question. So
let’s see what the Gemara says, and
only a question according to Rabbi Eliezer
according to this version. Well, right, why
does he say lo kidesh, it’s the
same thing, fine. Right. What’s the reason
of the one who says it’s not
like ba’al mum? So the Gemara says:
bedukin she’ba’ayin ve’aliba de’Rabbi Akiva. No, we’re
talking only about a particular type of
a mum, about like a cataract of
the eye which is very not noticeable
and according to Rabbi Akiva and who
cares that it’s not so noticeable? De’amar
because Rabbi Akiva says when it’s a
non-noticeable mum like that, im alu lo
yerdu. If it was put on the
mizbe'ach, you don’t take it down. So
you see we’re finally getting back to
Zevachim. Okay, so there was a whole
idea that the psulim, many psulim that
if you put it on the mizbe'ach
you don’t take it down, but there
were some that were excluded, that even
if it’s on the mizbe'ach you take
it down. And by the mum Rabbi
Akiva distinguishes between obvious mumim where even
if it was on the mizbe'ach you
take it off, as opposed to this
type of a cataract where it was
so unnoticeable that it’s able to stay
on the mizbe'ach, which is pretty funny
because halachically it doesn’t have a different
status, but nevertheless its noticeability affects this
issue of... well, now it does according
to Rabbi Akiva, prior to that it
didn’t, one minute, to this issue about
whether you come off. So how is
that relevant to this? So it’s relevant
in the following way: that who is
the one that says that ba’al mum
is kidesh halechem? Kidesh, Rabbi Eliezer. So
Rabbi Eliezer is saying look, even though
this mum predated, it’s not such a
devastating psul. It’s a psul that the
korban could still in some ways be
sanctified enough and be kasher enough that
if it went on the mizbe'ach it
wouldn’t have to come off. So even
if you didn’t put it on the
mizbe'ach? So even if you didn’t put
it on the mizbe'ach because when you
shacht a korban with this mum, it
could still in theory go on the
mizbe'ach, be left on the mizbe'ach if
it were put up, so therefore the
shechita is still powerful enough to be
kidesh halechem. As opposed to if it
was a major mum where the korban
would be so pasul that it couldn’t
even stay on the mizbe'ach, then it
would not be enough to sanctify. So
you understand the logic, right? Where if
we’re asking ourselves was this shechita? Even
if the korban is pasul, there are
some psulim that are very central and
there are some psulim that are more,
you know, secondary and incidental. So if
it’s a major problem like it was
a terefa, you can’t say the shechita
was meaningful, you can’t say kidesh halechem.
So same similarly by a mum, if
it’s a major mum... I agree, then
the whole animal is pasul, you can't
say kiddesh ha'lechem. But if it's a
trivial mum and that there would be
an element in which the korban now
would be okay, I mean not that
you'd be yotzei, but could be left
on the mizbe'ach, so in that type
of a mum is considered more of
a sort of incidental psul, not a
central psul. And therefore that type of
a thing is enough to say kiddesh
ha'lechem. May I ask a question like
this, you know, like if that's really
the case why doesn't the Mishnah just
say dukin she'be'ayin? Right. I agree with
you, I think that that's not pshat
in the Mishnah. I think pshat in
the Mishnah is whether it's a psul
based on the korban status or a
psul that it wasn't even a shechitah.
That where Rebbi Eliezer is saying is
look, the shechitah was kasher, it was
done technically correctly, and you know, it
wasn't a traifah. So if you have
introduced a new psul like chutz zmano
or chutz im komo, mum, korban types
of psulim, that will not prevent it
from kiddesh ha'lechem. Yes, things will be
pasul, but if you had a good
shechitah, that's how I would have said
it, that it was a korban psul
versus a non-korban psul. That's not what
the Gemara is saying. The Gemara is
saying whether it's a type of a
psul that would keep it off of
the mizbe'ach. That by the way also
explains why we don't have to be
concerned about chutz zmano and chutz im
komo, because chutz zmano and chutz im
komo are not—not concerned—but why kiddesh ha'lechem,
because those are types of psulim that
even when you put it on the
mizbe'ach, the animal gets to stay on
the mizbe'ach, you don't take it off.
However, that's not a universal rule, because
again, shelo lishmo, remembering if it's not
treated as a todah, then lo kiddesh
ha'lechem. But as I said, I think
shelo lishmo is of a different category.
I think once you're not defining it
as a todah, you can no longer
have the connection between the korban and
the bread. Okay, yes. If you are
trying to encourage people from giving korbanos
is it making it so let's say
someone was to shecht, he cut up
the the internal thing, what then? I
mean at what point does this become
after inspection of the sh'chitah or what
is this as a...? Yeah, there's nothing
you can do about it. If you
discover that it's a traifah after you
shecht it, you could have done everything
right and it could still be not
good. It's discouraging you from... I guess
that's true, you're right. You know, you're
right, and there is justification. I think
when they had free-range animals there were
a lot less traifos than there were
today. But but yes, I think that
the... even more, because then the wolf
can attack it. Okay, that would be
true. But but yes, I still think,
I still think that the conditions that
they have today increase—whatever. But whatever, anyway,
it's a good point that you could
do everything right and you could still
have trouble. The same now and—and if
you were just shechting it for the
meat, then even though there's going to
be a percentage of traifos, you could
always sell it to a non-Jew. Once
the korban has been sanctified and it's
a traifah, you're right, then the whole
thing you have to write the whole
thing off as a loss. So it's
a good point. It's a good point.
It's discouraging. I know, I can't say
anything about that. It's a good point.
It would be okay, but you'd bring
another korban? What? It would be okay?
If it's lo kiddesh ha'lechem, in the
scenario of lo kiddesh ha'lechem, then right,
then you could still preserve the bread
for another korban, correct. And if it
is kiddesh and the korban is pasul,
that's the worst of both worlds because
it was kiddesh, it was linked to
the korban, the korban is pasul, you
got to throw—then it becomes nifsul b'lina
and then burn it and destroy it.
You lose both, not even having the
bread... Because if it's lo kiddesh you
can use the bread for another korban.
Uh-huh. Right, so again, kiddesh ha'lechem is
not a good thing here. When the
korban becomes pasul, if the bread is
kadosh, you're stuck. It's—it's kadosh, it's linked
to this korban, you can't use it.
You got to let it—you gotta now
burn it, destroy it, whatever. If it's
lo kiddesh, it's still free to go
out to use for another korban. Okay,
let's put it on the side and
bring another animal and then everything is
together. Exactly. Exactly. And we're going to
see that in the next Mishnah as
well. Give this to somebody else or
sell it to... Or give it to
somebody else, sell it I'm not sure
because if it already has kedushas kli
shares, I'm not sure about what your
ba'alus is to sell it. I understand,
but like you also can't sell your
shelamim that you sanctified once it's been
linked to you. I'm not sure. I'm
not sure about that. But you can
certainly use it yourself for another korban
that you're going to bring. Okay, so
the Gemara says like this. Let's take
a look. Rebbi Yehoshua, how would Rebbi
Yehoshua respond why he's not why even
with this psul of the of the
dukin she'be'ayin he still says the bread
is not sanctified? So he would say
the following. Ki amar Rebbi Akiva im
olu lo yerdu b'psula d'gufei, that's when
it comes to the psul of the
animal itself. So because it's a, you
know, a relatively minor mum, we'll let
the animal stay on the mizbe'ach. Aval
l'kedushas lechem lo. To have the power
to sanctify the bread, any psul can
get in the way because you know
that's a derivative kedusha. So when it's
the animal itself, yes, it could be
kadosh enough that it stays on the
mizbe'ach. But to have the power to
sanctify the bread, that even these little
problems can interrupt that and get in
the way. Of course a problem like
chutz zmano chutz im komo doesn't get
in the way, but at least a
problem that predates the shechitah, any small
thing is enough to get in the
way. Okay, now the Gemara goes on.
Ismar, we said, chatas she'shechatah chutz l'zmano
im olu lo yerdu. So chutz im
komo now if you shechted a chatas
with a chutz l'zmanah. piggul thought, if
it goes on the mizbe’ach don't take
it down. Chutz limkomo, however, it's a
chutz limkomo thought. Rava amar tered, Rabbah
amar lo tered. Rava says take it
down, Rabbah says don't take it down.
So here, right, is the only place
where once again we are seeing a
decoupling of chutz lizmmano and chutz limkomo.
This drives Tosafot crazy, because Tosafot says,
you know, there are explicit beraitot in
Shas that say whether it's chutz lizmmano
or chutz limkomo, im alu lo tered.
So what the heck are Rava and
Rabbah doing debating it here? And he
really tries to figure out a whole
new way of explaining the Gemara. One
place Tosafot says, well, maybe they’re not
talking about the korban, maybe they’re talking
about whether if you put the bread
up, but that doesn't work because it's
chatat. Oh, so maybe we should switch
the girsah to say todah. So, you
know, but it’s a very strange, this
Gemara doesn't fit anything we've learned in
Zevachim. Okay, anyway, but that’s what you
have, this debate about if it’s chutz
limkomo. Again, ironically, chutz lizmmano because it’s
piggul has a concept of meratzeh l'piggulo.
So chutz limkomo ironically because it's piggul,
more severe, but nevertheless im alu lo
tered. Chutz limkomo, which doesn't have that
concept of meratzeh l'piggulo, could be that
there’s that it’s worse in that way,
you never look at it as if
it were kasher, and therefore even if
it’s put on the mizbe’ach, take it
down. Okay, so that’s what, that’s the
debate. Rava amar tered, take it down,
Rabbah amar lo tered. Rava k'Rabbi Yehoshua.
Now this sounds like they are debating
the Rabbi Yehoshua-Rabbi Eliezer debate within Rabbi
Yehudah. Rava says like Rabbi Yehoshua that
chutz limkomo is a bigger problem and
therefore come down. v'Rabbah k'Rabbi Eliezer, and
Rabbah says like Rabbi Eliezer that it’s
the same as piggul and therefore gets
to stay up. V'hadar beih Rabbah legabei
de'Rava. Rabbah in the end wound up
agreeing to Rava, he reversed himself and
he agreed to Rava that he said
that chutz limkomo is different than chutz
lizmmano. How do we know that? Mid'hadar
beih Rabbi Eliezer legabei de'Rabbi Yehoshua. Since
Rabbi Eliezer was silent to Rabbi Yehoshua,
presumably he, you know, he, right, he,
you know, accepted Rabbi Yehoshua’s argument. So
therefore, logically therefore, that position no longer
is the legitimate position. So we should
assume that Rabbah winds up agreeing with
Rava, which means it’s bizarre. Which means
that we’re going to assume that we're
going to take that chutz limkomo is
different than chutz lizmmano, which is not
what we ever assume anywhere else. And
this is only anyway, by the way,
Rabbi Yehudah's version of the debate. So
the Gemara actually stops this. So the
Gemara says like this: V'ika d'amri, some
say no. Af al gav d'hadar beih
Rabbi Eliezer legabei de'Rabbi Yehoshua, even though
Rabbi Eliezer reversed himself for Rabbi Yehoshua
and said I admit that chutz limkomo
is different than chutz lizmmano, Rabbah legabei
de'Rava lo hadar beih. Rabbah did not
reverse himself to Rava when it comes
to the issue of whether you have
to bring the korban down off the
mizbe’ach or not. Hatam hu d'ka'amar lei
nidonenu mishelo lishmah. There, the only reason
he agreed was because you could equally
learn out chutz limkomo from shelo lishmah
as you could from chutz lizmmano. So
there was another competing model. The competing
model was shelo lishmah, which is a
psul machshavah, and that case you would
say the bread does not become kadosh.
That's why he agreed, because there was
a competing model. Aval hacha, here, idaiyanta
lei mishelo lishmah, even if I were
to compare it to shelo lishmah, im
alu lo tered. It wouldn't come down.
He’s saying they're different halachot. The question
of whether something goes off of the
mizbe’ach is we already all psulei machshavah
get to stay on the mizbe’ach, whether
it’s piggul, whether it’s shelo lishmah, any
psul that as a result of a
machshavah, we say im alu lo tered.
So there's no reason we should treat
chutz limkomo any different. Okay, if there'll
be a difference, maybe it'll be in
your case about kiddesh halechem, where already
there's a difference between a piggul thought
and a shelo lishmah thought. And it
ends with this, which is again fascinating,
because the Gemara in the end says
at least within Rabbi Yehudah, we could
willing to admit that there's a difference
between chutz limkomo and chutz lizmmano when
it comes to this issue of kiddesh
halechem. It won't always play out in
other areas because other areas, you know,
we treat all thought cases the same,
but there are cases where it might
continue to play out. And again, this
really bothers Tosafot because everywhere else in
Shas, we never distinguish between chutz limkomo
and chutz lizmmano. Now you could say
it's because we rule like Rabbi Meir
over Rabbi Yehudah, this is already Rabbi
Yehudah's version of the debate. Tosafot has
other ways to try to really bracket
this whole discussion and to say, you
know, this is an entire discussion just
about the bread, not about anything else,
although the Gemara mentioned a chatat, we'll
switch the girsah to say todah. And
like Tosafot really wants to compartmentalize. And
a todah means a todah lechem l'todah.
Yeah, he has other ways of reading
the Gemara, but he really wants to
compartmentalize it because it's a shocking Gemara
to the ways in the past that
we've completely... Right. And the actual halachah
is normally we say anything all before,
that it's chutz lizmmano, chutz limkomo, ein
alu lo tered. Right, absolutely. Okay. So,
yeah, I think we managed to get
through all of Zevachim, daf lamed bet
amud aleph, to the ask him the
question, do you have any idea of
why there would be a difference between
machshavah of chutz lizmmano... Oh, now you're
going to start... ask people questions again.
Okay, not really. Obviously the psukim are
talking about, you know, you can't say
it's well one thing is, one thing
I would say is the following, but
in a way maybe it begs the
question, which is normally the way to
think about pigul is your thought is
as if it happened, meaning not that
you're chayav as if it happened, but
it makes the korban as if it
happened. So if you're thinking about a
chutz l'zmano and then you eat it,
what's the chiyuv for eating nosar, which
is bread meat leftover chutz l'zmano, it's
koreis. So the chiyuv for eating pigul
which is a chutz l'zmano thought is
also koreis. What's the chiyuv for eating
meat that was taken out of the
Beis Hamikdash is not koreis. There's a
koreis for being makriv a korban out
of the Beis Hamikdash. There might be
me'ila for eating the meat outside of
the Beis Hamikdash, but it's not exactly,
it's not the same type of a
koreis. But of course that just begs
the question. It does have something to
do with the fact that there was
not always a chutz l'mkomo. Oh, that's
interesting. The Gemara does say that at
times about the time of the heter
habamos. The other thing that I would
say is maybe the opposite of the
point you made, is that you know,
in general pigul is like everything has
to be perfect except this very narrowly
defined thought. You know, it has to
be meratzeh l'pigulo, you can't have other
problems, not every bad thought, only like
a very narrowly, so pigul is almost
like you just missed the mark, it
was all perfect except you blew it
here. And somehow some power to the
idea that it was so close and
yet it missed. And I think maybe
that could be a way of thinking
about the difference of chutz l'zmano and
chutz l'mkomo. The boundary of space is
very obvious. So the idea of out
of the space is a much more
obvious invalidity than the idea of just
waiting and doing it tomorrow. So maybe
the sense that somehow it's a more
subtle problem. I know it's like I'm
just again sort of begging the question,
but I do think that that's an
element of the pigul, that like everything
is right and the problem is just
you know you just missed it this
way and that therefore there's some greater
severity in that rather than some obvious
problem. But again, it's a good question
and I don't know. So let's now
finish up at least till the, let's
see the Mishna, shachto shelo lishmah, it
was shachted shelo lishmo, then as we
said that does not kadesh the lechem.
We learned it out from a pasuk.
Amar Rav Papa, shovak tana didan el
nazir, so he's a little bothered because
we also included in the shelo lishmah
that the bread isn't sanctified, the relationship
of the bread not only to the
toda but to the eil miluim and
the shtei halechem d'atzeres. So he says
why did you go to miluim which
is just historic, why didn't you talk
about the eil nazir? Remember we also
mentioned yesterday the shlamim of a nazir
also comes with bread. So why not
talk about that which is at least
a practical halacha, I mean practical to
the degree that any of this is
practical. Anyway, shovak tana didan eil nazir
d'shchiach, which is more common and should
have been mentioned, venokat eil hamiluim and
he talked about the eil miluim which
is only of historic interest. And so
that's you know he's noting that. And
then the Gemara says so why was
that true, d'tana didan what was the
motivation of our tanna? Ikar milsa nokat.
He wanted to go with the first
occurrence. The first time you have bread
linked to a shlamim is by the
eil miluim, so he wanted to refer
back to that although it was only
of historic interest. Okay now that is
the shchita sanctifying the bread and what
type of a shchita if it's pasul
still sanctifies the bread. Now we continue
with this whole with the relationship again
of the shchita and the bread. Let's
see. The relationship to the miluim carried
forward to any time that kohanim. Oh,
the mincha that was brought. That's true,
but not the bread that came with
the shlamim, but the concept of like
the minchas chavitin of the Kohen Gadol.
That aspect of it also became a
mincha that any kohen brings when he's
initiated into the avoda, but not the
bread that came with the shlamim. You're
right, the Gemara sort of conflated them,
but it's just as a mincha. Okay
now we move beyond the bread to
another thing that comes with the korban
and comes with a lot more korbanos
which is nesachim, the wine. We could
also talk about the minchas nesachim that
comes with free-will sacrifice, a free-will korban,
shlamim or an olah, whatever. What do
you bring with it? You bring with
it a certain mincha, actually not just
free-will, well, it's even if you're not
taking a neder, any olah and shlamim
you bring with it, this is why
we say in the musaf, you know,
minchasam veniskeihem kemishpat shlosha esronim lapar shnei
esronim la'ayil. So it's a certain mincha,
flour and oil, and there's a certain
amount of wine. So that too is
linked to the korban. But the link
is not the same because the general
principle is niskeihem afilu mikan ve'ad asara
yamim, that if you can bring the
korban today and you can bring the
nesachim tomorrow. So as opposed to the
bread which is tightly linked and it
has to be coming today and you
have to eat it on the same
day, this type of a thing can
come on a different day. So what
is now the relationship going to be
between the shchiting of the korban and
than the nesachim. Maybe different than the
relationship to the bread. So let’s look
now at the mishna. Hanesachim she’kiddshu bikli,
so the nesachim which you did put
it into a klee sharet and they
were sanctified. And now you shechted the
korban. So how is that defined? V’nimtza
zevach pasul. The korban is pasul. So
im yesh zevach acher yakrivu imo. You
can bring it with another korban. You’re
not stuck. V’im lav and if there
isn’t another korban and it already was
sanctified in the vessel, what do you
have to do? Yipslu b’lina. Then you
have to just let then it becomes
pasul. It stays overnight, it’s pasul, you
can’t use it. So if you were
to ask what is the simple sense
of this mishna? Is the shechitas hazevach
does it sanctify the nesachim or not?
What would you say? No. No, right?
It seems like it’s saying here the
shechita has nothing to do with the
nesachim. They were sanctified in the klee.
So now and it’s not about the
shechita. They have some independence. As I
said before, they can come on a
different day. So therefore if you can’t
use this korban, who cares? Doesn’t affect
this status. Go use it with another
korban. If there’s no other korban to
use it for and it was already
sanctified in the vessel, so because it
already had kdushas klee it’s going to
become pasul b’lina. So therefore if you
can’t find something by the end of
the day, then come night it’ll become
pasul. Why? Because it was already sanctified
not by the shechita. The shechita was
pasul. It was sanctified by the klee.
So the simple sense of this mishna
is exactly to distinguish this from the
lechem. This is about kdushas klee, not
about shechita. Of course the entire gemara
now we’re going to look at insists
that this is kdusha by the this
is shechitas hazevach and is now going
to try to make sense of the
mishna by taking that approach. What klee
would it have been into? Some type
of a klee sharet that was like
that to contain the wine. Some kind
of bowl like they used for the
blood? Hopefully a different one. Or hopefully
they washed it well. Okay so let’s
take a look. So the gemara says
amar Zieri. So Zieri now makes this
very complicated because Zieri insists that it
is similar to the bread. Ein hanesachim
mitkadshim ela bishchitas hazevach. So oh my
god. Like seems to be the opposite
of the mishna. The nesachim also only
become sanctified through the slaughtering of the
korban. Mai ta’ama what’s the reason? Amar
kra the pasuk says zevach un’sachim dvar
yom b’yomo. The korban and its nesachim
links them. Okay now let’s see if
we can if the Zieri can work
with our mishna. Tnan our mishna says
hanesachim she’kiddshu bikli v’nimtza zevach pasul im
yesh zevach acher yakrivu imo v’im lav
yipslu b’lina. Our mishna. Mai lav d’ipsal
bishchita. It sounds like the shechita was
pasul. And what does it mean that
the shechita was pasul? It means like
you know that there was either a
psul machshava or maybe it was a
treifa, maybe it was a mum, but
it actually sounds like the shechita was
pasul. Now if you’re right Zieri, why
can you now use it for another
korban? Why didn’t it become if the
shechita sanctifies then if the shechita’s pasul
it should also transfer the psul. If
it’s linked to the shechita. So if
the shechita was pasul how now can
you use it for another korban? It
says ipsal bishchita. So it says unimtza
zevach pasul. So it says lo d’ipsal
b’zrika. When we say that it was
found to be pasul it doesn’t mean
the psul occurred at the shechita, the
psul occurred at the zrika. So at
the shechita it had already become sanctified
and now there’s a problem that comes
with the zrika but that’s okay it
already became sanctified and now if you
can’t use it for this korban use
it for another. Now that’s already bizarre
because if you’re giving weight to the
shechita you would also think that it
doesn’t just sanctify it but that it
links it to the korban. If you’re
giving weight to the shechita. If you
don’t give weight to the shechita it
can be an it can be a
free agent. But if you’re giving weight
to the shechita it should link it.
Okay so that’s going to be very
bizarre. So let’s see where the gemara
could right that’s the question. But let’s
see where the gemara says d’ipsal b’zrika.
So the gemara says k’man who’s this
going like? K’rabbi d’amar shnei dvarim hamatirim
ma’alim ze belo ze. Are you saying
this is going like Rabbi who says
when you have two things that are
matir one can work independent of the
other. What Rabbi is this? So of
course you will remember that about I
don’t know two months ago we discussed
where if you have the two kivsei
atzeret and the bread the shtei halechem.
So what if the gemara says or
not the gemara the braisa says you
shecht the kivsei atzeret lishmo and you’re
zorek the dam shelo lishmo. So there
was one opinion Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbe Shimon
that says the bread only becomes sanctified
through the combination of the shechita and
the zrika without both you have nothing
and the bread does not become sanctified.
Rabbi said no the bread became sanctified
with the shechita even though the zrika
was not correct and it’s kadosh but
you can’t it’s not ne’echal or whatever
it is. Okay but at least it
worked somewhat independently. So the gemara’s saying
this is just the same idea. You’re
saying we have shechita and zrika you’re
saying that the shechita would be enough
by itself. That even though the korban
only becomes kasher with the zrika that
the shechita by itself is one step
and would be enough to sanctify the
nesachim. According to you that the nesachim
are linked to the shechita. So the
gemara says is that what you are
saying? So the gemara says no afilu
teima Rabbi Elazar b’Rebbe Shimon. Even Rabbi
Elazar b’Rebbe Shimon that argues with Rabbi
Rebbi over there and says it's either
all or nothing, hacha be-mai askinan, I'll
get you all here as well. It's
a very special case. What's the case?
Kegon she-kibel daman be-kos venishpach. You slaughtered
it correctly, you caught the blood and
the blood spilled. And therefore what? So
what? You still don't have the second
stage. But we're not done. Turn the
page. Rebbi Elazar bar Rebbi Shimon savar
lei ke-vatei de-avuha. De-amar kol ha-omed lizrok
kezaruak dami. Rebbi Shimon is of the
opinion that anything that is fit to
be thrown the blood, it's like it's
already thrown. Now it does not mean
this literally. It's not like oh, so
you don't have to do zrikas hadam,
the korban is still kasher, right? It
requires the act of zrika. Every time
you say it's as if, the question
is how much is it as if?
But it's as if enough that we
could say that the kedusha that emerges
from it, because all that was left
was the zrika and it was fit
for the zrika, at that moment there
was enough to be instilled with the
kedusha. Now that is different than if
I go ahead and I do zrika
shelo lishmo, I actually invalidate that stage.
Then I can't say oh, retroactively it
was kezaruak dami because I've actually now
invalidated that stage. But if I never
invalidated it, I just spilled it and
never did it, for some reason that
is still enough to say, well it
got to that point, that was enough
to create the kedusha. Okay? So yes,
maybe you need two stages to create
the kedusha, but as long as it
got to the point where it could
have been done, that was enough to
create the kedusha, as long as you
don't ruin it afterwards. So as long
as you spill it rather than be
zoreik shelo lishmo. Wait a second. So
I'll pause there. The case where originally
there it was zoreik shelo, there the
case of Rebbi and Rebbi Shimon bar
Elazar was she-shachatu lishmo venizrak shelo lishmo.
You actually did the zrika incorrectly. That
he said is a problem. There you
ruined it. But if you didn't ruin
it, you just never did it, then
we'll sort of give you credit, you
got to the stage where it was
fit and that's enough to create the
kedusha. Okay, so now what are we
saying? We are saying is rather than
reading this mishna nice and simply that
the shechita has nothing to do with
the kedusha of the nesachim, we're saying
it does have to do with the
kedusha of the nesachim. Why then if
the shechita was pasul can I use
it for something else? Very very special
case. The shechita really wasn't pasul, the
shechita was kasher, but not only that,
the zrika wasn't pasul, it's just the
blood was spilled. Go tell me how
the idea of spilling the blood fits
the language of nimtza zevach pasul? Okay,
it doesn't fit the language at all.
But anyway, the blood was spilled and
therefore the bread became kadosh and therefore
you can now use it for another
korban. But that still asks the question,
okay, I understand that it's kadosh. Why
can I transfer the korban? Shouldn't it
be linked to the korban if it's
all about the shechita? So that's what
what— Why can I transfer the bread?
Why can't I transfer the— why can't
I transfer the oil to another korban?
Okay, not the oil, the wine. The
wine to another korban. So that's what
the Gemara is now going to turn
to. Amar lo. So now he talks.
Im yesh zevach acher yakrivu imo. If
there's another korban, use it with that
korban, this wine. So now the Gemara—
so now it's going to turn to
this question about if it's linked to
it, how can I really transfer which
korban it's related to? Ve-ha amar Rav
Chisda, doesn't Rav Chisda say, shemen she-hifrishu
lishmo mincha zo pasul lishmo mincha acheres?
If you designate oil for one mincha,
you can't use it for another. And
there it was only designated. Here it's
the whole shechita which was mekadesh according
to the Iri. So amar Rav Yannai,
Rav Yannai says, no, lev beis din
masneh aleihem. Beis din stipulates and says
im hotzrechu hotzrechu ve-im lav yiheyu le-zevach
acher. Beis din stipulates for anytime anybody
brings wine with their korban, that if
it— if you wind up using it
for the korban, great. And if not,
we'll say from the very outset that
it is not linked to that korban,
we make like a stipulation and say
it'll be free to use for another
korban. Lev beis din masneh amai? By
private korban? Yes, that's a very good
point. I'd say that if anything it
would be with the communal korban, if
it's like, you know— right, right. So,
I think— why beis din all of
a sudden? Why the rabbis, and what
does beis din have to do— Right,
so that's similar to Michael's question, as
you know you could understand this expression
lev beis— yeah I mean, although the
Gemara, which is also interesting, you know
again sort of this rabbinic read of
the mikdash, they're always inserting beis din,
which is like rabbis, into the mikdash
as the ultimate authority in the mikdash.
But anyway, it's one thing to say
that you could believe that in like
a context of a communal korban. Michael's
actually correct, and very often we do
say lev beis din masneh by a
communal korban. I'm trying to remember because
Rashi here, Tosafos, somebody actually raises that
issue about communal versus non-communal. One minute.
It's not the authority, it's not the
authority, whether it's the rabbis or the
kohanim or whatever it is that's in
charge of the whole— Right, it's sort
of like when you say kol hamikadesh
ada'ata derabanan mekadesh. Rabbis get to define
everything about halachic life. But anyway, I
do think somebody does bring out a
difference between communal and private. I'll have
to check for it. So let's see
how the Gemara answers this, okay? So
the Gemara says, oh, we somehow stipulate
and say that if a problem occurred,
it will never have been sanctified for
that korban. That's what the Gemara says.
So the Gemara says, im hotzrechu hotzrechu
ve-im lav yiheyu le-zevach acher. Ei hachi,
says the Gemara, shemen nami. Let's say
the same by the oil. You sanctified
oil for your korban, but if somehow
some problem occurred, you have a right
to use it for— use it for
a different a different Mincha? So the
Gemara says, so Shemen gufa demincha hu.
No, Shemen is actually the ingredient, the
direct ingredient of the Mincha. You can't
say, oh, this is going to be
used for something else. It wasn't like
something that was used for a Mincha,
it was actually a part of the
Mincha. So we are not going to
so restipulate what you have said if
you're not just assigning it to something
but you're making it a part of
something. So if it's a part of
the Mincha, it can now not become
a part of another Mincha. But the
Gemara is still not satisfied. If it's
all about Beis Din, Beis Din should
do whatever they want. So the Gemara
says like this, so the Gemara after
this gufa demincha hu, velisney aleiha denayfku
lechulin. Okay, so if you're saying you
can't say use it for another Mincha
because it was not just assigned to
a Mincha but it was Mincha X
and it now can't become Mincha Y,
it can't become another Mincha. Nevertheless, why
don't you just say oh if some
problem occurred then it would never have
been kadosh from the get-go? Okay? And
at least let me get my shemen
back. Okay? So the Gemara says velisney
aleiha denayfku lechulin, that let me let
it now go out to chulin. No,
gezeira shema yomru motzin mikli shares lechul.
People will see that it was sanctified
in a kli shares, they won't understand
Beis Din's stipulation, they won't understand that
there was a problem that it couldn't
have been used in the original Mincha,
and they'll think that something that was
sanctified in a kli shares can become
chulin and that's not true. You can't
be... no, because the other case we
didn't say it was chulin, we said
use it for another korban. Right, and
then people will think that I can
use it for one korban and another
in a regular case. Ah, hacha nami
gezeira shema yomru nesachim shehefrishu leshum zevach
ze ksheirin leshum zevach acher. See, exactly,
right. The Gemara. Oh, so the Gemara
says people may make a mistake here
and say nesachim for one thing you
can just reassign it, they won't understand
it was a special case and that
it was all because of lev Beis
Din. So the Gemara says ha tanye
Matya ben Yehuda. No, because Matya ben
Yehuda teaches kegon shehaya zevach zavuach beosa
sha'a. I don't know. kegon shehaya zevach
zavuach beosa sha'a, that it was already
another korban was slaughtered. So it's not
like you're waiting around, hey, does anybody
have another toda, we've got some nesachim
available. No, you had another korban right
there and you immediately used it so
nobody would see that anything strange had
happened, right? You know, they don't sort
of see oh it was being moved
from here to there. That it was
a korban and you just now get
the nesachim. Right. So therefore the Gemara
says that's why we're not afraid of
this very special case. So the Gemara
says, you know, come on, give me
a break, it's not what the mishna
is talking about. The Gemara says aval
ein zevach zavuach beosa sha'a if there's
no other korban already shechted and ready
to use the nesachim, mai? What would
you say? Yipslu belina, we would have
to let it become pasul belina, we
couldn't reassign it. Ad tanye seifa since
the end of our mishna says im
lav yipslu belina. So if there's no
other korban then it becomes pasul belina.
Liflog velisney bdidi. Don't just tell me
it's about having a korban or not
having a korban. What it really should
say is bame devarim amurim when can
I use the nesachim for another korban?
Shehaya zevach zavuach beosa sha'a, there was
already a korban slaughtered and waiting for
it. Aval ein zevach zavuach beosa sha'a
lo, then I couldn't use it. So
the Gemara says hacha nami kama, that
really is what it means. Bame devarim
amurim when can I use the nesachim
for another korban? Shehaya zevach zavuach beosa
sha'a, it was already slaughtered. Aval ein
zevach zavuach beosa sha'a na'ase kmi sheyipslu
belina, it's just as good as if
it became pasul belina. Right, now, exactly.
Now, besides that it's reading a lot
into the mishna and this is all
very hard to buy into all of
this and it all argues that really
the Meiri's read is a very forced
read and the simple sense of the
mishna is that it's not linked. But
again see what the Gemara is now
saying. It's a very interesting how the
Gemara is now considering what happens. The
shechita of the korban sanctifies the wine,
okay, not to the point that it's
that well, the way they're sort of
framing it is, it is maybe linked
to the korban but Beis Din somehow
is able to redefine that. Well, there's
another korban, right. Well that's to be
concerned about maris ayin. And when they
redefine it, when they redefine it, they're
redefining it to a korban that was
already shechted. So this korban now that
was already shechted, its shechita had nothing
to do with this wine. You need
the shechita to sanctify the wine. The
shechita of korban A sanctified this wine,
now you're going to use this wine
for korban B that was already shechted
and its shechita was totally unrelated. So
the link of the wine to the
korban is very bizarre. Now, normally I
would say who cares, maybe it doesn't
have to be linked, but if you're
insisting that shechita is what creates the
kedusha, it is quite fascinating that we
can then decouple it from the first
korban and reassign it to another korban
to which it never had any relationship.
Okay, so it's all of this is
the baggage that we get besides the
textual problems if we assume that the
shechita sanctifies the nesachim. The simple sense
of the mishna is that it does
not. Did they have to bring their
wine? Or was wine there? No, they
had to bring their own wine. Okay?
There were some special cases that the
Beis Hamikdash provided the wine like if
a ger brought a korban... meaning because
he's already bringing his wine in. Was
it already shechted though? Oh yeah, that's
a good point. Yeah, that's a good
point too. If the korban was already
shechted, it would have already sanctified the
wine that it had. Yeah, so you'd
have to imagine a case but you
could bring wine on a different day,
right? Afilu mikan ad asara yamim. So
therefore, it could be a case where
the guy was planning on bringing it
later, says don't worry, we got some
extra wine. But again, that very fact
that you can bring the nesachim later
also should really prove that you can't
say the shechita was mikadesh. And I
believe that the Gemara in another place,
I'd have to check after that, on
Ze'iri, says Ze'iri's only talking about a
circumstance where they came together. When they
came apart, he would be modeh that
the shechita is mikadesh. But again, all
of that argues to say that it's
never mikadesh, that it always sort of
is kedusha exists independent, which is again
the simple sense of our mishna. Okay,
let's just wrap this up. So the
Gemara says like this, umi is leh
le'Rabbi Shimon lev beis din masneh lahen?
Does Rabbi Shimon hold this? Since we're
saying that Rabbi Elazar be'Rabbi Shimon held
like Rabbi Shimon, we're trying to say
this all works within Rabbi Shimon, although
that's questionable. Does he really hold of
this principle of lev beis din masneh
lahen? Ve'amar Rav Idi bar Avin amar
Rav Amram amar Rabbi Yitzchak amar Rabbi
Yochanan temidim shelo hutzrechu latzibur, if the
tzibur did not need the temidim, meaning
you bought your tamid with the communal
funds and then for some reason you
have extra, why, the tamid got lost,
so you separated another one and then
you found the one that got lost.
So now you have an extra korban
laying around here, what are you going
to do with it? And here it's
communal, so here the idea of beis
din makes a lot more sense. So
they said according to Rabbi Shimon ein
nifdin temimim, you cannot redeem it because
it doesn't have a mum, vedivrei Chachamim
nifdin temimim, the Chachamim let you redeem
it even though it doesn't have a
mum. Why? Because of the principle of
lev beis din masneh lahen. Although you
can never redeem something without a mum,
here we will stipulate that if somehow
this happened, and here particularly it's communal
korban and communal funds, we'll retain the
right to redeem it. So you see
that Rabbi Shimon does not say lev
beis din masneh lahen, and our whole
discussion before involved Rabbi Shimon. So how
could we introduce the idea of lev
beis din in the discussion before if
Rabbi Shimon doesn't hold of it? Because
you can do something about it. So
the Gemara says shani hasam de'is lehu
takanta bire'iya. I don't know if that's
what you meant but it says over
there you can fix the problem. Why?
Because you can lose okay, great, see
like you'd write the Gemara. You can
use that tamid that you couldn't use
now, you can wait till it gets
a mum and then you'll redeem it.
So there's a solution. Tosafos in Menachos
says precisely that, you can even bring
it as an olah that means kayitz
hamizbe'ach. So there there's a solution, so
we're not going to say lev beis
din. Here there's no solution, if you
don't let me use it for another
zevach, I'm going to have to let
it become pasul and that's why we
say it. So again, all of this
was very complicated thing to try to
defend how Ze'iri's position against our mishna
that says the shechita is mikadesh, but
the simple sense of the mishna is
to contrast it to the bread. By
the bread the shechita's mikadesh, by the
nesachim because they can come on a
later day and are not closely linked,
there it's the kli that's mikadesh, not
the zevichah. But that's not what Ze'iri
says. Alright, we finished the daf.